And as you're turning there, let me remind you to continue to pray for the Beacon of
Truth Ministries and got some opportunities for a number of Bibles and we're thankful
for the opportunity to assemble the scriptures here, but very exciting about what's going
on.
They have a deadline of getting those Samoan Bibles done and ready for shipment by October.
And so if you'd pray with them about that, I know they'd greatly appreciate that.
First chapter number 11 and that this portion of scripture, just looking at a few verses
this morning from numbers 11, but let me remind you that one of the characteristics that God
gives us in 2 Timothy chapter number three of the last days is that people will be unthankful.
And it's very interesting as you think about the lack of gratitude that is prevalent in
our society today.
I believe that really it doesn't take us long to just look around and listen to some things,
interact with some people, and we find in our society that there is a prevalent spirit
of lacking thankfulness, of discontent.
And we see it in all sorts of spheres of our society today.
And the reality is that oftentimes as we look at all that's taking place, I believe that
as the people of God, the attitude of discontent, the lack of thanksgiving really should alarm
us.
It should cause us to be greatly concerned and we should really put up guards that we
are not influenced by it.
We'll get into the message this morning and I'll make a statement that I'll make now as
well that to complain is contagious.
And really there's a spirit of complaining that as you live in our society and you see
these things that are happening, that it's very easy to join in and to begin to participate
in that same level of behavior.
It is often said, and you would think of the truth of the nation of Israel, we'll look
at this passage of Scripture this morning and a number of others here in the Old Testament,
when you think about the children of Israel, often we are quick to criticize them for their
complaining.
We read of their murmuring and their complaining all throughout the Old Testament.
It's very easy for us to quickly criticize them for it, but it's been often observed
that if we're not careful, we too will imitate that behavior that we criticize.
And how careful we must be, I think of this when I think about this spirit of discontent,
this lack of thankfulness in our society today, that oftentimes it is manifested through a
complaining spirit.
You interact with people just as I do and you know that it's very easy to be able to
begin a conversation with someone and to immediately begin to hear of complaints.
And that's amazing as to what we as human beings are able to complain about.
In fact, I've often thought if we'd put as much effort into finding things to rejoice
in, it'd certainly be a blessing because it seems as if sometimes it's very much effort
that is put into the idea of complaining and looking for things to complain about.
Notice in Numbers chapter 11, the Bible says this, and when the people complained, it displeased
the Lord.
And the Lord heard it, and His anger was kindled, and the fire of the Lord burnt among them
and consumed them that were in the uttermost parts of the camp.
Verse 2, the people cried unto Moses, and when Moses prayed unto the Lord, the fire
was quenched.
And he called the name of the place Tiberia because the fire of the Lord burnt among them.
I'm thankful that as Moses prayed that the fire was quenched, our God is gracious.
He's merciful.
He's full of compassion, and for that we ought to rejoice.
But you look at the first verse of Numbers 11, and we'll use it as our title this morning,
when the people complained.
The word complain means to utter expressions of censure or resentment, to murmur, to find
fault.
And if you look at this, and I think it's a wise observation, that fault is the easiest
thing in the world to find.
Think about that.
And so often it's easy for us to find fault with the society in which we live and all
sorts of things that we encounter, and we find here as we look at this passage of Scripture
that there's rich truth for us to glean from that I believe God will help us.
If you're taking notes this morning, notice number one, the tendency to complain.
The tendency to complain.
As you trace the steps of the children of Israel, you will find over and over the murmuring
and the complaining that is so prevalent amongst the children of Israel, the people of God,
there is a tendency on their part to complain.
I believe that it's a human tendency for us to complain, and we find that it's easy to
complain about things, and it's easy to get into the spirit of complaint, and we find
that their tendency, the tendency of the children of Israel is well documented in the
Old Testament.
Notice if you will, go back to the book of Exodus in chapter number 14, and we read in
Exodus chapter number 14 of just great might and great power and how God demonstrated this
power in drying up the Red Sea, and you think about the miracle of the crossing of the Red
Sea, and you think about what the people as they feared, and it tells us in verse number
10 that when Pharaoh drew nigh, the children of Israel lifted up their eyes, and behold,
the Egyptians marched after them, and they were sore afraid, and the children of Israel
cried unto the Lord, and they were fearful for their very existence, and Moses speaks
to them, and the Lord speaks, and Moses says, the Lord shall fight for you in verse number
14, and ye shall hold your peace, and God says in verse number 15 that Moses is to speak
unto the children of Israel that they go forward, that they will see the salvation
of the Lord, and you know the account and what a record it is in Exodus 14 to see how
the Lord allowed for the children of Israel to cross over on dry ground, and God destroyed
the Egyptians who assayed to go in after them, and God worked miraculously, and after they
had crossed, and after God had allowed the Egyptians to drive heavily their wagons there,
their chariots, we find that God closed up the Red Sea, and He destroyed the children
of Israel, and it was reason to rejoice, and in Exodus chapter 15 you see the song of deliverance,
you see the rejoicing, they say this in verse number 1 of Exodus 15, then sang Moses and
the children of Israel this song unto the Lord, and spake, saying, I will sing unto
the Lord.
Why?
For he hath triumphed gloriously.
The horse and his rider hath he thrown into the sea.
Notice in verse 13, thou in thy mercy hath led forth the people which thou hast redeemed.
Thou hast guided them in thy strength unto thy holy habitation.
Verse 18, the Lord shall reign forever and ever.
I mean, they're rejoicing, and rightly so.
God had worked miraculously.
It's amazing, on the heels of seeing such miraculous deliverance, on the very heels
of singing such a wonderful song of deliverance, the Bible tells us in verse number 22, so
Moses brought Israel from the Red Sea, and they went out into the wilderness of Shur,
and they were three days, they went three days in the wilderness and found no water.
So just a few days after seeing the miraculous, powerful hand of God Almighty, after singing
his triumphs and singing his praises and singing how the Lord shall reign forever and ever,
and God led them, we understand, by the pillar of cloud by day, the pillar of fire by night,
and they come to a place, and the Bible tells us that they find no water, and they came
to Marah in verse 23, and they could not drink of the waters.
Why?
Because they were bitter, and notice it says in verse 24, and the people murmured against
Moses.
It didn't take long for these nation of Israel, these people of God to begin to murmur and
complain about what?
About their circumstances, about their situations, about the things that they were facing.
The reality is that God knows that they needed water.
Amen?
God knows what our needs are.
He knows where we need to be, and God, he doeth all things well.
He led them exactly to where they were supposed to be.
We find that they find themselves here in this portion of Scripture where they're murmuring
against Moses, and they say, what shall we drink?
Notice in verse 25 that he cried unto the Lord Moses, and the Lord showed him a tree,
and he cast it into the waters, and the waters were made sweet, and he made for them a statute
and ordinance, and there he proved them, and what a great truth of seeing the power of
God.
Now, I want you to think about the experience of the children of Israel, their tendency
to complain.
They would see God work miraculously.
They would see God provide for them.
They would see God prove them, and he would prove himself and his power, and yet they
would face another obstacle.
They would face a circumstance, a situation that perhaps we would describe as being less
than desirable, and immediately, what would their default setting be?
It would be this tendency to complain.
It was like a default setting.
In verse number, excuse me, in chapter number 16, you find the Bible tells us that they
took their journey from Elam, and all the congregation of the children of Israel came
unto the wilderness of Sin, and it says, which is between Elam and Sinai, on the fifteenth
day of the second month after their departing out of the land of Egypt.
So I want you to consider with me that it's only the two and a half months after they'd
seen God work miraculously and deliver them, and think about all of the wonders that they
saw in the plagues in Egypt, and then delivering.
and the crossing of the Red Sea, and then the waters healed at Marah.
And the Bible tells us here in Exodus chapter number 16
that they go through and they are complaining again.
In verse number 3, it says,
"...the children of Israel said unto them,
Would to God we had died by the hand of the Lord in the land of Egypt,
when we sat by the flesh pots, and when we did eat bread to the full.
Notice what they said,
For ye have brought us forth into this wilderness
to kill this whole assembly with hunger."
Notice what the Lord said unto Moses in verse number 4.
He said,
"...I will rain bread from heaven for you,
and the people shall go out and gather a certain rate every day,
that I may prove them whether they will walk in my law or no."
I want you to think about the next 40 years,
how the children of Israel would receive this bread daily.
And God miraculously provided day by day.
Of course, we understand that on the Sabbath,
He would not send the manna for on the sixth day.
They were to gather twice as much.
And He here in Exodus chapter number 16 provides all of the details
and how He was going to prove His people,
and He was going to prove His power.
And we find that the children of Israel, however,
they were murmuring against Moses and Aaron in the wilderness,
according to verse number 2.
And they say,
"...it would have been better for us to have died in Egypt."
Certainly, for a people that had experienced
what they had experienced up to this point in their lives,
the default setting should no longer be complaining.
Amen?
The default setting could be a wonder how God is going to work.
What is God going to do in this situation?
Let us seek the face of God.
Let us praise God for the place in which He's brought us,
and let us look to Him for how He will provide for us.
But no, the people murmur.
They murmur against Moses and against Aaron.
God proves them in chapter 16.
We read about the manna.
It tells us in verse number 35 of Exodus 16,
that the children of Israel did eat manna 40 years
until they came to a land inhabited.
They did eat manna until they came into the borders of the land of Canaan.
And then we enter into the 17th chapter of the book of Exodus,
the book of Exodus.
We're speaking this morning of the tendency to complain
and how the tendency of the children of Israel is well-documented.
In chapter 17 of verse number 1, it says,
and all the congregation of the children of Israel
journeyed from the wilderness of sin after their journeys
according to the commandment of the Lord,
and pitched in Rephidim,
and there was no water for the people to drink.
So, the Bible tells us that they were in that place
according to the commandment of the Lord in verse number 1.
The Bible tells us of their circumstances
that there's no water to drink,
and it tells us in verse number 2
that the people did chide with Moses.
If you look at verse number 3,
it's the people thirsted there for water
and the people murmured against Moses.
We read of this tendency of the children of Israel
and we read how that as they had barely finished
seeing God provide miraculously,
they would complain about their situation
and then God would graciously provide for them
and he would prove his power,
and yet they would face another difficulty
and they would complain, the tendency of complaining.
Turn over to the book of Numbers
where we are here this morning in chapter number 11,
and really much of the remainder of the book of Exodus
would communicate for us the 10 commandments,
the requirements and the instructions
with regard to the tabernacle and all of those things.
And of course, the book of Leviticus
providing for us much detail with regard to the law.
And we come here and really kind of pick up
the journey of the children of Israel in Numbers 11.
You find that the Bible says,
and when the people complained,
it was a default setting,
it was a tendency for the children of Israel.
And it's a tendency in our human nature,
and we must be careful,
we must guard against this tendency of complaining.
I would say that, as I mentioned by way of introduction,
that complaining is contagious.
You get around at the workplace
and you begin to complain about the job,
you begin to complain about the supervisor,
you begin to complain about the requirements
and the responsibility and the lack of pay,
and there's no this and there's no that.
And guess what?
Before long, you got a whole crowd that wants to chime in
and wants to join in and sing the complaints
about the circumstances, right?
We see it in the job place.
I worked in the corporate world for years.
I know how it works.
Complain about gas prices.
You hear that complaint recently?
Right?
It's all over the place, right?
Complaining about gas prices, right?
Complaining about I had to dip into my savings,
I had to take out whatever.
I was talking to the kids and I said,
you know, I said,
one of the things that's interesting
is if we change our perspective,
maybe instead of complaining about the gas prices,
we can rejoice that God provided for us in advance
so that we could pay for the gas.
It's just a change of perspective, right?
What we sang this morning,
God is so good.
Is he good even if the gas prices go through the roof?
Sure he is.
Is he good if the boss requires you to do more
than you think that?
Yes, he is.
He's good.
And so often we find in our society
that there's this tendency to complain
and it's contagious.
It's something that impacts us.
We see people complaining in their homes.
We see people complaining about their spouses.
We see people complaining about their children.
We see children complaining about their parents.
And I mean, the list just goes on and on and on.
And lest we fool ourselves this morning,
we must acknowledge this morning
that there's a tendency to complain still today,
even amongst the people of God,
in the house of God.
Amen.
It happens.
There's a tendency to complain.
I remember when we lived out in Nevada,
hearing a story of a situation with a preacher
that was out in that area.
And if you've been out to the northwest part
of the United States,
you'll find that in a number of those states
in Nevada and up into Idaho
and some of the other parts of that area of the country,
you'll find that there are few and far of churches,
Bible-believing churches.
The town that we lived in in Nevada,
if we wanted to go to a church like our church today,
we would have had to have driven about 120 miles one way.
It's crazy.
And I heard a man make the statement
about a man that was complaining about his church.
And he said, you know, you ought to be thankful
you have a church.
Because I live in a place,
and he noted where he lived,
and he said, I can't hear preaching
that's solid to the Word of God.
I can't be in a place
where we can fellowship with believers
because there's just no church.
I have to listen to, back then when I heard this,
they listened to the church on the radio.
He said, if I want to hear good preaching,
I have to listen to the radio.
He said, so before you complain again about your church,
I want you to consider some things.
Man, that was impactful to me as a young person.
And thinking about the tendency,
listen, it's easy to complain.
I mentioned by way of introduction
that somebody made the observation
that finding fault is one of the easiest things
to find in the world.
Isn't it true?
Man, we can have a wonderful meal,
and there could be 95% of the things
could be just perfect.
I mean, spot on.
But we find fault in that one little thing, right?
It's a tendency of human nature.
We see the tendency.
It's well-documented for the children of Israel.
It's amazing as you look through
and you begin to see all that happens
in the testimony of the children of Israel
and their complaining spirit
and this tendency of theirs.
And again, how we criticize them,
but if we're not careful,
how we also will come to the place
where we imitate them.
We'll get there in just a few minutes,
but it's interesting how that
in the 21st chapter of the book of Numbers.
In fact, why don't you turn over there now?
I want you to look in Numbers 21.
I want you to see just the extent
of this tendency.
It tells us in verse 4 of Numbers 21,
it says,
Now, and they journeyed from Mount Hor
by the way of the Red Sea
to compass the land of Edom.
It says this,
that the soul of the people
was much discouraged because of the way.
The people, they spake against God
and they spake against Moses.
Here's what they said,
Wherefore have you brought us up
out of Egypt to die in the wilderness?
Notice what they say,
For there is no bread,
neither is there any water,
and our soul loatheth this light bread.
Now in their complaint,
they were discouraged about the way.
In their complaint, they said two things.
Number one, there's no bread.
And number two, there's no water.
And then their third complaint
is that our soul hates,
loatheth this light bread.
Now they just got done saying
there was no bread, right?
And now they're saying
our soul loatheth,
hateth this light bread.
What are they referring to?
Manna.
The manna that God graciously
and miraculously provided for them.
The manna that rain from heaven
that we looked at in Exodus 16
when God said,
I'm going to prove them
and I'm going to,
I'm going to rain bread from heaven.
And the people of God
are complaining about the.
provision of God, and we can criticize them.
And by the way, it's okay to criticize them, because God wasn't pleased with them.
And it's not appropriate behavior, but in the very midst of their complaint, it shows
their inconsistency.
It shows that their perspective is wrong.
Notice with me not only the tendency of complaining, but notice the tragedy of complaining.
Go back to Numbers 11, if you will.
I want you to look at the tragedy of complaining.
And honestly, this morning, it is a tragedy when people complain, it really is.
In Numbers 11, the Bible says this in verse number 1, and when the people complained,
notice this, it displeased the Lord.
What is it?
Well, it's their complaining.
It is their complaining that was the reason for God being displeased with them.
It's interesting, as Paul would deal with this truth for the church in Corinth in 1
Corinthians chapter number 10, and you don't need to turn there, but I'll reference two
verses of Scripture in 1 Corinthians 10, in verse number 5, God says this, but with many
of them, God was not well pleased.
In verse number 10, the final example that he uses of the behavior that did not please
the Lord, he says, neither murmur ye, as some of them also murmured and were destroyed
of the destroyer.
The tragedy of complaining, number one, it displeased the Lord.
I don't want to do anything in my life that would displease the Lord.
I didn't say that I never displeased the Lord, I said I don't want to do anything that displeases
the Lord.
And we need to come to that place in our life where we say, I don't want to displease God.
I don't want to displease my Father, because truly God is good and I don't want to displease
Him.
And when He tells us of things in His Word specifically that would displease Him, then
I want to stay far away from that.
I want to avoid it.
Notice, you continue reading in Numbers 11 and verse number 1, it says, and when the
people complained, it displeased the Lord.
But notice this, and the Lord heard it.
The Lord heard it.
You know, God hears everything.
God hears everything.
It's kind of interesting because in the New Testament when it talks about complaining
and murmuring, it kind of has the idea of having something that's just not well-known
and well-documented, something that's done in secret.
But God knows.
God hears.
And the Bible tells us that it displeased the Lord, but it says the Lord heard it.
Isn't it so much better for the Lord to hear the praise of His people?
Seriously.
That He would hear the praise of His people, not the complaints of His people.
It's not for us to complain and we must recognize the tendency, but it's important that we understand
the tragedy of complaining, that it displeases the Lord, that He hears it.
And then notice as we continue in verse number 11, it says, and His anger was kindled.
Oftentimes we see that the complaining of the people of God resulted in severe judgment.
Here in Numbers 11, the Bible tells us that the fire of the Lord burnt among them and
consumed them that were in the uttermost parts of the camp.
The Lord heard their complaining.
The Lord was displeased with their complaining.
And the Lord brought judgment because of their complaining.
Now again, I want to steer clear of the judgment of God.
Amen?
I want to steer clear of the judgment of God.
And we find that there are many examples in which God has given us, especially as we look
in the Old Testament here, with regard to the complaining spirit of the children of
Israel and their tendency to complain, and the tragedy and the results of the severe
judgment.
Here in Numbers 11, again in Numbers chapter 16, you see that there's a plague as a result.
We see the fire at the beginning of the chapter.
You see the plague near the end of the chapter.
And in chapter 16, you see the plague.
In Numbers chapter 12, guess what?
Miriam and Aaron, they're complaining, they're speaking against Moses, and Miriam is stricken
with leprosy.
We find that the Bible tells us in Numbers chapter 16 that those that were complaining,
that the earth opened up and swallowed them.
Wow, amazing, the severe judgment of God.
In Numbers 21 that we looked at just a moment ago where they were complaining and saying
that our soul loatheth this light bread, they had complained about the way, they were discouraged
because of the way in which they had been led by God Almighty.
They were discouraged and they were complaining, and the Bible tells us in verse number 6 of
Numbers 21 that the Lord sent fiery serpents among the people, and they bit the people
and much people of Israel died.
We read about the brazen serpent and how that Moses obeyed the instruction of the Lord and
he gave the instruction of the people that if they were to look, they would live.
And certainly that was accomplished, and you see that at the end of the chapter, or at
the end of the passage in verse number 9, that truth of looking and living.
And we sing the song, Look and Live, and it's certainly derived from this portion of Scripture.
And I want you to think about the complaint of the people and the judgment, the severe
judgment.
They're complaining about no water and no bread and they were discouraged about the
way and God sent fiery serpents.
I bet you all of a sudden they weren't too upset about the way.
They weren't too concerned about the manna, right?
Because now they've got fiery serpents.
This morning as we think about the tragedy of complaining, I want to draw your attention
to a verse in the book of Psalms, Psalm 106, Psalm 106, I want you to think about the impact
of our complaining on others.
I mentioned already that complaining is easy and the tendency of complaining and the fact
that complaining is contagious and we've kind of given some truth with regard to various
circumstances and environments in which complaining takes place.
I want you to think about the way in which our complaining impacts others.
We look in Psalm 106 and the Bible tells us, it's an interesting verse of Scripture in
verse number 25, it's speaking of the children of Israel and going through several of their
things, their history and how they believed.
It's interesting, look in verse 12, they believed, then believed they His words, they
sang His praise.
They soon forgot His works, they waited not for His counsel.
They forgot God in verse 21, their Savior, which had done great things in Egypt.
It's amazing how quickly things can change and how they were remembering and praising
and then they're forgetting because of some circumstances and they're complaining.
It says in verse 24, yea, they despised the pleasant land, they believed not His word,
but murmured in their tents and hearkened not unto the voice of the Lord.
What is representative here of this phraseology, but murmured in their tents, this would be
their dwelling place.
We would say this, it would be in our homes, right?
When you think about the murmuring in our homes and perhaps the impact and the influence
upon a future generation, we've already mentioned the fact that God hears our complaints, but
we must also recognize this morning that there are other people that hear our complaints.
And when they hear our complaints, we must ask ourselves, how does it impact them?
How does it affect them?
What image are we portraying of our God when we're complaining about our circumstances,
when we're complaining about the environment in which God has placed us?
How's it impacting them?
We criticize the children of Israel, why?
Because they're complaining, they're not trusting God, they're not delighting in what God has
provided and how God has directed.
And we can look at their lives and we can criticize them, but the reality is that we
must understand there's this tragic impact of complaining and you think about how others
will hear, again, how wonderful for God to hear the praises of His people.
But even for others that hear our praises as opposed to our complaints, they hear that
our God is good.
I mean, in the midst of a society, again, as we mentioned there in 2 Timothy 3, that
one of the characteristics is that people will be unthankful.
It doesn't take us long as we go through this world to see that there's this complaining
spirit that is prevalent, but when they see something different about you and I, when
they see that we're not complaining about all of the things, the hot topics in the news
this week and what they will be next week and how we complain about all those things,
but they're hearing us sing praise to our God, that He's in control, that He doeth all
things well, that He has a plan, that He has a purpose, that we're not living under the
circumstances, we're living trusting that God is doing all things well.
We see the tragedy of complaining, not only the way in which it displeases the Lord, but
the way in which it impacts others, and certainly complaining has an impact on other people.
This morning we've noted from Numbers 11 the tendency of complaining, the tragedy of complaining.
Number three, I want you to think of this to triumph over complaining.
If we acknowledge this morning that there's a tendency amongst...
the children of Israel.
And if we'd be honest with ourselves
and we'd be honest before the Lord
that we'd say even in our own lives,
for some of us, there's a tendency to complain.
There's this human response to the adversities,
to the difficulties, to the things
that we just flat out don't like, that we just complain.
That we'd understand this morning
that there's that tendency and it's a tragedy,
then I must come to the place where I say,
can I, how can I triumph over this?
How can I have victory over this complaining spirit
that's so prevalent in our society today that impacts me?
Listen, when you go to the workplace
and you hear other people complaining,
even when you set out that today
is going to be the day, I am not gonna complain today.
And then all of a sudden, things happen.
People talk to you.
I can't believe, did you hear what?
And all of a sudden, man, it just, right?
That's how it works.
But look at the book of Philippians, if you will.
Look at the book of Philippians in chapter number two.
How to triumph over complaining,
we could ask ourselves this question, is it even possible?
Is it possible as we live in the midst
of a crooked and perverse generation,
is it possible as we live in the midst of a people
in these last days that will be characterized
as being unthankful and we hear it
and we're bombarded with it,
and you can ask somebody today, hey, how are ya?
It's a little bit too cold.
You ask them yesterday, how are ya?
It's a little bit too hot.
It's a little bit too windy.
I mean, we just complain about everything, right?
In the midst of that type of an environment,
I believe that we as the people of God
can triumph over complaining.
Notice in Philippians two and verse number 14,
notice what God says.
Do all things without murmurings and disputings.
How many things?
All things.
There's really in our minds sometimes in this day
in which we live, we like to separate
the sacred from the secular.
Compartmentalize, if you will.
But the reality is that for the people of God,
there's no real separation between
the sacred and the secular, amen?
And sometimes we think, well, we understand
the importance of the sacred over here
and this is this particular pillar in which we live in,
but then the secular over here.
But the reality is that when he says
do all things without murmurings and disputings,
we're not putting those categories,
we're not separating ourselves,
we're saying I am a child of God, that's who I am,
that's my identification and I belong to him
and I'm to do all things without murmurings and disputings.
Focus on that first thing there,
do all things without murmurings.
And as our subject matter this morning
would lead us to thinking of that truth,
and he says to do all things without murmurings.
Listen, there are some things that are easy
to do without murmuring, right?
There's some things that are just,
it's a delight for us to do them.
It's a joy, it's a privilege,
and it's something that we enjoy doing,
and so therefore, to do that thing,
whatever that thing is, and it's different
for each and every one of us,
it's easy for us to do it without complaining,
without murmuring.
But in like fashion for every single one of us,
there are some things that are a little bit
more difficult to do without murmuring, right?
We know, you know yourself.
I know myself.
And there are tasks, there are things
that sometimes it's some task that we have before us
that it's hard for us to do without murmuring.
It's gonna be a challenge.
And we come to the place where we say,
well, God said do all things,
not do the things I like without murmuring,
not do the things that are easy without murmuring,
not do the things that bring me joy
or bring me satisfaction without murmuring,
but he said do all things without murmurings
and disputings.
And so I think about these murmurings
and these do all things without murmurings,
and we say can we triumph over complaining?
Is it possible?
And I would say yes, absolutely,
with the help of the Lord.
Let me say this, there is no command
that God has given us that he will not enable us to keep.
Amen?
I believe that.
That God has, if he's told us to do all things
without murmurings and disputings,
that with the help of God and by the grace of God,
by his enablement, we are able to do all things
without murmuring.
Even that thing that is the least on our list, right?
We can do it without murmuring, without complaining,
only with the help of God.
Notice, if you will, in 1 Thessalonians chapter five.
I believe that this goes hand in hand
and we're familiar with the latter part
of 1 Thessalonians five and how many
just simple verses of scripture
and just commands and instructions that are given
in these closing verses of scripture.
In verse number 18, a familiar verse,
the Bible says in everything give thanks
for this is the will of God and Christ Jesus concerning you.
Why would I use this verse of scripture
in connection with this spirit of complaining
and this tendency to complain,
the tragedy that is associated with complaining
and how we would have victory over complaining?
It's that we change our perspective.
It's that we come to the place where in everything
we give thanks.
Why?
For this is the will of God and Christ Jesus concerning you.
I have the privilege of fill in the blank.
I remember hearing years ago,
it was an account that was given
while I was still in Bible college
and I think it was kind of given to us as a primer
to help us have the right response
if we were to encounter this situation.
But it was a situation in which a young man
was interviewing for a ministry position
and this particular pastor that would interview
for this position, every time in the midst of the interview,
he would have his secretary call in
and tell him that there was an overflowing toilet
in the men's bathroom and they needed immediate assistance
just to see how the one being interviewed would respond.
Would they go and help?
Would they not?
And it's kind of interesting how we say,
in everything give thanks,
for this is the will of God and Christ Jesus concerning you
that we can rejoice that God's given us the opportunity.
As I mentioned, we complain about the gas prices
but God's provided for us.
Thank you, Lord.
Well, I got to dip into my savings.
I heard somebody say that when I was in Tennessee.
It was no one of you, nobody that I even knew.
Ah, I got to dip into my savings.
Hey, what about being thankful you have a savings?
That God provided for you in abundance
at some time previous so that you could have a savings.
Right, it's a change of perspective is really what it is.
You think about Joseph in Egypt.
There were seven years of plenty.
If God had not graciously given that dream to Pharaoh
and God had not enabled Joseph to interpret that dream,
what do you think the Egyptians would have done
for those seven years of plenty?
They would have feasted.
And then what would have happened
in the seven years of famine?
They would have died.
It wouldn't have lasted seven years, right?
Because they wouldn't have had enough.
And so God provides graciously.
And as he provides, we see that his provision
sometimes is immediate.
Sometimes his provision was years ago
on allowing us to be in the position
where we can handle what God has allowed to happen.
I understand there's all reasons.
Listen, everybody wants to point fingers
about gas prices today.
Everybody.
Point fingers.
It's this person's fault.
This thing, blah, blah, blah, right?
And oh, it's easy for us to get caught into the trap.
Right?
I use that because it's just so prevalent right now.
They got little stickers on gas pumps all over the place
that you go to pump gas.
I mean, it's just, it's crazy what's going on.
And if we're not careful, we can fall into the same trap.
And so how do we triumph over complaining?
It's possible because God said, let all things be done.
Do all things without murmurings and disputings.
So if he's given me a command,
he also will enable me to meet that, to keep that command.
And it's that change of perspective
that God is good all the time.
All the time, God is good.
We find ourselves in this situation
as we sing about the goodness of God.
And it was really sweet this morning in Sunday school
singing that song, God is so good.
And I could just hear the voice of the people.
I mean, I believe we believe it.
God is good.
God was good to the children of Israel, was he not?
It didn't stop them from complaining though.
They complained about the very provision of God Almighty.
They complained about the very direction of God Almighty.
They complained about what God had provided for them
and how God had directed them.
Instead of rejoicing,
instead of expecting that God would work great,
There's a pastor friend that I know, when you chat with him as soon as you, you know,
some people have these interesting responses when you say, hey, how are you?
You see somebody, you talk to them on the phone, you see them in person, you shake their
hand and ask how they're doing.
For Mr. Don, it's absolutely wonderful.
Most of us have gotten to the point where we've understood that and we've heard that.
We have some people, thankfully none that are part of our congregation, at least not
that I've heard that I've experienced in the past that say, well, under the circumstances,
you know, it's kind of that Eeyore personality of, oh, bother, right?
Things are just kind of, and, you know, you see these different people, some people say
this, how are you?
Hey, I'm better than I deserve.
You ever heard somebody say that?
I've heard people say, I like that response, I'm better than I deserve.
This pastor friend of mine, as you chat with him, he'll say this, when you ask him how
he's doing, he'll say, if I complained, I'd be lying.
That's what he says.
It's kind of catchy.
It's kind of like thought provoking.
I've never heard anyone say that before when I've greeted them, but when I greet him, he'll
say, well, brother man, if I'd complain, I'd be lying.
That's what he says.
You know what he means by that?
God is good.
And so if I complain, I'm lying, because I'm saying that God isn't good.
Because whatever I'm complaining about, ultimately, my charge is against God.
How many times did the children of Israel complain toward Moses and toward Aaron?
But who really was their complaint directed at?
It was directed at God.
I mean, think about Moses just for a moment.
And I'm going to close with this.
Jim, I'm going to mess you up, because I'm going to come down here, and he's got to move
the camera all around.
But I want you to think about Moses.
The people come to Moses and say, you led us here.
Moses is like, you don't see the pillar?
What do you mean, I led you here?
Do you not see the pillar?
We were following the pillar, right?
But who are the people complaining against?
Well, they want to complain about Moses.
Why?
They don't really want to complain.
Now, sometimes they did complain directly about God.
But typically, we want to complain about someone human, not about God.
But the reality is that if God had provided the human leader, Moses, and had provided
the direction, then as they complained about Moses, really, their complaint was about God.
Do we believe that God is sovereign?
He is.
We believe He's in control.
He's sitting on His throne.
He knows exactly what's going on in the world today.
He's not surprised by anything that's going on in the world today.
We believe all that, right?
So when we begin to complain about what's taking place, who ultimately are we complaining
about?
God.
When we complain, I almost hit that cello.
That would have been a big mistake.
Is that yours?
That would have been a really big mistake.
Steve, I'd just say, sorry.
I've got to live with Brianna.
Amen.
That just messed me all up.
But the reality is that when we complain, we're complaining about God.
We come to the place where we say, you know what?
I want to have victory in this area of my life.
I know there's a tendency on the part of us as human beings to complain.
If we're not careful and if we don't guard against it, every single one of us can fall
prey to complaining.
We really can.
We can just come to the place where we just get into that rut, complain about this and
complain about that.
We see it in our society, but it ought not be amongst the people of God.
Amen?
It ought not be amongst the people of God.
Why?
Because our God is good all of the time.
Before I almost ran into the cello, I was going to go to the book of Daniel.
I won't take time to do it at this point, but you think about the truth that God gives
in the book of Daniel with regard to God being in control of the affairs of mankind.
We complain about our government leadership.
Listen, those people are only in place because God's allowed them to be in place.
I've said this before.
In fact, just a few weeks ago, I said as we preached on the subject of prayer, what place
does prayer have in our lives?
God said that we're to pray for those in leadership.
We're to pray for those that are in authority.
It's easier to complain about them, right?
You got a bad boss.
It's easier to complain about them than to pray for them.
And this morning, when the people complained, it displeased the Lord.
He heard them, and His anger was kindled against them.
It's tragic, but I'm thankful this morning that we can triumph.
We can be victorious over this matter of complaining, and oh, that God would help us.
Let's pray together.
We thank You for the Word of God.
We thank You for the truth, and we thank You for how You've provided these Old Testament
records and samples, as Paul said to the believers in Corinth, for our admonition, for our instruction,
that we would learn, even from this particular message this morning, that which would displease
You.
And Lord, I pray that as we would take a few moments this morning to honestly evaluate
our lives, that as we would take the time to let a man examine himself, that it's easy
for us to criticize those that complain.
It's easy for us to criticize the children of Israel for their complaining, but far too
often we imitate their behavior.
For all that You've done for us, for how good You've been to us, how sad that we would complain.
I pray that You'd help us as we evaluate our own lives personally to be honest.
God that we'd be able to identify if there's that tendency in our lives, that we'd run
to You seeking Your help so that we might triumph over it, that we would not get caught
up in these complaining sessions, these workplace, church house, wherever it might be, but God
we'd look to You and see how good You are and how good You've been, that we'd do all
things without murmurings.
Would You move and work as only You can, help us Lord to be honest with You, to be
doers of the Word, we'll thank You for it.
Would You stand with me?
Heads are out, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano.
As she does, the altar's open.
Maybe for someone there's confession that needs to take place, there's been complaining
and you want to just come get it right with God.
Maybe for someone this morning there's a recognition of that tendency and you want
God to help you so that you can triumph and you maybe need to visit this altar this morning
and ask God to just protect you and help you to prevent you from falling into that complaining
spirit.
Maybe God's spoken to your heart in some other way.
Maybe you just want to come and thank Him this morning.
But as Kimberly plays, the altar is open.