1 John chapter number two and verse number six.
And we, of course, this Wednesday is actually
our fourth week dealing with this thought
from 1 John chapter two and verse number six.
And we've been dealing for a number of months now
here on Wednesday evenings with this series
doing what we ought to do.
And a few weeks ago, as we started looking
at 1 John chapter number six, we said this,
that we ought to walk as Christ walked.
And we gather that from this verse of scripture
in 1 John two and verse six.
The Bible says, he that saith he abideth in him,
notice, ought himself also so to walk even as he walked.
And of course, as we've gone through these last few weeks,
we said that Jesus walked wisely, he walked humbly,
he walked purposefully.
And last week we dealt with the subject
that he walked courageously.
And I'm thankful for the opportunity
that we have to study the New Testament
and specifically with regard to this thought
as dealing with walking as Christ walked,
that we have the gospel records
that have been provided for us
so that we can see how Christ lived his life,
how he walked, how he left us an example
that we should follow his steps.
And so this evening, it's the fifth point
in this little mini series,
but it's the only one that we'll look at tonight.
I want you to consider this truth,
Jesus walked compassionately.
He walked compassionately.
And go back to the book of Mark, if you will,
we're gonna look at two passages of scripture
in the gospels to prove the point
that our Lord walked with compassion
and dealing with that subject
and then what it means for us, for you and for me
to also walk with compassion.
How is it that we can walk with compassion as Christ did?
What does that look like?
What does it mean?
And so notice, if you will,
there in Mark chapter number one,
pick it up with me in verse number 40.
The Bible says this,
and there came a leper to him,
beseeching him and kneeling down to him
and saying unto him,
if thou wilt, thou canst make me clean.
I want you to notice several things about this leper.
We're gonna look at verse 41 and 42 in just a moment
as we deal with how Christ walked compassionately.
But I want you to notice just a few things about this leper
as the Bible tells us in verse number 40
that there was this leper.
And of course, we understand the difficulty with leprosy
and the problem during,
especially in this particular time and what's going on.
The Bible says that he came to Jesus,
notice, beseeching him, begging,
and kneeling down to him.
And then notice what he says at the end of verse number 40.
He says, if thou wilt, thou canst make me clean.
And I love the way that this leper approaches
the Lord Jesus Christ,
because he obviously understood something
about the power of the Lord Jesus Christ.
He understood that Christ had the power to heal him.
That's pretty amazing.
And you see the faith of the individual coming and asking,
he's not gonna ask if he doesn't think it's possible.
And he says that he knew this,
he had this understanding, if thou wilt.
Now, listen, we have to recognize
it's gotta be within God's will.
Amen.
And God can do anything.
And there are times in which,
and we find the scripture say
that we're to pray according to his will.
And we understand that principle.
And here this leper says, if thou wilt,
thou canst make me clean.
And notice what Jesus in the response in verse 41,
the Bible says in Jesus, notice this,
moved with compassion.
He put forth his hand and touched him
and saith unto him, I will, be thou clean.
I want you to notice where the Bible says
that he was moved with compassion.
We find that that word compassion,
that emotion, if you will,
it carries with it the idea of painful sympathy.
It's really a mixed passion
compounded of both love and sorrow.
And we come up with this truth of the Lord Jesus Christ,
he's moved with compassion,
he sees the condition of this individual.
And here in Mark chapter number one,
we find that Jesus is moved with compassion
because of a physical need,
because of a physical ailment,
because of something that was wrong
with this man physically, he was a leper.
And this was a serious condition, a serious situation.
And the Bible says that Jesus is moved with compassion.
He puts forth his hand and he simply says this
after he touches him, by the way,
that's amazing in of itself
because you wouldn't touch a leper.
And he touched him and he said, I will, be thou clean.
Now, I believe that the leper probably was pretty thankful
that he asked Jesus, amen.
You know, what does he say?
You have not because you ask not.
Is that what the scriptures teach us?
The scriptures also teach us that you have not
because you ask amiss.
And so we understand those two principles,
but I want you to see here that this leper
had the courage and boldness to ask
and Jesus says, I will be thou clean.
And as soon, verse 42, as he had spoken immediately,
the leprosy departed from him and he was cleansed.
And we see here that Jesus walked compassionately.
We had visited this passage of scripture
a couple of weeks ago when we spoke about the fact
that Jesus walked purposefully,
that everything that Jesus did was with a purpose
and on purpose and for a purpose.
And here as we continue through Mark chapter number one
and we come to this truth that he walked compassionately.
I said this last Wednesday evening
that as we look at these various aspects
of how Christ walked, that what we have to understand
is that oftentimes they were all intertwined
one with the other.
He walked purposefully, he walked courageously,
he walked compassionately.
Those are the last three that we've dealt with.
He walked in wisdom.
We talked about the fact that he walked wisely.
He walked humbly.
And so as we look at those things
and we see how they're interconnected one with the other
and here because of a physical condition,
Jesus is moved with compassion.
Notice, if you will, back in the gospel of Matthew
in Matthew chapter number nine.
And we find that the Bible would share with us
a familiar passage of scripture,
one in which we're very familiar with in Matthew chapter nine
and it's a passage that we often reference
at least the latter part of verses 37 and 38
where Jesus gives the instruction
about the harvest being plenteous and the laborers are few.
But I want you to notice if you begin reading in Matthew nine
in verse number 36, the Bible says,
but when he, speaking of Jesus, saw the multitudes.
Notice what the Bible says.
He was moved with compassion on them.
He was moved with compassion in Mark one.
And here in Matthew nine,
the Bible says that he saw the multitudes
and he was moved with compassion on them.
Notice why, because they fainted
and were scattered abroad as sheep having no shepherd.
We find that Jesus then looks to his disciples
and he says to his disciples,
the harvest truly is plenteous, but the laborers are few.
Pray therefore the Lord of the harvest
that he will send forth laborers into his harvest.
If it was true then, it is true now.
And we see it in such a great light this evening
that indeed the harvest is plenteous,
but the laborers are few.
And we're reminded of that regularly.
I was at a pastor's meeting,
the monthly AIBF meeting that I attend.
And yesterday I was there
and heard more about churches without pastors
and that situation that's going on in mission fields
and missionaries coming home and so on and so forth.
But I want you to notice that before we ever get that truth
that Jesus gives to the disciples in verse 37 and 38,
that we're told that Jesus, he saw the multitudes
and he was moved with compassion.
I would believe and I would say it this way,
that in Mark chapter number one,
Jesus was moved with compassion over a physical need.
But here in Matthew chapter number nine,
I believe that Jesus is moved with compassion
over a spiritual need.
And we find that he says,
because they were as sheep scattered abroad
without a shepherd.
And we find that he then says
to pray to the Lord of the harvest
that he would send forth laborers into his harvest.
And so we'd see the spiritual aspect
of this particular text of scripture and the purpose.
There's many other examples that we could go to
within the gospels in which Jesus moved with compassion
and we see the compassion of our God.
And we can rejoice that God tells us in his word
that he is compassionate.
And we see that declaration,
but it's one thing to see and to hear where God says,
I am a compassionate God.
It's a whole nother thing to see him moved with compassion
and to see how he
how that compassion is visible through his actions.
And so we find here in the text of scripture
that there's a spiritual situation, a spiritual need
that leads to the Lord Jesus Christ
being moved with compassion.
He knew their spiritual condition.
He was aware of their spiritual need
and he's moved with compassion.
Can I tell you this evening that both the physical
and the spiritual should have an influence
and an impact on us?
And it's amazing to me how easy it is
for people to be moved with compassion at physical needs
but not at spiritual needs.
And can I tell you this evening
that the greatest need of humanity is a spiritual need?
And I don't say that to minimize the physical needs
that individuals have.
I don't say that to minimize or to overlook
the fact that there are people that are hungry,
there are people that need clothing
and I understand that and so do you
but the reality is that you can feed someone,
you can clothe someone, you can teach someone,
you can give someone an education,
you can provide for them a job
and you can provide housing and so on and so forth
but if you never tell them about Jesus and about their soul
then what's gonna happen is they're gonna die
and then go to a Christless eternity
and all we've really done is made their life here
a little bit more comfortable.
Does that make sense tonight?
And I wanna say that with compassion
and I hope that it's being received
in the way that I'm seeking to communicate it this evening
because no doubt the physical need is real
and there are individuals with physical needs
but even as our missionaries and at times
as we've had opportunity to help in certain situations
with physical needs, our goal is not to stop
at the physical, our goal is also to try
to meet the spiritual need
because that's the greatest need
and so we find this evening
that Jesus, he walked compassionately.
So what's the, we see the truth,
we see the example in both of these passages of scripture
in Mark one and in Matthew nine
where he was moved with compassion
in Mark's gospel a physical condition or need,
in Matthew's gospel because of a spiritual condition or need
and so what is the instruction for us this evening?
Where is it that we find that we too are to walk
or to live with compassion?
Turn to the book of Luke if you will in the 10th chapter.
In Luke chapter number 10,
this too is a familiar passage of scripture
and I want you to see this truth
that is given to us this evening
in this portion of scripture with regard to us
and the need for us to be compassionate
with those that we come in contact with.
You're there in Luke chapter number 10,
the Bible says this beginning in verse number 30,
and Jesus answering said,
a certain man went down from Jerusalem.
He went from Jerusalem to Jericho and he fell among thieves
which stripped him of his raiment and wounded him
and departed leaving him half dead.
Can I pause just for a moment and let you know
that this did happen regularly.
This was a situation that Jesus is teaching
and it's something that they could identify with
and relate with that this was something
that took place on occasion.
And so we find that Jesus as he's answering
the one that says who is my neighbor
according to verse 29,
we find that Jesus gives him this scenario if you will,
and he says that this man, he was robbed,
he was left for dead, he was half dead, verse 31,
and by chance there came down a certain priest that way.
And so we find that the Bible says
that there's this certain priest that goes
and as he's journeying, Jesus as he's speaking to this man
and giving him the truth, he goes that way,
the way in which this man was left
and it says and when he saw him,
he passed by on the other side.
That's interesting, is it not?
The Bible clearly tells us that Jesus
in speaking to this man, he says he saw him.
You're in a situation where you try to act
like you didn't see something
because you don't want to be bothered by it,
you want to just be able to keep on going,
well, it says he saw him.
And he passed by on the other side
and likewise, so that was a priest in verse 32,
likewise a Levite, when he was at the place,
came and looked on him and passed by on the other side.
That's a step worse in my mind,
he didn't just see him as the priest did in verse 31,
but the Bible says that this Levite,
he comes at the same place and he looked on him.
There's a difference between seeing something
and looking at something, would you agree?
and looking at something.
And listen, there's some things you can't help seeing,
but you can choose what you look at, amen?
That's why Jesus in Hebrews, it says looking unto Jesus.
It's a decision, a choice that we make
on where we fix our gaze upon.
And here the Bible says that this Levite,
he came and he looked on him
and passed by on the other side.
Verse 33, but a certain Samaritan as he journeyed
came where he was.
And when he saw him, notice what it says,
he had compassion on him.
Now, we understand and we don't have time this evening
to deal with all of the background
with regard to how the Jewish people viewed the Samaritans
and all that's taking place with regard to Jesus
talking about a priest and a Levite
and then a Samaritan in verse 33.
But we find that the Samaritan, it says of him
that he saw him and he had compassion on him.
And notice it says, and went to him and bound up his wounds,
pouring in oil and wine and set him on his own beast
and brought him to an inn and took care of him.
By the way, what you read in verse 34 and following
is what reveals the compassion.
We can say that we have compassion,
but it's seen in our actions.
Just as the case was with Jesus,
he had compassion on the man, so what did he do?
He touched him and he healed him.
He had compassion on those that were scattered
without a shepherd, and so what does he say?
Pray to the Lord of the harvest, by the way, who is that?
It's Jesus, that he would send forth labors.
You know that that's a prayer that God answers.
God calls people and God sends people.
And here we find that in verse number 35,
it continues and says, and on the morrow when he departed,
he took out two pence and gave them to the host
and said unto him, take care of him
and whatsoever thou spendest more when I come again,
I will repay thee.
Verse 36, Jesus says, which now of these three
thinkest thou was neighbor unto him
that fell among the thieves and he said,
he that showed mercy on him, then said Jesus unto him,
notice, go and do thou likewise.
I read an account years ago of a school of theology
where the students in a particular class
were tasked in this particular day
to come and to give a sermon.
It was a short sermon that each of the individuals
in the class were to give on this passage of scripture.
And the professor set a trap.
And here's what the professor did.
The professor gave the assignment
that here's the text of scripture
that you're gonna preach a little sermon on in class.
But what he did is he had something staged along the way
where there was a fellow student that was in need.
And everyone that was in that class
that was to preach on that particular text of scripture
passed right by their fellow student in need
so that they could get to class and preach a sermon
on the Good Samaritan.
Isn't that interesting?
The reality is that we find here in the text of scripture
that this illustration that Jesus gives
of the one, this Samaritan, that what did he do?
Well, because of his compassion,
because he saw someone in need,
and again, here in our text of scripture,
this is a physical need.
This is a physical need.
Well, the reality this evening
is that we can't meet everyone's physical need.
You understand that?
The physical needs of this world
far surpass our ability individually
or even collectively to be able to even begin to help.
It's amazing.
And we find that it requires much wisdom and discernment
with regard to several of those things,
and I don't wanna get into all of that this evening,
but if you have questions,
I'd be more than happy to discuss that with you
with regard to just having wisdom and discernment
on where is it that I help?
What is it that I help with?
And where's a need that I can try to help and satisfy?
But we find here that Jesus uses this account,
and he gives this parable, if you will.
with regard to this lawyer that was asking these questions,
and Jesus is painting this picture
and helping to illustrate, and then he says,
go and do thou likewise, in verse number 37.
And so we see here the instruction
with regard to our response
and being able to minister to individuals
and seeing a physical need
and where it is that God would allow us
to have opportunity to be able to help with those things,
by having compassion.
But now I want you to turn to the book of Jude, if you will.
Turn to the book of Jude,
and as you turn to the book of Jude,
it's only one chapter,
but what a power-packed chapter of God's word this is.
The book of Jude, just a, again, a very short letter,
25 verses in the book of Jude,
but you could spend just about a verse a week
going through it and really getting what God has for us
throughout this text of scripture.
We find that as you begin looking through this short epistle
that there's an introduction that's given
with regard to the reason, really, for the writing,
and you see that in the very beginning
where it says in verse three
that it was needful for me,
right in the middle of the verse,
to write unto you and to exhort you
that you should earnestly contend for the faith
which was once delivered unto the saints.
Why?
Why is there this epistle, this short letter
that's being written to help these individuals
to earnestly contend for the faith?
Well, because in verse number four,
there are certain men crept in unawares
who were before of old ordained to this condemnation,
ungodly men, turning the grace of our God into lasciviousness
and denying the only Lord God and our Lord Jesus Christ,
and we find that then after the introduction is given
with regard to the reason for the writing
that the text begins to deal with
and exposing false teachers.
We find that as the text deals with the false teachers,
he uses examples from Old Testament,
he goes through and provides descriptions
and dealing with the judgments and so on and so forth,
and we see that really all the way to verse number 16,
and then you find that beginning in verse number 17,
it really changes a course, if you will,
the direction of the letter,
because in verse 17, it says, but beloved,
and so now after the instruction is given
with regard to the false teachers
that have crept in unawares and how they're operating
and all of those things,
the examples from the Old Testament
so that we could understand how they behave
and what their tactics are,
but also how God dealt with them,
we then find that he says, but beloved,
and so the letter is now going back to the believers
with regard to how they are to live
and really some instruction for us,
and I want you to notice that the Bible tells us
in verse 17, but beloved, remember ye the words
which were spoken before the apostles
of our Lord Jesus Christ,
how that they told you there should be mockers
in the last time who should walk
after their own ungodly lust.
Now isn't that interesting?
We've been studying in 2 Timothy chapter number three,
what does it begin with in verse number one?
This know also, and we dealt with that two weeks ago
on Sunday morning, and so hey, God has informed us,
he's let us know that there are going to be mockers.
Peter, in 2 Peter chapter three,
he talks about the scoffers and the mockers,
and so he says they're going to walk
after their own ungodly lust,
and so God has already told us that.
He says, remember that you've been told these things,
verse 19, these be they who separate themselves,
sensual, having not the spirit,
but again, notice he says, but ye, beloved,
building up yourselves on your most holy faith,
praying in the Holy Ghost, and so we find that again,
listen, this is going to happen.
We knew about these false teachers.
God informed us.
He let us know about this, but what do we do?
Do we just give up, give in, say, well, all hope is gone?
No, we build up ourselves.
Timothy says, continue.
That's what Paul says to Timothy in 2 Timothy three.
Listen, just because evil men and seducers
are going to wax worse and worse,
it doesn't mean you give up and give in.
It means you continue,
and you stand in the face of the opposition.
Verse 21, keep yourselves in the love of God.
By the way, aren't you thankful that there's nothing
that can separate us from the love of God?
I mean, praise the Lord.
Jesus loves me, this I know, for the Bible tells me so,
and I know it's a little kid's Sunday school song,
but man, it's a precious song.
I love the song that we sing, Jesus Loves Even Me,
and many things in the Bible I read,
but this is the dearest,
that Jesus loves me, isn't that a wonderful song?
And praise the Lord for it,
and so here it says, keep yourselves in the love of God,
looking for the mercy of our Lord Jesus Christ
unto eternal life,
and then notice what the Bible says in verse 22,
and of some, have compassion making a difference.
Verse 23, and others, save with fear,
pulling them out of the fire,
hating even the garment spotted by the flesh.
When I read verse 22 and 23, and of course we see,
and we've mentioned many times it's,
there's actually a song that we sang years ago
from verse 22, called to make a difference,
and certainly we are called to make a difference,
and he says in verse 22, and of some,
have compassion making a difference.
Others, save with fear, pulling them out of the fire,
hating even the garment spotted by the flesh.
You ever found if you, as you've tried,
and attempted to share the gospel with people,
that the same approach doesn't work with everyone?
The same approach doesn't work,
I don't mean the gospel doesn't work with everyone,
obviously the gospel is the power of God unto salvation,
I'm not saying that we change our message,
I'm simply saying that our approach to them,
how we begin to communicate to them the truth of the gospel,
is going to vary based upon the individual.
And here the Bible says in verse 22,
and of some, have compassion.
You know, I find sometimes that maybe it's challenging
at times for us to have compassion on individuals,
because we really don't have the heart of Christ,
but we really look at them, I said this several weeks ago,
as being our enemies.
And I said this when I preached that text of scripture
on a Sunday morning, I said this,
that David never made Saul his enemy,
but Saul made David his enemy continually.
The Bible tells us in 1 Corinthians 2 and verse 14,
that the natural man receiveth not the things
of the Spirit of God, for there are foolishness unto him,
neither can he know them,
because they are spiritually discerned.
And sometimes what happens is because somebody
has a completely different worldview than we do,
they believe something entirely different than we do,
we look at them perhaps as being an enemy,
and we don't have compassion on them.
But the Bible says of some, have compassion,
making a difference.
It's amazing to me how blind, listen,
we understand 2 Corinthians 4, the God of this world,
that's a little g, God of this world, that's Satan,
hath blinded the minds of them which believe not,
lest the light of the glorious gospel
should shine in unto them.
When we approach people and begin to talk to them
about the Lord Jesus Christ, we must not approach them
and take this approach that I'm better than you.
No, we need to be compassionate,
because we understand their condition,
we understand they've been blinded,
we understand there's a spiritual battle
that's taking place for the soul of that individual,
and the enemy has done everything possible
to be able to keep them blinded to the truth of the gospel,
and then we come along and we have an opportunity
through whatever means it is,
whether it's just door knocking in a complete stranger,
or it's a neighbor, or it's a coworker,
or maybe even a family member,
but we show them the love of Christ.
We have compassion, why?
Because we understand what happens to that individual
if they die without Christ.
We've read the entirety of the Bible,
we've read Revelation chapter 20,
we're familiar with the judgment,
the great white throne judgment,
and we know that, and therefore,
we ought to have some compassion.
I said this before years ago,
and I believe that it's something that you've heard
from other sources as well, even within other contexts,
but the reality is that people in general
don't really care how much you know
until they know how much you care.
And I find that to be a biblical philosophy,
though you won't find those exact words in the scriptures,
you will find that the Apostle Paul,
as he went to minister in the city of Thessalonica,
as you read the book of 1 Thessalonians,
you find that the Apostle Paul was a man
that moved and worked with compassion.
He was a man that the Bible tells us,
in fact, turn over.
and just look at it, in 1 Thessalonians chapter number one and two, notice what the Bible tells
us about Paul's ministry there in Thessalonica, because I believe it's important for us to
understand of some have compassion making a difference. We ought to love people,
to understand, listen, remember what's the compassion? Painful sympathy,
a mixed passion compounded of love and sorrow. I remember Chris asking me years ago,
why do you care about me? Why do you care so much? It's because you're going to die one day,
and I know what the Bible teaches, and if you die without Christ, you're going to spend
eternity in the lake of fire. We ought to be compassionate about that. The Bible says in
the book of 1 Thessalonians, notice in chapter number one, the Bible says in verse number four,
knowing, brethren, beloved, your election of God, for our gospel came not unto you in word only,
but also in power to the Holy Ghost, and in much assurance, as you know,
what manner of men we were among you, notice, for your sake. And so we find that in verse number
five, Paul talks about the gospel coming to them. It came in word and in power of the Holy Ghost,
with much assurance, but also notice he says, and what, and you know, what manner of men we were
among you, for your sake. And so Paul gives us some insight in verse number five, as to the
approach of ministry there in the city of Thessalonica. You could go back to Acts 17,
and you can read it during the second missionary journey, and you find there's not much given to
us there, because they're just there for about three Sabbaths, is what the Bible says. And so we
find that they got saved. The Bible says in verse number six, and you became followers of us, and of
the Lord, having received the word, and much affliction with joy of the Holy Ghost. And these
people got saved. And so why did they get saved? Well, just because they were kind men that came
to the city of Thessalonica? No. Showing up as a kind person, and bringing some bread with you,
and some, that's not going to save anybody. Amen? We see the manner that they came, according to
verse number five, but they came with the gospel. Now, if they come with the gospel, and they come
with a terrible attitude, and they come condemning, and all kinds of, are the people going to listen?
Are they going to be receptive? Do you understand? Can you, are you following tonight? And so we find
that the Bible says that they became followers of us, and of the Lord. They received the word,
and much affliction with joy of the Holy Ghost. Notice in chapter number two, the Bible says this,
in verse number two, it says, but even after that we had suffered before, and were shamefully
entreated, as you know at Philippi, we were bold in our God to speak unto you the gospel of God
with much contention. For our exhortation was not of deceit, nor of uncleanness, nor in guile,
but as we were allowed of God to be put in trust with the gospel, even so we speak,
not as pleasing men, but God which trieth the hearts, and so we trieth our hearts. So we understand
that even though they came in with a certain manner in verse number five of chapter one, and
we're going to get there in just a couple of more verses to really give you the full picture of what
this manner or behavior was in which they entered into the city, they came not just as nice people
bringing some, they came bringing the gospel, but their manner was appropriate, their position
and disposition. Could I use those two words tonight? We could track and follow that.
Listen, the position is important, Jesus alone, grace alone. Amen? Is that what the Bible teaches?
Jesus said, I am the way, the truth, and the life. No man cometh unto the Father but by me.
But what's our disposition is we have the right position, we need to have the right
disposition having that manner. And so Paul says, as we were allowed of God,
notice what he says in verse four of chapter two, to be put in trust with the gospel,
even so we speak. So he didn't change the message in order to be liked. Are you tracking?
Notice he says in verse number four, not as pleasing men, but God which trieth our hearts.
So Paul says, we want to have the right disposition, but we can't sacrifice our position
for our disposition. All right? So we have to speak the truth. We understand that we have to
please God. We're not just trying to please men. You know what happens when you try to please men?
Number one, you go insane because you can't do it. But number two, you start watering things down.
Because you know what we find in second Timothy chapter number four, the time will come when they
will not endure, what does it say? Sound doctrine. Amen? And so we have to be careful. So Paul says
this is what we do. But notice as we continue in verse five, he says, for neither at any time
used be flattering words, as ye know, nor a cloak of covetousness. God is witness. Nor of men
sought we glory, neither of you nor yet of others, when we might have been burdensome as apostles of
Christ. And here it is. Here's the manner that he speaks of in chapter one in verse number five.
But we were gentle among you, even as a nurse cherisheth her children. So being affectionately
desirous, notice what it says, of you. We were willing to have imparted unto you, not the gospel
of God only, but also our own souls. Why? Because ye were dear unto us. That portion of scripture
is so impactful to me because it helps us understand a proper philosophy of ministry.
We've got to have the right position, but we also have to have the right disposition.
And we have to understand that compassion goes a long way. You know when somebody knows that
you love them and you care about them, like you truly care about their soul.
It makes a difference on how they listen to your message. It makes a difference.
Because they can see a genuine concern and a care and a compassion. And I believe that the
apostle Paul, I believe that he ministered with compassion. I don't believe that any of those that
he ministered to could honestly say, I know that people accused him in the attacks and so on and
so forth that came, but I don't think they could accuse him and it be just an accusation that he
didn't care about people. He cared about them. He cared about them. And this evening, our Lord and
Savior, he walked compassionately. By the way, I'm thankful for his compassion that he had on me.
Amen? And God has called us to walk as Christ walked, and we see all of these things on how
he walked, but we see tonight that he walked compassionately. So as I examine my life, as you
examine your life, we must ask ourselves this question, am I walking with compassion?
Is it obvious to others when I come in contact with them that I really, truly care? Or do we see
people as problems in my way? Do we have a situation like the disciples, hey Lord, they're
hungry and the day is far spent, send them home. Because we don't want to be bothered with it.
But what does Jesus say? Give them something to eat. Right? Give them something to eat.
And this evening, we cannot walk compassionately without walking in the Spirit.
We cannot show the love of Christ without walking in the Spirit. We absolutely must abide in him.
Remember, it starts in 1 John 2 and verse 6, he that saith he abideth in him. The gospel of John,
15th chapter, we're to abide in him. And as we're walking with him and we're walking in the Spirit,
God enables us to have and to walk with compassion. Let's pray tonight. Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us. Thank you for your Word, the truth contained therein. I pray that
you'd help us tonight. Lord, as we see the example of our Lord and Savior, I pray that you'd help us
also to receive the instruction for us to be compassionate, Lord, of some have compassion
making a difference. And God, help us to never sacrifice our position simply for sake of a
disposition. But God, I pray that our disposition would align properly even as we see there
in 1 Thessalonians. Help us, Lord, to walk with compassion. Thank you for the privilege of prayer.
I pray that you'd bless our time for it's in Christ's name we pray. Amen.