chapter number three, 2 Thessalonians chapter number three,
and I'll be looking at verse number 13 this evening.
And as you know, on Wednesday evenings,
the last couple of weeks, of course,
last Wednesday was Missions Conference,
the week before I had a lesson, a message,
kind of preparation, if you will, for Missions Conference.
And so this evening, after being away from the series
for a couple of weeks, we're returning to our series,
Walk Worthy, Please God.
And we studied through the latter part
of 1 Thessalonians chapter number five,
and after we completed that, we began studying
the latter part of 2 Thessalonians chapter number three,
and this is lesson number 21 in this series
of Walk Worthy, Please God.
We understand, and just to kind of give a quick review,
since we've been away from the book for a couple of weeks,
there were some in Thessalonica that were needed
to have their behavior corrected.
We found that in our previous two lessons,
we dealt with the subject matter of disorderly behavior,
and also dealt with the subject of busybodies,
as we looked at verse six of chapter three
down through verse number 12.
And we took two weeks to look
at those two particular subjects,
and so we understood that there were some
within the church that needed to be corrected.
Their behavior was not right,
their behavior was not pleasing to the Lord,
and therefore, it needed to be corrected.
We find, however, as we continue to study here
and looking at our verse this evening,
that there were some there in Thessalonica
that were doing right, and they were to be
not corrected, but commended.
And I'm thankful for those that do right.
I'm thankful for the acknowledgement
that we see this evening in this verse of scripture,
and we're encouraged to know
that there were some in the church.
Of course, we know that the church is a good church,
it's a model church, and we find that there were those
that were there that were walking disorderly
and Paul corrects them and gives the instruction
of the church on how to deal with that.
But as we come to verse number 13,
we are encouraged to know that there were,
I'm sure, many there that were not only doing right,
but we find that as they're acknowledged
for their right behavior, their well-doing,
that we, too, are encouraged by this verse of scripture.
Notice in verse number 13, it's a simple verse
of scripture, the Bible says,
but ye, brethren, be not weary in well-doing.
But ye, brethren, be not weary in well-doing.
The word weary means to faint.
It carries the idea of to be utterly spiritless
or to be exhausted.
We find that here, the word well-doing means to do well
or to act uprightly, and so Paul is giving,
after the correction in verses six through 12
of those that were not behaving properly,
he then changes his attention and he says,
but ye, brethren, be not weary in well-doing.
And I find this evening that this is a great charge
that is given to these believers that are doing right,
and sometimes, if we're not careful,
as we look at a simple verse of scripture like this,
we can say, well, what is it that I can take from this?
How is it that God is going to help me with this?
And so this evening, I really wanna consider three thoughts
or tips, if you will, and here's the title
for the lesson tonight, how to avoid growing weary.
How to avoid growing weary.
I think each of us could acknowledge this evening
that it's possible to grow weary.
It's possible, as we go through life, to grow weary.
It's possible when we are doing right
or doing that which is appropriate,
as we find in this text of scripture,
and yet there are others that are not,
that it can become difficult for us,
and so we find that the charge is given,
the encouragement, but ye, brethren,
be not weary in well-doing.
As we take this thought from 2 Thessalonians 3,
and of course, having the whole canon of scripture,
I believe that as we look and compare scripture
that there are at least three things this evening
that if we would keep in mind that it would help us
as we live life to avoid growing weary.
Now, I'm sure that you could add things.
I could add things.
The list is not exhaustive this evening,
but three quick thoughts for our Bible study tonight.
Number one, if you're taking notes, remember who you serve.
Remember who you serve.
See, the reality this evening is that
it is absolutely necessary.
I'd say it's imperative that we remain focused
on the one we serve.
We serve the Lord Christ, the Lord Jesus Christ, our Savior.
He is the one that we serve,
and when our focus is on the fact that we're serving Christ,
it enables us, when we remember that we're serving the Lord,
it helps us to avoid growing weary in that well-doing.
Why?
Because I'm not doing what I'm doing
to receive acknowledgement or accolades
or some level of recognition.
No, I'm serving the Lord,
and when I remember that I'm serving Christ, I'm not,
listen, people will disappoint you, amen?
People will disappoint you,
and you do something for someone,
and you're trying to serve them,
and if it's only focused on trying to serve them,
and they don't accept the gesture that you've given,
they don't acknowledge what you've done,
they don't give you some level of appreciation
or accolade, it can become difficult for you,
and the reality is that as believers, he says,
but ye, brethren, be not weary in well-doing.
When we understand that we've been bought with a price,
when we understand that we serve the Lord Jesus Christ,
and that we are his servants,
then it enables us to not grow weary in well-doing.
We can avoid growing weary by remembering we serve Christ.
We serve Christ.
Look over at the book of Colossians, if you will,
in the third chapter, and I want you to notice
what God says here to these believers in Colossae,
and really, these that he's speaking to contextually
in the relationships that are mentioned
are those that are servants that are obeying their masters,
according to verse 22,
but I wanna focus on verse 23 and 24,
Colossians three, verse 23 and 24,
and I want you to notice what the Bible says
in Colossians three and verse 23,
and whatsoever you do, do it heartily,
and then notice these words,
as to the Lord, and not unto men.
Whatsoever you do, that's all encompassing.
I mean, that's everything that we do, whatsoever you do,
notice, do it heartily, as unto the Lord,
not unto men, verse 24,
knowing that of the Lord,
ye shall receive the reward of the inheritance,
for ye serve the Lord Christ.
What a blessing it is to be his servant.
You know, we must remember,
we must remind ourselves regularly
that we're serving the Lord.
See, we're not gonna look at all the passages this evening,
but if you study through the New Testament and the epistles,
you find that Paul, on a number of occasions,
not every letter that he writes,
but many of them, he'll say something like this,
Paul, a servant.
You find it in the book of James.
James says, James, a servant.
Peter, in the second epistle, he says, Peter, a servant.
Jude says, Jude, a servant.
John, when he writes the book of Revelation,
obviously under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
he talks about that revelation,
he refers to it this way, unto his servant, John.
As we think about those references
and the greetings, if you will,
and the epistles and the opening statements,
it reminds us that those servants of the Lord,
they were reminded that they were serving Christ.
And this evening, if we're gonna take this admonition,
this charge that was delivered
to these believers in Thessalonica
that we're doing right, that we're living uprightly,
Paul says, but ye, brethren, he says,
listen, that when you're doing well, faint not.
Don't be weary, don't be weary in well-doing.
And so we mention that that word weary,
it means to be faint, to be exhausted.
And this evening, when I'm reminding myself,
when you would remind yourself that we're serving Christ,
we're serving Christ, what a privilege, what a blessing.
But it helps us keep that proper perspective
so that we do not grow weary in well-doing.
I know I've been in a situation before
where I am sure you've been there as well,
just a simple illustration where you may be entering
into a store of some sort that has a door
that is not automatic and you hold the door for someone
and they just walk right in through,
like you get paid to hold the door for them.
And sometimes if I'm not really in the right spirit,
I might say something like this,
as they walk through, you're welcome.
But as believers, if we remind ourselves
that we're serving Christ, it's a tip,
it's a truth that will help us avoid growing weary
while we're doing right.
Because he says, but ye brethren,
be not weary in well-doing.
Number two, not only do we remember who we serve,
but number two, we must rely on his power.
Listen, your strength is small, my strength is small,
but we serve the Lord God omnipotent.
He said that he would fill us with his power.
He told us that he has all power in Matthew chapter 28
when he gives the great commission.
He tells us, but ye shall receive power
after the Holy Ghost has come upon you
in Acts one in verse number eight.
And we find that he has given to us
the opportunity to serve not in our strength,
but in his strength.
And by the way, when you serve in your strength,
you will grow weary.
You will grow weary.
But when you serve and you rely upon his strength,
when you rely upon his power,
you're remembering that you're serving Christ,
you're relying on his power,
then we can come to the place where we faint not.
Notice what the Bible says in 2 Corinthians chapter four.
You can look at a couple of verses here
in this passage of scripture.
And we find that the apostle Paul
is giving this second letter to this church in Corinth.
And he's been dealing with lots of things.
And he talks about in verse eight
of 2 Corinthians chapter four,
being troubled on every side
and being perplexed.
But he says that they're not distressed
and they're not in despair.
And we find that they're dealing with all of these pressures
and all of these circumstances.
But we find that it begins the chapter
in 2 Corinthians four in verse number one.
Notice it says, therefore seeing we have this ministry
as we have received mercy.
Notice those words, we faint not.
Now in our text of scripture in 2 Thessalonians three,
when Paul writes to the believers in Thessalonica,
he says, but ye brethren, be not weary in well doing.
That word weary and this word faint not,
it's the same word in the Greek.
And we find that Paul says that we have this ministry
and that we have received mercy, we faint not.
But I want you to understand the truth
that Paul reveals to us in verse number 16
as to how they do not faint,
and though they're dealing with all of these difficulties
and all of this opposition, in verse number 16,
he says, for which cause, notice again,
you see the words, we faint not.
But though our outward man perish,
yet the inward man is renewed day by day.
What is Paul talking about?
He says the outward man is gonna perish,
but the inward man is renewed day by day.
And he's making this comparison
and helping us to understand
it's not in the physical strength of the outward,
it's of the spiritual strength of the inward.
How do we continue?
Have you ever heard somebody say,
and our theme for this year is continue,
have you ever heard someone say, I just can't go on?
I just can't do anything more.
I would tell you this evening
that if you come to that place,
that it's because you're relying on your own power
and not on his power.
And we have the opportunity to be in a position,
listen, if God has called us to be his servants,
if he has given us a place of ministry,
then he's also provided for us everything that we need
to fulfill that ministry.
He equips his saints.
And we talked about that in the beginning
of studying through the book of First Timothy,
where Timothy is given that charge
to continue there in Ephesus
and all the things that are going on
and how the man of God was equipped
for the work that God gave him.
And God will equip his people.
And so we see here that this inward man,
he says the inward man is renewed day by day.
How does that happen?
Go to the weight room?
No, that's the outward.
It's getting into your prayer closet.
It's getting into the word of God.
It's allowing God's word to get into you
and to minister to you and to strengthen that inner man,
to be strengthened spiritually.
Notice what the Bible says in Ephesians chapter three.
As Paul is writing to this church in Ephesus,
and he's now in the third chapter
recording for the believers in Ephesus,
a second prayer that he's prayed for these believers.
And we find that as these prayers are recorded
in the book of Ephesians,
that it helps us to understand
how Paul prayed for these believers.
We do not have the time to outline the entire prayer
that is given here in Ephesians three,
verses 14 through 21.
But I do want to jump into the middle of the prayer
in verse number 16 and notice with regard
to the subject that we're dealing with,
this being strengthened in the inner man,
notice what it says in verse 16.
That he, speaking of the Lord,
would grant you according to the riches of his glory,
notice, to be strengthened with might
by his spirit in the inner man.
That's what we need.
That's Ephesians three in verse 16.
And so that's what we need.
We need to be strengthened in the inner man
by his spirit to have that strength
that we can go forward.
Again, it's not physical strength,
it's spiritual strength that we need.
And we find that the book of Proverbs,
it says this in Proverbs 24 in verse number 10,
if thou faint in the day of adversity,
thy strength is small.
And so we see that verse in Proverbs 24 in verse number 10.
And again, I do not, yes, you could look at that
from a physical strength perspective
and you could understand that there's certainly
an application with that.
But I look at it from a spiritual perspective.
Listen, there's going to be adversity that you face.
You can guarantee when you decide
that you're gonna serve the Lord,
when you're going to do right,
remember, what does he say?
But ye brethren, be not weary in well-doing.
When you're doing right, when you're living up rightly,
you're gonna have the pressures,
you're gonna have the opposition that's going to mount.
And if you're doing it in your own power,
if you're not recognizing that you're serving the Lord,
then you're going to grow weary.
So how can we avoid growing weary
as we're seeking to live a life that's pleasing to God,
as we're seeking to walk worthy and please God?
We must remember that we serve Christ.
We must rely on his power.
Without me, we know the verse.
Without me, you can do nothing, John 15.
We know the verse, but I would submit to you
that many of God's people, though we know the verse here,
we try sometimes to live in our own strength.
We try to live independent.
We try to think that we can,
without me, you can do nothing, nothing.
How we need him.
The songwriter said, I need thee every hour.
We sing that song, we're familiar with that song,
and not to criticize or to correct,
but the reality is that we need God every second
of every minute of every hour.
We need him.
We need to rely on his power.
It's not through our strength or our power.
It's through his power.
And if you really wanna see what God is able to do,
you rely on his power.
And it's amazing what God can do in and through his people.
You think Peter stood up on the day of Pentecost
in his own power and preached?
No.
You think Peter stood up before the religious leaders
of the day as they stood and they commanded
that they no longer could speak or teach in his name
and he stood in his own power and said let it?
No, he stood in the power of the Lord.
And we, too, this evening, we must rely on his power.
Number three, I would say this.
If we're going to avoid growing weary,
we must rest in his promise.
What promise is that?
Well, turn to the book of Galatians, if you will.
We see that as the book of Galatians comes to an end,
that here in the sixth chapter of the book of Galatians,
God gives us a truth that is very similar
to the truth that we see in 2 Thessalonians 3 in verse 13.
But ye brethren, and he says be not weary in well doing.
As we come to Galatians chapter six
and beginning in verse number seven,
the Bible says this, be not deceived.
God is not mocked.
For whatsoever a man soweth, that shall he also reap.
Now, I admit to you this evening that oftentimes
when we look at the truth of Galatians six and verse seven,
many times we deal with it from a perspective
of the negative.
But the reality is that the text of scripture
deals with it from both a negative
and a positive perspective.
If you sow bad seed, you're gonna reap bad harvest.
If you sow good seed, you're gonna have a good harvest.
And we see that in verse number eight,
notice he says, for he that soweth to his flesh
shall of the flesh reap corruption.
But he that soweth to the spirit shall of the spirit
reap life everlasting.
It's a great truth that God gives us in verse number eight.
And then we see in verse number nine,
notice what he says, and let us not be weary in well-doing.
Now, does that sound awfully familiar
to our texts of scriptures
from second Thessalonians three and verse 13?
But ye brethren, be not weary in well-doing.
And so here to the churches in the region of Galatia,
the apostle Paul under the inspiration
of the Holy Spirit of God says,
and let us not be weary in well-doing.
And then notice the rest, for in due season,
we shall reap if we faint not.
Did you see what the promise is?
The promise is that in due season, we shall reap.
We shall reap if we faint not.
Now, the reality is that we may not reap in our lifetime.
We may begin to see some of the fruit in our lifetime,
but the full harvest may not be realized in our own lifetime.
In fact, I would submit to you this evening
that it would be.
better if the full of the crop was not reaped in our lifetime, that we're sowing
seeds of righteousness into the Spirit, that we're serving Christ so faithfully
that that harvest is not just in this lifetime but beyond our lifetime, that we
have the opportunity to impact a generation beyond our own lives. Why is
it today that we still speak of heroes of the faith, not only Bible characters,
but we can speak this evening about those preachers of yesteryear that went
home to be with the Lord many years ago, some centuries ago, and yet we speak
about them this evening and we're familiar with them and we we have our
children read their life accounts. Why? Because they they left an impression,
they serve the Lord, they serve faithfully, and they're still reaping
today from the seeds that they planted during their lifetime. It's really quite
amazing. The reality this evening is that we find that we can be confident in
the promise that God has given and we can continue to do right, we can continue
to labor for the Lord because we know that he's given us this promise that
that let us not be weary in well-doing for in due season we shall reap if we
faint not. How is it that you and I this evening, how is it that these believers
in Thessalonica could take that charge, could take that that truth that's given
in verse 13 of chapter 3, but ye brethren be not weary in well-doing. Maybe
tonight as you examine your life you could say there have been times that I've
grown weary in well-doing. Maybe you're in a place right now where you feel like
you're weary in well-doing and this evening as we look at these tips it will
help us as we remember that we serve the Lord that we rely only solely on his
power that we rest in his promise. You know there are missionaries, we speak
about some of them, William Carey, Adam Iron Judson and others of yesteryear
that we would speak of that labored for years without ever seeing a convert. They
went forth, they surrendered their lives, they went to a place and they labored
and they they gave truth but there were no results, there were no responses, but
they just kept on doing what God called them to do and you know God gave a
harvest, God gave fruit. I want to remind you what the Bible says in 1st
Corinthians 15 and verse number 58, therefore my beloved brethren be
steadfast, unmovable, always abounding in the work of the Lord. Why? For as much as
you know that your labor is not in vain in the Lord. See as we serve the Lord, as
we're doing right, as we're engaged in proper righteous living, as we're seeking
to walk worthy and please God, we can labor and not grow weary and not faint.
Why? Because we got our eyes on our master. I'm serving the Lord. People will
disappoint you. I understand the people are the ones that are right in front of
you and sometimes the people are the ones that can that can affect you
greatly. We must rely on this power. I am weak but he is strong. I am weak but he
is strong and then we rest in his promise. I want you to look in closing
to the Old Testament, look over if you will to the book of Nehemiah. The book of
Nehemiah gives us the work that God is going to do through his servant. Nehemiah
begins, we don't have time to go through the entirety of this book but just very
quickly, it begins with Nehemiah inquiring as to how things were in
Jerusalem. He cared enough to ask and he made that request to find out how are
things in Jerusalem and he found out that they were in great affliction and
reproach, that the walls were broken down and the gates were burned with fire. He
responded with prayer, weeping. I mean you see that he fasted, he wept, he mourned, he
prayed. He stands before the king. He was the king's cupbearer and throughout the
circumstance he is given opportunity to return back to Jerusalem. The request is
asked, the king says what does now make requests and he says that I may go
back to Jerusalem, that I might build it. We find that Nehemiah goes back and
everything's just, I mean everyone's supportive of Nehemiah coming back and
building and they, you know, just no. I mean there's opposition, right? Because
whenever you try to do a work for God, whenever I try to do a work for God,
there's gonna be opposition. But we find that throughout the opposition, if you
were to read chapter number four, I mean the attacks that come and all that
takes place and you go into chapter five and into chapter six and you find that
there's all of these tactics that are used and how the enemy doesn't just quit
after one approach. The enemy doesn't just have one tool in his tool bag. When
you are not going to give in and cave in and be overcome by that one approach, you
can guarantee there's gonna be another approach and you can read through these
chapters. But I want to draw your attention to chapter six. I want you to
see what happens in chapter number six. In verse number two, the Bible lets us
know that they're trying to get Nehemiah to come to a place, one of the villages
in the plain of Ono. And he says at the end of the verse, but they thought to do
me mischief. And I want you to notice what it says in verse number three. And I
sent messengers unto them. And notice where he says, I am doing a great work. I
want you to think about this this evening as we close with this idea of
how is it that we can avoid growing weary in well-doing. See, Nehemiah says, I
am doing a great work. What is it about the work that made it a great work? It's
that it was a great work because he's doing it for a great God. That's what
made it a great work. He could be in any other place. He could be in any other
city. He could be in any other place where he's trying to rebuild walls and
rebuild gates. And it's not necessarily a great work in the sense that it's a
great work here because he's doing it for our great God. And the Bible says
this, so that I cannot come down. Why should the work cease whilst I leave it
and come down to you? And then I want you to notice in verse number four, and they
sent unto me. Does your Bible say four times after the sort? Listen, the
enemy is relentless. You can say no. And I love it. It's kind of a funny thing. Oh
no, when they ask you to go to, oh no, right? I mean, I'm not coming. But four
times. And then there's an open letter sent that's accusing Nehemiah of wanting
to rebuild and do this so that he can be the king, so that he can, in this open,
it's just all false accusation. Eventually, at the end of the chapter,
they try to, not the end, the middle of the chapter, they tried to get him to
come into the temple so that he could be protected because someone's gonna try to
kill him. And he says, no, I'm not permitted to go into the temple. And they
tried to create this plan so that they could bring an evil report against him.
Trying to make him afraid. They try to get him to be weary in well-doing. At
every turn, there's opposition. I mean, they had to build, if you were to go back
and you look at what's taking place in chapter four, I mean, everyone's building.
They have a tool in one hand and a weapon in another hand. I mean, that's not
a great, efficient way to be trying to build. But that's what they're dealing
with because of the opposition. But I want you to notice that in chapter six,
in verse number 15, the Bible says, so the wall was, did it say finished? Isn't that good?
The wall was finished in the twenty and fifth day of the month, Elul. Notice what
it says, in fifty and two days. That's amazing. Absolutely amazing. It says that,
in verse 16, and it came to pass that when all our enemies heard thereof, and
all the heathen that were about us saw these things, they were much cast down in
their own eyes. Notice what it says, for they perceived that this work was wrought
of our God. You know what even the enemies recognized? It wasn't in Nehemiah's power
that this work got accomplished. It was God working through them. It was God blessing.
And as we look at this Old Testament example of Nehemiah and the walls being rebuilt and
what takes place, we find that as we could look at this truth this evening, how can I
avoid growing weary in well-doing? Can we avoid it? I mean, when the pressures come
and the opposition mounts and it seems like everyone's against us, can we not grow weary?
Well, if we remember we're serving the Lord. Sometimes we can be all about results. We can
be results-oriented. And so long as the results are...
What we're looking for, there's, if we can use it
in the context of a church, there's new visitors,
there's new members, there's salvations,
there's baptisms, there's activity.
Man, we can be kind of just pressing on.
But when the opposition mounts, when the difficulties come,
we serve Christ.
We serve Christ.
And we have to rely on His power.
It's not in my strength.
You ever feel weak?
It's not about the outward man.
It's the inward man that needs to be renewed day by day.
And if God's called you to do it,
He will give you the strength and the power to do it
by His grace, by His power.
And then we just simply rest.
Rest in the promise that you shall reap if we faint not.
Three key words for you this evening
if you wanna avoid growing weary in well-doing.
Remember, rely, and rest.
There are far too many that grow weary in well-doing.
And that's why I believe God gives us
on more than one occasion in His word
this truth about not growing weary in well-doing.
And we must have the right perspective.
Otherwise, we too will fall victim, casualty,
to growing weary in well-doing.
We oughta do right.
We oughta be living right.
But we're doing it for Christ and in His power.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
And God, I pray this evening that you would help each of us
as we endeavor to live for you, to serve you.
God, you would help us to avoid
growing weary in well-doing.
God, I pray that you would help us to keep our eyes on thee,
to recognize that all that we do is for thee,
truly for the audience of one.
And God, that you would help us to keep that perspective.
I pray that you'd help us to rely
upon your power and your strength.
Though the outward man may perish,
that the inward man is renewed day by day,
that we spend time in your word and in prayer,
that we'd be strengthened by your might,
by your spirit in the inner man.
And God, help us to rest in the promise
that our labor is not in vain.
Help us to remain steadfast and unmovable.
Help us to continue to sow good seed,
to continue to live right and to do right,
knowing that the harvest will come.
We thank you for the privilege of prayer
and corporate prayer.
We pray, God, that you'd bless our time.
I pray that you'd help us to be encouraged and strengthened.
We thank you that you're a God who can do all things.
We pray that you'd bless now and we'll thank you for it.
In Christ's name we pray, amen.
All right, on the.