the book of James, James chapter number 2, and we'll be looking at verses 14 through 20,
James chapter number 2, verses 14 through 20, as we get back here to the book of James,
and I had a couple of weeks there with Easter and all of that that was going on,
and thank the Lord for the opportunity to preach about the crucifixion and the resurrection,
and the resurrection is the cornerstone of our faith, and so thankful that we serve a risen
savior, and of course we say it often and reminded that we gather on the first day of the week
because we serve a risen savior, and to God be the glory, amen, and I'm thankful for the privilege of
being able to be here this morning, and I hope that you are as well, I prayed for you early this
morning, and prayed that God would meet with us, and that he would be exalted and magnified and
looking forward to what God will do in and through our lives today. Beginning in verse number 14,
the Bible says this, what doth it profit my brethren though a man say he hath faith
and have not works? Can faith save him? If a brother or sister be naked and destitute of daily
food, and one of you say unto them depart in peace, be warmed and filled, notwithstanding
ye give them not those things which are needful to the body, what doth it profit? Even so faith,
if it hath not works, is dead being alone. Yea, a man may say thou hast faith, and I have works.
Show me thy faith without thy works, and I will show thee my faith by my works.
Thou believest that there is one God, thou doest well. The devils also believe and tremble,
but wilt thou know, O vain man, that faith without works is dead? As we look at this portion of
scripture, we find that there are several questions that are asked. Beginning in verse
number 14, he asked two questions. He says this, what doth it profit? And what is he speaking of?
He says, what doth it profit my brethren though a man say he hath faith and have not works? So
what's the profit of that? And then he asked this question, can faith save him? He asked a question
in verse 16 when he asked, what doth it profit? Again, the context there, he begins to use an
illustration in verses 15 and 16 to illustrate the point that he's making. And he says, you see
someone here in need and you say to them, depart, but you don't do anything to help them. What is
the profit? He then says, he makes the declaration in verse 17, even so faith, if it hath not works,
is dead, being alone. In verse 18, he says, show me, prove to me, give me the evidence that you
have faith. And you say that you have faith, show me your faith. How do you show someone
your faith? How do you give the outward expression, the evidence of faith? What does it look like? And
we find that James says, show me thy faith without thy works. It's going to be really hard to do that.
And he says this, and I will show thee my faith by my works. He uses in verse 19 this important
truth that he says, thou believest that there is one God, thou doest well. But then he talks about
the fact that the devils also believe in tremble. Listen, Satan knows that God is real. Satan knows
that God has all power. The devils, the demons, we find that during the earthly ministry of the
Lord Jesus Christ, every time there was an interaction between Jesus and the devils,
we find that Jesus showed that he had all power. And we find that they said, have you come to
torment us before our time? They understand who God is. And so what James is speaking of,
he's going to make the statement again in verse number 20, but wilt thou know, O vain man, that
faith without works is dead. We find that throughout the passage of Scripture in this
section of the book of James, I believe that James is helping his readers to see a connection
between what they say and what they do. See, we find that he uses that phrase, though a man
say he hath faith. And in verse number 16, and one of you say unto them, in our talk, in the words
that we use, but we see that there's a connection, not only between what we say, but what we do.
I believe that as you read the Bible, that you will discover that there's an emphasis placed upon
the behavior of individuals. Specifically, we would say upon the behavior of God's people.
In fact, let me say it this way. The behavior of an individual is the evidence of their belief.
The behavior of an individual is the evidence of their belief. Let me use a couple of Old Testament
illustrations for you. Go back to the book of Exodus, and we'll look at two examples
in the book of Exodus. The first is in Exodus chapter number nine. In Exodus chapter number
nine, I want you to see this is during the time of plagues, and specifically, it's during the
seventh plague. And we're going to read a portion here, just a few verses of Scripture, to show us
that the behavior of these that are referenced here in these few verses of Scripture reveal is
the evidence of what they believe. So they've already experienced six plagues. They've already
been through the process of seeing God demonstrate His power and do exactly what He said He would do.
And we find that now they come to this seventh plague. And if you look in verse 18, the Bible
says this, behold, tomorrow about this time, I will cause it to rain a very grievous hail,
such as hath not been in Egypt since the foundation thereof even until now. So here's what the
follow-up is in verse 19. Send therefore now and gather thy cattle and all that thou hast in the
field. For upon every man and beast which shall be found in the field and shall not be brought home,
the hail shall come down upon them. Notice this, and they shall die. Now, was God clear in what was
going to happen? He made it abundantly clear in verse 18 and 19. Not only did He tell them what
was going to happen, He tells them when. He says, tomorrow about this time, here's what I'm going to
do. Here's what's going to happen. And here's what I advise you to do. Bring in, we find in verse 19,
He says, send thou for now and gather thy cattle and all that thou hast. Why? Because any man or
beast that's found in the field, they're going to die. So we find that there's truth that is given,
but the evidence of the, excuse me, the behavior of the individuals is the evidence of their faith.
What is faith? It's believing God. Faith is taking God at His word. And we find here in verse number
20, the Bible says, he that feared the word of the Lord among the servants of Pharaoh made his
servants and his cattle flee into the houses. What would you say of those in verse number 20?
I would summarize it this way. They believed God. They believed that this hail was going to come.
They believed that it was going to come tomorrow about this time. And they believed that anything
that was in the field, man or beast would die. And so therefore their actions, their behavior
is the evidence that they believed what God said. However, in verse 21, notice what it says. And he
that regarded not the word of the Lord left his servants and his cattle in the field. So to regard
not, they did not believe. And so therefore they did nothing. They left their beast in the field
and the men in the Bible. If you were to continue to read through here, you would find in verse 25,
it says in the hail smoke throughout all the land of Egypt, all that was in the field, both man and
beast. And so guess what? Those in verse 21 that regarded not the word of the Lord,
their behavior was also evidence that they did not believe. So the behavior of an individual is the
evidence of their belief. We're there in Exodus. Look at a few chapters over in chapter 16.
Now at this particular time in Israel's history, we're now looking at the children of Israel in
Exodus 16. And we find here in Exodus 16, they've experienced, they've seen the plagues, but they've
also now they've crossed the Red Sea. We find that not only have they crossed the Red Sea,
they rejoiced greatly in all that God was accomplishing and all that God did. They saw
the hand of God.
and then they come to Marah, there's bitter water,
they see God give direction and heal those waters.
I mean, they've seen God do some amazing things.
And now we find in Exodus 16,
that God's going to give them instruction
with regard to the manna.
The manna, the provision of God.
And we find that here in the text of scripture again,
to speak about the fact that the Bible
will place an emphasis upon the behavior, why?
Because behavior is the evidence of belief.
Notice in Exodus 16 and verse 19,
Moses said, let no man leave of it till the morning.
So we find that there's been instruction given
with regard to the gathering
and how they're supposed to gather
and the amount they're supposed to gather
and each day what they're supposed to do.
And he says, let no man leave of it till the morning.
Now God had told him that if they did,
that it would stink, it would breed worms
and we understand what's taking place here.
And so we find in verse 20,
notice how it starts, notwithstanding.
They hearkened not unto Moses.
The Bible says, but some of them.
I'm thankful it wasn't all of them, amen.
There were some that believed.
There were some that took what was instructed
and they said, yeah, we're not gonna keep it
because he said not to.
And it says that some of them left of it until the morning
and what happened, it bred worms and stank
and Moses was wroth with them.
We find that on the, as we continue looking in the passage,
if you skip down to verse number 25,
the Bible says, and Moses said, eat that today
for today is a Sabbath unto the Lord.
Today you shall not find it in the field.
Verse 26, six days you shall gather it,
but on the seventh day, which is the Sabbath,
in it there shall be none.
And it came to pass that there went out,
notice what it says, some of the people.
When did they go out?
Well, they went out on the seventh day.
Why did they go out?
Well, it says for to gather, but guess what?
They found none.
Why?
Well, because God said that wasn't how it was gonna work.
What am I saying?
Why do I use these two illustrations this morning?
I use these two biblical illustrations
just as a little piece of evidence to show to us
that what an individual or how an individual behaves
reveals to us what they believe.
I've often said over the years
that our belief will impact our behavior,
but the other side of that coin
is that our behavior reveals our belief.
Perhaps you've heard somebody say this,
or maybe you've even said it yourself
at some point in your life.
The message of your life is more impactful
than the message of your lips.
Have you ever heard somebody say that?
Have you ever said that?
And what do we mean by that?
Well, what we see in your behavior speaks volumes.
What I see in your life, remember Solomon says,
give me thine heart and let thine eyes observe my ways.
As much as I wanna give instruction,
as much as I wanna teach,
as much as I wanna use my words,
the reality is that there's gotta be some proof,
or the proof is in the pudding.
There's gotta be the evidence
that what I say is proven, is backed up by what I do.
As we examine the portion of scripture
there in James chapter number two this morning,
I've simply entitled the message this, talk is cheap.
Talk is cheap.
You know, it really is.
You can say a whole lot of things,
but talk is cheap.
Show me thy faith is what we read in James chapter number two
and as we begin to look at this portion of scripture
and begin to understand what God is communicating to us
and how James, as we've mentioned
for several different times of looking at this book
and studying through the book of James,
James is a book that's extremely practical in nature.
The application of truth.
How does the truth impact us?
How does what we believe impact how we behave?
Is there a change?
Is there evidence in your life and in my life
that I truly believe what God says in his word?
And as we look at the portion of scripture,
we find and I'll go through great lengths
to try to help us understand this morning
that there's no contradiction.
It's not a situation here where James is teaching
something different about salvation
than what any other portion of scripture,
Paul or anyone else would teach on salvation.
We find again that as James, it's already been established
that he's writing to save people.
And so as we look at the portion of scripture,
I would say just, I have two points for you this morning.
Number one is this, genuine conversion is always by faith.
Genuine conversion is by faith.
And it's important that we understand that.
Again, James is writing to save people
and he's not discussing how a man is saved.
This is not a treaties on the subject of salvation
with regard to justification and so on and so forth.
We find that he's talking to save people
and he's addressing the reality that true faith works.
All right, true faith works.
And we'll look at a number of things.
Remember in James one in verse number 18,
remember, we looked at this several weeks ago,
but James made this declaration.
He says, of his own will begat he us with the word of truth
that we should be a kind of first fruits of his creatures.
When we looked at that verse of scripture
in verse number 18, we spoke about the fact
that James would be referencing his own conversion.
And the Bible says of his own will begat he us
with the word of truth.
There's no reference whatsoever
with regard to a works-based salvation.
We find that he understood the truth of salvation
being all of God and none of us.
It is his grace and it is his mercy.
For by grace are you saved through faith, all right?
And we find that he mentions that.
But then we notice the expectation,
not only the experience of James,
but the expectation that we should be a kind
of first fruits of his creatures.
The idea of many, the harvest of souls
through the age of the church
that would come to Christ as their savior
is what is in view here in verse number 18 of chapter one.
And we certainly rejoice with understanding
that here James is speaking
and he's talking about this thought
with regard to true faith works.
True faith works.
Now, as we will know in a few minutes
as we get into our next point,
we will understand that there are zero contradictions.
We must be careful
not to take the scriptures out of context.
Not only must we be careful
not to take the scriptures out of context,
but let me say this as well.
It's important that we do not allow some organization,
some denominational teaching
about a certain portion of scripture
to mess us up with how we look at what God's word says.
What do I mean by that?
Listen, there are plenty of denominations
that will take out of context
and will teach in error portions of scripture.
We see it not only with soteriology,
the doctrine of salvation,
but we see it often with eschatology,
the doctrine of end times.
In both of those particular categories,
not that it's exclusive to only those two categories,
but we see that it's often in those two categories.
Why is it that there's so many religious organizations,
denominations, if you will,
that will teach on the subject of soteriology
by taking portions of scripture
and teaching them erroneously?
Why is that the case?
Well, because salvation
is the most essential need of humanity.
And we find that the Bible tells us
that the little g God of this world
hath blinded the minds of them which believe not,
lest the light of the glorious gospel
should shine unto them.
Someone has noted a particular scholar,
theologian of yesteryear,
that the enemy, the devil,
is the author of many theological books.
What did he mean when he made that assessment?
What was he trying to communicate
in making that assessment?
Well, there are many in the name of religion
that have peddled false teaching.
And we find that here,
as we look at the whole of scripture
and we understand what is taking place here,
again, real faith, true faith works.
Lotus, if you will,
we'll look at a few verses of scripture.
Again, we never seek to interpret the obscure,
or excuse me, interpret the obvious by the obscure.
We always interpret the obscure with the obvious.
And it's important that we understand that principle.
Look in Romans chapter six, if you will.
It's a verse of scripture that many of us
could probably quote.
this morning and we find in Romans chapter 6 in verse number 23 if you ever
share the gospel with an individual at some point through the process of
talking to them about their need for salvation you'll find yourself here in
Romans 6 in verse number 23. The Bible says that the wages of sin is death and
oftentimes we'll pause right there and make some explanation with regard to the
wage of sin being death what you earn what humans earn for their sin is death
it's not only a physical death but it's a spiritual death separation from God
for all of eternity in a place called the lake of fire but there's a great
contrast in Romans 6 in verse 23 for the wage of sin is death but the gift of God
is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord you know there's something
extremely important to understand and I always stress this when I talk to people
individually about their need for salvation there is a vast difference
between a wage and a gift they're completely opposite the one from the
other a wage is something that you earn a gift is something that you receive if
you just even 1% contribute to a gift it ceases to be a gift amen and and I've
used the illustration before in various contexts with regard to giving gifts and
what have you if you I ask people this all the time have you ever bought a gift
for if they're married for your wife if if they have children for your children
have you ever bought a gift if they don't have any spouse or children here
about a gift for your mom and so on and so forth and I'll ask that question and
so when you bought the gift who paid for it and every time they say well I did of
course someone had to pay for the gift so once you paid for the gift and you
wrapped it and you presented it and and you presented that gift and it was open
and it was appreciated did you then tell them how much they owed you for the gift
and every single time they've looked at me and said no we understand that in our
human interactions how much more so with God he paid it all every single thing
that was was required was was satisfied when Jesus Christ the Son of God went to
the cruel cross and he was crucified and then he was buried and then he rose
again and he paid it all and he offers the gift to humanity and a gift is
something that you cannot work for as soon as you try as soon as you attempt
to work for a gift it ceases to be a gift we find in Ephesians chapter 2
again familiar verses of Scripture but it's so important that we understand
what the Scriptures teach and as we interpret what James is dealing with
here in James chapter number two it's helpful for us to look at the whole of
Scripture and to see what God is saying in Ephesians 2 verses 8 & 9 again
familiar verses for by grace are you saved through faith notice very plainly
and that not of yourselves it is the gift of God not of works lest any man
should boast can I tell you that we will not glory in his presence meaning
that we won't come to a place where we all stand there and it's like okay well
you were really good and so you can come in and you did a great job you can come
in but you weren't so good you can't come in well then this one that got in
by their own works they have reason to boast but he says lest any man should
boast listen it's not by your works it's not by my works there's no
contradiction here in fact we'll look at verse 10 in a few moments as we get
through the message this morning and see that it's not only that it's there's no
contradiction it's also it's extremely complimentary the truth that James is
teaching in the truth that we see from Paul and others throughout the
Scriptures and so we find that the Bible very plainly teaches us it's not by
works and Titus chapter number 3 in verse number 5 and here we find again
this simple reference with regard to the subject of salvation not by works of
righteousness which we have done but according to his mercy he saved us by
the washing of regeneration and renewing of the Holy Ghost and so we find that he
plainly says not by works of righteousness which we have done by the
way Isaiah says that all of our good works are as filthy rags as humanity
would try to appease a holy God it's it's utterly impossible for us to attain
that no he says this is the gift this is the only way to be saved in 1st Peter
chapter number 1 in verses 3 through 5 Peter here is reminding us of the same
truth and how God has saved us by his grace and we're saying this genuine
conversion is always and only by faith
Christ alone grace alone in time in 1st Peter 1 in verse number 3 notice blessed
be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ which according to his abundant
mercy hath begotten us again unto a lively hope by the resurrection of Jesus
Christ from the dead no reference of any kind of works that an individual would
be able to do to be born again to be begotten unto a lively hope no it's
according to his abundant mercy verse 4 to an inheritance incorruptible and
undefiled and that fadeth not away reserved in heaven for you who are kept
by the power of God through faith unto salvation ready to be revealed in the
last time not only do we find here in this portion of Scripture that we're
saved by faith but we understand that we're kept by God it's not a situation
that we have this idea of that our good works can save us no we understand
that's impossible but nor is it the fact that our good works can keep us I'm not
saved by works and I'm not kept by works I'm saved by God and I'm kept by
God to God be the glory to understand the truth of genuine conversion listen
there are people that do not understand this very plain truth that we've
examined this morning briefly something that for most of us in the in this room
this morning that we understand that we're aware of that we could go to the
verses but there are literally billions of people upon planet earth that have
been deceived they do not know the truth of the Bible with regard to salvation
many are trying to work their way to heaven somehow and do some kind of good
things no doubt in my mind that even on a Sunday morning at quarter after 11
there are thousands upon thousands millions upon millions that are sitting
in church houses all across the world that are trying to buy their good works
earn God's favor and it's impossible they're going to a church service
they're putting in an offering they're doing this they're doing that whatever
it is that they're doing they're trying to get to earn God's favor I'm thankful
this morning for the front of the bulletin for God so loved the world
listen God declared his love to you long before you ever existed he knew when you
would be born he knows all things he said that while we were yet enemies
right while we're you look at Romans chapter 5 God commended his love toward
us and that while we're yet sinners Christ died for us and we begin to
rejoice and understand that God so loved the world listen you can't make
God love you he just loves you to God be the glory and so we find that genuine
conversion is always and only by faith number two genuine conversion produces
fruit genuine conversion produces fruit and and we find that really that's what
James is focusing on here I said this at the very first message of this year
going through the book of James and I said this that Paul deals with the root
and James deals with the fruit and to me and to understand as we look here at the
portion of Scripture and we find that James is telling them and trying to
explain to them the understanding that your faith is is proven by your works
it's not that you're saved by your works it's that your works are the
evidence of your faith and so we begin to understand that genuine conversion is
going to produce fruit understand that it's not just the message of Paul first
I want to show you that this is the truth of the teaching of the Lord Jesus
Christ turn around Matthew chapter number seven if you will and we've
obviously in those first couple of messages as we've gone through the book
of James here in 2026 we've dealt with the very fact that James is the half
brother
of the Lord Jesus Christ, not only did he have an opportunity to hear some of what
Jesus taught and observe some of what Jesus did publicly, but he lived with
them. And so we find that here in Matthew chapter number 7, as the Lord Jesus
Christ, we would understand here being the Sermon on the Mount and all that's
going on, and we find in chapter number 7 of Matthew, in verse number 20, notice
what the Scriptures say. Wherefore, by what? By their fruits ye shall know them.
By their fruits ye shall know them. Why? Because their fruit is the evidence of
their faith. Their behavior, what they do, is the evidence of what they truly
believe. And so we find in verse 24, as Jesus is going to further illustrate
this, he says in verse 24, therefore, whosoever heareth these sayings of mine
and doeth them. That's a work, is it not? Amen? To do. We are preaching through the
book of James and our theme is doers of the word, not hearers only, but doers of
the word. And so he says, whosoever heareth these sayings of mine and doeth
them, I will liken him unto a wise man which built his house upon a rock. The
rain descended and the floods came, the winds blew and beat upon that house, and
it fell not, for it was founded upon a rock. And we find that, again, as you look
at this portion of Scripture, another familiar portion of Scripture, that Jesus
says, you're going to hear these sayings, but what's your response? Just like what
we read of the Egyptians back in Exodus chapter number 9, just what we read of
the children of Israel in Exodus chapter number 16, what they did in response to
what they heard was the evidence of their faith. They believed that the hail was
going to come. They believed that whoever was left out, beast or man, would die. And
so those that believed it went and gathered. Why? Because they believed. Those
that regarded not, well, we'll just see what happens. You don't want to see what's
going to happen. Listen, God's word is true. Whosoever is not found written in
the book of life was cast into the lake of fire. Probably one of the saddest
verses of all the Bible. Truly. Well, we're just going to see what happens. Let God be
true, and every man a liar. Jesus continues in verse 26, and everyone that
heareth these sayings of mine and doeth them not shall be likened unto a foolish
man which built his house upon the sand. The rain descended, the floods came, and
the winds blew and beat upon that house, and it fell, and great was the fall of it.
It's interesting for the one that doeth and the one that doeth them not, for both,
as the illustration is given here, there's a storm, there's a flood, there's
wind, there's rain. Being saved doesn't exempt you from storms. Build your house
upon the Lord Jesus Christ. Build your life upon the rock, the Lord Jesus Christ.
Amen? And what are we, what's the evidence that I believe God, what's the evidence
that I believe what God has said, that I've put my faith in God, is that I obey
his word, that I do what he says. Not so that I can, I already understand I can't
get saved that way. I already understand I can't stay saved that way. But I
recognize that I have believed, I have faith, and true faith works. And we look
here, we find, again, talk is cheap. Anyone can say whatever they want to say.
James says, show me, show me. What's the evidence? Jesus said this in Luke 6.
Take your Bible and look at Luke chapter number 6.
In Luke chapter number 6, in verse number 46, notice this question.
And why call ye me Lord, Lord, and do not the things which I say? It's a powerful
question. It's a piercing question, is it not? Jesus says, why are you calling me
Lord? Why callest thou or why call ye me Lord, Lord, and do not the things which I
say? I do not believe this morning that it would be a stretch from this verse of
Scripture to make this statement that the Lord has an expectation that we do what
he says. That's not a stretch. That's not a misinterpretation or misapplication of
the verse of Scripture. When Jesus says, why call ye me Lord, Lord, and do not the
things which I say, I believe it's abundantly clear and obvious that Jesus,
the Lord, has an expectation that those that say, Lord, Lord, do. Why?
Because we have faith and faith works. He is Lord. One day every tongue will
confess and every knee will bow. I've said often through the years, it's not a
matter of if, it's a matter of when. And when makes all the difference. And how
important it is that that confession that Jesus Christ is Lord is made on
this side of eternity. While we're living here upon this earth, before we take that
final breath and enter into eternity. Why? Because it will forever be too late. But I
guarantee you that your knee will bow and your tongue will confess that Jesus
Christ is Lord on the authority of God's word. Because that's what God says. And so
Jesus says, why call ye me Lord, Lord, and do not the things which I say. There's an
expectation that the faith is, the behavior is the evidence of the faith.
That we do. Notice in John chapter 14, Jesus says it this way in John chapter 14
in verse number 15. We know that John will tell us later in the book of 1 John
that we love God because he first loved us. But here Jesus says this in John 14
and verse 15, if you love me, keep my commandments. What does it mean to keep
his commandments? It means to do something, to obey, to do what he said to do. And so
Jesus isn't saying if you want to be saved, keep my commandments. No, that's not what
he says. He says if you love me, keep my commandments. What's the evidence of your
love? That you obey him. We'll see it in 1 John here in just a few moments as well.
The evidence of our love. Listen, we have people all around America that are in
front of cameras, quote unquote celebrities, that are playing sports and all sorts of
things saying I love Jesus. And I'm not saying that none of them are being
sincere, but I'm simply saying that the evidence is not there to support the
claim. They're out there living a life of just terrible wickedness and sin and all
sorts of things going on and profanity coming out of one side while the other
side is saying I love Jesus. If you love me, keep my commandments. Anyone can say I
love Jesus. Talk is cheap. Talk is cheap. What is the evidence? And that's what
James is dealing with. He's dealing with the evidence. What's the behavior? Show me
your faith. Show me. Let me see the evidence of what you believe. Not only
the message of Jesus, consider the message of Paul. Paul said this in 2
Corinthians 5 in verse 17, if any man be in Christ, he is a new creature. Old
things are passed away. Behold, all things are become new. Did you experience that
at conversion? Did you experience when you were born again, when the Holy Spirit
of God came and lived within you and all of a sudden you started being convicted
about things that you never were convicted about before? All of a sudden
the Spirit of God began to teach you the Word of God and move in your heart. And
why? Because you were born again. You were a new creature. This amazing
transformation took place and the Holy Spirit of God now lives within you. And
it's amazing to see what God does at that moment of salvation and we're new
creatures. We find that in Ephesians chapter 2, we mentioned earlier verses
8 and 9 and we read those verses of Scripture. But I want you to notice and
understand here in verse number 10 of Ephesians chapter 2, the Apostle Paul
makes it very clear that it's by God's great mercy, it's by God's grace that
we're saved. He makes it abundantly clear that it's not by our works, it's not of
anything that you
could do or that I could do. It's all about what Jesus has already done, but he
says this in verse number 10. For we, for we are his workmanship created in Christ
Jesus, notice what he says, unto good works which God hath before ordained that we
should walk in them. In what? In the good works. We are his workmanship created in
Christ Jesus unto good works. The good works, he's already made it plain. It, that
doesn't save us. It doesn't keep us safe, but that is God's plan. It says that
which God hath before ordained that we should walk in them. You know what God's
plan is for those that have trusted Jesus Christ as their personal Savior?
God's plan is that they would be like Jesus. God's plan is that they would be
sanctified. Yes, I understand positional, but I'm talking about progressive. I'm
talking about here upon this earth that we're having that growth in our lives,
that we are, though we are his workmanship and that we are engaged,
that we're walking in good works. In the book of Ephesians, there's a great
division that is obvious as you outline the book. In the first three chapters,
Paul is heavily focusing on and concentrating on the fact that we are
saved by grace through faith, that we are, this is the way by which humanity is
saved. There's only one way to be saved, and it's Jesus Christ, and we find that
he makes it very plain about our position in Christ. But chapters 4, 5, and 6 become
extremely practical in nature, where you have the understanding of my position,
but now the practical aspect that now I am to walk, I am to behave a certain way.
Why? Because I'm saved, because I'm his, and what a blessing.
The book of Philippians, notice what Paul says to these believers at Philippi as
he's teaching them and as he's writing to them and getting ready to finish the
letter, obviously we understand under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of
God, but we notice that he comes to his conclusion in the fourth chapter, and he
tells them this in verse number 9. Notice, he says, those things which you have both
learned and received and heard, but then notice where he says, and seen in me. What
does it mean to see something in someone? Well, that's the message of his
life. That's his behavior. That's the evidence that what he's preaching he
believes, right? He says, listen, he says, the things that you have learned,
received, and heard. But then he says, and seen in me. And then notice the next word,
do. So what's Paul's expectation? Paul says, listen, church at Philippi,
you believers, those of you that have been saved by grace, you've learned some
things, you've heard some things, you've seen some things, but now I want you to do
those. I want you to follow the example. In fact, Paul would say it this way to the
believers in Corinth, be followers of me even also as I am a follower of Christ.
And so Paul says the things that you've not only learned, received, and heard,
but seen in me. Those works, the outworking of his faith, they saw it. It was obvious
to them. How obvious is our faith? How obvious is our faith? What we say that we
believe, is there evidence to support it? Would someone observe our behavior?
Would someone observe and see the things that we do and say, man, they believe the
Bible, because they behave according to the teachings of the Bible?
Why do they call them Christians in Antioch? Well, because they were like Christ.
Amen? It's a great compliment, by the way. We are to be conformed to the image of his
dear son, according to Romans 8 and verse 29. That's God's plan for us.
And so he says, and the God of peace shall be with you as he ends the verse there. And
you think about God's favor as we begin to do the things that we have heard, the things
that God enables us to do. By the way, if you're not saved, you can't keep these things.
You can't do these things. You can try. It'll just drive you crazy. I've heard people say,
I try to read the Bible, I don't understand it. Yeah, because the Bible tells us that
the natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God. Lost people can try to
read the Bible all they want. I know I've said it before, but over, we have a missionary
and they're in Albania and Albanians historically would say that they're atheist. I think there's
been a little bit of a shift and what have you with regard to that, but they have historically,
they have said they're atheist. But in their highest levels of education, they use a King
James Bible in their English classes for literature purposes. But they say they're atheist.
The question could be asked, well, what do you think about the Bible? Well,
it's a great literary work. No, it's God's word. Listen, the Bible makes so much more sense as we
read it as saved people. The Holy Spirit of God is the teacher, the divine teacher. He teaches us
his word. And so when we begin to understand this thing, listen, as Paul was saying to these
believers, he says, listen, do these things. Why? Because the Spirit of God enables you. I can't
keep his commandments except for the fact that he enables me to keep his commandments.
In Titus chapter number two, now we read earlier Titus chapter number three about not of works or
not by works of righteousness. But I want you to notice in the book of Titus, and there's only
three chapters, a very short letter that Paul pens to Titus. And we find on multiple occasions that
Paul mentions about good works to Titus. In Titus chapter number two, notice with me in verse number
14, he says, who gave himself for us. By the way, aren't you thankful he gave himself? Let me back
up and read verse 11. For the grace of God that bringeth salvation hath appeared to all men.
It's only the grace of God that bringeth salvation. And it's for all men, teaching us that denying
ungodliness and worldly lusts, we shall live soberly, righteously, and godly in this present
world. Listen, that's those that have been saved, that salvation has been received, and we're God's
people. And it teaches us, God's grace teaches us something. It teaches us how to live, how to
please him. Verse 13, looking for that blessed hope and the glorious appearing of the great God
and our Savior, Jesus Christ. And hallelujah, he's coming one day. And it's the blessed hope. But
notice in verse 14, who gave himself for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquity and purify
unto himself a peculiar people. Notice what it says, zealous of what? Good works. There's no
contradiction in these verses of scripture. It's not a God's grace will save you and he gave himself
to redeem us, but oh, there's good works. No, it's that we, true faith works. That those that are
saved by the grace of God, that we are his workmanship created in Christ Jesus unto good
works. We find in chapter number three, we read already in verse number five, not by works of
righteousness, which we have done, but notice if you will, in verses six and seven, which he shed
on us abundantly through Jesus Christ, our Savior, that being justified how? By his grace. We should
we should be made heirs according to the hope of eternal life. This is a faithful saying,
and these things I will that thou affirm constantly that they which have, what does it say?
Believed in God. What is that? That's faith. Might be careful to maintain good works.
These things are good and profitable unto men. Yeah. Praise the Lord. So listen, you'll have
some people that will want to run around and say that James's message contradicts Paul's message.
Really? We're just looking at all these verses of scripture, not only the message of Jesus,
but we see the message of the apostle Paul here in these verses, uh, in the book of Ephesians
and Philippians and Titus, and we see in verse 14, he is near the end and he says,
and let ours also learn to maintain good works for necessary uses that they be not unfruitful.
They be not unfruitful. All right. So this, that genuine conversion produces fruit,
it produces fruit. So we see the message of Jesus. We see the message of Paul, but consider with me
finally the message of John, the book of first John. And I want you to see a few verses of
scripture here in the book of first John. We'll look in chapter three to begin in first John,
chapter number three. And it's interesting because this really goes right along with.
what we read there with regard to the situation with the illustration of James in chapter
number two about seeing someone that was destitute and naked.
And here we find that he talks about, he'd say this, and what does it profit.
But notice in chapter number three of 1 John in verse 18, my little children, let us not
love in word, neither in tongue.
Notice what it says.
But in deed and in truth, in deed and in truth.
What is deed?
Well, that's some outward expression, right?
It's a work.
It's some evidence that's through your behavior and it's like, let us not love in word, neither
in tongue.
What does it say?
Talk is cheap.
In James, again, to look at what we mentioned by way of looking at this portion of scripture,
he said in verse 16, and one of you say unto them, this one that is a brother or sister
that's naked and destitute of daily food.
If you say depart in peace, be warmed and filled, notwithstanding you give them not
those things which are needful to the body, what doth it profit?
That person walks away in the same exact condition, right?
And you've said something, but talk is cheap.
And so what does John say here in 1 John 3 in verse 18, let us not love in word, neither
in tongue, but in deed and in truth.
I'm not saying that it's wrong to say I love you to someone, but your actions better also
support the fact that you've said, I love you.
Amen.
In 1 John chapter number five, notice in verse, we'll just start in verse number one.
First John chapter five in verse number one, whosoever believeth that Jesus is the Christ
is born of God and everyone that loveth him that begat, loveth him also that is begotten
of him.
By the way, it's a great verse of scripture that teaches how the family of God is to interact
one with another and thankful that we have a church family and there is to be love one
for another.
Remember the Lord Jesus Christ gave that teaching in John 13, this new commandment I give unto
thee that you love one another, but it wasn't that you love as you would love yourself or
your neighbor, but you would love as Christ loved.
In verse two, by this, we know that we love the children of God when we love God and notice
it says, and keep his commandments for this is the love of God that we keep his commandments
and his commandments are not grievous.
And so again, we see that the behavior, the keeping of the commandments is the evidence
of our love for God.
He then says in verse number four, for whatsoever is born of God, overcometh the world.
And this is the victory that overcometh the world, even our faith.
When we sing, and I believe that was that portion of scripture that really influenced
the songwriter as we sing that song, faith is the victory.
So we go back to the book of James and we begin to understand as James is saying to
these recipients of these saved people, he's telling them not that their works would save
them, not that faith is not sufficient.
He's telling them that true faith works.
I know what happened when I got saved.
I can just simply talk from personal experience.
I know what happened when I got saved and I know what I wanted to do after I got saved
and not so that I could get saved because I already knew I was saved, not because I
could stay saved because I already knew that God would keep me, that I was taught that
at that time when I placed my faith and trust in Jesus Christ, they sat and showed me some
verses of scripture about eternal security for which I'm so thankful.
But I wanted to serve God.
I wanted to do something for God.
And here's what I found out as I studied through the scriptures and read and understand what
I was experiencing, that true faith produces works.
Why?
Because we're saved and we are God's workmanship and we are to walk in good works.
Not to be saved, not to stay saved, but because I am saved and because I have a new nature.
You know how many times I wanted to go to church before I got saved?
You know how many times I wanted to read the Bible before I got saved?
But all of a sudden you get saved and it's, what can I do for my master?
Not so that I can earn more of his love because he loves me.
He loves me.
It's not so that I can earn his grace because he's gracious.
It's not so that I could have more mercy because his mercy endureth forever.
It's because I have a new nature and it's because true faith works.
Talk is cheap.
And so James says, show me your faith.
I'm going to show you my faith by my works.
Try to show me your faith without works.
It's going to be near impossible.
We could use so many illustrations this morning to try to illustrate the fact that things
we exercise faith in and how our behavior is impacted by that.
I shared with a man years ago, probably at this point, Holland and I weren't even married,
we'll be married for 25 years this year, just in a few months, so it was probably 27, 28
years ago.
And I was talking to a man and I was on the second level of a mall and the King of Prussia
mall up in Pennsylvania, it's a very large mall up there and I was in that mall, I was
on the second level, I was working through Bible college at a place that I don't think
exists anymore, Payless Shoe Store.
And I was on break and I was talking to a man on a bench and he said, I don't believe
nothing.
Just like that.
Kind of agnostic, whatever he wanted to call himself and I said, well, do you believe in
gravity?
No.
I said, really?
I don't know why I asked that question, but I did, just the Holy Spirit kind of led me
to ask that question out of so many that I could ask.
And he said, no.
I said, okay, why don't you just kind of step over that little railing there and just kind
of step off?
And he's like, no.
I said, why not?
He said, because I'll fall.
Why?
Gravity.
Right?
It's simple.
There's a law of gravity.
So he was not going to step over the railing, though he said he did not believe in gravity.
You know what his behavior revealed to me?
That he believed in gravity, right?
So what does your behavior reveal?
What does my behavior reveal?
Do I really believe this book?
Do I really believe that it's true?
Do I really believe that people are going to die and spend eternity in the lake of fire?
Do I really believe that God wants me to be a witness, to share a gospel tract, to share
a word of testimony?
Do I really believe what the book teaches?
Or do I just say?
Because talk is cheap.
Talk is cheap.
And so show me, is what James says, your faith by your works.
Because the only thing, listen, God sees the heart.
And I'm thankful for that.
But the only thing someone can see, humanly speaking, is the outward.
That's all we can see.
And so you say that you believe?
I'm going to know what you believe by observing how you behave.
What does the evidence say?
Do we have true faith?
Because true faith works.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you so much for loving us.
We thank you for the word of God.
We thank you for the truth.
We thank you that we can compare scripture with scripture.
We thank you that genuine conversion is only by faith.
Lord, maybe there's someone here this morning that needs to be saved by the grace of God.
Maybe they've rejected the message.
Maybe they don't believe it to be true.
They've rejected time and again.
The Holy Spirit so sweetly used the word of God today to pierce their heart, to convince
them of truth, to convict them of their own sin, of Christ's righteousness, of judgment
to come, that it is true that whosoever is not found written in the book of life is cast
in the lake of fire.
Maybe they need to be saved this morning.
God, I pray that you'd work and draw that individual to yourself.
We also said that genuine conversion produces fruit.
We've been saved to serve you.
We are your workmanship.
And God, I pray that we'd evaluate our lives, those of us that are saved this morning, evaluate
our lives to see if that true faith is working.
What's the evidence?
Do we really believe you?
Do we really believe that what you say in your word is true?
Has it impacted our behavior?
Is it evidence through what we do day by day?
Lord, would you work in this moment?
I have a brief invitation. I pray that you would work in hearts and lives. Lord, we've heard, but now help us to respond.
I pray, Father, that you would be glorified through every decision that's made. For it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me?