chapter 14 this morning, Exodus chapter 14,
be looking at verses 1 through 31.
It's a lengthy passage of scripture.
I will not read the entirety of it
as we begin here this morning,
but let me read just a few verses for you.
Begin with me in verse number one of Exodus 14.
The Bible says this,
"'And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,
"'Speak unto the children of Israel,
"'that they turn and encamp before Pi-hahiroth,
"'between Migdal and the sea,
"'over against Baal-zephon,
"'before it shall ye encamp by the sea.'"
Notice in verse number 31,
the Bible says,
"'And Israel saw that great work
"'which the Lord did upon the Egyptians.
"'The people feared the Lord and believed the Lord
"'and His servant Moses.'"
The children of Israel had left Egypt
and God led them,
as we look at the text of scripture this morning,
to Pi-hahiroth, between Migdal and the sea,
over against Baal-zephon.
We read that in verse number two,
and we find that it would be in this place
where God would instruct His people to set up their camp,
but it would also be here at this place.
As they had the sea before them,
and as we read through the text of scripture here
in just a little while,
the Egyptians in hot pursuit behind them,
we find that it would be in this place,
in this text of scripture,
where the children of Israel would be eyewitnesses
of God's great work.
It's amazing to me, and it's encouraging to me,
it's exciting to me,
to be able to hear people give testimony
of how God is working in their lives.
It's exciting to hear folks give testimony
of what God has done in their lives,
and man, those are encouraging times and exciting times.
In fact, the Bible says,
"'Let the redeemed of the Lord say so.'"
We're to let our mouths open and give praise unto our God,
and it's encouraging, it's exciting to hear
what God is doing in the lives of His people.
I would say this, this morning,
it's exciting, encouraging to be able to read the accounts
of what God has done in the lives of His people.
You read through the Bible, it's encouraging,
it's exciting to read what God has done
for these, His people.
It's exciting to read books
of those that have gone on before us
that have written out testimonies
of what God has done in and through their lives.
A pastor friend gave me a book a couple of months ago,
and he said, have you ever read this book?
And I said, no, I've not read that book,
I've not heard of that book before,
and he gave me the book,
and I began reading it this past week,
and I typically, I have a reading schedule
that I'm going through in books,
and I kinda, somebody gives me a book,
and I put it on the list,
and I'll finish the books that I'm reading,
or maybe whatever the next one is,
and I got to this book this week,
and began reading, and it was a man that really,
he's just giving the testimony
of what God did in and through his life.
They're short chapters,
but man, it's encouraging to hear
how a servant of the Lord surrendered his life to God,
and God used him.
But I'll say this,
what's most exciting is when you have front row seats,
and you get to see God work,
and you're an eyewitness of God's great work.
Oh, it's good to hear
about what God's doing in your life,
and how God's working.
It's exciting to read of what God has done,
and what God is doing in the lives of other people,
but I'll tell you,
when you have the opportunity and the privilege
to see God work in your own life,
and to have those front row seats,
and I've titled the message Eyewitnesses of His Great Work,
because there's nothing like seeing God work personally.
Oh, it's exciting to read it.
It's exciting to hear about it,
but oh, how we long to see God work in our own lives.
By the way, God's still working.
God's still on His throne.
God's still able to do exceeding abundantly
above all that we ask or think.
Listen, God's still in control.
He still rules, and He reigns,
and we can rejoice in all of that wonderful truth
that God gives us in His word,
and we find that God is still working today.
As we look at this portion of scripture,
if you're taking notes this morning,
I want you to notice with me, first of all, the dilemma.
In verses one through nine,
we find that God provides for us a record,
and I use the phrase the dilemma,
because this would be really the perspective
of the people of God, the children of Israel,
and they obviously thought from a human perspective,
humanly speaking, there was absolutely no way out.
We find, as we've read already in the first two verses,
where they are, and notice in verse number three,
the Bible says, for Pharaoh will say
of the children of Israel, they are entangled in the land,
the wilderness hath shut them in.
It says in verse number four,
and I will harden Pharaoh's heart
that he shall follow after them,
and I will be honored upon Pharaoh and upon all his host
that the Egyptians may know that I am the Lord,
and they did so.
And it was told the king of Egypt
that the people fled, and the heart of Pharaoh
and of his servants was turned against the people,
and they said, why have we done this,
that we have let Israel go from serving us?
The simple answer is all those 10 plagues,
and we dealt with that last week,
how that in Egypt, God made his greatness known,
and we looked at the portion of scripture,
and we understood those ways
in which God made his greatness known,
not only to the Egyptians,
but also to the children of Israel,
but we noticed the Bible says in verse number six,
and he made ready his chariot,
and took his people with him,
and he took 600 chosen chariots,
and all the chariots of Egypt,
and captains over every one of them.
The Lord hardened the heart of Pharaoh, king of Egypt,
and he pursued after the children of Israel.
The children of Israel went out with a high hand,
but the Egyptians pursued after them,
all the horses and chariots of Pharaoh,
and his horsemen and his army,
and overtook them in camping by the sea beside Pi-hahiroth,
which before Bel-Zephon.
I want you to understand that
as we look at this dilemma here,
that the children of Israel would be facing,
it's important for us to recognize this morning
that they were in the place where God led them.
They're in the place where God led them.
We find that God spoke that in verse number two to Moses
with regard to the place of the camp,
but if you were to back up into chapter number 13,
and notice in verse number 17 specifically,
we won't read the entirety,
but you could read down through the end of the chapter,
but notice in Exodus 13 and verse 17,
the Bible says, and it came to pass
when Pharaoh had let the people go,
notice these words,
they're important words that God led them,
that God led them.
Moses was the human leader for the nation of Israel,
God had put him in that place,
but we understand and we see very plainly in the scriptures
that it was God that led them.
It's important for us to understand
and recognize that truth this morning,
and it says that God led them, notice,
not through the way of the land of the Philistines,
although that was near.
For God said, lest peradventure the people repent
when they see war and they return to God,
but God led the people about
through the way of the wilderness of the Red Sea,
and the children of Israel went up
harnessed out of the land of Egypt.
And so we find that God led the people, notice,
it says that he led them not in a certain way.
By the way, it could be argued, as you see here,
that it says, although that was near,
that it would have been a closer route.
Some kid told me years ago, I said, man, how was the trip?
He said, we took the long cut.
I'd never heard anyone say that before,
and they were really making an insult against the driving
of the fact that they didn't take a shortcut,
but we find that God led them.
Listen, I'm sure that within the congregation
of the nation of Israel,
that there were some that said, why don't we go this way?
Moses, the reason why we're not going that way
is because Moses isn't leading, it's God that's leading.
We find that God led them to the exact place
where he wanted them to be,
and we find that as God would lead them,
that they find themselves in this position.
We find that as we've read the text of scripture
in verses five through nine, that God records for us
the way in which the Egyptians would pursue
the children of Israel.
Their thought would be that they were entangled in the land,
that the wilderness hath shut them in,
according to verse number three.
Humanly speaking, it seems like there's no way out.
Maybe you've been in a position like that
before in your life.
Maybe you would say, not publicly,
but maybe in your heart this morning,
you'd say, you know, I'm in a position like that right now.
But humanly speaking, it seems like there's no way out.
I'm facing a dilemma in my life, I'm facing a difficulty,
and it seems as if there's no way out.
Listen, do not doubt God.
Someone said this, a preacher of yesteryear,
never put a question where God's put a period.
And the reality is that there are times in our life
that God will lead us, and we follow the leadership of God
in our lives, and it might take us directly to a place
where it seems like there's no way out.
But God, but God.
I'm so thankful that we have a God of the impossible.
I'm so thankful that we have a God,
in fact, it's how appropriate the bulletin this morning,
Luke 137, for with God nothing shall be impossible.
I don't pick the bulletins, but what a blessing.
This was the next one in line, we order them quarterly.
And what a blessing, listen,
we serve the God of the impossible.
And humanly speaking, sometimes we just look at things
on the human plane, we look at it from our own perspective.
If you're like me, at times you face a situation,
you wanna roll your sleeves up and get to work,
and let's figure this thing out.
And sometimes it's difficult for us to.
But stand back and let God work.
The dilemma.
I want you to notice that their dilemma, as we continue reading through the text of Scripture
beginning in verse number 10, number two, their distress.
Their distress.
Unfortunately, the children of Israel forgot some of what they had just seen in Egypt.
In fact, they'd saw the power of God on display as we mentioned with the plagues and all that
took place and God demonstrating His greatness and those plagues that affected all, both
the Egyptians and the children of Israel.
But then, as we would note and as we looked at last week, how there were a series of plagues
that only affected the Egyptians.
They did not affect the children of Israel and God was showing, He was making that distinction.
He was making His power, His greatness known to His people.
We said this last week, we ended the service by saying that God always has a purpose and
that God was making His greatness known so that we would know it personally, so that
we would praise Him accordingly, and so that we would trust Him fully.
You know what's very interesting to me?
There are times in which God will lead us directly into a place to see if we'll trust Him.
To see if what we say is really how we live.
It's easy to talk.
It's another thing to live the walk.
And we find that the children of Israel, their dilemma is followed by their distress.
Notice their perspective as it is revealed to us in verses 10, 11, and 12.
The Bible says in verse number 10, and when Pharaoh drew nigh, the children of Israel
lifted up their eyes and behold, the Egyptians marched after them.
The Bible tells us they were sore afraid.
The children of Israel cried out unto the Lord.
But notice what they say as they cry out.
They said unto Moses, because there were no graves in Egypt, hast thou taken us away to
die in the wilderness?
Wherefore hast thou dealt thus with us to carry us forth out of Egypt?
Their perspective, they were going to be controlled by fear.
As you look at this text of Scripture, it shows us in verse number 12, notice it says,
is not this the word that we did tell thee in Egypt, saying let us alone that we may
serve the Egyptians?
They were regretting the fact that they even left Egypt.
So there are times in which we begin to face a difficulty in life, a dilemma, and then
we start retracing our steps and we can regret some things.
And they respond with fear, they're being controlled by fear.
They regret leaving Egypt, they believe that death was certain.
They say in verse number 11 that you've taken us, there's not enough graves in Egypt, that's
why you brought us here to die in the wilderness.
Notice at the end of verse number 12, for it had been better for us to serve the Egyptians
than that we should die in the wilderness.
Now several weeks ago, we looked at a portion of Scripture in Horeb, God made His greatness.
And we looked in that portion of Scripture to start in the life of Moses, because Moses
made that declaration that God hath begun to reveal His greatness to him.
And we looked at how that started in Horeb, and if you remember with me back to that portion
of Scripture, you find that it was there that God revealed to Moses that He heard the cries
of His people.
And what was their cry?
Well, they weren't loving Egypt.
They were overworked.
They had a rough time.
They were crying out for deliverance, and now after they've been delivered, after they're
facing this dilemma, notice what they say, that it had been better for us to serve the
Egyptians.
Oh, they're beginning to doubt, they're beginning to doubt how God had led them in what God
was doing.
Their distress is evident to us as we note their perspective.
But I'm so thankful that as we see their perspective that we find in the next several verses here
in Exodus chapter number 14, we see God's promises.
I'm so thankful for the promises of God, aren't you?
You think about the promises we sing about, standing on the promises, we find about Peter
saying that God has given us exceeding great and precious promises.
I'm so thankful for the promises of God's Word.
And here as we note the perspective of the people of God, we find that God is going to
give some promises in verse number 13, and Moses said unto the people, fear ye not, stand
still and see the salvation of the Lord which He will show to you today.
For the Egyptians whom ye have seen today, ye shall see them again no more forever.
Notice the Bible says the Lord shall fight for you and ye shall hold your place.
The Lord said unto Moses, wherefore cryest thou unto me, speak unto the children of Israel
that they go forward.
I want you to think about that simple phrase at the end of verse number 15, that they go
forward.
Humanly speaking, it's impossible.
What is before them?
The Red Sea.
How are we going to go forward?
How are we going to do that?
Notice as we continue and consider the promises of God in verse number 16, the Bible says,
but lift thou up thy rod.
Remember that rod?
Remember when Moses in Horeb, he says, they're not going to believe me.
God told him, I am, hath sent thee unto them, and he then asked him, he said, Moses, what's
in your hand?
His rod.
And here we find he says, but lift thou up thy rod and stretch out thine hand over the
sea and divide it, and the children of Israel shall go on dry ground through the midst of
the sea.
That's amazing.
Listen, I understand that Exodus 14 is a familiar passage of scripture, but that's amazing.
It's absolutely phenomenal.
Listen, they'd not seen anything like this before.
They'd never experienced anything like this before.
God says, go forward, and here's what I'm going to do, I'm going to make a path for
you.
I'm going to provide a way.
He says, Moses, take that rod, lift it up, stretch out thine hand over the sea and divide
it.
Understand with me this morning that it was God that divided the Red Sea.
It was not Moses that divided the Red Sea.
Yes, God used him and he had to do what God told him to do, but it was God Almighty that
parted that Red Sea.
And God said this, that you would go over on dry ground.
That's amazing to me because reality would tell you that if you part some waters that
had just been flowing, they're going to be mucky and muddy and difficult to travel over.
Correct?
God said, I'm going to make it dry.
God is able.
He's able.
We find that the Bible says in verse number 17, and behold, and I, behold, I will harden
the hearts of the Egyptians and they shall follow them.
And I will get me honor upon Pharaoh and upon all his hosts, upon his chariots and upon
his horsemen.
And the Egyptians shall know that I am the Lord when I have gotten me honor upon Pharaoh,
upon his chariots and upon his horsemen.
The angel of God, we'll get to verse 19 in just a moment.
But listen, what it tells us in verse 17 and 18 about the Egyptians following, I'd understand
why they would want to follow.
If you just watched the whole congregation of the children of Israel cross over on dry
ground and the whole reason that you left Egypt to come to where you did in the first
place was to kill them and to conquer them, you'd follow after them as well.
You just watched them walk over there.
You said, well, we're going to go also.
But notice what the Bible says in verse number 19.
This is amazing.
As we begin to see the deliverance of God, even in verses 19 and 20, we see his great
power.
The Bible says, and the angel of God which went before the camp of Israel removed and
went behind them.
The pillar of the cloud went from before their face and stood behind them.
Who was behind them?
The Egyptians.
The sea is before them.
The Egyptians are behind them.
The Bible says in verse number 20, and it came between the camp of the Egyptians, the
camp of Israel.
There's a cloud and darkness to them.
Who's them?
That's the Egyptians.
The Bible says, but it gave light by night to these.
These are the children of Israel.
So the one came not near the other all the night.
Isn't that amazing?
Honestly, I think that as many times I've read through the passage of scriptures, many
times I've looked at this portion, and I love the account of the crossing of the Red Sea,
that oftentimes we skim over verses 19 and 20, but that's miraculous as well.
How that God set that difference, how that He came between them.
And we find that for one, it was darkness for the Egyptians, but for the children of
Israel, it was light for them.
And it says so that the one came not near the other all the night.
Listen, our God is able.
Our God is able.
We see the dilemma.
We see their distress, but I want you to notice with me their deliverance.
Their deliverance.
And it begins in verse 19, as we've just read about that distinction that God did in
demonstrating His power.
But notice with me as we continue reading in verse number 21, and I want you to see
what they saw.
I want you to read verse 21.
It says, and Moses stretched out his hand over the sea, and the Lord caused the sea
to go back by a strong east wind all that night, and made the sea dry land, and the
waters were divided.
Could you imagine seeing that?
You knew what was right in front of you.
You knew it was the Red Sea.
You knew there was a big body of water.
The reason that you were in distress
is because there was no way out, humanly speaking.
You knew that the Egyptians were behind you,
and you knew what was before you,
and you had no way to cross over that Red Sea.
And the Bible says in verse 21
that Moses stretched out his hand over the sea,
and the Lord caused this strong east wind
to come all that night, and he divided the waters.
Can you imagine seeing this?
This is miraculous. This is amazing.
We think about the deliverance of God,
and we see what God is doing,
and the Bible says in verse 22,
And the children of Israel
went into the midst of the sea
upon the dry ground,
and the waters were a wall unto them
on their right hand and on their left.
I want you to think about this just for a moment.
Joseph, I'm going to come down off the platform here.
They've got to move the camera a little bit.
But I want you to think about this.
If we could pretend this is the Red Sea
where they would cross through.
I want you to think about Moses standing here
and holding up the rod with his arm
and God causing that wind to come
and to part those waters.
And I want you to think about standing here
on this side as one of the children of Israel
and seeing this great power,
this great sight that is before you.
I mean, you've never witnessed
anything like this before.
This is amazing.
I mean, your jaw is on the ground.
You're seeing this great display of God's power.
And Moses says go forward.
Can I tell you there's an element of faith?
There's an element of faith.
Because as I step into that parted sea,
and I'm stepping on dry ground, by the way,
it'd be kind of interesting to feel that ground, wouldn't it?
You step on that dry ground,
and you take some more steps,
and guess what?
You have to have faith that God's going to continue
that red sea parted as you cross over.
Each step that you take, listen,
some of them in the front might have tried to run.
I don't know.
But I think about them crossing over and seeing that.
The Bible says the waters were a wall on both sides.
Can you imagine?
I'd want to try to touch it.
I don't know that I would,
but it'd probably cross my mind.
It'd be amazing to cross over.
Listen, they're eyewitnesses of God's great power.
They're seeing God do what they've never seen before.
Oh, they had the opportunity in Egypt with the plagues.
Some that they saw.
Some, no doubt, that they'd simply heard about.
They knew what was going on.
There was a portion of distance between where Pharaoh was
and Ramses and all of that and all that was going on.
But I want you to understand
that now they're crossing over that red sea.
They're experiencing personally God's great power.
And as they're experiencing personally God's great power,
they're taking one step after the other,
and they're crossing over, and they're going.
The Bible says that the children of Israel
went into the midst of the sea upon the dry ground,
and the waters were a wall unto them on their right hand
and on their left.
Notice if you skip down to verse number 29,
the Bible says this,
Wow.
Again, I know that we're familiar with this portion of Scripture,
but I want you to see how God's demonstrating His power.
And I want you to see how the children of Israel
are eyewitnesses of this great work, of God's great work.
And what a blessing it is to be an eyewitness
of what God is doing
and to see how God is able to do
what you could never even imagine.
I don't think there was probably one within the group
that said, you know, I think God can just part the sea
so that we could go over.
But God did it.
God did the impossible.
See, they've never experienced anything like this.
But what a blessing to experience personally
the power of God Almighty.
In verses 23 through 28,
the Bible tells us about the Egyptians.
And by the way, the miraculous work
doesn't cease in verse number 22.
We find that in verse number 23
that the Bible says that the Egyptians pursued
and went in after them to the midst of the sea,
even all Pharaoh's horses, his chariots, and his horsemen.
That's what God said He would do,
that He would, in verse 17 and 18,
that He would harden the hearts of the Egyptians,
that they shall follow them.
We find that they come in, they pursued after.
In verse number 24, it says,
and it came to pass that in the morning watch
the Lord looked unto the host of the Egyptians
through the pillar of fire and the cloud
and troubled the host of the Egyptians.
Notice what it says in verse 25,
and took off their chariot wheels,
that they drove them heavily.
So the Egyptians said, let us flee from the face of Israel.
Notice this, for the Lord fighteth for them
against the Egyptians.
What did God say there?
Moses said to the people of God in verse number 14,
the Lord shall fight for you
and ye shall hold your peace.
We find here that God, as He sees the Egyptians,
listen, He knew exactly how far to let them get
into the midst of that Red Sea.
He knew the exact distance to let them travel
through the midst of that Red Sea,
and then He caused their chariot wheels,
as the Bible says in verse 25,
that He took off their chariot wheels,
that they drove them heavily,
so that the Egyptians said, let us flee.
Listen, His timing is perfect.
He knows everything, and He let them get to exactly
where they were supposed to get,
and He had those chariot wheels come off,
and then the Bible says they're going to flee.
Notice in verse number 26,
and the Lord said unto Moses,
Stretch out thine hand over the sea,
that the waters may come again upon the Egyptians,
upon their chariots, and upon their horsemen.
And Moses stretched forth his hand over the sea,
and the sea returned to its strength.
When the morning appeared, and the Egyptians fled against it,
and the Lord overthrew the Egyptians
in the midst of the sea.
The Bible says that the waters returned
and covered the chariots and the horsemen
and all the host of Pharaoh that came into the sea after them
that remained not so much as one of them.
Verse 30 says, Thus the Lord saved Israel that day
out of the hand of the Egyptians,
and Israel saw the Egyptians dead upon the seashore.
This is amazing work that God did.
Not only did God part the Red Sea,
He allowed the Egyptians to pursue after,
and at just the right mark,
at just the right distance into their traveling through,
the Bible says that they got stuck,
their wheels came off, they drove heavily,
and then God said to Moses,
Now raise up that rod again,
and we're going to close the sea.
It's amazing, the power of God.
That Red Sea stayed parted because God kept it parted,
and that Red Sea closed up because God caused it to close up.
Listen, don't listen to the scoffers today
that will try to take you to this portion of Scripture
and say it wasn't the Red Sea, it was the Reed Sea.
The Bible says it's the Red Sea.
By the way, you study your Bible,
and you'll find that repeatedly through the Scriptures,
the Bible speaks about this event that took place,
and every single time, it's the Red Sea.
Even in the New Testament, as Stephen is preaching,
he preaches about the Red Sea
and what God did here in delivering the people of God
from the Egyptians.
Listen, you must always trust the Word of God.
Do not listen to what the scoffers say.
By the way, the scoffers and their attack upon the Word of God
often make themselves look ridiculous,
because I would submit to you that if it were the Reed Sea,
and it is not, it is the Red Sea,
that it would be absolutely amazing
for God and just a few inches of water
to overthrow the entire army of Egypt.
But we find here that it's the Red Sea,
and God worked miraculously,
and we find that their deliverance is recorded for us
and how we can rejoice in seeing what God did
and understanding as the children of Israel
had the opportunity to be eyewitnesses
of the power of Almighty God.
It tells us in verse number 31,
and Israel saw that great work which the Lord did
upon the Egyptians.
They saw it, they experienced it,
they understood as eyewitnesses the power of God.
It tells us the impact in verse number 31,
that the people feared the Lord.
By the way, it's a good thing for people to fear God.
Some people today that run around saying,
I don't fear anything or anyone.
I've seen people wearing clothing that says
only God can judge me,
and they wear it boldly as if to say,
make some statement about no one can judge them.
Listen, it's a fearful thing to stand before God Almighty,
the judge of all the earth.
It's a fearful thing.
Our God is to be feared.
He has great power.
By the way, it was a proper thing...
for them to respond in this manner. It says that they feared the Lord, notice this, and believed
the Lord. You know, God wants you to believe Him. He wants us to believe Him.
He wants us to trust Him. He wants us to believe that He is able to do
in your situation, in your circumstance, amazing things.
So we continue to think about the impact of this particular event in the nation of Israel.
We'll look at just a few verses in chapter 15, and I want you to notice what the Bible says.
This chapter 15, the first 21 verses at least, are dealing with the people singing and rejoicing
and how God had delivered His people and how they're rejoicing. It starts in verse number one
of chapter 15, then sang Moses and the children of Israel this song unto the Lord. Here's what
they said in verse number one, I will sing unto the Lord, for He hath triumphed gloriously. The
horse and his rider hath He thrown into the sea. Do you notice in their song what they recognize?
They recognize that it was God that did the work, for He hath triumphed gloriously. When God works
in your life and in my life, I hope that we give God the credit. I hope that we give God the glory.
I hope that we recognize that it's God that did the work and that we do not try to explain it
through, well, you know, I made this decision and I did this and I had it. No, no, no. We got to give
God the glory. We got to give God the glory. He alone is worthy. We find that they recognize that
it was God who had triumphed gloriously. Notice with me in verse number seven, the Bible says,
And in the greatness of thine excellency, thou hast overthrown them that rose up against thee.
Thou sentest forth thy wrath, which consumed them as stubble. You notice there it speaks about the
greatness of thine excellency and the work that God did. You notice in verse number 13, in verse
number 12, it says, Thou stretchest out thy right hand, and the earth swallowed them. Thou in thy
mercy hast led forth the people which thou hast redeemed. Thou hast guided them in thy strength
unto thy holy habitation. Listen, they're singing a different song than they were singing there at
Pi-hahiroth, aren't they? Because they saw God work. They're eyewitnesses of what God did.
They're saying, look at what God did in thy mercy. Understand this morning that our God is
merciful. He's merciful. I'm so thankful this morning to be a recipient of God's great mercy.
The Bible says that thou hast led forth the people which thou hast redeemed. Notice thou
hast guided them in thy strength unto thy holy habitation. I'm thankful for the leadership and
guidance that God gives in our lives. Listen, as we faithfully seek the face of God,
we understand that He provides direction for us. They were not singing that same tune when
they were found there at Pi-hahiroth at the beginning of chapter 14, even though it was God
that led them. They're saying, Moses, why did you bring us here? You brought us here to die in the
wilderness. But now they're saying God led and God guided them. Notice in verse number 16, Fear and
dread shall fall upon them. By the greatness of thine arm, they shall be as still as a stone.
Till thy people pass over, O Lord, till the people pass over which thou hast purchased.
Let me say this, as we think about the children of Israel, they say this in verse 18, the Lord
shall reign forever and ever. And that's true. He's going to reign forever and ever. But I want
you to understand, as we think about the children of Israel in this portion of Scripture, and we see
their dilemma, their distress, we see their deliverance, we see how that they had the
opportunity to be the eyewitnesses of His great power, of God's work here in this portion of
Scripture. And what they were murmuring and complaining, and they were beside themselves,
they're saying we should have never left Egypt. It was better for us to serve there in Egypt,
and we're going to die in this wilderness. And now they're singing and they're rejoicing.
Listen, after God works, it's easy for us to rejoice.
But I hope that God would help us to learn a lesson from this portion of Scripture this morning,
that in the midst of the difficulty that we must remember that God is on His throne,
that we're faced with that dilemma that we say, I wonder what God's going to do? I wonder how
God's going to work? And we find that just as the children of Israel in this portion of Scripture,
so we too, in our lives, often are prone to forget. We face a difficulty, we have a dilemma
in our lives. God works miraculously. I mean, you're an eyewitness of God's great power. You
see God's work in your life. It's not just that you've read about what God did for someone else,
or you heard someone else in a testimony service give praise to God for how God worked in their
life. No, I'm saying that you personally experienced God's power and God's work in your
life, and you're an eyewitness. And then there's another trial. You ever find in life that just
because you've had victory that, man, that means there's no more trials. No, no, the only time we're
going to have no more trials when we get to heaven. Amen? There's coming a day that we're going to get
to heaven, and we're going to have no more trials. Praise the Lord. But until that day,
there'll be trials in our life. And just after they're singing this wonderful song of praise to
God, after they've seen God work as eyewitnesses of God's great work, of God's great power,
the Bible tells us at the end of chapter number 15 of the book of Exodus that they come to a place,
and the Bible says that they come to a place called Marah. If you know anything about Marah,
it's a place that the Bible describes as being a place of bitter water, a place where they could
drink no water. Look at it with me in verse 22. So Moses brought Israel from the Red Sea,
and they went out into the wilderness of Shur, and they went three days in the wilderness and
no water. Now let me ask you, does God know that you need water? Absolutely. He made us.
He created us. He knows that we need water. And the Bible tells us, and they went, and they came,
notice in verse 23, and when they came to Marah, they could not drink the waters of Marah. Why?
For they were bitter, therefore the name of it was called Marah. And the people,
they got together and they said, let's see what God's going to do. Let's see how God's going to
work. Do you remember what He did in Egypt? Do you remember what He did at the Red Sea? Do you
remember how He parted at the Red Sea? No, they didn't say any of that. They murmured, the Bible
says, against Moses saying, what shall we drink? He cried unto the Lord. The Lord showed him a tree
and he cast it. But the Bible says at the end of verse number 25, notice what the Bible says. I'll
read the entirety of it. And he cried unto the Lord and the Lord showed him a tree, which when
he had cast in the waters, the waters were made sweet. There he made for them a statute and
ordinance and there he proved them. God proves us. You're going to trust Him? You see God work.
They were eyewitnesses of His great work. They got to see God do something
that no one had ever seen before. This group of people in Exodus chapter number 14,
they experienced something that no other group of people have ever experienced.
The Jordan River is a different situation. You can read it in the book of Joshua.
But this circumstance here in Exodus chapter number 14, only this group of people experienced
this personally. And though they experienced some great, mighty work of God, they come to the next
trial and they murmur. They forget what God is able to do. I hope that it would not be the case
for you or for me. I hope that as God allows us to be eyewitnesses of His great power, as God would
allow us to see His great work in our lives, that when we face those next times of difficulty,
when we have that next trial and that next test, that we would have great excitement and enthusiasm
about what is God going to do? How is God going to work? Because we get to see what God is able to
do. Listen, it's exciting to see God work. It really is. But many times, you know what has to
happen before you see God work? A dilemma, a problem, a difficulty. You know how most of us
deal with difficulties? We don't like them. We try to avoid them at all costs, right? But we see that
God leads us. And at times, as God is leading us, He is leading us directly into a place
where He's going to prove His great power. He's going to show you His work. Turn to the
book of Psalms, if you will. We'll finish with this in Psalm 119. In Psalm 119,
there's a verse of Scripture here that I want to close our service with this morning. I hope that
it would be a verse that would be a prayer of each of ours this morning and this week. In Psalm 119,
in verse number 126, the Bible says this, it is time for thee, Lord, to work.
For they have made void thy law.
No doubt, we live in the midst of a place where they've made void the law of God.
We understand that.
But I want you to see that statement to begin the verse, it is time for Thee, Lord, to work.
I wonder this morning, how many of us are anxious to see God work?
I mean desiring to see God do something, that we would surrender and yield our lives to
God and say, God, I just want to see you work.
I want to see you.
Listen, it's all for God's glory.
It's not for my glory.
It's not for your glory.
It's all for His glory.
And we would be careful, even as they sang the praise, to understand that the Lord, it
is He that hath worked gloriously, triumphed gloriously.
And we find this morning that we would pray and say, God, it's time, Lord, for Thee to
work.
We long to see you work in our lives personally, in our church, corporately, in our nation.
We long, God, to see you work.
God is able.
The children of Israel faced a great difficulty, but God wasn't concerned for one moment.
For God knew that He led them exactly to that place, and He was going to show His great
power.
And they were eyewitnesses of His great work.
This morning, I enjoy reading about, I enjoy listening to people give testimony about what
God has done.
But the most exciting is seeing God work personally.
And I want to be an eyewitness of God's great work in my life, in your life, in our lives
corporately.
Let's see what God will do as we yield and surrender to Him, that we would give God the
glory for He is worthy of it.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love You.
How we thank You for loving us.
We thank You this morning for this record that's given to us in Exodus 14.
Many of us this morning are familiar with this portion of Scripture.
No doubt within a group this size, there are some that would say, that's my favorite account
of all of God's Word.
I love that passage of Scripture.
God, I pray this morning, as we've had the opportunity to go through and to learn from
this portion of Scripture, God, You would help us to have that longing of the psalmist.
It is time for Thee, Lord, to work, that we would be eyewitnesses, just as the children
of Israel here in Exodus 14, that we be eyewitnesses of Your great work.
I pray, God, that this morning You would help Your people.
No doubt there's some that are dealing with some difficulties, some dilemmas, some situations
that from a human perspective seem to be no way out, no path forward.
I'm so thankful that in those circumstances, in those situations, You love to prove Your
power.
I pray, God, that You would work and move in hearts and lives as only You can.
There's someone this morning that's not sure of heaven.
I pray that today, Lord, they'd understand their need for Christ.
Give us an opportunity to take a Bible and show them how they could know for sure that
heaven is their home.
We pray that in these few moments of invitation that You'd have Your will and way.
We'll thank You for each decision that will be made, for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would You stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
He's going to play quietly on the piano this morning.