You could turn that down just a tad.
I'd appreciate it, thank you.
And in verses one and two, remember he said this,
how are they increase that trouble me?
Many are they that rise up against me.
Remember what they were saying of David.
They said, according to verse number two,
there is no help for him in God.
And so we discovered the situation
in which David was facing, the reality of the situation.
It was not something that he was embellishing,
that he was exaggerating.
It was not something that he was imagining.
This was a real serious situation that he was facing.
We find that it was in 2 Samuel 15,
really through chapter 19, that you read about the revolt,
the rebellion of Absalom.
And that's the time of the particular writing of this psalm.
And we find that in verses three and four,
as we studied last week,
we examined the response of David to the situation.
And so we found the reality of the situation,
but we said, how does he respond to the situation?
The fact of the matter is that each of us
have circumstances, situations that we face in life,
trials and troubles and difficulties.
And the reality is that our response to that circumstance
or that situation is of utmost importance.
How do we deal, how do we respond to the circumstances
in which we're facing?
And as we studied last week, we discovered right away
that to summarize the response of David to this situation,
we could simply use one word
and say that it was the word prayer.
David responded by praying.
It's exciting to me that first in his prayer,
in verse number three, he rehearsed who it was,
who God was or is to him.
And what a blessing.
Remember, as we mentioned a moment ago,
in verse number two, they were saying the enemies,
those that were rising against him,
were saying there is no help for him in God.
There is no help for him in God.
But David, as he responds to the situation in prayer,
he says, oh Lord, he says, thou art a shield for me.
And what a blessing.
The enemy says there's no help for you, not even in God.
And David rehearses, he remembers the fact
that God is his shield.
It's the first reference in the book of Psalms.
There are many references throughout the book of Psalms
with regard to the reality that our God is our shield
and our buckler, and he's a strong tower,
he's our fortress, and I'm thankful for the security
and the defense that God provides for his children.
We find that David then rejoiced as we finished reading
and examining the portion of scripture last week.
We found that he rejoiced, why?
Because God heard him.
And what confidence David had in understanding
that as he prayed, that he prayed to the living God,
to the Lord God Almighty, to the omnipotent Lord,
the creator of heaven and earth,
and that he, God, heard his prayer.
Isn't that precious?
We were reminded of that truth even as we studied
on Sunday evening in Genesis chapter 25
and we noticed the supplication of Isaac
and then of Rebekah and how we rejoice
in understanding that God hears us when we pray.
We contrasted last week the idols, the works of men's hands
and how the Bible would tell us that they have ears
but they hear not.
And I'm thankful that our God is the living God
and that he hears us when we pray.
This evening as we study verses five and six,
we will examine and understand the rest
that David experienced.
We see the reality of the situation.
It was dim, it was difficult,
it was a very serious situation.
We see the response, it's a response of prayer,
it's a response of rejoicing.
And then this evening we see the rest
that David experienced.
Notice in verse number five,
the Bible says, I laid me down and slept.
I awaked for the Lord sustained me.
I will not be afraid of 10,000s of people
that have set themselves against me roundabout.
For this third study through Psalm three,
I've titled the message from verse number five,
I laid me down and slept.
We mentioned the reality, we mentioned the response.
Tonight we see the rest that David experienced.
And honestly, as we examine Psalm three,
I hope that just as it's been an encouragement to me
as I've prepared and delivered the messages,
that you too have been encouraged.
But as we look at these verses of Scripture,
I find the impact to be great.
I hope that it will have an impact
on each of our lives this evening.
My experience far too often, not only personally,
but through ministry and through years
of speaking with folks and praying with folks
and counseling folks is that there are times
in which we understand the circumstances
of the situation that we're dealing with.
And we may even respond properly.
We may respond by praying,
we may respond by taking it to the Lord,
but far too often, we do not leave it there.
Far too often we respond properly by praying,
but then we do not rest in Him.
We continue to worry, we continue to fret,
we continue to try to figure things out.
But we find this evening that in verses five and six,
that this is a beautiful picture and a beautiful example
of taking our burdens to the Lord and leaving them there.
And understanding that we understand who He is.
David just rehearsed that in verse number three.
But thou, O Lord, art a shield for me,
my glory and the lifter up of mine head.
He understood who God was to him.
He understood that God heard him.
I cried unto the Lord with my voice
and He heard me out of His holy hill, Selah,
and then what?
I laid me down and slept.
Isn't that amazing?
When you read verse one and you read verse number two
and you see the situation that David is facing,
you see the increase of those that would trouble him
and the many that were rising against him
and you understand contextually
as you go back to 2 Samuel 15
and look at all that was taking place
and the size of the rebellion and the revolt
and you say, to go from understanding his situation
to laying his head down and going to sleep, wow.
What a rest.
What a great example.
He went to sleep.
I believe that it's a great picture of the peace of God.
There's no sleepless night for David.
No, we look at this passage of Scripture
and we understood that David took his need
to the only one that could do something about it.
He took it to the Creator of heaven and earth.
He took it to the Lord God omnipotent.
He poured out his heart.
He says, I cried unto the Lord with my voice.
In understanding that God heard him,
he laid down and went to sleep.
I love it.
It's so impactful.
Why, because far too often we don't live there.
I'm just being honest tonight.
Far too often we don't live there.
We take it to God and we continue to worry and fret
and we continue to try to figure things out,
but we find that he went to sleep.
See, worry will not change one thing of your circumstance.
It really won't.
Someone said this, everything I've ever worried about
never came to pass.
And so worry works.
No, no, worry doesn't work.
It's just that the things you worried about didn't happen.
And often we find that to be the case.
Isn't it true?
We worry about things.
Someone said this worry is like a rocking chair.
It'll keep you busy, but it won't get you anywhere.
How many of you have a rocking chair?
You know, you just sit there and rock, right?
Kind of get the picture of the folks
sitting on the front porch, sipping the sweet tea,
and they're not getting anywhere off that front porch.
They're just, it keeps them busy.
It keeps them doing something,
but they're not getting anywhere.
So often in our lives, we worry,
and we say that as we think about worry,
the fact that it will not change the situation,
but I would submit to you this evening,
that worry also reveals in us a lack of faith.
It really does.
When we worry about the circumstances,
about the situation, we're revealing that we're
really not sure that God's able to take care of it.
Right?
Turn to the book of Philippians.
Keep your place here in Psalm 3,
and look over the book of Philippians.
We're familiar with the passage of scripture
in Philippians chapter number four,
and we know that the picture often throughout
the scriptures in here in Psalm 3 is one such example
of this truth that we read in Philippians 4,
and there are many that we could go to,
but this evening we'll just stick to Psalm 3,
but I want you to see how that Psalm 3
really shows us the working of the truth in Philippians 4.
Notice in Philippians 4 in verse number six,
be careful for nothing.
We're not to be full of care.
It doesn't mean be careful, like watch your step,
be careful, that's not the idea of the phraseology
when you understand the English,
and you understand he's saying don't worry about things.
Be careful for nothing.
Do not be full of care.
Have no anxiety.
Be not anxious.
Be careful for nothing.
Notice what he says, but in everything.
How?
By prayer and supplication.
With thanksgiving, let your requests be not in vain.
made known unto God."
It's a verse that we know.
But knowing it doesn't mean we practice it.
Right?
Be careful for nothing.
But in everything,
by prayer and supplication,
with thanksgiving,
let your requests be made known unto God.
And then notice verse 7.
And the peace of God,
which passeth all understanding,
shall keep your hearts and minds
through Christ Jesus.
Do you not see a great peace in David
in Psalm 3 and verse 5?
Laid down and went to sleep.
That's peace.
That's a peace that passeth all understanding.
That's a peace in the midst of a great storm.
In great difficulty.
We mentioned as we studied three weeks ago
that the situation that David was facing was real.
It was not a make-believe.
It was not an exaggerated situation.
No, this was a real difficulty.
But he went to God in prayer.
He understood who God was.
Who God is.
And he said, therefore,
I'm going to go to sleep.
I've prayed about it.
I've gone to God about it.
And I'm going to leave it with Him.
Because God is able.
And me staying up all night
worrying about what Absalom is doing
and how they're scheming
and where they're going to come from
isn't going to do anything whatsoever
to change the situation.
Right?
I'm going to change it.
And so therefore, when we look at our own lives,
when we look at our own situations,
and we look at the troubles and the difficulties
in which we deal with,
and we say, listen,
there's nothing that's going to change
our circumstances that we're going to do
that God is not able to do better.
Because He does all things well.
Amen?
Notice what it says in verse 5.
I laid me down and slept.
And then it says this, I awaked.
For the Lord sustained me.
He sustained me.
And we think about the truth this evening
that our God is our sustainer.
That He is able to keep us.
That He is able to protect us.
That He is able to provide for us all that we need.
And we sing the song,
He is able, He is able.
I know He is able.
Right?
We sing it.
We know the song.
And we sing a great hymn.
He is able to deliver thee.
And as we sing that hymn,
often my mind races to the truth
of the passage of Scripture in Daniel chapter number six.
Remember when Daniel prayed after the writing
and Daniel prayed and the Bible says
that the response of him seeking the Lord
was the attack of the enemy
and he was going to be put into the den of lions.
And we find that Darius comes to him
and Darius says, I know that the Lord
that you serve continually,
I know He is able to deliver thee.
Now in that account in Daniel six,
who slept and who didn't sleep?
Daniel slept.
But the king didn't sleep.
Right?
And the king didn't sleep
and he comes to Daniel and he says,
Daniel, is your God whom you serve continually
able to deliver thee?
And Daniel responds, yes.
Yes, the Lord is able.
And so this evening,
we see this truth where he went to sleep.
He is showing us,
he's revealing to us this peace of God that he has.
Why?
Because he took it to the Lord and he left it there.
And the Lord sustained him.
The Lord kept him.
I want you to see as we continue
and look at verse number six,
note the resolve of David.
I love the I wills of the Psalms.
In fact, if you want to do a study,
you can go through the entirety of the book of Psalms.
In fact, there are many in just Psalm 119,
but you'll find where the Psalmist
makes these declarative statements,
these statements with resolve.
I will do such and such.
I will keep thy commandments.
I will not forget thy commandments.
I will, I will, I will.
And we find here that David says,
I will not be afraid.
Now we'll know what he's not going to be afraid of
here in just a moment,
but I want you to think and I want you to understand
that in the situation in which David is facing
and the circumstances that we understand
in verses one and two,
there was reason to fear from a human perspective.
Correct?
And when you understand how David words this
in verse number six,
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
and you have an opportunity to really wrap your mind
around the size of the rebellion and the revolt,
you find that David is saying, I will not be afraid.
Why?
Because David has some great level of courage,
because David is some manly man with this courage
that none of us can understand.
No, that's not why he's saying I will not be afraid.
He's saying I will not be afraid.
Why?
Because I've looked to my God
and my God is able to do what I cannot do.
And since I've looked to my God
and since I've placed my confidence and my trust in my God,
I will not be afraid.
He has not given us a spirit of fear, right?
Is that not what the New Testament tells us?
He's not given us the spirit of fear.
And I want you to consider as David says here,
I will not be afraid.
Notice what he says, of 10,000s of people
that have set themselves against me roundabout.
That's a situation.
But David says, I'm not gonna fear.
I'm not gonna fear, because my God is greater.
My God is able.
And when we think about the peace, the rest of David,
when we find in verse number five,
this rest that he has, where he lays down,
I laid me down and slept,
in the midst of all that's taking place,
we see this rest as a result of him taking it to the Lord
in verses three and four,
that response to his situation
results in this great rest, this great peace.
Can I tell you this evening,
that's where God wants us to be.
He wants us to have that peace and that confidence
in who He is, in what He is able to do.
He does not want us to worry and fret like the unbeliever.
I understand when the unbeliever worries and frets.
I understand that they do not have
an understanding of who my God is,
and they do not have a relationship
because they've not trusted Christ
as their personal Savior,
and therefore, I understand when they worry and fret.
But as a child of God, as a believer,
when we understand all that He said He was to us
and is to us, we ought not worry and fret.
Amen?
Because God is able.
Notice, look at Psalm 27.
We're gonna look at a few Psalms
and then look at a passage in the book of Hebrews,
and I want you to see in these other references here
in the book of Psalms, Psalm 27,
I want you to notice here in these three references
the resolve and the statement of not fearing
because of understanding who God is.
In Psalm 27, in verse number one,
the Bible says, the Lord is my light and my salvation.
Whom shall I fear?
The Lord is the strength of my life.
Of whom shall I be afraid?
When the wicked, even mine enemies and my foes,
came upon me to eat up my flesh,
they stumbled and fell.
Though an host should encamp against me,
my heart shall not fear.
Though war should rise against me,
in this will I be confident.
One thing have I desired of the Lord,
that will I seek after,
that I may dwell in the house of the Lord
all the days of my life,
to behold the beauty of the Lord
and to inquire in his temple.
I will not fear.
You notice three times he says, of whom shall I fear?
Of whom shall I be afraid?
He says in verse three, my heart shall not fear.
Why?
Because God is my light and my salvation.
Because the Lord is the strength of my life.
Because I understand who he is.
And it changes my response to circumstances and situations.
Notice in Psalm 56, and really,
we will not take the time,
but we could read the entirety of this Psalm.
It's only 13 verses.
Perhaps you'd like to take the time
to do that later this week and read the entirety.
But I'll just pick a few verses here this evening
to help us see what's taking place.
Notice in verse number one,
be merciful unto me, O God,
for man would swallow me up.
He fighting daily oppresseth me.
Mine enemies would daily swallow me up,
for they be many that fight against me.
O thou most high, what time I am afraid,
I will trust in thee.
In God, I will praise his word.
In God, I have put my trust.
I will not fear what flesh can do unto me.
Why?
Because in God, I have put my trust.
Every day, he says in verse number five,
rest my words, all their thoughts are against me for evil, they gather
themselves together, they hide themselves, they mark my steps when they wait for my
soul." Wow. Verse 8, thou tellest my wanderings, put thou my tears into thy
bottle, are they not in thy book when I cry unto thee? Notice in verse number 9,
when I cry unto thee, then shall mine enemies turn back, this I know. Notice
this last phrase of verse number 9, for God is for me. Isn't that good? God is for me.
Oftentimes we want to say, you know, who's on God's side or however we want to
look at something like that. We see that the psalmist here is declaring the
circumstances in which they're facing and dealing with all that's taking place
and he says here in verse number 9, I know, this I know. See, God wants us to be
confident of who he is to us. He says, this I know, for God is for me. If God
be for us, who shall be against us? Greater is he that is in you than he
that is in the world. And we find that the reality of God's Word, again, we've
said this over the years, it's not just a book of theory, it's a book of practice.
When we understand and we study the Scriptures and we understand who he is
and who he is to me and we rejoice in that and we rehearse that and we
remember that, then when the day of adversity comes, our strength has been
increased. It's not small. We will not faint. Why? Because we know who he is and
we have confidence in him. We've put our trust in him. Notice in Psalm 118. In
Psalm 118, in verse number 6, notice it says, the Lord is on my side. I will not
fear. What can man do unto me? You understand that man can only do to you
what God would let him? Remember Job? Satan wanted to go after Job, but Satan
was limited in what he could do to Job, right? You read Job and you understand
that there were limitations placed upon what Satan could and could not do to
Job. Everything that happens in our life goes through God's filter. Everything. And
he has a purpose for it. I was chatting with one of the pastors yesterday. He wasn't
able to make it to the meeting and I just called him to encourage him. He's
starting a church and just kind of new at it and so on and so forth and they're
doing well and he wasn't able to make it so I called him to just try to
encourage him and dealing with some some obstacles and what-have-you and he made
this statement. He said, but we know and we're confident of this that
everything that God does is for our good. And I said, and for His glory. And that's
true. It's biblical truth. Everything that God allows. Remember the truth of Romans
828. Oftentimes we don't quote the beginning when it says, and we know that
all things work together for good to them who love God, to them who are the
called according to His purpose. And it starts by saying, and we know because God
wants us to know that. He wants us to have confidence in that. Hebrews 13 and
verses 5 and 6, the Bible tells us in that portion of Scripture that God will
never leave us nor forsake us and what great truth and great promise that is.
But you understand with a promise such as that, there's an impact. And the impact
is really revealed to us as we look at this passage. He says, let your
conversation, and in Hebrews 13 and verse number 5, let your conversation be
without covetousness and be content with such things as ye have. For he hath
said, I will never leave thee nor forsake thee, so that we may boldly say, the Lord
is my helper and I will not fear what man shall do unto me. What was it that
they said, the enemies, in verse number 2 of Psalm 3? There's no help for him in
God. But David said, Lord, thou art a shield for me. And he went to sleep
because he was resting. He had peace. Isaiah 26, it's a familiar verse of
Scripture in verse 3 where the Bible talks about the the peace that God
offers us and that perfect peace. Verses 3 and 4 of Isaiah 26 are precious verses
of Scripture. It tells us this, thou will keep him in perfect peace whose mind is
stayed on thee. Where's our mind? You know, oftentimes when we deal with adversity
and trouble and difficulty, the battle's in our mind. I've said to people over the
years, how much of what you're thinking about passes through the filter of
Philippians 4.8. Philippians 4.8, whatsoever things are true and honest and
pure and so on and so forth, think on these things, right? The battle for our
mind, so often what's happening is our mind is not stayed on thee, on the Lord.
We're too focused on our problem and on the situation, on the trial. Remember we
mentioned that last week when we talked about the response of David. Yes, this is
the situation, but I'm gonna look to God. I will lift up my eyes unto the hills
from whence cometh my help. And we find that he says, my help cometh from the
Lord which made heaven and earth. And it says this, thou will keep him in perfect
peace whose mind is stayed on thee because he trusteth in thee. Verse 4,
trust ye in the Lord forever for in the Lord Jehovah is everlasting strength.
Man, I need that perfect peace. That perfect peace comes as a result of
trusting him, of keeping my mind stayed on him. This evening we think about the
the truth of Psalm 3. There was a real situation, the reality is given to us in
verses 1 and 2. The response is exemplary. It's a response of prayer, of
rehearsing who God is to me. David is understanding that he is a shield for me,
that he is my glory, that he is the lifter up of mine head, and he's not
going to fear. He lays down, he has peace, he has rest. I thought about this tonight
as I was, actually this afternoon, as I was just kind of meditating and reviewing
the notes for the message, I don't know, 3 or 4 o'clock this afternoon, just kind
of reviewing and meditating on the message for this evening. And as I was, I
was thinking about this subject of faith and trust, and how we are to trust God in
all situations, and how so often we take something to the Lord but then we
continue to have worry or concern. And we've learned how to use the vernacular
where we won't say I'm worried, we'll just say I'm concerned about this, and
I'm concerned about that, because we know we shouldn't use the word worry, and we
just try to, you know, Christianize it a little bit, make it sound better. But I
thought about this, and I know it's probably not a perfect illustration, but
it's what the Lord gave me as I was praying about it and just thinking about
it. And here was the the illustration I thought about. How many of you ever have
mailed a letter, mail a letter in the Postal Service, put the address on it, put
a stamp on it, you put it in the mailbox? How many of you worry about it for the
next five days until it gets delivered? Dean, liar. I don't, I don't worry about
it. I put it in the mailbox, and quite honestly, I just kind of forget about it,
right? But guess what I'm doing? I'm trusting a whole lot of people to get
that envelope from wherever I put it in a box to wherever it's supposed to go.
Now let me ask you this, how many of you ever mailed something that didn't get
delivered? I have. So you know what that tells me? The Post Office, the United
States Postal Service has, on more than one occasion, failed me. But I still take
a letter and mail it, and don't worry about it when I do. God has never failed
me one time. Not once. But there are times that I take something to God, and I cast
my burden, but then I keep worrying about it, as if He is not dependable, as if He
is not trustworthy. Again, I know it's not a perfect illustration, but it was
impactful to me in my office this afternoon, because I can't tell you how
many times I've dropped a letter, a card, in the mail, and never thought about it
again. And I'm putting a level of confidence, of faith, of trust, in a bunch
of people to get a letter from wherever I put it.
God dropped it off to wherever it's supposed to go, but God, God's never going to fail.
He is able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think.
He's never failed.
He's never said, oh, I wasn't supposed to do that.
No, never.
He is dependable.
He is trustworthy.
And when we understand that, we can do what David did.
We can lay down and go to sleep.
We can have rest and we can have peace.
Why?
Because I know that God is able and I know that he doeth all things well.
And me sitting up and worrying about it and fretting about it isn't going to change it.
And if Dean's worried about his letter getting delivered by the post office, he's going to
have to drive it himself, right?
Because that's what we would do.
We just go ahead and take it ourselves.
Because you worry about it, you don't even know where it is.
I don't know how it gets from one place to another.
But I know that God has given us promises upon promises upon promises, and he's trustworthy.
He laid down and he went to sleep.
Wow.
Impactful.
Precious.
Lord, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
I thank you for the rest that David experienced.
I thank you for the resolve.
I will not fear.
God, when we understand who you are to us and we understand the promises that you've
given us, we understand your sovereignty, God, there's no reason to fear.
You've not given us a spirit of fear.
You desire that we'd have peace and rest.
And this is where you desire for us to live.
I know that we deal with situations with opposition and difficulty.
We know that the enemy will say all sorts of things, even as they said to David.
But God, we trust what you say.
And you said that you're our helper.
You said that you'd never leave us nor forsake us.
You said that you're able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think.
God, we believe that.
We trust you.
I pray that you'd help us to be careful for nothing, but that in everything, by prayer
and supplication, with thanksgiving, we would let our requests be made known unto you so
that we might have that peace of God which passeth all understanding.
Help us, Lord.
Bless our time of prayer.
We'll thank you for it.
In Christ's name we pray, amen.