29 down through chapter 50 in verse number 14. And so we'll kind of bridge
both chapters this evening and look there if you will, Genesis
49 verse 29. This is the 101st message
in the book of Genesis and I thought we'd hit
a hundred and I wasn't able to quite get it all done in a hundred messages
so we're gonna be at like a hundred and three or four something like that
but praise the Lord I have thoroughly enjoyed the study I hope that you have
as well
and I've been praying about where to go next I think I think the Lord confirmed
it
but I'm not a hundred percent sure and so I'm gonna wait one more week to
announce it
but I'm pretty confident where God is leading me for our next study
and I'm excited about it. Genesis chapter 49 verse 29 and he
this is Jacob speaking, remember he blessed all the sons brought them in
before him we've had
three weeks of lessons covering the first 28 verses
of Genesis 49. Each son stood before Jacob
and we find that he's speaking it says he charged them
and said unto them I am to be gathered
unto my people. Bury me with my fathers in the cave that is in the field of
Ephron the Hittite. The cave that is in the field of Machpelah which
is before Mamre in the land of Canaan which Abraham bought with the field of Ephron
the Hittite
for possession of a burying place. There they buried Abraham and Sarah's wife
there
they buried Isaac and Rebekah his wife and there I buried
Leah. The purchase of the field and of the cave that is
therein was from the children of Heth.
When Jacob had made an end of commanding his sons
he gathered up his feet into the bed and yielded
up the ghost and was gathered unto his people.
We'll read into chapter 50 as we get to the message this evening I've titled the
message Jacob's final request
and as we look at this passage of scripture we're reminded even as we've
mentioned for a number of weeks now
with regard to the death of Jacob being recorded in this chapter
the Bible tells us as it appointed unto man once to die
but after this the judgment. In fact I just had someone tell me recently
when I asked them if they were sure that if they were to die that heaven is their
home
they said no. I mean they were confident that the answer was no
and I thought that was an open door of opportunity to be able to share the
gospel and let them know
how they could be for sure and yet they were
rather they would desire to listen to various world views and ideologies with
regard to what happens
after death. I'm thankful that God has given us the authoritative word
and he has revealed to us in his word what happens after death.
As we look at the account that is given to us of Jacob's death
let me say this tonight not everyone is going to experience the same kind of
death.
What do I mean by that? Well it's not always possible that you're going to
know that you're going to die and have opportunity to bring your family members
into your presence and to speak to them and to
share with them what's on your heart and then after you're done speaking get in
bed and die.
It'd be pretty nice if it happened that way
wouldn't it? But the reality is it doesn't happen that many for many.
It just doesn't happen that way for many people.
And we do understand that as we look at this passage of scripture I really just
have two thoughts
with regard to points if you will with regard to the message this evening
but then I want to give you a number of practical tips that I hope would be
helpful this evening
as we look at a passage of scripture like this things that are
just practical applicable truths that we can deal with tonight but as we look at
the scripture let me give you one
two thoughts tonight number one the request
given. We read these verses in verse 29 through 33
and we see that Jacob gives a request to his children
the boys are gathered we mentioned already the purpose in the process and
the prophetic view even as Jacob shares things
that stretch all the way from the time of Jacob into the millennial reign of
Christ
those events have not even taken place yet but Jacob
in Genesis chapter 49 with this prophetic view he speaks words that are
yet to be fulfilled
but we have confidence in knowing that they will be fulfilled
our Lord is going to return and after seven years of tribulation on this
earth he is going to establish his millennial kingdom
he is going to rule and reign for a thousand years
amen this is this is true Bible
teaching and we find that Jacob's
message really covers a large span
of human history all the way into the millennial reign of Christ but after
this
process is completed and after each of the the boys stand before dad and
and after he gives them the the blessing it says
and he charged them you notice that in verse number 29
and I believe that as he begins to to give this charge it's the request that's
given it's Jacob's
final request and as he would have his sons gathered together
and he gives them this request he says that he charged them
and notice specifically what Jacob makes request of
he tells them I'm gonna die how's he worded he says well I am to be gathered
unto my people and notice he says bury me
with my fathers in the cave that is in the field of
Ephron the Hittite Jacob at this particular time
is where well he's in Egypt remember
God has moved in such a way that he allowed Joseph
to go through some circumstances that were less than desirable
and after going through all of those circumstances and sold into slavery and
all that takes place
we find that Jacob eventually receives word that Joseph is alive
and he calls for his father and his brethren his family
to come to Egypt and it was there in Egypt that
that God would use Joseph to sustain his children his people
we find that it was there that God would give them a possession
and he would give them the the the provision that they would need and we
find
that before they went on their journey
that God in Genesis chapter 46 spoke
to Jacob and he tells Jacob fear not to go down
there why to go down into Egypt for I will there make of thee a great nation
he says in verse number four I will go down with thee into Egypt
notice and I will also surely bring thee
up again and Joseph shall put his hand
upon thine eyes
and we find that Jacob received that promise he's been there now
as we study the scripture we put the timeline together he's been there for
seventeen years
and after seventeen years of being in Egypt his
death is now at hand the time of his departure
as Paul would say in 2nd Timothy chapter 4 is
at hand and he makes this single request
don't bury me in Egypt don't bury me in Egypt
he says bury me with my father's in the cave that is the field of
Ephron the Hittite I won't read all the verses again because
I've already read them for sake of time but I want you to notice
that in this request that Jacob is very specific
he makes sure that he specifically indicates
the particular place where he is to be buried he doesn't just say don't bury me
here he says bury me in this place
he then goes through the events that led to this particular cave
being purchased in this land being purchased
and the right of ownership that's where I want to be buried
he says that there are others that are buried there if you look in verse 31
he mentions Abraham and Sarah he mentions Isaac and Rebekah
and he mentions Leah and he makes it extremely clear and
extremely specific with regard to the request
by the way we could make various application with regard to that
and we'll make some at the end of the message but I want you to understand
that Jacob in making this request he's being very clear
he's making it known this is my desire
this is my request I do not think that the boys after verse number 33
when Jacob puts his feet back up into the bed and yields up the ghost in
other words he died he was gathered into his people I do not think that at
that moment
that the boys stand around and say well what should we do no it was very clear
what had been communicated
the request of Jacob his final request
was given as we enter into chapter 50
I want you to notice number two with me the request is granted
I want you to notice that the Bible tells us in verse number 50
and excuse me in verse number one of chapter number 50 and Joseph
fell upon his father's face and wept upon him and kissed him
I want you to notice from verse number one as we look at this verse of
scripture
that the Bible regularly I dealt with this
probably at this point a year and a half ago when Sarah died and we read of
Abraham and his mourning for the death of his wife Sarah
and we see in verse number one of chapter 50 we understand that we are
emotional people
God has made us that way and we understand
that at times of loss like as we look at here
and we talk about physical death and we're associated we understand
what it is to have a loved one pass on into eternity
the reality is that we do have emotions
we do mourn we do have
sorrow, but I'm thankful for the truth of 1 Thessalonians chapter number 4 that tells
us if we have loved ones that are saved, that are heaven-bound, that if they die, that we
sorrow not as others which have no hope.
Aren't you thankful that we have a whole Bible?
Aren't you thankful this evening that God gives us the truth with regard to eternity,
with regard to not only how to live this life, but what happens thereafter?
So thankful this evening to have the authority of God's Word, and listen, I understand this
evening that when you have a loved one that enters into eternity, that there's an emotional
aspect of that.
But oh, how we can hold and cling to the promises of God.
So often we use the terminology, I think actually I just used it a moment ago, that you lose
a loved one.
Listen, if your loved one is saved by the grace of God, they're not lost, they're in
heaven.
We know exactly where they are.
Amen.
They're with our Savior, hallelujah.
To be absent from the body is to be present with the Lord.
Isn't that a wonderful promise of God's Word?
And we find this evening that we sorrow not as others which have no hope.
At the end of that passage in 1 Thessalonians chapter number 4, the Bible says, wherefore
comfort one another with these words.
These words are comforting words.
These words are words that in our time, in our moment of sorrow and grief, that we can
have the comfort of God's Word and the comfort of the Holy Spirit.
We find that Joseph is weeping.
Again, an emotional individual, an emotional being in dealing with the departure of his
father.
Again, we have the whole of Scripture and we can rejoice and understand that one day
by the grace of God we'll be reunited.
What a wonderful truth that is.
I remember reading of D.L. Moody and it says that D.L. Moody gave this testimony that one
day you're going to read that D.L. Moody has died.
Now some preachers, I've heard some preachers say, I check the obituaries every day to find
out if I'm in there.
I don't understand that.
But the reality is that he said, you're going to read one day that D.L. Moody is dead.
He said, don't believe it.
Don't believe it for one second.
He said, because at that moment I'm going to be more alive than I've ever been.
And then you're going to go into this testimony of sharing the truth of knowing that to be
absent from this body is to be present with the Lord, that this mortal shall put on immortality,
that this corruption shall put on incorruption.
And what a joy and what a blessing.
We'll be more alive then than we've ever been.
Verse two says, and Joseph commanded his servants, the physicians, to embalm his father and the
physicians embalmed Israel.
That's Jacob.
Of course, his name had been changed to Israel.
Notice in verse number three, and 40 days were fulfilled for him.
For so are fulfilled the days of those which are embalmed and the Egyptians mourned for
him three score and 10 days.
When the days of his mourning were passed, Joseph spake in the house of Pharaoh saying,
if now I have found grace in your eyes, speak, I pray you in the ears of Pharaoh saying,
my father made me swear, saying, lo, I die in my grave, which I have digged for me in
the land of Canaan, there shalt thou bury me.
That's what he understood his father.
That's the summary statement of what he understood that final request to be.
And it says now, therefore, verse number five, let me go up, I pray thee, and bury my father
and I will come again.
Notice Joseph understood exactly what the request was.
And Joseph gives his petition before Pharaoh, and we find that Pharaoh responds and says
in verse six, go up and bury thy father according as he made thee swear.
And Joseph went up to bury his father, and with him went up all the servants of Pharaoh,
the elders of his house, and all the elders of the land of Egypt, and all the house of
Joseph and his brethren in his father's house, only their little ones and their flocks and
their herds they left in the land of Goshen.
There went up with him both chariots and horsemen, and it was a very great company.
They came to the threshing floor of Atad, which is beyond Jordan, and there they mourned,
notice with a great and very sore lamentation, and he made a mourning for his father seven
days.
And when the inhabitants of the land, the Canaanites, saw the mourning in the floor
of Atad, they said, this is a grievous mourning to the Egyptians, wherefore the name of it
is called Abel Mizraim, which is beyond Jordan.
And his sons, notice verse number 12, did unto him according as he commanded them.
The request was granted, we read where they travel, they make the journey.
God details for us those that went and the great group of people that went to go for
this funeral procession, if you will, this burying of Jacob, and we find that even the
inhabitants of the land, they saw the great host of company, they made their assumptions
based on what they observed, and we find that the Bible tells us in verse 13, for his sons
carried him into the land of Canaan and buried him in the cave of the field of Machpelah,
which Abraham bought with the field for a possession of a burying place of Ephraim the
Hittite before Mamre.
Is that not the exact place that had been given at the end of chapter 49 by Jacob in
his request with regard to where he would be buried?
We find that the request is granted and Jacob is buried in this cave, in this burying place
that is mentioned in chapter 49 and again in chapter number 50, and I want you to notice
in verse number 14, the Bible says, and Joseph returned into Egypt.
Remember he told Pharaoh that I will, I pray thee to let me go up, I pray thee and bury
my father and I will come again in verse number 5, and the Bible says that Joseph returned
into Egypt, he and his brethren and all that went up with him to bury his father after
he had buried his father.
As we look at this passage of Scripture this evening and we understand the request that
was given, we understand the request was granted, and we understand those things that are captured
here with regard to mourning and weeping, and we understand that we sorrow not as others
which have no hope, and we can make those applications, I think it's important to understand
in verse 14 that the Bible says that Joseph, not only Joseph, but all of his brethren,
they returned back to Egypt.
Listen, I've heard people make the statement when they're at a funeral, I just can't go
on.
No, no, you have to continue going on, amen?
There's some people that think life's not worth living, I'm just, no, no, no, God still
has a purpose for you, God still has a plan for you, and we understand that life, there's
a time to be born, there's a time to die, and I know that there are times in which families
will have discussions and maybe some would think it's a dark conversation, one that they
don't want to have, but they'll make comments with regard to if I die first or if you die
first and that sort of thing, but the reality is that we don't always have what we would
wish with regard to our departure from this life.
I've already made that known in Genesis 49.
Not all of us are going to have the opportunity to bring our family into our presence and
then put our feet up into bed and then die.
So as we look at this passage of Scripture and we understand that God has recorded for
us this request and this desire of Jacob and we see it fulfilled, I find this evening as
I consider this passage of Scripture that God has revealed to us in His Word that we're
all going to face death.
We find that Hezekiah is told that he's going to die, set thy house in order, wow.
You know, not everyone has that opportunity either to be told you're going to die, set
your house in order.
Sometimes death is, I mean, it's just a quote-unquote unexpected from human perspective, right?
So unless the rapture occurs, and I don't say unless the rapture occurs as if I don't
think it's going to occur, I know that the rapture is going to take place, but unless
in our lifetime it doesn't take place, then we're going to die.
I like what Brother Mershawn says, I'm looking for the upper taker and not the undertaker,
and certainly that is true.
I'm listening for the trumpet.
You see the things that are happening in our world today, man, it's getting close.
It's getting close, amen?
You look at world events, listen, unless you have your head in the sand, you have to acknowledge
we're getting close.
I got those alerts on my phone last night, just like you probably did, with regard to
all that was taking place internationally, listen, that's a big deal.
That's a really significant situation.
I've mentioned from this pulpit before, listen, before there can be a peace treaty, there's
got to be much turmoil.
And the anti-Christ is going to begin with a peace treaty.
We read that.
We understand that.
I don't know how much turmoil will take place before the rapture, before we hear the trumpet
of the Lord, but I believe we're getting close.
We ought to be ready.
I said to someone just recently, not only the…
return of Christ is imminent, but the reality is that there's just really a step between
me and death.
I shared actually the last two Saturdays that I've had the opportunity to go out on visitation,
I've shared with people about that bridge collapse.
You read about it.
You saw it.
Can you imagine?
There's no expectation of those folks driving over that bridge and thinking that, no, but
death, it can just happen.
And so for each one of us, unless we're raptured out of here, we're going to face death.
Each one of us, unless we're raptured out of here, we're going to deal with a loved
one dying.
Amen?
We're going to deal with it.
You say, I don't want to think about that.
It's life.
It's just the reality.
Amen?
I don't seem, I don't want to be unkind or cold about it, but the reality is that it's
something that we must acknowledge, we must consider.
The Bible says, as I quoted just a moment ago in Hebrews 9 and verse number 27, as it
is appointed unto man once to die, after this the judgment.
I don't know when I'm going to die, and you don't know when you're going to die either.
We just don't know.
But can I tell you this evening, when we understand a passage of Scripture like this, when we
take into consideration what God tells us in His Word and other portions of Scripture
with regard to death, let me say a couple of things.
Number one, you better be ready.
Be ready.
What does that entail?
What does it mean when I say be ready for death?
Well, number one, I would say this, you better be sure that you're saved.
Listen, we could take a trip this evening to any number of grave sites in our region,
and you could go to any number of tombstone and those grave markers, and you could look
at those, and you could take a journey, and you could find this evening that there are
people that are younger than you, and there are people that are older than you that are
buried in those places.
See, death has no determination of your age.
In fact, the reality is that there could be some very sick people that will live longer
than those of us that think we're relatively healthy.
I remember sitting with Mary Fenley's granddaughter before she died, and I remember sitting there,
and I don't believe her husband was saved.
The doctor had just given her a few days to live.
She had cancer and had been going for a while, and I looked at that man, and the reality
is there was only so much you could still say to the granddaughter that was nearing
death.
Her cognitive abilities were just deteriorating significantly, her ability to communicate,
so on and so forth.
And I looked at that man, and I said to him, he had the same name as I, and I said, Chris,
listen, I understand that it seems as if your wife is going to die at any moment.
And it was reality.
It was a certain situation.
And I said, let me ask you, Chris.
And I said, because the reality is that either one of us could die before her.
No medical doctor has diagnosed me with any terminal illness.
No one's given me a time, but I could leave your house this afternoon, and on my way back
to the church, I could get in a car accident and enter into heaven, enter into eternity.
We don't know, and so we better make sure that we're saved.
Every young person, every old person, everyone in between, you say, am I young or old?
You figure that out, amen?
But every single person that's understanding the truth of the gospel needs to make sure
that heaven is their home.
Can I say this when I say be ready?
Not only that you know that you're saved, I mean, I hope that you know that you know
that you know that you know that heaven is your home.
I mean, no doubts, no concerns.
I mean, no one can talk you out of it, amen?
You know that you're saved by the grace of God.
But let me say this, you've got to be ready, but I would say that you have no regrets.
What I mean by having no regrets is, hey, pastor, how could I ever have no regrets?
There's so many things in my life, and so on and so forth.
Listen, I've heard people say this, and this is where I'm trying to be very practical this
evening.
I've heard people say, I wish I would have.
Just do it.
I wish I would have told them, pick up the phone and call them.
Why?
Because you don't want to stand at some funeral service and regret not telling them whatever's
on your heart.
I'm just being transparent this evening.
Have no regrets.
Because you don't know when that loved one is going to die, and you don't know when you're
going to die.
You have a loved one that you're praying for.
I have loved ones that I have prayed for, for salvation for years, that I've tried to
talk to them and they just no longer want to listen to me.
And a number of years ago now, I sat down and I wrote handwritten letters.
I know that's old school, but I wanted them to know that it was from the heart.
I didn't just send a text or an email.
I sat down and I wrote handwritten letters expressing to my relatives my desire for them
to be saved, and sharing the gospel in written form.
Why?
Because they stopped listening to me.
And I want them to know that I love them, but more than me loving them, God loves them.
And God wants them to be saved.
Amen?
1 Timothy chapter 2, that God's will that all men would be saved, and coming to the
knowledge of the Lord Jesus Christ, the Lord is not slack concerning His promises.
Some men count slackness, but His longsuffering to us, we're not willing that any should
perish, but that all should come to repentance.
I don't want to be in a situation where I find out that a loved one passed on into eternity,
and I said, man, I wish I would have told them about Jesus.
We hear that there are many that have other regrets with regard to, I never told them
X, Y, or Z, whatever it might be.
Listen, you know how you have no regrets?
You just deal with it now.
You say, but it's a hard conversation.
It'll be better to have a hard conversation than have no conversation.
Amen?
You say, pastor, I don't like that.
I'm just being honest with you tonight.
You don't know how many times I've had the, I'll call it an unfortunate privilege to sit
with people that are mourning, and they're beating themselves up over what they wish
they had done, and now it's too late.
What do you say to someone?
The only thing you can say to someone is on this side of eternity.
Amen?
And so this evening, I would say be ready.
Make sure of your salvation.
I would say have no regrets.
Let me say this, very practical this evening, really probably my most practical thought
from this passage of Scripture.
Make your desires known.
What do I mean by that?
Jacob sat down with his boys.
He called them in knowing that he would soon die.
He not only shared with them and gave them the blessings, and we read all of that, that
we've dealt with over the last three weeks, but at the end of that conversation, he makes
his requests known.
He makes his desire known.
He makes it abundantly clear.
And so why do I say that this evening to make your desires known?
Well, what do you, let me just be very practical this evening.
As a pastor, I have the responsibility, I'm going to come down here, I have the responsibility,
the privilege, and the honor of marrying people.
It's a blessed time.
I have the opportunity, the privilege, the responsibility of having baby dedications.
The privilege, responsibility, opportunity of seeing people saved and baptized and doing
the baptism.
And man, what a joy that is.
But I also have the privilege, the responsibility, and opportunity to conduct funerals.
Do you know how hard it is for a pastor to do a funeral when the deceased has not made
their desires known to their family?
What do I mean by that?
Well, not all of your family is saved.
I'm being very practical this evening.
I'm trying to help all of us, okay?
Not all of your family is saved.
And you know who has the most say in your funeral?
Your family, not your pastor.
So if you're saved by the grace of God and you know that you're heaven-bound and you
have family that's not, it'd be a good idea to let your family know what you desire for
your funeral service, your home-going service.
Why?
So that when your pastor wants to have that home-going service and that celebration of
life, and that family comes in and they say, here's what we want, and we want this, and
we want this, and we want this, and then it's all kinds of chaos.
It's the way it happens.
See, at my homegoing service, I want the gospel preached.
I want there to be some songs of rejoicing.
One of the best funeral services we've ever had is when Joe Harrow went home to be with
the Lord.
Man, it was just a celebration.
He was in heaven.
We were rejoicing.
There was no real conflict with the family with regard to what they wanted.
They knew.
I don't know that he sat down and specifically told them, here are the songs, but see, here's
what happens sometimes is somebody will come to me as the pastor and say, hey, at my funeral
I want these songs and I want this and that and so on and so forth, but they never let
their family know.
And then it gives me a difficulty because not all of your family is saved.
David makes his requests known, very direct and very specific.
You have loved ones that most likely, friends, loved ones are going to come to your funeral
service.
You want them to hear the truth.
You know what's a sad thing?
I have been to funeral services and I'm sure you have as well where the gospel is not preached.
What an opportunity.
In fact, we find in the Bible that the Bible tells us that it's better to go to the house
of mourning than to the house of feasting for this is the end of all men.
I understand tonight that it's not the most popular subject to deal with, but what a tragic
situation when a loved one enters into glory, into heaven, and the gospel is not even preached.
Sometimes as the pastor I'm extremely limited on what I can say and do.
There's a family pressure, I'm being very transparent with you this evening, that can
become very difficult to deal with.
I won't mention the names, but we've had funerals here, that I've had funerals at other
places that I've gone and done funerals that are very difficult.
I had a pastor friend that was going to be having to travel to preach the funeral for
his brother, and he was already on the schedule to preach a funeral for an individual, and
so he contacted me and said, hey, can you help me out and can you preach this funeral?
I don't know the people, I don't know anything about them, talk about a difficult situation.
And then I get the email with all the information, and they're, I don't say this in a negative
way, but they're Polish, and all of these names I couldn't even begin to pronounce,
and I'm like, this is such a mess, I'm going to be in so much trouble.
And I had some conversation with the funeral home director, and they were giving me some
information.
So it's really best that I connect with the wife of the deceased so that we can figure
out some things.
She communicated to me through the funeral director, not to me personally, but she communicated
that we're not really religious people, and we're not really interested in the Bible,
and we really don't want any reference to heaven.
What am I supposed to do with that?
That's a tough situation.
And I wrote back, and I said, listen, it was through email, and I said, I'm a Baptist preacher.
I'm not trying to convert anyone to become a Baptist, but if I'm going to conduct a funeral
service, I am going to say something about Jesus, and I am going to say something about
heaven, and I am going to use the Bible.
If you don't want that, I suggest that you find someone else.
I'm not trying to be unkind.
I'm accountable to God.
Amen?
And how can I stand at a funeral service with a bunch of lost people, and tell them, your
loved one is doing just fine, and everyone's going to be okay, and no.
The Bible doesn't teach us that.
Do you read that in your Bible?
No.
When we die, there's either heaven or the lake of fire.
There's no in between.
There's no changing from one to the other.
Amen?
That individual wasn't a member of our church, but what I submit to you this evening, it
wasn't a member of that pastor's church either, just to be clear.
If you let your requests known to your loved ones, it goes a long way to having the kind
of funeral service that you'd like to have.
Because just letting your pastor know isn't enough.
Because your family is going to have more say in your funeral than your pastor is.
I've done it so many times.
I'm just being honest with you.
And so how can we be practical when we look at a passage of Scripture like this?
Number one, you better be ready for your departure.
Not all of us are going to have the blessing and the benefit that Jacob did of knowing
and being able to speak to and then putting his feet back up in the bed and dying.
So you better be sure of your salvation.
If there's any doubt whatsoever, get it settled.
Paul says to the believers in Corinth, he says, today is the day of salvation.
Proverbs tells us, boast not thyself of tomorrow.
Why?
No man knoweth what a day may bring forth.
James says, what is your life?
It's but a vapor that appeareth for a little time and then vanisheth away.
Don't delay.
Don't live in this state of doubt and I'm not really sure.
No, get it settled.
Have no regrets with your family, your loved ones.
Communicate to them what's on your heart.
Share the gospel with them.
If it has to be through letter form because they won't listen to you again, at least you
can rest assured that you shared with them the truth and you don't have to regret saying,
I wish I would have told them.
Because standing at a funeral, trying to console an individual that is beating themselves up
because I never told them is a difficult situation.
So have no regrets.
But then let your desires be known.
Communicate.
Here's what I want.
You want a certain song?
Man, have a certain song.
You want a certain verse?
Have a certain verse.
I ask people, I just, the most recent funeral I did was for my great aunt.
I didn't even have any idea that she wanted me to preach her funeral.
But she let her daughter know that when I die, I want, they call me Christopher because
my dad's Chris.
I want Christopher to do my funeral.
And when I got the phone call, I said, she wants me to do the funeral?
I mean, I'll do the funeral, that's great.
I began to ask questions.
There's really little information.
So I was able to just do whatever I wanted to do.
They didn't give any pushback.
So that was really nice.
But listen, if you have a life verse, if you have a certain song, if you want the gospel
preached, if you want your pastor to do the service, Mary Fenley died, she'd always made
it known that she wanted Brother Abbott to have part of her funeral service.
She thought she was going to die way before she did.
She didn't think I'd be her pastor very long.
She didn't know I'd be her pastor for almost nine years.
She thought she'd die well before then.
But I was their pastor for almost nine years.
But I knew she had made it known to me and to her family that she wanted her other pastor,
Pastor Abbott, to have part of that service.
That was a sweet service.
Brother Abbott took part of it.
I took part of it.
It was a blessing.
Some of you were here.
Let it be known because your family is going to have more say about your funeral than your
pastor will.
And if you want the gospel preached, even if they don't accept it, let it be known.
I want the gospel preached at my service, at my home going.
Amen?
Because I think each of us here this evening, if you're saved by the grace of God, you would
say tonight, when my time of departure comes, I want to have a home going service, a celebration
of life.
The fact that I'm in heaven with my Savior, I want the gospel preached, I want songs of
rejoicing.
Listen, I don't want it to be a sad time.
It's a time of rejoicing.
I understand that there's the sorrow part of it.
But the reality is that our loved one's not lost with our Savior if they're saved by the
grace of God.
Jacob, he gathers his sons together.
He blesses them.
He has time with them.
But then he specifically tells them what he desires.
And then they fulfill specifically.
me, the request that was given. They bury him in the place where he desired to be buried.
What a joy and what a blessing. One day, I don't know the day, I don't want to be dark
this evening. The reality is that death is just a doorway for the child of God. Death
is not something that we have to fear. I might not be excited about the process, amen? But
I'm going to be with Jesus for all of eternity. We'll see him and we'll worship him. We'll
praise his wonderful name this evening. I hope you're ready. I hope that you know for
sure that heaven is your home. If you have any doubt whatsoever, let us take a Bible
and show you how you can know for sure. Don't leave here tonight without knowing with 100%
confidence that heaven is your home. Let's pray together. Father, we love you. We thank
you so much for loving us. We thank you for the text of Scripture that records for us
the death and burial of Jacob. I thank you for the practical lessons that we can learn.
Lord, as I've tried tonight to be very practical and applicable, I pray that we'd take heed.
That we'd each be ready for our time of departure, though we may not know when that will be.
Lord, help us to be ready. Lord, help us to have no regrets. God, maybe you've laid
upon someone's heart this evening something they need to deal with, a loved one they need
to contact, someone they need to speak with. God, I pray that you'd help us to not soon
forget that. Lord, help us to, with your help, have what might be a hard conversation so
that we do not regret having no conversation. God, I pray for each of us that know you as
Lord and Savior. Unless we are raptured out of here, that when our home-going service
takes place, that it'd be a time of great rejoicing and celebration. That perhaps even
in those services that loved ones would gather together, they'd hear the gospel and they'd
be saved by the grace of God. What a joy and blessing that would be. I pray that in these
moments of invitation that you'd have your will in weighing. We'll thank you for it.
In Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me?