He is Lord, He is God.
Ephesians chapter number 2, Ephesians chapter number 2 this morning,
and thankful for God's word, thankful for the instruction that He gives us.
I'm thankful that He reveals to us His greatness,
and we've been on the theme all year long, great is the Lord,
and greatly to be praised, and we continue to look at what it is that we would,
or why it is that we would say that God is great.
I believe this morning that all of us probably would agree,
and we would say yes, God is great, but why is God great?
We've looked at a number of things this year as we've studied through His word,
and on a quest, if you will, to discover God's greatness,
and then as we close out this calendar year,
we will transition from discovering God's greatness to declaring God's greatness,
and as we are aware of the very truth that our God is great,
we need to let others know how great our God is.
There are so many people that we come in contact with on a regular basis
that simply do not know how great our God is,
and how are they going to find out if we don't tell them,
and we'll transition to that phase of the series, if you will, near the end of the year,
but this morning as we look at Ephesians chapter number 2,
we'll be reminded that last week we examined God's greatness,
and we said He's great because He has a great plan of redemption.
We talked about that plan of redemption and the reason that it was required,
but then we talked about the fact that God's plan of redemption reaches all people
of all times, and we sang this morning, whosoever will,
and I'm thankful that you can go anywhere around the world and you can preach the gospel
and you can say, based on the authority of God's word,
that Jesus died for them so that they could have eternal life,
and a free gift of salvation, and what a wonderful true blessing that is.
And we find that as we are understanding
of the truth that God has a plan of redemption, we continue
and understand as we look at the text of scripture this morning
that the believers here in Ephesus, they're being reminded of God's grace
and of God's mercy, His great love, as Paul is speaking
to them about the redemption, but then he tells them this in verse number 10
that they and we are His workmanship.
And we find that as we look at this portion of scripture,
and yes, we understand that God is great because He has a great plan of redemption
that reaches all people of all times, but I would say
that God is great this morning because God has a plan
for each individual believer. And you begin to think about
the plan that God has for us as individuals, those who have
responded in faith and trusted the Lord Jesus Christ
as their personal Savior, God has a plan for your life.
And I want to encourage us to understand this morning that
the great God, the God that they just sang about, the God that we
are worshiping today, that we're singing about, seeking to exalt and magnify,
that He's the God of the universe, but He has a plan
for your life, individually. And He has a plan for every
single believer throughout the ages. He has
a plan for their lives. And that is such an encouragement to me.
I believe that it's a fascinating truth of God's Word
that He has a plan for me. And you say, who am I, right?
We're just really a speck of nothing when you think about the
big picture, but God loves us so much that He saved us.
But after He saved us, He says, now I have a plan for your life.
And here's what's amazing about God's plan for our life, is God has an individual
plan for each and every single one of us, and as we fulfill
God's plan for our lives, the ultimate purpose is to bring glory
to Him and to complete His master plan.
Now that's amazing when you think about God and His greatness
that He has a plan that will come to pass
and then He includes us. Sometimes we can be
hard-headed, right? We can not do...
But God says, I have a plan for you, for your life, and I want to use you.
Notice in the text of Scripture, I said that as Paul is
teaching and ministering to these people in Ephesus, He reminds them of their
salvation. He begins in verse number 1, and you hath He quickened who were
dead in trespasses and sins. And I'm thankful to be quickened,
to be made alive, to be saved, to be born again by the blood of Jesus
Christ. It says, wherein in time past ye walked according to the course of this world,
according to the prince of the power of the air, the spirit that now worketh in the children of disobedience,
among whom also, notice it says, we all had our
conversation in times past in the lust of our flesh, fulfilling the desires
of the flesh and of the mind, and were by nature the children of wrath, even as others.
We all were in that same condition, but God, verse number
4, who is rich in mercy, for His great love wherewith He
loved us, even when we were dead in sins, hath quickened
us together with Christ by grace, ye are saved, and hath raised us
up together and made us to sit together in heavenly places in Christ Jesus,
that in the ages to come He might show the exceeding
riches of His grace and His kindness toward us through Christ Jesus,
for by grace are ye saved through faith. And that not of yourselves, it is the
gift of God, not of works, lest any man should boast. And then notice verse number 10,
the subject matter we'll be dealing with this morning, for we. Paul didn't
say for I, he didn't say for you, he said for we. Why?
God has a plan for each of us individually, for we
those that have been born again, those that are saved by the blood of Christ, for we
are His workmanship, created in Christ Jesus
unto good works, which God hath
before ordained that we should walk
in them. Now understand very clearly this morning that though
He speaks about us being His workmanship and He says that we have been
created in Christ Jesus unto
good works, that you understand that though we're to walk in
this newness of life that He speaks of and we're to be involved
in doing these good works, it's not so that we can be saved
nor is it so that we can stay saved. I'm thankful that salvation
is entirely and completely dealt with
by Christ's substitutionary atonement on the cross of Calvary, His
death, burial, and glorious resurrection. It is finished.
But I can't
keep it by my good works either. I am sealed
under the day of redemption according to Ephesians chapter 1. I am kept
by the power of God according to 1 Peter chapter 1. Jesus said in
chapter number 10 that my sheep hear my voice and I know them and I give unto them
eternal life and they shall never perish.
And so I'm thankful this morning that the good works that are spoken of here
they don't save me and they don't keep me saved, but I am
God's workmanship. I am to do a work
for the Lord and as I begin to think about the fact that God
has a plan for me and for you as individuals, I believe
that this truth this morning reveals to us just how
great our God is. Think about it.
I mean there's really not that many people that are gathered here this morning
but there's no way that any one of us could individually
have a plan for each individual and bring it all to pass
and by the way every other believer around the globe.
And not only for this moment in history
but for all of history. It's absolutely amazing
that God would use us and that God has a plan for our lives.
As we begin to think about this truth and the title is from verse number 10, we are
his workmanship. I want you to consider some biblical examples this morning.
We're going to go all the way back to the Old Testament, the book of Exodus and we're going to walk through and look at a few
verses of scripture this morning in order to give some biblical
examples to this truth that God has a plan for us
as individuals. Look at Exodus chapter number 3 if you will.
In this portion of scripture even as I mentioned Exodus 3
many of us will be familiar with the fact that we'll deal with Moses and many of us are
familiar with Moses and his place in God's
work and what God did in and through his life. But I want you to
see in Exodus chapter number 3 and really the first three examples that we're going to look
at here from the book of Exodus is just an amazing truth as you see
them all come together and how God brings to pass
his work through these individuals. In verse number 10 in Exodus
3 the Bible says this, come now therefore and I will send
thee unto Pharaoh that thou mayest bring
forth my people the children of Israel out of Egypt.
Do you see that God is speaking personally, individually to
Moses and he's saying to Moses, Moses I'm going to send
thee to Pharaoh and I'm going to send you to Pharaoh
for a purpose, for a work to bring my people out
of Egypt. Now we know that God's going to work miraculously and God's going to
do the work but God used a man, a man by the name of Moses
so think about Moses and think about the way in which God used him and obviously
Aaron and you can look at the text of scripture and see Aaron being used as well but I want you to
forward if you will to Exodus chapter 28 much after
the Exodus Moses is here receiving instruction with regard
to the tabernacle that was to be constructed and
as you come to this portion of scripture in Exodus chapter 28 and I begin to
this picture in my mind come together to help me
understand how great our God is and how he has a plan
for each of us as individuals.
He used Moses, he called Moses by name.
He's gonna use Moses to lead the children of Israel
out of Egyptian bondage and we know that Moses,
if we could use this term this morning,
would be the human leader for the nation of Israel.
But we know that Moses was not going to do everything.
He couldn't do everything.
But God had a plan for his people.
So what does God do?
Well, God is telling Moses about this tabernacle.
He's giving him all of the instruction
with regard to the tabernacle.
You come to chapter 28 and you notice
that the Bible says this,
and take thou unto thee Aaron thy brother
and his sons with him from among the children of Israel
that he may minister unto me in the priest office,
even Aaron, Nadab, Abihu, Eleazar, Ithamar, Aaron's sons,
and thou shalt make holy garments for Aaron thy brother
for glory and for beauty.
And we see that in these verses of scripture
in Exodus chapter 28, as we could speak of
and reference the Aaronic priesthood
and understand that God is calling Aaron
and he has a plan for Aaron and for his sons.
And we find that this plan for Aaron
is going to differ from the plan that God has for Moses.
God has a plan for Moses.
God has a plan for Aaron.
But then I want you to look at a few more chapters
over in Exodus chapter 35,
because after there's kind of a parenthetical here
between Exodus chapter 28 and Exodus 35
and what happens is while Moses is up there on the mount,
the people of God defile themselves
and Moses comes down and then God reconfirms
some things with Moses and we find there's repentance
and what have you, but you come to Exodus chapter 35
and I'm gonna draw your attention to verse number 30.
We've seen Moses, we've seen Aaron,
but now I want to introduce you to a man
that you're familiar with perhaps for the name of Bezalel.
The Bible says in verse number 30 of Exodus 35,
and Moses said unto the children of Israel,
see, the Lord hath called by name Bezalel,
the son of Uri, the son of Hur of the tribe of Judah.
And he, that's speaking of God, hath filled him
with the spirit of God and wisdom and understanding
and a knowledge and all manner of workmanship
and to devise curious works, to work in gold
and in silver and in brass and in the cutting of stones
to set them and in carving of wood
to make any manner of cunning work.
And it's put in his heart, that's God putting it
in the heart of Bezalel, that he may teach
both he and Aholiab, the son of Ahissamack
of the tribe of Dan.
Then hath he, God, filled with wisdom of heart
to work all manner of work of the engraver
of the cunning workman and of the embroiderer
in blue and in purple and scarlet and in fine linen
and of the weaver, even of them that do any work
and of those that devise cunning work.
As I look at these first three examples
of Moses, Aaron, and Bezalel,
and you can include Aholiab there
in this portion of scripture in Exodus chapter 35,
I find that God has a plan and a purpose
for his people corporately to be able to worship
at a place called the tabernacle.
And God would use Moses as the human leader
for the nation of Israel, but Moses could not do
all of the work by himself, and God has a plan for Moses.
And then God in his infinite wisdom
and his omniscience and his omnipotence
and in his individual plan for his people,
he says I have and I've called by name Aaron
and I have Aaron for this task.
The priest had a very important role
in the process of worship at the tabernacle.
You enter the tabernacle through one way.
You first come to a thing, a piece of furniture
that's called the brazen altar,
and at that brazen altar, the first thing
that has to be done is an offering has to be made.
How do we approach God?
Only through Jesus Christ.
There's only one way.
There's only one entrance into the tabernacle,
and as soon as you enter, there's a sacrifice
that's required, and we know that Jesus is our Passover,
and what a great blessing that is.
But the priests, they ministered and they served
and they were the ones that accepted
and processed the offering and all of those things,
and God had a plan for them.
But then you think about all the furniture
that had to be made, the curtains and the brazen altar
and the laver, and you could go through
all of the pieces of furniture that had to be created,
that had to be assembled, and God says
I've called Bezalel for that task.
I have a plan for Bezalel.
Now understand this morning that God had a plan for Moses
and that plan for Moses was an individual plan
that God had for that individual Moses.
God had a plan for Aaron and God had a plan for Bezalel.
Their plans differ, their roles differ,
but ultimately God would use each of them
to bring to pass what he wanted to accomplish.
That's absolutely amazing to me.
Fascinating that God would use us in that way.
Bezalel says no, I'm not gonna do it.
That'd be disastrous, unfortunate.
God would have to raise up somebody else,
but I want you to see that as they fulfill
their individual roles and as they do
what they're supposed to do, that ultimately
you get to the last chapter of the book of Exodus,
in Exodus chapter number 40, and you read in that chapter
that they did all that they were commanded to do.
They finished the work that God had given them to do.
The Bible tells us in verse number 33
of Exodus chapter number 40, and he reared up the court
around about the tabernacle and the altar
and set up the hangings of the court gate.
So Moses finished the work.
And as you begin to look forward and understand
all that's taking place, yes, at the end of Exodus 40,
the Bible tells us that God's presence,
the glory of the Lord, filled the tabernacle
in verse number 35, and then you begin to think
about the place of the tabernacle in Israel's history
as you go forward from this point forward
and you see it being a place of worship.
God used individuals.
We could speak this morning of Joshua.
You could read in Deuteronomy 31.
We're gonna just reference some things.
I'm not gonna even go to the passages
and read them this morning for sake of time,
but you could go to the book of Deuteronomy
in the 31st chapter in verses seven and eight,
and you can read how that God called Joshua specifically.
Why?
Moses was going to die.
Moses was not permitted to enter into the land of promise,
and God says, I've raised up Joshua,
and Joshua, this is your job.
Joshua, this is my plan for your life.
Now, Joshua would be the human leader
for the children of Israel, and you could look
and you could look at David, a man that was just out
as a young teenager that was just tending to the flock
that when the man of God, Samuel, came to his hometown,
that they didn't even call for David to come.
Samuel was sent to that place in order to anoint
the one that would be the next king of Israel,
and though they stood there and Samuel thought,
for sure, this is the one, God said, no, not him,
and one by one, the sons of Jesse passed by,
and God said, no, and God said, no, and God said, no,
and Samuel says, are there any others?
The youngest, and he comes, and God says, he's the one.
You know how it's referenced this way?
You can read of that in 1 Samuel 16, but in Psalm 78,
I love how the psalmist references this.
In Psalm 78, in verse number 70 through 72,
the last three verses of Psalm 78, the Bible says this,
speaking of God that he chose David, also his servant,
and took him from the sheepfolds,
from following the ewes, great with young,
he brought him to feed Jacob, his people,
and Israel, his inheritance, so he fed them
according to the integrity of his heart,
and guided them by the skillfulness of his hands.
This morning, if you were to speak about David
within a Jewish context, oh, how they would hold David
in such high regard and high esteem,
and we, as we look back to the Old Testament,
we look at the nation of Israel, and we say often
that David is probably the greatest king that Israel had,
and you can look to that, and you can see,
but God had a plan for his life as an individual.
We can speak of Elijah.
We look at Elijah a couple of weeks ago,
and looked at God's comfort and care for Elijah,
but Elijah's ready to give up.
He's ready to, he said, just, I'm ready to die.
Why?
I'm the only one, that was his perspective.
That's not bowed the knee to Baal.
Jezebel said, I'm gonna kill him.
That's what happened.
You know what God does?
God comes to Elijah and says, Elijah, I have a plan for you.
You can read of that in 1 Kings 19, verses 15 through 17.
God says, I have a plan for you, Elijah.
What do you think about Paul?
God had a plan for Paul.
Paul says it this way.
If you look over at 2 Timothy, chapter number one,
and look at the New Testament with regard to this plan
that God had for Paul,
we find that in 2 Timothy, chapter number one,
that Paul is giving as he's writing
to his son of the faith, Timothy.
He's rehearsing this truth that God had a plan for his life.
In 2 Timothy, chapter number one,
beginning in verse number eight,
the Bible says, be not thou therefore ashamed
of the testimony of our Lord, nor of me, his prisoner,
but be thou partaker.
the afflictions of the gospel according to the power of God.
Notice what the Bible says, who have saved us.
Remember we talked about his plan of redemption last week,
but then he says this, and called us with a holy calling.
Not according to our works, but according to,
notice what it says, his own purpose and grace,
which was given us in Christ Jesus before the world began,
but is now made manifest by the appearing of our savior,
Jesus Christ, who hath abolished death,
and hath brought life and immortality to light
through the gospel.
Notice what Paul says, where unto I,
this is God's plan for Paul's life,
where unto I am appointed a preacher,
and an apostle, and a teacher of the Gentiles,
for the which cause I also suffer these things,
nevertheless I am not ashamed,
for I know whom I have believed,
and am persuaded that he is able to keep that
which I have committed unto him against that day.
You know what Paul says as he's writing
to the believers in Philippi,
as he speaks about his call,
and understanding that God has a plan for his life,
he says this, he says that I follow after,
if that I may apprehend that for which also
I am apprehended of Christ Jesus.
God had a plan for Paul.
In the same text of scripture,
God reveals to us that he had a plan for Timothy.
In 2 Timothy 1 and verse number six,
notice what God says as Timothy is being written to him
to the inspirational Holy Spirit of God
as Paul is writing this letter.
It says in verse number six of 2 Timothy 1,
wherefore I put thee in remembrance
that thou stir up the gift of God,
which is in thee by the putting on of my hands.
Now understand that this is not that Paul
somehow supernaturally put this gift on him
through the laying of his hands,
but it was a very common thing you've heard
and you've read about somebody laying hands
on somebody and that recognition of God
calling and equipping an individual.
It's God who does the work,
but Paul says that through this process,
but he says listen, remember that God
has a plan for your life.
Stir up the gift of God which is in thee.
This morning, I believe it's obvious,
and we get the point as we look at all of these examples
this morning that God had a specific plan for their lives.
But here's really the question.
Does God have a plan for my life?
Or is it just that he had a plan for the saints of old?
See, if we're not careful, we can go to God's word
and we can say, well yeah, God used that person.
God had a plan for that person
and God had a plan for that person.
I read about their life and yeah,
we can read about Moses and Aaron and Bezalel
and Joshua and David and so on and so forth
and we could list a whole host of other Bible characters
this morning that God used in a specific way.
But I would submit to you this morning
that God has a plan for you as an individual.
God knows you.
He knows you by name and has a plan for you.
And the plan that God has for you,
let me say it this way, can only be fulfilled by you.
God has a plan for you.
And he desires that you would serve him with your life.
And as you yield to his plan for your life,
he will use you as an individual
to be part of the corporate
to bring to pass his ultimate master plan.
Now that's amazing to me.
That's our great God.
He's got a plan for your life.
Look at what the Bible says again
in Ephesians 2 in verse number 10.
We've read it already.
We're gonna look at another verse of scripture
and then get into a couple of thoughts this morning.
Very lengthy introduction this morning
in order to prove and to understand
that God has a plan for our lives.
Again, as we referenced in Ephesians chapter number two,
Paul is obviously under the inspiration
of the Holy Spirit of God,
writing to those who have been saved.
If you've been saved this morning,
you know the Lord Jesus Christ is your personal savior
and you've accepted that free gift of eternal life.
The Bible says in verse number 10,
for we are his workmanship.
That word we is so important
because it's Paul writing to a group of believers
and he's saying that we are his workmanship
and God had a plan for their lives.
Notice over in the book of Philippians in chapter number one,
Philippians chapter number one in verse number six,
Paul is writing to a different church here,
the church at Philippi.
And as he's writing to this church at Philippi,
he's rejoicing at the introduction of the letter
and understanding that this church is an established church
but he's saying I thank my God upon every remembrance of you
and he's letting them know how he's praying for them
and all of these things.
But I want you to notice what Paul says in verse number six.
He says being confident of this very thing
that he, God, which hath begun a good work in you
will perform it, that good work,
until the day of Jesus Christ.
Paul was confident that these believers in Philippi,
that just as God had a plan for his life individually,
just as God had a plan for the believers in Ephesus,
that Paul was confident that God had a plan
for the people at Philippi,
for those believers that had placed their faith and trust
in the Lord Jesus Christ.
He says I'm confident that God is going to,
he started that work but he's gonna bring that work
to completion.
What a blessing to consider this morning
that God has a plan for us as individuals.
See, so many people today go through life
and they ask this question, why am I here?
What's my purpose?
What's my point?
God has a plan for us.
His plan for all mankind is that they'd be saved.
After salvation, his plan for all of his children
is that they would grow in Christ.
We're talking about the plan that God has for us
in a certain sense, there are many aspects of that plan
that are consistent for each of us.
He wants each of us to grow in grace
and knowledge of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ.
But we find that he has an individual plan for our lives
and as we understand that truth this morning,
simply two thoughts.
Number one, if you're taking notes,
finding God's plan for your life.
This is a question that so many people struggle with.
How do I find God's plan or God's will for my life?
Again, there are many things that are known
that are consistent for all of God's children.
You'll read throughout the scriptures
where the Bible will say, this is the will of God, right?
We're to give thanks in everything, right?
We're to certain things that we understand.
I've mentioned this, I said it last week
in our Family Sunday School class last week.
I said this, listen, there's some things
that we just simply don't need to pray about.
What do you mean by that?
Well, when God says to do something,
we don't have to pray about whether we're gonna do it
or not, we just need to obey.
It's not a matter of say, well, I'm gonna pray about that.
No, you don't pray about obedience,
you just do what God said to do.
We speak this morning about this individual plan
that God has for our lives and we say, yes,
there's some revealed will of God for all of his people,
but what does God want for my life?
What is God's plan for my life?
If I'm trying to find God's plan for my life,
very simply this morning, I would say this.
Number one, we need to ask him, ask him.
Why ask him?
Because it's his plan for your life.
You know how many people go through life saying,
this is my plan for my life?
You talk to people, hey, what are you going to do
with your life?
I was asked that question so many times
when I was entering into those years of high school,
getting close to graduation.
What are you going to do?
What is your plan?
And then I got saved as a senior in high school
and all of a sudden, my whole thought process changed
through the preaching of God's word
and through a man of God who'll be here
for our revival meeting, Palmer Sean,
who instructed me and helped me to get a perspective
that it's not about my plan for my life,
but it's about what God's plan is for my life.
And it doesn't matter what I want to do,
it matters what God wants to do in and through my life.
And here's the thing, if I delight myself in the Lord,
man, all of a sudden, what his plan is for me
is what I want to do.
It's what I most desire to do.
And so when I say, and it seems very obvious
and almost elementary to say,
I'm going to find God's plan for my life
and it starts by asking him,
but look over in Acts chapter nine.
We talked already about the fact
and we referenced in 2 Timothy chapter number one
that Paul is referencing that God had a plan for him
individually and he's sharing that testimony.
But here in Acts chapter number nine
is where we meet the, or read the text of scripture
where Saul trusts Christ as his savior,
where Saul is born again.
We obviously refer to him often as Paul.
And, but we find here in this text
that this is the conversion of Paul
and his name is referenced here as being Saul.
But I want to draw your attention in verse number four,
the Bible says that he fell to the earth after what?
After this, the suddenly in verse number three,
there shined round about him a light from heaven.
So, so Saul falls to the earth.
He heard a voice saying, Saul, Saul,
why persecutest thou me?
And he, Saul said, who art thou Lord?
And the Lord said, I am Jesus whom thou persecutest, it is hard for thee to kick against the pricks.
And I want you to notice that it was in that moment that Saul trusted Christ as his Savior.
And look at the question that he asks immediately.
He trembling and astonished said, Lord, what wilt thou have me to do?
It's a very simple question, but how important it is.
The Bible tells us that we have not because we ask not.
I understand that it continues that we have not because we ask amiss, there's two aspects
of that.
But you know, so many people today struggle with this idea of trying to find God's plan
for their lives.
But the reality is that they need to start by simply asking Him, God, what's your plan
for my life?
God, what do you want me to do?
How can I serve you, Lord?
Because God has a plan for you.
And in order for us to understand the significance of this truth this morning of how great our
God is and that He has a plan for each individual, that we simply ask Him as Paul did, Lord,
what would thou have me to do?
What would thou have me to do?
It's interesting as you look through this chapter that in verse number 15, the Bible
says, but the Lord said unto him, go thy way.
He's speaking to Ananias here and it says, for he is a chosen vessel unto me to bear
my name before the Gentiles and kings and the children of Israel, for I will show him
how great things he must suffer for my name's sake.
You know, when you read that verse in verse 15 that it says that he shall bear my name
before the Gentiles and kings and the children of Israel, that was God's plan for Paul and
God did that through Paul.
Why?
Because Paul said for me to live as Christ.
He asked and then he submitted to.
It's important that when we ask God what His plan is for our life, that we're not asking
God so that we can determine if that's something I want to sign up for.
You understand what I'm saying?
No, no.
We're asking God with a heart of obedience and submission that as God reveals to us and
answers to us what His plan is for our life, that we say, yes sir.
Why callest thou me Lord, Lord, and do not the things that I say?
And we find this morning that as we are seeking to find God's plan for our life, we look and
we've given example after example this morning to prove without any shadow of a doubt that
God has a plan for individuals and as God has that plan for individuals and they vary
from person to person but ultimately they're bringing to fulfillment His perfect will and
His master plan, that we simply ask God, what is it that you want me to do?
And as we wait on the Lord and we listen for His direction in our lives, that we have that
heart attitude of submission to His plan.
Let me say this this morning, that God's plan for your life is better than your plan for
your life.
God's plan for your life is far better than your plan for your life.
You say, well you haven't heard my plan.
God's plan for your life is better than your plan for your life.
Guaranteed.
Why?
Because God knows everything.
God has this master plan, He's going to bring all these things to pass and God says I have
a plan for your life.
Notice that as we find God's plan for our life that we recognize this morning that it
is God who has called us as we read there in 2 Timothy chapter 1 but it's also God who
equips us.
It's an amazing truth that God calls us, He has this plan for our lives, He calls us,
He will reveal it to us as we ask Him, as we seek His face.
God, what is it that you want me to do?
What wilt thou have me to do that God reveals it to us but then God equips us to do what
He's called us to do.
I remember when I first realized that God was calling me to preach, I can't.
Honestly that was my first answer, I can't.
Absolutely terrified of the idea of public speaking.
You sit here and say yeah right, I promise you.
Absolutely terrified to stand in front of people and talk.
Felt like Moses, God are you sure?
God equips you.
I'm not saying I'm a great preacher or any of that sort of thing but I'm saying God equips
you as you submit and you let God work, God equips you.
We look at the truth in God's Word, look at Romans chapter 12.
In Romans chapter 12 the Bible gives us here in these verses of Scripture this truth about
how God equips us and I'm so thankful for God's equipping.
In Romans chapter 12 beginning in verse number 3, the Bible says, for I say through the grace
given unto me to every man that is among you, not to think of himself more highly than he
ought to think, but to think soberly according as God hath dealt to every man the measure
of faith.
Notice in verse number 4, for as we have many members in one body and all members have not
the same office.
God's individual plan for each of us.
Notice in verse number 5, so we being many are one body in Christ and every one members
one of another, having then gifts differing according to the grace.
Notice these words, that is given to us, whether prophecy, let us prophesy, whether
according to the proportion of faith, or ministry, let us wait on our ministering, or he that
teacheth on teaching, or he that exhorteth on exhortation, he that giveth, let him do
it with simplicity, he that ruleth with diligence, he that showeth mercy with cheerfulness.
The Bible tells us in the book of 1 Corinthians that God, the Holy Spirit, that he gives the
gift to every man as he will.
It's God's plan for our lives individually, yes a corporate, the body of Christ.
We can think about a local church, we can think about the universal church and understand
that God's plan for the ages and God's plan globally, but he says that we have, yes every
one of us, we have this gift and it differs one from another.
Some people have multiple gifts that God has given them.
They're responsible for those gifts that God has given them and as we discover, we're finding
what God's plan is for our life, we're understanding that he's called us, but he's also equipped
us and he's given us the ability, notice in 1 Peter chapter number 4, the Bible speaks
about this truth of ministering and having received this gift and it's so precious as
we look at this truth this morning that no child of God, anyone that's been born again
that's been saved by the blood of Christ, no one can sit back on the sidelines and say
nope, God didn't give me a gift, he has no plan for my life.
You know why I can say that?
Biblically, God says that he's given every man, every child of God, a gift.
Every single person.
The Bible says that's trust in Christ.
Notice in verse number 10 of 1 Peter 4, as every man hath received the gift, even so
minister the same one to another.
Notice I mentioned this in Sunday school this morning, this verse of scripture, as good
stewards of the manifold grace of God.
If any men speak, let them speak as the oracles of God.
Notice the difference.
If any men minister, so we have differing gifts, but every man has one, every child
of God has one.
He says if any men minister, let them do it as of the ability of which God giveth.
Notice this, and I say this by way of introduction this morning, that God in all things may be
glorified through Jesus Christ to whom be praise and dominion forever and ever, amen.
As every person does what they're supposed to do, as Moses did what he was supposed to
do, and as Aaron was doing what he's supposed to do, and as Bezalel and Aholiab did what
they were supposed to do, there's a tabernacle that's able to be reared up where sacrifices
can be brought, where God's glory can be known, where worship takes place.
This morning, as we each understand that God has a plan for our lives individually and
it reminds us, it helps us to understand how great our God is, that he'd use each and every
one of us, but ultimately it's so that he would be glorified and so that his plan would
come to pass.
It's not so that any one of us individually could receive some level of recognition, look
at that person, look at this person, look at what the, no, no, it's the grace of God.
It's God who has equipped us and he's equipped us so that we could do his work for his glory.
Do we find God's plan for our life?
Ask him, ask him.
God is such a gracious God.
He's wonderful.
He says, he uses the comparison in Matthew 6 and 7.
when he talks about various things there,
with regard to us and how we, as evil people,
that we know how to give good gifts.
Let us see this in verse number seven of Matthew seven.
I wasn't gonna go here,
but I think it's appropriate for us to do it.
Look at Matthew seven in verse number seven.
Because it begins with asking.
Ask, and it shall be given unto you.
Seek, and ye shall find.
Knock, and it shall be opened unto you.
For everyone that asketh receiveth,
and he that seeketh findeth,
and to him that knocketh it shall be opened.
Or what man is there of you whom, if his son ask bread,
will he give him a stone?
If he ask a fish, will he give him a serpent?
If ye then, being evil,
know how to give good gifts unto your children,
how much more shall your Father, which is in heaven,
give good things to them that ask him?
Listen, if God has a plan for your life,
and I believe this morning, biblically, he does,
and you ask him, he's gonna reveal it to you.
You come to him with that submissive, obedient heart.
God, I just wanna know what you want me to do with my life.
Because my life, Lord, as the songwriter said,
is yours to control.
I've been bought with a price, and I wanna glorify you.
Lord, what is your plan for my life?
What will thou have me to do?
We find God's plan for our life,
but then I would say, number two,
this morning, fulfilling God's plan for your life.
It's a very basic statement this morning,
but you will never fulfill God's plan for your life
if you don't first find God's plan for your life.
You say, well, that's pretty obvious.
You know how many people miss the obvious?
You're not gonna fulfill what you don't know.
You have to find it, and then you must live to fulfill it.
Use Paul as an example this morning again.
Paul knew what God's plan was for his life.
Why did he know?
Because he said, what will thou have me to do?
God answered that question and revealed to him
what his plan was for his life,
and so Paul then had a desire to do what he knew
what God called him to do.
He had a desire to fulfill that plan in his life.
Look at Acts chapter 20, and notice what Paul says
in his testimony as he's sharing and having revealed to us
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God
what his heart attitude was in desiring
to fulfill God's plan for his life.
By the way, isn't it better to fulfill God's plan
for your life than to fulfill your own plan for your life?
To be able to say, as Paul says at the end of his life
in 2 Timothy 4, I have finished.
I finished, I've completed what God wanted me to do.
And it's wonderful.
In Acts chapter 20, notice, before he can ever say
in 2 Timothy 4 that he's finished,
he says in Acts chapter 20 and verse number 24,
but none of these things move me,
neither count I my life dear unto myself
so that I might finish my course with joy.
And the ministry, notice what he says,
which I have received of the Lord Jesus
to testify the gospel of the grace of God.
Paul would say this to those that he's writing to
in the region of Galatia, you don't need to turn there,
but in Galatians chapter number one,
he would tell these churches in the region of Galatia
that were reached during his first missionary journey.
He says in verse number 11 of Galatians one,
but I certify you, brethren, that the gospel
which was preached of me is not after man,
for I neither received it of man,
neither was I taught it,
but by the revelation of Jesus Christ.
Paul was not in the ministry
because some man sent him into the ministry.
God called him, and he said,
I want to fulfill what God's plan is for my life.
How many parents have plans for their children?
You better make sure your plan aligns with God's plan.
I'd never, never would I want to be held accountable
for having a plan for my children
that prevented them from knowing
and doing God's plan for their lives.
Never in a million years,
I don't want to be in that position.
I don't want to be accountable for that.
I want my children to know what God wants them to do.
I want to help try to facilitate that
and to encourage that and to help them
and guide them in any way that God would use me to do it,
but they got to know what God's plan is for their life.
Joseph, not often now, but when he was younger,
was asked repeatedly,
are you going to be a preacher like your daddy?
You know what I taught Joseph?
You can't be a preacher like your daddy
unless God calls you to be a preacher.
It's not just something you decide to do.
No, it's God's plan.
By the way, if you think you just want to decide
to be a preacher and God didn't call you,
you're probably not going to last very long.
And I don't say that for any kind of sympathy
or it's just you got to know what God wants you to do.
And Paul, he says, none of these things move me.
Neither count I my life dear unto myself, why?
Because I want to fulfill what God has for me to do,
his plan for me.
He's revealed it to me, why?
Because I asked him, Lord, what wilt thou have me to do?
And now my gaze is fixed and I am absolutely set
on doing what God has called me to do.
We find that Paul is able to say,
as I referenced already in 2 Timothy 4, that he's finished.
He's finished his course.
He's done what God's called him to do.
This morning though, for you and for me,
I want to draw your attention as we look at a couple
of verses in closing to Colossians 4.
Colossians chapter 4.
See, Paul wasn't just concerned
about fulfilling the plan that God had for his own life.
The Apostle Paul was interested in other servants of God,
people of God, fulfilling what God's plan was for their life.
And in Colossians chapter 4, we see this charge
that is given to Archippus that's mentioned here
in verse number 17.
And we find that this charge is given,
and we find that again, it summarizes,
help us to understand that God has an individual plan
for each of us.
Most of us this morning, if we were to ask as you came in,
who's Archippus, who are you talking about?
There's not, it's not like Paul or David.
He's mentioned here, and notice what the Bible says,
and say to Archippus, take heed to the ministry
which thou hast received from what?
In the Lord, from the Lord, that thou fulfill it.
See, Paul understood that God had a plan
for this man Archippus, that God had given him a ministry.
And God uses Paul to try to give this charge
and to try to encourage this saint of God
that he would fulfill God's plan for his life individually.
Now understand, as I mentioned about finding God's plan
for my life, that he calls me and he equips me,
and then as I'm seeking to fulfill God's plan for my life,
he's there and he's enabling us.
It's so awesome that he equips us for what the plan is,
and then he enables us as we're seeking to fulfill
the work that he's given us to do,
and he's enabling us to do it, and he's there,
and his spirit gives us the strength
and the power that we need as we're seeking
to fulfill the ministry that he's given us to do.
And then this is an amazing truth,
as we finish our lives and as we fulfill the role
that God has given us to do, the plan that God gives us,
you know what he does?
He rewards us.
He rewards us, so he's the one that called us,
he's the one that equips us, and then he enables us,
and then as we do it, he rewards us.
It's absolutely amazing.
How am I gonna fulfill it?
What am I gonna do?
You say, I'm struggling with finding it.
Once you find it, you gotta have that fixed perspective
that I'm gonna finish, I'm gonna fulfill
what God's given me to do.
Look at Hebrews 12 in closing.
Verses that we're familiar with, no doubt.
In Hebrews chapter 12,
it's interesting for in chapter number 11,
if you're familiar with Hebrews 11,
we often will refer to the chapter
as being the hall of faith chapter.
And as you look at Hebrews chapter 11,
you'll read of those saints of old,
those heroes of the faith that sometimes we refer to them
as that by faith, this person did this,
and by faith, this person did that.
I would say to you that as you look at Hebrews 11,
you know what it was?
It was individuals fulfilling God's plan
that God had for their lives.
That's Hebrews 11.
So then Hebrews 12, it says this,
wherefore, seeing we also are compassed about
with so great a cloud of witnesses,
let us lay aside every weight,
and the sin which does so easily beset us,
notice what he says, and let us run with patience
the race that is before us.
So we can.
of those saints of old that had fulfilled the plan that God had for their lives. God
revealed what His plan was for them, and they fulfilled the plan that God had for their
lives. But what about us? Paul says, let us lay aside every weight, and the sin which
doth so easily beset us, and let us run with patience the race that is set before us. Notice
the key in verse two, looking unto Jesus, the author and finisher of our faith, who
for the joy that was set before Him endured the cross, despising the shame, and is set
down at the right hand of the throne of God. For consider Him that endured such contradiction
of sinners against Himself, lest ye be wearied and faint in your minds. I don't want to be
wearied and faintish. I want to fulfill, but I've got to keep my eyes on Jesus. It's amazing
to me. I look at the messages that God placed upon my heart to deliver today, and it's interesting
how they're all connected. If you were in the family Sunday school this morning, Samuel,
he judged Israel all the days of his life. God had a plan for his life, and Samuel fulfilled
God's plan for his life. He had a testimony of faithfully doing what God called him to
do. This evening, we're going to look at a passage of Scripture that I hope would be
an encouragement to you as we think about our own testimonies. And sandwiched between
those two thoughts is this truth this morning, this biblical truth, that God has a plan for
our lives. And I must come to the place where I say, I want to know. Again, God has a plan
for all people of all times to be saved. We dealt with it last week, the plan of redemption.
But if you've been saved this morning, God has a plan for your life as an individual.
How do I find it? Ask Him. With a heart attitude of obedience and submission. God, what wilt
thou have me to do? And as He reveals that to us, and as He equips us for it, we seek
to fulfill through His enablement. And Paul, after he makes that statement in 2 Timothy
4 about finishing his course, he says this in verse number 8, henceforth there is laid
up for me a crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous judge, shall give
me at that day. Not to me only, but unto all them also that love is appearing. He'll reward
us for doing what He's called us to do, what He's equipped us to do. This morning, child
of God, I hope that you recognize God's greatness through the truth that He has a plan for His
individual children. But I hope this morning that we're convicted of, God, what's your
plan for my life? If you don't know, man, ask God to show it to you. Because you're
never gonna fulfill what God's plan is for your life until you find it. It's gonna be
spinning your wheels. You ever hear that term floundering around? Right? Spinning your wheels.
Sitting in a rocking chair, keeping you busy but not getting anywhere. Find God's plan
for your life. Know that He has a plan for your life. Find it. And then God, help me
to fulfill your plan for my life. Why? Because I wanna please you. Let's pray together. Father,
we love you. Thank you for loving us. Thank you for your word. Lord, we looked at so many
examples this morning of those saints of old, if you will, that you used. You had a plan
for their lives and you revealed it to them and they fulfilled and you were glorified
and you worked and your plan was accomplished. And God, I pray that today, in 2023, that
we would acknowledge that we are your workmanship and that you have a plan for us as individuals.
God, I pray for those that have already found your plan for their lives. God, you'd help
them to fulfill it. Help them to be faithful. Faithful unto death. Keeping their eyes on
Jesus, the author and finisher of our faith. Maybe this morning there's some that have
not yet gotten to that point where they've actually found, discovered what your plan
is for their life. Maybe there's some that have been saved that quite honestly they would
just say, I didn't even know that God had a plan for me. God, I pray that you'd help
them to seek your face diligently and earnestly. That God, you would reveal to them your plan
for their lives and they would fulfill it. God, if there's one that's not been saved,
that's in our midst today or tuned in via live stream, they've never trusted Christ
as their Savior, I pray that today they would get that settled. They would trust Christ,
they would be redeemed. I pray, Lord, that in these few moments of invitation as we have
an opportunity to respond to you, Lord, I pray that you'd help us to be doers of the
word and not hearers only. Help us once again to stand in awe of how great you are through
this truth that you have a plan for us as individuals. Ultimately to bring glory to
yourself and to fulfill your master plan, would you move and work as only you can? For
it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.