to be in church tonight.
Fernando, that is super loud to me
and I don't know what's going on there.
When you came in this evening,
you should have got a handout from Brother John
and he was letting you have these.
This is a visual outline, if you will.
And we've been preaching through the book of Revelation.
We went away from the chapter
or from the book for a period of time
and back to it this evening.
And we'll be looking at Revelation chapter number five.
And I've mentioned to you with regard
to the book of Revelation.
Revelation five is where we'll be this evening.
But the book of Revelation is the only book in the Bible
that gives us within itself the outline for the book.
And we find that in chapter one and verse number 19.
And you'll see that this chart is broken up
into those sections.
And the first one is the things which thou hast seen.
And then chapters two and three, the things which are,
and those are the letters to the seven churches.
And then you find the things which shall be hereafter.
And that really begins in chapter number four
and goes all the way until the end.
And then you see at the very end,
eternity as we have the opportunity to see
at the end of the book.
And so what I wanna mention to you
as we get into chapter number five this evening,
Revelation chapter number five,
did anyone not get one of these sheets?
There's enough for everyone to have one.
It wasn't one per family, it was one for every individual.
Does anyone need one?
All right, make sure everyone has one.
Brother John did a fabulous job.
Everyone has one and praise the Lord for that.
And Revelation chapter four and five gives us a glimpse
into the throne room of heaven.
It's really like a parenthetical, if you will,
where we find that the seven churches,
chapter two and three, the letters have been written,
the messages have been delivered.
And then John begins in verse number one
of chapter four after this.
And so after those things in chapters two and three,
behold, a door was opened in heaven.
And the first voice which I heard was as it were
of a trumpet talking with me, which said,
come up hither and I will show thee things
which must be hereafter.
And immediately I was in the spirit.
And the Bible says that he gives us a glimpse
of what's going on.
And behold, a throne was set in heaven
and one sat on the throne.
Now we've studied through chapter number four
as a number of months ago.
When we did that again on Sunday evenings,
we've had different things going on
and some guest preachers coming in,
giving some of our college guys some opportunities
and what have you.
And so now we get back to the preaching
through the book of Revelation,
chapter number five this evening.
And we find that the emphasis here in Revelation five
is the book that is sealed with seven seals.
And the only one who is worthy to open the book,
the Lord Jesus Christ and what a great chapter
as we have the opportunity again
to be in the throne room of heaven to see this
that John is recording for us.
I've titled the message this evening.
It's a little lengthier.
You saw it on the back of the bulletin.
The Lord hath prevailed and is worthy of worship.
Listen, I'm so thankful to know the Lord Jesus Christ
as my personal savior.
I'm so thankful to be able to not only know him,
but to live for him, to tell others about him.
And he is worthy.
He is victorious as we see with that word prevailed.
And so as we look here at the passage,
I'll begin reading.
We'll go through the entire chapter this evening,
but in Revelation five,
I'll begin reading with me in verse number one.
The Bible says this,
and I, John speaking again about this scene in heaven.
And I saw in the right hand of him that sat on the throne,
a book written within and on the backside,
sealed with seven seals.
And I saw a strong angel proclaiming with a loud voice,
who is worthy to open the book
and to loose the seals thereof.
And no man in heaven nor in earth,
neither under the earth was able to open the book,
neither to look thereon.
The Bible says that John wept much.
Why?
Because no man was found worthy to open
and to read the book,
neither to look thereon.
We'll get through the end of the chapter
as we go through the message this evening.
But as we look at verses one through four,
number one in your notes, if you are taking notes,
I want you to notice first of all, the scroll.
We find in verse number one that the Bible says
that he saw in the right hand of him
that sat on the throne, a book written.
And the Bible tells us that it was written on both sides,
within and on the backside, sealed with seven seals.
And so we begin to see this description
that God is giving to us in verse number one,
as John has this recorded for us,
what he is seeing and he is recording it for us.
And we find that this book is a special book.
And we find that it's sealed with these seven seals.
And we'll notice what that is
as we get into chapter number six.
But we find that not only does God provide us
with the description in verse number one of this scroll,
but we find that he also records for us the despair.
Notice in verse number two, a question is asked,
who is worthy to open the book
and to loose the seals thereof?
And if you can imagine being in the throne room of heaven
and seeing what John is beholding
and understanding what is transpiring,
John is seeing this scroll
and he's observing what's taking place.
And there's a strong angel that's proclaiming
with a loud voice, looking for an individual
to take and to open the scroll.
The Bible tells us in verse three,
as I read a moment ago, that there were none.
The Bible says in no man in heaven nor in earth,
neither under the earth, was able to open the book,
neither to look thereon.
And we find the despair because John,
the Bible says that he wept much.
And we begin to understand as John
is relating to us this experience
and as he's recording faithfully for us what has transpired,
he says that he's wept much
because of the fact that there was no one
that was worthy to open and to read the book.
The scroll in Revelation 5 is likely the book of prophecy
that Daniel was commanded to seal up.
In fact, if you go over to Daniel chapter number 12,
we're not gonna read all of it,
we're gonna look at several things in the book of Daniel
next Sunday evening.
In fact, we'll spend the entirety of our time
next Sunday night in the book of Daniel.
The book of Daniel helps unlock truth
with regard to the book of Revelation.
And the Bible is an awesome book, all fitly joined together.
The Bible is God's word,
and we find that no prophecy of the scripture
is of any private interpretation.
We interpret scripture with scripture,
and so many get things messed up
because of the eisegesis
and taking things out of context and what have you.
But we find in Daniel chapter number 12,
notice what the Bible says here in Daniel chapter number 12.
We find that in verse number one,
it says, and at that time shall Michael stand up,
the great prince, which standeth
for the children of thy people,
and there shall be a time of trouble,
such as never was since there was a nation
even to that same time.
And at that time, thy people shall be delivered,
everyone that shall be found written in the book.
By the way, you noticed in verse number one,
a couple of references to thy people.
Who are Isaiah's people?
Israel, the Jews, right?
And in chapter number nine,
which we'll study next week
and look at several things there,
but we find in Daniel chapter number nine
that it says the same thing in verse number 24.
70 weeks are determined upon thy people
and upon thy holy city.
And so who again are Daniel's people?
Daniel's people are the Jews, Israel,
and what is their holy city?
Well, that would be Jerusalem.
Are we tracking and understanding here?
We see that in verse number one of chapter 12.
And so we find that Daniel really,
in chapters 10 through 12, he's getting this vision.
And in verse number four, it says,
but thou, O Daniel, shut up the words
and seal the book.
Even to the time of the end,
many shall run to and fro
and knowledge shall be increased.
And we find that as you look here
in Daniel chapter 12 in verse four,
at the end of really hearing and receiving the vision
and God instructs him very plainly
to shut up the words and to seal the book.
Notice, even to the time of the end.
He gives to us that many shall run to and fro
and knowledge shall be increased.
And really, evidence with regard
to some of the end times things.
As we look at this, as we consider the book
in Revelation chapter five,
the scroll that we're referencing in verses one through four
and we couple it with the scriptures
and look at this truth from Daniel 12.
Again, we'll look at it in greater detail next week
and looking at Daniel nine and some other portions as well.
But really, it's another confirmation for us
that the events of the tribulation,
which begins with the seven seals.
In chapter number six and verse number one,
when that first seal is open,
that's when the tribulation begins.
It's the 70th week of Daniel's prophecy,
Daniel 9, 24 through 27.
And in that 70th week,
we understand it's a seven year period.
If you look at it,
and again, we'll study it more detail next week,
it's split up into two
because at the midpoint of that 70th week,
something significant is going to happen.
And so we find that it begins,
that 70th week begins in chapter number six
when the scroll is opened.
And it once again confirms for us
that that 70th week pertains to Israel.
It pertains to Israel.
Now, why is that important?
So often, and you might hear people ask the question,
when is the rapture gonna happen?
Have you ever had anyone ask you that question?
Have you ever had people that have sat around
and made videos and wrote books
and all sorts of things about when is the rapture?
You have some people that evidently
haven't read all of the scriptures
and they've tried to set a date and a time
and that's really problematic.
And then you have others
that have different aspects of interpretation
with regard to when is the rapture.
I always try to say this,
it's impossible for us to answer the question when
without first answering the question why.
Why is there a tribulation?
Why is there this 70th week?
Why is there a rapture?
The Bible clearly says, as we mentioned a few months ago,
as we looked at chapter number four,
the picture of the rapture there,
the Bible, you have to agree that the Bible says
that there's a time that Christ is coming for his saints
and there's a time in which Christ is coming
with his saints.
And there's a difference between coming for
and coming with.
And we find that as you study through the scriptures,
you begin to compare scripture with scripture
and you look through this and again,
I mentioned Daniel 12 in verse number one,
I mentioned Daniel nine in verse number 24,
again in Daniel 10 in verse 14,
it says, thy people.
In Daniel 11, it references the antichrist
and the things that are happening.
So we know that that's dealing with this same time period.
And so again, we see this book that has been sealed.
And when you compare scripture with scripture,
it seems as if, as we can interpret and look at things,
that it would be the scroll that Daniel
was instructed to seal up.
So we notice the scroll,
notice now in verses five through seven, our savior.
The scroll, but then notice our savior in one,
in verse number five,
and one of the elders saith unto me, weep not.
Now, I'm thankful that the verse doesn't end there
because John was weeping much.
He says, and I wept much.
And it wasn't just that the individual came
and said, weep not with no explanation,
but we find that as we begin to look at our savior
in verses five through seven,
we find here in verse number five,
there's a great announcement that is made.
This one says to John, weep not.
Behold, the lion of the tribe of Judah,
the root of David, hath prevailed to open the book
and to loose the seven seals thereof.
Hallelujah.
And we find the announcement that is given to us
in verse number five.
And as we begin to look at the announcement,
we see this reference of the lion of the tribe of Judah.
If you were to look in Genesis chapter number 49,
and we'll look at just a few verses this evening,
and so have your fingers ready to go.
In Genesis chapter number 49, in verse number nine,
all the way, think about the time
of this particular prophecy that is given in Genesis 49
and the fulfillment and now the reference
in Revelation chapter five.
In Genesis 49, the Bible says in verse number nine,
Judah is a lion's whelp.
From the prey, my son, thou art gone up.
He stooped down, he couched as a lion,
and is an old lion who shall rouse him up.
The scepter shall not depart from Judah,
nor a lawgiver from between his feet until Shiloh come.
The Bible says, and unto him shall be the gathering,
shall the gathering of the people be.
And so we find that when the elder makes the announcement
to John here in verse number five, he says,
weep not, why?
Behold the, he says, the lion of the tribe of Judah.
We find that he then continues and says,
the root of David is the next statement
that is made there in verse number five,
and we're reminded of what we read in the book of Isaiah
in Isaiah chapter number nine,
and then again in Isaiah chapter number 11,
and we'll look at just a few verses.
Look in chapter nine, if you will,
in Isaiah nine, in verse number seven.
We're familiar with verse number six,
I'll read it together.
In verse number six, the Bible says,
for unto us a child is born,
unto us a son is given,
and the government shall be upon his shoulder,
and his name shall be called Wonderful, Counselor,
the Mighty God, the Everlasting Father,
the Prince of Peace.
Of the increase of his government and peace,
there shall be no end.
Upon the throne of David and upon his kingdom,
to order it and to establish it with judgment
and with justice from henceforth even forever,
the zeal of the Lord of hosts will perform this.
And so we find that it says,
the root of David there in verse number five.
Look in chapter number 11,
verse number five in Revelation chapter five,
but look back at Isaiah 11, if you will,
and notice what the Bible says here in Isaiah 11.
It says in verse number one,
and there shall come forth a rod out of the stem of Jesse,
and a branch shall grow out of his roots.
Do you see that branches capitalized there?
It says in verse number two,
and the spirit of the Lord shall rest upon him,
the spirit of wisdom and understanding,
the spirit of counsel and might,
the spirit of knowledge and of the fear of the Lord,
and shall make him of quick understanding
and the fear of the Lord.
And he shall not judge after the sight of his eyes,
and neither reprove after the hearing of his ears,
but with righteousness shall he judge the poor
and reprove with equity for the meek of the earth,
and he shall smite the earth with the rod of his mouth,
and with the breath of his lips shall he slay the wicked,
and righteousness shall be the girdle of his loins,
and faithfulness the girdle of his reins.
The wolf also shall dwell with the lamb,
and the leopard shall lie down with the kid,
and the calf and the young lion and the fatling together,
and a little child shall lead them.
He's talking, this is messianic prophecy.
This is the millennial reign prophecy
of all that's going on.
It says in verse seven,
and the cow and the bear shall feed,
their young one shall lie down together,
and the lion shall eat straw like the ox.
The sucking child shall play on the hole of the asp,
and the weaned child shall put his hand
on the cockatrice's den.
They shall not hurt nor destroy,
and all my holy mountain for the earth
shall be full of the knowledge of the Lord,
as the waters cover the sea.
Verse 10, it says this,
and in that day there shall be a root of Jesse,
which shall stand for an ensign of the people.
To it shall the Gentile seek,
and his rest shall be glorious.
What did it say in Revelation five in verse number five?
Well, it said the line of Judah,
but it said the root of David,
and what a blessing.
We find that the Bible then tells us this announcement.
It then tells us not only that he is the lion
of the tribe of Judah, the root of David,
but it says that he hath prevailed.
Listen, he is victorious.
Amen, he always wins.
He always has.
He is victorious.
He is never gonna be defeated.
He's never going to be conquered.
He is king of kings, Lord of lords.
He is sitting upon his throne.
He doeth all things well.
He doeth all things right,
and we find that he hath prevailed.
The Bible tells us in Colossians one
in verses 14 and 15 with regard to this victory,
this victorious savior that we serve and we know,
and what a blessing in Colossians.
Notice, if you will, in chapter number two,
Colossians chapter number two, verse number 14,
it says blotting out the handwriting of ordinances
that was against us, which was contrary to us,
and took it out of the way,
nailing it to his cross,
and having spoiled principalities and powers,
he made a show of them openly,
triumphing over them in it.
Hallelujah.
Listen, our God is victorious.
Victory in Jesus is a song that we sing.
Victory is one, is a choir song that we've sung before,
and we just rejoice in the victory.
I'm reminded in Hebrews chapter number two
that we find again this reminder
about the victorious God that we serve.
In Hebrews two, in verse number nine, it says,
but we see Jesus, who was made a little lower
than the angels for the suffering of death,
crowned with glory and honor,
that he, by the grace of God,
should taste death for every man.
Aren't you thankful that he died for you?
Aren't you thankful that he took your place on the cross?
But we read, I won't take time to read
the entirety of the passage,
but if you look at verse 14,
the Bible says, for as much then
as the children are partakers of flesh and blood,
he also himself likewise took part of the same,
that through death he might destroy him
that had the power of death.
That is the devil, and deliver them,
who through fear of death were all their lifetime subject
to bondage.
Listen, when the stone rolled away,
the devil, he understood.
I mean, the victory is won, and he hath prevailed.
And what a joy to be able to understand that.
So we know, as we begin reading about our Savior in Revelation 5,
beginning in verse number 5, the announcement,
but then I want you to notice the appearance, or his appearance,
in verse number 6, John begins by saying this,
and I beheld.
And so he sees this, he's in the throne room of heaven,
and he has this scene, and he sees the one that's sitting upon the throne
in a scroll that is in his hand,
and he finds that there's none that's able to open,
that's worthy to open, and he's weeping,
and he hears the announcement in verse number 5,
but then he says, and I beheld.
In verse number 6, his appearance.
It says, lo, in the midst of the throne, and of the four beasts,
and in the midst of the elders stood a lamb,
notice what it says, as it had been slain.
He did go to the cross for us, amen?
He did die a horrific death in our place,
but he's no longer dead.
Amen, he is victorious, he rose, he conquered sin, death, and the grave,
and so it says, stood a lamb as it had been slain,
having seven horns and seven eyes,
which are the seven spirits of God,
sent forth into all the earth.
And so we find that the appearance that is given to us,
this record in verse number 6, as John is beholding,
it reminds us, there's a clear reminder
of the sacrifice that was made for the redeemed.
That for all of eternity, we're going to see,
as we see Jesus, he'll be as a lamb that had been slain.
A reminder of what he did so that we could be in his presence.
A reminder of what he did so that we could be redeemed,
what a blessing.
We find that it talks about seven horns representing the power
and the authority that our God has,
and he has all power, he has all authority.
The seven eyes representing the knowledge and the omniscience of our God,
and he has all knowledge, and he knows all things.
We find also a reference with those seven eyes to the,
or the seven spirits of God,
referencing to the Holy Spirit in Revelation 1, in verse 4,
again in chapter 4, in verse number 5,
and we've dealt with that in the past.
But we find, as John is there,
can you imagine in the throne room of heaven,
and how it begins, but then,
as he hears they're looking for one, and no one's found,
and then he hears the elder say,
weep not, and the announcement, but then, there's the Lord.
Now John knew Jesus, John walked with Jesus.
John was there when Jesus was crucified.
John had the privilege of being able to see the risen Savior, amen?
And now John is in that position.
By the way, John was there at the Mount of Transfiguration.
I mean, he had so many opportunities,
and now he's in the throne room of heaven,
and he's seeing this, he's beholding this,
and we find his, the announcement, his appearance,
but then in verse number 7, we see his authority.
Notice the Bible says, and he came,
the he is the lamb that stood,
in verse number 6, that had been slain,
the he is the one that's the lion of the tribe of Judah,
the root of David, the he is Jesus Christ, my Savior.
And the Bible says that he came,
and took the book out of the right hand of him,
that sat upon the throne.
The question is asked, who is worthy in verse number 2?
The statement is made in verse number 4,
no man was found worthy,
but in verse number 12, and we'll get there in a moment,
it says, worthy is the lamb.
Aren't you thankful?
As we look here, and we see the scroll,
but we find that really, in the midst of the passage,
we find our Savior.
Oh, hallelujah, I'm so thankful.
Hallelujah, what a Savior.
We sing it, it's in our song book,
and oh, more about Jesus, what I know.
And this evening, we ought to rejoice
in the wonderful Savior that we have.
And understanding that he's prevailed, and he comes,
and the Bible says in verse number 7,
that he took that book,
and we find that as we continue reading here
through the text, it says in verse number 8,
and when he had taken the book,
the four beasts and four and 20 elders
fell down before the lamb,
having every one of them harps and golden vials
full of odors, which are the prayers of saints.
And so we find, as we look at what's transpiring,
and what John is seeing, and what John is recording,
that there's the reference to the four beasts
and to the 24 elders there in verse number 8,
and so as we look here and close out the passage,
we've seen the scroll, we've seen our Savior,
and now I want you to notice the song,
the song that ends the chapter.
We find that the song is made up of a choir,
and we find the choir is made up,
according to verse number 8, of those four beasts,
and we studied that as we looked in chapter number 4,
those are angels, I believe seraphims,
as you study back to the book of Ezekiel
and back to the book of Isaiah,
and again, you compare scripture with scripture,
not only those four beasts, but the four and 20 elders
that represent all of the redeemed.
And then we read this in verse 13.
Notice it says, and every creature,
which is in heaven and on the earth and under the earth
and such as are in the sea and all that are in them,
heard I saying, blessing and honor and glory and power
be unto him that sitteth upon the throne
and unto the Lamb forever and ever.
The choir is assembled, if you will,
and we find that here as we study through the passage,
you begin to see this song that is unfolding,
but not only do we notice as the scriptures reveal to us
who is singing, the choir that is assembled,
but I want you to notice the lyrics, the lyrics.
In verse number 9, the Bible says,
and they sung a new song.
And here's what the song says.
Verse number 9, thou art worthy to take the book
and to open the seals thereof,
for thou wast slain and hast redeemed us to God
by thy blood out of every kindred and tongue
and people and nation,
and hast made us unto our God, kings and priests,
and we shall reign on the earth.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne and the beast and the elders
and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000
and thousands of thousands.
Isn't this amazing?
I mean, what a scene that God is allowing us to see here.
And listen, we'll be part of it one day.
I mean, this is something that is yet to happen
and we will be there just as John is
and then those 24 elders representing the redeemed.
We find in verse number 12, I read it a moment ago,
saying with a loud voice,
worthy is the lamb that was slain to receive power
and riches and wisdom and strength
and honor and glory and blessing
and every creature which is in heaven
and on the earth and under the earth
and such as are in the sea and all that are in them,
heard I saying, blessing and honor and glory
and power be unto him that sitteth upon the throne
and unto the lamb forever and ever.
And the four beasts said, amen.
And the four and 20 elders fell down
and worshiped him that liveth forever and ever.
We see the scroll, we see our savior, but we see the song.
He says, thou was slain.
He truly died.
There's some false teachings, some cults that teach
that Jesus didn't really die.
He did die.
He died a horrific death.
It was necessary for Christ to die, to pay,
to make the atonement, to be our substitute.
And he took death.
We read that in Hebrews chapter number two.
He tasted death for every man.
There was not some hocus pocus that took place.
There was no, no, no, Jesus went to the cross
and he suffered and he bled and he died.
But we find that as you look at the lyrics
and even as the announcement had been made
in previous verses, that it's always in the past tense.
Why? Because he's now resurrected.
I'm so thankful for Sunday.
Why? It's the first day.
It's the resurrection.
We gather, we meet.
Why? Because we serve a risen savior.
My God's not dead.
He's alive and he's well and he's able.
And that ought to cause us to rejoice greatly.
And we find this evening that as the lyrics here,
it reminds us, if you look at it,
it reminds us of the gospel.
Why? Because it says thou was slain.
We understand that he's now alive.
He's standing there, they're worshiping him.
So he was slain.
He's now resurrected.
But notice what it says,
in verse number nine there,
and hast redeemed us to God by thy blood.
And so we think about the truth of redemption.
Listen, I know it's the Sunday night crowd,
but if you've never been redeemed by the blood of the lamb,
today is the day of salvation.
The reality is that there's no other way to be saved
but through the blood of the Lord Jesus Christ,
redeemed how I love to proclaim it,
redeemed by the blood of the lamb.
And what a blessing to know that we've been saved,
that we've been forgiven.
There's no remission without the shedding of blood.
We remind ourselves as we observe the Lord's supper
that not only was his body broken for us,
but his blood was shed for us.
And here we find this reference in this song,
we're reminded.
In Revelation chapter number one, look if you will, just very quickly turn a few pages
back and look at what the Bible says in Revelation one in verse number five.
The Bible says this, and from Jesus Christ, who is the faithful witness and the first
begotten of the dead and the prince of the kings of the earth unto him that loved us
and washed us from our sins in his own blood.
Hallelujah.
What a savior.
We find that the song, the lyrics, it's referencing the fact that he was slain and that through
his crucifixion, through his substitutionary atonement, that we've been redeemed to God
by the blood.
Some people ask the question, why did Jesus have to die?
Some people ask the question of Baptists, why do you get so excited about the blood?
Listen, if there's no blood, there's no shedding of blood, there's no forgiveness, there's
no redemption.
And I'm so thankful that Jesus was willing to take my place on the cross.
But notice the scriptures continue, it says, and has redeemed us to God by thy blood, then
notice the last part of verse number nine, out of every kindred and tongue and people
and nation.
Aren't you thankful?
I mean, the gospel's for everyone.
Hallelujah.
There's not one person on the face of the earth that God doesn't love and that Jesus
didn't die for.
And it's a blessing that we take and we understand that as he's speaking here, he says, listen,
there's going to be people in heaven that are going to have the truth that they've been
saved, they've been redeemed, it's all by the blood, but of every kindred, tongue, people
and nation.
I am so thankful for this truth.
And you begin to think about what God is revealing to us, and again, how did they get redeemed?
Well, they got redeemed through the blood of the Lord, but how did they know about the
blood?
How did they know about redemption?
Well because someone went and told them about the Lord Jesus Christ.
Go ye into all the world and preach the gospel, to what?
To every creature.
For whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved, but the scriptures
continue and tell us how shall they believe on him in whom they've not heard and how shall
they hear without a preacher.
And we have missionaries that go all across the globe, why?
Because every single person on planet earth needs to be saved.
They need to know about Jesus.
It doesn't mean that every single person is going to be saved.
They have a choice, whether they'll receive or reject.
As we read in John chapter number 1, he came to his own, but his own received him not.
But as many as received him, to them gave he power to become the sons of God, even to
them that believe on his name.
And so we begin to get the glimpse here into the throne room of heaven and understanding
this great song that is being sung by those that are assembled, and we begin to rejoice.
Listen, heaven is going to be a rejoicing place.
Amen?
I mean, listen, you got to get used to worshiping God.
I mean, we're going to worship him for all of eternity, and he is worthy.
He is worthy.
I'm so thankful to be able to lift my voice and sing.
I understand I don't always sing all the right notes.
I get it.
I understand.
But man, God's put a song in my heart, and I want to worship him.
I was praying this morning and just thinking about the blessing and the privilege of being
able to sing, being able to lift our voices as we open our songbook and we're reminded
about who our God is and reminded about what our God has done.
Man, it's awesome.
Pierre and Kimberly were playing that offertory this evening.
It is well with my soul.
Fernando was up here this morning early before others were here gathered, and I came up to
bring him something, and he was there with a songbook, and he said, I'm just working
on some songs and just singing, and I said, praise the Lord.
He said, I'm having a little trouble with how the full tune goes for it as well with
my soul.
And he had the first couple of lines, but then he wasn't sure exactly the timing, and
Pierre, you would do better than I, but I helped him out.
Amen?
And we sang it together.
Listen, it's awesome to worship God.
Listen, the song service isn't just a filler.
I can preach longer than 40 minutes.
Amen?
I was teaching this week at this Bible Institute last week, Monday through Friday, two-hour
sessions.
Hallelujah, man, two hours.
I just taught.
And they said, there's supposed to be a break.
I said, do we really need a break?
Let's go, man.
And those young guys needed a break, and so that was okay.
We took a 10-minute break in between, but man, it was awesome.
But the reality is that singing is part of worship.
The singing is not just a filler.
The singing, listen, the time of singing in the church is not a time to be doing and going
and whatever, and no, no, no, no, we're worshiping God.
Amen?
What a privilege, what a blessing.
We read about the song, the choir's assembled, the lyrics are provided for us.
We find in verse number 10 that the Bible teaches and reveals to us about the position
that we'll have of ruling during the millennial reign of Christ, that we'll reign and we'll
rule with Him, and what a blessing.
It says, and we shall reign on the earth, a reference to that millennial kingdom.
If you look at that sheet and you understand that there's the rapture and then the seven-year
tribulation followed by the millennial reign of Christ, it is a literal thousand-year reign
and Jesus will rule and reign and we will reign on the earth with Him.
It's all about worship.
It's all about the Lord, who He is, what He's done.
You read these verses and listen, you look at chapter four and five as a combination,
you get into chapter number five and you just get filled with so much joy of knowing who
our God is.
And the fact that one day, listen, John has the privilege of seeing this and recording
this, but one day we'll be there.
What a glorious day when I see Him face-to-face.
What's the response to all of this?
Well, you notice in verse number 14, the Bible says, and the four beasts said, amen, amen.
So be it.
I agree.
This agreement statement that is made.
But then we find the four and 20 elders, again, representing the redeemed, the church age,
if you will, saints, and it says, the four and 20 elders fell down and worshiped Him
that liveth forever and ever.
Hallelujah.
I'm looking forward to that day when I get to see my Savior face-to-face.
I'm looking forward to that day where there'll be an opportunity to be in His presence and
to worship Him and to sing and to just, listen, time shall be no more.
And what a joy.
There's no sickness.
There's no parting.
I mean, there's no hardship.
It's going to be glorious.
Hallelujah.
And I know I said this last week on Sunday morning.
It's a joy to think about the sweet by and by, but we're living in the here and now.
God has a purpose for us in the here and now.
He has a purpose for us, and if you think about it from the text of Scripture, as you
look at this, man, I rejoice that I'm part of that company.
I'm part of the company of the redeemed.
And if you're here this evening and you've been saved by the blood of the Lamb, you too
are part of the company of the redeemed, and what a blessing.
But until that day, we better be busy telling other people about Jesus.
We better be busy telling other people about the one that died for them, the one who rose
conquering sin, death, and the grave, the one who is alive forevermore, the one who
loves them and wants to save them, that wants them to be redeemed.
It's an absolute privilege and honor to be able to talk to somebody about Jesus, to tell
them how much they mean to God and how valuable they are because they were made in the image
of God and that Jesus Christ died for them.
Hallelujah.
What a Savior.
I understand not everyone's going to listen, but I'm telling you, we have the responsibility
to tell them, to let them know the truth.
We don't just keep it to ourselves, no, we let it be known.
We preach the Word and we are commanded to go to all creatures.
He said that we are to preach the gospel, preach the Word of God to every creature,
and what a blessing.
You see here in Revelation chapter number five, the Lord hath prevailed and is worthy
of worship.
Aren't you thankful to know Him as your Savior tonight?
If you know Him as your Savior, you ought to rejoice, you ought to thank Him for allowing
you to know Him and to know the truth of the gospel.
If you don't know Him as your personal Lord and Savior, tonight's the night of salvation,
the day of salvation.
If you know Him, you're saved, maybe God's put somebody in your heart, you want to be
faithful to go tell somebody.
Man, I look forward to seeing them forever and ever and ever, being with them forever,
but I want to take some people with me, tell some people about Jesus, and what a blessing
to know Him and what a privilege to tell others about Him.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you so much for loving us.
Thank you for the passage of Scripture that is before us.
this evening, we thank you for the opportunity
to have a Bible and to read and understand.
And I pray, God, that you'd give us a mind to understand,
give us a heart to understand.
Lord, give us a burden.
Those of us that have been saved by the blood of Christ,
give us a burden to reach the lost around us.
I pray that in the moment of invitation that you'd work,
I pray that we'd be doers of the word and not hearers only.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's gonna play quietly on the piano
and as she does, the altar is open.