Genesis, chapter number 25, and you'll remember last Sunday evening we looked at the first
section of this chapter, Genesis 25, and looked at the truth that Isaac and Ishmael buried
Abraham.
We read of the death of Abraham there in that portion of Scripture, and really I mentioned
at the closing of the message last week how that the focus, if you will, the lens of Scripture
is going to shift focus from being upon Abraham to being upon Isaac, and really eventually
obviously Jacob who becomes Israel, and that's the focus of Scripture.
But in our text this evening we'll be looking specifically at verses 19-26, but we find
that there is a parting word in verses 12-18 that is given to us with regard to Ishmael.
We understand that Abraham had died, he was buried, and we are briefly told in these verses
of Scripture of Ishmael's death, his descendants, and their dwelling place.
And I want you to note right at the beginning this evening that these chapters as we are
looking at the history that is given to us, of course the book of Genesis, the book of
beginnings, genealogies that are provided, you'll find the phrase twice tonight, these
are the generations of, this reference of this truth is given multiple times in the
book of Genesis.
And so it's important to understand that in this particular section of what we're dealing
with it is not in strict chronological order, and it's important for us to understand that
if we think that it's in strict chronological order all of a sudden the events don't really
line up and don't make sense to us and we can get confused quite quickly as we look
at these chapters.
And so we understand there at the beginning of chapter 25 as we look at the death of Abraham,
we mentioned this last week, that Abraham was 175 years old according to verse number
7, when he died, and we understand that was 38 years after the death of Sarah, which would
have put Ishmael and Isaac at 89 and 75.
So Ishmael would have been 89 years old, Isaac would have been 75 years old when they buried
Abraham.
So it's interesting to note as well, and we'll look at some of this this evening, is that
Jacob and Esau would have been 15 years old.
Now there's no reference of Jacob and Esau even being born until what we're looking at
this evening in our text of Scripture, but when you line up the chronological order you
find that these boys, these grandsons of Abraham, would have been 15 years old at his burial,
and it's important that we understand that as we go through the portion of Scripture
it's not as if Abraham died and then Ishmael died and then all of a sudden we're reading
about Jacob and Esau being born to Isaac and Rebekah.
It's not strict chronological order.
So at the onset this evening we want to make sure that that's clear.
Again in verses 12 through 18 we read, we are receiving this parting word with regard
to Ishmael.
Notice the Bible says, now these are the generations of Ishmael, Abraham's son, whom Hagar the
Egyptian, Sarah's handmaid, bear unto Abraham.
And these are the names of the sons of Ishmael by their names according to their generations.
The firstborn of Ishmael, Nebajoth, and Kidar, and Adbil, and Mibsam, and Mishmah, and Dumah,
and Masah, Hadar, and Timah, Jator, Naphish, and Kedemah.
These are the sons of Ishmael, and these are their names by their towns and by their castles,
twelve princes according to their nations.
And so we see here in these verses of Scripture that we are told of these twelve princes according
to their nations.
Now, hold your place here, but turn back to Genesis 17 if you will.
You might want to throw a bookmark in Genesis 17, we'll look back here in just a moment
as we get further into the message this evening.
But you'll remember that God had given that promise to Abraham with regard to a son being
born, that son being Isaac.
And in verse number 18 of Genesis 17, Abraham said unto God, O that Ishmael might live before
thee.
And God's response to Abraham in verse number 19 was, Sarah thy wife shall bear thee a
son indeed, and thou shalt call his name Isaac, and I will establish my covenant with him
for an everlasting covenant, and with his seed after him.
But notice what the Bible says in verse number 20, and as for Ishmael, I have heard thee.
Behold, I have blessed him, and I will make him fruitful, and will multiply him exceedingly.
Twelve princes shall he beget, and I will make him a great nation.
And we see the fulfillment of that right here in the passage that we're looking at
in Genesis chapter 25 when we read of the descendants of Ishmael.
These are their names, it says in verse number 16, by their towns, by their castles, twelve
princes according to their nations.
We then are told that Ishmael in verse number 17, and these are the years of the life of
Ishmael, and 137 years, and he gave up the ghost and died, and was gathered unto his
people.
So Ishmael dies at 137 years old, Abraham was 175 years old according to the previous
passage in which we've looked at, and we find therefore that Ishmael lived 48 years after
the death of his father Abraham.
We find that in verse number 18, the Bible tells us about the dwelling place of the descendants
of Ishmael.
It tells us that they dwelt from Havilah unto Shur, that is before Egypt, as thou goest
toward Assyria, and he died in the presence of all his brethren.
And so really, again, the generations is provided to us.
We see this parting word with regard to Ishmael, but again, the lens of Scripture is focused
not on Ishmael because the promise that was given to Abraham that was, of course, fulfilled
with the birth of Isaac, that was the Messianic line, and that is the focus of the Scripture.
We have often referred to that wonderful book that was written by Mr. Strogge many
years ago, The Unfolding Drama of Redemption, and considering the truth of God's Word in
tracing that Messianic line, and thus the focus of Scripture is transferred from Abraham
now to Isaac.
As we get into verse number 19, really we get into the message this evening, I want
to just draw your attention to verse number 23, and we'll get into the message.
The Bible says this, and the Lord said unto her, speaking of Rebekah, two nations are
in thy womb, and two manner of people shall be separated from thy bowels, and the one
people shall be stronger than the other people, and the elder shall serve the younger.
If you are taking notes this evening, you've probably noticed already on the back of the
bulletin that the title of the message tonight is The Elder Shall Serve the Younger.
The elder shall serve the younger.
I want you to note the supplication, as we look at the text of Scripture, God helps us
and gives us some insight here as to the life of Isaac and Rebekah.
Remember it was at the end of chapter 24, it was in chapter 24 in its entirety, in which
Abraham had given the responsibility to his servant to go find a wife for his son Isaac.
And we find that God blessed and made prosperous his journey, the servant prayed specifically
and God answered specifically, and there was great rejoicing as we study Genesis 24.
And we read now in Genesis 25, in verse number 19, the Bible says, and these are the generations
of Isaac, Abraham's son.
Abraham begat Isaac, and then notice verse number 20, and Isaac was 40 years old when
he took Rebekah to wife, the daughter of Bethuel, the Syrian of Paddan Aram, the sister to Laban,
the Syrian.
And so we find that the Scriptures give us a point of reference with regard to the age
of Isaac.
Again, we understand that Isaac would have been 75 when he buried his father Abraham,
and so this event that we're looking at here tonight in this portion of Scripture happens
35 years before Abraham dies.
And the Bible tells us that they're married, Isaac and Rebekah, and he's 40 years old.
And notice verse number 21, this is where we note the supplication.
The Bible tells us here in verse number 21, and Isaac entreated the Lord for his wife.
The reason for his prayer, the reason for the supplication is revealed to us here in
verse number 21, because she was barren.
Now think about this and understand, no doubt Abraham had shared with Isaac the promises
that God had given him, right?
God had given Abraham promises, and we understand the truth with regard to the birth of Isaac
and the many years in which they waited.
But in Genesis chapter 17, I asked you to keep your place there, in verse number 21,
the Bible says, but my covenant will I establish with Isaac, which Sarah shall bear unto thee
at this set time in the next year.
And we think about the covenant that God is speaking of, and He says that the covenant
that He would, that is speaking to Abraham that He would establish with Isaac, remember
it was with regard to a land and also a seed, correct?
We know that for Abraham that was Isaac, but what did God tell Abraham with regard to his
descendants?
They would be as the number of the stars in the sky, of the sand on the shore, right?
And now here's Isaac, he's now married to Rebecca, the Bible tells us in verse number
20 that he was 40 years old, it tells us in verse number 21 that he entreated the Lord,
he prayed, he sought the face of God, why?
Because she, Rebecca, was barren.
I want you to understand that in verse number 26, the Bible tells us that Isaac was 60 years
old when these boys were born.
So that means that they were married for 19 years before Rebekah conceived.
Now again, having the promise that God had given Abraham, and no doubt Abraham would
have shared with Isaac, there would have been every expectation that they would have children,
correct?
And the Bible tells us that Rebekah, however, is barren.
And so therefore we find that Isaac is going to seek the face of God.
And you think about these 19 years of marriage and of no children and understanding the promise
that had been given, and no doubt it was a stressful time.
And we find that he's praying, and the Bible tells us at the end of verse number 21,
And the Lord was entreated of him, and Rebekah his wife conceived.
Isn't that a blessing?
Once again, and obviously as you read the Word of God, we are regularly confronted with
the truth and reminded of the precious reality of the believer's life, that we have a God
who answers prayer.
We have a God who hears and answers prayer.
It may not be in our time, it may not be according to that timeline that we've set up in our
timetable and our mind and so on and so forth, but we find that here the Bible tells us that
Isaac sought the face of God and he prayed for his wife specifically, why?
Because she was barren.
So what's he praying?
That she would bear fruit, that she would conceive.
No doubt, as you look at the passage of Scripture, that's the specific nature of the prayer,
and what a joy to understand that the Bible tells us that Rebekah his wife conceived.
As we look at the natural implications of this truth this evening, we find that even
there would be spiritual application for us because we understand as believers that we
too are to bear fruit, right?
And we are to bear fruit, and there are times, no doubt, we understand that we're not the
ones that give the increase.
The truth that Paul reveals to the believers in Corinth is some plant and some water, but
God gives the increase.
But we find that in John chapter number 15, we often reference the beginning of that portion
of Scripture.
If you want to take a moment to turn there, in John chapter number 15, I mentioned it
actually this morning, how that we are the branches, but he is the vine, and the importance
of bearing fruit, and we see it here in this portion of Scripture.
In fact, it is encouraging to me as we think about the truth this evening, even that we
see here in the passage of Scripture with Isaac and Rebekah, that Isaac sought the Lord.
He prayed, and God was entreated, and God blessed, and we find that Rebekah conceived.
And this evening, we think about our responsibility to produce, or to bear, I should say, spiritual
fruit, then we need to pray and ask God to use us to that end.
We need to pray that God would give us the opportunities.
He would give us the boldness.
Notice here in John 15, I am the true vine, and my Father is the husbandman.
Every branch in me that beareth not fruit, he taketh away.
And every branch that beareth fruit, he purgeth it, that it may bring forth more fruit.
Just at the very beginning of this passage of Scripture, do you not see that it is God's
will and God's plan that we produce fruit?
Right?
I mean, that's the plan of God.
So we see in verse number three, now ye are clean through the word which I have spoken
unto you.
Abide in me, and I in you, as the branch cannot bear fruit of itself.
We understand that as we look at the natural world, and spiritually the truth is being
provided to us as well.
It says, except it abide in the vine.
No more can ye, except ye abide in me.
I am the vine, ye are the branches.
He that abideth in me, and I in him, the same bringeth forth much fruit.
For without me ye can do nothing.
If a man abide not in me, he is cast forth as a branch, and is withered.
And men gather them, and cast them into the fire, and they are burned.
If ye abide in me, and my words abide in you, ye shall ask what ye will, and it shall be
done unto you.
Well, that's a precious truth, is it not?
Specifically, contextually, what's he talking about?
Bearing fruit.
Correct?
Now, do you think that that's a prayer that God is delighted in answering?
God help me as I seek to be your witness, your ambassador.
You have planned it so that we would be fruit bearers.
God used me to that end.
God is delighted in that.
Notice the truth of verse number eight, herein is my Father glorified that ye bear much fruit.
So shall ye be my disciples.
Perhaps this evening, even at the beginning of this message, we look at what's taking
place here in John 15, and look at some spiritual application from the truth in Genesis 25,
and we say, God, we want you to be glorified, and we understand from John 15 in verse number
eight, herein is my Father glorified that you bear much fruit.
God help me, use me, help me to abide in you so that fruit can be produced.
Amen?
God wants to use us.
God wants to use you.
You say, I can't do it.
That's right, because you're the branch.
Amen?
And the branch, it can't produce fruit on its own.
But if you abide, if the branch is connected to the vine, and He is the true vine, then
all of a sudden, fruit can be produced.
And we are to be bearing fruit.
Back in Genesis chapter 25, we note the supplication in verses 19 through 21.
I want you to note the struggle in verses 22 through 26.
The Bible tells us this, and the children struggled together within her.
Now, of course, Rebecca had not been with child prior to this.
We find the Bible tells us, as we mentioned a moment ago, that she was barren, but now
she's conceived.
And it would seem as if, as you look at verse number 22, that the struggle was so intense,
the struggle was so unusual, that it resulted in her seeking the face of God to figure out
what in the world is going on.
And we find the Bible tells us here that there was this struggle within her, and she said,
if it be so, why am I thus?
Why this struggle?
Why of all of this that's going on?
And the Bible tells us that she went to inquire of the Lord.
Once again, we see the supplication, we see the prayer, we see the seeking the face of
God.
We noted it in verse number 21 with regard to the fact that Rebecca was barren, and Isaac
sought the Lord on her behalf with regard to that need, and now Rebecca herself, because
of the struggle that is taking place, she now seeks the face of God.
This struggle was intense, and thus she seeks God, and she wants to know why.
If it be so, why am I thus?
She didn't have an answer.
Isaac certainly didn't have an answer, amen?
And if you, any of you men, have wives that have had children, and we don't have answers
for why they feel the way that they feel, amen?
And the reality is that God, however, has an answer for Rebecca.
And she seeks the face of God, again, with just great joy, we are reminded of the fact
that our God hears and answers prayer.
Because she seeks God, she went to inquire of the Lord, notice verse 23, and the Lord
said unto her.
Aren't you thankful that God answers prayer?
I mean, honestly, we can just read through a passage like this, and just really, just
kind of mind not really connected, and just, yep, God answered her, so on and so forth,
but God hears us, and He answers us.
And here, Rebecca, she didn't know why she was dealing with what she was dealing with,
she didn't know why in her womb that these two children that were in her womb, why the
struggle was so intense, she could not understand it.
And perhaps, as we look at the passage, we know that she'd never been with child before,
but you have to acknowledge that at this point, she would have had people that she knew that
were with child, and experiences that were spoken of, and this was so unusual, and she
seeks God, and God answers.
And God says, here's why, two nations are in thy womb, and two manner of people shall
be separated from thy bowels.
And the one people shall be stronger than the other people, and the elder shall serve
the younger.
That answer is huge.
I mean, the far-reaching aspect of this answer, the prophetic implications of the answer that
God gives to Rebecca in verse number 23 of Genesis 25 is phenomenal.
And we find that God gives her an answer, why?
Because she asks.
She inquired of the Lord.
And there are times, no doubt, remember, I preached this message several months ago,
I think it was in August, I preached the message there in 1 Samuel, with Samuel, where he says,
speak Lord, for thy servant heareth.
There are times when God wants to speak to us, but we're not listening.
We're not seeking His face.
We're not asking Him,
why, God, are these things going on?
Give me wisdom. Give me answers.
Help me to understand.
But we find here that Rebekah,
she sought the Lord.
She inquired of the Lord.
And God answered her.
We find that here in this passage of Scripture,
God reminds us again that He knows all things
and that He reveals those things.
And we find that in v. 24,
the Bible says,
"'And when her days to be delivered were fulfilled,
behold, there were twins in her womb.
And the first came out red,
all over like an hairy garment,
and they called His name Esau."
Isn't that an interesting way to describe your newborn baby?
You understand, Esau means red.
The name Edom means red.
And we find that it says He was like a hairy garment.
And some commentators said that He resembled
more of an animal than He did a baby.
And I thought that was kind of comical.
But the reality is that the description
is provided for us here in v. 25
with regard to note, the Bible says,
and the first.
Now, we have never had twins,
but we understand and we know people that have had twins.
And there is an older and a younger, right?
There's a firstborn and a secondborn,
and that's just the way it works.
And we find that oftentimes with twins,
there's a level of competition amongst them
as to I'm five minutes older or whatever the situation is.
In fact, we knew some people up in Pennsylvania
that had twins and they were actually born
on two different days because of the time, of course.
And so they had birthdays on two different days,
but they were twins.
Only separated by about seven minutes,
but it was on two different days.
And so we find here, notice it says, and the first,
and that first being Esau.
But remember the truth at the end of v. 23,
the elder shall serve the younger.
And so who's the elder?
Well, the first is the elder,
and that's Esau according to v. 25.
Notice in v. 26, and after that came his brother out.
And so he'd be the younger, correct?
After, and it says, and his hand took hold on Esau's heel
and his name was called Jacob
and Isaac was three score years old when she bared him.
And so we see that in v. 20, he's 40.
In v. 26, he's 60.
And so in just a few verses of scripture,
we cover 20 years of the life of Isaac.
And we find that in this period of time,
as we note what's going on,
we see the fact that Rebekah conceives.
We find the fact that she then delivers the children
after she'd inquired of the Lord and received word
with regard to why the struggle was so intense.
So we see the supplication, we see the struggle,
but I want you to note this evening
and really deal with some application tonight.
I want you to note the symbolism.
There's some great symbolism for us here
in this portion of scripture.
And we ask the question,
even as we looked at that last point of v. 22
and the children struggled,
why the struggle in the womb?
Well, first of all, it was because of their two nations.
And we see the two nations that are mentioned
in v. 23, two nations are in thy womb.
And this is the contextual truth
of this passage of scripture.
When you interpret the scripture,
you find that these two nations that were within the womb,
Jacob, whose name would be turned to Israel,
and we find Esau, who often is referred to as Edom.
And we see those two nations
being the Israelites and the Edomites.
And often as you read your Bible,
as you read through the Old Testament,
you will come across and you will read
of the descendants of Esau, the Edomites.
And you will find on regular occurrence,
the controversy between the Edomites and the Israelites.
But we find that that was told to Rebekah
in this portion of scripture.
It should be no surprise to us as we read the scriptures
and we understand what's taking place
where we find here that God said
that two nations are in thy womb
and two manner of people shall be separated from thy bowels.
And the one people shall be stronger than the other people
and the elder shall serve the younger.
In fact, the Old Testament minor prophet,
the book of Obadiah is specifically written.
It's only one chapter,
but it's specifically written about Edom and the Edomites.
Take just a moment and turn to the book of Obadiah,
if you will.
Hosea, Joel, Amos, Obadiah, and then Jonah.
And help you out there just a moment
so you can find it and see where it is.
In Obadiah, notice, we won't dig real deep into this,
but notice what the Bible says in verse number one.
The vision of Obadiah, you there, you found Obadiah?
Amen, I'll give you another second.
One preacher always says it's after Genesis
and before Revelation, isn't that helpful?
And somewhere in the middle.
And Hosea, Joel, Amos, Obadiah,
if you get to Jonah, just turn back a page or two
and you'll be there.
Obadiah chapter one, there's only one chapter in the book.
Notice it says in verse number one,
the vision of Obadiah,
thus saith the Lord God concerning Edom, right?
Is that what your Bible says?
This is Esau, Edom, the Edomites.
We have heard a rumor from the Lord
and the ambassador is sent among the heathen.
Arise ye and let us rise up against her in battle
and we'll skip a few verses
and I want you to notice in verse number 10
and we'll just kind of move on from here.
In verse number 10, it says this.
For thy violence against thy brother Jacob,
shame shall cover thee and thou shalt be cut off forever.
That's a pretty serious indictment against them.
And really, if you look back and you begin to study
and you look specifically in Numbers chapter 20,
there's a specific incident that is there
that provides you with some insight
into how that the Edomites really rejoiced
at the difficulties and the trials of the Israelites.
And we find that God deals with that.
In verse number 11, it says this.
In the day that thou stoodest on the other side,
in the day that the strangers carried away captive
his forces and foreigners entered into his gates
and cast lots upon Jerusalem,
even thou wast as one of them.
But thou shouldest not have looked on the day
of thy brother in the day that he became a stranger,
neither shouldest thou have rejoiced
over the children of Judah in the day of their destruction,
neither shouldest thou have spoken proudly
in the day of distress.
And so we find that many of those things
going back to the book of Numbers
and in various portions of scripture
and seeing this hostility really is a good way
to describe it between the Edomites and the Israelites.
And we see it historically.
And it is given to us prophetically
here in Genesis chapter 25,
when the inquiry is made of Rebecca,
she has this struggle and she says,
why is it thus?
And God says, well, the symbolism
is that there are two nations within thy womb,
the nation of Israel and the nation of Edom,
the Edomites and the Israelites.
I want you to notice in Romans chapter number nine
and look at this passage of scripture
and we'll finish here with this aspect of the symbolism
and then make some application.
Remember the Bible says that the older
shall serve the younger,
the older being Esau shall serve the younger being Jacob.
And Jacob of course would be Israel
and of course the Messianic line and so on and so forth.
In Romans chapter number nine in verses 10 through 13,
by the way, let me say this,
many people get all sorts of afraid and sideways
reading Romans chapter number nine
and they fret over Calvinism.
And the reality is that Calvinism is very popular.
It's actually gaining a great amount of popularity
in many of our churches today.
And I believe with all of my heart
that the teaching of Calvinism is not biblical.
And I believe that we do not have to align our theology
with some person if that person,
really it's systematic theology,
is a development of Calvin
and he developed this kind of thought
of these points of Calvinism.
But if his points don't align with God's word,
what do we stick to?
The word of God, amen.
And so people shy away from this passage of scripture
because they don't know how to deal with it.
The reality is that God did not predestine people
to go to hell.
He didn't do that.
The Bible teaches us whosoever will may come, right?
Whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord
shall be saved.
God is not willing that any should perish,
but that all should come to repentance.
God so loved the world that he gave his only begotten son.
How do you get around those verses of scripture?
If you say that God just foreordained certain people
to go to hell, he didn't.
And here in Romans chapter nine,
people want to run to this passage of scripture
and say, see, God chose Jacob and he hated Esau.
And God, it has nothing to do with salvation.
Zero.
Nothing.
Romans nine, look at verse number 10.
And not only this, but when Rebecca also had conceived
by one, even by our father Isaac,
for the children being not yet born,
neither having done any good or evil,
that the purpose of God, according to election,
might stand not of works, but of him that calleth.
Now everyone gets afraid of that word election.
It's a Bible word.
We don't have to get worried about somebody
using it the wrong way.
In verse number 12, it says,
"'And it was said unto her,
The elder shall serve the younger,
as it is written,
Jacob have I loved, but Esau have I hated.'"
And we see in this passage of Scripture
that what God is dealing with
is not selecting one for heaven
and one for hell,
one for redemption
and one for damnation.
He's choosing a nation.
Amen?
The nation of Israel.
The Messianic line.
His purpose is being fulfilled.
And we find that to be the case.
If you want to understand,
Ephesians 1 is another passage of Scripture.
We won't take the time this evening,
but let me just reference it for you.
Ephesians 1 is another one of those passages of Scripture
that so many people today are shying away from
because of the word chosen
and because of predestined
being in the passage of Scripture.
Listen, God in Ephesians 1,
let me just say this and we'll move on.
In Ephesians 1,
God is not speaking about the who of salvation.
God, however, is speaking about the how of salvation.
Let me put it this way.
God predetermined before the foundation of the world
not who will be saved,
but how anybody will be saved.
Does that make sense?
So what He said,
before the foundation of the world,
He didn't say, nope, you're out.
Yep, you guys, you're good.
Yeah, I think you're good.
He didn't do that, okay?
That's not how God operated.
But what God did before the foundation of the world
is He said salvation is going to be
through one Person.
That's Jesus Christ, God in flesh.
There's no other name under heaven
given among men whereby we must be saved.
Right?
So therefore, that's Acts 4 and verse 12.
Therefore, God, before the foundation of the world,
determined the how of salvation.
The only way to be saved
is to be born again through the blood of Jesus Christ,
accepting His sacrifice on the cross of Calvary
for your payment.
You can't work your way to heaven.
There's no other way to get to heaven.
There's no other name.
There's no other process.
It's only through this one process.
It's exclusive, right?
That's the how of salvation.
But then, it's whosoever will may come.
As long as you come this predetermined way.
Does that make sense?
Remember back in Genesis
when we were beginning our study
through the book of Genesis,
and we got into Adam and Eve and all of that,
and we kind of went forward
and dealt with the truth
that Adam no doubt would have taught
Cain and Abel about sacrifice and so on and so forth.
Remember Cain and Abel both brought a sacrifice.
They were very different one from the other, correct?
One was accepted and one was rejected.
But I want you to understand
that when Cain's offering was rejected,
God said to Cain,
if thou doest well,
shalt thou not be accepted.
You know what God's saying to Cain?
You didn't come the right way.
If you come with an offering of blood,
you'll be accepted.
But you came the wrong way,
and therefore, you're rejected.
It's not that God chose Abel and rejected Cain.
It's not that God was choosing that
for salvation for those individuals.
No, rather, it's that he, Cain,
chose that he was going to do it his own way.
And if you choose that you're going to do it your own way,
and you say, I don't really care what God's Word says.
I don't care what the Bible says.
I'm going to just be a good person.
I'm going to do this, that, and the other.
And I'm going to get to heaven my own way.
It's not going to happen.
By the authority of God's Word, it's not going to happen.
And so here in Genesis chapter 25,
when you think about the symbolism,
and you think about the truth of Romans 9, verses 10 through 13,
nothing to do with salvation,
everything to do with choosing a nation
and dealing with the Messianic line.
Now think about the next aspect of the symbolism
that is given to us here in Genesis 25.
Not only two nations, but really two natures.
Notice what the Bible says back in Genesis 25,
in verse number 23.
And the Lord said unto her,
Two nations are in thy womb,
and two manner of people
shall be separated from thy bowels.
And the one people shall be stronger than the other people,
and the elder shall serve the younger.
So we see the two nations.
We see the contextual truth,
the interpretation with regard to the two nations.
But when we begin to look at application,
and we look at these two natures,
we can look at the two natures as being
the old man and the new man.
The old man and the new man.
The old man would be the older, correct?
The new man would be the younger, correct?
Because you have, if we've used this terminology before,
to be born once is to die twice,
but to be born twice is to die once.
When we say that, we're looking at what Jesus said to Nicodemus,
ye must be born again.
And we use that terminology, and we say,
you must be born again.
What does it mean to be born again?
It doesn't mean to be baptized.
It doesn't mean to say your first holy communion
or whatever anyone wants to say.
Being born again is placing your faith and trust
in Jesus Christ alone for your salvation.
And at that very moment,
the Bible tells us that we're quickened.
We're made alive.
We're born again.
And so we understand.
I have, therefore, if you've been born again,
as I've been born again, I have two birthdays.
I have a physical birthday, and I have a spiritual birthday.
And I look at those two birthdays
that I would acknowledge in a calendar year,
and they're separated by 17 years.
So the elder is my old man,
and the younger is the new man.
And that's the same for you as well.
Regardless of what that separation of time is,
whether you were born again when you were 30,
or 5, or 4, or whatever the age is,
there's the elder and there's the younger.
There's the old man and the new man.
And we find that here when we think about
this symbolism of these two natures,
the application for us from this passage of Scripture this evening,
we find that he says that two manner of people.
Isn't it amazing how different our old man is from our new man?
The desires of the old man versus the desires of the new man.
What about the struggle between the old man and the new man?
The Bible tells us in Galatians 5
that the Spirit and the flesh are at enmity one with the other.
Have you experienced it?
Do you understand the symbolism that we see here
in this passage of Scripture?
And so when we talk about the two natures
and we talk about the application,
we see no doubt the two nations
and the interpretation here,
and we see historically the struggle
between the Israelites and the Edomites,
and we can read of the judgments in the book of Obadiah,
and Hosea deals with it as well,
and you can read of those things and you can understand.
But when we make application for this symbolism
with regard to the two natures,
and we say the older shall serve the younger,
the old man shall serve the new man,
how is that even possible?
Through the Lord Jesus Christ.
There's no other way.
It's only through Jesus.
And I want you to look at Romans 6,
and we're going to look at several verses here,
and I hope this will be a blessing to you this evening
as we consider the symbolism that is provided.
We see the historical context.
We understand what's taking place with these two nations,
and we see the struggle that took place
after the conception
that was a result of the supplication.
But here, when we look at this symbolism
and we think about the two natures,
the reality is that the struggle that we have
between our old man and our new man
is a direct result of the birth.
The second birth.
You didn't have any struggle before you got saved.
There was no Holy Spirit of God that lived within you
that was convicting you.
There may have been some morals that you had
and a moral compass and so on and so forth,
but you think about the way in which that struggle
became real after salvation.
And all of a sudden, you went to do something
that you used to do and enjoy.
You say, man, I don't have any pleasure in this anymore.
And the struggle becomes real.
Romans 6 and verse 6, it says this,
knowing this,
that our old man is crucified with Him,
that the body of sin might be destroyed,
that henceforth we should not serve sin.
For he that is dead is freed from sin.
Now if we be dead with Christ,
we believe that we shall also live with Him,
knowing that Christ, being raised from the dead,
dieth no more, death hath no more dominion over Him.
For in that he died, he died unto sin once,
but in that he liveth, he liveth unto God.
Likewise, in like manner,
reckon ye also yourselves to be dead indeed unto sin,
but alive unto God.
How? Through Jesus Christ our Lord.
Let not sin therefore reign in your mortal body,
that you should obey it and the lusts thereof.
Neither yield ye your members as instruments of unrighteousness.
righteousness unto sin, but yield yourselves unto God, as those that are
alive from the dead, and your members as instruments of righteousness unto God.
For sin shall not have dominion over you, for you're not under the law, but under
grace." Man, that's precious. And we understand this controversy, this
struggle, again, the symbolism of the struggle. Yes, there's two nations within
thy womb, but there's two manner of people, and you think about the spiritual
application this evening, and we think about that old man and that new man, and
we see that the older shall serve the younger, not through any willpower that
we have, but through living for Christ and allowing Him, yielding to Him, and
allowing Him to give us the victory. We find that here, Paul says it this way in
Galatians 2, in verse number 20. It's a very familiar verse of Scripture. Often,
as we think about the truth in Paul's life and understanding so many of the
things that Paul was able to see God use him in great ways, it really
oftentimes, in my mind, I go back to the truth of Galatians 2.20 to see why God
was able to use Paul in the way that he was. Because Paul said, remember this
morning, Acts 20 and 24, none of these things move me, neither count I my life
dear unto myself. Why? Galatians 2.20, I am crucified with Christ. Nevertheless, I
live, yet not I, but Christ liveth in me, and the life which I now live in the
flesh I live by the faith of the Son of God who loved me and gave Himself for me.
We think about these two natures, and we think about the importance of crucifying
that old man so that we could have the older shall serve the
younger, the elder shall serve the younger. It's through crucifying that old
man and through the power of Christ that that new man, the younger, is able to have
the blessedness that God has designed for us to experience in the Christian
life. We notice in Galatians 5, a few chapters over, notice what God says here
in Galatians 5, in verse number 16. We referenced verse 17 a moment ago, but in
verse number 16 it says this, this I say then, walk in the Spirit and ye shall not
fulfill the lust of the flesh. Did he say that the lust of the flesh would be gone?
No. Do you still have, does your flesh still have desires? Sure it does, but as
we walk in the Spirit, he says ye shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh. When
we've crucified that old man, we've crucified the flesh, we now are walking
in the Spirit. Aren't you thankful that the moment of salvation, Ephesians 1
deals with this as well, the proof of redemption is the Holy Spirit of God
lives within me. I didn't understand all of it when I got saved, and you probably
didn't either. It was a miracle that took place at salvation, and then as you
begin to grow and you understand that God in the person of the Holy Spirit
came and dwelt, and my body is the temple of the Holy Ghost which is in me, which I
have of God, and man it's amazing, and then it starts to make sense as to why
all of a sudden, you know, I didn't have the same level of ease and comfort of
doing these things because the Holy Spirit of God is convicting, and
he's dealing with us, and then the Holy Spirit of God enables us to have the
victory as we yield to him. It says this in verse 17, for the flesh lusteth against
the Spirit, and the Spirit against the flesh, and these are contrary the one to
the other, so that ye cannot do the things that ye would. Skip down to verse
number 24, and they that are Christ, are you Christ? Do you belong to him? Amen! I've
been born again. I belong to him. They that are Christ have crucified the
flesh with the affections and lust. If we live in the Spirit, let us also walk in
the Spirit. The things I used to do, I don't do them anymore. We sing that song
with the kids and we talk about it. Listen, the reality is that if you've
been born again, and as we that are belonging to Christ, we crucify the flesh.
Ephesians 4 deals with this. Colossians 3 deals with this. We preached on this, I
preached on this on Sunday mornings this year several times in Colossians 3, when
we understood our position in Christ, who we are in Christ. We're complete in him.
We seek those things which are above, not those things which are below. We mortify
our members which are upon the earth, Colossians 3 and verse number 5, and we
understand this put-off and put-on truth of Ephesians and Colossians and
the way in which we deal with this truth. And listen, the flesh is not
eradicated at salvation. It'd be wonderful if it was, but it's not. And the
way that we have victory is through yielding to Christ. And the Holy Spirit
of God lives within us, and it's such a precious truth. And so when we look at a
passage here this evening of Genesis chapter 25, and we note the
supplication, and we see the way, and we're reminded again how God hears and
answers prayer, and how that ought to cause us to rejoice, we find that Isaac
prayed, and then Rebekah conceived, and then we see that Rebekah prayed, and God
answered. Why am I thus? Why the struggle within? And God gives the answer, and
we find the symbolism. They're two nations. They're also two natures. When
you look at the life of Jacob and Esau, you see two very different people. You
trace their lives. I mean, right from their birth, just their looks were
so different, right? And you see the difference in them, and you understand
the difference in the old man versus the new man. I'm so thankful that I'm not
what I used to be. I'm not all that I am supposed to be, because he's still
working on me, and he's still working on you, but I'm so glad I'm not what I used
to be. Aren't you? And the work that Christ has done through us as a
result of redemption and salvation, and we say, listen, there are two natures, and
the application this evening is so important. We understand the need for
us to submit ourselves and to yield ourselves to Christ. Sin no longer shall
have dominion over us. The flesh, according to Ephesians 1, there are
desires of the flesh, but as we walk in the Spirit, according to Galatians 5, you
shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh. And this evening, I'm thankful that we
can have victory. Aren't you thankful for that? I'm thankful for salvation, but
I'm thankful that we can live the victorious Christian life, and we can
live and have the joy and the peace that God has designed for us to have. The
Christian life is supposed to be just magnificent, I mean, marvelous,
wonderful, all that God has for us as we yield to him and allow him to work
through us. There's two natures, but God's plan is that the elder shall serve the
younger. The old man shall serve the new man, and it's only possible through the
Lord Jesus Christ. The elder shall serve the younger. Let's pray. Father, we love
you. We thank you for loving us. Thank you for the Word of God. We note this evening
the truth. We understand the contextual interpretation and the truth with
regard to these two nations. We read all throughout the Old Testament of the
conflict between the Edomites and the Israelites. We see how that your focus
and the truth of Jacob being chosen for the nation of Israel and the Messianic
line, and Lord, we rejoice in that truth that was revealed in this passage of
Scripture. Personally and practically this evening, we think about our own two
natures. I thank you for salvation, redemption through the blood of Jesus
Christ, and God, I pray that you'd help us to walk in the Spirit so that we
would not fulfill the lust of the flesh, that truly the elder shall serve the
younger, and I pray that we'd understand this evening that it's only possible
through your power, that you'd help us to yield and submit to you, that we'd allow
you to have your will in a way that we'd live in victory. Pray that you'd move and
work as only you can, that decisions would be made that would please thee, and
we'll thank you for all that you'll do. For it's in Christ's name we pray.