text in the book of Ruth but Ruth chapter number three
and if you're familiar with the book you'll understand
that Ruth, the book is obviously named
after her and she's a central character throughout the book
and at this point we come to chapter three, they've already returned back to
Bethlehem
and it was there in Moab where Ruth was
married to a Jewish family or into a Jewish family
and she went back to
the place of Bethlehem with her mother-in-law Naomi
and as she's there we see the wonderful account
of Boaz and all that takes place and really the book
if you were to look at the entirety of the book of Ruth it's a beautiful picture
of the kinsman Redeemer and obviously a great picture of the Lord Jesus Christ
as our kinsman Redeemer
and Boaz as the human
character here in the book of Ruth, he ensured that the law was fulfilled
before he redeemed Ruth, there were certain things that had to happen
based on the law that God had set forth
and I find that as we would look at the passage of Scripture and understand the
completeness of it
that we can praise God that Jesus Christ also fulfilled all of the law so that we
could be redeemed
and what a blessing it is to know that Jesus is our Savior
and if you're here this morning and you know that you can remember a day in
which you trust that Christ is your Savior that you recognize you are a
sinner
and Christ was the only Savior you turn to Him
alone not your works not anything you think you could do but Christ
alone then we rejoice in our salvation if you're not saved we would trust that
God will work in your heart in such a way
that you would trust Christ as your Savior today
we find that today May 11th
2025 is Mother's Day and it's very interesting
because it was a hundred and twelve years ago today
that Worley was the first observance of Mother's Day though the law had not been
established yet was May 11th 1913
and what had happened is yesterday would be a hundred twelve years ago so the day
before on May 10th
the House of Representatives passed a resolution calling on all federal
government officials
from the president all the way down to wear a white carnation the following day
on May 11th 1913 on observance of Mother's Day
in the 1870s 80s 90s you can see a number of things with regard to
some of the history with regard to Mother's Day and when it was first
observed in certain
places around the country and so on and so forth but we find that it was the
following year
in 1914 that the US Congress passed
a law and in doing so they designated the second Sunday in May
as Mother's Day so since 1914 it's been the second Sunday
in May in the United States of America that we observe Mother's Day I feel
like I'm safe to say that means for all of us
since 1914 so all of our lives the second Sunday
in May has been Mother's Day. Now not every country celebrates Mother's Day
on the same day but we find that best I can tell I tried to do a bunch of
research this week to get a number and it was kinda
scattered with regard to some of the information I could find but best I
could tell from the sources that I combined
there are 179 countries around the world
that have some day on their calendar to
honor mothers and a number of them have it set up like we do that it's the
second Sunday of May
but 179 countries that's a large majority of the countries around the
globe
that have a day to celebrate mothers and to
honor their role. This morning as we begin to look at this passage of
scripture and
couple it with some verses from the book of Proverbs I want to deal with the
subject
here from the book of Ruth where the Bible refers to Ruth as being a virtuous
woman. A virtuous woman and that's the title for the message this morning. The
word virtuous means morally good
it's acting in conformity to the moral law. It carries with it the idea of being
chaste
that word means to be undefiled, to be pure
we find that this phrase virtuous woman if you were to search through the
entirety of the Bible
the phrase is used just three times. Just three times you'll find the phrase
a virtuous woman. When you begin to think about those three times obviously since
it's so few you can easily go to them and study them and
easily reference them but in those three references
we find that there's only one time in the entire Bible that God describes
an individual as being a virtuous woman
and that's here in the book of Ruth. It's very interesting as you begin to understand
what's taking place. Notice in verse number 11 of Ruth chapter 3
and I'm jumping, I'll read verse 10, we'll read the context. In verse 10 he said
to Ruth, blessed be thou the Lord my daughter
for thou hast showed more kindness in the latter end
than at the beginning and as much as thou followest not young men whether poor or
rich
and now my daughter fear not I will do to thee all that thou requirest
then notice this phrase for all the city of my people doth know
that thou are a virtuous
woman. I believe there's probably arguments that we could make that we
could say that there are other
ladies within the scriptures that could be referred to as being a virtuous woman
but God chose to only record on one occasion in his word
where he refers to someone as a virtuous woman
and that's Ruth. It's very interesting because the other two passages of
scripture
or verses of scripture that deal with the subject that you'll read the word or
the phrase a virtuous woman
those two references are found in the book of Proverbs.
We find that in the book of Proverbs we're reminded of course that the human
penman in the book of Proverbs is Solomon
the wise man and it's interesting to note that he is the great
great grandson of Ruth and so Ruth is his great great grandmother the one that
God says is a
virtuous woman. This testimony that is
shared in verse number 11 as Boaz is speaking to her and says for all the
city of my people
doth know that thou art a virtuous
woman. Many years later
God will allow Solomon to pen two verses of scripture
that speak about a virtuous woman and it's his great great grandmother that's
referred that way. I just find that
interesting and I don't believe that he probably knew his great great
grandmother
but there's no doubt in my mind that he knew about
and we have the opportunity to read scripture
that outlines the life of Ruth and so obviously there was a
an awareness that Solomon would have had regarding
this beautiful account that God has given to us in his word.
As we begin to think about this subject or this title a virtuous woman and thinking
about this
description that is given to us I want you to consider a few thoughts this
morning
Number one, a virtuous woman is invaluable.
Is invaluable. The word invaluable means precious
above estimation. It carries this idea so valuable
that its worth cannot be estimated.
Why would I use the word invaluable? Well I do have three eyes this morning for my
points
but I did not simply try to find a word that would fit
in there so that it could be consistent but I truly believe that as we look at
the scriptures
that we find that God communicates to us that a virtuous woman
is invaluable. That her value
that the value of her worth is it cannot be estimated.
Notice if you will over in Proverbs chapter 31
these are the two verses that we'll look at in the book of Proverbs that Solomon
would pen
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God. Turn to Proverbs 31 if you will.
In Proverbs 31
in verse number one the Bible tells us the proverb or the words, excuse me, of
King Lemuel. We believe that's a title that's
given to Solomon. The prophecy, notice this, that his mother
taught him. In fact I preached from this few verses of
verses 1 through 9 last year on Mother's Day and I talked about the
teaching of a mother and the words, these things that
that his mother taught him and what a blessing and a privilege. But we're going to look
through the chapter and it's in this chapter we often refer to as the
Proverbs 31 woman and we'll use that phraseology and all of the description
that is given
but I want you to look in verse number 10. The Bible says this
who can find a virtuous woman
for her price is far
above rubies. This is God giving to us, it's
His word. We know that Solomon is the human penman but God is communicating to
us here this morning as we
consider this verse of scripture that the virtuous woman is invaluable, that
she's precious above estimation.
This one that would be described as being morally good
in conformity to the moral law, being chaste, being undefiled and pure.
that she's invaluable.
We find that God, as Solomon is writing here
and communicating to us, and we know if we were to study
the life of Solomon, that one of the problems
that Solomon had was a problem with women.
But it's interesting that God would even use him
to pen such valuable, powerful truth for us this morning
that we understand, he says,
who can find a virtuous woman for her price
is far above rubies?
Begin to consider, as I look at this verse of Scripture
and considering that a virtuous woman is invaluable,
that we'd understand this morning that if you are blessed
and you would begin to understand maybe your wife
or maybe your mother, maybe your wife and mother
of your children, if you were to consider this morning
that you have a wife that is a virtuous woman,
maybe this morning for the ladies that there's this desire
that we would be known as being a virtuous woman
and the appreciation of a child,
the appreciation of a husband, of this virtuous woman,
our bulletin today from Proverbs 31, the same chapter,
it says her children rise up and call her blessed.
It says that her price is far above rubies.
I hope this morning that you can understand the value
that God places back in Proverbs chapter 12.
You're there in chapter 31.
Look back, if you will, at chapter 12 just for a moment
and this is the other passage or verse of Scripture
that God gives us with regard to a virtuous woman.
And in this verse, like so many others
in the book of Proverbs, there's a contrast
that is provided to us in the verse of Scripture
and it begins by speaking about the virtuous woman
and notice what the Bible says in Proverbs 12
in verse number four, a virtuous woman is a crown
to her husband, is a crown to her husband.
You know, the Bible says here in the book of Proverbs,
whoso findeth a wife, findeth a good thing
and obtain the favor of the Lord.
I'm thankful that God gave me a wife
and that I found a good thing, as he would say
and I don't use that word to be negative,
I'm just using the biblical context,
whoso findeth a wife, findeth a good thing
and obtain the favor of the Lord.
And the Bible says that a virtuous woman
is a crown to her husband.
The contrast, but she that maketh ashamed
is as rottenness in his bones.
I mean, what great contrast in one verse of Scripture
that we find here in Proverbs 12 in verse number four
and again, as he begins speaking about the virtuous woman,
he says that she's a crown to her husband.
What a blessing.
As we consider Ruth this morning
and we look in this passage of Scripture
in the book of Ruth and we begin to understand
and deal with her and the situation
in which she was dealing with as she would go back there
to Bethlehem and being in that place
and all that would take place
and having this testimony.
Boaz understood the value.
He understood that she was invaluable.
Boaz says to her in verse number 11 of our text,
I will do to thee all that thou requirest.
Why was he willing to do all that was necessary?
Because he, not just the city,
he says all the people in the city, they know,
but he knew that she was a virtuous woman.
That's what we say.
I'm gonna do whatever's necessary
to be able to have her as my wife.
Praise the Lord.
She's invaluable.
And Boaz acknowledged that.
He recognized that this morning.
I hope that we would understand if God has blessed you
and you would sit there and not in a prideful way,
but you say, I believe that God has given to me a wife
that's a virtuous woman.
God's given to me a mother that's a virtuous woman
that you thank God for that, that you appreciate that truth.
We find that as we continue and look at this text
and we say that a virtuous woman is invaluable,
but I would say this, number two,
a virtuous woman is identifiable.
Identifiable.
What do we mean by that?
Well, we look in chapter three and we understand what happens,
but I wanna back up just a little bit,
if we could, into the book of Ruth
and catch some of the context.
The Bible tells us in chapter number one,
look back, if you will, in chapter number one.
We begin to see what happens and they were there.
They had gone to Moab.
Why?
Because there was a famine in the land
and they get there to Moab
and it's just the husband and wife and two sons
and they marry girls from Moab
and Ruth and Orpah are the names of these daughters-in-laws
and we find that the husband, Malon and Chilion,
the sons, they all die
and so we find that here, Elimelech, Malon, Chilion,
they've all died and Ruth is there
with her two daughters-in-law.
She's gonna go back.
She heard, she did not experience,
but she heard that God had visited his people
according to verse number six and gave them bread.
There was a famine in the land,
but she heard that God was working
so she's gonna go back to her homeland
and as we look at the text, the Bible says that she says,
notice if you will, in verse number 11,
and Naomi said, turn again, my daughters.
Why will you go with me?
Are there yet any more sons in my womb
that they may be your husbands?
Turn again, my daughters, go your way
for I am too old to have a husband.
If I should say I have hope,
if I should have a husband also tonight
and should also bear sons,
would you tarry for them till they were grown?
Would you stay for them from having husbands?
Nay, my daughters, for it grieveth me much for your sakes
that the hand of the Lord has gone out against me.
They lifted up their voice and wept again
and Orpah kissed her mother-in-law,
but notice this, the Bible says,
Ruth, clave unto her.
In verse number 15 of chapter one,
the Bible says that she said,
behold, thy sister-in-law has gone back
unto her people and unto her gods.
Return thou after thy sister-in-law.
And so what does Naomi say to Ruth?
She says, Orpah's gone back.
Orpah's not coming with me.
Orpah's returned as I've even suggested for her to do.
And yet Ruth clave to her.
And she says, go back with her,
not only to her people,
but she says this unto her gods.
You notice it's a little G,
they're false gods, they're idols.
And we find that the Bible says
that Ruth said, entreat me not to leave thee,
in verse number 16,
or to return from following after thee.
For whither thou goest, I will go,
and where thou lodgest, I will lodge.
Thy people shall be my people,
and thy God, my God.
Where thou diest, will I die,
and there will I be buried.
The Lord do so to me,
and more also, if ought, but death part thee and me.
When she saw that she was steadfastly minded
to go with her,
then she left speaking unto her.
The Bible tells us in verse 19,
so they too went until they came to Bethlehem,
and it came to pass,
notice what it says,
when they were come to Bethlehem,
that all the city was moved about them,
and they said, is this Naomi?
She said unto them, call me not Naomi,
call me Mara,
for the Almighty hath dealt very bitterly with me.
I went out full,
and the Lord hath brought me home again empty.
Why then call you me Naomi,
seeing the Lord hath testified against me,
and the Almighty hath afflicted me.
The Bible tells us in verse 22,
that Naomi returned,
and Ruth the Moabitess,
her daughter-in-law with her,
which returned out of the country of Moab,
and they came to Bethlehem
in the beginning of barley harvest.
We won't take time to read
much of the next couple of chapters,
but we understand that in these days,
this is the entrance into the city of Bethlehem.
This is the first experience
that Ruth would have in the Jewish land,
in that Jewish city of Bethlehem,
and she comes,
and we find that the Bible tells us
that Naomi had a kinsman,
according to chapter two,
and his name is Boaz,
and Ruth was given specific instruction
throughout the next chapter and a half,
and we find that she was diligent
in her duties and her responsibilities.
She worked hard.
She did all of these things
that she was doing
to be able to provide
and to help reach,
provide the food that they needed,
and so on and so forth,
and we find that during this time,
it's only about four to six weeks
at the end of chapter two.
Notice the Bible says
at the end of chapter two in verse 23,
so she kept fast by the maidens of Boaz
to glean unto the end of barley harvest
and of wheat harvest,
and dwelt with her mother-in-law.
If you notice,
at the end of chapter one,
it tells us it was the beginning,
and now it tells us the end,
so it's only really about four to six weeks.
We're talking about
a virtuous woman is identifiable.
There was something about her behavior
in those four to six weeks,
because what happens
is we read chapter number three,
and we find that in chapter number three,
as we begin reading the chapter,
that Ruth is given
specific instruction from Naomi
with regard to what she is to do
and how she is to go about
presenting herself to Boaz
as being the one,
the kinsman, the near kinsman.
that would redeem or buy her back.
And we find that Ruth receives all of this instruction
and she says that she's going to do,
according to verse number five,
and she said unto her,
all that thou sayest unto me, I will do.
She was submissive to the instruction.
She was obedient to what her mother-in-law
had given her to do.
Not only did she say that she would, but she did.
If you read verses six through nine,
it's the fulfillment, the actual obedience, the outworking.
We can say that we're going to do and not do, right?
The Lord Jesus Christ used the illustration.
He said about that situation there
that one says, I'm not gonna do it,
but then later on went and did it.
And one said, I'm going to do it, but never went and did it.
The reality is that Naomi had given to Ruth
good instruction with regard to the law of her people.
Remember, she said, your people will be my people.
Your God will be my God.
And so there was a process that God had given to them
that had to be fulfilled.
And Ruth is going to that place.
She fulfills all of that.
And we find that when Boaz speaks to her,
as we've read already this morning in verse 10 and 11,
that in verse number 11,
Boaz says, for all the city of my people
doth know that thou art a virtuous woman.
That's precious to me.
To think about the testimony that Ruth had
in just four to six weeks,
and to consider this morning
that a virtuous woman is identifiable,
that we could understand this morning
that your testimony is important,
that how, listen, people are watching you.
People are observing you.
You come to that place and you think that no one sees,
no one cares, no one has any idea.
No, there's people that are watching.
And in four to six weeks,
the amount of time that she was there in Bethlehem,
she had this testimony.
Boaz says, all the city, not just a few people.
She was, obviously there's a big talk in town
when Naomi comes back.
We read it at the end of chapter number one,
is not this Naomi?
And of course, Ruth is with her,
and there's no husband, there are no sons,
and they know, they're understanding what's taking place.
And as they would observe the behavior of Ruth
over the next couple of,
these next month and a half,
they reach the conclusion, she's a virtuous woman.
For all of us this morning, we have a testimony.
We have a testimony.
There are people watching us.
There are people that know that we're Christians.
There are people that know in the workplace,
they hear some of the things that we say.
They wonder, didn't they say they were Christian?
Talk about our testimony, our testimony.
How do we respond?
How do we deal with difficulties in our life,
trials, hardships, frustrations?
Our testimony, our testimony matters.
Our testimony matters.
And our testimony is impactful.
These people that observed Ruth,
they reached this conclusion, she's a virtuous woman.
I wonder, as people observe us,
as they observe your life, they observe my life,
what conclusion do they reach?
How many of you have heard somebody say
something like this before?
I don't wanna go to church
because church is full of hypocrites.
You ever hear somebody say that?
I've heard people say that so many times through the years.
What do they mean by that?
Well, they mean that our lifestyle doesn't always equal
what we say.
Now, we understand and we'd readily acknowledge
we're not perfect, we're just saved people.
But you know, there's some things that we do
that tarnish our testimony.
There's some decisions that we can make
that can tarnish our testimony.
And we find this morning that the purpose of our testimony,
yes, a good name is precious.
We think about that truth,
and I just started to quote that all messed up,
but the reality is that we understand this morning
that we are desiring to have a good name,
but not just for our own selves.
We understand that it says a good name
is rather to be chosen than great riches and loving favor
rather than silver and gold.
A good name, that testimony.
But ultimately, what's our testimony to reflect?
Well, my savior, amen?
Jesus said this, we're to let our light shine, why?
So that men may see your good works
and glorify your father, which is in heaven.
Which is in heaven.
And I just wonder as I look at the text of scripture
and consider this morning
that a virtuous woman is identifiable,
I wonder this morning how people,
what type of conclusion people would reach
about our testimony.
Yes, for mothers, yes, for the ladies,
but also for the men here this morning.
We have a testimony, we have a testimony.
We need to be careful that we seek to lift up
and exalt the Lord Jesus Christ in our lives.
We ought to be careful that people understand
that it's Christ that's the hero of our story,
that he's the one, if there's anything good about us,
it's because of Jesus Christ and him alone.
And that we'd be careful not to make decisions
that would tarnish our testimony.
That we'd be careful, see Paul says this,
he says, all things are lawful
but not all things are expedient.
That's a great truth that God gives us in his word.
You say, oh, you're a Christian, you can't do this.
Well, there's certain things that I choose not to do
because of testimony sake.
Does that make sense?
Because of testimony sake.
And there's some times in your life
that you have to evaluate and say, what are we doing?
Why are we doing?
Are we making decisions
that are tarnishing the testimony of ourselves
and more importantly of our God?
How important do people think your God is to you?
How important do people think your church is to you?
You understand what I'm saying?
And this morning we have a testimony,
Naomi had this great testimony.
Boaz says, the whole city of my people doth know
that thou art a virtuous woman.
A virtuous woman is invaluable.
Her price is above rubies.
He says, a virtuous woman, who can find?
Her price is far above rubies.
A virtuous woman is identifiable.
They're observing and they say, she's a virtuous woman.
Number three, I would say this,
a virtuous woman is influential.
Influential.
The reality this morning is that if we're to be
completely honest and transparent,
every single one of us are influential.
We have influence.
You have influence.
You say, I don't have much influence.
It doesn't matter how little
or how much your influence is, you have influence.
There's someone that's observing you.
The last point that we looked at,
but there's a measure of influence
that you have in people's lives.
When I'm speaking about a virtuous woman being influential,
I'm speaking about the truth that we read
at the end of chapter four.
If you were to read the entirety of the fourth chapter,
you find that Ruth and Naomi, they had to wait
and they had to sit still and they had to wait on God
and wait on the situation with Boaz fulfilling the law.
Why?
What happened, if you look contextually,
is that there was someone, it was true that Boaz
was a near kinsman, but there was someone that was nearer.
What that meant under the law that God had prescribed
was that it was the right for someone else
to first redeem Ruth to himself.
And so Boaz could not overstep what the law had given
and prescribed and he had to follow the law.
As much as he understood that she was a virtuous woman
and he desired that she would be his wife,
he had to do things the right way.
And Ruth had to wait.
She had to wait and trust.
You come to the fourth chapter and you find
that the conversation takes place, the witnesses are there
as they would, again, fulfill the law
that God had prescribed.
And it says in verse number nine,
and Boaz said unto the elders and unto all the people,
ye are witnesses this day that I have bought all
that was Alimelech's and all that was Chilion's
and Malon's of the hand of Naomi.
Moreover, Ruth the Moabitess, the wife of Malon,
have I purchased to be my wife,
to raise up the name of the dead upon his inheritance,
that the name of the dead be not cut off
from among his brethren and from the gate of his place.
Ye are witnesses this day.
And so we find that Ruth is now the wife of Boaz.
Speaking about influence.
If you read verse number 13, the Bible says,
So Boaz took Ruth, and she was his wife,
and when he went in unto her,
the Lord gave her conception, and she bare a son.
She became a mom, a mother.
I understand that not all are mothers.
I understand that not all have children.
I understand there are some that are unmarried,
some that have never been able to have children.
And I'm sensitive to that.
We understand this morning that children are an
inheritance of the Lord.
The fruit of the womb is His reward,
and we're thankful and we're blessed.
But we find that here, Ruth, entering into this new phase,
listen, she was a virtuous woman when she was single.
Amen?
She was a virtuous woman when she was single.
She was a virtuous woman when she had no children.
I believe she's still a virtuous woman when she has children.
And so we understand this morning as we look here
at the example of Ruth, and we look at this,
and we understand that God now has chosen
to bless her with a son.
I believe that the greatest area of influence
for a mother is her children.
Someone of yesteryear said,
The hand that rocks the cradle rules the world.
It's a familiar quote.
The reality is that God would give her a son.
As we look through the text of Scripture
and understand the truth of what takes place,
the Bible says that God gives her this son.
And who is this son?
Well, the Bible tells us in verse number 17,
And the women, her neighbors, gave it a name,
saying, There is a son born to Naomi,
of course that's the mother-in-law,
and they called his name Obed.
What makes this interesting is that Obed
is the father of Jesse.
Jesse is the father of David.
A virtuous woman is influential.
I was at this men's retreat,
and I was talking to this young fella,
and I knew the pastor, I didn't know anyone else there,
and just chatting as we were sitting around
on Friday evening, Saturday morning,
had some time just kind of chatting and fellowshipping,
and I began to ask him, he had a shirt on,
it said he had his name and said firefighter,
so it was pretty easy to say you're a firefighter.
And we got to talk about what he did and so on and so forth,
and was he married, did he have children,
and we began to talk about being married.
He's a younger fella, has a two-year-old son,
and we were talking and what have you,
and he mentioned that they made the decision to,
and I'm just sharing this testimony,
I'm not being critical of it,
but the reality is that he says,
we made the decision that my wife would stay home
so that she could spend time raising our son.
Because the influence that she can have in his life,
we want her to influence our son, not someone else.
And I thought, wow, praise the Lord.
I understand that not everyone can do that.
I understand that.
I'm aware of that.
But if you can, it's a huge blessing.
A huge blessing.
Why?
Because virtuous women are influential.
And you think about the influence
that no doubt Ruth had in the life of Obed,
and no doubt the influence then
that would pass down generationally.
There's a generational influence.
We find that the Bible tells us here
that Naomi took this role with regard
to even helping with Obed
and all that would take place.
In fact, in verse 16, it says that Naomi
took the child and laid it in her bosom
and became nurse unto it.
And you think about that influence of a grandmother.
Naomi, she came back into Bethlehem bitter.
Mara, don't call me Naomi any longer,
but now she's got joy
because of all that has transpired.
And we find as we look at the text of Scripture
that Obed is born to Boaz and to Ruth,
and then as we begin to think about Jesse,
it was Jesse that God identified
when He would reject Saul
from being the king of Israel.
And He says to Samuel,
go to the house of Jesse.
Why?
Because I have the next king
as one of his sons.
And you're going to go and you're going to anoint him.
David.
The book of Acts says that David
is a man after God's own heart.
If we were to look at the history of Israel
and the kingdom and all of that,
we'd say that David was the greatest king.
In fact, as you read through the Chronicles and the Kings,
you'll find that many times
what is referenced is the behavior
of the individual king compared to David.
David wasn't perfect.
We know his sin.
God records it for us.
But we find that there's influence
that a virtuous woman has.
Can I tell you today
that if you never have had children,
you still have influence.
If your children are raised,
We have opportunity to influence others.
Listen, they need to see,
they need to understand that testimony
of a virtuous woman.
What does it look like?
Listen, can I tell you this morning
that the example that the world is providing of a woman
is not an example that I want my daughters to follow
nor my granddaughter?
I'm being very honest with you.
My daughters, praise the Lord,
they're 22 and 20.
Well, almost 22.
Next week should be 22, 22 and 20.
But I got a 19-month-old granddaughter.
I don't want my daughters
nor do I want my granddaughter
emulating what the world portrays.
Are you tracking?
I want them to see some examples
of some virtuous women first in my wife,
but then in the ladies of our church.
You have influence.
These girls stood up here and sang this morning,
Brianna, 20, and how old's Camilla?
Six, seven?
Seven, she just had a birthday.
She's seven.
Don't tell her I said six.
You're in trouble with kids, man.
Listen, those young girls,
they need to see some virtuous women.
You have influence.
Yes, mom has influence,
but the ladies of our church,
you have influence.
You have influence.
I want you to think about Timothy in closing.
Turn, if you will, to the book of 2 Timothy.
I want you to see what God tells us
in the book of 2 Timothy.
I'm going to read a verse from chapter 3
and then we're going to go back to chapter 1.
In 2 Timothy chapter number 3,
God tells us this about Timothy.
In 2 Timothy chapter 3,
Paul is speaking to Timothy,
obviously writing to him as his son of the faith
and giving him instruction.
He tells him all of these things in chapter 3
about the perilous times of the last days
and so on and so forth.
What's the answer?
What do we do knowing all of these things?
We continue.
We don't give up.
We don't quit.
We don't run.
We don't hide.
We continue.
And what is Paul saying?
Notice if we will pick it up in verse 14.
He says,
I believe that he's speaking in verse 14
of many of the things that Paul himself
had taught Timothy.
But he continues on in verse number 15
and he says,
Thou hast known the holy scriptures,
which are able to make thee wise unto salvation
through faith which is in Christ Jesus.
I'm thankful that the scriptures are holy.
He says,
Thou hast known the holy scriptures.
And he says that from a child
thou hast known the holy scriptures.
There was some influence taking place
in the life of little Timothy.
He was just a child.
We find the Bible tells us that the scriptures are holy
but they're able to make thee wise.
Notice what the Bible says unto salvation
through faith which is in Christ Jesus.
By the way,
I'm thankful that God provides for us
the plan of redemption in his word.
Salvation.
And salvation through how?
Not your works.
The Bible plainly says
that he has made thee wise unto salvation
or the holy scriptures,
which are able to make thee wise unto salvation
through faith which is in Christ Jesus.
That's what God has determined.
But I want you to go back to chapter one
as we deal with this influence of a virtuous woman.
The two that are mentioned here
are not referred to as virtuous women
but we find that God will provide us
with the level of influence
that they had in the life of Timothy.
The Bible says in 2 Timothy chapter one in verse three,
I thank God whom I serve from my forefathers
with pure conscience that without
Without ceasing, I have remembrance of Thee in my prayers night and day, greatly desiring
to see Thee, being mindful of Thy tears, that I may be filled with joy.
Then notice what Paul says in verse number five, when I call to remembrance the unfeigned
faith that is in Thee.
It's a great testimony that Paul has, that Timothy has, that Paul is referring to.
That word unfeigned means not to be counterfeit or not to be hypocritical.
I could go back to our second point about our testimony, a virtuous woman being identifiable.
But notice what Paul says.
He says, I'm calling to remembrance the unfeigned faith that is in Thee, but then he says this,
which first, which dwelt first in Thy grandmother Lois and Thy mother Eunice, and I am persuaded
that in Thee also.
That from a child Thou hast known the Holy Scriptures, which are able to make Thee wise
unto salvation through faith, which is in Christ Jesus.
Paul didn't meet Timothy when he was a child and have that influence.
No, it was grandmom and mom.
It was Lois and Eunice that had the influence in the life of little Timothy.
This morning, a virtuous woman is invaluable.
Who can find a virtuous woman?
Their price is far above Ruby's.
A virtuous woman is a crown to her husband.
A virtuous woman is identifiable.
Boaz says, for all the people of my city doth know that thou art a virtuous woman.
A virtuous woman is influential.
She has influence, Obed, Jesse, David.
We fast forward to the New Testament and we consider Timothy, Lois and Eunice.
Listen this morning.
I hope that God would give us the opportunity to be used of Him to influence other people
for the cause of Christ, that they would set their hope in God, that they would serve God
all the days of their lives, that they would see that your testimony, that our testimony
is God-honoring, that we're not making decisions that are carnal and fleshly decisions that
are tarnishing our testimony, our reputation with others, that are teaching our children
something that we do not desire to teach them because the decisions that you make are influencing
your children.
The decisions that you make reveal to your children how important you think things are
in your life and how unimportant things are in your life.
This morning, God gives us influence.
I hope that if your wife, you would say, she's a virtuous woman if you're married.
I hope this morning if you'd say, my mother, she's a virtuous woman.
You thank God, thank God.
If she's still living, you make sure that you call her, reach out, let her know that
you appreciate her, that you love her.
Your blessing to see that on only three occasions God uses this term, a virtuous woman.
He describes one, Ruth, and then he uses her great-great-grandson to pen two verses of
Scripture that provide further description of a virtuous woman.
I pray that God would help us this morning.
You say, I'm not a woman, the message wasn't for me.
I'm not a mother, the message wasn't for me.
I hope that you heard all the application throughout for all of us because God has given
to all of us a measure of influence.
Somebody's watching you.
Can I say, lots of somebodies are watching you and if you have kids, they're very much
watching you.
They're watching everything you do.
I remember years ago reading a little thing that said about a little boy what their aspirations
were.
He said, I want to be just like my daddy.
I remember reading that, being convicted.
Why?
Because I have a son that watches me.
You have children that watch you.
And if your son, my son, our children were just like us, would that be a good thing?
I hope we could say yes.
People are watching us.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you, God, for your Word.
Thank you for the testimony of Ruth.
God, I pray that you'd help us to have a testimony like Ruth.
Not all of us are women, but all of us have a testimony.
God, would you help us to live in such a way that we'd have godly biblical influence in
the lives of those that you would allow us to have influence in their lives.
Lord, help us.
I pray that you would, on this day, help us to honor and to remember our moms.
Lord, the blessing.
For those that have children, Lord, would you strengthen them this morning?
Would you help them to have that reset moment, maybe, refocus on the joy and responsibility
that's been entrusted to them?
I know that it's a lot of work.
I know it's hard.
But, God, with your help, we can fulfill what you've called us to do.
I pray, God, that you'd have your will and way in the hearts and lives of your people
today.
If there's one not sure of heaven, God, we earnestly pray that today would be the day
of their salvation.
We pray that you'd move and work as only you can for it's in Christ's name.
We pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed.
Eyes are closed.
At the end of each of our services, we have an opportunity to have an invitation, give
you.