10 this evening, plan to preach a little bit shorter
this evening at the end of the invitation tonight.
We have a couple of update videos
that we're gonna watch from our missionaries.
We've gotten a couple of updates recently
from missionaries via video,
and I always like to be able to show those to you
so that you can see what God is doing
and how God is working.
And we'd gotten a couple right at the same time,
and I was just praying about when to show those.
Sometimes we show them on a Wednesday evening,
but of course, several folks aren't here
with student ministries and other things going on.
And the Lord laid this passage of scripture
upon my heart for this week, for tonight,
and to show these videos.
In Romans 10 is a familiar passage of scripture.
We think about missions.
I've titled the message tonight, Why Missions?
And really, the thought of the songs
that we've had the opportunity to sing tonight about heaven,
well, that's a good reason to answer the question,
why missions, because eternity is certain,
and people are gonna die,
and people are gonna spend eternity in either heaven
or the lake of fire, and we have the truth.
We have the opportunity to take the message of the gospel
to a lost and dying world.
If you've been around Fellowship Baptist Church
for any period of time,
you know that world missions is a priority.
A number of years ago, in fact,
the first calendar year that I was here as the pastor,
I worked with Brother Doug Cook about an idea
in order to put a map in our sanctuary
that would give us an idea of missions
that would say, as you walk in,
it would just kinda scream for your attention.
All of you are looking over there,
even as I'm talking about it,
because what happens is you walk into this sanctuary,
and you have immediately,
your eyes are drawn to a couple of things,
the pulpit area, by the way, that's on purpose,
but also to the map on the wall,
and over here, send the light with another map of the world.
That's our duty, that's our mission,
and we began to talk about
how we could do something like this.
I had a lot of ideas,
and knew where to buy a lot of things
from my days in the corporate world,
but the ability to put all of that together,
well, God allowed Doug Cook to be here
and to have that ability,
and he worked, and several of our men
would go over to his house regularly
as they worked on this project,
and still today, I hear many people,
in fact, I think Mimi last Sunday night,
we had some visitors, and she said,
do you see our missions map?
And she takes them over there to show them our missions map.
Every time we have a missionary that comes,
we have the opportunity to show them our missions map,
and to show them how it lights up,
and give us that indication of where we have representation,
and where we do not have representation,
and missions is a priority,
and I'm thankful for that.
We make every effort, I make every effort
to ensure that you're provided with updates,
and that you have an opportunity
to be able to pray effectively and intelligently
for our missionaries.
How can you pray for them intelligently
if you don't know what their needs are,
if you're not receiving updates,
and so missionaries provide updates at various times.
Some people, some missionaries provide updates every month,
some every other month.
We require no less than one a quarter,
and we have the opportunity to get those update letters,
and we seek to provide you with those updates
Wednesday evenings on the back of our prayer bulletin,
three or four a week that we give you,
and Sunday mornings, we have a missions moment
in our Sunday morning service,
so that we can bring an update to you.
The young men have been helping,
I've done some of those,
and Joseph and Tim have been helping with that,
getting them some opportunity to serve,
and we have an opportunity to have a directory.
It's amazing to me, especially with,
I think of Brother Scott Cottle and others
that have come and seen our missionary directory,
and they say, man, can I take one of these?
This is phenomenal, this is a great tool,
and we wanna keep that in front of you, why?
Because missions is important.
Missions is a priority,
and we encourage you regularly to give to missions.
Why do we encourage you to give to missions?
Well, because it is our privilege
to be able to give of our resources
that God blesses us with,
not just to give a tithe and an offering
to the local church,
but to designate and give toward missions,
toward world missions, why?
So that we can support all those missionaries,
so that the gospel can go forward.
We have on our weekly offering envelopes,
there's only two categories,
and one is general offering, tithe and offering,
and one is missions.
I'm thankful that when I first got saved,
someone challenged me with regard to missions giving,
and I've had people ask me over the years,
how do you determine your missions giving,
and so on and so forth.
I don't think there's a magic formula.
I do know that it's not part of your tithe.
I know that the tithe is one thing,
and missions is a different thing,
and to be able to give to missions, what a blessing,
and for all these years,
Holly and I have had the opportunity
to give personally to missions.
I don't just encourage our church family
to give to missions, but I, we participate,
we give to missions, why?
Because we're investing in eternity.
We're investing in eternity.
Missions, I believe, is the heartbeat of God.
I really do.
For God so loved the world
that he gave his only begotten son, right?
He sent the Lord Jesus Christ to this world.
Why?
To save sinners.
This is a faithful saying and worthy of all acceptation
that Christ Jesus came into the world
for what purpose?
To save sinners, 1 Timothy,
and we find that missions is not only the heart of God,
but it really should be the life of any local church,
any New Testament church,
they should have a robust missions program,
and we ought to be mindful of our responsibility
to reach our Jerusalem,
but at the same time reaching
to the uttermost part of the earth, the world.
What an opportunity.
I mentioned this morning in the book of Acts,
the Bible says that the early church,
they filled Jerusalem with their doctrine,
but then we see also in the early church
that it said of them that they turned the world upside down.
The known world received the gospel,
the missionary journeys that we read of
beginning in Acts 13 and how even in Acts 8,
that they that were scattered from Jerusalem,
they went everywhere preaching the word,
and how God was using his people
to take the gospel message to the world,
and that still remains our responsibility to this very day.
I say this to just simply say to God be the glory.
I did a little research last week.
Why?
Because we say that missions is a priority,
but you know the reality is you can say anything you want.
You can say anything you want.
I know church is the same mission is a priority,
but really it's not a priority,
and I'm not casting stones, it's just the reality,
and as we say that missions is a priority,
I did a little research,
and during the time that God has allowed me
to be the pastor at Fellowship Baptist Church,
almost 30% of our total income has gone to world missions.
I say to God be the glory,
and that's a phenomenal testimony of a church
that has a focus on reaching the world with the gospel,
and I praise the Lord for it.
This year, this calendar year,
if God would allow, if things would continue,
and of course we're not presuming upon the Lord
or in anything else, but if things would continue,
and at the close of this calendar year,
we will come very close to hitting or exceeding
one and a half million dollars of missions giving
through our church during my tenure,
and I just praise the Lord for that.
I think to God be the glory.
I've often been asked, and I'm at the age now
where I'm really not an old man, praise the Lord for that,
I'm still a young man,
but I've been pastoring the same church
for 12 and a half years,
and so often I begin to get questions from other pastors,
younger pastors or pastors that are going to a church
and just kind of beginning,
and they've asked questions about missions and what have you
and I regularly try to tell these pastors
that if you wanna have a missions-minded church,
you need to place an emphasis on missions.
It's not gonna happen on accident,
and I appreciate your investment.
I appreciate the opportunity that we have corporately,
collectively to be involved in world missions.
Why missions?
We deal with the subject and we understand that missions,
as we give to missions, as we pray for missions,
that we're making an investment in eternity.
We're making an investment in eternity.
You ever hear people talk about investing and investments
and they have portfolios and all sorts of things
that they wanna give you,
and quite honestly, I'm readily admitting
that that is not my strong area, my strong suit,
but there are some people that are very smart
and wise in that situation and what have you,
and they have people that you can talk to,
but I want you to understand that when you give to missions
that you're investing in eternity.
You're investing in eternity.
A missionary once said this,
and the returns are out of this world,
and I understand what they meant by that,
and I like the phraseology because so often
when you start talking about investments,
what is the question you wanna have is,
what is the return on my investment, ROI, right?
What is my return on my investment?
We've had, I don't know the numbers.
It would be impossible for me
to be able to calculate the numbers
because of the number of missionaries that we have
and the way that the update letters come in,
but hundreds, if not thousands of souls
have been saved through our missions program
as we have the opportunity to support these missionaries.
Now think about that.
Paul says the church at Philippi
in Philippians chapter number four
that this is fruit to your account,
and God keeps record of that,
and these missionaries,
that we have the opportunity to support
and we hear back from them of souls being saved
and lives being changed and discipleship going forward,
you have a part in that.
If you're giving to missions,
our church has a part in that, why?
Because we support missions.
And we want you as an individual,
every individual to have a part in that, why?
Because collectively we're making an investment,
but it's made up of individuals
that are giving and making that investment.
Dozens of churches have been started.
We can look at pictures over the years of empty fields
where there was no church and now there's a church.
We can look at pictures of storefront buildings
where other establishments and businesses
had their business in these particular locations
and they were vacant and now there's a church in that place.
We can think even most recently of a situation
there in Belgium with the Haley family
where a restaurant has been converted to a church
and to God be the glory.
That's exciting when you have the opportunity to see that
and to think about the local church
and what God intends for the church and what the church is.
We've had the opportunity as we provide help
with Beacon of Truth,
not only in supporting that ministry financially,
but also in putting Romans booklets together.
I've said jokingly,
but I think there's a measure of seriousness to it
that if I ever said
that we were gonna cancel scripture assembly
and we're not gonna do it anymore,
I'd get fired and you'd look for a new pastor.
And why?
Because you love that ministry.
We've put over 400,000 Romans booklets together.
We have, our church personally, we've done that.
I mentioned it's fruit to our account.
The Bible says you're there in Romans 10.
We'll be there in just a moment.
But in Philippians,
I want you to see what Paul says
about the church at Philippi
and how he commends them here beginning
in verse number 14 of Philippians chapter four.
And what a blessing to think about the church at Philippi
and the part that they had
in helping the work of the ministry
through their offering, through their contribution.
It says in verse 14,
notwithstanding ye have well done,
that ye did communicate with my affliction.
Now you Philippians know also
that in the beginning of the gospel,
when I departed from Macedonia,
notice what he says,
no church communicated with me
as concerning giving and receiving.
Notice those last three words,
but ye only, but ye only.
Aren't you thankful for the church at Philippi?
Why?
Because it enabled Paul to be able to go
and to continue to preach the gospel message.
Notice in verse 17,
Paul says this,
not because I desire a gift,
but I desire fruit that may abound to your account.
How does that work?
I just trust God with it.
I'm not sure how it all works.
I'm not sure how God keeps account of all of that,
but I know that God does.
And I know that it's an investment in eternity.
And we can trust that God,
he'd do with all things well.
In verse 18, he says,
but I have all that abound.
I am full having received of Epaphroditus,
the things which were sent from you.
And then notice how those things,
that offering, how it's described,
an odor of a sweet smell, a sacrifice,
acceptable, well-pleasing to God.
God was pleased with the church at Philippi
because they gave, they gave regularly.
And then the great promise that many of us
are familiar with in verse 19,
but my God shall supply all your need
according to his riches in glory by Christ Jesus.
And we read in the book of 2 Corinthians
how that they gave out of their poverty
and they were first willing to give of themselves.
And quite honestly, I'm convicted as I read that truth
in 2 Corinthians, when the Bible speaks about,
as Paul is speaking to them about
how they gave out of their poverty.
And I begin to think about that
and I begin to be challenged, why?
Because so often here in 2024,
most often we give out of our abundance,
not out of our poverty.
We really do.
It's fruit to our account.
It's a joy, I mentioned already,
to personally be involved in giving to missions.
It's a joy to know that as we give to Bible projects
and we've given to Papua New Guinea Bible project,
to Samoan Bible project, involved in other Bible projects
as we send these Bibles around the world.
But those two in particular,
we had very specific designated campaigns, if you will,
to raise funds for those Bibles.
I'm thankful to have had a part, our family, your family,
us as a church in knowing that there's some people
on the other side of the world
that can hold a Bible in their hand today because you gave.
Isn't that amazing?
It's absolutely phenomenal.
This book, the Bible says in Psalm 119,
the entrance of thy words giveth light.
And what a joy and what a blessing.
It's a blessing to be a pastor of a church
with a heart for world missions.
And I just thank you this evening for your part in missions.
And it's not something that I obviously could do on my own.
I try to cast the vision and try to encourage you
and do all that I can to keep it before you.
And I appreciate your response.
I appreciate your sensitivity to the Lord.
I appreciate the fact that when a missionary has a need
that people are ready to help and do what we can
to help with those missionaries.
I appreciate how you pray for our missionaries.
I appreciate the way in which you give and pray
and support our missionaries.
As we answer the question, why missions?
We come to Romans 10.
We'll look at just a few verses of scripture this evening.
It's a passage of scripture
that is quite familiar to many of us.
In Romans chapter number 10, beginning in verse number 13,
again, a verse that many of us could quote tonight.
The Bible says,
for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord
shall be saved.
Aren't you thankful for that Bible verse?
For whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord
shall be saved.
Verse 14 says this,
how then shall they call on him
in whom they have not believed?
And how shall they believe in him
of whom they have not heard?
And how shall they hear without a preacher?
And how shall they preach except they be sent?
As it is written,
how beautiful are the feet of them
that preach the gospel of peace
and bring glad tidings of good things.
But they have not all obeyed the gospel.
For Isaiah saith, Lord, who hath believed our report?
So then faith cometh by hearing,
and hearing by the word of God.
As we look at this passage of scripture,
if you're taking notes,
just a couple of thoughts.
Number one, we see that there's a precious promise.
Verse 13 is a precious verse of scripture
that I remember someone sharing with me many years ago.
I remember many years ago,
as I was not certain, of course, of my salvation,
I did not know that heaven was my home.
And someone took a Bible
and showed me how I could know for sure
that heaven was my home.
And I remember that eventually
he got into Romans 10 in verse number 13.
And I can't tell you how many times over the years
I've had the opportunity to speak with people
about the gospel and to share the gospel
of the Lord Jesus Christ with individuals,
with groups of people in preaching services
and so on and so forth,
and use this verse of scripture to say to them,
for whosoever, and I kind of pause there and say,
you know, that means anybody.
We could take and insert our name
into that verse of scripture.
And we can understand that the Bible
gives this precious promise,
for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord
shall be saved.
Man, I hope you never get over this precious promise
of Romans 10 in verse number 13.
The reality this evening is that God gives us a promise.
He does not say that you might be saved.
He does not say that you could be saved.
He says that you shall be saved.
The reality this evening is that God is not a man
that he should lie, amen.
Titus says it this way.
In Titus chapter number one,
it's a precious truth that God gives us.
In verse number three,
but hath in due times manifested his word
through preaching, which is committed unto me
according to the commandment of our Savior,
to God our Savior.
In verse number two, in hope of eternal life,
which God that cannot lie promised before the world began.
God can't lie.
God said, for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord
shall be saved.
That's a precious promise.
We can stand with authority.
You ever talk to somebody that's doubted their salvation?
I have.
Maybe you at some point in your life
have doubted your salvation.
And I do not minimize when someone doubts their salvation.
I understand the seriousness of it.
I understand the complication that someone deals with
when they have that doubt.
I understand how the enemy works and uses doubt
to really hinder the effectiveness of the child of God.
Why?
Because if you're doubting your salvation,
if you're not confident and certain of your own security,
your own salvation,
you're gonna have a hard time telling other people
how they can be saved.
Because you yourself are doubting and you're struggling
and you're not certain.
And we find that many,
it is a tool that the enemy uses regularly from his toolbox
in the lives of God's people
is to cause them to doubt their salvation.
And I do not minimize those that would struggle with.
With that, there's a number of verses that God gives us that teach eternal security very
clearly and plainly and we rejoice in them.
And I've often said to people, listen, either you didn't call or you don't believe God.
And really it just boils down to that because God said, for whosoever shall call upon the
name of the Lord shall be saved.
God is not a man that he should lie.
God always does what he says he will do.
And if you called on him, believing on him, then he saved you.
The Bible says, my sheep hear my voice and I know them and I give unto them eternal life
and they shall never perish.
Isn't that precious in John 10?
We find in the book of 2 Peter, the Bible says that we're kept by the power of God in
the first chapter and we have an inheritance that's incorruptible, it's undefiled, it
fadeth not away.
It is reserved in heaven for us.
Hallelujah.
It's a precious promise that God gives us in Romans 10 and verse number 13.
But I want you to see not only the precious promise, but we see four piercing questions.
Number two this evening, four piercing questions.
I'm going to deal with them in reverse order tonight.
I'm going to begin with the question that is asked in verse 15 and then we'll go back
and answer the questions in verse 14.
We've read it already this evening from verse 13 through 17, but if we look at these four
piercing questions, I want you to notice how verse number 15 begins.
The Bible says, and how shall they preach except they be sent?
We have an opportunity to support missions and to be involved in world missions.
What we're doing is we're investing in, we're giving to missionaries so that they can be
sent to the foreign field.
They're being sent with a mission.
They're being sent with a purpose.
We are very careful as we vet missionaries and have an understanding of what their ministry
plans are.
I get phone calls and emails regularly from missionaries that never come and present their
ministry to our church.
Why?
Because they're not doing what I believe biblically missions that we would support are to be doing.
And so we find that there's a process that we go through in vetting missionaries so that
we can understand that this is, we're investing in, we're giving so that they can be sent.
Do you know there's a number of countries around the world that as a missionary family,
if you were to go to that country, first of all, there's a lot of process that you have
to go through, but many of them require that you would be able to show them financially
that you can enter into that country and not take of the resources of that country.
You're not, not just that you're going to get handouts, but you're not even going to
go and get a job in that country because they want a national from their country to be able
to have that job.
They don't want you coming and taking their jobs.
That's regular around the world.
I know it's not like that in America, but it's like that around the world.
It really is.
And here's what I say.
These missionaries, they can't go if they don't have finances.
God places a call on their life.
They surrender to that call.
We read in Isaiah where God says, who will go for us?
And Isaiah says, here am I, Lord, send me.
And we have missionaries that are saying, I've answered the call, I'm ready to be sent,
and they need resources.
How shall they preach except they be sent?
The model that we have adopted in our independent Baptist churches is that these missionaries
receive support from a number of churches, often somewhere to 80 to 100 different supporting
churches.
They travel on deputation, they present their ministry, a church like ours votes to pick
them up for support.
And we have one piece of the pie that gets the missionary to the field.
How shall they preach except they be sent?
Notice in verse number 14, the Bible begins to ask these questions, of course, leading
back to the promise, that precious promise of verse 13.
But the last question in verse 14, the first that we'll deal with, is this, how shall they
hear without a preacher?
I don't know if you've ever been in a place, I don't know if you've ever been aware of
someone that's been in a place where there's no gospel presence.
In other words, there's a place that is void of Bible preaching, a place where there's
no gospel message that's being proclaimed.
There's no church, there's no missionary, it's a dark place.
There are places like that around the world.
And we find that the Bible says, how shall they hear without a preacher?
How shall they preach except they be sent?
So we want to send the preachers, why?
Because how shall they hear without a preacher?
If we never take the important step of verse number 15 of sending a missionary, a preacher,
then the person that's in that place that is void of the gospel, that is dark, that
has no presence of a church or a missionary, how are they going to hear?
You know, it's amazing to me how many places around the world do not have a true gospel
witness but, oh, there are so many false teachers in those places.
It's heartbreaking.
The cults that we're familiar with, often you can find them almost anywhere in the world.
I remember going to villages while I was in Mexico.
My brother Lacey Wheeler would say, as we'd go to a particular village, now as far as
we know, as far as any missionary here in Mexico that I'm a friend with, that I've talked
to, as far as we know, there's never been a church that preaches the gospel in these
particular villages.
Hundreds, thousands of people that do not have an opportunity to hear because there's
no preacher.
I showed you pictures.
I could still show them this evening if you had interest in seeing them, but I showed
you in a particular village, El Rodeo was the name of the village that we went to, and
in that particular village there was no gospel presence but there was a Coca-Cola distribution
plant.
And I had remembered reading years ago at the time the CEO of Coca-Cola made the statement
that he had a vision that every living soul on the planet Earth would know the refreshing
taste of a Coca-Cola.
That was the vision of the CEO of Coca-Cola.
I saw it in print form.
It's probably 25 years ago at this point that I read that.
When I got to that village, I saw firsthand how there's no gospel presence but there's
Coca-Cola.
Isn't that sad?
How shall they hear without a preacher?
Second question in verse number 14, going of course backwards again, it says here, how
shall they believe in Him of whom they have not heard?
Well obviously you can't believe in Him of whom you've not heard.
How shall you hear without a preacher?
But if belief is necessary and there's no way, how can you believe in Him of whom you've
not heard?
And verse 14 says this, how then shall they call on Him in whom they have not believed?
As we look at the precious promise of verse 13 and we think about these four piercing
questions of verses 14 and 15, we find that the Bible says, for whosoever shall call upon
the name of the Lord shall be saved.
But then the Bible says, how shall they call, how then shall they call on Him in whom they
have not believed?
How shall they believe in Him of whom they have not heard?
And how shall they hear without a preacher?
How shall they preach except they be sent?
Why missions?
Well because there are billions of people in this world and a large majority of them
are not saved.
It's staggering to think about the number of people in this world that have never even
heard the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ one time.
We used to think that often that was the case of various far-reaching places in the
world.
But you know we're finding it to be more and more common here in the United States
of America.
It's sad to me the number of young people that are growing up that the only reference
that they have to Jesus is as a curse word.
That's shameful.
It's sad.
Verse 17 is a precious verse of scripture, so then faith cometh by hearing and hearing
by the word of God.
Yes, the truth is there in verse 16.
They have not all obeyed the gospel.
Have you found it to be so?
Not everyone's going to hear the gospel.
Not everyone's going to believe.
There are people that reject.
We just move on and we just go on to the next place and the next person.
And so as we think about the subject of missions and we understand tonight the focus of our
church and I think every once in a while, yes, we have a missions conference during
the year and we have guest speakers that come and will challenge us, but it's important
for me to be able to cast some vision, if you will, and to help you understand and obviously
those that have been here for a long time, you have a greater understanding.
Those that would be a little newer to the ministry, it's good for you to understand
the emphasis and the importance and why, why missions.
I wonder this evening, if you ever think about how the gospel got to you.
I wonder this evening, you know, it'd be easy for us to say, I think of Holly, she was born
in a Christian home.
Her parents were both saved when she got, when she was born, they were saved.
Her dad was employed at the church, he was an assistant pastor, school administrator
when she was born.
She was born in church, but you know, Holly still had to get saved, she had to be born
again and she got saved, a little girl, what a blessing that is.
My parents weren't saved when I was born.
I was a teenager when my parents got saved.
To God be the glory that there was a man that shared the gospel, that was faithful.
But you know, the reality is that Holly's story might be different than my story, might
be different than your story, but there was someone that brought the gospel to her mom
or to her dad or to her grandparents.
Somewhere along the line, someone brought the gospel to her family.
The same is true in your family.
And I wonder this evening how often we thank God for some faithful people that went before
us so that we could hear the gospel.
They took the baton that was given to them and they were obedient and faithful to take
the gospel message and now here we are and we have the opportunity.
We've been saved by the grace of God.
We say this is a privilege, this is an opportunity for us to be involved in missions.
Yes, actively involved in reaching our Jerusalem as God has placed us here as a lighthouse
to reach this community, but at the very same time to reach the world with the gospel.
It's not going to happen on accident.
We've got to be purposed.
We have to be purposed in doing it.
We have to understand when we fill out that check, when we fill out that offering envelope,
it's not just a, I hope, and I know sometimes I said it already, that so often in 2024,
we don't give out of our poverty, we give out of our abundance.
And I'm not being, I'm not trying to criticize anyone, I'm in the same boat.
What I'm saying this evening is that it's not just a budget line item, can I use that
terminology this evening?
It's an investment in eternity, souls.
How shall they call on Him in whom they've not believed?
How shall they believe in Him of whom they've not heard?
How shall they hear without a preacher?
How shall they preach except they be sent?
God, that He would put us in a position of being the ones doing the sending and not waiting
for someone to come.
Can you imagine?
Can you imagine being somewhere and maybe just looking up and recognizing maybe in a
place where there's polytheistic worldview, all sorts of false gods, but deep down is
the Bible says the heavens declare the glory of God and you look and you, there's got to
be something, someone, but there's no one there to give you the truth.
And I'm thankful that God's allowed us to be on this side of the equation, if I could
use that terminology, but we must recognize how indebted we are to give the gospel to
a lost and dying world and to be involved in world missions.
I love the fact that the children sang this morning.
They quoted Romans 1 in verse 16, for I'm not ashamed of the gospel of Christ.
If you look in the context in verse 14 and 15, before you get to verse 16, there's three
statements that Paul makes.
He says I am ready in verse 16, but he also says I am, or I'm not ashamed in verse 16,
but he says I am ready and I am debtor.
I am debtor.
Paul understood the responsibility that God had given him.
They sang that song and they talked about yellow and that crayon box, and yellow represents
the Christian.
Some of these little kids helped me.
What does it represent?
The Christian who is what?
Afraid or ashamed to tell.
I love how they got quiet there on that last little stanza repeat of the chorus and challenged
us a, don't be, don't be a Christian that's yellow, that's ashamed.
Why missions?
A mission is a heartbeat of God, it's the lifeblood of any local church.
You kill missions, really you kind of lose your whole focus.
I've heard preachers say finances are tight, we need to get rid of our missionaries.
I say that is such a wrong perspective.
I heard a missionary say once that their pastor said finances are tight, we better pick up
a new missionary, and I say I like it.
Why?
Because you're doing what God wants you to do, you're proving God, and I'm thankful that
God's given us the opportunity to be involved in world missions.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the privilege of being able to serve you.
And thank you for those that have gone before us that have faithfully proclaimed the gospel
message, those that brought the gospel to us personally or to our families.
God I pray that you'd help us to have our focus aligned biblically.
Lord, that we would give, that we'd pray, that we'd be involved.
Lord I pray that you'd just do a work in our lives.
Encourage us, challenge us.
We'll give you the glory for every decision that's made.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.