and verse number 9, and we'll plan to go through the end of the chapter this evening.
And let me just read a couple of verses for you, and then we'll get into the message this evening.
Revelation chapter 1, beginning in verse number 9,
I, John, who also am your brother and companion in tribulation and in the kingdom and patience of Jesus Christ,
was in the isle that is called Patmos, for the word of God and for the testimony of Jesus Christ.
I was in the Spirit on the Lord's day, and heard behind me a great voice, as of a trumpet,
saying, I am Alpha and Omega, the first and the last, and what thou seest, write in a book,
and send it unto the seven churches which are in Asia, unto Ephesus, and unto Smyrna, and unto Pergamos,
and unto Thyatira, and unto Sardis, and unto Philadelphia, and unto Laodicea.
And I turned to see the voice that spake with me, and being turned, I saw seven golden candlesticks.
And in the midst of the seven candlesticks, one like unto the Son of Man,
clothed with a garment down to the foot, and gird about the paps with a golden girdle.
His head and his hairs were white like wool, as white as snow, and his eyes were as a flame of fire,
and his feet like unto fine brass, as if they burned in a furnace, and his voice as the sound of many waters.
And he had in his right hand seven stars, and out of his mouth went a sharp two-edged sword,
and his countenance was as the sun shineth in his strength.
And when I saw him, I fell at his feet as dead.
And he laid his right hand upon me, saying unto me, Fear not, I am the first and the last.
I am he that liveth and was dead, and behold, I am alive forevermore. Amen.
And have the keys of hell and of death.
Write the things which thou hast seen, and the things which are, and the things which shall be hereafter.
The mystery of the seven stars, which thou sawest in my right hand, and the seven golden candlesticks.
The seven stars are the angels of the seven churches, and the seven candlesticks which thou sawest are the seven churches.
To begin Revelation, we find that God provides us with a glorious picture of our wonderful Savior.
We're reminded in this opening chapter to this book of Revelation of who he is, and what he has done, and what he is going to do.
We find that in the midst of all of our difficulties and all that we're facing in life,
just as these original recipients were dealing with great adversity and persecution,
that we are reminded in these opening verses of Revelation 1, as we preached last week,
get your eyes on Jesus.
And it's so easy to get our eyes on other things.
It's so easy to become distracted.
It's so easy to become overwhelmed with the adversity and the opposition that we face in life.
But we must be disciplined to keep our eyes on Jesus, the author and finisher of our faith.
We read and we studied last week in verses 4 through 8,
and I handled that passage of Scripture and gave the charge that we would get our eyes on Jesus.
And as we look at this portion this evening, we find that John heard him, and then John saw him.
We read in verse number 10, where the Bible says that he heard behind me a great voice,
and in verse number 17, and when I saw him.
We begin to think about this portion of Scripture, and we find that unlike really any other book of the Bible,
we have for us in verse 19 of chapter number 1, an outline for the entire book.
And we find that he tells us in verse 19, right, the things which thou hast seen,
and that's the first part, the first division, if you will, if you're going to outline this book,
and that covers chapter number 1.
And then he says this, and the things which are,
and we find that those things which are are going to cover chapters 2 and 3,
dealing with the letters that are going to be written to the seven churches in Asian.
And we find that that second section is chapter 2 and 3, things which are,
and then verse 19 ends this way, and the things which shall be hereafter.
And we find that that's the third division of the book,
and it begins in chapter number 4 and ends in chapter 22 at the conclusion of the book.
And it's so wonderful to see that God has given to us an outline for the book,
but he also gave us in chapter 4 and verse number 1 that clear distinction
with regard to the division between the things which thou hast seen,
the things which are, and the things which shall be hereafter.
For we find in Revelation 4 and verse 1, the Bible says,
After this I looked, and behold, a door was opened in heaven,
and the first voice which I heard was as it were of a trumpet talking with me,
which said, Come up hither.
Notice, and I will show thee things which must be hereafter.
And so we find that that third division that is mentioned in verse 19 of chapter 1
covers chapters 4 through 22.
And as we look at the text of Scripture before us this evening,
and beginning in verse 9 and going through the rest of chapter number 1,
I'm going to title the message, if you've seen in the bulletin already,
John saw him.
And I'm thankful that one day I will see him as well.
Isn't that an awesome truth?
We find that the Bible teaches us, we sing songs about seeing him face to face,
and what a joy to know that one day, if you're saved by the grace of God,
that you will see your Savior.
Let me remind you of what John said in 1 John chapter number 3.
The Bible says this in verse number 2,
Beloved, now are we the sons of God, and it doth not yet appear what we shall be,
but we know that when he shall appear, we shall be like him,
for we shall, notice, see him as he is.
Can I tell you that John was that disciple that when he writes the Gospel of John,
he always refers to himself in the third person.
We find that often he will refer to himself as the disciple whom Christ loved.
And we find that he had that close relationship with the Lord Jesus Christ.
Yes, he was in that inner circle, but we find often that John had that relationship,
that closeness with the Lord Jesus Christ.
But now in Revelation chapter 1, when John sees Jesus in this passage of Scripture,
he sees him unlike he saw him during his earthly ministry.
He sees him in his glory, and God gives us a glimpse of this vision.
And I'm so thankful that one day, and I believe that the day is quickly approaching,
that we will hear the trumpet of the Lord sound, and we will be raptured out of here,
and we will see our Savior face to face.
Can I tell you that that truth is a comforting truth, but it also is a sobering truth.
Because when we see him, when that trumpet sounds,
and time shall be no more, then only what's done for Christ is really going to matter.
And the reality is that we look forward with great anticipation and excitement
to that day when the trumpet sounds and we see our Savior face to face,
but we must understand that it's important that we are busy now doing the work that he's called us to do.
As we study this first chapter of the book of Revelation,
notice with me in verses 9 and 10, number one this evening,
I want you to notice how John is identified.
The Bible says, I, John, who also am your brother.
And we find that it begins as he's writing here.
Remember, John is going to write to these that are facing great adversity and persecution.
And we find that he's writing to these suffering believers,
and he's trying to encourage them to get their eyes on Jesus,
to understand that though the wicked emperor is ruling,
and though you're facing great adversity,
that our God rules and reigns, and he's on his throne, and he has a plan.
And again, the idea of the book of Revelation,
our approach cannot simply be to try to satisfy our thoughts with regard to a timeline,
but we're to see our Savior in his rightful place.
And these suffering saints that John is writing to,
these that have been dealing with great adversity,
John says, I am your brother.
And I want you to just pause for a moment and think about the relationship
that we have as brothers and sisters in Christ.
And I want you to understand that as John is writing to these that are suffering greatly,
he identifies with them.
He says, I am your brother.
What makes him a brother is that he too has been saved by the blood of Christ,
and he is a Christian.
We are the sons of God.
Remember, John chapter number 1,
but as many as received him in verse number 12,
to them gave he power to become the sons of God,
even to them that believe on his name.
So often we refer to one another as brother or sister,
and it's not because we have the same biological parents,
it's because we've been saved by the grace of God,
and we're in the family of God.
And that is a precious truth of New Testament Christianity,
and I'm so thankful for it.
But John goes on to say this,
not only does he say that I'm your brother,
but he says, and companion.
in tribulation.
John understood that these, that he was writing to,
that they were suffering,
that they were dealing with this adversity,
but he himself was also suffering
and he's able to write to them
and say that I'm your brother,
but I'm also your companion in tribulation.
I understand what it is to face the hardships
and the difficulties.
I understand what it is to stand for Christ
in an evil, wicked day.
I understand how it is to try to live for Jesus
in the midst of all that's taking place.
He says, I'm a companion in tribulation.
I'm so thankful as you think about the apostle Paul
and we mentioned as we've studied
through 1st and 2nd Timothy this year,
that so often as he's encouraging Timothy
with regard to how he is to live his Christian life,
that Paul himself is an example of doing the very things
that he encourages Timothy to do.
Paul says that, listen, he suffered.
You're going to suffer.
He faced difficulty.
You read the book of Acts
and you read the missionary journeys
and you find that time and time again,
the apostle Paul faced great adversity
and great tribulation and great difficulty,
but what did he do?
He kept on preaching.
He kept on going.
He kept on serving the Lord.
And John says to these hurting that are suffering greatly,
he says, I'm your brother
and I'm your companion in tribulation.
And I believe that that introduction
and how John is identified in verse number nine
helps us to understand that there would be this bond
with regard to those that are receiving the letter
and the information.
It would help them to understand
as John has introduced this way,
understand why the cause for which he is suffering,
the cause for which he's facing tribulation.
In verse number nine, it says,
in the kingdom and patience of Jesus Christ,
notice was in the aisle that is called Patmos.
Why was he there?
He was sent there really in a difficult place,
hard labor that he would be sentenced to.
And basically it was to make his life miserable.
And he was sent there.
Notice the Bible says for the word of God
and for the testimony of Jesus Christ.
Can I remind you what Peter says
in 1 Peter chapter number four?
If you have a moment to turn back just a few pages
in 1 Peter chapter number four,
I wanna remind you of what Peter tells us about suffering
for the cause of Christ.
I wanna remind you this evening of the disciples
in Acts chapter number five,
after they were beaten and they were threatened,
they departed from that place and they rejoiced.
Why?
Because they were counted worthy to suffer shame
for his namesake.
And we find in 1 Peter chapter four in verse number 12,
the Bible says this,
beloved, think it not strange concerning the fiery trial,
which is to try you as though some strange thing
happened unto you.
Notice, but rejoice in so much as ye are partakers
of Christ's sufferings,
that when his glory shall be revealed,
ye may be glad also with exceeding joy.
If ye be reproached for the name of Christ,
notice this, happy are ye.
We often see that same word translated blessed.
Blessed, happy are ye,
for the spirit of glory and of God resteth upon you.
On their part he is evil speaking of,
but on your part he is glorified.
Notice verse 15, but let none of you suffer as a murderer
or as a thief or as an evildoer or as a busybody
in other man's matters.
In other words, we're not suffering
because of our own wrongdoing,
but like John, as it says in Revelation one
in verse number nine, he was suffering.
He was a companion in tribulation for the word of God
and for the testimony of Jesus Christ.
And therefore he's blessed, he's to be happy.
It was not that he was doing something wicked
and suffering those consequences.
No, he was serving his master.
Verse 16, yet if any man suffer as a Christian,
let him not be ashamed,
but let him glorify God on this behalf.
And it's wonderful.
And I understand you say,
well, I don't want to face persecution.
Neither do I.
But can I tell you that if we suffer for Christ,
if we suffer for the cause of Christ,
I believe that God gives us mercy
and God gives us grace.
And I believe that God will be glorified in
and through that.
Notice in verse number 10, back in Revelation one,
the Bible says, I was in the spirit on the Lord's day.
I want you to just for a moment consider this,
that John says that his physical location
in verse number nine was that he was in the aisle
that is called Patmos.
But we find in verse number 10, he says,
I was in the spirit on the Lord's day.
And I'm thankful that our physical location,
our physical difficulties do not have to define us,
do not have to cause us to live,
listen, under the circumstances that woe is me.
I'm on the aisle that is called Patmos.
I've been exiled out here.
I'm suffering, it's so hard and woe is me.
And this isn't fair.
No, no, he says my physical location
is not going to have victory over the fact
that I can be in the spirit.
Isn't that awesome?
Listen, we cannot allow our circumstances
to dictate our walk with God.
We cannot allow our circumstances
and the difficulties that we face
to cause us to have a pity party
and just go over and just give up and say it's not,
no, no, no, we can still worship God.
And he says, I'm physically in the aisle
that is called Patmos, but spiritually,
I'm in the spirit on the Lord's day.
Now, I do not believe that as we look at this
and there's many people that have debated over this,
I believe that when he says the Lord's day,
he's speaking about Sunday, the first day of the week.
We find that in the Roman Empire,
the first day of the month was often referred to
as Emperor's day, and we find that that phrase,
the Lord's day, was often used by Christians
with regard to Sunday being the day of resurrection
and it being the Lord's day.
In fact, oftentimes today, we still use that terminology,
speaking of Sunday being the Lord's day.
I'm thankful that it's not the Lord's hour,
it's the Lord's day, and we have an opportunity
to be able to serve the Lord and to be used of him.
We find that here in this text of scripture,
when Paul, excuse me, when John mentions
that he's in the aisle, but he's in the spirit,
it reminds me of what Paul said
to the believers at Colossae.
Don't take the time to go there,
I'm just gonna read it very quickly for you,
but in Colossians one and verse number two,
and I want you to notice what Paul says,
to the saints and faithful brethren in Christ,
which are at Colossae.
I'm thankful that I can be in Christ,
but I'm at a particular location.
Tonight, we're in Oakton,
but you know that we're seated in the heavenlies?
It's an awesome truth of God's word.
Listen, tonight, we're citizens
of the United States of America,
but greater than being a citizen
if you're saved tonight, you're a citizen of heaven.
This world is not my home, I'm just passing through,
is what the songwriter said.
Hebrews 11 says this, that we're pilgrims
and we're strangers, and what a joy to know
that though John was exiled to this place
for the word of God and for the testimony of Jesus Christ,
that he was in the Spirit on the Lord's day,
and I want you to notice that as he's in the Spirit
on the Lord's day, the Bible tells us
at the end of verse number 10,
and heard behind me a great voice as of a trumpet.
We know how John is identified.
Now notice how John is instructed,
beginning in verse number 11,
and really containing much of the remainder
of our text this evening.
Notice the voice that he heard in verse 11,
it says, saying, I am Alpha and Omega.
Now remember, we just read last week
in verse number eight of our text of Scripture,
that the Bible says, I am Alpha and Omega
at the beginning and the ending,
saith the Lord, which is and which was
and which is to come, the Almighty.
And now John, as he's there at Patmos,
and he's in the Spirit of the Lord's day,
he hears this voice behind him,
and here's what the voice says,
I am Alpha and Omega, the first and the last.
Notice he says, what thou seest, write in a book,
and send it unto the seven churches which are in Asia.
We'll deal with these churches over the next several weeks
as we deal with chapters two and three,
and deal with each church individually,
and I'll make a few comments about the churches
that are listed at the end of the message
this evening as well, but let's just keep moving
in verse number 12, and see the content
of this vision, and to see how John is instructed.
What a great vision he receives.
He hears this great voice, which identified
as being the Lord, Alpha and Omega,
the beginning, the first, and the last,
is what he says here in verse number 11.
It's in verse number eight that he says
the beginning and the ending.
We find that as we continue, he says in verse number 18,
I am he that liveth and was dead,
and behold, I am alive forevermore, amen,
and have the keys of hell and of death.
We find that he's identified this voice.
that speaks to John, that he hears,
it's identified as being the Lord,
he's eternal, he's immortal, he's almighty,
he has all authority.
And we find that in verse number 12,
a description begins to be unfolded for us
to see what John is hearing and as he looks
and he begins to see, the Bible says,
I turn to see the voice.
Now, think about that just for a moment.
Is that not a natural reaction?
You hear a voice and what do you do?
You turn to see.
And we find that as John hears this voice behind him,
it's a great voice and he hears it saying,
I am Alpha and Omega, in verse 12,
he turns to see the voice.
And the Bible tells us he sees that spake with me
and being turned, notice what he saw,
seven golden candlesticks.
We'll mention that in just a moment
as we look at verse number 20,
but I want you to see specifically in verse 13,
it says, and in the midst of the seven candlesticks,
one like unto the Son of Man.
Notice how he's described for us.
We find that in the midst of these seven golden candlesticks
is the Son of Man, one that's like unto the Son of Man
and he begins to provide this description to us.
The vision is explained in verse number 20
with regard to the golden candlesticks
and we'll look at that in just a few moments,
but just look at the description that God gives us.
In verse number 13, he begins by saying,
clothed with a garment down to the foot.
I want you to think about the Lord Jesus Christ
when he went to the cross of Calvary for you and for me,
he was ripped of his garments.
They gambled for his garments,
but now when John sees him,
the Bible tells us that he sees one
that's in the midst of the seven candlesticks,
one like unto the Son of Man,
clothed with a garment down to the foot.
There's many that have debated what this is
and what it represents,
but I believe that we can understand
that the Lord Jesus Christ is our great high priest
and I believe this evening that we can see in this picture,
in this image of this vision,
the high priestly garments of the Lord Jesus Christ
I'm thankful that Hebrews goes to great lengths
to teach us that we have a great high priest.
I'm thankful for the work of intercession that he's doing.
According to Hebrews seven and verse 25,
he ever liveth to make intercession for us.
I'm thankful that he's given us direct access
to the throne room of heaven
and that he is our great high priest.
We find that it continues and it says this in verse 13,
and girt about the paps with a golden girdle.
Now this would have been something
that would have been very easy for John
to understand the garments and how it's robed.
It's maybe something not very much clear in our minds
because it's not how we dress,
but we find that what this would represent,
this being girt with a golden girdle
would represent that authority.
And I want you to think about the authority
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
Even during his earthly ministry,
when he spoke and when there were crowds that gathered,
many times they would leave that place
and they would say, none spake like this man.
He speaketh as one that has authority.
Can I tell you what he reminded the disciples of
when he gave that great commission?
All power is given unto me in heaven and in earth.
I'm thankful that our God has all authority.
And this being girt with a golden girdle
represents that authority that our God has
that he is robed in this fashion.
In verse number 14, his head and his hairs
were white like wool.
And we find that as we look at that description
in verse number 14, we can see a couple of things.
Number one, the eternality of our God,
the fact that he has no beginning and no ending,
the fact that he introduced in verse number eight
that he's alpha and omega, the beginning and the ending,
and then in verse number 11, I am alpha and omega,
the first and the last, we find that our God is eternal.
I'm thankful that he's outside of time.
See, we are bound by time.
Everything that we do has time constraints, right?
Everything that we do, they're time constraints.
And we understand this evening when we think about
the time constraints that we live with
and that we deal with, that we must rejoice
in knowing that our God is outside of time.
And our God is eternal.
There's some, they've asked me over the years,
I've been asked this question, well, who created God?
No one created God, he is the creator.
In fact, the name Jehovah means the self-existent one.
And I'm so thankful that our God is the eternal God.
And here we find when he talks about his head
and his hairs were white like wool,
it not only reveals to us his eternality,
but it reveals to us his purity, that he's pure.
I'm thankful the Bible says that Jesus,
that he suffered for us, the just for the unjust.
He's completely pure, he's holy and undefiled.
We find that the verse continues in verse number 14,
it says, as white as snow, can you see the description
that is given there, and you see as John is writing,
and I believe that he's going through great lengths
to be able to provide for us exactly what he's seeing
and to give us this description.
He ends verse 14 by saying his eyes were as a flame of fire.
I believe that this really reveals to us two thoughts
with regard to his eyes being as a flame of fire.
Think about his eyes and think about what we perceive
with our eyes, what we see.
And I want you to understand this evening
that when we think about his eyes,
as it's mentioned in verse 14, our God knows all things.
Our God sees all things.
There's nothing that's hidden from our God.
And again, that's a comforting truth,
but it's also a convicting truth
that there's nothing hidden from our God.
And we find that he knows all things,
his eyes, notice, were as a flame of fire.
Not only does he know all things,
but he judges all things.
Fire often would represent judgment.
And you think about the work of purifying
and all that would take place and being tried by fire
and understanding that his eyes,
he knows everything and he judges everything.
There are times in which we can go through life
and we can think, does anyone even know?
Does anyone even see?
Does anyone even care?
We can be assured this evening
that our God sees and he knows and he cares.
We find in verse number 15, as the description continues,
it says that his feet likened to fine brass
as if they burned in a furnace.
You begin to think about his feet being like fine brass
and that judgment.
Listen, Jesus is the judge.
He is the righteous judge.
We understand that as we enter into Revelation 19
and he sets up his millennial kingdom
that he will rule and reign for 1,000 years upon earth.
But we understand that he's the righteous judge
and he's been given that position
and that role of being the judge.
When we begin to think about for us as believers
that we will stand at the bema seat of Christ,
the judgment seat of Christ.
We will stand before him.
We find that 1 Corinthians and 2 Corinthians
both deal with this teaching and this truth
with regard to the judgment seat of Christ
and his feet are likened to fine brass
as if they burned in a furnace.
Notice at the end of verse 15,
and his voice is the sound of many waters.
Again, you would think about the authority
that is being communicated to us
as you think about his voice
being as the sound of many waters.
I mean, it's not a faint voice.
It's not a weak voice.
I mean, the Bible says in verse number 10
that he heard behind me a great voice as of a trumpet
and then it's described at the end of verse 15
as the sound of many waters.
Oftentimes I've been told that I have a strong voice
and I praise the Lord for it.
God gave me that voice.
We had this marriage conference this past week.
We're in this weekend and we're in this conference room
and they had no microphones and that sort of thing
and Holly commented.
She said, well, I guess you didn't really need
a microphone, did you?
And I said, no, I'm perfectly fine.
I could handle it.
The first time I ever preached in this church,
the microphone wasn't on and I thought it was
and someone tried to tell me that the mic wasn't on.
I said, no, I'm pretty sure it is
and then we found out afterwards that it wasn't
and but I think about the voice of God.
It's unlike any voice you've ever heard
and it's a voice that has authority
and it's a voice is the sound of many waters
and he had in verse 16 in his right hand,
the right hand picturing that hand of authority.
It says he had in his right hand seven stars,
that authority and that power of his right hand
and we'll see again in verse number 20
with the vision being explained,
the seven candlesticks and also the seven stars
in just a few moments as we get to verse 20
but notice the middle there, verse 16
and out of his mouth when a sharp two-edged sword.
We obviously see in this verse of Scripture
the reference to the Word of God.
In the reality, listen, the Bible tells us
in Ephesians chapter number six and verse number 17
that we're to take the sword of the Spirit
which is the Word of God.
We find that in Hebrews chapter four and verse number 12,
it says, for the Word of God is quick and powerful
and sharper than a two-edged sword,
piercing even to the dividing asunder of soul and spirit
and of the joints and marrow and as a discerner
of the thoughts and intents of the heart.
When the Bible says the Word of God is quick,
it doesn't mean that it's fast, it means it's alive.
It's a living book.
And I wanna remind you that in Revelation 19,
that the Bible tells us in verse number 11 of Revelation 19
and I saw heaven open and behold a white horse
and he that sat upon him was called faithful and true
and in righteousness he doth judge and make war.
His eyes was a flame of fire and on his head
were many crowns and he had a name written
that no man knew but he himself
and he was clothed with a vesture dipped in blood
and his name is called the Word of God.
The armies which were in heaven followed him
upon white horses clothed in fine linen, white and clean
and out of his mouth goeth, notice, a sharp sword
that with it he should smite the nations
and he shall rule them with a rod of iron
and he treadeth the winepress of the fierceness
and wrath of Almighty God and he hath on his vesture
and his thigh a name written,
King of kings and Lord of lords.
See Jesus when he comes back,
he's coming back as the conquering king, amen.
He's coming back in all of his authority
and all of his power.
We're gonna come back with him in Revelation 19,
he's coming for us and to start the tribulation
and then he's coming with us to end the tribulation
and we're gonna rule and reign with him, amen.
Hallelujah.
And we find that here in Revelation chapter one
in verse 16, he mentions about the Word of God.
Understand that in the scriptures,
that term Word of God is used to reference,
a name for our savior that he is the living Word of God.
The Word was made flesh and dwelt among us,
John one in verse 14.
But we understand that the phrase Word of God
is used in reference to the written Word of God as well.
And I'm thankful that God has given us his Word.
I mentioned this morning that every Word of God is pure.
It's trustworthy, it's dependable.
And I've had people say, well, don't you know
that the Bible contains in it the words of men
when they were not speaking the truth?
Absolutely.
Don't you know that the Bible contains
the words of Satan?
Absolutely.
I've read it countless times.
But if the Word of God isn't pure,
then we wouldn't know that it's a valid, accurate record.
We'd have no idea.
But every Word of God is pure.
If I were standing on trial this evening
before a judge and I was an eyewitness to something
and they said, Mr. Mann, can you please tell us
what so-and-so said?
And if what so-and-so said was a lie,
but I give an accurate testimony,
then my testimony is pure.
Even though the testimony that I'm giving is a lie.
Does that make sense tonight?
And so we find God's given us,
not only is he the living Word,
but he's given us the written Word.
And it says that out of his mouth
went a sharp two-edged sword.
And then notice at the end of verse 16,
it says that his countenance
was as the sun shineth in his strength.
This reveals to me his glory and his sovereignty.
I think about the glory of our God.
The Bible says that his countenance
was as the sun shineth, notice, in his strength.
You ever try to look directly at the sun?
I hope you haven't, it's a bad idea, amen?
But I want you to think about the sun and its strength.
And John says, that's what the countenance says
as the one that was standing in the midst
of the seven candlesticks.
And so John, when he is given this instruction
and we find that he's provided with all of these things,
and again, Jesus says to him in the end of verse number 17,
fear not, I am the first and the last.
Now he had already said that in verse number 11.
He then says, I am he that liveth in verse 18
and was dead, and behold, I am alive forevermore, amen,
and have the keys of hell and of death.
Having the keys gives us the truth of authority.
The one who has the keys has the authority, has the power.
And he has the keys, notice, of hell and of death.
In verse 20, he begins to give us
the explanation of this vision.
It tells us in verse number 20 that the mystery
of the seven stars, which thou sawest in my right hand,
and the seven golden candlesticks.
The seven stars are the angels of the seven churches.
What are the seven churches?
Where does that come from?
Well, if you read in verse number 11, remember,
he says, what thou seest, write in a book
and send it unto the seven churches, which are in Asia.
And so he says that the seven golden candlesticks
that are there, he says, you saw the stars,
which thou sawest in my right hand,
and the seven golden candlesticks.
The seven stars are the angels of the seven churches,
and the seven candlesticks, which thou sawest,
are the seven churches.
There's been much discussion with regard to,
obviously, we understand the candlesticks
are the seven churches, very straightforward.
The stars are the angels of the seven churches.
And I believe that the word angel
often is used as being a messenger.
And that would be the understanding.
I believe that most likely it's the pastor
of those particular churches
that's being represented by those seven stars.
Some have argued that it's not the pastor,
it's maybe just a messenger that is the one given authority
by which to receive the correspondence from John
and so on and so forth.
But I believe that we find here
that as God has given to John this vision,
we're reminded again of the work
that God is doing through the churches.
Remember, he says,
write the things which thou hast seen,
and the things which are.
And those things which are
are what we're gonna read in chapters two and three.
And we find that those are seven literal churches
that are in Asia that John has the responsibility
of being able to send these messages to,
and to be able to give them the instruction.
These churches are local, visible churches.
Notice, if you will, in verse number 11,
the Bible says unto the seven churches which are in Asia.
It does not use the word church singular,
but it uses the word plural
because they're all individual churches.
In their individual locale,
it says unto Ephesus, unto Smyrna,
unto Pergamos, unto Thyatira,
unto Sardis, unto Philadelphia, and unto Laodicea.
And we find that these are all churches in Asia,
Asia Minor, modern-day Turkey
is where these churches were located.
And we find that John would have the responsibility
of writing and sending to these seven churches
the message that the Lord Jesus Christ,
the head of the church, has for each church.
We'll look at those seven churches
and those seven letters over the next couple of weeks,
but I want you to think about a couple of things.
Let me actually touch on this before I deal with that.
If you're taking notes, number three,
notice how John was impacted.
And then we'll get back to just a moment
making an application.
Notice how John, we said this,
how he was given to us, how he was identified,
and then how he was instructed.
Notice how he was impacted by this whole thing.
In verse number 17, the Bible says,
and when I saw him, I fell at his feet as dead.
You know, I've often heard through the years
people say something like this.
When I get to heaven, I'm going to,
and you just kind of fill in the blank.
Can I tell you that I honestly believe
that when we get to heaven, all we're gonna do
is fall at the feet of Jesus.
We're not gonna ask him questions about this, that,
and the other thing, what happened here.
None of that's gonna matter.
It's all gonna be over.
We're gonna fall at his feet.
We're gonna worship him
because he's worthy of our worship.
And we find that John says, when I saw him,
I'm so thankful tonight that I'm gonna see him one day.
If you're saved tonight, you're gonna see him one day.
I hope that motivates you.
I hope that encourages you.
I hope that comforts you.
I hope it convicts you.
You say, pastor, I like the first three things
that you said I hope it does.
I don't know about that convicting thing.
Honestly, it's a convicting thing to know
that I'm gonna see my savior face to face.
It's a comforting thing for sure,
but it's a convicting thing.
But I want you to see the grace and the kindness of our God.
In verse 17, it says, when I saw him,
I fell at his feet as dead,
and he laid his right hand upon me,
saying, fear not, I am the first and the last.
Our God is so great.
How gracious. Our God is so kind.
And even as John fell at his feet as dead,
I can see in this great vision
and all the description that we gave
from verses 13-16 and all the glory
that the Bible says that He laid His right hand upon me.
Isn't that awesome?
To consider the grace and the kindness of our God.
We see how John is impacted.
Let me make application just very quickly this evening.
I believe that there's special insight
that's given to us in this passage of scripture
with regard to the judgment of the Lord Jesus Christ.
I believe that as we look at the outline
that is given in verse 19
and we begin to understand the scriptures
that God has given to us with regard to judgment,
we see the verse number 11,
the churches that are to be addressed.
We find that Jesus is going to,
in Revelation 2 and 3,
those seven churches, those local churches,
they're going to receive letters
that truly are records of the judgment
that God is giving to those churches.
If you read those letters
and we'll study them over the next several weeks,
we find that one thing that is said
to every one of the seven churches,
I know thy works.
And we find that Jesus,
in certain of the letters to the churches,
you know what he does?
He commends the church for what it is that they're doing.
But we find that there's other churches
that even if they're commended for something,
they're also corrected for something.
We find that there are many of the churches
that are given this word of repent.
The judgment has been given
and the God that loves us
and the God who corrects us
and the God who chastens us,
he calls us to change our behavior to repent.
And that judgment is recorded in chapters 2 and 3
of first, the church.
And then we see in chapter number four and following,
really in chapter six and following,
because verses, chapters four and five
give us scenes of heaven.
But beginning in chapter number six,
you know what we see?
We see God's judgment on the world.
On the unbelievers.
On those that rejected him.
And we see God's judgment, his wrath being poured out.
The Bible tells us this in first Peter four
and I wanna close with this thought tonight.
In first Peter chapter four,
we read verses 12 through 16.
I so badly wanted to read verse 17 with it when I was there,
but I knew I was coming back to it
at the end of the message.
In chapter four, verses 12 through 16,
we read about that suffering for the cause of Christ
and being happy, being joyful,
rejoicing that we're able to suffer for the name of Christ.
But we find that in verse 17 of first Peter chapter four,
the Bible says,
for the time has come that judgment must begin
at the house of God.
And if it first begin at us,
what shall the end be of them that obey not
the gospel of God?
In a very different way than in years previous,
this past week, this verse of scripture
has been so heavy on my heart and my mind
in connection with the outline of revelation.
In chapters two and three,
where the Bible records for us
the judgment of these seven churches
and here where this verse of scripture says,
for the time has come that judgment must begin
at the house of God.
And then it says, if it first begin at us,
what shall the end be of them that obey not
the gospel of God?
And you begin reading in chapter number six and following
and you read the judgment of God
and literally the wrath of God
being poured out upon this earth.
When you begin to read the seals as they're open
and the death and the destruction and all of that,
literally there will be billions of people
that will be killed during the tribulation.
And you say, no way, yes way.
It is absolutely overwhelming to read of the judgment,
but it's of those notice that obey not the gospel of God.
I'm so thankful that the gospel came to me.
I'm so thankful that we've been entrusted with the gospel,
but I wanna encourage you tonight to know
that as we see in Revelation chapter number one,
yes, John saw him, he gets this vision,
but he gets this instruction,
write these letters to these churches,
these local assemblies of believers
and these letters contain judgment.
And then after that, beginning in chapter four,
and we get to chapter six,
we begin to see the judgment upon the world.
I don't want those people that I know,
my loved ones, family, friends,
for you I would say coworkers,
my coworker is my wife and she's saved,
but we ought not want anyone to suffer the kind of judgment
that will be suffered beginning in Revelation
chapter number six.
And obviously that's just the beginning of the judgment
because eventually the judgment is contained
in Revelation 20,
where they will be judged for all of eternity.
And it's a sad thing.
This evening I'm thankful to be saved by the grace of God,
to know that the second death has no power over me,
to know that I won't stand
at that great white throne judgment,
to know that my sins have been forgiven.
But can I tell you that for us as a church this evening,
just like those seven churches
that we'll begin studying next Sunday evening,
judgment must first begin at the house of God.
We must have a measure of humility and honesty
and we must listen to what the one who has all power
and authority would say about our local assembly.
We don't have, we're not going to receive a letter
like they did, but we can take the truth of God's word
and seek to apply it in our own lives, our own ministry.
Is God pleased with us?
Is God going to commend us?
Where is it that God's going to correct us?
And where is it that God might say to us, repent?
You've lost your focus.
Ephesus, you left your first love.
And oh, that God would help us
over these next several weeks on Sunday nights,
as we look at these seven churches in chapters two and three
to have a humble approach of what God has for us.
John saw him.
Let me leave you with a positive.
One day you will see him as well.
And what glorious, glorious day that is going to be.
We sing the song, what a day that will be.
And certainly it's going to be a wonderful, wonderful day
when I see my savior face to face.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for your word.
We thank you for the vision that John sees here.
And Lord, as we were encouraged last week
and in the middle of this first chapter
to get our eyes on Jesus, and then John sees you.
And Lord, we know that one day we will see you.
And I pray that you would help us, Lord,
to be found faithful, obediently serving you
and living for you.
I pray that as individuals,
we would live for you and serve you.
I pray that corporately as a church,
that we would live and operate in such a way
that you'd be honored and glorified.
I pray, Father, that you'd help us
to recognize your great power and your great authority,
that we would rejoice in who you are,
that we'd keep our eyes on Jesus.
I pray, God, that you'd work in the moment of invitation.
I pray, Lord, that you'd help us to rejoice in thee.
Lord, help us to obey thee.
And we'll thank you for the work that you'll do.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's gonna play quietly on the piano.
And as she does, the altar is open.