for 2020, and we'll get into the 12th chapter in our next study, and of course that's where
that verse of Scripture is found, Hebrews 12, and verse number 2, looking unto Jesus,
the author and finisher of our faith, and we'll deal with that next week, but as we
look at Hebrews 11 and finish up the chapter, we've seen some amazing things that God has
recorded for us here in Hebrews 11 with regard to those that have gone before us.
Of course we know that as we look at the passage of Scripture and really think about the book
of Hebrews, and we understand the way in which these believers have been instructed,
we find the theme of the book really that Jesus is better, he's superior, he's greater,
and we find that the writer of Hebrews goes through a whole host of things that he deals
with and proves biblically that Christ is superior, that he's better.
We find that there's many Old Testament references in the book of Hebrews that are properly applied
to the person of the Lord Jesus Christ, to Messiah.
And what a joy that is, and what a blessing, and these believers, they were suffering under
some great, intense difficulties, and there were all sorts of things going on, and there
was a real draw to return to Judaism, and perhaps that would just take care of some
of the problems that they had encountered and that they were enduring, and yet we know
that the book, the idea, is because Christ is superior, why would you go back?
The law having a shadow of good things to come, it certainly is appropriate, it's a
picture, it's a pattern, but we have the substance, the person of the Lord Jesus Christ has come
and he's completed the work, and what a joy that is.
And we find that these believers have been encouraged to go on, to continue, to live
by faith.
It's interesting that at the end of Hebrews chapter number 10, that he quotes that Old
Testament truth that we find quoted many times here in the New Testament, the just shall
live by faith.
He says that this interesting truth in verse number 39 of Hebrews 10, we are not of them
who draw back unto perdition, no, we go on, we go forward, we live by faith.
We see, if you would look at the end of Hebrews chapter number 10 and the beginning of Hebrews
chapter number 12, and you really could look at Hebrews chapter 11 as being a parenthetical,
if you will, to say, listen, we go on by faith, let us run our race, but let me take a moment
to remind you of all of those that have gone before us who have lived by faith.
And what a joy and what a blessing to be encouraged by these Old Testament accounts.
It's interesting, as we've worked our way through Hebrews chapter 11, especially in
the last two Sunday morning services, we've seen that there's been really a sufficient
amount of Scripture that has been given.
You think about, of course, the greatest amount of Scripture in this passage that is given
to an individual is that of Abraham, and we read about those things.
And then we come to our text this morning, and the writer says in verse number 32, and
what shall I say more, or what shall I more say?
For the time would fail me to tell of Gideon, of Barak, of Samson, of Jephthah, of David
also, and Samuel of the prophets.
Now, we're going to look at the whole text, but I want you to skip over and look at verse
number 39.
It says, and these all, having obtained a good report through faith, received not the
promise.
I want to preach a message this morning that I've simply entitled from verse number 39,
a good report through faith.
Now you'll recall with me as we began studying this portion of Scripture, that in Hebrews
11, in verse number 1, the Bible says, now faith is the substance of things hoped for,
the evidence of things not seen.
And then it tells us this, for by it, by what?
By faith, the elders obtained a good report.
And as we get to the end of the chapter, we are reminded, and these all, having obtained
a good report through faith.
And as we look at this passage of Scripture, and we think about these names that are provided
to us really in rapid succession, it causes our mind to race back to those Old Testament
events that are being referenced.
And we find there are a number of names given in verse number 32 and verses 33, down really
through verse number 37, 38.
You begin to see all of these events that are being referenced, just quick references
and in rapid succession.
And as we would have an understanding of the Old Testament, we have some familiarity with
the Word of God, our mind races back to those events that are mentioned, back to the Old
Testament account.
Now think about the original recipients to the book of Hebrews, and how well they would
have been acquainted with the Old Testament.
And now as these names and these events are being provided to these believers in rapid
succession, no doubt their mind is going back to all of those things that they were
very familiar with.
And as we look at the passage of Scripture, I believe that at least two important principles
are being communicated to us this morning.
The first of these two important principles would be this, in every era of human history,
there are those that believe the Lord and lived by faith.
We begin to look at Hebrews chapter 11, and we find that this is written to the believers
in the first century, and we find that we began Hebrews 11 all the way back in creation.
And then we begin to deal with, as we looked at the portion of Scripture about the faith
of Abel, and the faith of Enoch, and the faith of Noah, and we go through human history,
we begin at creation in verse number 3, and we end up, notice at the end of verse number
32, he says, in Samuel and of the prophets.
And you think about that, and of the prophets, and you just begin to think about all of the
great prophets of God that ministered, that are recorded in the Old Testament, and for
these believers of the first century, really what we're finding is that in every era, there
were those that believed God and lived by faith.
If we were to look this morning at the last 2,000 years of human history, and we were
to dig in, and we were beginning to examine church history, we would begin that we could
easily identify that there are people all throughout history that believed God and lived
by faith.
Now, it's not recorded for us here in the words of Scripture, because the canon of Scripture
was closed there, of course, several centuries ago, many centuries ago, and we find here
though that this is a great principle that these believers are being confronted with.
There's always been people that believed God.
Will you believe God?
There have always been people that have lived by faith.
Will you live by faith?
And then we find that a second principle that I believe that is being communicated here
in this portion of Scripture is this, living by faith is not synonymous with having no
problems.
Amen?
Have you found it to be so?
The reality is that at times in our lives, when we think about the great heroes of the
faith, when we think about those that live by faith, we think that they have a life void
of problem.
The reality is that the portion of Scripture proves otherwise, and we find that as we would
begin to examine history, biblical history, and then even contemporary history, we would
find that those that live by faith, many times, yes, we get to see God work miraculously,
and we get to see the great victories, but there are problems that we encounter.
There are difficulties that we endure, but I want you to understand that even in those
moments it's still by faith.
And the reality is that we understand, biblically speaking, that God has a different definition
for success than the world does.
The world thinks of success in certain terms of what you have, what your possessions are,
what your position is, what your bank account looks like, all of those types of things,
and there are those that would look at people with all of these pleasures and possessions
and position, and the world would say, oh, they're so successful.
But we find that God says to Joshua, in Joshua chapter number one, with regard to having
good success, that it was resulted in the reality that you believe the Word of God,
that this book of the law shall not depart out of thy mouth.
Thou shalt meditate therein day and night, that thou mayest observe to do according to
all that is written therein, then thou shalt have good success, amen?
And your way will be prosperous.
And we begin to think about that principle in Joshua 1 and verse number 8, and I'm so
thankful that God's given us a Bible, and I'm so thankful that He's given us the truth
with regard to how to please Him.
We looked at that great truth in verse number 6 of this great chapter.
But without faith, it is impossible to please Him, for he that cometh to God must believe
that He is, and that He is a rewarder of them that diligently seek Him.
And God has given us the truth all the way back in the Old Testament, and it's been repeated
in the New Testament, the just shall live by faith.
He asks the question, when the people of God have been delivered from the bondage of Egypt,
when they've been able to see the power of God through all of the plagues, and His provision
and His leadership, and the crossing of the Red Sea.
And yet, when the spies go,
they come back and ten of them say,
listen, the land, there are giants there
and it's well fortified and we're not able.
Joshua and Caleb, they say if God is for us,
since God is with us,
since God has promised us,
we can't deny any of what they said
about the things that we saw in the land,
but we know that our God is able.
But the ten, that evil report,
influenced the whole congregation
and God says this to Moses,
how long ere it be that my people believe me?
And still today, all of these years later,
we ask the question, will we believe God?
Because faith is simply taking God at His word.
Believing what God said.
Let's dig into the passage.
If you're taking notes this morning,
notice with me, number one, the accomplishments.
Notice the accomplishments.
Hebrews 11, v. 32 through the very first phrase
of v. 35, there's a great list
that is provided to us.
The Bible says this,
and what shall I more say?
For the time would fail me to tell of Gideon,
of Barak, and of Samson, of Jephthah,
of David also, and Samuel, and the prophets.
And then notice these accomplishments
in v. 33.
Who through faith subdued kingdoms,
wrought righteousness,
obtained promises,
stopped the mouths of lions,
quenched the violence of fire,
escaped the edge of the sword,
out of weakness were made strong,
waxed valiant in fight,
turned to flight the armies of the aliens.
The first section of v. 35,
women received their dead,
raised to life again.
Then we begin to read those verses of Scripture
and we begin to see the accomplishments.
We begin to see what was wrought through faith
and how God was working supernaturally.
Why? Because His people believed Him.
And they believed what God said.
That He would do what He said.
And we see their great accomplishments.
No doubt as we read the names of the people
in v. 32, we are reminded of some of the great victories
that are represented by these names.
We're reminded of some of the most familiar
Bible accounts in all of the Word of God.
We're reminded of some of those right here in this list
that is provided to us in v. 32.
Notice Gideon.
What do you think?
I mean, the little kids in Sunday school,
they've been learning about Gideon
from the youngest of age.
You mean to think about Gideon
and what do we know about Gideon
when we know that he had an army?
First of all, he was the youngest
and he was the least and God, the angel of the Lord
comes and calls him a mighty man of valor.
And Gideon thinks he's got the wrong guy.
You've come to the wrong place.
And God, through a series of events,
encourages Gideon and builds his faith.
See, in the beginning, Gideon didn't have enough faith
to believe that they would be able to have this victory.
They were outnumbered.
But God, from His perspective,
He says, actually you have too many.
What do you mean I have too many?
I mean, we're outnumbered like four to one.
Yeah, yeah, but that's too many
because if I give you the victory,
then you're gonna think that it was
because of your own power.
And all the way down to just 300 men,
through a series of events, faith builders.
We're familiar with Gideon.
Barak, Jephthah, Samson, I put them out of order there.
David also, isn't that interesting?
Just to say, and David also.
Now, what is your mind?
I mean, when you think about David and I don't have time,
I'm gonna say the same thing that the writer of Hebrews said
what shall I more say for the time
would fail me to tell, right?
I mean, we can't dig into all of this,
but we find the great record that is provided
in the way in which the people of God,
not only in the first century,
but even still because it's been preserved
in the Word of God.
For us this morning, we're reminded
that people live by faith.
You think about David.
You think about the great victories.
You think about probably one of the first things
that comes to many people's minds
if you were to list Bible characters and say,
what's the first thing that comes to your mind?
You list Bible characters,
you're gonna get a variety of answers.
And with David, no doubt,
someone is gonna say David and Goliath.
Someone will, maybe many will.
You see the faith of David.
Goliath says, I'm gonna kill you.
And David says, the battle is the Lord's.
And he goes in faith believing that God can and God will.
He said, is there not a cause?
When Saul and all of the other soldiers were fearful
when Goliath would make himself known,
and we find that David had faith.
He just believed God.
Saul says, okay, I'm gonna let you go,
but you need to have some armor.
You need to have these things.
And of course, he told him before that,
that you can't go fight against them
because you're just a youth
and this man is a man of war from his youth.
What does David do?
He remembers what God has done.
Right?
There's a bear.
Begins to reflect upon what God did
and showing His power.
And he says, the same God who wrought victory then,
He is able in this situation.
We go through, we see the Samuel and the prophets
and we begin to think about these events
that are mentioned.
And you think about the way in which
they subdued kingdoms,
the victories of the Old Testament
that you can read of,
wrought righteousness,
the great revivals that you can read of in Judah's history,
obtained promises,
stopped the mouths of lions.
What do you think about when you read those words?
Right?
What do you think of?
Daniel, right?
Again, one of those very familiar Bible accounts, right?
And remember, Darius, he can't even sleep, right?
I mean, he's all kinds of messed up
because Daniel has to go into the den of lions.
And he knew that those lions,
I mean, they purposed,
they understood what the whole process was
and those lions are ready to destroy and devour.
And in fact, after Daniel is delivered,
those accusers and their families are cast in
and before they even touch the ground,
they're devoured.
But he comes to that den that morning
after a sleepless night.
And he says,
is your God that you serve continually able to deliver thee?
Yes.
We sing the song,
He is able to deliver thee.
We see obvious reference to Daniel in chapter number six.
We look at the passage and we see that he continues,
quenched the violence of fire.
What do you think about?
Again, you think about the book of Daniel,
Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, right?
Remember Nebuchadnezzar with all of his power
and all of his might in the world empire at that time,
the Babylonian kingdom.
And he says,
who is that God that will deliver you out of my hand?
I mean, he has power.
He says, I can't believe that you're not gonna bow.
In fact, I'm gonna give you another opportunity.
We'll play the music just for you.
And they said,
we're not gonna bow.
We're just not gonna bow.
And they believe that their God was able.
And they said,
and if not,
we're still not gonna bow.
Amen?
And what happens?
He cast them in.
We understand that the ones who cast in
these three Hebrew children,
they died because the furnace was so heated.
And they're cast in bound.
And Nebuchadnezzar says,
just a little while,
he's a stone, the Bible says.
And he looks and he says,
hey guys, how many did we throw in there?
Three.
He says, well, I see four.
And they're walking around.
They turn down the fire,
get them out.
They don't even have the smell of fire.
That's our God.
Armando, I've had fires at your house.
We've gone and had a fire,
a campfire.
I've never left from a campfire
not smelling like smoke.
And I've never been in the fire.
Amen?
I've been close to the fire,
but I've never been in the fire,
but I've never left without smelling like smoke.
These boys went into the fiery furnace.
You keep going,
you see escape the edge of the sword.
Out of weakness were made strong.
Wax valiant in fight.
Turn to flight,
the armies of the aliens.
Of course,
that's not talking about extraterrestrial aliens
and all that sort of thing.
That are those that are not the Hebrews.
And so please understand that.
Verse 35,
women received their dead raised to life again.
What do you think about?
There are two examples.
One with Elijah,
one with Elisha.
Right?
The woman at Zarephath,
the widow of Zarephath,
and the Shunammite.
And you look at those two examples,
you see the way in which they were raised again.
And we look at this passage of Scripture
and we notice their accomplishments.
And I would say this,
as I think of their accomplishments,
I look at it as being this.
Faith on the mountaintop.
I mean,
seeing God work
and experiencing the great victories
and the accomplishments
and knowing that our God is able.
And then we continue with the text of Scripture.
And again,
as I mentioned by way of introduction,
the two principles that are being communicated.
One,
that there's always been a group of people
that have lived by faith
and believed the Lord.
Number two, it's not synonymous.
To live by faith is not synonymous
with having no problems.
And we get to our second point this morning.
I noticed the accomplishments,
and now I notice the adversities.
The adversities.
Notice with me as we continue reading in v. 35
and really go down through v. 38.
It says this and others.
I want you to take note of that phrase others.
It's used twice in our passage.
You'll see it again in v. 36.
And the names of these aren't given.
We can of course look back historically
and see some of who would be referenced
with these particular descriptive terms.
But it says and others were tortured.
Notice what it says, not accepting deliverance.
You understand there were certain times
throughout the history of mankind,
those that believed God,
that they suffered great affliction,
that they were tortured.
But the ones that were doing the torturing
offered them deliverance
if they would just stop living for God.
Stop preaching Christ.
Stop and we'll leave you alone.
You'll be delivered.
John Bunyan, by the way, had the opportunity.
We're told of John Bunyan
that when he was in prison,
that he of course was illegally preaching
because it was not sanctioned
by the state church.
And he's preaching.
Why couldn't he be part of the state church?
Because it didn't line up with the Word of God.
And he's preaching and he's in prison.
And it's understood through history
that just without the side of the bars of the prison,
he could have signed his own release
if he would just agree to no longer preach.
And he stayed in prison.
Not accepting deliverance.
I understand that John Bunyan's
someone spoken of here.
He lived many years later.
But you understand that there are those
that lived by faith.
That dealt with great adversities.
The end of v. 35,
that they might obtain a better resurrection.
And others, we see that word again,
and others had trial of cruel mockings
and scourgings.
Yay?
Moreover, of bonds and imprisonment.
They were stoned.
They were sawn asunder.
Were tempted.
Were slain with the sword.
They wandered about in sheepskins and goatskins,
being destitute, afflicted, tormented.
Of whom the world was not worthy.
They wandered in deserts and in mountains
and in dens and caves of the earth.
Remember, as we studied several weeks ago,
that the Bible told us in v. 16,
but now they desire a better country,
that is in heavenly,
wherefore God is not ashamed to be called their God,
for He hath prepared for them a city.
And we notice that at the end of v. 13,
it says that they confess that they were
strangers and pilgrims on the earth.
We confess this morning,
this world is not my home.
I'm just a passing through.
I'm a stranger and a pilgrim.
I'm not home, but I'm going home.
I don't know when I'm going to get there.
But I know that there's one of two ways
that I'm going to get there.
The trumpet of the Lord's going to sound
and the rapture will take place
and I will forevermore be with my Lord and Savior.
Or, I will cross the door of death
and to be absent from the body
is to be present with the Lord.
We're pilgrims and strangers.
It tells us in v. 38,
they wandered in deserts and in mountains
and in dens and caves of the earth.
And we begin to look at this list
and we begin to think about the adversities
that these individuals would face.
My mind races back.
I'm just going to use a couple of illustrations.
Turn over to 2 Chronicles if you will.
And look at chapter 16.
We're going to begin there.
I'm just going to give you three references this morning
of some of those that were faithful
and lived by faith
and did the work of God,
but they suffered.
They dealt with adversity.
By the way, if you read the testimony
of the Apostle Paul,
he suffered greatly, did he not?
He suffered greatly.
I think about the very first missionary journey
of the Apostle Paul.
He gets in every city that he goes to.
Iconium, Lyster, Derbe, Antioch, and Pisidia.
All four of those places that he goes to
in that first missionary journey.
He suffers the same thing.
He deals with adversity.
But yet, he gets up and goes to the next place
and preaches.
He understands that the work that he's doing
he was called of the Lord to do it.
In 2 Chronicles 16, you're there.
Look in v. 10 to give you just kind of
the understanding.
Let me back up and look in v. 7.
This is a situation here between a man of God,
a seer, a prophet, and Asa the king.
The Bible says this in v. 7,
At that time, Hanani the seer
came to Asa king of Judah
and said unto him,
Because thou hast relied on the king of Syria
and not relied on the Lord thy God,
therefore is the host of the king of Syria
escaped out of thine hand.
Now, you understand Asa wasn't very pleased
to receive that word.
The prophet did not gain any level of popularity
by standing before the king
and telling him this truth.
In v. 8, the Bible says,
Were not the Ethiopians and the Lubams a huge host
with very many chariots and horsemen?
Yet, because thou didst rely on the Lord,
he delivered them into thine hand.
And so he reminds them of a past victory
in which he relied on the Lord
and received the deliverance,
and God worked.
But in this particular situation with the Syrians,
he did not rely on the Lord
because he relied on the king of Syria,
and therefore they've escaped.
V. 9, notice this great truth,
this Bible principle,
For the eyes of the Lord
run to and fro throughout the whole earth
to show Himself strong in the behalf of them
whose heart is perfect toward Him.
Herein, thou hast done foolishly.
Therefore, from henceforth, thou shalt have wars.
Then Asa was wroth.
You understand, there are people
that don't like the preaching of the Word of God.
Amen?
They just don't want to hear the Bible.
They want to hear somebody tell them
everything's going to be okay
There are plenty of false prophets in the Old Testament.
We're going to go in the next passage
and look at Micaiah.
There are a lot of false prophets
that were telling the king,
oh yeah, go, you're going to have victory.
Telling him what he wants to hear.
The New Testament principle is there in 2 Timothy 4.
They're not going to endorse sound doctrine, right?
They're going to have itching ears, right?
They want to hear this feel good, do good, whatever.
And the reality is that Asa now is wroth.
He's angry with the seer, with Hanani,
because he gave them the truth of the Word of God.
The Bible says, and put him in a prison house,
for he was in a rage with him because of that thing.
And Asa oppressed some of the people the same time.
Chapter number 18, turn over if you will,
just maybe a page or two in your Bible.
In chapter number 18, we see the record of Jehoshaphat,
who basically was a good king in Judah,
join with Ahab, who was an extremely wicked king
of Israel.
The Bible tells us about this agreement that they make,
and it was an ungodly agreement.
We find that they're going to enter into battle,
and of course, Jehoshaphat asks Ahab,
is there not a prophet of the Lord here
that we can inquire of?
And Ahab says, well, there's this guy Micaiah,
but he's always prophesying bad about me,
and so on and so forth.
Well, Ahab was an extremely wicked man.
Married to Jezebel.
There's probably a reason that there's not a whole lot
of Jezebels and Ahabs running around schools today, amen?
We don't name our kids Ahab.
We don't name our kids Jezebel.
And we notice here that Micaiah comes.
I'm gonna just pick it up in verse 13.
We don't have time to look at the whole text,
and I'm gonna skip down to verses 25 and 26,
but notice Micaiah said, as the Lord liveth,
even what my God saith, that will I speak.
And so he's going to go, and he's gonna give the truth,
and we find that Micaiah is faithful
to be a prophet of the Lord,
but his message is not well received.
Notice verse 25, then the king of Israel said,
take ye Micaiah, and carry him back to Ammon,
the governor of the city, and to Joash, the king's son,
and say, thus saith the king,
put this fellow in the prison,
and feed him with bread of affliction
and with water of affliction until I return in peace.
He's never gonna return in peace.
He's gonna die in battle.
Skip over, if you will, and look at chapter 24.
Chapter 24 of the book of 2 Chronicles,
in my opinion, is a very sad passage of Scripture,
a very unfortunate situation here
with this one Joash, who was the king,
and Joash had a very godly influence in his life.
It was the priest Jehoiada.
The Bible tells us that the priest Jehoiada
had great influence on the life of Joash,
and as long as Jehoiada lived,
Joash really kind of did that which was right.
But at some point,
that person that has influence in your life is gonna die.
And Jehoiada dies.
And then there's some new influence in Joash's life.
And unfortunately, I would conclude
as I look at the passage of Scripture,
that Joash was a very godly influence in Jehoiada's life.
never had his own personal walk with God.
And how vitally important it is
that we teach our young people
that we instruct the generation behind us
to understand that they need to develop
their own personal walk with God.
We've often said this,
that God has no grandchildren.
He only has children.
What do we mean by that?
You're not saved because your mom saved,
your dad saved, your grandma saved.
You've got to trust Christ as your personal Savior.
And when you get saved,
you need to develop that walk with Christ.
And unfortunately, Joash didn't do that.
We pick it up in v. 17.
The Bible says this,
now after the death of Jehoiada
came the princes of Judah
and made obeisance to the king.
Then the king hearkened unto them.
Isn't it amazing how this new influence
comes into Joash's life
and they begin to lift him up
and they make obeisance to him
and they wow him, so to speak,
and now they're going to influence him
in an ungodly manner.
They left the house of the Lord God
of their fathers.
They served groves and idols
and wrath came upon Judah and Jerusalem.
For this their trespass.
Yet, v. 19, God in His faithfulness
and in His grace says this,
that He sent prophets to them
to bring them again unto the Lord.
And they testified against them.
But notice the end of v. 19,
but they would not give ear.
I'm so thankful that God is faithful
to send a messenger.
I'm so thankful that there are messengers
that have been faithful to deliver the message.
Though at times the message is not popular.
But we see the faithfulness.
Unfortunately, they would not give ear.
There's some people that just don't want to listen.
They don't want to listen.
The Spirit of God came upon Zechariah,
the son of Jehoiada, the priest.
Now think about that.
He was the son of Jehoiada.
Remember, Jehoiada was the man
that had a great influence in Joash's life.
Furthermore, we find that Joash
was seven years old when it began to rain.
So we could easily understand
as we look at the passage of Scripture
that Joash and this one that is mentioned here
in v. 20, Zechariah the son of Jehoiada,
they were very close in age, no doubt.
The influence of Jehoiada upon Joash,
they knew one another.
And yet, the Bible tells us in v. 20,
it says,
"...which stood above the people and said unto them,
Thus saith God,
why transgress ye the commandments of the Lord
that ye cannot prosper?
Because ye have forsaken the Lord,
He hath also forsaken you.
And they..."
Who's they?
Well, that's Joash and this new group of friends.
"...they conspired against him, Zechariah,
and stoned him with stones
at the commandment of..." who?
The king.
Joash.
"...in the court of the house of the Lord."
See, I look at these three Old Testament principles.
Make your way back to Hebrews, if you will, chapter 11.
And no doubt, we could look at others.
No doubt, we could begin to discuss
the things that are not recorded in Scripture.
Tradition would tell us of some of the deaths
of some of the prophets.
When it speaks about here in v. 37
that they were saunas under,
tradition would tell us,
though it's not recorded in Holy Scripture,
that it was Isaiah, the prophet of the Lord,
that was sauna and sunder.
They say that they put him in a tree,
a hollowed out tree, and cut him in half.
Wow.
And we could go on and we could think about
even with the New Testament list of folks
that we could look to being even further in history
removed from the writing of Scripture
and we could think about the disciples
and we could understand the historical accounts
given to us of the death in which they faced,
the difficulties, the adversities in which they endured.
But I want to draw your attention to two phrases
in this same section that deals with the adversities.
The first phrase is found in v. 35.
The Bible says this,
that they might obtain a better resurrection.
Now, the reality is that there are times
really in the New Testament
even during the era in which this was written
in the first century there,
you could offer just a little salt on the altar
and you could really avoid a whole lot of problems.
But it says no, we're not going to do that.
The writer of Hebrews is saying to these people,
live by faith.
Listen, don't accept deliverance.
Why?
Because it says here that they might obtain
a better resurrection.
See, the reality is that we're going to stand before God one day.
Every single person that has ever lived
upon the face of the earth will stand before God.
If you have accepted the Lord Jesus Christ
as your personal Savior,
you can rejoice in the truth that God gives us
in the book of Revelation
that the second death has no power over us,
and you can rejoice in the fact
that you will not stand at the great white throne judgment.
That judgment is given to us
and provided a record of that judgment
in Revelation 20.
If you begin to look at that judgment,
you see that that's the judgment
for those that have not accepted
the Lord Jesus Christ as their personal Savior.
And the Bible says that they'll be cast in the lake of fire.
And that's terrible.
It says this is the second death.
Mankind without the Lord Jesus Christ
will suffer for all of eternity in the lake of fire.
But we find that there's another judgment,
the bema seat, the judgment seat of Christ.
Paul says on a regular occurrence
that we all must stand before God
and give an account.
I preached a message before a revival meeting.
Actually, the Sunday morning of our revival meeting,
I preached a message about examining ourselves
and understanding the preparation
and understanding the fact
that I'm going to stand before the Lord,
and therefore, if I'm going to stand before Him
and give an account,
I ought to be preparing for that.
But we find that it says
that they might obtain a better resurrection.
The fact that though I am tortured
at the hands of mankind
and though they might put me to death
as it goes into the next passage of Scripture
about those that had these trials
and about those in v. 37
that were stoned and were sawn asunder,
yet we have a better resurrection.
We can stand before the Lord
and understand that we never bowed down.
It's like what the three Hebrew children said
in the book of Daniel,
and we referenced it already a few moments ago,
but you understand that as they're standing there
before the King Nebuchadnezzar,
that they say this in Daniel 3,
when they make it known,
they say, if it be so,
if you're going to send us into this fiery furnace,
we want you to understand that our God
whom we serve is able to deliver us
from the burning fiery furnace,
and He will deliver us out of thine hand, O King.
But it says this,
if not, v. 18,
be it known unto thee, O King,
that we will not serve thy gods
nor worship the golden image
which thou hast set up.
Whether it was by being delivered
through the fire,
from the fire,
in the fire,
whatever it was,
they knew that God was going to deliver.
We're not going to bow down to your gods.
He is, our God,
is going to deliver us out of your hand,
and it might be through death.
We are rejoicing as we look at Daniel 3
that they were delivered from the fire.
The reality this morning
is that there are times
in which God will deliver us
as we live by faith.
He will deliver us from
whatever the difficulty is.
There are times in which He will deliver us
through that adversity.
He's with us in the storm.
The disciples encountered storms in the boat.
The Lord was with them.
We've often said this,
that there are,
as we understand the attributes of God,
the Bible reveals to us
that our God is omnipotent.
He has all power.
He declares after His resurrection,
all power is given unto Me in heaven and on earth.
And we understand that He is the Lord God omnipotent,
that He has all power,
and no doubt He could prevent
any difficulty in your life and in my life.
And if we'd be honest this morning,
we would say we'd be okay
if He would deliver us from any problem.
Amen?
We don't like problems.
I don't like problems.
But the reality is that
sometimes God's delivering us
through the problem.
And He's proving us.
And He's developing us.
And He's being glorified.
And we find that there's this better resurrection.
Can you imagine how Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego,
I mean, obviously we wouldn't read the passage as we do.
Can you imagine as we couple that thought
with the thought of if they had accepted deliverance,
and then couple that thought with what John says in 1 John
about those that would be ashamed of His appearing,
I wonder how Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego
would have felt if they went ahead and bowed down.
First of all, we would not read it the way that we read it.
Right?
Because Nebuchadnezzar never would have sent them into the fire.
Because he simply said if you're going to bow down,
you don't have to go into the fire.
What if they accepted it?
What if they said, okay, that's easy.
You know what, we justify it in our minds.
And we don't really mean it, God, but we're going to...
You know what I mean?
We wouldn't read Daniel 3 the way that we read Daniel 3.
And I believe as the Apostle John says in 1 John
when he talks about the fact that our God is going to return
in verse 28 of chapter 2, he says,
Our little children abide in Him that when He shall appear...
we may have confidence and not be ashamed before him it is coming."
I'm thankful that they didn't accept deliverance.
We know that they were delivered by God, but they didn't accept deliverance from Nebuchadnezzar.
We find that these others that were stoned, that were sawn asunder, the folks that dealt
with these adversities, that they might obtain a better resurrection, that we could stand
before the Lord knowing that we are faithful unto death, unto the end, right?
We notice not only that truth with regard to these that dealt with these adversities,
these others, but notice the statement in verse 38.
Only to begin it, it's in parenthesis, of whom the world was not worthy.
You know, the reality is that our worth is not based on what the world says.
The world hates you?
Don't be surprised by that.
They hated Jesus.
By the way, isn't that what Jesus said in John when he was preparing his disciples?
I mean, if they hate you, you've got to understand that they hated me first.
That's what Jesus says to the disciples, and the reality is that we're not looking for
acceptance or worthiness by the world's standard.
We can rejoice in the truth of Ephesians when he says that we're accepted in the Beloved.
Why?
Because Jesus Christ is our Savior.
We've been born again.
We've been adopted in the family of God.
We see that the Bible says of whom the world was not worthy, but I'm thankful that though
the world might scourge us, and though the world might mock us, and though the world
might imprison us, and though the world might kill us, I'm not looking for acceptance by
the world.
I'm thankful to be a child of God and to know that one day, one glorious day, I will see
Him face to face, and we shall be like Him.
And what a great truth that is.
We notice the accomplishments.
We notice the adversities.
If we likened the accomplishments to faith on the mountaintop, we would liken the adversities
to faith in the valley.
We need faith in the valley.
We need faith on the mountaintop.
We need to live by faith.
And help us not to believe the lie of the enemy, to think that if we live by faith that
that means we'll have no problems.
Paul is reminded of a truth in 2 Timothy when Paul says to Timothy,
Yea, all those that live godly in Christ Jesus shall suffer persecution.
By the way, when you begin to think about Ezra and Nehemiah, those guys had a certain
level of comfort and ease until they went to go do something for God by faith, and all
of a sudden the adversity showed up.
The adversary showed up.
Right?
Sanballat and Tobiah, you read about those guys.
And many others.
And we find here that there are a list of accomplishments, there's a list of adversities,
but then I notice as we conclude the passage of Scripture, I notice all.
You say, that's weird.
I understand it's weird.
I thought it was weird when I wrote it down too.
But the reality is that in verse number 39 it says this,
And these all.
These all.
What does all mean?
There was a Bible college professor that was super deep, and he said, I'm going to give
you a lot of insight this morning, I'm going to tell you that all means all, and that's
all that all means.
And Brother Bish, he pastored for a number of years and he's with the Lord now, he was
a Bible college professor, he's a great man, and I remember that day, there were many times
that he would do something of that nature where he would begin to enter into class and
you'd think that he was going to give you this just deep, profound, and you'd get your
pen out and you're ready.
And then he'd say something like that, and you'd be like, you know what, that is good
though.
It's true.
All does mean all.
And when I read it, when it says in these all, my mind races back, not just to verse
number 32, but all the way back to the beginning of the 11th chapter of the book of Hebrews,
we begin to see all, remember every era of human history, remember not every name is
mentioned because it says of Samuel and of the prophets, and so we begin to think about
all of these, the entire body of people represented by what is given to us in Hebrews chapter
number 11, these all having obtained a good report through faith.
We're going to deal with the last name in just a moment, but I want you to understand
that when we look at this list of people, there's not a better report or a better testimony
that they receive because of accomplishment or because of adversity.
They all receive a good report through faith.
Because God's interested in our faith.
Remember, success is not measured in God's eyes the same way man measures success.
It's not appropriate for us to say, well, David was better than Micaiah.
No, they both were faithful and they both lived by faith.
We could look at some that seem to be great pillars and wonderful things that were accomplished
and we look at others and say, man, they were faithful, but they just suffered and they
were afflicted.
I mentioned to the family last night as we're having devotions.
So often we talk about these great things that have happened with the people of God
and we should and we rejoice and we enjoy speaking about the triumphs of Scripture.
How often do we hear a message?
I ask myself, how often do I preach a message on John the Baptist being beheaded?
I've preached on it before, but it's certainly not my favorite topic to go to.
I like dealing with some of those great accomplishments.
But you know what the Bible says that Jesus says about John the Baptist?
That he was a bright and burning light.
He fulfilled his role.
He did what he was called to do.
He lived by faith.
He stood before the king and he gave him a message from the Lord and it wasn't a very
well-received message.
Herod wanted to kill John the Baptist, but he couldn't because he was afraid of the people.
If you read the passage, you understand what happened and he says, well, you know, I made
an oath that I would do whatever they asked for.
But the reality is that it says, and these all, having obtained a good report through
faith, if you live by faith, you please God.
Without faith, it is impossible to please him.
But if you live by faith, you please God.
And in pleasing God, it's not measured by, well, you know, sometimes pre-COVID because
COVID's messed everything up.
But sometimes, unfortunately, even within Christian circles, someone will look at the
success or the faithfulness of a pastor based on the size of the congregation.
But the reality is the church is God's, amen?
And I believe, and I've said this for years, I believe that there's some men that pastor
in some remote parts of this nation and other parts of the world that have just a handful
of people and they're going to be rewarded in like fashion, maybe even in greater fashion
than some that have some of the largest churches.
Why?
Because they were faithful.
They were faithful.
Moreover, it's required in the steward that a man be found faithful.
We're seeing the faithfulness of these people and we notice all, all of them have received,
they've obtained this good report and it was through faith.
We understand the last phrase of verse number 39.
That's what it says, received not the promise.
Now let me ensure, just ensure you this morning that there's no contradiction in scripture.
I'm thankful for that.
In verse 33, it says of the list of accomplishments that they obtain promises, but now it says
this, that they receive not the promise.
There's an important aspect.
Listen, every jot and tittle in our English Bible, every letter, right?
Every word of God is pure.
But it says promises in verse number 33 and it says promise in verse number 39.
What's it referring to in verse number 39?
Well, the reality in verse number 33, there were promises that God gave and they received
those promises.
But the promise that is mentioned in verse number 39 is the coming of Messiah.
Remember, all the way back in Genesis chapter number 3, God promised that his, that Messiah
would come.
And all throughout the Old Testament, there is a picture in type after type of Messiah
who would one day come.
The book of Hebrews deals in such depth with all of those pictures and all those typologies.
And now, as the writer of Hebrews concludes this 11th chapter, he speaks about all those
Old Testament saints and how they lived by faith, but they received not the promise.
Jesus did not come in their time.
Messiah had not come.
Paul says in the book of Galatians, when the fullness of time was come, that God sent forth
his son.
We understand that as Paul continues, he sent them forth for a purpose and that was to live
a sinless, perfect life, to go to the cross of Calvary, to bleed and die, to be buried
and to rise again, conquering sin, death, and the grave.
And so we look at the portion of Scripture and we understand they received not the promise.
They looked for Messiah, but in their lifetime, he never came.
Because God's...
timing is perfect. He's never late. He's rarely early. He's always on time because
God has a plan. And we find that it continues and ends in verse number 40
and it says this, God having provided some better thing, look at those next two
words, for us. Now it's interesting because if you go all the way back to
the beginning of chapter 11, he says this in verse number 3, we dealt with
this, for through faith, we. Remember we dealt with this with regard to creation
and we talked about the fact that there's a record all throughout the
scriptures of those that believed in creation and even we, those that he's
being written to, and we still today, we understand creation through faith. We
take God at his word. We believe that the account of Genesis is a true
account and we believe that God said and it was so. And we find that from
verse number 3, beginning in verse number 4, all the way through verse number 39,
he's talking about these other people. Abel, Enoch, Noah, Abraham, Sarah. You go
through the list. You get to Joseph and before then Jacob and you look at Moses
and you look at Rahab and you look at and then he deals with we don't have the
time and let me just list all these people and all these events. And what is
he doing? He's referencing them, others, people of history. But then he brings it
back. God having provided some better thing for us. Notice that they, all those
that we've been talking about, without us should not be made perfect. So we look at
and we begin to say, what is God talking about? Well, God has a perfect timeline of
history. And we can look at the history and we can begin to
analyze the end times and we can give a chart of eschatology that's revealed to
us in the Word of God. We don't know the dates of what's going to happen, but we
understand the timeline. We understand what God has told us is going to take
place. And we understand the next event on the prophetic calendar is the
rapture. And when that happens, we can draw out a timeline and know exactly the
dates, but the timeline of what happens. And what we see here is that all of
those that have been mentioned in Hebrews chapter 11, those Old Testament saints
that are referenced, they were looking back, or excuse me, looking forward to the
Incarnation. They were looking forward to Messiah coming. But we, like these first
century believers, we live on this side of Calvary. And we're looking back
understanding that Jesus did come, that he did complete the work of redemption.
The plan of redemption has been completed. He said it is finished. And
then he gave up the ghost. And we find that he completed the plan of redemption.
And I understand as I look at this whole thing and I begin to look at God's
perfect timeline, listen, sometimes we say, when is he gonna come back? He's
gonna come back on time. I don't know when he's gonna come back. But all I know
is that I've been given marching orders. Occupy till I come. Redeem the time for
the days are evil. Go and preach the gospel to every creature. These are
commands that we've been given. And we understand that in God's perfect timeline,
listen, he might not return during your lifetime. Just like for the Old Testament
prophets, Christ didn't come the first time in their lifetime. But we rest
assured that there is this truth of having some better thing for us, that one
day, for all of eternity, my faith, your faith, will be made sight. We will see him
face to face. And we will be with him for all of eternity. And we begin to think
about that truth. And we begin to think about the completion of God's plan of
in our faith. And we begin to think, there's a great song, it is well with my
soul. Many of you know the song. In that last line, the last verse, when my faith
shall be made sight. And we understand this morning, that as we look at this
11th chapter, I wish I could get into chapter 12. By the way, do you have lunch
plans? We just keep on going, amen? I mean, it's exciting. But you enter, I'll give you
a preview of Hebrews chapter number 12. After he gives all of this great truth
of those that lived pre-Calvary, but lived by faith, and stayed faithful, and
did not accept that deliverance, they served God, some with great
accomplishments, some with great adversities. And then he says this,
we're foreseeing we also are encompassed about with so great a cloud of witnesses.
Let us lay aside every weight in the sin which doth so easily beset us, and let us
run with patience the race that is set before us. You have a race, I have a race,
and we, on this side of Calvary, we still continue on looking unto Jesus, the
author and finisher of our faith. And begin to understand all that God is
giving us here, and to these first century believers that were dealing with
great adversity. For us today, in 2020, that are dealing with difficulty. Listen,
I get periodicals every day, I get emails about the fact that, man,
they're gonna close down churches, they're not gonna let you preach anymore,
they're gonna arrest you, they're gonna imprison you. We gotta be faithful, amen?
We live by faith, we trust God. I'd rather not go to jail, amen? But if that's what
happens, we live by faith. And we know that we could stand before God and
receive, as these did, a good report through faith. This morning, are we living
by faith? I know I've asked that question for a number of weeks now, as we've
studied Hebrews chapter 11. It's so easy to live by sight, it really is. But oh, we
have to embrace the promises of God. We have to understand that he will be with
us as he promised to be with us, that he will give us the power, that he will use
his word in the preaching of the gospel to save sinners. And that, as Paul said,
I'm gonna straight betwixt two. Having a desire to depart to be with Christ, which
is far better. That's what he said. For to me to live is Christ, and to die is gain.
Why? Because I'm gonna be with them. And we looked this morning, these all, verse
number 39, they've obtained a good report through faith. We too, I believe, as we
look at the passage, we too can obtain a good report through faith. Without faith,
it's impossible to please him. Oh, that God would help us this morning to live
by faith, to believe God, to take God as his word. Let me tell you what Charles Spurgeon
said. I wasn't gonna use this quote, but I want to use it, and I hope it'll be a
blessing to you. And I want to tell you what, let me just look it up, I got it right here.
Here's what Charles Spurgeon said about faith. He said this, I would recommend you either
believe God up to the hilt, or else not to believe God at all. Believe this book of God,
every letter of it, or else reject it. There is no logical standing place between the two.
It's not a, I'll take some and leave some. It's all. He says this, be satisfied with
nothing less than a faith that swims in the deeps of divine revelation. A faith that paddles
about the edge of the water is poor faith at best. It is little better than a dry land
of faith, and is not good for much. What he's saying, believe God. Just believe God.
We had many years ago, some folks that would say things like this, you can take that to
the bank. What do they mean by that? Oh man, I'm gonna fulfill what I said I was gonna
do. Listen, every promise of God is in him, yea. He will do what he said he will do. He's
not a man that he should lie. Amen? We serve a great God, and he's given us his revelation.
And what does he want us to do? Believe him. Believe him. Live by faith. Father, we love
you this morning. We thank you for loving us. Thank you for your word and the truth
contained therein. We look at this great chapter. We love the Bible, all of it is so good. We
think about this particular chapter, and as we finish up this morning at this eleventh
chapter of the book of Hebrews, Lord, we are encouraged by those that have gone before
us and lived by faith, took you at your word. Those that had great accomplishments as they're
mentioned there. Those that dealt with great adversities that are mentioned there. Then
we notice all, and these all having obtained a good report through faith. God, I pray that
you'd help us to live by faith, just as these examples were provided to these first century
believers. May we this morning be stirred up, challenged, and convicted to live by faith.
Help us to run our race. Help us to keep our eyes on the Lord Jesus Christ, the author
and finisher of our faith. Help us, Lord, to have an eternal perspective and to be used
to bring honor and glory to thy name.
Would you move?
and work this morning in the lives of your people.
As we have a moment of invitation,
I pray, God, that you would just help us to respond
in obedience to thy word.
As the Holy Spirit has spoken to each of us,
Lord, I pray that we would be doers of the word
and not hearers only.
I'll say yes, Lord, yes, to your will and to your way.
Thank you for speaking to our hearts.
I pray that you'd seal each decision that is made.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me, heads are bowed,
eyes are closed, no one's looking around.
As our custom is, we have an invitation
at the end of our service,
is give you an opportunity to respond
to how the Lord may have spoken to you
through the preaching of his word this morning.
Kimberly's gonna play quietly on the piano.
You can make your pew an altar.
You can come to this old-fashioned altar.
If you're not sure of heaven,
we'd love to take a Bible and show you
that you know for sure that heaven is your home.
If you're a child of God and you just need to come
and ask God to help you,
make a commitment that you're gonna live by faith,
trusting him, believing him.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.