5, and I want you to remember we're studying through the first and second letters that
Paul writes to Timothy.
We're entering into the fifth chapter here this morning.
Our theme, of course, for this calendar year is continue, as we see the charge that's given
throughout both of these letters.
To continue in the face of adversity and difficulty, the admonition, the charge is continue.
And we find that as we look at this letter, this epistle, it provides not only a charge
to Timothy, but we find that there's much within this particular letter that is given
as instruction for how God's people are to behave in God's church.
And we spent much time in the third chapter, really the end of the second chapter and through
the third chapter, dealing with behavior in God's church.
We had two messages with that title, part one and part two.
And we find that as we understand the truth that God has given, we find that God is the
one that is the head of the church.
He instituted the church.
The church is God's idea.
But we find that he gives instruction for behavior in his church.
There is behavior that pleases God, and there is, that behavior is appropriate.
We find there is inappropriate behavior that does not please the Lord.
It does not bring honor and glory to God.
We find that Jesus said this in John chapter number four, God is a spirit, and they that
worship him must worship him in spirit and in truth.
We find this morning as we, of course, last week looked at the fourth chapter of the book
of 1 Timothy, there was an emphasis, an obvious emphasis that was placed upon sound teaching
versus false teaching.
Timothy had the responsibility to teach truth.
The individual believer must recognize what they should receive and what they should refuse.
We asked the question, the title of the message last week was really a question, how is your
diet?
We're speaking spiritually about our diet and making sure that we are receiving those
things that we ought to receive and refusing or rejecting those things that we ought not
receive.
And so we looked at that last week in 1 Timothy chapter number four.
As we enter into the fifth chapter, we find that Paul begins to provide instruction with
regard to relationships within the church.
You find that we, obviously as a church, we're a church family, and there are relationships
that we have in the church, and so Timothy is instructed on how he is to interact with
those that are making up the church, the members of the church, and his behavior and interactions
with church family would be an example to the rest of the body.
The pastor is to set forth the pattern.
We find in this chapter in 1 Timothy 5 that God, the first 16 verses we're going to look
at this morning, God deals with relationships in the church.
In verses one and two, notice the Bible says, rebuke not an elder, but entreat him as a
father and the younger men as brethren, the elder women as mothers, the younger as sisters
with all purity.
Verse three, honor widows that are widows indeed.
We'll skip down and look at verse 16, and we'll get into the message this morning.
The Bible says, if any man or woman that believeth have widows, let them relieve them, and let
not the church be charged that it may relieve them that are widows indeed.
So as we come to this fifth chapter, look at 1 Timothy, we find that God provides this
instruction with regard to relationships within the church.
By the way, God is an eternal God that understands all things, he has all wisdom and all knowledge,
and we find that he's given us a book, the Bible, the mind of Christ, and he's given
us the instruction that we need to follow.
It's very interesting as you come to 1 Timothy chapter number five that there are two verses
that are given really with regard to the members of the church as a whole, the senior saints
and the younger folks, and you pick which category you're in, but we find that there's
a two verses given to that, and then from verse three down through verse number 16,
God deals with the subject matter of widows, and we find that he provides a great deal
of instruction, obviously, and we'll deal with this as we go through it.
There was a number of widows that would be there in the church at Ephesus, and they needed
instruction on how to handle this.
It's also interesting to note that in Acts chapter number six, there's a contention that
arises within the church at Jerusalem, and that contention is really with regard to how
the widows were being cared for.
It's very interesting as you begin to couple this passage with that truth in Acts chapter
number six and understanding the attack of the enemy that is laid forth in the book of
Acts and how that the enemy seeks to attack from without, and that persecution, the religious
leaders, they, you cannot speak in the name of Jesus, and so on and so forth, we're going
to beat you, we're going to imprison you, and we're going to try to stop you, and that
wasn't very successful.
And so then we find that the enemy would bring some division within in Acts chapter number
six.
I'm thankful for the leaders of the church in Jerusalem and the wisdom that God gave
them for handling that situation, but we find that as we come to First Timothy chapter number
five that God gives instruction so that not only the church at Ephesus, but every New
Testament church would have a pattern and would have the mind of the Lord with regard
to how to deal with these situations.
There are a variety of situations that churches have, the interactions of people, the relationships
within a local church, and we find that God provides instruction, and when God provides
instruction, it is our duty to know it and to apply it.
And so we find that as we enter into this passage of Scripture, number one, if you're
taking notes, regarding the elder.
We see this in verse one and two regarding the elder.
Now the word elder is interpreted by the context.
Understand that even in this single passage of Scripture, we find that the word elder
is used in verses one and two, but then again in verse 17 and 19, here in verses one and
two it is referring to those who are the elderly, those that are up in age, if we could use
that phraseology this morning, the senior saints, if you will, that is who is being
referred to in verses one and two.
In verse 17 and 19, when he uses the word elder, it gives clarity in verse 17 where
it talks about let the elders that rule well be counted worthy of double honor.
Verse 19, against an elder received not an accusation.
He's speaking about the leader of the church, the office that was dealt with in chapter
number three, that office, the pastor.
And so we find that here in verses one and two, he first deals with instruction with
regard to the elder and emphasis is placed, notice in verse number one, rebuke not an
elder, but entreat him as a father.
In verse number two, the elder women as mothers.
So we find that Paul is giving this instruction to Timothy with regard to how he is to interact
with those within the congregation and not only how he is to interact, but then setting
forth the pattern for how each member is to interact one with another.
We find that there's an emphasis placed in verse one and two when we talk about the instruction
regarding the elder or the elderly, that there's an emphasis placed on honoring and respecting
the elder men and the elder women.
He says this, notice what he uses as an example, he says in verse number one, as a father.
He says in verse number two, as mothers.
You think about that relationship that we understand physically in our immediate families
and you find that the application is being made within the context of a church family
and understanding that there are churches, and really a church should have representation
in each age bracket.
A church that only has senior saints is a church that's dying, a church that needs to
be revitalized, a church that needs to reach a next generation, and you have a church that
has elderly, you have a church that has younger, and everywhere in between, and if you're not
sure where you fit, you just kind of pick a category, you say I'm not ready to be a
senior saint, ask your spouse or ask somebody else that you trust and they'll let you know
if you're a senior saint or not.
But the reality is that there's an emphasis placed on honoring and respecting.
That's important for us to understand, especially within the shift that's taking place today,
culturally speaking, within our nation.
Culturally speaking, there is a shift that is taking place in America with regard to,
and I'm speaking in general terms, with regard to how we interact with the elderly.
It's a sad thing when it's as if a younger generation lives and acts as if they do not
need the older generation.
And we find that the importance within, and bringing it back into the context of the scripture
and dealing with the church, there's opportunity to glean from the experience and wisdom of
those that have gone before us.
It's an opportunity that we have to learn.
I have men, personally, that are pastors of churches that are...
that exceed my age, that some of them have pastored
the church that they pastor longer than I've been alive,
and those are men that I will counsel with,
those are men that I like to get into their presence
and to have conversation with, why?
Because I can learn something from them.
They have experienced the many times that I've not yet had,
and I have the opportunity to glean from,
to learn from their experiences.
I'm now getting to the place and being at that age
where I'm kinda shifting a little bit,
where I have younger folks that come to me
that are just new in the ministry, starting a church,
and they say, hey, you've been pastoring now
for this number of years, and I got some questions for you.
Have you experienced this?
And I begin to hear the questions, and I see, Tim,
that I'm changing from one category to another category,
but the reality is that's life, that's how it works.
It's a troubling thing when you find, and no doubt,
you've seen it in the news over the last several years,
where there are elderly people that are targeted for crimes.
It breaks my heart when I see those things,
because there used to be an understanding culturally,
even without the church on the outside,
just culturally speaking, there was a respect
for the elderly.
There are still today in some cultures,
and especially if you were to study the Asian culture,
it's extremely prevalent within their culture
of respect for the elderly.
They are extremely careful.
I've spoken with many that have ministered
in that particular context, and it's amazing
of the way in which they teach the young people,
and it's really just driven into them
on that responsibility to have the honor
and respect for the elderly.
So when Paul is writing to Timothy, he says to him,
look, within the church, you're gonna have
some elderly people, and that's a good thing,
that's appropriate, a healthy church is going to be made up
of a diversity of those age brackets, if you will,
but he says, here's how you handle,
here's how you interact with, you entreat him,
meaning the elderly men, as a father,
and then for the elderly women as mothers.
What a great picture that we find that God gives
for the church and how they're to function.
He then deals with, again, in verses one and two,
regarding not only the elderly,
but he gives instruction regarding the younger.
Notice in verse number one, he says,
rebuke not an elder, but entreat him as a father,
and then he says this, and the younger men as brethren.
In verse number two, the elder women as mothers,
the younger as sisters with all purity.
And so as we begin to understand the interaction
that Timothy would have with the younger men and women
in the church, that he's to interact with them
as a brother or as a sister.
We find that we often will use that phraseology
that we're brothers and sisters in Christ.
What a blessing to have that relationship,
that bond, if you will.
And we find that he gives this picture
for us to understand that bond that is there,
the relationships between the pastor and the members,
but then for member to member
and how they're to interact one with another.
And he talks about these relationships.
We would understand that they're to be appropriate
and they're to be pure.
He says at the end of verse number two,
with all purity, the importance of appropriateness
and purity, I think about a brother.
I only have a, physically speaking,
I only have one brother.
And you think about brothers and the bond.
And you may not have a good relationship
with your brother.
I'll just speak of my relationship with my brother.
I have a good relationship with my brother.
I got to see him this past weekend
as his daughter graduated from high school
and what a blessing to be able to see him.
And we have that bond.
Did we always get along all of the time?
No, if you have a brother,
you know there are times that you disagreed
and you had some kind of,
but you know there was something
that was interesting about that.
Though my brother and I could have a disagreement,
we were on the same team.
We were unified and if someone else were to step in,
no, sorry, that's not how it works.
There was a bond.
A brother is born for adversity.
And that doesn't mean that a brother is born
so you can fight with them.
It means that your brother is your brother
and when there's adversity that comes,
it means that you have that relationship.
God did not allow me to have a sister,
but I have two daughters and we have a son
and so I get to see in their relationships
and their interactions some of how that works.
And you know, though God didn't allow me
to have any sisters, just having one brother,
I do understand through seeing other relationships
and other families that oftentimes a brother
has a protective spirit about a sister.
A protective spirit about a sister.
Why?
Because it's his sister.
Joseph is the youngest of our children,
but even as the youngest of our children
having two older sisters, you know,
Joseph, he wants to protect his sisters as much as he can.
And it's just, we didn't have to teach him that.
It's just kind of a natural thing
that he always loved them telling him.
We used to joke that he had three moms
and you know, that kind of thing,
being the youngest boy and what have you.
But the reality is that he wanted to protect his sisters.
And I begin to think about the physical relationships,
family relationships that we have one with another
and how God gives us this picture in verses one and two
and you begin to think about the way
that the family of God is to interact one with another.
You know, we find that in the scriptures,
the church at Corinth is an example,
of course a negative example,
of a church that was having great difficulties,
a church that had divisions and contentions,
a church that was carnal,
that could not receive all
that Paul wanted to instruct them with
because they were carnal.
They had those divisions and those contentions
and that is not God's plan for a local church.
God's plan for a local church
is that they would operate as a family.
He uses the term in the book of 1 Corinthians
that we're a body of the body of Christ,
a body that is fitly framed together,
a body that is to weep with those that weep,
to rejoice with those that rejoice.
Why?
Because we're a family.
What a blessing.
And here he gives this admonition to Timothy
with regard to the relationship
between him and the church family,
the elderly and the younger.
As we look, and I mentioned already by way of introduction,
beginning in verse number three,
he now turns the attention
not only to the elderly and to the younger,
but now instruction regarding the widows.
In verses three through 16,
we see that this instruction is provided
and the situation of emphasis
was obviously one where there were many widows.
The church was in need of direction.
Why do I say that?
Well, because God gave it.
The church was in need of how do we handle this circumstance?
How do we handle this situation?
I think about Moses
when he was leading the children of Israel,
there were times in which Moses
was leading the children of Israel
and he just simply did not know what to do.
There had not been instruction that had been provided
with dealing with a particular circumstance or situation.
And you know what Moses did?
He said, let us ask the Lord.
Let us seek the face of God.
Now at that point, the canon of scripture was not closed
and we find that God would answer the question.
God would give counsel and direction, instruction
for how to deal with that circumstance.
What a great example.
We now find here with Timothy ministering in Ephesus,
again, the canon of scripture not being closed.
They're dealing with this situation with having widows
and widows that are widows indeed.
The scripture uses that terminology and then younger widows
and how do we deal with this?
How do we as a local church handle this?
And God gives them instruction.
The instruction is clear.
The instruction is pointed.
We find that today that we have the opportunity
to go to the scriptures and to find what God says
with regard to these circumstances that even we may face.
Now it's important for us to understand
that in the first century, many times,
if a husband was a father, a husband and father was killed
through whatever means it was,
whether it was just a sickness or an accident or so forth,
there was really no way, no means by which the spouse,
the wife, the widow in this context
would be able to provide for herself.
And so we find that there's instruction that's given.
Today across the world, there are places that have systems,
if you will, that are very similar
to what you would have found in the first century.
Today in America, we have various systems and things
where many times I think about myself
with regard to having a life insurance policy.
And I'm not here, I don't sell life insurance,
so don't get the wrong idea,
but I made a decision when we got married
and we had children that I got a life insurance policy on me
so that if or when I die,
that Holly would receive some amount of finances
to be able to take care of her and the children.
Why?
Because I felt like that was my duty, my responsibility, and so therefore I made that decision.
And so every month, still to this day, I pay for a life insurance policy so that that would
be taken care of, not to be a burden and what have you.
And so we have different circumstances today, but we understand that the biblical truth
is still appropriate and applicable, and as we seek the mind of God with regard to
circumstances that we would face, we run to His word, we establish that God has the answers
and the principles that we need to glean so that we can make application.
So notice with me in verse number three, Paul says to Timothy, honor widows that are widows
indeed.
So it's interesting because he starts using that phrase right away, widows indeed, and
we'll see it repeated, and then notice in verse number four, it begins with a conjunction,
it says, but, but if any widow have children or nephews, let them learn first to show piety
at home and to requite their parents, for that is good and acceptable before God.
Now anytime that you find where God's word says this is good and acceptable, you ought
to take note because this is what pleases the Lord.
And so we find that God is giving the instruction, He says in verse number five, now she that
is a widow indeed and desolate, trusteth in God and continueth in supplications and prayers
night and day, but she that liveth in pleasure is dead while she liveth, and these things
give in charge that they may be blameless.
But in verse number eight, if any provide not for his own, and especially for those
of his own house, he hath denied the faith and is worse than an infidel.
Let not a widow be taken into the number under threescore years old, having been the wife
of one man, well reported of for good works, if she have brought up children, if she have
lodged strangers, if she have washed the saints' feet, if she have relieved the afflicted,
if she have diligently followed every good work, but the younger widows refuse.
For when they have begun to wax wanton against Christ, they will marry, having damnation
because they have cast off their first faith, and withal they learn to be idle, wandering
about from house to house, and not only idle, but tattlers also in busy bodies, speaking
things which they ought not.
Verse 14, I will therefore that the younger women marry, bear children, guide the house,
give none occasion to the adversary to speak reproachfully, for some are already turned
after, turned aside after Satan.
If any man or woman that believeth have widows, let them relieve them, and let not the church
be charged that it may relieve them that are widows indeed.
It's interesting as you look at verse number seven, the Bible says, and these things give
in charge that they may be blameless.
So Timothy has the responsibility to communicate this truth so that those that are within the
church, and now we find that as God's Word, this letter has been preserved in the Bible,
that we can understand the mind of the Lord in dealing with these situations.
So let's break it down, if you will.
The first aspect, he deals with widows that are widows indeed.
We see this really primarily in verses three through ten, there's a couple of verses scattered
in there that deal with the younger, but notice that there is here given to us, those that
are widows indeed, the primary responsibility, and now understand, this is important for
us to understand, the primary responsibility for caring for a widow that is a widow indeed
is the immediate family, not the church, okay?
That's biblical.
I've had people say, oh, we have widows, man, the church should just pay them all every
month a certain amount, that's not what the Bible says.
If they're widows that don't have family, now all of a sudden we've gotten to deal with
that, but the primary responsibility for the widow's care is the immediate family.
Notice in verse number four, but if any widow have children or nephews, let them learn first
to show piety at home and to requite their parents, for that is good and acceptable before
God.
Not only do we see there in verse number four the truth with regard to the primary
responsibility being to the immediate family and not to the church, we find again, as Paul
would summarize the entire teaching in verse number 16, he says, if any man or woman that
believeth have widows, let them relieve them and let not the church be charged.
Now, that's not confusing, is it?
Pretty clear.
And it says why, why should the church not be charged?
Well, that it, the church may relieve them that are widows indeed.
They have no family, they have no one that could care for them, and therefore it becomes
the responsibility of the church.
There's a warning that is given to the family members of widows in verse number eight.
Notice the warning, if any provide not for his own, and especially for those of his own
house, he hath denied the faith and is worse than an infidel.
That's strong language.
We find that within the context of this passage of Scripture, many times verse eight is taken
out of context and people just use it and make the application however they want, but
we understand primarily within the context of this verse of Scripture is the teaching
with regard to widows.
And therefore, if you have a widow that's a widow indeed in your immediate family, you
have a responsibility, you have a responsibility.
And we find that that responsibility, that warning is given in verse number eight.
It's not something that you just simply say, well, I'm going to let somebody else have
that responsibility.
No, it's your responsibility.
We find that the criteria is laid forth, the qualifications, if you will, for assistance.
Notice in verse number five, now she that is a widow indeed and desolate trusteth in
God and continueth in supplications and prayers night and day.
This one that is being referred to in verse number five, that now there's no family, there's
no immediate family, and there's the need for the church, there's some criteria that
is given.
Notice in verse number one, excuse me, verse number nine, let not a widow be taken into
the number under threescore years old, having been the wife of one man.
So there's actually an age that's given in verse number nine, an age of 60 that's provided.
And we find that that is given to us as we see the contrast in the teaching with regard
to the younger widows and what their tendency would be, and no doubt writing from and dealing
with the situation in Ephesus, not only a tendency, but probably something that had
actively taken place.
So he gives an age in verse number nine and then notices that the criteria continues in
verse number 10, well reported of for good works.
If she have brought up children, if she have lodged strangers, if she have washed the saint's
feet, if she have relieved the afflicted, if she have diligently followed every good
work.
And as we look at verse number 10, these are not things that are given that would make
this individual a saved person.
No, they're saved by the grace of God.
They're saved because of what Jesus Christ did on the cross of Calvary, his death barrel
and glorious resurrection.
But because they were saved, this was how they were serving God.
These were the works that they were doing not to be saved or to stay saved, but because
of their salvation.
And we find that the instruction is given with regard to, if you will, criteria or qualifications
for how the church would provide that assistance.
And we find that the responsibility is given.
I read verse 16 a moment ago, but the last part of the verse says that it may relieve,
speaking about the church, them that are widows indeed.
So there may be a local church.
The church at Ephesus was in a situation evidently where there were several widows.
We have a number of widows in our church.
And there may be a situation that presents itself where there's a widow that has no family,
that has no ability to be able to provide for themselves, and therefore the church then
has a responsibility.
But we find that primarily the responsibility is for the immediate family.
By the way, as you look at this portion of Scripture, it's not so that a church can say,
well, that's not my problem or not my responsibility.
It's so that this is God's Word that God gives the instruction to the church on how
to handle these matters.
And what a blessing to have the mind of the Lord.
Notice with me, he then not only deals with those that are widows indeed, but he deals
with younger widows, the terminology that is used.
We find that in verse number five, he talked about the one that was a widow indeed in verse
six, but she that liveth in pleasure is dead while she liveth, evidently dealing with those
that were widows, that were the young widows, because we find that we come back to verse
number 11, and it says, but the younger widows refuse.
For when they have begun to wax wanton against Christ, they will marry.
And so we find that there would be some that were widows, that were widows indeed, the
older, the...
verse nine dealing with the age,
but then verse number 11 talking about younger widows.
And again, with regard to the timeline,
and we understand that there would be those
in the category of younger and older
when their spouse would die, their husband would die.
And so we find that here,
God says in verse number 11 to refuse them.
Why?
Because when they wax wanton against Christ,
they will marry.
But not only that,
notice what the Bible says in verse 13
with regard to the behavior, if you will,
of these younger women, these younger widows
in contrast to what we read in verse number 10.
In verse number 13, the Bible says in with all,
they, speaking about the younger widows,
they learn, notice what it says, to be idle.
Wandering about from house to house,
and not only idle, but tattlers also in busy bodies,
speaking things which they ought not.
And so Paul begins to address the situation.
Again, I believe that there were probably some experiences
or some circumstances that Paul had understanding
of these things taking place.
And it was not just a matter of this may happen,
but probably this was something that had taken place.
And this one that is referred to as being a younger widow,
not only when they wax wanton against Christ,
will they marry, but they learn to be idle.
And then it goes downhill from there.
They're wandering about from house to house
and not only idle, but tattlers in busy bodies.
The Bible says this, speaking things which they ought not.
That's not a compliment in verse number 13.
It's an indictment against behavior that's not appropriate,
not behavior that's pleasing to God.
You think about the idea of being idle
and being busy bodies and speaking things
which they ought not.
Let me say this, this morning by way of application,
it doesn't just have to be a young widow
that gets involved in this kind of inappropriate behavior.
Amen, it doesn't have to even be a widow.
It doesn't even have to be a lady.
Amen, sometimes all people,
regardless of their marital status,
regardless of their age,
can be guilty of being busy bodies.
We find, we've been studying on Sunday night,
excuse me, on Wednesday night,
through 1 and 2 Thessalonians,
walk worthy and please God.
In verse number 11 of 2 Thessalonians 3,
the Bible says, for we hear that there are some
which walk among you disorderly,
working not at all, but are busy bodies.
And we find here, listen, it's not just a marital status
or an age relation that determines every person,
regardless of those criteria,
can be guilty of being a busy body.
Speaking, as it says at the end of verse number 13,
things which they ought not.
Sometimes we refer to it as having a filter.
You ever meet somebody that seems like they have no filter?
And what do we mean by that?
Well, they just speak.
They speak and they speak and they speak.
Sometimes they say things that they ought not say.
They get involved in areas
where they ought not get involved.
You ever said something, you say, man,
I wish I had not said that, it's already been said.
We need to be careful about this situation
because what can happen is we can become,
if we're not careful, again,
without regard to marital status or age,
you can become a busy body getting yourself involved
in areas where you ought not get involved.
And you hear that word about being a gossip.
Now I understand how it works typically
in a church setting.
It's not really gossip, it's just a prayer request.
I understand how it works.
But sometimes you fool yourself
more than you fool somebody else.
You fool yourself more than you fool somebody else.
Hey, I got a prayer request for you,
but really I just want to gossip.
I want to tell you what I found out.
Let me tell you, did you hear what happened?
Oh, would you please pray for them?
Listen, be careful, be careful.
This is not pleasing to God.
And we understand again within the context
He's dealing with the younger widows,
but the reality is that any of us could be guilty
of speaking about things which we ought not,
becoming tattlers and busy bodies.
Let me say this.
They didn't have social media back then like we do today.
Amen?
They went, according to verse number 13,
from house to house.
You know what people do today on social media?
They don't have to leave and leave anywhere.
They just sit there and they just,
I don't have social media.
Sometimes I wish I did, but most times I'm glad I don't.
The times that I wish I did is when I hear
about a good article or something
that a preacher friend wrote
and I didn't have an opportunity to see it
because I don't have the social media, what have you.
And sometimes I'll ask somebody,
hey, can you just email it to me, whatever.
But most times I'm happy I don't have social media.
And here's the problem.
You can sit around and you can be guilty
of being tattlers and busy bodies
and speaking the things that you ought not speak
because you're sitting behind a screen somewhere
on a phone or a device of some nature.
Be careful, be careful.
We continue and we look here at a pattern
that God establishes as Paul gives this instruction
with regard to those that are the younger widows.
He speaks about those that are widows indeed,
the older, and he talks about their testimony
and their behavior.
But he talks about these younger and he says refuse them
because here's the likelihood of what they will do
and here's perhaps what some have already done
and participated in and we find that he gives us
in verse number 14, excuse me, a pattern to be established.
He says, I will therefore that the younger women marry,
bear children, guide the house,
give none occasion to the adversary to speak reproachfully.
Now, I understand again that this is not
a culturally popular verse of scripture
with regard to the roles, if you will,
but we understand that Paul is establishing a pattern
and I'm thankful.
We started a few weeks ago a Sunday school class,
a marriage Sunday school class.
I'm thankful for marriage.
I'm thankful that God instituted marriage.
I'm thankful, I remember reading the verse,
when I first, after I got saved,
whoso findeth a wife, findeth a good thing
and obtain the favor of the Lord, amen.
And I'm glad for Holly.
I'm glad that God allowed me the opportunity to be married
and that we'll be celebrating our 23rd wedding anniversary
this year.
What a blessing, I am blessed.
We understand that there are some that will not be married,
but we find here, Paul deals with that
in 1 Corinthians chapter seven,
but we find that here in verse number 14,
he's laying forth this pattern
and he talks about being married,
he talks about bearing children.
I spoke about this on Mother's Day.
We're living in a time today where people,
unfortunately, especially in our society in America,
they're viewing children as being a burden
and not a blessing.
What a sad situation that is,
because the Bible says that the fruit of the womb
is his reward.
Children are an heritage of the Lord.
And we find that there are some that have that idea.
Children, why do they look at them as being a burden?
Well, they get in way of their career,
they get in way of their ambitions
and their bucket list of where they wanna go
and what they wanna do and all of this type of thing,
but Paul lays forth this pattern.
He says, not only would they have opportunity
to marry and to bear children,
but this says guide the house.
What a blessing to think about the ministry
of a wife and a mother within the parameters here
that we find of giving this guidance to the house.
And having the opportunity,
yes, the husband is to be the head,
and we understand that as we look at Ephesians
and you look at Colossians
and you understand the pattern that God has set forth,
but what a privilege for ladies,
if they're married and have children,
to give that guidance,
to invest in the fulfillment that is there.
Ends this verse by saying,
not only to marry, bear children and guide the house,
but give none occasion to the adversary
to speak reproachfully.
You know, the devil, the adversary,
you know that he hates everything that God is for
and that God loves.
God hates the church.
Or excuse me, sorry, let me rephrase that.
Satan hates the church.
Why?
Because God loves the church and gave himself for it.
The church is the bride of Christ.
Amen?
We find that Satan hates the church,
but Satan hates the family.
The family is under attack today.
We see it all over in our society.
Why?
Because the enemy hates the family.
Because God is the one that established the family.
And so it says here that none occasion
to the adversary to speak reproachfully,
that they're in a situation
where they're not putting themselves in a position
where they're going to give place to the devil,
that they're going to speak reproachfully,
as we saw earlier in verse number 13
with regard to the behavior that is established.
No, they're too busy to be dealing with that stuff.
They're focused on their home
and they're focused on their children
and they're doing those things.
They don't have time to get involved
with all these other things.
It's amazing to me how many times I hear people say,
And this is a general statement, it's not about anyone specific in our church, though
we've all been guilty of saying it, I just don't have time to do X, Y, or Z.
But yet, they spend how many hours a week on social media, they spend how many hours
a week watching this stuff and doing this thing, and it's how we steward our time.
I hear people say, I've got to make time for that.
I tell people all the time, you can't make time.
You can't make time.
All you can do is steward time.
Because you have a certain number of hours every day, and how you steward those hours,
you can't make more.
So man, if I just had more time, you've got to steward it wisely.
Steward time.
And so they would not have the time to get involved in the behavior that is outlined
in verse number 13 because they're doing that which is outlined in verse number 14, and
they're not giving any occasion to the adversary to be involved in that behavior.
He says this in verse 15, and this is why we believe, and I said earlier, that some
have already been doing these things because it says in verse 15, for some are already
turned aside after Satan.
There were some that were widows that were already behaving in this manner that was not
pleasing to the Lord.
And so we find that he ends the whole conversation, the whole instruction in verse 16, if any man
or woman that believeth have widows, let them relieve them, and let not the church be charged
that it may relieve them that are widows indeed.
As we look at the first 16 verses of 1 Timothy chapter 5, you see it passes as an unusual
message for a Sunday morning.
It's a lot different than last week's message on Sunday morning.
But the reality is that God gives us instruction for a reason.
The Bible says in 2 Timothy chapter number 3, a verse that we often reference, that all
Scripture is given by inspiration of God and is profitable for doctrine, for reproof,
for correction, for instruction in righteousness, that the man of God may be perfect, throughly
furnished unto all good works.
So we have God's instruction.
It is not for us to sit around and say, well, what do you think we should do about this
situation?
Hey, I think we should, no, we need to go to God's Word and we need to find out what
did God set forth as the instruction that we as His people are to follow.
You say, well, I don't like that very much.
Well, you better change your perspective because I can assure you that God's not going to change
His Word.
Amen?
You say, I just don't like that.
Well, you better change because God's not changing.
He was the same yesterday, today, and forever.
Amen?
He said, I'm the Lord, I change not.
And so what happens is we live in culture, we live in society that if we're not careful,
we develop our thought process based upon the ideas of the world as opposed to the
truth of God's Word.
It is imperative that even as we look at a passage of Scripture like 1 Timothy chapter
5, verses 1 through 16, we say, why do we focus on this?
Well, because God's church is made up of people, and the people that make up a church are to
interact one with another in a manner that is appropriate, that is God-honoring.
That we have the opportunity as a church family to show by our interactions one with another
the love of Christ.
That we get to set forth a pattern.
You know, what a terrible thing when a church has a testimony in a community that, man,
all they do is fight and argue down there, there's always problems down there, I'd never
go to that church.
I've heard people say that.
That's a terrible testimony.
That's not what God's plan is.
So God gives to Timothy and then gives to all of us by way of preservation instruction
for relationships within the church.
Did God know that there were going to be some elderly people in the church?
Absolutely.
Did He know there were going to be some younger people in the church?
So He says, here's how you interact.
Did He know there'd be some widows?
Some widows that are widows indeed, some that are younger?
Yes, God knew.
So God gives instruction.
We have a wonderful book here, the Bible.
And in this book, God has given us the instruction for every situation we'll ever face.
You say, well, I have this circumstance and I don't have
Sometimes you've got to dig a little deeper.
Sometimes the answer isn't as surface ready as this one is in 1 Timothy chapter 5.
Sometimes you've got to dig in, be students of the Word.
But you run to God and you run to His Word and say, how do we behave?
How do we interact?
Hey, there's a widow.
What do we do?
Do we just
No, let's run to the Bible and find out what God says and let's follow God's pattern
because that's going to bring honor and glory to God and result in His blessing and
His favor.
And we want God's blessing, we want God's favor individually, but also corporately as
a church we want God's blessing and God's favor.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
We thank You for the privilege that You've given us to gather today.
And Lord, though this text of Scripture and this message is a little different for a Sunday
morning, we thank You that You've given us the instruction.
And God, we thank You that when we face circumstances in life, when we face questions and scenarios
that we do not have to just rely on our own understanding, no, we can run to Your Word
and we can receive Your instruction and we're thankful for the clarity that You've provided.
And God, I pray that You would help us to determine even in a message like this that
we're going to be biblical, we're going to be scriptural.
That as we deal with circumstances and relationships in a church that we're going to seek the
mind of Christ, that we're going to apply the truth of Your Word in our interactions.
Father, I pray that if there's one here that's not sure of heaven, God, we pray that they'd
be saved today, that they understand that, God, You love them.
You love them so much that You sent Your Son to die for them.
The Lord Jesus Christ came here, God in flesh, to the sin-cursed world, lived a perfect sinless
life, went to a cruel cross, bled and died, buried, but rose conquering sin, death, and
the grave.
He did all of that so that we might be forgiven.
God, if there's one that's not sure of heaven, they've never trusted the Lord Jesus Christ
as their personal Savior, I pray the Holy Spirit of God would convict them this morning,
convince them of their sin and of Christ's righteousness and of judgment to come.
I pray for every child of God, Lord, would You help us to determine this morning that
we will be doers of the Word, that we will think and behave biblically, scripturally.
In this moment of invitation, we pray that You'd have Your will in way.
We'll thank You for it.
In Christ's name we pray.