You use 50 verses of scripture
and you're gonna try to turn to every one of them.
We'll be here for a couple of hours, amen.
And I know that you're not wanting to be here
for a couple of hours.
And so I've put the majority of the verses.
There's one passage of scripture
that I did not type out all of the 20 verses
of that passage, but for everything else,
I've typed out the verses
so that we can see it here on the screen.
In Psalm chapter 10, it's the title
that I've used for the message this morning.
Verse number 16 says this,
the Lord is king forever and ever.
The Bible says the heathen are perished out of his land.
And I'm thankful to know the Lord is king forever and ever.
It is important that we understand
from the start this morning that our God is on his throne.
I mean, right now at this very moment,
the Lord God omnipotent reigneth.
And it's important for us to understand that.
And we find that Jesus is king.
Can I say this this morning?
He's not on the ballot.
Why isn't he on the ballot?
Because he doesn't need to be, it's his rightful place.
All right, we're not voting for Jesus.
Jesus is on his throne.
Aren't you thankful for that?
Amen.
And he's not on the ballot.
Listen, he always has been,
and he always will be king of kings and Lord of lords.
And that ought to cause us this morning to rejoice greatly.
And we look at this and I got a picture there
that has a Bible open to the book of Psalms.
And then it has a individual that's casting a ballot.
As you know, and you cannot,
if you don't know, your head is in the sand.
I'm not sure how you could not know.
But in just a couple of weeks,
we're gonna have a, actually a week
in just a couple of days, an election here in our nation.
And this morning, I want us to understand
with great clarity that the truth of this here
has to impact this here.
What do I mean by that?
The Bible is our sole authority for faith and practice.
And it's absolutely vital that Christians once again
recognize the authority of God's word
and its influence on how we cast a ballot.
We have the privilege of casting a ballot
and I'm thankful for that.
But I rejoice this morning to know that my King,
my King Jesus, that he rules and that he reigns.
Notice with me, we mentioned Psalm 10, 16 already,
but notice if you will, in Psalm 29, in verse number 10,
the Bible says this, the Lord sitteth upon the flood,
yea, the Lord sitteth King forever.
We find in Psalm 97 and verse number one,
the Bible says this, the Lord reigneth.
Aren't you thankful?
The book of Revelation says,
the Lord God omnipotent reigneth.
Our God reigns.
And I'm so thankful this morning that we understand that
and we can rejoice in that truth,
but we must acknowledge that long ago,
mankind rejected God as their ruler.
We understand as you were to study the Old Testament
and study the people of Israel,
that they had a theocracy where literally God was their King.
God was their ruler.
And we find that they rejected God and they said this,
give us a King.
Samuel was disappointed with their interest
in having a King.
They desired to be like all the other people.
They were so distinct and so unique that God was their King.
They had a theocracy,
but yet they wanted what the other nations of the world had.
We find that Samuel was disappointed,
that Samuel struggled greatly with that.
But we find that in that rejection of the nation of Israel,
rejecting God and changing the truth of a theocracy
into a monarchy,
that human history from that point forward
has really plunged into the situation
of having humans rule us
or lead us from a government perspective.
Now here's what I'm thankful for.
God knew that.
If you study the book of Deuteronomy,
well before the people ever asked for a King,
God gave instruction to Kings.
Why would he give instruction to Kings
if it wasn't his plan that there be Kings?
Because he knew that man would not follow his plan
and because he's the omniscient eternal God,
he provided them with instruction
and for that we can rejoice.
But from that point in human history,
we find that man has been ruled by humanity.
Humanity has been ruled by humanity.
Sometimes there have been good rulers.
Sometimes there's been ruthless rulers.
But consider this thought from Proverbs 29
in verse number two.
When the righteous are in authority,
notice what the Bible says,
the people rejoice.
But when the wicked beareth rule,
the people mourn.
There's a contrast in this verse of Scripture
between the righteous that are in authority
versus the wicked that beareth rule.
And we find that the contrast between the leadership
has a profound impact on those that are being ruled.
The Bible says that when the righteous are in authority,
the people rejoice.
But when the wicked beareth rule,
that the people mourn.
Understand some foundational truth
as we consider the thought this morning,
as we go through this thought this morning
with regard to our role in understanding biblical truth.
One day, Jesus will come back
and set up his millennial kingdom.
He'll literally rule and reign for a thousand years.
He'll rule with a rod of iron.
We as the people of God will have the privilege
of being able to rule with him
and to experience that truth.
And we find that Revelation 20 verses one through six
gives in a very condensed passage that truth.
We can find references to the millennium
all throughout the pages of Scripture.
In fact, the Old Testament prophets speak much
about the millennial kingdom of the Lord Jesus Christ.
Until that time, however, we are governed by human rulers.
We have the unique blessing
of living United States of America
where we have elected officials.
We find that as citizens, we have not only a privilege,
but a responsibility to vote.
But as Christians, I would say this,
when it is our privilege and our responsibility to vote
that we have to understand that the Bible
must influence how we cast our ballot.
It's absolutely imperative.
I cannot separate my Christian life duty obligation
from my civil duty and obligation.
I am a Christian first and foremost,
and therefore it must affect every part of me.
I understand that in Proverbs 14 in verse number 34,
the Bible says this.
It says that righteousness exalteth a nation,
but sin is a reproach to any people.
It's interesting to me when I look at this verse
of Scripture that God did not say righteousness
exalted Israel or sin is a reproach to Israel.
The truth that is given to us is a truth
that's beyond just Israel.
It's for all people, all nations.
And thus God says righteousness exalteth a nation,
but sin is a reproach to any people.
Understand this in Psalm 11 in verse number seven,
the Bible says that the righteous Lord
loveth righteousness.
He's a righteous God and he loves righteousness.
The Bible tells us in Psalm 33 in verse number 12,
blessed is the nation whose God is the Lord
and the people whom he hath chosen
for his own inheritance.
But then consider this truth of Psalm nine in verse 17,
the wicked shall be turned into hell
and all the nations that forget God.
You say pastor, that's strong language, it's Bible.
Our God is a righteous God and he loves righteousness.
I've said this from the pulpit many times over the years,
even in recent days, our nation is ripe for judgment.
Our nation is ripe for judgment.
We read throughout the pages of Scripture
of God judging nations and peoples,
even his own people because of their wickedness
and because of their disobedience.
America as a nation is ripe for judgment.
I'm thankful that our God is long suffering.
I'm thankful that he's long suffering.
Consider with me this morning,
we have to remember as we consider
some of these foundational truths
before we dig in to specifics
with regarding this upcoming election.
But I want you to remember that our main purpose
for being left here upon this earth,
Jesus said in Acts one in verse number eight,
ye shall be witnesses unto me.
And I want you to see I got both verses on the screen
because in Acts 5.32, the disciples just,
they absolutely embraced what Jesus had told them
in Acts one in verse number eight,
when Jesus said ye shall be witnesses unto me,
then in chapter five in verse 32,
they say we are his witnesses.
And God's people must embrace that truth once again,
that we are his witnesses.
Listen, we have been given the responsibility
of not only being his witnesses, but being his ambassadors.
The Bible says in second Corinthians five
in verse number 20, now then we are.
ambassadors for Christ. I'm thankful that I'm a pilgrim. I'm a stranger. This world
is not my home. I'm just a passing through. The reality is that I have dual citizenship.
Number one, I'm a citizen of heaven. My conversation is in heaven, for which I rejoice, but I also
happen to be a citizen of the United States of America. But I'm an ambassador. The Bible
says at the end of that verse, as though God did beseech you by us, we pray you in Christ's
stead be reconciled to God. And it reminds us just a couple of verses earlier that God
said this, that all things are of God who hath reconciled us to himself by Jesus Christ
and hath given to us the ministry of reconciliation. I'm so thankful to be reconciled. I was at
variance with God. I was an enemy. I was lost and undone. But because of the work at Calvary,
I've been redeemed. I've been justified. I've been reconciled. And I'm so thankful for that.
And he's given to us the ministry of reconciliation. So it's important that we understand our purpose
for being here on earth. Our purpose is not primarily political. Amen? That's not our
purpose. Now we get to engage in that arena. We get to influence that arena, but that is
not our main purpose. Our main purpose is to preach the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
I understand this morning that principles and policies matter more than personalities.
Principles and policies matter more than personalities. Listen, we have to have the right position,
and it's also helpful that we have the right disposition. If one of those things is going
to be out of balance, it's far better to have a right position and a wrong disposition
than to have a right disposition with a wrong position. Did you follow that with me? And
the reality is that we want to have it in harmony. We want to have the right position,
and we want to have the right disposition. We want people to know that we love them.
We want people to know that we care about them, and we're giving them the gospel because
we love them. Yes, we've been instructed to do so, but I don't want to be ugly about it.
I want to be gracious about it. Let me say this. There will never be a candidate that
aligns with you 100%. Never. You don't agree with yourself 100% of the time. Amen? What
do you want for dinner? Just think about it. You don't agree with yourself 100% of the
As Christians, as followers of the Lord Jesus Christ, we must no longer allow politicians
to take biblical matters and politicize them. Then they demand that we as the people of
God not speak up with the threat of being labeled a bigot or worse. Can I tell you?
We've got to talk about the Bible. What's happened in our nation is politicians have
taken biblical truth and they've politicized it. Then they've told us as Christians you
don't belong in the political arena, and therefore you can't talk about it because we're going
to label you as, and we're going to cancel you as, and so on and so forth. But the reality
is that they're biblical principles. A bigot is defined as a person who is obstinately
or unreasonably attached to a belief, opinion, or fraction. Listen, I am absolutely attached
to this book. We have been called as Baptists throughout the centuries. We've been called
people of the book. That's a compliment. It's a compliment. And listen, we must understand
this morning, we must remember this morning that this truth of speaking on biblical matters
and biblical principles is absolutely imperative. Our world is blind. Our world has been blinded
by the enemy. I want to read to you a quote. It's not going to be on the screen there,
but in 1983 Howard Hendricks said this, and if it was true in 1983, it's so much more
true today. He said this, in a midst of a generation, or in the midst of a generation
screaming for answers, Christians are stuttering. Think about that just for a moment. They're
screaming for answers. Listen, our world is confused. Our world has no absolute truth
because they've made themselves the authority. And when you don't have an absolute truth,
when you enter into an arena of just do what makes you feel good and you redefine terms
and you have no boundaries, then you end up with what we're dealing with in America today.
Christians can no longer stutter. We must know why we believe what we believe and be
able to speak it in love. We must be able to articulate our position. We must be able
to speak on these matters. We've been given the responsibility, I'm going to say it one
more time, to preach the gospel to a lost and dying world. Understand with me this morning
that those with a different view are our mission field. They're not our enemy. Let me remind
you of something. Saul considered David his enemy continually. But David did not consider
Saul his enemy. I don't have time to develop all of that this morning, but I hope you can
be mindful. Listen, Saul was hunting David to kill him. He made David his enemy continually.
But David never viewed Saul as his enemy. He said, why do you come out to fight against
us? I mean, he understood that Saul was anointed to be the king. And this morning, we must
understand that those with a different view, they're not our enemy. You say, but they've
made…they're our mission field. The natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit
of God. For their foolishness unto him, neither can he know them, because they're spiritually
discerned. 1 Corinthians 2 and verse 14. So let me give you some biblical principles
for casting your vote. If you're taking notes this morning, I only have two points, but
they're two very long points. All right? Number one this morning, biblical principles for
casting your vote. I used that first slide. I'm going to show it again at the end of
the presentation this morning. But the first slide was a picture of an open Bible and a
picture with an American flag and an individual casting a ballot. And I say this, that there
are biblical principles that must influence and impact how we cast our ballot. Know the
issues and study your Bible. Don't go reading all of these political things and listening
to all these politicians. No. Get into your Bible, because your Bible is the authority.
Let me mention, I'm going to mention a number of things this morning that are matters that
we must consider. Number one, the matter of life. Do you understand this morning that
they have made life a political issue, but life is a biblical issue? God is the author
and giver of life. We find that the Bible tells us in Psalm 139 and verse 14, I will
praise thee for I am fearfully and wonderfully made. Marvelous are thy works, and that my
soul knoweth right well. Verse 15, my substance was not hid from thee when I was made in secret
and curiously wrought in the lowest parts of the earth. And then verse 16, it says this,
thine eyes did see my substance, yet being unperfect. And in my book all my members were
written, which in continuance were fashioned, when as yet there was none of them. What a
marvelous passage of Scripture dealing with the sanctity of life and understanding that
our God is the giver of life. The subject of abortion is all over our map today. It's
all over. There's individuals that are just fighting for up until the very last moment
that they could kill a baby. It's so sad. And all they want to talk about is, well,
it's a choice, and it's a choice. And no, it's not a choice, it's a human being. And
God is the giver of life. And we have to understand this morning that this is not a political
issue, it is a biblical issue. Jeremiah 1 and verse number 5, the Bible says this, sorry,
I think I'm on Exodus 21, sorry. Exodus 21, notice in verse number 22 it says, if men
strive and hurt a woman with child, so that her fruit depart from her, and yet no mischief
follow. Now do you understand the language here? What's happening is there are men that
are fighting, they hurt a woman that's expecting, her fruit depart, she has the baby. But it
says here that there's no mischief to follow. In other words, the baby survives. The baby
survives. The Bible goes on to say, he shall be surely punished according as the woman's
husband will lay upon him, and he shall pay as the judges determine. But verse 23 says
and if any mischief follow, then thou shalt give life for life. What does it mean if any
mischief follow? It means if the baby dies. That's what it means. And so if two people
are fighting and there's a woman that's expecting that's there, and that woman gets hurt in
the fight, and her baby is born.
and there's no mischief, there's still a consequence,
there's still a price to be paid,
but if the baby dies, God says life for life.
The Bible tells us in Proverbs 6 and verses 16 and 17,
these six things doth the Lord hate,
yea, seven are an abomination unto him,
a proud look, a lying tongue,
and notice, and hands that shed innocent blood.
If there's ever a description of abortion
that I can find in the Bible,
it's hands that shed innocent blood.
I believe with my whole heart this morning
that if we could deal with the subject
of fornication in our society,
it would go a long way to dealing with the subject
of abortion in our society.
We live in a loose living, sexualized society,
and therefore abortion is the byproduct,
I don't want that consequence, I don't want that result.
Righteousness exalteth a nation,
but sin is a reproach to any people.
Consider with me this morning the matter of gender,
the matter of gender.
God said this in Genesis 1 and verse 27,
so God created man in his own image,
in the image of God created he him,
male and female created he them.
In Matthew 9 and verse number four,
and he answered and said unto them,
have ye not read that he which made them at the beginning
made them male and female?
We're living in a society today,
listen, I don't know how you think about this,
I don't know how you feel about this,
but for me, when I begin to look at some of these things
that are going on, I shake my head and say,
how in the world did we get here?
How did we get here?
The slippery slope of sin.
They did not want to acknowledge God,
Romans chapter number one,
and God gave them over to a reprobate mind.
And we find this morning that we're living in the midst,
listen, they don't know, they say you can figure it out
at some point, no, no, we know if you're a male or a female.
It's absolutely obvious and easy to identify.
This idea of allowing people to think
that they're something else and to participate in sports
and all the others, it's nonsense, it's against God.
And it's against his order.
The subject of gender is not a political subject.
It's biblical.
God is the author and giver of life,
and he's the one that determined your gender.
And by the way, I'm thankful for it.
Notice with me, consider number three,
the matter of marriage.
God instituted marriage.
God instructed, gave instruction for marriage
in Genesis two and verse 24.
Therefore shall a man leave his father and his mother
and shall cleave unto his wife and they shall be one flesh.
The subject of marriage.
As a nation, we bought into the lie that love is love.
It's such a catchphrase today.
Whatever makes you happy, no, God defined.
God gave the truth.
And it's important this morning that we understand
that the matter of marriage is settled by God,
not by politicians, it's settled by God.
Let me say this, the matter of family.
God designed the family, and we find that the family
has been designed by God, it's been defined by God,
and God has directed the family.
How do we operate as husband, as wife, as children?
Understand with me this morning that there is an effort
to destroy the nuclear family structure as we've known it.
That term nuclear family refers to a man and a woman
that marry and have children and live in a home.
And that's the idea of a nuclear family.
And this morning, they have distorted that,
they have tried to break that down.
Can I tell you that those are the truths
of the backbone of our society
that made America what it is?
It's the enemy, it's Satan that wants to attack
what God instituted and to attack what God has designed,
and we find that happening in the family.
And it's so sad to see what's happening in our society
today with regard to the family.
I want you to think about the matter of justice,
the matter of justice.
You say that we live, you're familiar with this,
the lady justice is supposed to be blindfolded.
And we find that today, we live in a time in which
there's, we could say that the justice is corrupt.
And we don't have to, we're not exaggerating
by saying that this morning,
but we understand the importance of justice.
The Bible says this, righteous art thou, O Lord,
and upright are thy judgments, in Psalm 119, in verse 137.
In Isaiah 59, in verses 14 and 15,
there's an indictment that is made,
the Bible says in verse 14,
and judgment is turned away backward,
and justice standeth afar off,
for truth is fallen in the street,
and equity cannot enter.
Verse number 15, the Bible says this,
yea, truth falleth, faileth, excuse me,
and he that departeth from evil maketh himself a prey,
and the Lord saw it, and it displeased him
that there was no judgment.
Sad.
Our God is a righteous, just God.
There is right, and there is wrong.
There is good, and there is evil.
And God is the one that defines that.
Isaiah deals with it.
The Bible says that they were saying
that that which was good is evil,
and that which is evil is good.
That's what's happening in our society today.
We see it.
And we begin to think about biblical principles
for casting our votes,
and we're gonna go stand at a ballot box,
and we're gonna cast a vote,
and these things that our politicians have tried to take
and politicize them,
we must acknowledge that they're biblical matters.
The Bible tells us in Leviticus 19, in verse number 15,
he shall do no unrighteousness in judgment.
Thou shalt not respect the person of the poor,
nor honor the person of the mighty,
but in righteousness shalt thou judge thy neighbor.
In righteousness thou shalt judge thy neighbor.
We find this matter of justice again
living in a corrupt society with corrupt justice system.
And we begin to understand the authority of those
that are elected in the positions
in which they're able to fill
and how it affects our justice department.
It's important that we understand this.
I want you to think about this one,
the matter of partiality.
Today, many people wanna use the word racism,
and I understand the term,
and I understand why they use it.
I use the word partiality because it's a Bible word,
and I believe that partiality defines much clearer
the subject than just racism,
because partiality can be done
without race being even in the conversation.
You can be partial towards someone
because of their economic status,
though they are the same race as you are
from that perspective of what they have
as race being their calling card.
You can have prejudice or partiality towards someone
because of their religious identification.
We see this all around the globe, by the way.
You see it over in Asia,
and you see it in Africa, the Middle East.
You see people that have all of this partiality
based on the economic status
and the religious identification,
and they all have the same skin color,
but they're partial, they're partial.
So the Bible says this in Acts 17,
and it's so important that we understand this this morning,
and hath made of one blood all nations of men
for to dwell in all the face of the earth
and hath determined the times before appointed
and the bounds of their habitation.
James 2, verses eight and nine, the Bible says this.
If you fulfill the royal law according to the scripture,
thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself, ye do well.
But if you have respect to persons,
ye commit sin and are convinced of the law as transgressors.
This thing of partiality is important
that we understand as biblical people.
Can I help you understand an important truth
that so many have missed, I believe, today,
and that is this.
Darwinian evolution ideology
promotes further perpetuates partiality.
I put up here on a screen a picture of the book
that Darwin wrote.
Many of you would know it by the name
On the Origin of Species,
and really that's the only title that they want us today
to really be aware of,
but I want you to understand the full title of that book
goes on to say, or the preservation of favored races
in the struggle of life.
That's the full title of the book.
You look at me like it's strange, I didn't make that up.
It's the full title of the book.
Wow is right, because Darwinian evolution
permeates our society.
And Darwinian evolution ideology
not only permeates our society,
but it influences our perspective,
and it changes how we approach things.
Listen, the second book that he wrote,
The Descent of Man,
I didn't take a picture of that one and put it there,
but I'm telling you that Darwinian evolution
is a major, major contributing factor to this subject.
I was blown away when I visited England several years ago,
and some of you have been to England, you know this.
but when I was in England, I was absolutely blown away
by the fact that while I was there,
that I got some pounds, and when I got the pounds,
that Charles Darwin is on one of their notes.
We have folks on our notes,
and we talk about the presidents that are on the notes,
and so on and so forth, on our paper bills,
and even on our coins, and one of those,
I think it was a 10, a British pound, a 10 currency,
and it had Charles Darwin's face on that bill.
It's sad.
Can I tell you this?
Partiality existed way before Charles Darwin, okay?
Just as it said in James two and verse number nine,
the truth of being in sin if you show partiality,
partiality in racism, it's sinful, it's wicked.
It's been going on for centuries.
Jesus was the one that said in John four,
thy must needs go through Samaria.
Why did he have to go through Samaria?
Why does that interaction take place?
Well, because the Jewish people hated the Samaritans.
They were partial towards them,
and Jesus was showing them that we're all of one blood.
Jesus further said in Acts one and verse number eight,
ye shall be witnesses unto me both in Jerusalem, Judea,
help me, Samaria.
Why did he say Samaria?
Why do you think he said Samaria?
Because he's talking to Jewish people,
and they had to know that the Samaritans
also had to hear the gospel.
As much as Darwinian evolution ideology
further perpetuates the idea of partiality,
I mention this.
Listen, it existed before Charles Darwin,
but at the time of Charles Darwin and his prominence
and all that he did, can I tell you what happened?
All of a sudden, especially men like Adolf Hitler
and others, they took and they ran with the fact
that now science and biology supports my wicked heart
and my agenda to be able to have this perspective
and to kill masses of people.
Until then, partiality existed,
but now all of a sudden, it could be justified
in the wicked hearts of mankind
because science supports it.
No, science doesn't.
We're all of one blood.
I'm thankful for that.
God created man in his own image.
As much as we find that Darwinian evolution perpetuates,
I want you to understand that the Bible,
that the gospel and biblical Christianity is the answer.
Why is it the answer?
Well, notice he said in Mark 16 and verse 15,
and he said unto them, go ye into all the world
and preach the gospel to every creature.
We find that the Bible tells us
in the book of Colossians chapter three
and verse number 11, where there's neither Greek nor Jew,
circumcision nor uncircumcision,
barbarian, Scythian, bond nor free,
but Christ is all and in all.
What's he talking about?
In the church, listen, we're made up
of different nationalities or backgrounds,
but we're saved by the blood of Christ
and we're brothers and sisters in Christ.
The gospel of Jesus Christ and the truth
of biblical Christianity will absolutely
be the answer to partiality.
I wanna remind you that in the book of Revelation
chapter five and verse number nine,
the Bible says they sang a new song
and here's what they said.
Thou art worthy to take the book
and to open the seals thereof for thou was slain
and has redeemed us to God by thy blood
out of notice every kindred and tongue
and people and nation.
Hallelujah.
I love our church.
I mentioned this often to individuals
about the diversity of our church.
I absolutely love it.
I don't know today as we'd go around
and determine where people are originally from,
there'd be a number of nations that are represented
and I love that.
You know why I love it so much?
That's what heaven's gonna be like.
The gospel in biblical Christianity
is the answer for partiality.
Listen, our world is trying to use this thing
of partiality specifically in America
of racism to divide, to cause hatred
and we must understand that the Bible speaks on this.
The Bible speaks on this.
It's not a political issue.
Think about this, the matter of,
this is the last one I'm gonna deal with,
the matter of debt.
You know how in debt we are as a nation?
It's absolutely sickening how in debt we are
and here's what the Bible says in Proverbs 22 in verse seven,
the rich ruleth over the poor
and the borrower is servant to the lender.
As a nation, I'm gonna put up some numbers here
and it's hard for us to understand these
but as a nation, our current debt is nearing $36 trillion.
That's a lot of money.
To be honest with you, Ron,
I can't even think about that kind of number.
I don't even know how many zeros there are.
Actually, I was working on it this week
trying to figure it out.
I was trying to do math on these numbers
and you know what the calculator did?
Error.
There ain't enough space on the calculator.
36 trillion is what we're nearing.
This year alone, $892 billion to pay
just for the interest of our debt
and for some reason, we can't help people
that were devastated by a hurricane.
You understand what I'm saying?
They made it political but there's a biblical truth
that the borrower is servant to the lender
and we need some fiscal responsibility.
Listen, how does it work in your home?
You have to be responsible to pay your bills.
How does it work as a church?
Why do we have a budget as a church?
Why don't we just spend and spend and spend
and borrow and borrow and borrow
and spend and spend and spend?
No, we have to be fiscally responsible.
In my home, I have to be fiscally responsible.
Has there ever been a situation where you said in your home,
hey, we don't have the money to do this.
We can't afford this right now.
Why?
Because you're being fiscally responsible.
As a nation, we've got out of control with debt.
Here's an interesting calculation.
If you suppose that every $1 equals one minute,
that equals 68,493 years.
If we could talk about our debt in terms of time
because 36 trillion is so, 68,000 years,
that's 10 times, almost 10 times
as long as the earth's been around.
Unbelievable.
I want you to understand this morning
that these matters are biblical matters.
But all of these matters that I touched on,
they've tried to politicize.
It's not an exhaustive list.
Can I tell you that Israel is a biblical matter?
It's not a political issue, it's a biblical issue.
Amen?
Can I tell you that borders, immigration,
you start talking, they're all,
listen, I don't have time in one service
to deal with all of it, but you have a Bible.
Go home and study your Bible.
Go home and figure out the principles
that God has given us that are to influence
how we cast our ballot because if we're Bible believers,
then the Bible has to influence every part of me.
Not just Sunday morning, not just Sunday night,
not just Wednesday night, but every part of me
is impacted and affected because I am a child of God,
I'm a follower of Jesus Christ.
Now, let me change gears just for a moment
and deal with this second.
I told you my points were long.
Number two this morning, biblical principles
to cope with election results.
You say, pastor, why are you dealing with this?
Well, because my head's not in the sand.
My head's not in the sand and I've heard people
for years discussing whether there's election interference,
election fraud, and so on and so forth,
whatever term you wanna use, I've heard many of them
and I'm aware of how some have taken that perspective.
But I want you to understand that there are
biblical principles that we must be aware of
that will help me cope with the results of an election.
Can I remind you this morning that there are some things
that are outside of your control and there are some things
that are outside of my control, but there's absolutely
nothing outside of the control of my God.
Nothing is outside of his control.
So we must remember this morning that all things
are within the control of God.
And I can rejoice in that.
Listen, if I had to sit around and worry about
all the things that some of you have shared with me
about election fraud, interference, and all that stuff,
I'd have less hair than I have.
I'd have more, if I had any more, it'd be gray.
I'd be worried all the time.
I'd have all kinds of, but listen,
I don't have to worry about it.
I told you last week about the friends, the niece of Jackie
who told me about in Washington State, you have to write
the particular party of the vote that you're casting
on the outside of the envelope before you mail it in.
And here's what I told her when she shared that with me.
I said, listen, if I didn't know Jesus,
if I didn't know God, it would drive me insane
to think about those things that are going on.
But I know God.
I know God.
And he gave me a peace.
I was reading this morning in John 14,
where Jesus said, my peace I give unto you.
Not as the world giveth.
Man, I have the peace of God
which passeth all understanding.
Can I remind you this morning that when we talk about
these election things and we talk about interference
and fraud and all of those things,
we're looking just at this plane.
We're looking at the temporal.
We're removing the eternal God who's in control.
And we're saying, listen, it's not fair.
That's what people want to say.
Can I remind you of the.
trial that Jesus had? Was it fair? Can I remind you of the trial that Stephen had? Was it
fair? But God was in control. Can I tell you this? There are some times I believe with
all my heart that sometimes a way, a way, that God judges a nation is through its leadership.
So how do I cope? What are some biblical principles? Number one, let me give you this verse. I'll
share some things here in just a moment, but let me give you a couple of verses. Psalm
75, verses 6 and 7. For promotion cometh neither from the east nor from the west nor from the
south. But God is the judge. Notice this. He putteth down one and setteth up another.
So really it comes down to this. Do we believe the Bible? Do we believe these verses of Scripture?
Do we believe that God's in control? Let me remind you of Daniel 4 and verse 17. The
Bible says this matter is by the decree of the watchers and the demand by the word of
the holy ones to the intent that the living may know. What is it that the living may know?
That the Most High ruleth in the kingdom of men and giveth it to whomsoever He will and
setteth up over it the basest of men. The question is do we believe the Bible? He said
in Daniel 4, 17 that the living may know. As far as I know, we're all still alive here
this morning. And that the living may know what? That the Most High ruleth in the kingdom
of men. Listen, God did not create and then take His hands off. God is still very much
involved in the affairs of mankind. God is still a very present help in the time of trouble.
I'm thankful that God did not just remove His hands after creation, but that He withholds
all things by the power of His hand and that He's involved. He knows. Listen, if it wasn't
the truth, then prayer would never have been given to us to pray to the God who's able
to do exceedingly abundantly above all that we ask or think. But He gave us prayer because
He's actively involved in the affairs of mankind. Notice this truth in Proverbs 21 and verse
number 1, the King's heart is in the hand of the Lord. As the rivers of water, He turneth
it, the King's heart, whithersoever He will. So the question basically is this this morning,
do we believe God? Do we believe God? Do we believe that in 2024 that God is still on
His throne? Do we believe in 2024 that God still has a plan and that God is still able,
listen, whoever you want to accuse of whatever you want to accuse them of with regard to the
results of an election, I want to remind you that God's in control. Here's the thing that's
important for us to understand. There were people that tried to bring me, I mean, I had
videos sent to me in 2020 and I had documents printed out and sent to me in 2020. I had
videos, Bart, that were, I mean, like 40 hours long of videos. I ain't watching them, man.
I don't have time for that. I'm just being honest with you. You say, I watched every
single one of them. I'm sorry. I'm being honest. I'm sorry. Because what it did is it messed
with your head. And it caused you to not have a right view of God. Because even if all that
stuff happened, you know what the bottom line is? God allowed it to happen. God allowed
it to happen. And we must acknowledge that this morning. So, what do we do? How do we
respond? How is it that we can cope with the results of an election? See, the reality is
that in America, elections have boiled down basically to two individuals or two parties.
Okay? And so, I'm not here to say how or who or any of that sort of thing. I'm simply giving
you biblical principles. I think that as we study our Bibles, we have an individual responsibility.
But the reality is that the one that has to be able to cope with the election results
is the one that's in that situation. They're going to begin to look at some of these things
and maybe their particular candidate didn't win and they wanted them to or whatever the
case may be. But I have to acknowledge that God's on His throne, that God's in control.
And therefore, number one, I trust the Lord. I trust the Lord. Can I tell you this morning,
can I remind you this morning, that as Bible believers, our hope is not in the White House.
Sometimes I fear that we say that but don't really believe that. Our hope is not in the
White House. Our hope is not in the State House. Our hope is not in Wall Street. Our
hope is in Jesus Christ, who is King of Kings. And for that, we trust Him. We trust Him.
We come to that place where we say, I'm trusting the Lord, that His plan is perfect, that He
knows what He is doing. Blessed, in Psalm 2, in verse number 12, blessed are all they
that put their trust in Him. Psalm 20, in verse number 7, some trust in chariots and
some in horses, but we will remember the name of the Lord our God. Listen, don't be putting
your trust and confidence in the wrong thing. Isaiah talks about the fact that they were
trusting in Egypt. That's the picture of the world. They weren't trusting the living God.
They were trusting in Egypt. Jeremiah 17, in verse number 7, it says, blessed is the
man that trusteth in the Lord and whose hope the Lord is. There was a recent, I'll just
say this to be pretty generic about it, but in the time that I've been here, this is the
fourth election cycle, presidential election cycle, that I've had the privilege of being
the pastor through. And the reality is that during one of those, somebody that's not a
member of our church, never really attended our church, but a Christian worker, actually,
from another church and heavily involved in some ministry things, after the result
of one of those elections over the four cycles that I've been here, sent an email with this
verse of Scripture and said, we have hope because of the result of the election. And
I was absolutely furious. And I sent the individual an email and I said, listen, we have hope
because Jesus is on His throne. Listen, if on November 6th you become depressed, your
eyes aren't on Jesus. You're not trusting the Lord like you should be. Because regardless
of what the result of the election is, my God's still on the throne. And my God still
has a purpose. And my God still has a plan. And He's still going to use us. And by the
way, one day I'm going to heaven. Hallelujah. This world is not my home. I'm just a passing
through. My treasures are laid up somewhere beyond the blue. That's what the songwriter
said. And we need to start living like that. But the reality is that if we take the perspective
that God is in control, only if my candidate wins, you are not understanding the truth
of the Bible. You cannot say, because my candidate wins, that God is in control. And
then if your candidate loses, you say, well, God must not be in control. They did this,
they did… No, no, no, no, no. God is in control regardless. And we have to understand
that. So what do I do? Number one, I trust in the Lord. Number two, I rejoice. I rejoice.
You know what Jesus said in Luke? Those disciples came back because the spirits were made subject
to them, and they were rejoicing, man. They saw the power of God demonstrated. And Jesus
said this, don't rejoice in that. But rather rejoice, why? Because your names are written
in the book. Listen, this morning, it does not matter who wins an election in this nation
with regard to my eternity. I'm going to rejoice. Psalm 5 and verse number 11, but
let all those that put their trust in thee, what? Rejoice. I said, number one, we must
trust Him. But if I put my trust in Him, then I must rejoice. Let them ever shout for joy,
because thou defendest them. Let them also that love thy name be joyful in thee. Can
I tell you that really, if you study the church history, there has never been a nation like
our nation that has had as much liberty and freedom for a church as we have experienced.
And you know what's happening? We're doing less for God today than we ever have. There
literally, last week, Brother Hummel stood in this pulpit and said, America is now in
the place where we need missionaries to come to her. Where we used to be the number one
sending mission field of the, or mission sender of the entire world. And guess what?
England was that at one point. And if you go to England today, you find that church
after church after church has been turned into pubs, has been turned into apartments,
has been turned into mosques. And guess what has to happen in England? We have missionaries
that we support from the U.S. going to England. America's not far behind. But you know what
I'm going to do? I'm going to trust in the Lord. And I'm going to rejoice because my
God's on His throne. And I'm going to rejoice because God is able. Listen, can I say this?
Number three, continue.
It's been our theme for this whole year.
It's been our theme.
The truth of 2 Timothy 3, verses 13 and 14.
But evil men and seducers shall wax in worse and worse,
deceiving and being deceived.
Isn't it interesting that God reveals that truth to us?
And then right after revealing that truth to us
in verse 13 says, but continue, in verse 14.
But the evil men are waxing worse and worse.
I mean, they're deceiving and they're being deceived.
I mean, it's bad, it's perilous times
is how it starts in chapter three in verse one.
And all of this is going on.
What are we supposed to do?
Continue.
Continue in what?
Continue thou in the things which thou hast learned
and has been assured of, knowing of whom thou hast
learned them.
And we find that as we look at this truth,
that we as the church of God, we must continue.
We don't give up.
We don't run for the hills.
We don't, do you remember what Jesus said in Matthew 16?
He said, I will build my church.
And the gates of hell shall not prevail against it.
This morning, we must put our trust in the Lord.
We must rejoice in him.
And we must continue until the trumpet sounds.
I believe that one day, and I think it's soon
that the trumpet of the Lord is gonna sound.
We're gonna be raptured out of here.
But until then, God's given us a responsibility.
And we must understand that the Bible must influence
how we cast a ballot.
But then the Bible must also influence on how I cope
with the results of an election.
This morning, I'm gonna use a quote from someone
that perhaps you've heard the quote before.
I thought it was so pertinent to our thought this morning.
But Booker T. Washington said this,
a lie doesn't become truth, wrong doesn't become right,
and evil doesn't become good,
just because it's accepted by a majority.
What defines, what is truth?
Well, Jesus is truth.
But then he said that he gave us his word,
and his word is truth.
He said, sanctify them through thy word.
Thy word is truth.
We must filter everything through the Bible.
It means that we have to be Bible students.
We have to know our Bibles.
It says here that wrong doesn't become right.
Who defines wrong?
Who defines right?
God does.
Remember the one came to Jesus and said, good master?
He said, why callest thou me good?
There's one good, that's God.
Well, Jesus is God, and he defines what's good,
and he defines what's evil.
And here it says that the third part here,
evil doesn't become good.
I understand this morning,
we start getting into, well, the majority.
It's never been about the majority.
We don't make decisions based upon the majority.
We make decisions based upon the truth of God's word.
And so I submit to you this morning,
as I used this line at the very beginning,
that your Bible and my Bible should influence my ballot.
There are biblical principles that we must understand
in casting a ballot.
We must no longer allow the politicians
to hijack biblical truth and politicize it
and then demand that you don't speak about it
and that I don't speak about it,
because their Bible matters.
And if we're Christians, if we're followers of Jesus Christ,
the Bible must influence how I vote.
It influences how I live.
And then how do we cope with it?
Say, I don't know what's gonna happen.
You don't know what's gonna happen,
and if you keep watching the polls every day,
you're gonna go absolutely insane.
I'm telling you, it's crazy.
So you know what I do?
I just choose to focus on Jesus.
I sat here this morning and I was praying for our service.
I sat right here and I was praying this morning
for a while in the sanctuary.
It was just, you know, we pray,
we're in the presence of God.
I was just thanking the Lord for how great He is
and the peace that He gives and the joy that He gives.
We live in a world that's full of turmoil,
chaos, confusion, but God has given us the truth.
And this morning, we must allow the truth
to impact every area of our lives.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
We thank You for Your Word.
This morning, we looked at so many verses of Scripture
and quickly deal with so many matters that we face.
And God, I hope that this morning,
every individual has been able to see the truth
that these are biblical matters.
God, I pray that You would help us to remember
with great clarity and conviction
the reason that You've left us here,
to be Your witnesses, to be Your ambassadors.
You've given to us the ministry of reconciliation.
God, I pray that You would help each and every one of us,
Lord, to keep our eyes on Jesus.
Let come what may, You rule and You reign.
You are King forever and ever.
And yes, we live in this incursed world
and we're ruled by other humans
because long ago, we rejected,
humanity rejected Your rulership.
And God, we pray that You would help us
to be the salt and the light You've called us to be,
that we would trust You, rejoice in You,
and that we would continue.
I pray that You'd use us for Your honor and for Your glory.
Help us, Lord, to be people of the book.
Well, thank You, God, for what You'll do
in this moment of invitation.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand?