11 and I'll be looking at verses 23 through 31. I mentioned this morning at the end of the service that we would
be observing the Lord's Supper this evening and it's been a long time since we've observed the Lord's Supper and
we
Are now going to look at this passage of scripture
Typically as we observe the Lord's Supper, I'll preach a message and then we'll read this passage before we distribute the elements
But with it being as long as it has been I thought it appropriate for us to revisit the passage and spend a little bit
More time just going systematically through the passage of scripture
We understand as New Testament believers as even as I said this morning
That the Word of God is the sole authority for our faith in our practice
And we believe biblically that the Lord Jesus Christ has given two ordinances to the local church
one is believers baptism by immersion and number two is the Lord's Supper as
You study the scriptures you will find that God has provided us with the instruction for purpose of and
Practice of these two ordinances. I'm thankful that he's given us the truth that we have in his Word with regard to these
instructions and the purpose of these
Practices if you will and we find it's here in 1st Corinthians chapter 11 that we really have the most detailed
Instruction regarding the Lord's Supper
We understand some things about the church in Corinth and they weren't always doing things the way that they were supposed to be doing things
We find at the church in Corinth was a church. That was a carnal church
It was a divided church and all sorts of things going on
In fact leading up to the text of scripture that we're going to look at this evening
Paul says on two occasions I praise you not and
There were they were doing some things
Not
Appropriately and so Paul says I praise you not the way that you're doing it isn't right
So I'm gonna give you instruction and really to me that's a blessing. I'm so thankful for it
You know, it's one thing for someone to come and tell you you're doing something wrong
It's another thing for them to give you the instruction on how to get the wrong thing, right?
Amen, you're doing this wrong and then they just walk away and you're like, well, that's wonderful. I'm doing it wrong
I don't know how else to do it, right?
But God is faithful to give us the word to give us instruction
And we find here this detailed instruction with regard to observing the Lord's Supper in verse number 23
Notice what the Bible says 1st Corinthians 11 and verse 23 for I have received of the Lord
That which also I delivered unto you
and so again as we would be mindful of the truth even that we're dealing with this morning and we'll continue as we look at
the book of Colossians
With this this truth and the source of truth and Paul is saying listen, this isn't just my opinion
This didn't originate with me. I've received this from the Lord and I'm delivering it unto you
He says this that the Lord Jesus the same night in which he was betrayed took bread and when he had given thanks
He break it and said take eat
This is my body which is broken for you this do in remembrance of me
After the same manner also he took the cup when he had sup saying this cup is the New Testament in my blood this do
Ye as oft as you drink it in remembrance of me for as often as you eat this bread and drink this cup
You do show the Lord's death till he come
Wherefore whosoever shall eat this bread and drink this cup of the Lord
unworthily shall be guilty of the body and blood of the Lord, but let a man examine himself and so let him eat of that bread
And drink of that cup for he that eateth and drinketh unworthily eateth and drinketh damnation to himself not
Discerning the Lord's body for this cause many are weak and sickly among you and many sleep
For if we would judge ourselves, we should not be judged if you're taking notes and you've seen in the bulletin as well
We got the sermon titles in the bulletins as we're using bulletins again this do in remembrance of me
This do in remembrance of me as we first kind of by way of introduction speak about the elements and what they represent
We understand that in verse 25
Excuse me
Verse 24 and then in verse number 25 God gives us the Apostle Paul is sharing with the believers in Corinth here the elements the bread
of course representing the body of Christ and
We of course would use unleavened bread because he the Lord Jesus Christ is without sin
We find that leaven throughout the scriptures is a type or picture of sin and therefore we would use an unleavened bread
The cup as mentioned in verse number 25
Represents the precious blood of the Lord Jesus Christ. I'm so thankful for the blood of Christ that was shed the price of our redemption
We understand again that we would use unfermented grape juice again because our Lord is without sin and
You would find that the process or fermentation is a process biblically when you look at those things and the type
of sin and what-have-you and so our Lord is sinless and
He is he was tempted in all points such as we are yet
Without sin and what a wonderful blessing as we think about the elements that will be
Partaken this evening as we observe the Lord's Supper
It's important for us to understand that these elements do not mysteriously
Magically turn into anything other than what they are
it's an unleavened cracker and it's unfermented grape juice and it is a
Representation of the body and blood of the Lord Jesus Christ. It's we understand that biblically
there are some groups of people that would teach that the
Substances the elements that they change into something other than what they are
And we need to be careful that we understand that the Lord is giving us this as a table of remembrance
And we'll look at these things in just a moment
As we go through the text of Scripture, but he was crucified once
Amen this man after he'd offered himself one sacrifice for sins forever and
He said on the cross of Calvary it is
Finished these elements cannot save you
Amen, you can take as many unleavened crackers and unfermented grape juice as you want
It's not going to cause you to be saved. It's not going to redeem you and
the reality is that
These elements that we've purchased and that we use there is absolutely zero saving power in those elements
We're saved through the blood of Christ the precious blood of Christ again, it's a representation
and so it's an important that we would understand that truth this evening a
picture if you will a
Memorial making known to us and being mindful of what the Lord Jesus Christ did on the cross of Calvary
We could ask ourselves this question again by way of introduction
Not only would do what are the elements and what do they represent?
But who is it that should participate we find that this ordinance is to the local church
We mentioned that just a few moments ago that I believe and as you study the scriptures
You'll find there are two ordinances for the local church and there's some Bible truth
That God gives us with regard to the local church who can be a member of a local church
Well, we believe that saved people are members of a local church. Amen
You come to me and say pastor. I want to join your church and I want to be a part of this local assembly
I want to have my membership here
Well, it's not a club that you pay some dues and you kind of just join up and be part of the club
No membership in a local church is an important thing. No doubt
It's a biblical thing, but we find that membership in a local church. There's proper candidates for membership
Are you saved have you been scripturally baptized?
and if you have been saved and you've been scripturally baptized then you are eligible to be a member of a local church and
Those are the conversations that I have with individuals as they would come and speak to me about membership here and we'd have those conversations
It's a great opportunity to speak about
Just our our testimony and sharing what Christ has done in our lives and what a blessing that is
And so we know that this is for the local church and the Bible speaks about this truth in verse 27 where it says wherefore
Whosoever shall eat this bread and drink this cup of the Lord
Unworthily shall be guilty of the body and blood of the Lord and then it talks about examination again
We'll deal with that as we get into the message this evening, but we find that again. It's for the
The believers it's for those that are born again saved baptized members of a local church. There are some and I don't know
You perhaps you've been exposed to some that have this idea of a close or a closed
communion as they would call it or maybe they would use the terminology of an open communion and
Someone that would have an idea of an open communion
they would carry with it the idea that man anyone can partake of it and really they would not give any type of
instruction as to who it's really for and
Someone that would believe and I would fall in this category of a close communion
If you're saved baptized member of a church, maybe you're not a member at this moment
But you're actively looking for membership and praying and asking the Lord to provide direction with regard to membership
You're a member of another local
Independent church that stands for the truth of the Bible then there's close fellowship
I visited churches in the past and you show up if we had visitors here from out of town that were members of a good
Solid Bible believing church and we're observing the Lord's Supper. I would not tell them. No, you cannot partake
I believe in close fellowship if you will or a close communion. And so as we look at these
truths and we look at these
Introductory kind of comments a final question that could be asked is this how often should we observe the Lord's Supper?
Well, the Bible doesn't give us any specified timeline.
In fact, in verse number 26 of the text of Scripture, the Bible says for as often as
ye eat this bread and drink this cup.
And so it does not tell us specifically that you're to observe the Lord's Supper every
week, every month, every quarter.
It just doesn't tell us.
It says as often as you do.
And so I believe that it's important that we observe the Lord's Supper with regularity.
Of course, with this situation that's gone on in the last calendar year, we've had difficulties
with regard to some of the things that have been said to us with regard to transmission
and so on and so forth.
And so we have sought to take certain precautions and we have been able to secure these particular
items that we can distribute and not have individuals passing them and everyone touching
them and so on and so forth.
And I am thankful for the opportunity to be able to have that.
And I appreciate the opportunity to observe the Lord's Supper.
I think it's an important thing.
It's a God-mandated ordinance for the local church and it's important.
And we understand as we approach the Lord's Supper, as we approach the table, there's
a level of sobriety that comes with it and a sobering understanding of what these elements
represent and what our salvation really cost the Lord Jesus Christ.
And so as we think about this passage of Scripture and we think about these specifics that are
given and some of the truth that is revealed to us, I want to just three quick thoughts
this evening with regard to the purpose.
Why is it that the Lord gave us this ordinance to be observed by the local church?
In verses 24 and 25, I believe that we could look at and refer to the Lord's Supper as
being a table of remembrance.
A table of remembrance.
You know that as human beings we are prone to forget.
We really are.
And sometimes we forget entirely.
We just cannot remember.
Other times it's not so much that we've completely forgotten something, it's just not at the
forefront of our memory.
We're not living with a daily awareness of that particular truth or that particular thing.
And I believe that as we look at this passage of Scripture and we see these words at the
end of verse 24 and 25 where it says, in remembrance of me, in remembrance of me, you'll be mindful
of the nation of Israel.
They, of course, had been given instruction.
In fact, God instructed Moses to give the children of Israel this instruction in Deuteronomy
chapter number six, after you come into a land and you are in a land and you're living
in a place and there's vineyards that you did not plant, there's houses that you did
not build, beware lest thou forget the Lord.
You can ask yourself the question as you look at the history of Israel, you can say, how
could they forget?
But you know what Jeremiah said?
God's indictment against the children of Israel, against Judah in particular, my people have
forgotten me days without number.
Wow.
They're not living with the daily awareness of who God is and what God has done for them.
And there are times in our lives that if someone were to stop us and say, hey, are you saved?
Are you redeemed?
Man, you, yeah, absolutely.
But sometimes in the rut of life and you're dealing with all sorts of things, maybe you're
not just as aware of it as you should be.
I have, I don't know, maybe I'm just weird.
I try to do things creative.
Now I'm not a very creative person, but I try to do things creative.
And so, you know, they tell you I'm going to wear a mask, I'm going to wear a mask that
has a message on it that I'm going to try to share something about the Lord.
And Jesus loves you, Jesus saves, I have them, I try to use them.
In fact, most always when I put a mask on, it's one of those two.
I have a, how many of you have like, you know, your online banking and they want to
give you a password, but then sometimes they give you a catchphrase, give me a phrase.
And so when you call in, they want to know, okay, tell me what your phrase is.
It's some manner, some way in which they're identifying your identity, secure.
So I had to call the bank the other day.
My code word is, I'm going to tell like you guys, listen, if you steal my identity, it
is the Lord bless you, amen.
All those people watching online, they're getting all excited, you know, my code word
is saved.
I'm trying to be creative on picking that word.
Why?
Because it means something.
Saved from what?
So I called the bank on Friday and that guy gets on the phone and he's going to help me
out.
And of course he knows the answer and he gets excited on the other end of the phone.
He says, oh man, this is good.
He's like, I want you to shout this answer.
That's what he said to me.
He said, I just want you to shout it.
He said, what's your code word?
I said, saved.
He said, man, that's good.
I don't know who the guy is, but I can tell you something that may be in your occupation
and the monotony of life, something like that could happen in your life.
And as a believer, you could be encouraged.
I think on Friday afternoon, when I spoke to that man, I think I encouraged him.
I don't even know who he is just by using that word.
But all I'm saying about that is that, listen, this doing remembrance of me in understanding
what the Lord Jesus Christ did for us, remembering the cost of our redemption, remembering that
I'm a child of the King.
I mean, the fact that my citizenship is in heaven.
We sing with the kids, I'm going to heaven, can't wait.
There's some of God's people, they can't sing that honestly, because they got some tent
stakes driven into this earth.
They're not anxious to go to heaven, honestly.
We sing with the kids, gonna see Jesus, can't wait, amen, right?
You know, when you think about the reality of it, and you think about this pause, this
doing remembrance of me, that's why it's so important to walk with God every day.
Because every day when we walk with God, I hope that you thank God for your salvation.
And you can spend a few moments just rejoicing in what he did for you.
He did for you what no one else could ever do for you, what you could not do for yourself.
As I was speaking with a man this week, and I talked to him about what Jesus did for us,
I said, listen man, I'm a sinner, I can't die for you and save you.
Me dying for you does nothing for you.
And you can't die for me.
But God in flesh, the Lord Jesus Christ, he died for me.
What are we remembering?
Well, notice in verse 24, when he had given thanks, he break it and said, take, eat.
This is my body which is broken for you, this doing remembrance of me.
I'm not sure how often you read the gospel accounts, especially the latter chapters that
deal with the crucifixion, and how that Jesus suffered for your redemption, for my redemption.
The way in which they smoked him, the things that they did, the torment that they tried
to inflict upon him.
He said, this is my body, take, eat, this is my body which is broken for you, this doing
remembrance of me.
After the same manner also, he took the cup when he had supped, saying, this cup is the
New Testament in my blood, this do you as often as you drink it in remembrance of me.
The plan of redemption required a price to be paid.
The Bible tells us in 1 Peter that Jesus is the lamb that was slain before the foundation
of the world, that you're redeemed not with corruptible things, but were redeemed with
the precious blood of Christ, as of a lamb without blemish.
Oh, I'm so thankful for the blood of Christ.
There's no other way to be saved, amen?
And so this do in remembrance of me, we're being mindful of those hours in which the
Lord Jesus Christ hung upon the cross of Calvary.
And what was it that kept him there?
Love.
Understanding that he was paying a price to redeem mankind.
This do in remembrance of me.
Not only is it a table of remembrance, but I believe as we look at the passage of Scripture,
that it's a table of expectation.
In verse 26, we touched on the first portion of this verse a moment ago when we spoke about
how often we observe the Lord's Supper, but the Bible says for as often as you eat this
bread and drink this cup, notice what it says, you do show the Lord's death till he come.
Aren't you thankful that he's coming again?
Hallelujah.
I mean, what great truth.
I mean, the reality of the truth that is before us of the soon return of our Lord and
Savior Jesus Christ, the blessed hope, as it would be referred to as Paul is writing
to Titus, and we find that for us as we would look to the Scriptures and we'd understand
the promise that Jesus himself gave, I will come again and receive you unto myself that
where I am, there ye may be also.
Isn't that precious?
See, I wonder how often, listen, I believe.
today that if I were to contact you at any point during the week and I were to
stop you in the middle of whatever you're doing and say, hey listen, do you
think Jesus could come today? I think every single one of you would say yes,
myself included. But you know there's some times in life that we just get so
bogged down with the things of the world and the things that are going on that
we're not living with that expectation that Jesus could come at any moment.
When we observe the Lord's Supper, not only are we remembering a table of
remembrance of what the Lord Jesus Christ did for us and the price that was
paid for our redemption, but it's this table of expectation that my Savior's
coming back for me. I mean hallelujah, what a blessing. We don't know when, but
we can rest assured that he's coming back. There's not one promise of God
that will not be fulfilled. We understand that God is
not a man that he should lie, amen, and what God says he will fulfill. We spent
time last Sunday evening, the entirety of our time in fact, looking at that truth
from Genesis 17 and verse number 1 when God appeared to Abram and said, I am the
Lord God Almighty, El Shaddai. We spent the entirety of our time last Sunday
evening looking at that truth so that we could lay a foundation for the remaining
verses in Genesis 17 and really set a foundation not only for Abraham and the
truth that would be revealed there in Genesis 17, but even for our own lives.
Because on about a dozen occasions, God is going to tell Abraham, I will do this.
He's the Lord God Almighty. He's able and he promised that he's going to come back
for us. And so we find this evening that as we observe the Lord's Supper and what
a privilege and blessing it is to be reminded, remember as human beings we're
prone to forget and we're reminded of what Christ has done for us. We have this
expectation that we're showing the Lord's death till he come. Wouldn't it be
wonderful if he came tonight? I mean honestly, man what a wonderful truth of
the Word of God, the imminent return of Christ to table not only of remembrance
and expectation, but as we look forward into the passage of the table of
examination. I'll say this, self-examination is not practiced as
often as it should be. Sometimes in our lives we look to perhaps look at
ourselves in a better light than what the reality really is. We mentioned last
week in Colossians 2 how that Paul had a great conflict not only for the
believers in Colossae, but those in Laodicea. We went to Revelation and
looked at the passage of Scripture with the Laodiceans and they had quite a
different perspective with regard to their standing than God did. I mean it
was greatly contrasted what they believed and what God said was the
reality. You didn't know that you were poor, naked, and blind. You thought you're
filled with all these things, you have need of nothing. And so this evening we
think about this truth of this table of examination. The Bible says in verse 28,
but let a man examine himself and so let him eat of that bread and drink of
that cup. For he that eateth and drinketh unworthily eateth and drinketh
damnation to himself, not discerning the Lord's body. He says in verse number 30,
for this cause many are weak and sickly among you and many sleep. And we'd
understand that even as Jesus said to the disciples in John 11 that Lazarus
was asleep, he said he was dead. And here the idea of this passage, if you look at
the truth here, is that there are some that would die. He says for if we would
judge ourselves we should not be judged. This truth of self-examination, let a man
examine himself. You understand the standard is Christ and his Word. Paul
warned the believers in Corinth about comparing themselves among themselves.
He said it's not wise. The standard is Christ. You know that Christ is the
cornerstone. The standard is his Word. The Prophet said that his Word is like a
plumb line. You have a cornerstone and a plumb line, you can build any kind of
building. And the reality is that we have the standard, the Lord Jesus Christ and
his Word. He's given us in his Word the truth with regard to those things that
please him and how we're to live our lives. And we examine ourselves as
individuals based upon the truth of God's Word. But let a man examine
himself. I know that often as we would think about this passage of Scripture
and think about this process of self-examination, perhaps it's a process
in which we're not eager to enter into. But it's a good process for us. It's a
vital process for the child of God to have this this self-examination. But
there's some important aspects to self-examination. Number one, we need to
be honest with ourselves. Truly say, I think Mark you prayed it this morning
from Psalm 139, search us. Show us if there be any wicked way. Right? And we
find that this truth of this self-examination that we would truly ask
the Lord and take his Word and let it search us out. What are some things that
I'm not doing that I need to be doing? What are some things that I'm doing that
I need to stop doing? And we have this process of self-examination. And so as we
look at the passage of Scripture, we rejoice in the instruction that God has
given us, and we rejoice in the process that we have as a local church that
we can observe the Lord's Supper. And as we do, it's not just a tack-on kind of a
thing that we just, you know, have the Lord's Supper. Man, it's a time in which
we're really reflecting, taking some time to really remember what was done to pay
for my salvation. You know, I think if we would have a greater appreciation for
our salvation, it would really impact how we live for God. It really would. See, our
salvation didn't really cost us anything. It cost Christ everything. I'm thankful for
my salvation, and I'm thankful for the table of remembrance, this dew and
remembrance of me. I'm so excited about the return of Christ, and I'm listening
for the trumpet, amen? I mean, honestly, I'm looking for the coming of the Lord. As
we find in the book of James, the coming of the Lord, it draweth nigh. It draweth
nigh. We don't know the hour or the day, but oh, that God would help us to be
motivated in how we live our lives. And as we take this evening, partake of these
elements that we would not only remember what He did for us and what it
cost Him, but we would be mindful of His soon return, and we'd live in accordance
to that truth. This evening, we're going to have a time of examination. I think
it's important before we observe the Lord's Supper that we take a few
moments in the quietness of the moment to just really seek the face of God and
allow God to deal with us. In a moment, Holly will play quietly on the piano.
This idea of drinking and eating unworthily. I was in a church many, many
years ago where someone said, well, I'm not worthy. They just kind of let it pass
by them. Now, if you're not saved, you should not take these elements this
evening. If you've not been born again, it's not for you. And I don't say that
with not being kind. I'm just telling you, it's not for you if you're not
saved. But if we have sin in our lives, it's not that we say, well, I'm not worthy,
I can't partake. Because if we have sin in our lives, we have a forgiving God, as
Holly mentioned in her testimony earlier this evening. I'm so thankful that the
Bible tells in the Old Testament that with thee there is forgiveness. He's a
God ready to pardon, ready to forgive, if we confess our sins. He is faithful and
just to forgive us and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness. The idea is not
to hold on to our sin. As we go through the process of self-examination and God
points something out, it's that we'd confess it and forsake it and have
forgiveness so that we can partake. So, Holly, if you'd come and play quietly on
the piano in just a moment, I'm gonna pray and then we'll have this time of
examination. We'll pray again and then we will partake of the elements. Let's pray.
Father, we love you. We thank you for your Word, the instruction that's contained
therein. We pray, God, that you would help us tonight as we partake of these
elements to be mindful of the price of our redemption. This due and remembrance
of me, the body that was broken for us, the blood that was shed to pay for our
sin, how thankful we are for redemption through Christ. I pray that you'd help us
to have a level of excitement as we have the expectation of your soon return in
these few moments as we have a time of self-examination. I pray, God, that you'd
help us to be transparent and honest before you. God, that we truly allow you
to have your way in our lives. We truly allow you to search us and know us and
show us. And Lord, that we would confess and forsake and receive forgiveness. I
pray, God, that you'd bless the time
I pray that you alone would be honored and glorified for it's in Christ's name. We pray
Amen