to, but then we understand that the Bible says, moreover, it's required in stewards
that a man be found faithful.
God's looking for faithful men, faithful followers of the Lord Jesus Christ, and we can be faithful.
Amen.
And faithful unto death.
Second Corinthians chapter number 12, as we continue to make progress through the book
of Second Corinthians here in 2025, it's the first Sunday of November, and it's hard to
imagine how quickly this year has gone by.
I feel like it was just a few days ago that I was preparing for what the theme would be
for 2025 and getting ready to preach through this book, and here we are.
I've already chosen the theme for next year and got planned what the book is that I'll
preach through and all of that, and we're nearing the end, and someone said, are you
on track?
I'm on track.
And we'll be done by the end of December, and thankful for what we've learned from Second
Corinthians chapter number 12.
In fact, as you begin to understand the truth that God's grace is sufficient, we've kept
that thought before us throughout the calendar year, I'm so thankful for God's grace.
I'm reminded each day that God's grace indeed is sufficient.
We face trials and troubles and difficulties and pressures and all the things that we encounter
in this world, but God said that His grace is sufficient, and I'm thankful for that.
As we come to Second Corinthians chapter number 12, we're reminded of what we've studied the
last couple of Sunday mornings in Second Corinthians chapter number 11, and you'll remember that
Paul begins the text of Scripture by requesting that the believers in Corinth bear with him
for a little while.
He says, bear with me a little in my folly.
We ask the question, we began to answer it as we studied through the 11th chapter of
the book of Second Corinthians, why is it that Paul approached it the way that he did?
We understand that he was exposing the false teachers, but in so doing, it was necessary
that he was able to explain to the believers in Corinth his ministry and his trials.
The false teachers that were present there in Corinth, they were boasters.
We mentioned this last week, and we begin to think about these boasters.
We understand that the result of boasting is pride.
We could say that the root of and the result of is pride, this boasting spirit of these
false teachers, and we find that it was brought to Paul's attention that, well, look at these
Judaizers and look at what they're saying and look at what they're doing.
And so Paul is going to begin to explain, but as we finished last week, we said this,
that Paul said, if I must needs glory, I will glory of the things which concern mine infirmities.
We find that what Paul is really doing as he's put in this position of having to explain
his ministry and explain his trials and really to quote-unquote boast for a little season
for a little while, as you study through the passage, you find that what Paul's really
doing is bringing honor and glory to the Lord Jesus Christ.
And that's what our lives are all about.
We must decrease, but he must increase.
And we find that as we continue into the book of 2 Corinthians, we come here to 2 Corinthians
chapter number 12, and just as we'd say that those boasters, those false teachers were
boasters, there was pride that was the root and the result of their boasting, that we
would say that there was an issue in Corinth with pride.
There was an issue in Corinth with pride.
How do we know that?
Well, we understand that there in the church in Corinth, there were contentions and there
were divisions.
And we find that the apostle Paul, he addresses that in the first letter in very great detail.
There was envy between the members of the church.
And can I say this this morning, that pride continues to be prevalent amongst God's people
even to this very day.
Pride is something that we must deal with.
And we find that as we look at the text of Scripture, that the apostle Paul, in these
verses of Scripture, is going to place a priority on humility.
A priority on humility.
The Bible tells us this in the book of Proverbs, in chapter 13 and verse number 10, it says,
only by pride cometh contention.
You begin to think about contentions and there were contentions in the church in Corinth.
And God's Word says, only by pride cometh contention.
And so we find that there's contentions.
Can I tell you today in the world that we live in, there's contention in our society.
There's contention in churches.
There's contention in families.
There's contention in relationships.
And you begin to think about that contention and it's the result of pride.
The wise man goes on to say in Proverbs chapter 16 and verse 18, that pride goeth before destruction.
And we find that as we study the Word of God, that God places a priority on humility.
We'll look at it here in 2 Corinthians 12, and we'll be reminded of biblical truth throughout
the Word of God that will help us in placing a priority on humility.
Can I tell you this, this morning, when we have a proper perspective of who God is, it
will enable us to have a proper perspective of who we are.
If I do not see God in His proper place, if I do not see God high, holy, and lifted up,
then all of a sudden I get high and I get lifted up and I think that it's about me.
But when I keep my focus on the Lord, when I understand who He is, when I understand
what He's done for me, when I understand that without Him, I'm nothing, I can do nothing,
but it's only by His grace, then it keeps me humble.
Everything that I have, everything that you have, is because of God's favor.
You came here today, you woke up this morning, you were able to get here today because God
enabled you.
When we stand in awe of who He is, it helps us to have a proper view of ourselves.
We find in the text of Scripture, the Bible says in verse number one, it is not expedient
for me, doubtless to glory.
I will come to visions and revelations of the Lord.
I knew a man in Christ about fourteen years ago, whether in the body I cannot tell or
whether out of the body I cannot tell, God knoweth.
Such in one caught up to the third heaven.
And I knew such a man, whether in the body or out of the body, I cannot tell, God knoweth.
Verse four, how that he was caught up into paradise and heard unspeakable words, which
it is not lawful for a man to utter.
Of such in one will I glory, yet of myself I will not glory, but in mine infirmities.
For though I would desire to glory, I shall not be a fool.
When I say this by way of introduction in verse number six, every human being, if you're
honest this morning, you have a desire to glory.
But Paul says, for though I would desire to glory, I shall not be a fool.
Why?
Because it's foolish when we glory in ourselves.
Notice he continues and says this, for I will say the truth, but now I forbear, lest any
man should think of me above that which he seeth me to be, or that he heareth of me.
And lest I should be exalted above measure.
Through the abundance of the revelations, there was given to me a thorn in the flesh,
the messenger of Satan to buffet me, lest I should be exalted above measure.
For this thing I besought the Lord thrice, but that it might depart from me.
And he, the Lord, said unto me, My grace is sufficient for thee, for my strength is
made perfect in weakness.
Most gladly, therefore, will I rather glory in my infirmities, that the power of Christ
may rest upon me.
Therefore I take pleasure in infirmities, in reproaches, in necessities, in persecutions,
in distresses for Christ's sake.
For when I am weak, then am I strong.
This morning, like the Apostle Paul, it is necessary that we place a priority on humility.
As we look at the text of Scripture, it's interesting that in verse number six and seven
and eight, he mentions about this thought of humility, and he says in verse six at the
end of the verse, lest any man should think of me above that which he seeth me to be,
or that he heareth of me.
Can I tell you a trap when we come to the subject of pride and of humility is that an
individual might have this, well, I'm humble, but they take some level of pride in how others
view them or speak of them.
And the Apostle Paul takes this thought of humility to a whole other level because the
Apostle Paul says, I don't want others to think of me above what they ought to think
of me.
We find that the Apostle Paul, as he's writing to his son of the faith, Timothy, he says
that it was a faithful saying and worthy of all acceptation that Christ Jesus came
into the world to save sinners.
And then he says this, of whom I am chief.
The Apostle Paul had a proper view of self.
He knew that he was saved by the grace of God.
He knew that he was serving through the grace and power of God, but he did not want others
to have a improper view of him.
And that's a whole other view and a whole other level of humility.
And that's where we need to be.
This is the priority that Paul places upon humility.
As we look at the text of Scripture, notice with me, first of all,
that Paul was given visions.
Paul was given visions.
As you read verses 1 through 5, which I read by way of introduction,
you find that the Apostle Paul is informing these believers in Corinth
about these visions and revelations.
In fact, we find that the Apostle Paul will say in verse number 7
that there was an abundance of revelations.
We find that the Apostle Paul,
as he speaks about these visions and revelations of the Lord,
he begins to focus in specifically on one specific revelation or vision.
And we find that in verses 2 through 4,
he begins to speak about this specific example.
He tells us the timing and the place of this particular vision.
And we find that he says that it was over 14, above 14 years ago.
Now, consider with me in context, if we're not careful,
there are times in which we look at 2 Corinthians chapter 12
and we think that Paul had some infirmity,
this thorn that we'll get to in just a moment,
and he prayed thrice and it was a really short time
and God said, my grace is sufficient.
But when he's speaking here to the believers in Corinth,
he speaks about these visions and revelations
and he uses an example of 14 years previous.
The specific example that he gives, it's interesting
because when we end at chapter number 11,
we said that Paul was rejoicing in how God had delivered him
from all of his troubles and all of his trials.
And he mentions that in 2 Timothy,
but when he gives a specific example at the end of 2 Corinthians 11,
he goes all the way back to the first time that the Lord delivered him.
And it was when he was in Damascus and he references that first time
and it was the first of many
and how he knew that God was faithful and that God would deliver
and he had proven God over and over.
And he comes to this example that he speaks to the children
or to the people at Corinth about
and he says it was 14 years, above 14 years ago
and he says that he was caught up in the third heaven,
God's dwelling place.
It's pretty amazing that Paul is speaking.
Now remember, the church in Corinth is all kinds of sideways
because of these false teachers that are coming in.
These false teachers say, no, don't listen to Paul.
He doesn't know, he's not really an apostle, so on and so forth.
And they're attacking his person, they're attacking his ministry
and the apostle Paul is giving instruction and he's teaching them
and he comes to the place of defending his position, his ministry
and he's giving and he says,
let me talk to you about revelations and visions.
But it's interesting because as the apostle Paul shares the example,
he says to them, notice with me in verse number four,
how that he was caught up into paradise and heard unspeakable words,
which it is not lawful for a man to utter.
It's very interesting that the apostle Paul says that.
Now we understand that Paul, God used him as the human author
to 14 of our New Testament books.
Amen.
The apostle Paul, he writes to individuals, he writes to churches
and we find that God used him.
We know that all scripture is given by inspiration of God,
but we also know that holy men spake as they were moved by the Holy Ghost.
And so we find that God used the apostle Paul to write much of our New Testament.
And in writing much of our New Testament,
we find that there are times he speaks to the church in Ephesus
about I show you a mystery and he speaks about these mysteries
and it's the truth of progressive revelation
and the truth of God's word being given to God's people.
And I'm so thankful that we have a Bible,
but we find that Paul, he says that he had these visions
and he had these revelations, but he says that he cannot,
it's not lawful for a man to utter.
What's interesting to me because many are being deceived today,
just like people in Corinth were being deceived by these Judaizers
Can I tell you this morning that there are people that are being deceived
by people today that are saying, I had a vision.
I had a revelation.
I was, I died and went to heaven.
And then I came back and I wrote this book.
Listen, if Paul couldn't talk about it, come on.
If Paul couldn't talk about it,
why are you going to listen to some of these people and say,
Why are you going to listen to some of these people on YouTube
and some of these people that are writing books and bestsellers
and all this kind of thing?
No, no, no.
We understand that God has given us all that we need right here.
We're not looking for any more revelation.
We're not looking for any new revelation.
No, he has given to us the whole canon of scripture.
I am thankful that we have a Bible that is,
it's been preserved, providentially preserved.
It was given by inspiration, but it's preserved for us.
And we can know what God wants us to know as we study this book.
And we have people today that are running around.
They want to have a vision.
They want to have a revelation, but they don't want to look at this book.
They then take, perhaps they would look at their vision or their revelation
and they would put it as being superior to God's word.
It's a problem.
The apostle Paul, he was given visions.
Now, let me say this about visions and revelations.
And we understand that Paul is speaking the truth here
and he's giving the truth, but he says,
I can't speak about these things.
And he then begins to talk about glorying in the Lord.
But someone like Paul that had visions or revelations,
if he handled it the way that the Judaizers did,
oh, that would puff him up.
That caused him to be prideful.
That would cause him to boast in the fact that God chose me to give me
and we find that it could lead to pride.
God knows our frame.
Aren't you thankful for that?
He knows your heart.
You know, the Bible tells us that the heart is deceitful
and it's desperately wicked in Jeremiah 17.
And then the question is this, who can know it?
I, the Lord, try the rains.
He tries the heart.
He knows your heart.
You read through the scriptures.
You find that the Bible says that God, he knew their thoughts.
Isn't that amazing?
God knows us.
He knows our hearts.
He knows that we are, he knows our frame.
He knows that we're prone to wander, that we're prone to being prideful.
And we find that in the text of scripture
that Paul speaks about these revelations, these visions.
And so Paul was given a vision,
but we find that Paul was not only given a vision,
but number two, he was given a thorn.
He was given a thorn.
I want you to think about this in comparison this morning.
If you were to be the recipient of a vision of having revelation,
that might cause you to be prideful.
It might cause you to think highly of yourself.
It may cause you to rejoice and to be thankful
that you had this vision or this revelation,
but a thorn, a thorn.
See, oftentimes we take the same approach that the apostle Paul does
in beseeching the Lord to remove the thorn.
And we'll get to that in just a few moments.
But I want you to focus just for a moment here this morning
on this truth that Paul was given a thorn.
We think about this.
Notice what the Bible says in verse number six.
For though I would desire to glory, I shall not be a fool,
for I will say the truth.
But now I forbear, lest any man should think of me above that
which he seemeth me to be, or that he heareth of me.
And lest I should be exalted above measure,
through the abundance of the revelation,
there was given to me a thorn in the flesh.
There was given to me a thorn in the flesh.
Who gave it to him?
God.
Who gave him the visions?
Who gave him the revelations?
God.
But then God gave him a thorn.
Sometimes our perspective in life is not really biblical.
What do I mean by that?
Sometimes when we see this pleasant thing, this good thing,
we say, oh, God gave me this.
But then we see something that from our perspective,
from our vantage point is not that pleasant thing
or that good thing and we are disappointed in it.
We don't rejoice for the thorn like we rejoice for the visions.
But I want you to understand this morning
that the thorn came from God and the thorn was necessary.
And the thorn is reason to rejoice.
Why?
Because the Bible says twice in our passage of Scripture,
lest I should be exalted above measure.
What happens when we get full of pride?
Destroys us.
Can I remind you of what the Bible says?
The Bible says this, God resisteth the what?
The proud.
So Paul says there was given to me a thorn in the flesh.
Why?
Lest I should be exalted above measure.
And if I'm exalted above measure, if I am full of pride, God resists me.
Am I telling you the truth?
God hates pride.
God resisteth the proud,
and what's the rest of the verse?
But giveth grace unto the humble.
Amen?
And we find that as we study the Word of God
and we look at this passage of Scripture,
we find that the Apostle Paul,
he's speaking to the believers in Corinth,
and he says there was given to me
visions and revelations,
but there was given a thorn.
A thorn.
Many have debated what this thorn is.
Many have had their ideas
and they've set forth their reasons
of why they believe what they believe
with regard to the thorn.
We find that Paul simply says
there was given to me a thorn in the flesh.
The messenger of Satan to buffet me
lest I should be exalted above measure.
Isn't it interesting in verse 7
that bookends to the verse of Scripture
are lest I should be exalted above measure.
Do you think God wants us to stay humble?
Absolutely.
Did Nebuchadnezzar find that God
could humble a man?
He found out the hard way, did he not?
And at the end of the whole situation,
did Nebuchadnezzar recognize
that God is able to humble?
But you know what Peter tells us?
Humble yourselves in the sight of God.
And there are some things that God
will bring into your life and into my life
to keep us humble.
Just like God did here for the Apostle Paul,
and the Bible says that He gave him a thorn,
this experience of these visions and revelations
could lead to pride, could lead to glory,
but we find God in His infinite wisdom,
He gave to Paul this thorn in the flesh.
And Paul besought the Lord that this thing would depart
and God in a single word said no,
we'll look at the entirety of it in just a moment,
but we find that God knows best.
God knows what you need.
He knows what I need.
He knows what will happen in our lives
given certain circumstances
and how we might be led to not trust Him like we should.
That we'll come to a place where we begin
to lean on our own understanding like we should not.
Right, you understand what I'm saying?
And God will allow things in our lives.
God will allow things to cause us to come to a place,
listen, to depend on Him.
Have you ever been in a place
where you just didn't know what to do?
I was having discipleship and training
with Fernando last week and he asked me a question.
He said, have you ever felt like it's hard?
Have you ever felt like you don't know what to do?
And I said, Fernando, listen, let me just tell you,
there's plenty of times that you see it's hard
and you don't know what to do
and it's not just at the beginning,
it's throughout the life and ministry
of a follower of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And we find that what is God doing in those moments?
He's leading us to a place of dependence,
depending upon Him, seeking Him for direction,
seeking Him for what is next.
And we find that as you study through the Psalms
and we have on Wednesday nights here,
the last several weeks that David was in a place
where he needed direction and he sought the Lord.
There were some circumstances in his life
that brought him to that place of dependence.
We see that the purpose is given to us
in verse number seven as bookends to the verse
that lest I should be exalted above measure.
But I want you to understand that as we look at this thorn
that Paul received, that this result of this thorn
would bring humility and dependence.
Can I tell you this morning that we need both?
We need both.
We need to be humble.
We need to be dependent upon the Lord.
Sometimes what happens, Brother Mike and I
were talking last night, and as we were talking
after we had dinner and the kids were playing
and his son wanted to beat everybody at UNO
and we were just kind of talking for a few minutes
before we got into the UNO game and we began to talk
about preparing messages and that sort of thing.
And I said this to him.
I said, you know, the message is important,
but the man is of greater importance, the vessel.
The vessel.
And sometimes what can happen is we can get so professional
and so methodical in the Christian life
that we just figure out how to do it
like it's a well-oiled machine.
But that's not ministry.
Ministry is to be lived in dependence.
Your Christian life is to be lived in dependence
every single day on the Lord Jesus Christ.
Because when he said in John 15 that ye are the branches
and I am the vine, and without me you can do nothing,
he was speaking truth that was necessary
for his people to understand and to accept.
There are times in which we get so focused.
I preached last Sunday night of too busy for Jesus
and looking at Martha and that whole situation
and we can just get so busy serving the master
that we forget to spend time with the master.
Ministry is important, serving is important,
but we cannot forego, we cannot forfeit
our time with Christ.
So Paul was given visions, Paul was given a thorn.
And let me say this as we finish up this morning,
number three, Paul was given an answer.
Paul was given an answer.
As we look at verses eight and nine,
the Bible records for us this request that Paul makes
and the answer that he receives.
The request is simple.
In verse number eight, for this thing,
I besought the Lord thrice that it might depart from me.
It's very plain what Paul was requesting.
In fact, for some of us, we've prayed the same type
of prayer that Paul has prayed.
We pray in a situation, God, would you remove this?
Why do we pray that way?
Because we believe that he can.
I believe that God can move the mountains.
I believe that God can part the seas.
I believe that God is still on his throne.
He has all the power that he's ever had
and that he ever will have.
He is omnipotent.
He is able to do exceeding abundantly above
all that we ask or think.
And I pray at times that God would remove something.
Why?
Because I believe that he can.
And Paul besought the Lord thrice.
This was not something that just one time he prayed.
No, it was three times.
There's an element, an aspect of maybe fervency
that we could speak of here with regard to the request.
And Paul sought the Lord.
He knew that God was able.
But we find that Paul was given an answer.
Can I say it this way even before we read verse number nine?
It may not always be the answer that we're looking for.
I think Paul was looking for an answer
that was different than the answer that he received.
I think that Paul truly desired
that God would remove that thorn.
That's why he prayed it.
But God said, I'm gonna do something better.
Can I tell you that his way is perfect?
Can I tell you that his way is best?
Can I tell you this, that his way is not always my way?
His ways are not our ways.
Is that not what Isaiah tells us?
He transcends us.
He knows better.
And I was thinking this morning
as I was looking at the bulletin,
actually yesterday I was thinking
as I was sitting on my desk,
this is the way, walk ye in it.
From Isaiah 30 and verse 21.
I was beginning to meditate upon that.
Aren't you thankful that God knows the way?
Aren't you thankful that God will tell you the way?
Amen?
I mean, praise the Lord.
Have you ever been lost and you just needed
somebody to tell you the way?
How do I get out?
How do I find my...
And you want somebody to give you the truth,
somebody that knows.
And we have the God of the universe
who knows everything.
Who knows you and knows me
and he knows the end from the beginning.
And he gives us direction.
He gives us answers.
And there are times unfortunately in our lives
where we're not content with the answer that God gives.
And that's tragedy.
Because we want what we want.
It's a real danger for us in America
because we're spoiled.
We're spoiled.
Burger King made the little catchphrase years ago,
have it your way.
Right?
And that appealed to the American public.
Why?
Because we want it our way.
It's what we want.
We want it our way.
Now we want God's stamp of approval on it,
but we want it our way.
And here's what happens.
Paul says, I have assaulted the Lord thrice,
that it might depart from me and he, the Lord.
The Lord said unto me,
my grace is sufficient for thee.
For my strength is made perfect in weakness.
See, I believe that God could have removed the thorn.
I believe that.
Just like I believe that God could still the storm.
But I believe that God chose to do something greater in this passage of Scripture and He
chose to give us a principle that was so important for us to know.
And here's the principle, God's grace is sufficient.
We find that here as He besought the Lord that He was understanding that God was able.
But God said, I'm going to do something for you that's so important for you to understand.
My grace, that enablement is sufficient for thee.
He tells them this, for my strength is made perfect in weakness.
We're going to look entirely next week at the latter part of these two verses and preach
a message on how Paul really, what his response is and his embracing of the truth, the answer
that God gave.
But I want you just for a moment to focus here on God's grace.
We've preached about it all year, God's grace is sufficient.
God's grace is sufficient and it is.
I said this on the very first Sunday of this year when I preached to open up this theme,
that God did not say my grace will be sufficient.
He did not say that my grace was sufficient.
He said that my grace is sufficient.
It's present tense.
It's understanding that in the moment, whatever moment we're in, that God's grace is sufficient.
And this is so powerful and it's so helpful for us as God's people, why?
Because we understand that God's enabling.
This grace here is not talking about God's saving grace.
Paul's already a man that's saved.
We're not talking about, for by grace are you saved through faith, although I'm thankful
for the saving grace of God.
This is the enabling, that service grace, the enablement that God would give to the
apostle Paul.
And can I tell you this?
God's grace is sufficient for you and it is sufficient for me.
We find that there's an unending supply of God's grace.
It's not going to run out.
It's not going to run dry.
His grace is sufficient.
And you say, sometimes we play this game and we say, I don't know if I could ever deal
with, and we get into this hypothetical mode of what happens if this were to come in my
life or if this were to come in my life.
And I just, it would just destroy me.
And the problem with that kind of thinking is that God's grace is sufficient in the moment.
Not in advance, not in the hypothetical, when in the moment you find that God's grace
is sufficient.
And this morning, when we look at the answer that the apostle Paul received, I do not think
it was the answer that he was expecting, the answer that he was looking for, but it was
the answer that he needed.
And it's the answer that we need.
God's grace is sufficient.
And we find here this morning that we must ask ourselves this question, and it will lead
into the message for next week.
Will we, will you trust God?
Will you believe God?
Will you believe that God's grace is sufficient?
Will you believe in the midst of your storm, in the midst of the turmoil, in the midst
of all that's going on, will you believe, will you embrace the very truth that God's
grace is sufficient?
Because Paul, he embraces it.
He embraces it.
He believes God.
And we too must believe God.
You say, but you don't understand the storm.
You don't understand God.
Listen, the storms will vary in their intensity.
The storms will vary in their duration.
But one thing that we must acknowledge is that God's grace is sufficient, regardless
of the intensity of the storm, regardless of the duration of the storm, God's grace
is sufficient.
And it's so powerful for us.
And in the text of Scripture, God gave to Paul revelations, visions.
He gave him a thorn, and he gave him an answer.
This morning, we see that God's grace is sufficient, it's so vital, it's so important for us to
embrace that.
But as we make that priority on humility, as we find that Paul says, lest I should be
exalted above measure, can I ask you this morning, are you battling pride?
Some things that cause you to be prideful, lifted up, not trusting God like we should.
I've referenced already the truth of James when he says that God resisteth the proud
but giveth grace to the humble.
I want to remind you of what Paul said to the believers in Corinth in 1 Corinthians
chapter 4 as he speaks to them about this, about a foundational principle that will
help them in their approach to having humility.
He says in verse 6 of 1 Corinthians 4, and these things, brethren, I have in a figure
transferred to myself and to Apollos for your sakes, that you might learn in us not to think
of men above that which is written, that no one of you be puffed up for one against another.
And then Paul asks these questions, for who maketh thee to differ from another?
In just a little while in the book of 1 Corinthians, Paul's going to begin to deal with spiritual
gifts.
And the Holy Spirit giveth to every man severally as he will.
Who maketh thee to differ from another?
God gave you a specific gift, but he gave somebody else a specific gift, but the reality
is that God gave it.
He says as he continues in verse number 7, what hast thou that thou didst not receive?
Because everything that we have is from the hand of God.
So if we understand the foundational principle, what is there to be prideful about?
Because all that I am and all that I have is the result of God and His favor.
Notice with me as we close this morning in 1 Peter, in 1 Peter chapter number 5, Peter
is writing to these that are facing great persecution, they're scattered abroad, all
that's going on.
As he comes to the end of the epistle, he writes to specifically, the attention here
turns to the church leaders.
He says, the elders which are among you I exhort, who am also an elder.
So we find that Peter is giving this instruction, he gives a great warning in the text about
our enemy who's walking about, not just to trip up, but to devour.
But we find in the midst of this passage, I want you to notice verses 5 and 6 and what
Peter says here.
He says this, likewise ye younger, submit yourselves unto the elder, yea, all of you
be subject one to another.
And then he says this, and be clothed with humility.
For God resisteth the proud and giveth grace to the humble.
Humble yourselves therefore unto the mighty hand of God that He may exalt you in due time.
As we notice in verse 5, he makes the statement to be clothed with humility.
To be clothed with humility.
That it would be evidenced, just like you can see someone's clothing, that we would
be clothed in humility.
Do you know what a pride person looks like and acts like?
Can you pick them out?
You can, right?
Pride is easily detectable in others, not always in ourselves.
Am I right?
But he says, be clothed with humility.
Be clothed with humility.
And then he goes on and he talks about, as we mentioned from James, that God resisteth
the proud, giveth grace to the humble.
I don't want God resisting me.
I want God's favor.
I want His grace.
I want His enabling.
And then he makes the statement, humble yourselves.
Humble yourselves.
If we choose not to take and follow that admonition, God will humble you.
And He is able.
And can I say this?
It'd be far better for every single one of us that we humble ourselves than that God
would humble us.
I said in the beginning, but if we can see God in His rightful place, if we see Him high,
holy, and lifted up, it'll help us to be humble.
We stand in awe of Him and say, what am I?
I'm undeserving.
Aren't you undeserving?
I don't deserve to go to heaven.
but God's grace.
Can I tell you that sometimes
we have a right position
doctrinally?
The truth?
If we're not careful, it can make us prideful.
And having the truth can make us
look down upon others that don't have the truth.
It can cause us in our witnessing
to be prideful,
to be arrogant.
But knowing the truth doesn't make us better,
it makes us simply responsible.
We are debtors, as Paul says in Romans 1.
God's given us the truth,
and it's not so that we can look down at others,
it's so that we can give them...
Listen, Satan, if we believe all of the Bible,
the God of this world hath blinded the minds
of them which believe not,
lest the light of the glorious Gospel
should shine unto them.
And the reality is that it doesn't make us better,
it makes us responsible.
That there are people that are lost
just like I was lost,
just like you were lost.
They don't need some pride, arrogant person
to come in their pride of I have the truth.
No, they need somebody that's clothed in humility,
that's carrying the truth of God's Word
to love them to Jesus.
That's what they need.
Paul says there needs to be a priority on humility.
He was given a vision, visions really.
He was given a thorn,
and he was given an answer.
I'm thankful this morning
that he was given all of this truth
that can help us.
But I hope that as we take away this morning,
we say, lest I should be exalted above measure.
What is it gonna take in your life to keep us humble?
Will you humble yourself under the mighty hand of God?
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for your Word.
And God, I pray that you would help us to walk
in humility.
Lord, we believe that you said
twice that you resist the proud.
Help us like Paul to place a priority on humility.
Father, I pray that if there's one that's here
that's not saved,
I pray they would humble themselves.
Come, let us take a Bible and show them
how they can know for sure that heaven is their home.
Father, if there's some that are dealing with pride
at whatever measure, whatever level it might be,
would you help us this morning to humble ourselves?
Would you help us to be clothed in humility?
As we think about the example of our Lord and Savior
who humbled himself
and became obedient unto death,
even the death of the cross,
Lord, you are God.
You left the throne of heaven,
the glory to come to this sin-cursed world to die for us,
to rise.
Leave us an example
and help us to be clothed in humility.
Would you work in these moments of invitation
as only you can?
We'll give you the honor and glory
for every decision that's made.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's gonna play quietly on the piano.
If you're not sure of heaven,
if you're a man, we have a brother Mark,
he'll take a Bible and show you
you can know for sure that heaven's your home.
Holly's here.
If you're a lady, don't know that heaven is your home,
we'd love to take a Bible and show you how to know.