Chapter number nine, Genesis chapter number nine this evening, and we'll be finishing
up Genesis chapter nine, looking at verses 18 through 29 this evening will be our text
of scripture.
And if you're taking notes, I've titled the message this evening, Noah's final days.
And it's kind of interesting because I'll title the message Noah's final days, and it's
only a few verses of scripture, but it covers about 350 years.
And so it's kind of ironic, but that is the passage that is before us here as we get back
to the book of Genesis.
We've been studying the book of Genesis.
Of course, we've taken off several weeks now with some other subjects that we've been dealing
with.
And this is our 32nd lesson, believe it or not, through the book of Genesis.
I've thoroughly enjoyed the study, and we've been going at it for a lengthy period of time.
We first met Noah back in Genesis chapter number six, in the midst of great wickedness.
And the Bible tells us that Noah was a just man and perfect in his generations.
And then the Bible tells us this, that Noah walked with God.
What a great testimony.
We think about the testimony of Noah, and we think about all of the things that were
going on as God describes for us in Genesis chapter number six.
We find that Noah walked with God, and we find that the Bible tells us that Noah found
grace in the eyes of the Lord.
We find that God begins to reveal to Noah the plan that God has to destroy the earth
and to destroy the inhabitants of the earth.
And we find that in verse number 13, in fact, of Genesis chapter number six, God speaks
directly to Noah and informs him.
He says, the end of all flesh has come before me, for the earth is filled with violence
through them.
And behold, I will destroy them with the earth.
He then tells him this.
We see the grace of God in verse number 14, make thee an ark of gopher wood, room shalt
thou make in the ark, and shalt pitch it within and without with pitch.
And God gives him the instruction.
We find that we have noted on several occasions, and we've studied through these portions,
Genesis six through eight, and we've studied the great flood, and we've studied the life
of Noah, and we have noted the obedience of Noah.
How he obeyed the Lord, how he did what God told him to do.
And what a blessing.
In our last study from the book of Genesis, we actually studied the first half of chapter
number nine.
There's a net up here that's about to drive me crazy.
And so I don't know where the fly went, but if the fly would get the net, I'd be happy.
And in any case, in Genesis chapter number nine, verses one through 17, we dealt with
the Noahic covenant.
And that was in our last study from the book of Genesis this evening.
As we complete the ninth chapter, we'll see the summary that is given to us with regard
to Noah's final days.
Notice in verse number 18 of Genesis nine, the Bible says, and the sons of Noah that
went forth of the ark were Shem and Ham and Japheth.
And Ham is the father of Canaan.
These are the three sons of Noah.
Notice this, and of them was the whole earth overspread.
We'll get through the entirety of the chapter this evening, but let's begin and take some
notes.
Notice number one, the replenishing of the earth.
In verses 18 and 19, as we break down this passage of scripture, we see an important
truth that is given to us.
The important truth that is given to us is with regard to the replenishing of the earth.
And we find that the Bible says at the end of verse number 19, and of them, who is them?
It's the three sons of Noah, Noah and his wife, his three sons, Shem, Ham, and Japheth.
And we see that the Bible says of them was the whole earth overspread.
Now we understand as we've studied here over the last several lessons from the book of
Genesis and studying in chapter six through eight, we understand that God has given us
the record of the Noah flood, the global flood.
We understand that it's global in nature.
It was not just a local flood, it was a global flood.
In fact, as we looked at the Noahic covenant and we discussed the various aspects of the
covenant that God gave in the first 17 verses here of Genesis chapter number nine, we understood
again the fact that it was a global flood.
Now understand with me, there are some that would seek to promote this idea that there
are other groups of people on the face of the earth that were somehow sheltered from
the flood and part of the replenishing of the earth, and there were pockets of population
in various parts of the earth.
Can I tell you very firmly that that is not biblically based?
And we must understand that we approach these things biblically.
The Bible must be our guide, and we understand that God gave us very specific things.
Let's go back to Genesis chapter number six, and I want to just walk through these three
chapters and just point out a few verses of scripture along the way to help us understand.
It was in Genesis chapter number six, we read verse 13, let me read verse number seven to
you.
The Bible says in Genesis six and verse number seven, and the Lord said, I will destroy man
whom I have created from the face of the earth, both man and beast and the creeping thing
and the fowls of the air, for it repenteth me that I have made them.
And so we find that in Genesis chapter number six, verse number seven and verse number 13,
both give us the announcement of this judgment that was impending.
We find that in Genesis chapter number seven, that the Bible tells us in verse number seven,
and Noah went in.
What did he go in?
He went in the ark.
Not only did Noah go in, but it says, and his sons and his wife and his son's wives
with him into the ark because of the waters of the flood.
Let's skip down and look at verse number 13.
The Bible says in the self same day entered Noah and Shem and Ham and Japheth and the
sons of Noah and Noah's wife and the three wives of his sons with them into the ark.
God gives us a record of the human beings that entered the ark.
There were eight.
In fact, if you look at the new Testament, the Bible talks about the eight persons referring
to Noah, his wife, his three sons, and their wives.
These eight entered into the ark.
We find that in, as you skip down to verse number 21 of Genesis chapter number seven,
the Bible says, and all flesh died that moved upon the earth, both of fowl and of cattle
of beast and of every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth.
What's it say?
And every man, verse 23, notice the Bible says in every living substance was destroyed,
which was upon the face of the ground, both man and cattle and the creeping things and
the fowl of the heaven, and they were destroyed from the earth.
And Noah only remained alive in they that were with him in the ark.
Aren't you glad that God gave us a record of who went into the ark?
He didn't leave it for our speculation.
He didn't leave it for some theologians or from some whoever group of people to sit around
and say, well, let's think about how big the ark was and let's think about how many could
have fit on it.
And this, no, the Bible tells us who went on the ark.
And so we find that as we look here in the passage of scripture in chapter six, seven,
eight, of course, is when the ark, when the waters were assuaged and when the ark rested
and when Noah came off the ark and you find that it was Noah and his wife and his sons
and their wives notice in verse number 18 of chapter number eight, actually back up
to verse number 15.
And God spake unto Noah saying, go forth of the ark, thou and thy wife and thy sons and
thy son's wives with thee.
So they all survived during the time on the ark.
It tells us in verse number 18 and Noah went forth and his sons and his wife and his son's
wives with him.
And as we move into chapter number nine, we find the Bible says in verse number one, and
God blessed Noah and his sons and said unto them, be fruitful and multiply and replenish
the earth.
And so as we look at this entrance or the beginning of this passage of scripture that
we're studying this evening and looking at verses 18 and 19, the Bible repeats to us
again who the sons of Noah are that went forth of the ark.
And the Bible very clearly teaches us that of them was the whole earth over spread.
And so we find biblically speaking, the human race traces its lineage back to Noah, Shem,
Ham, and Japheth.
Of course, they go back to Adam, right?
The first man.
We read of that, of course, in Genesis one, when God said, let us make man in our own
image.
And of course, we understand and we've studied that in the past.
Notice what the Bible tells us in Acts chapter number 17, in verse number 26, Paul is here
in this situation and he is going, of course, to Athens and he's preaching there.
And we find that he saw a city that was wholly given to idolatry.
And these people that served idols, they had a whole grove of them, if you will.
And we find that Paul mentioned that as he went through, he noticed that there was one
with the inscription to the unknown God.
And Paul says that you worship him ignorantly.
And then he says this, him declare I unto you.
And then we begin noticing what Paul declares of this God, the Lord God, Jehovah, in verse
number 24 of Acts 17, it says, God that made the world and all things therein, seeing that
he is Lord of heaven and earth, dwelleth not in temples made with hands.
Neither is worship with men's hands as though he needed anything, seeing he giveth to all
life and breath and all things. And hath made of one blood all nations of men, for
to dwell on all the face of the earth, and hath determined the times before
appointed, and the bounds of their habitation." And so we find that Paul is
preaching to these idol worshipers, these individuals in Athens that had
this plurality of gods, and he says you have this one altar that has this
inscription to the unknown God, Him declare I unto you, and he begins to
share with the fact that he's creator, and then he deals with the fact of course
of the human race being of one blood, and we see that very plainly in the Bible. We
find the Bible record is accurate, and it is to be of course giving, it provides
for us a biblical worldview. Notice as we continue back in Genesis chapter number
nine, not only the replenishing of the earth, but notice the drunkenness of Noah.
I'll be honest with you, it's a sad portion of Scripture when we read these
verses of Scripture. We find the the wonderful way in which we first were
introduced to Noah, as I've mentioned already by way of introduction back in
Genesis chapter number six, and now we come here to Genesis chapter number nine,
and the Bible tells us in verse number 20, and Noah began to be in husbandmen,
and he planted a vineyard. And so the Bible begins to share with us some
things with regard to the occupation of Noah, to the life of Noah. Again, there's
just a few verses of Scripture that capture a lengthy period of history. As
you get to the end of the text of Scripture, the Bible tells us in verse
28 that Noah lived after the flood three hundred and fifty years. So obviously God
is not providing us with a diary of Noah's life, of all of the events and all
of the things that had transpired, but we find here that God is sharing this
singular event that took place in the life of Noah, and we find that as he
shares this event, he tells us that Noah had this occupation. He began to
be in husbandmen, he planted a vineyard. Notice in verse 21, and he drank of the
wine and was drunken. The Bible tells us this at the end of verse 21, and he was
uncovered within his tent. Really, we could note the shame of Noah in verse
number 21. I do not believe for a moment of time that Noah intended for this to
be the result of what he did. In fact, as we often would speak about alcohol and
we would deal with, you know, wine and alcoholic beverage and that sort of
thing, and we look at the biblical context, we can always find within the
context of whether the wine is an alcoholic wine or if it's the the fruit
of the vine, and we can always determine that contextually as to what takes
place. Here, very specifically, the Bible says that he was drunken. It's obviously
alcoholic wine in its nature, and then as we see the result, it says that he was
uncovered within his tent. There's shame that's associated with this activity
that God describes for us here in verse 21. Notice as we come to verse number 22
that God gives us the record of the actions of Ham. Of course, Noah has three
sons, Shem, Ham, and Japheth, and we notice here that the Bible tells us specifically
about Ham. It tells us this, that Ham—notice this again—the father of Canaan. Now, we
saw this back in verse number 18 when the Bible says the sons of Noah that went
forth of the ark were Shem and Ham and Japheth, and then it says this, and Ham is
the father of Canaan. We come to verse number 22, and it says, and Ham the father
of Canaan. Do you think God wants us to understand something about lineage? He
wants us to understand something about the genealogy here, and he mentions twice
within just a few verses of Scripture that Ham is the father of Canaan. We'll
get to that in just a few moments, but it is important to make that note. It then
continues to say this in verse number 22, that Ham saw the nakedness of his
father and told his two brethren without. I will be honest with you,
theologians have argued the point for generations as to what this means that
Ham did. The Bible doesn't tell specifically what Ham did. The Bible
simply reveals to us that he saw his father's nakedness and that he told his
two brethren. He did not seek to cover as Shem and Japheth will, and we'll notice
that in the next passage of Scripture and the next verse of Scripture, but we
find that he, Ham, went in and he saw it, and then he went and told his brethren.
Shem and Japheth. We find that upon hearing the news of what had taken place,
of the shame, if you will, of Noah as he's in the tent after he had drunk in this
wine, that the Bible tells us that Shem and Japheth, in verse number 23, that they
took a garment. Notice what the Bible says, and they laid it upon both their
shoulders and went backward and covered the nakedness of their father, and their
faces were backward and they saw not their father's nakedness. We find that
these two boys, they find the entrance to the tent, we'll pretend that it's
here, and they get here side by side and they put a, the Bible tells us here in
verse number 22, excuse me, 23, they put a garment upon their shoulders and they
walked backwards into the tent to cover the nakedness of their father so that
they did not see it. We find that there was a difference in action between what
the Bible records for us of Ham and what the Bible records for us with regard to
Shem and Japheth, and we find that the Bible then tells us that Noah awoke in
verse number 24. He woke from his wine, and the Bible says that he knew what his
younger son had done unto him. He was aware of that which had transpired, he
was aware of what had taken place when he was within his tent. We find that he
then, as he has this understanding of the events, God records for us in verses 25
through 27, if you're taking notes, number three, the prophecy of Noah. As we look at
the prophecy of Noah, we break down these verses of Scripture in verses 25
through 27, it actually becomes a little bit clearer as to what happens not only
here in Genesis 9, but you'll be familiar with this taking place later in the life
of Jacob. Remember when he calls all of his boys around in Genesis chapter
number 49, and he's going to give the blessings to all of his sons, and he goes
through and he lists each of the sons and he speaks about them and so on and so
forth, and we find here that as Noah, the prophecy of Noah is recorded for us in
verses 25 through 27. Now it begins in verse number 25 with dealing, and here's
what it says, and he said, Cursed be Canaan, a servant of servants shall he be
unto his brethren. We understand that as this prophecy of Noah is recorded for us
here in verses 25 through 27, that it begins with a curse. We'll find that
there's a blessing and an enlargement that is mentioned in verses 26 and 27,
but it begins with this curse. It says, Cursed be Canaan. Notice again, if we go
back into the text of Scripture, that we've made note that the Bible says that
Ham is the father of Canaan, that Ham is the one that went in and saw the
nakedness of his father. He saw the shame. Noah was aware of what had taken place.
He knew what his younger son had done unto him, and it says, Cursed be Canaan.
You understand that the curse that is mentioned here in chapter number 9
and verse number 25 is not on all of the descendants of Ham, rather upon the
descendants of Canaan. It's important for us to note that. There are some, by the
way, that have misapplied and misgiven the interpretation of this passage of
Scripture to say something that it does not say. Notice, he says, Cursed be Canaan,
and he says this, A servant of servants shall he be unto his brethren. It's
interesting, at the end of verse number 26 and at the end of verse number 27, it
says, And Canaan shall be his servant. And Canaan shall be a servant. Can I tell
you that the Canaanites were known for their wickedness and their
immorality. As you study the Scriptures and begin to see all that transpires, as
you begin to see the interactions between the children of Israel and the
Canaanites, in fact, even within the book of Genesis, you see references to the
Canaanites, you see they are known for their wickedness and their
immorality. We find that in Genesis chapter number 10, turn over there if you
will and look at verses 15 through 19, it's important for us to note this
because the Bible says, Cursed be Canaan, and we find that in Genesis 10 verses
15 through 19 that God provides us with a list of the descendants of Canaan.
Again, this prophecy of Noah is not on all of the descendants of Ham, it's
simply on the Canaanites. Notice in verse number 15 of Genesis 10, And Canaan
begat Sidon his firstborn in Heth, and the Jebusite, and the Amorite, and the
Gergesite, and the Hivite, and the Archite, and the Sinite, and the Arvidite, and the
Zemurite, and the Hamathite, and afterward were the families of the Canaanites
spread abroad. Verse 19, And the border of the Canaanites was from Sidon
as thou goest to Gerir, unto Gaza, as thou goest unto Sodom, and Gomorrah, and
Admah, and Zeboiim, even unto Lasha." In fact, as you read the book of Joshua, as
we've been studying the book of Joshua, you'll note many of those places and
many of those names are found within the context of the book of Joshua. We find
here that, as we would think about this curse that's been placed upon Canaan,
this prophecy more than a curse, and we think about it as a prophecy in the
sense of, yes, it says, curse it be Canaan, we understand that, but what we find that
is happening is Noah is giving this prophecy with regard to the descendants,
the wickedness that he saw in Ham, he would see it fully
gone in Canaan, his son. And we find that in Genesis chapter 15, let's take a
walk through some scripture here and look at some things with regard to the
Canaanites. In Genesis chapter number 15, we often look at the passage of
scripture and we deal with this wonderful promise of the Abrahamic
covenant, and what a great promise it is, what a great truth of God's Word, and we
think about the covenant, we've mentioned, even as we've studied through the book
of Hebrews, that the promise is of a land and of a seed, right? Abraham never
actually possessed the land that was promised. We find that the seed that
was promised, he did have that son from he and Sarah, Isaac, and we find here that
the Bible tells us in chapter number 15 and verse number 16, notice what God
says, let me back up to verse number 12, and when the sun was going down, a deep
sleep fell upon Abram, and lo and horror of great darkness fell upon him. And he
said unto Abram, know of a surety that thy seed shall be a stranger in a land
that is not theirs, and shall serve them, and they shall afflict them four hundred
years. And also that nation whom they shall serve will I judge, and afterward
shall they come out with great substance. Knowing the entirety of scripture, does
this not sound familiar to you, as to the time in which the children of Israel
would spend in Egypt, and they of course would be delivered after the tenth plague,
the death of the firstborn, the Passover, and they would come out with great
substance. But notice in verse 15, and thou shalt go to thy fathers in peace,
thou shalt be buried in a good old age, but in the fourth generation they shall
come hither again, notice, for the iniquity of the Amorites is not yet full.
And we find here in verse number 16, as God would use this phraseology of the
iniquity of the Amorites, what he's meaning is all of the Canaanite tribes
that were in that region. And we'd understand as he's speaking about all of
the Canaanite tribes that are within that region, again, as you look at the
sons of Canaan, and you look and you notate the names that are given there in
Genesis chapter number 10, you find that many of them occupied that land when the
children of Israel, led by Joshua, would come in to inhabit the land. Now what
happened? We know that God gave the commandment that they were to go in and
they were to conquer the land, right? That's what they were told to do. They
were to go in and they were to conquer the land and then inhabit the land. The
question that we'd ask is, did they destroy all the Canaanites? The answer is
no, they did not. Look over, if you will, at Joshua chapter number 16 and notice
what God shows us here in the portion of Scripture. Now remember, this prophecy of
Noah back in Genesis chapter number 9, he says,
Notice, a servant of servants shall he be unto his brethren. In Joshua
chapter number 16, in verse number 10, notice what the Bible says. This is
speaking of the lot for the inheritance of the children of Joseph, Ephraim,
specifically dealing with the tribe of Ephraim, the Ephraimites. It says this in
verse number 10, and they drave not out the Canaanites that dwelt in Gezer.
Notice, but the Canaanites dwell among the Ephraimites unto this day, and what
does it say? And serve under tribute. And serve under tribute. What did he say? A
servant of servants. Chapter 17, notice in verse number 12, the Bible says here,
speaking of the half-tribe of Manasseh, yet the children of Manasseh could not
drive out the inhabitants of those cities, but the Canaanites would dwell in
that land. Yet it came to pass when the children of Israel were waxen strong
that they put the Canaanites to tribute, but did not utterly drive them out. We
find that the descendants of Ham, specifically being the father of Canaan
and dealing with this prophecy, he says, cursed be Canaan a servant of servants
shall he be unto his brethren, and we see exactly that coming to pass in the book
of Joshua. In fact, if you turn to the book of Judges in the first chapter,
notice what God records for us here. Again, recording some of what we just
read in Joshua 16 and 17, notice how the writer notes it here in Judges 1. Judges
chapter number 1, beginning in verse number 27, it says, neither did Manasseh
drive out the inhabitants of Bethshean and her towns, nor Panach and her towns,
nor the inhabitants of Dor and her towns, nor the inhabitants of Iblim and her
towns, nor the inhabitants of Megiddo and her towns, but the Canaanites would dwell
in that land. Verse 28, and it came to pass when Israel was strong that they
put the Canaanites to tribute, but did not, and did not, excuse me, utterly drive
them out. Neither did Ephraim drive out the Canaanites that dwelt in Gizir, but
the Canaanites dwelt in Gizir among them. Neither did Zebulun drive out the
inhabitants of Kitron, nor the inhabitants of Nahalal, but the Canaanites
dwell among them and became tributaries. Neither did Asher drive out the
inhabitants of Akot, nor the inhabitants of Zidon, nor of Elab, nor of Exib, nor of
Helba, nor of Aphic, nor of Reho, but the Asherites dwelt among the Canaanites, the
inhabitants of the land, for they did not drive them out. Neither did Naphtali
drive out the inhabitants of Beth Shemesh, nor the inhabitants of Beth
Anath, but it says he dwelt among the Canaanites, the inhabitants of the
land. Nevertheless, the inhabitants of Beth Shemesh and of Beth Anath became
tributaries unto them. We find that the Bible tells us in verse number 34, and
the Amorites forced the children of Dan into the mountain, for they would not
suffer them to come down to the valley, but the Amorites would dwell in Mount
Heres and Ajalon, and then shelled them, and the hand of the house of Joseph
prevailed, so they became tributaries. And the coast of the Amorites was from the
going up to Acribim, from the rock and upward. You notice several times within
the passage in Judges chapter number 1, the Bible mentions the Canaanites
dwelling there and being under tribute, being servants. They would have this
thing of paying taxes and what have you, and really it became this idea, it's very
interesting, the Bible says that when Israel was strong, that they put the
Canaanites to tribute. In fact, you'll find various interactions throughout the
the Old Testament with regard to this people group, the Canaanites as they're
referred to as, but you find that when Israel was strong, they would put them
to tribute, they would be a servant of servants. In 1 Kings chapter number 9,
we'll finish up with this particular passage of Scripture dealing with this
first aspect of the prophecy of Noah. In 1 Kings chapter number 9, in verses 20
and 21. In 1 Kings 9, now think about this, the amount of time that has passed, we go
all the way now to the time of Solomon, and it tells us in the beginning of the
passage in verse number 1, and it came to pass when Solomon had finished the
building of the house of the Lord, and the king's house, and all Solomon's
desire, which he was pleased to do. Now, that's a long period of time from
Genesis chapter number 9, and this prophecy of Noah. We see the entrance
into the land, and the way in which the Canaanites became servants, and they were
under tribute, and we've read all of those things, and we now fast forward through
the period of the judges, and we get through the period of course of Saul
reigning as king, and David reigning as king, and now we find that Solomon is
king, he's built the temple. The Bible tells us here in the passage of Scripture
some things about Tyre, and so on and so forth, but look in verse number 20, the
Bible says, and all the people that were left of the Amorites, Hittites, Perizzites,
Hivites, and Jebusites, which were not of the children of Israel, their children
that were left after them in the land, whom the children of Israel also were
not able utterly to destroy, upon those did Solomon levy a tribute of bond
service unto this day. And so we find that this prophecy of Noah that is given
to us in Genesis chapter number 9, as we trace a course throughout this portion
of Old Testament biblical history, we see that it came to pass just as God said it
would, through this prophecy that Noah made here in Genesis chapter 9, verse 25,
with regard to the Canaanites. Again, it's important that we understand that he's
not speaking about all of the descendants of Ham. In fact, as you get
into Genesis chapter 9, verse 25, we see that he's speaking about the descendants of Ham.
to chapter number 10 and you begin to read about the sons of Ham, you start
reading in chapter number six, excuse me, in verse number six about the sons of
Ham, Cush and Mithraim and Put and Canaan. Canaan wasn't his only son, it was his
youngest son and it was the one in which this curse would be upon that they would
be again a prophecy that they would be servants of servants unto his brethren.
Notice as we move forward through the prophecy we come back to Genesis chapter
9 and we look to verse number 26 and the Bible says this, and he said, Noah
again continuing to speak, he said, blessed be the Lord God of Shem and
Canaan shall be his servant. He says blessed be the Lord God of Shem. It's
interesting for we would mention the fact that of course the Jews are
Semitic and they come through the line of Shem and we would find that this
would be the Messianic line as we speak of. Now, we understand the blessing when
we would consider that truth, amen, and we would understand the blessing.
Remember, even as he would give that blessing to Abraham and he would talk
about the seed and we find the fulfillment in Galatians very plainly
that Paul speaks about the seed, singular, he didn't say seeds, he said seed, this is
Christ, and he mentions how that we are the descendants of Abraham, how? Through
faith. And we find the blessing that is here, blessed be the Lord God of Shem,
dealing with the fact that the Jews are Semitic, the Messianic line is no doubt
in view within the prophecy that is recorded here in verse number 26. We then
come to verse number 27 and we find the Bible continues and says, God shall
enlarge Japheth and he shall dwell in the tents of Shem and Canaan shall be
his servant. We've dealt with the subject of Canaan in each of these situations. It's
interesting that we find here when he speaks about Japheth, he says God shall
enlarge Japheth. And we can think about and consider the territorial ways in
which the descendants of Japheth went, so on and so forth, and it's kind of an
interesting study. In fact, if you wanted to study all of these lines and kind of
see where all of these groups of people went and so on and so forth, because we
do understand that of them was the whole earth overspread. And so that's a
lot of land, the whole earth, there's just eight people, and of course when we come
to Genesis chapter 11 in the Tower of Babel and we see the disbursement of the
people and all that that takes place, and we find that this prophecy with regard
to Japheth, that God shall enlarge Japheth, but notice this aspect, the Bible
says, and he shall dwell in the tents of Shem. It's interesting because we really
know through this phraseology at the middle there of verse number 27 that the
spiritual blessings upon Japheth would come through the God of Shem. Why?
Because that's the Messianic line, that's the Lord God, that's our
Messiah, and of course we look at this prophecy in verses 25, 26, and 27, and in
fact, again, you could study various things and you could go through all
sorts of things to see the way in which throughout history these particular
descendants have gone to different places, but what a blessing to understand
the way in which God is using this prophecy of Noah and we can see the
fulfillment of it. Again, as we look at this passage of Scripture, we see not
only the replenishing of the earth, the drunkenness of Noah, the prophecy of Noah,
but then we see the death of Noah. Finally, this evening, number four, if
you're taking notes, verses 28 and 29, the Bible says this, and Noah lived after the
flood 350 years, and all the days of Noah were 950 years, and he died. That's pretty
good age, amen? 950. Man. Now, it's interesting as we know what's taking
place because really as we begin to understand the time frame, if you will,
that Noah and his wife and his boys and their wives, they came off the ark in
chapter number 8. Remember we said this, at the end of chapter number 8, the Bible
tells us that Noah built an altar unto the Lord. What did he do? He offered burnt
offerings on the altar. First things first, the first matter of business was
worship. They worship the Lord, they make these offerings, and then we find that
God comes and speaks to Noah, he blesses Noah and his kids, he gives them
direction with regard to the replenishing of the earth, and he gives
the Noahic covenant, and then we find in just these few verses of Scripture, the
entirety of those 350 years wrapped up for us. Now, again, the Bible tells us
that Noah was 950 years old and he died. Now, it's interesting that we would
understand the age of Noah being mentioned here. It's approximate, and
there's some different Bible scholars of yesteryear, of what have you, that have
given chronological dates to events in the Scriptures, but roughly speaking, at
this particular time in history, the earth was just over 2,000 years old from
creation, and so you think about Noah being 950 years old and the earth only
being created for a little over 2,000 years. When I say a little over, like 2004,
2006, somewhere in that ballpark, number of years since the earth had been
created, but Noah was alive for 950 of them. That's almost half of the known
human history at that point that Noah was alive for, and we think about it
being summarized for us here in just these few verses of Scripture, and God is
giving to us, helping us to see this prophecy of Noah, and again, as we've
mentioned throughout the book of Genesis, as we begin to study the
foundational nature of these really first 11 chapters of the book of
Genesis and how foundational they are for understanding the entirety of
Scripture. If you did not have these chapters and these verses and you did
not understand some of these things, it would be challenging to have proper
interpretation of the balance of Scripture. We find that it's these first
11 chapters that are so often under attack by those that do not have a
biblical worldview that would like to destroy those that have a biblical
worldview. They want to cast doubt as to the historical accuracy of these things.
They want to provide various interpretations as to what these things
mean, but we find that God has given us the Word that He has given us. He, in His
wisdom, has given us exactly what He has given us, and as we study it and begin to
interpret the history from the foundation of God's Word, we are able to
come to proper conclusions. It is interesting to note this truth this
evening as we think about kind of coming to this end point, if you will, in the
book of Genesis. We find that in chapter number 10, of course, the genealogies are
provided. We see the sons of Japheth, of Ham, of Shem, and really the entirety of
the chapter is given to the genealogies. We then come to chapter number 11 with
the Tower of Babel, and at that point we're kind of then going to start
dealing with Abraham and going forward into the book of Genesis. And as we think
about the foundation, we come to the end of chapter number 10 and look at the
death of Noah, and we think about all of these things that have happened, all of
these things that we've studied, and we begin to have this biblical worldview, we
understand some of, or really all of, we have the understanding of what God is
giving us in the New Testament and with His plan as a whole. We have so many
people running around today that do not have a biblical worldview that are
trying to provide solutions for the world's problems. The solutions for the
world's problems are not going to come from something outside of God's Word, and
we've had such a move away from the Bible in our nation in the last several
generations, away from the Bible, away from God, away from the principles of God,
and we've introduced all sorts of other thoughts and mindsets and ideologies
that are out there that are permeating the minds of people today that
are not going to adequately provide solutions to the problems that we deal
with. In fact, as you look at the way in which the account of these first
chapters of Genesis are being attacked, what is it, what is the the biggest way
in which they attack? There's no creator, right? This teaching of evolution,
this idea of humanism that really comes out of the teaching of Darwinianism and
understanding all of their ideologies with regard to undermining the authority
of God. Can I tell you that if there is no God, that there is no creator, that
there's no purpose? We're just some random chance. That's not true. God has
created us. God has given us a purpose. God has given us a plan, and God has
recorded these things for us, and we find that as we look to the Scriptures and we
look to the Word of God that we...
We must ensure that our mindset is biblical, that our worldview is biblical.
There are people...
I had someone come to me a couple of years ago now, no one from our church, but someone
came to me that had a solid, what I thought, a solid Bible foundation.
And they came to me and they said, do you really think there only had to be one Adam
or could there have been many Adams?
And they began to ask about the replenishing of the earth after the flood, they began to
provide these ideas about various groups of people in various regions of the world.
And I simply said, sir, you got to look at the Bible, but how do you know it's true?
And what has happened is they began to get attacked and attacked and attacked, and the
attack upon the foundation of God's Word, began to mess with the thought process, begin
to introduce various ideas and thoughts with regard to human history.
But we find that God has given us the truth that He has given us for a purpose.
Why did God decide, and I'm not questioning Him, I'm not saying it in this way to question
Him, but we look at this and we say, in 350 years, to summarize the life of Noah in verses
18 through 29, why is this the content?
Why is it that God takes note to tell us, and of them was the whole earth overspread?
He wants us to understand the way in which the earth was replenished.
He wants us to understand that all mankind was killed during the flood, and all men and
every living being, they were all killed, they were destroyed.
He told us specifically who got on the ark.
He told us specifically who got off the ark.
Why did He tell us about this event?
Why did He tell us about the prophecy?
Begin to see the way in which God is unfolding the future events that would happen and how
we can look here and see this and begin to interpret properly future events that take
place.
And it's so important that we understand that.
I mean, think about it this morning when we mentioned about the order of Melchizedek.
I was chatting with someone after the service.
The reality is that the truth of coming to that messianic psalm in Psalm 110 and thinking
about this promise of this one that would come, Messiah, and as the prophecy would be
given there, and they would be very familiar with it as they would understand here in Psalm
110 in verse number 4, where the Bible tells us, the Lord hath sworn and will not repent.
Notice that terminology.
The Lord hath sworn and will not repent, and then it says, thou art a priest forever after
the order of Melchizedek.
And then they think about Melchizedek, Melchizedek, where do we know that name from?
I'm not sure that they would say that, but maybe for us.
And they go back to Genesis 14 and they just look at a couple of verses of Scripture and
they just, man, how does this all come to pass?
We see now living in this day and living and looking back historically, we see how,
and Holly and I were talking this afternoon, like the peel of the onion kind of coming
off, the wrapping of the present coming off in the presentation.
We find this such is the case with this prophecy of Noah recorded in these few verses of Scripture.
It helps us to have a proper understanding of all that takes place.
You know, there are a lot of people that take the approach that Ham was cursed.
It doesn't say that Ham was cursed.
It says cursed be Canaan.
Amen?
They try to make application to certain ethnicities with regard to that curse that is mentioned
in Genesis chapter number nine.
They were Canaanites that dwell in the land of Canaan, okay?
They were servants of servants.
We looked at the passages of Scripture, and so we don't have to come up with some hypothesis
of what does this mean and how does this all work out.
No, we can go to the Scriptures and we can trace what the Scriptures tell us and we can
see the fulfillment of the prophecy.
And I'm thankful that God in His wisdom provided us with the record that He provided us with
because He knows exactly what we need.
And we need to be biblical.
Amen?
We really do.
We need to return to the Bible.
We need to be biblical people.
We need to be in the place where we think and act biblically.
There's so many ideas that are being thrown out in our world today, and it's so dangerous
for our young people to kind of get caught up in some of these ideologies and some of
these...
I mean, listen, they package them neatly and they make it sound really good.
I say, hold on a minute.
Is it biblical?
Because first and foremost, we must have a biblical worldview, and everything will then
flow out of that.
Genesis chapter 9 records for us the final days of Noah.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
Thank You for the Word of God, the truth contained therein.
We thank You for the opportunity to study Thy Word.
Lord, we thank You for allowing us to have the Bible preserved in our language.
We thank You for Your wisdom that's been displayed throughout the book of Genesis.
We've seen Your power and Your wisdom on display.
God, I pray that You would help us to be biblical.
Lord, to think and act biblically, to consider those things that would be presented to us
and take them through the filter of Your Word.
Lord, help us not to be deceived by those things that are going on in our society today.
We thank You for Your Word.
We thank You for loving us.
We pray that You'd give us a good week.
Lord, help us to honor You and glorify You.
We think of those that are traveling, pray that You'd keep them safe.
Lord, help us to be the salt of the earth and the light of the world.
We'll thank You for it.
In Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?