of the year that Brianna, along with one of her classmates
there at college, helped us in writing that song
and the words along with the music.
And so I hope that you'll catch that tune
and be singing it, and certainly a great truth
and great blessing of the importance of continuing
and very thankful for that song.
I hope you're working on the memory verse
for the month of January, 1 Timothy 1, 17,
and that's the memory verse for the month of January,
1 Timothy 1, 17, I hope you're working on that,
commit it to memory.
If you do it all year long, you'll have 12 verses memorized
by the end of the year from 1 and 2 Timothy.
All the verses will be from those two books
as we preach through those books
on Sunday morning this year.
1 Thessalonians chapter five, last week we looked
at verses 12 and 13 and dealt with the subject matter
of a pastor, or excuse me, a church and its pastor.
A church and its pastor, we talked about the responsibility
of the pastor, the responsibility of the church,
and we mentioned this last week that the last statement
of verse number 13 would be the focus
of our attention this evening,
and as we continue studying through this instruction
that is given to the church at Thessalonica,
we see the subject matter of unity
being addressed this evening.
Notice the end of verse number 13,
the Bible says, and be at peace among yourselves,
and be at peace among yourselves.
It is necessary that we understand the importance
of unity in the church.
The enemy, we have an enemy, and we understand
that we have an enemy personally,
but we corporately, collectively have an enemy,
and the enemy desires, his desire is to destroy
the unity of the church.
I believe as you study through the book of Acts
that you find that initially the attack of Satan
on the church was from without.
Through persecution and all that the church endured
in those early days of the book of Acts,
we find that the enemy was seeking to stifle,
to stop the advancement of the church,
the preaching of the gospel,
and he used that persecution,
but we know this as we come to Acts chapter number eight,
and verse number four, the Bible says,
they that were scattered abroad went everywhere
preaching the word, hallelujah,
that they went everywhere preaching the word,
but Satan recognized that his tactic did not work,
and some have said it this way,
that the fires of persecution that burned in Jerusalem,
that when they tried to stamp them out at the gospel,
excuse me, the fire of the embers of the gospel,
when they tried to stamp it out through persecution,
spread the embers around the world,
and certainly there's great truth to that,
and so we find that as we continue to study
through the book of Acts,
and even into the history throughout the New Testament,
that Satan, he really begins to change his approach,
and he learned the ineffectiveness of that tactic
of persecution he saw to attack the church from within.
What is it that he uses within?
Well, of course, we know false doctrine, false teaching,
no doubt that that's part of it,
but specifically with regard to the subject
that we'll deal with tonight of unity,
we find that he uses divisions and schisms
to render the church ineffective.
Now think about this, if a church has turmoil within,
resulting in the focus and attention being inward
and not outward, so often we think about churches
that do not have unity,
there's that lack of unity within a church,
and you find that there's so much focus,
so much resource that's given to all that's taking place,
the fighting, the tension, the division,
all those things inside, all of a sudden,
we've lost focus of what our real purpose is,
and that is to reach the world
with the gospel of Jesus Christ,
and so we find that the enemy has been seeking
to provide disunity, to cause disunity
within the household of faith, within the church of God.
The Lord, however, is our peace,
and I believe that he places an emphasis in his word
on the subject of unity.
If you are taking notes this evening,
I've titled the message from this last phrase
of 1 Thessalonians 5, 13, unity in the church,
unity in the church.
Number one this evening, God's plan for unity.
We're gonna look at a number of verses tonight,
because we see that the text of scripture
simply says, and be at peace among yourselves,
but we begin to look at God's plan for unity,
and I would argue this evening, biblically,
as we'll look at a number of scriptures tonight,
that it is God's plan for his people to be in unity,
and we find all the way back in Psalm 138,
it's a familiar verse of scripture,
but I'll read it this evening,
as we consider this thought tonight of unity
and God's plan for unity,
and we find that in Psalm 138, in verse number,
it's not Psalm 138, I got a typo here,
but it's when, behold, chapter 133,
I can't read my own writing,
Psalm 133, in verse number one,
behold, how good and how pleasant it is for brethren
to dwell together in unity.
Psalm 133, in verse number one.
I don't know about you, but just personally,
I am not a big fan or advocate of fighting, division.
I know, sometimes you meet people that just like to fight,
you ever meet somebody like that?
Yeah, I mean, it's like their calling in life,
they just gotta be divisive,
and that's just the way they are,
you say it's blue and they know it's green,
you say, I mean, that's just the way it is, right?
And there's some people that like fighting,
it just seems like they're bent toward that.
I personally, I don't like it, I don't care for it,
I don't like disagreement, I don't like arguments,
I don't like that type of thing,
but we see here that God says, behold, how good
and how pleasant it is for brethren
to dwell together in unity, in unity.
Now, we look at this verse of scripture
and we see really the beginning of this thought
of God's plan for unity, I want you to go
to the New Testament as we think specifically
about the church this evening,
go to the book of Romans, if you will,
and we'll look at a number of verses of scripture tonight,
and go to Romans chapter number 12,
and I want you to see what God's plan is
for unity within his church, within his people.
We find that here in Romans, and again in 1 Corinthians,
we won't take the time to look
in the 1 Corinthians chapter 12 and following there
with regard to the same analogy that's used,
but here in Romans chapter 12, in verse number five,
notice what the Bible says, so we, being many,
are one body in Christ, and every one member
is one of another, and then he talks about
the different gifts and how he's given gifts
to the church and so on and so forth,
but we see that statement in Romans 12, five,
where it says, so we, being many, are one body in Christ.
You think about the unity.
Listen, I'm thankful this evening,
and I'm sure that you are as well,
that when your brain tells your right hand
to do something, it does it, right?
Your body works in agreement, and there's certain aspect.
You wanna walk over there, and you just kinda,
you walk over there, right?
Your body functions as one.
If my foot says to my hand, I'm not gonna do this,
Paul deals with that in the book of 1 Corinthians,
and so we find that we're many members, but we're one body.
God is giving us this insight with regard
to his plan for unity.
Look at 1 Corinthians, if you will,
and as we look at 1 Corinthians,
we're obviously familiar with the church in Corinth,
and understanding that this church in Corinth
was a church that dealt with a number
of divisions and contentions, but I want you to notice
how Paul begins to issue this call
to this church in Corinth in chapter one,
in verse number 10, and really revealing
to us God's plan for unity.
Notice what the Bible says in 1 Corinthians one,
in verse number 10, now I beseech you, brethren,
by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ.
So Paul is not begging the believers in Corinth
based on his own desire, based on his own goal
or ambition for the church.
No, he says, I beseech you, brethren,
by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ,
that ye all speak the same thing,
and that there be no divisions among you.
He didn't say that there be fewer divisions among you.
He said that there be no divisions among you.
That's unity.
Notice he continues and says this,
but that ye be perfectly joined together
in the same mind and in the same judgment,
for it hath been declared unto me of you, my brethren,
by them which are the house of Chloe,
that there are contentions among you.
So we know of the contentions, we know of the divisions.
He immediately enters into the situation
where they were saying, I am of Paul,
I'm of Apollos, I'm of Cephas, I'm of Christ,
and what have you, and these schisms
that were just brewing in the church at Corinth,
and we find that Paul says that he's beseeching them
by the name of the Lord Jesus Christ.
Notice that you speak the same thing,
and that there be no divisions among you,
but that ye be perfectly joined together,
notice, in the same mind, in the same judgment.
What is that same mind that he's speaking of?
Well, I believe, and we'll get to it later this evening,
it's the mind of Christ.
And we find that Paul is helping us to understand here
that it's been reported, Paul believes,
he understands what's taking place there in the church,
and he says that there are contentions among you,
there are divisions among you.
Now, remember what Jesus said about a house being divided.
In Matthew chapter 12, you don't need to turn there,
but in verse 25, the Bible says that Jesus knew
their thoughts and said unto them,
every kingdom divided against itself
brought to desolation, and every city or house divided against itself shall not stand."
I believe that we could obviously make the application for Matthew 12, 25 to even a church,
a church that is divided, is losing its effectiveness for Christ.
And so we find that the enemy desires to cause division and to disrupt the unity, but God's
plan for the church is that they would be in unity, that they would have unity.
We're not going to take the time.
It's almost like a homework assignment this evening, but the fact of the matter is that
I'm not going to check it to know if you did it or not.
It's just going to be an honor system.
But I want to give you this challenge.
I want you to look in the book of Acts, and I want you to go through the book of Acts,
the beginning chapter of the book of Acts, and I want you to see how often the Bible
says that they were of one accord.
One accord.
Really, with one mind is the idea of that statement.
And we find that the Bible says repeatedly throughout the opening chapter of the book
of Acts how that they were in one accord.
That's God's plan.
God's plan for the church is that they would be in unity.
He says here to the church at Thessalonica, and be at peace among yourselves.
No fighting, no division, no turmoil, but be at peace.
Now, we think about this truth, God's plan for unity, but I want you to consider this
evening the path to unity.
The path to unity.
If we acknowledge tonight that it's God's plan for unity, for his church, for his people
to be in unity, he says how good and how pleasant it is for brethren to dwell together in unity.
We find that he says Paul is beseeching the church at Corinth that they be of the same
mind, that there be no divisions, that this is God's plan, that his church is a church
that's unified, that has unity.
What is the path by which we can achieve unity?
Let me say this, it is not by ignoring doctrine.
There are some today that would seek to have and really try to give this idea within Christendom
and ecumenical movements that we just kind of want to have this unity and so set aside
those things that would divide us and just simply embrace so we can have unity.
That's not true unity.
The only way to truly achieve unity as we'll look at this evening is to follow the path
that God outlines for us in his word.
And as we follow the path that God outlines for us in his word, we can achieve unity.
We can have a church that is unified, that has that unity, and we could say how good
and how pleasant it is for brethren to dwell together in unity.
Look back at Romans chapter 12.
We were there just a moment ago in verse number five.
We talked about we're many, but we're to be one body in Christ.
Then notice in verses nine and 10 as God gives us some insight here with the path to unity.
How is it that we can have this unity, that we can have this understanding that we're
one body in Christ?
Notice in verse nine, let love be without dissimulation, abhor that which is evil, cleave
to that which is good.
Be kindly affectionate one to another with brotherly love and honor, preferring one another.
He goes through a number of other things that he lists here, but verses nine and 10 are
quite insightful as we begin to think about this path to unity and really having the mind
of Christ.
And we say that because we couple this passage with Philippians chapter number two.
Turn over there if you will and look in Philippians two and notice what the Bible tells us.
Again here, Paul is writing to a local church.
He's writing to the church at Philippi.
It's a church that God allowed him personally to be able to see established and we find
that he's writing back to this church and he's giving them instruction.
And notice in verse number one of Philippians two, he says, if there be therefore any consolation
in Christ, if any comfort of love, if any fellowship of the spirit, if any bowels and
mercies fulfill my joy, notice that ye be like minded, having the same love, being of
one accord, of one mind.
Do you see that?
I mean obviously the idea of unity is screaming from this verse of scripture where he says
that we're like minded, that we're of one accord, that we're of one mind.
But notice as he continues, let nothing be done through strife or vainglory.
But in lowliness of mind, let each esteem other better than themselves, looking not
every man on his own things, but every man also on the things of others.
You know, so often the way that unity gets disrupted is by pride, is by pride.
I want my way, I want this done and so on and so forth and it can disrupt unity.
And so the path to unity, the key verse number five of Philippians two, let this mind be
in you which was also in Christ Jesus.
And so we have the mind of Christ and we find that as God would give us the instruction
on the path to unity, that it must be that we take and we accept the truth of God's
Word and we agree that we're going to agree with God.
Here's a thought tonight.
I don't have to agree with you and you don't have to agree with me.
But we must agree with God, amen?
And here's what brings unity.
When you agree with God and I agree with God, guess what the byproduct is?
Unity.
We agree with each other because we're agreeing with God.
Does that make sense tonight?
So the reality is that what happens so often when those people in Corinth, I'm of Paul,
I'm of Cephas, I'm of, there's these divisions that are brewing out of I'm better than you
because I'm of.
The divisions that were brewing in Corinth based on the gifts of the Holy Spirit of God,
the spiritual gifts and they said, well I have this spiritual gift and therefore I'm
better than you.
And what does Paul say?
Who gave you the gift?
The Holy Spirit of God gave you the gift.
And so if he's the one that gave you the gift, why are you boasting in the gift?
Why is it resulting in this division?
We find that he says here, let this mind be in you which was also in Christ Jesus.
And so we must get self out of the equation and we must determine that we're going to
agree with the Lord.
Look in the book of Ephesians, if you will, again another church that's being written
to here in Ephesians chapter number four, and I want you to notice what Paul says to
this church in Ephesus as we consider the fact that God's plan is for unity but there's
a path for unity.
And here in Ephesians chapter number four in verse number one, notice what Paul says,
I therefore the prisoner of the Lord beseech you that you walk worthy of the vocation wherewith
you are called.
Notice what he says, with all lowliness and meekness with longsuffering forbearing one
another in love.
And so again, we see the humility, right, not having the sin of the flesh and the pride
that would enter.
And he says, no, with all lowliness and meekness with longsuffering forbearing one another
in love.
Look at verse three, endeavoring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace.
What did he say in 1 Thessalonians 5 verse 13, the last statement, and be at peace among
yourselves.
And here Paul says endeavoring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace.
The word endeavoring is a great word, it's really the idea of laboring for something,
to labor for something.
It has the idea of desiring whatever that something is here in the context that unity,
we desire unity and therefore we are diligent to get unity.
But how do we get the unity, what is the path to unity?
It must be that we determine that we're going to agree with God, that we're going to agree
with God.
And if we're going to agree with God, then we can have unity.
But if the standard is me or if the standard is you and it's that you must come to my position
or I must come to your position, that's never going to result in unity.
Why?
Because I might say it for a little while, but deep down I really don't agree with you.
And deep down you don't really agree with me.
But if you say I want to agree with God, what does God say?
That's why we're to be students of the Scripture, we're to study the word, we're to study to
show ourselves approved unto God, we're to understand that as we're going to have this
unity, if we're going to endeavor to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace
that we must labor for it.
Why?
Because there's an enemy that wants to disrupt it.
There's an enemy that wants to cause division and to cause turmoil.
And you find that there's times in which there are some people that want to come in that
cause division.
It happens.
I've been asked in the past, why do you have to have a doctrinal statement that's so detailed?
Because we believe what the Bible says.
You know, you could have made it really simple, pastor, if you just said we believe God, we
believe the Bible, we believe in heaven.
That's just too generic.
Amen?
Because the reality is that if we're going to have unity, we have to agree with God and
His word.
And so when we come to this thought this evening that Paul gives to the church at Thessalonica,
this church that's under intense hardship and persecution and all that they're dealing
with, and Paul says, listen, I want you to be aware, as I give you this instruction,
I want you to be aware of the relationship between a church and its pastor.
But I also want you to understand the importance of unity.
And I want you to, as he uses the terminology, to be at peace among yourselves.
to be at peace among yourselves.
Well, how is it, if we acknowledge that that's God's plan,
how is it that we can accomplish that?
What is the path by which we can obtain that unity?
Notice in 1 Timothy 3,
and we're gonna look at this final verse this evening,
and really just look at what God tells Timothy.
Now, Timothy is not a church, but he's a leader of a church,
and he's giving Timothy this truth,
and I think it's very insightful for us
with regard to the path to unity,
as we desire this evening,
to have a church that is unified, a church that has unity.
In 1 Timothy 3, notice in verse 15,
the Bible says, but if I tarry long,
that thou mayest know how thou oughtest
to behave thyself in the house of God.
Now, notice what he refers to
and how he refers to the house of God.
He says, which is the church of the living God,
the pillar and ground of what?
Of the truth.
Now, we know what truth is.
Truth is God's word.
Sanctify them by thy word.
Thy word is truth, John 17 in verse 17.
And so, the church is to be the pillar.
It's the church of the living God.
It's the pillar and ground of the truth.
And so, if a church is going to have unity,
that unity is only going to be achieved
as we have the mind of Christ,
as we take the truth and the teaching of God's word
and say, okay, here's what we're gonna agree to.
Often, as I have opportunities to have counsel
with people over the years,
I've often said this sort of thing
as we'd sit in my office and I'd say something like this.
Before we begin this discussion,
can we agree that we're gonna agree with God's word?
Can we agree that we're gonna agree
with what God's word says?
I'm gonna open the scriptures.
I'm gonna show you what the scriptures say.
And I'm gonna take you to the Bible verses.
And this is the truth that God has left us with.
And if we're truly going to achieve and have that unity,
there's a path by which we must take.
And it's that we elevate the Lord Jesus Christ,
that we humble ourselves and that we elevate his word
and say, it's not about me.
It's not about you.
It's about the Lord Jesus Christ.
It's about the work of his kingdom
about the work of his church.
And we're going to determine
that we're going to be Bible-based.
We're gonna do what God says in his word.
Now, when we start throwing the Bible out
and every man does that, which is right in his own sight,
and say, well, this is how I was raised.
This is what my background is.
This is my this, this is my that.
Then all of a sudden you get all kinds of different
and all of a sudden there's no unity.
There's no unity.
The thing that's awesome about the Bible
is that the Bible is cross-cultural.
The Bible is true.
No matter where you go,
you can preach the truth of this Bible.
And that's awesome.
You don't have to change the Bible
because of the group of people that you're speaking to,
the culture in which you find yourself.
No, the Bible is cross-cultural.
Why?
Because God is the author of the Bible.
And so because he's the author of the Bible,
the Bible is cross-cultural.
It's supposed to be used in every area of this world.
And as we think about the globe and all that's therein,
and we think about churches
and how churches can have unity
as they agree with God and his word.
Somebody said this, and I'll finish with this.
Some of you've heard this illustration before, no doubt,
but they're speaking about a tuning fork on a piano.
Now, I don't even know
that they really use tuning forks anymore,
but they used to, that's how they would tune a piano.
They use some other very sophisticated material,
different things when they come in now,
but a tuning fork would be used to tune a piano.
Now, something that's interesting about a tuning fork
is that when you bring that tuning fork in,
you are setting the piano to that tuning fork.
That is the standard.
The tuning fork is the standard.
Does that make sense tonight?
And I'm not a musician, not a piano player,
but I understand enough
that if we're gonna tune this piano,
if we have a tuning fork, even if the tuning fork is off,
that piano is going to be tuned to the tuning fork.
Does that make sense tonight?
So, if someone comes here with a tuning fork
and they tune this piano,
and they tune it to this tuning fork,
and then they go down to my house,
I have a piano in my house,
and they use that same tuning fork
and they tune the piano in my house to that tuning fork,
and then they drive over to the Fezdekian's house
because they have a piano in their house
and they use that same tuning fork
and they use that tuning fork to tune their piano,
then they drive over to the Mills
because they have a piano in their house.
And then to the Trejo's, all these pianos,
and they use the same tuning fork.
You know what's gonna be the byproduct?
This piano, and that piano, and their piano,
and their piano, and their piano
are all going to be in tune with one another.
Why?
Because they use the same tuning fork.
Use the same tuning fork.
The same standard.
So, guess what our standard is?
Right here, the Bible.
And if this is the standard, then we can have unity,
even with diverse backgrounds,
with diverse upbringings,
with all sorts of things that we have
of who we are as individuals.
We come before the Lord and we say,
nope, this is the standard,
and if we abide by this, we can have unity.
It's amazing.
It's absolutely amazing.
That's why you've often heard me say
that my identity, first and foremost,
is that I'm a Christian.
And if that's our identity, that I'm a Christian,
I'm a follower of Jesus Christ,
and that's the approach that each one
in a local assembly takes, we can have that unity.
And we find here this evening that Paul,
as he's writing to this church in Thessalonica,
he says, and be at peace among yourselves.
You know, it's very insightful to me
that he would say to this church,
a good church, a model church,
we laid the groundwork for that two weeks ago,
and how the church at Thessalonica,
five reasons that they're a model church,
and we look now, we say,
man, he's talking to them about the relationship
between a church and its pastor,
and he's talking about unity.
Why is he dealing with these subjects?
Why is he giving this instruction
to a church that's a model church?
Well, because, you know, it's amazing
how quickly the unity can be disrupted.
And almost always, it's when someone or someones
get a little sideways, and they get a little bit prideful,
and they get a little bit all about them,
and they forsake this, they wanna go over here,
and all of a sudden, they can disrupt the unity
that God's plan for a local church is to have unity.
And what's the path?
The path is that we agree with God.
Again, you don't have to agree with me,
I don't have to agree with you,
but we must agree with God.
And if I agree with God, and you agree with God,
then we agree, amen?
I say, that's oversimplified.
I know, but that's the way it works.
A church, God's plan for a church
is that they would have unity, unity in the church.
Be at peace among yourselves.
Let's pray, Father, how we love you,
and how we thank you for loving us.
I pray, Lord, that you would help us
in our church to have unity.
I pray that you'd help us, Lord,
to be students of your word, that we would know you,
and Lord, that we would seek you, that we would serve you.
I pray that you'd help us to be humble, Lord,
that we would have the mind of Christ.
I pray, Lord, that if or when divisions and schisms
would rise up, that you'd help us to deal with them quickly,
Lord, so that we could have, that we would endeavor
to keep the unity of the Spirit through the bond of peace.
I pray, Lord, that you would use us
for your honor and for your glory.
Help us not to get distracted, Lord.
Help us to have that unity, and we'll thank you for it.
Bless our time of prayer.
We thank you for the privilege.
Thank you that you hear us, and you answer,
that you're able to do exceeding abundantly
above all that we ask or think.
I pray that you'd bless now, for it's in Christ's name
we pray, amen.
Does anyone need a?