John, we'll be in John chapter number 16,
John chapter number 16 this morning.
I'll read the verse of scripture
that we'll be using for our message this morning.
We'll be referencing a number of different passages
of scripture as well, so have your fingers ready
this morning, John chapter number 16.
I love the gospel of John,
and obviously I love the Bible.
All of it is good, it's profitable,
and we're thankful for it.
But there's something about the gospel of John
for me personally, specifically,
I thoroughly enjoy reading through the gospel of John.
I just read it again last week
and just thoroughly was blessed and encouraged.
John 16, in verse number 33,
notice what the Bible says.
These things I have spoken unto you,
that in me you might have peace.
In the world you shall have tribulation,
but be of good cheer, I have overcome the world.
Jesus gives these words to the disciples
and what precious words they are.
I've titled the message from this verse of scripture,
be of good cheer.
John chapter number 12 records for us
the triumphal entry of the Lord Jesus Christ
as he makes his way into Jerusalem.
And we understand that even as that event
is given to us and the record is provided
in John chapter number 12,
that it was 500 years earlier
that Zachariah prophesied of this very event taking place.
And as Jesus would make his triumphal entry into Jerusalem
and there were many that were crying out
and worshiping and all that was taking place.
And of course, in just a short period of time,
those cries changed drastically
where as he's riding in and all that's taking place
and we look at that triumphal entry
and we look at how they were glorifying.
And it says in verse 15, fear not daughter of Zion,
behold thy King cometh sitting on an ass's colt.
And he's coming in the fulfillment again
of what Zachariah would say.
And by the time you get to the 18th and 19th chapter
of the book of John,
you find that the crowd is crying crucify him, crucify him.
And what changes have taken place
in just a short period of time in Jerusalem.
But we find that over the next few days
from John chapter 12 and the triumphal entry
of the Lord Jesus Christ,
over the next few days,
we find that several things occur.
We find that in John chapter 13,
God provides us with the record
of Jesus washing the feet of the disciples.
And of course, there's a great truth
in that passage of scripture
that we can understand the truth of being a servant,
the humility and what joy that is,
the great lesson that we learn of Peter
and his objection and the instruction that's given.
But after that portion of scripture in John 13,
we find that Jesus to conclude the 13th chapter,
chapter 14, 15 and 16,
we find that in these pages of God's word
that Jesus is spending these times,
this period of time alone with his disciples.
And as he's there alone with his disciples,
we find that it is in this intimate setting
that Jesus is preparing his disciples
for that which will transpire in the days ahead.
Not only immediately,
but we find that even in their life and ministry
and for us today,
the truth of preparation is still found
within these words that Jesus spoke.
We find that really John 16 and verse 33,
the verse that I read a moment ago
that is our text for our message this morning
is a concluding verse.
It closes out all that Jesus taught his disciples,
all of the instruction,
all that he had communicated to them
during that special time.
We find that Jesus in the gospel of John
regularly refers to his hour.
And he speaks about in John chapter number two
that his hour is not yet come,
but we find that as immediately following
our text of scripture this morning,
that when you come to John 17 and verse number one,
that Jesus says, father, the hour is come.
What is he referring to?
Well, he's going to the cross of Calvary.
He's going to pay for the sin of mankind.
He's going to fulfill his singular purpose
of coming to this earth and that's to save sinners.
He had to go to the cross of Calvary.
We understand that he was buried
and he rose conquering sin, death and the grave.
The things that would transpire in these days ahead
were going to be events that were going
to cause the disciples to have many emotional responses.
There were several things that they were going
to have to deal with, not only during the crucifixion,
the arrest and the trial and the crucifixion,
the resurrection and then following thereafter.
We find that as they would begin their ministry,
as you study the book of Acts,
that they would face much adversity and much persecution.
And in these chapters of the gospel of John,
Jesus Christ is seeking to prepare his servants.
I'm so thankful that our God knows all things.
I'm so thankful that he is alpha and omega.
He is the beginning and the end.
I am so thankful that he knows all things
and he has communicated to us as his people
what we need to know.
And he has given us all that we need to know
so that we would be prepared for all that we will face.
The reality is that we're going to face some things.
We're going to look at it in this text
of scripture this morning.
We're going to face some things in life
and you are facing some things in life today,
but we can rejoice that God has given us his word
and in so doing, he has prepared us
for that which we will face.
You're in a situation where somebody tells you something
that you didn't know was that important
when they were saying it and afterwards you found out,
man, I wish I was paying more attention to what they said.
Maybe they were giving you some piece of instruction
for something you were going to do.
Maybe they were providing you with some details
with regard to accessing a property,
whether it's through some means of disarming
or arming some device or a combination for a lock.
And you say, man, I wish I would pay more attention
to what was being said.
Why?
Because I don't remember I'm stuck at this step.
Ever happened to you?
Well, God's given us some instruction
that we need to be very, very attentive to.
Why?
Because we're going to face some things in life.
We're going to face some things in life
and God has provided us with the instruction that we need
so that when the hour comes, when the day comes,
when the difficulty comes, that we can be prepared.
The disciples heard these things audibly.
We have them written.
Isn't that a blessing?
You ever forget something that somebody told you audibly?
You ever forget something that you've read?
Sure you have.
Well, we have the blessing of being able to go back
to the precious Bible and being able to read
these words that Jesus spoke.
If you're taking notes with me this morning,
notice number one, something to embrace.
As we look at John 16 and verse number 33,
I find that there's something for us to embrace,
something for the disciples to embrace,
but this morning for each of us
as the people of God here in 2024,
there is something for us to embrace.
Notice the way that the verse begins.
These things I have spoken unto you.
What is it that we're to embrace?
We're to embrace the word of God.
We're to embrace the scriptures.
We're to embrace that which God has given to us.
And we find contextually as Jesus is here,
literally with his disciples,
leading up to the time in which he would go
to the cruel cross and pay for the sin of mankind,
that he's literally speaking these words.
It says, these things I have spoken unto you.
They are to embrace these spoken words.
But I would say to you this morning
that as we have the written word of God
that we understand that all scripture is given
by inspiration of God, that's God breathe.
That's what the word means, inspiration.
And God has given to us his word.
He has providentially preserved his word for us this morning
so that we have the very word of God.
What a blessing this morning to have the confidence
that God has given to us exactly
what it is that we need to know.
He has provided for us in this book
something that is to be embraced.
It is precious, it is profitable.
We find this morning that as Jesus is speaking
in these chapters to his disciples
that he's very deliberate in what he says.
He's purposed in what he's going to communicate.
I want you to think about you having some measure
of communication with someone
and you're providing them with instruction
because of your departure,
because of something you're doing.
And you say, I wanna give you some words of instruction.
You would be deliberate, you would be pointed,
you would be purposed, you would seek
to communicate with clarity
the message that you need to deliver.
Well, that's exactly what Jesus did.
And Jesus gave this message with great clarity.
I want you to back up to chapter 14
and I want you to notice, we're gonna look at
several places here in which Jesus reiterates
this thought that he's spoken these things to his disciples.
In John chapter 14, we understand that at the end of chapter 13,
he speaks about this new commandment that they love one another.
He begins chapter 14 with that wonderful promise
that he's going to prepare a place for us and he's going to come again and what joy that is.
But if you look in chapter 14 and verse 25, notice what Jesus says.
He says, these things have I spoken unto you,
being yet present with you.
So Jesus, in between and repeatedly throughout this period of time with his disciples,
he's going to reiterate this truth that he's speaking these things to them,
that he's giving them this truth.
And he says in chapter 14 and verse number 25,
I'm speaking these things to you, being yet present with you.
Jesus was not going to be present with them for much longer, physically speaking.
We understand that he says in the very next verse,
but the comforter, which is the Holy Ghost, whom the Father will send in my name,
he shall teach you all things and bring all things to remembrance,
whatsoever notice I have said unto you.
I'm thankful for the ministry of the Holy Spirit of God.
You know, if you saturate your mind with the word of God,
the Holy Spirit of God will regularly bring up, remind you of biblical truth.
The reality is that if you don't saturate your mind with the scriptures,
that God is not going to just, bam, bring some scripture principle in your mind
that you never heard or never read or do not know.
But no, as we saturate our minds, as we read regularly,
as we hear the truth of God's word, the Holy Spirit of God uses that.
It's amazing to me, those of you that have taught, that have preached,
you can understand this.
It's amazing to me how often, even in the midst of teaching and preaching,
that the Holy Spirit of God will bring up a verse of scripture that's not in my notes,
it's not something that I prepared to say or to go to,
but the Holy Spirit brings it to mind.
Why? Because I've saturated my mind with his word.
And can I tell you that in your life, that when you deal with a trial,
when you deal with a difficulty, when you're going through that daily routine of life,
as you've saturated your mind with the scripture,
the Holy Spirit of God will remind you.
He'll bring it to your remembrance.
In the text, he's speaking in chapter 14 and verse 15, he says this,
If ye love me, keep my commandments, and I will pray the Father,
and he shall give you another comforter, that he may abide with you forever.
And we find that he's talking about this comforter,
the Holy Spirit that he was going to give, what joy that this is.
And Jesus is speaking these things to them.
Why? To encourage them, to prepare them, to help them to have the joy.
He says, I will not, verse 18, leave you comfortless.
I will come to you.
Isn't that a precious truth?
He says, I'm speaking these things to you.
Listen, these are things to embrace.
There's something to embrace.
Notice in chapter 15 and verse number 11, he says again,
These things have I spoken unto you, that my joy might remain in you,
and that your joy might be full.
We understand that as God's people, as Christians,
we ought to be the most joyful people on the face of the earth.
The joy of the Lord is my strength.
Rejoice in the Lord always.
And again, I say rejoice.
Joy unspeakable and full of glory.
In 1 Peter, he's speaking about having joy.
And in the midst of speaking about joy, he says,
if need be, you're in manifold temptations.
The trying of our faith, it bears forth, it brings forth that which is precious,
the work that God is doing.
And even in the midst of those difficulties, we can have joy.
Why? Because it's his joy.
You know, there's so many people that are trying to manufacture joy today.
They use and they try to speak of joy in the terms of happiness,
and they try to manufacture it.
There's a place in Florida that some of us have visited.
They say it's the happiest place on earth.
And the reality is that if you've ever been there,
you find some of the most miserable people you'll ever find on the face of the earth.
It's 105 degrees.
You've been standing in a line for three hours to go on one ride.
Your kids are crying.
You've got to use the bathroom, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
And it's the happiest place on earth.
Isn't that what they say?
Listen, people are trying to manufacture joy.
If you get this, if you have this, it'll bring you happiness.
It'll bring you joy.
Can I tell you that joy is found in the person of Jesus Christ?
And he says, I'm giving you these things.
I'm speaking these things unto you that your joy, that my joy might remain in you,
and that your joy might be full.
Look at verse 17 here in John 15.
He says, these things I command you that you love one another.
You know, I want you to think about what would happen in the days ahead
and all that would take place with the religious leaders of the day
and then with the persecution that would rise from the Jewish leaders
there in the book of Acts and all that would transpire.
Listen, they would have to understand this love one for another
as they would be scattered, as they would face persecution.
Listen, I'm thankful for the bond that we have as brothers and sisters in Christ.
I'm thankful for the family of God.
I'm thankful that when we deal with opposition and adversity and difficulty
that we have brothers and sisters in Christ, that we love one another.
He says, listen, I'm commanding you this.
Why?
Because I know what's going to happen.
I know what's going to.
Listen, none of us can be on an island to ourselves.
We cannot have this perspective of I'm just independent.
I don't need anybody.
We need each other.
Why are there so many commands in God's word of one another in the New Testament?
It was one of my biggest issues.
I shouldn't say biggest because I had so many of them,
but one of my issues with 2020 and COVID and all the lockdowns
and all the things they try to do.
Listen, as God's people, we have the responsibility
of fulfilling the one another commands.
And how can we do that if we're not together?
A church is a called out assembly.
It's what it is.
We find here this morning that Jesus, knowing what would take place,
he says, I'm commanding you that you love one another.
You're going to need each other.
John 16 and verse number 1, these things have I spoken unto you
that you should not be offended.
Notice where he says in verse 2, they shall put you out of the synagogues.
And then he says, if you are of the world,
the world will hate you, but because you're not of the world,
I have chosen you out of the world.
Therefore, the world hateth you.
Listen, sometimes we walk around as Christians and say,
why does the world hate me?
Listen, if the world hates you, it's a good thing.
If the world loves you, I'd be concerned.
I'm being honest.
If the world hates you, I'd be concerned.
If the world loves you, I would be concerned.
We often talk about separation, come out from among them and be separate,
but can I tell you this morning that if we live godly lives,
they're going to separate from us.
We don't even really have to separate from them.
They're going to just separate from us.
Why?
Because men love darkness rather than light.
And so we find that Jesus says, listen, I'm speaking these,
there are some things that are going to happen,
and I'm speaking these things unto you.
I'm trying to give you the instruction that you need.
Look in verse number four of John 16,
but these things have I told you that when the time shall come,
you may remember that I told you of them.
And these things I said not unto you at the beginning because I was with you.
And so we find that Jesus says, I'm telling you these things
because I know what's going to happen.
And I'm preparing you.
I'm providing for you that which you need.
And when the time comes, you're going to remember that I told you of them.
What a joy to know that our God loves us so much
that he's given us the truth that we need.
There's something to embrace.
We find in verse seven of John 16, Jesus says,
nevertheless, I tell you the truth.
I tell you, he's speaking to them.
It is expedient for you that I go away.
See, they really didn't want him to go away.
And I understand why.
But Jesus says it's necessary.
It's appropriate.
It's expedient for you that I go away.
It's absolutely necessary for if I go not away,
the comforter will not come unto you.
But if I depart, I will send him unto you.
And Jesus concludes once again in chapter 16 and verse number 33,
these things I have spoken unto you.
Listen, Jesus was deliberate with what he said to his disciples.
It is imperative this morning that these disciples
would have understood the importance of the message that was being given.
But I would say for each of us this morning,
it's imperative that we understand that God's Word is profitable.
That God has given us exactly what we need,
and there is something to embrace.
That we embrace the truth of God's Word.
That we hold it dear.
That we seek the face of God through his precious Word.
Not only do I find in John 16 and verse 33 that there's something to embrace,
but number two, there's something to expect.
The Bible says this in John 16 and verse 33.
these things I have spoken unto you."
Notice, number one, when we think about this expectation
that in me, you might have peace.
I'm so thankful that he is the prince of peace.
I'm so thankful that he is a peace,
according to what Paul said,
that passeth all understanding.
I'm thankful that even in the text of this dialogue
that Jesus has with his disciples,
and of course we have the division of chapters and verses,
but really he's just giving in this intimate setting
all of this instruction that we have divided into chapters.
He's providing this instruction to his disciples.
And notice back in John 14 and verse 27,
notice what Jesus says with regard to peace.
He says, listen, there's something to embrace.
I've spoken these things I have spoken unto you,
but there's something to expect.
He says, listen, in me, you might have peace.
Notice in John 14 and verse number 27,
Jesus says this, peace I leave with you.
Do you notice the next word?
My peace I give unto you.
Not as the world giveth, give I unto you.
Let not your heart be troubled,
neither let it be afraid.
We understand as we study the scriptures,
the importance of this truth of peace.
And we find that God has promised to give us this peace.
And he says that it's his peace.
He said, my peace give I unto thee,
not as the world giveth.
Listen, I'm thankful that Jesus gives us a peace
that passeth all understanding,
that he will keep us in perfect peace.
The Bible says to who?
To those who have their minds stayed upon him.
And you think about this truth this morning
as we look at the scriptures and we understand,
listen, we live in a world today that's seeking for peace.
They're longing for peace,
but they're looking for it in all the wrong places
for Jesus is the prince of peace.
And he offers peace.
He says, my peace give I unto thee.
Listen, I'm so thankful this morning
that God's peace can rule in our hearts.
That's what Paul says to the believers in Colossae.
Let the peace of God rule in your hearts.
There's all kinds of things that are going to try
to take place of that peace of God.
The turmoil, the trouble, the tribulation, the difficulties,
but he says that we're to let the peace of God
rule in our hearts.
That we understand that Jesus,
as he's instructing these disciples
and he tells them these important truths,
he says, listen, not only is there something to embrace,
not only am I speaking these things to you,
but there's something to expect.
And number one, you have to understand that in me,
you might have peace.
In me, in the Lord Jesus Christ.
But notice what he says in John 16.
He says, in me, you might have peace,
but he follows it up and says this,
in the world, you shall have tribulation.
We know a little bit about that, don't we?
He says, in me, what a great contrast.
In me, you might have peace.
In the world, you shall have tribulation.
We have a world full of tribulation, trouble, trial.
The disciples were going to face tribulation.
The disciples were gonna face persecution.
They were gonna deal with difficulties and adversity.
And Jesus lets them know that even though
in the world they're gonna have tribulation,
that in him, they can have peace.
This is a great truth that is given to us in John 16
in verse number 33, that yes, we understand
that in that world, there's going to be tribulation
and we see it, we experience it,
we understand this morning the way that the world operates.
But I understand this morning that though
all of the enemy is raging and all the wickedness
that is taking place and all the tribulation
that is around me, that we can still have peace.
Why?
Because Jesus said, in me, you might have peace.
He said in Hebrews 13, I will never leave thee
nor forsake thee.
We find that in Acts chapter 12,
it's an interesting passage of scripture
in which God provides for us an account
of what's taking place with the persecution
and Herod and all that he's doing
and killing James and intending to kill Peter
and putting him in prison and the church is praying
and all that is taking place.
And Peter, listen, Peter saw what happened to James.
He was aware of what happened to James.
Peter understood the plan of Herod, if you will.
The church understood the seriousness of the situation.
They had an all-night church prayer meeting.
You know what Peter's doing while they're praying?
He's sleeping.
If that's not a great picture of peace,
I don't know what else would be.
Then in the midst of all that was taking place,
in the midst of the understanding that I'm next,
I mean, he has me in prison and he's intending to kill me.
He already killed James.
He's gonna do it.
The church is praying fervently.
Peter's asleep.
He's asleep.
He has peace.
In the world, you shall have tribulation.
But in me, you might have peace.
How is it that we view the circumstances of life?
Have you ever heard somebody say this
when you ask them how they're doing?
Well, under the circumstances.
Whoever told us that we're to live under the circumstances?
Amen?
We're not to live under the circumstances.
But so often what happens is we get our focus
so much on our circumstances
and we're not focused upon our God.
And it's in him that we have peace.
It's in the world that there's tribulation.
And we fill up our minds with all that's going on
in the world and all the trial and all the tribulation.
And we have no rest.
We have no peace.
I think about Peter.
We mentioned in Acts chapter 12.
But you think about Peter when he walked on the water.
Jesus comes walking on the water.
And I mean, what a scene it must have been
in the midst of a storm and all this taking place
and they see him and it's Jesus.
He's walking on the water and Peter's the only one.
He gets criticized.
But I'm telling you what, he's the only one
that said, if it be thee, bid thee come to thee.
Bid me come to thee.
He's the only one that took a step out of the boat.
So we can criticize him for sinking in the water,
but he's the only one that got out of the boat.
Amen?
And that means that most of us, if we were there,
we would have stayed in the boat too.
All right?
And Peter said, if it be thee, bid me come to thee.
And Jesus says, come, and he steps out of the water.
What's he doing when he's walking?
I don't know how many steps he took.
And neither do you.
But he had to take a certain number of steps.
He gets to wherever he gets to.
And what is he focused on?
Well, he's focused on Jesus.
Did he know that the storm was raging?
Did he know that there was a storm before he saw Jesus?
Sure he did.
They were in the midst of the storm.
He knew that the storm was raging,
but his focus was on Jesus.
But when he took his eyes off Jesus,
what happened?
Began to sink.
Now, he had enough sense to say, Lord, save me.
The Bible says that they got back.
I believe they walked back on water to the boat.
When Peter took his eyes off Jesus,
listen, the storm didn't cease
until they got back on the boat.
And we find that as you look at the passage of Scripture,
that Peter, as his focus, his gaze is upon Jesus,
and he's not focused on his circumstances,
he's walking on the water.
But when his gaze gets fixed on the circumstances,
the waves being boisterous and all that's taking place,
he begins to sink.
Listen, this morning,
sometimes we have our focus in the wrong place.
We're gazing at our problems
and just simply glancing at our Savior,
when in reality, we must be gazing at our Savior
and simply glancing at our circumstances.
The Bible says in Hebrews chapter 12,
looking unto Jesus, the author and finisher of our faith.
We keep our eyes on Jesus.
We find that there's something to expect.
Jesus says, I've spoken these things,
these things I have spoken unto you
that in me, you might have peace.
In the world, you shall have tribulation.
So we know that this is to be expected.
In fact, we'll be studying it here in just a few weeks
as we continue studying through the book of 2 Timothy.
We find that in chapter number three,
Paul is giving Timothy truth
with regard to the end times, the last days.
And he says in verse number 10 of 2 Timothy three,
but thou has fully known my doctrine,
matter of life, purpose, faith,
long-suffering, charity, patience,
persecutions, afflictions,
which come unto me at Antioch, at Iconium, at Lystra.
I endured, but then he says this, but out of them all the Lord delivered me, yea, and
all that will live godly in Christ Jesus shall suffer persecution."
There's going to be tribulation.
In fact, as you look in 2 Timothy chapter number 2, as we'll be dealing with it next
week, verse number 3, thou therefore endure hardness as a good soldier of Jesus Christ.
There's going to be hardships, but the soldier endures because he's got his eyes on Jesus
and he's understanding that in him we can have peace.
You have no peace, you're lacking peace, you're troubled.
Jesus says let not your heart be troubled.
Jesus says in me you can have peace.
Pastor, did you see what happened?
Did you see the news?
Did you see this?
Did you see that?
What's going on with this and what's going to happen there?
In me, Jesus said.
In me, Jesus said, you might have peace.
In the world, there's going to be tribulation.
Do we not see it?
It's all around us.
I just mentioned this to somebody last week, two weeks ago, and it was not any real scientific
calculation that I used to come up with it, but during the days of COVID, so many were
glued to their TV and watching all of the news because of, well, you couldn't go anywhere.
And I would say regularly to people that if you, you should have a ratio of four to one.
If you watch the news for an hour, you better read the Bible for four.
There was nothing scientific about it, I just kind of pulled it out of my hat and just kind
of four to one.
I thought it sounded good.
But I would tell you that that stands true, not just during a COVID year, but during any
time because we need to have these things that God has given to us.
We need to embrace them because in Him, we have peace.
We know these things.
Listen, Jesus has revealed to us just as He did to His disciples here in this portion
of Scripture, in these pages of Scripture, He revealed to them the things that were
going to happen, and He's preparing them, and He's given to us truth that as we embrace
it, that we can expect, look, there's going to be tribulation, but He said in Him there's
peace.
And what joy that is to every child of God.
I find in John 16 and verse 33, there's something to embrace, there's something to expect, but
I find there's someone to exalt.
In John 16 and verse 33, there's someone to exalt.
He says, in the world you shall have tribulation, but be of good cheer.
Why?
I have overcome the world.
Isn't that exciting?
Listen, there's someone to exalt.
We serve the King of kings and Lord of lords.
We understand this morning that because of who He is, because of the fact that He says
I have overcome the world, because of His victory, that we can be of good cheer, that
we do not need to walk through this life, we don't have to say, woe is me, and dragging
our lip on the ground and saying I'm so overwhelmed and I have all these problems and all these
difficulties.
No, Jesus said you're going to have persecution.
You're going to deal with tribulation.
But in Him there's peace and be of good cheer.
Why?
I have overcome the world.
We are on the winning side.
You say it doesn't seem like it, it doesn't look like it.
Get your eyes off of that stuff and get your eyes on Jesus because there's someone to exalt.
There's someone that is victorious.
He's our Savior.
He's my God.
He's my shield.
He's my buckler.
He's my strong tower.
He's my everything.
This morning as we get our focus on God, as we get our focus on our Lord and understand
that He's overcome the world, that we too are overcomers.
That He's victorious and we too are victorious.
What a joy.
Too many Christians today are living under the circumstances.
Too many Christians today are not embracing the Word that God has given to us.
Too many Christians today are acting like they didn't know that we should expect these
things even though God's told us these things.
Too many Christians are failing to exalt the Lord Jesus Christ.
As we live, we act, we talk as if our Savior's been defeated.
How sad that is.
Victory is ours.
Victory is sure.
We're not defeated.
We have an enemy but He is a defeated foe.
Greater is He that is in you than He that is in the world.
Is that not what the Bible says in 1 John 4?
We find that He tells us that we are more than conquerors in Christ.
We find it in 1 Corinthians in chapter 15.
He tells us, but thanks be to God which giveth us the victory.
How?
Through our Lord Jesus Christ.
Listen this morning, we need to exalt the Lord Jesus Christ and see Him in His rightful
place and understand that He has overcome the world.
Listen Satan tried to do everything he could.
He understood the spiritual war and the spiritual battle.
He did everything that he could to prevent the Lord Jesus Christ from going to the cross
of Calvary in the first place and then after He goes to the cross He does everything that
He can to prevent the resurrection but there's nothing He can do.
He's defeated because God is greater and we have to see Him in that rightful place.
Great is the Lord and greatly to be praised.
We need to see Him high, holy and lifted up.
We need to see Him exalted.
We find in John 17 that as Jesus says the hour has come glorify thy son that thy son
also may glorify thee.
We find that in verse number 2 the Bible says as thou hast given Him power over all flesh
that He should give eternal life to as many as thou hast given Him and this is life eternal
that they might know thee the only true God and Jesus Christ whom thou hast sent.
I have glorified thee on the earth.
I have finished the work which thou gavest me to do.
You know at that point Jesus had not yet gone to the cross but He was able to say that He
had finished the work because it was so absolutely certain that He would go to the cross.
He would bury and He would rise again that He would speak in absolute terms of an event
that had not yet taken place because we can't talk that way because I don't know what's
going to happen tomorrow but He can and He did.
And as He hung upon that cross He said it is finished.
He was buried in that borrowed tomb in the grave.
We sing the song often times on resurrection Sunday the grave that could not hold Him.
He tore the bars away up from the grave He arose.
He conquered sin, death and the grave.
He lives forevermore.
Hallelujah.
What a Savior.
Notice with me if you will Revelation chapter 5 when we consider that there's someone to
exalt understand this morning that we are to exalt and magnify the Lord Jesus Christ
every day of our lives.
We're to keep our eyes upon Him fixated upon Him exalting Him seeing Him in His rightful
place lifting Him up.
We come to Revelation chapter number 5 and I'm going to take the time to read the portion
of Scripture because it's so encouraging and so helpful for me as a believer, as a
Christian to enter into the throne room of heaven as God gives us this glimpse in Revelation
chapter 5 and what truth is here for us and how helpful it is as we see our exalted Savior
this morning.
He says I have overcome the world.
Notice in Revelation chapter 5 in verse number 1 the Bible says and I saw in the right hand
of him that sat on the throne a book written within and on the backside sealed with seven
seals and I saw a strong angel proclaiming with a loud voice who is worthy to open the
book and to loose the seals thereof and no man in heaven nor in earth neither under the
earth was able to open the book neither to look thereon and what is John doing verse
4 and I wept much why because no man was found worthy to open and to read the book
neither to look therein and one of the elders said unto me weep not behold the lion of the
tribe of Judah the root of David hath prevailed to open the book and to loose the seven seals
thereof and I beheld and lo in the midst of the throne and of the four beasts and in the
midst of the elders stood a lamb as it had been slain having seven horns and seven eyes
which are the seven spirits of God sent forth into all the earth and he came and took the
book out of the right hand of him that sat upon the throne and when he had taken the
book the four beasts and four and twenty elders fell down before the lamb having every one
of them harps and golden vials full of odors which are the prayers of saints.
In verse 9, it says, they sung a new song, saying,
Thou art worthy to take the book and to open the seals thereof, why?
For Thou wast slain and hast redeemed us to God by Thy blood out of every kindred and
tongue and people and nation, and hast made us unto our God kings and priests, and we
shall reign on the earth.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was ten thousand times ten thousand, and thousands
of thousands, saying with a loud voice, Worthy is the Lamb that was slain to receive power
and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing, and every creature
which is in heaven, and on the earth and under the earth, and such as are in the sea, and
all that are in them, heard I saying, Blessing and honor and glory and power be unto him
that sitteth upon the throne and upon the Lamb forever and ever.
The four beasts said, Amen, and the four and twenty elders fell down and worshipped him
that liveth forever and ever.
That's our God.
He rules and he reigns.
The heathen rage.
God shall laugh, has them in derision.
They hold their fist at God.
They think they're victorious.
But Jesus says, Be of good cheer, I have overcome the world.
When we take in context the entirety of what Jesus says in these few chapters of the Gospel
of John, we find that Jesus, there's something to embrace, why?
Because Jesus says, I want to prepare you, I'm being deliberate in what I'm speaking
to you, I want you to understand that the persecutions are going to come, I want you
to understand that the world's going to hate you, I want you to understand that they're
going to think, they're going to put you out of the synagogues and the time's going to
come when they, the one that thinks that they're killing you is doing God's service
and all of these things, and I'm telling you, I want you to have peace and I want you to
have joy and I want you to be able to remember these things.
There's something to embrace.
Listen, this morning, we need to be in the Bible, we need to be in the Bible.
There's a lot going on in our world.
A lot going on in our world.
But I submit to you this morning that our God's still on His throne.
He's never going to be overthrown, He's never going to be defeated, He's never going to,
He's on His throne and He forever will be.
The Bible says, the Lord God omnipotent reigneth.
He rules and He reigns.
Everything's happening in His time.
Everything's falling into place, just as He said it would, because He knows all things.
And He has revealed to us in His Word these truths and He's providentially preserved for
us the Bible so that we could know them and we must embrace them.
How often we have people today, I mean people that profess to be believers, followers of
Christ that do not have a biblical worldview.
Their worldview is shaped by whatever news group that they listen to, that they watch,
that they read.
I shared with you weeks ago the statistics of worldview, biblical worldview.
Listen, that's a serious situation in our society today.
Of those that profess Christ, they don't have a biblical worldview, why?
Because they're not embracing the Word.
But Jesus says, these things I have spoken unto you.
This morning, we need to embrace His Word.
We need to expect that there's going to be tribulation.
In the world, you shall have tribulation, but we need to understand that in Him, we
can have peace.
And He says, be of good cheer.
Isn't that amazing?
In the midst of all that's taking place, I mean some of the message that Jesus is giving
to His disciples with regard to the hatred that they would face and the persecution that
they would face and the tribulation that they would endure, He says, be of good cheer.
Be of good cheer.
Why?
Because I have overcome the world.
I have overcome the world.
There's someone to exalt.
This morning, this week, in our lives, we need to be diligent and purposed in exalting
the Lord Jesus Christ, lifting Him up, seeing Him in His rightful place, high, holy and
lifted up.
Because we serve a great God.
We serve the victorious Savior.
And thanks be to God, which giveth us the victory.
John would say this in 1 John chapter number 5.
We sing the song, faith is the victory.
You familiar with the song?
Well, 1 John 5 and verse 4 says, for whatsoever is born of God overcometh the world, and this
is the victory that overcometh the world, even our faith.
Who is He that overcometh the world?
But He that believeth that Jesus is the Son of God.
Faith is the victory.
We sing the song, victory in Jesus.
Isn't it wonderful?
But sometimes we live like we've been conquered.
No, Jesus says, be of good cheer.
I have overcome the world.
Let's pray together.
Lord, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
We thank You for Your Word, the truth contained therein.
The message that was delivered to the disciples in this intimate setting was so valuable.
You've chosen to give us a recorded, written Word.
It's inspired and preserved.
I pray that You'd help us as Your people to embrace Your Word.
Help us to go through life with our eyes wide open, knowing that You've revealed to us the
things that we should expect.
Help us to abide in You that we might have Your peace, a peace that passeth understanding,
that Your peace would truly rule in our hearts.
And God, I thank You that You overcome the world, that You're victorious.
I pray that You would help us to exalt You in our lives daily, in our church corporately,
that we'd see You in Your rightful place, high, holy, and lifted up.
God, we'd be found faithful until that day that we meet You face to face.
In the midst of all that's taking place, would You help us to be of good cheer?
Would You help us to keep our eyes on Thee?
Lord, in this moment of invitation, maybe there's someone that's not sure of heaven.
They need to be saved this morning.
I pray that the Holy Spirit of God would convict them of their sin, of Christ's righteousness
and of judgment to come.
Father, maybe there's someone here this morning, maybe several, Lord, that are Your children
that are troubled, that don't have that peace that we spoke of this morning.
They're not of good cheer.
They're troubled by all that's going on.
God, would You help them this morning to refocus?
Would You help them, Lord, to fix their gaze upon Thee, to embrace the truth of Your Word,
to know that You have revealed to us those things that would transpire in the days ahead?
I pray that You'd move and work as only You can.
We'll give You the honor and glory for all that You'll do.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.