And it's been a couple of weeks since we've been in the book of 2 Corinthians.
I preached the first few verses of this chapter a few weeks ago,
and then we had a group here from the Rapidan Baptist camp.
And then I preached a message from Acts 8, preached unto him Jesus.
And then now we're going to pick it back up here in 2 Corinthians 8.
As you know our theme, you see it on the banners behind me,
God's grace is sufficient.
And I'm so thankful for that biblical truth.
And each year, in fact on Thursday,
celebrated 14 years of being the pastor here at Fellowship Baptist Church.
And starting in 2012, I got here in August of 2011,
in 2012 we had a theme for that calendar year.
And every year we pick a theme,
and I preach something on Sunday mornings that goes along with that theme.
Often times it's been through a book of the Bible,
and sometimes there's been a few years where it's been a topical theme.
And this year, God's grace is sufficient.
I've been preaching on Sunday mornings through 2 Corinthians.
What a great book. We've learned many wonderful, valuable truths.
And we find here that as we enter into this section of the book of 2 Corinthians,
the Apostle Paul is dealing with a subject that sometimes people shy away from
because it's uncomfortable, but it's a biblical truth that God gives us,
and it's principles of giving.
And I'm thankful this morning that when we worship God,
there's a number of different ways in which we worship the Lord,
but one way that we worship God is through our giving.
And we see that throughout the entirety of Scripture.
In fact, in 2 Corinthians 9, I won't be dealing with it this morning,
but we find that the Bible says that God loveth a cheerful giver.
I find that one of the most exciting examples throughout all the Scripture
of a cheerful giver is when David leads those to give towards the building of the temple.
He gave of his own resources. He then encourages others to give for the temple.
And they are rejoicing.
In fact, if you were to pick it up and look in the text of Scripture in 1 Chronicles,
and just kind of midpoint, you might think that they're rejoicing over some great military victory
or some other great feat,
but we find that the reason that they're rejoicing in the manner in which they are
is because God enabled them to give.
That they were able to give, and they were giving.
David was giving for the construction of a temple that he would never step foot in,
that he would never worship God in,
but he knew that God had enabled him to be able to give for a future generation.
And so I'm thankful that God gives us encouragement and truth.
In fact, as we look at the first six verses of this passage of Scripture a couple of weeks ago,
we dealt with verse number one, and notice the Bible says,
Now that would be Philippi, Thessalonica, Berea, Athens, Corinth.
Those were the places in which were going during that first missionary journey
that the Apostle Paul had the opportunity to go there to.
And those churches would be Philippi, Thessalonica, Berea.
And what an opportunity as Paul begins to encourage the believers in Corinth
with the testimony of those that he refers to as the churches of Macedonia.
Paul wanted them to know some things, and as we look through that text of Scripture,
we learn, first of all, that those believers were suffering.
The Bible describes their suffering as being deep poverty.
And as we notice that they're suffering, we also notice that they were surrendered.
The Bible tells us that they were first willing, they first gave their own selves to the Lord.
They were willing, in verse number three, of themselves.
And then we notice that they were sensitive.
They were sensitive to the leadership of the Holy Spirit of God in their lives.
We see that in verse one and verse five.
We see that they were sensitive to the needs of others.
And so as we look at that first six verses, again, it was a few weeks ago, just a quick recap,
we come to verse number seven, as we enter into our text this morning,
and notice what the Apostle Paul says as he's writing here to this church in Corinth.
He says, therefore, based upon what he's just mentioned and given,
he says, therefore, as ye abound in everything,
in faith, and utterance, and knowledge, and in all diligence,
and in your love to us, see that ye abound in this grace also.
I've titled the message from verse number seven, abound in this grace also.
I would say this morning that as we look at the text of Scripture,
and we'll make our way through verse number 15 as we get through it this morning,
but I would say that as we begin looking here at verse number seven,
and we see that the Apostle Paul says that ye abound in everything,
and he lists these things, but he says that ye abound in this grace also.
I'm reminded this morning that God has called his people to be complete in Christ.
God has called his people to be mature believers.
We're to grow in grace and knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ
as we walk with Christ, and I don't know where you are on your journey,
but as we walk with him, and as we are conformed to the image of his dear son,
as we're growing and gaining that maturity where we are able to deal with
and to partake of that which God refers to as strong meat of the word,
we find that God wants us to be mature, to be complete.
I'm reminded, hold your place here in 2 Corinthians,
but turn to the book of 2 Peter if you will,
and we'll be back to 2 Corinthians 8 in just a moment,
but by way of introduction, I want to remind you of what Peter says
as he's writing here in 2 Peter chapter 1, and as he's writing to these believers,
we find that there's this obvious emphasis that is given with regard to growth spiritually,
and we understand the importance, we understand the growth charts
when we talk about physical growth, when we have children,
and you see their development and the different stages in which they go through,
and the reality is that as believers, there should be spiritual growth in your life and in my life,
and it should be that we're growing in grace and knowledge,
that we're not just kind of settled and getting stagnant and just kind of floundering around,
no, that we're going on unto perfection, that we're growing in our Christian life,
and here's what Peter says, here's how he says it in 2 Peter 1,
notice if you will, in verse number 3,
according as his divine power hath given unto us all things that pertain unto life and godliness,
through the knowledge of him that hath called us to glory and virtue,
whereby are given unto us exceeding great and precious promises,
that by these ye might be partakers of the divine nature,
having escaped the corruption that is in the world through lust,
all that good stuff, verse 3 and 4, I mean, praise the Lord, I'm saved by the grace of God,
I understand that I have these precious promises, I understand the work that he's doing,
I've escaped the corruption that's in the world through lust, I mean, hallelujah,
but notice in verse number 5, and beside this, notice what he says,
giving all diligence, you ever see somebody that's not diligent?
You know what it is to be diligent, you know what it is to not be diligent,
and here Peter says giving all diligence, notice the next two words, add to, add to,
now understand he's not saying that we add to so that we can be saved, stay saved, that we can know,
but we're to grow in our walk with Christ, we're to grow spiritually,
and he says add to your faith virtue, and to virtue knowledge,
and to knowledge temperance, and to temperance patience, and to patience godliness,
and to godliness brotherly kindness, and to brotherly kindness charity.
Now notice with me in verse number 8, he says for if, what does it say? These things.
He doesn't say if this thing, he says if these things, again, that's that growth,
spiritual growth in the life of a believer, if these things be in you and abound.
What did Paul say as we're looking at this passage in 2 Corinthians chapter 8?
Abound in this grace also.
And so Peter says that if these things be in you and abound,
they make you that you shall neither be barren nor unfruitful in the knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ.
See the reality is that as a believer, we want to abide in Christ,
we want to grow spiritually, we want to be fruitful in our Christian lives,
and we find that Peter says add these things, again,
we find that the product is that if they're in us and they abound,
they make you that you should neither be barren nor unfruitful in the knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ.
I'm reminded of what the Lord Jesus Christ said to the scribes and Pharisees in Matthew 23 and verse 23.
You don't need to turn there, but here's what Jesus says.
Woe unto you.
Now anytime you see that phraseology, it'll caught your attention.
Why? Because Jesus is speaking, of course, he's talking to these scribes and Pharisees,
and notice what he says. Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites.
For ye pay tithe of mint and anise and cumin and have omitted the weightier matter.
matters of the law, judgment, mercy, and faith.
But then I want you to catch what Jesus says at the end.
So he says, you're doing this, but you've omitted this.
You're paying tithe of mint and anise and cumin,
but you've omitted the weightier matters,
the judgment, the mercy, and faith.
And here's what Jesus says, these ought ye to have done
and not to leave the other undone.
So what's Jesus saying?
You should be doing all of it, amen.
Don't get this part right and not do this part.
Don't do this part and not do this part.
No, the complete in Christ.
And we find that it's only through the work
of the Holy Spirit, using the word of God,
that God will allow us to be complete in him,
that we can grow in knowledge of our Lord
and Savior, Jesus Christ.
Peter said, we read 2 Peter 1, but in 1 Peter 2,
as newborn babes desire the sincere milk of the word,
that ye may grow thereby.
So now as Paul is referring to these here in Corinth,
back in 2 Corinthians chapter number eight,
we find that Paul offers praise to the churches
of Macedonia for their sacrificial giving.
He tells the church in Corinth that these churches
of Macedonia, they gave sacrificially,
they were an example, and now he's going
to encourage the believers in Corinth
to abound in this grace giving also.
So notice in our text, if you're there back
in 2 Corinthians chapter eight, in verse seven,
and we'll see it in verse 10 and 11 as well,
notice if you're taking notes, number one,
Paul commends the believers in Corinth.
Paul commends them.
We find that he begins in verse number seven,
he says, therefore, as ye abound in everything.
And then Paul lists something specifically.
He says, as he's commending these believers in Corinth,
he references their faith.
You know, this morning, it's important
that we have the right belief, amen?
It's important that we contend earnestly
for the faith that was once delivered to the saints.
It's important that we live by faith.
We can use this word faith by understanding
the body of doctrine that we hold to,
but we also understand faith cometh by hearing,
and hearing by the word of God.
The just shall live by his faith,
and we understand that without faith,
it's impossible to please him,
and Paul references their faith.
Listen, it's important for us to know
what the Bible teaches.
It's important for us to be able to stand firm
upon the truth of God's word.
It's important that when somebody asks us
of the hope that lieth within us,
that we can go to the Bible,
and we can take and prove biblically
why we have the position that we do.
So Paul, as he commends the believers in Corinth,
he starts by their faith.
He then says, and notice, in faith and utterance.
Those are the things that we speak.
And so Paul is acknowledging,
now understand, there's a great difference
between the church in Corinth
in 1 Corinthians and 2 Corinthians.
There's still some problems,
but man, they responded to what Paul had written
to them in 1 Corinthians,
and there's some growth that's obvious
when you read 1 Corinthians and 2 Corinthians.
There's some growth that has taken place
within the believers in Corinth.
And so Paul says, I'm commending you.
Why?
Because you abound in everything in faith and utterance.
And then he says, he references their knowledge.
He says, and knowledge.
Now, when we look at the biblical word for knowledge here,
and understand what Paul's talking about,
he's really referencing not just the knowledge
of worldly wisdom or worldly things.
No, he's talking about the knowledge of God.
How do we know God?
We only know God through his word.
To know God is to know his word.
And you can ask people questions about who is God
and what their thoughts are about God,
and they could give you a number of different answers
based on various sources,
but I'm thankful this morning that God gave us a Bible.
And that in the Bible, he's revealed himself to us,
and he wants us to know who he is.
He wants us to know that he loves us,
that he wants us to know the plan of redemption,
of salvation through the Lord Jesus Christ
as we study the scriptures.
And it's a statement that was made
by a theologian of yesteryear
that the Bible he described
as being the unfolding drama of redemption,
and how the Old Testament would point
towards Messiah who would come,
and that would live a perfect and sinless life,
Christ Jesus, God in flesh,
and that he would go to a cruel cross,
that he would die,
and he would pay for the sin of humanity.
And we find the Old Testament prophesying of that.
We read the gospel records recording that for us.
And then we read the New Testament church
going forth and proclaiming this wonderful message
of the gospel that Jesus saves.
Listen, God wants us to know who he is.
He wants us to know him deeply and intimately.
I think about the apostle Paul
when he says that I may know him.
I may know him.
And Paul, as he's commending the believers here in Corinth,
he says that you abound in everything,
in faith, and in utterance, and knowledge,
and he says, and in all diligence.
There were some things that were sent to them,
and they responded appropriately,
and they dealt with what God had given to them.
And then notice how he finishes this.
He says, and in your love to us.
I want you to think about the understanding
of what Paul is mentioning here of this love.
In fact, we read about brotherly kindness
in 1 Peter chapter number one.
We read about love.
We understand that Jesus said this,
a new commandment I give you.
What was that new commandment?
That we love, and he said, by this shall all men know
that you're my disciples.
By what?
By your love one for another.
As the apostle Paul is writing to the church in Thessalonica,
he's encouraging them to abound in their love,
one towards another.
He tells them, as he's really commending the believers
in Thessalonica, he says, look, you already do this.
You already love one another, but I want you to exceed,
to grow more and more in this area.
So Paul, as he's commending these believers here in Corinth,
he says, in your love to us.
Now, I want you to see how he commends them
in verse number seven, as we look at this list
of these five things that he mentions,
but I want you to also go back
to 1 Corinthians chapter number one,
and I want you to see what God tells us
about the church in Corinth here
in 1 Corinthians chapter number one.
We'll be right back to 2 Corinthians chapter eight,
but I want you to notice, as Paul is writing
in this first letter to the same church,
in 1 Corinthians chapter number one, in verse number four,
Paul says, I thank my God always on your behalf
for the grace of God, which is given you by Jesus Christ,
that in everything ye are enriched by what?
By him.
In all, what does it say?
Utterance and in all knowledge.
Were those not two of the things mentioned
in 2 Corinthians eight?
Two of the very things that were mentioned
in 2 Corinthians eight were utterance and knowledge,
and Paul says that in everything ye are enriched by him,
in all utterance and in all knowledge,
even as the testimony of Christ was confirmed in you,
so that ye come behind in no gift,
waiting for the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ.
And so we begin to see what Paul says
in 1 Corinthians one, and we look here
in 2 Corinthians chapter number eight,
and here's the key for each of us,
is that it's through him.
God is working in us.
Your growth and my growth and the growth of every believer
is the result of the Holy Spirit of God working
and using his word in your life,
and as you yield and surrender, you grow spiritually.
Have you ever met anyone that wants to be taller?
Man, if I could just have another inch,
if I could just have another four inches,
and the reality is that there's some part of genetics
that play into that, and Joseph, of course,
he's about six, eight now, and he says,
I don't want any more inches, I'm tall enough at this point,
and the reality is that when you look
at some of those genetics and physical growth,
you can wish and wish and wish and wish
that you could get taller, but there's nothing you can do
to add to your stature, right?
Nothing you can do, but can I tell you
that that's quite the opposite
when we talk about spiritual growth?
How you grow spiritually is dependent
upon how you let God work in your life,
how you yield to him and you surrender to him,
because the Holy Spirit of God, if you trust at Christ
or when you trust at Christ as your savior,
if you're here this morning and you're saved
by the grace of God, the Holy Spirit of God gave you.
a gift, a spiritual gift, and he is,
the Bible says that our body is the temple
of the Holy Ghost, which is in you,
which you have of God.
We're not our own, we're bought with the price.
And he begins to do a work in our lives,
and as we yield ourselves to Christ,
as we yield ourselves to his word,
as we spend more time in his word,
as we come and hear the preaching and teaching
of God's word, and we surrender and yield
and obey, then we grow.
I have an idea when I think about physical growth
that we reach a place where this is where,
this is as tall as I'm ever gonna be.
And I reach that end point of physical growth,
there's no more height for me.
I'm 45, I'm past the growing years.
People keep telling Joseph, well as men,
you can grow until you're 21.
He's like, I'm good.
He's only 18.
I kinda stopped growing when I was about 16.
I was 5'11 and a half when I was a freshman
in high school, and I graduated high school
at six foot and about a half.
I grew one inch through high school.
I just kinda stopped growing.
But that's not the case spiritually.
And Paul says, you abound in this, in these things,
but notice as he is commending them,
not only does he mention these things individually,
but if you skip down to verse 10,
and we'll get back to verse eight and nine
in just a moment, but look at verse number 10.
He says, and herein I give my advice,
for this is expedient for you who have begun before,
not only to do it, to do, excuse me,
but also to be forward a year ago.
So in verse 10, I believe that the apostle Paul
is really commending them for their intentions,
for their intentions.
They, when they heard about this need,
they intended to participate it.
They intended to do something about this need.
He tells them that they were forward a year ago.
He says in verse number 11,
now therefore perform the doing of it.
Can I tell you this morning that good intentions are good,
but it's gotta be more than just intentions.
Have you ever had somebody,
I plan to do this, I intend to do this,
and they just never get around to it.
They just never do it.
And so Paul is commending these believers,
but then as we kinda transition in the text of scripture,
he goes from commending them to number two,
Paul challenges the believers in Corinth.
See, the apostle Paul was acknowledging the areas
in which these believers in Corinth
were doing what they ought to do.
But then he challenges them, why?
Because we're to be complete in Christ.
We're not to do these and leave this undone
or to do this and leave that undone.
We're to add to giving all diligence, why?
So that I could be mature, complete.
And so Paul commends them, but then he challenges them.
The first challenge is at the end of verse number seven,
when he says that ye abound in this grace also.
Oh, church in Corinth, you're doing all of these things,
your faith, your utterance, your knowledge,
your diligence, your love towards us.
But listen, there's an opportunity for you to grow,
to abound in this grace also, to be complete in Christ.
He is going to issue this challenge
to the believers in Corinth.
And we find this morning that for each of us,
as we have the record of scripture,
not only do we see the challenge issued to these believers,
the recipients of this letter,
but I believe that God is issuing a challenge to us as well.
That we too would desire to be complete in Christ,
that we would understand that,
yes, we can be engaged in doing this,
but God wants us to be well-rounded.
He wants us to be complete.
We find in the text of scripture,
not only does he challenge the believers
to abound in this grace also,
as he says at the end of verse number seven,
but I believe that he challenges the believers in Corinth
to remember the example of Christ.
What an example it is.
Notice in verse number eight,
we find that here the Bible says,
I speak not by commandment,
but by occasion of the forwardness of others,
and to prove the sincerity of your love.
Verse nine, for ye know the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ,
that though he was rich,
yet for your sakes he became poor,
that ye through his poverty might be rich.
I could preach a whole message on verse number nine
from 2 Corinthians eight.
The reality is that as Paul would challenge
these believers in Corinth to remember the example of Christ,
he starts out in verse nine by saying, ye know.
If you're saved this morning,
if you've been saved by the grace of God,
ye know the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ.
You know the truth of the incarnation,
and you know the truth of the substitution
where he went to that cruel cross,
and he took your place and my place and paid for our sin.
We understand the truth of the burial
and the resurrection and the ascension.
We know those things.
In the context of the passage of scripture,
the apostle Paul is challenging the believers
in this area of giving,
this area of abounding in this grace also,
and he says, remember the example of the Lord Jesus Christ.
Notice, it says that though he was rich, he's God.
In the beginning was the word, and the word was with God,
and the word was God, is God.
The Bible tells us in John,
as we look at the beginning of this passage of scripture,
that all things were made by him.
Without him was not anything made that was made.
We find that in just a little while
as we go through the text of scripture
of John chapter number one,
that John the Baptist is crying out,
and he speaks about there's one
that is preferred before me.
Why?
For he was before me.
Physically speaking, John the Baptist was older,
but he says that Jesus was before him.
Why?
Because of the eternality of Christ.
And though he was rich, notice if you will,
look at your Bibles and turn to the book of John,
and I want you to look in John 17,
and I want you to see how this is worded in John 17.
When we think about remembering the example of Christ,
though he was rich, yet for your sakes he became poor.
In John chapter number 17,
in verse number three, it says,
and this is life eternal, that they might know thee,
the only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom thou hast sent.
I have glorified thee on the earth.
I have finished the work which thou gavest me to do.
And now, O Father, glorify thou me with thine own self,
notice what he says, with the glory which I had with thee
before the world was.
Jesus is eternal, he's God.
And he was worshiped as God,
but he left the throne room of heaven.
Though he was rich, he became poor for your sakes,
that we, through his poverty, might be made rich.
And we begin to understand the example
that they're being encouraged to remember
of the life of Christ, and understanding this morning
that everything that I have, everything good about you,
about me, is all because of God.
Everything.
He says to the believers in 1 Corinthians,
the same people that he's writing to here,
he says, what hast thou that thou didst not receive,
in 1 Corinthians chapter four, in verse number seven.
In the book of Deuteronomy, we find that God is warning
the children of Israel as they would enter
into the land of promise that he would provide for them.
And he says, when you go into the land,
and you find houses which you did not build,
and you find vineyards which you did not plant,
and you enjoy all these good things of the land,
beware lest thou forget the Lord.
And then he tells them a couple of chapters later
that it's God who gives the power to get wealth.
Everything that we have is because of the good hand of God.
And we find that the Apostle Paul,
in the midst of this instruction with regard to giving,
and this challenge in which he's issuing
to the believers in Corinth, he has already dealt
with the churches of Macedonia
and their sacrificial giving, their example.
And now he says, but you believers in Corinth,
I commend you for all these things that you've done,
but I wanna challenge you that you abound
in this grace of giving, this grace also.
I wanna challenge you to remember the example of Christ.
I wonder this morning, how often do we really go
through life remembering the example
of the Lord Jesus Christ?
What he truly did so that you could be saved.
What he truly did, what he did so that.
that I could be saved. We sing about His greatness and we should. We sing about salvation and
we should. But sometimes we just need to get along with God and just really let it sink
in of what He did to save us. Listen, how shall we escape if we neglect so great salvation
is how it's worded in the book of Hebrews. Listen, this thing of being saved is an amazing
gift. The gift of God is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord. He gave Himself. He
gave all. He left it all so that we could be saved because He loved us. And as Paul
is writing to these believers in Corinth that know this, they're saved. And he says, listen,
the churches of Macedonia, they gave sacrificially. And now I'm going to challenge you to abound
in this grace also. And the reality is that we used some examples a couple of weeks ago
of those that gave sacrificially and for the most part many in America really have no concept
of what it means to give sacrificially. Many of us in America have no concept of what it
means to pray for our daily bread. We're just so distanced because of the provision
that we have here in America. We don't know what it's like. And Paul is writing to these
believers in Corinth and he's saying to them, would you abound in this grace also? Remember
what Christ did for you. Remember the sacrifice. See, when we truly remember the sacrifice
that Christ made for us and we truly acknowledge all that He's done for us, what is it that
we would not be willing to give Him? What is it that we say, no, no, this is, no, He
did it all for me. Jesus paid it all. Did He not? Aren't you thankful He didn't just
put a down payment for your salvation and then told you to figure it out? No, no, He
paid it all. Because He died for me, I'm going to live for Him. And we come to this passage
and it's a beautiful verse of scripture that we could preach an entire message on in verse
number 9, but it's in the context of giving in this challenge. Remember what Christ did
for you. Can I ask you this morning, where would you be without Christ? Theologically,
we understand the answer. It would be that we'd be lost on our way to hell. Spend eternity
in a lake of fire. But I wonder, not only would it be that we're eternally damned to
the lake of fire, lost, but I wonder how many of us would have lives that are just wrecked.
Lives that are just miserable. I mean, maybe we'd have nice things, maybe we'd have a secure
bank account and a nice vehicle, but just empty. Because the things of this world cannot
provide you with true joy. Where would we be without Jesus? He continues to challenge
them. He's going to challenge them, number three, to fulfill their commitment. In verse
10 and 11 we read, I read verse 10 a moment ago, but look at the two verses together.
He says, and herein I give my advice, for this is expedient for you. Listen, Paul understands,
listen, he's not trying to get anything for himself. He says, this is expedient for you.
He tells them who have begun before, not only to do, but also to be forward a year ago.
Now therefore, verse 11, perform the doing of it, that as there was a readiness to will,
so there may be a performance also out of that which ye have. So we find that Paul as
he's challenging them, he's challenging them to fulfill their commitment. And as Paul is
challenging them, he's saying this, he's saying that he wants them, it's expedient, it's beneficial
for you. I've said from this pulpit before, listen, I, Holly and I, we give. We tithe,
we give to missions, there's a special project, we give to, we give. The reality is that when
the preacher, and I'm not saying every preacher because I understand there's some issues out
there, but when the preacher biblically is preaching about giving, it's not for his benefit,
it's for your benefit. I already give. I'm going to have the blessing of God because
God gave me promises. Amen? And God gave you promises. And as you do what God has commanded
you and what the Holy Spirit of God has moved in your heart to do, as these believers in
Corinth had had this readiness to do, but they had not performed it, he's saying to
them it is beneficial, it's expedient for you that you do it, that you fulfill your
commitment. We understand, we've used the analogies over the years. We understand we're
not going to take anything with us. And, and I got a, I got a friend in Pennsylvania and
here's what he said. He said if I, when I die, and he was a man of wealth, he said when
I die, I, I know how those that are going to get my wealth will spend it, and it's not
for the cause of Christ. And here's what he told me. He told me this about 18 years ago.
Here's what he told me. He said, you know, it's going to be a surprise when I die because
they're not going to get what they think they're going to get. And he wasn't being unkind,
he was just saying, listen, I'm laying up treasure in heaven. Amen? And so Paul says
it's expedient for you. I understand, again, I, I made the comment by way of introduction.
Some people get all sideways about preaching on giving and they get uncomfortable about
it, and I understand it's an uncomfortable thing, and I understand that there's been
a, a, maybe a, a shadow upon churches, Christianity, that they, I hear people, they just want your
money. It's not the case. How was the tabernacle built? Free will offering. People just came
and gave. Why? Well, because if we could look at the picture, everything that they had was
because of God's good hand upon them. Amen? And so they gave. What about the temple? People
gave. They gave willingly. God loveth a cheerful giver. And he says here that there may be
a performance also that you would fulfill the commitment. Now here in the text we find
that he also is going to challenge them in, beginning in verse 12 and through the end
of our text this morning, to recognize the opportunity before them, to recognize the
opportunity before them. See, this giving that is spoken of here in the text of Scripture,
this giving was not necessarily for the tithe, if you will. This was a, a, because of some
saints that were suffering, and they needed some assistance. We find this, and Romans
talks about it, and Paul talks about it in 1 Corinthians. In fact, we touched on it a
bit on Wednesday evening as we were dealing with that text of Scripture, of praying for
us and the request that Paul made. And in Romans chapter 15, he talks about going and
performing the service which I have for Jerusalem, that it may be accepted to the saints. And
that's what he's referring to. And as we look at the opportunity that is before these
believers. And Paul wants to challenge them to consider that. So again, it's not just
talking about a tithe, then he's talking about this extra, this, this grace giving.
He says, for if there be first a willing mind, notice in verse 12, it is accepted according
to that a man hath and not according to that he hath not. And so we find that the, the
apostle Paul, he said in verse number 11, out of that which ye have, he says in verse
number 12, according that a man hath and not according to that he hath not. And then he
says in verse 13, for I mean not that other men be eased and ye burdened, but by an equality
that now at this time your abundance may be a supply for their want. Do you see the words
that the apostle Paul is using? The apostle Paul is saying, listen, there's some believers
that are struggling. Now he used the example of those in Macedonia, the churches in Macedonia
that begin the text of scripture, and he says that they had a great trial of affliction,
that they were in deep poverty, but that it abounded unto the riches of their liberality.
Amazing verbiage that God uses to describe the giving of the churches of Macedonia. Now
when we come to Paul reminding, challenging these believers in Corinth and, and challenging
them to recognize the opportunity that is before them, notice what Paul says, that now
at this time, notice when he says, your abundance.
The church, the believers in Corinth, they had an abundance according to the Scriptures,
that your abundance.
And he says this, may be a supply for their want.
Now I believe that we need to be careful that the word want here is not just a, I want a
yacht.
Okay, that somebody's talking about, it's truly a need that they had.
In this need that they had, and so here's the amazing thing, the amazing thing in God's
economy is that God can give something to someone here and bless them abundantly so
that they can be a channel that God will use to meet this person's need.
It's amazing how God does that.
I think about it with missionaries, so often how we have these missionaries and how it's
opportunity that people will feel a burden, the Holy Spirit of God will move in their
heart that they feel like they need to give a special offering to a missionary.
And we have the policy here that if someone gives a special offering to a missionary,
it goes directly to the missionary.
We're not in this business of, well do they really need it?
No, no, if God impressed upon somebody's heart that a missionary and a designated offering
is given for a particular missionary, that money goes to the missionary.
And God can use our abundance to meet their need.
It's amazing how God's economy works.
And here's the thing, God knows about your situation too.
He knows about your situation.
And sometimes we can overanalyze this and we can have the paralysis of analysis as we're
trying to go through the whole process and what if this and what if that and so on and
so forth.
But Paul is saying, I want you to recognize this opportunity.
I want you to recognize that God has blessed you in such a way that now you can be used
to be a supply for their want.
He continues at the end of verse 14 that their abundance also may be a supply for your want
that there may be equality.
So what does he say at the end of the verse?
Listen, the reality is that there might be a day in your life and it may be today, it
may not be today, but there may be a day in your life where you have an abundance and
God can use you to help somebody else's want.
And then there may be a day in your life that you have the want and God will help use somebody
else's abundance to meet that need.
That's how God's economy works.
Because we're sensitive to the leadership of the Holy Spirit of God.
And we find that, I said this a number of years ago, that there are times in which we
may be the individual that needs the prayer from our brothers and sisters in Christ.
And there may be times that we're the ones praying for them.
Now we don't always pray one for another, but you understand what I'm saying.
That we may be in a serious spiritual battle and we need to enlist the prayers of God's
people on our behalf.
And there may be other times that we're not quite in the level of the thick of it, so
to speak, and we're praying for others.
And God says through the Apostle Paul to these believers in Corinth, you're in a position
now at this time that your abundance may be a supply for their want, that their abundance
also may be a supply for your want, that there may be equality, and again, the opportunity
that God will use us as channels, as conduits to meet the needs of others.
He uses this Old Testament reference in verse 15, as it is written, he that had gathered
much had nothing over, and he that had gathered little had no lack.
I believe they're referring back to the manna in Exodus 16.
You begin to read about that and you see that he's using this example for these believers
in Corinth to understand that this is a biblical truth and they can learn from that.
I was in Brother Mark's class this morning and he talked a little bit about 1 Corinthians
10.
They're written for our admonition.
We learn from the truth of the Old Testament, and here Paul is going to go all the way back
to Exodus 16 and make a reference to help these believers apply the truth currently
in their lives.
So as we look at the text of Scripture, verses 7 through 15, and we deal with the title,
abound in this grace also, we find that Paul was able to first commend these believers.
He was able to commend them because of what they were doing, but then he challenges them.
We read in 1 Peter, we, excuse me, 2 Peter 1, we reference what Jesus said in Matthew
23, and I just wonder this morning, as we look at this text of Scripture and we see
specifically that he's dealing with this principle, these purposes of giving, but I wonder this
morning, what area of our lives do we need to add to?
See, none of us have arrived.
None of us are perfect.
We sing the song with the kids, God's still working on me to make me what I ought to be.
Right?
God's still working in our lives.
And so maybe this morning you sit through this whole message and you say, you know,
this area of giving, man, God's thoroughly worked in my heart and my life and I got this
one squared away.
Well, what other area in your life maybe, even through the passage when we dealt with
other things, has God maybe challenged you on?
What area of my life, as we think about that, those words, add to, in 2 Peter chapter number
1, what area of your life, what area of my life do I need to add to in my Christian life
so that I can be complete in Christ?
Like be complete in Christ, mature believers.
This morning there must be a desire on the part of every believer to be mature, to be
complete.
I want my life to please God.
I don't want God to look at my life and say, well, you got those things okay, but these
things you left undone.
No, we take all Scripture as given to us by inspiration of God and it's profitable for
us.
And as God's Word profits us, as we hear the truth of God's Word, how do we respond to
it?
What area of your life, what area of my life do we need to raise that flag of surrender
and say, Lord, I'm yours.
Lord help me to grow in this area of my life, specifically as we look at the text this morning
in this area of giving.
Listen, we live in a world that is so driven by finances.
We live in a world that is driven by finances.
I don't think you believe it, so I had to say it again.
The market tickers are all over the place and people checking all their IRAs and 401Ks
and this investment and that investment and all the retirement planning companies that
exist and I'm not against any of it in its proper perspective.
You know, there are some people that spend way too much time worrying about retirement
planning that never give two thoughts to eternity planning.
There are people that see the market fall and they're all kinds of sideways, like the
world's falling apart.
Can I tell you that one day, during the tribulation, and I don't plan to be here, but during the
tribulation a day's wage is going to give you enough food for a day.
That's what the Scriptures tell us.
Listen, at some point, and I'm not preaching economy, economic collapse, but I'm just simply
saying that if it does, my God's still on His throne.
Amen?
You know what the back, if you have a valid U.S. currency in your wallet, your pocket
today, it should still say on it, in God we trust.
But you know how most Americans live?
In the dollar we trust.
And as Christians, that's not how we live.
That's not how we live.
Because everything that we have is given to us by God.
And He gave all so that we could have life.
And as we evaluate our lives, when's the last time we gave sacrificially?
When's the last time we really let God have His way?
So you know what?
God, it's yours.
I'm not going to be so concerned about that retirement planning as I am about eternity
planning.
I'm not going to hold on so tight to the things of this earth.
No, no.
It's all God's.
My dad has told me this for years.
He's preaching this morning, so he won't hear this, but he's told me this for years.
Son, one day, it's all going to burn.
That's what he's told me.
one day, it's all going to burn. And if you read 2 Peter 3, that's where he bases that
comment off of the truth. It's going to melt with a fervent heat. And so this morning,
will you abound in this grace also? Say, God, I want to be complete in Christ. I want to
be mature in my walk with you. Let's pray. Father, we love you. We thank you for loving
us. Thank you for the day. Lord, I know this morning that we did not deal entirely on the
gospel, but we certainly sang about the gospel and we had the opportunity at looking at verse
9 there to understand the gospel. And Lord, maybe there's one here that's not sure of
heaven. I pray that the Holy Spirit of God would convict them of their need for Christ.
Help them to not receive this message inappropriately, to understand that their greatest need is salvation.
The lost man cannot understand the things of God. The natural man receiveth not the
things of the Spirit of God, their foolishness unto him. But those of us that have been saved
that know that we're going to heaven, we've been transformed. Our minds have been renewed.
We have a different perspective on life as a whole, on finances specifically. It's a
joy to be able to give to you, Lord. I thank you that we can worship you through our giving.
And I pray this morning that you would help us to be mature believers, complete in Christ.
That we take the challenge that's issued to the believers in Corinth and that we'd accept
it ourselves. That we would abound in this grace also. I pray, Father, that you'd move
and work in the moment of invitation. I pray that, Lord, you would help us to be doers
of the word and not hearers only. Well, thank you for all that you'll do. For it's in Christ's
name we pray. Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.