Probably one of the, I don't know if I would say the most familiar verses in this particular psalm is verse number 24.
This is the day which the Lord hath made, we will rejoice and be glad in it.
And it's a verse of scripture that not only is familiar to many of us, but it's a verse of scripture
that goes with a song that we sing in Sunday school, junior church, vacation, Bible school.
And this is the day, this is the day, and it's a great verse of scripture.
I'm going to try to walk through the entire psalm this evening.
I'm going to draw your attention by way of introduction to verses 28 and 29.
I want you to notice what the psalmist says in these two verses of scripture.
It's a powerful declaration that the psalmist uses to close this particular psalm.
The Bible says in verse 28 of Psalm 118,
Thou art my God, and I will praise Thee.
Thou art my God, I will exalt Thee.
O give thanks unto the Lord, for He is good, for His mercy endureth forever.
You notice on two occasions in verse number 28, the psalmist says,
Thou art my God.
And what a great truth of God's word that we can know that He is mine and I am His.
Isn't that wonderful?
There are countless billions of people on planet Earth tonight
that do not have a belief that they can have a personal relationship with any deity.
They serve all sorts of false gods.
Seek to be able to appease the gods through various rituals and sacrifices and what have you.
But we understand biblically that God has given to us,
He has revealed to us in the precious word of God
that the God that created the universe,
the God who created me,
the God who created you,
that He loves us and He died for us
and we can have a personal relationship with Him.
That is absolutely amazing.
And what a privilege it is for us and what a privilege it was for the psalmist
to be able to, with certainty and with confidence,
to be able to say, Thou art my God.
Praise the Lord.
If you can say that this evening,
you are in a very small percentage of the world population
that is privileged to know the truth of the Bible,
that you've had someone who has given to you the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ,
someone who has been faithful to declare to you the scriptures,
and what a blessing to know as the psalmist,
Thou art my God.
He is God, but He's my God.
There's a great difference between us acknowledging,
Thou art God alone, and He is, and the scriptures say that.
And it's not a problem that the scriptures say, Thou art God alone, because He is,
but there's something personal, there's something intimate
about the psalmist here in this text of scripture
saying, Thou art my God.
It's just like in the 23rd Psalm when David says,
The Lord is my shepherd.
It's that possessive use of that pronoun that He is my shepherd,
that yes, the Lord is the shepherd, He's the good shepherd,
He's the chief shepherd, He's the great shepherd.
All of that is true biblically,
but what a profound thought for us this evening
that we could say, Thou art my God,
that we could say, The Lord is my shepherd.
It's an amazing privilege.
Again, billions of people on planet Earth tonight
have no concept of the reality
that they can personally know the God of the universe.
That ought to break our heart, it ought to burden us
to be able to share the gospel with a lost and dying world,
no doubt, but it ought also to cause us to rejoice,
because Thou art my God, and I am His, and He is mine,
and I belong to Him, and we sing the song,
A New Name Was Written Down in Glory, and it's mine,
oh yes, it's mine, hallelujah.
And we find that the psalmist on two occasions here
in Psalm 118 and verse 28 when he says, Thou art my God,
notice his response to this understanding
of this personal relationship, to this recognition
of the fact that I belong to God,
that I am His and He is mine, he says this,
here's his response, number one, I will praise Thee.
By the way, isn't that a proper response
to the truth, Thou art my God?
He says, I will, he didn't say I might,
he said, I will, this is a declarative statement,
this is something that the psalmist is saying,
I will do this, I will praise Thee,
I will, notice number two, he says, I will exalt Thee.
By the way, it's important that we praise God,
and as we praise Him, yes, we're exalting Him,
the two are complementary one to the other,
and we have the privilege of being able
to exalt our Lord and our Savior.
What a blessing, I'm reminded of what John the Baptist
said in John chapter number three,
I must decrease but He must increase.
So often in life, we can go around
trying to lift up our own names,
how many people in the world today
are trying to make a name for themselves?
But our job is to preach the glorious name
of the Lord Jesus Christ, and He is my God.
So I've simply titled the message this evening
from Psalm 118 and verse number 28,
Thou art my God, and I will praise Thee.
Let's walk through the psalm and note
some of the reasons the psalmist was rejoicing.
He begins in verse number one,
Oh, give thanks unto the Lord.
And he begins to provide us as we walk through this psalm
a variety of reasons for which he is rejoicing,
for which he is praising, for which he is exalting
the God who is his God.
He says, if you were to look in verses one through four,
he's really focusing on the fact that God is merciful.
I'm thankful that the book of Ephesians
would say it this way, God who is rich in mercy.
And I begin to look here and we find he says,
Oh, give thanks unto the Lord, for He is good,
because His mercy endureth forever.
Think about God's mercy, God's mercy.
We don't get what we deserve because He's merciful.
Our God, it is part of His very nature that He is merciful.
And no doubt, each one of us that are here this evening,
each one that might be tuned in via live stream this evening,
we have experienced the mercy of God.
And we would say that we're so thankful
that our God is merciful and that His mercy endureth forever.
He says, thou art good there, and we'll get to that here.
We see it again at the end of the psalm.
But understand, we praise God not because our circumstances are always good,
but because He is always good.
Our God is always good.
He never, ever fails.
He never does anything wrong.
He is good.
It is His nature.
We find in verse 2,
let Israel now say that His mercy endureth forever.
Let the house of Aaron now say that His mercy endureth forever.
Let them now that fear the Lord say that His mercy endureth forever.
Do you think there's a theme there?
Do you think there's some truth that the psalmist is trying to nail,
drive deep down in the hearts of those that would read this?
In fact, you don't need to turn there,
but in Psalm 136, you see it repeated throughout the entire psalm,
for His mercy endureth forever.
The repetition is not filler.
I've written some papers in college and seminary,
and you write some papers, and sometimes you have filler, right?
And you just kind of get to that number of pages and words that you need.
And sometimes, if you're not careful, you can use some filler.
This is not filler.
God is repeating because He wants to drive home a point
that God's mercy endureth forever.
Why is the psalmist rejoicing?
Why is the psalmist praising?
Why is the psalmist exalting?
Well, number one, because he recognizes that God's mercy endureth forever.
It was Moses, as he prayed for the people,
that he was praying for these individuals that he had called to lead,
humanly speaking, to be the human leader.
And after they had doubted, and after they had turned back,
and they would not go forward, they said in Numbers 14,
we be not able.
Actually, it was the end of chapter 13 that they make that statement.
And we find that it was there that God was ready to really just destroy the people.
And here, Moses is a great intercessor.
And he begins to pray and he says in verse 17 of numbers 14 and now I beseech thee
He's begging and he's pleading let the power of my Lord be great according as thou hast spoken saying the Lord is
long-suffering and of great
mercy
this evening
God is merciful
We have been
We are the recipients of God's mercy in fact in Titus chapter number three in verse number five
It says not by works of righteousness, which we have done but according to his mercy
He saved us by the washing of regeneration and renewing of the Holy Ghost
This evening we praise God
Because he's merciful
You know, he's always merciful. He never stops being merciful. He says his mercy endureth forever
That's for us as his people
Because we know that the wrath of God during the tribulation days will be poor at poured out on humanity
But for us as his people his mercy endureth forever
Rejoice in that number two as we continue to walk through the psalm
We notice in Psalm 118 in verse number five. He's rejoicing because of answered prayer
I preached this morning on the subject of prayer and being a praying church a praying people and we find here in verse number five
Notice what the psalmist says I called upon the Lord in distress and then notice these four words the Lord
Answered me and set me in a large place
Listen, when's the last time God answered your prayer? I
Hope you can have some record in your life of when God has answered some prayer
By the way, one of the reasons that it's so important that we pray
Specifically is because we see God answer specifically when we pray generically
It's very difficult for us to know did God answer did he not answer because it was just some generic prayer
But when we pray
Specifically we see God answer
Specifically and the psalmist said I called upon the Lord in
Distress listen you have distress in your life. We all have distress in our life
There are things that happen things that occur and what do we do? How do we respond?
I mentioned this morning the pattern that was established in the early church the early church
the first century church was a praying church and
It was not the the crisis. It was not the
The the problem that they faced there in Acts chapter number 12 with Peter that that led them
yes, that was a
Particular situation, but but they had been praying all along
How do we respond
He says the Lord answered me the Lord answered me. It's a blessing when God answers prayer and
It excites us it
Encourages us
But you know what? It also does it gives us an opportunity to praise him and to exalt him
Why because God answered prayer because God did it because God hurt
Can you imagine this evening that God hears you when you pray?
Every single one of us we could all pray at the very same time
Every Christian on planet earth could pray at the same time and God understands and God hears and God is able and God answers
It's amazing
But remember, how does he end the the Lord? He says?
Thou art my God
He's my God and he hears me and he answers me in verses six and seven. We see
That the psalmist is rejoicing because God is on my side
Notice how he says it in verse six. The Lord is on my side
I will not fear what man can do unto me the Lord taketh my part with them that helped me
Therefore shall I see my desire upon them that hate me. Can you imagine this evening?
The Bible says the Lord is on my side. I mean this gives the the psalmist a great measure of confidence
We consider about the truth in the book of Romans
That that if God before us who can be against us
We are more than conquerors through Christ
We sang this evening faith is the victory
Amen, but thanks be to God which giveth us the victory through our Lord. Jesus Christ. Praise God and
The psalmist says the Lord is on my side
Evidently historically you can look back and you can find out that there was a conversation that took place and Abraham Lincoln
Then the president United States of America was asked this question
Whether or not God was on their side or the other side and he said son, I'm not concerned about that
I'm concerned whether or not I'm on God's side. That's a good perspective. Amen
Listen, God's gonna be on your side when you're on the right side
Amen
Then you can have the confidence listen if you're walking in obedience
If you're following the truth of the scripture if you're doing what God has commanded you to do
You can have confidence. The Lord is on my side
Now if you're out living in sin, if you're disobeying God and you're doing all kinds of whatever don't think God's gonna come over to your side
No, no, you need to come to God's side
Amen, and then you can have the confidence. The Lord is on my side why because I'm living right? I'm doing right?
I'm pleasing God with my life
And the psalmist says the Lord is on my side
Sometimes we
Can get concerned about whose side of something we're on and we can think about
you know if you ever played sports and you played pickup games and you begin to pick teams and who gets picked first and
Then who gets picked last it's always sad for the person that gets picked last but you have that
Situation and you want to see who's on which I listen the psalmist says I have confidence because God's on my side
Holy living is worth it
Holy living is worth it. It is worth pleasing God with your life
Because you have God's favor in your life. I want God's favor
God's blessings aren't just a
Smorgasbord kind of a situation. No. Yes
We find that as we look here that God blesses us as we live for him and we obey him
This is the Lord is on my side notice with me
God is trustworthy
Aren't you thankful this evening that he's never failed you. I
Failed him you failed him. I
Will fail him you will fail him, but he has never ever
Failed you and he never will
He never will God is faithful. God is trustworthy notice in verse 8 it is better
To trust in the Lord than to put confidence in man verse 9
It is better to trust in the Lord than to put confidence in
Princes, you know any people today are putting confidence in man
How many people today are putting confidence in and in those that have some level of authority?
We use the term here princes and we could look at that in our kind of
Generation and look at that as someone that has this authority. Listen, it's better to put your trust
It's better to put confidence in the Lord
Why because he's not gonna fail you
God always does what he says he will do always a hundred percent of the time
And we can rejoice in knowing that our God is trustworthy
some
Trust in their own ways
But we find the Bible plainly tells us that we're to trust in the Lord with all our heart
We're to lean not on our own understandings
Amen, and and all thy ways acknowledge him and he shall direct thy paths
Who are we trusting?
Well here the psalmist is rejoicing because God is trustworthy
Have you ever placed your trust in something that wasn't really?
Trustworthy someone or something and you were failed you were let down and it it impacted you
It adversely affected you maybe
You were on the other side where someone put some level of trust or confidence in you and you failed them
But God is trustworthy and the psalmist is is here rejoicing. Remember he starts the psalm. Oh give thanks unto the Lord
I mean, this is a a powerful a a powerful jubilant Thanksgiving
Now we understand that this particular Psalm Psalm 118 would be sung by those as they're going to the temple
It's a rejoicing. It's a a time of Jubilee
Why because God's trustworthy as we look at verses 8 and 9
Again, there's a number of reasons as we go through this portion of Scripture to see why is the psalmist rejoicing?
This evening. Can I tell you that we have many reasons to rejoice?
It's not just in Psalm 118 and we'll continue looking at a number of other things here
but understand with me that we have so many reasons to rejoice as
God's people thou art my God. I will praise thee thou art my God
I will exalt thee notice as we look at verses 10 through 13 that he is
My help in time of difficulty the Bible says in verse number 10 all nations compassed me about
But in the name of the Lord will I destroy them? They compassed me about yay
They compassed me about but in the name of the Lord, I will destroy them. They compassed me about like bees
They are quenched as the fire of thorns
for in the
name of the Lord I will destroy them thou has thrust sore at me that I might
fall but the Lord helped me he helped me you know it's a great truth as you study
through the Psalms to recognize that the Lord is my helper the Lord is my helper
the Bible says that he's a very present help in the time of trouble in that
encouraging to know that he's a very present help in the time of trouble
normally when trouble comes people flee you got trouble that's brewing and you
have people that flee and some have said it this way if you really want to know
who your true friends are it's in the time of difficulty in the time of trial
look around and who's there kind of a perspective well the Bible says that
that our God is a very present help in the time of trouble he doesn't forsake
us he doesn't leave us no he's present he's there he's my helper you notice
repeatedly that the psalmist said in verses 10 through 12 about the fact that
they compassed me about I mean surrounded I mean in a difficult place a
challenging place but the Lord helped me listen this evening he'll help you in
the time of your difficulty he'll help you day by day oftentimes we don't get
the help from God because we don't ask him we don't ask him I think of the
psalmist crying out help Lord I mean just just a simple prayer help Lord why
we need help but when you don't acknowledge the fact that you need help
you don't ask for help right in Hebrews chapter 13 in verse number 6 the Bible
says so that we may boldly say the Lord is my helper and I will not fear what
man shall do unto me help Lord we find that in verse number 14 there's three
statements that are made here that would cause the psalmist to rejoice that
should cause God's people to rejoice number one in verse 14 the Lord is my
strength my strength remember this from 2nd Corinthians chapter number 12 that
his strength is made perfect in weakness remember the fact that when we
talk about strength we're not always talking about physical strength and
though there's a need at times for our physical strength to be renewed in fact
in Isaiah 40 we read about that physical strength being renewed but we find that
oftentimes in the scriptures when you think about the strength it's talking
about that spiritual strength the strength in the inner man Paul speaks
about in 2nd Corinthians how that they fainted not why though their outward man
perished but the inward man was renewed day by day Paul prays for the believers
of Ephesus that they would be strengthened in their inner man the
spiritual strength and he says the Lord is my strength we are limited he is
unlimited the Bible tells us a verse that's often quoted and I would say out
of context I can do all things through Christ which strengthens me I can't tell
you how many times I've been to a Christian school basketball game and
have seen that verse on their jerseys are on their warm-up shirts as if God is
strengthening them to dunk or shoot a basketball that's really not the context
of it but here's what the context is whatever God has called you to do God
will strengthen you to do it we say I can't you're not trusting him because
the Lord is my strength and he will give you the strength he will give you
that strength that you need and listen I understand as human beings there are
times in which we grow weary there are times in which we don't have if you will
the strength to carry on but the Bible says as I referenced in Isaiah 40 in
verse 31 but they that wait upon the Lord shall renew their strength they
shall mount up with wings as eagles they shall run and not be weary and they
shall walk and not faint there's times in which people think I just can't go
any further abide in him amen he is the vine we're the branches he will give us
strength and here the psalmist is rejoicing why well one of the reasons in
verse 14 is because the Lord is my strength not only is the Lord my
strength but notice in verse 14 and song has it put a new song in your heart I
mean you go through life and you just have a song is he your song the Bible
says if you take your Bible there turn back to Psalm chapter number 40 notice
it's a great Psalm in Psalm chapter number 40 the Bible tells us and I love
the the perspective of a song God is my song listen this evening we have a new
song the Lord is my strength but the Lord is my song in verse 1 of Psalm 40 I
waited patiently for the Lord and he inclined unto me and heard my cry he
brought me up also out of an horrible pit out of the miry clay and set my feet
upon a rock and established my goings and he has put a new song in my mouth
even praise unto our God many shall see it and fear and shall trust in the Lord
this evening I'm not asking you if you can sing on tune I'm asking you if you
have a song amen the Lord is my song he's my strength
but he's my song how many times do you find yourself going through the the day
and just singing a hymn of the faith just singing a little chorus that we
sing in church and God encourages you and God uses that what a blessing I know
that I've said it a few times over the last month or so because I happen to
walk in on it so often but Fernando was sitting here this evening not in the
sanctuary he was sitting here and he was looking through the songbook and he said
this one right here pastor he said I can't say it is my favorite but it's
really up there and can it be oh what a great song man praise the Lord a song
the Lord is my strength the Lord is my song notice and has become my salvation
now let me say two things about this in verse 14 when he says and is become my
salvation oftentimes in the Old Testament the Psalms in particular the
word salvation will be used as deliverance not salvation and what we
might think of in a New Testament context of being saved and being
heaven-bound but there's truth to that as well but we think about the
deliverance listen God has delivered us God has done great things for us the
Apostle Paul rejoices greatly as he's speaking and talking about what the Lord
did for him in 2nd Timothy 4 and verse 17 he says notwithstanding the Lord
stood with me and strengthened me that by me the preaching might be fully known
and that all the Gentiles might hear and I was delivered out of the mouth of the
lion and the Lord shall deliver me from every evil work and will preserve me
unto his heavenly kingdom to whom be glory forever and ever amen that's the
salvation in the context of deliverance but I want you to understand that as New
Testament believers as we would use that word about salvation being saved being
heaven-bound that Paul talked about that a little bit in 1st Timothy chapter
number 1 when he said this in verse number 12 and I thank Christ Jesus our
Lord who hath enabled me for that he counted me faithful putting me into the
ministry who was before a blasphemer and a persecutor and injurious but I obtained
mercy because I did it ignorantly and unbelief and the grace of our Lord was
notice this exceeding abundant with faith and love which is in Christ Jesus
this is a faithful saying and worthy of all acceptation that Christ Jesus came
into the world to save sinners of whom I am chief the Apostle Paul his name was
Saul when he got saved in Acts chapter 9 his life was changed forever and he was
saved going to heaven he's the one that penned those words humanly speaking to
be absent from the body being confident that were absent from the body were
present with the Lord but he also was delivered and again in the Old Testament
particularly particularly in the book of Psalms that word salvation is often used
in the context of deliverance and the psalmist says the Lord is my strength
and song and has become my salvation and so we see these reasons why is it that
the psalmist is rejoicing in the way that he is why is he saying I will
praise thee I will exalt thee Oh give thanks man look at this list that we're
looking at this evening and this is just barely scratching the surface of all the
reasons to rejoice in verse 15 and 16 he's rejoicing because of God's power
the voice of rejoicing in salvation
is in the tabernacles of the righteous, the right hand of the Lord doeth valiantly.
The right hand of the Lord is exalted, the right hand of the Lord doeth valiantly.
Listen, our God has all power.
He is the Lord God omnipotent.
There is nothing that's too hard for Him.
Nothing too hard for Him.
He is able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think.
I said it this morning, there's hope because there's God.
Amen?
You live in a place, you live in a time when there's people that are hopeless,
that have no direction but as God's people.
Listen, don't get so caught up in the news and all the things that are going on
and lose your hope.
No, we have hope because we have God.
The blessed hope, the truth that Jesus is going to come back,
I don't know when and nor do you, but we have confidence.
We know that one day He's coming back and we have hope
because He doeth all things well.
He's on His throne.
He's alive and He's well.
He's never been defeated and He never will be.
As Curtis Hudson used to sing at the end of so many of his messages,
we are on the winning side.
And our God has all power.
Listen, it's good for us to recognize the power of God.
The power of God.
And He works through us.
His power through us.
But ye shall receive power after that the Holy Ghost has come upon you.
And ye shall be witnesses unto me both in Jerusalem and all Judea
and under the uttermost part of the earth.
Listen, we need God's power.
He said this when He gave the Great Commission in the Gospel of Matthew.
He said, all power is given unto me in heaven and in earth.
Go ye therefore, and He says this at the end,
and I will be with thee.
Hallelujah.
Listen, we need boldness.
We need power.
We need God's power to rest upon us.
I need God's power behind the pulpit.
But I need God's power every day of my life.
And you need God's power every day of your life.
I'm thankful that the Holy Spirit indwells us at the moment of salvation,
indwell with the Spirit of God.
But understand there's a difference between being indwelled by
and being filled with the Holy Spirit of God.
And we're to be filled with the Holy Ghost,
emptied of self so we can be filled with the Holy Ghost and have that power.
How we need some people today that would have God's power resting upon them.
We find that in verse 17 and 18,
something a little bit maybe that you might not think about,
but I like the fact that it's included here.
And that's the psalmist is rejoicing for chastisement.
God's correction.
Notice in verse 17,
I shall not die, but live and declare the works of the Lord.
The Lord hath chastened me sore, but he hath not given me over unto death.
You know, it's interesting.
He begins to talk about chastening here in verse 18.
And we begin to consider some things that God tells us about chastening.
Look, if you will, in the book of Proverbs in chapter number three.
Sometimes if we're not careful, we can have a wrong perspective on chastening, correction.
The Bible tells us in Proverbs chapter number three, verse number 11,
my son despise not the chastening of the Lord,
neither be weary of his correction.
For whom the Lord loveth, he correcteth, even as a father the son in whom he delighteth.
What would concern me is if God didn't correct me.
What would concern me is if there was never any chastening in my life.
Amen.
And the psalmist is rejoicing.
And I preached a message several years ago.
We had our theme as count your blessings.
I preached a whole message on being thankful for chastisement.
Look over in Hebrews 13, if you will.
It's repeated what we read in Proverbs chapter three.
There in Hebrews chapter 13, notice the truth that God gives to us.
I said 13, it's chapter 12, sorry.
Hebrews chapter number 12, in verse number four,
you have not yet resisted unto blood striving against sin,
and you have forgotten the exhortation which speaketh unto you as unto children.
My son, despise not thou the chastening of the Lord,
nor faint when thou art rebuked of him.
For whom the Lord loveth, he correcteth, even as a father the son in whom he delighteth.
He chasteneth and scourgeth every son whom he receiveth.
If ye endure chastening, God dealeth with you as with sons.
For what son is he whom the father chasteneth not?
Notice in verse 10, it says,
for they verily, speaking about the correction of fathers here on earth,
he says, for they verily for a few days chasten us after their own pleasure.
But notice this phrase, but he for our profit,
that we might be partakers of his holiness.
Now, no chastening for the present seemeth to be joyous.
Have you experienced that?
In the moment, it's not joyous, but I'm telling you, it's for our profit.
It's because God loves us.
It's a birthmark of a believer, right?
If he doesn't chasten you, if he doesn't correct you,
then you don't belong to him.
And the psalmist is, he's given us a whole list of things here.
In Psalm 118 of why he's rejoicing and why we ought to rejoice.
In the next several verses, he's kind of looking forward.
And I would kind of call it this, as we look at the next few verses,
I would say that it's kind of an expectation of what God's going to continue to do.
You know, the Bible tells us that we're to pray with thanksgiving.
Now, think about that just for a moment.
We understand we're to pray,
but he says that we're to pray with thanksgiving.
There are times that we pray and we can thank God for the answers even before they come.
Not that we're being presumptuous, but we're trusting that God will work.
And here, the psalmist in Psalm 118 is having,
in these next several verses of scripture, this perspective,
this understanding that God, he's not done working.
Aren't you thankful for that?
He's not done working.
It's not a situation where we can always just look to the past of what God has done.
It's not just that we look at the present as what God is doing,
but we can have confidence and we can rejoice that God is still going to.
Listen, this young man and his wife, they're going to go to Guatemala.
I'm assuming that they're pretty thankful that God is still going to work
and that the gospel is still going to be effective when they get there.
Amen.
Brother Sommerdorf goes all over preaching.
Why? Because he's trusting that the promise that God gave,
that his word would not return void,
the promise that God gave that through the preaching of the cross,
the promise that God made to preach the word,
to be instant in season, out of season, to reprove, rebuke,
exhort with all longsuffering and doctrine.
Yes, the time will come when they will not endorse sound doctrine,
but we still preach the word.
I preach the word every week.
Why? Because I believe God will still work.
I have confidence that not only has God worked,
not only is God working, but God will continue to work.
And he says in verse 19,
open to me the gates of righteousness.
I will go. Do you see how it's future?
I will go into them and I will praise the Lord.
This gate of the Lord into which the righteous shall enter.
I will praise thee for thou hast heard me and art become my salvation.
The stone which the builders refused is become the headstone of the corner.
This is the Lord's doing. It is marvelous in our eyes.
This is going forward, messianic type prophecy.
We find in verse 24, this is the day which the Lord hath made.
We will rejoice and be glad in it.
Save now, I beseech thee, O Lord.
O Lord, I beseech thee, send now prosperity.
Blessed be he that cometh in the name of the Lord.
We have blessed you out of the house of the Lord.
God is the Lord which hath showed us light.
Bind the sacrifice with cords even under the horns of the altar.
And then as we read by way of introduction, thou art my God.
And I will praise thee.
Thou art my God. I will exalt thee.
Oh, give thanks unto the Lord for he is good, for his mercy endureth forever.
It is good for us to take time to praise and to exalt our God.
It is good for us to take and evaluate some things as the psalmist does here
and just step back from the busyness of all that goes on around us.
Get our eyes off of all of the things that bother us.
Listen, there are some things that bother you.
Come on, I know there are.
Get your eyes off them circumstances that bother you.
Get your eyes on God who satisfies.
He's my God.
He's always good and his mercy endureth forever.
This evening,
How's my praise?
How's your praise?
How we doing praising the Lord?
I asked this question on Wednesday night,
just this past Wednesday.
We looked at Psalm 119.
I will talk you of all his wondrous works.
And I said that the average person
speaks 10,000 to 16,000 words every day.
That number, there's some factors
that determine the exact number.
Of course, what you do for a profession
will have an impact on that number.
Your gender will have an impact on that number.
And your personality will have an impact on that number.
But how many of our words are used praising God?
How many people have you talked to
this past four days since Wednesday?
How many of them heard you praising God?
With how many of your words?
Because the psalmist says, thou art my God.
I will praise thee.
Thou art my God.
I will exalt thee.
And this evening, he is worthy to be praised.
He is worthy to be exalted.
And we see so many reasons in Psalm 118.
And it's not an exhaustive list.
There's so many other things that you could go to
and look at this evening.
But what a power-packed psalm
of why the psalmist is rejoicing in the way that he is.
Do you know tonight that the God of the universe
is your God?
Can you say, as the psalmist said, thou art my God?
And if so, are you praising him?
Are you exalting him?
Because we ought to be.
We ought to be.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you so much for loving us.
Thank you that you're our God.
Lord, I don't know.
I've not heard every single person's personal testimony
of salvation in this room this evening.
But for most, I have.
God, I believe that the majority of us tonight,
if not all of us, could say, thou art my God.
The question before us is,
how are we doing in this area of praise?
We were challenged this morning
on how we're doing in the area of prayer,
to be a praying church.
But not only to be a praying church,
but to be a praising church.
Not this nonsense of praise and worship
and carnality and fleshly.
No, I'm talking about God honoring,
godly, biblical praise.
You are worthy.
We will praise you for all of eternity.
I pray that you'd help us now to start every day.
Would you help us to say, as the psalmist said there
in Psalm 118 and verse 28, thou art my God.
I will praise thee.
Thou art my God.
I will exalt thee.
Would you move and work in hearts and lives
as only you can, and we'll give you the honor
and the glory, for it's in Christ's name we pray.