verse of Scripture this morning, 2 Corinthians 5 and verse number 9, and I'll give you a moment
to turn there, 2 Corinthians 5 and verse number 9 this morning. Notice the Bible says this,
Wherefore we labor, that whether present or absent we may be accepted of him. Paul just concluded,
as we studied last week, these first eight verses of chapter number 5, he concluded the section
dealing with the certainty of heaven and the reality that all the redeemed will be with our
wonderful Savior for all of eternity. What a glorious truth. Amen. What a glorious truth
that God has given to us in his word so that we could have the confidence and the certainty
that when this life is over, when I take my final breath here, that I can be, I can know that I'll
be in his presence and I will forever be with him. We talked about last week the expectation
of every believer. If you've been saved by the grace of God this morning, your expectation is
heaven. You have that confidence. As he says in verse number 8, we are confident, I say,
and willing rather to be absent from the body than to be present with the Lord. And we have
that expectation. But I said this as we concluded the message last week, that not only do we have
the expectation, but we think about the excitement that should cause, that the expectation should
cause us to have great excitement. Why? Because I'm going to be with Jesus. And so many people,
as I mentioned last week, they want to talk about heaven and what is heaven like and so on and so
forth. And there are many things that God tells us in his word with regard to describing heaven.
But I want you to understand this morning that heaven is only heaven because our Savior is there.
If you take all of the descriptive terms, all of the wonderful things, but if Jesus is not there,
then it's not really heaven. And the amazing truth is that we find in this section of 2 Corinthians
5, verses 1 through 8, that Paul, he ended the fourth chapter talking about having that
eternal perspective and immediately goes to heaven and thinking about what our future is.
I said this last week, on our worst day, in our worst circumstance, we're still going to heaven.
If you're saved this morning, if you've been saved by the blood of Christ and you
have placed your faith and trust in the finished work of Christ at Calvary, His death,
burial, and glorious resurrection on your worst day, on my worst day, no matter what happens,
no matter who says or does whatever it is, I'm going to heaven. I'm going to heaven.
And what a blessed truth that is. Verse 9 begins in our text this morning,
wherefore, for which cause, on account of, that's what it means, wherefore,
based upon what has just been revealed, this is the response of the apostle Paul when he talks
about heaven, when he talks about the certainty and the confidence that he has that when he
finishes his life, when he takes that final breath that he'll forever be with his Lord,
he says, wherefore, wherefore, I'm saved. I'm saved. I have a secure future.
But notice he says, wherefore, we labor. We labor. What are we laboring for? Notice that whether
present or absent, we may be accepted of him. He says, my future is certain. My future is secure.
It got settled a long time ago when I was on the road to Damascus for the apostle Paul. His name
was Saul at the time, but it was settled. We sing the song. It's not in our songbook. And well,
I think we had a group of guys sing at one time, and it's a song that I remember singing when I
was younger. The old account was settled long ago. And if you get a good base in there, they say,
down on my knees, long ago, it was settled long ago. And certainly I remember that song as we
were singing it at an old mission, a rescue mission in downtown Los Angeles. I mean, a place where
some of these people, I mean, just terrible sets of circumstances, and they'd been saved by the
grace of God, and they came. And I'm telling you what, you had a worship service with those folks,
and you got up in there, and you're preaching, and they're worshiping the Lord. And I remember
listening to those old group of guys sing, the old account was settled. Listen, it was settled for
Paul. He knew where he was going. He knew that heaven was his home. It's secure. It's certain.
But he says this, I'm striving to please Him. I'm laboring. I'm striving to please Him. I'm not
striving to please Him so that I can be saved. I'm not striving to please Him so that I can stay
saved. No, I'm striving to please Him because I'm saved. The scriptures are clear. Your behavior and
my behavior matters to God. How we live matters to God. The matter of salvation is settled at the
cross, and I'm so thankful for that. But then how we behave, listen, our beliefs should impact our
behavior. And what Paul believed to be true as he writes to these believers in Corinth in this
fifth chapter, those eight verses about heaven, he then says, wherefore we labor, that
whether present or absent, we may be accepted of Him. I've simply titled the message this morning,
striving to please my Savior, striving to please my Savior. Let me share with you the first
thought this morning. Point number one, if you're taking notes, the desire of Paul. We're going to
look at this verse really in reverse order this morning because we see the desire at the end of
the verse. Notice what it says, we may be accepted of Him. Now, it's important that we understand
this word accepted. It means to be well-pleasing. It means that God would look at your life and look
at my life and it would be well-pleasing in the sight of God. And Paul says that his desire
is that he, that we, because he's speaking to this church at Corinth, to these believers, that he's
already said to them, for we know, we have this expectation, we have this certainty of heaven, but
then he says we. He's including these believers. And for us this morning, that we would say
collectively as Fellowship Baptist Church, that we should have the desire that we would be accepted
of Him, that we would be well-pleasing in the sight of God. We find that as you look at the life of
the Apostle Paul, I believe that his desire was a sincere one. I believe that as you look through
his life and you trace his steps, that he earnestly desired that his life would please
his Lord. He knew that he was going to heaven, that was settled, that was certain, but he wanted to
live in such a way that he would please God. I believe that Paul understood and faithfully
communicated with those that he ministered to that there was behavior that was pleasing to God,
and there's behavior that's not pleasing to God. In fact, Paul wrote to this same group of believers
in Corinth back in 1 Corinthians chapter number 10, and as he spoke of those of old, referring to
those in the Old Testament, he mentions to the church in Corinth that with many of them,
God was not well-pleased. He goes forth and he provides several examples as to why their behavior
did not please their God, and we find this morning that the Apostle Paul, he had this personal desire,
but not only did he have a personal desire, he desired that those to whom God allowed him to
minister, that they too would please God, that they too would have that desire, that they would be
accepted of him. We find that next week as we move forward into the text of Scripture, beginning in
verse number 10, what does Paul begin to talk about? He talks about the judgment seat of Christ, that we
must all appear before the judgment seat of Christ, and so understanding the certainty of heaven,
understanding the certainty of the judgment seat of Christ, tucked in between those two
realities, he says, here's what I do. I labor to please God. I am striving to please my Savior.
This desire that he has to be accepted of the Lord. Notice with me, if you will, over in Philippians
chapter number three, we'll look at a number of verses this morning in order to lay down and to
prove the truth of what we see in Paul sharing with these believers in Corinth and with us this
morning, this desire to please the Lord. In Philippians chapter number three, we find that Paul
begins, and we'll just pick it up in verse number 10 and go down through verse number 14, and notice
what he says in beginning in verse number 10, that I may know Him, that I may know Him. How well do
you know God? How well do you know Him? Think about that. Paul is right in this church in Philippi.
Paul had been walking with God for a long time, but he says that I may know Him. I don't want to
just know about God. I want to know Him personally and intimately. I want to know Him.
And he says that I may know Him, and the power of His resurrection and the fellowship of His
sufferings being made conformable unto His death, if by any means, notice what he says, I might
not as though I had already attained,
either were already perfect,
but I follow after,
if that I may apprehend that
for which also I am apprehended of Christ Jesus."
This is Paul's desire.
What is he trying?
What is he seeking to apprehend?
What is he seeking?
What's the goal of his life?
He says in verse 13,
brethren, I count not myself to have apprehended
brethren, I count not myself to have apprehended,
but this one thing I do,
forgetting those things which are behind,
and notice, reaching forth unto those things
which are before.
I press, I press toward the mark
for the prize of the high calling of God
in Christ Jesus.
Well, this morning we see this language
that Paul uses as he's writing to the church
in Philippi and he's expressing his own personal desire.
I'm desiring to know Him
and I'm desiring to please Him
and I'm pressing toward the mark
for the prize of the high calling of God
in Christ Jesus,
ultimately so that Christ alone would receive the glory,
but we find that Paul recognized
that this is his desire,
through all that he would do through his life,
that he would please God.
The book of 1 Thessalonians in chapter number four,
Paul, this is where we read of Paul
having this desire for others,
yes, for himself,
but we find in 1 Thessalonians chapter number four,
he's writing to this church in Thessalonica
and notice what he says to them
as he's commending them and encouraging them
and he's instructing them throughout this letter,
but he says in verse number one
of 1 Thessalonians chapter four,
furthermore then we beseech you,
I mean the language of this I beseech you,
this begging, this earnest pleading
with these believers in Thessalonica,
not only does he say we beseech you,
but then he says and exhort you by the Lord Jesus,
notice that as ye have received of us
how ye ought to walk and to please God,
so you would abound more and more.
Paul knew he was gonna stand before God personally,
but Paul knew that every person
that trusted Christ as their savior,
that they too would stand before God personally.
He says in the book of Colossians in the first chapter
that he's warning them,
that he might present them perfect
before the Lord being complete
and here as he's writing to these believers in Thessalonica,
he says that you would walk in a such a way
that you would please God,
so you would abound more and more.
Notice he says for we know, for ye know
what commandments we gave you by the Lord Jesus.
He says in verse three, for this is the will of God,
even your sanctification that you should abstain
from fornication, why?
Well, because fornication would not please God
and it's specifically laid out here in verse number three,
that every one of you in verse number four
should know how to possess his vessel
in sanctification and honor
and he begins to go through and he says in verse number seven
to kind of summarize all that he's saying here,
for God hath not caught us unto uncleanness,
but unto holiness.
Remember what God said in the book of Leviticus
and it's repeated by Peter in first Peter
that be holy, for I am holy.
God is holy and we as his people are to walk in holiness,
that we are not, God has not caught us unto uncleanness,
but unto holiness.
I'm reminded of what the truth of God's word is
with regard to the grace of God,
which bringeth salvation hath appeared to all men,
teaching us that denying ungodliness,
not only that, but worldly lusts,
we should live soberly, righteously and godly
in this present world.
That's today, that's how I'm living my life today
and what a blessing to know that God is concerned
about my behavior and your behavior and we can please God
and we ought to be striving to please God.
In 2 Timothy chapter two, Paul is writing,
we studied this book last year,
1 and 2 Timothy and he's writing in this second chapter
about a good soldier and what does it mean
to be a good soldier of Jesus Christ?
And I preached, I think for five weeks
from 2 Timothy chapter two last year
and we looked at various aspects
of what does it mean to be a good soldier?
I don't wanna just be a soldier, I wanna be a good soldier.
I don't wanna be content with just,
well, it's good enough, it's status quo,
no, I wanna be a good soldier of Jesus Christ.
He says in 2 Timothy one, thou therefore my son endure,
be strong in the grace that is in Christ Jesus
and the things that thou hast heard of me.
Among many witnesses the same,
commit thou to faithful men who shall be able
to teach others also.
Thou therefore endure hardness
as a good soldier of Jesus Christ.
No man that woreth and tangleth himself
with the affairs of this life,
notice that he may please him
who hath chosen him to be a soldier.
One of this morning, where's our desire?
Do we truly have a desire like Paul had,
that I wanna be accepted of him,
that I wanna please my savior?
We find that there are several verses of scripture
that we could look to to understand this word,
accept it again, well pleasing in the sight of God.
Look at a few with me, Romans chapter number 12.
We're familiar with this text of scripture
and we find in Romans chapter 12
as Paul has given all such wonderful truth
throughout the book of Romans
and he comes to this 12th chapter and he says,
therefore I beseech you, therefore,
based on all of that which I've already shared with you,
all of the truth that has been revealed,
I beseech you, therefore, brethren, by the mercies of God.
Notice what he says, that you present your bodies
a living sacrifice, holy.
Notice what it says, acceptable unto God,
which is your reasonable service.
It's your reasonable service.
It is reasonable for God to have the expectation
that we would live our lives for his glory,
that we'd understand that as we have been saved
by the grace of God, we can't earn our salvation,
we can't keep our salvation, but now that I belong to Jesus,
that I would, as the songwriter said, live for Jesus.
Be not conformed to this world,
but be ye transformed by the renewing of your mind
that ye may prove what is that good and acceptable
and perfect will of God.
We see in verse one, and again in verse number two
of Romans chapter 12, that word acceptable.
And Paul said there in 2 Corinthians 5 and verse number nine
that I might be accepted, that we may be accepted of him.
Well-pleasing in his sight.
Ephesians 5 and verse number 10 says it this way,
and it's a great verse of scripture.
In fact, I think it's a verse of scripture
that really should be a verse that is a filter
that we use for our daily activities,
for the things that we do.
We should use Ephesians 5 and verse number 10 as a filter.
Why do I say that?
Well, notice what the Bible says
in Ephesians 5 and verse number 10.
Proving, proving what is acceptable unto who?
What's it say?
The Lord.
Not proving what's acceptable to my neighbor,
to my spouse, to my parent, to my children,
to my church, to my pastor, to my, no, no, no.
Proving what is acceptable unto the Lord.
Why does that matter?
Because that's who you're gonna stand before.
That's who you're gonna stand before.
And so we ought to prove.
What does it mean to prove?
Well, that's work, that's labor.
It's labor.
Many times the word proving was used
within the context of metalworking,
where you would prove a metal,
where you would refine that process
of adding the heat and the fire
to take out all of that which is to be removed
so that you would have the purity of that metal.
And you find that here the Bible says
proving what is acceptable unto the Lord.
It's a simple verse of scripture.
I believe that every one of us here this morning
could memorize this week this verse.
Proving what is acceptable unto the Lord.
It's not a hard verse.
But oh, implementing the truth of this verse
into our lives is so much more challenging
than simply memorizing the verse.
But could I tell you this morning,
it's worth it to implement the truth.
Proving, how do I prove?
When I look at this truth this morning
in Ephesians five and verse 10,
how do I prove what is acceptable unto the Lord?
You know what it means?
It means we gotta dig into God's word.
We gotta dig in and find how.
Is this activity, this behavior,
this whatever I'm looking at doing,
is this acceptable unto the Lord?
Is he going to be pleased with it?
So important.
And can I tell you this morning,
that if you honestly.
search the Scriptures, and you're not just trying to twist the Scriptures, but
if you honestly search the Scriptures, I believe that God and His Spirit will
reveal to us what is acceptable to Him. And we can prove what is acceptable unto
the Lord. It takes work. It takes diligence. And you'll only do it if you have the
desire to be accepted of Him. Notice we find in Philippians chapter 4 and verse
number 18, the Bible says this in Philippians 4 and verse number 18, as
Paul is writing, and really what he's doing in this section of Philippians 4
is he's commending the believers in Philippi for their gift, a financial
gift that they gave to help him, and they gave once and again. And really the
context of Philippians 4 has nothing to do with tithing. It has everything to do
with giving above and beyond tithing, specifically with regard to really what
we would call today missions giving. And we find that here they had given, they
had communicated once and again, they had given of their own resources so that
Paul could fulfill the ministry that God had called him to fulfill, and he says to
them in verse 18, but I have all and abound, I am full, having received of
Epaphroditus the things which were sent from you. That's the offering that I just
alluded to. But notice how he describes it, an odor of a sweet smell, a sacrifice
acceptable, well-pleasing to God. You know what Paul's saying to these believers in
Philippi? What you did there in following the will of God, following God's
leadership in your life, and you communicating with me and enabling the
ministry to go forward, enabling the gospel to be spread forth, that that
sacrifice was acceptable and well-pleasing to God. I want my life to
be acceptable and well-pleasing to God. I want God to be pleased with those
things that we do, that we say, I want it for myself personally, I want it for our
church corporately, that God would be pleased with us. We find in Hebrews, you
don't need to turn there, but Hebrews 13 and verse number 21, the Bible says, I'll
read verse 20, now the God of peace that brought again from the dead our Lord
Jesus, that great Shepherd of the sheep, through the blood of the everlasting
covenant, make you perfect in every good work to do His will, working in you that
which is well-pleasing in His sight, through Jesus Christ, to whom be glory
forever and ever. Amen. I like that little phrase in verse 21 that says
well-pleasing in His sight. You know the amazing thing? The Bible says in verse 21
that He is working in us, that it says this, working in you that which is
well-pleasing in His sight. But you know what you have to do? You have to let Him
work in you. You have to let Him work in you. He desires to work in you, He desires
to work through you, He wants to work in you that which is well-pleasing, and He's
ready and He's able, but we have a will, and we have to allow Him. So often we
look at the life of the Apostle Paul and we may be tempted to put Paul on some
type of pedestal, if you will, and we may look at Paul at some level of this great
Christian, and oh, that we might be used of God like Paul was, but you know
why God used Paul? Because Paul surrendered. Because Paul made himself
available. Because Paul had that desire that he would be accepted of Him, and
Paul made himself available. He said, I am crucified with Christ, nevertheless I
live, yet not I, but Christ liveth in me. In the life that I now live in the flesh,
I live by the faith of the Son of God who loved me and gave Himself for me. And
just a few verses in 2 Corinthians chapter 5 and verse number 15, a verse
that's really my favorite Bible verse, and that He died for all that they which
live should not henceforth live unto themselves, but unto Him which died for
them and rose again. Paul was used of the Lord because Paul was surrendered to the
Lord. Paul desired to be that vessel that was meat for the Master's work. This
morning we see this desire in 2 Corinthians 5, in the end of verse
number 9, we may be accepted of Him daily as we live our lives. Do we have that
desire? Do we think through the daily things that we do, do we examine them
through that filter of Ephesians 5 and verse number 10, will this please my
Savior? Will this please my Savior? The desire of Paul, number two this morning,
the dedication of Paul. His desire to please the Lord resulted in his
dedication. Can I tell you, most times in life when we think about people that have
a desire for something, if they truly have a desire to achieve something, to
accomplish something, to attain something, they are dedicated to whatever
that thing is. If it's a true, deep-rooted desire that they have, then there's some
dedication that is going to be evident in their life. You find somebody that
says, well I want to do this, and they share with you the desire, but you see
absolutely no evidence that would have any, give any kind of thought to your
mind that they truly desire that. You say, I'm not really sure you desire that, but
Paul is dedicated. Notice what he says here in verse number nine as we look at
this verse of Scripture. He says, wherefore, notice these words, we labor. We
labor. That whether present or absent, notice we may be accepted of Him. Why
does he use this word labor? We mentioned earlier in Ephesians 5 and verse number
10, proving what is acceptable in the Lord, the work that's required in that proving
process. And here in 2 Corinthians 5 and verse number 9, he says we labor. Paul, I
believe, regularly examined his life. I believe that Paul, as he writes to the
church in 1 Corinthians and chapter number 11 about examining ourselves with
regard to the Lord's Supper, I think that regularly in Paul's life he examined
himself. He desired to know on a regular basis was he living in such a way that
was pleasing to God. Turn over here to the book of Acts, in Acts chapter 24, and I want you to see what Paul says here in Acts chapter 24, and in this text of
Scripture, he is giving his defense before Felix. We find that Paul, in this
section of the book of Acts, he's had the opportunity to stand and to share his
testimony and stood before the religious leaders of the community there, the Sanhedrin, if you will. We find that many of those religious leaders were there, and then he's going to be before Felix. We find that he will have
opportunity to stand before Festus and Agrippa as well in the next several
chapters, and so Paul is having this unique opportunity in this section of the
book of Acts to be able to share what Christ did for him with these people. We
find that in Acts 24, as Paul is going through the process here of giving his
defense, if you will, before Felix, notice, if you will, in verse number 13,
neither can they prove the things whereof they now accuse me. Paul had been
accused of some things, and in verse 8 it talks about how they accused him, and he
says, in verse 10, I do the more cheerfully answer for myself, and he says
they can't prove those things, but then notice what he says. He begins in verse
14, he gives this, he says, I confess. He gives this testimony, if you will, unto
Felix and those that would be there, and he says, but this I
confess unto thee, that after the way which they call heresy, so worship I the
God of my fathers. Notice what he says at the end of verse number 14. Believing,
what's it say? All things. Not some things, not most things, not the things that I
like or the things that I can kind of fit in, but he says, believing all things
which are written in the law and in the prophets. Now what does that refer to?
That refers to the Old Testament, the law and the prophets, and so we could talk
about Bible preservation right here from this verse of Scripture, and how Paul
believed that God's Word had been preserved, and he says, I believe all of
it. He wasn't coming with a textual critic mindset of let's criticize and
let's try to critique and change and so on and so forth. No, he says, I believe
all things which are written in the law and in the prophets and have hope toward
God. That word hope is an interesting word. It's so unlike the word that is
used in our vernacular today. People talk about hope today with all sorts of
ideas of really the best way I could describe the most common usage that I
hear is kind of a wishful thinking idea. I hope this is gonna happen. No, no, that's
not, when you see the word hope in the Bible, that is not the definition. It is a
confident expectation. It is having this confidence, he says, and have hope toward
God, which they themselves also allow that there shall be a resurrection of
the dead.
Both of the just and unjust and why is he saying this? Why is he talking about this resurrection?
Well, because this motivates his living
This is what plays into that desire which leads to that
dedication that Paul has and we come to verse number 16 and notice what he says and
Herein
Do I exercise?
myself
You know what that word exercise means it means to labor
It means to just drive
What did we see over in 2nd Corinthians 5 and verse number 9? He says wherefore
Wherefore we labor
Right. So we find here. He says that I I
Exercise myself. What is he exercising himself for in Acts 24 in verse 16?
What is he laboring and striving for in this verse of Scripture notice to have always?
to have always
a
conscience void of
offense
toward God and
Toward men. I want you to think about this just for a moment
Paul says I'm exercising myself. I'm laboring. I'm striving
For what purpose Paul? Why are you exercising Paul? What is this this this effort that is going forth?
Why are you dedicated to this because I want to have
Always
not most times but always a
Conscience that is void of offense
Toward God
We sing the song nothing between my soul and my Savior
Paul
Communicates to Felix. Why why is he doing the things that he's doing?
Why is he being accused of what he's being accused of?
why did Paul go and preach in all of these places and and give the gospel and and tell people that
Jesus is the only way why did Paul do all of this?
Well, he desired to live his life in such a way that he would please his Savior
He desired he exercised himself to have always listen if he's going to have always a conscience
That's void of offense toward God. This exercise was regular
He didn't let things just kind of build up and just kind of well
We'll do this once a month once every whatever. No, this was a regular occurrence in his life. I
Want to have nothing between my soul and my Savior, but then notice he ends with these words and
toward men and
toward men
Someone has said if you're not right with your neighbor, you're not right with God
If you're not right with one another you're not right with God
There's some people that have this idea I'm right with God
I'm concerned about my relationship with God, but I really don't care about any other relationship
Paul says I desire I exercise myself to have a conscience. That's void of offense. That's always
void of offense toward God and
toward men
Paul desired
To live his life in such a way that God would be pleased with him
That that he would not bring a reproach against the name of the Savior
we find that earlier if you turn back just a
Book or a chapter or so in your Bibles there in chapter 23
Maybe it's on the same page for you
But in verse 1 of chapter 23 notice the Bible says this and Paul
Earnestly beholding the council said men and brethren. I have lived in all good conscience before God
until this day
How could Paul make that statement
Well, because then he later reveals to us. Listen, he didn't start exercising himself when he stood before Felix
He had already been exercising himself to have always a conscience
That's void of offense toward God and toward men
And so when he stood before these religious leaders in Acts chapter 23
He says I have lived in all good conscience before God until this day
Now I want you to think about the context of 2nd Corinthians and we talked about this several weeks ago as we've been studying through
This chat or through this book and we found that in chapter number one. I preached a message when you're misunderstood
When you're misunderstood and I said this when I preached that message. There's been a time in your life
I guarantee there's been a time in your life that you have been misunderstood
There's been a time in your life where you misunderstood someone else we can all relate to this
And as we look at that passage of Scripture at the end of 2nd Corinthians chapter number one, we noticed how Paul
Approached that situation of being misunderstood. What was the misunderstanding?
Well, they were accusing Paul that hey, you said you were gonna come visit us and you didn't and so therefore you're not trustworthy
and you're kind of your yay means nay and your name means yay and Paul just he's
He's double-minded and so on and so forth. And that was not true
But I said this when I preached that message that before Paul ever tried to explain himself. He first examined himself
And how that be a good rule for us
To examine ourselves before we ever try to explain ourselves. And what does he say?
Well in verse number 12 of 2nd Corinthians 1 he says for our rejoicing is this the testimony of our conscience that in simplicity and godly
Sincerity not with fleshly wisdom, but by the grace of God
We have had our conversation in the world and more abundantly to you word
You know what Paul was saying in that verse of Scripture
He was saying that he had examined himself and that before the Lord he was right
He was right before the Lord. There was nothing that he had done. That was offensive. That was inappropriate. That was sin
That was not pleasing to his God. And so he went through that process. And so why do I bring that up?
Well, because he says that in verse 9 of our text this morning in 2nd Corinthians chapter 5 we therefore we labor
We labor this was something that was ongoing. This was something that was regular. This was a regular occurrence
This was something that Paul was dedicated to whether absent or present or absent. We may be accepted of him
Can I tell you this morning? There's not one of us that knows when we're gonna leave this earth
None of us know
The rapture could happen at any moment
But death could happen in any moment
David said this as he's being sought by Saul
There's but a step between me and death and as I've often thought about that passage of Scripture
The reality in David's life is that yes Saul was hunting him
I mean Saul had made David his enemy continually and he had his
Choices men and he was seeking after and he sought to kill David and yes
There was but a step between him and death, but you know for each of us. There's about a step between us and death. I
Shared some with some of the folks that were here for visitation yesterday morning
we're driving home late on Friday evening and we're driving home and
We're on 95 and we come around this corner and you could see not much more than maybe a quarter mile ahead of us
It was coming in the opposite direction
But you could see a car that was on fire that I'm telling you the flames had to be 15 20 feet out of that car
Just an inferno
There was no accident. I have no idea what happened. We're going on our way
So you can't really you know, you're not stopping and checking it out
But the reality is that that thing was just up in flames, but there was no accident
It's not like there was a crash that reason I have no idea what happened
but what I know is or what I
assume is
That that person didn't get in their car that evening to travel down 95 south and think that their car was gonna catch on fire
In that manner. I don't think they thought that was gonna happen
How many people we read? I mean look think about recent things that have been in our backyard a
Plane going to land at Reagan National. How many of you have flown into Reagan National before?
How many of you been on an airplane before
How many of you bought a ticket after you or you said maybe I'm not gonna buy a ticket right
135 or whatever the number was people in that plane
if you've flown into Reagan before and I have many times
When you're flying into Reagan, what do I do? I see the Potomac
We're getting close
Am I am I telling the truth if you've landed in Reagan you're flying in there. You can see it. You know, the approach is there. I
Can't even hardly imagine that
But that's how frail our lives are
That's the frailty of life
And
So why does Paul say I'm laboring? Why does he say I'm striving?
Why does he say that that I'm exercising myself because in any moment you can meet the Lord
And
Is your life well pleasing?
to God is
my life
well pleasing
to God
Speaking with regard to the the rapture and again
We know that that could happen at any time if you read the book of 1st
John and you end the second chapter and you enter into the third chapter and in those few verses of Scripture
It's very clear that he's speaking about the the Lord Jesus Christ coming back and he says at the end of chapter number two
That we would not be ashamed of him at his appearing
But the reality is that you don't know when he's going
going to appear, because it says, in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye.
Is that not what the Bible says?
As a thief in the night, listen, the reality is that Jesus is not going to send you a two-minute
warning, a two-week warning.
He's not going to say, hey, listen, get your life straightened up because I'm coming back
next Tuesday.
No, no, in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye.
Is that not what the Bible teaches?
So why is Paul so concerned about this thing?
Why is Paul living his life in the manner in which he is, this desire of being accepted
of him has just led to a dedication in his life that I'm laboring, I'm striving, I'm
exercising.
Why?
Because I want God to be pleased with my life.
And this morning, every believer in Corinth and every believer throughout the church age
that has read this portion of Scripture should have the same desire, should have the same
desire, I want to please my Savior.
How often do we examine our lives to truly determine if God is pleased?
My thoughts.
God knows your thoughts.
You can hide your thoughts for a period of time.
You can hide your thoughts from other people.
Why do I say for a period of time?
Because your thoughts eventually are going to become your actions.
But for a period of time, your thoughts can be hidden from other people, but God knows
them.
God knows what you're thinking.
Do you remember when Jesus stood there and as He's ministering and those people are reasoning
amongst themselves and He says, why do you think this in your heart?
Can you imagine how they must have thought at that moment?
How do you know what I'm thinking?
You ever look at your spouse and you kind of can just see and you say, I know what you're
thinking.
You might be wrong when you say, I know what you're thinking.
But God knows exactly what we're thinking.
We think about my thoughts being pleasing to God, my words being pleasing to God.
My actions.
Thoughts lead to words, lead to actions.
In this age in which we live, I wonder this morning if my electronic communication is
pleasing to God.
The text that I send, the emails that I send, the whatever social media posts.
Listen, sometimes people just throw stuff out there and they think that it doesn't really
matter.
Listen, is it pleasing to God?
Is God pleased with it?
My online activity.
No one's ever going to know.
Can I give you a newsflash?
So many people know.
They can get your device, they can track your IP, they know what you're doing.
You think you're hiding something.
It's like Rachel when she hid those images in the tent.
You know who didn't know?
Jacob.
You know why I think he didn't know?
Because he said to Laban, whoever you find them with, let them die.
Do you think he would have said that if heno.
But God knew what was in the tent because years later Moses wrote about it.
God knew.
I've hidden this, I'veno, no.
God knows.
And the question this morning, is it well-pleasing to God?
Not is it well-pleasing to my parents and I'm sure that if it were your parents they
wouldn't be well-pleased.
Not is it well-pleasing to my spouse, I'm sure if they knew they wouldn't be pleased.
I'm saying God knows.
And is it well-pleasing to God?
The places that I go, the entertainment that I choose, thelisten, the list could go
on and on and on this morning.
Proving what is acceptable unto the Lord.
Paul says, wherefore we labor.
Paul knew he was going to heaven.
There's no doubt about that whatsoever.
Paul knew that as he's writing to these believers in Corinth that they too had trusted Christ
as their Savior because he speaks in the plural sense.
We know, we have this confidence.
It's not a matter of whether I'm going to go to heaven.
It's not a matter of whether I'm going to lose my salvation.
You can't.
You're secure in the hand of God.
We talked about this very truth even from the text last Sunday morning that he's given
to us the earnest of the Spirit in verse number 5.
I have an inheritance.
I'm secure in the hand of God.
But he says, wherefore we labor that whether present or absent we may be accepted of him.
And I hope this morning that from a single verse of Scripture that we can have that same
level of desire that Paul communicates.
I want to be accepted of him.
I want to be well-pleasing in his sight.
How can I please him?
He's given us a Bible and he's told us how we can please him.
Have you ever felt like I don't know how to please somebody?
Maybe it's a boss.
Yeah, you've been there.
I don't know.
There's nothing I can do to please him.
God tells us exactly what we can do to please him.
And he also tells us the things that do not please him.
And so Paul says that I want to be accepted of him and therefore I'm dedicated to this.
I am laboring.
I am exercising.
I am striving.
This morning, are you striving to please your Savior?
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for your Word.
We thank you for this truth in the testimony of the Apostle Paul.
God, I pray that you would help us this morning to have the same desire and the same level
of commitment, dedication, that we would labor, that we would strive, that we'd exercise,
that we might be accepted, well-pleasing in your sight.
Thank you for saving us.
Lord, we know that one day we'll see you face-to-face.
And as we'll examine next week, we'll stand before you to give an account at that judgment
seat of Christ.
God, it's our heart's desire this morning, my heart's desire this morning to be pleasing
in your sight.
Help us to live every day for your glory.
I pray that in these moments of invitation that you'd have your will in way, that we
would be responsive, that we'd be doers of your Word.
Well thank you for every decision that's made, for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's gonna play quietly on the piano.
And as she does, the altar is open.