chapter number nine as we continue our series on Sunday evenings through the book of Genesis.
And last week, as you'll recall, we were in the first seven verses of Genesis 9.
Tonight we'll be in verses 8 through 17, Genesis 9, verses 8 through 17.
And let me just bring you up to speed with those events that have transpired in leading
up to the text of Scripture that we'll study this evening.
Of course, at the end of chapter number 8, the Bible gives us the information that Noah
and his family, they departed the ark, the animals, they came off of the ark, and God
had given them the direction to do so, and God gave them that direction and they obeyed.
We find the first matter of business after leaving the ark was that Noah built an altar
and he made offerings unto the Lord.
The Bible tells us in verse number 20 of Genesis 8 that he offered burnt offerings
on the altar.
We understand that God was pleased with these offerings, for it tells us in verse number
21 that the Lord smelled a sweet savor, and notice what the Bible says, and the Lord said
in his heart.
And what God said in his heart in verses 21 and 22, as it's recorded there at the end
of Genesis chapter number 8, will really be further expounded on in the text of Scripture
that we're studying this evening in verses 8 through 17.
We find that the Bible says that what God said, the Lord said in his heart, I will not
again curse the ground anymore for man's sake, for the imagination of man's heart is evil
from his youth, neither will I against my anymore everything living as I have done.
While the earth remaineth, seed time and harvest and cold and heat and summer and winter and
day and night shall not cease.
As we studied last week on Sunday evening, the first seven verses, God begins to provide
Noah and his family with direction, instruction, if you will, for life after the flood.
As they come off the ark and they make those offerings, those sacrifices unto the Lord,
we find that the Lord speaks to them, God blessed Noah and his sons and said unto them,
beginning in verse number 1 of chapter number 9, and gave them instruction with regard to
living life after the flood.
I'm thankful, as I've mentioned last week, that God has given us instruction in his word
and he's given us direction for how to live our lives.
It was important for Noah and his family to understand how they were to live that behavior
which would please the Lord.
I'm often reminded of the great truth of Ephesians 5 in verse number 10, where Paul says to the
believers of Ephesus that we're to prove what is acceptable in the sight of the Lord.
That's a process of studying the word of God and digging into God's word, examining
the instruction that God has given us within his word to determine that which is well-pleasing,
that which is acceptable in the sight of the Lord.
I'm thankful that God has been faithful to give us instruction, to give us direction.
Can you imagine if we had no Bible?
It's a hard thought for us to even comprehend.
Many that are within our congregation, and we think about, of course, even my children
and young people that have been here for years, just how they've always had a Bible.
They never were in a place where maybe they didn't have a Bible, they didn't have instruction,
they didn't have the direction that God's given us in his word, but I'm so thankful
that we've been blessed, that we have the Bible, we have the instruction, that God has
been faithful to give us his word.
I know I've mentioned in the past in various settings that it's not as if God is sitting
back and allowing us to live life and saying, nope, that's not going to work, that's not
going to cut it, that doesn't please me, no, try again.
We just were aimlessly, helplessly, hopelessly trying in vain to find out what might please
God.
No, he's given us his word, and he tells us, these are the things that please me.
You find that on many occasions, we find that the Bible tells us, even as we look at 1 Corinthians
chapter 10, and use the example that Paul would give to the believers of the church
in Corinth, he says, with many of them, God was not well pleased.
Okay, we'll take note of that.
That behavior that is mentioned did not please God, and therefore, I ought not behave in
like manner.
We find that God gave instruction to Noah and to his family, and what a blessing that
is.
We come to verse number 8, and this evening we'll look at verses 8 through 17, and if
you're taking notes, this is actually lesson number 31 through the book of Genesis, believe
it or not.
Lesson number 31, the Noahic Covenant, the Noahic Covenant, and often we talk about the
Abrahamic Covenant, and the Davidic Covenant, and those things, and this is the Noahic Covenant,
and really it's captured for us in verses 8 through 17.
We'll read the text of Scripture, and then get into the lesson this evening.
The Bible says this in verse number 8 of Genesis 9, and God spake unto Noah and to his sons
with him, saying,
And I, behold, I establish My covenant with you, and with your seed after you, and with
every living creature that is with you, of the fowl, of the cattle, and of every beast
of the earth with you, from all that go out of the ark to every beast of the earth.
And I will establish My covenant with you, neither shall all flesh be cut off any more
by the waters of a flood.
Neither shall there any more be a flood to destroy the earth.
And God said, This is the token of the covenant which I make between Me and you, and every
living creature that is with you, for perpetual generations.
I do set My bow in the cloud, and it shall be for a token of a covenant between Me and
the earth.
And it shall come to pass when I bring a cloud over the earth, that the bow shall be seen
in the cloud.
And I will remember My covenant, which is between Me and you, and every living creature
of all flesh.
And the waters shall no more become a flood to destroy all flesh.
And the bow shall be in the cloud, and I will look upon it, that I may remember the everlasting
covenant between God and every living creature of all flesh that is upon the earth.
And God said unto Noah, This is the token of the covenant which I have established between
Me and all flesh that is upon the earth.
And we speak about the rainbow.
What a joy, as you would think about the beauty after a storm, and maybe those storm clouds
are moving out, and you see a beautiful rainbow.
There are times in which the sight is so spectacular that you want to capture it on camera, and
just be able to have that image reminding you of the beauty of that rainbow.
Not long ago, there was just a terrible storm that had come through our neighborhood, and
Joseph and I, just shortly after, were walking through the neighborhood, and we saw a double
rainbow, and it was just so vivid and so beautiful, and we took some pictures, and it was just
beautiful.
But when we think about the rainbow, we ought to be reminded of the Noahic covenant and
understanding that this is the token that God gave to Noah and to his sons with regard
to this covenant that we'll study this evening.
We'll get into that token in just a little while, but it is interesting that we find
that God gave that sign to Noah.
As we look at the text of Scripture and we deal with this subject, I want you to see
the details of the covenant.
Notice the details of the covenant.
It's interesting to me that it is God that initiated this covenant.
It is God that is the initiator, and He is the one that gives the terms of the covenant.
You notice in verse number 8 that the Bible says that God spake unto Noah, and He says
in verse number 9, and I, behold, I establish my covenant with you and with your seed after
you.
Remember, as we mentioned at the end of verse number 8, after Noah built that altar and
he offered those burnt offerings on the altar, that God smelled that sweet savor and the
Lord said in his heart, and we looked at those verses already, but now God is speaking to
Noah and to his sons, and He's providing Noah and his sons with the details of this covenant.
He is the initiator.
He is the one that will give the terms of the covenant.
We know the details as they're given to us there in verse number 9, that He says that
it's a covenant that He establishes, notice what He says, with you and with your seed
after you.
We'll look at the impact of some of these statements here in just a few moments, but
we notice that God is providing the details with regard to this covenant, the Noahic covenant
that He's making in this portion of Scripture.
It's interesting that God's speaking to Noah and to his sons, and He says to you and then
with your seed after you, but notice what He says in verse number 10.
Again, He will make this reference throughout the portion of Scripture, but we find that
He says here that He, with every living creature that is with you, of the fowl, of the cattle,
of every beast of the earth with you, from all that go out of the ark to every beast
of the earth, and we find that this covenant, we understand that God is the creator, that
He's created all of the plant life, animal life, and of course, all of the animals.
of course, human beings.
He is the Lord God Omnipotent.
He is the Creator of the universe.
And He's making this covenant.
You'll recall with me
the death that was the result of the flood.
And not only did every living creature,
speaking of man, that died,
but all of those that were not on the ark,
they died.
We see today, even as we've studied
throughout the portions of Scripture
in Genesis 6, 7, and 8,
as we think about the fossil records
and we see so much of the evidence
of the flood of Noah's day
through the fossil record
and all that is given.
And so God is establishing this covenant
with His creation.
Of course, with mankind being
the crown of His creation, if you will.
And we mentioned that as we studied
Genesis chapter number one.
And we find that He's giving this instruction.
And notice what He says
when He provides the details.
As we look in verse number 11,
He says, I will establish my covenant with you.
Again, we notice throughout this covenant
that this is a covenant that God is making.
He's the initiator.
He's the one making the details,
giving the details.
This is not a covenant
that is conditional or dependent
on anything that Noah
or any of His descendants will do.
This is a promise, a covenant,
that God is making
to His creation.
Of course, Noah being the direct recipient
in His children, His adult sons,
as they came off of the ark.
He says this,
neither shall all flesh be cut off any more
by the waters of a flood.
Neither shall there any more
be a flood to destroy the earth.
Now, as we'd see the details of this
and we'd notice here in verse number 11,
the Bible tells us
that He will not destroy the earth.
He says that all flesh
should not be cut off any more
by the waters of a flood.
He will not destroy the earth by a flood.
And we'd understand the detail here
that is given,
but also we'd understand
by looking at this detail
that there was a global flood.
Why would God have to promise Noah
and generations to come
that He would never destroy the earth again
with a global flood
if there were not a global flood?
You remember as we studied
Genesis 6, 7, and 8
and we dealt with the subject
of the global flood
and we dealt with that passage of Scripture
and we spoke about the truth
and there are those
that of course will be the scoffers
that will say,
no, it was just a regional flood.
It was not a global flood.
No, we understand the earth was destroyed.
It was a global flood
and therefore we find that in the details
of the Noahic covenant,
it gives evidence to the fact
that it was a global flood.
Notice what he says,
neither shall there anymore be a flood
to destroy the earth.
Even in our lives, in our lifetime,
we have seen local floods.
We have read about the catastrophes
that have been suffered by many
that have experienced these localized floods.
In fact, while my in-laws
were missionaries in Thailand,
they suffered a terrible flood in Thailand.
I don't remember the exact year
that they were there
when they had that flood,
but I remember seeing pictures
and we as a family being deeply concerned
for their welfare and their well-being
and where would they be able to go?
Where would they find refuge and safety
and would they be able to get out of the city
and all of those things?
And it was a destructive flood,
but it was a local flood.
And if it was only a local flood,
then this covenant that is made here
would be null and void
because there have been local floods
for generations.
But there's never been another global flood.
There's only been one global flood.
There only will ever be one global flood.
And that was the flood of Noah's day.
That's when God said,
as we read and studied in Genesis 6,
when He saw the wickedness of mankind
and all that was going on,
the violence that filled the earth,
He said to Noah in v. 13 of Genesis 6,
the end of all flesh has come before Me,
for the earth is filled with violence through them,
and behold, I will destroy them
with the earth.
And He did.
Then He makes a covenant.
When we think about the details of the covenant,
we see that God is the initiator.
He's the one that gives the terms
that it's to Noah and to future generations.
It's a covenant that is not conditional.
It is a covenant that is unconditional.
It's not based upon the actions of Noah
or his descendants.
This is God saying,
I am establishing this covenant with you
and with future generations.
And He tells them that not only would it be for them,
of course, all of His creation is included.
And we look in v. 10,
and then He says that there would never be a flood
that would destroy the entire earth.
What a great promise.
We think about the details of this covenant.
Yes, it's mindful the destruction of the flood.
And think about Noah.
See, God didn't have to convince Noah
that there was a global flood.
Noah had spent all that time in the ark.
He knew there was a global flood, right?
And he was well aware of the destruction.
He was well aware of that which happened.
He had just stepped off the ark
there at the end of chapter number eight,
and he, of course, was there at life right after the flood.
He saw what was going on before the flood.
He then, of course, had safety refuge in the ark.
And then he comes off of the ark,
and God tells him this truth with regard to this covenant.
He did not need to be convinced of a global flood.
But for some reason in our society today,
there are many that seek to undermine
the authority of the word of God.
And they seek to, of course,
as they would attack the first 11 chapters
of the book of Genesis and destroy the foundation,
if you will, they're seeking to cause people
to have doubt in what God has said.
There was a global flood, but God's made a promise
that there would never be such a flood again.
Notice, as we would continue to look
through the text of Scripture
and consider the details of the covenant,
that there's a sign that is given.
I mentioned it by way of introduction.
The token of the covenant there was a rainbow.
Notice in verse number 12,
and God said, this is the token of the covenant
which I make between me and you
and every living creature that is with you
for perpetual generations.
He says, this is what it is.
I do set my bow in the cloud,
and it shall be for a token of a covenant
between me and the earth.
This is very interesting to me.
I had not really thought of it in this manner
until I began preparation.
Of course, I've studied through
and I've read through Genesis countless times,
but I never really considered this thought
as we look here at the token, the bow.
He says in verse number 14,
it shall come to pass when I bring a cloud over the earth
that the bow shall be in the cloud.
Notice what he says, and I will remember my covenant,
which is between me and you
and every living creature of all flesh.
But notice what it says as we look in verse number 16,
and the bow shall be in the cloud.
Notice this, and I will look upon it.
So often I think about me looking at the rainbow.
So often I think about me being here on earth
and you being here on earth,
and we endure a storm and we see the rainbow
as God's people and having a level of understanding
of Genesis 9 and the Noahic covenant.
And we say, that's the token,
that's the sign that God did destroy the earth
once with a flood, but He will not do it again.
But the Bible tells us that God looks upon it.
And when He looks upon it, it says that I may remember.
It's not that God would forget, God is omniscient, right?
But it's that God remembers the everlasting covenant
between God and every living creature of all flesh
that is upon the earth.
Isn't that precious?
To think from our vantage point,
we look and we see the rainbow and we are reminded
and we're encouraged by the truth
of what that would communicate to us
with regard to the Noahic covenant,
but God from heaven, He looks down and He sees the rainbow.
And He remembers the covenant that was made with Noah
here in Genesis chapter number nine.
The details are given to us in this portion of Scripture.
And I want you to consider
not only the details of the covenant,
but I want you to consider number two,
the duration of the covenant.
The duration of the covenant.
Notice in verse number nine,
and we've mentioned these things already,
but at the end of verse,
or we've read them as we've read the passage,
but notice at the end of verse number nine,
and with your seed after you.
We find again in verse number 11,
that it says that neither shall there any more
be a flood to destroy the earth.
That would give, those terms would reveal
that it would never again happen.
We find at the end of verse number 12,
it says that this covenant that He made
between me and you and every living creature
that is with you.
Notice the phrase, for perpetual generations.
We find that He says to them in verse number 16,
He says, and the bow shall be in the cloud
and I will look upon it.
that I may remember," what does he say?
The everlasting covenant
between God and every living creature
of all flesh that is upon the earth.
God said unto Noah,
this is the token of the covenant
which I have established between me
and all flesh that is upon the earth.
We see the details of the covenant,
but we are mindful of the duration of the covenant.
That this is an everlasting covenant
as God calls it in v. 16.
That it's for perpetual generations.
That we still today in 2020,
many thousands of years after the global flood
of Noah's day, after the terms
of the Noahic covenant were initially given,
we still today can find hope
in the truth of the Noahic covenant.
When we see that rainbow,
we can be mindful of what our God has said.
When we think about this covenant,
we think about the details and the duration,
and we must be mindful of the fact
that it's the God that made the covenant
that is of significant importance.
I'm thankful that we serve a God who is eternal.
How could He make an everlasting covenant
if He Himself were not eternal?
Amen?
We think about the fact that He has all power,
that He controls all things.
He is in control of His creation.
We find that our God rules over all,
that by Him all things consist,
and He holds the power of the universe in His hands.
Remember, we looked this morning at Matthew 28,
in verse 18, all power is given unto me
in heaven and in earth.
And I'm mindful as I think about the details
of the covenant and the duration of the covenant,
and we study that which God gives us here
in Genesis chapter nine, what Noah received,
but how we rejoice in understanding
the God of the covenant,
the God that was able to make this covenant,
to give these details,
to establish the duration being eternal or everlasting,
and we find that this God is our God.
And that's encouraging.
I'm mindful of Psalm 48,
where the Bible speaks about the greatness of God.
In fact, we often sing as a Bible psalm,
the Psalm 48 verses one and two,
a Bible song, great is the Lord
and greatly to be praised.
And we know that song, verses one and two of Psalm 48,
and you skip down to the end of the psalm,
I believe it's in verse number 10,
it says that this God is our God forever.
And what a joy to know the God of the universe,
to know that the God that made this covenant with Noah
is our God.
It's interesting that this truth is mentioned in Isaiah 54,
turn over if you will,
and we'll close with this passage of scripture
and we'll get to our video,
our update video from the Davastus family.
But in Isaiah chapter 54,
it's interesting reference that is given here
with regard to Noah and the Noahic covenant.
And it's interesting for this purpose,
I've often said that throughout the word of God,
there are many that would attack
the first 11 chapters of the book of Genesis.
There are many, of course,
that would attack creation and all of those things.
But we've made the case throughout our study
of the book of Genesis,
that the truth that is given in the book of Genesis
is not only found in the book of Genesis.
The truth is found throughout the word of God.
We find that Jesus, in fact,
mentioned back to the days of Noah,
and he speaks about that which was happening
and dealing with the second coming of Christ.
And we find that Peter spoke about
the ignorance of the people,
that they were willingly ignorant
of the fact that the earth that once was
was destroyed by the waters.
We find here in Isaiah 54 in verse number nine,
it says, for this is as the waters of Noah unto me,
for as I have sworn that the waters of Noah
should no more go over the earth,
so have I sworn that I would not be wroth with thee
nor rebuke thee.
And it's just an interesting reference
to Noah and to the waters of Noah
and dealing back with that which we find
in Genesis chapter nine with the Noahic covenant.
See, God said that he would never destroy the earth again
with a flood, with waters.
But we do find that in 2 Peter chapter number three,
the reference that I made just a moment ago
of those that were willingly ignorant
of the fact that the earth was destroyed
was overflowed with water and perished.
We see that in 2 Peter chapter three, verses five and six.
But we find this truth with regard to the day of the Lord.
In verse number 10, it says,
but the day of the Lord will come as a thief in the night
in which the heavens shall pass away with a great noise
and the elements shall melt with fervent heat.
The earth also and the works that are therein
shall be burned up,
seeing then that all these things shall be dissolved,
what manner of persons ought ye to be
in all holy conversation and godliness,
looking for and hasting under the coming of the day of God,
wherein the heavens being on fire shall be dissolved
and the elements shall melt with fervent heat.
Nevertheless, we, according to his promise,
look for new heavens and a new earth
wherein dwelleth righteousness.
And we find that rate prior to the passage
that I just read in verses 10 through 13,
we read that verse about the promise of God.
Jesus is coming again.
We believe that he's coming soon.
And we believe that as we look at even the things
that are taking place in our society today,
that they're giving us that confidence and that hope
that Jesus is coming again and he's coming soon.
The Bible says,
the Lord is not slack concerning his promise
as some men count slackness.
But his long suffering to us,
we're not willing that any should perish,
but that all should come to repentance.
No, the earth will not be destroyed
by a flood of waters ever again,
based upon the truth of the Noahic covenant.
The details are given in Genesis 9.
The duration is revealed to us
that it will be with you in your seat after you,
that it will never happen again,
that it's for perpetual generations.
It's an everlasting covenant.
But the earth will one day be dissolved with a fervent heat,
according to what we see in 2 Peter 3,
verses 10 through 13.
We understand that to be the case.
Jesus is coming again.
And when we understand the truth of his second return,
yes, we as God's people are looking for the rapture.
We're looking for the day in which
the trumpet of the Lord shall sound
and the dead in Christ shall be raised.
And then we, which are alive and remain
shall be caught up together with the Lord
to meet him in the clouds.
And so shall we ever be with the Lord.
1 Thessalonians chapter number four.
What a fabulous passage of scripture.
I mean, great truth that is given.
Jesus is coming again.
But that begins, the rapture begins
that seven-year tribulation
after which Jesus will come back
as King of kings and Lord of lords.
He will come as the conquering king.
We find that, of course, the battle of Armageddon
and various things will take place
followed by the millennial reign of Christ.
As we think about the terms of the Noahic covenant
and the encouragement that we receive,
there's a warning for one that might not know
the Lord Jesus Christ as their personal Savior.
Jesus is coming again.
And He has given us the opportunity to hear the Gospel.
For you that perhaps have listened to our services,
you've heard the truth of the Gospel.
The death, the burial, the glorious resurrection
of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.
Neither is there salvation in any other
for there's none other name under heaven
given among men whereby we must be saved.
That name is Jesus.
And the only way to avoid the destruction that will come,
not through a flood, but of course,
we think about the terms of the tribulation
and then followed by the destruction
that we dealt with there in 2 Peter 3,
is to trust the Lord Jesus Christ, your personal Savior.
And I'm so thankful that Jesus saves.
We sing the song, we rejoice in the truth,
Hebrews 7 and verse number 25,
that He is able to save to the uttermost
of all men that come to God.
And what a joy to know that our Lord,
that He offers forgiveness and salvation.
The Noahic covenant, we see the details
and we see the duration.
I'm so thankful that our God, my Savior,
that He is able to provide such a covenant
thousands of years ago.
And still today, when we see the rainbow,
we can be reminded of the promise that God gave to Noah
so many years ago.
And what a great God that we serve.
He always does what He says He will do.
He keeps His word and we can thank God for that.
We'll close with a word of prayer
and then we're gonna watch this update video
from the Damascus family.
We do trust it'll be a blessing to you
to see and hear what God has done
in and through their ministry over the last 18 months or so.
And so let's have a word of prayer
and then we'll get right into the video.
Father, we love you and we thank you for loving us.
Thank you for the opportunity to study
this passage of scripture here in Genesis chapter number nine
and I pray, Father, that you would help us
to be encouraged and strengthened
as we are mindful of the details and the duration
and to rejoice in the fact that you as the initiator,
that you set the terms and, Lord,
that you've given this truth
and how we can be reminded each time
we see a rainbow of this promise
that you gave to Noah on this day.
Lord, I pray that if there's one that's not sure of heaven.
And they would be, Lord, that Your Holy Spirit would just convict them, Lord, convict them
of their sin, convince them of their need for Christ.
I pray, Lord, that they would trust the Lord Jesus Christ before it's eternally too late.
We thank You for the opportunity to participate in world missions.
We thank You for the Damascus family there in Scotland and for the work that You're doing
in and through their ministry.
And I pray that as we watch this video that You would help us to be encouraged and strengthen
that You would help us to have a renewed vision and passion for Thee and to pray more specifically
for the ministry there in Scotland.
We pray that You'd bless and we'll thank You for it.
In Christ's name we pray, amen.