4, I got a lot of material this evening.
I'm hoping that we can get through it.
I will not be here next Sunday,
and so I'm hoping to get through all of this in one message.
So I will not talk any faster than I normally do,
at least I don't think so,
but you gotta listen fast and intently,
and we'll get through the text this evening
and all that God has for us.
In Revelation 4, we started here two weeks ago,
and we learned that we're entering part three
of the book of Revelation,
and the things which shall be hereafter
or must be hereafter.
And notice with me in Revelation 4 in verse number one,
the Bible says, after this, I looked
and behold, a door was opened in heaven.
The first voice which I heard was as it were
of a trumpet talking with me, which said,
come up hither and I will show thee things
which must be hereafter.
And immediately, I was in the spirit
and behold, a throne was set in heaven
and one sat on the throne.
We understand that John is caught up
into the throne room of heaven here
in Revelation chapter four.
According to Revelation one in verse number nine,
up until this point, John was exiled
on the island of Patmos,
and we see that he's writing from there.
The Lord Jesus Christ instructs him
with writing to the seven churches of Asia,
and those records are provided to us.
And then as we enter into the fourth chapter,
we find that the scene here just for a moment
will shift from earth to heaven.
We enter into the throne room of heaven
for chapter four and five,
and then as we begin chapter six,
we see once again that the scene shifts back to earth.
As I mentioned to you as we started the study
through the book of Revelation,
that there are times in which events
are happening simultaneously,
events that are happening in heaven
and happening on earth at the same time,
but that's very challenging to read that way.
And so we find that in chapters four and five,
we have the opportunity to enter
into the throne room of heaven.
We talk about, and I've titled the message this evening,
the rapture.
It's a subject matter in which is often discussed,
and we speak about, we sing about
the return of the Lord Jesus Christ,
and many people wanna ask this question,
when will the rapture occur?
They wanna know when.
They may not wanna know when as far as setting a date,
because we all know that the Bible says
that we cannot know the hour.
We do not set a date,
but we understand that there's great discussion
with regard to the timing of the rapture.
We're gonna get through a number of things this evening,
but we must first answer the question,
what is the rapture?
The Greek word that is translated to be caught up
in First Thessalonians chapter number four is harpazo,
and the Latin word is rapturo.
And so you will not see the word,
the English word rapture in the scriptures,
but you find that the Greek word harpazo
and the Latin word rapturo,
both of those words mean to be caught up.
And we find that as we read
in First Thessalonians chapter number four,
that the Bible clearly teaches us
that we will be caught up to meet the Lord in the air.
And so we begin to define what the rapture is,
and then seeking to give the answer
of when the rapture will occur.
I believe this evening, the Bible clearly teaches
that Christ will return with his saints
at the end of the tribulation.
And so we begin to read and understand
the timeline that God gives us.
And so as God gives us the timeline
that Jesus is going to return
at the end of the seven year tribulation,
and he will return with his saints.
So the question is, when does he return for his saints?
And we try to answer that question
as we look at scripture,
as we begin to set the idea and understanding
that he will return with his saints.
Notice what the Bible says in Revelation 19,
at the end of the tribulation period,
we understand that the tribulation,
that 70th week of Daniel,
that that 70th week ends in Revelation 19
with what we've often referred to
as the battle of Armageddon.
And we understand that as Jesus would return,
the Bible tells us in verse number 11 of Revelation 19,
and I saw heaven opened and behold a white horse
and he that sat upon him was called faithful and true,
and in righteousness he doth judge and make war.
His eyes were as a flame of fire
and on his head were many crowns
and he had a name written that no man knew but he himself.
And he was clothed with a vesture dipped in blood
and his name is called the word of God.
And the armies which were in heaven
followed him upon white horses,
clothed in fine linen, white and clean.
And so we see in verse number 14,
that the armies which were in heaven
followed him upon white horses,
clothed in fine linen, white and clean.
These armies, we find that some would say
that those are angels,
but we find that throughout the scriptures,
that not only does God speak about Jesus
returning with angels,
but he talks about him returning with his saints.
Notice if you will in Jude,
only one chapter in the book of Jude,
and right there next to the book of Revelation,
Jude, notice in verses 14 and 15,
and we see again,
reference to the Lord Jesus Christ
coming back with his saints.
It says in Jude verse 14,
in Enoch also the seventh from Adam,
prophesied of these saying,
behold, the Lord cometh with 10,000 of his saints
to execute judgment upon all
and to convince all that are ungodly among them
of all their ungodly deeds,
which they have ungodly committed
and of all their hard speeches,
which ungodly sinners have spoken against him.
We also see over in 1 Thessalonians chapter number three,
and I mentioned this last week,
that when you study end times,
when you study the books of 1 and 2 Thessalonians,
these two books,
these letters that are written to the church at Thessalonica
are so helpful in understanding the end times,
because there's much reference within these two books
concerning the return of the Lord.
But look in 1 Thessalonians three, if you will,
in verse number 13, the Bible says to the end,
he may establish your hearts unblameable
in holiness before God,
even our father at the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ,
what does it say, with all his saints.
And so we find that as we begin
to try to answer this question,
as we navigate through the pages of scripture
and we interpret scripture with scripture,
we understand that the Bible speaks about a time
in which the Lord Jesus Christ
is going to return with all his saints.
So we're trying to determine this evening,
well, when is it that he comes for his saints?
Because the rapture is when he's coming for his saints,
the revelation, if you will,
that second coming is when he comes with his saints.
There's a clear distinction in the scriptures
between the saints being caught up
to meet the Lord in the air,
and when Jesus Christ comes back to earth,
according to Zechariah chapter 14,
the Bible teaches us that the Lord Jesus Christ
is literally his foot is gonna come down
on the Mount of Olives.
If you read Zechariah 14, one through five,
you find that that's going to happen,
and that's at the end of the tribulation.
And when he returns, the Bible tells us,
I'll read it for you in Zechariah chapter 14,
and in verse number four and five,
I said verses one through five,
if you read the whole context,
speaking of the day of the Lord,
but in verse number four, it says,
and his feet shall stand in that day
upon the Mount of Olives,
which is before Jerusalem on the east.
I've been there.
And you can stand on the Mount of Olives,
and you can see the Temple Mount.
You can stand on the Temple Mount
and see the Mount of Olives.
It's right there.
And it says this, and the Mount of Olives shall cleave
in the midst thereof toward the east and toward the west.
When he puts his foot on the Mount of Olives,
it's gonna separate, and the Bible says,
and there should be a very great valley,
and half of the mountain shall remove toward the north
and half of it toward the south,
and ye shall flee to the valley of the mountains,
for the valley of the mountains shall reach unto Azal.
Yea, ye shall flee like as ye fled
from before the earthquake in the days of Uzziah,
king of Judah, and that's a reference back historically
that they would be mindful of.
And it says, and the Lord my God shall come,
and notice again, and all the saints with thee.
And so again, we understand that the Bible teaches
this distinction between the Lord Jesus Christ
coming back with his saints and coming back for his saints.
In fact, as you continue to recognize through God's word,
you find that it's an absolute clear distinction
between these two events.
And so we seek to try to answer the question,
when will the rapture occur?
We have to first acknowledge that there's a distinction
between Jesus coming for his saints
and Jesus coming with his saints.
The next thing that we must answer is we must determine
what is the purpose of the tribulation?
So when we begin to dig into scripture
and we find that God records for us a tribulation period,
we would understand that if you were to read
Daniel chapter number nine,
and you read the prophecy of Daniel's 70 weeks,
that when we're speaking about the tribulation,
we're speaking about Daniel's 70th week.
And when we talk about Daniel's 70th week,
it's very clear in scripture that that 70th week
has two distinct parts to it.
There's the three and a half and the three and a half.
There's an event that takes place,
we'll get to it in just a moment.
But when we begin to understand the tribulation
and answer the question, what is the tribulation for?
Why is it that God has?
expressed to us, that he has revealed to us, that there's going to be this
tribulation. We find that Jeremiah in chapter number 30 refers to this day of
the Lord, this day of great trouble, as the time of Jacob's trouble in Jeremiah
30 and verse number 7. And we begin to understand that Jacob, his name was
changed to Israel, right? His name was changed to Israel. And so we find that as
Jeremiah is prophesying and he says that it's the day, the time, of Jacob's
trouble. So we begin to try to understand the tribulation. I believe
that Daniel's 70th week, this time that we refer to as the tribulation, is in
fact all about Israel. It's entirely about Israel. Notice, if you will, in
Romans chapter number 11. And as we look in Romans chapter 11, I'm gonna read a
lengthy passage of Scripture because I believe it's important for us to look at
the entirety of the content and be able to understand what God is giving to us
with regard to this age that we refer to as the church age, which by the way was
a mystery to the Old Testament prophets. We find that in Romans chapter 3 11, look
in verse number 11 with me. Notice what the Bible says. I say then, have they
stumbled that they should fall? God forbid, but rather through their fall
salvation has come unto the Gentiles, for to provoke them to jealousy. Now if the
fall of them, them being Israel, be the riches of the world and the diminishing
of them the riches of the Gentiles, how much more their fullness? For I speak to
you Gentiles, and as much as I am the apostle of the Gentiles, I magnify mine
office. If by any means I may provoke to emulation them which are my flesh, and
might save some of them, for if the casting away of them, Israel, be the
reconciling of the world, what shall the receiving of them be but life from the
dead? For if the first fruit be holy, the lump is also holy, and if the root be
holy, so are the branches. And if some of the branches be broken off, and thou,
being a wild olive tree, work graft in among them, and with them partakest of
the root and fatness of the olive tree, notice what he says, boast not against
the branches. But if thou boast, thou bearest not the root, but the root thee.
Thou wilt say then, the branches were broken off, that I might be graft in. Well,
because of unbelief they were broken off, and thou standest by faith. Be not
high-minded, but fear. Notice, for if God spared not the natural branches, take heed
lest he also spare not thee. The natural branches, again, referring to Israel, and
the Gentiles are graft in. He refers to it as being that wild olive tree in verse
number 17, and he says there that if he spared not, if God spared not the natural
branches, why? It was because of their rejection, right? It was the rejection of
the people of Israel. They rejected the Lord Jesus Christ as being their Messiah.
They said, we have no king but Caesar. Crucify him is what they cried out, and
we find that the Gentiles, the wild olive tree, are graft in. Verse 22, behold
therefore the goodness and severity of God on them which fell severity, but
toward thee goodness. If thou continue in his goodness, otherwise thou also shalt
be cut off. And they also, if they abide not still in unbelief, shall be graft in,
for God is able to graft them in again. What's he telling us? Listen, Jewish
people can be saved today. Amen. Jewish people, listen, it is a, it is a lie from the pit
of hell. It is heresy when someone stands up and says all Jewish people are going
to heaven. That is not what the Bible teaches. There are people that have
proclaimed that, prominent voices that have proclaimed that. That is simply not
what the Bible teaches. The gospel is the power of God unto salvation to everyone
that believeth to the Jew first and also to the Greek. And so we're all saved the
same way. We understand that there when they had the council at Jerusalem, Acts
15, they settled that whole thing and gave us a record of that. Notice in verse
24, for if thou were cut off or cut out, excuse me, of the olive tree which is
wild by nature, and were graft contrary to nature into a good olive tree, how
much more shall these which be the natural branches be graft in their own
olive tree? For I would not, brethren, that you should be ignorant of this
mystery. Look at that. Once again, God says I don't want you to be ignorant. I want
you to know. I want you to be informed. Notice what he says, lest you should be
wise in your own conceits. How many times we mess ourselves up because we don't
follow the teaching of God's Word. We say in Romans chapter number one,
professing themselves to be wise, they became fools. Romans chapter number one.
And we find here, notice what he says, that blindness in part is happened to
Israel, notice, until the fullness of the Gentiles be come in. There's a certain
measure of blindness. It's speaking of spiritual blindness. If you remember the
miracle from John chapter number nine when Jesus healed the man that was born
blind, and remember the disciples said who did sin, this man or his parents, that
he was born blind. And Jesus said neither this man nor his parents, but for the
glory of God. And we find that as you go through that miracle, they ask him
repeatedly, what happened to you? What's going on? He said, listen, all I know is I
was blind and now I see. And he tells them, and he tells them, and then he
finally says, will you be his disciples as well? And that enraged them. And we
find that as you go through the text that here's what happens. They ask this
question, are we blind also? That was a question asked by the religious Jewish
Jewish leaders of the day. And the reality is that they were not blind
physically, but oh, they were blind spiritually. And spiritual blindness is
far worse than physical blindness. And we find that the Bible says that this
blindness in part has happened to Israel. Again, it's in part because Jewish people
can still be saved today. It's temporary because he says until the fullness of
the Gentiles be come in. And so Jesus is dealing with this church age as we
refer to it. If you look at Daniel's prophecy of those 70 weeks, there's a
gap between week 69 and week 70. And we don't know how long that gap is. We find
with the progressive revelation of Scripture, as God would continue to
unfold truth from the day of Daniel until, of course, the closing of the
canon in the book of Revelation, that this progressive revelation that God has
revealed to us, there's this gap, this period of time between the 69th and 70th
week. By the way, if you were to look at Daniel's prophecy of the 70 weeks, it all
has to do with Israel from the rebuilding of the walls. That's when the
commandment goes forth. That's when the clock starts. And you find if you go 49
years, it's exactly at the decree that was given. If you go another, what is it,
434 years, you find the time of Messiah being cut off exactly as it's
prophesied. And then there's this gap. We're living in this church age, this gap.
But we find that he says until the fullness of the Gentiles be come in. And
notice verse 26, and so all Israel shall be saved. As it is written, there shall
come out of Zion the Deliverer, and shall turn away ungodliness from Jacob.
For this is my covenant unto them, when I shall take away their sin. So now in
verse 26 and 27, he's really focused on, because when the fullness of the Gentiles
are come in, now Israel is going to be the focus again. Verse 26 and 27. And we
find that during the tribulation period, that Israel is the focus. And Israel is
being prepared. If you were to read Ezekiel chapter 20 in verses 33 through
44, I'm not going to read all of that this evening. There's a number of other
passages throughout the prophets, both major and minor prophets, that God
reveals to us that this tribulation period of time is a time in which God is
preparing Israel to receive Messiah. And we find that all of that is taking place.
All of these, remember in Revelation chapter 7, there's 144,000. Who are they?
There's 12,000 from each tribe. In Revelation chapter 11, there are two
witnesses that are going forth and they're proclaiming. And we find that
these characteristics are provided to us so that we could understand, why is there
a tribulation? What is the purpose of the tribulation? And when we can answer that
question, it helps us to go back and answer the question about the rapture.
Because we have a good understanding of this period of time known as the
tribulation. Can I tell you this evening that the tribulation is characterized,
I'm just going to share a few thoughts with regard to how the tribulation is
characterized. And obviously, over the next several months, we'll study through
the chapters that detail for us the tribulation. But the tribulation is
characterized by great wrath. The tribulation is characterized by great
deception, by death, by conflict, by judgment. Those are words that help us
understand the time of what we see during the tribulation. We understand as we read
through the book of Revelation that there will be many that will be saved during
that time. We'd refer to them as being tribulation saints. Now, I believe,
as you look at 2 Thessalonians...
in 2 Thessalonians, chapter number two,
that if you reject Jesus Christ now,
and the rapture occurs and you enter into the tribulation,
that God will actually send you strong delusion
and you will not get saved,
based on 2 Thessalonians, chapter two.
Some people that are, well, I'm just gonna find out
what's gonna happen and I'm gonna reject it
and I'm gonna live however I wanna live
and I'll just find out then, it's not gonna happen.
There'll be people that will enter into the tribulation
that never heard the truth.
There'll be people that will then be exposed to the truth
and they'll be saved, obviously many of them Jewish people.
So what does Christ say to the church
when we understand that the tribulation period
is really all about Israel
and we understand how the tribulation is characterized?
We then ask ourselves this question,
what kind of promises did Jesus give to the church?
Well, notice in the book of 1 Thessalonians, if you will,
we'll look at chapter one and also at chapter five
and I want you to notice what Paul says
to the church in Thessalonica
with regard to these wonderful promises
that the church has been given.
1 Thessalonians, chapter one,
again, each chapter has some reference
to the return of Christ
and so we find in 1 Thessalonians, chapter number one,
notice in verse number nine,
Paul's talking about his entrance there to Thessalonica
and how they trust at Christ.
Notice in verse number nine of 1 Thessalonians one,
for they themselves show of us
what manner of entering in we had unto you
and how ye turned to God from idols
to serve the living and true God.
What happened?
They got saved by the grace of God, hallelujah.
I mean, Paul came in there, he's preaching the gospel
and Paul's saying to these believers in Thessalonica
that you've been so effective
on sharing the truth of the gospel
that when we go to other regions,
they're telling us about your witness
and they're telling us about what happened to you
and they turned to God from idols
to serve the living and true God.
Notice in verse number 10,
and to wait for his son from heaven,
whom he raised from the dead, even Jesus,
which delivered us from the wrath to come.
We read in chapter number five of 1 Thessalonians,
notice in chapter four, we deal with the rapture.
We looked at that two weeks ago pretty extensively,
but as you enter into chapter number five
of 1 Thessalonians, you find that the Bible says
in verse number one,
but of the times and the seasons, brethren,
you have no need that I write unto you.
For yourselves know perfectly that the day of the Lord
so cometh as a thief in the night.
For when they shall say peace and safety,
then sudden destruction cometh upon them
as travail upon a woman with child
and they shall not escape.
Skip down if you will and look at verse number nine.
For God hath not appointed us to wrath,
but to obtain salvation by our Lord Jesus Christ.
I'm thankful as the bride of Christ
that he's not appointed us to wrath, amen.
Now you read in some people that have,
and I'll deal with this in just a few moments
as we wrap up this evening,
but some people will take this approach
or this position of being a pre-wrath rapture.
And they take that as being the midpoint of the tribulation,
but I argue that if you begin reading in chapter number six
when the tribulation begins,
when the seals are first being opened,
there is a great amount of wrath
that is being poured out immediately
in Revelation chapter number six.
So we find that God has told us in his word,
he's told the church that he's not appointed us to wrath,
but to obtain salvation by our Lord Jesus Christ.
Understand there's a distinction
between wrath and tribulation and persecution.
The persecution that the church, that believers endure
is a persecution that comes from lost people,
so on and so forth.
And we find that he says,
yea, all those that live godly in Christ Jesus
shall suffer persecution.
But you understand when you enter into the tribulation
that it is God's wrath that is being poured out.
As a saved, as a saint, a saved individual,
God took, the Lord Jesus Christ took all of the wrath
already for me.
And we find that here,
he says that he's not appointed us to wrath,
but to obtain in salvation by our Lord Jesus Christ.
The next question that we must answer
or the next issue that we must address
is the matter of imminence.
Have you ever heard somebody talk about,
you've heard me say it,
that we believe in the imminent return of Christ?
What do we mean by that?
Well, what we mean by that is it could happen at any moment.
It's imminent, it could happen at any moment.
There's nothing necessary to take place
in order for Christ to return.
We believe that the scriptures teach this doctrine,
this teaching of imminence, why?
Well, 1 Corinthians 15, 52,
in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye.
That sounds pretty imminent, does it not?
We find that in 1 Thessalonians 5, in verse two,
we read the verse just a moment ago,
it's repeated in 2 Peter 3, in verse number 10,
that he's gonna come like a thief in the night.
We find that James says this in James 5, in verse number eight
that the coming of the Lord draweth nigh.
And so we find that as God would give to us this idea
of in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye,
as a thief in the night,
we understand this idea of imminence.
I would say to you this evening
that when you look at Daniel's 70th week,
and you look at the prophecy that's given
in Daniel chapter number nine,
that there's something very specific
that happens at the start of the 70th week,
there's something very specific that happens
at the midpoint of the 70th week,
and there's something very specific
that happens at the end of the 70th week.
Therefore, if something specific happens at the start,
the midpoint, and the endpoint,
if the rapture occurs at any time other than pre-trib,
then you could actually calculate the time
in which Christ would come.
What do I mean by that?
Well, how does the 70th week begin?
Well, in Daniel chapter nine, in verse 27,
we're told that there's a covenant
that is made with Israel.
Notice, if you will, turn back to Daniel nine,
and notice this prophecy that's given to us.
We can all look at the entirety of it
instead of just verse 27.
I'll just look just a few verses earlier in verse 24.
In Daniel nine, in verse 24, notice what the Bible says.
70 weeks are determined upon thy people
and upon thy holy city.
Israel, Jerusalem, Hebrews, the Jewish people,
to finish the transgression and to make an end of sins
and to make reconciliation for iniquity
and to bring in everlasting righteousness
and to seal up the vision and prophecy
and to anoint the most holy.
Know therefore and understand
that from the going forth of the commandment
to restore and to build Jerusalem
unto the Messiah the Prince shall be seven weeks
and three score and two weeks.
We see this is given to us,
the timeline that is provided here.
The street shall be built again
and the wall even in troubleless times
and after three score and two weeks
shall Messiah be cut off but not for himself.
These seven weeks will be from that commandment
to the building of Jerusalem
and then 62 weeks going forward
that Messiah would be cut off.
The end of verse 26,
and the people of the Prince that shall come
shall destroy the city and the sanctuary
and the end thereof shall be with a flood
and unto the end of the war,
desolations are determined.
You can read of what happened there,
of course, with Christ and Jerusalem and all of that.
Verse 27, and he, speaking of antichrist,
he shall confirm the covenant with many for one week.
And so this is the 70th week.
And so he's gonna confirm this covenant
with many for one week.
So that's gonna be the start of the tribulation.
Again, it's a known event.
Something that's specific that's going to happen
that's gonna start the 70th week.
Okay, there's gonna be a peace treaty.
If I can call it that this evening.
Then notice in the midst of the week,
that's the three and a half year mark.
So seven years is the 70th week.
And so three and a half years in,
the Bible says in the midst of the week,
he shall cause the sacrifice and the oblation to cease.
And for the overspreading of abominations,
he shall make it desolate, even until the consummation.
And that determined shall be poured upon the desolate.
We often refer to this as the abomination of desolation.
Jesus mentions it.
Notice what Paul says about it
over in second Thessalonians chapter two.
Notice what the apostle Paul says
about what we just read in Daniel.
Again, Jesus mentions it in Matthew 24,
but look at what Paul says in second Thessalonians
chapter two.
Again, here in second Thessalonians chapter two,
he's speaking to this church in Thessalonica,
that he's already given much truth to them
with regard to the coming of the Lord.
As he's writing to the church, the same church,
the second letter, this we call it second Thessalonians,
we find that he begins chapter number one,
in verse number one, saying this.
Now we beseech you, brethren, by.
the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, and by our gathering together unto him, that ye be
not soon shaken in mind, or be troubled, neither by spirit, nor by word, nor by letter, as
from us, as that the day of Christ is at hand.
So what was happening?
Well, there were peoples telling the church at Thessalonica that the day of the Lord was
already at hand, that the day of Christ was at hand.
And Paul says, don't be troubled.
He says, not by your spirit, by word, nor by letter, as from us.
It's believed, as you look through the entire book and you come to verse 17 at the end of
the book, that he says that the salutation of Paul with mine own hand, which is the token
in every epistle, so I write.
There were some counterfeit letters that were sent to the church at Thessalonica.
For what purpose?
To deceive them.
Can I tell you what counterfeit letters look like today?
YouTube.
Do I need to say it again?
You can go out there and you can watch all kinds of crazy nonsense that doesn't align
with what God's word says.
And you can get so in trouble with those things.
And we find that Paul says, don't be deceived.
Notice in verse number three, let no man deceive you by any means.
For that day shall not come, except there come a falling away first, and that man of
sin be revealed, the son of perdition, who opposeth and exalteth himself above all that
is called God or that is worshipped, so that he as God sitteth in the temple of God, showing
himself that he is God.
That's the midpoint of the tribulation, the abomination of desolation.
We can read it in the book of Revelation.
We will in several weeks as we get through it.
But we understand that this is a specific event.
So there's a specific event that starts the tribulation, the 70th week.
It's a covenant that's made, a peace treaty.
There's a specific event in the midpoint of the tribulation.
It's breaking the covenant.
It's the abomination of desolation.
And you find that there's a specific event that ends the tribulation.
It's called the battle of Armageddon.
We read it a moment ago in Revelation 19.
And that's when the millennium begins, the tribulation ends, and we enter into the millennial
reign of Christ.
Not only do we see the specific events that happen with regard to dealing with the subject
of imminence, but we also find that here in 2 Thessalonians chapter 2, that God reveals
to us that the restrainer, the Holy Spirit, will be removed before this will occur.
Notice as you continue reading in 2 Thessalonians chapter 2, in verse number 5, we read verses
1 through 4.
Look in verse number 5.
The Bible says this.
Remember ye not that when I was yet with you, I told you these things.
Now I know today we say we shouldn't tell somebody I told you this before because it's
like kind of offensive.
But Paul's saying I've told you these things.
But what happens?
We forget.
We easily forget.
You know when we're most prone to forget?
When the pressures are going on in life.
Pressures in life cause us to forget some things.
And we find that he says, remember ye not that when I was with you, I told you these
things and now ye know what withholdeth that he might be revealed in his time.
So we see in verse 6, the Bible refers to and now ye know what withholdeth that he might
be revealed.
We see that in verse 7 the way that it's described.
For the mystery of iniquity doth already work.
We see that.
John speaks about there's many antichrists.
The spirit of antichrist is working.
The mystery of iniquity doth already work.
Then notice this phrase in verse 7.
Only he who now letteth will let until he be taken out of the way.
I believe that verse 7 is specifically referring to the Holy Spirit.
In the restraining work of the Holy Spirit here on earth.
The Holy Spirit, the ministry of the Holy Spirit is different in the Old Testament than
it is in the New Testament.
We find in the Old Testament the Holy Spirit would come upon people for times and we find
many times, in fact you can read of some of the Bible characters where the Bible speaks,
Samson, the spirit of God came upon him, the spirit of the Lord departed from him and so
on and so forth.
But as New Testament believers at the moment of salvation the Holy Spirit of God takes
residence.
The Bible says that our body is the temple of the Holy Ghost which is in you which you
have of God.
He is the earnest of our inheritance.
We're sealed under the day of redemption.
And so he is this restrainer and he's the one, as the Bible refers to in verse 7, the
one that leadeth, only he who now leadeth will lead until he be taken out of the way.
So the question is this, how is the Holy Spirit removed?
Well who's taken away at the rapture?
Believers.
Where does the Holy Spirit abide?
In the lives of the believers.
So we find here it says, and then in verse number 8, shall that wicked be revealed whom
the Lord shall consume with the spirit of his mouth and shall destroy with the brightness
of his coming, even him whose coming is after the working of Satan with all power and signs
and lying wonders.
And we find that in this text, I referred to it a moment ago, in verse number 10, and
with all deceivableness of unrighteousness in them that perish, notice this, because
they receive not the love of the truth that they might be saved, and for this cause God
shall send them strong delusion that they should believe a lie, that they all might
be damned who believe not the truth but had pleasure in unrighteousness.
Those are some sad verses of Scripture.
I'll take care of it later.
Once the rapture takes place, it's not going to happen.
They're going to believe that God's going to send them strong delusion that they should
believe a lie.
Again that aspect of being deceived, deceivableness is mentioned in verse number 10, that they're
going to believe this lie is mentioned in verse number 11, and again the characteristics
of the time of the tribulation.
So we've dealt with many things this evening.
We've asked the question, what does the word rapture even mean?
Why is the rapture not in our New Testament, in our English Bibles?
We see it in the Greek.
We see it in the Latin.
We understand what the word means, and the word means to be caught up.
We find here this evening that the rapture is a biblical teaching, and many times what
happens is people want to know when will the rapture occur.
Again, not so much with regard to setting a date as much as understanding the timeline,
if you will, in God's prophetic calendar.
The Bible teaches us many things.
We talked about the imminence.
We talked about the fact that there's some very specific events that take place, and
if we look at this tonight, we ask ourselves, okay, what have we learned?
What is it that we've learned?
Let me review quickly seven simple things that we've learned this evening.
Number one, Christ comes for his saints.
That is an event in which Jesus Christ himself does not come all the way to the earth, but
we do know that he comes himself.
The Lord himself shall descend from heaven, and we find that we'll meet him in the air,
and so shall we ever be with the Lord.
We find that the Bible clearly teaches us that Christ comes for his saints.
The Bible also teaches us very plainly and very clearly that Christ comes with his saints.
When does he come with his saints?
Well, that is a known time.
It's at the end of the tribulation.
It's at the time when he's revealed in Revelation 19, and he comes, and he's going to set his
foot on the Mount of Olives, and we read that in Zechariah, and we see that in Revelation
19 as well, and so we understand that Christ comes for his saints.
Christ comes with his saints.
We understand the Bible teaches us that the restrainer, the Holy Spirit, needs to be removed
in order for Antichrist to operate.
That's going to happen.
We understand that the tribulation is for Israel, not for the church.
In no way, I read through all of the text of Romans chapter 11, why, in no way do we
believe that the church is spiritual Israel.
Absolutely not.
The Bible very clearly makes a distinction between Israel and the church.
The Bible refers to, as Paul is writing to the church in Ephesus, about the mystery,
and he talks about the mystery.
What's the mystery of the church?
Well, it's where Jews and Gentiles will be in the same body, the church body, and we
find that they're saved the same way, and so the tribulation, it's not for the church.
It's for Israel, and when we understand that, it helps us to properly interpret.
Why does Jeremiah refer to it as the time of Jacob's trouble?
Why is it that we see that blindness has happened to Israel?
For what part?
Well, because until the fullness of the Gentiles should come in, and we see this distinction
that God is making.
He makes the distinction of the natural branches versus the ones that are grassy.
in. And so we see these distinctions all throughout the Scriptures. Not only is
the Tribulation for Israel and not for the church, but we'd say this, that the
Tribulation starts with a specific event. The Tribulation has a specific midpoint
event and the Tribulation ends when Christ returns with His saints, the
Battle of Armageddon. I would say to you this evening that as we talk about when
is the Rapture, that if the Rapture were to occur at any, there's much discussion
about various aspects of beliefs, the most three prominent ones would be a
pre-Trib Rapture. What do they mean by that? Pre-Tribulation. So again, that the
Rapture occurs before the 70th week of Daniel. All right, do we understand?
Pre-Trib, that's what pre-Trib means. Mid-Trib, midpoint of the Tribulation. So
what does that mean? Well, at that three and a half year mark of the Tribulation,
that that's when Christ is going to return. That's what the mid-Tribulation
people that would believe and have that position, that's what they would say as
with regard to the timing of the Rapture. And then there's a post-Tribulation
period, and I know many people that hold to a pre-Trib and a mid-Trib. I really
don't know a whole lot that hold to a post-Trib. It's not as common. In fact,
J. Dwight Pentecost referred to it as the cosmic U-turn. I always remember that
hilariously because he said that the post-Trib, you get raptured and you make
a U-turn and you come right back with Christ, and I thought that was comical
the way that he described that. But the reality is that there are those that
would teach that the Tribulation ends, and that's when the Rapture takes place
at the end of the seven-year Tribulation. There are some that just simply don't
believe in a Tribulation at all, a Rapture at all, a Millennial at all,
they're amillennialist, and so on and so forth. There's a lot of different
positions out there, but primarily the three most that we would be confronted
with when we talk about the timing of the Rapture is pre-Trib, mid-Trib, and
post-Trib. I believe, and I am convinced biblically, that it is a pre-Trib
Rapture. The Rapture will take place prior to the Tribulation starting. I do
not take that position by matter of convenience. I take it by all of the
Scripture that I've shared with you this evening, and there's many more
verses that we could go to tonight. I believe it's biblical. It's not just a
matter of a convenient doctrine or teaching. No, it's a biblical teaching
that God gives us with regard to what's the purpose of the Tribulation? Why is
there going to be a Tribulation? So why is there a Rapture? What's the purpose of
God removing His Church, and at what point does He do that? So I believe that
the Bible plainly teaches that it's a pre-Tribulation Rapture. Furthermore, if
you believe if someone takes the position of being a mid-Trib or a
post-Trib, you actually can calculate, based upon the events that start the
Tribulation, the midpoint of the Tribulation, you could calculate when the
Rapture will take place. Why is that? Well, we know that that covenant is going to
be made to begin the 70th week. So you just go ahead and set your timer for 42
months, three and a half years, and that's when the Rapture will take place. But no
man knows the hour. It's going to come as a thief in the night, in a moment, in the
twinkling of an eye. If it's post-Trib, not only do you have the ability to
start the seven-year clock, but you have the ability at the midpoint of the
Tribulation of the abomination of desolation to say, okay, we have three and a
half years left. And so the reality is that when we look at the Tribulation and
we see the truth of the Tribulation, it really helps us to be able to answer the
question, when will the Rapture occur? Again, I'm not seeking to answer when as
with regard to a date, but the timeline of Christ's prophetic calendar, what's the
next event that's going to happen? I believe wholeheartedly this evening that
the Rapture of the Church is the next event on God's prophetic calendar. It
could happen at any moment. It's imminent. And as soon as it happens, there's going
to be the Holy Spirit, the Restrainer, will be removed, the Antichrist will be
revealed, the Covenant will be made, that Tribulation period, that 70th week begins,
God once again dealing directly with Israel to prepare them for receiving their
Messiah, et cetera, all that I dealt with this evening. And so what does that mean
to us? We don't try to take a position with regard to prophecy so that we can
stand up and debate with somebody else that has a different position of eschatology
than we do, that, well, I'm a pre-tripper and I'm a mid-tripper. We're not trying
to argue with people. The reality is that it ought to motivate us to do what Christ
has left us here to do. See, sometimes we can get so deep in the weeds of certain
things and arguing over the fine points of Christianity, of prophecy, of eschatology,
but we're missing the fundamental truths that God has given to us, the things that
we're supposed to be doing. You know what God says? Redeem the time. Redeem the
time. That we understand time is short, life is short. Jesus is coming soon. I better
be busy about doing what I'm going to do because He's coming back. And we understand
this evening that when He does, we looked at Scriptures, when He does, we'll be raptured.
But the people that heard the gospel, they're going to believe a lie. We've got to work
with urgency. I preached it this morning. The urgency in 2 Corinthians 6 is more about
the urgency of the ambassador than it is the urgency of the sinner. Oh, there's an aspect
of the urgency of the sinner, but oh, the ambassador. We need to work with urgency.
I believe Jesus is coming back. We sang about it this evening. I believe there are many
songs we sing. It's a wonderful Bible truth, but how does that truth affect me day by day?
How does it motivate me to live for Jesus today, to reach somebody? Dean prayed. I don't
know. I don't think he's ever prayed this way before when we've prayed before services,
but he prayed specifically this morning and again tonight, God, give me a soul this week.
He prayed specific, an urgency. People need to know the Lord. We've got to work to do.
I'm listening for the trumpet, but as I listen for the trumpet, I better be busy doing the
work of the master. Let's pray. Father, we love You. Thank You for loving us. Thank You
so much for Your Word and for the truth contained therein. We thank You that we could look at
so much Scripture this evening, and Lord, seek to adequately, clearly, logically interpret
Scripture with Scripture and to be able to answer a question with regard to the timeline
of the rapture of the church. I'm thankful for the teaching that You've given to us in
Your Word, and I'm thankful that we can know You. And I pray, Lord, that the truth would
motivate us this evening to be busy about the work that You've given to us to do. Would
You work in hearts and lives, bless the time of invitation, and we'll thank You for it.
In Christ's name we pray.