isn't it? And it's a wonderful privilege to know him as our personal Lord and Savior.
If you have your Bible with you this morning, James chapter number two,
James chapter number two. Of course, here on Sunday mornings, we've been preaching through
the book of James, our theme, doers of the word. And that is found in James one and verse number
22. And we've been making some progress here through the book of James and thankful for what
God has given us. I'm thankful to have a Bible. And there's a lot of people around the globe that
do not have a Bible. And I'm thankful that we have a Bible and God's word is preserved for us. And
we can trust it. It is profitable and we rejoice in having a Bible. Last week, we examined the
principle that now we will find that James is going to illustrate that principle in verses
21 through 26. We're going to spend a couple of weeks looking at this portion of scripture.
But we find that last week, as we looked at James chapter number two verses 14 through 20,
we understood that James was establishing a principle that's important for us to understand.
And we kind of outlined the text of scripture this way last week. And number one, genuine
conversion is only and always by faith. And for by grace are you saved through faith. And we
understand it's not by works of righteousness, which we have done, but according to his mercy,
he has begotten us. And so we understand as we look at the text of scripture and we compare
scripture with scripture, that genuine conversion is always and only by faith. But then we said this
and really looking at the portion of scripture and finding as James is dealing with this subject,
and we find this that genuine conversion produces fruit. Genuine conversion produces fruit. I said
this several times last week, your behavior is the evidence of what you believe. How I behave
and how you behave really is the evidence of what we truly believe. And what you believe to
be true will impact how you behave. And it's a two-sided coin and we understand that principle.
I said this real faith works and those works are not to save us. Those works are not to keep us,
but we understand that when we're saved, when we're born again, if any man be in Christ,
he is a new creature and we are his workmanship created unto good works and God hath before
ordained that we should walk in them. And we took a bunch of time last week to really just
to go through and understand the principle that we find James dealing with. Again, this morning
we'll find that he now is going to illustrate that principle and he's going to go back to the
Old Testament. The first illustration that he'll use will be the focus of our message this morning
in verses 21 through 24 and that is of Abraham. Now let me say this, we understand that the
original recipients of this book of James being first century Jewish believers, they would have
and be extremely familiar with Abraham. And oftentimes, in fact, even during the ministry
of the Lord Jesus Christ, there were times in which they would make comments about Abraham,
our father, and so on and so forth. And Jesus made that great declaration while having an
interaction with those religious leaders before Abraham was, I am. And what a tremendous
declaration of the deity of Christ and understanding that he is God in flesh. And so we
look here and we understand that these original recipients, they would have been very, very
familiar with Abraham. And so James uses this illustration. Look in verse 21. The Bible says
this, was not Abraham our father justified by works when he had offered Isaac his son
upon the altar? Seest thou how faith wrought with his works and by works was faith made perfect?
And the scripture was fulfilled which saith, Abraham believed God and it was imputed unto him
for righteousness. And he was called the friend of God. Ye see then how that by works a man is
justified and not by faith only. Of course, we understand and we made it clear last week that
there's no contradiction in the Bible. And I'm thankful that as you study the scriptures and
even as we did last week in dealing with that subject and the thought that genuine faith
produces fruit, we looked at the teaching of the Lord Jesus Christ. We looked at the teaching of
the apostle Paul. And then we looked at the teaching of James. And we see that they're
complementary the one to the other. They're not contradictory. And so as we come to the portion
of scripture this morning, the same is true. And I would say this, the Bible is an amazing book.
And the Bible must be studied. The Bible says of itself that no prophecy is of any private
interpretation. And we are to be students of the word. And so as we come here to this portion of
scripture, I've simply titled the message this morning, Living by Faith, Part One. Living by
Faith, Part One. We understand that the scriptures teach us and we read repeatedly that the just
shall live by faith. And we find that here is James is illustrating this principle that he set
forth that your behavior is the evidence of what you believe. He's going to use Abraham. Now,
the word justified there in verse 21, let me just provide for you a definition of that word
justified. Primarily, the word means this, to render or to declare righteous. And I'm thankful
that we're justified by faith. But we find the word used here in verse 21. And again, as I said
last week, many people will take out of context and say different things about the whole of the
book of James because of really primarily this portion of the book. But I want you to understand
that the word, the Greek word that is used that's translated justified, it also has this idea
and a secondary definition is to show or exhibit one to be righteous, to make evident or to show
in a clear manner. So when we begin to understand the secondary definition of this word justified,
as it's used here in James 2 in verse number 21, we could say as we look here that yes, Abraham,
and we see again in verse 23, and we'll look at the two verses of scripture and really the whole
text, but we find that in verse 21, it says that he was our father justified by works. It's really
the secondary definition that is in view here and understanding, and it was to make evident or to
show in a clear manner. Abraham's faith was evidenced by his works. And your faith is evidenced by your
works. And what you believe to be true will impact your behavior. Let me use just a couple of
illustrations before we get into the text this morning. If you believe that Jesus still saves,
if you believe that the gospel is the power of God unto salvation, if you believe that
Jesus is not willing that any should perish, but that all should come to repentance, then your
behavior really is the evidence of you believing that and it will be seen in how you interact with
people. Do you share the gospel? Do you give out gospel tracts? Are you concerned? Are you praying
for lost people to be saved, to come to the knowledge of the truth? And we find that our
behavior really is the evidence of what we believe. We can sit around and we can have all sorts of
conversations about, we believe the gospel has the power to save, but if we never share the gospel,
we have to really question, do we really believe it? Does that make sense?
We believe that Jesus is coming soon. Hallelujah. And what a blessing. But we find that the Bible
says that every man that hath this hope in him purifieth himself, even as he is pure,
that we redeem the time that we're busy doing what Christ has called us to do. Why? Because we believe
the imminent return of the Lord Jesus Christ. We could go through so many illustrations this morning
with regard to what we believe and how it impacts our behavior. But as we look here at the text of
scripture and we find, again, the principle illustrated in the life of Abraham, let me just
have you consider a couple of things this morning. Number one, consider the events. In verse 21,
James begins to deal with Abraham and using Abraham as an example. But we find that James,
in using Abraham as an example, that it's important for us to consider the events
that James is referring to as we would look back in the book of Genesis. So we find in verse 21,
the Bible says, was not Abraham our
justified by works, notice what it says,
when he had offered Isaac his son upon the altar.
Now for many of us here this morning
that we've been in church for any period of time,
we've read the Bible, we've heard some preaching,
we would immediately upon reading verse 21
be familiar with the event in Genesis chapter 22
that James is referring to, amen?
And we could understand, we could in our minds go back
and we could begin to consider the things
that transpire there in Genesis 22.
And so we find that James in verse 21,
the work specifically that he's referring to
is when he had offered Isaac his son upon the altar.
Now we find that in verse number 23,
James is going to reference a different event.
Notice what the Bible says in verse 23,
and the scripture was fulfilled which saith,
Abraham believed God and it was imputed unto him
for righteousness and he was called the friend of God.
Now in verse 23, when the Bible says
that Abraham believed God and it was imputed unto him
for righteousness, we find that this scripture,
notice he says the scripture was fulfilled which saith,
and he said in verse number 22 at the end of the verse,
and by works was faith made perfect.
And so we find that what's referenced in verse 23
is something that had taken place
in the life of Abraham years earlier.
You have to go back to Genesis chapter 15,
and the Bible would say there in Genesis 15
that Abraham believed God and it was imputed unto him
for righteousness.
And so let me just say this,
it's a little bit technical this morning
with regard to looking at these events,
but I hope it will help us to really grasp
and understand what James is dealing with
and what he's seeking to illustrate
here in the portion of scripture.
Far too many people write it off,
just dismiss it as there's contradiction
so we're gonna excuse it, we're gonna dismiss it,
we're not gonna deal with it, but there's no contradiction.
In fact, a Bible scholar of yesteryear said this,
if you think there's a mistake in the Bible,
then you are mistaken.
And I think that's a pretty good summary
and for us to study and to dig in to the scriptures
to find what God is seeking to communicate to us.
So take your Bible if you will,
go back to Genesis chapter 15,
and we're just gonna look very quickly here
at the text of scripture in Genesis 15,
and there's something that took place in chapter 14,
this battle that took place, Lot was taken captive,
and through that process, Abram,
his name has not been changed yet in the text of scripture,
and we find that Abram goes out,
he brings not only Lot, but everyone back
and all of the goods, and the Bible tells us
that at that time that the king of Sodom
went out to meet Abram.
And what a great interaction we find here
because not only the king of Sodom,
but then more importantly, the king of Salem, Melchizedek.
And we preached through this in years past
and we look here and we see that now,
Abram is in this position, we come to chapter 15,
and we'd often refer to Genesis 15
as the Abrahamic covenant.
And we find that here within the covenant
that God tells Abram in verse number one,
fear not, I am thy shield and thy exceeding great reward.
In verse number six, the Bible says,
and he, that's Abram, he believed in the Lord,
and he, God, counted it to him, Abram, for righteousness.
And that's where we find in James chapter number two
and verse number 23, where it was imputed unto him,
that idea to be applied to one's account,
to be counted as righteousness.
And so we find here in Genesis 15 in verse number six,
that this is where Abram, his faith in God,
his, if I could use the term, New Testament term,
his saving faith, all right?
He believed God and it was counted unto him
for righteousness, he believed in the Lord.
Now, we find that then you go through
a number of events that take place.
I'm not gonna study all through the book of Genesis here
and deal with each of the particular chapters
and what have you, but we find that in Genesis chapter 15,
this declaration of Abram's faith is recorded for us
before Ishmael is born.
Now, we know that Ishmael is born
when Abram is 86 years old, all right?
Now, just, I'm trying to get us a little timeline here
and understand what's taking place.
And so Abram is 86 when Ishmael is born
and then we go through, that's in chapter 16,
you get to chapter 17 and Abram is 99 years old, all right?
So there's a period of time that passes
and Ishmael, of course, was born and is growing
and what have you.
We find that it was in chapter 17
where the covenant is renewed
and established plainly and clearly
and we find that the token of the covenant was given,
which is circumcision.
We read that at the end of chapter 17.
You go through the destruction of Sodom and Gomorrah
and then you come to the birth of Isaac in chapter 21.
The birth of Isaac in chapter 21,
we know that when Isaac was born, Abram was 100.
Why do I say that?
Well, 14 years has passed, okay,
since the declaration that Abram believed in the Lord
and it was counted to him for righteousness.
So 14 years has passed when we get to chapter 21,
the birth of Isaac.
We come to chapter 22.
This is the first event that James references
in James 2 in verse number 21.
In this first event that his faith was declared,
through his works, when he offered Isaac.
And so we come to chapter 22.
We do not know the exact age of Isaac in chapter 22,
but we do understand that when you start chapter 23,
Isaac is 37 years old, all right?
So I'm not gonna tell you that that means he was 32
in chapter number 22.
I don't know.
The scriptures don't tell us for sure his age,
but here's what we can understand with certainty,
that the events that James references
in James chapter number two,
with regard to the life of Abraham,
again, these first century Jewish believers,
they get it immediately.
They understand immediately that James is talking
about two very different events.
And not only do they understand immediately
that James is dealing with two different events,
but they also understand that those two different events
are separated by at least 25 to 30 years.
So these events did not happen right on top of one another.
I mean, there's a few decades that takes place
between the two events that James is referencing.
And so we find that when we look at James chapter number two
that it's necessary that we acknowledge
and consider the events that James is referring to.
Why?
Well, because somebody will take verse 21 out of context
and say, hey, the Bible says
that Abraham was justified by works.
And then you're like, how do I deal with this?
Because the Bible does say in verse 21,
was not Abraham our father justified by works
when he had offered Isaac his son upon the altar.
So God gives us, remember, every word of God is pure.
And so God gives us the exact event
that James is referring to.
Now, consider all of that
and look at Romans chapter number four.
And let me say this,
as you're turning to Romans chapter number four
this morning, the wonderful thing,
and I mentioned by way of introduction
that all scripture is given by inspiration of God,
that there are no contradictions,
that it simply is something that we need to study.
What happens far too often is on the surface level,
there may seem to be a contradiction
and people just dismiss it.
They just immediately,
oh, there's a contradiction right there.
Hold on, dig in, study the scriptures,
ask God to make it clear to you
to understand what he's saying.
So we come to Romans chapter number four.
Look in verse number one of Romans four.
The Bible says this, what shall we say then?
Notice that Abraham, our father,
as pertaining to the flesh, hath found.
Oh, here in Romans chapter number four,
Paul is going to use Abraham as an example as well.
And he's going to use Abraham as an example
and notice in verse number two,
for if Abraham were justified by works,
he hath whereof to glory,
but not before God.
What's Paul saying here in Romans four in verse number two?
That if Abraham.
were justified by works, that initial definition to render or declare
righteous, then we find that Abraham would have reason to glory, to boast.
Ephesians 2 verse 8 and 9, for by grace are you saved through faith and that not
of yourselves. It is the gift of God, not of works. Remember this, lest any man
should boast. And so we find that Paul here says, listen, if Abraham were
justified by works, then we find that he hath whereof to glory, but notice not
before God. And then I love verse 3, for what saith the scripture? Isn't that a
good question? Let's go back and appeal to the scripture. What does the Bible say?
Not what does some church father say, not what does some theological book say.
No, no, we want to know what saith the scripture. Amen? As Baptist people,
we often will refer to ourselves as being people of the book. What would we
say by that? Well, the Bible is our sole authority for faith and practice, and I'm
thankful for that. Look, I got a lot of books in my library, but
none of them are inspired by God, except for this one. Amen? Listen, I got a lot of
books in my library. In fact, I got a lot of books in my library that I have found
mistakes in. Have you ever read a book and you found a mistake? Have you? I have
plenty of times, and I'm not an English scholar. Amen? And I'll read books. I was
reading a book just last night and found a mistake in the book. In fact, I was
reading a book one time and I was so disappointed because the individual, the
topic of the book was about how perfect this book is, and that book was full of
errors, and it was sad. It was hard to read it. Not only were there grammatical
and punctuational errors, but there were verses of scripture that were this
reference put with a different verse. It was just really a poorly put together
book, but you know what? I've read this book over and over again. I mean, I read
it, and I reread it, and I reread it, and I've never found a mistake. God's Word.
And so Paul says, what sayeth the scripture? Notice in verse 3, Abraham
believed God, and it was counted unto him for righteousness. Now, does that sound
like Genesis 15 and verse number 6? Sure it does. Does it sound like what we read
in James chapter number 2? Not verse number 21, but verse number 23, where the
Bible says, and the scripture was fulfilled, which sayeth, Abraham believed
God, and it was imputed unto him for righteousness. Again, that word counted
and imputed, they would be synonymous one with the other, and it's what the word
imputed means, to be counted or accounted to your account. And so we find here that
the scriptures in Romans chapter number 4, Paul here is dealing with Genesis
15, the event that we see James referring to in verse 23, different from
the event in verse 21, where he talks about works. Amen? Are we tracking this
morning? I know it's a little bit more technical of a message this morning, but
I think it's important for us to understand the portion of scripture that
we're looking at. Why? Because it's so highly debated. So look, continue looking
here in Romans 4, in verse number 4, not to him that worketh is the reward not
reckoned of grace, but of debt. Now we understand that in the physical realm, do
we not? If you work for something, it's not a gift, it's not a
reward, it's a wage. We could look at it here, it talks about a
debt. Listen, God is a debtor to no man.
Salvation, remember, genuine conversion as we studied last week, is always and
only by faith. It is the gift of God. The Bible says very plainly in Romans 6 in
verse number 23, for the wages of sin is death, but the gift of God is eternal
life through Jesus Christ our Lord. Now the whole chapter here in Romans chapter
4 deals with Abraham. I don't have time to read the entire chapter, I would
encourage you to do that later, but I do want you to skip down to the end of the
chapter as we look at verse 23 through the end. Notice what the Bible says in
verse 23 of Romans 4. Now, it was not written for his sake alone that it was
imputed to him. Okay, so the Scriptures were written, Abraham believed God, and
it was counted unto him for righteousness, it was imputed unto him for
righteousness, and here it says it was not written for his sake alone that it
was imputed to him. Notice verse 24, notice these words, but for us also. This
is precious, this is important for us to understand, but for us also to whom
it shall be imputed. Notice as we look at verse 24, and I'll read the entirety of
it in just a moment, but I want to just pause for a moment because here's what
Paul is saying that we have, what saith the Scripture, we have the record of the
event in Genesis 15, but that is not written just for Abraham's sake. It is
written for us as well, and notice it says, to whom it shall be imputed. What is
it? Well, it's the righteousness. The righteousness of God shall be imputed
upon whom, notice at the end of verse number 24, if we believe on him that
raised up Jesus our Lord from the dead. Now, this is wonderful as we begin to
break down what Paul is communicating here as he's writing in the book of
Romans. He's saying, listen, here's the truth for Abraham, but the truth for
Abraham has been recorded because it's for us also. How do I become righteous?
How can a man be declared righteous? Begin to look and begin to examine.
Listen, it's not hard. You don't have to spend a lot of time with most people for
them to acknowledge that they're sinners. Most people acknowledge they're sinners.
Now, they don't acknowledge that they're sinners that are condemned because of
their sin because oftentimes they think, well, I'm not as bad a sinner as the
other person, and there's far worse out there than me, and we understand that
comparison thing. It's not wise. It's not profitable, but we understand as humans
that that's a tendency that we deal with. And so, how is a man justified? How is
someone going to have that confidence? We sang this morning, Ring the Bells of
Heaven, and we talked about the rejoicing in heaven when a soul is born
again. What does it mean to be born again? Well, Jesus said there in John
chapter 3 with Nicodemus, except a man be born again, he cannot see the
kingdom of God. He then says this, marvel not that I say unto thee, ye must be born
again. To be born again. To be born of the Spirit. To understand that I am a
sinner, and I'm in need of the only Savior, and that Jesus is the only Savior,
and that Jesus went to a cruel cross, and he died, he shed his blood on the cross
of Calvary for the sin of humanity. He was buried in a borrowed tomb, but he
rose conquering sin, death, and the grave, and you put your faith and trust in the
Lord Jesus Christ, and as we read here in verse 24, if we believe on him that
raised up Jesus our Lord from the dead, notice, who was delivered for our
offenses, in verse 25, and was raised again for our justification. The just for
the unjust. Listen, Jesus is the perfect sinless Lamb of God, and he went to the
cross of Calvary for our offenses, for the sin of humanity, and here what we
find that Paul is saying is that this is the truth for Abraham, but for us also
that the righteousness of God can be imputed, and listen, I was saved, I was
born again in 1997. Hallelujah. I'm so thankful for my salvation, and I know I'm
going to heaven, not by anything that I've done, but all because of what Jesus
Christ did for me, and he gave me that precious gift of eternal life, and I'm
going to heaven. We find that it says it shall be imputed. It doesn't say that it
might be. It doesn't say that it could be. It says that it shall be imputed. What
was it that happened there when the Philippian jailer and all that took
place with Paul and Silas and the earthquake and all of those things? Sirs,
what must we do to be saved? Believe on the Lord Jesus Christ, and thou shalt be
saved, and then he says this, and thy house. Now understand that that little
phrase there, and thy house, didn't mean that if the Philippian jailer got saved
that that automatically meant his whole family was saved. What he's communicating
there is that the same way that you're saved is the same way anyone else is
saved. In the same way Philippian jailer that you would be saved, believe on the
Lord Jesus Christ, and thou shalt be saved, that that message is true for you,
for your spouse, for your children, for your grandchildren, and so on and so
forth, because the gospel is forever.
everyone. And we find here that that we notice at the end of Romans chapter 4
this wonderful declaration with regard to the truth of of salvation and it
reminds us of what Paul said in 2nd Corinthians 5 and verse number 21 for he
hath made him to be sin for us who knew no sin that we might be made the
righteousness of God in him. How is this transaction even possible? How is this
I mean it's it's absolutely just glorious and marvelous to think about
salvation and what it is. It's miraculous the transaction is so
wonderful that God looks at what Jesus did on the cross of Calvary and he says
that is sufficient. And this morning for every single person that places their
faith in trust in the finished work of Christ at Calvary not by any works that
we do for we understand we can't work to get to heaven it's God's grace it's
God's mercy it's God's gift to us that we accept it by faith. And hallelujah
we're born again. Isn't that wonderful? I mean it's miraculous. We sing about being
saved we sing about the old account was settled long ago and hallelujah what
wonderful songs they are and let me just say this this morning for many of you
you have been born again you've trusted Christ as your Savior and to God be the
glory. But let me just say this if someone is either here this morning or
tuned in via live stream this morning that's watching or listening to this
message and you're not sure of heaven maybe you've been trying to work your
way to heaven maybe you've learned from some world religion some denominational
teaching that you have to work to be saved. By the way most religions of the
world if you boil them all down it comes to a work based salvation. In fact there
are many people that have the idea the concept that all my good works are going
to be on this side and all the bad things on this side and we're going to
kind of see how it all works out at the end. How tragic. It's not by works of
righteousness which we have done. And so when we look here at James chapter
number two and we begin to understand how James is illustrating the principle
that was established in the previous text of Scripture he uses Abraham but
it's important that we consider the events not only that we consider the
events but we consider the emphasis number two we consider the emphasis what
is the emphasis that James is trying to deal with what is the emphasis that
James is placing here in this text of Scripture what is God trying to
communicate to his people. Oftentimes we look at the book of James and I've said
it many times already this morning what is James saying what is James writing
and what did Paul say what is Paul writing but we understand as Bible
believers that all Scripture is given by inspiration of God. This is not just
James sitting down somewhere and deciding that he's gonna write a letter
to these first century believers on his own no this is Scripture this is God's
Word and so therefore God had a message not only for the early believers in the
first century but he's preserved it for us and he has a message for us and he
wants us to understand what's the emphasis what is the point that James is
seeking to drive home what is it that God is trying to confront his people
with. Now we've said already throughout the text of Scripture that that James is
dealing with brethren he's talking about those that have been saved those that
have been born again. We also said this that the book of James is extremely
practical in nature it's a book that deals with the idea of spiritual
maturity the idea of being a doer of the Word and not a hearer only that we've
been saved but it doesn't end there. I'm thankful to be heaven-bound but if I am
God's workmanship if God has saved me and he's equipped me and he's gifted me
and he wants me to to be zealous of good works then we find that we have to to
apply the truth in the teaching we see that what's happening here is that James
and through the inspiration of Holy Spirit of God is saying listen consider
Abraham yes he had faith we see it in Genesis 15 but you know where you really
see his faith fully on display is in Genesis 22 because in Genesis 22 when
God says take thine son thine only son and offer him then guess what Abraham
does he takes his son to offer him that's the evidence of his faith and by
the way what is the faith that Abraham had what is the faith that we see there
in Genesis chapter 22 is it saving faith what what is the faith that we're
dealing with well again I'm thankful to have a Bible and we can compare scripture
with scripture amen and we take and we compare scripture with scripture and we
find that look in Genesis 22 God tells us there in Genesis 22 of the faith of
Abraham I can't imagine I've often looked at Genesis 22 I don't know how
many times I've read it I've preached from the text of scripture but we find
that we come to Genesis chapter 22 and God speaks to Abraham and here the Bible
says this in verse number one in Genesis 22 in verse number one and it
came to pass after these things that God did tempt that means to test to try to
prove Abraham and said unto him Abraham and he said behold here I am notice in
verse 2 and he said take now thy son thine only son Isaac whom thou lovest
and get thee into the land of Moriah now I think it'd be nice if there were a
period there it's a semicolon and God says here's what I want you to do and
offer him there for a burnt offering upon one of the mountains which I will
tell thee of the Bible says in verse 3 that Abraham rose up early in the
morning there's no delay there's no arguing questioning just obedience
because faith obeys the Bible says that he rose up early in the morning and
saddled his ass and took two of his young men with him and Isaac his son
and claimed the wood for the burnt offering and rose up and went under the
place of which God had told him of then on the third day Abraham lifted up his
eyes and saw the place afar off notice verse 5 and Abraham said unto his young
men abide ye here with the ass and I and the lad will go yonder and worship
notice what it says and come again to you you start seeing faith right there
in verse number 5 because Abraham says to his servants there hey you guys stay
here I'm gonna take my son Isaac I'm gonna take the the lad with me and we're
gonna go yonder and we're gonna worship now what did he already knew what God
told him to do in verse 2 we read it a moment ago to offer his son but we find
that he says that we're gonna go yonder and worship and come again to you and
here in the text of Scripture in Genesis chapter 22 notice as we continue to
trace and track the steps of Abraham and Isaac it says in verse number 6 and
Abraham took the wood of the burnt offering and laid it upon Isaac his son
and he took the fire in his hand and a knife and they went both of them
together and Isaac spake unto Abraham his father notice what Isaac says can
you imagine my father and he said here am I my son and and notice what Isaac
says behold the fire and the wood but where's the lamb for a burnt offering
Isaac knew that they're gonna go worship and that meant there's gonna be a
sacrifice doesn't mean offering and Isaac was aware enough to understand
that you have the the fire and you have the knife and we're going up there but
where's the lamb notice again the faith in verse number 8 and Abraham said my
son God will provide himself a lamb for a burnt offering so they went both of
them together I've said this before from Genesis 22 in verse number 8 I think the
statement is prophetic and I'm not sure that Abraham even fully understood
exactly what he was saying I believe that immediately in the context of the
fulfillment I believe that Abraham understood that God would provide a
sacrifice that that he believed that God was able to provide he had the fire he
had the knife his son says where's the lamb and he says God will provide
himself a lamb I believe that Abraham believed that but prophetically it's
looking all the way down through the ages to the Lord Jesus Christ as John
the Baptist was announces his arrival and say behold the Lamb of God which
taketh away the sin of the world as Peter would later write that the Lord
Jesus Christ the lamb that was slain before the foundation of the world
world. And so what do we find? We find the faith of Abraham. But can I share with you this morning,
it's not just faith here that we see in Genesis chapter 22 that God was able to provide and we
see through the actions. Listen, Abraham gets all the way up there with Isaac and he binds his son
and he lays him. I mean, listen, Abraham, he's believing God, he's having faith.
And how do we know he has faith? Well, we see it through his actions, through his works. Amen?
It's like I used my way of illustration to start this morning. How do I know that you believe the
gospel is powerful? How do I know that you believe that the gospel has the power to save someone?
Well, because you're telling somebody about Jesus. You're taking gospel tracks and someone
said this, what kind of person gives out gospel tracks? The kind of person that carries them.
You say that's oversimplifying. I'm telling you what, if you don't carry them, you're not giving
them. Right? You don't have it to give it out. So we have tracks available. Why? Because, and listen,
I pick every track that comes in here and I want to make sure that the message is clear and I want
to make sure that the message includes the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ, the death, the burial,
and the resurrection. And we've kind of, in recent months, we've kind of refreshed our track
offering. Why? Because we kind of had the same tracks in the same company for a number of years
and not that the message inside changes, but just give somebody something a little different.
I found myself regularly giving the same gospel track to the same people a week or after week
and that sort of thing. Why? Because we have routines in our lives. So I have to do something
a little different, refresh it. But listen, if we believe the gospel is the power of God into
salvation, we're going to give the gospel. Amen? So Abraham believes God. Abraham has faith. But
how do we know? James is saying, how do we know he has faith? Well, consider what he did at Moriah.
His actions, his behavior is the evidence, the manifestation of his faith.
But we also see in Hebrews chapter 11, look in Hebrews 11. And on Wednesday evenings,
we're going through Hebrews 11. And so we'll look at this portion of scripture here in the
next couple of weeks. We just finished verse seven last week with looking at Noah.
Verse eight begins looking at Abraham, but it's all the way down in verse 19. There's a lot of
text here in Hebrews 11 that deals with Abraham. But look in verse number 19. Well, look at verse
17, because that way we can catch the event and understand the emphasis that we're reading here
in James chapter number two. So notice in verse 17 of Hebrews 11, by faith Abraham, when he was
by faith Abraham, when he was tried, offered up Isaac, and he that had received the promises
offered up his only begotten son, of whom it was said that in Isaac shall thy seed be called.
That's what God told him. Look at verse 19, accounting that God was able to raise him up,
even from the dead, from whence also he received him in a figure. Abraham had faith
that God would provide a lamb, but also that if he took his son's life, that God was able to raise
him up. We can see the picture obviously of the Lord Jesus Christ. For God so loved the world
that he gave his only begotten son, that whosoever believeth in him should not perish, but have
everlasting life. What does it mean that he gave him? Well, Jesus Christ, the Son of God, God in
flesh, he left the throne room of heaven. He came to this sin-cursed world. He humbled himself and
became obedient unto death, even the death of the cross. And after that cruel crucifixion, he was
put, laid in that tomb. By the way, just in case the scoffers and mockers got you confused,
he was really dead. Amen? He was really dead. The Romans knew how to do it.
They knew how to do it. They made sure that he was dead. Listen, they didn't break his bones,
they didn't break his knees. Why? Because the prophecy of the Old Testament told us that no
bone would be broken. By the way, when Pilate was so surprised that he was dead already,
we understand it this way. Even as Jesus said in John chapter number 10,
no man taketh it from me, but I lay it down. The Bible says that he gave up the ghost. He died.
He was buried in that borrowed tomb. Just a few weeks ago, we had Easter Sunday.
We sang that familiar song, Up from the grave he arose. Amen. He tore the bars away,
the grave could not hold him. Praise the Lord. He rose, conquering sin, death, and the grave. He's
alive forevermore. And we find the picture, even with Abraham, that we see in Abraham and Isaac,
and the prophetic picture. And the Lord Jesus Christ, yes, he offered himself once for all.
And he rose. And he's alive. He ascended to heaven. He's coming again. And we should rejoice
in that. We should have great confidence in understanding the Scriptures this morning,
because we find the emphasis in which James is dealing with here. In James chapter number two,
again, what's the point that he's seeking to drive home? He's saying this, real faith works.
Genuine conversion produces fruit. Remember that Jesus, as we looked last week at the
text of Scripture and understood that Jesus, even in his teaching in Matthew chapter number seven,
you don't need to turn there. But he said this in verse 20, wherefore, by their fruits, ye shall
know them. What's the emphasis? He's trying to tell these New Testament believers, he's trying
to get them to consider the illustration of the principle that he set forth, that show me
thy faith without thy works, and I will show thee my faith by my works. I said that last week. I
preached the title of the message last week. Talk is cheap. Talk is cheap. Show me. Show me.
And it's not to be saved. It's not to stay saved.
I'm saved by the grace of God, and I'm kept by the power of God.
But we're to be zealous of good works. Why? Because genuine conversion produces fruit,
produces fruit. What a privilege it is to serve the master, to serve the king of kings.
He saved us. He then enables us. The Bible says, as every man hath received the gift,
even so minister the same one to another. He gifts us, he equips us, and then as we serve him,
as we serve him, he blesses us. It's amazing. Absolutely amazing.
And so genuine faith, genuine conversion produces fruit. So as we look at the portion of scripture
again in James chapter number two, understanding the events and understanding the emphasis,
let's read through it again in James chapter number two. In James two and verse 21, again,
we find these two events that are referenced from Abraham's life. These Jewish believers
immediately would have understood the two events that were being referenced.
We find that James is putting this emphasis upon the principle with regard to,
show me thy faith without thy works, and I will show thee my faith by my works.
And so he says this, was not Abraham our father justified by works when he had offered Isaac his
son upon the altar. Again, it was shown, it was exhibited, it was made evident, it was clearly
manifested that he was saved because of his works. Notice, when he had offered Isaac his son
upon the altar. Then notice what he says in verse 22, seeest thou how faith wrought with his works
and by works was faith made perfect. This completion of it. And we find again that
James is saying to these really immature believers, these individuals that are suffering and all that
they're facing, and he's wanting them to let their faith be known. Listen, being a Christian is not
being undercover. Amen? We used to refer to our youth group as Christians in action.
The idea that, listen, we're not undercover agents. Amen? Let the redeemed of the Lord say so.
We said this last week about Noah on Wednesday evening, that he believed God with the unknown,
but he also believed God in the midst of an unholy people. And the reality is as he,
Noah, went forth and he allowed his life to shine. So also are we in the midst of the heathen,
the Bible says in the book of Psalms. I said this on Wednesday evening, it's hard enough to get God's
people to give a testimony in God's house. Sometimes it's like, I said this on Wednesday
night. Sometimes when you try to take testimonies, I think I'm a dentist giving.
a dental procedure like a root canal or something.
It's like pulling teeth, man.
The Bible says, let the redeemed of the Lord say so.
Amen?
We have so many things to praise God for,
but the psalmist says, I'm gonna praise God
in the midst of the heathen.
So what's James saying?
Listen, James, remember, who's he writing to?
People that are facing persecution.
People that are suffering for the faith.
And so now if you're living out your faith,
guess what you're doing?
You're making yourself easily identifiable.
Amen?
Brother Mark shared with me a book years ago,
Tortured for His Faith, Harlan Popov.
And you read that book and you find that when the communism,
when it all came in and all that was going on,
they gave them a free license to worship
for a period of time.
You know what they were doing?
They were just taking down names, man.
That's what they were doing.
And then when they locked it down,
they already knew what they had to go get.
But real faith, trust God.
And we live by faith.
We walk by faith.
And so he's saying to these New Testament believers
that are suffering persecution
and all that they're dealing with,
remember, we've read the book of James,
sorry, the book of Acts,
we've gone back to the book of Acts
and we understand that persecution that was taking place
as the church was just starting
and all those Jewish believers
were facing great persecution.
This is different than the persecution of Peter
with regard to what he's writing in 1 Peter
with the persecution under Nero.
It's different.
It's a different timing.
And they're facing this persecution,
but James is saying, hey, listen,
you got to live by faith.
Your faith, it's not just an undercover kind of thing.
It's an out there on display.
Why?
Because we believe God and we live by faith.
So he says, seeest thou how faith wrought with his works
and by works was faith made perfect?
By the way, what a great example of Abraham
offering his son Isaac.
We find in verse 23, and the scripture was fulfilled,
which saith, what is this scripture?
Well, this is Genesis 15.
Abraham believed God
and it was imputed unto him for righteousness
and he was called the friend of God.
That happened 30 or so years prior to the event in verse 21.
He's called the friend of God.
Not by works.
No, the works are the manifestation of his faith.
So verse 24, you see then how that by works, amen,
is justified and not by faith only.
Again, let me say this in closing this morning.
Instead of dismissing the text of scripture
due to an apparent contradiction
or due to some denomination using the text
to teach false doctrine,
what we really should do is examine our lives
to see if our faith is evident to others
through our behavior.
It's easy to dismiss scripture for some.
No, we shouldn't.
But when there's an apparent contradiction
or maybe there's a denomination that teaches something false
about a portion of scripture,
if we're not careful and say,
well, we're just not gonna,
we're gonna kind of dismiss, no, no, no.
Every word of God is pure.
And it's there for a reason.
And I'm not gonna dismiss it.
I'm not gonna excuse it.
I'm not gonna say, well, some denomination
corrupted this portion of scripture
and therefore I'm not gonna follow.
No, no, no.
Listen, the Pentecostals have messed up
with the whole Holy Spirit thing,
but it doesn't mean that we don't believe
that the Holy Spirit and that I'm supposed to be filled
with the Holy Spirit, amen?
Yeah, no, no, you're not supposed to be speaking in tongues
and all that kind of nonsense.
But we understand that there is a Holy Spirit
and he is part of the Trinity
and he does indwell us at the time of salvation
and we are to be filled with the Holy Spirit
and I am to walk in the Spirit
so that I do not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
Hallelujah.
I'm not gonna skip teaching on the Holy Spirit of God
because of some denominational group that's corrupted it.
Does it make sense?
So the same is true in James chapter number two.
There's no contradiction.
Well, it says that Abraham was justified by works.
Understand the events, understand the emphasis,
and then evaluate your own life.
What work in my life, what in my behavior
is the evidence to those around me that I believe God?
Remember, I said this on Wednesday, thinking about Noah.
That ark is huge.
He couldn't build that thing undercover.
He couldn't.
Amen?
Everybody around knew that Noah was building an ark.
There was no way to hide it.
I asked this both in the morning session
and the evening session on Wednesday,
who's been to the ark?
I've been there, out in Kentucky.
Listen, you come around the corner,
you're not gonna miss it.
You have to be absolutely blind to miss it.
It's huge.
What are you doing, Noah?
Well, God told me it was gonna rain
and he's gonna destroy it with flood,
and he told me to build this ark.
What's rain, Noah?
What's a flood, Noah?
What's an ark, Noah?
I don't know, but God told me to do it,
and I'm gonna do it because I believe God.
Though you might be mocked, ridiculed,
made fun of, whatever it might be,
my faith is evidenced through my behavior.
And that's the emphasis that James is seeking
to drive home for these believers.
And so this morning, we must evaluate our lives.
What does my behavior say about my faith?
Would others see my behavior and say,
man, they believe God?
I hope it would be the case.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
Thank you for loving us.
Thank you for the word of God.
Maybe this morning someone's here that's not saved.
Lord, they need to be saved.
They need to be born again.
I pray in these quiet moments of invitation
that they'd come and allow us to take a Bible
and they'd place their faith and trust
in the finished work of Christ at Calvary.
Maybe this morning, though, there's some people of God,
some that have been born again, saved,
that aren't really living by faith.
They're not living by faith.
If they were asked, they would say
that they believe all the right things,
but their behavior doesn't really support what they say.
Their prayer life doesn't reveal that they believe
that you're a God who hears and answers,
that's able to do exceeding abundantly
above all that we ask or think.
God, I pray that as we would evaluate our lives
after examining the portion of scripture
after examining the portion of scripture,
that you would help each and every one of us
to live by faith.
I pray that each decision that's made
would bring honor and glory to thy name.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
At the end of our services, we have an invitation.
It's just an opportunity for you to respond.
God spoke to you through his word this morning.
Maybe you're not sure of heaven.