Genesis chapter number 15, and we have been studying
through the book of Genesis for quite a while.
I don't know exactly how long I could look in my notes
and tell you, this is lesson 43, I know that.
And the very first lesson that we had,
if I scroll through my notes here,
was back on March 10th, 2019.
And so we've been going through the book of Genesis,
making progress as we've gone through.
Of course, we haven't been every single Sunday evening
in the book of Genesis.
We've taken a few off, but we'll finish up
chapter number 15 this evening.
And if you think about the 15th chapter
of the book of Genesis, you find that there's really
a continuation of a dialogue, a meeting,
that God gives us a record of between the Lord and Abram.
And we find that as we really focused upon the first verse
in our first study of Genesis 15,
and really the way in which Abram was greeted by the Lord
and God told him to fear not.
And he said, I am thy shield, thy exceeding great reward.
Last Sunday evening, we looked at verses two through six.
And in that text of scripture, we dealt with the fact
that Abram comes to the Lord and says to me,
thou hast given no seed.
And of course, we find that God begins to provide
a record to Abram and Abram's perspective is revealed to us
as he says, here's the problem,
here's a potential solution, Eleazar,
one that's born in mine house.
And God says, no, and he gives him
very specific instruction with regard to the promise.
And that explanation is provided,
and of course, the promise is embraced.
As we continue to move through the 15th chapter
of the book of Genesis, really,
we are given further insight detail
with regard to the Abrahamic covenant
as we'd often refer to it.
And we find that here in this passage of scripture,
there's some time that lapsed, not much,
but we do see the days that go on.
You'll recall from our study last week
that it was in verse number five,
as the Lord is giving the promise to Abram,
he brings him out and he says, look up toward heaven.
And he tells him to look at the stars.
And so we see it would be evening,
he's looking at the stars and we made note of those things.
And of course, God gives them the promise
with regard to his seed.
And then we find in verse number 12,
the Bible says when the sun was going down.
And so there's another day that is unfolding here
throughout this process, this dialogue,
this meeting, if you will.
And this conversation will continue.
And as we look at the passage,
I want you to notice the statement in verse number 18,
where the Bible says on the same day,
the Lord made a covenant with Abram.
And so I've titled the message this evening,
We'll be looking at verses seven
down through verse number 21.
And as we dig into the passage this evening,
I want you to notice with me first of all,
what is requested.
Notice what is requested as we begin to look at this passage
and we see how that in verse number one,
God comes and this message is given to Abram in a vision.
And then Abram speaks to God and God responds to Abram
and so on and so forth.
And we find that in verse number six,
that as we finished up last week,
it says he believed in the Lord
and he counted it to him for righteousness.
That was of utmost importance as we looked at that verse
and seeing the faith of Abram
and believing what God said would come to pass.
And we find in verse number seven, it says,
and he said unto him,
I am the Lord that brought thee out of the Ur of the Chaldees
to give thee this land to inherit it.
And so we find that God is now speaking to Abram again
in verse number seven.
And he tells him, it's interesting.
He says, I am the Lord that brought thee
out of the Ur of the Chaldees.
And so we'd go all the way back to chapter number 11 and 12
and begin to see that call of Abram that God extends
and how Abram would leave the Ur of the Chaldees
and he would go on this journey, of course,
eventually coming to the place
where God had told him to travel to.
And we find that he's saying,
I am the Lord that brought thee out of the Ur of the Chaldees
to give thee this land to inherit it.
So as we look at the passage of scripture
and we've understood over the last several chapters
of studying the life of Abram,
that the promise to Abram really is twofold.
There's the aspect of the seed
and there's the aspect of the land.
Last week, we really focused upon
the seed portion of the promise.
This evening, we'll see that the focus now will shift
and not so much be with regard to the seed
as much as it is with regard to the land.
We see that in verse number seven
where God ends that verse of scripture by saying,
to give thee this land to inherit it.
And he said unto him, excuse me,
go back to verse number eight.
And he said, this is now Abram talking to the Lord.
He says, Lord God, whereby shall I know
that I shall inherit it?
And so this is what we find
when we notice what is requested in verse number eight,
Abram is requesting a sign.
He is requesting, he says,
he hears what God says to thee this land
or to give thee this land to inherit it.
And in verse number eight, Abram is saying to the Lord,
whereby shall I know that I shall inherit it?
Now it's interesting because when we're speaking
about the seed in our previous message,
we find that Abram comes and he says,
you've not given me any seed.
I understand this promise that's been given.
I have no seed.
Lo, one born in my house is mine heir.
And what does God do?
God says, no, that's not the way it's going to work.
He tells him in verse number four,
this shall not be thine heir,
but he that shall come forth out of thine own bow
shall be thine heir.
And then what does God do?
He gives him a, it really goes and gives him this picture
of let's go out, look toward the heavens, see the stars.
And so as God would give him and tell him
to look to the stars, if thou be able to number them,
and he said unto him, so shall thy seed be.
And so now the same God is saying to Abram,
by the way, I've brought you out of the earthy Caldes
to give you this land.
And Abram saying, okay, what is the sign
with regard to the inheritance of the land?
And so he's requesting this sign.
It is interesting as we find that Paul is writing
to the believers in Corinth.
And in first Corinthians one and verse 22,
he says that the Jews require a sign.
And that's interesting as it would go all the way back
even to Abram and asking the Lord
in this very passage of scripture, of course,
many times the Hebrews, Jewish folks,
Father Abraham, and they understand their ancestry
and so on and so forth.
And we find that he's asking, he's requesting this sign.
He says, whereby shall I know that I shall inherit it?
And so we notice what is requested.
I now want you to notice what is required.
In verses nine through 11, God is going to give
some specific requirements to Abram,
specifically in verse number nine.
And we see how Abram will respond
to that which is required.
In verse number nine, God said to Abram,
it says, and he said unto him,
take me an heifer of three years old
and a she goat of three years old
and a ram of three years old
and a turtle dove and a young pigeon.
It is interesting as we look at verse number nine
and we begin to consider this evening what is required
when this request is made by Abram
with regard to this sign.
What is it that you'll give me
that I know that I shall inherit the land?
God gives him some very detailed instruction.
He tells him to get an heifer of three years,
a she goat of three years, a ram of three years,
a turtle dove and a young pigeon.
And very detailed, very specific.
Our God is a God of order in detail.
And we find that throughout the whole of scripture.
And we find that the action of Abram
in verse number 10 is immediate obedience.
We see the detailed instruction
followed by the detailed action
where the Bible says this in verse number 10,
and he took unto him all these.
Aren't you thankful for the obedience
that we read of in the life of Abram?
Our God, we understand as we study the scriptures,
there is a principle of obedience throughout the word of God
in that our God blesses obedience.
And we find here that Abram did
as the Lord had commanded him.
He took unto him all these.
Notice it was not partial obedience.
He did not say, well, this will work
or I could do it this way.
No, Abram gets the detailed instruction.
And we find that there's detailed action
on the part of Abram, this immediate obedience.
It says this, that he divided them in the midst
and laid each piece one against another,
but the birds he divided he not.
And so in your mind's eye,
you can see there's some land here.
He takes these animals with the heifer,
the she goat and the ram.
He divides them in half.
He lays one over here aside from each other.
So as he divides the heifer half here, half here,
so on and so forth with the she goat and the ram,
the turtle dove and the young pigeon, he did not divide.
Now, the significance of this
is that this was a common custom of the day
for those making a covenant.
It's not something that we're accustomed to
as believers living in 2020.
You've made some agreements with people
and I'm guessing you probably never divided some animals
and put them apart from one another and so on and so forth.
And so we have different means in which we make covenants
or agreements one with another today,
but this was a very custom, common custom,
excuse me, during this particular era.
And we find what would happen is the parties
that are making this agreement or this covenant,
the two parties, they would pass in between
those divided animals and as they would pass in between
what they were doing is.
symbolically, they were saying this is the fate of either party that would
break the covenant. In other words, if I make a covenant with you, we go through
this common practice, this custom, we go through, we walk through these divided
animals. If I then break the covenant, I'm to be cut asunder. That's basically what
is being communicated. And so we find that this was a common custom, and it's
important that we understand that because as we look at the passage of
Scripture and we understand the era in which this is happening, we understand
the custom, and then we understand actually what happens in just a few
verses in the significance of the covenant based upon the action that is
taken. And so it's very important that we understand that. Notice in verse number
11, the Bible says this, and when the fowls came down upon the carcasses,
Abram drove them away. And so this was a long process. We find that the Bible says
in verse 12, when the sun was going down, and so from the time in which Abram would
cut asunder these animals and place them out, no doubt those
birds, the scavenger fowls, they would come down and try to eat upon that which
had been divided, and Abram would spend the majority of that day driving
away those fowls, as the Bible tells us there in verse number 11. As we look here
at what's taking place, it's important that we, again, understand the detail in
which God is giving us. And we find that this man, Abram, makes this request and
then God gives this requirement. The significance of those two
things that are mentioned in the beginning of this passage really begin
to unfold in an amazing way as we look at the latter portion of Genesis 15. We look
at verses 12 through 21, and I would say this, as we've noticed what's requested
and required, we now will notice what is revealed. And this is the bulk of the
message this evening, as we see the significance of that which God would
reveal to Abram during this particular time, and of course being recorded for us
in the Word of God, so that we'd understand this Abrahamic covenant.
These details are provided to Abram. Notice it says in verse number 12,
"...and when the sun was going down, a deep sleep fell upon Abram, and lo and horror
of great darkness fell upon him. And he," God, of course, is the he that is being
referred to, "...said unto Abram." Now, notice as we look at these verses of
Scripture, and we consider that which will be revealed to Abram, we see first
of all that God will reveal some truth with regard to the events that
would lead to the possession of the land. It goes back to what God said in verse
number 7, "...to give thee this land to inherit it." And right, so we find that the
the context of what we're dealing with is God has said to Abram, I'm gonna give
you this land. Abram says, what is the sign that you're going to give me that I
know this? And God is going to lay out the details in these verses of Scripture
with regard to his plan. It reveals to us some amazing things with regard to our
God. He's omniscient. He knows all things. He's eternal. He knows the end from the
beginning. He's going to speak to Abram in these verses of Scripture, just a few
verses. He's gonna speak to him about events that would take place centuries
later, and he deals with them in detail. Why? Because our God is eternal. He is
Alpha and Omega, the the beginning and the end, the first and the last. And so we
find here that God begins, as he's gonna speak to Abram in verse number 13, notice
what he says, "...know of a surety." Now it's interesting, as we study the Word of
God, we understand that God wants us to know some things. He wants us to be aware
of what his plan is. He wants us to have confidence in what he has said. We looked
at it this morning as we were studying there in 2 Chronicles, in the life of
Jehoshaphat, king of Judah, and that great event that is recorded in chapter
number 20 with regard to the coalition and all of those things, and how that
Jehoshaphat was aware of what God had promised, what God had said, and in simple
faith he believed God. See, God wanted Jehoshaphat and others to know what he
had told Solomon years earlier, and he's given us his Word this evening, and
throughout the Scriptures we understand that God has said that there are some
things that we need to know, that we can have confidence in, that we can be sure
of. Notice what it says, "...know of a surety that thy seed shall be a stranger in a
land that is not theirs." Now it's interesting because now we begin to see
the reference to the seed and also to the land. Remember as we dealt with the
seed last week, the first aspect of this promise that had been given to Abram,
that he gives them the details with regard to the seed, and we followed that
throughout the New Testament, the book of Galatians specifically, and now in
answering the question with regard to the land, God says to Abram that, "...thy seed
shall be a stranger in a land that is not theirs, and shall serve them, and they
shall afflict them four hundred years." And so here, as we begin to think about
the events that would lead to the possession of the land, God in Genesis
chapter number 15 is giving truth to Abram with regard to the Egyptian
bondage. Now we understand that's going to happen many years from this event
that we see. It's going to be 25 years before Isaac is even born, the promise
of the seed. And now we find that hundreds of years are now in view with
regard to the possession of the land and some events that would lead to the
possession of the land. And so we see the the reference to the Egyptian bondage
here in verse number 13. We see in verse number 14, it says this, "...and also that
nation whom they shall serve will I judge, and afterward shall they come out
with great substance." Now does that sound familiar to you as to what takes place
during the Passover, right? And we read about the Passover, the tenth plague. We
understand that as the children of Israel were serving there in Egypt, as
they were slaves, and there arose that Pharaoh that knew not Joseph, so on and
so forth, and we find that God would raise up Moses and Aaron, and they would
stand before the Pharaoh, and there were great plagues to demonstrate the power
of God. And we find that after that tenth plague, the Passover, that the children
of Israel were delivered. Yes, the Egyptians were judged, and they left with
great substance. Notice with me, hold your place here in Genesis, and turn to the
book of Exodus, if you will, in Exodus chapter number 12. So not only do we see
here in Genesis chapter number 15 a reference to the Egyptian bondage, but
also to the Exodus. We find in Exodus chapter number 12, excuse me,
in Exodus chapter number 12, notice in verse number 40. Let's look in verse
number 40. The Bible says this,
Now the sojourning of the children of Israel... I'll give you a moment, I hear
some pages turning. Verse number 40, Now the sojourning of the children of Israel
who dwelt in Egypt was four hundred and thirty years. And it came to pass at the
end of the four hundred and thirty years, even the selfsame day, it came to pass
that all the hosts of the Lord went out from the land of Egypt. And we find here
in Exodus chapter number 12, the reference with regard to the departure.
Now you will note, and I think it's of significant importance, because we find
in Genesis chapter number 15, in verse number 13, that the years, the number that
is used is 400 years, and here in Exodus chapter number 12, the number that is
used is 430 years. In fact, if you look at the New Testament, you'll find the
book of Acts in chapter number 7, it references 400 years, and the book of
Galatians in chapter number 3, it references 430 years. You say, Pastor, why
are you telling us all of this? Because here's what happens.
Mockers and scoffers want to tell you that there's an error in the Bible. They
want to tell you that. And they'll look at something like this and say, is it 400
or 430? Because your Bible says both. The answer is yes. It's both. How is it both?
Well, here's the importance, right? Here's what, so some Bible, if you
disagree with me, there's a lot of theologians that disagree with what I'm
gonna tell you, and I don't, I'm not trying to say that someone's right, wrong.
I'm trying to simply give you a Bible answer based upon my own study of the
scriptures of what I believe God is giving us in His Word with regard to
these years. Some simply just kind of skim over it by saying this, well, 400 is
kind of a round number for 430. And they just try to explain it away real easy.
Well, if that's okay for you, then fine, but I don't like that answer. Because I
believe that every word of God is pure. Amen? And so if God is a God of detail,
and He is, then there's some significance between this 400 and this 430. We have a
difference of 30 years, and what could that be? I believe specifically that the
400 years is in reference to Isaac, okay? That's the seed, right? Abram has been
given the promise with regard to the seed. There's the seed and the land, and
God is giving this promise with regard to Isaac, and the time of Isaac, from the
time in which he would be weaned until the time of the Exodus, would be 400
years. And we find that...
that difference. Notice in verse number 13 again of chapter number 15 of the book of Genesis,
he says, "...know of a surety that thy seed shall be a stranger in a land that is not theirs,
and shall serve them, and they shall afflict them four hundred years." Again,
the reference of seed, I believe, dealing with Isaac. And so from Isaac, if you include
from his time of weaning, if you will, to the time of the exodus, there would be that 400 years.
And then you look at the 430 years, and you begin to think about Abram himself.
And the reality is that Abram had left the Ur of the Chaldees, if you remember,
here at this particular time in which Abram is dealing with these things. According to
chapter number 12, where the call and the promise was initially given, he was 75 years old. So 75,
and then when is Isaac going to be born? Well, Abram's going to be 100. So there's 25 years.
The time of weaning obviously is different in our society culture than it was in biblical times,
but it's very common for them to say that a time of a child being weaned was five years old.
So if you take 25 years from the age of Abram at 75 to the time of 100 when Isaac was born,
there's 25 years. The time of weaning being five years, there's your 30 years. The difference
between 400 and 430, there's not a discrepancy in the Word of God. The question is, what timeline
are we starting? What's the starting point? Is the starting point the time of Isaac, or is the
starting point the time of Abram? If it's Abram, it's 430 years. If it's Isaac, it's 400 years.
Does that make sense? And so we begin to study the Word of God, we begin to compare Scripture
with Scripture, and you find that there is, I believe, an answer in the Word of God with regard
to these things. It's interesting because, again, sometimes people just simply try to skim over it,
excuse it, and say, well, it's just a round number, so on and so forth. There are other
types of examples that we could look to this evening. We won't take the time to do so
for the sake of our study here in Genesis 15, but what I would say to you is that there are
many scoffers out there that seek to attack the Word of God. This is nothing new. We understand
that from the very beginning, in Genesis chapter number 3, that the enemy, Satan, says,
yea, hath God said. And he begins to question the authority of God's spoken Word, so no doubt the
enemy is going to question the authority of God's written Word. And what does he do? Why do
these scoffers attack and try to dig in and tell us that there are errors and discrepancies?
I believe that if they can be successful in doing so, that it puts doubt in the mind of
the individual to say, how can I know if it's true or not? And ultimately, that's what Satan
wants to do. Satan wants to have people come to a place where they say, I can't trust this book.
And there are people that you can come in contact with, no doubt, that will laugh at you, will mock
when you say that you're a Bible believer, when you say, well, the Bible says,
because they have believed, they've been blinded by the enemy, and they believe the lie of the
enemy. So I would say this evening, when someone asks me, is it 400 or 430 years? Yes, it depends
where the starting point is. And if we're starting with Abram, then it's 430. If we're starting with
Isaac, it's 400. And so that's just kind of a side note. It's for free. If you don't like it,
you don't have to have it. They gave me some beans at lunch yesterday. I didn't want them.
They just kind of took them away, you know. But that's for free this evening. I believe that it's
a valid explanation of the Word of God as you study and compare Scripture with Scripture.
Notice, so we see these things that are revealed to Abram with regard to the events leading to
the possession of the land. There's also events that are going to be revealed, as we're noticing
what is revealed, with regard to the death of Abram. Notice what God says in verse number 15,
and thou, now he's speaking directly to Abram. He's speaking in verse 13 and 14 about his seed
and about the land that they would be a stranger in before they would possess the land, how they
would leave during the exodus. In verse 15, he changes attention back to Abram and says,
and thou shalt go to thy fathers in peace. Thou shalt be buried in a good old age.
So now, Abram is getting, God is speaking directly to Abram with regard to
revealing details about his death. If you look over, hold your place here, turn to the book of,
excuse me, to chapter 25 in Genesis, and look in chapter 25 in verse number 7, you'll notice
that certainly Abram was buried at a good old age. The Bible says in Genesis 25 in verse number
7, and these are the days of the years of Abraham's life, which he lived, and hundred,
threescore, and fifteen years. That's 175 years old. That's a good old age. And we understand
that as we look here after the flood, and we've made note of this through our study of the book
of Genesis, that the patriarchs, obviously, prior to the flood, they had very long lifespans.
It begins to decrease, and it decreases pretty rapidly after the flood, and just all of the
catastrophic impact to not only the earth and all of the geological things that took place,
but also just the environment itself. You get to the end of the book of Genesis, and you read about
the death of Joseph, and he lived to be 110 years old. And then eventually you get to where God
speaks to Moses about the threescore and ten and so on and so forth, if by reason of strength,
fourscore. And here, Abram is given this truth from God with regard to his departure, his death,
that he would be buried in a good old age of 175 years. Again, in sight is the fact that our God
is eternal, that our God is omniscient, that he's able to give truth to Abram with regard to his own
death. Notice with me also that God reveals information to Abram with regard to the judgment
upon the inhabitants of the land. We see that in verse number 16. It says,
but in the fourth generation they shall come hither again, for the iniquity of the Amorites
is not yet full. It's an interesting reference. You begin to look in verses 19 through 21,
and you begin to see the other groups of people that are mentioned, the Kenites, the Kenizzites,
the Kadmonites, the Hittites, the Perizzites, the Rephaims, the Amorites, the Canaanites,
the Gergesites, and the Jebusites. And you find here that the Amorites are mentioned
specifically in verse number 16 about this fourth generation, again, this time period in which they
would come again. And he says that the iniquity of the Amorites is not yet full. It's interesting
because the judgment would come upon the inhabitants of the land. This year, during the
shutdown and all that was going on, I taught through the book of Joshua. We had those daily
lessons that we sent out. And one reference that I made to you often throughout the book of Joshua
is the fact that those inhabitants of the land were being judged because of their wickedness.
And God had given warning to his people, to Joshua and the children of Israel,
to be careful about their walk with God and their obedience to the revealed Word of God,
lest they also be judged. And so we find here that he says that the iniquity of the Amorites
is not yet full. In other words, God knew because he's omniscient and he's eternal,
he knew the timing of what was going to happen. But really, I believe that as he says it's not
yet full, that God had given them some space, if you will, some time to repent.
But the inhabitants of the land, they never repented. They continued to go and serve
idols and live in their wicked behavior. And we find that they eventually would be judged. And our
God, of course, is the judge. And we understand that. He's gracious and he's merciful, but he is
the righteous judge. And we understand this evening that as we think about the end times,
and we think about the judgments, that as the people of God, if you've been born again,
you've trusted Christ as your Savior, that you'll stand at the bema seat of Christ,
the judgment seat of Christ. But for those that have not trusted Christ as their Savior,
they will stand at the great white throne judgment, as is revealed to us in Revelation chapter number
20. And so here, God is referencing the judgment that would come upon the inhabitants of the land.
We can read of all of those events. Of course, after the Exodus and before the conquering of the
land, you have the wilderness wanderings. That was never what God's plan was for the nation of
Israel. But because of their doubt and unbelief, that generation would die in the wilderness.
Now, we get here as we wrap up the 15th chapter of the book of Genesis, we now come to this,
what is being revealed with regard to the details of the covenant that God is making
with Abram. And so we see that he's revealed several things, and now he's coming back to what
the passage started with that we're looking at this evening. When Abram says to God, after God
says to give thee this land to inherit it, at the end of verse number 7, that Abram then says,
Lord God, whereby shall I know that I shall inherit it? And so God revealed these things to
him, and now God is going to give him this sign, and he's going to give us details with regard to
the covenant. Notice in verse
verse number 17, and it came to pass that when the sun went down and it was dark.
We notice that in verse number 12 it says when the sun was going down.
Now the Bible tells us in verse number 17 that the sun went down and it was dark.
Notice what it says, behold a smoking furnace and a burning lamp that passed between those
pieces.
What are the pieces?
Well those are the animals that had been, God had given that detailed instruction with
regard to that which was to be brought as we looked in verse number 9, and heifer of
three years old, a she goat of three years old, a ram of three years old, a turtle dove
and a young pigeon, and they had been divided and set in the midst, and so the Bible tells
us in verse number 17 that passed between those pieces.
Now remember I mentioned to you that the common custom of the day was that both parties that
were involved in making the covenant or the agreement would pass through those pieces
that had been divided.
So both parties would pass through signifying that the covenant is being established and
symbolically saying if I break the covenant then it is for me to be divided asunder.
And so we find here in verse number 17 that the manifestation of God passing through is
a smoking furnace and a burning lamp and it says that it passed between those pieces.
What's the significance?
Well the significance is that this Abrahamic covenant, as we often refer to it as, is an
unconditional covenant.
This is based upon the goodness, the grace and mercy of God.
This covenant that is being made has nothing to do with Abraham, it has everything to do
with God.
And that's important, it's significant for us to understand that as we think about promises
in the Word of God, there are conditional promises and there are unconditional promises.
Some of the conditional promises, some of the most common conditional promises are ones
that would be categorized as being if-then.
If you do this, then God will do this.
That's a conditional promise.
God's action is a response to our action.
If you do this, then this is what God's going to do.
In fact, you could read Proverbs chapter number two and you'll see a whole list of them at
the beginning of the second chapter of the book of Proverbs.
If-then, if-then, you'll read right through it and you'll see a number of them.
And so those are scattered, littered throughout the Word of God and we find also there are
unconditional promises.
This covenant that God has made, the significance of the manifestation of God through this smoking
furnace and this burning lamp passing between the pieces would signify for us this evening
that this is an unconditional covenant.
This is a promise that God is making to Abraham with regard to that which had been promised.
Remember, he says, to give thee this land to inherit it and Abram says to God, whereby
shall I know that I shall inherit it?
And so God then passes through those pieces, the manifestation of such as we've mentioned
already, and he passes through.
Abram himself, he did not pass through.
Why?
Because God is the one making the promise.
Now, keep that thought and look at a few verses with me in the preceding chapters.
Actually, let's read verse 18 and then we'll do that.
In the same day, the Lord made a covenant with Abram, saying, unto thy seed have I given
this land, from the river of Egypt unto the great river, the river Euphrates, the Kenites
and the Kenizzites and the Kadmonites and the Hittites and the Perizzites and the Rephaims
and the Amorites and the Canaanites and the Gergesites and the Jebusites.
We see in verse number 18 where we received our title for our message this evening that
in that same day, the Lord made this covenant with Abram and notice what he said, unto thy
seed have I given this land.
Abram says to God in verse number eight, God, whereby shall I know that I shall inherit
it?
What is it?
The land, as it's mentioned in verse number seven, to give this land, to give thee this
land to inherit it.
And so God then answers that request that Abram made at the beginning of our study this
evening.
He passes through giving Abram the sign that this is the sign, I've made this covenant,
this promise with you that I now am telling you I have given this land to your seed.
Now it's interesting because now we're speaking in terms that it's already settled.
It says unto thee have I given this land.
Prior to this verse of Scripture, everything that is spoken of with regard to the land
is spoken of in future.
I'm going to give this to you.
Now he says I have given you this land.
Notice with me, turn back if you will to chapter number 12.
We did this last week as we looked at the promise with regard to the seed, but look
at it now as the passage in Genesis 15 shifts from seed to land.
We find in verse number seven of Genesis 12, the Bible says, and the Lord appeared unto
Abram and said, unto thy seed will I give this land.
That's future, correct?
Will I give this land?
And there builded he an altar unto the Lord who appeared unto him.
Abram then responded to that promise by worshiping the Lord.
We see in chapter number 13, look in verse number 15.
This is after the division between Abram and Lot.
And we know that Lot went toward the plain and pitched his tent towards Sodom.
And the Lord then says to Abram in verse number 14, he says this, and the Lord said unto Abram,
after that Lot was separated from him, lift up now thine eyes and look from the place
where thou art northward and southward and eastward and westward for all the land which
thou seest to thee will I give it and to thy seed forever.
We see again in verse number 17, it says, arise, walk through the land and the length
of it and in the breadth of it, for I will give it unto thee.
In chapter number 15, as we started our message this evening in verse number seven, God says
to Abram and he said unto him, I am the Lord that brought thee out of Ur of the Chaldees
to give thee this land to inherit it.
And now Abram says, God, in verse number eight, he's asking for that sign.
That's what's requested.
Whereby shall I know that I shall inherit it?
And God goes through this, what was a common practice, a custom in that particular day
in those making covenants and God himself, the manifestation through the smoking furnace
and the burning lamp, he passes through those pieces and he says to Abram, unto thy seed
have I given this land.
What a great promise that God gives to Abram on this particular day.
Now we understand the significance of the Abrahamic covenant.
We understand that here the specifics are given with regard to the territory.
He says there at the end of verse number 18, from the river of Egypt unto the great river,
the river Euphrates.
He then lists out a number of people groups that are mentioned in verses 19 through 21.
And we find this significance with regard to the territory that God has given.
As we've looked at this 15th chapter and we dealt with the two aspects of the Abrahamic
covenant, we see first of all the seed and we understand the birth of Isaac that would
come later on here in the book of Genesis as we begin to read about that miraculous
birth and how God was fulfilling the promise that he made to Abram and Sarah.
And we see that in chapter number 21.
But of course we understand the fullness of that Abrahamic covenant and that promise with
regard to the seed is the Lord Jesus.
We find that Paul mentions that in the book of Galatians.
If you want to take a moment to turn there, we referenced this last week briefly and we'll
reference it again this evening.
We see in Galatians chapter number 3 that as the reference to Genesis chapter number
15 in verse number 6 is seen in Galatians 3 and verse number 6.
The Bible says even as Abraham believed God and it was accounted to him for righteousness.
And we find it in verse number 16 of Galatians 3.
It says,
Now to Abraham and his seed were the promises made.
He saith not unto seeds as of many, but as of one, and to thy seed, which is Christ.
And so we understood as we studied through the 15th chapter of the book of Genesis over
these last few weeks and really over the last few chapters of the book of Genesis that this
promise has been given to Abram and it's a seed and it's a land and we focus upon that
seed and we see that as Christ.
Now you understand as you go from this portion of scripture in Genesis 12 through 15 and
look at how God zeros in.
Remember he starts in Genesis with creation.
He looks at the creation of man, all of the different groups of people.
You see the tower of Babel, the spreading of the people and so on and so forth.
And then God zeros in upon Abram and the Hebrew people and that will be the direction
in which the book of Genesis and really all of scripture begins to travel.
There are references that are provided to us with regard to other people groups as they
interact with God's people.
But why?
What's the significance?
Well, that's the seed.
That's where Messiah would come from.
come through the line the messianic line and the significance of all that you
read of and you think about the spiritual warfare that were engaged in
the spiritual battles that Satan has spent all of those years as recorded in
the Old Testament to try to defile and destroy that line so that that Messiah
would not be able to come. Why is it that that Haman so hated Mordecai? Was it
just because of Mordecai? Why was it that Haman wouldn't be satisfied with
simply killing the one that would not bow down? No, he wanted to destroy all the
Jews and you see the enemy, Satan, working to try to destroy the promised line, the
seed. There's also the significance with regard to the land. God had promised them
this land and you find the territorial battles that have taken place not only
biblically but even still to this very day. The battles that take place with
regard to the land that God promised to his people Israel and you find that
throughout the scriptures the the borders of Israel, the children of
Israel, they were large and they shrunk and they were all kind of all over the
place throughout their history depending on the particular kings and so on and so
forth. They never had really reached the fullness of the potential of what God
outlines in Genesis chapter number 15. The closest they ever came is during the
reign of David and that of Solomon. In fact if you look during the time of
Solomon's reign when God had given rest and after the all of those amazing
things that had taken place during of course the reign of David and then
entering into the reign of Solomon that God had given rest from from those
enemies and so on and so forth. But the fullness of this promise with regard to
the territory that is described in Genesis 15 and verse number 18 will
ultimately be fulfilled during the millennial reign of Christ. And so you
begin to see that all the way back in Genesis chapter number 15 how you see so
many years of time that are being referenced not only with regard to the
people of Israel, the events leading to the possession of the land, the time of
Abraham's life of course and his depart his death, but also we see the fullness
of the millennial reign of Christ that seed that is mentioned being Christ in
Galatians chapter 3 and during the time in which he will physically rule
and reign on this earth for a thousand years. Now we're not there yet we've not
reached the millennium of course we're going to have the rapture of the church
will take place and the Great Tribulation and then the millennial reign
of Christ. It will happen and we don't know the time in which it will happen we
know that it's at least seven years and a few moments away because there's seven
years of tribulation and the return of the Lord could happen at any moment and
and that's when that timeline will begin. And so we find that here as we look at
this passage of Scripture what an exciting opportunity to see that in the
life of Abram that God has given these promises he told her about the seed he
took him out he said look up in the stars look toward the heaven if you can
number them and he says so shall thy seed be. Then he says by the way I'm the
Lord that brought you out of the earth the Chaldees to give thee this land to
inherit it and Abram says whereby shall I know that I shall inherit it and God
gives them this sign after he reveals these details he gives them this sign by
he alone passing through those pieces that were divided showing us the fact
that this is an unconditional covenant. These things were not based upon
anything that Abram would do anything that he would offer any gifts that he
would bring and we understand that salvation for a child of God is all
based on the grace and mercy of God and it's important that we wrap up in that
fashion this evening. We understand the Bible says for by grace are you saved
through faith and that not of yourselves is the gift of God not of works lest any
man should boast and we understand this evening that our God is gracious and he
is merciful he's full of compassion and he is the Savior of the world and the
reality this evening is that as we think about the truth of salvation we ought to
rejoice in the fact that it has everything to do with what the Lord
Jesus Christ did on the cross of Calvary apart from anything that you could offer
why because I can't there's nothing good enough that I could do to earn his
merit to earn his salvation it is the gift of God not by not by our works of
righteousness the Bible says that the wages of sin is death but the gift of
God is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord I'm so thankful that Jesus said
on the cross of Calvary it is finished he paid for your sin and for my sin he
paid for the sin of the world and we find that the truth of salvation the
promise that God has given with regard to salvation in like manner to this
promise that he gave to Abram in Genesis chapter number 15 it has nothing
to do with anything that we would do other than just simply believing and
receiving and receive that great promise that he said for whosoever shall call
upon the name of the Lord shall be saved I'm so thankful for the truth of
salvation this evening as we understand the foundational aspect I understand it
was more teachy this evening but as we understand the foundational the the
impact of Genesis chapter 15 it will help us to understand the events that
take place within the next pages of Scripture not only here in the book of
Genesis but throughout the whole of Scripture with regard to this covenant
that God made with Abram it is a significant event that helps if we don't
fully comprehend and understand this event in Genesis 15 it really hinders us
from a proper understanding of future things that will be detailed and dealt
with throughout the Word of God and that's why the book of Genesis is so
foundational and I believe that's why the book of Genesis is under such great
attack because it's so foundational to understanding the whole of Scripture let
us pray together father we love you this evening we thank you for loving us we
thank you for the Word of God the truth contained therein we thank you for this
truth that you gave us in Genesis 15 that sets the firm foundation with
regard to your dealings with the the children of Israel with the Hebrews the
Jewish race and as we begin to study throughout the rest of this book and
even the whole of Scripture and we see just your interactions and your dealings
and Lord we thank you for this covenant that was made with Abram on this
particular day and in its significance I pray that you would help us to rejoice
in the fact that you are eternal and omniscient that you are able to with
specific detail lay out events that will happen generations to come even as we
see here in the life of Abram because you are eternal and because you are
omniscient I pray God that you'd help us to rest in that and help us to find just
have our faith increased and to find great encouragement through those truths
this evening I pray God that if there's one that has never trusted the Lord
Jesus Christ as their personal Savior they do not know for sure if they were
denied today that heaven is their home I pray God that they'd understand the
truth of salvation redemption through the blood of Christ that Jesus Christ
the Son of God went to that cruel cross he suffered and bled and died he was
buried in a borrowed tomb and he rose in victory conquering sin death in the
grave he said he declared it is finished and I pray this evening that if there's
one under the sound of my voice whether they're here present in our auditorium
or they're watching online that they never have trusted Christ as their
Savior that they would understand the promise of redemption the gift of God
which is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord and that today is the
day of salvation the Bible declares for whosoever shall call upon the name of
the Lord shall be saved have your will and way in these moments of invitation
and we'll thank you for all that you'll do for it's in Christ's name we pray