if you're taking notes, I would say this, that the response of the eunuch, his response
to Philip reveals humility. His response reveals humility. The question in verse number 30
is a very important question. It is a question in which opens the door for this conversation.
And the question is very simple. The Bible tells us that Philip ran to this chariot,
the Spirit of God told him to go there, and he heard this eunuch reading. Obviously, he's
reading out loud, he's reading audibly, he's reading the prophet Isaiah. As we go through
the passage, we see that he's reading Isaiah 53. What a great passage of Scripture. And
he's reading this portion of Scripture, and Philip says to this eunuch, do you understand?
Understandest thou what thou readest? Now, I've said that his response reveals humility,
because what he says is, how can I except some man should guide me? That is a response
of humility, is it not? Certainly, it would be easy for a man of his position, we've mentioned
already that verse 27 gives us some insight to his position, that he could have brushed
it off and said, I'm good, I understand, even though he didn't. Right? We've been in situations
like that. We have encountered experiences in our lives where people will say that they
understand something, and they really don't. They just don't want to be embarrassed. They
feel like it would be an embarrassment if they reveal that they don't understand something.
But the reality is that that's pride, and it hinders our ability to be taught. And so
his response to the question that is asked reveals humility, and we find that this man,
this Ethiopian eunuch, can you imagine how things would have been so different in his
life if he said to Philip, if his response in verse number 31, instead of being one of
humility, was one of pride, and he said, I'm good, carry on, there's no need for you to
be here. He would have continued on being ignorant of the truth that he was reading.
Right? It would have been tragic. And so his response of humility leads to the opportunity
for teaching. We find that as we think about this idea of having a teachable spirit, I
would say that it's of utmost importance that we are humble, that we have humility in our
lives. The Bible speaks much about humility. The Bible tells us that God resisteth the
proud, but He gives grace to the humble. James and Peter both tell us that. We find that
the Bible tells us in 1 Peter, right in that same section when he talks about God resisting
the proud and giving grace to the humble, in the 5th chapter, he mentions this, that
we are to be clothed in humility. And the reality is that the Bible tells us, if you
read the book of Proverbs, there are many references with regard to pride in the book
of Proverbs, and God hates pride. He hates pride. And we find that this response reveals
humility and how important it is that we, as we consider the subject matter of having
a teachable spirit, that it begins with humility. It begins with a recognition of, I don't understand
and I need to be taught. Right? None of us have arrived. None of us are at a place where
we have all knowledge. No, God has all knowledge, and we need to continue to have that teachable
spirit, and humility is so necessary. Notice the response. It continues in verse number
31. He says, how can I except some man should guide me? I would say this, as you look at
the remainder of verse number 31, it says, and he desired, Philip, that he would come
up and sit with him. So, his response reveals humility, but I would say that his invitation
reveals desire. His invitation reveals desire. So, it's one thing to have the humility and
say, no, I don't understand what I'm reading. He says, how can I except some man should
guide me? But the remainder of the 31st verse here in Acts 8 says, he desired, Philip, that
he would come up and sit with him. I like that desire. And it reveals, this invitation
reveals that desire we mentioned as we looked in our very first lesson of the subject matter
of teach me, how the plea of the psalmist when he cries out, teach me, that plea reveals
desire. It reveals that I want to learn. I want to be taught. You don't say, teach me
to someone if you don't want to learn, right? It reveals a desire to learn something. Again,
it's not a use of flattery where the psalmist is just using some cliche of teach me and
using flattery. No, I believe as you look through the references in the book of Psalms
that the psalmist is earnestly desiring, he's longing to be taught.
I want you to think about this when you think about the invitation of this eunuch, the response
revealing the humility, his invitation to have him come up into the chariot reveals
that desire. I want you to think about this truth this evening that the Lord Jesus Christ
in the book of Matthew, we looked at this last week, he says he offers an invitation
to come unto me, and he tells them, and learn of me. Now, think about this. If Jesus offers
an invitation that we would come and learn of him, but then we also have that teachable
spirit that we're saying, Lord, teach me, man, we're in a really good spot to learn.
Wouldn't you agree? Because Jesus wants to teach us. The Holy Spirit of God who indwells
us is the teacher, one of his ministries, and so we're there in that place. I want
you to notice that if you look down to verse number 34, and we'll catch it back up in
verse 32, but I just want to jump down here for a moment, look in verse number 34, it
says, and the eunuch answered Philip and said, I pray thee. You see that phrase? He says,
I pray thee, of whom speaketh the prophet this of himself? Excuse me, let me read it.
It says, I pray thee, of whom speaketh the prophet this, of himself or of some other
man? I would say this, that this phrase, when he says, I pray thee, it gives us more insight
to his desire to be taught, correct? And you notice when he makes the statement in verse
number 34, when he says, of whom speaketh the prophet this, of himself or of some other
man, he's acknowledging his ignorance. He's acknowledging his confusion. He doesn't know,
but he wants to be taught. He has humility. He has desire. I don't know how many days
ago it was, but in the devotional book that we've distributed for this week, there was
an illustration about a car that was broken down, and the man that had his car broken
down is on the side of the road there, and a man comes by and offers help, and he says,
no, I'm okay, I got it. And the one that offered the help was Henry Ford. And who better to
have provided assistance to the individual than Henry Ford himself, right? But the reality
is that the man that had been broken down, he didn't have humility and desire like we
see here with the eunuch. He was like, no, I'm okay. I don't need your help. Okay. Henry
Ford went on his way. It's interesting when you look at the illustration that was used
in that book. Henry Ford didn't insist on helping. Let me say this. God doesn't…
I believe that He teaches us some things. He takes us through some various schools of
learning, and we'll look at that as we go through this series over the next several
weeks and months. But the reality is that if we're going to learn, we have to have
a teachable spirit. And how do we develop that teachable spirit? I would say that humility
and desire are keys to being teachable. If you have no desire to learn, you don't have
a teachable spirit, right? Have you ever met someone that has no desire to learn? And they…
I remember when I was coaching Little League Baseball with Joseph when he was a little
younger, and we're out there in coaching. And some of those kids, you're trying to teach
them how to play baseball, and they don't want to learn. They're there because their
parents want them to play baseball. And you're trying to teach them, and they're doing,
you know, it looks like they're doing ballet moves out in the outfield instead of paying
attention to what's going on in the field. And you're saying, this kid's going to get
hurt, you know? And just no desire. We can look at that in a whole host of avenues or
arenas this evening and speak about it. We're looking, as we think about this subject matter
in this series of Teach Me, looking at it from a spiritual perspective. I want to learn
the Word of God. I want to learn who God is. I want to know Him in a more intimate way.
I want to have that teachable spirit. It begins with humility. Desire is essential. And let
me say this, as we continue looking through this passage of Scripture, I would say that
His profession and His baptism reveal understanding or reveal learning has taken place. Now, look
at it, if you will, in verse number 32. The Bible says this, the place of the Scripture
which He read was this, He was led as a sheep to the slaughter, and like a lamb done before
His shearer, so opened He not His mouth. In His humiliation, His judgment was taken away,
and who shall declare His generation, for His life is taken from the earth? This is
Isaiah 53, and the eunuch answers,
Philip as they're looking at this place where he was reading in the Old Testament,
and he says, as we made note of a moment ago,
I pray thee, of whom speaketh the prophet this, of himself or of some other man?
I love verse number 35.
The Bible says, then Philip opened his mouth and began at the same Scripture
and preached unto him Jesus.
Amen?
So as we think about the reading and we think about the confusion and the ignorance
that is evidenced through the questions that are given in verse number 34,
the eunuch offers up these questions because there's confusion, there's ignorance.
He doesn't know, but he wants to know.
He says, I pray thee.
He's already demonstrated the humility.
How can I except some man should guide me?
He's demonstrated his desire.
And so now with that humility and that desire, with that teachable spirit,
now Philip is able to go up into the chariot,
he's able to see the passage of Scripture that he's reading,
and he's able to start in that same passage, in that same Scripture,
and preach unto him Jesus.
I think that it would be fair to say that preaching is not always teaching,
and teaching is not always preaching,
but oftentimes preaching includes teaching.
Amen? Is that fair?
The Bible in the book of Ezra teaches us, it provides really an outline of preaching,
that you read the Word of God distinctly, you give the sense of it,
and enable the people to understand it.
So we understand here that as he's preaching unto him Jesus,
that we could say that he's teaching him.
He's teaching him the truth.
He's teaching him what it is that he's reading in Isaiah 53,
and the Bible tells us in verse number 36,
I want you to notice that the Bible says they went on their way.
I'm not sure how long the preaching was in verse number 35.
I don't know how long Philip took to explain these biblical truths to this Ethiopian eunuch,
but for however long it took, they were there, and it says they went on their way,
and they came unto a certain water.
I want you to notice again the question that is asked of the eunuch.
The eunuch says to Philip,
See, here is water. What doth hinder me to be baptized?
Is that not, again, a revelation of humility and desire?
He's asking a question.
You know, when we ask questions, sometimes we sit in places,
we're sitting in a classroom having some type of interaction.
Maybe it's not even in a group setting,
but sometimes we're embarrassed to ask questions,
and the reality is that there are times in which we're embarrassed to ask questions,
especially in a group setting because we don't want somebody else to think we don't know something.
You know what I've learned over the years?
Many times there are other people in the room that have the same question that you have,
and many times they don't want to ask it, and neither do you.
So the question never gets asked, and the teaching never can take place,
and the reality is that asking questions is important.
We should ask ourselves questions as we read the Word of God.
We should go through the Scriptures,
and as we go through and evaluate and study the Word of God,
we're asking ourselves, What does this mean to me?
What is it that God's trying to show me?
What is He trying to teach me?
Why did God include this in the Word of God?
Have you ever asked yourself that question?
There'll be times I'm reading the Scriptures and I'm saying,
God, I understand that this is Your Word and You've included this,
but help me to understand why You've included this.
Why is it that this piece of information, this portion of Scripture,
why did You deem it necessary to be in the Word of God?
Not that I'm questioning God or His authority for doing so,
but I want to learn why it's there.
I want to have a better understanding.
And so, evidently, as His time in Jerusalem,
the Bible tells us in verse number 27,
they had come to Jerusalem for the worship.
And so, obviously, there was some level of exposure
that this man had to baptism in order for him to ask the question.
And he says, Here is water.
What doth hinder me to be baptized?
And great truth that Philip reveals.
Again, we've used this many times over the years.
You look at the truth of not only the mode of baptism,
but who it is.
Who is the candidate for baptism?
We don't just baptize anyone because they want to get baptized.
We don't baptize infants.
We don't baptize people just to baptize them.
We understand that it's believers' baptism by immersion.
We understand that.
That's why baptism is so important.
That's why, for many generations,
Baptist people were referred to as Anabaptists, re-baptizers.
Why? Because we would reject the baptism of the state church
because we don't believe in infant or paedo-baptism.
And you see that here in this portion of Scripture.
He says, What doth hinder me to be baptized?
Philip doesn't just say, Oh, if you want to, let's go.
No, he answers, he says in verse number 37,
Philip said,
And notice what this eunuch says.
He answered and said,
Isn't that a great profession?
A great declaration?
I would say to you that he didn't have the same opinion
in verse number 30.
He didn't know.
Right?
Of whom speaketh the prophet this?
Of himself or of some other man?
And Philip preaches unto him Jesus
and he shows him how that he is the Messiah
and that he came and he bled and he died
and he was buried and he rose in victory
and he is the Lamb that was slain
before the foundation of the world.
And you think about the preaching.
Again, I don't know all that is contained
within the preaching because the Bible simply says
that he preached unto him Jesus,
but obviously because of that humility
and because of that desire,
there was some learning that took place.
Amen?
A teachable spirit leads to learning.
Right?
If we have a teachable spirit,
it's going to lead to learning.
It's going to result in learning.
So we find that he says,
I believe that Jesus Christ is the Son of God.
The Bible says that he commanded
for the chariot to stand still
and they went down both into the water,
both Philip and the eunuch,
and he baptized him.
Isn't that exciting?
A man that was confused.
A man that was ignorant of the truth.
He was reading.
He had been in Jerusalem.
He was reading the Old Testament.
But God in His grace and His mercy,
He takes Philip and He says,
here's where you need to go.
There's the chariot where you need to go.
And Philip obeyed.
And he's reading.
He says, do you understand what you're reading?
Understandest thou what thou readest?
How can I except some man should guide me?
And by the end of the interaction,
the man is saved and the man is baptized.
It's precious.
It says in verse number 39,
and when they were come up out of the water,
the Spirit of the Lord caught away Philip
that the eunuch saw him no more.
But notice the last phrase of verse number 39,
and he went on his way rejoicing.
That's a blessed ending to this portion of Scripture
that he went on his way rejoicing.
The Bible tells us in verse number 40
about Philip and we see where he is
and what's going on there.
But when you think about the subject matter
in which we're dealing with this evening
of a teachable spirit,
and understanding how is it that I can
develop a teachable spirit.
As I evaluate my life, are there some things
that would hinder me from being teachable?
Are there times in my life
where I'm not teachable?
where I have that response of pride
instead of that response of humility?
Are there times in which
I do not demonstrate the desire to learn?
I'm not eager to learn.
We find here that as this Ethiopian eunuch
illustrates in my mind
an example of someone that has a teachable spirit,
and I hope as we've looked at the passage this evening
that you too would agree that he demonstrates,
he illustrates for us someone
that has a teachable spirit,
we'd say, I need to have a teachable spirit.
And the result of having the teachable spirit
is that learning has taken place.
We've mentioned that part of our series
will conclude at the end of several weeks,
months of studying this subject matter,
will conclude with a lesson
on evaluating our growth,
evaluating our learning.
How can we evaluate?
Have we learned?
The reality is that if we looked at this passage of Scripture,
we could evaluate by his own life
that yes, there was learning that took place.
And he responded properly to truth.
And he responded, he accepted that truth,
and he made his profession,
he followed the Lord entirely.
baptism, and we find that he went on his way rejoicing. The Scriptures are mute to anything
else about this man. You can read a variety of historical accounts of the influence and
impact that this man had, and the region is a return back, and there's some good information
out there. The Scriptures, however, are silent as to the man. But I'd like to think that
this man's like a missionary, amen? And he went on his way rejoicing. Why do you think
he was rejoicing? Because he had learned, right? He went for the purpose of worship.
You can see there's a desire there, no doubt, as he's going to Jerusalem, and you find that
even as they're leaving that he's still reading the Word of God. He had not yet found out
the truth while he was there in Jerusalem, and he's reading, he's desiring to know. And
God graciously and mercifully gives Philip the direction to go and to be with this man,
and he learns, and he goes on his way rejoicing. Listen, when we learn, we ought to rejoice,
because we understand that God is teaching us His Word, and we speak about it from the
perspective of spiritual learning and spiritual growth. The reality is that we are to grow
in grace and knowledge of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ. When we use that phraseology
of grow in grace and knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ, that's, we're learning. We're
growing. We know more about Him, about the Lord, now than we did when we first got saved,
and as we walk with Him, as we've had our theme this year, walking in the light, the more that
we walk with Him and the closer we draw to Him, the more we learn, and the more we apply that
truth that we're learning, and then we have the opportunity, as we looked at our lesson from last
week, we think about two purposes for learning, the application of truth, but then the dissemination
of truth, and that's why I say that this man is like a missionary. He went on his way rejoicing.
I think he wanted to tell some other people. Again, as we would look at some historical
records that are provided, we see that there are many accounts that would give testimony
to that end. Again, the Scriptures are mute to it, but we find that he went on his way
rejoicing. It's a wonderful thing to be informed. Amen? I mentioned, as we study the Book of
1 John on Sunday mornings, that God wants us to know some things. The word know, in some form,
is used repeatedly in the Book of 1 John, but here's something interesting, and maybe for you
it will happen as well, but sometimes as we kind of focus on something, all of a sudden you start
seeing it in other places. Whatever happened to you, you focus on one thing, and then you kind of
see it in other places, right? And so, I've been speaking and preaching in 1 John, and I've been
studying and preparing and talking about, no, no, no, God doesn't want us to be ignorant. He wants
us to be informed. He wants us to know. I've mentioned several other passages of Scripture
in the New Testament where God wants us to be informed. Paul says on more than one occasion,
I would not have you to be ignorant, brethren. He wants us to know. I've been reading through
the books of 1 and 2 Kings the last couple of days. You know how many times the Bible talks
about that you would know, and God gives a truth that He wants the people to know? How many times
it was that you would know that there's a God in Israel? Why? Because how often the children of
Israel were guilty of idolatry. Sure, I've read those books, I don't know how many times, but as
I focused on this study of 1 John, all of a sudden that word, know, K-N-O-W, just keeps popping off
of the pages of Scripture. God's always desired for people to know Him. You go all the way back
to the Scriptures, you look at all sorts of accounts of the Scriptures and all of the interactions of
the Lord with His people and how that He would demonstrate to others that they would know who
He is. I think about Pharaoh tonight. Did God not make Himself known to Pharaoh? Sure He did.
Pharaoh begins by saying to Moses, who is that God? I should let you go. Right? That's how he
begins. Through a series of events, God graciously and very distinctly reveals Himself to Pharaoh.
His magicians say this is the finger of God. Right? I think about Nebuchadnezzar, king of Babylon,
mighty man, great power, world empire. Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, they're not going to bow.
We know the story, we know the account. And what does he say? Who is that God? That shall
deliver you out of my hand. Right? Is that what he says? Goes in the fiery furnace,
heats it up way higher than it's supposed to be. The guys that put Him in there die because of the
heat. And then the Bible uses the word, He's astonied, astonished, we would use. Why? Because
He says, didn't we throw three of them in there? Yes, sir. And they were bound. Yes, sir. But
there are four and they're walking around and the fourth is like unto the Son of God. At the end of
that event, did Nebuchadnezzar have an understanding of who God is? He made a great declaration that
no one could speak amiss about their God. And so this evening, as we think about this truth of
having a teachable spirit, God wants us to know Him. He wants us to know this book, and He is the
divine teacher and He's offered to us an invitation, come and learn of me. And He wants us to learn,
He wants us to grow. The people that are being written to in the book of Hebrews, the Bible
tells us at the end of the fifth chapter, for in the time that you ought to be teachers, you have
a need that one teach you. And He goes on to explain to them that what they needed to be
taught were the basics of the Word of God, the first principles. He was not speaking that to
honor them. It was spoken to their shame because they were supposed to be learning at the time
you're now supposed to be teaching, but you have need that one teach you. And so as we think about
our Christian lives, when we think about our walk with Christ, it is God's design and God's plan
that we grow, that we learn. But what hinders learning is not having a teachable spirit. So
this evening, when we think about all of the ways that God's going to teach us, and we'll look at
several examples over the next several weeks, the thought of this lesson, I hope, will be impactful.
Because if I do not develop a teachable spirit in my life, learning is not going to take place. If I
constantly say, I know, I know, I know, I know, I know, if I have no desire, and we see the humility
and the desire of the Ethiopian eunuch, how can I except some man should guide me? He desired
Philip to come up into his chariot with him. They read the passage, and then Philip preached Jesus
unto him. What a great passage of Scripture. I believe a great illustration of someone who had
a teachable spirit. I know that God would help us, that we, too, would have a teachable spirit.
Let's pray. Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. Thank you for this biblical example
tonight, the life of this Ethiopian eunuch. It's a familiar passage of Scripture, perhaps looking
at it afresh and from a slightly different perspective or angle. I pray tonight that we
would acknowledge this teachable spirit of this man and that we would desire that we, too, would
have a teachable spirit. God, you'd help us to develop a teachable spirit in our lives. Help us
to learn of you. Help us to grow in grace and knowledge for Lord and Savior Jesus Christ. Help
it to not be said of us that in the time that you ought to be teachers, you have need that one teach
you. Help us, God, to grow and to learn. Bless our time of prayer. We do thank you for the privilege
of prayer. Thank you that you hear and answer. You're able to do exceeding abundantly above all
that we ask or think. Bless now and we'll thank you for it. In Christ's name we pray. Amen.