Genesis chapter number 32, and this is, it's been a long time since we've been in the
book of Genesis.
It was last, right before our missions conference last year, and we had Sunday evening before
missions conference in the book of Genesis, and then we had missions conference and then
got into the summer months, and I've been dealing with, since then, Ask the Pastor.
There were a lot of questions that were submitted for Ask the Pastor, and it took a whole lot
longer than I expected.
I actually didn't even answer all of them.
I saved a handful for this summer, and we'll have that as a summer Sunday evening series
again this upcoming summer.
But this is message number 71 in the book of Genesis, and it's back from May when we
finished up chapter number 31, and so as we look at chapter number 32 in the title for
the message this evening, as you see on the back of the bulletin, is Jacob prepares to
meet Esau.
Before we get into the passage here in Genesis chapter number 32, it's important for us to
understand, really, the backdrop and all that had taken place in previous years.
We understand that the circumstances surrounding Jacob's departure from Beersheba were marked
with much tension.
You'll remember that Esau was to be blessed by Isaac.
It was, that was the desire.
Isaac had given the instruction for Esau to go out and to bring him some venison, like
he enjoyed, and that he would give him a blessing.
And we know that through a series of events that Jacob was the one that received the blessing.
In fact, if you turn back to Genesis chapter 27, I'll mark a couple of verses as we study
through and kind of catch up to where we are here in Genesis chapter number 32.
But we find that Jacob receives the blessing.
You'll remember that Esau comes in, and Esau wept.
He was very bothered by the situation, and he desired for a blessing.
And Esau was angry because of what had transpired, and Esau intended to slay Jacob after the
days of mourning for Isaac were fulfilled, excuse me, for Jacob there.
The Bible tells us that Isaac and, or Esau and Jacob, that situation, there's obviously
some tension there.
And notice in verse number 41, Esau said this, it says, Esau hated Jacob because of the blessing
wherewith his father blessed him, and Esau said in his heart, the days of mourning for
my father at hand, notice what he says, then will I slay my brother Jacob.
And so these words of Esau, her elder son, were told to Rebekah, and she sent and called
Jacob her younger son and said unto him, behold, thy brother Esau, as touching thee, doth comfort
himself, purposing to kill thee.
Now therefore, my son, obey my voice and arise, notice what she says, flee thou to
Laban my brother, to Haran, and it says this in verse 44, and tarry with him, notice this,
a few days, until thy brother's fury turn away.
We find that Rebekah provides this instruction to Jacob.
She was also the one that provided the instruction to Jacob with regard to providing the meal
by which he would receive the blessing.
And she says, flee to my brother Laban and go for a few days.
Jacob departed as he was instructed.
We find that in Genesis chapter number 28, he's given instruction from Isaac.
Isaac gives him a blessing and charges him with regard to his departure, and Jacob departs
from Beersheba and heads toward Haran.
The Bible tells us that as he was receiving that instruction as he departed, that he then
would be in that region with Laban for 20 years.
A few days, she said, 20 years, that's a long time, that's a very long time.
We find that after 20 years, he's then going to depart from Paddan Aram, and as he's planning
to return to the land of his fathers per the instruction of the Lord, we find that the
departure from Paddan Aram was also marked by some excitement.
We read of and studied in Genesis chapter number 31 as we ended our study last May in
this chapter, and remember that after they departed, that Laban comes and he gathers
and he finds them and he comes and there's a confrontation that takes place.
And God had appeared to Laban and told Laban that he was not to do anything to Jacob, he's
not to cause him any harm and what have you.
And so we find that at the end of that confrontation and all that interaction that took place in
chapter 31, we then come to chapter number 32 where Jacob is still leaving, he's left
Paddan Aram, he's heading back to the land of his fathers, and he's planning to reunite
with Esau.
Twenty years earlier, Esau said, I'm going to mourn the death of my father and I'm going
to kill my brother.
That's what he intended to do.
Twenty years had passed and now Jacob is preparing to meet his brother.
Notice in verse number one of Genesis 32, the Bible says, and Jacob went on his way
and the angels of God met him.
When Jacob saw them, he said, this is God's host and he called the name of that place
Mahanaim.
And Jacob sent messengers before him to Esau, his brother, under the land of Seir, the country
of Edom.
And he commanded them saying, thus shall you speak unto my lord Esau, thy servant Jacob
saith thus, I have sojourned with Laban and stayed there until now.
And I have oxen and asses, flocks and men's servants, and women's servants, and I have
sent to tell my lord, notice the way it says, that I may find grace in thy sight.
We'll read down through this passage of Scripture this evening to verse number 23, we'll deal
with the remainder of chapter 32 next Sunday evening, but as we're looking at this text
of Scripture, if you're taking notes this evening, I want you to notice number one,
the preparation of Jacob.
The preparation of Jacob.
In the first eight verses of Genesis 32, God provides for us a record of Jacob's preparation
as he plans for this meeting, this reunion with his brother Esau.
We find that in verse number three that the Bible tells us that Jacob sent messengers
before him.
He's trying to prepare the way.
He's got these servants, these messengers that are going to take word to his brother
Esau, and we find that as he sends these messengers, that he sends them with a specific message.
In verses four and five, we find that as he would give these servants of his, these messengers,
this specific message that he records for us, or God records for us, how it is that
he commanded his servants, his messengers, to bring this specific message to Esau.
Notice if you will, how Jacob said to refer to Esau.
Notice in verse number four, and he commanded them saying, thus shall you speak unto my
Lord Esau.
You notice how he says to refer to Esau is my Lord, but also notice how he refers to
himself.
In verse number four, thy servant Jacob.
He says, thus shall you speak unto my Lord Esau, thy servant Jacob saith thus, I have
sojourned with Laban and stayed there until now.
We notice, of course, as you would look back at the blessing that God had given to Isaac,
and we mentioned very briefly of that interaction in chapter number 27, but if you were to look
back there in that passage of Scripture, and notice in verse number 33 of Genesis 27, the
Bible says that Isaac trembled very exceedingly and said, who?
This is when Esau comes in.
He says, where is he that hath taken venison and brought it me, and I have eaten of all
before thou camest, and have blessed him, yea, and he shall be blessed.
When Esau heard the words of his father, he cried with a great and exceeding bitter cry,
and said unto his father, bless me, even me also, my father.
And he said, thy brother came with subtlety, and hath taken away thy blessing, and he said,
is not he rightly named Jacob?
For he hath supplanted me these two times, he took away my birthright, and behold, now
he hath taken away my blessing, and he said, hast thou not reserved a blessing for me?
Notice what it says in verse 37, and Isaac answered and said unto Esau, behold, I have
made him, who's him?
Jacob, right?
I've made him, what's it say?
Thy Lord.
That's what it says.
And all his brethren have I given to him for, what's it say?
Servants, is that what your Bible says?
That's what my Bible says.
My Bible says in verse 37, follow along with me there in Genesis 27, verse 37, Isaac answered
and said unto Esau, Esau says, dad, is there not a blessing for me?
And Isaac says to Esau, behold, I have made him, your brother, Jacob, I have made him
thy Lord.
And all his brethren, that includes Esau, correct?
Yes or no?
Talk to me tonight.
Absolutely, right?
He says, and all his brethren have I given to him for what?
Servants.
But what does Jacob say to his messengers to go to Esau with?
He says, refer to Esau as my Lord, and refer to myself as thy servant.
That's actually reverse of the blessing and the instruction that God gave in Genesis 27.
I do see, however, a measure of humility within the life of Jacob here in this text of Scripture.
Jacob, of course, is fearful.
He's going back.
home and Esau is ready to kill him, right? Last time he was there, why did he flee in
the first place? He fled in the first place because Esau is going to kill him. So he fled.
Now God, and we'll look at this in just a few moments, now God has divinely directed
for Jacob to return. But he knows in so doing that he is going to meet Esau. And the last
time he was there, Esau is going to kill him. And so he's concerned. I believe that he's
genuine in this in Genesis chapter 32 when he's sending these messengers with this message.
But we have to understand that God is sovereign. And God gave that blessing and God was in
control. And we find here that he sends this, not only does he give instruction with regard
to how to refer to Esau, how to refer to himself, he tells us in verse number five, he mentions
about the blessing of the Lord and how much substance he had received. And during that
20 years where they had been separated one from the other, how God had blessed him. And
he records that in verse number five. But then we find that he has this desire that
he might find grace in the sight of Esau. The messengers returned to Jacob, according
to verse number six. And we find that as these messengers returned to Jacob, that they bring
him a message that he's not really too excited to receive. For the Bible tells us that they
returned to Jacob saying, we came to thy brother Esau, notice what it says, and also he cometh
to meet thee and 400 men with him. We know the entirety of this passage. Many of us are
familiar with Genesis 32 and 33. And we see in chapter 33 the reunion. What a reunion
it is, by the way. But I want you to think about Jacob just for a moment. These messengers
come back and they say, oh, we went with the message that you gave us to give. And by the
way, when we went, Esau was coming to meet you. And oh, by the way, he's got 400 men
with him. What are you thinking if you're Jacob? Probably thinking he's coming to kill
you. I mean, that's a natural response of interpreting those circumstances that he's
seeing. We find that the Bible tells us in verse number seven, then after Jacob received
this news from his messengers, notice what it says, then Jacob was greatly afraid and
distressed. He was greatly afraid and distressed. You know, throughout the Bible, God tells
us over and over to fear not. But the reality is that as human beings, there are times that
we fear. It's an emotion that we have. God made us. He knows that we're emotional people.
And he knows that one of the emotions that we have is fear. There are things that happen
in your life. There are things that happen in my life. There are things that happen in
the lives of those that are recorded for us in the pages of Scripture that those circumstances
led to fear. They led to fear. The sin is not so much in being afraid. The sin is what
happens after that immediate fear. Do I stay? Do I remain in a state of fear? Do I allow
fear to control me? Do I allow fear to trump what God has said in his Word? Or do I have
the eye of faith and do I trust the Lord? Do I turn to God? Do I trust him in the moment
when fear creeps in? I remember, and I think I did not do any research on this, but I would
assume the company still exists. But I remember while I was in high school, there was a particular
clothing line that made clothes that we would, a lot of things sports-wise, attire. And it
was called No Fear. No Fear. And they'd have certain things on them. And I played baseball
very competitively. And in Nevada, as a baseball, our team, we won state playoffs. And my sophomore
year we were very competitive. And we used to have a shirt that we had made up that said
No Fear Serpent Baseball because we were the Mineral County Serpents. That was the name
of our team. That was our mascot. But the reality is that as many times as people want
to put no fear on things and talk about it, everybody that I know has gotten some kind
of fear. Right? People that say, I'm not afraid of anything. You're lying, man. I'm just telling
you. You're lying. The sin is not in being afraid. It's how we handle it. What happens?
Listen, Jacob was greatly afraid and distressed. I would argue that most of us, if we were
in this same situation, given the same exact circumstances, where we knew that somebody
wanted to kill us, we were separated from them for 20 years, and we're going to reunite
with them, and we find out they're coming to meet us with 400 people, I'm afraid. I'm
afraid. But I want you to notice what Jacob does. The Bible tells us in verse number 7
that Jacob was greatly afraid and distressed. He divided the people that was with him and
the flocks and herds, the camels, into two bands and said, if Esau come to the one company
and smite it, then the other company which is left shall escape. So we find that he made
some preparations there. But then as we continue through the passage of Scripture, if you're
taking notes, notice number 2 with me. We see number 1, the preparation of Jacob in
verses 1-8. Number 2, the prayer of Jacob in verses 9-12. In verses 9-12, we see that
Jacob responds in prayer. The Bible says in verse number 9, and Jacob said, O God of
my father Abraham and God of my father Isaac, the Lord which said unto me, return unto thy
country and to thy kindred, and I will deal well with thee. Notice what he says in verse
number 10. Again, we see this measure of humility. By the way, in Jacob's life, there was many
times where you did not see much humility in his life, but we find that he says this
in verse number 10 as he continues to pray. I am not worthy of the least of all the mercies
and of all the truth which thou hast showed unto thy servant. For with my staff I passed
over this Jordan, and now I am become two bands. You know, we're not worthy of God's
blessing. We really aren't. God's grace, God's mercy, what a blessing. I'm so thankful
to be adopted in the family of God. I'm so thankful to be a child of the King, join heirs
with Jesus. That's what the Bible tells us. It's all because of His grace, all because
of His mercy. I didn't deserve it. You didn't deserve it. I'm not worthy of it. You're not
worthy of it. But God's grace, God's mercy, His love for us. Jacob says this in verse
number 11, deliver me, I pray thee, from the hand of my brother, from the hand of Esau,
for I fear him, lest he will come and smite me and the mother with the children. Listen,
when you're afraid, God already knows that you're afraid. Does He know everything? Yes.
So what kind of sense does it make for us to be afraid and then act like we're not?
God knows. And He says specifically, I fear him. Deliver me. What is He thinking? No doubt
in my mind that Jacob responds to this situation and he's thinking worst case scenario. By
the way, sometimes some of us, some more than others, are worst case scenario thinkers.
You know what I mean by that? Something happens, it's worst case scenario. I mean, you got
a little sound in your car and it's like the whole thing needs to be replaced, the engine's
just falling out. I mean, the whole deal's just, you know what I mean? Just worst case
scenario kind of people. You got a little ache over here and you're like, oh man, who
knows what the doctor's going to say, right? And sometimes we're just worst case scenario.
That's how Jacob is looking at this situation. He's, I am afraid. But listen, what's he doing?
He's letting God know. He's being transparent with God. Again, God already knows. He knows
your heart. He knows your thoughts. He knows your fears. And so Jacob is coming before
the Lord. He's praying and he's saying, God, I am afraid. I am fearful of this situation.
I don't deserve what you've done in my life. You've been so good to me. But Lord, would
you deliver me from the hand of my brother? For I fear him. Not only is he going to smite
me, but also my family. This is what he's thinking. But I want you to notice that as
he's praying, that he also is recognizing, in this prayer it reveals to us, that Jacob
had a knowledge of what God had said to him. In verse number 9 and also in verse number
12, we find that Jacob understood that God had given him direction. Notice in verse number
9, Jacob said, O God of my father Abraham and God of my father Isaac, notice what he
says, the Lord which said unto me, return unto thy country and to thy kindred. So guess
what? Jacob knew that he was not going back on his own will. God had given him the instruction.
God had given him the direction to go back. In fact, if you turn back to Genesis chapter
number 31 and look at the beginning of the chapter, notice what the Bible says in verse
number 3 of Genesis 31, And the Lord said unto Jacob, Return unto the land of thy fathers
and to thy kindred, and I will give you rest.
be with thee.
That's what God told him to do.
This was not Jacob that was just saying,
listen, things were tough with Laban, no doubt.
No doubt there was a desire for him
to get out of that circumstance,
but God Himself told Jacob, return.
Is Jacob being obedient?
He is.
He's returning.
But he knew what God said.
He knew that God had given him
that divine direction to return
back to the land of his fathers.
He knew that God had promised to be with them
and to bless them.
Notice at the end of verse 9,
he says, return unto thy country
and to thy kindred.
Notice where he says,
and I will deal well with thee.
In verse 12,
and thou saidst,
I will surely do thee good
and make thy seed as the sand of the sea,
which cannot be numbered for multitude.
Jacob is saying, God, you made a promise.
I'm returning based upon your direction in my life.
Now, understand, this isn't being irreverent.
He's simply acknowledging that,
God, you've led me into this,
and now I'm dealing with this perceived,
really it's a perception here,
it's a perceived difficulty that he's going to face.
He makes some assumptions
based upon what the messengers tell him
about Esau and the 400 men that are coming
and the fear that he now has,
but he takes it to the Lord.
And as he prays,
it's revealed to us that he knew what God had told him.
Listen, in the time when it's either real adversity
as we've studied the last two Sunday mornings,
or even perceived adversity,
do not forget God's leadership.
Do not forget God's promises.
That's exactly what the enemy wants us to do.
Sometimes the enemy is going to bring real trial
and real adversity in your life,
like he did with Hezekiah,
like he did with the disciples
that we studied the last two Sunday mornings,
but sometimes, like here in the passage with Jacob,
sometimes it's just a perceived thing,
it's an assumed thing.
And the enemy would like nothing more
for Jacob to be afraid and turn back
and not do what God's told him to do.
The enemy doesn't want you to obey God.
The enemy doesn't want me to obey God.
The enemy will do whatever,
within his power, whatever he's allowed to do,
because he's limited,
he will do whatever he can to keep you and I
from doing the will of God.
Even if it's just an assumed, perceived danger.
Nothing actually had happened.
But he's fearful because of what could happen.
But in that moment, we must see the response of Jacob
and say, listen, we have to remember the promises of God.
Never stop in doubt what God has led us to do by faith.
I preached for an entire year,
our theme was count your blessings,
and we talked about the blessings of the Lord,
and I spent an entire year talking about increase our faith.
And those two years were years in which we sought
to really have our faith increase
by remembering the blessings of God,
remembering the promises of God.
And so often, especially in the year in which we dealt
with increase our faith,
we spoke about the fact that if faith is a flower,
I use the analogy often that doubt is a weed.
And if you want the flower to grow and to flourish,
you must deal with the weeds.
You must deal with doubt.
It doesn't mean that doubt's never gonna come.
It means that when doubt comes, we deal with it,
and we let the promises of God stand.
Because God has given us some promises, and God is faithful.
God has never failed us.
And God made these promises to Jacob.
God gave the direction to Jacob to return.
We read it at the beginning of Genesis 31.
Not only did he say, return unto the land of thy fathers,
but he said, unto thy kindred.
Unto thy kindred, and I will be with thee.
God said that.
Did God not know about Esau being back there?
Sure he did.
God knew all about it.
But God said, return, and I'm gonna be with you.
Jacob was a humble man.
I mentioned already in verse number 10,
where he mentions, I'm not worthy
of the least of all the mercies,
and of all the truth,
which thou hast showed unto thy servant.
You know, we're not worthy, but we're blessed.
We're blessed.
To know the Lord, to have his word, we're blessed.
God's been so good to us.
The blessing of the Lord should not cause us
to become prideful.
In fact, the blessing of the Lord should help us
to remain humble, to thank God for his grace
and for his mercy.
Where would we be without the Lord?
Jacob was a humble man.
We see the preparation, we see the prayer.
I want you to notice a present for Esau.
In verses 13 through 23, we find that Jacob,
after he concludes his prayer,
is gonna lodge in that place that night,
that he gathers together and he prepares a present
for his brother Esau.
At the end of the chapter, and we'll focus on it next week,
in verses 24 through following,
we will speak about the interaction that he had there,
but I want you to notice in these verses of Scripture
what Jacob does.
Says this in verse 13,
and he lodged there that same night
and took of that which came to his hand a present
for Esau, his brother.
We understand that the reason that he desired
to send this present, it tells us in verse number 20,
and say ye, moreover, behold, thy servant Jacob
is behind us, for he said, I will appease him
with the present that goeth before me,
and afterward I will see his face.
Peradventure, he will accept me, accept of me.
In verse number five, we noticed already
that when he sent the messengers out,
he shared with us that truth that he was seeking
to find grace in the sight of Esau.
He now prepares this present that he would deliver
to Esau, and it's desiring to appease him
that he would see his face
and that he would be accepted of him.
I want you to notice this present is detailed for us
in verse number 14 and following.
The Bible says 200 she goats and 20 he goats,
200 ewes and 20 rams, 30 milt camels with their colts,
40 kine, 10 bulls, 20 she asses, and 10 foals,
and he delivered them into the hand of his servants
every drove by themselves and said unto his servants,
pass over before me and put a space
betwixt drove and drove.
He commanded the foremost saying,
when Esau my brother meeteth thee and asketh thee saying,
whose art thou and whither goest thou
and whose art these before thee,
then thou shalt say, they be thy servant Jacob's.
Notice it is a present sent unto my Lord Esau,
and behold also he is behind us.
We find that as he prayed,
as we recorded and noted in verses nine through 12
that Jacob is still a man that I think we can relate to.
We can see that though he's prayed,
he now still is trying to do something in his own hand
to try to appease his brother.
Yeah, sometimes we're guilty of that, aren't we?
We talk about take it to the Lord
and the songwriter said, leave it there.
You ever sing those words and think about
how many times we take something to the Lord,
but we don't really leave it with the Lord.
So we prayed about it.
Cast thy burden upon the Lord and he shall sustain thee.
Casting all your care upon him, why?
For he careth for you.
But there are times, listen, I understand we're humans.
We can relate to Jacob, can we not?
He prayed about it.
He was like, okay, so I prayed,
but now I'm gonna also get this present ready.
I mean, I'm not trying to beat Jacob up
because we do the same kind of thing.
It might not be in the same context
of what Jacob is dealing with,
but what I'm saying this evening is that
I hope that we can relate to Jacob
and that we can learn something from the passage
of Scripture and it's so interesting to me
that the timing and we see God is so good
and he's so sovereign and we think about the theme
that I've been dealing with this year
in the last several weeks and thinking about the truth
that the God of the universe, the God of the creator,
God, that he's our helper.
And we find here that Jacob is,
he's trying to do something.
He's still got that situation of fear going on
in his heart and his life.
Oh, he responds by praying and it's appropriate,
but sometimes we pray,
but then we try to still figure something out.
We pray and then we still try to appease somebody.
That's what Jacob's doing, right?
Is that fair?
That's what's taking place.
And this evening we find that,
I mean, this was a significant gift.
According to verse 13, it was 200 she goats,
20 he goats, 200 ewes and 20 rams.
According to verse number 14,
30 milch camels and their colts, 40 kine,
10 bulls, 20 she asses and 10 foals.
I mean, this was a serious present
that Jacob has.
prepared to send to Esau. What a scene! The Bible tells us in verse number 17
that he commanded the foremost saying, well look back in verse 16, excuse me, he
delivered them into the hands of his servants, every drove by themselves, and
notice the Bible, the drove, the idea of the herds, he says every herd, every drove
by themselves, and sent them to his servants, Passover before me, and put a
space between, drove and drove. So ask this, this wasn't just like one arrival
of servants with all of these herds, no, there was a group of
servants that came with the first herd, there's a little space, and then all of
a sudden there's another group of servants that come with another drove,
and oh, what is all this, a present for you from Jacob? And he says in
verse 17, and he commanded the foremost saying, when Esau my brother meeteth thee
and asketh thee, saying whose art thou, and whither goest thou, and whose are
these before thee, notice what he says, this is what you should say, they be thy
servants Jacob's, it is a present unto my Lord Esau, and behold also he is behind
us. So Jacob was behind, he's sending all this stuff, in verse 19, so commanded he
the second, and the third, and all that followed the drove. So again, you see, can
you see the scene, you see how it's unfolding? I mean Esau, the first
servants come with this portion of the the present that that Jacob has
provided and presented, and we find that he's, what is all this? He's like, oh, this
is a present for you. A little while later, another drove comes, servants, it's a present
for you. It says in verse 19, and so commanded he the second, and the third,
and all that followed the drove, saying, on this manner shall you speak unto Esau
when you find him. So there's more than four droves that went. Can you imagine
the scene? Esau, another group of people come, another group of people come, and
notice verse 20, and say ye moreover, behold thy servant Jacob is behind us.
For he said, I will appease him with the present that goeth before me, and
afterward I will see his face. Peradventure he will accept of me. So
went the present over before him, and himself lodged that night in the company.
As we find in verse 21 that the servants that he had commanded, and all of that
livestock that is recorded in verse 13 and 14, that it went forward as he had
instructed, no doubt he's seeking reconciliation. It says at the end of
verse number 20, peradventure he will accept of me. He said in verse number 5, that I
might find grace in thy sight. It says in verse 22, after it says this in verse 21,
that he lodged that night in the company, that he rose up that night and took his
two wives, his two women servants, and his 11 sons, and passed over the Ford Jabbok,
and he took them and sent them over the brook, and sent over that he had. Why?
Because he wants to protect them. Remember what he said back as you looked
in verse number 11? He said, deliver me, I pray thee, from the hand of my brother,
from the hand of Esau. Why? For I fear him, lest he will come and smite me, but
notice what he says, and the mother with the children. Jacob wasn't simply
concerned about losing his own life, but he was concerned about his wives and his
children. And so, therefore, we see his action in verse number 22 and 23, and how
he rose up and put some space and separated the family in purpose of, hey,
I'm trying to protect. But we're going to look at this passage of Scripture, and I
don't want to get ahead of myself for next week, but the reality is that if you
look at verses 24 through 32, and you find what happens here, the Bible says,
and Jacob was left alone, and there wrestled a man with him until the
breaking of the day. What an encounter Jacob has at the end of this chapter,
and how his life has changed forever. In fact, as you look at the text of
Scripture, and again, I don't want to preach the message for next week, this
evening, but it tells us the end of verse number 31, and he halted upon his thigh.
I look at that end of verse number 31, and I see a limp. It's something that Jacob
would never forget, an encounter that would stay with him the rest of his life.
Every time he would limp, when he leans upon the staff in Egypt to give a blessing,
he remembered the meeting he had with God. I'm thankful for God's grace.
I'm thankful that God knows our frame. I'm thankful that God knows that we're
but flesh. He made us. He knows us, and I'm thankful that though Jacob prayed,
and then Jacob still kept his hand in the mix and presented this present so that he
could appease his brother, I'm thankful that God still met with him.
That's precious to me because God knows where we are. He knows what we're dealing
with, and he loves us, and he ministers to us, and the reality is that Jacob here in
this text of Scripture, he brought his fear before the Lord, but you can tell by his actions
that he still has a measure of fear with regard to this reunion, and in our lives this evening
when we look at Genesis chapter number 32, I hope that we can relate to Jacob. I understand
that the specifics are going to be different. I don't know any of us that have been separated
from a brother for 20 years that wanted to kill us. Circumstances are different, but
God knows your heart, and God knows what you're dealing with, and God knows if you're afraid,
and he knows that anxiety that you're dealing with or whatever that opposition is that you're
facing. When you take it to the Lord, at times in our lives we act just like Jacob.
We pour our heart out before the Lord, and then we leave from the presence of the Lord,
and we go and try to figure something out. We try to take matters into our own hands.
I think if we'd be honest tonight, I'll be honest with you from the pulpit, I've
done it. I think if we'd be honest tonight, at times in our lives we've all done it.
We try to take matters into our own hands. You know what I find out more times than not?
I mess it up. I mess it up. And you know what I find out in my life? God is much better
than I am. God is able to work in hearts I can't. God was able to do something in Esau's
heart that Jacob could never accomplish. God was able to do something in Esau's heart
that no present, no matter the size, the cost, the whatever, that could never do. Why? Because
he's the Creator God. Because he's able. And this evening as we look at this passage
of Scripture and we see the preparation, and we see that Jacob's going to meet Esau, it's
been 20 years. I mean you think about the flood of emotions that would come over Jacob,
and even the initial apprehension of, God, are you sure you want me to go back to that
place? God, do you remember the circumstances that surrounded my departure from there?
But he rose up to go. He left Padonaron. He's heading back. We went, as you told us, and
we found that Esau's coming. He's got 400 men with him. Throw you for a loop sometimes.
Because sometimes we have this idea that if I'm obeying the will of God that there will
be no difficulties. But you know, as many times as I've read the Bible, and I've read
it quite a few times, I've never found the Bible to tell me that. That if I follow God
I'll have no problems, I'll have no difficulties, I'll have no opposition. In fact, I read over
and over, throughout the pages of this book, people that follow the Lord, that because
they follow the Lord, face difficulties. But God knew about them, and God sustained them,
and God blessed them, and God grew them. You know, some of the most fascinating accounts
in the Word of God, if we were to ask the children this evening, I don't like using
the word story when we talk about a biblical account, but many people refer to it as a
Bible story. I like using the word biblical account because its story kind of gives the
idea that it's a story. Something that maybe is just made up. They're biblical accounts.
And I know it's just a little nuance of syntax, but that's just my personal approach to it.
But if we were to ask the kids this evening, or maybe even some of the adults, what biblical
account is your favorite? I'm sure some would speak about David and Goliath. Joseph in the
pit, being delivered, in the prison, being delivered. Maybe Daniel, right? Maybe Daniel
the Den of Lies, maybe Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego.
We could go on and on.
But you know what's amazing about most of those accounts?
We read of those and we find that they face some difficulties, they face some adversity
and some opposition, and God showed Himself mighty.
He revealed His power and we look at Him and say, man, look at what God did.
And then we face a difficulty and say, oh, woe is me.
What might God do in our lives?
How might God show Himself real in your life, in my life?
Jacob's a man just like we are.
He dealt with fear just like we do.
He took it to the Lord and just like we do, we sometimes try to keep our hand in it.
I'm thankful and we'll look at it in its entirety next week that God met with him at the end
of chapter 32.
You read chapter 33, it's a great reunion that takes place between Jacob and Esau.
It's amazing to see the reconciliation between those two men.
It's a blessing.
But I hope that as we look at these, just 23 verses tonight, this preparation of Jacob,
that as we relate to Jacob, say, Lord, would You help us?
Would You help me to be able to see in the life of Jacob what sometimes I even do in
my own life?
And help me to keep my hands out of it.
Let God have His way.
Let God do what only God can do because He is able.
We sing it.
He is able.
I know He is able.
He is able to deliver thee.
We sing the hymn.
Deliver thee from what?
From anything.
Isn't that what Darius said to Daniel?
He said, Daniel, is thy God that thou servest continually, able to deliver thee?
Isn't it amazing that Darius had such a high view of Daniel and of Daniel's God?
Because Daniel was a man that walked with God.
Daniel had a great testimony.
And Daniel returned word, he is.
They've not touched me all night.
Those men that accused, they didn't hit the ground before they were devoured.
Our God is able.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
As we look at this account tonight of Jacob and his preparation, Lord, I pray that in
our lives, we deal with opposition, whether real or assumed.
As we see in the text tonight, this was just an assumed problem, the perception of Jacob.
Worst case scenario thinking.
No doubt in our lives, there are times that we've been guilty of the same thing.
I thank You that Jacob prayed.
Lord, I pray that we'd come to You, seeking Your face.
Lord, I pray that we'd learn from the life of Jacob to leave it with You, to trust You,
to know that You are the God that spoke everything into existence, that You rule and that You
reign, that You're our God and that You're able.
So often, we mess things up by trying to get our own hands into the mix.
Lord, I pray that You would help us to simply trust You, help us to follow You, help us
to obey You.
I pray that in a moment of invitation this evening, that You'd move and work in hearts
and lives as only You can.
Well, thank You for all that You'll do, for it's in Christ's name we pray.