and the Old Testament.
And this is just gonna be a launching point this evening.
And eventually, as we begin here,
we will also end here in Jonah chapter number four,
verses one and two.
And we will continue with our Ask the Pastor series.
And I'll be honest, if you look in the bulletin,
there's a different series,
or title for a message this evening.
And that's because I was gonna preach
a different Ask the Pastor, but the folks aren't here.
And I am not gonna always be able to adjust that,
but it happens that I'm able to adjust it for this evening
and wanna try to make sure.
I didn't wanna be like, well, it's too bad you weren't here,
get the recording, sort of a situation.
So we'll try to adjust that as we can.
So if you've given a question
and you know you're gonna be on vacation,
would you let me know?
And that might help a little bit.
But Jonah chapter four, look at verses one and two.
If you're familiar with the book of Jonah, of course,
we know that Jonah's already been swallowed
by the great fish and he's already been spewed out.
He's already gone to Nineveh and he's preached.
And we come to the fourth chapter.
The people of Nineveh have responded in repentance.
And it says this in verse number one,
but it displeased Jonah exceedingly.
And he was very angry.
Notice it says, he prayed unto the Lord and said,
"'I pray thee, O Lord, was not this my saying
"'when I was yet in my country?
"'Therefore I fled before unto Tarshish, why?
"'For I knew that thou art a gracious God,
"'and merciful, slow to anger, and of great kindness,
"'and repentest thee of the evil.'"
I wanna preach a message tonight
that I've titled from verse number two,
I knew that thou art a gracious God.
The question that was submitted says this,
many skeptics of Christianity say they like the God
of the New Testament,
but not the God of the Old Testament.
How do we, as the people of God,
explain the annihilation of whole people groups
as being in line with a truly loving and merciful God?
And I think it's a great question,
one in which you may have been exposed to,
where someone will question you with regard to
noticing or at least seeming to notice a contradiction
between the Old and New Testament.
And I believe it's a wonderful question.
I hope that you'd bear with me this evening
as a preacher friend of mine says,
I didn't come to church to get out of church,
I came in to get something from church.
And I will admit to you at the very beginning,
it's gonna be a little bit longer of a message this evening
and at least that's what my notes say.
And we hope that we'll get through it
and hope that it makes sense.
But in order to answer the question,
I believe it's imperative for us to understand
and acknowledge all of God's attributes.
And we will not study all of his attributes this evening,
but with dealing with the question specifically,
with regard to God being loving and merciful
and seeing this seeming discrepancy,
we also notice that yes, God is loving and God is merciful
and we ought to rejoice in that.
But at the very same time,
we understand that God is righteous and he is just.
And as we understand the attributes of God
and we understand the character of God
as it's been revealed to us in the word of God,
we would understand that God's attributes
are in perfect harmony.
We as people, as human beings,
our attributes are not always in perfect harmony.
In fact, there are times in which we perhaps had a bad day
and we're more on the side of judgment
than we are on the side of grace or mercy.
And we find that we can fluctuate as human beings,
but God is perfect in his attributes
and they are harmonious.
We find this, it's interesting to me
and you don't need to turn there,
but in Genesis chapter number 18 and verse number 25,
as Abraham is having a conversation with the Lord
regarding the pending destruction of Sodom and Gomorrah,
we find that in that verse of scripture,
Abraham reveals to us and we are given the truth
of two very important aspects of our God.
Number one is this, God is the judge of all the earth.
Number two, he always does what is right.
And so we find that Abraham
is having this conversation with the Lord
and he's finding out about the impending judgment
of Sodom and Gomorrah.
And Abraham, as he's having this conversation,
he reveals two important truths.
Number one, God is the judge of all the earth.
And number two, he always does what is right.
So I believe as we begin starting this message this evening
that many of those that would come to a perspective
such as what has been asked this evening,
I believe that for many of them,
obviously I cannot say for all of them,
I would never seek to do so because of the individual nature
of those that would have this perspective,
but for many of them, I believe that perhaps
they have approached the Bible incorrectly and incompletely.
And why I say that is for this reason,
I believe that their approach,
many times individual skeptics
that would approach the Bible,
they have an approach of a critical nature.
They approach the Bible by seeking to find fault
and criticize, and therefore they reach a faulty conclusion.
Why is that?
Well, because they just like to look
at certain portions of scripture.
They look to a certain portion that's going to be in line
with what they want, what fits their presupposition,
and therefore they're going to seek a passage
that they can run to and support what they already think.
Now, as the people of God,
we understand that our approach
to God's word is much different.
Our approach to God's word, my approach to God's word,
is God is right and I'm in error, right?
And so as I come to the word of God,
it's God's word that is going to correct
and instruct my thinking.
And if I approach the word of God at that level,
and I approach the word of God with understanding
that he is the judge of all the earth,
that he always does that which is right,
that he is perfect in harmony with regard to his attributes,
then my perspective of the word of God
is going to be quite different.
Let me also say this by way of introduction.
The Bible tells us in the book of 1 Corinthians
that the natural man receiveth not
the things of the spirit of God.
Why?
Because they are foolishness unto him.
They must be spiritually discerned.
And so as we go to the word of God
and we begin to seek the face of God
and looking at God's word,
we want to give an honest approach to the word of God.
And indeed, there are times in which,
as the skeptics would say,
as the question gives us this evening,
that there are people groups that are destroyed.
And there are some that would look at that and say,
how could that be in line with a God
who's loving and merciful?
I hope this evening that after reviewing several examples
that we could conclude,
even as Jonah concluded there in Jonah 4,
that we know that God is gracious.
He's gracious.
There's a number of other things
that are mentioned there in Jonah 4
and verse number two that we'll look at
as we end this evening.
Let me start here with the Egyptians, if we could.
I'm gonna give a number of examples.
These examples were not given on the question that was asked
but I will give some examples
of perhaps what is being referred to
and hope that that helps us to answer the question.
Turn to Exodus chapter number four, if you will.
In Exodus chapter number four,
we find that in verses 22 and 23,
Moses has been given instruction.
He's objected and God has given him the signs, the miracles.
And we find that in Exodus chapter four in verse number 22,
notice what God says to Moses.
He says, and thou shalt say unto Pharaoh,
thus saith the Lord, Israel is my son, even my firstborn.
And I say unto thee, let my son go, that he may serve me.
And if thou refuse to let him go,
behold, I will slay thy son, even thy firstborn.
I have every belief as we look at this instruction
that God gives to Moses in Exodus four in verses 22 and 23.
I have every reason to believe
that Moses faithfully communicated to Pharaoh
what was at stake, that God said to Moses,
deliver this message to Pharaoh.
If he doesn't let my people go,
that I will slay thy son, even thy firstborn.
Over the next several chapters,
we find the interaction between Moses and Pharaoh.
And of course, Aaron is there.
And we find that as Moses is interacting with Pharaoh,
that in chapter seven through 10,
plagues one through nine are recorded for us.
As you read about those plagues,
you read about the devastation,
you read about the destruction of Egypt,
you read about how that in Exodus 8 and verse 19,
how that the people, the counselors of Pharaoh,
they say they recognize that this is the finger of God.
We find it in the 10th chapter
that the people, the counselors of Pharaoh,
they say to Pharaoh,
do you not know that our land has been destroyed?
And we find that God was revealing Himself
to Pharaoh and to the Egyptians.
I believe that in so doing,
that God was demonstrating a measure of grace,
a measure of mercy.
Because when Moses first comes to Pharaoh and says,
God said, let my people go.
Pharaoh says, who's God?
And so God begins to reveal Himself
and to reveal His power.
And everything that God said He would do, He did.
In the ninth chapter, which would reveal His power,
record for us the seventh plague. I want you to notice that in verse number 19
the Bible says this, Moses of course has received the instruction from God and I
believe this is a great picture of God's mercy, of God's love and grace. Notice
what he says before the arrival of the seventh plague, send therefore now and
gather thy cattle and all that thou hast in the field. For upon every man and
beast which shall be found in the field and shall not be brought home, the hail
shall come down upon them and they shall die. That's gracious and merciful of God
to let them know of what was going to happen. And we find that even after six
plagues had already taken place and all that God had demonstrated that
particular point, that the response of the people was still mixed. Even though
God gave him warning, the Bible tells us in verse number 20 that he that feared
the word of the Lord among the servants of Pharaoh made his servants and his
cattle flee into the houses. They believed. They responded to the merciful
truth that God had given the warning. We find that in verse 21 it says, and he
that regarded not the word of the Lord left his servants and his cattle in the
field. What happened to them? They died. They died. The plague came just as God
said. We find that the scriptures, it's interesting to me and we don't have time
to develop each of these truths that we'll look at this evening, but I do want
you to understand that the scriptures record for us interaction between Pharaoh
and Moses during several of the plagues. And in those interactions you will find
that many times Pharaoh makes the request, would you make the plague stop?
And God graciously responds to that request and the plague is stayed. But you
know it's interesting to me that with regard to the death of the firstborn,
there's no request. There's no reference that we find that as God would reveal to,
of course, at the end of chapter 10 we find that Pharaoh told Moses to flee, get
out of his sight, that in the day that I see your face you're gonna die. And we
find that Pharaoh had expelled Moses from his presence, but all the way back
as we mentioned in chapter 4 that God had set the consequence. If you don't
let my people go, the firstborn is gonna die. And there was no request, there was
no interaction between Pharaoh saying, okay Moses how do we avoid that? Just let
the people go. Let me say this also, it was the Egyptians that had given the
instruction, in fact Pharaoh himself, to kill all of the male children of the
children of Israel. They were very known for human sacrifice themselves and so we
find that this is a situation in which I believe as you look at the text of
Scripture and you honestly evaluate these chapters that provide us the
record of the the plagues and the consequence of the death of the
firstborn, that God indeed was gracious and merciful. He didn't just come in and
wipe them out in just a moment, he came in and revealed himself to them. Who is
God? Okay, over the next several plagues you're gonna see who God is. And they
still rejected. I believe this evening that Pharaoh had been given light, yet he
failed to respond to the light that was given. And in a lack of response or maybe
in responding to that light by rejecting the light, we find that he had to deal
with the consequences and the nation of Egypt dealt with the consequences. I
think about not only the Egyptians but I think about the Amorites. We think about
the Amorites, we find that God provides details for us in the Abrahamic
Covenant as it's recorded in Genesis chapter 15 and as God would give the
Abrahamic Covenant in Genesis chapter 15, not only would he speak about all of the
the details with regard to the place and what have you, but he also speaks of the
time of the Abrahamic Covenant, the time of entering into the land that was
promised. And we find that in Genesis 15 and verse number 16, God says this,
but in the fourth generation they shall come hither again. Notice what he says,
for the iniquity of the Amorites is not yet full. We read that statement that the
iniquity of the Amorites is not yet full. In other words, I believe that God here
is demonstrating once again his grace and his mercy. Why? Because he was going
to give them time to repent. He was going to give them opportunity to repent
before his judgment would come. It's interesting as you go to the book of
Joshua, turn to the book of Joshua, if you will, in chapter number 5, because we
begin to see some things about the Amorites here in Joshua chapter number
5, and we find that the Amorites in chapter number 5 of the book of Joshua
and also in chapter number 10, there's a different response of the Amorites,
the king of the Amorites, the kings, excuse me, of the Amorites, versus the
response that we see of Rahab in Joshua chapter number 2. Here in Joshua chapter
number 5 and verse number 1, notice what the Bible says,
and it came to pass when all the kings of the Amorites, which were on the side
of Jordan westward, and all the kings of the Canaanites, which were by the sea,
heard that the Lord had dried up the waters of Jordan from before the
children of Israel until we were passed over, that their heart melted, neither was
their spirit in them anymore because of the children of Israel. That's very
similar to what we read of Rahab as the spies went, as we read in Joshua
chapter number 2, when the spies go into Jericho, and we read about the
understanding of Rahab and the people of Jericho, and the Bible tells us in
Joshua chapter 2 and verse number 9 that Rahab says to these men, I know that the
Lord hath given you the land, and that your terror is fallen upon us, and that
all the inhabitants of the land faint because of you. For we have heard how the
Lord dried up the water of the Red Sea for you when you came out of Egypt, and
what ye did under the two kings of the Amorites that were on the other side,
Jordan, Sihon, and Og, whom ye utterly destroyed. By the way, with Sihon in
particular, it was asked that they could pass through freely. They did not want to
have interaction, but there was a rejection of that. You can go back and
read of that in the book of Numbers. Notice it says in verse number, well we
won't continue reading, but you remember that Rahab believed that God was going
to give the people of Israel the land, and she feared, and there was an
agreement that was made. There was a scarlet thread that was hung out, and God
through these spies told Rahab that there's safety in the house. Jericho
was still destroyed, but Rahab and whoever she had in the house, there was
mercy, there was grace. Why? Because of a response. But notice I mentioned in
Joshua 5 that these kings of the Amorites, it's also mentioned about the
Canaanites here, that they hear about this, but I want you to see what their
response is, and really you got to flip over to chapter number 10, and I want you
to really see the response of the kings of the Amorites as it's recorded for us
in Joshua chapter number 10. In fact, we find that it's in Joshua chapter number
9, the account of the Gibeonites, and if you want to have an add-on to the
message from this morning of the way in which the false teachers, the depth of
depravity, excuse me, deception, read about the Gibeonites in Joshua chapter
number 9. We find that we, after the situation with southern Canaan being
destroyed in Joshua 9 and all the victory, that in Joshua chapter number
10, these five kings of the Amorites, as it's mentioned in verse number 5, the
king of Jerusalem, the king of Hebron, the king of Jarmut, the king of Lachish, the
king of Eglon, they gathered themselves together and went up, they and all their
hosts, and encamped before Gibeon and made war against it, and they would soon
be defeated. So we find that the Amorites, as it's mentioned because of the
reference in Genesis chapter 15, and then here in the book of Joshua, and we read
about the fact that they were destroyed, but you think about the mercy
and the grace of God even still being understood within the context of their
destruction. For Rahab responded in belief, but these kings of the Amorites,
they formed a coalition to go into battle. We find that they were ultimately
defeated. One that many like to look at is the Amalekites, and turn over the book
of 1st Samuel, if you will, and I want you to look here. Of course, this
instruction is given in 1st Samuel chapter 15 with regard to the
Amalekites, and maybe this is one in which someone had in mind. As you look at
the instruction that Samuel would give to Saul, we find that this instruction is
given with regard to the Amalekites, and it says in verse number one of 1st
Samuel 15, Samuel also said unto Saul, the Lord sent me to anoint thee to be
king over his people, over Israel. Now therefore hearken thou unto the
voice of the words of the Lord. Thus saith the Lord of hosts. Notice what it says,
I remember that which Amalek did to Israel, how he laid wait for him in the
way when he came up from Egypt. Now go and smite Amalek, and utterly destroy all
that they have, and spare them not, but slay both man and woman, infant and
suckling, ox and sheep, camel and ass. There are people that look at verse
number three completely out of the context of verse number two, or of Exodus
and Deuteronomy, and say, man, God gave the instruction to just annihilate all
of them. Notice what he says in verse number two, I remember that which Amalek
did to Israel. Well what is it that Amalek did to Israel? Turn back to Exodus
chapter number 17. In Exodus chapter number 17, of course we understand that
at this particular point they've already left Egypt, they've already crossed the
Red Sea, they've already complained about water and about food and about water
again, and God has miraculously provided for them.
But then we find that as we come to the latter part of Exodus chapter number 17 in verse number 8 the Bible begins to reveal
to us this about Amalek and it says then came Amalek and fought with Israel in Rephidim and
Moses said unto Joshua choose us out men and go out fight with Amalek
Tomorrow I will stand on the top of the hill with the rod of God in mine hand and this is the time in which
remember they had to stay up the hands of
Moses and as Moses hands were stayed up the children of Israel had victory as they were let down they had defeat
We find that in verse number 16 of Exodus 17 the Bible says
Because the Lord hath sworn that the Lord will have war with Amalek from generation to generation
Now what is it that the Amalekites did? What is it that the king of Amalek did?
Well, God gives us more insight to that in the book of Deuteronomy in chapter number 25
in Deuteronomy chapter number 25 God gives us some insight as to the tactics of the
Amalekites the behavior of the Amalekites and what they did and
God is using Moses here in Deuteronomy to prepare the nation of Israel for entrance into the land and he's going to remind them of
This and what it is that they're to do notice. It says in verse 17 of Deuteronomy 25
Remember what Amalek did unto thee by the way?
When you were come forth out of Egypt, what is it that he did notice verse 18?
How he met thee by the way and smote the hindmost of thee even all that were feeble behind thee when thou was
faint and weary and he feared not God
That's what he did
So therefore verse 19 it shall be when the Lord thy God hath given thee rest from all thine enemies round about in the land
Which the Lord thy God giveth thee for an inheritance to possess it that thou shalt blot out the remembrance of Amalek from under heaven
Thou shalt not forget it
So when read first Samuel 15 apart from Exodus 17 apart from Deuteronomy 25
You can certainly come to a different conclusion
You can reach a conclusion that says how could God do that? Well God says I remember what they did and here's what the
Consequences here's what's going to happen and we read it in Exodus chapter 17. We read it in Deuteronomy 25
what the details are of
The behavior of Amalek and the Amalekites
Think about the people of Nineveh. I'm going to use this from a positive perspective toward the book of Jonah if you will
I'm trying to use this as a contrast
between the the two
Aspects in which we're looking at here in the city of Nineveh
I believe that as Jonah preaches this message after God got a hold of them in Jonah 3 and verse number 4
The Bible tells us that he began to enter into the city a day's journey and he cried and said yet 40 days in
Nineveh shall be overthrown. I
Believe with all my heart
that Nineveh
Including the hundred and twenty thousand children in Nineveh and we get that number from Jonah 4 in verse number 11
After God deals with Jonah and the Gourd and all of that situation
He says in verse 11 of chapter 4 and should not I spare Nineveh that great city where there are more than six
64,000 persons that cannot discern between the right hand and their left hand and also much cattle
I believe that in 40 days based on the preaching of Jonah in verse number 4 of Jonah 3
that God would have destroyed Nineveh including those hundred and twenty thousand children and
He would have destroyed them, but we find that the response of the people of Nineveh
Stayed the judgment of God and spared the people
Notice in verse number 5 of Jonah chapter number 3 the Bible says so the people of Nineveh believed God
They believed God they proclaimed a fast and put on sackcloth from the greatest of them
Even to the least of them verse 10. You can read the rest of it later
but in verse number 10
It says that God saw their works that they turned from their evil way and God
Repented of the evil that he had said that he would do unto them and he did it not. I
believe again that God would have
Destroyed the city of Nineveh all of the inhabitants including those hundred and twenty thousand children
the question that we could ask about the
Situation there with Egypt the situation here with Nineveh and you look at two very different
situations where God is revealing himself to Pharaoh and to the people of
Egypt and the the
Magicians they are
recognizing as they see these
These plagues and these miracles they are recognizing. This is the finger of God
But yet there's not a response like we read of in Nineveh
There continues to be a refusal to let the people of God go
they see the
Time in which God allowed for these plagues and all that he does and he reveals his his grace
I believe in his mercy to the Egyptians yet. They continue to resist
yet for the people of Nineveh
They respond with repentance and thus they are spared
So as we look at the text of Scripture we look at these examples the the the Egyptians the Amorites the
Amalekites the people of Nineveh
We see the people of Nineveh have a different outcome than the other three that we've looked at but we find that God. Yes
He is just and he is righteous and he is the judge of all the earth
This evening we could ask the question would God have been justified in destroying the the people of Egypt
Would God have been justified in destroying the the people of Nineveh? Yes
One was destroyed and one was spared what was different not God the response of the people
And we find this evening that our God is no
Respecter of persons and we find that as we look at these examples
We again mention how that he says that the iniquity of the Amorites is not yet full you read about the Amalekites and it's
Specifically a result of their own behavior and the judgment of God and we find that here
God's judgment is seen
yes
but if you look at it in its
Entirety and look at the entirety of the passages and all that goes into it
You find that it's not void of God being merciful. It's not void of God giving space for repentance
for we see that in Nineveh and
Let me say this as we would consider God's judgment and perhaps those that would like to
Reach this conclusion and have this perspective of that which was asked this evening
Oftentimes they would look at the people groups as being different
The the people groups void of Israel right other than Israel
Maybe I should say it that way and this evening for just a few minutes
I want us to consider God's judgment upon his own people and
As we consider God's judgment upon his own people. I believe that it demonstrates God's justice in a very clear way
Because God is no respecter of persons
and so when God judges these people groups that we speak of and people say look at what God did to
This people group or that people group I say yes, he did
But do you want to look at what God did in the nation of Israel who were his own people?
Why because God is just
Right. God is merciful, but God is just
think with me turn to look at 2nd Chronicles if you will and
2nd Chronicles chapter number 7 and many times when we speak about 2nd Chronicles chapter number 7 a verse
Immediately comes to our mind and that's verse number 14
If my people which are called by my name shall humble themselves and pray and seek my face and turn from their wicked ways
Then will I hear from heaven and will forgive their sin and will heal their land. What a great verse
But I want you to understand that in 2nd Chronicles chapter number 7 not only does God give that promise
We've looked at that as being revival promise
But I want you to notice what God says in verses 19 through 22 with regard to his judgment
Notice in verse number 19
But if you turn away and forsake my statutes and my commandments
Which I have set before you and shall go and serve other gods and worship them
Then will I pluck them up by the roots out of my land
Which I have given them and this house which I have sanctified for my name will I cast out of my sight and will make?
It to be a proverb and a byword among all nations in this house
Which is high shall be an astonishment to everyone that passeth by it so that he shall say why hath the Lord done thus?
Unto this land and unto this house and it shall be answered
Because they forsook the Lord God of their fathers
Which brought them forth out of the land of Egypt and laid hold on other gods and worshiped them and served them
Therefore hath he brought all this evil
upon them
If you want to jot down in your notes, I won't take time to read all the verses
But look at Psalm 106 verses 35 through 43
You'll see how the psalmist records this very same truth with regard to the judgment of God the justice of God
I want you to think about it within the context of the Assyrian captivity and
second Kings chapter number seven and I know we're in a lot of places this evening and I
Hope that as we look and compare scripture with scripture that we don't want to just take one
isolated
incident
From here or from the Word of God and come to a conclusion
First Kings chapter number seven. I think I said second Kings, but it's first Kings chapter number seven seventeen, excuse me
First Kings chapter number seventeen and I want you to look here at what the Word of God tells us. I
Don't know why I'm in first King it did I say second Kings at first I
Said first I said second now, I'm gonna say second again. All right
2 Kings chapter 17, please forgive me.
2 Kings chapter 17, my notes even say 2 Kings 17.
But beginning in verse number seven,
2 Kings 17 and verse number seven,
I will not have time to read all the way down
through verse number 23, but this really records for us
the record of the Assyrian captivity
of the nation of Israel, the 10 tribes of the north.
In verse number seven it says,
for so it was that the children of Israel
had sinned against the Lord their God,
which had brought them up out of the land of Egypt
from under the hand of Pharaoh, king of Egypt,
and had feared other gods.
And notice what it says in verse number 14,
notwithstanding they would not hear,
but hardened their necks like to the neck of their fathers
that did not believe in the Lord God.
They rejected his statutes and his covenant
that he made with their fathers and his testimonies,
which he testified against them.
And they followed vanity and became vain
and went after the heathen that were around about them,
concerning whom the Lord had charged
that they should not do like them.
And they left all the commandments of the Lord their God
and made them molten images, even two calves,
and made a grove and worshiped all the host of heaven
and served Baal.
Notice in verse 18 it says,
therefore the Lord was very angry with Israel
and removed them out of his sight.
There was none left but the tribe of Judah only.
And verse number 23 says,
until the Lord removed Israel out of his sight,
as he had said by all his servants, the prophets,
so was Israel carried away out of their own land
to Assyria unto this day.
They face judgment.
They face the justice of God because of their wickedness,
because of their behavior.
Does it mean that God isn't merciful?
Oh no, God is merciful.
But they rejected.
The Bible told us as we looked at these verses here,
it says that they would not hear,
that they hardened their necks,
that they rejected his statutes,
that they left all of his commandments
and the judgment of God comes.
We read this of the Assyrian captivity.
I want you to think about the Babylonian captivity
of Judah from the book of Jeremiah, if you will.
And I want you to notice,
there's some very strong language in the book of Jeremiah
that I really hope helps us this evening
with regard to this subject that is before us.
Because again, there are people
that will bring this charge against God,
that they will bring this charge
as they look at the word of God
and they'll say that there's some discrepancy.
But I hope that as we look at God's dealings
with his own people, the nation of Israel,
that we would see very clearly
that yes, our God is merciful and gracious,
but our God is righteous and just.
And his attributes are in perfect harmony.
In Jeremiah 11, look at verses 11 through 13.
Notice what the word of God says.
Therefore, thus saith the Lord,
behold, I will bring evil upon them,
which they shall not be able to escape.
And though they shall cry unto me,
I will not hearken unto them.
You say, God said that?
Yes.
God said that.
And he's not talking about the Amalekites
or the Amorites or the Philistines
or the Egyptians or the people of Nineveh.
He's talking about his own people, Judah.
He says in verse number 12,
then shall the cities of Judah
and inhabitants of Jerusalem go
and cry unto the gods unto whom they offer incense,
but they shall not save them at all
in the time of their trouble.
For according to their number of thy cities
were thy gods, O Judah.
And according to the number of the streets of Jerusalem,
have you set up altars to that shameful thing,
even altars to burn incense unto Baal.
God says, I'm gonna judge you.
He says in verse number 13,
I will bring evil upon them
that they shall not be able to escape.
Notice in Jeremiah chapter 21,
turn over several chapters, if you will.
You can look at verses one through 10 for sake of time.
I just want to look at verses four through six.
Jeremiah is responding to Zedekiah.
The request had been made
that he would inquire of the Lord.
Notice in verse two, this is the request.
I pray thee of the Lord for us,
for Nebuchadnezzar, king of Babylon,
maketh war against us.
If so be that the Lord will deal with us
according to all his wondrous works
that he may go up from us.
They're wanting God to just intervene
into some miraculous way in his wondrous works.
And they say, Jeremiah, go inquire the Lord for us
and find out if he's gonna show up
and deal mightily for us.
Jeremiah said unto them,
thus shall you say to Zedekiah.
Look at verse four.
Thus saith the Lord God of Israel.
Behold, I will turn back the weapons of war
that are in your hands,
wherewith you fight against the king of Babylon
and against the Chaldeans,
which besiege you without the walls.
And I will assemble them into the midst of this city.
And I myself will fight against you
with an outstretched hand and with a strong arm,
even in anger and in fury and in great wrath.
And I will smite the inhabitants of this city,
both man and beast.
They shall die of a great pestilence.
That's not the answer they were hoping for.
But if you read the indictment against Judah
in the beginning of the book of Jeremiah,
you find that there are people that forgot the Lord,
they forsook the Lord and they followed after idols.
And God said, you're not listening to my prophets.
There's no repentance.
Judgment is coming.
Did God not send a prophet?
Jeremiah's prophesying until he can't talk anymore.
And there's just rejection.
So guess what happens?
Judgment.
They're carried away into Babylon.
Turn to the book of 2 Chronicles, if you will.
2 Chronicles chapter number 36.
I want you to notice here,
as it's described to us, the Babylonian captivity.
We read there in 2 Kings 17 about the Assyrian captivity.
Here in 2 Chronicles 36 and verse number 15,
the Bible says this,
and the Lord God of their father sent to them
by his messengers, rising up at times and sending
because he had had compassion on his people
and on his dwelling place.
God is merciful, he's gracious, but notice what they did.
They mocked the messengers of God and despised his words
and misused his prophets
until the wrath of the Lord rose against his people.
Notice the last statement of verse 16,
till there was no remedy.
Wow.
Yeah, God is merciful, but God is just.
And it's not just that as you study the Old Testament
that there's some people groups outside of Israel
that face the judgment of God because of their wickedness,
the iniquity of the Amorites.
Listen, they were wicked people that served idols
and God gave them space to repent, but they repented not.
And we find that God, his judgment comes,
but his judgment came for the nation of Israel as well.
And I believe that that ought to help us
to understand the fullness of God's attributes this evening
that he is gracious and merciful,
but he's righteous and just.
The question put a statement with regard
to the God of the Old Testament
versus the God of the New Testament,
that they like the God of the New Testament,
but they do not like the God of the Old Testament.
I said this that I feel like, and again, not all, but many,
have an approach to the Bible
that's incorrect and incomplete.
Why do I say that?
Well, turn to the book of Acts.
New Testament, by the way.
In Acts 5, you reach a faulty conclusion
when you have a faulty approach.
If you want your approach to be that God is unjust
in the things that he did, you begin to read to that end.
If you want to see a distinction
between the Old and New Testament,
perhaps you ignore certain passages
like we'll look at here in the New Testament
very quickly as we conclude.
We find that there's judgment in the New Testament as well.
In Acts 5, we read of Ananias and Sapphira.
What was the offense of Ananias and Sapphira?
They lied.
Now, sin is sin, right?
We see that in the Word of God.
But you know, for many people today,
I would say many people today on a Sunday
in the United States of America that sat in church today,
lying is no big deal to them.
They don't even think about it.
They don't even think twice about lying.
If it means that I'm gonna face a consequence
that's not pleasant, I mean, people lie all the time.
I'm not saying that it's right, it's wrong.
But the offense of Ananias and Sapphira is that they lied.
The Bible records for us here
that Peter actually says to them,
listen, when it was your land, you could have kept it.
You didn't have to sell it.
And when you sold your land and you made your money,
you didn't have to give it all.
Right?
That's what happens.
We won't take time to read all of it,
but I want you to notice what happens
that Peter says that you've conceived
this thing in thine heart.
You've lied, not unto men at the end of verse number four,
but unto God.
And Ananias, hearing these words,
fell down and gave up the ghost.
And great fear came on all them that heard these things.
I guess so.
Right?
I mean, what happens if one of us lied today
and you just died?
Do you understand what I'm saying?
It would impact us.
Sapphira, the Bible tells us, it continues.
In verse number six, the young man arose, wound him up,
and carried him out and buried him.
And it was about the space of three hours after
when his wife, not knowing what was done, came in.
And she's asked the same line of questions.
And she says, yep, yay for so much.
At the end of verse number eight,
then Peter said unto her,
how is it that ye have agreed together
to tempt the Spirit of the Lord?
Behold, the feet of them which have buried thy husband
are at the door and shall carry thee out.
Then fell she down straightway at his feet
and yielded up the ghost.
And the young men came in and found her dead
and carrying her forth, buried her by her husband.
Look at the result in verse number 11.
And great fear came upon all the church.
and upon as many as heard these things. They lied and they died." Is that not judgment?
Absolutely. God is just and He is righteous, and the judge of all the earth shall do what's
right. Turn to the book of...right here in the book of Acts, turn to the chapter 12.
In Acts chapter 12, we read of Herod. You say, well, Herod deserved it. He killed James
and he was going to kill Peter. Well, Herod is here at the end of Acts chapter 12, and
the Bible says that in verse number 20, and Herod was highly displeased with them of Tyre
and Sidon, but they came with one accord to him, and having made Blastas the king's chamberlain
their friend, desired peace because their country was nourished by the king's country.
And upon a set day Herod arrayed in royal apparel, sat upon his throne and made an oration
unto them. The people gave a shout, saying, It is of the voice of God and not of man.
And immediately the angel of the Lord smote him, because he gave not God the glory, and
he was eaten of worms and gave up the ghost. We're talking about judgment, New Testament,
God's judgment, right? And so we begin to look at the Scriptures, and sometimes what
happens is we don't see the judgment in the New Testament, maybe in the same light as
we see the Old Testament. One of the reasons I believe that to be the case is because God
is dealing with Israel as a nation in the Old Testament. He's dealing with the church
as a organism in the New Testament, and there's distinction between that. There are many people
groups that come against Israel as a nation, and therefore they have the right to protect
their borders and all of those things, and they have the Philistines are constantly
coming against the nation of Israel and to fight against them, and the Amorites that
set that coalition that we read of in Joshua chapter 10, they're coming against, they
set in battle against the city of Gibeon. Why? Because of the agreement that had been
made between the Gibeonites and the nation of Israel, and we find that they're defeated.
But we see that in the New Testament, God is still a God of just judgment.
I want to remind you of 1 Corinthians chapter 11. We have our Lord's Supper table before
us, every single service you come in, and as you walk into these doors, one of the first
things that you see is up here on the platform area, this Lord's Supper table. It says,
This do in remembrance of me. We should be mindful of the fact that as we observe the
Lord's Supper, and even as we think about the table of remembrance that is there, and
we see those words and we're mindful of the truth of 1 Corinthians chapter 11, we speak
about that importance of eating and drinking in a fashion in which we're not eating and
drinking unworthily. We let a man examine himself, but I want to remind you what 1
Corinthians 11 and verse number 30 says. Those that would eat and drink unworthily, it says,
for this cause many are weak and sickly among you, and many sleep. You understand that word
sleep is not, you took a siesta this afternoon. The word sleep means died. They were dead.
God's judgment. God's judgment. I would say this, as you look at the churches in the book
of Revelation, the churches of Asia, sometimes the judgment is maybe different judgment than
what we see in the Old Testament. Maybe it's not that a people group is destroyed, but
you know it's sad judgment when God says to the church at Ephesus, If you don't repent,
I'm going to remove your candlestick. That's serious. But sometimes what happens is we
don't look at that as being judgment, because the reality is that sometimes we go through
the motions of church. We don't even know if the Holy Spirit's present, if He's even
We're just going through what we do. We're just on our routine. We're just on our check
the box, go to church. But God's judgment, removing His presence, removing the candlestick
as it says here in Revelation chapter 2 with dealing with the church at Ephesus. It's interesting
as you read the messages to the churches, you find that many times that God says, Repent,
or here's the consequence. And this evening we begin to think about some of the judgment
that we would see in New Testament Christianity. It might not be the same kind of judgment
that we see in the Old Testament with some of these people groups, but nonetheless it's
judgment. And there are times that people die a premature death. Why? Because of their
carnality, because of their behavior. I think it was D.L. Moody that said this, When God's
people are not walking in holiness, that God begins to deal with them. And the first way
in which God deals with His people that are not walking in obedience to His Word and walking
in holiness, for God said that we're to be holy as He is holy in all manner of conversation.
And he said the first form of the way in which God deals with His people is that of conviction.
You ever face conviction? What happens when we get convicted? When we hear the preaching
of the Word of God, when we read the Word of God in our daily lives, we're reading the
Word of God and God begins to convict us. We can respond to that in one of two ways.
We can have a soft heart and respond in obedience to the Word of God and we can get right whatever
we need to get right. Or, we can harden our hearts. We can quench the Spirit of God. We
can grieve the Spirit of God. When we quench and grieve the Spirit of God, that conviction,
we just learn how to kind of deal with it. And after a little while, we're not so impacted
by the conviction. Someone drew a diagram and explained conviction like a triangle in
a sandbox. And eventually, the triangle in the sandbox as it rotates either way, whichever
way you want to have it rotate in your mind, eventually after it rotates one complete revolution,
that triangle now becomes a circle. And the circle, the triangle will move freely within
the circle without any friction from the sand. Do you see it in your mind's eye? Why? Because
we've just quenched the Spirit of God. We've grieved the Spirit of God. And so, God deals
with conviction. And after conviction, if we don't respond to conviction, you know what
God uses? Chastisement. You know why He chastens us? Because He loves us. And there are people
that look at the chastisement of the Lord in a wrong way. We say, no, God chastens us
because we're His sons, because He loves us. Dale Moody went on to say that if we don't
respond to the conviction, we face the chastisement. And if we don't respond to the chastisement,
we face a coffin. That's pretty serious. As you look at the Word of God and you look
at 1 Corinthians 11, and for this cause, many are sick and weakly among you, and many sleep.
Listen, not everyone that's sick is facing the chastisement of God. We understand that
biblically. Not every time somebody's sick. But I'm going to tell you what, if I'm sick,
I want to... Lord, did I do something like... I want to make sure I'm not sick or weakly
because of my disobedience. He says, many sleep. They've died. Premature deaths from
a human, from our human perspective. Why? Because they ate and drank unworthily.
Listen, in the New Testament, we find that God, He exercises judgment. We read it in
Acts 5 with Ananias and Sapphira, in Acts 12 with Herod. Believers in general in 1 Corinthians
11. The churches of Asia that are mentioned in the book of Revelation, specifically there
with the church at Ephesus, as we referenced in Revelation 2. And this evening, as we begin
to think about our God, I'm so thankful that our God is gracious and merciful. But the
writer of Hebrews said that our God is a consuming fire, is a fearful thing to fall in the hands
of a living God, an angry God. And you think about His justice and His judgment. I'm thankful
that God is gracious and merciful. And we do see His judgment in the Old Testament and
the New Testament. Listen, God said of Himself, I'm the same yesterday, today, and forever.
Begin to approach the Scriptures with that perspective as we begin to read a passage
that seems to contradict from man's perspective what that truth reveals to us, then we better
dig in and dig deeper and try to understand what it is that's taking place and what God
is recording for us. So, how do we answer the skeptics? I said we'd end with Jonah 4.
I already put my Bible away, and so some of you did as well. But look back at Jonah 4.
Look back at Jonah chapter 4. You know, from Jonah's perspective, the people of Nineveh
deserve judgment. Capital of Assyria, wicked people. They say that the city of Nineveh
was lined with stakes that had skulls on them from the people they defeated. It was a wicked
place, immoral, ungodly. I think that that Nineveh, Jonah would have been perfectly happy
if Nineveh had been destroyed. He'd have been happy about it. That's why he fled. He says
in verse number 1, it displeased Jonah exceedingly, and he is very angry. Why? Because God repented
the evil that He had said that He would do against them or unto them, and He did it not.
Verse number 2, he prayed unto the Lord and said, I pray thee, O Lord, was not this my
saying when I was yet in my country? Therefore I fled before unto Tarshish. Why? For I knew
that Thou art a gracious God, and merciful. Slow to anger.
and of great kindness, and repentest thee of the evil." God is gracious, God is
merciful, God is slow to anger and of great kindness, and God is just, and God
is righteous. When people reject, whether Old Testament or New Testament, when people
reject the grace and mercy of God, the light that God gives, judgment is the
consequence. And so this evening I hope that that would help us in dealing with
some skeptics, taking a more thorough approach to the Word of God, a complete
understanding of the passages that often are looked to and attacked and
criticized, and say, okay, let's dig in. Why did this happen the way that it did?
What was God really revealing? Why did God send ten plagues before nine and
then the death of the firstborn? Is that not the grace and mercy of God? Is that
not God revealing Himself? Absolutely. But there's a refusal, there's a rejection.
We find that throughout the Word of God, He is the judge of all the earth, and He
always does what is right. Let's pray. Father, we love You this evening. We thank
You for loving us. We thank You for Your precious Word, for the truth that's
contained therein. I pray this evening, we've looked at so many passages of
Scripture, we've used some examples that some may turn to in order to attack.
We've looked at passages that show that You're no respecter of persons, that when
Your people rejected You and refused to obey You and turned to idols, they faced
Your judgment, severe judgment. We've looked at examples in the New Testament
of those that have faced judgment. God, I pray that this evening, as we consider
our own lives, that we would determine that we will walk in holiness and that we would
walk in obedience to Thy Word. For we do not want to face Your hand of judgment. We'd
much rather have Your hand of blessing. And God, I pray that You would continue to enable
us to adequately interact with those that we come into contact with, that we'd be ready
to give an answer of the hope that lies within us. I pray that as we have a time of invitation
that we would respond. Lord, that You do a work in our hearts and lives where You would
be glorified, and we'll thank You for it. In Christ's name, would You stand with us?