First Timothy chapter number six this morning,
and we'll be looking at verses 13 through 21,
and looking at the end of this book,
and we'll get into Second Timothy
beginning next week, Lord willing.
And as you know, we've been studying
throughout this calendar year,
our theme, as you see on the banners, continue.
And as we think about that theme of continue,
we've used, or we've taken that theme
really from First and Second Timothy,
as we find that Timothy is given a charge
and responsibility to continue,
and you and I, as well, have been charged
and given the responsibility to continue.
I find, in this text of Scripture,
as the letter concludes, Paul issues a charge
to his son in the faith.
It's interesting, he refers to Timothy
and also to Titus as being his son in the faith,
and there's a great bond and relationship that they have.
We understand that Paul, according to,
there's not much time between the writing
of First and Second Timothy,
and so Paul is near the end of his life.
He reveals in Second Timothy, chapter number four,
that the time of his departure is at hand,
and we understand that Paul,
if we could use symbolically this morning,
is really kind of passing a baton, if you will,
to his son in the faith, and he's issuing this charge,
and we find that as we look here at this charge,
it is made in the sight of God and before Jesus Christ.
It's interesting that Paul, of course,
all Scripture is given by inspiration of God,
and God would have it so, to use those words,
and there's little doubt in my mind
that the reality that this charge is being given
in the sight of God and before Jesus Christ
really drives home the seriousness of this charge.
We find that it would bring an awareness,
and Timothy is given the charge to keep.
To keep what?
To keep this commandment,
and it says without spot, unrebukable,
until the appearing of our Lord Jesus Christ.
Look at it with me, if you will,
beginning in verse number 13.
The Bible says, I give thee charge in the sight of God,
who quickeneth all things, and before Christ Jesus,
before Pontius Pilate witnessed a good confession,
that thou keep this commandment without spot,
unrebukable, until the appearing of our Lord Jesus Christ,
and so we see the charge is given to keep this commandment,
notice without spot, and unrebukable.
We understand the importance of God's people
living godly lives.
We mentioned last week, as we looked at verses 11 and 12,
that there's this thought of flee, follow, and fight,
and we find that what is it that Timothy
was to follow after?
Righteousness, godliness, faith, love,
patience, and meekness,
and we find that Timothy is now given this charge
to keep this commandment without spot, unrebukable,
and then it says this, until the appearing
of our Lord Jesus Christ.
We find that this word keep is an interesting word.
It means to attend to carefully.
It means to guard or to observe,
but it also carries with it the idea of to practice,
do, or fulfill.
To continue in a course or an action,
and I think about this word
and how Timothy is receiving this charge,
and really Paul is going to remind Timothy
of three important biblical truths,
and I believe this morning that these three truths
that are given to us in this portion of scripture
provide motivation and encouragement
to Timothy so that he would continue.
I believe this morning that these same truths
will provide for each of us the motivation
and the encouragement that we need to continue.
I'm not sure of you.
I know for me, I've never ran a long-distance race.
I was never interested in running a long-distance race.
I thought one time in my life,
I was in my mid-20s, and I thought in my mid-20s,
I said, you know, I think I'm gonna run a marathon,
and I had that thought because I did some research
and I found that there is a super small percentage
of the world population that has ever run a marathon,
and so I thought, well, so few people globally
have ever done this, so I think, bar,
I'm gonna run a marathon,
and so I began to train for a marathon.
How many of you ever run a marathon?
All right, a couple of you, all right,
and I've never run one, but I started training,
and I got up to six miles and seven miles and eight miles,
and I thought, okay, we're making progress,
and then I did eight miles for a few times
in a particular two-week period of time,
and I had this thought, this is insane,
and I've not even made it close
to what a marathon would be,
and I never have run that distance again in my life.
Holly was training for a half marathon about a year ago,
and I ran out and ran five miles with her
to try to just accompany her on a run,
and I thought, you know, I used to play baseball.
You run like 90 feet to the base,
and you know, maybe if you hit a double or triple,
you know, whatever, a little bit longer,
but long-distance running, not my thing,
but I have seen races and long-distance running
where there's a measure of motivation
and encouragement from some onlookers.
To do what?
To continue.
Really, what is the thought?
Finish, finish.
Many times when you're looking at someone
that's running a marathon,
the course of the marathon is not necessarily
littered with onlookers for the entire duration
of that particular race,
but you will find that near the finish line,
there's a great host of people that are assembled,
and they're assembled near that finish line,
and they're cheering people on,
they're motivating them,
they're encouraging them to cross the finish line.
This morning, we're running a race.
The race that we're running is not a sprint.
The race that we're running is better described
as a marathon, and in this life, we're running this race.
The analogy is used throughout the scriptures.
We find it in Hebrews chapter number 12,
particularly where the Bible talks about
looking unto Jesus, the author and finisher
of our faith, and as we're looking unto Jesus,
as we're running, we're not growing weary,
we're not being overwhelmed, we're running this race,
we're giving, seeking to cross the finish line.
You say, pastor, when is the finish line?
Where is the finish line?
You know, the reality is that for every one of us,
the finish line might be at a different place,
unless the Lord Jesus Christ comes back
while we're still alive, and all of us
that are alive at that time, that'll be our finish line.
But I want you to understand that for Paul,
his finish line came way back.
In 2 Timothy chapter number four,
the time of my departure is at hand.
I have finished.
He crosses that finish line.
He understood that he was going to put off
this earthly tabernacle, and he was going to go
to be with Jesus, his savior, for he said,
to be absent from the body is to be present with the Lord,
and what great truth that is.
But I want you to understand that you never
are going to finish your race with joy
unless you purpose to do so.
In fact, in Acts chapter number 20,
Paul makes that declaration as he's speaking
to the very people that Timothy is now ministering to.
In Acts chapter number 20, Paul calls for the leaders
of the church at Ephesus to gather together
as he is on his way to Jerusalem,
and as he calls them to gather together,
he gives them some very important truth.
But one thing that he tells them is that he had a desire,
a purpose, to finish his course with joy.
We find this morning that now Timothy
is ministering in Ephesus, and Timothy is going
to receive this charge from Paul to keep,
to continue on, to do, to follow,
and as he's encouraging him, as he's giving him this charge,
he's gonna provide motivation and encouragement
so that he too might finish his course.
This morning, I desire to finish my course with joy.
I hope this morning that that's your desire as well.
I wanna finish strong.
I wanna finish what God has given me to do.
You know, there are a lot of people that start a race.
It's not about whether you start at the race.
Now, that's important, but we're only gonna talk
about finishing, finishing.
This morning, I've titled the message,
if you look at the back of the bulletin,
really hear from our text of scripture.
Notice in verse number 15, I read verse 13 and 14.
Look at verse 15, which in his times he shall show
who is the blessed and only potentate,
the King of kings and Lord of lords.
You know what the Apostle Paul is going to do here
in this text of scripture?
He's going to exalt and magnify the Lord Jesus Christ,
just like he does in Hebrews 12 and verse two,
and as we're running that race,
he says it in verse number one of Hebrews 12.
he talks about the race.
He says at the end of the verse, he says this,
let us run with patience the race that is set before us,
looking unto Jesus, the author and finisher of our faith.
And here in 1 Timothy chapter number six,
I believe there are three particular truths
that Paul gives to Timothy to motivate and encourage him,
but what he's doing is he's elevating
and magnifying the Lord Jesus Christ, why?
Because he's the one that we're running for.
He's the one that we're running for.
You know, you're not running for me,
you're not running for your spouse,
you're not running for your children,
you're not running for your parents,
you're not running for, you're running for Jesus,
you're running for the Lord.
And we find that if Paul is going to understand
what Timothy is going to endure,
and obviously he does because he's given
throughout these six chapters of this book,
this letter to Timothy, he's mentioned many things
about some of the difficulties
and understand with me this morning,
that when those difficulties come, we can get overwhelmed.
When those difficulties can come,
we can be tempted to throw in the towel, so to speak.
Those of you that ran a marathon,
just a couple of you raised your hand,
there was a point in that race,
there was a point in that time
that your body just wanted to stop.
You had to push through, you had to continue.
And we find this morning, these wonderful truths
that point our attention to Jesus Christ.
He is the one that we run for.
He is the one that we live for.
We sing the song, living for Jesus.
My theme verse for my life,
2 Corinthians 5 and verse number 15,
and Mady has made some things for me over the years,
knowing that that's my favorite Bible verse,
and I've summarized it,
because to write the whole verse out
is just too much to put on a shirt or something.
And I said it this way, I said,
here's how I think we can summarize it,
living for him who died for me.
And that's really what our goal should be,
because he is king of kings and Lord of lords.
Notice with me as we dig
into the text of scripture this morning,
what does Paul first remind Timothy of
when he's giving him this charge,
as he's closing this letter,
he reminds Timothy of God's power, his power.
I'm so thankful this morning
that we serve an omnipotent God,
a God who has all power.
I'm so thankful this morning
that we serve a God who is able to do
exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think.
I'm so thankful this morning
that our God appeared to Abraham
and he announced himself that he is El Shaddai,
the almighty God.
And then a chapter later,
he says to Abraham, is anything too hard for me?
Obviously understanding that you're the Lord God almighty,
that you are El Elyon, the strong one, the mighty one,
that there's nothing outside of your power.
There's no problem that's too big for God.
And I'm so thankful this morning
that as we are running this race,
as we're given this charge to keep,
to continue, that we're looking toward that finish line,
that we understand that all the things
that happen around us,
that we're serving a God who has all power.
He doesn't have most power.
He doesn't have some power.
He has all power.
In fact, he says in Matthew 28,
as he gives the great commission,
all power is given unto me in heaven and in earth.
Go ye therefore.
I mean, what a blessed truth.
What an understanding that we have
that our God has all power.
Where do we see it here?
Where notice with me in verse number 13,
Paul says, I give the charge in the sight of God.
And then notice this phrase, who quickeneth all things.
Understand with me this morning that he alone gives life.
He is the life giver.
He has the power to give life.
And I'm so thankful this morning
that he is the life giver.
Yes, we understand about this life that we have
as we talk about being living beings,
but I understand this morning
that there's a focus that I have
that goes beyond just the temporal life, if you will,
and that's the eternal life,
that he is the author of eternal life.
He is the only one that can provide salvation
for a soul, for an individual.
And I'm thankful this morning that he alone,
he said, I am the way, the truth, and the life.
No man cometh unto the Father but by me.
There's no other name under heaven given among men
whereby we must be saved.
That's what Peter says as he's preaching there
in Acts chapter number four.
I'm thankful that not only does he give me
this life here that I have,
but he's given me eternal life.
I was born, tomorrow's my birthday.
I was born on July 15th, 1980.
I'll be 44 years old tomorrow,
but I'm telling you that I'm thankful for that.
I'm thankful for that truth,
but I am so much, just great thankfulness
that on August 31st, 1997, I received eternal life.
I was born again.
See, to have one birth isn't enough.
To be born once is to die twice.
But if you're born twice, you only die once.
Because the Bible tells me and tells you
that the second death hath no power over us.
Hallelujah.
I mean, I want you to think about it
as we're thinking about the grind of life
and Timothy has been receiving this instruction
that there's false teachers there in Ephesus
and there's these problems in Ephesus
and Timothy, you gotta deal with all this stuff
and it can become overwhelming and say,
what, we're serving God.
Continue, Timothy.
Keep these things, Timothy.
Why?
Because you serve the Lord God Almighty.
You serve the God who is omnipotent.
We find that here in verse number 13,
he says that he quickeneth all things,
that he says before Christ Jesus,
who before Pontius Pilate witnessed a good confession.
Now, I think this is interesting as we look at this truth
at the end of verse number 13 with regard to Jesus Christ
and the reference that is made as I look at this
as God giving us the truth that he has all power.
You know that it was there in John 19
that Pontius Pilate thought he had some power.
Do you remember?
In John chapter 19, maybe you wanna turn over there
and I'm gonna read a couple of verses of scripture
for you from John 19.
Jesus Christ had already gone through
the process of some trials and now he stood there
before Pilate and all that's taken place
and we find that Pilate had asked a question about truth
and then he left and did not stick around for an answer
and then we come to the 19th chapter
and the trials continuing there before Pilate.
Pilate reenters into the presence.
He said a couple of times at the end of verse 18
and twice in the beginning of chapter 19,
I find no fault in him.
Why is that?
Because he's the perfect Lamb of God.
He is sinless, he is perfect, he is holy, he is pure.
The just for the unjust.
He did not have to make a sacrifice first for his own sin.
He was sinless, he simply made a sacrifice
for the sin of mankind.
But we find in the text of scripture in verse number 10,
I'll read verse number nine.
And when again into the judgment hall and saith unto Jesus,
whence art thou?
But Jesus gave him no answer.
Then saith Pilate unto him, speakest thou not unto me?
Notice what Pilate says.
Knowest thou not that I have power to crucify thee
and have power to release thee?
Now Pilate, I mean, from his perspective,
he did have some power.
But understand that Jesus is gonna set him straight.
And Jesus is gonna help him understand a perspective
that unfortunately sometimes humanity doesn't have.
You know, there's some people on this earth
that think they have power over people.
Listen, I'm thankful that as Jesus says here to Pilate
in verse number 11, Jesus does give an answer to this.
He says, thou couldest have no power at all against me
except it were given thee from above.
Therefore he that delivered me unto thee
hath the greater sin.
You know, I'm interested here in this text of scripture
as we look at the truth that Paul is giving to Timothy.
Continue, finish, why?
Because our God has all power.
Pilate said, I have power to crucify thee
and I have power to release thee.
And Jesus says, let me just help you understand.
You could have no power at all except I give it to you
except it were given thee from above.
I'm thankful this morning that Jesus finished the work.
He finished.
He went all the way to Calvary,
went all the way to the cross,
suffered and bled and died.
As he hung upon that cross,
several things that he cried out,
but one was this, it is finished.
Hallelujah.
With that, he gave up the ghost.
You know why it says that he gave up the ghost?
Because he laid down his life.
He willingly and freely offered his life
as a substitute for humanity.
Otherwise we'd be on our way to the lake of fire
with no hope whatsoever.
He finished.
Notice with me back in 1 Timothy chapter number six,
not only do we see that he quickeneth all things,
he alone is the one who gives life.
He witnessed a good confession,
but notice it says this in verse.
number 16, who only hath immortality. I want you to think about that. He is the
one that not only has the power to give life, but he is the one that has power
over death. He has power over death. The Bible tells us we understand as we read
through the pages of Scripture that he conquered sin, death, and the grave. He
triumphed over the enemy. He triumphed over Satan. We understand that he rose in
victory. Listen, during his earthly ministry, we see his power displayed
through the miracles, not only over nature and over disease, but we see his
power displayed over death. When you come to John chapter number 11, and both Mary
and Martha say, Jesus, if you had been here, our brother had not died. They
understood that Jesus had power to heal. He had power over disease. That's why
initially they even sent for Jesus, because their brother was sick. Jesus
loved him, but Jesus delayed. He didn't leave immediately, and he arrives right
on time, because he was going to show not only Mary and Martha, but all those that
were gathered, that not only does he have power over disease, but he has power
over death. And he says, roll that stone, he stinketh. He's been dead for four days.
Is that not the objection? Jesus says, Lazarus, come forth. He tells him, take
off the grave clothes and come walk. Could you imagine? Man, hallelujah. Listen, this
morning, our God conquered sin, death, and the grave. We find that he makes this
statement. You don't need to turn there in Revelation chapter 1, in verse 18, it
says, I am he that liveth and was dead. Behold, I am alive forevermore, amen, and
have the keys of hell and of death. I'm thankful this morning that the one for
whom we are running has all power. What motivation and encouragement that we
receive through this reminder. Number two, we understand his position. We see his
power, but then we also see in 1st Timothy chapter 6, his position. Notice
with me, in verse number 15, it says, in which in his times he shall show who is
the blessed and only potentate. The word literally means the only all-powerful
one. That's what it means, the only all-powerful one. By the way, there's
none like him. There's none like our God. He alone reigns. He alone is God. We find
this morning that here in the text of Scripture, it says, not only who is the
blessed and only potentate, the king of kings and Lord of lords. We read those
names ascribed to the Lord Jesus Christ in Revelation 17, in verse 14. We read it
in chapter 19, in verse number 16, that he is king of kings and Lord of lords. I
mean, what a contrast that is given to us in verse 15 about our Lord, about the one
who we're running for, the one that we're having our eyes on, compared
the contrast to the Roman emperors that would have been obviously known during
that day. No, no, no, no. Listen, we're serving God. We're not serving some man.
We're not running a race for some man. We're not running a race for some Roman
emperor. No, we're running the race for the only, that he is the blessed and only
potentate. We're running a race for the king of kings and Lord of lords.
Hallelujah. His position. In Isaiah 52, in verse number 7, the Bible says,
thy God reigneth. Aren't you thankful this morning that our God is on his throne?
We read in Revelation 19, in verse number 6, hallelujah, for the Lord God
omnipotent reigneth. It really reminds me of how Paul, in the first chapter of 1
Timothy, turned back, if you will. It was our January memory verse.
As Paul says this, in 1 Timothy 1 and verse 17, under the inspiration of the Holy
Spirit of God, now under the king eternal, immortal, invisible, the only wise God,
be honor and glory forever and ever. Listen, he's the one that we're running
for. He's the one that we got to have our eyes on. If Timothy is going to continue,
if Timothy is going to finish his course like Paul is going to finish his course,
if you are going to finish your course, if I am going to finish my course,
I must remember this morning, I must have this awareness this morning that he has
all power and he's the one that I'm running for. I must recognize this morning
and I must regularly remind myself of his position. Listen, we live in a world that's
chaotic. We live in a world that it seems like evil is just everywhere and ruling,
but understand that the heathen, they rage according to Psalm chapter number 2.
But you know what God's doing? He's sitting on his throne in Psalm 2.
He's not worried. He's not up in...you know what happens sometimes when we worry?
Sometimes people will kind of ring their...God's not ringing his hands.
God's not worried. God's not concerned. God's not sitting up in heaven saying,
what are we going to do? No, he's God and he reigns and he's in control.
His position motivates me. It encourages me because I'm running a race for God Almighty
who's on his throne. This morning, as we look at the text of Scripture,
we see not only that Paul reminds Timothy of the power of God, the position that God
has, but he reminds him, number 3, of God's plan. I'm so thankful this morning that God
has a plan. Have you ever made a plan? Sure you have. You have plans. Have you ever made
plans that didn't kind of go the way that you had hoped they would go? Sure you have.
There was a wrinkle. There was something that was unexpected. There was something you
didn't plan for. Something that was outside of your control. You know why that's the case?
Because we're mere men. We try to make plans, but we don't know what's on tomorrow. Right?
We try to make plans, but we can't control all the circumstances. But our God is outside
of time. Our God is the all-powerful one. Our God has a plan that nobody is going to
alter. No one can. You know they've been trying to alter His plan. I mean the enemy. They've
been trying to alter His plan throughout. If you read the page of the Old Testament,
even as you get into the New Testament, you begin to see how the enemy is trying to thwart
plan of God through all sorts of means. But understand with me this morning that at every
time the enemy has been unsuccessful. Why? Because God's plan is going to come to pass.
It is absolutely certain. Amen? I'm sure that you've made plans that you thought,
man, I went to, I mean, extremes to ensure that everything is going to happen. And then
the disappointment that comes when it doesn't work out the way that you thought it would.
It doesn't happen to God. Nothing has ever occurred to Him. He knows everything. Nothing's
ever surprised Him. He knows everything. I've said at times, and I'm sure you have as you've
sought to see your plan unfold, why I didn't think about that. It's never happened to God.
Notice His plan as it's given to us here in verse number 14. It says that thou keep this
commandment without spot, unrebukable notice until the appearing of our Lord Jesus Christ.
Now obviously God's plan goes beyond just His return, but here within the context of
1 Timothy chapter number 6, the aspect that is highlighted of God's plan that's given
to us here with regard to the charge that is issued to Timothy is the fact that Jesus
is coming again until the appearing of our Lord Jesus Christ. I believe as we look throughout
the pages of Scripture how we can rejoice in understanding this truth with regard to
the return of Jesus Christ. The fact that He said in John chapter number 14, let not
your heart be troubled. You believe in God, believe also in Me. In My Father's house are
many mansions. If it were not so, I would have told you. And then He says this, I go
to prepare a place for you. And if I go and prepare a place for you, I will come again
and receive you unto Myself that where I am, there ye may be also. Isn't that a wonderful
promise? He had given to the disciples in John chapter 13 much information with regard
to His going and being crucified and all that would take place.
and they were overwhelmed, but he says let not your heart be troubled. Listen,
there is no one, there is no situation, there is no circumstance that is going
to keep our God from coming back. Now I understand this morning that many times
we pray as John did, even so come Lord Jesus, we're looking for his
return, we're looking for his soon return, but understand that he's not coming back
on your timetable or on my timetable. He's coming back at the exact right
moment. Now would I like to be alive when it happens? Hallelujah.
We'll look at that passage in just a moment of 1 Thessalonians, what a great
truth it is, but I want to remind you of what happened in Acts chapter number 1.
See this is a truth that goes throughout the the New Testament, the church as we
have understood this teaching of the return of the Lord Jesus Christ, and even
as Paul would give this charge to Timothy in motivating him and
encouraging him, why? Because Jesus is coming again. In Acts chapter number 1,
the resurrection had already taken place, Jesus was there for 40 days, and he was
teaching and all that he was doing, and now he's going to ascend to heaven. He
gives the Great Commission, it's recorded in Acts chapter 1 and verse number 8, and
in verse 9, as soon as he finishes giving the Great Commission, this is when
he'd spoken these things, while they beheld he was taken up, and a cloud
received him out of their sight. And while they looked steadfastly toward
heaven as he went up, behold, two men stood by them in white apparel, which
also said, Ye men of Galilee, why stand ye gazing up into heaven? Notice these
words, this saying Jesus, which has taken up from you into heaven, shall so come
in like manner as you have seen him go into heaven. I believe that this truth
that is given in Acts 1 and verse 11 served as a great motivator for the
early church. You read the book of Acts and you can read that even the
opposition of the disciples, those that opposed Christianity, if you will, that
they say of the disciples that you have filled Jerusalem with your doctrine. And
then later in chapter 17, they say that they've turned the world upside down.
These that have turned the world upside down have come hither also. And we find
that as you look at those truths that are mentioned, those statements that are
given, even from those that oppose the work, that they're acknowledging that the
early church was a church that was motivated to get the gospel to every
creature. Why? Because Jesus is coming back. The last thing they heard before he
ascended to heaven and before the angels said he's going to come back in like
manner was, ye shall be witnesses unto me, both in Jerusalem and Judea and Samaria
and unto the uttermost part of the earth. That's what the Lord has commissioned us
to do. Now many today, when is he going to come back? People have written books
trying to set a time. You can go on the internet and I do not suggest that you
do. Go back to my message from 1 Timothy chapter number 4, how's your diet? You
got to be careful what you're watching and what you're listening to, what you're
reading. There's a lot of stuff out there that's not for us to consume. There's
people that have all kinds of theories and this thing happens and that happens
and all these things with regard to, listen, I don't know when he's coming but
I know he's coming. And you know what the amazing thing is? I don't really need to
know when he's coming. And actually it's better for us if we don't know when he's
coming because it motivates us to do what we're supposed to do. Because as I
understand that I want to be found faithful, I want to be found when he
returns doing what I'm supposed to be doing, I do not want, as we read in 1
John 2 and chapter 3, I do not desire to be ashamed of him at his appearing. Amen?
So Paul says to Timothy, keep. Keep doing. Fulfill. Continue. For how long? Until the
appearing of our Lord Jesus Christ. Finish strong. Finish well. 1 Thessalonians
chapter 4, a favorite passage of Scripture, as I look here and consider
this truth of our Lord Jesus Christ coming back and I'll get to the mockers
and the scoffers in just a moment. We find in 1 Thessalonians 4 and verse 13,
the Bible begins by saying this, but I would not have you to be
ignorant, brethren, concerning them which are asleep, that you sorrow not even as
others which have no hope. I don't want you to be ignorant, I want you to be
informed. I want you to understand something. I want you to have truth
regarding those that are asleep, those who have died. And he says this, that you
sorrow not even as others which have no hope. So obviously we understand that the
book is written to a local church, the church of Thessalonica. A church is made
up of individuals that have been saved and baptized. They are the people of God.
They're Christians. They're heaven-bound. And we find that he says in verse number
14, for if we believe that Jesus died and rose again, and we do, even so them also
which sleep in Jesus will God bring with him. For this we say unto you, notice
these words, by the word of the Lord. This is not Paul sitting up at a Q&A
time and saying, well let me give you my opinion, here's what I think is going to
happen. No. Paul says I'm telling you this by the word of the Lord, that we which
are alive and remain under the coming of the Lord shall not prevent them which
are asleep. Now I hope I'm part of that group. Amen? I really do. I think it'd be
awesome to be alive when the trumpet of the Lord sounds. I really do. But I don't
know. I could die tomorrow. I could die today. We have no idea. David said there's
but a step between me and death. And that's true for every single human being.
Says that we shall not prevent them which are asleep or go before them. Verse 16, for
the Lord himself, remember what it said in Acts 1 and verse 11, this same Jesus.
Listen, he's not sending an angel. Amen? He's coming himself. In verse 16, for the
Lord himself shall descend from heaven with a shout, with the voice of the
archangel, with the trump of God, and the dead in Christ shall rise first. Then we
which are alive and remain shall be caught up together with them in the
clouds to meet the Lord in the air and so shall we ever be with the Lord. Wherefore,
notice verse 18, comfort one another with these words, how comforting these words
are. I'm thankful this morning that my God has a plan. His plan is extensive. For
sake of the message this morning, the aspect of God's plan that is zeroed in
on is his return. His return. Why is it that that aspect of the plan of God
would be zeroed in on? Because there's a motivation, there's an encouragement
that's given to Timothy with regard to continue to do what God has called
him to do. And as he's going to receive this charge and as this motivation and
this encouragement is given, there's an understanding that Timothy, you have
to remember that our God has all power. You have to remember, Timothy,
that our God, he is on his throne. His position is that he is King of kings and
Lord of lords. And Timothy, you have to remember that God has a plan. And God's
plan is that he's coming back. That's part of his plan. Remember I said a
moment ago that there are scoffers and there are mockers according to what we
read in 2 Peter. The Bible says that these folks were there in the first
century. Can I tell you this morning they continue to be here in our day and age
as well. In 2 Peter chapter number 3, these scoffers and mockers and they're
asking about when is the time of his appearing. In 2 Peter chapter 3,
beginning in verse number 1, the Bible says, The second epistle, beloved, I now
write unto you, in both which I stir up your pure minds by way of remembrance.
They may be mindful of the words which were spoken before by the holy prophets
under the commandment of us the apostles of the Lord and Savior, knowing this
first, that there shall come in the last days scoffers walking after their own
lust. And here's what it says that they'll say, Where is the promise of his
coming? Where's the promise of his coming? And notice the rest of the verse says
this, For since the fathers fell asleep, all things continue as they were from
the beginning of the creation. So they're going to say where's the promise of his
coming and they're gonna try to to cloak that if you will with this
statement that everything continues as it ever has been. And then in verse 5,
it's interesting, it says this, For this they willingly are ignorant of. You know
there are some people that we come in contact with that are willingly ignorant.
It's almost as if they would say it this way, Don't confuse me with the facts.
Don't confuse me with the truth.
Why?
Because I wanna believe what I wanna believe.
And I wanna believe what I wanna believe
regardless of what anyone says including God and his word
because I already have settled what I wanna believe.
And so of this they are willingly ignorant.
Notice it continues that by the word of God
the heavens were of old
and the earth standing out of the water and in the water
whereby the world that then was being overflowed
with water perished.
Now what's he talking about?
The flood.
Do you know how many people are attacking
the Genesis record of the flood?
Why are they attacking it?
You say, pastors, just Genesis doesn't really matter.
Oh, it matters so much
because if the Genesis record isn't true
then how do we know anything is true?
Verse seven, but the heavens and the earth
which are now by the same word are kept in store
reserved under the fire against the day of judgment
and the perdition of ungodly men.
But then in verse eight it says this,
but beloved, be not ignorant of this one thing
that one day is with the Lord as a thousand years
and a thousand years as one day.
Now why does he say that?
Well, we are bound by time.
Everything that we do is time-sensitive.
You buy a product, there's an expiration date.
Right, am I not telling the truth?
But listen, bottled water has an expiration date.
It does.
It's like five years,
but I mean, it's got an expiration date.
Milk has an expiration date.
Cheat, I mean, you go through it, it has an expiration date.
Everything that we do is bound by time.
Sometimes it's so hard with children,
they don't understand time.
How many of you can remember when you're little kids,
they wanna know, especially if you're taking a road trip,
are we there yet?
20 more minutes.
They don't know what 20 minutes is.
20 minutes to my kids was a long time.
But understand that as we grow older,
we get a greater awareness of time.
You start talking in measurements of time of months
to a little kid.
Well, we're gonna go on vacation in nine months.
They can't understand that.
But for us, nine months is like that.
It's July, it's the middle of July right now.
It seems like we just were having a new year, right?
It just goes so quick.
But see, God is outside of time.
And so he says this in verse number nine,
the Lord is not slack concerning his promise.
I love that terminology, why?
Because every promise that God has given will come to pass.
He is not slack concerning his promise.
I don't know if you've ever said something
that then you kind of step back and you regret it,
saying it, saying, man, I wish I didn't say that.
I wish, not that it was a sinful thing,
but you made a commitment, you made a promise.
I remember promising Juliana something
when she was a little girl.
I've used the illustration before.
I told her, Bart, I promise on Saturday
we're gonna go do this.
And Saturday came and it was pouring rain.
And the activity was outside.
We weren't gonna be able to do it.
You know, she looked at me and she said,
but daddy, you promised.
Man, that was, I did.
And I said, honey, I'm not God.
I have no control over this.
I said, Jesus, this is what I told her.
I said, Jesus, when he was in the midst of the storm,
he was able to say, peace be still.
And the winds and the waves obeyed and it was calm.
But daddy doesn't have that kind of power.
I told her that.
And she kind of calmed down.
But you know what I learned?
I didn't promise her anything anymore.
I didn't.
I'll do my best to do that.
We'll plan to do that.
But I tried to take that word promise out
because I can't control the circumstances,
but God controls everything.
The Lord is not slack concerning his promises.
Some men cannot slackness,
but his long suffering to us word.
Notice where it says, not willing that any should perish,
but that all should come to repentance.
Why hasn't he come back yet?
Because he's long suffering.
Remember what Paul told Timothy in the beginning
of this book of 1 Timothy.
He said, this is a faithful saying
and worthy of all acceptation
that Christ Jesus came into the world
to save sinners of whom I am chief.
So Jesus came to save humanity.
And so he has a desire for people to be saved.
And that of course is his plan.
And so with regard to the aspect of the plan of his return,
he's not slack concerning his promise.
He is going to come back, but he's long suffering.
Why?
Because he's not willing that any should perish,
but that all should come to repentance.
Back in the text of scripture,
it says in verse 16 in 1 Timothy 6,
who only hath immortality dwelling in the light,
which no man can approach unto whom no man hath seen,
nor can see to whom be honor and power everlasting.
Amen.
Isn't that exciting?
I mean, just the climax, if you will,
of how this charge is given.
The text continues in verse 17
through the end of the chapter,
really highlighting on some truth
with regard to now giving a charge to those
that's already been referenced earlier in the chapter
in verse 17, charge them that are rich in this world.
Now, remember the problem of verse number nine
was not they that are rich,
but they that will be rich.
That's their motivation.
That's their drive.
That's all they're consumed with.
It's not a problem to be rich.
It's a problem if that's our driving, motivating,
all I'm living for is to get rich.
That's a problem.
But so he says, charge them that are rich in the world,
that they be not high-minded,
nor trust in their uncertain riches.
You know, there's a lot of people
that trust in uncertain riches.
But what?
In the living God.
Who?
Giveth us richly all things to enjoy.
I'm thankful that our God is a benevolent God.
He's a giving God.
For God so loved the world
that he gave his only begotten Son,
that whosoever believeth in him should not perish,
but have everlasting life, the greatest gift,
the unspeakable gift.
It says in verse 18 that they do good,
that they be rich in good works,
ready to distribute, willing to communicate,
laying up in store for themselves a good foundation
against the time to come,
that they may lay hold on eternal life.
Remember this truth of having the focus of eternity,
not the temporary.
So often we can get caught up living in the temporary,
the mundane, the monotonous, but no,
we as God's people,
we look not at those things which are temporal,
but those things which are eternal.
And we find that he had said to Timothy in verse number 12,
the good fight of faith, lay hold on eternal life.
And I mentioned this even as we see it in verse number 19.
It's not the idea that you're somehow
going to get eternal life.
It's rather the idea that because you have eternal life,
you are a possessor of eternal life.
You ought to also be a professor of eternal life.
You're to be living like you're saved.
Oh, Timothy, verse 20.
Keep that which is committed to thy trust,
avoiding profane and vain babblings
and oppositions of science, falsely so called,
which some professing have erred concerning the faith.
Grace be with thee.
Amen.
This morning, we're not in Ephesus and we're not Timothy.
But this morning, if you're saved by the grace of God,
you're running a race.
And just as Paul is seeking to motivate
and encourage Timothy to finish his race,
I believe this morning that we too are being motivated
and encouraged to finish our race.
When times get hard, when we just want to give up,
what's the point?
No, no, don't go down that path of thinking.
Fix your attention on our King of Kings and Lord of Lords,
our God, our Savior, the one for whom we are running.
And remember his power.
He has all power.
I am weak, but he is strong.
His strength is made perfect in weakness.
2 Corinthians 12.
We must remember this morning that our God has all power.
Remember his position,
that he is the blessed and only potentate,
literally the only all powerful one.
He is King of Kings and Lord of Lords.
Thy God reigneth.
You say, pastor, it's chaotic, things are crazy.
I know, but God's on his throne.
None of it surprised God.
You say, I read the news and I was surprised.
God wasn't.
Rest in knowing that thy God reigneth.
And number three, remember his plan.
Are you looking for, as he would say to Titus,
the blessed hope and glorious appearing
of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ.
Listen for the trumpet, the songwriter said.
Jesus is coming. Hallelujah. This morning, I want to finish well. I want to finish strong.
I want to continue our theme for this year, continue. You say, but all these things are
against us. If God be for us, who can be against us? Remember, we are more than conquerors
through Him, but thanks be to God, which giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus
Christ. This morning, we serve the King of Kings and Lord of Lords, and He is worthy
of all of our worship, and He is worthy this morning of us continuing, continuing, pressing
on, finishing. He's worthy. Let's pray. Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. We
thank you for your Word, the truth contained therein. We thank you for this letter that
we've been able to study over these months, the encouragement, instruction that we have
received. And Lord, this morning, I pray that you would help us, even as Timothy was receiving
this charge and being reminded of these truths, Lord, so that he would continue, so that he
would finish. I pray that you would help us to rejoice in knowing that you have all power,
your position is settled. We have a plan that will never be altered. And God, I pray you'd
help us to keep our eyes on Jesus, the author and finisher of our faith. God, if there's
one here this morning or one that's tuned in via live stream that's not sure of heaven,
I pray that today they'd be saved. They'd trust the Lord Jesus Christ as their personal
Savior. Maybe this morning there's someone here or on live stream that's struggling,
they're overwhelmed, they're just dealing with it. God, I pray that you'd encourage
them to continue. I pray, Lord, that for the one that has their eyes on you, would you
help us to continue in that same manner. Help us not to be distracted. Help us not
to be detoured. No, help us to continue. I pray that in this moment, this time of invitation
that you'd have your will and way, I pray that your people would respond. Do business
with God this morning. And I pray that you'd be honored and glorified, that you'd be exalted
through every decision that's made. Well, thank you for it in Christ's name. We pray.