Verses 7 through 10 is a familiar passage of Scripture
to many of God's people.
In fact, it's one that perhaps you've heard someone
preach on, you've heard somebody reference
the portion of Scripture.
Maybe you have even memorized part of this passage
that I'm gonna preach this morning.
I believe this morning that the truth
that is contained within this passage
is a truth that it's imperative that every child of God
truly understands and grasps this truth.
We notice in verse number seven,
I'm actually gonna back up and look at verse number six,
five, sorry, in verse number five,
notice what Paul says.
He says, of such in one will I glory,
yet of myself I will not glory, but in mine infirmities.
For though I would desire to glory, I should not be a fool.
For I will say the truth, but now I forbear,
lest any man should think of me
above that which he seeth me to be,
or that he heareth of me.
So in the first six verses,
I only read the last couple of them,
verse five and six, we find that Paul
is referencing some visions, according to verse number one,
that he, visions and revelations
that are received of the Lord.
But it wasn't only glory in those things,
but we find that Paul was privileged to see
and to have those visions and revelations.
He also mentions in the text of Scripture
that he was not able, it was unlawful for him to speak
or to utter these things.
And many times I've heard people through the years say,
someone had this vision or someone had this experience.
And I've often replied back to them and said this,
if Paul wasn't permitted to talk about the visions
and revelations that he received,
I'm not listening to the vision or revelation
that you think you received,
because the Bible also tells us in this very book
that the devil, the enemy,
he transforms himself into an angel of light.
And so we must be careful, we must understand the truth
of 1 John to try the spirits.
But notice, with understanding all these revelations
and visions that Paul received,
he starts in verse seven and says,
and lest I should be exalted above measure
through the abundance of the revelations,
notice, there was given to me a thorn
in the flesh.
Now, this isn't really part of the message
or the bulk of the message this morning,
but I want you to consider what Paul says
in verse number seven.
He says, there was given to me a thorn in the flesh.
I want you to acknowledge that Paul recognized this morning
that this thorn in the flesh that he references,
it was given to him.
It was on purpose, it had a purpose,
it was given to him by God.
And Paul recognized that.
Listen, nothing in your life happens by accident.
Nothing in my life happens by accident.
We find that God is in control of all things.
We find that God was giving to Paul this thorn in the flesh.
Notice it says, the messenger of Satan to buffet me,
lest I should be exalted above measure.
Now notice in verse eight, for this thing,
for what thing, this thorn in the flesh,
I besought the Lord thrice that it might depart from me.
So Paul prayed on three different occasions,
specifically prayed that this would be removed,
that he says that it might be depart from me,
that it might depart from me.
Have you ever had a situation,
you pray and you ask God that it would depart from you?
Come on, we pray, God,
would you help this thing depart from me, right?
I don't wanna deal with this thing.
I don't wanna deal with this infirmity.
I don't wanna have this issue.
I don't wanna have this problem.
I don't want this heartache.
I don't want this obstacle.
Are you with me this morning?
You pray that God would remove it.
By the way, aren't you thankful that God can remove it?
Amen, you pray that he would remove it
because you know that he has the power to do so.
But we find this morning that sometimes
as we look at our text this morning,
it is not always within the will of God
that he will remove from your life or my life,
what we desire for him to remove from our lives.
Now, it doesn't mean that he cannot.
It simply means that it's not within his will.
It means that he has a greater purpose in that thing
than maybe we understand or recognize
at the particular moment.
We can look through the gospel records.
We can see as the Lord Jesus Christ is walking
upon the face of the earth in his earthly ministry,
and we can see many times in which God healed
and God performed miracles,
but we find that there were certain times
in which God led his people directly into difficulty
to prove himself and to increase their faith.
And this morning, we find that Paul,
because he understood the power of God,
because he experienced the work of God in his life,
he prays that God would remove this thing from his life,
this thorn in the flesh.
He says, I besought the Lord.
Listen, this is earnest prayer.
This wasn't just a passing, Lord, would you?
No, he's earnestly seeking, he's beseeching the Lord
that it might depart from me.
And I want you to notice in verse number nine,
and he, that's God, said unto me, that's Paul,
my grace is sufficient for thee,
for my strength is made perfect in weakness.
Most gladly, therefore, will I rather glory
in my infirmities that the power of Christ
may rest upon me.
Therefore, I take pleasure in infirmities
and reproaches and necessities and persecutions
and distresses for Christ's sake,
for when I am weak, then am I strong.
This morning, if you're taking notes,
I want you to notice number one, the promise explained.
The promise explained in verse number nine.
We find that God replies, responds to the request of Paul,
according to verse number eight,
that he would remove this thing from his life,
and God's response is given to us in verse number nine,
and there are two elements to this promise
that are explained to us,
and I want you to notice number one.
It's very simple truth, but it says, number one,
my grace is sufficient for thee.
I'm thankful this morning to know the grace of God.
I'm thankful this morning
to have experienced the grace of God.
We sang about God's grace this morning,
wonderful grace of Jesus.
Listen, you're saved by grace, amen?
For by grace are you saved through faith.
And Ephesians two and verse number eight,
we understand that truth,
and we find that God is a gracious God.
He reveals to us throughout the pages of scripture.
Remember all the way back in Genesis,
the Bible says that Noah found grace
in the eyes of the Lord.
I'm thankful that our God is a gracious God.
Yes, he's merciful and he's holy
in all of the attributes of God,
but this morning, just for a moment,
we're gonna focus our attention
upon this truth of God's grace,
and he has a limitless supply of grace.
I mean, he's not restricted
by too many people needing grace.
No, he is gracious.
His grace will never be exhausted in your life
or in my life or in our lives collectively.
He says, my grace, my grace.
Have you ever tried to be gracious with someone?
And you try to be gracious with someone,
you try to be gracious with someone,
and you say, my grace is kind of running out.
Have you ever been there?
You ever feel that way?
You say, I know I'm supposed to be gracious, right?
Speak, we're supposed to speak,
our speech is supposed to be with grace, right?
How many times our speech hasn't been with grace, right?
We say, my grace is being exhausted here.
You're testing me, you're pushing me to my limits.
And some of you are like, man,
I was there this morning, amen?
But you understand, listen, God's grace is sufficient.
God's grace is limitless.
There's no exhausting the grace of God,
and here we find that God says to Paul,
my grace is sufficient for thee.
And I find in this truth of God's grace being amazing,
and certainly it is, and we sing amazing grace,
how sweet the sound.
We speak about God's grace being abundant.
We see that as Paul testifies of his own personal conversion
as he's speaking to Timothy in 1 Timothy,
and he talks about God's grace being abundant in his life.
And here we find that as Paul is writing
to this church in Corinth
and he's rehearsing his own personal experience,
this promise is being explained
that my grace, God says, is sufficient for thee.
But God, I'm suffering with this thorn in the flesh.
God, this thorn in the flesh is hindering my ability
from a human perspective of what I could accomplish
and so on and so forth.
And God, I think it'd be so much better
if I didn't have this thorn in the flesh.
And God says, my grace is sufficient for thee.
Notice the second element of the promise
as we look at this truth of the promise explained.
We find that the second element,
Jesus says not only is my grace,
my grace is sufficient for thee,
but he says my strength is made perfect in weakness.
Whose strength?
Well, God's strength.
How much strength does he have?
all power, all authority. He is the omnipotent God. He
rules and He reigns. He said, let there be light, and
there was light. He spoke and it was done. We find that He
has all power. Brother Jeff this morning referenced one
of the miracles as he was dealing with the life of
Gideon there of the impotent man at the pool of Bethesda.
And that impotent man met the omnipotent God, the One who
has all power. That man had no power, but God has all
power. And He says, my strength is made perfect in
weakness. Now here's the thing. We don't like to be
weak. We feel vulnerable. We don't like to be weak. We
like, we like to have it figured out. Can you relate?
We want to, we want to have the answers we're going to
be able to do. But, but here we find that, that Christ
is giving a, a truth to Paul, but not just to Paul, to us
as well as it's preserved in His Word. And it's a promise
that is being explained that God's strength is made
perfect in weakness. I want you to go back to 1
Corinthians chapter 1 just for a moment. And I want you
to look, Paul had previously written to this church in
the, the first letter of 1 Corinthians as he sends this
letter to them. But I want you to consider with me some
of what God says here in the first chapter as Paul is
speaking to this church. And we know it's a carnal
church. And there's definitely been some growth as
you look at 2 Corinthians. And we'll deal with that
throughout the year. But notice in verse number 23,
but we preach Christ crucified unto the Jews a
stumbling block and unto the Greeks foolishness. But unto
them which are called, both Jews and Greeks, Christ the
power of God and the wisdom of God. Notice this, because
the foolishness of God is wiser than men. The weakness
of God is stronger than men. For ye see your calling,
brethren, how that not many wise men after the flesh, not
many mighty, not many noble, are called. But God hath
chosen the foolish things of the world to confound the
wise. God hath chosen the weak things of the world to
confound the things which are mighty. And base things of
the world and things which are despised hath God chosen,
yea, and things which are not to bring to naught things
that are why, that no flesh should glory in His presence.
Brother Jeff hasn't gotten there yet in the Sunday
school class with Gideon, but you know why the army got
shrunk down to 300? Because he said, if I give you the
victory with the large number you're going to think you
got the victory. That no flesh should glory in His
presence. We acknowledge it's all because of the grace of
God. In fact, Paul would say that, I am what I am by the
grace of God. We find that God's strength is made
perfect in weakness. I'm reminded of what the Bible
says in John chapter number 1. Turn over quickly if you
will to John chapter number 1 as we read this very
important passage of Scripture dealing with the truth of
the Incarnation and the eternality of the Lord Jesus
Christ. In John chapter number 1 the Bible begins in
verse number 1, In the beginning was the Word, and
the Word was with God, and the Word was God. The same was
in the beginning with God. All things were made by Him.
Without Him was not anything made that was made. In Him
was life, and the life was the light of men. Isn't that
wonderful? I'm going to skip down to verse number 14. The
Bible says, And the Word was made flesh, and dwelt among
us. Now the Word that's referenced in verses 1 and
following we find then referenced in verse 14. In the
beginning was the Word, the Word was with God, and the
Word was God. And then in verse 14, And the Word was
made flesh. That's the Incarnation. And dwelt among
us, and we beheld His glory. The glory is of the only
begotten of the Father. Notice what this says, Full of
grace and truth. John bare witness of Him, and cried,
saying, This was He of whom I spake. He that cometh after
me is preferred before me. Why? For He was before me the
eternality of Christ. And of His fullness have all we
received, and grace for grace. For the law was given by
Moses, but grace and truth came by Jesus Christ. No man
hath seen God at any time. The only begotten Son, which is
in the bosom of the Father, He hath declared Him. He's full
of grace. He's gracious. The promise is explained. I want
you to notice, He says, My grace is sufficient for thee.
And then He says, My strength is made perfect in weakness.
Just for a moment in 2 Corinthians chapter 12 as we
consider the promise being explained, I want you to
notice that little word, is. That little word, is. My
grace is sufficient for thee. My strength is made perfect
in weakness. The Bible does not say that My grace was
sufficient for thee. The Bible does not say My grace will
be sufficient for thee. The Bible says My grace is
sufficient for thee. Listen, I understand that sometimes we
can talk about the past. I understand sometimes we can
worry about the future. You say, oh pastor we don't worry.
Come on, we know we do. I understand the Bible says be
careful for nothing. But there are times in your life, there
are times in my life that we're not perfect in obedience.
Amen. There are times that we worry about things, and we
talk about the past, and we worry about the future. But
you know where we live? We live in the present. You can't
live in the past, and you can't live in the future. All you
can do is live in the present. So you know what God says? My
grace is sufficient for thee. He didn't say it was, or it
will be. He said it is. So you know what that means to me?
That means to me, and it means to you this morning when this
promise is explained, that today in my circumstance today,
in my situation today, in the obstacle today, in the
infirmity, the difficulty, His grace is today sufficient for
me. And it's important that we understand that little word is.
You say it's so little word, but it's so important. The
promise is being explained to us. God Almighty, the Creator
of the universe, the One who formed you and me, the One who
knows our thoughts. He knows everything about us. He knows
the hairs on our head. He knows our thoughts. He knows our
cares. He says my grace is sufficient for thee. And it's
so mightily important, it's imperative that we understand
this promise that's being explained to us this morning.
And it's something that Paul is receiving from the Lord.
He's receiving this word. He prayed. God said my grace is
sufficient. My grace is sufficient. We see here in the
text, not only the promise explained, but we see a
response here of Paul that I believe is revealing an
exemplary. If you're taking notes, number two, consider
this. Not only the promise explained, but number two, the
promise embraced. The promise embraced. I'm thankful that
God explains the promise to us. I'm thankful that God
recorded verse number nine in our Bible so that we could see
the promise explained. That we could understand that when
Paul said, has he besought the Lord thrice that it might
depart from me, that the Bible doesn't just simply say that
God said no. But that the answer was my grace is
sufficient for thee, for my strength is made perfect in
weakness. But then we see this response. And we find the
promise is understood as God explained this to Paul. And
the promise is explained, but now the promise is embraced.
The word embraced means to seize eagerly. It means to lay
hold on. I want you to understand this morning that
this truth of 2 Corinthians chapter 12 is not something
cliché for the Christian. It's not some cliché that the
Christian is to use for marketing purposes or
advertisement. We find that there are many times in which
even the thought, my grace is sufficient for thee, or as
we've worded it, God's grace is sufficient for our theme for
this year. Listen, it's not just a cliché for marketing
purposes. It is a Bible truth that God has given to us that
must be embraced by us. See, the promises of God are
important. And we find that God has given us many promises.
In fact, Peter would say that they're exceeding great and
precious promises. But we find that in the beginning of this
book, 2 Corinthians, in chapter 1 and verse number 20, I want
you to notice what the Bible says. Because we find that
this promise is explained that we're dealing with, and then
it's embraced. But notice what Paul says in 2 Corinthians
chapter 1 and verse number 20, for all the promises of God in
Him are yea, and in Him, amen, unto the glory of God by us.
Aren't you amazed?
you thankful? Listen, the Apostle Paul, the Lord was
revealing and giving him truth. We know all scripture
is given by inspiration of God with regard to all the
promises of God. In him are yea and in him amen. Listen,
our God cannot lie. Aren't you thankful for that? I mean,
he can't lie. Every promise in the book is mine. Every
chapter, every verse, every line. That's what the
songwriter said. And we look at the promise and listen,
it's not just about an intellectual exercise of being
able to know the promises to being able to rehearse the
promises to be able to recite the promises. No, it must
be that we embrace them personally, that we take the
promise that God has given in his word and not just
memorize it, not just share it for someone else, but we
embrace it personally. That we understand as we look at
this text of scripture that the Apostle Paul, he
embraced this promise. I mean, the almighty God gave
him a promise and it's embraced. And I would submit
to you this morning that for each of us here, that we
look at this passage of scripture and that we too
would embrace the promise that's been revealed, that we
would understand that in every scenario of my life, in
every scenario of your life, in every situation that we
face, that we claim embrace the promise of God, that
God's grace is sufficient. You ever been in a place
where you say, I just don't think I could go on. I just
don't think I could do this anymore. This is too much
for me. There are times that you feel that way. And by
the way, God knows our frame. Aren't you thankful for
that? He knows that we're but dust. We have an enemy
that's relentless. David, at one point in his life, he
fled and went to Philistine territory because Saul and
all that was taking place got to be too much for him.
We have an enemy. There are times in your life and in my
life that we can take a wrong perspective and a wrong
approach and say, what's it worth? I just can't do this
anymore. I'm just ready to throw in the towel. No. I'm
going to continue. Why? Because God's grace is
sufficient. And I'm going to embrace that promise. Notice
in the text, we see how Paul embraced this promise.
Notice what he says. In verse 9, we see the promise. And
he, speaking of God, said to me, speaking of Paul, my
grace is sufficient for thee. For my strength is made
perfect in weakness. And then notice what Paul says. This
is the embracing of the promise. He understood it. It
was explained. He says, most gladly therefore, because of
this promise, because of understanding what God
Almighty has just revealed to me, most gladly therefore,
will I rather glory in my infirmities. Why? That the
power of Christ may rest upon me. We want the power of
God to rest upon you. We want God's power in my life. I
want to be used for the glory of God. I want God to, as it
says here, that my strength is made perfect in weakness.
And Paul, dealing with this thorn in the flesh, and we
don't understand all that it was. There are many that
have concluded and they've assumed that it has to do
with his eyesight. And I understand the reasons why
they would reach the conclusion. But we don't know
with a hundred percent certainty. But I want you to
understand this morning that Paul says, because God made
this truth known to me, that His grace is sufficient and
that His strength is made perfect in my weakness, that
I'm going to, and he says, most gladly therefore, I'm
going to glory in my infirmities. Well, that's a
different perspective, is it not? It's not natural to
glory in your infirmities. It's not natural as a human
being to glory in your infirmities. To complain about
your infirmities would be a natural response as a human
being. Am I not right? But Paul says, most gladly
therefore, most gladly therefore, will I rather glory
in my infirmities. Why? That the power of Christ may rest
upon me. Paul's embracing this promise. He's believing
God. He's saying, God told me as I sought Him that this
thing would be sought Him, so that this thing would depart
from me, that God said, my grace is sufficient for Thee,
that my strength is made perfect in weakness. And so
Paul has this response. It's a response of embracing, to
seize it eagerly, to lay hold on it, to apply it in his
life. And he says that he would glory in his infirmities.
Not only does he say that in verse 9, but we find in verse
number 10, it says, therefore. We've used this little
phrase before. You've heard it, no doubt. Therefore, when
you see a therefore in the Bible, you find out what it's
therefore. And he says, therefore, because of this
revealed truth, because of the promise that has been
explained, because of what I've understood that God has
communicated to me, not only did he say in verse 9, I will
glory in my infirmities, but he says in verse 10, I take
pleasure, notice what he says, in infirmities, in
reproaches, in necessities, in persecutions, in
distresses, for Christ's sake. There are many things that
Paul suffered because he followed Jesus. He's not
speaking about things that he would suffer because of his
own sin, because of his own wrongdoing. No, he's talking
about the things that he would suffer for following Christ.
There are many times we could study through the book of
Acts, as we have in years past, where you find that the
apostle Paul, he faced these great levels of difficulty,
and distresses, and persecutions, simply because he
was following Jesus and preaching the gospel. And so
when he's speaking about these things, he's speaking
about taking pleasure and understanding that God was
going to give him the strength, that God was going to
supernaturally, through his grace and through his power,
he was going to enable Paul to carry forth and to do what
God had called him to do. He says, for when I am weak,
then am I strong. For when I am weak, then am I strong.
We find that even, as you read the book of 1 and 2
Corinthians, there's truth revealed to us with regard to
really the perspective that many had of the appearance,
the stature of Paul. And we find that it was God's power
that was seen in him and through him. We find that Paul
is saying, I'm taking pleasure, I'm glorying in. Why?
Because I understand this promise. It's a full embrace.
It's a full embrace. This morning, the testimony, as we
look here at this passage, is a testimony of an individual
who not only knew the promise of God, but he personally
embraced, most importantly embraced, the promise of God.
And this morning and throughout 2025, our theme will be
God's grace is sufficient. And can I tell you this morning
that we need to see it in our lives every day.
We live in the present and God says my grace is sufficient.
God's grace is sufficient. And it's by the grace of God,
this promise is one that must be embraced. How am I going to
do this? How am I going to? Listen, if God's called you to
do it, he'll empower you to do it. And his grace will enable
you because his grace is sufficient. You say, I can't do
this. You're right, but God can do it through you if he's
called you to do it because his grace is sufficient.
And this morning and throughout 2025, I want us in our lives,
those of us that have been saved by the grace of God to
experience daily that God's grace is sufficient and that we
would give God the glory for his grace in our lives every day
because God's grace is sufficient. And we begin to live
life every day with this thought in our minds, saturated in our
hearts that God's grace is sufficient. And we pause as we
face that obstacle, that difficulty, that opposition,
whatever it might be. We say, God, you said that your grace
was sufficient. God, I'm trusting you. I'm embracing the
promise that you gave because God, I need your grace this
morning. I need your grace. I need your grace in this moment.
And I understand that your grace, you're full of grace.
It's not going to be.
be exhausted. Your grace is sufficient. And I hope that as we go through 2025 that we
would experience the grace of God in a very definite, real way. That we would be able
to give the glory to God. See, when it's God's grace and when it's God's strength, it's God
who gets the glory. Amen? It's God alone who gets the glory. You know, Paul didn't want
other people to think more highly of him than they should. Why? Because he wanted God to
be glorified. Because he says, I am what I am by the grace of God. And this morning,
I don't know all that we'll face day by day, but you know what encourages me? God does.
He knows. And what encourages me even greater is that he said my grace is sufficient. And
I want to challenge each and every one of us to not just have a promise explained, but
to have a promise embraced. God in my life, I want to see your grace. I want to experience
your grace. When I don't think I could, God's grace is sufficient. When that phone call
comes, when that whatever happens, God's grace is sufficient. Don't get so caught up in the
future. Don't get so caught up in the what ifs. Because in the moment that you need God's
grace, God's grace is sufficient. Don't let your mind say, well, I don't know what I would
do if. I don't know how I could if. No, no. God said my grace is sufficient. You know
what you'll find? In the moment that you need it, God's grace is sufficient. Let's pray.
Father, we love you. How we thank you for loving us. God, I pray this morning that just
as Paul embraced this promise that was explained in response to his request that this thorn
in his flesh would depart from him. God, I pray this morning that you'd help us to understand,
but most importantly, help us to embrace this promise. God, I'm thankful this morning that
your grace is sufficient. I've experienced it and I give you the glory for it. I pray
that you'd help us throughout this next calendar year as we study through this book to remind
it regularly of your grace. Thank you for saving us. Lord, if there's one here that's
not been saved by the grace of God, they don't know for sure that if they were to die that
heaven is their home. Their greatest need at this moment is to be saved. To have their
sins forgiven, to know for sure that heaven is their home. And I pray that the Holy Spirit
of God would convict them and help them to understand that Jesus saves. And for my grace
are you saved through faith and not of yourselves. It's the gift of God, not of works, lest any
man should boast. And I pray that if there's one under the sound of my voice that needs
to be saved, that today would be the day of their salvation. Lord, I pray for those
that have been saved, that know you as personal Lord and Savior. They've been saved by grace.
In a room of any size of people, there are great needs, difficulties, infirmities, hardships.
Lord, I pray that you'd help us to embrace this promise, that your grace is sufficient.
Lord, that you would help us to experience your grace in our lives. Maybe the Holy Spirit
has touched a particular area in someone's life, or would you help us to be responsive
this morning, to be doers of the word and not hearers only. We pray that you alone would
be honored and glorified through every decision that would be made. For it's in Christ's name
we pray. Would you stand with me?