Introduced our theme last week from the 7th verse of 1st John chapter number 1,
and we'll go back to the first four verses as we begin preaching through the book of 1st John
this year, and I'm definitely looking forward to it. Our theme for this year, as you see in our
banners, Walking in the Light, and what a blessing. I'm so thankful for the Word of God, for the
truth that is just conveyed to us, communicated to us through this precious book, and I trust that
you too are excited about the opportunity to study the book of 1st John together through 2022.
Beginning in verse number 1, the Bible says, "...that which was from the beginning,
which we have heard, which we have seen with our eyes, which we have looked upon,
and our hands have handled of the word of life. For the life was manifested, and we have seen it,
and bear witness, and show unto you that eternal life, which was with the Father, and was manifested
unto us. That which we have seen and heard declare we unto you, that you also may have fellowship
with us, and truly our fellowship is with the Father, and with His Son, Jesus Christ. And these
things write we unto you, that your joy may be full." I mentioned last week, as we touched on
verse number 4 during part of the message, that some of the most joyful people of all the earth
should be God's people, amen? And we have much to rejoice in. We'll deal with that a little bit as
we get through the message this morning, but I'd like to preach a message that I've simply
entitled from these first four verses, an eyewitness account, an eyewitness account.
There's a great similarity between the opening of this epistle and the opening of the Gospel of John.
You find that many times as you read the epistles, especially in the New Testament,
you look at a lot of the Pauline writings as he is writing under the inspiration of the Holy
Spirit of God, but there's an introduction. In the introduction, there's typically a greeting as to
who the book is being written to, the church or the individual, and then some information about
Paul as being the writer of the book, and so on and so forth. But here we find that John, under
the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God, just gets right into it, and he does the same thing
in the Gospel of John. And of course, we understand all Scripture is given by inspiration of God,
but it's very interesting to see how there's really no introduction in this book like there
is in some of the other books that you read in the New Testament. But the introduction that is here
is a powerful introduction, and we find that such is the case even with the Gospel of John. I mean,
it just starts with a bang. It's right in your face, the truth that is being declared and how
powerful that is. I'm thankful that God's Word is truth and that God's truth changes lives, and God's
truth must be proclaimed. John, of course, as we know, was one of the twelve disciples. But more
than being one of the twelve disciples, John was really in that inner circle. We understand that
God gives us the record of the Mount of Transfiguration. We're told that John, Peter,
and James as well, Jesus brought the three of them up into a mountain, and the Bible says that He was
transfigured before them. We find that John was in that inner circle many times as you read the
Gospel of John. You find that under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit, He will refer to Himself as
the disciple whom Jesus loved. And you think about the closeness of that relationship that He had
with the Lord Jesus Christ, and you understand that it is this man that God has chosen to be
the human penman of this short epistle. We find that false teaching continues to invade the church
of God during the first century. We studied through the book of Colossians in 2021, and as we studied
through the book of Colossians, we referenced the false teaching that was prevalent there and how
the Gnostics were one of the groups of people that Paul was no doubt dealing with, and the truth that
was given in that book to those believers to help them combat the false teaching. We've often said
over the years that the remedy for false teaching is truth, and how we need to know the truth. And
we understand that God has warned throughout the scriptures that there would be false teachers.
In fact, He uses the parallel, as Peter would tell us, that just as there were false prophets,
there will be false teachers. And we know that the false teaching invaded the church in the first
century, and it continues to seek to invade and influence the church to this very day, and how we
need to be built up in the faith, how that we need to earnestly contend for the faith. We cannot know
and cannot defend the faith, excuse me, we cannot defend it if we do not know it, and how imperative
it is that we know the faith that was once delivered. The Gnostics continued to be active,
even amongst these that John is writing to, but really the bigger group of people that were quite
active were the Docetists. And this idea of these that would claim and follow this teaching
of these Docetists, they were making an impact in the region here and amongst the believers,
and really they denied the humanity of Jesus Christ. They, similarly to the Gnostics,
they would really take some of the Gnostic teaching and they would come to this conclusion
that there's no humanity, that it was just a figure that Jesus went to a cross, that it really
didn't happen, there's no human form there. And so, obviously, that's a huge false teaching and
a huge problem. I believe that as we understand the false teaching that was really prevalent in
seeking to invade the churches and the believers, it gives us great insight to these first four
verses of the book of 1 John, because these false teachers are denying the humanity of Jesus Christ,
and John says, that which was from the beginning, which we have heard, which we have seen with our
eyes, which we have looked upon, and our hands have handled of the word of life. Well, that smacks you
in the face, doesn't it? And we find that he's going directly at the false teaching, and he's
proving, yes, the deity of Jesus Christ, but the humanity of Jesus Christ, the great truth of the
incarnation. In the beginning was the word, and the word was with God, and the word was God. That's how
John's gospel begins, and you find that you skip down to the 14th verse, and it says this,
and the word was made flesh and dwelt among us. We'll look at that verse in more detail in just a
moment, but you find that Jesus Christ is 100% God and 100% man, and John, who was one of those 12
disciples, John, who was in the inner circle, he was able to give this eyewitness account and help
these believers to understand truth so that they would not be influenced by this false teaching.
If you look at the text of Scripture, if you're taking notes this morning, I want you to notice,
first of all, the credibility of the account. We speak about an eyewitness account, or you speak
about an account in general, you find that the eyewitness account has great credibility and is
one that is sought after. When you think about someone giving an account, giving a testimony,
giving some type of record, if it's in a court of law, if it's to some type of law enforcement
personnel, having an eyewitness to the event that is being discussed or evaluated is of great value.
Someone comes, and they see this particular situation, an accident or something else, and
you stand there, and you say, well, I want to tell you what happened. He says, well, were you here?
Did you see it? Well, no, but I'm just going to kind of give you what I think happened.
I'm not interested in that kind of an account, right? That's not necessary. But the individual,
when the law enforcement shows up, when the lawyer is speaking to the clients and seeking to get
testimony and what have you, and there's an eyewitness of that particular event that stands,
sits upon that stand and gives testimony and can say, I was there, and I saw it, and here's my
testimony. There's a level of credibility. And here we find the credibility of this eyewitness
account. Notice again, in verse number one, he says, which we have heard. He says, that which
was from the beginning, which we have heard. Then he says this, which we have seen with our eyes,
which we have looked upon. And so you see the next two statements are dealing with what he saw.
So, he speaks about what he heard. He speaks about what he saw. And then notice at the end
of verse number one, it says, in our hands have handled of the word of life. He says in verse
number two, he says, for the life was manifested. Notice this phrase again, and we have seen it.
Look in verse number three, that which we have seen and heard, declare we unto you.
The credibility of the account is laid out just beautifully for us in these first few verses
of 1 John chapter number one. And we see that John is giving the credibility to this eyewitness
account that he's going to provide, and of course, the entirety of this epistle. But he begins by
letting the readers and letting us know under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God, that this
is not some second hand type of information, that this is not something that he's just conjured up
in his own mind and some theory that he's.
No, this is an eyewitness account.
This is what I have seen with my eyes.
This is what I've heard with my ears.
This is what I've handled with my hands.
And what a blessing to think about the power,
the credibility of this account.
Notice in John 1, back in the Gospel of John,
I mentioned that we'd be in this verse in just a moment,
but look at John 1 in verse number 14.
In fact, we're gonna take a little journey
through the Gospel of John
to just look at the testimony of the Apostle John
and to deal with this credibility that he has
with regard to the writing of this book
and the information that he would give.
The Bible says in John 1 in verse number 14,
and the Word was made flesh and dwelt among us.
We know the incarnation
when God took upon himself human form.
And the Bible says, and dwelt among us,
tabernacled among us.
He lived and breathed.
He walked among the disciples.
And Jesus, as you look at the entirety
of his earthly ministry
and John being one of those disciples in the inner circle,
remember, John, he saw that Jesus slept, right?
He was tired.
He was asleep on the boat.
He saw that Jesus was unhungered.
He saw that Jesus was thirsty.
He saw these things,
these human attributes of the Lord Jesus Christ.
He saw the deity of Christ.
He saw the power of Christ.
He saw the same God that was sleeping in the boat
stand and say, peace, be still.
He saw the same God who was wearied with his journey
that was looking for water
that gave freely of the living water
that we look at in John 4.
And he talked to the lady, the woman at the well
of all of her history and all of those things.
He is the God-man.
And John says that he was made flesh and he dwelt among us.
Notice the next phrase.
And we beheld his glory,
the glory as of the only begotten of the Father,
full of grace and truth.
That phrase, when it says we beheld his glory,
is really the same phrase that we look at in 1 John
when it says that we looked upon him.
We beheld his glory.
As we notice, as we study through the gospel records
and we read of the life and ministry
of the Lord Jesus Christ,
and you think about the great privilege of these disciples,
and John in particular with regard to the subject at hand,
how that he had the opportunity to see all of these things,
to hear from the Lord Jesus Christ, to sit with him.
What a great blessing.
Notice in John one, skip down if you would,
to verse number 35.
The Bible says, again,
the next day after John stood and two of his disciples,
this is speaking of John the Baptist,
it says this in verse number 36,
and looking upon Jesus as he walked,
notice what John the Baptist says,
behold, the Lamb of God.
And the two disciples heard him speak
and they followed Jesus.
It says, then Jesus turned and saw them following
and saith unto them, what seek ye?
They said unto him, Rabbi, which is to say,
being interpreted, Master, where dwellest thou?
Notice what Jesus says,
the invitation that is extended in verse number 39.
He saith unto them, come and see.
They came and saw where he dwelt
and abode with him that day,
for it was about the 10th hour.
One of the two which heard John speak and followed him,
it says, was Andrew, Simon Peter's brother.
We believe that the second one was the John
that we're speaking of this morning,
John the Apostle, the disciple.
He does not regularly refer to himself
throughout this book, as you know,
as we've studied in the past,
but you find that after they come and see,
they respond to the invitation and John is there,
and then the attention goes to Andrew in verse number 40,
and it says that he first findeth his own brother
and saith unto him, notice what he says,
and no doubt John would have come to the same conclusion,
we have found the Messiah,
which is being interpreted, the Christ.
John has the opportunity to walk with the Lord Jesus Christ.
He has the opportunity to see great miracles,
to hear great teaching,
and John chapter number 15,
turn over, if you will, several chapters,
and you note that in this particular section
of the Gospel of John, that the hour is nigh,
it is not yet come, we find that he makes that statement
in John 17, the hour is now come,
but we know that soon,
Jesus would go to the cross of Calvary.
We know that he's told the disciples,
he's explained to the disciples what's happening,
and he's giving them information here in this 15th chapter,
really into the 16th chapter,
with regard to the comforter that would come
and the adversity that they deal with,
and so on and so forth,
but notice what Jesus says in John 15 and verse number 27,
and ye also shall bear witness, why?
Because ye have been with me from the beginning.
Right, doesn't that parallel so beautifully
to first John chapter number one,
when John, under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
he begins this testimony that he's going to give,
and says that which was from the beginning,
which we have heard, which we have seen with our eyes,
which we have looked upon,
and our hands have handled the word of life,
he says in verse number three,
that which we have seen and heard declare we unto you,
Jesus said, ye shall bear witness, why?
Because ye have been with me from the beginning,
and John is testifying, he's giving this witness.
Notice in the very last statements of John 21,
the last two verses of this great book,
in John 21, we understand that it's at this time
in which the focus is really primarily dealing with Peter,
here at the end of John 21, and John is there,
for the Bible says that Peter, in verse number 20,
turning about, seeth the disciple whom Jesus loved,
following, and that's John, and so John is there,
and Jesus is interacting with Peter,
and we find that in verse number 24,
as the book concludes, the Bible says,
this is the disciple which testifieth of these things,
and wrote these things,
and we know that his testimony is true.
Notice verse 25,
and there are also many other things which Jesus did,
the which, if they should be written,
everyone, I suppose, that even the world itself
could not contain the books that should be written, amen.
And I want you to just meditate upon that for just a moment.
We really, as we started our study in Sunday school,
the family church Sunday school class
that we started back in November,
and going through the miracles of Jesus Christ,
we looked at this verse of scripture,
John 21 and verse 25, coupled with the truth
in John 20, verse 30 and 31,
speaking about the things that were written
versus the things that were not written,
but I want you, just for a moment,
to think about John giving this eyewitness account
in 1 John, these first four verses
that are our focus of study this morning,
and as you consider the credibility of the account,
the credibility of that which John is giving,
you must understand the great things that he heard and saw.
He says, these things are written,
but if all of the things were written,
I'm not sure the world could contain.
Can you imagine when we look through and study the gospels
as we journey with Jesus during his earthly ministry,
we have the opportunity to see some great things,
but there's so many things that Jesus did
that are not recorded for us in scripture,
and John is a witness of those things.
John is an eyewitness, and he says,
I'm gonna give an account,
and when you think about the senses,
he says, the things that I've heard,
the things that I've seen,
as I've handled the word of life,
this is the testimony that I'm going to give.
Now, when somebody enters into a law firm,
when someone enters into a courtroom,
and they preface the account that they're going to give
with that kind of a statement,
this is an exciting testimony that I'm ready to hear, right?
There is credibility in this testimony.
Now, we understand the credibility
because it's the word of God,
but I want you to understand
the original recipients of this book
and all that's going on with the false teaching
and all of the influence and how that John comes,
again, under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
but he's going to just come out full steam, full go,
and say, here's the testimony that I'm going to give,
and here's why it's credible,
because I'm an eyewitness.
I would say this of John,
when I think about the credibility of the account
that is given to us in this epistle,
I would say that he was a faithful, credible witness.
He was faithful.
He did what God had instructed him to do.
He fulfilled the ministry that God had given him to fulfill,
and we find that he is laboring and seeking to influence,
and he's giving this testimony.
So we think about the credibility, and that's wonderful,
but now as we.
move through the passage, I want you to think not only of the credibility, but I
want you to think about the content of this testimony, this eyewitness account
that is given. I'm thankful for the credibility of it, but I want to know the
content of it. Well, stick with us for all year to get the content of it, amen?
Because I can't give it to you in one service, but I do believe he gives us a
great preview as to what the content is of this witness that he is going to
provide this testimony. Notice in verse number two, for the life was manifested
and we have seen it. How similar that is to John 1 and verse number 14. He says
this, and bear witness and show unto you that eternal life which was with the
Father and was manifested unto us. Now isn't that really the most important
thing to be able to, the content of the message, the content being eternal life,
the true need of every human being? And we find that he begins speaking about
this eternal life in verse number two, and as we think about this eternal
life, we really think of it from two perspectives. Number one would be the
source. What is the source of eternal life? It's not John, it's not the
disciples or the apostles' creed. It is the Father. It is God's plan that we find
that is given throughout the Word of God that he is going to redeem his creation
through the substitutionary atonement of his Son, right? The gift of God is
eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord. We find that in Ephesians chapter
number one, we won't take time to look there, but if you want to go back and
look through Ephesians 1, you see three really beautiful divisions in the first
15 verses of that chapter, and what you see is the plan of redemption, that
this is God's plan on how mankind is going to be redeemed. So many people over
the years have confused Ephesians 1 with dealing with the who is going to be
redeemed instead of the how people are going to be redeemed. He's not dealing
with the who, he's dealing with the how. Mankind, the plan of God is that mankind
will be redeemed only one way, and that's through Jesus Christ. So he deals
with the plan of redemption, he then deals with the price of redemption. It's
with the precious blood of Christ. Redemption is not possible apart from
the blood of Christ, amen? You can't be redeemed. Redeemed how I love to
proclaim it, redeemed how? By the blood of the Lamb, right? That's what we're
saying. And there's only one way to be redeemed. We know that Peter says this,
that we're not redeemed with corruptible things such as silver and
gold received by our tradition from fathers and so on and so forth, but we're
redeemed how? With the precious blood of Christ, as of a lamb that was slain
before the foundation of the world. We see the plan and the the price, and then
you see the proof of redemption in that next section of Ephesians 1, where you
find that God in his wisdom has given us the Holy Spirit of God, who is the, he
seals us into the day of redemption, and you think about the wonderful truth of
that proof of redemption. And so we think about eternal life, a subject that will be
dealt with throughout this book, and you find the source of eternal life, but then
you find really, and this becomes a very large focus of the book of 1st John,
really he deals with the security, the security. You know, I'm so thankful that
we can know that we're saved, that we can have that security. We find that
throughout the book of 1st John, in one form or another, the word know is used
over 30 times. Now when you think about the word being used, it's, I think it's 38
times, know, known, knoweth. Many of those, not all of them of course, but many of
those are in reference specifically to knowing that you have eternal life,
knowing that you belong to the Father, knowing that you're saved. And so the
content of the testimony is that we're going to tell you the source of eternal
life, and that is God, and we're going to teach you and we're going to share with
you the security of eternal life, knowing that you belong to the Lord. I want you to
think about what John heard Jesus say in John chapter number 10. In John
chapter number 10, in verses 27 through 30, John hears Jesus say this,
I know my sheep and they hear my voice, and I give unto them eternal life, and
they shall never perish. John heard Jesus speak those words. Now when John heard
Jesus speak those words, those are words of security, are they not? I give unto
them eternal life, and they shall never perish. Man, those are absolutes. Those
are cherished statements within the Word of God. And when you think about the
security of the believer, and you find that Peter says this, that we are kept by
the power of God, when you find, I've said this to people over the years, that
God promises that the gift of God is eternal life. He didn't tell us that the
gift of God was temporary life, and he sure didn't tell us it was probationary
life. I've never been on probation. I hope to never be on probation. Amen? If you
were, don't tell me. If you are, definitely don't tell me. But the reality
is that I understand some things about being on probation, and one of the things
that I understand about being on probation is that you better walk a fine
line, right? Because what happens if you don't walk the fine line, you go
back to the big house, so to speak, right? I mean, that's what happens. So
therefore, when we think about the eternal life, he didn't say I give you
probationary life. He didn't say I made the down payment, and now you try to keep
it. And John, as he's writing in this book, under the inspiration of the Holy
Spirit of God, he says, I want you to understand the source of eternal life,
but I want you to know the security of eternal life. I want you to know that you
belong to Him, that I am His, and He is mine. Isn't that precious? When you think
about the truth of eternal life, and you think about who He is to us, and we
understand the relationship of adoption, and that we become His children, and yes,
our fellowship will vary during our walk with Christ, but our relationship is
constant. And what joy that is. You think about the truth of the psalmist in Psalm
23, a familiar passage of Scripture that we often refer to to be a source of
great encouragement to us and strength to us, that the Word of God says the Lord
is my shepherd. It was an understanding that the psalmist had that there was a
relationship there, and that He is my shepherd. And here, throughout this book,
we understand that part of the content here will be that of eternal life, the
source, and the security. I would say this, that as you continue reading, notice
we've noted in verse number two about the eternal life, but look in verse
number three, that which we have seen and heard declare we unto you that you
also may have fellowship with us. And truly our fellowship is with the Father
and with His Son, Jesus Christ. I believe that as you look at the content of the
account of the testimony that is given, then another theme that will be
developed throughout this epistle is that of fellowship. Fellowship, yes, first
with the Lord, but then fellowship one with another. I belabored the point last
week, and we'll look at it again next week, as you look at verse number seven,
that He says that if we walk in the light, our theme, walking in the light,
that if you walk in the light, living that life of obedience as He is in the
light, that we have fellowship, He doesn't say with God, He says with one another.
Now, we understand that we do have fellowship with God, because we're
walking in the light as He is in the light, so we have fellowship with Him, and
that is rejoicing, or that should cause us to rejoice greatly, but He
notes specifically that we have fellowship one with another, and how
precious that is, and how God has designed it that we would have
fellowship one with another, and we find that here, that John is in this opening,
he's speaking about the credibility of his witness, of his testimony, that he has
heard and seen and handled of the Word of Life, of Jesus Christ, and he's
going to declare that which he's heard, and that which he has seen, and he's
speaking of eternal life, and he's speaking of fellowship. Truly, our
fellowship is with the Father, and with His Son, Jesus Christ, he says in verse
number three. You know, apart from redemption, there's no way to have
fellowship with God. We're at enmity with God before salvation. It's what the Word
of God teaches. We're dead in our sins and our trespasses. We mentioned the
biblical term, the theological term of reconciliation. We had to be reconciled.
Why? Because we were separated. Our sin separates us from God. We cannot have
fellowship with God, so we must be redeemed.
And as we're redeemed, I mentioned last week as we studied that introductory message with
regard to walking in the light, that number one, walking in the light requires relationship.
You cannot walk in the light if you don't belong to Him.
It requires relationship, and it is based upon relationship.
And because I belong to the Lord, because I've been saved, I can walk in the light
and I can have fellowship with Him.
Now think about that.
Isn't that a great privilege of every child?
It's a unique privilege that we can have fellowship with God, the God of the universe, the God
of the impossible, the God who simply spoke and it was.
He loves us so much.
He desires to have fellowship with each and every one of us.
What a unique privilege that is.
And through the book of 1 John, we'll find that this thought of fellowship, this truth
of fellowship is developed throughout the study of the book.
And how joyful it is that we can have fellowship with God.
Indeed, there are times in which our fellowship is hindered.
Have you experienced that in your life?
Our fellowship can be hindered.
Our fellowship can be hindered with those that we have relationships with here on earth,
correct?
We can have hindered relationships with a spouse, we can have hindered relationships
with a sibling.
Sibling rivalry, right?
We'll talk about that tonight, actually, Jacob and Esau, amen.
And what a dysfunctional family.
Anyway, we'll get to that tonight.
The reality, however, is that, listen, we can have relationship with somebody here on
earth and have hindered fellowship with them.
And we can have relationship with God, but have hindered fellowship.
John deals with that.
He tells us how that we can have that fellowship restored.
Isn't that wonderful?
What tragedy it would be if that fellowship was hindered, but there was no way back.
But there is a way back.
Why?
Because our God is gracious and He's merciful and He's ready to pardon and ready to forgive.
And we'll see those themes develop throughout the book of 1 John.
So we find the credibility of the witness, the content of the witness, but I want you
to see as we close this morning in verse number four, I want you to note the purpose
of this witness.
Notice he says it very simply, and these things write we unto you, that your joy may be full.
I want you to keep that in mind, but turn to the book of John in the 20th chapter, and
I want you to see, hold your place in 1 John, we're going to come right back, but I want
you to see what it says in John 20.
He says here in 1 John, and these things write we unto you, why?
The purpose is stated, that your joy may be full.
Notice in the gospel of John in chapter number 20, he says this in verse number 30, and many
other signs truly did Jesus in the presence of His disciples, which are not written in
this book.
But these are written.
Why?
That you might believe that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of God, and that believing you might
have life through His name.
Do we understand the purpose of the gospel of John?
Yeah, the purpose of the gospel of John is that you might believe that Jesus is the Christ,
that He is the Son of God, and that as you believe that and receive that, that you have
eternal life through His name.
The purpose, as it's stated in 1 John, He's writing to believers.
It's always helpful to understand the audience, the recipients, because He does not say here
in 1 John 1 that I'm writing these things unto you so that you would believe that you
would know that Jesus is the Christ, but He says, I'm writing these things unto you that
your joy may be full, that your joy may be full.
Listen, there are times in which our joy tank isn't full.
We're running on fumes, so to speak, running on empty.
Somebody said this and I do not like the statement whatsoever, fake it until you make it.
That's nonsense.
You know what that is?
That's fleshly.
I shouldn't have to fake it when I understand the source of joy, right?
It's not fake it until you make it.
That's carnal and fleshly.
He says, these things write we unto you that your joy may be full.
Now, I want you to think about this as we close this morning.
What would cause my joy to be full?
Well, number one, joy is the result of salvation.
It is a byproduct of salvation.
And we find that He said, when we looked at the content, two of the truths that will be
developed, the themes, if you will, that will be developed through the book, is that of
eternal life, the source and the security.
And so we think about that big theme, if you will, that's developed here and having the
knowledge that you belong to Christ, that should cause you to have fullness of joy.
Amen?
I belong to Him.
I am His and He is mine.
He will never leave me nor forsake me.
In Luke chapter number 10, you don't need to turn there, but in Luke chapter number
10, the disciples come back, and He'd sent out these 70, and they come back, and we find
that they're coming back and they're rejoicing.
They come back with joy, and they say, even the devils are subject unto us through thy
name.
And I mean, they're excited about it.
And Jesus says this in Luke 10 and verse number 20, notwithstanding in this, rejoice not that
the spirits are subject unto you, but rather rejoice, why?
Because your names are written in heaven.
I want you to think about that for a moment.
We sing the song, there's a new name written down in glory, and it's mine.
Oh, yes, it's mine, right?
And as we sing that song, I hope for you the same way for me, I remember back as I'm singing
that song to the day in which I trust that Christ is my Savior.
I'm thinking back to the day in which my name was written down in glory, the day in
which I trust at Christ, and the reality is that Jesus says, listen, what should be the
real cause of your rejoice is that your name is written in the book of heaven, the book
of life.
And you think about that this morning.
Who can take your name out of that book?
You can't even take your name out of the book.
And the reality is that that security that we have in Christ that will be developed throughout
this book, He says these things, and these things write we unto you, what?
That your joy may be full.
You know, someone that does not know the Lord Jesus Christ as their personal Savior, certainly
they may have some periods of happiness in their life, but happiness and joy are really
not synonymous one with the other.
There's a distinct difference between the two.
Because we can be living...happiness, I would say this, is based on our happenings, if I
could use that phraseology.
Why do they call Disney the happiest place on earth?
Honestly, I have no idea.
I've been there.
I've been there pre-COVID when there's 8,000 people trying to stand in line for one line
to one ride, and it's 900 degrees, and the sun is beating down on you, and it's the happiest
place on earth.
And I'm like, man, there's a lot of places I can think of that would cause more happiness
than this.
I'm just being honest.
If Disney gets a hold of the video, they're not going to like what I said, amen?
It's all good.
But the reality is that happiness typically is based on our happenings.
Joy is different.
It's well within us.
It's something that God gives us.
No man taketh your joy, right?
It's what the Word of God tells us.
And we can be dealing with some of the most adverse circumstances on this earth, some
of the hardest trials that we've ever faced, and have joy.
We can face the most intense and the most severe storm, we can have peace and we can
have joy.
It's completely different than happiness.
Joy is the result of salvation.
David said this in Psalm 51, his great psalm of repentance.
He says, restore unto me the joy of thy salvation.
He did not say, restore unto me salvation, he didn't lose it, but he certainly lost the
joy of his salvation.
You know why he lost the joy of his salvation?
Because sin robs you of your joy.
And so we find here that he says that your joy may be full.
Number one, joy is the result of salvation, but then I would say this, number two, that
joy is the result of fellowship.
It's the result of fellowship, of that godly living.
We mentioned that in verse number seven, the theme that we have, walking in the light,
that if we walk in the light as He is in the light, we have fellowship one with another
in the blood of Jesus Christ, His Son cleanseth us from all sin.
We understand that that walk in the light or walking in the light, we said this last
week, could be synonymous with obedient, godly living.
And you know that when we're saved and we have the joy of the Lord, it's our strength,
we have joy because our names are written in heaven, but there's a joy that we have
in obedient living.
living, because to him that knoweth to do right and doeth it not, to him it is sin.
And D.L.
Moody said this, sin will keep you from this book, or this book will keep you from sin,
referring to the Bible.
And I would submit to you this morning that one of the ways that we lose our joy as God's
people is by sinning.
It robs us of our joy.
We're not right with God.
We're not walking with God.
We're not in fellowship with God.
And his presence, the psalmist said in Psalm 1611, is fullness of joy.
So there's a joy that's the result of salvation, and I'm so thankful for that joy, that source
of joy is now there with me, within me, but the reality is that it also is a result of
our fellowship.
And so when we think about the content of the testimony that he gives, and then he tells
us the purpose, these things right we unto you, that your joy may be full.
Now, of God, he never designed it that you'd run on fumes.
That you'd be almost at empty, but that your joy would be full.
Notice if you will, we'll quickly look at a few verses of Scripture.
Turn to John 15.
Look at a couple of verses here in John 15 and 16, and then we'll make a reference to
the book of Galatians and be done this morning.
John 15.
Joy is the result of salvation, but joy is also the result of fellowship, of godly living.
We find that in John 15, and beginning in verse 10, the Bible says this,
15.
If ye keep my commandments, ye shall abide in my love, even as I have kept my Father's
commandments and abide in His love.
These things have I spoken unto you, that my joy might remain in you, and that your
joy might be full.
Isn't that amazing?
How similar what he heard Jesus say is now what he's declaring.
By the way, that's what Jesus tells him at the end of John 15.
We looked at it earlier in verse number 27.
We find that Jesus is saying, I've spoken these things unto you, that my joy might remain
in you, and that your joy might be full.
What was it?
He says, if ye keep my commandments, ye abide in my love.
Notice in verse number 12, this is my commandment, that ye love one another as I have loved you.
Notice verse number 14, ye are my friends if you do whatsoever I have commanded you.
You know, in the book of 1 John, as we go throughout the entirety of the book, you'll
find that there are many references to walking and obeying the Lord Jesus Christ, and having
that fellowship results in joy.
Let's just be honest with one another this morning.
When I'm not walking in fellowship with God, my joy suffers.
I'm not as joyful when I'm not walking with God as I am when I am walking with God.
And if you'd be honest and evaluate your life this morning, you'd say, yeah, I've experienced
that.
Notice in John 16, in verse number 24, hitherto have ye asked nothing in my name.
Ask and ye shall receive, that your joy may be full.
You think about the prayer and prayer being answered.
The Bible says, if I regard iniquity in Psalm 66 and verse 18 in my heart, the Lord will
not hear me.
It's not that He can't hear you.
He can hear us, and so that sin hinders our fellowship with Him and hinders His answering
to us.
And here He says this, when you think about that praying, you know praying is a result
of being in fellowship, right?
Let me ask you, don't answer me, please don't answer me, but let me ask you to think about
this personally in your life.
If there's some hindrance between you and your spouse, and there's some contention between
you, and your fellowship has been hindered, how's your communication?
Not great, because your fellowship's been hindered, right?
So therefore, your communication suffers.
Is that valid?
So what happens in our walk with God?
When our fellowship is hindered, our communication is also hindered.
How do we communicate with God?
Through prayer.
My prayer life isn't what it's supposed to be if I'm not in fellowship with God, right?
And neither is yours.
And so the byproduct of that fellowship is that communication.
And so we find here that He talks about your joy being full, how it results in the ask
and ye shall receive that your joy may be full.
We'll turn to the book of Galatians, and we'll end there.
In Galatians chapter number 5, the Bible speaks about the fruit of the Spirit.
He talks about the works of the flesh.
He talks about the fact that the flesh and the Spirit are enmity one with the other.
But then He lists out the fruit of the Spirit.
He describes it with all of these different descriptive terms that are so powerful, really
you note that He says the fruit of the Spirit, singular, it's not plural, it's singular,
but here's how the fruit of the Spirit is described.
These are the descriptive terms that help us understand the fruit of the Spirit, love,
joy, peace, longsuffering, gentleness, goodness, faith, meekness, temperance, against such
there is no law.
How do we have the fruit of the Spirit?
As we walk in the Spirit, right?
What is walking in the Spirit?
Well, it's the same, really similar to walking in the light.
And so we have this joy.
He says, I want you to understand the purpose of the testimony that I'm giving.
I'm writing these things to you that your joy may be full.
I want my joy tank to be full.
It starts with salvation.
Because if our names are written in the book of life, we ought to rejoice.
Doesn't matter what happens, it doesn't matter how hard the day is, it doesn't matter how
many people say whatever they say, I'm going to heaven.
Can't wait, we say to the kids, we sing with them, going to see Jesus, can't wait, right?
A little song that we sing with the kids.
Listen, Deon Moody said some guy pulled a gun on him.
He said, you can't threaten me with heaven.
I love it.
I don't know that I'd say it.
But that's what he said.
Listen, at the end of the day, no matter what happens, we're going to heaven.
It's my long home, amen?
For all of eternity, I'm going to be with my Savior.
That should cause us to have joy.
And as we walk in fellowship with Him, we have joy.
In His presence is fullness of joy.
So we see the credibility.
John says as he gets up on the witness stand, listen, yes, I'm a disciple.
Yes, I'm in the inner circle.
I have heard, I have seen, I have handled of the Word of life.
The content, we're going to talk about salvation.
We're going to talk about eternal life, the source, and the security, and the whole purpose
is that your joy might be full.
Oh, that we live as joyful people, that truly the joy of the Lord would be our strength,
and that we'd rejoice greatly because we belong to Him and because we walk with Him.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
Thank You for loving us.
I thank You for the Word of God.
I thank You for the truth of these four verses and how impactful they are in my life, and
I trust in the lives of those that are gathered here this morning.
If there'd be one present, one that's tuned in, that's never trusted the Lord Jesus Christ
as their personal Savior, I pray that today they would trust Christ.
Oh, we pray that the Holy Spirit of God would convict them of their sin and convince them
of Christ's righteousness and of judgment to come, that they would place their faith
and trust in the finished work of Christ at Calvary, that their names would be written
in the book of life, they might have joy and fellowship.
God, I pray for each child of God as we evaluate our lives, perhaps if we would take time to
evaluate and be honest with ourselves and with You, there are times in which our joy
tank is not full.
There are times in which we're living under the circumstances.
There are times in which we have believed that little statement that I mentioned that
I disagree with, fake it till you make it.
There's no reason to fake it.
God, I pray that if our fellowship's been hindered because of some sin, it'd help us
to see that fellowship restored, that we might have fullness of joy, that our joy would be
full.
Indeed, Your people, we, should be the most joyful people in all the world.
I pray that You'd move and work as only You can, that decisions would be made that would
please Thee, that would cause us to be conformed to the image of Christ and impact eternity.
Well, thank You for all that You'll do, for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would You stand with me?
As your bowed eyes are closed, Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano.
At the end of our service, we have an opportunity for you to respond.
Come to the altar, make your pew and altar, and ask the Lord to speak to your heart, or
you respond to how the Lord has spoken to your heart.
I'll say, yes, Lord, yes.
Help me to have that fellowship.
Acknowledge that the fellowship is hindered, that the joy is not what it should be, and
have that restored.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.