I am not planning to preach through the book of Exodus after finishing Genesis.
If I were to do so, we'd start in chapter one.
Someone asked me, are you preaching through Exodus?
I say that we're in chapter three.
No, I'm not preaching through Exodus.
In fact, I think over the summer we're going to implement once again, we'll have it on
Wednesday evening, but the Ask the Pastor series on Sunday nights, I got a couple from
last summer that we did not finish and I'll begin with those and then we'll do that.
We'll start that after the missions conference and have that through the summer and then
in September we'll start a brand new series on Sunday evening and look forward to the
opportunity to do that.
This evening as we look at Exodus chapter number three, I want to draw your attention
to really the center part of the text.
We're going to read verse seven.
I'll get right into the message, but verse number seven, notice what the Bible says.
The Lord said, I have surely seen the affliction of my people, which are in Egypt and have
heard their cry by reason of their taskmasters.
And then notice this statement, for I know their sorrows.
I'm going to preach a message this evening that I've simply entitled, I know their sorrows.
After the death of Joseph, of course, recorded in Genesis chapter number 50, we understand
the nation of Israel, the people of God, they face great afflictions and yet though suffering
great affliction, we understand they grew and they multiplied and we're told that the
Egyptians, if we're to study the first chapter, you're understanding that they made their
lives bitter with hard bondage, is the terminology that God uses to describe that period of time
of the children of Israel, after Joseph died, after the Pharaoh died, there rose up another
Pharaoh which knew not Joseph and it was a difficult time for the children of Israel.
We find that the birth of Moses and really his first 80 years of life are recorded for
us and it's amazing because you read chapter two and all, I mean, that's a lot of history
that's covered in one single chapter of scripture.
You come to the third chapter of the book of Exodus, we begin reading about the call
of Moses.
Now, we must understand that a great number of years has passed between Joseph dying,
the period of time of bitter, hard bondage for the children of Israel, and now Moses
being called by God.
We find that most of Exodus 3 and Exodus chapter number 4 record for us and provide us with
a dialogue, if you will, of the interaction between God and Moses.
As God calls Moses and Moses says, I think you got the wrong guy and you see the interaction
with the excuses and so on and so forth.
But we find that as we look at this portion of scripture, and I really want to focus on
verses 7 through 12 this evening, and I hope that it'll be a blessing to you and a help
to you because God says, I know their sorrows.
I'm thankful that our God is an eternal God.
I'm thankful that he's omniscient and that he's omnipotent.
He is immutable.
He never changes.
He's no respecter of persons.
And I'm thankful this evening that as we look at a text of scripture in Exodus 3, a period
of history that literally took place thousands of years ago, that we have the opportunity
to see that we serve the same God today, and if you're facing challenges and difficulties
and you say, I have sorrows, I want you to know tonight that God knows your sorrows.
He knows.
He's aware.
As we look at this portion of scripture, I want you to quickly, if you're taking notes,
number one, notice the perspective of God.
We've read verse 7 already.
I'm going to read it again.
And we find that God speaks, of course, we understand the call is recorded in the first
several verses of Exodus chapter 3.
And he begins to, God begins to speak to Moses out of that burning bush, the bush that burned
with fire but was not consumed according to verse number 2.
In verse 7 it says, the Lord said, I have surely seen the affliction of my people which
are in Egypt and have heard their cry by reason of their taskmasters, for I know their sorrows.
Verse number 9 says this, now therefore, behold, the cry of the children of Israel
has come unto me, and I've also seen the oppression wherewith the Egyptians oppress them.
When I consider the perspective of God from verse 7 and verse number 9, clearly revealed
to us are two truths this evening.
Number one, God knows everything.
God knows everything.
Number two, God sees everything.
God knows everything and God sees everything.
Have you ever heard somebody say something like this?
Nobody knows and nobody cares.
Nobody knows what I'm dealing with.
No one understands the sorrow of my heart.
No one understands the burden that I'm carrying.
No one seems to care.
No one sees all the things that I'm dealing with.
I want you to know tonight that God knows everything and God sees everything.
We serve a God who is amazing.
I mean simply, we sang this morning about our Savior's love, I stand amazed in the presence
of Jesus the Nazarene.
I wonder how He could love me, a sinner condemned unclean.
And we sing the chorus, oh how marvelous, oh how wonderful, oh how marvelous is His
love for me.
Oh, you think about the love of God, it's amazing.
And as we look at this passage of Scripture, we understand that God knew all about their
circumstances.
He knew all about what they were facing and what they were dealing with and I want you
to understand that it wasn't on day one of facing the difficulties and the adversities
that God comes and gives this call and this announcement.
But all along the way, God knew what was taking place.
He was aware.
It's not as if all of a sudden after all of these years and all of the tragic circumstances
that all of a sudden God has now made, no, God knew about it from the first day.
God has a plan, He has a purpose, He's always at work and there are times in which we wonder
and we've said something like this in the past with regard to God's timing, it's perfect.
There are times in my life, there are times in your life that we could say, I wish God
would hurry up and work, I wish He would, but God is at work.
God is doing something.
There are times in which we can understand and many times on the other side of it, so
to speak, that we can see that God was working to develop us as individuals through that
period of difficulty and trial and God was humbling us and God was at work and God was
doing something in those circumstances that could not be done any other way.
And we ought to rejoice in that.
As much as God knew about their circumstances, I want you to know this evening that God knows
about your circumstances.
It could be this evening that there are some that are dealing with things that no other
person on the face of this earth understands that they know.
You've not shared it, you've not told anyone.
Maybe there's a family that just a couple, a husband and wife are carrying a burden dealing
with a situation, a circumstance and nobody else knows about it, just the two of you,
but I want you to know that God knows about it and God cares and God has a plan and God
is at work.
We must understand this evening as we look at a passage of Scripture that for many of
us is familiar, but we must be reminded of the perspective of God.
He knows everything.
He sees everything.
He cares deeply about His people.
He loves us with an everlasting love, an unconditional love.
It's absolutely amazing.
We see the perspective of God.
I want you to see number two, the promise of God.
The promise of God.
I want you to notice in verse number eight, the Bible says this, and I am come down to
deliver them out of the hand of the Egyptians and to bring them up out of that land unto
a good land and a large unto a land flowing with milk and honey unto the place, the Canaanites,
the place of the Hittites, the Amorites, the Perizzites, the Hivites and the Jebusites.
We find that in verse number eight, God gives a promise to Moses.
He lets Moses understand that he was aware of what was taking place.
He reveals to Moses that I know what's going on.
I see what's going on.
I am aware of the circumstances.
But then in verse number eight, he gives this promise and he says, I am come down to.
He's coming to do something.
And we find that really, as we look at verse number eight, it's a twofold promise.
He's going to bring them out in order to bring them in.
Notice he says in verse number eight, I am come down to deliver them out of the hand
of the Egyptians and to bring them up out of that land.
He's coming to deliver them.
We read through the book of Exodus and we understand that God will deliver them with
a high hand, with a mighty hand.
We read through the portion of the next several chapters and we read of the plagues and we
read of the great deliverance as they go and cross over the Red Sea.
And what a tremendous miracle of God and how God delivered them.
He brought them out.
He promised that that's what he was going to do.
But notice the promise is not simply to bring them out of that land and then to leave them
to themselves and figured out now I've delivered you from Egypt.
and now good luck, I mean, figure it out.
No, he says, and not only to bring them up
out of that land into a good land,
in a large, in a land flowing with milk and honey,
he brought them out so that he might bring them in.
Now, we've understood as we study
through the history of Israel that they disobey God,
their unbelief causes them to wander in the wilderness
for 40 years, and all that takes place.
That was never God's plan.
God knew about it because he knows all things,
but God's plan was to bring them out and bring them in.
See, what limits God is your unbelief, my unbelief,
our doubt, it limits God.
In Psalm 78, the Bible talks about
they limited the Holy One of Israel.
He did not many mighty works there, why?
Because of their unbelief.
And so we find that they doubted,
they said, if you were to read in Numbers chapter 14,
throughout that portion of scripture,
when God had Moses send those spies,
they come back and 10 have the evil report,
and they say, we are not able, we cannot.
They have walled cities, they have strong cities,
they have giants, I mean, we're just not capable.
And so what do they do?
Well, 40 years.
But God made a promise,
and we find that even after that 40 years,
you know what God did?
He brought them in.
Look over, if you will, quickly at Exodus chapter six,
and then we're gonna look at Deuteronomy just for a moment.
In Exodus chapter number six,
the Lord's speaking to Moses.
It's very interesting.
If you were to study the life of Moses,
the end of chapter five is really amazing.
Moses is pouring his heart out to the Lord,
and he says in verse 23,
for since I came to Pharaoh to speak in thy name,
he hath done evil to this people,
neither hast thou delivered thy people at all.
It really got worse before it got better.
You say, well, that's encouraging, Pastor.
I'm just telling you what happened.
In chapter number six, it says,
then the Lord said unto Moses, notice what he says,
now shalt thou see what I will do to Pharaoh.
God was about ready to work.
We start reading about the plagues here
in just a few moments,
but I want you to notice in verse seven,
what the Bible says,
and I will take you to me for a people,
and I will be to you a God,
and ye shall know that I am the Lord your God,
which bringeth you out
from under the burdens of the Egyptians,
and I will bring you in under the land
concerning the witch.
I did swear to give it to Abraham, to Isaac, to Jacob,
and I will give it you for an heritage.
I am the Lord.
Deuteronomy, the Bible says this in chapter six.
A great reminder as so much history has passed
between the portions of Scripture in Exodus three,
in Exodus chapter six,
and now in Deuteronomy chapter number six,
we find that the new generation has risen up.
The 40 years of wilderness wanderings are completed,
and we find now that Moses is preparing these people
for entrance into the land,
reminding them of the ways of God and the plan of God,
and we find that Moses will say this
in verse 23 of Exodus six,
and he brought us out from fence,
referring to Egypt, if you look at verse 22,
it says, and the Lord showed signs and wanders,
great and sore upon Egypt, upon Pharaoh,
and upon all his household before our eyes,
and he brought us out from fence
that he might bring us in to give us the land
which he swear unto our fathers.
The book of Joshua,
we're not gonna look there this evening,
but the book of Joshua records for us
the entrance into the conquering of,
the inhabiting of, the dividing of the land
that God promised to Moses,
and now repeats here, excuse me, to Abraham,
then to Moses, and so many others,
Jacob, of course, had received the promise,
Joseph, and we see here with Moses
in Exodus chapter number three.
So we see the perspective of God,
that God knows everything, that God sees everything,
we see the promise of God,
he says he's gonna bring them out,
that he might bring them in.
Now I want you to leave a little space
if you're keeping notes,
because there's a third promise
that I'm gonna circle back to at the end,
and I hope that you'd leave just a little space
in your notes here this evening.
I wanna give you the third thought
before I go back to that promise,
and so number three, if you're taking notes,
the plan of God, the plan of God.
So God reveals to Moses his perspective,
what he knows, what he sees, what he understands,
he then reveals to Moses his promise,
but then he gives him the plan,
like now here's how I'm going to do
what I've promised to do.
That's pretty neat that God does that,
it's pretty amazing that God makes the promise,
but then reveals to Moses how he's going to do it.
Now, the interesting thing
as we look at this portion of scripture
is that in verse number eight,
God in giving the promise, he says,
I am come down to deliver them,
who's then the children of Israel,
out of the hand of the Egyptians.
But we begin to think about the plan of God
as it's revealed here in verse number 10,
notice what God says to Moses.
Come now therefore, and I will send thee unto Pharaoh.
So in Exodus three in verse number 10,
he says, come now therefore,
and I will send thee unto Pharaoh,
that thou mayest bring forth my people,
the children of Israel, out of Egypt.
Now, when God reveals this plan,
there's something interesting that's revealed.
God said in verse number eight,
I am come down to deliver them.
But then in verse number 10, he says,
come now therefore, and I will send thee unto Pharaoh,
that thou mayest bring forth my people,
the children of Israel, out of Egypt.
Now, we understand what takes place
in the next chapter and a half
with regard to the dialogue between Moses and God.
It begins in verse number 11,
when Moses says, who am I?
But I want you to understand that I believe initially
that in verse number eight,
when Moses is first hearing that God's going to do this,
Moses is all on board.
This is great, God's gonna take care of this.
He's gonna come down, he's gonna bring the people out,
he's gonna bring them in, it's wonderful.
But then in verse number 10, God says to Moses,
now you come, I'm gonna send you.
Hold on a minute.
I thought you were gonna do this.
Well, I am, but I'm gonna use you.
See, what God reveals to Moses in this portion of Scripture
that's so important for us to understand
with regard to the plan of God
is that God's plan includes God's people.
God's plan includes God's people.
God, the creator of all things,
the Lord God Almighty, the strong one,
the self-existent one, the Almighty God,
he is going to use Moses.
Isn't that amazing?
You know what's even more amazing?
Is that he'll use us.
Not only that he will use us, but he wants to use us.
It's amazing.
It's almost beyond comprehension
for us to consider this evening
that the God of the universe would use us.
That he would use us.
See, God wants to use you tonight.
And I wonder this evening if we will surrender
and yield ourselves and allow God to use us.
How does God wanna use you?
I'm not sure how to answer the question specifically,
but I know generally speaking,
he wants to use you for his glory.
Amen?
He doesn't wanna use you so that you can be promoted.
He wants to use you so that he might be exalted.
And we find in this text of scripture
and in the portion of scripture that follows
with the dialogue and the interaction
between Moses and God,
we find that God is going to give Moses instruction.
And every time Moses provides an objection,
a reason that it shouldn't work or isn't going to work,
God gives him an answer and encourages him
and helps him to understand.
And so it's very interesting that in verse number 10,
that God reveals this plan of his,
this plan of how I'm going to fulfill the promise.
I am going to come down to deliver my people
out of the hand of the Egyptians
according to verse number eight,
and then to bring them into a land,
a good land according to verse number eight.
But then he says in verse number 10,
I will send thee unto Pharaoh
that thou mayest bring forth my people,
the children of Israel, out of Egypt.
And Moses said unto God,
who am I that I should go unto Pharaoh
and that I should bring forth
the children of Israel out of Egypt?
We find that there's other excuses that are given,
and we've spent time in past messages
over the years of reviewing the excuses of Moses
and the interaction and what have you,
but understand this evening that.
And many times, when God reveals His plan to His people, there's a moment of objection.
No, God, you got the wrong…no, I'm not…I can't speak, I'm not eloquent, right?
That's what He says at the end.
He was trained in all the ways of Egypt.
If you look at Acts, he was actually very mighty, and yet he offers this excuse before
God, and God simply says, who made your mouth, your tongue?
See, we can offer excuses to God as to why we're not the vessel, the individual that
God can use.
But it's far better that we'd come to a place of just surrender and yieldedness and
say, God, I want you to use me for your honor and for your glory, for the advancement of
your gospel, for souls to be saved, for lives to be changed.
I've shared recently in a number of services, and especially on Wednesday evening, I know
that some of you are in other classes and what have you on Wednesday evenings, but we
have a real problem that's going on in our independent Baptist churches with regard to
workers.
I'm saying about pastors and missionaries.
Ronnie was asking me after church this morning, what's going to happen to our churches?
And I said, Ronnie, we're in a problem.
We got a problem.
There's a dearth in the land.
There's a problem.
Young people are not answering the call of God.
They're just not.
There's been this drastic shift with regard to, if you were to look back at, and I'll
use the terminology of our movement, but if you look back at fundamentalism, if you will,
and you look at independent Baptist churches before my time in the 60s and 70s, I mean,
there were preacher boys being called, I mean, they're just, just, I mean, Bible colleges
were exploding and people were training for the ministry.
And I think in a number of ways, some of them weren't really called by God.
They were called by their parents.
It was kind of a, you know, a pushing them into the ministry kind of a situation.
And then we've had this shift that's taken place in our churches where there's almost
a discouragement to the next generation of answering the call of God.
Why?
Because you could do so much better for yourself.
You could go and work in this career or that career and you could have this kind of salary
and this kind of, and why would you, and there's almost this discouragement.
A number of years ago, there was a young man at camp and he felt as if God was calling
him into the ministry.
He felt as if God was calling him into youth work.
And it was said over my dead body.
How tragic, how sad.
But it happens and we're in a situation today where we have churches that have pastors that
are literally aging out.
It's not that they don't want to do it anymore.
It's not that they want to retire so they can go travel the world and just enjoy life.
It's that they just physically can't do the work of pastoring anymore.
Unless you've pastored, no one can fully understand the responsibility of pastoring.
Preaching is easy.
And I don't say that to say it in a way that it's not depending upon the Lord, but preaching
the public aspect of pastoring is the easiest part of pastoring.
By far.
The easiest part.
I mean, it takes time, it takes study, but it's enjoyable, the Holy Spirit of God helps
you.
Like, it's just, it's the easy part of ministry.
When Paul says, that which cometh upon me daily, the care of all the churches, that's
a big situation.
And so there are men that are just, I can't do it anymore.
But the problem is that there's no one in the ranks to follow.
But God's plan is that He uses people.
He uses people.
I said this on Wednesday evening and kind of belabored the point, the fact that the
Lord Jesus Christ, He said, listen, pray ye therefore the Lord of the harvest that He'd
send forth laborers.
Why?
Because the harvest is plenteous, but the laborers are few.
I talked to a president of a Bible college, he says, he says, Chris, we don't have anybody.
Nobody.
There is no name that I can give you of somebody that could go and possibly be a candidate
in pastor church.
Zero.
None.
I talked to two evangelists that circle this country every single year.
Don't know anybody.
A third evangelist that's primarily on the East Coast, don't know anybody.
A director of a mission board, he said, I got one guy, he's in his mid-40s, here's his
resume.
That's sad.
See, God still uses people today.
The question is, are God's people willing to be used?
Are we coming to a place of saying, Lord, it's like what Isaiah said.
But why did Isaiah say what he said in Isaiah 6?
It's because he saw God in his rightful place.
He saw God high, holy, and lifted up.
And when he saw God in his rightful place, he says, here am I, send me.
You know what's amazing about Isaiah 6, if you were to go back and study that portion
of scripture, Isaiah had no idea what he was volunteering to do.
He just volunteered.
Why?
Because he saw God in his rightful place.
He said, I'm willing to do whatever my God would want for me to do, whatever, wherever.
And then when he gets the details at the end of chapter number 6, he's told, by the way,
they're not going to listen to you.
Isn't that encouraging?
Ezekiel's told the same thing.
Hey, you're called to go to the house of Israel.
If you were called to a different people of a hard language, they'd listen.
But the children of Israel, they're not going to listen.
Well, that's encouraging.
But you know what's amazing?
Is that God measures, I'll use the word success, different than the world measures success.
Because God's way of measuring success is the faithfulness of the individual.
Are you faithful to the task that I gave you to do?
So God uses people, and he says to Moses, come now therefore, and I will send thee unto
Pharaoh.
But God, I thought you were going to do it.
Well, I am.
But I'm going to use you.
Isn't that amazing that God would use us?
I asked you to leave space because we're going to go back to that second point with regard
to the promise of God.
I believe that this really third aspect of the promise of God in this text of Scripture
is a powerful, I'll call it a life-altering promise.
And it's found in verse number 12, when God says these words, certainly I will be with
thee.
Wow.
God says, I'm going to do this.
I'm going to bring my people out.
I'm going to bring them in.
Moses, I'm going to send you to Pharaoh so that you can bring forth my people, the children
of Israel, out of Egypt.
And Moses says, who am I?
And God says this, certainly I will be with thee.
What a promise that God gives to Moses in Exodus 3 and verse number 12.
A promise of his presence.
The reality that God was not simply sending Moses on a task to stand before and he was
going in his own power and his own ability.
No, God says, I will be with thee.
You know what's amazing is that God's promise of his presence has been given to each of
us this evening as his people.
God says that he will never leave us nor forsake us.
Within the context of the Great Commission, we find that Jesus Christ, our Savior, the
Creator, he says, and lo, I am with you always.
What a great promise that God gives.
We ought never seek to do the work of God in our own power.
We must always be dependent upon God and we must recognize this wonderful promise.
Notice he says, certainly I will be with thee and this shall be a token unto thee that I
have sent thee when thou hast brought forth the people out of Egypt.
Notice what he says, ye shall serve God upon this mountain.
You know, God gave him a promise of where they would serve God after their deliverance.
That you will serve God upon this mountain.
And what a joy to understand the promise that God has given here with regard to his presence.
I wonder this evening, the, I almost said girls, but young ladies sang a wonderful song
about what God can do and how God wants to use us.
Considering the many things that were referenced that God has done in the past, but then how
could God use us?
God's perspective is such that He knows.
He knows.
He understands.
He's aware.
He sees.
He knows everything.
He knows their sorrows.
He said, I know their sorrows.
He knows tonight what you're dealing with.
He's given promises.
In the text of our Scripture, He gave promises specifically with regard to the deliverance
and out of Egypt and into the land of promise, to bring them out and to bring them in.
But He gave this final promise as we conclude the service of His presence, that I will be
with thee.
And we understand God's plan tonight, that God uses people.
God uses people.
It's amazing how God's creation, aside from humankind, obey Him supremely.
God's creation obeys.
I believe that Jonah, oftentimes we speak of him as being the disobedient prophet.
I believe that Jonah was pretty thankful that the whale obeyed.
Amen?
Jonah was pretty…
I think Jonah was happy that the whale obeyed in a different manner than he did.
He went…
What did Jonah do?
Well, he went the opposite way.
What if the whale went further into the center of the ocean?
Jonah didn't get spit up onto dry land.
Jonah's happy that the whale obeyed.
God's people, let me say it this way, God wants to use His people.
He wants to use you tonight.
Are we usable?
Paul talks to Timothy about being a vessel that's fit for the Master's use.
I hope tonight that when you recognize the plan of God, God wants to do some great things.
God's capable of doing some great things.
But God uses people, He uses people.
And how surrendered and yielded are we to allowing God to work in and through us, not
for our advancement, but for His glory, for His glory?
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
We thank You for the privilege of being able to be gathered here this evening.
We thank You for Your Word, the truth that's contained therein.
God, I thank You for the promise of Your presence.
Certainly I will be with Thee.
That's what You said to Moses.
And Lord, we still today understand that You've promised to go with us, to be with us.
And God, I pray that You would help us to submit to Your plan, that we'd be willing
to do whatever You have for us, that we'd go wherever You'd send, that we will be
faithful and obedient to Your plan.
I pray, God, that You would move and work in hearts and lives in these few moments as
only You can.
And we'll thank You for it in Christ's name we pray.