evening, Genesis chapter number 30, and this is part two of the message that I started
last week that I entitled, The Sons of Jacob, and of course, as we began studying last week,
we started to go through, starting in chapter 29 and verse number 31, and going down and
looking at the sons of Jacob and the way in which God blessed, and of course, his recognition
of understanding that life is a gift from God, and we're thankful that God is the giver
of life.
And as we studied through the first eight of the sons of Jacob last week and looked
at what was taking place, we understand that there was a real competition that was going
on between Leah and Rachel, and as we highlighted through the names of the sons of Jacob and
the way in which the mothers would name their children, that you would see that competition
that was taking place, and we mentioned as we went through and studied the names of
these sons and what their names mean and the recognition at times by the mother with the
name of God and recognizing God's favor and God's blessing, and then the depth of carnality
and the competition and how they began to compete one with another, and as we looked
at these first eight sons, we noticed and left on a high note with son number four in
verse number 35 of Genesis 29, that this son, his name was Judah, and here's what the Bible
tells us, that here's what Leah said in verse number 35 of Genesis 29, "'Now will I praise
the Lord.'
Therefore she called his name Judah and left bearing.'"
As we looked at that particular juncture of our text of Scripture and we mentioned
how that she says, "'Now will I praise the Lord.'"
Once again, she's acknowledging God as being Jehovah God.
That reference was completely dismissed when she named Levi in verse number 34.
There's no reference to God whatsoever, and here in verse 35 of Genesis 29, she's saying
that she's going to praise the Lord Jehovah, and she called his name Judah, which literally
means praise.
I believe that her joy and praise, as I mentioned last week, would be in the Lord, that no longer
would she be focused upon this conflict with Rachel, and what a joy and what a blessing.
But we find that Rachel begins to implement some really worldly, carnal behavior because
she sees that she has no children.
And seeing that she has no children, we find that she goes through these extents of being
able to have children legally and handmade, and we find that this competition and this
depth of carnality had a great impact upon Leah.
And I'm kind of reviewing these things very quickly because it's interesting when we left
off with Leah at son number 8 in verse number 13 of Genesis 30, I want you to notice what
Leah says, and the contrast between son number 4, Judah, and son number 8, Asher.
In verse number 13 of Genesis 30, it says, and Leah said, happy am I, for the daughters
will call me blessed, and she called his name Asher.
We mentioned that the name Judah means praise, and she says, now will I praise the Lord,
acknowledging Jehovah, and here after the carnality that Rachel employs, and after
all that takes place with this fleshly living, and Leah operating in like fashion, now she
can only name her son happy.
She says, happy am I, and notice what it is that would bring her a level of happiness.
She says, for the daughters will call me blessed.
You know, it's a terrible thing when we're more concerned about what people think about
us than what God knows about us, and we find that in this verse of Scripture, these two
verses of Scripture in verse 35 of chapter 29 and verse 13 of chapter 30, we see the
height and the depth in the life of Leah.
And as I mentioned last week, and I believe that it's important that we understand tonight
that we look at the historical context of this portion of Scripture, and we understand
that God is giving us the record of the sons of Jacob, but as we trace through and we see
what's taking place, we can understand as well that we can operate spiritually, or we
can operate carnally, and the reality is that there are times in which we can allow other
people to influence our behavior.
Leah was at a high point in verse number 35.
In Rachel, she employed fleshly, carnal methodology, and Leah responded in like fashion.
She goes from that pinnacle of spirituality, if you will, in verse 35, to a place of just
slinging mud and competing with her sister.
And that's tragic.
As we continue through the text of Scripture, we come to verse number 18 and we see son
number 9, and notice the Bible says in verse 17 of Genesis 30, it says,
And God hearkened unto Leah, and she conceived and bare Jacob the fifth son.
And Leah said, God hath given me my hire, because I have given my maiden to my husband,
and she called his name Issachar.
We find that here in verse number 18, we see son number 9, and his name Issachar means
there is recompense or there is reward.
I will say this for sake of the audience this evening, verses 14 through 17 I'm not going
to read publicly this evening, but I want you to understand that the circumstances surrounding
the birth of Issachar are unfortunate to say the least.
And when you see what happens between Leah and Rachel in those verses of Scripture, and
you see how Reuben the firstborn was used and how Jacob comes back and all of the carnality,
it's really a sad situation.
And here as she names him Issachar, there is recompense or there is reward.
We see once again this battle, this conflict between sisters.
And we find that in verse number 18 when she calls his name Issachar, she also says
this, notice what she says, God hath given me my hire.
She's acknowledged God, but she's no longer acknowledging God as being Jehovah.
She's acknowledging God as being Elohim or Lord.
And we've mentioned this before, we've seen this behavior in the life of Leah in previous
text of Scripture, in the life of Rachel, and we find here that as she has this ninth
son, that these circumstances that are just wild beyond our imagination, the depth of
carnality.
But as we see historically in the context of what's happening, we must understand that
we too can sink to some pretty low levels of carnality.
The Bible tells us in 1 Corinthians 10, let him that thinketh he standeth, take heed lest
he fall.
You know, it's absolutely imperative that you and I walk in the Spirit so that we do
not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
After salvation, the Holy Spirit of God indwelled us, isn't that wonderful?
And He enables us.
We still have a flesh.
And our flesh still has fleshly desires.
And we can still reach these depths of carnality.
And we see that here with son number nine, continue to move forward with me in verse
number 19.
It says that Leah conceived again and bear Jacob the sixth son.
And it says that Leah said, God hath endued me with a good dowry.
Now will my husband dwell with me because I have born him six sons.
And she called his name Zebulun.
The name Zebulun means dwelling.
And notice what she says, God hath endued me with good dowry.
She then makes this statement in verse number 20.
She says, now will my husband dwell with me.
Isn't that what she's been longing for all along?
She acknowledges in the beginning of our text in chapter number 29, how that when she had
Reuben that God, the Lord Jehovah, hath looked upon my affliction.
Now, therefore, my husband will love me.
And she goes through that process and she has that, that confidence when Levi is born
in verse number 34.
Now this time, will my husband be joined unto me?
Why?
Because I have born him three sons.
And we find that she was longing for that relationship with Jacob and that that's what
she desired.
And Rachel was desiring what Leah had.
She wanted to have children and she was barren.
We see this conflict that's taking place and she comes to this place in verse number 20
where she says, now you see the confidence.
Now Jacob will dwell with me.
I have born him.
She gave Him six sons.
It's interesting.
There was a time in which she acknowledged
that God was the One that was the Giver,
that God was the One that was in control,
and she comes to the place in the birth
of her fourth son Judah
where she says, now will I praise the Lord.
And here's the last of the sons of Leah, Zebulun,
and she refers to God.
She says, God hath endued me with a good dowry.
And she refers to God once again
as Elohim, not as Jehovah.
And we find once again this desire
that she voices of my husband
will dwell with me.
Afterwards, in v. 21,
the Bible says that she bared a daughter
and called her name Dinah.
And it says this in v. 22,
it's interesting, the Bible says that God remembered Rachel
and God hearkened to her
and opened her womb.
Let me just help us understand
a little bit about v. 22 here.
You understand that God doesn't forget anything.
So when the Bible says that God remembered Rachel,
it's not that he had forgotten her,
it's not in that context.
But we find that the Bible tells us
is the attention of the dialogue
is now turned back to Rachel.
And it says that God remembered Rachel.
Notice where it says that God hearkened to her,
he heard her, remember her desire
to begin chapter number 30.
In v. 1, it says,
and when Rachel saw that she bared Jacob no children,
Rachel envied her sister and said unto Jacob,
give me children or else I die.
We found that in chapter number 29,
the Bible taught us that she was barren
and she longed to have children.
And I think there's a great problem here
where she was envying her sister.
We mentioned that last week
and how terrible envy is
and we ought not be envious.
We ought not have envy in our lives
and we understand that that was her position
at the beginning of the chapter.
But as we come to the latter part here
of Genesis chapter number 30
and looking at the birth of Joseph,
we see that the Bible tells us
that God remembered her, hearkened to her
and had opened her womb.
And the reality is that that envy
that she had at the beginning of chapter 30
led to great strife.
It led to just carnality and fleshly living.
And if we're not careful,
envy in our lives will result
in the same type of behavior.
I understand that the circumstances
will be quite different than what they are here
in Genesis 29 and 30.
But it's amazing to me how there's this,
when there's envy, there's this desire for vain glory.
There's this desire for attention.
There's this desire.
And you see that between Rachel and Leah
and I believe that it's so imperative
that we can make that application in our lives.
The Bible tells us in verse 23 of Genesis 30
that she conceived and bear a son.
And notice what she says,
God hath taken away my reproach.
She says God hath taken away my reproach.
She recognizes that God is the giver of life.
She acknowledges God here in verse number 23
as being Elohim.
We see that in the verse that she says,
God hath taken away my reproach, the Lord.
Now remember that she says,
or Jacob said this to her in verse number two
of Genesis 30, when she said,
give me children or else I die.
He said, am I in God's stead
who hath withheld from thee the fruit of the womb?
Jacob is looking at Rachel and saying,
this is beyond my ability.
And here now we find that when she conceives
and bears a son that she says,
God hath taken away my reproach.
We spoke last week about the significance
within the culture of having children
and especially having male children.
You see it throughout the Old Testament
and you see that culture and that society
placing such an emphasis and importance upon that.
And she says, God hath taken away my reproach.
I want you to see in verse 24, the continuation here.
The Bible says that she, Rachel, called his name Joseph.
She called his name Joseph and notice what she says,
the Lord shall add to me another son.
I believe here as you see the name Joseph,
the word, the name literally means Jehovah has added.
And you see here that she says
that the Lord shall add to me another son.
And when you think about the name Joseph
and you think about the significance of Joseph,
and of course, as we close out over the next several months,
the book of Genesis will see a great emphasis
on the life of Joseph from chapter 37
until the end of the book.
And you see that emphasis,
but we find here that she calls his name Joseph.
And again, she's in this text of scripture,
she's not only referred to God as Elohim in verse 23,
but now in verse 24, she refers to the Lord as Jehovah.
She refers to the Lord as Jehovah.
I believe that in the life of Rachel,
it started with carnality and with envy
and all of this fleshly desire.
But as we come here to verse number 24,
and we see the birth of Joseph,
we find that now Rachel is the one
that is on this pinnacle of spirituality, if you will.
She's at this place where she's acknowledging God,
not only as Elohim, but also as Jehovah.
I believe that her life and her behavior
are now being dominated not by carnality, but by faith.
Notice what she says again there
at the end of verse number 24.
She says, the Lord shall add to me another son.
Not only is she now operating with this understanding
of God being the giver of life and God blessing her
and allowing her to have son,
but she now has this faith
that God's going to add another son.
You know, it's interesting,
the correlation between our walk and our behavior
and as we walk with God and as we're walking in the Spirit,
how we can exercise faith.
As we're walking with Him and we're trusting Him
and we're enjoying, I love this chorus
that we're singing this year that goes along with our theme.
I walk with the King, hallelujah.
I mean, it's a joy to walk with the Lord Jesus Christ,
to enjoy that fellowship with Him on a daily basis.
And we find that now Rachel is in this place
of really the mountaintop, if you will,
that Leah had vacated.
Leah had left that place at the end of chapter number 29
and she calls His name Judah and she says,
I'm gonna praise the Lord,
but she allows outward influences.
She allows those external influences
to impact her walk with God.
But now we find Rachel
on that mountaintop of spirituality.
We see Rachel not only being spiritual,
but we see the faith that she displays
when she says the Lord shall add to me another son.
This evening, we ought not allow any external influences
to affect our walk with God.
Honestly.
My walk with God must be protected.
Your walk with God must be protected.
And as we walk with God,
we're not going to allow the external influences
to hinder my walk with God.
I'm not willing to sacrifice my walk with God
because of some external influence in my life.
I'm not willing to get into a carnal match of wits
and of fleshly ambitions as Rachel and Leah
find themselves in and seeing my spirituality
just disappear.
No.
I'm walking with my King.
And you can't influence my walk with God.
Oh, that we'd really be in that place.
If we'd be honest this evening,
there are times no doubt that external influences
do in fact impact our walk with God.
I'm not speaking this evening
just of the positive influences.
I'm speaking primarily of the negative influences.
That we allow the behavior of others
that we would respond in like manner,
that we would go to the same level of carnality
as others would deal with
and that we would jeopardize our walk with God.
It's tragic.
It happens so often.
Turn to Psalm 90, if you will.
I want to look at just a reference here in Psalm 90.
Psalm 90 is a prayer of Moses.
We don't have time to look at the entirety
of the Psalm this evening,
but I want you to begin looking with me in verse number nine.
He says, for all our days are passed away in thy wrath.
We spend our years as a tale that is told.
The days of our years are three score years and 10.
And if by reason of strength, they be four score years.
Yet is there strength, labor, and sorrow
for to soon cut off and we fly away.
Who knoweth the power of thine anger
even according to thy fear.
So is thy wrath. So teach us to number our days that we may apply our hearts unto wisdom
I want you to look back in verse number 9 and I want you to consider that last phrase when he says we spend our
Years as a tale that is told
I want you to think about your story
I want you to think this evening about Leah and Rachel and their story in Genesis 29 and 30
And I want you to think this evening if we can make
Application and using this portion of scripture this evening to make application and to think about our own lives
I want you to think about their story
Because the Bible says that we live our life as a tale that is told
Every day there's some
Entry into our story
The the story of our lives is being written as I think about it from a from a
perspective of
My life and I think about the the entirety of my life
I think about the fact of course my story if I would look at it from a from a pure
Total lifespan of my life. It started on my day of birth
The greatest page inserted in my story was the day of my second birth and
If you've been born again, that's the greatest page in your story as well
Amen that day that we trust that the Lord Jesus Christ is our personal Savior
That's the I mean, by the way, that's the most important page at any of our books
But I want you to think about this as
our
life is being lived as
that
Story the tale that's going to be told. I want you to think this evening of
The way in which that that book is being written
and as we think about that book being written that tale that is told and and we think about the
The ending of that book is going to be when we leave this earth
None of our book has ended yet. You're all still here. Amen, and
But but the reality is that the book is going to end
We read books and we see there's a beginning to a book and there's an end to a book and our tale our life story
There's a beginning and there's an end
But I want you to think about the the entries into the book on a daily basis and I want you to think about
Who influences
How that story is written as?
We think about Leah and Rachel
Now we have the ability to read it
This portion of their life that's recorded for us. And by the way
It's not something that I'd be pleased to have preserved for other people to read
Amen I
It's tragic
The carnality
fleshly living
But God recorded it
Aren't you kind of happy that your story isn't gonna be read by people for you understand I'm saying
Would it be something if Leah's story
Was not influenced by Rachel
If Leah said you know what I'm not gonna allow that behavior that external influence to affect
my story
I'm not going to to go to that same measure. I'm not going to employ those same
behaviors
Unfortunately as we've read and as we've studied and as you know the passage of Scripture that's not what happened
But as we make application tonight and we think about our own lives
Who's that person that we came into contact with last week that really kind of?
Pushed our buttons. I used that phrase last Sunday night. My dad likes using that phrase. I
Have no idea what it means
I'm teasing. I know exactly what it means
But
Listen if we're honest this evening with the Lord and with ourselves
There are times that people
Influence how our story is written
Positive and negative
I'm thinking tonight more of the negative aspect because of the the context and what we're dealing with with Rachel and Leah
But
Oh that we'd come to the place where we say listen, I'm not gonna let you
External influence. I'm not gonna let your carnality
impact my walk with God
My tail that is being told I think about Joseph
that's the 11th son that we're speaking of here at this spiritual high point in the life of Rachel when she
Acknowledges God as both Elohim and Jehovah when her life is not only
Demonstrating her
Spirituality but her faith and we find that at this particular point
But when you think about the life of Joseph and you think about his story
Isn't it a blessing to read Genesis 37 through 50?
I understand that Genesis 38 doesn't deal with Joseph whatsoever, but it starts in Genesis 37
It skips 38 and 39 through 50 so much of the life of Joseph is on display
Are there some people that had an opportunity to have an external influence in the life of Joseph to cause him to live
fleshly and carnal
Absolutely, but do we read it? I
Don't read there in the life of
Joseph where he behaved himself unwisely
I don't read in the life of Joseph where he allowed the
the wicked behavior of his brothers when he allowed the the false accusation of
Potiphar's wife. I don't read where Joseph is allowing those things to cause him to respond in like fashion
right and
This evening we must understand as we look at this portion of Scripture that that God is
In control and God has a purpose and I must get to the point where I say my walk with God is of utmost
Priority and I'm not gonna allow these other people to influence my walk with God
I'm gonna keep my eyes on my God
I'm gonna I'm going to to seek to walk with him daily
I'm going to crucify my flesh. Listen. We all have the flesh and you know if
You'd be honest this evening, you know what thing it is that can get you into the flesh faster than any other thing
We know what it is
Don't we
Sometimes we allow competition that's what's going on here this conflict this competition between Rachel and Leah
Go back to Genesis chapter number 35, if you will, we ended in 30 in verse 24
when we read of the birth of Joseph and Rachel naming the
11th son of Jacob and she says that she calls his name Joseph and said the Lord shall add to me another son
many things transpire between the birth of Joseph and the
Final son that would be born to Jacob here in Genesis chapter 35 and over the next several weeks and months
We'll study these portions of Scripture and we'll see the events in the life of Jacob and all those things that transpire
But we pick it up in Genesis 35 in verse 16. The Bible says that they journeyed from Bethel
there was but a little way to come to Ephra Ephrath and
Rachel travailed and she had hard labor and it came to pass when she was in hard labor that the midwife said unto her fear not
Thou shalt have this son also and it came to pass as her soul was in departing for she died
That she called his name Ben. Oh, Ben. Oh nigh, but his father called him Benjamin
verse 19 says that Rachel died and was buried in the way of Ephrath, which is in Beth
Which is Bethlehem and Jacob said a pillar upon her grave. That is the pillar of Rachel's grave unto
This day we find son number 12 of Jacob born here in Genesis 35 in verse number 5 15. Excuse me
Rachel named him Ben. Oh nine, which means son of sorrow
but we find that Jacob named him Benjamin and we often
Obviously as we look at the tribe of Benjamin and we speak of Benjamin we use that name
That's the name that Jacob gave him and it's it means son of my right hand
or son of honor or good fortune and we understand that
Rachel here dies and she is departing
It says as her soul was departing in verse number 18 for she died and in the birth of Benjamin
And so thus we see the twelve sons of Jacob. I mentioned this last week
Obviously God could have just given us a list and just a few verses of Scripture and said here are the sons of Jacob
Bam, bam, bam, bam, bam, bam and just given us all twelve
But he gave us all of these details
some of which we've not read for sake of the the audience and sake of the the youth that's here this evening and we've
We've skipped over some of those things in the last two weeks
But as God has given us this
Passage of Scripture and he's given us the record of the sons of Jacob. I believe this evening that there is application in our lives
certainly
The circumstances are going to vary
The circumstances aren't going to be in having sons being born
But when you see the behavior between these two individuals, you can see that we can operate in like fashion
Isn't amazing the things that can cause us to get into the
flesh, and to behave carnally.
Let me just finish with this example this evening as we look at a New Testament principle.
It's in the book of 1 Corinthians, and we know as we'd study through the book of 1 Corinthians
that the church in Corinth was not a model church.
Amen?
The church in 1 Corinthians, in Corinth that's being written to there in 1 Corinthians, they're
not a model church, and they have so many problems.
Paul says, I can't write unto you as unto spiritual.
Why?
Because you're carnal.
He tells them right in the beginning of the book, he speaks to them about the reports
that he's received and how he believes them, and the carnality that was there.
But let me remind you, just as we look at this passage of Scripture with the sons of
Jacob, and we can look at it and say, what in the world is going on?
The depth of depravity really that you see in the carnality and the fleshly behavior.
Why must I remind ourselves of the church in Corinth?
You know what they were fighting about?
You know what they had carnality about?
There's a whole lot of things, but one thing in particular was spiritual gifts.
Now just think about that for just a moment.
Who gives the spiritual gift?
God, right?
We understand that biblically.
The Bible says that he giveth to every man as he wills.
Who gave the children for Jacob, the sons of Jacob, to Rachel and Leah?
It's God that gives children.
And that was the source of their conflict and their carnality.
And here we find in a church, a New Testament body of believers that have understood the
gospel of Jesus Christ that had been preached to them, and they've been saved by the blood
of Jesus Christ, that now they're having divisions and they're having fighting.
I'm of Paul, I'm of Cephas, all of that stuff is going on, but then there's this huge battle
over spiritual gifts.
My spiritual gift is better than yours, right?
You read the book of 1 Corinthians, it's absolutely what happens.
And there's this competition about the spiritual gifts, but we find that as we read the whole
of Scripture, we find that as we read the book of 1 Corinthians, that absolutely it
is God that gives the gift and he gives it for the purpose that all would profit from
it.
And ultimately the number one goal is that God would be glorified.
We find that Peter writes of spiritual gifts and he says, as every man hath received the
gift, even so let him minister as of the ability that God giveth, that in all things he might
be glorified.
And that's the purpose of the spiritual gifts.
But when we look at that example this evening in closing, it is absolutely striking to me
that we too as New Testament believers can get involved in mudslinging, fleshly, carnal
behavior.
And it ought not be.
It ought not be that Paul had to write to those believers as babes because they couldn't
handle because they were carnal.
This evening, I don't want to be carnal.
I hope that you have no desire to be carnal.
And I don't want to allow anyone else to cause me to operate in the flesh.
Paul said, I am crucified with Christ.
We are to mortify the old man.
We are to walk in the Spirit so that we do not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
A preacher of yesteryear, he said this often, he said, you know what's something that's
interesting about a dead man is that you can't offend a dead man.
It's a simple statement, but it's true.
And he said, if I am dead, if I've been crucified with Christ, you can't offend me.
I'm not going to be carnal.
And this evening, we see it in the life of Rachel and Leah, and oh, how we can criticize
and we can just say, how in the world?
Some of you came to me and said that.
You said something like this three weeks ago.
How are you going to preach that passage of Scripture?
I got a few of those questions.
I hope that after we've studied through this that we can see, yes, the historical context,
but we can make application in our lives and say, I'm not going to live that way.
I'm going to keep my eyes on Jesus, and I'm going to walk in the Spirit with the help
of God, by the grace of God, and I'm not going to behave that way.
And if my story were preserved and written down for others to read, they wouldn't read
that kind of behavior, amen?
Because I wouldn't want…
I'd be embarrassed.
Wouldn't you?
We say day by day, I'm going to walk with my Savior.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
Thank You for the Word of God.
Indeed, a challenging passage of Scripture that we've looked at these last two weeks,
but I hope in some way that as we've sought to make application and thinking about our
own lives, and even looking this evening in closing at the believers in Corinth, that
we'd acknowledge that we too can operate in the flesh.
Carnality can be prevalent in our lives.
We can allow those external influences to cause us to abandon spirituality and faith.
God, I pray that it would not be so in our lives.
I pray that we'd stay so close to You, that we'd be so concerned about protecting
our walk with You, that we'd allow for no external influences to hinder that walk, that
we would walk in the Spirit, that we would please You, and that You would be pleased
with our lives.
I pray, God, that You'd move and work as only You can.
We'll thank You for every decision that is made, for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Amen.