He is our refuge and strength,
a very present help in trouble.
In verses 2 and 3,
the idea really of the verses
is no matter what happens,
notice what the Bible says,
therefore, will not we fear.
Why? Because we understand who God is.
He's our refuge. He's our strength.
He is a very present help in trouble.
Therefore, will not we fear,
though the earth be removed,
and though the mountains be carried
into the midst of the sea,
though the waters thereof roar and be troubled,
though the mountains shake
with the swelling thereof?
Selah.
That word selah means let it sink in.
Meditate upon it. Think about that.
You notice in verse 7,
the Bible says,
the Lord of hosts, notice this,
is with us.
The God of Jacob is our refuge.
Selah.
Verse 10, be still and know that I am God.
I will be exalted among the heathen.
I will be exalted in the earth.
Verse 11, the Lord of hosts is with us.
The God of Jacob is our refuge.
Selah.
Isn't that encouraging?
God is with us.
He says as we notice the truth in Hebrews,
I will never leave thee nor forsake thee.
You understand even there in that passage of Scripture,
the implication of that truth is
therefore, we shall not fear
what man shall do unto us.
Why? Because God is with us
and God is for us.
We understand, listen,
people ask the question all the time,
why do bad things happen to good people?
If God really is in control,
if He really is omnipotent and omniscient,
why is it that we go through troubles
and trials and difficulties
so that He would be glorified?
You ever read John 9?
In John chapter 9, the disciples said,
who is it that sinned,
this man or his parents,
that he was born blind?
And Jesus said, neither this man nor his parents,
but for the glory of God.
You read the entirety of John chapter 9
and you'll find out that there are people
that are gathered there
that are the religious leaders of the day
that see the miracle of Jesus
and they stand with astonishment
and say we've never seen it like this before.
In fact, several chapters later
as the dialogue in John continues
following the life of Christ,
you find that at the tomb of Lazarus
that some were still talking about
the miracle of the man that was born blind
that was healed,
for they said, the one that could heal the blind
couldn't he have healed Lazarus?
Sure he could have.
But he let Lazarus die
so that he could bring him back from the grave.
Our God is in control.
He is our refuge.
A very present help in trouble.
How is it that God might be glorified
through a season of difficulty in my life or your life?
Isn't it worth it?
I mean, honestly, for God to get the glory,
for someone to get the Gospel.
Ms. Joyce convicted me on Wednesday evening
during prayer time.
She had to go to the dermatologist
and she mentioned about the opportunity
to speak with her doctor about the Lord.
And then said this,
I am praying that I have more cancerous spots
so that I can go back
and share the Gospel with her again.
I said, can you repeat that?
I want to make sure I heard you right.
If you were in the auditorium on Wednesday night,
you know that's how it happened.
I said, let me get this straight.
You're praying that you get cancer spots again
so that you can go back and share the Gospel.
Yes.
Praise the Lord.
And Paul said, the things that happened unto me
in Philippians 1 have happened
for the furtherance of the Gospel.
That was all for you this morning.
I hope it was a blessing to you.
First Chronicles chapter 22.
If you have a bulletin with you,
you see that we're preaching from this passage.
Not in the book of Colossians this morning.
And be looking at First Chronicles 22.
Really, I'll read the entire passage
and then really follow, trace if you will,
the circumstance that is there with Solomon
and then make some application for us this morning.
I do trust it will be a blessing
and encouragement to you.
In First Chronicles chapter 22,
we find here beginning in verse number one,
notice the Bible says,
then David said,
this is the house of the Lord God
and this is the altar of the burnt offering for Israel.
And David commanded to gather together
the strangers that were in the land of Israel
and he sent masons of hue rock stones
to build the house of God.
Verse three, and David prepared iron in abundance
for the nails for the doors of the gates
and for the joinings and brass in abundance without weight
and cedar trees in abundance for the Zidaneans
and they of Tyre brought much cedar wood to David.
And David said,
Solomon my son is young and tender.
The house that is to be built for the Lord
must be exceeding magnificent.
I like that terminology.
Of fame and of glory throughout all countries.
I will therefore now make preparation for it.
So David prepared abundantly before his death.
Then he called for Solomon his son
and charged him to build a house for the Lord God of Israel.
We'll get through the entirety of this passage
but I want to draw your attention to verse number 16.
The Bible says of the gold,
the silver and the brass and the iron,
there's no number.
Arise therefore and be doing
and the Lord be with thee.
This morning I've used that phrase
from verse number 16 as our title.
Arise therefore and be doing.
As we look at the text of Scripture
we would be reminded that just a few chapters earlier
in 1 Chronicles 17,
God provides us with a record of David's desire
to build the temple.
If you're familiar with the passage of Scripture
you understand that David had this desire
to build the temple and the man of God,
the prophet of God at that time was Nathan
and Nathan says to David,
go and do all that is within thine heart.
And that very night,
God Almighty appeared to Nathan and said,
no, that's not my plan.
That's not my will.
It's not for David to build the temple.
We know that contained within the dialogue
between Nathan and David,
as Nathan would convey the word of God to David
is the Davidic covenant as we've come to know it.
But we find that there,
as we would think about the way
in which God revealed His plan to David
and we look at the background really
to the text that we're looking at this morning
in 1 Chronicles 22,
I believe that even by way of introduction this morning
there are some valuable lessons for us
from the thought of 1 Chronicles 17.
Number one, think about this.
Though you desire a good thing,
God's plan must take priority.
It was not a bad thing for David
to desire to build a temple.
It was a good thing.
It was a commendable desire.
But God said, that's not my plan.
How is it that we would respond if God said no to us?
No, David, I don't want you to build a temple.
Sometimes you tell a kid no and you see how they behave.
Unfortunately, there are times in which you tell an adult no
and though they may not throw the same kind of fit
that Johnny will as two or three years old,
they kind of respond in like fashion.
We've just kind of been able to clean it up a little bit.
You understand.
But God told David no.
See, though you might desire a good thing,
God's plan must take priority.
Number two, another thought is that we need to rejoice
in God's faithfulness to reveal this plan.
I'm so thankful that God that night appeared to Nathan
and said, no, no, this is my plan.
Communicate this to David.
And Nathan was faithful to go and take to David
the plan of God.
I'm so thankful that God has revealed his plan.
He doesn't just leave us here with no direction, no plan.
He's given us a plan.
A third thought from that passage
that's really the introduction to this chapter
in 1 Chronicles 22 is that we need to submit
to the plan of God and do our part.
You know, when you look at David receiving a no answer,
David didn't just throw in the towel and say,
well, then fine, I'm not gonna do anything.
If I can't do what I wanna do,
I'm just not gonna do anything.
Kind of the kid on the basketball court.
If we're not gonna play by my rules,
I'm taking my ball and going home kind of an attitude.
No, no, David understood the plan of God
and David prepared and he worked
and he understood the future
and he understood that Solomon, his son,
was going to be the one to build the temple.
And so he was going to do his part
in the preparation for the construction of the temple.
That's commendable.
As we think about this text in 1 Chronicles 22
and fast forward from that desire that David had
and the plan of God being revealed,
I want you to consider with me this morning
the importance of David's communication to Solomon
as it's contained here in chapter 22
of the book of 1 Chronicles.
I want you to notice if you look at the text
and you're taking notes,
number one, consider what Solomon recognized.
In the first few verses of 1 Chronicles 22,
we've read them already.
We find that David is communicating here.
He's commanded in verse number two
to bring all of these individuals together
and we find that the scene is being set for us
as to this great event that is taking place
in Israel's history.
And we find the Bible would tell us
in these verses of Scripture,
those that had been gathered
and as David is then addressing
those that have been gathered,
he tells them that Solomon is his son
and young and tender.
And he tells them about the house
that was going to be built for the Lord.
And he tells them that Solomon
He tells them how that he prepared abundantly.
And then we find that in v. 6,
that he called for Solomon.
He called for Solomon.
And as he brings Solomon in to his presence,
we find that here Solomon is called
and will receive a charge.
We find that really from v. 6
all the way down through v. 16,
the attention now,
though there's all of these individuals
that are gathered together,
the attention and the focus of the passage
and the scene is that David
is issuing a charge to Solomon.
He'll address some of the others
throughout the process,
but primarily we find that the focus
in this next section of this chapter of the Bible
is that Solomon is receiving this charge.
I want you to consider what Solomon recognized.
We find in v. 6 that the Bible says,
then he, David, called for Solomon his son
and charged him to do what?
To build a house for the Lord God of Israel.
David rehearses what his desire was
in v. 7.
It says,
And David said to Solomon,
My son, ask for me.
It was in my mind to build a house
unto the name of the Lord my God.
But the word of the Lord came to me,
saying, Thou hast shed blood abundantly
and hast made great wars.
Thou shalt not build a house unto my name,
because Thou hast shed much blood
on the earth in my sight.
Behold, a son shall be born to thee,
who shall be a man of rest.
And I, God says, I will give him rest
from all his enemies round about.
Notice this, for his name shall be Solomon,
and I will give peace and quietness
unto Israel in his days.
He shall build a house for my name,
and he shall be my son,
and I will be his father,
and I will establish the throne of his kingdom
over Israel forever.
Now, think about these verses.
Think about Solomon receiving this charge,
this reference that is given to us
of Solomon standing there in the presence
of all of those that have been gathered
according to verse number two.
And David says,
Listen, Solomon, I want you to understand,
it was in my heart.
It was my plan.
It was my desire.
But God said no,
and God said that it would be my son.
Solomon, it would be you
that would build a temple.
And that's a big responsibility.
We find that David is going to give
the encouragement to Solomon.
He reveals to Solomon that this is the plan
and will of God for you, Solomon.
It is to build a temple.
He goes further and he encourages Solomon
to depend upon the Lord for the work,
for the task that was at hand.
He says in verse number 11,
Now, my son, the Lord be with thee
and prosper thou,
and build the house of the Lord thy God
as He hath said to thee.
Only the Lord give thee wisdom
and understanding
and give thee charge concerning Israel
that thou mayest keep the law
of the Lord thy God.
Then shalt thou prosper.
If thou takest heed to fulfill the statutes
and judgments which the Lord charged Moses with
concerning Israel,
be strong and of good courage.
Dread not, nor be dismayed.
Solomon, this is the plan and will of God for you.
Trust the Lord.
Depend upon God.
You need His strength.
You need His direction.
You need His wisdom.
And Solomon, this task that is before you,
this is your responsibility.
And God has revealed His plan.
And therefore, I want you to understand
that this I'm communicating to you.
Remember the significance of the communication
here between David and Solomon
in 1 Chronicles 22.
And Solomon had to recognize something.
And what Solomon had to recognize
is he had to recognize for himself
that this indeed is the will of God
and this is my responsibility.
We find that in verse 14
and really the beginning of verse number 16
that David communicates to his son Solomon
that the materials have been provided.
Notice in verse number 14,
Now, behold, in my trouble,
I have prepared for the house of the Lord
and a hundred thousand talents of gold
and a thousand talents of silver
and of brass and iron without weight.
For it is in abundance.
Timber also and stone have I prepared
and thou mayest add thereto.
Verse 16, of the gold, the silver,
and the brass and the iron,
there is no number.
David says, though it was not permitted
for me to build this house,
I understood the plan of God
and I prepared.
And here are the materials
that have been set aside.
The materials that have been provided
for the task that is at hand.
Not only did he provide the materials,
but according to verse number 15,
the labor was provided as well.
The Bible says, moreover, in verse 15,
there are workmen with thee in abundance,
hewers and workers of stone and timber
and all manner of cunning men
for every manner of work.
I like the perspective of David.
And I like the plan of David
and the preparation and the way in which
he was going to leave his son
in a position in which he could
fulfill the will of God.
See, David understood that this is the will of God,
that it was Solomon that would build a house,
and David didn't say,
well, then I'm going to just retire
and enjoy the rest of my days on life
and I'm going to sit back in my easy chair
and just enjoy life.
No, I'm going to prepare so that I can
have my son in a position
where he can do what God has for him to do.
That's commendable.
But really, the focus of the chapter
has to do with Solomon.
Is Solomon going to recognize and accept
that which is being communicated to him?
Is Solomon going to embrace
the responsibility that David is communicating?
The plan, the will of God for his life.
We find that in verse number 16
at the end of the charge.
I would say that it's a lengthy charge.
There's detail that is provided.
The latter phrase of verse number 16,
Arise, therefore, based upon Solomon
what I have communicated to you,
arise and be doing.
And be doing.
And the Lord be with thee.
In other words,
I believe that David is saying to Solomon,
you have your assignment.
Now get busy.
I've done my part to communicate to you.
You need to recognize that this is your responsibility.
I believe based upon the next chapters
that we're going to look at,
I believe that Solomon recognized
that this indeed was the will of God for his life.
He trusted what his father was communicating to him.
And as David, the king of Israel,
would communicate this truth to him,
we find that Solomon is going to recognize
that yes, indeed, this is my responsibility.
Thus, we find not only what he recognized,
but notice number two with me,
consider how Solomon responded.
How did he respond?
Let me finish reading chapter 22.
The Bible says David also in verse 17
commanded all the princes of Israel
to help Solomon, his son.
So we find that again,
those that were gathered according to verse number two
are addressed by David.
And he says to them in verse 18,
is not the Lord your God with you?
And hath He not given you rest on every side?
For it's given the inhabitants of the land into mine hand,
and the land is subdued before the Lord
and before His people.
Now set your heart and your soul
to seek the Lord your God.
Arise therefore and build ye the sanctuary of the Lord God
to bring the ark of the covenant of the Lord
and the holy vessels of God
to the house that is to be built
to the name of the Lord.
They recognize the responsibility,
but notice how Solomon, consider with me
how Solomon responded.
See, I believe this morning,
even before we look at turn over to 2 Chronicles 2,
but before we dig into that passage,
I want you to consider with me this morning,
the fact that he, Solomon had to recognize something.
Listen, no one this morning
or throughout the history of the church
would criticize Solomon for not building the temple
if it had not been communicated to him
that that was his responsibility.
Would you agree?
If David did not communicate to Solomon,
if David did not say this is your duty,
this is your responsibility,
this is the will and plan of God for you, Solomon,
and here's what I've done
and now this is your responsibility,
if that had not been communicated to Solomon appropriately,
then no one would criticize Solomon
for not building the temple.
However, if David, as he did, as we see,
if he effectively communicated to Solomon
the plan and will of God,
and Solomon said, not really interested in doing that,
I have other plans, I'm gonna do what I want to do.
Thanks, Dad, I know you're the king,
but I'm gonna live my life, I'm gonna do what I want to do.
From that point until now,
we'd have reason to criticize Solomon.
Would we not?
Why?
Because it was communicated to him
what his responsibility was.
And so how he responds to that
which he recognizes in chapter 22 of 1 Chronicles
is of significant importance.
We can recognize something as being the plan
and will of God, but how do we respond to it?
And we find here in the text of Scripture
in 2 Chronicles chapter number two
that I am thankful to be able to say
that Solomon responded properly.
In verse number one, notice the Bible says,
of 2 Chronicles chapter number two.
and Solomon determined to build a house for the name of the Lord and a house
for his kingdom." This wasn't something that just came into the mind of Solomon
one day, you know, I think I'm gonna build a temple. No, no, it had been communicated
to him that this was the plan and will of God, and therefore, I love the verbiage,
the Bible says, and Solomon determined. That word determined, we see that
Solomon's response to that which he understood, to that which he recognized,
he responded with determination, firm resolution, settled purpose. When you say
that you're gonna determine to do something, that's not a half-hearted
approach, is it? You ever hear somebody say, well, I'm gonna try to do that, and I
often say, don't try, you're either gonna do it or you're not. Don't tell me this,
I'm gonna try to do this, because really, we need to determine to do some things.
When we know that it's the plan and will of God, when we understand that God has
communicated and revealed to us what his purpose and plan is for us, we need
to respond with determination like Solomon did. And Solomon determined to
build a house. He understood and recognized his responsibility, and he
responds appropriately in verse number two, and Solomon told out three score and
ten thousand men to bear burdens, and four score thousand to hew in the
mountain, and three thousand and six hundred to oversee them. And Solomon
sent to Haram the king of Tyre, saying, as thou didst deal with David my father,
and didst send him cedars to build a house to dwell therein, even so deal with
me. Behold, notice what he says in verse number four, I build a house to the name
of the Lord my God, to dedicate it to him, and to burn before him sweet incense, and
for the continual showbread, and for the burnt offerings, morning and evening, on
the Sabbaths, and on the new moons, and on the solemn feast of the Lord our God.
This is an ordinance forever to Israel. I believe that we see in verses one
through four of 2nd Chronicles 2 that Solomon is responding with
determination. I find that in verses five and six that he responds with humility
and reverence. He responds with determination. I'm resolved, I have this
settled purpose that I'm going to do this, and it's good that he has
determination, but I find in verses five and six that his response is one of
humility and reverence. Notice the Bible says, and the house which I build is
great. Why? For great is our God above all gods. He understands the greatness of God.
He stands in awe of who God is. We find that if Solomon would recognize who God
is, and he would recognize the task that is before him, this is something that
will be done with reverence and with humility. You find in verse number six,
but who is able to build him in house? Seeing the heaven and heaven of heavens
cannot contain him. Who am I then that I should build him in house, save only to
earn sacrifice before him? You ever wonder why God lets us serve him? I mean,
honestly, he is the God of the universe, the creator and sustainer of all things,
but he loved us so much that he sent his son to die for us, so we can enter into a
relationship with him, and we can enjoy his presence, and he allows us to serve
him. Who am I? Who am I? I mean, you find in Isaiah, chapter number six, the call of
Isaiah, I'm a man of unclean lips. I mean, Isaiah falls in the very presence of the
holiness of God. God says, who shall go for us? I'm thankful that Isaiah says,
here am I. See, we may not have, as we look at the text of Scripture here, this same
responsibility. We understand that we don't. We're not building a temple today.
We understand that God has a plan and a will for our lives. And as I notice the
response of Solomon, he responds with determination, he responds with humility
and with reverence. I believe that he responds with understanding. Notice in
verse 7, send me now therefore a man cunning to work in gold and in silver
and brass and iron and purple, crimson, blue, and that can skill to grave with
the cunning men that are with me in Judah and in Jerusalem, whom David my
father did provide. Send me also cedar trees, fir trees, algum trees out of
Lebanon, for I know that my servants can skill to cut timber in Lebanon, and
behold, my servants shall be with thy servants. Even to prepare me timber in
abundance for the house which I am about to build shall be wonderful, great. He had
understanding. Remember it was David in 1st Chronicles 22 that told him he had
prepared, but that he also would be able to prepare and thou mayest add thereto
according to the last statement of verse number 14 of 1st Chronicles 22. But
remember that one of David, as he was charging Solomon, one of the statements
that he made was that only the Lord give thee wisdom and understanding in verse
number 12. I believe that Solomon displays here in chapter 2 of 2nd
Chronicles that he had understanding. He responded with understanding to that
which had been given to him to do. Turn over, if you will, to chapter number 3
here in 2nd Chronicles. Notice in verse number 1. Until we get to chapter 3,
verse number 1, it's all a plan. We can plan all kinds of things, but what
is it that that David charged Solomon with? Arise therefore and be doing. Not
arise therefore and be planning. Again, I'm not trying to say that planning isn't
important, but understand that we can plan and plan and plan and plan and plan
and plan up some more and never actually do. In chapter 2, there's still planning
that is taking place. Preparation, more materials, more workers. But in chapter
number 3, the Bible says in verse number 1,
then Solomon began. Then Solomon began to build the house of the Lord at
Jerusalem in Mount Moriah, where the Lord appeared unto David his father in the
place that David had prepared in the threshing floor of Arnon, the Jebusite.
Again in verse number 2, and he began to build in the second day of the second
month in the fourth year of his reign. There's a lot of preparation that was
going on, but I'm thankful that it came to the place where the work commenced. It
started. Arise therefore and be doing. And when we think about the response here of
Solomon, and we understand by his response that he recognized and embraced
the assignment that God had given him, and this morning as we think about
Solomon and we think about his response and we look at these portions of
Scripture in 2 Chronicles 2 and 2 Chronicles 3, we must conclude, we must
identify this morning that he, Solomon, embraced the assignment and
he engaged in the work. It wasn't enough if he just recognized that this was what
had to be done. It wasn't enough if he just said, well, somebody else can do
that. It's just gonna be too much trouble. I mean, this is a really big
assignment. This is, man, as far as we can tell, there are no excuses that are
offered. There's an understanding. There's a response. The embracing of the plan
that God has revealed through David, his father, and he engages in the work. We
notice in this morning, we consider what he recognized. We consider how he
responded. Notice with me, consider the result. Turn over to chapter number 5, if
you will. In chapter number 5 of 2 Chronicles, the Bible says in verse
number 1, thus, all the work that Solomon made for the house of the Lord was, what's
it say? Isn't that good? It was finished. It was finished. You might want to
underline or circle that word in your Bible because you find that the
admonition, the charge of David, arise therefore and be doing that in chapter
number 3, the work commences, it begins, and now in chapter number 5, we find the
Bible says that the work that he had, the house of the Lord, was finished. There's
something about finishing a task. There's something about seeing something through
to the end. One of my children follows in the same kind of personality thing that I
have of wanting to mark off some tasks that you do in a particular day. It just
makes me feel good to check a box that I completed something. And you say, you're
weird. I know, it's okay. And you got weird things about you too, amen? I remember
sitting in a seminar when I was working for Sikorsky in a leadership program and
we're there and we broke up into various groups and began to reveal what our
personalities and how we dealt with things and because of the assessment
that had been done they had already put us in certain groups and it was a great
relief to me to find that everybody at the table that I was sitting with was a
list person and they just found such satisfaction of checking off a box of
the list. I was like, man, this is wonderful.
I thought I was the only one and I'll let you in on a secret sometimes
I have my list of things that I'm gonna do and then something comes up that I have to do that wasn't on the list
You know what? I do. I add it to the list so I can check it off
Amen, it brings me satisfaction
Maybe some of y'all are gonna start taking a list you say I need to do something like that too, but but the reality he finished
He finished notice what it says in the rest of verse number one and Solomon brought in all
The things that David his father had dedicated the silver the gold the instruments
Put he among the treasures of the house of God
We don't have time to read the entirety here of this chapter nor the next
But I want to draw your attention to verses 13 and 14 of chapter 5
It'll remind you of what you read in Exodus chapter number 40 when?
The work of the tabernacle was completed and they reared it up and the wonderful blessing that you find
at the end of that chapter
another era
another group of people, but the same God
And we find that in second Chronicles 5 in verse 13. It says it came even to pass as
The trumpeters and singers were as one to make one sound to be heard in praising and thanking the Lord
When they lifted up their voice with the trumpets and cymbals and instruments of music and praised the Lord saying
For he is good for his mercy endureth forever that
Then the house was filled with a cloud
even the house of the Lord
So that the priests could not stand to minister by reason of the cloud for the glory of the Lord had filled the house of
God
You see there's a little word at the end of verse number 13 then
You don't get then if you don't do
Arise therefore and be doing if
Solomon did not respond properly if he did not embrace the task that had been assigned to him the will and plan of God
He's never going to see the glory of the Lord fill the temple. Why because he never built the temple, right?
So why is it that we get to this passage in 2nd Chronicles 5 verses 13 and 14 to see this great?
Just image in our minds and your sanctified imagination to see the temple being built into now
It's finished and the work is completed in the glory of the Lord fills the house
So much so that the Bible tells us that the priest could not stand to minister by reason of the cloud in
verse number 14 chapter 6 records for us how that Solomon is
Speaking there and of course the the prayer of Solomon is contained in much of chapter number 6 and
Really the last two-thirds of the chapter is the the prayer of Solomon
If you fast-forward to verse number 1 of chapter 7
I want you to notice that the Bible says now when Solomon had made an end of praying again
That's what we contain in the two-third the latter two-third portion of chapter number 6
We don't have time to read it this morning. Go back and read it later
But when he finished praying the Bible says that the fire came down from heaven and consumed the burnt offering and the sacrifices and the glory
of the Lord filled the house
the priests could not enter into the house of the Lord because the glory of the Lord had filled the Lord's house when all the
Children of Israel saw how the fire came down the glory of the Lord upon the house
They bowed themselves with their faces to the ground upon the pavement and worshiped and praised the Lord saying for he is good for his
Mercy endureth forever when you notice verse number 3
I want you to notice what the Bible says and when all the children of Israel saw how the fire came down
They saw how the glory of the Lord filled the temple
You know what those people got to see God work because somebody obeyed what God said to do
Amen all the people in Israel wouldn't have seen this great thing if Solomon said well
I don't know if that's really what I want to do
Arise
Therefore and be doing and
Solomon recognized the charge he accepted and recognized the the responsibility that was his and he responded in obedience
And he engaged in the work and the work is finished and God moves and God works and the people
See and worship the Lord
verse 11 of 2nd Chronicles 7 says thus Solomon finished the house of the Lord and the king's house and
All that came into Solomon's heart to make in the house of the Lord and in his own house. He prosperously affected
We see here as we would think about this portion of Scripture and really we've looked at a number of chapters this morning
As we look at this thought
Today with regard to Solomon and the responsibility and that which had been communicated to him
We understand that again as I mentioned a moment ago, there's no temple for us to build today
I'm not going to say to you this morning. Hey, listen, we need to go build a temple
It's not our responsibility
It's not the will of God for us this morning to go build a temple
But you know God has revealed to us what his plan and will is for us as a church
The church is the pillar and ground of the truth
The church is a lighthouse the church is a beacon the church is
The responsibility of the the believers, you know, we understand the church will use the term church, but we understand the church is made up of believers
we understand this morning that we'd speak about the the local church that it's a a
visible church the organized people that God has placed in the church the body of Christ and
And we find this morning that if we were to to take some
Application as we look at the life of Solomon and look at what takes place again this morning
We can rejoice that Solomon fulfilled what God had for him
And we can understand for a number of generations. There's the temple that's there in
Jerusalem and the beauty of it and all that took place there
It's because he did what God told him to do
David the king of Israel
gave
to Solomon his son who would become the king a charge a command if you will a
mission
Arise, therefore and be doing
We find that Solomon responded properly
I'd like to tell you this morning if we could make application for us as New Testament believers that the king of kings and Lord of
Lords has given us as his people a mission a
responsibility a duty a
Commission as we'd often refer to it as
And you'd find this morning that there are some even I I know a fella a pastor that actually wrote a book as he would
Speak about the Great Commission, and he said that really in our churches today. It's the great omission
Wow
The Great Commission notice what Jesus says in Matthew 28 turn over there you're familiar with the passage, but I want you to see it
In Matthew chapter number 28
Jesus has already gone to the cross of Calvary's already shed his blood. He's been to the tomb
He's risen in victory conquering sin death in the grave. He's appeared to the disciples. It's soon before now
He will be going and ascending to heaven
But before his ascension he speaks to his disciples and in Matthew's
Account here the Bible says in verse number 18 of Matthew 28 and Jesus now understand who he is
He's king of kings the Lord of Lords. He's spake unto them saying all power is given unto me in heaven and in earth
Go ye therefore I understand the the verbiage is different
But you remember what David said arise therefore and be doing here. We find it says go ye therefore
And teach all nations
Baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son of the Holy Ghost
Teaching them to observe all things whatsoever. I have commanded you and lo I am with you all way even unto the end of the world
Amen
What a powerful instruction that's been given to us
now this morning
We mentioned that David communicated to Solomon. He was faithful to communicate the plan the will of God
Remember David in 1st Chronicles 17 he had in his heart. I'm gonna build a temple
Nathan said go and do it and then God said to Nathan no
That very night God appeared to Nathan and said you need to go and you need to tell David
no, and and share with him what my plan and what my will is and
David takes that instruction from God and then he communicates that to Solomon thus making Solomon
responsible
Amen if
David did not communicate to Solomon the plan and will of God as I mentioned earlier this morning
He would not we would not go through the process of criticizing Solomon for not doing what he didn't know. He was supposed to do
right
Anyone ever say to you? Why didn't you do that? And you're like you didn't tell me to do that and
Now I'm accountable for something that you didn't even communicate to me to do
Can I tell you that God Almighty?
Has been faithful to communicate to us as his people what his plan and will is
It's not a matter of whether or not God communicate it the truth to us
really
It hinges upon our response to what has been communicated
Because God has clearly
Faithfully communicated what his plan and will is for us as a church a church is not a club
It's not a church has got a mission a purpose
a plan. We think that here as God would communicate to us maybe this morning
it's possible that there'd be one that would sit amongst us or one that's
watching on livestream that honestly this morning before the Lord was
ignorant to the teaching of the Great Commission and they say I never knew
that I never knew that that was my responsibility it's absolutely possible
but now you know. Is that fair? And so the question is how do we respond? We rejoice
with Solomon as to how he responded to the assignment what his response was to
to that which had been communicated to him and so this morning as we think
about an application for us as the people of God in 2021 the question would
be do we recognize our assignment and if so as we'd answer if we don't
recognize it we teach it as we recognize the assignment this morning the question
is how do I respond? How do I respond? Is it possible this morning that Solomon do
you think that it's possible this morning that Solomon could have offered
some excuses for not doing that that work? Sure he could have. I mean man is
full of excuses. Amen? You just talk to people for a little while and you
understand we got excuses for all kinds of things but we find that Solomon
didn't make excuse. He got busy. He got busy preparing planning but then the
work began. Arise therefore and be doing. You understand as New Testament
believers according to James chapter 1 and verse number 22 we're not to be
hearers only we're to be doers of the Word. Doers. Taking the truth that's been
communicated to us from the Word of God and putting it in practice in our life
and doing working out the will of God in our lives. According to Acts 5 and verse
number 32 we are his witnesses. According to 2nd Corinthians 5 and verse number
20 we are his ambassadors. His representatives. By the way you'd
understand that that's not simply referring to someone that would fill a
clergy quote-unquote position. That's a born-again believer. We're his witnesses.
You know what makes us effective witnesses is that we've been born again.
If you've experienced what Jesus has done for you, if you've experienced the
transformation power of the gospel and you've been saved it makes you a
witness. You can be effective as a witness because you've experienced what
Jesus did for you. I was taking Brianna out yesterday to do some highway driving
because she's getting ready to get her license. By the way kid I make
congratulations on getting your license. We've been more careful recently. I'm
just teasing but congratulations. So Brianna is getting close to the point of
getting her license. She's not driven on the highway on 66 and so I said we're
gonna drive out to Front Royal and we did. And wouldn't you know that just as
we're getting close to Gainesville there's a three-car accident right in
front of us. It was right in front of us with about 200 cars in between us so
guess what I didn't see what happened. So if an officer showed up and said hey can
you give me a statement were you a witness? All I could have done in that
situation is assume what happened based upon what I saw. That's not a good
witness. That's not reliable in a court of law. But there was a truck that was
there that seemingly was right behind it when it happened and he pulled off to
the side and I think he was an eyewitness based upon how he was
behaving. And I think he could probably give a good report as to what happened.
Why? Because he saw it. He was an eyewitness. He doesn't have to assume
that something happened. He doesn't have to well I think maybe this and I think
it was that car. No he saw it. If you've been born again you're a witness and
you're effective in being a witness because you can say this is what this
is what Christ did for me. This is how he changed my life. This is how he gave me
not only eternal life but he gave me abundant life and we're his ambassadors.
And the Bible tells us in Ephesians chapter number two when we think about
that great truth of the fact that we're saved by grace through faith it's not of
ourselves that it's the gift that we understand that it's not by works lest
any man should boast but we notice in chapter number two in verse number ten
the Bible says this in Ephesians 2 10 for we are his workmanship created in
Christ Jesus unto good works which God hath before ordained that we should walk
in them I would say this this morning being a disciple of Jesus Christ would
be best described as being a participant and not a spectator a participant getting
involved in the work of God what is it that God wants for me to do where is it
that I can serve God how is it that I can be a witness that I can take that
Great Commission that has been communicated to me from God Almighty the
King of Kings and I'm going to embrace it and I'm going to seek to to be the
witness that God would enable me to be and by the way you don't go in your own
power he said I'm with you you shall receive power after the Holy Ghost has
come upon you right in Acts 1 in verse number 8 I'm so thankful that I don't
go in my own power my own strength and I don't have to come up with whatever the
if you read all of the text between 1st Chronicles and 2nd Chronicles you know
David gave some plans for the temple he made lots of preparation you understand
that when you go out to to give the gospel to people you don't have to come
up with your own ideas of what to say just get on the Word of God and then
guess what the Holy Spirit of God uses the Word of God and he convicts and
convinces John tells us that he's to reprove the world of sin of Christ
righteousness and of judgment to come as we use the Word of God he does that what
a blessing March Madness is going on right now I don't have a TV so I'm not
seeing any of the games but I've seen some of the news and typically in a
normal year it's a very exciting time of the year for college basketball and it's
interesting obviously with regard to Kovat and what-have-you there's some
places they have spectators not as many as they used to have but it's a very
different thing being a participant on that floor and being a spectator right
our team won what did you do I watched I cheered I know man that guy hit the
winning shot I saw this morning and again I don't really normally use sports
but Texas got beat by somebody they shouldn't got beat by and that guy stood
at the foul line down by one with 1.2 seconds left and had two shots whoo he
made both of them and they won that guy has got a different perspective than the
guy sitting in the stands and here's the amazing thing turn over to first
Corinthians and we'll look at this and then I'll say what I was going to say
1st Corinthians chapter 3 the church in Corinth there was division and
carnality and all of that that was going on and Paul gives them valuable
instruction we know it's the Word of God in verse number 5 of 1st Corinthians
3 the Bible says who then is Paul and who is Apollos but ministers by whom you
believed even as the Lord gave to every man remember when Solomon said when he
responded with reverence and humility who am I to build a house for God you
know who are we to go and proclaim this message other than the fact that God
would call us to do so Solomon who am I to do this well this is God's plan and
will for you Solomon it's God's plan and will for you to go tell somebody
about Jesus you say well I'm not qualified if you're saved you're
qualified and by the way not being qualified isn't a good excuse anyway get
qualified if you feel like I don't know what to say find out what to say amen
who are we we're just servants we're just ministers notice verse 6 I have
planted Apollos watered but God gave the increase so then this is good
because it helps us with that humility thing so then neither is he that plant
death anything try to get full of yourself man I gave that person the
gospel we're nothing we're just servants just ministers neither he that
watereth but God that giveth the increase now he that planteth and he
that watereth are one and every man shall receive his own reward according
to his own labor notice this for we are laborers together with God you're God's
husbandry you're God's building I wonder this morning how are we laboring
together with God how are we laboring together with God we're familiar you
don't need to turn there we don't have time
but we're familiar with the account in Mark chapter number 2,
the man that was born of four.
And you think about the text of Scripture,
and you think of all that's taking place there,
that man had no way to get to Jesus on his own.
And I believe it was very unlikely that one person
was going to effectively be able to get him to Jesus.
And so he gathered, the one maybe gathered his friends and said,
hey, listen, you take that corner, you take that corner,
I'm going to get this corner and you get that corner,
and we're going to take this guy to Jesus.
And we're laborers together with God,
according to 1 Corinthians 3 and verse number 9.
And I just wonder this morning,
arise therefore and be doing.
Arise therefore and be doing.
Are we really putting into practice our Christianity?
Are we living out the Gospel?
We're His representatives.
There are many people today that would give all of their opinions and ideas
as to what's wrong with our nation and our world.
The answers vary and there are many.
But I would submit to you this morning that one of the main factors
that has led to so much wickedness in our world
is the fact that the church has not fulfilled its responsibility.
And it falls on our shoulders to repent and say,
you know what God, forgive us.
We've not done what you've called us to do.
We got real comfortable, been real convenient for a season.
We see wickedness is prevailing all around us.
What's the answer?
Elect somebody different.
Baloney.
It's not the answer.
The answer is Jesus.
And until we as the church stand up and rise and be doing,
we can expect more of the same.
In fact, worse and worse.
We're the light of the world.
Brannon and I were singing this morning on the way to church.
She's been coming early with me on Sunday mornings.
This little light of mine.
I'm going to let it shine.
We sing it with the kids.
But somewhere in between adolescence and adulthood,
we get to the place where we say,
no, I am going to hide it under my bushel
because I don't want anybody to know
because I don't know that they're going to respond.
Right?
We got to rise up.
Arise, therefore, and be doing.
Do the work of God.
We commend Solomon.
We applaud, rejoice in reading 2 Chronicles 5-7.
I mean, it's an exciting portion of Scripture.
And just as those individuals in Israel saw the glory of God,
you know, when you engage in sharing the gospel,
not every person you share the gospel with is going to be saved,
but eventually you're going to see somebody get saved.
Man, I can't even explain to you, humanly speaking,
what that joy is like.
When you see somebody in a moment pass from death unto life,
if you've led somebody to Christ in your life,
you know what that experience is like.
It's amazing.
But if you ain't sowing the seed,
you're probably not going to have that opportunity.
Arise, therefore, and be doing.
Let's pray.
Father, I thank You for convicting me,
not only as I prepared the message,
but even now as I've delivered the message.
Thank You for Solomon.
This portion of Scripture, the charge from David,
the King of Israel, to his son.
I'm thankful this morning that You are the King of Kings
and that we are Your children, the sons of God,
because we've believed in Your name.
We've been saved.
And though the verbiage is different
from 1 Chronicles 22.16 to Matthew 28.19,
I believe the sentiment is similar, if not exact.
Go ye, therefore, is what You've told us.
David said, Arise, therefore, and be doing.
God, would You help us this morning to be honest
and responsive to the Word of God?
Your witnesses, your ambassadors, your workmen.
Help us, God, to recognize our responsibility,
to respond properly to it,
to embrace and engage in the work.
That we might see You work in a mighty, powerful way.
Christ Jesus came into the world to save sinners.
He's able to save them to the uttermost.
We believe, even as we sing the song,
Jesus saves, that You still save.
You're the Savior of the world.
And oh, that we'd be careful to obey Your instruction.
As we have this time of invitation,
I pray that You'd work and move the hearts of Your people.
I pray this morning that the response
would not be one of emotion.
Emotional responses rarely last.
But I pray for a response that would endure,
because it's based upon the truth of Your Word.
We'll thank You and praise You for the work that You'll do
and for the decisions that are made.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would You stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano.
And as she does, I want to give you an invitation,
an opportunity to respond.
At this altar or in your pew,
would you let God have His way in your life
as Kimberly plays?