is chapter 11, and I know that the bulletin says Revelation chapter 2, and that was my
plan at the beginning of last week, and as we went through the week, God kept pushing
me, pushing me towards 1 Corinthians 11. We're observing the Lord's Supper this evening,
and I want to take some time to study through this passage as we prepare this evening to
observe the Lord's Supper. I believe that it's important to be reminded of some things
that God shows us here in this passage. Typically, we deal with verses 23 down through verse
number 31. I want to back it up and begin in verse 17 this evening, in 1 Corinthians
chapter number 11, beginning in verse number 17. Notice the Bible says now in this that
I declare unto you, I praise you not, that you come together not for the better, but
for the worse. For first of all, when you come together in the church, I hear that there
be divisions among you, and I partly believe it. For there must be also heresies among
you, that they which are approved may be made manifest among you. When you come together,
therefore, into one place, this is not to eat the Lord's Supper. For in eating, everyone
taketh before other his own supper, and one is hungry, and another is drunken. What? Have
ye not houses to eat and to drink in? Or despise ye the church of God, and shame them that
have not? What shall I say to you? Shall I praise you in this? I praise you not. In
verse 17 and verse 22, you see repeated that phrase, I praise you not. The Apostle Paul
is dealing with a church that is a carnal church. In fact, we find that he mentions
in verse number 18 that when they come together, that he heard that there were divisions. He
says, I partly believe it. Of course, the Apostle Paul had been given a report about
the things that were taking place in the church in Corinth, and if you were to go
all the way back to the beginning of the book, you find that he begins to call them out for
those things, beginning in verse 10 of chapter number 1. In verse number 11, he says that
there are contentions among you. And Paul was aware of the contentions and the divisions,
and he was aware of the fact that they were carnal. Remember, it's to this church that
the Apostle Paul says that I have many things to write to you, but I can't write them to
you because you're carnal. You can't receive them. You're not able to receive what I have
to give you. And so Paul, with regard to the instruction that we've so often referred to
in this portion of Scripture as the instruction for the Lord's Supper, he begins with a very
strong correction to the church and tells them, I praise you not. They were not doing,
they were not observing the Lord's Supper in the manner in which they ought to be observing
the Lord's Supper. So then Paul begins to give them the instruction in verse number
23, of course, for us, the passage that guides us into the how, if you will, that we observe
the Lord's Supper. And he says this, for I have received of the Lord that which also
I delivered unto you, that the Lord Jesus, the same night in which he was betrayed, took
bread. We find that he begins to provide the instruction for us. And as we look at this
instruction that is here, we find that it's the most detailed instruction with regard
to this ordinance for the local church. And we understand that this, as we'd refer to
it as maybe a memorial, the Lord's Supper, that it is one of two ordinances that's given
to the New Testament church. This ordinance has a specific purpose, just as baptism has
a specific purpose. And we understand that just as so many other things have been taken
out of context, so also has the biblical teaching of the Lord's Supper been taken
out of context and misunderstood. It's been taught inappropriately. And so it's important
that we understand the purpose, but that we do not misunderstand what God is giving to
us with regard to the Lord's Supper. We must guard against the Lord's Supper becoming simply
a religious activity. We must guard against it just becoming a religious activity.
You ever hear of the term rote religion? I mean, just going through the steps, if you
will, and just kind of on autopilot. How many of you know your ABCs? How many of you would
we probably, if we're going to recite the ABCs tonight, probably almost all of us would
recite it the same way with the same tune because of how we learned it. It's rote. It's
rote learning. It's what it is. But we don't want to have rote religion, right? We don't
just, it's not just a religious exercise. It's not just some religious exercise that
we observe the Lord's Supper on the whatever day or whatever it might be. No, this is a
sacred time for the local church. And it's so important and it's so vital that we understand
the instruction that God has given. Furthermore, we must understand that the elements of the
Lord's Supper do not have the power within them to save anyone. They do not have the
power within them to give anyone a certain extra special blessing. These elements are
elements that are representative of what or who the Lord Jesus Christ is, His body that
was broken for us, His blood that was shed for us. But these elements, the cracker, the
unleavened bread and the juice, the unfermented grape juice, those elements are never going
to change into something other than what they are. They were put here, Holly prepared for
the Lord's Supper this afternoon and she put those elements here and those elements are
always going to be what they were when she put them there. But they're a picture. They're
memorial. They're helping us to remember what Christ did. And so we find that as we go through
the text in verse number 24, the Bible says,
And when he had given thanks, he break it and said,
Take, eat. This is my body which is broken for you. This do in remembrance of me.
After the same manner also he took the cup and when he had supped, saying,
This cup is the New Testament in my blood. This do ye as oft as you drink it in remembrance
of me. If I would think tonight of the Lord's Supper and the elements being a memorial and
a picture, first we must remember. You know, as human beings we're prone to forget. I mean,
I don't think any of us would come in here this evening and forget that Jesus died for
us. But sometimes we don't remember with the same depth of appreciation that we ought to
remember. We don't have the same level of remembrance every day of our lives with regard
to what Christ did. And I made this statement a number of months ago with regard to our
loving the Lord Jesus Christ as we should. And I said that if we'd take the time to read
the last couple of chapters of each of the gospel records that would go a long way in
impacting our lives and giving us a greater level of gratitude for what Christ did for
us. What does it do? It reminds us. Notice the price that was paid for my sin and for
your sin. The brutal death that the Lord Jesus Christ experienced on the cross of Calvary.
He said this is, as he talks about the bread, he said this is my body. Notice which is broken
for you. We know that no bones were broken. And by the way, that's a fulfillment of prophecy
that not a bone would be broken. But we begin to think about all that the Lord suffered
on the cross and how his flesh was literally torn away and ripped away and all that took
place. And he says that it was for you. It was for me. We sing that song oftentimes.
It's a song that we'll sing around the resurrection Easter season of it was for me. What a great
reminder. It was for me. He says this is my body which is broken for you. This do in remembrance
of me. Notice when he speaks about the cup representing the blood of the Lord Jesus Christ,
that sinless blood, the blood that needed to be shed for the remission of sins without
the shedding of blood. There is no remission. The Bible plainly tells us in Hebrews chapter
nine, we understand that all of the Old Testament just pictures that God gave us. We can go
back to Cain and Abel and we can understand the importance of the blood and we can understand
the pattern that was set forth of a of an offering and go even before Cain and Abel
and you can go to the garden and after the sin and entered into the world and after the
word there pronounces the judgment and they were clothed in leaves, right? They made themselves
coverings of leaves and it was not sufficient and what had to happen? Well, an animal had
to lose its life and blood had to be shed so that God could provide for Adam and Eve
a covering of skin. We see throughout the Old Testament, you're reminded of the Passover
and the blood that had to be applied, the blood, the blood, the blood, the brazen altar.
I mean, every time that you would visit the tabernacle, every time that you would go to
the temple, the nation of Israel would be confronted upon immediately entering into
the tabernacle and then later the temple with the brazen altar where sacrifice was made,
that blood was required.
And Jesus shed his precious blood for us so that we could have eternal life.
It says, this cup is the New Testament in my blood.
This do you as often as you drink it in remembrance of me.
We find that the Lord wants us to remember.
Not only does he want us to remember, but he wants us to expect his soon return.
The Bible says for as often in verse 26, as you eat this bread and drink this cup, you
do show the Lord's death till he come.
Obviously we understand that Jesus was buried in a borrowed tomb and he rose conquering
sin, death and the grave.
We spoke about that a little bit this morning.
We find that he's coming again and what a wonderful truth that is.
And every time we observe the Lord's supper, we show the Lord's death till he come.
We're reminded of what Christ did for us personally on that cruel cross, but we're reminded and
we have that expectancy that Christ is going to come again.
And all what wonderful truth that is.
We see that God provides this instruction.
And then as we move further into the text, we come to the portion that I really want
to focus our time on this evening.
In verses 27 through verse number 31, the Bible says this, wherefore, whosoever shall
eat this bread and drink this cup of the Lord unworthily shall be guilty of the body
and blood of the Lord, but let a man examine himself and so let him eat of that bread and
drink of that cup for he that eateth and drinketh unworthily, eateth and drinketh damnation
to himself, not discerning the Lord's body.
For this cause, many are weak and sickly among you and many sleep for if we would judge ourselves,
we should not be judged.
As we look at this portion of Scripture and really the title for the message this evening
is let a man examine himself from verse 28, we find in verse 27 and then again in verse
number 29 that God uses this word unworthily.
And it's a word that is so important for us to understand and the reality is that in of
ourselves none of us are worthy.
The reality is that none of us on our own merit, on our own worth can enter, can even
come close to the throne room of God.
Amen?
But I'm reminded of the wonderful truth that God gives us in 2 Corinthians 5 verse 21,
for he hath made him to be sin for us who knew no sin, that we might be made the righteousness
of God in him.
And now as I approach the throne of God, as I enter into the presence of God, I'm doing
it not on my merit, not by my worth, but because I have been saved by the grace of God.
And I have been clothed in his righteousness.
It's not my own righteousness, it is the righteousness of Christ that has been imputed upon me.
And so when we understand that truth, we must acknowledge that now as Paul is writing to
this church at Corinth and he speaks about this subject of being unworthy and eating
and drinking unworthily, I believe that what Paul is dealing with and what God wants us
to focus on this evening as we look at this truth and as we examine ourselves and prepare
ourselves for observing and partaking of the Lord's Supper, that it is important that we
have no unconfessed sin in our lives.
It is unconfessed sin in the life of a believer that would lead the believer to being in a
place of verse 27 and verse 29 of being unworthy to partake.
Now I've said this for many years and it's worth repeating again this evening.
The idea as we come to this portion of Scripture, as we prepare to observe the Lord's Supper
this evening, is not that I would sit in a pew, that I would examine myself and say,
yep, I have unconfessed sin in my life and so therefore I'm going to let the plate pass
me by.
The idea is not to be aware of the unworthiness and to stay in that state.
The idea of examination is for the Holy Spirit of God to expose and reveal sin in my life
that I would then confess that sin and have the promise that God gave of forgiveness.
It would be crazy to have known sin in the life of a believer and do nothing about it.
In fact, it says, whoso covereth this sin shall not prosper.
And we'll look at that verse here in the book of Proverbs as we go through the message this
evening.
As we begin to think about this idea and understanding that as believers we must determine to deal
with sin biblically, sin hinders my fellowship with my Savior.
Sin will hinder your fellowship with your Savior.
Sin will rob you of the joy that you can have in Christ.
Do you remember what David said in Psalm 51, restore unto me the joy of thy salvation?
See David didn't have to get saved again, David just had to get right with God.
And David lost the joy of his salvation because of his sin.
By the way, David did not immediately confess his sin, did he?
He did just about everything a man could do to cover his sin.
And it wasn't until Nathan the prophet of God having the message from God stood and
said thou art the man that David confesses his sin and I'm thankful that God forgave
him.
That's a great pattern for us this evening to understand the truth that our God is ready
to pardon and ready to forgive.
In this very book of 1 Corinthians as we would find that even prior to getting to the passage
that is before us this evening with regard to observing the Lord's Supper and the instruction
that the church needed to have and the importance of self-examination and the importance of
eating and drinking worthily, we find that the Apostle Paul dealt with the subject of
sin.
We find that back, if you will, in 1 Corinthians chapter number 6.
Someone said this.
It's recorded a number of years ago that a member of a church said to the pastor after
the pastor preached on sin said, listen, sin in the life of a believer is different than
sin in the life of a lost person and the pastor said, yes, it's worse, it's worse.
What a perspective, what a proper perspective.
In 1 Corinthians 6, the Bible says in verse 18, flee fornication.
Every sin that a man doeth is without the body, but he that committed fornication sinneth
against his own body.
Then notice verse 19 and 20, they're familiar verses of Scripture but worth reading this
evening.
What?
Know ye not that your body is the temple of the Holy Ghost which is in you, which you
have of God and you're not your own?
For you're bought with a price, therefore glorify God in your body and in your spirit
which are God's.
In the 10th chapter of this book of 1 Corinthians, we find that the Apostle Paul beginning in
verse number 5 begins to share with the people there in Corinth about some Old Testament
examples and we find that he says of these beginning in verse number 5, but with many
of them God was not well pleased, for they were overthrown in the wilderness.
Notice in verse 6, now these things were our examples to the intent we should not lust
after evil things as they also lusted.
Neither be idolaters as were some of them.
As it is written, the people sat down to eat and drink and rose up to play.
Neither let us commit fornication as some of them committed and fell in one day three
and twenty thousand.
Neither let us tempt Christ as some of them also tempted and were destroyed of serpents.
Neither murmur he as some of them also murmured and were destroyed of the destroyer.
And I just want to pause here just for a moment because when we go through this list
we can start out and talk about the examples in verse number 6 and we can come to verse
7 and say, okay, good, I pass, I'm not, I'm not, I'm not guilty of idolatry, I'm not,
I don't have any idols.
Now be careful because an idol is anything that we put before God.
First John ends by saying, my little children, keep yourself from idols.
Not everything that was an idol for the children of Israel, when you think about these little
images and so on and so forth, and sometimes that's what comes to our mind when we think
of an idol, but an idol can be anything that's before God.
That in all things, according to Colossians 1, he, Christ, who is the head of the church,
must have the preeminence.
That's what the Bible teaches us.
And so we come to this one of idolatry and if we're not careful, we cannot understand
exactly what that is, we say, okay, I'm not guilty of idolatry.
We come to verse number 7 and 8 and we say, okay, I've not committed fornication, I've
not tempted Christ, but you come to verse number 10, neither murmur ye.
You know what murmuring is?
It's complaining.
If you somehow made it through verse 7, 8, and 9 and said, I'm not guilty of any of those,
you come to verse number 10, I'm pretty sure every single person is guilty of complaining.
I said this to someone this morning, I don't know how many of you when you talk to people
about their salvation, you should have an opportunity to share the gospel.
I often will say, as I said to this man yesterday, I said, listen, the Bible says that all have
sinned.
Do you acknowledge that you're a sinner?
And he didn't say this yesterday, but many times over the years, people have said something
like this to me, I've never murdered anybody.
And I'm like, man, that's good, I'm glad, amen?
And sometimes, as Christians, we almost take that same approach.
Well, I'm not really that bad, because I'm not like killing people, I'm not doing
X, Y, and Z, but the reality is that if you go back to the Old Testament and you read
about the situation with the fiery serpents, the Bible says that the people complained
and the Lord heard it, and He was displeased.
You know, when we complain, you know what, they complained about manna.
Did they not?
They loathed it, the Bible says.
They hated this manna, they despised it, but that was the provision of God.
Let me say it this way, that was the miraculous provision of God.
Sometimes we complain, and we must understand that our complaining displeases the Lord.
In everything give thanks, for this is the will of God and Christ Jesus concerning you.
Is that not what the Scriptures teach us?
In everything give thanks.
Now in verse number 11, it says, all these things happened unto them for in samples,
and they are written for our admonition upon whom the ends of the world are come.
Wherefore let him that thinketh, he standeth, take heed, lest he fall.
Verse 13, there hath no temptation taken you, but such as is common to man.
But God is faithful, who will not suffer you to be tempted above that you are able, but
will with the temptation also make a way to escape, that you may be able to bear it.
I'm thankful that our God is faithful, and I'm thankful that He provides a way to escape,
and we can look at the Scriptures, and we can look at examples, and we can find that
if you were to make a comparison between two Old Testament characters, one of Joseph
and one of David, that Joseph looked for that escape route, that Joseph looked to get away
from the temptation, that when Potiphar's wife, day by day, and finally came and kind
of cornered him, and had a, he, look, he left his coat, retained his character, his integrity.
He was lied about, he suffered, falsely accused, but before God, he was clean.
Amen?
Amen.
David, on the other hand, when he inquired about Bathsheba, he was told who she was,
a man's wife, but he said, bring her to me anyway.
God provided a way of escape, but God doesn't make us escape.
God will provide the way to escape.
He is faithful.
The Bible says it right here.
God is faithful.
God will provide the way to escape.
But you know what happens?
Sometimes our flesh desires more the activity than it does the fleeing.
Your flesh is strong.
Your flesh is powerful.
Your flesh has an appetite, a desire.
And we find that God is faithful.
We need to look for that escape route.
I think it was Pass the Pirate that put this song out years ago, put on your running shoes.
I mean, you just got to run.
He says, flee fornication.
Listen, there are some times you can find yourself in a position you just need to get
out.
Amen?
You just need to get out.
Notice with me in the book of Ephesians chapter 4.
Ephesians chapter 4, and this is really the statement that I made a moment ago where sometimes
Christians and we think about, well, I'm not really doing, and we have in our minds
this list of the really bad sins.
And we think, well, like if we were doing these things, then that would really be a
problem and my fellowship would be hindered and I would.
But I want you to understand that as we come to Ephesians chapter 4 that God's teaching
us about this putting off and putting on principle that we find here and also in the book of
Colossians.
And you begin reading in verse number 21, it says, if so be that you have heard him
and have been taught by him as the truth is in Jesus, that you put off concerning the
former conversation, the old man, which is corrupt according to the deceitful lust and
be renewed in the spirit of your mind and that you put on the new man, which after God
has created in righteousness and true holiness.
And so he gives this principle in verse 21 through 24 of putting off and putting on,
and then he's going to illustrate, he's going to give examples and application for what
this looks like.
And I want you to understand that within the next several verses, he does not say stop
killing people, but he does say stop lying, stop stealing, stop being angry, stop speaking.
Look at it with me.
Verse 25, wherefore putting away lying?
Speak every man truth with his neighbor if we are members one of another.
It's really sad to me how in our nation today, there's a large percentage of people that
are just, they've come to the place, they're just okay with understanding that people are
not honest.
They've just accepted it.
You can read studies and statistics where they've just simply accepted the fact that
people do not speak truth.
That's just sad to me.
How many of you have heard somebody say, maybe your parents said, or you said it to your
children, honesty is the best policy.
You ever hear somebody say that or you said those words?
We could take it a step further and say it's the only policy.
I've told our children as they're growing up, listen, tell me the truth.
You might get in trouble for telling me the truth, but you're going to get in more trouble
if you lie to me about it and then I find out.
Amen?
How many of you like being lied to?
Come on, anybody?
Oh, we don't like being lied to.
So he says, in order to speak the truth, stop lying.
That's the first thing that he talks about on the put off and put on.
That's the first thing.
Verse 26, be angry and sin not.
Let not the sun go down upon your wrath, neither give place to the devil.
Let him that stole steal no more, but rather let him labor, working with his hands the
thing which is good that he may have to give to him that needeth.
Let no corrupt communication proceed out of your mouth, but that which is good to the
use of edifying, that it may minister grace unto the hearers.
We could park there for a little while, but our speech, you know, we can do more damage
with our tongue than you could even imagine.
What does James say?
It's a little member that kindleth a great fire.
Out of the same mouth should not proceed blessing and cursing.
I mean, it ought not be.
And we find that here he's talking about the importance of our words, not only removing
certain things out of our vocabulary and certain things that we would not speak about, but
he says that we're to speak that which is good to the use of edifying, that it may minister
grace unto the hearers.
You can take out all the foul language and still speak ugly.
You can, but you ought not.
Minister grace.
Grieve not the Holy Spirit of God, whereby you're sealed on the day of redemption.
Let all bitterness and wrath and anger and clamor and evil speaking be put away.
Forgiveness from you with all malice, and be kind one to another, tenderhearted, forgiving
one another, even as God, for Christ's sake, hath forgiven you.
What a passage of Scripture that teaches about the sanctification of the believer, the putting
off and putting on, the importance of living a life that is pleasing in the sight of God.
As you continue into the fifth chapter, notice it says, be therefore followers of God as
dear children and walk in love as Christ also hath loved us and hath given himself for us
an offering and a sacrifice to God for a sweet-smelling savor.
But fornication and uncleanness or covetousness let it not be once named among you as becometh
saints, neither filthiness nor foolish talking nor jesting which are not convenient, but
rather giving a thanks.
Eventually you come to verse 10 and it says, proving what is acceptable unto the Lord.
God's serious about his people being holy.
We see it repeated from the Old Testament into the New Testament, be holy for I am holy.
He says in Peter, in all manner of conversation, in every area of our lives, there's not a
sacred part of us and a secular part of us if we're saved by the grace of God.
Everything is sacred.
It's to be holy.
Amen?
Psalm 19, if you will, we'll look at a couple of Old Testament passages and we'll wrap up
here in just a few moments.
But Psalm 19.
It's a familiar psalm that begins speaking about the heavens declaring the glory of God
and right in the middle there talking about the law of the Lord is perfect and I mean
what a great psalm.
We come to verses 12-14 as the psalm concludes and we find important truth for us pertaining
to the thought, the message this evening.
Verse 12, who can understand his errors, cleanse thou me from secret faults, keep back thy
servant also from presumptuous sins, let them not have dominion over me, then shall I be
upright and I shall be innocent from the great transgression.
Verse 12 talks about secret faults, verse 13 presumptuous sins and ends with the great
transgression.
It's interesting as you begin to look at verses 12 and 13 and you see how the Bible
says about these presumptuous sins, let them not have dominion over me.
Listen, sin will lead you into bondage, but here's the reality is that we, if we're saved
this evening, that we have been delivered from the bondage of sin.
I mean Romans chapter 6 clearly teaches that sin no longer has dominion over us, but when
we go back we become entangled again with what we had been delivered from.
Hebrews chapter 12 and verse number 1 talks about laying aside every weight and the sin
which doth so easily beset us and here in Psalm 19 it says that it would have dominion
over me.
Some have categorized verses 12 and 13 of sins of omission and sins of commission.
The reality is that there were examples in the law as you would study through the Levitical
law that there were sins of omission and sins of commission, things of not doing something
that they just didn't know they were supposed to do or they had been ignorant of something
or sins that they knew they were committing something that was contrary to the law and
to the teaching and the reality is that for us this evening that we come to this place
and we have the whole canon of Scripture and we understand that we're to live lives that
are holy, that are clean, that are pure, that we say God help me here as we look at this
text to cleanse me from secret faults, to keep me from presumptuous sins.
That pride, you know pride is destructive.
Pride is so destructive.
Secret faults, again many have mentioned that as being sins of omission but I want
you to consider with me this evening as we could seek to try to make some level of application
and take that phrase of secret faults and begin to apply it in a life today.
You know there are times in which people think, oh it's in secret, nobody knows about it.
But God does.
And you know what the secret sin does in the life of a believer?
It hinders their fellowship and robs them of their joy.
They might be able to hide it from every other believer that they know for a time, eventually
it will start being evident in their life like something's not right, can only play
the game for so long.
David thought he hid his sin, thought it was a secret.
God knew.
Achan thought he got away with it.
We're going to have another battle, we're going to get some spoil and I can bring those
things out and everyone's going to be fine.
But God knew.
Rachel thought she could take those idols, those images and hide them in the camel's
furniture in the tent and sit upon it.
But God all along knew all about it.
We can't hide anything from God.
Nothing can we hide from God.
Notice verse 14, let the words of my mouth and the meditation of my heart be acceptable
in thy sight, O Lord, my strength and my Redeemer.
See the reality is that God hears all of my words.
God knows all of my thoughts.
God hears all of your words and he knows all of your thoughts.
You read the Gospels and many times the people were not saying anything verbally that Jesus
could hear but he knew their thoughts.
Why reason ye amongst yourselves?
How does he know what we're thinking?
Because he knows everything about us.
And the psalmist says let the words of my mouth and the meditation of my heart be acceptable
in thy sight, O Lord, my strength and my Redeemer.
When I understand that he hears everything, he knows everything, it will have a great
impact on how I live my life.
Learning to live in the presence of God is what I call it.
That's what Joseph did.
You read in the book of Genesis in chapter 37 and you read and you understand the situation
that's unfolding, chapter 39, excuse me, and you read and you understand the situation
that's unfolding and you find there that Joseph, Mrs. Potiphar, she thought it was
the perfect opportunity but Joseph said how can I do this wickedness and sin against God?
He was in Egypt.
His dad wasn't there.
I don't think it would have mattered if his brothers were there but I think it would have
mattered if his dad was there, maybe from a human perspective.
But nobody was there humanly.
God was very present.
And so we learn to live in the presence of God.
Psalm 119 verses 9 through 11, a familiar passage, in fact I preached from this just
a few weeks ago in Psalm 119 and I'll just read it and we'll move on.
In verse 9 the Bible says, Wherewithal shall a young man cleanse his way?
By taking heed thereto according to thy word with my whole heart have I sought thee.
O let me not wander from thy commandments, thy word have I hid in mine heart that I might
not sin against thee.
I wonder this evening, what happens when we sin?
I mean how does it affect you?
Does it bother you?
Do you acknowledge that it hinders your fellowship and robs you of your joy?
Or we just kind of carry on through life and like, well everyone else is doing it.
I mean it's just kind of, it's not as bad as what some people are doing.
That's never been the litmus test.
That's never been the approach that God gives us in His Word.
I'm deeply concerned about my fellowship with my God because in His presence is fullness
of joy.
And I recognize as Dino Moody said that this book will keep you from sin or sin will keep
you from this book.
I've learned it to be the case.
The Bible says in Proverbs 28, I told you that we'd get to this verse of Scripture as
we conclude this evening.
I want you to read it with me tonight.
I want you to actually turn there and look at it.
In Proverbs 28, I have the entire verse underlined in my Bible.
Some of you mark your Bible, some of you don't and that's a personal decision.
The Bible says, he that covereth his sins, what does your Bible say, what are the next
three words?
Shall not prosper.
Now we like the word shall, don't we?
I mean in Romans 10, 13, for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved.
We like that, don't we?
Here it says, he that covereth his sins shall not prosper.
It's a truth of God's Word that is not going to be nullified or voided.
You say, I got away with it for a little while, you're not going to prosper, Bible truth,
you're not going to prosper, but I want you to see the verse continues and says, but whoso
confesseth and forsaketh them shall have mercy.
Which side of the equation would you rather be on?
I mean honestly tonight it's a simple question, I mean it's a no-brainer, right?
I mean as you look at the verse of Scripture, any individual would say, well obviously I
want to be the one that confesses and forsakes and I'm going to receive mercy.
I don't want to be in the side of the equation that I'm covering and not prospering, but
the reality is the human tendency is so frequent that we try to cover.
God knows about it.
You're not covering it from God.
You're not hiding it.
Hiding it from God.
Adam and Eve in the garden when they sinned.
They knew that they were naked.
They sowed those fig leaves and what did they do?
They tried to hide from God.
But you understand that God knew exactly where they were.
God knew exactly where they were.
The New Testament truth of 1 John 1
verse number nine, if we confess our sins,
he is faithful and just to forgive us
and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness.
Isn't that a wonderful promise of God's word?
And yet so often, God's people are guilty of covering
and hiding.
Thinking it's not really that bad.
It's not really that big of a deal.
I'm not doing x, y, and z.
Remember what Ephesians 4 dealt with.
Remember what we see about complaining.
God was not pleased.
I mean, surely God's not pleased with someone that murders,
but he's not pleased with someone that complains either.
And this evening, we must have this reset, if you will,
in our minds with regard to sin.
And we must come to the place this evening
as we look at this passage and let a man examine himself
and, Lord, search me and know me and show me
if there be any wicked way in me.
Lead me into the way everlasting.
And we'd come to that place where we say, listen,
there's no unconfessed sin in my life.
You're never going to reach a place of sinless perfection.
There were preachers of yesteryear that taught it.
I believe that it's wholly inaccurate
from what you read in God's word.
For God says in 1 John very plainly
that if we say that we have no sin,
that the truth is not in us, that we make him a liar.
But when we sin, we have an advocate with the Father,
Jesus Christ, the righteous.
And so we understand we're not going to ever become sinless.
But the reality is that we should be sinning less and less
as we walk closer and closer with God.
And we should have, and I'll use this term,
and I don't mean to use it inappropriately,
but we should have a short sin account with God.
What do I mean by that?
Well, the Holy Spirit, we should be walking
in such communion with God, abiding with him,
that when we sin, the Holy Spirit of God convicts us
and we immediately confess that and forsake that
and get that right and have that forgiveness
and have that restoration,
that restored fellowship and that joy.
See, this evening, this table that is before us
is a wonderful, wonderful table.
The Lord's Supper reminds us of what Jesus did for us
so that we could be saved.
It reminds us that Jesus is coming again.
It reminds us the importance of living holy lives.
Let a man examine himself.
For the invitation this evening,
it'll be the time of examination.
Oftentimes, I preach a different message on the evenings
of doing the Lord's Supper, and then we come
and look at this and we'll have a time of examination.
But for this evening, it'll be our invitation
that will serve as our time of examination.
And I wanna encourage you this evening
to let God have his way.
If there's someone confessing in your life,
he's done to Jesus, he's gracious and he's merciful,
he's promised to forgive.
He's a God who's ready to pardon, ready to forgive.
And I'm so grateful for that this evening.
And after we have our invitation,
we'll prepare for distribution of these elements
and observe the Lord's Supper this evening.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for your word, the truth that's contained therein.
And I pray that in these moments of invitation,
you'd help us, Lord, to do business with you.
Lord, I pray that you'd have your will and way.
Lord, thank you that you're a gracious God.
You're rich in mercy.
Thank you that you're ready to pardon and ready to forgive.
In these moments of invitation,
I pray that you'd have your will and way.
We'll thank you for it.
In Christ's name, we pray.