number four this evening
and i plan to preach this message last wednesday evening
uh... we were of course dealing with the power issue last wednesday night
and i'm not able to have services and we miss the opportunity to be here and
gathered together
uh... but uh... thankful uh... that power of course has been restored
and uh... the long time but there's some folks in some of the parts of the
country that have had no power for a lengthy period of time
and uh... we ought to pray for those folks but uh... this evening i want to
look at this
single verse of scripture in james chapter number four
and uh... before we get into the verse i want to remind you over the last several
weeks on sunday mornings
uh... we've been looking at that passage of scripture in colossians chapter
number three
now we've been dealing with colossians three really verses five through fourteen
this past sunday morning we looked at verses fifteen through seventeen
and dealt with our behavior in the church house but in verses five through
fourteen
we really spent three weeks examining that portion of scripture and it starts
out with the apostle paul saying to the people at colossi
mortify therefore your members which are upon the earth literally
crucify your flesh that was the title of the message that i preached in
after we go through that portion of scripture look at all of those verses we
find
that it's there in colossians three that the principle of putting off and putting
on
is given to us we find that the book of ephesians as well
but we see it laid out for us in colossians chapter number three
as we begin to focus upon that principle we understand the instruction that we've
been given
really to put off the old man with his fleshly deeds
you know your flesh has a desire
we understand as we
uh... live in this world that after salvation
uh... our flesh still has a desire and we must learn to crucify our flesh
we must learn to put off the old man the flesh with his deeds
uh... we referred to it as being the old man with his grave clothes
and we also understand that after we put off all these things that were to put on
all of these other things and as we begin to look at the put on
uh... principle and the truth there that were to put on the new man that we're to
walk in the spirit
i'm thankful for the promise that god has given us in galatians five that if
we walk in the spirit
you shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh
and what a blessing to know that with the power of god remember god's plan is
that we would be sanctified
that we would be conformed to the image of his dear son
and as we go through that process of sanctification it's the putting off of
the old the putting on of the new
and uh... what a blessing now as i think about those messages on sunday mornings
i am well aware of the fact that the enemy doesn't like that kind of
preaching
uh... the enemy don't like that kind of preaching why because he'd rather us
just go ahead and walk in the flesh and he'd rather us just go ahead and
uh... flounder around and waste a bunch of time and so on and so forth
he's not probably he don't really have a whole lot of problems with the
of the nominal type of believer
and uh... just going through the motions and so when you preach messages a series
such as this from colossians three
i find that the enemy doesn't like that kind of preaching and therefore i assume
that the enemy has
or the enemy soon will
increase his attack upon those who are desiring to be doers of the word
as soon as we decide that we're gonna start putting off all of these things
and putting on all these things and
that the holy spirit of god is working through the preaching of the word of god
and we determine that we're gonna walk in the spirit by the power of god not
in our own power not in our own
might but through god's power
uh... that we're going to to seek to be doers of the word and not hearers only you
can expect that the enemy will intensify
his attack
and therefore the message this evening i trust will be a message
that will be both practical and applicable
a message that will help us as we engage in spiritual warfare
uh... the title if you're taking notes this evening for this message is simply
this
battle plan
for victory
i'm thankful that the word of god tells us that we are more than conquerors
through christ i'm thankful
that paul testifies in stands in great
uh... just uh... victory when he says thanks be to god which giveth us the
victory
through our lord jesus christ uh... john says this in first john
greater is he that is in you than he that is in the world
we understand that
uh... the word of god teaches us that we can
uh... be overcomers we can be valiant we can be conquerors in fact
uh... in first john two you don't need to turn there stay in james but in first
john two in verse number fourteen
as john is addressing the young men in that verse halfway through the verse he
says
because you're strong
but he's not speaking about physical strength because he says in the word of
god abideth in you
and ye have overcome
the wicked one
oh what insight is given to us about being strong in the lord in the power of
his might
by that word of god abiding in us so the battle plan for victory
i believe is given to us here in james four
in verse number seven
it's a familiar verse of scripture
it's a simple verse of scripture
but i hope again this evening that the message will be both practical and
applicable
that god would help us
as we engage in spiritual warfare notice the bible says this in james four
in verse number seven
submit yourselves therefore to god
resist the devil
and he will flee
from you
you're taking notes number one the principle of submitting
the principle of submitting the bible says submit yourselves therefore
to god the word submit means to yield to obey to be subject to
the word submit is synonymous with the word surrender and we often will use
that word surrender
and speaking about in fact kimberly
uh... played on sunday morning for invitation i surrender all
and we understand the idea of this word submitting the bible says to us in james
excuse me in
uh... romans chapter number six the importance of whom we yield ourselves to
and we're to yield ourselves to god we are to submit to god
see the reality is that this battle plan for victory
begins not in my strength not in your strength but it begins in a submission
to the omnipotent god
we need to be strong in the power of his might
and we find here that this principle of submitting is key
we find it's the first step
uh... this evening you and i must recognize the lordship of the of the
lord jesus christ
really in every area of our lives
and then submit completely
just come to that place of submission you know it's interesting to me
uh... that this idea of submission really for the child of god
uh... at times seems to be a challenge it seems to be difficult for us to
really submit and surrender
to come to that place of yielding
uh... oftentimes in our own lives we seek to
to engage in warfare in our own power in our own might
but remember we're told in ephesians that we wrestle not against flesh and
blood
thus we are to be strong enough in the power of god
uh... and to to go in his power it begins with the submission
i believe this evening that as we find the first reference here
uh... this this first aspect of this battle plan submit yourselves therefore
to god
that submission
think about this submission
is an indication of humility
submission is an indication it really reveals
our humility
which according to verse number six
leads to god's grace
god's grace in this particular context is dealing with his enablement
uh... i'm thankful for god's saving grace but i'm also thankful for his
enabling
and we find that the bible says in verse number six
but he speaking of god giveth more grace wherefore he saith
god resisteth the proud
but giveth grace unto the humble submit yourselves therefore to god that act of
submission
reveals it's an indicator of our humility
and it's going to lead to god's grace his enablement
it's so critical it's so essential that we have the grace of god
uh... as we think about this battle plan for victory we need his enabling
we need his power we need his might
we need to be strong in the lord and we find that it begins
with submission
begins with submission
i can't tell you how many times i've heard somebody misquote james four seven
and here's how they misquote it
resist the devil and he will flee
not what it says
you can try to resist as much as you want in your own power
but you're no match for satan
but when you submit to god
and then you resist the devil
he will flee why
because satan's no match for you
when you're walking in the power of god
and we must be careful to understand the importance of submission this evening
it's the first step for victory
uh... this battle plan for victory we see not only the principle of submitting
notice number two
the process of resisting
uh... the bible says
therefore submit yourselves therefore to god then notice it just says resist the
devil
the word resist means to withstand it means to oppose
and i think about this idea of resist and as we look here in this particular
text of scripture
we say okay this is great i'm supposed to resist
We're supposed to resist the devil,
but my mind says how?
How do we resist them?
What do we do?
How is it that we are able to resist
the enemy Satan as he would come
and bring engaging in this spiritual warfare?
Well, I believe first of all,
we must put on the armor of God daily.
It is absolutely imperative
that we put on the armor of God.
Turn over to the book of Ephesians if you will.
I'm going to change your place here
and James will be back in just a few moments,
but I want you to notice in Ephesians 6
how that God gives us this truth
with regard to the armor of God.
Listen, it is absolutely imperative.
It would be foolish for someone
that is a soldier in an army
in a military campaign,
it would be foolish for them
to enter the battlefield without their armor.
Would it not?
There are certain elements that you would put on.
There are certain pieces of equipment
that you would be sure to put on
before you would go out and engage in battle.
Why? Because otherwise,
you'd be vulnerable to the enemy.
I saw a report just the other day
about an individual that was testifying
of just almost losing his life
by a sniper bullet,
but if it were not for his helmet,
he would have passed into eternity
in just a moment.
But that helmet,
I bet you that guy was happy
that he put on his armor.
Amen?
And so listen, in a spiritual sense,
we're engaged in battle.
If we were walking outside
and there's people shooting guns at us,
we're going to take some precaution.
We're going to do certain things, right?
We're going to make sure that we're going
with the armor that we can have.
Well, spiritually speaking,
you know that the enemy is firing his fiery darts.
We're engaged in spiritual warfare,
so how is it that I'm going to resist the devil?
Number one, I put on the armor of God.
Notice in Ephesians 6,
beginning in v. 10,
the Bible says,
finally, my brethren,
be strong in the Lord
and in the power of His might.
Put on, notice what it says,
the whole armor of God.
We don't select which pieces we think
are important for that particular day.
We don't go through and say,
you know what, that one,
I don't need that one,
but I think this one's important.
No, he says put on the whole armor of God.
Then notice he says this,
that ye may be able to stand
against the wiles of the devil.
Now I told you that the word resist
there in James 4,
in v. 7 means to withstand or to oppose.
We see here in v. 11,
the reference to that you may be able to stand
against the wiles of the devil.
Notice as we continue going through,
you'll make note of the word withstand.
In v. 12, the Bible says,
for we wrestle not against flesh and blood,
but against principalities,
against powers,
against the rulers of the darkness of this world,
against spiritual wickedness in high places.
Wherefore, notice he's going to give this instruction again.
It's so imperative that we put on the whole armor of God
that he references it again in v. 13.
Wherefore, take unto you, again note,
the whole armor of God,
that ye may be able to what?
Withstand in the evil day.
And having done all to stand.
Stand therefore,
having your loins girt about with truth,
having on the breastplate of righteousness,
your feet shod with the preparation of the gospel of peace,
above all, taking the shield of faith,
wherewith ye shall be able to quench,
notice, all the fiery darts of the wicked.
And take the helmet of salvation
and the sword of the Spirit,
which is the Word of God,
praying always with all prayer and supplication
in the Spirit,
and watching thereunto with all perseverance
and supplication for all saints.
I notice as we look at this list
that is provided to us with the armor of God,
it is imperative for us as the people of God,
if we want to resist the devil,
we understand the first step is that
that principle of submitting.
And I say, I am yielded.
I am submitting.
I am surrendering to God.
I'm not seeking to walk in my own power
by the pride that I might have.
No, I'm going to humble myself
and I'm going to submit myself
to the Lordship of Christ,
and I'm going to then resist the devil,
but I must follow the principle
of what it means to resist.
And the process, I believe,
begins with putting on the armor.
Right in the middle of all of this that is mentioned,
we find that, really, it's not in the middle,
it's towards the end that he talks about
the sword of the Spirit,
which is the Word of God.
I would say the second aspect of this process
that we would deal with for resisting
is that we must know this book.
We must know the Word of God.
It is absolutely essential for us
to know the Scriptures.
If there's a particular area in your life
in which you know that the enemy
seeks to attack on a regular basis,
maybe there's a particular weakness in your life,
I would counsel you to go find a bucket load of verses
that deal with that particular subject,
that topic, and just memorize them.
Commit them to memory.
Put them on index cards,
and put them in the dashboard of your vehicle,
on the mirror in your bathroom.
Put them all over the place.
Why?
Because you need to know the Word of God.
Because it's the only way,
that's the only offensive weapon that we have
when we put on this armor of God.
But then he says,
and take the sword of the Spirit,
which is the Word of God.
We understand that it's very unusual today
that we would fight with swords,
but at the time of this writing,
that was a very common practice
in how they would enter into battle.
It was absolutely necessary for a soldier
to be skillful with his sword.
Otherwise, it could end in defeat.
It could end in death.
And so in like manner,
as the people of God,
we must be skillful when it comes to the Word of God.
We must know how to combat the temptations that come
when the devil is seeking to tempt us.
We must know some verses of Scripture
that deal specifically with that temptation.
I'm thankful for the testimony of Joseph
when Potiphar's wife sought to,
on day-by-day basis,
sought to get him to commit sin
and commit just an awful, awful practice
of lying with her,
that he said,
how then shall I do this great wickedness
and sin against God?
He understood that it was a sin before God Almighty.
And this evening,
as we would understand the importance,
the process of resisting,
it's not just something that we say,
okay, I'm resisting.
What does that mean?
No, I'm actively resisting.
I'm putting on daily the whole armor of God.
I'm daily seeking to know this book
so that I can have an understanding of the Word of God
so that I can use skillfully the sword of the Spirit.
We find that back in James 4,
in verse 7,
there's the principle of submitting.
There's the process of resisting.
There's a promise to claim.
I love the last words of James 4,
in verse 7.
Because the Bible says this,
and he will flee from you.
Isn't that wonderful?
That's a promise.
Listen, God didn't say
all Scripture is given by inspiration of God, right?
God didn't say he might flee from you.
No, no, God's given us here
in this single verse of Scripture,
a battle plan for victory,
that when the devil seeks to tempt us,
when the devil seeks to come in and devour us,
he desires to do so.
Remember, Peter says that in 1 Peter 5,
when he likens the enemy to a lion
who walketh about seeking whom he may devour.
Again, in that text of Scripture,
in verse number 9 of 1 Peter chapter number 5,
notice what Peter says,
whom resists steadfast in the faith.
And again, we see that word resist, right?
So we understand this evening
that as we look at this battle plan for victory,
that God says, listen, it starts with submitting.
It starts with a submission.
And as you submit, you're revealing your humility
and it leads to the grace of God, His enabling.
And then you resist the devil.
You put on the whole armor of God.
You know the Word of God.
You're able to use that sword of the Spirit skillfully.
And then you have a promise to claim
he will flee from you.
That's wonderful.
He will flee from you.
I want you to think this evening,
as we look at this battle plan for victory,
and I want you to consider with me
how this battle plan was implemented perfectly
in the life of the Lord Jesus Christ.
Take your Bibles and turn to the book of Luke,
if you will, in the fourth chapter.
In Luke chapter number 4,
God gives us a record of the temptation
of the Lord Jesus Christ in the wilderness.
And in these 13 verses of Luke chapter number 4,
verses 1 through 13,
I believe that it provides us
with a perfect implementation
by the Lord Jesus Christ of this battle plan
that we're speaking of this evening.
Notice with me as we started in James 4,
and we said that number one
was a principle of submitting.
Submit yourselves therefore to God.
Notice in Luke 4 in verse number 1,
the Bible says,
and Jesus, notice this,
being full of the Holy Ghost,
returned from Jordan,
and then, notice this,
was led by the Spirit into the wilderness.
He was led of the Spirit into the wilderness.
He did not go into the wilderness on His own accord.
Now, we understand that He is God,
but you understand that what Paul tells us
in the book of Philippians
is that the Lord Jesus Christ humbled Himself.
Remember that He took on Himself no reputation.
He took upon Himself the form of a servant.
He was made in the likeness of man.
He humbled Himself, became obedient unto death,
even the death of the cross.
And we see here that often the Lord Jesus Christ
would speak about always doing the will of the Father.
And here in this verse of Scripture,
in Luke 4 and verse number 1,
it tells us two important things
about the Lord Jesus Christ.
Again, we know that He's God,
but you understand that He's left us an example
that we should follow His steps.
And number one tells us
that He was full of the Holy Ghost.
And number two tells us
that He was led by the Spirit.
I believe that that reveals to us
a level of submission
on the part of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And I know there are some that would say,
how could He submit? He's God.
He is God.
It will make your head hurt
as you try to think about all of those things,
because the reality is that
as He humbled Himself and took upon Himself
the form of a servant,
the likeness of man,
there were certain things that He gave up.
He never gave up His deity in its entirety,
but we understand that He submitted to the will of God.
Remember, as He prayed in the garden,
nevertheless, not my will,
but thine will, right?
And so we find here that there's this first principle
that we see from James 4,
this first aspect of this battle plan.
The second aspect of this battle plan
that we mentioned in James 4
was the process of resisting.
And I talked about putting on the whole armor of God.
I talked about knowing the Word of God.
Notice, we won't take time to read the entirety
of the passage,
but I want you to note three verses of Scripture
in particular.
And notice in verse 4
that Jesus answered Him, the enemy,
the devil, Satan,
and said this,
It is written
that man shall not live by bread alone,
but by every word of God.
He's referencing a verse from the book of Deuteronomy.
He's using the Word of God
specifically with regard to the temptation
there in verse number 3.
The temptation was to command this stone
that it be made bread.
The Bible tells us that after those 40 days
that He was and hungered in verse number 2
because He did eat nothing.
And so Satan comes at that particular time
in that particular moment.
He says, hey, command that this stone be made bread.
Now could Jesus have done that?
Sure He could have done that.
But He said it is written,
man shall not live by bread alone,
but by every word of God.
He's resisting.
We find that in verse number 8
the Bible says this,
And Jesus answered and said unto him,
Get thee behind Me, Satan,
for it is written,
Thou shalt worship the Lord thy God,
and Him only shalt thou serve.
Again, He's referencing Old Testament
from the book of Deuteronomy.
He's using the Word of God.
And He's using it skillfully.
Why? Notice the temptation in verse number 7.
If thou therefore wilt worship Me,
all shall be thine.
If thou wilt worship Me.
And Jesus says it is written,
Thou shalt worship the Lord thy God,
and Him only shalt thou serve.
I'm thankful that obviously
the example that is given to us
is an example of using the Word of God skillfully.
The verse that is quoted
is directly relevant to the temptation
that is given.
It's not just some,
you know, Jesus wept.
I memorized John 11.35.
That's not going to help you
when the temptation comes.
I'm not suggesting that there aren't verses
that you ought to memorize,
that you memorize skillfully.
Notice, number 3,
in this process of resisting,
in verse number 12,
Jesus answering said unto him,
It is said.
He doesn't say it is written.
He says it is said.
It's the same idea.
Thou shalt not tempt the Lord thy God.
Another reference from the book of Deuteronomy.
And so as we look at this battle plan
for victory that we find in James 4
and verse number 7
that we're seeking to make very practical
and applicable in our lives this evening,
and we look at that battle plan
and we break it up into these particular areas,
and then we look at the life of the Lord Jesus Christ.
He's our example.
He's the perfect example.
And we find this resisting
that is taking place in verses 2-12
where He's using the Word of God skillfully.
It is written.
It is said.
When the enemy comes to you
and he begins to tempt you,
if you pull out some verses of Scripture,
what was the promise?
He will flee from you.
What happened in Luke 4?
We'll read verse number 13.
Remember we said it was a promise to claim?
Well, here in verse number 13,
the Bible says this,
And when the devil had ended all the temptation,
notice these words,
he departed from him.
I understand it says for a season.
And that also gives us insight
that we'll mention in just a moment.
But I want you to rejoice in that truth
where it says he departed from him.
Because the promise to claim in James 4-7,
Submit yourselves therefore to God,
resist the devil,
and he will flee from you.
You know that Satan, the devil,
he don't like messing with Christians
that are walking in the power of God
that know the Word of God.
He just doesn't.
He'd like to go have an easier opponent.
Someone that's walking in the flesh.
Someone that's carnal.
Someone that doesn't know the Word of God.
Much easier for him to have victory.
And so, when we take this model
that's been given to us
and we incorporate it,
we implement it in our lives,
we take the practical aspect
and apply the truth,
and we say daily,
I'm going to submit myself to God.
I understand his lordship
in every area of my life.
And I'm going to submit to his authority.
I'm going to follow his direction.
And as I do that,
I'm also going to resist the devil.
I'm going to put on the whole armor of God.
I'm not going to leave off certain pieces.
I'm not going to go out
and make myself vulnerable.
I'm going to put on all,
the whole armor of God.
I'm going to memorize the Word of God.
Wherewithal shall a young man cleanse his way?
By taking heed thereto according to thy word.
Thy word have I hid in mine heart
that I might not sin against thee.
Psalm 119 verses 9 and 11.
And we take this practical aspect
and we are resisting the enemy
and then we can claim the promise
that he will flee from you.
It's a wonderful truth of the Word of God.
At the end of verse number 13,
the Bible says,
for a season.
You understand this evening
that though you may have submitted to God today,
and though you may have resisted the devil today,
and though he may have fled from you today,
he may come back tomorrow.
Amen?
That's why it's a daily exercise.
This battle plan for victory
that we are daily engaged
in this spiritual warfare
and daily I have to submit
and daily I have to resist
and daily if I do those things,
he'll flee from me.
I don't know how long a season is
in my life, in your life.
But I know that the Bible says
that he departed from Him.
And that's precious.
We see the battle plan for victory
given to us in James 4
in verse number 7,
but we find here in Luke chapter number 4
how the Lord Jesus Christ
implemented perfectly
this plan that we've dealt with this evening.
I know that God would help us
as His people.
Listen, the Word of God is relevant.
The Word of God is practical.
We are to be doers of the Word.
And as we understand that we have an enemy
and we're engaged in this spiritual warfare,
I am rejoicing this evening
that God gives us a blueprint,
a battle plan for victory.
It's not something that's just kind of,
well, I think somehow if everything falls right,
you can have victory in your life.
No, no, no.
He's given us a process to follow.
I asked this question in recent days
to an individual.
How is it that we can make a decision
that would endure?
In other words, not to engage
in some type of sinful behavior.
A decision as the three Hebrew children
did in Daniel 3, not to bow.
How can we make a decision such as that
not to bow, not to sin?
It's when that decision is made
on the truth of the Word of God.
It is written.
See, God's Word doesn't change.
Aren't you thankful for that?
Can you imagine if God's Word changed?
Man, it'd be crazy.
But God's Word doesn't change.
It's a constant.
The society changes.
The culture changes.
What they say is right,
what they say is wrong changes.
But God's Word doesn't change.
word is steady, it's a constant. And as we hide the Word of God in our hearts and we
stand upon the principles of God's Word, God will enable us to have victory. Submit, resist,
and then claim that victory. The promise, He will flee from you. Let's pray. Father,
we love You. How we thank You for Your Word. And I pray this evening that You'd take this
simple message and help each one of us to apply it in our lives. We thank You for giving
us the truth, providing for us this blueprint or this battle plan for victory. We thank
You for the example of our Savior, as it's recorded in Luke 4. God, I pray that as we
engage in spiritual warfare, You'd help us to submit, help us to resist, and then help
us to rejoice as we see our enemy flee. Help us not to get prideful, help us not to get
overconfident, help us to continue daily submitting, lest we enter into that next conflict in the
power of our own flesh and fail miserably. Thank You for the opportunity to pray as a
church family. We pray that You'd bless our time, and we'll thank You for it. In Christ's
name we pray, amen. Anyone need a prayer?