this evening, Jeremiah chapter number 38. And really, as we look at this passage of
Scripture this evening, I'll be looking at portions of Jeremiah 37, 38, 39, and 40.
And so hold your fingers there in that section of Scripture, and we'll be kind of bouncing
back and forth. And as we look at this particular text, I'm trusting that the Lord will enable
us tonight to be encouraged from that which we read of with regard to the life of Jeremiah.
As we have now completed almost 10 months in 2020, we know that there have been many
that have made commentary with regard to 2020. And as we think about the days in which we're
living, many have expressed this thought, is that we are living in uncertain times.
However, as we would think about the fact that we're living in 2020 and that our God
is omniscient and He's eternal, though from man's perspective we may face some level of
uncertainty, the reality is that God knows all about it. God is never surprised by anything
that happens. He knows the end from the beginning. And so as we begin to think about that truth
and we think about the way in which people have used various verbiage to describe 2020,
and no doubt it's been varied at times, it's been quite accurate from man's perspective.
And I'm thankful that it's not only our perspective that matters. I'm thankful that we can understand
that God is still sitting upon His throne and that God is still in control. And though
from my vantage point, though from your vantage point, speaking from a human perspective,
we may look at things and say, what is going on? The uncertainty of the times and so on
and so forth. But we must rest in the fact that God is aware. As we look at the life
of Jeremiah in these particular chapters that we'll look at this evening, we really understand
that there were some things that were certain, just as there are some things that are certain
for us this evening. We understand that God has given us some certainties with regard
to end times prophecy. We understand that as we would consider some of the truth that
God has given us in His Word with regard to end times in the last days and understanding
that we're living in those last days, there are some things that we should expect to happen
in these last days. And Jeremiah was a man that was, of course, serving God on the eve
of the Babylonian captivity. Historically speaking, we understand that as he is there
and as he's preaching and giving the prophecies that have been given to him by the Lord God
Almighty, that Jeremiah is in a place where he is actually seeing the very things that
he's preached unfold. He's seeing the fulfillment of the very prophecies that he's proclaimed.
As we begin to think about the events that are surrounding the Babylonian captivity and
conquest of Jerusalem and the life of Jeremiah, I've asked you to turn to Jeremiah 38, and
I want you to be there, but I want to remind you even before we jump into the portion of
Scripture that we'll look at this evening, I want to remind you of a great promise that
God gave to Jeremiah in Jeremiah chapter number one. In Jeremiah chapter number one in verse
number eight, God said to Jeremiah, be not afraid of their faces, for I am with thee
to deliver thee, saith the Lord. We have, as we have looked at Scripture and considered
these similar words that we read in Jeremiah 1.8, we read how that God promised to be with
Moses, he promised to be with Joshua, he promised to be with Jeremiah as we've just read, and
we understand that he is with us. We understand that Hebrews 13 tells us and we can rejoice
in the truth that he had said, I will never leave thee nor forsake thee, that Jesus said,
I am with you always, and for that we could rejoice. But as we think about that promise
and we think about the life and ministry of Jeremiah, we find that he was called of the
Lord and we find that he was faithful. Notice in Jeremiah 38 in verse number 28, it's where
I'll get the title for the message this evening, and then we'll go through a host of Scriptures
in these four chapters and trust to be a blessing to you this evening. In Jeremiah 38 in verse
number 28, the Bible says, so Jeremiah abode in the court of the prison until the day that
Jerusalem was taken. And he was there when Jerusalem was taken. I've said already by
way of introduction that Jeremiah witnessed what he had faithfully prophesied. If you're
taking notes this evening, I've simply entitled the message this evening, Jerusalem was taken.
Jerusalem was taken. We can see that from a historical perspective. We see the Bible
record that God gives us in His Word with regard to the captivity. And we find that
Jeremiah is called to minister and called to serve the Lord in really some difficult
days. As we would think about the life and ministry of Jeremiah, we would find that Jeremiah
had the privilege of prophesying and ministering during the times of really some kings, Josiah
in particular, where there was revival under the time of Jeremiah's ministry in the reign
of Josiah. And we'd find that when Josiah died, that Jeremiah, with a whole host of
those within Judah, they wept at the death of Josiah. Jeremiah, however, also prophesied
and ministered during the time in which many in those that he was preaching to, they forsook
the commandment of the Lord. They did not hearken to the Word of God. We find that Jeremiah
is prophesying in such a day and he's ministering in such a day. If we're to take notes this
evening, first I would like you to take note of the coming judgment. It helps me to understand
the times in which Jeremiah is ministering, is prophesying, to understand and to take
note of the coming judgment. I'll just look at some verses here in the text in which we're
looking at this evening, but look in chapter 37 if you will. In verse number 6 of Jeremiah
37, the Bible says this, then came the word of the Lord unto the prophet Jeremiah saying,
thus saith the Lord, the God of Israel, thus shall ye say to the king of Judah. Now, pause
with me just for a moment at that phrase in verse number 7, for we find that the king
of Judah at this particular time is Zedekiah. And we see that in verse number 1 of Jeremiah
37, and king Zedekiah, the son of Josiah reigned. And it tells us in verse number 2, but neither
he nor his servants nor the people of the land did hearken unto the words of the Lord
which he spake by the prophet Jeremiah. And so we find that from the king to the servants
to the people, they did not hearken unto the words of the Lord which he spake by the prophet
Jeremiah. And so Jeremiah 37 tells us that they're not listening, they're not hearkening,
but yet we find that in verse number 3, they come to Jeremiah and they say, pray now unto
the Lord our God for us. And the word of the Lord comes unto Jeremiah, as we mentioned
in verse number 6, and God tells Jeremiah, thus shall you say to the king of Judah. Now
this is the same king that has not hearkened. This is the same king that's not following
that which God has already revealed through his prophet and through the message. And it
says, thus shall you say to the king of Judah that sent you unto me to inquire of me. Behold,
Pharaoh's army, which has come forth to help you, shall return to Egypt into their own
land. And the Chaldeans shall come again and fight against this city and take it and burn
it with fire. Thus saith the Lord, deceive not yourselves, saying, the Chaldeans shall
surely depart from us, for they shall not depart. For though ye had smitten the whole
army of the Chaldeans that fight against you, and there remained but wounded men among them,
yet should they rise up every man in his tent and burn this city with fire. Now can
I tell you this evening, this isn't a pleasant message to have to deliver. Jeremiah is given
this instruction, he's given the word of the Lord, and as he goes back to Zedekiah and
those that had asked him to inquire, to go unto the Lord our God for us, that God does
not change the message. In fact, if you were to look back through the book of Jeremiah,
you would find that Jeremiah had faithfully proclaimed the same message. It was a message
of coming judgment. We find that in these verses of Scripture, they had this idea because
the Pharaoh's army, according to verse number 5, came forth out of Egypt, and the Chaldeans
that had besieged Jerusalem heard tidings of them, and they departed from Jerusalem.
So there's some folks that are thinking, okay, now the Chaldeans have left because
the Egyptians have come, and that's kind of our ticket out, if you will. That's our
deliverance. And Jeremiah, as he's speaking the word of the Lord unto these in Judah,
he says, listen, I want you to understand that this army, the army of the Egyptians,
they're going to return into Egypt. They're not going to help you. Furthermore, the Chaldeans,
they're going to come back.
and even if you had smitten the entire army
and they were all wounded men,
they would still conquer and burn this city.
That's not a very exciting message, right?
But we find that it's a message of coming judgment.
We find that in v. 17 of the same text of Scripture,
the Bible says,
then Zedekiah the king sent and took him out
and the king asked him secretly.
It's always of interest to me
when I read those words
where we find that this man Zedekiah the king
had already heard the word of the Lord from Jeremiah
on a number of occasions.
He says to Jeremiah in secrecy,
he says, is there any word from the Lord?
Yeah, the same word I've been giving you.
Coming judgment.
Notice at the end of v. 17,
Jeremiah said there is.
For said he, thou shalt be delivered
into the hand of the king of Babylon.
We find that as we look at the portion of Scripture
that is before us and we see that which would unfold,
you notice that it continues in chapter 38 in v. 1,
Then Shephatiah the son of Matan,
and Gedaliah the son of Pasher,
and Jucal the son of Shalamiah,
and Pasher the son of Malchiah
heard the words that Jeremiah had spoken
unto all the people.
Now they didn't like the words.
And we'll get to that in our next point.
But the Bible says this,
here are the words saying,
Thus saith the Lord,
this is the prophecy of Jeremiah
taking note of the coming judgment.
It says this,
He that remaineth in this city
shall die by the sword,
by the famine, and by the pestilence.
But he that goeth forth to the Chaldeans
shall live, for he shall have his life
for a prey and shall live.
Thus saith the Lord,
this city shall surely be given
into the hand of the king of Babylon's army,
which shall take it.
As we take note of coming judgment,
we see that judgment is announced by Jeremiah.
And then we read how that judgment
is actually experienced.
The Bible tells us as we've used
for our text verse this evening
in verse 28 of chapter 38,
that Jeremiah abode in the court of the prison
until the day that Jerusalem was taken.
And he was there when Jerusalem was taken.
Notice as we enter into the 39th chapter,
the Bible says in the ninth year
of Zedekiah king of Judah,
in the tenth month came Nebuchadnezzar
king of Babylon.
And all his army against Jerusalem
and they besieged it.
In the eleventh year of Zedekiah
in the fourth month,
the ninth day of the month,
the city was broken up.
The Bible tells us as you continue to look here
in verse number five,
it says that the Chaldeans army
pursued after them and overtook Zedekiah
in the plains of Jericho.
For we find that in verse number four,
the Bible says that Zedekiah
the king of Judah saw them
and all the men of war and they fled.
That was not following the direction
in which Jeremiah had given them.
And we find that the Bible tells us
that they overtook them
according to verse number five.
And notice what happens.
It says this at the end of verse number five
that they had them there in the land of Hamath
where he gave judgment upon him.
Notice verse six.
Then the king of Babylon slew
the sons of Zedekiah in Riblah
before his eyes.
Also, the king of Babylon
slew all the nobles of Judah.
Moreover, he put out Zedekiah's eyes
and bound him with chains
to carry him to Babylon.
The last thing that Zedekiah ever saw
with his physical vision
was the death of his sons
and of these nobles.
The Bible tells us in verse number eight
that the Chaldeans burned the king's house
and the houses of the people
with fire and break down the walls of Jerusalem.
So we begin to see here this evening
as we look at this portion of Scripture,
we note the coming judgment.
And we understand historically
the prophecy with regard to the judgment
and the judgment that was poured out.
And we read that and we see that.
I want you to take note though, however,
not only of the coming judgment,
but I want you to take note of the circumstances
in which Jeremiah faced.
So Jeremiah is a faithful servant of the Lord.
Jeremiah is faithfully proclaiming
the Word of the Lord.
When God spoke to Jeremiah
and said speak this message,
give this message,
deliver these words to My people,
Jeremiah faithfully did so.
He was obedient to the commandment of the Lord.
And we find that as we begin to look
at the circumstances in which he faced,
that he dealt with some difficult circumstances.
We find that back in chapter number 37,
according to verse number four,
the Bible says that Jeremiah came in
and went out among the people,
for they had not put him into prison.
And so we find that at that particular point,
we begin to follow the course of Jeremiah
in these few chapters of Scripture
and these events that are provided to us
that he's not yet in prison.
That soon would change as we're aware of.
In verse number 15,
the Bible says after Jeremiah
had delivered this message of judgment,
it says,
wherefore the princes were wroth with Jeremiah.
They didn't like his judgment.
They didn't like the Word of the Lord.
They didn't like the message
that was being proclaimed.
And the Bible says that they smote him
and put him in prison
in the house of Jonathan the scribe,
for they had made that the prison.
So we find in chapter 37 and verse number 15
that he's now in prison.
According to chapter number 38,
after once again,
we mentioned how in verse number one,
these folks, they heard the words
that Jeremiah had spoken.
And it says in verse number four of Jeremiah 38,
therefore, the princes said unto the king,
as he beseeched thee,
let this man be put to death.
For thus he weakened the hands of the men of war
that remain in this city
in the hands of all the people,
and speaking such words unto them.
For this man seeketh not the welfare of this people,
but the hurt.
Verse number five tells us that Zedekiah the king
gave them permission.
It says this, that he said,
behold, he is in your hand.
For the king is not he that can do anything against you.
Verse six, then took they Jeremiah
and cast him into the dungeon of Melchizedek,
the son of Hamelak,
that was in the court of the prison.
And they let down Jeremiah with cords.
And in the dungeon there was no water but mire,
so Jeremiah sunk in the mire.
No longer is Jeremiah in prison now.
He's cast into the dungeon
in verse number six of chapter 38.
We find that there's some deliverance
and we'll look at that in our final point this evening.
And we skip down to verse number 13 of Jeremiah 38.
We find that they drew Jeremiah with cords
and took him up out of the dungeon.
Then it tells us that Jeremiah remained
in the court of the prison.
So he's in prison. He goes in the dungeon.
Now he's back in prison.
We've read as our text verse,
verse number 28,
that he's there in prison until Jerusalem is taken.
As we begin to think about the circumstances
in which Jeremiah was facing
and we take note of those circumstances,
and we see the description of what God gives us
with regard to those circumstances,
we understand that they were dire circumstances.
Notice with me the phrases of Scripture
that reveal to us the severity of that
which Jeremiah is dealing with
in chapter 37 and verse number 20.
The Bible says Jeremiah is speaking to Zedekiah.
This is when Zedekiah had come to him secretly.
And he's speaking there and it says,
Therefore, hear now, I pray thee,
O my Lord the King,
let my supplication, I pray thee,
be accepted before thee,
that thou cause me not to return
to the house of Jonathan the scribe.
That, remember, according to verse number 15,
that's where the prison was.
It says that they put him in prison
in the house of Jonathan the scribe
for they had made that the prison.
And so Jeremiah says to Zedekiah
that thou cause me not to return
to the house of Jonathan the scribe.
Notice the last phrase of verse number 20.
Lest I die there.
This is a very serious situation
in which Jeremiah is facing.
We find that he recognizes the potential
of him dying in that prison.
In chapter number 38, we've already mentioned
that in verse number 4,
the adversaries had the desire
to have Jeremiah put to death
because of the message that he proclaimed.
In verse number 10 of Jeremiah 38,
Ebed-Melech is used of the Lord.
He's an Ethiopian man.
And we'll deal with him a little bit
in our final point this evening.
We find that the Bible tells us
in verse number 10 of Jeremiah 38,
then the king commanded Ebed-Melech
the Ethiopian saying,
take from hence 30 men with thee
to take up Jeremiah the prophet
out of the dungeon.
What's it say?
Before he die.
Dire circumstances.
Great difficulty in which Jeremiah is facing.
We find that after Jeremiah
is delivered from the dungeon
and sent back to the court of the prison,
according to verse number 13,
he's now back in the prison
that in verse number 16,
the Bible says,
so Zedekiah the king swears secretly
unto Jeremiah saying,
as the Lord liveth that made us this soul,
I will not put thee to death,
neither will I give thee into the hand
of these men that seek thy life.
Or people that were seeking the life of Jeremiah.
Why did they want him dead?
They didn't like his message.
They didn't like the message of coming judgment.
They didn't like the message
that they were going to face
the judgment of God.
By the way,
the enemy understood,
and we'll make note of this again
in just a few moments,
but in verse number 3 of chapter number 40,
the Bible says,
now the Lord hath brought it and done
according as He had said,
because ye have sinned against the Lord
and have not obeyed His voice,
therefore this thing is come upon you.
So the portion of Jeremiah that we're dealing with...
We started in chapter 37
with identifying the fact
that they did not hearken
unto the words of the Lord.
They did not want to hear
what the prophet had to say.
the message of God.
And even as Zedekiah would go secretly
and inquire and say,
is there a word from the Lord?
Is there any word from the Lord
that Jeremiah says it's the same
that it has been?
You've not been obeying.
You've not been following.
You've not been listening.
And judgment is coming,
and we find that Jeremiah
in the midst of obeying the Lord,
in the midst of proclaiming the truth,
that he faces some very difficult circumstances.
But I submit to you this evening
that as Jeremiah would find himself
in these days of difficulty,
that as he'd find himself
dealing with many adversaries,
that God was well aware of where he was.
And not only was God aware
of where Jeremiah was,
but God was able to take care of his man.
This evening, as I begin to think about
many things that have been said
with regard to not only the circumstances
in which we're facing,
but even the uncertainty of the days
that lie ahead of us,
I take great comfort in knowing
that our God is in control.
that our God is able to take care
of His children.
He's the Lord God Omnipotent.
And He's able.
Does it mean that everything's going to be
just as easy as it's always been?
No, probably not.
Jeremiah dealt with some adversity.
I don't want to go to prison
like Jeremiah's in prison,
but the reality is that
listen, there are brothers and sisters in Christ
around the globe that are in prison
because of preaching the Word of God.
And there have been many that have gone before us
that have faithfully proclaimed the message
of the Word of God
and that suffered greatly because of it.
Honestly, in America,
thankfully, we've had a pretty easy road
here in our lifetime
with regard to religious liberties,
with regard to freedoms.
And I'm thankful for them.
But even though Jeremiah was living in a day
in which there was great wickedness
and we see about the coming judgment
and we see the circumstances
that he was facing,
we understand that through all of it,
God was aware.
God was able.
As we look at the passage,
these chapters of Scripture,
I not only note the coming judgment
and the circumstances,
but I want you to take note
of the compassion of the Lord.
Really, we'll look at it from two perspectives
this evening.
Number one, I see the compassion of the Lord
as seen in Jeremiah's deliverance
from the dungeon.
We find that there are these men
in chapter 38 that want to kill Jeremiah.
And they take Jeremiah
and according to verse 6,
they let him down into this dungeon
where there's no water
and Jeremiah sunk in the mire.
The Bible tells us of this man
in verse 7,
Ebed-Melech the Ethiopian.
He was one of the eunuchs
which was in the king's house.
He heard that they had put Jeremiah
in the dungeon.
The king then sitting in the gate of Benjamin,
Ebed-Melech went forth
out of the king's house
and spake to the king saying,
notice what he says.
In v. 9 of Jeremiah 38,
My lord the king,
these men have done evil
in all that they have done
to Jeremiah the prophet,
whom they have cast into the dungeon
and he is like to die for hunger
in the place where he is,
for there's no more bread in the city.
Then the king commanded Ebed-Melech
the Ethiopian saying,
take from hence 30 men with thee
and take up Jeremiah the prophet
out of the dungeon before he die.
Notice what happens in v. 11,
so Ebed-Melech took the men with him
and went into the house of the king
under the treasury
and took thence old cast clouts
and old rotten rags
and let them down by cords
into the dungeon of Jeremiah.
Now can you imagine being Jeremiah?
He's sinking in the mire.
He's in this dungeon.
We find that they placed him there
so that he would die.
We find that Ebed-Melech
as he approaches the king,
he says, would you allow us to go?
He's like to die for hunger
in the place where he is.
The king gives permission in v. 10
that they go and deliver Jeremiah
before he'd die.
And it says in v. 12
that Ebed-Melech the Ethiopian
sent him to Jeremiah.
I mean, just hearing the words of Ebed-Melech
must have brought some level of comfort
and encouragement to Jeremiah
as he's there in that dungeon.
It says, put now these old cast clouts
and rotten rags under thine armholes
under the cords.
And Jeremiah did so.
So they drew up Jeremiah with cords
and took him out of the dungeon.
And Jeremiah remained in the court of the prison.
I see God's deliverance here.
I understand that as I look
at the passage of Scripture,
I begin to see how God is able
to deliver and we see the compassion
of the Lord and we understand
that there were some men
that had this evil plan against Jeremiah.
They wanted Jeremiah to die in the dungeon.
But the reality is that God wasn't done
with Jeremiah.
And God knew where Jeremiah was
and God would work on the behalf
of Jeremiah by allowing this Ethiopian man
that is mentioned here, Ebed-Melech,
this Ethiopian man,
to go and to inquire of the king
and to seek permission from the king
to go with these 30 men
in order to bring this man Jeremiah out.
It's of interest to me
that in v. 4, there were four of them
that put Jeremiah in the dungeon
and then there's a group of 30
that come to bring him out.
God is aware of where Jeremiah is
and God is working on the behalf
of His servant.
We find that Ebed-Melech
would be rewarded for his work
that he does here in Jeremiah 38
if you look over quickly
as kind of a sidebar.
In Jeremiah 39, verses 16-18,
we see where this man would be rewarded
for his faithfulness.
It says this in v. 16,
Go and speak to Ebed-Melech the Ethiopian,
saying, Thus saith the Lord of hosts,
the God of Israel,
Behold, I will bring My words upon this city
not for evil and not for good,
and they shall be accomplished in that day before thee.
Again, we see the reference to the coming judgment.
We see the reference to the fact
that God was going to bring this judgment
upon His people because of their wickedness.
But notice the promise in v. 17-18
with regard to Ebed-Melech.
It says this,
But I will deliver thee in that day,
saith the Lord.
And thou shalt not be given
into the hand of the men
whom thou art afraid.
For I will surely deliver thee,
and thou shalt not fall by the sword,
but thy life shall be for a prey unto thee.
Why? Notice this at the end of v. 18.
Because thou hast put thy trust in Me,
saith the Lord.
See, this evening, we have to ask ourselves,
even as we, yes, we're looking at Jeremiah in particular,
but within the context of these chapters of Scripture,
we are introduced to this other man
that God used to bring deliverance
in the life of Jeremiah.
And we see how that he is rewarded.
And we find that the Bible tells us
that he put his trust in God.
Remember in v. 17, it says this,
But I will deliver thee in that day.
But we find that in this promise,
the significance of the promise
is that it begins in v. 16 by saying,
Thus saith the Lord of hosts,
the God of Israel.
He is able.
And Ebed-Melech receives this word
of encouragement from Jeremiah.
And Jeremiah says, as he's speaking the Word of God,
he says that God says,
This is what's going to happen
because thou hast put thy trust in Me.
God wants us to trust Him.
We sing the song, Trust and Obey.
We speak about trusting the Lord.
But I wonder in your life and in my life,
how often do we really trust Him?
I made the statement to someone not too many weeks ago.
We're speaking about some historical things
within our nation and just various things
that are taking place even now today.
We're speaking about trust and confidence
and how some put their trust in chariots
and some put their trust in men.
And we understand that.
You read history, you understand how those things work.
But it's of interest to me that on our paper money,
it says,
In God, we trust.
Now I understand there's a group of people today
that would like to remove those four words from our money.
And I understand that.
But the reality is that when it was first designed
and had those words placed upon it,
we see the significance of that.
In God, we trust.
Is it not shameful this evening
that in the very money that we have in our currency
in the United States of America,
that it says in God we trust,
yet we have many countless people that trust in money?
And the very money says in God we trust.
It's amazing.
The Bible tells us about money that makes wings as eagles
and flies away.
We find that in the very currency that we have,
there's this reminder in God we trust.
This man, Ibn Maliki, put his trust in the Lord God Almighty
this evening.
we find that our God still today
wants us to trust Him.
He wants us to trust Him
even in days of what man would describe
as being uncertain days,
as challenging days,
as difficult days.
God says, I'm still in control.
I'm still on the throne.
Will you trust Me?
We find that Jeremiah,
in the very midst of dealing with all that he's dealing with,
and I want to be careful not to go to too many other portions
because we could really just spend all night here
looking through the passages in the book of Jeremiah,
but in chapter 32,
Jeremiah sees the Babylonians out there
besieging the city
and God tells them to go by the field.
To go and by the field.
But we're going to be taken captive.
By the field, Jeremiah.
You know what he did? He bought the field.
He believed God.
By the way, in the very passage,
God mentions there about the remnant
that would return.
About the fact that the captivity
would be a 70 year captivity.
And certainly we understand historically
that a remnant did return.
Jeremiah obeyed the Lord.
He trusted God.
Listen, when all of the things that he could see,
all that he could understand around him,
everything said the city's being taken.
Even God told him the city was being taken.
But yet he trusted God.
God said, by the field.
And he did.
Not only did Jeremiah trust God,
but we find that Ebed-Melech trusted the Lord
through these actions that are recorded in chapter 38.
We find that as we look at chapter 39
and look at the reward that is offered to him
and the word of encouragement
that it was based upon his trust in God.
You'll never go wrong trusting God.
He'll never let you down.
He'll never fail you.
Our God is able.
God wants us to take Him at His word.
He wants us to live by faith.
I want you to notice not only
do we see the compassion of the Lord
in Jeremiah's deliverance from the dungeon,
but I see the compassion of the Lord
through the command of Nebuchadnezzar.
We find that in chapter 39,
as we read already,
we will not review these same verses
and read them again.
We find that the Bible tells us
that the Babylonians enter in
and they take the city.
And it says that the city was broken up
in verse 2 of Jeremiah 39.
We find that the Bible records for us
how Zedekiah and a group of others
sought to flee from the city
and yet they are taken
and the army of the Chaldeans
pursued them and overtook them.
And we find that his sons are slain
and his eyes are put out.
And we come to that.
We see all that's taking place.
And if you know anything about the Babylonians,
you understand if you look at the history
and you see the power of these folks
and really the brutality of these groups of people,
and you find that you come to Jeremiah 39
in verse 11,
and you notice a charge, a command
that the king gives to the captain of the guard.
It's amazing.
In verse 11, the Bible says
that Nebuchadnezzar, king of Babylon,
gave charge concerning Jeremiah
to Nebuchadnezzar Adan,
the captain of the guard.
Now think about this.
Just pause in your mind for a moment
and think about all that's taking place.
The Chaldeans, the Babylonians,
they've come in.
They've been in a place
where they've besieged the city
for a lengthy period of time.
The armies of Egypt and Pharaoh,
they come in and the Chaldeans leave,
but then the Egyptians leave
and the Chaldeans come back.
Now the Chaldeans have taken the city.
It's broken up.
They've already dealt with Zedekiah's sons.
They've dealt with Zedekiah.
They've dealt with the nobles.
And we find all of these things going on.
And the king of Babylon
comes to the captain of the guard
to speak to him about Jeremiah.
About one person
that's in the city.
Isn't that amazing to you?
I mean, we're going to see what he says.
But I want you in your mind tonight
to think about the power of our God.
The compassion of our God.
The ability of our God
to take care of His people.
From our human perspective,
we would maybe come to the conclusion
that Nebuchadnezzar's not going to have any idea
who Jeremiah is.
How does he get a hold of dealing with this situation
and taking time away from all the other events
that are going on to deal with this?
Because God is at work.
God's taking care of His prophet.
He's taking care of His man.
The Bible says this.
Notice the charge, the command
that Nebuchadnezzar gives to his captain of the guard,
Nebuchadnezzar Adan.
In verse 12, it says this.
Take him and look well to him.
Hold on, you want me to do what?
Look well to him.
Furthermore, do him no harm.
Can you imagine saying this to a captain of the guard?
A man that was a man of war.
No idea how many he had slain in his life.
And the king says, take him
and look well to him
and do him no harm.
And then it says this,
but do unto him even as he shall say unto thee.
You want me to do what?
If you know the passage of Scripture,
don't act like, well, I heard this before.
This is amazing that God would work
in the life of this wicked, ungodly king
and captain of the guard,
and He brings this.
Listen, God is at work.
He knows where you are.
He knows where I am.
He knows what we're dealing with.
He is able to deliver us.
I preached a message in the very beginning
of this whole COVID thing
from the book of Daniel.
I think it was the very first Sunday
when I preached all day long
and had different crowds of people in here
each service as we were seeking
to maintain the numbers by which
our governor was restricting us by.
And I preached from Daniel
that our God is able to deliver us.
And He is.
And here Jeremiah,
remember, the very people
that he was ministering to,
the very people that he was delivering a message to,
they threw him in prison.
They wanted him dead.
They put him in the dungeon.
And now comes this wicked Babylonian king,
and he says to his captain of the guard,
take him.
He says, look well to him.
He says, do him no harm.
By the way, here's what you need to do.
Whatever he tells you to do, do.
I'm not sure that Nebuchadnezzar had ever received
instruction from Nebuchadnezzar in this fashion before.
I'm not sure that this is a common approach
to dealing with a conquered people.
But yet, God is working.
God is protecting His man.
The Bible says in v. 13,
so Nebuchadnezzar, Adam, the captain of the guard,
says that he sent Nebuchadnezzar,
Rabsarus, Nergal, Sherezer, Rabmag,
all the king of Babylon's princes.
He even sent them and took Jeremiah
out of the court of the prison,
committed him unto Gedaliah, the son of Ahiakim,
the son of Shaphan,
that he should carry him home,
so he dwelt among the people.
We read the latter part of chapter 39 already
as it dealt with the situation with Ibn Malik,
so skip down to v. 1 of chapter 40 if you will.
It says this,
the word that came to Jeremiah from the Lord
after that Nebuchadnezzar, Adam,
the captain of the guard had let him go from Ramah
when he had taken him,
being bound in chains among all
that were carried away captive of Jerusalem and Judah,
which were carried away captive unto Babylon.
And the captain of the guard took Jeremiah
and said unto him,
The Lord thy God hath pronounced this evil upon this place.
Now the Lord hath brought it and done
according as he hath said,
because ye have sinned against the Lord
and have not obeyed His voice.
Therefore this thing has come upon you.
And now, behold, I loose thee this day from the chains
which were upon thine hand.
Who put those chains there?
His own people.
If it seem good unto thee to come with me into Babylon,
come, and I will look well unto thee.
But if it seem ill unto thee to come with me into Babylon,
forbear.
Behold, all the land is before thee.
Whither it seemeth good and convenient for thee to go,
thither go.
It says in verse number 5,
Now, while he was not yet gone back,
he said, Go back also to Goliath the son of Ahiakim,
the son of Shaphan,
whom the king of Babylon hath made governor
over the cities of Judah,
and dwell with him among the people.
Or go wheresoever it seemeth convenient unto thee to go.
Notice the last part of verse number 5.
So the captain of the guard gave him vittles and a reward
and let him go.
He gave him a bit of a reward and let him go.
Let's begin to look at the passage of Scripture and stand and view what Jeremiah has just
experienced.
I see it as being the compassion of the Lord.
I see how that God is taking care of His servant.
We understand that Jeremiah one day would die.
We'll begin to look at these events that unfold and are provided historically for us in chapters
37 through 40.
We see how that God was taking care of His man.
He was taking care of His servant.
And I wonder this evening, as we would look at a passage of Scripture like this, I wonder
if we really believe tonight that God is able to take care of us.
I wonder this evening if we believe that God is able to take care of us, if we begin to
remove certain things that we've come to take for granted in our own nation.
I'm thankful for the Bill of Rights.
I'm thankful for the U.S. Constitution.
I'm thankful for the First Amendment.
Thankful for those things.
We have brothers and sisters around the globe that don't have a U.S. Constitution.
They don't have the Bill of Rights, but yet they serve God faithfully and God is using
them and God protects them and God delivers them.
I hear testimony from missionaries all of the time as to how God is working and what
God is doing.
It encourages my heart.
And this evening, I hope that we'd understand that as we live here in America and we have
great freedoms and I'm thankful for them.
And there are many that are sounding the alarm today and no doubt, just as I have received
countless pieces of communication, no doubt you've come across some things where people
are sounding the alarm on what's going to happen in the days ahead and how our religious
liberties are being attacked and so on and so forth.
And I say this, listen, I'm not interested in dealing with hardship, but I'm thankful
to know that God is in control.
I'm thankful to know that He sits upon His throne.
I'm thankful to know that my responsibility and your responsibility is to be faithful
to God and to trust Him.
This evening, as we think about the truth that is before us and we look at the events
in the life of Jeremiah, we say, is it not true that Jeremiah, as he experienced the
deliverance of God, as he experienced the compassion of God, is it not true that we
serve the same God?
Is it not true that he too could work on our behalf?
That he could provide and protect us and he could deliver us from any of the opposition
that we might face in dealing with the blessing.
Now we see, listen, Jeremiah dealt with some hardship, but God knew where he was.
And we take note that Jeremiah was faithful and Jeremiah was committed to obedience.
It was not, I'm going to obey and I'm going to be faithful because it's easy.
In fact, because of his obedience and his faithfulness, it cost him dear.
But he pleased God.
I want you to, with the thought of what we've looked at in Jeremiah this evening, I want
you to turn to the book of 2 Timothy, if you will.
And I hope to conclude the message this evening with a thought from this third chapter of
2 Timothy chapter number 3.
And I hope that God would help us this evening.
That God would encourage us and strengthen our faith by seeing the testimony of Jeremiah
in those chapters that we've reviewed quickly this evening.
And then look at this truth that Paul would give Timothy.
We looked this morning at some of 2 Timothy chapter 4, but I want you to notice in chapter
number 3, the Bible begins this way.
This know also.
Now it's of interest to me that many times, as you look at the Word of God, that you find
that God wants His people to be aware of some things.
He wants us to be informed.
He does not want His people to be ignorant.
He says this know also.
Paul is speaking to Timothy.
We find the preservation of Scripture that God is giving us this truth.
And there's some things that we need to be aware of.
There's some things that we need to be informed of.
We find that Paul says on a number of occasions in other portions of Scripture, I would not
have you be ignorant brethren.
He wants them to be informed.
He wants them to have the instruction.
He wants them to have the Word of the Lord.
In this evening, we come to this chapter and the Bible says this know also.
Be aware of these things.
Have knowledge of these things.
That in the last days, perilous times shall come.
For men shall be lovers of their own selves, covetous, boasters, proud, blasphemers, disobedient
to parents, unthankful, unholy.
It continues.
Without natural affection, truce breakers, false accusers, incontinent, fierce, despisers
of those that are good, traitors, heady, high-minded, lovers of pleasure more than
lovers of God.
You read these descriptive terms, can you not see the fulfillment of these very things
even in the world in which we live today?
What great description is given with regard to these last days and that which would characterize
these last days, and God says He wants us to know this.
Verse 5, having a form of godliness but denying the power thereof, from such turn away.
For of this sort are they which creep into houses and lead captive silly women, laden
with sins, led away with divers lust, ever learning and never able to come to the knowledge
of the truth.
He deals with the description of these last days.
He says this, beginning in verse number 10, about the things that he knew with regard
to Paul.
But thou hast fully known my doctrine, manner of life, purpose, faith, longsuffering, charity,
patience, persecutions, afflictions which came unto me at Antioch, Iconium, Lystra,
what persecutions I endured, notice this phrase, but out of them all the Lord delivered
me.
I would encourage you, I actually gave a homework assignment on Wednesday night, I said I want
you to go back and read Psalm 48, don't raise your hand and tell me if you did, but I got
one message from someone that said I went and read it and it blessed my heart.
It began to share with me some things that God showed them in that psalm and I was encouraged
by that.
The Word of God is powerful.
I want you to think about what Paul mentions in one verse of Scripture, he says about Antioch,
Iconium, and Lystra, and you think about these statements that are made and how that Paul
says the persecutions that he endured, but out of them all the Lord delivered me.
I would encourage you this evening, if not tonight, maybe one day this week, to go back
and read Acts 13 and Acts 14 and read about that first missionary journey of the Apostle
Paul and read about the things that he suffered, the things that he endured, and how that God
delivered him.
By the way, for some of us we might not call it deliverance as he did, he was stoned and
left for dead, but God raised him up and he went back and preached some more.
Notice verse 12 of 2 Timothy 3,
It does not tell us that men are going to get better and better, they're going to get
worse and worse.
Are we not seeing it?
Honestly.
We look around our country, we look around our world.
We can see the evil.
We can see, as Isaiah speaks of, where they call evil good and good evil.
We see it.
We see where they legislate wickedness.
It's abounding in our nation.
And it's not going to get better and better.
Contrary to what some would like for you to believe, contrary to what some would stand
and proclaim as they would seek to garner your vote, or whatever it might be, and we
find that the Bible tells us that evil men and seducers, they're going to wax worse and
worse.
And with that message you say, okay, what is it that I'm supposed to do then?
Paul gives all this information to Timothy, he says, I want you to know this, I want you
to understand the characteristics of these last days, I want you to understand that it's
going to be perilous times, and here's what it's going to be like, and here's what you're
going to deal with.
And by the way, if you live godly in Christ Jesus, you're going to suffer persecution
because evil men and seducers are going to wax worse and worse.
And then he says this, continue.
That's what your job is.
But continue, verse 14.
But continue thou in the things which thou hast learned, and hast been assured of, knowing
of whom thou hast learned them.
It's a simple instruction, continue.
It's a whole lot easier.
to hear the instruction
and to give the instruction
than to heed the instruction.
For in the midst of the adversity
and the difficulties
and the perilous times that are described,
the reality is that many have said,
no, I'm not interested in all of that.
I'm not interested in dealing with the effects
and the persecutions that would come my way
because of staying faithful and continuing.
Paul enters into the fourth chapter
before he will make the statements
with regard to him finishing his course.
And he enters into this fourth chapter
with a charge for his son in the faith, Timothy.
He says, I charge thee before God
and the Lord Jesus Christ,
who shall judge the quick and the dead
as it is appearing in His kingdom.
Preach the Word.
Be instant in season, out of season.
Reprove, rebuke, exhort
with all longsuffering and doctrine.
For the time will come
when they will not endure sound doctrine.
But after their own lusts
shall they heap to themselves
teachers having itching ears.
They shall turn away their ears from the truth
and shall be turned into fables.
But watch thou in all things,
endure afflictions,
do the work of the evangelist,
make full proof of thy ministry.
Let's begin to think about
the days in which we're living.
I take great encouragement and comfort
from looking at the passage of Scripture
in the book of Jeremiah
that we've studied this evening.
Jeremiah was living in a day
when judgment was coming.
He faced some terrible circumstances,
but he experienced the compassion of God.
He saw God take care of him.
He saw God use Ibed-Melech
to get a host of men together
to deliver him from the dungeon.
Why? Because God wasn't done with him yet.
He gave the direction to a wicked
Babylonian king to tell his captain of the guard,
don't do him any harm.
Look well to him.
Take good care of him.
By the way, here's just whatever he says to do, do.
And Nebuchadnezzar of Dan
gives Jeremiah supplies, a reward,
and sends him on his way.
And this evening,
we serve the God of the universe.
And He is able.
We don't need to take this approach tonight
of the sky is falling.
Our God has a plan.
And His plan is that we would be faithful
unto death.
Amen?
Then we'd be faithful.
Just serve Him.
Just watch Him work.
I was reading this afternoon
and someone was making a comment on faith.
He was a preacher of yesteryear.
And he said the thing that's interesting about faith
is that faith goes beyond human ability
because if it's humanly possible,
God doesn't get the glory.
And so faith goes a step beyond human possibility.
That's good.
Because we believe that our God is able.
My trust this evening
is not in a system, in a government.
My trust this evening is not in some leader.
My trust this evening is not in some words on a page.
I'm thankful for the things that we have
and the freedoms that we have.
But if you take it all away,
you still have God.
And He's still in control.
And He's still God.
And we must still serve Him.
Do you believe that tonight?
There are people all over the world tonight.
You look at our missions map
when you leave here this evening,
and you remind yourself of the places
in which we have missionaries.
That literally because of meeting
in the fashion in which we're meeting tonight,
they could be imprisoned or worse.
Literally because of the people
that they share the Gospel with,
that if they trust Christ as their Savior,
they're disowned by their family.
At times, they're beaten.
At times, they're put to death
because of the culture in which they're in.
We have such freedoms and such liberties.
And I'm thankful for them.
But I fear that for too long,
we've taken them for granted.
Someone said, I don't know who it was,
that sometimes we don't know
how much we appreciate something
until it's taken away.
It might become a whole lot more difficult
to be a faithful Christian
in my lifetime and in your lifetime.
But can I tell you that that's
what we've been called to do?
We know, listen, Jeremiah knew
the coming judgment.
I don't know when the Lord's going to come,
and neither do you.
But we do know that the Bible tells us
the characteristics of the last days
as we read in 2 Timothy 3.
Evil men and seducers,
they're going to wax worse and worse.
Our society as a whole
is becoming more and more anti-God.
And by the way, they're not shy
about being anti-God.
They're not shy at all.
Some of the things that I've read
in recent days and weeks
with regard to some of that
which we may face as believers,
I don't know if it's true or not.
And I would not speculate on the truth of that,
but what I have to do is I say,
I've got to spend more time in this book.
I've got to have my faith increased.
I've got to be prepared for the battle.
And so do you.
Because our God is in control,
but we're in a battle.
And we see the wickedness
that is being proclaimed unashamedly.
And this evening,
we serve a God that is able.
And here's the beautiful thing.
Paul says at the end of 2 Timothy 4,
my time is well gone this evening,
but at the end of 2 Timothy 4,
let me read it to you
because I want to leave you with this.
It's powerful.
He'd already said that the time
of his departure is at hand.
He's ready to leave.
He's fought a good fight.
But notice with me in verse 17.
It'd be appropriate to read verse 16
along with it.
In 2 Timothy 4 and verse 16,
the Bible says that my first answer,
no man stood with me,
but all men forsook me.
I pray God that it be laid to their charge.
Verse 17, notwithstanding, notice this,
the Lord stood with me
and strengthened me,
that by me the preaching might be fully known
and that all the Gentiles might hear.
And I was delivered out of the mouth of the lion.
It says in verse 18,
and the Lord shall deliver me
from every evil work.
Notice this phrase,
and will preserve me
unto his heavenly kingdom,
to whom be glory forever and ever.
Amen.
One day, I'm going to die and so are you,
but I'm going to go to heaven.
And we understand that as Paul says here,
that the Lord will preserve me
until that day.
He was delivered, as he said in verse 17,
out of the mouth of the lion.
Many things in which Paul was delivered from,
as we mentioned in chapter number three,
that he said that out of them all,
the Lord delivered me.
But one day he faced death,
a martyr's death.
But we find until that day,
the Lord preserved him.
And then when that day came,
he entered into the glory of heaven.
And he said,
as he's writing to the believers in Philippi,
it's not easy for me to live as Christ,
but to die as Cain.
He says, I'm in a straight betwixt two,
having desired apart to be with Christ,
which is far better.
And this evening,
on a particular day in history,
Paul faced his last day.
He faced a martyr's death.
But he understood that until that day,
God was going to deliver him.
And when that day came,
listen, there are many martyrs
that have gone before us.
They were faithful.
They faced a martyr's death,
but then they entered
into the presence of our Savior.
I'm not saying to you this evening
that I want to face a martyr's death
or that we would.
I'm just asking tonight,
would we be faithful unto death?
What if it were that we had to
face some of those things
that people faced years ago?
Are we prepared?
What if someone came to you and said,
deny Christ or?
I don't know what the or is.
Are we willing to stand?
Are we willing to continue?
Are we recognizing that our God is able?
He's able to take care of us.
But you don't understand,
I need to have this job.
I need to have this.
No, you don't understand that God is able.
I'm saying that in love, I promise.
Our God is able.
And I believe tonight
that He wants some of His people
to stand and say,
I will follow Thee.
I will be faithful unto death.
Because I know,
I know that you're able.
And I know that you have a perfect plan
and through your plan,
you will be glorified.
Jerusalem was taken.
Jeremiah was there.
Jeremiah received good care
because of the compassion of the Lord.
Father, we love You. We thank You for loving us.
Thank You for Your Word.
I hope this evening that
You've taken Your Word and the truth contained therein
and You've helped us.
I know that many have described these days
as being uncertain.
And I understand that from man's perspective.
But God, we understand tonight that You're in control.
That You have a plan and a purpose.
We've understood this evening that You've called us
to continue to be faithful.
Father, I pray
that You would encourage each of us
through the example of Jeremiah,
through the example of Paul,
to determine that by Your grace and with Your help,
we will continue.
I pray, God, that You would work in hearts and lives.
Help me.
Help us to be faithful.
It's in Christ's name we pray, would You stand with me?