13 this evening and talk about someone that lived for the Lord, that walked with God and
was used of the Lord mightily, Elisha would fit that bill.
And I'm thankful over the past several months we've had the privilege to trace the steps
of Elisha and we understand that God has providentially preserved many of the events from Elisha's
life for our learning.
And what a blessing to be able to study these passages of Scripture, to be encouraged and
to be challenged through these studies.
The reality is as we come to 2 Kings 13, we'll read of the death of Elisha and we understand
from Hebrews 9 and verse 27, and as it's appointed unto man once to die, after this the judgment.
And with that in mind and thinking about the truth of Psalm 90, that psalm has been ascribed
to Moses and we find that in that passage of Scripture that it's recorded that we spend
our years as a tale that is told.
And therefore, I believe that Moses, obviously it's God's Word, he's the human author, he
rightly concludes and reminds us of the importance of numbering our days that we may apply our
hearts unto wisdom.
It's always interesting to me to study the final days of someone's life and throughout
the Scriptures, God gives us the opportunity to study a number of great patriarchs and
even in the New Testament as we had the opportunity to read of some of the disciples and the apostles
and see what God was doing in and through their lives and read some of those final days
and the final message, if you will, of what the Lord had done for them and what they desired
to pass on to the future generation and what have you.
Of course, we've seen even in our own history, we've seen the opportunity to have things
recorded of those that were nearing the end of their life and to think about just what
was on their mind.
I think about David in particular and the desire that he had to instruct Solomon and
to give him counsel and direction with regard to the kingdom, with regard to his own life.
Of course, as we would think about our study of Elijah and Elisha, we understand that his
death, as we studied there in 2 Kings 2, the translation, if you will, of Elijah and
how Elisha was there and how they journeyed together in all that took place and Elijah
continuously said to Elisha, Terry here, and he said, no, I'm coming, I'm coming, I'm coming
and he kept following and of course, the Lord brought Elijah to heaven.
Here in 2 Kings 13, we read about Elisha and his death.
It's interesting if we take the passage, begin reading with me in verse number 14,
if you will.
The Bible says this, now, Elisha was fallen sick of his sickness, whereof he died and
then you skip down to verse number 20 and you find that the Bible says, and Elisha died
and they buried him.
If you're taking notes this evening, I simply have titled the message tonight, and Elisha
died, and Elisha died.
Notice with me that the passage that is before us records for us a final meeting, a final
meeting.
There's a meeting that is given to us here in verse number 14 and it's a meeting between
Elisha, the prophet of God, and Joash, the king of Israel.
In fact, in the previous verses of scripture from verses 10 through 13, there really is
a brief synopsis of the entire reign of Joash and then we see that the Bible then begins
to give us some of the details of those things that happened and here in verse number 14,
we find that the Bible tells us that Joash, upon hearing of Elisha's sickness, that there
was a meeting that took place between these two men.
It is interesting for us to be mindful of the fact, even before we read the fullness
of verse number 14 and kind of the description of what is given, it's important for us to
note that Joash, just as all of the kings of Israel, were wicked.
He was a wicked man.
We find that after the divided kingdom, when you begin to look at Israel's history with
the northern kingdom, Israel, the southern Judah, you'll find that within the history
of Judah, there were some good kings.
There were some kings that they experienced revival under their ministries and we understand
as we study some of those things, but as you look through Israel's history and the northern
tribes, there are no good kings.
And the reality is that the Bible tells us in verse number 11 of 2 Kings 13, and he,
speaking of Joash, he did that which was evil in the sight of the Lord.
He departed not from all the sins of Jeroboam, the son of Nebat, who made Israel sin, but
he walked therein.
And obviously, many of the kings of Israel are given to us with that description of following
after the sins of Jeroboam, and we've made note of that on several occasions.
And we find here that Joash, he's a wicked man, he's following after the sins of Jeroboam.
However, as we note the greeting that is used here in verse number 14, it reveals to us
really the influence that Elisha had during this particular time.
Notice in verse 14, now, Elisha was fallen sick of his sickness, whereof he died.
And Joash, the king of Israel, came down unto him, and wept over his face, and said, O my
father, my father, the chariot of Israel, and the horsemen thereof.
That's an interesting greeting.
We find that in this particular greeting and the words that are uttered by Joash, it would
be mindful for us to consider the fact that these are the same words that Elisha uttered
at the time of Elijah's translation.
If you turn back to 2 Kings chapter number 2, and we will not go through the entirety
of all that took place there in 2 Kings 2, however, we find that there was some discussion
that took place between Elijah and Elisha.
And Elijah tells Elisha in verse number 10, Thou hast asked a hard thing, nevertheless,
if thou see me when I am taken from thee, it shall be so unto thee, but if not, it shall
not be so.
This was with regard to the double portion that he requested.
In verse number 11, It came to pass, as they still went on and talked, that, behold, there
appeared a chariot of fire, and horses of fire, and parted them both asunder.
It says this, And Elijah went up by a whirlwind into heaven, and Elisha saw it, and he cried,
My father, my father, the chariot of Israel, and the horsemen thereof.
And he saw them no more.
It says that he took hold of his own clothes and rent them in two pieces, and of course
we begin the life and ministry of Elisha after Elijah's translation.
It's interesting as we begin to see the way in which Joash would approach and greet Elisha
here in 2 Kings 13.
I mentioned already that it reveals the influence that Elisha had, but I also believe that it
reveals to us that Joash understood not only the position that Elisha had as being a prophet
of God, but the way in which God's power had been used and had been evidenced in the life
of Elisha.
Of course, we've studied many of the miracles of Elisha, and you study the miracles, you
begin to see how God used Elisha in mighty ways, and no doubt that God is continuing
to give His people Israel a witness and an opportunity to hear the truth of the Word
of God.
I think about the time in which Ahab and Jehoshaphat made affinity and they were to go into battle
together and Ahab of course had called some false prophets over and Jehoshaphat inquired
were there not a prophet of God that we can inquire of, and in that passage of Scripture
Ahab reveals that there was one, but his name was Micaiah and he always prophesied that
which was evil with regard to Ahab.
It had something to do with the wickedness of Ahab, not with the prophecy of Micaiah.
The reality is that we find that God would use Micaiah to give that voice and to give
that truth that was needed, and I'm thankful that God has always, as we look throughout
the history of Israel, we study the entirety of the Old Testament, you find that God always
sent prophets, there was a voice, there was truth, and we find that even Jeremiah on the
eve of captivity of the Babylonians there of Judah, that he's prophesying and he's giving
the truth.
We find here that Joash, though he departed not from all the sins of Jeroboam, in this
final meeting it is revealed to us the influence that Elisha had and the fact that he, Joash,
recognized the position that Elisha held as being a prophet of God.
Notice with me, not only a final meeting, but there's a final message.
In verse number 15, the Bible says, "...and Elisha said unto him..."
In verses 15 through 19, this final message is revealed to us, and really we could call
it a final prophecy if we'd like, and in this final message we find that really Elisha will
use two object lessons and then give a prophecy with regard to those object lessons.
In verses 15 through 17, we see the first of these two object lessons, and it has to
do with shooting an arrow.
Notice in verse 15, look at what Elisha says to Joash, "...take bow and arrows, and he took
unto him bow and arrows.
And he..."
He, Elisha, said to the king of Israel,
that's Joash,
put thine hand upon the bow.
And he put his hand upon it.
And Elisha put his hands upon the king's hands
and he said, open the window eastward.
And he opened it.
Then Elisha said, shoot.
And he shot.
And he said, the arrow of the Lord's deliverance,
the arrow of deliverance from Syria,
for thou shalt smite the Syrians in Aphac
till thou have consumed them."
Think about this first object lesson
of shooting this arrow.
And you see how step by step,
Elisha took Joash through the process
and Joash takes that bow and he takes those arrows.
And the Bible tells us that Elisha
then put his hands upon the king's hands.
And he told him to open the window and to shoot.
And he shot.
And you find that Elisha then says,
the arrow of the Lord's deliverance,
there in verse number 17.
If you look back into our passage of scripture
at the beginning of chapter 13,
you find that the Bible gives us an overview
of the time in which Jehoahaz was king of Israel.
And while he was king of Israel,
the Bible tells us in verse number three
that the anger of the Lord was kindled against Israel
and he delivered them into the hand of Haziel,
king of Syria, in the hand of Ben-Hadad,
the son of Haziel, all their days.
And you begin to read through these verses of scripture
and you find how that Syria had been once again
oppressing Israel.
It tells us at the end of verse number seven
that the king of Syria had destroyed them
and had made them like the dust by threshing.
And so now we find that Elisha is now speaking to Joash.
And Joash is the king after Jehoahaz.
And we find there's still these problems with Syria
and all these things are going on.
And Elisha gives him an object lesson.
And within that object lesson,
he reminds him of the prophecy.
The first mention there in verse number 17,
the deliverance from Syria.
And you notice he says,
the arrow of the Lord's deliverance.
And then he says,
and the arrow of deliverance from Syria.
Once again, as we've made note
throughout the life of Elisha,
many of his prophecies are very specific.
And that's because God is a very specific God
and he's omniscient, he knows all things.
And Elisha is his servant, his prophet,
and he's speaking the word of the Lord.
We find that the second of these object lessons
is found in verses 18 and 19
and it has to do with smiting the arrows.
It says this in verse number 18,
and he said, again, Elisha speaking to Joash,
take the arrows and he took them.
And he said unto the king of Israel,
smite upon the ground.
And he smote thrice and stayed.
And it's interesting response in verse number 19,
the Bible says, and the man of God was wroth with him
and said, thou shouldest have smitten five or six times,
then hast thou smitten Syria till thou hast consumed it.
Whereas now thou shalt smite Syria but thrice.
So we find in the second object lesson
that Elisha now says, take those arrows
and he tells them to smite the ground.
He tells them to smite upon the ground
and he smote thrice and stayed.
And we find that Elisha is angry with them
and he says, you should have smitten five or six times
and because you only did it three times,
your deliverance and your victory,
it should be but thrice,
according to the end of verse number 19.
Again, we find that in this passage,
that Elisha in the final message
that he would use these object lessons
for the purpose of giving this prophecy
of deliverance from Syria,
but that it would be only thrice,
three times that they would smite Syria.
You notice here in verse number 19,
the final message is given.
Skip over if you will,
we'll look at verses 20 and 21 here in just a moment,
but look at verses 22 through 25,
where we see the fulfillment of this prophecy.
The Bible says, but Haziel, king of Syria,
oppressed Israel all the days of Jehoahaz.
We mentioned that in the beginning of chapter 13.
It says, and the Lord was gracious unto them
and had compassion on them and had respect unto them
because of his covenant with Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob
and would not destroy them,
neither cast he them from his presence as yet.
It's interesting, two final words to verse number 23,
for we know that eventually the nation of Israel
would be taken captive by the Assyrians
and that is recorded for us later on in their history.
But at this particular time,
we find that the Lord continued to show grace
and mercy, compassion to his people.
In verse 24, so Haziel, king of Syria, died
and Ben-Hadad, his son, reigned in his stead and Jehoash.
Now that's Joash that we've been speaking of.
It's interesting if you study
through all of the history of what's going on,
there's actually a Joash that's king of Judah.
And so there's a distinction
that is given at this particular time
in using the phraseology Jehoash as opposed to Joash
because there was a Joash that was king of Judah.
And here the distinction being known
that it is speaking of the king of Israel.
In verse number 14, the distinction was not in name,
but it said, and Joash, the king of Israel,
so that we could make sure that we're having
the proper knowledge of who is being spoken of.
Notice in verse 25, that he took again
out of the hand of Ben-Hadad, the son of Haziel, the cities,
which he had taken out of the hand of Jehoahaz,
his father by war.
Notice what it says, three times did Joash beat him
and recovered the cities of Israel.
It's exactly what Elisha had prophesied
in verses 17 through 19 with regard to this final message
that they would have, it was the Lord's deliverance,
it was the arrow of the Lord's deliverance,
and that they would have deliverance from Syria
and that he should smite Syria but thrice.
And that's exactly what happens in the fulfilled prophecy.
So we see a final meeting, a final message,
notice a final miracle.
It's interesting if you look at verses 20 and 21,
the Bible tells us in verse number 20
that Elisha, he died and was buried.
It tells us that there's something that's taking place
at the same time, Elisha died, notice in verse 20,
and they buried him, and the bands of the Moabites
invaded the land at the coming in of the year,
and it came to pass as they were burying a man.
So there's this man, he's not named for us here
in the passage of scripture, but he dies in battle.
The Bible tells us that they spied a band of men,
and so they cast this man into the sepulcher of Elisha.
And it's interesting because the Bible tells us
at the end of verse number 21,
and I've called it a final miracle, of course,
God was in this and allowing this to happen
and giving to really the Joash
and the nation of Israel at this time
the fact that the prophecy would come to pass
as we've just read in verses 22 through 25.
And the Bible ends in verse number 21 and says,
and when the man was let down
and touched the bones of Elisha,
he revived and stood up on his feet.
That's kind of interesting, isn't it?
That's not what you would expect, right?
You're casting this guy in, you see this band of soldiers,
the Bible tells us that this one was,
they were gonna bury this guy, they spied a band of men,
and so they cast him into the sepulcher of Elisha.
And when that man touches the bones of Elisha, he revives.
And he stands up and he's gonna get out.
That's amazing, right?
Not what you would expect, not what's going on.
And we see really, again, a final miracle.
Elisha, of course, his ministry was known
for many miracles that took place.
We've studied through those miracles.
We've seen the power of God and the hand of God,
and we've seen how God was helping his people
understand the power that he had.
And we find here, even after the death of Elisha,
that God would allow this miraculous reviving
of this individual as he was cast into the sepulcher
of Elisha to come to be revived and to stand upon his feet.
Now, as we think about this passage of Scripture,
we see a final meeting, a final message,
and a final miracle.
I want you to think about the life of Elisha.
And I want you to think, as we've studied now
for so many weeks, and we understand that Elisha,
he ministered faithfully and courageously.
I want you to understand that Elisha served the Lord
during a time of great wickedness.
We think about the condition of Israel as a nation,
and we think about the way in which he was serving.
And, of course, Elijah served during a time
of great wickedness in the nation of Israel,
Ahab as being the king, married to Jezebel,
and all of the wickedness.
And we made mention of several of those things.
But we find that when Elisha begins to reign,
or when he begins to serve, that Jehoram is the king,
as we find in the passage of Scripture
right after the translation of Elijah,
King Jehoram and King Jehu, King Jehoahaz,
and then King Joash.
Now, we're not sure exactly of how many years
of Joash's reign that Elisha was ministering,
but if you take the first three kings of Israel
under whom Elisha was serving and ministering,
their three reigns total 57 years.
So Elisha ministered for nearly 60 years,
and he ministered faithfully and courageously.
And we begin to read, as we've studied
throughout these passages of Scripture.
begin to see how that he dealt with all sorts of things
and looking at the wickedness of Israel and their idolatry
and all of those things that are going on,
and yet you see a man that faithfully and courageously served God.
A man who stood for the Lord.
A man who stood upon the truth and prophesied faithfully.
As I study the life of Elisha and as we conclude this evening,
I believe that we ought to be not only encouraged by the life
and ministry of Elisha, but I believe we should be challenged.
I believe that as we study through the lives of those
that are recorded for us within the Word of God,
but even those contemporaries that have gone before us
begin to think about their lives and their faithfulness
and we begin to, yes, be encouraged by that,
but we ought to be challenged.
I believe there are times in which we are tempted to think about
the difficulties in which we have to serve.
We begin to think about the landscape of the things that are going on
in our society, in our culture,
and we begin to think about the wickedness and say,
man, it's so bad, it's so terrible, and it's so challenging.
Listen, there are many people that have gone before us
that have served God faithfully and courageously
in times of great wickedness,
that dealt with great levels of adversity and oppression.
We think about the way in which Elisha would stand and he would serve,
and I say, oh, that God would enable us to have that same level of courage,
that God would enable us to have that same level of faithfulness to serve Him.
As I think about the life of Elisha and it comes to its end here
in 2 Kings 13, and we say it's a life that was used by God,
that he was a man that was surrendered to the Lord
and to the work that God had for him,
and I say, oh, that we too would be in that same position,
that we would allow God to work in and through us.
We sang tonight about channels only,
how appropriate to think about how Elisha was used of God as a channel,
and God used him, and God was glorified through his life,
and I think about our lives today,
and I'm mindful of two passages in the New Testament.
Quickly going to make reference to them.
Turn to the book of Ephesians, if you will, and chapter number 6.
I'm going to make reference here,
and then we'll make reference in 2 Timothy chapter number 3,
and then be done this evening and have our time of prayer.
But I want you to consider with me
these many years of faithful ministry of Elisha,
and ask the Lord to help us to have the strength and courage
to stand in days of adversity and great wickedness.
The Bible says in Ephesians 6 and beginning in verse number 10,
Finally, my brethren, be strong in the Lord and the power of His might.
Put on the whole armor of God,
that ye may be able to stand against the wiles of the devil.
For we wrestle not against flesh and blood,
but against principalities, against powers,
against the rulers of the darkness of this world,
against spiritual wickedness in high places.
We are engaged in spiritual warfare, amen?
We see it all around us.
I mentioned to a couple of folks that I spoke to on the phone today,
with just a little bit of spiritual discernment,
you can easily acknowledge today
that we're living in great spiritual warfare.
The Bible continues in verse number 13,
Wherefore, take unto you the whole armor of God,
notice that ye may be able to withstand in the evil day,
and having done all, to stand.
Stand therefore, having your loins girded out with truth,
and having on the breastplate of righteousness,
and your feet shod with the preparation of the gospel of peace,
above all, taking the shield of faith,
wherewith ye shall be able to quench all the fiery darts of the wicked,
and take the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the Spirit,
which is the Word of God.
You notice on a number of occasions in these few verses of Scripture in Ephesians 6
that the word stand or withstand is used,
and the importance of standing.
I'm thankful as we've studied,
and really we began the study of the life of Elijah and Elisha
back in August of last year,
and we've studied through their lives on Wednesday evenings,
and we've had the opportunity to study the lives of these two great prophets,
and to see individuals that stood for the Lord,
that took that stand.
And as New Testament believers,
we have this instruction in Ephesians 6
with regard to the spiritual warfare that we're engaged in,
and that we're to be strong in the Lord, and the power of His might,
to put on the whole armor of God.
Why? So that we can stand in this evil day,
so that we can withstand in this evil day,
and we understand that we have been given this responsibility to stand for truth.
You look in our society today,
and you see people all over the place that are folding.
They're not standing.
Amen?
You see it.
And I'm not saying that you have to be ugly about standing,
but you need to stand.
Amen?
Truth is truth.
In Romans, Paul asks the question as he's speaking there about the Jews,
you know, what can we do against the truth?
You can't do anything against the truth.
Only for the truth.
And the reality is that Jesus is the truth,
and He's given us His Word which is truth.
Oh, that we'd stand on it.
We don't have to cave in to the pressures of our society.
We don't need to be in a position where we feel like we have to be
quote-unquote politically correct.
I'd much rather be biblically correct than politically correct.
Amen?
I mean, to think about the fact that we would try to cater to the demands of a culture
that we're living in, and at the very same time, not please our Savior.
See, sometimes we don't think about it that way.
I'd much rather please my Savior.
Amen?
I'm going to stand before Him, by the way, and so are you.
I'd much rather please Him than cave in to the pressures of this world.
I'm thankful that Elijah and Elisha, they didn't cave in.
They stood boldly.
They stood courageously.
Oh, that we would stand.
Not only that we would stand even as we've studied so many of these lessons
through the lives of these two prophets,
but I think of this truth in 2 Timothy chapter number 3.
Not only that the New Testament principle of standing according to Ephesians 6,
but this word in 2 Timothy 3, continue.
Continue.
It's not a time to wave the white flag of surrender.
It's not a time to give up.
It's not a time to retreat.
It's not a time to, no, it's a time to continue.
Amen?
We find that in 2 Timothy chapter number 3,
we don't have the time this evening to read the entirety of the passage,
so if you'd let me just read a few of these verses
and give you kind of the overview.
Paul begins it this way in verse number 1.
This know also.
You find often throughout the Word of God that our God wants us to be informed.
He doesn't want us to be ignorant.
In fact, many times in the writings of Paul,
he'll use that phraseology,
I would not that you be ignorant, brethren.
There are some, according to 2 Peter chapter number 3,
that were willfully ignorant.
Amen?
They were willingly ignorant of these things.
Oh, I trust that we'd be informed.
I remember what one evangelist said that was here many years ago,
Brother Caldwell.
He said this, he said,
the thing that bothers me the most is not somebody that doesn't know the truth,
it's somebody that doesn't want to know the truth.
That's sad.
Paul says, know this, be informed of this,
that in the last days perilous times shall come.
For men shall be lovers of their own selves,
covetous, boasters, proud, blasphemers,
disobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy,
without natural affection, truce breakers,
false accusers, incontinent, fierce,
despisers of those that are good,
traitors, heady, high-minded,
lovers of pleasure more than lovers of God,
having a form of godliness,
but denying the power thereof from such turn away.
What a list.
We don't have time to go through all of these points this evening,
but Paul's letting Timothy know,
here's the description,
here are the characteristics of these last days.
Skip down to verse number 12.
Yea, and all that will live godly in Christ Jesus shall suffer persecution.
You say, I wish it wasn't there, but it is.
Paul's letting Timothy know.
You don't live for God.
Persecution's gonna come.
What did Jesus say?
If they've hated me, they're gonna hate you.
Peter will later say, don't think it strange about this fiery trial.
Right?
And here he says this,
but evil men and seducers, verse 13,
shall wax worse and worse, deceiving and being deceived.
Now, after Paul gives all of that information,
after Paul lets Timothy know,
here's how it's gonna be characterized,
here's what you're gonna deal with,
there's gonna be persecution if you live godly in Christ Jesus.
These men are gonna wax worse and worse,
they're not gonna get better and better,
that's what you're gonna deal with.
And then, how would Paul then tell Timothy what to do with this?
But, continue.
Continue.
You know all of this stuff,
but it's not that you...
retreat. It's not that you go hide. It's not that you give up. It's not that you
know you continue. Continue in what? Continue thou in the things which thou
hast learned and has been assured of, knowing of whom thou hast learned them.
To make sure that it was clear for us, I'm believing that that Timothy had an
understanding of what Paul would be referring to. And we find that the
continuation goes that from a child thou has known the Holy Scriptures, which
are able to make thee wise unto salvation through faith which is in
Christ Jesus. All scripture is given by inspiration of God. It's profitable for
doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for instruction in righteousness, that the
man of God might be perfect, throughly furnished unto all good works. And then
he tells them, preach the word in verse number two of chapter number four.
Continue, Timothy. So when I think about Elijah and Elisha, this this is our 34th
lesson that we studied these prophets of God. We've seen so many wonderful things.
But if we could finish our study of these prophets, Elisha in particular, over
the last 17 or so of these lessons, that we'd understand that they they stood.
They stood. They didn't serve in a time in which the kings were promoting
righteousness and cleaning out the false idols. They didn't serve in times of
where we see some that had served. They served in times of great wickedness. Yet
they stood. And they continued. They were faithful. One thing that I like about
both of these prophets is they were faithful unto the end. Faithful unto the
end. You know, God has called us to live a life of faithfulness until the end. But
we talk much about wanting to finish well. In this same book, in 2nd Timothy,
you get into chapter 4 and you begin to see how Paul mentions about
finishing, and how he had finished his race. It didn't happen by accident. All
the way back in Acts chapter number 20, when Paul is speaking to the Ephesian
elders, he makes this statement that, I might finish my course with joy. You have
to purpose to finish. If you're gonna stand, if you're gonna continue, oh, you
need to to follow the admonition of God in his word, that we put on the whole
armor of God and understand that we're to be strong in the Lord, the power
of his might, so on and so forth, that we follow the truth of the Word of God. But
there are so many pressures in our society today. But don't think for a
moment that those that have gone before us, that faithfully and courageously
served God, did not face similar pressures. The pressures are nothing new.
The opposition, the work of God, has always been. But throughout history, you
get the privilege of reading about some some folks that stood and continued, even
in the face of adversity. And I'm thankful that Elijah and Elisha are two
such prophets that stood and continued, and they serve faithfully unto the end.
Oh, that God would not only encourage us through the study of these two great
prophets, but challenge us that we would live in like manner. That we just
determine, you know what? I want to be biblically correct. I want to stand, and I
want to continue. I want to be found faithful. Well done, thou good and
faithful servant. Amen. Let's pray. Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for the lives of these two prophets of Israel. We thank you for the
privilege over so many months to now study their lives, and to trace their
steps, and to see, God, what it was that you were able to accomplish through them.
Lord, we know the times of great wickedness in which they served, and how
grateful we are that they stood, and they continued, and they were faithful unto
the end. Father, we understand that you've given us now a responsibility. This is
our time to serve you, to live for you. Before the service this evening, the
instrumentalists were playing, Living for Jesus. Oh, Father, I pray that you'd
help us to live for you. Lord, help us to stand. Help us, Lord, to continue. Help us
to not cave to the pressures of our society or our culture. Help us to live
for you, and to make a difference. I pray, God, that you would use us as channels.
Lord, that we would be clean vessels, fit for the Master's use. That, God, you alone
would be honored and glorified through our lives. Well, thank you for the work
that you'll do. For it's in Christ's name we pray, amen.