came from. I mean, can you imagine that bass came out of
that guy? I mean, you know a young guy with a bass voice
like that, that was amazing. What a great finish that was,
amen. And I heard some of you Baptists back there tapping
your toes. Amen. Praise the Lord. I enjoyed that. I
videoed that and I'm going to put it on my Facebook page so
that everybody can see the great music you folks have
here. I appreciate so much your music. It's been a joy
these last few days just to be able to sing the old hymns of
the faith. And to have these young men tonight get up and
sing, they're really good. I'll tell you what, I think I
ought to take them with me. I need some singers. You know
some evangelists travel in a team and they have singers
with them, several of them do. And I've never had anybody
travel with me to sing. Sometimes I try to sing, but
they always tell me, no don't sing Brother Meshon, just
preach, amen. But I enjoyed that tonight, it was a
blessing. Just want to let you know before I preach tonight
how much we appreciate you folks. You've been a blessing
to us over the years. And it's been good to be back here
again and to meet some old friends after a few years of
not having been here. And then also too we've met some new
people that have been added to the church since we were last
here. And we have really enjoyed this week together
with you. It's been a blessing to spend time with the
pastor and his wife and his family. We've enjoyed that as
well. And we've eaten well over there, praise the Lord.
Mrs. Pastor has been feeding us well. And so we are leaving
here a little heavier than we came. But that's alright
because you know it's always a blessing to be able to sit
down and enjoy a good meal and just have fellowship around
the table with God's people. And we've enjoyed that. Also
too I want to let you know how much we appreciate your
support of our ministry. You've been faithful and we
certainly appreciate that. And by the way let me say this, I
want to commend you, you are one of the few of our
supporting churches that sends us birthday cards, and
anniversary cards, and Christmas cards. And you keep
up with those events in our lives. And that means a lot to
us because many times even though we have supporting
churches that we love and we appreciate sometimes we don't
always hear from our churches. And it's so good for us to be
able to hear from your church. And it means a lot, it really
does. We have a church up in Alaska what they do is every
fifth Wednesday night they come to the Wednesday night
service. And what they do is everybody in the church
writes to missionaries. And they've been doing that now for
several years. I think the pastor told me for at least the
last 25 or 30 years. And so we always get a nice card from
them at different events and that's always been such a joy
to us. So we appreciate that. And your support means a lot
to us because we couldn't stay on the road really without
having some support from churches that we've known over
the years that we love, and they love us, and they've
helped us. And it's been a blessing because our ministry
has always been geared towards small churches. We don't
generally go into bigger churches. The largest church
that I think I've ever preached in was probably the weekend I
was there was about 1,500 in attendance. And I'm not used to
that many people. And usually I'm preaching in churches that
run between 50 and 150. And we want to help the smaller
churches. And we want to help the church planters. And I've
been involved in church planning. And I'm glad that
I've had the opportunity to do that. We planted a Spanish
speaking church in the inner city of San Diego. We started
that church with a Mexican national. And that work is
doing well. And we're thankful for it. I understand that we're
getting ready to plant another church out of that one. So we
support that work out of our home church. I think we still
do. And so we're glad for that. And I've helped other young
men as well and try to be an encouragement to them in church
planning. So you help us to help them. And you minister to
us and it helps us to minister to others. And by the way it
helps us to put gasoline in the tank. Amen. That SUV it doesn't
go down the road without gasoline. It is not electric.
And it is not hybrid. It's gas engine. And even though it's a
pretty thrifty little vehicle at the same time gasoline out in
our area of the world is extremely expensive. So we're
thankful for your support of our ministry and your partners with
us. And we don't take that for granted. So thank you. We
appreciate it church. God bless you for it. And we want you to
know we love you and we appreciate you. Deuteronomy
chapter 6 in your Bible tonight. Now I am not feeling well and
I've been telling you that the last couple of days. I'm not
shaking hands tonight I'm just blowing my nose. So forgive me
for that. I had a bad day today. I got up I guess this morning
about 5.30 and I thought I'd been hit by a truck. And
apparently this thing has moved from my chest down to my head.
And so prayerfully I'll be able to get over this the next couple
of days. I'm glad I have a couple of days to rest. So thank
you for your prayers and we appreciate that so much.
Deuteronomy chapter 6 and if you will stand please with me out
of respect and reverence to the reading of God's holy, infallible
and earned inspired Word. Deuteronomy chapter 6 reading
from the Old King James Bible. I'm going to read you can
follow along silently if you will please. In fact I think
what I'll do is I'm going to begin in verse 1 usually I start
in verse 4. But I'm going to begin in the very first verse of
Deuteronomy 6. Now this was written to the children of
Israel. However what we're going to see here tonight in this
particular text has an application to us today. It has
an application to us as a church. It has an application to
us as individuals. And so what I'm going to read here even
though like I say it was written to the children of
Israel, the nation of Israel it has a definite application to
us in this period of time, in this dispensation. So beginning
in verse 1 of chapter 6 I read this, Now these are the
commandments, the statutes and the judgments, which the Lord
your God commanded to teach you, that ye might do them in
the land whither you go to possess it, that thou mightest
fear the Lord thy God to keep all His statutes and His
commandments which I command thee, thou and thy son, and
thy sons' sons, all the days of thy life, and that thy days
may be prolonged. Hear therefore, O Israel, and
observe to do it. Now it's the second time God says that
there's something that needs to be done, you need to do it.
Hear therefore, O Israel, and observe to do it, that it may
be well with thee. So I understand this to mean if you
don't do it it's not going to be well with you. See obedience
is an important thing. Amen, would you agree with that? So
hear therefore, O Israel, and observe to do it, that it may
be well with thee, and that ye may increase mightily as the
Lord God of thy fathers hath promised thee in the land that
floweth with milk and honey. Verse 4, Hear O Israel, the
Lord our God is one Lord, and of course that's the doctrine
of monotheism. Verse 5, Now listen to this I want you to
see this, And thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thine
heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy might. And
these words which I commanded this day shall be in thine
heart. And thou shalt teach them diligently, by the way
enthusiastically, fervently. And thou shalt teach them
diligently unto thy children, and shalt talk of them when
thou sittest in thine house, when thou walkest by the way,
when thou liest down, and when thou risest up. And thou
shalt bind them for a sign upon thine hand, and they
shall be as frontless between thine eyes. And thou shalt
write them upon the post of thy house, and on thy gates.
Father, we thank you now for the reading of your precious
Word, as your blessing now to the preaching of your Word
over the next several minutes. Now, God I need your help
tonight, so please help me. I am a needy preacher, and I
cannot do this except you help me and strengthen me this
evening. So, I pray for your hand upon me as I attempt to
rightly divide the Word of truth. So, God meet with us
now, speak to us afresh tonight, and we'll thank you
for it. In Jesus' name and for His sake, amen. Thank you,
may you be seated. When I look at this passage of
Scripture one of the things that I see is this, God does
not want us to be half-hearted Christians. Now, I'm going
to say this tonight as I get started, I see a lot of
half-heartedness many times amongst God's people. Now,
God wants us to worship Him with the whole heart. He
doesn't want us to be a half-hearted people. He
doesn't want to worship Him in a half-hearted way. And I
really love what he says here in this passage of
Scripture how wonderful it is, and how practical it is as
well when you read down through this. And it makes it
very personal when he says, "...and now shalt love the
Lord thy God with," what does it say? "...with all thine
heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy might." With
every fiber of being, everything that is within us
we ought to be loving the Lord. With all our heart, all
our soul, all our might. And that's what God says. And you
know the Christian that's not living that way is really
living a pretty miserable life. Wouldn't you think? But
yet we see an awful lot of half-hearted Christianity
today. Now, I like to go into churches sometimes just
watch people. By the way let me say this, I like airports.
I really do, I enjoy airports. Now, I don't like
traveling, but I will say that I enjoy airports. You know
why? Because I'm an embedded people watcher. So, I like to
watch people. So, I'll sit in airports and I'll watch
people. You ever do that? And you say, well what's up with
this guy? You know I mean you try to figure out what
they're all about. You can't really do that, but I mean
it's kind of fun to try to think about it. You know and
you sometimes see a guy going through the airport with a
fairly attractive woman and this guy is not looking so
good. And you wonder how did they ever get together?
You know? I mean, and that's maybe not fair, maybe that's
not kind, but you know it's just the way you are when
you're a people watcher. So, when I come into churches
sometimes I like to watch people. Now, certainly I'm
going to watch people when I'm preaching. Now, I'm
standing up here in the sacred desk where your pastor
stands all the time, and others that have preached
here as well and have been extended the courtesy, the
privilege, the honor of preaching from his pulpit. And
I'm going to tell you what, I can see everything going
going on out here from this perch? I can see it all. And you know sometimes things show
up on people's countenances that really sometimes disturb me. Now maybe they don't like my preaching
or something, I don't know what it is. And then there are the people who like to sleep
during the preaching. Now I know that sometimes you come from work, you're tired, or like
in our home church we have our morning prayer meeting at quarter to nine, we have the Sunday
school hour at 9.30, we have the church service at 10.30, it ends up at around noon, and then
we break and then we have lunch, and Filipinos man, gotta tell you, they eat the whole thing.
And so when you're done eating we come back in for the afternoon service at 1.30 and guess
what happens? Everybody wants to take a nap. Now I can see all that from the pulpit. And
I found this out. Some people can sleep with their eyes open. I mean I'm serious. I mean
you can go down there and go like this and you know it's like the elevator's at the top
but there's nobody home on that floor. I mean it's just one of those things. And so I watch
people all the time. One of the things I really watch for is I watch during the course of
the congregational singing, if I'm on the platform I like to watch people sing. And
you can really kind of tell sort of what's going on in a church. And you can really kind
of tell what's going on in an individual's life by the way they respond to the singing
of the old hymns of the faith. Dr. Ron Comfort told the preacher boys, in fact I was in the
class when he said it, he said this, he said, now listen, he said, you fellas, you young
fellas, and I was glad that he said that because I was the oldest guy in the classroom when
he said it, but he said, you young fellas, he said, when you go into your revival meetings,
your first revival meetings, one of the things you need to do is you need to sit on the platform
during your preliminaries on the first day of the revival meeting and watch the people
sing the old hymns of the faith and you can pretty much tell what kind of crowd you're
going to preach to that week. And I found that to be true. I found out that that's a
factual thing. You can watch people when they sing, I mean how can you sing? There is a
fountain filled with blood drawn from Emmanuel's veins. How can you sing and can it be? How
can you sing amazing grace? How can you sing anything that we sang tonight and not experience
the joy of the Lord? And some people just kind of, you know, we Baptists, we've learned
all the hymns, so we just kind of sing them by rote. You know, we just kind of go through
the motions. You know what I'm saying? I'm not saying everybody does that, so don't think
this is a blanket indictment. I'm not trying to paint this with too broad a brush. I'm
just saying that many times it's a litmus test. So you watch people and you say, wow,
there's something missing. Half heart of Christianity will steal the joy of the Lord right out of
your heart. You know, I've heard people say, well that brother over there, man he stole
my joy. Nobody can steal your joy. You've got to give it up. You've got to give it up.
No one can take your joy from you. You have got to surrender it. And if you're living
a half heart of Christian life, which is again a terrible way to live your life, if you're
living a half heart of Christian life, I'm going to tell you right now, you're not going
to enjoy being in the house of God. You're not going to enjoy singing the old hymns of
the faith. You're not going to enjoy the preaching of the Word of God. You're not going to enjoy
the fellowship of God's people because you're half hearted. Can you imagine serving the
Lord with a half a heart? I mean, I would not, I'll tell you this right now, there's
been times, I've only said this, I've only done this twice. In my ministry over the years,
especially when I pastored, I told our people this. I said, let me tell you what. I said,
if I know beyond a shadow of a doubt that I am not going into the pulpit filled with
the Spirit of God, I'm not preaching. So if I get up one night and I say I'm not preaching
tonight because I do not believe that I'm filled with the Spirit of God tonight for
whatever reason it is, and I've only had that happen twice in my ministry, and then we have
a prayer meeting. And, you know, I kind of felt half hearted sometimes. And God convicted
me of that. I don't want to be a half hearted preacher. I don't want to be a half hearted
soul winner. Amen? Hey, listen, I don't want to be a half hearted husband. I'm invested
in this relationship. I mean, we've been, we're going on 59 years. I mean, there's an
investment here. We've been husband and wife all these years, and I don't want to be a
half hearted husband. Because the Word of God says that I'm to love my wife as Christ
also loved the church and gave himself for it. That requires that I give my all to her.
And I have to, my heart should be in my marriage, and in my home, and in my family. So half
hearted Christianity is definitely a downer. And I see too much of it today. You know where
I saw some real wholehearted Christians was in the Philippines. Every time I, you go into
a Filipino church in the Philippine islands, there's 743 islands there. We're seeing independent
Baptist churches planted all over that country of 100 million people now. Bible college is
being started. Bible Institute is being started. Missionaries are being sent all over the world.
They say within the next five to seven years, it'll be the number one missionary sending
nation on the face of the earth. And I mentioned it the other day, you can find Filipinos everywhere.
Now I know it's part of their culture. They're just a happy people. Amen. They're just a
happy people. But I tell you what, when they come to church, man, they come to church all
in. And here's a message that I preached years ago, and I haven't preached it for a while.
Maybe they're all in or they're all out. There just doesn't seem to be anything in
the middle. You know, when people get lackadaisical, they get lethargic, they get apathetic, and
they just kind of go through the motions. And a guy told me one time, he said, oh, you
know what? I come to church, he said, I hear you preach, but I've heard all that before.
I said, oh really? He said, yeah, I've heard all that before. I know everything you said
today. The message you just preached, he said, I've heard that all, I don't know how many
times I've heard that. And I said, well, you need to hear it again. You didn't get
it the first time. You didn't get it the second or third time. And now you're telling me you've
heard all this before. Okay, well, if you've heard all this before, then my question for
you is what are you doing with it? What are you doing with it? Unto whom much is given
much is required. So listen, when God spreads a table for us in the wilderness, and we live
in a wilderness today, friends, you know that's through a spiritual vacuum in this country.
When God spreads a table before you in the wilderness, man, it's time to come and eat
and get everything you can get. And I'll tell you this, the worst preacher, people say,
well, you know what? I've heard some pretty bad preachers. Well, you know what? I don't,
I've never heard a bad preacher. If they're preaching the Word of God, they're preaching
the old book, man. I don't care if they're dynamic. I don't care if they're charismatic.
I don't care if they've got this great personality. If they're preaching the Word of God, then
praise the Lord. Amen. Jonathan Edwards in his day, that old pilgrim, that old Reformed
theology guy, which I'm not a Reformed theology type, but that old pilgrim, Jonathan Edwards,
when he preached that great message, Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God, and it actually
triggered the first great awakening in America, you know what? He didn't preach like I'm preaching
right now. He read his messages. He wrote them out meticulously and he read them. And
I heard someone say that a lot of those guys back in those days used to read those things
in almost just a dull tone. Now, but the thing is, it was full of the Word of God. So the
Word of God is powerful, sharper than any two-edged sword, able to divide and sunder
both bone and marrow. Let me tell you what, the Word of God is a powerful thing. So really
when it comes down, it's not all based upon the way the message is delivered, it's the
message itself and what it's based on. That should stimulate God's people. And they should
rejoice over it. You know, I mean, half-hearted Christians, they come to church in a half-hearted
manner and they're going to end up leaving the church with a half-hearted response. Well,
I think we should come to church excited. Don't you? Now, I'm not suggesting we come
into church like, you know, Bozo the Clown with a fake smile on her face and get Popeye
bug-eyed, foam in the mouth, roll down the aisles, bounce off the wall kind of happy.
I'm not talking about that. I'm talking about coming to church with a whole heart and being
ready to receive from God whatever it is He has for us. Amen? I'll tell you what, I want
to be a whole-hearted Christian. I want to be all in. I want to be totally invested.
I want to be completely and totally absorbed with my Christian life.
Let's go back to the book of Revelation. I'm going to move along quickly tonight, so stick
with me if you will please. Try not to go too off-long this evening, but I do want to
share this. I want to go to Revelation chapter 3. Is everybody with me? Revelation chapter
3 and verse 4. Now, I could actually go through all seven churches of Asia. And of course
this was Asia Minor where these churches were located in what's now known today as Turkey.
And of course Laodicea was the last of the seven churches. And of course we know if you
even look at it geographically the churches were organized in somewhat of a circle. And
the Bible says that the Lord Jesus at one point was standing in the midst of the seven
churches, the seven golden candlesticks. We'll talk about that in a little bit in a minute.
But I want you to look at Revelation chapter 3 and verse 14. And we look at the church
of Laodicea and I'm going to read down through this very quickly and then make some comments
along the way. By the way, Laodicea was an interesting place. I did a little bit of study
on the city of Laodicea and it was an interesting city. It was built by Antiochus II and he
named it after his wife, interesting name, her name was Laodice. And he named it after
It was located on the River Ulysses and it's still located there obviously today in what
is now today Turkey.
I wrote this down so I didn't forget it.
It was rich in Greek culture, it was the center of business, the center of science, the center
of millinery, and the center of medicine.
And it had a great reputation.
It was a wealthy city.
It was a wealthy place.
And by the way, there's evidence that there were, besides the church at Laodicea, there's
evidence there was one other there as well.
If you go there today, you can see the ruins of both churches.
Those churches don't exist today, but you can see the ruins of both churches.
And so this church at Laodicea was a very wealthy, very prosperous church at one time.
But look at this.
In Revelation chapter 3 and verse 14, I begin reading here.
And under the angel Angelos, this was the pastor of the church, that's what it's speaking
of, of the Laodiceans' rite.
These things saith the Amen.
Now, of course, we know the Amen is Jesus.
Amen?
These things saith the Amen, the faithful and true witness, the beginning of the creation
of God.
Now, look at verse 15.
He says this.
He said, I know thy works.
I know thy works.
Now, that ought to either bring consolation or conviction.
Now, I'm going to say this.
As I get into this text here, it's not a very long text, but as I get into it and share
some things along the way, I want you to know this tonight.
God knows our works.
He knows what we're doing and why we're doing it.
What motivates us, what causes us to do what we do, why we do what we do.
I ask people this all the time.
Why do you do what you do?
I've seen people sing in the choir, for example, and I'll ask them sometimes, I mean, I just
do this.
I kind of probe once in a while.
I kind of have a tendency to meddle a little bit.
And sometimes when I suspect something's not quite right with somebody that's in the choir
or any other area of ministry, I might ask them, why are you in the choir?
Why do you want to sing in the choir?
Amen.
Well, that's a good answer right there.
Why do you want to be part of the music program in the church?
You know?
Well, they give a lot of different answers.
And just like he just got done saying, our brother said, because I love singing, amen.
And he loves singing because he loves Jesus.
It should be for him.
I think that people should do what they do with a whole heart.
Not half-hearted, just going through the motions.
Okay.
Pastor says, brother, can you help me with something this week?
In fact, would you drive a Sunday school bus for me?
Because I know you have a class B license and we need a driver this week.
Okay.
I really don't like to drive buses anymore.
I kind of gave that up.
Okay.
And why do they complain and moan about it?
Well, why?
Because they're half-hearted.
When they say, hey, pastor, great.
I'll be glad to do that.
I'll be glad to do it.
Oh, would you sing this?
You have people in the church that can sing.
We just heard some great singing tonight, amen?
And so you say, now, brothers, would you sing a special this Sunday?
No, if I have to.
Well, that's really half-hearted, isn't it?
It's really what it is.
And that's not the way that we should respond.
When God asks us to do something, we should be in all in and we should do it with a whole
heart.
I want to serve God with a whole heart, don't you?
What he couldn't do this week, I couldn't do what I'm doing.
Whatever it is God's called you to do, you couldn't do it if you weren't doing it with
a whole heart.
Your heart would not be in it.
You've heard that said many times.
Well, my heart's not in it.
Well, how come?
You know, I had a fellow tell me one time, well, I think I'm going to retire from the
ministry.
Oh, I said, is that right?
He said, yeah.
I said, well, man, you're only 55 years old.
Why are you going to retire from the ministry?
Well, he said, my heart's not just in it anymore.
And I thought, now, hold on a minute.
Did God call you to the preaching ministry?
Did God give you the gift of pastor, evangelist, teacher?
Did God give you that gift?
The gifts and the calling of God are without repentance.
Well, God didn't change his mind, but obviously you have.
And now you're telling me your heart's no longer in it.
I'm going to tell you what, that's not a good answer.
Was your heart in it when you started preaching 25 years ago?
Well, yeah, back then it seems like my heart was in it.
And I said, okay, well, then how come it's not in it today?
I mean, you're 55 years old.
You got some good years left in you.
You ought to keep on preaching.
Amen.
Now, if he doesn't want to preach and he doesn't have the heart to preach for whatever reason,
and I think there's something wrong with that, then maybe you ought to go get a job.
Because he'll cause damage.
So this thing of being half-hearted, or really having like, this guy, I have no heart at
all in this thing.
I mean, that's just a dangerous proposition.
So it says, under the angel of the church that led us to your right, these things said,
the amen, the faith, and the true witness, the beginning of the creation of God, he said,
I know thy works, that thou art neither cold nor hot.
I would thou were cold or hot, so then because thou art lukewarm, uh-oh, thou, I want you
to see that word, lukewarm.
That's an interesting word, isn't it?
That word, lukewarm, comes from the Greek word, ameo, ameo.
So what it means is this, the word lukewarm in the Greek, the word ameo means this, and
by the way, it can also mean from, it also can come from this word, kleoros, and it
means half-hearted, tepid, or fluctuating, no zeal, lost appetite.
He says, he said this, he said, I know thy works, that thou art neither cold nor hot.
I would that thou were cold or hot, so because thou art lukewarm and neither cold nor hot,
I will spew thee out of my mouth.
It's like, it's like in a medic, he said, listen, because you're lukewarm and you're
not on fire, I'd rather have you, I'd rather have a cold or hot.
Because you're lukewarm, I'll spew you out of my mouth, it makes me sick.
Lukewarm Christianity.
So kleoros, that's a Greek word, means half-hearted, tepid, fluctuating, no zeal, lost appetite.
To lose one's appetite for things of God really, to me, is a disaster.
It really is.
So he said, so then because thou art lukewarm and neither cold nor hot, I will spew thee
out of my mouth.
So lukewarm, kleoros, and spew, along with the word lukewarm, also, it comes from a Greek
word, it just makes me sick, he said.
Because thou sayest I am rich and increased with goods, and have need of nothing, and
knowest not that thou art wretched and miserable and poor and blind and naked.
He said, Dave, we don't need anything, man.
We got this thing down pat, we know how to do ministry, we don't need you in it either.
He said, no, you're poor, you're blind, you're wretched, you're naked.
He said, I counsel you to buy me gold, trident and fire, that thou mayest be rich, and white
raiment that thou mayest be clothed, that the shame of thy nakedness do not appear,
to anoint thine eyes with eye salve that thou mayest see.
I think that's interesting because the city of Laodicea was known for its eye salve.
It was famous for its school of medicine.
And so he uses that as an illustration.
But the eye salve they needed was not the eye salve that came from the apothecary, it
was the eye salve of the Word of God.
You people need to get your focus back where it belongs.
You got an eyesight problem, you need to get your eyes back on Jesus.
Get your eyes off Jesus and you're going to have a problem with half-heartedness.
So I counsel you to buy me gold, trident and fire, that thou mayest be rich, and white
raiment that thou mayest be clothed, and that the shame of thy nakedness do not appear,
to anoint thine eyes with eye salve that thou mayest see.
He said, as many as I love, I rebuke and chasten.
Be zealous therefore and repent.
And I like that word zealous.
That's a good word.
Amen.
That's a good Bible word.
And by the way, we see over in Titus chapter 2 where the Bible says that we who are saved
by the grace of God ought to be zealous of good works.
We ought to be zealous.
We ought to be excited about this thing of serving God.
I don't know about you, but I'm excited about being here in church tonight.
I've already enjoyed myself.
I really have.
I can go, hey, I'll tell you what, when you come to church meetings like this, whether
it be Sunday school or Sunday morning service, Sunday evening service, or special meetings
like we're having this week, boy, that ought to be, that ought to be a blessing.
That ought to be a joy.
That ought to send you out of here with a little bit of a bounce in your step.
Boy, I got to be with God's people tonight.
I got to be in church tonight.
You know, it ought to promote zeal.
I've said this all the time.
I said, man, we just need some people to get on fire for God.
Man, if people get on fire for God and start serving the Lord all out, we could see a lot
of things happen in our churches today.
We had a program years ago, I can remember it started with Sword of the Lord.
I don't remember who started it, but they had a program called Win One, Disciple One
every year.
So if you would win one person, disciple that person every year, one a year, the church
would double its size within one year.
If people had a zeal for souls.
If people had a zeal for winning people to Christ.
They'd be zealous of good works.
Amen?
I think that's a, it's just a joy to be zealous.
I mean, think about the opposite.
You know, being, you know, kind of dead, you know.
Several years ago, there was a pastor who began to realize that his church was just
kind of spiritually sagging.
It was in really bad shape.
And he knew they needed a revival.
And he had preached his heart out and he wasn't altogether sure exactly what it was going
to take to get there.
attention. So one Sunday morning he came into church and in his
morning message he said, oh, by the way I want to announce
we're going to have a funeral tonight. And everybody thought
a funeral tonight? Yeah, the evening service we have a
funeral tonight so everybody will be here. And so everybody
left the church wondering who was the dead person? Who was
the funeral? Who were they going to have a funeral for? So
word got out all over town and no one knew who the deceased
individual was and so they decided that we better come and
see who it is. So the whole town showed up. It was standing
room only in the church house. So when they came in the church
house there was a casket down here. Amen? Some of you may
already get this one. There's a casket down here. But the thing
that was amazing about it is that the lid of the casket it
was turned around backwards so you were looking at the lid of
the casket which was open. Ordinarily it would be the other
way around so that when you filed past the casket you would
see the deceased. But he turned it around and so the casket
sitting in the middle of the aisle just like this and the
lid is up, the top is up on it and he said, now that
everybody is here? He said, I want you all to come and just
file past the casket and view the deceased. And so they all
got up and they said, wow we're going to find out who this is
now. And as they filed past the casket they looked into it and
there was a mirror on the bottom of it. There was a mirror
on the bottom of it. And everybody saw themselves in the
reflection. And he said this, he said, you are the deceased.
The church is dead and it needs to be revived. It needs to live
again. It needs to be resurrected back to what it once
was. And the zeal of the Lord needs to be back in the house
of God. Now that was a pretty radical way of getting their
attention, but it got their attention. And again I'm not
saying that about this church tonight, I'm just saying this
in a general statement that really in many churches today
we just need an awakening. We just need to be awakened. And
we need to get back to the part to where we're not living a
halfway Christian life. We're living all out for the Lord. So
I thought that was a pretty good illustration. And of
course here as we look further on the church at Laodicea we
see what ends up happening here. I'll just very quickly read
this in verse 19 it says, "'As many as I love I rebuke and
chasten.'" I like that. Somebody said, well you know
what we're living in Laodicea in the period of the church
age. Well yeah, but we can still repent and get right with
God. Amen. "'As many as I love I rebuke and chasten.'" And it
said, "'Be zealous and repent. Behold I stand at the door and
knock.'" That's an amazing thing. "'If any man hear my
voice and open the door I will come in unto him and will sup
with him and he with me.'" And of course we use that in Saul
winning. But what Jesus is saying here is, hey listen you
folks have locked me out of my church I want back in again.
There he is knocking on the door, let me back in. He wants
back into his own church again. It's amazing. Psalm 86 and
verse 12, "'I will praise the Lord my God with all my heart
and I will glorify thy name forevermore.'" Joshua 22, 5,
"'But take diligent he to do the commandment and the law
which Moses, the servant of the Lord, charged you to love
the Lord your God and to walk in all His ways and to keep
His commandments and to cleave unto Him and serve Him with
all your heart and with all your soul.'" 1 Samuel 12, 24,
"'Only fear the Lord and serve Him in truth with all your
heart for consider how great things He hath done for you.'"
Psalm 91, "'I will praise thee O Lord with my whole heart I
will show forth all thy marvelous works.'" Psalm 111,
verse 1, "'Praise ye the Lord. I will praise the Lord with
my whole heart in the assembly of the upright and in the
congregation.'" Psalm 119, 2, "'Blessed are they that keep
His testimonies and seek Him with the whole heart.'" Psalm
119, 10, "'With my whole heart have I sought thee O let me
not wander from thy commandments.'" Psalm 119, 69,
"'They are proud they have forged a lie against me but I
will keep thy precepts with my whole heart.'" Psalm 138,
verses 1 and 2, "'I will praise thee with my whole heart
before the gods will I sing praise unto thee. I will
worship toward the Holy Temple and praise thy name for thy
loving kindness and for thy truth for thou hast magnified
thy word above all thy name.'" And what of the
backslidden? What about the backslidden? Isaiah 1, verses
4 and 5, "'The vision of Isaiah the son of Amoz which
he saw concerning Judah and Jerusalem in the days of
Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, Hezekiah kings of Judah.'" Ah, sinful
nation of people laden with iniquity and the seed of
evildoers, children that are corruptors. "'They have
forsaken the Lord, they have provoked the Holy One of
Israel and in anger they are gone away backward. Why should
you be stricken anymore? Will you revolt more and more? The
whole head is sick and the whole heart faint.'" See that's
that principle that's the whole idea of half-heartedness.
Jeremiah chapter 3 and verse 10, "'And yet for all her
treacherous sister Judah hath not turned unto me with her
whole heart, but faintedly saith the Lord.'" So when
people are backslidden this is what they do, they no
longer serve God with the whole heart. But Jeremiah 29
verses 11-13 says this, "'For I know the thoughts that I
think toward you, saith the Lord, thoughts of peace and
not of evil, to give you an expected end. Then shall you
call upon me, and ye shall go and pray unto me, and I will
hearken unto you. And ye shall seek me and find me, when
ye shall search for me with all your heart.'" Amen. When
you search for me with all your heart. What a wonderful
passage of Scripture that is. That's the cure by the way for
half-heartedness is searching God with your whole heart.
Pastor Stephen Becker of Regency Baptist Church in the
Sacramento, California where he wrote this, and I preached
for him not too long ago. He said this, he wrote this in a
devotional he wrote for his church. He said, "'If you had
to choose between a Christian that was cold and hardened
towards the Lord, one that was a middle of the road
Christian, which one would you choose?' Our logic would
certainly think that coming to church sometimes instead of
never coming is at least doing some good, right? Well I
believe half-hearted Christianity is a battle of
our era. This lukewarm lifestyle does more harm to
the faith than those who have completely turned away from
the Lord. Some good is better than none, I agree. But what
kind of an impact will this way of living make on future
generations? That's a pregnant thought. King Amaziah was a
half-hearted follower of the Lord. In 2 Chronicles 25.2 it
reads this, "'And he did that which was right in the sight
of the Lord, but not with a perfect heart. He did some
good, but he certainly wasn't sold out on fire, dedicated
and fervent in his service. Half is better than none, but
in terms of what kind of future influence this will make it
is detrimental.' There is a story of a man who wanted to
sell his house for $2,000, you can't imagine a house for
$2,000. Another man wanted very badly to buy it but
couldn't afford it. After much bargaining the owner agreed to
sell the house for half the original price with a catch
that he would retain ownership of one small nail protruding
from just over the door." I read that and I thought,
what? After many years the original owner wanted the
house back, but the new owner was unwilling to sell. So,
the first owner went out, found the carcass of a dead
dog and hung it from the single nail he still owned.
Soon the house became unlivable and the family was
forced to sell the house to the owner of the nail on his
terms. The moral of the story is this, give the devil just
one small part of your life and he will make it impossible
for Christ's presence to live there. Huh? It's simple but
profound. So, the truth is this, there is no such thing
as a half-hearted Christian. You're either in or you're
out. Pastor Becker says, surrender yourself fully to
the Lord and leave no part behind. Now that's important
to leave no part behind. What part of us do we leave
behind? You know, God doesn't want us to leave any part
behind. He wants us to be in service to Him with all heart.
And to be lukewarm is to be half-hearted. And Jesus said,
a half-hearted Christianity makes me sick. Makes him sick
of heart. It breaks his heart when he sees that we are only
living half way. No such thing as a half-way Christian. You
know, I mean that's why I hear people say, well, you know
God is kind of a half-way Christian. Listen, you're
either going to serve Him or you aren't. You're not going
to serve Him and you're not walking the way you should.
Then the Bible says you're backslidden. Half-hearted
Christianity is very damaging and detrimental to the cause
of Christ. By the way, our children need to see that
we're all in. We want our children to have a holy zeal
for the things of God. We want them to want to live for
Jesus. If they don't see us do it then why would you be
surprised when they don't do it? They need to see the
sincerity of our Christianity, the zeal, the joy, the
happiness, the excitement, the enthusiasm. Not about you
but I'm just excited about being saved. You know, being
saved to me that's an exciting thing.
I mean, you remember when you got saved?
You remember?
You remember how excited you were?
Someone said to me one time, oh, you Christians miss all the fun.
I said, no, the only thing I'm going to miss is going to hell.
I don't have to go to hell.
Amen?
In fact, I'm not going to hell.
Now that right there is enough to make you happy and joyful.
People just, if someone said, well, you know what, brother, my son, it seems like people
get saved and after about 18 months to two years, it kind of just wears off and it gets
just, you know, just becomes the norm.
Should never be that way.
The longer you live, the more excited you should be.
You know?
The more that whole enthusiasm ought to be there, really should be.
We don't want to be half hearted.
Half hearted Christianity does not please the Lord.
So David mentioned several times, I want to serve the Lord and live for him with a whole
heart, with a whole heart, a whole heart.
I trust that God has used his word tonight to speak to you about this as he's spoken
to me today.
Let's all stand with our heads bowed and eyes closed tonight.
With every head bowed and every eye closed tonight, as our sister comes to play the instrument,
how's God spoken to you?
Thou shalt love.