Every tongue is gonna confess, every knee is gonna bow,
and it's not a matter of if, it's a matter of when,
and when makes all the difference, amen?
And what a blessing, thank you for those large group there
that sang this morning, they've been working on that.
I've had the opportunity to hear it several times
on Sunday evening during practice, and just a blessing.
And so we thank the Lord.
Luke chapter number two this morning,
Luke chapter number two, and we're gonna look at
a part of this particular passage of Scripture
here this morning, and then we're going to look
at a part of it this afternoon.
And we're gonna look at the beginning this afternoon,
and we're gonna look at the section here,
really in the middle this morning,
and look forward to what God has in store for us.
It's certainly good to be in the Lord's house,
and thankful to know Him as my personal Lord and Savior,
knowing that heaven is my home.
And if you're here this morning
and you don't know for sure that heaven is your home,
could I encourage you, the greatest gift
is the gift of eternal life,
and Jesus Christ paid for it with His precious blood.
We're gonna look at some of that this morning,
and He offers that gift to you,
and all you have to do is accept it, and I'm thankful.
If you look in the Scriptures here,
beginning in verse number eight of Luke chapter number two,
the Bible says this,
and there were in the same country shepherds
abiding in the field,
keeping watch over their flock by night.
And lo, the angel of the Lord came upon them,
and the glory of the Lord shone round about them,
and they were sore afraid.
In verse 10, the Bible says,
the angel said unto them,
fear not, for behold,
I bring you good tidings of great joy,
what shall be to all people.
For unto you is born this day
in the city of David a Savior,
which is Christ the Lord.
And this shall be a sign unto you.
You shall find the babe wrapped in swaddling clothes,
lying in a manger.
And suddenly there was with the angel
a multitude of the heavenly hosts,
praising God and saying,
glory to God in the highest,
and on earth peace, goodwill toward men.
And it came to pass as the angels
were gone away from them into heaven,
the shepherds said one to another,
let us now go even unto Bethlehem
and see this thing which has come to pass,
which the Lord hath made known unto us.
As you think about this time of year
and we celebrate the incarnation
of the Lord Jesus Christ,
the birth when God became man.
He never stopped being God.
He is the God-man.
He's 100% God and 100% man,
but he had to take on flesh.
Why?
So that he could die for us.
And we find that during this particular time of year,
we celebrate the incarnation.
We refer to it as Christmas.
And we don't know, of course,
the exact time of Christ's birth.
There's much debate with regard to the timing.
Most likely it probably was not December 25th,
but we know that he was born.
And we know that he came into the world
and we'll look at several portions
of scripture this morning.
But as we look at this familiar text
in Luke chapter number two,
I've often thought about these shepherds.
And you think about these shepherds
and the announcement that they received of Christ's birth
as we've just read it.
And I often think in my mind of these men
as they stood there, as they watched over their flock,
the Bible says by night,
I think that probably the night started
like any other night.
This was their profession.
This was something that they did.
This was something that they lived.
Perhaps some of them, even as young boys,
would accompany their fathers and they would be there.
And this was somewhat of a routine, if you will.
It was what they did.
It was what they were, who they were.
And that night started probably like no other night,
but I want you to know, as we've just read,
that things changed quickly.
And this night became like no other night ever was
or ever would be.
And the reality is that I believe that these shepherds,
even as you look at the end of the passage
in verse number 20,
the Bible says that the shepherds return,
notice glorifying and praising God
for all the things that they had heard and seen
as it was told unto them.
I think this was probably something
they talked about quite a bit.
I think it was something that stood out to them
as being a subject of discussion.
Can I tell you what happened one night when I was out there?
You understand, you're tracking with me this morning.
And this night was like no other night.
And we begin to look at this portion of Scripture
and it announces for us the birth of our Messiah.
And as you continue through the passage,
you read a number of things,
but I wanna draw your attention to verse number 10,
where the Bible says that the angel said unto them,
fear not.
Notice it says, for behold,
I bring you good tidings of great joy,
which shall be to all people.
I wanna preach a message
that I've simply entitled this morning,
good tidings of great joy.
I wanna focus on that word great
just for a few moments this morning.
As we begin to understand the truth of God's word
and how blessed we are to have a Bible
and understanding that in this time in our society,
in our culture,
we find that there's many things that are going on
and our culture has tried to really inundate us
with all sorts of distractions
during this period of time on our calendar year.
But I want you to understand the greatness
of what we're celebrating.
Now, Jesus wasn't born to stay in a manger.
Jesus wasn't born to stay an infant.
He was born to die.
He was born to grow up and to begin his public ministry
to prove that he was indeed Messiah,
that he would heal
and he would live a perfect and sinless life
and then he would go to that cross.
But to begin to think about all the distractions today,
I would figure that if you were to talk
to a variety of people this afternoon,
tomorrow or Tuesday,
if you still have some last minute shopping to do
and Amazon can't deliver on time,
you'll find yourself at the Walmart
or at the whatever shopping center
and you could just kind of take a survey.
What is Christmas all about?
And I would venture to say that most people
that you would chat with would have no idea
the true meaning of this holiday Christmas.
And I'm thankful that God's given to us a Bible
and that we can understand
the significance of the incarnation.
If you're taking notes this morning,
I'll focus on that great, the word there,
good tidings of great joy.
Notice with me the great promise of Christ's birth.
The great promise of Christ's birth.
We have to go all the way back to the book of Genesis.
Turn back, if you will, to Genesis chapter number three
and I want you to notice with me
that in Genesis chapter three,
we won't take time to develop all of it
but it's the record that God gives us
when sin entered into the world.
Mankind disobeyed, Adam and Eve
were in a perfect environment
and Eve took of that fruit of the tree.
She was deceived by the serpent.
And then Adam partook of,
and the Bible tells us that sin entered into the world
at that very moment in human history.
In fact, the writer of the book of Hebrews,
or excuse me, the book of Romans, the apostle Paul,
he references directly back to this passage of scripture,
how that by one man, sin entered into the world.
And we find that in Genesis chapter three,
when God confronts Adam and Eve
about this disobedience, about this sin,
they hide themselves, they tried to cover themselves
but of course we know that their covering of fig leaves
was not sufficient and God comes into the garden
and begins to talk with them.
And throughout the passage,
there's many things that you could learn
but I want you to notice in verse number 15
of Genesis chapter three, the Bible says,
and I will put enmity between thee and the woman,
between thy seed and her seed,
it shall bruise thy head and thou shall bruise his heel.
This is the very first mention
with regard to the promise of Messiah.
The reality that Jesus Christ would come
to this sin-cursed world and he would die in your place
and in my place to pay for the sin of humanity.
And we find that as you look here
at Genesis chapter three in verse 15
and you see this great declaration
of what God says that he will do,
he does not provide a particular timing in this passage.
We find that if you read the book of Daniel
and the prophecy of Daniel in the ninth chapter,
that you can determine the timing of the arrival of Messiah
but I want you to understand
that as you read the New Testament,
the book of Galatians and we're gonna turn
to a number of passages.
You don't need to turn to all of them this morning.
I'll read them for you.
But Galatians chapter number four,
I love how the word of God states this truth.
It says in verse number four,
but when the fullness of the time was come.
And I've always taken great comfort in those words
to begin Galatians four in verse four,
because what God is revealing to us is right on time.
When the fullness of time was come.
Listen, everything that our God does is right on time.
We talk about a second coming
and I'm looking forward to the return
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And no man knoweth the hour.
There's no prophecy regarding the second coming
that will allow you to pinpoint it
the way there was with the first coming.
But we do understand that he's coming
and what a glorious truth that is.
And he's gonna come right on time.
Amen, just as he came right on time the first time,
he's gonna come right on time the second time
and we better be ready for his return.
And the Bible says,
but when the fullness of time was come,
notice God sent forth his son,
made of a woman, made under the law.
For what purpose?
And we'll look at this later in the message
and verse number five,
to redeem them that were under the law,
that we might receive the adoption of sons.
I'm so thankful for the great promise
that we read in Genesis three.
And then you look at the truth in Galatians four
and see that at that right time,
when the fullness of time was come,
God sent forth his son.
Aren't you thankful this morning for the truth?
It is absolute truth.
It is human, excuse me,
it's historical evidence proof that Jesus was born.
And I'm so thankful that he came
and it was exactly on time.
Isaiah seven says this,
as you consider,
continue to think about the great promise of Christ's birth
and you read in the book of Isaiah,
we'll actually look in chapter seven
and also in chapter number nine
and understand this great proclamation that is made
with regard to the birth of Messiah.
And then we'll look at the fulfillment in the New Testament.
But in Isaiah chapter seven,
the Bible says this in verse number 14,
therefore, the Lord himself shall give you a sign.
Behold, a virgin shall conceive and bear a son
and shall call his name Emmanuel.
Isn't that precious?
Some of the modern versions today change that word virgin
for a young maid.
Can I tell you this morning that a virgin and a young maid
are not the same thing?
Amen.
Why is the virgin birth so important?
Because it was necessary that he have no sin nature.
It's a critical truth of God's word.
And here we find that this would be a sign
and it says that,
and shall call his name Emmanuel.
Notice in chapter nine,
before we run to the New Testament,
in Isaiah chapter nine,
in verse number six,
the Bible says this,
for unto us a child is born,
unto us a son is given
and the government shall be upon his shoulder
and his name shall be called Wonderful,
Counselor, the Mighty God,
the Everlasting Father,
the Prince of Peace.
Of the increase of his government and peace,
there shall be no end.
Upon the throne of David and upon his kingdom to order it
and to establish it with judgment
and with justice from henceforth even forever,
the zeal of the Lord of hosts will perform this.
The promise of the fulfillment of the Davidic covenant
is in view in verse number seven.
And one day Jesus Christ,
when he returns after the rapture
in the seven year tribulation,
there's going to be a millennial reign
and Jesus Christ himself is going to rule and reign
for a thousand years,
fulfilling the prophecy of the Davidic covenant.
And I'm thankful for that.
You notice in the book of Matthew,
again, the great promise of Christ's birth
and you think about these wonderful declarations
in the Old Testament,
but then you see their fulfillment in the New Testament,
Matthew chapter number one.
And it's a familiar passage,
one in which often is referenced
during the Christmas season.
But in Matthew chapter number one,
when we think specifically of these prophecies
of Isaiah seven and Isaiah nine,
we find in Matthew chapter number one,
the Bible says this in verse number 23,
behold, a virgin shall be with child
and shall bring forth a son
and they shall call his name Emmanuel.
Notice which being interpreted is God with us.
Now we find that in verse number 22,
the Bible says now all this was done
that it might be fulfilled,
which was spoken to the Lord by the prophet.
And this was the announcement of the birth of Christ
and Joseph in verse 24,
the Bible says then Joseph being raised from sleep
did as the angel of the Lord had bidden him
and took unto him his wife
and knew her not till she had brought forth
her firstborn son and he called his name Jesus.
Wonderful.
In Luke chapter number one,
in verses 31 through 33,
we read here of the fulfillment
of what we had read there in Isaiah chapter number nine.
In Luke chapter number one,
we find the announcement with regard to the birth
of not only the Messiah,
but the birth of John the Baptist is recorded here.
We do see the announcement and then of course his birth.
We see in chapter two, as we've read just a moment ago,
the birth of Christ,
but I want you to notice in Luke chapter number one,
during this announcement that is given
at the beginning in verse number 31,
the Bible repeats again,
and behold, thou shalt conceive in thy womb.
The angel of the Lord, we read verse 30,
and the angel said unto her,
fear not Mary, for thou hast found favor with God.
And behold, thou shalt conceive in thy womb
and bring forth a son and shall call his name Jesus.
He shall be great.
Isn't he so great?
It says, and shall be called the son of the highest.
And the Lord God shall give unto him the throne
of his father, David,
and he shall reign over the house of Jacob forever.
And of his kingdom, there shall be no end.
In the book of Micah chapter number five,
God specifically provides a promise.
When we think about the great promise of Christ's birth,
we read in Micah chapter number five,
the place where Christ would be born.
If you read the book of Matthew,
you'll find, and we'll look at that in just a moment,
how that the heritage is like,
hey, where is this one that's to be born?
And you see the prophecy here in Micah five.
But in Micah chapter five, notice in verse number two,
but thou Bethlehem Ephrata,
though thou be little among the thousands of Judah,
yet out of thee shall he come forth unto me
that is to be ruler in Israel,
whose goings forth have been from old, from everlasting.
And in Matthew chapter two,
we find that there as the Bible records for us,
those wise men that arrived to Jerusalem,
and they asked this question,
where is he that is born King of the Jews?
And they came to Jerusalem, they're seeking,
and of course this caused a great ruckus there in Jerusalem
and there's all sorts of things that took place
and Herod, the king, he's troubled
according to verse number three
and all Jerusalem with him.
But then notice in verse number four of Matthew two,
the Bible says, and when he had gathered
all the chief priests and scribes of the people together,
let me explain to you just for a moment,
in verse number four, what Herod does
is he gathers together all of the religious leaders
of the Jews.
These religious leaders, these Jewish religious leaders,
they would be very familiar
with the Old Testament, experts of the Old Testament.
And we find that he gathers them together
and notice at the end of verse number four,
he demanded of them where Christ should be born.
The Bible says in verse number five,
and they said unto him in Bethlehem of Judea,
for thus it is written by the prophet.
Isn't it sad that they knew the prophecy,
but they weren't looking for the Messiah.
They knew the prophecy,
And in verse number six, they quote from Micah five,
and thou Bethlehem in the land of Judah,
art not the least among the princes of Judah,
for out of thee shall come a governor
that shall rule my people Israel.
So this morning, when we think about
these good tidings of great joy,
I want you to notice with me
the great promise of Christ's birth.
By the way, every promise of God
is sure, we can stand on the promises, amen.
And I'm so thankful that our God cannot lie.
He's given to us countless promises.
As we look through the scriptures
and we can claim them and we can embrace them
and we can find that they will come to pass.
Not only do we notice the great promise of Christ's birth,
but number two, notice with me
the great proclamation at Christ's birth.
This was read earlier in Luke chapter number two,
but let me just very quickly.
make a couple of comments from Luke chapter number two,
as we think about this great proclamation
that was made at Christ's birth.
There was a promise of Christ's birth,
but now there's this great proclamation.
It's the angel that makes the proclamation
according to chapter number two in verse number 10.
The Bible says, and the angel said unto them.
And I think about this scene again,
as you begin to wrap your mind around these verses
of scripture that I read by way of introduction this morning
and in your mind's eye,
I hope that you can see the scene of what's unfolding.
And again, they're out there like any other night,
but there's this great stirring that takes place.
And we find that the Bible tells us
that an angel speaks to them.
Notice what the angel proclaimed
and the good tidings of great joy
that are referenced in verse number 10.
What is that?
What is the greeting?
Well, it's in verse number 11,
the proclamation for unto you is born this day
in the city of David, a savior, which is Christ the Lord.
I want you to understand that this proclamation
was made to these shepherds.
I don't know how many of them were there
and neither do you.
It's plural, so it was more than one.
We don't know how many shepherds were there,
but however many were there,
they received this glorious, this great proclamation
of the birth of Christ.
Can you imagine being the ones,
however many of them there were that God saw fit
to allow that angel to appear to them
to deliver that message?
But I want you to understand something very important
in verse number 10.
The Bible says, for behold,
I bring you good tidings of great joy,
which shall be, what's it say, to all people.
This great proclamation at Christ's birth
that we find was given by the angel to the shepherds.
Yes, it was given to them,
but it was not to be kept to themselves.
This was a message that was given to them,
but it was a message that was for all people.
Isn't that a wonderful truth?
I think about the glorious gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ
and I was in my office this morning praying
and just thanking God for having a Bible
and for someone that shared the gospel with me
and knowing the Lord Jesus Christ is my personal savior.
And as I was rejoicing and just praising God
for my own salvation,
I was reminded that God saved us
and God gave us the gospel not to keep it to ourselves,
but to proclaim it to all people.
These shepherds, they were given this great proclamation.
They were the original recipients, if you will,
of those that were on that hillside that night
that heard this great proclamation by this angel.
We find that there was a sign that was given
according to verse number 12,
and this shall be a sign unto you,
ye shall find the babe wrapped in swaddling clothes
lying in a manger.
And it's interesting
because when you see the scene,
it almost seems to me as you read the text of Scripture,
that almost as quickly as these angels arrived,
this heavenly host arrives,
almost as quickly as they come, they depart.
For the Bible says in verse number 15,
and it came to pass as the angels were gone away
from them into heaven.
I mean, the angels appeared, there's this great host
and we find that the heavenly host,
notice in verse number 13, the Bible says,
and suddenly there was with the angel
a multitude of the heavenly host praising God
and saying glory to God in the highest
and on earth, peace, goodwill toward men.
But as soon as that proclamation
and that praising in verse 13 and 14 was completed,
the host is gone.
And the shepherds, as they're standing there,
they say one to another.
You ever have a conversation with someone?
I'd love to think about the situation here in the scene
and they say one to another,
let us now go even unto Bethlehem.
You know what they expected?
They expected to find exactly what the angel
had proclaimed to them, amen.
I mean, they had expectation.
I think they had excitement.
I think that as they left that field, wherever they were,
they left with haste and they left with excitement
and they left with expectation.
I believe they had within their hearts
every measure of confidence that they would find the Messiah
just as the angel had proclaimed.
The Bible tells us that they said,
let us now go even unto Bethlehem
and see this thing which has come to pass,
which the Lord hath made known unto us.
It says that they came with haste
and found Mary and Joseph and the babe lying in a manger.
Notice verse 17, and when they had seen it,
it says, they made known abroad the saying
which was told them concerning this child
and all they that heard it wondered at those things
which were told them by the shepherds.
But Mary kept all these things and pondered them
in her heart and the shepherds returned glorifying
and praising God for all the things that they had heard
and seen as it was told unto them.
We see the great promise.
We see the great proclamation.
For the rest of our time this morning,
I wanna focus on our third thought this morning,
the great purpose of Christ's birth.
I've alluded to it throughout the message
already this morning.
As you think about the purpose,
why is it that the Lord Jesus Christ
had to leave the throne room of heaven?
In John chapter number 17,
the Bible tells us of the glory that he had in heaven.
The Bible reveals to us as John is speaking
about the Lamb of God,
he talks about the one that is after him
is preferred above him.
And you begin to understand this morning
that the great purpose of Christ's birth.
In Matthew chapter one,
the Bible tells us something extremely important.
We read the latter part of the text earlier,
but I wanna draw your attention
specifically to verse number 21.
As we consider this morning,
the great purpose of Christ's birth.
Why was Jesus born?
In Matthew one in verse 21,
the Bible says,
and she shall bring forth a son
and thou shalt call his name Jesus.
Then notice this,
for he shall save his people from their sins.
Remember we looked at Genesis chapter three earlier
in the message
and we spoke about the great promise
and that very first reference that God gives
of the first promise that Messiah would come.
And we find that that promise is given
on the heels of sin entering into the world.
And the reality this morning
is that humanity has an issue with sin.
Can I tell you that it's a universal condition?
Every single human being outside of the Lord Jesus Christ,
because he had no earthly father, the virgin birth,
every other human being has been born with a sin nature.
We've been born with a sin nature.
You know, you don't have to teach kids to sin.
They sin by nature.
We sin by nature.
And we find that the Bible says that Jesus,
his name shall be called Jesus, why?
For he shall save his people from their sins.
This universal condition brings with it a great cost.
The Bible says that all have sinned
and come short of the glory of God.
The Bible tells us that the wages of sin is death.
And we find that as we study the scriptures
and we understand this universal condition
that every person under the sound of my voice,
every person that I've ever met physically
on this planet Earth is a sinner or sinners.
Now, some have been saved by the grace of God.
Aren't you thankful this morning?
We've been quickened, we've been made alive.
But there are many, and I would say there are more.
The Bible talks about the broad way, right?
Versus the narrow way.
And there are many that are still lost in their sin.
There are many today that do not know
the significance of the name Jesus.
They do not understand,
though they will celebrate a holiday in a few days.
And they many do not know the significance
of the holiday and its fullness.
Some may not understand the fullness
of the meaning of the holiday,
but have some knowledge of the fact that,
well, Jesus was born,
but they don't really know who Jesus is.
They don't really know why Jesus was born.
I spoke with a man just this past week,
and as I had interaction with this young man,
I just asked him this question.
I said, listen, who is Jesus to you?
And he gave me an answer, and it was an honest answer, it just wasn't a biblical answer.
He was sincere, he was honest, but he was wrong.
Because I submit to you this morning that Jesus is more than a prophet, he's God.
He's more than a prophet, he's God.
And we find this morning that who Jesus is, is revealed to us through the canon of scripture,
through the Bible, and I'm so thankful to have a Bible this morning.
And God tells us the great purpose of Christ's birth, to save his people from their sins.
Why?
Because we have a sin problem.
And what is it that will pay for your sin or for my sin?
How can we, if the wages of sin is death, what do we do about our sin?
And I tell you this morning that sin separates us from a holy God.
Sin separates us from a holy God.
And it doesn't matter what type of sinner you are, it doesn't matter what kinds of sins
you have committed, sometimes we like to make ourselves feel better by saying, well I'm
not as bad as that person, or I haven't sinned like those people, or I haven't, but the reality
is that sin separates us from God.
The Bible says in the book of James that if you've been guilty in one point, if you've
offended in one, you're guilty of all.
And the reality is that when you read Revelation chapter 21, the Bible ends, there's a whole
list of sins that are gathered there, but it ends with this, and all liars.
The Bible says that all men are liars.
Some might not want to accept that truth, but you're just lying to yourself.
You're deceiving yourself.
All men are liars.
The Bible tells us of this sin problem, but it tells us that Jesus came to save His people
from their sins.
We read it in Galatians 4, look there again with me, in Galatians chapter 4, we'll look
at a couple of more verses and make some finishing comments before we end this morning,
but in Galatians chapter 4, the Bible said, as I read just a few moments ago, in verse
number 4, but when the fullness of the time was come, God sent forth His Son, made of
a woman, made under the law, why?
For what purpose?
There is a great purpose.
To redeem them that were under the law, that we might receive the adoption of sons.
Can I unpack this verse of Scripture with you just for a moment this morning?
The reality is that the Bible says that at the right time, when the fullness of time
was come, that God sent forth His Son, for God so loved the world that He gave His only
begotten Son.
We read that in John chapter 3, in verse number 16, that whosoever believeth in Him should
not perish, but have everlasting life.
And we read here that the Bible says to redeem them.
The word redeem means to buy back.
We're dead in our sins, in our trespasses, according to Ephesians chapter number 2, and
we find that the Bible says to redeem them.
How is redemption made possible?
Well, we're going to get there in just a few moments in the book of 1 Peter, but I will
tell you this morning that there's no redemption without blood.
Without the shedding of blood, there is no remission for sin.
There's no redemption.
We're redeemed through the blood.
And we find that it says to redeem them.
Notice that we're under the law, and there's a law of sin.
And we find that we are in that situation when you were born, you were born a sinner,
and you were under that law, and we find that this morning as we look at this truth,
the Bible says, you don't need to turn there, I just want to read it quickly.
In Romans chapter 8, in verse 1, the Bible says, there is therefore now no condemnation
to them which are in Christ Jesus, who walk not after the flesh, but after the Spirit.
Verse 2, for the law of the Spirit of life in Christ Jesus, notice, hath made me free
from the law of sin and death.
We understand in the society in which we live, and I'm not going to try to have debate with
you, I would readily acknowledge with you this morning that our judicial system in America
is flawed.
But we do have a judicial system.
We understand justice.
We understand that if there's a crime, that there's supposed to be a penalty.
We understand that there's an infraction, there's a consequence.
Again, as flawed as our system may be, that's not the point of the conversation this morning.
We understand justice.
God's system is not flawed.
God is perfect.
God is perfectly holy.
He is perfectly loving, and He is perfectly just.
And I could go on and on and on of all of His attributes, but let me stop there this
morning.
Our God is holy.
Our God is loving.
God's so loved, but our God is just.
And here's what our God cannot do.
He cannot dismiss sin.
He can't just turn and say, well, we're just going to let that one go.
Sin brings with it a penalty.
So the Bible says to redeem them that were under the law.
What does the law do?
Well, the law reveals to us that we're sinners.
Paul says, how would I know that I'm a sinner unless the law said, thou shalt not covet?
So the law redeems.
Let me say this.
In the book of Galatians, the Bible says that the law is a schoolmaster.
You know what the schoolmaster does?
The law can't save.
You say, okay, I'm going to keep all the law.
That's what I got to do.
You can't.
That's impossible because what the law does is it reveals to you that you can't keep it,
that you're a sinner.
But what the law does is it points us to the only one that can give us life, and that's
Jesus Christ.
We're under the law, but the law simply reveals that we're sinners.
And it points us, according to the book of Galatians, to the Lord Jesus Christ, the one
that can give life, the only one, the one that said, I am the way, the truth, and the
life.
No man cometh unto the Father but by me.
We find, as we continue looking in Galatians 4 and verse 5, the Bible ends by saying this
in the verse, that we might receive the adoption of sons.
Can I tell you, this is a wonderful truth of God's word.
I'm at enmity with God when I'm a sinner, when I'm lost before my salvation.
Every human being that is under the law, that has not been born again, that has not been
saved by the grace of God, they're at enmity.
They're needing to be reconciled.
We think about the ministry of reconciliation, and we find that the Bible says that we would
receive the adoption of sons.
And I remind you that in John chapter number 1, the Bible says in verse number 11, that
he came unto his own, and his own received him not.
But as many as received him, to them gave he power to become the sons of God, even to
them that believe on his name.
Adoption is wonderful.
The truth that I'm adopted into the family of God, join heirs with Jesus Christ.
It's a precious truth of God's word.
How is it that I could have this redemption?
How is it that I could have this forgiveness?
Well it's through the Lord Jesus Christ.
It's accepting his free gift of eternal life to as many as received him.
We think about this truth during this holiday season, Christmas, and giving of gifts, the
exchanging of gifts, and the giving and the receiving.
God has a gift.
It's called eternal life, and he wants you to receive it.
And if you do, you'll have that truth of being adopted as a son.
What a joy that I belong to him and he belongs to me.
It's a precious truth.
Paul says it this way in 1 Timothy chapter 1.
Again we think about the great purpose of Christ's birth.
The Bible says in 1 Timothy chapter 1 and verse number 15, 1 Timothy 1 and verse number
15, this is a faithful saying, meaning that it's truthful.
It's a faithful saying.
And notice in verse number 15 of 1 Timothy 1, and worthy of all acceptation, that Christ
Jesus came into the world to save sinners, of whom I am chief.
We read it in Matthew chapter 1, his name shall be called Jesus, why?
For he shall save his people from their sins.
And we read here in 1 Timothy 1 and verse 15 that Paul says that Christ Jesus came into
the world to save sinners.
Paul understood that he was a sinner in need of the Savior.
He understood that he could not earn his own salvation.
He couldn't get to heaven by just being a good person.
He'd receive the gift of God, eternal life.
He'd receive the Lord Jesus Christ, Jesus as his personal Lord and Savior.
Peter says it this way in 1 Peter chapter 1.
In 1 Peter chapter 1, as you think about this truth of to redeem them
and the truth of redemption to be bought back and we find here that Peter gives us insight
with regard to that way that redemption would be provided through the blood of the Lord
Jesus Christ.
In verse number 18 of 1 Peter chapter 1, the Bible says this,
for as much as ye know that ye were not redeemed with corruptible things, as silver and gold
from your vain conversation received by tradition from your fathers.
Can I pause here just for a moment?
There's a lot of people that have a lot of beliefs.
They have all sorts of beliefs and I think that the enemy, Satan, the Bible calls him
the little G God of this world in the book of 2 Corinthians chapter 4, that he has blinded
the minds of them that believe not, lest the light of the glorious gospel should shine
unto them.
I believe that the enemy has used, quote unquote, religion to deceive multitudes.
Because religion cannot save you.
It can't.
Going through rote religion and I do this and I do that and it can't save you.
I've asked countless people, if all of that could save you, why did Jesus have to die?
Why did Jesus have to leave heaven to come to this sin-cursed world to die a horrific,
horrible death at Calvary if we could just be good enough to make it?
And the answer is that we can't.
Religion has condemned scores of people, traditions, thinking I read this morning, actually I read
it yesterday, of the net worth of some of the most wealthy people in the world, $680
billion or something like that.
I can't even, like I don't know how many zeros that is, right?
I mean I do, but it's just hard to comprehend.
All the money in the world can't save you.
All your good works can't save you.
He says in verse 19, but with the precious blood of Christ, as of a lamb without blemish
and without spot, who verily, notice verse 20, was foreordained before the foundation
of the world, but was manifest in these last times for you.
So it was always the plan of God that Jesus would come.
And he says that it was manifest in these last times for you.
Peter is writing, he's one of the disciples, he's an apostle, he's an eyewitness, he walked
with Christ, he saw these things he speaks about at the end of the book, observing and
being an eyewitness of the sufferings of Christ.
In verse 21, who by him do believe in God that raised him up from the dead and gave
him glory that your faith and hope might be in God.
This morning, who are you trusting in?
This morning, are you 100% sure if you were to die today that heaven is your home?
Have you trusted Jesus Christ, your personal savior?
Have you been a recipient of that great news, the gospel?
And if you have, praise God.
But just like the shepherds on the night that we read of in Luke chapter number 2, it was
given to you, but not to be kept to you.
It was given to you, and praise God for it, but it was given to you to share with others.
But maybe this morning there's someone here, maybe there's multiple people here that you've
never understood who Jesus is.
You've never understood the consequence of sin, the fact that we do have a holy God that
does love and is gracious and is merciful and he's holy, but he's just.
And I'm thankful that he's just.
And we find this morning that the Bible says that the wages of sin is death, but the gift
of God is eternal life through Jesus Christ, our Lord.
We can't get to heaven by our own works.
Every one of us is going to die one day, as it is appointed unto man once to die.
After this, the judgment.
I preached the message last Sunday evening about finishing well, and I said repeatedly,
we don't know where the finish line is.
If we were to have a race today, Bart, you and I were going to race.
I use Zachary as the example on Sunday night.
We would try to determine where's the finish line.
I want to know where the finish line is before I start the race, right?
If we start a race and I say, I won, and he's like, what do you mean?
I'm like, we got to the finish line.
I got there before you, but I never told him where it was.
I went through this Sunday night.
In the Christian life, we don't know where the finish line is.
We're all running a race, but we don't know where the finish line is.
I said this on Sunday night.
Death can come at any moment, but the rapture can come at any moment.
Savannah Gardner, I don't think she was 28 years old.
Her race ended.
From all I know, she finished well, serving the Lord, faithful.
You see, it's so young.
God doeth all things well.
He knows.
He has a purpose.
I don't understand.
I don't need to understand.
I just trust God.
I don't know when your race is going to end.
If you're saved, live for Jesus, but if you're lost this morning, you've never trusted Christ,
you've not received that gift, you say, man, I'm looking forward to the gifts I'm going
to get on Christmas.
Can I tell you?
None of that matters.
The greatest gift is eternal life, and it's been paid for with the blood of Jesus Christ,
and He offers it to you for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you so much for the opportunity that you've given us to gather this morning and
to see once again afresh the greatness of the incarnation, the great promise, the great
proclamation, and I think about the great purpose.
God this morning, there may be one or several that are not saved, that have never trusted
Jesus Christ as their personal Savior.
I pray that the Holy Spirit of God would convict them of their sin of Christ's righteousness
and of judgment to come.
I pray that they would not leave this place without knowing for sure that heaven is their
home.
I pray that during this time of invitation for those that are saved, would you help us
to rejoice in our salvation?
Would you help us to purpose in sharing the truth of the gospel with others?
I pray that you would move in these moments as only you can, and we'll thank you for it.
In Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
If you're a man here this morning and you're not sure of heaven, you say, if I were to
die today, I'm not sure that I'd go to heaven.
Mark is standing down here with a Bible, and we'd encourage you to come and chat with Brother
Mark and he'll share some verses with you how you could know for sure that heaven is
your home.
If you're a lady here this morning, Holly is here with a Bible and she'd take a Bible
and show you how you too could know for sure that heaven is your home.
We never want to embarrass anyone, but we want you to go to heaven when you die.
Those that are saved, would you rejoice in what Christ has done for you?
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.