Second Thessalonians chapter number three.
Second Thessalonians chapter number three,
we continue looking through the concise instruction
that is given to the church at Thessalonica.
We've mentioned several times
that the church at Thessalonica is a good church,
a model church.
It's a church that is commended for many things
as you study through the first and second letters.
You find primarily in that first letter
that you'll see much of what Paul is commending them for,
but he starts out in the second letter
and talks about how their faith groweth exceedingly.
If you notice that in chapter one in verse number three,
and what a blessed truth to see that there's a church,
a body of believers, that their faith was growing.
How does our faith grow?
Well, by being in the word of God.
And we find, so then faith cometh by hearing
and hearing by the word of God.
And the Bible tells us that their faith groweth exceedingly,
that the charity every one of you all
toward each other aboundeth.
And they were a growing church, they were doing well.
They faced some opposition, they faced persecutions,
they faced that attack from without,
but really the greatest danger
that the church in Thessalonica was dealing with
was false teaching.
And let me say this,
that's the greatest danger of any church.
There are false teachers that exist
that continue to peddle their false doctrine,
their false teaching,
and they package it real nicely
so that they can deceive as many as they possibly can.
And we find that the church in Thessalonica
was dealing with some of that false teaching
and how it was adversely impacting some of the members.
We looked last week at verses six through 10,
and this evening we're gonna continue the thought
really from last week regarding that disorderly behavior
that we noted in verses six through 10.
We discover tonight in verses 11 and 12
some additional instruction that is given
regarding those that are defined as being busybodies.
Notice verse number 11 and 12,
it'll be our text this evening.
I've simply titled the message this evening, Busybodies.
And the Bible says this,
for we hear, verse 11,
that there are some which walk among you disorderly.
He's dealt with that subject of disorderly
in verses six through 10 a couple of times.
It says this, working not at all, but are busybodies.
Now, we understand that, as we mentioned last week,
with some of that false teaching,
if you look in the second chapter
of the book of 2 Thessalonians,
there were those that were saying
that the day of the Lord was at hand.
And so there were some that, through this false teaching,
they thought that they didn't have to work anymore
and what have you.
No doubt there were probably others
for other reasons that didn't wanna work,
and we have certainly deal with that
throughout human history.
We see it in our time as well,
where there are some folks that just don't wanna work,
but it says here, working not at all.
Notice this, but are busybodies.
Now, verse 12, them that are such,
we command and exhort by our Lord Jesus Christ
that with quietness they work and eat their own bread.
Now, last week, when we looked at this situation
with the disorderly behavior,
we mentioned the fact that there were some
that were not working.
We see that in verse number 10.
If a man doesn't work, he shouldn't eat.
And we find that the really,
as we looked at that text of scripture,
that we needed to identify the disorderly behavior,
and then you correct the disorderly behavior.
The fact of the matter is that that correction,
that warning is given, but the response to the warning,
we have no control over.
And we have the responsibility to identify it
to give the warning or to correct it,
but we found in the text last week
that if they continue down that path,
it comes to a place where we are to withdraw ourselves,
we see that in verse number six,
from every brother that walketh disorderly,
literally to separate from them,
to remove oneself or to depart.
As we come to verses 11 and 12,
we really continue to look at the instruction
that Paul is providing as he addresses specifically
this group of people,
and he refers to them as being busybodies.
Now, what is a busybody?
You've heard the term, no doubt,
but really an individual that would be identified
as being a busybody is one that is busy,
they busy oneself about trifling, needless, useless matters.
That's what they do.
They fill up their time with those things.
It's defined this way,
one who is inquisitive about others' affairs,
a meddling person,
one who concerns themselves with the affairs of others.
Can I tell you this evening that it's very easy
to fall into a trap of being a busybody?
It really is.
It's very easy with,
especially in the day and age in which we live,
hey, did you hear about this clickbait stuff
that's on the internet and on social media
and all this sort of thing?
And people can really fill up their time
meddling in the affairs of others,
useless, just needless information
and matters that don't really impact or affect you,
but we can get so caught up with it, and it's a danger.
And we find that as we look at this text of Scripture
in verses 11 and 12,
we understand that Paul is writing
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God
to a local church.
A local church is not a building,
it's a group of believers.
And we find that the local church is a family,
it's a body, it's those that have been saved
and baptized members of the church.
And we find that as the Apostle Paul is writing this letter,
I want you this evening,
before we get into points and look at this,
I want you this evening to consider
being a member of the church at Thessalonica
and receiving this letter.
And as this letter is being read,
you're reading these things,
you start out in the first chapter,
man, their faith groweth exceedingly
and their love one toward another aboundeth.
And you're thinking, yes, this is great.
And then you get into the second chapter
and there's the instruction that's given
with regard to helping them understand
the timing of the end days and the return of Christ
and the appearance of the antichrist
and the abomination of desolation.
And all of those things are looked at in the second chapter
you come to the third chapter
and Paul begins by talking about praying for them
and the opportunities that are there.
And then he starts addressing disorderly behavior.
And then the Bible says this in verse number 11.
Now again, stay with me.
You're a member of the church at Thessalonica,
like just think that way tonight.
And as you are reading this,
for we hear that there are some
which walk among you disorderly,
working not at all, but are busybodies.
Not me.
I mean, I don't know who,
can you imagine the atmosphere?
The difference in excitement
from the first few verses of chapter one
to now these verses in chapter three.
And Paul says, we have heard.
So as we look at this passage of scripture,
I have two main thoughts for you
and then we're gonna close it up
with giving you three points of application this evening.
But number one, I want you to notice in verse number 11,
the exposure of busybodies.
They're exposed.
And we find that Paul has received a report.
I'm not sure how this report was delivered to him.
We find that he mentioned something similar to this
as he's writing to the church in Corinth.
As he's writing to them in the first chapter,
he says to them that they have,
it's been declared unto me of you, my brethren,
by them which are of the house of Chloe,
that there are contentions among you.
That's first Corinthians one and verse number 11.
And so there in the church in Corinth,
Paul says specifically who it was
that gave them the information.
It was those from the house of Chloe.
And they tell Paul there's contentions in the church.
There's problems, divisions.
And so Paul begins to address that.
Well, here in 2 Thessalonians,
we do not have the information with regard to who it was
that delivered this report to Paul.
But we find that Paul says,
for we hear that there are some
which walk among you disorderly.
And so it's no longer just a situation.
And we hinted at this last week
that it seemed obvious that there were those
that were behaving themselves disorderly.
And you get to verse number 11,
and it's no more a situation where this is a church
where it could or could not be applicable.
You ever been in a situation like,
well, that doesn't really apply to us.
No, no, it applied to the church of Thessalonica.
There were some there that were within the body of Christ
in this local church that were walking disorderly.
They did not work at all.
And they're referred to as being busybodies.
The exposure of busybodies.
Their disorderly behavior, not working at all,
as we see in verse number 11,
left them with some time on their hands.
They're not working.
They have this extra time, if you will.
And with that time, they begin to use it inappropriately.
They begin to meddle in the affairs of others.
They begin to go, as we read on Sunday morning.
regard to those young widows, how they would go from house to house, and they would begin
to engage themselves into the affairs of others.
And here we find, though it does not go into that level of detail, but we understand how
busybodies, what their behavior is like, and what they're typically going to do.
And we find that Paul, the Scriptures expose these individuals.
They no longer can hide behind, they no longer can excuse their behavior, no, the Scriptures
are exposing these busybodies.
I believe, as we look at this portion of Scripture and see the situation where they're not working
and they're called busybodies that we find this evening, that there is, let me put it
this way, if a child of God is doing all the things that they're supposed to do, I think
you probably find yourself by saying, I just don't have enough time.
Not that I have just this idle time to get engaged in the affairs of other people.
No, I don't have the time for that.
And I don't have the interest in that, but I don't have the time for it.
I mentioned this last week, how that so often I hear people today that mention about not
having time to do X, Y, or Z.
And the reality is that it always baffles my mind when I hear that.
Why do I say that?
We have more conveniences today than any other generation that's ever gone before us.
I mean, honestly.
You know, I think about it today.
Now I'm kind of a weird person.
I actually like going to the store, and I like buying my own food, okay?
I like going and picking out my own vegetables and my own fruit.
What am I getting at?
I don't want them to deliver it to my house, okay?
Now if you're getting food delivered, I'm not criticizing you, I'm not telling you you're
wrong.
I'm saying I'm weird.
I like going and doing it myself.
Look, I'm picky with my apples.
I'm picky with my grapes.
I don't want squishy grapes.
If you like squishy grapes, Lord bless you.
I don't like squishy grapes.
So when I go in and I'm going to buy my grapes, you know what I do?
I feel them.
Some of you smell them.
I don't smell them.
I don't know what they're supposed to smell like, but I feel them, and if they feel squishy,
that's not the bag for me.
But you know what?
The person at whatever place that's doing the Instacart, the whatever, they don't care
what they're giving you.
Why am I saying all that?
Because these are modern, you know what they had to do back in this time and in our grandparents'
time?
They had to go out to a field.
They had to go and, I mean, there was no local, there was no one that was going to deliver
their, I mean, it was, it was a lot of work.
Now I don't do much wash, admittedly, all right?
Joseph throws me under the bus for it.
He says, I can't believe you don't even know how to use the washing machine.
I said, Mommy takes care of that stuff, man.
I don't, I mean, I, when she went away for all that time to go visit with Nova, I said,
I need a lesson on the washing machine.
And he said, I can't believe that.
I just don't, Holly just takes care of it, and I'm more than happy to have her take care
of it.
Amen.
And so she gave me the instructions, because when she's gone for a month, I'm going to
have to do some laundry, and so I had to figure it out.
But you know how our great-grandparents had to do some laundry?
The washboard, do you ever, I've never used one.
I've seen them, right?
We have all these modern conveniences, but yet we say, I don't have time to read my Bible.
I don't have time to whatever it might be, spiritually speaking.
But then you start looking at the screen time.
Now if your device is like my device, every week you get this little alert that says your
screen time increased by or decreased by.
Does your phone do that for you?
And sometimes I look and I'm like, there is no way my screen time increased by that
much.
And then I go back and I think in my week, and I'm like, oh yeah, I was driving somewhere
and I had the maps on for that whole trip, and it kind of calculates that in there.
You know, there's something, the studies are out there of how much time people spend on
social media just scrolling and scrolling and scrolling.
It's a danger.
And what happens is it lends itself to this busybody stuff, because all of a sudden we're
getting into the affairs of other folks that really are needless, useless matters, trifling
things.
And it's all because of the inquisitive nature of mankind.
Hey, did you hear about, and all of a sudden you don't even, yeah, it doesn't matter to
you what happened, but you got interest in the story, it's a problem.
So these folks, they weren't working, they were busybodies.
And we find the exposure, but then notice with me number two, the exhortation to busybodies.
The exhortation, in verse number 12, we find that the Bible says, now them that are such.
Paul doesn't call them out by name, but let me ask you this, did the Holy Spirit know
who they were by name?
Absolutely.
Could the Holy Spirit have chosen to put the names in there?
Sure He could.
Now them that are such.
I think about Achan, he's referred to in the book of Chronicles as being the troubler of
Israel.
No one knew when you start Joshua chapter number seven, that Achan was the one that
took the accursed thing, but God knew.
God gave Joshua the path forward for how to determine, take the tribe, take the house,
take the family, the house, the man.
Can you imagine Achan one by one as the family's, nope, not that one, it's this one right here,
and he knew he took it.
And so here the Scriptures just say, now them that are such.
In other words, examine yourself, and if the shoe fits, this is you.
Do you understand?
I mean, again, they were in the church at Thessalonica.
This is not a passage of Scripture as we would take it today as being God's Word, and it
could be that there's a church today that has no one that's a busybody, but that wasn't
the case in Thessalonica.
There were busybodies there.
They're exposed.
Now the exhortation is given, now them that are such, notice we command and exhort by
our Lord Jesus Christ.
What is the exhortation?
What is it?
Number one, that with quietness they work.
With quietness they work.
Now that doesn't actually mean that they work quietly as to regard to the decibel of their
activity.
The word quietness actually carries with it the idea of no more meddling.
Get away of that busybody stuff, go and work, and don't be concerned in the affairs of others.
And so it says, number one, what do they do?
They're to go and work.
With quietness they work.
And then notice, and eat their own bread.
Now why does the Scripture say, eat their own bread?
Well obviously they were eating somebody's bread if they weren't working, right?
They're eating somebody's bread, whether, and we use the word to mooch off of someone
or whatever you want to use, they were eating bread somehow.
And Paul says, no, here's what you need to do.
With quietness you need to work and eat their own bread.
Now I said this last week, and it's worth repeating tonight, this is not, verses 6 through
12 is not instruction that's given to those that cannot work.
This is written to people that can work that are not working.
There's a great difference between somebody that physically is incapable of working because
of some health condition or whatever it may be.
That's a different situation than what we find here.
These people were able-bodied people that could go and work, but they chose not to work.
And they're eating other people's bread, and they're, whether they're, you know, show up
at the right time so that you can bring the story from the other folks that you're, I
got a story to tell you, oh it's lunch, hey do you want to have lunch?
I don't know how it all worked, but the reality is that they were given this instruction on
how they needed to correct their behavior.
As I look at these couple of verses and couple it with last week's lesson, I'm reminded of
three powerful truths.
And in closing this evening, I want you to consider these three truths that we find that
are applicable for each of us this evening.
Number one, God's Word confronts.
God's Word confronts.
What do I mean by that?
Well as you get into God's Word, God's Word will confront you in areas that you need to
examine and you need to deal with.
As we honestly and regularly study the Scriptures and read the Scriptures and attend church
where the Scriptures are being preached, then God's Word will confront us.
There are times we could use the truth as we look at this passage of Scripture where
we find that these busy bodies that were being exposed in this portion of Scripture,
they were being confronted with their behavior.
It reminds me when we think about how God's Word confronts that we...
must examine oneself. It's actually vital. See, so often, and I've said this many
times, and you find it to be true, it's far easier for us to examine someone
else's life than for us to examine our own life. Far easier to be able to look
down at someone else and be able to identify areas of weakness and areas of
error and what-have-you, but we don't like the personal self-examination.
It's important that we understand that when God's Word confronts us that we
must examine oneself, that the reality is that in we deal with the subject of
self-examination is that it requires two very important things. Number one, it
requires honesty. It requires honesty, and it requires humility. Typically, human
nature is to think that we're better than we really are, to think that we
really don't have any problems, that, yeah, I know there's a lot of people that
that applies to, but it's not really for me. I've not heard it recently, thankfully,
but I remember years ago hearing somebody as they would leave church
from hearing a message, oh man, that would have been a great message for so
and so, I wish they were here. You missed the whole point, because God has
something for you in it as well. That's how God works through His Word. Oh man,
I'm gonna get that message so I can share it with so-and-so, and we just
totally forget about ourselves. And so this evening we understand, number one,
in closing, that God's Word confronts. Not only does God's Word confront, it
convicts. God's Word convicts. This is the work of the Holy Spirit. Conviction
is the work of the Holy Spirit. The Holy Spirit of God uses the Word of God to
bring conviction in the people of God. Can I tell you this evening, conviction
is a good thing. It's a good thing to be convicted. It's a good thing to have our
toes stepped on. You hear sometimes, especially when you start thinking
about old-time preaching, and you hear about some of the Billy Sundays and
other guys say, man, they'd step on people's toes. No, listen, it's God's work
to do that, to convict. The Holy Spirit convicts us. We ought to be sensitive to
the leadership of the Spirit of God in our lives, and as the Holy Spirit of God
would put His finger in an area of our lives, we must respond to that. And we
find that as we look at this passage of Scripture, and I think, again, as I've
asked you this evening to put yourself in the position of being the church at
Thessalonica and receiving this letter and finding out, listen, there are some
amongst us that are busybodies. I better examine myself. Is God talking about me?
Now, I understand we're not the church at Thessalonica, but I also understand that
there's probably very few churches in the world that have any size of a
congregation at all that have zero busybodies in it, all right? I don't have
my head in the sand, all right? The Holy Spirit of God writes this and gives this,
yes, to the church at Thessalonica, but we find the truth is preserved for all of
the church age, and this evening, as God's Word confronts, we examine ourselves, and
the Holy Spirit of God begins to convict us and to put His finger, and I hope, I
don't know, but I hope that there were some in Thessalonica that readily
acknowledge, yes, that's me. See, I'm thankful that God doesn't just leave us
to ourselves. You know what the Bible tells us? The Bible says, whom the Lord
loveth, He chasteneth. When you have children, if you have children, you
correct them because you love them. Now, we're not perfect like God is, so there
certainly are times that we correct with a motive that's not as pure as it ought
to be. Is that fair? But God is perfect, and God loves, and therefore, God convicts,
and He corrects. He doesn't just leave us over to ourselves. No, He wants us to live
our lives in such a way that we're walking worthy so that we might
please Him, and so He provides this instruction, and through His Word, He
confronts, He convicts, and then I would say, as we look at this passage, that God's
Word corrects. The behavior is corrected. In verse number 12, the remedy is
provided. The reality is that if you were in the church at Thessalonica and you
acknowledged after receiving and hearing the words of this epistle that, yes, I am
a busybody, that is me, I am guilty, then you look at the truth of the exhortation
and the command in verse number 12 that God's Word corrects. How do I make
this behavior appropriate? What do I do so that I can please God? Well, in this
context, go to work and eat your own bread. That's what it says, that with
quietness they work and eat their own bread. Now, the correction must be
accepted. How do we respond? No doubt, because I know human history, I know
human tendency, and you know human tendency and human nature. I'm assuming
the Scriptures do not tell us, but just by knowing how humans deal with things,
that there were probably some in Thessalonica that were busybodies that
did not accept that they were a busybody. That's not me. I mean, that
might be Tom, but that's not me. They didn't have, you understand what I'm
saying. And this evening, as we look at a passage of Scripture like this and we
see the exposure of these busybodies, we see the exhortation, we're reminded
tonight of how God's Word, how God uses His Word in the lives of His people.
That's why it's so vital that we have a proper daily time with God and His Word,
because God's Word will confront us about our behavior, about the things that
we're doing or not doing, and as God's Word confronts us, the Holy Spirit of
God begins to convict us, using His Word to convict us of, hey, what you're doing
is not right, or hey, you're not doing this thing and you should be doing this
thing, and we have that conviction, but you know the reality is that we can be
convicted, we can be stirred, and then not receive the correction and not take that
step of altering or changing our behavior so that it's aligned with what
God has prescribed. We find that as God's Word corrects, as the remedy is provided,
that it's absolutely essential that every believer, those that would be in
this particular category and setting, busybodies, that they take heed and that
they respond properly. But this truth this evening of God's Word confronting
and convicting and correcting is a truth that's applicable in a variety of areas
of our lives, and we study the Scriptures and we read the Scriptures so that God
can help me be the believer that I'm supposed to be. I know that it's a very
popular, it's probably not as popular as it was several years ago, but you would
see regularly, you still see it today, this WWJD. And how many of you know what
that stands for? All right, some of you know. All right, what does it stand for?
Help me out. What would Jesus do? All right, you know what I believe? I believe
that most people that wear that paraphernalia that says WWJD have
absolutely no idea what Jesus would do because they don't have a relationship
with this book. They don't study the life of Christ. You see in their behavior, they
have the WWJD, but they don't study the Scriptures to know. Listen, Peter said that
Christ left us an example that we should follow His steps. Paul tells us in the book of Romans
that we are to be conformed to the image of His dear Son, in Romans 8 and verse 29, speaking
about God, speaking about Jesus, and we're to be conformed to His image. We're to be
like Him. Why in Antioch did they call them Christians? Well, because their behavior was
that of Christ, and so they were called Christians first in Antioch. And so this evening as we
look at the context and we see what's happening in Thessalonica, that we can broaden the scope
this evening and say that God's Word will confront, convict, and correct in a variety
of areas of our lives. In our thinking, our behavior must be aligned with God's Word.
We must be able to prove what is acceptable unto the Lord. Do you remember at the end
of 1 Thessalonians chapter 5, it was one of the studies that we did several weeks ago
in verse 21, prove all.
things, hold fast that which is good.
And we find that as we couple that with the book of Ephesians where the Bible tells us
that we're to prove what is acceptable unto the Lord, that we understand that we must,
we must get into God's Word.
This church received this letter to expose some behavior that needed to be corrected.
But it didn't just expose, there was an exhortation given, there was instruction provided for
how to correct and how to please God.
The study has been titled for all of these weeks now, this is our 20th lesson through
1st and 2nd Thessalonians, these just the last chapters and the last sections of the
last chapters in our 20th lesson to walk worthy and please God.
These individuals that are exposed, that are confronted, they were not walking worthy.
They were not pleasing God.
But God gives them instruction so that they can change, alter, confess, repent, and they
can walk worthy and please God.
I'm so thankful that we have a gracious Heavenly Father who loves us so much that He gives
us truth and then He takes the interest in our lives individually, that when we sit down
to study the Scriptures, to read the Scriptures, when we come to a church service, that we
have the opportunity, Lord, would You speak to me?
God, would You give me something from Your Word?
Would You correct my behavior?
Lord, would You show me if there's something I need to do that I'm not doing?
God, would You show me if there's something that I'm not doing that I need to do?
God has that personal interest in our lives that He answers that prayer.
Why is it that we on Sunday morning and Sunday evening have a time of prayer before the service?
A couple of reasons.
Number one, God said, Jesus said that His house should be a house of prayer and a number
of years ago now it was under great conviction that we almost, in our church services, use
prayer like bookends.
We'd pray to open the service and say, God, would You bless the service, and we'd pray
to close the service and say, thank You for blessing the service.
But a time to pray specifically during that time, the morning service, the evening service,
those few moments that we have of prayer time is really not designed to be praying for Aunt
Susie who has a, no, no, the time is to be fixed upon praying for the service, what's
at hand, and God, speak to me.
God, use the preacher.
You know, there's spiritual warfare that takes place when you're trying to preach the Bible.
God, would You help me to not be distracted, to be attentive?
God, I know I came this morning expecting, I came this evening expecting to hear from
You, and God, show me.
Sometimes I think that if we're not careful, we can get to the time of invitation, and
I'm not saying any of this to try to emotionally impact anyone, but I think that if we're not
careful, we can get to a time of invitation where God has confronted us and God has convicted
us, but we don't take that step of dealing with it.
God, help me.
Help me to be a doer of the Word and not a hearer only.
Help me to apply those things.
Help me to confess, and sometimes I think that if we're not careful, we can have the
mindset of, well, if I go forward in invitation, everyone's going to think I'm a sinner.
Everyone already knows you're a sinner, amen?
For all have sinned and come short of the glory of God, amen?
We already know that.
They're going to think my life's messed up.
Why do you care?
Just do business with God, amen?
God's Word is powerful, and I'm thankful for the ministry of the Word.
We see it at work in the Church of Thessalonica and how God was confronting and addressing
these individuals and seeking to correct their behavior so that they could please God.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
We thank You for Your Word.
Thank You, God, for the truth, the application.
I pray, Lord, that You'd help us to be sensitive to Your leadership.
Help us, Lord, to be doers of Your Word.
I pray that You'd bless the time of prayer.
We thank You for it.
I pray that You'd move and work as only You can, and we'll thank You for it in Christ's
name we pray, amen.
Does anyone need a bulletin this evening?
You didn't get one.
We don't have any left, so if you didn't get one, you should come earlier next week.