12, Mark chapter number 12 this evening, and I'll be looking at verses 18-27, Mark chapter
number 12 verses 18-27, and the text of Scripture that is before us this evening provides us
with a record of a conversation that takes place between the Lord Jesus Christ and the
Sadducees.
As you read the New Testament, you have the opportunity to come across the terminology,
the group of people that are referred to as the Sadducees, and then of course the Pharisees,
and as you read about these religious groups of people, you read about the scribes and
what have you, but here, specifically, the context of the conversation that is recorded
for us is that between the Sadducees and the Lord Jesus Christ.
These Sadducees were religious leaders during this particular time of Christ, and they come
to Jesus with a question.
As you study the Gospels, you'll find often that the Pharisees, the Sadducees, and the
scribes, the religious leaders of the day, that they often would try to catch Jesus in
saying something that was contrary to what they believed, and try to find occasion to
find fault, and so on and so forth, and often times they would show up to where Jesus was
teaching for all of the wrong reason, and they had wrong motives, and here we find in
this particular conversation that really what is recorded to us is that they think
they have this question that is going to leave the Lord Jesus Christ cornered without an
answer.
And we know that He is God and that He is omniscient, He knows all things, and as a
side thought, I kind of wonder this evening how long these Sadducees sat around and how
many different seminar hearings they had in order to come up with this question, right?
I mean, they're trying to corner the Lord Jesus Christ, and we find that as we look
at the passage of Scripture, I would mention just very quickly, and we'll kind of circle
back to it at the end, but I wonder tonight if these Sadducees would have spent as much
time actually studying the Word of God as they did on trying to figure out how to corner
Jesus, that perhaps they wouldn't have had to have the question for Jesus because they
would have come to the proper conclusion biblically.
And I mentioned this many years ago as you look at David and Saul, and it's a completely
different context, but the Bible says that Saul made David his enemy continually and
he sought him, and he spent all of this time seeking David, seeking to kill him, and I
often wonder what if he would have sought God with just a measure of that which he sought
David, how things would have been different in the life of Saul.
But we find here that these religious leaders, they weren't really interested in studying
the Scriptures to come to the conclusion that they needed to come to, rather they sought
to question the Lord Jesus Christ and corner Him.
As we look at the passage, I really want to focus our attention upon the response of Jesus,
which is recorded for us in verses 24 through 27.
As we would focus our attention this evening on the latter part of the text that we'll
study, the purpose in so doing is so that we can be better equipped to deal with this
matter of deception.
I've mentioned as we've had this series here on Wednesday evenings for a little over a
month now that we are living in an age of deception, there is the danger of deception,
and we find that as we look at the truth that is before us this evening, you will not find
the word deceive or deceived or deceiving, but I want you to understand, look at it in
verse number 24, the Bible says,
"...and Jesus answering said unto them, Do ye not therefore..."
Look at that word, err, "...because ye know not the Scriptures, neither the power of God."
Now, skip down to verse 27, we'll look at the whole context as we go through the message
this evening, but look at verse 27, it says,
"...he is not the God of the dead, but the God of the living."
Notice this phrase, "...ye therefore do greatly err."
I've used that phrase at the end of verse number 27 for our lesson tonight as a title,
"...ye therefore do greatly err."
That word err in verse number 24, and again in verse number 27, is actually the same exact
Greek word that is used in many of the other passages that we've studied in these last
six weeks that is translated deceive or deceived.
And we find that here, as we've mentioned that word and we've looked at it and we've
dissected it, we understand that it also carries with it the idea of being led into error.
And here we find that that's really the context in what we're finding, is that Jesus says
to these Sadducees, "...do ye not therefore err?
Ye therefore do greatly err."
They had been deceived.
And we find that as we look at this passage of Scripture, we can answer the question,
what led to their deception?
Start back with me in verse number 18.
The Bible says, "...then come unto him the Sadducees, which say, there is no resurrection.
And they asked him, saying, Master, Moses wrote unto us, if a man's brother die and
leave his wife behind him, and leave no children, that his brother should take his wife and
raise up seed unto his brother."
Without having to go back to the Old Testament, the Pentateuch, we would quickly acknowledge
that what they're saying is accurate with regard to what Moses had written to them concerning
the particular subject.
They then come up with this particular scenario, this hypothetical, and they say this in verse
number 20, "...now there were seven brethren, and the first took a wife, and dying left
no seed.
And the second took her, and died, neither left he any seed.
And the third likewise, and the seven had her, and left no seed.
Last of all, the woman died also.
In the resurrection therefore, when they shall rise, whose wife shall she be of them?
For the seven had heard a wife."
Now it's kind of interesting that in verse number 18, the Bible reveals to us that they
say, the Sadducees, they say there is no resurrection.
Bible scholars for years have said that's why they're sad, you see, because they don't
believe in a resurrection.
But the reality is that when they're trying to corner Jesus, they say in verse number
23, "...in the resurrection therefore, when they shall rise."
But they don't even believe in a resurrection.
We find that Jesus, as He's going to respond to them, He graciously answers their question,
but He also corrects their error in their doctrine, in their theology, if you will.
So we notice that these Sadducees, they've come up with this question, this hypothetical,
they've come and they've provided this scenario to the Lord Jesus Christ, and they ask in
verse number 23, "...whose wife shall she be of them?
For the seven had heard a wife."
Notice how Jesus responds.
I do not believe for one second that they expected that this would be how He would respond.
He says, "...do ye not therefore err?"
Whoa, what do you mean we're, what do you mean we err, right?
Notice what He says, "...because ye know not the Scriptures, neither the power of God."
Here in verse number 24, we find that God gives us insight as to what led to their deception.
Now I believe that as we study the passage of Scripture and we gain this insight that
is provided to us, it will help us in preventing deception in our own lives.
What was it that led to the deception in the lives of these Sadducees when they come and
they bring this question and they seek to corner Jesus and to cause Him to not be able
to answer the question?
Well, God gives us two reasons that they had been deceived, or two things that led to their deception.
I want you to understand that He says this in verse number 24, "...ye know not the Scriptures."
Ye know not the Scriptures.
Understand, they had the Scriptures.
It was not a matter of them being truly ignorant without having biblical truth that led to
the question, a question in which they were seeking truth.
No, they're trying to corner Jesus.
Their motive is not right.
And here Jesus says that they had been led into error, they had been deceived because
they do not know the Scriptures.
Again, it was not that they did not have the Scriptures.
It wasn't even that they didn't use the Scriptures.
For we find that they say in verse number 19, "...Moses wrote unto us."
And then they say, if a man's brother died, they quote a passage from Deuteronomy.
And they're familiar with the Scriptures.
The Pentateuch, as we would often refer to it as, the Law, the five books of Moses, is
what he's referring to here, these Sadducees are referring to.
Moses wrote unto us, and they accepted the Pentateuch as being the Word of God.
They accepted the Scriptures as being these first five books, and we find that they used
the Scriptures.
But Jesus said, "...ye do err."
Why?
Because you know not the Scriptures.
It wasn't that they didn't have them, it wasn't that they didn't use them,
it was that they did not properly know the Scriptures.
Let me say it this way.
They refused, the Sadducees refused, to allow the Scriptures to dictate their belief.
Instead of allowing the Scriptures to dictate and to determine what they would believe,
they had their own belief, they had their own tradition,
they had their own presuppositions, if you will,
and they already had their mind filled with what they wanted to believe,
and we're not going to let the Scriptures mess with that.
Does it not sound familiar with some stuff that we deal with in society today?
There's no room for the real truth
because there's all this false stuff that's filled the heads of people.
And you try to give them truth, but they've already erred,
they've already believed something else,
and they're so set in what they believe
that they're not willing to allow the Scriptures to dictate their belief.
This evening, we understand, we say it often as Baptist people,
that the Bible is our sole authority for faith and practice.
There is nothing else that stands at the same level as the Bible
with regard to dictating our doctrine, our belief.
The Bible stands alone. Amen?
There's no other religious book, there's no other tradition,
there's no other anything that we set at the same level as the Bible,
or even at a higher level than the Bible.
Today, if you were to look at many groups of people around the world
that would claim to be religious,
even as the Sadducees would claim to be religious,
they may not deny the Bible,
but they would hold the tradition of their church fathers
in higher regard than the Bible.
They would hold some other holy book higher in regard than the Bible.
And we find that what Jesus is saying to these Sadducees,
He says, you err. Do you not therefore err?
Why? Number one, because you know not the Scriptures.
You refuse to allow the Scriptures to dictate your belief.
I hope that we'd never be there.
I hope that we'd be humble enough to say,
it's the Bible that's going to tell me what to believe.
It's not me that's going to misinterpret or misapply Scripture
to make it fit what I want to believe.
There are people that twist Scriptures all kinds of ways
to try to make it fit what they want to do.
And we must understand that this is one of the great dangers
that is revealed to us with regard to what leads into error,
what leads into being deceived,
is not having the knowledge of the Scriptures.
Notice what he says is really the second reason
that led to their deception at the end of verse 24,
neither the power of God.
They did not know the power of God.
Now with regard to the answer in verse 24,
I want you to understand,
Jesus is not giving these two truths in verse 24
to answer their question about whose wife shall she be.
He'll answer that in a moment.
He's giving this truth because of their error
with regard to the resurrection.
He's fixing their doctrine.
He's correcting their belief.
Now, they didn't believe in the resurrection
because they didn't believe in the power of God.
How is it that this could happen?
Paul says in 1 Corinthians 15,
and I'll say some among you that there is no resurrection.
If Christ be not risen,
then our preaching is vain, our faith is vain,
but now is Christ risen, he says.
And so we find that as we notice here,
he says neither the power of God.
Now I want you just for a moment in your mind tonight
to think about these Sadducees
and they had the book of Moses
and we use that terminology to refer to the Pentateuch.
They had the first five books of the Bible
and they believed them
according to what they would say,
what they would acknowledge.
They held that the books of Moses were Scripture.
Is it not amazing
how in those first five books of the Bible,
God demonstrates His power in amazing ways?
How can you not know the power of God,
but read the Pentateuch?
Just the first pages of Genesis.
God said, let there be light.
And there was light.
How is that not a demonstration of the power of God?
So He can create everything out of nothing,
but He can't resurrect?
I mean, we could look at a whole host of things.
We understand we've studied through
the book of Genesis on Sunday evenings
for a long time now
and finished up chapter 22 this last Sunday evening.
But in so doing, we've learned many things
about how God revealed Himself to Abraham.
El Shaddai, the Almighty God.
Is anything too hard for me? He asks Abraham.
We find that you would begin to look
through the book of Exodus,
a reference to what Jesus will give here
in just a few moments in His answer to their question.
And we find that as we look at the book of Exodus
and you begin to read about the plagues,
is that not a demonstration of the power of God?
I mean, even the Egyptians
recognize this is the finger of God.
They recognize this power.
And here are these religious leaders.
We believe the book of Moses.
We have the first five books.
But we don't believe in the resurrection.
But yet, they're going to corner Jesus and say,
in the resurrection, when they shall rise,
whose wife shall she be?
And Jesus says,
do you not therefore err?
Number one, because you know not the Scriptures.
Number two, because you know not the power of God.
I hope tonight that we would be absolutely
convinced of God's power.
That there is nothing too hard for Him.
That He is able to do exceeding abundantly
above all that we ask or think.
That as we understand,
even as we started our Sunday School series
on the miracles of Jesus Christ,
that with God, nothing shall be impossible.
Indeed, we think we have moments in our lives
where we look at circumstances
and we look at the mountains in our lives
and we say, how can we ever deal with this?
How can this ever?
Don't leave God out of the equation.
Amen?
Because He's the God of the impossible.
And here, what led to them being in error,
what led to them being deceived,
was two-fold.
They did not know the Scriptures,
and they did not know the power of God.
Jesus answered the question that they asked
in verse 23,
and I believe it's gracious of our Savior to do so,
but we find that He corrected their wrong doctrine
as I mentioned a moment ago.
And it's very interesting that He did so
by using the Pentateuch.
The very books of the Bible
that these Sadducees would have claimed to believe,
Jesus is going to use those very books
to answer and to correct their doctrine.
Notice in v. 25-26,
for when they shall rise from the dead.
Don't you love how Jesus says that?
It's not a matter of if.
Yes, they will. Why?
Because He understands,
I am the resurrection and the life.
Is that not what He said?
If you look at the seven I Am statements
of Jesus in the book of John,
one of them is I Am the resurrection and the life.
For when they shall rise from the dead,
they neither marry nor are given in marriage,
but are as the angels which are in heaven
and as touching the dead that they rise.
So we find again, He gives the answer
and He really focuses in on this thing
of the resurrection.
Because it was their doctrine that was wrong
and they had been led into this error
and into this deception.
And so we find that He tells them,
listen, they're not going to marry.
They're not going to be given in marriage.
They'll be like the angels which are in heaven.
Again, this is a truth that is revealed to us here.
Obviously, this is not the truth
that He's referring to when He says,
you know not the Scriptures.
The truth that He's referring to
when He says, you know not the Scriptures,
is the truth of the resurrection.
And so He says, for when they shall rise from the dead,
and He gives the answer with regard to the marriage
that is asked in v. 23.
Then we come to v. 26 and He says,
and as touching the dead that they rise.
You see how He's focusing on that thing of the resurrection?
Listen, it's so vital.
We understand that the resurrection of Jesus Christ is...
He is the cornerstone of our faith.
I mentioned 1 Corinthians 15 a few moments ago.
If Christ be not risen,
there's no reason for us to even
think about meeting.
It's pointless.
But He is risen.
He is risen indeed,
as Luke 24 tells us.
And notice, he says,
have ye not read,
and what does he say?
In the book of Moses.
Don't you love that?
Our Lord had such a way
of answering the questions
and really dealing with people in grace.
Speaking, we mentioned on Sunday morning
about the importance of our speech
being always with grace
and how they observe the graciousness
of the speech of Jesus.
But He says, have ye not read
in the book of Moses
how in the bush God spake unto Him?
What's He talking about?
Exodus?
Remember the burning bush?
Remember Moses?
He's referring to an account
that they would have absolutely
been familiar with.
And He says this,
that how in the bush God spake unto Him
saying, I am the God of Abraham
and the God of Isaac
and the God of Jacob.
Now, when God Almighty appears to Moses
in that portion of Scripture
in Exodus chapter 3,
we find that at that point,
these men that are mentioned here,
Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob,
they had died physically.
Correct?
You can read of it in the book of Genesis.
You can understand of their death.
And you can look to the places
in which they were buried.
And we find that they no doubt
had been familiar with this,
but they did not connect the dots.
Remember, they did not allow
the Scripture to dictate their belief.
He is the God of Abraham,
the God of Isaac,
the God of Jacob.
Notice what He says.
He is not the God of the dead,
but the God of the living.
He's the God of the living.
And then He says again,
ye therefore do greatly err.
Again, as we think about this subject
of deception and we notice
in this passage of Scripture
how that Jesus deals with a group of people
that have been deceived.
And as we dig in and say,
okay, why have they been deceived?
What is it that led to their deception?
And we answer the question
with that twofold answer from verse 24
of not knowing the Scriptures
nor the power of God.
We find that this gives us insight
as to how we can guard against deception.
How can we guard against deception?
Remember, He says be not deceived.
Remember, He says that there are many
that lie in wait to deceive.
He says in the last times
that evil men and seducers
are going to wax worse and worse
deceiving and being deceived.
And so we understand
that all of these warnings
have been given to us
with regard to this age of deception.
And so what do we do?
How do we come to a place
where we are prepared for this deception?
I would say simply this,
know the book.
Know the book.
Know the truth.
Notice what John 5 says.
Turn over, if you will, to the book of John.
We'll look at three passages of Scripture
that will be done tonight
and enter into our prayer time.
John 5 and verse 39.
Here again in this passage of Scripture,
we find that Jesus is speaking here
and a discourse is going on
and of course, dealing with some of those
religious leaders of the day again.
And He says this in verse 39,
Search the Scriptures,
for in them ye think
ye have eternal life.
And they are they which testify of Me.
Search the Scriptures.
Study the Word of God.
Dig in.
And we find that as we study
and search the Scriptures,
that we allow the Scriptures
to dictate our belief.
When we find that we're in a place
where I come to a passage of Scripture
and there's something different
that I believed prior to reading
this portion of Scripture,
and God, as I'm reading the Word of God,
the Holy Spirit of God is teaching me
and illumining the Scripture to me,
and I say, that's different than what I believe.
Who's right? Me or God?
We know the answer. God is right.
And so what must I do?
I must change my belief.
I must align my belief with the Bible.
I do not seek to twist and manipulate Scripture
to make it say what I want it to say
so that I can continue to believe
what I want to believe.
No.
Let God be true.
Let every man a liar.
Let God's Word stand.
So we need to search the Scriptures.
We're familiar with 2 Timothy 2.
In 2 Timothy 2, in v. 15,
Paul is giving this admonition
to his son in the faith
and he tells him to study.
Study to show thyself approved unto God.
A workman that needeth not to be ashamed,
rightly dividing the Word of Truth.
Some people don't like study.
I'm not talking about Bible study.
I'm just talking about study in general.
Study is hard work.
If you're going to study something,
you're going to dig into it.
Some people love studying.
But a lot of people don't like studying.
I remember in Bible college,
there was one professor in particular.
We had a couple of professors that were really kind.
They would give us some insight
as to what our final would be in our classes
and they would tell us,
know these things, so on and so forth,
and give you kind of a study guide
of what to study to be prepared for the final.
And we had one professor
that every class I ever took with that man,
every time we'd come to the week before finals,
he would say this,
know everything.
Well, that's helpful, isn't it?
Thank you.
And that's what he would say.
And he wanted to help us understand
the importance of study.
Study. Know it.
Study to show thyself approved unto God.
A workman, notice what he says,
that needeth not to be ashamed,
rightly dividing the word of truth.
Listen, when you've studied the word of God
and you've come to the conclusion
as to what God's Word says,
you don't have to be ashamed of it.
It doesn't matter that there are other groups of people
that will disagree.
It doesn't matter that the popular opinion
is in disagreement with what you have concluded scripturally.
You have studied and you have concluded
that this is what God says on the subject.
You don't need to be ashamed about it.
God said it.
That settles it.
I know there's a saying that was very popular years ago.
God said it.
I believe it.
That settles it.
I think that's cute.
I think it's good.
But the reality is that whether you believe it or not,
it doesn't really matter.
Because God said it and that settles it.
Amen?
I don't believe it.
Well, God ain't gonna change.
Right?
It's just not gonna happen.
And so we ought to just believe what God says.
Let's finish in 2 Peter 3.
2 Peter 3, I want you to notice
at the end of this portion of Scripture
that Peter's gonna give these folks
some really important truth.
In the book of 1 Peter,
if I could just really quickly summarize,
in the book of 1 Peter,
that book is being written to those folks
really that are in need of encouragement.
They had been scattered abroad
because of the persecution under Nero
and all that was going on,
and they were in need of encouragement.
Can I tell you, there are times
that we're in need of encouragement.
And I'm thankful that God's Word encourages us.
In 2 Peter, really the idea
in the main thrust of the book
is not one given because of a need of encouragement.
Rather, they were in need of instruction.
Again, I'm thankful there are times
that we need instruction.
And God's Word provides instruction.
In the book of 2 Peter,
as you study through the book,
you'll find that there are many things
that are given to us about false teachers
and about their behavior
and about how they operate
and so on and so forth.
And these believers needed instruction.
And God, in His infinite wisdom,
He spoke through Peter
to write the book of 2 Peter.
It is Scripture.
It's been preserved for us.
And oh, how beneficial it is for us
to have the instruction that's contained therein.
As He ends the book,
notice the last two verses of 2 Peter 3,
verses 17 and 18.
The Bible says this.
Ye, therefore, beloved,
seeing ye know these things before,
beware, lest ye, also being led away
with the error of the wicked,
fall from your own steadfastness.
You see that word error?
It's not the same exact Greek word,
but it's the Greek word that is derived,
excuse me, the Greek word deceive
that we've been mentioning throughout this study
is derived from this word.
that's translated error.
And guess what a valid translation
of that Greek word is?
Not only error, but deceive.
So guess what?
He's saying to these believers
that are in need of instruction
that they have known these things
and they need to take warning
and to beware lest ye also
being led away with the error of the wicked
fall from your own steadfastness.
What's the answer?
But grow in grace
and in the knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.
To Him be glory both now and forever.
Amen.
How do I avoid being led away
with the error of the wicked?
I better grow.
And I better grow in the grace
and in the knowledge of our Lord and Savior
Jesus Christ.
How am I going to grow?
Well, back in 1 Peter,
he said in chapter 2 and verse number 2,
as newborn babes,
desire the sincere milk of the Word
that ye may grow thereby.
The Word of God produces growth
in our lives spiritually.
You're not going to grow spiritually
apart from this book.
It is this book that provides
the spiritual growth that we need.
So these Sadducees, they come to Jesus.
I think, man, we got them now.
Let's see what Jesus is going to say
about this one.
Let's paint this scenario
and here's the situation.
There were seven brethren
and they go through the scenario.
So in the resurrection,
whose wife shall she be?
Jesus said, you guys have been deceived.
You therefore greatly err.
You've been deceived.
Why? What led to their deception?
You don't know the Scriptures.
Neither the power of God.
They had the Scriptures.
They referred to the Scriptures.
But they didn't know them.
They didn't allow the Scriptures
to dictate their belief.
They had their own beliefs.
They had their own traditions.
And they said, how are we going to make this
fit what we believe?
This evening, I hope that we would not
be led away with the error of the wicked one.
We understand that we're living
in an age of deception.
They're lying in wait to deceive.
There are many deceivers.
What must we do?
We must know the book.
He said, you don't know the book.
Oh, that it would never be said of us.
That we don't know the book
or we don't know the power of God.
But that we would understand
that God's given us this book
and oh, what a joy it is to study it.
To search it.
You find the truth that God gives us.
And when people come and make their statements
and try to lead us into error,
we say, no, no, no.
The Bible says,
and we have studied
and we do not need to be ashamed.
Amen?
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
Thank You for this conversation
that was recorded for us
that helps us.
That helps us to understand
the ways in which we can be led into error.
Led into being deceived.
Help us to know the Word of God.
Help us to know the power of God.
I believe that as we would have
a knowledge of Your Word,
that we also would have a knowledge of Your power.
For Your power is not only declared in Your Word,
but it's demonstrated over and over
through this precious book.
Thank You for the privilege of prayer.
We pray You've commanded us,
You've invited us to enter into Your presence.
And we demonstrate our dependence upon You
recognizing that we can't, but You can.
And God, I pray that as we engage
in corporate intercessory prayer,
that You'd meet with us.
Encourage us.
Help us to labor in prayer.
And we'll thank You for it.
In Christ's name we pray,
Amen.