And we should stand in awe of Him because of His power being displayed.
And then the verse finishes this way.
Praise Him according to His excellent greatness.
We are to praise God because of who He is, His nature, His character,
the fact that, yes, He has all power and all knowledge and wisdom,
and He's everywhere present.
But we're to praise God because He is holy, because He is just and righteous,
and with Him is forgiveness, and He's ready to pardon and to forgive.
And He's a God who is full of compassion.
And often we see throughout the gospel records how the Lord Jesus Christ was moved with compassion.
And what a blessing to understand this morning
and to be able to give God the glory and the praise that is due to His name
because of who He is and because of what He has done.
A familiar psalm to many of us is Psalm 48 where the Bible begins,
and really it's a song that we sing in Psalm 48.
Great is the Lord, and greatly to be praised,
in the city of our God and the mountain of His holiness.
Beautiful for situation, the joy of the whole earth,
is Mount Zion on the sides of the north, the city of the great King.
And we see the rejoicing and the praising that begins in Psalm 48,
but I'm always reminded of verse 14 where the Bible says,
For this God is our God forever and ever.
He will be our guide even unto death.
What a blessing to know personally the God of the universe,
that He is my God and that He is interested in me as an individual.
He's interested in you as an individual.
He knows where you are.
He knows the difficulties.
We've been studying through 2 Corinthians.
This morning we'll be somewhere else, but we've been studying through 2 Corinthians.
This calendar year as we've dealt with the subject matter of the theme for our church,
His grace is sufficient.
And we spoke about the wonderful promise that we read in 2 Corinthians chapter 12,
but then as we got into the first chapter,
we started dealing with the truth that with suffering comes comfort,
and our God knows what we're dealing with, and He loves us, and He comforts us,
and He comes alongside us, and He provides for us the encouragement that we need.
And what a blessing that is.
And then last week we looked at that passage of Scripture
where Paul was sharing with us such transparent experience
that he had with his relationship with the believers in Corinth
and how he had been misunderstood.
And we asked the question, how do we respond when we're misunderstood?
And God gives us and provides for us wonderful truth in His Word,
and He's interested in us as individuals, and He guides us.
If we'll allow Him, He will guide us.
And what a blessing to understand that truth this morning.
We serve a wonderful Savior.
We study through the Scriptures, and especially the Gospel records,
and we have the opportunity to see the life and ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And as we have an opportunity to study through the Gospel records,
we see that our Savior moved with purpose,
and we find that He walked in humility and obedience.
We find that He was very purposed in all that He did,
and though there were many instances where multitudes would throng Him
and He would deal with feeding the thousands,
we find that many times throughout the Gospel records
that Jesus records for us His interaction with individuals.
And what a joy to consider this morning that our God is interested in us as individuals.
He loves the entire world.
It's a global truth that every person that's walking upon the face of the earth today,
that God loves them and that God desires for them to be saved by His wonderful grace.
But we understand that He's interested in us as individuals.
He knows us personally.
He knows your thoughts.
He knows everything about you.
And He says to us that we're to cast our care upon Him, for He careth for us.
The Lord Jesus Christ lived a perfect and a sinless life,
and He performed miracles and proved His deity that He indeed is God in flesh.
And we find that His whole purpose of coming to this sin-cursed world
was to go to that cruel cross.
We understand that He was born to die.
We understand that even as Paul would say in the book of Galatians
that when the fullness of time was come,
God sent forth His Son for what purpose?
To go to a cross to redeem them.
How could He redeem us?
Only through going to the cross and shedding His blood.
Many times during His earthly ministry He shared with His disciples
about the plans and about the events that would transpire in days ahead.
And He talked to them openly about His going to Jerusalem
and dying upon the cross and being buried and then resurrecting.
They didn't always track and follow what Jesus was sharing,
but we understand that Jesus was providing them with truth.
We find that He gave them, in John chapter number 13,
as they're nearing His time to go to the cross,
He gives them a great example of servanthood
and being a servant when He washed the feet of the disciples
and gave them instruction.
And we find that we enter into the 14th chapter,
and Jesus begins this way in John 14.
In verse number one, He says,
Let not your heart be troubled.
The reality is that all that Jesus had been explaining to His disciples
and all that was getting ready to transpire,
that Jesus knew the impact that these events would have upon His own disciples.
And He says, Let not your heart be troubled.
Now, there are times in which we may be able to say to someone else,
we may be able to say, My heart's not troubled,
but God knows if our heart is troubled.
And He says, Let not your heart be troubled.
And then He gives one of the most impactful promises
that we read with regard to His return.
And He says to the disciples, and it's preserved for us today,
and it's been a passage of Scripture that's given great hope
and assurance and confidence to the people of God throughout the centuries.
Jesus says, Let not your heart be troubled.
You believe in God? Believe also in Me.
In My Father's house are many mansions.
If it were not so, I would have told you.
I go, notice where He says, to prepare a place for you.
And I want to draw your attention to verse number three.
And if I go and prepare a place for you,
I will come again and receive you unto Myself,
that where I am, there ye may be also.
I want you to note those four words in verse number three
where Jesus says, I will come again.
This, as we remember this promise,
and we look at this passage for just a moment
by way of introduction this morning,
and we consider this thought that Jesus is coming again,
we find that He says, I will come again.
He didn't say, I might come again.
He didn't say, I may come again.
He said, I will.
There's an aspect of this promise that gives us this certainty,
this confidence.
And God wants us to be confident.
He wants us to be certain of His promise.
And we read last week in 2 Corinthians chapter number 1
as we were dealing with that passage of Scripture
where Paul was misunderstood,
where he spoke of the promises of God in 2 Corinthians 1.20.
And he says, for all the promises of God in Him are yea,
and in Him, amen, under the glory of God by us.
And he says, I will come again.
It's a certain truth.
It's a certain promise that God has given to us.
But I want you to also notice that he says, I.
I will come again.
I'm thankful for that certainty that I will.
But when I think about I, Jesus says,
I personally am going to come again.
We'll look at it in just a few moments.
But in Acts 1, the angel said,
this same Jesus shall come in like manner.
We find that in 1 Thessalonians chapter 4,
the Bible says, the Lord Himself.
What a joy to know that Jesus is coming again.
We look at the truth of God's word,
and it's a promise that is so precious to us.
And it's recorded over and over in references
that we have throughout the scriptures
with regard to this promise.
I'm reminded of Hebrews chapter number 10
and verse number 37 where the Bible says,
for yet a little while,
and He that shall come will come
and will not tarry.
Jesus came the first time right on time.
And He's going to come the second time right on time.
No one's going to delay His arrival.
No one is going to stay His coming.
No, we find that He's going to come.
The Bible says, yet a little while.
I don't know.
You don't know how long a while is.
But we know that God's timetable is perfect.
In fact, we find in Acts 1,
it's not for us to know the hour of His return.
He's given us marching orders,
and we'll look at some of those things in just a moment.
But what a joy to be reminded for yet a little while,
and he that shall come will come and will not tarry.
In James chapter 5 and verse number 8,
the Bible says, be also patient.
Establish your hearts for the coming of the Lord draweth nigh.
The Bible clearly teaches that Jesus is coming again.
I stand here today, and I believe that we're
living in the last days.
In fact, as we had for our theme in 2024 continue,
and I had the privilege of preaching
through 1 and 2 Timothy on Sunday mornings,
and we came to 2 Timothy chapter 3,
and this know also in the last days
there shall be perilous times.
And God gives us all of that truth
with regard to the days in which we're living.
And we understand that we're living in the last days.
And I believe this morning that Jesus
could return at any moment.
In fact, I believe that he could return before I finished
the sermon this morning.
His return is imminent.
And we find that the Bible clearly teaches us
that Jesus is coming again.
I've often, as I've considered that wonderful Bible promise,
I've considered the question, are you ready?
When someone asks you the question, are you ready,
it's a question that requires context.
Am I ready for what?
And we find that this morning as we consider this truth
that Jesus is coming again, I wonder this morning,
are we ready for his return?
Are we ready that if today were the day,
are we ready to see our Savior face to face?
We find that the great passage of scripture
in 1 Thessalonians chapter 4 that is so familiar to us,
and I'll read it in just a moment,
and begin to just understand how God wants us
to be confident of this truth.
He wants us to be comforted by this truth.
In 1 Thessalonians 4, again, it's a familiar passage
of scripture, but there was much confusion
with regard to the timing of Christ's return
and the truth of this end times eschatology, if you will.
And we read in 1 and 2 Thessalonians much information
that is given to us with regard to eschatology,
and as Paul, under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God
is instructing the church at Thessalonica.
Notice with me in 1 Thessalonians 4 and verse 13,
it begins this way,
but I would not have you to be ignorant, brethren,
concerning them which are asleep,
that you sorrow not, even as others which have no hope.
For if we believe that Jesus died and rose again,
even so them also which sleep in Jesus
will God bring with him.
For this we say unto you by the word of the Lord,
that we which are alive and remain
unto the coming of the Lord shall not prevent them
which are asleep.
For the Lord himself shall descend from heaven
with a shout, the voice of the archangel,
with the trump of God and the dead in Christ
shall rise first.
Then we which are alive and remain
shall be caught up together with them in the clouds
to meet the Lord in the air.
And notice these precious words,
and so shall we ever be with the Lord.
Wherefore, comfort one another with these words.
And oh, how comforting these words are
as God provides for us the order, if you will,
of the resurrection that the dead in Christ
shall rise first at the end of verse 16.
Then we which are alive and remain
shall be, notice, caught up,
referring to and understanding this reference
to the rapture of the church.
And I hope, I hope that I'm alive during the rapture.
That'd be a wonderful thing.
And it says to be caught up together,
notice, with them where?
In the clouds to meet the Lord in the air.
And so shall we ever be with the Lord.
This is the reference of the rapture.
We're talking about Jesus coming again.
We understand that his return,
there's these two aspects.
There's the rapture of the church,
and then there's the return of the Lord Jesus Christ
with his saints at the end of the tribulation.
We read that in Revelation chapter 19,
when he comes all the way back to earth
and the battle of Armageddon and all that takes place.
And we read of that in Revelation 19,
but the focus of what we're dealing with this morning
is dealing with that aspect of the rapture,
when the church, the believers,
we talk about what is the church?
Well, the church is the body of believers.
How do I become a member of a church?
Well, I have to be saved by the grace of God.
I have to be baptized by immersion.
And I voluntarily join myself with a church
to carry out the great commission.
A church is made up of saved, baptized believers.
And we find that the church,
the believers will be raptured.
We do not know the time of the rapture.
It will be sudden, it is imminent.
It'll be like, as we read in 1 Thessalonians 5,
a thief in the night.
We'll deal with that in just a moment.
And we find that this event
is the next event on God's prophetic calendar.
What we believe must impact how we behave.
What we believe to be true
impacts how we live our day, how we behave.
The Bible clearly reveals to us this truth
that it would impact our belief,
that we would believe.
Remember already that Paul said in verse 13,
I would not have you to be ignorant, brethren.
He wants us, God wants us to be informed.
He says in verse number 15,
this we say unto you by the word of the Lord.
This is not Paul just simply offering an opinion
to an answer that the church in Thessalonica
has posed to him.
No, this is God giving to his people truth
that would impact how we would live our lives
because belief impacts behavior.
So I ask myself the question,
and I ask you the question this morning as well,
how does the wonderful promise
that Jesus is coming again impact my daily behavior?
How does the wonderful promise
that Jesus is coming again impact your daily behavior?
In 1 John 2, God gives us this record
that John, who by the way,
heard the words of Jesus spoken in John 14
that we referenced a moment ago.
John was literally there and he heard Jesus say,
let not your heart be troubled.
He heard Jesus say, I'm going to prepare a place for you.
He heard Jesus say, I will come again
and receive you unto myself
that where I am there you may be also.
John heard those precious words
and John was the one that God used
to record those precious words
in the gospel of John that we read just a moment ago.
So not only did he hear them verbally as they were spoken,
but he had the privilege of writing them
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God
to have for us the gospel of John.
And then as he's writing this epistle
in 1 John 2, notice in verse 28,
John says, and now little children abide in him.
Notice it says that when he shall appear,
I believe that John had all of the confidence
and assurance that any individual could have
that Jesus was coming again.
He heard it spoken with his own ears.
He knew that what Jesus said was true.
He knew that he could not lie, that he's God.
And he says that when he shall appear,
notice we may have confidence
and not be ashamed before him at his coming.
I'll be honest with you this morning,
this verse has always challenged me.
This verse has always reminded me
that it is possible for a child of God
to be ashamed before him when he comes.
Oh, I don't want to be in that position.
Oh, this morning, I hope that you say,
I don't want to be in that position.
I don't want to be embarrassed.
I don't want to be ashamed of my savior when he comes.
Notice in verse 29, if you know that he is righteous,
you know that everyone that do with righteousness
is born of him, enter the third chapter.
Behold, what matter of love
the father hath bestowed upon us.
He's actually saying to start the service,
Jesus loves even me.
Oh, what love the father hath bestowed upon us.
Notice that we should be called the sons of God.
Therefore the world knoweth us not
because it knew him not.
Beloved, now are we the sons of God.
And it doth not yet appear what we shall be,
but we know that again, notice the words,
when he shall appear, we shall be.
we shall be like Him, for we shall see Him as He is.
And every man that hath this hope in him purifieth himself,
even as he is pure."
When you read verse number three,
you're reminded of the truth that I mentioned a moment ago
that belief will impact behavior.
Every man that hath this hope, that believes this truth,
that believes that Jesus is going to appear,
that we shall be like Him,
that that individual believer that has that hope,
that he purifies himself because his Savior is pure.
It impacts our behavior.
As I read verse two, I'm reminded
of what we read in 1 Corinthians 15,
and in a moment, until we can live an eye,
and we read how that this mortal shall put on immortality
and this corruption shall be put on incorruption,
that we shall be changed.
What a blessing.
We shall be like Him, it says in verse number two.
We asked the question this morning,
how does the promise that Jesus is coming again,
how does that impact us?
How does it impact me daily?
Do I live each day with the awareness
that Jesus could come today?
I know that it's a truth that if you were to be asked
this morning by an individual,
someday this week by some random person
that just approaches you and says,
hey, listen, do you believe that Jesus is coming again?
I think that each of us would without hesitation, yes.
We believe it.
We know it to be true.
But we live in a busy world.
We have so many responsibilities.
We're being pulled in so many different directions.
And the reality is that because of those circumstances,
it may very well be that we could live days consecutively,
weeks, months, without even considering
that today could be the day.
And so how would it impact us?
Just a few thoughts this morning.
Number one, if you're taking notes,
the promise of Christ's return
should energize our service for him.
What do I mean by that?
Well, the reality is that I believe
that Jesus is coming again,
and you believe that Jesus is coming again,
and we read the scriptures,
and there's so many references,
many of which I've already looked to,
and many more that we could examine this morning.
And we see that his return is imminent,
that he could come at any moment.
And so that promise, that truth,
should energize our service for him.
The songwriter said it well when he said this,
work for the night is coming.
Work for the night is coming.
Listen, Jesus is coming again,
and we have a service, a work to do for him.
And this truth, this reality,
this promise should energize our service.
It should cause us to be more engaged
in doing the work that God has called us to do.
I'm reminded of the truth of Ephesians 5,
and verse number 16,
where we're told that we are to redeem the time
because the days are evil.
That we literally would make each day count,
that we would understand that the time
that God has given to us,
that life is precious,
that time is limited.
And we're to redeem the time because the days are evil.
I wanna remind you that Jesus said in Luke 19,
in verse number 13, he said this,
occupy till I come.
He's talking to those 10 servants.
There's a parable that is given to us
in that passage of Scripture,
but he uses those words at the end of that verse,
occupy till I come.
And what does that give us?
The idea of doing a work,
being busy about the work that he's given to us.
And I believe this morning
that the promise that Jesus could return today
should energize our service for him.
Listen, this morning, I'm thankful
that when Jesus appears,
when the trumpet of the Lord shall sound
and I'm raptured out of here
and I meet the Lord in the clouds,
if that happened today,
then I'm gonna ever, I'll be forever with my Savior,
the one who died for me.
We sing so often about seeing him face to face
and what a day that will be
and certainly it's gonna be a wonderful day.
But I recognize this morning
that once the rapture takes place,
once Jesus comes again,
I will never preach another sermon.
I will never, I should say,
the musician will never play another special,
the musician will never sing another special,
the nursery work,
I mean, the work that God has given to us to do.
I'm not gonna do it anymore.
Oh, we're gonna be in his presence
and we're gonna worship him for all of eternity.
I mean, we're gonna,
you look at Revelation 4 and 5
and what a scene it is.
We're gonna be with him,
we're gonna worship him and it's wonderful.
But the work that he's given to us
for this time, for this life will cease.
And so the promise of his return
should energize our service for him,
that we make every effort
to do what he's equipped us to do
and to be that good steward of his manifold grace.
Number two, the promise of Christ's return
should cause us to engage in evangelism.
Why do I say to engage in evangelism?
Why do I make the distinction
between engaging in evangelism
versus energizing our service?
Because certainly there is a connection
between the two that part of my service to Christ
is evangelizing the world
and we understand that.
But I focus specifically
on the second thought this morning
that his promise should cause us
to be engaged in evangelism
because I'll never tell a sinner about Christ
once the rapture takes place.
Oh, during the tribulation
there will be witnesses here upon the earth
that many will be saved during the tribulation.
But recognize this morning
that I'm not and you are not
any of those witnesses
that the Bible gives us record of
in the book of Revelation during the tribulation.
So if I'm going to engage in evangelism,
I must do it before the return of Christ.
I must do it before I lay down my life,
before I'm no longer here,
whether that's through rapture or through death,
but I must engage in evangelism.
Remember with me that after
the Lord Jesus Christ went to the cruel cross,
after He bled and suffered and died,
after He paid for your sin and for my sin,
that He went to that borrowed tomb.
And after three days,
He rose conquering sin, death, and the grave
and what wonderful day that was
and it's the reason that we meet on Sundays,
the first day of the week.
I mean, we serve a risen Savior, hallelujah.
But I want to remind you that after His resurrection
and during those days of His ministry
before He ascended to heaven,
that He gave the Great Commission.
The Great Commission remains today our mandate.
The Great Commission that was given by Christ
to the disciples continues to this very day
to be the mandate of Christ's church.
He said, I will build my church
and the gates of hell shall not prevail against it.
He said that His church is the pillar
and ground of the truth.
He says that His people are to be engaged in evangelism,
that we are to go forth and preach the gospel
to every creature.
Let me remind you, we're familiar with Matthew.
Let me remind you, 28,
but let's look at Acts chapter one just for a moment.
And I want you to look at Acts chapter one
and we, of course, are reminded
that each of the gospel records
have a reference to the Great Commission.
In the gospel of John,
Jesus mentions how that He was sent
and that He now sends us
and what a blessing to be sent by Christ.
What a blessing, as the disciples would say
in the book of Acts,
that we are His witnesses,
that as we'll study in several weeks,
maybe months as we study
through the book of 2 Corinthians,
that I am an ambassador.
We've been given the ministry of reconciliation.
In Acts 1, in verse number 6, the Bible says when they, therefore, were come together,
they asked of him, saying, Lord, wilt thou at this time restore again the kingdom to
Israel?
And he said unto them, It is not for you to know the times or the seasons, which the Father
hath put in his own power.
Understand that right now Israel's kind of been put on the back burner, if you will,
and God is dealing with the church.
Why?
Because Israel rejected.
He came to his own, but his own received him not, and they rejected Messiah, and the church
has been, Gentiles were grafted, Jewish people, Israelites can still be saved today.
They must be saved by the blood of Christ.
They must recognize Jesus as their Messiah.
But we find that during the tribulation, after the church is raptured, guess what, Jesus,
God is now dealing front and center with Israel.
And so he tells them, it's not for you to know the times or the seasons, which the Father
hath put in his own power.
But notice how he answers the question.
They ask, and he says, it's not for you to know, but ye shall, verse 8, receive power
after the Holy Ghost has come upon you, and ye shall be witnesses unto me both in Jerusalem
and all Judea and Samaria and unto the uttermost part of the earth.
And so he answers their question by saying, it's not for you to know, it's not for you
to be concerned about, but ye shall be.
This is what you should be focused on.
This is what you should be concerned with.
This is what your responsibility is.
And when, verse number 8, he had spoken these things, while they beheld, he was taken up
and a cloud received him out of their sight.
As I read the Bible, there are several passages of Scripture, several events that I come to
that I say something like this to myself, man, I wish I was there for that.
I mean, I just read a few days ago about the crossing of the Red Sea, oh man, I wish I
was there to see that.
I mean, you start looking through as you read the Bible and you read these great miracles
and you read about God's power being displayed, you say, oh, I wish I could have seen that,
I wish I was there to witness that.
And here, as I come to Acts chapter 1, that's a thought that I have.
Can you imagine being there, hearing the very words of Christ, and as he's speaking those
words he's taken up and out of your sight.
Wow.
Verse 10, while they looked steadfastly toward heaven, as he went up, behold, two men stood
by them in white apparel.
God looked steadfastly toward heaven as well, and I think you would too.
Notice what is said by these angels, ye men of Galilee, why stand ye gazing up into heaven?
This same Jesus, what did Jesus say in John 14, I will come again.
This same Jesus, which is taken up from you into heaven, shall so come in like manner
as ye have seen him go into heaven.
You think that impacted these disciples?
Oh, absolutely, absolutely.
They see the ascension, they remember the words, but you shall receive power, you shall
be witnesses unto me.
They remember those words, they remember the ascension, and then they hear this same Jesus
shall so come in like manner.
Probably reminding them of what they heard before the crucifixion, I will come again.
And we find that as you would trace the steps of the disciples through the book of Acts,
I am thoroughly convinced that the truth that was given to them in Acts 1 impacted how they
behaved and what they did.
The Bible says that they filled Jerusalem with their doctrine.
The Bible says that they turned the world upside down.
The Bible tells us that when the persecution came and intensified and reached that place
in Acts chapter 8 where the people were scattered, and remember, it wasn't the leaders that were
scattered, no, the leaders of the church stayed in Jerusalem, it was the people that were
scattered.
It wasn't Peter and James that were scattered, it was the people.
And when they were scattered abroad, the Bible says that they went everywhere preaching
the word.
The Bible records the missionary journeys.
The Bible records for us as Paul would make that wonderful declaration that we're so familiar
with in Romans 1 and verse 16, I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ, but you know he said
prior to that truth that he's not ashamed, he said that he was ready.
He was ready to do what?
Well, he was ready to go to Rome, he was ready to go there and to preach the gospel.
Paul understood that Christ was going to return.
He didn't know when, just like we don't know when.
But God used Paul to write many of the references that we've already acknowledged this morning,
the verses of Scripture.
Paul was aware of the truth and his belief impacted his behavior and he says I'm ready
to preach the gospel.
I mean, when you read about Paul on the missionary journeys and you read about his desire to
go to regions beyond and to preach the gospel because he understood that he had to engage
people with the gospel.
He had to engage in evangelism personally.
Second Peter chapter three, if you take a moment in your Bible to turn there and oftentimes
we read or reference at least verse number nine with regard to the promise that is given
to us there and the fact that God is not slack concerning his promise and I'm thankful for
that and I know that you are as well.
But I want to read the context here as we pick it up in verse number one in second Peter
chapter three and the Bible says this second epistle beloved I now write unto you in both
which I stir up your pure minds by way of remembrance.
They may be mindful of the words which were spoken before by the holy prophets and of
the commandment of us the apostles of the Lord and Savior knowing this first that there
shall come in the last days scoffers walking after their own lust.
Oh have we not seen that?
Maybe we've experienced it, scoffers.
The Bible says that these scoffers that are walking after their own lust and here's the
reference contextually what they say in verse number four where is the promise of his coming?
For since the fathers fell asleep all things continue as they were from the beginning of
the creation and notice what God tells us in verse number five for this they willingly
are ignorant of.
They don't want to know the truth because they want to keep believing what they're believing.
And it says that by the word of God the heavens were of old and the earth standing out of
the water and in the water whereby the world that then was being overflowed with water
perished.
You know what he references?
The flood.
The global flood.
That's what's referenced.
How many people deny the flood?
Many.
Verse seven, but the heavens and the earth which are now by the same word are kept in
store reserved unto fire against the day of judgment and perdition of ungodly men.
Read about the tribulation and God's wrath being poured out upon the wicked.
But beloved, notice verse number eight, be not ignorant of this one thing that one day
is with the Lord as a thousand years and a thousand years as one day.
Our God is outside of time.
He's outside of time.
He's eternal.
Though there are some that would say as he mentions in verse number four where's the
promise of his coming?
He says don't be ignorant of this truth.
Don't be ignorant of the fact that that one day is with the Lord as a thousand years and
a thousand years as one day.
Listen, Jesus is coming and he's going to come right on time.
And it says in verse number nine, and what a blessing this verse is, the Lord is not
slack concerning his promise as some men count slackness.
But notice what the Bible says, but as long suffering to usward, not willing that any
should perish, but that all should come to repentance.
God is not slack concerning his promise.
He is going to come again, but he's long suffering.
Why is he long suffering?
Well, because he's not willing that any should perish, but that all should come to repentance.
With that understanding in, in
2 Peter 3 and verse number 9, with the understanding of the heart of God, how that should impact
us that God is long-suffering.
He's not willing that any should perish, that all should come to repentance.
And when I understand the promise of Christ's return, that He says, I will come again, that
it should cause me, it should cause you to engage in evangelism.
Because the reality is in verse number 10, but the day of the Lord will come as a thief
in the night, that day is going to come.
And I don't know the day and neither do you, but we do know that we have opportunity now
to engage in the gospel, to engage in evangelism, to share the gospel with some neighbor, coworker,
relative, whomever it may be, that God would lead us into their path.
Interesting circumstances yesterday occurred, and I won't get into the details, but basically
a little accident right outside of the church driveway here, and unique circumstances, but
led to an opportunity to share gospel tracks and talk to one man about the Lord.
I could never orchestrate those circumstances.
The young man, who was 18 years old, is from another country.
He's here in this country studying at Virginia Tech, and he was just here literally heading
to a bus stop to take a bus back, was able to share a gospel track with him.
God gives us opportunities, but we must engage in evangelism.
We must understand this morning that the gospel is powerful, that people are dying and they
need to hear the gospel.
I believe that according to 2 Thessalonians, that those that have heard and have rejected,
God's going to send them strong delusion.
They're not going to be able to say, okay, now I'm going to go ahead and get saved because
the rapture took place.
No, God's going to send them strong delusion, and we have an opportunity to give the gospel.
We've all read, I hope, we've all read at some point Revelation chapter 20.
We've read about the great white throne judgment, how sad that passage of Scripture is, but
it records for us an event that will take place at least a thousand and seven years
from now, but it will take place.
And this evening, or this morning, as I think about being engaged in evangelism, I want
to be motivated by this promise of Christ's return to do more, to be more engaged, because
people need the gospel.
People need to hear the truth of salvation.
For all have sinned and come short of the glory of God, but we have this treasure in
earthen vessels.
If our gospel be hid, it is hid to them that are lost, according to 2 Corinthians chapter
number 4.
So how does the promise, how does it impact us?
Well, it should energize our service, should cause us to engage in evangelism.
Chapter number 3 this morning, the promise of Christ's return should cause us to live
with expectancy, live with expectancy.
Here's the thought, today could be the day.
I mean, when we live every day with that expectancy that Christ could return, that today could
be the very day, that's going to change how I live today.
It's going to change what I do today.
It's going to impact, and we find that there should be this level of expectancy, and shall
I also say excitement.
I mean, what a joy to know the truth of God's word.
What a truth that the Lord himself shall descend from heaven, that we shall meet him in the
air.
I mean, I hope, as Brother Mershon often says, I'm not looking for the undertaker, but for
the upper taker.
I mean, oh, I hope that I'm alive when the rapture takes place, and I live with expectancy.
I think the enemy wants to lull us to sleep, to think, yeah, yeah, yeah, I know Christ
is going to come, but it's probably not going to happen anytime soon, and to kind of drive
our stakes real deep and just, no, no, no.
He is going to come, and it could be today, and I live with that expectancy.
I read 1 Thessalonians 4, 13 through 18 earlier in the message, but I want to reference back
to 1 Thessalonians chapter 5, and I want to share with you two truths that God gives us
with regard to this idea of expectancy.
In verse 1 of 1 Thessalonians 5, the Bible says,
That's the one example.
We read that just a moment ago in 2 Peter chapter 3 in verse number 10.
This example that God is giving to us with regard to the imminence of His return and
the expectancy that we should have, and then it says in verse number 3,
I remember when Holly was expecting Juliana, and I remember having this thought when she
would say to me, I'm having some contractions, and I had zero interest, I mean not point
anything zero, zero, zero interest in delivering a baby at home or in the car.
And so when she said, I'm having contractions, and I've been timing them, and they're this
many minutes apart, I said, it sounds like it's time to go to the doctor.
And we'd get in the car, we'd go to the hospital, and we learned, I think with Juliana, two
or three different times going to the hospital to find out that it was not really happening.
I was teaching Sunday school the Sunday before Juliana was born on Monday.
The entire time I'm teaching Sunday school, I can see Holly, and I can see in her countenance,
and I can see that she's not feeling real well.
And I'm really concerned.
I'm trying to get through the lesson as quickly as I can to find out what needs to happen
again.
I'm not interested in delivering a baby.
We headed over to the hospital, and they said, no, not yet.
Come back tomorrow.
And they ended up inducing her.
But, you know, there are many records you've read, no doubt.
You've heard the stories of babies that are delivered on the side of the road as they're
driving on the way to the hospital, and so on and so forth.
And listen, this thing, it says that, as travail upon a woman with child, it helps us to understand
this expectancy that we have, that Christ is soon going to return.
In 1 Corinthians chapter 15, a passage that I referenced earlier, the Bible says it this
way, in 1 Corinthians 15, in verse number 51, behold, I show you a mystery.
We shall not all sleep, but we shall all be changed in a moment, in the twinkling of an
eye, at the last trump.
For the trumpet shall sound, and the dead shall be raised incorruptible, and we shall
be changed.
For this corruptible must put on incorruption, and this moral must put on immortality.
We find in a moment, the twinkling of an eye.
See, the Lord has informed us of this glorious truth.
He wants us to believe that He's going to come again.
He wants us to be assured of it, to be confident that Jesus is coming again.
I mean, you can't talk me out of it, you can't convince me otherwise, why?
Because I've got this book right here, I've read the book, I've read where Jesus said
where we started this morning, I will come again.
I'm convinced, I believe, but my belief and your belief must have an impact on my behavior.
It must impact how I live my day, how I live and lead my life.
And I wonder this morning, when we rejoice that Jesus is coming again, and we should
rejoice that Jesus is coming again, but I wonder this morning, am I living, are you
living with the thought that today could be the day?
When I consider the wonderful promise that Jesus is coming again, does it energize my
service?
Does it come and say, I want to do more for Christ?
Do the words of the song, work for the night is coming, ring in my mind, because time is
limited.
It's precious, but it's limited, and it should energize my service.
It should cause me to engage in evangelism, that I should be reminded that the command
that Christ gave just prior to His ascension is the mandate for His church.
church, that we're to go and preach the gospel to every creature, that we're to be engaged
in evangelism, and then do I live with expectancy? I mean, today could be the day. What a great
truth. As we live each day, help us to live with these four words in our mind, I will
come again. Jesus is coming again. Are you ready? Are you ready? Are you saved? Do you
know Christ as your personal Savior? I mean, you have recognized that you're a sinner,
for all have sinned and come short of the glory of God, but you recognize that there's
a penalty, a consequence for sin, for the wage of sin is death. Jesus died in your place.
He died for you. And he offers to you the free gift, the wage of sin is death, but the
gift of God's eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord, for whosoever shall call upon the
name of the Lord shall be saved. You recognize that you're a sinner and he is the only Savior,
and you repent and you turn from your old ways of thinking of, I could be a good person,
or whatever your thoughts are with how you might be able to get to heaven, and recognize
it's not by works of righteousness which we have done. It's according to his mercy that
it saved us, and what a joy for the promises given to us that Jesus came to save sinners.
This morning, the first step for being ready for his return is that you're saved by the
grace of God, that you know, that you know, that you know. If you're to die today, that
heaven is your home. Oh, if you don't know for sure that heaven is your home, we'd love
to be able to chat with you and be able to take a Bible and show you how you can know
for sure that heaven is your home. You say, Pastor, I'm saved. I've been born again. Praise
the Lord. I'm so thankful for that. Let the promise impact your behavior. Let what you
believe impact how you live. Let our service be energized. Let us engage in evangelism,
and let us live with expectancy. Shall we pray? Father, we love you. We thank you for
loving us. We thank you for your word. We thank you for the opportunity to open your
word and to have this technology, to have a live stream service. Lord, I do pray that
you would work in hearts and lives, that you would help us, Lord, to be responsive in this
moment of invitation. Lord, that we would examine our own hearts and our own lives and
our daily behavior. As we examine, we desire to be able to correct whatever might be need
of correction, in need of correction. God, we would allow this wonderful promise to impact
how we live each day. If there's one that's not saved, Lord, I pray that you'd give us
an opportunity to talk with them about the gospel and about their need for Christ. I pray
that you'd be glorified through every decision that's made, for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Amen.