And our faith, really, as we live out our faith,
really what's happening is our faith is being observed.
And I mentioned this morning about some thoughts
with regard to others seeing Christ in us.
And I wonder this evening,
really at the beginning of the message,
the thought tonight is, do others see Christ in me?
Do others see Christ in me?
Ask ourselves that question.
And we desire that we would live our lives in such a way
that He alone would be exalted and magnified.
Do they see something different about us?
Are they intrigued by the way that we live our lives,
by the things that we do,
by the things that we perhaps do not engage in conversation?
Do they notice something different about our speech?
Do they notice something different
about how we respond to difficulties and adversities?
Is there something about our behavior
that is intriguing to those that are observing us?
Do they see and say,
something's different about this person?
I'm not sure exactly what it is.
I can't quite put my finger on it,
but something is different.
They don't respond in the office
the same way everyone else responds in the office.
They don't respond when someone does them wrong
in like fashion and so on and so forth.
And our lives are being observed.
We could ask ourselves this question this evening.
Are we the salt of the earth and the light of the world?
Jesus told us in Matthew chapter number five
in verses 13 through 16,
that we are the salt of the earth
and you're the light of the world.
And what great responsibility that is,
what great opportunity that presents.
And we could ask ourselves these questions this evening.
And the reality is that as we look
in Philippians chapter number four,
we're really gonna deal with a statement that Paul makes.
And when I think about the life of Paul,
I understand that his life was transformed.
In Acts chapter number nine, God tells us,
he records for us the conversion of Saul.
And we find that his life was transformed,
and I would say this, it was evidenced through his behavior.
In fact, if you were to read Acts nine
and you read the first portion of the chapter
and then you skip the middle section
and go toward the end,
you'd be confused as all get out
because you'd say, what happened to this guy?
What happened is that he met Jesus
and his life was changed forever.
And I think about this,
when I think about his life being transformed
and it being evidenced through his behavior,
I would say this, his faith was observable.
His faith was observable.
And no doubt you've heard people say,
do this and do that,
and their actions really don't even line up
with their instruction.
But we find that Paul was a man that lived out his faith.
He did not simply go and travel and teach and preach
and write and instruct,
but he was living out the very faith
that he was teaching to others.
Notice here in Philippians four in verse number nine,
we'll use this as our really text verse
into the message this evening.
Notice what Paul says,
those things which you have both learned
and received and heard,
and then notice this phrase,
and seen in me.
Do.
And the God of peace shall be with you.
As we think about this phrase of Scripture
when he says and seen in me,
I think about the impact of his behavior being observable.
I think about the importance of living out our faith.
It's one thing for us to teach and to give the words
and to give the instruction,
but when our faith becomes action
and we're living out the word of God,
we're living out our faith,
it is impactful.
And as we think about the text this evening,
he says and seen in me.
Think about the believers in Philippi
and think about the portion of Scripture
as we would not take the time this evening,
but if you went back to the book of Acts
in the 16th chapter and read about that entrance
into the city and the time in which they ministered
in Philippi and all of the uproar
and of course the imprisoned experience there
with Paul and Silas and understanding their singing
and glorifying God and just all that takes place
and Paul had an opportunity to minister
and there were some that had observed his behavior
and he says the things that not only you have learned
and received and heard,
but the things that you have seen in me.
As we begin 2022 and embark on a new year,
I wanna be challenged to live out my faith.
I wanna challenge each of us this evening
to live out our faith.
Others need to see Jesus in us.
They need to see that there's something different about us.
They need to see that when we deal with difficulties
and trials, that our God is real.
That it's not just a book of theory,
it's not just that we go through and say,
oh, just pray about it and just this and so on and so forth,
but then when the trouble comes knocking on our door,
we just kind of fall apart and they say,
well, what's different about you than me?
Do you understand what I'm saying?
And this evening, as we think about these truths
of living out our faith and being a doer of the word,
I really wanna be challenged
and I'm gonna share with you three particular areas
in which I think that it would be appropriate
for us to deal with and at the end of the message tonight,
I'm gonna give out a little card and I'm gonna ask you,
not necessarily to even fill out the card this evening,
but perhaps to take it and to pray over it and to meditate
and to ask the Lord to provide you with some direction
and I wanna challenge you to make some commitments to God.
I don't want these cards back.
I don't want you to put your name on them.
I want you to take the card
and I want you to put it in the Bible
and I wanna encourage you and as I remember,
I will seek to on a monthly basis,
just kind of mention, hey, how are we?
What kind of a monthly checkup, if you will?
How are we doing with our goals?
Because we make commitments to the Lord.
We set goals and if we're not reminded of them,
we can soon forget them and then all of a sudden
in September, we're flipping through our Bible
and you find this tucked in some part of the scriptures.
And so we don't wanna do that.
Again, I'm not asking for these back.
I'm not asking for you to make some commitment to me.
I'm asking for us to before the Lord, make a commitment.
Three areas that we're gonna deal with.
The first one and I'm calling it my 2022 spiritual goals.
The first one is on prayer.
As believers, we have the privilege of prayer.
It is a unique privilege to every child of God
that we can enter into the very presence of God Almighty
and commune with him.
This unique privilege that is really reserved
for God's people, this unique privilege,
unfortunately is often neglected.
We've understood this, not only is it neglected,
but there are times that you will find that prayer
is one of those things that is used only
in time of emergency.
And that's not how God designed it to be.
We're to commune with him.
We're to have that fellowship with him.
The reality is that you've seen those things
that say in case of emergency, use this.
And maybe there's some things at your workplace
that are their medical type of equipment.
And you say, in case of emergency, use this
and perhaps you've been trained.
The door on the airplane is not to be used
unless it's in case of emergency, right?
You don't just go and open the door up
while you're at 25,000 feet.
That's not a good idea.
And so in case of emergency,
that's not how prayer is detailed in the word of God.
It's sad that there are times in which
it's tragedy or emergency that must enter into our lives
to really bring us to our knees.
But the reality is that we ought to have such a
pattern of prayer in our lives
that when that trial and that difficulty come,
it's just natural response.
It's not a last resort.
It's a first response.
It's a let's pray about this.
Let's seek the face of God.
Let's engage in intercessory prayer.
And let me say this,
as we look at these three particular areas
of the Christian life this evening
and make some commitments,
the reality is that I understand
I'm not suggesting in any one of these areas
that we're not doing it.
So please understand, I'm not suggesting that.
I'm just suggesting that we ought to evaluate it
and say, let's make a commitment to the Lord.
Think about these verses, Luke 18, dealing with prayer.
I want you to look at a few verses of Scripture with me.
And Luke chapter number 18 and verse number one,
in Luke 18 and verse number one,
the Bible says,
and he spake a parable unto them to this end.
Notice what he said,
that men ought always to pray and not to faint.
On Wednesday evening for about a month
or maybe six weeks this year, this past year in 2021,
I did a mini series on prayer, teach us to pray.
And I said this repeatedly through that message
or through that series of messages
that of all of the things that the disciples
could have asked the Lord Jesus Christ to teach them to do,
the only thing that we have recorded in the word of God
is that they said, teach us to pray.
Teach us to pray.
Let me say this, prayer is tough.
Prayer is hard work.
Distractions abound.
The enemy doesn't want us to pray.
Have you found in your life that prayer is difficult?
Have you found in your life that prayer is spiritual battle?
It seems as if, as those that are moms of children,
as soon as you think you have that time that you have
to be able to go and pray, something happens.
Those that no longer have little kids,
there's something else that comes up.
There's a phone call, there's a text message,
there's a notification.
I think that technology is wonderful,
but sometimes it's such a hindrance.
You know, there are times in which we ought to be able
to take these devices and we ought to be able to unplug.
Like, go in and say, do not disturb,
turn off notifications, however your phone allows you
to do so, and put it aside and just get alone with God.
But what happens is we start to pray
and we've not disconnected and then,
bzz, bzz, if you have it on vibrate like I do,
if you have it on some kind of other tone,
I don't know, there's a hundred thousand of them,
it seems like, but it's a distraction, is it not?
And the reality is that prayer is so important,
it's so vital.
John R. Rice wrote a book, Much Prayer, Much Power.
He wrote a book on prayer and in that book,
he spoke of this, he often was known of saying this,
much prayer, much power.
Little prayer, little power.
No prayer, no power.
Someone else said this, the only place that power
comes before prayer is in the dictionary.
The only place power comes before prayer is in the dictionary
and the reality is that men ought always to pray.
We know the truth of 1 Thessalonians 5 and verse 17,
the Bible says pray without ceasing.
To be in that continual spirit of prayer.
It doesn't mean that every waking moment of our day
that we're spent engaged in prayer,
but it means that we're so engaged in prayer
and we're in that spirit of prayer that at any moment,
we can just continue to have that dialogue with our Father.
That we're just in that such sweet, close communion with him.
Notice in 1 Timothy chapter two,
1 Timothy chapter number two,
and we'll look at all eight verses that start
this text of scripture, this great chapter,
and he deals with prayer and I want you to see
the priority that is placed upon prayer.
I've mentioned already that prayer is a unique privilege
that is reserved for the people of God
and what great joy is ours that we can enter
into the very presence of God Almighty,
that he actually invites us to enter into his presence.
It's never a bother, it's never a problem.
God wants us.
We sang on Friday evening as we took testimonies
and sang favorites, I must tell Jesus.
And after we sang that song, I said the wonderful thing
is that he wants us to tell him.
He invites us to tell him.
It's wonderful, it's glorious.
Notice in 1 Timothy two, I exhort therefore
that first of all, supplications, prayers,
intercessions, and giving of thanks be made for all men.
You notice where he says first of all, it's a priority.
If you don't plan to pray,
it's likely that you're not gonna pray.
If you do not plan to pray, if you don't have a time,
a place, if you're not intentional about prayer,
it's likely that it's never gonna happen
because things happen, right?
And the devil doesn't want us to pray.
Notice in verse number two, for kings
and for all that are in authority,
that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life
in all godliness and honesty.
I think if we'd be honest with one another
and with ourselves this evening,
we are guilty of complaining about
and criticizing our authorities
more than we are praying for them.
If we'd be honest tonight with ourselves,
with God, with one another,
we spend far more time criticizing and complaining
about our elected officials than we do praying for them.
It's just a sad reality of the state of the church.
It's where we are.
Verse three, for this is good and acceptable
in the sight of God our Savior.
Now when God tells us that something's good,
we ought to take heed to that, amen?
I mean, we ought to say, okay, draw my attention to that.
This is good, God is pleased with this.
Verse four, who will have all men to be saved
to come unto the knowledge of the truth.
Isn't that wonderful?
Whosoever will.
The gospel is available to everyone.
Those officials that make decisions
that we don't agree with, Jesus died for them.
He shed his precious blood so they'd be redeemed.
I understand that many of them reject.
Some of them, no doubt, have never even heard
a clear presentation of the gospel.
Verse number five, it says, for there is one God
and one mediator between God and men, the man Christ Jesus,
who gave himself a ransom for all
to be testified in due time,
whereunto I am ordained a preacher and an apostle.
I speak the truth in Christ and lie not,
a teacher of the Gentiles in faith and verity.
Notice verse eight.
I will, therefore, that men pray everywhere,
lifting up holy hands without wrath and doubting.
Prayer, asking and receiving, that was the title
of the book that John R. Rice wrote.
And you think about praying in faith
and believing that God hears and that God answers.
And what a blessing.
I mean, we have so many prayer promises
throughout the word of God.
Call unto me and I will answer thee
and show thee great and mighty things
which thou knowest not.
We think of Hebrews four and verse number 16
when the Bible says, let us, therefore,
come boldly unto the throne of grace
that we may obtain mercy and find grace
to help in time of need.
Prayer.
I ask this question, would you make a commitment to God?
Would I make a commitment to God
to spend a specific amount of time in prayer each day?
I have on the PowerPoint there five minutes per day,
10 minutes per day, or blank.
Because sometimes, some are maybe already praying
60 minutes a day.
And so to make a commitment to pray five minutes a day
would not be progress, right?
And I don't know how, what our commitments are.
I don't know, perhaps, if there are days that go by
where we've forgotten to pray.
The busyness of the schedule, we intended to,
we thought we would, but so many things came up.
But God chose, and by the way, God can,
because He's God, He chose that it was through
the means of prayer that it would move the hand of God.
So what He chose.
Prayer changes things.
The effectual, fervent prayer of a righteous man
availeth much, right?
And so prayer.
I'm gonna pass these cards out at the end
so you don't have to take all these things in your notes,
but I want you to think about that.
And would I make a commitment to God
to pray each day a certain amount of time
that I would just commit that time to God in prayer?
To praying on behalf of one another,
to interceding on the behalf of not only our church family,
but the missionaries that God enables us to support.
It's not just about putting money in an offering plate.
I'm thankful for your faithfulness in giving.
I'm thankful that we can support missionaries financially,
but they need our prayer support.
For them to know that we're praying for them
to be engaged in intercessory prayer.
It's work, it takes time.
The second area in which I would deal with tonight
when we think about my spiritual goals
would be that of Bible reading.
The reality is that it's not possible
that I'm going to take heed to that which I do not know.
Right?
I can't take heed to that which I do not know.
When we think about Bible reading, it's sad.
There are many today that would sit in churches
all across the nation and they have answered requests,
polls, surveys that have been taking place
and they've answered questions with regard
to how often they read their Bible.
And you will find that, shockingly, mind-boggling
is that very few people that sit in church every week
actually read their Bible regularly.
It's just sad.
It's such an encouragement.
I mentioned this this morning.
It's such an encouragement to me
when people are saying, hey, I was reading my Bible
and I have a question about this portion of Scripture.
When someone says, for the first time in my Christian life,
I read the Bible from cover to cover in its entirety.
That's encouraging.
And what a blessing.
I know that there are some that have read the Bible
through cover to cover annually.
You've done it many years in a row.
And you've already started and continue to do so
and you plan to do so.
But I think about this.
When I think about reading the Bible,
we understand that the Bible, the Word of God,
it reveals to us who God is.
How do I know God if I don't read His Word?
To know God is to know His Word, right?
God has told us who He is.
If we're depending upon the school systems
to tell us who God is, if we're depending upon Hollywood,
if we're depending upon the elected officials,
if we're depending on any person to tell us who God is,
it's gonna be different than what God's told us in His Word.
God has already revealed to us in His Word.
He's defined for us who He is.
And all we need to do is read the Word of God.
and we'll know who God is.
The Word of God reveals the plan of God.
It reveals God's plan.
We understand that God has a plan, He has a purpose.
He moves with purpose.
There are times in which we may deal with life
and we may say, I don't know what the plan is.
I don't know what God is doing,
but I can rest assured that God has a plan.
And God is not sitting in heaven saying,
oh, I didn't know that this was going to...
No, that never happens.
Nothing ever occurs to God.
He knows everything.
He has a plan for everything.
The Word of God provides direction.
The Word of God increases my faith.
The Word of God is so vital.
I did a little research
to determine the amount of time commitment
that would be necessary in order
to read the Bible through annually.
There are 1,189 chapters in the Bible.
If you divide that by the number of days in a year,
it's basically three and a quarter chapters per day.
It's really not a lot.
They say at an average rate of pulpit speed,
that probably wasn't my speed
because I'm a little faster, I think.
Mady tells me, pastor, you were talking fast
when you were preaching the other day.
Sometimes I gotta get on a little roll, you know?
And the reality is that they say it takes 52 hours
and 20 minutes to read the Old Testament,
18 hours and 20 minutes to read the New Testament.
So the total time commitment to read the entirety
of the Bible is 70 hours and 40 minutes.
You know that if you do the math, it's 12 minutes a day.
12 minutes a day.
There's a lot of things that we do
for a lot longer than 12 minutes a day, right?
Any of you guys have an iPhone
that tells you weekly what your screen time was?
Or did y'all just turn that thing off?
You know what I'm saying?
Because it tells you, right?
Your screen time went up by 27% this week,
and you're like, man, what was I doing on my phone?
You know, people spend, and I didn't do all the research,
and I've done it before,
but it's absolutely just sad
to see how many hours a day people spend on social media.
How many hours a day people spend watching,
fill in the blank, TV shows, movies, sports.
I'm not saying that any of those things in and of themselves
are wrong or wicked, but what I'm suggesting
is that how can we spend hours a day on social media
and on news and on fill in the blank,
and then say, well, I just didn't have time
to read God's Word?
None of us can make time.
It's absolutely impossible to make time.
We simply have to use our time,
and we have to plan our time.
12 minutes a day, that's not a lot.
It really isn't.
Notice some verses of Scripture.
First Timothy four.
First Timothy, chapter number four.
You understand this evening that I read my Bible through,
whether you read your Bible through or not.
Why do I make that statement?
Because the reality is that I wanna encourage you
to read your Bible because I know it will help you.
Right, it doesn't help me if every single person
in our church reads their Bible and I don't read my Bible.
It doesn't help me, right?
So for me to read my Bible through helps me,
and for you to read your Bible helps you.
Typically, I read the Bible through twice every year,
in the New Testament, a third and fourth time.
That's just what I do.
I'm not suggesting that's what somebody else should do.
I'm not suggesting, that's not what I've always done.
I remember the first year I ever read
the whole Bible through in one year.
I remember that as a new Christian
and being encouraged to read my Bible through in a year.
I remember the first time I ever did that.
I remember the first time I ever tried to do it
and didn't succeed, and what happens?
Well, for me, I got discouraged
because I saw that little checklist and I was behind
and I knew where I was supposed to be
and I got discouraged and I got overwhelmed.
And I've tried to encourage people,
listen, it's not about the quantity, it's about the quality.
If you can only read a chapter a day,
then read a chapter a day, but get something from it.
In 1 Timothy 4, in verse number 13,
the Bible says, till I come, give attendance to reading,
to exhortation, to doctrine.
No doubt, when he speaks of reading,
he's speaking of reading the Word of God.
Many books can inform, but only the Bible can transform.
A scholar of yesteryear said that of all of the volumes,
you remember they used to have encyclopedias
that were printed, now it's Wikipedia typically.
I think it was a few years ago that, what was it,
Britannica, is that the company that did the encyclopedias
all those years?
For the very first time, they didn't print out
a series of encyclopedia, because so many people
are using the internet and what have you.
But this particular theologian of yesteryear,
he said, of all of the books in my library,
and he listed a whole host of how many volumes he had,
he said, I could put all of those on this side of the table
and I could put the Bible over here
and the Bible's more valuable.
And it really is.
It's amazing to me, and I'm not against somebody
reading a novel, but it's amazing to me
how somebody can sit down and read a novel
in a couple of days and they say,
well, the Bible's just too big.
It changes our lives.
It's God's love letter to us, right?
You think about that.
Back in the day, if Mike and Elizabeth were here,
I would tell them before they started dating,
because they were giving me a hard time
a couple of weeks ago about how old I am.
There was a time when Holly and I were dating,
you know what we did?
We wrote notes to each other.
That was like using a piece of paper and a pen
and actually writing a note, right?
You know what that means.
Some people are like, we just text, we just email.
Used to be a time that you sent letters in the mail.
Many times, I would read those letters more than one time.
Why?
Because it was from the girl I loved.
And I wanted to read it and reread it,
and then after we got married,
she found a box of letters I wrote her,
and one night, she's like, hey, honey, look what I found.
Maybe I should read some of them.
I was like, I'm going to bed.
I said, what?
I'm just teasing.
But the reality is that this is God's love letter to us.
When my dad was in Desert Storm back in 1990, 1991,
they didn't have FaceTime, they didn't have internet
that was available for video conferencing
and all that sort of thing,
and they didn't even have reliable phone service
that we could talk.
And he was in Desert Storm,
I think it was about seven months altogether
that he was there, and I don't know exactly
how many letters I received from my dad during that time.
I think it was just two or three letters.
But I remember as a 10-year-old kid,
the excitement.
I got a letter from my dad.
How do we neglect it?
But yet, so many do.
2 Timothy 2 and verse 15 tells us to study.
Study what?
Study the Word of God to show ourselves approved.
It tells us, study to show thyself approved unto God,
a workman that needeth not to be ashamed,
rightly dividing the Word of truth.
I gotta read it if I'm gonna study it.
1 Peter 2 and verse number two says,
as newborn babes desire the sincere milk of the Word,
that ye may grow thereby.
2 Timothy 3 and verse 18 says,
but grow in grace in the knowledge of our Lord and Savior,
Jesus Christ, to whom be glory and honor forever and ever.
Amen.
This book produces growth in God's people.
And so the question this evening
with regard to Bible reading
is will we make a commitment to God
perhaps to read the book of Proverbs each month,
perhaps to read the New Testament in one year,
perhaps to read the entirety of God's Word in one year,
and make that commitment to God?
You say, well, I already do that.
Good.
Continue.
Maybe add to it.
I change it up year by year.
I think it was in 2018.
I read the Bible through twice,
but I read the book of Psalms every month.
It requires that you read five Psalms a day,
and you do that,
and you get through the whole book of Psalms each month.
Someone says, what do you do when you get to Psalm 119?
You spend more time reading.
It's really not a bad thing, right?
And so there's a whole host of things you can do.
Personally, I enjoy reading, starting in Genesis,
and going through Revelation, and then starting over.
That's what I personally enjoy.
That's what.
It works for me.
Some people enjoy reading the New Testament and the Old Testament at the same time.
Reading a chapter or two from the Old Testament, a chapter from the New Testament.
Some people, it just, whatever works for you.
But purpose to read the Word of God daily.
Make that purpose.
Make that commitment.
The third area this evening is the area of witnessing.
The reality tonight is that we have the truth and the world needs it.
We have the truth and the world needs it.
The reality is that being saved and having the truth, really more than making us prideful
or boastful or better, it really makes us indebted.
What did Paul say?
I'm a debtor.
Why?
Because God has entrusted something with me that needs to go to other people.
Just a few weeks ago, we dealt with the Christmas season, really just a week ago.
Many times you read through the accounts in Matthew and Luke.
In Luke chapter number two, we read of those shepherds.
It's always insightful to me that when the shepherds receive the great news that they
receive, the great message, the good tidings of great joy, the truth that is given to us
that is so impactful to me in that passage of Scripture is that the Bible says in verse
number 10,
I bring you good tidings of great joy which shall be to all people.
I bring you, but it shall be to all people.
And as believers, having this precious book, we are indebted.
We have a responsibility.
We have been commissioned by God and He promises to bless His Word.
Sometimes we say, well, it doesn't really work.
Leave the results to God.
Just keep sowing the seed.
Just keep sharing the Gospel.
I'll quickly read some verses of Scripture in Matthew chapter 28.
I'll read each account in the Gospels where the great commission is given to us.
And I think it was Paul Chappell wrote a book entitled Out of Commission.
And it was a book that was written about the great commission.
Someone, I'm not sure who the author was, I believe they wrote a book or at least preached
a message.
He called it great omission because the church is failing to do what we've been entrusted
to do.
And the reality is that God's final command to His people remains our mission today.
In Matthew 28 verse 18, Jesus came and spake unto them saying,
All power is given unto me in heaven and in earth.
Go ye therefore and teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the
Son and of the Holy Ghost.
Teaching them to observe all things whatsoever I have commanded you.
And lo, I am with you always, even unto the end of the world.
Amen.
In Mark chapter number 16 and verse number 15, the record is given here in a single verse
of Scripture with regard to the great commission.
And here in Mark 16 and verse 15, He, Jesus said unto them, the disciples, go ye into
all the world and preach the gospel to every creature.
Luke chapter number 24 and verses 47 and 48 before the ascension, the Bible tells us this
as Luke records it, that repentance and remission of sins should be preached in His name among
all nations beginning at Jerusalem and ye are witnesses of these things.
John chapter 17 and verse number 18.
John 17 is a great passage of Scripture dealing with the prayer of the Lord Jesus Christ before
He'd go to the cross of Calvary.
The hour has come is how He begins that prayer in verse number 1.
And I want you to notice in verse number 18, as He's praying, He says, as thou hast
sent me into the world, even so have I also sent them into the world.
Why did He send us into the world?
To be the light of the world, to be the salt of the earth, to be His representatives.
We're familiar with the truth.
I mentioned this morning, Acts 1 and verse number 8.
When God tells us to do something once, it's important.
God doesn't repeat Himself because He forgot that He already said it.
There's an obvious emphasis in the Word of God on the responsibility of the people of
God being the witnesses that He's commissioned us to be.
In Acts 1 and verse number 8, but ye shall receive power after that the Holy Ghost has
come upon you and ye shall be witnesses unto me both in Jerusalem and in all Judea and
in Samaria and unto the uttermost part of the earth.
In Acts 5 and verse number 32, the Bible tells us, and we are His witnesses of these things.
And I think about that ownership, that we take it personally, that it is our personal
responsibility to share the gospel with the people that God places in our lives.
That we understand nothing is done by accident and that God gives us, we sometimes use the
terminology, that was a divine appointment.
You know what I really believe in my life is that I miss a lot of divine appointments.
And one of the reasons that I miss them is because I'm not looking for them.
I'm not mindful of them.
I'm busy trying to accomplish the things on my list to do today and I have all of these
things that I need to get accomplished that I forget that He's left me here for a greater
purpose.
We find that really as you look at the book of Acts and you read it in its entirety and
you see the way the gospel went forth and you read about the missionary journeys and
you read the testimonies of the enemies where they say that you have filled Jerusalem with
your doctrine.
We told you, we commanded you, we threatened you not to speak in His name but yet you have
filled Jerusalem with your doctrine.
When they say of Paul and the others on the missionary journey, these that have turned
the world upside down have come hither also, oh that it would be said of us that we have
filled this region with the gospel.
Amen?
That the next person you try to give a gospel tract to says, man I just got one of these
a little while ago.
That's exciting.
That's encouraging.
Have you ever seen the same person repeatedly and you give them a gospel tract and you're
saying, man you kind of have that internal dilemma of I just saw this same person three
days ago because I go to the same place five times a week and I don't know if I should
give them a gospel tract again and so on and so forth.
The last time that happened to me, I noticed the guy, I know this guy, I've given him gospel
tracts before.
So I go to give him a gospel tract and I already kind of prepared for what he was going to
say.
You already gave me one of these.
And I said this.
I said, but did you read it?
And he just looked at me.
And that was his answer.
Right?
I mean, I knew his answer by his response of just that blank stare.
And I said, how about this?
I'll give you another one if you read it.
I've never seen the guy again.
But he took a gospel tract that day.
And the reality is that Paul said this in Romans 1, I mentioned about being indebted.
He says that if you look at verses 14 through 16, he talks about being a debtor, he talks
about being ready, and he talks about not being ashamed.
I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ.
Why?
It's the power of God unto salvation.
When we understand the power of the message that has been entrusted to us, we ought not
be ashamed to speak of it.
When we understand, as I mentioned in Sunday school this morning, when you look at that
maniac from Gadara, as we often refer to him as, that man that had his life transformed
by the power of the Lord Jesus Christ, he had a desire to be with Christ, yes, but Christ
left him there in that place.
He forbid him, he suffered him not to go with them.
And he left him there and he said that you're to be a witness.
Go and tell these people how great things the Lord hath done for thee.
And he went and he published it, the Bible tells us, in Decapolis, and the people marveled.
They saw what was happening.
They saw the power of God on display.
And this evening, we are His ambassadors, we're His representatives.
Second Corinthians 5 and verse number 20 tells us that we are His ambassadors.
This world is not my home, I'm just a passing through.
My citizenship is in heaven.
I happen to be a United States citizen, and this is my mission field.
It is my responsibility to reach this place with the gospel.
Psalm 126, I want you to see these verses of Scripture, and then I'll get some assistance
here in just a moment to pass these cards out.
We'll use that by way of our invitation this evening.
In Psalm 126, in verses 5 and 6, I want you to see what the Bible says here.
"'They that sow in tears shall reap in joy. He that goeth forth and weepeth, bearing precious seed,
shall doubtless come again with rejoicing, bringing his sheaves with him.'"
I wonder, when's the last time we've really prayed for lost souls?
When's the last time we've wept over lost souls?
The weeping. The Bible says of Paul, you don't need to turn there, but in Acts 20 and verse 31,
"'I cease not to warn every one night and day with tears.'"
With tears.
The psalmist in Psalm 119 speaks about the wickedness that he observes and the tears that are response.
Hating every evil way.
But it affects us.
Do we weep for lost souls?
I preached a message.
I guess I really shouldn't say I preached the message.
I plan to preach a message.
I'll give you a preview.
I don't know when I'm going to preach it because God hasn't given me liberty.
But I shared the thought with a small group of preachers.
I wasn't at a pastor's meeting, just a small group of pastors.
And they asked me if I'd share a thought.
And I was by far the youngest one there, and I felt like it would be more appropriate for someone else to share a thought.
But nonetheless, I was the one that was asked.
And I shared a thought from the prophet when the Bible says that the man of God wept.
And I shared a thought with the reason of him weeping was because God had revealed some things
as destruction that was going to come upon the people of Israel.
And then I asked this question to that small, really just a handful of preachers.
When's the last time the man of God wept?
When we read Revelation 20.
Dean read verse 10 this morning in our Sunday school.
Man, Satan is going to be cast in a lake of fire.
He's going to be tormented day and night forever and ever.
It's a choice.
That's exciting.
But the very next verse says there was a great white throne.
And as you read verses 11 through 15, it talks about the eternal destination of those that die without Christ.
And the Bible tells us that those that were not found written in the book of life were cast into the lake of fire.
This is the second death.
That's real.
And that ought to affect us.
It ought to impact us.
It ought to cause us to have, obviously, let me say it this way,
we give the gospel because we've been commissioned to do so and we walk in obedience to God.
But when we understand how desperately the world needs it,
it ought to prompt us to be even more aggressive in sharing the truth.
Here I've given a couple of thoughts.
Five tracks per week.
A track per day, so seven per week.
But then let me just make a quick comment on this third point.
Purpose to share the gospel with one person each month.
Let me say it this way.
We ought to be praying that God would give us an opportunity.
I believe that if we pray that God would give us an opportunity to share the gospel with someone each month,
I believe that's a prayer that God would like to answer.
Right?
God, cross my path, give me the opportunity.
Help me to see the opportunity.
Help me not to miss it.
Help me to look for and to be aware of.
I think God will answer that prayer.
And you'll find that he gives you opportunities and maybe that commitment,
that purpose to once a month share the gospel, you say,
man, God's given me an opportunity each week.
Praise the Lord.
Keep sharing the gospel.
Amen?
And we ask God.
Dio Mudi, it's said of him.
Sorry, I just turned that off.
I shouldn't have turned that off.
Dio Mudi, it is said of him that he made a commitment that he would not pillow his head at night
until he had shared the gospel with one person each day.
There were times in his life, it's reported, I've read,
where he had busy long days, all sorts of things going on.
Exhausted, tired, he gets home, he's ready to turn in for the evening, pillow his head.
The Holy Spirit of God reminded him that he did not share the gospel with someone.
Literally gets out of bed to go down into the city of Chicago
to find somebody to share the gospel with.
Why?
Because he made a commitment to God.
And he understood the power of the gospel.
It's said of Dio Mudi that God used him to shake two continents.
It's said that over a million people came to know Christ under his ministry.
That's powerful.
Someone asked, just as they asked Spurgeon what the secret to his ministry was,
and in one report that I read, he simply pointed to the window and said,
it's there.
And the individual that was inquiring was perplexed,
and he said, just go over and look, and you'll see.
And the guy still didn't understand what he was saying.
If you look out that window, you see all the people that are walking.
He said, God's called me to reach those people.
And he took it personally.
So he made a commitment.
I said this this morning, little quote there in the corner,
if you fail to plan, you plan to fail.
It's 6.59, bear with me just a few more minutes.
When I was in the corporate world, we used to have to set every year goals.
It was always exciting.
You'd have reviews and determine how you did with those goals and what have you.
But I remember as I would try to counsel with some of the people that worked for me
and try to help them to formulate their goals, that we'd always talk about SMART goals.
Some of you are familiar with that terminology and acronym.
Just real quickly before we pass these out, when you set goals, the S of SMART goals,
they should be specific and they should be stated.
Make specific goals.
I'm going to pray more.
Okay, that's good, but what does that mean?
It's really not specific enough, right?
There's not enough substance to it.
So SMART goals start with them being specific and stated.
Measurable goals, something that we can measure.
Let me say this, attainable goals.
If you've never read the Bible through, if your Bible reading is very haphazard,
maybe you just make a commitment to read the New Testament through this year.
Don't make a commitment.
I heard pastors say he read the Bible through two times.
I read it three times.
You're just going to get discouraged.
I'm just being honest with you.
And then what's going to happen with that goal?
It's going to go out the window.
Set a goal that's attainable.
R, a goal that is realistic.
And I would say this as well, relevant.
What is the purpose of me setting these goals?
When I speak about these spiritual goals, these commitments to the Lord,
it's relevant to my walk with God.
It's relevant in my development as a child of God, in my progress, in my walk with God.
And T for SMART goals, I would say this, trackable or time-bound.
Something that's trackable or time-bound.
That's why I say I'm going to pass out five gospel tracks a week.
It's something that's specific.
It's something that's measurable.
It's something that's attainable.
It's something that's relevant.
And it's something that is time-bound.
I'm going to make a commitment to pass out tracks.
It doesn't really hit all of the criteria of a SMART goal.
And so I want you to think about that, and I'm going to have some folks, Jared, Luke, Steve,
you guys come and help me pass these out.
And on the front is just the same thing that we had up here is on the front of this.
And on the back is the little commitment sections.
And again, I'm not asking you tonight to fill this out right here on the spot.
I'm not asking you.
I don't want it back.
If you try to give it back to me, I don't want it.
I honestly don't.
I don't want it.
But I want you to, before the Lord, it's a different kind of message.
I don't think I've ever preached a message like this.
In ten and a half years of pastoring, I don't think I ever preached a message like this.
But God just really put it on my heart.
And I really think that it's important.
it's important that we make some goals
and make some commitments to God.
All year, we're going to have as our theme
walking in the light.
How am I doing walking in the light?
These three particular pillars,
if I could call them that this evening
that we looked at,
it's not the entirety of Christian life,
but they're three pillars,
three legs of biblical Christianity
that are vital.
Prayer, Bible reading, and witnessing.
It's our responsibility.
See, I'm not a missionary.
Somebody said this.
You're a missionary if it's only to the supermarket.
We are God's representatives.
And so before the Lord,
those little circles are not as big
as I wanted them to be.
The font kept messing with me,
but you can fill it in.
And maybe you want to circle a couple of them.
Maybe you want to change it up.
You say, I thought about this goal,
and I want to put this down
instead of one of the options that you gave.
Man, praise the Lord.
But just be open with the Lord
and let God direct you.
And stick that in your Bible.
And refer back to it.
And let's have monthly checkups.
Not that I'm going to come to you and say,
hey, what was your commitment and how are you doing?
But you know, accountability is good.
Accountability is something that's missing
in our society today.
People don't want to be accountable.
And it would be a benefit, I think.
I believe that husbands and wives
share your commitments with one another.
Why?
Because who better to pray for you,
who better to hold you accountable to help you
than your spouse?
Children with your parents.
Maybe some single folks.
There's some other single folks
that you can have an accountability partner with.
I'd be more than happy.
I know I said I don't want them,
but I'm not saying that in a standoffish way.
I'm not trying to check up on people.
But if you want me to be an accountability partner,
I'd be more than happy to do that.
I've never been offended one time
when someone said to me,
hey, did you read your Bible?
It doesn't offend me.
Because I do.
I've never been bothered when somebody says,
I do.
I'm not ashamed of it.
I'm not embarrassed by it.
I'm not bothered by it.
I know I've shared this story before.
Joseph, with our children,
we used to ask him all the time,
did you read your Bible today?
Did you read your Bible today?
When they got old enough to read their Bible.
And I was sitting in our living room in Manassas,
and it was a Saturday afternoon,
and Joseph goes to walk up the stairs
to go to his bedroom.
And he stops partway up the stairs,
and he looks at me.
He says, hey, Daddy,
did you read your Bible today?
That blessed my heart.
And I was able to say, I did.
I could share with you what I read
if you want to know.
And it's accountability.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
I know it's been a different kind of a message
this evening,
but God, I pray that Your Spirit has moved.
I've sought to be obedient.
And I pray that it's been helpful.
And I pray that we make some commitments
to You this evening.
And that God, You would use us.
Help us to grow
through our time of prayer and Bible reading.
That our faith would be increased.
That we'd be ready to give an answer
to every man of the hope that lieth within us.
Help us to see the hand of God moved
because of prayer.
God, help us to see souls saved.
Lives changed.
Baptismal water stirred.
Discipleship classes filled up.
Because we've purposed to share the Gospel.
And we've set some specific goals.
As we look and evaluate the group
that's here tonight,
if in this next year,
2022,
You would allow each one of us
to just reach one person,
our church would double.
I know that's simple.
But it's true.
It's not about the numbers.
It's about seeing souls saved.
Eternal destinations changed.
God, we want You to be glorified
and exalted.
Herein is my Father glorified
that You bear much fruit.
And help us to be about Your business.
I pray that in the quietness of the moment,
as Kimberly plays on the piano,
that we would respond.
That we'd be doers of the Word.
That we'd leave here tonight
with that desire to serve You.
That we'd make these commitments to You.
Well, thank You for the work that You'll do.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would You stand with us?