Thankful for the privilege of being able to sing
the great hymns of the faith, aren't you?
And what a tremendous blessing.
We will be in the book of James this morning,
but I want you to start with me
in 1 Thessalonians chapter number two,
1 Thessalonians chapter number two,
and read a couple of verses, I think,
that are pertinent here to our message this morning.
If you were here last Sunday morning,
I preached a message that I entitled Do Not Err Part One,
and this morning we'll look at Do Not Err Part Two,
and we'll be looking at James 1, verses 16 through 18.
We'll get there in just a moment.
But I want to remind you, the Apostle Paul
had the opportunity during the second missionary journey
to go to a number of places,
but one of them was the city of Thessalonica.
A church was established there,
and the Apostle Paul is writing this book
of 1 Thessalonians back to them.
He's giving thanks and reminding them
of all of what was going on, not only in their ministry,
but there in the church at Thessalonica,
and really the testimony of the church,
and what a great testimony they had.
And they were a church that often,
throughout the book of 1 and 2 Thessalonians,
are being commended for their faithfulness
and their obedience to the truth of God's word.
And we're gonna think about the church in Thessalonica,
and you could contrast and compare,
as you study the scriptures,
some of the churches that are referenced
throughout the New Testament.
And there's no perfect church, amen,
and every church is made up of believers
that are sinners saved by grace.
And I'm thankful that we have a perfect book,
and we have a perfect savior,
and he has a perfect plan,
but we understand that churches are made up of humans,
and we are imperfect people.
And someone says, I'm looking for the perfect church.
And if you find, well, you're not gonna find it,
but if you did and you joined it,
it wouldn't be perfect any longer,
because we're a bunch of imperfect people.
But I'm thankful that God's working in and through us
and doing a work that he will perform
until the day of Jesus Christ,
according to Philippians one and verse number six.
But really the church in Thessalonica is a model church.
And again, they're commended repeatedly
through these first chapters of 1 Thessalonians one,
and then in the beginning of 2 Thessalonians,
it's really interesting to see how they're commended
and how they're growing and what's going on.
And I think there's a key for us,
and I referenced the verse last Sunday morning,
but there is a key as to why this particular assembly,
why this church in Thessalonica
would be viewed as being a model church.
And it's because of how they viewed the word of God.
And the Bible tells us in 1 Thessalonians two
and verse number 13,
again, I referenced this verse last Sunday morning,
but the Bible says this,
for this cause also thank we God without ceasing.
And so Paul is rejoicing, he's thanking the Lord,
and he tells us why, he says because.
Notice in verse 13, when ye, the church in Thessalonica,
the people in Thessalonica,
when ye received the word of God, which ye heard of us.
By the way, somebody has to declare the word of God, amen.
The Bible is God's word, the Bible is powerful,
the Bible tells us who God is,
it tells us the plan of redemption,
but we understand that even in Romans 10,
and we'll look at it in just a few moments this morning,
how shall they hear without a preacher?
And we find that Paul says that when ye receive
the word of God, which ye heard of us,
notice ye received it not as the word of men.
There's some people that just say, well, that's man's word,
and they just dismiss it,
they just say that's your opinion, that's your thought,
that's a book that's been compiled by man,
they don't understand what these folks
are commended for here.
He says, you received it not as the word of men,
but as it is in truth.
Notice what it says, the word of God,
which effectually worketh also in you that believe.
I am so thankful to have a Bible.
I am so thankful that God, in his infinite wisdom,
chose to give to humanity the Bible,
God's word, the word of God,
and I'm thankful that God not only gave his word
through inspiration, but we understand
that God has providentially preserved his word,
and we can have confidence this morning
in having the word of God,
and we can understand that as we look
at the church in Thessalonica,
what was it that made them a model church?
Why is it that they're being commended
the way that they are repeatedly in these two letters?
Well, I really believe the key
is how they received God's word.
See, I made the comment last week
that some err because they give more credibility
to the philosophy of the world,
to the things that they've been taught,
to the things that they see,
that they are able to look at here.
They give more credibility to their opinion
or to their own logic than they do to God's word.
God's word is authoritative.
God's word is not open for debate.
God's word is, God's not gonna,
well, people in 2026 don't believe it anymore,
so I'm gonna change it, I'm gonna rewrite it.
No, that's not gonna happen.
We are to conform our lives to God's word,
not try to take God's word and conform it to our lives
or what we wanna do.
No, we conform our lives to the standard,
which is the word of God,
and I'm thankful that we have God's word.
The problem today with,
as we look at the subject matter in James 1,
and I'll turn over there if you will,
when we look at this where he says, do not err,
I made the comment last week
that in between these two truths that James is giving,
he mentions, do not err, my beloved brethren, in verse 16.
And I said this, I believe that it has a dual application,
one, with regard to the content of verses 13 through 15,
and then number two, with regard to the content
in verses 17 and 18.
And the reality is that we are prone to wander,
we are prone to err,
but the answer to error is always truth.
The answer to error is always truth.
And that's why it's so important
that we know the truth of God's word.
That's why it's so important that we get into God's word
every day of our lives,
that we're soaking up the truth of God's word
and allowing God's word to impact my life.
I think often of the truth in Psalm 118,
we see the psalmist there,
and of course, the psalm is all about the Bible,
and you find that really the psalmist gets to a point
where he's having this desire
that he wants to think and behave biblically.
And the way that we think and behave biblically
is by spending time in the word.
There's no shortcut, there's no secret shortcut
with regard to how can I, no, it's just time in the word,
it's just diligence and consistency and time in the word
and studying the word and reading the word
and hearing the word.
And I'm so thankful that we have a Bible
and that it is truth.
Last week in verses 13 through 15,
we talked about the way in which people can err
with regard to sinful temptation.
Well, that's the way I was made,
this is somebody else's fault,
blame shifting, all of that,
and how that the passage of scripture sets straight
all of those misconceptions and all of those excuses
and lays plainly in front of us the culpability of sin
that I am responsible.
Because the Bible says, but every man is tempted
when he has drawn away of his own lust and enticed.
And we understand the course of sin as it's outlined,
and I believe what happens sometimes
is people really don't believe the Bible.
The Bible says, then when lust hath conceived,
bringeth forth sin, and sin when it is finished,
bringeth forth death.
Why do I say people don't believe the Bible?
Because they think, well, God's okay with this,
I'm doing this and I haven't been judged
and it's not really that big of a deal
and everyone else is doing it and it's okay,
it's acceptable in our culture and our society,
but God's word says it brings death.
God's word is true and I fear that sometimes
even as believers that we really don't believe the Bible
and that's why God says, do not err.
You ever read over there in the book of Galatians
where the Bible says, be not deceived.
That's a great truth, is it not?
Why, why would he start a verse by saying,
be not deceived?
Because many are deceived with this thinking,
God is not mocked.
Whatsoever a man soweth, that shall he also reap.
That is a biblical truth that God gives us
and what happens is people, well, you know,
God hasn't really judged me yet.
God is long-suffering, praise God for his long-suffering.
I was rejoicing this morning in my time of prayer,
thanking him that he's long-suffering,
but I don't wanna mistake God's long-suffering
for God's approval, amen?
Because God is never okay with sin
and so we talked about how people can err
with regard to that understanding
as it's presented to us in verses 13 through 15.
Now.
As we move into verses 17 and 18,
I think that there's truth given to us
with regard to really the broad subject, if you will,
of God's blessings.
And here's what happens is if we're not careful,
people err with regard to the blessings in life.
You ever hear somebody have this perspective,
I'm a self-made man.
I pulled myself up by my own bootstraps.
You say, we don't talk that way in Northern Virginia.
I'm sure many of us have heard
some of those types of phraseologies.
Can I tell you this morning that you're here this morning
simply for one reason, and that's God's grace.
The air that you're breathing this morning is God's air.
The ability that you had this morning to get out of bed
and the ability that you had this morning
to get in a vehicle and drive here
and the ability that you had to even have a bed
or a vehicle, amen?
And the reality is that sometimes if we're not careful,
we err with regard to the truth
that James is going to present here in verses 17 and 18.
Notice with me, he says, do not err in verse 16,
my beloved brethren, verse 17,
every good gift and every perfect gift is from above
and cometh down from the Father of lights
with whom is no variableness, neither shadow of turning.
Of his own will begat he us with the word of truth
that we should be a kind of first fruits of his creatures.
As we look at this portion of scripture,
I notice first of all in verse 17,
and I want you to notice with me, number one,
notice how James exalts the Lord.
We begin reading in verse 17, of course,
this idea of do not err, but we find in verse 17,
as it begins to exalt the Lord,
that it helps us to understand
how we can prevent erring in our life
with regard to the blessings that we enjoy.
And by the way, I'm thankful that my God
daily loatheth me with benefits.
I agree with the psalmist.
He daily loatheth me with benefits.
I'm thankful that we can say my cup runneth over, amen.
He's been good to us.
And we sing the song counter blessings,
name them one by one.
And if you've watched Dean lead the song,
anytime he leads the song, he starts counting
when he says one by one.
And the reality is the songwriter said,
it will surprise you what the Lord hath done.
And oh, it's a good exercise in our lives to just thank God.
And we see here that James is exalting the Lord.
First, we find that he's exalting the Lord for this reason,
because our God is benevolent.
Aren't you thankful that God is benevolent?
He's a giving God.
He's a gracious God.
He's a benevolent God.
We find that the Bible tells us in this verse of scripture,
notice the use twice, he uses the word every.
He says every good gift and every perfect gift.
I believe that that word is used to address the root
and also to correct man's perspective.
Because if we're not careful, we can have the perspective
that I got this on my own.
I earned this.
Whatever our perspective might be.
And so James says every good gift and every perfect gift.
And so he addresses the root.
He corrects man's perspective.
And we find that the word good means pleasant.
The word perfect, it carries with it this idea
of to lack nothing.
Remember we talked about our spiritual perfection,
our spiritual maturity.
And here when he talks about every good gift,
that which is pleasant, every perfect gift,
that which is lacking nothing.
Can I tell you this morning
that God knows exactly what we need?
You believe that this morning?
We don't know exactly what we need.
We think we know what we need.
But God knows exactly what we need.
And the Bible says every good gift and every perfect gift.
And so we're reminded as James begins to exalt the Lord
of the fact that God is benevolent.
Let me remind you of a couple of verses of scripture.
Turn back if you will to the book of Deuteronomy
in chapter number eight.
We'll look at a verse in the Old Testament
and a verse in the New Testament.
It was we deal with the subject of God's benevolence.
And when we begin to think about our God being benevolent,
understand that there's the caution not only for us
but also for the children of Israel in the Old Testament
to forget the source of blessing,
to forget the fact that God is benevolent.
In fact, I've asked you to turn
to Deuteronomy chapter number eight,
but back in chapter six of the book of Deuteronomy,
God tells them, beware lest thou forget the Lord.
You're gonna go into a land
and you're gonna live in houses that you did not build.
You're gonna eat from vineyards that you did not plant.
And you're gonna enjoy all of these good things,
but beware lest thou forget the Lord.
God was the one that brought them into that land,
miraculously by the way.
And we find that in chapter number eight,
notice the instruction that God gives
in Deuteronomy chapter number eight.
In verse number 11, the Bible says,
beware that thou forget not the Lord thy God
and not keeping his commandments
and his judgments and his statutes,
which I command thee this day,
lest when thou hast eaten and art full
and has built goodly houses and dwelt therein,
and when thy herds and thy flocks multiply
and thy silver and thy gold is multiplied
and all that thou hast is multiplied.
Think about the goodness that's being revealed to us
in verses 11 through 13, this multiplication,
this abundance, if you will.
God says, beware to start verse number 11,
because in verse 14, he says,
then thine heart be lifted up
and thou forget the Lord thy God,
which brought thee forth out of the land of Egypt
from the house of bondage.
He talks about God's leadership in verse 15,
who led thee through the great and terrible wilderness.
By the way, they didn't know how to go
without God's direction.
Right?
There was a pillar of cloud, a pillar of fire.
In fact, when you read there in the book of Exodus
in chapter 13, when it talks about how God led them,
he led them a way that was different
than the way that they would presume.
Why?
Because God knew what they would encounter in that way,
and he led them this way.
And it was God's leadership
and it was God working in their lives.
We find that the Bible says in verse number 15,
who led thee through that great and terrible wilderness,
wherein were fiery serpents and scorpions and drought,
where there was no water,
who brought thee forth water out of the rock of Flint,
who fed thee in the wilderness with manna,
which thy fathers knew not,
that he might humble thee and that he might prove thee
to do thee good at thy latter end.
Verse 17, and thou saying in thine heart,
notice what he says,
my power and the might of mine hand
hath gotten me this wealth.
Is that not a potential for every single one of us
to have that wrong perspective?
To think, look at what I've been able to attain,
look at what I've been able to build up,
look at what I've been able to accomplish.
And in verse 18, but thou shalt remember the Lord thy God,
for it is he that giveth thee power to get wealth,
that he may establish his covenant,
which he swear unto thy fathers as it is this day.
It is God that gives us the ability.
It is God who is the source,
that it is God who is benevolent.
And we begin to look there
and we see that Old Testament principle.
And if we're not careful,
we can look at the children of Israel
and we can criticize them,
but there are many times in which we mimic their behavior.
Look at all of this.
Look at what I've been able to, no, no, no.
Remember that it was God that gave you the ability.
Look in the book of 1 Corinthians in the New Testament,
if you will, 1 Corinthians chapter four.
Now, the church in Corinth, as you're turning there,
is much different than the church in Thessalonica.
If you know anything about the New Testament,
the church in Thessalonica would be that model church
that I mentioned at the beginning of the message.
The church in Corinth, not so much.
A church that is regularly, especially in the first book
here in 1 Corinthians, regularly corrected
for their immaturity, their spiritual immaturity,
for their carnality, the divisions,
and all the things that are taking place.
And notice what the Bible says in 1 Corinthians four
in verse number six.
The Bible says,
and these things, brethren, I have in a figure
transferred to myself and to Apollos for your sakes,
that you might learn in us
not to think of men above that which is written,
that no one of you be puffed up for one against another.
He then says this in verse seven.
He asks a couple of questions
that are really designed to probe, to reveal.
He says, for whom maketh thee to differ from another?
And then notice this question,
the second one in verse seven.
And what hast thou that thou didst not receive?
Now, if thou didst receive it,
why dost thou glory as if thou hadst not received it?
So James, as he's writing here to these folks
that are dealing with persecution and trials
and all that's going on,
and he's trying to correct their error.
He says, do not err.
I don't want you to have a wrong understanding
of sinful temptation,
but I don't want you to have a wrong understanding
of God's blessings.
So our Lord, he begins to exalt,
our Lord is benevolent,
that he is the one that every good gift
and every perfect gift is from above.
He says, and cometh down.
from the Father of lights.
By the way, we're told that God is light
and in Him is no darkness at all.
The Bible gives us the instruction in the book of 1 John.
In fact, we used it as a theme in our church
a few years ago that we're to walk in the light
as He is in the light.
And I'm thankful that He is the light of the world
and I'm thankful that He is the light.
And the Bible says that it cometh down
from the Father of lights.
It helps us understand to have no misunderstanding
or contradiction with regard to the source,
who it is that's giving every good and every perfect gift.
But then notice, not only is our Lord benevolent,
not only is He the Father of lights,
but He mentions and He's exalting the Lord, why?
Because our God is immutable.
Our God is immutable.
Notice how He describes the immutability of God here
in our verse of scripture.
He says, with whom is no variableness.
Now think about that, He doesn't vary.
He's constant.
The Bible says in the book of Malachi that I am the Lord,
I change not, therefore you sons of Jacob are not consumed.
We read over the book of Hebrews where the Bible says
that Jesus Christ, the same yesterday, today, and forever.
And listen, everything around us changes.
You change, we all change, amen?
Life changes, culture changes, society changes,
your car changes, your home.
I mean, everything around us, but God is constant.
There's no variableness, think about that.
Oh man, what a reason for us to rejoice.
What a reason for us to recognize how wonderful our God is.
The psalmist said it this way in Psalm 90.
Now Psalm 90 is a psalm that's ascribed to Moses
as the human penman, and we find that in Psalm 90,
Moses says it this way in verse number one,
that Lord, thou hast been our dwelling place
in all generations.
And then he says it this way,
before the mountains were brought forth,
or ever thou hast formed the earth and the world,
even from everlasting to everlasting, thou art God.
He's eternal and He is immutable.
And that ought to cause us to rejoice,
and we could say it this morning this way,
hallelujah, what a Savior, just as the songwriter said.
What a privilege to know Him.
What a privilege to exalt Him.
Can I tell you this morning, He is worthy.
We looked last week at Revelation 5 on Sunday evening,
and we talked about that scene there
in the throne room of heaven,
and how there was the scroll,
and we understand that there's our Savior,
and then we understand the song,
and we look at the latter part of Revelation 5,
and we read about those that are assembled,
the choirs assembled, the lyrics,
and how we're singing about redemption for all of eternity.
Hallelujah, He is worthy.
Look over quickly, if you will, at Psalm 34,
and I just wanna read these verses to you,
and I hope that they would be an encouragement to you,
because what we see James doing
as we begin this portion of scripture,
this second aspect of do not err,
he wants us to understand how great our God is.
He wants us to exalt our God.
He wants us to recognize that He is the source,
the giver of all, everything that is good,
and He corrects man's perspective.
And notice what the psalmist says in Psalm 34.
It's the Psalm of David.
He says, I will bless the Lord at all times.
His praise shall continually be in my mouth.
My soul shall make her boast in the Lord.
The humble shall hear thereof and be glad.
Notice verse three.
Oh, magnify the Lord with me,
and let us exalt His name together.
As we look at these three verses of scripture
to begin Psalm 34, we find is the remainder
of the passage deals with many experiences of David
and why he's saying that he will bless the Lord
at all times in God's goodness and in God's favor
in his life, but I want you to understand
that verse one begins with the personal praise
and exaltation of the Lord.
I will bless the Lord at all times.
I wonder this morning, have you made that decision?
I've been teaching in the teen Sunday school class
going through the latter part of 1 Thessalonians 5
and dealing with the instructions that God gives us,
kind of just rapid fire succession instruction,
and this morning we're in verse 18.
In everything, give thanks for this is the will of God
in Christ Jesus concerning you.
Now, last week we're in verse 17.
Pray without ceasing, but the week before,
we're in verse number 16.
Rejoice evermore.
So I asked the teenagers this morning,
did God forget that He said rejoice evermore?
So four words later, He says in everything, give thanks
for this is the will of God in Christ,
because there's a lot of similarity
between those two verses of scripture.
No, God didn't forget.
Did Paul forget that he wrote rejoice evermore?
No, Paul didn't forget.
It's the recipients that struggle with giving thanks
that need the reminder to give thanks.
So I ask this question, can we in everything give thanks?
Yes.
Should we in everything give thanks?
Do we in everything give thanks?
No, we really don't.
But here, the psalmist says,
I will bless the Lord at all times,
but notice how that personal exalting the Lord
in verse number one turns into a plural sense
in verse number three where the psalmist says,
oh, magnify the Lord with me
and let us exalt His name together.
And there's a praising that's taking place there.
And listen, James is exalting the Lord.
He wants the readers, these original recipients,
and then of course, by way of preservation
for us this morning to recognize how great our God is
and to have this proper perspective, not to err,
because our God is benevolent.
Our God is the Father of lights.
Our God is immutable, and it is an absolute blessing
for us to know Him and to exalt Him.
And when we have that proper perspective,
then it keeps us from erring and thinking,
well, look at all of these things
that I've been able to accomplish.
Look at, no, I am what I am by the grace of God.
Amen?
We notice not only does James exalt the Lord,
but notice with me in verse 18,
I want you to notice number two, what James experienced.
We're gonna split verse 18 into two thoughts this morning,
but I want you to see in the beginning part of verse 18,
the Bible says of His own will.
So His is talking about the Lord as we looked in verse 17,
the one that He's exalting.
He says of His own will, begat He us with the word of truth.
You know what James is talking about?
He's talking about his personal experience
of being born again.
I believe that.
We look here, the Bible says of His own will,
begat He us with the word of truth.
Now, let me remind you that when we read there in the,
and we've been doing some kind of going back and forth here
with the book of 1 Peter and looking at some of the things
that are going on, but I want you to look back
or look forward to 1 Peter chapter one just for a moment.
And the Bible says in James one in verse 18,
of His own will, begat He us with the word of truth.
But look in 1 Peter chapter one,
the Bible says this in verse number three,
blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ,
which according to His abundant mercy, notice this,
hath begotten us again unto a lively hope
by the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead
to an inheritance incorruptible and undefiled
and that fadeth not away, reserved in heaven for you,
who are kept by the power of God through faith
unto salvation, ready to be revealed in the last time.
Skip down if you will to verse number 17.
It says this, and if you call on the Father,
who without respect of persons, by the way,
aren't you thankful that our God is no respecter of persons?
It says judgeth according to every man's work
past the time of your sojourning here in fear.
For as much as ye know that ye were not redeemed
with corruptible things as silver and gold
from your vain conversation,
received by tradition from your fathers,
but with the precious blood of Christ
as of a lamb without blemish and without spot,
who verily was foreordained
before the foundation of the world,
but was manifest in these last times for you.
Verse 21, who by Him do believe in God
that raised Him from the dead
and gave Him glory that your faith and hope might be in God.
Seeing ye have purified your souls
and obeying the truth through the Spirit
unto unfeigned love of the brethren,
see that ye love one another with a pure heart fervently.
Look at verse 23.
Being born again, not of corruptible seed,
but of incorruptible by the Word of God,
which liveth and abideth forever.
And we find again in verse 25, it says,
but the Word of the Lord endureth forever.
And so we notice here.
In James 1, the Bible says of his own will,
begat he us with the word of truth.
Let me help us this morning understand and be reminded
that salvation has everything to do with God.
Amen.
But God commendeth his love toward us
in that while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us.
Hallelujah.
I'm so thankful for God so loved the world
that he gave his only begotten son,
that whosoever believeth in him should not perish,
but have everlasting life.
Listen, I did not help God in my salvation.
It was all him.
Amen.
I'm thankful for the spirit of God
who convicted me of my sin.
who convicted me of Christ's righteousness.
I'm thankful for the spirit of God
that convicted me of judgment to come.
And I understood, listen, there was a day,
and I remember the day vividly in my mind.
I remember when I understood that I was a sinner.
That Christ was the perfect sacrifice.
And that he died in my place because he loved me so much.
And he offered to me eternal life.
I remember that day.
And I remember recognizing that it was not
by works of mine own righteousness.
There was nothing, it wasn't a 50-50,
it wasn't a 60-40, it wasn't a 99-1.
Amen.
It was all God.
And he sought me.
And I'm so thankful that someone preached the gospel
and I heard the truth of the gospel.
And listen, for by grace are you saved through faith.
And that not of yourselves.
It is the gift of God, not of works,
lest any man should boast.
I remember being a teenager.
It was about a year before I got saved.
I got saved at the end of August
and it was, I believe it was the Christmas before.
So about nine months earlier at Christmastime,
I remember a relative getting for another relative,
it was a son of theirs, a vehicle for Christmas.
And they said this, we made the down payment
and here's the rest of the payment book.
They were thankful, but that's not a gift
that's paid in full.
Amen.
I'm thankful that the gift of God,
he said it is finished, paid in full.
And we recognize here that God uses his word to convict
and to convince lost people of their personal need
to be born again.
That's why God's word is so important,
that we use the word of God,
that we preach the word of God.
That's why when there's opportunities
that maybe you only have a brief interaction
with an individual that God might allow you
to quote a verse of scripture.
Why, because God's gonna use his word
more than he's gonna use your word.
And we wanna preach the word,
we wanna give the truth of God's word
because God uses his word.
Let me remind you, I already referenced it,
but look in Romans chapter number 10.
A wonderful, wonderful promise is given to us
in Romans chapter number 10 and verse number 13.
In fact, I believe many this morning
could probably quote Romans 10 and verse number 13.
It's a familiar verse of scripture to many of us.
And the Bible says this in Romans 10 and verse number 13,
for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord
shall be saved.
Man, I'm so thankful for that powerful truth.
For whosoever.
How many times I've sat with an individual
and said, that's you, that's anyone.
You put your name in there.
For whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord.
What is gonna cause them to call upon the name of the Lord?
Well, we continue reading and the Bible says in verse 14,
notice there's questions that are asked,
how then shall they call on him
in whom they have not believed?
Well, that makes sense, right?
If you don't believe, you're not gonna call in.
The Bible says, and how shall they believe in him
of whom they have not heard?
Well, that's also logical.
If I don't hear about Jesus, how can I believe in Jesus?
Right?
If I've not heard that God loved me so much
that he sent his son, Jesus Christ, God in flesh
to die for my sins, how can I believe in him?
How can I call on him if I've not heard?
The Bible says at the end of verse 14,
and how shall they hear?
Without a preacher.
You know, every one of us,
the word preacher there is not just the pastor.
Every believer has a responsibility to preach the gospel.
Go into all the world and preach the gospel
to every creature.
Every believer this morning is an ambassador.
If you're trusted Christ as your savior this morning,
you are an ambassador.
I preached as we were going through the book
of 2 Corinthians last year, that we are his ambassadors.
And then I preached the following week,
a faithful ambassador.
And the reality is that we are responsible
and we do have the privilege of preaching
the truth of God's word.
It says in verse 15, and how shall they preach?
Except they be sent.
We talk about our missionaries,
we send them all over the world, why?
We support them financially, why?
Because we want to get the gospel to all the world.
That every single person would hear the truth
of the gospel.
Does it mean that every single person will trust Christ
as their personal savior?
No, he came to his own and his own received him not,
but as many as received him, to them gave he power
to become the sons of God.
There are, listen, I don't know,
I'm not gonna ask you to raise your hand,
but I know for me, I did not get saved
the first time I heard the gospel.
Now you may have.
The very first time you heard the gospel,
you may have gotten saved, I did not.
For many of us, I believe in this room,
I've heard many of your, if not all of your testimonies
of salvation, those that are here that are saved,
I've heard your testimony of salvation.
And listen, for many of us, it was continuous.
I mean, we heard it and we heard it.
And I'm thankful that God was long suffering
and he was faithful and there were some people
that were faithful to preach the gospel.
It says here, and how shall they preach
except they be sent, as it is written,
how beautiful are the feet of them
that preach the gospel of peace
and bring glad tidings of good things.
I want you to think about this at the end of verse 15.
Sometimes we kind of, we'll be a little fastidious
about the how beautiful are the feet of them
that preach the gospel.
But I want you to think about this,
think about being in a place
where the gospel has never been.
And think about being in that place
and being blinded by the little G God of this world
and a missionary comes in there
and they come on their feet carrying this glorious message.
Man, how beautiful are the feet of them.
Listen, I'm thankful for those that are going forth,
that are going and preaching the gospel
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
I'm indebted and you're indebted
to those that have gone before us.
And we have a responsibility to go forward.
And James says, as he's writing
and he's speaking about do not err,
listen, this thing of salvation.
Yes, our God is benevolent and we exalt the Lord,
but he's talking about his own experience,
how he was born again.
And we find that the Bible says in verse 16 of Romans 10,
but they have not all obeyed the gospel.
For Isaiah saith, Lord, who hath believed our report?
So then faith cometh by hearing
and hearing by the word of God.
Listen, I believe and I'm thankful as Paul declared
in Romans chapter number one in verse number 16,
for I'm not ashamed of the gospel of Christ,
for it is the power of God unto salvation
to everyone that believeth,
to the Jew first and also to the Greek.
I believe that because it's God's word.
I also believe that because I experienced that.
Amen.
God's word is powerful.
The gospel is the power of God unto salvation.
If any man be in Christ, he's a new creature.
I'm not who I used to be.
And I'm thankful for that
because God saved me and God changed me.
And so James here, back in James chapter number one,
he's exalting the Lord.
He's helping the readers to understand
that our God is the source of every good gift
and every perfect gift, that he is benevolent,
that he is the father of lights, that he is immutable.
And he's exalting the Lord,
but then he's talking about his own experience
of his own will, begat he us with the word of truth.
He used the word us, plural,
not only about his own experience,
but obviously we understand that he's writing,
according to verse number one of chapter one,
we looked at this several weeks ago,
James, a servant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ
to the 12 tribes, which are scattered abroad, greeting.
And we understand that as James is writing to these,
he's writing to these Jewish believers
that are facing such hard, difficult times of persecution.
We understand that it was the Jewish people
that cried out, crucify him.
He came to his own and his own received him not,
but there were Jewish people that got saved
by the grace of God, amen.
Paul was Jewish, they were Jewish people.
And there was a great harvest of Jews that got saved.
You think about the day of Pentecost.
You think about the early church in Jerusalem
with those thousands and multitudes of people
that got saved and all the persecution.
And we studied this in the beginning of the year,
how that they went and they were preaching the gospel
to the Jews only.
But the gospel is not just for the Jews, by the way,
aren't you thankful for that, amen?
And praise the Lord that the gospel is for every creature.
And so we find that James highlights
at the beginning of verse number 18, his own experience.
But then at the end of verse number 18, number three,
if you're taking notes, I want you to notice
what James expected, what James expected.
And I want you to just rejoice
in this last part of verse number 18.
It's so encouraging to see what James says.
The Bible says of his own will begat he us
with the word of truth.
Then notice what he says that we, again,
that's the same group of us that were born again,
those Jewish believers, that we should be a kind
of firstfruits of his creatures.
Now these original recipients would have
a clear understanding of the term firstfruits.
It was something that was very familiar to them
in their culture and in their history.
And we find that James,
as he's talking about what he expected,
that he says to these believers
that we should be a kind of firstfruits.
Now firstfruits is something interesting
because it represents an expectation of a full harvest.
The firstfruits represents that expectation
of a full harvest.
It is the first of more, right?
Now we understand the term is used
in 1 Corinthians 15, that Christ is the first fruit,
speaking about the resurrection,
and we can rejoice in that.
But here, as we begin to understand
what James is unfolding,
and he's talking about his own experience
at the beginning of verse 18,
but then he's talking about what he's expecting.
And I believe that as you look here
at the text of scripture,
he's looking down, God, of course,
all scripture is given by inspiration of God,
but looking down through the ages
and seeing souls that would be saved.
Hallelujah.
Look, if you will, at what Jesus said in John 17,
in John chapter 17,
and this is truly the prayer of the Lord,
this is not the model prayer.
Some people talk about the model prayer
as being the Lord's prayer,
but this truly, if you were to coin something
you'd look here in John chapter 17.
I'm not gonna take the time to read the entirety
of this portion of scripture,
but I wanna draw your attention
to what he says in verse number 20,
because actually I am gonna back up
to verse number 14,
and we'll read down through verse number 20.
But I want you to understand here
that as Jesus is praying,
he's revealing truth to us
that's so relevant to what we read
at the end of verse 18 in James 1.
In verse 14,
I have given them thy word.
The world hath hated them
because they are not of the world
even as I am not of the world.
I pray not that thou shouldest
take them out of the world,
but that thou shouldest keep them from the evil.
They are not of the world
even as I am not of the world.
Sanctify them through thy truth.
Thy word is truth.
And we focused on that
with the truth of do not err,
my beloved brethren.
He's given us truth.
Look at verse number 18.
As thou hast sent me into the world,
even so have I also sent them into the world.
Why did he send them into the world?
Well, he sent them to preach the gospel.
Amen.
We've been sent,
where we talk about being sent ones,
and he would send them forth
to preach the gospel.
We can read of the great commission
in each of the gospels
and also in the book of Acts.
And we find that this is the responsibility
and the privilege of every born again believer.
In verse 19,
and for their sakes I sanctify myself
that they also might be sanctified
through the truth.
Notice verse 20.
Neither pray I for these alone,
but for them also
what shall believe on me
through their word.
You know, from the first century,
these believers that Jesus is speaking of
as he's praying in John 17,
those believers faithfully preached
the word of God.
And there were souls that got saved.
James being saved
as he's writing in James chapter number one.
And he talked about being that first fruits,
and there's that expectation.
Why?
Because the gospel continuously got preached
and souls continued to come to Christ.
Because the preaching of the gospel
has been given to us as our mandate,
the great commission,
to go forth and preach the gospel
to every creature.
And the gospel works.
Amen.
The gospel works.
It is the power of God unto salvation.
And so Jesus is praying this
with this long view,
not for these alone,
but for, notice what he says,
for them also what shall believe on me
through their word.
In a very real sense, that's us.
I understand that it's 2026
and it's been 2000 years,
but there's been faithful individuals
that have been preaching the gospel.
There have been churches
that have stood on the truth of God's word.
Listen, all through that time,
Satan has attacked the work of God.
Satan has tried to destroy the work of God.
But remember, Jesus said,
I will build my church
and the gates of hell
shall not prevail against it.
The church has looked different
through the ages.
Church hasn't always met
as we're meeting here today.
Amen.
There are times in which they met in caves.
There are times in which they met in fields.
There are times in which they met in houses.
And you begin to look through the history
and maybe if you studied some church history,
you would see some of the progression
and you would see some of the,
how they had church buildings
and you can look at certain eras of history
and see where church buildings
almost all looked exactly the same
and there were very consistent types of construction
and all of those things.
But you understand that through the ages,
the enemy has tried to destroy the church of God.
Tried to destroy it from without
and then tried to destroy it from within.
But the church of God remains.
And God's given us a responsibility.
And James, as he's writing here,
he says that we should be a kind of first fruits.
It's very like what Jesus prays in John 17
and we understand that we are
the continuation of what James is referring to
and it's a joy to read through the history of time
and to see how many have come to Christ.
Notice, if you will, in Acts chapter number 15.
It's the council at Jerusalem that's being recorded here
in Acts chapter number 15
and there's some debating that goes on.
There's some Judaizers, these false teachers
that are making this claim,
except to be circumcised after the manner of Moses,
you cannot be saved
and that could not be further from the truth, amen.
And so we find that there's this discussion
and all that takes place
and talks about the conversion of the Gentiles
and Peter stands up and Paul is there
and James is gonna make declaration.
But I want you to notice that the Bible says this
in verse number nine
and put no difference between us and them
purifying their hearts by faith.
Now, therefore, why tempt ye God
to put a yoke upon the neck of the disciples
which neither our fathers nor we were able to bear.
Verse 11, for we believe
that through the grace of the Lord Jesus Christ,
we shall be saved even as they.
Speaking of Gentiles.
Why did the church send out missionaries?
Why did Paul go on a missionary,
multiple missionary journeys?
Well, because God told him to, yes,
but the church supported him in that, why?
Because they believed as James says here
that we should be a kind of first fruits of his creatures.
Listen, God is still in the business of saving souls.
I believe that.
He is able to save to the uttermost.
The Bible tells us that he's not willing
that any should perish,
but that all should come to repentance.
I begin to rejoice in understanding
that as James is speaking about this expectation
and you think about how when we have an expectation,
how that affects us.
I think about, you know,
when we were there visiting with Juliana and Evan
and the kids and we would be able to say something to Nova
about something we were gonna do
and she had this expectant heart and attitude.
She was excited because of what she was expecting to happen.
Does that make sense?
And listen, we're expecting Jesus to come back,
hallelujah, and I'm looking forward to that,
but I'm expecting until that day
that the gospel is still gonna work
and there's still gonna be souls that get saved.
And when we go out and we preach the gospel,
we're expecting that God is going to work,
that God is going to use his word.
And when I believe what God says,
then it keeps me from erring.
God's done with, no, no, no, no,
God's not done with
because God's still using his word
and I still believe the word
and we're still gonna go forth and preach.
Why do you think the Bible, again,
to reference back as we started this morning
to the church in Thessalonica,
the Bible says in the first chapter of 1 Thessalonians
that from you sounded the word of truth,
that they were in samples to all.
Listen, they heard the testimony
and it was almost as if Paul,
if I could paraphrase.
and kind of summarize what Paul is saying
in that portion of scripture in 1 Thessalonians 1,
he's saying this, we are going out to preach the gospel,
but when we get there, it's like,
we don't have anything to say
because you've already done it.
Hallelujah.
It's not happened all of the time.
We live in a very busy place, in a very transient area,
with, I mean, just so many people.
But you know, there have been times,
even ministering here now in almost 15 years,
that I give a gospel tract to somebody,
and they're like, hey, somebody else just gave me one.
In fact, there was a time
that somebody pulled one off of the counter,
and they said, yeah, I just got this from somebody else.
Does it look familiar?
And I'm like, yeah, it's from our church.
Hallelujah.
Praise the Lord.
When we were there in Idaho,
a much smaller area as far as population is concerned,
and for those of you that were there on that trip,
you remember, and we shared testimony when we got back,
that there were times that we're passing out
some of those invitations,
and there were other people that were nearby,
and said, yeah, I got one of those earlier this week.
Praise God.
Why do we do that?
Because we're expecting God to use His word.
Why do we stand and preach the word
week after week, week after week?
Because we expect God to use His word
in the hearts of His people,
but also in the hearts of lost people.
And so here we find, again,
this dual application of do not err.
When it comes to the situation of sinful temptation,
don't make excuses.
Don't excuse behavior.
It's me.
It's my own flesh that has the lust,
and I need to identify that,
and I need to walk in the Spirit
so that I will not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
So long as I excuse and make excuses
and blame shift and all of those things,
I'm never gonna have that proper walk with God
that I'm supposed to have.
But then when it comes to the situation
that we read in these last couple of verses
of our text this morning,
you didn't pull yourself up by your own bootstraps.
It's God's blessing and God's favor.
And everything that we have and everything that we are
is because of the good hand of God.
And I believe that.
And when we believe that and we have that perspective,
it changes how we live our lives.
And then we see this thing about the gospel.
James was saved, praise God,
but God intends to save a whole harvest,
not just the first fruits.
And we're engaged in that work.
We are, if you're saved this morning,
part of that harvest,
but we understand there's more that need to be saved.
And what a privilege it is to be involved
in the work of the Lord.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you so much for loving us.
Thank you for the word.
I pray, God, that you would use your word
in the hearts of your people this morning.
God, I pray for the one that might be here
or tuned in via live stream that's not sure of heaven,
whether it's the first time they've ever heard the gospel
or maybe they've heard it repeatedly.
God, I pray that your spirit would work distinctly
in their heart, draw them to you.
Lord, would they humble themselves
and would they accept the free gift of eternal life
before it's eternally too late.
God, I pray for those that are born again.
Lord, help us to have a proper perspective in life.
Help us to have a biblical worldview
and a biblical perspective that your word
would set the course for our thinking and for our behavior
that God, we would not err in this arena.
Lord, that we would recognize that everything that we have
and everything that we are is because of you.
And that God, we belong to you.
Everything that we have, we belong to you.
God, I pray that you'd use us to go forth
with an expectancy that you will use your word,
that you will use the gospel.
It is the power of God unto salvation
and use us as your people.
God, I pray that you'd help us now as we've received
now that we would respond.
Well, thank you, God, for every decision
for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's gonna play quietly on the piano.
Maybe you wanna come this morning and thank God
for every good gift and every perfect gift.
Maybe you wanna come and ask God to help you
to be more faithful and fervent and preach in the gospel
with that heart of expectancy.
Maybe you're not saved this morning.
You've never experienced being born again.
And today is the day of salvation.
However, the Lord may have spoken to you this morning.
Would we do business with God
as Kimberly plays the altars open?