We are his people in the sheep of his pasture
Entered to his gates with thanksgiving and into his courts with praise be thankful unto him and bless his name
For the Lord is good. His mercy is everlasting and his truth endureth to all generations
and what a blessing that song was an encouragement a blessing to my heart this morning and trust to yours as well and
Thank you for providing that special music for us to be in Hebrews chapter number six this morning
Hebrews chapter number six and if you're taking notes will be in verses 1 through 8 the title for the message is go on
to spiritual maturity
Go on to spiritual maturity
You'll remember from our message last Sunday morning as we looked at Hebrews chapter number 5 verses 11 through 14
And we dealt with the subject of your dull of hearing and really I mentioned that this is that warning passage the third warning passage
That we find in the book of Hebrews
It begins in chapter 5 verse number 11 and it goes through the end of chapter number 6 and at the start of the warning
passage the
recipients of the book of Hebrews were
Confronted with their spiritual immaturity
We find that this was a direct result as we studied the passage of Scripture as they're
Being dull of hearing now as we move into the sixth chapter of the book of Hebrews and continue looking at this
Warning passage we find that these recipients will now be challenged to move on to spiritual maturity
The subject of spiritual maturity is of significant importance
often in our lives we are challenged with regard to maybe physical or professional development and
We of course have read things and we've been engaged with the corporate world
I remember the years that I spent working in the corporate world and how much time and energy was spent on professional development
in fact
Many resources personally are invested in those areas of development and there are times in which
We might even develop a plan
In a chart so that we can see our progress we can see
prevent professionally
I remember when I worked at Sikorsky for those several years how that they would make us on an annual basis
We'd have to write goals and we'd have to set all of these things and a number of classes that we would take and how
We were going to develop
Professionally and how we were gonna get there
It was not just something that I want to be better next year than I was this year
Like that's just not cutting it for a goal and we understand those things sometimes from a professional perspective
But I wonder this morning how many of us have a plan with regard to our spiritual maturity our
spiritual development if you will
Do we chart our progress? Do we even know how to chart our progress? Do we have specific goals with regard?
to our spiritual maturity
And I wonder how often we evaluate
those goals if we've made some
Again to use the analogy this morning of the professional development and that
Progress that we would seek to make professionally now
We would set those goals in the beginning of the year, but it was in our best interest
in fact, if you did not go into the portal and
And review those things and chart where your progress was with regard to if you were on track or not
The supervisors would begin to get alerts as to the fact that you've not logged in and you've not made these things
And what were they seeking to do? They were seeking to have us
Regularly go in and evaluate. Okay. I set this goal. How am I doing? Am I on chart?
Am I not again? It would help us to avoid procrastination
in those areas and so
Spiritually speaking the Bible tells us that we're to grow in our walk with Christ that we are to mature
spiritually and we
Understand as we look at this passage of scripture this morning that the foundation for these individuals had been laid
The foundation was there the foundation the gospel the Lord Jesus Christ, but it was time for them to go on
To spiritual maturity notice the first few verses of chapter 6
He says therefore leaving the principles of the doctrine of Christ
Let us go on unto
perfection not laying again the foundation of repentance from dead works and of faith toward God of the doctrine of
baptisms of laying on of hands and of resurrection of the dead
And of eternal judgment and this nursery says this will we do if God permit?
See God desires that we would grow in our walk with him that we would be spiritually mature that we would have the discernment
That we read of in chapter 5 in verse number 14 that spiritual discernment that we could discern both good and
evil and what a blessing to see the
opportunity for the people of God to mature spiritually and we find really as we look at this the
Context of this warning at this point. They had been confronted with their spiritual immaturity
But they were not left there to just flounder around and just well
That's your condition and just it is what it is
No, they were confronted with their position and then they were challenged to move on to spiritual maturity
to make that progress and their walk with Christ and
how
Important it is that we understand that aspect of this challenge that is given in this warning passage
Now the passage that is before us
Admittedly this morning. This is one of the most debated passages in all of the New Testament and you say well, that's encouraging
I agree, and I hope that this morning
I'll say this theologians for generations have debated the passage and they have offered
varying interpretations as to what is being meant
Specifically in verses 4 through 6 and I would like to closely examine the passage of Scripture this morning
Provide you Lord willing I have I have pleaded with God to give me wisdom and direction in that the Holy Spirit of God
Would just give me insight to this passage of Scripture and I hope that I'd be able to
effectively communicate to you what I believe God is teaching us in this passage of Scripture and
Then even I believe sometimes in in the the lives of believers the devil wants us to be distracted
And there are times that he'll distract us from all sorts of things and though we're going to dig in and analyze
closely examine this passage of Scripture and this
context of one of the most
Debated passages in all of the New Testament. We cannot lose sight of the broader message
That is being given to the recipients of the book of Hebrews
The broad message to them and I've mentioned it by way of introduction. We'll deal with it again in the conclusion this morning
but the broad message in this warning passage is that they are confronted with their spiritual immaturity and they are
Challenged to go on to spiritual maturity and we can get caught up in I hate to use this expression
But sometimes you get caught up in the weeds if you will and we can spend so much time
debating
And analyzing a few verses of Scripture and spinning all sorts of interpretations that we miss
The the real emphasis that God is giving to these believers
So as we look at the passage of Scripture this morning and seek to examine
I want you to notice as we look at this passage and really we'll go back to the fifth chapter in verse number 11 and we'll
Go through verse number eight this morning
I'll even touch on verse number nine a little bit
But I want you to notice first of all the use of the pronouns and you say is this English class
No, I hate English class, but it is important
I believe that as we determine or as we seek to analyze and to interpret properly
the passage of Scripture it is of
Significant interest when you go through these verses of Scripture and you notice the way that these pronouns are used
Go back to chapter number five in verse number 11
And I'm gonna read these few verses in verses 11 through 14
And then I'll tell you the pronouns that are used here
Notice what it says of whom we have many things to say and hard to be uttered seeing ye
Are dull of hearing for when the time?
For for when for the time ye ought to be teachers ye have need that one teach you again
Which be the first principles of the oracles of God and are become such as have need of milk and not of strong me as
We dealt with this passage last Sunday morning
I mentioned that obviously the passage is dealing with the believers
Here in verses 11 through 14 for they in the time that you ought to be teachers lost people are never supposed to be teachers
They need to be saved first. Amen. And so they're not going on to spiritual maturity because they're dull of hearing
They're not going through that process of discipleship. And so we find that here he continues in verse 13
For every one that useth milk is unskillful in the word of righteousness for he is a babe
But strong meat belongeth to them that are a full age
Even those who by reason of use have their senses exercised to discern
Both good and evil in those few verses of Scripture at the start of the warning passage
This third warning passage in Hebrews
we find that the pronouns that are used are ye you everyone he them those in there and
contextually as you look at these verses of Scripture and you
the message that is given, it seems quite obvious that these pronouns are
referring to believers. We get into the sixth chapter and of course we
understand that chapter divisions and verses were put in there for the ease of
readership for us and not the way that it was originally given, but we come to
verse number one of chapter six and it says, therefore, and I want you to notice
in these first three verses of chapter six the use of pronouns here, therefore
leaving the principles of the doctrine of Christ, let us go on unto perfection,
not laying again the foundation of repentance from dead works and of faith
toward God, of the doctrine of baptism, of laying on of hands, and of resurrection
of the dead, and of eternal judgment, and this will we do if God permit. We find, as
I mentioned, the foundation that is given to these believers in verses one and two,
the idea is not that we would leave the principles of the doctrine of Christ and
go on and never review those things, for it's important that we have a strong
foundation, it's important that we revisit the basics of Bible teaching, if
you will, and that we're settled and grounded on the faith. I mentioned
last week that as we mature physically our diet no longer exclusively will
consist of milk, but we will begin to have other things, and obviously the
passage deals with milk and meat, and I'm thankful for the meat in our diet as
adults, but my diet that exclusively consisted of milk as a babe now has
broadened as to the things that I partake of, but it does not mean that I
remove completely milk. I don't like milk as much as some others, Joseph likes milk
quite a bit, especially if you put some chocolate in it, I guess that makes it
taste a little better, but the reality is that we understand, even physically
speaking, that the diet, although it progresses to using meat, you don't leave
milk altogether. There are benefits of the milk, and such is the case even for
us as believers, as that analogy would be used. But we notice in chapter 6, verses
1 through 3, the pronouns us and we are used, again, I believe contextually as you
look at the verses of Scripture, that it seems quite obvious that he's referring
to believers. And so we find that in chapter 5, verses 11 through 14, in
chapter 6, verses 1 through 3, there are many pronouns that are used that really
are referring all to the same group of people, believers. These believers that
are dull of hearing, these believers that have not gone on to spiritual maturity,
these believers that are being confronted with their spiritual
immaturity, and they're being challenged to go on to spiritual maturity. But we
come to verses 4 through 6, again, that very debated passage of Scripture, and we
find, as we continue to notice the use of pronouns, that the Bible says this,
for it is impossible for those who were once enlightened and have tasted of the
heavenly gift and were made partakers of the Holy Ghost and have tasted the
good Word of God and the powers of the world to come, if they shall fall away
to renew them again unto repentance, seeing they crucify to themselves the
Son of God afresh and put Him to an open shame. And so we find that there's an
obvious change in the choice of pronouns in verses 4 through 6. The author begins
to use the pronouns those and they and them, and we find that as we would
understand and see this obvious change in the choice of pronouns, I believe that
it reveals to us quite clearly that the author is speaking about a different
group of people. He had been spending time in the first three verses of
chapter 6 of the last four verses of chapter 5 dealing with a specific group
of people, addressing them with the pronouns that he was using, and we
believe contextually being believers. But then all of a sudden, in verses 4
through 6, he uses a different choice of pronouns, referring to a different group
of people, and I believe that as we look at verses 4 through 6 that
contextually, again, that he's referring to unbelievers. So he's referring to
believers at the end of chapter 5, in the very beginning of chapter 6, and then in
verses 4 through 6 he's dealing with a different group of people, that being
unbelievers. We see an example given in verses 7 and 8 that we'll get to as we
get through the scripture, but I just want to touch quickly on verse number
9 of Hebrews 6 because I want you to see how that he once again will use
pronouns and really, by the use of the pronouns, reveal to us that he's going
back to that first group that he was referring to. In verse number 9 of
Hebrews 6 it says, "...but beloved, we are persuaded better things of you and things
that accompany salvation, though we thus speak." In our next message from Hebrews,
next week is Mother's Day, so we will not be in Hebrews, but in the following week
as we continue through the book of Hebrews, we'll be dealing with that truth
of those things that accompany salvation. There are, as I've often used the term,
birthmarks of the believers, and we find that he now will use these pronouns in
verse number 9 to go back to referring to that first group of people, those that
are believers, those who are saved. And so as we begin to seek to analyze the
passage of scripture and begin to look at that which is given to us, I believe
that it's important that we first notice the use of pronouns. Number two, there's a
principle that is important for us to understand hermeneutically. And we speak
about hermeneutics, we're speaking about the interpretation of scripture. We find
that this truth is given in 2 Peter chapter 1, verses 20 and 21. It says,
"...knowing this first, that no prophecy of the scripture is of any private
interpretation. For the prophecy came not in old time by the will of man, but holy
men of God spake as they were moved by the Holy Ghost." When we're proper
hermeneutics would teach that we're supposed to interpret scripture by
scripture. A theologian of yesteryear said this, the best commentary on the
Bible is the Bible. And I think that's a great truth and it's a it's very worth
pointing out. And when you begin to dig into the scriptures, remember God has
given us the responsibility to study to show ourselves approved unto God. Study
means work, it means digging in. And as we begin to look at a passage like verses
4 through 6, and we understand the importance of proper interpretation, I
would say this if you're taking notes, number two, that we always interpret the
obscure with the obvious. We always interpret the obscure with the obvious.
You know what the problem is with many modern-day false teachers, many
modern-day cults, is that they'll go and they'll take a verse of Scripture, they
will completely isolate it from the text, they will not exegete it, but isogete it,
and they will then develop some false doctrine based upon a wrong
interpretation. And one of the problems with this passage of Scripture, and
I don't say a problem as in it's a problem with God, it's a problem with
people that interpret it incorrectly, is that they'll come to this passage of
Scripture in verses 4 through 6 and they will teach that you can lose your
salvation. They will teach from this passage of Scripture that you can lose
your salvation. Now, they take three verses of Scripture, I believe, completely
out of context. That's why I started in chapter 5, verse 11, and go down
through verse 9 and deal with the pronouns that are used there so that we
can begin to really dissect and dig in and see the way that the author is
referring to this group, and then he's obviously used a different choice of
pronouns to give obvious evidence that he's speaking about a different group of
people, then he comes back to that first group, the believers. If you interpret
this passage of Scripture that you can lose your salvation, what you've done is
you have ignored many obvious passages of Scripture that teach the eternal
security of the believer, and it's so precious truth in the Word of God with
regard to the eternal security of the believer. Remember, the Bible teaches us
clearly that the gift of God is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord.
Romans chapter 6 and verse number 23. I'm so thankful that he did not say that
the gift of God is temporary life. He did not say that the gift of God is
probationary life. No, he said the gift of God is eternal life through Jesus
Christ our Lord. One of the most common, I guess, quoted verses in all of the
Bible, at least it used to be, John 3 and verse number 16. For God so loved the
world that he gave his only begotten Son that whosoever believeth in him should
not perish but have everlasting life. It's interesting, if you look in John
chapter number 10, it's one of my favorite passages of Scripture to go to
to deal with the subject of eternal security. Again, we're dealing with the
fact that we always interpret the obscure with the obvious. The Bible is
the best commentary in the Bible, and so when we go to a passage like Hebrews 6
verses 4 through 6, and it might seem that some have spun this idea that you
can lose your salvation, you say, hold on, what does the Bible teach completely on
this subject, and how do we then take that text of Scripture and properly
interpret it? In John chapter number 10, notice what Jesus says in verse
Number 27, my sheep hear my voice, and I know them,
and they follow me.
He says this, and I give unto them, what kind of life?
Eternal life.
And then notice what he says, and they shall never perish.
That's precious.
I mean, the double emphasis, if you will,
that is mentioned in the verse of Scripture,
he said that I give them eternal life,
and they shall never perish.
Neither, notice this as it continues
to elevate the measure of security,
neither shall any man pluck them out of my hand.
My Father, which gave them me, is greater than all,
and no man is able to pluck them out of my Father's hand.
I and my Father are one.
We find that as we studied last year
in the book of Ephesians in the first chapter,
dealing with the plan of redemption
and the price of redemption.
See, before the foundation of the world,
there was a plan that mankind, there would only
be one way to be redeemed.
The passage of Scripture is not speaking about,
in Ephesians 1, the who of salvation,
but the how of salvation.
And God determined before the foundation of the world
that there's only one way to be saved,
and that's through Jesus Christ.
The blood of Christ, the death, burial,
and glorious resurrection of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.
So that was the plan.
The price was the precious blood,
and the proof is the Holy Spirit of God who indwells us.
The Bible tells us there in that passage of Scripture
in Ephesians chapter 1, with regard
to the indwelling of the Holy Spirit,
it says, in whom ye also trusted.
In Ephesians 1, verse 13, after that you
heard the word of truth, the gospel of your salvation,
in whom also after that you believed,
ye were sealed with that Holy Spirit of promise, which
is the earnest.
Notice where he says, of our inheritance,
until the redemption of the purchased possession,
under the praise of His glory.
And if you keep in mind what he says there about inheritance,
and you interpret that and compare that
with the truth of 1 Peter chapter 1, in verses 3
through 5, as Peter here is speaking about salvation
and the blessedness of salvation,
he says this in 1 Peter 1, verses 3 through 5,
blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ,
which according to His abundant mercy
hath begotten us again into a lively hope
by the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead.
Then he speaks about this thing, inheritance,
that we mentioned in Ephesians 1.
Here in verse number 4 of 1 Peter 1,
it says, to an inheritance incorruptible and undefiled,
and that fadeth not away, reserved in heaven for you.
I like the fact that every word of God is pure.
And God put all of these words in here
to reinforce the truth with regard to inheritance.
And then notice verse number 5, who are kept how?
By the power of God.
Who are kept by the power of God through faith unto salvation,
ready to be revealed in the last time.
Paul says this to Titus in Titus chapter 1 and verse number 2
in the introductory statements that he gives.
He says, in hope of eternal life,
which God, that cannot lie, promised before the world
began.
And it's very interesting, and I mentioned this a couple
of weeks ago in our study in the book of Hebrews
when we dealt with the truth of Hebrews 5, verses 1 through 10.
And in that particular message, we
dealt with the truth of our great high priest.
And I made this statement when we
were studying that passage of scriptures.
We looked at verse number 9, that it's
a powerful verse of scripture that
teaches the eternal security of the believer.
And it'd be quite strange for the writer of the book
of Hebrews to say to the recipients
that God, the Lord Jesus Christ, our great high priest,
that he, in verse number 9, being made perfect,
he became the author of eternal salvation
unto all them that obey him.
And then all of a sudden, a few verses later,
say that you can lose it.
It doesn't make any sense.
And so an interesting truth with regard to the passage
that we're studying, not only the fact
that we would interpret scripture by scripture,
and we would interpret the obscure with the obvious,
and we'd look at a number of verses that I've mentioned now,
but it's interesting that even as we examine
the passage of scripture that is before us,
that two very powerful verses that
teach the biblical truth of eternal security
are really set as bookends to this difficult passage.
On the front end, you have that Hebrews 5 and verse number 9
that I just read to you, where he became
the author of eternal salvation.
But then look in chapter number 6 and verse number 19,
and we'll get here in a couple of weeks
and we finish up chapter number 6.
But notice what he says.
It says, which hope we have as an anchor of the soul,
both sure and steadfast, in which entereth
into that within the veil.
So as we begin to examine scripture,
as we begin to interpret scripture,
and we look at this passage, and we
look at these few verses of scripture,
we ask ourselves, is the Bible teaching that you
can lose your salvation?
I would say with great confidence, no.
The Bible is in no way teaching that we
can lose our salvation.
I believe, however, that what we see here
in the passage of scripture is that there
are some that can profess to be saved that are actually lost.
In other words, they have the appearance of being saved.
They have, and we'll look at a few examples.
We get into this here a little bit this morning,
and we begin to look.
It says in verse number 4, for it is impossible for those,
again, remember the use of the pronouns,
but then begin to notice the five descriptions that
are given to us in verses 4 through 6
of this group of people that are being mentioned.
We find in verse number 4, it says,
those who were once enlightened.
That's the first description.
And that word, enlightened, means to give light.
It means that which is exposed to the view of all.
It then says, and here in verse number 4,
not only who were once enlightened
and have tasted of the heavenly gift.
It's interesting as we think about this second descriptive
term, and really the second and the fourth,
because he says there in verse number 5,
and have tasted the good word of God.
And that word, tasted, is used both in verses 4 and verse 5.
And we find that that word means, really,
it has the idea of to make a trial of something.
To try it.
Now, keep these things in mind as we begin to examine
and begin to lay out, I believe, the interpretation
of the past descriptions before us.
So we find, first, they were once enlightened.
Number two, they have tasted the heavenly gift.
Number three, at the end of verse number 4,
it says that they were made partakers of the Holy Ghost.
That word, partakers, it means to be
a partner or a participant.
But you will notice that it does not
say that they were indwelled by the Holy Spirit
or the Holy Ghost.
We understand at salvation that we immediately
are indwelled by the Spirit of God.
Remember what Paul said in 1 Corinthians chapter 6.
What?
Know ye not that your body is the temple of the Holy Ghost,
which is in you, which ye have of God?
We're not our own.
We're bought with a price.
And therefore, we're to glorify God
in our body and our soul, which are his.
And we find here, even as we mentioned
that passage in Ephesians 1, that the Holy Spirit of God
is the earnest of our salvation.
That's the indwelling of the Holy Spirit.
These that are mentioned here in verses 4 through 6,
it does not say that they were indwelled by the Holy Ghost.
It says they were made partakers.
And that word, it means to be a partner or a participant.
And I want you to hold these thoughts
as we begin to use some examples here in just a moment.
I touched already on the fourth description,
that they have tasted the good word of God in verse number 5.
And then the last description that
is given at the end of verse number 5,
it says in the powers of the world to come.
Now as we begin to look at this, we
find that it's described in verses 4 and 5.
It says it's impossible for those.
And then those five descriptive terms are given.
And then notice it says in verse number 6,
if they shall fall away, to renew them again
unto repentance, seeing they crucify to themselves
the Son of God afresh, and put him to an open shame.
By the way, for those that would interpret that you could lose
your salvation, which I do not in any way, shape, or form
believe, they must acknowledge the fact
that if they teach you can lose it,
you could never be saved again.
It's impossible.
And so the question that we'd ask ourselves
as we look at this passage of scripture
is, is this teaching that you can lose your salvation?
Or is this teaching that someone can appear to be saved,
but actually not be saved?
And we find that as we begin to examine
the passage of scripture contextually
within the first century, and understanding all that's
taking place, especially with regard
to the recipients of the book of Hebrews,
these Jewish believers, and we begin
to dissect some things that God gives us in the gospel accounts
and also in the book of Acts.
And I believe that as we look at this passage of scripture
and look at these that are described here,
we can see some that fit this example perfectly.
the Gospels and in the book of Acts. And so if you're taking notes, number three
this morning is consider some first century examples. We want to consider
some of these first century examples and as we consider these and we look at the
passage that's given and we begin to examine some of these examples we say
okay so this is the the teaching that is given but this is someone that that we
can look to and see an example say okay they that's the the position of that
person. Let me start with Judas. We know Judas right? He is one of the twelve. In
John chapter number six, turn back over to John 6 if you will, and I want you to
look in John 6. In fact John 6 is a powerful passage of Scripture that
teaches us many things. It's interesting there were some that came seeking for
Jesus in verse number 24. You can read of that and when they found him they said
rabbi they begin to come to him as teacher in Jesus tells them in verse
number 26 verily verily of a truth of a truth I say unto you you seek me not
because you saw the miracles but because you did eat of the loaves and were
filled. So there are some people that were seeking him and it's interesting as
you study the sixth chapter of the book of John that Jesus repeatedly says to
these individuals I am the bread of life and as he talks about being the
bread of life he tells them that they are to eat of that bread. Right? What were
the words that were used? They had tasted the heavenly gift. They had tasted the
good word of God and so it's interesting in John 6 even to consider those things
but what happens at the end of John chapter number 6 is Jesus is teaching
the the Bible says that he's teaching he says at the end of verse number 60
this is a hard saying who can hear it I believe that many of these and if you
study history and you study various portions of the scriptures you can find
that there are a number of Jewish people that would follow the Lord thinking that
he would provide deliverance from Roman control. He was coming to set up a
kingdom that was going to deliver them from the oppression of the Romans and
when Jesus would confront them about their personal need for salvation that's
when things got a little hairy and when we say that we find that what happens in
this passage of Scripture in verse 66 it says from that time many of his
disciples went back and walked no more with him. Then we find that Jesus turns
to the disciples and says will ye also go away Peter stands up and gives that
powerful answer and says Lord to whom shall we go thou hast the words of
eternal life and we believe and are sure that thou art that Christ the son of the
living God. So remember we're talking about Judas the example notice in verse
number 70 the Bible says Jesus answered them have not I chosen you twelve and
one of you is a devil and it says in verse 71 he spake of Judas Iscariot the
son of Simon for he it was that should betray him being one of the twelve. I
want you to quickly forward to John chapter number 13 we won't have time to
read the entirety of the passage but you'll recall that John chapter number
13 is the passage of Scripture that begins with Jesus washing the feet of
the disciples and we find that he came to minister and he gave a wonderful
example of servant of being a servant and all of that in that passage but then
we find that after the washing the feet we come to verse number 21 and it says
when Jesus had thus said he was troubled in spirit and testified and said verily
verily I say unto you that one of you shall betray me. Now I want you to put
yourself in the position of being one of the disciples at this moment and I
want you to consider the passage we're dealing with from Hebrews 6 and looking
at this example from the first century the example of Judas he says Jesus says
verily verily of a truth of a truth I say unto you that one of you shall
betray me. Do you know that the eleven did not all immediately look at Judas
and say he's the one? They didn't know and in fact you know what they say they
look one to another doubting of whom he spake and there was leaning on Jesus
bosom one of the disciples whom Jesus loved Simon Peter therefore beckoned to
him that he should ask who it should be of whom he spake. We find it in various
portions of Scripture other gospel records that say is it I? Is it I? They
didn't know that it was Judas. Even when Jesus said to Judas in verse number 27
that thou doest do quickly when Judas left the disciples thought that maybe he
was going out to buy the things that they needed but Jesus said one of you's
gonna betray me. Do you know that Judas was was a lost person but he appeared to
be one of the disciples he appeared outwardly all of those things the other
eleven they could not say it's Judas. That's pretty interesting. Not only do we
see the example of Judas consider the example of Simon in Acts chapter number
eight there are others that we can look at in the gospel accounts in fact it's
quite interesting that as we speak about the fact that it says that they have
tasted the good word of God that oftentimes the scribes and the Pharisees
the Sadducees the religious leaders of the day in which Jesus ministered you
will find that oftentimes they would go into his presence not for the purpose of
truly learning something from him but so that they might catch something out of
his mouth that they might accuse him. You go back to the book of Luke and even
the book of Mark and you can read in all of the Gospels but in particular I was
looking at Luke chapter number 11 there as I referenced that portion of
scripture but they they did not go so that they could hear the truth and the
purpose of receiving it but they were trying to catch him in something to
accuse him. We find that Simon in Acts chapter number eight what a powerful
passage of scripture as to all that's taking place in Acts chapter 8 with the
persecution of the church and then they that were scattered abroad went
everywhere preaching the word and how blessed that is and to see how that God
would use Philip and as Philip is preaching and he's being used of the
Lord and the Bible tells us that he's in the city of Samaria that he preaches
Christ unto them that the city that there was great joy in the city people
were saved I mean it's exciting what's going on but there's a guy by the name
of Simon and Simon was there in verse number 9 of Acts 8 the Bible says there
was a certain man called Simon which before time in the same city used
sorcery and bewitched the people of Samaria giving out that himself was some
great one and then we find that some of the manner and then the Bible says in
verse number 12 and we're just gonna kind of cherry-pick through the passage
to lay down the point this morning it says in verse number 12 but when they
believe speaking of those from Samaria believed Philip preaching the things
concerning the kingdom of God and the name of Jesus Christ they were baptized
both men and women then notice verse 13 Simon himself believed also and when he
was baptized he continued with Philip and wondered beholding the miracles and
signs which were done they find that as they look and see all these things that
are happening in verse number 15 that they sent down the news was heard by the
Apostles in Jerusalem and they sent Peter down and John as well and we find
that they come and the Bible tells us in verse 17 that they laid their hands on
them and they received the Holy Ghost and so Simon sees that according to
verse number 18 and he then the Bible says that through laying he saw that
through laying on of the Apostles hands the Holy Ghost was given he offered
them money saying give me also this power that on whomsoever I lay hands he
may receive the Holy Ghost and Peter said unto him thy money perish with
thee because thou hast thought that the gift of God may be purchased with money
thou hast neither part nor lot in this matter for thy heart is not right in the
sight of God repent therefore of this thy wickedness and pray God if perhaps
the thought of thine heart may be forgiven thee for I perceive that thou
art in the gall of bitterness and the bond of iniquity you say man Peter's
tough Peter had spiritual discernment Peter's one of the Apostles one of the
leaders in the first century church remember it was Peter that when Ananias
and Sapphira come in Acts chapter number 5 and they say here here's what
we sold it for God gave Peter spiritual discernment to say really you sold it
for that much and now we find I believe Peter in his level of spiritual
discernment he sees that this one Simon is not truly born again you say but he
believed the Bible says he believed it says it is baptized you know if the
Bible tells us in James 2 19 that the devils believe in tremble you know what
John 1 12 says it doesn't say just believe on Jesus has received to as many
as received him to them gave he power to become the son of it's one thing to
mentally say I believe this but until you actually exercise faith and receive
it you're not a possessor though you might be a professor it's important for
us to understand that distinction it's interesting because when Peter tells him
what he tells them we find that Simon answered in verse number 24 notice what
he says pray you to the Lord for me that none of these things which you have
spoken come upon me he wasn't really interested in salvation he just didn't
want the consequences of those things our time is running out I want to give
you a final example and really I wish we could look at all of them that I have
here my notes but let me give you the example of Felix here in Acts 24 and
except number 24 I'm just gonna read a few verses at the end of the chapter
and I want you to look at the example of Felix where the Bible tells us
that Paul is going to preach to this man.
The Bible says, of course, Paul had been facing
various situations with the persecution and all that he was dealing with.
He'd already stood before the Sanhedrin and given testimony.
And now he's going to give his defense before Felix.
He soon will give his defense before Festus and then Agrippa.
But we find here in Acts chapter number 24,
he's standing before Felix and it says in verse 24.
And after certain days, when Felix came with his wife Drusilla,
which was a Jewess, he sent for Paul and heard him concerning the faith in Christ.
He heard him. What did he hear? He heard the word of God.
It says this, and he reasoned, Paul, and as he reasoned of righteousness,
temperance, and judgment to come, Felix trembled.
Why do you think he trembled? I think he was under a great
heavy dealing with all of that, just conviction of the Holy Spirit of God.
Paul's preaching, and he reasoned of righteousness, temperance, and judgment to come.
And Felix trembled and answered, go thy way for this time.
When I have a convenient season, I will call for thee.
The Bible then tells us in verse number 26 that he'd hoped that he'd get money from Paul
so that he could loose him, so he could let him go.
You know, it's interesting, as we use those terms in Hebrews 6 verses 4 through 6,
and we speak about enlightened, and taste of the heavenly gift,
and all of those terms that were given that I provided you with
in the beginning of this particular point,
I want you to consider what the Bible says of the Lord Jesus Christ in John 1
with regard to this truth of being enlightened.
In verse number 9, John the Baptist is saying that he's not that light.
He was sent to give or bear witness of that light.
But in John 1 in verse number 9, it says,
that was the true light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world.
You know that there is the testimony of creation, that there's a God.
The heavens declare the glory of God.
The firmament showeth forth its handiwork, Psalm 19.
There's the witness not only of creation, there's the witness of conscience.
The Bible tells us of that truth in Romans,
and the fact that God has impressed upon the heart, the conscience of every man,
that there is a God.
And the Bible tells us here, of course, there's the testimony of the Scriptures.
And we look at the Scriptures and how grateful we are to have the whole canon of Scripture.
But we find here in verse number 9 of John 1, it says that,
speaking of Jesus, that he was the true light
which lighteth every man that cometh into the world.
To speak about the truth of the Holy Spirit,
when it says that there are many partakers of the Holy Ghost,
and we witnessed what happened with Felix as he trembled.
It's very interesting, I referenced this morning,
after we sang that song, The Comforter Has Come,
the end of John 15, and then also in John 16, verse number 7.
But in the very next verse of Scripture, it says this,
speaking of the Holy Spirit of God, when he has come,
he will reprove the world of sin, and of righteousness, and of judgment.
Of sin, because they believe not on me.
Of righteousness, because I go to my Father and you see me no more.
Of judgment, because the Prince of this world is judged.
You notice it's very interesting that in the message that Paul preaches to Felix,
the Bible says that he reasoned of righteousness, temperance, and judgment to come.
And this man Felix was under the conviction of the Holy Spirit of God.
You know, the Holy Spirit of God works.
We understand as God's people the work of the Holy Spirit.
Before I was ever indwelled by the Holy Spirit of God,
the conviction of the Holy Spirit came in my life.
And we find here that there are examples that are given to us,
and we mentioned the last reference that is given of the description in Hebrews 6
about the powers of the world to come.
I want you to recall what Jesus said in Matthew chapter number 7.
In Matthew chapter number 7, the Bible gives us a record in verses 21 through 23
of some powerful truth that Jesus gives.
The Bible says in verse number 21,
not everyone that saith unto me, Lord, Lord, shall enter into the kingdom of heaven.
But he that doeth the will of my Father, which is in heaven.
Notice verse 22, many will say to me in that day,
Lord, Lord, have we not prophesied in thy name?
And in thy name have cast out devils.
And in thy name done many wonderful works.
And then I will profess unto them.
Those are sad words.
I never knew you.
Depart from me, ye that work iniquity.
He said, I never knew you.
He didn't say, I knew you once and then you lost it.
I never knew you.
As we go back to Hebrews chapter number 6 and we finish up the passage of scripture,
I want you to notice that there's an illustration that is given in verses 7 and 8
that really helps solidify this whole thought for us this morning
with regard to what the passage is teaching.
We find that there's this illustration that's given in verses 7 and 8
and it really illustrates the truth of verses 4 through 6.
Notice it says this,
For the earth, which drinketh in the rain, that cometh oft upon it,
and bringeth forth herbs meat for them by whom it is dressed,
receiveth blessing from God.
But that which beareth thorns and briars is rejected,
and is nigh unto cursing, whose end is to be burned.
And we can deal with the parable of the Lord with the sowing of the seed
and the various grounds and what have you.
But the reality is, as he would use this illustration,
when the rain comes, the rain comes upon the earth.
And it's interesting how one piece of ground that receives that rain,
that it will produce fruit,
and another piece of ground that receives rain,
it will produce thorns and briars.
And it's a physical illustration of this spiritual truth in verses 4 through 6
that these individuals that are mentioned,
again, as we looked at that use of the pronouns,
a different group of people that are being addressed,
that they had been exposed to the truth of the gospel.
In fact, there were some that even walked with the Lord Jesus Christ.
There was one Judas that was in the inner circle of Jesus Christ,
and yet they were not true believers.
The Holy Spirit of God convicted them.
We see that with Felix.
We can see of many examples of the Jews in the first century
as you read the book of Acts
and you see how they saw the work of the Holy Spirit of God
and how people were healed
and just amazing miracles that took place,
and yet they walked away.
They rejected the light that was given to them.
And we find that John says this in 1 John.
I want you to jot this verse down.
In 1 John 2 and verse number 19,
notice what the apostle John says.
They went out from us, but they were not of us.
For if they had been of us,
they would no doubt have continued with us.
But they went out that they might be made manifest
that they were not all of us.
Now we look at this passage of Scripture,
and as I said in the beginning of our message this morning,
it's important for us to have a biblical understanding
as to what is being dealt with here.
And I trust that you would never allow someone to come to you
and use out of context these few verses of Scripture
and say, see, you can lose your salvation.
If you're not doing this, this, and this,
you can lose your salvation.
It's a scare tactic.
It's not truth biblically.
The Bible says that we're secure in the hand of God,
which is in the hand of Christ.
He says that my sheep hear my voice,
and he says I give them eternal life
and they shall never perish.
I'm so thankful for the biblical teaching of eternal security.
By the way, I cannot say this broadly speaking
because it would not be true of everyone
that teaches the doctrine that you can lose your salvation,
but for many that teach that you can lose your salvation,
it is a form of manipulation and control
to make you do certain things so that you can stay saved.
I didn't get myself saved.
I can't keep myself saved, amen.
It's all, it's not a matter of me holding on to God.
It's a matter of him holding on to me,
and I'm so thankful for the truth of eternal security,
but lest we miss really the greater context of what's going on,
we must remember the warning that is being given here
in Hebrews 5.11 through 6.20,
and they're confronted with their spiritual immaturity,
and then they are challenged that they would go forth,
go on to spiritual maturity.
He says in verse number nine,
the matter of which we'll study in our next lesson,
but beloved, we are persuaded better things of you,
things that accompany salvation, though we thus speak.
The fact of the matter is that we're not saved by works,
and we're not kept by works,
but because I'm saved, I do the works, amen.
James talks about that.
We see it throughout the book of James.
In fact, Titus, as we study the book of Titus
in our adult Sunday school class,
we'll see many references to good works in the book of Titus.
In fact, the apostle Paul,
when he's writing to the believers of Ephesus,
and he tells them that we're not saved through our own works,
he says, we're by grace, or you're saved through faith,
and that not of yourselves, it is the gift of God,
not of works, lest any man should boast,
for we are his workmanship created in Christ Jesus unto good works.
Which God hath before ordained that we should walk in them. What did James say?
James and Paul by the way are not contradictory in the New Testament, and I know there's not a book of Paul
But the writings of Paul they're not
Contradictory Paul often deals with the root of salvation being faith in Christ
But we find even in the verse that I just read in Ephesians and the references in the book of Titus
That he too deals with good works, and he deals with the fruit James
Predominantly is focusing on the the fruit of salvation
You say that you have faith show me your faith
How do you show your faith through your works, but it's not the works that save us
It's the fact that he's now working through us. It's the gift of the Holy Spirit
He gives us those spiritual gifts, and we find that we're to engage in the operation of those spiritual gifts
so that our Heavenly Father would be glorified and so as we look at the passage of Scripture and though we fully
Evaluated the text of Scripture, and I hope have provided you with
with sufficient
Information with regard to proper interpretation
I do not want to lose sight this morning of this truth to go on to spiritual maturity
that we would
invest in
our spiritual development
That we would invest time and perhaps resources
into our walk with God
That we would set goals with regard to our spiritual maturity and that those goals
I want to read my Bible more this year than last year. That's that's not a measurable goal
But we set something out as to what we want to do and how God's gonna work in our lives
And maybe we want to study wouldn't do some word studies a book study
Whatever it might be but but my purpose is that we are to go on to spiritual maturity, and we must have a plan
It's not gonna happen on accident
There's not one day this week that I can think of that I prayed on accident
There's not one day this week that I read my Bible on accident. Oh, I prayed daily
I read my Bible daily because I purpose to do so
Because I had a plan
And in the the passage they're confronted with their spiritual immaturity in their challenge to go on
To spiritual maturity and know that God would help us in
2020 as God's people to go on to spiritual maturity father. We love you. We thank you for loving us
We thank you for the Word of God. Thank you for the truth that is contained therein. I thank you for
The fact that you've told us in your word that the Holy Spirit of God is our teacher and God I pray this morning
That you have helped us
With regard to the passage that is before us. I pray this morning God that you have
Challenged us in our walk with thee that we would go on to spiritual maturity
That we would understand that the foundation has been laid and we need to build upon that foundation
We need to go on to spiritual maturity
Soon, we'll get to the seventh chapter that subject in which the writer is referring to
With regard to those things that were hard to be uttered seeing that you're dull of hearing and God I pray
He would help us to be
Believers that are able to have the strong meat of the word
It'd help us to discern between good and evil
You'd help us to grow spiritually I pray that you'd work in hearts and lives as only you can
Perhaps there's one
That's tuned in this morning. That does not know you as their personal Lord and Savior
Lord perhaps
They this morning are under the conviction of the Holy Spirit of God. I pray father that they would trust Christ
for it's eternally too late as
You're prodding and as you're working in their hearts and lives Lord
Would you help them to place their faith and trust in the finished work of Christ at Calvary?
understanding that Jesus paid it all and
That the gift of God is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord
I pray that you'd have your will and way in each of our lives. We'll thank you for it in Christ's name. We pray
Amen, we'll have a moment of invitation here and I want to