9, verses 15-28.
Really, as we look at the passage of Scripture,
I'll begin reading in v. 15.
We understand that part of the thought
that we finished last week's message with
is a continuation into this week.
And so, we'll mention several things
by way of introduction.
But look at v. 15.
The Bible says,
"...and for this cause He,"
speaking of the Lord Jesus Christ,
God in flesh,
"...He is the mediator of the New Testament,
that by means of death,
for the redemption of the transgressions
that were under the first testament,
they which are called might receive
the promise of eternal inheritance.
For where a testament is,"
notice v. 16,
"...there must also of necessity
be the death of the testator.
For a testament is of force after men are dead,
but otherwise it is of no strength at all
while the testator liveth."
We look at this passage of Scripture.
We'll actually go through the end of chapter 9 this morning.
I've simply entitled the message there
from v. 16-17,
The Death of the Testator.
And you look at the passage of Scripture
and you understand the entirety
of what we're dealing with in the book of Hebrews
and the main thought and the subject matter
and how the writer exalts the Lord Jesus Christ
and proves His superiority.
And what a joy to understand
how these original recipients of this book
that is titled Hebrews,
and we are mindful of that
which they were dealing with
and the immense pressure
to return to Judaism
coupled with the fact that they were living
under intensified persecution
at the hand of Nero.
And you think about those two factors
and you think about all that they were dealing with
and how the content of this book,
the book of Hebrews,
would provide them with encouragement.
It would provide them with instruction.
And we find this morning in 2020,
a couple thousand years almost
since the original writing of this book,
we find that still today,
the people of God are in need of encouragement.
We're in need of instruction.
And we find that the content of this book
will help us in our daily walk with God.
It will remind us over and over
as we read the book of Hebrews,
as we study the book of Hebrews,
that Jesus is superior.
He is better.
There's nothing better than you're ever going to get.
Amen?
There's no other world system.
There's no other religious system.
There's no other thing
that is better than Jesus.
The reality, however,
is that we have an enemy
that is seeking to devour and destroy.
We have an enemy that seeks to say to you
and to say to me
that this is better.
Is it true?
He walketh about seeking whom He may devour.
And He says this is better.
And we say, no, we have Jesus.
Nothing is better than Jesus.
No thing that the world can offer you
is better than Jesus.
No promotion, no person, no popularity.
Nothing is better than Jesus.
Not only does the passage of Scripture tell us
as we study the book of Hebrews as a whole
that Jesus is superior,
but we find that after spending
and laboring through 11 chapters
and really the first 10,
we know that in chapter 11,
dealing with the example of those
that lived by faith,
we come and we find that the writer says
because Jesus is so much better,
because He is superior,
look to Him.
Looking unto Jesus.
Our theme for this year
from Hebrews 12.
And we understand the truth of looking to Him.
And can I tell you that as we gaze upon our Savior,
as we fix our eyes upon our Savior,
that the things of this world
will grow strangely dim.
The songwriter penned those words.
Run your race.
The truth from the book of Hebrews.
Listen, he didn't say the race was going to be easy.
He didn't say there would be no obstacles
or hindrances.
Difficulties along the way.
But he said run your race when or how
as you're looking to your Savior.
And understanding that He will give you
what you need to run that race.
Paul said that there was an open door.
Great and effectual.
But there were many adversaries.
We read throughout the passages
of the Old Testament,
we see how that as the work of God
would go forward in the book of Ezra
and Nehemiah,
you find that they were constantly
met with opposition.
I believe that as we look at Hebrews,
we are reminded that heaven is real.
Heaven is real.
This world is not my home.
I'm just a passing through.
We're looking for a better city.
Heavenly.
Amen?
And as we come to look at the text
of Hebrews as a whole, as a book,
we are reminded of those great truths of Scripture.
And we continue in this 9th chapter
and we find that here as we're going
through this process and the reality
this morning as we get in really
to the beginning of the message
is that we find that for us today,
that we look at the cross
as being something wonderful.
Because we understand that it was there
at the cross that my Savior bled and died.
It was there at the cross that He did
that which He had come to this earth to do.
But you understand for the Jewish people
at the original time of this writing,
in fact, many times even still today
as we see in the book of 1 Corinthians,
that the cross is a stumbling block.
They ask this question immediately
following the timing of the life and death
and of course the resurrection
and the ascension of Christ
and all that's moving forward
with the early church
and all that's taking place
and you find that there are many
that would say, why did He have to die?
The death of Christ really kind of
adversely affected many that were Jews.
Why? Because they were looking for a Messiah
who was going to set up a kingdom,
who was going to deal with the Romans,
who was going to do all of those things
and they missed the fact that the Old Testament
had consistently given the truth,
the picture, the typology
that the Messiah would die
for the sins of the world.
And so as we look at this passage of Scripture,
we find that as the writer is kind of again
peeling back another peel of the onion
and providing another glimpse
into the understanding that He's better.
Why? He's a better priest
and He served in a better place, right?
The sanctuary in heaven.
That true tabernacle.
He presented a better offering.
It was His own blood.
And we find that He gave us through that
a better gift.
And as we look at the truth
of what the passage that we're dealing with
in Hebrews 9 is dealing with,
we come and we notice first of all,
if you're taking notes,
it's the bulk of the section
in which we'll be dealing with.
In fact, as I mentioned,
that really the latter part of last week's message
goes right into it.
And it's this, number one,
notice the atonement of Christ.
That word atonement is the expiation of sin
made by the obedience and suffering of Christ.
We understand when we speak about the death of Christ,
we understand that as He said there in John 17,
the hour has come.
Jesus understood the purpose
in which He came to this earth.
In fact, earlier in the book of John,
He mentions about destroying this temple
and in three days I'll raise it up.
And speaking of His own body
and of course, not only the death,
but the resurrection.
You remember that during the time
in which the Lord Jesus Christ
interacted with His disciples and He said,
whom do men say that I am?
And then He says, but who do you say that I am?
And after Peter stands up with great boldness
and says, thou art the Christ,
the Son of the living God,
we find that Jesus,
if you look at the text of Scripture,
He then began to share with them
the things that would shortly come to pass
concerning what?
His death and His resurrection.
And so we notice the atonement of Christ
as we look at those few verses
that we've mentioned.
Actually, back up into verse 12.
The Bible says,
neither by the blood of goats and calves,
but by His own blood,
He entered in once into the holy place,
having obtained eternal redemption for us.
Remember, He went to a better place,
the heavenly tabernacle.
He offered a better sacrifice.
It was His own blood,
not the blood of bulls and goats.
And we find that He obtained for us
a better gift, eternal redemption.
We see it unfolded in verse 12.
The Bible says that He entered in once.
As I mentioned last week,
as we look at that phraseology
and we even couple it with what we find
in verse 26,
the latter part of verse 26,
but now once in the end of the world
hath He appeared to put away sin
by the sacrifice of Himself.
It's interesting as we understand
the beginning of the ninth chapter
of the book of Hebrews
dealing with the earthly tabernacle
and dealing with the holy place
and the Holy of Holies.
And I told you last week
that what was in view
was really the Day of Atonement.
And it's interesting because we understand
that it says that He entered in once.
Not only did He only go in once,
but He only had to do it once.
Once for all.
The High Priest,
when He would go in on the Day of Atonement,
He would enter in that first time
to present the blood of a bull
for His own sins.
And then He would come out
and He'd have to go in a second time.
Look at Leviticus 16. You can see it.
With the blood of the goat.
Why? For the sins of the people.
Jesus had no sin.
The just for the unjust.
Therefore, He only had to enter
into the Holy of Holies once
to present His perfect, sinless blood.
And by the way,
as you look at the truth of the Day of Atonement,
not only did the High Priest go in twice
on that same day,
but then next year it would have to be repeated
and the year after that and the year after that.
But with the sacrifice of Jesus, it's not so.
We see the atonement of Christ.
It's in full view.
We understand that it's a substitutionary atonement.
He took your place.
He took my place.
We understand that it was a blood atonement
as we continue looking through the passage of Scripture.
Pick it up with me in verse 18.
The Bible says,
"...whereupon neither the First Testament
was dedicated without blood.
Notice, for when Moses had spoken
every precept to all the people
according to the law,
he took the blood of calves and of goats
with water and scarlet wool and hyssop
and sprinkled both the book and all the people,
saying, this is the blood of the Testament
which God hath enjoined unto you.
Moreover, he sprinkled with blood
both the tabernacle and all the vessels
of the ministry.
And almost all things are by the law
purged with blood,
and without shedding of blood is no remission."
What is the writer saying to these believers?
What is he saying to us this morning?
The death of Christ was absolutely necessary.
We find that as we read in v. 16,
it says for where a Testament is,
there must also of necessity
be the death of the testator.
As we understand that truth
and we understand through His death
and glorious resurrection
that the promise of eternal redemption
can now be received.
See, the reality is that at the end of v. 15,
it says they which are called
might receive the promise of eternal inheritance.
Remember, in v. 12,
He said that He had obtained
eternal redemption for us.
How many of you have a will?
Not very many of you.
You need to go see a lawyer or something.
I'm not trying to get anything on the side.
I'm just simply saying it's common, right?
People have wills.
The reality is that if you have a will,
until you are deceased,
it is not in effect.
Correct?
In fact, I am often reminded,
though my dad's not here this morning,
I believe he's watching live stream,
he has a will.
And he'll say something like this
every once in a while.
I'm going to change my will.
Right? Doesn't he?
Taking you out of my will.
Why can he say that?
Because he's still alive.
You have a will.
It can be changed if you're alive.
What probates the will is the death.
Correct?
So understand that as we're looking
at the passage of Scripture,
and we find that the writer of Hebrews
is presenting to these Jewish believers
that it was absolutely imperative,
it was necessary for Christ to die.
We find that all the way back in Genesis.
We find that in chapter 3,
when sin entered into the world,
you see the truth in Genesis 3
in verse 15 concerning the first mention
of the truth that God Himself,
the Lord Jesus Christ,
would die for the sins of man.
You find that there in Genesis 3,
immediately after Adam and Eve
committed the sin,
what did they try to do?
They tried to cover it with the works
of their own hands,
with the fig leaves that they sowed together,
but it was not accepted.
What did God do?
He sacrificed an animal
and He made a coat of skins.
From that day forward,
you read, as you think about Cain and Abel,
the reality of the accepted offering
was the one that was blood.
And you go through the whole
of the Old Testament,
and you see that God has designed it
such that without shedding of blood
is no remission.
And therefore, God Himself,
the Lord Jesus Christ,
He would go to the cross of Calvary
and He would shed His precious blood
so that that which He had promised
could be obtained.
We find that what had been pictured
has now been purchased.
We find the necessity.
We see the Old Testament type
in the verses that we just read
speaking of Moses
and how He took and He sprinkled that blood.
The people. The book.
And all that He did.
He talks about the fact that He
did all those vessels of the ministry.
And you look back in the books of Exodus
and Leviticus,
and you see the carrying out
and the reference in which the writer is making.
And we're mindful this morning
of this wonderful truth again
as we think about the death of Christ
and His glorious resurrection.
We find that the offering of Himself
was accepted.
It was an acceptable offering.
In verse 23 of our text of Scripture,
it says,
it was therefore necessary...
We see that word again.
That the patterns of things in the heavens
should be purified with these,
but the heavenly things themselves
with better sacrifices than these.
For Christ is not entered into the holy places
made with hands,
which are the figures of the true,
but into heaven itself,
now to appear in the presence of God for us.
For yet, that He should offer Himself often
as the high priest entereth into the holy place
every year with blood of others.
For then must He often have suffered
since the foundation of the world.
But now once in the end of the world
hath He appeared to put away sin
by the sacrifice of Himself.
Let's look at several passages of Scripture
throughout the Word of God this morning.
Look over to the book of Philippians if you will.
I'm going to reference a number of passages
and hope that we understand
not only the necessity of the death of Christ
and His shed blood,
but we understand this morning
what it accomplished.
How that our redemption was paid for
with the blood of Christ.
How that the problem of sin
is dealt with only with the blood of Christ.
And is dealt with once and for all.
And what a joy that is.
Remember, I mentioned last week
how that the Old Testament sacrificial system
was a constant reminder of sin
while the sacrificial offering of Christ
once for all offers remission for sin.
What a blessing.
We find in the book of Philippians
in chapter 2, beginning in verse 5,
the Bible says,
let this mind be in you,
which was also in Christ Jesus,
who being in the form of God
thought it not robbery to be equal with God.
Why? Because He is God.
Verse 7,
But made Himself of no reputation
and took upon Him the form of a servant,
was made in the likeness of men.
Notice verse 8,
And being found in fashion as a man,
He humbled Himself
and became obedient unto death,
even the death of the cross.
My sin, O the bliss of this glorious thought,
my sin, not in part, but the whole,
is nailed to His cross,
and I bear it no more.
Praise the Lord! Amen?
Look at Colossians, if you will,
and notice in chapter 2,
in verse 14,
the Bible says,
blotting out the handwriting of ordinances
that was against us,
which was contrary to us,
and took it out of the way,
nailing it to His cross.
Do you know this morning
that every sin that you've ever committed
was future when Jesus died?
You say that's not very deep.
I understand.
But we need to be reminded of that.
Why?
Because we sing, even as our family in the past
has sung that song,
it's under the blood.
Listen, there is an accuser of the brethren
in Revelation 12.
I understand you don't need to turn there.
It's about the midpoint of the tribulation.
And you understand the Bible speaks
about the accuser of the brethren.
And He is.
And here's an interesting truth
that is given with regard to our adversary.
The Bible says that He came down to them.
Again, I understand contextually
in the midst of the tribulation,
but it says having great wrath.
Why?
Because He knoweth?
that He hath but a short time.
I believe this morning,
more than I've ever believed it,
that our Enemy is real
and He is active.
He is active.
But we have the blood.
We have the blood!
And this morning, as we understand
the atonement of Christ
and we understand what was accomplished
through the atonement,
we understand this morning
that we rejoice in it.
We see glory in the cross.
But again, for these Jewish believers,
and even still to this day,
many Jewish folks have a challenge
speaking about the cross.
And we find that Paul reveals to us
as he's writing to the believers in Corinth
in 1 Corinthians 1,
he's speaking often about the preaching
of the cross.
But he says in verse 23,
but we preach Christ crucified
unto the Jews a stumbling block
and unto the Greeks foolishness.
But, verse 24,
unto them which are called
both Jews and Greeks,
Christ, the power of God,
and the wisdom of God.
I'm so thankful for the privilege
and the opportunity to preach the cross.
To understand what happened
on the cross of Calvary
and how the wrath of God
was poured out upon the Son of God.
God Himself.
He hath made Him to be sin for us
who knew no sin
that we might be made
the righteousness of God in Him.
We find that as we look at the passage of Scripture
and we are mindful of what was accomplished
on the cross of Calvary,
I want you to understand this morning
that as a child of God,
you've trusted the Lord Jesus Christ
as your Savior,
that it was the payment of His blood
that allowed for you to receive that free gift.
But can I tell you this morning
that the enemy's still working?
We find that the Bible would reveal to us
as we mentioned in previous messages
the truth of 1 John 1
and even going into the second chapter
about the fact that the sin
in the life of a believer,
if we confess our sins,
He is faithful and just to forgive us
from our sins and to cleanse us
from all unrighteousness.
What a wonderful truth.
What a wonderful promise of the Word of God.
See, this morning,
turn over if you will to the book of Jeremiah.
I'm going to go to Isaiah in a moment,
but I want to start here in Jeremiah 2.
Because I want you to understand
the power of the blood.
We sing about the power of the blood, right?
There's power, power,
wonder-working power.
We sing about the blood
in many references.
Are you washed in the blood?
In the soul-cleansing blood of the Lamb?
When we sing that chorus,
I love to say these words.
When it says, are you washed in the blood?
I love to say, yes, I am.
Isn't that wonderful?
Notice in Jeremiah,
you understand that the people of God
are under a great indictment.
In fact, as you look at the second chapter
of the book of Jeremiah,
you will find many things
with regard to the indictment
that is laid against the nation of Judah.
And you would understand
that they had forsaken God.
Why? Because they had forgotten God.
And because they had forgotten God
and forsaken God,
they followed after idols.
We find that throughout the Old Testament
in many of the messages of the prophets,
amend your ways.
Right?
Look at what God says in Jeremiah 2
in verse 22.
For though thou wash thee with niter
and take thee much soap,
yet thine iniquity is marked before Me,
saith the Lord God.
Niter and soap doesn't do it.
It doesn't work.
By the way, these are two very powerful things
that can cleanse a lot of stuff.
But it can't cleanse you and it can't cleanse me.
It's only the blood.
He said, look, there's the indictment.
Here's what's going on.
Here's the sin.
And I want you to know,
it's interesting in the book of Ezekiel,
I'm going to go to Isaiah 1 if you will,
but I want you to understand that there
as we read through the book of Ezekiel again
as the prophet is prophesying,
and the Bible tells us
at the end of chapter 33
in the book of Ezekiel
about the fact that they heard the words,
but they didn't do it.
Jeremiah's calling them to a place of repentance
God had often given
through the prophets
not only in Jeremiah 2,
but there in Ezekiel,
He had given a voice.
In Isaiah 1,
I wish I could read the entirety of the passage.
Let me read just a couple of verses.
In verse 2, the Bible says,
Hear, O heavens, and give ear, O earth,
for the Lord hath spoken.
I have nourished and brought up children
and they have rebelled against Me.
The ox knoweth his owner,
the ass his master's crib,
but Israel doth not know My people,
and they doth not consider.
Look what it says in verse 4.
All sinful nation.
A people laden with iniquity.
A seed of evildoers.
Children that are corruptors.
They have forsaken the Lord.
They have provoked the Holy One of Israel into anger.
They are gone away backward.
Can I tell you this morning
that as we look at the truth of the New Testament,
even if you're saved this morning
and your relationship with God
is settled at Calvary,
that there can be sin in the life of a believer.
And that sin in the life of a believer
causes our fellowship to be hindered.
It's not worth it.
Why?
Because Christ is better.
Because He's better.
He's better than that position.
He's better than that person.
He's better than whatever!
He's better.
And here's what God says in Isaiah 1.
Again, I wish we could read the entirety of the passage.
But the indictment is clear
in the first few verses that I've read.
You come in verse 18.
Come now, and let us reason together,
saith the Lord.
Though your sins be as scarlet,
they shall be as white as snow.
Though they be red like crimson,
they shall be as wool.
If ye be willing and obedient,
ye shall eat the good of the land.
But if ye refuse and rebel,
ye shall be devoured with the sword.
For the mouth of the Lord hath spoken it.
The reality this morning,
when we think about the death of Christ
and we notice the atonement of Christ
there in Hebrews 9 and verses 12-26
and we see the necessity of it.
In Isaiah 53, by the way,
the passage that we referenced last week
on Sunday evening,
we talked about the eunuch, right?
That was the passage he was reading.
And we find that it would be clear
in the passage that Christ would suffer,
that He would go to the cross of Calvary,
that our iniquities were laid upon Him,
the Messiah.
We find that Christ's death
accomplished for us eternal redemption.
We find that as believers,
that as we walk in this life
after we've trusted the Lord Jesus Christ,
that we have the accuser of the brethren,
that we understand that He attacks,
we understand that we have this flesh.
And when we sin, we have an advocate with the Father.
Isn't that precious?
1 John 2.
We have an advocate with the Father
who says, I paid for that with my blood.
What shall we say then?
Shall we continue in sin
that grace may abound?
God forbid!
We don't live as if we say,
well, I have this liberty.
I can do whatever.
I can do what pleases me
because I can just confess it.
Oh, but what we miss out on.
The joy of what we have on this earth
with our fellowship with God,
that we willingly surrender that
for something far inferior.
For some momentary pleasure.
Hebrews 11 says that there is pleasure in sin
for a season.
And as we look at the truth of God's Word,
we say Christ is superior.
We see that the believers in Hebrews 9,
they're being instructed with regard
to the necessity of Christ's death,
but their understanding as the writer
is packaging this thing together.
He's saying, listen, Jesus died
so that you could be saved
and His blood is sufficient
and it's accepted.
And if He didn't die,
these promises that we've spoken of
could never be in effect.
Remember, all the way back in Hebrews 2,
in verse 14,
the Bible says for as much then
as the children are partakers of flesh and blood,
He also Himself likewise took part of the same,
that through death...
he might destroy him that had the power of death. That is the devil. 1st John
chapter number 3 and verse number 18 we find that the Bible tells us there that
that we excuse me in verse number 8 he that committed sin is of the devil for
the devil sinneth from the beginning for this purpose the Son of God was
manifested that he might destroy the works of the devil. I'll repeat what I
said moments ago our enemy is real and our enemy is active he's active he's
seeking whom he may devour you have a target on you I have a target on me the
world the flesh and the devil it's against us but we have something so much
greater we have Jesus but the enemy knows he knows how to get you he knows
how to get me he knows how to get you he's been studying mankind for a long
time he's not God praise God for that he's far listen greater see that is in
you than he that is in the world but here's the problem sometimes we make
ourselves vulnerable submit yourselves therefore to God resist the devil what
does it say and he will flee from you I often compare to known Bible accounts
when I think about this truth one of Joseph and one of David the wife of
Potiphar cast her eyes upon Joseph day by day listen just because you say no
once doesn't mean the devil is gonna give up he didn't keep coming you can
keep knocking on your doors and keep knocking on your door he's gonna keep
tempting you but Joseph he put on his running shoes so to speak he got out of
there I've often said of Joseph that he lost his coat but he retained his
integrity his character oh he was lied about he suffered in prison it's part of
God's plan it was not part of God's plan for him to commit that sin with that
woman amen what about David who is that it's Bathsheba she's the daughter of but
she's the wife of Uriah the Hittite God given warning through his servant what
did David say bring her to me for I want her if you read about the confession of
David in Psalms 51 in Psalm 51 you read a brokenhearted man that receives
forgiveness and restoration because we have a great God we have a merciful God
who's ready to pardon ready to forgive we have a God who is extending that
mercy and we find that David praise many things in Psalm 51 but one thing that he
prays restore unto me the joy of my salvation David what took your joy sin
it robbed my joy it stole it from me see the atonement of Christ is so important
we understand what it does for us in salvation but understand this morning
what it does for you daily to understand the blood the fact that based
on what Christ did at the cross of Calvary I can confess my sins and know
that I have an advocate with the father and know that we can plead the blood and
when the devil as the accuser of the brethren wants to come to you and accuse
you say I have Jesus and here's what he provided for me here's what he did for
me see the world's not worth it but can I tell you the devil wants you to think
it is the devil wants to make it look shiny and pretty and fill in the blank
right the devil he knows what he's doing this morning we see we notice the
atonement of Christ as you look back in Hebrews 9 we read through verse 24 look
at verse 25 nor yet that he should offer himself often actually read this verse
2 but that's okay and verse 25 as the high priest enters in the holy place
every year with blood of others notice 26 for then must he often have suffered
since the foundation of the world but now once in the end of the world hath he
appeared to put away sin by the sacrifice of himself do you like that
phrase to put away sin I've often said and I appreciate the truth that we find
in the Word of God with regard to the fact that prior to salvation we were
bound we were slaves to sin we're lost and undone strangers foreigners we're
bound by our sin we were under a heavy penalty death for the wages of sin is
death I'm so thankful that the death burial and resurrection of the Lord
Jesus Christ gave me freedom from the penalty of sin but can I tell you this
morning that it gave me the victory over sin it power over sin sin no longer I'm
no longer bound by sin Romans chapter 6 you look through there and you see the
the wondrous truth of the fact that I'm no longer bound by sin I said this as we
look at the passage that's there in Romans chapter number 6 I've said this
in the past that that the reality is that what we need in America what we
need in our homes of salvation with that transformation and then we need to walk
with Christ because we understand our identity in Christ Ephesians you look at
the passages throughout the book and you find that it is absolutely hammered home
in Ephesians 1 through 3 that if you've trusted Christ your Savior you are his
child you are secure in Christ but now you better start living like it walk
worthy of your calling of your vocation walk not as other Gentiles walk walk in
truth walk in love we look at all of that truth walk circumspectly right and
we find that as we look at the truth of the Word of God that Paul says this in
Romans 6 and verse 17 but God be thanked that ye were the servants of sin but ye
have obeyed from the heart that form of doctrine which was delivered you being
made free from sin you became the servants of righteousness praise God
sin no longer has that power over us but sometimes we we walk in the flesh and
not in the spirit the enemy makes it look real good but he's a liar he's the
father of it he hates you he hates God we see the atonement notice most out of
time and I got a lot more to say amen does anyone got a roast on this morning
that you're afraid is gonna burn don't answer change that timer on the thing
hope you have a Wi-Fi oven amen they sell those things now by the way notice
as we continue through the passage notice our appointment with death verse
27 I won't spend much time here I'd like to get to the latter part of the
passage Hebrews 9 in verse 27 it's a verse that we often quote the Bible says
as it and as it is appointed unto men wants to die but after this the judgment
you know there are people today that have this belief that you just die like
you just die and you buried and it's all over it's not true on the authority of
the Word of God why is it appointed unto man wants to die because of sin right
the penalty of sin is death but we understand that this is speaking of a
spiritual death right there's a physical death and a spiritual death we live in
this sin cursed world where everything's breaking down the disease and all that's
taking place in our society in our world it's because of sin God didn't make it
that way in the beginning it was perfect but sin entered in the the society
begins to break down and we have death as a result and you find that physical
death but more importantly the truth of the spiritual death or the Bible says
that in row in Revelation chapter number 20 that death and hell were cast in a
lake of fire this is the second death I've often mentioned that to be born
once is to die twice but to be born twice is to die but once why because
Jesus said to Nicodemus in John chapter number three he must be born again he
must be born again we've been born physically and praise God
I thought I was born spiritually, I was born again.
The first birth, we celebrate annually, typically.
Some people don't like celebrating it
once they get to a certain age.
Or they like to pretend that it's number 29 or 39
for the however many times, you know, that sort of thing.
Can I tell you that I'm more excited
about my spiritual birth even than I am my physical birth?
I understand this morning that I couldn't have
a spiritual birth if I didn't have a physical birth.
I get that.
But can I tell you that August 31st is my spiritual birthday
and that day in so many ways is more important to me
than my physical birthday?
Because I was born again.
I was delivered from the penalty of sin.
I didn't understand on that day all that Christ did for me.
But the more I walk with Christ,
the more over these 23 some years
that I've been walking with the Lord and reading His Word,
oh, how precious it becomes
what Christ did for me on that day.
The Bible says,
no point unto man once to die, after this the judgment.
We know of two judgments specifically,
there's a bema seed, the judgment seed of Christ.
If you're a believer this morning,
you will stand before Christ at that judgment.
Paul deals with it, he speaks of it
as he's giving truth with regard to the bema.
But we find the Bible speaks
about the great white throne judgment
in Revelation chapter number 20.
I quoted part of that when I said death and hell
were cast in like a fire, this is the second death.
That's the verdict at that great white throne judgment.
If you've been born again, thank God,
you will not have to stand
at the great white throne judgment.
Thank God that the second death has no power over you.
We look at the last part of Hebrews 9,
we notice the atonement,
we notice our appointment with death,
but I want you to consider the appearing of Christ.
I mentioned how that the song service,
especially the last song that we sang this morning
as a congregation, it is well with my soul,
how wonderful to think about how verse three and four
fit so beautifully with the passage that is before us.
My sin, oh, the bliss of this glorious thought,
my sin not in part, but the whole, right?
And we rejoice that it's nailed to His cross,
I bear it no more, but then we come to the fourth verse,
and Lord, haste the day when my faith shall be sight.
Hebrews 9 and verse 28, so Christ was once offered,
remember, we've mentioned this multiple times
through the passage of Scripture,
not only was it once as opposed to twice
as the day of atonement with the high priest,
he only had to enter once, why?
Because he didn't have to make a sacrifice for his own sin,
just for the sin of the world.
I say just, that's a significant truth,
but he didn't have to for his own sin, he had no sin.
And he only had to do it one time forever.
We see that it says, to bear the sins of many,
notice, and unto them that look for him
shall he appear the second time,
without sin unto salvation.
The reality is the first time he came,
he came to deal with sin, and he's dealt with it.
We've often said that he came as a lamb the first time.
When he comes at the end of the tribulation,
he will come as a conquering king,
the lion of the tribe of Judah.
He is king of kings and Lord of lords.
Can I tell you this morning,
that though this truth of his second appearing
has not taken place,
we have full confidence that he shall appear.
It says, they that look, notice,
and unto them that look for him
shall he appear the second time
without sin unto salvation.
The reality is that it's not meaning
that if we're not looking that he's not gonna come,
but I want you to think about the truth
and the splendor, the joy of those that are looking for.
We find that Paul says it this way to Titus
in the second chapter.
He's speaking of the blessed hope looking,
and we understand the appearing of our great God and Savior,
the Lord Jesus Christ.
This blessed hope that he shall appear.
I'm listening for the trumpet, amen.
I know that Brother Mershawn often says,
I'm not looking for the undertaker,
I'm looking for the upper taker.
I mean, I'm thrilled to be able to report to you this morning
that we are closer than we've ever been.
And I can say that every day until he returns, amen.
We are closer than we've ever been.
There are many things, I believe,
in the world that seem to be indicators
of the fact that we are really, really
on the doorstep of the rapture.
But the reality is that no man knows the hour.
The truth of the appearing of the Lord Jesus Christ,
his second coming ought to affect his people.
It ought to impact you.
Think about how it influenced
the disciples in the book of Acts.
I got 25 verses to look at.
We don't have anywhere near the time.
So let me just share a few things with you.
Actually, Jason, you sent me a really nice note recently.
Amen.
You know what he said to me in the note?
He said, sometimes I'm watching live stream
and it seems like you kind of feel like
you're looking at the clock and you need to kind of hurry.
He said, just preach the word.
Amen.
He gave me permission, amen.
I like it.
Let's look at the verses, amen.
God's word is powerful.
John 14 and verse number six.
He says, I am the way, the truth, and the life.
But before that, we look at John chapter number 14
and we find that he says, let not your heart be troubled.
You believe in God, believe also in me.
In my Father's house are many mansions.
If it were not so, I would have told you.
I go to prepare a place for you.
He then says this, and if I go and prepare a place for you,
I will come again and receive you unto myself
that where I am, there you may be also.
In Acts chapter number one,
now understand that the disciples heard that
in John chapter number 14.
They heard that truth before Jesus went
to the cross of Calvary.
In Acts chapter number one,
Jesus has already been crucified.
He's already been buried.
He's already raised from the dead.
He's been there for 40 days.
He's about to ascend.
And in fact, he gives that great commission once again
about being his witnesses.
And in verse number eight,
and the Bible says that when he had spoken these things
in verse number nine, while they beheld, he was taken up
and a cloud received him out of their sight.
And while they looked steadfastly toward heaven
as he went up, behold, two men stood by them
in white apparel, which also said,
ye men of Galilee, why stand ye gazing up into heaven?
This same Jesus, which was taken up from you into heaven,
notice, shall so come in like manner
as you have seen him go into heaven.
I like the absolutes of God's word
where he uses the word shall.
I like that word.
He says, I will come again.
By the way, every promise that God has ever given,
he fulfills.
Amen?
We notice that in the book of 1 Thessalonians
in chapter number four,
and really 1 and 2 Thessalonians are full of truth
with regard to the subject of eschatology
and the instruction to the people of God.
In 1 Thessalonians chapter number four,
Paul says, I don't want you to be ignorant.
I want you to be informed.
I want to give you the word of the Lord.
I want you to understand the truth.
He tells them in 1 Thessalonians chapter number four
in verses 16 and 17,
for the Lord himself shall descend from heaven
with a shout,
the voice of the archangel,
with the trump of God,
the dead in Christ shall rise first.
Then we which are alive and remain
shall be caught up together with them in the clouds
to meet the Lord in the air.
And so shall we ever be with the Lord.
I mentioned earlier the truth of Titus two in verse 13,
where Paul says, looking for that blessed hope
and the glorious appearing of the great God
and our savior, Jesus Christ.
Hebrews nine and verse 28,
the verse that we've looked at,
but I want you to see in chapter 10,
what the Bible says about the truth of Christ's return.
It says at the end of chapter number nine
that he shall appear in Hebrews 10 in verse number 37.
And it says for yet a little while
and he that shall come will come and will not tarry.
James five in verse number eight.
You say this is a repeated message.
Yes, because it has a powerful impact
and we'll get to that in just a moment.
Notice James five in verse number eight,
but be ye also patient,
establish your hearts for the coming of the Lord.
And draweth nigh.
First Peter five in verse number four.
Peter is speaking in the passage to pastors
and about the importance of our responsibility
to feed the flock of God, so on and so forth.
And he goes through that process
and he comes to verse number four and says,
and when the chief shepherd shall appear.
Who is that?
That's Jesus.
shall receive a crown of glory that fadeth not away."
Peter didn't say if, he said when the chief shepherd
shall appear, amen?
Because he's going to.
Second Peter three, in verse number nine,
the Lord is not slack concerning his promise, right?
We find that it says as some men count slackness,
but what he is long suffering to us,
we're not willing that any should perish,
but that all should come to repentance.
The context of what Peter is saying here
is that there are those that are walking around
that are scoffers and mockers, and they're saying,
hey, where is the promise of his coming?
And Peter says, don't get discouraged.
He's coming.
He's going to come, right on time.
First John chapter two.
Let me make some comments
before I read the portion of scripture.
I've read many passages to you
with regard to the promise of his coming.
We see as we finish Hebrews chapter nine,
we consider the appearing of Christ,
the fact that he is going to return,
and we find that this truth of God's word
had a great impact and influence on the people of God.
No doubt as you read the book of Acts
and you see all that happened to the church
in that first century,
and you see how the gospel went forward
under great levels of persecution,
and you read of all that happened,
I believe that it was mindful to those disciples
that they watched Jesus ascend up into heaven,
and they heard those angels say, he's coming again.
Listen, when we live daily,
understanding that today could be the day,
when we're looking for his appearing,
it will change our behavior.
It will change what we do.
We'll be living under the understanding
that today will be the day.
It could be the day.
No doubt it influenced the people of God
that we read of in the word of God.
The New Testament, full of truth
with regard to the return of Christ.
We can look at history of the church.
We can see how this truth of the return of Christ
has influenced generations of believers.
We come to 1 John 2 and notice verse 28.
And now little children abide in him,
that when he shall appear, we may have confidence.
Notice what this says.
And not be ashamed before him at his coming.
I asked a question on Wednesday evening.
Some of you were here.
Hopefully some of you are watching live stream.
If not, it's recorded, you can go watch it.
I would encourage you to do so.
Exodus chapter number 16, would you have passed the test?
Would you have passed the test?
I said I wanted to ask myself the question.
I said I want you to ask yourself the question.
You say, what test?
I didn't know there was a test.
Exactly.
Go listen to the message.
They didn't know there was gonna be a test either.
Some passed, praise God.
Some failed.
I'll ask you to ask yourself the question here
just as I've asked myself.
I'm not asking you to answer me.
I'm asking you to be honest before the Lord God.
It says that we may have confidence
and not be ashamed before him at his coming.
What if he came today, would you be ashamed?
What if he came last Tuesday at, name the time?
Would you have been ashamed?
You say, hold on, let me check my calendar.
You shouldn't have to check your calendar.
It shouldn't matter where you were or what you were doing.
Why, because you're living with this truth
that he shall appear.
And notice what the passage tells us.
If ye know that he is righteous,
ye know that everyone that doeth righteousness
is born of him.
Go into chapter three.
Behold what manner of love the Father hath bestowed upon us
that we should be called the sons of God.
Therefore the world knoweth us not
because it knew him not.
Beloved, now are we, sorry,
now are we the sons of God.
And it doth not yet appear what we shall be.
But we know when he, what's it say again?
Shall appear.
You see it repeated.
We shall be like him for we shall see him as he is.
I'm not gonna read verse three yet.
Listen, we know the truth
that we're dealing with this morning.
We consider the appearing of our Savior.
We know that it says repeatedly that he shall appear.
Notice it says that the world knoweth us not.
But the enemy continues to seek to attack us
and destroy us and devour us.
I'm thankful to report this morning
that the devil can never take your salvation.
We believe in the eternal security of the believer.
That as I was born of the Spirit
that I am washed in the blood,
that I am redeemed.
That positionally speaking,
I am righteous before Almighty God.
Not because of my righteousness,
because of the righteousness of God
that was imputed upon me and you.
By the way, if you're trying to stand
in your own righteousness,
it's just a bunch of filthy rags.
And I don't say that to be unkind.
I'm telling you what the Bible says in Isaiah 64.
The reality is that as we look at the truth
of the Word of God and we understand this truth
of the atonement and what it provided for us
not only in salvation, but in sanctification.
In walking a life that is pleasing.
Remember what Paul says in the book of Ephesians
in chapter number five.
Proving what is acceptable unto the Lord.
And we come to the third verse
of 1 John chapter number three
after he speaks about the return
and the truth of Christ's return
and how it should impact and influence us.
It says in every man,
that's every individual,
that hath this hope in him.
Pause.
I know the verse isn't done there.
There's not even a comma there.
I don't believe.
But I want you to pause.
Do you have that hope within you?
If you don't, you need to get it in you
because it's a Bible truth.
Amen?
You say, but I'm just hoping he doesn't come yet
because there's some things I wanna do.
Man, you don't understand that Christ is better.
You don't understand that he's superior.
You don't understand that there's nothing
the world can offer you that comes close.
If we have this hope,
it says every man that hath this hope in him
purifieth himself,
even as he is pure.
The songwriter wrote a song,
nothing between my soul and my savior.
How can we have that?
Because of what Christ did on the cross of Calvary.
Because of that atonement,
because of what he provides for us
even as we walk here upon this earth.
You say, but it's hard.
The devil's attacking.
I know he's real and he's active.
I understand it.
But can I tell you that greater is he that is in you
than he that is in the world.
We are more than conquerors through Christ.
We are on the winning side.
We do have victory.
And if we have this hope,
if we're influenced and impacted by the Bible truth,
then we purify ourselves,
even as he is pure.
We say, I don't want there to be anything
between my soul and my savior.
I asked you this morning,
would you be ashamed of his coming?
Have you purified yourself?
Are you able to say, as the songwriter wrote,
there's nothing between my soul and my savior?
I'm not asking you if you're perfect
because none of us are perfect.
But I'm asking you this,
are you living in sin?
Are you being attacked by the enemy?
Are you giving place to the devil?
Because he's real and he's active.
If there's known sin,
oh, thank God that you have an advocate with the Father.
You can have forgiveness and restoration
and the joy of your salvation
that the devil stole from you.
This morning, we look at Hebrews 9.
It could have been three separate messages,
but I tried to put it all together.
The atonement, the appointment, and the appearing.
Jesus Christ is coming again.
I know I've mentioned this before,
Holly was in a singing group in college.
They never let me join one of those tour groups.
We won't go there.
She was in a tour group.
There was a song that they sang that was impactful.
It wasn't the most beautiful song I ever heard
from a melody, whatever kind of perspective.
But the question throughout the song was this,
are you ready?
Are you ready, are you ready?
It would repeat it, repeat it, repeat it.
Are you ready for the coming of the Lord?
Because he could come today.
I don't want to be ashamed of his appearing.
Can I tell you this morning?
Look, you look, I'm not, I don't have my head in the sand.
You look at our world, you see what's going on.
God's people need revival.
We need revival.
We need to understand the seriousness of walking with Christ.
and understand what his atonement not only provides for me
in eternal security and eternal salvation,
but what it can enable me to do here even now
in walking in victory.
The death of the testator, he had to die,
and I'm so thankful that he did.
Again, our approach to the cross is much different
than these original recipients would have been.
And so we find that the writer is saying,
here's why, and here's what's accomplished.
Praise God for the cross.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the word of God,
the truth contained therein.
God, I pray this morning,
the Holy Spirit of God would work as only he can.
God, I've sought this morning to use your word
and to preach your word.
I've sought to give the sense of it,
to make the application,
to draw the line in the sand, so to speak,
as Moses did when he said,
who is on the Lord's side?
God, if there's one not sure of heaven,
would you help him today to be saved?
God, if there's one this morning,
that if they're honest before you,
they'd have to admit that there have been activities
that they've been engaged in in recent days,
weeks, months, years, however long it's been,
that if you would have appeared,
they would have been ashamed.
They've not purified themselves.
What I believe for each one of us,
because we'll never be perfect until we get to heaven,
there's a need to purify ourselves.
So we think about the truth of John 13.
The disciples' feet got dirty
because they were in the world.
We're in the world, but we're not of the world.
We're thankful for the cleansing power
of your word and the blood.
I pray that you'd have your will and way,
that decisions would be made,
that we truly would reflect on the truth of thy word
and say, can I honestly say, ask ourselves,
can I say there's nothing between my soul and my savior?
Not asking if I'm perfect.
Is there a known sin?
Have you given place to the devil?
Are you playing with fire?
Run to the cross.
Understand that Jesus is better.
There's nothing that old serpent,
that old liar, the devil, can offer you
that would even pale in comparison
to what Christ has provided.
Lord, would you have your way?
It's in Christ's name we pray, amen.
Would you stand with me?
Kimberly's gonna play quietly on the piano.
No one's looking around.
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Come to this old-fashioned altar.
Make your seat an altar.
Get along with God.
Let God have his way.
I beg you not to allow it to just be
another Sunday checkbox.
Went to church.
Let God have his way in your life as Kimberly plays.