So thankful for the opportunity to be gathered together, thankful for the privilege of having
the Word of God, and I trust that you are as well.
And by way of introduction, I'm going to read the first several verses of Luke chapter 2,
though we will focus this morning on verses 8 through 20 will be the focus of our message
this morning.
But by way of introduction, let me read these first seven verses to Luke chapter 2.
The Bible says this, and it came to pass in those days that there went out a decree from
Caesar Augustus that all the world should be taxed.
And this taxing was first made when Cyrenius was governor of Syria.
And all went to be taxed, every one into his own city.
And Joseph also went up from Galilee out of the city of Nazareth into Judea, out of the
city of David, which is called Bethlehem, because he was of the house and lineage of
David, to be taxed with Mary, his espoused wife, being great with child.
And so it was that while they were there, the days were accomplished that she should
be delivered.
And she brought forth her firstborn son and wrapped him in swaddling clothes and laid
him in a manger, because there was no room for them in the inn.
Again, we'll focus on verses 8 through 20 in this passage of Scripture this morning,
but we understand that this is a special time of year when we take some time out of our
schedules, of course, to reflect upon the birth of our Savior.
We understand that we live in a world in which they have commercialized holidays and they
have sought to through their just materialism and other means, they've sought to reach people
and impact people.
And really, through that process, you lose the true meaning of those holidays.
And we understand that to be the case here with Christmas.
And the reality is that we do not know the date of the birth of our Savior.
It is uncertain as to the exact date.
However, we can rejoice greatly in the knowledge that each prophecy with regard to the coming
of Messiah has been fulfilled exactly as it had been given.
I would say this morning that the reality of Christ's birth is a settled matter historically.
I'm sure we could find some that would debate that, but I think by and large, it is a settled
truth of history that Christ was born.
Unfortunately, there are far too many, even those that would acknowledge the birth of
the Lord and Savior, our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ, that they do not understand
why it is that Christ was born.
As we look at what the Scriptures teach us, obviously, within the passage here and other
portions of Scripture, we understand with great clarity as to the reason that Christ
was born.
Paul says it this way in the book of Galatians as he's writing to the believers in that region
in Galatians 4 and verses 4 and 5, but when the fullness of the time was come, God sent
forth His Son, made of a woman, made under the law, verse number 4.
Verse number 5 says, to redeem them that were under the law that we might receive the adoption
of sons.
I'm so thankful that not only do we have the reality, the truth with regard to the fact
that Christ was born, but through the pages of Scripture, we understand the reason that
Christ was born.
And we understand, listen, we are privileged, I use that terminology, we are blessed to
be able to have the truth with regard to not only has Jesus come, but why He has come.
Many in our world today, they do not understand the reason that Jesus Christ came to this
earth.
Why is it that He was born?
There are people today in your neighborhood, in my neighborhood, that will have Christmas
decorations, that perhaps will even have a little manger scene that they will put somewhere
in their home, yet they have no true understanding as to the significance of this holiday that
we seek to celebrate.
And that's a sad thing to me, that there's so many that are in darkness.
We understand that the enemy, the devil, seeks to keep people blinded, and no doubt the world
and the materialism and the commercialism has advanced the blindness of a great host
of people, not only in this country, but around the world.
As we look at the record that is given in Luke chapter number 2, verses 1 through 7,
of course we could look at other portions of Scripture this morning, but as we look
at the record of Christ's birth in those first seven verses, we ought to rejoice in understanding
that these prophecies that we could read of in the Old Testament were fulfilled just as
they had been given.
Not only do we rejoice in the record that has been provided to us, but as we continue
looking at verses 8 through 20 and really focusing this morning our attention upon these
shepherds, I hope that as we examine and really try to relate to the shepherds this morning,
that God would challenge us through some lessons that we can learn from these shepherds.
I want to draw your attention as we look at this passage of Scripture in verse number—let's
look here in verse number 10, I'll give you the title for the message and we'll dig right
in.
The Bible says this in verse number 10, the angel said unto them, fear not, for behold,
I bring you good tidings of great joy, which shall be to all people.
This morning if you're taking notes, I've simply entitled the message, Good Tidings
of Great Joy.
Good Tidings of Great Joy.
As we dig in and trace the steps of these shepherds, I want you to notice as we look
at these shepherds just for a few moments this morning, number one, I want you to notice
and consider with me that these shepherds were faithful.
They were faithful.
If we look at verses 8 and 9, let's look at just verse number 8, notice what the Bible
says here, and there were in the same country shepherds abiding in the field, notice what
it says, keeping watch over their flock by night.
As I first am introduced in the account that Luke gives us of the birth of our Savior,
we find that quickly the attention in these verses will turn to the shepherds and to the
announcement of the angel, and we will trace that through verse number 20, and as we begin
to notice these shepherds as we're introduced to these individuals, I would find them faithfully
fulfilling their responsibility.
They were faithful to do the work that they were supposed to be doing.
Now, I've never been in this particular regard a shepherd.
God calls pastors shepherds, obviously in a different context, but in this particular
context, as we think about these individuals and the responsibilities that they have, I'm
mindful as I think about this night that these individuals, when they left their dwelling
place, when they said goodbye to their children, perhaps, as they went out to the fields that
night, this was the same as it had been maybe hundreds or perhaps even thousands of times
before.
They were going out to watch over the flock, and sometimes as we begin to think about these
shepherds and we think about what they were doing, and it says that they were abiding
in the field, notice at the end of verse number 8, keeping watch over their flock by night.
Though we could say that this duty, as we look at them being faithful, what we would
say is that this was an essential work that they were doing.
This was absolutely imperative that someone would fulfill this job, this responsibility
of watching over the flock by night.
Why?
Because the flock is vulnerable, and these shepherds had an important job, and faithfulness
was necessary on their part to do their job.
And we find that they were faithful, of course, we understand the word of God speaks much
about faithfulness.
I'm thankful that God's word teaches us that our God is faithful.
He is dependable, he is trustworthy.
I find that Paul often will rejoice and thank God for the express purpose that God is faithful.
We sing, great is thy faithfulness.
We've experienced as individual believers this morning, we have experienced the faithfulness
of God.
But you know that he expects us as his people to be faithful as well.
The Bible says in 1 Corinthians 4 and verse number 2, moreover, it's required in Stuart's
that a man be found faithful.
I'm mindful of what the wise man said in Proverbs 20 and verse number 6, the latter
part of the verse, he says, but a faithful man, who can find?
And if you were to read through the book of Proverbs, and perhaps you would do a study
on a faithful man and on an unfaithful man, you would find the great truth that God gives
us in the importance of faithfulness.
When I look at these shepherds, when I'm first introduced to these shepherds in verse number
8, the first thing that I notice, the first thing that I'm met with is the fact that they
were faithful.
They were faithful.
I believe that though, as I mentioned a moment ago, they had probably hundreds or perhaps
thousands of times had this same kind of routine.
You go to work, you go through a routine when you leave the house, when you do whatever
you do, when the kids are saying bye and so on and so forth, and they had gone through
this process, if they had families, right?
And we understand that they've gone through this process, but little did they know that
on this day, on this night, their life was going to change.
I mean, this is an amazing experience.
See, things were going to be different this night.
These things that are going to unfold in these next few verses, they did not have the expectation
that this is what was going to happen this particular night.
that particular night.
But they were faithful.
And because they were faithful,
they were in the place where they were supposed to be
in order to have the experience
that they're going to have.
Amen?
I notice not only that these shepherds were faithful,
but I would say this as we continue
through the passage of Scripture,
I notice that these shepherds were attentive.
They were attentive.
Why do we say that?
Well, they listened to what the message was
and they followed it.
And so there was some attentiveness
to that which was being communicated to them.
Notice, they're there in the night.
They're watching over their flock by night.
And the Bible says in verse number nine,
and lo, the angel of the Lord came upon them
and the glory of the Lord shone round about them
and they were sore afraid.
Can you relate to these shepherds just for a moment?
I mean, they're out there.
They've done this many times.
They're watching over their flock by night.
And then in a moment,
the Bible tells us that this angel of the Lord comes
and the glory of the Lord shone round about them.
You'd be fearful as well.
I mean, in this moment, I mean,
I hope this morning that as we look through this passage
that we can begin to relate to these shepherds
and to understand what they experienced in this moment
and what they're dealing with.
And we find this scene that is explained to us here
in these verses of Scripture.
The Bible continues in verse number 10
and the angel says, fear not.
I'm thankful that this was the first of the greeting
to these shepherds, fear not.
Why? Because they were sore afraid.
The angel said unto them, fear not.
Notice, for behold, I bring you good tidings of great joy,
which shall be to all people.
In Luke 2, in verse number 10,
the announcement is given to these shepherds
that there was a message
that was going to be delivered to them.
Now, notice the way in which this message
is described for us in verse number 10.
The message is described, we use as our title this morning,
good tidings of great joy, good tidings of great joy.
Now, these shepherds, again, they're out there,
they're in the field,
they're watching over their flock by night.
This angel of the Lord appears and says, fear not,
and then says to these shepherds,
I'm bringing you good tidings of great joy.
Now, I think just that announcement
that perhaps they would be more attentive
because they understand that this message
that is going to be delivered to them
is a message of good tidings and great joy.
They're going to be attentive.
And you know, the attentiveness that we would have
as we understand what's happening here
and we understand the Word of God
as the Word of God week after week,
day after day in your personal life
as you read the Scriptures,
that we would be attentive to what thus saith the Lord.
That as we open the pages of Scripture
that we would take note
and that we would focus our attention,
that we would eliminate the distraction
so that I can be attentive to what God has for me
because God has a message for you.
The angel had a message.
See, God had summons this angel to go
and to deliver this message to the shepherds
and as these shepherds are experiencing this moment
and this scene, the angel says,
I'm bringing you good tidings of great joy.
Notice what it says at the end of the verse,
which shall be to all people.
Notice with me that in verse number 10,
it says, behold, I bring you good tidings of great joy
which shall be to all people.
These shepherds, because of their faithfulness,
as we mentioned in our first point,
because they were in the place
where they were supposed to be,
the angel comes and gives them this message.
They were privileged to receive this message.
But they understood right at the onset,
before the content of the message is even given to them,
as we'll find in verse number 11,
before the content of the message is given to them,
they are made keenly aware of the fact
that this message that I'm giving you
is a message of good tidings of great joy,
but it's for all people.
This message isn't just for you.
This message isn't just to be contained by yourself,
something that you keep to yourself.
No, this message of good tidings
or these good tidings of great joy,
this message that will be delivered to these shepherds,
it shall be to all people.
That's important for us to understand.
This morning as we think about the word gospel
and we'd understand the good news,
the gospel of Jesus Christ,
that this term good tidings
would be a synonymous term that would be used
with what we often refer to as the good news or the gospel.
And we find that, listen, as God's people,
because you have been given the truth of the gospel,
you understand this morning that it's for all people.
It's not for us to keep to ourselves.
Someone said this, a theologian of yesteryear,
that Christianity is not a closed-mouth religion.
Now, I don't like using the term religion
to describe Christianity.
I prefer to use the word relationship
because of some of the context
of what people will take with that term religion.
However, I agree with the theologian
that we are not to be closed-mouthed about the gospel.
We've been given responsibility.
And these shepherds, in like fashion,
as we have been entrusted with a message,
they are going to receive this message of great joy,
but they understand at the very beginning,
before the message is actually even given to them,
that it shall be to all people.
Note the message.
Verse 11, for unto you is born this day
in the city of David a Savior,
which is Christ the Lord.
Isn't that a wonderful truth of the Word of God?
We read verses one through seven by way of introduction
as we dealt with the record of the birth of Christ.
And we understand, even as we read verses one through seven,
the sovereignty and the providence of God
and how that God would, at the appointed time,
let this one raise up and cause these taxes
to be collected in these particular cities
so that Mary and Joseph were in the place
where they were supposed to be.
Why? Because the prophecies of the birth of Messiah,
that He would be born in Bethlehem.
And so we see that God is working
and the sovereignty of God is no doubt on display
in these first seven verses of Scripture.
And we come and we understand that these shepherds
are receiving this powerful message,
this life-changing message with regard
to the birth of Messiah.
Notice, the place of the birth is announced
in the city of David.
In the city of David.
You understand that Jesus is the Messiah,
that He is God, that He is the Savior of the world.
I'm thankful this morning that I could stand and say
that He is my Savior personally,
that I have personally placed my faith and trust
in the finished work of Christ at Calvary.
And I trust that you have as well.
And we could stand and say,
not only is He the Savior of the world, and He is,
but He's my Savior personally.
And we find that the Bible continues not only
to give the truth with regard to the city
in which Christ was born and this announcement,
this message is being given to these shepherds.
It says in verse number 12,
and this shall be a sign unto you.
Ye shall find the babe wrapped in swaddling clothes,
lying in a manger.
Now, if you go back and look at verse number seven with me,
we read it a moment ago.
The Bible says that she brought forth her firstborn son
and wrapped him in swaddling clothes
and laid him in a manger.
Notice this, because there was no room for them in the inn.
Why was there no room?
Well, there was a great influx of people in the city
for the purpose of paying these taxes.
And as they would come into the city,
as you notice, as we've read these verses already,
that they were to go into their city.
And they went to the city of David, which is Bethlehem.
And as they come, no doubt, great groups of people
would come for the purpose of fulfilling
that which was required.
And they come to this place,
there's no room for them in the inn.
And Mary gives birth and they're there.
She wraps our Savior in swaddling clothes
and lays him in a manger.
And the angel says to these shepherds
that this is the sign that will be unto you,
that ye shall find the babe wrapped in swaddling clothes,
lying in a manger.
Now, notice the message in verses 11 and 12
that is given the content of this message.
I'm thankful as we're speaking about these shepherds
that they were faithful, but they were attentive.
I mean, can you imagine the scene
as soon as the message is given in verses 11 and 12,
the Bible tells us in verses 13 and 14
that there was this multitude of heavenly hosts.
Notice it says, and suddenly there was with the angel
a multitude of the heavenly hosts praising God
and saying, glory to God in the highest,
and on earth peace, goodwill toward men.
And it came to pass, verse 15,
as the angels were gone away from them into heaven.
So just think about the scene for a moment.
They're out in the field being faithful,
doing what they have done perhaps thousands of times before
and an angel appears to them.
And in the moment they're fearful
and the angel says, fear not.
but I bring you good tidings of great joy,
which shall be to all people.
For unto you is born this day in the city of David a Savior,
which is Christ the Lord."
And then talks about the sign that they would receive,
that they would find the babe wrapped in swaddling clothes.
I mean, the excitement of the time.
But they were attentive to the message.
I'm thankful that they were attentive.
Why?
Because they couldn't say, can you repeat that to me?
Have you ever asked somebody something
and you've not really been giving your full attention?
You've not been attentive.
And someone's giving you directions.
And you kind of just wander a moment.
And they say, OK, have a nice day.
And you're like, can you repeat that?
I really wasn't paying attention.
Listen, as soon as the message that
is given to these shepherds is completed in verse number 12,
there's this multitude of this heavenly host
that's praising God.
And they're saying, glory to God in the highest.
On earth, peace, goodwill toward men.
And then they're gone, and the shepherds are left alone.
There's no repeat.
They had to be attentive.
And I'm thankful that they were attentive.
I'm thankful that these individuals, these messengers,
that on this night that they were faithful,
but I'm thankful that they were attentive to that which
had been delivered to them.
Again, as I begin to note here and think about the scene that
has unfolded before us, I think about the experience
of these shepherds and what a joyous experience it was,
no doubt.
And now, as I mentioned a moment ago,
they're left in verse number 15.
The Bible says, it came to pass as the angels were gone away
from them into heaven.
Now think about that.
I don't know how many shepherds it was.
It's plural, so it was more than one.
I don't know how many.
But can you imagine just for a moment being in this situation?
I mean, what has just happened is
so outside of the ordinary, something they'd never
experienced before.
They're there, and they didn't expect this to happen.
But because of being faithful, they're
in the place where they're supposed to be.
They receive this message.
They're attentive to the message.
And notice what they say.
Let us, look, it says this, the shepherds said one to another.
So there's a little conferring, if you will.
There's a little discussion that takes place.
They say one to another.
Notice, let us now go even unto Bethlehem
and see this thing which has come
to pass which the Lord hath made known unto us.
As we continue to trace the steps of the shepherds,
I find that they were faithful.
I find that they were attentive.
I find, number three, that they were obedient.
They were obedient.
They had been given this message,
and they had been given the truth
of that momentous occasion, what had happened
on this particular day, that the Son of God, the incarnation
that he was born.
Remember, as we look at the pages of scriptures,
we note it already in the book of Philippians,
but we note what Paul says in the book of,
I mentioned Galatians.
Notice in Philippians chapter number two,
as we consider the incarnation of our Savior,
the Bible tells us in Philippians chapter
number two, verses six through nine,
really down through verse number 11.
But notice in verse number six of Philippians chapter number
two, the Bible says, who being in the form of God,
thought it not robbery to be equal with God,
but made himself of no reputation,
and took upon him the form of a servant,
was made in the likeness of men, and being found in fashion
as a man, he humbled himself and became obedient unto death
even the death of the cross.
Wherefore, God also hath highly exalted him
and given him a name which is above every name.
The name of Jesus every knee should
bow of things in heaven, and things in earth,
and things under the earth.
And that every tongue should confess
that Jesus Christ is Lord to the glory of God the Father.
The incarnation that we speak of and we remember,
especially at this time of year, these shepherds
had just been given the announcement
that Messiah has come.
And now the angel's gone.
I'm thankful that they were obedient.
They said, let us go, let us now go, even unto Bethlehem,
and see this thing which has come to pass,
notice where it says, which the Lord hath made known unto us.
Notice the first phrase of verse number 16.
And they came with haste.
The obedience of these shepherds was,
an immediate obedience.
I think about the excitement again of the moment.
I think about all that they had experienced
and what they had just been informed of.
And the angel departs and they say one to another, let us go.
And they go with haste.
And we find that as they are obedient,
that their obedience resulted in a special opportunity.
Notice the Bible tells us in verse number 16
that they came with haste, notice,
and found Mary and Joseph and the babe lying in a manger.
They found it just as they had been told.
The angel said, in verse number 11,
for unto you is born this day in the city of David a Savior,
which is Christ the Lord.
The angel continued, this shall be a sign unto you,
you shall find the babe wrapped in swaddling clothes,
lying in a manger.
See, they were going to find Messiah, the Son of God,
perhaps there had been other babies that were born that day.
Perhaps there'd be other parents that were rejoicing
in the birth of their children on that day.
But this is God in flesh.
This is the incarnation.
And we find that he says, the angel says,
go to the city of David.
They say, we're going to Bethlehem.
Why? That's the city of David.
The angel said, you're going to find the babe wrapped
in swaddling clothes, lying in a manger.
And the Bible tells us in verse number 16
that they came with haste and they found Mary and Joseph
and the babe lying in a manger.
It says to us in verse number 17,
and when they had seen it,
they made known abroad the saying
which was told them concerning this child.
As I begin to think about their obedience,
I find that their obedience resulted in this special opportunity
that we find in verse number 16.
But I also, as I consider their obedience this morning,
I noticed that in verse number 17 that they were obedient
not only to go to the place where they were told that Messiah would be,
but they were obedient to proclaim the message
that they were supposed to proclaim.
See, because the message as it's contained for us in verse number 10,
the angel says, fear not, for behold, I bring you good tidings of great joy.
Remember, which shall be to all people.
Which shall be to all people.
And so now, as they have been entrusted with this message,
as they have received this message,
remember what they said at the end of verse number 15,
which the Lord hath made known unto us.
And so they had been entrusted with this message,
with this truth with regard to the birth of Messiah.
The Bible says that when they had seen it,
notice verse 17,
they made known abroad the saying
which was told them concerning this child.
What is it that they made known?
For unto you is born this day in the city of David a Savior,
which is Christ the Lord.
You know what they proclaimed?
The Messiah has been born.
Christ has been born.
That's the message that they proclaimed, no doubt.
Because it says here that they made abroad the saying
which was told them concerning this child.
Now you understand as we compare Scripture with Scripture,
begin to think about the names of Christ
and the significance of the birth of Christ.
You'll go back, hold your place there in Luke 2,
go back to Matthew 1 if you will,
as we understand the significance
these men would have been familiar with the Old Testament.
We think about the announcement of the peace
that had been given there in Luke 2
when they were singing and praising God on earth,
peace, goodwill toward men.
Remember Isaiah prophesied that his name shall be
the Prince of Peace was one of the names that was given.
But here in Matthew 1 in verse 18,
the Bible says now the birth of Jesus Christ
was on this wise.
When as his mother Mary was espoused to Joseph
before they came together,
she was found with child of the Holy Ghost.
Then Joseph, her husband being a just man
and not willing to make her a public example
was minded to put her away privily.
But while he thought on these things,
behold, the angel of the Lord appeared unto him in a dream
saying, Joseph, thou son of David,
fear not to take unto thee Mary thy wife
for that which is conceived in hers of the Holy Ghost
and she shall bring forth a son
and thou shall call his name Jesus.
Why?
For he shall save his people from their sins.
Verse 22, now all this was done that it might be fulfilled
which was spoken to the Lord by the prophet saying,
behold, a virgin shall be with child
and shall bring forth a son
and they shall call his name Emmanuel
which being interpreted is God with us.
Then Joseph being raised from sleep
did as the angel of the Lord had bidden him
and took unto him his wife
and knew her not till she had brought forth
her firstborn son and he called his name Jesus.
Here in Matthew one, we see the name Jesus,
we see the name Emmanuel
and we understand the significance
as this angel then appears in Luke chapter number two
to these shepherds and shares with them
that Christ is born, he is the savior,
he is the Lord that they go forth.
Listen, his name is Jesus.
Why?
For he shall save his people from their sins.
How is he gonna accomplish that?
through the cross, through the shed blood at Calvary,
his death, burial, and glorious resurrection.
That's how he's gonna accomplish the fact
that they would be saved from their sins.
His name shall be called Emmanuel
from Isaiah chapter number seven,
which is being interpreted God with us.
Why?
The incarnation, Jesus Christ is God in the flesh.
And we find the significance here of these names
that are mentioned in Matthew's gospel,
and we find these shepherds are now making abroad
the saying which was told them concerning this child.
The Bible says in verse number 18 of Luke chapter number two,
and all they that heard it wondered at those things
which were told them by the shepherds.
You know what I find in verse number 18
is proof or evidence of the fact
that they did talk to people
and give the truth that they had been given.
They delivered the message to people
that they had been entrusted with unto you.
It says there in verse number 10,
I bring you good tidings of great joy
which shall be to all people.
I'm not sure how many people they were able to find.
I'm not sure where they found the people.
I'm not sure of all that's going on,
but in my mind I see these shepherds
overwhelmed with excitement,
not only because of what they had experienced
out there in the field,
but now as they enter into the city
and they come to the manger
and they find the babe wrapped in swaddling clothes
just as the angel had said they needed to tell somebody.
They were willing to tell anybody.
Amen?
Why?
Because of what they'd experienced
and what they had seen.
And the Bible says in verse number 18,
and all they that heard it wondered at those things
which were told them by the shepherds.
There were a group of people that heard
the message that the shepherds proclaimed.
They greatly wondered,
the Bible tells us in verse number 19,
but Mary kept all these things
and pondered them in her heart.
I want you to think about the obedience of these shepherds.
And I want you to consider how their obedience
resulted in a special opportunity.
We started with their faithfulness
and how that because they were faithful,
they had the opportunity to receive that message
from the angel.
Can you imagine if one of them decided
they weren't gonna be there that night?
Man, that was the wrong night to call out.
You understand what I'm saying?
It was the wrong night to miss church.
It was the wrong day.
Listen, Thomas found out
it was the wrong night to miss church.
Why?
Because Jesus showed up, right?
Read it in John.
You find here these shepherds,
listen, I think they were happy that they were there.
They were faithful.
They were attentive.
They heard the message
and they were able to go in obedience
and go to exactly the place where they were supposed to go
because they had been attentive to the message.
Can you imagine?
What did they say again?
Where did they say we're supposed to go?
What are we supposed to find?
No, no, they were attentive.
Their obedience resulted in this special opportunity.
I ask you this question this morning,
what if they had disobeyed?
Or perhaps I ask it this way,
what if they simply delayed?
What if they said, you know what,
there's no urgency in obeying.
We can get around to it at some point.
We don't have to go right now.
I would submit to you that as you compare scripture
with scripture, go back to Matthew, if you will.
I believe, and if you disagree, we can talk later,
but I believe that if these shepherds
had just simply delayed their obedience,
that they would not have found Jesus
in that manger wrapped in swaddling clothes
because the Bible record tells us in Matthew
in chapter number two, we're introduced to the wise men.
The wise men come from far.
The Bible says that when they come into Jerusalem,
they say here, as we look at what's going on,
they say to Herod in verse number two,
where is he that is born king of the Jews?
For we have seen a star in the east
and are come to worship him.
Herod the king had heard,
when Herod the king had heard these things,
he was troubled and all Jerusalem with him.
Notice verse four of Matthew two.
And when he had gathered all the chief priests
and scribes of the people together,
he demanded of them where Christ should be born.
And they said unto him in Bethlehem of Judea,
for thus it is written by the prophet.
We understand that you go back to Micah
and you can read of that.
You understand the fulfillment of prophecy.
That's why I said in Luke chapter number two,
in those first seven verses,
you see the providence and sovereignty of God.
How did they end up in Bethlehem?
They weren't, that's not where they lived,
but they were there because of the taxing
and they had to go there.
And that's where he was born.
Notice in verse number six,
and thou Bethlehem, this is the record of Micah five
in verse number two in the land of Judah,
art not the least among the princes of Judah
for out of these shall come a governor
that shall rule my people Israel.
Then Herod, when he had privily called the wise men
and inquired of them diligently,
what time the star appeared.
And he sent them to Bethlehem and said,
go and search diligently for the young child.
And when you have found him,
bring me word again that I may come and worship him also.
The Bible tells us in verse number nine,
when they had heard the king, they departed.
These wise men depart.
The Bible says in lo the star,
which they saw in the East went before them
till it came and stood over where the young child was.
Where was he?
Verse number 10, it says, when they saw the star,
they rejoiced with exceeding great joy.
And when they were come into, what does it say?
Does it say the house in your Bible?
It doesn't say the manger, does it?
Came into the house.
I believe this morning that if these shepherds
would have delayed their obedience,
they would not have found Jesus in the manger.
Jesus didn't stay in the manger long.
Why was he in the manger?
There was no room in the inn.
Why was there no room in the inn?
Because there are a lot of people in town
to pay their taxes.
By the way, if you came into town to pay taxes
and had to pay to stay in an inn,
you'd leave pretty quick.
Amen, you get your business transaction done
and you get back to your hometown.
Does that make sense?
I mean, it makes sense in my mind.
And so guess what happens?
There's room in the inn.
There's a place to stay.
They probably wouldn't have immediately,
and if you've given birth, you could relate.
You're probably not ready to take a journey
back to your hometown of Nazareth
by way of either walking or a camel or donkey.
Amen, I've never given birth,
but my wife has given birth three times.
I'm pretty confident that she would not
have been delighted if I said,
let's get on the camel and head back to town.
This is not gonna work.
I mean, I'm trying to just help us this morning
because what I'm trying to help us understand
is the importance of obedience, immediate obedience.
Had they delayed, see, their immediate obedience
resulted in an opportunity that was unlike
any other thing they'd ever experienced.
They get to the manger
because they immediately obeyed
what the angel of the Lord said.
They get to the manger and they find Mary
and they find the babe wrapped in swaddling clothes.
We mentioned that they come to the house,
these wise men in verse number 11
of Matthew chapter number two.
Again, I don't believe that these shepherds
of chapter number two of the book of Luke
that they would have found Mary and Joseph
and the babe, Jesus Christ, our Savior, the Messiah,
the Savior of the world,
they would not have found Him lying in a manger.
And then what happens?
Can you imagine?
Just for a moment.
I mean, let's use our sanctified imaginations
just for a moment.
Now these shepherds, they delay their obedience.
They don't go to the city of Bethlehem.
They don't do what the angel had said.
They don't go and find what had been announced to them
and they delay their obedience
and perhaps they show up to this place, this manger,
but they do not find Mary.
They do not find Joseph
and they do not find the babe wrapped in swaddling clothes.
What do they do?
Where do they go?
Who do they tell?
Do you understand what I'm saying?
Because now all of a sudden they're looking at each other
and saying one to another, now what?
How do we find them?
Because the sign that was given to them,
according to what verse number 11 says,
excuse me, verse number 12,
is that you shall find the babe wrapped in swaddling clothes
lying in a manger.
That sign that the angel gave in verse number 12,
that was significant because it showed,
it demonstrated, it proved that this is the one
that I'm speaking of that is the Messiah,
that is the Savior, that is Christ the Lord.
Again, perhaps there were other babies
that were born that day.
And once Mary and Joseph and Jesus leave the manger,
how do you find them?
How do you find them?
I understand the context.
None of us are going to a manger to find Jesus.
I understand that.
But I wonder in our lives,
how important is obedience to us?
I mean, immediate obedience.
I joked the other day with someone,
I do not have Alexa, I do not want Alexa.
I do not have whatever their other names are,
I don't want them, Echo, this, that, blah, blah, blah.
I think they're spying on you, man.
If you don't agree, that's fine, we can talk later.
But if she's listening all the time,
it doesn't matter what I'm,
anyway, that's another story for another time.
But what I'm saying is I said to somebody,
I was at someone's house, they have Alexa.
You know what's kind of funny about that thing?
You say, Alexa, do this, and she does.
Alexa, do that, and she does.
And I said to the person, I asked him to do something,
it was my dad, I was messing with him.
And we were celebrating Christmas with him on Friday
because they're up in Rhode Island, New Hampshire,
and they left yesterday,
so we celebrated Christmas with him on Friday.
And I told him something, I said, you should do this,
and he just kind of, I said, Alexa listens better than you.
And I was just kind of joking with him.
But in that statement, there's a little bit of a truth
for us as Bible-believing Christians
that we ought to obey immediately to the voice of God.
Amen?
I mean, I see these shepherds, they were faithful.
As God's people.
we're to be faithful. They were attentive. Can I tell you as God's people we better
be attentive to the Word of God. We better zero in and focus in. Let's
eliminate distractions. Let's understand what God's telling us. Why?
Because then and only then are we going to be able to obey the way that we're
supposed to. There are times no doubt that we leave our time of Bible reading,
perhaps we leave our time of being in church and we can't tell you in a
half an hour what it was that we heard or read. Because we weren't attentive. So
if we can't even rehearse what it is that we heard or that we read, how is it
that we would even remotely think that we'd obey it? Is that logical? If I can't
remember what I heard or what I read this morning, there's little
chance that I'm obeying it. Right? And so the importance of attentiveness. These
shepherds, they were attentive. We understand that the Bible talks about
there in the Old Testament when you read the the account of the the remnant
returning and you read about the preaching of Ezra and all those things
how that the people were attentive. Man, they wanted to hear the Word of God. They
wanted to get the truth of God's Word and they wanted to to listen as we
understand that we're to be hearers of the Word. Why? So that we can be doers of
the Word. Right? We're not to be hearers only, deceiving our own selves. We're to
be doers of the Word. And you know when the best time is to implement the truth
that you receive is immediately. As soon as you're confronted with truth. When you
read your Bible this morning, if God used his Word in your life this morning to
confront you, to challenge you in some area of your life, the best time is to
immediately obey. Not, well, let me think about that. Let me see. Whatever. And then
we begin to justify and reason and, you know, before long we just forget all
about it. And these shepherds, because of their obedience, it resulted in
this special opportunity to find, it says in verse number 16, and found Mary and
Joseph and the babe lying in a manger. And when they had seen it, verse 17, can
you imagine the excitement? I mean, honestly. They made known abroad the
saying which was told them concerning this child. This morning, we look at the
shepherds and we consider these things and we notice these aspects as we follow
their, the verses of Scripture and follow their night, this experience that they
had. And I think we can relate to them. I think we can learn from them. I think we
can be challenged by them. And I just wonder this morning, how obedient are we
to follow the Lord and to proclaim the message? See, because not only did they
follow and go, but then they made known abroad the saying which was told them
concerning this child. I remember, and perhaps you can recall this as well, we
can think about some Bible characters, no doubt, that we could speak of this morning,
that when they first encountered the Lord, their excitement to share with
someone. I mentioned a moment ago about the shepherds, that they're willing to
tell anyone. I mean, just anyone. They're just willing to, if you don't want to
listen, I'm gonna find somebody else. Kind of an idea. You know what I'm saying? I
think about the record in the book of John. You don't have to turn there, but
in John chapter number one, the Bible records for us how that John the
Baptist, as he was looking upon Jesus in verse number 36, as Jesus was walking
there, he said, behold the Lamb of God. And you understand that the disciples, there
were two of them there, that they followed Jesus. Jesus says, what seek ye?
And they say, they said unto him, Rabbi, which is to say, being interpreted, Master,
where dwellest thou? He said, come and see. We find that as they go there, the Bible
tells us of some amazing things that unfold. And the Bible tells us one of the
two which heard John speak, followed him, was Andrew. You know what he did? He went
and found his brother, Simon Peter, immediately. And what did he do? He
brought him to Jesus. In verse number 42, Jesus speaks to Peter. And then the day
following, he would go to Galilee and he findeth Philip. And he says to Philip,
follow me. Philip was of Bethsaida, the city of Andrew and Peter. What does it
say in verse 45? Philip findeth Nathanael. We could look at other accounts and
records, but what I'm saying this morning is that just as these shepherds had a
desire, an overwhelming longing and yearning to tell somebody, to make known
abroad the saying which was told them concerning this child, I wonder as God's
people in 2020 how we are in this area. Are we just looking for anybody
that would listen to us tell them about Jesus? I've changed my approach prior to
2020, but for a long time what had been taught kind of in personal
evangelism, I was in college, and how I'd been taught even with people that I
would go out on visitation with and so on and so forth, was this kind of
approach of inviting people to church. And I understand that I'm not suggesting
that we shouldn't invite people to church, but a while back I changed my
approach, probably two years ago now, and instead of inviting people to church, I
asked them if I can share with them what Jesus did for me. Can I just tell
you what Jesus did for me? Can I tell you how he changed my life? Can I tell you
how he gave me joy and peace and direction? And Joseph was with me as my
door-knocking partner the very first time on that very first Saturday that I
changed my approach, and I would say this in about 15 or 20 doors that we knocked
that morning, I had more opportunity to share the gospel with people than in
months added together. Why? Because when you say, can I invite you to church,
people are gonna have an idea about church. Maybe they had a bad experience,
maybe they have a church, maybe they're bored in church, whatever it might be, it
doesn't matter. But when I say to them, can I tell you what Jesus did for me? Can I
tell you how he changed my life? All of a sudden there's gonna be some, what did he
do for you? How did he change your life? And what I'm saying to you this
morning is that we ought to have some excitement about telling people about
what Jesus did for us, who he is, and what he has done. And we ought to be
willing to just, listen, we're gonna have people that say, no, I'm not interested.
That's okay. Don't get discouraged. Just find somebody that will listen. Anybody
that will listen. Amen? And what a joy. Notice as we conclude the passage, I
notice finally from verse number 20 that these shepherds were changed. They were
changed. I think about the excitement of these shepherds as they returned. The
Bible says in verse number 20, and the shepherds returned, glorifying and
praising God for all the things that they had heard and seen as it was told
unto them. I would argue this morning that this event, this passage of Scripture,
these few verses of Scripture in verses 8 through 20, I would argue this morning
that this was a life-changing experience for these shepherds. I would argue this
morning that these shepherds, that they would at every opportunity share this
experience. I can, in my mind's just eye, in my imagination, I see these shepherds
returning home. You ever go home and your wife or your children say, how was work?
It was fine. It was okay. Right? Sometimes you say, how was work? And you say, what's
for dinner? It's just better not talk about it. You know what I mean? How was work?
Let me tell you what happened. Maybe before they were even asked, how was it
tonight? Let me tell you what happened. I mean, as they're entering into the door,
they barely can contain themselves to be able to share with their families what
God had shown them and what they had experienced. I think it changed them. I
know Christ changed me. And I understand that my experience and your experience
is different than this experience. But I'm trying to look at these shepherds
and try to be helped this morning. And the Bible says if any man be in Christ,
he's a new creature. There's a transformation that takes place. And we
think about the power of the gospel to change lives, and I think about these
shepherds. I'm not sure, as we look at these individuals, we don't know
their names. We don't know their family situations. We don't know anything
about them other than the fact that they were faithful. They were where they were
supposed to be. They were attentive. They listened to the message of the angel.
They were obedient. They said, what are we gonna do? Let's go. And they went with
the taste. And they were changed. And this morning, as I think about their joy and
their excitement, as I see it in verse number 20, I would say this. I hope it
never faded away. But I would say this morning, as we would be honest one with
another, that there are times in our lives when the joy seems to slip away. It
seems to fade, if you will. Maybe we don't have the same joy and excitement to
share Christ with others as we one day did. Maybe it's just kind of gotten just
normal, just regular, just I'm a Christian, I'm saved, I'm going to heaven. And maybe
we've lost the joy of it all. Do you understand what I'm saying? It's possible in
life, by the way. It's possible when some think, listen, we see it in life when
people buy a new car. They're excited about that new car. They wash it, they
detail it, they whatever.
And it gets a little ding, they're all tight, right, you understand?
And then all of a sudden it's just a car that maybe you're still making payments on.
And that's even worse, you understand what I'm saying?
But what I'm saying is that don't let it be the case with Jesus that it just kind of gets,
it's just, yeah, He's my Savior, no, He changed my life.
I hope this morning that if we were to go out this afternoon and if somebody were to
give us the opportunity to share with them Christ, that they would see in us the level
of joy and excitement that would be at the same level as it was the first day we met
Him.
Why?
Because we understand every day afresh what He's done for us and how He's changed our
lives.
And that we would not get into the monotony of life and just lose the freshness and the
excitement of it.
Let it not fade away, but help us each day of our lives to be mindful of what Christ
did for us and who He is to us.
The last couple of Wednesday evenings I've been teaching a lesson, Jesus is all the world
to me.
We sing the song, in our songbook it's number 100.
Peter said, to them that believe He is precious, and He is precious.
The songwriter said, He's a wonderful Savior to me, and He is.
And as we've taught those lessons over the last couple of weeks and given a sampling
of answers as to why Jesus is all the world to you, if someone came to you and said, you
sang that song, you said that Jesus is all the world, why is He all the world to you?
I hope that we'd be able to communicate it with joy and excitement, and that they would
see the passion and the genuine aspect of what He did for me.
This, listen, this is not religion.
Religion's dead.
It's dead orthodoxy, honestly.
But I'm talking about a relationship with the God of heaven.
These shepherds, their lives were changed.
And on the day that you met the Lord Jesus Christ, the day in which you got saved, your
life was changed.
My life was changed.
As I look at these shepherds, oh, I'm thankful for the good tidings of great joy.
I'm thankful for the record of Christ's birth, that it's settled historically.
He was born, but He was born to die.
There are many today that would acknowledge, that would recognize the coming of Christ,
that He was born.
But they do not know why.
They have no concept as to why Christ was born.
And we have been given the truth of the Word of God, not only with regard to the record
of His coming, but with regard to the purpose of His coming.
And as I examine the lives of these shepherds, I pray that God would help me to be faithful.
I pray that God would help me to be attentive.
I pray that God would help me to be obedient.
And I know that I'm changed.
And I hope this morning, my prayer for you this morning is in like manner, that God would
challenge us through the reading of this, tracing the steps of these shepherds just
for a little while in Luke 2, verses 8 through 20.
Let's pray together.
Father, thank You so much for the record of Your Word.
And thank You for the privilege of being able to gather together to sing, to worship,
to open Your Word.
God, I pray that the Holy Spirit of God has taken the Word of God this morning and ministered
to each individual as only He can.
God that somehow in our lives, we could take a few moments and relate to these shepherds.
God help us to have the excitement as we go into a lost and dying world and proclaim the
truth of Thy Word.
These good tidings of great joy which were given to these shepherds, it was intended
to go to all people.
We think about the gospel and we make the link and application for us this morning.
We've been told to go into all the world and preach the gospel to every creature.
I pray that the evidence of a changed, transformed life would have a powerful impact upon those
that we would share this truth with.
Would You have Your will and way in these next few moments?
We'll thank You for it.
In Christ's name we pray.
Father, would You stand with me?
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano as she does.
The altar's open.
You're free to make Your pew and altar.
You're free to come up here to this old-fashioned altar.
But would You let God have His way in your life?
As we relate to the shepherds this morning, I pray that God would use His Word to change
us as Kimberly plays.