the message but it was on my heart and I hope that this morning all that thrills
your soul is Jesus. Aren't you thankful for the Lord Jesus Christ? Amen. Praise
the Lord. Where'd we be without Him? Hopeless, helpless, right? Praise the Lord.
Jesus is the sweetest name I know. It truly is. You know when I hear the name Jesus it means
something. It means something. It brings to my mind who Jesus is. Not according to what the
world might say but according to what God's Word says, what He revealed to us. And I'm so thankful
to know the Lord Jesus Christ personally. Last week in 2 Corinthians chapter 5 we dealt with
verse number 17 and this week we're going to deal with verses 18 through 20. I've titled the
message We Are His Ambassadors. In Acts chapter 5 and verse 32, you don't need to turn there,
but the disciples declared we are His witnesses. What a great declaration for the disciples as
they're dealing with all sorts of persecution and resistance and they'd been facing various
levels of persecution up to that point and they're given threats from the religious leaders that are
to no longer speak in the name of Jesus. They're not to preach anymore in the name of Jesus and
they make this declaration. There are several declarations that they make but one of them is
we are His witnesses. We find that John would later say in 1 John chapter number 1 how that
he was an eyewitness and that he's given us this account and really this morning we can rejoice in
understanding that we are His witnesses. The apostle Paul as he's writing to the church in
Corinth here in the book of 2 Corinthians, we find that he's going to provide greater instruction in
the passage of scripture that we're going to study this morning with regard to the ministry that he
spoke of in 2 Corinthians chapter 4 and verse number 1. If you note there in your Bible that
the apostle Paul says, therefore seeing we have this ministry as we have received mercy we faint
not and we find that in these few verses of scripture in 2 Corinthians 5 verses 18 through 20
Paul under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God is going to provide greater instruction and
information to us with regard to the ministry that he spoke of in 2 Corinthians chapter 4
in verse number 1. We find that in this text of scripture as I mentioned in Acts 5 in verse 32
that the disciples say we are his witnesses but we find here in 2 Corinthians chapter 5 that we see
a distinguished title given to those who are entrusted with this ministry that the apostle
Paul spoke of in 2 Corinthians 4 verse number 1. We have this ministry and that distinguished
title that he gives to us is that of ambassador. Ambassador. What a title. What a description.
I believe that every word of God is pure. I believe that God chose his words with purpose and
I believe that as we look at this passage of scripture and see this word ambassador it is
communicating something extremely important to us this morning. I find that in the New Testament
that the word ambassador is only used twice in all of the New Testament. We find that the apostle
Paul as he's writing to the church in Ephesus in Ephesians chapter 6 in verse number 20
he refers to himself as being an ambassador in bonds and we understand the apostle Paul
as he would even say later to Timothy though he was bound the word of God is not bound and what
a blessing and the apostle Paul that while he was in prison he still recognized this distinguished
title that he was an ambassador though he had been in prison though he did not have the same
level of liberties that he once had he recognized that he was still an ambassador and as you study
through the New Testament you study the the truth of God's word you'll find that the apostle Paul
even while he was bound even while he faced times of imprisonment that he was actively sharing the
gospel because he recognized that he was an ambassador for Christ and we find that there
were people that got saved there were people that trusted Christ as their personal Lord and Savior
why because he was faithful to do the work that God had entrusted to him to fulfill we find that
as he's writing to the church in Philippi it's very interesting the church in Philippi how did
the church start what was the circumstances regarding the apostle Paul in Philippi well we
know that shortly after the the healing and what took place with that demonic possessed girl
that we find that he's imprisoned Paul and Silas they're imprisoned in Philippi
they're singing and praising God but Paul you're in prison but God is good God has a plan
my life is his I'm in his hand he's singing praises and at midnight the Bible says
that God sent an earthquake and that jailer who is ready to kill himself supposing that all the
prisoners had escaped he he finds out Paul says we're all here do yourself no harm and he says
sirs what must I do to be saved Paul later writing to the church at Philippi he would say to that
church that he did not want them to have this misunderstanding he didn't want them to have
be ignorant concerning the things that befell him he tells them this in the first chapter he
wanted them to understand that it happened for the furtherance of the gospel we find that as
you come to the end of chapter four of the book of Philippians that Paul begins to write the names
and those that were saved that were of the household of Caesar how they get saved
God who knows all things who do with all things well he allowed for the apostle Paul to be
imprisoned and he allowed for the apostle Paul to be in that place and to have those prison guards
and those of the household and and Paul got the opportunity to share the gospel with him he didn't
just have a pity party he didn't just say woe is me I mean it's not fair I was just preaching I was
just doing what God called me to do and I I'm gonna give up no he just kept doing what God
called him to do and God blessed and here as we look at the apostle Paul making that statement
in Ephesians 6 that he was an ambassador in bonds we find that that's one use of the word but we
find that here in our text that he says to the believers in Corinth and by way of application
to us as well this morning that we are ambassadors for Christ note the passage with me beginning in
verse 18 the bible says this and all things are of God who hath reconciled us to himself by Jesus
Christ and hath given to us the ministry of reconciliation to wit that God was in Christ
reconciling the world unto himself not imputing their trespasses unto them and hath committed
unto us the word of reconciliation now then we are ambassadors for Christ as though God did
beseech you by us we pray you in God Christ dead be ye reconciled to God this morning as we think
about this truth that we are his ambassadors I want you to consider first with me this morning
the privilege of being an ambassador it's a great privilege to be an ambassador sometimes I believe
and I've been guilty of this in my own life in my own ministry sometimes we might focus more on the
responsibility side of things versus the privilege side of things the reality this morning we
understand it is absolutely true that that we do have a responsibility but I hope this morning that
as we think about this this truth this this this this title that is given to us as being an
ambassador that we recognize the privilege to be appointed by the king of kings and lord of lords
to be his representative to be his ambassador what a joy we say this this world is not my home I'm
just a passing through my treasures are laid up somewhere beyond the blues what the songwriter
said we sing it the bible tells us in the book of hebrews in the 11th chapter that we're strangers
and pilgrims the reality is that sometimes if we're not careful brother mark we dealt you dealt
with this a little bit in sunday school this morning if we're not careful sometimes this
world can almost be more like our home we treat it that way but this world is not my home I'm an
ambassador what is an ambassador it's representative it's a privilege in an appointed position
we find that that the lord jesus christ he showed to us he gave us in this passage this
this understanding of the privilege it's necessary that we acknowledge this morning
the great privilege that is ours the honor that is ours to be an ambassador for the lord jesus
christ the one who is the king of kings the lord of lords the one who knows all things
and he says to us that we are his ambassadors it's amazing paul would say as he's writing to
the church in ephesus that our citizenship is in heaven our citizenship is in heaven it's
interesting of an ambassador an ambassador is one who represents a foreign country you think about
a u.s ambassador that's going to another country it is said uh that while george schultz was
during the Reagan administration,
that he would meet with every newly appointed ambassador
before he or she left for the new posting.
As he would meet with them in his office,
he kept this globe there in his office,
and he would say, as he would bring in the individual,
he'd bring up that globe, and he would say this,
show me where your country is.
That's what he would say.
And it says this, this was the account,
that almost in every case,
the new ambassador would spin the globe,
they would find the country in which they were appointed to
or assigned to, and they would point to it.
And Mr. Schultz would correct them.
And he would point to America, and he would say this,
this is your country.
Why?
Because they had to understand they were representing the U.S.
in whatever country they were going to.
That was their purpose.
Can I tell you this morning,
we can't take a globe and point to heaven,
but can I tell you if you're saved this morning,
if you're a child of God, your citizenship is in heaven.
This world is not my home.
Amen?
Listen, we're here for a purpose,
and we're ambassadors.
We're to represent the Lord Jesus Christ.
It is a privilege that we have to be his ambassadors.
In John chapter 20, turn there very quickly, if you will,
I want you to notice what Jesus says in John chapter 20.
We understand that we could go to each of the Gospels,
Matthew, Mark, Luke, John.
We could go to the book of Acts,
and we could deal with the Great Commission this morning.
But I want you to see the way in which Jesus says it
in John chapter 20.
In John chapter 20, we find that the resurrection
has already taken place, and Jesus is appearing.
It's the evening of the same day,
according to verse number 19.
He appears, and he says,
Peace be unto you at the end of the verse.
But I want you to notice that as he's there,
in verse 20, it says,
When he had so said,
he showed unto them his hands and his side.
Then were the disciples glad when they saw the Lord.
Then said Jesus to them again,
Peace be unto you.
And then notice what Jesus says,
As my Father hath sent me,
even so send I you.
I'm thankful that Jesus left the throne room of heaven
to come to this sin-cursed world,
to die in my place and in your place,
to go to that old cross,
to be buried in a borrowed tomb,
to rise, conquering sin, death, and the grave.
But I understand this morning that the resurrected Christ,
that he now has ascended to heaven,
he's on the right hand of the throne of God,
and we find that what he's commissioned,
he said, as I've been sent,
now I'm sending you.
We're his ambassadors.
It's a privilege.
The apostle Paul says it this way
as he's talking to the church in Thessalonica.
Notice, if you will, in 1 Thessalonians chapter 2.
In 1 Thessalonians chapter 2,
the Bible tells us that, of course,
Paul had had the opportunity
during the second missionary journey.
You read Acts 17.
You can see of the time in which he went to Thessalonica.
But as he says this to this church,
this group of believers,
notice the perspective of the apostle Paul
in 1 Thessalonians 2 and verse number 4.
He says, but as we were allowed of God
to be put in trust with the gospel,
even so we speak,
not as pleasing men, but God,
which trieth our hearts.
He says that we were allowed of God
to be in trust with the gospel.
You think about the gospel,
the death, burial, and glorious resurrection
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ,
for it is the power of God unto salvation
to everyone that believeth,
to the Jew first and also to the Greek.
We read that in Romans chapter 1.
And we find that the apostle Paul,
as he's communicating to this church in Thessalonica,
he says, I want you to gain this perspective
that we have been allowed of God
to be entrusted, to be put in trust
with the gospel.
This morning, do you recognize
the privilege that is ours
to be an ambassador of the Lord Jesus Christ?
It's absolutely amazing.
I believe this morning that it is appropriate
and it's necessary at times that we focus
and we deal with the responsibility that we have.
It's important we have missions conferences,
we have missionaries that come in
throughout the calendar year to stir us up
and to speak to us about the responsibility
to the desires to reach the world
with the gospel.
And what a task that God has given to us.
Yes, we've been commanded.
Yes, we have a responsibility.
But I want you to look at it
from a perspective of privilege.
Not just duty.
But privilege.
There's a privilege.
To be able to sit down with someone
and tell them about the one
who loves them more than anyone else.
The one, the only one,
that can save them and change their lives.
What a privilege that has been given to us.
And we find that we recognize
that it's been given to us
for we find in our text in 2 Corinthians 5
that the Bible says in verse 18,
we spoke already in the past two weeks
about verses 14 and 15
and that he died for all in verse 15
that they which live should not henceforth
live unto themselves but unto him
which died for them and rose again.
We dealt with verse 17 last week.
Therefore, if any man be in Christ,
they're saved, they're born again.
The Bible says that he's a new creature.
Old things are passed away.
Behold, all things are become new.
But then we find in verse 18,
the Bible says that all things are of God
who hath reconciled us
to himself by Jesus Christ
and then notice,
and hath given to us
the ministry of reconciliation.
He did not give this ministry of reconciliation
to anyone other than those
who have been reconciled.
See, you have to be reconciled
before you can be engaged in the work
and the ministry of reconciliation.
The angels desire to look into it
but they cannot be engaged
in the ministry of reconciliation
because they can't, they're not reconciled.
They don't need to.
But this morning, we think of this passage
and the privilege that is ours.
I'm so thankful to know the Lord Jesus Christ
as my personal savior.
The privilege of knowing him and serving him
and knowing that he's given me.
You know, it's amazing to begin to think
about who we are in Christ.
Who he is to us and who we are in him.
We find that as many as receive him,
to them gave he power to become
the sons of God,
even to them that believe on his name.
We find in 1 John 3,
John stands up and says,
behold what manner of love the father
hath bestowed upon us
that we should be called the sons of God.
Hallelujah.
And he says we're his ambassadors.
What a privilege.
What a privilege this morning.
We have gospel tracks out there.
We have opportunities for outreach
and ministry and try to reach people.
Why?
It's a privilege.
Yes, it's a responsibility,
but it's a privilege.
It's a privilege to go
as a representative, as an ambassador.
I want you to understand not only the privilege,
but number two, the purpose.
There's a purpose in being an ambassador
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
We understand the ambassadors
that are sent from our nation to other nations
and we can see that physically
and understand that application
and see how they behave
and what they're to do
and what their purpose is.
And they don't always fulfill it properly
and appropriately and what have you,
but the reality is they have a purpose.
This morning, when we look at the text of Scripture,
we understand that we too have a purpose.
As he's given to us this distinguished title
that we are his ambassadors,
we have a purpose.
Notice with me in verse 18,
the Bible says at the end of the verse,
and hath given to us
the ministry of reconciliation.
Verse 19,
to wit that God was in Christ
reconciling the world unto himself,
not imputing their trespasses unto them.
And then notice this phrase
at the end of verse number 19,
and hath committed unto us
the word of reconciliation.
Now then, verse 20,
we are ambassadors for Christ.
As though God did beseech you by us,
we pray you in Christ's stead,
be ye reconciled to God.
Do you see the number of uses of the word reconcile
or some form of the word reconcile
in these verses of Scripture
that we've read this morning?
We see that the ministry,
the purpose of being an ambassador
is that he's given to us
this work of reconciliation.
Now here's the amazing thing.
I can't personally reconcile anybody.
But as an ambassador,
I've been given the ministry of reconciliation.
Notice with me,
specifically in verse number 20,
he says now then we are ambassadors for Christ
as though God did beseech you by us.
And so listen,
the Bible tells us that God is not willing
that any should perish,
but that all should come to repentance.
Amen, is that what your Bible says?
2 Peter 3.
We could turn over there if we need to.
We understand that's what he says.
In fact, as he's writing to Timothy,
he says that he would have all men to be saved
and come unto the kingdom of God.
the knowledge of truth.
That's God's plan.
Now we understand that not all mankind will be saved
because we understand they will not be reconciled.
There are many that reject him.
He came to his own, his own received him not.
Is that not what the Bible tells us?
We find that there is a great white throne judgment
in Revelation chapter 20,
and there will be subjects that will stand
at that great white throne judgment.
Who are those people?
Those that were not reconciled to God.
Those that were never born again.
But we understand this morning that God's heart
and God's desire for God so loved the world.
He loved the world.
He is the propitiation for our sins,
but not for our sins only,
but also for the sins of the whole world.
First John chapter two.
And we find that it says as though God did beseech you
by us, and then notice this, we pray you.
It's an interesting word.
Sometimes we look at the New Testament
and there's obviously a number of Greek words
and the English language is somewhat limited,
but that word pray literally carries with it
the idea of to beseech, to beg.
In fact, the same Greek word that we see that's used
for pray in this verse, in verse number 20,
it's translated 12 times in our English Bible as pray,
but it's translated nine times
in our English Bible as beseech.
Think about this.
The apostle Paul says, I beseech you
in Romans chapter number 12.
What's he saying?
I'm pleading with you.
I'm begging you.
I've laid out the truth that I've laid out
and now I'm begging you.
I'm pleading with you.
And begin to look at this truth this morning
and considering the purpose that we have
as being an ambassador.
Yes, it's a great privilege, but we have a purpose.
And it says that we pray you in Christ's stead.
In other words, on his behalf, the Lord Jesus Christ,
he's seated at the right hand of the throne of glory.
We find that he has left us as his ambassadors
and so we're his representatives.
We're going out on his behalf and we have a purpose.
The purpose that we have is not to feed the hungry.
The purpose that we have is not to build.
I'm not saying there's anything wrong with those things.
I'm simply saying that if we only do those things,
we've fallen short of what our true purpose is.
Because our true purpose is to bring,
to do the work of reconciliation.
Notice what he says.
We pray you in Christ's stead, be ye reconciled to God.
Why is it that man needs reconciliation?
What is it that reconciliation means?
It means the act of reconciling parties,
notice this, at variance.
Why are they at variance?
Why does the Bible say that he's given to us
the ministry of reconciliation?
It's because of sin.
See, God didn't do anything wrong, but humanity did.
Sin entered into the world in the garden.
And death passed upon all men.
Amen?
We're all sinners for all have sinned
and come short of the glory of God.
We're all sinners.
And therefore, every sinner needs reconciliation.
Why?
He's at enmity.
He's at variance with God.
God has done everything necessary
to provide for reconciliation.
There's nothing that any of us can do to add to it.
It would show the fact that his offering was not sufficient.
He did it all.
But he's entrusted to us the ministry of reconciliation.
See, you know there's a lot of people
that we come in contact with on a daily basis
that do not know that they need to be reconciled to God.
They don't know it.
They have no idea.
Oh, they might admit that they're a sinner,
but they may have been in a position
where they've been taught some false thoughts
with regard to salvation and how to approach God.
And I've heard many people over the years say,
especially in their later years,
I've made my peace with God.
And I've often wondered and I've often asked the question,
what do you mean by that?
Because the Bible tells us there's only one way
to have peace with God.
The Bible is very clear with regard
to this ministry of reconciliation.
And we find that mankind is in need of reconciliation.
And God has entrusted to us as his ambassadors,
as his representatives, this great privileged title,
this distinguished title, the privilege and honor
that I can represent the Lord Jesus Christ here on earth,
but I have a purpose.
And it's the ministry of reconciliation.
Turn to the book of Romans, if you will.
We're gonna look at a few verses of scripture
and kind of hammer in this ministry of reconciliation
and what this really looks like and what we must deal with
as we consider the purpose that God has given to us.
In Romans chapter five, beginning in verse number six,
notice what the Bible says.
Romans five and verse number six.
For when we were yet without strength,
in due time, Christ died for the ungodly.
For scarcely for a righteous man will one die,
yet peradventure for a good man,
some would even dare to die,
but God commendeth his love toward us.
And that while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us.
You know why he died for you?
Because you're a sinner.
You needed a substitute.
And he died for us because he loves us.
This is the payment that was made
so that the two parties that were at variance
could be brought to peace.
It tells us in verse number nine,
much more than being now justified, how?
By your works?
No, by his blood.
Amen.
Is that what it says?
How are you gonna be justified?
There's only one way to be justified.
Only one way to be reconciled.
Only one way to be saved.
Jesus is the only way.
Justified by his blood,
we shall be saved from wrath through him.
Notice in verse 10,
for if when we were enemies,
we were, what does it say?
Reconciled.
Listen, I know sometimes we wanna,
I wasn't really an enemy of God.
You were an enemy of God.
God wasn't your enemy.
God wants you to be saved.
But we, in our rebellion, in our sin,
we were at enmity with God.
We were at variance.
And we needed to be reconciled.
And he says, for when we were enemies,
we were reconciled to God, how?
By the death of his son.
Much more, being reconciled,
we shall be saved by his life.
Hallelujah.
Verse 11, and not only so,
but we also joy in God through our Lord Jesus Christ,
by whom we have now received the atonement.
Man, it's good to be reconciled.
It is absolutely necessary to be reconciled.
Amen?
If you're not saved this morning,
if you've not been reconciled,
if you're still at variance,
you've never accepted the Lord Jesus Christ
as your personal savior.
Listen, chapter number six
of the book of 2 Corinthians,
today is the day of salvation.
We plead with you, we pray,
we beseech you in Christ's name,
be reconciled to God.
You need to be reconciled,
because you're at variance.
Notice in verse number one of this passage,
I didn't read it to start out.
I read verses six through 11,
but notice verse number one,
therefore being justified,
we read of that in verse number nine,
by his blood, notice by faith,
we have peace with God
through our Lord Jesus Christ.
He's my peace.
I have peace with God.
Does it mean I'm perfect?
No, but he is.
He is.
The next verse in 2 Corinthians chapter five
that we'll study, probably not next Sunday,
but the following Sunday,
for he hath made him to be sin for us
who knew no sin, that we might be made
the righteousness of God in him.
Hallelujah.
It's that imputed righteousness.
It's not my own righteousness.
All of my own righteousness is in filthy rags.
It's his righteousness.
And I have peace with God.
If you're saved this morning,
if you've been reconciled,
you have peace with God.
Ephesians chapter two,
notice what the Bible says here
in Ephesians chapter two,
as we think about this truth of reconciliation.
In fact, I wish we could,
we actually will.
We're gonna back up and start reading
in verse number one.
It's just so important to see all of this this morning.
I'll do my best not to make many comments
and just let God's word speak for itself here this morning.
In verse number one,
the Bible says,
and you hath he quickened
who were dead in trespasses and sins.
I was dead spiritually,
but he made me alive.
I was born again.
We talked about that last week.
Verse two, wherein in time past,
you walked according to the course of this world,
according to the prince,
the power of the air,
the spirit that now worketh
in the children of disobedience,
among whom also we all had our conversation in times past
in the lust of our flesh,
fulfilling the desires of the flesh
and of the mind,
and were by nature the children of wrath,
even as others.
But God, aren't you thankful for the but God?
But God who is rich in mercy for his great love,
wherewith he loved us,
even when we were dead in sin.
hath quickened us together with Christ, by grace ye are saved, and hath raised us
up together and made us to sit in heavenly places in Christ Jesus, that in
the ages to come he might show the exceeding riches of his grace and his
kindness toward us through Christ Jesus. For by grace are you saved through faith,
and that not of yourselves, but of the gift of God, not of works, lest any man
should boast. For we are his workmanship created in Christ Jesus unto good works,
which God hath before ordained, that we should walk in them. Notice verse 11.
Wherefore remember, remember, remember what? That ye, being in time past Gentiles in
the flesh, who are called on circumcision by that which is called the circumcision,
in the flesh made by hands, that at that time, notice what it says, ye were without
Christ. Can you remember that? Can you remember in your life when you were
without Christ? I'm saying before you got saved. See, because being saved is not a
process, it's a moment, it's the miracle of a moment. You must be born again, and I
remember in time past. I remember when I was without Christ. I remember having no
hope. I remember having no peace. I remember having no real joy, because I was without
Christ. I remember that. By the way, it's a good thing for us every once in a while
to remember what he did for us, where we were headed. A songwriter, I haven't heard the
song for years, but he said, speaking of his life, when he was prior to being saved, he
was on a road heading to nowhere. Now, the reality is that he was heading to the lake
of fire. This morning, we find that he says, you were without Christ, notice, being aliens
from the commonwealth of Israel and strangers from the covenants of promise, having no hope
and without God in the world. In the beginning, I read the whole passage because the reality
is that in verse number three, it says that, among whom also we all had our conversation
in time past, we were all in the same boat. We were all without hope. We were all without
Christ. You weren't born saved. Amen? God has no grandchildren. Amen? Why do we pray
that our kids in our junior church, in our Sunday school ministers, why do we pray that
they get saved at a young age? Because just having a saved mom and dad doesn't make them
saved. Amen? My grandkids are 18 months old and two weeks old, and I've already prayed
for their salvation. Why? Because just because their parents are saved and their grandparents
are saved and just because their grandfather's a preacher doesn't mean that they're going
to heaven. Amen? They need to be saved. He tells us in verse 13, but now. But now. Remember
in time past, verse 11, but in verse 13, but now, in Christ Jesus, those that have been
ye who sometimes were far off are made nigh by the blood of Christ. For he, the Lord Jesus
Christ, for he is our peace, who hath made both one and hath broken down the middle wall
of partition between us, having abolished in his flesh, notice, the enmity, even the
law of commandments contained in ordinances, for to make in himself of twain one new man,
so making peace, and that he might reconcile both unto God in one body by the cross, having
slain the enmity thereby. He's provided the way, but he has given to us the ministry of
reconciliation. And when we understand the privilege of being an ambassador, and then
we understand the purpose of being an ambassador, the purpose is that we are, as he says in
verse number 20 of our text of Scripture, that we pray you in Christ's stead be ye reconciled
to God. I'll be very transparent with you this morning. I do my best to help us. God
convicted me this week on this truth in verse 20, that we pray you in Christ's stead be
ye reconciled to God. You know why God convicted me this week? I know there are times that
all we might be able to do is hand a gospel tract to somebody at a grocery store, at a
whatever, it might be all that we can do, but can I tell you this, God convicted me,
that's not praying you in Christ's stead that you be reconciled to God. It's not really
being an ambassador and pleading with someone. It really isn't. God convicted me this week.
I think we should give out gospel tracts. I think we should send out literature. We
have things. I've asked you to take them. We use door hangers. We have invitations.
We mail things at times, but God didn't call us to be marketing agents. Amen? He didn't
call us to be marketing agents. He said you're ambassadors. An ambassador is different than
a marketing agent. An ambassador, we pray you, we beseech you, we beg you in Christ's
stead, be ye reconciled to God. Why? Because I understand if they're not reconciled, they're
going to spend eternity in the lake of fire. And I understand that they're at enmity, they're
at variance, and God's given to us the opportunity, the privilege of going in and trying to bring
these two parties that are at variance. God did nothing wrong. Man sinned, and man needs
to be brought back, reconciled, and that's our ministry. That's our ministry. I wonder
when's the last time we wept over a soul. I wonder the last time we pled with someone
to be saved. I wonder. I examine my own life. Do you have people right now that you're praying
for? I asked this question a few weeks ago, maybe a couple of months ago now. Time goes
so quickly. When's the last time you shared the gospel with someone personally? Not the
last time you gave somebody a gospel tract. I think it's good to give gospel tracts. When's
the last time you personally shared the gospel with someone personally? God beat me up this
week because we are His ambassadors. Man is at variance, at enmity with God, and the
only way for them to be reconciled is if those that are true ambassadors that have already
been reconciled are engaged in the work, the ministry of reconciliation. The government
can't reconcile man to God. And by the way, God didn't give him that responsibility. God
instituted government, but God did not give government that responsibility. He gave it
to us. We are His ambassadors. And what a privilege that is ours to have that distinguished
title, but with it comes a purpose. We pray you, we pray you, plead with you, beg you,
beseech you, in Christ's stead, be reconciled to God. I've had someone ask me at various
times, I've had people ask this question, why do you care so much if I get saved? And
I've said this, listen, I'm going to heaven whether you get saved or not. I'm going to
heaven whether someone else gets saved or not, because I've been saved. But I want them
to go to heaven. Why? Because I know the alternative. And we've been reconciled and
we want others to be reconciled to God to have that peace and He's given to us this
ministry of reconciliation. Can I tell you, it's not passive, it's active. It's not passive,
it's active. Listen, it's got to be purposed, intentional. I told you about the stranger,
Marcel, that we drove with for six hours and 15 minutes from Nashville to Pensacola. If
you don't know the story, I'm not going to give it all to you right now because I don't
have time, but we were stranded in Nashville and we're going to have a 14-hour layover
and so we're going to rent a car and drive.
fellow said, can I ride with you? And I said, sure. And Joseph was like, what in the world
is going on? And Armando, I promise you, I promise you, it was as if the Holy Spirit
of God said that man needs to know the truth of the gospel. I sat in that car, and I'm
just going to be transparent with you. I didn't want to bring it up too early in case it was
super uncomfortable. You say, Pastor, that's kind of fleshly and carnal. I'm just being
honest with you. It was a six-hour drive. But I kept watching that GPS. When it got
to about an hour, it's go time. How do we transition? It was purposed. I wish he got
saved. He didn't. Jeff brought up somebody in Sunday school a few weeks ago they got
to share the gospel with because of a circumstance. I've been praying for that lady by name.
He's followed up with her. The prophet of God in the Old Testament wept. Elisha wept.
Why? Because he knew the destruction that was going to come. God revealed it to him.
Paul wept. He served the Lord night and day with tears. So, what the Bible tells us in
Acts chapter 20? He's pleading with people to be reconciled to God. We know God has revealed
to us the truth of eternity. There's a lot of dry eyes in 2025. I just wonder, do we
really truly understand what it is to be an ambassador? The privilege, the privilege
to be the representative of the King of Kings and Lord of Lords and the purpose. We pray
you in Christ's stead be reconciled to God. Let's pray. Father, we love you this morning.
Thank you for reconciling me. Thank you for saving my soul. God, I pray you would help
us, help us to be good ambassadors, to recognize the privilege, the purpose. Would you move
and work in hearts and lives. If there's one here not sure of heaven, God, I pray they'd
be saved by the grace of God. For every child of God, would you help us this morning to
be stirred, to be changed. Pray that you'd have your will and way, for it's in Christ's
name we pray. Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed. Kimberly's going
to play quietly on the piano. As she does, the altar's open. If you're not sure of heaven,
we'll take a Bible and show you how to know for sure that heaven's your home. Maybe God
just convicted you this morning. We're going to have a heart, a passion for souls. We're
going to be known as ambassadors. As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.