And a couple of weeks ago, of course, last week,
we had a missionary with us, Brother Josh Mead,
and thankful for the work that God is doing
in and through the Mead family there in Senegal.
Thankful that God gives us an opportunity
to partner with them.
We dealt with, two weeks ago,
in 1 Timothy chapter two, verses nine through 15,
behavior in God's church, part one.
This morning is behavior in God's church, part two.
And we're looking at 1 Timothy three, verses one through 15.
And I wanna read to you verses 14 and 15
by way of introduction this morning.
I read these verses by way of introduction
two weeks ago as well.
And the Bible says in verse 14,
these things write I unto you, unto thee.
And we know that God tells us in his word
that all scripture is given by inspiration of God
and it's profitable for us.
And God is using the apostle Paul
to write under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
a letter to Timothy, his own son of the faith,
a leader in the church.
He's there at the church at Ephesus.
We've already dealt with that
in 1 Timothy chapter number one.
So we understand where Timothy is
and we understand why God left Timothy there,
what his responsibility was there in Ephesus.
There was false teaching.
There were all sorts of things going on.
And he was to give them the truth.
He was to preach sound doctrine.
We find that he had responsibilities
with helping the church.
And it says these things write I unto thee.
Notice the Bible says hoping to come unto thee shortly.
Paul's desire was to be able to go back to Ephesus,
this church that God allowed him on the missionary journey
to see established and to help them.
But he's writing these things
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God
until he can be present to instruct the church.
The church needed some instruction.
And so Paul is writing, in fact, in the fourth chapter,
the memory verse of the month of April,
till I come, give attendance to reading,
to exhortation, to doctrine.
When Paul mentions till I come,
really you look at this verse in chapter number three
and verse number 14 when he says,
I'm hoping to come unto thee shortly
until I can get there, keep on doing these things,
chapter four, but I'm writing you these things.
Notice verse number 15.
He says, but if I tarry long.
Now I'm thankful.
There are sometimes you hear somebody talk about Jesus
tarrying his coming.
The Bible says that Jesus said he will not tarry, amen?
So you hear, and I'm not trying to split hairs,
but when somebody says, if he tarries his coming,
understand he's not going to, amen?
Jesus is coming right on time.
By the way, I thought it was gonna be last week, hallelujah.
It didn't happen, we're still going, amen?
And we're still serving the Savior,
redeeming the time for the days are evil.
We understand all of that, but we're looking,
we're expecting to hear, come up hither, amen?
Praise the Lord.
Jesus is not gonna tarry his coming,
but Paul says, if I tarry long,
if my circumstances do not allow me to get there to Ephesus
the church is in need of some instruction,
so I'm writing these things.
Notice why, that thou mayest know
how thou oughtest to behave thyself.
Notice the Bible says, in the house of God, amen?
It's God's church, which is the church of the living God,
the pillar and ground of truth.
So thankful that Jesus Christ is truth.
I am the way, the truth, and the life,
but I'm so thankful that he's given us the Bible,
which is truth.
He said, sanctify them through thy word.
Thy word is truth.
And what a blessing to understand the instruction
that has been given, that thou mayest know
how thou oughtest to behave thyself.
And so there is proper behavior in God's house.
There is a behavior that is appropriate in God's house.
There is behavior that is inappropriate in God's house.
Amen?
And we understand that.
We see in the day and age in which we're living,
I dealt with it a few weeks ago.
I mentioned the comment in one of the messages
about some things that have happened
in churches around our land
that are absolutely irreverent.
They are just absolutely inappropriate.
God says, I'm using Paul to write this letter
so that you know how you ought to behave.
Now understand that God has preserved this letter
of 1 Timothy for every church throughout the church age
to have this instruction so that we would understand.
At the end of chapter number two,
as we dealt with last week,
we find that specifically that text of scripture
addresses women in the church.
As we move into chapter number three,
dealing with behavior in God's church,
we find that as we continue this study,
we discover that more instruction
is being provided to the local church.
We understand that here,
God is going to give some instruction
with regard to the officers in the church,
to leadership in church.
Now we understand that the church was instituted by God.
It's important to understand.
The church was instituted by God.
The church is not man's idea.
Amen?
The church didn't start with Constantine.
The church is God's idea.
He, Jesus Christ, said I will build my church
and the gates of hell shall not prevail against it
in Matthew 16.
So the church is instituted by God,
but we also understand that God has graciously provided
instruction for his church in his word.
How's the church to function?
How's the church to operate?
It's not man's institution.
That man designed.
So it's not man's duty to determine
how a church is to function.
God provided that instruction.
By the way, we ought to be thankful for that.
Amen?
And we ought to go to the source that God gave us
and say here is the source and this dictates to us,
and yes, I choose that word on purpose
because God has the right to dictate
how his church is to function.
It's his church.
By the way, we understand that Jesus Christ gave himself
for the church.
Amen?
Ephesians chapter number five.
We understand that Jesus Christ is the head of the church.
Colossians chapter number one,
the book of Ephesians deals with that as well.
We understand that one day,
Jesus is coming back for his church
and then one day Jesus is coming back with his church.
Amen?
Hallelujah.
We're gonna come back, you read Revelation 19,
we're coming back with him.
Hallelujah.
And we find this morning that this era in which we're living
that some theologians have used the term
that we would say that we're living in the church age
or the church era.
And we find that in this particular time,
after the ascension of Jesus Christ
and before the rapture of the church,
that this time that is not known
exactly how long it will be,
we know the tribulation will be seven years,
we know that the millennium will be a thousand years,
the church age,
we don't know how long it's going to begin or to be,
but during this era, this time of the church age,
God has designed it that the church is the organism
that God is using for this day and age.
The church is important.
It's the bride of Christ.
Church is not something that we just do.
Church is not something that we just kind of have
a membership like we do at some other place
where we just kind of belong to.
You know, I have a gym membership,
I ain't been there for like six months.
But I'm still a member.
I haven't been there in so long,
I took the key tag off my key.
And I saw just last week, they charged me.
I said, I better start going
or cancel the membership, amen.
That's not church.
Church is the bride of Christ.
Church isn't just a club.
Church isn't just a place where we come
and just kind of social gathering.
I'm thankful for the fellowship
of brothers and sisters in Christ, amen.
But understand the church is something different than that.
Listen, you can get together during the week,
you can have fun and games and do that sort of thing.
But when we come to church, we're coming to worship Christ.
We're coming to exalt the Lord Jesus Christ.
We understand we come together,
we gotta follow what God's pattern is
that he's established in his word with regard to leadership.
And we see that instruction here.
We are to be subject to Christ in all things.
As believers individually, but then as a church,
we're to be subject to Christ.
We understand that he has instituted leadership
for his church.
We believe that the Bible clearly teaches
there are two offices in the local church.
These offices are identified
and we find that qualifications
for those filling the position
are clearly outlined in his word.
We find here this morning
in 1 Timothy chapter number three
and verses one through,
we're gonna go down through verse number 15,
but really down through verse number 13
are the two offices described, defined,
and we find that the qualifications are listed.
What are the two offices?
Well, we believe the Bible teaches very plainly and clearly
that there's the office of the pastor
and there's the office of a deacon.
Those are the two offices that God has outlined.
Let me first address the matter of title.
This is all by way of introduction.
The points are easy this morning,
but let me just deal with this this morning,
because unfortunately there are some that teach
that bishops and elders are different offices.
Okay, you may hear someone say that,
you may be exposed to that.
In fact, I've heard somebody that's very well known
on a radio broadcast in recent months
make a statement about the error of our Baptist brethren
that do not have elders and bishops.
And let me explain to you this morning
why we believe that the Bible teaches
that there's an office of pastor
and there's an office of deacon.
Why is it that God has provided us
with these different words, bishop and elder,
that we see in the New Testament?
I believe that God is giving those two words
to help us understand the role and responsibility
of the individual that fills the office.
Does that make sense this morning?
So we find that the word pastor,
the word elder, the word bishop,
those words are all words that are describing
the office of a pastor, the duties and responsibilities.
Why is it that we believe that?
Well, we believe that, remember as a Baptist,
we would say that the Bible is our sole authority
for faith and practice.
So as we determine what our polity will be,
the structure, the leadership organization
within a local church,
it's not just that we're following some man-made traditions.
No, we wanna go to what the Bible says
because the Bible is our sole authority
for faith and for practice.
The word bishop and the word elder
are used interchangeably in the New Testament.
And as those two words are used interchangeably
in the New Testament,
it helps us to explain and understand the work,
the duty of the one that's in that office.
I'm being a little technical this morning
by way of introduction,
but I hope that we understand the importance
of this principle this morning
because there is much confusion
that is out there this morning
with regard to church polity
or leadership structure in a local church.
Someone may say to you, well, who are your elders?
Well, our pastor is, no, but who are your elders?
They might wanna make that distinction.
And we understand biblically, again,
the word bishop and elder are used interchangeably.
Go over to the book of Acts, if you will.
Keep your place in 1 Timothy.
And we find that it's here that it uses the word bishop,
the office of a bishop.
But turn to the book of Acts in chapter number 20.
And I use this portion of scripture for two reasons.
One, Paul is writing to Timothy who's there in Ephesus.
And Acts chapter number 20 is a record
where Paul is having a communication and interaction
with the leaders of the church at Ephesus.
And so it's insightful
as we look at this passage of scripture.
In verse number 17, notice in Acts 20 and verse 17,
Paul is desiring to go to Jerusalem
to be there for Pentecost according to verse 16.
He does not have time to go to Ephesus.
But there's a message that he needs to deliver
to the leaders of the church at Ephesus.
Therefore he calls, according to verse 17,
it says, for Miletus, he sent to Ephesus
and called the elders of the church.
Do you see that in your Bible?
He called the elders of the church.
And then it says in verse 18,
and when they were come to him.
Now, if he called for the elders,
do you think the elders came?
Just kind of makes sense that they,
in verse number 18, that came
are the ones that were called for.
And those elders come and Paul begins,
it says that he said unto them.
Now we don't have time to read all of it.
We're not preaching from Acts 20 this morning,
but Paul begins to instruct these leaders
of the church at Ephesus,
as it's referred to in verse 17,
the elders of the church at Ephesus.
As we come down to verse number 28,
notice the charge as Paul is wrapping up his charge here,
this admonition to these church leaders.
He says in verse 28,
take heed therefore unto yourselves
and to all the flock over the witch,
the Holy Ghost hath made you overseers.
Now, do you see that word overseer?
That word is bishop.
It's translated overseer
because that's what bishop means, okay?
In the book of 1 Timothy chapter three,
when it says, if you desire an office of a bishop,
it's the same Greek word that we see here, overseer.
Okay, so he called for the elders,
but he says to the elders
that God hath made you overseers or the bishop.
Are we tracking?
To look, feed the church of God,
which he hath purchased with his own blood.
And we're gonna look at that last phrase,
to feed the church of God,
and really that helps us understand
some of the role of the pastor.
Again, the word that would be used only in our New Testament
in Ephesians four and verse number 11,
where he says, and he gave some apostles,
but then he says pastors and teachers.
It's the only place you're gonna find the word pastor
in the New Testament.
But you find that the pastor,
as we would outline the responsibility
and the word that is used there,
is the one that's shepherding or feeding the flock.
So the pastor has the responsibility
as the bishop of being the overseer.
There's a lot of matters that need to be overseen.
The elder, the principal official,
or the spiritually mature individual
that's shepherding the flock of God.
Notice as we look at this text in Acts 20,
but then turn to 1 Peter chapter five,
and notice what Peter says in 1 Peter chapter five.
Keeping in mind what we've just read there
in Acts chapter number 20,
Peter begins to address at the end of this letter
that he's writing, he addresses the elders specifically.
Notice in chapter five in verse number one.
1 Peter five in verse number one.
The Bible says, the elders which are among you I exhort.
Who am also an elder?
And a witness of the sufferings of Christ
and also a partaker of the glory that shall be revealed.
Notice what he says to the elder.
That's what he references.
Feed the flock of God, which is among you,
taking the oversight thereof.
Remember, the bishop is the overseer.
Taking the oversight thereof,
not by constraint but willingly,
not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind.
Neither as being lords over God's heritage,
but being in samples to the flock.
And when the chief shepherd shall appear, hallelujah.
He's the chief shepherd, he's the head of the church.
The word under shepherd is never used in the New Testament,
but we have used that terminology
to describe the office of the pastor.
That he's the under shepherd.
Why would we use,
why did the term get coined the under shepherd?
Well, because Christ is the chief shepherd.
So the pastor is the under shepherd because notice,
it says when the chief shepherd shall appear,
we shall receive a crown of glory that fadeth not away.
Who is ye that Peter is referring to in verse number four?
Well, the elders that he's exhorting.
This is an opportunity to receive a crown,
a crown of glory that fadeth not away,
that's reserved for the one that fills that office
and fulfills it properly, biblically.
And so as we pay close attention to the words of scripture
and understand how God uses these terms interchangeably,
it helps us to understand as we come back
to 1 Timothy chapter number three,
it helps us to understand that these aren't different
offices, but they are words that are used
to describe the responsibility of the individual
that fills the office.
Are we tracking this morning?
As we come back to 1 Timothy chapter number three,
we pay close attention to the language that God uses
in this passage because he's going to provide Paul,
of course, all scripture is given by inspiration of God,
so God is using, it's God's word he's using,
Paul is writing to Timothy and he's providing him
with qualifications for the officers in his church.
The first one, if you're taking notes,
the two points this morning are very easy,
the office of a bishop and the office of a deacon.
All right, those are the two points.
I'm not gonna say a whole lot about
those particular points, I'm gonna give you
some information, look at what the Bible says
in verse number one, this is a true saying.
Aren't you thankful that God's word is true?
Amen, this isn't just Paul coming up with,
you know, there's a structure problem,
an organizational issue, the org chart is off
and so I'm gonna give you my, no, no, no,
this is God's word, God's instruction.
He says it's a true saying, notice where he says
if a man desire the office of a bishop,
he desireth a good work.
It's a good work, it's an honorable work.
And the one, the man that would fill that position,
the office of a bishop, as it's noted here,
it is an honorable work and it is an honorable position.
And we find that as Paul is writing,
he says the office.
of a bishop. And so we have to understand again the office that is being spoken of
when we speak about this structure or this polity within the local church. He then says
in verse number two, a bishop then, notice this phrase, must be. Must be. The qualifications
that God is going to give, the requirements that are laid out in this portion of Scripture
are not just good ideas or good thoughts. These qualifications or requirements, I would say,
I've said it this way before, they're non-negotiable. It's not a situation where you say,
well, this person is just, man, they're a good orator. I mean, they have a bubbly personality
and they just seem to be able to draw people to themselves. And man, they just, they can organize
well and they're a natural born leader. Do you know none of what I just said is in First
Timothy chapter three? It's not there. Now, is it good? Does God gift and equip those who He calls?
I believe He does. By the way, the Bible tells us the Holy Ghost, the Holy Spirit gives gifts
as He will. And God can equip the man. But the man must be qualified. Just because, I said this
in Sunday school, just because a man desires the office doesn't mean he's qualified for the office.
There's a list that's provided. The requirements, as we look here, are specific. I would say it this
way, they really deal with the character of the individual. Can I say to you this morning,
character matters? Can I say to you this morning, that as we look at this passage of Scripture
and we deal with the office of a bishop and the office of a deacon and we understand the structure
that God establishes for His church, that it's also important that we understand that these
qualifications that are outlined are good things for every child of God to desire to be true of
them? Amen? God holds a high standard for His people. We represent the Lord Jesus Christ.
God holds a high standard for the one that would fill the office of a bishop or a deacon,
and it's outlined specifically. Why does God give the specifics? Why does God provide
us with these specifics? Well, because He wants us to understand as Timothy is there in Ephesus
seeking to set in order some things, just as we see with Titus, we're going to flip over to Titus
in just a moment, just as we see Titus is given that responsibility, that God has structure. By
the way, I'm thankful that our God is a God of order. Amen? He does all things decently
and in order. Our God is a God of order. Hold your place here, turn over just a few pages to the book
of Titus, if you will, and notice in Titus chapter number 1, beginning in verse number 5, now Paul
is writing to Titus here, again under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God.
Titus is not in Ephesus and Timothy is not in Crete,
but Timothy in Ephesus has some things, responsibilities that he has to do, and Titus
in Crete has some responsibilities, some things he's supposed to fulfill, and interestingly enough,
there's some similarities between what's going on in Crete and what's going on in Ephesus,
and so God leaves these people, these servants there in order to set some things in order. Notice
in verse number 5 of Titus 1, for this cause left I thee in Crete. For what cause? That thou
shouldest set in order the things that are wanting, notice, and ordain elders in every city
as I have appointed thee. If any be blameless, and he gets into those particular qualifications.
It's interesting that he says ordain elders in verse number 5, but then notice in verse number
7, for a bishop must be. Again, do you understand, as we've noted already over in the book of Acts,
and we've gone over the book of 1 Peter, that God uses those terms interchangeably.
We're not going to look at the entirety of Titus 1, 5 through 9, and look through those. We're
going to do that in chapter 3 of the book of 1 Timothy, but we find that the requirements are
specific, and God deals with, I would characterize it this way, he deals with not only the public
life of the one that would have the office of a bishop, but also the private life.
God is concerned about those who hold an office of leadership of authority in his church. And by
the way, he should be. He has every right to be. He has every right to list out the qualifications.
We find, the Bible says back in 1 Timothy chapter 3 and verse number 2, a bishop then must be
blameless. I'm not going to give the explanation for every one of these. We'd be weeks in this
chapter. I don't have time. We're trying to get through 1 and 2 Timothy. I've taught through this
before, but understand the word blameless doesn't mean that someone can't blame you for something.
It means that you're in that place where it doesn't stick, right? You have a good report.
Listen, understand also, as we look through this passage of Scripture, that the bishop and also the
deacon, the level of qualification is not perfection. If it were perfection, then no one
would be qualified. Jesus Christ is the only one that's ever walked on this earth that's been perfect.
Amen? And some people are looking for a perfect pastor. They're looking for a perfect church.
And they're an imperfect person. And they're going to find an imperfect pastor, an imperfect church.
By the way, if you find a perfect church and you try to join it, you're going to mess it up
because you're not perfect. You say, I can't believe you'd say that.
We're not perfect. Amen? None of us are perfect. But the character of the individual is what's
under the microscope. We find that he deals with the private life and the public life. He says they
must be blameless, the husband of one wife. There's been much discussion about that over the centuries
with regard to the understanding of this particular phrase, the husband of one wife. It's
said there of a deacon as well. And there's some that say, well, it just means one wife at one time.
I believe that it's a one woman man. It's not somebody that's given to all of these
inappropriate type of situations. God says that there's one man and one woman, one lifetime.
Amen? We find that he says husband of one wife, notice vigilant, sober, of good behavior,
given to hospitality, apt to teach. Remember what he said? I'm going to pause just for a moment.
Remember what he said in verse 7 of chapter 1 about those false teachers they had swerved and
turned aside into vain jangling? He said, desiring to be teachers of the law, understanding neither
what they say nor whereof they affirm. So one of the qualifications, they're apt to teach,
not given to whine, no striker. That'd be a bad thing. You see the picture of your pastor on the
news because he got in a fight. No, no striker, not brawler. It says that in verse number 3 as well.
Not greedy, a filthy lucre, but patient, patient, not a brawler, not covetous.
So we look at verse 2 and 3 and we list very quick bullet points that are given,
and we find again that the scriptures are dealing with the character of the individual,
the private life, the public life. We find that he says of this one that would desire the office
of a bishop, that he desireth a good work, but then there's some qualifications, there's some
requirements. So Timothy, so Titus over in Crete, as you're going to put people in position of
leadership, understand that there's some criteria that must be met, that these are
non-negotiable, that these are requirements that God sets forth. We find that it says,
again, if we even look at those things in verse 2 and 3, that it's an examination process,
that a person, a man that desires that office, they ought to be willing to prove themselves.
It says in verse 4, one that ruleth well his own house, having his children in subjection with all
gravity, for if a man know not how to rule his own house, how shall he take care of the church
of God? Noticing again the private life, he talks about one that ruleth well his own house. Let me
say this, the children of a pastor are not going to be perfect either, just like your children
aren't perfect. You know that through the decades that there's been a problem in some of our
churches where there's an expectation of the children of a pastor that are different than
children of other people within the church. I'm thankful that as we've had the opportunity to
raise our family here that I personally never dealt with that, where someone, some group of
folks within our church would want to hold my children to a different, higher standard than
their children. The fact of the matter is that they're not going to be perfect, but notice what
the Bible says in verse number 5, for if a man know not how to rule his own house, how shall he
take care of the church of God? It's a very practical question that's laid out. You understand
that the pastor has the responsibility, as we outline here, some of these responsibilities
that also give insight to the, some of these requirements that give insight to the responsibilities.
the pastors to take care of the church of God.
Paul makes this comment in 2 Corinthians as he's writing to the church in Corinth.
He talks about all of those things that came upon him daily, but then he says, or all of
the various trials and difficulties and persecutions that he faced, but then he says, and that
which cometh upon me daily, the care of all the churches.
The pastor has the responsibility to care for the church of God.
Qualifications continue, not a novice, why?
Lest being lifted up with pride, he fall into the condemnation of the devil.
Listen, we understand this morning that there's no particular time that's listed with regard
to how long a person, a man has to be saved before he can be a pastor, but the Bible clearly
says not a novice, amen?
And it gives us the reason why, again, as God, God didn't have to give us the reason
why, by the way, but He did graciously.
He tells them later in this book, lay hands on no man suddenly.
Some have believed that to believe not to ordain people hastily, not, you know, there
are times in which somebody's like, man, we haven't had a pastor for so long, just anybody
that's willing to fill the position, just somebody do it.
When I finished Bible college, I had the opportunity to preach for one of my professors
in a number of different churches.
Never, as I went to any of those churches, was I going as a potential candidate for any
of those churches.
I had just graduated from Bible college, but I was seeking to help him in a ministry that
he was doing, but also to get some experience with preaching.
It was a great opportunity.
There were a number of churches that he was working with that didn't have pastors, and
he would work with pastors and try to kind of pair the two together, if you will.
And I remember going to some churches, and Holly would travel with me, and as we would
travel to go to these churches, we would find that there were some churches that didn't
have a pastor for two or three years.
That's a tragic situation.
And unfortunately what happens in a church like that is sometimes 1 Timothy 3 kind of
gets set aside because we just want a pastor.
Usually they'd be willing to do it.
No, God sets forth requirements.
He gives us these qualifications, and it's important that we understand that God provides
these to us.
He says, moreover, notice verse number 7, he must, he uses that word again, have a good
report of them which are without.
Now that's interesting.
Remember, I've talked to you that it's dealing with the private life and the public life.
The pastor not only has a good report of those within, but it says, it actually doesn't
say that, but it says a good report of them without, lest he fall into reproach and the
snare of the devil.
The pastor ought not be known in the community as being a bad person, a wicked person.
In fact, it's always interesting to me, and I love the passage of Scripture in the book
of 1 Samuel where Saul's friend says, there is a man of God in this city, talking of Samuel.
That's how the pastor ought to be known, and I understand we live in a very big place,
lots of people, but back in the day in America, small community, small town America, the pastor
was known in the community.
Amen?
It ought to be known that there's a man of God in this town, in this city, in this community.
We find that he says that he must have a good report of them which are without, lest
he fall into reproach and the snare of the devil.
I've not addressed specifically each one of these, go through them relatively quickly
this morning, but it's understood that as we look at this list that's provided for the
office of a bishop, the pastor, again the word used interchangeably throughout the New
Testament of a pastor, a bishop, an elder, as to what the requirements are.
And he says likewise in verse number 8, we segue to the office of a deacon.
We see that reference in verse number 10 and also in verse number 13.
The Bible says to them that use the office of a deacon in verse number 10, and verse
number 13, for they that have used the office of a deacon.
I said this in Sunday school this morning, it's important that we understand that here
he's speaking about the office of a deacon.
The language here makes clear that these qualifications are necessary, not just desired.
We've said that of the bishop, the pastor, but it's true also of the deacon.
It's important that we note that the word deacon in its most plain form means a servant,
a minister.
In fact, many times in the New Testament, only here in fact, in 1 Timothy 3, is the
Greek word translated deacon.
Everywhere else it's translated either minister or servant or something with regard to that
kind of idea of ministering, of serving.
I said it in Sunday school that every deacon is a servant, is a minister.
But not every servant or minister is a deacon.
Does that make sense?
We're all to be servants of the Lord.
We're all to serve Christ.
We find that God establishes again as He's giving the order in the church that thou mayest
know how thou oughtest to behave thyself.
He's providing this structure and this order and He says there's an office of the pastor,
the bishop, the elder, but there's an office of a deacon.
By the way, we're not a deacon board run church.
Hallelujah.
We got three deacons.
But the deacons don't tell me what to do.
And I'm not saying that to be sarcastic, to be prideful or arrogant, but a deacon run
church is not biblical.
Amen?
The deacons don't tell me here's, no, that's, no, we have deacons that fit the qualifications
and I counsel with them.
By the way, that's just wise.
Amen?
We have church meetings.
We have one next Sunday night where the church makes decisions.
Just because I'm the pastor doesn't mean I just go rogue and make all the decisions.
That's not what the idea is, the overseer, but you understand there's some churches that
are board run churches all across our land.
And the deacons think that they have some level of authority over the pastor, over the
pulpit.
I've often said to people over the years, listen, no one's dictating to me, and again,
I hope you understand how I'm saying this.
I'm not saying it pridefully or arrogantly, what I preach.
The pulpit is an area that's kind of like reserved for the pastor.
Amen?
And I'm to preach the Word of God, to be instantencies and odysseys and to reprove, rebuke, to exhort
with all longsuffering, and we understand the time will come when they will not endure
sound doctrine.
We find here this morning that the deacons are not some ruling board in a church.
The deacons are servants or ministers.
Some people have the idea.
I remember in the church that I did my internship in after college, actually, I was still in
college when I was doing my internship, and I remember a man being voted on to be a deacon,
and he stood up and he made this comment, he said, you know, all my life I was attaining
to be a deacon.
I thought if I could just be a deacon, it was some prominent position within the church.
You know what I've learned?
I've learned that being a deacon is a servant, it's a minister.
That's what it is.
But there are qualifications for the one that has the office of a deacon.
Notice in verse number 8, likewise must the deacons be grave, not double-tongued.
By the way, that's an interesting phrase that we see much in our society today where somebody
says one thing to one person and another thing to another person with regard to deceiving
and what have you.
Not to be double-tongued, not given to much wine, not greedy of filthy lucre.
It says of the pastor and also the deacon not to be greedy of filthy lucre, not to be
covetous.
And I've said often over the years, I don't do what I do for money.
You know, there are a lot of televangelists and big-name preachers in America today that
bring a bad name on all pastors, they really do, flying around in $50 million jets and
all this crazy stuff and what have you.
I mean, it's insane, not greedy of filthy lucre.
Notice holding the mystery of the faith in a pure conscience and let these also first
be proved.
Remember it said of a pastor not to be a novice, here it says of a deacon that they must first
Then let them use, again we see the phrase in verse number 10, the office of a deacon
being found blameless.
Even so must their wives be grave, not slanderer, sober, faithful in all things.
Let the deacons be the husbands of one wife, ruling their children, their own houses well.
For they that have used, again notice the office of a deacon well, purchased to themselves
a good degree and great boldness in the faith which is in Christ Jesus.
To be that servant, to be that minister, that deacon.
I'm thankful for the deacons that we have in our church.
There are some that believe that you must have deacons in order to be an established
New Testament church, but I would say it this way, if you don't have qualified men to be
a deacon, that you leave the office vacant.
It would be better to have the office vacant than to fill the office with someone who's
not qualified, amen?
And we find here this morning, it's very similar, in Acts chapter number 6, hold your place
here in 1 Timothy, but turn back to Acts 6 if you will, and we find that in Acts chapter
number 6, there's a situation.
that happens. Now, the word deacon is not used here. There are some that would argue
over Acts chapter number 6, whether it's the first deacons or not. But as we look at Acts
chapter number 6, it fits the context of understanding the responsibility in the office of a deacon.
And we look here in Acts chapter number 6. I've often said over the years, and it's a
good rule of practice, that you do not build doctrine from the book of Acts. The book of
Acts is a transitional book, okay? And in the early church in the first century, there
was a lot of transition that's taking place. You don't necessarily build doctrine from
the book of Acts, but as the Bible is continuing to be written and the instruction is given
to the local church, such as we find in 1 Timothy, as we're studying through this book,
we can go back to the book of Acts and see, as the instruction is provided and doctrine
is being built, how it's applied in the book of Acts. In Acts 6, it says, and in those
days, in verse number 1, and in those days when the number of the disciples was multiplied,
by the way, the church was growing, praise the Lord for that, there arose a murmuring
of the Grecians against the Hebrews. You know what? When a church grows, sometimes there
are problems. Hallelujah. You ever hear somebody say, growing pains? It happens. You know why?
Because not everyone that's going to be added to a church is going to come from the same
background that you've came from. Listen, it's a good thing when people visit church
that are lost. Amen? Not everybody that walks through that door is going to look like you
and talk like you and sound like you, but they need the truth of the gospel. They need
a church family, a church home. Amen? It says, because their widows were neglected of the
daily ministration, then the twelve called the multitude of the disciples unto them and
said, it is not reason that we should leave the word of God and serve tables. It wasn't
so much that the church leadership, the pastor here, thought that they could, like, it's
beneath me to serve tables. No, it was that I have a responsibility to feed the flock
of God, to pray and to minister in the word, and if I'm cutting grass and serving tables
and mopping floors and changing this, then I'm not able to do what God has entrusted
me to do. Does that make sense? It doesn't mean that the pastor, listen, there was a
mess over in the fellowship hall on Sunday morning, Easter Sunday. We had the breakfast.
I walked through there. Some of you, I didn't do it so that somebody could see me, but there's
a mess. I went and got a broom and I was sweeping it up. Some of you saw me do it. I didn't
do it so that you would see me. It's not beneath me. The reality, though, is I've got to stand
behind this pulpit and feed the church of God. And so the leadership says it's not for
us to leave the word of God and serve tables. There's only so much time that an individual
has, so I've got to understand what my calling is.
Wherefore, brethren, look ye out among you seven men of honest report. First let them
be proved. You saw that in 1st Timothy chapter 3. It says this, full of the Holy Ghost and
wisdom whom we may appoint over this business, but we will give ourselves continually to
prayer and to the ministry of the word. We find that the Bible says the saying pleased
the whole multitude and they chose Stephen, a man full of faith and of the Holy Ghost
and Philip and Proctorius and Nicanor and Timon and Parmenas and Nicholas, a proselyte
of Antioch, whom they set before the apostles and when they had prayed they laid their hands
on them and the word of God increased and the number of the disciples multiplied in
Jerusalem greatly and in great company the priests were obedient to the faith. Hallelujah.
You know what God did in Acts chapter number 6? He gave them direction for dealing with
this situation in the local church and then in the book of 1st Timothy, we find in the
book of Titus with regard to the pastor, but in the book of 1st Timothy with regard to
the deacon, he gives the instruction with regard to the office of a deacon. Why is
this important? Why do we spend a Sunday morning dealing with this passage of scripture? Well,
it's God's word and it's God's church and we must understand this morning that behavior
in God's church is important and we must behave appropriately. It's important that every local
church understands the leadership structure that God has ordained and that we adhere to
the leadership standards of conduct that are set forth in His word. It's absolutely imperative.
I am thankful. Again, I say this often, it's changing over the years because I'm getting
older just like you are, but I'm still a young man. But the reality is that I won't be here
forever. This is the way it is. I won't be here forever. And if I'm not here in this
position of a pastor and the Lord hasn't come back yet for a church, it'd be fine with
me if He came back while I'm still the pastor and we're all just raptured out of here. But
if I die before the rapture, if God moves me, whatever the case might be, I'm not the
pastor here anymore, guess what Fellowship Baptist Church has to do? They have to find
a new pastor. And guess what you need to do? You need to follow the biblical standards
that are set forth. Why? Because it's God's church. Amen? And God's church must be run.
It must follow what God has instituted in His word, the instruction that He's given.
It's God's church. He alone has the right to establish the standards of conduct that
must be upheld to qualify for said office. Well, so-and-so's a really good guy. I mean,
maybe they should be a deacon. Did you see a good guy in there? I'm not saying that they're
not a good guy. You have to be qualified biblically. Amen? The candidate of an office must be qualified
biblically before ever assuming the position of leadership within God's church. It'd be
a silly thing for someone to assume a position of leadership knowing that they've not qualified
biblically. By the way, can I say this this morning? He said, if a man desire the office
of a bishop, he desires a good work, an honorable work. Can I tell you my experience when God
was calling me to be a pastor? I'd rather not. Just being honest with you. So God, somebody
else can do that. I can serve in whatever other capacity. I was afraid. But I also understand
the weight, the responsibility. You know what the Bible says in the book of Hebrews? It's
not a qualification. It gives us some insight to the duty of the pastor. He watches for
your souls. That is a weighty responsibility. It truly is. And so we find here that as God
calls and God equips that the man that would fill the position must be qualified. He must
adhere to the standards that are set forth, the standards of conduct. Furthermore, it's
important to understand that the individual that's in an office must remain qualified
lest they be removed from the office. Just because someone is a pastor doesn't mean they
should always be a pastor. You know, there's behavior that can disqualify a man from being
in the position of being a pastor or a deacon. There's behavior that can disqualify. Does
it mean he's not a Christian anymore? No. Does it mean that he can't serve God in some
capacity anymore? No. It just simply means that he's not qualified for those two offices.
Does that make sense this morning? And we still give an opportunity to serve, to be
used of God. Listen, as a local church, we believe and we teach and we practice that
our God is a forgiving God. And we understand restitution and reconciliation and what a
blessing that is. We've often said, as I even sat on an ordination council not long ago,
listen, church discipline, the idea of church discipline is not excommunication, but what?
It's that we would restore such in one. Restoration. But someone that's committed certain things,
behaved in certain manners, though they may still be used of the Lord, they may not qualify
for the office of a bishop or the office of a deacon. God's church, behavior in God's
church. Why does God outline all of these things? Well, because it's his church and
he can. And he says, here's how I want my church to function. Here's how I want the
leadership in my church to function. If you start a business, you know what you get to
do? You get to establish the organization chart. You do. You say, my name's going to
be at the top. Good luck. Everyone wants it until they get it. But what I say this
morning is that God instituted the church and he instructed the church and he said,
here are the two offices and here are the requirements for an individual, a man to fill
either office. And it's imperative that we do God's work God's way. Wouldn't it be a
shame to think that this is God's church or to know that this is God's church and then
to ignore the teaching that he gives with regard to leadership qualifications and determine
that we're just going to do things our own way and then we lose God's favor. Don't we
want God's favor? I want God's favor, personally and corporately. And so, if God has instructed
us on how we're to be organized and what the offices are and who the individual that would
fill that office must meet a standard of conduct qualifications, we must know it and we must
adhere to it. Behavior in God's church. Let's pray. Father, we love you. We thank you for
loving us. We thank you for your word. This morning we deal with maybe some technical
type of things.
But God, I pray that you'd help us to be sound in the faith, that we'd have an understanding
why we function the way that we do.
Why do we have a pastor?
Why do we have deacons?
Why are there qualifications?
Why does it even matter?
Lord, I pray that we'd be settled and ground in the faith, that we would be able to give
an answer as to why church leadership is functioning the way that it is.
God, I pray that you'd help us to walk worthy.
Lord, help us to please you and to honor you and to glorify you.
God, it is my desire that Fellowship Baptist Church would be used to be a lighthouse in
our community.
God, we see souls saved, lives changed.
God, that we would have your favor, your blessings upon us.
Father, I pray that if there's one not sure of heaven, we sang that song to start the
service this morning, are you saved?
Are you washed in the blood, saved by the blood of Christ?
Or if there's one that's not sure of heaven, I pray that today, Lord, they'd trust Christ
as their Savior.
Or maybe some that just need to thank God.
Thank you, Lord, for the structure that you've provided.
Lord, I pray that in this moment of invitation, you'd have your will in way, that you'd work
as only you can, that we'd thank you, Lord, for providing us with the guidance and the
leadership, that you did not leave this for us to figure out on our own.
We thank you for the instruction.
We pray that you'd help us to adhere to it.
And we'll thank you for what you'll do, for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano.
Maybe you want to come and just thank God this morning for the leadership, the direction
that He gives us in His Word.
Maybe this morning God has spoken to your heart through some other way.
Maybe you're not sure of heaven.
We'd love to take a Bible and show you how you can know for sure that heaven is your
home.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.