We're not going to get real far just looking at the first verse, in fact, this evening,
and I'll be dealing with the full content of Genesis 19 in our next study with regard
to the destruction, of course, of Sodom and Gomorrah and all that was taking place there.
But I want to note, as we really look at the introduction to this particular chapter, and
I want to take note of the life of Lot, and I hope that it would serve as a warning to
each of us that are here this evening, those that are watching via live stream, as we would
note the progression of Lot in his life.
And of course, as we understand even in the 19th chapter, some of the information that
is given to us with regard to Lot, and look at verse number one, if you will, Luke, excuse
me, Genesis 19, verse number one, the Bible says, and there came two angels to Sodom at
Even.
These are the two, of course, that had been there with Abraham back in chapter 18.
We studied on two Sunday evenings through Genesis chapter 18, and we made note of the
ministry of Abraham as he met these that came, and of course, the Lord being one of them
and these two angels.
And then we took note as to the interaction and the discussion that took place, the intercession
of Abraham as he prayed to the Lord with regard to the total destruction of Sodom and Gomorrah
because of their wickedness and their sin, as God announced was very grievous, according
to verse number 20 of Genesis 18.
The Bible says that these two angels, they came to Sodom at Even, and it says this, and
Lot sat in the gate of Sodom, and Lot, seeing them, rose up to meet them, and he bowed himself
with his face toward the ground.
You'll remember that as we looked at chapter number 18 that the two angels left from the
presence of Abraham, but the Lord God Almighty stayed there, and Abraham drew near.
If you look in verse number 21 of chapter 18, it says, I will go down now and see whether
they have done all together according to the cry of it which has come unto me, and if not,
I will know.
And the men turned their faces from thence and went toward Sodom, the two angels.
It says, but Abraham yet stood, excuse me, stood yet before the Lord, and Abraham drew
near and said, wilt thou also destroy the righteous with the wicked?
And then the progression from 50 all the way down to 10, and you see in verse number 33
of chapter 18, the Bible says the Lord went his way as soon as he had left communing with
Abraham and Abraham returned unto his place.
And so we see that while Abraham is interceding, while Abraham is speaking to the Lord, in
verses 23 through 32, we find that really the event in verse number 1 of chapter 19
is taking place where those two angels, they come to Sodom at even.
And we make note of the statement when it says that Lot sat in the gate of Sodom, and
that will be the title for the message this evening, Lot sat in the gate of Sodom.
I remember that while I was in Bible college and we had a professor, I don't remember which
one it was, but one of our professors, he would say often with regard to sin that it
will keep you longer than you want to stay.
That sin will take you further than you want to go, and that sin will cost you more than
you want to pay.
And I always thought that was interesting that this particular professor would use that
phraseology and that quote, if you will, and it reminded us of that and about the importance
of God's people walking in holiness as obedient children unto our Heavenly Father.
And as we look at the Word of God, we understand that there is an influence here in the life
of Lot, and we'll note the progression as we go through the message this evening.
But I want you to think about a couple of New Testament principles.
Hold your place here in Genesis 19.
I want you to turn to the book of Hebrews in chapter number 3, and then we'll go back
to 1 Corinthians just for a moment.
And I want to mention these two principles from the New Testament as we begin our study
this evening.
In Hebrews chapter number 3, note what the Word of God says.
Of course, in this particular text of Scripture, in verse number 8, the Word of God says,
"...hardened not your hearts in the day of provocation, in the day of temptation, in
the wilderness," and speaking about that hardened heart and what have you.
We come to verse number 12, it says, "...take heed, brethren, lest there be any of you an
evil heart of unbelief and departing from the living God.
But exhort one another daily while it is called today, lest any of you be hardened through
the deceitfulness of sin."
One thing that the Bible teaches us about sin is the deceitfulness of sin.
We speak about being deceived, and we understand what it means to be deceived, and we've been
deceived no doubt in our lives at some point.
We think about the way in which others could deceive us.
We are aware of self-deception, where we could deceive ourselves.
We think about this deceitfulness of sin, and the reality is that there are times in
which individuals would engage in sinful behavior, and they would be deceived in thinking that
they have some level of control over that which they're doing, perhaps even over the
consequences in which they will endure.
The reality is that sin is deceitful, and it reminds me again, I'll say it, what that
professor said to us on a number of occasions, sin will keep you longer than you want to
stay.
It will take you further than you want to go, and it will cost you more than you want
to pay.
When we think about this truth, the deceitfulness of sin, notice over the book of 1 Corinthians
chapter 15, and I want you to note verse number 33, as we use these principles as we dive
into the text of Scripture there, and thinking about Lot, and learning from his life, hopefully
a valuable lesson for us.
In 1 Corinthians 15 and verse number 33, notice what the Bible says, be not deceived.
That's interesting, is it not?
We just talked about the deceitfulness of sin, and now we see that the Word of God says,
be not deceived.
So, therefore, we understand that what God is preparing to tell us here is given the
introductory thought of be not deceived.
Why?
Because we can be deceived with this thought.
And therefore, be not deceived, notice what he says, evil communications corrupt good
manners.
How many of you ever had your mom tell you when you were growing up that the bad apple
is always going to spoil the good apples, right?
You've heard it so many times as children, you heard it, maybe you've said it to your
children, and the idea is that you don't want to be around that bad apple because the bad
apple is going to spoil the good apples.
And here the Word of God says, evil communications corrupt good manners.
Be not deceived, evil communications corrupt good manners.
Oh, well, I can go over here and I can be with this group of people, and I will influence
them.
Be not deceived, evil communications corrupt good manners.
There's more than one person that has lived and walked upon the face of this earth that
thought that they could put themselves into a group of people that were evil people, that
were wicked people, ungodly people, and that they would be able to influence them to be
good.
And yet, evil communications corrupt good manners.
And we understand that principle.
We've lived, many of us, long enough in life to understand how that works and to see how
that works out in life.
I believe that as we look at the life of Lot back in Genesis 19, and really we're going
to look at a few chapters preceding Genesis 19, I want you to note back, if you will,
to Genesis chapter number 13.
This is where it really began in the life of Lot with regard to his demise, if you will,
to his downward spiral.
We note the progression in his life.
In Genesis chapter number 13, remember there was the strife between the herdmen of Abram
and the herdmen of Lot's cattle, according to verse number 7, and Abram gave Lot the
option of picking the land.
The Bible tells us in verse number 12, Abram dwelt in the land of Canaan, and Lot dwelt
in the cities of the plain, and pitched his tent toward Sodom.
So we see, initially, if we were to consider the progression of Lot and to see where he
ends up in chapter 19, that it begins here in chapter 13, where he simply pitched his
tent toward Sodom.
He wasn't all the way in Sodom yet.
He wasn't living among them, but he faced his tent.
He pitched his tent toward Sodom.
The Bible tells us in verse number 13 of Genesis 13, but the men of Sodom were wicked and sinners
before the Lord exceedingly.
Yet we find that Lot pitched his tent toward Sodom.
Now there are some things that we understand about Lot, and we'll look at it more even
next week as we study the entirety of chapter 19, but when you look at the life of Lot and
you look at the unfortunate set of circumstances with regard to his family, and really the
way that he lost his family, and all of the things that go on, I don't think that here
in Genesis chapter 13, when he pitched his tent toward Sodom, that he ever thought that
would be the end.
We don't we don't think that way right? I don't think that lot said, you know, I'm gonna offer my children
I'm gonna let them go and live wicked ungodly lifestyles
And and these are going to be the actions that my children are gonna be known for
And and I I know that's gonna happen, but I'm gonna pitch my tent towards Sodom anyway now
Wasn't what he planned to happen
But he pitched his tent towards Sodom chapter 13 and verses 12 notice in chapter number 14
in chapter number 14
The battle is recorded here
of course Abram goes and delivers Sodom and
Lot and all of those that were dwelling there in that particular land
But I want you to notice in verse number 11 of Genesis 14
The Bible says and they took all the goods of Sodom and Gomorrah and went all their vittles and went their way
Notice verse number 12 and they took lot
Abram's brother's son
who dwelt in Sodom and
his goods and
departed in
chapter number 13 he pitched his tent towards Sodom in
Chapter number 14 the Bible tells us that he dwelt in Sodom
There's a progression, right?
He's no longer
There in the plain that's well watered and just simply looking toward Sodom
But now according to Genesis chapter number 14 he dwelt in
Sodom
And then of course we come to our text this evening in Genesis 19 in verse number 1 where the Bible says that lot sat
in the gate of
Sodom he wasn't just living in a wicked community. He wasn't just living in a wicked
City, but he was actually in a place a prominent position of leadership
Even within that city thus sitting in the gate of the city Wow
What a progression
It's true that we're in the world, but we're not of the world
In fact in John 17 in verse number 15 when Jesus is praying before he would go to the cross of Calvary
He asked the Lord to keep us his people keep them from the evil. We live in an evil world
We live in a wicked world
And we live in a world that does not
follow
Biblical teaching with regard to morality with regard to behavior that is acceptable to God
It's interesting if you were to consider the verbiage that the New Testament uses in describing lot
If you want to jot it down in 2nd Peter chapter 2
verses 7 and 8
The Bible says this and delivered just lot
vexed with the filthy
conversation of the wicked
For that righteous man it then says this dwelling
among them in
seeing and hearing
vexed his righteous soul from day to day with their unlawful deeds
See
Lot made a decision in Genesis chapter number 13
The decision he made was that he was gonna pitch his tent
towards Sodom
And by the time you come to Genesis chapter number 14, he's dwelling in Sodom
By the time you come to Genesis chapter number 19, he's sitting in the gate of Sodom you see the progression
It's easy for us to note it in these few chapters and just looking at these few phrases of Scripture
I believe this evening that the enemy continues to work in the lives of the people of God and I believe that even as he worked
in the life of lot and seeking to do this very thing and that is this to
desensitize
the people of God to sin
To desensitize us to just kind of get used to it
No longer seeing sin for as wicked and ungodly as it really is
See as lot if you can imagine your mind this evening as he would pitch his tent towards Sodom and the Bible tells us that
These people were wicked
people
Grievous sinners and
Lot according to what Peter says in 2nd Peter chapter 2
Seeing and hearing vexed his righteous soul from day to day with their unlawful deeds
and you believe as you look at the progression to begin to see how that he would be
desensitized to wickedness
And no longer has that
appalling response that maybe at once did I
Don't know in your life if you can evaluate and identify
Maybe how that you've become desensitized to sin
How that living in this fallen world?
We've just kind of gotten comfortable with some things that are going on around us
We begin to hear some things we begin to see some things and we begin to just get desensitized to it. We're not as
Maybe it's not as appalling to us as it once was
Maybe that thing that we saw maybe that thing that we heard
We've just heard it so many times. We've seen it so often. It's just we've just become desensitized to it. You understand
It's a danger
Because sin is wicked. It's ungodly and
we as God's people are called to be holy and
Here's what happens
Think about this just from when I was meditating upon this this week
When you read Genesis chapter 19 and you look at all of it and you see
Lot
You see his family
He's the nephew of Abraham. I
Mean think about that
Abraham we hold Abraham in high regard
and you think about the
the influence of Abraham and you think about the the position of Abraham in the Word of God and
his faith
But lot made a decision and
Lot pitched his tent towards Sodom and before too long. He was desensitized to wickedness to sin
He lost his family
It's a sad sad truth as we study through this 19th chapter
As you begin to read and understand all that takes place
Remember he goes to talk after he hears about the destruction that's coming
He goes to talk to his children and they don't even listen to him
They're not gonna listen to him
they become desensitized and
What lot had allowed in his life what what he had?
Just accepted as being
Allowable you start seeing that others begin to practice that immoral behavior
Read the end of Genesis 19. We'll look at it next week. Oh, man, it's terrible. What happens?
with the daughters of lot
But you think about this
Truth this evening. I wonder
How is the enemy trying to desensitize us?
Maybe I should ask it this way first is the enemy trying to desensitize us
Do you think the enemy is trying to desensitize you to sin?
You look at the morals of our society
Have they not gone in an extremely downward spiral in the last 50 years in this nation alone?
Have they I mean sure
You see the downward spiral the
Immorality that is so prevalent in our society today in our culture today in which people just accept it as being well
That just happens
Right. I mean honestly, let's just be transparent this evening. It's all around us and listen
I'm not suggesting this evening that we need to go attack every individual that's living in some sort of sin
Misunderstand what I'm saying, but we need to be careful not to be desensitized to the the sinfulness of sin
That we're not deceived by it that our children understand that sin is is a reproach against the Holy God and
That we're not seeking to be desensitized to it that we still have
That response that sin is appalling to us that when we see or observe certain things that we say look at we're not gonna watch
That we're not gonna listen to that. We're not gonna allow that why because it's wicked. It's ungodly
I don't want to become
desensitized to that
Does that make sense this evening?
Because we get desensitized to it and before long what happened to say? Hey, did you hear what they just said?
I mean, I don't even know what they just said
Why because we just hear it so often. Did you see that? No, did I see what?
You
Didn't see that over there. Whatever that is. Whatever is being referred to. Well, you just see it so often
You just become so desensitized to it
We think about this
progression in the the life of lot
And we're gonna study chapter 19 next week
But I want to take you to a different passage this evening
And I want to share with you some things about King a has look at 2nd Chronicles chapter 28
2nd Chronicles chapter 28 now, I'm just gonna pick through a few of these verses this evening
To kind of illustrate the point if you will in in someone else's life
of this desensitizing to sin and sin keeping you longer than you want to stay taking you further you want to go and
Costing you more than you want to pay
As you think about King a has some of you
Immediately would be familiar with the wickedness of this man through your own Bible study
study and reading of the Scriptures,
and this is that King Ahaz,
the Word of God says about him,
and he's wicked.
But before we jump into chapter 28
of 2 Chronicles and look at some things
in the life of King Ahaz,
I want you to understand that he was
the son of Jotham
and the grandson of Uzziah.
You say, ok, what does that mean?
Well, these guys, Jotham and Uzziah,
we find that Uzziah in particular,
he was a man that God used in a great way.
The Bible says that God helped him.
God used him.
God strengthened him.
The Bible says of Uzziah
that he was marvelously helped.
We understand that in the life of Uzziah,
he goes in to offer incense
and he's smitten because of that
and he becomes a leper.
We understand that,
but Uzziah would basically be counted
as being a good king.
He's the grandfather of this man Ahaz.
Jotham, in chapter 27 of 2 Chronicles 27,
the Bible says of this man Jotham,
the father of Ahaz in verse 2,
it says he did that which was right
in the sight of the Lord
according to all that his father Uzziah did.
Howbeit, he entered not into the temple
of the Lord and the people did yet corruptly.
It's interesting in verse 2 of 2 Chronicles 27,
the Bible tells us about Jotham
that he was a man that was a good king.
He obeyed the Lord.
In fact, he learned a very valuable lesson
from his father entering into the temple
and offering that incense.
And this man Jotham did not enter into the temple.
He understood that there was a role for the king
and there was a role for the priest.
But this man Ahaz,
his father is Jotham.
His grandfather is Uzziah.
But yet the Bible says in verse 1 of 2 Chronicles 28,
Ahaz was 20 years old when he began to reign,
and he reigned 16 years in Jerusalem.
Notice what it says,
but he did not that which was right
in the sight of the Lord like David his father.
For he walked in the ways of the kings of Israel
and made also molten images for Balaam.
We're going to read some more about Ahaz here in just a moment.
But you understand that in the life of this man Ahaz,
though he had a godly heritage,
he had some decisions he had to make for himself.
He had to make a determination of how he was going to live
before the Lord God Almighty.
And we find that this man Ahaz,
he followed in the ways of the kings of Israel,
often as there would be a reference in the Word of God
to the ways of Jeroboam.
I'm not sure why I said Jehoshaphat.
Jeroboam.
And they would walk in the ways of Jeroboam.
And the reality is that here,
you find that it just simply says
in the ways of the kings of Israel.
If you were to understand the nation of Israel
as a united kingdom,
and then after the reign of course of Solomon
as a divided kingdom,
Israel referring to the ten tribes of the north,
and then Judah the two tribes of the south,
and you would find of those ten tribes of the north,
the nation of Israel as we'd often refer to it as,
they were taken captive by the Assyrians,
but if you were to trace their heritage
and you were to look at all of their kings,
there's not one good king.
They're all wicked.
It's an immediate downward spiral.
You find that within the ranks of the kings of Judah,
that there were periods of revival.
There were good kings and there were bad kings.
And you see that process.
And here we find that Ahaz is one of those bad kings.
He's one of those that would follow
in the ways of the kings of Israel.
As we begin to think about the slippery slope of sin,
if you will,
the Bible tells us that he really had ungodly influences
according to v. 2 when it says that he walked
in the ways of the kings of Israel.
What are some of the things that this man Ahaz did?
In v. 2 it says that he had idols.
He made also molten images for Balaam.
It tells us in v. 3,
moreover he burnt incense
in the valley of the son of Hinnom
and burnt his children in the fire.
Did you catch that?
He burnt his children in the fire.
You know the Word of God warns
about offering your children to Molech?
And yet we find that Ahaz,
as he would get wrapped up in this idolatry
as he would be influenced by these ungodly influences,
and he's burning incense to idols,
and now you find that he's offered his children,
it says, and burnt his children in the fire
after the abominations of the heathen
whom the Lord had cast out
before the children of Israel.
V. 4, he sacrificed also and burnt incense
in the high places and on the hills
and under every green tree.
Wherefore, the Lord his God delivered him
into the hand of the king of Syria.
Isn't that interesting verbiage?
Often we like to hear how God delivers us
from something,
but yet because of the wickedness of Ahaz,
the Bible tells us that God delivered him
into the hand of the enemy.
The king of Syria.
And they smote him
and carried away a great multitude of them captives
and brought them to Damascus.
And he was also delivered into the hand
of the king of Israel
who smote him with a great slaughter.
Wow.
You think about the negative influences and impact.
I don't believe as you look at chapter 28 here
of 2 Chronicles that Ahaz had anticipated
that this would be the result of his behavior.
He was participating in this wicked behavior
and he was doing these wicked things
and we find that he paid a great price,
that he suffered greatly.
He was deceived by sin.
We noted in v. 5 the way that he was dealing
with being delivered into the hand of the enemy.
Notice in v. 19, if you will, skip down
and look at v. 19, it says,
for the Lord brought Judah low
because of Ahaz king of Israel,
for he made Judah naked
and transgressed sore against the Lord.
When you look at the passage here
and you begin to think about how the Lord
brought Judah low,
and it says in v. 20,
until Gath-Pilneser king of Assyria
came unto him and distressed him,
but strengthened him not.
If you look previous in the passage,
we don't have time to deal with it,
but he actually offered to have these guys
come and help him.
It says that they helped him not.
They strengthened him not.
Notice v. 21, the last phrase,
but he helped him not.
Notice v. 22, in the time of his distress,
did he trespass yet more against the Lord.
This is that king Ahaz.
For he sacrificed unto the gods of Damascus
which smote him.
Notice this.
And he said,
because the gods of the kings of Syria
helped them,
therefore will I sacrifice to them
that they may help me.
But they were the ruin of him
and of all Israel.
Now, did you catch v. 23?
Notice what it says.
This man Ahaz,
he sacrificed unto the gods of Damascus.
Now, those are false gods.
Those are idols, right?
So he's offering these sacrifices
unto these idols,
and it says which smote him.
And so he suffered at the hand
of the people of Damascus,
and so he's going to make these offerings
unto these false gods, these idols.
And his logic, his reasoning
for making these sacrifices
was because the kings,
excuse me, because the gods,
these false gods, these false idols
of the kings of Syria helped them.
And so I was defeated by these guys,
and they served these false gods,
and they have these idols that they worship,
and so their idols evidently helped them,
so now I'm going to go offer sacrifices
to these idols
because those idols helped them,
so maybe they'll help me.
He says, therefore, will I sacrifice to them.
Now, does that make your head hurt?
I mean, honestly,
when you read that,
and you understand who his father
and his grandfather were,
when you understand the responsibility
that he had as serving as a king
under the Lord God Almighty,
and in the book of Deuteronomy,
the kings had been instructed
that if they were to write out
the law of the Lord,
and they were to read it
and to be engaged in it and to know it,
in what's one of the commandments,
thou shalt have no other gods before Me.
Amen?
I mean, listen, he's literally...
You tell me that sin's not deceptive?
The deceitfulness of sin?
He's now offering sacrifices
to these false gods, to these idols,
because he says, well, the idols helped them,
so therefore, I'm going to sacrifice to them.
Really?
Therefore, will I sacrifice to them
that they may help me.
Messed up.
You say, oh, pastor, you're being...
It's not gonna happen like that in my life.
Do you think Ahaz planned for that
to happen in his life?
Do you think Lot planned for it
to happen in his life the way that it did?
I mean, we can go through a whole number
of illustrations.
In fact, there are people
that have written books.
that have given testimony of the deceitfulness of sin in their own lives and how they began
being engaged in activities that they never planned to participate in.
Sin is deceptive.
Don't you think we're being a little overzealous here?
No, I don't think Ahaz planned that this was going to happen.
Young people begin to play around with sin a little bit, think they can get away with
this and get away with that and let's participate in this and let's do that.
Oh, sin is deceitful.
But sometimes we just think about young people doing that.
Listen, sin is deceptive for all people.
The devil's trying to get you in a trap, deceive you.
He's trying to get you to be desensitized.
The thing that comes up on the internet when you're searching for something that is supposed
to be wholesome or good, and the enemy allows that thing to come up, you begin to get desensitized
to it because you've seen it and you've seen it and you look at it and you look at it.
You know, pornography is a big problem in America, huge issue.
It's amazing, it used to be something that predominantly affected males, but there are
studies that suggest almost as many females are caught up in pornography as are males.
You say, I don't believe it.
You just go look at the studies yourself then.
Sad.
I worked with a man at this point, probably 20 years ago, 19 years ago.
The man got desensitized to images on his computer.
I really didn't know the man well, but I know the story well.
He was a schoolteacher at a public school and he got desensitized because a deacon in
a church is a public schoolteacher, and he got desensitized.
And then he began to have an appetite for that stuff.
And then he had to start using the computers at school because he didn't want his wife
to find out.
Well, then there were some people in the school that had some IT experience and knew what
was going on and he got fired, he lost his job.
It was found out, terrible, terrible consequences for him.
That man came and worked for our company for one day.
I had jury duty that day and my boss had an exam in his master's class.
It was just a small office, we only had four people, the other two were out of the office
that day, and this man came to work for our company one day, and all he did for the four
hours he was there was search pornography and destroy our whole system.
It just destroyed him.
What I'm saying this evening is that that man never set out to lose his wife, his career,
his family, his children.
The devil wants to desensitize us.
He wants to think that we can handle it, that we can control it, but sin is deceitful
and it's destructive.
You find here at the end of verse number 23 in 2 Chronicles 28 it says,
But they were the ruin of him and of all Israel, and Ahaz gathered together the vessels of
the house of God, and cut in pieces the vessels of the house of God, and shut up the doors
of the house of the Lord, and he made them altars in every corner of Jerusalem.
Not only did he worship these false gods and sacrifice and make offerings to these false
gods, but the Bible says that he took all the vessels of the house of God and he cut
the pieces of the vessels of the house of God.
He shut the doors for the house of the Lord.
I mean, it wasn't that he had gone far enough that he's just worshiping and sacrificing
these idols, but he's ensuring that there's not going to be any worship of Jehovah either.
And it says that he made him altars in every corner of Jerusalem at the end of verse 24
and verse 25.
And in every several city of Judah he made high places to burn incense unto other gods
and provoked to anger the Lord God of his fathers.
It's amazing that Hezekiah would be the son of Ahaz and that Hezekiah would be a good
king.
I mean, there'd be a revival in Judah under the reign of Hezekiah.
But as we begin to look and to really consider this evening of this thought in Genesis 19
and verse number 1, that this man Lot, he sat in the gate of Sodom.
I want to remind you of Psalm 1.
The Bible says this in Psalm chapter number 1, blessed is the man that walketh not in
the counsel of the ungodly, nor standeth in the way of sinners, nor sitteth in the seat
of the scornful.
And this evening, as God's people, I hope that we would understand the importance of
godly living.
Listen, we can live right in a wrong world.
We can.
We can live right in a wrong world.
We can obey God and serve God acceptably.
And we can, you know, somebody said this, I think it was actually Brother Mershawn said
this, it seems as if in America we don't blush at sin anymore.
And you can think about that expression and the verbiage in which Brother Mershawn used
in making that assessment.
But why would it be that in America we don't blush at sin anymore?
Perhaps because we've been desensitized.
It's just become acceptable that this is just the way it is.
I wonder when's the last time we've been able to, parents, sit down with our children
and explain to them why some of the accepted behavior in our society is not accepted by
God Almighty.
Biblically, why this is not approved, why this is not acceptable.
Why we don't support this.
Not suggesting that we go out there and boycott everybody and throw a big fit and have all
these kind of scenes.
No, I'm just saying, are your children being desensitized?
If you're not teaching them why the standards of morals in our society are not accepted
by God, they're being desensitized.
In the classrooms, alternative lifestyles and behaviors, again, I'm not suggesting we
go out there and attack everyone.
I'm just simply saying we can't be desensitized to it.
Because all of a sudden, you're a young person, you're going to come home and think that this
thing is okay, whatever this thing is.
Because it's just another option.
You say, no, here's what God says.
See we've been saved, we've been born again.
We have a higher authority and a higher standard.
Lot, he made a terrible mistake when he pitched his tent towards Sodom.
And it wasn't long before he was dwelling in Sodom.
And then according to verse number one of chapter 19 of Genesis, we find that he's sitting
in the gate of Sodom.
This evening, I believe that each of us would acknowledge that the enemy wants to desensitize
us to sin.
He wants us to think sin is normal and acceptable and it's just another way of doing things.
And I wonder this evening in your life, how is God working in your life, and then how
is the enemy working to desensitize you to sin in your life?
Are we permitting things in our home that maybe just a few years ago we wouldn't have
permitted in our home?
We're permitting things on our TV, we're permitting things in the radio, permitting
things through publications, permitting things through video games.
What are we permitting that's desensitizing us to sin?
And what we permit, unfortunately, we're going to begin to accept.
Unfortunately, you're going to see some people doing some things, perhaps even our own children
participating in activities and say, why in the world would they do that?
They weren't taught the sinfulness of sin.
They were deceived by it.
They thought it was acceptable.
They thought it was okay.
Next week, we'll study the entirety of Genesis 19, but I thought it important for us to understand
this progression and to be warned against being desensitized to sin in our society.
Because though the world and the enemy want to paint sin as being something glamorous,
it's a reproach against the Holy God.
And we need to understand that as the people of God.
So no, I don't want to be desensitized to this stuff.
I don't want to get on that slippery slope of sin.
I don't want to come to a place and we say.
Say, how in the world did we get here?
What little things did I allow that opened up the floodgates, if you will, that brought
me to the place where I am now?
It's a much better thing to acknowledge the way in which the enemy is seeking to work
and say, I'm going to stand against that.
I'm going to get into the Word of God and allow the Word of God to get into me, and
I'm going to be careful as to what we will allow in our home, the things that we would
participate and engage in, because I don't want to become desensitized to sin.
Lot sat in the gate, but before he ever sat in the gate, he lived in the city, and before
he ever lived in the city, he pitched his tent toward the city.
We need to be careful what we're allowing in our lives.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the warning from the life of Lot, the life of Ahaz.
God, I pray that this evening you would allow this warning from your Word to help us as
your people.
We know that the enemy would like to desensitize us to sin.
The way in which they would seek to describe the era in which we're living, the things
that they would allow and celebrate and legislate, just because the law of the land would allow
certain behavior doesn't mean it's right.
God, I pray that you'd help us as your people to blush at sin, to guard against the influences
and the deceitfulness of sin in our lives, the lives of our children.
Would you help those that have children at home still to be particularly aware of the
dangers and the influences of the sin and the culture upon their children, that we'd
guard against it, that we might live as obedient children, that we might be holy even as you
are holy in all manner of conversation.
I pray that you'd work in this time of invitation, and we'll thank you for it.
In Christ's name we pray.