Chapter number one this evening,
you're looking at a couple of verses of Scripture here.
First Corinthians chapter number one,
as you're turning there, I would say this evening,
there is little doubt in my mind
that you have experienced conflict in your life.
Do you agree with that?
You've had conflict at some point,
at some level in your life,
you have experienced conflict.
We find that relationships, no doubt,
are an important part of life.
I'm thankful for relationships, it's a blessing.
But at times, relationships can be impacted adversely.
There can be conflict in relationships.
We find that as we begin to think about that subject
this evening and thinking about relationships
and conflict and what have you,
two questions come to my mind,
and one is this, how do we respond to conflict?
And then really a better, more appropriate question
would be how do we resolve conflict?
I have found in life, as we look at the headlines
and the things going on in our society today,
that there is a real lack of ability
on the part of this generation to resolve conflict.
And our conflict resolution skills are lacking,
if I could put it that way, this evening.
And we find that as we think about that truth
and the inability for so many to resolve conflict,
we would find that that's not really something new
for this generation.
The problem that all of us have when we deal with conflict
is the old man, the flesh.
And the flesh can be revived very quickly,
and the flesh has its own desires
and has its own just way of dealing with things.
And that's why it's so important
that we understand the truth,
that God tells us that we are to crucify our flesh,
we are to mortify our members,
is what we read in the book of Colossians.
We find that the Bible promises us
that if we walk in the spirit,
we shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
And I'm so thankful for the ability,
the opportunity that we have as the people of God
to walk in the spirit.
And what a blessing that God has given us that opportunity.
As you begin to read the book of 1 Corinthians,
this book, we find it is written to a local church.
We find that there's conflict within this local church.
There are many words that we've used
to describe the church in Corinth.
And we find that as you study through the book,
you'll find a number of the issues
in which they're dealing with.
Some of the problems that are in Corinth,
there's spiritual immaturity that is there,
there's division and contention,
there's jealousy, there's envy.
We find that there's legal issues that are dealt with,
there are marital issues that are dealt with.
I mean, you just start talking about a church
that has problems.
The church at Corinth is a church that has problems.
But you know why it's a church that has problems?
Because it has people.
Has people.
And all those people come from a different background.
All those people have different backgrounds
as they come together.
What is the bond that joins us as Christ?
And we are thankful for that bond that we have in Christ.
But the reality is that we all have different personalities
and different backgrounds and ways of thinking
and operating and so on and so forth.
And we find that in Christ,
those things are to be set aside as we strive for unity.
We find that this church here that has the conflict,
we find that it's described in our text of Scripture
in verses 10 and 11 as divisions and contentions.
I find that as we look at this text of Scripture,
look at it with me there in verse number 10,
notice the Apostle Paul gets through
the introductory statements up through verse number nine
and he says this in verse 10.
"'Now I beseech you, brethren,
"'by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ,
"'that you all speak the same thing
"'and that there be no divisions among you,
"'but that you be perfectly joined together
"'in the same mind and in the same judgment.
"'For it hath been declared unto me of you, my brethren,
"'by them which are of the house of Chloe,
"'that there are contentions among you.'"
So we read of divisions and contentions,
thus the title for the message this evening.
As we look at these two verses of Scripture,
we find very quickly,
we discover a couple of important truths.
Number one is that Paul is made aware of the problem.
Notice he says that he's beseeching them
and then he tells them in verse number 11,
"'For it hath been declared unto me of you, my brethren,
"'by them which are of the house of Chloe,
"'that there are contentions among you.'"
And so we find that the Apostle Paul, a spiritual leader,
God used the Apostle Paul to go to the city of Corinth
to see this church established.
God would now use Paul to write this letter back to them.
Of course, 2 Corinthians being written to them as well.
We find that the Apostle Paul has been made aware
of an issue that's taking place at the church at Corinth.
And the reality is that I commend the house of Chloe
for making Paul aware of this situation.
And they no doubt had some concern
with regard to the division and contention.
They were concerned for a measure of unity.
And so Paul was made aware of the problem,
but I'm thankful that as Paul was made aware of the problem
that then Paul addresses the problem.
And we find that he addresses it.
Notice in verse number 11, he says,
"'I beseech you.'"
And he uses this terminology, this verbiage
to show the importance, this call to unity.
He says, "'Brethren, by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ,
"'notice that you all speak the same thing
"'and that there be no divisions among you,
"'but that you be perfectly joined together
"'in the same mind and in the same judgment.'"
He then says at the end of verse number 11,
"'that there are contentions among you.'"
We find that he gives some insight in the next few verses
with regard to the source of some
of this contention and division.
He says, "'Now this I say that every one of you sayeth,
"'I am of Paul, and I have Apollos,
"'and I have Cephas, and I have Christ.
"'Is Christ divided?
"'Was Paul crucified for you?
"'Or were you baptized in the name of Paul?''
As we begin to see, and we're not gonna harp
on that portion too much,
but we see that these things are causing this division.
There's a group of people in the church that's over here
that says, well, we, this group, we associate,
we're identifying, we're of Paul.
And then there's a group over here that says,
well, you guys are of Paul, and that's fine,
but we, we're of Apollos.
We're of Cephas, or Peter.
I'm of Christ.
And you begin to get this division and this contention
and how that they would look down upon one another
and begin to operate.
Obviously, there's spiritual immaturity,
there's carnality that we read of as we continue studying
through the book of 1 Corinthians,
but we find that Paul, he addresses the problem.
He seeks to resolve the problem.
He wants them to understand the importance
of having unity.
The circumstances here in the church at Corinth,
I would say, are unfortunate.
They're unfortunate circumstances,
because what happens is when a church, a family,
any group of people that are in a relationship
have divisions and contentions,
the problem is that we can't go forward
the way that we're supposed to.
The church in Corinth was not able to really do
all that God had commissioned them to do
because of these divisions and these contentions.
By the way, that's the goal of the enemy.
That's the goal of the enemy.
And we find that the circumstances are unfortunate,
yet we find that still today,
churches and families continue with conflict,
and if that conflict is not resolved properly
and biblically, we find that it will lead
to divisions and contentions,
and we find that the flesh will thrive in the,
I mean, it's just a terrible situation.
Look at two verses of Scripture with me,
one in the Old Testament, one in the New.
Look at Psalm 133 and verse number one.
Psalm 133 and verse number one.
Then we'll look over at the New Testament
book of Ephesians.
Then I wanna give you five thoughts this evening,
seeking to be extremely biblical,
and I would say extremely practical this evening.
What do we do when there's conflict?
How do we resolve conflict?
Notice what God says, because God's plan
and God's desire is unity, unity.
By the way, unity is a wonderful thing.
It really is.
If you have a relationship, listen,
husbands and wives, it's a good thing
when you're in unity one with another.
It's not pleasant when there's contention and division.
I mean, I don't like it.
I don't like contention, I don't like division.
I like unity.
I don't like to be in a situation
where there's some relationship in life,
whether it's a work relationship,
whether it's just a relationship in the neighborhood,
maybe it's a church member relationship,
whatever the relationship is,
I don't like it when you are in a situation,
you see somebody and you feel like
you have to try to avoid them.
Why?
Because there's conflict, there's contention,
there's division.
That's not God's intent.
Notice what the Bible says in Psalm 133 and verse number 1.
Behold, how good and how pleasant it is
for brethren to dwell together in unity.
Notice how he describes it as being good and pleasant.
Good and pleasant.
For brethren to dwell together in unity.
Notice what the New Testament says in the book of Ephesians.
I want you to understand there's a great difference when you think about the Old Testament and
think about the children of Israel and all that's taking place there and God giving that
truth to the children of Israel and understanding their situation.
But then when you look at the book of Ephesians, you begin to see, and Paul makes mention of
the mystery of the church and how the church is this organism, it's a living organism,
this organization many have called it.
We think about the church as a body of believers.
The church is not a building.
The building is the place where we meet.
Often we say we're going to church.
But what makes this place church is that the brethren assemble.
We could assemble anywhere and we would say we're having church because the church is
the body of believers that have assembled.
The local church, as we would say fellowship Baptist church, is this group of believers
that have voluntarily, voluntarily, no one forced anyone, by the way if it's forced it's
a problem, it's a voluntarily join themselves together for the purpose of carrying out the
Great Commission.
That's the purpose.
And we find, however, that the church has made up the mystery, that which is being spoken
of, of Jews and Gentiles.
Now I want you to just think about that just for a second.
There's conflict from the start between Jews and Gentiles.
You can read of it in the Scriptures.
You can read and you can understand as you study historically and you look at those historical
writings, you can read of the divisions, the contentions, the conflict, if you will, between
Jews and Gentiles.
To be very plain this evening, the Jews hated the Gentiles.
Just the way it was.
Jesus said, I must needs go through Samaria in John chapter number 4.
That was a problem for many Jewish people because the Samaritans were a hated people.
But Jesus went because they needed the gospel, they needed the truth.
So what was it that would bind, that would be that common bond between Jews and Gentiles
in this thing called the church would be Jesus Christ.
And I'm so thankful that in Christ we are brothers and sisters in Christ.
We have different backgrounds, we have different upbringings, different cultures and manners
and so on and so forth.
But what we have in common is Christ.
And notice what he says in Ephesians 4 in verse number 3.
He says this, endeavoring to keep the unity of the spirit in the bond of peace.
You know, when there's unity, there's peace.
He uses that word endeavoring.
That word endeavor is an interesting word.
It means, it carries with it a few thoughts.
One is to make haste, to be diligent, to labor.
Now think about the context of what we're reading here.
He says endeavoring to keep the unity of the spirit in the bond of peace.
That we are laboring, we are being diligent, we are making haste.
For what purpose?
To have, to keep, to maintain the unity of the spirit.
That God would give us that unity that we were to have.
It's the idea of laboring for something, desiring to have it and being diligent to get it.
Endeavoring.
And God says that should be our approach when it comes to this idea of conflict, here unity.
We're endeavoring for unity, we're striving for it.
So when conflict arises, how do we respond?
What do we do?
Five thoughts this evening, biblical, I believe extremely practical.
Number one, recognize the real enemy.
Recognize the real enemy.
Go over to the book of 1 Peter, if you will, in chapter number five.
I'm going to tell you this evening, this is super practical, super basic truth.
You know sometimes it's the basics that we really need.
In 1 Peter chapter number five, in verse number eight, a verse of scripture that we are familiar
with, the Bible says this, be sober, be vigilant.
Is your adversary the devil?
As a roaring lion walketh about seeking whom he may devour.
Whom resist steadfast in the faith knowing that the same afflictions are accomplished
in your brethren that are in the world.
I believe when conflict would arise in your life or in my life, it's important that first
we recognize who the real enemy is.
The real enemy is Satan.
Husbands, your wife is not your enemy.
Satan is your enemy.
Wives, your husband is not your enemy.
Children, your parents are not your enemy.
Parents, your children are not your enemy, right?
We have an enemy and it's Satan.
Church member, a fellow church member is not your enemy.
Satan is your enemy.
And it is absolutely important for us, I would say it's imperative for us at the time when
conflict would arise, that we take a step back and we recognize, we take the situation
and we say, the enemy is at work here.
And the enemy is not you, the enemy is Satan.
You know what Satan likes to do?
He likes to divide.
You know what Satan is?
He's a liar, the father of it, he's a murderer, deceiver, he's the accuser of the brethren.
He's a defeated foe, but he's active.
And what he wants to do in any local church is he wants to cause conflict between members.
What he wants to do in any home is cause conflict between the members of that home.
Why?
Because he hates everything that God loves.
And he wants there to be conflict because he wants there to be division and contention.
He wants there to be infighting and so many things going internally that we forget about
what God has really instructed us to do.
I believe it's imperative that when we begin to think about the subject of conflict in
your life and in my life, that we must recognize the real enemy and that is Satan.
Number two, we must resist the enemy.
We must resist the devil.
We see in verse number nine, the Bible says, whom resists steadfast in the faith.
Turn to the book of James, if you will.
In the fourth chapter of the book of James, we see again in this portion of Scripture
the importance of resisting the devil.
We understand here that there is a truth that is given that is essential for us to
understand in James 4 and verse number seven, where the Bible begins by saying, submit yourselves
therefore to God.
Submit yourselves therefore to God.
Then after we're submitted to God, he says, resist the devil and he will flee from you.
Isn't that a wonderful promise?
I mean, we sang this morning, standing on the promises.
Oh, there are so many promises and we can thank God for the promises that he's given
us in his word, but this promise right here, when he says, submit yourselves therefore
to God, resist the devil and he will flee from you.
I like that promise.
I'm thankful that God has given us that promise.
We must recognize who the real enemy is.
We must resist the devil.
Look over at the book of Ephesians, if you will, in the fourth chapter.
We started here in chapter three at the endeavoring, excuse me, chapter four, endeavoring to keep
the unity of the spirit in verse number three there.
But we find that as we move forward through the chapter, Ephesians chapter number four,
we find that God continues to give us instruction.
It's interesting what he says, and I'm going to get back to verse number 26 here in just
a moment.
But look, if you will, at verse number 27.
The Bible says this in Ephesians 4 and verse 27, neither give place to the devil.
Neither give place to the devil.
You know, often we talk about the devil having a stronghold.
A preacher said it this way, that really all Satan's looking for is a toehold so they get
a foothold so they can get a stronghold.
And listen, we need to give no place to the devil.
We need to acknowledge who he is.
We need to acknowledge that he is the real enemy.
And when the conflict arises, when something is said, when someone does whatever it might
be, we recognize who the real enemy is and then we resist the enemy.
We say, no, not today, right?
Like get thee behind me, Satan.
I stood out in the foyer this morning and I told that young girl that that's what she
needed to say to Satan because God is true and Satan is a liar.
And when Satan comes and tries to whisper to her that you're really not saved, I said,
You need to believe what God said.
He said that, listen, if you believe that He's the only Savior and that you're a sinner
and you called out to Him for salvation, He promised that He would save you.
So what do you say to the enemy?
Get thee behind me, Satan.
We find this evening when we have conflict in our lives that we have to recognize that
the devil is the real enemy.
He wants you to think that it's your spouse.
He wants you to think it's your child.
He wants you to think it's a fellow church member.
But the reality is that it's the devil, Satan himself, he's the enemy.
He's the accuser of the brethren and we must resist the devil.
I would say this, number three, number three, we must review what we know to be true.
We must review what we know to be true.
What do I mean by that?
Well, I know that Holly loves me.
I know that I love Holly.
So if Holly were to say something to me that I took maybe as being inappropriate, something
that was cutting, I need to review what I know to be true.
I need to review that I know that she loves me.
That changes things.
It helps us in our perspective.
Notice in the book of Philippians, chapter number four, we'll look at a couple of verses
and really they deal with my, these two points, number four, three and four.
But look at the book of Philippians, if you will, in chapter number four, Philippians
chapter number four.
You know, what you know to be true should permeate your mind.
The Bible says in Philippians four and verse number eight, finally brethren, what sort
of things are true?
What sort of things are honest?
What sort of things are just?
What sort of things are pure?
What sort of things are lovely?
What sort of things are of good report?
If there be any virtue and if there be any praise, notice what he says, think on these
things.
Think on these things.
So when that individual says something, when something happens, we must review what we
know to be true.
No doubt in your life and in my life there's been a time that you've said something that
maybe didn't come out exactly the way that you intended for it to come out.
Has it ever happened?
And we find here that when you think about conflict, there are times and I've had opportunity,
I'll use that word, over the years to sit and to have counseling sessions with people
and so on and so forth.
And at times you sit there and you're thinking, this is so insignificant.
But it became such a huge matter.
Why?
Because they were thinking about the wrong thing.
They didn't really recognize who the enemy was.
They didn't resist the enemy.
They didn't review in their mind what they knew to be true.
But they were thinking about these other things and they took them and twisted them and so
on and so forth.
We see that Paul says, think on these things.
Notice over in the book of 2 Corinthians chapter number 10.
2 Corinthians chapter number 10.
Notice what the Bible says in verse number 3.
Second Corinthians 10 and verse number 3, for though we walk in the flesh, we do not
war after the flesh.
For the weapons of our warfare are not carnal, but mighty through the God to the pulling
down of strongholds, casting down imaginations and every high thing that exalteth itself
against the knowledge of God and bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience
of Christ.
You know what happens sometimes when there's a conflict?
Not only do we not review what we know to be true, number three, but if you're taking
notes number four, sometimes what we do, and I've put it this way in my notes, is the action
that we must take is that we must refuse to continuously replay the event.
Refuse to continuously replay the event.
Sometimes what happens when we're, have some kind of a conflict is instead of thinking
about and reminding ourselves, reviewing in our mind what we know to be true, we just
keep replaying something in our mind that happened.
I can't believe that happened that way that it happened.
Whatever it is that happened and we keep replaying that thing in our mind and we think, we're
thinking about it, we're thinking about it, we're thinking about it, and we're getting
more and more angry and, right?
I'm trying to be very helpful this evening because we all face conflict in life.
Listen, there are people that don't know how to handle conflict in our world today, seriously.
Two days ago, some guy went and shot five people because they asked him to be quiet.
That's nuts.
It's insane.
Would you agree?
That's not how you resolve conflict.
And if we're not careful, sometimes we can think, well, the conflict is just loss of
people, lost people.
Paul's writing to a church.
He calls them brethren.
There's conflict in the church at Corinth, and we'd be foolish to say that I don't have
any conflict in my life whatsoever.
No, there's conflict, and how do we deal with the conflict?
We find that he says that we're to bring into captivity every thought to the obedience of
Christ.
Sometimes we can just permeate and just kind of like that percolator, that coffee is percolating
and we just allow that thing to replant our mind and replant our mind and replant our
mind.
We're getting upset and we're getting angry and it's just boiling over.
No.
We must review what we know to be true in that situation.
Listen, I'm sure in your life and in my, I asked in Sunday school this morning, I said,
how many of you are thankful when God is long suffering to you?
Just about everybody raised their hand.
I said, now how many of you don't understand when God's long suffering to somebody else?
It's hard, right?
But when God's long suffering to us, we're thankful that God's long suffering.
Listen, I'm thankful when somebody could be gracious to me.
If I say something, if I do something, there's a measure of grace that's extended, right?
And we ought to be responsive in the same manner.
We find here that there are times in which we just allow something to replay in our minds
and it's a dangerous thing.
Listen, the enemy is going to use that.
The enemy is going to use that and it's not a good thing.
Number five this evening, I would say this, resolve the conflict quickly.
Resolve the conflict quickly.
See, we read in Ephesians 4 and verse number 3 where he said that we're endeavoring and
I talked about making haste, be diligent, labor.
And we go back to the book of Ephesians and that fourth chapter and we see this as endeavoring
to keep the unity of the spirit and the bond of peace and this laboring for something and
diligent and laboring for it, making haste for it.
We come to the end of the text of Scripture in Ephesians chapter number 4 and very quickly
all of this back and forth things are going on of put off this and put on that and the
importance of walking not as other Gentiles walk and walking as believers.
But we come to verse number 26 of Ephesians chapter number 4 and we read verse 27 already
but when you put them together in context, notice what the Bible says, be angry and sin
not.
If you'd be honest this evening, that is a very hard thing to do because you know what
many people do when they're angry?
They sin.
So here we find that the Scriptures tell us be angry and sin not.
Anger is an emotion that we have as people, as human beings, it's an emotion that we have.
Could we say this evening there are times in the life and ministry of the Lord Jesus
Christ that he was angry?
Sure, but yet he's without sin.
It can be done.
You can be angry and sin not.
The problem for many of us is we have no idea how to do that.
But he says be angry and sin not.
The point where he resolved the conflict quickly, notice what he says, let not the sun go down
upon your wrath.
Let not the sun go down upon your wrath, neither give place to the devil.
Resolving conflict quickly that we would understand in relationships that we have in
life that the real enemy is Satan.
We're not each other's enemy.
I don't think so.
I don't consider you an enemy.
I hope you don't consider me an enemy.
I hope you don't consider the people sitting next to you an enemy.
We have an enemy.
We have a common enemy.
And what our common enemy wants us to do is he wants us to think that someone other than
him is the enemy.
He wants you to start getting in your mind that somebody else is your enemy and he wants
you to replace some things and so on and so forth and he wants there to be that division,
those contentions.
And as the people of God, we've been warned in God's Word as to how the enemy works, how
he operates.
The Bible tells us as Paul is writing to the believers in 2 Corinthians, he says we're
not ignorant of his devices.
We know how Satan operates.
We know what he seeks to do.
And we find this evening that as we look at this thought in 1 Corinthians 1 and verses
10 and 11 and we see how Paul is made aware of what's going on in the church of course.
4th and then Paul addresses it, I mean he hits it, he faces it head on. He says we need
to address this thing, we need to deal with this thing, we need to resolve this thing
because it's not good for there to be contention and division. We must have unity and unity
is possible. It is possible to resolve conflict in a manner in which God is honored. I would
say this, it requires humility, it requires humility. Many times it requires someone saying
I was wrong, I'm sorry. Those are two phrases that many times pride will keep an individual
from saying because they don't want to acknowledge that they are wrong, they don't want to acknowledge
that they're sorry. That's your flesh. But we find that as we give no place to our flesh,
as we're walking in the Spirit, we're understanding what the enemy is really trying to do and
how the enemy is trying to work. Listen, Satan knows that his time is short. We'd be crazy
to think that he wouldn't try to cause some contention or division amongst our congregation.
We'd be nuts to think that. The enemy is active. He wants to do all that he can do
to cause contention and division in your home, amongst your family, and in our church. Five
very simple, biblical, I believe practical tips if I could call them that this evening
of how we can resolve conflict. He says, let not the sun go down upon your wrath, neither
give place to the devil. I believe that as we would consider that statement there in
verse 26 and 27, what happens oftentimes is we just kind of muse upon it. It festers up.
It gets bigger. It becomes a larger problem. You ever heard the expression, don't make
a mountain out of a? You've heard it. You know it. People talk about it. But you know
what? Sometimes we're really good at making mountains out of molehills. It's our flesh.
So this evening, as we think about this church in Corinth and so many things we could say
about this church in Corinth, so many lessons that we learn, I'm thankful that God chose
to record for us in His Word the situation in Corinth. I believe that many churches throughout
church history can be helped by what we read that the church in Corinth dealt with this
evening. What do we do when conflict comes? How do we respond? How do we resolve conflict?
I hope tonight just some basic biblical thoughts that we could apply in our lives, in our homes
in our church, in our relationships, wherever those relationships might be, that would enable
us to resolve conflict, that we could have unity. It is a good thing. It is a pleasant
thing is what the psalmist said in Psalm 133, for brethren to dwell together in unity. Let's
pray together. Father, we love You. We thank You for loving us. Thank You for Your Word,
for the truth that's contained therein. Really a simple thought this evening. It's so necessary
in our lives. I pray that tonight, Lord, You would help us, each of us, Lord, as Your people.
Lord, I pray that You would allow us to have unity in our homes, in our church, in our
relationships. Lord, help us to walk in the Spirit so that we would not fulfill the lust
of the flesh. Lord, help us to be clothed in humility. Help us, God, to recognize who
the real enemy is. And help us to place our efforts not towards one another in contending
and dividing, but help us to resist the enemy, steadfastly, as Peter said. I pray that You'd
move and work in hearts and lives as only You can. We'll thank You for it. In Christ's
name we pray. Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed. Kimberly's going
to play quietly on the piano just for a moment, giving opportunity to respond. As Kimberly
plays, the altar is open.