one and very thankful for the opportunity to be gathered together in
the Lord's house this morning. Thankful for the blessings already and what
wonderful songs that we have the privilege of singing this morning.
Oh Lord send a revival and the songwriter said let it begin in me and
what a wonderful prayer that is and then we sing that wonderful hymn nothing
between. I hope that this morning you can say that there's nothing between my
soul and my Savior and I'm so thankful that we have a God who is gracious and
merciful and as it's said in the Old Testament on more than one occasion that
there is that he is ready to pardon and ready to forgive that with thee there is
forgiveness. John said it this way if any if we confess our sins that he is
faithful and just to forgive us and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness and
what a blessed truth and so thankful for the Word of God and that God has
allowed us to have the Bible. Of course Brother Mershawn was scheduled to
preach this morning and this evening and throughout the week as well and I am
thankful that I normally don't have an opportunity to preach during a revival
meeting and I typically have the opportunity ahead of in preparation of a
revival meeting preaching a series of messages on preparation for revival and
then possibly after revival meeting preaching and so I'm thankful this
morning for the opportunity and I really saw the face of the Lord with regard to
the passage to preach and what have you just trusted to be a blessing to you
this morning. I mentioned already after our first song that we have that
question are we revival ready or are we revival resistant. Unfortunately there
are some folks that are just kind of like in that mindset of just leave me
alone I'm okay with how things are I'm kind of status quo I'm not interested in
getting my toes stepped on I don't want preaching that's gonna sit in my lap so
on and so forth and there are others that say I want to be revival ready I
want God to work in my heart in my life I understand that when the Word of God
is preached and the Holy Spirit of God uses the Word of God to convict me that
that's a good thing amen and I'm so thankful for the ministry of God's Word
that it has the ability to at the very same time not only convict me but
comfort me and it's an amazing truth that we see within the Word of God and
this morning as I think about revival and I think about the the truth of
revival and the opportunity to study historically revivals that you can read
in in the history of not only our nation but other nations that experienced
revival if you go back to the Old Testament and you read about some of the
revivals during the Judah's history Israel the ten tribes of the north they
never really after the divided kingdom there is no real record of any revival
they had bad wicked Kings and idolatry really was was rampant there and so on
and so forth but there in Judah every once in a while you'd see where a king
comes along that was a good king that believed in the power of the Word of God
and was open to the message of the prophets and you would see revival and
something that's interesting and really if you think about my mind this morning
specifically thinking about the time of Jehoshaphat and his reign and some of
the revival that took place during his reign you can think of Josiah as well
and something that you see consistent is not only the preaching of the Word of
God in fact during Josiah's time you see that they were cleaning out the temple
and they found the Word of the Lord and they read it and of course the response
to the to the reading of the Word of God and we see that something that is
consistent we think about revival is this subject of cleansing this this
truth you see within the scriptures of the Old Testament during the period of
those revivals how that the the temple needed to be cleansed why because it had
been polluted and you would see that there were times in which there were
some some wicked Kings and there was idolatrous worship that was taking place
and the the temple was polluted and you'd find that one of the very first
things that would happen is a cleansing of the temple and it reminds me as we
would think about the truth of that in the Old Testament we think about the
ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ and you understand that on two occasions
once in the beginning of his ministry and once right near the end of his
ministry publicly speaking during that period of time you find that Jesus went
to the temple and he cleansed the temple once in the beginning of his ministry
once at the end of his ministry we find that for New Testament believers this
morning if you have trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as your personal Savior
you've been bought with a price that is the precious blood of Christ we're not
our own we belong to him and the Bible tells us that we are the temple of the
Holy Ghost and what a blessed truth we find that the Word of God reveals to us
the truth with regard to the indwelling of the Spirit of God and also the
filling of the Spirit of God we think about the indwelling of the Spirit of
God we find that both that Paul deals with it both with the believers in
Corinth and also with the believers in Ephesus that the indwelling of the
Spirit of God that is the earnest of our salvation that is the proof of our
redemption and what a blessed truth that is but we find that as we go through our
lives this important aspect and we think about the cleansing aspect and we'll get
to it as we get in the message this morning that only comes as a result of
some examination some examination and so this morning as we look at this passage
of Scripture I really want to focus upon the what I would call the discipline of
self-examination the matter of self-examination I believe is of
significant importance however I would say this morning that far too often in
2020 broadly speaking in Christian circles it is a discipline that is far
too often ignored this morning we understand as we observe the Lord's
Supper we have the the table there and it says this do in remembrance of me and
so often as we think about the table and the Lord's Supper and that ordinance
that he gave us yes it's a table it's a memorial it's a table of remembrance but
we find that the Bible says in 1st Corinthians 11 let a man examine himself
this process of self-examination in fact Paul says not only the believers as he
writes that first epistle in 1st Corinthians chapter 11 but again in the
book of 2nd Corinthians he says examine yourselves and so this morning I've
simply used that as our title examine yourselves notice what the Bible says
Peter here in 1st Peter 1 in verse number 13 the Bible says this wherefore
gird up the loins of your mind be sober and hope to the end for the grace that
is to be brought unto you at the revelation of Jesus Christ notice verse
14 as obedient children not fashioning yourselves according to the former lust
in your ignorance but as he which hath called you is holy so be ye holy in all
manner of conversation because it is written be holy for I am holy I'm so
thankful that we serve a holy God in fact as we think about the holiness of
God on display throughout the scriptures we find that probably one of the great
passages of scripture where you're confronted with the holiness of God is
when you see Isaiah in the sixth chapter in the year that King Uzziah died the
Bible tells us that Isaiah saw the Lord high holy and lifted up and his train
did fill the temple the Bible goes on to explain to us that vision of use of
Isaiah in Isaiah chapter number six where the Bible says that he sees the
angels and they're crying out holy holy holy our God is holy he says there to
the the children of Israel in the book of Leviticus and really this is a quote
from Leviticus you find that he says this truth of being holy because he is
holy and as we begin to consider the passage of scripture begin to consider
the preparation if you will for revival and being in a place where we are
revival ready I believe that this process of self-examination is of great
importance I thought this week as I was preparing and I was meditating and just
musing upon the the subject matter that I believe the Lord led me to to preach
this morning I had recollection and some of you no doubt can understand the
pressures that an organization feels in the subsequent preparation that they go
through when they're facing an audit in fact there are times in which when I
worked in the corporate world that when they would announce that there was an
audit coming you kind of wish that you were on vacation that week because it's
something that was not always a pleasant experience there were a number of
pressures that would be upon not only the management team but also upon the
individuals within that organization you would find that all of a sudden
then there'd be a certain amount of preparation
that the employees would go through
in preparing for that audit.
This morning, as I can recall,
times in which I interacted with auditors
over the years,
I believe that there are valuable lessons
that we can learn from their work
that will be of assistance to us,
to me, to you,
as we consider the subject matter
to examine ourselves.
See, the reality this morning
is that for an organization
that has properly fulfilled
all of their responsibilities,
the announcement of an audit
does not really bring that great
of an amount of pressure.
Why? Because you've already been doing
what you're supposed to do.
The problem is when you're not doing
the things that you're supposed to do,
when you're not following the protocols
and so on and so forth,
when you find out that there's an audit scheduled,
there is a very high level of stress.
And this morning,
for a company to go through a process
of having an outside company come in
and perform an audit,
if they have been going through
proper channels and proper processes
as they go through their daily routine,
they don't have to stress over it.
And this morning, I tell you,
one day we're going to stand before God.
We're going to stand before God.
And the reality this morning
is that I so much look forward to the day
that I will see my Savior face to face.
But the very thought of standing before
the Lord God Almighty
at the bema seat of Christ,
the judgment seat of Christ,
is something that as we would consider
the subject matter,
would lead us to this process
of self-examination.
Why?
Because if I just neglect this whole process,
this whole discipline,
then one day I'm going to stand before the Lord
and I'm not going to quite be prepared.
I don't know that any of us
could be fully prepared.
But the truth of God's Word
with regard to examine yourselves
and self-examination
will go a long way to help us
to be in a place
where we are ready for that day.
Let me share a few thoughts with you.
Number one, this morning if you're taking notes,
and I'm going to use four R's
to alliterate it this morning
in this fashion.
Number one is review.
What does the auditor do
as soon as they come in?
They begin to take all of the documentation, right?
They begin this thorough review.
And so, as I begin to think about
this process of examine yourselves,
this self-examination,
this discipline that we're referring to this morning,
I say, well, first of all,
there has to be a review.
That review, I say, how do we do it?
Well, first of all,
we must understand that it has to be
an honest and a thorough review.
It must be honest.
It must be thorough.
It must be a situation.
Notice what Peter says here,
and we'll reference this often
throughout our message this morning,
that in verse number 14 he says,
as obedient children,
in verse number 15 he says,
so be holy in all manner of conversation.
So there must be a review,
and the review must be honest
and it must be thorough.
When I consider the review
and I consider how it is that we would review
our own lives as we would examine ourselves,
I find this morning that the standard
for the review must be the Word of God.
It is not valid that we would use
somebody else's life as the standard
by which we would examine ourselves.
No, it must be the Word of God.
The prophet said that the Word of God
was like a plumb line,
and that's how they were going to be judged.
And this morning as we would consider
the power of God's Word
and the truth of God's Word,
we find that it is this book
that must be the standard
by which we examine ourselves.
An auditor has a standard.
They come in with some type of,
if you're having a financial audit,
they have certain protocols
and certain standards by which
they're going to audit that company by.
And this morning as God's people,
I say this is the standard.
The very Word of God.
As Baptist people, we have said for years,
in fact, for years,
Baptist people have been referred to
as people of the book.
By the way, that's a good terminology.
Amen?
And we find that as Baptist people,
we would say that the Bible
is our sole authority for faith and practice.
This morning, the Word of God
must be the standard by which
we examine ourselves.
Notice, if you want to take,
and we're going to look at a number of passages
this morning, but look back a few pages
in your Bible at James 1 if you will.
In James 1, the Bible's referring to a verse
that we often reference as verse 22
of being doers of the Word
and not hearers, only deceiving your own selves.
But I want you to focus and look
at what the Bible says in verse 25.
The Bible says this,
but whoso looketh into the perfect law of liberty.
I'm thankful that God describes His Word
in that manner.
It is the perfect law of liberty.
And the Bible says,
whoso looketh into the perfect law of liberty,
notice what it says,
and continueth therein.
He being not a forgetful hearer,
but a doer of the work,
this man shall be blessed in his deed.
We say that the Bible is our sole authority
for faith, what we believe,
and practice, the things that we do.
And as we would go through the process
of self-examination,
we find that the Bible says,
and you don't need to turn there,
but Paul as he's writing to the believers in Ephesus,
and he's speaking to them about their walk,
and really in chapters 4 and 5,
he references five different areas
with regard to the walk of the believer.
And he says this,
proving what is acceptable unto the Lord.
In Ephesians 5, in verse 10.
This morning, the Word of God must be the standard.
It absolutely must be the standard.
So we understand how.
It must be honest.
It must be thorough.
We understand that there's a standard,
and for us this morning as the people of God,
that standard is the Word of God.
By the way, I'm thankful that God's Word hasn't changed.
I'm thankful that we're not looking for a revision.
For an updated version.
I'm thankful that God is eternal,
and He has given us a book
that is applicable and relevant today.
So many people that say,
oh, it's so old.
Yeah, but the author is eternal.
Amen?
What a joy.
It's the Word of God that's the standard.
This morning we ask ourselves, why?
Why do I go through this?
Why do you think we should go through
a process of examining ourselves?
Why do we have to have this discipline?
Can I say to you very simply
that Paul says in Romans 14 and verse number 12,
so that every one of us
shall give account of himself to God.
What does a steward do?
He's responsible for the things
that have been entrusted to him,
but he also is called to give an account regularly.
Or at least he should be.
We're stewards.
And this morning, in Romans 14 and verse number 12,
as Paul is referencing,
and there are a number of chapters
and a number of references
to the fact that we will give an account
and stand before the Lord,
but I understand how Paul says it
in this particular text,
so then every one of us,
if you're a believer this morning,
if you've trusted the Lord Jesus Christ,
you can rejoice in the fact
that the second death has no power over you.
You can rejoice this morning
that you will not stand
at the great white throne judgment
and what blessed truth that is.
However, as a child of God,
we will give an account
and we give that account of himself to God.
Wow.
I hope this morning you see the seriousness
of the subject matter.
You understand this morning
that you're not giving an account for someone else.
I preached a message two Wednesday nights ago.
Search me, oh God.
Why?
Because I'm not gonna stand
and give an account for someone else.
I'm standing and giving an account for myself.
Now as a pastor, I will give an account.
I'm told as one of my responsibilities in Hebrews
that I watch for your souls.
And it's very interesting what the writer says
there in Hebrews with regard to that subject matter.
The Bible says in Hebrews 13 and verse 17,
obey them that have the rule over you
and submit yourselves for they watch for your souls,
notice this, as they must give account
that they may do it,
notice what it says, with joy and not with grief.
But then it says this,
for that is unprofitable for you.
We understand the subject matter this morning
dealing with the Bema Seat of Christ
and the examine ourselves
because the reality is that every one of us
shall give account of himself to God.
That word shall, we like when it's in the context
of like Romans 10, 13,
for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord
shall be saved, we say praise the Lord.
He shall come, we say praise the Lord.
You shall give account.
It's certain.
I remember there were times,
the very first audit that I remember
when I worked for Sikorsky Aircraft Corporation,
I had not been there very long
and unfortunately there were some practices
that had taken place.
prior to my arrival that weren't really
within the way in which things
were supposed to be conducted
and so on and so forth.
And I remember having this thought
and really everyone within our department
had the thought,
I hope they don't talk to me.
I'm hoping that they just pass right past
where I am and they go to somebody else
to talk to that someone else
can give an account.
Can I tell you biblically speaking
the matter of the subject
that's before us this morning?
You're going to give an account.
It's certain.
So therefore, we must go through
this review process.
It behooves us.
It is advantageous for us.
I think this way.
My understanding of the truth
leads me to this process.
We understand that truth impacts.
Amen?
I've often said over the years
that truth, that belief,
will impact our behavior.
If I understand the truth
that is before us this morning
and I understand the fact
that I will stand before the Lord,
then it leads me to this process
that has an impact and effect
upon my behavior.
So number one, I review.
Number two, recognize.
What do I mean by recognize?
Well, the purpose of reviewing
is so that we can properly identify
areas that need to be addressed.
Remember, we're doing a thorough
and honest evaluation
and a thorough and honest review.
We're using the Word of God
as our standard.
And we understand that,
as we've mentioned already
on two occasions,
that in 1 Peter 1 and verse 15,
he says,
So be ye holy.
Notice the phrase,
in all manner of conversation.
I had a Bible college professor
that was a real sharp fella.
And he said, listen, fellas,
all means all.
And that's all that all means.
And he would say that regularly.
And the reality is that
when we look at the passage
of Scripture, he says,
all manner of conversation,
the whole of it,
every aspect of it,
and what is it?
The manner of conversation.
That's our manner of life.
That's our conduct.
That's our behavior.
And so begin to boil down
and look at what God is saying.
And we understand that He says
that we're to be holy
in all manner of conversation.
Now, we understand this morning
that Peter is writing to believers.
He's writing to people
that are saved.
They've been justified.
He tells to those believers
in chapter 1 and verse 5
that they are kept by the power of God.
That they have a treasure,
an inheritance that's incorruptible,
that's undefiled,
that's fadeth not away,
that's reserved in heaven for them.
I mean, he's writing to believers.
But he says, listen,
you're to be holy
in all manner of conversation.
Can I tell you this morning
that God cares how we live?
He does.
Paul says this to the believers
in Thessalonica in 1 Thessalonians 4
that you know how you ought to behave.
That you know how you ought to walk.
I believe that's exactly how he says it there
in 1 Thessalonians 4.
That you know how you ought to walk.
Again, we don't walk in a certain way
so that we can keep our salvation.
We don't walk, live in a certain way
so that we can earn our salvation.
That was settled on the cross of Calvary.
Jesus Christ said it is finished.
He was buried and He rose in victory
conquering sin, death, and the grave.
But He is concerned about how we live our lives.
Listen, this morning,
there is not a sacred part of you
and a secular part of you.
All of you has been redeemed
by the blood of Christ.
Aren't you thankful for that by the way?
And he says that we're to be holy
in all manner of conversation.
It's not a situation where you say,
I'm in this place now
and so I can behave this way.
I'm over here in this place
around these people and I behave this way.
No, no, no.
We're to be holy in all manner of conversation.
Now, admittedly this morning,
there's no way I could exhaust a list
of all manner of conversation.
But I'm gonna try to help us this morning
to pinpoint a few areas that ought to be reviewed,
that ought to be considered.
Now, listen, let me tell you this
before I even get into the verses.
God already stepped on my toes.
I anticipate that He's gonna step on my toes again
as I deliver it to you this morning.
Don't get mad when God steps on your toes.
It's a good thing.
Because He's confronting us
and He's helping us to live.
Listen, I'm saying this morning
that the standard is the Word of God.
I'm gonna show you what God's Word says.
I cannot give you an exhaustive list
of what all manner of conversation is.
We'd be here forever trying to go through
every little detail of our lives.
But let me give you a sampling.
We think about this truth that I am bought with a price.
Remember, Paul says it this way in 1 Corinthians 6.
What?
No ye not?
I mean, he's going to these believers
in the book of 1 Corinthians
with regard to all of their carnality
and all of the things that are going on.
And he says, what?
No ye not that your body is the temple of the Holy Ghost
which is in you, which you have of God.
You're not your own.
You're bought with a price.
Therefore, glorify God in your body
and in your spirit, which are God's.
Let me just point out a few things this morning.
When we think about this recognition,
we've reviewed and we recognize,
well, what is it, preacher, that I should review?
Number one, we should review what I read.
What I read.
What am I reading?
What am I putting into my mind?
The first three that I have in my notes this morning,
what I read, what I watch, and what I listen to.
The reason why I have those three in my list this morning
that I believe the Lord led me
to those three things to begin with
is because we must recognize this morning
how those three things affect my thoughts.
What I read, what I watch, and what I listen to.
The reality this morning is that
when we begin to use the Word of God
and we think about what He tells us
with regard to our thought life
and we understand how that these three areas
will impact my thinking,
we find that Paul says this to the believers in Philippi
in Philippians 4 and verse number eight,
finally, brethren, whatsoever things are true,
whatsoever things are honest,
whatsoever things are just,
whatsoever things are pure,
whatsoever things are lovely,
whatsoever things are of good report,
if there be any virtue and if there be any praise,
think on these things.
In 2 Corinthians 10 and verse number five,
he says that we're to bring into captivity
every thought to the obedience of Christ.
How's my thought life being impacted by what I'm reading?
How's my thought life being impacted by what I'm watching?
The psalmist said,
I will set no wicked thing before mine eyes.
How's my thought life being impacted
by the things I listen to?
You ever been in a situation
where you get into somebody's car
and they turn off the music real quick?
They must have some level of understanding
that what they had been listening to
probably isn't good for your presence.
What about God's presence?
I'm thankful this morning that our God is omnipotent.
He has all power.
I'm thankful this morning that our God is omniscient,
that He knows all things.
And I'm thankful this morning that our God is omnipresent,
that He is everywhere present.
And that truth of God's omnipresence is a comforting truth.
I will never leave thee nor forsake thee.
I am with thee.
It's also a convicting truth.
He's always with us.
If it wouldn't be appropriate
if God were sitting next to you physically, bodily
to hear, read, or watch something,
then you ought not be doing it.
Amen?
It's very simple.
What does the Word of God say?
How do those things impact my thoughts?
Am I bringing every thought into captivity?
Am I able to have that honest and thorough evaluation
and say, hey, look, this thing right here
I shouldn't be listening to.
This thing right here I shouldn't be reading.
This thing right here I shouldn't be watching.
Why?
Because it doesn't pass the test of Philippians 4.8.
If you're taking notes,
not only would I read, watch, and listen to,
I want you to consider your speech.
I said this on Wednesday night a couple of weeks ago
when I talked about search me, oh God,
and I mentioned that often we kind of look at it
from this lens.
We begin to think about our standing before God.
Well, I'm not a murderer.
I'm not a, and we start naming these big things
that we're not.
I said this on that Wednesday night.
I'm glad that you're not.
Amen?
I'm glad you've not murdered anyone.
I mean, that's a blessing.
I'd have to visit you in prison, you know?
But the reality is that when you look at the walk
when God deals with it,
when he deals with it with the believers in Ephesus,
he doesn't say, don't kill anybody.
He says, speak the truth.
Stop lying.
That's what he says.
And we think about our speech,
and the first aspect that I think about
is that of speaking the truth in Ephesians 4 in verse 15,
but speaking the truth in love
may grow up into him in all things
which is the head, even Christ.
You know, we live in a place, we live in a time,
we live in an era where unfortunately,
speaking the truth does not have the value
that it once had.
But as God's people, we're to speak the truth.
He says later in this same chapter
in Ephesians 4, and as you go through the passage
and you look,
He says in verse number 25,
"'Wherefore, putting away lying,
speak every man truth with his neighbor,
for we are members one of another.'"
We're to speak the truth.
Not being a gossip.
It's kind of funny how gossip works within church.
It's typically, it works kind of this way.
I have a prayer request for you.
And all we really want to do is gossip about something.
And we kind of put the facade on
that it's a prayer request.
We don't spiritualize it.
Now, it might be a legitimate prayer request
that may not be gossip,
but we've got to be careful.
What about the situation where we gossip
because we think, oh man, this thing happened
and somebody needs to know about it.
Maybe we don't say it's a prayer request,
but we just feel like we've got to point out
somebody else's issue.
I think about the fact that we're to
praise God.
My speech.
Is my speech characterized by complaining
and murmuring?
Or is it characterized of praising and thanking?
You know what Paul says in the book of Philippians?
If you want to turn over there to the book of Philippians
in chapter 2.
It's a really interesting verse.
We so often talk about the truth of
in everything give thanks.
And those are great verses.
Those are very appropriate.
And they speak to our heart.
And they give us the fact that in everything
we're to give thanks.
This is the will of God in Christ Jesus
concerning you.
But I want you to notice how Paul says
of the believers in Philippi.
In chapter number 2 of Philippians
in verse number 14.
He says this.
Do all things without murmurings
and disputings.
I've often told you that I like the word murmur
probably more than I like the word complain
because murmur just sounds bad.
Often in the Old Testament
they were guilty of murmuring.
You find that the word is used often
in the Old Testament.
You find that they were murmuring in their tents.
That's their homes.
That's where they lived.
You think about the influence upon their children
in the next generation
because all they heard was murmur and murmur.
We hate this bread.
They murmured all the time.
See, Paul says do all things.
Okay, that's pretty inclusive, is it not?
I mean everything, right?
I mean all things without murmurings and disputings.
How is my speech characterized?
I think about the way in which our speech
could be used to sow discord.
The Bible speaks about unity in the church of God
and I'm so thankful that we can have unity
because we embrace the same truth.
Paul said to the believers in Ephesus
that we're endeavoring to keep the unity
of the Spirit and the bond of peace.
But it's interesting as you would think about
the subject matter of sowing discord.
God says in Proverbs 6,
how we can sow discord is absolutely with our mouth,
with our speech,
and it says that God hates it.
He hates it.
That's serious language.
Yea, these six things that the Lord hate,
yea, seven is an abomination.
Proverbs 6, verse 14,
and then you look at verses 16 through 19.
We don't have time to go there this morning.
It is interesting that speaking the truth
also is in that same text of scripture.
He hates lying.
By the way, it's part of the Ten Commandments.
We speak the truth.
So again, we kind of go through this process
saying well I'm not really that bad
because I haven't done all these things,
but really when we think about the people of God
and we think about all manner of conversation being holy,
he's not just concerned about these big areas,
he's concerned about every area.
Notice with me, not only my speech,
but I think about my associations.
My associations.
Notice what Paul says.
Turn to the book of 2 Corinthians, if you will,
in chapter number six.
It's interesting because really
in this same passage of scripture
in 2 Corinthians 6, 14 through chapter seven
in verse number one,
you can see really the entirety of the message
that we're preaching this morning
with regard to this process.
Number one, review.
Number two, recognize.
Notice what he says in verse number 14
of 2 Corinthians 6.
Be ye not unequally yoked together with unbelievers.
For what fellowship hath righteousness with unrighteousness?
What communion hath light with darkness?
What concord hath Christ with Belial?
Or what part hath he that believeth with an infidel?
These questions are posed this way
to help the believer understand there's no union.
There's no association that should be made.
And he says this in verse 16.
What agreement hath the temple of God with idols?
For ye are the temple of the living God.
As God hath said, I will dwell in them and walk in them
and I will be their God and they shall be my people.
Wherefore, based upon this principle, what are you to do?
Come out from among them and be ye separate,
saith the Lord.
He then gives these wonderful promises.
He says this, and touch not the unclean thing
and I will receive you and will be a father unto you
and you shall be my sons and daughters,
saith the Lord Almighty.
You understand that at the end of verse number 17
in verse 18, again, Paul's writing to the church
in Corinth, he's writing to believers there in Corinth,
and what he's saying to them is not that you're gonna be
saved, it's that you're gonna have that fellowship.
Because you've done these things,
you've come out from among them
and you've been ye separate.
Listen, when I'm living a life of sin,
when I'm allowing sin in my life
and I'm not examining, I'm not dealing with it,
my fellowship with my God is hindered.
He's still my God.
I'm thankful for that.
He's still my Savior, but my fellowship is hindered.
We find that he says that these associations are important
and we're not to be, be ye not unequally yoked
together with unbelievers, and he goes through the list.
I think about what I read, what I watch,
what I listen to, my speech, my associations.
I would say this, what about my attire?
It's kind of interesting because so often
it's a subject matter that people don't like to deal with.
But you know something that's interesting,
I was thinking about it this week
and I actually heard somebody on American Family Radio
deal with it, and it was quite interesting
how they dealt with it, and they even addressed it
in the same manner, that for some reason
in our churches today, we don't like to talk about attire.
But you know, every company I ever worked with
or worked for had a dress code.
Every single one.
Every school that I went to had a dress code.
Now they varied, admittedly.
Something that's a super interesting study,
and I say that it's a super interesting study
from my perspective, you might have no interest
in it whatsoever, you might think it's just dumb,
and that's fine, you can have your opinion,
I'm entitled to my opinion.
But a fascinating study to me was when I went to England
when my brother lived there a couple of years ago,
he was there for three years and we had the privilege
of going and visiting, it was an interesting,
fascinating study to study some things
about the royal family.
And you know the royal family has an extremely
detailed dress code.
I mean, big time.
Go look it up, it's fascinating.
And it's not just for females, it's for males as well.
I mean, you're part of the royal family.
There's a certain expectation.
Can I tell you this morning that you're part
of a greater royal family?
Here's what Peter says, we're in 1 Peter chapter number one
for our text of scripture this morning,
but I want you to understand that Peter will go on to say
in chapter number two in verse number nine,
but ye are a chosen generation, a royal priesthood,
and a holy nation, a peculiar people that you should
show forth the praises of him who hath called you
out of darkness into his marvelous light.
What a joy to understand.
I think about the Old Testament example in 2 Samuel
where David said I want to show the kindness of the Lord.
Are there any left of the house of Jonathan?
And there was one Mephibosheth, but he was down
in Lodabar and he says bring him to me.
I'm gonna make him as one of the king's sons.
If you've been saved this morning,
you are adopted by the king of kings and lord of lords.
Our father is the god of the universe
and we are his children and we are part of a royal family.
And can I tell you that the Bible deals with attire.
The Bible addresses it.
Notice with me in 1 Timothy chapter number one,
notice what Paul is telling Timothy here
in the passage of scripture and he's dealing with things
with regard to the church and all that's going on there.
I said chapter number one, sorry, chapter number two.
And I want you to notice in chapter number two
in verses nine and 10, notice what he says.
In like manner also that women adorn themselves
in modest apparel with shamefacedness and sobriety,
not with braided hair or gold or pearls or costly array,
but which becometh women professing godliness
with good works.
I understand that the era in which we live in
is a different era than when the Bible was written.
It's very interesting, by the way,
if you read in the book of Proverbs
and really look at the Old Testament,
in Proverbs chapter number seven in particular,
it talks about the attire of an harlot.
Won't deal with that whole subject matter this morning,
but the reality is that their attire was sending a message.
And this morning, we have two daughters and I have a wife,
praise the Lord, and I got a son
and I'm thankful for all of them.
But I've said to my girls often,
listen, the subject matter of modesty
is an important subject matter.
And I understand that as teenage girls,
you wanna, and I've said this to them,
you wanna be cute, you wanna wear something that's cute,
but you cannot, you cannot, you must not
sacrifice modesty for cuteness.
It's just not appropriate.
And so therefore, we find that as we would go through
this evaluation, we're reviewing,
we're saying all manner of conversation,
I wanna recognize some things.
And so I think about my attire, I think about my finances.
I heard a preacher just last week, I was at a preacher's meeting,
he said this, give me your checkbook and I'll tell you what's important to you.
I think about finances. God's Word says a lot about finances, by the way.
You know, in Malachi, they were receiving rebuke because they were robbing God.
How are we robbing God? In tithes and offerings.
God goes on to say, prove me.
Luke says, give and it shall be given.
And he goes through that whole process.
Listen, we don't give so that we can get something from God.
We give because we recognize all of it already belongs to God.
And He's been so very good to us.
And what a privilege to be able to give back to Him.
I think about what Jesus said in Matthew chapter number 6.
In Matthew chapter number 6, verses 20 and 21, Jesus says this.
I'll read verse number 19 along with it.
In Matthew 6, verses 19 through 21.
Lay not up for yourselves treasures upon earth, where moth and rust doth corrupt,
and where thieves break through and steal, but lay up for yourselves treasures in heaven,
where neither moth nor rust doth corrupt, and where thieves do not break through nor steal.
For where your treasure is, there will your heart be also.
I want God to evaluate my finances.
I think about this, my prayer life.
The sin of prayerlessness.
The fact of the matter is that Samuel says this.
You don't need to turn there, but it's a powerful statement that Samuel makes.
Of course, he's grieved in his heart because the nation wants a king.
And he goes through that whole process and God gives him instruction.
Of course, we understand that Saul is anointed to be the first king of Israel.
But Samuel says this in 1 Samuel 12, in verse number 23.
Moreover, ask for me, God forbid, that I should sin against the Lord in ceasing to
pray for you.
The sin of prayerlessness.
We're busy.
We don't have time.
How's my prayer life?
See I want to be able to recognize these things as I review and I'm recognizing, okay, God,
I need some work there.
Okay, God, I need some work here.
Okay, God, there's a problem here.
There's a problem there.
I want to be able to recognize those problems.
I think about my being engaged in sharing my faith.
God says that we are ambassadors.
We are his representatives.
God says that we're to go and preach the gospel to every creature.
I don't know how you feel right now, but I know I feel, I shared with somebody on the
phone last night, I feel so twisted up inside that I can't go freely knock on somebody's
door and share the gospel with them.
Because we're living during a time where people, I don't think, are very kind towards me knocking
on their door with all of the current pandemic and everything that's going on.
And we're trying to be aware of those things and be wise with regard to those things.
But man, I love being able to engage people and speaking with them about the gospel.
Admittedly, I don't do it as often as I should.
But can I tell you when something's removed from us, it gives us that much of a greater
appreciation and longing for it.
How's my witnessing?
I really think this, when I consider all of these things, and again, it's not an exhaustive
list.
You can add plenty of things to it.
But really, I boil down the principle to being this.
It's a principle that you find in Ephesians 4 and also in Colossians 3.
And it's this principle, put off, put on.
Because of who I am.
Because I've been redeemed.
Because I'm adopted into the family of God.
Because I am part of his family.
I am his child.
Here's some things I'm going to, this is how I'm going to behave, be holy in all manner
of conversation.
So as we go through our process, we have reviewed, we've recognized, okay, here's some things
I need to deal with.
And we come to number three, resolve.
Resolve it.
I mean, deal with it.
The reality is that we don't identify it just so that we can say, yeah, there's a problem
there.
We identify it so that we can resolve it.
One thing that I said often when I worked in the corporate world, and it carries right
over into the church work, is that there are a lot of problem identifiers and very few
problem solvers.
Amen?
I mean, you find it all over the world.
This morning, I made a commitment when I worked in the corporate world that I might not have
the right answer to the problem, but I would never take a problem to my boss without also
taking a solution.
It may not be the solution that they take.
It might be dumb, but I'm going to try my best to come up with a solution.
Why?
Because I didn't want to just be a problem identifier.
So this morning, if I go through this process of self-examination, if I'm reviewing, if
I'm recognizing some areas now, I need to resolve those things.
I need to deal with it.
God in His grace and His mercy has allowed it to be exposed, has allowed it to be revealed.
Why?
So that I would deal with it.
It's a reference back to what we said in the very beginning of the message with regard
to the revivals in Judah.
They heard the word of the Lord, and Josiah responded, he said, there's some things we
need to change.
Jehoshaphat said, there's some things that need to be cleansed, there's some things that
need to be done.
And this morning, I say, I want to resolve the issues.
I want to confess and forsake.
I think about a great example.
Come to the book of Acts in chapter 19, if you will.
Here in Acts chapter 19, really what we're seeing is the revival in Ephesus.
I mean, it's a powerful passage of Scripture, but I want you to see and consider with me
this morning the example of this church, and I want you to see how they resolved the issues,
how the word of the Lord went forth, and how they responded as they were able to identify
some things that needed to be addressed.
Verse number 17 in Acts 19, the Bible says, and this was known to all the Jews and Greeks
also dwelling at Ephesus.
And fear fell on them all, and the name of the Lord Jesus was magnified, and many that
believed came and confessed and showed their deeds.
Notice verse 19, many of them also which used curious arts brought their books together.
What did they do?
And burned them before all men.
They counted the price of them and found it 15,000 pieces of silver.
And look at the result of what happened.
So mightily grew the word of God and prevailed.
I'm thankful they resolved the issues.
That they didn't just have their toes stepped on and say, well, that's okay, that's just
what the preacher thinks.
That's just Paul getting on his little thing and whatever, we'll just keep on going along.
Well, then the word of God's not going to grow and multiply and prevail.
Because God, listen, I believe that God wants to send revival, but the question is are we
revival ready?
The question is, is there anything?
There's nothing between my soul and my Savior's.
There's something that I know that God has confronted me about from His word, and I say,
yeah, I'm not going to deal with that.
I like that more than this, and whatever the situation is, no.
We say, I surrender.
I'm giving it all to God.
I want God's favor and God's blessing.
Nothing, nothing is worth forfeiting His blessing and His favor.
Nothing is worth it.
And this morning, I see that the Bible says that they burned them before all men.
I remember when my dad got saved.
Now young people in here, you're probably not going to remember cassette tapes, but
y'all older folks, you remember cassette tapes.
You remember A-tracks.
I don't even remember those things.
And then records.
I remember the first time Breonna saw a record.
She said, what in the world is that?
I said, you play music on that thing.
And she's like, really?
I said, it's like a big CD, but it holds only a fraction of what a CD holds, you know?
But the reality is, I remember when my dad got saved, and I remember he had a bunch of
tapes of music that somehow, through the preaching of the Word of God and the Spirit of God,
convicting him that that music wasn't appropriate for a believer.
Am I right?
Okay.
I remember what he did.
He took all those cassette tapes, and he didn't take them down to somewhere and sell them
and try to get money for them, though he could have.
But what he thought was that it's not right for me.
I don't want to give that to somebody else, even if I'm going to profit from it.
I remember him taking those cassette tapes, and young people, you've got to realize how
that all that stuff would come out of the cassette tape, right?
It was always a mess, man.
You try to get pencils and fix it and what have you.
But he took all those things, and I remember him tearing them all up and throwing them
in the garbage.
He didn't burn them, but he disposed of them.
And he disposed of them in such a way that even if he had second thoughts later and said,
well, I really like that one song, I think I'm going to go back and get it, he's going
to have to pay money to buy it again, amen, because he destroyed it.
And I'm saying to you that when I look at what happened here in Ephesus, this is a proper
response.
They said, we don't want to just have the issue identified, we want to resolve it.
We don't want to just recognize it, we want to deal with it.
I think about what we read in 2 Corinthians 6, we read the latter part of the chapter,
but in chapter number 7 and verse number 1, the Bible says this, Paul's instruction to
the believers in Corinth was simply this, cleanse yourselves from all filthiness of
the flesh and spirit.
I'm thankful for the ministry of the Word of God.
Paul deals with it in the book of Ephesians, how that we are cleansed.
Notice in Ephesians 5 and verse 26, that he might sanctify and cleanse it with the washing
of water by the Word.
See, I believe that when we resolve the issue, that we also need to put in some protections.
We need to make...
ourselves accountable. I think of a company that has an audit. The auditor
comes in, the auditor reviews, the auditor recognizes some areas that have
problems, and the auditor says, hey these things need to be resolved, and by the
way, you need to put some things in place to prevent this from happening again. And
so for us as God's people, when we're gonna resolve something, I believe that
there is an important aspect of accountability and establishing some
protections in our life, in our lives. This morning we go through the process
of examine yourselves, this process of self-examination. We review, we recognize,
we resolve, and I want you to consider with me the result this this morning, the
result of going through this process. The Bible tells us, as I mentioned already in
Romans chapter 14 and verse number 12, so then every one of us shall give account
of himself to God. In my mind this morning, and I hope that you can follow
my logic, that we come full circle. As to the why of the review, we come full circle
back to the result of the process, is that now God's people can be properly
prepared to give an account. I think it's advantageous that someone would care
enough, that God would care enough to give us in his Word the truth that we
will stand before him, but also the manner in which we can be prepared to
stand before him. Admittedly, I don't know that any of us would say, I'm fully
prepared, I'm gonna, I'm ready to do it right now, because it's a fearful thing.
But this morning, I want you to consider, we don't have time, we're out of time
this morning, but I want you to consider something that God tells us in his Word
here in Ephesians 5. We read about the cleansing in verse number 26, in verse
number 27 he says that he might present it to himself, he's speaking about the
church, a glorious church, not having spot or wrinkle or any such thing, but
that it should be holy and without blemish. We read the same truth in the
book of Colossians, we reference James 1 as being the fact that we're to use the
Word of God as the standard by which we do the review, the process by which we
review our lives, the standard must be the Word of God. But a couple of verses
later in the book of James in the first chapter, in verse number 27, it says pure
religion and undefiled before God and the Father is this, to visit the
fatherless and widows in their affliction and to keep himself unspotted
from the world. John says in first John 2, love not the world, neither the things
that are in the world. I think about this and we'll close here, turn to the book of
Revelation if you will, in chapter number 19. At the end of chapter 19, really I'll
say the middle portion of chapter 19, is you see the return of Christ, the advent
of Christ, when he comes back with us, with his bride. See in Revelation
chapter number 4, you see the picture of the rapture where the church is caught
up and you find the tribulation period recorded and revealed in those next
several chapters throughout the book of Revelation and all of the judgments that
are poured out. You come to chapter 19 and there's a reference that we're
going to deal with with regard to the marriage supper of the Lamb and then you
look at the advent of Christ, that he comes back not as the Lamb of God but as
the Lion of the tribe of Judah and he comes back and we come with them and of
course we understand that he's going to establish his millennial reign and what
a joy that is, but I want you to focus just for a moment this morning on this
truth with regard to the marriage supper of the Lamb. In verse number
seven, now you understand biblically speaking that God refers to himself as
the Bridegroom, the Lord Jesus Christ is the Bridegroom and the church is the
Bride. We just looked at that just a moment ago in Ephesians 5 and we see
that that example, that relationship is referenced many times
throughout the scriptures and now we come to Revelation 19 in verse number
7 and the Bible says, let us be glad and rejoice and give honor to him for the
marriage of the Lamb is come. It's going to happen one day, we don't know when
it's going to happen but we know it's going to happen, but I want you to notice
the latter part of the verse. The Bible says, and his wife, who's his wife? It's the
church, the church is the Bride. His wife hath made herself ready. Now we
understand marriages here upon our earth and we understand the process in which
goes through for a marriage ceremony and we understand the preparation of the
bride for the wedding ceremony. I've never gone through the preparation but
there are plenty of times that I've been at weddings when you're kind of waiting
around and saying, I wonder if this thing is going to happen or not. She's almost
ready, you know, this kind of message gets sent back and what have you. She's
preparing herself, she's readying herself for the ceremony. I wonder this morning
how the Bride of Christ, the church, the church is made up of believers,
individual believers, how are we preparing ourselves, how are we readying
ourselves for that marriage supper of the Lamb? I believe this morning that we
must examine ourselves. We must go through this process. I have to go
through this process. I am sharing with you this morning my heart because I want
you to go through this process because the reality is you're gonna stand before
Christ one day. And I wonder this morning, as John says in first John, he talks
about the fact that we have this confidence that he is going to appear, we
know that he's going to appear, but he mentions how that there could be some
that could be ashamed before him it is coming. And then of course he talks about
in chapter 3 and verse number 3, and every man that hath this hope, what hope?
The fact that he's going to come. We have that hope in us, we purify himself even
as he is pure. Peter said this in first Peter, that we're to be obedient children,
not fashioning ourselves according to our former lust, but he says that we're
to be holy in all manner of conversation. God's concerned how we live our lives,
and because we've been redeemed, because we've been bought with the precious
blood of Christ, we have instruction on how we're to behave, how we're to walk, in
this morning, I want to encourage you, examine yourself. I want to encourage
myself, examine ourselves. I want you to know I'm not preaching this message to
you, I'm preaching this message for all of us. God's already stepped on my toes,
and I hope this morning that God, the Holy Spirit, would use his word to really
help us come to that quiet place and say, Lord, I need to examine myself. And it
needs to be honest, and it needs to be thorough, and the standard by which I
review and examine my life has got to be your word. And God, as I go through this
process, I want to recognize the areas of deficiency, the areas of sin in my life,
the areas of things that need to be changed, and God, I'm gonna resolve those
things with your help, by your grace, so that the result is that I can be
prepared to give an account. Because as Paul said to the believers in Rome, we're
going to give an account of himself to God. Let's pray. Father, we love you, we
thank you for loving us. God, I thank you for your word this morning and the truth
contained therein. Lord, I pray that the Holy Spirit of God would speak to hearts
through your precious word. Help us this morning, God, to be doers of the word.
Help us, God, to be thankful that your word confronts us. I pray that we would
respond properly. Help me, Lord. Help each one that's present this morning. We want
to be revival ready. More than that, I understand this morning, one day I'll
stand before you. God, I want to be prepared for that day. And I trust that
each one that's present this morning has the same heart attitude. We pray that
you'd have your will in way, that you'd work as only you can. It's in Christ's name we
pray. Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed. I'm not going to go
through a series of questions this morning. I'm just going to ask you to say
yes to God. Just respond. Julianna is going to play quietly on the piano. As
she does, the altar's open. Make your seat an altar. Let God have his way in your
heart and life as Julianna plays.