you my experience and the truth. You have the most gracious and hospitable pastor
and pastor's wife of any that I know of. I tell them that that apartment
downstairs is my apartment and they can only let others use it with my
permission, you know. It is so comfortable and they are so kind and it is so
enjoyable to be there. Well then you walk up the hill and come over here and
you get the same thing over here. I hope you never lose that. I hope you welcome
people, be an accepting congregation. It is just a blessing to walk in here and
have people that care about you and speak to you. It has been a real blessing
to be here. Again I say appreciate the church God has given you and be part of
it and protect it and participate in everything that you can participate in.
How do people live in this world without a church? I don't get it. I really don't.
And I don't understand why they do less church. I think we ought to do more
church as we see the day appearing. All right that's my cranky old man
statement of the night. Take your Bible if you would and turn with me to
2nd Timothy chapter 4. One verse is our text though we'll look at a number of
verses in the passage as we study tonight. 2nd Timothy chapter 4 and verse
8. There the Bible says this, henceforth there is laid up for me a crown of
righteousness which the Lord the righteous judge shall give me at that
day and not to me only but unto all them also that love his appearing. I'll make
one more statement. How anybody could not love the King James Bible I don't
understand. I love the poetry of it. I just love the wording and might have to
study to understand a word but that's okay too. Thank you Lord for your word.
Let's pray. Father we thank you so much for the blessing of being able to be in
this place tonight with this group of people. Thank you for the refreshing that
it has been to me to be with pastor, his wife, and Joe, and these entire this
entire congregation of people. Thank you for the blessing of it and Lord I pray
now that as we study this passage you'd give us something. Speak into our hearts
about your love for us and our need to be faithful. Lord I just pray that you
would reveal great truth and encourage people tonight. Challenge them. We just
love you and thank you for working in our hearts. We pray in Jesus name. Amen.
That is a landmark verse that I just read but it sets in a landmark setting
of verses. And I want you to understand that when Paul pins those words in verse
8 he is not sitting in a comfortable office. He's not in his home. In truth he
is sitting in a prison called the Mamertine in Rome. It's not his first
imprisonment in Rome. In his first imprisonment in Rome he had freedom.
He was imprisoned. He was a prisoner but he was allowed to have a servant, if you
will, or a friend who would see to his needs, accompany him. He had great liberty
in speaking to the guards. This is not his first imprisonment. This is his
second imprisonment. As a matter of fact, Rome has actually sent for him. He wasn't
actually in the city when he was arrested. They sent for him and brought
him back to Rome. You say well what was the occasion of that? The occasion of
that was the first persecution that was now beginning under the wicked Emperor
Nero. It would be hard for us to understand what a vile man Nero was. He
murdered his brother. He murdered his mother so that there would be no
question that it would be him that would accede to the throne. You hear myths, did
he actually burn believers on stakes? He did actually burn believers on stakes. He
lit his raucous parties by taking Christians and soaking them in oil and
then burning them and they would provide the light and the screams. I'm not trying
to be crude. I'm just telling you it's hard to imagine how wicked the man was.
The occasion of Paul's arrest is this. Nero wanted a certain piece of property
on the Palatine. Rome is built on seven hills and the most beautiful, the
affluent hill that everybody wanted was Palatine. And the property in the house
that Nero wanted was owned by a senator who would not sell it to him. And I don't
know if Nero fiddled while Rome burned, but I do know that Nero set the fire
that burned Rome. And so outraged were the citizens of Rome that they wanted to
blame somebody and they would have come after Nero, but Nero said, no, no, no, it
wasn't me this time. And he picked that unpopular group of people whom people
in Rome hated because these people preached that there was only one true
God. And that you didn't have to go to all the temples that dotted Rome and
there in those temples worship those false gods. And you didn't have to take
your pinch of salt each year to this temple where Caesar was worshipped. That
there was one true God and he loved men and died for them on a cross and those
men could be saved. Hey, Rome loved their pagan religions and they hated the
Christians. And so Nero said, it wasn't me, it was that sect that is called
Christians, those ones that preach that there's only one God. And Paul was known
as a leader and so they sent and arrested him, brought him back in chains
to Rome and now he sits in the Mamertine. The Mamertine, if you've had the
privilege of visiting Rome, you look at it and it has an apt description of what
it is. It's actually called the rat's nest because it was infested with rats.
It was a horrible, dark place. By the way, if you looked up to your right, not too
far in the distance, you would see that great Circus Maximus, that great arena
where the horses and the chariots that maybe you saw in Ben-Hur would race
around that great arena. And literally, there were times when no doubt Paul was
imprisoned in the Mamertine. He heard the screams and the cries as the hooves of
the horses crushed the Christians that they would half bury and then run over.
If you look to your left as you're standing in the Mamertine, just a block
or two down the street is the great Roman Colosseum. And there's no doubt
that when Paul was imprisoned, on some days he would hear the screams and the
cheers of the bloodless cry as they brought those Christians into the floor
of that arena and either released the gladiators on them or the animals on
them, and with bloodlust cheered as they were torn apart. And there Paul knows
that his day is coming. Paul knows that it won't be too long before he might
well be taken to the circus or he might well be taken down to the arena. It's
amazing to me that as Paul writes these words, he says in the first part of the
chapter, he says, I charge thee there before God and the Lord Jesus Christ who
shall judge the quick and the dead at his appearing and his kingdom. Preach the
word, be instant, in season, out of season, reprove, rebuke, exhort with all long
suffering and doctrine. He's preaching to his young mentor Timothy and he says to
Timothy, hey Timothy, I know I'm sitting in prison. I know my time is about over. I
hear the cheers and the cries of those who lust for the blood, but Timothy
here's what I'm saying to you. I know it's preaching the word that landed me
here. Now Timothy, preach the word. Why would that old man tell that young man
to follow the same path that landed him in the mammertine? Here it is,
because there are some things in this world and life worth more than stuff.
Paul says, Timothy, don't sell yourself out for stuff.
Don't sell yourself for what this world offers, because there's something beyond this life.
There's something beyond this world.
There's something at His appearing that will make all of this seem so small, so trivial.
It'll run through the hands of the people that lived for it like sand or water runs
through our hands.
And so He says, Timothy, I want you to understand that I know I'm near my last, but there's
something that I'm going to receive, and there's something that you can receive.
And if Paul were standing before us tonight, he would say to all of us, there's something
better than this world.
And there's something available to all of us.
There is a crown of righteousness, a crown that God will give to each and every one who
lives their life, not for the world, but lives their life in the light of Jesus coming again,
and says, that's what I'm going to focus on.
I'm going to focus on my life in the Lord, looking for what He offers, not for what the
world offers.
Paul goes on and begins to describe what and how he arrived at this point, and that's what
I want to talk about tonight.
I want to give you three thoughts.
Before any of us, to include Paul, can receive that crown of righteousness, reaching precedes
grasping that crown.
Reaching for the crown precedes grasping.
Number two, we'll talk about obeying precedes the rewarding of the crown.
And number three, we'll talk about occupying precedes appearing.
Notice with me, reaching precedes grasping.
Paul said in verse 8, henceforth there is laid up for me.
What he's saying is, is literally there's something remaining.
After all these years that I've lived this life, both before I knew the Lord and now
that I've known the Lord, all these things that have come my way and all these ways that
I've tried to serve the Lord, there is yet something remaining for me.
And because of that which has gone before, there's something that Paul is going to receive.
It is that crown of righteousness.
Paul is reaching for faithfulness in serving the Lord.
It precedes his grasping that crown.
But long ago, Paul had decided something.
There was no more worthy goal in his life than knowing and serving the Lord Jesus.
That is far easier to say than to live.
To look at all the world has to offer.
To look at all those who are around us who are chasing what the world has to offer.
And to make this decision, I have to live in this world, I have to provide for my family
in this world, I have to serve the Lord in this world, but nothing this world has will
become the focus of my life.
The focus of my life will be to pursue Jesus Christ in this life.
Paul said it this way, that I may know Him and the power of His resurrection and the
fellowship of His sufferings being made conformable unto His death.
Listen, we know that's Bible, but if I walked into this room or into a room of most Christians
and say, I'll tell you what my passion is.
My passion is, is to know the power of the resurrection, well you've got to die first.
I'll tell you what my focus is, I want to be involved in the fellowship of the sufferings
of Jesus.
What do you mean, you're going to welcome suffering?
I don't know if welcome is the right word, but if it requires that I walk through suffering
to become more like Jesus, I'm telling you that's what I want to focus on.
I want to tell you, if I rented a room, a coliseum, and I put on a card, we're going
to have a conference, a seminar on desiring to suffer like Jesus.
I don't think we'd have many in the conference.
Now if I said, hey, here's how faith words, you can have everything you want from the
Lord, hey, here's what God owes you, hey, here's how you can be healthy and wealthy,
I think we'd fill the place up.
But I'm telling you, making what the world has and living like the world could allow
us to live, it doesn't lead to the crown that Christ is offering.
His commitment, Paul's commitment, is seen in three statements, notice them with me in
verse 7.
He says, well notice verse 6 first, I am now ready to be offered.
The time of my departure is at hand.
Paul's not a young man, he's an old man, and he knows what's going to happen.
I think Paul fully understands he is going to be martyred, he's going to be killed for
the faith.
But look what he says, I have fought a good fight.
The Christian life is often pictured as a warfare.
In this same epistle, listen to what Paul says in 2 Timothy chapter 2, you can turn
back there, look at verse 3.
Thou therefore, he's talking to Timothy, endure hardness as a good soldier of Jesus Christ.
Again, do we go to church and hope there's a sermon on enduring hardness?
Most people would avoid that and think there's something weird about that kind of preaching.
But I want to tell you, the Christian life is not an easy life in an adversarial world.
And there are times when we are expected to endure hardness.
Look at how he finishes that thought.
Not only to endure hardness, but no man that warreth entangleth himself with the affairs
of this life, that he may please him who hath chosen him to be a soldier.
I had the privilege, all of my ministry and pastoring, of pastoring Marines.
And I want you to know, I highly respect and love Marines.
And they make wonderful church members.
They understand authority and if you know where you're going, they'll gladly follow
and join in and help.
But I want to tell you, there is no Marine alive who thought that you could be excused
on a hot day from being in the field because it was too hot.
There's no Marine when they walk down the streets of Fallujah who asked to be excused
because it was a little too dangerous.
Now I'm not trying to make us Marines.
I'm not trying to be a Christian nationalist in getting you to join the Christian army.
I'm just telling you, we have become a weak generation of Christians.
It's too much sacrifice to have to go to church too much.
It's too hard.
It's too cold.
It's too hot.
I'm a little sick.
And again, I don't want you to come if you've got a fever.
I'm not saying that.
I'm just saying that where did we get the idea that being a Christian in a world that
is not a Christian world, where did we get a thought that it was supposed to be easy?
And why do we quell every time it gets a little tough?
I'm just saying, a few good believers wage this battle over a lifetime.
They don't give up and go back.
They get up if they fall and they start again and they keep pressing on when they're tired.
And when others are falling off or falling out, they stay with it.
And that was Paul's attitude then and it needs to be our attitude now.
I don't have time to read his entire story, but I don't know any man that could have suffered
more than that guy other than Jesus.
But he got up and he kept going through persecutions, all kinds of afflictions.
Man, he was stoned and left for dead outside of Lystra.
Now, that's not the path I'm called to walk.
It's not the path you're called to walk.
But goodness gracious, we are called to be enduring soldiers of Christ.
And I wonder, can we say at the end of our life, I have fought the good fight?
I was in the place of line where I was supposed to stand.
I moved forward when we were supposed to move forward.
I was in the battle when it was tough and I stood and I stayed.
And Paul says it ought to be the goal of every one of us to fight the good fight.
He tells us something about his life as well.
He says, I have finished my course.
Being faithful over a lifetime is not just a war to be won,
it's a race to be run.
The Christian life, by the way, is not just a dash,
it's a marathon.
Over the years that I pastored, I saw so many people
that would come and I honestly,
the first three or four weeks they were there,
I thought Dwight L. Moody had come to Heritage
and man, this was great.
And then slowly, they faded.
I'll say something, I don't want to be a statistic
of having started and not finished.
I love fast cars, I love cars, I like NASCAR.
I like racing, I like that.
Forgive me.
One thing I've never understood,
I've never understood being excited
about the guy that won the poll.
So when he was in time trials, he went the fastest
and he gets to start the race in first.
Now the truth is, most of the time,
when you win the poll, you have set your car up
to win the poll but not go the distance.
And most of the time, people that win the poll
don't win the race.
Now all I'm saying is, is I don't care much
about being the fastest on the first lap,
I care about being in first place on the last lap.
And I think the spirit of believers today ought to be,
I want to start good, I want to start great
but I want to finish strong.
And Paul says, I have run my race, I've finished my course.
I used to jog.
I never would call it running but I did jog.
And I would run three miles a day, every day.
I did it for 10 or 12 years,
that's why I have knee surgeries now.
But I also quit running when two 70-year-old women
power walked past me, all right.
But I remember thinking to myself, at some point,
I ran the same basic three miles every day,
six days a week and I remember thinking to myself,
at some point, this will get easy.
At some point, I'll probably have to go to five miles
because this three miles will get so easy.
And here's my testimony and I mean it,
not on one day did that three miles get easy
over 10 or 12 years.
As a matter of fact, most of the time, every day,
on the same three miles that I was running,
I would have to say to myself, be a man.
Put one foot in front of the other,
my lungs are burning, my legs are hurting
and I would have to say, be a man, finish, finish, finish.
Paul says, I've finished my course.
And brother, there were times when I was so tired,
Paul would say, I could barely lift my head up,
much less my feet.
There were times when friends would forsake me.
There were times when I knew I was trying
to do the right thing, but people would come against me.
There were times when Satan fought so hard,
but he said, I may not have run fast
and I may have had to tell myself,
put one foot in front of the other,
but bless God, I finished.
Can I tell you my goal in life
and I hope your goal in life?
I'm gonna finish with the Lord.
I do not wanna be that guy who used to go to church.
I don't wanna be the guy who used to read his Bible.
I don't wanna be the guy that used to have prayers answered.
I don't wanna be the guy that used to care about lost souls.
I want to finish strong for the Lord.
I wanna be able like Paul to say,
I have finished my course.
Then he said this, a third statement.
He said, I have kept the faith.
Paul had fought and run the race
according to the word and the will of God.
He had strived lawfully.
He loved people.
He exhorted people.
He rebuked when he was necessary, but he was patient.
He was long-suffering.
He was meek.
He was humble.
He never made himself the big deal.
It was always about the Lord and reaching people.
He was faithful to the word of God,
faithful to the testimony of the Lord.
He never veered from the course for the sake of expediency.
He kept the faith.
When Paul finally grasped that crown,
remember that he has spent a lifetime reaching for it.
He has battled ever since the Damascus Road.
He has faced enemy after enemy, but refused to quit.
He has gone forward.
He has finished his course.
He has come to the end,
and he knows he's about to be martyred,
but bless God, he has kept the faith.
He has not recanted.
He has not trimmed the message for his entire lifetime.
From the Damascus Road on,
he has said, Jesus, I will suffer with you.
Jesus, I want to know your power through the resurrection.
Jesus, I am pressing toward the mark.
I am pressing toward the mark.
I don't care what has gone behind.
I'm following you,
and I'm looking for the day when you appear.
I can have that crown.
I have people all the time telling me,
or sometimes say to me, well, I don't want crowns.
I just want to praise the Lord.
You don't want crowns.
That means you don't want to live for the Lord.
I want a crown.
You say, why do you want a crown?
You want to wear that thing?
No, I love my hair.
I want to have that crown,
because here's how I see heaven working out.
We're gonna take the crown or crowns that we receive,
and we're gonna toss them at the feet of Jesus,
and we're gonna have the wonderful blessing
of being able to express to him,
hey, this is not mine.
This is yours.
I think we're gonna get them back,
and I think we're gonna give them back.
and I think we're gonna give them back,
and if you want to miss out on that,
okay, you be fake humble.
I want to participate in that,
and so bless God.
I am going to reach for that crown
until the day of his appearing.
Here's second.
I'm going to obey,
because I know that obedience
is what must proceed being rewarded.
We've spoken much of Paul's effort
and much of Paul's commitment,
but I want to be careful
that it is not about some superior human being
making an extraordinary effort.
He did make an extraordinary effort,
but he's not a superior human being.
Paul is no different than you and I.
Paul did not have angel wings under his cloak.
Paul did not have any measure of the Spirit
that we do not have access
to the measure of the Spirit.
Paul had a calling of God
and a pathway of life,
and I have a calling of God
and pathway of life,
and you have a calling of God
and pathway of life.
All I'm saying is,
is that when Paul was shipwrecked
and when Paul was left for dead
outside of Lystra and got back up,
and when Paul and Silas sang
down in that dungeon in Philippi,
and when Paul was in the Mamertine,
and when Paul was martyred,
he did nothing more than his reasonable service,
because it is what God had laid out for Paul.
God is the righteous judge.
It is God who is judging our faithfulness.
It is God who is watching our lives,
and when Paul receives that crown,
it will be because he has been faithful
to what God has called him to do.
I don't have to walk Paul's path.
I don't have to walk another preacher's path.
I don't have to walk your path.
You don't have to walk my path,
but each and every one of us
have been given a plan of life,
and God is watching for us
to do our reasonable service.
You see, that crown is reserved for Paul,
but you have one,
and I have one that is reserved for us,
and God is watching.
God is keeping track,
and we have the possibility of receiving that crown,
but it only comes when we live lives
that are obedient to the Lord,
obedient to his call,
obedient to his path.
Can you imagine the glorious day
when you stand before the Lord,
and the Lord says to you,
well done, thou good and faithful servant,
and you're not gonna stand before the Lord
when he's got that crown of righteousness
because you reached for it,
because you lived focusing on his appearing.
You lived focused on his plan for your life.
You're not going to say, oh shucks, no, I don't want that.
You're going to be glad.
You're going to receive it gladly.
Third, occupying precedes appearing.
If we're ever going to get to that crown, then we've got to understand that reaching
for it has to be part of our life.
We've got to be focused on that goal just like Paul was.
Whether it takes us through suffering, whether it takes us to the mountaintop of victory,
we've got to be pressing towards that mark.
We've got to be obedient to the plan of life that God has given us.
If you're a secular job and serving in a local church, God created that path for you and
your path is as valuable as pastors are mine.
Our path is as valuable as Paul's.
We may not be called to the shipwreck or to the jailhouse, but our path of obedience
is as essential as Paul's was.
And then, we've got to occupy our place until Jesus calls for us or until Jesus comes.
I want you to note something about the crown.
Go back to verse 8, henceforth there is laid up for me a crown of righteousness, which
the Lord, the righteous judge, shall give me at that day.
Not today, at that day.
Here's a wonderful true statement.
Jesus is coming again.
And at His appearing, we're going to be brought up from the grave or caught up in the air
and changed and we're going to stand before Him at the great Bema Seat.
The Bema Seat of judgment is not to judge us for whether we are sinners or not or whether
– to be at the Bema Seat is to have received Christ as your Savior.
But please understand this.
The living of our life and whether it has been lived for Him will be a matter of judgment
at the Bema Seat.
And all of a sudden that focus will seem very important.
What did I focus on?
What did I give myself to?
What occupied my mind?
What filled my heart?
Was there a little piece of the week, maybe a little piece of the day that was given to
the Lord, but primarily the focus of my life was chasing what the world had or thinking
that I had to do all that the world said?
Or was I in my place doing what the Lord wanted me to do?
Was that the focus of my life?
Because until the Lord appears, He has given us the command to occupy.
He called His ten servants, the parable says, delivered them ten pounds and said unto them,
Occupy till I come.
God gave each of us a gift or gifts.
I'm not a two or three gift man, I'm a one gift.
You say, what's your gift preacher?
I think it's to teach and preach the Word.
Not everybody agrees with that, but I'm convinced.
And Jesus says, I'm going to give you that gift.
Don't put that down.
Don't put that away.
Well, I've reached retirement age.
Yeah, I didn't give you that gift till retirement.
I gave you that gift.
Just like I told in that parable, you occupy.
You use that until I come.
Your gift isn't preaching, maybe.
I don't know what your gift is, but I want to tell you, your gift is as vital to the
ministry of Jesus in this church and in this community and in this world as any gift I
have or pastor has.
And God's command to you and me and pastor is, you use that.
You occupy until I come.
God may move you from here, but use that gift.
Maybe God is speaking to you tonight and asking you, are you so focused on other things that
you're not focused on using what I've given you to be used in my service?
I come to this great point.
I said earlier, I don't want to be a statistic, and I don't want you to be a statistic, but
I'm telling you that the spirit of our generation is not to be as Paul, focused on the appearing
of Jesus.
It's to be so distracted by the world that we barely remember it.
Can I give you an example?
Skip down to verse 10, for Demas hath forsaken me, having loved this present world, and is
departed unto Thessalonica.
Sometimes we think it could never be me, and there's very little doubt in my mind that
Demas ever thought it could be him.
I'm not for the sake of time, but I can take you to places where Demas was of great value
to Paul and the ministry.
Demas had been gifted of the Lord with a gift, but Demas had the same problem then that so
many believers have today, and that is the world has a siren call that is always calling.
It's always calling.
There's always a distraction.
There's always something else to focus our mind, our heart, our talent, our energy, our
treasure.
There's always something else.
And I'm saying to you people, and I'm saying to myself, that we have got to resist that
call because our focus must be His appearing, and using what He has gifted us with, and
using what He has provided to us, and using what He is allowing us to steward, to focus
on Him and His appearing, and using it for the building of the church, and the building
of our homes, and the building of our lives, and the reconciliation with those that surround
us.
It is focused on Him, focused on Him.
It does not mean that we don't live life.
It does not mean that we don't buy homes and cars.
It does not mean that we don't have careers, but He is our focus.
I occupy, until He comes, more than anything in my life.
I want you to know that I wasted 23 years of my life.
I wasn't vile.
I wasn't wicked.
I was a daddy.
I was a husband.
I loved my wife.
But I had no room for God in my life.
I cannot undo that.
But I stand here tonight saying this, that I don't want to waste another day, another
hour of my life pursuing something that does not please Him and His appearing.
Yes, I have to live in this world.
Yes, I have to provide.
Yes, I have to work.
But He is my focus, even in the work.
I don't ever want the testimony of Demas.
God, help us.
Because the day is coming when Jesus will appear.
And on that day when He appears, do not misunderstand me.
I have not lived a perfect life since 23 years old.
Thank God for His mercy and His long-suffering.
But I want the trajectory of my life to be ever focused on Him.
And when He comes, I want to be able to say, I fought the good fight.
I didn't run the fastest.
I'm sure not the prettiest runner.
It's a big blob moving.
But I did finish my course, and I've kept the faith.
And henceforth, there is laid up for me a crown of righteousness.
I want to be found faithful.
Let me tell you a quick story, and I'll quit.
Not far from here, a place called Antietam Creek.
September 16th, pretty close to our date, 1862.
And General Lee was riding, catching up with his armies.
He had been in a council of war all day, setting up the battlements and so on, and unbeknownst
to him, his entire battle line, every brigade, every group, was in his saddlebags and fell
out.
It was discovered by a Union lieutenant who immediately took it to the Union General McClellan,
and McClellan had in his hand the position of every brigade, every part of the fighting
force of Lee, how strong they were, where they were, he knew everything.
It's hard to imagine the advantage that gave them.
The weakest point of the line was in the very center of the line, and it was occupied by
a fellow named Colonel John B. Gordon and his brigade of Georgia boys.
Lee and Longstreet in the middle of the night rode to that place and said to Gordon, you
have got to hold this.
You cannot, you cannot retreat.
You cannot be routed.
You must hold this.
If they come through here and route you, they'll roll up both sides of the line, it's over,
they will march straight to Richmond.
John B. Gordon, one of my heroes, became governor of Georgia and a senator from Georgia
and he was an eloquent Christian orator preacher.
He said to Lee that night, only death or the evening tomorrow will cause me to leave this
line.
The next day, the first charge came at about daylight, 6 or 6.30 in the morning.
It was the worst position possible, the middle of the line, the Union had the high ground
and they charged down on the Confederate line and they held.
Another charge came about an hour later.
About that time, Gordon was shot in his right foot, kept his sword as a cane but he wouldn't
retreat.
About an hour after that, in the same battle, he was shot through the thigh on the right
leg, broke a bone, but he kept his sword.
His men kept saying, Gordon to the rear, Gordon to the rear, but he wouldn't.
That retreat, they backed and again, about noon, they charged again and he was shot in
the left wrist.
Same moments, he was shot in the left shoulder.
That one so broke his shoulder that he fell and they laid him against a tree but before
he lost consciousness, he said, do not take me off this field, I gave my word.
He was able to stand again and they put him against the tree and he was shot a fifth time
in the jaw, into the right side of his jaw, came out the left, shattered all of his teeth.
He fell over and would have drowned in his own blood except for bullet holes in his hat
that let his blood out.
That group of men stood and held that line that day.
They took Gordon to the hospital, still alive.
He was seven months before he could leave the hospital.
About three months after that, Lee visited him.
We don't know what passed in that conversation but I will tell you this, that at the end
of the war, when the Confederates surrendered to the Union, the highest honor was to lead
the Confederate Army for the last time and that was bestowed upon, now, General John
B. Gordon.
By the way, he surrendered to a character man named Chamberlain.
You say, preacher, do you have a point in that?
Yeah.
Here's the point.
I can cite for you story after story, true story of men who are faithful to a cause that's
not even a righteous cause.
I can show you men and women who literally give all of their energy and all of their
time and all of their treasure to things that someday will just slide through their
hands.
And yet we as servants of the Lord have the opportunity to focus all that we have and
to live for him every day of our lives, following the path that he's laid out for us, not for
someone else, for us.
And in that last moment, when we stand before him, receiving that crown, the crown of righteousness,
and can you imagine for eternity being able to acknowledge that it was not me, it was
what you did in my life and through my life, and to be able to cast that crown at the feet
of Jesus.
Nothing you own, nothing you will become in your career, nothing you could possess, no
place you could go in that moment will be even a trifling comparison to what it is to
have that before the Lord.
So let us say to ourselves, let me focus on him, his calling, his gifting, and let
me be one of those that is found to be faithful to the very end.
Let's pray.
Father, I do not want to be Demas, and I know no one in this crowd wants to be Demas,
but there are so many things from this world that call to us.
Oh my goodness, there's wealth, sports, so much that can distract, possessions, places,
people.
Lord would you help us tonight, would you help every one of us tonight to purpose in
our hearts.
I've got to live here, I've got to have a job, I've got to enjoy life, and God gives
me that capability, I don't have to live on a mountaintop in a commune, but I do have
to carefully guard my focus.
I have to understand that all the little stuff, the bling and the baubles that the world offers,
none of it goes when Jesus comes.
The only thing that will matter when he appears is have I been faithful to his call, have
I been focused on living for him, have I occupied, have I reached, have I obeyed?
God would you speak to me now, and if in your examination of my heart, Lord, you see something
that I need to correct, you see something in my attention, something in my focus that
I need to bring back to the Lord, and not pursue it, but pursue him.
It may be a hard choice, it may be something I have to put down, put away, it may be something
I love, but it's distracting me from the Lord, it's distracting my family from the Lord.
I don't want Demas' testimony, I want Paul's.
I can't do what Paul did, I can't write like he writes and preach like he preached, but
I can be faithful to what you've given me to do, and I can make my focus, my focus,
my focus pleasing you.
I'm looking for that day of your appearing, so God would you help us to be found faithful,
and Holy Spirit in this moment, in every heart, would you search the corners and the deep
recesses, the dark places, and where we have lost focus, where we have turned our ear to
the siren's call, would you just speak to us, would you remind us, would you teach us
and bring to remembrance where we need to be, and I pray that our decision tonight,
individually but as a group, would be, I will be found faithful.
No matter the wounds.
No matter the difficulties, no matter the distractions, I will stay focused on the Lord.
Help us, I pray in Jesus' name, amen.