show at the conclusion of the service. I'm going to preach the message first,
and then we'll watch these update videos. I do trust that there'll be a blessing to you,
not only the message from the Word of God, especially, of course, as we look to the
truth of God's Word, but then as we have the opportunity to see the work of missions
and to see the investment that we've made, as we've given, as we've prayed.
And what a tremendous blessing this evening, as we have as our theme here for Mark 16 and verse 15,
the Bible, a very familiar verse of Scripture, and He said unto them,
Go ye into all the world, and preach the gospel to every creature.
We're familiar with that verse of Scripture. It's a verse of Scripture that is used often
with regard to the work of missions. Of course, the truth, as we would refer to this verse of
Scripture, is this is the Great Commission. We read it in the book of Matthew here in Mark. We
read it in Luke and John, also in the book of Acts. And we read that God has given us the Great
Commission. Someone wisely observed that the Great Commission is not an option to be considered,
but a command to be obeyed. Think about that. The Great Commission is not an option to be
considered. Rather, it is a command to be obeyed. And I like that quote. I like that thought.
And we need to fulfill our responsibility here to the Great Commission. I've titled the
message tonight, as you see in the bulletin there, Finding My Place in World Missions.
Finding my place. You say that yourself. I say that myself. Finding my place. Where is
my place in world missions? Do I have a place in world missions? The answer is yes.
And we need to find what our place is in world missions. And this evening, as we think about
the work of world missions, we think about the work of evangelism, the responsibility that we
have to reach the world with the gospel of Jesus Christ, we understand that this task that is
before us, that God has given us instruction with regard to completing the task. Not only has He
given us instruction with regard to completing the task, but I'm so thankful that He empowers us
to complete the task. This is a task that is beyond us. It is a task that we cannot, in our
power, in our own strength, we cannot complete this task. But in dependence upon the Lord,
we find that He will enable us to fulfill what He has called us to do. I'm thankful for the
opportunity that we have to be a light in this community. And as we look at the truth of world
missions and we think about the place that we have individually and then corporately as a church,
we find that we have a responsibility to reach our Jerusalem, and at the same time,
to reach the uttermost as we have our map on the world, on our wall, the world map that reminds us
every time we come into this building, we're reminded about world missions. We see on this
side of the auditorium, send the light, and we sing that powerful gospel song of send the light,
the blessed gospel light. And then we see over here a map and all of the pictures and the
missions, and what a joy to think about the opportunity that we have to be engaged, to be
involved in world missions. I believe this evening that if you're here and you're saved,
that you have a place in world missions. We each have a place in world missions.
Let me just share with you three thoughts this evening. Number one, pray. Pray. We think about
world missions and I think what is my place, finding my place in world missions? I believe
it starts with prayer. I've said this many times over the years. Prayer is a distinct privilege to
the child of God. It is reserved for us as the people of God that we can go to the throne of
grace, that we can seek the very face of God, that we have many promises with regard to prayer,
that we have a God who hears and answers prayer. We hear that so often. We're so familiar with that
truth, but I hope this evening that we would stand in awe of that statement, that we recognize
how wonderful it is that we indeed have a God who hears and answers prayer. You think about the
billions of people around the globe that do not know the Lord Jesus Christ. They do not know
Jehovah God. They're serving some false deity, some idol, and they're praying and they're
seeking to appease, but they have a God, little g, that cannot hear. We have a God that hears us
and He answers. It's amazing to understand that truth. I wonder this evening as we think about
our place in world missions and we think about this aspect of prayer, I wonder this evening that
if we were to go and evaluate our prayer time and our daily time of prayer, is there a dedicated
time of prayer in our lives for world missions? Is it something that we consider? Think about this.
Turn to the book of Matthew, if you will, in chapter number 9. As we think about this place
in world missions, in fact, this is a place that every single child of God, we ought to, every
single one of us ought to be praying about world missions. We think about the truth, the statement
that is given here in Matthew 9 from the Lord Jesus Christ, the instruction from our Savior
with regard to prayer. And He says this in Matthew 9, in verse number 36, the Bible sets the scene
for us and it says, but when He, speaking of Jesus, saw the multitudes, He was moved with compassion
on them. Why? Because they fainted and were scattered abroad as sheep having no shepherd.
Then saith He unto His disciples, notice what He says, the harvest truly is plenteous, but the
labors are few. We know that to be the case. We see that this has been the case for many generations
and we find that Jesus gives this truth here in the passage of Scripture as He's speaking to the
disciples and He speaks about the harvest being plenteous, but the labors being few. I mentioned
to you before how many churches are without pastors, how many communities do not have churches,
how many mission fields, how many regions of the world, how many countries have no gospel witness,
and you think about the labors are few. Someone shared with me last week the number of churches
in their area in a radius of about 50 miles of churches that did not have pastors and it was
staggering. They're down in the south and so there's a lot more churches within the 50-mile
radius of where they were located than maybe other parts of the nation, but it was staggering. So,
what does Jesus say to the disciples? We're familiar with the passage of Scripture, but let
me say this, being familiar with the passage of Scripture is a lot different than applying the
passage of Scripture. When I mention Matthew 9, 36-38, many of us tonight know the passage.
But when I say that Jesus said the labors are few, He said that the harvest is plenteous,
but the labors are few, we know what the next statement is that Jesus makes.
Pray. Pray ye therefore the Lord of the harvest that He will send forth laborers into His harvest.
And I just wonder this evening as we understand the truth of it, but when's the last time or how
often are we praying to the Lord of the harvest that He'd send forth laborers?
That we are actually fulfilling what Jesus said to us to do. Is the request of Jesus that He gave
to the disciples, is that part of my prayer life? Is that part of your prayer life? It ought to be.
Amen? It ought to be. We ought to be praying to the Lord of the harvest that He would send forth
laborers into His harvest. And as we pray that prayer, then we get to see God answer
that prayer, because God hears and answers prayer, and He answers specific prayer.
And I'd love to see God send forth a laborer from our congregation. Amen? I think it'd be wonderful,
and not called by the pastor or called by the parent, but called by God and answer that call
and go. That'd be wonderful. But if we're not praying to the Lord of the harvest that He'd
send forth laborers, why would we expect that someone would say, here am I, send me?
Think about the request of the Apostle Paul. Notice in Colossians chapter number four,
and I'll look at two references, the Apostle Paul actually on a number of occasion
requested prayer with regard to the work of missions in Colossians four, in verses two
through four. Notice what Paul says. He says, continue in prayer and watch in the same with
thanksgiving. And then he directs them specifically with regard to a prayer request, really with regard
to the work of missions. With all praying also for us that God would open unto us a door of utterance
to speak the mystery of Christ, for which I am also in bonds, that I may make it manifest as I
ought to speak. Man, that we'd be praying for open doors. We'd be praying for those opportunities,
not only opportunities for ourselves, but opportunities for our brothers and sisters
in Christ, those that we attend church together, those that are church members together, that we're
praying that God would open doors of opportunity, that we're praying for our missionaries that God
would open doors of opportunity, doors of utterance. Notice what Paul says.
says in 2 Thessalonians, it's very similar
to what we read here in 2 Thessalonians 3.
It's interesting, in 1 Thessalonians in chapter five,
he simply says this, brethren, pray for us.
And it's a broad statement, and obviously,
the request of prayer and understanding
the importance of prayer.
But as he's writing to that same church
in 2 Thessalonians chapter number three,
beginning in verse number one, Paul says,
finally, brethren, pray for us.
What does he ask that they pray for?
That the word of the Lord may have free course
and be glorified, even as it is with you,
and that we may be delivered from unreasonable
and wicked men, for all men have not faith.
Have you realized that truth of verse number two?
All men do not have faith.
And we pray that God would give deliverance
from unreasonable and wicked men.
You know, there are people that wanna silence the church.
They wanna silence the gospel from going forth.
But we pray, and we pray that as Paul says here,
that the word of the Lord may have free course.
I'm so thankful that as Paul is writing to Timothy,
he says, listen, I'm thankful that I'm bound,
but God's word is not bound.
Aren't you thankful for that?
What a blessing to think about the opportunity
that we have when we think about my place in world missions
for each and every one of us,
prayer is part of my place in world missions.
And part of my prayer time daily ought to be,
there should be a dedicated time in my prayer time daily
with regard to the work of missions,
to reaching the world with the gospel of Jesus Christ.
I think of this number two, not only to pray,
but to give, to give.
Obviously, we understand that our missionaries,
it requires funds for them to be able to go to the field
and to serve in the capacity in which they're serving.
In fact, many of the missionaries,
if not all of them on our wall this evening,
you find that there's a few of them
that are in the United States,
and so it really wouldn't be applicable to them.
But to those that are abroad in a different country,
most countries of the world,
before you enter into their nation as a missionary,
they require that there's some level of guarantee
that you are financially stable,
that you're not going to take from their economy.
So guess what that means?
That means missionaries come to a church like ours.
We know it, we have missionaries.
The Ballou family, they're gonna come next week.
They're gonna be in Idaho.
And so certainly they can get a job in America
because they're US citizens, but they're gonna go.
And what a blessing for them to have support
for a couple of years that they won't have to work a job,
Lord willing, and be dedicated completely
to starting a church and not have that responsibility
of working a job and full-time
and then trying to part-time pastor a church
and start a church.
And man, the missionaries that come
that are going all over the world that we can give.
So that they can be on the field,
so that they can serve, so they can do the work
that God has called them to.
We pray, but we give.
Giving financially to missions is separate from tithing.
It's just a separate thing.
And I say personally in my own life,
and I'm not saying this boastfully or pridefully,
but I am so thankful for the privilege
that we have to give to world missions.
We watch these missionary update letters, videos,
when we hear these missionary update letters
and we hear about what God is doing
and how God is working, I understand that a part of that,
and it doesn't matter how small of a part of that,
but a part of that is an investment
that personally I have made in world missions.
What a blessing.
What a privilege to give to the work of world missions
that we can take of the resources
that God has blessed us with,
and we can take those and we can say,
I'm going to specifically give these funds for missions,
that the work of missions can go forward.
Think about this, turn to the book of Philippians,
if you will, in Philippians chapter number four,
it's a designated giving that is for a specific purpose,
that of world missions.
In Philippians chapter number four,
I'm thankful that someone taught me many years ago,
not only about the truth of tithing,
but about the truth of giving to world missions,
and it has been a great joy in our lives,
the 20 plus years that Holly and I have been married,
and then even before we were married as an individual
to be able to give to the work of world missions.
Notice in Philippians four in verse number 14,
the Bible says, notwithstanding ye have well done
that ye did communicate with my affliction.
Now you Philippians know also
that in the beginning of the gospel,
when I departed from Macedonia,
no church communicated with me
as concerning giving and receiving,
but ye only, so Paul is commending them,
thanking them for their giving to the work of missions,
we know that Paul went on three missionary journeys,
he was a, you study the book of Acts,
and you can see those missionary journeys,
and he says how you communicated with me,
with specifically, he says with giving and receiving,
notice in verse 16, for even in Thessalonica,
ye sent once and again unto my necessity.
But notice what he says, not because I desire a gift,
but I desire fruit that may abound to your account.
Now listen, God's economy is different than our economy,
and God has designed it such,
so often people wanna talk about
what's the return on my investment,
the return on investment in missions is out of this world,
and I don't say that just tongue in cheek to be funny,
but the reality is that it is an eternal return.
When you think about that return on that investment,
and Paul says, listen, I'm not desiring a gift,
but I'm desiring, listen, that fruit
that may abound to your account,
and somehow, in God's economy, he has designed it,
and determined that as we give to world missions,
as an individual, as we give to world missions,
and the work of missions is done,
then at some level, there's a blessing for us
in what is being done, it's amazing.
It's fruit that would abound to our account.
It says in verse number 18,
but I have all and abound, I am full,
having received of Epaphroditus
the things which were sent from you,
an odor of a sweet smell, a sacrifice acceptable,
well-pleasing to God.
What great truth in verse number 18
that it is a sacrifice, and certainly,
there are times in which we make sacrifice
in giving to God with regard to this thing of missions,
and Paul says it is a sacrifice that's acceptable,
and it's well-pleasing to God.
So often, this promise of verse 19 of Philippians 4
is really taken out of context,
but really, the context of this promise
is with regard to giving to world missions.
Notice what he says in verse number 19,
but my God shall supply all your need
according to his riches in glory by Christ Jesus.
How much do we give to missions?
Pray and ask God.
I don't have a formula.
I know what a tithe is, it's easy to calculate.
Really, it is, right, it's pretty simple.
Missions, there's nothing that's in the word of God
that says here's how much of your income
you're to give to missions,
but can I tell you that as you give to missions,
God will bless, and you'll be able to see
that this is an eternal investment.
I believe that every single person,
every single child of God
ought to be involved in giving to missions.
I just believe that.
I believe that as we come to that place
and say, well, things are tight,
just start with a dollar, honestly,
just do something, and see God bless, and see God work.
We think about the, sometimes we have this perspective
that we can't do much, so we do nothing at all,
but the reality is little is much when God is in it.
The reality is that when Jesus saw those people giving,
he says of this widow that cast in really the least,
he said that she gave more than they did.
Why?
Because they all gave out of their abundance,
but she gave everything that she had.
It's just that God's ways are not our ways,
and so as we have an opportunity, we say,
God, I don't have much, but what I have,
I'm gonna invest it in missions,
and I'm gonna seek to be involved in giving.
I'm gonna pray.
I'm gonna give.
And then finally this evening, I would say go.
Look at Acts 1 and verse number eight.
I mentioned that the Great Commission,
as we started this evening in Mark 16,
is given in each of the four Gospels,
and then also in the book of Acts.
In Acts 1 and verse number eight,
we find that the Bible speaks and gives us here
the record of the Great Commission.
In Acts 1 and verse number eight, Jesus says,
that you shall receive power,
after that the Holy Ghost has come upon you,
and I'm thankful that he enables us
for the work of missions.
It says that ye shall be witnesses unto me,
both in Jerusalem, and I'm gonna stop there.
We'll get to the rest in just a moment,
because when I speak of going,
first it starts locally,
as coworkers together in reaching the world
with the Gospel of Jesus Christ.
I know I've said this before,
but it's worth repeating this evening.
If you were to go and look at our missions map,
if you push every single tile on that wall
and see every single light,
if you push the red button
and see them all light up at one time,
you will not find a light,
you will not find a tile of missionaries
to Oakton, Virginia.
Why?
because we're the missionaries to Oakden, Virginia.
We're the missionaries to Fairfax.
We're the missionaries to Vienna.
We are the missionaries.
We are the light that God has placed in this community.
And we take that responsibility
and we need to take that responsibility seriously
and we need to understand that we have a responsibility
to go locally.
And as we go locally, what does that look like?
We know that we have coworkers, we have neighbors,
there are friends, there are people that we interact with,
there are people at the store.
Ms. Joyce shared with us a testimony on Wednesday evening
about the worker there at Wegmans
that she gave some gospel literature to.
You think about doctors and nurses and appointments
and auto care, all of those types of things.
Wherever our daily routine takes us,
there's opportunity for us to go.
Someone said this,
being a missionary doesn't require crossing a sea.
Sometimes it's just crossing the street.
Sometimes we have the idea of being a missionary
is that we go to some foreign land
that has a different culture and a different language
and a different time zone
and that means that we're a missionary.
The reality is that we're a missionary here.
God's called us.
God's given us a responsibility to let our light so shine,
not just locally, but we think about the aspect of globally.
It says, and you shall be witnesses unto me.
That word both is significant
because really the idea in Acts 1A,
when he says both in Jerusalem and all Judea
and then Samaria and to the uttermost part of the earth,
that word carries with the idea is at the same time.
So we're to be reaching our Jerusalem
at the same time of reaching Judea, Samaria
and the uttermost.
And we understand the region geographically
with the nation of Israel
and you understand the early church there in Jerusalem
and you understand the geographic implication
of what Jesus is saying to these disciples.
And then if we would by application
take that and apply it for us this evening
and we understand that our Jerusalem,
as I mentioned just a moment ago, is our locale.
It's our region.
It's where we are.
And then you just keep making a circle bigger and bigger
until you encircle the whole globe.
And that's the uttermost part of the earth
as verse number eight ends.
And so this evening when we think about praying
and giving and going and we say,
I wanna find my place in world missions.
God, I want you to use me.
I want you to use me in this area of world missions,
of reaching people with the gospel of Jesus Christ.
God, I'm gonna make a commitment
to pray specifically about missions.
That I'm gonna carve out some time daily, weekly
to pray about missions.
I'm gonna pray that request that Jesus gave
that we would pray to the Lord of the harvest
that he would send forth laborers into his harvest.
I'm gonna give.
And God, I'm gonna go.
I'm gonna go locally.
But then I'd say this,
I ought to be willing to go wherever he calls me to go.
Amen?
I was at BIMI last week and someone gave the testimony
about the oldest person that they knew
that surrendered to missions and went through BIMI.
Nearly 65 years old.
I said, wow.
That's encouraging.
Because you know what someone decided?
Whoever that, I don't know who the person is.
I have no idea who they are.
I didn't ask, I wouldn't ask.
But you know what they did?
They were just willing to go.
It's like Isaiah, here am I, send me.
I think really all of us should have that perspective.
God's not gonna call all of us to go somewhere globally.
But he might.
It's amazing as I consider the work of world missions.
We're gonna watch these videos here in just a few minutes.
And as we look at these videos,
I want you to think about what God is doing
and how God is working.
The Thomas family in Ukraine, we'll watch a video from them.
The Vallis family down in the Turks and Caicos Islands,
we'll watch a video from them.
The Clement family over in Liverpool, England,
watch a video from them.
And then the last, I don't know if I got them in the order.
However the order is, is fine that you do back there, bud.
But the fourth family is the McKinney family,
serving the Lord in Bolivia.
I want you to think about those servants of the Lord.
They found what their place was in world missions.
And say, God, I wanna know what my place is
in world missions.
I wanna do, God, what you want me to do.
I wanna pray, give.
God, I'm willing to go.
Pray that maybe God would raise someone up
from within our congregation.
What a blessing.
What a tremendous blessing to have the privilege
of being able to be the sending church
of someone that goes into world missions.
It's exciting.
What is my place in world missions?
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the opportunity
to have service this evening.
As we've briefly considered this thought
of finding my place in world missions,
I pray, God, that you've used your word
in the hearts of your people.
And that we take a few moments
before we watch these videos
to truly evaluate our own lives.
To evaluate our level of surrender.
I know often we sing, I surrender all.
God, that we would evaluate our prayer lives.
That we would evaluate specifically our giving to missions.
Not our tithing, but our giving to missions.
That we would evaluate this evening
our obedience to the Great Commission.
Would you move and work as only you can
in these few moments of invitation.
We'll thank you for all that you'll do
for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
We'll have a brief invitation
before we watch the videos this evening.
Kimberly's gonna play quietly on the piano.
Maybe you just need to come to this altar tonight
and pray and ask the Lord to help you.
Maybe God spoke to you specifically
about something from his word
with regard to your place in world missions.
The altar is open as Kimberly plays.