Acts chapter number 18 this evening.
As we continue to prepare for our missions conference,
it starts on Saturday with our opportunity
to have our international banquet dinner
and looking forward to it.
I love missions conference.
I just really do.
I love revival meetings,
but there's something special about the missions conference
that almost has a mix of revival meeting
and also the exposure and the awareness
of world evangelization and the importance
of fulfilling our responsibility
and how we can be co-laborers together.
It's just an exciting time.
I absolutely love missions conference
and I'm looking forward to with great anticipation
of what God is going to do.
I find it vitally important that we are prepared spiritually
when we enter into these special meetings.
I was sharing with somebody even this afternoon
that the first year, year and a half of pastoring,
I would always feel very conflicted
when we were entering into a season of a special meeting,
a missions conference or revival meeting,
and I felt like as I was praying about what to preach
that the Holy Spirit of God was leading me
into a direction with regard to preaching,
but then I felt like I can't preach on those subjects
because that's what they're going to preach on.
That's what the evangelist is gonna be preaching on.
That's what the missionary is gonna be preaching on
and I would feel somewhat conflicted
and have this internal struggle, if you will,
and I remember having a conversation
with Brother Palmer, Sean, a great friend, mentor of mine,
and he said this.
He worked in evangelism for years, he still does,
and he says, you know, the more work that a pastor does
in preparing the congregation for a special meeting,
the greater work that God is able to accomplish.
He said, what I found throughout the years of ministry
is that a church can either be revival resistant
or revival ready, and I thought that was quite interesting
and it really gave me a sense of relief.
Of course, I desired to follow the leadership
of the Holy Spirit of God.
It was my brain that was getting in the way
and causing the conflict on whether I should
or shouldn't preach on those particular things,
and if you've not preached before,
you might not understand that,
but that's just something occasionally that you deal with,
and so I desire personally, but I desire for our church
to be prepared for the special meetings.
I've talked to missionaries before
that they enter into a church
and they're telling me these firsthand accounts,
and so I'm just believing
that what they're telling me is true,
and they enter into a church, they enter in,
and there will be some members that will be standing
in the foyer area, maybe on a porch
or whatever the greeting area is
that the particular church has,
and the members will say, oh, how are you today?
You know, what are you doing here?
And they're like, well, we're here
for the missions conference,
and the members of the church are like,
oh, we're having a missions conference.
They walk into the church and there's no sign whatsoever
that missions conference is gonna take place,
there's no flags or any kind of decor
that would give indication,
and missionaries have shared that type of story with me,
and I just wonder in that situation,
no doubt that there's little to no spiritual preparation
on the part of the people to be ready
for what God is going to do in and through those services.
Over the last few weeks, we've looked at some things
on Sunday night with regard to God has a plan.
We studied that, we understood that in the life of Moses.
God's plan includes his people,
and what a blessing to know that God would use us.
In fact, it's often overwhelming to think
that God would use us to accomplish his plan on this earth.
Last week on Sunday night, we talked about we have a place,
and every man must be in his place.
You have a place, I have a place,
and we need to be in our place.
We need to be doing what God has called us to do,
and of course this morning, bringing people to Jesus,
looking at that passage in Mark chapter number two.
I hope to encourage you this evening from Acts 18,
we look in this portion of scripture,
and God provides us really with the timing
right as we enter into the beginning
of this portion of scripture
with regard to Paul's second missionary journey
and his arrival in Corinth.
Now the Bible says in verse number one of Acts 18,
after these things, now understand that those three words,
they convey a large message to us.
After these things, well, what are these things?
We find that the Bible,
and we'll answer that question in just a moment,
but it says after these things,
Paul departed from Athens, notice, and came to Corinth.
The Bible tells us in verse number 10,
for I am with thee.
You remember the promise that God gave to Moses?
Certainly, I will be with thee.
God says to Paul, for I am with thee,
and no man shall set on thee to hurt thee.
Notice the statement, for I have much people in this city.
I'm gonna preach a message this evening
that I've simply entitled from verse number 10,
I have much people in this city.
As we look at the text of scripture,
we find that God provides us with timing,
that Paul departs from Athens and he arrives,
he came to Corinth.
We understand the second missionary journey,
it begins at the end of Acts chapter 15.
At the end of Acts chapter 15, beginning in verse number 36,
and throughout the first several verses of chapter 16,
we find that Paul, on this second missionary journey,
his desire is to follow up with the churches
that were established during the first missionary journey.
And we find that as those churches, what a great pattern,
by the way, of follow up and the importance
of following up with those churches,
and they've been established,
and he goes back to minister,
and we find that that portion of scripture covers that.
We enter into verse number 11 of Acts chapter 16,
and down through verse number 40,
and God provides us with a record of the work at Philippi.
Of course, we are familiar with the book of Philippians,
and the church that was established there in Philippi,
and we're mindful of the events
with regard to the ministry in Philippi.
Of course, Paul and Silas, they were imprisoned,
and they're singing, and they're praising God,
and at midnight, God delivers them miraculously,
and the jailer, sirs, what must I do to be saved?
I mean, God was working and using them,
and how wonderful it is.
We enter into the 17th chapter,
and we find that in Acts 17,
it begins with Paul and company going to Thessalonica.
As best we can tell, Paul and company
are not in Thessalonica very long.
There's some opposition that comes up,
and of course, everywhere that Paul went preaching
with those that were with him and part of the team,
they always were met with conflict and controversy.
By the way, God's work is always going to be opposed.
We see that throughout history,
as you look throughout the scriptures,
God's work is regularly opposed,
and so they're there in Thessalonica.
They go over to Berea, and then we find
that Paul is transported down to Athens,
and we find that as Paul is moved down to Athens,
because of the trouble there in Thessalonica and Berea,
we find that Paul, really, if you were to look
at the text of scripture there in chapter 17,
it seems as if Paul is going there
to have some type of rest, if you will,
some reprieve from all that's been taking place,
but we find that Paul, in Acts chapter number 17,
the Bible tells us that he notices a city.
The city is Athens, and what the Bible tells us
about what he observed was that it was a city
that was wholly, entirely given to idolatry.
As he saw all of their images
and various things that they had there,
we find that their superstition was there,
and we find that he found this altar,
and the altar that he mentioned specifically
was an altar that had the inscription to the unknown God.
The Bible tells us that Paul, that he was stirred up
because he saw that this city was wholly given to idolatry,
and I hope this evening that just as Paul was stirred,
that we too would be stirred, but we must understand
that the stirring must be followed up with some action.
It's not enough to just be stirred, to have that impact.
No, we must allow the Lord to use us
and allow that stirring to bring forth action in our lives,
and so he was stirred.
The great statement of verse number 23 of Acts 17
is when he says, him declare I unto you.
What a great privilege we have
to declare the Lord Jesus Christ to a lost and dying world.
You know, there are some people
that you'll come in contact with
that they've only ever heard the name of our Savior
in a negative context.
They've only ever heard the name of our Savior
used as a swear word.
They do not know our wonderful Savior,
and we have the privilege of declaring him to them.
It's awesome.
We find that after they're there in Athens
for a short period of time,
the stirring led to preaching, to declaring,
to making known the one true God,
and we come to Acts chapter number 18,
and the Bible says after these things,
Paul departed from Athens and came to Corinth.
Paul continues to serve the Lord.
He continues to move forward.
He continues to follow the path
that God has established for him.
He understood that God was not finished with him,
that God was still interested in using him,
and we look at the passage of scripture,
and it says in verse number two,
notice it says, and found a certain Jew named Aquila,
born in Pontus, lately come from Italy
with his wife Priscilla,
because that Claudius had commanded all Jews
to depart from Rome and came unto them.
And because he was of the same craft,
he abode with them and wrought,
for by their occupation they were.
tent makers.
And notice in verse 4, and he reasoned in the synagogue every Sabbath and persuaded
the Jews and the Greeks.
As we look at this passage of Scripture and we speak on this subject, for I have much
people in this city, if you're taking notes, number one, I want you to notice the passion
of Paul.
The passion of Paul.
This morning during the invitation, if I'm not mistaken, Kimberly played A Passion for
Souls.
And I was running in the back to get changed for the baptismal and all that was taking
place, but I could hear the piano, and man, I love that song.
And in that song, the songwriter says, Jesus, I long to be winning.
Men who are lost and constantly sinning.
He talks about having this passion for souls, oh, that this passion that it would be mine,
that God would give us that passion.
We find in the life of the Apostle Paul a man who was passionate, a man that displayed
through his actions this passion to reach the lost with the gospel.
I believe that Paul longed to see souls saved.
So what does he do when he gets to Corinth?
Well, he begins to preach.
He follows the same pattern in which he's established on these missionary journeys of
going.
We find it in verse number 4, he enters into the synagogue and he's there every Sabbath.
And notice the Bible says that he's persuading the Jews and the Greeks.
We find that the Bible says in verse 5, and when Silas and Timotheus were come from Macedonia,
Paul was pressed in the spirit and testified to the Jews that Jesus was Christ.
And it's very interesting because back in chapter 17, we find that the Bible tells us
in verse number 3, verse 2, that he's there in the Sabbath in Thessalonica and he's reasoning
with them out of the scriptures, the Old Testament.
And it says in verse number 3, opening and alleging that Christ must needs have suffered
and risen again from the dead and that this Jesus whom I preach unto you is Christ.
And so here in chapter number 18 in verse number 5, the Bible says that he testified
to the Jews that Jesus was Christ.
What is the significance of this?
Well, the reality is that they understood who Jesus was as a man.
The things that Jesus did were not done in secret.
Jesus in fact says that.
We understand that Paul makes that known to Agrippa when he's standing before Agrippa.
You know these things.
They were not done in a corner.
They were not done secretly.
The miracles, listen, his fame was noised abroad.
They knew who Jesus was.
They knew this person, Jesus, but they did not understand that he was Messiah, that he
was Christ.
In fact, still even today, we would understand even as Romans speaks about the blindness
that has happened in part to the Jews, that there are many Jews today that are still looking
for Messiah.
They reject that Jesus Christ is the Messiah.
So we find that Paul, as he's preaching Jesus, God incarnate, Jehovah is salvation, but he
is the Christ, the anointed one, the Messiah, the Son of God, and he's making and alleging,
he's taking from the Scriptures and giving that truth.
He's passionate about people knowing the truth.
You know, we ought to have some passion.
We ought to have some passion.
You know, the reality is that if you don't really believe what you're saying, it's likely
that the person you're talking to isn't really going to believe what you're saying either.
Have you ever had somebody try to sell you something that you could tell they weren't
really convinced on using themselves?
They're just trying to sell a product.
They're trying to make a living.
They're trying to sell something, like, listen, man, you're not going to buy this thing either,
but we ought to have some passion.
I remember a young man telling me, probably the first year I was here, he thought it was
cool.
You know, like, teenagers, they think they're cool, and he's like, yeah, man, the Bible's
just boring.
That's what he says to me.
And I said, well, do you think when I'm preaching, do you think that I think the Bible's boring?
Oh, no.
I don't think that you think the Bible's boring.
I mean, you seem excited about it.
We ought to have some passion.
I'm not saying that we ought to be flying around from the rafters and what have you,
but we ought to be passionate about what Christ has given us to do.
Paul, he knew, I mentioned it this morning, he knew what God did in his life, and he believed
that God was still at work, and he was able to still save others.
The Bible says in verse 6, when they opposed themselves and blasphemed, he shook his raiment
and said unto them, your blood be upon your own heads.
I am clean.
From henceforth I will go unto the Gentiles.
I love verse 6.
You really could build a whole message on verse number 6.
The gospel is the power of God and salvation to the Jew first, but also the Greek, and
you understand that he went to the Jews, but the Jews, they opposed themselves, they blasphemed,
so what does he do?
He shakes off his raiment, and he says, your blood be upon you.
Notice where he says, I am clean.
He's going to say this in Acts chapter number 20, where he talks about, in fact, turn over
there.
Notice what he says in Acts chapter 20 as he's talking to the church leaders of the
church at Ephesus.
He says in verse number 26 of Acts chapter 20, wherefore I take you to record this day
that I am pure from the blood of all men.
Now understand with me this evening that there are some commentators in Bible, theologians
and what have you, that would say to you, they would make it as if Paul had no knowledge
of the book of Ezekiel when he was writing these things.
Paul was extremely aware of the Old Testament.
He was a master in the Old Testament.
He was trained at the feet of Gamaliel.
He knew the Old Testament.
You know what the Old Testament talks about?
It talks about Ezekiel being a watchman.
And as the watchman, he had a responsibility to warn.
That warning being given, the watchman has no control on the response of the warned.
He has a responsibility to warn, but he has no part in how they respond to that warning.
And God tells Ezekiel that if you warn, then you're free.
You don't have any blood on your hands.
You've done what you're supposed to do.
Now if they don't listen, that's on them.
If you fail to warn, the blood's on your hands.
Ezekiel 3 and 33, you can look at both passages and you can see that God deals with that.
So now for Paul, of course we understand in the inspiration of the Holy Spirit, he says
I am clean.
He says your blood be upon your own heads, I am clean.
I don't know how somebody cannot see the book of Ezekiel in that statement.
I don't understand in Acts chapter number 20 when he says I am pure from the blood of
all men, that why does he say, well if you look at the passage, he says listen, for the
space of three years I ceased not to warn everyone night and day with tears.
He was doing what he was supposed to do.
He had passion about what he was doing.
Paul says in the book of Romans, if you look at the ninth chapter and also at the tenth
chapter of the book of Romans, you find some wonderful statements that the apostle Paul
makes with regard to his desire for people to be saved.
In Romans chapter number nine, in verse number two he says, in verse one, I say the truth
in Christ, I lie not, my conscience also bearing me witness in the Holy Ghost, that I have
great heaviness and continual sorrow in my heart, for I could wish that myself were accursed
from Christ for my brethren, my kinsmen, according to the flesh.
Verse number one of chapter ten, brethren, my heart's desire and prayer to God for Israel
is that they might be saved.
Paul had passion.
Paul was called of God, he was commissioned of God.
Paul understood what his responsibility was and he sought to fulfill with passion what
God called him to do.
We find that he says to these individuals that I am free, he says, your blood be upon
your own heads, back in chapter 18 in verse number six, I am clean from henceforth I will
go unto the Gentiles.
By the way, I'm thankful because I'm a Gentile.
In fact, I think probably all of us here tonight are Gentiles.
The reality is that we've been graft in.
What a wonderful biblical truth.
We were wild branches, but we are graft in, hallelujah.
And he says that he's going to turn to the Gentiles, remember it was the Jews that said
crucify him.
It was the Jews that rejected, it was the Jews that continued to even here in this text
oppose themselves and blaspheme.
And Paul says from henceforth I'm going to the Gentiles.
We find this evening that even through these ministries, these missionary journeys that
eventually the gospel gets to Europe and even through that if you trace the timeline
and you see how the gospel gets here even to America so many centuries later through
that process of that passion and what a joy, what a blessing.
See this evening, this passage of scripture encourages me, we ought to have passion.
But can I tell you this evening, you ought not be discouraged if somebody doesn't want
to hear it.
It's outside of your control.
The only thing that we're responsible for is giving the truth.
It's all we're responsible for.
I told you before about the guy at Aldi that ripped up the tract in my face and some of
the other folks in our church have had the same experience with the same.
same guy. I'm not mad at that guy. I feel sorry for that guy. He says, you're sure this
is for me? Oh yeah, it's for you. I want you to read it. He comes right in my face and
rips it in half, throws it in the trash. I'm not mad at him. I'm not responsible for how
he responds, but I am responsible for giving the truth. And here we find that Paul, he
served Christ with passion, and we see it. Notice in verse number 7, he departed fence
and entered into a certain man's house named Justice, one that worshiped God, whose house
joined hard to the synagogue. And Crispus, the chief ruler of the synagogue, believed
on the Lord, notice, with all his house. Well, I'm sure that was exciting. It's exciting
when you get to lead somebody to Christ. It's exciting when somebody wants to hear the message.
Sometimes we come to the place where, because we've received so many rejections, and I'll
just speak for myself, that when I say to somebody, hey, could I take a Bible and show
you how you could know for sure that heaven's your home, that I'm surprised when they say
yes. Because I hear no so many times. Ah, you know, it's okay. Joseph and I were out
knocking doors a few weeks ago, and man, I thought for sure this guy is a younger fella.
And man, he acknowledged he was lost. He acknowledged that he could die at any moment.
He had no clue and no peace. And I said, listen, can I tell you that God has the answers,
that His Word tells us we can know, that heaven is our home, if I could take the Bible in
just a few moments and show you how you could know for sure that heaven's your home, would
you be willing to take a few minutes? He said, nah, I'm okay. And I thought, you've got to
be kidding me. But then somebody says yes. You know, I'd like for you to show me how
I could know for sure that heaven's my home. And it's exciting. When in that moment a miracle
takes place, a new birth. They were dead spiritually on their way to a Christless eternity like
a fire, but they're born again, they're made alive, they're quickened, and they're heaven-bound.
It's absolutely amazing. We find that the Bible tells us that there were those that
trusted Christ, they believed on the Lord, but then notice it continues in verse number
eight, and many of the Corinthians, hearing, believed and were baptized. And there was
a work going on there in Corinth. Paul was passionate. Paul was preaching the Word and
he was giving the truth and the Holy Spirit of God was actively working and people are
being saved and they're being baptized. And man, it's exciting. We see the passion of
Paul. Number two, I want you to see the promises of God. As we look at verse nine and ten,
I want you to consider with me these wonderful promises that God gives to His servant, Paul.
The Bible says, then spake the Lord to Paul in the night by a vision. It's amazing to
me when I read verses nine and ten and I think about the encouragement that Paul would have
received from these promises. And then I'm reminded this evening that we have a whole
Bible full of promises that God intends for us to have and to claim and to be encouraged
by. And here we find that God says to Paul, be not afraid, but speak and hold not thy
peace. Why? Notice, for I am with thee. We focused on that for a little while a couple
of weeks ago in Exodus chapter number three, when God gave that promise to Moses, certainly
I will be with thee. You know, He gave that promise to Moses. He gave that promise to
Joshua. You read Joshua chapter one. He gave that promise to Jeremiah. He gave that promise,
I mean, over and over. He gives it here to Paul. But you know, He gave that promise as
He gave the Great Commission. And He said, lo, I am with you always. What a joy to understand
this promise. Paul, yes, Silas and Timotheus came according to verse number five from Macedonia.
But Paul, though there could be encouragement by having those co-laborers, by having those
partners to do the work of the ministry with together, the greatest encouragement is when
God Himself says to Paul, I am with thee. No man, notice, shall set on thee to hurt
thee. Wow. Praise the Lord. This is a, in verse number ten we see the promise and reality
of His presence. We find in verse number ten the promise, the reality of His protection.
I'm thankful that God gives the protection. The horse is prepared for the day of battle,
but safety is of the Lord. And He tells Paul, listen, Paul, he was not someone that was
unfamiliar with opposition. I mentioned this morning how in Acts chapter fourteen he stoned
and left for dead. So Paul understood what it was to deal with being imprisoned and being
beaten and all that takes place. But God says here to Paul, He says, be not afraid but speak
and hold not thy peace, for I am with thee and no man shall set on thee to hurt thee.
But then I want you to notice what He says, for I have much people in this city. What
city is it that God is speaking of when He gives this promise? Well, it's the city of
Corinth. The city of Corinth. A city that is known for its immorality. A city that is known
for its idolatry. A city that is pagan. A city that you could almost look at and say
there's no purpose of going here. They're not going to want to listen. God says I have
much people in this city. Can I tell you this evening, I understand the historical context
and promise that's given here, but I would submit to you this evening that God has much
people in this city. In this region. The Bible says that God is not willing that any should
perish but that all should come to repentance. The Bible in the context of that truth in
2 Peter chapter 3 is when there are those that are scoffing and mocking about the return
of Christ, the promise of His coming. Where is? That's the question that they're asking.
All things continue as they have been. They're willingly ignorant, the Bible says, of these
things. They have ignored the truth. They don't want to be confronted with the truth.
And then the wonderful truth that is given to us in verse number 9, the Lord has not
slack concerning His promise. As some men cannot slackness. Or to us-ward. As some men
cannot slackness. He's long-suffering to us-ward. Not willing that any should perish but that
all should come to repentance. Listen, we live in a county that has like 1.2 million
people. I believe God has people in this city that need to hear the gospel that need to
be saved. In this county. We're surrounded by counties that have populations in the millions
as well. There's a lot of people. We know that. We live here. We know that. I was talking
to someone, a church planter, and they were speaking about the place in which they're
ministering and there's like 16,000 people in the whole county. And 16,000 people in
the whole county. I said, we got Walmart that has 16,000 people, man. Not really. I know
that Walmart doesn't have that many people. But you almost could think, Costco might,
you know, on a Saturday morning. But the reality is that we have so many people. If we're not
careful, people can get in our way. People can become a problem. They're hindering me.
I can't get to where I want to get to. But they're, as I said this morning, they're souls.
And I believe this evening that God has people in this city. He has us here for a purpose.
If God was done saving people, if the last person was saved that's going to be saved,
we'd be in heaven. We'd be in heaven. But we're not in heaven. How many of you know
we're not in heaven? Hallelujah, man. I am not in heaven right now. All right? Somebody
was talking to me last week and I said, listen, I'm just telling you one thing. We are not
in heaven right now. I can guarantee you this is not heaven. Amen? So God has people.
He has us as His people that He says we're His ambassadors. Paul was the representative.
He was the servant. But Paul receives this promise, this word of encouragement from God,
I have much people in this city. And I can't help but believe this evening that there's
some people that need to be reached in our communities, in your neighborhood and I don't
really have a neighborhood, but in this neighborhood. There's people that need to be reached, people
that need to be saved. I was talking to a pastor friend that teaches a Bible Institute
class a few weeks ago and he was telling me about a project that he gave to the students
to do in the project. That was actually quite interesting.
There's a project that they had where they had a responsibility to talk with someone,
a coworker, a neighbor, a relative, whoever it might be, and ask them as part of an assignment
that they had, that they had a responsibility in this assignment to share their testimony
with a stranger.
It's kind of a good idea, right?
Unique approach.
Like, hey, we're going to share our testimony with a stranger.
And it's a class that we're taking.
It's a graded assignment.
And so the students in the class, they met with different people and coworkers, and they
said, hey, listen, I got a requirement for a class that I'm taking, and I got to sit
down with somebody and share my testimony with them.
Would you be willing to meet with me so that I could share my testimony with you?
I like, that's pretty neat.
And one of the students comes back that's actually an assistant pastor at a church that's
taking some night classes, and he comes back, an assistant pastor, and he didn't do the
assignment, just like pastors to not do what they're supposed to do, amen?
But he didn't do it.
And the pastor that's the teacher, the professor, he says, why didn't he do it?
He said, I don't know any lost people.
That's what he said.
I don't know any lost people.
So the pastor, and if you knew who he was, you'd laugh at this, how he responded.
He called the pastor that this guy worked for, and he said, I just want to congratulate
you.
And the pastor that's receiving the call says, what are you congratulating me on?
He said, you have reached everybody in your community.
I just want to, I don't know how you've done it.
We still have thousands of people that we're trying to reach, but you evidently have reached
everybody in your community, and I just want to congratulate you and find out, obviously
they've not reached everybody in their community, amen?
But the reality this evening is that God's given us some promises.
He's promised that His Word is effective.
He's promised that it'll be with us.
He's promised that the Holy Spirit will work, and we need to claim those promises just as
Paul would here.
We close this evening, number three, if you're taking notes.
We see the passion of Paul.
We see the promises of God.
Number three, the persistence of Paul.
I love verse number 11, the final verse of our text this evening.
The Bible says, and he, what does it say?
Continued.
Our theme for this year is continue.
Our theme for our missions conference is going to be continue.
There have been a number of years since I've pastored here that we've had a different theme
for our missions conference than we do for our annual theme, but as I was praying about
it this year, I just had a piece from the Lord of keeping the theme consistent because
the idea is that we need to continue in the area of missions as well, home and abroad,
continue.
And here the Bible says he continued there.
Where's there?
Where there's Corinth.
He continued where God had him for that season.
Paul, of course, we know he went to a number of different places.
God used him in a great way on his missionary journeys, but it says that he continued there
a year and six months, 18 months.
He continued in Corinth.
I think the promises, by the way, of verse 9 and 10, went a long way to helping Paul
to continue because he understood the promises.
He believed what God told him and he continued there a year and six months, 18 months that
he's there.
And I want you to see what he's doing.
He's teaching the Word of God among them.
Souls, no doubt, are being saved.
We read in verse number 8 how in Crispus, the chief ruler of the synagogue, believed
in the Lord with all his house and many of the Corinthians hearing believed and were
baptized in.
So the truth of God's Word is going forth and Paul, as he continues there for this 18
months, he's teaching the Word of God among them.
And not only are souls being saved, but souls are being discipled.
Sometimes we do not deal with the entirety of the Great Commission.
The Great Commission has three aspects.
We give them the gospel, they get saved, if that's their response, we can't make them
get saved.
But if they get saved, they're to be baptized, and then we're to teach them all things, right?
Whatsoever I've commanded you.
That aspect of discipleship is absolutely imperative.
It cannot be ignored.
It cannot be something that we do not focus on and that we do not make a big deal out
of.
Why?
Because people that are not discipled are forever babes.
We understand how tragic it is when someone leaves a newborn baby at some place, a police
station, a fire department, a hospital, emergency room, whatever it may be.
We've read in the news over years of tragic events such as that.
We have heartfelt sorrow in those types of conditions.
But I would submit to you that as spiritually speaking, if we do not focus on the aspect
of discipleship, we're failing not only to do what God's commanded us to do, but we're
leaving people ill-equipped to do what God has called them to do, to be what God has
called them to be.
Discipleship is something that takes work, it's something that takes commitment.
There must be someone that's willing to do the discipling and someone that's willing
to be discipled, someone that has the level of humility that I need to be taught, somebody
that understands, as Paul would say to the believers in Thessalonica, that you're lacking
in some areas and you need to perfect that which is lacking.
And what a joy.
Listen, this evening, 20-some years after I've gotten saved by the grace of God, I understand
tonight as 27 years ago I got saved, I've been discipled since I got saved.
And I'm thankful for that discipleship, that teaching, that training.
I'm thankful that someone was willing to invest in me and teach me because I did not know
then what I know now.
And I would not know now what I know now if someone was not willing to disciple.
The work of the ministry is outlined for us here in Acts 18, and I want you to consider
as we think about this missions conference and our part in world evangelization, and
yes, we want to pick up new missionaries, we want to continue to send missionaries abroad
so that they can do in these fields where we're calling them to, or where they're called
of God to go, that we're partnering with them.
We want to see in the Netherlands a church established where souls are being saved, the
Word of God is being preached, and people are being discipled.
We want to see that in Spain and all of these other fields, but we must not lose sight of
the fact that it has to be done here as well.
It has to be done here as well.
It starts in Jerusalem, and this, as we make application, this is our Jerusalem.
He says both, it's to be all at the same time, and we strategically approach that through
supporting missionaries that are going around the globe.
And I hope that by the end of the missions conference next week that we'll be able to
partner with two brand new missionaries and be able to support them financially and add
them to our list as missionaries of the Fellowship Baptist Church that we've partnered with and
we can begin supporting them financially and praying for them, and I trust that that
will be what happens.
But we never can lose sight of the fact that that over there does not replace what we're
supposed to be doing here.
It's not enough to just put money in an offering plate or to pray for a missionary and say,
okay, I've done my part, both.
God said He had much people in that city, the city of Corinth, a wicked, immoral, idolatrous
people, but they needed to be saved by the grace of God.
You say, do you know how bad our county is?
Do you know all the problems we have?
There's a lot of them, but they're sinners that need to be saved.
Why would we, and I know I've said this before, it's hard enough to get a saved person to
act like a saved person.
You're never going to get a lost person to act like a saved person.
They don't understand the Scripture.
They don't have the Holy Spirit of God living within them.
They need to be saved.
This evening, God has a work for us and this is our place.
This is where God has us.
I believe that God wants to use us to reach people with the gospel for His glory, not
for any of our glory, but for His glory.
God said I have much people in this city.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
We thank You for Your Word and the truth contained therein and I pray, God, that You would help
us to serve You passionately.
Help us to claim the promises that You've given us.
Help us to continue.
We see the persistence of Paul.
Help us not to give up or to give in.
Help us not to be overwhelmed.
Lord help us to continue.
I pray that You'd move and work in hearts and lives as only
you can. We'll give you the honor and glory for it. For it's in Christ's name we pray.