18 and as you're turning there
I'll remind you of our text of scripture in the book of Titus our study really is through the book of Titus and as we
Understood in the beginning portions of the first chapter that Titus had been given a specific responsibility
to go into Crete and to establish
there
Those things that were wanting and to ordain elders in every city and the subject matter of sound
Doctrine is repeated a number of times in the first chapter you come to chapter 2 in verse number 1 of the book of Titus
And it says but speak thou the things which become
sound doctrine and so we studied first the doctrine of Bibliology the study of the scriptures and
The reason that we started there is because that is foundational
Our doctrine our theology is to be born out of a proper understanding of the Word of God
And I'm so thankful that God has given his word
I'm thankful this evening that we have a copy of the Word of God and that God has revealed himself to us
Through his word aren't you thankful that we're not dependent upon the politicians to tell us who God is
Aren't you thankful that we're not dependent upon the movie makers in Hollywood to tell us who God is
Amen God saw fit that he would give us his word and that in his word
He would reveal himself to mankind. He does not need to be
described by some
Person today. He has given us in his word
All that he wants us to know of his character and what a great God he is
And I'm so thankful that he has revealed himself to us through his word
Theology is of significant importance
We must acknowledge this evening that as we begin the study of theology that there is much confusion in our society
Concerning this doctrine the doctrine of God. There are people that ask the question. Who is God?
There are people that wonder what is he like?
there are people that ask this question, how is it that man can approach God and
Unfortunately, the enemy has given an answer to all of those questions through society through false
religion through all sorts of means the enemy has answered those questions, but
We find that this study of theology must be
Born out of the scriptures that we hold in front of us. We understand this evening
Then in addition to the confusion
In our society, there are some that simply deny the existence of God
In fact, we're living in a time in the midst of a generation in which it's becoming
more and more
Just common for us to run into individuals to interact with people that just simply deny the existence of God
The reality is that God in no way shape or form
Seeks to prove his existence in the scriptures. We see that he simply
declares his existence in the beginning God
Amen, and we find that the scriptures reveal to us who God is. We understand that there is
Absolute proof of his existence
But when we understand these two
important aspects with regard to the confusion that
lies in our in our culture and with regard to those that deny the existence of God and we find that our theology being
biblically based that we then have
The opportunity and really we must seize the opportunity to declare God to the world
People don't know who he is
Paul said in the book of Romans, how shall they hear without a preacher?
Paul as he was left in and
After he ministered in Thessalonica and Berea
We find that there were many obstacles and difficulties and he was left in Athens and we find that he sees a city that is
wholly given to
Apostolatry and we find that the Apostle Paul being moved being stirred in his spirit
He goes and the Bible tells us in Acts chapter number 17 in his own
Words as his spirit is stirred within him and it brings forth action
He stands in the midst of Mars Hill and he says to these men of Athens in verse 22 of Acts 17
He says I perceived and in all things you're too superstitious
For I passed by and beheld your devotions I found an altar with this inscription to the unknown God
And Paul says this whom therefore ye ignorantly worship him
declare I
Unto you and what a blessing and privilege that God has given us
to know the truth of who he is and
Then that we would be able to take that truth and deliver it to a lost and dying world
I've mentioned before in various messages that and really as we study through the book of Hebrews this year that knowing the truth
I'm so thankful that we know the truth
But we better be careful not to get prideful in knowing the truth that ought to keep us humble
to understand that there are many in darkness and
Those that are in darkness
Need those of us who know the truth to not hide the light of the gospel
But to let it shine forth and we live in the midst of a crooked and perverse generation
We find that we're to shine as bright lights as I mentioned already. God has graciously revealed himself to us
Through his word the existence of God is declared through creation
The heavens declare the glory of God the firmament showeth forth this handiwork in Psalm 19
we find that there are people groups throughout the
history of
Mankind you can look at some of the most remote civilizations and you can find that they had some
understanding that there was some greater power than themselves and
We find that in many instances in those particular cases if they do not have the truth of the gospel
They would worship a whole host of things
But through their idolatrous worship it indicates that they understood there was somebody
something greater than them
We've been given the truth and what a blessing that is
Conscience reveals that there's a God
We've often mentioned that as you begin to look at the truth of mankind and how God has
Created man that he's given us a God awareness
But we find that those that would find themselves as denying the existence of God as Psalm 14 and verse 1 says
That the fool hath said in his heart. There is no God you read Romans chapter number one
We don't have time to deal with it in its entirety this evening
but if you look in verse number 28 you find that they do not like to retain this knowledge of God and we
understand that as we begin to
Study and to dig into why these deny the existence of God
I believe that it boils down to this very simple truth is that they do not
Want to be accountable to God
They want to be their own authority
Gonna make their own decisions as it said in the book of Judges every man did that which was right in his own sight
I want to be my own authority
and we find that in the absence of a
understanding of who God is we see the impact and influences upon the morals of a community of a
Culture and oh how we're seeing that even in our own land today
We find that of course the scriptures as we mentioned declare the existence of God all the way in Genesis 1 in verse number 1
As you begin the scriptures in the beginning God created the heaven and the earth
And I'm so thankful that God has chosen to reveal himself to us as we look here in Jeremiah chapter 10
will really use verse number 6 as the
Outline the basic outline if you will for a three-part study that I've put together here on the subject matter of theology the doctrine of
God look at verse number 6 the Bible says this
For as much as there is none like unto thee O Lord
thou art
great and
Thy name is great in might
verse number 10 says but the Lord is
The true God he is the living God an everlasting king at his wrath
The earth shall tremble and the nations shall not be able to abide
His indignation if you're taking notes this evening from verse number 10 is where we've got our title for this first message
the Lord is
the true God
As we begin to think about the subject matter of theology and begin to understand the study of God
We understand that there are some that would have that belief system that has been called atheism
That really is a belief that they deny the existence of God. There is no God
we find that there are those that would consider themselves and it's a
Truth a name that would be given of pantheism the fact that they would say that the universe is God
God is everywhere and everything is God
We find that there's polytheism
Polytheism they believe in a plurality of gods you find that there are certain groups of
religions across the globe that are very polytheistic
In fact, as you begin to look through many of the people groups that you find within
the pages of Scripture, when the children of Israel would go into the land of promise,
they would go into a land that had been inhabited by groups of people that were polytheistic.
They believed in a plurality of gods.
I spoke with a man who claimed to be a Hindu, and he told me this.
He used a word in the particular dialect that he spoke, and he asked me if I knew what it
meant, and I couldn't even repeat the word that he said, and he asked me if I knew the
definition of the word, and I said, sir, I have no idea what that word means.
He said that is the word that we would use to describe the gods that we serve, and it
literally means millions.
That's sad.
Monotheism is a system of belief that believes in the existence of only one God.
The Lord our God.
We find that here in the book of Jeremiah, as we'll be studying this evening, looking
at a number of verses in this particular text of Scripture, but we're mindful of the way
in which God has revealed Himself in the Scriptures.
He says this in Deuteronomy 6,
Here, O Israel, the Lord our God is one Lord.
We'll deal with the subject matter and the teaching of the Trinity.
We'll deal with that in our next lesson.
But we find this evening that as we begin to look at the subject matter of theology
and we begin to understand the importance of sound doctrine as we find the truth that
is given in the book of Titus and the importance of speaking those things which become sound
doctrine, it's interesting that here in our text of Scripture in Jeremiah, I want to call
your attention to verse number 8.
The Bible says this, speaking of really the idolatry, the polytheistic worldview of those
that are being mentioned, of course, Judah on a number of occasions is guilty of this
as well.
But the Bible says this in verse number 8,
But they are altogether brutish and foolish.
The stock is a doctrine of vanities.
And we're seeking to understand the importance of sound doctrine.
And here when we think about this passage of Scripture in Jeremiah 10 that gives us
great nuggets of truth with regard to the study of theology, and we find the comparison
of the one true God, Jehovah God, in comparison to these idols, we find that the truth is
revealed to us that the stock is a doctrine of vanities.
It's empty.
As we begin to think about the source, we're mindful of our study of bibliology and what
the Apostle Paul said in 2 Timothy 3, in verse number 16,
All Scripture is given by inspiration of God.
And then he says this,
And is profitable first for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for instruction in
righteousness.
Verse 17,
That the man of God may be perfect, throughly furnished unto all good works.
So as we look at Jeremiah 10, look with me if you will, in verse number 1, the Bible
says this,
Hear ye the word which the Lord speaketh unto you, O house of Israel.
Thus saith the Lord,
Notice,
Learn not the ways of the heathen, and be not dismayed at the signs of heaven.
For the heathen are dismayed at them.
For the customs of the people are vain.
For one cutteth a tree out of the forest.
The work of the hands of the workmen with the axe.
They deck it with silver and with gold.
They fasten it with nails and with hammers, that it move not.
They are upright as the palm tree, but speak not.
They must needs be borne, because they cannot go.
Be not afraid of them, for they cannot do evil.
Neither also is it in them to do good.
He's going to deal with this customs of the people.
But you notice in verse number 2 that he says this,
Learn not the way of the heathen.
We're not to learn this subject matter of theology, the doctrine of God.
Who is God?
What is he like?
How can man approach God?
We don't find those answers from the heathen.
We don't find those answers from mainstream media.
We don't find those from academia.
And looking at all of these various aspects of people that are seeking to try to,
in our society today, define who God is.
No, we must go to the Word of God.
We must understand that this is the source of truth.
And that God has chosen to reveal Himself to us through His Word.
And so we begin to see how the Lord is saying,
Learn not the way of the heathen.
Be not dismayed at the sign of heaven,
nor for the heathen are dismayed at them.
Notice, for the customs of the people are vain.
We're living in a time today, in our society, in our culture,
where mankind is seeking to redefine all sorts of things.
And one thing that they're seeking to do is to redefine who God is.
What God accepts.
What God, who God is.
What He's like.
And they seek to redefine who God is.
And they've misunderstood how God has revealed Himself in the pages of Scripture.
Many today like to run around speaking about the fact that God is love.
You know that the Bible says that God is love.
And I'm so thankful this evening that our God is loving.
I'm so thankful that the Bible tells us that God so loved the world,
that He gave His only begotten Son,
that whosoever believes in Him should not perish,
but have everlasting life.
I'm thankful that the Bible says that God commendeth His love toward us,
and that while we're yet sinners, Christ died for us.
But we begin to understand that it is the society in which we're living this day
is seeking to promote this idea that God is love.
Really what they're seeking to promote,
and what they're seeking to indoctrinate people with is that,
it's okay, God loves you.
He accepts anything.
He's okay with whatever you decide to do, because God is love.
And they would like to define the love of God as being some kind of permissive love.
That because God is love,
He permits you to do whatever you want to do, because God is love.
That's what the Bible tells us about God's love.
God loves us so much that He wants to protect us.
He wants to protect us from the error of society, of culture, of false teachers.
He wants to protect us from ourselves.
And we find that throughout the pages of Scripture that, yes, God is love,
but because God loves us, He gave us the truth of His Word to guide us,
and to show us what it is that we're to do.
People say, how could a loving God send anyone to the lake of fire?
People ask that question all the time.
In fact, there are cults, there are false religious groups of people
that deny the very existence of hell or the lake of fire,
because they do not want to accept that that could be the truth.
Well, the Bible tells us that there is a hell and there is a lake of fire.
And the reality is that God so loved the world,
and He died so that mankind would not have to go and spend eternity in the lake of fire.
But when mankind rejects the free gift of eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord,
the Bible says that whoso was not found written in the book of life was cast in the lake of fire.
That doesn't make me very happy, by the way.
It saddens my heart to understand when you read Revelation chapter number 20,
it will cause you to have a tear that comes to your eye
to understand the eternal damnation of those that would reject the free gift of salvation.
We find that as God is speaking here, Jeremiah speaking to the people of God,
we see that God is giving Jeremiah this message,
He says, learn not the way of the heathen.
Listen, the customs of the people are vain.
We need to be careful how we're influenced by the thinking of the people that are around us.
When somebody seeks to explain God, we better make sure that it matches up with the Word of God.
We better be sure that we're understanding that God has revealed Himself to us in this book.
You say, well, it's going to make me narrow-minded.
I'd rather be right.
I'd rather be in line with what God has revealed to us
than to be with the popular group or the group that has the greatest numbers, if you will.
You see the way in which the idols are described in the next several verses.
You come to verse number 6.
The verse that I said would serve as our outline for this three-part study.
The Bible says, for as much as there is none like unto thee, O Lord.
He's beyond comparison.
There's no one like Him.
We're going to look at a number of verses here in just a few moments,
but we find that He continues and says,
thou art great.
Aren't you thankful for the greatness of our God?
We sing about His greatness.
The psalmist says, great is the Lord and greatly to be praised.
We find that the psalmist says, I know that the Lord is great.
And this evening we find that He says that there's none like unto thee.
He's beyond comparison.
Thou art great.
And then you find that the Bible says this,
and thy name is great in me.
might. Our final study of theology, we're going to look at a number of names of
God. In the Old Testament in particular, God reveals Himself to His people
through His names and through the revelation of the names of God we find
how that the attributes and character of God are being revealed to His people and
the importance of understanding that. We'll look at a number of them in that
final study. Notice as we look here at the passage of Scripture in verse number
7 it says, Who would not fear Thee, O King of nations? For to Thee doth it
appertain, for as much as among all the wise men of the nations and in all their
kingdoms, notice, there is none like unto Thee, but they are all together brutish
and foolish. The stock is a doctrine of vanities. Silver spread into plates is
brought unto Tarshish and gold from Uphaz. The work of the workmen in the
hands of the founder. Blue and purple is their clothing. They're all the work of
cunning men. Notice verse 10, the contrast. But the Lord is the true God. He is the
living God and an everlasting King. At His wrath the earth shall tremble and
the nation shall not be able to abide His indignation. Thus shall you say unto
them, the gods that have not made the heavens and the earth, even they shall
perish from the earth and from under these heavens. Notice verse 12, He,
speaking of the one true God, the Lord is the true God. It says in verse number 12,
He hath made the earth by His power. We understand that He is the Creator. We
understand that He said and it was done. You begin to read the account of
creation in Genesis 1 and you begin to marvel in the very power of God and the
Word of God, the spoken word, let there be light and there was light. And He made
the stars also and we begin to see the power of God and it says that He made
the earth by His power. Notice, He hath established the world by His wisdom. Not
only is our God omnipotent, that He has all power, but our God is omniscient. He
has all wisdom. Now in understanding the importance of this truth, the omnipotence
and the omniscience of God, that He has all power and He has all wisdom, He knows
what to do and He has the power to do it. And for that we ought to rejoice. Notice,
and hath stretched out the heavens by His discretion. When He uttereth His
voice, there is a multitude of waters in the heavens and He causeth the vapors to
ascend from the ends of the earth. He maketh lightnings with rain and bringeth
forth the wind out of His treasures. Every man is brutish in his knowledge. Every
founder is confounded by the graven image. For his molten image is falsehood and
there is no breath in them. Their vanity and the work of errors in the time of
their visitation, they shall perish. The portion of Jacob is not like them, for he
is the former of all things and Israel is the rod of his inheritance. The Lord of
hosts is His name. Gather up thy wares out of the land, O inhabitant of the
fortress. For thus saith the Lord, Behold, I will sling out the inhabitants of the
land at this once and will distress them that they may find it so. As we begin to
understand this evening, there's none like unto Thee, O Lord. We begin to rejoice in
the greatness of our God. We begin to rejoice in the fact that our Lord is the
true God. And this evening if you go over to the book of Isaiah, start in
chapter number 40, I'm just going to look at a number of verses, read them, make a
few comments here throughout the book of Isaiah, to just rejoice this evening in
the fact that God has revealed Himself to us through His Word. It is imperative
that the Word of God is the source of our theology. It is profitable for
doctrine. Isaiah 40 and verse number 18, to whom then will you liken God or what
likeness will you compare unto Him? The workman melteth a graven image and the
goldsmith spreadeth it over with gold and casteth silver chains. He that is so
impoverished that he hath no oblation chooseth a tree that will not rot. He
seeketh unto Him a cunning workman to prepare a graven image that shall not be
moved. Have you not known? Have you not heard? Hath it not been told you from the
beginning? Have you not understood from the foundations of the earth? It is He
that sitteth upon the circle of the earth and the inhabitants thereof are as
grasshoppers that stretcheth out the heavens as a curtain and spreadeth them
out as a tent to dwell in that bringeth the princes to nothing. He maketh the
judges of the earth as vanity. Yea, they shall not be planted. Yea, they shall not
be sown. Yea, their stock shall not take root in the earth and He shall also blow
upon them and they shall wither and the whirlwind shall take them away as stubble.
To whom then will you liken me or shall I be equal, saith the Holy One? Lift up
your eyes on high and behold who hath created these things that bringeth out
their hosts by number. He calleth them all by names by the greatness of His
might for that He is strong in power, not one faileth. Why sayest thou, O Jacob,
and speakest, O Israel, my way is hid from the Lord and my judgment is passed
over from my God? Hast thou not known, hast thou not heard, that the everlasting
God, the Lord, the Creator of the ends of the earth, fainteth not, neither is weary.
There is no searching of His understanding." Wow, we begin to look at
these verses and looking at these ten verses that are given in verses 18 through
28, begin to understand the God that we serve and understanding that there's
none like unto thee and you would see the comparison as these, even as the
people of God, the nation of Israel and Judah alike would serve idols and would
get caught in that trap time and time again. We find that here it is God who
has created these things and so we find that they're graven these images and
they're using this stock and they're they're they're worshiping these idols
but God the Creator of all things has revealed Himself to us in His precious
Word. It's amazing as you begin to look through the the era of the Kings and you
begin to see how that God would give victory to His people and there were
times in which the the people of God of course as they would serve idols and
they would suffer and deal with all sorts of difficulties but we find that
as the people of God would declare their dependence upon God, when they would
understand that He was the Creator, that He is the Sustainer, how that they would
see God move and God work and they would be able to rejoice in the the power of
God. We find that in Isaiah chapter 43 notice in verse number 11 Isaiah 43 in
verse number 11 he says this, I even I am the Lord and beside me there is no
Savior. Now is that hard to understand? Is that in conflict with some of what is
taught in mainline circles today? Oh just be sincere, all roads lead to. We
look at the New Testament, Jesus said I am the way, the truth, and the life. No man
cometh unto the Father but by me. We understand that Peter as he's standing
before the religious leaders of the day and giving an answer as to the great
miracle that took place there at the gate beautiful but he says understand
that it's not by my power that this man is made whole but it's through the power
of Jesus Christ of Nazareth and he says this that that salvation is in his name
there's no other name under heaven given among men whereby we must be saved. God
says here I even I am the Lord and beside me there is no Savior. Notice with
me in chapter 44 in verse number 6 thus saith the Lord the King of Israel and
his Redeemer the Lord of hosts I am the first and I am the last and beside me
there is no God. Chapter 46 in verse number 8 he says fear ye not neither be
afraid have not I told thee from that time and have declared it ye are even my
witnesses is there a God beside me? Yea there is no God I know not any. Chapter
44 excuse me chapter 45 in verse number 5 he says I am the Lord and there is
none else there is no God beside me I girded thee though thou hast not known
me. Look down and skip down to verse number 21 if you will in chapter 45
there look at verse 21 tell ye and bring them near yea let them take counsel
together who hath declared this from ancient time who hath told it
but from that time.
Have not I the Lord?
And there is no God else beside Me,
a just God and a Savior.
There is none beside Me.
Look unto Me and be ye saved
all the ends of the earth,
for I am God and there is none else."
Chapter 46 and verse 5,
to whom will you liken Me
and make Me equal and compare Me
that we may be like?
Let's get down and look at v. 8.
Remember this and show yourselves, men,
bring it again to Mine,
O ye transgressors.
Remember the former things of old,
for I am God and there is none else.
I am God and there is none like Me,
declaring the end from the beginning
and from ancient times the things
that are not yet done,
saying, My counsel shall stand
and I will do all My pleasure.
We could go on this evening
and look at a whole host of verses of Scripture.
But tonight, I want us to rest
in the fact that there's none like our God.
There's none like unto Thee, O Lord.
And we begin to think about the questions
that mankind may ask with regard
to this subject matter of theology,
to this subject matter of God.
Who is God?
Well, I'm thankful that He's revealed Himself to us.
We begin to look at His character.
We begin to look at His greatness.
We begin to look at His characteristics
and how God has revealed Himself to us.
He's not simply declared
that He's loving.
He's not simply declared that He's powerful.
He's not simply declared that He's merciful.
We find that He's demonstrated those things as well.
What a blessing that is.
How can man, how can sinful man
approach such a holy God?
I'm thankful for the Lord Jesus Christ.
I'm thankful that God hath made Him to be sin
who knew no sin that we might be made
to righteousness of God in Him.
Begin to think about the plan of God
and how mankind could be reconciled to God Almighty.
And begin to look at the pages of this book
and to think about just the wonder,
the truth of redemption
and how we ought to rejoice
that the God of the universe,
the Creator God,
He's interested in you as an individual.
He loved you so much as an individual
that He wanted to allow you to be reconciled to Himself
through Calvary.
The death, the burial, and the resurrection of our Savior.
He desires to hear from you.
He wants you to pray.
He extends an invitation.
God loved us so much
that He died for us
so that we could be reconciled to Him.
I tell you this evening, there's none like Him.
There's none like Him.
The teachings of false religions and cults around the world,
their desire of being able to put forth
some understanding of who God is,
it's all vague.
I asked a man recently,
how can you know if God is pleased with you?
I have no idea.
Well, we know in the Scriptures,
we can go to the Word of God
and we can find that these things please God.
These things displease God.
He revealed it to us.
He communicated with us so that we could know Him,
so that we could be accepted by Him,
not in our own power and our own doing,
but because of the fact that He died for us.
And we have this great truth this evening.
And the reality is that we're living in a time
in which there's much confusion about who God is.
Much confusion.
God's never changed.
Aren't you thankful for that?
We spoke about the fact that He's omnipotent
and He's omniscient.
We understand that He's immutable.
The fact that He doesn't change.
He said, I change not.
He's the same yesterday and today and forever.
The reality this evening
is that our God has made Himself known to us.
What's in this book?
We can accept who He is,
or we can reject who He is,
but we cannot redefine who He is.
In seeking to do so,
we simply are rejecting who He is,
because we cannot redefine God.
God has revealed Himself to mankind.
And this evening, as we begin the start of this journey
in this three-part study of theology,
I hope tonight that you would rejoice
in the fact that God, in His grace and His mercy,
has allowed you to know the truth of who He is.
But then that we would acknowledge
that in the midst of such confusion,
in really the days in which we're living
in all-out attack on who God is,
that we'd understand the opportunity that God has given us
to declare Him to a lost and dying world.
Because there are people that just flat out
don't know who God is.
They have their own little image of who they think God is.
But we don't have to rely on some other source,
we just go to His source.
And this evening, as we would rejoice
in what God has given us,
I pray that God would help us to understand
the responsibility to share that truth.
Paul says, Him declare I unto thee.
He says, how shall they hear without a preacher?
We live in a society, we say,
how can people think that way?
You listen to the things that people say,
and you say, how can they think that way?
They don't know who God is.
They don't know the truth of this book.
Who's gonna tell them?
Not the schoolteachers, right?
Not Hollywood, not the politicians.
No, not the media.
Who's gonna tell them?
Somebody that knows the truth, you and I.
Stand up and give the truth.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
Thank you for loving us.
Thank you for revealing yourself to us through your word.
We acknowledge this evening that we've been blessed.
To know the truth of your word
as you revealed yourself to us.
I pray that as we, over the next couple of weeks,
study the subject matter of theology,
that our hearts would just rejoice.
The very same time, I pray, God,
that you'd help us to recognize the importance
of proclaiming this truth to a lost and dying world.
Understanding that there are so many in our society
that do not know you.
I pray, God, that you would help us.
Bless our time of prayer.
We thank you for the privilege of prayer.
We pray that you would be honored and glorified
through the remainder of our service.
For it's in Christ's name we pray, amen.
I did send out the prayer bulletin via email
just before church this evening.
And so those that are watching online.