We're going to begin, however, in the book of Amos and Old Testament prophet, Hosea Joel
Amos, and try to help you out there, Amos chapter 3.
And we'll give you just a moment to turn there, and I'll read to you the question that was
submitted for our message this evening.
As many of you know, throughout the summer, and I know we're past the summer at this point,
we have, on Sunday evenings, had a Ask the Pastor series.
And we gave you opportunity to submit questions and ask the pastor, and those questions have
become a series that I've answered and try to answer these questions biblically and give
you the truth of the Word of God.
And this series, I was just mapping it out yesterday in my office, and it's probably
going to take me until January to finish.
And so, our summer series is going to go straight through the fall into the winter.
But that's okay, and I'm thankful for the questions.
I've often learned this over the years, that when someone has a question, it probably means
that someone else has a similar question.
And so, it's been a real good opportunity.
We did this several years ago, and thankful for the opportunity to do it again.
But the question that was provided that we're looking at this evening actually had a disclaimer
put on the question, and I thought that was kind of interesting.
The disclaimer was this, this is not an antagonistic question.
And that's always encouraging when you see those words to begin the question.
And the question reads this.
It's a lengthy question, so I'll read the entirety of it.
It says this, why are independent Baptist churches, that's what we are, reluctant to
affiliate with other denominations when it comes to missions work?
The example that is given is missionaries will often say there are only X number of
independent Baptist churches in a particular area, the field in which they're going to
minister.
And then the question ends this way, do other denominations really not preach the gospel?
And so, this evening, as we begin to look at this particular question that was submitted,
really I have a few immediate thoughts with regard to this question that are actually
more questions in themselves of responding to that question, and just a few thoughts.
Number one would be this, why don't we affiliate with other denominations here?
Talking about the missions field and the reluctance of missionaries to affiliate or partner with
other denominations of people that are there, well, why don't we do it here?
And I'll answer that as we get through the message this evening.
But then let me ask this question, what distinguishes one denomination from another?
In other words, why do we call ourselves Baptist?
What's in a name?
Does a name matter?
I think a name does matter.
I think it's extremely important when we say and we identify as being Baptist people, historically
that means something, and I'm thankful for what it means, and we understand.
And listen, there's a number of Baptist churches that have not stood for what Baptists have
historically stood for, there's a slide that is taking place, but the reality is that historically
when someone would say I'm a Baptist, there's a number of things that you immediately begin
to understand about what that means.
Of course, we would say this, that the Bible is our sole authority for faith and practice.
Now that in of itself sets us apart from a lot of denominations.
And so the question about affiliation, really, we would ask ourselves what distinguishes
one denomination from another?
Is there really significance in a name?
I would say yes, it matters.
Let me share this thought with you.
What biblical teaching would we be willing to abandon in order to accomplish some goal?
Whatever that goal is, the goal of ecumenical partnership, the goal of this affiliation,
what teaching of the Bible would we be willing to abandon to set aside for the purpose of
trying to accomplish some goal?
I hope that we'd say none, amen?
Because the Bible is the sole authority for faith and practice.
And so we cannot say, well, that doesn't really matter.
Or for the sake of unity, no, there is no unity apart from God.
There's no unity apart from this book.
And if we're going to have unity, it's because we're going to agree with God, not because
we're going to try to agree with each other apart from God.
Then I had this thought, how much is enough to agree on?
Where do we kind of draw that line?
Where does it say, well, that's enough?
Is there enough in common that we can partner with and we can affiliate with?
And those are just some immediate thoughts and questions.
And really, the subject that is before us this evening is of significant importance.
It is absolutely worthy of our study.
I believe that when we could define the question this evening, that really what we're dealing
with is ecumenical separation.
We're dealing with the subject of ecumenical separation.
I've titled the message this evening there from Amos 3.
I used the entire verse as our title this evening.
Verse number 3, can two walk together except they be agreed?
We begin to think about this subject of ecumenical separation, begin to think about this affiliation
that's being referenced, and missionaries mentioning that there's only, I think when
Brother Thomas was here, he mentioned there were six or seven independent Baptist missionaries
in all of Guatemala.
And you begin to understand, as we would make those distinctions, in fact, I've even spoken
about the number of independent Baptist churches in Fairfax County, in Northern Virginia, and
we begin to understand those churches that are standing on that same faith that we would
hold dear and that we'd understand.
Let me say this when we speak about ecumenical separation, it is important for us to note
that the New Testament, and we'll look at a number of verses this evening in the New
Testament, that the New Testament does not define essential and non-essential doctrine.
There's no distinguishing in the New Testament between this being an essential doctrine and
this being a non-essential doctrine.
Now I understand that oftentimes we will speak about the fundamentals of the faith and we'll
speak about these essential doctrines, but you understand that this is more of our identifying
the particular doctrines and us classifying the teaching of the Word of God.
We do not see this distinction within the Bible.
Let me show you a few verses of Scripture.
Notice in the book of Philippians, if you will, and I want you to see as God is giving
us the truth in the New Testament with regard to the body of doctrine, the faith that was
delivered to us, I want you to see what Paul is saying here in the book of Philippians
as he's writing to a local church, the church in Philippi, and he comes to the conclusion,
he's in Philippians 4, and notice in verse number 9, I want you to notice how he says
this under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God, he says, those things which you have
both learned and received and heard and seen in me do, and the God of peace shall be with
you.
Now, he summarizes everything that he taught them with those things, right?
That's how he summarizes the body of doctrine that he taught the believers in Philippi,
all of the teaching that he gave.
He says those things which you have both learned and received and heard and seen in me do.
There's no real exception in that verse of Scripture, and we find that as he's talking
to Timothy, turn to the book of 2 Timothy chapter number 1, and I want you to see what
he says here to Timothy.
There's a whole host of verses that we could look at.
I'm just picking a few so that we can get through the message this evening, and I want
you to see how that the Word of God references the body of doctrine, the faith, if you will,
that we hold dear, and the importance of the fact that the New Testament does not make
a distinction or define between essential and non-essential.
Notice in 2 Timothy 1 and verse number 13, notice where he says, hold fast the form of
sound words which thou hast heard of me in faith and love which is in Christ Jesus.
So we find that he refers here, as he's speaking to Timothy, this teaching, this doctrine as
sound words.
If you read the book of Titus, and we won't take time to look at the book of Titus this
evening, but if you look at the book of Titus, you'll see that Titus is given the instruction
to go and to ordain leadership there, and we find that he's given the responsibility
on a number of occasion with regard to sound doctrine.
Sound doctrine.
Jude has only one chapter, but I want you to see the significance of what we find in
Jude as he's writing here, and he gives us, it's amazing as you begin to look at the introduction
here as to what Jude is dealing with, and it's interesting where it says in verse number
three of Jude, he says, Beloved, when I gave all diligence to write unto you of the common
salvation, then notice where he says, it was needful for me to write unto you and exhort
you that you should earnestly contend for the faith which was once delivered unto the
saints.
So now here in the book of Jude, how does Jude refer to doctrine or the body of doctrine?
He refers to it as the faith.
Things, sound words, the faith.
And we find that it's inclusive of all the teaching.
And we find here that Jude says it was needful for me to write, and not only to write but
to exhort you that you should earnestly contend for the faith which was once delivered unto
the saints.
So we have a faith which is worth contending for.
Amen?
Do you believe that this evening?
When we think about doctrine, listen, doctrine matters.
Doctrine is important.
And we begin to think about doctrine this evening, and we understand the importance
of doctrine.
I'm thankful that we have a doctrine that is worth fighting for, contending for, standing
on the truth of the Word of God.
It's not my doctrine.
It's not some religious organization, some denomination's doctrine.
It's Bible doctrine.
And we must understand and make that distinction that what God says settles it.
Just settles it.
I said this on Wednesday evening, and then on Thursday evening I heard another preacher
say it, and he's about 40 years older than I am, not quite, maybe 35 years older than
I am.
And I said to Holly, I was like, I like what he said.
I said the same thing on Wednesday evening, and here's what it is.
Listen, I didn't write the Bible, I'm just telling you what it says.
If you've got a problem with it, you've got a problem with God, right?
And we can rejoice in that in saying, here's what God said.
And so we find that there's no distinction.
Let me show you, however, what the Bible says with regard to those that would teach some
other doctrine.
Turn back to the book of Romans, if you will.
In the 16th chapter, I told you that we'd be in a number of passages, and I want to
give you some things to think about this evening with regard to the subject of ecumenical separation
and why it is that we would not partner with, affiliate with people that do not hold the
same teaching or doctrine that we do, and then give you some thoughts with regard to
that.
In Romans chapter number 16, in verses 17 and 18, notice what the Bible says.
Now I beseech you, brethren, mark them which cause divisions and offenses contrary to what?
To the doctrine which ye have learned, and avoid them.
So in verse number 17, we're given two instructions.
One is to mark them, and two is to avoid them.
That's pretty strong language.
Mark them and avoid them.
Notice in verse number 18, for they that are such serve not our Lord Jesus Christ, but
their own belly, and by good words and fair speeches deceive the hearts of the simple.
Listen, if I'm going to mark someone that has false doctrine, it must mean that I have
to know Bible doctrine.
I can't mark someone that's teaching someone that's false or something that is false.
I can't avoid someone that's teaching something that's false if I don't know the truth.
That's why it's so important that we have a good handle on the Word of God.
That's why it's so important that we study to show ourselves approved unto God, a workman
that needeth not to be ashamed, rightly dividing the Word of truth.
And we find that here, the instruction, notice what Paul says, now I beseech you.
I mean, we look at this word and we speak about the significance.
Paul's saying, I'm begging you, don't mingle, don't mix.
Mark those that are not teaching sound doctrine that cause divisions and offenses that are
contrary to the doctrine which ye have learned and avoid them.
Notice in 2 Thessalonians chapter number 3, 2 Thessalonians chapter number 3, and notice
in verse number 14, this is very interesting because it's speaking about those that aren't
obeying even the words of the epistle that is written to a local church.
And if you look contextually, he's dealing with those that would not work and also with
those that are busybodies.
And he says this in verse number 14, and if any man obey not our word by this epistle,
note that man and have no company with him that he may be ashamed.
Wow.
Note them and have no company with them.
Notice in 1 Timothy chapter number 6, just a few pages over, in 1 Timothy chapter number
6, in verses 3 through 5, in 1 Timothy 6 and verses 3 through 5, the Bible says this beginning
in verse number 3, if any man teach otherwise and consent not to wholesome words, even the
words of our Lord Jesus Christ and to the doctrine which is according to godliness.
And so we find what Paul is referring to as being what we referenced earlier, those
things, sound words, the faith, as Jude refers to it.
He says if someone's teaching contrary to that, otherwise, he notes it in verse number
4, he is proud knowing nothing but doting about questions and strifes of words, whereof
cometh envy, strife, railings, evil surmisings, perverse disputings of men of corrupt minds
and destitute of the truth, supposing that gain is godliness.
Notice what he says at the end, from such withdraw thyself.
From such withdraw thyself.
It doesn't say find what's common between you and them and just embrace those common
things for the cause of X.
No, no, he says from such withdraw thyself.
Notice in the book of Titus in chapter number 3, I mentioned already that Titus had the
responsibility of being given the commission.
In fact, Paul says that he left him in Crete for this purpose, that he would set in order
things that are wanting and ordain elders in every city that I had appointed thee.
He gives them the truth of those that are…the sound doctrine.
He mentions it three times within about 12 verses.
And we find as we come to chapter number 3, in verse number 9, the Bible says, but avoid
foolish questions and genealogies and contentions and strivings about the law, for they are
unprofitable in vain, for they are unprofitable in vain.
A man that is an heretic, after the first and second admonition, what does it say?
Reject.
The word heretic is a follower of a false doctrine, that's what it means.
We use the word heresy.
You understand we've used the word apostasy or apostate, and you notice that many that
are today of these, if you quote-unquote call them mainline denominations, that there's…they
are apostate.
They are heretical in their teaching, following false teaching, false doctrine.
The issue facing the believers in the churches throughout the region of Galatia is addressed
in the book of Galatians.
I don't have time to look at the entirety of the book of Galatians this evening, but
as you study the book of Galatians, you will find that Paul is addressing head-on this
problem that is facing these churches in the region of Galatia, these churches that were
established during that first missionary journey.
And there were some false teachers, they were called Judaizers, and these Judaizers were
coming in and they were teaching that works are necessary to be saved.
And here's what the Bible says in Acts chapter 15, we're going to look at Galatians 1, but
let me tell you what Acts 15 says with regard to really the situation in the region of Galatia.
The council, if you will, in Jerusalem in Acts 15 is in reference to what's happening
in Galatia.
And as we follow the chronological understanding of the book of Acts and what's happening with
regard to the other churches and the other regions, you find that this council that's
called in Jerusalem, that's referenced and recorded for us in Acts 15, has everything
to do with what Paul is writing in the book of Galatians to these churches in the region
of Galatia.
And it is with regard to the Judaizers, and here's what the Judaizers were saying.
It's spelled out for us in Acts 15 in verse number 1,
And certain men which came down from Judea taught the brethren, and said, Except ye be
circumcised after the manner of Moses, ye cannot be saved.
Paul says, I have a problem with that, because salvation is by grace through faith.
Grace alone.
Amen?
It's not grace plus law.
It's not in you have to be circumcised, no, no, no.
And so this drew sharp contention.
There's a great council that takes place in Jerusalem.
If you read the entirety of Acts 15, you see the discussion that takes place, and I'm thankful
that in verse number 11, it says, We believe that through the grace of the Lord Jesus Christ,
we shall be saved even as they, glory, hallelujah, they got it right.
They understood the teaching of the Lord Jesus Christ, and of course, the apostles, they're
giving that truth.
But I want you to see what Paul says in the book of Galatians in chapter number 1.
I want it to reference that Acts 15 so that we could understand contextually what's happening.
And notice the language that Paul uses in Galatians 1.
It is strong language.
In verse number 6, he says, I marvel that ye are so soon removed from him that called
you into the grace of Christ unto another gospel, which is not another, but there be
some that trouble you and would pervert the gospel of Christ.
But though we or an angel from heaven preach any other gospel unto you, then that which
we have preached unto you...
let him be accursed."
Let him be accursed.
Notice in v. 9,
as we said before,
"...so say I now again,
if any man preach any other gospel unto you
than that ye have received,
let him be accursed.
For do I now persuade men, or God,
or do I seek to please men?
For if I yet please men,
I should not be the servant of Christ."
Paul's not trying to be a man pleaser.
Paul says, I know, in fact,
in v. 11 he says,
I certify you, brethren,
that the gospel which was preached of me
is not after man.
For I neither received it of man,
neither was I taught it,
but by the revelation of Jesus Christ.
He says I'm not trying to please men.
I'm not trying to make friends, so to speak.
I'm trying to please God.
And so therefore, if these Judaizers
are coming in and they're teaching
contrary to what I've delivered unto you,
let him be accursed.
That's a strong language.
So we begin to think about the New Testament
and the teaching that is laid out
with regard to the sound words.
Those things.
The faith.
Sound doctrine that is mentioned
multiple times in the book of Titus.
We see what the Bible says in the New Testament
about those that would teach something that's contrary.
And now I ask the question again,
what is it that we'd be willing
to set aside or to abandon
in order to accomplish something?
What part of our Bible would we be okay
with just cutting out and setting aside
and saying no, I don't need that?
And you say, well, that kind of brings it to another level.
I understand.
And that's really what we've got to do in our mind
is we just kind of tear a page out
and say okay, I don't like that.
I'm going to get rid of it.
Well, we would never do that.
I hope not anyway.
Right?
We're not going to take portions of God's Word
and just tear them out and say nope, we don't need that.
We're not going to take a black Sharpie marker
and just mark through portions of verses of Scripture
so that we can have some level of affiliation
with some other group of people, some other denomination.
No, doctrine matters.
And so as we begin to consider the subject,
I just have several things, and again,
I'm not going to teach through all of this this evening.
I hope that it's enough to give us an answer
to help us have some direction for our own lives
with regard to studying and understanding
and being able to draw that line
as to where we would have fellowship or cooperation.
Obviously, we think about theology or the teaching,
the doctrine of God, the deity of Christ.
Listen, there is no room for movement
with regard to the deity of Christ.
Amen?
So many, so many have gotten it wrong
on the person of Jesus Christ.
And listen, if you get it wrong with Jesus,
you get it wrong.
It's just wrong, amen?
We've studied through the book of 1 John
here on Sunday mornings throughout this year,
and as you go to the fourth chapter,
you understand he talks about trying the spirits.
And we understand the importance
of being able to identify,
and he gives us the test there in 1 John 4,
it's with regard to what people say about Jesus.
And I understand in this evening
I don't think we're speaking of,
I don't think the question
that has been submitted this evening
is with regard to some of the false religions of the world
that obviously cults, if you will,
that totally get it wrong on Jesus.
But understand that there are some mainline denominations
that also get it wrong with Jesus.
They teach that Jesus did some for your salvation,
but then there's something else
that needs to be done for your salvation.
Well, that's not the Jesus of the Bible.
Amen?
And so we find that obviously
that is of significant importance.
Let me ask this question.
When you think about doctrine for consideration,
areas of doctrine for consideration,
what about salvation?
What about salvation?
Soteriology, as we often refer to it as,
the doctrine of salvation.
And as we begin to think about salvation,
I'm thankful for what the word of God teaches
with regard to salvation.
I cannot partner with,
I cannot affiliate or associate
with someone that teaches Calvinism.
I just can't.
Why?
Because Calvinism is not biblical.
I do not find in the Bible
where God before the foundation of the world
determined who would be saved and who would not be saved.
I do find, however, in the word of God
that God did determine before the foundation of the world
how man would be saved.
And that is through the Lord Jesus Christ.
And that's why Jesus said,
I am the way, the truth, and the life.
No man cometh unto the Father but by me.
That's why Peter could stand up with great boldness
in the book of Acts in the fourth chapter
in verse number 12 and say,
there's no other name under heaven
given among men whereby we must be saved.
The name of Jesus Christ.
But the idea, please, no pictures, no video, thank you.
What I'd like to say is this,
with regard to the teaching of Calvinism
is that they would say that there's a,
and I'm not gonna go through all of Calvinism this evening,
but listen, they would say that there's a limited atonement
that Jesus only died for the elect.
I got a problem with that.
Why do I have a problem with that?
Well, let me just show you one verse.
We could spend all night on this and we're not going to,
but look at the book of 1 John, if you will,
in the second chapter.
And notice here what the word of God says.
They often will say, see, we sing the song,
whosoever will may come.
Aren't you thankful that you're a whosoever?
The Bible says in Romans chapter 10 and verse number 13,
for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord
shall be saved.
Whosoever, I'm a whosoever, amen, and I'm thankful for that.
And Calvinism will all of a sudden say,
well, that's not really what whosoever means.
All doesn't really mean all.
World doesn't really mean world.
They begin to redefine terms.
I'm not telling you a line here.
I'm telling you the truth, okay?
And here's what the Bible says in 1 John 2
and verse number two.
And we know it's speaking of Jesus.
We see in verse number one, it says, my little children,
these things write I unto you that you sin not.
And if any man sin, we have an advocate with the Father,
Jesus Christ, the righteous.
Aren't you thankful that we have an advocate with the Father?
Praise the Lord.
And that advocate is Jesus Christ.
And he, according to verse number two,
is the propitiation for our sins.
There's not a period there.
But I'm thankful for that.
He's writing to save people in the book of 1 John.
And you and I this evening, we'd say,
he is the propitiation for my sins, right?
Amen.
He's the covering.
He's the mercy seat.
He's the satisfaction for our sins.
God Almighty was satisfied with the offering
of the Lord Jesus Christ, God's Son,
God in the flesh on the cross of Calvary.
But note the next words, and not for ours only,
but also for the sins of the whole world.
There's no limited atonement.
God so loved the world that he gave himself.
He died for all of mankind.
So can I partner with someone that's Calvinistic?
I can't.
Let me ask you this.
What if someone says that you need to have grace plus works
in order to be saved, or how about this,
in order to stay saved?
Is that what the Bible teaches us?
No.
The Bible says, for by grace are you saved through faith
and that not of yourselves is the gift of God,
not of works, lest any man should boast.
And then it tells us this in the book of 1 Peter,
that we are kept by the power of God.
Listen, I'm not, we've mentioned this
throughout the study of the book of 1 John,
when he talks about the things that we're to do,
the evidences of our salvation,
when we look at the book of Ephesians
and see the walk of the believer,
the behavior of God's people,
he's not saying live like this so that you can be saved.
He's not saying live like this so that you can stay saved.
He's saying because you are saved,
this is how you're supposed to live.
This is how you're supposed to behave.
And it's not so that we can be saved,
nor is it so that we can stay saved.
Listen, if I could lose my salvation,
I would have lost it the day after I got it,
maybe an hour after I got it, amen?
I'm serious.
So if someone says it's grace plus works,
remember in the book of Galatians chapter two
in verse number 21, I believe it is,
Paul says, I do not frustrate the grace of God,
for if, and he talks about if righteousness came by the law,
then Christ is dead in vain.
Listen, my Savior did not die in vain.
He was raised from the dead.
And if I could earn my way to heaven through my works,
then there's no reason that Jesus Christ
had to leave the throne room of heaven
and come to this sin-cursed world
and die on that cruel cross.
But the reality is that I couldn't, neither could you.
And so he came so that he could do for us
what we could not do for ourselves.
So it's not grace plus works, it's grace alone.
And there are some denominations
that would teach grace plus works for salvation.
There are others, again, you need to be careful,
that would teach salvation is grace alone.
But then when you begin to understand and study,
you find that they say, but you need to have these works
in order to stay saved.
Now I want you to think about something with regard to that.
I believe, obviously, we can look historically
at some really large denominations
that had that teaching and still hold that teaching today.
And really what that teaching does.
does is it gives power to the clergy. It gives power to the clergy because the clergy is
able to say, hey, if you don't do this, then you're not saved. Well, all of a sudden, that's
a great motivator to get people to do things, to give money, to serve, to do whatever, right?
Because hey, you're not going to be saved if you don't do these things. But that's just
not what the Bible teaches. So I can't stand with someone that would say it's grace plus
works for salvation or even to keep my salvation. What about those that would teach that you
could lose your salvation? I'm sorry, the Bible says that we're kept by the power of
God. I'm sorry, but the Bible tells me that Jesus, He said, I know my sheep, they hear
my voice, they follow me. He says, I give unto them eternal life and they should never
perish. Those are precious words. He did not say that the gift of God is probationary life.
He did not say that the gift of God is temporary life. He said that the gift of God is eternal
life. Aren't you thankful for that? I've never been on probation and I hope I never will
be. Amen? But the reality is that probation, if I understand it properly, you're out on
probation and you have to walk a pretty fine line or you go back to the big house, right?
It's kind of how it works. God didn't give you and I probationary life. He gave us eternal
life. He knows our frame. You know that He knew that you'd sin and He saved you anyway
because He's gracious, He's merciful. So you think about salvation, okay? All of a sudden
here's what we're doing. We're identifying, nope, I can't partner with that group of people.
Nope, I can't affiliate with them. Nope, I can't. And I'm not saying it to be prideful
or boastful and just stand up and say, we're the only ones that have it right. I'm just
simply saying, why is it that we'd say there are only this many people in this particular
country? Well, because I can't partner with someone that's teaching something contrary
to the Word of God. What about ecclesiology, the doctrine of the church? Listen, the church
is God's idea. It's not man's idea. The church was not Constantine's idea. Amen? The church
is God's idea. The Lord Jesus Christ said, I will build my church and the gates of hell
shall not prevail against it. So when we think about ecclesiology, we think about the church.
What about officers in the church? The Word of God teaches that there are two officers,
pastor and deacon. And by the way, they're to be men. So what about a denomination that
ordains women? Are we going to be okay with that? Are we going to say, well, we can partner
with them because there are some other things that are okay? Oh, you've got to be careful.
Where does it lead to? What kind of questions come in, right, when they start reading their
Bible and say, well, how does that? No, no. Many denominations have a hierarchical structure
or system. We find that the local churches throughout the New Testament are dealt with
as local churches. God gives a pastor as an under-shepherd. It is His church. He is
the head of the church. There's not some person on earth that, some hierarchical structure.
What about baptism? Does baptism matter? Sure it does. What does the Bible teach about baptism?
You know that there are a number of denominations that would teach infant baptism that would
practice infant baptism. Why don't we baptize infants? Because we believe the Bible teaches
clearly that the candidate for baptism is someone that is saved. Amen? That has professed
their faith in the Lord Jesus Christ. There are some, I was doing some research, I was
going to give you a whole list of different denominations and call them all by name, and
I thought that might not be a good idea. The Spirit of God didn't give me permission to
do that. But I had all sorts of research and ready to do it. But you know, there are a
number of people, there's one denomination that said this, that will allow someone to
get baptized as long as there's someone else that's vowing that they will stand with them
and train them and teach them, and that when they're older, what in the world? That's not
what Philip said to the eunuch when the eunuch said, hey, there's water, see, here's water,
what doth hinder me to be baptized? And Philip says, if thou believe, believe what? That
Jesus is the Christ, that He's the Son of God, then you can. So when we baptize someone,
what do we say? I say this, we have a baptism, I say, if I'm baptizing, who hasn't been baptized
yet? Isaac, you haven't been baptized yet. And so I'm not saying that he should be, I'm
just saying, I'd say, Isaac, have you trusted the Lord Jesus Christ, your personal Savior?
He says, yes, I have. Are you sure that when you die that you're going to go to heaven?
And he says, yes, I am. And I say, Isaac, based upon your profession of faith, I now
baptize you in the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghost, buried in the likeness
of His death, raised to walk in newness of life. So not only do we have the candidate,
but we have the mode. Are we okay with sprinkling? You understand what we're saying here? As
we begin to dig in and begin to look at doctrine and look at what the Word of God says, listen,
Paul didn't give any kind of lateral movement with regard to these things are the most important
things and these things, well, they're kind of just secondary. No, no, he says those things,
what you have heard of me, the sound words that I have taught you. Jude says the faith.
What about the Lord's Supper? There are denominations. It's just not the Catholics, by the way. There
are others that teach transubstantiation. What does that mean? Well, it means that they
teach that the bread literally turns into the body of Christ and that the blood literally
turns into the, or excuse me, the wine, the grape juice literally turns into the blood
of Jesus. When you read 1 Corinthians 11, the Bible tells us that it's a picture, that
it's a memorial. This do in remembrance of me, right? So, many denominations, they would
teach that with regard to baptism of the Lord's Supper, that's how you're born again. That's
what they would teach. Are you going to heaven? Well, have you been baptized? Have you taken
the Lord's Supper? Listen, it's not about baptism of the Lord's Supper to go to heaven.
Those are steps of obedience. Those are the ordinances for the local church. Those are
reminders of what Christ did for us, but salvation is through the Lord Jesus Christ, period.
The thief on the cross didn't get baptized and didn't take the Lord's Supper, right?
So we find these things are important. What about eschatology, the doctrine of the end
times? I can't, we're out of time. Let me ask you this, what about today in our society
we're living in? What about human sexuality? Does it matter? Absolutely, it does. Does
it matter that God said that He made man and woman, male and female? Absolutely, it matters.
And so we begin to think about that, how many denominations have followed culture instead
of Bible, right? There's a pressure from the culture to fold, to cave in, to try to
accommodate. Unfortunately, God said that we're to stand on the truth. I say unfortunately,
but it's really not unfortunate. I'm thankful that God's given us the truth, amen? And truth
doesn't change. Truth is not relative, that it's your truth or my truth or their truth
or someone else's truth. It's God's truth, He is truth. And so human sexuality matters.
And you begin to find, listen, you don't even have to go to a lot of websites to find out
what churches believe on it. Just drive by their churches and you can see the signs.
They just put it right out there. By the way, there's some Baptist churches that are flying
flags that they shouldn't be flying, amen? It doesn't mean that we don't love people.
Don't misunderstand what I'm saying. I preached this morning about loving. Listen, love never
excuses sin. God's love is not a permissive love that I'm going to permit you to do whatever
you want to do because I love you. No, God's love is a protective love. And because God
loves us, He gives us the truth. And if we really love people, we need to tell them the
truth. Because honestly, if we think about this this evening, if we cave in to the pressures
of our society, to the pressures of our culture, if we try to be accommodating and we set aside
Bible truth and we just begin to tell people, hey, everything's going to be okay, you're
going to be just fine, just be sincere in what you believe, they're going to spend eternity
in the lake of fire. Because it's not about being sincere in what they believe. It's about
believing what Christ said, amen? And there's a great distinction between those two things.
What about godly living? Again, culture or Bible. Does holiness matter? Does godly living
matter? Sure it does. My Bible says that we're to be holy in all manner of conversation.
Because He is holy.
And He said, be ye holy, for I am holy.
So holy living matters.
Bible versions.
Does it matter?
Sure it does.
You know how many of the modern translations today
are taking and attacking the person of Jesus Christ?
The doctrine.
So many people say, oh, the new modern translations,
they're just trying to ease of readability.
They're not really changing anything.
I would challenge you to study it out.
Study the verses.
This evening, we could go on and on.
But I hope that just these things
that I've shared with you tonight
would help us understand why ecumenical separation is
so important.
It's not enough for someone to say, I believe Jesus.
OK, I believe Jesus too.
Let's go.
No, there's a whole lot more.
And we must understand the doctrine, the faith that
was delivered to us.
And we're to earnestly contend for the faith.
And so when we begin to try to reach people
with the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ,
and we begin to partner with other groups of people
because we think that it's going to accomplish some greater
goal or greater accomplishment, and then we
find out that that particular group of people
is teaching something contrary to the word of God,
what mass confusion is the result?
Because we encourage people to read their Bibles,
and to begin to read their Bible,
and to begin to see, well, this isn't really lined up here.
And that's not really lined up there.
And what about this?
And what about that?
Are there people out there that we can fellowship with,
associate with?
Sure there are.
There are people that we can associate with.
But we must make sure that we do a test
and make sure that they align with this book.
And let me say this.
At the same time, we must make sure we align with this book.
Amen?
We say that it's the sole authority for our faith
and our practice.
And we must make sure that we align with this book,
that what we do is biblical, and that we're seeking
to please Him with our lives.
So can two walk together except they be agreed?
At what point along the journey does the division,
does the difference matter enough?
What Bible teaching would you be OK with just marking out
of your Bible, saying, OK, I'm going to take that,
and I'm going to just put that aside.
Because for the sake of whatever,
we're going to be willing to, man, this book is precious.
And God said every word is pure, every word.
I'm not going to take a pen knife or a Sharpie
and start removing things from my Bible.
We have to stand on the truth.
Amen?
Listen, it doesn't make us better.
It shouldn't result in pride.
I am humbled.
I am humbled that God allowed me to receive the truth,
honestly.
And I am not only humbled, but we have been entrusted,
and we are responsible to give the truth.
It's not about a group of people sitting back and saying,
we're right, everybody else is wrong.
No, that's the wrong approach.
God's been so gracious to give me truth.
And now I want to give that truth to those
that He would allow me to come in contact with.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the word of God and for the truth
contained therein.
We thank you for those things and sound words, the faith,
doctrine, sound doctrine.
Lord, we thank you so much for the word of God.
I pray that you would help us this evening, Lord,
in this moment of invitation, that we would just
rejoice in the fact that you've given us truth.
And then, God, I pray that you'd help us to be burdened,
to share that truth with others.
I pray that you'd move and work in the hearts of your people
as only you can, and we'll thank you for it.
In Christ's name, we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
We'll have a moment of invitation this evening.
And Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano.
And as she does, maybe you want to visit this altar
and thank God for the truth, for the sound words
that he's given us.
Maybe you want to ask God to help
you to be faithful, to give that truth to others.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.