Dealing with great levels of difficulty, of course
We understand that after David was used by God and God enabled him to defeat Goliath
that of course there were some other battles with the Philistines and
David was recognized by several within the the ranks of Israel as being a wise person
of course
the women were singing his praises and they said something of this nature that Saul had slain his
Thousands, but David his ten thousands and of course Saul as the king didn't like that a whole lot and of
Saul sought
Continually to kill David and so over this portion of Scripture in this section of 1st
Samuel you see often where David is fleeing
From the dangers of Saul and how God is working miraculously on his behalf
And as we look at the passage of Scripture this evening
we're gonna look focus for the the main thought of the lesson from verses 16 through 18 and
Somebody read that passage and then we'll get into the lesson this evening. The Bible says in Jonathan Saul's son arose and
went to David into the wood and
strengthened his hand in God
And he said unto him fear not
For the hand of Saul my father shall not find thee and thou shalt be king over Israel and I shall be next unto thee
and that also saw my father knoweth
they too made a covenant before the Lord and David abode in the wood and
Jonathan went to his house
Again, if you will a lesson within a lesson really the thought of 1st Samuel 23 as we look throughout this passage of Scripture
You find that it begins with the Philistines attacking the city of Keilah
The Bible begins in verse number one and says then they told David saying behold the Philistines fight against Keilah
And they robbed the threshing floors
And so we find that David is made aware of the situation with the Philistines
Attacking the city of Keilah and David inquires of the Lord
He seeks the face of God he and his men go to Keilah and they provide deliverance from the Philistines
I mean, that's a wonderful
passage of Scripture the first five verses
I mean you think about the victory that they experienced you think about the
The joy that was in that city and amongst those people when they experienced the victory of the Lord and how God's
guidance and leadership
Gave them the direction that they needed for that particular time, but we find that the Bible tells us
that they
After they experienced victory that Saul was aware of what was taking place
In fact, if you read in verse number seven
You find that Saul was going to seize the opportunity if you will
To go and get David and we know that he wanted them dead in verse number seven
The Bible says and it was told Saul that David was come to Keilah and Saul said God hath delivered him into mine hand
For he has shut in by entering into a town that hath gates and bars
So what does Saul do he gathers the people of war together according to verse number eight and they were gonna go down to Keilah to
Besiege David and his men. It's interesting that Saul was not the one he and his men
they didn't come to help Keilah from the Philistines and
We find that it was David and his men that went to the city to help deliver
These inhabitants from the attack of the Philistines
But now when Saul hears word that David is in this city
And he looks at as being a grave mistake for he's shut in
He's in a city a town that hath gates and bars
And so Saul is going to seize his opportunity to finally get David
We find that David inquires of the Lord
he asked the Lord two simple questions as
We look at the first really twelve verses of this passage of Scripture to really set the scene for what's going on
And he asked two questions number one. He asked the Lord is Saul going to come
See David had heard that Saul he'd heard about the plan that Saul had devised and that Saul was going to come and so David
Inquires and he asked specifically of the Lord is Saul going to come you can read of that in verse number 11 and you find that
God answers the specific request notice. It says will the men of Keilah
Deliver me into his hand will Saul come down as my servant hath heard and the Bible tells us that the Lord God of Israel
Gives an answer at the end of verse number 11. It says the Lord said he will
Come down
The second question that David asked and really it was posed first in verse number 11
But it's addressed second and the answer is given in verse number 12
And that question was this whether or not the men of Keilah would deliver him and his men into the hand of Saul
the Bible says that
God answered again at verse number 12 at the end. It says the Lord said they will
Deliver thee up now. Can you imagine put yourself just for a moment in the shoes of David?
Understand the circumstances that are going on
I'm trying to set the scene this evening to help us understand really the condition in which David has found himself
He goes and he delivers this city from the Philistines
While he's experiencing victory and there's a level of joy. He hears about this plan of Saul
he's gathered up the men of war and they're going to come together for the purpose of besieging David as men and
David says God is he gonna come and are these people gonna deliver me into his hand and God says yes
He's coming and yes, they will deliver you into his hand
Now you might have a different expectation of what the inhabitants of Keilah would do for you after you did for them
Right. I mean, is that a fair assessment?
David and his men they went they fought against the Philistines
They're the ones that brought victory to the city of Keilah
But yet these men these inhabitants of this town this city Keilah when they find that Saul is coming
no, they're gonna deliver David and
His men and we find that as we look at the really the main emphasis of the story that rate within the lesson is
A lesson that I want to focus on this evening. We've read the verses of Scripture already in verses 16 through 18
Let me read verse 16 again
Give you the title and we'll get into the message
The Bible says and Jonathan saw son arose and went to David into the wood and strengthened his hand in God
I've simply entitled the message this evening
Jonathan strengthened
David's hand
David's hand, you know, the reality is that there are times in which we're all in need of encouragement
We're all in need of someone to help strengthen us encourage us
And we find that David was in a situation here where he was being hunted
In fact, the Bible tells us in verse number 14 of the passage of Scripture that Saul saw him David
Everyday, can you imagine?
David had earlier made this confession that there was but a step between him and death
Saul was serious about his
agenda to kill David
Dave was in this position
And so as we look at the passage and we think about the fact that Jonathan strengthened David's hand
I want you to consider just two thoughts this evening. Number one is this
Jonathan was aware of the situation
The Bible tells us in verse number eight and Saul called all the people together to war
To go down to Keilah to besiege David and his men early on
We find that Saul tried to keep his motive secret as to what he wanted to do to David
we find that early on in 1st Samuel chapter number 18, in fact when
Saul has this idea that he was going to send David out to war and thinking that David would fall by one of the hands
Of the Philistines when Saul had the idea that he was gonna make David his son-in-law
He's gonna give his daughter in marriage
he requested of the the dowry if you will and he thought that
David would be killed by the Philistines that he would fall by the hand of the Philistines
We find that Saul kind of had this secretive agenda
If you will early on on his desire to see David killed
Of course, we know that he threw the javelin and tried to kill David on more than one occasion in chapter number 19
as you kind of progress through the situation and really think about what Jonathan was aware of we
Understand that they had this friendship
In fact, let me read a couple of verses before we get into chapter 19 in chapter 18 in verses 1
Really 1 through 4 the Bible says and it came to pass when he had made an end of speaking unto Saul
That the soul of Jonathan was knit with the soul of David
Jonathan loved him as his own soul and Saul took him that day and would let him go no more home to his father's house
It says this in verse 3 then Jonathan and David made a covenant because he loved him as his own soul
And Jonathan stripped himself of the robe that was upon him and gave it to David and his garments even to a sword and to
His bow bow bow, excuse me and to his girdle
We find that as we look at the passage of Scripture
We begin to think about this
friendship that had been developed over the years between these two men and we find that that Jonathan was aware of the situation for this
Is what said in chapter 19 after?
those events in chapter 18 when Saul had kept his
Agenda his motive secret in verse 19 and verse 1 of chapter 19
It says in Saul spake to Jonathan his son and to all his servants notice this that they should kill David
Saul's plan in chapter 18 his secret agenda didn't come to pass and so now Jonathan is made aware of this in fact in
chapter 19 Jonathan says to his father what why what has he done I mean you saw
how that God used him to provide deliverance in fact in verse number five
it says for he did put his life in his hand and slew the Philistine and the
Lord brought a great salvation for all Israel thou sawest it and did rejoice
wherefore then wilt thou sin against innocent blood to slay David without a
cause this particular time in verse number six Saul hearkened under the
voice of Jonathan and Saul swear as the Lord liveth he shall not be slain so
David is brought back into the presence of Saul and shortly thereafter we find
that David was playing with his hand in verse number nine and John Saul was
there with a javelin in his hand and what did he do in verse number 10 Saul
sought to smite David even to the wall with the javelin he slipped away out of
Saul's presence he's delivered by his wife and we see all sorts of things
taking place and it's in chapter number 20 when we find that as David and
Jonathan devised this plan as to how he would determine if there was ill set
against him that the Bible tells us after their event there they're really
their plan that they came up with David of course was not going to be there to
eat his place would be empty and the Bible tells us in chapter 20 in verse
number 30 that Saul's anger was kindled now against Jonathan the Bible says that
he said unto him thou son of the perverse rebellious woman do not I know
that thou hast chosen the son of Jesse to thine own confusion and under the
confusion of thy mother's nakedness for as long as the son of Jesse liveth upon
the ground thou shalt not be established nor thy kingdom wherefore now send and
fetch him unto me for he shall surely die Jonathan then answered his father
look at what he says in verse 32 he said to him wherefore shall he be slain what
hath he done so Saul then cast a javelin at Jonathan it says this and Saul cast a
javelin at him to smite him whereby Jonathan knew that it was determined of
his father to slay David so he was aware of the situation chapters 21 and 22
provide us some events in the life of David when he's seeking refuge he is
delivered by the priest of Himalaya and of course Doeg one of the servants of
Saul was there and he heard about what's going on and in all of the slaughter of
the Levites in that passage in his his family and we come to the 23rd chapter
and as David is there at Keilah and now the Bible tells us that Saul called all
the people together to war he was gonna go down and so this man Jonathan he was
aware of the situation he was aware of what was going on he was aware of the
plan of his father he was aware of the situation of David no doubt in my mind
because of the friendship that had been developed over the years between these
two men and their experiences together that the Bible tells us that Jonathan
loved David as his own soul so we find that Jonathan has a level of concern and
compassion for David we find that he's aware of the situation there are times
in our lives where we may be aware of something where someone is going through
a difficulty there's some hardship some trial some difficulty that someone is
going through and we're aware of the situation being aware of the situation
is good but we got to do something about it and that's where we find as we really
look at the passage of Scripture we find first of all that he was aware of the
situation number two notice this that Jonathan took action to strengthen David
he did something about it I want you to consider what's taking place I want to
consider with me this evening really the the risk that Jonathan was taking upon
his own life I mean in chapter number 20 when he stood before his father Saul and
said what has he done we find that Jonathan is the one now that's having a
javelin thrown at him so Jonathan is going to go and we find that Saul is
seeking David at this particular time because David was diligent to seek
counsel from the Lord and he found out that yes all is coming and yes these
people are going to deliver you into his hand what did David do they got out the
Bible tells us in verse 13 then David is men which were about 600 arose and
departed out of Keylon went whithersoever they could go and it was
told Saul that David was escaped from Keyla and he forbear to go forth and so
the Bible tells us in verse number 14 that David abode in the wilderness and
strongholds and remained in a mountain in the wilderness of Zipf and Saul sought
him every day but God delivered him not into his hand thank God for his
protection and what a blessing that is the Bible says in verse 15 and David
saw that Saul was come out to seek his life and David was in the wilderness of
Zipf in a wood we find that he's in this place he's being sought teen as men and
we find that the Bible tells us in verse 16 and Jonathan Saul's son arose notice
what it says and went to David what did he do he went to David in the place
where David was the Bible says that he went to David into the wood he found
where David was and he went to him David was in a situation here we know later on
in the book of 1st Samuel as you would come to the 30th chapter of this book
you find that David is in a situation where he returns from the potential of
going into battle and he returns to the city of Ziklag and he finds that the
Amalekites had come in and had taken captive all of the family and they'd
taken everything and David was greatly distressed and there in that passage the
Bible tells us that David encouraged himself in the Lord but in this
particular occasion in 1st Samuel chapter 23 we find that Jonathan was
used of the Lord to come to where David was and to strengthen his hand in God to
encourage him I think about the joy that must have filled David's heart and
soul at the sight of Jonathan can you imagine we've quickly gone through
several chapters of references from chapter 18 through 20 to help us to
understand this relationship that had developed between Jonathan and David
this friendship this godly friendship and we find that now as David is being
hunted and he's going from place to place and he's there in the wood in
this wilderness of Zipf what a joy to see the face of Jonathan have you ever seen
someone that maybe not seen for a while and man there's just a great sense of
joy that fills your heart upon the sight of that individual they're coming for
the purpose of encouraging and strengthening you we find that Jonathan
comes not only do we notice what he did but we notice what he said in verse
number 17 the Bible records for us really this brief encounter that
Jonathan has with David this brief opportunity that he has he sees the
opportunity to encourage his friend to strengthen his friend notice he says
unto him number one fear not fear not now typically you tell someone to fear
not because you sense that there might be a sense of fear right I mean if I
show up and you look like man everything's going great I mean
everything's wonderful and you're enjoying great victory if I greet you by
saying fear not you're gonna be like what is he talking about why does he
get the idea that I'm afraid right you understand but when we can can you sense
when someone's afraid sure you can there are times and situations in which we can
see on the countenance of an individual that there is something that has caused
them a level of fear there's something that's going on and the Bible tells us
as we go through the passages amazing passage of Scripture here in first
Samuel 23 but as we look at the lesson within the lesson we think about this
moment of time in which Jonathan comes and encourages David the Bible says that
he says fear not no notice what he says for the hand of Saul my father shall not
find thee is it interesting to you how easy it was for Jonathan to find David
and yet Saul was not able to find David he saw him in fact as we look through it
says that he sought him every day he saw him every day but God delivered him
not into his hand what a blessing we find that Jonathan comes and he shows up
and he says to David is he's there in his presence he says fear not for the
hand of Saul my father shall not find thee then he tells him this and thou
shalt be king over Israel see Jonathan understood the plan Jonathan understood
what God was doing Saul no doubt was aware of it even as Jonathan mentions
here at the latter part of verse number 17 that Saul also was aware of this plan
remember that it was back before David ever was anointed to be king of Israel
that God through Samuel had told Saul that God has rejected you from being
king see Saul had been disobedient we find that there's occasion in which he
did not wait as he was supposed to he did not obey in the manner in which he
was to obey and we find that Samuel had to deliver that message to Saul that
He was rejected by God.
I do not believe that Samuel
enjoyed delivering that message,
for the Bible tells us that Samuel mourned for Saul.
In fact, as you come to the first verse
of 1 Samuel 16,
the Bible says,
"...And the Lord said unto Samuel,
How long wilt thou mourn for Saul?
Seeing I have rejected him
from reigning over Israel.
Fill thine horn with oil,
and go, I will send thee to Jesse the Bethlehemite,
for I have provided me a king among his sons."
Who is that? It's David.
And so Jonathan reveals to David,
now I want you to understand,
a man that's on the run,
a man that's been hunted now
for a number of chapters
as recorded here in the book of 1 Samuel,
he's delivered at the end of chapter 18.
We find that there's the truth
of what Saul's trying to do.
He then makes it broadly known
in chapter 19,
he's delivered by his wife
and protected by Samuel.
And we find that as you go through
chapters 19, 20, 21, 22,
that David's on the run.
And you find that he says to Jonathan
at one particular occasion,
there's but a step between me and death.
And we think about understanding
that's there in 1 Samuel 20
in v. 3, the latter part of the verse,
but truly as the Lord liveth
and as thy soul liveth,
there's but a step between me and death.
If you're in that situation,
if you're considering the fact
that you're being hunted,
as you're considering the fact
that there's but a step between you and death,
the thought of being king of Israel
is not really close on your mind.
Right?
What does Jonathan do?
He reminds him of God's promises.
He reminds him of God's plan.
Jonathan comes to David.
He comes to the place where he is.
It says that he arose and he went
to David into the wood.
Strengthened his hand in God.
He tells him to fear not.
He then tells him that Saul's not going to find him.
He reminds him of the plan and promise of God.
He says, thou shalt be king over Israel.
If God has ordained it that you're going
to be king over Israel, and He has,
and we know that you've been anointed to be king,
you're not king yet,
so you know that God is going to protect you.
He's going to provide for you.
Can you imagine the encouragement?
See, there are times in our lives,
thinking about the life of Jonathan,
but also thinking about the life of David,
there are times in our lives
when we're in a situation,
we're dealing with a level of circumstances
and a difficulty in which we might think
it's helpless.
It's hopeless.
We're not thinking properly.
We're in a place where we're not thinking properly
because of a circumstance,
a situation that you're dealing with,
and somebody's able to come alongside of you
and remind you of some of what God's plan is,
some of what God's promises are.
It may not be that you have forgotten them entirely
or completely,
but it's just not fresh on your mind
because you're dealing with all of these circumstances
and all of these adverse situations
that you're dealing with,
and you say, I'm overwhelmed with these things.
In fact, many of the psalms in which you read
where David is crying out
and saying, how long, O Lord?
When David's crying out and saying
that his heart is overwhelmed,
many of those psalms are penned
during this period of time of the book of 1 Samuel
when he's on the run.
And I can't help but think about
the encouragement of Jonathan
in this passage of Scripture.
It's a lesson within the lesson.
And think about the impact that it made
on David's life in this very moment of time.
The Bible says in v. 17,
"...and I shall be next unto thee,
and that also saw my father knoweth."
The Bible tells us in v. 18,
"...and they too made a covenant before the Lord,
and David abode in the wood,
and Jonathan went to his house."
Jonathan couldn't stay where David was,
but he risked whatever the cost would be,
perhaps his life,
to go to where David was
to encourage him, to strengthen him.
As I think about this passage of Scripture
and I think about the truth that
Jonathan strengthened David's hand,
I wonder this evening,
whose hand is it that God has for us to strengthen?
Who is it that God may allow us
to have some knowledge of a circumstance
or situation that they're dealing with
and God may use us to go and strengthen their hand?
That we would take action.
See, Jonathan was aware of the situation,
but Jonathan took action.
He did something about it.
He was willing to go into the presence
to risk maybe even his own life.
Do you think that Saul would have been pleased
to know that Jonathan was going to find where David was?
No, this is a dangerous situation.
Jonathan had already been in the presence of Saul once
when Saul took a javelin and threw it at him.
We find that Jonathan said,
I need to go encourage my friend.
I need to go and strengthen his hand in God.
He was aware of what was going on.
And this situation with David was again,
a number of passages of Scripture,
chapters that we read of this ongoing drama
that David is facing
and all of this difficulty that he's dealing with.
And we find that he comes and they make this covenant
and then David stays there in the wood
and Jonathan returns to his house.
As I think about this passage of Scripture
and think about the role of Jonathan,
I'm reminded of what the Bible tells us about Job.
Go over to Job 4 if you will.
Now, often we think about the book of Job.
We think about all of the difficulty that Job encountered
and certainly he had some great difficulty.
You read there in Job 1
and you read of all the things that befell him
and you read into chapter 2
and see how that it continues to just increase.
And the Bible tells us that he had some friends
at the end of chapter 2 that were going to go
and they were going to come and they sought to bring comfort.
And of course, we know that later in the book of Job,
that Job will describe his friends
as being miserable comforters.
But I want you to consider what is said of Job
in Job 4.
In verse 3, it says,
Behold, thou hast instructed many,
and thou hast strengthened the weak hands.
Thy words have upheld in him that was falling,
and thou hast strengthened the feeble knees.
Job was a man that was used of God to encourage many.
To strengthen them.
We see it in verses 3 and 4 here of Job 4.
And of course, we find that it goes into the fact
that now Job is in that position
where he needs the encouragement.
He's dealt with some tragedy, some difficulty,
and now he needs the encouragement.
And no doubt, there are times in our lives
where we need encouragement,
but this evening as we look at this passage of Scripture
and we consider what's going on in the life of David,
and we say, thank the Lord
that Jonathan was sensitive to the need
and Jonathan was willing to take action and go
and strengthen the hand of David.
And I just wonder this evening,
I think about the New Testament.
I think about many throughout the portions of Scripture
that were used to be encouragers.
Barnabas is probably one of the first examples
that would come to our mind
as one that was an encourager.
No doubt, he encouraged Paul on a number of occasions.
We find that as we would look throughout the Scriptures
and we think about those that came
and there were several that Paul would mention
how they refreshed me.
They oft refreshed me
and how these individuals were used by the Lord
to go and to seek him out,
to seek to encourage him and to strengthen him.
This evening, David was in a difficult situation.
God delivered him
just as Jonathan had given him the encouragement.
God worked miraculously.
If you read the end of 1 Samuel 23,
you find that just as David and his men
are completely surrounded by Saul and his men,
that the Bible tells us that there came a messenger to Saul
and said the Philistines have invaded the land
and we find that Saul and his men
have to retreat and go take care of that
and God miraculously delivers David and his men.
And what a blessing.
But in the midst of the trial,
Jonathan comes and strengthened his hand in God.
This evening, is there someone that God might want you
to encourage, to strengthen?
Are we looking for that opportunity?
No doubt there are times you say,
pastor, I hear what you're saying,
but I'm the one that needs encouragement.
Sometimes it's easy for us to look at things that way.
Amen?
We're all dealing with difficulties
and I'm not trying to discount those difficulties.
I'm simply saying that God could use you
to be an encouragement to someone else,
to strengthen someone else.
their truth from His Word,
to be able to strengthen their faith
to continue on.
I can only imagine
how David must have felt
at the sight of Jonathan.
I'm sure it was refreshing.
It was encouraging.
Just him coming.
And then as they sat there
and they talked
and Jonathan shared these truths,
reminded David,
God has a plan for you, David.
You're going to be the king.
We find that David was strengthened
by Jonathan.
Oh, that God would use us in like fashion.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You this evening.
We thank You for loving us.
Lord, we thank You for the encouragement
that You give us through Thy Word.
We thank You for the examples
that we're able to read of.
We believe in this particular account
here this evening of Jonathan
being aware of the situation,
but then taking action
to go to where David was
to speak to him,
to encourage him,
to strengthen him.
God, this evening, I pray,
You'd help us to be sensitive
to the leadership of the Holy Spirit of God
in our lives.
Help us, God, to be used of Thee.
Help us to encourage and strengthen
the brethren.
I pray that You would bless our time of prayer.
We thank You for the privilege of prayer.
We pray that You'd be honored and glorified
through all that's said and done.
For it's in Christ's name we pray,
Amen.