Number one, 2 Timothy chapter number one,
we finished last week, 1 Timothy.
And of course, our theme for this calendar year is continue.
And we have had this theme throughout the year.
In fact, even for our missions conference this year,
we kept the same theme
because we wanna keep ingrained in our minds
the importance of continuing
and to continue to serve the Lord,
to remain faithful in the midst of opposition
and adversity and all that we would face,
that our eyes are on Jesus,
we're looking unto Jesus,
the author and finisher of our faith.
We find that the apostle Paul is used of God
in 1 and 2 Timothy to encourage his son in the faith,
as he's referred to, to continue.
And he tells them in this particular book
in 2 Timothy, we'll get there in a few,
probably a couple of months,
in 2 Timothy chapter number three,
he tells them about the last days that we're living in
and the perilous times
and all the characteristics of those days.
And he says that evil men and seducers
shall wax worse and worse,
deceiving and being deceived,
but continue and don't give up,
don't throw in the towel,
continue, remain steadfast, unmovable,
always abounding in the work of the Lord.
Why?
For we know that our labor is not in vain in the Lord.
And what a joy, as we enter into the second book,
the second letter, 2 Timothy chapter number one,
we'll just be looking at two verses this morning.
And we note the similarities and the greetings
in 1 Timothy, 2 Timothy, and also in the book of Titus.
These three books or three letters
are often referred to as the pastoral epistles.
We think about these three particular letters
and we find that as Paul would have it,
of course, all scripture is given by inspiration of God,
but as Paul would be writing to Timothy and to Titus,
he refers to both of them as being his son.
Now, they're not his son biologically or physically,
but we understand that spiritually speaking,
the apostle Paul had a great relationship
with both Timothy and Titus.
I believe that that relationship
with these younger servants of the Lord
was both special and unique.
I believe that the apostle Paul in his heart
had a special place for Timothy and for Titus.
And I think that Titus and Timothy also held in their heart
a special place for Paul and all the influence
that he had upon their lives.
In fact, it's interesting to note how Paul,
yes, he encourages many that he writes to
with regard to how he's praying for them,
but I think about these individuals,
Timothy and Titus engaged in the work of the ministry
as pastors that God would use Paul to encourage them
and to remind them that he's praying for them.
And what a tremendous blessing that is.
Paul, of course, through these two books,
specifically dealing with the life and ministry of Timothy,
Paul would be used of the Lord to both instruct
and encourage Timothy.
We find that he'll be used of the Lord
in the book of Titus to, again,
both instruct and encourage Titus.
But what was Paul's desire?
I believe that Paul desired that these men,
that Timothy, in the context of what we're looking at
this calendar year,
that Timothy would serve the Lord faithfully,
that Timothy would serve God all the days of his life,
that he would be able to say, as Paul will say
in this particular letter in the fourth chapter,
that I have finished.
I've come to the end and I fought a good fight.
I kept the faith and what a joy.
And I believe that that's Paul's desire.
So Paul, understanding all of the circumstances
of what was taking place at Ephesus
with regard to the false teaching
and all of the opposition
that Timothy would be dealing with,
God understands that as well.
And therefore, God would send and use Paul
to write these letters to be a blessing
and an encouragement to Timothy.
We find that this letter that is before us this morning
is the final letter that we have of the Apostle Paul.
We do not know with certainty how many weeks, months
took place between the writing of this letter
and Paul's death.
But we know that it was within this short period of time
that after Paul wrote this letter,
that Paul would face a martyr's death,
that he would die for his faith in Christ Jesus.
And as we look at this passage,
notice with me in chapter one,
we're just gonna look at verses one and two.
The Bible says this,
Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ,
by the will of God,
according to the promise of life,
which is in Christ Jesus,
to Timothy, my dearly beloved son,
grace, mercy, and peace
from God the Father and Christ Jesus, our Lord.
If you've looked at the back of the bulletin
already this morning,
I've simply titled the message
from verse number two this morning,
grace, mercy, and peace.
I mean, just the sound of those words
brings a measure of encouragement, does it?
And we think about this truth
and what Paul is giving to Timothy here.
And I just have two thoughts for you this morning,
but remember, just because there's two points
doesn't mean it's gonna be any shorter.
And first point this morning, if you're taking notes,
the first thought is this,
notice what Paul acknowledged.
As we look at these two verses of scripture,
we find that Paul acknowledged some things
that are important not only for Paul,
they're important for Timothy,
but they're important for each of us as well.
As the people of God,
there are some things that we must acknowledge
or recognize.
And we find in the text of scripture,
number one, that Paul acknowledged the authority of God.
Notice in verse number one,
the Bible says Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ,
by the will of God.
And we find that the apostle Paul,
he understood who he was,
and he understood who God is.
I believe that if we begin to understand
how that Paul acknowledges the authority of God,
even in the greeting that he writes to Timothy,
that it's crucial, it's absolutely imperative,
it is critical for every child of God
to acknowledge God's authority in our lives.
See, the reality is that we have this society
and this culture has almost ingrained
in the minds of people that you are your own authority
and you are the one that determines
and you make the decision.
But as a child of God,
I understand that Paul says to the believers in Corinth
in chapter number six of the first letter he writes them
in first Corinthians six,
what?
Know ye not that what?
Your body is the temple of the Holy Ghost,
which is in you what you have of God,
and ye are not your own,
for you are bought with a price.
Therefore, we're to glorify God.
How?
In every way, in every part of my being,
I am to glorify God.
Why?
Because he owns me.
It's a matter of authority.
It's a matter of ownership.
And we find this morning as we look at this truth
as the apostle Paul,
he's acknowledged the authority of God in his life.
Understand with me that the apostle Paul,
before his name was ever Paul,
we know him as Saul.
And we understand that Saul was a man
that was a religious man.
Saul was a man that knew the Old Testament.
I mean, he was trained by the best of the best.
He was extremely familiar with Judaism
and all of its ins and outs.
And he was a religious man,
but as he's going and persecuting
and giving consent to the death of Stephen
and all that he's doing,
he has letters in his hand.
He has the authority that he could go
and put to death to imprison any that be of this way
or of that way, that being Christians.
We find that the apostle Paul,
at that point, his name is Saul.
He meets Jesus.
In Acts chapter number nine, it's recorded for us.
The Bible says that he sees this bright light
and he hears a voice.
And the voice is, Saul, Saul,
why persecutest thou me?
And we find that Saul answers and says,
who art thou, Lord?
I am Jesus, whom thou persecutest.
It is hard for thee to kick against the pricks.
There was a measure of conviction
that was coming in Saul's life.
And then Saul follows up the question
of who art thou, Lord, with this,
Lord, what wilt thou have me to do?
Isn't that amazing?
To consider immediately upon salvation
how the apostle Paul, in that moment,
he acknowledged, he recognized the authority of God
in his life that he's going with a certain purpose,
with a certain agenda.
But his life is transformed.
If any man be in Christ, he is a new creature.
Old things are passed away.
Behold, all things are become new.
And we find that this man, after his conversion,
he says, Lord, what will Thou have me to do?
He did not say, now, Lord, here's what I plan to do.
He didn't say, now, Lord, here's my ability.
Here's my talent.
Here's how you, God, can use me.
No, he said, Lord, what will Thou have me to do?
Now, God used the apostle Paul in a mighty way.
God used Paul to establish churches and regions
where the gospel had not yet been.
He used Paul to stand before leaders,
both religious and political, and to profess
the gospel of Jesus Christ.
But I believe that no matter, as we look at the life of Paul,
I believe that no matter what God would have assigned him
to do, he would have willingly done it.
Why?
Because he recognized God's authority.
I believe this morning that when you and when
I acknowledge God's authority in our lives,
that it will have a great impact.
It will change the direction of our lives.
Shortly after I got saved as a senior in high school,
I mean, I was just a couple of days
into my senior year of high school
when I trusted Christ as my Savior,
when my life was changed radically
by the truth of being born again.
And my pastor at that time, you know,
as a senior in high school, typically,
you've already been thinking about what you're
going to do with your life.
You've already considered the colleges
that you potentially are going to attend,
and perhaps even the majors that you're
interested in pursuing.
And I'd had those conversations, and I'd
had those ambitions, and what have you.
And I remember my pastor saying something like this
after I got saved.
He said, now, Chris, what does God
want you to do with your life?
You know, up until that point in my life,
no one had ever asked me that question.
You know, the question that I heard so often is,
what do you want to do with your life?
And if we're not careful, sometimes we still
ask young people that question.
Hey, what are you going to do with your life?
What do you want to do with your life?
Can I tell you, if we're saved by the grace of God,
the best question is not, what do I want to do with my life?
It's, what does God want me to do with my life?
We must acknowledge this morning God's authority.
I believe that the Apostle Paul recognized
and he acknowledged that God has authority in his life.
When God opens a door, Paul goes forward.
When God shuts a door, Paul waits.
Paul understands God's authority.
By the way, it is far better for God
to have the authority in your life
than for you to have the authority in your life.
Sometimes we want to hold on to that authority,
that power, and think that we have control,
but you know, oftentimes we end up shipwrecked.
In fact, that's what Paul spoke of
in the book of 1 Timothy.
We talked about those that were shipwrecked.
And the reality is that it's far better
to let God have control.
Perhaps some of you have seen the bumper sticker
that says, God is my co-pilot.
Can I tell you this morning, God better be your pilot.
Amen?
God better be your pilot.
He has all the authority in your life.
That's true of every child of God.
We mention even at times with pastors
moving from one place to another,
or missionaries moving from one place
of ministry to another.
Listen, God is God, and he is the authority.
And if God tells us to move, we better move.
If God tells us to stay, we better stay.
Because God is the authority.
And that's true of every child of God.
I've heard people say, I'm gonna move.
I'm gonna move here, I'm gonna go do this.
Are you sure that's what God wants you to do?
I'm not God, I can't tell you,
but I better encourage you and counsel you
to know that it's the will of God.
God's authority.
See, we find that Paul first acknowledged
the authority of God in his life.
Number two, Paul acknowledged God's will for his life.
Notice in verse number one, he says,
Paul an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God.
And so we find that there's an acknowledgement
of God's authority.
God is sovereign and God has the right.
And we find that Paul also acknowledged
what God's will was for his life.
He says that his will, he's an apostle of Jesus Christ
by the will of God.
Can you understand with me just for a moment this morning
that the apostle Paul did not submit an application
to be an apostle.
He did not submit an application with the resume
and he came to the, no.
We find that it was the Lord's will
that Paul be an apostle.
And we find that Paul embraced that, why?
Because he understood authority.
Because of understanding the authority,
it's no problem accepting the will of God for our lives.
Because if I do not understand the authority of God,
if you do not understand the authority of God,
it's gonna be really difficult to accept
and acknowledge the will of God.
We start with acknowledging the authority of God.
It's interesting here in 2 Timothy chapter one,
he says Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ
by the will of God.
If you turn back a few pages in your Bible
and look at the beginning,
the introduction to the book of 1 Timothy,
I want you to notice how Paul references it here
in 1 Timothy.
He says this in 1 Timothy one and verse number one,
Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ.
So we understand his office.
He says in chapter, in the second letter,
by the will of God, here he says,
by the commandment of God.
It's kind of interesting.
He uses in the first letter, the commandment of God
and the second letter, the will of God.
Do you know that God's commandment to you and to me
is God's will?
And God's will for you and I is his commandment.
They really can be used synonymously.
And we understand this morning that God gave a command
and Paul understood that command
to be also God's will for his life.
And what a joy to think about the apostle Paul
fulfilling what God had desired for him to do.
Listen to me this morning,
God's will is not simply revealed to me
or to you so that we could consider it.
God's will is revealed to us so that we would fulfill it.
God's will is not something that's open for consideration.
Far too often though, that's how we deal with it.
Well, I'll consider that, I'll think about that.
Maybe we even say, I'll pray about that.
But when God makes his will clear to us,
it is not something for me to simply consider,
to think over, no, it is for me to fulfill,
for me to simply obey.
By the way, it's a joy to know
that you're doing what God wants you to do.
It is an absolute joy to know that you're in the very place
where God wants you to be doing what God wants you to do.
We find here this morning that understanding
the authority of God helps me to obey the will of God.
And Paul acknowledged in these first few words
of the second letter to Timothy,
that he's an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God.
How does this help Timothy?
Well, Timothy had a position as well.
Timothy had to understand God's authority as well.
And as Paul is seeking to encourage his son in the faith
who's dealing with adversity and opposition in Ephesus,
Paul reminds him of what he personally
had acknowledged in his life.
By the way, Paul faced much persecution
and adversity as well.
What kept him going?
God's authority and God's will.
Because he knew that God had authority in his life
and he knew the will of God.
And therefore he continued to do
what God had commanded him to do.
How would Timothy be able to continue in Ephesus?
How would Timothy be able to come to the end of his life
and say, as Paul will say in the fourth chapter,
I have finished, I have completed,
I have fulfilled what God had for me to do.
How could Timothy in the midst of the opposition
and the adversity, well, Timothy,
he better understand and acknowledge the authority of God.
And he better understand and acknowledge the will of God.
Listen, God's will doesn't change
just because there's some opposition.
We don't just run in the face of adversity or opposition.
No, if we're doing the will of God,
we continue, we remain steadfast, why?
Because we're doing the will of God.
And Timothy had to understand that.
Let me say to you this morning
that we too must understand this truth.
We must acknowledge God's authority.
Who's the authority in your life?
Honestly, who's the authority in your life?
Who's the authority in my life?
God is the ultimate authority.
authority in our lives and we must acknowledge that this morning. What is God's will for your life?
Do you know God's will? Are you doing God's will? Are you fulfilling the will of God?
I'll tell you this morning that at times no doubt the will of God can be a scary thing.
I mean when God first called me to preach, I thought you got the wrong guy. Like that's not for me.
That's not something I'm interested in doing.
But the question kept coming back.
What does God want you to do?
What is God's will? He acknowledges something else in this text of scripture. Notice with me number three.
The Apostle Paul acknowledged that God is the source
of grace,
mercy,
and peace.
The Bible says in verse number two to Timothy, my dearly beloved son,
grace,
mercy,
and peace.
From God the Father
and Christ Jesus,
our Lord.
Grace,
mercy,
and peace.
We understand as we speak about grace and the unmerited favor, love, and favor of God. We understand
grace. We sing about amazing grace.
We talk about saving grace and no doubt for by grace are you saved through faith and that not of yourselves
is the gift of God, not of works lest any man should boast. And we understand being
saved by grace, but we acknowledge this morning that Paul is writing to a saved man.
He's writing to Timothy, his own son in the faith that's saved. He's going to heaven.
He's been born again. He's a child of the king,
but he says grace.
We look in the scriptures and we find that not only
is there saving grace, but there's serving grace.
The grace to serve God.
The grace,
the ability that God gives us to do what God has called us to do.
In fact, we find that Paul says this, for by the grace of God I am what I am. We find that Paul
acknowledges this as he's praying for deliverance and God says
as he did not deliver him, he says in 2 Corinthians chapter 12, my grace
is sufficient
for thee. We find that Peter would say that we're to be good
stewards of the manifold grace of God in 1 Peter chapter 4. Within the context
specifically, the Bible says as every man hath received the gift, even so minister.
Right? And we see that he says how are we to minister as being good stewards of the manifold grace of God?
And the reason by which we minister is so that God might receive the glory.
So that God would be exalted and magnified. And so we find this truth of grace that's being
reminded to Timothy of God's grace. Oh, that grace
would be evidenced in your life that you would understand
the grace of God.
He says mercy.
Mercy.
I'm thankful that the Bible tells us that his mercy endureth
forever.
I'm thankful this morning, mercy dealing with compassion that's manifested
towards a person
in distress.
That's one of many definitions for mercy.
But I think specifically with regard to
the writing of this particular letter to his son in the faith, to Timothy as a pastor, as a
leader there in Ephesus, that he, the apostle Paul, is saying, listen, yes, there's going to be times of distress,
but I'm praying for God's mercy
in your life.
God's grace.
God's mercy. But then notice number three. He says
peace.
Peace.
Harmony and rest.
Psalm 118 and 165 says, great peace have they which love thy law and nothing shall offend them.
Great peace have they which love thy law. I'm thankful that our God is the prince of peace.
I'm thankful that he gives a peace according to what the Bible says in Philippians 4 and verse number 7 is a peace that passeth all
understanding.
We're to allow, let the peace of God rule
in our hearts according to the book of Colossians.
We find that Paul,
as he's speaking to Timothy as he's writing this letter, Paul acknowledged that God alone is the source of grace.
mercy
and peace.
Peace is not simply found in the absence of trouble.
So often we find that the mindset of an individual is that if I could just have my life void of trouble,
then I might achieve peace in my life.
The problem is that God reveals to us in the book of Job that man is born a woman of few days and full of troubles.
The psalmist says that God has delivered me out of all my troubles and no doubt
we understand that as we live in this life, there will be troubles.
But you know that we can have peace in the midst of trouble.
Why? Because peace comes from God.
Peace is not found in the absence of trouble rather in the very presence of God.
So understand that my God is on his throne. My God has a plan.
My God
loves me with an everlasting love, with a love that is beyond my ability to fully comprehend.
And I find that I can have great peace.
Great peace.
This morning
we look at these two verses of scripture and we find that Paul acknowledged
the authority of God in his life.
I hope that every one of us this morning would acknowledge God's authority in our lives.
I am not the authority of my life. God is.
And I must. If I understand, if I recognize,
if I acknowledge this morning that he is the authority,
then it will help me to do
what he commands me to do.
And Paul acknowledged the will of God. I'm an apostle of Jesus Christ by
the will of God.
I want to fulfill what God's will is for my life.
And he acknowledged that God is the source for grace, mercy, and peace. Paul knew
he'd been in the ministry for a number of years.
Paul knew
the hardships and the difficulties that would be encountered, the opposition that would be faced. And Paul knew
that he himself needed grace,
mercy,
and peace. And therefore, as he writes to Timothy, he says grace, mercy, and peace. Why? Because Timothy, if he's going to fulfill
what God has for him, he needs grace,
mercy, and peace.
So do you. So do I. I'm thankful that God is the source
of grace,
mercy,
and peace.
Number two,
in your notes this morning, we, number one, notice what Paul acknowledged. Number two, notice what Paul appreciated.
What did he appreciate? Well, as I look at these two verses of scripture and just kind of
meditate upon them, and I begin to find that Paul,
in these two verses, he reveals some things to us. I believe that that one thing that he appreciated, if you're taking notes,
he appreciated the work of the ministry. He appreciated the work of the ministry. You know,
I believe that Paul believed that it was a privilege to be an apostle.
He said that he was the least of all the apostles.
He says in the same text that I mentioned a moment ago that I am what I am by the grace of God.
Listen, Paul, I believe he appreciated the opportunity to serve God.
Do you recognize this morning what a blessing it is to serve the Lord?
I mean,
there are times in which we think about service to God, and maybe we think about it just in the context of the preacher
standing up and preaching as I'm doing now, or the musicians standing up and singing as they did a few moments ago.
But I'm telling you, it's a blessing to serve God when you're cutting the grass of God's property, when you're
vacuuming the floors in the house of the Lord, when you're a doorkeeper, is what the book of Psalms says, in the house of the Lord.
Amen?
Why? It's just a privilege to serve him. He's the king of kings, lord of lords. He's the creator of the universe.
He has all power, all authority, and I know me and you know you,
and he says that he would allow us to serve him.
It's absolutely amazing.
I think,
as I studied the scriptures,
I think that there probably wasn't a day that passed that Paul didn't appreciate
what God did in his life.
Not only by saving his soul, but letting him serve.
Can you imagine? It's a joy and privilege to serve the Lord. We sing the song,
there is joy in serving Jesus. And there is, there's joy.
We get to go and be his
representatives, his ambassadors, to be able to serve. I believe that specifically as we look here and think about the apostle Paul,
yes, he's appreciative of the work of the ministry, the privilege of being an apostle.
I think also he's appreciative of the ministry with regard to the role of being a mentor. Notice
he says in verse number two, to Timothy, my dearly beloved son.
That opportunity to be a mentor, the ability to influence somebody else for the cause of Christ.
I mean, what a joy.
we ought to appreciate the fact that God would use us
to be able to have an impact in someone else's life.
I hope this morning that you have in your life a Paul,
somebody that invested in you,
somebody that discipled you, somebody that taught you.
I've heard before preachers say
that every Christian needs to have a Paul.
What do they mean by that?
Well, somebody that mentors us,
somebody that instructs us, somebody that invests in us.
Maybe this morning, even as I make those statements,
you can think in your mind of who your Paul is.
It's interesting for me, my Paul is Paul.
Paul Mershon is his name,
and he's a man that has the same name as this apostle,
and many of you know him, and he is a mentor to me.
I spent an hour on the phone with him on Thursday
to see how he and his wife are doing
because of the current situations,
and man, he's just invested in me over the years.
And oh, how I appreciate that.
He's not the only Paul.
There's a number of others
that I could mention this morning by name
that have actively invested in my life.
Just like every believer needs a Paul,
I'll say this, every believer needs a Timothy.
What do I mean by that?
Well, Paul had a Timothy.
Who's your Timothy?
Who are you investing in?
Who are you trying to be a mentor to,
that you're trying to point them to Christ,
that you're trying to lead them along
in their journey and their walk with Christ?
You understand this morning,
I enjoy, I thoroughly love discipleship.
I truly do.
I love sitting down with people on a one-on-one
or a one-on-two kind of a setting in my office
and just discipling people,
just teaching them and having questions and answers
and all of that, it's enjoyable.
But you understand this morning
that I can't do that with every single person,
nor is it really my job.
Every Christian should have a Timothy.
Who are we investing in?
I mean, purposefully.
Who are we seeking to influence?
Acknowledging and appreciating the fact
that God would use us.
You say, well, I don't know everything.
Listen, whatever you do know, you can help somebody with.
You can let them know what God's done in your life
and you can lead them and teach them.
It's also said in that same context
that every Christian needs a Barnabas
and we understand how he encouraged.
Paul often was encouraged by others.
In fact, in this first chapter,
he mentions a man by the name of Anesiphorus,
a man that oft refreshed him is what he says.
He oft refreshed me.
What a blessing.
The thing about Barnabas and the ministry that he had
in the life of the Apostle Paul early on
with regard to Paul's ministry,
this morning we ought to be encouraging one another.
You know what Paul appreciated?
He appreciated that God saved him
and God would let him serve him.
I hope this morning you appreciate
the privilege of serving.
You say, well, all I do is cut the grass.
Praise God, praise God.
All I can do anymore is this, praise God.
Everyone can't, listen, can you know how chaotic it'd be
if all of us tried to preach right now at the same time?
It'd be absolute mess.
Would it not?
I remember talking to a man years ago.
I would describe him as a senior saint.
I think he would describe himself the same way.
And he met with me one day and he said,
Pastor, I just can't do this anymore
and I can't do this anymore and I can't do this anymore
and I just can't do this anymore
and I can't do this anymore.
And I kind of, after about four or five things,
I just kind of stopped them.
And I said, listen,
I really don't care about what you can't do.
Here's what I want to know, what can you do?
Because if you're still here,
there's something that God can use you to do.
God can use you to do something.
And you know, when I asked that gentleman that question,
his whole demeanor changed
because he's really kind of overwhelmed
with a measure of sadness
because of the things that he no longer could do
because of his elevated age.
And I said, well, what are some things that you can do?
And he said, well, I can do this.
And I was like, you know, as far as I know,
there's no one else in our church that can do that.
That's how God has equipped you.
And that's what God wants you to do.
And his countenance just completely changed
through that conversation.
Why?
Because he recognized there's still something
that God can use me to do.
And it's a joy to serve Christ.
What did Paul appreciate?
Well, he appreciated the work of the ministry.
Number two, I think he appreciated physical life.
He says this in verse number one,
notice it says, Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ,
by the will of God, notice it says,
according to the promise of life, which is in Christ Jesus.
Now, I'm gonna get to a final point here in just a moment,
but I do think there is an acknowledgement here
of being appreciative of life, physical life.
Somebody says, you've heard people say it before,
that every day I put my feet on the ground,
I thank God for the day that he's given me.
The Bible says this in Psalm 118,
this is the day the Lord hath made.
We will rejoice and be glad in it.
God is the author and giver of life.
He's given you the ability to breathe
and to have life today.
But he asked this question,
or he tells us this truth in his word, what is your life?
It's but a vapor that appears for a little time
and then vanisheth away.
We find that here in 2 Timothy chapter number one,
as Paul is taking out the pen and he's writing this letter
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
we find that Paul is sitting in a prison awaiting death.
As Paul was aware of the reality
that he would soon be put to death,
I believe that this reality would cause Paul,
but really would cause any individual to evaluate
and to appreciate the gift of life that was given to them.
I'm so thankful for life.
And I think Paul, he was thankful for life.
But I think greater than being thankful for physical life,
as it says, the promise of life, which is in Christ Jesus,
I think in a far greater sense,
he was appreciative of the truth of eternal life,
of eternal life.
See, Peter says it this way,
that his tabernacle he would soon put off.
In other words, he would die.
I said to a half a dozen people yesterday
as we're out door knocking,
that one day we're gonna die.
And I said this to several of them,
that David said in the book of 1 Samuel,
there's but a step between me and death.
I said, no, contextually,
the reason that David says that
is because Saul's trying to kill him, hunting him.
And David says there's but a step between me and death,
but in a very real way,
in a very real way, for all of us this morning,
there's but a step between me and death.
You say, oh no, I'm young, I'm full of life.
And I got, have you ever read the obituaries?
Have you ever gone through a cemetery or a graveyard?
You can find, I don't enjoy doing that,
but I have before, and you can go through
and you can see dates on headstones.
And you can see some that the individual was 70, 80, 90.
Some that they're seven, eight, nine.
Some that are just infants, days old.
Am I not right?
I spoke with a man years ago,
Mary Finley's granddaughter was dying.
Some of you wouldn't remember Mary Finley
and her granddaughter was dying
and she's probably about my age.
And her husband was Chris and I sat in the room,
Holly and I were sitting there with them
and the doctor had given her just a few days to live.
As best I knew, and in fact, as best I still know today,
Chris was not a saved person.
The focus in that particular day was not on Chris,
but on his wife who had been given the words
from the doctor that you just have a few days to live.
But as best I knew and what had been communicated to me
was she had trusted Christ as her savior.
So I knew and I had assurance that if that were true,
based upon the truth of the Bible,
that she would enter into heaven
because her physical life would end,
but she would cross that door
and enter into the presence of heaven.
So my concern really was Chris.
And I said this to Chris, I said, listen,
I understand what the doctors have said
and you understand what the doctors have said,
but you know that either one of us could die before she does.
I had driven to their house that day and I said, listen,
I could get in the car to go back to the office
and I could die in a car accident
on the way back to the office.
You know, people die in car accidents all the time.
All the time.
We're about a step between us and death.
And Paul knew that his physical life was soon going to end.
But I think Paul appreciated the truth of eternal life, in this great sense of being
a recipient of the gift of God, which is eternal life.
Paul, I believe, that as he's writing here, and he says, according to the promise of life
which is in Christ Jesus, yes, there's the life that we're living, that physical life,
but we understand the focus on eternal life.
I asked this question this morning, before I ever got into the Scriptures in 2 Timothy,
after they sang that song, I said, are you sure that you're going to heaven?
Are you a child of the King?
I'm thankful that the Apostle Paul, he had this assurance that though he would soon die,
that he would be in the presence of his Savior.
Turn back, if you will, to the book of 2 Corinthians in chapter number 5.
2 Corinthians, chapter number 5, there's a great discourse here in this passage of
Scripture with regard to the certainty that Paul had of eternal life, and the certainty
this morning that every human being can have of eternal life.
Ron and I, we were knocking doors yesterday.
He was my partner as we went out, and one man said this to us when I asked him if he
was 100% sure if he were to die that he'd go to heaven.
How could anyone know that?
If you try to tell me that you know that, you're just prideful.
Can I tell you this morning?
I don't know that I'm going to heaven because of anything I've done.
It's all because of what Jesus did.
The truth of the matter is that there's not one of us that deserve it.
We're not deserving.
It's because of His grace and His mercy that we could be born again, that we could be saved.
By the way, Jesus said to Nicodemus, a religious man, marvel not that I say unto thee, ye must
be born again.
Except a man be born again, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God.
We find here in 2 Corinthians chapter number 5, notice how it begins in verse number 1,
for we know.
For we know.
Aren't you thankful that we can know?
Paul doesn't say for we think.
He doesn't say for we hope.
He says for we know.
The authority that God has given us in His Word.
For we know that if our earthly house of this tabernacle were dissolved.
What does he mean by that?
Why is he using this language?
Well basically he's saying, listen, when this old flesh, when I die, when this, if our earthly
house of this tabernacle were dissolved, notice we have a building of God and house not made
with hands eternal in the heavens.
For in this we groan, earnestly desiring to be clothed upon with our house, which is from
heaven.
What's he saying in verse number 2?
Listen, there are days that we long for heaven, amen?
We say, man, heaven is a wonderful place and I'm ready to go.
Now what a joy it's going to be to be in the presence of our Savior.
People sometimes ask this question, what's heaven going to be like?
Oh, there's a whole lot of things that God tells us that heaven's going to be like, but
I'll tell you what makes heaven heaven is Jesus will be there.
You can take all the other things that are mentioned about heaven and if you remove Jesus,
it ain't the same.
Jesus in the presence of our Savior.
Listen, verse 3, if so be that being clothed, we shall not be found naked.
For we that are in this tabernacle do groan, being burdened, not for that we would be unclothed,
but clothed upon that notice when he says that mortality might be swallowed up of life.
D.L.
Moody said this, he said, one day you're going to read in the headlines that D.L.
Moody's dead.
Don't believe it for a second.
For in the day that you read that headline, I will be more alive than I've ever been.
What was he talking about?
He's talking about mortality being swallowed up of life because we have the truth of eternal
life.
Now, verse 5, he that hath wrought us for the self, same thing as God, who also hath
given unto us the earnest of the Spirit.
If you've been born again this morning, if you've been saved by the grace of God, the
Bible teaches us that at the moment of salvation, the Holy Spirit indwells us.
He is the earnest of our inheritance.
We see it here in 2 Corinthians 5.
We see it in Ephesians chapter 1.
I referenced earlier about 1 Corinthians chapter 6, that the Holy Spirit is, that our bodies
are the temple of the Holy Ghost, which is in you, which you have of God.
And he says that we have been given the Holy Spirit, which is the earnest of our inheritance,
Ephesians 1, verses 12 through 14.
Therefore, we are always confident, knowing that whilst we are at home in the body, we
are absent from the Lord.
Do you know that this morning?
I mean, listen, this is not heaven.
Someone tried to tell me that this is heaven.
Man, this is not heaven.
This is absolutely not heaven.
How many of you know this is not heaven?
Amen?
This is not heaven.
Somebody try to tell me that.
This is not heaven?
You've lost your mind if you think this is heaven.
Amen?
We know, look in verse 7, for we walk by faith, not by sight, and I love verse number 8.
He says, we are confident, I say, and willing, rather to be absent from the body and to
be present with the Lord.
Wherefore, we labor that whether present or absent, we may be accepted of Him.
Listen, Paul said, I'm confident.
Paul wasn't afraid of dying.
Paul had no fear of death.
Why?
Because he knew whom he had believed.
He knew that Jesus is the author of eternal life, life, yes, but eternal life.
And he had been given that gift of God.
He could not work for it.
You cannot work for it.
He did not earn it.
You cannot earn it.
Jesus paid for all of it.
He didn't just put a down payment and you got to work for the rest.
No, He paid for it all.
Paul, he says, we're confident, I say, and willing, rather, to be absent from the body
and to be present with the Lord.
Back in the book of 2 Timothy, notice with me in chapter number 4, familiar text of Scripture,
one that I've hinted at twice already this morning.
But in chapter number 4 and verse number 6, Paul says this, for I am now ready to be
offered, and the time of my departure is at hand.
I want you to think about the phraseology that he says, I'm ready.
Listen, if you're not confident of heaven, you're crazy to say, I'm ready to die.
But when you're confident of heaven, because of the gift of God, which is eternal life
that you are a possessor of, then you can say, I am ready.
I am ready to be offered.
The time of my departure is at hand.
I have fought a good fight.
I have finished my course.
I have kept the faith.
But I want you to notice verse number 8, henceforth, there is laid up for me a crown
of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous judge, shall give me at that day, and not
to me only, but unto all them also that love his appearing.
You know, he gives clarity here in verse number 8.
Some people, I asked the guy yesterday, what's going to happen when he dies?
He's like, well, you know, you just become a tree, you become a dog, you become a bird.
Like, come on, man.
We just know that's not true.
Amen?
As is appointed unto man, he wants to die, but after this, the judgment.
Here Paul says that there is laid up for me a crown of righteousness, which, notice what
he says, the Lord, the righteous judge, shall give me, but he says at that day.
There are two judgments that are mentioned in the Bible, and we're running out of time
this morning, but one of them is the bema seat, the judgment seat of Christ.
Can I tell you this morning, if you're saved by the grace of God, that's the judgment seat
that you'll stand at.
By the way, that's the one you would prefer to stand at, the bema, the judgment seat.
And the Bible tells us that Paul had this confidence that he would receive a crown from
the Lord, the righteous judge, and he says this, not to me only, but also unto all them
also that love his appearing.
There's some crowns that we could receive.
We could suffer loss.
We could receive reward, according to 1 Corinthians.
But there's a second judgment that's explained to us in the book of Revelation in chapter
20, and it's called the great white throne judgment.
That's a judgment that you don't want to stand at, because that judgment is for those that
have not trusted Christ as their Savior.
That judgment is a judgment that will end in being cast in the lake of fire.
The Bible tells us very plainly and very clearly that there's but two destinations for mankind,
heaven or the lake of fire.
And we look at this text of Scripture and we say, listen, Paul acknowledged some things,
but Paul was also appreciative of some things. What did Paul appreciate? Well, he appreciated
the work of the ministry, he appreciated life, but most importantly, he appreciated the truth
of eternal life. I wonder this morning, how thankful are we to have eternal life? I hope
every day of your life, you thank God for being saved. I hope every day of your life,
you thank God that somebody cared enough to tell you the truth of the gospel, and that
it would convict us to tell others the truth of the gospel, because men are dying. People
are dying. They need to know the truth of the gospel. Do you acknowledge this morning
that God has all authority in your life? Young people, so often, it's the young people that
hear this message so often about God as the authority of your life, and it's true. But
can I tell you, for every single one of us, regardless of our age, we must acknowledge
this morning that God is the authority, that God has a will for us, a purpose, a plan for
your life and for my life, that God is the one who gives grace, mercy, and peace. Now,
we would serve the Lord joyfully, appreciating the fact that He would allow us to serve Him.
You know, He could have used the angels, but He chose to use us. It's amazing. It's amazing.
Grace, mercy, and peace. There's some things that Paul acknowledged, some things that Paul
appreciated, and I hope this morning, just as it would be the case for Timothy, that
he had to acknowledge and appreciate those things, that we too, we must acknowledge those
things and appreciate those things. Allow God to have His will and His way in our lives.
Let's pray together. Father, we love You. We thank You for loving us. We thank You
for Your Word, the truth contained therein. God, if there's one here this morning or tuned
in via live stream that's not sure of heaven, God, I pray that today would be the day of
their salvation. They'd come to this old-fashioned altar in just a moment as we have an invitation
and allow us to take a Bible and show them how they could know for sure that heaven is
their home. God, I pray for every Christian, every believer this morning. I pray, God,
that You'd help us to acknowledge Your authority in our lives. God, if we've been trying to
live as if we are the authority, would You help us to confess that and forsake that?
Lord, help us to yield and submit to Thee that You might use us, God, for Your honor
and for Your glory. I pray that however it may be that You've worked in the hearts and
lives of Your people this morning, God, that You'd help us to be doers of the Word and
not hearers only. Help us to respond in obedience and we'll thank You for it. In Christ's name
we pray.