with you Romans chapter number 12, Romans chapter number 12 and it certainly is a familiar portion
of scripture this morning. Romans chapter number 12, we'll look at a number of verses this morning
but as we think about our theme for the year, great is the Lord and greatly to be praised.
And we've had the opportunity throughout the calendar year, we're nearing the very end
and we've had the opportunity to discover God's greatness. We've spoken about those that have
declared God's greatness and then how do we respond? How does God's greatness impact your
life? How does his greatness impact my life? If I truly believe that God is great, it should be
evidenced in my behavior and we spent a number of weeks looking at the thought with regard to how
his greatness will shape our prayer lives. We spent some time looking at how his greatness
will impact and shape our service to the Lord and as we kind of look at this thought this morning
in Romans chapter number 12, kind of bringing everything together that we've looked at throughout
the year and we deal with the subject matter of absolute surrender. When I truly understand how
great God is, it should impact every area of my life, every area of your life, we should be
surrendered to the Lord. Why? Because great is the Lord and he is greatly to be praised. He is deserving
of every aspect of our lives. The reality is that when we hear the word surrender,
when an individual hears that word, it can be met with a mixed type of response, various emotions
that someone may have with regard to the idea of surrender. In fact, some immediately will resist
the idea of surrender. Why? Simply because they desire to be in control. They don't want to
surrender, not even to God, and that's unfortunate. And we think about those that would resist. They
would respond with a resistance to the idea of surrender because they desire to be in control.
I would say to you this morning that that response leads to a great struggle. That response not only
leads to a great struggle, but I believe this morning that it hinders our effectiveness for
the Lord. Our lack of surrender will have a direct adverse impact that will hinder our effectiveness
to the Lord. As believers, the concept, the idea of surrender is well known. In fact, we preach
about it, we read about it, we even sing about it. I surrender all. How many of you know that song?
Raise your hand. Help me this morning. How many of you know the song, I surrender all? Not every word
of it, but you're familiar with it. Almost everyone's hand was raised. I know this. Listen, we are
familiar with the idea of surrender. However, this morning, it isn't a matter of how much one knows
about surrender, rather how surrendered one is to the Lord. It's not enough to sing about surrender.
It's not enough to read about surrender. It's not enough to preach about or hear preaching
about surrender. The reality is that we can know a lot about a subject and still not do it, not
apply it. And we find that the idea, the word surrender, in Noah Webster's 1828 dictionary,
here's what the word surrender means. To yield to the power of another. To yield to the power
of another. To give or deliver up possession upon compulsion or demand.
Idea of compulsion, to be compelled, to be constrained. Keep that in mind as we think
about this subject matter of surrender and thinking about that definition to yield to
the power of another. As believers, when we speak about surrender, we're speaking about
surrendering to the Lord who was great, the one who created all things, the one who saved your
soul, the one that is worthy of our all. We speak about the subject of surrender and you could deal
with it in a number of contexts. You could deal with it from a military perspective, in one army
surrendering to another army. You can deal with it in a number of different contexts. But this
morning, as we deal with the subject of surrender, we're speaking about we as the people of God
surrendering to the King of kings and Lord of lords. We sing this song, it is best to let him
have his way with you. What is that? That's surrender. That's yielding. My life, Lord,
is yours to control. Is that not what the song says? That's what the songwriter says?
Why is it that the songwriter would be led to write a song, to write the words of that song
and then to sing that song because they understand the biblical principle of surrender?
Notice in Romans chapter number 12 in verses 1 and 2, the apostle Paul is writing to these
believers. He says, I beseech you, therefore, brethren. And so we find that he's writing to
believers. It's always important for us to understand the context. He's not writing to
lost people. This morning, the message to lost people throughout the Bible, the message to lost
people is you need to be saved. Amen? Repent and trust Christ as your Savior. It's the message that
Jesus delivered to Nicodemus, ye must be born again. That's the message to an unbeliever.
This morning, we find that this passage of scripture is written to people that have
already trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as their personal Savior. Therefore, they are called
brethren. By the way, I'm thankful to be a brethren. I'm thankful to be saved this morning.
Amen? What a glorious, glorious truth. Notice it says, I beseech you, therefore, brethren, by the
mercies of God that you present your bodies a living sacrifice, holy, acceptable unto God, which
is your reasonable service. And be not conformed to this world, but be transformed by the renewing
of your mind that you may prove what is that good and acceptable and perfect will of God.
This morning, as we deal with the subject matter of absolute surrender, I have simply two thoughts
for you this morning. Number one, if you're taking notes, the reason we should live a surrendered
life, the reason we should live a surrendered life. Now, remember the definition, to yield to
the power of another, to give or deliver up possession upon compulsion or demand. I'm
thankful that as you think about that truth of that definition from that 1828 Noah Webster's
dictionary, and we think about as a child of God, the reason that we should live a surrendered life,
I ask this question, what is it that compels or constrains the child of God? Well, if you take
your Bible and turn to the book of 2 Corinthians, we find that God tells us exactly what it is that
would compel or constrain us. And here's what the truth is, it is the love of Christ. We must never
get over the fact that God loves us. We must never get over the truth that we are loved by God. And
what does love reveal to us? What does love teach us? We find this morning that God loves us, and
so God instructs us. And of course, the greatest demonstration of God's love for us is sending His
Son to die for us so that we could be saved, so that we could be born again. But we find that He
loved in love. You know what God does? He corrects us. Whom the Lord loveth, He chasteneth. You say,
well, that's not very loving. No, it is loving. That is actually exactly what love is. If love,
if someone loves an individual, if God loves you as His child and He sees you going astray,
it is an act of love to correct and to chasten us. And how thankful we ought to be for that.
But notice in 2 Corinthians 5 and verse 14, the Bible says, for the love of Christ
constraineth us, because we thus judge, that if one died for all, then we're all dead. Listen,
you were dead in your sins and your trespasses. You were dead. Here's the truth that someone
spoke. They articulated it this way that brought great conviction in the life of my Father.
It led Him to going to a Baptist church and hearing the gospel proclaimed and trusting Christ as His
Savior. Here's what it was. There's a lot of dead people that are walking around.
My dad said, what in the world is that guy talking about? And he said, well, here's the reality.
There's a lot of people that are dead spiritually. They're just alive physically. I hope that's not
you this morning. I mean, you have life physically, but I wonder this morning, do you have
life spiritually? Have you been born again? I'm not asking if you go to church. I know you're
here this morning. I'm not asking if you've done some kind of religious duties and you're following
some type of religion mandate. No, I'm asking, have you trusted Jesus Christ as your personal
Savior? It's the only way to be made alive. It's the only way to be born again is through the Lord
Jesus Christ. He said, I'm the way, the truth, and the life. No man, no one's going to get around
that. No man cometh unto the Father but by me. But I'm sincere. You can be sincerely wrong.
It's only through Jesus Christ. The love of Christ constraineth us because we thus judge
that if one died for all, then we're all dead. That word constraineth, we talked about the
definition of surrender, to give or deliver up possession upon compulsion.
or demand, and really, it's that being compelled
or being constrained, and the word here
in 2 Corinthians 5 and verse number 14,
to the love of Christ constraineth us,
it really carries two ideas with it.
One of them is this, to urge with irresistible power.
And then it carries with it this idea, to hold together.
And really, when you think about those two truths
and how they're coupled together
in that simple verse of scripture,
that the love of Christ constraineth us,
it urges us with irresistible power.
Listen, what does it urge us to do?
In just a minute, we'll read verse 15
and we'll see what it urges us to do,
but we find also that it holds us together.
It's as if the love of Christ, it holds us together,
it controls us, it's pushing on all sides,
and it's giving us that which holds us together.
But notice verse 15, and that he died for all.
Who is that?
That's Jesus Christ.
He died for all that they which live.
Who's that?
Well, that's us, those that have been born again,
should not.
Now, that's pretty simple, is it not?
You should not henceforth no longer
should you live unto yourselves.
Why?
Well, because we're to live unto him
which died for them and rose again.
You know who you lived for before you got saved?
You know who I lived for before I got saved?
I lived for me.
And you live for you.
But if we truly understand the love of Christ,
if we truly understand this morning what he did for us,
it would compel us, it would constrain us
to voluntarily give up possession
to yield to the power of God
and no longer live for myself,
no longer live for yourself,
but live for him.
Why?
Because he loves us, because he demonstrated that love,
he died for us and he rose again.
I'm thankful we serve a risen savior.
He's alive.
He lives, he rules and he reigns,
and we find this morning that as we look at this truth
that we should not no longer should we live for myself
but for Christ here in the book of Romans
in Romans chapter number 12,
it's nearing the end of the book of Romans
and we find that as he comes to this 12th chapter,
Paul is literally begging the believers
and he's begging them really,
the basis of his plea is what had been previously revealed
in the book of Romans.
Remember, if you look back
and maybe you've held your place in Romans 12,
he says I beseech you therefore brethren
by the mercies of God.
Then we begin to understand
that Paul is giving this plea to the believers
and it's on the basis of what had been previously revealed
in this book of Romans
and we'll look at some things very quickly this morning
that had been revealed that would give Paul
the basis for which he's pleading
and begging with these believers
and then notice at the end of verse number one,
he says which is your reasonable service.
At the end of all of it,
it's just our reasonable service.
Sometimes someone that lives a surrendered life,
we might hold up on some great pedestal
and look at them and say look at this,
it's just reasonable service.
See when we truly understand what Christ has done for us,
the reason we should live a surrendered life
is because the only reason you have life
and the only reason I have life is because he died for me.
Apart from him, I'm nothing and so are you.
He said for without me, you can do nothing.
So notice, what is it that Paul had previously revealed
in the book of Romans?
We won't look at all of the verses for sake of time.
I'll simply reference chapters
and I could provide you with the verses
if you would be interested in having them specifically
but for sake of time this morning,
let me just remind you that in Romans chapter number three,
Paul reveals that all mankind is guilty.
We're guilty sinners for all have sinned
and come short of the glory of God.
As it is written, there is none righteous, no, not one.
And so Paul, as you look at the book of Romans
and you consider the basis for the plea
in Romans chapter number 12,
we look at the truth in chapter number three
of the book of Romans that we're all guilty sinners.
Every single one of us.
You say, well, pastor, I'm a pretty good person.
No, you're guilty, you're a sinner.
Well, I'm not as bad as, listen, the requirement,
the truth of God's word, the standard is not someone else.
The standard is the perfection of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And we're all guilty.
We all fall short of the glory of God.
He says in Romans chapter number five,
in chapter number six,
if you were to look at both of those chapters
and to work your way through those chapters,
you'd find that he reveals to these people,
he reveals to us as the word of God
has been preserved for us today
that the penalty for sin is death.
Penalty for sin is death.
So he says, you're all guilty sinners.
No one's getting off the hook.
Everyone that's been born of man is a sinner.
And because of that sin, you are the penalty,
the just penalty, by the way, for sin is death.
For the wages of sin is death.
Now, we understand this morning
that it's more than just physical death.
We understand this morning, the Bible teaches us
as it had appointed unto man once to die,
but after this, the judgment.
There's some people that are living
upon the face of the earth today
that think that when they take their final breath
physically, that that's it, it's over, there's nothing more.
They could not be more wrong.
The Bible plainly teaches that after the physical death,
for the believer, there's life forever with Christ.
Hallelujah.
But for the lost individual,
they will stand at the judgment seat
at the great white throne judgment.
And as they stand at that judgment,
the Bible says that they'll be cast in a lake of fire.
This is the second death.
So we find that Paul, he says to these people in Rome
that we're all guilty sinners in chapter number three.
In chapters five and six, he says that the penalty,
the just penalty for sin is death.
He then says this in those same chapters,
chapters five and six, he says, what a wonderful truth,
the gift of God is eternal life.
And that gift is made possible through the death, burial,
and glorious resurrection of the Lord Jesus Christ.
He says that you're all sinners
and the penalty for sin is death.
If it stopped there, it'd be just,
it would not be called the gospel.
You know why?
Because the gospel means good news.
And if it ended there, it would not be true
to call it the gospel, but I thank God
that it doesn't end there.
He says, listen, you're guilty, you're a sinner,
and the wage of sin is death, but what a great conjunction.
The gift of God is eternal life
through Jesus Christ, our Lord.
And we find this morning that that wonderful gift,
what a great contrast between the thought of a wage
and the thought of a gift.
A wage is something that we earn.
A wage is something that we work for.
And many of us throughout this week,
we have the opportunity to work a job.
And as we work that job, we have an opportunity
to earn a living, to make a wage
because of our labor, because of our work.
And we understand in our economy today,
we understand what wages are.
The end of the week, depending on how often you get paid,
but if we could use the illustration,
at the end of the week, you worked your hours
and you get paid, it is your wage, it is what you earned.
Your boss does not come and say, here's a gift for you.
No, I worked for that, right?
We also understand what a gift is.
In fact, this time of year in our culture,
the idea of giving gifts is very prevalent.
In fact, the marketing industry has capitalized on it,
have they not?
We purchase gifts and we exchange gifts.
And something interesting about the gift
that you'll receive, if you receive a gift
this Christmas season from maybe a loved one,
you receive that gift, they paid for it
and they gave it to you.
And simply all you must do is receive that gift.
So the gift that God offers to us this morning,
as we look at this truth of living a surrendered life,
why should I live a surrendered life?
What is it that compels or constrains us
as a child of God to live a surrendered life?
We understand that we're guilty sinners
and the payment is death, the wage of sin is death,
but we understand that Jesus Christ died for us.
He paid in full for your salvation.
He offers that gift.
And as he offers that gift, all we must do is receive it.
We find that we come to the 10th chapter
of the book of Romans and we find that
as we come to that chapter, a very famous,
a familiar, precious truth is revealed in verse number 13,
for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord
shall be saved.
Aren't you thankful this morning that you're a whosoever?
I'm so thankful that somebody gave me the gospel.
I'm so thankful this morning that Jesus paid.
He paid it all and he offered me the free gift.
And he said, there's nothing you can do to earn this.
There's nothing you can do to work for this.
I simply give it to you.
as a free gift if you'll simply receive it.
You know what's sad to me is how many people
reject the gift.
By the way, it's not customary in our culture
to reject gifts.
Sometimes you might feel uncomfortable
when somebody brings you a gift.
Maybe you have the thought,
well, I don't have anything to give them.
But it's not customary in our culture to reject the gift.
And we find here this morning that how many people
in your life, in my life, that I have shared with them
the gift of God, which is eternal life,
that they say, no, thank you.
I'm not interested.
Maybe they say, I'm gonna try to earn it myself.
Maybe they've been influenced by some false teaching,
some false religion that gives them the idea
that they could earn their own salvation.
It can't be that easy.
Listen, it might be easy for us,
but it costs Jesus everything.
Not only did he suffer on a cruel cross,
but he left the glory of heaven,
the splendor and the glory that he had
with the Father from ages gone by for all of eternity,
he left that so he could come to a sin-cursed world.
We find this morning he said,
for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord
shall be saved.
Think of this truth in Galatians 2.
So Paul writes to these believers in Rome
and he tells them, you're guilty sinners,
but the wage, the payment for that sin is death,
but Jesus Christ died for you
and he offers you this free gift
and if you call on him, he'll save you.
Therefore, I beseech you, therefore, brethren,
by the mercies of God that you present your bodies
a living sacrifice, holy, acceptable unto God,
which is your reasonable service
when you understand the foundation
by which we find in the book of Romans,
it seems as if it would simply be
that we as God's people, we would live surrendered lives,
we would voluntarily yield to Christ
because we understand what he did for us.
It's amazing how many of God's people,
how often in my life I try to live for myself,
I try to take back that control.
Paul, he didn't simply beg others,
he did not simply encourage others
to live a surrendered life,
but we find that Paul himself lived a life of surrender.
In fact, we're familiar with Galatians 2 in verse 20.
Why does Paul say I'm crucified with Christ?
Why does he say this truth of his position of surrender?
If you look at the end of the verse,
he says this, who loved me and gave himself for me.
What's the reason, child of God?
What's the reason that we should live a surrendered life?
Because he loved me and he gave himself for me.
Because without him, I'd be hopeless and helpless.
You know where you'd be this morning without Christ?
I don't even like to think about it.
I don't know where I would be like geographically today
without Christ, I'm not sure.
But I know where I would be headed today without Christ
and that's to a Christless eternity
to a place called the Lake of Fire.
Oh, what grace and what mercy, what love.
We find that in 1 Corinthians 6 in verses 19 and 20
that Paul, as he's speaking to the believers
there in Corinth, he says what?
Know ye not that your body is the temple of the Holy Ghost
which is in you, which you have of God,
and you're not your own, why?
He says it this way, for you are bought with a price.
Therefore, because you've been bought with a price,
we are to glorify God.
How is it that we live a life that would bring glory to God?
Will we live a life that would bring glory to God
by living a life of surrender?
He says therefore glorify God in your body and your spirit
which are God's.
Listen, I am bought with his precious blood.
If you're saved this morning, you've been bought
with the precious blood of Christ,
you are no longer the owner of you.
Amen?
You're not.
And by the way, you thought you owned yourself before,
but you were really owned by the devil.
If you go back and you read the book of John,
you'll understand in John chapter number eight that truth.
Listen, I'm so thankful that I'm owned by Christ.
I've been bought with a price.
Therefore, what's the impact of that?
The impact is that I live a surrendered life.
Now understand this morning that though we can give
the reason, and even as I said by way of introduction,
it really is not about how much we know about surrender.
It's not the verses that we could look to.
It's not the songs that we could sing.
No, it's really how surrendered are we?
I said this in Sunday school this morning.
We talked about the subject of obedience
in Sunday school this morning.
It's not a matter of how much you know about the Bible.
It's a matter of how much of the Bible you obey.
I can quote the whole book of,
how much of it are you obeying?
I'm not saying that you shouldn't memorize the Bible.
You should.
The Bible says that we're to memorize it,
but what I'm saying is that it's not about being able
to win a contest of Bible,
some kind of Bible game of trivia pursuit type of Bible game
and Bible knowledge game.
No, no, no, how much are we obeying?
And the truth is the same here with surrender.
It's not about knowing about surrender.
It's about being surrendered.
The reason, simply put, because He loved me
and gave Himself for me because He saved my soul.
Number two this morning, if you're taking notes,
not only the reason that we should live a surrendered life,
but what's the result of living a surrendered life?
What's the result?
I believe that when we live a surrendered life
that we'll live a life of obedience
and submission to the Lord because I'm surrendered to Him.
I have yielded, I have voluntarily given myself
to a place of surrender to the power of another
and that being the Lord and understanding
that as I understand the basis for which I should surrender,
but then the result is that I live a life
of obedience and submission.
Look over at Romans chapter six
and then we'll go over to a passage in 2 Corinthians.
Romans chapter number six, notice what the Bible says
and we've referenced a number of verses
throughout the book of Romans
without turning to them specifically,
but I want you to notice in Romans chapter number six.
In Romans chapter number six,
the Bible says in verse number 10,
for in that he died, he died unto sin once,
but in that he liveth, he liveth unto God.
Likewise, reckon ye also yourselves
to be dead indeed unto sin,
but alive unto God through Jesus Christ our Lord.
Let not sin therefore reign in your mortal body
that you should obey it in the lust thereof.
Neither, notice what it says,
neither yield ye your members
as instruments of unrighteousness unto sin,
but notice what that phrase says,
yield yourselves unto God.
As those that are alive from the dead
and your members as instruments of righteousness unto God.
The Bible says in verse 16,
know ye not that to whom ye yield yourselves,
servants to obey, his servants ye are to whom you obey,
whether of sin unto death
or of obedience unto righteousness.
And what a privilege to be able to surrender,
yield to God.
What is the result?
Well, look at 2 Corinthians chapter number eight,
we'll look at an example here in the New Testament
of some people that lived lives of surrender.
They lived lives of surrender.
Speaking of the churches of Macedonia
in this particular passage of scripture,
as Paul is making an appeal to the church at Corinth,
and as he makes this appeal to the church at Corinth,
he uses the example of the churches of Macedonia.
And as he uses the example of the churches of Macedonia,
we find that they were giving
and the context is with regard to giving,
but I want you to understand
the fact that they were surrendered.
Notice in verse number one
in 2 Corinthians chapter number eight,
the Bible says, moreover, brethren,
we do you to wit of the grace of God
bestowed on the churches of Macedonia,
how that in a great trial of affliction,
the abundance of their joy and their deep poverty
abounded under the riches of their liberality.
Now, the truth is that verse number two
could occupy our time for a long time.
Why?
Because it's amazing what God reveals to us
in verse number two about the people
in these churches of Macedonia.
Notice very quickly with me,
we don't have much time,
but notice they had a great trial of affliction.
But in the midst of that great trial of affliction,
there was an abundance of joy.
Now, that ought to cause us to stop in our tracks.
Why?
Because normally, if there's a great trial of affliction,
it's not coupled with great joy.
Am I accurate?
Come on.
But he says that in this great trial of affliction,
the abundance of their joy,
notice in their deep poverty.
Now, understand.
That the poorest among us
is wealthy by the world's standards. You can go to a lot of places around the face of this world.
You saw pictures from Brother Jeff last Sunday night, if you were here, of some folks in Fiji.
And you saw some pictures of the houses. We have a shed that we keep our tractors in
that look nicer than some of those houses. I'm just being honest.
Brother Jeff, is that true? You were there. I saw pictures, but you were there.
The poorest among us is wealthy.
But when it says of their deep poverty,
and coupled with that, notice the riches of their liberality.
Do you remember the time in the life of Christ when he observed those that were giving?
And here come the religious leaders, and they want everyone to see how much they're giving.
And what does the Bible tell us? They're giving out of their abundance,
out of their plenty. And then he sees a widow woman.
She comes and she gives, and you know the amount that she gave was nominal.
From an economic perspective, it wasn't going to help with anything.
But you know what Jesus said? She gave more than all the others. Why? Because she gave everything.
She gave everything. That's amazing to me. And here, these believers in these churches
of Macedonia, they had a great trial of affliction, but yet they had an abundance of joy.
Abundance of joy. They had deep poverty, yet they were liberal in their giving.
Notice why. What would lead somebody to that? Why in times of great affliction would you have joy?
Why in times of great poverty would you give? Notice in verse number three,
for to their power I bear record, yea, and beyond their power, they were willing of themselves,
praying us with much entreaty that we would receive the gift and take upon us the fellowship
of the ministering to the saints, and this they did not as we hoped. But notice this,
and I have it circled in my Bible, but first gave their own selves to the Lord
and unto us by the will of God, insomuch that we desired Titus, and as he had begun,
so he would also finish in you the same grace also. The truth of verse number five is impactful.
The Bible says that as Paul rehearses the behavior of these believers in these churches
of Macedonia, and as he is rehearsing and challenging the believers in Corinth with
the example of these believers from these churches in Macedonia, he says, I want you
to understand that they did this, but the way, the reason that they did this is that first
they gave their own selves to the Lord. I believe that's a great picture of surrender,
of surrender. Lord, everything that I have, everything that I am is yours, Lord.
Now, understand that truth this morning. That is a deep, impactful truth,
and no doubt in my life and in your life, there are some things that we hold grips on
a little tighter than other things. Is it not true? Sometimes we struggle with the idea of
surrender. Why? Because I want it. I want to do what I want to do. I want to have my
control in my life. We find that they first gave their own selves to the Lord
and unto us by the will of God. What's the result of living a surrendered life? Well,
it's obedience and submission to the Lord, but what does it lead to? What does it look like?
What happens? What is the result when we live a life that is surrendered to the Lord? Well,
I believe, first of all, the Lord is magnified. The Lord is magnified. Listen, in our lives,
in your life and in my life, we ought to desire nothing more, nothing less, but then for Jesus
Christ alone to be magnified, to be exalted. You know how that's achieved? You know how that's
accomplished? By living a life of surrender, by living a life of surrender. Because through
living that life of surrender, which results in obedience and submission to the Lord,
it leads to a place of God being magnified. Let God be magnified. You read that in Psalm 70.
Let God be magnified. You read that John the Baptist, he said, he must increase, I must decrease.
And the idea this morning that we desire that through our lives that the Lord Jesus Christ
would be magnified. I said this by way of introduction that when we struggle with the
idea, when our response of resisting the idea of surrender, that it leads to great struggle in the
life of a believer and it hinders our effectiveness for the Lord. You want God to be magnified?
I hope your answer would be yes. Live a life of surrender. Lord, take my life and let it be.
Lord, you died for me. You loved me. You gave me life. I just want to live for you.
We find that it will lead to the Lord being magnified. I believe this morning that it will
lead to brethren being edified. We see it here in 2 Corinthians chapter number 8.
How that through this gift that they would give, how that others would benefit and be
encouraged and be edified. And we know that Paul is using this passage of scripture not
only as a great encouragement to him. I believe that if you read verse number 5,
the beginning part when it says, and this they did not as we hoped. I mean, they did beyond what
Paul could imagine. Could you imagine seeing the poverty of these individuals and yet they're giving
liberally. It's difficult to receive. And Paul says they did beyond what we even really expected,
not as we had hoped. Brethren are edified. I believe this morning when we live a life of
surrender that the lost will be impacted. The lost will be impacted. See, this morning we begin
to think about this idea of living a life of surrender and understanding the truth of that
that word being yielded. It's interesting, we won't take time to read the whole portion of
scripture, but if you want to jot it down in your notes, maybe in reference back, it's a familiar
passage of scripture in the book of Daniel in the third chapter. And we're familiar with this
portion of scripture with Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego and all that took place with the
idea of the bowing down when they would hear the playing of the music and to worship the
image that Nebuchadnezzar had set up. But after God had delivered, and I'm just giving the very
abbreviated version of Daniel chapter number three, they refused to bow down and they found
themselves in a fiery furnace. And the Bible says that Nebuchadnezzar was astonished. He was a
stone-eyed, the Bible says in Daniel chapter three and verse number 24. What was it that
impacted Daniel, or excuse me, what was it that impacted Nebuchadnezzar? It was the fact that
those three Hebrew young men that he threw in the fiery furnace, that they were now loosed and they
were walking around and there was a fourth that was like unto the Son of God. And we find that
as you look at the passage of scripture that eventually through a series of events, the
guys, those men, they're brought forth and as they come out, notice what Nebuchadnezzar says
in verse number 28. Then Nebuchadnezzar spake and said, blessed be the God of Shadrach, Meshach,
and Abednego. Why? Who had sent his angel and delivered his servants that trusted in him. So
what do we learn about Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego? Well, they trusted in the Lord. They
said to Nebuchadnezzar before they were thrown into the fiery furnace that our God is able to
deliver. Our God whom we serve is able to deliver us from the burning fiery furnace. Now for a
moment of time, I don't really believe that Nebuchadnezzar thought that was true. I don't
think that Nebuchadnezzar thought that these guys would be able to be delivered from this fiery
furnace. I mean, you're saying that your God is able? Remember who Nebuchadnezzar is. He's the
ruler of the known world, the Babylonian kingdom. I mean, they just conquered so many people.
And here we find that the Bible says that his servants that trusted in him and then notice
and have changed the king's word. And then there's this little phrase and yielded their bodies.
Who did they yield their bodies to? Well, I believe ultimately they yielded themselves to God.
They yielded themselves to God. And they were willing to go into that fiery furnace. Why?
Because they were not going to bow down before that image. When we begin to think about
surrender and living a life of surrender, you know, Nebuchadnezzar was greatly impacted so much so
that he says in verse number 29, there is no other God that can deliver after this sort.
You know, when we live a life of surrender, God will be magnified.
The brethren will be edified, but lost people will be impacted.
Simply this morning, as we think about all of the messages I've preached throughout the year
with regard to how great God is, I believe that very easily this morning we should all acknowledge
That our God is such a great God and His love constrains us that we should live surrendered
lives.
But knowing what we should do isn't always what we do, right?
We know what we should do, but we don't always do what we should do.
This morning I wonder, as we evaluate our lives personally, are we living a life that's
surrendered to God?
Let me ask it this way.
Is there a part of your life that's not surrendered to God?
The Holy Spirit of God is able to work in amazing ways and He can take His divine finger
and point the life of every believer and say, what about this area of your life?
I just wonder this morning, is there an area in your life, is there an area in my life
that I'm not surrendered to the Lord?
If not, why not?
What would keep you today from saying, as we sing the song, I surrender all?
I think this morning, in my life, and for most believers today, that it would be better
if we would sing, I surrender some or I surrender most.
Why do I say that?
Because I don't care if you're singing a song, if it's not true, it's lying.
Can we truly sing, I surrender all?
Or would it be better to say, I surrender some or most?
This morning, the reason we're compelled, we're constrained because of the love of Christ.
It results in God being magnified, the brethren being edified, and the lost being impacted.
This morning, absolute surrender.
What's keeping you from surrendering to God?
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us or we thank you for our salvation this morning.
God, if there's one that's here that's not saved, God, I pray that they'd understand
this morning, plainly and clearly, their need for salvation.
God, I pray that they would surrender in this area of their lives and they would accept
the free gift of eternal life through Jesus Christ, our Lord.
Oh, Holy Spirit, I pray that you'd draw them to yourself, that you'd work as only you can.
Father, I think of the many believers that are here this morning.
God, as we take this moment of invitation to examine and evaluate our own lives, I pray
that we'd be honest in our evaluation.
Are we surrendered?
Is there an area of our life that's not surrendered, that we're holding back?
God, would you help us to surrender all?
Would you use us, God, for your honor and for your glory?
I pray that you'd move, work as only you can.
I pray that decisions would be made that would be long-lasting.
Decisions not made on emotion, but made on principle of your Word.
God, I pray that you'd use us for your honor and glory.
Well thank you for it, in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.