I'll be finishing up this chapter this evening, verses 22 through 34.
And this is our 55th lesson through the book of Genesis.
And we have been just kind of slowly making our way through this book.
Of course, the first 11 chapters, we spent many, many weeks, months, in fact, looking
at those foundational truths.
And I often said, as we were studying those 11 chapters, how that the enemy seeks to attack
that portion of Scripture and the creation account and all that's contained within the
first several chapters of the book of Genesis.
Because if they can attack and cause doubt with regard to the foundation, then the rest
can kind of crumble.
And I am thankful that God's Word has been given to us.
And God's Word is sure, and it stands, it's profitable.
And I'm thankful for what God teaches us.
As we study this 21st chapter, we find that it begins with that miraculous birth of Isaac.
Remember, the Lord had made many promises to Abraham with regard to a seed, a son.
And we find that it begins in verse number one, and it says, the Lord visited Sarah,
notice, as he said, and the Lord did unto Sarah as he had spoken.
God always does what he says he will do.
And we find that though there was a period of waiting and though this oft-repeated promise
that was made to Abraham seemed as if it was far off, we find that it was fulfilled in
the beginning of this chapter, chapter 21 of the book of Genesis.
We find that after this miraculous birth, we find that the child grew and was weaned
and Abraham made a great feast.
Throughout that process, we noticed how that, of course, Hagar and Ishmael were cast out.
And these things, according to what Paul says, under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of
God in the book of Galatians, these things are an allegory.
The truth that was taught to us, that the Spirit and the flesh, they're at enmity one
with the other, and you had to cast out Hagar and Ishmael.
And just like as believers, we must put off the old man.
We must put off and crucify the flesh.
We find now that as we enter into this final section of the book of this chapter, the book
of Genesis, chapter 21, we find here that there is an interaction that is recorded between
Abimelech, Phicol, the chief captain of his host, and Abraham.
It's really an interesting dialogue that takes place, an interesting event that is
given to us, and I believe that as we end the chapter, you'll find it's interesting
to note how that Abraham is worshiping the Lord.
As we begin looking at this passage of Scripture, we find in verse 22, the Bible says,
"...and it came to pass at that time that Abimelech and Phicol, the chief captain of
his host, spake unto Abraham, saying..."
Notice this phrase, "...God is with thee in all that thou doest."
I mentioned this morning as we were dealing with the subject matter of our behavior in
the workplace, how there was such a connection between that passage of Scripture and what
our behavior is to look like, and what we find here with this description, this observation,
if you will, that is given of Abraham from Abimelech, "...God is with thee in all that
thou doest."
I've taken that phrase from verse 22 to use as our title this evening.
And if you're taking notes, I want you to see first the perception of Abimelech.
The perception of Abimelech.
I want to remind you of the interaction back in Genesis chapter number 20.
If you go back to chapter number 20, we find that the Bible tells us about Abraham taking
a journey.
This is the second time in which this same type of situation occurs.
The first time was back in previous chapter, and we looked and studied that and understood
what was going on.
But here as we come to the 20th chapter of the book of Genesis, we find that this is
the first encounter between Abraham and Abimelech.
There are some Bible scholars that doubt that this is the same Abimelech in chapter 21 as
we find in chapter number 20.
I tend to believe that it's the same Abimelech.
I believe that there's credibility with regard to the account, but there's also indication
as to why it is that Abimelech would desire to do and to have this covenant with Abraham
that we'll read of in just a moment based on what we see in chapter number 20.
But it's here in chapter number 20, you'll remember that Abraham operated in fear.
Abraham went into this place, he was going to sojourn, and he goes in.
And remember, he says that Sarah is my sister.
And this is a recurring situation for Abraham, and we find that Abraham in this particular
situation, he'd done it back in chapter number 12 when he goes into Egypt with Pharaoh.
And now in chapter number 20, he does it again.
And we find that he was operating under fear, but yet God displayed his power.
I'm thankful that our God is omnipotent.
The Lord God omnipotent reigneth.
And we find here that God says, notice in chapter 20 in verse number 3, but God came
to Abimelech in a dream by night and said to him, behold, thou art but a dead man.
For the woman which thou hast taken, for she is a man's wife.
Now can you imagine that kind of a greeting?
Abimelech was operating under what was supposedly social norms for him to be able to take this
Sarah.
Again, it's a different environment than what we live in, but with understanding the times
and what was going on, Abraham says, she's my sister, and Abimelech says, man, I'm going
to take her, and God says, you're but a dead man.
What a greeting, what an interaction.
But Abimelech in verse number 4 had not come near her, and he said, Lord, wilt thou slay
also a righteous nation?
He said, he nodded unto me, she is my sister, and she, even she herself said, he is my brother.
In the integrity of my heart and in the innocency of my hands have I done this, and God said
unto him in a dream, yea, I know that thou didst this in the integrity of thy heart,
for I also withheld thee from sinning against me, therefore suffered I thee not to touch
her.
Now therefore restore the man his wife, for he is a prophet, and he shall pray for thee,
and thou shalt live.
And if thou restore her not, know thou that thou shalt surely die, thou and all that are
thine.
Wow.
We studied this in great detail when we looked at this passage of Scripture, but just by
way of remembering and understanding the backdrop to what we're reading now in chapter 21, and
you think about this Abimelech, and you think about how God demonstrated His power and how
God shows up to him in a dream at night and tells him that he's but a dead man, and then
says I understand these are the things that you've done, but I want you to know that you're
to restore the man his wife.
And notice what God says in verse number 7, for he is a prophet, and he shall pray for
thee, and thou shalt live.
And then He tells him if you choose not to obey, you're going to die.
He says that if thou restore her not, know thou, know thou, that thou shalt surely die,
thou and all that are thine.
You know what Abimelech does?
He believes God.
He really does.
It says then Abimelech rose early in the morning.
You wonder why he rose early in the morning?
Because he believed what God said.
Amen?
And he rose early in the morning and called all his servants and told all these things
in their ears, and the men were sore afraid.
We find that Abimelech took and restored Sarah, and we find that as he obeyed the Lord
and he restored Sarah, the Bible tells us that Abraham prayed for him.
God said that would happen in verse number 7.
He says that he is a prophet, and he shall pray for thee, and thou shalt live.
Notice with me in verse number 17, the Bible says, so Abraham prayed unto God, and God
healed Abimelech and his wife and his maidservants, and they bared children, for the Lord had
fast closed up all the wombs of the house of Abimelech because of Sarah, Abraham's wife.
Now we leave that account in chapter number 20, and we begin to read in chapter number
21 of the birth of Isaac and the growth of Isaac, the weaning of Isaac, the casting out
of Hagar and Ishmael, and then the Bible comes back in verse 22 and says, and it came to
pass at that time that Abimelech and Phicole, the chief captain of his host, spake unto
Abraham saying, God is with thee in all that thou doest.
As we think about this observation, the perception of Abimelech, I do not believe that this is
just Abimelech acting in some level of flattery.
I believe that he is very sincere.
He's recognized some things.
I mean, understanding as we consider the backdrop that we just reviewed in chapter number 20
if you were in the shoes of Abimelech and you see that God Almighty appears to you and
says these things to you and operate in this way, and this is what God says of Abraham,
he's a prophet and he's going to pray for you, and then he prays for you and you're
healed and you can reproduce, I mean, there's a certain understanding that you have with
regard to how God is working in the heart of this individual, amen?
And so Abraham is there and we find that Abimelech comes and says, this is my perception,
this is what I've observed, this is what I've seen in thee, that God is
with thee in all that thou doest."
I believe it was very obvious to Abimelech.
I believe that as Abimelech observed,
maybe even from a distance,
that he could see the blessing
and favor of God upon Abraham.
And though we would believe
that Abimelech was a powerful individual
and had great might,
we find that he was intimidated.
Remember, why was it in the first place
that Abraham said, she's my sister?
Because he was fearful, right?
He wasn't going to be fearful of somebody
that was weak and unable to fight or defend.
We find that he was fearful of this.
And so we find that this man Abimelech,
he and his host, no doubt they had power,
but they understood the power of God
because of what they'd experienced in chapter number 20.
And then they perceive,
they understand that God is with Abraham.
I mentioned it this morning,
but I wonder this evening,
how many people watch us and observe us
and have seen us and would conclude
that that's a child of God.
God is with them.
God is prospering them.
God is blessing them.
God is working through them.
God is using them.
See, I wonder even as we begin to think about
the time, the day and age in which we live
and thinking about some of the thoughts
from this morning and looking at this passage
of Scripture this evening,
the reality is that we're living in a time
in a society when, look, people are confused
and people are fearful and people are afraid
and people don't know where to go and what to do.
And it's a chaotic time that we're living in.
If they see that we as the people of God
are just as confused and just as fearful
and just as living in chaos as they are,
we don't really have a whole lot to offer.
But God says that he'd give us his peace.
It's a peace that passeth all understanding.
We got our eyes on Jesus and we're understanding
that things are not falling apart,
they're falling in place and we understand
that God has a plan and a purpose and he's using us.
And they see that, man, there's something,
why don't you behave the same way?
I don't know all that was going on.
I don't know all that Abraham did and how he behaved
and what it was that Abimelech had observed,
but for him to have this statement,
for him to make this declaration
that God is with thee in all that thou doest, wow.
To me, that's a high compliment.
To me, that's a wonderful perception of Abimelech
and again, I do not believe that it's a form of flattery.
I believe there was a level of sincerity.
And I believe that Abraham had lived his life in such a way
and as Abimelech had observed what had taken place
and what he'd experienced, he recognizes that God is,
God is working on his behalf
and I don't want anything to do with this guy.
So what does he do?
Well, as we continue through the passage of Scripture
in verses 23 through 32, number two,
if you're taking notes, the proposal from Abimelech.
What he does, he makes a proposal.
Notice what he says in verse 23.
Now therefore, because of what I've observed,
because of what I've perceived,
because of what I understood,
because God is with thee in all that thou doest,
now therefore, swear unto me here by God
that thou wilt not deal falsely with me,
nor with my son, nor with my son's son,
but according to the kindness that I have done unto thee,
thou shalt do unto me into the land
wherein thou hast sojourned.
And we find that this proposal is made in verse number 23.
And though he had a measure of power
and capability from a military perspective,
I do not believe that this man desired
to really have any kind of engagement
in battle with Abraham because God was with him.
And not only for himself,
but he says for my son and for my son's son.
And we find that as we look at this portion of Scripture,
we begin to understand this proposal,
really what he's desiring,
he's seeking after a peace treaty.
There'll be some level of peace agreement.
Now, I believe that as this proposal is made,
the reality is that Abraham,
if he was going to walk with God
and he was to behave in the manner
in which he was to behave in,
that he would not deal falsely with Abimelech anyway.
Amen?
But that's not the common practice.
And so therefore, we understand why it is
that Abimelech would desire this peace treaty,
this covenant to be made.
But as the people of God,
we don't need somebody to come
and try to make some kind of a deal with us
that we're gonna deal properly with them,
that we will not deal falsely with them.
The reality is that as the people of God,
we're to live lives of integrity.
We're to live lives that are pleasing in the sight of God.
We find that I believe that Abraham
would have dealt properly in any case,
but this desire, this request,
this what he is seeking after
is on the part of Abimelech,
not on Abraham's part.
And Abraham says in verse 24,
I will swear.
It's interesting in the next few verses,
we see that there is a disputed well that is discussed
and Abraham takes a moment to reprove Abimelech
because of this well.
Notice in verse 25, it says,
and Abraham reproved Abimelech
because of a well of water.
The servants of Abimelech,
it says which Abimelech's servants
had violently taken away.
You understand that in this particular region
that wells were extremely important.
The process of digging a well
was a tiring, difficult process.
And we find that water is necessary.
The need for water, not only for yourself,
but you think about for your flocks and for your herds
and the necessity of water.
And so a well is a very important,
I mean, it's imperative to have wells of water.
We find that Abraham is reproving Abimelech
because of this well,
and he says that your servants had violently taken it away.
Abimelech said, I will not who hath done this thing,
neither didst thou tell me,
neither yet heard I of it, but today.
Abimelech says that he was not aware of this situation
according to what we read in verse 26.
And we find that Abraham had told him
what had taken place.
Now, I believe, remember this is the same Abraham
that back in Genesis chapter number 14,
he heard about what was taking place with his nephew Lot
and all that was taking place with the battle
and the group of kings,
that coalition that had set themselves
and had taken Lot captive.
And he takes his own trained servants from his own house
and he goes and he has victory in chapter number 14.
I believe, based on what I read in chapter number 14,
now these many years later,
as God has blessed and prospered Abraham,
that most likely he could have fought
against the servants of Abimelech
and retained possession of the well.
I can't prove that biblically,
but I do believe that it's certainly
within the realm of possibility.
For whatever reason, Abraham chose not to engage
in that particular response to what had taken place.
And we find that though these servants had come
and taken it, that now he's taking the opportunity
to reprove Abimelech for that which had happened.
And Abraham then, in verse 27,
took sheep and oxen and gave them unto Abimelech
and both of them made a covenant.
And Abraham set seven ewe lambs of the flock by themselves.
And Abimelech said unto Abraham,
what mean these seven ewe lambs
which thou hast set by themselves?
And he, Abraham said, for these seven ewe lambs
shalt thou take of my hand
and they may be a witness unto me
that I have digged this well.
This was customary in this particular time
in this culture that they would deal
with things in this manner.
And he says that I want it to be a witness
that I have digged this well.
And then he called the place Beersheba
because there they swear, both of them.
We see that this covenant now is ratified, if you will.
It's interesting, the word Beersheba,
it means a well of the seven.
In fact, it's still, of course, a place today
that you could go and visit and see that.
And the reminder, even of the name of the place,
all the way back in Genesis 21,
because of those seven ewe lambs that were set forward
as being this token, if you will,
this witness that Abraham had digged that well.
So we see that the covenant is ratified.
I just pause here for a moment
to think about what has just transpired.
And we see the perception of Abimelech
and we see that he recognizes that God is with thee
in all that thou doest.
And therefore, he makes this proposal of this peace treaty,
this covenant, if you will,
and the covenant is ratified.
And I wonder, as we would consider our own lives
and the different era, no doubt, in which we live,
but I wonder this evening,
how many people know that we can pray
and see God answer prayer?
You understand what I'm saying?
It almost seems as if there's a great mocking
that's going on in our era today, in our culture today,
toward the people of God.
There's a great mockery of those that would speak against the people of God as if we have
no God in heaven that can answer.
But we serve the Lord God omnipotent, and He rules and He reigns.
And listen, we don't serve false gods that can't hear and can't act and can't respond.
We're not the worshipers of Baal that you see in the situation with Elijah.
No, we serve the true God of heaven that is able to do exceeding abundantly above all
that we ask or think.
And I believe at times it may be that people don't see the power of our God because we
don't have faith to exercise in our God being able to do something.
You know what God says in Malachi?
I understand it's with regard to giving and how they had robbed God of the tithe, but
He says, prove me, prove me and see if I won't do this.
You know, there are times in our lives that God says, prove me, prove me.
A couple of examples.
The one that I just mentioned with Elijah, praying and God sending fire from heaven.
How bold would you have been, how bold would I have been in the midst of that great company
to pray that prayer?
Believing that God could do it?
That God would do it?
I preached a message on Tuesday at the AIBF meeting to the pastors that were there.
And as I preached that message, I used a portion of Scripture and I spoke about Moses.
And when Moses was instructed in Exodus 17, they got to the place where there's no water.
And God says, here's what I want you to do after he prayed and God answers and He says,
I want you to go out this way and I'm going to go before you and I'm going to show you
the rock and I want you to strike the rock.
But He tells them this, to take the elders and do it in front of the people.
You know what I said to the men that were in that room on Tuesday, I said, you know,
if it were me and perhaps if it were you, we'd try to find out if that thing would happen
privately.
Do you understand what I'm saying?
But we serve a God that is able to do all things.
And there's a time in our lives where we need to come to a place where other people see
that our God is real, that our God hears and answers prayer.
That I'm not going to operate in fear and I'm not going to cave in to the pressures
of the world and I'm not going to fold to the deception and to the open-mindedness and
all the things.
No, no.
We got a God in heaven that is able.
Amen?
I want to tell you about the, some may know this particular account, but it's just a powerful
example of what we're looking at here this evening where this man Abimelech, he perceives
this truth, this reality about Abraham and therefore he says, listen, I don't want anything
to do with this guy.
I need to find out a way to have a peace treaty with this guy.
I need to have a covenant with this guy because God is with him.
But I don't want to mess with that, right?
The Queen of Mary, excuse me, the Queen Mary, the Queen of Mary, that's good, isn't it?
Queen Mary, she says this, she said this, that she feared the prayers of John Knox more
than she feared all of the armies of Scotland.
John Knox.
She feared his prayers, one man, more than all of the armies of Scotland.
That's powerful.
It's not about John Knox.
It's about his God.
It's about our God.
Amen?
And we look and we find what's going on and we say, listen, we serve a God that is capable,
that is worthy, and there are times in our lives, and I believe that now is the hour
that people need to see in us and through us that our God is real.
It's not just theory.
It's practice.
It's not just some level of theory that we have all of these right answers and can rehearse
all of these verses of Scripture and know that this is what, no, no, it's practice.
This is how God can work in my life today.
In my difficult situation, in my moment of, humanly speaking, impossible.
With God, all things are possible.
Do we believe that?
Do we live that way?
Do we prove God?
Right?
Because, look, I understand there are times in which it's like, what happens if it doesn't
turn out right?
And we get intimidated.
But you know what that is?
That's doubt.
I preached a series several years ago.
Our theme for that particular year was increase our faith.
And as we had as our series for that particular year, it wasn't through a particular book.
It was more of a topical study.
And each week of that year, I purposed to preach a message that would deal with something
that would help increase our faith.
And how our faith can be increased.
We looked at a number of different portions of Scripture and we looked at how God built
the faith of His people and so on and so forth.
But one particular statement that I repeated often in that particular calendar year was
that if faith is a flower, then doubt is a weed.
And weeds choke out flowers.
And so we must deal with the weed of doubt.
We must get rid of doubt.
How do we deal with doubt?
How do we deal with unbelief?
We need to get in the book.
We need to have our faith increased.
Why was it that as those spies went to spy out the land, as we read, as Moses had given
the instruction to go and to spy out the land, they came back, ten of them, with an
evil report of unbelief?
They didn't believe that God was able.
Why?
Because of what they saw.
But I want you to think about this just for a moment.
They saw some things as they went and spied out that land for forty days.
They saw that there were giants in the land.
They saw that they had fortified cities.
They observed those things and therefore they concluded we be not able.
But can you just for a moment rehearse in your mind all of the things that they had
seen God do?
When they were in Egypt and when they were there and they were under great turmoil.
And God sends Moses and there's a series of plagues.
You think about those ten plagues and you think about the power of God that was displayed.
They saw that.
Then you go forward and you begin to think about the crossing of the Red Sea.
What power was displayed by our God?
You think about after they crossed the Red Sea and you think about the water that God
provided.
You think about the manna that God provided.
You think about more water that God provided.
And you just begin to think about all that they saw God do.
Then they go in and they spot a land and they see some giants and they see some fortified
cities and all of a sudden they don't believe that God is able.
Doubt and unbelief.
In Psalm 78 the Bible says that they limited the Holy One of Israel.
You know how we limit the unlimited God?
Doubt.
Unbelief.
You say He's the unlimited God.
How could He be limited?
By our unbelief.
He did not many miracles there.
Why?
Because of their unbelief.
It's time that we believe God and that other people can see in us that God is real.
That God does answer prayer.
That God does work and God is still on His throne.
We see the perception.
We see the proposal.
I want you to notice as we finish up the chapter this evening here in Genesis 21.
I want you to notice the priority of Abraham.
The priority of Abraham.
The Bible says in verse 33,
And Abraham planted a grove in Beersheba.
Now understand that this is pre-law.
Understand that this was a valid process, a place where he would worship, no doubt,
as the Bible says, and called there on the name of the Lord God, the everlasting God.
In the law it would be forbidden to have groves, but we find this again predates.
And Abraham planted a grove there.
He planted it with the purpose.
Obviously there's work involved.
Abraham is an old man at this point.
We understand that.
But there's work that's involved.
He plants this grove in Beersheba and he worships.
The Bible says that he called there on the name of the Lord.
Notice this, the everlasting God, El Olam.
It's interesting as we begin to remind ourselves this evening of the way in which God reveals
his character and his nature through his names.
We find that for Abraham, it was back in Genesis chapter 14, turn back there if you will.
I referenced this passage of Scripture moments ago with regard to the coalition that was
formed and took Lot captive and how Abraham took the trained servants from his house and
then had victory.
And we find that Melchizedek, the king of Salem in verse number 18, brought forth bread
and wine.
and he was the priest of the Most High God."
El Elyon, that's the first reference of this name of God
in all of the Scripture.
And we find that it was here that Abraham understands,
his name is still Abram,
but you find that he understands
that God is the Most High God.
It's interesting that Abraham then says this
in verse 22 of Genesis 14,
and Abram said to the king of Sodom,
"'I have lift up mine hand unto the Lord,
the Most High God, the Possessor of heaven and earth.'"
Aren't you thankful that God revealed Himself
to Abraham as being the Most High God
before the king of Sodom was able to get to him
and offer what he offered?
No, no.
God had Melchizedek, the king of Salem,
to first meet Abraham and tell Abraham about El Elyon,
the Most High God, the Possessor of heaven and earth.
We find that it's in Genesis 17
that God reveals Himself to Abraham as El Shaddai.
Notice the Bible says in verse number one,
"'And when Abram was 90 years old and nine,
the Lord appeared to Abram and said unto him,
"'I am the Almighty God.
"'Walk before Me and be thou perfect.'"
El Shaddai, the Almighty God,
the name that is mentioned here for the first time
in Genesis 17 in verse number one,
where God reveals Himself to Abraham
as being the Almighty God.
We find that it would be in chapter 18,
just a short period of time later,
that God asks Abraham in verse 14,
"'Is anything too hard for the Lord?'
I'm thankful that God asked Abraham that question
after He had first revealed Himself to Abraham
as being the Almighty God.'"
Amen?
Because God says,
"'Abraham, I am El Shaddai, I am the Lord God Almighty.'
And then He says a little while later,
"'Is anything too hard for Me?'
Well, you just told me that you're the Lord God Almighty.
The answer to the question must be no.
There's nothing too hard for you.
Why?
Because you're the Almighty God.
You're El Shaddai.'"
Here, in Genesis 21, in verse 33,
He uses the name El Olam, the everlasting God.
I want you to think about the significance of this.
It's interesting because there have been many references
to the idea of forever and eternal things
that are mentioned to Abraham,
but it's not here until the 21st chapter
that the name El Olam is first given to us
in understanding that He is the everlasting God.
Again, turn back to chapter 13, if you will,
and I want you to notice what God says to Abraham
here in this portion of Scripture.
Again, I understand his name is still Abram at this point.
Forgive me if you want to be that technical,
talking about the same guy.
And so it says here,
I'll just get all messed up if I keep going back and forth.
In verse 15, it says,
"'For all the land which thou seest,
to thee will I give it, and to thy seed,'
what does He say?
Forever.
Is there anything that you can do
that you can promise somebody forever?
I will always do this.
But you might not.
Forever.
God can say I'm going to give it to you forever
because He's the everlasting God.
He'd not yet revealed Himself with that name El Olam.
We find that comes here in chapter 21,
but notice the context of the promise
that He's going to give it to His seed forever.
Notice in chapter number 17,
a number of references that we'll look at quickly.
Notice in verse number seven,
it's oft repeated throughout this passage of Scripture.
The Bible says this in Genesis 17 in verse number seven,
"'And I will establish My covenant
between Me and thee and thy seed after thee
in their generations for an'," what?
Everlasting covenant.
To be a God unto thee and to thy seed after thee.
Notice in verse number eight,
"'And I will give unto thee and to thy seed after thee
the land wherein thou art a stranger,
all the land of Canaan for an everlasting possession,
and I will be their God.'"
Notice verse 13.
He says, "'He that is born in thy house
and he that is bought with thy money
must needs be circumcised,
and My covenant shall be in your flesh
for an everlasting covenant.'"
Again in verse number 19,
"'And God said, Sarah, thy wife shall bear thee a son indeed
and thou shall call his name Isaac,
and I will establish My covenant with him
for an everlasting covenant and with his seed after him,
though the name of God El Olam is not mentioned
until Genesis 21 and verse number 33.'"
No doubt we understand through the promises
that had been made through the statements
that God had given to Abraham
that there was an understanding
that He is the everlasting God.
I am thankful that we serve the everlasting God.
He is Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end,
the first and the last.
Aren't you thankful for that?
I mean, when we think about the eternality
of God, it ought to cause us to rejoice greatly
that He has chosen to reveal Himself to us.
That He has given us the truth in His Word
with regard to His person, His character, His nature,
and we understand that He is indeed the everlasting God.
And the Bible says here in verse number 33
that Abraham called there on the name of the Lord
the everlasting God.
His reign is forever.
He'll never be conquered.
He'll never be defeated.
He's the everlasting God.
It says in verse number 34,
and Abraham sojourned in the Philistine's land many days.
It's interesting that we find that the Bible
would reveal to us in verse 33
about him planting this grove in Beersheba
and their calling on the name of the Lord.
I believe this was a priority for Abraham.
I believe that as you study the life of Abraham
as we started many, many, many months ago
back in Genesis chapter number 12
and you begin to see how Abraham,
just how he worshiped the Lord and how he set up altars.
And you begin to consider as we look here in Genesis 21
and he was gonna dwell in this place for many days
and understanding that this is where God had him
and he's calling on the name of the Lord.
I wonder this evening as we look at the context
of all that's given to us here
in this last section of Genesis 21,
I believe that it is this truth
that is given to us in verse number 33
that's a key to the observation that is made by Abimelech.
It's the key.
It's the priority of Abraham to worship God
that results in the favor of God
upon the life of Abraham.
That leads to Abimelech making the observation
and perceiving that God is with thee
in all that thou doest.
And the observation that is made
in the beginning of our text of scripture this evening
is the direct result, I believe, of the worship,
the priority of Abraham that we read of
at the end of the chapter.
We must make worship a priority.
We must make our time with God a priority.
There are many times that we face life,
listen, I understand we live in a busy time.
I understand.
We're pulled in different directions all of the time.
There's something that is always pulling for you
in your time and your attention.
But if we're not careful,
we can take care of some of these emergencies
and miss out on the most important thing that we could do,
spending time with God.
There are certain things in our lives that we prioritize.
There are people that prioritize things.
No doubt you have certain responsibilities
that you have in your life
and you have a list of priorities
and you have maybe this week a list of things
that you have to tend to and take care of.
And perhaps you'll go through an exercise
of prioritizing those things
and you'll list the most pressing,
most important thing at the top of that list
that requires your attention to take care of that.
Can I tell you that we must prioritize our time with God?
And we must guard our time with God.
As we think about Abraham here
in calling on the name of the Lord
and prioritizing his worship of God,
I believe that in our lives today
that it's not sufficient enough for us
to just kind of haphazardly try to have a time with God.
If we don't purpose to spend time with God,
it's just not gonna happen.
There are way too many things to do
and way too many things that are pulling for your attention
that it's just going to.
by chance, happen that you're going to spend time with God.
You've got a purpose to do it.
You have to prioritize to do it.
And there may be things that you have to cut out.
There may be things that you say, you know what?
I'm not going to be able to tend to that today
because I need to have my time with God today.
There are things in which people have prioritized
in their lives and there are things in which people,
depending on what their, maybe their profession
or what their desires, their dreams and aspirations are,
that they will prioritize certain things
and they will allow nothing to interfere with that thing
because they've set a particular goal.
And I just wonder, as the people of God,
do we have that same perspective
with regard to our priority of our time with God?
Listen, something better be burning down
to interrupt my time with God.
Seriously, it has to be a priority.
It has to be a priority.
Because as we spend time with God,
as we have that walk with God,
that's when somebody's going to say, God is with thee.
I see that it's real.
Why?
Because it is real.
Because I have spent time with God.
Do you ever wonder about the disciples
in Acts chapter number four?
There's a great miracle that takes place
in Acts chapter number three.
Peter and John are going into the temple
and the man that's lame is laying there
and he's asking for money.
He's asking for alms.
And Peter looks at him and says, look over here,
and I think the man had every expectation
that he was going to get some type of monetary gift.
And then those words come out of Peter's mouth,
silver and gold have I none.
What disappointment that man might have had in that moment.
Why?
Because that's what he was looking for.
But such as I have, give I thee
in the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth,
rise up and walk.
He got a whole lot more than he was looking for.
Amen?
And the Bible tells us that he gets up,
man, he's leaping and praising God.
He goes into the temple.
It's amazing what happens.
You come to Acts chapter number four.
And there's a big stir and a big controversy.
Because the religious leaders of the day,
the Sadducees and the Pharisees and the Sanhedrin,
they don't like what's taking place.
They don't like all these people getting saved
and all these things happening.
And they're not profiting the way they'd like to profit.
And they call these men into question.
Peter stands and he says, if we be questioned
on this day of the miracle that took place.
And he goes through and he says, look,
it's not in our power, it's not in my name.
It's in the name of Jesus.
And he says this, and there's no other name
under heaven given among men whereby ye must be saved.
The boldness.
They didn't like it.
If you read the very next verse,
I believe it's Acts 4.13,
it says that they perceived that they were ignorant
and unlearned men.
But that they had been with Jesus.
Is that what it says?
I closed my Bible, that's what it says, right?
They perceived they were ignorant and unlearned men,
but they had been with Jesus.
Does anyone know that we've been with Jesus?
Seriously.
You look at Abraham and Abimelech says,
God is with thee in all that thou doest.
Therefore, I need to make a covenant with you.
I need to have a peace treaty.
And we see at the end of the passage,
the priority of Abraham that is the key
to the observation that is made
in the beginning of our text this evening.
Why is it that Abimelech perceived?
Why is it that he observed that God is with thee
in all that thou doest?
Because Abraham made a priority to worship God.
And when we make a priority to worship God,
when we spend time with Jesus,
when we take and we protect that time,
when we say nothing's gonna interrupt this time,
I'm going to spend time with God,
it's gonna make a difference.
And people will perceive you've been with Jesus.
And God works, and God does amazing things.
Because we've spent time with him, we've worshiped him.
What a great observation of Abimelech.
But it didn't happen by some kind of random chance.
There's a priority of Abraham.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
I pray God that you would help us
to prioritize our time with thee.
God, we recognize tonight that we live
in the hustle and bustle era.
So many things that are vying for our attention, our time.
God, we need you.
We need that time with you.
We need to enter into your presence.
We need that quiet time with you.
To just be still and know that you are God.
To worship you as you deserve.
That you might teach us your word and your way.
That while others observe us and see us,
that it would not be about us, it'd be all about you.
They would see that we've been with Jesus.
We'd say, as John the Baptist said,
he must increase, I must decrease.
Would you help us, Lord,
to exalt and magnify you in our lives?
Well, thank you for the work that you'll do.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?