Well, amen. Thank you, Tim and Lydia.
And certainly our God is faithful. He is good. He is immutable. He never changes.
And because of that, and I love what they sang, I will bless His name. Amen.
And what a blessing and thankful for that song this morning.
I had no idea they were singing that song, but it's awesome how the Lord leads and directs.
I have your Bible with you, John chapter 14. John chapter number 14 is where we'll begin this morning.
And someone asked me a couple of weeks ago, Pastor, are you going to finish the book of James?
And I said, I am. Amen. We're going to get back to the book of James.
And then this past week when I sent Holly the title for the message, she said,
you know you haven't been in James, right? And I'm like, yep, I'm aware of that. Amen.
And I do plan to get back to the book of James. I've thoroughly enjoyed teaching and preaching through the book of James.
This, our calendar year, of course, our theme is doers of the word.
But God has just laid some things on my heart the last several weeks.
And I felt led of the Lord to preach some messages that are outside of the book of James.
And we'll get back there and we'll plan to finish the entirety of the book, studying through it.
And we're thankful for God's word.
Our world this morning is filled with turmoil, conflict, trouble, and fear.
It really is. There are many today that are struggling with anxiety.
In fact, if you were to look up the statistics, it's alarming as to the percentage of American people
that are suffering with anxiety.
People that are going to see doctors and receiving treatment and etc.
with regard to this situation with anxiety. It's real.
And we see all of these things around us and we are aware of the day in which we're living.
And we find that God has revealed to us in his word that these last days would be marked by troubled times.
And we find that there would be wicked men that would rise up.
And the Bible tells us that they would be evil and that they would deceive and they would be deceived.
And we see all sorts of things that are going on in our world around us.
As we think about the context of John chapter 14 this morning,
we find really that these are the days that are leading to the crucifixion of the Lord Jesus Christ.
We find that the Lord Jesus Christ in these days leading to the cross of Calvary,
that he would spend much time with his disciples.
And we understand that in those moments that he would spend with his disciples,
that he provided them with some valuable instruction.
We find that for nearly three years, these disciples had had the opportunity to walk with the Lord Jesus Christ.
God in flesh.
It's absolutely amazing to consider the privilege and opportunity that these men had.
They were eyewitnesses of the many mighty miracles of the Lord Jesus Christ.
They really had front row seats, if you will, to many of his powerful sermons and his teaching.
And they had those moments of not only when Jesus would teach the multitudes,
but even after he would teach the multitudes, they had the opportunity in a private setting
to inquire further and deeper and say, what do you mean by this?
And it's absolutely amazing, extraordinary, if you will, to consider the opportunity that these men had.
The time had come, however, we find that John uses the terminology about the hour.
You'll see that reference throughout the gospel of John.
It begins in chapter two and he says, the hour's not yet come.
But it reveals itself in John 17 where the Bible says that the hour has come.
And we understand the hour, which is being referenced in the gospel of John,
is the time in which the Lord Jesus Christ would go to Calvary.
He would suffer upon an old rugged cross.
And they played that during the offertory this morning.
And he would suffer and he would bleed and he would die and he would be buried in a borrowed tomb.
But we understand that he would rise, conquering sin, death, and the grave.
And he would make the payment for the sin of humanity.
And we find that thereafter, about 40 days later, he would ascend up into heaven.
And now, even still to this very day, we find that he ever liveth to make intercession for us.
We know, we have the assurance, in fact, in the beginning of this chapter I have you in John 14.
That we read those wonderfully encouraging and comforting words when Jesus said,
let not your heart be troubled. Amen?
Let not your heart be troubled.
He said, you believe in God, believe also in me.
In my father's house are many mansions.
If it were not so, I would have told you.
I go to prepare a place for you.
And what a great truth that is, but then it gets better.
He says, and if I go and prepare a place for you,
I will come again and receive you unto myself that where I am, there ye may be also.
That's how the 14th chapter of the book of John begins.
Let not your heart be troubled.
Why were they troubled?
Because of all the news that they had received about the things that would transpire in the days ahead
with Jesus going to Calvary.
We find that Jesus is providing them with this wonderful instruction, and I believe,
and I understand as I read the chapters 13, 14, 15, and 16 in the gospel of John,
I understand how desperately the disciples needed that instruction.
How just appropriate it was that Jesus would take them and give them this instruction.
But we understand today that God's word has been preserved for us,
and God has preserved the record of these interactions of this instruction that he gave to his disciples
when they were facing the difficult days that they were facing,
when they were in a position where their hearts were troubled because of the circumstances,
and we find that that instruction that was needful for them is needful for us as well.
And we find that the Bible says in verse number 27 of John 14,
I want you to notice as Jesus says,
Peace I leave with you.
My peace I give unto you.
Not as the world giveth, give I unto you.
Let not your heart be troubled, neither let it be afraid.
He begins the chapter, let not your heart be troubled.
He says in verse 27, at the end of the verse, let not your heart be troubled,
neither let it be afraid.
But we find that the reason that he would tell the disciples,
the reason that he would give them this instruction to not be troubled,
to not be afraid, is because of this word peace.
And he says, peace I leave with you.
My peace I give unto you, not as the world giveth.
The word peace, as you look in the 1828 Noel Webster's Dictionary,
it means the tranquil state of a soul assured of its salvation through Christ.
Are you 100% sure this morning that heaven is your home?
I'm saying blessed assurance this morning, praise God.
Blessed assurance.
Jesus is mine.
Hallelujah.
The tranquil state of a soul assured of its salvation through Christ
and so fearing nothing from God and content with its earthly lot
of whatsoever sort that is.
That's a great definition for peace.
And it's a lot different than the peace that many are seeking today.
So I want to preach a message that I've simply entitled this morning,
The Peace of God.
Number one, if you're taking notes, and I only have two points,
but I have a whole lot of sub points this morning,
and I hope it'll be helpful for you, a very practical message this morning,
something that will help us.
Why?
Because I truly believe that many people are troubled today.
There's turmoil all around us.
There's conflict all around us.
Anxiety is real.
You turn on the news and you watch the news and you see all of the turmoil
and conflict and all the things that are going on.
And listen, God has not given us the spirit of fear.
Amen?
And we find here this morning that we think about the subject of peace
and we see what Jesus said in John 14 with regard to this wonderful passage
of scripture and helping these disciples with all that they would encounter.
He says, peace I leave with you.
Praise God.
If you're taking notes this morning, number one, the source of peace.
The source of peace.
Well, very easily and simply this morning, the source of peace is God.
The Lord Jesus Christ, in fact, if you have your Bible there,
turn to the book of Isaiah.
Isaiah and I want you to notice in Old Testament prophecy
with regard to the coming of Messiah,
we find that in Isaiah,
there's a couple of wonderful messianic prophecies
that God gives us.
One in Isaiah seven, one in Isaiah nine,
but we find the book of Isaiah is full of prophecies
with regard to Messiah.
We of course are very familiar with the chapter,
the 53rd chapter and a wonderful truth
with regard to the suffering savior.
And we find in Isaiah chapter number nine,
that God reveals to us some truth with regard
to this understanding of the source of peace.
In Isaiah nine in verse number six,
the Bible says for unto us a child is born.
That shows the humanity of our savior.
And then it says this unto us a son is given
that shows the deity.
What a blessing to understand the truth
that he's 100% God and 100% man.
He's the God man, the Lord Jesus Christ.
And it says for unto us a child is born
unto us a son is given
and the government shall be upon his shoulder
and his name shall be called wonderful.
Isn't he wonderful?
Counselor, isn't he a great counselor?
If any man lack wisdom, let him ask of God.
He's the all wise God.
He's the counselor.
He is the mighty God.
Praise God.
Nothing is impossible with our God.
He is the everlasting father,
the alpha and omega, the beginning and end.
He left the throne room of heaven
and all the glory that he had for all of eternity past
according to John 17 and many other passages
that you could look to.
He was rich, but he became poor for our sakes.
He's the everlasting father.
I'm thankful this morning that he's alpha and omega.
I'm thankful this morning that though we're confound by time
and we're stuck in time and everything is related to time
that our God is outside of time.
He's always in the present.
Praise God for that.
But he says at the end of the verse,
the prince of peace, the prince of peace.
We think about the source of peace
and we understand Jesus is the prince of peace.
We understand even as we read in John 14 in verse number 27
that Jesus said, my peace I give unto you.
Now consider that with me this morning
when we consider that Jesus says not as the world giveth.
Listen, the peace of God, the source of peace
because it comes from God and Jesus says,
my peace I give unto you.
This is different than what the world,
he uses the contrast.
He says not very plainly as the world giveth.
I'm thankful the source of peace is the Lord Jesus Christ.
Consider what the apostle Paul said
in the book of Ephesians.
Notice in Ephesians two in verse number 14
as we find that Paul would be speaking to this church
that had trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as their savior,
these individual believers that make up the church
there at Ephesus.
And the apostle Paul is speaking to them
in the second chapter and he starts out
by talking about their pre-salvation days,
in times past.
And we begin to consider as you read
the chapter of Ephesians chapter number two
that before they were saved,
according to verse number 12,
it says that at what time you were without Christ.
Do you remember before you trusted Christ as your savior?
Do you remember the conflicts that you had
before you trusted Jesus as your savior?
You think about all that turmoil
and he says that you were aliens
from the commonwealth of Israel
and strangers from the covenant of promise,
having no hope and without God in the world.
I didn't get saved until I was 17 years old.
I remember what it was to not be saved.
I remember.
Some of you were saved younger,
some of you were saved older
and you too remember what it was
to not be in Christ, to not be saved.
But notice the next two words of verse number 13,
but now.
I'm thankful I'm not who I used to be.
I'm thankful that I now know the Lord Jesus Christ
as my personal savior.
There was a day that I had no hope.
There was a day that I was separated
and my sin separated me from a holy God
and I was going to a place called the lake of fire
because of my sin and because of the fact that I was guilty
and God is righteous and he is just
and he says that the wage of sin is death
and we find here in verse 13,
but now in Christ Jesus,
ye who sometimes were far off
are made nigh how?
By the blood of Christ.
We sang when I see the blood, hallelujah.
I don't pick out the songs,
but don't they go so wonderful so far this morning
with what we're looking at.
And then notice verse 14, the first statement,
for he is our peace.
He is our peace.
The source of peace.
Jesus is the prince of peace.
He says, my peace I give unto you.
Paul says, speaking of the Lord Jesus Christ,
as he mentioned in verse 13,
and we find that he says for he is our peace
who hath made both one and hath broken down
the middle wall of partition between us.
Oh, I'm thankful to have peace with God,
but we think about the peace of God
and I'm really focusing this morning on the peace of God.
It's important that we have peace with God.
There's only one way to have peace with God
and that's through the Lord Jesus Christ.
Romans five makes that abundantly clear.
We find that we read this truth that he is our peace.
Notice in the book of Philippians in chapter four,
and we'll look at this verse again in just a little while,
but notice the way that it's referred to here
in Philippians chapter four in verse number seven,
we find that he says, and the peace of God.
He uses the same phraseology in Colossians three
in verse number 15, when he says, and the peace of God,
and let the peace of God rule in your hearts.
And so we find that as we begin to think about
the source of peace, that Jesus is the prince of peace,
that Jesus says to his disciples within the context
of let not your heart be troubled,
he says, peace I give unto you,
but he says, my peace I give unto you,
not as the world giveth, give I unto you.
And I'm thankful that it is the peace of God.
We find that the Lord would then be referred to
in Hebrews chapter 13 in verse number 20,
this way he would be referred to as the God of peace,
the God of peace.
In Hebrews 13 in verse number 20,
the Bible says now the God of peace
that brought again from the dead, our Lord Jesus,
that great shepherd of the sheep through the blood
of the everlasting covenant, verse 21,
make you perfect in every good work to do his will,
working in you that which is well pleasing in his sight
through Jesus Christ to whom be glory forever and ever.
Amen.
When you read through the epistles of the New Testament,
we won't turn to all of them.
But when you read through the epistles,
you'll find that oftentimes in the greeting
of that particular, of many of those letters,
in fact, Romans, 1st and 2nd Corinthians,
Galatians, Ephesians, Philippians, Colossians,
1st and 2nd Thessalonians, 1st and 2nd Timothy,
Titus, Philemon, and 2nd John,
all of them say this,
from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ, what?
Peace, peace from God our Father
and the Lord Jesus Christ.
We begin to think about this truth
with regard to the source of peace.
And as we look at these references,
as we mention the truth that God has given us
in his word, do you not recognize this morning
that God has made it abundantly clear
that he is the source of peace?
It is God who is the source of peace.
People are running around today,
in fact, there's times in which even believers
are running around looking for peace,
but maybe they're looking in all the wrong places
because the reality this morning is this,
peace is not found in the absence of trouble.
It is found in the person of Jesus Christ.
And far too often, you might hear,
I just want some peace, I'm just longing for some peace,
and they think, they believe, they're seeking after
to have that absence of trouble.
But can I remind you this morning
that Job said it so eloquently when he said,
man that is born of woman is a few days and full of trouble.
We find that the psalmist, David,
the sweet psalmist of Israel,
the man that's after God's own heart
that he mentions in the scriptures
about all of his troubles, but he says this,
that God delivered him out of all of his troubles.
You read the life and the account of David
in the scriptures, and you find that
he suffered many troubles.
Now, some of them were by his own doing,
but many of them were of no doing of his own.
He just faced troubles.
And so if you're seeking peace
and thinking that it would be found
in the absence of trouble,
I hope that I could help you this morning.
to tell you that that's not where you're going to find peace.
Because peace is found in the presence of Jesus Christ.
In the person of Jesus Christ.
And we begin to understand here this morning this truth
as the Lord is giving to his disciples in John 14.
A troubling time. Difficult days.
I think about the disciples that walked with the Lord
and I think about hearing all that he would suffer
and then even as they would be there and they would be eyewitnesses
of his sufferings as Peter would say.
As he's writing in 1 Peter chapter 5 and talking about being eyewitnesses
of the sufferings of Christ.
Difficult days.
But Jesus said, I give you peace.
My peace.
So we see the source of peace but I want you to notice this morning
not only the source of peace but the scope of peace.
Number two, the scope of peace.
See, peace is something that we can talk about.
We have some maybe idea as I've tried to kind of describe some things here
and look at the source of peace.
But the reality is that today you're going to leave here
and you may have trouble right as you leave here.
You may go to work tomorrow and you may face some troubled times.
You might have some real difficulties.
Something that you didn't see coming.
Something that you didn't anticipate.
And you have this trouble.
You have these problems.
You have these issues that arise in life.
You hear some news from somewhere and there's this turmoil and this conflict
and someone's sideways over this or that or whatever it may be.
And you find yourself dealing with this and we find the source of peace.
But it's important that we understand the scope of peace.
What did God really mean when he told us that he was going to give us peace?
What's the scope of it?
What's the outworking?
What's the application for us?
Because we will face difficulties.
We will face troubles.
We will have bad news that we receive from time to time.
And we may be tempted to ask that question or to maybe respond this way
that I don't have time for this or maybe we say something like this.
Why me?
Why now?
Have you ever felt that way?
I was talking to someone a number of years ago and they said instead of saying why me,
maybe we should say why not me.
Think about that.
I want you to consider with me the scope of peace, sort of the Old Testament,
Psalm 119 if you will.
I'm going to look at four references this morning that help us to have an understanding,
a biblical understanding of the scope of peace.
And what is truly meant when the Bible tells us that we're to have peace,
that we're to let the peace of God rule in our hearts.
And this peace that we find that God is the source of peace
and he told us that he would give us peace.
And what is the scope of that?
In Psalm 119, the latter part of the chapter, very lengthy,
of course the longest chapter in the Bible, 176 verses.
But look at Psalm 119 in verse number 165.
I want you to notice how the Bible describes this peace.
It says, great peace.
Great peace.
Have they which love thy law and nothing shall offend them.
Who's the Bible all about?
It's all about God.
Amen.
William Strogge, preacher of yesteryear, wrote a book
and he called the book The Unfolding Drama of Redemption.
He said that the central figure in all of the Bible is the Lord Jesus Christ.
The Old Testament prophesies of his coming.
The New Testament records his coming and his work and his life in the Gospels
and then instruction for us with regard to how we live for Christ
and how we serve him and understanding that he's coming again.
And truly, when the Bible says, great peace have they which love thy law,
if we understand that the Lord is the central primary figure of the Bible,
that if we love the law of the Lord, if we're spending time in his word,
if we're engaged in studying and reading and hearing the preaching and teaching of his word,
then guess what?
We're learning more about Jesus.
We sing the song more about Jesus, what I know.
How do I know the Lord? I know him through his word.
Everything that you know to be true about God, I understand.
Psalm 19 says that the heavens declare the glory of God,
the firmament showeth forth his handiwork.
I agree 100%.
But the reality is that the testimony of nature points us to the testimony of the book
and we find that it's the book that reveals to us that our God,
as these young people sang this morning, that he's good.
How do you know God is good?
Because the Bible says, taste and see that the Lord is good.
Amen.
How do you know that he's great?
Because the Bible says, great is the Lord and greatly to be praised.
How do you know that he's immutable?
Because he says, I'm the Lord, I change not.
How do you begin to just understand that everything you know to be true about God
comes from this book?
And he says, great peace have they which love thy law.
I wonder this morning, can you say that you love the law of the Lord?
You love the Bible.
I'm so thankful that God's given us a Bible.
I know I say that regularly, but I want you to really know
how much I'm so thankful that God gave us a Bible.
Could you imagine where you'd be today if you didn't have a Bible?
Man, thank God for the Bible.
And he says that if we love thy law, he says, great peace
have they which love thy law.
But notice the last part of the phrase it says, or the last part of the verse,
and nothing shall offend them.
Nothing.
Now, nothing is like that word anything.
Right?
All, right?
Well, all, not really, no, no, no.
Nothing shall offend them.
The word offend, it doesn't mean in that idea that this person offended me
and didn't like my tie or something like that and I was offended by it.
That's not what the word means.
The word offend here means to be a stumbling block, to make someone fall.
And the reality is this, that when the Bible says, great peace have they which love thy law,
and nothing shall offend them.
You're not going to stumble, you're not going to fall, you're not going to be tripped up.
Why? Because you have this great peace
that comes from loving the law of the Lord.
As I spend time in God's word and as God's word infiltrates my heart and saturates my life
and I begin to think and act biblically and God gives me that great peace
and then some things happen and the Bible says, and nothing shall offend thee.
Nothing is going to make you fall and stumble.
Why? Because you have a firm foundation because you're in the law of the Lord.
Praise God for that.
Great peace have they which love thy law and nothing shall offend them.
I want you to notice over in Isaiah chapter 26 as we begin to think about the scope of peace.
Isaiah chapter 26.
In Isaiah chapter 26, and we won't take time to turn and look at other portions here in the book of Isaiah,
but we find that in the book of Isaiah the Bible says that the wicked have no peace.
The wicked have no peace.
But understand what the Bible says here in Isaiah chapter 26 with regard to this scope of peace.
We read in Psalm 119, great peace, but now we find in Isaiah chapter 26, notice the Bible says this
in verse number 3, thou wilt keep him in perfect peace.
Notice what it says, whose mind is stayed on thee.
Because he trusteth in thee.
Trust ye in the Lord forever, for in the Lord Jehovah is everlasting strength.
Let me ask you this morning, when the Bible says thou wilt keep him in perfect peace,
notice what it says, whose mind is stayed on thee.
How easily are we distracted by the affairs of this world?
How often do we focus on the problems more than we focus on the Savior?
You understand what I'm saying?
His mind, it says, whose mind is stayed on thee.
I'm not distracted by the things that are going on in this world,
and I'm not focused on all of those mountains of problems.
No, my eyes are looking unto Jesus, the author and finisher of my faith.
I'm lifting up mine eyes to the hills from whence cometh my help,
understanding that my help cometh from the Lord who made heaven and earth,
whose mind is stayed on thee.
You know how easily we're distracted today?
You know how easily we can face tomorrow some difficulty, some trouble,
and so quickly our minds can no longer be on the Lord,
who is the one that's able to do the impossible,
the one who knows all things, the one that has all power.
Our mind is just on this problem instead of being stayed on thee.
How do I get my mind stayed on thee?
You better get in his word.
We read about that great peace from Psalm 119 and verse 165.
Notice whose mind is stayed on thee because he trusteth in thee.
Because he trusteth in thee.
You know why we trust in the Lord?
proven to be trustworthy. Amen?
Trust in the Lord with all thine heart.
We read in Proverbs 3, a very familiar verse
and passage of scripture,
but we find here this morning that it's easy for us
as we study the word of God,
as we get into the word of God,
as we see God who never fails, who never falters,
who knows all things, who has all power,
it's easy for us to trust in him.
But if we separate ourselves from this book,
if we focus more on the problems,
all of a sudden we're not trusting in him.
All of a sudden we're crumbling and falling apart
and we don't have that truth where it says
that will keep him in perfect peace.
We find that he says in verse four,
trust ye in the Lord forever.
Now think about that, forever.
No matter the magnitude of the storm,
we're gonna trust in the Lord.
See, storms come at different times
and in really different levels.
Sometimes the storm is mild,
sometimes the storm is severe, right?
Have you experienced it?
Have you lived life?
You've experienced it.
And he said that we're to trust in the Lord forever,
for in the Lord Jehovah is everlasting strength.
So we're gonna think about the scope of peace.
We understand that God is the source.
We looked at all those verses,
but we think about the scope.
Okay, so as a child of God,
I have the truth that God says,
great peace have they which love thy law
and nothing shall offend them.
But I have the truth here in Isaiah
that will keep him in perfect peace,
whose mind is stayed upon thee,
for he trusteth in thee.
Great peace, perfect peace.
We already referenced it in John 14.
We won't take the time to turn there,
but really the third aspect of the scope of peace
is when Jesus said my peace, my peace.
Now that's so precious to me.
We're gonna think about the truth that we have
in having this walk with the Lord
and we think about the disciples
who are the original hearers of that truth
in John 14 and verse 27.
But then we think about our own lives
and Jesus says my peace, give I unto thee.
It's his peace, it's God's peace.
We know that everything about God is perfect.
Amen?
And he makes the contrast
as we've already focused on this morning
dealing with the source.
It's not like the world giveth.
It's not this false type of peace.
It's not this temporary kind of peace.
No, it's his peace.
You think about the peace that he exhibited in his life
as he went through all that he went through.
I understand he's God,
but I mentioned already from Isaiah nine,
he's 100% God, he's 100% man.
We have not an high priest which cannot be touched
with the feeling of our infirmities,
but was in all points tempted like as we are
yet without sin.
Amen?
So he understands.
And we understand that he's able to help or to succor us.
And what a thankful truth that he helps us,
he aids us in all of our infirmities.
And he says my peace.
Think about that.
As the disciples would hear that,
as the disciples would receive that again,
he said to them twice, let not your heart be troubled.
Can you imagine if he said that without giving the truth
that he was gonna give them peace?
How could my heart not be troubled given the circumstances?
How could I not be fearful given the events
that are taking place?
Oh, it's only because Jesus said my peace give I unto thee.
I want you to look in Philippians chapter number four.
We're gonna finish looking here this morning.
In Philippians chapter number four,
notice what the Bible says.
We already referenced there in Philippians chapter number four
how that the Bible tells us about this truth
that it's the peace of God.
But I wanna focus in here just for the remainder
of our time this morning to understand the peace
that God is describing, really the scope of peace,
how it's described for us.
And we look in Philippians chapter number four.
We're gonna look at verse seven in just a moment,
but I really wanna catch the entire context here.
So I'm gonna read verses four through nine,
and then we'll go back to verse number seven.
Notice in verse number four, the Bible says,
rejoice in the Lord always.
And again, I say rejoice.
Now, Paul's writing from prison.
And by the way, not only is he writing from prison,
but really the way the church in Philippi was started
was because Paul was in prison, right?
And you think about the significance of all of that.
We understand that he met Lydia, the seller of purple,
and all those things that had transpired.
But we find that after they're going forth
and all the things that are taking place,
they get beat and they get imprisoned,
and they're singing, and they're praising God.
Sounds a lot like peace, doesn't it?
Sounds a lot like peace.
And we find that there now the Lord is using Paul
to write back to this church,
and he says rejoice in the Lord always.
And again, I say rejoice.
Let your moderation be known unto all men.
The Lord is at hand.
Be careful for nothing.
Now, that doesn't mean that you're not using care
when you're doing something.
It's saying to not be full of care.
In other words, don't worry.
Don't worry.
Sometimes we're really good at worrying, aren't we?
Really good at worrying.
Somebody said this.
I think it's a great illustration to help you in your mind.
Worry is like a rocking chair.
It'll keep you busy, but it won't get you anywhere.
You ever sit in a rocking chair?
You just rock, and you stay busy the whole time.
You go to Cracker Barrel,
and they say you got a two-hour wait to have lunch,
and you're just sitting there rocking away,
and you didn't get anywhere.
That's how worry is.
He says be careful for nothing,
but in everything,
by prayer and supplication with thanksgiving,
let your requests be made known unto God.
And the peace of God, notice what it says,
which passeth all understanding,
shall keep your hearts and minds through Christ Jesus.
Verse eight, finally, my brethren,
whatsoever things are true, whatsoever things are honest,
whatsoever things are just, whatsoever things are pure,
whatsoever things are lovely,
whatsoever things are of good report,
there be any virtue, and there be any praise,
think on these things,
those things which you have both learned and received
and heard and seen in me do,
and the God of peace shall be with you.
Isn't it interesting that in verse number seven,
he says in the peace of God,
which passeth all understanding,
shall keep your hearts and minds through Christ Jesus,
and in verse number nine, he says,
and the God of peace shall be with you.
I'm thankful for the truth that our God is omnipresent.
I'm thankful for the promise that he gave us,
that as we are his children,
he says, I will never leave thee, nor forsake thee.
And we find that as we look at verse number seven
and try to help us this morning,
understand the scope of peace.
We understand the source,
but I want you to understand the scope
because the Bible says in verse seven,
and the peace of God, notice how it's described here
and how it's defined for us,
which passeth all understanding.
Now that's significant for us to understand here this morning
because there are times in which you're facing a real trial.
You're facing a real difficulty.
You're facing a real hardship.
Listen, the disciples were facing a day
when Jesus was going to go to the cross of Calvary.
It was real what they were going to encounter
in those days ahead.
And those events could keep them
in a place of being troubled.
And we know that they all did not respond
the way that they really should have responded.
But we understand that they're in the midst
of great difficulty,
and you and I will face great difficulties.
But he says that the peace of God,
which passeth all understanding.
How can I try to describe that for you this morning?
Well, it's kind of like the idea
when you look at somebody and you say,
man, those circumstances, they should be falling apart.
But they're not.
How are they continuing on
with all that they're facing?
How are they able to keep on doing
when they're facing all that they're facing?
Because the peace of God, which passeth all understanding.
It's not the peace that the world can give us.
It's not this kind of pseudo kind of peace
of like kumbaya and everything's gonna be okay,
pie in the sky.
No, it is God's peace.
And God's peace passeth all understanding.
That's the scope.
When it doesn't make sense,
because I understand the circumstances
and I see the reality of the mountain
that's standing in front of me.
But the peace of God, which passeth all understanding.
See, this is the peace that we need.
This is the peace that God gives.
But I want you to notice that the verse continues.
And notice it tells us it's gonna keep.
Notice what it says specifically.
It says this, shall keep your hearts
and minds through Christ Jesus.
Now this is worthy of our examination this morning.
We see that he says that it's gonna keep,
notice it says your heart and your mind.
Can I tell you?
is a great battle for your mind. A great battle. That's why I believe we read in verse number
eight about the things that we're supposed to think about. Because you know what happens
when we're facing difficulties and trials and troubles? We think bad thoughts. How many
of us face something and we immediately think worst case scenario? It happens. We're fragile.
We are frail people. We are but dust. God knows our frame so he gives us instruction
and he gives us peace that passeth all understanding and he says that it shall, the peace of God
that passeth all understanding shall, it is certain, it is an absolute promise, shall
keep your hearts and minds. Listen, your heart and my heart is deceitful. It's desperately
wicked. The Bible tells us that we are not to trust our heart. Follow your heart. You
hear people say that. That's bad counsel. It's bad counsel. You know what we need?
We need our heart to be kept. We find that Proverbs would tell us to keep thy heart with
all diligence for out of it are the issues of life. I want you to notice that little
word there, keep. Keep. It's such an important word in this verse of Scripture because the
word keep means to protect or guard. But it doesn't just mean to protect or guard. It
literally carries with it the context, the idea of this word keep in verse number seven
is to protect or guard in order to prevent hostile invasion. Now think about that. That's
what the word means. Now you think about somebody that's a guard, somebody that's keeping, that's
watching duty for a military and providing that protection. They're keeping watch, they're
guarding. Why? To prevent the enemy from invading. Seems pretty basic and understandable. We
find here though that God tells us that His peace that He gives us, that the Bible says
that not only does it pass all understanding, but He says that it's that peace of God that
shall keep, that will guard and protect in order to prevent hostile invasion, your heart,
my heart, your mind and my mind. That's precious to me. That's the kind of peace that we all
need. See why? Because there is the potential, there is the real danger of hostile invasion.
Amen? We're engaged in a spiritual battle. We wrestle not against flesh and blood. We
read it a few weeks ago as we preached about that idea of being able to stand in the evil
day. And we find that the Bible tells us in 1 Peter chapter number 5 that we're to
be sober and to be vigilant. Why? Because we have an adversary, the devil, that walketh
about as a roaring lion seeking whom he may devour. Listen, there's the real potential
for this hostile invasion. The individual that's a member of the military services
of the United States of America that's assigned a responsibility maybe even on foreign soil
to watch, to keep watch. Listen, their job is so important because the enemy is always
ready to invade. And can I tell you this morning that we live and we're operating in this time
of dealing with spiritual battle and warfare. And listen, you're going to have some difficulty.
You're going to have some trials, some trouble. You'll receive some news. And listen, you'll
have that hostile invasion. You'll have all of that anxiety and all that trouble and turmoil.
Why? Because you don't have, you're not allowing the peace of God to rule in your hearts. You're
not being in that position and we're all guilty at some point in our lives where we're looking
and focusing more on the problem than we are on our Savior because of the circumstances.
But I want to encourage you this morning to understand the scope of peace. That it is
great peace. It's perfect peace. It's God's peace. And it is a peace that passeth all
understanding that the Bible says shall keep your hearts and minds through Christ Jesus.
Listen, we need the peace of God. We need God's peace. The Bible then says in verse
number 8, finally brethren, and it ends with think on these things. You know that's a decision
that you have to make. What are you going to think about? What are you going to focus
on? Right? It's a decision that we make. We can focus on the problem that's right in front
of us or we can focus on the God who's going to give us peace. And it's so vital that we
understand the peace of God. Go back to John 14 in closing. John 14, sorry John 16. John
16. Jesus has spent these chapters, 13, 14, 15, 16, giving vital instruction to his disciples
that were preparing to face some really difficult days. And we find that Jesus summarizes in
John 16 in verse 33, these things I have spoken unto you that in me you might have peace.
In the world you shall have tribulation, but be of good cheer. I have overcome the
world. Isn't that awesome? Listen, we're on the winning side. Our God reigns. He rules.
And he wants us to have that peace that he offers. Can I, can I transparently tell you
this morning, and if you'd be transparent with yourself, we don't live each day with
the peace of God like we should. We let the things in life mess with us. Don't we? Listen,
we're frail. We're just dust. I get it. He's still working on me. Amen? And he's still
working on you. But this message encourages me. Because we're going to face difficulties.
We're going to face troubled times. It's not going to get any better. But our God reigns.
And he's overcome the world. And he says, these things have I written unto you. Listen,
I'm thankful that the disciples were listening to the message. God's given us his word. You
say, I'm just longing for peace. Oh, God said he'll give you peace. He's the source of it.
He wants you to allow his peace to rule in your heart. What are you going to think about?
What are you going to focus on? The problem or the Savior? The one who gives the peace
or the one that's trying to take your peace? You know what I'm saying? And this morning
we need the peace of God. We need the peace of God. Would we come to that place where
we just understand the scope of it and say, oh, God, I need your peace. I'm going to focus
on you. I'm going to get in your word. Praise the Lord. I'm going to get in your word and
great peace have they which love thy word and nothing shall offend them. Thou shalt
keep him in perfect peace whose mind is stayed upon thee. My peace give I unto thee. And
it's a peace that passeth all understanding. And it's that peace that shall keep your hearts
and minds through Christ Jesus to guard and protect from that hostile invasion that's
going to try to get you sideways and me sideways. No, I'm going to let the peace of God rule
in my heart. Let's pray. Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. We thank you for
the truth of thy word that you are the prince of peace, the source of peace. We thank you
that you've given to us the scope throughout your word of the peace that you promised to
give us. God, I'm thankful to have peace with you through the Lord Jesus Christ that
I know for sure that when I die that I'll be in heaven, not because of any merit of
my own, but all because of what Jesus did on that cruel cross, his death barrel and
glorious resurrection. Father, as your children, we live in this world, we face these circumstances,
we deal with all sorts of troubles and trials and difficulties and you told us that not
only can we have peace with you, but we're to have your peace. We're to let your peace,
the peace of God rule in our hearts. Would you help us this morning? God, I don't know
all of the troubles and all of the difficulties that those that are seated here or tuned in
via live stream are facing this morning, but God, I know who you are. I know what you've
revealed to us in your word and I know that your peace is real. And I pray that you would
help us to have the peace of God, which passeth all understanding. If there's one that's not
sure of heaven, I pray that today be the day of their salvation. They would not leave
this place without knowing with 100% assurance that heaven is their home. In these moments
of invitation, would you have your will in way? Would you help us for to be doers of
the word and not hearers only? For it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with
me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed. Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano. If you're
not sure of heaven, today is the day of salvation. Have peace with God. If you're not 100% sure
of heaven, Mark is here with the Bible.
man, and Holly's here with a Bible if you're a lady, and be able to take a Bible and show
you how you can know for sure that heaven is your home.
But what about you Christian, do you have the peace of God, are you allowing the peace
of God to rule in your hearts, do you have great peace and perfect peace, do you have
that peace of God which passeth all understanding?
Maybe you need to come and ask God to help you, maybe you're dealing with some difficulties,
some troubles and trials and hardships, and maybe you've been facing that fear and anxiety
and you just need to come and ask God to help you to allow His peace to rule in your heart
as Kimberly plays The Altar is Open.