And this morning, we're gonna deal with our service
to the Lord.
I've titled the message for the audience of one,
for the audience of one.
And I hope that as we go through the message this morning,
that that title will be abundantly clear to you
as what I'm seeking to communicate through this message
for the audience of one.
For the last three weeks,
we had the opportunity minus last Sunday,
but as we've dealt with this third phase, if you will,
for our annual theme,
the great is the Lord and greatly to be praised.
We discovered his greatness.
We spoke about the importance of declaring his greatness.
And then for this third phase,
we've dealt with the subject of how God's greatness
will impact our lives.
And I believe that when we understand how great he is,
it should have an impact on each of us.
For indeed it is true that what we believe
will impact our behavior.
For three weeks,
we spent time looking at the subject matter of prayer.
And there were several times that we noted
that what we believe to be true about God,
and we find that in his precious word
will impact how we pray.
We pray that God will move mountains because he can,
because he's God, because he has all power,
because he's reigning and ruling.
We pray that God would save sinners because he's able.
And you think about the way that we pray,
it's based upon what we believe to be true
about God's word, about who God is.
We find that we've looked at David,
the life of David in Psalm 32.
We look at the life of Daniel.
Why did Daniel have such confidence in praying
that God would show him not only the dream,
but the interpretation of the dream,
because he knew who God was.
He knew who God was.
And therefore he prayed that God would give an answer.
And guess what God did.
And Daniel did not stand before Nebuchadnezzar
and say that I'm able.
He said, there's a God in heaven and praise the Lord.
He's still there.
He rules and he reigns and he's able.
We had the opportunity to look at the life of Paul.
And we dealt with the subject matter of a life
marked by prayer.
And we looked at his life.
And as we were challenged through those messages
to examine our own prayer lives,
and in order to determine how our prayer lives
have been shaped, have been impacted
by what God has given to us in his word
about how great he is.
What is it that's on your prayer list?
What is it that we're praying about right now
that only God can do?
And that really will impact as we examine these things,
how we pray.
This morning, I'd like to move into a second thought
and that would be our service to God.
You know, it's a privilege to serve God.
And I would say this morning that when I truly understand
how great our God is, it should impact how I serve him.
I'm not just serving a mere human.
I'm not just serving some false idol.
No, I'm serving the great I am.
I'm serving the King of Kings and Lord of Lords.
And as we consider that thought this morning
and understanding that as we serve God,
we must never lose sight of the fact
that we are serving God.
Yes, will our service be to people?
No doubt.
But ultimately, our service is for the audience of one.
It's for God.
What a privilege it is to serve the Lord.
Notice in Ephesians chapter two,
we're familiar with verses eight and nine.
I'll read them together with verse number 10.
The Bible says, for by grace are you saved through faith.
And that not of yourselves, it is the gift of God,
not of works, lest any man should boast.
Notice verse 10, for we are his workmanship,
created in Christ Jesus unto good works,
which God hath before ordained that we should walk in them.
So we're gonna think about this truth
of our service to the Lord.
I want you to consider just a few thoughts
with me this morning.
Number one, we should review our attitude
towards serving the Lord.
We should review our attitude towards serving the Lord.
In other words, we understand, the Bible says here,
we are his workmanship, created in Christ Jesus,
notice, unto good works, which God hath before ordained
that we should walk in them.
Before salvation, before you trust
that Christ is your Savior,
before I trust that Christ is my Savior,
if you're here this morning and you've not yet been saved,
according to the Bible in Romans six and verse number 17,
I was a servant of sin, but in Christ.
According to Romans 6, 18,
no longer am I a servant of sin,
but now I serve the Lord Jesus Christ
and I am a servant of righteousness.
And you know, the reality is I'd much rather
be a servant of righteousness than a servant of sin.
And we find that truth to be there for us
in Romans six, verse 17 and 18.
But when we understand this truth about serving the Lord
and reviewing our attitude towards our service,
I wonder this morning, do we have the perspective
that I have to serve the Lord,
or do we have the perspective that I get to serve the Lord?
There's a great difference between having that perspective
that I have to do this,
and sometimes when we take that perspective,
it becomes overbearing, it becomes duty,
it's just difficult and maybe with drudgery,
but when we have the perspective,
when we review our attitude and understand
that we are his workmanship,
that God has created us for this,
that he has designed it to be so,
then I say, I get to serve the Lord.
I get to serve Christ.
What a privilege, what a blessing.
We find this morning that the Bible is abundantly clear.
When we think about this truth of our service to God,
we do not serve the Lord to get saved.
Ephesians two and eight in verse eight and nine
are quite clear that the Bible says,
for by grace are you saved through faith,
and that not of yourselves, it is the gift of God,
not of works, lest any man should be saved,
lest any man should boast,
and so we think about Ephesians two, verses eight and nine,
we understand the Bible is abundantly clear
when we speak about our service to God.
It's not so that you can be saved.
It's not even that you could stay saved.
See, you can't serve God to stay saved
just like you can't serve God to get saved.
The Bible tells us in 1 Peter one, verses four and five,
that we are kept by the power of God.
We find that we have an inheritance
that's reserved in heaven for us.
I cannot work to be saved, nor can I work to stay saved,
but when we understand and we examine,
we review our attitude towards serving the Lord,
we understand this morning that we get to serve God
because we are saved.
It's the result of being saved
that gives us the privilege and the opportunity
to serve the master, to serve the king of kings
and Lord of lords, and what a great privilege it is.
But at times, if we're not careful,
our attitude can kind of get sideways
with regard to service.
We can kind of get into the drudgery
and the monotony, if you will,
and we can get overwhelmed with it,
and we lose our focus that we're serving the Lord,
we're serving the master, and what a blessing.
Think about the perspective, if you will,
of the psalmist, or Psalm 84,
and I want you to look at a couple of verses
within the Psalms, because really,
I hope this morning that your service for Christ
is a delight, that it's a delight.
We understand that God has designed it
that his children would serve him,
and what a blessing it is, and you say,
as we look at this truth of serving the Lord,
we understand that it comes,
and we'll look at our next point,
it comes in a variety of shapes and sizes,
and everyone's service is not the same,
but what a privilege it is to serve the Lord,
and it should be a delight.
In Psalm 84, notice in verse number 10,
the Bible says, for a day in thy court
is better than a thousand.
I had rather be a doorkeeper in the house of my God
than to dwell in the tents of wickedness.
I want you to think about that just for a moment.
The psalmist says that they'd rather be a doorkeeper
in the house of my God, a doorkeeper.
You say, well, that's kind of a,
no, no, no, that's a service to the king.
It's a privilege, it's a delight
to be able to serve the Lord,
and you think about the perspective here.
It says I'd rather do that
than to dwell in the tents of wickedness.
I want you to think about your service to the Lord,
and the reality is that, listen,
I'd rather clean bathrooms for the Lord
than do something else for the world, amen,
and what a delight.
Somebody came to me not long ago and said,
pastor, what can I do?
I'll clean toilets, I'll clean this, I'll do that,
whatever, I just wanna serve the Lord,
and praise the Lord for that kind of perspective
because why, it's a privilege to serve God.
It is an absolute privilege.
The psalmist says here in Psalm 84,
what he would rather do,
be a doorkeeper in the house of my God.
I want you to think about Psalm 100,
and of course, we're familiar with that psalm.
It's a very familiar psalm to us,
but I want you to see what the psalmist says
in Psalm 100 in verse number two.
The Bible says this, serve the Lord how?
With gladness, with gladness.
Come before his presence with singing,
and we think about this truth
as we review our attitude towards serving the Lord.
I get to do this, I get to serve God.
I can do it with gladness, and why?
Because my perspective is that it's for the audience of one,
for the audience of one.
I'm serving the Lord.
I have the privilege of being able to serve Christ.
You say, well, as the pastor, you get to,
no, no, listen, we get to serve Christ.
There were many a day after I trusted Christ as my savior,
I was an usher at our church,
the first church I ever went to after I got saved,
and I was an usher at that church as a teenager,
and you know what the job of the ushers were?
All the ushers are gonna get scared this morning.
The job of the ushers every Saturday morning
was to go to the church house and clean the house,
the church house, and we went to that church house.
church house, all the ushers, we get together on Saturday morning early before visitation and we'd
get there and we'd spend a couple of hours before visitation cleaning that church house. Then we go
on visitation, we come back after visitation and we clean the church house some more. And you know
it was a delight. It was just a joy to be able to serve the Lord. And at times we must review
our attitude towards serving the Lord because we don't want to get bogged down in the work.
We don't want to get overwhelmed. We don't want to look at the wrong thing. We want to remind
ourselves that we're serving the Lord, that it's for the audience of one. I don't have to,
but I get to. It's a great perspective in life. Number two, we must rejoice for the ability to
serve the Lord. Rejoice for the ability to serve the Lord. You know it's God who has gifted each
of his children and given us the ability to serve him. And as I begin to think about that truth
and we understand this morning that we are his workmanship created in Christ Jesus notice unto
good works. And then at the end of verse number 10 of Ephesians 2 it says, which God hath before
ordained that we should walk in them. And this is great for us to rejoice in having the ability
to serve the Lord. So I can't do what I used to do. God knows that. There's a great Bible
character that we're familiar with. We won't take the time to go to the book of Joshua,
but you understand in the life of Joshua that there comes a time in Joshua's life,
he was the human leader for the nation of Israel. He's the one that leads the children of Israel
into the land of promise. He's the one that leads the children of Israel into all the battles that
we read in the beginning of the book of Joshua and all of that. But there comes a time when God
says to Joshua, you're old. You're old. He no longer was going to go out and lead in battles,
but what was he going to do? He's going to divide the land. That was his duty. That was
his responsibility. And guess what we find about Joshua? He was faithful to lead the children of
Israel into battle, but as his life stages changed, he was faithful to serve God in dividing the land.
If you're to study the book of Joshua, the latter part of the book, you'll find that there's some
children, some tribes of the nation of Israel that kind of just sat around and they didn't do
anything. And Joshua said, hey, what's going on? Aren't you going to go and claim your land,
claim your inheritance? And he was used of God. And then he challenges the people before his death
on serving the Lord. There are different stages that you see in the life of Joshua
through that book of Joshua. And you find that all along the way, he's serving the Lord. Is it
in different ways? Absolutely. But he's still serving God. And he had the ability to do what
God called him to do at that time. Why? Because God equipped him and God enabled him for the task
that was at hand. God equipped him and God enabled him for the battles that took place in the
beginning of the book of Joshua. But then God enabled and equipped him for the division of the
land that you read of in the midst of the book of Joshua. And then God equipped and enabled him to
deliver those challenging messages to the two and a half tribes and to the leaders and the people
of Israel before he would die. God enabled him. God equipped him. And God equips and enables each
of us. Turn to the book of 1 Corinthians, if you will. And I want to go through a few verses here
in the book of 1 Corinthians. And it's interesting as we look at this particular book, the church in
Corinth, as we understand, turn to chapter number one to begin. But the church of Corinth is not a
model church. The church in Corinth has lots of problems. The church in Corinth is being corrected
for a lot of things that they're doing wrong. And the Lord would use the apostle Paul to pen
this book in order to give them instruction with regard to how they were to serve the Lord and what
was to take place. But when we understand and we're rejoicing for the ability to serve the Lord,
I want you to see what God says to the people at Corinth with regard to their service. In verse
number four of 1 Corinthians 1, notice what Paul says to these believers under the inspiration of
the Holy Spirit of God. He says, I thank my God always on your behalf. Notice this, for the grace
of God which is given you by Jesus Christ. I would submit to you this morning that that grace of God
which is given you by Jesus Christ is not only saving grace, though it encompasses that, but it's
also serving grace and the ability to serve the Lord. Paul talks about the grace that was bestowed
upon him. At the end of this book, we find that Peter mentions about being a
good steward of the manifold grace of God. And we find here that he's speaking about, notice, the
grace of God which is given you by Jesus Christ. That in everything, verse number five, ye are
enriched by him in all utterance and in all knowledge, even as the testimony of Christ was
confirmed in you. Notice verse seven, so that you come behind in no gift, waiting for the coming of
our Lord Jesus Christ. Now, as you study the book of 1 Corinthians, you find that one of the reasons
that there's some division and some jealousy and envy within the members of the church at Corinth
is because of the subject of spiritual gifts. Some were saying, well, I have this gift and you
have that gift and my gift is better than your gift and so on and so forth. And we'll look at a
few verses because the apostle Paul is going to deal with that and try to help them. But I want
you to notice as we speak about the ability to serve God and how we ought to rejoice that he's
given us the ability to serve the Lord, that it is God who has given us the grace. It is God who has
given us the ability. He has equipped us. And it says here of the church in Corinth that they come
behind in no gift. This church that was full of division and envy was a church that was gifted
spiritually. But they allowed those spiritual gifts to cause them to look at each other and say,
I'm better than you because of the gift that I have. And they totally missed the purpose for which
God gave them the spiritual gifts in the first place. Notice in chapter number 4 of 1 Corinthians
verses 6 and 7, notice what the Bible says here. In chapter 4, 1 Corinthians 4 verse 6 and 7,
the Bible says this, and these things brethren I have in a figure transferred to myself and to
Apollos for your sakes that you might learn in us not to think of men above that which is written,
that no one of you be puffed up for one against another. He's dealing with the importance of
humility. And notice in verse 7 he says, for who maketh thee to differ from another? By the way,
aren't you happy everyone's not like you? Amen. I'm happy everyone's not like me. I'm happy
everyone's not like you. I'm happy I'm not like you. Amen. But the reality is God's made us
different. But then notice when we think about the spiritual gifts, notice in verse number 7,
and what hast thou that thou didst not receive? He's going to build upon this as we go through
the book of 1 Corinthians, and we'll look at a few more verses. He says, now if thou didst receive
it, why dost thou glory as if thou hadst not received it? And we find that he's speaking,
we look at this idea of the ability to serve the Lord, and we rejoice that God's given us
the ability. Why? Because it's God who has equipped us. It is God who has enabled us.
Think about this, the God of the universe, the one who spoke it all into existence,
the one who formed man from the dust of the ground and then breathed the life into them
through the breath of God, that he would allow us, he would allow you to serve him. It's amazing
that he would allow us to serve him in any capacity. It's amazing the ability that he's
given us to serve him. In 1 Corinthians chapter 12, notice as he continues to help this group
of believers in Corinth to understand the subject matter of spiritual gifts and to understand
the ability that God had given them to be able to serve the Lord. Remember, we don't serve God,
we don't do good works to be saved, we don't serve the Lord or do good works to stay saved,
but because we are saved, we are to serve Christ. We are to do good works. Notice in 1 Corinthians 12,
now, verse number one, concerning spiritual gifts, brethren, I would not have you ignorant.
Ye know that ye were Gentiles, carried away unto these dumb idols, even as ye were led.
Wherefore, I give you to understand that no man speaking by the Spirit of God calleth Jesus a
curse, and that no man can say that Jesus is the Lord, but by the Holy Ghost. Now there are
diversities of gifts, but notice this, the same Spirit. Verse number five, and there are differences
of administrations, but the same Lord. And there are diversities of operations, but it is the same
God which worketh all in all. But the manifestation of the Spirit is given to every man to profit
with all. Every man has been equipped and enabled to be able to serve Christ. Every child of God.
Remember the book of 1 Corinthians has been written to save people, to people that have been
born again, saved by the grace of God. And he says that the manifestation of the Spirit is given to
every man to profit with all. For to one, notice verse eight, is given by the Spirit the word of wisdom.
To another, the word of knowledge by the same Spirit. To another, faith by the same Spirit. To
another, the gifts of healing by the same Spirit. To another, the working of miracles. To another, prophecy.
To another, discerning of spirits. To another, diverse kinds of tongues. To another, the
interpretation of tongues. Now I'm not going to get into all the spiritual gifts this morning,
but understand that some of those were temporary sign gifts. The gift of healing, the gift of
tongues, those are temporary.
sign gifts. We think about even the gift of prophecy with regard to
foretelling versus what we would look at it today as being
foretelling. We see that those things have ceased. In fact, as you read through
chapter 13 and 14, you see it very plainly that they would cease, that they
would be done away with those temporary sign gifts. But notice in verse number 11
he says, but all these, and so everything that he references beginning in verse
number 8 and following, he says, but all these worketh that one in the self same
spirit dividing to every man severally, notice these words, as he will. God has
equipped you. God has enabled you. And we think about this subject matter of our
service to God, we think about how great God is, and we've examined it throughout
this year, to think this morning, to comprehend this morning that the God of
the universe would equip us as individuals and enable us to be able to
serve him. He's given us the ability. It ought to cause us to rejoice greatly. By
the way, it ought to motivate us to serve him. Amen? We're not to sit on the
premises, we're to stand on the promises. We're not to be on the sidelines, we're
to get in the game. Listen, I like playing sports. I'm getting older now, but I enjoy
playing sports. I enjoy playing them a whole lot more than I enjoy watching them. We had
our Labor Day picnic. I haven't played soccer in years. But I got sick and tired of watching
them play soccer. Guess what? I went and played soccer. Right, Fernando? You and I, we're
out there playing soccer. I think I scored four goals. Amen? Amen. Praise the Lord. I'm
getting older. But I had a good time. I wanted to get in the game. I don't want to just watch.
We're talking about serving the Lord. It's a participation thing. It's not just an observation
thing. It's not just being a spectator, but being a participator. And he's equipped
us to be able to serve the Lord. And we ought to rejoice for the ability that God has given
us. Notice in the book of Ephesians, in chapter number four, notice with me, in the book
of Ephesians, in chapter number four, and I'm going to read a few verses of Scripture
and I hope as we look at this portion that we find here that as Paul is writing to the
church at Ephesus again, how God had equipped them and how God had enabled them, that we
would recognize that it's God who has given us the ability to serve him and we would rejoice
greatly because of it. Notice in Ephesians four and verse number seven, but unto every
one of us, it's kind of all inclusive, isn't it? No one's left out. If you're saved by
grace, you've been enabled to serve the Lord and equipped, is given grace according to
the measure of the gift of Christ. Wherefore he saith, when he ascended up on high, he
led captivity captive and gave gifts unto men. Verses nine and 10 is a parenthetical
and it's, I'm not skipping it for the purpose of just avoiding it, but going into the thought
of spiritual gifts that God is dealing with in this text of Scripture and you find that
he says and gave gifts unto men at the end of verse number eight. He talks about the
measure of the gift of Christ in verse number seven and then notice in verse number 11,
and he gave some apostles and some prophets and some evangelists and some pastors and
teachers for what purpose? For the perfecting of the saints, for the work of the ministry,
for the edifying of the body of Christ. And we find that it's God who gave, it's God who
equipped, it's God who has enabled and when we understand that, we ought to rejoice that
he's given us the ability to serve him. Listen, I did not just sign up to be a pastor. I wasn't
at a job fair somewhere and looking at the benefits of what they might be and say, you
know, I think that's a really good career path for me. No, God called me. God equipped
me. God has enabled me. And by the way, I rejoice for the opportunity. Let me say this,
when he was first calling me, I resisted the call. I was scared to death. No, that's not,
it's not for me. It's not something, but it was God. I had to realize that as God calls,
God enables and there might be a place of service that God has called you to, that God
has gifted you in a particular area and God will equip you. God will enable you to do
that work. Brother Somerdorst was with us this morning. He didn't just sign up again
at the same job fair and I go to the pastor line and he goes to the evangelist line. It's
not how it works. God calls and God equips. And what a joy and what a blessing. And you
don't need to turn there, but in 1 Peter chapter 4 and verse number 10, the Bible says, as
every man hath received the gift, even so minister the same one to another as good stewards
of the manifold grace of God. We're to be good stewards. It's required in stewards,
the Bible tells us in 1 Corinthians, that a man be found faithful. And Peter says in
1 Peter 4 and verse number 10, that we're to be good stewards of the manifold grace
of God. That as God has enabled and equipped us, that we're good stewards, that we're faithful
with that which he has entrusted us with. That we recognize that God has given us the
ability to serve him. Paul says it this way. I think about the testimony of Paul when I
rejoice for this ability to serve the Lord, but I see Paul rejoicing as well to the same
group of people. Notice in 1 Corinthians 15, we were there in chapter 12 just a moment
ago, just a few chapters over. Notice what Paul says in 1 Corinthians 15 and verse number
10. As the apostle Paul would understand that it was the Lord that equipped him, that gave
him the ability and that Paul had the privilege of serving the Lord and the various ways in
which he had the privilege of serving the Lord. He says this in verse 10 of 1 Corinthians
15, but by the grace of God, I am what I am. He says in his grace, which was bestowed upon
me was not in vain, but I labored more abundantly than they all, yet not I, but the grace of
God which was with me. Therefore, whether it were I or they, so we preach and so ye
believed. Remember there's division in Corinth. I'm of Paul, I'm of Apollos and Cephas and
so on and so forth and we find that Paul is saying, listen God, I am what I am by the
grace of God. God has enabled me and God has equipped me and Paul is rejoicing for the
opportunity that he had. He says that I'm laboring, I'm labored more abundantly than
they all. Why? Not because he wanted to be a good steward of the manifold grace of God.
God used Peter to pen those words in 1 Peter 4 and verse number 10, but no doubt Paul is
an example of an individual that had been equipped and enabled by God who was a good
steward of the manifold grace of God. He says this as he's writing to the folks in Thessalonica.
Notice in 1 Thessalonians chapter number 2, in 1 Thessalonians chapter 2, notice what
Paul says. Again, this ability that we have in rejoicing for the ability to serve the
Lord. Again, my attitude as I review my attitude, it's a get to situation, not a have to situation.
Now the bottom line is that really if you were to dig real deep, you really do have
to serve the Lord because you need to be a good, at least you're going to stand before
Christ. You're going to give an account. You're going to give an account. But man, I get to.
I get to serve him. I get to serve him. In 1 Thessalonians chapter 2, notice what Paul
says in chapter 2 and verse number 4. He says, but as we were allowed of God to be
put in trust with the gospel, even so we speak, not as pleasing men, but who? But God, which
trieth our hearts. Why? For the audience of one. For the audience of one. Paul says as
he went into Thessalonica and he's preaching the gospel and of course all that was taking
place with regard to the persecution during that particular era of his missionary journey
and we see that his attitude is this. We were allowed of God. I had the privilege. I had
the opportunity. It was a delight. But Paul, you suffered. But Paul, you were persecuted.
But I was allowed of God. God entrusted me. God allowed me to do this. But Paul, you suffered.
But it was worth it. You read 2 Corinthians chapter number 4. He says it's worth it. It's
worth it. And he says here that we were put in trust with the gospel even so we speak
not as pleasing men, but God, which trieth our hearts. You know what happens when you
try to please men? You fail. You know why you fail? Because it's impossible to please
everyone. It is absolutely impossible to please everyone. And if you want a case study
on it, you can control the thermostat next week. You say, well that's such a simple thing.
You can't please everyone. Promise you. Promise you. But you know, it's for the audience of
one when we serve the Lord. For the audience of one. We're serving God and He's the one
that tries the heart. By the way, I'm thankful. My heart's deceitful and so is yours. But
God, He trieth the heart. He knows. He knows your motive. He knows why you're serving Him.
He knows. He knows what your motive is. By the way, if your motive is to be recognized
by man, you have your reward. Just go back to Matthew and read what he says about those
Pharisees and those Sadducees. When they prayed those big high prayers and they wanted to
be noticed of men, they have their reward.
reward. That's what Jesus says. What's the reward? The applause of man. Did you hear
him? No, no, no. It's for the audience of one. And when our motive is to please Christ,
when our motive is to please Christ and to serve Christ and to do it with a pure heart
then he is the one that's exalted and magnified and it's all about him. Will you make people
upset? Yeah, you will. But when you keep your focus on I'm serving the Lord, I'm serving
the Lord. Paul says it this way in 1 Timothy chapter 1. Think about what Paul says here.
It's a verse of scripture that Holly has on her signature of her email and I appreciate
this verse of scripture. Many of us have what we might refer to as a life verse. Maybe we
sign a card or an email with a particular verse and again Holly has verse 12 of 1 Timothy
1. I want you to notice what Paul says in this verse of scripture. And I thank Christ
Jesus our Lord who hath enabled me for that he counted me faithful putting me into the
ministry. Notice verse 13 with it. Who was before a blasphemer and a persecutor and injurious
but I obtained mercy because I did it ignorantly in unbelief. Listen I'm thankful that I'm
not what I used to be. In fact they sang about that this morning in that song. I'm a sinner
saved by grace and I'm not what I used to be. Aren't you thankful? I'm no longer a servant
of sin, Romans 6 we mentioned that in the beginning of the message. I'm now a servant
of righteousness and Paul says this is what I was before but now I have the privilege
of serving the Lord and he says I thank Christ Jesus our Lord who hath enabled me for that
he counted me faithful putting me into the ministry. What a great perspective. Rejoicing
for the ability to serve the Lord. Number three if you're taking notes we must review
our attitude, we must rejoice for the ability but number three I want you to recognize what
is accomplished when we serve the Lord. Recognize what is accomplished when we serve the Lord.
Clearly our service to God is for the audience of one but I would submit to you this morning
that it has an impact on many. Our service to God is for the audience of one, the Lord
Jesus Christ but it has an impact on many. We read already in 1 Corinthians chapter number
12 where the Bible said and we'll look at a couple of verses there in 1 Corinthians
chapter 12 notice as we talked about the gifts of the Spirit he said I don't want you to
be ignorant concerning the spiritual gifts in 1 Corinthians chapter 12 he mentioned in
verse number 7 that the manifestation of the Spirit is given to every man to profit with
all. And so as the body of Christ is assembled and the people of God are enabled and equipped
and we serve the Lord it's yes for God to be glorified but we find that it will have
a profit on all. Notice this truth see the greatest aspect we talk about recognizing
what is accomplished when we serve the Lord is that he is glorified. He's glorified.
If our service to God is done the way that we've spoken of thus far in the sermon this
morning then God is glorified. Let your light so shine before men that they may see your
good works and do what? Glorify your Father which is in heaven. Is that what the Bible
tells us? Those are the words of Jesus and we find that that's the purpose right? Notice
in 1 Corinthians chapter 12 we look at verse 18 it says but now hath God set the members
every one of them in the body notice as it hath pleased him and for the glory of God.
See it's his church and in his church he is to receive glory and when we serve the Lord
every single one of us as we serve the Lord in the manner in which God has enabled us
to serve the Lord and we're good stewards of the manifold grace of God and we're serving
God out of that pure heart in doing what he's called us to do then God is glorified. He's
exalted and he's magnified. Look at 1 Peter chapter 4 we referenced verse number 10 earlier
that the Bible talks about being a good steward of the manifold grace of God but I want you
to see what the Bible says in verse number 11. In 1 Peter chapter 4 we find that every
man hath received the gift and we're thankful for that and we're to be good stewards of
the manifold grace of God but verse number 11 of 1 Peter 4 says this if any man speak
let him speak as the oracles of God if any man minister let him do it as of the ability
which God giveth and notice this phrase that God in all things may be glorified through
Jesus Christ to whom be praise and dominion forever and ever amen. In Ephesians 4 we won't
take the time to turn there but we spoke in that portion of scripture how the Lord gave
some to the church. He gave the evangelists, some apostles, evangelists, pastors, teachers
and he said why for the perfecting of the saints. It's that God would be glorified but
number two so that God's people would be edified. What is accomplished when we serve the Lord?
We must recognize what's accomplished when we serve the Lord and by the way all of these
things are connected. When I recognize what's accomplished it's going to impact, it's going
to help me have the right attitude. When I understand that it's him that's given me the
ability it's going to help me to have the right attitude. When I have the right attitude
then I'm going to serve him the way that I'm supposed to with a pure heart and not for
any kind of man accolades and recognition but I'm going to serve the Lord with that
pure heart and it's going to accomplish what it's supposed to accomplish. Number one for
God to be glorified but number two for God's people to be edified. For the profit of all.
That God's people would be edified. That word means to be built up. We find that it's a
word the Greek word would often in this particular era be used with regard to the construction
of a building and thinking about the edification and how people are to be built up and we find
that the Bible says for the perfecting of the saints, for the work of the ministry,
for the edifying of the body of Christ in Ephesians 4 and verse number 12 and we find
that God's people are to be edified and as we serve again, as we serve God it's for the
audience of one but it has an impact on many. It's for the audience of one but it has an
impact on many and we have been given the opportunity to serve the Lord. What a privilege.
What a privilege as we examine our lives and understanding how great God is and certainly
each of us would say great is the Lord and greatly to be praised. How has his greatness
impacted the way that I pray? But this morning how has his greatness impacted how I serve
him? Because he's a great God. He's worthy of our best. Amen. He is worthy of our best.
I was reading an author a week ago and I was reading a particular author and he was quoting
somebody else and I don't remember who he was quoting so I can't tell you who it was
because it wasn't the man that actually wrote the book that I was reading but he was quoting
somebody else and here's what he said. He said you and I have a best part of our day.
What he was talking about is like some people are morning people, some people are evening
people, whatever. We know what the best part of our day is. He said you know what I try
to do in my life? I try to give God the best part of my day. The best. Why? Because he
deserves it. You go over and read the book of Malachi. What a convicting book. They're
bringing some offerings but God says no, no, no would you take that to your governor? No
you wouldn't. So why are you bringing it to me? I'm a great God and he is. Listen I know
we've joked and I've said it before about that phraseology of it's good enough for government
work. Listen it's not good. Our best is what God deserves. By the way aren't you thankful
that he gave you his best? I don't want to just mail it in. I don't want to just kind
of go through the motions. No, no he deserves my best. He deserves your best. Let me use
an example in closing this morning. An example from the Old Testament. Turn back to the book
of Exodus if you will. We won't take time to look through all of it. In fact it would
be a sermon series to look at all of it. But I want you to look at Exodus 36 and we're
going to kind of walk our way through a few verses of scripture throughout the end of
the book of Exodus here this morning in closing. With this idea of our service to God for the
audience of one. As we examine our lives and we begin to consider how is my service to
God? What am I doing for God? How am I serving God? I hope that you have an answer for that
question because God has equipped you. He's enabled you. He's given us the opportunity,
the ability to serve him. What a privilege it is. We find that in the book of Exodus
there's a lot of things that are taking place in the book of Exodus. Of course God is bringing
his people out of Egyptian captivity, Egyptian bondage and as God would bring his people
out we find that God gives them instruction. He takes Moses up and gives them the Ten Commandments
and so on and so forth and the law. He provides for them. The people break even the law as
he's up there and receiving instruction with regard to the construction of the tabernacle.
And many of us would be familiar with the tabernacle in the Old Testament. The gathering
place, the meeting place, the worshipping place if you will for the children of Israel
until the time of...
Solomon when the temple would be built. So, for a number of generations, it was that God's
presence was known physically on earth through the tabernacle. We find that the Bible tells us,
and what a joy, in the book of John, that Jesus, he dwelt among us, and that Greek word truly is
tabernacled amongst us. What a privilege and what a blessing. You think about the incarnation.
But here, we think about the construction of the tabernacle. All of the instruction is given.
If you were to study the book of Exodus, and if you were to have an idea of the tabernacle,
and all of the intricacies. I mean, it was a very elaborate structure. There was a lot of work that
took place. But I want you to understand that if you were to study through the book of Exodus,
and begin to try to nail down a time frame, it's about five to six months that it took
them to construct the tabernacle. Now, that's pretty amazing. When you consider all that was
involved with the tabernacle, and all of the pieces of furniture, and the elaborate work,
five to six months for its completion. And we think about this truth as we look at this idea
of our service to the Lord. And as we think about the construction of the tabernacle,
God had equipped Bezalel and Aholiab. He gives us their names specifically. And by the way,
he told Moses about them, not only equipping them for the work, but enabling them to teach others
how to do those things. But we find that as we look here, and we think about their work for God,
the Bible tells us in Exodus 36, in verse number one, notice it says,
then wrought Bezalel and Aholiab, notice, and every wise-hearted man. And then notice this phrase,
in whom the Lord put wisdom and understanding to know how to work all manner of work
for the service of the sanctuary according to all that the Lord had commanded. So,
who was it that equipped them? It was the Lord. Who was it that equips you? It's the Lord.
We've belabored the point in the New Testament this morning, for us as God's people in 2023,
that God has equipped and enabled us. And here, as we look at this Old Testament illustration
to prove the point this morning, to nail it home, if you will, that it was God who had given
to Bezalel, Aholiab, and every wise-hearted man, the Lord put wisdom and understanding
to know how to work all manner of work for the service of the sanctuary according to all the
Lord had commanded. Notice verse two, and Moses called Bezalel and Aholiab and every wise-hearted
man, in whose heart the Lord had put wisdom, and every one whose heart stirred him up to come unto
the work. Notice these words, to do it. What a privilege. I don't know. God doesn't tell us a
whole lot about Bezalel or Aholiab. The other men aren't even name by name. But I'd like to think
that these men had a perspective of who am I that God would allow me to be used in this manner.
Who am I that I would be privileged, that God would enable me to make these pieces of furniture
that would be within the holy place and even the holy of holies. It's amazing. And they were
equipped, but they had to do the work. They were equipped for it, but they had to do it.
We've been equipped, we've been enabled, we've been given a gift, but we better use it.
We better use it. And we find in chapter 36 that God tells us how they were to do the work and how
the people brought the materials that were needed. And you read through chapter 36 and 37 and 38 and
you find that throughout these chapters that they're working and they're working diligently.
They're working. It seems as if as you read the chapters here in the book of Exodus that it's a
delight for them. You don't see Moses having to run around and try to, hey, let's go guys, we got
to get this done. Let's go. No, no, it looks like it's a delight. It's just joy. We sing the song,
there's joy in serving Jesus. And here they're serving the Lord. And you come to chapter 39
of the book of Exodus and look down, if you will, at verse number 32. The Bible says,
I'll give you a moment, 39 and verse 32,
thus was all the work of the tabernacle of the tent of the congregation, look at that word,
finished. It was finished. The children of Israel did according to all that the Lord commanded Moses,
so did they. They were faithful. Notice what it said, it was finished. They did the work that
they did the work that God called them to do. Notice what it says, according to all that the
Lord commanded Moses, so did they. No shortcuts. They did it all. Notice in verse number 42,
the end of the chapter, Exodus 39 verse 42, according to all that the Lord commanded Moses,
so the children of Israel made all the work. And Moses did look upon all the work and behold,
they had done it as the Lord had commanded. Even so had they done it and Moses blessed them.
Wow. What an amazing time in Israel's history. Chapter 40 of the book of Exodus,
one of my favorite chapters of the Bible, because you see what takes place with the
rearing up of the tabernacle. We don't have time to read through it, but you'll notice if you read
it later on your own, that you'll find a number of references. In fact, 13 times from verse three
down through verse number 15, you read this statement, and thou shout. God told them what to
do. God explicitly explained to them the instruction that they're to follow. And then you find that the
Bible tells us as the Lord commanded Moses, repeated seven times, and you find that they
did it. They did the work. They did what God called them to do. And you come to verse number 34.
And in Exodus chapter 40 and verse number 34, it starts with a word then.
Then. The word then is an interesting word because it means after something. After the Lord commanded
and after they did according to what the Lord commanded then. Then does not come
if they don't do. Would you agree? We never read the end of Exodus 40 if they don't do as the Lord
commanded them to do. What is accomplished? What is it when we think about this truth of serving
the Lord and we recognize what is accomplished when we serve the Lord? We've already noted
their attitude. We've understood that God's given them the ability and we find what is accomplished.
Well, because they did the work, we're able to read the end of Exodus when the Bible says,
then a cloud covered the tent of the congregation and the glory of the Lord filled the tabernacle.
Verse 35, and Moses were not able to enter into the tent of the congregation. Why? Because the
cloud abode thereon and the glory of the Lord filled the tabernacle. I hope that you'd agree
with me this morning that here we would find that God is glorified. There's no, listen, there's no
way that God would fill the tabernacle with his glory if he wasn't pleased with what they did.
And we find here that God's glory is manifested. His glory fills the tabernacle according to verse
34 and verse number 35 and the Lord is exalted. The Lord is glorified. That's what happens in
your life and in my life when we serve the Lord. Listen, God's not called any one of us to build a
tabernacle. God's not called, he is, I'm thankful that my body is, when I got saved, when you got
saved, our body is the temple of the Holy Ghost. Amen? That's what the New Testament believers,
we understand that. You don't have to, God's not called you to do what he called a bezel on a holy
abbey and these wise-hearted men, but we find that as they did what God called them to do,
as they reviewed, they had the right attitude, they understood the ability that God gave,
and they accomplished bringing glory to God. That's the first and primary reason that we serve
God is to bring honor and glory to him. But I said this is for the audience of one but has an impact
on many. I want you to understand that for generations, for generations, the people of Israel
went to a tabernacle and brought their offerings, pointing to Messiah who would one day come
because some people served the Lord. There's no record, none that I have found, if you found it,
please help me, none that I have found where any of these pieces of furniture are ever remade
before the construction of the temple. They did a thorough work. They were diligent in serving
the Lord and generations of people were impacted because of their service to God. It was for the
glory of God, but it had an impact on many. And I wonder this morning,
does our service bring glory to God? How are we serving God? Is it bringing glory to him?
Who's it impacting? How is our service having an effect on others? What a joy to have the
opportunity to serve the Lord. I think of some Bible characters that served the Lord and had
a proper perspective and they understood what God had given them to do. And I think about the
way in which David prepared for the house of the Lord, the temple, if you fast forward all of these
generations later and you think about what God is doing and how David would prepare for the palace
and he says that the palace is not for man but it's for God.
So therefore, what was David doing?
Man, David was preparing with all of his might, the Bible tells us.
He talks about how the house that God would dwell in, that Solomon would build, how that
it was to be a great house and how it was to be magnificent and so on and so forth.
And we find here that God would use David in this way.
I think about the situation as you look at the, after the destruction of Jerusalem and
the Babylonian captivity and all that takes place and you begin to think about the rebuilding
and what takes place and those opposition and how that the Bible tells us that there
were some people that had the opportunity to go and to do a work and here the people
were calling, hey, come down here and let's talk and let's do this and what have you and
all of those that were trying to prevent the work of God from continuing to go forward.
And we find that the perspective was that we're doing a great work.
Why?
Because it's a work for God.
It's a work for God.
This morning as we serve the Lord, we're not serving men.
As you serve in our church, you're not serving me as the pastor.
You're serving the Lord.
Does it profit with all?
Sure it does.
Does it have an impact on the whole body?
Sure.
That's how it's supposed to work ultimately to bring honor and glory to the Lord.
And as we bring honor and glory to the Lord, then we have the opportunity to also have
an impact on many.
This morning for the audience of one, we serve a great God, a great, great God and He gives
us the opportunity, the privilege of being able to serve Him.
I wonder this morning, how's our attitude towards serving the Lord?
How's our attitude?
Do we have the perspective that I have to do this or do we have the perspective that
I get to do this?
I hope this morning it's a get to perspective, that it's a delight, that there truly is joy
in serving Jesus.
Recognize this morning it's God who's given us the ability.
We must remember that.
The only thing special about us is God.
It's the only thing special about us.
Paul said, I am what I am by the grace of God.
This morning we can accomplish great things as we serve the Lord, glorifying Him and then
impacting others.
This morning for the audience of one, O Lord, would our service be pleasing to Thee?
Would we have that right perspective?
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
How we thank You for loving us.
We thank You for the opportunity that You've given us to gather, to hear from Your Word.
Thank You for the examples of those in the Scriptures that served You faithfully.
God I pray that You would help us to serve You faithfully and acceptably.
Lord that we would evaluate our lives, our attitude toward our service to You.
God I pray that we bring You honor and glory.
I pray that others would be impacted by our service to Thee.
Lord maybe there's someone here that's not sure of heaven.
They've never been saved.
God I pray that today they'd be saved.
They'd trust Christ as their Savior.
You're understanding they could never work to get to heaven.
They could never work to keep themselves saved.
Yes, the Bible speaks of our works, our service, it's a result of being saved, not the means
by which we are saved.
God I pray that the Holy Spirit of God would convict that one that might be here, Lord,
that they would understand their need today to be saved.
I pray for every child of God, Lord, as we've gathered this morning, we've been challenged
by Your Word.
I pray that we would evaluate our lives and our service to You.
God I pray that You'd help us to do what You've called us to do.
That we would be good stewards of the manifold grace of God.
That You would use us for Your honor and for Your glory.
That many others would be impacted by our service.
We'll thank You in these moments of invitation, Lord, for the work that You'll do.
I pray that You'd have Your will and way in every individual that's gathered together.
We'll thank You for it.
In Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano and as she plays the altar is open.
Maybe this morning you want to come and thank God for the opportunity to serve.
Maybe this morning you've not been serving like you should be and maybe you want to come
and ask God to help you in that particular area of your life.
If you're not saved we'd love to take a Bible and show you how you can know for sure that
heaven's your home as Kimberly plays the altar is open.