41 this evening, Genesis chapter 41. We'll be looking at verses 44 through 53
and then next Sunday evening we'll finish up Genesis chapter number 41.
It's kind of interesting if you think about Genesis 41 to this point in our
study
as we enter into the 44th verse tonight. Up to this point Joseph
has been released from prison. Remember we start at the passage of Scripture and
he's still in prison. Pharaoh had a dream
no one could interpret the dream and the butler remembers, oh yeah
I was in prison you were angry with me and there was a man there
and he was able to interpret my dream and the baker's dream and they both came
to pass just as
he said they would and we find that Pharaoh sent and
called for Joseph with haste and Joseph is released from prison.
Joseph tells Pharaoh the dream. Not only does Joseph tell Pharaoh the dream
but remember he provides counsel to Pharaoh
with regard to what has to happen really over the next 14 years.
The dream that Pharaoh had really was God revealing to Pharaoh
what was going to happen in Egypt over the next 14 years.
We find that the Bible spoke of God
doing this work and that it would come to pass soon. It would shortly
be brought to pass according to verse number 32 and we find that he, Joseph,
after giving the interpretation and the counsel to Pharaoh
that he is promoted to second in command over all of
Egypt. Wow, what a chapter. I mean so many amazing
things that take place in such a short period of time
to begin Genesis chapter 41. It reminds me
of God's timing and God's timing is amazing
and when God is ready, when God's time is right
and he brings it to pass and what a blessing. There are times in which we
could be waiting and we're
waiting and we're waiting and it seems like what's going on
but when God is, when things are taking place in God's timing
it's perfect and it happens just as he wants it to happen.
We find this evening as we look at our text of scripture in verses 44 through 53
that God will provide us really an overview of the first seven years
of the famine. Of course we know after the first seven years or those seven
years of famine, we know, excuse me, the seven years of plenty,
we know that those seven years of plenty would be followed
by seven years of famine and so these few verses of scripture
cover seven years of time,
the seven years of plenty. Now it's interesting because up to verse number
all of those events that I just told you happened very quickly
and here we find in just a handful of verses that God
is going to give us an overview of those seven years of plenty
and in doing so God gives us some information with regard to Joseph
and what has been taking place. Joseph,
in this text of scripture, we find that he is given
an Egyptian name, he's also given an Egyptian bride
and God blesses, he has two children. Notice in verse number 44
the Bible says, and Pharaoh said unto Joseph, I am Pharaoh
without thee shall no man lift up his hand or foot
in all the land of Egypt. And Pharaoh called Joseph's name
Zaphnath-Paneah and he gave him to wife Asenath,
the daughter of Potipharah, priest of On
and Joseph went out over all the land
of Egypt. The Bible tells us in verse 46 that Joseph was 30 years old when he
stood before Pharaoh, king of Egypt
and Joseph went out from the presence of Pharaoh and went throughout all
the land of Egypt. If you draw your attention down to verse number 52
the Bible says the name of the second called he Ephraim, this is the second child
and notice what it says, for God hath caused me to be fruitful
in the land of my affliction. I've titled the message this evening from that verse
of scripture there
in verse number 52, fruitful in the land
of affliction. Fruitful in the land of affliction. Many times when we think
about the land of affliction we do not think of it as being a place that would
produce fruit, that would be a fruitful place. In fact,
we think about the land of affliction or times of affliction in your life, in my
life,
we don't think of them in very pleasant terms and an idea of
looking at this passage of scripture, God helps us to learn
some important truths. As I begin to look at this passage
let me just say this by way of introduction, the name that Joseph
called, or that Pharaoh gives Joseph, the Egyptian name Zaphnath-Paneah,
the exact meaning is unclear and I'll admit that you can look at a number of
different commentaries and theologians. In fact,
the meaning of Joseph's
Egyptian name has been debated amongst theologians and amongst
Jewish rabbis for centuries, but it seems as if as you look at this and you
look at some things
that this name Zaphnath-Paneah, and it really makes sense when you think about
this meaning,
and again there's a lot of debate and some have different opinions as to what
it means,
but it seems that it carries this meaning, God speaks
and he lives. Now it could be God speaks and he giveth life,
but that idea, and I want you to think about that just for a moment,
as Pharaoh, a polytheistic,
idolatrous individual that he himself was looked at as being some level of
deity
by the people of Egypt, and yet as he stands there he has no
way of having this dream interpreted, he is troubled,
and Joseph comes in and Joseph says, remember,
he says, it is not in me, God shall give Pharaoh
an answer of peace, and when God uses Joseph
to share with Pharaoh the interpretation of the dream and to give him counsel,
Pharaoh could have picked any Egyptian name
to give Joseph, but it seems as if there's a consensus
with this meeting that God speaks
and he lives. Isn't that precious?
To think about the influence and impact
that Joseph could have in the life of Pharaoh because he stood there with
boldness
and he stood there in humility, I believe that his only concern, I mentioned this a
couple of weeks ago,
his only concern was for the glory of God, and when you and I are only concerned
for the glory of God, it's amazing what God can do
in and through our lives. As we look at the text of Scripture tonight, we begin
to
look at these verses of Scripture, I believe that there are two principles
that God
really brings into focus for us as you read through the verses,
and I hope tonight that we can consider these two principles
and seek to make application in our lives. Number one,
I believe that we see in this passage of Scripture
the principle of preparation, the principle of preparation.
Why do I say that? Well, we read verses 44 and 45 already
and we find that Joseph is elevated to this position. The Bible tells us in
verse number 46,
I read it a moment ago, but notice it says, and Joseph was 30 years old
when he stood before Pharaoh, king of Egypt. It's interesting to me that in
this particular age, being 30 years old, he is elevated to a position of great
power,
but also a great responsibility. I want you to think about the power that he has.
Only Pharaoh would have more power
over all the land of Egypt, but then I want you to think about the
responsibility
that would be entrusted to Joseph. I mean, a great deal of responsibility
is given to Joseph in placing him in this particular
position. I believe that as we look at this portion of Scripture, we begin to see
what's happening. Notice the Bible says
that Joseph, at the end of verse number 46, he went out from the presence of Pharaoh
and went throughout all the land of Egypt. The Bible says in verse 47, in the
seven
plenteous years, the earth brought forth by
handfuls. Now this is aligned with what Joseph said would happen when Joseph
gives the interpretation.
He tells Pharaoh that there would be seven years of plenty
and we find that it's exactly what's taking place. The Bible says that during
those plenteous years,
the earth brought forth by handfuls.
Notice in verse 48, and he gathered up
all the food of the seven years, which were in the land of Egypt,
and laid up the food in the cities, the food of the field,
which was round about every city, laid he
up in the same. And Joseph gathered corn as the sand of the sea very much until
he left
numbering, for it was without number.
Do you see the responsibility of this position that Joseph has?
If we begin to think about the responsibility, no doubt having a
position like this
and having the power, but also having the responsibility
to gather up during these years of plenty,
no doubt there would be some that would not be happy with Joseph with regard to
that which he was doing. There would be certainly
a number of people that he would have to
delegate responsibility to, that he would have responsibility entrusted to
them.
He had a great deal of responsibility laid
upon his shoulders, but I would submit to you this evening that God was
preparing Joseph for this very moment
for years. The principle of preparation.
See, in Genesis chapter 37, we are first introduced to Joseph
when he is 17 years old. We don't know, we really don't know anything biblically
scriptural
about Joseph's life prior to that event in Genesis 37 when he comes on the scene
as a 17-year-old,
but I want you to think about Joseph when he first comes on the scene at 17
years old, it seems as if Joseph already at that point in his life had proven to
be both faithful and trustworthy. Joseph was in a position, remember the Bible
tells us that he brought back the evil report of his brothers. He understood the
difference between right and wrong, good and evil. Oh today we have people that
are much older than 17 that seem to not have any idea of morality and the
difference between right and wrong, good and evil. And we find that Joseph, he
observing their behavior, he knew of their evil report or their evil behavior
and he brought back that evil report. So as his brothers depart, we find that it's
Joseph who is given the responsibility to go see what your brothers are doing.
Bring me word again. And we find that this is the responsibility that is
entrusted to him and at that point in his life we find that Joseph is
immediately obedient to what his father had instructed him to do. His dad calls
him and says here son here's what I want you to do. Now we already know that his
brothers didn't like him. His brothers were upset because of the dreams and all
that had taken place and his brothers are are not kind towards him. They could
not speak kindly to him and we find that here he goes out to find his brothers to
fulfill the responsibility that had been given to him from his father and it's
there where he's taken and put into a pit and eventually sold into slavery. We
find that he comes to Egypt and he's there in Egypt, 17 years old, about 17. We
find that's where we're introduced to him in Genesis 37. It seems as if all those
events take place pretty quickly and we come to Genesis chapter 39 and we find
that he's bought by one named Potiphar. And of course we find that Joseph
immediately when he comes into the place of being in Potiphar's house, he's
elevated to a position of responsibility and he has the
responsibility to take care of, to be a minister there in the house of Potiphar
to be a steward. God's preparing Joseph. God's preparing him and we find that
Joseph after a period of time being the steward in Potiphar's house, we know that
he's lied about and he's falsely accused and he finds himself in prison and guess
what God's doing in Joseph's life in prison? He's preparing him. He's preparing
him. So nearly 13 years, about 13 years have passed since Joseph has been in
Egypt and all along the way God is preparing Joseph. God does a work of
preparation in his servants. By the way I'm thankful for the work of preparation.
I'm thankful for how God will lead and work in individuals lives and God has
particular purposes and wills for our lives and he desires that he would
prepare us for the task that he has for us to do. The problem is how do we deal
with the time of preparation? How do we handle that season of preparation when
God is shaping us and molding us and preparing us? Are we faithful? Are we
obedient to what God has called us to do so that we're learning what we're
supposed to learn? Because that principle of preparation is so important
in our lives, God is preparing us. I wonder tonight what is God preparing us
for? God has a plan and a purpose for you and your life and there are times in
which we have that opportunity even as Joseph did to go through a period of
preparation. And as Joseph would be entrusted with this great position of
not only power but great responsibility, we find that God had been preparing him
all along the way. Turn to the New Testament, if you will, the book of Luke. I
want to hold your place there in Genesis 41, but I want to show you two verses.
You're familiar with the verses no doubt in the book of Luke, but I want you to
look at Luke 16 and then we'll look at a verse over in Luke 19. And I want you to
consider with me the time, the principle that we see here of preparation. I am
thankful that through the the overview that I just provided you with all along
the way in Joseph's life, we find that he was faithful. And because he was
faithful, God was molding him and God was shaping him and he was in a position
that when Pharaoh says, okay Joseph, you're the one, you're the one that's
going to be in this position, that Joseph was ready for the task that was given to
him. Notice in Luke chapter 16 and verse number 10, the Bible says, he that is
faithful in that which is least is faithful also in much. And he that is
unjust in the least is unjust also in much. You know, a good indicator of the
faithfulness of individuals is how do they handle the little things that are
entrusted to them. The things that people might say, well that's really not that
big of a deal, but no, it is a big deal. And we learn to be faithful in the
little things and God will entrust us with bigger things. God will give us that
responsibility. Why? Because he's preparing us even through those times.
Joseph finds himself in Potiphar's house. What am I doing here? Why have I
been sold here? And God's preparing him and he's faithful and God is with him
and he's doing what he's supposed to be doing and he's the steward and he's so
able to do what God has given him to do that even the Potiphar, the ruler of the
home, he doesn't even know what's going on. He didn't trust at all to Joseph, the
prison guard. He does the same thing. Joseph is faithful in that which is
least and God gives him great responsibility. Notice in Luke chapter
19 and verse number 17. Luke 19 and verse number 17, this is a passage, we
could really look at the entirety of it from verse 11 down through verse 27 of
the truth of being faithful, but I want to just draw your attention to verse 17
and we'll get back over to the book of Genesis. Notice it says here,
and he said unto him, well thou good servant, because thou hast been faithful
in very little, have thou authority over ten cities. Faithful over little. You
know what God's doing when he entrusts us with those little things? He's
preparing us. He's preparing us. And I don't know exactly what he's preparing
each and every one of us for, but it's very interesting how God works in the
season of preparation. I'll use a personal illustration and when I was
working in the corporate world, I remember working in the corporate world
for a number of years and I had studied. I knew that God called me to the
ministry and I knew that that's what God wanted me to do. I was working in our
church doing all that the pastor would allow me to do with regard to ministry
and opportunities and things were going well there, but I knew God had called me
to pastor and I was working in the corporate world and honestly things were
going absolutely wonderful from a corporate perspective with regard to
promotions and all of those types of things, but I knew that's not where God
had me forever. I knew that God called me to the ministry. And yet during that time,
because of a principle that was taught to me by a spiritual mentor of
understanding that God is able to prepare us through every season of life,
that I determined that even while I was there, I was going to seek to be the best
that I could be for the Lord and learn what I could learn so that God could use
that time for whatever the future would be. And it's amazing to me, and I give all
the glory to God, it's amazing to me on the opportunities that the Lord allowed
me to have in the corporate world that have been such a blessing and a help
when it comes to pastoring. Things that they don't teach you in Bible college,
things that they don't teach you in seminary, things that you don't have any
classes on certain things, and the opportunity that I had in that
particular season of life in a time of preparation. And because of the influence
in my life that was given to me that, hey, I know that this is not where you're
going to be forever, I know that you believe God's called you to pastor, but
in this place, learn what God has for you to learn. It's a season of preparation.
And how I thank God for how he prepared and the things that he taught me.
As we look in the book of Genesis in chapter 41, I believe that here we see a principle
of preparation that Joseph, now at 30 years old, he is entrusted with this great position
and he has great responsibility, he has great power, but God had been preparing him all along.
It's not as if Joseph just, bam, you're going to be second in command. No, there was
he was 17 when he first there is introduced to us in Genesis 37. So 13 years of preparation
before he goes to the place, the position that we read of him having here. By the way,
I think that if Joseph could stand here and give testimony, he'd be able to tell us that
through those 13 years, God was preparing him for the task that was at hand. And what a blessing.
I see another principle in our text of scripture, not only a principle of preparation,
but I see the principle of perspective. Perspective. You know, everyone has a different
perspective in life. Everyone has a different perspective when it comes to circumstances
and events that take place in our lives, even in the lives of others. And we begin to
look here and we find even as I've mentioned for the time...
title of the message this evening, Fruitful in the Land of Affliction, we find that here
God gives us some glimpse with regard to the principle of perspective. I believe that it's
revealed to us Joseph, as I mentioned by way of introduction, had been given an Egyptian
name and he had been given an Egyptian bride, yet when his two sons are born he gives them
Hebrew names. And in giving them Hebrew names and understanding the meaning of the names,
we find that it helps us to be able to learn about Joseph's perspective. What is his perspective
with all that he's dealt with, with all that he's endured? The Bible tells us in verse
number 50, and unto Joseph were born two sons before the years of famine came. So in those
first seven years of plenty, we find that Joseph was blessed by the Lord to have two
sons, it says, which Asenath, the daughter of Potipharah, priest of On, bear unto him.
And Joseph called the name of the firstborn Manasseh. Notice what he says when we see
the firstborn that is named here, Manasseh, the name means forgetfulness. It means to
forget. Now it doesn't mean to forget like you forgot what was on your grocery list.
Alright, how many of you ever forget what's on your grocery list? You understand what
I'm saying? And we got so many tools that help us to remember things and yet we seem
to forget things. And I have the opposite problem with a grocery list. I add things
to it. I go down the cookie aisle and I'm like, oh yeah, we need those cookies and we
need ice cream. And Holly says that wasn't on the list, but it just got in the cart somehow,
you understand. But that's not what it means when we're talking about forgetfulness. It's
this purpose of forgetting, this intentional forgetting something. Notice what he says,
For God, said he, hath made me forget all my toil, and all my father's house. Now I
don't believe that he's meaning all of the positive things and the good things because
obviously there's some good things that he learned. He learned about Jehovah God. We
find that even in giving his testimony and standing before Pharaoh and standing before
his brothers as we go through the remainder of Genesis, we find that he continues to give
glory to God. He did not forget the God of his father. He did not forget those truths
that he was given. But I want you to understand that Joseph is saying that this idea of forgetfulness,
that God made me to forget all my toil and my father's house. You know there were a lot
of bad things that happened to Joseph. Right? We've studied them. Hated by your brothers.
I mean to the point where they can't even speak kindly to you. This is a hatred at a
whole nother level. We think about the selling into slavery. I mean they were going to kill
him and then they decided no let's not kill him because we can actually get some money
for him so why don't we sell him into slavery. And even as they had determined that they're
going to put him in that pit so they could kill him, they're sitting there eating. I
mean they have no care or concern whatsoever. And here's the thought tonight when we think
about the principle of perspective. The negatives that are in our past, they must not rob us
of our opportunity for today. See there are some negatives in each of our lives. There
are some negatives in Joseph's life. There were some things that happened to him that
if he determined that that was going to be the focus of his attention, if every day of
his life he was going to just focus upon the fact that my brothers did me wrong, that my
brothers did this and my brothers did that and this is not fair and this is not right,
Joseph would not be second in command. He had to forget that stuff because those negatives
would hinder Joseph from being able to do what God had for him to do. I want you to
think about the principle. Turn to the book of Philippians if you will. Again hold your
spot here in Genesis but turn to the book of Philippians and I want you to look at Philippians
chapter number 3. I want you to think about what Paul says in this portion of scripture
and there's so much rich truth in Philippians chapter number 3. I wish we could study all
of it this evening but I want to draw your attention to some things that Paul says with
regard to even what we find here in the life of Joseph in Genesis chapter 41 when he names
his firstborn Manasseh, the idea of forgetfulness. Notice that Paul says this in verse number
10, I'll start there, that I may know him and the power of his resurrection, the fellowship
of his sufferings being made conformable unto his death. So he reveals to us his desire
to know the Lord in a very intimate way, not just knowing about God but knowing him personally
and intimately. If by any means I might attain unto the resurrection of the dead, not as
though I had already attained, either were already perfect, but I follow after, if then
I may apprehend that for which also I am apprehended of Christ Jesus. And then notice
verse 13, brethren, I count not myself to have apprehended. But this one thing I do,
forgetting those things which are behind, and reaching forth unto those things which
are before, I press toward the mark for the prize of the high calling of God in Christ
Jesus. You know, there are a lot of people today that are crippled because of the things
that happened to them in the past. They're crippled, figuratively speaking, because of
the things that happened to them in the past. They've not forgotten them. They're holding
on to them. They're bothered by them. The Bible teaches in the book of Hebrews the danger
of a root of bitterness. You know what often happens when we cannot forget those negatives
in the past is we get bitter. We get bitter. And bitterness will absolutely destroy you.
It will destroy you. Someone said bitterness will destroy the vessel in which it's stored
more than the vessel in which it's poured. Bitterness will destroy you. Joseph could
have been bitter over the things that happened in his life, over the treatment that he experienced.
I've only focused on his brothers, but think about Mrs. Potiphar as she lied and had him
imprisoned. I mean, you think about Joseph coming into Egypt and all the events that
happened to lead him there. And then he's in the house of Potiphar. And I mean, even
though he's purchased as a slave, I mean, he's pretty successful and he's become the
steward of the house and things are going well. But then Mrs. Potiphar lies about him
and he finds himself in prison. Man, there's some things that he could get bitter about.
Listen, be careful about bitterness. Many people today are crippled because of things
that happened in their past. They just can't get over them. Can I say this? Be careful
about psychologists and psychiatrists. I'm not either one. Anytime I'm asked to give
counsel, I seek to give biblical counsel and I do it often. However, I would say this.
Sometimes they just want to dig up things in the past and never really resolve them.
Never really resolve them. And it can become very dangerous. And what I'm saying to you
this evening is that when we look at this principle of perspective, where's your focus
tonight? What are we focused on? If we just want to focus on the hurt and the harm and
the bad things that happened to us in our past, it will cripple you from doing today
what God has for you to do today. We can't live in the past. We can't change the past.
It doesn't matter how angry we are. It doesn't matter how bitter we are about the things
that happened to us. We cannot change them. Amen? You can't. You can't change them.
As we see the firstborn son, Joseph called his name Manasseh. Forgetfulness. For God
said he hath made me forget all my toil and all my father's house. I believe it's because
of the name of the firstborn that we're able to read of the secondborn. I believe it's
because of the perspective that I'm going to forget those things, the negatives, and
I'm not going to let those hinder me from doing what God has for me. I find that in
the 52nd verse we're told about the secondborn and it says here that he, the name of the
second, called he Ephraim. For God hath caused me to be fruitful in the land of my affliction.
I mean, what a perspective that Joseph has. Listen, he calls it what it is. It's a land
of affliction. We don't have to sugarcoat things. We can call them what they are, but
the reality is that even in the midst of what looks like and as we would look at this
portion of scripture and look at all of the events in the life of Joseph, we could say
yeah that's a land of affliction, but he says, but God made me to be fruitful. And so Ephraim
means fruitfulness. It means fruitfulness. God hath caused him to be fruitful in the
land of his affliction. And I want you to think about being fruitful. God has called
us to be fruitful. Has he not? Turn to the book of John, if you will, John chapter number
15, and I want you to look.
here at the truth of this idea of us as God's people being fruitful people.
We find here that Joseph says, God hath made me, he hath caused me to be fruitful in the
land of my affliction.
What enabled Joseph to be fruitful in the land of his affliction was his perspective
on understanding, as we looked at that firstborn son Manasseh, that forgetfulness.
Man, if he just focused and just stayed on all of that and just determined that's where
he was going to live, he would not be fruitful.
John 15, notice in verse number one, I am the true vine, Jesus is speaking.
My father is the husbandman.
Often Jesus would use illustrations and analogies that people could easily relate to.
And here he's using this very familiar teaching and truth with regard to agriculture, if you
will.
And he says, I am the true vine, and my father is the husbandman.
Every branch in me that beareth not fruit, he taketh away.
And every branch that beareth fruit, he purgeth it, that it may bring forth more fruit.
So who are the branches that are in Jesus?
We are, Christians, disciples, followers of Christ.
Do you track?
You see what's going on?
Listen, he is the true vine.
He'll say in just a little while, I am the vine, ye are the branches.
And he says here, every branch in me, and so we know that we are the branches if we've
trusted Jesus Christ as our personal Savior, we are the branches.
And he says, every branch in me that beareth not fruit, he taketh away.
That's a little bit scary.
You know why?
Because God's purpose is that we'd be fruitful.
What good is a fruit tree if it doesn't produce fruit?
They would understand this.
You've got a fig tree, and it doesn't produce figs.
How long are you going to keep the fig tree around?
Three years, four years, 14 years, 22 years, no, eventually you're going to cut that thing
down and you're going to plant something else because it's not producing fruit, correct?
And the Bible says here, and every branch that beareth fruit, notice it says he purgeth
it.
Now, I'm not an arborist, I'm not an agricultural guru, but I understand, I've done some study
and I understand the picture that Jesus is giving, and I understand the purpose of pruning.
You know what happens when you prune?
You get more fruit.
You've got to cut it back, and when it grows, it produces more fruit.
I pruned these crape myrtles out here a couple of years ago, and some of you are ready to
kill me.
Pastor, you killed the trees.
No, no, I did some research and I did it how they said to do it.
I'm not an arborist, but we didn't pay somebody to do it, and I just chopped them things up,
man.
You know what, Tim?
They came back and they were beautiful.
I mean, they just blossomed and flourished.
Here he says, that every branch that bear fruit, he purgeth it, that it may bring forth.
Notice what it says, more fruit.
Verse 3, now you're clean through the word which I have spoken unto you.
You can look at that in Ephesians 5 and 26 and see the ministry of God's word and cleansing.
Notice verse 4, abide in me and I in you, as the branch cannot bear fruit of itself
except it abide in the vine.
No more can ye except ye abide in me.
The principle of abiding is so critical.
He says, abide in me and I in you, as the branch cannot bear fruit of itself.
We know this.
When Holly first got home from down in North Carolina, the first time when she was here
for the scripture assembly, she arrived home and I had some roses waiting for her.
Amen?
All you husbands take notes and write things down.
I had some roses, I had a card and I had some chocolate.
I tried to cover all those boxes, amen?
And I had it there waiting for her and then she was going to leave to go back to North
Carolina and those roses got put down and guess what happened to those roses?
They died.
Why?
Because they were cut from the vine.
I mean, they were beautiful and then they died.
And I noticed that before she got home, I was going to have to deal with those roses
and I didn't deal with them on the Monday and then Tuesday I said, I got to take care
of that but I had some other things going on and I just kind of left it there and Wednesday
I walked downstairs and I said, what is that smell?
You know what those roses started to do?
They started to stink.
How many of you know roses smell good when they're alive and when they're fresh, right?
But they died and they stunk, I had to throw them away.
We know this but notice Jesus saying this is us.
He wants us to be fruitful.
Joseph says, God hath made me to be fruitful, he hath caused me to be fruitful in the land
of my affliction.
I mean in the difficulties, God hath caused me to be fruitful.
Notice in verse number five, I am the vine, ye are the branches, he that abideth in me
and I in him, the same bringeth forth.
What does it say?
Much fruit, for without me ye can do nothing.
If a man abide not in me, he is cast forth as a branch and is withered.
Men gather them and cast them into the fire and they are burned.
If ye abide in me and my words abide in you, ye shall ask what ye will and it shall be
done unto you.
Notice in verse eight, critical verse of Scripture, herein is my Father glorified that ye bear
much fruit, so shall ye be my disciples.
You know God wants us to be fruitful.
He said to, when he issued that call to the disciples, they're on the Sea of Galilee,
the call to Peter, he says, follow me and I will make you fishers of men.
When we begin to look at John 15 and thinking about this principle of perspective with Joseph
back in Genesis chapter 41, and he says, God hath caused me to be fruitful in the land
of my affliction, and I say God has intended for us as his people to be fruitful people.
And when we bear much fruit, see, it's fruit, more fruit, and much fruit, as you study through
John 15, and he says that if you bear much fruit, he says, herein is my Father glorified
that you bear much fruit.
I want God to be glorified.
So we've got to abide in him, and we have to allow God to work through our lives.
Listen, we cannot hinder what God is seeking to do in our lives today because we're so
focused on the hardships and the difficulties that happened at some time in our past.
Joseph says when Manasseh is born, God has caused me to forget.
God has caused me to be fruitful in the land of my affliction.
Listen, this evening, we're going to face some affliction, some difficulty.
You say, pastor, you're telling me I'm facing it right now.
I understand.
Turn to the book of 1 Thessalonians, if you will.
I want to just journey real quickly through just a few verses of Scripture, and I hope
that this helps us tonight.
We consider the principle of preparation.
God is working to prepare us.
Listen, don't despise the time of preparation.
Don't neglect a season of preparation in your life because we need that.
God's preparing us for something.
You think about this principle of perspective.
Perspective is so important.
In 1 Thessalonians chapter number 3, Paul had already mentioned in chapter 1 how that
they came to them with much difficulty as they brought the gospel, and that was what
they were dealing with.
And if you go back to the book of Acts, you can study and see on that journey all of the
hardship that they faced.
But as you come to the third chapter, notice that the Bible says in verse number 3 that
no man should be moved by these afflictions.
Listen, there were some difficulties that the people in Thessalonica were facing.
There were some persecutions that they were dealing with.
There were some afflictions, and Paul says that no man should be moved by these afflictions.
Listen, God is God, and He's on His throne, and He has a purpose, and even in that time
of affliction, God can use you and can cause you to be fruitful.
He says, knowing for yourselves know that we are appointed thereunto.
Notice in 2 Thessalonians chapter number 1, and then we're going to come back to 1 Thessalonians
because I want you to see the perspective and the opportunity that we can be fruitful
even in the midst of affliction.
In 2 Thessalonians 1 and verse number 4, the Bible says so that we ourselves glory in you
in the churches of God for your patience and faith in all your persecutions and tribulations
that ye endure.
They were suffering.
The church in Thessalonica, the believers, they were dealing with persecution and all
these hardships and things that were taking place, and Paul says that you have patience
and faith in all your persecutions and tribulations that ye endure.
He said in chapter 3 of the first book, he says that no man should be moved by these
afflictions, but I want you to go all the way back to the first chapter of 1 Thessalonians.
First Thessalonians.
And I want you to see that a people,
a church that was facing persecution,
affliction, and difficulty,
that God had allowed them to be fruitful
even in a season of difficulty and affliction.
The Bible says in verse number seven
of First Thessalonians one,
actually back up to verse number four, if you will,
knowing, brethren, beloved, your election of God
for our gospel came not unto you in word only,
but also in power and in the Holy Ghost
and in much assurance, as you know what manner of men
we were among you for your sake.
And ye became followers of us and of the Lord,
having received the word in much affliction
with joy of the Holy Ghost.
Now notice this, so that ye were in samples
to all that believe in Macedonia and Achaia.
Verse number eight, for from you sounded out
the word of the Lord, not only in Macedonia and Achaia,
but also in every place your faith to God
were to spread abroad, so that we need not
to speak anything, for they themselves show of us
what manner of entering in we had unto you,
and how you turned to God from idols
to serve the living and true God.
The church at Thessalonica had a great testimony.
I've said this over the years, there's no perfect church,
but the church at Thessalonica is a model church.
And as you study through the two epistles
to the Thessalonians, you find that they're a model church,
and here Paul is saying at this last part
of chapter number one, that even though
they had dealt with affliction,
and even though they had dealt with this persecution,
these persecutions and tribulations,
and all that they were dealing with,
that they were still fruitful, for notice it says,
for from you, in verse number eight,
sounded out the word of the Lord,
not only in Macedonia and Achaia,
but also in every place your faith to God
were to spread abroad, so that we need not
to speak anything.
It's almost as if Paul is saying,
we go to share the gospel in a region,
but you've already shared the gospel there.
Now think about that for a moment.
In the midst of their affliction,
and their persecution, and their difficulties,
and all they were dealing with,
they were still sending out the truth of the gospel,
they were still doing what they were seeking
to be fruitful, God was using them to be fruitful,
even in a time, a season of affliction.
I've heard many testimonies over the years
of people that have dealt with great hardships,
be it physical or otherwise,
and they share testimonies of,
in that season of great difficulty and of affliction,
how God used them to be able to share the gospel
with someone, and they got saved.
That's amazing to me, that God would work in that manner.
See, this evening, we think about
the principle of preparation,
it's important that we understand,
and we go through that season of preparation,
for God has a purpose and a plan for us.
And when he's ready to open that door,
did we get all the preparation we were supposed to get?
Are we ready to do what God has for us to do?
See, because when the opportunity arises,
that's not time to prepare, that's time to do.
Does that make sense?
But then the principle of perspective,
what do we focus on?
Do we focus on how bad things are?
How terrible, how we were wronged,
and how this happened and that happened,
and I just can't imagine this person didn't do this,
or this person didn't say hi to me,
and this person, I mean, we get mad about silly things.
Seriously, honestly.
Somebody came to me about five weeks ago and said,
Pastor, are you mad at me?
I said, no, why would I be mad at you?
Well, you didn't say hi to me last week.
I'm very sorry.
And it was a great conversation, everything was resolved.
But what I'm saying is that,
it wasn't that I didn't say hi because I was mad,
we had a problem with the sound thing,
my lapel wasn't working, and I was back there
trying to get things fixed up,
and working with whatever was going on,
and I think it wasn't my lapel, it was my iPad.
Because Joseph says, you just need to get a new one.
But the reality is that sometimes the devil
can use super little things to just mess us up.
Seriously.
And what's our perspective?
Listen, Joseph had a whole lot of bad things.
He said, God, he calls me to forget.
And therefore, God's called me to be fruitful
in the land of affliction.
See, sometimes we're in the land of affliction
when it's a time of great distress and just difficulty,
and we think that means that we have a pass
to just kind of do nothing.
Well, I got all this stuff going on,
and God understands, and it's just,
woe is me, pity party.
Joseph said, God, let me be fruitful.
God hath called me to be fruitful
in the land of my affliction.
I don't know tonight what everyone is dealing with,
but I know we have a God who if we keep our attention
and our perspective on him,
that even in the midst of difficulty and affliction,
he can cause us to be fruitful.
He can use us for his honor and for his glory.
There's a world that was directly impacted
because of Joseph's faithfulness and fruitfulness.
People's lives were spared
because there was a great famine that was coming,
and because Joseph understood the preparation,
Joseph had a right perspective.
When the opportunity came, God used him.
God calls me to be fruitful.
Tonight, I hope that God would help us
to have that perspective that Joseph had,
that we'd understand the preparation
that God is taking us through.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you that you're God,
and though at times we don't understand
all that's taking place, we can trust you.
We can rest in you.
God, help us to understand the seasons of preparation
that you would guide and lead us through,
and I pray that in those moments of preparation
that you would help us to get all
that we're supposed to get,
that we would be prepared for the opportunities
that you present us with.
I think about this perspective of Joseph
and the principle that we see here,
the naming of his two sons,
and God, I pray that you'd help us to look to Jesus,
the author and finisher of our faith,
help us to have an eternal perspective,
not a temporal perspective,
help us to not focus upon those things that are hurtful,
but God, help us to focus on you
and how you can cause us to be fruitful,
even in the land of affliction.
I pray that tonight you would move and work
in hearts and lives as only you can.
I pray, Lord, that we would not only see
the life of Joseph recorded for us,
but we would apply truth in our lives
that would cause us to be used in like manner.
We give you the glory for all that you'll do,
for it's in Christ's name we pray.