chapter tonight, Genesis 48, it's only 22 verses,
and this is message number 97 through the book of Genesis,
and we are near the very end,
and chapter 49 and then chapter 50.
I do not believe that I will be able to get
through chapter 49 in one message,
it's probably gonna take two,
and then probably two for chapter 50 as well,
but we are nearing the end,
and I have been praying about where to go
on Sunday evenings for our new series,
it's been a long time that we've been
in the book of Genesis, and obviously message 97,
but also we had some other things going on
on Sunday evenings, different periods of time,
I did a period of time where we did
Ask the Pastor on Sunday night, and what have you,
and so it's been a number of years
that we've been sending through the book of Genesis,
and by the way, let me say this,
I'm thankful for, we heard testimonies tonight,
Brother Mark and Brother Isaac,
they both said about God's word,
I'm thankful for Genesis to Revelation, amen,
and all God's word is profitable,
the Bible says all scripture is given
by inspiration of God, and is profitable
in the context of 2 Timothy chapter number three,
we know that Paul says to Timothy,
and that from a child thou hast known the holy scriptures,
what's he talking about, he's talking about
the Old Testament, which are able
to make thee wise unto salvation,
and what a blessing, Paul says to the folks
in Rome, to the people in Corinth,
that God's word, that which was written aforetime,
was written for our learning, written for our admonition,
and I am thankful for the Old Testament,
God gives us very important principles,
and I am thankful for those principles,
and what a blessing to have God's word.
In Genesis chapter 47, we spent two weeks
looking at that portion of scripture,
and through Genesis 47, we learn
that God used Joseph to take care of his family,
and of course, we know that Jacob was called for by Joseph
as the brothers went back with the goods,
and said, Joseph is alive, and he said to return,
and we find that as they were preparing to depart,
that God appeared to Jacob in chapter number 46,
and said, go, and I'll be with thee,
and in that place, I will build of thee a great nation,
and we find that God was doing just that,
and we read of that in chapter 47,
we learned how God provided for his people,
they received a place, and they received the best place,
according to Genesis 47,
and we find that not only did they have a place,
but they received provision,
and they had their needs taken care of,
I'm thankful that as our shepherd,
that God gives us all that we need,
he provides for us, he is a good God,
he is a good shepherd, and I'm thankful for that.
We find, the Bible tells us, there in Genesis 47,
the end of the chapter, in verse 28,
that Jacob lived there in Egypt for 17 years.
As we enter into Genesis chapter 48,
we find that the text of scripture begins
by informing us that Jacob is sick,
we find that this sickness that is mentioned
is obviously a serious situation,
for upon hearing of the news,
Joseph gets a word of the circumstances of the situation,
he gets his two boys, Ephraim and Manasseh,
or Manasseh and Ephraim, oldest youngest,
we find that he gets his two sons,
and he heads over, I would say this,
to have a visit with his dad.
We find that the text of scripture,
the details of this meeting,
are provided here in Genesis 48.
I'll begin reading in verse number one,
the Bible says this, and it came to pass
after these things, after those 17 years
in which they were there in Egypt,
that one told Joseph, notice the message,
behold, thy father is sick,
and he, Joseph, took with him his two sons,
Manasseh and Ephraim, and one told Jacob
and said, behold, thy son Joseph cometh unto thee,
and Israel strengthened himself and sat upon the bed.
We'll read the entirety of the text this evening,
but I wanna give you, you know, it's amazing,
the Bible is an awesome book, it's a living book,
and I said this this morning,
but I'll say it again this evening,
the best commentary on the Bible is the Bible.
I don't know who originally coined that phrase,
I know that I heard Clarence Sexton say that
a number of times during his ministry,
but the Bible is an awesome book,
it's a living book, it is God's word,
and I want you to hold your place here in Genesis 48,
but take with me just for a moment
over to Hebrews chapter number 11.
In Hebrews chapter number 11,
God gives us just a simple verse of scripture
that really in this simple verse of scripture,
I believe that great light is shed
upon the meeting that we read of in Genesis 48,
and we find that in Hebrews chapter 11,
many of us would refer to this passage of scripture
as the great hall of faith, if you will,
and we read of all of the great things
that were accomplished, and we find that in verse 21,
notice what the Bible says in Hebrews 11 and verse 21,
by faith Jacob, when he was a dying,
blessed both the sons of Joseph.
That's what we're talking about in Genesis 48,
that is, Genesis 48 is the record
of what is being referred to here
in Hebrews chapter 11 and verse 21,
when Jacob is going to die
and he blesses the two sons of Joseph.
The other blessings are recorded in Genesis 49
for the other sons, but the sons of Joseph in chapter 48,
notice this next phrase that says,
and worshiped, and worshiped,
leaning upon the top of his staff.
Why did he have a staff?
Because he wrestled with the Lord one night
and God touched his thigh, right?
And I believe that for the rest of his days, he had a limp.
And he remembered, I preached on this
when we dealt with that passage of scripture,
but it really comes up again
as we look at this tonight in Genesis 48,
and so we see that he's leaning upon his staff,
and it's not just because of his old age,
it's not just because of the health circumstances
that are leading to his death
that we're speaking of in Genesis 48,
but we find that he had that staff for a long time,
and it was a reminder of an event
that took place in his life,
but I want you to see also that in Hebrews 11, verse 21,
it says that he worshiped, that he worshiped.
Now, I like that, I was beginning
as I was preparing this week
and looking through this portion of scripture in Genesis 48,
and I was reminded of Hebrews 11,
and I'm thinking as I'm reading through the context,
turn back to Genesis 48, if you will,
and as you're reading through the context,
if you're not careful, you can look at Genesis 48
and just look at a meeting between a father and a son,
and two grandsons, and you can look at a discussion,
an interaction that's taking place,
but indeed, God says he worshiped, he worshiped.
By the way, God is worthy of our worship.
He alone is to be worshiped.
The word worship means chiefly and eminently
the act of paying divine honors to the supreme being.
Of course, we know that is our Lord and Savior.
I'm so thankful that the God of the universe is my father.
Isn't that awesome?
You think about that, our heavenly father,
the God of the universe, the one who said,
"'Let there be light,' and there was light."
And we find that in Genesis 48,
as God gives us the record of this interaction
and the people that are there,
the setting, the conversation,
but the Bible says that he worshiped.
Keep that in mind as we go through the text this evening.
I've titled the message really here in verse number 14.
The Bible says, in Israel,
Jacob stretched out his right hand
and laid it upon Ephraim's head,
who was the younger, and his left hand upon Manasseh's head.
Notice it says, guiding his hands wittingly,
for Manasseh was the firstborn.
And I've just titled the message,
Jacob guided his hands wittingly.
As we look at this portion of scripture,
I want you to notice a few thoughts this evening.
Number one, notice his praise.
Notice the praise of Jacob in this text of scripture.
We find that Joseph arrives,
Jacob is told that Joseph is coming,
and it says that Israel, in the end of verse number two,
that he strengthened himself and sat upon the bed.
And notice in verse three,
this is where we begin to see the praise of Jacob.
It says, and Jacob said unto Joseph,
notice how he's praising the Lord,
and by the way, praise is part of worship.
We find that the Bible says that Jacob says to Joseph,
God Almighty appeared unto me at Luz,
and the land of Canaan, notice what he says,
and blessed me.
And, notice verse number four,
and said unto me, behold, I will make thee fruitful,
and multiply thee, and I will make of thee
a multitude of people, and will give this land
to thy seed after thee for an everlasting possession.
And so we find that in verse number three and four,
that Jacob, Israel, as he's meeting with his son
and his grandsons, as he's nearing the end of his life,
he's going to die, the Bible says that this meeting begins
with praise.
That Jacob is looking back to the past,
he's looking at what God has done for him,
and how God has worked in his life.
He says, God appeared to me.
he says, God blessed me, he said, God has promised me.
Notice, if you will, in verse number 15,
the Bible says this after he guides his hands
wittingly in verse 14, the Bible says in verse 15,
and he blessed Joseph and said,
God, before whom my fathers Abraham and Isaac did walk,
the God, notice what he says,
which fed me all my life long unto this day.
You know what Jacob's doing?
He's recognizing the blessings of God.
He is praising the Lord.
He's taking the opportunity.
And by the way, our kids ought to hear us praise God, amen.
Our grandkids ought to hear us.
If you have children,
if you are blessed to have grandchildren,
they ought to hear you praise the Lord.
They ought to know that God is real in your life.
They ought to know that God's answering prayer,
that God's working and what God has done.
Listen, the kids in our church,
they need to hear it from their parents
and from their grandparents,
but they need to hear it from other church members.
The Bible speaks of in the book of Titus
about the aged women and the aged men
and the roles and the responsibilities
and how we invest in that next generation
and they're able to see that our God is real
and our God works and our God, he is worthy of our praise.
And we find this evening that is,
I want you to think about Joseph and Manasseh and Ephraim
entering into the presence of Jacob.
These grandsons of Jacob, of Israel's grandsons,
these boys were born in Egypt.
All they knew was Egypt.
In just a few moments, we're gonna continue to read,
we find that really what Jacob does
is he adopts these boys as his own
for the purpose of the blessing that he's going to give.
But I want you to recognize that as Jacob
is speaking to his boys, to his son and to his grandsons,
he wants them to know the God of the universe.
He says, notice how he begins.
He says to Joseph, but the boys are there.
Now, I understand that Jacob,
as we go through the text of scripture,
he actually is not fully aware
that the boys are there for this meeting.
He finds out a little bit later.
His eyesight, he cannot see, all right?
So he's told that Joseph is there,
but I want you to think about what Manasseh and Ephraim heard.
God Almighty, God Almighty appeared to me.
God promised me, he blessed me.
God has taken care of me, he has provided for me.
It's important for a next generation
to know how God has provided for us.
Listen, I understand that God has given many people
a good career and a good opportunity
and so on and so forth, but we better recognize
that it's God's hand of blessing, amen?
Deuteronomy says it's God
that gives you the ability to get wealth.
And we better recognize that it's not just in our ability
and our talents, no, God gave us those talents
and those abilities, he gave us those opportunities,
and we find that Jacob says that God fed me
all my life long unto this day.
I mean, those are good lessons for Joseph
and for Manasseh and Ephraim as he's praising the Lord,
as he's worshiping here in this meeting
with Joseph and his boys.
We see the praise, I've said this
for my second thought this evening, his present.
We see that really the praise is dealing with the past,
but notice in the present what's taking place.
In verse number five, it says, and now thy two sons,
thy two sons, Ephraim and Manasseh,
which were born unto thee in the land of Egypt
before I came unto thee into Egypt,
notice what he says, they are mine.
As Reuben and Simeon, they, speaking of Manasseh and Ephraim,
they shall be mine.
And thy issue, which thou begettest after them,
shall be thine and shall be called
after the name of their brethren in their inheritance.
You know, when they divide the land,
there's the tribe of Manasseh and the tribe of Ephraim,
because Jacob says they are mine.
He adopts them.
But notice as it continues, he says in verse number seven,
as for me, when I came from Paddan,
Rachel died by me in the land of Cana in the way,
when yet there was but a little way to come unto Ephrath,
and I buried her there in the way of Ephrath,
the same as Bethlehem.
And Israel beheld Joseph's sons and said, who are these?
He could not see, we're gonna see that in a moment.
In verse nine, Joseph said unto his father,
they are my sons, whom God hath given me in this place.
And he said, bring them, I pray thee unto me,
and I will bless them.
And so it's very interesting,
Jacob is saying the things about Manasseh and Ephraim
really without having the visual understanding
that they're there present.
He's not saying what he said in the previous verses
just because of their presence.
He's saying it because he's prophesying
about what will be.
And we find that now he says, the boys,
he says, bring them to me.
In verse number 10, now the eyes of Israel were dim for age
so that he could not see.
And he brought them near unto him
and he kissed them and embraced them.
Can you imagine in your mind's eye that setting?
I think that's a sweet moment
just a human relationship type of moment.
But notice the Bible says in verse number 11,
and Israel said unto Joseph,
notice what he says when he's rejoicing again
with regard to his present,
he speaks as we think about his praise
with regard to the past and what God has done,
but God was still working and blessing.
In verse 11, Israel said unto Joseph,
I had not thought to see thy face.
No doubt, Jacob had no thought
that he would ever see Joseph again.
In his mind, Joseph was dead.
He'd been told a story.
He'd been led to believe a lie.
The brothers bring back a coat of many colors
that was dipped in blood
and simply said, do you know whose this is?
They were certain that Jacob would be able
to recognize that coat of many colors.
And Joseph, the owner of that coat,
the one that Jacob had bestowed that coat upon,
he says, Joseph, no doubt as rent in pieces
an evil beast hath devoured him.
And he had no thought that he would ever see his son again.
And he says in verse number 11, notice,
think about the praise and the setting.
He said, I had not thought to see thy face
and lo, God hath showed me also thy seed.
Not only has God blessed me to be able
to see you, my son, again,
but I've had the opportunity to see your children.
Now remember, he was there for 17 years.
This is when he's sick and he's going to die.
I don't know, the Bible does not record for us
those 17 years, the details of any interactions
between Joseph and Jacob and his family.
We have no idea, God doesn't give us all of that,
but we find that for 17 years, Jacob lived in Egypt.
And Jacob says, I didn't think I'd see you
and God's been so good to me to allow me
not only to see your face again,
but to see grandchildren.
That's a blessing.
And again, Jacob is recognizing God.
He's worshiping the Lord.
I want you to notice as we continue reading
throughout the end of the chapter, his prophecy.
We see the prophecy, the blessing, if you will,
in verse number 12, the Bible says that Joseph
brought them out from between his knees
and he bowed himself with his face to the earth
and Joseph took them both, Ephraim in his right hand
toward Israel's left hand, Manasseh in his left hand
toward Israel's right hand and brought them near unto him.
And so in your mind's eye this evening,
if you could picture that Jacob is here
and Joseph is here and Joseph's going to present
his two sons to his father.
And Jacob is sitting, the Bible said that he got himself,
he strengthened himself and got on the side of the bed there
and the Bible says that Jacob is there
and so his left is here, his right is here,
but Joseph takes Ephraim and he puts Ephraim
to the left hand of Jacob.
And he puts Manasseh to the right hand of Jacob.
Now why is that?
Well, because the right hand in that culture
would signify the blessing.
And we find that the Bible tells us
that as Joseph put them in that position,
remember, Jacob could not see.
So Joseph takes it upon himself to put the boys
in the order in which he believes they are to be.
And the Bible says in verse 14,
and Israel stretched out his right hand.
And notice it says that he laid it upon Ephraim's head.
So he does like this, he doesn't go like this,
he goes like this.
And then the Bible says, who was the younger
in his left hand upon Manasseh's head.
So he has his hands like this.
And we find that the Bible says,
guiding his hands wittingly.
For Manasseh was the firstborn.
So Manasseh's directly across from his right hand,
but that's not the one that's received the blessing.
It's Ephraim that's to receive the blessing.
And we find that it says that he guided his hand.
This was not some mistake.
In fact, Joseph, if you look, it says in verse 15,
and he blessed Joseph and said,
God, before whom my fathers, Abraham and Isaac, did walk,
the God which fed me all my life long until this day,
the angel which redeemed me from all evil,
bless the lads and let my name be named on them
in the name of my fathers, Abraham and Isaac,
and let them grow into the multitude
in the midst of the earth.
Do you see, remember, in verse number four,
he said, they're mine, I'm adopting them, they are mine.
And we find that he says, let my name,
in the name, let my name be named on them.
That they would understand that they're not Egyptians.
Right, that's what he's saying.
They're Hebrews, they're to be my descendants,
and Jacob's name changed to Israel.
And we find that it says in verse 16,
that it says that let them grow into a multitude
in the midst of the earth.
And when Joseph saw that his father laid his right hand
upon the head of Ephraim, it displeased him.
And he held up his father's hand to remove it
from Ephraim's head into Manasseh's head.
And Joseph said to his father, not so, my father,
for this is the firstborn,
put thy right hand upon his head, in verse 18.
So we find that Joseph is standing here,
he puts the sons out in the order
in which he believes it's to be.
And we find that after Jacob is blessing the boys,
and Joseph recognizes, no, no, no, you have it wrong.
And he's gonna try to remove the hand
and put them in the right place.
Notice the Bible says in verse 19, and his father refused.
Notice what he says, he says, I know it, my son.
I know it.
He also shall become a people, and he also shall be great.
But truly, his younger brother shall be greater than he.
And his seed shall become a multitude of nations.
It says in verse 20, and he blessed them that day,
saying, in thee shall Israel bless,
saying, God make thee as Ephraim and as Manasseh.
And he set Ephraim before Manasseh.
And Israel said unto Joseph, behold, I die,
but God shall be with you and bring you again
unto the land of your fathers.
Moreover, I have given to thee one portion
above thy brethren, which I took out of the hand
of the Amorite with my sword and with my bow.
As we look at this prophecy, if you will, the blessing,
we find that the younger Ephraim shall be greater,
and we find that he, Jacob, was guiding his hands wittingly.
He is in this position.
Remember, we spoke about the original praise,
and he's speaking about the past and the present,
but then we see the prophecy,
and he's prophesying about what will be.
He has confidence in the God that he serves
as to what God is going to do.
And we find that it's certainly true.
If you turn to the book of Numbers, Numbers chapter one,
notice what the Bible tells us in Numbers one.
Numbers chapter one, I want you to see a couple of things.
We'll look in chapter one and two,
but in Numbers chapter one, notice in verse number 33.
Numbers one and verse 33, it says,
those that were numbered of them,
even of the tribe of Ephraim, were 40,500.
Now, that's the tribe of Ephraim.
He's the younger, but he was the one
that was to receive the blessing,
and we find that it says that it was 40,500.
In verse 34, the children of Manasseh,
by their generations, after their families,
by the house of their fathers,
according to the number of their names,
from 20 years old and upward,
all that were able to go forth to war,
those that were numbered of them,
even of the tribe of Manasseh, were 32,200.
So 32,200, a difference of 8,300.
Ephraim has the larger tribe.
In chapter number two, in verse number 18,
Israel and their camp and how they would be set up
is outlined for us in Numbers chapter two,
as they would be set up around the tabernacle,
and we find that in verse number 18,
it talks about the west side, and notice what it says.
On the west side shall be the standard
of the camp of Ephraim, according to their armies,
and the captain of the sons of Ephraim
shall be Elishamah, the son of Amahud,
and his host, and those that were numbered of them
were 40,500, and by him shall be the tribe of Manasseh,
and the captain of the children of Manasseh
shall be Gamaliel, the son of Padazar,
and his host, and those that were numbered of them
were 32,200, and also it was the tribe of Benjamin
that would be there on the west side.
But again, we find that even as you look
at this prophecy from Jacob in Genesis chapter 48,
and the blessing that is given,
we find certainly that Manasseh would not have the place,
though he was the firstborn, it would be Ephraim
that received that blessing.
We go through all of this, and we find this evening
that as Jacob is looking, as we look through
this text of scripture, and look at the interaction,
but when we couple it with the truth
of Hebrews 11 and verse 21, we find that throughout
this interaction, Jacob worshiped, he worshiped.
As I begin to think about Jacob worshiping,
I believe that really we could look at it in three phases
as I've already mentioned as we've gone through
the thoughts this evening, but Jacob worshiped God
for what he did, for what God did.
Jacob worshiped God, he praised God for what God was doing,
and then he also worshiped because of what God will do.
Begin to think about our own lives,
and begin to think about worship
and the importance of worship,
and I said this on Wednesday evening,
and I've said it before from the pulpit
that not all that's called worship today is truly worship.
A lot of places around the country today
that had a service at a place that they called church
and said that they were worshiping,
but I would say to you that it really wasn't
biblical worship, see because God is a spirit,
according to John chapter number four,
and they that worship him must worship him
in spirit and in truth.
You think about the Old Testament,
what a great picture God gives us in the Old Testament.
The people of Israel could not just decide
to approach God any way they chose to.
They had to approach God on God's terms.
They had to approach God God's way.
God prescribed the way for his people
to approach him and to worship him,
and when they did not follow the prescribed way,
it was met with judgment.
In fact, there were times in which you find
even in the Old Testament when the people of God,
the children of Israel, sought to worship God,
but their heart wasn't right with God.
You know what God says of those outward expressions?
He says, I don't want them.
Don't bring your offerings, don't do, why?
Because your heart is far from me.
See, God knows our heart, God knows,
and when we gather together for worship
and we speak about worship and the importance of worship,
I want you to look at a couple of passages with me
and consider the importance of worship,
and as the Bible tells us in Hebrews 11,
that in this setting, Jacob worshiped.
What was he doing?
He was acknowledging God.
You know, sometimes what happens if we're not careful
is we can get to the end of our life
or even in the midst of our life,
not even being in Jacob's position
of being at the end of his life,
but we can be in the middle of our life
at some point in our life,
and we can try to tell other people how good we are
and how, man, how we've made it
in all of these successes that we've had in our lives,
and look at my life and look what I've accomplished.
But Jacob, he says, let me tell you what God has done.
Let me tell you how God met with me.
Let me tell you how God blessed me.
Let me tell you how God promised me.
Let me tell you how God provided for me.
Let me explain to you what I expect God to continue to do.
Why?
Because God always honors his word.
He always does what he says he's going to do.
Turn over, if you will, to 2 Chronicles.
I want you to see a passage of scripture
in 2 Chronicles 29,
and it's a period of time in Israel's history
where they have revival under the ministry,
really the leadership, Hezekiah is the king of Judah
at this particular time in Judah's history.
We find that they have revival during his reign as king.
It's not the only time we find
that Judah had revival.
They had revival during the time of Jehoshaphat.
They had revival during the time of Josiah.
But we see here in Hezekiah's reign,
it's very interesting what happens.
And as we begin to,
we're just jumping right in the middle
of a passage of scripture
and how they were cleansing the house of the Lord
and all that they did.
And the Bible begins to talk about this revival.
And I want you to pick it up with me
in 2 Chronicles 29.
And I want you to see what God's people did
and how they worship.
The Bible says in verse 28,
and all the congregation worshiped
and the singers sang.
You know, singing is part of worship.
Singing is part of worship.
When we sing, we're not trying to bring
any kind of acknowledgement, recognition to ourselves.
No, the real true heart of those that are singing
ought to be to worship our God,
to sing praise.
He's unto His name.
The Bible says that we're to sing
and to make a joyful noise unto the Lord.
We find that the Bible says that they were singing,
they worshiped and the singer sang
and the trumpeters sounded.
Amen?
I told Tim this morning,
we've not had the trumpet for a couple of weeks.
And I said to Tim, I said,
man, it was good to hear the trumpet this morning.
Amen?
I enjoy that.
I get to hear it more than all of you
because I sit right in front of them
and that thing's pointing right at me,
but I love it.
I play the trumpet.
I don't play it that well.
I quit playing it for a lot of years.
And I said to Tim just a couple of weeks ago,
I better start getting back to it
because he's gonna be leaving soon
and we gotta have a trumpet
because I've gotten used to it.
Somebody else wants to learn how to play the trumpet,
please let me know
and we'll give you that opportunity.
Amen?
But it says that the trumpeters sounded
and all this continued notice
until the burnt offering was finished.
And when they had made an end of offering,
listen, you know when we give an offering to the Lord,
we're worshiping God.
The time of our service,
when we have our time of passing and offering play,
understand with me this evening
that that's part of worship.
It's part of worship.
I know that there's a lot of people
that send a lot of criticisms to church
and to Christians that they just want our money.
Has nothing to do with that.
It's a matter of worship
and it's a matter of obedience is what it is.
And what a blessing to be able to worship the Lord,
to give back to him a portion of what he's blessed us with.
The time of offering,
and I hope you can understand this,
I've sat in services over the years,
it really has always bothered me.
We've not had it much here because of,
well, I'm the pastor,
and so therefore I don't behave this way
and I don't really invite guest speakers to come
that would behave this way.
But I remember seeing for years
while I was in Bible college
and serving in other ministries,
where guest speakers would come in
and during the entire song service and offering,
they'd just be sitting there talking.
It just drives me crazy.
Because then you're gonna get up and preach
or they'd be working on their sermon.
Listen, man, you had yesterday to work on your sermon.
And last week, and most of the evangelists,
if anyone's gonna watch it tonight,
they preach the same sermon over and over, amen?
I'm just teasing, just teasing.
But the reality is that it's not a time for talking.
It's not a time for, no, no, it's worship.
It's worship.
I don't wanna miss the singing.
I enjoy the singing, why?
Because the singing prepares my heart.
It's an act of worship, but it's also preparatory.
And we find that as we look here in the offering time,
what a blessing to be able to give back to God.
It says, the king and all that were present with him
bowed themselves and worshiped.
Verse 30, moreover, Hezekiah the king and the princes
commanded the Levites to sing praise unto the Lord
with the words of David and of Asaph the seer.
And they sang praises with gladness
and they bowed their heads and worshiped.
I believe that it was done decently and in order.
In fact, we understand that the New Testament tells us
that our God is a God of order.
He is not the author of confusion.
He's a God of order.
And we're to worship Him orderly, decently in an order.
We find that here in 2 Chronicles,
there's a great revival during Hezekiah's time.
And we see how they're worshiping the Lord.
He's worthy of our worship.
I want you to notice over in Malachi, if you will,
and we're gonna get our way over to the New Testament
here in just a moment.
But look at Malachi with me just for a moment.
Malachi chapter one.
Notice what the Bible says in Malachi chapter one.
In verse number six.
Malachi chapter one, verse number six.
Last book of the Old Testament
just before the Gospel of Matthew.
Malachi chapter number one, verse number six.
A son honoreth his father and a servant his master.
If then I be a father, where is mine honor?
If I be a master, where is my fear?
Sayeth the Lord of hosts unto you,
O priest that despise my name.
And you say, wherein have we despised thy name?
Notice what he says,
ye offer polluted bread upon mine altar.
And ye say, wherein have we polluted thee?
In that you say, the table of the Lord is contemptible.
Notice in verse eight,
if you offer the blind for sacrifice, is it not evil?
And if you offer the lame and sick, is it not evil?
So there was prescribed,
in the book of Leviticus, there's a prescribed order
of what type of animals to be brought for a sacrifice.
And here what's happening is saying,
listen, are you gonna bring a blind or a lame?
What would be the significance?
Well, that one is not of any profit or benefit to me,
so I'm just gonna offer that to the Lord.
No, no, we're to take our best to the Lord, amen.
Notice what he says in verse number eight.
He says, offer it now unto thy governor.
Will he be pleased with thee?
Or accept thy person, sayeth the Lord of hosts.
I mean, that's convicting.
He's saying, you're trying to bring me these offerings
and saying that you're worshiping,
but you're not bringing them the way
that you're supposed to.
You don't bring me a blind or a lame.
Offer it to your governor, are they gonna accept it?
The answer is obvious, no.
By the way, most of them wouldn't have brought that
to the governor.
It would be shameful to do such things.
But yet they'd bring it to God.
I'm thankful as you look through
and understand in verse 14, notice what God says.
We've skipped some verses here, but it says this.
Well, let me read verse 11.
For from the rising of the sun,
even under the going down of the same,
that my name shall be great among the Gentiles.
And every place in sin shall be offering to my name
and a pure offering.
For my name shall be great among the heathen,
sayeth the Lord of hosts.
In verse 14, see they had profaned it.
Verse 14, though, notice it says,
but cursed be the deceiver,
which hath in his flock a male,
and voweth and sacrifices unto the Lord a corrupt thing.
Notice where he says, for I am a great king,
sayeth the Lord of hosts,
and my name is dreadful among the heathen.
He's worthy of our best.
He really is.
And we find that the book of Revelation
gives us a glimpse into worship in heaven.
One day we're gonna get to heaven.
I don't know when it's gonna be,
but one day we're gonna get to heaven.
Revelation chapter four and five,
give us a little taste, if you will,
a little view into the throne room of heaven.
We find in Revelation four and five,
there's gonna be a lot of worship going on.
And I know, I think it was Brother Meshon,
he said it maybe one of the last times he was here,
he said that we ought to prepare for it now
because we're gonna worship God forever,
and so we ought to get used to it now.
And again, worship isn't running around,
loud music, dark lights, smoke, all this kind of nonsense.
I talked about some stuff on Wednesday evening
that they did in a number of churches around America
on Super Bowl Sunday.
It's absolutely blasphemous what they were doing.
Kicking Bibles around the stage.
Are you kidding me?
Literally said, as they opened up a service,
and by the way, the preachers came out through a tunnel
with smoke coming up like they were some kind of celebrity.
What in the world?
Blasphemous.
There was a man dressed as a referee,
and here's the thing that was amazing,
they're all dressed, not their best,
but you know what was happening?
The commentators, quote unquote,
they're in suits and ties.
Isn't that interesting?
They're in suits and ties,
and then these folks come out,
and they say to the pastor,
they're gonna do a coin flip,
and they say this, quote,
do you want to kick or receive the Bible?
I can't even imagine saying those words.
I'm simply quoting them.
The pastor said, I'll receive it,
and they literally set up like a kickoff on the platform
and kick the Bible across the stage.
Unbelievable.
That's not worship.
That is not worship.
Our God is to be worshiped.
Listen, it's not about the size of a crowd.
The people in those auditoriums were going crazy.
Looked just like the people in the stadiums,
to be honest with you.
You know what those people were worshiping?
Not the creator God,
they were worshiping an idol.
Right?
In the stadiums, they're worshiping an idol.
That's what they're doing.
Bring that stuff into the house of God.
Crazy.
The house of God is the pillar and ground of truth.
Amen?
If I ever say we're gonna have a Super Bowl thing,
just fire me.
I mean, seriously.
The reality is that when we approach a holy God,
we approach him on his terms,
and we approach him his way.
He is a thrice holy God.
He is to be reverenced.
He's to be honored and to be glorified.
He's to be worshiped.
I don't know if you've ever heard somebody say, when I see God, you're not going to do
anything but fall on your face.
I want to know who...no, no, no, no, no, no.
Change your thinking.
You're going to simply fall on His face, in His presence, and He's worthy.
Revelation 4, notice in verse number 10, the 4 and 20 elders represented of the church
fall down before Him that sat on the throne and worship Him that liveth forever and ever.
And cast their crowns before the throne, saying, Thou art worthy, O Lord, to receive glory
and honor and power, for Thou hast created all things, and for Thy pleasure they are
and were created.
Chapter 5, and I saw in the right hand of Him that sat on the throne a book written
within and on the back side, sealed with seven seals.
And I saw a strong angel proclaiming with a loud voice, Who is worthy to open the book
and to loose the seals thereof?
And no man in heaven nor in earth, neither under the earth, was able to open the book,
neither to look thereon.
And I wept much.
Why?
Because no man was found worthy to open and read the book, neither to look thereon.
And one of the elders said unto me, Weep not.
Behold, the Lion of the tribe of Judah, the Root of David, hath prevailed to open the
book and to loose the seven seals thereof.
And I beheld, and lo, in the midst of the throne and on the four beasts, in the midst
of the elders, stood a Lamb as it had been slain, having seven horns and seven eyes,
which are the seven spirits of God, sent forth into all the earth.
And He came and took the book out of the right hand of Him that sat upon the throne.
And when He had taken the book, the four beasts and four and twenty elders fell down
before the Lamb, having every one of them harps and golden vials full of odors, which
are the prayers of saints.
Notice verse 9, and they sung a new song, saying, Thou art worthy to take the book and
to open the seals thereof, for Thou wast slain and hast redeemed us to God by Thy blood out
of every kindred and tongue and people and nation, and hast made us unto our God kings
and priests, and we shall reign on the earth.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was ten thousand times ten thousand, and thousands
of thousands, saying with a loud voice, Worthy is the Lamb that was slain to receive power
and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
And every creature which is in heaven and on the earth and under the earth and such
are as in the sea, and all that are in them, heard I saying, Blessing and honor and glory
and power be unto Him that sitteth upon the throne and unto the Lamb forever and ever.
And the four beasts said, Amen.
The four and twenty elders fell down and worshipped Him that liveth forever and ever.
Fourteen verses in chapter five, but man, what a scene.
We're going to be there.
Hallelujah.
Listen, we're going to worship Him.
But you don't have to wait until then to worship God.
Worship in a, if you just read Genesis 48, it just seems like a meeting between a father
and a son and a couple of grandsons.
And yes, he's talking about what God has done and the past and what He's doing in the present,
what He's going to do in the future, but Hebrew says that He worshipped this evening.
We need to worship our God.
He is worthy of worship.
He alone is to be worshipped.
Our children and our children's children, a generation that would rise after us need
to see that we're worshipping God.
We worship Him because of what He's done.
You know, He's done some amazing things, He really has.
We worship Him because of what He's doing.
I know that it's a dark hour that we live in, but God's still working.
God's still on His throne.
People are still getting saved.
God's still at work.
We need to worship Him for what He's doing and then, oh, we can worship Him knowing what
He's going to do because one day He's coming back for us.
One day we're going to see Him face to face, we were singing about a little bit this evening,
when we all get to heaven, what a day of rejoicing that will be.
But you know, we can have a little bit of that here on earth.
We can worship Him.
He's worthy of our worship.
This week, we come together for corporate worship, Sunday morning, Sunday evening, we
worship the Lord, the prayer and Bible study, worshipping the Lord on Wednesday.
But you know, you need to worship God every day in your life.
Worship God.
Worship Him.
He's worthy.
You don't have to necessarily come to a corporate meeting place to worship God.
You can worship God in your individual life.
It's a great thing to come together corporately and collectively worship God.
Singing with you is so much better than singing by myself.
It really is.
It's just a sweet thing when you hear the saints of God singing out the great hymns
of faith.
Man, it's encouraging.
You come to a place like this and you hear the singing, man, it encourages you.
Why?
Because we're worshipping God and He's worthy of our worship.
The Bible says that Jacob, he worshipped.
This evening, I hope that we'd be challenged.
Yes, we see the historical context and it's a blessing to see that God recorded that for
us.
But tonight, how's our worship?
How are we doing worshipping the Lord?
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for the Bible.
Thank you for what you have done in our lives individually, families that are gathered here
this evening, what you've done in their lives, as a church, what you've done in our history.
Thank you for what you're doing today, how you're working.
Thank you for adding to the church today, having someone join this morning.
God, we're thankful.
We've had baptism this year.
We've had salvation this year.
Lord, we just thank you for what you're doing and how you're working and we give you all
the honor and all the glory for it's due unto your name.
You are worthy.
God we thank you for what you will do.
We know that you have a plan.
You've revealed much of your plan to us, though we don't know the timing for several things,
we know you have a plan and God we look forward to one day being in your presence, worshipping
you.
We read that text of scripture in Revelation 4 and 5 and how our heart longs to be in your
presence, to worship you, to see you face to face.
God I pray that until that time you would help us to worship you in spirit and in truth
here in our lives with the days that you give us, to worship you in our own personal daily
lives, to worship you corporately and collectively.
Lord, there'd be a generation that would come behind us that would see that our God is real
and that he is worthy of worship and that he is the one that determines how we approach
him.
I pray God that you'd move and work as only you can and we'll give you the honor and glory
for it.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
We have a brief moment of invitation this evening.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.