We're nearing the end of our study
through the book of Hebrews and
we're nearing the end of 2020,
so we're right on track and our
theme this year looking unto Jesus.
And I hope that throughout the year
you have been encouraged and
strengthened and you have been
regularly reminded on the importance
of turning your eyes upon the Lord
and Savior Jesus Christ,
our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.
And what a blessing as we look at this.
12th chapter will finish up Hebrews 12
this morning as we started this
passage of Scripture a couple of weeks ago.
We were challenged in the first few
verses of Hebrews 12 to run our race
to run the race and as we looked
at that portion of Scripture,
we understood that we are in a race
and we are to run the race and we
began to look at the instruction
that was received in this passage
of Scripture and instruction.
Regarding the race and first,
we understood how that there would
be hazards and obstacles that he
says that were to lay aside.
Every weight and the sin which
doth so easily beset us,
and we understand that there are
distractions that abound and how
important it is that we understand that.
And then of course,
the instruction that follows is
regarding not only our approach to
the race that were to run with patience.
The race that is set before us,
but also the focus of our race,
and that is that we would look to Jesus,
the author and finisher of our faith.
We also understood that he,
the Lord Jesus Christ,
is our example and he finished
the work that he was given to do.
And he said on the Cross of Calvary
before he gave up the ghost,
it is finished and I'm so thankful
that he finished the race that he
had if we could use that terminology
this morning and understanding that
he finished the will of God and he
went to the Cross of Calvary.
He was crucified as we've spoken
about already this morning through song.
He was buried and he rose in victory,
conquering sin, death and the grave.
Now this morning as we finish chapter
number 12 we begin to look at the finish line.
So we started in chapter number 12
looking at run the race run your race.
And if you think about a race,
you would certainly expect that
there would be a starting block
and that there would be a finish line.
And this morning as we look at verses
18 through 29 and finish up Hebrews
chapter number 12, we will look at
this subject the finish line.
That's the title for the message.
The finish line notice with me.
If you look in verse number 18,
the Bible says this for ye are not
come unto the Mount that might be touched.
And that burned with fire nor unto
blackness and darkness and tempest
and the sound of a trumpet in the
voice of words which voice they that
heard entreated that the word should
not be spoken to them anymore for
they could not endure that which was
commanded and if so much as a beast
touched the mountain it shall be
stoned or thrust through with a dart.
And so terrible was the sight that
Moses said I exceedingly fear and quake.
Notice the next word of verse number 22.
The very first word, but what a great
contrast, a conjunction that is a
change of direction he's speaking here.
About Sinai in those first few verses,
but you find here in verse 22,
but ye are come unto Mount Zion and
under the city of the living God,
the heavenly Jerusalem,
and to an innumerable company of
angels to the General Assembly and
Church of the firstborn which are
written in heaven and to God,
the judge of all and to the spirits
of just men made perfect and to Jesus,
the mediator of the New Covenant.
Into the blood of sprinkling that
speaketh better things than that of
able we will go through verse number
29 this morning because we dig into
the message I want you to notice.
First of all with me,
if you're taking notes,
notice the contrast we've read.
Verses 18 through 24 is our
introduction this morning,
and in those verses we find that God
is providing us with a contrast.
Of course we are reminded as we've
studied the book of Hebrews and as
we've gone through the content of
this book and understanding the
original recipients of this book,
that these Hebrew believers,
these Jewish believers,
that they would have had a very good
understanding, a good grasp on
Old Testament teaching.
They would have been very familiar with
that which is mentioned in verses 18,
down through verse number 21,
speaking about the events at Mount Sinai,
and understanding that
these Jewish believers,
they of course held Moses in high regard.
They were familiar with the Pentateuch.
They were familiar with the Ten Commandments.
They were familiar with this event
that led to the giving of the law,
the Old Covenant.
We find that as we would look at
the description in verses 18 through 21,
and we would see that this mountain,
he says in verse 18,
ye are not come unto the
mount that might be touched.
And so as we would consider the race
and we would consider the finish line,
he starts by telling these believers,
now remember,
these very believers,
they are considering the thought
of returning to Judaism.
They have been given many instructions
with regard to how that Christ is better.
It's been proven over and over,
and they've been given this challenge,
this command to continue to press on,
to move forward,
and we find that they are now being told,
listen, this is not what we're coming to.
We're not coming to Mount Sinai.
So he's gonna use that example of the Old Testament,
the mount that might be touched,
he says, and that burned with fire,
nor unto blackness and darkness and tempest.
He begins to describe the events at Mount Sinai.
In just a moment, we'll look at Exodus 19
and notice the record that is given there.
But I wanna call your attention
to what the Bible says in verse number 20.
It says, for they could not endure
that which was commanded.
And if so much as a beast touched the mountain,
it shall be stoned or thrust through with a dart.
It then says this, and so terrible was the sight
that Moses said, I exceedingly fear and quake.
Hold your place here in Hebrews 12
and turn back to Exodus 19, if you will,
and look at what's taking place.
We're familiar with that Exodus 20
records for us the 10 commandments
and then goes from there into the law
in a broader spectrum.
But we find here in Exodus chapter number 19
that God gives us the record
about this which has taken place
that the writer of Hebrews is referring to
in verses 18 through 21 of chapter 12.
And we find that here in Exodus chapter number 19,
we'll pick it up right in the middle of the text,
but look in verse number nine.
The Bible says this, and the Lord said unto Moses,
lo, I come unto thee in a thick cloud
that the people may hear when I speak with thee
and believe thee forever.
And Moses told the words of the people unto the Lord,
and the Lord said unto Moses,
go unto the people and sanctify them today and tomorrow
and let them wash their clothes
and be ready against the third day.
For the third day, the Lord will come down
in the sight of all the people upon Mount Sinai.
And thou shalt set bounds unto the people,
round about saying, take heed to yourselves
that ye go not up into the mount
or touch the border of it.
Notice this, whosoever toucheth the mount
shall be surely put to death.
Great consequence for not heeding the warning
that is given in verse number 12,
when he says that you're to set bounds
unto the people, round about,
as a side, not really part of the message,
but just a side thought this morning.
Sometimes we think that fences are a bad thing,
that they're just designed to keep us in,
but they're also designed to keep things out,
and they're there for our protection,
and Moses put this bound as the direction of the Lord
and said to the people, take heed to yourselves
that you go not up into the mount
or touch the border of it.
Whosoever toucheth the mount shall be surely put to death.
There shall not in hand touch it,
but he shall be surely stoned or shot through,
whether it be beast or man.
It shall not live.
When the trumpet soundeth long,
they shall come up to the mount.
Verse 14, and Moses went down from the mount
unto the people and sanctified the people,
and they washed their clothes.
And he said unto the people,
be ready against the third day,
come not at your wives.
And it came to pass on the third day in the morning
that there were thunders and lightnings
and a thick cloud upon the mount,
and the voice of the trumpet exceeding loud,
so that all the people that was in the camp,
what does it say?
Trembled.
They trembled.
And Moses brought forth the people out of the camp
to meet with God,
and they stood at the nether part of the mount,
and Mount Sinai was altogether on a smoke,
because the Lord descended upon it in fire,
and the smoke thereof ascended as the smoke of a furnace,
and the whole mount quaked greatly.
And when the voice of the trumpet sounded long,
and waxed louder and louder,
Moses spake, and God answered him by a voice.
We see here in verse number 20,
it says, and the Lord came down upon Mount Sinai
on the top of the mount,
and the Lord called Moses up to the top of the mount,
and Moses went up.
If you continue looking at the passage,
the Bible says that the Lord said unto Moses,
go down, charge the people,
lest they break through unto the Lord to gaze,
and many of them perish.
Again, another warning that is given
with regard that they're not to come upon this mount.
Verse 22, and let the priest also,
which come near to the Lord,
sanctify themselves,
lest the Lord break through upon them.
And Moses said unto the Lord,
the people cannot come up to Mount Sinai
for their charge is to us,
saying, set bounds about the mount and sanctify it.
The Lord.
unto him away get thee down and thou shalt come up thou and Aaron with thee
but let not the priest and the people break through to come up unto the Lord
lest he break forth upon them so Moses went down into the people and spake
unto them and then we find that the Bible gives us in chapter 20 the
record of the Ten Commandments the broader law as you continue to go
through the next several chapters of the book of Exodus and we find here that the
writer of Hebrews is reminding these Jewish believers of this event that took
place as recorded in Exodus 19 and in so doing he's making this contrast because
he says we're not coming to that mount he says for ye are not come unto the
mount that might be touched and he's dealing with that of Mount Sinai of
course to follow the theme that we've discussed through the book of Hebrews up
to this point that Christ is better and we talked about a better covenant
remember several probably at this point months ago as we were looking and
dealing with the better covenant and the fact that that first covenant it was not
faultless and we find that in chapter number eight he deals with that new
covenant a better covenant and what he's referring to here in verses 18 through
21 is that old covenant the law and he reminds them of that mount and then he's
going to use this contrast and as we notice the contrast we come to verse
number 22 and he says but ye are come unto Mount Zion now there's a great
contrast between Mount Sinai and Mount Zion and we find that the read the
reader as they would receive this instruction that they are being
encouraged to consider the finish line this race that they have been
instructed to run as we began the twelfth chapter that were to run the
race were to run it with patience were to were to keep our eyes upon Jesus were
to consider him and we find that as we live this life this Christian life that
the analogy has been given as the race that there is a finish line and when we
get to that finish line it's not going to be Mount Sinai but Mount Zion heaven
itself and we find here that he says but you're come unto Mount Zion notice as
the description is given as we continue looking through these verses of
scripture it says this and unto the city of the living God the heavenly
Jerusalem and to an innumerable company of angels the Bible says to the general
assembly in church the firstborn we find that here in this first statement of
verse number 23 he's talking about those that have been born again those that
have been saved by the blood of the crucified one for he says there which
are written in heaven no doubt a reference to the Lamb's Book of Life and
we consider this morning that as believers that heaven is our home we've
understood as we've studied chapter number 11 already and we've made the
statement that we are strangers and pilgrims that this world is not my home
and we're just a passing through we're not home but we're going home and that's
a tremendous blessing and here as the finish line comes into sight as we
begin to be encouraged with the end of our race and coming to that finish line
he's giving this description he says not only to the general assembly and Church
of the firstborn which are written in heaven and to God the judge of all so you
think about heaven people say what's heaven like what we can begin to give
some descriptions and we can begin to talk about heaven this morning in the
streets of gold and all of that and what a blessing that is but the the real
joy is to understand that for all of eternity we're going to be in the
presence of God Almighty as we find here the Bible says and to God the judge of
all and it says into the spirits of just men made perfect I believe as we look at
that last statement of verse number 23 really dealing with those Old Testament
saints and how they looked forward to Calvary and remember as we ended chapter
number 11 and we talked about those that had had run the race that they had
received a good report but Christ had not come in their lifetime and they were
looking toward Calvary we now look back at Calvary but to think about the host
in heaven those that have by faith trusted in Christ those that in the Old
Testament were looking forward to Calvary those of us in the New Testament
that are looking back to Calvary and all by faith notice in verse 24 and to
Jesus the mediator of the New Covenant remember as we spoke about the contrast
here between Mount Sinai and Mount Zion we would think about the contrast of the
Old Covenant and the New Covenant the Old Covenant being law the New Covenant
being grace and we find here that the Bible says into Jesus the mediator of
the New Covenant again as we studied in the 8th chapter of the book of Hebrews
and began to deal with the subject matter of the New Covenant and we dealt
with many things with regard to that several weeks ago and we find here that
the Bible tells us that when we get to that finish line that we're going to see
our Savior and Jesus the mediator of the New Covenant in that wonderful we sing
songs about seeing Jesus we have songwriters that have gone before us
that have written great songs about the day that they would see Christ and I'm
reminded even this morning as we were singing and thinking reflecting on our
salvation and the price that was paid for our salvation that one day one
glorious day we shall see him and that wonderful the Bible says here in our
text of Scripture and to Jesus the mediator of the New Covenant and to the
blood of sprinkling notice what it says that speaketh better things than that of
Abel another reference to the blood of Christ and we find that throughout the
book of Hebrews there's been many references to the blood of Christ and to
the the fact that his blood is superior his work is superior of course as Peter
would tell us that it's the precious blood of Christ and it's because Christ
is God in flesh the sinless perfect Lamb of God that shed his precious blood and
what a joy as we look at this and we consider the finish line that we
understand that there's so much more than what this world has to offer I
want you to just for a moment think about the philosophy and the ideologies
of those in our world today those that are void of a biblical worldview those
that would try to live life on this plane and and have the idea what is
their goal what is their finish line what is it that they're working towards
what is it that they're seeking to accomplish he who has the most toys he
who has the most possessions the most riches whatever it may be but the
reality is that they do not have a finish line like we have a finish line
they don't have the hope of heaven the reality is that there are billions of
people in our world today that are going to die and spend eternity in the
lake of fire because they have not trusted Jesus Christ as their personal
Savior and for us that have been redeemed those of us that have trusted
Jesus Christ our personal Savior because we heard the gospel and received the
truth of the gospel and we've placed our faith and trust in the finished work of
Christ at Calvary we have this finish line that is so much different than the
end of mankind without Christ see for us this morning if you're saved death is
but a doorway from this life to the next and we leave this world and we go to be
with our Savior we're reminded in 2nd Corinthians 5 in verse number 8 where
Paul makes that declaration that we're confident of this thing what to be
absent from the body is to be present with the Lord Paul understood the
reality and the certainty of heaven and this morning as we begin to look at this
passage of Scripture and we see this contrast our minds race to the scene of
heaven and we think about that glorious finish line I don't know when I'm gonna
reach the finish line and neither do you but one day we're gonna take our last
breath here upon this earth I don't know when that day is but isn't it a joy to
know that Jesus is your Savior listen we're living in a day today where
there's much confusion I've said this as we look at all of the events that have
taken place in the last weeks and months and especially in the last days that one
word that could describe the scene in America today is uncertainty there's so
much uncertainty oh there's a host of division and all the things that are
going on but as the people of God we have some things that we're certain of
and this morning I want to encourage you not to focus upon those uncertainties of
life but to focus upon the certainties that God gives us through His Word to
focus upon Jesus the author and finisher of our faith to know that yes we're
running a race and there's going to be obstacles and adversities and
difficulties but there's a finish line and when we get there we're gonna be in
heaven and all that ought to cause us to rejoice it changes our perspective we
understand that as I prayed even this morning that we're in the world but
we're not of the world and what a joy to know listen I understand that people can
get down and people can get under the circumstances but oh how we need to lift
our eyes to Jesus and change our perspective so that we can focus upon
those certainties and we can have the joy and the peace
It's a joy that no man can take from you.
It is a peace that passeth all understanding.
Oh, would we rejoice in that this morning.
We find here that there's a great contrast.
Let me remind you,
as we think about this finish line
of what Jesus said in John 14
as He's speaking to His disciples,
and we find that they were troubled
at the message that they had received
in chapter 13 with regard to Christ
going to Calvary and all that
had taken place, and Jesus says to them
in John 14 in verse number one,
let not your heart be troubled.
Can I tell you this morning
that the same message is true
for the people of God in 2020
as it was for those disciples
as it's recorded here in John 14.
Oh, would you let not your heart be troubled.
You believe in God, believe also in me.
In my Father's house are many mansions.
If it were not so, I would have told you.
He says, I go to prepare a place for you.
And if I go and prepare a place for you,
I will come again and receive you unto myself
that where I am, there ye may be also.
This morning, we have a whole list
of things that are certain
that we can be confident of,
that we can rejoice in.
I submit to you this morning
that if you focus upon the uncertainties of life,
it's gonna cause you to get down.
It's gonna cause you to become discouraged.
It's gonna cause you to become overwhelmed.
You listen, I said this months ago
when we started this whole COVID crisis
in January, February, March,
and things began to kind of spike in March
and come to a head.
And I said to many people at that particular time
that if you're going to watch the news,
that you ought to take the amount of minutes
that you watch the news and multiply it by three
and spend that much time in the word of God.
There's no fancy calculations that I came up with.
I just said that right off the top of my head.
But I would submit to you that even still today,
with all the things going on in our world,
all the confusion and uncertainties,
if you spend all your time watching some news agency,
I don't care which one it is,
I don't care how conservative you think they are
or how liberal you think they are,
we don't need that stuff, we need this.
We need the word of God.
Because it reminds us of some things that are certain.
Listen, Jesus is king.
He controls everything.
Amen?
You believe that this morning?
He is king of kings and Lord of lords, the great I am.
And his plan is perfect.
We may not understand it, but our God reigns.
The Lord God omnipotent reigneth.
And we have a home reserved in heaven.
Notice what the Bible says in 1 Thessalonians.
Turn there if you will,
as Paul is encouraging these believers in Thessalonica.
And what a great church this was.
And there was some confusion that was taking place there
in the church of Thessalonica.
There were some false teachers that had come in
and had kind of told them that the day of the Lord
had already taken place.
And we find that in 2 Thessalonians,
he deals with that even in greater specific nature.
But even here in 1 Thessalonians,
Paul is going to give them the word of the Lord.
He's going to give them truth
with regard to the rapture of the church.
Notice in verse 13 of 1 Thessalonians 4.
But I would not have you to be ignorant, brethren.
Now, I want to pause there and just say this.
God doesn't want you to be ignorant.
He wants you to be informed.
He's given us this book so that we could be informed,
so that we could have the knowledge
that He wants us to have.
He told us that if any man lack wisdom,
let him ask of God,
who giveth to all men liberally and upbraideth not.
We find that He's given us the written Word of God.
We have the mind of Christ.
Let this mind be in you,
which was also in Christ Jesus.
That's what Paul says in Philippians 2,
in verse 5.
And we need to understand that Paul says,
listen, I don't want you to be ignorant.
I want you to be informed.
I want you to understand some things.
He says this.
Contextually, what he's speaking about
are those that have died,
concerning them which are asleep,
that you sorrow not even as others which have no hope.
Aren't you thankful to not be in the category
of those that have no hope?
A lot of people in our world today that are hopeless.
They're hopeless.
Verse 14.
For if we believe that Jesus died and rose again,
do you believe that this morning?
Do you believe that He died?
I mean, Paul says, here's the Gospel in 1 Corinthians 15.
The Gospel is this, that Jesus died
according to the Scriptures,
that He was buried according to the Scriptures,
that He rose again according to the Scriptures.
That's the Gospel.
The death, burial, and glorious resurrection
of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.
And here Paul says,
if we believe that Jesus died and rose again,
even so them also which sleep in Jesus
will God bring with Him.
For this we say unto you by the word of the Lord.
Now, again, I pause here to say,
we need to rejoice in the fact,
this isn't just Paul's opinion.
You ever have somebody say,
hey, would you give me your opinion on this?
Do you know that your opinion doesn't matter?
And neither does mine.
Honestly.
Paul says, I don't want you to be ignorant,
and I want you to understand something.
I'm giving you the word of the Lord.
This isn't just my opinion of last day things.
This isn't just my opinion of what's going to happen
to those that have died.
This is the word of the living God.
He says, for this we say unto you by the word of the Lord,
that we which are alive and remain
under the coming of the Lord
shall not prevent them which are asleep.
For the Lord Himself shall descend from heaven
with a shout, with the voice of the archangel,
and with the trump of God,
and the dead in Christ shall rise first.
Then we which are alive and remain
shall be caught up together with them in the clouds
to meet the Lord in the air,
and so shall we ever be with the Lord.
Isn't that precious?
Wherefore, comfort one another with these words.
Need comfort today?
The word of God will comfort you.
God says of Himself in 2 Corinthians chapter number one
that He is the God of all comfort.
The Bible tells us that Jesus says this of the Holy Spirit
that He is the comforter
and that He was going to send the comforter to be with us.
Oh, we need comfort.
We have the Holy Spirit of God who comforts us.
God Himself is the God of all comfort.
He gives us His word to comfort us.
Let not your heart be troubled.
No, be comforted through the truth of the word of God.
Listen, I don't know when the trumpet of the Lord
is going to sound, but I know one day it's going to.
And there's something else that I know
from the word of God.
The Bible tells us in 2 Timothy chapter number three,
as we begin to understand that
which is going to happen in the last days
and all that's going to take place,
that this world, the inhabitants of this world,
it's going to wax worse and worse.
Evil men and seducers are going to wax worse and worse,
deceiving and being deceived.
And we find that those things are going to happen.
Listen, there will come a time
when men will not endure sound doctrine.
But guess what Paul told Timothy anyway?
Preach the word.
Be instant in season, out of season,
reprove, rebuke, exhort with all long-suffering and doctrine
in one word, continue.
Continue thou in the things which thou hast learned
and been assured of.
And then he goes into the word of God.
That all Scripture is given by inspiration of God.
It's profitable.
And we begin to understand this morning
that as we look at this finish line
and we consider the contrast
here in Hebrews chapter number 12
and we see how that he's contrasting
the old covenant, the law with Mount Sinai,
with the new covenant,
and that Jesus is the mediator of this new covenant.
Of course, he's the testator as we'd mentioned
prior to this study in looking in the book of Hebrews
in that he died so that those things could be initiated.
And we find here that as we would consider the contrast
that we're made aware of this finish line,
this new covenant, Mount Zion,
not the old covenant, but the new covenant,
and heaven itself, what a joy.
See, we speak, we ask the question,
are you 100% sure if you were to die today
that heaven is your home?
We ask that question regularly.
We ask it in church services.
We ask it when we speak to people
that we come in contact with.
Are you sure of heaven?
And this morning, we have that confidence
that that finish line, when we're running this race,
the finish line is heaven.
We're gonna be with our Savior for all of eternity.
I hope that would change our perspective.
I hope that that would encourage us this morning.
We see that there's a contrast, number two in our notes,
if you continue to look through Hebrews 12
and look at verses 25 through 27,
we notice the contrast, number two,
we notice the caution.
We notice the caution.
As we look at these verses of Scripture,
we find that there is a caution here
at the very beginning of verse 25.
The Bible says this,
see that ye refuse not him that speaketh.
Now, it's interesting to think about this word of caution
that begins verse number 25
because it really goes in harmony
with those warnings that we've already received
in the book of Hebrews.
We understand that as we start in Hebrews chapter number one,
the Bible speaks to us about the fact that God speaks.
And of course, we have his word.
Notice in verse number one of Hebrews one,
God who at sundry times and in divers manners
spake in time past under the fathers by the prophets
hath in these
last days, spoken unto us by his Son, whom he hath appointed heir of all things, by
whom also he made the worlds." He tells them in chapter number two, in verses one
through three, he tells them to listen up. I preached a message that I titled
listen up. It says in verse number one, therefore we ought to give the more
earnest heed to the things which we have heard, lest at any time we should let
them slip. And I said this, I remember distinctly making this statement when I
preached that message many months ago from Hebrews chapter number two, have you
ever had somebody say to you, listen up? We have. We've had somebody say, a class,
a teacher, whatever the context, a parent, say, hey listen up. What I'm gonna tell
you is important. Listen, we need to listen to God. We need to listen to his
word. We find that in chapter number three, in verses seven and fifteen, and
really the entirety of that latter part of Hebrews chapter number three, the
Bible reminds us about hearing and believing. In verse number seven of
Hebrews chapter number three, it says, wherefore, as the Holy Ghost saith, today
if ye will hear his voice, harden not your hearts, as in the provocation in the
day of temptation in the wilderness. Notice in verse number fifteen, while it
is said, today if you will hear his voice, harden not your hearts, as in the
provocation. Remember in chapter number five, we read the warning passage in
verses eleven through fourteen. Paul began, or the writer of Hebrews if you
think it's not Paul, began to discuss the subject matter of Melchizedek, and he
began to speak about the high priest or the superiority of Christ's
priesthood, and he begins to deal with that subject matter, but then he says to
them that they were dull of hearing, in verse number eleven. He said, I have
many things to say and hard to be uttered, seeing that you're dull of
hearing, and so we've received these warning passages throughout the book of
Hebrews, and we find it as we come to chapter number twelve in verse number
twenty-five, that the Bible, in line with these other warnings, it says, see that
you refuse not him that speaketh. Listen, there may be some people that speak that
you can tune off, tune out, and it's not gonna really mess you up too much, but we
need to hear the Word of God. We need to listen up. We need to be in tune. He that
hath ears, let him hear. It says, see that you refuse not him that speaketh, for if
they escaped not who refused him that spake on earth. Now, what's he talking
about? He's using that analogy again, or that illustration again, of verses eighteen
through twenty-one, Mount Sinai, and the giving of the law. Remember, what was it
said? There were to be some bounds, and they couldn't cross, and if they touched,
they were gonna die. Hey, if they didn't listen, there was a grave consequence. So
we find here that there's this caution about listening and refusing not him
that speaketh. It says, for if they escaped not who refused him that spake
on earth, much more shall not we escape if we turn away from him that speaketh
from heaven, whose voice then shook the earth. Remember, they trembled at that
scene at Sinai. It says, but now he hath promised, saying, yet once more I shake
not the earth only, but also heaven. And this word yet once more signifieth the
removing of those things that are shaken as of things that are made, that
those things which cannot be shaken may remain. We begin to really look here as
we have the truth that is given to us, and we think about the giving of the
law on Mount Sinai, and really we think about his second coming when the Bible
speaks about here that not only the earth only would shake, but also heaven.
And we begin to think about the fact that he says, refuse not him that
speaketh. This morning I hope that you're thankful for the Word of God. I hope that
you understand that we have the complete canon of Scripture, and that God has
given us his Word, and oh that it would be in our minds this morning to
understand that it is in our best interest to obey, to take heed to the
Word of God. Just as it was in Exodus 19, it was in the best interest of those
children of Israel to listen to what the man of God said as he gave them the Word
of God. And as we look here and we consider the Bible the Word of God, and
we understand that the Scriptures that are profitable for us. I preached a
message last night at a youth rally about being warned. And you know the
the interesting thing in Psalm 19 and in verses 7 through 10 describes the Bible,
the law of the Lord is perfect, and it goes through that section and really
just helps us to rejoice in what we have in the Scriptures. And then you come to
verse number 11, and the Bible says that by them, moreover by them is thy servant
warned. I wonder this morning, when's the last time you've been warned from the
Bible? And when's the last time in your Bible reading, in your daily walk with
God, that you've received warning? And the question is what do you do with it? Do
you take heed? Do you take heed to the warning that you've received from the
Word of God? It is in our best interest. Peter would say this over in 2nd Peter
chapter number 1, turn there if you will, many people have this idea, I've heard
many tell me this throughout my years of ministry, well I just wish God would talk
to me in an audible voice. He's given us His Word. And as I've mentioned, even as
we study through the book of Genesis, that when we read the Scriptures and we
see where the Bible says, and the Lord said unto Abram, the Lord spake unto
Abram, the Lord spake unto Abraham, we read those verses of Scripture and
really, for that matter, anyone that we read in the Scriptures where it's given
in that manner, we must understand that when we approach the Word of God, because
this is the living Word of God, that God is speaking to us. And God is giving us
truth to help us. And Peter says this in 2nd Peter chapter number 1, it says this
in verse 16, we have not followed cunningly devised fables when we made
known unto you the power and coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, but were
eyewitnesses of His majesty. For He received from God the Father honor and
glory, when there came such a voice to Him from the excellent glory. And it
says this, this is my beloved Son in whom I am well pleased. You know what Peter's
talking about? He's talking about the Mount of Transfiguration. He's talking
about when Peter, James, and John had the privilege alone, just them, to go up into
the mountain to see the glory of the Lord Jesus Christ when He was
transfigured. And of course Peter, he didn't know what to say and he didn't
know what he was saying. He talked about making some tabernacles because there
was Moses and Elijah there as well, and let's make one for you and one for
Elijah and one for Moses. And then what happened? Moses and Elijah are gone and
it shone and you heard the voice of God the Father, this is my beloved Son in
whom I am well pleased. Peter says this, and this voice which came from heaven we
heard and we were with Him in the Holy Mount. He's given testimony, He's an
eyewitness. The gospel records record this event. Now Peter is speaking about
it, but notice what he says in verse number 19. For we have also a more sure
word of prophecy. Whereunto ye do well that ye take heed, as unto a light that
shineth in a dark place, until the day dawn and the day star arise in your
hearts. Knowing this first, that no prophecy of the Scriptures of any
private interpretation, for the prophecy came not in old time by the will of man,
but holy men of God spake as they were moved by the Holy Ghost. I'm so thankful
that we have a more sure word of prophecy. I'm thankful that God has seen
fit to give us the Bible in its entirety. I've often said over the years that no
one demanded that God gave us a word or how long this word had to be or what the
content had to be, but God in His grace, His mercy, and in His love for His people,
He gave us the Word of God. The very first mention of the book of the law
would be in Joshua chapter number 1. When you read that Moses, of course, the law
of the five books, we refer to it as the Pentateuch, Genesis, Exodus, Leviticus,
Numbers, and Deuteronomy. That now is finished, and God says to Joshua, this
book of the law shall not depart out of thy mouth, but thou shalt meditate
therein day and night that thou mayest observe to do according to all that is
written therein. For then thou shalt make thy way prosperous, and then thou
shalt have good success. And we find that God has given us a word. Listen, we need
to take heed to the caution. He says this, see that you refuse not Him that
speaketh. This morning, when we're running this race and we're thinking about the
finish line, we must be aware of the fact that there is a finish line.
There's this contrast that's given. There's this caution. Listen, there are
some that would give us some bad counsel. There are some that would say,
hey, it's not really worth it. Hey, don't put yourself out there in that fashion.
No, we need to hear Him. We need to get into the Word of God and allow the Word
of God to influence us and instruct us and that we would understand that in the
midst of all that's going on, if you were perhaps reading for the very first time
the content of 2 Timothy chapter number 3, if you were Timothy receiving in the
first century this letter from Paul giving you all of this description about
the last days and all of these things that are going to come, perilous times
and all of these things, you might not expect that the word of advice and
counsel would be, continue. That's exactly what it is.
And as the people of God, as we're running the race, we find that there's, yes, a contrast,
there's a caution, and it finishes with a charge.
Notice number three with me.
I want you to notice the charge in verses 28 and 29.
The Bible says this,
Wherefore we, receiving a kingdom which cannot be moved, let us have grace, whereby we may
serve God acceptably, with reverence and godly fear, for our God is a consuming fire.
As we look at this passage of Scripture and we've considered the contrast, the caution,
we now see that there's a charge we've mentioned during that caution about the way in which
the heavens and earth would shake.
Would notice in verse 27, it says,
In this word yet once more signifyeth the removing of those things that are shaken as
of things that are made, that those things which cannot be shaken may remain.
And then it says in verse 28,
Wherefore we, receiving a kingdom which cannot be moved.
As I begin to look at the first section of verse 28 and consider this charge, we find
that it begins really with helping us to realize the surety of our inheritance.
The surety of our inheritance.
What a blessing to know that we're receiving a kingdom which cannot be moved.
I want you to think about a few verses of Scripture with me this morning as we consider
the surety of our inheritance.
Notice what the Bible says in John chapter number 10.
Look at three portions of Scripture and look at what the Word of God says with regard to
the surety of our inheritance.
In verse number 27 of John chapter number 10, Jesus says this,
My sheep hear my voice, and I know them, and they follow me.
Notice verse 28,
And I give unto them eternal life, and they shall never perish, neither shall any man
pluck them out of my hand.
The Bible says that the wages of sin is death, but the gift of God is eternal life through
Jesus Christ our Lord.
And here Jesus says,
I give unto them eternal life, that's the gift of God, and it says they shall never
perish, neither shall any man pluck them out of my hand.
My Father, verse 29, which gave them me is greater than all, and no man is able to pluck
them out of my Father's hand.
I and my Father are one.
We find that not only here do we see this truth of the surety of our inheritance, but
I want you to notice what the Bible says in Ephesians chapter number 1.
In Ephesians chapter number 1, Paul is writing to this church that he had the privilege of
being able to minister in, and seeing established, and as he's writing back to these believers,
this book of Ephesians really begins, and the first several chapters deal with our position
in Christ, who we are in Christ.
And we find that in verse number 13 of Ephesians 1, the Bible says this,
In whom ye also trusted, after that ye heard the word of truth, the gospel of your salvation.
Now let me pause there just for a moment.
The Bible says that the gospel, as we've already declared and discussed this morning, is the
death, burial, and glorious resurrection of Jesus.
The Bible says that Paul, he says to the church in Rome, to the believers there in Rome, I
am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ, for it is the power of God unto salvation to everyone
that believeth, the Jew first and also the Greek.
And so here, he's preached the gospel.
By the way, the Bible says, So then faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word
of God.
Remember Romans 10 and verse number 13, For whosoever shall call upon the name of the
Lord shall be saved.
How then shall they call on him in whom they've not heard?
How shall they hear without a preacher?
And so we see that the word of God, the gospel was preached in Ephesus, and there were people
that believed, they trusted the Lord.
It says this, In whom also, after that ye believed, notice this phrase, ye were sealed
with the Holy Spirit, that Holy Spirit of promise.
Aren't you thankful for the Holy Spirit?
The Bible tells us that at the moment of salvation, the Holy Spirit indwells every believer.
And it says in verse number 14, Which is the earnest of our inheritance until the redemption
of the purchased possession unto the praise of his glory.
I've been bought with a price.
And if you're saved this morning, you've been bought with a price as well.
And you know what Jesus did?
You know what God did?
He said that I'm going to give you the Holy Spirit as the earnest of our inheritance.
Until the day, until the redemption of the purchased possession.
Listen, one day he's going to come to get us because he owns us.
And whether that's that we die, remember what did Paul say, for me to live is Christ
and to die is gain.
And we understand here that this surety of our inheritance, notice what Peter says in
first Peter chapter number one.
In first Peter chapter number one, verses three through five, notice what the scriptures
tell us about this inheritance and the surety of our inheritance.
Remember, the Bible is, we're looking here at Hebrews chapter number 12, that he says
that we are receiving a kingdom which cannot be moved.
In verse number three of first Peter chapter number one, it says, blessed be the God and
father of our Lord Jesus Christ, which according to his abundant mercy hath begotten us again
unto a lively hope by the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead.
That's talking to somebody that's saved, amen, and someone that's been born again.
And it says this, to an inheritance incorruptible and undefiled, and that fadeth not away, reserved
in heaven for you.
And that sounds awfully sure, does it not?
The surety of our inheritance, it says this in verse number five, who are kept by the
power of God through faith unto salvation, ready to be revealed in the last time.
I'm so thankful the word of God would teach us this morning the truth of eternal security,
the truth of the surety of our inheritance.
I believe this morning that as you'd look at the broad spectrum of Christendom, and
you begin to look historically even at those that would oppose the teaching of eternal
security, that in many of those cases it's used as a power chip.
What do I mean by that?
Well, I can tell you you have to do all of these things in order to be saved, in order
to keep your salvation, you've got to do all of these things, and if you fall out of
doing these things, then you're going to lose your salvation.
It's a power thing.
But God has bought us, He possesses us, He's given us the Holy Spirit of God, which is
the earnest of our inheritance.
What a blessing.
There are people all around churches in this world today that are hearing messages that
tell them you have to do all of these things in order to be saved.
A work-based salvation followed by a work-based keeping your salvation.
If I couldn't get it in the first place, there's no way I could keep it.
Listen, if you'd be honest this morning, if you'd be honest this morning, if you could
lose your salvation, you would have lost it the day you got it.
Amen.
But I'm so thankful that we, it says here, wherefore we receiving a kingdom which cannot
be moved, it helps us to be mindful of that surety of our inheritance, notice as it continues,
let us have grace.
I'm so thankful for the grace of God.
The Bible speaks about His saving grace, about His serving grace.
We find here that it says, really the context is dealing with His serving grace, for it
says whereby we may serve God acceptably with reverence and godly fear for our God as a
consuming fire.
As we notice here in our text of Scripture, we think about this charge, we find that really,
as we are reminded of the surety of our inheritance, remember, we're not doing these things to
keep our salvation, we're not serving God so we can keep our salvation, we have this
kingdom we've been given, we receive a kingdom which cannot be moved, we have this surety
of our inheritance, but we find that we, by the grace of God, may serve Him acceptably.
I want to serve God, not so that I can earn something, but because of all that He's done
for me.
It's a completely different perspective.
We find that the Bible says, for by grace are you saved through faith, that not of yourselves
but the gift of God, not of works lest any man should boast, and then it says, for we
are His workmanship created in Christ Jesus, we're created unto good works.
We are to serve Him, and notice what the charge is, that we may serve God acceptably.
We know that it is a privilege to serve God.
We sing the song, there is joy in serving Jesus, and there is.
Does that mean it's always easy?
No.
Just read about Paul a little bit, amen?
We know what he says, though the outward man perish, the inward man is renewed day by day,
amen?
Why?
Because we're serving the Lord, and we've got our eyes, listen, when we're serving the
Lord, we deal with obstacles and difficulties and adversities, and maybe the very people
that we're serving, as Paul says as he's speaking to the churches in Galatia, he said, hey,
at one point you would have given me your eyesight, and now you want to, you know, you
don't want to be my friend anymore, so to speak, and all of these things, you're not
going to hear the truth, and the reality is that, listen, it doesn't matter how the people
would respond if we're serving Christ, we want to serve Him acceptably, that He would
be pleased with our service.
Not that some person would be pleased with our service, we're not looking, we're
not seeking the applause of man, we're seeking the the acceptable nature of our
God saying, this is well done, this is acceptable, this is pleasing in my sight,
whereby, how is it that we serve God acceptably? And notice what it says,
with reverence and with godly fear. With reverence and godly fear. It's
interesting that verse number 29 would help us to understand how it is that we
have that fear of God. It says, for our God is a consuming fire. And he is. You
know our God is holy. He's holy. It's amazing to me when you read through the
scriptures and you find instances of God's righteous judgment. You read about
the righteous judgment of God and you find how that it has a profound impact
upon other believers. In fact, it has a profound impact even upon lost people.
One such example, and my time has gone this morning, but I want to share with
you this truth from Acts chapter number 5. You remember with Ananias and Sapphira?
They lied to God. They lied to the Holy Ghost. What happened? They died.
They died. That's serious. And the Bible says that she, we'll skip right through it
because we don't have time, in verse number 10 of Acts 5, that she fell down
straight with his feet and yielded up the ghost and the young men came and
found her dead and carrying her forth buried her by her husband and great fear
came upon all the church and upon as many as heard these things. We want to
serve God acceptably. We want to serve God with reverence and with godly fear.
And this morning, it's a privilege to serve the Lord and we ought to thank God
for the privilege that is ours to serve him and we ought to serve him
acceptably. We ought to seek to serve him acceptably. You know, this morning as we
think about the opportunity that we have to serve Christ, it's because we're not
under that law anymore that we're under grace. It's by the grace of God that he
enables me to serve him. The finish line. In every race, there's a starting block
and there's a finish line. Where did you start this race? When you trust that
Christ is your Savior. When do you finish this race? When you take your last breath
here upon this earth. And the finish line is heaven. And oh that God would help us
to finish our race, to finish our course. You know, I never ran track and field
surprise. Amen. I was always playing a different sport. Amen. But the
reality is that you keep your eyes on the finish line. You keep your eyes on
the finish line. You want to get to that, you want to reach that goal. And as we
mentioned several weeks ago, Paul said that I might finish my course with joy.
And I hope this morning that we could say, I got my eyes on the finish line. I
don't know when I'm gonna reach it, but I want to take this charge and I want to
serve God acceptably with reverence and godly fear. Let's pray. Father, we love
you this morning. We thank you for loving us. We thank you for the Word of God and
for the truth that is contained therein. We thank you for this passage of
Scripture that contains for us a contrast. We're so thankful that as we
would understand these Jewish believers in this first century receiving this
this letter, this book that we call Hebrews, that they would be reminded that
they're not going to a mount that could be touched, Mount Sinai, but to Mount
Zion. We'd find this truth this morning that the finish line is heaven itself.
God, we thank you for the caution that we would listen, take heed, that we'd refuse
not him that speaketh. And then for this charge, God help us to serve you
acceptably. We know that it's by the grace of God that we are what we are. We
know that it's your grace that enables us to serve you and I pray that we'd
serve you acceptably with reverence and with godly fear, understanding your
holiness that you are a consuming fire. I pray that you'd bless, that you'd work
in hearts and lives. Help us, Lord, this morning to be encouraged with all of the
uncertainties that abound in this world. Would you help us to focus upon the
certainties of thy word, knowing that you reign and you rule, that one day
you're going to come again, having the certainty of heaven, that heaven is our
home. I've been bought with the price to be absent from the bodies to be present
with the Lord. I pray, God, that you'd help us this morning to be encouraged.
Help us to make commitments to serve you. I pray that you'd work as only you can
for it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes
are closed, no one's looking around. Would you allow God to have his way in your
life this morning? Would you rejoice in the certainty of heaven? Would you make a
commitment to serve the Lord acceptably? As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.