A verse that we'll use as a springboard again into our lesson this evening, we've been dealing
with the subject matter of theology for the last several weeks as we have been looking
at the broader study of sound doctrine and the importance of understanding who God is.
I'm so thankful over the last two weeks that we've had the privilege of being able to study
about the attributes of our God.
I'm thankful that he has revealed himself to us in his precious word, and what a joy
to know him.
What a joy it is that he wants us to know him, and it's certainly a blessing as we began
to look at the attributes of God.
We spoke about the natural attributes, the fact that he's omniscient and omnipotent and
omnipresent, that he is immutable.
He never changes, the same yesterday and today and forever.
And of course the fact that he is eternal, and what a blessing that is.
As we began to look last week at the moral attributes of God, we dealt with the fact
that he is holy, he's righteous, he's faithful.
We said this, that he's compassionate, loving, gracious, and merciful.
And what a blessing.
And I mentioned to you that that's not really an exhaustive list of the moral attributes
of our God, and I'm so thankful to know that we serve the Lord God Almighty.
In Jeremiah 10, in verse number 6, we used it as a really an outline for our theology
study here over these past few weeks, and the Bible says there,
For as much as there is none like unto thee, O Lord, thou art great and thy name is great
in might.
So this evening, we're going to deal with that last part of Jeremiah 10, in verse number
6, where the Bible says thy name is great in might.
If you're taking notes, I've simply entitled the message this evening, Thy Name is Great.
Here in Proverbs 18, the passage in which I've asked you to turn to this evening, in
verse number 10, I want you to notice the Bible says this,
The name of the Lord is a strong tower.
The righteous runneth into it and is safe.
What a great word picture that the Lord uses here with regard to speaking about the name
of the Lord.
You'll notice in your Bible that Lord there is in all caps, and that, of course, denotes
the use of Yahweh or Jehovah.
We'll get to that in our study this evening.
But the Bible says the name of the Lord is a strong tower.
The righteous runneth into it and is safe.
Let's turn this over in Psalm 148, if you will, and we'll be looking at a number of
verses tonight as we get into the names of God, is really what we're going to look at.
But in Psalm 148, in verse number 13, the Bible reveals to us the importance of praising
the Lord.
Of course, we see that throughout the Psalms and really the whole of Scripture, and He
is worthy of our praise.
But the Bible says in Psalm 148, in verse number 13, let them praise the name of the
Lord.
Again, you see it's in all caps.
For His name alone is excellent.
His glory is above the earth and heaven.
I hope this evening when we consider the subject matter of theology, when we consider who our
God is, that we truly stand in all of Him, and I hope this evening that we praise Him
in the manner in which we should.
We've often mentioned that He is worthy of our praise, and this evening as we begin to
look at the names of God, we're going to look at ten names of God in the Old Testament.
There's more that we can look at, but we're going to look at ten of them this evening.
And as we look at these ten names, we'll begin to see how that God, through the names that
are ascribed to Him, how He is revealing Himself to us.
And we understand that names, especially in the Old Testament, in biblical times, carried
great importance and significance, the meaning of the name.
You can speak to people and you ask them their name, and half of the people, you say,
what does your name mean?
They have no idea what their name means.
It's just not as common or significant in our culture today as it once was.
Of course, there are plenty of cultures around the world today that it still is a very significant
thing when you speak about a name and really the context of that name, the meaning of that
name, and what is being revealed.
And so when we think about God and His Word and giving us all of these names, we find
that He is revealing to us who He is.
He begins to also reveal to us several of His attributes.
We'll start with the first one in Genesis 1, all the way back in the beginning, Genesis
1 and verse number 1.
And the first name that we'll look at this evening is Elohim.
Elohim, it means God, it means the strong one.
And the thing that's important when we understand here about the name Elohim is that we find
it here in Genesis 1 and verse number 1 when the Bible says, in the beginning, God created
the heaven and the earth.
And so we find that when the word Elohim, and it's used over 2,000 times in the Old
Testament in reference to our God, it often is referred, or excuse me, translated as God,
as it is here in this verse of Scripture in the beginning, God created the heaven and
the earth.
And we find that it means the strong one.
It is carrying it with it, it's giving to us, revealing to us, even as we see here in
the first mention of this particular name, that He is the creator.
Now that's of significant importance, and we understand on Sunday evenings for a lengthy
period of time now, and we've taken some weeks off, and we'll get back to the study and we
kind of have bounced back and forth, but we've studied through the book of Genesis,
and we've gotten up to the 15th chapter, and we spent months just in the first 11 chapters
of the book of Genesis to really establish the foundation and to prove the truth that
our God is the creator.
Of course, we live in a time today in which the subject, the teaching of creation is often
mocked and ridiculed and looked down upon, but we understand that God first reveals Himself
to us as being the creator, the strong one.
We understand that He created everything out of nothing, that He spoke it all into existence.
As we look through Genesis chapter 1, and it will not be part of the study this evening,
but you'll note that the Bible says, and God said, and it was so.
And you see the power, the strength of God, and the word that is used here, the Hebrew
word or name for God is Elohim.
The second one that we'll look at this evening is Yahweh or Jehovah.
Now this is, of course, if we could use it this way, it would be referred to as the proper
name of God.
In fact, oftentimes when you would study and learn and read about those scribes and those
that would write out the scriptures, anytime they would come to the word Yahweh or Jehovah,
they would not use the vowels, just the consonants, and they would be very careful.
They would not speak the name Yahweh because of the reverence of the name of God.
We would say that it's His proper name, if you will.
It's used over 6,500 times in the Old Testament.
You'll find that a number of times, of course, Yahweh is the root word, Jehovah is a derivative
of that, and so the two together are used over 6,500 times in the Old Testament.
And it's interesting to know, of course, we'd understand that it's really Israel's covenant
God is another way of understanding and looking at the use of the word Yahweh or Jehovah,
but we begin to think about the reality of this name of God.
It means the self-existent one.
The self-existent one.
Now many times you'll be asked the question, I was asked the question on our own property
several, probably seven or eight weeks ago, someone was on our property, and I went to
chat with them to see what was going on, and they began to, we engaged in conversation,
and their question was, well, who made God?
And that was, they were being very smart-alecky, and just kind of, the reality is that God
is the self-existent one.
No one created God, He is the creator, and through the name Jehovah or Yahweh, and understanding
the fact that it's the self-existent one, you find that there's no creator outside of
Him.
He needed no one to create Him, because He is.
And it really could carry the idea of this definition, to be, to have life.
And you understand, really in Genesis 2, the first reference of Jehovah or Yahweh,
but really when we're given explanation as to the name, you have to go to Exodus chapter
number 3.
In Exodus chapter number 3, even as you're moving there in your Bible and going to that
portion of Scripture, for some of you, your mind probably races to the, really the context
of that passage of Scripture, dealing with the call of Moses.
You'll remember that God told Moses, when He appeared to him there in that burning bush,
and Moses saw that, and God told him that He was going to send him, and Moses questions,
he says, who am I, and all of that sort of thing.
But the reality is that he then asks a very good question, that is Moses asks a very good
question of God.
Notice in verse number 12 in Exodus chapter number 3, let's look at verse number 11, and
Moses said unto God, who am I, that I should go unto Pharaoh, and that I should bring forth
the children of Israel out of Egypt.
And God says, and He continues here, and it says, and He said, certainly I will be with
thee.
Now, consider that great promise.
as we've mentioned that many times and even as we dealt with the attributes of God,
that He is omnipresent, He's promised His presence.
He tells Moses that He would be with him, it says,
And this shall be a token unto thee that I have sent thee,
when thou hast brought forth the people out of Egypt,
ye shall serve God upon this mountain.
And Moses said unto God,
Behold, when I come unto the children of Israel and shall say unto them,
Notice what he says,
The God of your fathers hath sent me unto you.
Now, why does he say that?
Well, we understand previous in the text of Scripture
that God says to Moses that He is the God of their fathers.
In verse number six, it says,
Moreover, he said, I am the God of thy father, the God of Abraham,
the God of Isaac, the God of Jacob.
And so Moses understood that truth.
He says that he's going to go to the children of Israel
and he's going to say to them,
The God of your father hath sent me unto you,
and they shall say to me,
What is his name?
What shall I say unto them?
That's a good question.
It's an appropriate question.
It really is a reverent question.
And we find that God then reveals,
and we often look at the truth of this passage of Scripture,
and we rejoice greatly in understanding
the way in which God reveals great, significant truth to Moses,
and of course, through the preservation of the Word of God for us this evening as well.
And Jesus uses this in John 8.
And what is said here in verse number 14,
God said unto Moses,
I am that I am.
And He said,
Thus shalt thou say unto the children of Israel,
I am hath sent me unto you.
And so we find that God is then going to share with Moses
this great truth in verse 15.
And God said moreover unto Moses,
Thus shalt thou say unto the children of Israel,
The Lord God of your fathers,
the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob,
hath sent me unto you.
This is my name forever, and this is my memorial unto all generations.
And so this is really the explanation, if you will,
as we begin to find more of the revelation of this,
the use of this name Jehovah or Yahweh,
that He is the self-existent one.
I am.
I am that I am.
We see it in this verse of scripture.
Remember, Jesus said in John 8, in verse number 58,
when He's speaking to the religious leaders of the day,
He said that Abraham rejoiced to see his day.
Of course, they're talking about the fact that they're the seed of Abraham,
and they've never been in bondage and all of that sort of thing.
And Jesus says,
Abraham rejoiced to see my day.
And they said,
You're not even 50 years old yet.
What do you mean?
And He said,
Before Abraham was, I am.
And you know, immediately at that time,
what did the religious leaders want to do?
They wanted to stone Jesus.
They wanted to kill Jesus.
And what was the crime?
The crime would be that of blasphemy, is what they would accuse Him of.
Why?
Because they understood that when He said,
Before Abraham was, I am, that He was claiming to be God.
Because He is God.
And that's another study for another week.
But we find here the use of that word, of that name.
And again, really the proper name of God.
Notice over in Psalm 68.
I can already tell you we're not going to get through all 10 tonight.
Amen.
Psalm 68.
If you're sitting there wondering,
How are we going to do it?
We're not.
And I really had high ambitions of getting through it.
But that's okay.
And notice in verse number four of Psalm 68.
Psalm 68 in verse number four.
The Bible says this,
Sing unto God, sing praises to His name.
Extol Him that writeth upon the heavens by His name,
JAH, and rejoice before Him.
That, of course, is another derivative, if you will, an abbreviation for Jehovah.
And not used as often.
In fact, the Hebrew word there is often translated as Jehovah or Lord.
And it's important for us to understand this is, again,
if we could say a proper name for God,
we would say that it's Yahweh or Jehovah.
Turn to the book of Isaiah.
We'll look at one more verse of scripture in Isaiah chapter 42.
Isaiah chapter 42.
And look at verse number eight.
Notice what the Lord says.
And again, it's important.
You've probably noticed as you've read your Bible,
as you read through the Old Testament,
there are times in which you see the word Lord translate in our English Bibles
with a capital L and then a lowercase O-R-D.
And then there are other times in which you see Lord translate it
with a capital L, capital O, capital R, capital D.
And when you see it in all caps, L-O-R-D,
that is this word, Yahweh or Jehovah, the self-existent one.
When you see the capital L with the lowercase O-R-D,
that's the next name of God that we're going to deal with,
and that's Adonai.
We'll look at that in just a moment.
But we see that that's the distinction in which the translators used
in distinguishing the name of God, Lord, L-O-R-D,
all caps being Jehovah or Yahweh,
and then Lord, capital L, lowercase O-R-D, dealing with Adonai.
Look here in Isaiah 42 in verse number eight.
Notice what it says.
I am the Lord.
It's all caps, right?
Is it all caps in your Bible?
That's the Hebrew word, Yahweh or Jehovah.
And the Bible says this,
that is my name.
In my glory will I not give to another,
neither my praise to graven images.
And this evening, again, as I said by way of introduction,
when we really look into the Old Testament
and we look at the usage of the names for God
and how it reveals to us who he is
and how he has given this truth to us,
it's important that we grasp this this evening
because there are many today
that will have that scoffing, mocking type of an approach.
When you say that God is the creator,
they want to know, well, who created God?
Well, no one, because he is the self-existent one.
He is Yahweh, Jehovah, that is his name.
And what a great truth of the word of God.
I'm so thankful that God has revealed that to us.
The third one, if you're looking,
the third name this evening, Elohim, Jehovah, or Yahweh.
Number three, Adonai.
Now, Adonai, again, means Lord or Master.
It means this, my strength.
When we think about the particular use of the word Adonai
to mean Lord or Master,
we'll see that when referring to the Lord, God,
it will use that, in the English,
you'll have a capital L with a lowercase O-R-D.
As I mentioned just a moment ago
with regard to Yahweh and Jehovah with all caps.
You will find at times that Adonai
is not referring to Lord God,
but referring to just a master, a human being, an individual.
And it's interesting because during those times,
often you'll see that it's translated lowercase L-O-R-D.
Now, often we don't refer to people,
we don't call our boss Lord in our particular culture,
but we will find that they will use that word at times
and you'll see it translated that way.
Turn back to Genesis chapter number 15, if you will.
In Genesis chapter number 15,
and here we'll see that the Bible is going to use here
this name for God, Adonai.
And it actually has a compound name
because it says Lord God.
But notice here as Abram is responding to God
in verse number one,
we studied this just a few weeks ago on Sunday evenings,
but the Bible says after these things,
the word of the Lord came unto Abram in a vision.
Now you understand it says the word of the Lord,
how's it is all capital in your Bibles, right?
In verse number one.
And so Yahweh or Jehovah,
it came unto Abram in a vision saying,
fear not Abram, I am thy shield
and I exceeding great reward.
We discussed that.
What a joy to know how God was making himself
known to Abram in verse two.
And Abram said, Lord God.
Now Lord should be capital L in lowercase O-R-D.
That's the Hebrew word Adonai,
which carries with it again, master or my strength.
Now, remember God has just said to Abram
as he gave him this vision.
He says, I am thy shield and I exceeding great reward.
And Abram then says, Lord God.
And realizing that God is his master, his Lord,
his strength.
It says this, what will not give me saying,
I go childless and the steward of my house
is this Eleazar of Damascus.
And we won't get into the context of that discussion,
looking at the name that is being used.
And really often you will find that this usage
of the word Adonai or the name Adonai
would be spoken in place of using Yahweh or Jehovah
in Jewish custom to display reverence.
And remember, as I mentioned about the usage
of the word or the name Yahweh or Jehovah,
they often would not speak the name of God,
Yahweh or Jehovah because of wanting to be reverent.
And they would use Adonai instead.
And we see here that it means Lord or master.
Now, this is interesting again,
as we begin to see how that God is revealing
who he is to us through his names.
He says, I'm Elohim.
I am God.
I am the strong one.
I am the creator.
And from that truth,
we find how it flows into really
the understanding who God is
and really the importance.
of understanding that God is the Creator and how important that is throughout all
of the Scriptures. Again, as we've mentioned about the subject of creation,
it's not simply isolated to the first few chapters of the book of Genesis. The
subject of creation is throughout the whole of Scripture, and we find that God
reveals himself as Elohim, that I'm the strong one, I'm the Creator. As Yahweh,
Jehovah, I am the self-existent one. To be, I am, and in him is life. We find that
then he uses the name Adonai, and really using that name denotes that he's Lord
or Master, and as our owner, if I could use that terminology this evening, as our
Lord, as our Master, then he rightly deserves our worship and our obedience.
And many times when we look at the New Testament, begin to think about the
way in which we would refer to the Lord as being our Lord, our Master, I'm
thankful that he's our Savior and our Redeemer, our God, but we begin to think
about the truth that I am not my own, right? I've been bought with a price, and
we go through that process and understanding that, and we find this
evening that as we would look at New Testament Christianity, we somehow along
the line maybe got our eyes off of the truth of him being our Master, and we
we've bought into this lie that we're our own people, we can do our own thing, I
can do what pleases me, and the reality is that all the way back here in the Old
Testament, when you use the name for God as Adonai, revealing and giving the
indication to his people that he is Lord or Master, yes, he is our strength, and for
that we are thankful, and we find that because he is our Lord or Master, that he
rightly deserves our worship and our obedience. Number four in your notes, if
you're taking notes this evening, the fourth name of God is El Shaddai, El
Shaddai. Now, Genesis chapter 17, if you will, just a page or two over in your
Bibles, and El Shaddai means the Lord God Almighty. You've often heard me use this
name of God as we find it revealed to Abraham here in Genesis chapter 17,
and you find that in verse number one of this passage, the Bible says, when Abram
was 90 years old and nine, the LORD, again it's all caps in your Bible, right, Yahweh,
Jehovah, appeared to Abram and said unto him, I am the Almighty God. El Shaddai. I
am the Almighty God. And then he says this, walk before me and be thou perfect.
Now, we understand this evening that as we look at this name for God, how that it
would cause us to rejoice greatly, and understanding that he is the most
powerful. We mentioned as we studied the attributes of God, how that he is
omnipotent, that he has all power, and the book of Revelation tells us that the Lord
God omnipotent reigneth, and how that ought to cause us to rejoice this
evening, and when we understand that he is the Lord God Almighty, that he is El
Shaddai, the all-sufficient one, he is our nourishment, he is the most powerful one.
Now, I want you to think about that this evening. How does that impact us? When we
know that the Lord God Almighty has revealed himself in the scriptures as
being omnipotent, when he says to Abraham here in Genesis 17, he says, I am the
Almighty God, El Shaddai. Now, you understand this evening, when we
understand who he is, when we understand the truth that is revealed to us through
the names that are given to God, that God has given to himself, we find
that he's revealing these bits of truth to us to impact our daily living. So, he
tells Abraham in Genesis chapter number 17, he appears to Abraham, Yahweh
Jehovah, the Lord appears to Abraham and says, I am the Lord God Almighty, I am El
Shaddai, and then, if you fast-forward in your mind to Genesis chapter number 18,
just to really, of course, in our Bibles it's a chapter division, but not long
thereafter, after God would reveal himself to Abraham in this way, God asks
Abraham this question in Genesis 18 and verse number 14, is anything too hard for
the Lord? Now, I'm thankful that God in his wisdom, and he has perfect wisdom, that
God first revealed himself to Abraham as El Shaddai, the Lord God Almighty. He
revealed himself to Abraham as being the most powerful, the all-sufficient one, El
Shaddai, and then he asks Abraham, is anything too hard for me? Now, Abraham has
just had this new revelation. Remember, as we've been studying the book of Genesis,
we made note, and we'll look at it probably next week because we won't get
it to this evening, but how that God had revealed himself to Abram in Genesis
chapter number 14 as being the most high God. Remember that interaction
between Abram and Melchizedek, and the king of Salem came, and he said that he
was the the most high God, and how that was the first usage of the name of God
in that manner, and here in Genesis 17, before he asks Abraham, is anything too
hard for me? He says, I want you to know my name, El Shaddai. I want you to know
that I'm the Lord God Almighty. In this evening, God has revealed himself to us
as being El Shaddai. He has given to us the whole canon of Scripture that's
been preserved for us this evening, and we have not only the declaration of
God's power, the fact that He's omnipotent, the names that would support
it, but we have ample illustrations, and I mean, just so many examples that we
could go to this evening within the Word of God to show the power of God, and I
wonder this evening if he came to you, or if he came to me, and he said, is there
anything too hard for me? I know the right answer that we would give. I know
the Bible answer. The Bible answer is, no. There's nothing too hard for God, correct?
You believe that this evening? That's the proper Bible answer, but I wonder this
evening, do I live my life daily understanding that there's nothing too
hard for God? Do you live your life daily understanding there's nothing too
difficult for Him? We can sing songs about it. We can reference verses about
it, but the reality is that God is revealing Himself to us. He's using names
in the Old Testament as our study is this evening looking at the names of God.
He's using these names in order to reveal these truths about Himself, and in
this particular instance, he says to Abraham that he's the Lord God Almighty,
then he asks him just a chapter later in our Bibles, is anything too hard for the
Lord? Of course, he's speaking contextually about the fact that he and
Sarah would have a child. Sarah had just laughed about the promise of God. She was
old. He was old. It's past the time for this to happen. God says, I work best in
the times of the impossible, right? Because it's in those times that He's
glorified. It's in those times that He alone will receive the glory that is due
unto His name. Number five, and we'll finish up this evening, and it's a
precious one, one in which we are very familiar with, Jehovah Ra. Jehovah Ra, and
we'll go to Psalm 23 for that one, and so you probably already know just by
turning to the passage that Jehovah Ra is the Lord is my shepherd. The Lord is my
shepherd. That is the Hebrew name of God, the Lord is my shepherd, Jehovah Ra, and
you see it here in verse number one of Psalm 23, and again, it's a compound name
where the Bible says the Lord. Again, you see it as Yahweh Jehovah, all caps in
your Bible. The Lord is my shepherd, I shall not want. Jehovah Ra, the Lord is
my shepherd. You understand throughout the scriptures, and I will not belabor
the point, we'll get to prayer time here in just a moment, but you understand that
throughout the scriptures that God will use the analogy of people being sheep,
and we find that especially in the New Testament. You'll find it, you find it in
the Old Testament where he speaks about his people not having a shepherd and so
on and so forth, speaking about the leaders and so on and so forth, and here
David, of course, it's a sweet psalm of David, we're familiar with Psalm 23, what
a precious, precious passage it is, but when the Bible says the Lord is my
shepherd, I shall not want, and we understand this evening the way that the
shepherd takes care of the sheep. We understand the role and responsibility, even
though we may not live in a herding industry type of a place where we have
ever perhaps even participated in some of the work of a shepherd, you can read
books on it, you can read analogies, you can study the scriptures that deal with
it, and you can understand this evening that when the psalmist, who by him, by the
way, was a shepherd, right?
David was a shepherd, that he understood what his role and responsibility was as a shepherd.
By the way, when the bear and the lion came to take care of the sheep, what did the shepherd
David do?
He protected them, did he not?
Now, his shepherd, God, gave him the ability, gave him the power, and he testifies of that
when he stands before Saul in 1 Samuel chapter number 17, he gives glory to God for giving
that victory and that deliverance, but we find here as we look at this verse of Scripture
that David, as a shepherd, would have understood the profound truth that is found in this name
of God, Jehovah-Ra, that the Lord is my shepherd, and that means he cares for me, he takes care
of my needs, he provides for me, he says, I shall not want, and we think about the way
in which the shepherd is providing and protecting, and we think about the presence of a shepherd.
Sheep are really, really nervous animals.
They really have no built, they have no good defense in and of themselves.
Very vulnerable animals, if they get alone by themselves, they're extremely vulnerable,
and so the presence of the shepherd gives them a sense of calmness, and it's amazing
if you read some books on shepherding and understand some of the analogy, it helps us
to understand even this truth in the Word of God that the Lord is my shepherd.
I spent some time earlier this year looking through Psalm 23 and speaking about the fact
that the Bible does reveal to us that he is the shepherd, he's the good shepherd, the
great shepherd, the chief shepherd, but the profound nature of the statement that is made
in Psalm 23 when he says, the Lord is my shepherd, it's personal.
And what a blessing to know as God would reveal himself, Jehovah Ra, the Lord is my shepherd,
think about the peace that would be in the heart and life of the believer understanding
the name of God, Jehovah Ra, the Lord is my shepherd.
Oh, it gives me a sense of peace and calmness, understanding that the shepherd knows, listen,
the sheep don't have to know where the green pasture is, the shepherd's going to lead them
to the green pasture, amen?
The shepherd does, excuse me, the sheep, they don't understand where their next meal or
their water or their provision, where all of that, but the shepherd is going to provide
for them.
And in simple faith, we rest in the fact this evening that the Lord is my shepherd, Jehovah
Ra.
We think about these names of God, I intended to get through ten of them this evening, but
we look at five of them, and as we think about these five, Elohim, Yahweh, or Jehovah, Adonai,
and we looked at, what was the fourth one, let me see here, the fourth one was El Shaddai
and then Jehovah Ra.
And I hope this evening that just as these Old Testament Bible characters, as they understood
the names of God, it would have had an impact in their lives.
I hope tonight that as we think about the names of God, these five, we'll study the
next five next Wednesday evening, I hope that it encourages us, I hope that it strengthens
our faith, and that we have this sense of peace and calmness, understanding who our
God is, even through studying the names of God.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you, we thank you for loving us.
Thank you for your word, thank you for the way in which the names of God have revealed
to us who you are and what you do.
And God, I pray tonight that each person that is gathered here, those that have gathered
and tuned in via live stream, God, that we've been encouraged tonight as we've studied
these five names of God.
Help us, Lord, in our time of prayer.
We thank you for the privilege of prayer.
I pray that you'd be glorified and we'll thank you for it.
In Christ's name we pray, amen.
Does anyone need a prayer bulletin this evening?