Book of 2 Corinthians here on Sunday mornings.
And this morning we'll deal with the end
of chapter number six and go into the first verse
of chapter seven, 2 Corinthians chapter six
beginning in verse number 11 is where we'll be.
And we've had the opportunity, our theme for this year,
God's grace is sufficient.
And I'm so thankful for that wonderful biblical principle
and we go through a number of things in our lives,
trials and difficulties and so on and so forth.
But to know that God said his grace is sufficient.
And I've experienced it and I know that you have as well.
And so we're extremely thankful
as we've studied through this book,
we understand that the apostle Paul
is writing back to a church that he had the opportunity
to be able to minister to and to have great influence in.
This church, as you read the book of 1 Corinthians
had many problems and troubles
and the apostle Paul is addressing a number of those things.
There were some things in fact
that the church had written to him about.
You see that beginning in chapter seven
of the first book of Corinthians.
And you find that he says the things
that you've written unto me.
He's gonna answer those questions
and I'm thankful that the Bible has the answer.
And I was talking to one of my nephews
just on Friday evening, he's studying biblical counseling.
And I said one of the wonderful things
about biblical counseling is that it's biblical counseling
and you're taking people and you're leading them
to the truth of God's word
and God's word will help God's people.
And I'm so thankful for that.
This morning as we look at the text,
we're reminded that the believers here in Corinth
in the preceding text of scripture,
it's been a couple of weeks since we've been here.
I was traveling, I was preaching in Belgium last Sunday.
The Sunday before was Father's Day.
And so it's been about three weeks since we've been here,
actually longer than that because the Sunday before that
was a missions conference.
But in any case, it's been a little while.
So let me just remind you that the apostle Paul
had the opportunity to address these believers in Corinth
and to remind them of their responsibility.
Often I will refer to responsibility
kind of synonymously with the idea that it's a privilege.
And yes, it is our responsibility
to preach the gospel to every creature,
but we must acknowledge that it's a privilege
that has been entrusted to us.
I love to tell the story.
We sang the song this morning
and what a wonderful hymn it is.
And to remind them of the fact
that we have been entrusted with the gospel.
We have been privileged, allowed of God,
as Paul says in 1 Thessalonians, to preach the gospel.
And so he spent some time
reminding these believers in Corinth.
We find that they were challenged
to engage in the ministry of reconciliation.
He talks to them as being saved people
and understanding that they had been reconciled
and then tells them that God has entrusted us
with this ministry of reconciliation
and we are to be ambassadors.
And what a blessing to be the representative
of the Lord Jesus Christ and to go and tell others.
We begin the sixth chapter and we find
that God says that we are workers together with him.
Of course, we understand that the verbiage
in the book of 1 Corinthians is used
that we are co-laborers, we're workers together,
co-laborers with Christ.
And what a blessing to think about the fact
that we are workers together with God.
And the apostle Paul is seeking to encourage
the believers in Corinth, he's trying to help them
understand what their duty and responsibility
and privilege is and how they're to be engaged
in the work of the ministry.
We find that as we come to the end of chapter number six
in 2 Corinthians that these verses of scripture
are quite familiar and I would say it this way,
oftentimes they are partially quoted.
We look at this portion of scripture
and we find that the subject of biblical separation
is addressed and it's absolutely imperative
that we understand this morning
the importance of separation.
I've titled the message simply that, biblical separation,
and we look at the Bible and we understand
that there's the truth of ecclesiastical separation,
but there's also the truth of personal separation.
As we look through the passage of scripture this morning,
we are reminded of the Old Testament principle
that God gives us in the little prophet of Amos,
chapter three and verse number three,
can two walk together except they be agreed.
And we find as we begin to look at this passage
of scripture, the apostle Paul is going to give
some very important truth to these believers
and God has chosen to preserve it for us today
so that it would be to our benefit as well.
Begin reading with me in verse number 11,
the Bible says, O ye Corinthians,
our mouth is open unto you, our heart is enlarged.
You're not straightened in us,
but ye are straightened in your own bowels.
Now for a recompense in the same,
I speak unto you as unto you my children,
be ye also enlarged.
We'll go through chapter seven in verse one,
but let's dig right in this morning
and I want you to notice just two points this morning.
The first thought is this,
I want you to notice with me in verses 11 through 13,
Paul's care for the Corinthians.
We find that in these three verses of scripture
that I've just read this morning,
that Paul is seeking to express his care and concern
for these believers in the church of Corinth.
We find that the apostle Paul,
you remember that there were some
that were within the congregation of this church
that had been attacking the apostle Paul
and their fellowship had been strained.
Remember they were saying that Paul says one thing,
but he actually means something else
and they're having all of this conflict
with the apostle Paul.
And so Paul in these verses of scripture,
he's seeking to express to these believers
how much he cares and loves them.
We find that the apostle Paul,
he had when he understood the misunderstanding
as we read in chapter two and entering into chapter three
of the book of second Corinthians,
that what did he do?
Well, before he answered them and explained,
he first examined his own heart.
And as he examined his own heart
and took that process of self-examination,
he then explained to the believers in Corinth
that were saying things that were not true.
And he explained to them why seeking
to have some restoration in that fellowship.
Paul had labored amongst these believers.
Paul had a heart for these believers.
He loved them and he cared deeply for them.
And so Paul is seeking to express this to them.
I believe that here is Paul would express to them
in these few verses,
it reminds us as he gives even further truth
in chapter 12, hold your place here,
but look at second Corinthians chapter 12
and notice how the apostle Paul writes it
here in these verses of scripture.
The apostle Paul, because of this group in Corinth
that had opposed him and the relationship,
the fellowship was strained,
I believe that their attitude and their spirit
laid heavy upon his heart.
It was something that was greatly concerned about.
And we find that in the 12th chapter,
notice with me in verse number 14,
the Bible says, behold,
the third time I am ready to come to you
and I will not be burdensome to you.
Notice when he says,
for I seek not yours, but you.
For the children ought not to lay up for the parents,
but the parents for the children.
And I will very gladly spend and be spent.
Notice where he says for you,
though the more abundantly I love you,
the less I be loved.
The apostle Paul cared about these believers.
Why did he care so much about them?
Well, he knew that God had entrusted him
with a responsibility to minister to them spiritually,
to be a spiritual leader in their lives.
And he knew that they one day would stand
before the Lord Jesus Christ.
And he desired that on that day,
they would be able to stand before Christ complete.
That he had that desire, that longing for these,
that God had given him the privilege of ministering to.
And what was happening is because of this conflict,
because of their own attitude,
we find that they were resisting the message
that God had given Paul to deliver to them.
Paul understood that it was God's word.
Paul understood that it was profitable for those believers.
Paul understood that what God had given him,
these people needed, but they weren't gonna receive it
because they had angst against Paul.
So what's Paul doing?
Well, before he's gonna give them the great truth
that we're gonna look at here in just a few moments,
he first lets them know how much he cares about them,
how much he loves them.
We find that in Galatians chapter four,
not concerning this particular church, obviously,
but the Bible tells us in Galatians four,
as Paul is writing back to those churches
in the region of Galatia, he says,
"'Am I therefore become your enemy
"'because I tell you the truth?'
Paul understood the importance of truth.
He had been entrusted.
He understood that God's word is truth,
and he faithfully preached the word of God,
but yet he says, "'Have I become your enemy
"'because I tell you the truth?'
You know what's sad is that there are many people today
that do not know the truth.
You know what's even more burdensome
is there's a number of people
that don't want to know the truth.
They're just willingly ignorant,
as it says in 2 Peter chapter three.
They just don't wanna know the truth.
They wanna continue down the path that they're traveling,
believing whatever it is that they're believing.
We have in our society today groups of people
that will say, well, this is my truth and your truth
and so on and so forth.
The reality is that truth is not subjective.
Truth is founded upon the Lord Jesus Christ and his word.
And Paul says, if I'm giving you the truth,
why are you treating me like I'm an enemy?
What was Paul trying to do?
He's trying to give them the truth to help them.
You ever have somebody get upset with you
because you give them the truth?
The gospel's offensive, amen?
And Lauren, I don't know where Lauren is,
oh, there she is.
You asked me a question a few weeks ago
about people being upset about door knocking,
and since then, I've gotten some calls.
I'm not saying it's your fault,
but man, we got a phone call where in Belgium,
somebody just absolutely ripped us.
I mean, just the profanity
and just a short little voice message
that was left on the voicemail at church
about the fact that we left some gospel literature
on their door.
They don't want the truth.
You know, I wasn't mad about the voicemail.
My heart was saddened.
Because that individual identified themselves
on that phone call as being a proud pagan atheist.
That's how they described themselves.
And here's the immediate thought that I had.
They held in their hand the very truth
that would save their soul.
And they rejected it.
And they got mad about the truth.
It's nothing new.
Paul experienced this, but Paul's trying to convey
and to communicate to the believers in Corinth,
I love you, I'm trying to help you.
You ever see children that don't like the instruction
that a parent gives?
And they're rebellious against the instruction
that the parent gives, why?
Because they want what they want.
And they believe that what they want will satisfy them.
And the parent knows better.
And there's great difficulty oftentimes that occurs.
And the reality is that we understand
that here the Apostle Paul, he says,
I wanna give you something that's good for you.
In First Thessalonians chapter number two,
Paul mentions to the church in Thessalonica
about his care for them.
See, this is consistent in the life of Paul
that he cared about those to whom God had given him
the opportunity to minister.
We find that in verse number seven
of First Thessalonians chapter two,
notice what Paul says, but we were gentle among you.
Even as a nurse cherisheth her children,
so being affectionately desirous of you,
we were willing to have imparted unto you
not the gospel of God only, but also our own souls,
because ye were dear unto us.
The reality this morning is that Paul,
notice what he says in verse number 11 back in our text.
He says, oh, ye Corinthians, notice he says,
our mouth is open unto you.
Paul believed because he understood the work
that God had entrusted him with.
Listen, Paul knew his position as being an Apostle.
Paul knew his calling.
He knew that God had called him to be a preacher
of the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
God had made it clear, and Paul clearly communicates
throughout the epistles that he knew
that he was doing the work of God.
He says, I'm warning you, why?
To present you perfect or complete at that day.
He says that to the people in Colossae
in Colossians chapter one, and we find that Paul knew,
and he says, our mouth is open unto you.
He continues in verse 11 and says, our heart is enlarged.
Paul says, listen, I'm not mad at you.
I'm not, there's no, it's not on my side.
You're resisting me, and I want you to know
that my mouth is open to you,
that my heart is enlarged unto you,
and we find that then in verses 12 and 13,
what Paul was communicating, he says,
ye are not straightened in us.
Again, it's not the fact that I have something
against you, but ye are straightened in your own bowels,
not for a recompense in the same.
I speak as unto my children.
Be ye also enlarged.
What is he doing?
Paul is communicating to them, and he's desiring
that their fellowship be restored.
He's literally pleading with them.
He loves them, and he desires to minister to them,
and he wants them to open their hearts to him
because he knew that if their heart was closed to him,
they weren't gonna receive what God had for them.
I've had times over the years where I'd get a phone call
from someone and say, hey, my neighbor or my relative,
they need some help, would you go help them?
And I say, nope, you can give them my phone number,
and if they want help, they can call me.
You know why I do that?
Because I've learned that if I try to go help someone
that doesn't really want help,
it's just absolutely torturous for me.
And the reality is that Paul's saying,
I have something that's beneficial for you.
Why, because he's Paul?
No, because it's God's word.
He knows, he says all scripture is given
by inspiration of God and is profitable.
And so Paul says, I have this for you,
and I want you to know how much I care for you
and how much I love you.
And a man asked me a number of years ago
as I would share the gospel with him repeatedly
and he would just continue to resist
and to resist and to reject.
And I find that eventually on one particular day,
he looked straight in my face and he said, why do you care?
It's what he said to me.
He said this, he followed up the statement by saying,
why do you care by saying, so what if I go to hell?
It's what he said to me.
I couldn't imagine the words that I was hearing.
And he said, but why do you care if I don't even care?
It's what he said.
You know what I told him?
I said, I understand the truth of God's word
and I believe it.
You're gonna die one day.
You're gonna go to heaven or hell.
God loves you and he wants you to be saved.
He died for you.
And here's what I told this individual.
I said, listen, I'm going to heaven
whether you get saved or not.
It's not necessarily a benefit.
It's not like it helps me get to heaven
because no, I want you to go to heaven with me.
But I'm going to heaven whether you receive
or reject the truth of the gospel.
And the reality is that Paul, listen,
he understood his walk with God.
Paul understood, he talks about at the end
of the book of Second Timothy that he's finished,
he's completed, he's done the work
that God's called him to do.
He knew that there would be a crown for him.
He knew that he had, not that he's perfect,
but he was seeking to do what God had called him to do.
He said that he exercised himself
to have always a conscience void of offense
before God and man.
And so Paul was seeking to walk with God,
but he wanted others to benefit from the truth
that God had given him.
So what does he do?
He expresses his care, his love, his concern.
It's not a Bible verse.
It's not a Bible verse, but I believe it is a principle
that is certainly founded upon biblical truth,
and that is this.
Many times people don't care how much you know
until they know how much you care.
And we've used that phrase at times,
and we understand that, again, it's not a Bible verse,
but I believe the concept and the thought
is certainly founded upon biblical principle.
This morning before Paul gets into the subject of separation
we find that he expresses his care
to these believers in Corinth.
I wonder this morning,
how many people truly know that we care about them,
that we love them?
You know, people have all kinds of ideas
about church and religion, quote unquote.
They think that somehow you're going to benefit
or I'm going to benefit,
that we're trying to get some gain for ourselves,
but the reality is that we're simply seeking
to impart truth to someone that will benefit them.
Now, do we seek to teach them all things
whatsoever I've commanded you?
Yes, we do seek to disciple and to train
and to teach the truth of God's word.
Why?
Because it's God's plan that all of God's people
are conformed to the image of Christ,
and you're going to stand before Christ one day.
But Paul says, I love you.
My heart's, my mouth is open unto you.
Our heart is enlarged.
So what does he say?
Be ye also enlarged.
We find that Paul's care for the Corinthians
is revealed in verses 11 through 13.
As we look at the remainder of the text
and enter into the seventh chapter,
we find number two, Paul's counsel to the Corinthians.
Paul's counsel to the Corinthians.
By the way, counsel is regularly received far better
from someone or by someone
that knows that you care about them.
So you care about them.
He says this in verse 14,
be ye not unequally yoked together with unbelievers.
For what fellowship hath righteousness with unrighteousness
and what communion hath light with darkness?
And what concord hath Christ with Belial
or what part hath he that believeth with an infidel?
And what agreement hath the temple of God with idols?
For ye are the temple of the living God
and as God hath said, I will dwell in them and walk in them
and I will be their God and they shall be mine.
My people, wherefore, come out from among them,
and be ye separate, saith the Lord,
and touch not the unclean thing,
and I will receive you and will be a father unto you,
and you shall be my sons and daughters,
saith the Lord Almighty,
having therefore these promises, dearly beloved.
Let us cleanse ourselves from all filthiness
of the flesh and spirit,
perfecting holiness in the fear of God.
What great counsel that we read
in these verses of scripture.
And we find that the counsel is really given
to us in verse 14, and then again, repeated in verse 17.
And here's the counsel,
be ye not unequally yoked together with unbelievers.
He rephrases it and says it this way in verse 17,
wherefore, come out from among them,
and be ye separate, saith the Lord,
and touch not the unclean thing,
and I will receive you.
We find that the counsel is very straightforward.
Be not unequally yoked together with unbelievers.
It's very straightforward, it's simple.
Then Paul spends the next couple of verses of scripture
in providing examples
as he explains this truth of separation.
Notice the explanation that is given
beginning in verse 14 and really down through verse 16.
In verse 14, the counsel had been given,
be not unequally yoked together with unbelievers,
but then we find the explanation.
Notice he says this,
and he explains it by asking a series of questions.
The questions that he asks are actually very easy to answer.
Notice he says the first one in verse 14,
he says, for what fellowship hath righteousness
with unrighteousness?
The things that are right
and the things that are not right.
What fellowship do they have one with the other?
It's pretty obvious as Paul is seeking to explain
the counsel that he's just given
to these believers in Corinth,
and he begins to ask them these questions.
What's the purpose of asking the question?
Is the purpose of asking the question
for Paul to gain some knowledge or wisdom?
See, sometimes we ask questions for information, right?
I don't know something, so I ask someone a question
so that I can gain information because I am not aware.
The questions that are asked here are not for information.
You ever hear somebody use the phrase
that that's a thought-provoking question?
Sometimes a question is asked so that the receiver,
the recipient of that question,
has a time of really considering
and contemplating in their own hearts and minds
the truth that is being given.
And here is the apostle Paul ask these questions
to these believers in Corinth,
and he says, what fellowship hath righteousness
with unrighteousness?
He's not really necessarily seeking information
or expecting them to answer,
but he's trying to communicate to them the truth
that hey, why is the counsel to be separate?
Why is the counsel to be not unequally yoked together
with unbelievers?
Because there's no fellowship
between righteousness and unrighteousness.
We live in a land, we live in a time,
and it's nothing new for us.
It's always been this way,
where they call good evil and evil good.
We see the prophets of old using that phraseology.
We understand that as we would not only see in a society
as we've seen in previous periods of history,
but even in our own society today,
where not only do they call evil good and good evil,
but they legislate wickedness.
We see it, we understand it.
It's not hard for us as believers
to look at the question that is asked in verse number 14
of what fellowship hath righteousness with unrighteousness.
The answer is there's no fellowship.
We see that he asks another question
at the end of verse 14.
What communion hath light with darkness?
You know, I'm thankful that I was in darkness,
but not any longer.
Amen.
We are children of the light.
We are to walk as children of light.
You read the book of Ephesians,
and you understand that we were, past tense,
if you're saved this morning,
if you've trusted Christ as your personal savior,
what you were in blindness and in darkness without Christ
and all of that, listen, that's our past,
but now as children of light,
we're to walk and behave a certain way.
And he says, what communion hath light with darkness?
You walk into a dark room and you turn on the light
and the darkness dispels, right?
We understand that.
Men loveth darkness rather than light.
We understand the darkness of the society in which we live,
but listen, he's talking about the fact,
this principle, this council being unequally yoked together
with unbelievers, and he's explaining this.
Why do we talk about biblical separation?
Why is it important that we understand the principle
that the apostle Paul is giving,
not only to the people in Corinth, but to us,
that we're to be careful and to be aware of this council
and the importance of separation,
because there's no fellowship between righteousness
and unrighteousness.
There's no communion between light and darkness.
And what I was is not what I am.
Praise God for that.
I'm so glad that I'm not what I used to be, amen?
God changed us.
You got saved by the grace of God and you're a new creature.
Old things are passed away.
Isn't that what he just told them in the fifth chapter?
He was providing to them about that truth
of the power of the gospel to transform an individual,
and old things are passed away,
and behold, all things are become new.
We find that in Corinth,
if you read the book of 1 Corinthians,
you find very quickly the way in which the culture,
the society had been impacting and influencing the church.
And today, the culture and the society continues
to want to influence a church.
Why do we see churches that so often are moving
and shifting from the truth of this book?
They want to be more accommodating, more relevant,
whatever the term is that they want to use,
but the reality is that we must stand upon the truth
and the principle of God's word.
He continues in verse 15 with an additional question.
Notice, actually, we find two in this verse.
He says, what concord hath Christ with Belial?
The word concord means to have an agreement.
We've talked about the fellowship and the communion,
this union in opinion, sentiments, views.
He says, what concord hath Christ with Belial?
Well, that's pretty direct, is it not?
I mean, very forward as Paul is providing this truth
of being not unequally yoked together with unbelievers.
Why?
Because you're different now.
You've been saved by the grace of God
and you're a new creature.
Yes, we still have to reach unbelievers.
We want to preach the gospel to them,
but we're not to be yoked up together with them.
Amen?
We find that he asked another question in verse 15.
What part hath he that believeth with an infidel?
An infidel is one that no doubt
just absolutely dismisses the truth.
They're unbelievers.
They do not believe the importance of scripture.
They do not believe the truth of God's word.
And he says, what part hath he that believeth
with an infidel?
Again, as Paul is asking these questions,
he's trying to get the believers in Corinth
to process this and to understand this
and to be able to sit back and say,
yeah, there's no fellowship.
There's no communion.
There's no concord.
There's no agreement.
Again, in verse 16.
What agreement hath the temple of God with idols?
With idols.
We understand in the Old Testament,
the children of Israel often were guilty of idolatry.
We read it over and over.
We see the accounts and we see the consequences
and we see the pattern repeated over and over again.
Idols today look different than they looked in that day.
Idols in America look different than they do
in other parts of the world.
You just travel a little bit or just jump on the internet
and look at, and I don't endorse everything on the internet,
but just look at some things around the world
and you'll see that idols in America look different
than idols around the world.
But John says in 1 John 5,
my little children, keep yourselves from idols.
Paul says, as he's writing to the church in Colossae, that in all things Christ, who is
the head of the church, who's my Savior, my God, my everything, that in all things He
must have the preeminence.
And we find that here the question is, what agreement hath the temple of God with idols?
Have you ever read the passages of Scripture in the Old Testament when you read about the
wickedness of the people of God and how they would bring idols into the temple?
And you read how that God would raise up a godly king, and you read of some of the revivals
that took place during the time of Judah's history, and you read how the Bible says that
they cleansed the temple.
What did they do?
They were getting those idols that had been brought into the temple and they're ridding
them.
And in the life of the ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ, on two separate occasions during
His ministry, the Bible says that He went up there, He drove out, He drove out those
that were up there on the temple mount, those that were violating the money changers and
etc.
And He drove them out, He turned over tables, so on and so forth.
Why?
Why did He have to do it twice?
Because if you're not careful, it'll creep back in in your life.
It'll creep back in.
Listen, the songwriter said, turn your eyes upon Jesus and the things of this world will
grow strangely dim.
But the reality is that when we're not really walking with Christ as we ought to, when we're
not in the book like we're supposed to be, when we're not abiding in Him and having that
sweet communion and fellowship with Him, it's really easy for the things of this world to
look really good.
We find that He says, what agreement hath the temple of God with idols?
And we've spoken and we've referenced about some Old Testament passages and how sad to
read of the magnificence of the temple and all that it was designed to be and the heart
that David had to make a temple and God didn't allow him to do it and for Solomon to build
that temple and then to read of various times in their history of the idols coming in.
But then notice what Paul says in verse 16.
He says, ye are the temple of the living God.
Now he told them this prior in the first letter.
Look back, if you will, in 1 Corinthians chapter 6.
In 1 Corinthians chapter number 6, we find that the apostle Paul is writing to this church
and he mentions to them many things in this chapter, but I want to pick it up and grab
the context beginning in verse number 9.
Notice what Paul says.
In 1 Corinthians 6 and verse 9 he says, know ye not that the unrighteous shall not inherit
the kingdom of God?
Be not deceived, neither fornicators nor idolaters nor adulterers nor effeminate nor abusers
of themselves with mankind nor thieves nor covetous nor drunkards nor revilers nor extortioners
shall inherit the kingdom of God.
And I love verse number 11 for Paul says, and such were some of you.
Listen, not one of us was born saved.
We had to be born again.
And he says, and such were some of you, but what a great conjunction.
He says, ye are washed, but ye are sanctified, but ye are justified in the name of the Lord
Jesus and by the Spirit of our God.
Isn't that wonderful?
But think about, listen, I'm not what I used to be.
God's grace is amazing.
Paul would stand and say as he's writing to Timothy that it's a faithful saying and worthy
of all acceptation that Christ Jesus came into the world to save sinners of whom I am
chief.
He didn't come to save the righteous, those religious leaders that said, look at me, look
at how good I am.
I do this and I do this.
You can never get to heaven that way.
It might make you feel good.
And in that particular culture, they were able to elevate to a certain position of prestige
because of all that they did.
But Jesus came to save sinners.
And I'm so thankful for that for the Bible says for all have sinned and come short of
the glory of God.
He saved my soul.
And he said, and such were some of you.
Past tense.
Remember Paul?
He says, he gives the testimony in the book of Galatians that he which once persecuted
now preaches.
Hallelujah.
You read Acts chapter number nine and you read about the intent that Paul had at the
beginning of the passage followed by the preaching of the gospel at the end of the passage.
What happened?
He was saved by the grace of God.
He's a new creature.
And here he says in verse 12, all things are lawful unto me, but all things are not expedient.
Oh, I could preach a whole message here on this simple phrase of scripture.
The reality is this, just because I can doesn't mean I should.
We've twisted up the whole truth of liberty.
We really have.
Because what Paul says to these that are dealing with the subject of liberty, you don't need
to turn there, but in Galatians chapter number five, he says, for brethren, you have been
called unto liberty, only use not liberty for an occasion to the flesh, but by love
serve one another.
And he says, all things are lawful unto me, but all things are not expedient.
All things are lawful for me, but I will not be brought unto the power of any.
Meats for the belly and the belly for meats, but God shall destroy both it and them.
Now the body is not for fornication, but for the Lord and the Lord for the body.
And God hath both raised up the Lord and will also raise up us by his own power.
Aren't you thankful for the truth of the resurrection?
In chapter 15 of this same book, Paul begins to talk about how Christ is the first fruits.
We have that truth and promise, the assurance of resurrection.
In verse 15, know ye not that your bodies are the members of Christ?
Shall I then take the members of Christ and make them the members of an harlot?
Do you see how pointed the apostle Paul is being here?
What is his answer?
Lord forbid, you've been saved.
Every part of you, body, soul, and spirit is to be for God.
He says in verse number 16, what?
Know ye not that he which is joined to an harlot is one body?
For two saith he shall be one flesh.
But he that is joined unto the Lord is one spirit.
Flee fornication.
Every sin that a man doeth is without the body, but he that committeth fornication sinneth
against his own body.
And then verse 19 and 20, really I grabbed all the context to get here, what?
Know ye not that your body is the temple of the Holy Ghost which is in you?
Which ye have of God, and ye are not your own.
For ye are bought with a price.
Therefore glorify God in your body and your spirit, which are God's.
Paul says that our bodies are the temple of the Holy Ghost.
At the moment that you trust at Christ as your Savior, the Holy Spirit of God indwelled
you.
As you walk with God on this Christian journey, there are periods in time in which you can
be filled with self or filled with his spirit.
We're indwelled at the moment of salvation and we are to be filled continuously on this
journey, but the reality is that there are times in which we're really filled with self,
not with his spirit.
And he says that the Holy Ghost is in you, and he says this, that you're bought with
a price.
What was that price?
Well, it's the precious blood of Jesus.
He did for us what we could not do for ourselves.
And he says that the outworking of this truth, when we truly understand this and how it's
revealed in us, he says, therefore glorify God in your body and your spirit, which are
God's.
Whether, therefore, you eat or drink or whatsoever you do, do all for the glory of God.
And we find that the apostle Paul is saying to these believers back in 2 Corinthians chapter
6, as he's asked these questions and he says, what agreement, in verse 16, hath the temple
of God with idols?
And then he says, for ye are the temple of the living God.
Just consider that for a moment.
You're saved.
You're the temple of the living God.
Praise the Lord.
He says, as God hath said, I will dwell in them and walk in them and I will be their
God and they shall be my people.
What a joy to know Christ as our personal Savior.
We find the counsel, we find the explanation, and we find the conclusion in these couple
of verses of Scripture as Paul has already expressed his care for the Corinthians, but
now he's given his counsel to the Corinthians.
And in verse 17 he says, wherefore, come out from among them and be ye separate, saith
the Lord, and touch not the unclean thing and I will receive you.
This and will be a father unto you.
You shall be my sons and daughters, saith the Lord Almighty.
Notice verse number 1 of chapter 7, having therefore these promises, dearly beloved,
let us cleanse ourselves from all filthiness of the flesh and spirit, perfecting holiness
in the fear of God.
If you look at these verses of Scripture, Paul is not saying that these folks need to
be saved.
They're saved already.
The reality is that they've been influenced and tainted by the world.
And he says to them, as we consider the conclusion that we're to come out from among them and
be separate, and then you consider the promises of the fact that he says, that I will receive
you, that I will be a father unto you, you shall be my sons and daughters, saith the
Lord Almighty.
Listen, that's the fellowship that we enjoy with our Savior.
It's not talking about salvation in this passage of Scripture, it's talking about that fellowship
that we have, that communion that we have, that as we're abiding in him and we're walking
with him and what sweet communion we can have with him.
Our God is holy, holy, holy, holy.
And we find that he calls us as his children to be holy in all manner of conversation.
We find that sin hinders our walk with God, it causes us to have our prayers hindered.
He says that if I regard iniquity in my heart, the Lord will not hear me.
We understand the truth of how our sin will hinder our fellowship with our God.
And so here as he's speaking at the end of the passage, he's saying, listen, you live.
Remember what Jesus said in John 17, you're in the world but you're not of the world.
Remember the truth of John 13, that Jesus washed the feet of the disciples.
And Peter says, no, no, no, Lord.
And Jesus says, if I don't, you have no part of me.
And Peter's like, well, then wash everywhere.
And Peter says, listen, if you've already been washed, you don't need not that I only
wash your feet.
What's he speaking of?
Peter, you've already been saved, but you live in the world and your feet get dirty.
You need to be cleansed.
Notice in verse 7, having therefore these, or verse 1 of chapter 7, excuse me, having
therefore these promises, dearly beloved, let us cleanse ourselves.
How do we do that?
It's not my own work.
It's the truth of God's word.
As I take the truth of God's word in the ministry of God's spirit through his word, he cleanses
us.
Again, it's not talking about salvation.
He's talking about that holiness, that sanctification.
In the book of Ephesians, in chapter number 5, the Bible says, speaking of the church
and how he's given the truth of husbands, love your wives, even as Christ so loved the
church and gave himself for it.
But then verse 26 of Ephesians 5 says that he might sanctify and cleanse it with the
washing of water by the word, that he might present it, that's Christ presenting his bride,
the church, to himself a glorious church, not having spot or wrinkle or any such thing,
but that it should be holy and without blemish.
That's what God's desire is.
We find that as we look at God's word in the book of James in chapter number 1, he says
this, pure religion in verse 27, and undefiled before God and the Father is this, to visit
the fatherless and widows in their affliction and to keep himself unspotted from the world.
That's Paul saying, come out from among them, be not unequally yoked.
We've heard many times where a parent will say and use the analogy of a good apple and
a bad apple, and they'll use that whole analogy, if you have a bad apple, it's going to cause
the others to be rotted and bad, and we understand that we use that, but we find that the biblical
truth is that Paul says, be not deceived, and he tells us the truth that we are to understand
that evil communications corrupt good manners.
That's the Bible truth.
Evil communications corrupt good manners.
And we find that he says, you're different now, you're saved, you're Christ, you belong
to him, you're a child of the king, I'm no longer what I used to be, and so how is it
impacting my behavior, my associations, my fellowships are different now, why?
Because there's truly no fellowship and communion and agreement and concord between what I was
and what I now am, between what I am and those who are not what I am, does that make sense?
And we find that Paul is saying this truth of separation is that I separate from the
world, but at the same time it's unto the Lord.
I'm separating from something to someone, from the world, love not the world, neither
the things that are in the world.
What does he tell them?
He says, well, the things of the world, they're going to pass away, but he that doeth the
will of God abideth forever, in 1 John chapter 2.
And we find that here, as we would understand the conclusion of having that sweet fellowship
that is enjoyed by those who are heeding the counsel that is given, this counsel that
is provided by the apostle Paul is given to benefit the hearers, that they would understand
that they could have that sweet communion and that sweet fellowship, they could enjoy
that with their Savior.
We sing the song, there's nothing between my soul and my Savior, and I hope that we
could be in that position where truly there's nothing between my soul and my Savior, that
I'm enjoying that sweet fellowship, that I'm keeping myself unspotted from the world, that
I'm being cleansed by the Word of God and the work of the Spirit of God.
That's why it's so important that we preach and teach, read your Bible, get in your Bible,
be in church, hear the preaching of God's Word.
Why?
Because God uses His Word to cleanse us.
You spend hours upon hours upon hours in the world.
You know what's happened to many of God's people is we get used to it.
We get numb to it.
The things that once caused an individual to blush, to be embarrassed, it's just commonplace
today.
We've just gotten used to it.
We invite it in on our phones, on our televisions, in our associations.
We hear it, we see it, and we become numb to it.
Hours upon hours that we spend in the world, and unfortunately some spend very few, even
minutes in God's Word.
It ought not be.
We need the truth of this book.
Let me remind you of two things.
One Old Testament, one New Testament as we close.
Go to the book of Leviticus, if you will, in chapter 18.
Leviticus chapter 18.
Leviticus is one of those books in the Old Testament that gets a bad rap by a lot of
people.
Oh, I get to the book of Leviticus and I just can't understand it.
It's so hard and all these kind of things.
And I've said over the years that as I look at it, I think the book of Exodus provides
for us a record of how God got His people out of the world.
The book of Leviticus deals with how God got the world out of His people.
Because God saved His people.
He delivered them.
The Egyptian bondage is recorded and the deliverance from Egypt is given to us in the book of Exodus.
But those people, they had lived in Egypt.
And then God's going to get the world, Egypt, out of them.
And the longer you were living in the world before you got saved, the more of the world
that's in you that needs to get out of you.
And unfortunately, as Christians that are walking with God for any length of time, sometimes
we take that guard down and we let some more of that world in and we've got to be careful.
So notice what he says in Leviticus 18.
It's a great principle that's given in verse number one.
The Lord spake unto Moses saying, speak unto the children of Israel and say unto them,
I am the Lord your God.
Notice in verse three, a two-fold principle that is given.
He says this, after the doings of the land of Egypt, wherein ye dwelt, shall ye not do.
And after the doings of the land of Canaan, whither I bring you, shall ye not do.
Neither shall you walk in their ordinances.
So what is God saying?
I'm bringing you out of Egypt and I'm going to take you into Canaan, but I don't want
you to do the things that you saw in Egypt and I don't want you to do the things that
you're going to see in Canaan.
Because neither one of those things are my things.
So what does he tell them in verse number four?
Ye shall do my judgments and keep mine ordinances, to walk therein.
I am the Lord your God.
Ye shall therefore keep my statutes and my judgments.
Notice this, which if a man do, he shall live in them.
I am the Lord.
Wow.
God says I'm bringing you out and I'm bringing you in, but I don't want you to do the things
that you saw there.
I don't want you to do the things that you're going to see there.
I want you to do my judgments, my statutes.
I want you to keep mine ordinances.
We do God's work, God's way.
We live according to the principles of God's word.
And here's the New Testament truth that I'll finish with in the book of James.
In James chapter number four, I love how pointed the Bible is.
How direct the Bible is.
Sometimes we can shy away from being so direct.
Bart and I were talking a couple of weeks ago, and the phraseology.
and I've used it before as well, where sometimes people like to tiptoe through the tulips.
I'm thankful that God's Word is direct, and I want you to see the principle that's given
here.
We're talking about biblical separation, come out from among them and be separate, the importance,
the counsel that's given.
He says in verse number 4 of James 4, ye adulterers and adulteresses, know ye not that the friendship
of the world is enmity with God?
Whosoever therefore will be a friend of the world is the enemy of God.
That's direct, that's pointed.
I like to be liked as much as anyone else would like to be liked, but we can't bend
on the truth of God's Word to accommodate, to be liked, to be relevant.
God's Word is relevant.
God's Word is true.
God changes not.
And this morning as we look at the passage of Scripture in 2 Corinthians chapter 6 and
the beginning verse of chapter 7, we find that Paul has a heart for those that he's
ministering to.
He says, I care about you, I love you, my mouth is open unto you, our heart is enlarged.
Like, I know that God has given me truth and I want to give it to you and I want you to
receive it because I know if you receive it that you'll benefit from it.
It will profit you.
But you're resisting me and therefore you're also resisting my message which is God's message
because you have angst in your heart against me.
So what's he saying?
Open your heart.
Because God has entrusted the man of God with the message from God for the people of God.
And he says, here's the counsel.
After he tells them how much he cares about them and loves them, here's the counsel.
Be not unequally yoked together with unbelievers.
And then he explains it with all of these questions that are thought-provoking that
cause each of us to reach the same conclusion.
There's no agreement.
And so therefore, we're to be separate.
Here's what I've learned.
If we truly walk with God, if we truly walk with God and we abide in Him, you know what's
going to happen?
The world's going to separate from you.
You say, I don't know if I could do it.
They're going to separate from you.
They're not going to.
Why?
Because darkness doesn't like light.
I found it to be the case in my life.
And sometimes we wrestle so much with this, but we just walk with God, keep our eyes on
the Lord, understanding I'm not going to make these friendships with the world.
I'm not going to get there.
But you'll start finding that they don't want to hang around with you anymore anyway.
Why?
Because there's something different about you.
There's something different about you.
What is it?
The Holy Ghost lives within you.
You're saved.
You're a new creature.
Put off, put on.
Biblical separation, it's so vitally important that we, just as the church in Corinth would
understand that, don't be tainted by the world.
Don't allow the world to influence the church, the churches to influence the world.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for your word and the directness of your word, the truth of your word, the
power of your word.
God, I pray that you would help us this morning to take heed to the counsel.
These believers in Corinth, as this book was originally written and delivered, received
the counsel and they had a decision to make on whether they would heed the counsel or
reject the counsel.
Continue in their own ways and reject or they would accept and follow the truth of
your word.
I pray this morning that as we still sit here in this place, Lord, we understand the importance
of biblical separation.
I pray that you'd help us personally to take and implement the truth of your word in our
lives, that we'd please you, that we would keep ourselves unspotted from the world, that
we would allow your word and your spirit to do a work in and through us.
Lord, this morning, if there's one not sure of heaven, what they need is to be saved by
the grace of God.
I know that you're able to save.
I pray that your spirit would convict of their sin of Christ's righteousness of judgment
to come.
Your spirit would move in a very distinct way.
They would trust Christ.
I pray that in the moment of invitation, Lord, in the quietness of the moment, that you would
help us, Lord, to be doers of the word and not hearers only.
Move and work as only you can and we'll give you the glory for it's in Christ's name we
pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.