42, and I am thankful for the blessings of the Lord.
Had a number of folks that were traveling
that God has brought back safely.
Have some folks that continue to travel.
Want you to pray for them.
And then Brother Fernando,
his grandmother had surgery last evening
and he sent me a text.
I mentioned this in Sunday School
and he sent me a text and we prayed
and we're thankful that that surgery went well
and she's recovering well
and so we praise the Lord for that.
And it's amazing our God does here
and answer prayer, amen.
And every time we go to the Lord in prayer,
we have that confidence knowing that he hears us
and that he's able and we certainly are encouraged
each time he answers prayer.
Genesis chapter 42 this evening
and we'll look at the entire chapter.
Genesis 42, one through 38.
I'm not gonna read the entire text this evening.
I'm gonna just kind of jump through the text
of scripture this evening
as we deal with this subject matter.
But notice beginning in verse number one in Genesis 42,
the Bible says,
now when Jacob saw that there was corn in Egypt,
Jacob said unto his sons,
why do you look one upon another?
And he said, behold,
I have heard that there's corn in Egypt.
Get you down thither and buy for us from fence
that we may live and not die.
And Joseph's 10 brethren went down to buy corn in Egypt.
But Benjamin, Joseph's brother,
Jacob sent not with his brethren
for he said, lest peradventure mischief
befall him.
The sons of Israel came to buy corn
among those that came for the famine
was in the land of Canaan.
We'll dig in further through the text
as we study through this portion of scripture this evening.
But you understand that the seven years of great plenty
had ended and the seven years of dearth began
according to the end of chapter number 41
of the book of Genesis.
We find that Joseph was diligent
during those seven years of great plenty.
And we find that because of his diligence
and his obedience to follow that
which God had revealed to him,
we find that there was food in Egypt.
Now we understand that as we look at this
and dig into chapter number 42,
it says now when Jacob saw that there was corn in Egypt.
And so we find that as we back up just a little bit
into chapter 41, by way of introduction,
we find that the Bible tells us in verse number 54,
notice of chapter 41, verse 54.
And the seven years of dearth began to come
according as Joseph had said,
and the dearth was in all lands.
But in the land of Egypt, there was bread.
Again, you see in verse number 57,
notice it says in all countries
came into Egypt to Joseph for to buy corn.
Why?
Because the famine was so sore in all lands.
We find that there in chapter number 42
in verse number five, at the end of the verse,
it says that the famine was in the land of Canaan as well.
And so we find that as we look at this portion of scripture,
I've titled the message this evening,
Joseph's brethren went down to buy corn in Egypt.
And you see that in verse number three,
and we find that throughout this passage of scripture
that God records for us this journey
that these 10 brothers took from Canaan to Egypt
for the purpose of getting food, of buying corn.
And we find that as God would rehearse for us
the account as it takes place,
that these 10 brothers, of course,
they meet their brother, Joseph.
Their brother who they had sold into slavery,
their brother that nearly 20 years had passed
since the last time they had seen him.
And we find that Joseph now
is in this elevated position of leadership.
We've studied through the book of Genesis.
We've understood the things that have taken place.
And we find that now these brothers,
because of what Jacob understood to be true,
in verse number one of chapter 42,
the Bible says that Jacob saw
that there was corn in Egypt.
In chapter 42 in verse number two,
it says that Jacob heard there was corn in Egypt.
And so Jacob, upon understanding
the fact that there was a source of food
and understanding the circumstances
in which they were facing,
it was a real bad time
because of this great dearth
that had came upon the land.
And notice at the end of verse number two,
he says that we may live and not die.
That gives us some insight
with regard to the conditions
and how bad it really was.
And so we find that Jacob,
understanding all of these things
and what he was experiencing,
we find that he sends his boys,
these 10 sons, to Egypt.
He did not send Benjamin, the youngest.
Why?
Well, because he'd already lost Joseph
and he did not want any mischief
to fall upon Benjamin.
In his mind, remember,
Jacob had every part of his being
believe that Joseph was killed.
When his brothers came back
and they said, hey, we found this.
Do you know whose this is?
What was it that they showed him?
The coat of many colors
that Jacob had given to his son
and they had dipped it in blood.
Remember, they killed an animal,
they dipped it in blood
and they said, we found this.
And what did Jacob believe?
A wild beast hath devoured him.
He believed that he was dead.
And the brothers, his sons,
his own sons allowed him to believe that lie.
And now we find that we come to chapter 42.
So many, I mean, 20 years,
at least a minimum of 20 years has passed
between the time in which Jacob,
his sons sold Joseph into slavery.
And now as they're dealing with this great famine,
and we find that as we read through Genesis chapter 42,
that as we look at the dialogue
that God provides of this record and this account
and all the interactions that take place,
really what we find is that God is at work.
God is working.
In fact, as we look at this portion of scripture
and we look at the circumstances
that are recorded here in Genesis 42,
it really reminds us that God is always at work.
God is always at work.
We may not recognize it, we may not see it,
but we can rest assured that God is always at work.
And we find that as we look at this portion of scripture,
I'm going to deal with two thoughts very quickly
so that we can spend the bulk of our time
on my final thought this evening.
But when I think about looking at Genesis 42
and consider the fact that God is at work,
we notice first of all, God is working locally.
When I say that he's working locally,
I'm saying he's working in Egypt.
Joseph was there, and you understand all the circumstances
with regard to the previous chapters
and all that we've studied in the life of Joseph,
and we see how God is working.
God had given Joseph the opportunity,
the ability to be able to interpret the dream,
to be able to come up with a plan
so that there would be food in Egypt.
God was at work in Egypt.
God was at work, not only locally,
but God was working globally.
We look at this particular portion of scripture,
and we find that this famine impacted more than just Egypt.
It was Pharaoh that had the dream.
It was Pharaoh that understood through this dream
that God gave, through Joseph's interpretation,
what was going to come
and how God was going to bring it to pass,
but understand that the famine impacted
more than just Egypt.
In fact, it says in verse 57
that all countries came into Egypt.
Why?
Because in Egypt, there was food,
and so God, listen, he knows where Jacob and the boys are.
He knows that they're in Canaan, and God is working.
He's working locally in Egypt.
He's working in Joseph's life.
He's working through those circumstances there,
but we find that he's working throughout the entire world,
and we find that here, the entire known world,
and we find that this particular famine
had an impact there in Canaan.
We see it in chapter 42 and verse number five.
Also in chapter 46 and verse number 31,
the Bible plainly tells us
that Joseph said unto his brethren
and unto his father's house,
I will go up and show Pharaoh and say unto him,
my brethren in my father's house,
which are in the land of Canaan, are come unto me,
and so they came from Canaan.
Why?
Because there was a famine.
God's working locally.
He's working globally,
but where I really wanna focus our attention this evening
and dig into this portion of Scripture
is that God is working personally.
Our God is a personal God.
I'm thankful that God is at work in Egypt,
and God is at work throughout all of these lands
as we look in Genesis chapter number 42,
but the reality is that we see
as we dig into the portion of Scripture
that God is working in the lives of individuals,
and God still today, listen, God is working locally.
God is working globally,
but the amazing truth of how God is at work
is that he's at work personally.
He's working in people's lives.
We may not always see it.
We may be praying, and we don't see the results,
and we don't see how God is working,
but we can be confident,
and we can rest assured that God is at work.
God is at work in our lives.
As we dig through Genesis chapter 42,
and we begin to see how God is working
and what God is doing,
and how he, being an omnipresent God,
he's everywhere, but he's working
because he's a personal God.
He's working in the lives of individuals.
Can I say this this evening,
even before we dig into the rest
of the portion of Scripture tonight?
Sometimes when God is at work,
at work, it's uncomfortable. It's uncomfortable. Sometimes when God is at work, we might resist
it. We don't like it. You know, sometimes God is working and He's kind of peeling back
the layers of the skin of the onion, so to speak, to expose some things in our lives
that have to be dealt with. And you know, sometimes when God is at work, it's an uncomfortable
thing. And sometimes we don't really like it. But God is at work. We ought to rejoice
that God is at work. We ought to rejoice that God is interested in working in our lives
personally. We ought to rejoice when we come to the house of God and we hear the preaching
of God's Word. When we go in our daily devotions and we open up the Word of God and we begin
to read and God begins to prick our hearts through the personal reading, through the
public preaching, we ought to rejoice that God would work in our lives individually.
It's a blessed thing. I've said, not recently, but I've said over the years that it's a good
thing when God's people deal with that circumstance in which we feel the preaching and God's Word
will bring in our lives some conviction. Conviction is a good thing. When my toes and your toes
are stepped on, it's a good thing because God's at work. Notice as we look at this portion
of Scripture and consider that God is working personally, I would say, number one, that
God is working in Joseph's life. God is working in Joseph's life. We find that Joseph is here.
Notice we stopped reading in verse number five. Pick it up with me in verse number six
of Genesis 42. The Bible says, and Joseph was the governor over the land. Now we knew
that, did we not? We knew, based on studying through this portion of Scripture and studying
through the life of Joseph, we know that God elevated Joseph to a place of great authority.
And we find that Joseph is the governor of the land. We understand that his brothers
have no clue that Joseph is the governor of the land. But Joseph is the governor of the
land and he it was that sold to all the people of the land. Now I want you in your minds
eye, we'll finish reading verse number six here in just a moment, but in your mind's
eye this evening, I want you to consider the busyness of where Joseph is. I want you to
understand the number of people that would be in and out trying to buy food. Listen,
if you're in a position in which there's a great famine, so much so that you're considering
that you're going to die as a result of this famine and you need food, it's going to be
a busy place. There are going to be a lot of people in and out trying to buy food, trying
to survive. And we find that the people, all the people of the land, they came there
to where Joseph was. In fact, in verse 57 of chapter 41, it says, and all countries
came into Egypt to Joseph for to buy corn. Remember when the people, when the Egyptians
cried to Pharaoh, we have no food. What did he say? Go to Joseph. God's working in Joseph's
life. Why do I say that? Well, look at the rest of verse number six. And Joseph's brethren
came. And Joseph's brethren came. And Joseph's brethren came. We read through the text and
we understand that Joseph recognizes who they are. They don't know who he is. But when I
think about Joseph's brothers coming and it says that they bowed down themselves before
him with their faces to the earth and Joseph saw his brethren and he knew them, but made
himself strange unto them and spake roughly unto them. And he said unto them, whence
came ye? And they said, from the land of Canaan to buy food. And so we find here in these
verses of scripture that God is working in Joseph's life. Why do I say that? Well, understand
that Joseph had some dreams about his brothers bowing down and the authority that he would
have and we see that this is being fulfilled here. But I also want you to understand that
Joseph is now coming face to face with the brothers that hated him, that wanted to kill
him, that wanted to, and eventually sold him into slavery. I want you to think about the
emotions of that. Listen, as we look in the life of Joseph, go back to chapter 41, if
you will, and look in verses 51 and 52 of Genesis chapter 41 and I want you to see that
as we look at this portion of scripture here and we understand what's taking place that
God tells us in Genesis 41 and verse number 51, and Joseph called the name of the firstborn
Manasseh. For God said he hath made me forget all my toil and all my father's house and
the name of the second called he Ephraim. For God hath caused me to be fruitful in the
land of my affliction. We studied this several weeks ago when we looked at Joseph and we
talked about the principle of perspective from this portion of scripture and the fact
that he names his firstborn Manasseh, which means forgetfulness. He names his secondborn
Ephraim, which means fruitfulness. And we looked through and we dealt with that and
we understood that God had been working in the life of Joseph. But I want you to understand
that now as Joseph's brothers come face to face with him, that what he had believed in
and what he had handled now, those emotions are raw. He's face to face with his brothers.
How are you going to respond? How are you going to deal with that? Listen, I wonder
this evening if there's anything in you, someone walks into a room and you have ought against
them. I mean maybe they did you wrong. We're supposed to forgive. Joseph says forgetfulness
and fruitfulness and naming his sons. But you know when you come face to face with someone
that hurt you, they didn't seek his forgiveness, did they? No. Man, God's at work in the life
of Joseph. I believe that God is proving some things in the life of Joseph. You know God
will prove some things in our lives. It's easy to say things. There's a whole different
story to actually live it. It's one thing to say I forgive that person but then to interact
with that person. Would you agree? You say I forgive him but I never want to see him
again. Have you ever heard somebody say that? Sure you have. Is that true forgiveness? I
mean listen, remember sometimes when God's at work it's not comfortable. It's not comfortable.
Joseph is he standing there and he sees his brothers. It's been 20 years. His brothers
don't recognize him. No doubt there's been a great transformation in his even physical
appearance and then of course with wearing all of the Egyptian garb that he would have
on they don't recognize he speaks Egyptian no doubt and he's speaking through a translator
as you'd find as we continue studying through these chapters and we find that he knew his
brothers. God was at work. God was at work. We find that God is working in the life of
Joseph but I would say that God is not only working in the life of Joseph but God is working
in the lives of Joseph's brothers. And really that's the bulk of this portion of scripture.
Look in verse number 8. The Bible says, And Joseph knew his brethren, but they knew him
not. And Joseph remembered the dreams which he dreamed of them, and said unto them, Ye
are spies, to see the nakedness of the land, ye are come. And they said unto him, Nay,
my lord, but to buy food are thy servants come. We are all one man's sons, we are true
men, thy servants are no spies. And he said unto them, Nay, but to see the nakedness of
the land, ye are come. They said, Thy servants are twelve brethren, the sons of one man
in the land of Canaan. Behold, the youngest is this day with our father, and one is not.
Who is that? That's how they refer to him. One is not. They're talking to Joseph. The
one who they say is not. And we find that through this portion of scripture that Joseph,
I believe, as you study the life of Joseph, he was a man that sought the Lord, he followed
the Lord, he obeyed the Lord. I believe that in this interaction between Joseph and his
brothers, he is in obedience to God. When he's speaking roughly to them in all the
circumstances that are going on, I believe that Joseph is doing exactly what God has
instructed him to do. Joseph's not, he's not walking in the flesh in this portion of scripture.
I believe that Joseph is obedient to the Lord, but God is working in the lives of those brothers.
We're going to see it here in just a moment. Notice with me, the Bible says that he says
that they come to see the nakedness of the land in verse 14. And Joseph said unto them,
That is it that I spake unto you, saying, You're spies. Hereby ye shall be approved.
By the life of Pharaoh ye shall not go forth hence, except your youngest brother come hither.
Send one of you, and let him fetch your brother, and ye shall be kept in prison, that your
words may be proved, whether there be any truth in you, or else by the life of Pharaoh,
surely, you're spies. And he, Joseph, put them, his brothers, all together into ward
three days. I think those were three long days. Don't you think so? They didn't know
what they were going to experience when they got to Egypt. They know that they were given
instruction from Dad to go buy corn in Egypt, and they arrive, and they immediately have
this interaction. Perhaps as they're waiting in line, as many are there to buy food, perhaps
they see person after person that stands, and they get their food, and they go on their
way. And then all of a sudden, they arrive, and there's all this questioning, and they're
put into ward. They're put into prison. There's this interaction. We find that
for three days, the Bible does not tell us
during this three-day period of time what they discuss.
However, when we look at verse number 21,
I think God gives us some insight
as to what they were discussing,
and what they were discussing were events
that took place over 20 years ago.
Notice with me that Joseph will keep it in context
in verse 18, after these three days, he says,
and Joseph said unto them, the third day,
this do and live, and then notice this phrase,
for I fear God, wow, now think about it,
Jacob sent his boys from Canaan to Egypt,
no doubt they had preconceived ideas about the Egyptians,
about their religion, about their polytheism,
and all of the things that they would be exposed to
and would deal with, and then as they're standing there,
speaking to the governor of the country,
the one who's in charge, he calls them out of prison
on the third day and says, for I fear God.
Wow, I believe God is working in the lives of these boys,
and God is going to continue as we look
through this portion of scripture,
how God is working and moving, he says this,
Joseph to his brothers in verse 19,
if ye be true men, let one of your brethren
be bound in the house of your prison,
go ye, carry corn for the famine of your houses,
but bring your youngest brother unto me,
so shall your words be verified,
and ye shall not die, and they did so.
And then verse 21, it says, and they said one to another,
notice what they say, we find that Simeon remains in jail,
and we'll look through here, but notice in verse 21,
as they wander off, as they leave from the presence
of Joseph, they leave and the Bible says that they say,
we are guilty concerning our brother.
Why did they have that thought?
Conviction, God was at work, nothing was said
about what they did to Joseph, nothing was said,
there was no insight that this was Joseph
that they were speaking to, it was God working
through these circumstances, it was God working
to bring conviction in the lives of these boys, why?
Because ultimately, God wants to bring them back to himself.
That's what God's doing, and as they leave, listen,
nothing is said about Joseph, the only thing that's said
about Joseph and one is not, and they say, we are guilty,
we are guilty, we are guilty about what?
Our brother, we are guilty concerning our brother.
I think for 20 long years, these things, it haunted them,
it haunted them what they did, why?
Because they never got it right, they never dealt with it.
I don't know how many times Jacob might have said
something about Joseph, and every time Dad would say
something about Joseph, how do you think
the 10 brothers feel?
They knew the truth, they knew what they did.
How do you think they felt when they saw Jacob
bereaving his son, I mean, he's weeping, no doubt.
I want you to think about it tonight, listen,
there are, and I know that the Bible doesn't tell us
all of this, but you know as a human being,
there are certain special events in your life,
there are things that take place in your life
that remind us, that trigger things in our lives,
maybe you've never heard of it, maybe you've never seen it,
but it triggers things in our lives,
maybe there's a special day, maybe it's a birthday,
as we would celebrate if we think about our own culture
and our own society, and you have a son who is not,
what happens on the day of their birth?
You think about that, do you not?
And when you think about that, perhaps you talk about that,
and those brothers that are under conviction,
and now they're standing there, listen,
all they wanted to do was buy food, but God was working,
God was working, God knew where they were,
God had orchestrated some events, why?
Because our God is a sovereign God,
and he had worked in such a way to elevate Joseph
to a place of prominence and of position,
and he had worked so that this famine would affect
not only Egypt, but also Canaan,
and all these other lands were impacted,
and now the brothers come, and they say,
we are guilty concerning our brother,
and that we saw, notice the rest of verse 21,
we saw the anguish of his soul when he besought us,
and we would not hear,
therefore is this distress come upon us.
I believe that these brothers were convinced
that the reason for their trouble
was rooted in what happened 20 years earlier.
Do you not, when you read verse 21?
I mean, no one had to convince them of it.
You know who was working?
God, God was working.
It's amazing, sometimes I'll preach a message,
and someone will say something,
and I'm like, I don't even think I said anything about that.
It really wasn't even something
that was part of the message,
but you know what happened?
God was at work, God was moving, God was working.
I've sat in preaching services,
I've sat and I've listened to preaching,
and God will trigger through something that is said,
a verse that I read, another thought,
and I'll go over, and maybe I'll miss
the next few sentences that the preacher says,
but God's working in my life,
and that's how God works.
A journey that was expected to simply go
and buy some corn and go home
to provide food for the family.
God is at work, God is at work.
Notice the Bible says in verse 22,
and Reuben answered, he answered them saying,
spake I not unto you, saying,
do not sin against the child, and you would not hear.
Therefore, behold, also, his blood is required.
I mean, the conversation continues.
Reuben, he's going back, listen,
he remembers with clarity the conversation
that had taken place.
Remember, Reuben was the one that went back to the pit,
and Joseph wasn't there,
because they sold him into slavery,
and we find here in verse 23,
and they knew not that Joseph understood them,
for he spake unto them by an interpreter.
Joseph is standing there hearing all of this.
He's hearing this conversation between his brothers.
He's hearing, listen, he didn't bring it up.
It's an awesome thing when God works.
Sometimes a preacher gets accused of,
you're preaching that because you knew this was going on,
and so on and so forth.
Listen, if you preach the whole counsel of God,
you just let God work, honestly.
And when God works, you just sit back and say,
look at what God was doing.
Listen, I think it was Brother Hummel,
maybe it was Brother Mershon,
talked about someone coming and saying,
the preacher must have told you all about my life,
because all you've done is preach about the things
that I've been dealing with.
He's like, I don't have any idea.
God's dealing in your life.
God's at work.
Joseph didn't say anything about what happened 20 years ago,
but those boys were under conviction, deep conviction.
Notice in verse 24,
and he turned himself about from them and wept.
Joseph, again, remember we started out,
God was at work in Joseph's life.
He returned to them again and communed with them
and took from them Simeon and bound him before their eyes.
And Joseph commanded to fill their sacks with corn.
Notice this, and to restore every man's money into a sack.
To give them provision for the way.
And thus did he unto them.
And they laid their asses with the corn and departed thence.
So we see what's happening.
Simeon remains behind,
nine of them are now going to travel back.
And Joseph gives this instruction.
Remember, he's the one in charge, he's the authority.
And he commands that their sacks be filled with corn,
but he also commands to restore every man's money,
notice where, into a sack.
He didn't just give the money back to them.
He said, put it back in their sack.
And we find that he also provided for them,
for their journey to give them provision for the way.
Verse 27, these nine brothers, Simeon is left in prison.
The nine brothers, they journey.
And it says, as one of them, we don't know which one,
opened his sack to give his ass for vendor in the inn,
he espied his money, for behold, it was in his sack's mouth.
Now he knew that he had given the money.
He knew that he bought the corn.
And now he opens up to be able to give his animal,
the provision, the food.
And as he does so, he sees the money.
Oh, praise the Lord, God gave us our money.
That's not how they respond.
It's not how they respond, why?
Because God is at work.
Notice in verse 28, and he said unto his brethren,
my money is restored.
But I think it was this kind of tone of,
my money is restored?
Like, what's going on?
And lo, it is even in my sack.
And their heart, notice what it says, failed them.
Failed them.
And they were afraid.
Notice what they say to each other.
What is this that God hath done unto us?
God was at work. God was at work. And we find that in the lives of these brothers we see
it very distinctly through these events that are recorded in Genesis 42 that God is working.
Listen sometimes I've mentioned twice now and for a third time sometimes it's uncomfortable
when God is at work. Sometimes it means we need to deal with things that quite honestly
we just really don't want to deal with. You know what I mean by that? Sometimes we just
rather not deal with stuff. But God says I'm working in your life. I want you to be right
with me. We're going to observe the Lord's Supper tonight and only as God could do it.
I had written on my calendar, my desk calendar that we'd observe the Lord's Supper tonight
months ago. But I never communicated that to Holly to put in the bulletin. Yesterday
morning I was praying and God impressed upon my heart hey we've got to do the Lord's Supper
tomorrow night. I was like man I didn't tell Holly about it. We're in the middle. We're
going to have the open house yesterday. And then someone asked me yesterday they said
hey when, how often do you observe the Lord's Supper? I was like actually tomorrow night
we're observing the Lord's Supper. We talk about self-examination. We talk about the
process when the Bible says let a man examine himself. We sing the song nothing between
my soul and my Savior. And we think about this process of God being at work. I often
say when we deal with the subject of self-examination that it requires both humility and honesty.
Here's the reality of life. The reality of life is that I would rather inspect Armando
and Armando would rather inspect me. That's the reality of life. Why? Because it's a hard
thing to inspect yourself, to examine yourself. You know why? We think we're better than we
are. We think we really don't have any problems. We think we've got it all together. But then
God starts working. That bitterness, lack of forgiveness, that contention, unresolved.
I mean you just go down a list. I'm not going to go down through a list tonight. I'm just
going to mention a few things. But the reality is that God is working. Listen this was something
that happened 20 years earlier. I think that the brothers probably tried to suppress it
as much as they possibly could. Isn't that what we try to do? Try to suppress those things.
Try to suppress them. But you know what God does? He brings it right to the forefront.
We can deal with this. I can handle this. I'm thankful that God was working locally
and globally but God was working personally. Our God is a personal God. And He works in
the lives of His people. And as we allow Him to have His way, as we say as the psalmist
does in Psalm 139, God search me oh God. Search me oh God. And show me if there be
any wicked way in my life. Right? That's what the Bible teaches us. That process of self-examination.
And so we find that God is working in the lives of these brothers. They say what is
this that God hath done unto us? Surely we are guilty concerning our brother. And they
understand what is taking place and how God is working. God is at work in the life of
Joseph. God is at work in the lives of the ten brothers. I believe that God is at work
in Jacob's life. Look at verse 29. And they, nine of them, He sent ten out. And they, nine
of them, came unto Jacob their father unto the land of Canaan. And notice what the next
phrase says. And told him all that befell unto them. They didn't just come back with
some food. They came back with a story. With an account of what took place. Here's what
happened. Dad you sent us there. We came back with food but a whole lot more. Now they don't
reveal everything to Jacob. They don't reveal to Jacob at this particular juncture. We don't,
we see that not a place here where they reveal what they have done and really the conviction
that they're dealing with. Why? They don't want to tell Jacob. So we find that the, verse
number 30, the man who is the Lord of the land. Now who is that? That's Joseph. That's
their younger brother. That's the one who is not. According to what they say in verse
number 13, and one is not, the man, the ruler of the land, he is Joseph. And it says the
man who is the Lord of the land spake roughly to us and took us for spies of the country.
And we said unto him, we are true men, we are no spies. We be twelve brethren, sons
of our father. One is not, that's Joseph. And the youngest is this day with our father
in the land of Canaan. The man, the Lord of the country said unto us, hereby shall I know
that you are true men. Leave one of your brethren here with me and take food for the famine
of your households and be gone. And bring your youngest brother unto me. Then shall
I know that you are no spies, but you are true men. So will I deliver you your brother,
that's Simeon, and ye shall traffic in the land. In other words, they'd be able to come
back and forth and receive the goods, the food that they would need during the time
of famine. Joseph was the one that knew it was going to be seven years long. We don't
know at this particular time exactly how much time has passed. You can kind of guess at
it. But the reality is that we find that when later on, when Joseph is revealing to
his brothers what was going on, he says in verse number 6 of chapter 45, for these two
years hath the famine been in the land. And so this is very early with regard to the seven
years of famine. And so he tells them, he gives the plan, and now the boys are telling
dad, these nine, verse 35, and it came to pass as they emptied their sacks, that behold,
every man's bundle of money was in his sack. And when both they and their father saw the
bundles of money, they were afraid. And Jacob, their father, said unto them, Me have ye bereaved
of my children. Notice where he says, Joseph is not. He's dead in his mind. Simeon is not.
He's in prison in Egypt, right? And ye will take Benjamin away. All these things are against
me. You know, Jacob, God was working in his life too. God was working in Jacob's life.
Reuben spake unto his father, saying, Slay my two sons, if I bring them not to thee.
Deliver him into my hand, and I will bring him to thee again. Now obviously Reuben had
no way of being able to really guarantee that he'd be able to do that, but that's what he
says. In verse 38, he said, My son shall not go down with you. For his brother is dead,
and he is left alone. If mischief befall him by the way, and the witchy go, then shall
ye bring down my gray hairs with sorrow to the grave. Listen, God's working in Jacob's
life. Jacob needs to learn to trust the Lord. Jacob needs to learn some things about who
God is and what God is able to do. In fact, as you fast forward through the life of Joseph
in the next several chapters, you find that it's reported that Joseph is alive. He makes
himself known to his brothers, and that news gets back to Jacob, and Jacob then will journey
to go into Egypt. But before we get too far ahead of ourselves, we understand that God
is working personally in Genesis chapter 42. I wonder this evening, as we look at this
portion of Scripture and we see the dialogue, we see the account, the events as they unfold
on this first visit to Egypt. So much more than what these 10 brothers expected. I don't
think for a moment they were thinking God was going to convict them, deal with them
in this manner. But I wonder as I look at this portion of Scripture, I'm amazed by the
sensitivity of them recognizing that God was at work. Think about it this way with me.
Sometimes we deal with circumstances and situations and we say, well, it's just bad luck, just
misfortune, just this thing happened. You know, these boys, I don't think they were
very close to God, but you know their immediate response? God is at work. What is this that
God hath done unto us? I wonder tonight, how quick are we to acknowledge God working
in our lives? When that circumstance, whatever it might be, when this thing happens in your
life and in my life, we know, listen, we know that God is sovereign. We know that God is
a pursuing God. God is an intimate, personal God. We can stand here and say, I want to
be right with God. God wants you to be right with Him more than you could ever want to
be right with God. I believe that with all my heart tonight. Draw an eye unto God and
He'll draw an eye unto you. Amen? And I wonder tonight when that thing happens in my life
and in your life, do we recognize it as being the hand of God? Do we examine our lives and
say, what is God trying to teach me through this? How is God trying to grow me through
this?
this? How's God going to use me through this? Or do we just write it off as some kind of
bad misfortune, bad luck, whatever word we want to use to just kind of again continue
to suppress something? You understand what I'm saying tonight? These boys, God is at
work. What has God done to us? And I just wonder tonight, how's God working in our lives?
Do you see God working in your life? Do you hear the voice of God when you read the Bible,
when you come to church, when you hear the preaching of God's word? Is God working in
your life? Are there some things that God's putting his finger on? And maybe we don't
like it. Maybe we don't want to deal with it. But God's at work. And God's going to
continue to pursue. God's going to continue to pursue. And God wants you to not have
a hard heart, but to have a tender heart. He doesn't want us to be hardened, but to
be softened, to be tender. And this evening, as we look at Genesis chapter 42, we see how
God is working in the life of Joseph, the life of the brothers, the life of Jacob. I
just believe tonight that God's working in our lives as well. And I wonder, are we able
to recognize it? And how do we respond to it? What is God doing? How is God working?
Will we let God be God and have his way? Let's pray together. Father, we love you. We thank
you for loving us. God, we thank you for this portion of Scripture, for the opportunity
to see how you're a personal God. Lord, I pray that in the quietness of the moment tonight,
as we've heard the preaching of your word, as we have a time of invitation even in preparation
for observing the Lord's Supper, God, I pray that you'd help us to examine ourselves. God,
I pray that you'd help us to submit, to surrender to thee. Lord, I don't know how you're working
in everyone's life. I believe that you are at work. And I know at times it's uncomfortable,
it's difficult. But God, I pray that you'd help us to submit and surrender. God, we would
see and acknowledge that you are at work. Would you have your will and way in these
moments of invitation? Well, thank you for what you'll do. For it's in Christ's name
we pray.