Matthew, Matthew chapter number 6.
And in just a very few moments, I'm going to begin reading
in verse number 19 of the chapter
and be reading through verse number 21.
We will be using our Bibles again tonight
and therefore I trust you'll leave them handy
throughout the course of the message.
My, hasn't the service been a blessing thus far?
I've enjoyed every part of the service,
the congregational singing has just been wonderful.
The children singing tonight was outstanding.
And then to be able to see firsthand
how God used Brother Tim there in Bulgaria.
And I know that thrills you as a sending church family
to have a part in what the Lord used him to do there.
And so it was a blessing to hear from him.
And what a blessing this week has been.
And it just seems like we've just really gotten started
and here it is Wednesday night.
And Cassie and I will be on the road early tomorrow morning
headed at least toward home.
And we certainly appreciate your prayers.
But as we leave, we're certainly going to be leaving blessed.
It has been a great few days here at the Fellowship Baptist Church.
Your pastor and your pastor's wife and their family
have been outstanding and very gracious hosts
to all of our missionary families here this week.
And we from the bottom of our hearts say,
thank you, thank you, thank you.
Let me say again that the Fellowship Baptist Church,
thank you so much for your prayerful
as well as your financial support.
We could not do what God has put in our hearts to do
without pastors like your precious pastor
and without churches just like the Fellowship Baptist Church.
And Cassie and I are blessed to be your representatives
literally all over the world.
Lord willing, next month we'll be in Brazil
and we appreciate your help to get there.
You've just been so good to us.
We're very, very grateful.
And we're already looking forward to the next time.
We've already got a date scheduled in 2028.
We're excited about that.
Now, if Jesus comes before then,
Brother Bill will be in charge of the services.
So you folks that are left,
maybe he can give you something from the Bible.
But I want to say it's so good to see my dear friend,
Brother Alton Bill, here tonight.
And all of these folks from Ambassador,
it's amazing to watch the Lord use them
during the D.C. outreach.
And we're just so thrilled about that.
I'm so appreciative for the burden
that God put on Brother Bill's heart about that.
Surely our nation needs the gospel.
And what better time to try to reach D.C. with the gospel
than during this 250-year celebration
when literally thousands upon thousands of people will be here.
So I'm so appreciative for your burden, Brother Bill.
And I'll tell you, I'm impressed.
I'm always impressed with the Ambassador guys.
They're just always a step above.
And I love Ambassador Baptist College and Brother Alton Bill.
It's a blessing to call him one of my friends.
And to get to meet these other fellas,
the fella from Brother Nate.
It's the first time I've met Brother Nate.
And from West Virginia, then Brother Ryan DeLay.
It's just been a great, great blessing.
And all of the missionary families this week,
it's just been very refreshing.
I so appreciate the message from Brother Perez last night.
And it's a blessing to hear a missionary preach
with tears in his eyes and with a flame of fire in his heart.
And that's exactly how Brother Perez preached last night.
And I'm so appreciative.
Have you found your place in the gospel of Matthew chapter number 6?
I felt impressed of the Lord tonight to challenge you
about your missions giving.
And on the way to the pulpit this evening,
I was careful to pick up one of your giving envelopes.
Now your pastor makes these available to you every single week
here at the Fellowship Baptist Church.
And of course, first and foremost,
there's a place right here for you to tithe every week.
And we know when we study our Bible,
giving begins with the tithe.
The tithe belongs to the Lord.
But then there is a place for you every single week,
right along with your tithes and offerings,
there's a place on your giving envelopes for you to pray
about a very special gift or an investment,
as we will call it tonight, in world evangelism.
And of course, that is to be given over and above the tithe.
So I'm thankful your pastor has given you an opportunity
through the ministry of Fellowship Baptist Church
for you to make an investment in world evangelism.
It is an investment, as we will see tonight,
in which you or I, either one, cannot lose.
Amen?
With that in mind, would you stand if you're able
as I read just three verses of Scripture
in the sixth chapter of the Gospel of Matthew
beginning with verse 19.
We'll read the text and then consider the context
of its writing throughout the introduction
of the Bible message tonight.
Matthew chapter 6 and verse 19.
The Lord says,
Lay not up for yourselves treasures upon earth,
where moth and rust doth corrupt,
and where thieves break through and steal.
But lay up for yourselves treasures in heaven,
where neither moth nor rust doth corrupt,
and where thieves do not break through nor steal.
For where your treasure is,
there will your heart be also.
I would like to back up and read verse 21 again
and encourage each and every one of you,
if you would please,
to read this verse of Scripture audibly with me.
Would you read it with me this evening?
Let's read verse 21 together.
For where your treasure is,
there will your heart be also.
With the help of the Lord tonight,
I want to preach on this thought,
truths concerning our treasures.
I believe the Lord Jesus shares such truths with us
here in these few verses of Scripture
that He's led us to tonight.
I like to call them truths concerning our treasures.
Let's see what Jesus has to say
about a few of those truths tonight.
Let's bow our heads for a moment of prayer.
Father, it has certainly been memorable,
to say the least,
last few days here at the Fellowship Baptist Church.
I want to thank you for Pastor Man and his family
and their leadership here
and how that you continue to use them in a mighty way.
And then, Lord, I want to thank you for a church family
that's willing to follow His faith.
And I pray, my Father,
that the greatest days of outreach
for the Fellowship Baptist Church
will still be yet to come in the days ahead.
And for that, I'll give you glory and honor.
Now, Father, would you please help me tonight?
I'm nothing without you.
So I pray you'd cleanse me of sin and self
and fill me with your Holy Spirit.
If you would be so kind as to make a preacher out of me tonight,
I certainly would appreciate it.
In Jesus' name I pray, amen.
Thank you so much for standing.
Please be seated.
As you and I consider the context of the verses
we've just been blessed to read together,
we'll discover they're actually a part
of what some Bible commentators have called
the very heart of our Lord's Sermon on the Mount.
During the course of that sermon,
the Lord Jesus, He addresses not merely outward conduct,
but rather inward priorities.
Here in the text that He's led us to tonight,
He's addressing truths.
Again, I like to call them truths concerning our treasures.
And while sharing those truths with us,
it's very interesting this evening.
Jesus isn't concerned with telling us what we want to hear.
Oh, no, no.
He's telling us in the text what we need to hear.
And friend, if there's ever been a day,
if there's ever been an hour,
that the world needs to hear
what our Lord is saying here in the text,
it's in this day and hour in which we're living today.
I say that because in a world that is driven by accumulation,
investment portfolios, and material security,
here in the text before us,
our Lord speaks plainly, and I believe very pointedly,
about what truly matters, about what truly lasts.
And His concern, according to the text,
isn't whether or not we possess earthly goods,
but rather whether or not earthly goods possess us.
Now, please, let me make it very clear.
beginning of the message this evening.
There's nothing wrong with having things.
There's nothing wrong with having earthly goods.
But the Bible is abundantly clear.
It becomes a sin when things or earthly goods have us.
I want to say tonight there's nothing wrong with having money.
Having been in the ministry now for over three decades,
I'm thankful for those that have money.
There's nothing wrong with having money.
And by the way, do you know what it takes to reach the world with the gospel?
Now you can dismiss this truth all you would like, but it takes money.
Do you know what it takes to plant a church in Uruguay or Bulgaria?
I'm telling you, it takes a lot of money.
Do you know what it takes to reach D.C. with the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ?
You can dismiss it any way you want to dismiss it,
but you can't deny it takes money to do it.
There's nothing wrong with money.
The Bible doesn't say that money is the root of all evil.
The Bible says in 1 Timothy chapter 6 and verse number 10
that the love of money is the root of all evil.
That's why these verses of scripture are so vitally important
for the Fellowship Baptist Church this evening,
especially as you seek God's perfect will
about your investment in world evangelism in the days to come.
These verses of scripture are vitally important
because here in the text before us,
the Lord can actually be seen contrasting two treasuries.
Two treasuries.
One treasury is temporal.
It is fragile.
But according to these verses of scripture,
the other treasury is eternal.
It is secure.
And then as the Lord so often does in his word,
in light of truths concerning those two treasuries,
he calls upon you and he ultimately calls upon me
to choose between them very wisely.
This last night of your missions conference,
I implore you, church, in light of eternity,
please choose wisely.
And as you and I contemplate our choices,
please allow me to remind you that world evangelism
is at its very core an investment question.
World evangelism causes us to ask ourselves,
where are we placing the resources
that God has entrusted us with?
I think it's important that you hear the preacher say tonight,
I don't think there's a thing in this world wrong with saving.
I don't think there's a thing wrong with investing.
In fact, I try to do a little bit of that myself.
Proverbs chapter six and verse number six says,
go to the aunt thou sluggard, consider her ways and be wise.
I would encourage you to save.
I would encourage you to invest and plan wisely.
However, in light of that,
I want you to listen to what I'm getting ready to say.
I would hate to think that I would have more invested
in this temporary world below
than I had invested in the eternal world in heaven to come.
So with that truth in mind,
there is a question that both you and I
ought to earnestly consider this evening.
Are we living only for what can be seen, counted, and consumed?
Or are we intentionally laying up treasures
where moth, rust, and thieves have no access?
Please hear me tonight.
Supporting the work of world evangelism,
both prayerfully as well as financially,
through our local church is one of the clearest,
and may I say most scriptural ways
to obey Christ's command to reach the world with the gospel.
And by the way, can I take yet one more opportunity tonight
to remind you that reaching the world with the gospel,
it isn't a suggestion to be ignored.
It is a command to be obeyed.
And Jesus said in the gospel of John chapter 14 and verse 15,
if you love me, do you remember what he said?
Do much more than just sing, oh, how I love Jesus,
because quite honestly, talk is really cheap.
Jesus said, if you love me, keep my commandments.
Shortly before Jesus ascended back to his throne in glory,
Jesus told his disciple in the book of Acts,
but ye shall receive power after that the Holy Ghost
is come upon you, and ye shall be witnesses unto me.
Somebody that knows the Bible, tell me that next word.
Both, that's right, both.
Do you know what that word both means?
It means simultaneously at the same time.
Both, Jesus said, here's where I want you to be witnesses.
Let's start in Jerusalem.
And then I want you to branch out and go from Jerusalem
and in Samaria and into all Judea,
and ultimately unto where?
The Bible says the uttermost parts of the earth.
So if Christ commands us to be witnesses for him,
both in Jerusalem and in all Judea and in Samaria
and under the uttermost part, how in the world
did Jesus ask something of us
that we do not possess within our power to do?
How can we be in Oakton, Virginia,
and yet be in Uruguay at the same time?
We do it through partnerships that have been formed
through the missions outreach of our local Bible-believing church.
And therefore, since that is most definitely the case,
I'm going to encourage you to consider just a few truths
directly from the text.
Truths concerning our treasures.
Quickly, number one tonight.
Jesus calls our attention to the perishing nature
of earthly treasures.
Isn't it interesting that according to verse 19,
the Lord begins the verse with a very solemn
and may I say a very sobering warning.
Jesus says,
lay not up for yourselves treasures upon earth.
Now again, please do not misunderstand.
Earthly treasures in and of themselves,
they're not sinful.
But the Bible clearly teaches that they at their best,
they're unstable, they are temporary,
and they are certainly unsatisfying.
In fact, the Lord drives that point home here in the text
by naming three enemies of material wealth.
Do you see the three enemies of material wealth in the text?
The Bible speaks of the moth.
The Bible speaks of rust.
And then the Bible speaks of thieves.
Each one of these enemies of material wealth
reminds us that everything you and I see today,
everything we can touch today,
is subject to decay, to loss, and removal.
The moth, the rust, and the thieves.
First of all, the moth speaks of silent destruction.
And I say that because in Matthew's day,
wealth was often measured by the amount of fine garments people owned.
However, as fine as a garment could have possibly been made,
moths, are you listening?
Moths could and often would destroy such garments
slowly but ever so surely from within.
That's why I say the image here emphasizes a gradual unseen decay.
The moth speaks of silent destruction.
The rust speaks of slow corrosion.
In fact, I found it interesting while studying for the message tonight
that the Greek word translated rust in the text
literally means, listen, eating or consumption.
It includes corrosion, but it also speaks of spoilage
as grain rotting in barns as much as metal oxidizing.
This is a Bible truth that assures us, are you listening?
Every carefully stored resource is subject to the natural process of decay.
What man preserves, time consumes.
And therefore we gather from the text that creation itself
works against the permanence of earthly wealth.
The rust speaks of slow corrosion.
No corrosion.
And then the thieves speak of sudden loss.
Unlike moth and rust, thieves involve sudden loss.
Eternal loss.
Again, it's interesting, in Matthew's day,
homes were often made of clay or mud brick.
And therefore, they were very easily broken through by digging.
And therefore, it goes without saying,
death could vanish in a moment due to crime
or economic collapse.
What took years to accumulate could be gone.
Just like that.
It's no wonder the Bible says in Proverbs chapter 23
and verse 5,
Wilt thou set thine eyes upon that which is not?
For riches certainly make themselves wings.
They fly away as an eagle toward heaven.
Isn't that interesting?
Not as a blue bird towards heaven.
Not as a black bird towards heaven.
But riches, they make themselves wings
and they fly away as one of the strongest birds of all.
Just like that.
As an eagle toward heaven.
That's exactly why in Proverbs chapter 11,
the first portion of verse 28 says,
He that trusteth in his riches shall fail.
Not might fall, not might fail, but shall fall.
Please hear me tonight.
Whether gradual or immediate,
earthly treasure never belongs to us.
No matter how carefully it is guarded.
No matter how carefully it is stored.
No matter how carefully it is kept.
It cannot, are you listening?
It cannot be secured forever.
The very moment we breathe our last breath on this earth,
every possession will be left behind.
I want you to listen to the preacher tonight.
Not one title, not one dollar, not one cent,
not one account will cross the threshold of eternity.
That is exactly why the Bible says in the 49th Psalm,
be not afraid when one is made rich,
when the glory of his house is increased.
For when he dieth, he shall carry nothing away.
His glory shall not descend after him.
Please hear me tonight.
Earthly treasure always, it always comes
with three guarantees.
Decay, damage, and disappearance.
According to the Bible, the world's wealth
has an expiration date.
And the world's wealth's expiration date
has been stamped with moths and rust and thieves.
Moths attack luxury.
Rust attacks utility.
Thieves attack security.
Nothing, nothing, nothing on this earth,
are you listening?
Nothing will escape loss, no matter how large the account,
no matter how vast the possessions.
Let me say it again.
Nothing on this earth will escape loss.
Ecclesiastes chapter five teaches us in verse 15
that we came into this world naked from our mother's wombs
and we're leaving the same way.
It was just a few weeks ago now that Cassie's mama
went home to be with the Lord.
Cassie was blessed to be in the room with her mother
when she breathed her last breath.
And when she breathed her last,
she did not take her house with her.
She did not take her land with her.
She left every bank, are you listening?
She left every bank account.
She left every dress, she left every automobile,
are you listening this evening?
The perishing nature of earthly treasures.
In the same portion of the Bible,
Jesus not only addressed the perishing nature
of earthly treasures, but he also addressed,
secondly, the permanence of heavenly treasures.
Isn't it interesting while Matthew chapter six
in verse 19 warns us what not to do,
the following verse, Matthew chapter six in verse 20
reveals what we should do.
Notice the word starts with a little three letter conjunction
but in light of the perishing nature of earthly treasures.
But what does our Lord instruct us to do?
Lay up for yourselves treasures in heaven
where neither moth nor rust doth corrupt
and where thieves do not break through nor steal.
Here, ladies and gentlemen, in verse 20 of our text,
we see the permanence of heavenly treasure.
The permanence of heavenly treasure.
As you pray about your investment in world evangelism
in the coming year, isn't it interesting in the text
that our Lord goes to great lengths to teach us
about the permanence of heavenly treasures.
And while doing so, he makes it abundantly clear
that unlike our earthly treasure,
heavenly treasures are never subject to decay.
They are never subject to theft.
No, the Bible teaches in our text
that our heavenly treasures are guarded by God himself.
You see, Christian friend, heaven's economy
is never affected by inflation, recession, or loss.
Heavenly treasures are accumulated
when eternal work is accomplished for God's glory.
as the gospel is preached, as sinners are saved,
as churches are planted, as disciples are made.
Please hear me tonight, fellowship Baptist Church.
Every missionary sent, every Bible distributed,
every church planted, every soul won
represents an eternal return in heaven
as a result of a temporary investment on this earth.
That's why I say when you invest in world evangelism
every single month, every single week,
however the Lord leads you to do it,
you are making an investment
in which you cannot and will not lose.
I'll tell you what I want you to do.
You were blessed, most of you,
were blessed to be here Monday night.
And I preached out of the book of Philippians chapter four
on the thought, the opportunity
that was not missed in missions.
I want you, before I give you my last point,
I want you to turn with me, if you would please,
to Philippians chapter four once again.
Philippians chapter four.
Do you remember what Paul said to his friends at Philippi
according to Philippians chapter four and verse 17?
Paul commended them in chapter four
for their partnership with him in his missions endeavors.
In fact, Paul said in verse 15 of that chapter,
now you Philippians know also
that in the beginning of the gospel
when I departed from Macedonia,
no church communicated with me
as concerning giving and receiving, but ye only.
For even in Thessalonica,
you sent once again unto my necessity,
verse 17, don't miss it,
not because I desire a gift,
but I desire fruit that may abound to your account.
Isn't this interesting?
Paul, listen, Paul uses a commercial terminology
used in Roman commerce
that every single one of those Philippians
would have been familiar with.
Paul reminds them here in the text
that they had an account with God.
Are you listening?
He reminds them they had an account with God.
According to the text, it was a very personal account.
Notice the Holy Ghost of God
led Paul to use the words your account in the text.
And then the Holy Ghost through the pen of the apostle Paul
begins to go into very great detail
concerning the Philippian believers account with God.
First of all, the Bible speaks
of the principle of their account.
Again, the words your account imply divine bookkeeping.
And the fact, listen,
the fact that God keeps really good records,
really good records.
Can I just say this about our God?
Our God's pencil doesn't have an eraser on it.
You know why?
God never messes up.
Especially.
when it comes to accounting, God keeps really good records.
Nothing invested in the gospel goes unnoticed or unrewarded.
The principle of their account.
The Bible teaches us about the product of their account.
Oh, don't miss this.
Notice that Paul never emphasizes the size of the offerings
the Philippians sent, but rather the spiritual outcome of them.
I personally believe the gift the Philippians sent once and again
to the Apostle Paul's necessity, I don't believe it was a big gift at all.
Remember, according to 2 Corinthians chapter 8,
they were living in what kind of poverty?
Deep poverty.
They were suffering great affliction.
No, the Bible never mentions the size of the offering the Philippians sent to Paul,
but rather the spiritual outcome of them.
Hear me tonight.
Heaven credits fruit, not finances.
The fruit is the product of our giving.
World evangelism, so many people get a misconception about it.
They think all world evangelism is, it's about finances.
It's about funds.
Oh, here we go again.
We're going to hear about missions.
Oh, no, no.
World evangelism really isn't about funds.
It's about fruit.
The product of their account.
And then, oh man, this is so good.
The Bible speaks of the profit of their account.
Do you see the word abound?
Oh, if you write in your Bible, you ought to underline that word abound.
You ought to circle that word.
You ought to highlight that word abound in the text
because that word abound suggests increasing, multiplying to the point of overflowing.
Hear me tonight, church.
Every act of gospel partnership compounds over time with interest according to the Bible.
Therefore, I could say it like this and be scripturally correct, biblically correct in saying it.
Missions, world evangelism, it really isn't about the finances but rather about the fruit.
Does it take money to get a missionary to the field?
Yes.
Does it take Brother Perez monthly support to enable him to do what God has called him to do?
Yes, it takes money.
But missions, world evangelism, it isn't about funds.
It's about fruit.
Money is the seed but fruit is the goal.
World missions isn't just about fundraising.
It's about fruit bearing.
Earth counts the money but heaven counts the outcome.
God is able to take our temporary currency and if invested properly turn it into eternal credit
or as Paul put it in Philippians chapter 4, fruit that abounds to our account.
To our account.
I've got an account.
You've got an account.
All God's children, we have an account with God.
And Jesus said in the gospel of Mark chapter 9 that even a cup of cold water given in his name would never go unrewarded.
Hear me as I say this tonight and I'll give you my last point.
Thank you for letting me preach.
Thank you for letting me just be me while I'm here because I get a little excited about this fruit bearing business.
Because you see I'll never, Cassie and I, Cassie and I will never have many material things here on this earth.
But I'm telling you we're counting on having something to lay at the feet of our Savior when we get to glory.
So thank you for letting me get a little excited about it.
I'll tell you what, why don't you go ahead and turn back to our text tonight in Matthew chapter 6
and I'll meet you there just in a few moments.
While you're finding your place again in Matthew chapter 6 for the final point of the message, let me say this.
Supporting the work of world evangelism through our local church aligns our giving with God's eternal purposes.
Missions giving through our local church allows believers to participate in gospel work far beyond their physical reach.
Therefore long after earthly investments are gone and forgotten, according to the Bible,
the eternal results of missions giving will still be rejoiced over in heaven.
A truth that is clearly understood as we consider the permanence of our heavenly treasures.
Well we see one other thing in the text.
The perishing nature of earthly treasures, verse 19.
The permanence of heavenly treasures, verse 20.
But then in verse 21, notice the priority revealed by our treasures.
Verse 21 says, for where your treasure is, there will your heart be also.
Now you did a great job a while ago. Why don't you say that verse with me again.
Let's quote it together audibly, shall we? Let's do it together now.
For where your treasure is, there will your heart be also.
There is a truth that is often taught in the Bible.
And that is the fact that how we invest our treasures reveals what we treasure the most.
Do you want to know why you're giving matters to God?
Now I'm just going to be honest with you.
If you don't ever give another dime to the work of God,
if you're determined after this Bible message tonight to rob God of His tithe
and never give another dime to world evangelism, guess what?
The sun's still going to come up tomorrow.
God causes it to rain on the just as well as the unjust.
And those of us that have determined to make a difference for the cause of Christ
through our giving, among other ways, we're going to go on down the road and we're going to serve God.
Do you want to know why your giving matters to God?
Your giving matters to God because your giving is a very clear indication of where your heart is.
And God, listen, God is very interested in your heart.
As Jesus shares truths concerning our treasures in the text,
He is careful to mention that our spending reveals our values or where our hearts are.
Our checkbook and our giving patterns expose what truly matters to us.
If our treasure is invested primarily in comfort, in leisure, and the temporary accumulation on this earth,
then our hearts will inevitably be anchored to this world.
However, if our treasure is intentionally placed in the eternal work of God,
we have God's word that our hearts will be drawn toward heaven.
I like to say it like this, missions giving is not merely a financial decision.
Missions giving is a spiritual declaration of priority.
When a church commits to missions, it publicly, and may I say unapologetically,
declares that reaching the world with the gospel matters more than expanding personal comfort or amusement.
Don't miss this.
When a family gives by faith to world evangelism,
it teaches the next generation that eternity far outweighs the present.
When you and I consistently invest in missionaries that God has called to reach the world with the gospel,
we align our hearts with God's global redemptive plan.
Missions giving through our local church ensures accountability, cooperation, and scriptural stewardship.
It connects individual obedience with collective impact,
allowing churches, just like the Fellowship Baptist Church of Oakton, Virginia,
to send, to sustain, and ultimately to strengthen gospel laborers around the world.
And therefore I'll say it tonight, and I believe be scripturally correct in saying it,
the question really isn't are you investing tonight?
Because according to the Bible,
Well, you are.
You're investing somewhere.
You're either investing in this temporary world
in which we are living,
or you are investing in the eternal things of God.
I wonder how my account looks tonight in heaven.
True story, and I'm through, you've listened so well.
I see why you hang around here now.
These folks like preaching, amen.
Even when it gets a little loud from time to time.
I love preaching here.
Thank you for letting me preach.
Thank you for listening so well.
There's a young man that pastors down the road
from our home office at Macedonia in Houston, Georgia.
His name is Landon Street.
Just a young man, got a beautiful family,
took a little old church that was about to close its doors
and man, God through him and his ministry
has turned that thing around.
And one of the things brother Landon has done
is he has introduced the church to missionaries
and church planning.
And boy, that little old congregation,
they've gotten ahold of that.
And man, it's just amazing
to see what the Lord is doing there.
Not long ago, brother Landon called me on the phone.
He said, hey preacher, you're in my office this week.
I said, why, yes, I am brother.
He said, let me take you to lunch.
And so he came to the office and he took me to lunch.
And we just had a wonderful time of fellowship that day
over a delicious meal.
And probably three quarters of the through the meal,
brother Landon told me, he said, preacher,
I got something I need to tell you.
I said, okay.
He said, you know, you were my grandma's pastor
for 12 years when you pastored the Canaan Baptist Church
of Kevington, Georgia.
I said, oh yeah.
I have nothing but fond memories about your grandmother.
Her name was Patricia Farah.
And she was one of those folks in the church.
Listen, every time the doors were open,
Patricia was there and always faithful, always loyal.
Man, you could have a Saturday morning outreach
and she'd be there working in the kitchen.
We had a youth camp and we'd take 200 people
to youth camp and spend a week.
And Patricia would go and labor in the kitchen.
Just one of those members never spoke out that much.
She never sung in the choir, but just steady,
just faithful, just loyal.
Brother Street told me, he said,
you know, when my grandma passed away,
the family gave me her Bible.
I said, really?
I said, that's a treasure, brother Landon.
I'm glad that you got it.
He said, I need to tell you what I found
in my grandma's Bible.
When I first got it, I opened it up
and I began to thumb through its pages
and I saw where she had underlined some verses
and some circled.
And she even wrote down a few messages
that you had preached since you was her pastor.
But she said, brother Landon said,
after a while I opened it up
and a check fell out of my grandma's Bible.
And I said, really?
And Landon said, yeah, it was the last tithe check
she ever wrote.
And she not only gave a tithe,
but she had instructions in the corner of the check.
This much is tithe, this much is missions.
Much like you have opportunity to do
every single week right here
at the Fellowship Baptist Church.
And Ms. Patricia had wrote out her check
and in the corner she put tithe
and she put the amount
and then she put the rest goes to missions.
Now, when Patricia Farah wrote that check,
brother Ryan, little did she know
that would be the last check she'd ever write.
Within three days, she'd be in glory.
She died very suddenly.
She got sick and just passed away.
If you ever thought about that,
you think when Patricia breathed her last
and knelt before the feet of our Savior,
do you think she said,
man, I wish I wouldn't have given that money to missions.
What could I have done with that money
instead of giving it to missions?
I assure you, she did not regret
what she was planning to do for world evangelism.
She did not regret tithing.
She did not regret laying up treasure in heaven
because in heaven, moth, rust,
and thieves cannot corrupt it.
And I assure you, should you write the last missions check,
the last tithe check this Sunday,
you will not regret it either.
For where your treasure is,
there will your heart be also.
You've listened so well.
Would you bow your head with me?
My father, you've met with us
in a very special way tonight.
And for that, I'm so grateful.
Lord, I wanna thank you for what you have done in my heart
while considering these few truths concerning our treasures.
Oh Lord, I'm thankful for the house
that you have provided for Cassie and I to live in.
I'm thankful for the automobile
that you have provided for us to drive.
I'm thankful for the clothes on our backs
and for the food on our table.
But Lord, I'm also thankful that you teach me in your word
that all of those things are just temporal.
So father, would you impress upon each of our hearts
the need to invest in things that are eternal?
Oh, nothing wrong with investing down here,
but again, Lord, I'd hate to think I had more invested here
than I did in heaven.
And so would you deal with our hearts about that tonight?
It is a matter of priority.
Would you help us to deal with it this evening?
Now, I pray for Pastor Mann
that you would give him both wisdom and discernment
as he comes to extend the invitation
as you lay upon his heart to do so.
And I'll give you glory in Jesus' name.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed,
and Anna's gonna play quietly on the piano.
And as she does, the altar's open.
The Lord spoke to you specifically this evening.
Come deal with, respond in obedience
to how God has challenged you.
Maybe there's another message earlier in the week
that you've just been...