Trip and back and good to see Durvin again this morning as well and always good to see folks returning
To be with us if you have your bible with you this morning the book of james chapter number one
James chapter number one and as we make our way here, uh through the book of james you say pastor
We're not going fast. I understand
And it's only five chapters and I had a pastor friend a guy I went to bible college with
And he contacted me in november of last year and he said hey
Have you ever taught or preached through the book of james?
And so I picked up the phone and called him and I said no, but i'm getting ready to and he said
Oh, i'm just working on it. I was wondering if I could get your notes
And I said, well, I don't have them all done yet. And uh, anyway, we had some conversation
He's like, yeah, i'm gonna do a five-week study and I said i'm gonna do a 52-week study
And he's like how in the world are you gonna do that?
And i'm like i'm not sure but there's a lot in the book of james and here we are march 1st
And we're still in chapter one and we are making progress
Not real fast, but that's okay
And we will by the lord's by god's grace and with god's help
We'll make through the book of james here in 2026
And if not, we'll continue in 2027. Amen. It's okay, and we'll just keep on keeping on
And i'm thankful, uh for the portion of scripture that we have god's word is so wonderful
And notice with me we'll read verses 13 through 16
I'll get into the uh kind of thoughts this morning before we get into the points
But notice the bible says this in verse 13. Let no man say
When he is tempted I am tempted of god
For god cannot be tempted with evil neither tempteth he any man
But every man is tempted when he is drawn away of his own lusts
and enticed
Then when lust hath conceived it bringeth forth sin and sin
When it is finished bringeth forth death
verse 16 do not air
my beloved brethren
I've titled the message this morning. Do not air part one
And next sunday morning will be do not air part two
It's kind of interesting that verse 16 is sandwiched between two very important truths that god wants
His people to know of course god wants his people to know all of the truth of his word
But it's interesting. He says do not air and we'll focus on that here in just a moment
But you know, I want you to understand this morning that it is a unique privilege to have the word of god
And god's word is truth
And god's word is settled
Amen, and uh, he said sanctify them through thy word thy word is truth forever. Oh lord thy word
Is settled in heaven god's word doesn't need to be revised god's word doesn't need to we're not looking for any new additions to it or
Subtractions from it. No god's word is settled and god's word is truth
And what needs to happen is god's people need to once again read god's word and apply god's word in their lives knowing
That god's word is truth. We understand that false teaching abounds, but that's nothing new
It is absolutely not new that false teaching abounds we understand in the old testament there were false prophets in the new testament
There's false teachers and all throughout church history. We find that there have been false teachers and uh,
the
Accessibility to false teaching today is a lot more
Accessible than it has been in previous generations because of the internet and so on and so forth
But that also means that the availability of god's truth going forward is also
Something that we can take advantage of and use the means of technology that god has provided us with the answer
to error
Is always truth
Truth endures truth
Uh remains and we find that we have been given the truth and it's important that we know
The truth we must be students of the word of god and we must accept the bible the word of god as it is
truth
And we find this morning that god wants his people to be informed
He he wants us to know truth. He says in verse 16 do not err
My beloved brethren and so there is the potential the possibility
For you and for me as the people of god to err
When we do not take the truth of god's word as the guide and the authority for our lives
When you lean on your own understanding when you follow after whatever is most popular and so on and so forth
Then you have the potential
of erring
And this book is what is going to correct
the error
Amen
God's word all scripture is given by inspiration of god. It's profitable for doctrine
But the bible also says for correction and for instruction for doctrine for reproof for correction for instruction in righteousness
That the man of god might be perfect throughly furnished unto all good works
And so we understand this morning what we hold in our hand
But it's interesting that james here under the inspiration of the holy spirit of god says do not err
And that reveals to me that there's the potential for god's people to err
In both of these areas the look what we're going to look at this morning in verses 13 through 15
What we'll look at next week in verses 17 through 18. And so the potential
Is there that we're going to err so he says?
Do not err. Amen like
Clear blatant grab your attention as the truth is given
And the reality is that as we study the bible we could insert do not err all sorts of places but god
Chooses to put it here as really grabbing our attention getting our attention that we do not err
I'm interested to share with you a verse of scripture. You don't need to turn there
But in first thessalonians chapter 2 I mentioned the privilege that we have
To have the word of god and that we need to accept the bible as it is and that is truth and it's god's word
Paul says to the believers in thessalonica and first thessalonians 2 and verse number 13
For this cause also thank we god without ceasing
because
When you received the word of god, which he heard of us
You received it not as the word of men
But as it is in truth the word of god which effectually worketh also in you
That believe what a great verse of scripture. What a great
comment that paul makes under the inspiration of the holy spirit of god with regard to the believers in thessalonica and how they
Receive the word of god and how they view the word of god today
We have people even some that would sit in churches that say well, that's just how you interpret it
That's just your interpretation. That's your perspective
Well, that's not really what god meant and they just begin to excuse it
No god means what he says and he says what he means
Amen, and we must accept the bible as it is in truth. It is the word of god
And hallelujah i'm so thankful to have it
You know where you'd be without the bible
If I were to take a survey this morning and ask each of you is god great and you said yes
And I hope every single person would say god is great and then I would ask you why is god great?
The answers that you would give no matter the number of answers that you would have on your list
The reason that we know god is great is because he's given us a bible
the reason that you know that uh
You can go to heaven when you die is because he's given us a bible and he's given to us the plan
Of redemption he's recorded it for us
The the reason that you know that you can go to god in prayer
Is because god reveals to us in his word that we can be people of prayer
And that god hears and he answers and he extends to us the invitation
To come boldly before the throne of grace everything that we know to be true about god
Is found in the bible
Amen
You know, there were some things I thought
About god before I got saved
But they were wrong
When I compared them with the truth of god's word
You know many people have the idea
Well, if i'm good if i'm better than those if you know
God looks at my life and i'm i'm better and I have more good than I have bad and then i'll you know
Many people are living life thinking that
That's their that's their perspective. In fact, there's some churches unfortunately that teach that
But the bible says it's not by works of righteousness which we have done
Amen
For by grace are you saved through faith and that not of yourselves. It is the gift of god not of works
Lest any man should boast so I kind of had this idea before I was saved before I read the bible that if I was just
Good enough and how do you define that? How do you determine that?
But if I was good enough that I would be able to get to heaven
And I had this idea that god understood
You know a lot of people that have this idea god understands god understands. Well god does understand but god's not okay with our sin
Amen
God understands but he's not okay with our sin. God doesn't just turn a blind eye. God doesn't just sweep it under the carpet sin is serious
God's serious about it
And so god wants us to accept his word as it is truth and he says do not err
Look at again verse 13 as we look and dig into the text in james chapter number one
And looking at verses 13 through 15 specifically
With regard to the context, what does james want the the readers?
What is it that he wants them to be careful not to be in error not?
to have a misunderstanding of life.
He says, and as he's looking here at the text of Scripture, the first thing that he mentions
is the character of God.
If you're taking notes, notice number one, the character of God.
In verse number 13, the Bible says,
Let no man say, when he is tempted, I am tempted of God.
For God cannot be tempted with evil, neither tempteth He any man.
So here, James is going to deal with a subject.
We understand the verbal derivative for the word tempted in verse number 13.
It's the same Greek word that's used previous in the passage of Scripture, but here the
verbal derivative is negative, which obviously is revealed to us through the context as well,
that here, because he says that when lust hath conceived, it bringeth forth sin, and
sin when it is finished bringeth forth death, that he's speaking about temptation with regard
to sinful temptation.
He's not talking about the same thing in verses 2 through 12 when he's talking about the trials
that we endure in life, and he talked about, as we studied last Sunday morning, blessed
is the man that endureth temptation.
He's talking about those trials.
Why?
Because we understand that there's a purpose that God has, and we're counting it joy because
God has a purpose, and we're not quitting, we're not giving up in the midst of the trial.
We're trusting God, and we're understanding that God has not allowed the trial to destroy
me, but to develop me.
But now as we get into verses 13 through 15, the negative is seen here, and it's talking
about the temptation to sin.
And so when we find the truth that James is going to reveal to us, he begins by talking
about the character of God, and as he begins to talk about the character of God, we notice
in verse number 13 that God is holy.
Our God is holy.
He's not becoming holy, he is holy.
The Bible tells us, you read the book of Leviticus, and you'll read it repeatedly throughout the
book of Leviticus, where God says to his people, be holy.
Why?
Because I am holy.
And God has revealed to us in his word that he is a holy God.
In Psalm 97 and verse number 12, the psalmist gives the admonition to the people of God
to rejoice, to give thanks at the remembrance of God's holiness.
And I hope that each day of your life that you're reminded that you serve a holy God.
He's holy.
In fact, as you read Isaiah chapter number six, what a great scene that we have in Isaiah
the vision of Isaiah, the call of Isaiah, and you hear the angel say, holy, holy, holy.
That's our God.
And here, James is highlighting the character of God.
In fact, first Peter, as Peter is writing, he'll reference back to the book of Leviticus,
for he says it is written, and he says to the believers that he's writing to there in
first Peter to be holy in all manner of conversation.
Why?
Again, be holy as I am holy is what God said.
And so we begin to think about the holiness of God and how this truth that's given to
us in verse number 13 should shape our understanding when it comes to the subject of temptation.
Notice the Bible says, let no man say when he is tempted, I am tempted of God.
And so therefore, the error could be that when you're tempted, you're in error saying
this is God that did this.
God tempted me with this evil.
And James says, let no man say when he is tempted, that I am tempted of God.
Why?
Because he highlights the character of God again in verse 16.
Do not err.
Do not have the wrong philosophy, the wrong mindset, the wrong belief to think that this
temptation is something that God has set evil before you.
For we find that James summarizes it this way in verse 13, for God cannot be tempted
with evil, neither tempteth he any man.
Well that helps me as I begin to understand.
Listen, have any of you been tempted since you got saved?
You said this morning I was tempted.
I was driving here and this guy, yeah, I understand.
Amen.
You were driving a couple of weeks ago and sometimes you see some crazy things when you're
driving and there were these two guys on 66 and they were like, I didn't know what was
going on, man.
They're racing each other and cutting each other off and then brake checking each other
and I'm just kind of letting my distance, I'm slowing way down.
I don't want to be involved in their accident or whatever's going on with them.
But listen, sometimes we're tempted.
Amen.
Somebody said something, somebody didn't say something, something happened, right?
You're tempted.
Listen, James says do not err.
Don't think that that temptation to do evil originated with God.
Don't put the blame on God.
Amen?
And so he instructs his people, God instructs his people to be holy and he is not, he is
not the author of sinful temptation.
Think about this.
If God tells us to walk in obedience, if God tells us to be holy as he is holy, it is inconsistent
with his character, his nature, it is inconsistent with his instruction to us to then put sinful
temptation before us.
It's inconsistent.
The trials that come, remember when the Bible says that in the book of Genesis when you
don't need to turn there, but when Abraham is dealing with the situation there, it says
that God did tempt Abraham.
That doesn't mean that he tempted him with a sinful temptation.
It was a test, a trial.
It was designed to prove.
That's the trials that we've been looking at in verses 2 through 13, sorry, 2 through
12 of James chapter number 1.
But now this temptation that is dealt with in verses 13 through 15 is sinful, it's evil,
it's wicked, and it is not consistent with God's character to put before the very people
that he said to walk in holiness, to walk in obedience, to then tempt us to do evil.
So he says, let no man say.
See, we could be in error, we could have the wrong philosophy, the wrong idea, and so what
is given here is God is correcting, he's instructing so that we are not living in
error, do not err.
And so we find that God, his character is here.
Let me say this, it deflates the argument that is so prevalent today where individuals
will say something like this, well this is the way God made me and it excuses their sin.
Have you heard that?
By the way, we understand that man is born a sinner, amen?
We understand that truth, you're not a sinner because you sin, you sin because you're a
sinner.
We're all born with a sin nature.
We understand that Adam sinned in the garden and it's been passed to all humanity and we
are sinners, we are born sinners, that's why we need to be born again, amen?
Because the penalty for sin is death, separation from God for all of eternity in a place called
the lake of fire, and so we need to be born again, but understand when somebody says well
this is just how God made me, what are they doing?
They're putting the responsibility for their sin on God, they're shifting it, they're in
error.
Yes, we're born sinners, but God did not, he's not the author of evil, he's not the
one that's tempting you, and in fact as you continue to look through the scriptures in
this portion of scripture, we find number two in verse number 14, so we see number one,
James first deals with the character of God, but now in verse number 14, I want you to
notice the culpability of sin, the culpability of sin.
The Bible says this, but every man is tempted when he is drawn away, notice this phrase,
of his own lust and enticed.
As we look at verse number 13, we understand that James says let no man say when he is
tempted that he's tempted of God, no, because God cannot be tempted with evil, neither tempteth
he any man, so then James says here's the character of God, this is why it would be
invalid for you to say you were tempted of God, but now let me address the area of the
culpability of sin.
This removes the blame shift problem with humanity, amen, because the Bible says right
there in verse 14, of his own lust, amen, the culpability of sin, and so we find that
it's a matter of personal responsibility.
The fact that you are understanding in verse 14, it says, but every man is tempted when
he is drawn away of his own lust and enticed.
Again, as we look at this truth and we understand that it's of his own lust, a matter of personal
responsibility, it deals with that blame shift.
In fact, in the garden, is that not what they tried to do?
Adam, Adam, right?
Where was Adam?
Well, they were trying to hide from God.
Why were they hiding from God?
Because their eyes were open, why?
Because they sinned, amen, and so God, no longer were they ready to...
have that communion with God that they had known and enjoyed, they're hiding
from God, God knew exactly where they were, God doesn't ask questions to gain
information, he's searching the hearts of his people, and he says, Adam, we hid
ourselves because we were naked. Who told you you were naked? Right? I mean, and so
then they're confronted with their sin, and what does Adam say? The woman you
gave me. Hey man! He tried to shift that thing immediately, right? I mean, he just
got after it, so then he talks to Eve, and what does Eve say? Serpent! Am I
telling it right, or do we need to go read it? Amen! That's what happens, right?
It's blame shift. You know how many times we do the same thing? Well, if that person
didn't do that, well, if this person would have, well, if they didn't, well, if this
was, and we begin to just, what we're doing is we're excusing our sin. We're
blame shifting, but I have this thing going on so God understands that I'm not
going to honor him, that I'm not, I had this bill come up so I'm not gonna give
to God, because no, God doesn't understand sin. In fact, in James, it's
gonna tell us this, and we'll get there, I would say in a couple months, but I
don't know how long, we'll get there eventually. In verse 17 of chapter 4,
therefore to him that knoweth to do good and doeth it not, to him it is sin.
How does he know what's right? Well, God gave us a Bible. That's why he says in
the text, do not err. That's why he says this, think about this and connect all
the dots with me, if you will, therefore to him that knoweth to do good and doeth
it not, to him it is sin. James 1, verse 16, do not err. He wants us to know the
truth, he's given to us truth so that we would know, and then in verse 22 it says,
but be doers of the word and not hearers only, deceiving your own selves. So we
take these things into, you know, as we interpret them and we take them and we
understand God has given to us truth and he wants us to understand, he wants us to
be personally responsible. When you're given the truth of God's Word, you have a
choice. We do not believe in conversion by force. You can trust Christ as your
personal Savior if you choose to do so. Amen? It's a choice that you recognize
that you're a sinner, that he's the only Savior and accept him as your personal
Savior, and the reality is that if you choose not to trust Christ and you
choose to just, I'm gonna figure it out my own way, then one day you'll stand at
the great white throne judgment, you will confess that Jesus is Lord to the glory
of God, but you will be cast in the lake of fire. That's just the truth of God's
Word. I don't say that as if I would like anyone to do that. In fact, that ought to
bring tears to our eyes to consider the condition of lost man. But as believers,
you know, you have the same kind of choice. You chose, you received Jesus
Christ your personal Savior. Praise God for that. But then what are you, what's
the holy living day by day? Are you honoring God with your life? Are you
recognizing this thing of the culpability of sin that it is, it is
your own loss, you're drawn away of his own lust? It is that personal walk with
God that is so important. Some of you would remember, some of you have no idea.
I actually don't remember because it was in the 1970s, and praise God I was born
in 1980, amen? But in the 1970s there was a fellow by the name of Flip Wilson, and
Flip Wilson used this phrase, he really popularized the phrase, the devil made me
do it. All right, some of you remember that. And in using and popularizing that
phrase, he tried to really make a, use it and make it as a humorous excuse for
impulsive behavior. It's kind of interesting that in 1970s that was going
on. You know the very first time in a court hearing that demon possession was
ever used as an excuse was in 1981. Kind of interesting isn't it? You think media
and TV and entertainment doesn't influence people? Come on, you put that
garbage in front of the kids and they're getting it and they're learning and
it's influence. And so in 1981 for a murder trial the defense attorney used
demon possession as an excuse for the murder of an individual. The devil made
me do it. No, no, you're drawn away of your own lust. We're not going to put the
blame, we're not going to say in verse number 13 that it was God that tempted
me, and yes we understand that the devil is going to accuse the brethren, and
there's yes the truth of temptation that comes from the enemy, but understand the
culpability of sin, the personal responsibility that we're drawn away of
his own lust reminds us of the truth of our sin nature, the old man. Before you
got saved you were bound by sin. Amen? Romans teaches us that and we find that
the truth is is so precious to us when we look at the fact the fact that sin
shall no longer have dominion over us. Man, aren't you thankful for that? If you
were saved, if you've been saved, if you're here this morning you're saved by
the grace of God, sin no longer has dominion over you. What does that mean?
You've been you've been saved from the the power of sin. You now can walk in
liberty. You now can walk in obedience, and now you have the old man and the new
man, and you have this conflict that takes place, and you have that old nature,
the sin nature, and so we find that as we begin to look at the culpability of sin,
again we're not gonna blame shift, we're not gonna take and use the approach of
humanity of somebody else made me do it, and I did this or I'm this way because
of, no, I'm taking the culpability, the responsibility. It's me. It's my own lust.
Look at Galatians 5 if you will. In Galatians chapter number 5 we read an
important truth and it's one in which we ought to be mindful of here with
regard to the text before us in James 1. The Bible says this in Galatians 5,
notice with me in verse number 16, the Bible says this, this I say then, walk in
the Spirit and you shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh. Now as you read that
verse of Scripture as it's before you, as you would interpret that verse of
Scripture, does it say to you that you no longer will have the lust of the flesh?
No. Not only does the Bible not teach that, but your own experience reveals to
you that your flesh still has lust. Amen? And so the Bible doesn't tell us that at
the moment of salvation that our flesh is no longer going to have lustful
desires. The Bible doesn't tell us any longer that you get saved and the old
man is eradicated. No, we have the responsibility to crucify the old man. We
have the responsibility of mortifying the old man. We have the responsibility
of walking in the Spirit, and by the way, that's the choice that we make. Amen? And
the Bible says, this I say then, walk in the Spirit and notice the powerful
promise, and ye shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh. Before you got saved,
you live to fulfill the lust of the flesh. Amen? Am I telling it right?
Before you got saved, you live to fulfill the lust of the flesh. You get mad at
lost people because they live to fulfill the lust of the flesh, but that's how we,
that's how lost people live. But now that I'm a new creature, old things are
passed away. Behold, all things have become new, and now I have this conflict
where within me and within you, we have this conflict of desiring to live
for God and to please the Lord, but we have the old man, that old flesh, and
you find that it still has desires. It still has lust. Aren't you thankful
that God allows us the privilege of knowing that He says, if we walk in the
Spirit, ye shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh? I just can't get victory. No,
you can have victory. Victory is possible. Amen? Listen, can I tell you, if victory
was not possible, we'd be miserable. But victory is possible. Is it easy? No. I
never, I'll never sit in my office with anyone and tell them it's gonna be easy
for them to have victory over some sin, over some vice in their life. No, it's not
easy, but God promises that we can have the victory. We do not have to walk in
defeat. Amen? And so we have to understand this thing of the culpability of sin, the
fact that it's our own lust, and in our flesh, and our old man. Notice in
Colossians, if you will, and there's a number of passages that we could go to.
I've just selected a couple of them here this morning, but look in just a few
pages there in your Bible. Turn to the book of Colossians, in chapter number
three. In verse number one, the Bible says, if ye then be risen with Christ, seek
the Lord.
those things which are above.
Where Christ sitteth on the right hand of God,
set your affection on things above,
not on things on the earth.
Isn't that precious?
Listen, I'm thankful to be saved by the grace of God.
The Bible says that because, since I'm saved,
that idea of that word if is dealing with since,
where you then be risen with Christ.
Listen, I'm a new creature, I've been born again,
and what am I to do?
I'm to set my affection on things above,
not on things on the earth.
He says this in verse three,
for ye are dead, and your life is hid with Christ in God.
Paul's writing this to the believers in Colossae,
but Paul said this of himself in Galatians,
chapter number two, I am crucified with Christ.
Amen?
It's understanding, as he says in verse number five,
mortify therefore your members which are upon the earth.
Your old man, your old nature has lust.
And if you try to say it doesn't,
you have deceived yourself.
Do not err.
James, do not err, right?
So what's he doing?
Well, he's talking to us about the character of God
in verse 13, don't err and say that God is the author.
Do not err and say God is the one
that tempted me with this evil.
Verse number 14, do not err and have this idea
that your flesh no longer has lust.
No, this is the path that we find.
Every man is tempted when he has drawn away
of his own lust and enticed.
Well, I can do this, it doesn't really bother me.
I'm not tempted by it.
You better be careful.
Let him that thinketh that he stand,
take heed lest he fall.
You ever read that verse in First Corinthians?
Amen?
And what a blessing to understand.
Listen, I believe that we ought to put on
the whole armor of God and we better be ready
to deal with the attacks of the enemy
and we ought to be ready to walk in the Spirit
so that we do not fulfill the lust of the flesh,
but don't be in a position where you're going
to think that I can face all of these things
and it's just not gonna bother me.
I'm gonna put myself in this position.
No, when we understand what James is giving us here
in these verses of Scripture,
it's going to help me to be able to put
and to do some things in my life that will keep me
from being in a place of temptation.
One of the greatest ways to avoid sinning
is just not being in the place of temptation.
Amen?
You know, people messed up by putting themselves
in the wrong place.
And that old nature.
Amen?
I never intended for that to happen.
I never intended for this to be the,
but you put yourself in a really bad spot.
You made a decision and you fought
that you could handle it.
You can't handle sin.
You can't in your own power.
You can have victory through Jesus Christ.
But we look at this passage and we understand that,
listen, just looking at verse 13 and 14,
there are a lot of people that err with this truth.
There are a lot of people that try to shift and blame
and this is how I was born or how I was made,
this is how God made me.
It's interesting, the people that deny that God exists
say this is how God made me.
Have you ever noticed that?
You just kind of scratch your head and be like,
which God are you talking about?
Because you say you don't believe in God.
That was for free.
But the reality is this, we do have a responsibility.
I have the old nature and so do you.
And we must understand the way it works
and that's where we get to verse number 15, number three
in your notes this morning, the course of sin.
We notice the character of God.
Our God's holy, holy, holy, holy.
We notice the culpability of sin, of his own lust.
It's our personal responsibility.
But notice the course of sin that is outlined for us
here in verse number 15.
It says, then when lust, so what did he say?
He's drawn away of his own lust and enticed.
Then, so this is the ball begins rolling, right?
The sequence of what's taking place.
Then when lust hath conceived, it bringeth forth sin
and sin, when it is finished, bringeth forth death.
Lust, sin, death.
We could look at examples as we would use
and we'll reference them here this morning.
Look at a couple of verses.
But even as we read in the Old Testament,
they saw, they desired, and they took, right?
That's the lust, the sin, and the death.
And you look through that process
and you look at the course that is revealed to us here
in verse number 15, and here's what I fear sometimes
is that people don't really believe it.
They don't really believe the course of sin.
Some people think they can handle sin.
It's not really gonna destroy me.
I can handle this.
It's not gonna really bring death.
I'm saved, I'm not gonna go to hell.
Praise God.
But salvation is a whole lot more
than I'm not going to hell, amen?
And I'm thankful I'm not gonna go to hell.
I'm not gonna go to the lake of fire because I'm saved,
but I don't wanna die a premature death
because I'm living in sin, amen?
I don't wanna lose out on God's blessings
because I'm living in sin.
I don't wanna deal with God's chastisement
because I'm living in sin, right?
So sometimes I just fear that some people
really don't believe this.
They think that they can handle it.
Somebody said this when I was in Bible college 25 years ago.
I remember somebody making this statement
that allowing sin in your life is like having a rattlesnake
running around your house.
Not running, but slithering.
Now you know that got my attention
because I don't like snakes,
especially not rattlesnakes, amen?
Because I'll tell you what,
if there's a rattlesnake in my house, I am moving.
I'm not gonna be living there anymore, but we got it.
I talked to these guys from South Africa.
I said, y'all got some snakes down there, don't you?
And they, yeah, mambas and this thing.
And I'm like, no man, uh-uh, that is not a place for me.
But what are they trying to say?
You don't wanna have a pet rattlesnake.
You ever see those guys that handle snakes,
them crazy dudes in West Virginia?
Have you ever seen videos of that stuff?
Those guys are insane, literally.
They misunderstand the sign gifts, right?
I can guarantee you that I would never handle a rattlesnake.
Nope, not happening.
But think about it.
Sometimes you let sin in your life.
So I can handle this.
It's not really gonna affect me.
It is.
Sin in the life of a believer causes our fellowship
with God to be hindered.
And that oughta concern you.
We sing the song, nothing between my soul and my Savior,
and what a great song it is.
But you know, at times we think,
well, this is just a little thing.
And sometimes we have these categories in our life
of what's a little sin and a big sin,
and what's a sin that we allow and don't allow.
And we go through this, and some people just don't,
I feel like they don't really believe it.
But I'm telling you, the Bible is true.
The Bible is true.
And you don't wanna mess around with sin.
We see in Genesis chapter number three, she saw the fruit.
She desired the fruit.
And she took it, she ate it.
Then her eyes were opened.
You know, spiritual death happened immediately.
Amen?
Physical death didn't happen immediately,
but spiritual death happened immediately.
And then physical death came.
Right?
And we find, think about Achan.
You know how Achan is described in 1 Chronicles
in the genealogies that no one likes to read?
He is the troubler of Israel.
How'd you like that to be what you're known for?
Why is he called the troubler of Israel?
Well, because he saw
some gold, Babylonian garments, right?
He saw those things, and he desired them, and he took them.
And then what do you have to do?
He had to hide them.
You know what happens?
Sometimes we try to hide our sin, right?
No one's gonna know.
It's just me.
No one knows.
God knows.
You know.
And before long, other people are gonna know.
And if you were to read Joshua chapter number seven,
the whole nation knew.
The whole nation.
God gave instruction on how to bring them out
to be able to determine who it was.
And they came by tribes, and their tribe was taken.
They came by families and households.
Can you imagine as that thing was narrowing down in?
And all of a sudden, Achan is standing there.
He knew the whole time that he was the one that sinned.
Sin is deceitful.
The Bible talks about in the book of Hebrews the deceitfulness of sin.
And we find here that as you look at those Old Testament examples, what I want you to
keep in mind, look at 1 Corinthians 11, look at this New Testament truth that Paul is giving
here to the church in Corinth in 1 Corinthians 11.
It's the passage in Scripture in which we deal with when we observe the Lord's Supper.
What a blessing to have the privilege of being able to observe the Lord's Supper, to be reminded
of what Christ did for us on the cross of Calvary, how His body was broken, His blood
was shed so that we could be redeemed, and it's a blessed opportunity.
It's also an opportunity not just to remember, but an opportunity for us to examine our hearts
and our lives, our walk with God.
And the Bible says in verse number 30, dealing with that context of examination, it says
in verse 30, for this cause many are weak and sickly among you, and many sleep.
You know that word sleep doesn't just mean they're sleepy, they're tired.
It means they died.
The course of sin that is outlined in verse number 15 of James chapter 1 is lust, sin,
death.
I want you to understand for the lost person that separation from God for all of eternity,
but I want you to understand that God's hand of chastening comes upon His people.
I heard it said this way, that when God convicts us of our sin, that we ought to respond.
How many of you would agree with that?
God convicts you of your sin, you ought to respond.
Yeah.
Deal with it.
Get right.
Amen.
If we ignore the conviction, then He brings chastisement.
Chastisement is another opportunity for us to get right with God.
Amen.
By the way, chastisement is a sign that you're a believer whom the Lord loveth, He chasteneth.
I'm thankful that God doesn't just let us go and just let us do whatever we want to
do.
He convicts us.
He uses His word to convict us.
He then chastens us.
Somebody said this, if we don't respond to the conviction, the chastisement comes.
If we don't respond to the chastisement, the coffin comes.
From 1 Corinthians chapter 11 and verse 30, and this caused many are sick and weakly,
but many sleep.
We don't like to think that way.
And part of the reason we don't like to think that way is because we're in error.
We don't understand what James is giving to us here in James chapter 1.
We think that God's okay with it.
We think we can skip doing this or skip doing that, and God understands.
Listen, I'm so thankful that God is long-suffering and gracious.
Praise God.
But God's serious about sin, and He wants us to understand these truths.
He wants us to understand this course of sin.
Why?
Because when I understand the truth, when I have an understanding of what we've looked
at this morning in verses 13 and 14 and 15, and we understand and we couple it with verse
16, do not err, my beloved brethren.
I'm taking the truth of verse 13, 14, and 15 as it is the word of God.
It is truth, and I'm going to take it, and I'm going to then, as I know it, I'm going
to be enabled to take that personal responsibility, and I'm going to be able to make some decisions
in my life, and I'm going to be able to apply some things in my life.
Why?
Because I want to live a life that is pleasing to God, that is holy, that is right.
Does it mean that I'll never sin?
No, but sin should not be something that's just common in our lives.
Someone said this, we won't reach the place of sinless perfection, but we ought to be
sinning less and less as we walk with God.
The closer we get with God.
Remember, I mentioned this last Sunday morning, if you were here, that the Bible ended in
verse number 12, which the Lord hath promised to them that love Him.
And I said that that truth enables us to endure the trials that we face in life, but I also
said that it had an application for the text that we'd look at this morning, and the question
really is this, how much do you love God?
Because if you love God more, I don't want the sin, because I love God.
Does that make sense?
I'll use an example, I love my wife, amen?
I love her.
I tell her that all the time, she knows that.
So I have no eyes for any other woman.
Because I love my wife, I love her more.
Did anyone see about the Olympic guy that was crying and moping because he met the love
of his wife, or love of his life, and he couldn't share the moment of having the silver medal
with the love of his life?
Did anyone read this or see this?
I don't know what country he was from, but he says as he was having a silver medal in
an Olympic contest in the Winter Olympics, he said, I got this silver medal, and he's
crying, and it's just kind of like a weird situation, he's like, I'm crying not because
I'm happy, I'm crying because I don't get to celebrate this with the love of my life.
I met the love of my life a few months ago, and she's the love of my life, but I cheated
on her, and now she's not with me anymore.
She's not the love of your life.
Because you loved whatever that pleasure was more than you loved her.
Are we tracking?
Amen?
So do we love God more than the sin?
Do we love God more than the pleasure of sin for a moment, right?
I love God more.
Does it mean that I never sin?
No, because I still have the old man, but every day I pray, Lord, help me to live crucified.
Lord, help me to walk in the Spirit so that I do not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
If you pray that enough, you'll be able, the Lord will give you the discernment when you're
dealing with that spiritual battle and that temptation, and you'll be in the moment, and
you're like, I just prayed a few hours ago to help me to walk in the Spirit so that I
do not fulfill the lust of the flesh, and I can feel the flesh wanting me to fulfill
the lust of the flesh, but I'm going to choose to walk in the Spirit, amen?
And so when I understand the truth, when I understand I'm not going to just listen to
the philosophies of the world, I'm not just going to lean on my own understanding, I'm
going to take the truth of the Bible, and it's going to give me a biblical worldview,
a biblical perspective, and I can then make decisions and choices in my life so that I
can ensure that the result of sin is not something that's going to be found in my life, death.
Amen?
Let me use two examples.
Many of you, perhaps not all of you, but many of you would be familiar with them.
Joseph, in Genesis chapter 39, repeatedly, lie with me, lie with me, and here's what
Joseph says, and I'm not going to develop the entirety of either one of these, I'm just
going to simply make a comment and keep going, but in Genesis chapter 39 and verse number
9, here's what Joseph says.
There is none greater in the house than I, neither hath he kept back anything from me
but thee, because thou art his wife.
How then can I do this great wickedness and sin against God?
No one will know, Joseph.
God will know.
No one will see, Joseph.
God will see.
Amen?
I think there's a Patch the Pirate song from this portion of Scripture.
Put on your running shoes.
Amen?
We understand God will provide a way of escape.
First Corinthians 10, verse 13, it's a promise that he gives us.
He'll provide a way of escape.
We've got to look for it.
We've got to want to take the escape route.
Joseph did.
You know what happened in Genesis 39?
He lost his coat, right?
He ended up in prison, but he was right before God, and that's what matters.
That's what matters.
David.
In 2 Samuel 11, we find the account is given to us in 2 Samuel 11 of David, and there's
a situation that's going on where it was time for the kings to go forth to battle, but David
tarried at Jerusalem, according to verse number one, and David, because he was really not
where he was supposed to be, and you could preach a whole message on that, amen?
I wasn't where I was supposed to be, and then this thing happened.
Yeah, you were, you put yourself in a vulnerable position for temptation, amen?
I wasn't even supposed to be there.
Well, why were you?
Amen?
So we find that he wasn't where he was supposed to be.
He's there, and he sees a woman, according to verse number two, and here's what he says
in verse number three, David sent and inquired after the woman.
We know it's Bathsheba.
One said, is not this Bathsheba, the daughter of Eliam, the wife of Uriah the Hittite?
It's very interesting as you begin to think about what's happening here, and even the
response of verse number three, as David sends and inquires, he's lusting after her.
We know, as we read the scriptures, that He wants to have her to be with Him, and the
answer is, is not this Bathsheba the daughter of Eliam?
And this is actually a family relationship to the one who was David's counselor.
If you go back and you look at the genealogy, and you see what's going on there, but then
He says this, the daughter of Eliam, the wife of Uriah the Hittite.
She was a married woman.
Thank God for the warning that David was given in verse number three.
But you know what David did?
He ignored it.
And you read verse number four, and the Bible says, and David sent messengers and took her.
She came in unto him, and he lay with her, for she was purified from her uncleanness,
and she returned unto her house.
You know how that thing turned out for David?
Terrible.
He tries to cover it, right?
Sends for the husband to come back from battle.
Tries to cover.
So when the baby is born, no one would think that it was a result of David.
The man has integrity.
All of his fellow soldiers are out fighting, I'm not going to go home to my wife.
So David continues to try, and then David sends orders in his hand of how he would be
killed in battle.
And then he's free to take her to be his wife.
No one's ever going to know.
God knew.
What I'm saying to you this morning is that when we understand the truth of what we read
in James chapter number 1, we have to take the truth of God's Word, not the philosophies
of this world.
And we have to be in the position where we're saying, I'm not going to err.
Do not err.
Don't get comfortable with sin.
Don't think it's okay.
Don't excuse your sin.
Don't ignore your sin.
Don't blame shift.
Don't say, well, this is, you know, God is going to be understanding because of.
No, what am I missing out on?
What am I losing out on?
Because I'm committing the sin, because I'm giving in to my own lust.
Because I'm not walking in the Spirit.
Because I'm not mortifying my members.
I'm not putting off the old man and putting on the new man.
See, when I understand the passage in James chapter 1 and verses 13 through 15, it helps
me to apply all these other passages in my life and say, here's how I want to live and
walk day by day.
Why?
Because I understand this flesh.
And I understand the culpability of sin that I'm drawn away of His own lust and enticed.
But that lust brings sin and that sin brings death.
And I don't want that.
I don't want that.
I want to please God with my life.
I don't want to have the consequences.
See far too often, people only think about the pleasures of sin and not the consequences
of sin.
Not just the consequences that you'll suffer here on this earth, but the consequence of
disappointing your God.
Think about that.
I don't like for somebody to not be pleased with me, humanly speaking.
I mean, just in human relationships.
I don't like it.
It happens sometimes.
Sometimes there's nothing you can do about it.
They didn't like that I preached that the Bible is the Word of God.
And I mean, I don't like it, but it is what it is.
Because I believe that to be true.
But I'm talking about relationships.
I just don't like...
Listen, I don't want God to be displeased with me.
I don't want God's chastening in my life.
It's not pleasant.
It's for our good, but it's not pleasant.
And so this morning, do not err.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
Thank You for loving us.
Thank You for Your Word.
Lord, I pray that You would help each of us this morning to accept the truth of Your Word
as it is truth.
Help our biblical worldview to be just that, biblical.
Help us not to be influenced by society, by the philosophies of this world.
Help us not to be influenced by our own thinking, our own logic and reasoning.
Help us, Lord, to trust You and obey You.
And Lord, help us to make decisions in our lives that will help us in living a life that
is pleasing in Your sight, being holy in all manner of conversation.
Thank You the Spirit of God lives within us and that we can walk in the Spirit so that
we do not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
Father, if there's one here that's not sure of heaven, I pray that even through the message
today that You've convicted them of their need for Christ and that they would, before
it's eternally too late, make that decision to trust You as their personal Lord and Savior.
In the moment of invitation, I pray that You would have Your will in a way, Lord, help
us to make decisions this morning that would please Thee to apply truth in our lives.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would You stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
At the end of our services, we have an invitation.
If you're not sure of heaven, Mark is here.
If you're a man, take a Bible, show you how you could know for sure that heaven is your
home.
Holly's here.
If you're a lady, take a Bible and show you how you could know for sure that heaven is
your home.
If you're a lady, you're not sure of heaven, it's your opportunity to come and trust Christ.
Maybe this morning you just want to come and ask God to help you in this area of godly
living to have an understanding biblically of what we've looked at this morning, rejoicing
that we serve a God who is holy, recognizing it's our own personal responsibility, that
culpability of sin, and in the course say, God, help me to walk in the Spirit so that
I would not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
Help there to truly be nothing between my soul and my Savior.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.