Morning will be the text that we'll be preaching from and the title for the message as you see in the bulletin there the power of
The gospel. I'm so thankful that we have been entrusted with the gospel of Jesus Christ and we have the unique privilege
I shall say
Responsibility of sharing that precious message the good news of Jesus Christ
You'll be mindful of the fact that before the Lord Jesus Christ went to the cross of Calvary in John chapter number 17 in verse
Number 18, he declared as thou hast sent me into the world
Even so have I also sent them
Into the world. We understand that the gospel has been given and we have been sent and we have a
Responsibility and Jesus made that declaration in John 17 before he would go to the cross of Calvary
Of course
We are mindful of the fact that after the resurrection of our Savior and before the ascension
we understand that he gave the Great Commission as we often refer to it as
You can read about the Great Commission and each of the Gospels again in the book of Acts
But you'll be mindful of the fact that he the Lord Jesus Christ
He said that we have been given this duty this job to preach the gospel to every creature
What a unique privilege and responsibility it is
we understand that as we read through the book of Acts that we have the
Privilege of being able to see the way in which the disciples
obeyed the declaration that Jesus gave and how the
obedience of the disciples
Resulted in the gospel going far and wide and many churches being established
You should read through the book of Acts. You'll find that there are two in my
Estimation just just amazing statements that are made in the book of Acts from those that opposed the gospel
These are not statements that were made by the leaders of the church
They're not made by the Apostles or one of the disciples
but we find that these are statements that are made by those that were in opposition those that were the
adversaries to the gospel going forth and really the statements that are made revealed to us the
obedience of the disciples and the
Work of Christ as we obey God and we do what he's told us to do
We see that he blesses beyond measure
the first of those statements is made in Acts 5 in verse 28 when those that are
Opposing the work of the ministry say this ye have filled
Jerusalem with your doctrine
that's a good thing, isn't it and
We have commanded you not to speak in his name yet. Ye have filled
Jerusalem with your doctrine. Oh that it would be said of us here in northern, Virginia
That we have filled this community this region of the state this part of our nation with the gospel of Jesus Christ
We find that later in Acts 17
When Paul and Silas would arrive to the city of Thessalonica that those in opposition said these
That have turned the world upside down
Are come hither
Also these that have turned the world upside down have come hither also that's Acts 17 in verse number 6
we find that
The gospel is powerful
we find that as you read through the journeys the missionary journeys as we'd often refer to them as in the book of Acts and you'll
find how that the
missionaries would arrive to a particular city a particular region you see how that the gospel preached change lives and
the power of the gospel those
That the cities that would be changed and transformed and just the the way in which the Lord would work mightily
I believe for us this morning that each and every one of us that we could stand
If we've been saved and we can stand and declare the power of the gospel in our own very lives
How he changed us what he's done in and through us as we look at Romans 1 in
Verses 14 through 16 this morning. We really are reading
the heart of the Apostle Paul as he's beginning to write to these believers in Rome and he shares with them some
important truth and I mentioned that our theme for our conference this year will begin on Saturday with the
Dinner and then Sunday Monday Tuesday Wednesday the theme of our conference is from Romans 1 16
I am NOT ashamed. I am NOT ashamed of the gospel
Why because Paul understood what the gospel is he understood that the gospel is powerful and as we look at this
Passage of Scripture. It is a familiar passage of Scripture
I want to make three observations this morning and I trust that as we consider these
Aspects of the life and ministry of the Apostle Paul that this morning we would be challenged
Through these verses notice in verse 14
Paul says this I am debtor both to the Greeks and to the barbarians
Both to the wise and to the unwise
So as much as in me is I am ready to preach the gospel to you that are at Rome also
For I'm not ashamed of the gospel of Christ for it is the power of God unto salvation
to everyone that believeth to the Jew first and also
to the Greek as
We look at this passage of Scripture. I'd like for you to consider first of all
The perspective of the Apostle Paul as we look at verse number 14
We begin to see his perspective and as we would consider his perspective
We would understand that the phrase and we'll use one phrase from each verse as we look through our message this morning
We would see that his perspective is summarized in these three words in first number 14. I am
Debtor I am debtor
You understand that as we would look at this passage of Scripture and understand that as Paul is writing to these believers in Rome
That he is sharing with them his personal responsibility
He has understood he has acknowledged and embraced the fact that he is
Personally accountable to God Almighty we find that as he would communicate these words and as he would say I am debtor
I want you to consider with me this morning. Really the the way in which these words would communicate the seriousness of Paul
He did not take this matter lightly
This this was not something that it was just a matter of convenience or if perhaps an opportunity would present itself
But you find that this perspective of the Apostle Paul when he says I am debtor
That as we look through the passage of Scripture and we consider the life and ministry of Paul as it's revealed to us
Throughout the Word of God
We find that it's this perspective that motivated him that allowed him to be used in the fashion in which he was
I am debtor. I mean notice he's he's not even saying to those in Rome that you are indebted
He's saying of himself. He's taking the personal responsibility and he's taking it seriously
I am mindful even as I read this passage of Scripture and I think about the way in which the
Apostle Paul is revealing to us that he is indebted
I'm mindful of what the angel said to those shepherds in Luke chapter number two. You'll be mindful that they were there
abiding in the field and those
Angels that appeared they say that I bring unto you right these glad tidings
But it says I bring unto you what shall be to all people
this wonderful
Proclamation that was given there in Luke 2 was not to just be given to the shepherds and held by the shepherds
But they were to go and proclaim
That message that Messiah was coming that he was born and we find this
This morning that as we look at this passage of Scripture that the gospel
the truth of the death burial and resurrection of Jesus Christ has been given to us and we are
Indebted to give that truth to a lost and dying world
You'll notice that he uses the phrase in verse number 14. I am debtor both to the Greeks and
to the barbarians
This was a very common idiom that would be used in this particular time and really what he's communicating
Is that he is indebted to all people?
Not just a certain group of people but to all people and we understand that as we've said many times over the years that
from the
Biblical perspective that we'd understand that there are simply two categories of people on this globe
There are people that have been redeemed by the blood of the Lamb
They are saved and heaven-bound and there are people that are lost in their sin
They are dead in their sins and their trespasses and the Bible says that the wage of sin is death
The Bible says death and hell will be cast like a fire
So we find it as we look at this passage of Scripture and we understand what Paul is saying
He's saying I have been entrusted with something that other people need
The gospel I am debtor both to the Greeks and to the barbarians
both to the wise and to the unwise as we consider the perspective of the Apostle Paul and
We notice the way in which he would use this terminology to communicate to us
By way of preservation the seriousness. I wonder this morning
How often do we take this matter as serious as Paul took it?
I wonder this morning how often how many of us would ever look at ourselves as being a debtor as being
Indebted to give this message to a lost and dying world
We find that as Paul would often communicate to those that he was ministering to I want you to look at what he says to
The believers in Corinth turn over if you will to the first Corinthians 9
And I want you to look at what Paul says
with regard to this responsibility that he had.
As we consider the responsibility,
and this is his perspective,
you will find why it was that Paul
went from city to city,
and as the Scriptures will say,
as his manner was,
he would enter into a city
and begin to preach the Gospel.
It's a perspective that we need.
It's a perspective that I need.
That we would have this perspective
that I am dead here.
Notice 1 Corinthians 9 and verse 16.
For though I preach the Gospel,
I have nothing to glory of,
for necessity is laid upon me.
Yea, woe is unto me
if I preach not the Gospel.
Notice in verse 23.
And this I do for the Gospel's sake,
that I might be partaker thereof with you.
Begin to see that Paul says,
woe is unto me there in verse 16,
if I preach not the Gospel.
I wonder how often we go through our lives,
and I wonder if perhaps there's a period,
a season of time in our lives
where maybe there's a few days
or maybe even a few weeks
that would pass by,
and we've not had the privilege
of sharing the Gospel with someone.
I wonder if we'd say like Jeremiah
that it's just bubbling in me.
It's like a fire within me.
I just can't wait to give the Gospel
to someone, anyone that would listen,
because I understand the truth
and the power of this wonderful message.
And Paul says, woe is unto me
if I preach not the Gospel.
He said I am debtor.
And I just wonder if we can in our minds
remember the last time we were able
to share the Gospel with someone.
I wonder if you can go to that place
in your mind and you can say,
I remember the last time I was able
to share the Gospel with someone,
and maybe they trusted Christ,
maybe they weren't interested,
but you remember that last time
you were able to speak of Christ
and speak of the good news of the Gospel.
Can I tell you this morning,
if that memory is way, way, way back somewhere,
I hope this morning that we'd have
that fire rekindled.
And we'd say, man, I just want to find someone
to give the Gospel to,
because I'm indebted.
I am debtor.
Notice what he says in 2 Corinthians 4.
In 2 Corinthians chapter number 4,
Paul says to these same believers in Corinth
in the same city,
this now second letter that he writes
in verse number three of this chapter,
we find that Paul says this,
if our Gospel be hid,
it is hid to them that are lost.
We obviously understand this morning
that those are the people that need the Gospel.
Those that are lost.
They need it.
We're indebted to them.
And Paul says if our Gospel be hid,
it is hid to them that are lost.
Notice what he says in verse number seven,
but we have this treasure in earthen vessels
that the excellency of the power
may be of God and not of us.
I notice the way in which he says
we have this treasure in earthen vessels.
We're but clay.
I mean, we're really nothing
except for the fact that we've been made
in the image of God Almighty
and the fact that God Almighty
came and died for us
so that we could be redeemed
and what a wonderful privilege,
but we have this treasure,
the Gospel of Jesus Christ.
Paul, in between the two verses
that we've read here in 2 Corinthians 4
and verse three and verse number seven,
we find that he mentions
about the work of the enemy
to keep blinded the minds of those
that have not received the Gospel of Jesus Christ.
And we understand that the enemy is alive
and active and he's working.
This morning, as Paul says here in verse number five,
we preach not ourselves,
but Christ Jesus the Lord
and ourselves your servants for Jesus's sake.
We don't preach ourselves.
I often say to individuals
as I have the privilege of sharing the Gospel with them,
I'm not asking you to come to our church.
I'm not asking you to give to our church.
I'm not asking you to do any.
I'm just trying to share with you the truth
of what Jesus Christ did for you
because one day you're going to die.
Are you ready?
See, I am dead hurt.
Notice what he says in 1 Thessalonians 2.
We'll move on to verse number 15 in Romans 1 here,
but look at what he says here
in 1 Thessalonians 2.
I made the statement by way of introduction this morning
that second statement that's made in the book of Acts
that's so impactful was in Acts 17 in verse six
when Paul and Silas arrived at the city of Thessalonica
and now he's writing this epistle back to these believers.
And I want you to notice what he says
in 1 Thessalonians 2 in verse number four.
And I believe that this will continue
to help us understand this perspective of Paul.
Notice what he says.
But as we were allowed of God,
notice what he says,
to be put in trust with the gospel.
Even so we speak, not as pleasing men,
but God which trieth our hearts.
I notice a few things here from verse number four
of 1 Thessalonians 2.
Number one, I understand that it's a privilege.
He says we are allowed of God.
Isn't it amazing that God would allow us
to be his spokespeople, to be his messengers.
In 2 Corinthians 5, Paul says that we are ambassadors.
And you think about that unique privilege
and opportunity that is ours.
And here Paul says that we were allowed of God.
And then notice that phrase,
to be put in trust with the gospel.
He says it this way in 1 Thessalonians
that we were entrusted to be put in trust with the gospel.
In Romans one, I am debtor.
Why did he recognize himself as being a debtor?
Because he had been entrusted with something.
And that something that he had been entrusted with
changed his life,
but it was something that he had to give to others.
So as Romans one, in verse 14,
we first consider the perspective of the apostle Paul
when he says I am debtor.
Number two, in Romans one, look at verse number 15.
Not only do we consider his perspective,
but I consider his preparation.
Consider the preparation of the apostle Paul.
Notice what he says.
So as much as in me is,
I am ready to preach the gospel to you
that are at Rome also.
We use the phrase from verse number 14
with regard to the perspective of Paul.
I am debtor.
We'll use the phrase from verse number 15
with regard to his preparation.
I am ready.
And we think about the apostle Paul,
what he's saying here.
So as much as in me is,
I am ready to preach the gospel to you
that are at Rome also.
When that opportunity presents itself,
are you ready?
Have you prepared?
Have you understood this perspective
that would then lead to this process of preparation?
See, we understand that as Paul
would have the perspective that I am debtor,
that I have been entrusted,
therefore we prepare.
We want to be ready to give the gospel
to those that we would come into contact with.
Perhaps there's been a time in your life
in which you have had a conversation
and you've left that conversation
and you've kind of said something like this,
man, I wasn't really ready to give the gospel
in that particular setting.
I wasn't mindful of it.
And maybe as you walked away
from that particular interaction that you had,
you said, man, I wish that I had handled
that conversation differently.
I wish I would have taken that conversation
more towards the gospel
and being able to present truth to that individual.
We, as we look at the perspective of Paul,
we then understand the preparation.
I wonder this morning,
as we would engage in conversation
that we come into contact with individuals
and we engage in conversation with them,
I wonder if we're ready to figure out
in those conversations how we make a beeline to the gospel.
We can talk for a long time about things
that really don't matter.
Right?
I mean, you talk to people
and they want to talk about the weather.
They want to talk about sports.
They want to talk about COVID
and they want to talk about all kinds of things.
I shared briefly a testimony on Wednesday evening
about an individual that I had contact with on Tuesday.
As I was speaking with them,
they were, what did they want to talk about?
They want to talk about the gas crisis
because that was the thing that was going on
that particular day on Tuesday, right?
And that was what they wanted to talk about.
And then it just went from the gas crisis
to you just name it, it was a free for all.
And as I stood there and listened to that individual
for that duration of just a few minutes,
my mind was thinking, how do I get to the gospel?
How do I get to the gospel?
And as he paused just long enough,
I was able to share with him truth
from Hebrews chapter number two.
And then went over to the truth
in the book of Revelations,
begin to share truth and try to take the conversation
to biblical matters, to the truth of the gospel.
Listen, there's all kinds of things
going on in our world today.
There's all kinds of opportunities for us
to talk about the way in which we find
some of these prophetical things in the word of God.
that are lining up and the way in which we see these things progressing and oh we
have opportunity. The question is are we ready? When I think about this term I am
ready, I think about someone that has entered into, they're mindful of,
and they're saying I am ready to preach the gospel. I'm ready, I'm prepared, I'm
mindful of it. I have prepared. The preparation of the Apostle Paul, I want
you to think about what he says in Galatians chapter number one. You'll be
mindful of the fact that Paul was converted and it's recorded for us in
Acts chapter number nine on the road to Damascus. His name was Saul at that time
and we find that after the first missionary journey which is recorded for
us in Acts 13 through 15. This is in the region of Galatia and he's now
writing back to those churches here in this book, but I want you to notice what
he says in verses 11 and 12 with regard to this thought of preparation. He says
this, but I certify you brethren that the gospel which was preached of me is not
after man. For I neither received it of man neither was I taught it but by the
revelation of Jesus Christ. Look over if you will skip down to verse number 18
and notice that he says then after three years I went up to Jerusalem to see
Peter and abode with him 15 days. During that period of time Paul was going
through some preparation. He was being instructed it says by the revelation of
Jesus Christ in verse number 12 and there's not a whole lot that we know
about that period of time in Paul's life, but we understand that there was this
process of preparation. You understand that as he would write to those that
he's ministering to over the years and as God would use them to write scripture
that often he will say to those individuals that he's writing to and
he's ministering to I say unto you by the Word of the Lord and he's giving
them the truth of God's Word. We find that even as he would deliver to these
individuals in Corinth the gospel that he helps them to understand that it's
the gospel of Jesus Christ what had been given to him he's then delivering to
others. I've been asked many times over the years what is it that you believe as
a Baptist? What is it that makes you different then? And they'll just start
listing some other denomination or group and I want them to understand that we're
seeking to follow the Bible. As a Baptist our number one if you will just a
statement that we seek to make with regard to our distinction is that the
Bible the Word of God is the sole authority for faith and practice. It's
something that we just kind of some traditions that we just follow like in a
in a wrong manner but we're seeking to follow the Word of God. What sayeth the
Lord? And if we're going to give truth if we're going to be ready to give the
gospel as Paul says in Romans 1 and verse number 15 we we have to have some
preparation. How is it that I'm going to give the gospel? What answer am I going
to give to someone when that opportunity presents itself? I'm mindful
of Ezra in the Old Testament in Ezra 7 and verse number 10 if you want to
jot that reference down but Ezra says in that passage of Scripture that he
prepared his heart to seek the law of the Lord and to do it and to teach in
Israel statutes and judgments. What a powerful verse of Scripture. Ezra he says
that he he was prepared as we would see that he understood that he sought the
law of the Lord to do it and then to teach in Israel statutes and judgments
the time of his preparation preceded the opportunity that was afforded him. We
find that if you were to read throughout Ezra 7 that's verse number 10 if you
read the remainder of chapter 7 and really get into chapter number 8 you see
that opportunities are given to Ezra because of the preparation that he's
already gone through. This morning as we think about these statements from
Romans chapter number 1 I believe that if we have that proper perspective in
verse 14 that I am dead or that it will lead us to that proper preparation of
being able to say I am ready and then as we have prepared I believe that God
will give us opportunities that he will present us with those opportunities. Why?
Well if we take these two thoughts in connection this morning then we are
mindful and we are looking for the opportunities because we have understood
the perspective that I am dead or and we've gone through the preparation I am
ready and therefore we are now looking for those opportunities. There are simple
statements that you can make to people that cause them to stop in their tracks
and inquire as to what you mean. I met a guy when I was in Bible college that
every time you asked him he wasn't in Bible college he was a preacher that
came through he preached a revival meeting at the college I think a couple
of the years that I was there and anytime you asked him how he was doing
he said better than I deserve. Why did he use that phraseology? Because countless
times he had the opportunity with saying to someone better than I deserve they
say what do you mean by that and then he had the privilege of being able to
right then right now go into sharing the gospel. Because when's the last time you
introduced yourself to someone or asked someone how they were doing and they
told you better than I deserve. It's not common it's not regular right and so
when you hear something that's out of the ordinary something that you're not
expecting it causes you to stop and say what do you mean by that? I told you the
story about the man at the bank when I said I was absolutely wonderful he says
you're lying nobody's wonderful huh I said you ain't met mr. Don yet because
he's been in the hospital bed and he's absolutely wonderful amen but he told me
I was lying that's what he told me I promise you
I was in Wells Fargo right over here on Germantown he said you're lying nobody's
wonderful I said well I'm going to heaven man I am wonderful and then he
got all kinds of sideways he's like are you dying I don't think so but one day
I'm going to amen and so are you what I'm suggesting to you this morning is
that I'm not perfect at it there are more times when I fail than I'm doing
what I'm supposed to do but that were mindful that were purposed and
understanding I am indebted I have been given the gospel of Jesus Christ it's
changed my life and now I have been entrusted with I better be ready to give
it notice in verse number 16 back in Romans 1 we consider the perspective of
the Apostle Paul we consider the preparation of the Apostle Paul and now
I want you to consider the passion of the Apostle Paul in Romans 1 in verse
16 he says for I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ for it is the power of
God unto salvation to everyone that believeth to the Jew first and also to
the Greek perhaps this morning you've not yet recognized this but I would
submit to you and I believe it to be the case that we're currently living in a
society in which they want you to be ashamed of believing the gospel they
don't want you to go talking about what you believe they want you to be ashamed
of the gospel of Jesus Christ that's the society that we're currently living in
but Paul says I'm not ashamed I am not ashamed as you study the New Testament
you'll find that Paul had a passion to reach people with the gospel of Jesus
Christ he understood what was at stake and he personally embraced the
responsibility we use the the phrases in verse 14 I am debtor in verse 15 I am
ready here I am not ashamed Paul as he would speak about in this very book the
book of Romans when he would speak about his brethren other Jewish individuals he
would speak about the way in which he had heaviness and continual sorrow in
his heart in chapter 9 and chapter 10 he would reveal his heart's desire in
prayer to God for Israel is that they might be saved you see a man that that
that was passionate about reaching people with the gospel of Jesus Christ
we find that this morning it's absolutely possible for us to have
passion in a variety of ways we find that there are people that we come into
contact with every day of our lives that are passionate about something whatever
that something is if you get them on the subject that they're most passionate
about they can talk about it and talk about it and talk about it some more you
know what I mean there are people that are passionate I just wonder this
morning do we have this same perspective and would we have that level of passion
to be able to say I am NOT ashamed of the gospel of Christ
Again, the society wants us, why does the society want you to be ashamed of it?
Because there's a spiritual war that's going on.
I hear more and more and more from folks all around in different periodicals that I receive
and different emails that come across my desk of people that want to talk about the cultural
war that we're engaged in.
And I submit to you, as I did a couple of years ago in preaching through the book of
Ephesians, that it is so much more than a cultural war, it is a spiritual war.
We're engaged in spiritual warfare.
And what happens at times in our lives is that we come into the place where we cower
in fear of sharing the gospel with someone because we're afraid of what they're going
to think or say.
And we're fearful and therefore we do not give the truth of the gospel.
We shy away from it.
We cower in fear and we find that this is happening at increased levels.
I'm going to share some things with you this evening.
I'm going to preach from the book of Jude and I'm going to look at a few things that
I hope would challenge us to have this proper perspective.
I understand that some won't be back this evening and so I'm going to read this tonight
so those that come back you'll hear it again.
But this is something that someone said with regard to acknowledging some of the great
hymns of the faith that we sing that were written many years ago in a generation that's
gone now and we find that they made this observation in mentioning about some of these
hymns that were made and here's what they say, in days when reaching the lost seemed
to be more of a priority for most believers.
I read that first statement, I'm going to read the whole thing to you this evening,
but I read the first statement, I highlighted it in yellow and it just crushed me as I read
it.
In days when reaching the lost seemed to be more of a priority for most believers.
Why isn't it a priority for us today?
What else has become a priority for us today?
And we've kind of not had that passion and we find that Paul had a passion.
He said, I am not ashamed.
We find that Paul, listen, he had his encounters with those that opposed the message that he
preached.
Amen?
There was opposition at every level and we find that there were times in which, and you
look at the first missionary journey, every city that they went into and they preached
the gospel and people got saved, they got ran out of.
Because there's opposition.
But Paul still says, near the end of his life, I am not ashamed.
Why?
Because I understand what the gospel is.
I understand that the gospel is the power of God unto salvation.
To everyone that believeth, to the Jew first and also to the Greek.
See, I mentioned this a moment ago, that Paul had an understanding of what was at stake.
Do you recognize this morning that each person that you come into contact with, whether that
be a coworker tomorrow, a neighbor this afternoon, someone at the restaurant in which you'll
have lunch this afternoon, every person that you come into contact with is going to die
and they're going to go to either heaven or the lake of fire.
That's just the reality.
And we find that he understood what was at stake.
These people aren't going to believe me.
These people are going to oppose me.
Well, at least I gave them the truth.
And I can stand before God and say, I told them, I did what I was commanded to do.
Look at Acts 17, if you will, as we think about this passion of Paul.
We've noticed his perspective, we've noticed his preparation, and now as we consider this
passion of his, we find in Acts 17, this is when they arrive in Thessalonica, according
to verse number one, notice in verse two, and Paul, look at these words, as his manner
was, went in unto them in three Sabbath days, reasoned with them out of the Scriptures.
We find that in verse number two, the Bible tells us as his manner was, this was the manner
of Paul.
This was his behavior.
This is what he did.
He comes into a city.
He's seeking to preach the gospel, to give the truth, as his manner was.
Notice what it says in verse 16.
Now you'll understand if we understand kind of what's going on here, the people that had
troubled in other cities had now come to Thessalonica, and so they have Paul, they sent him out,
and in verse number 16, the Bible says, now while Paul waited for them in Athens, his
spirit was stirred in him when he saw the city wholly given to idolatry.
We find that Paul, really, if we were to understand what's taking place, and without
having time to go through all of it this morning here in Acts 17, that they send Paul out ahead,
and they're going to basically get a little R&R, if you will, because of all that has
been encountered, and yet we find that when Paul is there, and he's waiting for them,
he's at Athens, his spirit was stirred in him.
Here's something that I've learned in my own life, and perhaps you can relate to this as
well, is that it's possible for us to be stirred up and do nothing about it.
It's possible.
Oh, that God would stir us, and it would bring forth some action.
No matter how small that action is, we've got to start somewhere, amen?
Maybe this morning, your prayer, because you can't remember the last time you shared the
gospel with an individual, as I mentioned earlier in the message, maybe the prayer this
morning of someone is, God, in the next 30 days, would you help me to share the gospel
with someone?
Maybe someone's prayer this morning is, God, would you help me in this process of preparation?
I'm not even sure how to take the conversation into the gospel.
Whatever it is, we start somewhere, because being stirred is a good thing, but that stirring
needs to bring forth some action in our lives, and some change in our lives, and we find
that here, the Bible says that he was stirred in his spirit, that his spirit was stirred
in him, and then notice verse 17, therefore, because of the stirring, what was it that
caused Paul to be stirred?
He saw a city that was wholly, entirely, completely given to idolatry, and his spirit is stirred
within him, and it says, therefore, because of what he saw, because of how he was stirred,
therefore, disputed he in the synagogue with the Jews, and with the devout persons, and
in the market daily with them that met with him.
What's Paul do?
Enough with the R&R, there's work to be done, amen?
I'm not suggesting that we don't ever need rest.
Jesus says, come apart and rest, amen, and we understand that there's a need for that,
but you look at Paul, and you see how he's stirred, and how he is brought to action.
He disputes with them.
Notice it says that, there in verse number 18, then certain philosophers of the Epicureans
and of the Stoics encountered him, and some said, what will this babbler say?
You know, some are going to call you a babbler, that's okay.
You know what Jesus said, newsflash, if they hate you, they hated me.
Isn't that what Jesus said, John 15?
You go and look at it, that's what Jesus said.
They say, what will this babbler say?
You know that there were people that encountered and went to where Jesus was teaching just
to criticize him?
That was the only reason why they went.
I'm reading through the Gospels right now, my personal Bible time, and as I'm reading
through the Gospels again, and I'm reading, I just finished Mark this morning, and as
I'm reading through the Gospels again, and I'm reading, and I'm just mindful, hey listen,
sometimes they just come to criticize him.
You know, that helps me when I get criticism.
There's some people that watch on that camera, on the other side there's a computer, and
they only watch to criticize.
It's just the way it is, and that's okay.
But what I'm saying this morning is that they might say, this babbler, don't worry about
that, just give the Gospel.
Notice what they say, he seemeth to be a setter forth of strange gods, because he preached
unto them Jesus and the resurrection.
What's he preaching?
The Gospel.
In verse number 23, he says this, as I passed by and beheld your devotions, I found an altar
with this inscription to the unknown God, whom therefore ye ignorantly worship, him
declare I unto you.
You know, we live in the midst of a lost and dying world.
We live in the midst of a people that are going to spend eternity somewhere, and there's
only two options.
I know that there are other groups of people that teach other things, but when you go to
the Word of God, you find that there's but two destinations, heaven and the lake of fire.
Because it is appointed unto man once to die, but after this, the judgment.
We find this morning that we need to understand what's at stake, and when we understand what's
at stake, it will impact our passion, and Paul, he's passionate and he's going.
In chapter number 18, when they get to Corinth, in verse number 4, it says this, and he reasoned
in the synagogue every Sabbath and persuaded the Jews and the Greeks, and what's he doing?
He's giving the Gospel.
It says that they opposed themselves and blasphemed and all these sorts of things
are happening but you find that the Lord Jesus Christ comes and encourages him.
Notice what it says in verse 9, then spake the Lord to Paul in the night by
a vision, be not afraid but speak and hold not thy peace. For I am with thee
and no man shall set on thee to hurt thee for I have much people in this city.
You know what Jesus said when he gave the Great Commission as it's recorded in
Matthew chapter 28? The last words in lo I am with you always, right? He's with us
and Paul receives encouragement because of this opposition and Corinth he goes
and he's preaching the gospel and God says the Lord says be not afraid but
speak and hold not thy peace. Be not afraid and speak. He says I am with thee.
What a precious promise of the Word of God. Turn over another couple of pages if
you will and look at Acts 20. I want you to notice what Paul says here in Acts 20. He's
here speaking to the leaders of the church at Ephesus. We think about the
passion of Paul to give the truth of the gospel. Notice what he says in verse
20 and 21. And how I kept back nothing that was profitable unto you but have
showed you and have taught you publicly and from house to house testifying both
to the Jews and also to the Greeks repentance toward God and faith toward
our Lord Jesus Christ. Skip down in verse number 31 if you will. Therefore watch
and remember that by the space of three years I ceased not to warn everyone of
everyone night and day with tears. Paul says I kept back nothing that was
profitable unto you. He says that he was testifying both to the Jews and also to
the Greeks repentance toward God and faith toward our Lord Jesus Christ. He
says that he did it with tears. He had a level of passion to just reach someone
with the gospel. And I believe this morning as we think about this portion
of scripture a familiar passage Romans 1 14 through 16. We notice these
statements and we are able to consider the perspective and the preparation and
the passion. I wonder this morning do we have a passion to reach people with the
gospel? The songwriter said we sing the song give me a passion for souls dear
Lord. A passion to reach the lost. What a wonderful hymn that is. And I just
wonder this morning what is it that we are passionate about? What is it that
if someone were to be asked, maybe a co-worker, maybe a friend, a neighbor,
maybe a family member, what is so-and-so passionate about? What would they say?
Would souls even be on the list anywhere as to what we're passionate about? Give
me a passion for souls. I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ for it is the
power of God unto salvation to everyone that believeth to the Jew first and also
to the Greek. As we draw closer to the Lord I believe that he will develop in
us a passion for souls as we draw closer to him. See because as we draw closer to
our Lord, as we walk with him as we're supposed to, we find that we'll begin to
love what he loves. Amen? Listen, before I was saved I didn't love the Bible. Before
I was saved I didn't love church. Before I was saved I didn't love the brethren.
Before I was saved I wouldn't give my money to a church or to missions. But as
we get saved and then as we walk with the Lord and as we draw closer to him we
begin to love what he loves. Jesus said this in Matthew 4, follow me and I will
make you fishers of men. They were fishers of fish. I am not a fisherman.
I've never been accused of being one. In fact, Joseph, I think it was their
basketball team, maybe it was a class, I can't remember where he was, he was the
only kid that his dad had not taken him fishing. I felt bad. I felt horrible. I
don't even have a fishing rod. I just, I don't know. I need to go to one of those
stocked ponds, you know what I mean? Where it's just easy. But the reality is that
these guys were fishers of fish. It's what they did. And Jesus said follow me
and I will make you fishers of men. The closer we get to the Lord the more we're
gonna love what he loves. And God so loved the world that he gave his only
begotten Son. Aren't you thankful for that love? The Bible says that he
commended his love toward us and that while we were yet sinners Christ died for us.
We've been the recipients but now we've been entrusted with something. And my
prayer, not only through the preaching today, I'm gonna preach another message
tonight on this same topic and really thinking about missions and next week as
we have our missions conference, anticipate hearing messages about
reaching the lost, reaching the world. My prayer for me and for each of you is that
God would not only stir us up but he would change us. That we would be changed
not just emotionally stirred but that we would be changed and that we would get
this same perspective that Paul had that would lead to a level of preparation and
give us a passion to reach people with the gospel. Listen, I believe we sang the
song Jesus is Coming Again. Some of you probably heard it says maybe morning,
maybe noon, maybe evening. The songwriter said maybe soon. I always say will be
soon. I think Jesus is coming back soon and I'm looking forward to it. Our time is
short. Amen? We have a work to do. May the Lord use us for his honor, for his glory.
Father we love you this morning. We thank you for loving us. We thank you for the
opportunity of looking at this passage of Scripture. I know it's familiar. I
pray God that you would help us to have a proper perspective. That we'd
understand that we are debtors. That we have been entrusted with the gospel of
Jesus Christ and that lost men need that message. Would you help us to prepare?
Would you help us to be mindful of taking those conversations and turning them to
spiritual matters? So that we might have the privilege of sharing the gospel with
those that we come into contact with. Oh in a day and age in which the hostilities
and the opposition seems to increase daily, I pray that you'd help us to not
be ashamed. Help us to be passionate. I pray God that you would not only stir
us this morning, but I pray that you'd change us. Help us to leave this place
understanding that we're entering into the mission field. I'm thankful for the
missionaries that we send across the seas, but you've caught us to simply go
across the street to our neighbors, our co-workers, our family, friends. Lord would
you use us for your glory. Would you help us to be mindful of the power of
the gospel. I pray that you'd move and work as only you can. For it's in Christ's
name we pray. Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's gonna play quietly on the piano. As she does, would you allow the
Lord to have his will and way in your life? Perhaps you want to use your pew as
an altar. Perhaps you want to come to this old-fashioned altar. But as Kimberly
plays, we invite you to respond to the message this morning.