Genesis chapter number 15, and for quite some time on Sunday evenings, we have been studying
through the book of Genesis.
Of course, every once in a while, as the Lord would lead, we'll take a diversion and go
to another portion of Scripture.
And the last time that we were in the book of Genesis, we looked at Genesis chapter 15
and verse number 1.
And as we looked at Genesis 15 and verse number 1, I titled the message, A Memorable Greeting.
And as we looked at the verse of Scripture and we understand really the context of what
had taken place in Genesis chapter number 14, you read the first verse of Genesis 15
and you are encouraged greatly and you have to come to the conclusion that Abram was encouraged
greatly as to hear these words from the Lord.
The Bible says this in verse number 1 of Genesis 15, after these things, the word of the Lord
came unto Abram in a vision, saying, Fear not, Abram, I am thy shield and thy exceeding
great reward.
You'll remember that in chapter number 14, there was a coalition of forces that came
and they were victorious in their attempt to conquer.
And of course, we find that Lot was one that was taken captive and Abram receives word
as to what has taken place.
And Abram goes with those men from his own house, his armed trained servants, and he
takes them and they pursue after and God gives victory.
And after that victory and after they recover all things, we find that there were two encounters
that Abram has.
The first was with the king of Salem, Melchizedek.
And what a blessing for Abram to have the opportunity to speak with the king of Salem
and how that the meeting, the discussion between Abram and the king of Salem, Melchizedek,
prepared Abram for the meeting that he would have with the king of Sodom.
And how we mentioned it's so important for us to spend time with the Lord and to be in
his word and to commune with him and how that we daily spend time in walking with our God
and he prepares us for the events that we will face in our day.
And we see exactly that in Genesis chapter number 14.
Remember it was Melchizedek that said that he was the priest of the most high God, El
Elyon.
And it's the first mention of that name of God in all of the scriptures that he is the
most high God.
He is the possessor of heaven and earth.
And what a blessing to see how God would reveal that truth to Abram through that encounter
with Melchizedek.
And then when Sodom comes, the king of Sodom, excuse me, when he comes and he offers to
give some goods to Abram, Abram replies and says, I have lift up mine hand unto the Lord,
the most high God, the possessor of heaven and earth.
And we spoke about the significance of that because the reality is that had he not just
met with Melchizedek, the king of Salem, he would have had no knowledge of what he shared
in response to the offer of the king of Sodom.
It was through that meeting that God revealed this truth about himself so that Abram would
be prepared, adequately prepared to be able to answer this king of Sodom.
Of course, there's the potential as you look at all that takes place, how that there was
the potential for that coalition to regroup and maybe attack again and so on and so forth.
I'm sure they weren't too excited about the fact that Abram came and recovered all and
maybe they'd go back and regroup and devise a new plan, a new strategy on how they would
go back.
And God appears to Abram and he says, first of all, fear not.
There's a lot of fear nots in the Bible.
Fear thou not, fear not, be not afraid.
I'm so thankful that God has given us into Abram in this greeting in verse number one,
he begins by saying, fear not, Abram.
You know, God is telling us to not fear.
We don't need to be afraid.
And we've, of course, finished up our study in the book of Hebrews and in our previous
couple of studies as we finished the 13th chapter, we were mindful of what we are told
in verse number six, where the Bible says that we might boldly say, the Lord is my helper.
I will not fear what man shall do unto me.
Of course, the end of verse number five, that great promise when the scriptures remind us
that our God is ever present.
He said, I will never leave thee nor forsake thee.
He says to Abram, don't be afraid, fear not, Abram.
And then he gives them two additional truths that are impactful.
He says, number one, I am thy shield.
We think about a shield.
And of course, we think about the protection that a shield would offer to an individual.
When we think about God himself, now you notice in your Bible, it says after these things,
the word of the Lord, it's all caps, it's Jehovah or Yahweh.
His name that is, of course, revealed throughout the scriptures, the proper name of God.
He's saying to Abram, I am thy shield.
I'm so thankful this evening to know that our God gives protection, that he is able
to protect, that he is our shield, our buckler.
And we find that Abram would be reminded of this truth.
And then he says, and thy exceeding great reward.
See Abram was offered some things from Sodom and he refused those things because he says,
I lift up mine eyes, or my hand, excuse me, unto the Lord, the most high God, the possessor
of heaven and earth, king of Sodom, I don't need what you're offering me.
And he's refused that which had been offered.
And then God comes and says, I am thy exceeding great reward.
I'm so thankful.
We sing the song, now I belong to Jesus.
Jesus belongs to me, right?
I mean, what a joy to know him as our personal Lord and savior, to understand that he is
our exceeding great reward.
Listen, there are a lot of people around the world today that are seeking all sorts of
things to bring satisfaction.
And there are people even within the broad category of Christendom that are looking to
find satisfaction through things, but we must understand that God is our exceeding great
reward.
And really, you know, he's all we need.
And we find that he supplies all of our needs and what a blessing to know the Lord.
After we find this interaction that begins in verse number one, the very beginning of
verse number two says, and Abram said, and so in the next few verses, we're going to
have the opportunity, we will be privileged to read really a discussion that takes place
between the Lord God Almighty and Abram.
And we find that Abram had introduced, had been introduced through this greeting with
these powerful truths, fear not, I am thy shield, I am thy exceeding great reward.
And then Abram responds to the Lord and we'll be looking this evening at verses two through
six in particular.
Notice the Bible says this in verse number two, and Abram said, Lord God, what wilt thou
give me seeing I go childless and the steward of my house is this Eleazar of Damascus.
And Abram said, behold, to me thou hast given no seed and lo, one born in my house is mine
heir.
The title for the message this evening is from verse number three, where Abram says,
to me thou hast given no seed.
To me thou hast given no seed.
Here in Genesis 15 verses two through six, notice with me number one, if you're taking
notes from verses two and three, I find that Abram's perspective is revealed.
Abram's perspective is revealed.
You know, the reality is that each of us have a perspective on things that we encounter,
things that we go through in life.
And sometimes if we would be honest, our perspective is wrong.
Sometimes our perspective needs to have some correction.
And we'll see that that's the case with Abram here this evening.
But Abram reveals his perspective to the Lord, and through this conversation and through
the opportunity that we have by it being recorded in the Word of God, we have the privilege
of looking at this discussion and really seeing the perspective of this man, Abram.
I find this evening that as I look at verses two and three, that Abram is a man that is
very transparent with the Lord.
Abram is a man that's coming and he's looking at what's taking place and we find that he's
sharing his heart, he's pouring out his heart and his concern to the Lord.
And I think that's important for us to understand this evening.
We see it throughout the Psalms when the psalmist is extremely transparent and shares his heart
with God.
You understand this evening that God knows your heart anyway.
But you know it does something for us when we're just transparent with God and we just
share our heart with God.
Abram is looking at this situation, he's received some promises we'll look at in just a moment,
and he's noticing the current situation and what he does in seeing this perspective being
revealed is, number one, he states the problem.
The problem is quite obvious.
He has no son.
He has no heir.
He says this in verse number two.
Lord God, what wilt Thou give me,
notice this,
seeing I go childless?"
Now, go back if you will a few chapters
in chapter 12,
and you say, why is Abraham,
of course, that's not his name yet,
it will be changed shortly,
but why is Abram asking this question?
Why is he stating this problem?
Why is it that he's saying,
what is it that Thou wilt give me
seeing I go childless?
Why is it that he says,
to me Thou hast given no seed?
Well, because in Genesis chapter 12,
in verse number one,
the Bible says,
and the Lord had said unto Abram,
get thee out of thy country
and from thy kindred
and from thy father's house
unto a land that I will show thee,
and I will make of thee a great nation,
and I will bless thee,
and I will make thy name great,
and thou shalt be a blessing.
No doubt from verse number two
of Genesis chapter number 12
that Abram would understand
that there would be a son,
a child that would be given
when God says,
I will bless thee,
I will make of thee a great nation.
Verse number seven,
and the Lord appeared unto Abram
and said unto thy seed
will I give this land.
And there builded he an altar
unto the Lord who appeared unto him.
We find that God gives him this promise
in verse number seven of Genesis 12,
and he says this,
he says unto thy seed
will I give this land.
Abram builds an altar,
he worships the Lord,
he responds in proper manner,
but yet we find that this promise
that is given in verse number seven
of chapter number 12,
when we come to chapter 15,
Abram's saying it's not happened yet.
We find that in chapter number 13,
look there in verses 15 and 16,
it's repeated what we just read
in Genesis 12 and verse number seven.
Here in Genesis 13 and verse number 15,
the Bible says for all the land
which thou seest,
to thee will I give it,
notice the next phrase,
and to thy seed forever.
Now you'll remember with me
as we study Genesis chapter number 13,
that here is the division between Abram and Lot.
Remember there was some discord,
there was some contention,
some strife between the herdmen of Abram's cattle
and the herdmen of Lot's cattle.
And Abram says listen,
this isn't good for us
and we need to separate.
He tells Lot you go ahead and you pick
and Lot picks and he goes towards Sodom.
We see and we understand that.
And the Bible tells us
that the men there were wicked
and sinners before the Lord exceedingly.
And Abram, he took that which was left,
he took that land
and he had given the option to Lot.
We find here that God then speaks to Abram
beginning in verse number 14.
And the Lord said unto Abram
after that Lot was separated from him
and you notice what he says,
that he was going to give him the land
and to thy seed forever.
Notice what he says in verse number 16.
And I will make thy seed
as the dust of the earth.
So that if a man can number the dust of the earth,
then shall thy seed also be numbered.
Do you see why Abram acknowledges a problem?
He's been given this promise.
In chapter number 12 in verses one and two
and verse number seven,
again in chapter number 13 in verses 15 and 16,
God has spoken to Abram
and God has told Abram
about making of thee a great nation
of you having this land and thy seed.
And yet Abram is saying,
I go childless.
I don't have a son.
There's no seed.
And so we have a problem
and we find that Abram
in offering not only the problem,
he really begins to offer a solution.
We notice in verses two and three again
of chapter 15,
notice what he says
and you see his perspective in verse number two,
he says, seeing I go childless
and then notice what he says
at the end of verse number two,
and the steward of my house
is this Eleazar of Damascus.
And Abram said,
behold, to me thou hast given no seed.
And lo, one born in my house is mine heir.
And so what is Abram saying?
He's saying, listen, God,
you've given me this promise.
I don't have a seed.
I don't have a child.
I go childless.
And so what about this one
that's been born in my house?
What about him being the heir?
What about that being the solution to the problem?
And I look at that and I say,
really, if we'd be honest this evening,
if we were in Abram's shoes,
we might come to the same conclusion.
We might come to the same perspective
that Abram has.
We understand as we go through the Scriptures,
Abram's not a young man
and he's getting more and more age
with each passing day.
And he's saying, I don't have a child.
I haven't had a child,
but God's given me these promises.
And as he's noticing,
he's analyzing the situation,
his perspective is being revealed to us
because he knows there's a problem.
He says here's a potential solution.
You know what the problem is with this solution?
It's the same problem that sometimes we have
with our solutions that we offer God.
They're by sight and not by faith.
It's a sight solution.
What do I mean by that?
Well, here's one that can fit the bill.
I got this one that's been born in my house
and he can be my heir.
And see, again, if we could understand this evening
and we could put ourselves into the shoes of Abram,
perhaps we too would come to the similar conclusion.
We say, Lord, how long do we have to wait for this?
Lord, I know You've promised this.
You said that You were going to make of me a great nation.
You said that this land was going to be
not only for me, but for my seed forever.
But I go childless.
And so Lord, one born in mine house,
he says this in verse number three,
is mine heir.
And I believe that it's a sight answer
and not a faith answer.
So we see number one, Abram's perspective revealed.
Number two, if you're taking notes in verses four and five,
notice with me God's promise explained.
I'm so thankful that our God is clear and precise.
I'm so thankful that our God is patient.
Aren't you thankful that God's patient with you?
The Bible word is long-suffering.
And our God is long-suffering.
And our God, we could look at a whole host
of examples this evening,
and we could look at how there are times in our lives
even that we could model some of that
which is contained within the pages of Scripture
where we kind of don't have the faith
that we need to have
and we're not responding in the manner
in which we should,
and yet our God is long-suffering with us.
And you notice in the text of Scripture
that God speaks a matter of factly.
He speaks clear.
He explains some things to Abram
in the next couple of verses,
but you understand that He doesn't like reprimand him.
And our God is so gracious and so merciful.
And here's what God does.
Notice in verse number four,
it says this,
and behold, the word of the Lord came unto him saying,
this shall not be thine heir.
Now, is that hard to understand this evening?
Sometimes we get these kind of things
from several different places
where people say, well, you know,
the Bible's just hard to understand.
And the reality is that much of the Bible
is extremely easy to understand.
And yes, there are some passages
that are much more difficult to understand.
And that's why I'm thankful that the Holy Spirit of God,
who's the author of Scripture, lives within me.
And He's the teacher, amen?
But the reality is that God comes to Abram,
and He says, again,
when we look at the promise being explained,
we find that the Lord came unto him,
and God is going to give a clear and precise response
to what Abram says.
Remember, Abram's identified a problem.
He's even offered a solution,
but God says, no, this shall not be thine heir.
Abram, you have the wrong perspective,
and we need to correct that.
We need to change that.
You need to understand something.
This is what God is saying to Abram.
And I believe that as we look here at the Scriptures,
that God is going to give Abram some truth
that Abram would have to then respond to.
And I want you to hold onto that thought
as we kind of go through the message this evening,
because the reality is that God has given us truth
that we need to respond to.
We've often said, and we've mentioned it
throughout the years,
that faith is simply taking God at His word,
that we believe God.
And here, Abram comes and his perspective is revealed,
but now God's promise is being explained,
and he says this,
not only is he going to dismiss
the potential solution that Abram has offered,
but he's going to once again rehearse with specific details
the promise that he's making.
Notice what he says.
This shall not be thine heir, verse number four,
but he that shall come forth
out of thine own bowels shall be thine heir.
Again, isn't that hard to understand?
No, it's quite clear, is it not?
Abram.
Abram, I know that you go childless.
See, you understand this evening
that God knows all things.
He's got perfect knowledge.
He's omniscient.
When Abram comes to God in v. 2
saying, I go childless,
that wasn't a surprise to God.
He knew that already.
But again, Abram is being transparent with the Lord.
He's concerned about this current situation.
He's received the promise.
He doesn't know how God's going to do
all that God said He was going to do.
And so he's offering the solution
and God says, no, Abram,
that's not the way it's going to work.
God says, he that shall come forth
out of thine own bowels
shall be thine heir.
I'm so thankful for the clarity of God's Word.
And that God spoke to Abram
in very clear language
as to what this promise would be.
Notice in v. 5, God then takes
and it says this,
and He brought him forth abroad
and said, look now toward heaven.
Now obviously, as we look at the context
of the passage of Scripture that is before us,
it was evening time.
It was dark.
And God says to Abram,
look toward heaven
and tell the stars.
In other words, it means to count the stars.
That's what that phraseology means.
And tell the stars.
Now I stepped out on the porch this evening
before the service to just look up
into the heavens.
And it's a little bit of an overcast
kind of an evening.
It's supposed to rain later this evening.
But last night, it was a pretty clear evening.
And Joseph and I were driving home
with Carter, my nephew,
and they noticed how bright the moon was.
It was just about a full moon last night.
And it was beautiful.
It was clear.
And I can't help but think,
see, for us this evening,
if it were a clear evening
as it was last night,
you can see a number of stars
in the heavens.
But if you've ever been to a place
where there's not as many people
and there's not as much light,
you can see, and pollution by the way,
another thing that kind of messes with
the number of stars you can see.
You go out and you see the stars
and it's like, man, I didn't know
there were this many stars.
Holly and I, almost 10 years ago,
we went to Arizona for our anniversary.
And I remember that evening,
I think it was the first evening we were there,
going on a walk.
And I was a little bit apprehensive.
Pierre, they told me there were rattlesnakes there.
And so you're walking at night
and I'm kind of, you know,
I'm looking down instead of up.
But you just got to a point
where you began to look up into the heavens.
And it's like, man, you don't see stars like this
around the big cities.
And God says, now think about when
this is being written several thousand years ago, right?
Abram is there and God says,
look toward heaven and tell the stars
if thou be able to number them.
Have you ever tried to count the stars?
There are people that have attempted to do such tasks.
The reality is that they're numberless.
The reality this evening is that
we're mindful of what God said to us in Genesis,
and I love it, in Genesis 1-16,
where the last five words of the verse of Scripture
says He made the stars also.
And in making these stars,
He made an innumerable host of stars
and He spread them through the heavens
and through the galaxies.
And we find here this evening
that Abram is taken by God
and He leads them out and He says,
Abram, I want you to look toward heaven.
And He says, Abram, tell the stars
if thou be able to number them.
And He said unto him,
God is speaking to Abram and He says unto him,
so shall thy seed be.
Wow.
I mean, when we really begin to look at
this promise being explained by God to Abram
and we understand this evening
that our God is omnipotent,
that our God is able to do all things,
and the reality tonight is that
because of having the whole canon of Scripture,
there's a whole lot that we know about God
that Abram has not yet learned about God
in this particular text of Scripture.
And we've learned names of God
that are revealed to Abram after this account.
El Shaddai, the Lord God Almighty.
God's not revealed Himself to Abram
at this point in that matter,
but we have the whole canon of Scripture
so we know that He shortly will do so.
And we find that as we look at this book
and we look at the promises contained therein,
that we stand in awe of who our God is
and we see how that God
who has made this promise to Abram,
that He explains it to him.
He says, Abram, I understand that you're coming
with your problem and I understand
that you've even brought a solution,
but this one that's born in your house,
no, he's not going to be thine heir
because one that comes from your own bowels,
he shall be thine heir.
He then gives him this wonderful example
and this teaching of the stars and the heavens,
and he says at the end of the verse,
so shall thy seed be.
Paul says this in 2 Corinthians 1
in verse 20,
with regard to the promises of God,
it says, for all the promises of God in him are yea,
and in him, amen,
unto the glory of God by us.
We find that Peter would make this statement
that we have been given exceeding great
and precious promises.
And we have.
One of the great hymns of the faith
that we sing,
standing on the promises.
And we sing that song,
and when we sing it,
I hope that our minds are thinking about
and aware of the promises that God has given us
and we find that God has explained
some of the promises in detail
such as He has to Abram in this passage of Scripture.
And we find that He's given us these promises.
We're familiar with various portions of Scripture
and how that God in His grace and His mercy
would work with His people
and He would begin to give them
and reveal to them the truth of who He is.
And He didn't always explain to them
how He would do what He would do,
but He simply promised to do it.
There are times in which the people of God
would hesitate and they would have
some level of doubt and unbelief
and God would come alongside them
and begin to prove Himself.
And I think this evening of Gideon,
and I love the account of Gideon in Judges 6-8
and how God would build the faith of Gideon
by revealing to him and showing him,
yes, you are going to be used of Me
to bring victory to My people.
It's a blessing.
And we have this precious book that sits before us
and we have the opportunity to read it
and to be encouraged by it.
And when we look at the promises of God's Word
and we consider this one tonight to Abram
and we find how God would explain the promise,
we ought to rejoice alongside Abram tonight.
I find myself thinking,
even as I'm turning here to the book of Numbers
and thinking about the scenario
in which Balaam was seeking to curse
the nation of Israel.
And of course, Balak's anger was kindled
against Balaam and all of that.
And you find that the Bible says this
in verse number 19 of chapter 23 of the book of Numbers,
God is not a man that he should lie,
neither the son of man that he should repent.
Hath he said, and shall he not do it?
Or hath he spoken, and shall he not make it good?
Can I tell you this evening,
and I know that we know this,
but God has never failed on one promise
that He's ever given.
He just never has.
And you understand this evening that He never will.
There's not one promise that God is not going to fulfill.
We can be encouraged this evening
as we understand again,
even as we read the Scriptures
and study the accounts of God's Word,
where we have the privilege many times
of knowing the end of the story, so to speak.
And we know in just a few chapters
that we're going to have the opportunity
to read about the birth of Isaac.
We understand that God is going to fulfill the promise
that He had given to Abram on this particular day, evening,
as God would recount these things to Abram.
We can read that and we understand that,
but Abram was just living life like we are,
day by day, moment by moment.
And so Abram had really, I would say it this way,
Abram had a decision to make.
Chapter 15 begins with a greeting that's a memorable greeting.
We then read of this discussion, if you will,
and Abram bringing his concern before the Lord,
the Lord responding to Abram,
and now it's up to Abram to respond.
It's up to Abram to do something with that which he's just heard.
You know, the reality is that just as Abram is here in this text of Scripture,
each of us every day when we go to the Word of God,
every day that we go to church and hear the preaching of the Word of God,
we have a decision to make.
What are we going to do with what we've received?
What will we do with the message that we heard at church?
What will we do with the message that we heard in our youth ministry,
in our Sunday school class, in our junior church class?
What do we do?
Listen, we're seeking to bring somebody to a place of decision.
What do we do with it?
Tomorrow morning when you read your Bible,
when you get up in the morning and you open up the Word of God
and you begin to read what thus saith the Lord,
you have a decision to make with regard to what you read.
And every day, we're faced with those decisions.
And Abram is in a similar position that we find ourselves in on a regular basis.
And I want you to notice that Abram's perspective is revealed,
God's promise is explained,
and if you're taking notes in verse number six, God's promise is embraced.
I'm so thankful for verse number six,
where the Bible says,
and he believed in the Lord.
He believed.
Remember, we've said, I mentioned it just a few moments ago,
that faith is taking God in His Word.
Faith is believing God.
Listen, I don't maybe understand all of how it's going to work,
I don't understand how it's all going to come together,
but I know that God has repeated and explained this promise
in very clear and precise terms,
and therefore I have to respond in my response.
Abram's response is, I believe God.
I just believe.
It says this, that he believed in the Lord.
He believed in the Lord.
I wonder this evening,
how many times we can go to the Word of God,
and read of those that did not believe what God told them.
Oh, there are many examples.
Perhaps this evening we can go to positive examples of others that did believe.
They just believed that God would work,
that God would show Himself mighty,
that God would do what He only could do.
I know that I often make the reference to the passage in Acts 27.
It's been so impactful in my own life,
and I've been so challenged through the declaration of the Apostle Paul
when they're in the midst of the terrible storm on the sea,
and all hope that they would be saved is gone,
and they've not seen the stars,
and I mean, they just were wishing for the day,
and there's just no hope.
God sent an angel to speak,
and the Lord gave Paul truth with regard to their deliverance,
and Paul simply declares to those other individuals that are on that boat,
I believe God,
that it shall be as it's been told to me.
And we just come to that place in our lives as Abram does,
where he embraces the promise,
and I believe this evening that this first half of verse number 6
is a powerful statement of Scripture.
I believe that this first statement of Genesis 15 and verse number 6
not only is a powerful statement of Scripture,
but it's a powerful testimony of Abram.
That Abram believed God.
He hears what God says.
Remember, it begins with this perspective of I go childless,
I mean, I don't have any seed, I don't have a son.
God, what are you going to do? How are you going to do this?
This one that's been born in my house, and he says,
here's what I'm going to do.
Here's my promise.
And Abram believes in the Lord.
He takes God in his word.
And it says this,
and he counted it to him for righteousness.
Wow, what a powerful truth of the Word of God.
And as we look at this statement at the end of Genesis 15 and verse number 6,
our minds will race to the New Testament
in which this particular truth is referenced on at least two occasions.
And I want you to think about what God is saying here.
We see the faith of Abram where he believed in the Lord,
but then we see the response of that,
the way in which God would respond.
And it says that he counted it to him for righteousness.
Go over to the book of Romans if you will.
In Romans chapter number 4,
look at the first three verses of Romans chapter number 4.
The Bible says this in verse number 1 of Romans 4,
What shall we say then that Abraham our father,
as pertaining to the flesh, hath found?
For if Abraham were justified by works,
he hath whereof to glory, but not before God.
Now, it's interesting when you read verse number 2 there
and you consider it with the truth that God gives us in Ephesians 2,
verses 8 and 9, in verse number 9 in particular,
where the Bible says, lest any man should boast.
Because the Bible says in Ephesians 2, 8 and 9,
For by grace are you saved through faith,
and that not of yourselves, it is the gift of God,
not of works, lest any man should boast.
What is he saying by that?
Well, if I could work my way to heaven,
I have whereof to glory, to boast.
And so in verse number 2 of Romans 4,
here's what Paul is saying to these believers.
He says, if Abraham were justified by works,
he hath whereof to glory, but not before God.
What is he meaning?
Well, he did enough good things to get to heaven.
But you understand you can't do enough good things
to get to heaven.
Because the Bible says that the gift of God
is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord,
not by works of righteousness,
which we have done in Titus 3 and verse number 5.
We just looked at Ephesians 2, 8 and 9.
The Bible is abundantly clear
that salvation is by grace through faith alone.
Paul says later in the book of Galatians,
I do not frustrate the grace of God.
If righteousness came by the law,
then Christ is dead in vain.
Listen, His death was not vain.
His death was absolutely essential and required
to pay for your sin and my sin and the sin of the world.
Why?
Because your works can't do it.
And the law, keeping of the law can't do it.
He says in verse number three,
for what saith the Scripture,
by the way, it's always good to go to the Scripture.
Amen.
You understand some of the things
that were going on in the first century.
Jesus dealt with it often with the Pharisees
and the Sadducees and the scribes
and those religious leaders.
What about the tradition?
What do men say?
What do you do?
And how is this?
No, what does the Scripture say?
You do err not knowing the Scripture.
And we find that the appeal is given
to these believers in the book of Romans.
And Paul says this,
for what saith the Scripture?
Notice where it says,
Abraham believed God
and it was counted unto him for righteousness.
That's exactly the passage
that we've been looking at this evening
in Genesis 15 verses two through six,
in particular, zeroing in on verse number six.
Abraham believed in the Lord
and he counted it unto him for righteousness.
And we see here that Paul knew the Old Testament.
He goes back to the Old Testament.
He references the Old Testament.
He says, now to him that worketh
is the reward not reckoned of grace, but of debt.
In other words, if you could work
to get your way to heaven,
you're earning something.
But no, it's of grace.
Verse five, but to him that worketh not,
but believeth on him that justifieth the ungodly,
his faith is counted for righteousness.
We could really look at the entirety
of Romans chapter number four.
We don't have time this evening to do that.
We could continue to go through
and just see how Paul is using with great wisdom
the truth of the Old Testament
to prove these truths with regard to salvation
and righteousness being by faith, not by works.
Go over to the book of Galatians, if you will,
in chapter number three.
Notice another reference to this same portion
of Scripture that we're looking at
in Genesis 15 this evening.
We'd find it in Galatians chapter number three.
Look with me, if you will, in verse number six.
Galatians three and verse number six.
Even as Abraham, what's it say?
Believed God, and it was accounted
to him for righteousness.
Oftentimes, we speak about the.
righteousness of our God and I'm so thankful for he hath made him to be sin
for us who knew no sin that we might be made the righteousness of God in him."
2nd Corinthians in chapter number 5 and we find here that the Bible's
speaking about this event in Genesis 15 in verse number 6 as Abraham
believed God and it was accounted to him for righteousness. Notice that as we
continue to kind of pick our way through the third chapter of the book of
Galatians that the Bible says this in verse number 8 let's read verse 7 with
it, "...know you therefore that they which are of faith the same are the children
of Abraham." So we get a look at the entirety of this promise that is made in
Genesis chapter number 15 we find the fulfillment with the land and we've
talked about that in previous messages but now we think about the seed and
we'll find that as we study the New Testament that yes there's the truth of
Isaac being born the promised son and what a blessing and all that would be
entailed in that but the fullness of the the blessing and the fullness of the
promise is the fact that we are children of that we that have trust at Christ we
by faith are looked at as being the children of Abraham and it says in verse
number 8, "...and the scripture foreseeing that God would justify the heathen through
faith preached before the gospel unto Abraham saying in thee shall all nations
be blessed." You understand that heathen there really is dealing with Gentiles so
then they which be of faith are blessed with faithful Abraham look down if you
will for sake of time to verse number 16 now to Abraham and his seed were the
promise made were the promises made notice what it says here in verse number
16 and he saith not and to seeds plural as of many but as of one and to thy seed
notice these last three verses which is Christ see the messianic line we talk
about that often and we look at the book of Genesis and we've just developed the
truth that God is giving us all the way in Genesis chapter number three about
the fact that Messiah would come and the truth of the the the messianic line and
how that the enemy Satan and you can study not only the book of Genesis but
throughout the Old Testament how that the enemy sought to destroy the line so
that Messiah would not be able to come but our God is greater and here we find
that as God is giving this instruction to Abraham and he's giving this promise
to Abraham he say in thy seed and we understand the New Testament that thy
seed which is Christ now we understand that it would be thousands of years
later before that would come to its fullness in the promise but the
immediate fulfillment would be in the birth of Isaac and from there you go
through the line and the of Messiah and eventually you can read of course in the
New Testament you can read about the genealogies and all of those things and
what a tremendous blessing it is to understand that we find that the Bible
says that he believed in the Lord and he counted it to him for righteousness
I'm so thankful that God's promise was embraced by Abram we understand the
account of Abram in fact we'll finish up chapter 15 and then get into chapter 16
and we notice there's some really some sad events that are recorded for us in
Genesis chapter number 16 and we'll look through those things and we'll see all
that's taking place but we rejoice this evening and what the Bible tells us
about him Abram responding to what God had given him and explained to him so my
question this evening as we look at the fullness of this and we really see not
only the immediate but of course as we see where it says so shall thy seed be
and how he told him in that if thou can tell the stars that they'll be able to
number them and he said unto him so shall thy seed be and we see the of
course the many descendants of Abram Abraham but then we think about the
truth of the the New Testament there in the book of Galatians with believers
being of the seed of Abraham I mean that number just grows exponentially at that
point we begin to see how that God has fulfilled that which he has promised to
do listen Christ came just as it had been prophesied this evening we see a
specific event in the life of Abram we see a specific promise we see a specific
situation I wonder tonight maybe there's been some promise that God has given you
in his word that maybe you've struggled with maybe there's been a measure of
doubt maybe there's been a measure of uncertainty maybe there's been some
unbelief if you will where you've read the promise you've you've seen what God
says in his word but there's just some difficulty with you being able to see
how it's going to come to fruition and you've struggled and you've dealt with
some difficulties and I would submit to you this evening if you're in that
position and you know that there's some promises that God has given in his word
and you're just struggling with it we're all human beings we understand that the
children of Israel when Moses sent those spies they came back and they didn't
believe God amen those ten spies they brought back an evil report and they
persuaded the entire congregation of the nation of Israel to doubt what God said
that God would do and we find that God would speak to a bro to Moses excuse me
and he would say how long will it be error my people believe me you
understand this evening that God wants us to believe him and he says this in
that same conversation with Moses he says for all the signs which I have
showed among them one of this evening when we look at this book and we study
it we read it and we see all the promises and the fulfillments and the
way our God works and what he does oh man we ought to embrace the promises I
mean more eagerly and readily even than those that we read of in the scriptures
why because we have so much more we have the whole of the scripture in this
evening I don't know the specific situation I don't know the specific
promise but maybe there's a promise that that we know in our heart the Holy
Spirit can can just kind of put his finger so to speak on that thing in our
own life and so you know you're not you're not believing me in this
situation your faith is not what it needs to be your there's a measure of
doubt and will you just believe God will you just take God at his word will you
just prove him and allow God to be exalted and allowed God to be magnified
see that's really the beauty of seeing God fulfill promises is that he gets the
glory it's not for us to take any level of credit for or recognition of those
things that happen but no we just see God working and we see God exalted in
God magnified and we just come to the place where we say I believe God I just
believe God I refuse to believe what the what the crowd wants to tell us I
refuse to believe what the the media wants to tell whoever I just refuse why
because I just want to believe God I just want to believe God and when you
come to that place in your life where you just believe God sometimes people
gonna look at you like you're crazy because why because you have faith in
what God has said and when you have that faith and what God has said and in
God is pleased with your faith with your belief we find that God will work in
amazing ways this evening there's a very specific conversation that takes place
between Abram and God I'm thankful that Abram was transparent maybe somebody
just need to be transparent with God tonight God I know you said this but I'm
struggling because of I go childless right that's what Abram said there's I
don't have a son and whatever the promises in your life you say I just
don't know I don't see it and we're transparent with God and we pour our
heart out before the Lord and we let God minister to us and we let him take his
word and perhaps lead us to some other portions and passages of Scripture that
would just minister to us and help us to just grow our faith we'd leave saying
God I believe you I just believe you I don't have to know how see sometimes I'm
guilty of wanting to know how I don't know if you are but a lot of times in my
life I'm guilty of wanting to know how how's it gonna happen how's it gonna
come together Holly can tell you that in the kitchen she's mixing things together
putting a meal together and I'm like man I don't know if I'm gonna eat that
but it comes together and it's great our God is amazing at bringing all these
things together and working them all together and saying I'm just gonna prove
myself I'm gonna show you my child what I'm able to do and all we need to do is
just believe them just believe them let's pray father we love you this
evening we thank you so much for loving us thank
We thank You for this account in Genesis 15
of this discussion between Abram and Yourself.
We thank You that
You explained Your promise in detail.
We thank You for Your clarity.
Lord, how we rejoice in the response of Abram.
Lord, I just pray tonight
that You'd help us.
I understand the account that is before us
is a specific situation for Abram.
But God, Your Word is full of promises for us
as Your children.
And if we'd be honest tonight,
there are times in which we stagger at Your promises,
that we struggle,
that we have doubt,
that we fail to exercise faith in what You've said,
perhaps even explaining or justifying.
But God, I pray tonight
that as only You can,
You would minister to each of us.
Challenge us.
Comfort us.
Help us, God, to simply believe You,
trust You,
and obey You.
I pray that in these next few moments
that the Holy Spirit of God would have His will in way,
that decisions would be made that would please Thee,
that would cause us to be conformed to the image of Christ
and impact eternity.
We'll be careful to give You the glory for all that You'll do.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.