at verses 7 through 11 of this passage of Scripture and dealt with my fellow
workers. And we talked about the recognition of those fellow workers.
Paul references them, he talks about them. We spoke about not only the recognition
but then the role. What was the responsibility? What was it that these
fellow workers were doing? And then we spoke of the reward for the fellow
workers. And what a blessing to know that our God has given us, not only it's
through His grace and His Spirit that we serve Him, but then He's given us the
truth that He will reward us for our faithful service. And what a blessing to
understand that truth. This morning we're gonna look at verses 12 and 13 and we're
gonna look specifically at Epaphras. Notice in verse 12 the Bible says,
Epaphras, who is one of you, a servant of Christ, saluteth you, always laboring
fervently for you in prayers that ye may stand perfect and complete in all the
will of God. For I bear him record that he hath a great zeal for you and them
that are in Laodicea and them in Heropolis. As we look at these verses of
Scripture, we're reminded that we first meet Epaphras or learn of Epaphras in
the first chapter of the book of Colossians. We understand also that he's
mentioned in the book of Philemon and these are the three references of this
particular character that we find throughout the Word of God. Once in
Colossians 1, here in Colossians 4, and then briefly mentioned in the book of
Philemon. You may remember that it was through Epaphras that the Apostle Paul
learned about these group of believers or this group of believers in Colossae.
Remember in the first chapter that Paul, we mentioned this as we began studying
the book of Colossians, that Paul did not personally know the believers in
Colossae. Paul was not on a missionary journey and went to the city of Colossae
and planted a church. It didn't work that way. Now we understand with some of the
books that we read and some of the churches, you think about the church in
Ephesus, you think about the church in Philippi, these are places where Paul
went specifically on missionary journeys and knew the people personally that he's
writing to. We can think about the churches in the region of Galatias. The
book of Galatians is written to those churches in those four cities and during
the first missionary journey, the Apostle Paul visited those particular
locations and souls were saved and churches were established and what a joy.
But here in the book of Colossians, we understand that Paul never was in the
city of Colossae. He heard about these believers, this group, this church in
Colossae through Epaphras. We're not sure, it's not a hundred percent clear
whether Epaphras simply visited the Apostle Paul while he was in Roman
prison or if Epaphras was imprisoned as well. But we understand that this book of
Colossians is one of those books that we refer to as being a prison epistle and
the Apostle Paul is in prison writing to this church and he mentions in the first
chapter how that from the first day that he heard about their faith that he was
rejoicing with them and he was praying for them and he gives them distinctly in
the first chapter how he was praying for them and his desire for them and all of
those things that he knew about this body of believers including the conflict
that they were dealing with because of the entry of false teachers was a result
of the ministry of Epaphras bringing that word to the Apostle Paul. I believe
that as we look at these two verses of Scripture here in the fourth chapter as
we near the end of our study of the book of Colossians we would find that from
these two verses of Scripture it seems quite evident that Paul spent some time
with Epaphras and I believe that as we look at these verses of Scripture that
we are given insight to the character of this man. We find that it was that it
seems as we look at these verses of Scripture that Epaphras was a genuine
sincere follower of the Lord Jesus Christ. I am sure this morning that
Epaphras was an encouragement to the Apostle Paul. And you think about the
ways in which God allows believers brethren to encourage one another and no
doubt that while Paul was imprisoned in Rome because of his faith we find that
God allowed for he and Epaphras to cross paths and what an encouragement it must
have been. As we look at these verses of Scripture it seems as if as I mentioned
a moment ago that there's some time that they spent one with another for we find
that some of the statements that are made are not made simply after a brief
30-minute kind of interaction. We find that there was definitely some length of
time there and you'll notice in verse number 13 that it says that he speaking
of Epaphras hath a great zeal for you as you've noticed on the back of the
bulletin this morning on a preacher message that I've simply entitled the
zeal of Epaphras. The zeal of Epaphras. To have zeal is to have passion. We find
that this man was a man of passion. As we begin to look at this man and look at
what Paul says of Epaphras if you're taking notes this morning I want you to
first note the devotion of Epaphras. Note his devotion. I believe that the
devotion of Epaphras is revealed to us through the way in which he is described.
Notice the Bible tells us that he is one of you. In other words that Epaphras had
been in Colossae. He had ministered there and we find that he is one of you but
notice this phrase, a servant of Christ. What a great way to be known. In fact
oftentimes as you read books of the Bible and especially in the New
Testament epistles you'll find that the particular human penman of those
particular books will begin by saying a servant of Jesus Christ. Paul, a servant
of Jesus Christ. James, a servant of Jesus Christ. Peter, a servant. You think about
the title of being a servant of the Lord Jesus Christ. We mentioned last week as
we noted some reasons to rejoice and we spoke about being thankful for his
person that he is King of Kings and Lord of Lords and to consider this morning
that we have the ability, the opportunity, the privilege to be his
servant. Wow. Many times the term servant is a term that is used in a negative
context. It's looked down upon but to consider this morning that we are
servants of the King of Kings and Lord of Lords, to consider the privilege that
is ours to be his servant, it is a great truth of the Word of God and we find
that the Bible says that he, Epaphras, is a servant of Christ. I find also the
Bible tells us here in verse number 12 that he's a man of prayer. A man of
prayer. Notice what the Bible says. He says that he saluteth you, he sends his
greetings, but notice this phrase, always laboring fervently for you in prayers.
The Word of God reveals much to us on the subject of prayer. We find that Jesus
often is praying. We find that of all the things that the disciples could have
asked the Lord to teach them, they make this request, Lord, teach us to pray. We
find that the Lord Jesus Christ was a man of prayer. He prayed. He gave us that
example that we should follow his steps. We find that the Word of God contains a
number of promises with regard to prayer. In fact, as you read and study the Word
of God, you can read and study the prayers of God's people and you can see
the way in which they pour out their heart to God and the way in which the
hand of God is moved through the prayers of his people. God has chosen that
prayer is the vehicle by which his hand is moved. Isn't that awesome? And when you
begin to think about the privilege again of prayer, we mentioned about the
privilege of being a servant of Jesus Christ, but you know that it is a unique
privilege that is reserved for the child of God to pray to the God of heaven. What
a privilege. That at any time, for any reason, we can go to God in prayer and we
can stay there as long as we want. Aren't you thankful for that? He never says your
time is up. He never says, wait, I'm busy. No, no. At any time, at any moment, for any
reason, for as long as we want, we can come boldly to the throne of grace. Why?
Because he's given us access through his death, burial, and resurrection. We have
direct access to the throne room of heaven and we can bring our petitions
before the face of God who is able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we
ask or think. He said to Jeremiah, call unto me and I will answer thee and show
thee great and mighty things which thou knowest not. You read over in the book of
Lamentations and you read how the Bible tells us that Jeremiah cried out to God
and how God answered. It's a direct just example of the the fulfillment of that
promise of Jeremiah 33 in verse number 3. Prayer. He, Epaphras, as we know his
devotion, we say first he's a servant of Christ.
We say, second, he's a man of prayer.
Notice the Bible says with regard to his prayer
that he's always laboring fervently for you in prayers.
We're mindful of the truth of James 5
in verse 16 when the example of the prayer of Elijah
is mentioned here in this passage of Scripture.
And the Bible says,
confess your faults one to another
and pray one for another
that ye may be healed,
the effectual fervent prayer of a righteous man
availeth much.
And then the Bible uses that example of Elijah.
It says he was a man of subject to like passions as we are.
And he prayed earnestly that it might not rain.
And what happened?
It rained not on the earth
by the space of three years and six months.
And he prayed again and the heaven gave rain.
And the earth brought forth her fruit.
You know, there was another prayer of Elijah
in between the prayer of no rain
and the prayer of rain.
You know what that prayer was?
It was a prayer for fire.
Amen?
And what happened when he prayed that fire?
He said, Lord, I've spoken all these things
according to Thy Word.
Remember the servants of Baal,
they're running around and they're crying out
and they're cutting themselves
and they're doing all that they can do
to appease their false God
and nothing, nothing happens.
Elijah, he says, let's fix this altar up.
Bring some water.
Bring some more water.
He prays.
And fire fell from heaven.
Listen, this man, Epaphras,
we speak of his devotion this morning.
And I believe that his devotion is revealed to us
through the way in which he's described.
And first, he's described as being a servant
of Jesus Christ.
Second, he's described as being a man of prayer.
I find not here in these verses of Scripture,
but back in chapter number one,
that he's described as being a faithful minister.
Look back at Colossians 1 in verse number seven.
The Bible says this,
as he also learned of Epaphras,
our dear fellow servant,
who is for you,
notice what it says,
a faithful minister of Christ.
What a great way to be described
as being a faithful minister.
The book of 1 Corinthians says that moreover,
it's required in stewards that a man be found faithful.
And we mentioned as we studied in verses seven through 11
a couple of Sundays ago,
dealing with these fellow workers
and how the faithfulness of these men was revealed to us.
And we find that Epaphras,
as we consider this morning his devotion,
we find that he was a servant,
he was a man of prayer,
but he was a faithful minister.
What a way to be described.
Servant, man of prayer, faithful minister.
I want you to think about his devotion.
We see that his devotion is revealed
through the ways in which he's described.
But I would say this of his devotion, number one,
I would say that his devotion was sincere.
His devotion was sincere.
I believe that this man Epaphras,
as I mentioned by way of introduction,
had a genuine walk with God.
There was no pretense,
there was no facade,
there was no trying to put on an act or a show
for someone to pretend to be something you were not.
No, I believe that as we look at this man Epaphras
and I think about his devotion to God
and I think about his walk with God,
it was sincere.
It was genuine.
He was a man that had been born again.
He's a man, we don't know how he heard the Gospel,
we don't know when he heard the Gospel,
but he was a man that heard the Gospel of Jesus Christ
and trusted Christ as his Savior.
He was a man that was used by God.
He was a man that was a servant,
that was a man of prayer, that was faithful.
And I would say that his devotion was sincere.
So often, in the day and age in which we live,
we find that there's so often people of pretense
and people with facade,
but oh, that we just be genuine, sincere followers of Jesus Christ.
That devotion of Epaphras, I believe,
can be described as being sincere.
I would say this of his devotion,
not only was his devotion sincere,
but his devotion was obvious.
This is not Epaphras speaking of himself.
This is not Epaphras saying,
hey, I'm a minister of Christ, a servant of Christ.
I am a man of prayer.
I am a faithful minister.
No, this is the Apostle Paul,
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
saying of Epaphras that he is a servant of Christ,
that he is a man of prayer,
that he is a faithful minister.
His devotion to God was obvious.
It was something that Paul was able to observe.
Oh, that people would see that our walk with God
is not only sincere, but that it's obvious.
That people would say,
as we studied a few weeks ago on Sunday evening,
remember just a few weeks ago in Genesis 21,
the Bible spoke of the way in which Abimelech
came to Abraham and said,
God is with thee in all that thou doest.
When we look at the life of Joseph,
remember they saw that God was with him.
When you begin to look at Bible characters
and you see that God is with them,
there's something obvious about their walk with God.
And this morning, when I think of the zeal of Epaphras,
when I first note his devotion
and understanding that his devotion is revealed
through the way in which he's described,
but I would say of his devotion
that it's sincere and that it's obvious.
I would say this, number three of his devotion,
his devotion is exemplary.
His devotion is exemplary.
What do we mean by that?
I believe this morning that as we read
just a couple of verses of Scripture
in Colossians 4, verses 12 and 13,
as we wrap up our text
in the study of the book of Colossians,
I mean, nearing the very end,
I think that this morning,
as we consider the devotion of this man,
that it should challenge us.
That each and every one of us,
as we look at the devotion of Epaphras,
and we'd say that it's exemplary,
that it should be a challenge
in my own personal walk with God.
How's my devotion to God?
How's my walk with God?
I'm not asking you to tell anyone out loud
or to respond publicly how your walk with God is,
but I'm simply suggesting this morning
that when we look at a man
that is described in the manner
in which he is described,
that it ought to challenge us.
And I wonder this morning,
as we consider the fact that this
is not just Paul writing,
because this is Scripture.
This is God's Word.
Therefore, it's God's saying of Epaphras.
Yes, Paul is the human penman.
Paul is the one that observed these things.
Paul is the one that says he sends your greetings,
but you understand that this is the Word of God.
You can deceive me.
You can deceive somebody else
to think that we can have this idea
that your walk with God is something
other than what it really is.
The church in Laodicea is mentioned here
in this text of Scripture.
It's mentioned in chapter two as well.
Remember, Paul had a great conflict
for those that were in Colossae,
but also for those that were in Laodicea.
And also, it says,
as many as have not seen my face in the flesh,
Hierapolis is mentioned here in verse 13.
No doubt that was on the mind of Paul.
But we understand as the reference
to the church of the Laodiceans
as it's described in the book of Revelation,
that they had an opinion of themselves.
Did they not?
Was their opinion reality?
Huh.
Not in God's eyes.
Right?
Church of the Laodiceans, ye say,
that you're increased with goods
and have need of nothing,
but you don't know that you're poor,
miserable, and naked.
Wow.
This morning as we think about
the devotion of Epaphras,
as we understand that this man
is described to us as being a servant of Jesus Christ,
that this man is described to us
as being a man of prayer,
of being a faithful minister.
His devotion was, we find, sincere,
and it was obvious,
but his devotion is exemplary.
It should challenge each and every one of us.
If God were to write about your devotion,
what would He say?
Not if you were to write about your devotion.
Not if I were to write about your devotion.
Not if your spouse or your children
were to write about your devotion.
But what would God say
if He were to write about my devotion?
About your devotion?
And here, the devotion of this man of Epaphras
is exemplary.
Oh, that it would be said of us
that we are servants of Jesus Christ.
Just a servant.
I'll do what you want me to do, dear Lord.
I'll go where you want me to go.
I'll say what you want me to say.
Why?
Because my life, Lord, is yours to control.
I'm just your servant.
Oh, that it be said of us that.
that were people of prayer.
I don't know a lot about that person,
but what I know is they can pray.
And they believe in prayer.
If there's somebody that I want to pray for me
as I go through a difficulty,
a trial, a problem in life,
if there's someone that I want to pray,
I have people that I say,
these are people that I know that pray.
Amen?
Faithful.
Faithfulness is so important in God's economy.
It really is.
We understand what it is to have
a level of importance placed upon faithfulness.
Do we not?
If you're an employer,
you want your employees to be faithful.
They show up to work.
Right?
I mean, it's kind of a requirement.
You don't just come and go when you please
and how you want.
There's an expectation.
In employment, there's an expectation
in a marriage.
Faithfulness.
Correct?
You to be faithful to your spouse
and your spouse to be faithful to you.
Amen?
In God's economy,
faithfulness is near the top.
He says it's required
from stewards that a man be found faithful.
We are the stewards of the grace of God.
And oh, that we be good stewards
of the manifold grace of God.
The devotion of Epaphras.
Moving along,
not only do I note his devotion,
but I note the desire of Epaphras.
This man, Epaphras,
had a teaching ministry in Colossae.
We mentioned Colossae 1 in v. 7
a few minutes ago
as he was described there
as being a faithful minister of Christ.
But we find also that in v. 7 of Colossae 1
that it says,
as he also learned of Epaphras,
our dear fellow servant.
And so we understand
whether he was the pastor
or he just had some teaching ministry
there in Colossae,
we do not know for certainty.
But we do understand
that he had some level of ministry
there in Colossae
as he was teaching these believers.
And I note that his desire
is revealed to us in v. 12.
That desire is a desire
that is coupled with great zeal.
Passion.
We find that that desire
is revealed through the way
in which he prays.
It says that he saluteth you
always laboring fervently for you in prayers.
And notice the desire.
Notice the means by which
this man Epaphras is seeking the face of God
on the behalf of these believers
that you may stand perfect
and complete in all the will of God.
Wow, what a desire.
I note that this desire
for the believers in Colossae
was spiritual in nature.
You'll note that this desire,
the way in which Epaphras is praying
for these believers in Colossae
is not physical.
It's not temporal.
It's spiritual.
So often, we are on the wrong plane.
We're on the temporal plane.
We're praying about things temporally.
We're praying about things physically.
And we fail to enter the spiritual plane.
We fail to pray for our brothers
and sisters in Christ in a spiritual manner.
An understanding that as Paul
was writing to the believers
and speaking as to how he was praying for them,
turn back quickly to Colossians 1
and begin in v. 9 how Paul reveals to us
how he was praying for these believers in Colossae.
He says, for this cause we also
since the day we heard it
do not cease to pray for you
and to desire, notice this,
that you might be filled with the knowledge
of His will and all wisdom
and spiritual understanding.
Well, that's a good prayer request, is it not?
That's a good way to be praying
for your brothers and sisters in Christ.
That your, notice where he says
that you might be filled with the knowledge
of His will and all wisdom
and spiritual understanding.
He continues that you might walk
worthy of the Lord unto all pleasing.
Well, that's a good way to pray as well.
Being fruitful in every good work.
Increasing in the knowledge of God.
If you read the book of Philippians,
there are two occasions,
excuse me, the book of Ephesians.
If you read the book of Ephesians,
there are two occasions in the book of Ephesians
where Paul's prayer for the believers
in Ephesus is recorded for us.
And you know how Paul prays
for the believers in Ephesus?
The same way he does for the believers in Colossae.
He prays for them spiritually.
He's concerned about their walk with God.
He's concerned about their spiritual well-being.
I'm not suggesting that he cares nothing
about their current circumstances
or their health or some physical issues,
but primarily he's concerned about that spiritual.
And we find the same thing
as we look at Epaphras here in the fourth chapter
and we note the desire of this individual
and we find that he's always laboring fervently,
praying and seeking the face of God
and the way in which he's praying
for these believers in Colossae
is that they would stand perfect
and complete in all the will of God.
Wow.
I mentioned already some of Colossians 1,
but I want to draw your attention
to verse number 28 of the first chapter
of the book of Colossians
and I want you to see what the Bible tells us
about the ministry of Paul as he describes it here
in this passage of Scripture.
In Colossians 1 and verse 28,
Paul says,
whom we preach,
warning every man and teaching every man in all wisdom
that we may present every man perfect in Christ Jesus.
Begin to think about the spiritual nature
of the desire of Epaphras,
the consistent desire of Epaphras
to that of Paul's desire for the believers in Colossae.
And as we think about this desire
and we see how that this desire is zeroed in
through the way in which he's praying.
I say this morning that if we are to be people of prayer,
if we evaluate our prayer lives,
how are we praying for our brothers and sisters in Christ?
Are we praying for our brothers and sisters in Christ
in this spiritual manner?
That our brothers and sisters in Christ
would stand perfect and complete in all the will of God.
would know the mind of Christ,
that they would know the will of God,
that they would do the will of God,
that they would be followers of Jesus Christ.
So often, we as believers,
and I would say I as a pastor receive criticism for,
well, you just want people to come to church
so you can feel good about it.
So much greater than that.
It's so much greater than that.
I don't go and knock on someone's door.
I don't give someone a gospel tract.
I don't invite them to church.
I don't pray for our church family
that they'd be in church and that they'd read their Bibles
and they would seek the face of God through prayer.
I don't pray that way so that I can gain something benefit.
It's because I'm concerned about the spiritual wellbeing
of others.
Why do we take the gospel to a lost and dying world?
Because the Bible tells us that the dead,
small and great will stand before the great white throne
and whosoever is not written in the book of life
will be cast into the lake of fire.
So why do we have a desire to preach the gospel?
Because souls are dying and they need the truth.
Amen?
And by the way, my responsibility and your responsibility
is to be the mouthpiece, to be the one that gives the truth.
I can't make anyone get saved.
And God doesn't hold me accountable
for making them get saved.
He just holds me accountable for giving the truth.
You understand that if you read your Bible this week
or if you don't read your Bible this week,
it doesn't affect my spiritual walk with God.
It doesn't.
But I pray that you read your Bible.
I encourage you to read your Bible.
We preach about the importance of reading your Bible.
Why?
Because the entrance of thy word giveth light.
Because the word of God is quick and powerful
and sharper than the two-edged sword.
Because the word of God is the word of God.
It's given by inspiration of God and it is profitable.
And therefore, it is good for you
just like it's good for me.
And I pray that you pray.
Why?
Because you need to walk with God
and you need to seek the face of God.
I pray that you would know the will of God.
To know the mind of Christ and to know the will of God
is to know this book.
Amen?
I pray that God would keep you from the evil one.
That God would help you to put on the whole armor of God
that you would be able to stand in the evil one.
day and oh how we're living in an evil day amen and we need to pray one for
another when's the last time we've prayed for someone on this plane
spiritually that he's gonna go and he's gonna go and you're gonna go into a
world that you're gonna be bombarded by the devil by the enemy and we need the
armor of God but we pray on a physical plane someone's got a cold I'm not
trying to minimize a cold please understand what I'm saying we need to
get on the spiritual because it's a spiritual battle you know how Ephesians
turn over to Ephesians 6 because I want you to see how Paul ends under the
inspiration of Holy Spirit of God the passage dealing with the whole armor of
God we're to put on the whole armor of God but he says in verse number 18
praying always with all prayer and supplication in the Spirit and watching
thereunto with all perseverance and supplications what are the next three
words for all Saints can you pray for yourself with regard to the spiritual
battle yes and you should amen but you know what the admonition is who to pray
for all the Saints why because they're facing spiritual warfare and we get on
that plane of praying spiritually one for another and Paul says let me tell
you about a path for us he's one of you he's a servant of Jesus Christ he
saluted you he sends his greetings but he's praying always for you fervently
what that you may stand perfect and complete in all the will of God Wow if
someone tells me they're praying for me that way that encourages me amen because
if I know that our people are praying for me that I would stand complete in
all the will of God as I understand as Paul prayed in Colossians 1 that they
would be filled with the knowledge of God then when I enter into my time with
God and I'm seeking his face and I'm reading his word and God is teaching me
that's not only answering my prayers but that's answering your prayers because
you prayed that God would give me truth amen it's good for me to pray as I begin
my Bible reading as I did this morning Lord open how mine eyes that I may
behold wondrous things out of thy word speak Lord for thy servant heareth God
help me to understand your word and to do your word I pray that for myself but
we ought to be praying that for each other and then God works and somebody
says can I tell you I love it when this happens brother summer if you probably
have this happen the ministry too can I tell you I was reading my Bible and God
showed me something where do you get stuck I get stuck on I was in my Bible
it encourages me seriously you know you can read your Bible through in about 60
hours it's kind of a just you can just do the math and figure it out you can
get CDs and you can hear them it's about 60 hours statistics tell us I've never
been asked so I'll put that disclaimer you may not have been asked either but
statistics tell us that like less than half of the people that regularly go to
church have read the Bible through cover-to-cover this book is the mind of
God and as we pray one front of their spiritually that we would have that we
would stand complete perfect and complete and all the will of God and we
have this this desire that a path for us has and we say God give me that desire
for my fellow brethren for my brothers and sisters in Christ that I would
desire that they would grow spiritually that they would mature spiritually and
help me to not only desire that but help me to pray that way for them amen as I
look at a path for us I see a man who just humbly followed God I see a man
that's mentioned just three times Colossians 1 Colossians 4 and Philemon
his life was about Christ he had a a close walk with God it's revealed to us
through the ways in which he's described his devotion to God was
sincere was obvious it's exemplary but he had a desire his desire was not even
just for himself it was for his brethren and his desire was that they would they
would be perfect and complete and all the will of God we've had as our theme
all year complete in Christ from Colossians 2 in verse 10 that we'd
understand we are complete in him but that we would continue to grow not only
knowing the will of God but doing the will of God and this morning as we look
at these two verses of Scripture I really hope that first we'd be
encouraged by such a soldier of the cross amen his life encourages me his
life challenges me but but first I want to think about that encouragement oh we
should be encouraged by a man like a path for us I think he encouraged Paul I
believe that I believe that when Paul was there in Roman prison and a path
first came and brought him the news and as Paul observed his walk with God I
think Paul was encouraged and we too should be encouraged by a follower of
Jesus Christ man that desires God hungering and thirsting after
righteousness as the psalmist said in Psalm 42 is the heart panteth after the
water brooks so panteth my heart after thee Oh God someone made this statement
to me I was having a meeting actually last week and someone made this
statement to me and it was it was impactful it actually caused me to stop
right in our conversation and kind of rewind and let's talk about that the
statement that was made was this we ought to be jealous about our walk with
God and I thought man that's a good thought to be jealous about my walk with
God to have such desire and such passion to follow the Lord Jesus Christ that I'm
jealous I don't want anything to interfere with that and to understand
that that my walk with God is my walk with God and your walk with God is your
walk with God and to have that perspective with regard to our walk and
we see in a path first I don't think he was trying to impress Paul you know I
don't think that because I'm not God wouldn't put it in the word like he did
because you know what God knows the heart he knows the motive amen so if a
path first was just I'm gonna impress the Apostle Paul and I'm gonna show him
I know how to pray and this that and the other thing Oh God of our fathers
Abraham and Isaac no no no God would have included it in the word his walk
was sincere passionate we're encouraged by that but this morning I hope that
we'd be challenged by it and that we'd evaluate our own lives and say if just a
couple of verses I didn't count the number of words but if just that many
words were written about me from God what would he have to say about my life
we mentioned in Sunday school last week we mentioned again this morning how that
Jesus marveled at the faith of the centurion in Matthew 8 he says to those
that were there the disciples I've not found so great faith no not in all of
Israel there are other times in the life and ministry of Jesus Christ that he
marveled at their unbelief I would much rather God marvel at my faith than at my
unbelief amen how long will it be air you believe me and so this morning as we
are encouraged by the life and testimony of a paraphrase the zeal of this man I
hope that we also are challenged say Oh God help me to have that kind of devotion
help my walk with you to be sincere genuine help it to be obvious help me to
be a person a man a woman of prayer a child of prayer help me to serve you
faithfully and then that God would give us that spiritual desire one for another
and then it would transform the way in which we pray because we're praying I'm
not suggesting we stop
worrying about physical needs, I'm just simply suggesting that we enter a new dimension,
if you will, we get onto the spiritual plane, and understanding that we are to be in prayer
one for another, even as Epaphras was for those believers, and it's spiritual in nature,
it's not temporal, it's not physical, it's spiritual, oh, that God would help us.
Only two points this morning, because I have like six or seven tonight, try to balance
it out, amen?
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you, we thank you for loving us, we thank you for the testimony of this
man Epaphras, and as we look at these couple of verses of Scripture, my heart is encouraged.
I thank you for his example, his walk with you, his devotion, I thank you for his desire,
for his brothers and sisters in Christ, Lord, I pray this morning that you'd use your word
to challenge us, that we would truly evaluate our own walk with you, that we'd evaluate
our prayer lives, how is it that we're praying, are we praying fervently, are we praying faithfully,
are we praying on this spiritual plane?
Lord, help us to be doers of the Word and not hearers only, help us to make some decisions
this morning that would cause us to be conformed to the image of Christ, that would cause us
to impact eternity.
I pray that you'd move and work in the moments of our invitation as only you can.
We'll give you the honor and the glory for every decision that is made, it's in Christ's
name we pray, would you stand with me, heads are bowed, eyes are closed, we have this time
at the end of our services to give you an opportunity to respond.
Maybe this morning you need to come to this old-fashioned altar and ask the Lord to help
you as you evaluate your own walk with God, to help you in your prayer life.
Maybe this morning you just want to thank God for the opportunity to pray, the privilege
that is ours to serve Him.
If you're not sure of heaven, we'd love to take a Bible and show you, I can know for
sure that heaven's your home.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.