said, I will never leave thee nor forsake thee, so that we may boldly say, the Lord
is my helper, and I will not fear what man shall do unto me.
When I know what God says, it enables me to boldly say, the Lord is my helper, I shall
not fear what man shall do unto me.
That was free tonight, amen?
Deuteronomy chapter number 11, and we'll be looking here at the first 17 verses of
Deuteronomy 11.
Of course, last week, as you know, we started a mini-series that I entitled, The Danger
of Deception.
I am thoroughly convinced that we are currently living in an age of deception.
I believe that as we look around our world, that it is not too difficult for any of us
to recognize that we are living in an age of deception.
In fact, as we study the Word of God, we find that our God has graciously warned us about
the reality of deception.
He told us that it was going to be the case.
Not only did He warn us about the deception that we would face, but I am very thankful
that He has given us the truth of His Word, He has provided us with the remedy for deception.
What a blessing to know and to have the Word of God and to know the truth.
What a blessing.
We will recall that as we began our series last Wednesday evening, that I mentioned to
you, and it is worth pointing out again this evening, that the tool of deception has been
in the adversary's toolbox since the Garden.
We understand that it is a tool that he regularly uses, the tool of deception.
It's in his toolbox and he uses it often, and we find that no doubt, even in the age
in which we're living, we are facing great deception.
If you're taking notes this evening, the title for the message is from verse number 16.
I'll read that verse.
For sake of time, I won't read all 17 verses.
We'll read them as we go through.
But in verse number 16, the Bible says this,
Take heed to yourselves, that your heart be not deceived.
And you turn aside and serve other gods and worship them.
So the title for the message this evening, that your heart be not deceived.
That your heart be not deceived.
I believe as we look at the book of Deuteronomy that we're mindful that God is preparing His
people for the entrance into the land of promise.
We understand that God had many years before given this promise that His people would enter
into the land of promise.
And as we study and read the book of Deuteronomy, we find that God is using Moses to prepare
the children of Israel for entrance into the land, reminding them of many things.
And as we understand the context here in Deuteronomy chapter number 11, we find that the first 15
verses are rich.
I mean, the first 15 verses of Deuteronomy chapter number 11 are really a reminder to
the people of what God has done and then revealing to the people what God will do for them.
And it's exciting.
Look at it in verse number 1.
Therefore, thou shalt love the Lord thy God and keep His charge and His statutes and His
judgments and His commandments always.
It's not a temporary thing.
It was a command given to them for the longevity.
It says this, and know ye this day for I speak not with your children which have not known
and which have not seen the chastisement of the Lord your God, His greatness, His mighty
hand and His stretched out arm and His miracles and His acts which He did in the midst of
Egypt unto Pharaoh the king of Egypt and unto all His land.
And what He did unto the army of Egypt, unto their horses and their chariots, how He made
the water of the Red Sea to overflow them as they pursued after you, and how the Lord
hath destroyed them unto this day.
Notice in these first four verses, we find this reminder again of the mighty acts of
God and what He did.
You think about as the Word of God is being given and as the minds of the people as they're
hearing the words, they're going all the way back to the time in Egypt when God performed
the miracles, the plagues, and then He's dealing in verse number 4 with the crossing over the
Red Sea and we find that this reminder of the miracles and the acts of God, it's encouraging
to be reminded of what God has done.
He says in verse number 5, and what He did unto you in the wilderness until you came
into this place, and what He did unto Dathan and Abiram the sons of Eliab, the son of Reuben,
how the earth opened her mouth and swallowed them up and their households and their tents
and all the substance that was in their possession in the midst of all Israel.
Now you understand that verse number 6 is really a word of warning, is it not?
This is, remember in verse number 2, He says that you've seen the chastisement of the Lord
but you've also seen His greatness and His mighty hand, His stretched out arm.
We understand that the Bible teaches us, whom the Lord loveth, He chasteneth, and they saw
the chastisement, they saw the judgment.
What is mentioned here in verse number 6 with Dathan and Abiram is the judgment of God.
What a great warning and a great reminder, in fact, Paul will reference some of those
types of things like what we see in verse number 6 in 1 Corinthians chapter number 10.
Notice in verse number 7,
But your eyes have seen all the great acts of the Lord which He did.
Therefore shall ye keep all the commandments which I command you this day, that ye may
be strong and go in and possess the land whither ye go to possess it, and that ye may prolong
your days in the land which the Lord sware unto your fathers to give unto them and to
their seed a land that floweth with milk and honey.
For the land whither thou goest in to possess it is not as the land of Egypt from whence
ye came out, where thou sowest thy seed, and waterest it with thy foot as a garden
of herbs.
But the land whither ye go to possess it is a land of hills and valleys, and drinketh
water of the rain of heaven, a land, notice this in verse number 12, a land which the
Lord thy God careth for.
The eyes of the Lord thy God are always upon it from the beginning of the year even unto
the end of the year.
And it shall come to pass, and then notice this word, if.
It shall come to pass if ye shall hearken diligently unto my commandments which I command
you this day, to love the Lord your God and to serve Him with all your heart and with
all your soul, that I will give you the rain of your land in His due season.
The first rain and the latter rain that thou mayest gather in thy corn and thy wine and
thine oil.
And I will send grass in thy fields for thy cattle that thou mayest eat and be full.
That sounds good, doesn't it?
God is telling them this is what I've done for you and God is saying this is what I'm
going to do for you as you obey me, as you follow me, as you hearken to me, that I'm
going to do these things.
And these are fabulous, wonderful things.
And then we get to verse number 16 and he says, take heed to yourselves that your heart
be not deceived.
And ye turn aside and serve other gods and worship them.
Do you know this actually happened to the children of Israel?
Their heart was deceived and they followed idols.
It says in verse number 17, and then the Lord's wrath be kindled against you and He
shut up the heaven that there be no rain and that the land yield not her fruit and lest
ye perish quickly from off the good land which the Lord giveth you.
Focus our attention on verse number 16.
It's interesting to me as we look at the context of Deuteronomy 11 and we understand the place
of the warning.
It's in the time of the blessing of God and a time in which God is doing what He said
that He would do and He says, take heed to yourselves that your heart be not deceived.
The heart we find as we look throughout the Word of God, God's Word says much to us about
the heart and we can look at a number of passages.
We will not have time this evening to do that, but we find the Bible talks about a hard heart,
a proud heart, a pure heart, an understanding heart, just to mention a few.
And there are many references to the heart.
It's been defined as the seat of the affections and passions, the seat of the understanding,
the seat of the will.
You'll be mindful that it was God in Genesis chapter number 6, you don't need to turn there,
but He's speaking to Noah and talking about the judgment that would come with regard to
the wickedness God saw in verse number 5 of Genesis 6, that the wickedness of man was
great in the earth and that every imagination of the thoughts of his heart was only evil continually.
We think about this warning in Deuteronomy 11 and really we couple it with what Jeremiah
proclaims in Jeremiah 17 in verse number 9 when he says,
The heart is deceitful above all things,
and desperately wicked.
Who can know it?
The answer is given in v. 10 of Jeremiah 17.
I, the Lord, search the heart.
I try the rains,
even to give every man according to his ways
and according to the fruit of his doing.
But in the idea this evening
that your heart be not deceived,
we recognize that God is telling His people
and telling us through preservation
that the heart is deceitful above all things,
and desperately wicked.
Who can know it?
He says that your heart be not deceived.
It's interesting back in Deuteronomy 11
in v. 16 when He says
that your heart be not deceived,
the Hebrew word there that is translated deceived,
it carries with it the idea of being
simple, naïve, gullible.
But this is the one that hit me the most.
Open-minded.
Why does it hit me the most?
Well, because how often do we hear people today say,
you just need to be open-minded?
Right?
We hear it all the time.
We hear people say,
oh, you just need to broaden your horizon.
You just need to be more open-minded
and you need to be more inclusive
and so on and so forth.
You need to be open-minded.
And when they use that phraseology,
oftentimes what they'll do is they'll say,
you are just narrow-minded.
That's the opposite of being open-minded
is being narrow-minded.
And we've been accused of being narrow-minded.
And often I've said I can only be
as wide as my Bible is. Amen?
And we're going to be as narrow
as the Word of God is. Why?
As a preacher from yesteryear said,
never, or let me put it this way,
this is how he said it,
where God puts a period,
don't put a question mark.
What's he saying?
Just trust God's Word.
It's not necessary.
Listen, God understood as He gave us the Word of God,
He is the eternal God,
Alpha and Omega,
the first and the last,
the beginning and the end.
He understood the cultures
and the various aspects of thoughts
that human beings would have.
It's nothing new.
We see all the way back in Genesis 6,
the reason that I use that passage of Scripture
to talk about the heart being wicked,
this idea of deception that began in the garden
in Genesis chapter number three.
And he says that we need to take heed to yourselves
that your heart be not deceived.
And the word means to be simple,
to be naive, to be gullible,
or to be open-minded.
I understand that we're living in a time,
in an era, in a generation,
when it's popular that people are saying
you just need to be open-minded.
You need to consider other ways of thinking.
You need to understand and consider other perspectives.
Why would I leave the truth
for something that's less than truth?
It doesn't really make sense, does it?
And so if God has given us the truth,
and He has,
and we hold the Scriptures in our hands,
and we have the truth,
I don't need to be open-minded
to all of the new ideas
and all of the ideas that our world would have.
No, I need to have the mind of Christ.
Amen?
Here's what Paul says in the book of Philippians.
He says, let this mind be in you,
which was also in Christ Jesus,
in Philippians 2, in verse number five.
And we find it in the book of 1 Corinthians.
He talks about that we have the mind of Christ.
To know God is to know His word.
And we understand that God has given.
In fact, throughout the chapter of Deuteronomy 11,
as we've read through these first 17 verses,
we see that there are many references
to the importance of keeping the commandments
and following the commandments.
In verses 18, 19, and 20,
I will not have time to read those verses,
but it's very similar to the text of Scripture
that I preached on Sunday morning
from Deuteronomy chapter number six.
The importance of the commands of the Lord
and His statutes and His judgments.
And we find that here,
the word of God is to have a prominent place in our lives.
And when God's word has that prominent place in our lives,
that is really the key that we would not have,
that our hearts would not be deceived.
As I think about the warning that is given here,
I'm mindful of Jeremiah once again.
Turn over to Jeremiah 44, if you will.
We referenced already in Jeremiah 17
the way in which the Bible tells us
that the heart is deceitful above all things.
And Jeremiah 44,
you'll find that in this passage of Scripture,
there's some dialogue that takes place.
And I just want to read a few verses of Scripture to you
to help you see the deception of these people.
God says this in verse number three,
because of their wickedness which they have committed
to provoke Me to anger in that they went to burn incense
and to serve other gods whom they knew not,
neither they, ye, nor your fathers.
Howbeit, I sent unto you all My servants,
the prophets, rising early,
and sending them, saying,
O, do not this abominable thing that I hate.
Isn't God so gracious in longsuffering?
They forsook the Lord.
They forgot the Lord.
They followed after idols.
But God in His grace and His mercy
and His longsuffering,
He sent prophets,
and He sent those prophets faithfully.
Jeremiah, one of them.
But notice what it says in verse number eight,
But they hearkened not,
or inclined their ear to turn from their wickedness
to burn no incense unto other gods.
Wherefore, My fury and Mine anger was poured forth
and was kindled in the cities of Judah
and in the streets of Jerusalem,
and they are wasted and desolate as at this day.
What did God say back in Deuteronomy 11?
He said that if you had a deceived heart
and you followed after other gods,
that He would withhold the rain.
Remember, He said, if you obey Me,
if you keep these commandments,
I'm gonna send the rain,
the former and the latter rain.
I'm gonna bless and I'm gonna,
God controls, listen, there's no mother nature.
It's God that's controlling, amen.
He is the creator and the sustainer of all things.
And we find here that as you skip down
and look at verse number 16, if you will,
as the word of the Lord then came,
it says, as for the word that thou has spoken unto us
in the name of the Lord,
we will not hearken unto thee.
And so, Jeremiah takes them a message.
They had requested of Jeremiah
to seek the face of God on their behalf,
and Jeremiah faithfully does that,
and God faithfully answers Jeremiah,
and Jeremiah delivers that message,
and they say, we're not gonna hearken unto thee.
By the way, they had made a commitment
when they initially requested Jeremiah
to go on their behalf and to get the word from God,
that whatever He says, we will do.
And then he brought back the message,
and they said, no, that's not right.
We're not gonna hearken to that.
It says this.
Notice what they say.
This is a deceived heart.
But we will certainly do whatsoever thing goeth forth
out of our own mouth to burn incense
unto the queen of heaven,
and to pour out drink offerings unto her,
as we have done, we and our fathers,
our kings and our princes,
in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem.
For then had we plenty of vittles,
and were well, and saw no evil.
God's grace and God's mercy and God's long-suffering
was misinterpreted by the people of God
as being God's approval,
that God was okay with their behavior,
because God didn't immediately judge them.
They thought, man, when we were serving these idols
and pouring these things out to the queen of heaven,
we had plenty.
We didn't have all these problems.
We have the problems that you're dealing with now
because God's judgment came.
And instead of them turning to God,
they said, you know what?
We're just gonna keep on doing what we did before.
Man, that's terrible.
And God tells us in Deuteronomy 11, take heed,
and here's what he says,
take heed that your heart be not deceived.
How many times have you heard somebody say,
I mentioned about hearing people say all the time
in the culture and the society in which we're living
that we need to be open-minded and we've dealt with that,
but I want you to consider this.
How many times do you hear people say, follow your heart?
You've heard people say that?
Do you know that's a bad idea?
Honestly.
You know why it's a bad idea?
Turn to the book of Proverbs, if you will.
Proverbs chapter 28.
It's not a bad idea because I'm saying it's a bad idea.
It's a bad idea because God told us it was a bad idea.
Amen?
Because our heart is deceitful above all things.
I've heard people say, follow your heart.
I'm just following my heart.
I've heard people say, I'm following my gut.
I'm not sure that's a good idea either.
But the reality is that you hear this thing about.
following your heart.
But notice what it says in Proverbs 28.
Look in verse number 25.
He that is of a proud heart stirreth up strife.
But notice what it says.
He that putteth his trust in the Lord shall be made fat.
Continue, verse 26.
He that trusteth in his own heart is a fool.
Is that what your Bible says?
I'm not making it up, amen?
That's what the Word of God says.
But whoso walketh wisely, he shall be delivered.
Do you see the contrast in verses 25 and 26 between the one that puts his trust in the
Lord versus the one that's trusting in his own heart?
Your heart and my heart can deceive us.
It's not about me following my heart.
It's about me following the Lord.
We sang tonight about following the Lord.
Anywhere with Jesus, I can go, right?
As I follow him.
And we find here that we trust in him, and as we put our trust in the Lord, it says that
he shall be made fat, but if we trust in our own heart, we're a fool.
Why does he say that?
Because the heart is deceitful.
And he gives the warning to his people in Deuteronomy 11, preserved for us, take heed
that your heart be not deceived.
You say, oh man, my heart's not going to be deceived.
I can trust my heart.
First Corinthians 11 says, let he that thinketh he stand, take heed lest he fall, amen?
I think it's verse 12 in First Corinthians 11, verse 12.
And so the reality is that we must take heed to the warning that God gives us.
How do we respond to the warning?
Well, he says take heed in the verse of Scripture in chapter 11 and verse 16 of the book of
Deuteronomy.
And I mentioned that last week because that's what Jesus said as well.
It means to see, to discern, to beware.
I believe this.
Turn back, you're in the book of Proverbs right now, turn back to the fourth chapter
if you will, chapter number four.
What must I do?
How should I respond to this warning when God tells me this word that my heart is deceitful
above all things?
When he tells me that I'm to take heed that my heart be not deceived, and I recognize
that the New Testament, as we studied last week, tons of Scriptures that we referenced
last week that say, hey listen, they lie in wait to deceive, right?
They're deceiving and they're being deceived and we understand that we're living in this
age of deception and so therefore what must I do?
Well I believe that I must keep my heart.
Notice in verse number 23 of Proverbs 4, it's a very simple verse of Scripture, but the
Bible says this, keep thy heart with all diligence for out of it are the issues of
life.
Keep thy heart with all diligence.
The word keep is an interesting word, it means to guard or to watch, but it really goes even
further than that.
It means to guard from dangers, but it also means this, to guard with fidelity, with loyalty,
with faithfulness.
And so when I begin to notice what he says here, why is he saying keep thy heart with
all diligence?
Why is there an emphasis of guarding our hearts and to watch them, to guard them from
danger, to guard it with fidelity?
Why does he tell us that?
Well because of out of it are the issues of life.
Well because it's deceitful and so therefore I must guard my heart and how do I do that?
I've got to get in the Word of God.
There are times in which as we go through life, as we live here on this earth, that
we face decisions and we have things that are before us and we know there are people
that are lying in wait to deceive us and we know that it's a bad idea to follow our heart,
we must get in to the Word of God.
I keep my heart, I guard it from the dangers and with fidelity.
Trust in the Lord, what's he saying in chapter number 3, with all thine heart, lean not unto
thine own understanding and all thy ways acknowledge him and he shall direct thy paths.
By the way, I want him directing my path, don't you?
Amen?
I need to follow his Word.
I trust in the Lord and I follow his Word.
Let's look at Psalm 119 as we kind of finish up this evening and I want to just point out
a few verses here in the beginning, a couple of stanzas of Psalm 119 as we finish up this
evening and really looking at how we would respond to this warning that is issued.
Listen, when you've been reminded of the blessings, when God is revealing what he's going to do
and he says, take heed, when you're dealing with all of those blessings that your heart
be not deceived, it leads me to believe that there's a potential for being vulnerable at
that time, right?
It's interesting, I know you're in Psalm 119, I don't want you to turn back to Deuteronomy
because I need to finish there, but it's interesting because in Deuteronomy chapter number 6, the
passage that I preached last Sunday morning, he gives all of that instruction about teaching
your children and so on and so forth, but then he says when you have houses that are
full of good things and you filled it not, you have wells that are digged that you didn't
dig and vineyards and oliveyards that you didn't plant and you're eating from it, then
beware lest thou forget the Lord.
That's Deuteronomy 6 and verse number 12.
Why in that moment?
Well, because we're increased with goods and have need of nothing.
Unfortunately, at times that even means God, if we're not careful.
Say, I got this.
In Psalm 119, notice verse number 2, blessed are they that keep his testimonies and that
seek him, how?
With the whole heart.
Look at verse number 10.
So it's interesting if you notice in verse number 2, the psalmist says, blessed are they
that keep his testimonies and that seek him with the whole heart.
He's looking at those that are doing these things and he's saying they're blessed because
of these actions.
And then in verse number 10, he says, with my whole heart, have I sought they?
Oh, let me not wander from thy commandments.
Thy word have I hid where?
In mine heart.
Why?
For I might not sin against thee.
This evening, we're living in an age of deception.
And there is a danger, there is a warning that is given to us.
Moses is being used by the Lord to instruct the people of God and he says, take heed to
yourselves that your heart be not deceived.
I don't need to have an open mind to all of the new age ideas and all of the craziness
that our society and our culture wants to pump down our throats.
I just need to know what God says on the subject.
Amen?
I just need to know what God says.
I don't need to be gullible and naive.
I want to take heed.
I don't want to have a deceived heart.
And it's absolutely essential that we understand that when we hear so often, just follow your
heart.
That's bad counsel.
That's not biblical.
We follow the Lord and we follow His word because our hearts are deceitful above all
things.
And there are many that lie in wait to deceive.
Remember in Crete, as I mentioned in the book of Titus last Wednesday evening, that in that
small island, there were many deceivers.
In a small island, many deceivers.
Our land is littered with deceivers.
And by the way, for some reason, they very regularly get microphones and have platforms
and audiences, right?
The tool is often used by the enemy, the tool of deception.
Tonight, we need to take heed unto ourselves that our heart be not deceived.
Let's pray.
Father, how we thank you for the warnings that you give us in your word.
We understand the word of God has revealed to us the danger of deception, the age of
deception in which we're living in.
I pray tonight, as we look at this thought of our heart being deceived, that you would
help us, Lord, to keep, to guard our hearts with all diligence.
That we'd hide your word in our heart.
That we would be biblically minded, not open-minded.
That we would get into your word and allow your word to get into us, so that we would
think and act biblically.
That we could give an answer of the hope that lieth within us.
Help us, Lord, to take heed to the warning.
Bless our time of prayer.
We thank you for the privilege of prayer, which in Christ's name we pray, amen.
Does anyone need a prayer bulletin this evening?
You did not get one on your way in, and you need one?