last time, so it's been a while since we're here.
We were supposed to be here back during COVID.
And of course, because of COVID, we weren't able to come
and we had to cancel out the meeting
that we had scheduled then.
So the Lord was gracious to let us come this year in 2023.
And I tell you, it's good to be here, amen?
In fact, at this point in life, it's good to be anywhere.
So I'm just thankful for the opportunity to be back here
in Virginia once again, in beautiful Oakton.
And we've been getting around a little bit,
my cousin and his wife live just south of here.
And so we went down and visited with them yesterday
for a little while.
They've lived here for quite some time,
so it's good to see them.
So it's having family near you was a bonus.
So getting to spend time with people we don't see
on a regular basis was a joy.
I'll be introducing us in the morning service
a little bit more, you pray for me.
I woke up this morning with a slight cold
and I thought yesterday it was allergies
and I told them then, if I get a cold,
a lot of times I lose my voice.
And I preached a missions conference
where I had to hold the mic at my mouth all week long.
I mean, I held up here, it felt so bad,
I told the pastor, I don't want my love offering,
you can keep it because I feel bad
that I wasn't able to do my normal preaching.
And he said, listen, he said, you know,
God can still use your squeaky voice, amen?
And so I had a good missions conference,
I had a good faith promise commitment
and took on some more missionaries, including us.
And so God blessed us in a great way
during the course of that meeting.
So you pray for me that I keep my voice
during the course of the week.
If you've not met us before, this is my wife, Linda,
I'll have her stand very quickly.
The Bible said, who so fond of the wife
finds the good thing and obtain a favor of the Lord, amen?
We've been married 58 years now, gone 59.
God's been gracious to give us long life together
and just mentioned bladder cancer, I've had it twice now.
So I know what it's like to go through the surgery
and I've had other cancers as well.
So God's kept me going in spite of all that.
And so I'm thankful for it.
But we've been on the road now and revival work now,
31 years, I pastored 14 years in the San Diego area.
And we've enjoyed our ministry,
but we're getting a little bit older now.
So traveling is getting harder.
So it was always difficult for us to get on planes
and fly to different places.
And of course, we drive quite a bit.
And in fact, we finished this meeting,
we go to Harrisonburg for a meeting
and be down there next week.
And then we fly back to San Diego
and then we're in the car four days later,
driving to Missouri for meetings there.
And then we'll be coming up in the Minnesota
and down through South Dakota.
So it's getting a little bit rougher.
I was saying to Brother Sommerdorf yesterday,
saw his big RV out there.
We had an RV, but we got to the point
where it was getting too difficult for us to use it.
Get a little bit older, it's harder to set it up
and tear it down every week.
We had a fifth wheel.
And so we get out of that and we've been just using our car
and our RV or SUV and now I'm flying as well.
But good to be with you.
We'll be talking a bit more about revival
during the course of the week.
Now, revive us again that thy people may rejoice
in thee, Psalm 85, six.
Now, in a revival meeting,
one of the things that's most important is prayer.
And we had some prayer yesterday,
but we need to continue to pray that God would work
during the course of the week.
Now, listen friends, I'll tell you,
we desperately need revival in America.
But we need it in our Bible believing churches.
I said, I told them yesterday,
judgment must begin at the house of God.
We have got to have a time in our churches in America
where we recognize the importance of revival
within the local New Testament church.
Now, I have had the blessing of seeing revivals take place
in churches over the years.
But I will say this, I've not seen much,
I've not seen much of a revival spirit in recent years.
Seems like there's been more of a resistance,
more of a hindering spirit.
People refusing to get right with God.
People refusing to confess their sin and repent
and turn from their wicked ways.
I mean, that's become a real problem.
There is a simple formula for revival, it's this,
and of course we see it in 2 Chronicles 7, 14,
and they say, well, now, Brother Meshon,
you know that was given to the children of Israel,
but as a practical application to us today,
if my people, which are called by my name,
number one, will humble themselves.
Now, there's a concept.
Will humble themselves and pray, amen,
and seek my face.
Now, hear this, and turn from their wicked ways.
He's not talking to the world there,
he's talking to his people.
Turn from their wicked ways.
He said, if you'll do that, those four things.
Now, those four things are not the result of revival,
it's what brings revival.
It's what invites revival.
That's not the fruit of revival, it's what brings revival.
That's the formula for revival, four things.
So if you do that, he said, listen, I'll answer your prayer,
I'll forgive your sins, I'll heal your land.
And I've said this for years,
the only hope America has is a revived church.
Unless we experience revival right here,
and we see God do a work here, America's done.
The answer's not in the White House, folks,
the answer's in God's house.
We got too busy with politics here in recent years,
and listen, I'll tell you what,
we need to understand and realize that you and I,
who are saved by the grace of God,
the Great Commission is what's most important,
first of all, winning people to Jesus Christ one by one.
But we've got to get our own household cleaned up.
Would you agree with that?
So I really do believe we need to give
some thought and consideration to that this week
as we go into the revival meeting.
I'm serious about revival.
I wanna see revival, amen, don't you?
I really do, I want God to start with me.
And that's an important thing.
Haggai chapter one in your Bible today,
let's go to Haggai chapter one.
Haggai chapter one, a great little book,
one of the minor prophets write stuff
right between Zephaniah and Zechariah.
Haggai chapter one, if you have a Cambridge-wide margin
Bible like I do, it's on page 1002, amen?
I said that in a church one time,
the guy said, oh, I got one of those.
So he got right to the page.
Haggai chapter one, we're gonna start there,
and then we'll just move around in the Bible
just a bit here in the Sunday school hour.
And I guess if I were to give my Sunday school lesson
a topic this morning, it'd be this.
Self-confrontation, self-examination,
putting yourself on trial.
Every once in a while, we just need to stop
and we need to confront ourselves and examine ourselves
in light of the word of God.
And I thought about this the other day,
I think sometimes we're too busy examining the world,
but let me say something to your friends,
the world's gonna do what the world's gonna do.
They're just gonna do what they're gonna do.
They're unsaved, they're lost, they don't know Christ,
they don't have the word of God,
so the world's going to do what the world's gonna do.
We get so busy looking at the world,
what the world's doing, that we don't stop
and take time to look at ourselves.
That's an important thing for us to sometimes
get engaged in self-confrontation, self-examination.
Now, I'm not talking about introspection here,
and I'm not talking about contemporary mysticism
or contemplative mysticism and some of the stuff
that goes on today in some circles of churchianity.
I'm talking about getting down and dirty with us,
with ourselves, and taking a hard look at ourselves.
And every once in a while,
it's good to just stop and do that.
But I want you to get Haggai chapter one,
we'll go down through just a few verses here
and just look at a couple of things
that God just spoke to my heart about.
Personally, my wife actually pointed this out to me,
and I went back and I studied this whole book.
And by the way, it's a post-exilic book,
and of course, there's four of them.
It's Haggai, Zechariah, Malachi, and Joel,
four post-exilic books, and this is one of them.
And it was when Cyrus gave the grant
to the children of Israel to reestablish
and rebuild the temple.
We see that back in the book of Ezra.
We see specifically what it says in Ezra chapter four.
We're gonna find out that when their adversaries
came against them, they left off building the temple.
And for 14 years, the work remained dormant.
And God was not really pleased with that.
And of course, we know that Artaxerxes
gave a mandate that they were stopped doing it
because of the lies, the false things
that were being said about them
and what their agenda was and what their desires were
and their purposes were.
So they left off building the temple
when they should have just continued on at some point.
So talk about that as we get into this.
But in Haggai chapter one, beginning in verse one,
I read this, in the second year of Darius the king
in the sixth month, that was Elal in the Hebrew calendar.
It's September in the lunar calendar.
In the first day of the month came the word of the Lord
by Haggai, the prophet of Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel,
governor of Judah and to Joshua, the son of Josedek,
the high priest saying,
thus speaketh the Lord of hosts saying,
this people say, now watch this,
this people say, the time has not come,
the time that the Lord's house should be built.
And of course, you can go back to reference it back
to Ezra chapter four in verse 24
to see what all was taking place there, the whole dynamic.
He said, they said, listen, the people say,
the time has not come,
the time that the Lord's house should be built.
But look in verse three,
then came the word of the Lord by Haggai the prophet saying,
well, is it time for you?
Oh, ye to dwell in your sealed houses
and this house lie waste.
God says, what about me?
He said, you guys are so busy building your own houses,
building your own mansions
that you've forgotten about my house.
He said, listen, you need to get back to building my house.
It's important for you to get back to building my house.
You need to reestablish the house of God.
And they weren't doing that.
Now, let me say this,
and then I'll move on to the next verse
because there's something here I want you to see.
It's important to us this morning,
just a very simple thing.
There's nothing.
something profound here. But let me say this, sometimes I think we just basically get so
lackadaisical and so kind of, you know, we're in our comfort zone and we're kind of comfortable
and enjoying our situation, our life the way it is right now that we don't stop and think
about, now listen, am I moving forward for God? Am I doing what God wants me to do? Am
I busy about God's work? Or am I just basically coasting along here in my Christian life?
There's too much of that. We don't have much time left. You're going to hear me preach
about that a little bit this morning. Let me tell you something, friends. We need to
understand this. Jesus is coming soon. And the night cometh when no man can work. And
so we all of us need to be busy about God's business. Now I'm going to walk down the aisle
so I'm not forgetting these people up here. I'll come back in a minute. We need to be
busy about God's business. And we've just gotten to the point, I think, where we've
gotten into this spiritual lethargy and this spiritual apathy and we forgot about God.
By the way, we see the children of Israel on two different occasions. God said to them,
listen, you've forgotten me days without number. Well, we used to be a God-conscious nation,
America. You remember that we were at one time a God-conscious nation? Amen? Our friends
back here are from western Pennsylvania. My brother, I don't know how old you are, but
I'm a little older maybe than you, I think. Amen? Pennsylvania was a blue state law. We
were a blue law state. I'm sorry, I got that backwards. We were a blue law state. Everything
was closed on Sunday. Nothing was open on the Lord's Day. I remember that. I grew up
under that in the 40s and the 50s and early 60s and everything was closed. But the churches
were open. And the neighborhood in which I lived, I was born in West Philadelphia and
then we moved out to the suburbs. The neighborhood I lived in and my wife lived in, I don't know
of anybody on my block that didn't go to church. Everybody went to church. Maybe not
the right churches, but everybody went to church because we were a God-conscious nation.
And then when they repealed the blue laws, I think it was in the late 60s, when they
repealed the blue laws and we had them down here, Virginia had blue laws as well. When
the blue laws got repealed and all the malls opened up and all the other stuff started
happening and everything else was going on on Sundays and everybody was playing baseball
and football and basketball and hockey, everything else going on on Sundays, all of a sudden
people stopped going to church. So America was no longer a God-conscious country. So
I can hear God say, well, what about me? What about me? So He says to the children of Israel,
and that's a little off topic, but He says to the children of Israel, well, what about
me? He says, is it time for you, O ye, to dwell in your sealed houses, and this house
lie waste? Look at verse 5, Now therefore thus saith the Lord of hosts, say it, Consider
your ways. He said, y'all need to consider your ways. I'm in Virginia, so I'm saying
y'all, amen? Even though we're in northern Virginia, it's still y'all. We're below the
Mason-Dixon line here, amen? He said, y'all need to consider your ways. And He says it
not only once, but if you read through Haggai, He says it five times. So moving on to verse
6, He said, You have sown much, you bring in little. You eat, but you have not enough.
You drink, but you're not filled with drink. You clothe you, but there is none warm. And
he that earneth wages earneth wages, to put him into a bag with holes. He said, you know,
you guys are so busy about you and not busy about me that you're not prospering at all.
When you're not right with God and you're not in fellowship with God, you're not walking
with the Lord, you're not walking in the Spirit of God, I guarantee you, you're not going
to prosper. Now, we're not talking about the, you know, the stuff that these, you know,
fools on TV talk about, about this health, wealth, and prosperity stuff, and faith, seed,
and all that stuff. No, God said, listen, the reason you're not prospering is because
you're not walking in accordance with My will. You get out of the will of God, you're not
going to prosper. Let me give you a good example. If you're not tithing, and of course, most
of you here are probably church members, you ought to be tithing. If you're not, you're
living in sin. But He said, if you, listen, if you're not tithing, you're going to tithe
somewhere else. If you don't tithe the Lord, you're going to tithe to the doctor, you're
going to tithe to the dentist, you'll tithe to the auto mechanic. God is going to get
that tithe somewhere. When I first got saved, I can remember, I got it somehow in my mind
because I was an E6 in the Navy, that I, at that point in time, that there was no way
that I could possibly tithe. I just, we weren't making a lot of money back in those days,
and the military never made a lot of money, but we definitely weren't making a lot of
money then. And I said, Lord, listen, you know I can't tithe. I mean, I just can't do
it. I can't pay my bills. I'm overextended. My family won't eat if I tithe. My wife wasn't
on board with that, having been saved seven years before I was, and she was a little bit
more spiritually astute, and so I didn't tithe. All right? The first month I didn't tithe,
my car broke down. Now hear this. I mean, this is my testimony. My car broke down. The
starter went out. It was my home to work car. 1967 Datsun. What a piece of junk that was.
The starter went out. So I went down to Napa and I bought a starter. Brought it home, put
it in my car. And then I looked at the receipt, which I charged, by the way. Then I looked
at the receipt. The starter cost me, to the penny, what my tithe would have been. I said,
Lord, you've got my attention. And from that point forward, I tithe. Because I realized
and understood the principle that we see right here. If you rob God, and we see that in Malchai
chapter 3, if you rob God and said, listen, I'm going to tell you one thing right now,
you're not going to prosper. I'm going to send the locust, the palmer worm, I'm going
to send all kinds of critters into your fields to eat up your harvest. Not a good thing,
So he said, you better tithe. So he said, listen, because you've not done this, you're
not prospering. And you wonder why. I like what he says there. It's kind of a funny statement.
But he says, and he that earneth wages, earneth wages to put into a bag with holes. So this
comes in and goes right out again. Now, verse 7, he says again, look, Thus saith the Lord
of hosts, Consider your ways. God wants us to consider our ways. When we go into a Bible
meeting, that's what we ought to be doing. We should be examining ourselves. We ought
to confront ourselves. The Word of God will confront us for sure. We ought to put ourselves
on trial. That's a volitional thing. It's a matter of choice. A lot of people aren't
going to pay any attention sometimes to the beck and call of the Holy Ghost. If I tell
you this, I was preaching down in Torrance, California, one time, a bigger auditorium
than this, a big crowd that morning. About halfway down here, back here, I'd ask your
dad if that ever happened to him. About halfway down here, there's a woman sitting here. She's
sitting right there, two kids in the middle, and her husband here. I'm preaching. I can't
remember this day why I was preaching. While I'm preaching, she stuck her fingers in her
ears. I said, now, that's kind of strange. So she sticks her fingers in her ears. Now
not only is she sticking her fingers in her ears, now she's shaking her head no at me.
I'm a young preacher, and I'm kind of irritated by this, I guess. It was bothering me. So
I thought, you know, I'm just going to go right back there and stand right where she's
sitting, and I'm going to preach right there. And the Holy Spirit, you know, that still
small voice, that whisper, said, don't you do it. I'll take care of her. So when the
service is over, she's at the back door. And I said to one of the deacons, I said, who
is that woman? And he said, oh, that's the head deacon's wife. And they're back there
shaking hands with people leaving the building. And I said, I'm going to go back there and
chat with her. I said, that woman stuck her fingers in her ears while I'm preaching. Oh,
she wouldn't do that. I said, she did it. I'm either lying or dying. And I was going
to head right back there. The Spirit of God said, don't you do it. I'll handle that. Now,
I've never heard anybody do that to me again. Now, it seems to me like I've read an account
in the Bible where it says they stopped their ears. Well, that's kind of what she did. And
I thought, why would somebody that claims to be saved by the grace of God do that? But
you know what the truth of the matter is? Something got to her from the Word of God,
she didn't want to hear it. Therefore, she was not willing to, you ready for this? It's
not a, listen, it's not profoundity here. Therefore, she was not willing to examine
her ways. Not willing to consider. Not willing to be confronted about her ways. Go back to
1 Corinthians, please. We'll go back there very quickly. 1 Corinthians chapter 11. Oh,
good. You've got a clock back there. Praise the Lord. I can see you, God. I have to keep
doing this. 1 Corinthians chapter 11. I want you to start in verse 17. I'll lay some foundation
here. Of course, we know this passage of Scripture. We use this when we have a Lord's Supper.
At least I've done it over the years. I'm sure you do it here as well. It's a classic
application of the Lord's Supper. But 1 Corinthians chapter 11, verse 17. I'm going to read down
through this very quickly.
So now, in this I declare unto you, and I praise you not, that you come together not
for the better, but for the worse. For first of all, when you come together in the church,
I hear that there are divisions among you, and I partly believe it. Boy, it's a terrible
thing to have divisions in the church. It's good when the brethren dwell together in unity.
For there must be also heresies. In other words, they were developing sex within the
church. There also must be heresies among you, that they which are proved may be made
manifest among you.
When you come together, therefore, at one place, this is not to eat the Lord's Supper.
For in eating every one taketh before the other his own supper, and one is hungry and
another is drunken."
Man, there's a lot of preaching right here.
"'Well, what, have you not houses to eat and drink in, or despise ye the church of
God, and shame them that have not?
What shall I say unto you?
Shall I praise you in this?'
Well, I'm going to tell you what, I praise you not.
"'For I received of the Lord that which also I delivered unto you, that the Lord Jesus,
the same night in which he was betrayed, took bread.
And when he had given thanks, he broke it, and he said, Take, eat.
This is my body, which is broken for you.
This do in remembrance of me,' because it's a symbol of his death, it's an emblem, it's
a memorial service.
"'After the same manner also he took the cup, and after he had supped and sang, This
cup is the new testament of my blood.
This do ye as often as ye drink it in remembrance of me.
For as often as ye eat this bread and drink this cup, ye do show, demonstrate the Lord's
death until he come.'"
Verse 27, "'Wherefore, whose service shall eat this bread and drink of this cup unworthily?'
By the way, none of us are worthy of the death, burial, and blood of Jesus Christ.
You think about his death, burial, and resurrection as we celebrate the Lord's Supper, we think
about the precious blood of Jesus.
None of us are worthy of that.
He said, so you drink this cup of this Lord, not to drink the cup of the Lord unworthily,
carelessly, or reverently, shall be guilty of the body and the blood of the Lord.
Now look at this.
"'But let a man examine himself,' you see that, "'and so let him eat of that bread and
drink of that cup.
For he that eateth and drinketh unworthily or carelessly eateth and drinketh damnation
or judgment to himself, not discerning or honoring the Lord's body.
For this cause many are weak and sickly among you, many sleep.
For if we would judge ourselves, we should not be judged.'"
Listen, if we would judge ourselves and get things right with God, we wouldn't have to
experience chastisement.
God wouldn't have to judge our sins.
But when we are judged, we're chastened to the Lord.
"'For whom, Lord, lovely chasteneth, that we should not be condemned by the world.'"
Amen.
It just basically proves you're saved when God chastises you.
No chastisement, you're not saved.
That's kind of what he's saying.
But I want you to see this.
He said, you need to examine yourself.
He said, don't come to the Lord's table and do so flippantly or irreverently.
Examine yourself.
God once again says, listen, consider your ways and examine yourself.
I can show you a whole lot of teaching in the Bible that speaks about this.
Examine yourself.
Just listen to this.
Job 13, 23.
"'How many are mine iniquities and sins?'
Job says.
"'Well, make me to know my transgression and my sin.'"
Psalm 26, 2, "'Examine me, O Lord, and prove me.
Try my reins and my heart.'"
Psalm 4, 4, "'Stand in awe and sin not.
Commune with your own heart upon your bed and be still.'"
Selah.
Psalm 77, 6, "'I call to remembrance my song in the night.
I commune with my own heart, and my spirit may diligent search.'"
That's talking about intense examination.
Psalm 119, 59, like this one, "'I thought on my ways and turned my feet unto thy testimonies.'"
Wow.
Well, there's something right there.
That's something to think about right there.
He said, listen, I'll tell you what I did.
I thought on my ways.
I mean, that's intentionally stopping and thinking about my ways.
God said at one point somewhere along the line, I remember reading, your ways are not
my ways, friends.
Sometimes you've chosen the wrong way, not my way.
And His way's the right way, always the right way.
He said, listen, I stopped.
He said, I thought on my ways, and as a result, I turned my feet unto thy testimonies.
Now, that's a good thing.
Lamentations 340.
I like this one, too.
"'Let us search and try our ways, and turn again unto the Lord.'"
Wow.
Galatians 6, 4, "'But let every man prove his own work, and then shall he have rejoicing
in himself alone, not in another.'"
Second Corinthians 13, 5, this is an important one, "'Examine yourselves.'"
"'Examine yourselves,' Paul says to the Corinthian church, "'Examine yourselves,' and he had a
reason for saying this, "'Examine yourselves whether you be in the faith.
Prove your own selves.
Know you not your own selves, how that Jesus Christ is in you, except you be reprobates?'
So Paul said, listen, you need to make sure you're saved."
Sometimes, you know, we've got people come into revival meetings just aren't saved.
I was preaching at my home church last week, and I used the Ten Commandments.
I went through all of the Ten Commandments, not the ten suggestions, the ten opinions.
Galatians chapter 20, I went down through each one of the Ten Commandments, and talked
about them, and explained why God gave the moral law.
Why did God give us the Ten Commandments?
Well, Galatians chapter 3 gives the answer.
As a schoolmaster, to bring us to Christ, to convict us of sin, because there's no man
except the God-man, Christ Jesus, that was ever capable of keeping the law.
And in fact, the Bible says the law was fulfilled in Him.
So we know He can't keep the law, so as you read down through the Ten Commandments, somewhere
along the line, you ought to get convicted.
For an unsaved person, I use the Ten Commandments in soul winning.
I'm not one of these one, two, three, pray after me guys.
I don't like this easy decisionism.
I want people to know why they're lost, and know what the Bible says about being lost.
And then you can lead them to Christ.
You can't get somebody saved, get them lost first, amen?
So I want to get them lost.
You can get them lost in the Ten Commandments.
Well, sir, have you ever told a lie?
Thou shalt not bear false witness.
Have you ever told a lie?
Well, yeah, I've done that.
Well, then the Bible says you're a liar.
You've got to be careful with how you approach this.
Amen.
Well, have you ever taken anything that's not yours?
No, yeah, when I was a kid, I stole something.
I shoplifted in a candy store.
I said, well, then you're a thief.
The Bible says you're a lying thief.
Have you ever coveted something that's not yours?
Maybe your neighbor's car.
Maybe you've got a Toyota.
He's got a Lexus.
You'd like to have his Lexus.
Well, thou shalt not covet.
So you're a coveting, lying thief.
I mean, you can go on and on.
You can go right on down the list.
Now, you've got to be careful with it.
Once again, you have to be careful how you approach people with that.
But you can get them lost that way.
Well, Glaser's chapter 3 says, well, what is the purpose of the law?
Well, the purpose of the law is to be a schoolmaster to convictives of sin.
The cause of the recognized were lost, it turned to Christ to be saved.
So I mean, you can use the law as an effective tool.
So it's a matter of people examining themselves.
And so I wanted our church to see that.
I said, now, we've got some people here this morning, I'll guarantee you, we've probably
got some church members here that are lost.
Just because you're a church member, it doesn't impress me.
In fact, it doesn't impress God.
Maybe you're a tithing church member and you take the Lord's Supper and all the rest of
it.
And maybe you're even out knocking doors with us on Saturdays, but you've never been
born again.
Examine yourselves, whether you be in the faith.
Because you've never been changed.
You may have changed the outside.
Oh, here we go now.
You may have changed the outside, but the heart's never been changed.
You got a three-piece suit and a King James haircut, but your heart's never been changed.
And because your heart's never been changed, it shows up on the outside in the way you
live your life.
And you've never been changed.
You live a two-standard life.
You'll live one way outside the church and one way in the church because it's more important
you have people see you than it is how God sees you.
Amen.
Preacher, that's good.
I mean, it really does convict people.
So I want them to see that.
Well, we had two people saved at the service.
Now I don't know, they weren't church members that I know of.
Amen.
I wrote this down for me.
The hardest thing to do is to honestly examine ourselves.
And the reason that we won't do it is because we sometimes engage in self-deception.
Well, I'm really okay.
It makes you feel easy and comfortable.
We can deceive ourselves sometimes when we don't examine ourselves the way we should.
So we ought to examine ourselves, inspect ourselves in detail, examine ourselves and
look at ourselves thoroughly in accordance with the Word of God.
Amen.
Now I've got to move along here.
I don't have much time left.
Oswald J. Smith put this out.
I really like this.
He's a great Canadian pastor.
Some of you have probably read some of his material.
He has a lot of good material out there, especially about missions.
But he wrote a little thing about self-examination.
He gave a list.
And in the entire list, are we guilty?
Let me just quickly read you the list.
Number one, this is when it comes to self-examination.
Number one, have we forgiven everyone?
Is there any malice, spite, hatred or enmity in our hearts?
Do we cherish grudges?
Have we refused to be reconciled?
We ought to be reconciled to our brother.
If you have one against another, you should make that right with him.
During revival times, that's one of the things that sometimes happens.
I've seen it happen in two churches.
We had a revival break out in two churches, and I had no idea, preaching that meeting,
that half the church was at odds with the other half.
And in one church, they were all upset with the pastor's wife.
And during the invitation, she's playing the piano, had to stop because people are
coming, weeping, asking for her forgiveness and hugging her because they had ought against
her, and asked her forgiveness.
The song leader got up and said, I preached on pride the night before.
We'd extended the meeting out another day.
And he got up and he said, listen, he said, I'm just full of pride.
He said, I think I raised perfect kids, had a perfect home, had a perfect marriage, and
I thought we had every hair in place, and the rest of the church was just really in
serious trouble.
And his wife got up and said the same thing.
And revival broke out in that place, and I just went back and sat in the back back there
and said, hallelujah, praise God, just let it go and happen, turn it over to the pastor
and let him just handle the thing.
And it went on and on and on.
And it all had to do with reconciliation amongst the church.
the brethren, saw it happen to another church. Number two, do we get angry? Come on now.
Do we get angry? Are there any uprisings within? Is it true that we still lose our tempers?
Does wrath hold us at times in its grip? Do you get angry? I get angry sometimes driving
through Los Angeles. It's not a rush hour. It's a parking lot, and I just can't handle
traffic, and I get angry. And my wife, I said to men yesterday, my wife says, you just stress
me out. When we were doing the RV, it was even worse. And she said, do you just have
joy? And I said, oh yeah, I'm really enjoying this, praise the Lord. Number three, is there
any feeling of jealousy when another's preferred before us? Does it make us envious and uncomfortable?
Do we get jealous of those who can pray, and speak, and do things better than we can?
Number four, do we get impatient and irritated? I had someone tell me one time, pastor, I
just want to let you know you irritate me. I said, wait a minute, get in line, brother.
What can I tell a guy that says that? I can only say, well, I'm sorry, I mean, how did
I irritate you? And then he's going to give me a list, you know. Do little things vex
and annoy, or are we sweet, calm, and unruffled under all circumstances? Number five, are
we offended easily? There's a big one. When people fail to notice us and pass by without
speaking, does it hurt? If others are made much of, and we are neglected, how do we feel
about it? Number six, is there any pride in our hearts? No, no, no, no, none of us ever
deal with that. Come on now, are we puffed up? Do we think a great deal of our own position
and attainments? Number seven, have we been dishonest? Is our business open and above
reproach? Do we give a yard for a yard and a pound for a pound? Are we honest in our
statements or do we exaggerate and thus convey false impressions? I submit unto you that
the number one most probably insidious, pervasive sin amongst Christian people is lying. We
come forth from the womb speaking lies. We're born liars. Unless the Holy Spirit of God
has control of that, we can still be involved in lying, and we have a tendency to exaggerate
when it benefits us. Number eight, have we been gossiping about people? No, we don't
do that in Baptist churches. I've got an example, I'll use it later. Do we slander the character
of others? Well, that seems like that's almost like a spectator sport in America today. People
just slandering each other, tearing each other apart, so much divisions and vitriol and so
much bitterness and angst. It's amazing what's happened to our society today. Everybody's
impugning each other's character and tearing each other apart to try to get their way and
to put forth their own agenda. It's disgusting. Do we slander the character of others? Are
we tail bearers in busybodies? Number nine, do we criticize unlovingly, harshly, severely?
Are we always finding fault and looking for flaws in others? Yeah, we do that. Number
10, do we rob God? Have we stolen time that belongs to Him? Has our money been withheld?
Number 11, are we guilty of the sin of unbelief? In spite of all He has done for us, do we
still refuse to believe the promises of His Word? God is good for His Word. Aren't you
glad for that? Number 12, have we committed the sin of prayerlessness? Are we intercessors?
Do we pray? How much time are we spending on our knees? Have we crowded prayer out of
our lives? Number 13, are we neglecting God's Word? How many chapters do we read each day?
Are we Bible students? Do we draw our source of supply from the Scriptures? Number 14,
are we burdened for the salvation of souls? Have we a love for the lost? Is there any
compassion in our hearts for those who are perishing? Number 15, have we failed to confess
Christ openly? Are we ashamed of Jesus? Do we keep our mouths closed when we're surrendered
by worldly people we're witnessing daily? Number 16, are our lives filled with lightness
and frivolity? Is our conduct unseemly? Would the world, by our actions, consider us on
its side? Well, that's a good one there. Number 17, have we wronged anyone and failed to make
restitution or has the spirit of Zacchaeus possessed us? Have we restored the many little
things that God has shown us? Number 18, are we worried or anxious? Do we fail to trust
God for our temporal and spiritual needs? Are we constantly crossing bridges before
we come to them? Number 19, are we guilty of lustful thoughts? Do we allow our minds
to harbor impure and unholy imaginations? That's a big problem today with men because
I'll tell you what, you can't hardly go out in the public anymore and not be offended
by what we see or be enticed by it. It's sad. A. W. Tozer wrote this in his classic work
The Pursuit of God. He said this, he said, the man who has struggled to purify himself
and has had nothing but repeated failures will experience real relief when he stops
tinkering with his soul and looks away to the perfect one. While he looks at Christ,
the very thing he has so long been trying to do, we'll be getting done with him. We
should examine ourselves in light of the truth being revealed to us from Scripture and allow
God's Word to convict us and change us. At the same time, we must humbly admit our inability
to change ourselves and rely on the power of ourselves and rely on the power of the
Holy Spirit within to transform us into the image of Christ. So, when you consider all
these things, this idea of self-examination, self-confrontation, to me personally is a
very important thing when it comes to revival, to revival. When God's willing to send revival,
the problem's not with him. The problem's not with God, the problem's with us. And
you say, well, that sounds like kind of a blanking indictment. Well, in some ways it
is. I mean, we really have to look at us, not only just individually, but corporately
as well. You know? One of the things that I've seen in revival is this. We talked about
this, we're talking about this a couple of times since we've been here. One of the
things I've seen in revival about this is that when revival comes, man, the old-fashioned
excitement that one time permeated our churches. I mean, just the joy, the zeal. Once again,
I'll bring it up a little bit, the sporting in the morning message. Let me tell you what,
the joy and the zeal that really ought to be in the house of God and the excitement
ought to be there, the enthusiasm ought to be there. When revival comes, God restores
that. You know? Some people come to church, look like they've been sucking lemon juice
through PVC pipe all week long, man, they just come to work sour. You know? God doesn't
want us to come to the house of the Lord that way. We ought to have joy, joy unspeakable
full glory. We ought to be excited about something. You know, the world's excited about all kinds
of things. Amen? I have a picture on my phone, Lord forgive me, I have a picture on my phone
of a 2024 Corvette Z06. No, I love Corvettes. Amen? I'm 77 years old, I have no business
even thinking about that. But if God give me one of them, I sure drive it, amen? I
sure would. And let me tell you this, I mean, I was in a car dealer the other day getting
my car serviced and there's one out in the showroom floor, it's one of the only ones
on the West Coast. It's a Copa, it's a beautiful car. And I'm looking at this thing, man, I'm
looking at it and I'm saying, wow, this is some car, let's take a picture of it. Guy
said, hey, can I sell this to you? I said, you could, but I said I couldn't afford it,
it was $172,000. And I said, yeah, I said, it's looking good, man. I said, that thing
looks fast just sitting there. And he said, do you think you can handle this car? I said,
try me out. He said, I'll road test it right now. Well, see, now that excites me. I just,
I'm a car guy, I'm an aviation guy for one thing, but I'm a car guy and I like cars and
the faster the better. And sometimes the Lord has to convict me of that.
Now preacher, you don't need to be thinking about that stuff. Now the car excites me,
just looking at it excited me. The thought of having one really excites me. But here's
the thing, if something like that, some kind of a material thing like that can excite us,
then what about the things of God? Why don't we get excited about the things of God? You
know? So we ought to get excited. We ought to be enthusiastic. We ought to rejoice about
the things of the Lord. God's been good to us. For God is good and his mercy endureth
forever. God's been so good. I praise the Lord for it. We need to examine ourselves
and sometimes engage in self-confrontation. Father, we thank you Lord this morning for
what we've seen in that word, just a very simple Sunday school lesson, but yet still
at the same time, I think very important. So God, as we begin this revival meeting this
week, I pray that we would be willing to spend some time as did David. We see in the
Psalms that he many times would, even in the early hours of the morning, in the middle
of the night at times, he would lay in his bed and he would muse and he would consider
and he'd think about and examine himself. Lord, sometimes we just need to stop and do
that as well. I pray God that we would this week just seek your face and Lord, we just
bow before you God, cry out your name and ask that you would once again breathe fresh
upon us. Oh Spirit of God, do that which only you can do. Work in our hearts and lives.
Begin with me, oh God, I pray. I'm a needy preacher. I need your help and I need you
to speak to me this week as well. So Lord, I pray that we would just have a meeting this
week which would be honoring and glorifying to you. We'll thank you for it in advance
in Jesus' name. Amen. Pastor?
Amen. You are dismissed.