night is to get through the entire chapter of Genesis 40 and we'll be making a couple
of applications as we look at this portion of scripture and I mentioned this morning
as we dealt with that passage in 1 Peter chapter number 1 of the importance of rejoicing through
trials and I told you that the messages today both this morning and this evening are complementary.
They are stand-alone messages but they certainly complement one another and as we looked at
those three truths this morning as to why we can rejoice in the midst of trials we remember
our position in Christ and we remember the power of God and then as we look at that we
recognize that God has a purpose in everything that he allows in our lives and as we understand
the ability to rejoice through trials we then look at this passage of scripture this evening
in Genesis chapter number 40 and deal with faithful through trials being faithful through
trials I mentioned this this morning I believe the enemy wants us to quit I believe that
there are times as we go through life you think about the Apostle Paul on his journeys
the missionary journeys and all of the adversity and difficulty and trials that he faced and
no doubt there was pressure on the Apostle Paul to quit to just stop we mentioned this
morning about the disciples in Acts chapter number 5 they were preaching they filled Jerusalem
with their doctrine and they were beaten because of that they were commanded not to
teach in his name any longer and yet they depart rejoicing and then immediately going
out in teaching and preaching the Lord Jesus Christ and we find that those religious leaders
they wanted the disciples to quit doing what they were doing to quit propagating the truth
of the gospel and preaching what Christ had given them to preach and so we find that still
today the enemy desires that you would quit that I would quit that we just say you know
what it's not really worth it but I will tell you this evening with full assurance it is
absolutely worth running your race and running it to completion and being faithful unto death
I am thankful that we serve a God who is faithful and you think about the faithfulness of God
we sing great is thy faithfulness and what a wonderful hymn it is and to remind ourselves
of our faithful God first Thessalonians 5 24 says faithful is he that calleth you who
also will do it and was a verse of scripture that I claimed as a promised verse when I
went to Bible college and God called me and I didn't understand all that that meant and
I just trust it that God the faithful God that he would give all that I needed when
I needed it and you know when you look at your walk with God you'll find that God is
faithful he's faithful he's trustworthy he's dependable and I am so thankful that we serve
a God who is faithful he then calls us as his people to be faithful that we would be
faithful as we begin to think about being faithful and thinking about the importance
of being faithful through trials I believe that here in Genesis chapter number 40 we
see an example of Joseph and of course Joseph in chapter number 39 was falsely accused by
Potiphar's wife he ends up he finds himself in prison of course prior to that he ends
up in Egypt because he was sold into slavery by his brothers and all of these things seeming
to stack against him if you will but we find that even as he's there and he's in the prison
the 39th chapter of the book of Genesis finishes with this reminder to us that the Lord was
with him and I'm so thankful that God was with Joseph as he's there in the prison and
we begin to chapter number 40 and it tells us and it came to pass after these things
we don't know exactly how much time has passed but it says after the butler of the king of
Egypt and his baker had offended their lord the king of Egypt and Pharaoh was wroth against
two of his officers against the chief of the butlers and against the chief of the bakers
and he put them in ward in the house of the captain of the guard into the prison and then
notice this phrase the place where Joseph was bound the place where Joseph was bound
it tells us in verse number four in the captain of the guard charged Joseph with them and
he served them and they continued a season in ward as we look at Genesis chapter number
40 we find the entire chapter that Joseph is in prison in fact as you start chapter
number 41 you find that it was two more years after the conclusion of chapter 40 that Joseph
still is in prison and we find that when Joseph is here in prison in Genesis chapter number
40 we read of a man we read of his life and we see that he's a man that's continuing to
walk with the Lord he's not quit he's not giving up he's not throwing in the towel because
of the lot that he was served because of the circumstances in which he is facing I begin
to think about this truth and as I think about this passage here in Genesis chapter
number 40 and looking at the truth of being faithful through trials through those difficulties
in the opposition I'm reminded of what the wise man says in Proverbs 24 in verse number
10 if thou faint in the day of adversity thy strength is small if thou faint in the day
of adversity then I strength is small now we can look at that from a physical perspective
we can think about physical opposition and adversity but the reality is that that is
not the focus of Proverbs 24 in verse number 10 it's really a focus of spiritual strength
and we find that he said listen the day of adversity will come we mentioned this morning
it's not a question of whether you will have a trial or I will have a trial it's a question
of how will we respond how will we behave in the midst of that trial and as we look
here in Genesis chapter number 40 and we see the trial the difficulty in which Joseph is
dealing with but yet we find that he's faithful he's faithful and there's a great example
for us in this passage of scripture I'm going to somewhat quickly go through the dialogue
of Genesis chapter number 40 provide you with some details with regard to the chapter and
then look at some application for how you and how I can through trials not only rejoice
as we look at this morning but also be faithful through those trials and I'm so thankful that
our God is faithful and what an example that we see here in Genesis chapter number 40 if
I said this this morning I want to just repeat it here if you desire if I desire to be faithful
through trials then we better learn to rejoice in the midst of trials because when you rejoice
in the midst of trials when I rejoice in the midst of trials it's going to really help us
in being faithful through that trial why because I'm reminding myself that my position in Christ
I'm reminding myself of the power of God I'm reminding myself that God has a purpose and I'm
rejoicing in the midst of that trial and it will enable me to have that being faithful through
the trial someone said this I don't want to I don't want to know how difficult the storm was
I want to know if you made it to the other side and there's a great truth in that the reality is
that I understand that sometimes we'll discuss the trials and the difficulties and what-have-you
but the reality is that we will notice the faithful hand of our God as we go through those
trials and it's our responsibility to be faithful to the Lord as we look at this passage and kind
of dissect it very quickly this evening the first five verses provide for us the record if you're
taking notes number one being the incarceration of Pharaoh's officers two officers of Pharaoh
are introduced to us in Genesis chapter number 40 the butler and the baker we do not know them
by name we simply know them by their office and we know that the Bible tells us that they offended
their Lord they offended Pharaoh in verse number one we don't know their offense we don't know what
it was that they did but we find that whatever they did caused Pharaoh to be quite angry the
Bible tells us that Pharaoh was wroth against two of his officers in verse number two and it
tells us that he Pharaoh sentenced them to go to the prison in verse number three he put them in
ward I want you to notice and I've already made note of the fact that the Bible tells us specifically
that this is the place where Joseph was bound again Joseph is there under false pretenses he'd
been falsely accused and I want you to think about your life and think about different circumstances
that you faced and how many times somebody might be tempted to say well this just isn't fair and I
don't deserve this and we can take that approach and then all of a sudden we can quit doing what
we're supposed to be doing in the midst of whatever those circumstances are and then God
might not have the opportunity to use us in that circumstance like he could have why because we've
just kind of given up because we're just having a pity party because of our lot in life and so we
find that the Bible says that it's the place where Joseph was bound notice what happens again we do
not know the exact time frame as to how long Joseph had already been in prison but we know that at the
end of chapter 39 that God reveals to us that the the Lord was with him and that Joseph was able to
find favor in the sight of the keeper of the prison and he was notice in verse 22 the keeper of the
prison committed to Joseph's hand all the prisoners that were in the prison and whatsoever they did
there he was the doer of it and so we find that just as Joseph rose to rank of being a an overseer
in Potiphar's house at the beginning of chapter number 39 we find that through his perspective
in Genesis chapter number 40 and in the end of 39 as he's there in prison that he obviously kept
his eyes on the Lord and understood that God was involved in this that God was doing
something. And so we find here that Joseph has risen to this place, so much so that in
Genesis chapter number 40, now think about this, the chief butler and the chief baker,
they've offended Pharaoh, they're cast into prison, into this ward, and the Bible tells
us in verse number four that the captain of the guard charged Joseph with them. And so
Joseph obviously had a level of testimony before the prison, the keeper of the prison,
that he would entrust these men to Joseph's keeping. Now that's important for us to recognize
and understand because Joseph wasn't just walking around dragging his lip on the ground
and saying woe is me and this is just unfair and I can't believe this and don't you understand
what they said and so on and so forth. No, Joseph must have been doing and performing
whatever duties he was responsible for performing because the keeper of the prison says I'm
going to commit these two men to your keeping. And we find that the Bible tells us in verse
number four, notice right in the middle of the verse, and he served them. And he served
them. That's kind of interesting. As we notice that Joseph is in this position and these
two men, the chief butler and baker, are cast into prison because they offended Pharaoh
and Joseph is committed, charged with their keeping and the Bible says that he served
them. He served them. Now they were in prison because they offended their Lord, Pharaoh.
I don't know what they did. We don't know what they did. But Joseph is there falsely
accused and yet the Bible tells us that he served them. He served them. And then it says
at the end of the verse, in verse number four, and they continued a season in ward. We do
not know exactly how long this was that they were there. It seems as if it wouldn't be
an extended period of time, but they were there for a period of time. And the Bible
tells us in verse number five, that both of these men, they dreamed dreams. Notice this
isn't a dream to dream. Both of them, each man, his dream in one night, each man, according
to the interpretation of his dream, the butler and the baker, the king of Egypt, which were
bound in the prison. And so we see the incarceration of Pharaoh's officers in verses one through
five and verses six and seven. I want you to notice the inquiry of Joseph. Number two,
if you're taking notes, the inquiry of Joseph. In verses six and seven, we find that Joseph
looked upon them and he inquired as to what was going on. It tells us, and Joseph came
in unto them in the morning, in verse number six. And he looked upon them and behold, they
were sad. And so we find that in verse number six, of course, we're told in verse number
five that these men, the butler and baker, they had a dream. Each of them had a dream
in that night. And as they gathered together that next morning, Joseph came in unto them
in the morning and he looks upon them. He notices that they were sad. Have you ever
seen somebody that you notice is sad? You can just look at their countenance and you
can have an understanding by looking at someone's countenance, especially somebody that you've
gotten to know a little bit, you can tell what's going on. And he, the Bible says that
he could tell, he saw that they were sad. And then in verse number seven, it says that
he asked Pharaoh's officers that were with him in the ward of his Lord's house saying,
wherefore look ye so sadly today? That's where we see the inquiry of Joseph. He asked
the question in verse number seven because he sees what's taking place and we find that
he observes the behavior of these individuals, the butler and baker. He notices on their
countenance and he asked the question, wherefore look ye so sadly today? You know what happens
for most people when they go through trials? They become very me focused. They become very
self-centered. They become very concerned about what's going on in their life and the
trial that they're dealing with. But we find here in this passage of Scripture, as we consider
being faithful through trials, that Joseph is falsely in prison and he's there and the
Bible tells us that he served them. And then the Bible tells us that he notices that they're
sad and so he inquires and says, wherefore look ye so sadly today? He was not me focused.
He was not self-centered. He was not just, hey, look at all of my problems. Look at all
the things that I have going on. And again, we live in a society that if we're not careful
we can fall into that trap because it's so common. We see that behavior. But Joseph was
a man that knew Jehovah God. He knew the Lord. The butler and the baker, most likely as we
look at them as being Egyptians and what we know of Egyptians and what we know biblically
with regard to their practices and their worship and so on and so forth, they were polytheistic.
They had a plethora of gods that they served and we find that with that polytheism they
had all of these gods and false idols and deities and so on and so forth and we know
that there's no God but one, that's the Lord Jehovah. And here Joseph is in this place
and he knows the Lord God Jehovah, but there's butler and baker that are there. They don't
know the Lord and Joseph is not going to be so self-centered to be like, hey, look
I got these problems too and it's this and this. No, no. He says, what's wrong? Wherefore
look ye so sadly today? He took notice of their condition and he cared enough to ask
and I find that as we look at this particular passage and then dig into the remainder of
it, I believe that these few, these couple of truths in verses 1 through 7 give us insight
with regard to the behavior and focus perspective of Joseph through the trial. Through the trial.
He's not just walking around telling everybody that he can come in contact with, let me tell
you how I ended up here and let me tell you how bad it is and let me tell you he's not
doing that. We don't see that. In fact, in our text of scripture we see one reference
in verses 14 and 15 as to what he says to them after he interprets the first dream,
but we do find that it's not given in such a way that it's a complaining perspective
in a woe is me type of syndrome. And so we find that as we look at this, the incarceration
of Pharaoh's officers, the inquiry of Joseph, number three, the interpretation of dreams.
Verse 8 through 23, the end of the chapter deals with the interpretation of these dreams.
Notice in verse number eight, after Joseph inquires of these men and says, why, wherefore
look you so sadly today, the Bible tells us in verse number eight and they said unto him,
we have dreamed a dream and there is no interpreter of it. Now their understanding again with
regard to their culture and what they would do. We find it in chapter number 41 that when
there was a dream, they would have magicians and so on and so forth that would come and
try to interpret those dreams for them. That's what Pharaoh does in chapter 41 when he has
the dream, but there's no one that can interpret. And so they're there in prison and they've
had these dreams and they say, because we're here in prison, we've had these dreams and
there's no one to interpret our dreams. And then notice what Joseph says in verse number
eight, Joseph said unto them, do not interpretations belong to God. Tell them, tell me them, I
pray you. As I look at verse number eight, I find that Joseph has a confidence in God
being able to provide the interpretation of the dreams for both the butler and the baker.
He's a man that has confidence. He has an understanding of what God is able to do. Remember
that Joseph is a man that's had some dreams. We dealt with that several weeks ago as you
look at his life and you look at that difficulty that he has with his brothers. In chapter
number 37 of the book of Genesis with regard to his dreams, and we've dealt with that.
And so now he says, do not interpretations belong to God. Tell me them, I pray you. And
so it's very interesting, no doubt as this interaction unfolds, the butler immediately
begins to share with Joseph the dream. Now that reveals to me that there's a high level
of confidence. If Joseph's just like, eh, you know, tell me your dream and we'll see
what we can, no, Joseph evidently through what we can read in verse number eight, but
the behavior of the butler and the baker, we find that there was a level of confidence
that was communicated to these men with regard to Joseph recognizing that God could give
the interpretation of the dreams. We can look at the book of Daniel and we can see the confidence
of Daniel with Nebuchadnezzar and what a blessing that is to understand the focus. There's a
God in heaven. That's what Daniel proclaims and makes known. And I'm thankful that Joseph
here, he's saying, look, interpretations belong to God. Notice in verse nine, the chief butler
begins to tell him his dream. It says the chief butler told him's dream to Joseph and
said to him in my dream, behold, a vine was before me. And in the vine were three branches
and it was as though it budded and her blossom shot forth and the clusters thereof brought
forth ripe grapes. And Pharaoh's cup was in my hand and I took the grapes and pressed
them into Pharaoh's cup and I gave the cup into Pharaoh's hand and Joseph said unto him,
this is the interpretation of it. The three branches are three days. Yet within three
days shall Pharaoh lift up thine head and restore thee unto thy place. And thou shalt
deliver Pharaoh's cup into his hand after the former manner when thou wast his butler.
Now that's a pretty good interpretation. In fact, the butler's pretty excited about
that. He's going to have his position restored. He's going to go back. And it's so compelling
that the baker, according to verse number 16, he's eager to tell him his dream as well
because he hears this good interpretation. Before we get to verse 16 and the baker, notice
what Joseph says in verses 14 and 15. And again, this shows the confidence of Joseph.
In verse 14, it says,
but think on me when it shall be well with thee.
Joseph was so confident in the interpretation
of the dream of the butler,
that the butler was, in fact,
indeed going to return to his place of butlership,
and he once again would give the cup to Pharaoh,
and he says, think on me when it shall be well with thee,
and show kindness, I pray thee, unto me,
and make mention of me unto Pharaoh,
and bring me out of this house,
for indeed I was stolen away out of the land of the Hebrews,
and in here also have I done nothing
that they should put me into the dungeon.
And so even though Joseph in verses 14 and 15
gives accurate dialogue with regard to his condition
and his lot and what's happened,
we find that Joseph is not in a place
where he's just given up
on doing what he's supposed to be doing.
We find that he continues to be faithful.
He's engaged.
He's trusting the Lord.
He's giving the interpretation.
I mean, he's not just sitting on the sidelines,
so to speak, and again, having a pity party,
and we find that Joseph is in this position,
and he has great confidence
that it shall be well with the butler.
The baker, he's excited.
He hears this good report.
So it says in verse 16,
when the chief baker saw that the interpretation was good,
he said unto Joseph, I can almost see in my mind's eye,
in my sanctified imagination,
that he's almost stuttering over his words
to get the dream out so quickly
because he's so excited about the interpretation,
and he wants to share it.
Why?
Because there's some similarities between the dreams,
and he's getting it out, and he's going to come,
and it says that he saw that the interpretation
was good for the butler,
and so he said to Joseph, I also in my dream,
and behold, I had three white baskets on my head.
Now remember, as we looked at the first dream there,
there were three branches,
and that represented the three days,
and so perhaps the baker's thinking,
man, I'm gonna be released in three days as well.
Well, he was, but not for a good reason,
and it says in verse 17, in the uppermost basket,
there was of all manner of baked meats for Pharaoh,
and the birds did eat them out of the baked meats
upon my head.
And so he did not give the baked meats to Pharaoh
as the butler gave the cup to Pharaoh.
It tells us that the birds ate the meats,
the baked meats out of that basket,
and so Joseph answered and said,
this is the interpretation thereof.
The three baskets are three days.
So far, so good.
Yet, within three days,
shall Pharaoh lift up thy head from off thee
and shall hang thee on a tree,
and the birds shall eat thy flesh from off thee.
That's unfortunate,
but just as Joseph was confident
in the interpretation of the butler's dream,
he too was confident
in the interpretation of the baker's dream.
And the Bible tells us in verse number 20,
and it came to pass the third day,
which was Pharaoh's birthday,
but he made a feast and all his servants,
and he lifted up the head of the chief butler
and of the chief baker among his servants.
Now, just as a side note,
and we look at this passage of scripture,
and it's another perspective,
but I want you to think about
what those guys did for three days.
The butler, his three days were probably spent
with a certain level of anticipation, excitement.
The baker, on the other hand,
you ever want days to go by fast?
Like, I can't wait for this thing to happen
because I'm looking forward to it,
vacation's coming, whatever.
The butler probably had that kind of a perspective.
The baker, slow down, he knew it was going to happen.
I just wonder,
as we look at this passage of scripture
and think about the perspective of these two men
and how they lived those days,
how different their perspective would be
on that time knowing what they knew.
You know, sometimes in life,
people will say something like this.
Pastor, I just wish I knew what was going to happen.
I would tell you that you don't want to know
what's going to happen
because it might not be super good,
and then you're just going to,
and it might not be super good,
and then you're just going to have difficulty with it.
We find here that these two men,
they understand what's going to happen,
the interpretations have been given,
and now on the third day,
Pharaoh calls for them.
And it says in verse 21,
and he, Pharaoh, restored the chief butler
into his butlership again,
and he gave the cup into Pharaoh's hand.
But he hanged the chief baker
as Joseph had interpreted to them.
And then it tells us,
yet did not the chief butler remember Joseph,
but forget him.
It tells us in chapter 41 that it was two full years
after this interaction between the butler and baker
and Joseph that the Pharaoh has a dream.
But as we focus on chapter number 40
and we see the dreams interpreted
and we see what takes place
and we understand what's going on here,
and ultimately as we look at this passage of scripture,
having the entire book of Genesis
and understanding what's going to happen next,
we can see God's hand in this circumstance.
We can see how God was orchestrating things
in the life of Joseph,
and we can see even as Joseph will testify later
in his life when he speaks to his brothers
how God sent him before them to preserve life
and they meant it for evil,
but God meant it for good and understanding all of that.
And we read all the way through Genesis 50
and many of us are familiar with what happens
in Joseph's life,
but I would submit to you this evening
that he's living moment by moment,
day by day as we do.
And as we look at this passage of scripture
and understanding what's happening,
Joseph does not know that while he is in this trial
and prison that eventually he's gonna end up
in second in command.
He doesn't know that that's going to happen,
but he's faithful anyway.
He's faithful anyway.
And we look at the passage of scripture
and we understand as we begin to piece things together
in the life of Joseph and we understand
that how he was sold into slavery
and we understand that how he was purchased by Potiphar
and then he's falsely accused and he ends up in prison
and then the butler and the baker,
they have disappointed,
they've offended their master, the Pharaoh,
and we find that they end up in the same prison
where Joseph is and God is using that
to allow these people to meet one another
and then Joseph makes a simple request, remember me,
but the butler forgets him for two years.
I believe that Joseph continued to be faithful.
I believe that Joseph continued to do
what was right before the Lord
and we find that as I would look at the truth
of chapter 41, that if the butler
had remembered Joseph immediately
and when he was restored to his place of butlership,
if he sits there and he says, hey, listen, Pharaoh,
I want you to know that there's this guy in prison,
his name is Joseph, he's a Hebrew
and we had dreams and we couldn't,
there was no one to interpret them
but he interpreted those dreams and they came to pass,
I think Pharaoh would have said that's nice.
I have magicians, I have people
that can interpret my dreams.
That's nice, thank you for sharing.
But two years pass and Pharaoh has a dream
and Pharaoh can find no one to interpret the dream.
And the butler says, I remember,
you're angry with me, you're angry with Baker,
you put us in prison, we had a dream.
There was a guy in prison that was able
to interpret the dreams and it came to pass
just as he said.
So at that moment in time, what does Pharaoh say?
Send for him, bring him here.
And we understand that as we look at Genesis 41
and following and we see all of these pieces
come together but Joseph didn't understand that.
The point this evening as we look at this passage
of scripture that we see that Joseph,
though ultimately God's hand was at work
and we have the entire record that he was living
moment by moment and day by day just as we are living
and we must have a level of confidence in our God
to know that he is working just like he was working
in Joseph's life.
I may not understand all of the ways
in which God is working.
I may not understand, you may not understand
all of the pieces if you will that God is placing
and orchestrating and what he's doing
but I trust this evening and I submit to you this evening
that our God knows what he is doing.
I don't always know, you don't always know
but we can rest in knowing that our God knows
and that should bring us great comfort
in the midst of trials and should enable us
to be faithful through the trials.
Why?
Because I'm trusting my Lord.
I'm walking with him day by day.
These unfortunate things have happened,
these trials, these difficulties, these adversities
but I know that God's in control
and I know that God has a purpose
and I'm going to be faithful.
I'm gonna rejoice through these trials
and I'm gonna be faithful because I'm gonna see
what God is going to do.
I mentioned in Proverbs 24 in verse number 10,
if thou faint in the day of adversity,
thy strength is small.
I want you to turn over to the New Testament if you will
in 2 Corinthians chapter four
as we seek to make some application this evening
from this portion of scripture.
This truth that we see in Genesis chapter number 40,
as we said this morning, we can,
it is possible that we can rejoice through trials.
It is possible that we can be faithful
in the.
midst of trials. We look in 2 Corinthians 4. We mention that the strength that's referenced
in Proverbs 24 and verse 10 is not a physical strength, but a spiritual strength. And notice
what the Bible tells us in 2 Corinthians 4. The Bible says in verse 1,
Therefore, seeing we have this ministry, as we have received mercy...
Notice the Bible says we faint not. We faint not. If thou faint in the day of adversity,
thy strength is small. Paul says, seeing that we have received this ministry, as we have
received mercy, we faint not. It's the idea of being faithful through the storm, through
the trial, through the difficulty, and we see it outlined for us here in 2 Corinthians
4. Notice in verse 2,
We have renounced the hidden things of dishonesty, not walking in craftiness, nor handling the
word of God deceitfully, but by manifestation of the truth, commending ourselves to every
man's conscience in the sight of God. But if our gospel be hid, it is hid to them that
are lost, in whom the God of this world hath blinded the minds of them which believe not,
lest the light of the glorious gospel of Christ, who is the image of God, should shine unto
them. For we preach not ourselves, but Christ Jesus the Lord, and ourselves your servants
for Jesus' sake. For God, who commanded the light to shine out of darkness, hath shined
in our hearts to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jesus Christ.
Now notice as we get further into this text, in verse 7 he says, But we have this treasure
in earthen vessels, that the excellency of the power may be of God, and not of us. He
says in verse number 8, We are troubled on every side, yet not distressed. We are perplexed,
but not in despair. Persecuted, but not forsaken. Cast down, but not destroyed. Always bearing
about in the body the dying of the Lord Jesus, that the life also of Jesus might be made
manifest in our body. For we which live are always delivered unto death for Jesus' sake,
that the life also of Jesus might be made manifest in our mortal flesh. So then death
worketh in us, but life in you. We having the same spirit of faith, according as it
is written, I believed and therefore have I spoken, we also believe and therefore speak.
And then notice it says, Knowing that he which raised up the Lord Jesus shall raise up us
also by Jesus, and shall present us with you. Again, we mentioned this morning about
the knowing this in James chapter number 1, and God wants us to know some things. Paul
will say in verse number 1 of chapter 5, For we know that if our earthly house of this
tabernacle were dissolved, we have a building of God and house not made with hands, eternal
in the heavens. And so Paul says, I know, I'm confident of this, and though I'm dealing
with being troubled in every side, though we're perplexed, though we're persecuted,
though we're cast down, I want you to understand that we're not distressed, we're not in despair,
and we're not forsaken, and we're not destroyed. Because I know who I serve. I know what God
is able to do. And we're going to be faithful. We faint not in verse number 1. Now notice
in verse 15, For all things are for your sakes that the abundant grace might through the
thanksgiving of many redound to the glory of God, for which cause we faint not. So we
see that a second time in this passage of scripture, that Paul says in verse number
1, We've received this ministry, as we have received mercy, we faint not. We see now in
verse number 16 that he says, For which cause we faint not. Now remember, Proverbs 24 and
verse 10, If we faint in the day of adversity, our strength is small. Paul says twice here,
we faint not. Again, the picture that we see of Joseph, of this continuing, of this
faithfulness through the trial, though he's in prison, he's been falsely accused, all
of these things are taking place, we find that he's still engaged. We find that he's
still inquiring, he's still ministering to others, he's still trusting God, he's still
proclaiming that, hey, interpretations belong to God. He's still evidently, as we look at
the passage, he's obviously walking with God and obeying God. In Genesis chapter 40,
and Paul is saying here, listen, we've dealt with some issues, we've had some adversity,
we've had some trials, but we faint not. Now notice the rest of verse number 16, But though
our outward man perish, and here's the key, yet the inward man is renewed day by day.
That's the spiritual strength that we need. That's the key to enabling us to be faithful
through trials. I don't know that I've ever met someone that says, I like trials, personally,
that I've ever met somebody that says that. And I'll be honest with you, that I am challenged
every time I read 2 Corinthians chapter number 12, because in verse number 10, Paul says,
therefore I take pleasure in infirmities, in reproaches, in necessities, in persecutions,
in distresses, for Christ's sake, why, for when I am weak, then am I strong. Paul had
an understanding about the purpose of God through trials and God working and God doing
what only God can do. And so as we look here at verse number 16, and we notice that Paul
says again for a second time in this short passage that we faint not, he says the outward
man may perish, but the inward man is renewed day by day. He then says this, our light affliction,
which is but for a moment worketh for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory,
while we look not at the things which are seen, but of the things which are not seen.
For the things which are seen are temporal, but the things which are not seen are eternal.
That God would help us to have an eternal perspective and not be so temporally focused.
But I want to just zero in for the last few minutes that we have this evening on this
truth in verse number 16 of how is it that your inward man, that my inner man can be
renewed day by day. How do we receive that spiritual strength to be faithful through
trials, to rejoice through trials? We looked at those three truths this morning on how
we can rejoice, but how is it that I can be faithful? I mean in the midst of difficulty,
in the midst of adversity, when we know that we've been falsely accused, when we know that
it's been kind of stacked against us so to speak, how can we be faithful? Can we be faithful?
Absolutely. We can be faithful. And we must have our inner man renewed day by day. I believe
that what Paul is referring here, referring to in this passage of Scripture with the inward
man being renewed day by day, is that personal walk with God. That spiritual strength that
comes from being with the Lord. I want you to think about two passages. We're going to
look at one in the book of Acts and then one in the book of Ephesians as we close this
evening. But I want to remind you of Acts chapter number 4. And in this passage of Scripture,
we looked at Acts 5 this morning. But in Acts chapter number 4, again, the religious
leaders are not happy with all that's taken place and the miracle of the healing of the
lame man in chapter number 3 and all of the results of that. And we find that the Bible
tells us that they were inquiring, they were questioning, interrogating if you will. Peter
stands up and John is there. And we find that Peter begins to speak and he makes that great
declaration in Acts 4 in verse 12, neither is there salvation in any other for there's
none other name under heaven given among men whereby we must be saved. And I want you to
think about the strength, spiritual strength of Peter to stand up in the face of this adversity
and this opposition and make this bold proclamation with regard to their continuing and following
the Lord. And the Bible says that they saw the boldness of Peter and John in verse number
13. These religious leaders, they saw, it was evident that the boldness, and it says
that they perceived that they were unlearned and ignorant men, they marveled. And they
noticed this as they took knowledge of them that they had been with Jesus. They'd been
with Jesus. And so when they're spending time with the Lord Jesus Christ, their inward man
is being strengthened and they have that spiritual strength that in the face of that adversity,
when those religious leaders are saying, listen, you cannot do this. You cannot speak
in this name. We're going to do this to you. If you continue, we find that Peter is able
to stand up with boldness. Why? Because he's been with Jesus. He's have, he has that spiritual
strength to be able to stand in that day of adversity. And notice in Ephesians chapter
number three, if you will, and we won't take time to look at the entire prayer that Paul
prays for the believers there at Ephesus, but the first aspect in which he prays will
be the focus of our attention to this particular verse of scripture this evening and with regard
to the content of the message, how can you be faithful through trials? Again, the trials
are going to come, the difficulties are going to come. How can we be, how can we be faithful?
Notice in Ephesians three and verse number 16, it says that he would grant you this jumping
right in the middle of this prayer in verse 14. It says, for this cause, I bow my knees
unto the father of our Lord Jesus Christ. So Paul is praying for the believers at Ephesus.
And here's how he's praying that he would grant you according to the riches of his glory.
notice to be strengthened with might, notice this, by his spirit in the inner man. Paul
is praying for these believers at Ephesus that they would be strengthened with might
by his spirit in the inner man. I would submit to you this evening that this is a prayer
that we ought to be praying one for another. Because as you deal with trials and as I deal
with trials, as we're praying intercessory prayer on the behalf of our brothers and sisters
in Christ, as we're praying that we would be strengthened with might by his spirit in
the inner man, that's what's going to enable us to faint not in that day of adversity,
in that day of trial, that we would not quit, that we would not give up, but that we would
continue that we would be faithful to our God even through the trials. So how are we
strengthened with might by his spirit in the inner man? Well it begins by spending
time with God. We mentioned already in Acts chapter number 4 it says that they had been
with Jesus. And when we think about spending time with the Lord, what are we doing? How
are we being strengthened? Well we spend time in his word. We spend time in his word. You
know we cannot overemphasize this evening how important God's word is in the life of
a believer. We need more of God's word, not less. We find that Job mentions about esteeming
the words of God more than is necessary food. Obviously all of us understand the importance
of eating and having the sustenance for the strength and if you begin to think about if
you go a period of time without eating, you begin to fast or maybe there's something that's
going on and you're not able to eat. You need that nourishment. You're exerting energy
and you can begin to feel that you need something to eat. You need some calories. You need some
energy. Have you ever felt that way? I didn't drink a lot of water today. I don't know how
you are. I typically drink a lot of water every day and for whatever reason today I
didn't drink a whole lot of water and I was sitting in my office and I just was like man
I need some water. I could start feeling that I was having a headache come on because I
didn't have a lot of water and I drank some water and it almost just kind of went away
immediately. I know Mr. Don doesn't like water at all but the reality is that I could just
feel I needed something. The way that you feel when you don't eat. You ever hear a kid
say I'm starving? You ever hear a kid say that? I mean they just ate a couple hours
ago. Joseph the other night, I promise you, we had gotten done eating and we weren't done
eating for 20 minutes and he's over there pulling out the bread to make a peanut butter
jelly sandwich and I was like son what are you doing? I mean we just ate dinner man.
And he just smiles as he's making the sandwich and then he says it's for tomorrow morning.
I'm going to the gym early and so I'm making it for tomorrow. So he's just, you know, he
wasn't, but sometimes he does eat right after we get done eating. You hear a kid say I'm
starving. I'm going to die. It's probably not true. But I want you to think about that
and then apply it spiritually. You know how many times we're starving spiritually because
we're not feasting on manna from heaven? Because we're not being strengthened in the inner
man through the Word of God. Listen, I say this with as much compassion as I can possibly
say it. So I hope that you receive it that way. A psalm and a proverb a day is not enough.
It just really isn't. And I say that with humility and with compassion. There's some
people that, you know, I read the psalm for today, I read the proverb for today and that's
good but it's not enough. What if you just had a piece of toast every day? Man, you'd
be malnourished. You need some food. You need some sustenance. Listen, we need God's Word.
And if we're going to be faithful through trials, the key is being strengthened in our
inner man. The key is feasting on the Word of God. The Bible tells us that newborn babes
that were to desire the sincere milk of the Word that we may grow thereby. The Bible tells
us but grow in grace and knowledge of the Lord and Savior Jesus Christ. The Bible tells
us that strong meat belongeth to them that are full age. We find that we must be students
of God's Word, that we must feast on the manna from heaven. And as we dig into God's Word
and the Holy Spirit of God uses the Word of God to strengthen our inner man and then we
face those trials and we face those difficulties and God is giving us the strength so that
we do not faint. So that we can be faithful through the trials. There's no doubt in my
mind this evening that you've experienced somewhere along your journey with Christ someone
that has fainted in the midst of a trial. This evening my purpose is not to criticize
them. My purpose is to say I don't want that to happen in my life. I want to be faithful
through trials. Can I tell you that the day to prepare for the trial is not the day the
trial begins? Preparation happens way, way before. You don't know when the trial is going
to come. That's why you need God's Word every day. I asked somebody this question. Sometimes
we treat God and we treat His Word like a spare tire. What do I mean by that? When was
the last time you checked your spare tire? For most people, not very often. Now some
people, car people, mechanics, you know, I don't ask them that question. They're like,
I checked it yesterday. I'm like, whatever. My car doesn't even have a spare tire. Seriously.
I bought it, the Kia that we have, it doesn't even have a spare tire. I looked in the back,
there's nothing there. They're like, oh yeah, you've got to pay extra for that. Isn't that
amazing? But what I mean is that, you know when you look for your spare tire? When you
have a flat. The person that doesn't regularly check their spare tire is all of a sudden
going to check for it when they have a flat tire. The time that we get into God's Word
is not when the trial comes. Say, oh man, I need God now. And I'm going to, no, no.
We've had that inner man being strengthened. So that trial comes and we have the strength
that God has given us because we've spent time in His Word and we've been faithful and
we've been diligent to study and to apply truth. And then the trial comes and we have
the strength for the trial. We're rejoicing in the midst of the trial because I know my
position in Christ. Why do I know my position? Because I've been in the Word. Why do I know
His power? Because I've been in the Word. Why do I know that He has a purpose? Because
I've been in the Word and I'm rejoicing and then I'm faithful through it and I see what
God isn't able to do. Listen, I'm thankful for the end of Joseph's life. I think most
believers are. They look at the life, the account of Joseph and they rejoice greatly.
Oh man, isn't that awesome? But he lived it day by day. And I'm thankful that in Genesis
40 he was faithful. He was faithful. God was orchestrating. He was moving pieces. He's
in control. And He was going to work in such a way to bring to pass, ultimately, His purpose
in Joseph's life to save much people alive, the Bible tells us. This evening, I don't
know what God's doing in your trial or in my trial, but I desire as we kind of combine
both messages today, I desire to rejoice through the trials. I don't want to be found complaining,
moping, dragging my lip on the ground. Woe is me. You have no idea how bad it is. I want
to rejoice. I serve a great God. I serve a God who's able to do anything. Nothing's too
hard for Him. I'm going to heaven. Remember what the songwriter said? I'm not discouraged.
Why? I'm heaven bound. Amen. How can you be doing wonderful in the midst of your... Because
I'm going to heaven. God wants us to be faithful. I'm thankful that He's faithful. Oh, that
God would help us in the midst of trials to be faithful. Let's pray. Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us. Thank You for the example of Joseph. Thank You as we can
compare Scripture with Scripture and look over to the New Testament and see the importance
of having our inner man strengthened. God, I pray that You'd help each of us daily in
our lives to understand how important it is that we feast on Your Word, that we spend
time with You daily, quality time, quantity time, that we get the Word of God in us so
that we can be strengthened in our inner man so that when those trials come, we can be
faithful. I thank You for the example tonight. I thank You for the admonition. Lord, I know
that each of us will face trials. And I pray that we'd rejoice through those trials, in
the midst of those trials, and that we would be faithful. I pray that You'd work in hearts
and lives as only You can. As we have a moment of invitation, I pray, Lord, that You'd move
and work. We'll give You the glory for what You'll do, for it's in Christ's name.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are out and eyes are closed.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano.
Maybe tonight you just want to come and ask God
to help you to be strengthened in your inner man,
maybe to commit to spending more time with Him
in His Word.
Maybe tonight your prayer is,
God, keep me faithful.
Help me to keep my eyes on You, looking unto Jesus,
the author and finisher of our faith.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.