Well, we'll be looking at verses one down through verse number 30.
And I sent a typo to Holly and told her it was through verse number 14.
And so if you're looking at the bulletin, there is a typo there.
And that is my fault.
We're going to look down through verse number 30 this evening.
And so if you have your Bibles there, Genesis chapter number 29.
Of course, we mentioned last week as we finished up Genesis chapter number 28, and we had the
opportunity to see a real change in the life of Jacob.
And we had mentioned that for so many years as we've studied the scriptures and you look
at his life and you study through the events, you find that there's really nothing in the
life of Jacob that he is concerned for other than himself.
And you find that he was concerned on how he could get the birthright, he was concerned
on how he could receive the blessing, and he's concerned about himself.
And we find that as he was given instruction to depart, to leave, and Isaac had given him
that charge and had blessed him at the start of Genesis chapter number 28.
We find that God appeared to Jacob at the end of chapter number 28.
And when he appeared to Jacob, we find that God gave him some very personal promises,
some very encouraging promises.
And we find that Jacob is changed.
When you leave the 28th chapter of the book of Genesis, you begin to see how that Jacob
is making some declarations, that Jacob is understanding some things about the Lord God
Jehovah.
No longer is God just the God of Abraham and Isaac, but he declares in verse number 21,
then, shall the Lord be my God.
And we spoke about the significance of that personal relationship and understanding that
it's not just the God of Abraham and the God of Isaac, but He's my God.
And we find that he's vowing a vow.
He makes a declaration.
He sets up the pillar, pours oil upon it there at Bethel.
He calls it the house of God.
He made a declaration that he understood that it was from the good hand of God that God
blessed him and God gave to him, and he committed to giving a tithe unto the Lord.
And we find that Jacob's life, really, there's a change, an obvious change in his perspective
as you end the 28th chapter.
It's interesting because as you enter into the 29th chapter, the Bible just simply begins
by saying, then Jacob went on his journey.
His journey continues.
And I want you to think this evening as we go through this passage of scripture and seek
to understand the historical context of what we're going to study and look at this evening,
I want you to think about our own walk with God, our journey, if you will, and how our
journey continues.
There's a time in which, as we'd use the New Testament vernacular, that we trust that
the Lord Jesus Christ is our personal Savior, that we were saved, and then we get to walk
with Him.
And we've been singing this year this theme song, I walk with the King, hallelujah.
Isn't it wonderful to be able to walk with the Lord Jesus Christ, to walk and to talk
with the King of kings and Lord of lords?
It's an absolute blessing, a unique privilege that we have.
And we find that Jacob, his journey is going to continue.
We find that Jacob, as you would study the remainder chapters of the book of Genesis,
really all the way through chapter number 49, you'll see tidbits throughout those chapters
with regard to the life of Jacob.
Some contain more information, such as the next couple, few chapters contain a whole
lot of information about the life of Jacob, and you'll get into some of those passages
as we enter into the section dealing with Joseph, where the primary focus is no longer
on Jacob, and it's on Joseph.
And Jacob, of course, still referenced in the 49th chapter of the book of Genesis.
You read his earthly journey with the Lord ends.
He dies.
And there's going to be some point in our life when our earthly journey with the Lord
ends.
Now, what blessing we have is that we understand the truth of being with Him for all of eternity.
And we understand that we shall see Him, and that the truth that Paul reveals to us to
be absent from the body is to be present with the Lord, and what great truth, encouraging
truth that is.
For Jacob, as we think about his journey and as we study this 29th chapter, the first 30
verses of it this evening, I want you to understand that his life unfolds, and there's some similarities
that we can see even in our life.
It's interesting.
There's some major life decisions that are made in Genesis chapter number 29, but yet
there's no reference whatsoever of Jacob praying.
Just not there.
There's nothing.
And there's a walk that we have.
Our journey continues with the Lord.
And as we have the whole canon of Scripture, and as we seek to learn what it is to walk
with the Lord Jesus Christ and how we are to walk with the Lord Jesus Christ, we begin
to incorporate the truth of God's Word into our lives so that we might have a walk that
is pleasing in His sight.
And as we notice here in Genesis chapter number 29, the Bible says, then Jacob went on this
journey and came into the land of the people of the east.
And notice, if you will, we'll use this for our title this evening, in verse number 10,
it says, and it came to pass when Jacob saw Rachel, the daughter of Laban, his mother's
brother, and the sheep of Laban, his mother's brother, that Jacob went near and rolled the
stone from the well's mouth and watered the flock of Laban and his mother's brother.
I've titled the message this evening from verse number 10, Jacob saw Rachel.
Of course, it's in this chapter that we read of the marriages, if you will, of Jacob, and
we'll study some things here.
If you are taking notes, notice with me, first of all, Jacob's arrival in Haran.
We understand that Jacob had left Bethel.
Remember he had left, according to chapter number 28 in verse number 1 and 2, that Isaac
tells him to go to Paddan Aram and to the house of Bethuel, thy mother's father, and
take thee a wife from thence of the daughters of Laban, thy mother's brother, according
to Genesis 28 in verse number 2.
We find that the Bible recorded for us that stop that he had at Beersheba.
It says, excuse me, he went out from Beersheba and went toward Haran in verse number 10,
and then the stop that he had in Bethel, as it was called according to verse number 19.
Of course, prior to that, the place was called Luz.
And we find that Jacob is now continuing on his journey.
He's continuing to go in the direction in which he had been instructed.
We find that this would reveal to us the obedience of Jacob to going to the place where he had
been instructed to go.
We find, as I mentioned last week, that Haran is the chief city of Paddan Aram, and that's
where we see the reference of Haran throughout these pages of Scripture.
But as we think about his arrival into the city of Haran, the Bible says that he came,
in verse number 1, into the land of the people of the east.
And notice the Bible tells us of his interactions as he arrives into the city, as he arrives
into Haran.
And the first interaction that is recorded for us, down through really verse number 12,
is his, excuse me, through verse number 8, are his interactions with these shepherds.
He arrives at the place, and the Bible says that he looked, in verse number 2, and behold
a well in the field, and lo, there were three flocks of sheep lying by it.
For out of that well they watered the flocks, and a great stone was upon the well's mouth.
It says in verse number 3, and thither were all the flocks gathered, and they rolled the
stone from the well's mouth, and watered the sheep, and put the stone again upon the well's
mouth in its place.
And so God's giving us some information with regard to the behavior of these shepherds,
to the mode by which they operate.
And we find, the Bible tells us, and they will give some information with regard to
this in verse number 8 as well, but these shepherds, they would all gather their flocks
together, and at a set time they would water all of the flocks once they arrived.
And we find that it tells us that they would roll that stone from the well's mouth, according
to verse number 3, they would water the sheep, and then they would return the stone again
to its place.
And so Jacob arrives, he's understanding some things, he sees these shepherds that
are there, and he begins to have an interaction with them.
Notice in verse number 4 that he says unto them, my brethren, whence be ye?
And they said, of Haran are we?
And there's not much interaction, not much discussion.
They give a simple answer to the question that was asked by Jacob, and he then pries
and probes, if you will, and he says to them, know ye Laban, the son of Nahor?
And they said, we know him.
Again, the conversation's not going real fast, real deep, right?
It's just kind of a, you asked a question, I gave you an answer.
And Jacob is interacting with these shepherds, and perhaps these shepherds, maybe by the
tone is what we're seeing here, maybe they were a little bit concerned as to who this
new guy is that's coming to town, what's going on, why is he asking questions, so on and
so forth.
And we find that Jacob then says in verse number 6, it says, and he said unto them,
is he well?
And they said, he is well.
And behold, Rachel his daughter cometh with the sheep.
And he said, now Jacob is responding, he says, lo, it is yet high day, neither is it time
that the cattle should be gathered together, water ye the sheep and go and feed them.
It's kind of interesting because he has this interaction in verse number 7, really you
don't see that there's any level of Jacob being shy whatsoever, he's going to give them
some instruction.
He says that it's high day.
day. It's not a time that the cattle, and that's a generic term, by the way. We would use the term
cattle to speak of cows, but this is a generic term to speak of livestock. And we see that,
speaking of the sheep in particular, and he says that they are to water the sheep and then go and
feed them. And notice what they say in verse number eight. We cannot, until all the flocks
be gathered together, until they roll the stone from the well's mouth, then we water the sheep.
And so they would wait, instead of opening the well and watering, they'd wait for all of the
flocks to gather, and they would then water the sheep, and then they would return the stone
according to what the operation or process was given to us in verse number three. Notice it says
in that while he yet spake with them, Rachel came with her father's sheep, for she kept them. And
it came to pass in verse number 10, when Jacob saw Rachel, the daughter of Laban, his mother's
brother, and the sheep of Laban, his mother's brother, that Jacob went near and rolled the stone
from the well's mouth and watered the flock of Laban, his mother's brother. And so now we see
the interaction, yes, with the shepherds, but now I want you to see the interaction with Rachel.
The Bible tells us, and he now has watered the flocks. It says that Jacob went near at the end
of verse number 10. He rolled the stone from the well's mouth and watered the flock of Laban,
his mother's brother. Now, he's brand new into the city, and he's interacted with these shepherds.
He's asked some questions. Why aren't you watering them? It's not a time for them to be gathered.
They're to be watered and then go feed them. And he's inquired about his family, and we find that
now Rachel comes. He, Jacob, takes it upon himself to remove that stone so that the flock could be
watered. And he waters the flock of Laban, his mother's brother. And Jacob kissed Rachel
and lifted up his voice and wept, according to verse number 11. I believe that there was great
joy. There was a measure of rejoicing in verse number 11. Remember, he had been sent out in
chapter number 28. He had been sent out from his house. He had been given direction as to
where to go and what to do. And now that he's arrived to the place where he's supposed to be,
now as he has been given that instruction to go to Bethuel or to the house of Bethuel,
thy mother's father, and take thee a wife from thence of the daughters of Laban,
thy mother's brother. And now I believe that Jacob is rejoicing. He kisses Rachel. He lifts
up his voice and wept. By the way, this isn't the way that someone would kiss someone here in
America. You have to understand the cultural aspects and what have you. And it's not just
that Jacob just, man, look, she's beautiful and kisses her, right? And it's not the way it works.
You've got to understand the cultural aspects and those greetings and what have you. In fact,
Laban and Jacob have a similar type of an embrace. And it says that Jacob told Rachel that he was
her father's brother in verse number 12, and that he was Rebekah's son. And she ran and told her
father. Now we find that it's now this interaction with Rachel is now giving her some insight as to
who this man is, this guy that just showed up. She comes to the well to water the flock, and
there's this new guy there. And he takes it upon himself to move the stone and to water the flock.
And the Bible tells us that now she has insight as to who this guy is. It's Jacob, and she ran and
told her father at the end of verse number 12. And verse 13 tells us that it came to pass when Laban
heard the tidings of Jacob, his sister's son, that he ran to meet him and embraced him and kissed him
and brought him to his house. And he told Laban all these things. In the first 12 verses of Genesis
chapter number 29, we see some interactions that Jacob has. His arrival to Haran, and we see these
interactions, the one at the well with the shepherds, the one at the well with Rachel.
And let me just say this. As we go on our journey with the Lord, we're going to have some interactions
with people. We're going to meet some people along the way. We're going to meet a variety of people.
We're going to have interactions with people, and we must be mindful of that. We also must be mindful
of the fact, and we don't see it here, and I'm just making some application as we think about
the parallels of Jacob's journey and our journey with the Lord and being the representatives that
we are, that in those interactions, that God has a purpose for those interactions. God has a plan
for those interactions, and we need to be careful, even as we mentioned in Sunday school this morning,
that we'd understand that God's purpose in those interactions is for us to be used of Him.
And what a joy it is that God would enable us, that He would involve us in His work.
We find that here, there's no doubt this introductory introduction and
greetings with these shepherds. Of course, there would be many years in which Jacob would be in
this region, and there'd be many more encounters with shepherds and what have you. But of course,
you think about the significance of this interaction with Rachel and how that those
things proceed, and we see the interactions lead to an invitation. The invitation is given,
it's not necessarily in verse number 13 where it's an actual invite that is given, but you notice
near the end of the verse that it says, "...and brought him to his house." And I see the hospitality
of Laban. We see also, no doubt, the relief of Jacob. Again, Jacob went out. He went out
really from his presence of his family, knowing that his brother desired to kill him, right?
Esau was ready to kill him. And you think about the departure there at the beginning of Genesis
chapter number 28, and I believe it was a great relief when he comes here and he interacts and
he meets Laban, and Laban then brings him to his house. And what a relief that would be. According
to verse number 14, the Bible tells us that he was there for one month. And Laban said to him,
"'Surely thou art my bone and my flesh.' And he abode with him the space of a month."
Remember when the truth was given in Genesis chapter number 27 about Rebekah telling him to
leave? Do you remember how long Rebekah said? A few days, right? You remember that? We know,
and we noted in that passage at the end of Genesis chapter 27, that those days turned into years.
But even in this initial stage of this initial departure, we find that he's there for a month.
And after that month, there's now some discussion that takes place between Laban and Jacob,
and it leads us to our second point this evening. Not only Jacob's arrival in Haran, but I want you
to notice Jacob's agreement with Laban. There's an agreement that is made, and we see how this
agreement, the details are provided to us in verses 15 through 20. Notice in verse 15,
Laban said unto Jacob, "'Because thou art my brother, shouldest thou therefore serve me for
not? Tell me, what shall thy wages be?' And Laban had two daughters. The name of the elder was Leah,
and the name of the younger was Rachel. Leah was tender-eyed, but Rachel was beautiful and
well-favored. And Jacob loved Rachel and said, "'I will serve thee seven years for Rachel,
thy younger daughter.' And Laban said, "'It is better that I give her to thee,
than that I should give her to another man. Abide with me.' And Jacob served seven years for Rachel,
and they seemed unto him but a few days for the love he had to her." As we note the details of
this agreement, we find that the question is asked by Laban in verse number 15, "'What shall
thy wages be?' And we find that in verses 16 and 17 that the truth is given to us with regard to the
two daughters of Laban, Leah and Rachel, and no doubt it would be in the best interest of Laban
to have his daughters married and understanding, again, some of the cultural aspects of those
things. And we find that the question that is asked is answered by Jacob in verse number 18,
where he says, "'I will serve thee seven years for Rachel, thy younger daughter.'" And we find that
it tells us that Jacob loved Rachel in verse number 18, and he's been given this truth to
Laban that, "'I will serve you for seven years.'" That's a long time. And he makes this commitment,
and we find that the details of the agreement, according to verse number 19, the terms of the
agreement are settled. I believe that they're agreed to, but we, of course, understand some
of what takes place in this passage of Scripture. Notice what Laban says in verse number 19. He says,
"'It is better that I give her to thee.'" Who's he speaking of when he says her? Rachel, right?
That was the question that was asked. Remember, when Laban said, "'What will your wages be?'
Jacob said, "'I will serve thee seven years for Rachel, thy younger daughter.'" And the Bible tells
us that Laban said, "'It is better that I give her to thee.'" He's speaking about Rachel to Jacob,
right? The follow? I know I'm kind of belaboring the point, but I am on purpose.
And the terms of the agreement are known and they're agreed to, and notice what Laban says.
He says, "'It is better that I give her to thee than that I should give her to another man.
Abide with me.'" So when he says, "'Abide with me,' that's
That's agreeing to the details that have already been provided.
Now let me ask you this question.
Did Laban know about the custom in their country that he refers to in verse number 26?
Did he know?
Laban knew about it, right?
Jacob didn't know about this custom, but Laban was aware of the custom.
Laban knows.
He says in verse number 26, it must not be so done in our country to give the younger
before the firstborn.
Did he know that in verse number 19 or was that just revealed to him afterwards?
He knew that.
He was well aware of what the custom and the culture where he lived and where he had raised
his family.
He was well aware of it.
But we find that as he's interacting with Jacob, he tells Jacob, it's better that I
give her to thee.
Abide with me.
And so Jacob served seven years for Rachel.
Again, that's a lengthy period of time.
And the Bible tells us, what a thought.
It says in verse number 20, and they, those seven years, they seemed unto him but a few
days.
Why?
For the love he had to her.
That's pretty good.
Amen?
All you guys that aren't romantic, you try to get something out of there, amen?
And figure it out.
But the reality is that he had such love.
It tells us in verse number 18 that Jacob loved Rachel.
And I believe that as Jacob is desiring to marry Rachel, as we see here in this passage
of Scripture, those seven years passed and it seemed like just some days to him.
Why?
Because it wasn't so much that he was just toiling in work.
It wasn't the monotony of the day.
It wasn't the task at hand.
It was the prize that was before him.
Does that make sense?
Right?
He's thinking, I got to get this work done and then I'm going to have a bride.
Kind of motivates you, right?
And Jacob is in this place of being motivated and he's working.
And as we will study, as we continue through the book of Genesis, we'll find that as the,
at the end of chapter number 30, the latter part, and of course, as you continue into
chapter number 31, you'll find that God blessed Laban for Jacob's sake.
And you'll read some of those things and no doubt Jacob was a hard worker.
How do we see that?
Well, as soon as he gets to the, to the well, what does he do?
He's like, why are you guys standing around?
It's not a time for the cattle to be gathered.
Like come on, let's, let's do what we're supposed to do, right?
That was his interaction with the shepherds, right?
And so no doubt Jacob was a hard worker.
He was diligent.
And I think that Laban found himself in a position where he is recognizing he's going
to have some free labor and he's also going to have a husband for his daughter.
Of course, all the while, he has Leah in mind, he has Leah in mind.
That is, Laban has Leah in mind.
And that's what we see in Jacob's agreement with Laban.
We see the details in verses 15 through 20, but I want you to see the deception in verses
21 through 30.
The Bible tells us in verse number 21 that Jacob said unto Laban, give me my wife for
my days are fulfilled that I may go in unto her.
And so we see that Jacob had fulfilled his end of the agreement.
He had served for seven years for Rachel.
We see that in verse 20, we see in verse 21 that he comes to Laban.
If I could use this terminology, it's payday.
I've fulfilled my responsibility and now it's time for me.
The agreement that we made is that I'm going to serve you for Rachel, and you said that
you would, it was better for you to give her to me than to another man, and so I'm ready
for my wife.
And we find that Laban gathered together all the men of the place and made a feast in verse
number 22.
Again, this would be customary for this time and this culture.
And you find that he's preparing for this wedding and all that's taking place.
All the while, Laban knows what he's doing.
Jacob has no idea what's going on.
I think Jacob has every thought that he's going to be marrying Rachel, the agreement
that was made.
And here we find that Laban's gathered together all the men of the place and made a feast
and it came to pass in the evening, look in verse 23, that he took Leah, his daughter,
and brought her to him.
And he went in unto her and Laban gave unto his daughter, Leah, his maid for a handmaid.
And it came to pass that in the morning, behold, it was Leah.
And he, Jacob, said to Laban, what is this thou hast done unto me?
Did not I serve with thee for Rachel?
Wherefore then hast thou beguiled me?
That's an interesting situation.
I'm just going to leave it at that.
But I'm going to notice in verse number 26, I want you to think about this this evening
and I hope it's helpful for us.
I've meditated upon this and I think that there's something really important for us
to glean.
It says that Laban said, it must not be so done in our country to give the younger before
the firstborn.
Isn't it interesting the verbiage that Laban uses?
Why is it that the verbiage that Laban uses is of such interest to us?
Well, because in Jacob's own experience, there was a situation with the younger and the firstborn.
And I think about the custom that is explained in verse number 26, and I think about the
use of that word firstborn, and I think about Jacob hearing those words when Jacob, listen,
I think Jacob's probably not a very happy individual in verse number 25, okay?
Would you agree?
When he goes to Laban and he says to Laban, what is this that thou hast done unto me?
I think there's some emotion behind that, all right?
I think that he's probably pretty upset about what's transpired.
He's very confused as to what's transpired.
I think there's a measure of emotion.
He's irritated.
He says, did not I serve with thee for Rachel?
Wherefore then hast thou beguiled me?
And Laban begins to explain, and he provides this explanation that it must not be so done
in our country to give the younger before the firstborn.
And I just wonder, when Jacob heard that word firstborn, I wonder if it had an impact in
his life.
I wonder if perhaps he had been mindful.
You'll remember as we've studied here through Genesis chapter 29 at this point, there's
no reference whatsoever of Jacob explaining to Laban or to Rachel why he was there in
the first place.
There's no explanation whatsoever.
And we know all that has transpired in the life of Jacob, and we come to this place and
we see that Jacob is in this situation and he hears these words and he hears about the
custom.
Now why am I making this focus and this emphasis here?
Well, I believe that as we journey with the Lord, that God seeks to teach us things, that
God seeks to deal with us and to help us in our journey with Him.
Some have given the idea of Genesis 29 that this is a great example of sowing and reaping
and so on and so forth, and you understand how Jacob deceived and he was a deceiver and
all that he did with the birthright and the blessing and what you do, what you sow, you're
going to reap and so on and so forth, and certainly there's a measure of that in this
passage of Scripture.
But I also believe that as you look at Jacob in this passage of Scripture and you consider
all that has transpired and you understand especially the end of chapter number 28 and
the change in Jacob's life, that yes, there is a measure of the sowing and reaping principle
in view here, but I also believe that it's a situation where God is teaching Jacob some
important life principles.
I believe that Jacob is being taught by God the importance of seeking the face of God.
I believe that he's learning some things.
See, Jacob is in this position where he's, again, as I mentioned by way of introduction,
there's no reference in Genesis chapter 29 of Jacob praying about any of these decisions,
about Jacob praying about any of these agreements.
And no doubt as we journey in our life with the Lord, there are times and perhaps as we
started our journey that maybe we didn't pray about things the way that we pray about things
now.
Maybe there are seasons in our life where we don't pray about things as often as we
do at other times, and so God is teaching Jacob some truth here, and Jacob, no doubt,
I believe that this is one of the things that God would use in the life of Jacob to really
humble him.
I think about the brothers of Joseph.
Do you remember when the brothers of Joseph will get to it in, I don't know how many months,
but we'll get to it eventually.
But we think about the interaction with Joseph and his brothers, and you think about the
guilt and the conviction that they have as they stand before Joseph, and Joseph doesn't
reveal himself to them quite yet, and he's going through the process, and we find that
the visit is there, and all that takes place, and you'll remember the passage of Scripture,
the second visit, and all that's taking place, and of course as we go through and you find
reveals himself, but you know,
before he ever revealed himself,
there was a measure of brokenness in the lives
and the hearts of the people, his brothers,
and we believe, as you study throughout
the portions of scripture, and you see what's taking place,
that their heart was breaking for Benjamin, remember?
How is it, how are we gonna go back to dad?
I mean, this is going to absolutely destroy him.
He's gonna go down to the grave.
They're concerned, the brothers of Joseph are concerned,
and listen, did they have any concern
on how they were gonna go to dad
with the coat of many colors that was dipped in blood?
They didn't have any concern whatsoever, did they?
They get that coat of many colors,
and they come to dad, and what do they say?
Do you know whose this is, right?
And then what they do?
And the reality is that they had no remorse whatsoever.
They knew exactly where Joseph was,
what they had done, what had transpired,
and they didn't care how it would impact their father.
But the reality is that years later,
through some circumstances, God works and God breaks them.
I believe that God is using this in the life of Jacob
to break him, to bring him to a greater level of humility.
We don't see all of it in the next couple of chapters.
There's a number of things that continue
in the life of Jacob that are challenges and difficulties
with this new walk with the Lord that he has
and all that's taking place.
And so we find that he's given an explanation
with regard to the custom,
and the Bible tells us in verse number 27,
notice what Laban says,
fulfill her week, and we will give thee this also
for the service which thou shalt serve
with me yet seven other years.
So here's what Laban is saying in verse number 27,
the week of festivities for the marriage to Leah
were to be fulfilled.
That's what he refers to in verse 27,
when he says fulfill her week,
he's referring to those seven days,
that week of festivities with regard to the marriage,
fulfill that for Leah,
and we will give thee this also for the service,
which thou shalt serve with me yet seven other years.
So seven more years, and you can have Rachel.
As your wife.
Now notice it says this in verse 28,
and Jacob did so and fulfilled her week,
and he gave him Rachel his daughter to wife also,
and Laban gave to Rachel his daughter Bilhah his handmaid
to be her maid,
and it says that he went in also unto Rachel,
and he loved also Rachel more than Leah,
and served with him yet seven other years.
And so Jacob really, as you look at the passage
and see the way that it unfolds,
he marries Rachel,
he confronts Laban about the deception,
and we find that Laban says, all right, fulfill her week,
and I'll give you Rachel,
but you gotta serve seven more years,
he fulfills the week,
he then is married to Rachel,
and then he is going to serve for seven more years
according to verse number 30 for Rachel.
And so think about Laban,
and think about what's taking place here,
Laban really sees the opportunity
to get 14 years of basically free labor, right?
And his older daughter,
the Bible tells us that she was tender-eyed
in verse number 17 and Rachel was beautiful,
he now has a means, a way
in which he gets to get both of his daughters married,
which again would be a desire of a dad of daughters.
Remember, think about this truth,
who was it that brought the sheep to the well?
It was Rachel, right?
So no doubt Laban was a place
where he wanted to have his daughters married,
he needed some free labor,
and so this deception takes place.
And we think about this deception
and we think about this situation
and we can offer all sorts of opinions,
and again, there's definitely an aspect
of sowing and reaping that's here,
there's an aspect in which God is molding and shaping
and through the interactions that we deal with in life
and through the experiences that we have
as we journey with the Lord,
as we walk with the Lord, God's growing us.
And sometimes he grows us through situations
that are less than desirable.
I don't like being deceived, do you?
I've never been deceived at this level, amen?
Mark laughed, I don't think any of you
have been deceived at this level, amen?
But the reality is that none of us like to be deceived.
But as we seek to journey with the Lord,
we're going to have experiences
where they're less than desirable experiences.
And how do we respond to those situations?
What do we do in those circumstances?
How is it that as we look at the life of Jacob
and we can see the historical context,
we see what happens, we understand,
we can follow the journey of Jacob
and we'll see as we get into our next message,
really probably a couple of messages
of all of his children and the sons
and you see all that takes place.
But I really want us to think about
as we could use a parallel in closing this evening
of really our journey with the Lord.
Listen, our journey with the Lord isn't always easy.
Have you found that to be so?
There's difficulties that we face.
There are challenges along the way.
As New Testament believers, I'm so thankful,
as I mentioned by way of introduction,
that we have the whole canon of Scripture
and we have truth that we can run to
and we can seek the face of God
and we can know the will of God
and we can understand what God's plan is
and we can follow it.
But there's still some difficulties that we deal with
and how we must trust him and how we must follow him
and though we might be wronged
and though we might be deceived
and though we might have adversity,
that we keep our eyes on the Lord
and we keep pushing forward,
pressing forward, onward.
As we look throughout the Word of God,
there's really not a Bible character
that we would refer to as being
some type of a hero of the faith,
someone that their life is worth studying and emulating,
but that did not have problems.
And this evening, as we think about our journey,
listen, there are some that paint the idea
of a Christian life being a bed of roses
and just trust Jesus
and all your problems are gonna go away.
No, no, you trust Jesus
and he's with you through all of your problems.
Isn't that precious?
I understand that man desires
for all of his troubles to go away.
But we live in a sin-cursed world, right?
Jacob, the very first experience
after he leaves the place
where he met the Lord there in Bethel
and after he'd made the vows and the commitments
and after he gets to Haran
and he meets Rachel and he meets Laban
and all that takes place,
seven years, he's deceived
and it's a great level of deception.
They're trials and difficulties that we face in life.
Someone that said that the trust Christ
and they've explained and tried to paint the picture
that the Christian life is like a bed of roses,
the reality is that knowing, think about this truth.
All men have problems.
All mankind has problems, right?
Have you ever thought in your life this thought,
I don't know how they do it without Christ?
You've had that thought, have you not?
You see people that suffer, you see people that struggle,
you see people that deal with adversity,
but so do we, but we have Christ.
We have the Lord with us and he sustains us
and he helps us and he guides us
and he has purposes and he's growing us
and he's molding us and listen,
sometimes the molding process isn't very comfortable.
Sometimes he uses some things
like using that phrase firstborn
where it's a flood of memories that must come back
in the heart of Jacob and the mind of Jacob
of all that he did to Esau
and how he deceived Esau
and all that took place and all that transpired
and no doubt there would be some recollection
of those things and God will use those types of things
in our lives to conform us to the image of his dear son
and I find that in the life of Jacob
as we chronicle his journeys, as we chronicle his life
and we trace his steps,
that there are definitely some parallels for us.
This evening, it is a joy to walk and talk with the king.
It is an absolute joy to know the Lord Jesus Christ
as our personal savior
but our problems don't go away overnight
but we have the Lord to help us through our problems.
Listen, it's interesting that even though Jacob
doesn't pray, in fact, it's a while before Jacob
really prays and seeks the face of God,
there's a lot of things that take place.
We're at 14 years right now.
The end of chapter number,
well, we're at seven years and a week
and then he's gonna serve for seven more years
and by the end of the chapter,
you're gonna be near 14 years
because he's going to say, I'm ready to depart.
So he's fulfilled that other seven years
by the end of the chapter
and still there's no record of Jacob praying at that point
but you know what's interesting?
God continued to bless Jacob.
Laban recognized the blessing that God had put in his life
because of Jacob.
God always fulfills His promises.
And God promised that He would be with Jacob and He would bless Jacob.
And He did.
And what a blessing that is.
This evening, we're all at a different place of our journey with the Lord.
But wherever you are, wherever I am in our journey with the Lord, I would say this, there
are a number of interactions that we're going to have with all kinds of people.
We're going to have various experiences, some that are less than desirable.
We're going to be hurt.
We're going to be deceived.
But through it, on our journey, God is molding us and shaping us and helping us to be who
we're supposed to be in Christ.
Remember that song, He's Still Working on Me?
See, He created all of the universe in just six days, right?
Powerful.
But see, He's still working on me, and He's still working on you.
And by the way, we ought to be thankful that He's working on us, amen?
And He's, in only the way that He can, as the potter with the clay, He's shaping us.
And sometimes there's some rough edges that have to be taken care of, and God has His
ways of taking care of those things.
And so as we journey with the Lord, help us to keep our eyes on the Lord.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
Thank You for the day.
Thank You for the blessings.
As we think about the life of Jacob, we chronicle his life, we trace his steps, we see the events.
I hope tonight that we could take, by way of application, some of this parallel of our
own journey with You, that we'd learn some things not to do, and we'd learn some things
to do.
God, that You'd help us to seek Your face, that You'd help us to obey You.
Such a blessing to have the whole canon of Scripture.
And Lord, I pray that You'd be pleased with our lives, that we'd walk worthy as the believers
in Ephesus are challenged to do so.
I pray that You'd move and work in these moments of invitation as only You can, and
we'll thank You for it.
In Christ's name we pray.