with the thought the real theme of the series being the Lord is my
dot dot dot was kind of the the series for about 15 weeks or so on Wednesday
evenings
and we dealt with the fact that about six weeks ago the Lord is my exceeding
joy
and after that message Miss Lorraine came to me and said do you know the song
the Lord is my exceeding joy and I said I didn't know there was a song
the Lord is my exceeding joy and so she sang a little bit of it to me back there
after the service on that Wednesday evening
and I'm thankful that you're able to sing the entirety of it this morning
certainly a blessing
and I said this during that message about six weeks ago listen there are a
lot of things that people try to find joy and happiness in in this world
and but when we understand that Jesus
is my joy he is my exceeding joy listen he never changes he's the same yesterday
and today and forever
and we have circumstances that change you get new things that get old and they
break and they wear down and
whatever it might be but the reality is that if he is my joy then I am able to
have he said that my joy might remain in you
and that your joy might be full as I read that verse from John 15
and what a tremendous blessing thank you for that song
this morning the book of second Kings this morning second Kings chapter number
five
second Kings chapter number five and
a couple of weeks ago we dealt with the subject matter of the proclamation
of Jethro and then last week we dealt with the proclamation of Rahab this
morning
we're gonna deal with address the subject matter of the proclamation of
Naaman here from second Kings chapter number five let me say this by way of
introduction I am thankful
to live in a country where the gospel has been faithfully proclaimed
and the reality is that the United States of America is a place in which
the gospel has been
readily available that it has been preached and it's been
delivered from one generation to another it does not mean that everyone within
our nation has heard the gospel or that everyone within our nation is saved we
know that not to be the case
but I'm thankful to be in a land where the gospel is known
I'm thankful to be in a land today we're still today
we can go we have the freedom to be able to preach the gospel of the Lord Jesus
Christ to those
that we would come into contact with and that is a tremendous blessing you know
there are places around the globe today
that people have never one time heard the name of Jesus
the gospel is not declared in a number of those lands around the globe today
then you can look at some lands today where there are some believers there
some Christians
but they do not have the freedom to faithfully
and freely share the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ
just openly with those that they come into contact with
they face great danger they face great levels of persecution
and we understand this morning that we have a mandate from the Lord a command
from the Lord
to make him known to preach the gospel to every creature
now whether we have the freedom from a government to do that or not
doesn't really change the command that we've been given
but I would say this living in a place where we understand the command that God
has given
but also coupled with the fact that we have the freedom to proclaim it
we better take advantage of that and we better be careful
and be diligent to be able to preach the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ
as we come to second Kings chapter number five were introduced to a man by
the name of Naaman
thus the title of the message the proclamation of Naaman
but were introduced to a man by the name of Naaman who's Assyrian
and he does not as we look at the passage of scripture he does not know
Jehovah God he does not know the God of the Bible
and at the onset of this passage of scripture
and I'm thankful that though he was in a situation in a land where he did not
know
the Lord that through some very divine circumstances God
allowed for this man to know
who he is I'm thankful this morning that God
wants to make himself known to his creation
God wants to make himself known to mankind
God is a loving God he
died for the sins of the world and he desires to make himself known
and I'm thankful that as we look at this passage of scripture
that this man Naaman will understand who God is notice with me
as we begin reading in second Kings chapter number five
and as we're introduced to this man notice how he is described the Bible
says in verse number one now Naaman
captain of the host of the king of Syria
was a great man with his master an honorable
because by him the Lord had given deliverance into Syria
he was also a mighty man in valor
but he was a leper he was a leper
we look at the description that is provided to us in verse number one
we see that he's described as being the captain of the host of the king of Syria
a great man with his master the Bible says that he's
honorable the Bible tells us that he's a mighty man in valor
the Bible tells us that he is a leper though the Bible does not say this in
verse number one I believe it would be accurate for us to be able to say
that he did not know the Lord he did not know the Lord
we find as we look at this passage of scripture we see what's taking place we
find that in verse number two
God introduces to us and reveals to us some circumstances that had transpired
that God was going to use for his honor for his glory notice in verse number two
the Bible says that the Syrians had gone out by companies
and had brought away captive out of the land of Israel
a little maid and she this little maid this servant girl this
captive the Bible says that she waited
on Naaman's wife now as we look at just that statement
before we get into the interaction that God gives us here between Naaman and
Elisha
I believe that it's important that we recognize a few important truths as we
look at this verse of scripture
and see what this little maid this little servant girl this
little Israeli what she says
to her master to Naaman's wife
the Bible says in verse number three that she said unto her mistress
would God my Lord were with the prophet that is in Samaria now she's speaking
of Naaman and she says would God
that Naaman were with the prophet that is in Samaria that's
Elisha and notice what the Bible says
the Bible says that he Elisha would recover him
of his leprosy as we look at this text of scripture were introduced here to
this
little servant girl this little maid she's
unnamed but we find that God would use her in a great way
as we look at the circumstances surrounding
this little maid ending up in the home of
Naaman we could look at it from the perspective of saying these are
unfortunate circumstances the Bible tells us that the Syrians had gone out
by companies
and they brought away captive out of the land of Israel
and this little maid came back as a captive
because of this military conquest that took place
and if you were the parents of that little girl you would probably be
disappointed
you would have heart that would be heavy
and you would look at that circumstance and we could look at it as being this is
unfortunate
but I want you to understand this morning that our God is sovereign
I want you to understand this morning that our God has a plan
and I'm thankful that God always has a plan
and I'm thankful this morning that as we consider the character in the nature in
the attributes of our God
that our God is a God who is gracious
our God is a God who is merciful and he allows this little maid this little girl
to be to be taken captive
and to end up a servant to Naaman's
wife. Naaman we've already been introduced in verse number one
with regard to the the description that is provided to us but the Bible
ends and says that he was a leper
at the end of verse number one and it's because of this
this disease this health concern
that this little maid after some period of time as she experiences and
understands what's taking place
the Bible says that this little maid she makes this statement in verse number
three as she's speaking to Naaman's wife
she says would God my Lord were with the prophet
that is in Samaria for he would recover him
of his leprosy. She was so convincing
as she spoke to the wife of Naaman
that we find that action takes place immediately
after she makes this known it says that one went in in verse number four
and told his Lord saying thus and thus said the maid
that is of the land of Israel. Now can you imagine how God would use this little
maid we don't know her name we don't know anything about her
but we know that she was faithful to stand up and speak up for the Lord
Amen. She's a
servant. Someone could easily say to her hey
hey no one asked you to speak right
but she stood up and she spoke up and
she speaks about the situation she had confidence
I believe not only in Elisha but in the God
God of Elisha.
As you begin to think about the miracles of Elijah
and the miracles of Elisha,
we understand that God would use those men
in miraculous ways just as he used so many of God's people,
just as he would continue to use us even today,
but it's God who does the work.
When we think about the miracles of Elijah,
when we think about the miracles of Elisha,
that's God's power being displayed
and he's using those individuals.
As we look here and we find that the servant comes in
and says to his master,
thus and thus said the maid that is of the land of Israel.
And notice now the Bible says that the king of Syria
gets involved in verse number five,
and it says, and the king of Syria said, go to go.
And I will send a letter unto the king of Israel.
And he departed and took with him 10 talents of silver
and 6,000 pieces of gold and 10 changes of raiment.
I mean, a large sum of money,
really a gift, if you will, a reward.
And he sends this and he sends this letter.
So the king of Syria, hearing all that has transpired
and understanding the place of Naaman,
he writes this letter to the king of Israel
and the king of Israel receives the letter.
Now he's not so excited about the letter that he receives
for the Bible tells us in verse number six,
and he brought the letter to the king of Israel saying,
now, when this letter has come unto thee,
behold, I have therewith sent Naaman my servant to thee,
that thou mayest recover him of his leprosy.
Now there's no way that the king of Israel
is going to even begin to know
how he might be able to do something like this.
The Bible says that as receiving this letter
in verse number seven, it came to pass
when the king of Israel had read the letter
that he rent his clothes and said,
am I God to kill and to make alive
that this man doth send unto me
to recover a man of his leprosy?
Wherefore, consider, I pray you,
and see how he seeketh a quarrel against me.
The king of Israel is beside himself.
He doesn't know what to do with the circumstances
that are unfolding, and he says,
what am I supposed to do about this?
And we find that Elisha, according to verse number eight,
he hears about what has taken place.
The king of Israel is overwhelmed.
Elisha is informed, he's understanding what's taking place.
It says in verse number eight, and it was so,
when Elisha, the man of God,
had heard that the king of Israel had rent his clothes,
that he sent to the king saying,
wherefore hast thou rent thy clothes?
Now, notice what Elisha says.
Let him, speaking of Naaman, come now to me,
and he shall know that there is a prophet in Israel.
Now, I want you to understand this morning
that not only would Naaman know
that there's a prophet in Israel,
but most importantly, he would know God.
And as we look at the portion of scripture,
as we see what's taking place,
and we've mentioned as we've studied this year
dealing with how great our God is,
and man, we sang some wonderful songs this morning,
our great savior, and what a great savior he is,
and how great thou art,
and thinking about the plan that God has,
and rejoicing in the fact of his creation,
and seeing his greatness,
and then understanding his plan of redemption,
and his greatness that is revealed therein,
and then understanding as we sing that fourth verse
of how great thou art,
that one day he's coming back,
and oh, how great our God is,
but we understand this morning
that even as we recognize how great he is,
we must declare how great he is,
and we see this proclamation on the part of Naaman,
and notice with me if you're taking notes this morning,
number one is we've gotten into the interaction,
but now between Naaman and Elisha,
I want you to notice with me number one,
consider what Naaman expected, what he expected.
Everyone has expectations, everyone has expectations.
You go out to eat somewhere,
you have an expectation as to what you're gonna receive.
You go have a meeting with someone,
you have an expectation, you just have expectations.
I often say to my children,
and to those that I have opportunity
to have influence in that we should manage expectations,
that we should communicate with people
so that we could manage their expectations, why?
Because if they come in with high expectations
and they're not realized,
then people can be greatly disappointed,
and we find that people have expectations in life,
and we find that as we look at this text of scripture
that Naaman, he expected something to happen
as he entered into, now remember,
why he's going to Elisha in the first place.
He's going to Elisha in the first place
because the little servant, the little maid
that was waiting on his wife
that had been taken captive from Israel,
she says, would to God my Lord,
remember we read it already,
was with the prophet that is in Samaria, why?
For he would recover him of his leprosy.
And so he goes expecting to be recovered of his leprosy,
but really his expectation is revealed to us
as we look at the text of scripture,
but notice how the interaction begins.
In verse number nine, the Bible says,
so Naaman came with his horses and with his chariot,
and he stood at the door of the house of Elisha.
Now, I hope this morning in your mind's eye
that you can see the picture of this unfolding,
this leper, this man from Syria that's heard this message,
he's been convinced based upon what the little maid says,
and the king of Syria sends a letter
to the king of Israel, Elisha says,
let him come to me and don't be troubled,
let him come to me, and we find that now this man,
he's there, Naaman, the Bible says,
with his horses and with his chariot,
and he stood at the door of the house of Elisha.
Now, right from the beginning,
if you go to somebody's house
and you know that it's the person
that you're looking to have an interaction with,
what do you expect?
Expect they're gonna come and answer the door.
Right, I mean, it'd be kind of an easy level of expectation,
but we find that in the text of scripture,
the Bible tells us in verse number 10
that Elisha sent a messenger, he sent a messenger.
Now, Naaman's traveled, he's come to this place,
he's heard what the little maid said,
and he's convinced, and he comes,
and Elisha even said to the king,
let him come, that he would know
that there's a prophet in Israel,
and now as Naaman is standing there
before the house of Elisha, he's at the right place.
He's not at the wrong house, he's not at the wrong address,
he wasn't given bad directions, he's at the right place.
And Elisha sends a messenger.
And here's what Elisha says to that messenger.
The messenger comes with a simple set of instructions.
Notice in verse number 10.
Go and wash in Jordan seven times,
and thy flesh shall come again to thee,
and thou shalt be clean.
That's not complicated, is it?
That's pretty straightforward.
I mean, a very simple set of instructions.
He tells him where to go, to the Jordan,
it's a specific place, he would know where that place is.
We find that he tells him to dip in the Jordan,
to wash in the Jordan, seven times.
There's a specific number of times.
He doesn't just, it's not instruction
that is like some of the manuals that you read today,
and you're saying, I don't know,
like, should I turn this a different way?
It doesn't make any sense.
No, no, go to a specific place, wash seven times,
and here's what the result will be.
Thou, notice it says, thy flesh shall come again to thee,
and thou shalt be clean.
This is not what Naaman expected.
Not for one second is this what Naaman expected.
Naaman, in fact, is angry.
The Bible describes it this way, that he was wroth.
In verse number 11, the Bible says,
but Naaman was wroth and went away.
Notice what he says, behold, I thought.
Now, here's where the text of Scripture
reveals to us what he, Naaman, expected to happen.
In verse number 11, he begins to share
with those servants that are there with him
after he hears what the messenger from Elisha says.
He says, here's what I thought was going to happen.
He, who's he speaking of?
He's speaking of Elisha.
He, Elisha the prophet, he will surely come out to me
and stand and call on the name of the Lord, his God,
and strike his hand over a place and recover the leper.
So he expected that there's gonna be some show.
I mean, there's gonna be, Elisha's gonna come out
and he's gonna raise up his hands
and he's gonna call on the Lord, his God,
and he's gonna strike his hand and bam,
he's gonna be healed of his leprosy.
I mean, that's what he's expecting.
Now, I could understand why he'd have that expectation.
I could understand why Naaman coming to the house of Elisha
would have this expectation of how this would play out.
I mean, can you imagine being a leper?
Can you imagine being in that situation?
The Bible doesn't tell us,
but I think about the position of Naaman.
I think that they probably did everything they could do
in order to deal with this issue of leprosy
with zero success.
Do you remember the woman in the gospel accounts
that had the issue of blood for 12 years?
The Bible says that she spent everything,
she tried everything by going to the medical professions
to be healed with no help whatsoever.
And she said, if I could just touch the hem of his garment.
And Jesus says, who touched me?
Who touched me?
And when she touched the hem of his garment, what happened immediately?
She was healed.
She was made whole.
Naaman had some expectation and I think that he's probably done everything.
Remember he's the captain of the host and remember that as we look at what's taking
place, I mean the king of Syria writes a letter on his behalf.
No doubt all of the remedies and all of the things have been exhausted that they could
do and he has this expectation that the man of God, Elisha, he's going to come out and
he says, here's what I thought, but he's angry.
Why?
Because it doesn't happen like he says.
He continues and he says this in verse number 12.
He says, are not Abana and Farfar rivers of Damascus better than all the waters of Israel?
May I not wash in them and be clean?
So he turned and went away in a rage.
Instructions were not complicated.
Very simple instructions.
He begins to lean on his own understanding.
He says, we've got rivers back in Syria that are better than this river.
The Jordan, I'm going to dip in that water?
We've got cleaner, better waters that I could dip in and be clean if that's all it is.
I mean can you see?
I mean he's angry.
The Bible says that he's in a rage at the end of verse number 12.
He's angry over what's taking place, but we notice, we consider in the text of Scripture
as this interaction unfolds for us, we consider first of all what Naaman expected.
Number two, if you're taking notes, I want you to consider with me what Naaman experienced.
Notice what he experienced.
He's ready to leave.
He's wroth.
He's in a rage, but there's a servant that comes to him in verse number three and I'm
thankful for the plea of this servant.
The servant pleads with his master and it says in verse 13 that his servants came near
and spake unto him and said, my father, if the prophet had bid thee do some great thing,
wouldst thou not have done it?
So he's pleading with Naaman and he's saying if the instruction were to do some great thing,
you would have followed it.
You would have done it.
And he says at the end of verse number 13, how much rather then when he saith to thee,
wash and be clean.
This servant, again, we don't have the name of this individual in verse number 13 who
speaks to Naaman, he's pleading with him and he, through some logical explanation, convinces
Naaman to follow the instruction.
So Naaman had to humble himself.
Naaman had to follow the instructions that were provided.
He had to stop leaning on his own understanding.
He had to submit to the instruction that has been provided.
You know how often today people ignore and refuse to obey the simple truth of the gospel?
Because they're leaning on their own understanding.
It's got to be something more to it.
I mean, there's got to be something more I have to do.
I've heard that so many times.
Listen, there's nothing you can do to save yourself.
There's nothing you need to do.
There's nothing that you can do.
You can't help God save you.
He did it all.
I'm so thankful for that wonderful Bible truth.
And you know what people have to do?
They have to humble themselves.
They have to humble themselves that they're going to stop believing whatever it was that
they believed beforehand, stop believing that there's some better way, some other way.
They have to submit.
Listen, there was only one way.
I would argue until I had no breath left in me that there was only one way for Naaman
to be healed of his leprosy.
He could have dunked in that Jordan five times.
He's not going to be healed.
He could have decided that he's going to do...
There was one way that Naaman was going to be healed of his leprosy.
Why?
Because the man of God was speaking what God, the Lord, told him to speak.
And I could say to you this morning, and I understand that as we live in this ever-changing
culture that it's becoming less and less popular to stand and proclaim that Jesus is the only
way, but I tell you based upon the authority of God's precious Word that Jesus is the only
way.
There's no other name under heaven given among men whereby we must be saved.
And this morning as we look at this text of Scripture and we see what Naaman experienced,
this servant comes and pleads.
I mean, Naaman's ready to leave.
I can see him.
I mean, he's a man that's in charge.
I mean, he's a leader.
He's ready to get everything and leave and go back and he's angry.
And this servant pleads with him and he says, listen, how much rather than when he sayeth
to thee, wash and be clean.
And then the Bible says that then, notice verse 14, then went he down and dipped himself
seven times in Jordan.
Notice the next phrase.
This is so important for us to understand, according to the saying of the man of God.
He humbled himself and he obeyed that which he had been told to do from the man of God.
The Bible tells us in verse number 14 that he does this and it says at the end of verse
14, notice what it says, and his flesh came again like unto the flesh of a little child.
And then notice the last phrase, and he was clean.
He was clean.
What an experience.
I mean, as I look at the circumstances surrounding this event in 2 Kings chapter 5, as God would
give us the record of this man Naaman and noticing what he expected and his disappointment
and his anger and his rage and his plan to depart and how God used a servant back home
in Syria to say, would to God my Lord, we're in Israel there with the prophet of God for
he would heal him of his leprosy.
And then there's another servant that says, listen, why don't you just follow what the
man of God says?
And we find that Naaman humbles himself.
I mean, you see him as he gets down into the Jordan River.
I mean, as he humbles himself and he obeys what the man of God says, he gets down into
the Jordan River and he dips himself one time and he comes back up and there's no change
and he does it a second time and there's no change in number three and number four.
And we find that the Bible tells us that as he dips that seventh time again, following
what God said through his servant, Elisha, his flesh came again like the flesh of a little
child and he was clean.
Wow.
What an experience.
What an experience that this man had.
And we find that this experience in his life, this event that we read of in verse number
14 had a profound impact upon him.
And it brings us to really the main emphasis of the message this morning, that proclamation
of Naaman number three in your notes.
If you're taking notes, consider with me what Naaman exclaimed.
I mean, he had an expectation and then there's a great experience, but then there's this
exclamation, what he exclaimed.
Notice in verse 14, it talks about him being clean and then it says, and he returned in
verse number 15 to the man of God.
He and all his company and came and stood before him.
Now notice with me at this particular time, remember what happens the first time he comes
to the door of Elisha, Elisha doesn't come out.
Elisha sends a messenger with a simple set of instructions.
And we find that they go down to the Jordan River and he dips seven times and he's made
clean.
And now he and all of his company, they returned to the house of Elisha.
And it seems as you read the text of scripture, it seems as if Elisha is standing there and
waiting for him because he gets there and notice what he says.
I don't think he said it quietly.
I don't think he said it sheepishly.
He says, now I know that there is no God in all the earth, but in Israel.
Now therefore I pray thee take a blessing of thy servant.
So notice with me as we consider what he exclaimed.
He says, now I know, see he had heard about the Lord.
He had heard about what God was able to do.
In fact, the Bible, there's many interactions as you think about Elijah and Elisha's ministries
between the children of Israel and the Syrians and you think about the ways in which they
would have heard about the Lord God Jehovah and the servant, the little maid, she says,
would God my Lord were with the prophet that is in Samaria for he would recover him of
his leprosy.
Elisha, the man of God says to come, but remember what the king of Israel says, am I God to
kill and to make alive?
And so now we find.
that this man, Naaman, who maybe had heard about the Lord and had heard, remember
what he said, I thought, in verse number 11, that he, Elisha, will surely come out to
me and stand and call on the name of the Lord his God. So he had heard, he had
known some things about the Lord, but now he says, behold, now I know that there is
no God in all the earth but in Israel. What is he really communicating? What is
he saying with the statement, understand that the Syrians, and even as we get
further into the text of Scripture, there was an idolatry, a practice of idolatry,
they'd be idolatrous people, and we find that this man, Naaman, is recognizing
that, yeah, there's some little g-gods, there's some deities that we worship,
that we sacrifice to, but they're not real. There's only one real God, and now
I know who he is. And that's a great proclamation. And we find this morning
that it's very similar to what Jethro said. Do you remember, as we studied a
couple of weeks ago in Exodus chapter 18, that Jethro, he comes and he's having
that reunion with Moses, and Moses begins to explain to Jethro all that
the Lord has done, and we find that Jethro proclaims very similarly to what
Naaman says. He says, now I know. Now I know. And we find that he makes this
declaration, and we find that he then says, now therefore, at the end of verse
15, I pray thee take a blessing of thy servant. This would be something that
would just be a cultural understanding of what he would do, how he would respond.
Remember, when he left, according to verse number 5, when the king of Syria wrote
that letter, he departed and took with him 10 talents of silver, 6,000 pieces of
gold, and 10 changes of raiment. But understand with me that Elisha says,
that's not how you get it. I don't need this blessing that you would want to give
me. He says, as the Lord liveth in verse 16, Elisha says, before whom I stand,
I will receive none. And he, Naaman, urged him, Elisha, to take it, but he refused.
Wanted to make sure there was no misunderstanding as to how Naaman was
healed. Listen, this morning, I've said to so many people over the years,
when I talk to them about being saved, listen, I never one time told you to come
to church in order to be saved. I never one time told you to put money in an
offering plate in order to be saved. I never told you one time to, you fill in
the blank, whatever it might be that people think in order to be saved. Now, I
would say this, I would encourage people after they're saved to be in church. Why?
Because that's God's will. But it's not so that you can stay saved. It's the
response of being saved. Listen, when you're born again, I don't know what your
experience was. I don't know how old you were when you got saved. But I'll tell
you my own personal testimony. Before I got saved, I really didn't have any
interest in being in church. I really didn't. No idea what's going on. I mean,
it's just a, why am I gonna go to church? But then guess what? After I got saved, I
had a desire to be in church. I wanted to be in church. I wanted to be with God's
people. I wanted to hear God's Word being proclaimed. I wanted to learn, but grow
in grace and knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ. The Bible says, as
newborn babes desire the sincere milk of the Word that you may grow thereby. You
know how many times I read this Bible through before I got saved? Zero. Not one
time did I read this Bible through before I got saved. I can't tell you how
many times I've read it through now. Countless times. I read it through
multiple times a year. Why? Because I love God's Word. Because God gave me a
love. Why? Because I was born again. Do I read it so that I can stay saved? No. I
want to learn about my Savior. I want to know more of how, who He is. I want to
know more about Jesus. Do I come to church? I know on the pastor, it's like
you have to come to church. Can you imagine if the pastor said, you know, I'm
just not gonna come to church today. That'd be kind of a problem. But the
reality is that it's not that I have to. I say to our children, I remember when
Juliana was just a couple of years old and we were going to go back to church
on Sunday night. And she was getting awakened from her nap so that we could
go back. And she says, Daddy, do we have to go to church? And I said, no honey, we
don't have to, but we get to. What a difference in perspective. Listen, I don't
have to go to church in order to be saved. But I get to. And I want to. And
begin to think about the the truth here of what's unfolding. And we see this
declaration, what Naaman exclaimed. He says, now I know. But notice with me that
not only what he says, but then notice his actions as we continue to read the
text of Scripture. In verse number 17, after Elisha refused to take the
blessing or the gift from Naaman, then we find that Naaman says this in verse 17,
Shall there not then, I pray thee, be given to thy servant two mules burden of
earth? That's an interesting request. Naaman says, let me give you a gift.
Elisha says, no. He says, I urge you to take it. Elisha says, no, I refuse. And then
Naaman says, okay, well, I pray thee, give me two mules burden of earth. Why? Notice
the end of verse 17. For thy servant will henceforth offer neither burnt offering
nor sacrifice unto other gods but unto the Lord. I mean, that's awesome. That is
absolutely awesome to see what Naaman is declaring here. He says, listen, I'm gonna
go back to Syria. But I'd like to take some earth here from Israel, two mules
burden of earth, so that when I go back to Syria and I make offerings, that I'm
making those offerings to the Lord Jehovah, not to any other small g gods,
deities, idols that he had previously given offerings to. That is absolutely
amazing to see in this portion of Scripture the transformation, what's
happened in this man Naaman's life just because of a little maid that had been
taken captive during a military campaign of the Syrians. And she says,
understanding the condition of Naaman, would to God my Lord, Naaman, that he was
there with the prophet of God in Israel. Oh, what an encounter. Listen, this man
Naaman, he learned more than just simply there's a prophet in Israel. He learned
that the Lord God Almighty, Jehovah God, He is the only God. And he declares in
verse number 17, that I will offer thy servant will henceforth offer neither
burnt offering nor sacrifice unto other gods, but unto the Lord. Then I want you
to see the sensitivity of Naaman. Because Naaman is gonna go back to a
position. He's gonna go back to a culture. He's gonna go back to a place where
where he's going to have some levels of requirements of things. And it's gonna be
an interesting transition. But we find that Naaman is sensitive with regard to
what he has now learned and been exposed to. And he says to Elisha, in this thing
the Lord pardon thy servant. In what thing? That when my master goeth into the
house of Rimmon to worship there, and he leaneth on my hand, and I bow myself in
the house of Rimmon, when I bow down myself in the house of Rimmon, the Lord
pardon thy servant in this thing. Man this is sensitivity on the part of
Naaman. He's saying, listen I'm gonna go back to Syria and there's gonna be some
some practices that are going to be taking place that I'm going to, because
of my position and because of what I've done and who I am, I'm gonna be in this
place. And the Lord pardoned this thing. And there's sensitivity on the part of
this man Naaman because of what he understands and how he's purposing to
worship Jehovah only. And he said unto him, that's Elisha replying in verse 19,
go in peace. So he departed from him a little way. We know that Gehazi makes a
terrible decision. We won't look at the rest of the chapter, but Gehazi makes a
terrible decision in seeking to get one of those gifts. And we find that he not
only received a gift, but he got leprosy as a result of that. And you can look at
the end of the chapter and read that. But this morning as we look here at this
situation, this proclamation of Naaman, this morning, how did Naaman learn about
God? Started with a little unnamed servant girl. Listen, this morning it's
not about our names being known. It's about the Lord God being exalted. There
are some people of God throughout the history of the church that are recognizable
by name. But you know what's very interesting to me is that so often we hear
the names of maybe a C.H. Spurgeon, maybe we hear the names of a D.L. Moody, we hear
the names of an Adoniram Judson or a Hudson Taylor. And you can go through the
list and you can name some people that you would be familiar with of those that
God used in a great way. But what's often...
and not known are the people that led those people to Christ.
It's very rare that you hear their names.
Why?
Because it doesn't really matter.
In fact, the names of those other people that I mentioned don't really matter either.
It's all about the Lord Jesus Christ being exalted.
But this morning, if we'd come to a place in our own lives where I think this little
maid was, where it's like, listen, I'm just a servant of the Lord God Almighty.
No matter where I am, no matter where I am, no matter what the circumstances are that
brought me to the place where I am, my duty is to make Christ known.
And it doesn't really matter who knows who I am, because God knows who I am and I'm seeking
to simply exalt His name and to let others know about my God.
And then I want you to think about Naaman just for a moment.
And I want you to think about what Naaman experienced.
And as we've sought this morning to make application, I understand contextually that he was healed
of leprosy and that that's his experience, but then he recognized that there's only one
God and that's Jehovah.
And he purposes to worship Him alone.
His life was changed.
If we're to use New Testament vernacular this morning, we'd say that he was born again,
that he's changed.
He is a new creature.
That's the terminology we'd use as New Testament believers this morning as we look at this
text of scripture.
And I would say to you this morning that after he experienced what he experienced, do you
see how boldly he exclaimed what he exclaimed?
Listen, he didn't care.
The Bible tells us that when he came back to the house of Elisha in verse 15, notice
the Bible says that he returned to the man of God, he, and notice this, and all his company.
He didn't go back to Elisha secretly and make his proclamation.
Everyone that came from Syria with him were there and he still stood and proclaimed.
Why?
Because he knew something.
He says, now I know.
I'm convinced of.
And this morning I wonder as we look at our own lives and begin to think about Naaman
and looking at this passage of scripture and the freshness, the newness of what's happened.
If we're not careful, we can become like the church at Ephesus where we've lost our first
love.
We can get in that place where we've just kind of gotten used to.
We've kind of gotten a little cold, if you will, gotten a little indifferent, if you
will.
We've believed the lie of the enemy that nobody wants to hear.
It's kind of, it's not as fresh as it was when it first happened.
Do you remember when you first got saved?
Man, you first got saved, you understood, listen, let me tell you what Christ did for
me.
Let me tell you how He changed my life.
I mean, let me tell you how I was on a road leading to a Christless eternity.
I had no peace and no hope and no joy.
But now, as a child of God, I have, as Miss Lorene sang this morning, exceeding joy.
Why?
Because He is my exceeding joy.
I have peace.
Why?
Because He is my peace and He gives me a peace that passeth all understanding.
I have hope.
Why?
Because He is my hope and He says that He's coming back and I'm going to spend forever
with Him.
And begin to think about, listen, sometimes it can just kind of, if we're not careful,
we can kind of lose, in time, that fervency.
And as I look at Naaman here, he stands and, man, he exclaims.
He didn't care who was there.
He didn't care, I don't think he cared what they thought.
And this morning, I wonder, as we look at an example of Naaman, how are we doing on
proclaiming how great our God is, declaring how great our God is?
Listen, I believe this morning, with every fiber of my being, that those of you that
are gathered here this morning, that each of us that are here, that we've discovered
God's greatness, that we could stand and we could testify of how great God is.
We can sing the songs.
We could give the answers.
If someone were to say, right on a list, five reasons that God is great, I think we could
all at least do five.
Extra credit, we could put more down, right?
But I wonder this morning, I ask myself, I ask you to ask yourself, in closing, how am
I doing not in simply knowing that God is great, but how am I doing in declaring that
God is great?
In letting other people know how great my God is.
Naaman, he had an expectation.
He didn't get what he expected at the first go, but then he had an experience.
He humbled himself.
He obeyed what the man of God said, and he was clean, man.
And then he exclaimed, now I know.
There's no God in all the earth, but in Israel.
Notice he's speaking of the Lord God Jehovah.
He's the only God, and I'm so thankful that this morning we get to live in a place knowing
the God of the Bible, and being able to make Him known to others.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for this Bible account.
We can look at the events and we can rejoice in what took place, but as we make application
in our lives, I pray that we'd humbly search our own hearts.
Father, maybe there's someone here this morning that has never trusted the Lord Jesus Christ
as their personal Savior.
Maybe they've not humbled themselves.
Maybe they're still leaning on their own understanding.
Maybe they're believing some other teaching with regard to the way of salvation that would
not be in agreement with what You said in Your Word.
God, I pray that today would be the day of their salvation.
That they'd understand, they'd humble themselves, that they'd obey what the Word of God says.
For by grace, through faith, alone, Christ alone.
It's not Christ in my works, it's Christ alone.
If righteousness came by the law, then Christ is dead in vain.
We know that our Savior did not die in vain.
Lord, if there's one that's not sure of heaven, I pray that today would be the day of their
salvation.
For every person that knows You as their Lord and Savior, God, I pray that we'd evaluate
our lives, not with regard specifically to knowing how great You are, but that we'd evaluate
our lives specifically with regard to declaring how great You are.
I pray, God, that You'd use us for Your honor and for Your glory.
I pray that in these moments of invitation that You'd have Your will and way in every
life and every heart, Lord, that we would be doers of the Word and not hearers only.
We'll give You the honor and glory for that which You'll do.
It's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.