number six, and I've titled the message this morning,
A Life Marked by Prayer.
Over the past two weeks, we've had the opportunity
in our Sunday morning services to focus our attention
on the subject matter of prayer.
This is week number three on the same subject,
and I said this at the end of the message last week,
why are we focusing on prayer so much?
And I said this because I need it,
and I believe you need it as well.
We need to be a praying people.
We are thankful for the Bible truth
that God has extended to each of us an invitation
to enter into his presence at any time for any reason,
and we have direct access to the throne of grace.
We are to come boldly unto that throne.
And what a wonderful privilege prayer is,
but I find today that so often prayer is neglected,
and we need to understand,
we need to be people of prayer.
Our lives need to be marked by prayer.
We've had the opportunity in these last couple of weeks
to be able to look at the life of David,
and also at the life of Daniel,
and taking some snippets, if you will, from their lives,
and consider their example of men that were praying men.
I believe that how we pray, how you pray, and how I pray,
is greatly impacted by what we believe to be true
about God.
If we didn't believe this morning that God hears prayer,
there'd be no reason to pray, amen?
But God has told us in his word,
he has revealed the truth to us in his word,
that he hears prayer.
And not only does he hear prayer, but he answers prayer,
and so what we believe to be true about God
will greatly impact how we pray.
What is true about God is revealed to us in his word.
It's not just what you think to be true about God,
it's what God has revealed to us through his precious word
with regard to who he is,
and that truth that we find with regard to who our God is
should impact every area of our lives.
How we live should be impacted by what we believe.
Our behavior is impacted by our belief.
And we find this morning as we continue with this thought
of the subject matter of prayer,
I hope this morning that each of us would consider
not only the example from David in Psalm 34,
the example of Daniel in Daniel chapter number two,
but this morning as we look at Ephesians chapter number six,
and just very honest with you this morning,
we're gonna be at a number of different passages
of scripture, primarily right here within the epistles
that we find, the Pauline epistles,
and so we're gonna look at a number of verses of scripture,
but I want you to consider the life of Paul this morning.
There are a lot of things that we could say
about the Apostle Paul, but I believe this morning
that one thing that we could say that would be true
of the Apostle Paul is that he was a man
that his life was marked by prayer.
His life was marked by prayer.
You begin to read the epistles.
You begin to read, and we understand that all scripture
is given by inspiration of God.
We understand that God is the author of scripture,
but we find that he, God, used the Apostle Paul, this man,
to be able to be the human penman
for a lot of our New Testament.
And we have the opportunity,
as we read through the Pauline epistles,
and we read the letters, and we begin to get the sense
of this is a man whose life was marked by prayer.
Notice in Ephesians chapter number six,
we're familiar with the portion of scripture.
I have in the bulletin just verse number 18,
but I wanna catch it all in context.
Begin reading with me in verse number 10.
In Ephesians chapter number six,
notice what the Apostle Paul says
to the believers of the church at Ephesus
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God.
Finally, my brethren, be strong in the Lord
in the power of his might.
Put on the whole armor of God that you may be able to stand
against the wiles of the devil.
For we wrestle not against flesh and blood,
but against principalities, against powers,
against the rulers of the darkness of this world,
against spiritual wickedness in high places.
How many of you know this morning
that we're engaged in spiritual warfare?
I think it was Torrey, he said the spiritual life,
the Christian life can best be described
not as a playground, but as a battleground.
And certainly we are engaged in spiritual warfare.
It's all around us.
And so Paul continues to say this,
wherefore in verse number 13,
take unto you the whole armor of God
that you may be able to withstand in the evil day
and having done all to stand.
Stand therefore, having your loins girt about with truth
and having on the breastplate of righteousness
and your feet shod with the preparation
of the gospel of peace,
above all taking the shield of faith
wherewith you shall be able to quench
all the fiery darts of the wicked
and take the helmet of salvation
and the sword of the spirit, which is the word of God.
Then notice verse 18, Paul says this,
praying always with all prayer and supplication
in the spirit and watching there unto
with all perseverance and supplication
for all saints.
And for me, that utterance may be given unto me
that I may open my mouth boldly
to make known the mystery of the gospel
for which I am an ambassador in bonds
that therein I may speak boldly as I ought to speak.
A man, the apostle Paul, he's a man just like you and I are.
Sometimes if we're not careful,
we elevate the apostle Paul to a place of such level
that really he would not desire for any of us
to elevate him to.
I believe that the apostle Paul,
though he's not the one that wrote the words,
John the Baptist says I must decrease and he must increase,
but I believe the apostle Paul
in 2 Corinthians chapter number 12,
he makes it obvious that he doesn't want others
to think more highly of him than they ought.
And I believe that Paul,
he demonstrates throughout his writings
that he was a man that sought to be humble
and understood the work that Christ did
in and through his life.
At times, however, we might elevate the apostle Paul
to a level, again, that he would not desire
for us to elevate him to.
But I think about the apostle Paul this morning
and I look at these various portions of scripture
that we'll look to and I find a man
who is a man just like we are.
He's made of the flesh just like we are,
yet he was saved by the grace of God
and what a transformation.
God used him to write this truth,
if any man be in Christ, he is a new creature.
Old things are passed away,
behold, all things are become new.
And we find that the apostle Paul was a man
who was zealous for the Lord.
He was a man that was, I believe, surrendered
to the Lord and to the Lord's will.
He's a man that God used greatly
and at times we could examine the scripture and say,
why did God use the apostle Paul
in the fashion in which he did?
And I believe the answer is very simple,
that the apostle Paul was fully surrendered
to the will of God.
He said, I am crucified with Christ.
He was willing to do whatever the Lord wanted him to do
and his life is a life that's marked by prayer.
As we look at the text of scripture
and we consider a variety of portions
of scripture this morning,
I want you to consider this,
a life that is marked by prayer,
three thoughts, number one,
there must be a commitment to prayer,
a commitment to prayer.
What do I mean by that?
Well, as we look at the portion of scripture
and we'll look at some verses
as we get through the message this morning,
I believe that the apostle Paul
was personally committed to prayer.
Not only was he personally committed to prayer,
but he also encouraged and instructed others
to be people of prayer.
He understood, the apostle Paul understood
the importance of making this commitment.
We find today that we live in a society
where commitments are maybe not as binding
as they once were,
where people will break their word and what have you,
but I want you to think about being committed to something
and there are some people that are committed
to a variety of causes and a variety of things,
but I want you to think about the importance
of making a commitment to prayer.
See, God has ordained it that prayer moves the hand of God.
Prayer moves the hand of God.
God said to Jeremiah, call unto me
and I will answer thee and show thee great and mighty things
which thou knowest not.
And so God has ordained it
that we would be people of prayer
and we must have a commitment to prayer.
In other words, it's not just a situation
of if I have time, I'll pray.
Let me say this, if that's your approach,
you're not gonna ever pray.
Why?
Because you're never gonna have time.
There's always gonna be something else
that's vying for your time.
There's something else that's gonna fill your time
and so there must be a commitment that we make
and I believe that the apostle Paul
made a commitment to prayer.
There's no doubt that his commitment to prayer
was a result of what he understood to be true
about God and about the subject matter of prayer
as revealed in the Old Testament.
Understand with me this morning
that the apostle Paul was a man that was well trained.
The apostle Paul was a man that was well acquainted
with the truth of the Old Testament.
He was a man that was really a leader.
He was a man that was sitting at the feet of Gamaliel.
He says that he was a Pharisee of the Pharisees
and he had been trained and the Old Testament understood it
and I believe this morning
that when you begin to look at the life of the apostle Paul
after his conversion in Acts chapter number nine
and you see the way in which he was taught by the Lord
and the instruction he received,
we find that he was a man that was committed to prayer.
He was familiar with the Old Testament records
of the subject of prayer.
The last two weeks, we've had the opportunity
to look at some of those examples of prayer
in the life of David and also in the life of Daniel
but I want you to understand
that if you were to go through the Old Testament,
something that you'll find is you'll find a lot of recorded prayers.
You'll find a lot of God's people, heroes of the faith,
that were people of prayer.
And their prayers are recorded for us in the Old Testament.
You can read them, you can go and you can read
of the prayers of those servants of the Lord
as they're recorded for us in the Old Testament.
You think about the way in which the New Testament
would reference back even to the Old Testament.
It's the Apostle Paul that says that those things
that were written aforetime were written for our admonition,
they were written for our instruction,
and we find that the Apostle Paul was very aware,
he was very familiar with the Old Testament,
and so he would have been aware of the recorded prayers.
Think about James, he references the prayer of Elijah,
the effectual, fervent prayer of a righteous man.
We often reference that in James 5,
but he speaks about Elijah.
You go back to 1 Kings 17 and 18,
and you read the prayer of Elijah.
You have the opportunity, you think about someone
that is a praying person in the Old Testament,
a number of thoughts would come to your mind
of people that would fit that category.
But what do you think about Hannah?
She was a woman of prayer.
She poured her heart out before the Lord,
and it was marked that she was a woman of prayer.
And you could go on and on,
and you could consider this morning
the record that God has given us in the Old Testament
with regard to the subject of prayer.
I find that as you read the Old Testament,
not only do you have recorded prayers,
but you have prayer promises.
I just quoted Jeremiah 33 just a moment ago,
and it's a wonderful prayer promise.
We have it on the front of our weekly prayer bulletin
on Wednesday evenings every week.
It's right on the front of the prayer bulletin. Why?
Because I want to be reminded, I want you to be reminded
that we have a God who says,
call unto me, and I will answer thee
and show thee great and mighty things,
which thou knowest not.
Jeremiah, if you read in the book of Lamentations
in the third chapter, he did just that.
He called to God, and God answered,
and God delivered, and God worked.
We find that he has the opportunity,
the Apostle Paul, this commitment to prayer.
Why did he make a commitment to prayer?
Well, he had the opportunity to know from the Old Testament
the recorded prayers, the prayer promises,
but he also had the opportunity to read of answered prayer.
You know it's encouraging to read the recorded prayers.
You know it's encouraging to read how God answers.
It's encouraging to read in 1 Samuel 1
of how Hannah prayed for a son.
Wasn't it encouraging to read how God blessed
and she had a son, his name being Samuel?
God answered.
And you find that throughout the Old Testament
as you read the prayers of God's people
that you also have the opportunity to read
how God answered their prayers
and what God did, how God showed his great power.
I wonder this morning as we think about this first thought,
this first point of a life that is marked by prayer,
there must be a commitment.
I wonder this morning, is prayer a priority in our lives?
I mean, is it a priority in my life?
Is it a priority in your life?
There are certain things that are priorities.
And sometimes when we go through life,
I understand that we're all bombarded
with things that are important,
things that are necessary,
things that fill up our schedules,
things that we did not expect to happen.
And we find how our schedules can get so filled.
But I wonder what place does prayer have in our lives?
Have we placed a priority in our lives
in the subject of prayer?
Is it a priority?
If I think about it as being a priority,
the reality is that if I go throughout a day
and I don't have a time of prayer,
I'm longing for it.
Why? Because it's a priority.
I don't know about you,
but I'm sure that at some point in your life,
it's happened in my life,
that your time of prayer is interrupted.
How many has had that experience?
It's interrupted, something comes up,
you receive a phone call, maybe a visitor,
or whatever it might be,
something comes up and interrupts your time of prayer.
And I wonder if we have a priority in prayer,
how are we thinking throughout the day?
Man, I can't wait to have my time with the Lord,
that quiet time, that time of prayer.
I wonder this question,
if we have a commitment to prayer,
do we have a time?
Do we have a place?
Because again, prayer's not gonna happen by accident.
You're not gonna pray by accident.
You think about this, I don't know,
I'll just be very transparent this morning
through the message,
I hope that it would help somebody,
but I'll tell you this,
in my life, if it seems like,
man, there's absolutely nothing going on,
and man, I have a time for being able to pray
or to study or read,
guess what happens?
Bam, bam, bam, distraction,
this comes up, that comes up,
the phone rings, the phone buzzes,
and there's a text message,
or there's a this, or there's a that.
Listen, the devil doesn't want you to pray.
He don't want you to pray.
We gotta have a time and a place.
We gotta have a commitment to prayer.
I wonder this morning, do we have a plan when we pray?
You know, if we pray without a plan,
it can just kind of get chaotic,
it can be all over the map, so to speak,
but I wonder if we have a plan.
When I speak about having a plan,
I don't mean just this religious exercise
of just going through mindlessly,
going through a list,
but I'm saying we have a plan when we pray.
What's our prayer life structured like?
How do we pray?
I wonder this, as I think about the example
before us this morning with a life that is marked by prayer
and a commitment to prayer,
I believe that it would be obvious
to those to whom Paul ministered
and to those who were acquainted with the Apostle Paul,
I think it would be obvious to them
that he was a man that was committed to prayer.
When I think about that truth,
I wonder this morning how many would know,
how many would have the opinion of us
that we are people that are committed to prayer.
I wonder when somebody in the office,
somebody in the family has a situation
and they need somebody to pray,
that they know that you're on their list of people to call
because I need you to pray
because they know that you're committed to prayer.
See, if we're going to have a life that's marked by prayer,
we must make a commitment.
Let me say this, number two,
as you look at the life of the Apostle Paul,
and we're going to start looking at a number of verses of Scripture,
and I'll read them for you,
and I hope that you can turn to as many as you can.
I'm going to turn to them as well.
I don't have any of them marked,
and I'm going to turn to them with you,
and I want you to think about this, number two,
not only a commitment to prayer,
but consistency in prayer.
You know what I find in life?
Consistency is a challenge.
You know how many people can go to the gym
the first two weeks of a new year?
In January.
You know gym memberships?
I mean, it's historical data
that in the month of January,
the first couple of weeks,
gym enrollment increases exponentially.
You know why that is?
All these people have these New Year's resolutions.
I'm going to go back to the gym,
and I'm going to work out,
and the people that have been there all year,
all of a sudden,
in the first two weeks of January,
they can't find a machine to work on,
they can't have any free time
because everybody else is there,
and it's like, just wait until February
because they're all going to leave,
and then they'll sign up again next year.
Consistency.
I get asked often about parenting.
One of the keys that I say often
with regard to any counseling
with regard to parenting
is consistency is key.
Consistency.
Consistency in prayer.
I wonder if a lack of consistency
in my prayer life,
a lack of consistency in your prayer life,
it might be the result of
how committed we really are to prayer.
Because if we're truly committed to prayer,
then there's going to be consistency
in our prayer lives.
Let's look at the Apostle Paul.
Turn back to the book of Romans, if you will,
and I want you to consider
as we look at a number of verses of Scripture,
and we won't look at every example,
but I want to really hammer the point down this morning,
and I want to look at a lot of verses.
Why?
Because I want you to see that
Paul was a man that was consistent in prayer.
I can't imagine,
as I read the New Testament,
I cannot imagine how much time daily
Paul must have spent in prayer.
Because of all the people that he writes to
and says, I'm praying for you,
if you start adding it all up
and start thinking about how much time that would take,
man, he was a man that was consistent in prayer.
And listen, it wasn't just that he prayed
for the people that were closest to him.
It wasn't that he just prayed
for an inner circle of people.
No, the people that God gave him
an opportunity to minister to,
some that he didn't even ever personally minister to,
he just heard about their faith
and about their walk in Christ.
He was praying for them,
and he had this consistent prayer life.
Notice what he says in Romans chapter number one,
in verse number nine, it says this,
for God is my witness,
whom I serve with my spirit in the gospel of his Son.
Notice what he says, that without ceasing,
I make mention of you always in my prayers.
Now, think about the way that he starts the verse,
for God is my witness.
I mean, he's revealing to these believers in Rome
that he is praying for them,
but notice that he says, without ceasing,
I make mention of you always in my prayers.
These are people in Rome that Paul is writing to
and he's saying that I'm praying for you.
Notice over in the book of Ephesians, if you will,
we were there just a moment ago in the sixth chapter,
but notice what Paul says in the beginning of this book
in Ephesians chapter number one.
Again, the apostle Paul had the opportunity
to go and to be used of God,
to see the church there at Ephesus established,
and notice what he says.
It says in Ephesians 1, in verse number 16,
it says this, and I'll read verse 15 with it.
Wherefore, I also, after I heard of your faith
in the Lord Jesus and love unto all the saints,
cease not to give thanks for you,
making mention of you in my prayers.
So we have the believers in Rome,
and now we have the believers in Ephesus.
Notice in the book of Philippians,
in Philippians chapter number one,
we find that the apostle Paul,
he, a verse that's familiar to many of us,
verse number three, where he says,
I thank my God upon every remembrance of you.
But notice what he says in verse number four
of Philippians one.
He says, always in every prayer of mine
for you all, making request with joy.
So we got the believers in Rome,
we got the believers in Ephesus,
we got the believers in Philippi.
I mean, the list is growing, right?
Think about, he was a man that was committed to prayer.
He was a man that was consistent in prayer.
Do you notice the words that we're using
where he talks about always and without ceasing
and having this consistency in his prayer life?
Notice over in the book of First Thessalonians,
actually in Colossians, look in Colossians chapter number one.
Now understand with me as you're flipping there
to the book of Colossians that Paul personally
had not ministered to these believers in Colossae.
Paul had heard about their faith
according to the beginning portions of chapter number one.
Epaphras was the man that was really the pastor,
if you will, the leader there.
And he was the one that was a faithful minister of Christ.
And Paul had heard about their faith
and he heard about their love for the Lord
and their love for the saints.
And notice what Paul says to these believers in Colossae
in Colossians one in verse number three.
He says this, we give thanks to God
and the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.
Notice this, praying always for you.
Praying always for you.
Notice verse number nine, what he says,
for this cause we also, since the day we heard it,
do not cease to pray for you
and to desire that you might be filled
with the knowledge of his will and all wisdom
and all spiritual understanding.
Do you see where he says there in verse number nine
that from the day that we heard it,
we do not cease to pray for you.
You know what that is?
That's consistency.
That's just not religious rote religion.
It's not just religious exercise.
No, we find that Paul was a man that was committed to prayer.
He knew that there's a God in heaven
that hears and answers prayer.
And he was committed to prayer,
but he was consistent in prayer.
I wonder this morning,
as we consider the thought of consistency in prayer,
there are times in our lives that we may pray
consistently about something for a short period of time
and then not long goes and we forget,
we're not praying about that thing anymore
and we've not been consistent in our prayers.
God hears, God answers.
We have folks sitting here this morning
that have prayed for loved ones to be saved
for not just a couple of days or a couple of weeks,
but for years, some for decades.
That's consistency in prayer.
So I want you to think about those that have prayed
for that length of time.
And when that loved one finally bows their head
and trust the Lord Jesus Christ as their personal savior,
I would say, was it worth it?
Absolutely, hallelujah to God be the glory.
They trusted Christ as their savior.
What an answer to the consistent prayers of his people.
You know, God doesn't get tired of hearing your pray.
He doesn't get tired of hearing you pray.
Notice over in the book of first,
Thessalonians, Paul had the opportunity
to go to Thessalonica and to minister there.
And we find in first Thessalonians,
he's mentioning to these believers here
in the church in Thessalonica,
how that he's praying for them.
Notice in chapter one in verse number two,
he says, we give thanks to God always for you all
making mention of you in our prayers.
He tells them again as he writes a second letter to them
in second Thessalonians chapter number one
in verse number 11, he's writing this second epistle
to them and trying to provide them with instruction.
He says in verse number 11 of chapter one,
wherefore also we pray always for you
that our God would count you worthy of this calling
and fulfill all the good pleasure of his goodness
and the work of faith with power.
So think about it, we got people in Rome.
I believe he's praying for the people in Corinth as well.
We skipped over looking at first and second Corinthians,
but you think he's praying for the people in Rome,
the people in Corinth.
You think about the people in Ephesus
and Philippi and Colossae.
And you begin to think about those in the region of Galatia
really four churches in the region of Galatia.
He's writing to the churches in the region,
the book of Galatians.
And you begin to think and now in Thessalonica,
I mean, Paul's prayer, time must be lengthy.
Must be lengthy.
You know, sometimes we talk about the conveniences of life
and we have a lot of conveniences, don't we?
I mean, there's a lot of things that we can do today
that are a whole lot faster
than what they could do a hundred years ago
and a whole lot faster
than what they could do 2000 years ago, amen.
I'm thankful for some of the modern conveniences,
but you know, many of the modern conveniences
are supposed to do something,
they're supposed to save you time.
They're supposed to save you time.
Listen, washing your clothes in a washing machine
is a whole lot more efficient than washing them
on a washboard.
Hallelujah.
How many of y'all thankful for a washing machine?
Come on.
How many of you know how to use them?
That was for the men, amen.
And listen, you think about the modern conveniences
that we have.
They're supposed to, the design, the idea,
what we're told is there to save us time.
But does it not seem like we have less time?
Listen, I'm not gonna get on it this morning
because it's not the focus of my message,
but I'll tell you, you know what?
Social media is robbing people of time.
People take this,
listen, I'm happy for this.
There's a lot of things that this is a blessing for.
But how many times you see people that are just,
for hours and hours.
Look, there are reports out there
that you can go and study on your own
to find out how many hours a week
people are spending on these devices.
And then we say, we don't really have time for prayer.
It's like the book that was written
at this point 25 years ago.
At least that's when my dad found it
in a Christian bookstore.
I don't know exactly when it was authored.
I've never read the book.
But I remember my dad using it as an example
for a men's prayer breakfast that we had back in 1998.
And the book was entitled this,
How to Pray in Less Than 10 Minutes.
How to Pray in Nine Minutes and 59 Seconds.
That's what the title of the book was.
I'm thankful that God doesn't just give me
nine minutes and 59 seconds.
But sometimes we say,
I mean, think about all the modern conveniences.
Think about Paul.
He's telling all these people, I'm praying for you.
But it's scripture.
It's scripture.
He says in Romans one that God is my witness.
I'm praying for you always without ceasing.
From the day that I heard of it.
Think about that.
There's not only a commitment to prayer,
but there's consistency in prayer.
A life that is marked by prayer
is a life that is going to have that commitment,
but there's going to be consistency.
He says to Timothy, I'm not gonna turn there,
but in Second Timothy one in verse number three,
he says, I have remembrance of thee in my prayers
night and day.
He says to Philemon in verse number four,
he says, I thank my God making mention of thee always
in my prayers.
So we find that Paul was a man
that was consistent in prayer.
He was a man that did not simply instruct
and teach others that they should be people of prayer.
He did not simply instruct the believers in Ephesus
in our text that we're looking at in verse number 18
to pray always with all prayer and supplication
in the spirit and watching there unto with all perseverance
and supplication for all saints,
but he was a man that was praying.
He was a man that was committed and consistent in prayer.
You know, Paul not only prayed for others personally,
but Paul requested prayer.
He requested prayer.
You know, one of the most repeated things
that Paul prayed for was boldness
and opportunity to preach the gospel.
Now I'll be honest with you,
and I've shared this thought before,
and so it's nothing new,
but I remember when it first hit me,
when I began to read about the requests that Paul makes,
some of them are very basic, brethren pray for us.
I mean, just a basic request in that sense,
but we find that there are other places here in Ephesians
chapter number six, he speaks about asking them to pray
that he would open his mouth boldly in verse 19.
In verse number 20, that I may speak boldly
as I ought to speak.
Dean, when we were praying this morning,
he said something as praying,
I didn't understand what he said.
Here's what he said, God help us to be otters.
And I thought an otter, like,
what is this man talking about?
I'm just being honest with you.
That's what he said right here.
He said, God help us to be otters.
He said, help us to do what we ought to do.
I never heard that before.
Maybe it's something you're familiar with,
but that's what he said, that's what he prayed.
And notice what Paul says as.
I ought to speak, that God would give me boldness.
But listen, this morning, when I think about Bible characters, when I think about those
that God has given us the opportunity to see their lives and to examine their lives that
God has recorded in this holy book, Paul is probably on the bottom of the list of people
that I would think needs boldness.
When you read of the life of the Apostle Paul, when you read the first missionary journey
and the second missionary journey and the third missionary journey, I mean Paul's going
from city to city and he's preaching the gospel and they're attacking him and they're
persecuting him and he just goes to the next place and he's preaching the gospel.
And he's the last person that I would think that needs boldness, but you know why he's
preaching the gospel like he is?
Because I believe everywhere he goes he says, pray that I'll have boldness, pray that I'll
have boldness, pray that I'll have boldness, pray that I'd open my mouth with boldness
and speak as I ought to speak.
And God's people were praying that Paul, when he would go on those journeys, when he'd go
to those new cities, when he would go and minister that he would have boldness and guess
what?
God answered prayer.
God gave him boldness.
By the way, if you think about, and I prayed this way in the Sunday school hour this morning
for some missionaries that are dealing with some difficulties, and you think about the
truth in Acts chapter number four, you don't need to turn there, but in Acts chapter number
four the Bible speaks about the early persecution of the apostles, the disciples there and they're
facing some difficulty from the religious leaders and they tell them that they command
them not to speak in the name of Jesus any longer.
And you know what their prayer was?
Their prayer was that God, they say this in Acts four and verse number 29, and now Lord
behold their threatenings and grant unto thy servants that with all boldness they may speak
thy word.
Now I'll be honest with you this morning, if I was in Acts chapter number four there's
some other things I could have thought about praying about.
Like God deal with those guys that are persecuting us?
God you can deal with them.
God you've heard their threatenings, now judge them, deal with them.
Come on, I'm not the only one that might think that way.
But they didn't pray that way.
God give us boldness.
In the midst of the opposition, in the midst of the difficulty, it wasn't God remove the
difficulty, it was God give us boldness in spite of the difficulty.
What a lesson for us this morning.
What instruction for us this morning.
You know what God did?
If you read down to the end of chapter number four in the book of Acts, it says this, that
when they had prayed the place was shaken where they were assembled together and they
were all filled with the Holy Ghost and they spake the word of God with boldness.
The very thing that they prayed for they received.
Why?
Because our God hears and answers prayer.
The Apostle Paul, he was a man that was committed to prayer.
He was a man that was consistent in prayer.
In the last few minutes that we have this morning I want you to consider with me not
only making a commitment and being consistent but I want you to think about the content
of Paul's prayers.
The content.
Begin to think about this, a life that is marked by prayer.
Begin to think about the lessons, messages from the last couple of weeks and then looking
at this passage and these passages and considering the life of the Apostle Paul and we see that
God gives us some insight to the content of Paul's prayers.
And begin to think about this and kind of put all of this together and I hope that it's
packaged in the same way for you this morning.
I think about this commitment that Paul has to prayer and I think about the consistency
but then when I think about the content and I begin to think about the way in which Paul
is praying for those to whom he is writing and God has recorded a number of those prayers
for us, we have the opportunity to receive insight this morning that really there is
a spiritual emphasis with regard to the manner in which Paul is praying.
And the spiritual emphasis is extremely obvious to us this morning as we'll look at a few
examples here in God's Word with regard to how Paul was praying for these believers.
And I just wonder this morning, if we were to examine our own prayer lives and we think
about the content, how are we praying one for another?
Let me ask it this way, are we simply praying for deliverance because of a situation or
are we praying for spiritual growth through that situation?
We believe this morning that our God doeth all things well, amen?
We believe this morning that our God's in control of everything, that our God makes
no mistakes and this morning when you have a difficulty, maybe it's a health situation,
maybe it's something else that's going on, that yes, we may pray that God would give
you grace and strength and deliver you from it but you know what, we ought to also pray
that God would teach you through it.
Because every experience that we have in life, God is teaching us something.
God is teaching us something about who He is, about who we are.
Sometimes God will reveal to us some things in our lives that we have to fix, amen?
Have you had that happen?
You have a situation and God's exposing some things in your life.
God's exposing some areas of your life that you need to grow in and you need to learn
from and we find that the Apostle Paul, the basic aspect of the emphasis of Paul's prayer
is spiritual, not temporal, not temporal, it's spiritual.
Notice with me in the book of Ephesians chapter number 1 and we've already mentioned we're
in Ephesians 6, we've looked at the first chapter and looking at the way in which Paul
is praying for them but here in the book of Ephesians, just six chapters that God gives
us in the book of Ephesians, there are two prayers of Paul that are recorded.
In the book of Ephesians chapter 1 and then also in chapter number 3, God records for
us the way in which Paul is praying for these believers at Ephesus.
Notice the first one in Ephesians 1 verses 15 down through 23, the content of Paul's
prayer for these believers at Ephesus.
Notice in verse 15, the Bible says this,
Wherefore I also, after I heard of your faith in the Lord Jesus and love unto all saints,
cease not to give thanks for you, making mention of you in my prayers.
But then notice verse 17 through 23 gives us the content of how he's praying for them.
That the God of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of glory, may give unto you the spirit
of wisdom and revelation and the knowledge of him.
You know he's praying that God would give them the spirit of wisdom, that God would
give them a knowledge of God.
Paul would say that I may know him in the book of Philippians and we find that here
he's saying I want you, I'm praying that you would have a deeper knowledge of who God
is.
I wonder when's the last time we prayed that way for one another?
When's the last time we prayed for our brothers and sisters in Christ that through the circumstances
they're going through that God would help them to have a deeper knowledge of who God
is?
This is spiritual praying.
This is an emphasis on the spiritual.
Notice verse 18.
The eyes of your understanding being enlightened that you may know what is the hope of his
calling and what the riches of the glory of his inheritance in the saints and what is
the exceeding greatness of his power to usward who believe according to the working of his
mighty power.
Notice verse 20.
Which he wrought in Christ when he raised him from the dead and set him at his own right
hand in the heavenly places for above all principality and power and might and dominion
and every name that is named not only in this world but also in that which is to come and
hath put all things under his feet and gave him to be the head over all things to the
church which is his body, the fullness of him that filleth all in all.
You know in those last verses of chapter number one, you know what Paul's praying?
He's praying that these believers in Ephesus would have an understanding of the power of
God.
You know why that's so important?
Because when we understand the power of God it impacts how we live our lives.
He says here of his power in verse number 19 and what is the exceeding greatness of
his power.
Notice what it says, to usward who believe.
He says this in chapter 3 and we'll look at it in just a moment but I want to reference
it with regard to the prayer in the first chapter.
In verse number 20 we're guilty, I'm guilty of often just quoting the first part of Ephesians
3 and 20.
Now unto him that is able to exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think.
Notice what it says, according to the power that worketh in us.
Listen it's not according to your power, it's according to his power that worketh in us
and in the first chapter of the book of Ephesians Paul says I'm praying for you but he says
let me tell you how I'm praying for you.
There's a spiritual emphasis.
He's praying that they would have the spirit of wisdom.
By the way our God is the all wise God.
He gives us wisdom through his word, heavenly wisdom.
They'd have a knowledge of God to know him, not just simply know about him but to know
him.
You know there's a difference of knowing about someone and knowing someone?
There's a difference to know him, to have a knowledge of God, the hope of his calling
he mentions in verse 18 and then through the end of the chapter he mentions about the knowing
the mighty power of God.
I wonder this morning, do you know how powerful our God is?
I mean are we praying this way for one another?
Ephesians chapter 3 the second prayer of Paul is recorded in verses 14 through 21 and we
look in this prayer how that Paul is praying again for these same believers and notice
with me beginning in verse number 14 of chapter 3 he says this, for this cause I beg you to
bow my knees unto the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, of whom the whole family in heaven
and earth is named." Notice what he says, that he would grant you according to the riches
of his glory. Notice what he's praying, to be strengthened with might by his spirit in
the inner man. You know what he's praying for? Spiritual strength. You know what we
need today? We need spiritual strength. We read in chapter number 6 we're engaged in
a spiritual battle. Listen, we don't wrestle against flesh and blood. It's a spiritual
battle, the warfare that we're engaged in. And Paul in the third chapter, before he tells
them about putting on the whole armor of God, he says, let me tell you how I'm praying for
you. I'm praying that God would strengthen you in the inner man. That he would give you
spiritual strength. You know how many young people today are trying to get physical strength?
How many people here today that are in their senior years, I'll use that terminology, would
say, my strength has failed me. I don't have the same kind of physical strength that I
once did. By the way, I'm not in my senior years, but I can admit to you I don't have
the same kind of strength that I once did. I just don't. I think if we'd all be honest
we'd say, yeah, I'm right there. But you know young men, what's their glory, man? Their
strength. Trying to get strong physically. I'm not against getting strong physically,
but not if you're not getting strong spiritually. You know, God tells us this, that bodily exercise
profiteth, what's the word say, little. I wonder this morning, if we were to take how
much time we spend on bodily exercise and then compare it to how much time we spend
on spiritual exercise. If bodily exercise, according to God's word, profiteth little,
I'm not saying that you shouldn't exercise, I'm not saying you shouldn't take care of
your body, but what I'm saying is that if we do it at the expense of spiritual, we've
got our priorities wrong. We've got our priorities wrong. He says, I'm praying that you'd be
strengthened with might by His Spirit in the inner man. Notice he continues in verse
17, that Christ may dwell in your hearts by faith, that ye being rooted and grounded in
love. Man, that they would abide in Christ, that they would be rooted and grounded in
love. Listen, the truth of being rooted and grounded, to having stability, to knowing,
keeping ourselves in the love of God, to knowing the love of God, he then mentions
that in verse 18, that we may be able to comprehend with all saints, notice what is the breadth
and length and depth and height, and to know the love of Christ which passeth knowledge
that ye might be filled with all the fullness of God. Listen, the love, why does the love
of Christ, why does it say that it passeth knowledge? Because it doesn't really make
sense that the God of the universe would die for you, or for me. That's why the songwriter
says, amazing love, how can it be? That thou, my God, shouldst die for me. Paul's praying
spiritually, the emphasis is on the spiritual. Notice with me quickly in Colossians chapter
1, and we'll end there. In Colossians chapter 1, we mentioned already in verse number 9
how that Paul says that he was praying for these believers. He said in verse number 3
that he's praying always for them, but again I want you to see the content of Paul's prayer.
Paul says in verse number 9 of the book of Colossians, again under the inspiration of
the Holy Spirit of God, for this cause we also, since the day we heard it, do not cease
to pray for you. But notice what he says, and to desire that ye might be filled with
the knowledge of his will in all wisdom and spiritual understanding. You know, Paul's
praying that these believers would know the will of God. They would know the will of God.
How do we find God's will? We've got to get in His Word. They didn't have the whole Bible
as we have today, and what a blessing to have the whole canon of Scripture, that we would
know the will of God. What is God's will for my life? What does God want from me? What
is it that pleases God? We were at the youth rally last night and the preacher said a number
of times, do right because right is what pleases God. Do right because right is what pleases
God. And we're to do the will of God. Paul prays that they would know the will of God,
but then that they would do the will of God. See, it's not an idea of knowing God's will
and then saying, yeah, you know, I'm not really interested in that. No, notice he says that
they would know, in verse number 9, but then in verse number 2, that ye might walk worthy
of the Lord unto all pleasing, being fruitful in every good work, and increasing in the
knowledge of God. This is spiritual praying. This is the kind of praying that we're guilty
of not praying. We pray for a lot of temporal things. We pray for a lot of things that are
on the plane of this world. But I'm saying that Paul is saying that they might walk worthy
of the Lord. See, Paul's desire, and he mentions this at the end of the chapter, and we won't
take time to deal with all of it, but Paul has the desire that when these believers would
stand before the Lord Jesus Christ, that they'd be able to give a good report, that they'd
be able to hear a good report, that he says that we might present every man perfect in
Christ Jesus. And so how does he pray for them? Well, he prays that they would know
the will of God, and then he prays that they would do the will of God. Notice in verse
number 11, at the end of verse number 10, increasing in the knowledge of God. You know,
this morning I believe that all of us could increase in our knowledge of God. There's
not one amongst us that knows everything about God, and you never will. He is infinite, and
we are finite. Every day, I wonder if we're increasing in our knowledge of God. This book
is a living book. It's alive. It's quick. It's powerful. It's sharper than a two-edged
sword. And God reveals things to us in His Word of who He is and how we're to increase
in the knowledge of God. Notice though in verse number 11, strengthened with all might,
according to His glorious power and all patience and longsuffering with joyfulness, giving
thanks unto the Father which hath made us meet to be partakers of the inheritance of
the saints in life. And he's praying here that they would have the strength, really
divine strength, in order to do the will of God. It's amazing that God would reveal to
us what His will is for us. And Paul says, for these believers in Colossae, I'm praying
that you would know the will of God, that you would do the will of God, that you would
be strengthened with divine strength so that you could do what God has called you to do.
So when I look at a life that's marked by prayer, I look at the life of the Apostle
Paul. Are there other examples that we could look to? Sure, there are. But this morning
as we spend this time focused on a life that's marked by prayer, the life of the Apostle
Paul, we see a man who is committed to prayer. I wonder this morning, what kind of commitment
do we have to prayer? Is our commitment to prayer stronger than our commitment to the
gym? I'm just going to throw it right out there. You know, there are some people that
are so committed to the gym that they just will not miss. It doesn't matter how long
the day went, it doesn't matter how many meetings they had that they didn't expect, how many
things got changed, they're going to the gym because they have a commitment. I wonder what
our commitment is to prayer. I mean, God hears and answers. God has ordained that prayer
moves the hand of God. Is there consistency in our prayer life? I mean, are we consistent?
I wonder this morning, what's the content of our prayer? Are we praying with a spiritual
emphasis or are we just praying kind of on this temporal plane? I hope this morning that
just as we said of the Apostle Paul, that his life is a life that's marked by prayer,
I believe that those people that Paul ministered to, those people that Paul interacted with,
they knew that he was a man of prayer. He was committed to it. I wonder this morning,
how many people know of us? That's a prayer warrior. That's a man, a woman, a young person
of prayer. A life marked by prayer. Let's pray. Father, we love you. Thank you for loving
us. Thank you for the opportunity to examine your Word this morning, to be challenged.
God, you've challenged me in this area of prayer as I've prepared, then again as I delivered.
Lord, I pray that you would challenge each of us in this area of prayer. I pray that
we'd be honest and humble before you as we truly examine our lives, our prayer lives.
I pray that what we believe to be true about you, what we find in your Word with regard
to who you are and what you're capable of doing, I pray that that would shape, impact
our prayer lives. Lord, I pray that if there's one that's not saved, that today would be
the day of their salvation. They've never trusted Christ. They don't have assurance
that if they were to die today, they'd go to heaven. God, I pray that you'd give us
an opportunity to take a Bible and show them how they could know for sure without any doubt
whatsoever, not because of anything they could do, but...
because of what the Lord Jesus Christ did, God in flesh on the cross of Calvary, His
glorious resurrection.
Would you give us that opportunity this morning to see someone trust Christ?
I pray that as we examine our prayer lives that we do business with you in these moments
of invitation.
I pray that we wouldn't rush, Lord, but we'd allow you to have your way in our lives, that
we'd be responsive, that we'd be doers of the Word.
Bless now as only you can and we'll thank you for all that you'll do, for it's in Christ's
name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano, and as she does, the altar is open.