hope that God has spoken to you and you've been encouraged as well. Take your Bible if
you will and turn with me to Acts chapter 13. Acts chapter 13. And I'm going to do something
a little different than I normally do tonight. I usually read a scripture, pray and preach.
But tonight I'm going to pray and read some select scripture in Acts chapter 13 and then
preach. So let's pray and ask God to help us in this time together. Lord I am so thankful
for being here at Fellowship Baptist Church. I'm thankful for the fellowship that I've
been ever able to have with Pastor and his family and with those that I have been able
to see. Lord I am so grateful for the faithfulness of your people as they tune in to live stream.
I know it's not the easiest thing to do and I am just grateful that they love you, love
your word and care about pleasing you with their time but also learning something that
can help them please you with their lives. So Lord we ask you to continue to work and
we pray tonight that your Holy Spirit would just take your word and apply it to our hearts
in the ways that we need it applied and may we be people who are ready to hear and Lord
ready to submit to what you teach us. I pray for you to speak to us so that we can be helped
in our service to you. I ask it in Jesus name. Amen. I want to read four verses out
of chapter 13. I want to begin with verse 22. Note it. And when he had removed him,
he raised up unto them David to be their king. To whom also he gave testimony and said, I
have found David the son of Jesse, a man after mine own heart, which shall fulfill
all my will. Normally when I read that verse I am arrested, I stop and contemplate that
phrase a man after mine own heart. God doesn't say that about anybody else in the word of
God, but he says it about David. And I think it's significant and I won't hazard to this
sermon say what I think that means because I don't want to take the time, but what an
honor for God to look at your life and say that's a man who has my heart. He's after
mine own heart. But tonight the emphasis that I see in that verse is not on that phrase
after mine own heart. My emphasis is on the last words of that verse, which shall fulfill
all my will. I don't know that there would be any higher accolade that I would try and
achieve than from the day I got saved back in 1975 until the day that God decides that
he is going to take me home, that God could look at the life of Mike Edwards and say he
fulfilled everything I gave him to do. David's course was not an easy course and it was an
unusual life, but David was careful even though he was a flawed man. And we're all flawed
people. But the marvelous thing is that a man, even though he is flawed and even though
he falls with God's grace and help, he can get back up and complete the course that God
has for him. I notice a second man. Look at verse 25. And as John, notice this word, fulfilled
his course. He said, Whom think ye that I am? I am not he. But behold, there cometh one after
me whose shoes of his feet I am not worthy to lose. The second time, the second man, God says
about John the Baptist, he fulfilled his course. Boy, I would suggest to you tonight that the
course of John's life was certainly no easy course. He was a hard man, a man who lived
in the wilderness much of his life, a man who did not have the dainties, the luxuries
that others had in life, not in dress, not in food, not in housing. He was a rough man.
And I'd also remind us that the end of John's life was not a sweet time gathered around
his family, but John lost his head at the request of a pagan and wicked woman, and a
wicked king gave her her desire, and he was beheaded for his testimony for Jesus Christ
and for righteousness. And yet God looks at that man and says, he fulfilled his course.
There's a third man that's mentioned in this passage. Look at verse 29. And when they had,
here it is again, fulfilled all that was written of him, they took him down from the tree and
him in a sepulcher, but God raised him from the dead. Well, we know who we're talking about,
though his name is not used in verses 29 and 30. We're talking about the Lord Jesus Christ.
And though the Bible says here that they fulfilled all that was written of him,
understand this, Jesus did not have his life taken, he laid down his life for all of us.
And any time he would have wanted to come off the cross or stop the process,
he could have but called to his Father or called 10,000 angels, and legions of angels
would have come to his aid. No, he fulfilled the hardest course that any man has fulfilled
in this life. He died for those who did not love him. He died for those who were sinners when he
never one time in his 33 years sinned. Oh, Jesus fulfilled the plan of redemption that had been set
from before the foundation of the world, and I stand here tonight a saved man, not because of
anything in my life that I have done or accomplished, but simply by the grace of the Lord
Jesus Christ. And that is true of you if you're saved tonight. And I thank God that Jesus fulfilled
all that was written of him. Now listen, we're not talking about David tonight because he was a king.
We're not talking about John Baptist tonight because he was the great and last of the Old
Testament prophets, and was the forerunner for Jesus Christ. We're not talking about Jesus
tonight because he was prophet and priest and king. I want you to understand what that word
fulfilled intimates in each of their lives. They fulfilled what someone else gave them to do. You
know what we call that? They were servants. They were servants. Look at verse 36. For David, after
he had served his own generation by the will of God, fell on sleep, was laid unto his fathers,
and saw corruption. But he whom God raised again saw no corruption. I don't think I do damage to
the scripture if I say to you, what is said of David is true also of John. What is said of David
is true also of Jesus, that they served their own generation, not by their own will, not in their
own way, but by the will of God Almighty. They were servants of God. I don't think you'll ever
read the name of Mike Edwards in Who's Who. I don't even know if they have Who's Who anymore.
I don't think that you'll ever read my biography unless I write it for myself. Don't intend to do
that. I don't think I'll ever be a king. I know I will never be a king. I will never be a great
prophet. I struggle to be a coherent preacher. I don't think, I know I will never attain to the
level of Jesus Christ, prophet, priest, and king. But I'll tell you what I can do. I can be a
servant. I can be a servant.
that's what I want to talk about tonight and it's outlined my sermon is outlined
in verse 36 number one they served number two and I'm gonna skip to the end
they served by the will of God and number three they served by the will of
God their own generation thought number one they served I love the word that is
chosen to be translated served in that verse God had many choices that he could
have made the Holy Spirit could have put the word diakonos in there because
deacons are most certainly servant and though we may not hold the office we can
serve with the spirit of the deacon he could have put doulas in there Paul
often referred to himself as a doulas a bondservant of the Lord Jesus Christ
that he owed Jesus so much that he bound his life to the life of the Lord and
served the Lord but he didn't choose diakonos he didn't choose doulas instead
he chose a word that if you were standing in the Greek market or the
Roman market and and you would have heard this word and someone referring to
someone else or to themselves as this word it would have turned heads I'm not
good or a Greek scholar but let me try to pronounce it it is the Greek word
hoop array hey oh hoop array hey oh that and seven dollars will get you a cup of
coffee at Starbucks but I love what it means it means literally to make
yourself an under rower you say what is an under rower pastor well I want you to
picture in your mind no doubt you've seen a picture of a Greek ship a Greek
galley or a Roman galley and most of them had a mast and they could be
powered by wind with a sail but a sail was not a trustworthy mode of power if
the wind wasn't blowing and if you were chasing someone running from one someone
or battling someone you needed a ready and steady mode of powering that ship
and so most of the time when you see those galleys you'll see one or two rows
of windows and out of that window you will see an oar and those great ships
were powered by those oars and those oars were manned not by the elite of
society not by the educated of society not by the Greek citizen not by the
Roman citizen they were manned by the lowest of slaves they were rode by those
who had nothing else to offer but a strong back strong arms and strong hands
and their sole duty in life was to row to the cadence of that Roman or Greek
officer as he beat the count on that drum and they rode and they rode and
they rode they had such little value in life that if they died at the oar and at
their seat their shackles were undone they were thrown overboard and a new
slave was put in their place I want you to get a hold of this David and John
Baptist and Jesus Christ so you know who I am I'm Hooper a tail I'm an under
rower I'm here to serve I'm not here with self-will I'm not here with
self-interest I'm not living a life that is so self-focused I'm not self-aware I
am here to serve someone other than myself I want to tell you my great fear
for Christianity in our day is that that word serve has been replaced with the
word and the concept of self it's all about me I'll never forget the first
time I heard the term many many years ago a seeker Church and I was sitting in
my office with one of my staff members and I said man that sounds awesome I
think we ought to be a seeker Church because I thought what it meant was
we'll go seek the lost and my staff member said preacher that's not what it
means it means that whatever you as someone in the community are seeking
will provide it for you just come to our church we have people who hunt for
churches not on the basis of how can I serve but on the basis of what's in it
for me hey I want churches to meet the needs of people please don't think
that's what I'm saying I'm I'm not saying that you ought not to get
anything out of church but when the focus of our lives is what's in it for
me we do not have the Spirit of Jesus the Spirit of John or the Spirit of
David and all of our positive thinking in all of our self-esteem and our
self-affirmation in in all of our selfies just let that just let that sink
into your mind do you ever take selfies I take selfies I don't anymore you say
preacher you got convicted about him no but my arm is short and this is all I
ever had in my picture and I said I don't think I want to broadcast that to
the world social media it's about me it's about me it's about me it's about
me here's what Jesus said Jesus called them unto him and said you know that the
princes of the Gentiles exercise dominion over them and they that are
great exercise authority upon them but it shall not be so among you but
whosoever will be great among you let him be your minister and whosoever will
be chief among you let him be your servant even as the Son of Man came not
to be ministered unto but to minister and give his life a ransom for many can
you imagine a church seminar founded on the principle hey gather we want you to
pay a registration fee because we want to teach you that you're nothing it
wouldn't be well attended would it but it is the model that Jesus left for us
more than that it is the model that Jesus lived in his life I never forget
when we in our starting our churches have been 40 years ago we had moved out
of the high school and we had purchased a very ramshackle the old building on a
couple of acres three acres and and we were trying to make it presentable and
my wife and I were in there painting and we had just hired an assistant part
time and he was in there painting with us and the phone rang and I had to go
down and take a phone call legitimate I had to deal with something about 20
minutes later I'm walking back down the hall towards the nursery that we were
painting and and I hear this conversation I hear this young assistant
say to my wife I didn't go to Bible college for years to paint walls he did
not have an appreciation of who he was talking to I heard her say back to him
no we got saved to do this who do we think we are can I remind us tonight
that we are under rollers we are servants we are saved to serve listen
David understood that being the king brought not only the privilege of the
office but the responsibility of service I think of how many years that man even
though he had been anointed to be king and God had taken his hand off of Saul
he humbled himself and served Saul you talk about tough to swallow serving a
guy whom you know you're replacing and he did it right and sweetly I think of
David understanding the need to serve the less fortunate men that couldn't
give back to him as he brought lame Mephibosheth the son of Jonathan to his
palace and set him at his table and gave him a perpetual place at his table
he understood the need to serve as God as he prepared materials for the temple
that God had told him no you can't build it I don't know about you but boy I
don't know about you but I don't know about you but I don't know about you
I'd have probably been upset about that and say,
well, okay, if I can't build it,
if I can't get the glory from it,
then let Solomon figure it out.
But you know what David did?
Because he had a servant's heart
and he knew he was an under rower,
David said, let me gather the materials,
let me get the plans drawn, let me get it figured out
and let me take it all to my son Solomon
and give it to him to be done.
And it's amazing to me today,
even though David did all of that,
it is called Solomon's Temple.
And David has no issue with that.
Because David had a servant's heart.
It wasn't all about him.
John the Baptist certainly understood servanthood.
As that powerful, dynamic man stood there and said,
he must increase, I must decrease.
What a powerful thought.
To know that you possess real ability,
to know that you have a great following,
to know that your name is well known
and to willingly say, I will be submissive to this one
and to this one whom I have prepared the way,
I will gladly allow him to surpass me.
What a man.
Look to Jesus and you know what you'll find?
You'll find him the king of glory with a towel
and a basin washing the feet of his disciples.
He's all, we call them disciples,
but can we just make a little bit of understanding
of who they are?
He's washing the feet of a man who will sell him for 30,
or has sold him for 30 pieces of silver.
He's washing the feet of a man who will deny him three times
when it comes down to it.
He's washing the feet of all of those
who when he is arrested will forsake him and run.
We sometimes get all upset with Thomas or Peter or Judas.
We do realize every one of them forsook him.
I don't know about you, but that night in the upper room,
I might have looked up in Peter's eyes and says,
you know, I'm not gonna wash the dirty feet of a denier.
I feel pretty sure I'd have struggled
with the feet of Judas.
And I'll tell you, I'd have come to John
and I'd have looked at John and said,
man, you laid your head on my chest.
You're known as the disciple of love and you're gonna run.
And yet he dutifully washed their feet,
gave what they needed.
My favorite parable, or one of them,
is that of the Good Samaritan in Luke 10.
And I won't belabor this, but there were three men,
there was a Jew who had been on business
or been to temple or whatever,
but he had been set upon by robbers
and he had been left in the ditch, ready to die,
bleeding, not gonna make it.
And the Bible tells us that three men came down that road.
The first man that came down that road was a priest.
If anybody should know the heart of compassion of God,
certainly it would be a priest
who had a course of duty in the temple.
He would understand the heart of God.
But the Bible says before he even came to the man,
he crossed to the other side of the road and walked on by.
Bible says the next man down the road was a Levite.
Hey, a man who studied the word, a man who led worship,
a man who knew who God was.
And the Bible says that when he saw the man,
he came over and looked upon him.
I see him in my mind, kneeling and looking
in that beaten, dying man saying, where's the preacher?
You see, it's always the preacher's job
to go down into the ditch and to serve in that humble way.
But the real point of the parable is,
it's every believer's job.
Because every believer is called to serve.
That Samaritan comes down the road.
If anybody should have a reason not to go down in that ditch
it is the Samaritan.
But the Bible teaches us that he got down off of his donkey,
went down into that ditch using his own resources,
bound up the wounds of that man, carried that man,
put him on his donkey, took him to the inn,
paid for his stay, and at the end of it,
God just asks us a simple question, who is his neighbor?
Oh, we want to be seen as believers and loving people
and serious in our walk for the Lord.
And we don't have a moment for a lost, bleeding generation.
The Bible college that I went to
outside the administration building
had this on a stone monument, this saying,
enter to learn, go forth to serve.
And I've walked past that a thousand times
and I've thought to myself, that's kind of a nice saying,
I'm not quite sure what it is,
but enter to learn, go forth to serve.
And I'll tell you, the longer I've pastored,
I've understood it.
You know what we are these days?
We enter to learn, we enter to learn, we enter to learn.
Who put the coffee on?
Who's got the donuts?
Because we're having Bible study.
We enter to learn, we enter to learn.
We've got a meeting, oh, what a speaker.
We've got to, we enter to learn, we enter to learn,
we enter to learn.
And so rarely go forth to serve.
And sometimes we just have to ask ourselves,
is this the Christianity that Jesus intended?
That we know all about him,
and yet never get off of our donkey
and get down in the ditch
with a bleeding and lost generation and try to help them.
Not only did they serve, they served by the will of God.
Notice that with me.
I'll say this to you, the world has never been
greatly impressed with anyone doing the will of God.
If you're waiting for somebody to applaud you
and your neighbor, oh, look at that,
they're going to church on Tuesday night.
Aren't they awesome?
They look at you and think, what's wrong with them?
If they knew that you tithed and gave to missions,
they'd say, what in the world?
I'm just saying to you that the world
has never been impressed with anybody doing the will of God.
But can I suggest to you that the wisdom of man
is foolishness in the eyes of God?
And you and I ought to find the will of God
and do it regardless of what any man thinks.
Michael thought it was foolish that David danced
before the ark when the ark was brought into Jerusalem,
but it was a day of rejoicing in the will of God.
Judas thought it was absolutely silly and wasteful
for Jesus to be anointed with that expensive oil,
but it was the will of God.
Peter rebuked the Lord for saying he was going to suffer
and die upon the cross, but it was the will of God.
And I say to us tonight, let the world have its opinions.
Let formal Christendom have its opinions.
Our lives and our ministries are not based
on the approval of the world.
They are based on the commandments
and the ultimate approval of God
as God set forth how he wants us to live.
The world may scoff at preaching,
but preaching is still the will of God.
The Bible howls at the thought of holy living.
Why don't you do what all the rest of us do?
Well, because God's not pleased with some of those things.
Obey God.
World hates confrontational soul winning,
telling a man that he's a sinner,
telling a woman that she needs to know Jesus Christ.
The world hates that and in many places
tries to outlaw that, but it is the will of God.
The world may sneer at parents
who accept the God given responsibility
of training our own children, but it is the will of God.
And you and I have to make a fundamental decision
that I'm going to serve and I'm going to serve
not in a modern way, not in a way
that's acceptable to the world,
but in a way that is acceptable and pleasing to the Lord.
Now mark this.
When I come into this room and I'm on live stream
preaching at Fellowship Baptist Church,
I love the stuff I'm saying.
Hey, preaching is what God wants.
Soul winning is what we need to do.
Holy living is what we need to pursue.
And you know why I love to do it?
I love to get kind of wild with it
and I love preaching like that.
You know why?
Because most everybody agrees with me in here.
You know where I'm not near as excited about it?
Out there, where absolutely nobody.
wants to hear what I have to say. Can I remind you of something? Jesus came unto
his own and his own received him not and therefore Jesus decided not to go to the
cross, not to humble himself and decided to go back to heaven and let mankind
find him. That's not true is it? He was forsaken, he was denied, he was rejected
and he marched right on to the cross because, ready for this? He was an underroar.
Well I'm not going to tell somebody about Jesus because they they might
think less of me. Hey, how can you think less of an underroar? The question we
need to ask ourselves is, who do we think we are? Are we too good to follow in the
steps of our Savior? Are we too good when he emptied himself and made of himself
no reputation and took upon himself the form of a servant and was obedient unto
death, even the death of the cross? Who do we think we are? Too good, too busy.
Friends, we're underroars and our calling in life is to, as our Master did not come
to be ministered to, but instead came to minister and give his life a ransom for
many. Let me speak finally, just a moment on this thought. Our generation, who did
you ever think you would live in a world like we live in? Can I be honest
with you? I hope you'll let me and not think less of me. Sometimes in my life I
just come to the place where I would like to take any money that I have and
go up in the deepest holler of West Virginia and buy a couple hundred acres
and at the opening of the holler just put a wall. I would take my wife and my
kids, I'd definitely take my dog, I would take my grandchildren, my children, both
of my friends, I've only got two, and I would close that wall off and I would
say, leave us alone. But you see, that life would indicate that I am self-interested,
self-serving, self-focused. That would mean I was the guy who didn't want to be
bothered with the bleeding man in the ditch and I was the guy who looked at
him and thought somebody should help him, but it can't be me, I can't do that.
No, we are called to engage with this generation. Can I be honest with you? The
behavior of this generation is repugnant to me. I don't know all the letters, but
LGBTQ, that's a lifestyle that I don't believe is consistent with the Word of God.
I don't understand all the drug use, I don't understand all the piercings, I don't understand
all the tats, I don't understand, honestly, I don't understand how a legislature of men and
women can vote on a bill that allows a baby to be born and then slain in the delivery room,
and then when you sign the bill that allows that, an entire legislature stands and applauds. That's
repulsive. But they're ours. They're our generation. And somewhere, somehow, you and I
have to remember that God placed us here at this time and he knew all of those things, and yet he
says to us, serve by the will of God your generation. Sometimes it's so big that I don't
see how it can possibly be done, and it's so awful that I don't feel like I want to even be part of
it. I don't know how you win this world, I don't know how you win this city, I don't know how you
win this community, but I do know this. I know how to see a guy lying in a ditch and trying to help
him. I won't belabor this, but I guarantee you something. If I could draw a five-mile circle
around this church tonight, I could find some certain things. I guarantee you I could find a
man who was injured, perhaps, at work. I'm making this up. And for a time, the company was helping
him, and they were writing prescriptions for painkillers, and boy, he just really was hurting.
And then the doctor said, well, I can't write those prescriptions anymore, and the pain was still
there. And he started looking for those pills somewhere else. And you say, wow, he's really in
bad shape, and his family is suffering because of it. Boy, that's weak. I can't stand that kind of
person. I don't want to be around that kind of person. Hey, I guarantee you that man, he can't go
to his work, his boss, and say, man, I'm hooked. I'm stuck. What do I do? He'll be fired. But I do
know a group of people who know the answer for that man. It's not a simple answer, but the answer
is Jesus Christ. That guy you work with, that you know he's having trouble in his home, that kid that
you go to school with, and you know they're going down the wrong path. I'm saying to us, look, I
can't win a city. I can't win a nation. I can't win a world. But I can be a servant. I can be a
friend to a man or woman that God leads me by, who is lying in a ditch, bleeding and dying. But
we've become so self-interested, so self-focused, that we, like the priest, run by because we've
got to get to our job in the commute, you know, and because Saturday's our only day, you know,
and because, oh well, you know, I'm not good at that, you know. Hey, can I remind you that we
are under rowers? Can I remind you that but by the grace of God, that's us? As a matter of fact,
some of us who are saved today, that was us. You know what I'm asking God to do tonight? To remind
us of who we are. To remind us that we are servants. And yes, we live in a horrendously
ugly generation. They save whales and kill babies. I get it. They have more sympathy for a puppy than
for a human being. But they are our generation. And God has placed us here for such a time as
this. And it is time that we stop building empires in our churches and stop looking for what pleases
me and what I like and why isn't someone serving me. Why, you forgot me, me, me, me, an under rower.
Nobody needs to coddle you. We're just under rowers. You there at livestream and you in this
room, here's what I'm asking God to do. In all the stages of our life and all the places of our life,
you and I have someone that we come in contact with that is a bleeding, dying person in a ditch.
We rush past them or we hope someone will help them. We hope someone will deal with them. I'm
asking God to lay a name on your heart. Not a city, not a nation, a name. Might be someone that
you already know and God has spoken to your heart. Might be somebody you work with. It might be the
neighbor next door and you
know that lady is so unhappy, and you know that she's in distress, and you know
it. She doesn't know where to turn, but you know the answer. You know Jesus
Christ is the answer. But until we come to the place in our lives where we are
willing to fulfill what God has given us to do amongst this generation in which
he's placed us, we'll be the priest hurrying by. We'll be the Levite wishing
somebody would do something. We need to get down off our donkeys and get down in
the ditch and be the friend to that person, the servant to that person with
the ideal and hope of leading them to Jesus Christ. Would you pray with me?
Father, I pray that every head is bowed in this room, every head is bowed in
these homes, and Holy Spirit, I ask you to do something just now. Would you please,
in the quietness of this moment, would you lay a name on the heart of every
believer that is listening? Maybe a neighbor or a workmate, it may be someone
they go to school with, maybe someone that comes to church, maybe someone they
know from business, but God, would you speak to their heart and lay that name
on their heart? And in the next days and weeks to come, I pray that these folks
that you've laid the name on their heart will be intentional with you,
asking you, God, to help them. Well, I can't deliver the gospel. You can be a friend
and a help. You can show love to a person that desperately needs it. You can get
them to Jesus. And I pray that they would purpose in their hearts, Lord, if you'll
lay someone on my heart, I will minister to that person with the goal of leading
them to Jesus Christ. I know it's hard, but God, we are servants. Lord, I pray for
those who are under the sound of my voice that you didn't lay a name on
their heart. I ask them to do this. Will you, in this invitation, ask God to lay
someone on your heart? Lord, help us. We curse the darkness, we're repulsed by the
sin of the world that surrounds us, and yet we so focus on ourselves that we
never reach a handout. We're never even convicted to tell somebody Jesus loves
them. We're never even moved to give them a track. Lord, break that selfishness in
our hearts tonight. Lay someone on our heart, and may we purpose to lead that
one to Jesus by serving, serving them. Help us, I pray, in Jesus' name. Amen.