chapter number two, Genesis chapter number two,
be looking at verses four down through verse number 23.
And if you notice in the bulletin this evening,
the title for the message is Life in the Garden of Eden.
As we continue to move through the book of Genesis,
it's important right here at this juncture
that we understand the perspective
of Genesis one and Genesis two.
There's been much discussion and debate
about the content of Genesis one and Genesis two.
And some that would look at it as being contradictory,
the one to the other, and the perspective
in which the account is given with regard to creation,
and so on and so forth.
If you'll recall a couple of weeks ago,
as we looked at verses 26 through 28,
where God created man, I mentioned to you
that there were additional details
that were provided to us about the how
that God did it in chapter number two.
We referenced some of that briefly.
But really as we look at the word of God,
we examine Genesis chapter number one,
really what you discover is that it's a record,
if you will, a summary of the creative acts
that God himself did during the six days of creation.
And we understand that it just goes very sequential
in order, and we've started, we've studied
through those 31 verses of Genesis chapter number one,
and we see how that God is providing us
with a summary record of that which he did
during those six days.
Some have referenced and used the analogy
that Genesis one is like a floodlight on creation
in its entirety, seeing all of the six days
and what God did in summary.
We find that as we come to Genesis chapter number two,
there are further specifics that are given to us
with regard to what God did specifically
on the sixth day of creation.
And as we examine this second chapter,
we discover that those greater details
with regard to certain aspects or events of creation
on day number six, we understand as we've mentioned
throughout the study so far,
that the pinnacle of creation,
and we think about the sixth day
and the fact that man was created
and how that in Genesis one,
we have 31 verses that deal with the creation of all things.
And really, as we get into chapter number two,
we find the placement of God's first created human beings
in their home, in their place where they would abide.
And from that point until the end of the book of Revelation,
you see God's interaction with man.
The theme of the Bible as we really look at it
is that God is providing us with the plan of redemption.
And we understand that it's in Genesis chapter number three
that sin enters into the world,
but we find as we study the entirety of the word of God
and we look at this truth
that man is God's most treasured creation,
then we understand that God begins to provide more specifics
about that creation that took place on day number six.
Just as some would refer to Genesis chapter number one
as being summarized and use the analogy of a floodlight,
they would then take and use the analogy
in Genesis chapter number two
with regard to these specific details of events
that were done on day number six
as really being a spotlight on those specific things.
Does that make sense to you?
You think about a floodlight,
it just kind of lights up a broad area,
you see things in its broadness,
but a spotlight kind of focuses in
and the purpose is to give the detail of that
which is before us and we find that God provides
some of that for us with regard to the creation of man
and we see that with Adam and Eve
here in Genesis chapter number two.
The focus, as we would understand here
in verse number four of Genesis two,
the focus at this point turns to man,
God's most treasured creation in dealing with man
and we would look at Genesis chapter number two
and we'd understand it as being the state of innocency.
The fact that man was created in a perfect environment,
God created man without sin, they were perfect
and in a perfect environment in all of that innocence
and yet when you come to Genesis chapter number three,
you find that man falls, that sin enters into the world.
So the period of time of Genesis chapter number two,
though there's no dates that are ascribed here
that are given to us, we would agree
that this period of time from verses four of Genesis two
down through the beginning of Genesis chapter number three
was a very brief period of time
in which man lived in complete innocence.
Notice in verse number four, the Bible says this,
these are the generations of the heavens and of the earth
when they were created and the day that the Lord God
made the earth and the heavens.
And every plant of the field before it was in the earth
and every herb of the field before it grew,
for the Lord God had not caused it to rain upon the earth
and there was not a man to till the ground.
There went up a mist from the earth, verse number six,
and watered the whole face of the ground.
In verse number seven, it says,
and the Lord God formed man of the dust of the ground
and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life
and man became a living soul.
The Lord God planted a garden eastward in Eden
and there he put the man whom he had formed
and out of the ground made the Lord God to grow every tree
that is pleasant to the sight and good for food,
the tree of life also in the midst of the garden
and the tree of knowledge of good and evil.
The river went out of Eden to water the garden
and from thence it was parted and became into four heads.
The name of the first, Basan,
that is it which composeth the whole land of Havala
where there is gold.
The gold of that land is good.
There's Delium and the Onyx Stone
and the name of the second river is Gayan,
the same is it that composeth the whole land of Ethiopia.
Verse 14, the name of the third river is Hittical,
that is it which goeth toward the east of Assyria
and the fourth river is Euphrates.
The Lord God took man and put him into the garden of Eden
to dress it and to keep it.
The Lord God commanded the man saying
of every tree of the garden thou mayest freely eat,
notice verse 17, but of the tree of the knowledge
of good and evil thou shalt not eat of it
for the day that thou eatest thereof thou shalt surely die.
The Lord God said it is not good
that the man should be alone,
I will make him and help me for him.
And out of the ground the Lord God formed
every beast of the field and every fowl of the air
and brought them unto Adam to see what he would call them
and whatsoever Adam called every living creature
that was the name thereof.
And Adam gave names to all cattle
and to the fowl of the air and to every beast of the field
but for Adam there was not found and help me for him.
Notice verse 21, the Lord God caused a deep sleep
to fall upon Adam and he slept and he took one of his ribs
and closed up the flesh instead thereof
and the rib which the Lord God had taken from man
made he a woman and brought her unto the man.
And Adam said this is now bone of my bones
and flesh of my flesh, she shall be called woman
because she was taken out of man.
As we look at this account that is given to us here
in Genesis chapter number two, I want you to notice
first of all if you're taking notes,
the details of God's work.
We understand that in Genesis chapter number one
that record is given to us, the summary of God's creation
and now God provides us with some further detail
in chapter number two.
We find that in verses four through six
he deals with the plant life and he talks about the climate
at that particular time of creation and how things were done
we see once again the maturity of God's creation.
The Bible says every plant of the field in verse number five
before it was in the earth and every herb of the field
before it grew for the Lord God had not caused it
to rain upon the earth, there was not a man
to till the ground.
And we find that what he's referring to here
in verses four through six and verses five and six
in particular dealing with the plant life
and the climate and what have you is looking back
to day number three of creation.
And we understood even as we mentioned
as we studied the third day of creation
that God spoke into existence all of that plant life
and we spoke about the maturity, they weren't saplings
and seedlings and so on and so forth
but it was mature creation in plant life
and here he referenced that the details are given to us
with regard to that process.
As we continue moving forward we find that in verse
number seven more information is given to us
with regard to this event on day number six of creation
when God formed man.
Now you remember back in Genesis chapter number one
in verse number 27 the Bible says so God created man
in his own image and the image of God created he him,
male and female created he them.
There is no contradiction in the word of God.
God's word is in perfect harmony and we find that God
is simply providing us with further detail
with regard to the forming of man.
Here in verse number seven he provides that detail
in forming of Adam and it says the Lord God formed man
of the dust of the ground and breathed into his nostrils
the breath of life and man became a living soul.
Once again we see the,
of God's interaction with creating man, again man being his prized creation, and
we understand as we would study the entirety of the Word of God, the way in
which God interacts with mankind, and here we find that in Genesis 1 he talks
about how God created man in his own image, and then he tells us what he did,
and you see his involvement in the creation in many of the other instances
throughout many of the other days of creation, God said and it was so, but here
we find that there's that personal touch, if you will, where the Bible says in
verse 7, the Lord God formed man of the dust of the ground, and breathed into his
nostrils the breath of life, and man became a living soul. We continue looking
at the details of creation that are provided here in chapter number two, we
find that in the forming of beast and fowl, as it is mentioned in verses 19
and 20, where the Bible talks about out of the ground the Lord God formed every
beast of the field and every fowl of the air, he brought them unto Adam to see
what he would call them, whatsoever Adam called every living creature, that was
the name thereof. Adam gave names, the Bible tells us in verse number 20, to all
cattle, to the fowl of the air, to every beast of the field, but for Adam there
was not found, and help me for him. And so part of the responsibility that God
had given to Adam, evidently, on day number six, now we understand the order
of creation that is given to us in Genesis 1, the beast of the field was
created first, right? And then man was created, we see that, and as God would
begin to provide this spotlight in Genesis chapter number 2, he's not
necessarily given us the sequence of things, but he's showing us that he's
given Adam the responsibility of naming all of these creatures that he created
that are referenced in verses 19 and 20. He didn't give us that information in
chapter number 1, but he's kind of zeroing in and sharing with us some of
the details of the work that he did. He then talks about making a woman, Eve, that
is created here, and we find that in verses 18 and then also in verses 21
through 23. As we look at the details that are provided, in verse number 18 it
says, the Lord God said it is not good that the man should be alone, I will make
him and help me for him. Now many would, many scoffers would say, well, there's
contradiction here because in chapter number one it says that he created man
in his own image, in the image of God created he him, male and female created
he them. Yes, it's exactly what he did. And again, he's providing us with details
here, specifics, zeroing in, and we understand here that God in all of his
knowledge, remember throughout the record of creation, were aware of God's
omniscience and God's omnipotence. And he understood, no doubt because of the
record of Genesis 1, that he was going to create male and female. He created both
on day number six of creation. We dealt with some of the things that are
answered by that, some of the problems that we deal with in our own society
even still today, but we look here and we find that the Bible tells us the details
in verse 21, the Lord God caused a deep sleep to fall upon Adam and he slept and
he took one of his ribs and closed up the flesh instead thereof. And notice
with me in verse 22, the Bible says the rib which the Lord God had taken from
man made he a woman and brought her unto the man. And you find that that's
very interesting to understand the way in which the language is used here in
verse number 22 to speak about the creation of Eve and how God did it,
but then how God brought her to Adam. Because remember back in verse number
18, he says, it's not good that man should be alone. I will make for him and help
me. It says in verse number 20, for Adam there was not found in help me for him
because he was naming all the animals and it was not yet that God brought Eve
to Adam. And we find that here the Bible says that Adam says in verse number 23,
this is now bone of my bones, flesh of my flesh, she shall be called woman because
she was taken out of man. Let me say that there's no contradiction in Scripture,
I've mentioned that already, but notice over the New Testament if you will, let's
look at a couple of verses in 1st Corinthians chapter 11, and we'll also
look over at what Paul says in 1st Timothy chapter 2, but as God gives us
some further insight and some further details here in Genesis chapter 2, he
provides us with the details of his work here of some of those events of day
number 6. Again, I've said it often through this study, this is the several
months now that we've been in this study, the book of Genesis, and I've often said
that God is the one that created it all and he could give us the very specific
details of every single action that he took if he chose to do so. He's not
chosen to give us all of those specific details, but he could, he's God, he's the
one that did it, but we find that the perspective of Genesis 2 focusing once
again on man, because the entirety of the rest of the Word of God is going to deal
with mankind and his relationship with God. Here in 1st Corinthians chapter 11,
notice in verse number 8, the Bible says, "...for the man is not of the woman, but the
woman of the man," referring back to creation, right? And we just read of that
and that process in which God formed man, and then as he took the rib out of the
the side thereof and he formed Eve, and it says in verse number 9, "...neither was the
man created for the woman, but the woman for the man, for this cause ought the
woman to have power on her head because of the angels." Notice verse 11,
"...nevertheless neither is the man without the woman, neither the woman without the
man in the Lord, for as the woman is of the man," notice the latter part, "...even so is
the man also by the woman, but all things of God." And so we find that in verse
number 8, Paul references creation. It was man first and then it was woman, that was
the account that's given to us in Genesis chapter number 2 that we've
just been studying, but then he speaks in verse number 12
about reproduction or childbearing. After Adam and Eve were formed, every single
human being that's been born has been born of woman, amen? And that's what he
deals with here in verse number 12, "...for as the woman is of the man, even so is
the man also by the woman." And here he says at the end of that, "...but all things
of God," and we do understand God's blessing in that. First Timothy chapter
number 2 and verse number 13, the Bible simply declares, "...for Adam was first
formed, then Eve." Adam was first formed, then Eve. And God gives us that detail in
Genesis chapter number 2 that we're studying this evening. We see the details
of God's work as it's given to us here, specifically of day number 6. Now notice
the description of man's home, and we begin to understand here what is taking
place and where Adam and Eve are planted, where they're placed here in
the Garden of Eden, life in Eden, and we find the description that is given to us
with regard to man's home. Back in Genesis chapter number 2 in verse number
8, we would understand that it was a place prepared by God for man. The Bible
says, "...and the Lord God planted a garden eastward in Eden, and there he put the
man whom he had formed." And so we find that this place, Eden as it's referred to,
was a place that was specifically prepared by God for his creation of
human beings, for Adam and Eve to dwell in that place. And not only was it a
place that was prepared by God, but it was a place that we understand here that
man was placed there by God. So God prepared the place, but then God then
placed man there, as it says at the end of verse number 8, "...and there he, God, put
the man whom he had formed." Notice over in verse number 15 where the Bible says,
"...and the Lord God took the man and put him into the Garden of Eden to dress it
and to keep it." And so this place, the Garden of Eden, is a place that was
specifically prepared by God for mankind, but we also find that it was God that
placed mankind in there specifically. It was a pleasant place. Notice in verse
number 9, "...out of the ground made the Lord God to grow every tree." It says this,
"...that is pleasant to the sight and good for food." We find that it was a pleasant
place, it was a perfect place. I've mentioned already by way of introduction
that as we look at Genesis chapter number 2 and we look at the creation and
everything being good and everything being perfect, that it was there in that
age, that state of innocency. The Bible ends in chapter number 2 at the end of
the passage, it says, "...and they were both naked, the man and his wife, and were not
ashamed." Because there was no sin that had entered into the world at that
particular point from the human perspective. And we find that
humanity falls into sin in Genesis chapter number 3, and so there's this
place of innocence and this place of perfection. It was a pleasant place. We
find that God, in giving us a description of man's home, he says that there he
planted to grow every tree that is planted, excuse me, that is pleasant to
the sight. And so we find that there were a number of trees there, but then God
specifically, in verse number 9, mentions
two trees specifically.
The first one is the tree of life.
He says, the tree of life also in the midst of the garden.
And then he says, and the tree of knowledge
of good and evil.
And so all of these trees that were there,
that were pleasant, that were good for food,
but God specifically zeroes in on two particular trees
as he provides us with the description of man's home,
the tree of life and the tree of knowledge
of good and evil.
We find that he speaks about a river
that becomes into four heads as it's given to us
in verses 10 down through verse number 14.
And we've read the text of scripture
and we see the names of those rivers
and the way in which they parted
and the regions in which they went.
It's important for us to understand
as we read verses 10 through 14,
there are many today that said,
oh, we wanna find where the garden of Eden is.
And the problem is that during the catastrophic event
that we understand as being the flood, the global flood,
it had a great impact, excuse me,
upon the terrain of earth.
We find that the depths were broken up
and I mean, all sorts of things took place
and no doubt even as we would understand
that a couple of these words that are used
that are places that we would be familiar with today
through world geography,
that most likely what was happening
is that these things were named that after the flood
by Noah and his descendants
because of the similarities prior to the flood.
But the reality is that the flood
had a catastrophic impact upon the earth
as it had originally been created.
Peter deals with that in 2 Peter chapter number three
and we've referenced that passage of scripture in the past.
We'll do so again in the future
as we get into Genesis six through eight
in dealing with the flood specifically.
We find that he then also mentions to us
in providing a description of man's home,
he provides with us here the responsibility that man has.
And it's interesting, he says in verse number 15,
the Lord God took the man
and put him into the garden of Eden
to dress it and to keep it.
And we find that with position always comes responsibility.
Man is placed into this position,
the price creation of God, if you will.
He's made a steward.
If you remember back in Genesis chapter number one
as we studied verses 26 through 28
and then we move forward in verses 29, 30 and 31
and we understood the responsibility
that God had given to mankind.
And here he tells them in verse number 15
to dress it and to keep it.
You would understand that after the fall of man,
that dressing and keeping of it
became a lot more difficult.
Why?
Because of the thistle, the thorn
and all of that impact of the fall.
And he tells man, in fact,
that thorns also and thistle shall it bring forth to thee
and thou shalt eat the herb of the field.
In the sweat of thy face shalt thou eat bread
till thou return unto the ground.
For out of it was thou taken,
for thus thou art and unto thus shalt thou return.
By the way, that is certainly in harmony
with what God tells us in verse number seven
of chapter number two,
that the Lord God formed man out of the dust of the ground.
Amen, there's consistency.
There is harmony there within the scriptures.
But we understand that even before sin entered
into the world and even before the negative impact
upon all of the creation,
that man had a responsibility there in the garden of Eden
to dress it and to keep it.
And that was a responsibility that they had.
No doubt, it was a pleasant experience.
I'm not sure how many of you enjoy pulling weeds today
and all the thorns and thistles,
but I know often as we're doing that job
and we think about the phrase that is given in verse 19,
in the sweat of thy face, amen,
and you're out there pulling weeds.
I was looking at the parking lot sidetrack, right?
Rabbit trail, but I was looking at the parking lot
on Friday and I'm like, how in the world
are these weeds growing in the parking lot?
It's like 150 degrees on this parking lot
and these things are green and growing and thriving.
Are you kidding me?
They should die, right?
That's what I'm thinking.
Oh, it's work, you gotta deal with it.
But there was work in the garden even before the fall,
but no doubt it was a pleasant experience for Adam
and it was something that they were given as a responsibility
because of that position that they held.
We notice that here, not only do we find the details
and the description, the details of God's work,
the description of man's home,
but notice with me the decree of God.
I'm gonna focus in in our latter part
of our message this evening in verses 16 and 17
and looking at the decree of God.
God issues a decree here and the Bible says,
the Lord God commanded the man.
It's interesting if you wanna mark that phrase there
at the beginning of verse number 16,
here is the first reference in all of the Bible
where God commands man.
We find that throughout the Scriptures,
we'll find many instances as we move forward
through the book of Genesis
and we continue studying the Word of God,
we'll find many instances where God commands His creation.
But here is the very first reference
in all of the Scriptures where God issues a decree,
where He commands man.
Understand with me this evening that as the Creator,
He has every right to command His creation.
Amen?
He's God, He is the Creator.
And the Bible says, the Lord God commanded the man saying,
notice here in this command that the Bible gives us,
first of all, what was permitted in verse number 16.
He says, of every tree of the garden, thou mayest freely eat
but verse number 17 begins with a but, a conjunction.
He's going to not only speak about that which is permitted
but that which is prohibited.
And we find that verse number 17 deals with that
which is prohibited.
And I want you to understand this evening
as we look at this decree of God,
that I believe that it was very gracious and kind
for God to communicate His command with His creation.
Amen?
It was gracious and kind for God to communicate
to His creation, to mankind, this decree.
And we look at the scriptures and we look at their entirety
and we understand the various commands
that God gives to us as His people.
And I believe this evening that our perspective
must be changed and we would come to that place
where we'd understand, thank you God
for giving me these commands.
Thank you God for giving me this direction
and this instruction.
Thank you for communicating this to me.
And I believe here that as we look at these verses
of scripture that we would conclude that it was in fact
gracious and kind of our God to communicate His command
with His creation.
What was permitted is given to us in verse 16
but verse 17 is that which was prohibited.
The Bible says, but of the tree of the knowledge
of good and evil, notice thou shall not eat of it.
That's pretty simple, is it not?
Pretty simple command.
We find that in verse number nine as God mentioned
about the trees, every tree that is pleasant to the sight,
good for food, but He references as we mentioned
during our previous point of the description of the home,
of the garden, that there was the tree of life
and there was the tree of knowledge of good and evil.
He tells them in verse number 16,
of all the trees that are there,
of every tree of the garden, thou mayest freely eat,
but of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil,
thou shall not eat of it.
He then tells them in giving this command
the consequence of violating that which God has given.
He says, thou shall not eat of it.
For in the day that thou eatest thereof,
thou shalt surely die.
It was a simple command with a known consequence.
The reality this evening is that we understand
what happens in Genesis chapter number three.
We're familiar with the account
and the fall of mankind and the partaking
of the fruit of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil
as we would understand that truth given to us
in Genesis chapter number three.
But here as we look at the decree of God
and we understand this command that was given
and He tells them very specifically,
He says, listen, thou shalt not eat of it.
And then He gives them the consequence.
For in the day that thou eatest thereof,
thou shalt surely die.
Now they were in a place of perfection, of innocence.
God created them in a perfect environment,
put them in a perfect garden.
We've noticed the description that is given to us
here in Genesis chapter number two of man's home,
their initial home on that day where God created them
and He placed them in that garden
and how He provided for them.
all of their needs from it, everything that they needed.
The Bible tells us, no doubt, in chapter number three,
as we'd read through it and we'd study through
what's taking place, that it says in verse number eight,
they heard the voice of the Lord God walking in the garden,
the cool of the day, and Adam and his wife hid themselves
from the presence of the Lord God
among the trees of the garden.
And God says in verse number nine, where art thou?
He said, I heard thy voice in the garden.
I was afraid because I was naked and I hid myself.
And we would find that as we'd read Genesis chapter number
three, that evidently they had enjoyed,
according to the time in Genesis chapter number two,
they had enjoyed fellowship with God, amen?
It was not an unusual thing for God to enter into the garden
as he did in Genesis chapter number three
in verse number eight.
It was not an unusual event for that to take place.
And in Genesis chapter number two, as they're there
created in this perfect environment,
in this state of innocence, we find
that they enjoyed all of God's beauty
and all of God's creation, and they
had that sweet fellowship and communion with God.
Some have asked the question, why did God even
create the tree of knowledge of good and evil?
Why is it that God even prohibited
the eating of the fruit of that particular tree?
The reality is that God did not make man as a robot.
He created man with a free will.
He created man as a moral agent with the ability
to make decisions.
And we find that God's desire throughout the scriptures
that is revealed to us is he certainly
desires to have the fellowship of his creation of mankind,
but he desires that fellowship not out of necessity,
but out of that heart of desiring
to spend that time in communion with our God,
that choice that we make.
And here, Adam and Eve created in this perfect environment,
and we find the decree of God is given.
Now, we understand that God in all of his wisdom,
in all of his knowledge and being omniscient,
that he knew the events that would take place
in Genesis chapter number three.
He was well aware of the fact that man would sin,
that man would partake of that fruit of the tree of knowledge
of good and evil.
He understood that sin would enter into the world.
He understood that he would have to take the place
and die for the human race.
The Bible tells us over there in 1 Peter
that he is the lamb that was slain before the foundation
of the world.
Amen?
And that it's by his blood that we are redeemed,
and not redeemed with corruptible things,
but we're redeemed by the precious blood of Christ.
It's interesting, this evening as we study these verses
in Genesis chapter number two, and we think about life
in the garden, and though we do not
know the exact period of time that they spent in innocence
and in the garden prior to that temptation that
is recorded for us in chapter number three,
in verse number one, and the subsequent fall of mankind
with sin entering into the world,
though this specific time is not notated,
for however long it was, it was a perfect environment
of innocence.
It is interesting, however, as we
think about this garden of Eden, and we
think about the two trees that are mentioned,
the tree of life and the tree of knowledge of good and evil,
it is interesting to note that the Bible mentions
the tree of life later in Revelation chapter number 22.
Turn over, if you will, to the book of Revelation,
and we'll conclude with this thought this evening.
And I want you to understand that as we
look at the book of Revelation, and not
a study of Revelation this evening,
obviously, we find beginning in chapter number 21
that God begins to describe the eternal state.
The end of chapter number 20 records for us
that great white throne judgment.
The millennial kingdom is already past,
and that judgment takes place.
And whosoever has not found written the book of life
was cast in the lake of fire.
This is the second death.
And we begin to see the eternal state
as it's described for us in Revelation 21 and 22.
And I want you to notice in chapter 22, the Bible says,
and he showed me a pure river of water of life,
clear as crystal, proceeding out of the throne of God
and of the Lamb.
In the midst of the street of it and on either side of the river
was there, notice, the tree of life,
which bare 12 manner of fruits and yielded her fruit
every month.
And the leaves of the tree were for the healing of the nations.
The Bible says in verse 3, and there shall be no more curse.
The throne of God and of the Lamb shall be in it,
and his servant shall serve him.
And they shall see his face, and his name
shall be in their foreheads.
There shall be no night there, for they need no candle,
neither light of the sun.
For the Lord God giveth them light,
and they shall reign forever and ever.
Aren't those exciting words, encouraging words,
as we think about the eternal state?
But we notice that the tree of life is there.
The Garden of Eden, if you understand,
as the two trees that are mentioned,
there was the tree of life and the tree of knowledge
of good and evil.
And after man sinned, they were exiled from the garden,
correct?
They were no longer permitted to be in there.
The Lord God sent them out of the garden,
according to verse number 23 of Genesis chapter number 3,
and the reason why is mentioned to us in verse number 22.
And the Lord God said, behold, the man
has become as one of us to know good and evil.
And now, lest he put forth his hand
and take also of the tree of life and eat and live forever,
therefore the Lord God sent him forth from the Garden of Eden
to till the ground from whence he was taken.
That was God's grace, by the way,
in not allowing man to live forever
in that condition of sinful knowledge of good and evil.
Because this mortal is going to put on immortality, amen?
And we are going to, as we think about that passage
in Revelation 22, and we think about the reference
of the tree of life, during that time of innocence
in Genesis chapter number 2, the tree of life,
they could partake of the fruit of the tree of life.
There's no prohibition against eating of that tree.
In fact, God said, of every tree of the garden,
thou mayest freely eat.
And God specifically mentions in verse number 9
that one of the trees mentioned by name that's there
is the tree of life.
But you can't eat of the fruit of the tree of knowledge
of good and evil.
And when they partook of that tree, that fruit of that tree,
God said, we're going to expel man from the garden,
lest he partake of the tree of life
and live forever in this condition.
Praise God for his grace.
But then we come to the end of Revelation 22,
to the eternal state, and we see the tree of life is there.
What made it possible?
We read about the Garden of Eden.
Can I tell you a little bit this evening
about the Garden of Gethsemane?
Amen?
It was in the Garden of Gethsemane
where our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ,
according to Philippians chapter number 2,
that he humbled himself and became obedient unto death,
even the death of the cross.
If you read the accounts in the Gospels,
we find that John mentions about being there in the garden.
Turn over, in fact, we have just a few minutes.
Turn over to John 19, if you will.
And I want you to notice here what's taking place.
And actually look in chapter number 18,
and I want you to see here that as they're there,
that he had a place where he resorted.
And we find that Jesus was in that place,
and it was in the Garden of Gethsemane
where he was arrested, and they come and they take him.
And the Bible tells us in verse number one of John 18,
when Jesus had spoken these words,
he went forth with his disciples over the brook Kedron,
where was a garden into the which
he entered and his disciples.
And Judas also, which betrayed him,
notice what it says, knew the place,
for Jesus oft times resorted thither with his disciples.
Judas then, having received a band of men and officers
from the chief priests and Pharisees,
cometh thither with lanterns and torches and weapons,
Jesus therefore knowing all things that should come upon him.
What were those things?
Well, if you read chapter number 17, he says,
Father, the hour is come.
What's he speaking about?
I'm going to the cross of Calvary.
I'm going to finish the work that you gave me to do.
And we find that he says in verse number four of chapter 18,
Whom seek ye?
Can you imagine Jesus there knowing all things
that should come upon him?
He said to those that came in, to this group,
this band of men and officers that
are mentioned in verse number three
that come with lanterns and torches and weapons,
and he says, Whom seek ye?
They answered him, Jesus of Nazareth.
And Jesus said, I am he.
The Bible tells us, as soon then as he said unto them,
I am he, they went backward and fell to the ground.
We understand as you would read through the remainder
of the passage of Scripture, you can read
of the trials of Jesus.
And you can read in chapter number 19
of the scourging and the crucifixion.
And then you get into chapter number 20
and you read of the resurrection.
And we find that there was a tree of life in that garden,
the place where man was first placed.
And life in the garden was a perfect life.
It was a pleasant life.
It was a place that was specifically
prepared by God for his creation of mankind.
It was in that place where they sinned according to Genesis chapter 3 and no longer could they
partake of the tree of life.
They were expelled there in Genesis 3, but once again in the eternal state, the tree
of life will be present as we find in Revelation 22 and it's because of that work of our Lord
and Savior Jesus Christ on the cross of Calvary that started in the Garden of Gethsemane when
He was arrested there in John chapter 18 and He went to that cross.
And I tell you that according to what the writer of Hebrews tells us, the Bible tells
us that for the joy that was set before Him, He endured the cross, despising the shame
and is set down at the right hand of the throne of God.
I'm so thankful for the wisdom of God.
He created man in a perfect environment in a state of innocency.
We'll study more specifically as we move forward through the series as we get into the third
chapter of the book of Genesis, the fall and all of its consequences and what have you.
But as we look at life there in the garden, we find that God provides additional details
with regard to some of the events on day number six of creation.
He provides the description of man's home, but then the first command of God to His creation,
the decree of God is given in verses 16 and 17, and oh that we would take heed to the
commands of our God.
Amen?
He gave them a simple command and gave them a known consequence, and yet when we come
to the third chapter, we find that they broke that single command that they were given of
partaking of that tree of the knowledge of good and evil.
Let us pray together.