door hanger, Holly and I followed up
and visited with her last Saturday.
And as we went into her living room
and were chatting with her,
she had a Fellowship Baptist Church mug
from her visitor's bag that she was drinking
her coffee out of, hallelujah.
And I noticed it as soon as I got into the house
and then a few minutes after we were there,
she said, did you notice I got the mug from the bag?
And I said, praise the Lord, I did.
I'm pretty, you know, I try to be pretty observant.
And so anyway, praise the Lord.
She was excited about that.
And we're excited for the visitors that God sends us.
He's been sending us a lot of visitors,
a lot of follow-up opportunities,
a lot of things going on.
And so we're thankful.
And we've just got another list of new move-ins.
And so we're gonna get ready to put another group
of packets on the back table there for some new move-ins.
I know some of you helped us in the fall last year
with a number of those.
And so if you'd be interested in helping us again,
that would be a blessing as we try to reach our community
with the gospel.
Psalm 78, as you know, here on Wednesdays,
we've had the idea throughout the calendar year
at this point throughout 2026, a longing to see God work.
And it is truly my desire to see God work
in a distinct way in my life, in your life,
in our lives, in our church.
And I'm thankful that God is alive and well, aren't you?
And I know there's some movies or whatever
that were out there, God's Not Dead.
Listen, He's alive, He's well, He's got all power.
He's got as much power as He's ever had, amen.
And He is my King, He is King of Kings,
and He's got a plan.
And I'm so thankful you say, have you seen the news?
Not this week, but I know some things that are going on.
It's been a super busy week for me.
And so if it's something new that happened,
I'm not aware of it yet, unless Ronnie told me.
But the reality is that, listen,
you ask if you've seen the news,
I just wanna remind you to read the Bible, amen.
And I got an email, I didn't read the email.
I told you it's been a busy week, I didn't read the,
I'm teaching a Bible college class this week.
It's busy, busy, busy, but it's exciting
and thankful for the opportunity of Mods
will be able to teach some young people
and try to just invest in them.
And so it's been busy, but I got an email
and it talked about a coming economic collapse,
are you prepared?
And I didn't read the email,
I just read the title of the email.
And as soon as I read it,
the first thing I thought about
was Revelation chapter number six.
I think it's the third seal,
might actually be the second seal.
And it says that a day's wage
is gonna cover enough for a day's ration of food.
And I thought, no one's preparing for that, amen.
I mean, that's gonna happen and it's absolutely gonna come.
And we know those things
and we know that God is in control.
He's on his throne and I am thankful
that I am secure in his hand, amen.
And what a blessing.
And so we understand even as I prayed this evening,
our God is able to do exceeding abundantly
above all that we ask or think.
He's able and through the years in various contexts,
I've had conversations with different people,
sometimes other pastors, sometimes church members,
senior saints, that sort of thing.
And you just have conversations with people
and sometimes you'll hear somebody say something like this,
well, God just isn't working today like he once did.
I don't know if you've ever heard anyone make that statement
or have that perspective,
but I've heard that on more than one occasion
that people as they analyze, they see what's going on,
they say, God's just not working today like he once did.
And maybe they look back to biblical times
or maybe they look back to just maybe the heyday
of maybe the independent Baptist movement, if you will,
and church growth and some of the fastest growing,
largest growing churches in America in the 70s and 80s
were independent Baptist churches.
And you say, he's just not working like he once did.
And I always have this thought
when I hear somebody say that or have that perspective.
And my question is why?
Why do you have that perspective?
Why do you think that?
And why, if that's true, why is it true?
It's not because God isn't able to work.
It's not because God doesn't have the power
or the ability to work.
When we begin to look at the situation,
if it were true that God's not working today
like he has in the past,
it's not the fault does not lie within God,
it lies within God's people.
Now, I understand that sin limits God
and I understand that unbelief is sin.
We're not gonna focus specifically generally on sin.
Last week, we looked at a passage of scripture in Mark 9
and we talked about that statement
when the disciples come,
there's a great miracle that's performed.
The man that had a son that had a devil that possessed him
and he went to the disciples,
but his disciples could not do anything.
And Jesus then after an interaction with the man,
cast out and then forbade that devil
from entering again into that young man.
And we find that the disciples then privately said,
why could not we cast him out?
And he said, because of your unbelief.
Remember, we looked at that last week
because of your unbelief.
And then we find that the scriptures taught us
as we look through that portion of scripture
about the fact that this kind can come forth by nothing,
but by prayer and fasting.
And we focused on that last week
and we understand this thing of unbelief.
And the title for the message this evening
is very similar to last week.
Last week, because of your unbelief,
tonight, they believe not.
You say, it's the same thing, I know.
But we're gonna look at a different passage.
I'm gonna try to help us
to kind of really dig into this thing.
This idea of what does it mean?
What is going on?
What does it mean to believe or to not believe,
to have faith or to have no faith?
And what is the circumstance in which we find ourselves?
And we find this evening that as we look in Psalm 78,
the Bible tells us in verse 32,
for all this they sin still
and believed not for his wondrous works.
And you begin to think about Psalm 78.
We don't have time to look at the entirety
of the Psalm this evening,
but it covers a lot of the history of Israel
and goes through a number of things.
And we find this sad declaration in verse 32
with regard to the fact that they believe not
for his wondrous works.
Now, I'm gonna pause just for a moment
and answer the question
or really try to look at a passage
to help us understand this mindset or mentality
of why isn't God working today like he once did.
Go to Judges 6, just real quick,
keep your place here in Psalm 78,
but look at Judges 6, just real quick.
Judges 6 has to do with Gideon.
And Gideon, of course, chapter 6, 7, and 8,
if you read all three chapters,
you'll see the life of Gideon revealed there,
recorded for us.
But we find that in chapter number six,
in verse number six,
the Bible says,
and Israel was greatly impoverished
because of the Midianites
and the children of Israel cried unto the Lord.
Verse number 10 says,
and I said unto you,
I am the Lord your God,
fear not the gods of the Amorites
in whose land ye dwell.
Notice the statement,
but you have not obeyed my voice.
So then look in verse 12,
the angel of the Lord appeared unto him,
this is Gideon,
and said unto him,
this is the message from the Lord,
the Lord is with thee,
thou mighty man of valor.
But I want you to look at the response of Gideon
in verse 13.
It says, and Gideon said unto him,
oh my Lord,
if the Lord be with us,
why then is all this befallen us?
And where be all his miracles,
which our fathers told us of,
saying, did not the Lord bring us up from Egypt?
But now the Lord hath forsaken us
and delivered us into the hands of the Midianites.
Why did that happen at this time of Israel's history
as we look in chapter six?
What Gideon is saying in verse number 13,
with regard to their circumstances,
there's truth there,
but it's not because the Midianites were too big
or too strong of a people that God couldn't,
it was because they disobeyed.
It's because that they didn't believe what God said,
because God said,
fear not the gods of the Amorites in whose land you dwell,
but you have not obeyed my voice.
They didn't believe the message,
because if we believe the message,
then we then do what the message instructs us to do, right?
If you believe something is true,
I go to a door and I see a sign that says, beware of dogs.
All right, I'm gonna believe the sign.
And I'm not gonna go, if it's a gate, I'm not going in.
You say, but it doesn't look like there's any dogs.
You go right ahead.
I'm just gonna believe the sign
and I'm gonna keep on going, right?
And Ronnie and I were knocking doors one day
and there were some big dogs
and they had the invisible fence.
I don't have a lot of confidence in the invisible fence.
I'm just being honest with you.
Because I'm like, if that dog just kind of thinks,
you know what, it's worth it,
I don't know what's gonna happen, right?
And so Ronnie said, what are you gonna do?
And we said, we're gonna walk on this side of the street
as we keep on going
and then we're gonna just kind of go the long way
to that house.
What about that house?
We can mail them something, we can do something like,
I saw the dogs, right?
But when I see a sign, I don't have to see the dogs,
I'm gonna just believe that they're saying the truth.
It's gonna impact my behavior.
I've said so many times over the years that belief impacts behavior.
So when he says that you have not obeyed my voice, it's because they did not believe what
God told them.
Does that make sense?
And so because they did not believe what God told them, they found themselves in a set
of circumstances that Gideon's saying, where are your miracles?
Why aren't you working?
I mean, they told us of what you did before, but you're not doing it now.
It wasn't the problem with God.
It wasn't the fault of God.
It was the unbelief of the people and the disobedience of the people.
Does that make sense?
And so we find as we look throughout the scriptures that this idea with regard to looking at and
dealing with as we have so far this year, a longing to see God work, God works.
He is able to work, and God works when his people believe and have faith.
And so as we look here in Psalm 78, I want you to notice just a couple of thoughts today
with regard to this passage, and we'll look at some other portions of scripture as well.
But I want you to notice, first of all, the truth revealed.
God reveals to us a truth here in Psalm 78.
Again we're not going to read the entirety of the passage.
We've already read verse 32, but I want to draw your attention to verse 22 as well.
In Psalm 78, verse 22, it says, because they believed not in God and trusted not in his
salvation.
Isn't that a sad commentary?
They believed not.
But now I want you to look at Psalm 106.
We see what's said there, that truth that is revealed in Psalm 78, but look at Psalm
106.
And Psalm 106, again, carries with it a lot of history from Israel, and it's another lengthy
psalm.
And I want to show you a couple of things here in Psalm 106 that I hope will help us
with seeing the connection that I'm going to make this evening.
But in verse number 12 of Psalm 106, the Bible says this, then believed they his words.
They sang his praise.
Now isn't that a good verse of scripture?
That's a good summary statement with regard to the condition of God's people, that God's
people believed, they believed his words, they sang his praise.
That's where we ought to always be as God's people, that we believe his words.
You say, yeah, but all the circumstances and all the, no, no, no, we believe what God said.
It's not about what we see, it's about what God said.
It's not about what we feel, it's about what God said.
Because sometimes what we see and sometimes what we feel is going to deceive us, but what
God has said is true.
And so we find that the Bible says, then believed they his words.
They sang his praise.
Praise the Lord.
But look at the next verse.
In verse number 13, it says, they soon forget his works.
They waited not for his counsel, but lusted exceedingly in the wilderness and tempted
God in the desert.
If you look at verse 21, it says, they forgot God their Savior, which had done great things
in Egypt.
Jeremiah, in part of his indictment against Judah, is that they forgot the Lord.
They forsook the Lord.
They followed after idols.
And he's giving that indictment and he talks about how they forgot the Lord and what a
sad commentary.
And here we find that they went so quickly from believing the words and singing his praise
to forgetting his works.
And following after their own lust, but lusted exceedingly in the wilderness and tempted
God in the desert.
And you see this quick transition that takes place within the children of Israel.
But then look at verse 24.
In Psalm 106 and verse 24, the Bible says, yea, they despised the pleasant land.
They believed not his word.
Let me ask you this evening, was there anything that God did that would lead to the people
having a reason to not believe?
Did God fail them?
Did God disappoint them?
Did God lie to them?
Of course not.
God didn't do any of that.
Not one promise that God made did he not make good on?
Not one thing that he said he would?
Nothing.
There was no reason for them to stop believing.
Now, have you ever had a situation maybe where you had placed confidence in an individual
and you had trust in an individual and they broke that repeatedly and you no longer trust
them to do what they say they're going to do?
You ask them to do something, they say they'll do it, but you make sure you have a contingency
plan.
Has it ever happened for you?
Have you ever had that experience?
And so what has happened?
Well, somebody did something and they caused you to lose trust in them not to believe their
word.
That's not the case with God.
This was just a, this was sin.
This was tragic what was happening where it goes so quickly where they believed his words
to they believed not his word.
And it wasn't because there was any problem where God had failed to fulfill what he said.
It was the people no longer believing God.
We find that here in Psalm 106 and we think about what's transpired and what's been revealed
to us and it says, but murmur in their tents in verse 25 and hearken not unto the voice
of the Lord.
Why would they hearken unto the Lord if they didn't believe his word?
Because belief impacts behavior.
If you don't think it's really going to happen, you're not going to be, you're not going to
have your behavior impacted by it.
And so we find this, this, we notice this truth that is revealed to us.
I want you to notice in Jude, it's just a really short book in the New Testament right
before the book of Revelation and Jude and just one chapter, but man, so much that's
given to us here in this little book of Jude.
And it's interesting because Jude is going to reference back to the people of God, really
in the book of Numbers, what he's referring to.
And I want you to notice what God says here in Jude, just one chapter, verse number five,
I will therefore put you in remembrance though you once knew this, how that the Lord having
saved the people out of the land of Egypt, by the way, that was with a strong arm, a
mighty arm.
Amen?
I mean, they saw his work.
They saw what he did.
It says afterward destroyed them that believe not.
This thing of believing God is serious.
God wants his people to believe him.
He wants us to have faith.
He wants the just shall live by faith.
I've repeated the verse every week, I think this calendar year on Wednesdays, but without
faith it is impossible to please him for he that cometh to God must believe that he is
and that he's a rewarder of them that diligently seek him.
This thing of faith, this thing of belief is important to God.
I asked the group this morning, I'll ask you this evening.
Do you want people to believe you?
Sure you do.
If you tell somebody you're going to do something, man, you want somebody to believe you.
You don't want them to doubt you and say, yeah, I know he said that, but you know, he,
his hit, remember what they said of Paul in second Corinthians, we started it last year.
We started it through Sunday mornings.
He says this, but he doesn't mean it.
His yay is nay and his nay is yay.
No, that wasn't true anyway.
It was a false accusation against Paul.
But the reality is that we want people to believe us.
God wants his people to believe him.
And it says that these people were destroyed.
What is he talking about?
Well, in Numbers 13 and 14, and we're going to study that over the next several Wednesdays,
but in Numbers 13 and 14, we see what happens with the spies.
And there were the, the 10 evil spies come back, those they bring a report back and it's
a report that's void of faith.
It's an evil report of unbelief.
And we find that they impact the entire congregation to not believe God and to not to go forward.
And what happened?
Well, they died in the wilderness.
They died in the wilderness.
God gave judgment.
And by the way, within the text of Scripture, God says to Moses, how long will it be?
Ere my people believe me.
Faith, belief.
It didn't matter that the, that the cities and the land were well fortified.
It didn't matter that they had walls.
It didn't matter that they had giants.
What mattered is that God said, I'm going to give you this land and they didn't believe.
After Moses, after God reveals to Moses and Moses reveals to the people there in Numbers
14, that they were going to die, they decided, okay, we'll go.
Moses said, don't go because God's not with you.
But they tried to go anyway, and then they had to run back.
And the reality is that we see here even in Jude referencing back about those that were
destroyed because they believe not.
The truth revealed as we look here in Psalm 78 and Psalm 106, and we could look at a number
of other places this evening, but I want you to think about the fact that the Scriptures
say they believed not.
If you study the Gospels and you study the life and ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ,
you'll find that there's a number of times in which the Lord interacts obviously with
all sorts of people.
And there are a couple of times in the New Testament where you'll read the statement
that God was, that He marveled.
The Bible tells us that He marveled because of great faith.
But He marveled because they had no faith.
Now I want you to think about that.
If God's going to marvel, do you want Him to marvel because you have no faith or because
you have great faith?
Great faith.
I mean, that's the right answer, right?
I mean, we look at this thing, we say, the centurion, he says, I'm not worthy that you
come to my house.
Just speak the word.
He said, I'm a man under authority.
I know what it is to have authority.
And I say to this man, go, and he goes and do this and he does it.
And you could just speak the word.
And Jesus marvels at the faith.
This man knew that Jesus was God and he believed it and Jesus healed.
Distance had no bearing on whether or not He could heal the individual and His power
was displayed.
You see the disciples at various times having little faith or having no faith.
Jesus tells them at one particular time to beware of the leaven of the Pharisees.
The leaven of the Pharisees is hypocrisy.
That's what it is.
You study out the scriptures and you see that that's what the leaven of the Pharisees is.
And Jesus says, beware of the leaven of the Pharisees.
And all of a sudden, you know what the disciples do?
Oh man, we forgot bread.
We forgot bread.
How do we get on the boat when we didn't have any bread?
Right?
Is that what they do?
That's what they do.
And Jesus, you know what Jesus says?
He's such a gentle, kind Savior.
He says, what about the 5,000?
How much bread did you have?
What about the 4,000?
You know what He's doing?
He's reminding them of His power.
It had nothing to do with bread.
The leaven of the Pharisees is hypocrisy.
But they immediately go to the physical, to the temporal, and they start saying, man,
we didn't bring any bread for the journey.
What are we going to do?
And Jesus, understanding where they were, meets them where they are.
And He says to them, don't you remember 5,000?
By the way, that was just the men, not women and children included.
And just a small lad's lunch and all of them were fed.
And I mean, they were fed completely.
And then they had 12 baskets remaining.
Hallelujah.
That's what our God's able to do.
But you know, you know what's interesting about the feeding of the 5,000 and the 4,000
as well?
But the feeding of the 5,000, one of the things that's very interesting about that is that
the disciples had to keep coming back to Jesus to get more to go pass it out.
They were personally, like, involved in the miracle.
And yet they come to another challenge, another trouble, another difficulty, and it's like
they don't have faith.
When we begin to look at this truth that's revealed, the reality is that we must be able
to examine our own hearts, as I mentioned last week, and we must be able to identify
with the man that we studied in Mark 9 a couple of weeks ago.
When Jesus says to him, because remember the question that the man asked Jesus, if thou
can't do anything, have compassion on us and help us.
That was the request of the man.
And Jesus responds and Jesus says, if thou can't believe, all things are possible.
And the man says, I believe, help thou mine unbelief.
And every one of us, if we get honest and humble before the Lord and we examine our
hearts, listen, it's not about we look at how much faith I have, no, I need my faith
to grow and to increase and to trust God.
Why?
Because sometimes the circumstances in life, as I mentioned, the things that we see and
the things that we feel, they can have a greater impact on us than the things that we know
to be true.
You say, I know that's what the Bible says, but have you ever heard somebody say that?
It's like, no, no, no, no, but I know what the Bible says and just trust what the Bible
says.
Just take God at his word.
I thought about this, I didn't share it this morning in the lesson there this morning,
and some of the folks that are there in the morning, they kind of laugh and some of them
were watching this evening, they say, it's funny, your evening is different than the
morning and it's the same message and the same passages, but there's differences and
well, that's just how it is because I don't write it all out word for word and don't read
it to you.
And so that's what you get.
And the reality is that I thought about this this afternoon and I thought about it within
the context of tithing and I don't know why I thought that way, but I did, but you know,
I've had lots of people over the years and I remember it even happening with my parents
when they first got saved.
I remember my dad coming home and saying, we're going to start tithing and my mom's
like, we can't afford to do that.
Like what are you talking about?
You know, tithing really comes down to two things, faith and obedience is what it comes
down to.
It comes down to believing that God will allow your 90% to go further than your 100%.
Because you're going to honor God, you're going to obey him and you're going to believe
him.
A tithe is very easy to figure out, it's 10%, it's not like it's rocket science, it's very
simple to figure out that we're not tipping God, we're tithing and it's a matter of faith
and obedience, that we believe God, that we believe that God is able to make it go
further, to rebuke the devourer.
We read that in Malachi and God says, prove me.
God wants us to believe him and so we find that even in our own lives there are times
in which we deal with this thing of not believing God, not believing his word.
So the truth is revealed, but I want you to go back to Psalm 78 because we notice the
truth revealed, now I want you to notice number two, the tragic result.
Notice the tragic result.
And this is so important that we understand and really worthy of our contemplation and
really just meditating upon the truth that we see here because there's a tragic result.
We saw in Jude where the Bible says they were destroyed, I mean that's tragic, but
we find here in verse 41 of Psalm 78, the Bible says, yay, they turned back and tempted
God and then notice the last part of the verse, and limited the Holy One of Israel.
How do you limit a God who is limitless, who can do all things?
He spoke the world into existence.
He said, let there be light.
He created all that he created.
He parted seas, I mean just think about all the miracles and all the power and all that
he's able to do and yet the Bible says the tragic result of the truth that was revealed
that they believed not is that they limited the Holy One of Israel.
It was not a matter that God could not, it was that God would not.
He would not do what he could do because of their unbelief.
That's worthy of our meditation, contemplation, I mean Lord, I don't want to limit you.
I mean it's God that says in his word that with God all things are possible.
It's God that appears to Abraham as El Shaddai, the Almighty God, and says is anything too
hard for me?
It's God in Jeremiah chapter 32 and you find in that portion of scripture that God is giving
instruction to Jeremiah and Jeremiah of course is the one that's been prophesying about the
Babylonian captivity.
The Babylonians have besieged the city, they know the armies are coming, he knows, he understands
what he's been prophesying and what he's been preaching and the people haven't been believing
but yet God comes to Jeremiah in Jeremiah 32 and says Jeremiah, buy the field.
Now with everything that I understand and understanding that we're going to be taken
captive and the land is going to be taken over, why am I going to buy the field?
Well I'm going to buy the field because I'm not looking at the circumstances, I'm listening
to God and if God said buy the field then I buy the field, does that make sense?
Because I believe God and we find that God gives him the truth, tells him not only to
buy the field but to ensure that all the evidence is clearly known that he did buy the field.
You study through the chapter, you find that Jeremiah understands the power of God and
we find that God even responds after Jeremiah worships the Lord, he buys the field and he
worships and he obeyed and we find that God says behold I am the Lord, the God of all
flesh, is there anything too hard for me?
The reality is that God reveals to Jeremiah in this chapter that after 70 years of captivity
they would return to the land.
And as God reveals that to Jeremiah.
Jeremiah, he tells them that fields shall be bought in this land.
And so therefore, he tells them ahead of time, why would there be 70 years of captivity?
Well, because they weren't honoring the Lord with the Sabbaths as they were supposed to.
And if you study it all out and understand that was why it was a 70 year captivity.
And then Daniel is reading Jeremiah in captivity and he's reading about Jeremiah and he's like,
oh, the years they've been fulfilled.
It's amazing as you study the whole thing out and you see what's going on.
But Jeremiah, the circumstances, the events that are immediately surrounding him, why
would I buy the field?
Because God said to.
And I believe God.
And so God who can do all things, God who has all power, God who is the same yesterday,
today and forever.
We find that here the Bible says that they limited the Holy One of Israel.
I don't want to limit God.
I truly want to see God do what only God could do.
I can't share all the details here because of the live stream, but we have a missionary
family that we've prayed for for a few weeks.
And I mentioned on Sunday how that after the prayer was answered, that there were people
within that country that have served and ministered there for years that said back
to our missionary with regard to all those that they were associated with and that had
been praying about the situation.
They said this, we've never seen God work like this.
We've never seen God work and answer prayer so specific and so quickly.
And I say, hallelujah.
That's my God.
That's what he's able to do.
Listen, it shouldn't surprise us when God answers prayer.
It shouldn't surprise us when God works and when God does what only God can do.
Why?
Because we're longing to see God work.
And God uses his word.
Listen, I understand we live in a time where you could look at all the things that are
going on and unfortunately there are some people that say, well, it's just head, run
for the hills and just kind of, you know, bunker down and get your, what do they call
that when you're going to bug out, your bug out kit, right?
I don't have one.
I don't plan to bug out.
Amen.
And the reality is that, listen, Jesus is still on his throne.
And the gospel still works today.
Listen, the Lord said, I will build my church and the gates of hell shall not prevail again.
Do you believe that he said that?
Now, when he made that statement, there's a really hard question.
Bart said he's tired.
He'd been working hard this week.
He, this easy question, right?
When Jesus said, I will build my church, did America exist?
No.
So when Jesus said, I will build my church, it wasn't because we had a US constitution
and bill of rights.
Amen.
And by the way, he's building his church in countries that don't have the bill of rights
and don't have a US constitution.
In fact, there are some countries that have far fewer rights than we do that are doing
far more for God than we are.
And shame on us.
Shame on us.
It's not God's fault.
It's our fault.
The book of 1 Peter says, judgment must begin at the house of God.
Why isn't God working?
I understand sin.
Unbelief is sin, but I think there's this, we don't have, we're not believing God.
We're not believing his word.
I mean, it's not having an impact on our behavior.
And we find that we look here and we say, listen, I was talking at a pastor's meeting.
Actually, it's come up several times at pastor's fellowships and meetings.
And there's some people that are concerned about the fact that churches potentially could
become non-tax exempt.
And I'm not trying to get into a political thing, but the reality is that there are some
evidently that would like to change the law so that we're not tax exempt.
And here in the Commonwealth of Virginia, and I believe in all of the United States
of America, churches are tax exempt.
And I'm thankful for that.
But that is not the reason that Jesus is going to build the church.
Amen.
If tomorrow the tax exempt status was removed and we had to pay taxes, it doesn't mean that
we put a for sale sign up.
You say, but do you know how much it's going to cost?
Yeah, it would cost us about $50,000 a year if we had to pay taxes on this property.
You say, that's a lot of money.
God is able.
Amen.
You don't start a church because you're tax exempt.
You don't give to God because you can get a tax deduction.
It's just not the way it works.
You understand what I'm saying?
We believe God and we say, God, this is His church and God is able.
And I've heard pastors at some of the pastors meetings say, we wouldn't be able to function
if we had to pay taxes on our property.
We'd have to get rid of some staff because we have way too much property and the...
Then get rid of staff.
I mean, I don't like...
Trust God.
Like, I mean, you know, but sometimes we get so concerned about what we're feeling and
what we're seeing and we just need to get back to what God said.
I'm thankful that I do not live in Iran, but I read some reports coming out of Iran
about people getting saved and the underground church thriving.
And it's unbelievable from a human perspective, understanding the things that we see commonly,
but understanding what they're reporting spiritually that's happening there.
There's some people that believe God.
They just believe God.
And so we see the tragic result.
The Bible says that they turned back and tempted God and limited the Holy One of Israel.
I do not want to limit God.
Look at Matthew 13 and we'll close in Matthew 13.
And here, the Lord Jesus Christ, He's teaching and had finished up with some parables and
we find in Matthew 13, I'm going to read a few verses of scripture starting here near
the end of the chapter, verse 53.
In Matthew 13 and verse 53, it says, and it came to pass that when Jesus had finished
these parables, He departed thence.
And when He was coming to His own country, He taught them in their synagogue and so much
that they were astonished and said, whence hath this man this wisdom and these mighty
works?
In those first 55 and 56, the Bible says, is not this the carpenter's son?
Is not his mother called Mary and his brethren, James and Joseph and Simon and Judas and his
sisters?
Are they not all with us?
Whence then hath this man all these things?
See, they didn't believe He was God.
The religious leaders of the day did not want to acknowledge that He was Messiah, that He
was God.
They were influencing the people and the Bible says that Jesus responds in verse 57
and it says that they were offended in Him, but Jesus said unto them, a prophet is not
without honor, save in his own country, in his own house.
And then I want you to look carefully at verse 58.
The Bible says, and He, Jesus, did not many mighty works there.
Why?
Because of their unbelief.
They limited the Holy One of Israel, Psalm 78 and verse 41.
Here in Matthew 13 and verse 58, it says that He did not many mighty works there because
of their unbelief.
Do you think, do you think it would be a stretch for us to say that there were some people
that needed healing there?
There's some people that needed to see the mighty works that God could do, that only
God could do.
It says that He did not many mighty works there because of their unbelief.
It wasn't a fact that He could not do the mighty works.
It was that He did not the mighty works.
That's important for us to understand this evening, why?
Because as we look at this and we understand what's taking place, we say it's not a problem
with God, it's a problem with God's people.
You say, I don't like that.
I understand because we don't like to examine ourselves.
We like to think more highly of ourselves than we should.
The reality is that I really believe that God wants us to just believe Him in childlike
faith.
You know, childlike faith is something so precious.
I believe, I shared this, I used this illustration, and I don't have a stack of chairs here like
I did over there to use the illustration, but I believe this evening that if I brought
Nova over here and I set her up on a stack of chairs and said to Nova, jump to Papa.
Have you ever done that with your children?
Nieces, nephews, somebody, and they jump to you, right?
They just believe that you're going to catch them, right?
Ashley, you do that with Ashley?
Yeah.
Sometimes if you're not careful, Ashley will jump before you think she's going to jump.
I've had that happen where like they're jumping and you catch them.
But here's the thing, you know what's going to change for Nova, that childlike faith,
is if I say jump and I drop her.
Am I right?
So then I'm like, oh, let's try that again.
No, Papa, that's what she would say to me, right?
You, she said, it's okay.
She wouldn't do it.
So if I dropped her, she would have reason to not trust me.
Right?
God's never dropped you.
God never will drop you.
There is no reason for us not to trust him.
He is trustworthy.
He is faithful.
He will always do what he said he will do.
Amen?
And so we have to have that childlike faith.
Say, but you don't understand this.
No, no, no.
Do you understand God?
But the doctor said this, or the economist said this,
or the whatever said this.
No, no, no.
You just keep obeying God,
and you keep doing what God said,
and you keep following God's word,
and you keep trusting God, and you prove God,
and you see that God is able to do.
We could use illustrations this evening.
You could talk about the widow of Zarephath.
We're gonna eat this little bit, and we're gonna die.
We got nothing left.
And Elijah says, I understand, but give me one first.
And the meal wasted not.
God did that.
The oil with Elisha.
What do you have in the house?
Nothing, just a little pot of oil over here.
Go borrow every vessel that you can, and fill them up.
The boy's going, get the vessels.
The mom says, are there any more?
No, we got them all, but there's still oil.
That's God.
We have those accounts in our Bible
because there's some people that believe God.
You read about some people of yesteryear
that have provided for us written testimony
of great miracles and answers to prayer.
You say, man, yeah, God is able,
and they just believe God.
They just believe God.
George Mueller, you ever read about George Mueller?
Sit down with a whole bunch of orphans
and say, God, thank you for the food, but there's no food.
And then God provides the food.
Like, that's our God.
And in 2026, we gotta come to the place
where we believe that He is truly who He says He is,
who He reveals to us in His Word,
that the gospel still works,
it is still the power of God unto salvation.
We still give it and preach it.
Why?
Because it works.
We believe God.
They believe not.
Oh, would it never, ever be said of us.
Would it never be that God would marvel
that we have no faith,
but that God would look at us and say,
there's a group of people that have faith.
They believe me.
They have faith.
And our faith needs to grow.
As the church in Thessalonica,
their faith groweth exceedingly.
How does that happen?
Get in the book.
Get in the book and let your faith grow.
Every time we see God answer prayer, it increases our faith.
Every time we read the Bible, our faith is being increased.
Oh, that we would believe God.
Why?
Because we don't wanna have that tragic result.
We don't wanna limit God.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
Thank you for loving us.
Thank you for your word, the truth contained therein.
Thank you for giving us what we need.
And I pray that you'd help us, Lord,
to have our faith increase.
Lord, help us to examine our hearts.
Lord, if there's any area of unbelief in our lives,
Lord, would you help us to deal with that?
God, I don't wanna limit you.
In my life, in our church,
help us to have faith.
Help us to believe you.
Bless the time of prayer.
Thank you for the privilege.
I pray that you'd be honored and glorified
for it's in Christ's name we pray, amen.