number four, and be looking at verses six through eight
this morning, 2 Timothy chapter four,
verses six through eight.
And this is a familiar passage of scripture,
one in which I'm sure that many of you
have had the opportunity to hear messages
preached on this portion of scripture
at some point in your Christian life.
And you've had the opportunity, perhaps,
to even memorize verses six and seven.
I believe it's the memory verse for the month
of December of this year.
We've had memory verses all throughout this calendar year
from 1 and 2 Timothy as we've been preaching through
these two books with our theme
for this calendar year, continue.
And what a joy.
Last week, we looked at the thought, press on.
And as the Apostle Paul, under the inspiration
of the Holy Spirit of God, made us aware
of all that we would deal with, all that we would face,
all that we would encounter in these last days,
that we're to press on, we're to continue,
we're to move forward, we're to preach the word,
we're to be instant in season, out of season,
reprove, rebuke, exhort with all long-suffering
and doctrine, that we are to continue doing
what God has called us to do.
And what a blessing to know that God is at work.
We find that Paul, as he has spent so much time
in these writings, of course, under the inspiration
of the Holy Spirit of God, seeking to encourage
his son in the faith.
Timothy is serving the Lord.
Timothy is facing certain trials and adversities there
in Ephesus, as he's seeking to serve.
And the Apostle Paul is being used of the Lord
to encourage his son in the faith to carry on, to continue.
And the reality is that every generation must encourage
the next generation to continue to serve God,
to continue to stay faithful to what God has delivered.
Remember, the Apostle Paul said there in 2 Timothy 2,
and the things that thou hast heard of me
among many witnesses, notice this,
the same commit thou to faithful men
who shall be able to teach others also.
It was not that Timothy needed to find some new message
for some new generation.
No, it was the same truth that God has given,
the same truth that we have this morning.
And we're thankful, of course, to have the whole canon,
the complete canon of Scripture.
And God gives us the responsibility of encouraging those
that come behind us.
The reality is that there are certain difficulties
that we face that will be consistent with the difficulties
that the future generation will face.
But we also know that the times are becoming
more and more evil.
Remember, evil men and seducers shall act worse and worse,
deceiving and being deceived.
And so we understand this morning that the generation
that's coming behind us needs our encouragement
to continue to press on, to fight the fight,
to be a good soldier of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And we come to this passage of Scripture,
and what we find is that the Apostle Paul
is now writing, really, this truth to Timothy,
a son of the faith, that his course is complete.
His course is complete.
I've titled the message this morning,
I Have Finished My Course.
And notice what Paul says in verse six
of 2 Timothy chapter four,
for I am now ready to be offered.
Notice he says the time of my departure is at hand.
Verse seven, I have fought a good fight.
I have finished my course.
I have kept the faith.
Verse number eight says this,
henceforth there is laid up for me
a crown of righteousness, which the Lord,
the righteous judge, shall give me at that day.
And not to me only, but unto all them also,
that love his appearing.
What a great passage of Scripture,
of a man that we often look to as the Apostle Paul
as being a great hero of the faith,
a man that God used in an amazing way,
a man that God used to share the gospel
with so many new territories on those missionary journeys,
a man that was used of God for this reason,
he made himself available to God.
He was a man that was willing to surrender.
He encourages others in Romans chapter number 12 to,
he says I beseech you to do what?
To present your bodies a living sacrifice.
But this was not something that the Apostle Paul
had not already done in his own life.
He had already made himself a living sacrifice.
He says I am crucified with Christ.
We find that the Apostle Paul says in Philippians one,
for to me to live is Christ, and to die is gain.
There's a great contrast between Philippians 121,
that verse that I just quoted, and Philippians 221,
where the Bible says that for all seek their own
and not the things of Jesus Christ.
And the reality of this morning is that the Apostle Paul
was used of God in such a great way
because he was a man that made himself available to God.
Remember what he said on the road to Damascus
when he got saved, he said who art thou Lord?
But then he said this, what wilt thou have me to do?
See, he recognized that he was Lord.
And he said what do you have for me to do?
And we find from that point forward,
the Apostle Paul was a man that was fully surrendered
to God to be used in any way that God saw fit.
And we come to this passage of scripture,
and we find this morning that Paul is able
to write these words again under the inspiration
of the Holy Spirit of God, and knowing
and having assurance this morning
that he'd finished his course.
I wanna give you this morning three words
that I hope you would remember these three words
this morning as you think about this passage of scripture,
that these three words would ring in your mind,
in your heart, that we would not soon forget this truth
from this portion of scripture.
Number one this morning, recognize.
It's the first word that I want you to be mindful of
and to remember this morning is recognize.
You say recognize what?
Recognize that you too are running a course.
Recognize that you too will come to the place
where your time of your departure will come.
Recognize this morning that just as Paul says,
for I am now ready to be offered,
the time of my departure is at hand.
Recognize this morning that one day,
and we don't know the day.
As Paul had this understanding,
we do not have the knowledge of when that day will come,
but we recognize this morning that one day our time,
the time of our departure will come.
And it's vital that we recognize that.
It's vital this morning that we recognize
that this is the truth that every one of us will face.
We have opportunity today, but we don't know about tomorrow.
None of us do.
You say I'm young and I'm vibrant.
Take a trip to the cemetery, to the graveyard,
and you'll find tombstones with names and dates
of the reality that death is no respecter of age.
Amen?
And so we have opportunity today.
And the reality is that the time of our departure will come.
I wanna remind you as Hebrews 9, 27 says this,
for as it is appointed unto man once to die,
but after this, the judgment.
And we find this morning that as the Apostle Paul
is writing this, and no doubt from a perspective
as we have the opportunity to look at it this morning
from a perspective of finishing well,
a course that he ran, a course that we are running
this morning, and we must recognize
that our course will end.
We don't know when the finish line,
where the finish line is.
But we know there's a finish line.
This morning, the reality is that we all have a course.
Notice he says this.
I want you to, we mentioned in verse number six
that he says that I'm ready to be offered.
The time of my departure is at hand.
I want you to notice, he says in verse seven,
I have fought a good fight.
I have finished, and then notice these words, my course.
Can I tell you this morning that the only person
that could finish Paul's course is Paul?
The only person that can finish your course is you.
I can't run your leg of the race,
and you can't run my leg of the race.
I can't run your course, and you can't run my course,
because the reality is that each of us
have a specific individual course that we're running.
Now, there's a lot of similarities in our course.
There's a lot of things that are exactly the same
in the course that you're running
and the course that I'm running,
but the reality is that we have our own course,
and we must recognize that.
We must recognize this morning that this Christian life
that we find that Paul likens it
to that of being in the army as he speaks
about being a good soldier of the Lord Jesus Christ.
We find that as he's writing to the people in Corinth
and then now making this reference here
in 2 Timothy 4 that he likens it to an athlete
being in a competition and running a course,
and we find here that he says I have finished my course.
I want you to just for a moment as we recognize the truth,
as we initially get into the text of Scripture this morning,
I want you to recognize this morning that you have a course,
and that the time of your departure will come
just as it did for Paul.
And when we recognize that.
that causes us to evaluate our lives,
it causes us to step back and say,
where am I on this course?
How am I doing on this course, the course of life?
You know, life, they sang that song this morning,
what a wonderful song, by the way,
I think they've been trying to sing that song
for a few weeks because there's been different people
that have been sick and what have you,
not been able to get all together.
But the reality is that that song,
based upon the truth of Romans 8, 28,
and we know that all things, listen,
the bumps along the way, the high times,
the low times, the mountains, the valleys,
as we often refer to them,
they work together for what?
For good, why?
Because our God is in control
and when we surrender our lives to him
and we know that we're on this course,
we say, listen, I wanna finish my course.
I understand, I recognize this morning
that I have this course, I recognize
that the time of my departure is going to come
and how am I doing on running this race?
That's called the Christian life.
I want you to think of this word, number two, rejoice.
The meat of the message is in the third point this morning
as we will get there in just a moment,
but I want you to think about this, rejoice.
Why do I say rejoice?
Well, in verse number eight, notice what Paul says,
henceforth, there is laid up for me a crown of righteousness
which the Lord, the righteous judge,
shall give me at that day and not to me only,
but unto all them also that love his appearing.
Why do I say rejoice?
Because you're gonna see the Lord.
When your course ends, when Paul says,
I have finished my course, I have kept the faith,
when he says the time of my departure is at hand,
he immediately, in verse number eight,
speaks about the fact that he is going to receive a crown,
but who is it that's going to give him the crown?
It's the Lord, the righteous judge,
the one that died for us, the one who intercedes for us,
the one who is our advocate, the one who lives forevermore.
We will see him face to face.
Hold your place here in 2 Timothy four
and turn back, if you will, to Acts chapter number seven,
and I'm gonna dig in right to the end
of the passage of Acts seven,
and there's such great truth in this passage of scripture
where the first martyr of the church, if you will,
Stephen, as he's going to be stoned,
and he's preached such a powerful message,
he knew the scriptures, he knew the Old Testament,
and we come to chapter number seven,
and I want you to notice in verse number 54,
those that heard the message
that Stephen preached on this day,
it says this in verse 54,
when they heard these things, they were cut to the heart.
Now, I want you to just pause for a moment
and consider those words.
Why were they cut to the heart?
Because the word of God is quick and powerful
and sharper than a two-edged sword.
The word of God is powerful, it's effective,
it's profitable, and we find that they heard
the truth of God's word.
Stephen did such a great job of taking principles
and truths from the Old Testament
that these people would have been very familiar with
and taking all of that Old Testament
and then coming right up to Jesus
and pointing his finger at those people and saying,
this Jesus, you have rejected him, he is the Messiah,
he is the promised one, and you rejected him,
and the Bible says that they were cut to the heart.
Listen, that doesn't happen just because of some person
that can stand up and wax eloquent.
That's somebody that's filled with the spirit of God.
That's what Acts 7 tells us.
The key to this whole thing in Acts chapter number 7
is that Stephen was a man that was filled
with the Holy Spirit, the Holy Ghost,
and we find that they were cut to the heart.
They gnashed on him with their teeth.
Can you imagine the response of the people
of being so convicted because of the message they heard?
It says they gnashed on him with their teeth,
but he, notice in verse 55, again,
a reminder of him being full of the Holy Ghost.
It says, but he, being full of the Holy Ghost,
looked up steadfastly into heaven.
Notice what the Bible says, and saw the glory of God
and Jesus standing on the right hand of God.
Isn't that awesome?
I mean, he's standing there and he's preaching
and they're under conviction and they gnash on him
with their teeth and he, being full of the Holy Ghost,
he looks up and what does he see?
Well, the Bible says that he saw, as he looked into heaven,
he saw the glory of God and he saw Jesus standing
on the right hand of God.
Notice what he said in verse 56.
Behold, I see the heavens open and the Son of Man
standing on the right hand of God.
Then they cried out with a loud voice and stopped their ears
and ran upon him with one accord and cast him out of the city
and stoned him and the witnesses laid down their clothes
at a young man's feet whose name was Saul.
When they stoned Stephen, notice what the Bible says,
calling upon God and saying, Lord Jesus, receive my spirit.
And he kneeled down and cried with a loud voice,
Lord, lay not this sin to their charge.
And when he had said this, he fell asleep.
The peace that Stephen had in this moment of being stoned,
the first martyr of the church and all that transpired.
And we find that the key, yes,
being filled with the Holy Ghost,
but when he looks up to heaven, he sees the glory of God
and he sees Jesus standing on the right hand of God.
Listen, I'm thankful this morning
that when we finish our race,
you think about someone running a race.
I wasn't much of a race runner.
I played other sports.
I was never interested in track and field.
And baseball season was kind of the same time
and I played baseball,
but I'd always see those track and field folks
running over there.
And you think about running a race
and there's something about getting to that finish line.
And typically, in fact, if you watch the Olympics
and that sort of thing,
and especially when you like in the Christian life,
not to a hundred meter sprint, but to a marathon,
there are a crowd of people that are gathered where?
At the finish line, at the finish line.
And I believe this morning that when we finish our course,
as the Apostle Paul says here
in 2 Timothy chapter number four,
that we're gonna see our Savior face to face.
You know, remember what the songwriter said,
it will be worth it all when we see Jesus,
when we see Jesus.
Listen, it's not just something
that we try to pep ourselves up with
and try to make ourselves feel better about.
No, it's a reality that if you're saved this morning,
if you're a child of God this morning,
that you're running a course,
we have to recognize that we're running a course.
We have to recognize that our course is going to end one day.
We don't know the time of our departure,
but we know that one day our course will end.
And what's done for Christ today is what's going to matter.
We need to recognize that,
but then we need to rejoice in the fact
that when that day comes,
that we will see the Lord Jesus Christ face to face.
What glory, what glory.
Consider with me not only that we'll see
the Lord face to face,
but we find in verse number eight that the Bible says
that Paul had this confidence.
Paul was not boasting, Paul was not being prideful.
Paul was simply stating a fact.
By the way, when we state facts,
it doesn't mean that we're boasting or prideful.
We're simply stating a fact based on a revealed truth
that God has provided.
And here in this text of scripture,
we find that God has provided
and revealed to the apostle Paul a stated truth,
and therefore Paul is rejoicing
and he's being able to with confidence
to make this statement without pride, without boasting.
Why?
Because God had revealed this to him.
Notice he says, there is laid up for me.
Paul is speaking and he says,
there's laid up for me a crown of righteousness.
Now we notice as we consider this thought of rejoicing,
not only we'll see the Lord, but there are crowns,
there are rewards that are to be received.
What a joy to think about the fact that our God saved us.
I mean, just pause there for a moment.
Thank you, Lord, for saving my soul.
Didn't we just sing that song just a few moments ago?
He saved us and then guess what he did?
He equipped us, right?
As every man hath received the gift.
Who do we receive the gift from?
Well, the Bible says that the Holy Spirit of God
give it to every man severally as he will.
And we find that he's gifted us, he's equipped us.
I am what I am by the grace of God.
It's his grace that enables me.
I wanna be a good steward of the manifold grace of God
because he has enabled me.
And then the God who saved me, that has equipped me,
that will use me, then rewards me.
It's absolutely amazing to consider that this morning.
Now we understand as we look at the passages of Scripture
that deal with the judgment seat of Christ
or the behemoth seat of Christ that we can receive reward
or we can suffer loss, we can suffer loss.
But Paul here speaking from a perspective of rejoicing
from what Paul says, there is laid up for me
a crown of righteousness, which the Lord,
the righteous judge shall give me at that day.
But notice.
there's not a period there and this is the the encouragement for us this
morning it says and not to me only but unto what does it say in your Bible all
them also that love his appearing you know this morning it's not just the
Apostle Paul that's going to receive this crown of righteousness but but you
this morning could receive this crown of righteousness the Bible speaks we're not
going to deal with it this morning because of the the time that would be
involved but the Bible speaks specifically of five different crowns in
the New Testament that the child of God can receive I believe that four of them
can be received by anyone and one is for pastors according to first Peter chapter
5 but we find this morning that there are crowns to be received now what do we
do with these crowns the reality is that we think about the the fact that we're
gonna stand before Christ that we're going to be able to receive as the
Apostle Paul says he knew it said he is reserved in heaven there he has this
this crown that he'll receive there's laid up for me a crown of righteousness
but hold your place here and look over at Revelation chapter 4 and Revelation
chapter 4 on Sunday nights we're going through the book of Revelation but we're
just early on in chapter number 2 and so be a little while before we get to
chapter number 4 but in second in Revelation chapter 4 we find this scene
into the throne room of heaven and I want you to notice in verse number 10 in
verse number 10 the Bible says it says this the four and twenty elders fall
down before him that sat on the throne and worship him that liveth forever and
cast their crowns before the throne saying thou art worthy oh Lord to
receive glory and honor and power for thou hast created all things and for
thy pleasure they are and were created you know this morning that crown that we
could receive are those crowns that could be received or not so that we can
walk around in glory and have someone look at us and say look at all the
crowns that they have know it so that we might cast them back to the Lord why
because he alone is worthy he is the one that receives the glory listen anything
good in you anything good in me is because of the Lord Jesus Christ it's
because of his work in us we find this morning that we ought to rejoice listen
the Apostle Paul had a confidence about going to heaven we find that he says in
2nd Corinthians 5 in verse number 8 that he said to be absent from the body is to
be present with the Lord we find that there's a confidence I think about the
confidence of David as he writes Psalm 23 and he says at the end of the Psalm I
will dwell in the house of the Lord forever how does he have such great
confidence to be able to say I will dwell in the house of the Lord forever
well it's because he says this the Lord is my shepherd in verse number one you
never get to verse number six before you first deal with first number one you
never can say that I will dwell in the house of the Lord forever if you first
do not understand the Lord is my shepherd personal he saved me he's my
shepherd my sheep hear my voice and I know them and they follow me aren't you
thankful this morning for the Good Shepherd I'm thankful that he's my
shepherd and the Apostle Paul as we look at this passage of scripture the first
thought is that we need to recognize this morning you're running a course your
course will end one day we don't know the time of our departure we don't know
when our course will end but we know that it will end and so I want to run
well every day because I don't know when the last day is going to come I don't
know when my course is going to end so I have to recognize that I want you to
rejoice this morning because as many adversities as we can face in this life
as many oppositions as we can have on this journey of life as much opposition
as the the enemy will bring to you and to me as we run this race this course we
understand that at the end we get to see Jesus and it will be worth it all I
want you to rejoice in that this morning to rejoice in that but number three the
third word that I want you to remember this morning is this resolve resolve
what does it mean to resolve well we're gonna make this determination we're
going to to resolve that we're going to run our race well how is it that we can
come to a place what's the application for us what is the the the point of
looking at this passage of scripture and and understanding what the Apostle Paul
says how is it that we can come to the place where where we can say I have
finished my course that that I have kept the faith that I have fought a good
fight how is it that I could come to the end of my life that you could come to
the end of your life and have some level of confidence that you too would receive
a reward as Paul mentions in verse number 8 that you have completed what
God has called you to complete see can I tell you this morning it's not gonna
happen on accident you're not gonna finish well by chance by accident it's
not gonna just happen you have to resolve there's some decisions that you
have to make you have to be determined you have to be determined that you're
going to to be ready for that day notice again in verse number 6 the Bible says
for I am now ready to be offered many believe that this is a reference to the
Apostle Paul referencing a drink offering that would be poured out and
speaking about his life being that type of a drink offering that's poured out to
the Lord and he says I am now ready how can we come to the place where we say I
am ready to be offered that we understand that that that we've made
some decisions along the way we have resolved to do some things along the way
that would bring us to this point that Paul is at on this day that he can make
the statement I am ready it's interesting to me and there's a few
different references within the New Testament specifically of Paul making
the statement I am ready but I want you to think about two of them in Romans
chapter number one he says I am ready ready to do what well he's ready to go
to Rome and to preach the gospel and now at the end of his life he says I'm
ready to be offered I am ready and I want you to understand this morning that
there are many people and it's not just lost people there are many saved people
this morning that that when that time comes when they're nearing the end and
it seems as if the the life can pass at any moment there are people that are
full of regrets full of regrets I wish I would have if I could just go back if
I could change this if I could change that you know what the problem is with
all of those statements you can't you can't can't and so how do we live a life
without regrets how do we live a life that we can come to the end and say I am
now ready to be offered but notice not only does he say I'm now ready to be
offered but he says this and the time of my departure is at hand he says I have
fought a good fight notice verse 7 I have finished my course there's
something important about finishing something important about finishing
anyone can get into a race doesn't really matter how many people are in a
race matters if you finish the race in this morning we understand that the way
to get in the race spiritually as we speak about this particular text of
scripture in this course that is being referenced is that you're saved you're
born again you've trusted the Lord Jesus Christ is your personal Savior you're
not trusting in church membership you're not trusting in baptism you're
not sure trusting in good works you're not trusting in any of those things
because none of that can save you it's only the blood of the Lord Jesus Christ
that can save you this morning and you're trusting in Christ alone as your
personal Savior that's what gets you into this race into this course that
we're speaking of this morning and we find that in this course in this race
the Apostle Paul says I have finished my course there's something important
about finishing but not just finishing but finishing well see we're all going
to reach the end of our race we mentioned that already but the question
is whether we finish well because it says not only have I finished my course
but notice he says I have kept the faith I have kept the faith I didn't
just finish but I finished well he's gonna speak about in just a couple of
verses about Demas and the Bible says that he has forsaken me having loved
this present world we find that there are others that we can look at along the
that have fallen off that that that are going to yes finish their course but are
they gonna finish well in this morning my goal as I seek to deal with this
third word of resolve is that I don't simply want to finish
I want to finish well.
Let me say it this way, I think that the picture in verse number 6
when he says, I am now ready to be offered and that thought of the drink offering,
it's finishing with nothing left in the tank.
Do you understand what I mean by that? I mean literally finishing
with nothing left in the tank. It's not coming
to the finish line and saying, you know, I should have pushed it a little bit more, I could run
another couple of miles. No, it's literally finishing
with nothing left. I have poured out my
life for the cause of Christ.
I have surrendered and yielded
and I am ready to be offered. I have finished well. Again,
it will not happen by chance. It will not happen on accident. You must
and I must resolve, as Paul did, to finish our course
with joy. Let me take you back to the book of Acts for a moment.
In Acts chapter number 20, and many times we've looked at Acts 20
throughout this study of 1st and 2nd Timothy for a couple of reasons.
Number one, Paul is writing to Timothy who is actively
ministering in Ephesus and in Acts chapter number 20
it's when Paul speaks to the leaders of the church in Ephesus
on his way to Jerusalem. We find that as the apostle Paul
would speak to these church leaders of the church at Ephesus
here in this portion of scripture, he makes many references
with regard to his own ministry and his own work, but then he
gives them a challenge. He gives them instruction and exhortation
on what they must do as being the church
leaders of the church at Ephesus and how this truth would enable them
to be able to finish their course as well. But I want you to look, if you will, in verse
number 18, the Bible says this, and when they were come
that's the church leaders from Ephesus, and when they were come
he said unto them, ye know.
Now think about that, just those statements. Paul is not telling them anything
they didn't already know. See, remember what he talked about
we mentioned this last week in 2nd Timothy chapter number
3 towards the end of the message. He says, this know in the last
days there shall come perilous times, but then in verse number, I think it's
11, he says, and ye have known my manner of life,
my doctrine, so on and so forth, and so Paul says to these leaders of the
church at Ephesus, he says, ye know, you know my ministry
the work that I did, the labor that I did, you know
you're aware of this, but he rehearses it. He says, from the first day that I came into Asia
after what manner I have been with you at all seasons, serving
the Lord with all humility of mind and with many tears and temptations
which befell me by the lying and weight of the Jews
and how I kept back nothing that was profitable unto
you, but have showed you and have taught you publicly and from house to house.
Verse number 20 is so important as we make connections
in the scriptures and of course we understand that the Bible is a
the best commentary on the Bible is the Bible. No
scriptures of any private interpretation were to compare scripture with
scripture, and here Paul says, I kept back nothing that was
profitable unto you. Do you remember one of our verses from last Sunday morning?
2 Timothy 3 and verse 16, all scripture is given by inspiration of God and is
profitable, right? And so what is Paul saying? I'm giving you that
which is profitable. I'm giving you the word. I'm giving you God's
word, the Bible, and listen, we must
understand this morning that the truth is profitable.
He said people don't want truth. I understand that, but it's the truth that
will make you free. And the reality this morning
is that we must speak the truth as he says in Ephesians 4 in love
but we must speak the truth. Amen?
We can't, we have to speak
the truth. We must do it in love. We must understand that the
little g God of this world hath blinded the minds of them which believe not.
We have to understand and with compassion
give truth because it's profitable. Notice
he says in verse 21, testifying both to the Jews and also to the Greeks,
repentance toward God and faith toward our Lord Jesus Christ.
It's interesting. Salvation, there's only one way to be saved. It doesn't matter
if you're a Jew or a Greek. He says testifying both to the Jews and also to the Greeks.
Repentance toward God and faith toward our Lord Jesus Christ.
Jesus is the only Savior.
He said I am the way, the truth, and the life. No man cometh unto the Father but by me.
He's the only Savior. And Paul preached that.
Verse 22, and now behold I go bound
in the Spirit unto Jerusalem, not knowing the things
that shall befall me there, save that the Holy Ghost witnesseth
every city, saying that bonds and afflictions abide me.
The Apostle Paul didn't know exactly what he would face when he'd go to Jerusalem, but he knew
that there would be more opposition and more adversity. And of course you know
as you study through the book of Acts that he did face serious
turmoil when he got to Jerusalem and all that was taking place. And we find
that we come to verse 24, and this is the key verse that I want to get to when we talk about
this having this resolve that we're going to finish our course,
we're going to finish and finish well. He says, but none of these
things move me. Notice the statement, neither
count I my life dear unto myself.
You know what we find out in life? A lot of people count their lives
dear unto themselves. This is my life. I'm going to do what I
want to do. I'm going to be the, I sit on the throne of my heart.
I'm going to, and it's, listen, Paul says, but none of these things move me.
None of what things? Well, in verse 23 he talked about the bonds and afflictions
that abide him. He says, these things don't move me. The uncertainty that he
speaks of in verse 22, not knowing the things that shall befall me there, those
things don't move me. Why? Because I don't count my life dear unto myself.
Why? Because I've already given my life as a sacrifice to God.
I am crucified with Christ. If I'm
crucified with Christ, if you're crucified with Christ, then none of these
things will move us. Amen?
Notice he says, so that I might finish
my course with joy.
Years before the Apostle Paul ever pens
2 Timothy 4, verses
6-8, he says to the church leaders of
Ephesus that he desires to finish his
course with joy.
That stated, resolute
statement that he makes here, this is a statement that each of us
must make. We must resolve, I want to finish
my course with joy. Notice he
continues and says, and the ministry.
Now, the Apostle Paul had a ministry that was different than the ministry
that you have or that I have. See, remember I mentioned early on when I
talked about that thing of recognize, that first word I shared with you this morning, that you
need to recognize that you have a course. He says, I have finished
my course. Only Paul, he had a specific course
that was for him and you have a specific course that's for you.
Your ministry is different than my ministry. We all are seeking
to, of course as I mentioned there are similarities with our course
or our race. We're all seeking to bring honor and glory to God. We're all
working together as a body of believers to exalt
and magnify the Lord Jesus Christ, but the reality is, he says, and
the ministry, notice, which I have received
of the Lord Jesus. I want you to pause just for a moment and understand
the perspective of the Apostle Paul when he says, I want to finish my
course with joy and I want to finish the ministry, the
work that God has given to me, the work that
he's called me to do, he says, which I have received of the Lord Jesus.
Now understanding who Jesus is and understanding
him using this phrase, Lord Jesus, the reality
is that Paul, he says, I want to finish, I want to do
what God, my Savior, has given to me
to do. Can I tell you this morning when you recognize
that the ministry that you have has been given to you by
God, it changes your perspective. And it
gives you a desire to finish and to do.
It's not just a task that my pastor gave me. It's not
just an assignment that I received from some other person. No.
It's a ministry that I have received from my Savior.
And when I recognize who he is, that he's the
God of the universe, that he's the one that spoke it all into existence, that he
created me and then he redeemed me, that I say, man, I want to
finish. I want to do what he's called me to do.
We find that he says to testify
the gospel of the grace of God.
He wanted to just finish his course with joy.
This morning when we consider this thought of finishing our course
with joy and coming to the place where Paul came to
there in 2 Timothy chapter number 4 and that he was able to make
the statements that he made, this did not happen
by happenstance. No, it happened because he resolved. He said, I want to finish my
course with joy. In Acts chapter 26, turn over a few pages if you will, the
Apostle Paul is here testifying before Agrippa, the king who desired to hear of
him, and you find that he made that request to Festus in chapter 25 and
verse 22, and now the Apostle Paul is speaking to Agrippa. The Bible says in
verse number one that Agrippa says to Paul, thou art permitted to speak for
thyself. Man, Paul was rejoicing in this opportunity that God gave, and he
understood that it was God who gave the opportunity, and he's rejoicing in it, and
I want you to notice, I'm just gonna dig one truth out of this whole passage
that Paul is speaking to Agrippa, but I want you to notice in verse 19 what
Paul says. He says, whereupon, O King Agrippa, I was not disobedient under the
heavenly vision. You know, he mentions about his testimony. He mentioned
starting in verse number 14 about that road to Damascus and hearing that voice,
Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me? He starts there and he begins to to deal
with the fact that God had given him a task, a ministry, a responsibility, and he
says that I was not disobedient unto the heavenly vision. How does that happen? How
is it that that we could come to the place in our lives where we too could
say, as Paul said, for the time of my departure is at hand. I have fought a
good fight. I have finished my course. I have kept the faith, because you must
remember this morning that the enemy wants to hinder you. The enemy wants to
hinder you. You understand this morning that the enemy doesn't want you to
finish your course with joy. He doesn't want you to finish well. It's amazing
how active the enemy is on attacking the people of God. He doesn't want you to
finish your course with joy. He doesn't want me to finish my course with joy.
Notice what Paul says to the believers in Galatia, the churches in the region of
Galatia are being written to, and in Galatians chapter number 5, the Apostle
Paul makes a statement that is so impactful with regard to the subject
that we're dealing with this morning of making, having this course, and
being able to finish our course with joy, to finish well, that we must resolve, as
Paul did. Galatians 5 and verse number 7, the Bible says, ye did run well. Who did
hinder you that you should not obey the truth? Ye did run well. Oh, I hope it would
never be said of us. Ye did run well, but that it would be that we could come to
the place where we say, I have finished my course. I have kept the faith. I finished
well. I finished strong. How am I to do that? Well, I recognize that he
saved me, and I understand, and I recognize that he equipped me, and he
gave me a work to do, that I recognize that I have this course, I have this life
that I'm living, and I'm living this life to please the one who died for me.
Second Corinthians chapter 5, powerful passage of Scripture dealing with the
fact that he died for all, that they which live should not henceforth live
unto themselves, but unto him which loved them, and he died for us, and he rose
again, and he lives forevermore, and we're to live for him, and we're to serve
him. We take the truth of Hebrews chapter 12 in verse number 2, looking unto Jesus,
the author and finisher of our faith, that we keep our eyes on Jesus, that as
we go through this life, this Christian life, this course that we're
running, that we are resolved, that I want to finish well. I want to
finish well. I want to hear, well done, thou good and faithful servant. I want to
this morning, and I hope, and I trust that each of you do as well, when I stand
before Christ, and what a terrifying thought. I want to receive reward. I
don't want to suffer loss. This morning, recognize, rejoice, but resolve. You're on
a course this morning. I'm on a course this morning, and one day our course is
going to end, and we're going to see Jesus. Wonderful, wonderful truth, but how do I
get to the point where I could say, I have finished my course. I am now ready
to be offered. The time of my departure is at hand. I have fought a good fight. I
have finished my course. I have kept the faith. This morning, you have to be
purposed. You have to be purposed. You have to make the statement like Paul did
years ahead of time today, making that statement not knowing when we will
finish our course. I want to finish with joy, because I recognize what he's given
me. I can't run your course. You can't run my course. You can't run your kid's
course. You can't run your spouse's course. You can't run anyone else's
course. You have a course. You have a life that you're living, and one day your
life is going to end. This mortal shall put on immortality. This corruption shall
put on incorruption. Is that not what 1 Corinthians 15 tells us? Life is going to
end one day. It's appointed unto man once to die, but after this, the judgment. We
must, number one, know that we're saved, but then, number two, we must resolve that
we're going to finish our course and finish it well. The Lord will help you.
The Lord will help me. The Lord helped Paul. He mentions it throughout the last
part of the fourth chapter that we'll study over the next couple of weeks. He
mentions how God helped him, not only there, but other portions of Scripture as
well, and God will help you this morning. He will enable you to be able to say, as
Paul said, I have finished my course. Let's pray together. Father, we love you.
Oh, how we thank you for loving us. Thank you for saving my soul. We sang about that
earlier this morning. God, I'm thankful that I'm saved by the blood of Christ.
I'm thankful that I'm kept by the power of God. I'm thankful that I have a home
in heaven. God, I recognize this morning that between my day of salvation, the day
in which I was born again, and the day in which my life ends here on earth, that
I'm running a course. God, I desire to finish my course with joy. I desire to
finish well. I rejoice that I'll see you one day. God, I pray that you'd help each
one of us this morning to resolve, to make some decisions, to purpose, to chart
this out. How am I going to get to the place where Paul did to be able to say,
I have finished my course. I have kept the faith. So often we make plans for so
many things in life. We spend time mapping out retirement plans and unfortunately
at times give little thought to eternal plans. Lord, I pray that this morning, in
this moment of invitation, that your spirit would work in hearts and lives. Help us,
Lord, to make some decisions this morning that would please thee. Help us, Lord, to
not leave this place as we came to this place, but help us to leave different,
stirred up, to finish our course with joy. Well, thank you for every decision that's
made. For it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed,
eyes are closed. Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano. And as she does,
the altar is open.