Genesis chapter number six this evening, if you have your Bible with you, Genesis chapter
number six.
We'll be looking at verses eight through 13 this evening.
You'll recall from our message of last Sunday evening that the first seven verses of Genesis
six provide us with an understanding of the society in which Noah lived.
We dealt with that subject matter.
I preached a message that I entitled The Wickedness of Man Was Great, and we looked at those things.
As we observed the corruption of mankind and noted that the ungodly marriages, the
unbridled lust, and we dealt with all of those things that are recorded there in the first
seven verses of Genesis chapter number six, and I'll have to admit to you this evening
that at times I am guilty of looking at the society in which we live and lamenting at
the wickedness around us and just kind of feeling sorry for myself.
If I could just be honest with you, sometimes we live in this society, we see some things
that are going on.
You see the legislation and the decisions of those in our culture and our society where
they call good evil and they call evil good.
I read a report just this afternoon actually about a survey that was done, not here in
America but over in Europe, and they were asking questions about morality, and it was
so troubling to read the responses of the individuals and the moral compass of our society
today is just not where it needs to be, amen?
And sometimes we can kind of get kind of looking at that and focusing on that, and we see all
of the wickedness around us, and yet we have to remember this truth that man is born a
sinner, and sinners sin, amen?
That's what they do.
And we need to be reminded of the truth that man is not basically good.
Man is wicked.
Man is evil, amen?
And we have to remember that the answer is Jesus Christ and new life in Christ.
That is the only hope for this nation or any other nation upon the face of the earth is
the new life found in Christ.
If any man be in Christ, he is a new creature, amen?
Old things are passed away, behold all things become new.
And what a blessing it is to know the power of a transformed life.
This evening we could trace through the history of mankind, and we could note on a number
of different periods of time, and we'd look at the era of history, and we could find that
throughout the pages of history that we can understand the wickedness and the darkness
of mankind.
The thing that's exciting for us is what would cause us to rejoice is that in the midst of
that darkness and wickedness, we have the knowledge of this truth that God always has
a man.
And we find throughout the pages of history, if you were to study and look at various periods
of history of mankind, yes, we can see the wickedness and we can see the darkness, but
I'm thankful that there's a remnant, that there's a group of people that stand for truth
and for righteousness.
And we find that in the book of Genesis in the sixth chapter that we're studying this
evening, that man was Noah.
The Bible begins in the text of scripture that we're going to study this evening that
says this.
We read about the wickedness and the corruption, and then we come to verse number eight.
It says, but Noah found grace in the eyes of the Lord.
These are the generations of Noah.
Noah was a just man and perfect in his generations, and Noah walked with God.
Noah begat three sons, Shem, Ham, and Japheth.
It says this.
The earth also was corrupt before God.
The earth was filled with violence.
God looked upon the earth, and behold, it was corrupt, for all flesh had corrupted his
way upon the earth.
God said unto Noah, the end of all flesh has come before me, for the earth is filled with
violence through them.
Behold, I will destroy them with the earth.
We understand as we look at the life of Noah that he resisted the ungodly influence of
those all around him, and the Bible tells us in verse number nine that Noah walked with
God.
That's the title for the message this evening, and we think about that phrase, and in our
minds, as you've been studying with us, our minds would race back to the fifth chapter
of the book of Genesis in the 22nd verse, where the Bible tells us of Enoch.
It says, Enoch walked with God.
Now we find that Noah has that same testimony, that he walked with God.
What a powerful truth.
In the midst of a crooked and perverse generation, in the midst of great wickedness and corruption,
the Bible says that the earth was filled with violence, yet there was a man.
The Bible says, but Noah found grace in the eyes of the Lord.
The Bible tells us some things about Noah.
If you're taking notes this evening, just notice with me, to begin tonight, the characteristics
of Noah.
Notice with me in verses eight and nine the characteristics of Noah.
I want you to understand, first of all, the Bible says, but Noah found grace, notice,
in the eyes of the Lord.
I'm impressed as we would look at that phraseology and we'd understand this evening it's a truth
that we see throughout all of the pages of Scripture, that God is aware of all things.
Aren't you thankful this evening that God is aware of all things?
The reality is that the truth of that thought this evening, when it says that he found grace
in the eyes of the Lord, that God knows and that God sees, the writer of the book of Proverbs,
the wise man, said it this way in Proverbs 5, in verse number 21, for the ways of man
are before the eyes of the Lord, and he, God, pondereth all his goings.
We find here that Noah, though he was living in the midst of a corrupt society, in great
wickedness, we find that the Bible says that he found grace in the eyes of the Lord, that
God observed this man, and he begins to provide us in verse number nine with these characteristics
that says these are the generations of Noah.
Notice first of all, it says Noah was a just man.
The idea of Noah being called and referred to as a just man would carry with it the idea
of being righteous and lawful.
We find that at this particular time in human history, God had not yet given the law of
Moses.
God had not yet communicated those things to his people, yet we find that God had indeed
communicated to his people.
We know that Adam walked in the garden and he walked with the Lord, and we know that
there were offerings that were brought, and we're certainly aware of the fact that God
had communicated certain aspects of his law and of his way to mankind, and Noah, the Bible
says, was a just man.
He was righteous and lawful.
The Bible continues and says this, that he was perfect in his generations.
That word perfect, and the understanding of this phraseology is that he would be complete
or whole, entire.
I think about the New Testament truth for us as the people of God today, and I'm mindful
if you hold your spot there in the book of Genesis and go over to the book of 2 Timothy
in the third chapter, and we'll actually be back here in a little while this evening as
we finish up tonight, but I want you to notice what the word of God tells us as we think
about the description, the characteristics of Noah, where God says not only is he a just
man, but he's perfect in his generations.
In 2 Timothy 3, in verse number 16, the Bible says, all scripture is given by inspiration
of God, and it's profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for instruction
and righteousness.
Notice verse 17, that the man of God may be what?
Perfect, throughly furnished unto all good works.
Understanding the place of being complete, whole, entire.
The idea is we would look throughout the use of this word, and obviously words change
their meanings, and it's important to understand the time in which the words were used and
so on and so forth, and we find here that it's meaning that he's complete.
It does not carry with it the idea of perfection and the idea of sinless perfection.
We know that Noah was a man that was born after Adam.
We look even in the book of Romans in the fifth chapter and understanding that he was
a sinner, but he was a man that was complete.
The Bible summarizes it this way, at the end of verse number nine, and Noah walked with
God.
You get a picture in your mind about this walk that Noah had with the Lord, we begin
to, in our mind, in our sanctified imagination, consider this wonderful testimony of this
great patriarch, and you think about Noah having that testimony just as Enoch did, and
the Bible gives us some insight into the life of Enoch, and certainly it does for the life
of Noah as well, but it's interesting when we think about Enoch walking with God, it
says this in the book of Hebrews, in the eleventh chapter and verse number five, that
he was translated, but it says this, before his translation he had this testimony, that
he pleased God, and Enoch walked with God and he pleased God.
Noah walked with God, and I believe that we could conclude this evening that he pleased
God as he walked with God.
You know, what a privilege it is that we can walk with the Lord, isn't it a great privilege?
Our God is personal, isn't that wonderful?
He is the creator of the universe.
He is the Lord God omnipotent.
He transcends us.
His ways are not our ways.
His thoughts are not our thoughts.
He is so much greater than we are, yet in all of his greatness, in all of his holiness,
he's a personal God.
We can walk with him.
We can have fellowship with him.
Walk in the light as he is in the light, 1 John, isn't that precious?
If we say that we have fellowship with him, but we walk not in the light, we lie.
The truth's not in us, right?
And we understand 1 John dealing there much about the idea of fellowship, and what a joy
it is that we can have that fellowship with God.
Fellowship with God was hindered after Adam and Eve sinned, right?
The relationship between God and man was forever changed, altered at that moment in which sin
entered into the world.
And I'm thankful for the truth of reconciliation, that mankind can be reconciled to God, but
only by the blood, amen?
It's the only way of redemption.
It's the only way of reconciliation.
And we find that he caused us to, because of the blood of Christ and the imputed righteousness
of Christ, that we have that restored fellowship, and we can enter into the very presence of
God, and we can have communion with him.
The God of the universe.
This is amazing.
You look at some of the religions of the world, you look at some of the cults of the world,
and they have this far out, distant God that is not reachable, not personal, yet the God
of the universe, the true and living God, the only true and living God, he's a personal
God, and we can walk with him.
Isn't that a great testimony?
The Bible says that Noah, he was a just man, he was perfect in his generations, and it
summarizes it by saying this, Noah walked with God.
We note in the text of Scripture not only the characteristics of Noah, but notice the
corruption and coming destruction.
Such of, or much of this text of Scripture that we're going to look at here in these
few verses, in verses 11 through 13, is really a summary of what we've already looked at
from last Sunday evening, when God had shared with us the culture and society and what have
you, but you notice in verses 11 through 13, the Bible says this, the earth also was corrupt
before God.
The earth was filled with violence.
God looked upon the earth, and behold, it was corrupt, for all flesh had corrupted his
way upon the earth.
And God said unto Noah, the end of all flesh has come before me, for the earth is filled
with violence through them, and behold, I will destroy them with the earth.
You know what's interesting is that as we look at verses 11 through 13 of Genesis chapter
number 6, God had previously notated in our text of Scripture in the first few verses
of Genesis chapter number 6, he had given us the insight concerning the society and
the corruption and the wickedness, but now we find that God is communicating this truth
to this man, Noah, that walked with God.
You know that when we walk with God, we get truth from God.
When we spend time with God, when we get into the Word of God, and we spend that sweet communion
with God, God teaches us, and God reveals truth to us.
And we find here that Noah was a man that walked with God, and now God begins to share
truth with Noah.
He begins to share with Noah personally what God's plan is.
Isn't that special?
So there's a bunch of people tonight that live in our world, there are a bunch of people
that are running around and they have all these ideas as to what's going to happen and
trying to identify signs of the times and this and that and so on and so forth, but
the reality is that the man that would walk with God, the individual, the believer that
would walk with the Lord, that would get into His Word, we can be taught by God, and God
can give us truth.
I think about those servants at that very first miracle of the Lord Jesus Christ at
the marriage of Cana, and we think about all that took place, and the Bible would tell
us in John chapter number 2 that those that were gathered together, they knew not how
these things had come about, but the servants, the ones that were with Jesus, they knew.
They knew.
Why?
Because they were with Jesus.
In this evening, we think about Noah, notice specifically in verse number 13 that God speaks
directly to Noah.
God said unto Noah in Genesis 6 in verse number 13, the end of all flesh has come before me,
for the earth is filled with violence through them, and behold, I, God, He says, I will
destroy them with the earth.
He didn't give this truth to any other person.
He gave it to Noah.
We find that Noah walked with God, the corruption and coming destruction, the society in which
he lived.
Can you imagine this evening living in such a society?
Perhaps some of us could say, yes, we can imagine living in such a society.
But I want you to think about Noah and his testimony, and I want you to think about the
fact that the Bible tells us that Noah walked with God, and he walked with God in the midst
of this society, in the midst of the corruption and the violence and the wickedness when God
says, I'm going to destroy them with the earth, that's the society in which Noah walked with
God.
You know, there are times in which we will hear the individuals use the excuse, well,
you know, it's just too hard for me to walk with God.
It's just too hard for me to, you don't understand the pressures, you don't understand the influences,
you don't understand the ridicule, you don't understand how they make fun of me.
Whatever the excuse might be, listen, Noah walked with God.
Can you imagine the pressures that he must have had?
Can you imagine some of the ridicule that he must have faced?
Can you imagine when he was for over 100 years building an ark, and how that people probably,
we don't know, it's just something that we're saying as far as assuming would be concerned,
but the ridicule in which he must have faced.
The Bible says he was a preacher of righteousness, but yet there were only his sons and their
wives and his wife that got onto the ark.
He had no one that responded to his message outside of his family.
And this evening as I think about the characteristics of Noah, I think about the corruption and
coming destruction, and we see what God is telling us, I look at this and I want to make
application for us this evening, and I want you to consider the call for God's people
today.
I want you to consider with me and look over in the New Testament, we're going to look
at a number of passages of Scripture, keeping Noah in our minds tonight, and his testimony
that he had, but I want you to consider the call for God's people today.
Though we find ourselves living in the midst of wickedness and corruption, and indeed,
we find that legislation indeed is being given, written, that is legislating wickedness in
our society.
We see it.
If you are not aware of that tonight, your head is in the sand.
Amen?
I mean, that's where we're living.
But yet, our God is on his throne, and our God has called us that even in the midst of
such a society, he has called us to live a life of holiness and separation.
Romans chapter number 12 is where we'll begin with looking at some of these New Testament
truths with regard to the child of God, living and walking with God, the call that God has
placed upon our lives.
In Romans chapter number 12, it's a familiar passage of Scripture, the first two verses
of this chapter.
Many of us, no doubt, could quote these verses of Scripture, but we find that Paul comes
here near to the end of the book of Romans, and he has laid out such great truth in these
first 11 chapters.
And now he gets to this 12th chapter, and he says this,
I beseech you therefore, brethren, by the mercies of God, that you present your body
as a living sacrifice, holy, acceptable unto God, he says this, which is your reasonable
service.
And be not conformed to this world, but be ye transformed by the renewing of your mind
that ye may prove what is that good and acceptable and perfect will of God.
We find that the apostle Paul in the book of Romans had gone through a series of very
well-documented truth as he's presented as a lawyer would present his case, if you will,
and he shares with those in Rome about the truth of mankind's wickedness and sinfulness
and that all have sinned and come short of the glory of God.
He deals with the fact that that sin is inherited in us, it's a sin nature that we receive from
Adam all the way back in the garden as he would refer to in Romans chapter number 5.
He speaks about the gift of God.
He contrasts the gift of God with the wages of sin.
We're so thankful that salvation is a gift.
It cannot be earned.
It's a gift.
We come to that 10th chapter
as we would look at and share truth
and we begin to speak to individuals
about the fact that the Bible says
for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord
shall be saved.
Isn't that precious?
Think about our salvation.
We find that Paul then says to these believers,
note, he says, I beseech you therefore, brethren.
He's speaking to those that have been born again.
To those that have accepted that message
that have been laid out.
And he says that I'm begging you,
I beseech you, brethren.
He says this, by the mercies of God
that we present our bodies this living sacrifice.
We'd understand that he says,
be not conformed to this world.
That's the world system in which we live.
The influences of the world.
Listen, the world has always been the enemy of God's people.
Amen?
You read there in the book of 1 John
in chapter number two,
you read over in the book of James
and it speaks about the love of the world.
Listen, if you love the world,
he says that the love of God is not in you.
We can't love God and love the world.
Amen?
You say, well, that's harsh language.
That's the Bible.
Amen.
And the reality is that we find
that there's a call that's been issued
to the child of God that they would live
a life of holiness and a life of separation.
Being not conformed to this world.
Listen, we're to be the agents, excuse me,
of change in our society
that were to go out and let our light so shine before men
that they may see our good works
and glorify our Father which is in heaven
that we would shine in the midst of this darkness.
We find that here in Romans 12,
verses one and two, what a great truth.
If I could call it my life verse,
2 Corinthians chapter five,
if you turn over there to the passage of Scripture,
in 2 Corinthians chapter number five,
many of you that have received
any kind of correspondence from me,
whether it's an email or a card,
I often will sign with this verse of Scripture,
2 Corinthians five in verse number 15.
It's a verse of Scripture that's so precious to me.
The Bible says this, and that he died for all,
that they which live should not henceforth
live unto themselves,
but unto him which died for them and rose again.
If we were to continue to go through
the passage of Scripture,
we come to that verse that I quoted earlier
in my way of introduction in verse 17.
If any man be in Christ, he's a new creature.
We find that he speaks about the importance
of our responsibility and our position
as being ambassadors for Christ in verse number 20.
He speaks in verse number 21
about the imputed righteousness of God
where it says he hath made him to be sin for us
who knew no sin that we might be made
the righteousness of God in him.
And when I consider all that God has done for me,
when I consider what Jesus paid for my salvation,
when I understand that he died for me and he rose again,
oh, that I would live for him.
And we see that Noah,
as we notice in Genesis chapter number six,
Noah's a man that lived for God, he walked with God.
Can I tell you this evening,
he didn't have all the Bible that we have.
He didn't have any of the Bible, amen?
Now God spoke to him,
but Moses wouldn't even write the book of Genesis
for many generations.
And yet we have the whole canon of scripture this evening.
What a joy, what a blessing.
And we can go and we can look at what God has given us
and we can see in ink on paper
the instruction that God has given us,
the call that he's given to his people
to walk and to live this life of holiness and separation.
Philippians chapter number two,
notice here as the apostle Paul
is writing to this church in Philippi.
And as he's writing to this church
and he's giving them instruction,
we find that he's just given them in the second chapter
the wonderful example of the humility
of the Lord Jesus Christ about his incarnation,
how he left the throne room of heaven
and he humbled himself and he became obedient unto death
and so on and so forth.
And we find that the Bible tells us
that God also hath highly exalted him
and given him a name which is above every name.
In verse number 10, it says that the name of Jesus,
every knee should bow and every tongue should confess.
It says this, excuse me,
every knee should bow in verse number 10
of things in heaven and things in earth
and things under the earth, verse number 11,
and that every tongue should confess
that Jesus Christ is Lord,
to the glory of God the Father.
I've often said as I look at that passage of Scripture,
it's not a matter of if, it's a matter of when.
Every knee will bow and every tongue will confess.
It's not a matter of if, it's a matter of when.
We find that just a few verses later in verse number 15,
the Bible says that you may be blameless and harmless,
the sons of God without rebuke
in the midst of a crooked and perverse nation
among whom you shine as lights in the world.
He doesn't say, listen, I'm gonna give you a pass.
I know that you're living in the time of wickedness
and I know that it's challenging and it's hard
and just go find yourself a cave somewhere
and just hold on until Jesus comes back.
No, no, no, no, no, that's not what he said.
Amen?
He said that we're to shine as lights in the world.
In the world that he's speaking of
that you live in the midst of a crooked and perverse nation
that Noah, in the midst of all of that wickedness
and corruption, that he walked with God.
What a great testimony.
Oh, that we'd walk with God.
Turn over if you will to the book of 1 Thessalonians.
I'm looking at all these passages of Scripture this evening
because it's so important that we would find
the truth and the call that's been issued
to God's people tonight
that we would have that same testimony that Noah had,
that we'd just get over the excuses of the wickedness
and you just don't understand how hard it is.
No, God is God and he is eternal
and he's given us this call.
Oh, that we as his people would stand
and live as we're called to live.
I preached a message many years ago
that I entitled Living Right in a Wrong World.
Man, we live in a wrong world.
We might get ridiculed,
but it's our responsibility to live right.
Here in 1 Thessalonians 3, notice in verse number five,
he says, for this cause,
when I could no longer forbear,
I sent to know your faith,
lest by some means the tempter of tempt at you
in our labor be in vain.
But now when Timotheus came from you unto us
and brought us good tidings of your faith and charity
and that you have good remembrance of us always,
desiring greatly to see us as we also to see you.
We notice that there's some information given here
concerning their walk.
He then will tell us,
if you skip over to the fourth chapter in the first verse,
and he says, furthermore, then we beseech you, brethren,
and exhort you by the Lord Jesus,
that as you have received of us,
how you ought to walk and to please God
so you would abound more and more.
Can I tell you that here,
as Paul would give this truth to the believers
in Thessalonica there in chapter four in the first verse
about his exhortation of how they are to walk
and how they're to please God,
that they were living in a time
in which they were dealing with much affliction.
In fact, if you'd go back to the first chapter,
we find that the Bible tells us in verse number six
of 1 Thessalonians one,
and you became followers of us and of the Lord,
having received the word in much affliction
with joy of the Holy Ghost.
They were dealing with affliction and adversity,
but yet Paul tells them,
you received of us how you're to walk,
how you're to please God.
I'm so thankful that God has given us
the truth of his word that would reveal to us
how it is that we're to walk
and how it is that we could please him with our lives.
Turn over, if you will, to 2 Timothy chapter number three.
We'll finish here this evening.
In 2 Timothy chapter number three,
and I'm gonna read a little lengthier passage
of Scripture here than what I've read
in the previous passages that we've gone to,
but I want you to notice as the Apostle Paul
here writing the final letter
that he would ever pen humanly
before he would face his martyr's death,
and he's writing to his son in the faith, Timothy.
We find that it's in that fourth chapter
that we read of those parting words,
but here in 2 Timothy chapter number three,
we find that the Apostle Paul
is going to give Timothy some insight
with regard to the last days,
the last days, I believe, this evening
that we're living in the last days.
It says this beginning in verse number one
of 2 Timothy three,
this, what's that next word say?
No, this know also.
What did God reveal to Noah?
He revealed his plan, did he not?
Remember, as we look there in Genesis chapter number six
in verse number 13, because Noah had that testimony,
because Noah walked with God.
It was God that then spoke to Noah
and told Noah what He was going to do.
And here we find that God intends for His people
once again, even as I preached this morning,
to be informed, and He says,
this know also that in the last days,
I believe we're there,
perilous times shall come.
Notice the description, if you will.
In v. 2, it says,
for men shall be lovers of their own selves.
Lovageous, boasters, proud, blasphemers,
disobedient to parents,
unthankful, unholy,
without natural affection,
truce breakers, false accusers,
incontinent, fierce,
despisers of those that are good,
traitors, heady, high-minded,
lovers of pleasure more than lovers of God,
having a form of godliness,
but denying the power thereof
from such turn away.
We don't have time this evening
to go through and define
every characteristic that God gives us
here in this passage of Scripture,
but when you read those verses as I read
and emphasized each of those identifiers
and the characteristics that God gives us
with regard to these last days
and the way in which He describes the people,
oh, we can relate to seeing those things
even in our society today.
Let's get down to verse 10.
He says,
"...but thou hast fully known My doctrine,
manner of life, purpose, faith,
long-suffering, charity, patience,
persecutions, afflictions,
which came unto Me at Antioch,
at Iconium, at Lystra,
what persecutions I endured,
but out of them all the Lord delivered Me."
Verse 12,
"...yea, and all that will live godly in Christ Jesus
shall suffer persecution."
But notice verse 13,
"...but evil men and seducers shall wax..."
What's it say in your Bible?
Worse and worse.
It doesn't say better and better, right?
It says worse and worse.
Deceiving and being deceived.
And so we stop there just for a moment this evening
and we see the picture that has been painted
with regard to these last days
and we see some of the characteristics
that are given in those first few verses
of 2 Timothy 3.
We come to those middle verses
that we've just read in verses 10
down through verse number 13
and we see that the Apostle Paul is saying,
you've known my behavior,
you've known what I've done,
you've known my teaching,
my doctrine, so on and so forth.
He speaks about some of those hardships
in which he endured.
He refers back to the first missionary journey
in verse number 11
when he went to Antioch and Iconium and Lystra
and you can read in the book of Acts
and you can read and trace the history
of that first missionary journey
and you can read about all that he suffered
and all that he dealt with
and he says, he gives this testimony
that the Lord delivered him out of them all.
What a blessing.
And we read in the book of Acts
and we see how God was miraculously working
and using the Apostle Paul.
He says, those that would live godly in Christ Jesus,
yea, and all that will live godly in Christ Jesus,
shall suffer persecution.
And then he tells Timothy,
but evil men and seducers shall wax worse and worse,
deceiving and being deceived.
Far too often, as I would go to various conferences
and read various things that come across my desk,
I so often read of individuals
that love to quote 2 Timothy 3 in verse number 13.
And they love to focus on the fact of these last days
and indeed it's true.
We can get so caught up in verse number 13
that we forget what Paul told Timothy.
Paul didn't end it at verse number 13.
Paul didn't say, hey, it's just really bad out there,
just hang on until Jesus comes back.
No, no, Paul told Timothy, but continue.
You mean to tell me that in the midst
of what you've just described
and all of these characteristics that are mentioned
with the truth that evil men and seducers
are gonna wax worse and worse,
deceiving and being deceived,
you want me to continue?
Yes, but continue thou in the things
which thou hast learned and has been assured of,
knowing of whom thou hast learned them.
Notice verse 15, and that from a child,
thou hast known the Holy Scriptures,
which are able to make thee wise unto salvation
through faith, which is in Christ Jesus.
By the way, if you've known the Scriptures
since you've been a child,
you ought to thank God for that, amen?
There's a number of people in this room tonight
that could stand up and give testimony
that I didn't get saved while I was a child.
I was almost an adult when I got saved.
I know that Joyce often,
when she shares her testimony of salvation,
you were in your 30s when you trusted Christ as your Savior.
Some say, man, I was even older than that.
But here, Paul says to Timothy that from a child,
thou hast known the Holy Scriptures,
which are able to make thee wise unto salvation.
And what a joy that is.
He says all Scripture is given by inspiration of God.
It's profitable.
Well, look what he says.
It's profitable for what?
For doctrine, for reproof, for correction,
for instruction in righteousness.
We read verse number 17
in the beginning of the message this evening
when it said that Noah was perfect in his generations.
And we noticed here, the Bible says
that the man of God may be perfect,
thoroughly furnished unto all good works.
But notice how Paul continues into chapter number four.
He issues a charge.
He says, I charge thee.
Therefore, before God and the Lord Jesus Christ,
who shall judge the quick and the dead
that is appearing in this kingdom.
What's he telling them to do?
Preach the word.
Hold on a minute.
Chapter three is still there.
All of those characteristics.
Evil men waxing worse and worse,
deceiving and being deceived.
And yet, Paul tells Timothy, preach the word.
Preach the word.
He tells them here, be instant insees and outsees
and reprove, rebuke, and exhort
with all longsuffering and doctrine.
Notice verses three and four.
It says, for the time will come
when they will not endure sound doctrine.
But after their own lusts,
shall they heap to themselves teachers,
having itching ears.
They shall turn away their ears from the truth
and shall be turned unto fables.
But watch down all things, endure afflictions,
do the work of evangelists,
make full proof of thy ministry.
Paul to Timothy, he says, listen.
Here's the characteristics of the last days.
Here's what's going to happen.
But Timothy, the message is continue.
And for us this evening,
the call for us as God's people today
is not to get overwhelmed and distracted
by the things that we see going on in our society.
We just keep our eyes on Jesus
and we just keep on preaching the word of God
and doing what God called us to do,
living as lights in a crooked and perverse generation.
That we would, listen, we might face ridicule,
but the Bible says all those
that live godly in Christ Jesus
shall suffer persecution.
Can I tell you that anything that any of us,
as far as I know, that any of us have faced
by way of persecution pales in comparison
to what the believers in the first century faced
and it pales in comparison
to what some of our brothers and sisters
in other parts of this world face today.
We find that the answer is that we,
as God's people, would continue.
See, Noah, he lived in the midst of that society
and it was corrupt and it was going to be destroyed
because of the wickedness
and God defines all of that to us,
but we find that Noah continued to walk with God.
And this evening, who's walking with God?
Are we walking with God?
Do we have that testimony if God were to come and say,
if he were to give just a summary of our society today
and were to look in the midst of just our region
of this state and say, here's the characteristics,
here's what's going on,
but I got some people that are walking with me.
I got some people that are living and shining
and they're doing what they're supposed to do
because God's issued this call to us.
And it's not appropriate that we would make excuses
and that we would allow the society to influence us.
One of the major problems in the church in Corinth
is that they were being influenced by the society
as opposed to them influencing the society.
We find that worldliness was creeping into the church.
If we'd be honest this evening,
we see it all across our land
where worldliness is creeping into the church.
There are preachers all across this land
that have decided that they're going to change
the messages that they preach
so that they would be more palatable for the people.
It happens all the time.
I read stuff all the time.
Well, the people just won't endure it.
I know, Paul told Timothy that.
But he didn't change Timothy's responsibility
to preach the word, amen?
And we stand upon the truth of the word of God.
Listen, our nation needs revival.
They need to see that God is real.
And who's gonna reveal that to them
if we allow the society to influence us?
We gotta walk with God.
We gotta have that testimony that Noah had.
We look at that testimony of Noah and we say.
I say, man, in the midst of such a time, Noah found grace in the eyes of the Lord.
He was a just man, he was perfect in his generations, and it summarizes it this way, that Noah walked
with God.
God's called you, God's called me.
In the midst of whatever the wickedness might be around us, to walk with God, to walk with
God, and to be a light in this dark world.
This evening let's be like Noah, let's not make excuses and say, well, it's just so hard.
I understand it can be hard, but with God, with the help of God, it's possible.
It is possible that we can walk with Him in this dark world.
Amen?
Let's pray.