chapter number 4, Genesis chapter number 4, and we'll look at the latter part of this
particular chapter and then all of chapter number 5 this evening.
Genesis chapter number 4 will begin in verse number 25, and you'll recall that last week
we studied the record of the ungodly line of Cain as it's recorded really in verse 16
through 24 of chapter number 4, and we noticed as we studied that portion of Scripture last
Sunday evening that there was the departure of Cain.
The Bible says that he went out from the presence of the Lord.
He went to the city of, or to the land of Nod that was on the east of Eden, and we looked
at that, the departure of this one Cain, and then we also looked at the description of
the society.
We said this last week, that from a temporal perspective as you'd read those verses of
Scripture that you would conclude that they made progress, that there was development,
there was a city, there were all sorts of things that were taking place, but yet it
was a society that was apart from God.
It was a society that from a temporal perspective, it seemed to be going well, but we find that
it was just a, what can we accomplish?
What can we do?
The reality is that God has made us as eternal beings and we need Him.
We need God.
We've been designed by God to have fellowship with God.
The wickedness of that line is noted, but we can rejoice as we study the passage of
Scripture that's before us this evening in understanding that God always has a remnant.
Though we can read of the worldliness and the ungodliness of that line of Cain, we can
rejoice this evening in a line that is a godly line, the line of Seth.
In this passage of Scripture, we travel from Adam to Noah, covering nearly over 1,500 years.
It's amazing how the time so quickly we go through the generations that are mentioned.
Look at it, if you will, with me in verse number 25.
The Bible says this, and Adam knew his wife again, and she bare a son and called his name
Seth.
For God, said she, hath appointed me another seed instead of Abel, whom Cain slew.
And to Seth, to him also there was born a son, and he called his name Enos.
Then began men to call upon the name of the Lord.
Verse 1 of chapter 5, this is the book of the generations of Adam.
The day that God created man and the likeness of God made he him.
Male and female created he them and blessed them and called their name Adam, and the day
when they were created.
And Adam lived 130 years and begat a son in his own likeness after his image and called
his name Seth.
As we look at the passage of scripture that's before us this evening, we are reminded of
a truth that was given to us back in Genesis chapter number 3 and verse number 15.
Remember it was in that passage of scripture that the Lord says as the judgment was being
executed because of the sin that entered the world, he says to Satan in Genesis 3 and verse
15, and I will put enmity between thee and the woman and between thy seed and her seed.
It shall bruise thy head and thou shalt bruise his heel.
And during that particular message we discuss the seed of the woman, of course understanding
Messiah who would come.
And I want you to just for a moment think about what we're reading now in Genesis chapter
number 4 and 5, and thinking about the genealogies that are provided, Adam, of course the first
two sons that are mentioned, Cain and Abel.
Abel has been slain and Cain is wicked and so God raises up another son.
The son's name is Seth and it says that this is what Eve said in verse number 25, for God
said she hath appointed me another seed instead of Abel whom Cain slew.
Now here's the thing that's interesting.
If you go to the book of Luke, and we won't take time to read all of the passage of scripture,
but if you go to Luke chapter number 3 and you look at verses 23 through 38, God provides
a record of the genealogy of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And in providing that genealogy we find that Matthew 1 contains genealogy there as well,
but in Luke chapter number 3, I'll just take a moment to read the last few verses of the
third chapter of the gospel of Luke, and it begins in verse number 23 about the genealogy
of the Lord Jesus Christ, but in verse number 37 it says, which was of the son of Methuselah,
which was the son of Enoch, which was the son of Jared, which was the son of Melialiel,
which was the son of Canaan, which was the son of Enos, which was the son of Seth, which
was the son of Adam, which was the son of God.
And you go to Luke chapter number 3 and you see that God fulfilled the very promise that
he made in Genesis 3 in verse number 15 of that seed, Messiah who would come, that would
be the seed of the woman, and it is through the line of Seth that you find here, yes ultimately
going back to Adam as the first man, but you find that in our genealogy this evening as
we're studying the godly line of Seth, that it goes not to Cain or Abel, but we find that
it goes to Seth.
And what a blessing that is to see the whole of scripture and to see how God provides and
how God blesses.
Remember, we've made this statement, this understanding, not only in our study of the
book of Genesis, but really broadly as you study the word of God, you find that the enemy
is against God.
Satan is against God, and as you read the Old Testament, you study the Old Testament,
you see the repeated attack upon the seed, upon the line, the promised line of Messiah.
So often you find these groups of people, the Philistines as being one that comes to
mind very quickly, that are constantly going against Israel to try to wipe Israel out,
to try to destroy them.
Remember the man by the name of Haman, what did he want to do?
He wanted to kill all the Jews.
By the way, he had received authority from the king in order to carry out his evil, wicked
plot, but God intervened.
Why?
Because God is greater, but there's this continued conflict throughout the Old Testament that
you can read of and you can see what's taking place, and really, yes, it's the enemy against
the children of God, against the nation of Israel, but you find that it's really an attack
upon that line of Messiah that had been promised all the way back in Genesis chapter number
three.
Now as we get into the study this evening, I want you to notice some important points,
some important truth that is revealed to us in this portion of Scripture that I've read.
We're going to continue to look through the end of chapter number five this evening.
By the time we get done, we'll end with Noah at the end of chapter number five, but I do
want you to notice a few things from the passage that I've read already.
I want you to notice, first of all, that Adam was created by God and he was made in the
likeness of God.
You say, we already know that.
Yes, we studied the first chapter of Genesis, but it's important to note specifically what
is said in Genesis five in verse number one.
The Bible begins by telling us, this is the book of the generations of Adam.
Notice in the day that God created man.
What day?
Day six of creation, right?
We have that record in Genesis chapter number one.
It was on the sixth day of creation that God created man, and notice God created man in
the likeness of God, made he him.
In Genesis one, in verse number 27, the Bible says, so God created man in his own image,
in the image of God created he him, male and female created he them.
We have been created by God.
Adam was created in the image and likeness, he was made in the image and likeness of God.
We find the consistency between that which is given to us in Genesis five one, and Genesis
one in verse number 27.
He says this, not only do we notice as we look at this important truth that's revealed
to us that Adam was created by God and made in the likeness of God, but you notice that
there's a very different statement that is made with regard to Seth.
In verse number three, the Bible says, and Adam lived in 130 years and begat a son, what
does it say?
In his own likeness.
After his image, and called his name Seth.
Adam was made in the image of God, in the likeness of God, but there was something catastrophic
that happened between Adam being created and Seth being born.
What is it?
The fall.
Right?
The fall of man.
The consequences of the fall is death, separation from God.
We understand those things, we've studied it in the past, but it's important for us
to know that when Seth comes on the scene, when he's born, 130 years old was Adam when
Seth was born, and it tells us specifically that Adam begat a son in his own likeness,
and it says this, after his image, and he called his name Seth.
What does that reveal to us?
What's the sin nature?
The sin nature that would be passed on through Adam and through that line.
We understand, couple it with New Testament truth, Romans chapter number five, it tells
us in verse number 12, for as for one man, sin entered into the world.
Right?
Who's that?
That's Adam, and then it says, and death has passed upon all men, for that all have sinned.
And it is that nature.
And we understand the distinction that is made between.
Genesis 5.1 and Genesis 5.3 and it is imperative that at the very
understanding foundational truth that yes Adam was made in the likeness and
image of God but after the fall we find that Seth was born and he was in the
likeness of Adam. It's important for us to understand that it's so foundational.
We continue as we look at this important truth that is mentioned to us in the
text of Scripture. I didn't read much as we go forward but I want you to notice
in verse 3 it says and Adam lived notice that word lived in a hundred and
thirty years and begat a son in his own likeness after his image and called his
name Seth and the days of Adam after he'd begotten Seth were 800 years and
he begat sons and daughters and all the days that Adam lived were 930 years and
he died. Why am I emphasizing lived and died? What's interesting when you read
the genealogy the ungodly line of Cain there's no reference to them living or
dying yet they did. I would submit to you this evening that more than living they
existed. There's a difference. You know what Jesus said in John 10 in verse
number 10 I have come to give them life right he says that it would be more
abundant and you understand that truth in that concept remember that the
ungodly line of Cain the godly line of Seth and it says repeatedly through
Genesis chapter number five is you read all of these names and you read this
genealogy these ten generations you will find that it says
repeatedly they lived and they died. They lived and they died. Now living again I
mentioned John 10 in verse number 10 where Jesus said and it's in the same
context in which he speaks about being the good shepherd and what have you but
he says the thief cometh not but for to steal and to kill and to destroy I am
come that they might have life and that they might have it more abundantly and
here we find that these patriarchs that are mentioned in Genesis chapter number
five the Bible tells us they lived and then the Bible tells us they died. Now
again did the did the line of Cain did they die? Sure they did. It's just not it
doesn't tell us specifically that they died we know that they did but the
reality is that this was the consequence remember what did God say in Genesis
chapter number three in the day that you eat thereof really in Genesis chapter
number two in the day that you eat thereof ye shall surely die. What does
Satan say? Ye shall not surely die. Well it says they lived and they died but I
submit to you this evening that the Bible tells us in Psalm 116 in verse
number 15 that that the death of the Saints is is just it's a precious thing
in the sight of the Lord precious in the sight of the Lord is the death of his
Saints Psalm 116 in verse number 15 and so it's interesting that these words are
let listen every word of God is pure amen they're important it says over and
over that they live they live they live they died we understand that and I'm
just making a point this evening that as we look at this passage of Scripture
and we see the the godly line of Seth we see so many things different from what
we read in those verses at the end of chapter number four with regard to the
ungodly line of Cain. Lastly we notice and the important truth that is revealed
to us through the genealogy the longevity of the patriarchs as we've
read already the Bible tells us that Adam is that Seth was born when Adam was
130 years old it tells us that in verse 4 the days of Adam after he'd begotten
Seth were 800 years and he begat sons and daughters all the days that Adam
lived were 930 years and he died 930 years old that's pretty good amen you
guys feel young all of a sudden and 930 years old you notice the ages of the
patriarchs in fact as we look at these first 10 generations that are mentioned
in Genesis chapter number 5 you will find the ages of these patriarchs many
of them being 900 years or more of course Lamech was only at 777 only and
Enoch was only 365 years when he was translated 365 years old it's amazing
and you can look at some things I mentioned this at the beginning of our
study of the book of Genesis obviously not only the corruption of the the DNA
and what have you that you see after the fall of the genetic code that would
would go forward you also understand some of the environment in which God had
created with the ferment and so on and so forth that would help with that
longevity we also notice the impact of sin and the statement of God that man's
life shall be and he says that to Noah we find that later he says that to Moses
and it's recorded for us in Psalm 90 about the life of 3 score and 10 or if
by reason of strength 4 score and we see that in Psalm chapter number 90 it's
interesting though when you look at the longevity of the patriarchs here in the
book of Genesis and you see this lengthy period of time and there are some of
course there are scoffers that want to attack everything that you find in the
Word of God and they try to explain it some other way but it is kind of
interesting when you consider the fact that Isaiah prophesies that during the
time of the millennial that this idea of longevity is going to return in fact in
Isaiah 65 you could turn there I'll read it to you in Isaiah 65 in verse number
20 as Isaiah is prophesying dealing with the the period of the millennial excuse
me the Bible says this there shall be no more fence an infant of days nor an old
man that hath not filled his days for the child shall die in hundred years old
but the sinner being in hundred years old shall be accursed and so you see
again that reference to the longevity of life that will take place during the
millennial reign of Christ and we find here just some interesting truth that is
imparted to us even as we read through sometimes we read through genealogies
and it's like yeah let me just get through this and let me just get through
the genealogy well there's truth for us even within the genealogy that God wants
us to understand and he's communicating to us this evening let's just consider a
few of those that are mentioned in the passage of scripture I'm not even going
to take the time to read all of it if you want to pronounce all of those names
publicly in a fast fashion you feel free to do that I am not going to attempt it
this evening some of them are easy Jared he's in there and some of them are not
as easy and so I'm not going to read all of the passage this evening but let
me do this let me just highlight three of these that are mentioned in this
genealogy of the godly line of Seth and let's learn some lessons from them
number one is the son of Seth Enos it's mentioned to us in Genesis 4 verses 25
and 26 obviously verse 26 records the birth of Seth's son that he gave the
name Enos notice here that the the name Enos means man and really the root word
for this word man would be mortal man and so the idea of the name Enos really
is carrying with it the frailty of man the the mortality the mortal man now
think about that in comparison with what Lamech was just saying at the previous
scripture that we looked at he's really boasting about his power and his ability
and his pride but yet when Seth was to name his son Enos he names him a name
that would carry with it the idea of the frailty of man of mortal man in other
words recognizing a need for God that's exciting is it not and we find that here
that that during this particular time as God would tell us that it's Adam and
then it's Seth and then it's Enos that the Bible tells us something extremely
important happens at this time in history it's recorded for us at the end
of verse number 26 it says this then began men to call upon the name of the
Lord now as you would move forward through the the pages of Scripture as
you would read through the Old Testament you would understand that this
phraseology then began men to call upon the name of the Lord that this action
was often associated with altars and sacrifice and worship and we find here
that it's as you couple together the the name Enos the meaning of the name and
you see this statement that is made for us in Genesis 426 you would understand
here that this would reveal to us that these men their dependents they're
calling upon the name of the Lord I'm thankful for the many altars that you
read of throughout the book of Genesis and of course as you get into the law
and you'd find in all that Moses would communicate from God to the people
concerning the sacrifices and the offerings that were required and you
think about that process and in that worship and here we find that there's
something different than what's happening remember at the beginning of
Genesis 4 the Bible tells us that they brought an offering remember and we
mentioned as you were to look through in Genesis chapter 4 in the very
beginning of that passage of Scripture it records for us the offering of Cain
and the offering of Abel and how they brought that offering well now we find
at the end of Genesis chapter 4 by the time you get to the grandson of
Adam, Enos, you find that the Bible tells us,
then began men to call upon the name of the Lord. I'm mindful of what the New
Testament would tell us, and no doubt we can understand the truth of this verse
of scripture in Romans 10. In verse number 13, a verse of scripture that
many of us have had memorized, for whosoever shall call upon the name of
the Lord shall be saved. What a wonderful verse of scripture that is in Romans 10.
In verse number 13, and we find here that there's something that takes place that
is extremely important and is recorded for us in the pages of scripture with
regard to this historical event and what began to happen there with the grandson
of Adam. Notice, secondly, with me this evening, I want you to see in
Genesis 5 and verses 18 and through 24, notice the Bible character, the patriarch
Enoch. Enoch is the son of Jared. The Bible begins in verse number 18, and it
says, and Jared lived in 160 and two years, and he begat Enoch. Jared lived
after he begat Enoch 800 years and begat sons and daughters, and all the days of
Jared were 960 and two years, and he died. And Enoch lived 60 and five years and
begat Methuselah. Notice that the Bible says in verse 22, and Enoch walked with
God. It says after he begat Methuselah 300 years and begat sons and daughters.
It says all the days of Enoch were 360 and five years, and Enoch walked with God,
and he was not, for God took him. Isn't that amazing? Enoch has this testimony as we
look, really the the seventh generation, if you were to go through the genealogy
that is recorded for us in Genesis chapter number 5, and you would find it
in verse 22, and again in verse number 24, that the Bible tells us of this man
Enoch, that he walked with God. What a great testimony. He walked with God. And
we understand the point that we made a moment ago with the time of Enos and
that passage of Scripture, and now we see that Enoch is there, and he's walking
with God. The Bible tells us in Hebrews chapter 11 in verse number 5, not
only does it tell us that he walked with God, but the Bible adds this truth in
Hebrews 11 and verse number 5. What a great insight that is provided to us. It
says, by faith Enoch was translated that he should not see death. It says this, and
was not found because God had translated him, for before his translation he had
this testimony, that he pleased God. He walked with God, but he pleased God. I
preached a message several weeks ago in Ephesians 5 in verse number 10, where the
Bible says, proving what is acceptable unto the Lord. The word acceptable
literally means well-pleasing, and we talked about the truth that it is our
responsibility. We've been given the command, the instruction, the admonition
there in Ephesians 5 and verse number 10, that we are to prove what is
acceptable, what is pleasing to God. He gives us his word. It's interesting if
you were to look in Ephesians 5 in verse number 10, and you back up to the end of
chapter number 4, remember as Paul is providing the instruction to the
believers of Ephesus, he says, put off concerning the old man, the former man,
put off these things, but put on these things. And really, if you go through the
list, you'll find it's very practical. Now, does God like it when you lie? Does it
please God when you lie? No. Right? So he tells them, stop lying. Speak the truth.
Right? In Ephesians 4, go and look at it. That's what he tells them. Does it please
God when you steal? No. So stop stealing. Go to work. That's what he says in
Ephesians 4. By the way, it's all referenced back to Exodus chapter number
20, the Ten Commandments. Does it please God when we use our speech in an
appropriate way? That wicked communication, no, it doesn't please God.
We're to use our tongue for edification. Right? And you really, you go through that
passage in Ephesians 4, and you can answer some things as to what's
pleasing to God. See, sometimes we go through life and say, well, I don't know how to
please God. Well, we read the Bible, and the Bible tells us how to please God. I
mean, if Enoch was able to please God, and he didn't have anything that we have as
far as the Bible is concerned, then surely we can please God. And Enoch had
this testimony. Number one, he walked with God. Number two, he pleased God. It's
amazing. He walked with God, and he pleased God. It's amazing to understand
the timing. It tells us after the birth of Methuselah, because it tells us
in verse 22 of Genesis 5, and Enoch walked with God after he begat
Methuselah three hundred years, and begat sons and daughters. And then it tells us
this in verse number 24, and Enoch walked with God, and he was not, for God
took him. Now, I want you to just, I know you know about Enoch, you've read it, it's
mentioned in Hebrews, it's mentioned in Jude, but just consider with me, this guy
is 365 years old, but people are living to be 930 years old, okay? So he's a young
man, amen? And he's walking with God, he's pleasing God, and he walked with God, and
he was not, for God took him. Now, I want to know what Methuselah thought, what
other people thought, what did Jared think? He's looking for his son, Enoch, and
Enoch's nowhere to be found, they can't find him, why? Because God translated him.
He walked with God, he pleased God, and he was translated. God took him to heaven.
That's amazing to me. By the way, if you look at the passage of Scripture, and you
understand what's happening, and we referenced this last week in the book of
Matthew, if you recall with me, I asked you the question in the beginning of the
text of Scripture that we studied last week, why is it that this information is
being given to us in Genesis 4 and 5? It's leading up to the great, really the
the judgment of God upon the earth, the flood upon the people in Genesis chapter
number 6, and it was in Matthew chapter 24 that God taught us the Lord Jesus
Christ said, as it was in the days of Noah, so it will be in the days when, when
the Son of Man is going to return. And we notice here that Enoch, he walked with
God, he pleased God, and then he's translated to heaven, not seeing death.
Isn't that amazing? And we find this great testimony of this one Enoch. He's a
prophet, really, he names his son Methuselah, and we find that Methuselah,
he is the oldest man recorded in Scripture. He dies at 969 years old.
Oldest man in all of the Scriptures. Methuselah, 969 years old. Now, we find
that Methuselah, if you track and go through, he's the eighth from Adam, but we
notice our third Bible character that we'll notice this evening is Noah is
mentioned for us in verse number 28. Methuselah lived and he died. His son was
Lamech. It tells us in verse number 28, Lamech lived in 180 and two years and
begat a son. And he called his name Noah. Here's what he said, this same shall
comfort us concerning our work and toil of our hands because of the ground which
the Lord hath cursed. And Lamech lived after he begat Noah 590 and five years
and begat sons and daughters. And all the days of Lamech were 770 and seven years
and he died. And Noah was 500 years old and Noah begat Shem, Ham, and Japheth. If
you understand what is being said here as we look at the text of Scripture, you
find that in verse 29 when he names his son Noah, he mentions about the way in
which the ground had been cursed by the Lord. Remember Genesis chapter number 3?
Right? This is part of God's judgment that was being executed. We see that in
Genesis chapter number 3. And so there is a well, they are well aware of what
happened during the fall and the consequences thereof. And we find here
that Noah is mentioned and we come to the very beginning, the start of the sixth
chapter of the book of Genesis where God records for us the flood. And as we
think about the history of what's taking place here and we think about these
genealogies that are, or this genealogy that is provided to us, we would find
that it was Methuselah that I mentioned a moment ago that he died at 969 years
old. But when he died, he died in the very same year that the flood came. And we
find that he came the very same year that the flood came and it's recorded
for us in Genesis 6, the preparation, the course of the flood, so on and so forth.
And you begin to see how that God would shut forth them into the ark, Noah and
his wife and his three sons and their wives, eight people that were saved alive.
But I want you to notice that as we look at these three particular individuals
that we've taken this evening from this genealogy, you find Enos. The Bible tells
us that he is the son of Seth and it tells us his name, it means the
mortal man, the frailty of man, and it tells us that it was during that time
that men began to call upon the name of the Lord. We read of Enoch, a man that
walked with God, a man that pleased God, a man that was translated miraculously to
heaven.
that did not see death, and then we come to this final one
in Genesis chapter number five, the man that we know well
and we've been aware of many things from the life of Noah,
and this is the man that the Bible tells us
in Genesis six and verse number eight,
but Noah found grace in the eyes of the Lord.
Now, we look at these things this evening
and we see the genealogy that's provided to us,
the godly line of Seth, as opposed to the ungodly line
there of Cain, and when we looked at the ungodly line
of Cain, we saw some development, we saw some progress,
we saw some things that were taking place
from a developmental perspective, but nowhere did we read
of anyone calling upon the name of the Lord,
nowhere in the line of Cain did we read of somebody
that walked with God, nor did we read of anyone
that pleased God, nor was translated to heaven.
We did not read of anyone in that ungodly,
that wicked line of Cain that had the testimony
that they found grace in the eyes of the Lord,
yet you look at the godly line of Seth
and you find that God does not highlight
any kind of progress that they made
from a temporal perspective.
The Bible doesn't tell us of any cities that they built,
of any developments that they made,
of any inventions that they were responsible for,
the Bible records for us their walk with God.
Isn't that amazing?
And you see the difference between the ungodly line of Cain
and the godly line of Seth.
What the world values is not the same thing that God values.
Amen?
Far too often, we've been influenced by the value system
of the world, and we've been led to believe
that we have to make some kind of whatever you wanna call it
in order to be accepted.
But oh, what God values is a man that walks with him,
a man that lives his life pleasing,
a man that understands his frailty and his need for God,
that calls out to God, that worships God.
That's what God values.
That's what pleases God.
And we come to Noah, and the Bible says that he found grace
in the eyes of the Lord.
You know what's gonna happen in Genesis chapter number six?
The flood is gonna come.
The preparation, we see the announcement of it,
but God says in Genesis chapter number six
that he's seen the wickedness.
He's gonna destroy man that he created.
But Noah found grace in the eyes of the Lord.
This evening, there's advancements taking place.
There are accomplishments taking place.
And I'm not saying that we shouldn't accomplish anything,
but we need to use the value system that God uses
and not the value system of the world.
Because if we're not careful, we'll get too caught up
in the value system that's only focusing upon temporal things
and lose sight of the eternal things.
You know what Paul says?
Turn over there in 2 Corinthians chapter number four
in verse number 18, Paul shares with us a powerful truth
with regard to his life and his own testimony
and really the encouragement to these in Corinth.
And what a powerful truth for us to conclude with here
this evening, to understand the importance and the purpose
by which God has placed us here.
We find in 2 Corinthians four in verse number 17,
he says, for our light affliction,
which is but for a moment,
worketh for us a far more exceeding
and eternal weight of glory.
See, there's something for us after death.
Amen?
Death is simply a doorway to the presence of God
and being with Him for all of eternity.
And we find that, listen,
they sang the song this morning,
little is much when God is in it.
And in that song, it talks about
there's a crown that you can win.
The Bible records for us five crowns
that can be obtained by the people of God.
And you read Revelation four,
and you see how that they cast Him
at the feet of the Lord.
And what power, listen, the lost man,
he's just living for today.
He has nothing that he's looking forward to.
He has no hope of eternity.
We find here, Paul continues,
while we look not at the things which are seen,
but at the things which are not seen.
For the things which are seen are temporal.
The things which are not seen are eternal.
Oh, that God would help us to have an eternal perspective.
That we'd understand as we read Genesis four
and Genesis five,
such a contrast between these two genealogies,
the ungodly line of Cain,
the godly line of Seth.
And you notice what God chooses to record
about each of those lines of people
and their generations.
This evening, oh, that we'd be numbered
with those that would be called the godly.
That we would call upon the Lord,
trust Him, depend upon Him, worship Him.
That we'd walk with Him.
That we'd please Him.
That it could be said of us
that we found grace in the eyes of the Lord.
We're living in a time today,
we don't need to be tainted by the world
as I preached this morning.
What we need is to be able to stand
and to stand in the power of His might.
And to be able to stand against
the wickedness in high places.
Standing in His strength
and pleasing Him with our lives.
We see in Genesis four and five,
these two genealogies and what a contrast they are.
Let's pray together.