for God's word and a tremendous blessing
to be able to have a Bible.
This year on Wednesdays,
we've been really dealing with this thought
of having a desire to see God work,
to see God do what only God can do.
And we've understood as we've studied
various portions of scripture
on Wednesdays throughout 2026,
we've understood the fact that
we have a longing to see God work.
The Psalmist said, it is time Lord for thee to work,
for they have made void thy law.
And we've said that we desire to see God work,
to see God do again what only God can do.
We've acknowledged the fact that God is able to work.
And that's a blessing to know that
we are longing for God to work,
but he has the power, he has the ability.
The Psalmist tells us that he's a very present help
in the time of trouble.
And I think about having a desire for someone
or something to work and it doesn't work.
I use the illustration this morning
with the Wednesday morning crowd.
We have a snowblower and the desire when it snows
is that your snowblower works.
And that just makes sense, amen.
And sure enough, January, big snowstorm,
all that snow comes in and I'm sitting in Hawaii
with Holly visiting our daughter and grandkids
and got out of town before all the snow came
and Joseph said, this thing won't work
and couldn't get the snowblower to work.
And that was most disappointing.
And I told Joseph, one thing I was confident of
is that if he couldn't get it to work,
that there was no hope that if I were here
that I'd get it to work
because he's much more mechanical than I am.
And we just had nothing.
And so that thing didn't work.
We had a piece of machinery, but nothing going.
And you think about that, that happens sometimes in life
with things, even with people.
We want somebody to help with something,
they're not available, whatever it might be.
But I want you to acknowledge this evening
that God is always available and God has all power
and he is a very present help in the time of trouble
and he is able to work.
We've also understood and it's one of those things
that's important for us to look at.
That's a little bit maybe something
we don't wanna acknowledge or admit, but we must.
And that is this, our doubt or our unbelief
limits God from working.
The Bible says in Psalm 78
that they limited the Holy One of Israel.
The Bible tells us in Matthew 13,
as we've studied throughout this year,
that he did not many mighty works there, why?
Because of their unbelief.
And so this week, as we've looked at numbers 13 and 14,
last week we kind of started here.
And last week we talked about identifying doubt.
How does doubt come into your life and into my life
and how do we identify it?
And if we don't identify it, then we can't deal with it.
And we use the analogy and we'll continue
to use the analogy this evening.
The analogy last week was of a garden
and whether it's a vegetable garden, a flower garden,
you plant that which you want,
but you understand that weeds are probably going to pop up.
And we said that the flower, the plant is like faith,
but the weeds are like doubt.
And you need to be able to identify the doubt
so that you can get rid of it.
You need to be able to identify the weeds
so that you can move it, remove it from the garden.
And if we do not identify it, then we cannot deal with it.
But just because we identify it
doesn't mean we will deal with it, right?
And so this evening we're gonna talk
about the consequences of doubt.
What happens in your life and in my life
when doubt, unbelief is present?
Just like those weeds in the garden,
if we do not deal with them,
eventually what happens is the weeds take over.
And you've seen gardens, you've seen flower beds
where the weeds have just totally taken over
and they'll choke out the things that you've planted,
that you've desired to reap a harvest from.
And so when we looked at this portion of scripture
last week, we found at least three reasons
that the people of God began to doubt what God said.
They had unbelief and we were able to learn those things.
But now as we begin to consider the consequences of doubt,
I hope that it would help us to have
just a greater concern in our lives
to be able to identify and deal with that doubt.
Let me say this, last week I said that doubt,
unbelief is sin and it is, it's sin.
We don't believe God, we doubt what God says, it's sin.
And it's important that we acknowledge
that doubt is not benign, it is not harmless.
Doubt is not something that we just kind of think,
oh, it can exist and it's not gonna really do anything bad.
Doubt and unbelief needs to be rooted out
of the life of a believer.
We find that the Bible says that without faith,
it is impossible to please him.
For he that cometh to God must believe that he is
and that he's a rewarder of them that diligently seek him.
In Hebrews 11 and verse number six,
throughout the scriptures, Old and New Testament,
we read this truth that the just shall live by faith.
And faith is believing God, taking God at his word.
And so this evening as we consider some of the consequences
of doubt, I hope that it would help us to have
a greater desire to rid and root out doubt from our lives.
Number one, I have five thoughts,
they're not gonna be lengthy, but number one this evening,
I want you to recognize that your doubt
and my doubt will impact others.
It will impact others.
Let's look at the passage of scripture.
In Numbers chapter 13, beginning in verse number one,
the Bible says, and the Lord spake unto Moses saying,
and here's the instructions that God gives to Moses,
send thou men that they may search the land of Canaan,
which I give unto the children of Israel.
Notice of every tribe of their father,
shall you send a man, everyone a ruler among them.
It says in verse number four, and these were their names
from verse four down through verse number 15,
you read the names of those that are assigned the task.
It says in verse 16, these are the names of the men
which Moses sent to spy out the land.
And so we find that verse number two says,
of every tribe of their fathers, shall you send a man.
That means there's 12 spies, all right?
Now we sing the song with the kids,
12 men went to spy on Canaan, 10 were bad and two were good.
And so we think about that and we understand this evening
that there's 12 spies.
Now we know that Joshua and Caleb are the two good spies
and so that leaves us with 10 men that are these evil spies
that bring back this evil report.
The Bible tells us in verse number 27, and they told him,
that's the spies as they return, they tell Moses,
they're bringing back the report.
And remember in verse 27, we looked at it last week,
they begin to tell about the land and what they saw,
but they say this in verse 28, nevertheless,
and it changes direction.
They get their eyes off of what they're supposed
to be looking at and considering,
and they begin to look at the circumstances.
They begin to get their eyes on the obstacles
that they would face and they begin to talk about the fact
that the cities are walled and very great,
that the sons of Anak, the giants are there
and they're overwhelmed with the obstacles
and they conclude, according to verse number 31,
we be not able to go up against the people
for they are stronger than we.
So Joshua and Caleb, Caleb here in chapter number 13
in verse 30, he tries to steal the people.
Joshua and Caleb are two good spies out of the 12,
but I want you to consider with me this evening
that your doubt and my doubt will impact others
because as we notice this, as we look at these verses,
there's 10 men, 10.
That's not a big number.
It's a small number, but begin reading in chapter 14
in verse number one, the Bible says this,
and all the congregation lifted up their voice
and cried and the people wept that night.
Notice again in verse two, and all the children of Israel
murmured against Moses and against Aaron
and the whole congregation said unto them,
would God that we had died in the land of Egypt
or would God we had died in this wilderness
and wherefore hath the Lord brought us unto this land
to fall by the sword that our wives and our children
should be a prey were it not better for us
to return into Egypt.
Notice in verse number 10, it says,
but all the congregation bade stone them with stones
and the glory of the Lord appeared in the tabernacle
of the congregation before all the children of Israel.
So we notice that there's 10 men in chapter number 13,
but when we come to chapter number 14,
it says in all the congregation,
it says that the whole congregation,
all the children of Israel, it says all the congregation
bade stone them with stones.
We don't know, you can look in the beginning
of Numbers chapter one, you can begin to see the numbers
that are provided with regard to the various tribes.
There's probably a couple million people
that are influenced by 10, by 10.
Your doubt and my doubt.
influences and impacts others.
You think about a generation that's following us.
If parents don't have faith,
if they don't believe that God is able,
if church leaders don't have faith
and believe that God is able,
what's gonna happen to the others?
What's gonna happen to the next generation?
Our doubt, our unbelief, our lack of faith
will impact others and we see it here
in Numbers 13 and 14, very, very obvious to us.
In Galatians 5 and verse number nine,
the Bible says a little leaven leaveneth the whole lump.
Just a little impacts the whole.
And so we understand this evening
the consequences of doubt.
Sometimes we're led to think or we like to believe
that we operate and function in some type of a bubble
and all that we do and all that we are only affects us,
but that's just not true.
And our doubt will impact others
and I'd rather that my faith impacts others, amen?
That people see the faith of somebody
that just believes God, that just trusts God
and that will have an influence and an impact.
But these 10 men, they influenced an entire congregation.
Let me say this, number two,
not only will our doubt and our unbelief impact others,
but it leads to a failure to move forward.
The Bible says in verse number four of Numbers 14,
notice what it says, this congregation is speaking
against the leadership and it says in verse number four,
and they said one to another,
let us make a captain and let us return into Egypt.
And so what are they doing?
Well, they're failing to move forward.
Someone said this, we can't stay here and we can't go back
so we must go forward.
And the Christian life is a life that's based upon
and really the impact or the opportunity to go forward,
to press on, to claim what God has given us
as the promises of his word and having faith
and living by faith.
We sing the wonderful hymn, onward, forward.
We think about the truth of the Apostle Paul
during the missionary journeys
as we read of them in the book of Acts
and man, they just were going forward with the gospel.
Was it because everyone welcomed them
and they rolled out the red carpet
and said, we're so glad that you've come to our city?
No, it's because they had faith.
They were just believing God.
God said in Acts chapter 13, separate unto me,
Paul and Saul and Barnabas for the work
whereunto I have called them.
And we find that they were just operating
based upon what God had revealed to them,
living by faith and they were moving forward.
And by the way, I'm thankful that they obeyed the Lord
and they lived by faith.
Why?
Because the gospel went throughout the known world,
eventually got to Europe, eventually got to America.
If you kind of, I know that's a big couple of jumps,
but historically, that's how it happened.
Because some people that had some faith,
they just believed God.
They just said, I'm not concerned about all the obstacles.
We know they're there, but we're gonna go forward.
The children of Israel say, let us make a captain
and let us return into Egypt.
You know, oftentimes when we have doubt
and unbelief in our lives,
it causes us to lack real reason and logic.
How are they gonna go back?
You know, there was something really monumental
that had to happen for them to get where they were,
and it was the crossing of the Red Sea.
And they didn't do that on their own, by the way.
In fact, when they were up against the Red Sea
and the Egyptians were behind them,
they were convinced they were gonna die there as well.
Let's go back to Egypt.
How are you getting back?
Right, I mean, you don't even think about that.
Well, because why?
Because you've got this doubt and this unbelief
and it's controlling your life
and you're not reasoning and logic,
having proper logic through the processes
in which you're facing, why?
Because you're not believing God.
God's plan was not for them to go back to Egypt.
By the way, when they were in Egypt,
how much did they like being in Egypt, right?
I mean, you read the beginning chapters
of the book of Exodus, they're crying for deliverance.
The Bible tells us that God's heard their cry.
That's why God raised up Moses, correct?
Because he's gonna deliver his people.
Let us go back to Egypt.
Listen, doubt and unbelief will keep us from moving forward.
And sometimes we use that terminology in our society,
you've used it, I've used it, about a comfort zone, right?
We just wanna stay in our comfort zone
and somebody says, get out of your comfort zone, right?
And we understand what that means,
we can relate to that terminology.
But the reality is that we need to, by faith, move forward.
What is God able to do?
God's able to do all things.
I shared a part of a book that I was reading,
I think today is Wednesday, so I think it was Monday night.
I was reading a book and the author said something
that just made me laugh, it said,
God is omni-everything and you are omni-nothing.
Praise the Lord, amen?
And our God is able and without him, we can do nothing.
Now, I'm thankful that he works in us and through us
and he enables us, he equips us,
he's given us spiritual gifts and we thank God for that.
But our God is the omnipotent, omniscient God
who is able to do all things.
There is nothing too hard for him,
but yet doubt creeps into your life and my life
and instead of going forward, we go backwards.
And so it keeps us, it results in a failure to move forward.
Let me say this, it's a number three,
it's a results in a failure for us to see what God can do.
To see what God can do.
I want you to hold your place here in numbers
and I want you to turn to the book of Psalms, Psalm 81.
And I want you to look here at a few verses of scripture
and just a few months ago on Wednesday evenings,
I preached through, actually it was the end of last year,
through Psalm 81.
And I want to revisit just a few verses here
because I think it's important for us to recognize
that doubt and unbelief results in not being able to see
what God is able to do.
I want to see God work,
I want to see God do what God is able to do.
It says here in Psalm 81 in verse number 10,
I am the Lord thy God,
which brought thee up out of the land of Egypt,
open thy mouth wide and I will fill it.
Verse 11, but my people would not hearken to my voice
and Israel would none of me.
Now I want you to keep in mind what I've just read there
in verse number 11 and I want to read to you
what the Bible says there in numbers 14.
You don't need to turn back there,
but in numbers 14 in verse number 22,
it says this at the end of the verse
and have tempted me now these 10 times
and have not hearkened to my voice.
So God says, but my people would not hearken to my voice
and Israel would none of me.
Why would they not hearken to the voice of God?
Because they didn't believe God.
It was because of their unbelief.
So they didn't believe God,
so therefore they didn't hearken unto God
and we find that God says this,
so, verse number 12,
I gave them up unto their own heart's lust
and they walked in their own counsels.
Oh, that my people had hearkened unto me
and Israel had walked in my ways
and I want you to focus specifically on verse 14
and here's what God says,
I should soon have subdued their enemies
and turned my hand against their adversaries.
That's what God was gonna do
and they miss seeing what God could do
because of their doubt, because of their unbelief.
See, I don't wanna miss out on seeing what God can do.
I wanna see what God is able to do
and the reality is that as we look at this portion
of scripture in Psalm 81,
when God says in this historical psalm
that here's what I would have done had they hearkened to me,
that you can mark it down as truth certainty
that that's exactly what would have happened.
That's not men speaking to each other about,
hey, I would have paid for your dinner tonight if I,
no, no, no, that's not somebody just making a nice gesture.
That's God saying, here's what I would have done
if you would have obeyed
and obeying is based upon our belief.
Do we believe it?
Do we believe God?
God says, here's what I'm commanding you to do.
Here's my instruction for you.
Here's my word to you.
If we believe it by faith, then we do it
or preaching on Sunday mornings, doers of the word.
I said last, what, two, three weeks ago,
at the end in James there,
when the Bible talks about the course of sin
and I made this statement, I'm just thinking,
I just believe that some people
just simply don't believe the Bible.
They think that the truth that God has revealed
with regard to the course of sin,
that, well, that's not gonna happen to me.
I'm gonna be the exemption.
It's just not gonna happen.
No, no, no, there's no being exempt from it
or the exception to the rule.
No, God's word is true and we cannot think
that we're going to be able to get away with
or the long suffering of God is never the approval of God.
It's just a matter of believing God's word
and they did not hearken because they did not believe
and they missed out on seeing what God could do.
Let me say this, number four, God is not pleased.
Our doubt and our unbelief, it's sin
and it does not please God.
It just doesn't please God.
God. I asked this question last week, how many of you like it when people believe you?
Right? I mean, if I tell somebody something, I like it when they believe me. Now, in our
relationships as human beings, there are times in which we fail one another, and if someone
fails you enough, then you have a lower level of confidence in their word. You don't trust
them, right? Does that make sense? We've experienced that in life. Somebody tells me they're going
to do something, but I have a backup plan because they've told me before they're going
to do it, and they don't show up. You know what I mean? But it's one of those situations
where we desire that people would trust what we say. There used to be a day in our society,
even as a nation and through interactions and business interactions, that there was
what they would call a gentleman's handshake. You just make contractual agreements based
on handshakes. Now, the contractual agreement contains 150 pages of legalese that no one
can understand, and you are just as guilty as I am of saying, I have read and agreed
to, and you didn't read and agree to anything. You just clicked the box so that you could
continue. Amen? When you get an update on your phone, and it's like, I am not reading
all of this stuff. How far do I have to go to hit, bam, I accept and continue? Right?
Yeah. And here's the deal. God has never failed you. God has never failed me. God had never
failed me. God had never failed these people, and they didn't believe Him. How sad. How
sad. It says in verse number 11, the Lord said unto Moses, how long will this people
provoke me? And how long will it be ere they believe me? For all the signs which I have
showed among them. God wants His people to believe Him, and He's trustworthy. He's trustworthy.
It isn't amazing how we can believe Him for eternity, but we struggle to believe Him for
today. Have you ever experienced that? You're trusting Him for eternity. You're trusting
Him. Right? You're believing that when the Bible said, to be absent from the body is
to be present with the Lord. You're believing that He said, in my Father's house are many
mansions. If it were not so, I would have told you. I go to prepare a place for you,
and if I go and prepare a place for you, I will come again and receive you unto Myself,
that where I am, there you may be also. You believe it. And you should. And you should
believe it. But when He says that He's going to be with you today, that He will provide
for your needs, that He will bless as you honor Him with your tithe and your first fruit,
that He will, all of a sudden, we start doubting. We start having that unbelief. We can trust
Him for eternity, but we have a hard time trusting Him for today. Listen, I'm thankful
that my God knows everything about me and everything about you. He knows exactly what
I need. He knows exactly what you need. And just, listen, if He is able, and He is, since
He is able for eternity, He's able for today. Amen. I believe that. He knows. Listen, the
Bible teaches us that He knows what we need before we ask. Right? He says, why, don't
take no thought for tomorrow. He tells us, when we think about this thing about, seek
ye first the kingdom of God and His righteousness and all these things shall be added unto you
in Matthew chapter number 6. What's He talking about? He's talking about the things that
we worry about. Right? The things, but here's what God says. I already know that you need
those things. He's the one that created us. He knows our frame. He knows that we're but
dust. He knows that we need food, and He knows that we need drink, and He knows that
we need raiment, and He knows that we need shelter. He knows those things, and He provides
those things. And we find this evening that God says, how long will it be, e'er my people
believe me? It is impossible. Now think about that word just for a moment. That is a word
that, that we must wrap our minds around when we read it, when it says that with God
all things are possible, we rejoice. But when the Bible says it is impossible to please
Him without what? Without faith. Without faith, it is impossible to please Him. So you live
with doubt. You live with unbelief. You're not trusting God and His word. It's impossible
to please Him. I mean, that's just Bible. And so we've got to deal, listen, again, as
I said by way of introduction, doubt and unbelief is not benign. It's not harmless. It's very
harmful actually. There's many consequences of allowing doubt and unbelief to root in
your life and in my life and in our lives, corporately and collectively as a church.
So, we want to deal with it. These are not in any actual order of relevance, if you will,
these five points this evening. But if I were to think about the one that should be most
impactful, it's this one that God's not pleased. Because I want God to be pleased with me.
I think about the Apostle Paul. He had this goal that he would please the Lord. He shares
with Timothy about being a good soldier of Jesus Christ. Why? So he could please Him.
That called him to be a soldier. I want to please the Lord. When I preached through 2
Timothy a couple of years ago, through 1 and 2 Timothy, I said this, you're a soldier.
If you're saved, you're a soldier. The question is if we're a good soldier. We're soldiers.
But are we a good soldier? There's a difference between being a soldier and being a good soldier.
When we want to be a good soldier and we want to please our Lord, let me say this,
number five, there's missed blessings. You say, well, that's pretty similar to the fact
that we miss out on seeing what God can do. I agree with you, but I want to focus on a
few things here with regard to the missed blessings. Look at verse 23, back in Numbers
chapter 14. I'm going to read down through verse number 31, and the Bible says this in
verse 23. Surely they shall not see the land which I swear unto their fathers, neither
shall any of them that provoked me see it. Isn't that a sad verse? They're not going
to see it. They're going to miss out on the blessings. Verse 24, but my servant Caleb,
because he had another spirit with him, and it followed me fully, him will I bring into
the land whereunto he went, and his seed shall possess it. Did it happen? Yeah, it did. In
fact, Joshua 14, give me this mountain, right? We preach about it. God saw fit that Caleb
was able to go into the land. Now, verse 25, the Amalekites and the Canaanites dwelt in
the valley. Tomorrow turn you and get you into the wilderness by the way of the Red
Sea. And the Lord spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying, How long shall I bear with
this evil congregation which murmur against me? I have heard the murmurings of the children
of Israel, which they murmured against me, saying to them, As truly as I live, saith
the Lord, as ye have spoken in mine ears, so will I do to you. Your carcasses shall
fall in the wilderness, and all that were numbered of you, according to your whole number,
from twenty years old and upward, which have murmured against me. Doubtless ye shall not
come into the land concerning which I swear to make you dwell therein, save Caleb the
son of Jephunneh, and Joshua the son of Nun. Isn't that sad? Did it happen? Yeah, they
died in the wilderness. They died in the wilderness. And it says this in verse 31,
but your little ones, which ye said should be a prey. When did they say that? Well, remember
back in verse number 3, when they're complaining and murmuring, it says in verse number 3,
And wherefore hath the Lord brought us unto this land to fall by the sword, that our wives
and our children should be a prey? Were it not better for us to return unto Egypt? And
so God says, But your little ones, in verse 31, which ye said should be a prey, them will
I bring in, and they shall know the land which ye have despised. Can I tell you? It happened
exactly like God says. We're on this side of it. We have the record of it. We believe
in the inspiration of Scripture. We also believe in the preservation of Scripture. And God
has providentially preserved his word for us. And we have the Bible this evening and
we can read the book of Joshua and we can read all that took place with the children
of Israel entering into and conquering and then inhabiting the land. And it happened
exactly as God said. So these individuals that we're speaking of, this whole congregation
that was influenced by ten people. Ten people. Think about that.
It's not a big crowd, 10, influenced the whole congregation, the whole nation.
This is congregation, I'm not talking about a congregation of a church, I'm talking about
the nation, all the children of Israel, influenced.
And that generation died in the wilderness.
By the way, it was never God's plan.
God's plan was to bring them out of Egypt and to bring them into the land.
It was never for 40 years of wilderness wanderings, that was not God's plan.
It was because of their doubt and unbelief that they wandered in the wilderness and that
generation died in the wilderness.
Let me just remind you, now we won't turn there and go through it, but let me just remind
you that Joshua chapter number three records for us the crossing of the Jordan River.
What a miraculous crossing it was.
Very different than the crossing of the Red Sea, but very miraculous.
It was flood stage and the Bible tells us that as they were going to cross over that
Jordan River that was at its flood stage, that they were to go and as they stepped their
foot in, God parted that thing, isn't that awesome?
I mean, seeing God work, you say, I'd like to cross the Red Sea, that's a miracle too.
That God told Moses to raise up that rod and God parted the Red Sea, but God parted the
Jordan River and guess what, they went over on dry ground.
Then they got some stones and they put a memorial right there in the midst of the river where
they crossed over.
Then they got some more stones and they made a memorial over at Gilgal, amen?
Why?
Because they're seeing what God has done.
But this generation of people that we're reading of in Numbers 13 and 14, they missed it.
They didn't get to experience it.
They missed out on the blessings.
Joshua chapter number six records for us the victory at Jericho.
It's the first victory, the first battle that they have at Jericho.
And by the way, what's so interesting about Jericho is the fact that when we talk about
the battle at Jericho, we talk about the victory at Jericho, what's the one thing that stands
out in all of our minds when we think about Jericho?
Help me out, what is it?
The walled cities, right?
And I mean, they're fortified.
What was it that these ten spies said?
Oh, the cities are walled, right?
That was what led to their doubt and their unbelief.
And guess what?
God brought those walls down flat, right?
The people didn't do anything.
They just walked around, just having faith in what God said.
Isn't it amazing?
They just obeyed.
They just believed.
And God did the work.
Joshua chapter number eight records for us the victory at Ai.
Yes, chapter number seven records the defeat at Ai.
But that was another issue where there was sin in the camp, number one.
And number two, I think there also was some doubt and unbelief.
Because they said, it's not that big of a city, let us just take two or three thousand
and we can take care of it.
And so they really kind of thinking about what they could do and what their abilities
were.
And they suffered defeat primarily because of the sin in the camp, the sin of Achan,
of course.
But we find in chapter number eight, the victory at Ai.
We find in Joshua nine and chapter number 10, those two chapters record for us the conquering
of southern Canaan.
We find that chapter number 11 of the book of Joshua, the conquering of northern Canaan.
And by the way, when you read about the conquering and all the battles that took place, you see
God working.
You see God giving the victory.
You see the sun standing still because Joshua prayed.
Whoever thought to pray a prayer like that?
Somebody that believes the God that can do anything.
Amen?
And God did.
There were more that died from the hailstones than from the swords.
And you just begin to think about what God did and the opportunity for that generation
that we're speaking of in the book of Joshua to see all of this.
But the generation that we're speaking of in numbers 13 and 14, the generation that
was marked by doubt and unbelief, they missed the blessings.
They missed it.
They didn't see God work.
They didn't experience it.
Chapter 12 summarizes all of the conquering.
The names of all the kings are listed that were conquered.
Then you turn to Joshua 13 through Joshua chapter number 21 and you read in all of those
chapters about the division of the land and the inhabiting of the land.
You get to the end of the book and you read the addresses from Joshua to the people, to
the leaders, to the two and a half tribes, and you read those particular messages that
Joshua delivers to them.
But in chapters 13 through 21, it's the division and the inhabiting of the land and how God
gave the tribes the land and the cities of refuge and the cities of the Levites.
And you begin to see all of that.
What am I saying?
When we have unbelief and doubt, we miss the blessings.
All that that we read of in the book of Joshua, this generation right here was supposed to
experience that, right?
They were supposed to experience that, but doubt and unbelief.
We be not able.
I said this last week and it's important for us to acknowledge as we conclude this evening.
In Joshua 13 and verse 31, they say at the end of the verse, we be not able to go up
against the people for they are stronger than we.
I had forgotten what God said because in verse number two of chapter 13, God said,
send down men that they may search the land of Canaan, which I give unto the children
of Israel.
It was never about them.
It was always about God.
And it's the same thing today.
It's never about us.
It's always about God.
And He uses us to God be the glory that He would use us.
But I think about what John said, John the Baptist, he must increase, I must decrease.
It's always about God getting the glory.
And God said, I'm going to give you this land.
But somewhere along the line, they got things crossed up.
They got their eyes on the obstacles instead of on the Lord.
And they say, we be not able.
Listen, doubt is a serious issue.
It's sin.
And I fear this evening that we're living in a time when lots of God's people have a
lot of doubt and unbelief.
And it's impacting so many others.
And maybe we could, not that we'd like to blame it on someone, but when we think about
our own doubt and unbelief and we look at this passage this evening and understand how
it impacts others.
Listen, no doubt we've been impacted.
I preached a message last Thursday at Chapel, at Vision Baptist College.
I preached a message about believing God to do the impossible.
And I tried to encourage those young people that are studying for the ministry that God
is able.
God is able.
And then Thursday night, Brother Charlie Clark at their church service, they have church
on Thursday night, he preached a message about God being able.
In revival praying and praying, he preached through 2 Chronicles chapter number 7, 6 and
7.
And man, it was amazing how God took those two messages and just kind of dovetailed them
together.
Brother Tim told me, Tim Trejo from our church here studying up there on Friday, we had lunch
and he said this, he said, man, your message, Brother Charlie's message had such an impact
on the folks in the dorm, the men.
We had prayer meeting last night.
We just want to see God do something.
Hallelujah.
But can I tell you on Friday, there was a preacher that stood in the pulpit and preached
at the chapel on Friday, and I'm not trying to take beef with the guy, but he got up in
the pulpit and he said, you guys think you're going to go pastor church, you're going to
get 200 people, it's not going to happen?
Come on.
I understand where he's coming from, his experience, he's been a pastor for 50 years, whatever,
but my God is able.
He is able to save to the uttermost, Hebrews 7 and verse number 25.
He's not willing that any should perish, but that all should come to repentance.
And we don't change our position to try to grow a church, but we seek to obey the Lord
and follow the Lord, and listen, I still believe that the Bible says that the gospel is the
power of God unto salvation.
The gospel still works.
Listen, if God wasn't working, if God didn't have a plan, we'd just go ahead and close
up and just go do something else, honestly.
But if we truly believe that God is still on his throne, and he is, and he still wants
to do something in 2026, you say, pastor, have you watched the news?
I don't watch the news a lot.
You know why?
It's kind of discouraging.
Just honestly.
I told you during COVID, if you're going to watch the news for an hour, you better read
the Bible for four hours.
And I just on the fly made up a one to four ratio.
Somebody came to me and said, how'd you figure that out?
It just came out.
I don't know.
But you know, sometimes we spend so much time on the news and on those things that are negative.
Listen, our God still reigns.
He still has all power, as much as he's ever had.
Amen?
And he wants to use us.
We got to deal with that.
We identify it.
Last week's message.
But when we acknowledge the consequences, it's not benign.
It's harmful.
It's dangerous.
It chokes out.
We got to deal with it.
And just like the disciples in Mark 9, thank God they came to Jesus and said,
why could not we cast him out? And Jesus said, because of your unbelief.
And they came to Jesus and they had that private moment and Jesus gave them the truth.
We don't know what the God of the universe, our Savior, and say,
God, where's the doubt and unbelief in my life? Help me to deal with it.
Help me to get rid of it. Help me. Lord, as the disciples prayed in Luke 17,
Lord, increase our faith. The church in Thessalonica, their faith groweth exceedingly.
So then faith cometh by hearing and hearing by the word of God.
We need to deal with doubt because doubt has some serious consequences.
Let's pray. Father, we do love you. We thank you so much for loving us.
We thank you for your word, the truth contained therein.
We thank you for the privilege of being able to study it.
Lord, I pray that you'd help me and help us to not only identify doubt,
but Lord, help us to acknowledge the serious consequences of doubt
so that we will root it out of our lives with your help, by your grace.
Lord, I pray that you'd help us to get alone with you and search our hearts.
And Lord, that you would search our hearts and show us if there's some area of doubt.
Think of that man that said, Lord, I believe. Help thou mine unbelief.
Lord, help us to be honest and transparent with you.
And God, I pray that you would increase our faith.
Thank you for the privilege of prayer.
We have our prayer meeting and we think about the blessing of corporate intercessory prayer.
And I pray that you'd bless, you'd be honored and glorified.
For it's in Christ's name we pray. Amen.
And does anyone need a prayer bulletin this evening?