with regard to a theme.
It's always amazing to me
how God will use the truth in my own life,
and then also in the lives of our church family.
And I'm thankful for this year's theme,
to be reminded regularly that God's grace is sufficient.
And what a blessing that is.
If you have your Bible with you this evening, Psalm 23,
and a couple of weeks ago, we started looking
at Jehovah Ra, the Lord, my shepherd.
And so we'll be continuing, I mentioned to you
when we arrived to the name Jehovah Ra,
that we would spend several weeks
looking at this particular name of God,
because there is so much that is communicated to us
with regard to the subject matter, the name Jehovah Ra.
And so last, not last week,
because we had Brother Baloo with us,
but two weeks ago, we considered the provision of my shepherd.
We looked at Jehovah Ra previously, Jehovah Jireh,
my God will provide, and we looked at that, another name
for God, but Jehovah Ra, or another name of God,
Jehovah Ra, the Lord, my shepherd.
But as we understand what is communicated to us
through these names of God, this teaching
and this truth with regard to the Lord, my shepherd,
that my shepherd not only provides for me,
but tonight as we look at verse four in Psalm 23,
we're reminded of the provision of my shepherd.
And what a blessing to be reminded of this truth.
Notice with me, we'll begin reading in verse one,
we're familiar with it, but Psalm 23, in verse number one,
the Bible says, the Lord is my shepherd, I shall not want.
He maketh me to lie down in green pastures,
he leadeth me beside the still waters, he restoreth my soul,
he leadeth me in the paths of righteousness
for his namesake.
And so last week, we looked at those first three verses
and we dealt with the provision of the shepherd,
of my shepherd, and we dealt with the nourishment,
the restoration, refreshment, the direction
that he provides.
And now as we look at verse number four,
really we're reminded of what we'll look at tonight
and then also next week, it kind of segues into it.
But we see in verse number four, the Bible says,
yea, though I walk through the valley
of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil,
for thou art with me, thy rod and thy staff,
they comfort me.
Begin to look at verse number four
and we find not only the protection,
but also the presence of our shepherd
and we'll deal with the protection this week
and next week, we'll look at the presence of our shepherd
and what a blessing it is to know
that he'll never leave us nor forsake us.
But tonight as we focus on the protection of my shepherd,
I'm reminded that David as a shepherd himself,
remember, we dealt with several weeks ago,
the instrument, the human instrument that God used
to reveal to us this name, Jehovah-Raw,
was David who himself was a shepherd.
And so therefore, immediately David would be able
to relate with various aspects of what's being communicated
through this name Jehovah-Raw, the Lord my shepherd.
And so as we look at verse number four
and begin to think about the protection of our shepherd,
we're reminded that David understood
that he was responsible for protecting the flock.
David understood that he had been entrusted
with the responsibility of that flock
and the sheep that his family had.
And as he was in that position,
he understood that there were several things
that he was required to do or responsible for doing,
those duties that he would fulfill.
And one of them was in providing protection.
In fact, we know that when David is having a conversation
with King Saul, he mentions to King Saul
about an occasion that he had
in which he had to protect the sheep.
And we look at that text of scripture,
we'll look there quickly, 1 Samuel 17,
but as we look at that text of scripture,
I doubt that it was the only time
that David had a situation in which he had to step in
and provide some level of protection for the sheep.
Why? Because sheep need protection.
There's many dangers, there's many dangers that they face.
And so we find that here, David,
as he's speaking with King Saul,
he says to him in verse 34, 1 Samuel 17,
and David said unto Saul,
thy servant kept his father's sheep.
And there came a lion and a bear
and took a lamb out of the flock.
And I went out after him and smote him
and delivered it out of his mouth.
And when he arose against me,
I caught him by his beard and smote him and slew him.
He acknowledges later in the passage of scripture
that it was God who gave him the victory.
He also acknowledges that the same God
that was enabling him to kill the bear and the lion,
that that same God would give him victory over Goliath.
And we understand the greater context there,
but this evening, as we're considering
the protection of my shepherd, Jehovah-Rah,
the Lord, my shepherd, and how he protects us,
we're reminded that sheep need protection.
There are many dangers.
And so David would understand that.
David knew personally what it was
to provide a safety, a measure of safety for the sheep.
And just as sheep face danger,
it's important that we understand this evening
that we face great danger as well.
We have an enemy.
We find this evening that as we begin to understand
the truth that the Lord is my shepherd,
Jehovah-Rah, and he protects me,
I'm reminded Psalm 121, turn there if you will.
In Psalm 121, we begin to look at this familiar Psalm
and we find that there's a reference
and we actually made up a song
from verses one and two several years ago.
I think it was in 2020, actually,
when we dealt with this particular thought
of looking unto Jesus.
And the Psalm begins in verse number one,
I will lift up mine eyes unto the hills
from whence cometh my help.
My help cometh from the Lord, which made heaven and earth.
And we rejoice in the promises and the principles
here in verses one and two.
But then as we continue through the chapter,
notice in verse number three, the Bible says he,
who's he?
Well, that's the Lord, that's my helper.
It says he, the one who created heaven and earth,
he will not suffer thy foot to be moved.
Notice this phrase, he that keepeth thee
will not slumber.
You see that?
He that keepeth thee will not slumber.
You know, there's never a time
when our shepherd isn't aware.
He's awake, he's aware, he's able, amen?
We see in verse number four,
behold, he that keepeth Israel
shall neither slumber nor sleep.
Praise the Lord, praise God.
We find here this great principle,
he that keepeth thee.
Our God is providing protection for us.
When are we most vulnerable?
Well, when we're asleep at night, are we not vulnerable?
You think about some of those dangers
as you could consider that aspect.
And we find that he is not he that keepeth us,
he will not slumber.
It mentions in verse four
that he's neither gonna slumber nor sleep.
I begin to think about our lives
and the many dangers in which we face in life.
There are times in which we go in to situations
and we think we can handle it.
We have these dangers, we have an enemy.
The Bible tells us that our enemy is like a lion.
What did David say?
There was a lion and a bear.
The Bible tells us that our enemy is like a lion
and he walketh about seeking whom he may trip up,
whom he may devour, whom he may devour.
And we find this evening that as we begin to understand
and consider the truth that is before us
that God provides to me protection
because he is my shepherd,
I begin to think about a couple of verses
and we're just gonna use a few of them
that David uses throughout the Psalms.
And as he uses these verses of scripture,
I believe that it reveals to us
the understanding that David had
that God is my protector,
that God my shepherd, that he protects me.
And we find that he says this.
Look at Psalm 28.
You're there in the book of Psalms.
Notice what God says or what David says here
about the Lord.
In Psalm 28,
in verse six, it says,
blessed be the Lord,
because he has heard the voice of my supplications.
Aren't you thankful that God hears you when you pray?
What a joy to know the truth of that.
It says in verse number seven, notice this.
The Lord is my strength and my shield.
What does a shield do?
A shield protects.
Now, I understand today
that when we were to go into battle today
that we may not use the same type of weaponry
that they use during the time of the writing
of the book of Psalms.
And you can look through the centuries of humanity
and you can see wars and conflicts
and you can see various aspects of weaponry
and what they would use,
but they would understand right here
in the context of what we're dealing with
in the time period,
they would understand the importance of a shield.
Amen?
And we find that as we look at the truth
of the armor of God in Ephesians chapter number six,
we're told to take the shield of faith
and we're told that it will quench
all the fiery darts of the enemy.
And we're reminded of that.
But here, David says,
the Lord is my strength and my shield.
Notice my heart trusted in him and I am helped.
Therefore, my heart.
greatly rejoiceth, and with my song will I praise him."
David said, God is my shield.
See, no soldier would enter into battle
in this era of human history without having their shield.
It was absolutely essential.
We find that David says, understanding the truth,
Jehovah-Rah, the Lord is my shepherd.
My shepherd protects me.
He says, he's my shield.
He's my shield.
We find that in Psalm 31, maybe on the same page for you,
but beginning in verse number one,
the Bible says, in thee, O Lord, do I put my trust.
Let me never be ashamed.
Deliver me in thy righteousness.
Bow down thine ear to me.
Deliver me speedily.
Be thou my strong rock for an house of defense to save me.
Notice this, for thou art my rock and my fortress.
Therefore, for thy name's sake, lead me and guide me.
I see in verse number three,
where he talks about God being his rock and his fortress,
and I begin to think about the safety or the security
that is communicated to us throughout this,
these two references of my rock and my fortress,
and we see that security and that safety.
Why?
Because the Lord gives that protection.
You know, some of you have had the opportunity to travel
and to see some of these castles and some of these fortresses
and you can see how they would have safety within the walls
and some of them, for periods of time,
just, they were impenetrable.
I mean, there was nothing that an enemy could do.
It was amazing where they would build them
and all that they had.
And David says, God is my rock and he's my fortress.
He's providing me with that security, that protection.
We find in Psalm 4.8,
I know it's some chapters back,
but look at Psalm 4.8, if you will,
and then we'll reference a verse in the book of Proverbs
that we often reference.
We find here in Psalm 4, in verse number eight,
that the Bible says this,
I will both lay me down in peace and sleep,
for thou, Lord, only makest me dwell in safety.
Isn't that a good verse of scripture?
It's a good verse of scripture.
I understand we have security systems
in the era in which we live
and we have people that have various aspects of weaponry
and so on and so forth, and I understand all of that.
But can I tell you that there's no safety like God's safety?
There's no safety like God's safety.
The Bible says, the Proverbs 21 and verse 31,
the Bible says that the horse is prepared
for the day of battle or against the day of battle,
but safety is of the Lord.
And we've used this verse of scripture,
we've shared this verse of scripture,
dealing really with a principle guiding verse
that we use for even church security here,
the fact that we have a responsibility to be prepared,
but ultimately our trust is in God providing the safety.
We don't wanna have our head in the sand,
we don't wanna be silly about it,
we wanna be vigilant, we wanna be prepared
because the Bible does say that the horse is prepared
against the day of battle,
but ultimately safety is of the Lord.
And we see that David is making these references,
there's so many more that we could look at
throughout the book of Psalms,
and we could look at areas of his life
and events in David's life where,
listen, God was protecting David supernaturally.
I mean, it's amazing when you understand
how Saul was trying to kill David,
and Saul immediately did not wanna raise
his own hand against David,
he was desiring that the Philistines would kill David,
and he made up this situation about bringing back a dowry
and so on and so forth,
that maybe the Philistines would kill him.
And we find that then David was simply
in the presence of Saul seeking to minister,
and he takes a javelin and he tries to kill him,
and you look through the life of David
and even the interactions with Saul,
you see God's protection.
David's in a situation where he goes
and he delivers a city, Kilah, from the Philistines.
I mean, he just provided for them
the kind of work that the king should have provided
for them and didn't.
And Saul found out that David was shut up in that city
and he figured, I can go and I can catch him and kill him,
that's what he wanted to do.
And David inquires of the Lord,
what a principle that we must apply in our lives,
seeking God.
And God says, yeah, he's gonna come after you,
and yeah, the people of Kilah
are gonna deliver you to him.
But you know what God did?
He protected him, he protected him.
Jehovah-Rah, the Lord is my shepherd
is what the word, the name, the title, Jehovah-Rah,
the Lord my shepherd, but we begin to understand
that this name of God reveals to us,
it communicates to us certain aspects
about what our relationship to him is
and what he does for us.
Not only does he provide for us
as we looked at a couple of weeks ago,
but we find that he protects us.
So this evening, when we understand Jehovah-Rah,
the Lord my shepherd, and we understand tonight
the protection of my shepherd,
I want you to consider a couple of thoughts
from the New Testament.
Number one, as believers,
we should expect protection from our shepherd.
Now, understand, I'm not being presumptuous upon God,
I'm simply saying that if God said that he is my shepherd,
that I should expect that he's gonna protect me.
My children, when they were younger,
and I hope even to a degree, really, in their lives,
that they would expect that there are certain things
that I would provide for them
and how I would protect them, why?
Because of my role as being their parent.
And we find this evening that God is our shepherd.
Look at John chapter 10, if you will,
and I want you to talk about,
I want you to just consider with me this evening
that we should expect God to protect us.
We should, again, it's not presumptuous,
I'm not seeking to presume upon God,
I'm simply taking the principles
that God has given to us in his word
and helping us to understand
that we should expect God to protect us.
It's not based upon solely your ability
to protect yourself or someone else,
we're trusting and we're understanding
that the Lord, my shepherd,
that one of the things he's going to do for me
as my shepherd is to protect me.
Notice in John chapter 10, a familiar passage of scripture,
Jesus says in verse number 10,
the thief cometh not but for to steal
and to kill and to destroy, that's the thief.
Then Jesus says this, I am come that they might have life,
that they might have it more abundantly.
I'm the good shepherd, the good shepherd giveth his life
for the sheep, but he that is an hireling
and not the shepherd, whose own the sheep are not,
seeth the wolf cometh, and what does he do?
He sees the sheep coming, or excuse me, the wolf coming,
and he leaveth the sheep.
Do you see that in the middle of verse 12?
It's what the hireling does, that's what the thief does.
It says that he sees the wolf coming and he fleeth,
and the wolf catcheth them and scattereth the sheep.
The hireling fleeth because he's an hireling
and careth not for the sheep.
I am the good shepherd and know my sheep
and am known of mine.
As the Father knoweth me, even so know I the Father,
and I lay down my life for the sheep.
As we begin to look at these verses of scripture
and we see this great contrast that the Lord Jesus Christ
is providing to us with regard to his role
as being our good shepherd, we understand contextually
that ultimately, even as we continue reading,
that he's speaking about the fact that he's gonna go
to the cross of Calvary and he's gonna give his life
for the sheep, why?
Because it's the only way for us to be redeemed,
to be reconciled to God.
But we find that it's obvious within the text of scripture
as he speaks about this contrast and he highlights
the behavior of the hireling, the behavior of this one
that he sees the danger come and he flees.
Implied within the text of scripture is that's not
what our shepherd does.
That's not what the good shepherd does.
See, there's some, you look around, you get in a bunch
of trouble and a bunch of difficulty and all of a sudden,
you can look around and you find that the ones
that you thought were your friends aren't there anymore.
Right?
Can happen in life.
I'm telling you, the good shepherd, he doesn't flee.
He's with us.
He provides for us that protection.
We find that as we continue reading, look if you will,
we'll skip down for sake of time, look if you will
at verse 26.
The Bible says this, but you believe not because you're not
of my sheep as I said unto you, my sheep,
here's the application here, we begin to look at this,
my sheep hear my voice and I know them and they follow me.
Notice verse 28, and I give unto them eternal life
and they shall never perish, neither shall any man
pluck them, do you notice what the Bible says here
at the end of verse 28?
Neither shall any man pluck them out of my hand.
So I want you to understand this evening that we are safe
and secure.
secure in the hand of God. We find that the Bible actually would give us this truth as
we look at verse 28, that Jesus is speaking, God the Son, and He says, no man shall any
man pluck them out of My hand. And then in verse 29 He says, My Father which gave them
Me is greater than all, and no man is able to pluck them out of My Father's hand. I and
My Father are one. Listen, this is like double security. Amen? I want you to understand this
evening that this is in the context of Jesus saying, I'm the Good Shepherd. And He says,
My sheep hear My voice, and I know them, and I give unto them eternal life. And I know
that often as I look at and quote this passage of Scripture, that I speak about the fact
that He gives us that eternal security. And it's true, that's what God is teaching here.
And I want you to understand that we're secure in the hand of Christ, and it's in the hand
of God the Father, and we have that protection. Why? Jehovah-Raw, the Lord is my shepherd.
And my shepherd, what does a shepherd do? He protects the sheep. Not only does he provide
for the sheep, we looked at it two weeks ago, but we find that he protects the sheep. And
I wonder this evening, how often do we go through life and truly, are we truly expecting
that God will protect us as He said that He would? He says this, this is what David
says in Psalm 23 and verse number 4, Yea, though I walk through the valley of the shadow
of death, I will fear no evil, for thou art with me, thy rod and thy staff, they comfort
me. The instruments that the shepherd would use, the rod and the staff, they brought comfort
to the sheep. Why? Because with that rod and staff, not only were they able to keep the
sheep close that would wander, but they were able to use them to fight off the prey. And
what a joy to understand the predator, excuse me, what a joy to understand this evening
that my God provides for us the truth of yea, though I walk through the valley of the shadow
of death. We often will use that and speak of that time in which we're nearing the departure
from this life and going and entering the presence of God. While I was in Israel, we
went to a place and I thought we were gonna die as we drove there because we're on this
big bus and there are these hairpin turns to get up to this place and we got up to this
place and they told us this is the valley of the shadow of death, it's what they called
this place. I have pictures of this place. And here's what they said would happen, it
was a main highway, if you will, they used the word highway, not like we think about
highway, a path of journeying from one place to the next and on their livestock and on
their feet, however they would be traveling depending on their abilities and their wealth
and what have you, but it would be a place where they would be able to journey from up
in the north, Galilee, up in that region to Jerusalem. And they'd have to go through this
place and it was just on the west, kind of south side, but westernly there of Jericho
and as you would go to that place and we looked down and you saw just this narrow passage.
And they say what would happen is there would be those that were not very kind people, robbers
and thieves and others that had bad intent that they would hide out in these places and
they would take advantage, they would try to kill or they would steal or whatever they
would do and the reality is that for them when they would say, yea, though I walk through
the valley of the shadow of death, it was a literal place that they would often refer
to as they would make that journey. They didn't have to fear. Why? Because Jehovah Ra, the
Lord's my shepherd and he protects me. I know that his presence is with me. We should
expect God to protect us. We're his sheep. I belong to him. I belong to him. If you're
saved tonight, you belong to him. You're his sheep. Not only should we expect it, but I
would say this, not only do we expect the protection, but we experience protection from
our shepherd. There are times in your life, there are times in my life that we've experienced
the protection of God. There are times in which we can look and we can see and we're
able to, to identify clearly how God protected us from a, from a situation. There are times
in which God protects us from things that we don't even know. I'm sure that's happened
in my life more times than I could even imagine. In your life as well. God protects us. We
see in John 11 a divine delay and there are times in which maybe God will allow something
in our life because he's protecting us from something else and God is working that way.
We find this evening the testimony of, of Paul. We'll look back at David and Psalms
here in just a moment, but look first with me at 2 Timothy chapter number four. In 2
Timothy chapter number four, we see in this passage of scripture, these two verses of
scripture, we see both the expectation and the experience of this protection. And we
begin to look at this and we see that Paul, of course, nearing the end of his life, he's
already announced to Timothy earlier in the chapter that he's ready to be offered, that
the time of the, of his departure was at hand and he had finished his course. And we find
that we come to the end of the book and we find in verse 17, notice what the Bible says.
Notwithstanding, the Lord stood with me and strengthened me. Now what's he talking about?
Well, early in verse 14 he says, Alexander the coppersmith did me much evil. We find
that in verse 16 he says, at my first answer, no man stood with me, but all men forsook
me. And so Paul here is saying in verse 17, notwithstanding, the Lord stood with me and
he strengthened me that by me the preaching might be fully known and that all the Gentiles
might hear. Notice this phrase, and I was delivered out of the mouth of the lion. That's
a powerful statement that Paul makes. Who delivered him? God, Jehovah-Rah, the omnipotent
El Shaddai, the Almighty God. I mean, we could go on, El Elyon, the, the, the most high God
and we could look at all these names that we've been focusing on and we can see that
God provided for, for Paul this protection. Paul's testimony was that I was delivered
out of the mouth of the lion. Listen, the enemy wanted to destroy, devour. He wasn't
destroying, devour us. He, I mean, he wanted to devour Paul. No doubt. You look at Paul's
life and you look at all that he did for the cause of Christ. I mean, he had a mark on
him. The enemy wanted to destroy, devour him, get rid of him. Verse 18, notice, and
the Lord, what's that next word? Shall. What is that? Future? The, the, the, the presence,
the, the, he begins to speak about future as well. The, the Lord shall deliver me from
every evil work. This certainty, right? This, this word shall. He didn't say the Lord might.
That was our first point tonight, the expectation. See, Paul experienced it in verse 17. In verse
18, he's communicating to us as well the fact that he was expecting that God would once
again deliver him. He says, and the Lord shall deliver me from every evil work and will preserve
me unto his heavenly kingdom to be, to whom be glory forever and ever. Amen. I'm in God's
hands and so are you.
D. L. Moody, it is said, I've read, that a man took out a gun one night and threatened
to shoot him and kill him. D. L. Moody had set a principle, a guiding principle in his
life. He made a commitment to God. He would never pillow his head at night if he'd not
shared the gospel with someone during the day. And he realized one night, it was late,
that he had not shared the gospel with anyone that day, so it was, he was going to get up
out of, instead of going to bed, he was going to get out and go share the gospel with someone
in Chicago. It's worse now, but it's never been a good city. The guy threatened him.
You know what, you know what D. L. Moody said? The testimony I read, here's what he said,
you can't threaten me with heaven. You can't threaten me with heaven. He wasn't afraid.
Why? He's in God's hands. He's in God's hands. I've read accounts of missionaries that have
shared testimonies about people that came to the place where they lived because they
wanted to get rid of them out of the communities where they were bringing in this gospel and
changing all of the normal way of living. They came with the purpose of killing them.
And they give testimony that they arrive at the place where the missionary and his family
lived to kill them, and when they arrive there's men guarding the dwelling place. And they
were later asked, where did you find these men? And the missionary said, I have no idea
what you're talking about. Oh, we came. We're going to kill you and your family.
family. But we couldn't. God works as God chooses to work. And for whatever reason in
that particular account, in that situation, I've read that account more than once, that
God chose to allow some angelic beings to be able to be there to show that these people
could see. Do you remember with Elisha? There's more with us than with them. The Lord opened
his eyes. Do you remember the account? Look at Psalm 34, and we'll finish here this evening.
Psalm 34. Listen, I'm so thankful that God protects us. I expect Him to. I've experienced
it. We find that David, I'm just going to reference two verses here, I think. Look at
verse 6. The Bible says, this poor man cried and the Lord heard him and saved him out of
all his troubles. He gave him deliverance. He provided protection for him. Verse 7, the
angel of the Lord encampeth round about them that fear him and delivereth them. I know
I said I was going to look at two verses, but skip down if you will and look at verse
15. The Bible says that the eyes of the Lord are upon the righteous and his ears are open
unto their cry. God knows where we are. You know there's times in which we are in danger
and we don't even know it. We're not aware of it. Spiritually, physically, emotionally.
We don't even know it. The Bible says that the eyes of the Lord are upon the righteous.
Aren't you thankful that God sees you and He knows where you are? It says that His ears
are open unto their cry. Verse 17, the righteous cry and the Lord heareth and delivereth them
out of all their troubles. There's a certain expectation that we would have and there's
an experience that we have as the people of God that are shepherds. Listen, I want to
remind you of what the Bible says in the Old Testament. Our rock with a capital R is not
like their rock with a little r. Amen? Jehovah-Ra. The Lord is my shepherd. And one of the things
that's communicated to me and to you through this name Jehovah-Ra is that our shepherd
protects us. And I hope this evening that we would acknowledge the safety and protection
of God in our lives. By the way, we need it. We desperately need it. We have an enemy.
We have an enemy. But we have a Savior and He's our shepherd. And He's not like the hireling.
When the wolf comes, He doesn't flee. He protects. And for that we ought to rejoice tonight.
Let's pray together. Father, we love You. We thank You for loving us. Thank You for
Your Word. Lord, we thank You for the truth. Lord, I pray that this aspect of what You
do for us as our shepherd would bring encouragement in our lives. Lord, that You would help us
daily to rest in You. Lord, help us not to be anxious. Help us, Lord, to have that peace
knowing that You make us to dwell in safety. That You neither slumber nor sleep. That You're
able and that You're our shepherd. I pray that You'd bless the time of prayer. We thank
You for the privilege. We've referenced a few verses even this evening that remind us
that You hear us when we pray. God, that encourages me tonight. I'm thankful to know that You
live, that You ever live to make intercession for us. I'm thankful tonight that You hear
us and that You're able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think. I'm reminded
of what You said to Jeremiah, call unto me and I will answer thee. Show thee great and
mighty things which thou knowest not. Bless our time and we'll thank You for it in Christ's
name we pray. Amen.