and says, Luke, and we will get there.
I wanna start in 1 Corinthians 11 this evening
as we are observing the Lord's Supper.
We know that the Lord's Supper
is one of two ordinances for the local church
and repeated twice within the instruction
that we find here in 1 Corinthians 11
is the phrase that really we're familiar with,
in remembrance of me.
In verse number 24, it says,
this do in remembrance of me.
At the end of verse 25,
it simply says, in remembrance of me.
And of course, we have it on our Lord's Supper table,
this do in remembrance of me.
I don't think you can see it right now.
The cloth is covering, is that correct?
Or can you still see it?
You can still see it.
I can't see it, amen.
But this do in remembrance of me.
We see that twice here,
and we find that, I would say this,
obviously one purpose of the Lord's Supper
is to remind us of the price
that was paid for our redemption.
Peter reminds us in 1 Peter 1,
you don't need to turn there,
but in verses 18 and 19,
Peter says this, for as much as you know.
Now think about that.
Peter actually, as you read the books of 2 Peter
and particularly, but you read the book of 2 Peter
and Peter talks about stirring them up
by putting them in remembrance of these things.
Though you know them,
I'm gonna stir you up by putting you in remembrance.
And there's some times in which
we need to be reminded of some things.
It's not that we're being taught
as if it's the first pass for us.
It's a reminder for us.
It's being reminded of the price
that was paid for our redemption.
And we find that Peter in the first epistle
in verse 18 of chapter one says,
for as much as you know,
that you were not redeemed with corruptible things.
As silver and gold from your vain conversation
received by tradition from your fathers.
And in verse number 19, he says,
but with the precious blood of Christ
as of a lamb without blemish and without spot.
And what a great two verses of scripture
it goes on to talk about how Jesus is the lamb
that was slain before the foundation of the world.
And I'm so thankful for the price
that was paid for my redemption.
The reality is that we could not redeem ourselves.
We cannot.
I can't redeem you.
You can't redeem me.
There's no amount of good works
than any individual could do to earn them redemption.
Redemption is only through the precious blood
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And without shedding of blood, there is no remission.
We'll look at a couple of other verses this evening
as we get into the message with regard to that.
But I'm reminded as I look here at 1 Corinthians 11,
when the apostle Paul is writing to this church,
he tells them twice leading up into the instruction
that he's going to give them for the Lord's supper.
He says, I praise you not.
See, this was a church,
we're familiar with the church in Corinth,
that really they were carnal divided,
just a church that needed some direction, some instruction.
And he says that he praised them not,
but then we find that it begins to give them the instruction
in verse 23, and it says this,
for I have received of the Lord
that which also I delivered unto you,
that the Lord Jesus,
the same night in which he was betrayed, took bread.
When he had given thanks, he break it and said,
take eat, this is my body, which is broken for you.
This do in remembrance of me.
Verse 25, after the same manner,
also he took the cup when he had supped saying,
this cup is the New Testament in my blood.
This do ye as oft as you drink it in remembrance of me.
For as often as you eat this bread and drink this cup,
you do show the Lord's death till he come.
We'll look at the rest of the verses
as we get into observing the Lord's supper this evening,
but I just wanna take a pause this evening
because we find this reference of in remembrance of me.
And again, as I mentioned a moment ago,
I believe that at least one purpose for the Lord's supper
is to remind us of the price that was paid
for our redemption.
And that's why I titled the message
this evening, Back to Calvary.
We're gonna go back to the book of Luke,
but before we do, I wanna read to you
the words of a familiar song.
And it's a hymn that many of us
have had the opportunity to sing many times.
And it's simply this at Calvary.
Years I spent in vanity and pride,
caring not my Lord was crucified,
knowing not it was for me he died.
On Calvary.
Do you remember when you were in verse one?
Do you remember when you were lost without Christ
that you didn't know that he died,
that he died for you,
you were living years in vanity and pride?
It says in verse number two of the song,
by God's word, aren't you thankful for the word of God?
By God's word at last my sin I learn.
Somebody took a Bible, somebody preached the word of God,
somebody took and opened the scriptures
and showed you from the scriptures the truth of the gospel.
And it says, the songwriter said,
by God's word at last my sin I learned,
then I trembled at the law I'd spurned.
We're guilty.
Did you believe that before you got saved?
You believe I was guilty.
I talked to that man yesterday and I said,
listen, no one had to convince me that I was a sinner.
No one had to convince me that I was guilty.
And he said, me too.
He knew he was a sinner.
He knew he was guilty.
Trembled at the law I'd spurned.
Why? Because God is just.
The soul that sins shall die.
Amen.
The songwriter goes on to say,
till my guilty soul imploring turned to Calvary.
Repentance.
Verse three, now I've given to Jesus everything.
Isn't that the, shouldn't that be the natural response?
I mean, honestly, when we understand where we were
and what he did for us,
the songwriter says, now I've given to Jesus everything.
Now I gladly own him as my king.
Now my raptured soul can only sing of Calvary.
I wonder how often do you think about
and sing about Calvary?
The last one, the last verse,
oh, the love that drew salvation's plan.
The love that was displayed on Calvary.
It wasn't the nails that held him to that cross.
It was his love for humanity.
Oh, the grace that brought it down to man.
Oh, the mighty goth that God did span at Calvary.
Because it was there at Calvary that God the father
made him God the son to be sin for us.
Who knew no sin that we might be made
the righteousness of God in him.
Can you imagine?
Mercy there was great and grace was free.
Pardon there was multiplied to me.
There my burdened soul found liberty at Calvary.
I'm thankful for the place called Calvary.
Go back to the book of Luke, if you will.
Kind of interesting, it's the only place
where we see the reference to Calvary is in Luke 23.
Golgotha you'll read and rightly so,
but we see this phrase in Luke chapter 23.
I'll read verse 33 and then we'll kind of look
at a variety of portions of this text
of scripture this evening.
I just have two simple thoughts for you tonight.
And it's just a message to remind us.
It's not anything I hope for any of you,
anything that's brand new.
It's something that we're being reminded of.
And the first reminder is this,
we need to remember what he suffered.
He suffered greatly.
I've often asked people as I look at the truth
of the book of Galatians, when Paul says this,
that if righteousness come by the law,
then Christ is dead in vain.
And what Paul is saying there is that if it were possible
that humanity could earn redemption,
then Christ did not have to die.
But because Christ died, it gives to us the understanding
that it was impossible for us to have righteousness
in our own works.
And so his death, the death of the Lord Jesus Christ
was not in vain.
He went to the cross because it was absolutely necessary
for any individual to be saved.
He had to go to the cross, he had to die,
he had to be buried, he had to rise again.
And he suffered a horrific death on the cross of Calvary.
And the Bible says in Luke 23 and verse 33,
and when they were come to the place
which is called Calvary, there they crucified him.
And the male factors, one on the right hand
and the other on the left,
begin to think about what my Lord, what your Lord suffered.
We find that as we referenced already
in the book of 1 Corinthians 11,
we saw in verse 24 that it was the body that was broken.
In verse 25, the blood that was shed.
We begin to think about the suffering
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And we find that within Luke's gospel,
really going back to the 22nd chapter in verse number 47,
we begin to see the suffering
that he endured before the cross.
The cross itself was great suffering,
but we understand as we read the records of the gospels,
that there was great suffering that took place
even before he got to the cross.
And it begins for us in verse number 47, the Bible says,
and while he yet spake, in Luke 22, in verse 47,
and while he yet spake, behold, a multitude,
and he that was called Judas, one of the 12,
went before them and drew near unto Jesus to kiss him.
But Jesus said unto him, Judas, betray us now
the son of man with a kiss.
When they which were about him saw what would follow,
they said unto him, Lord, shall we smite with the sword?
And one of them smote the servant of the high priest
and cut off his right ear.
And Jesus answered and said, suffer ye thus far.
And he touched his ear and healed him.
Then Jesus said unto the chief priests
and captains of the temple and the elders
which were come to him, be ye come out as against a thief
with swords and staves.
When I was daily with you in the temple,
you stretched forth no hands against me,
but this is your hour and the power of darkness.
Verse 54, then took they him and led him
and brought him into the high priest house.
And Peter followed afar off.
And when they had kindled a fire in the midst of the hall
and were set down together, Peter sat down among them.
But a certain maid beheld him as he had sat by the fire
and earnestly looked upon him and said,
this man was also with him.
And he denied him saying, woman, I know him not.
And after a little while, another saw him and said,
thou art also of them.
And Peter said, man, I am not.
We find that the account of Peter's denial,
I'm gonna skip forward.
In verse 62, Peter went out and wept bitterly
after the completion and the cock crowing.
In verse 63, the Bible says,
and the men that held Jesus mocked him and smote him.
And when they had blindfolded him,
they struck him on the face and asked him saying,
prophesy, who is it that smote thee?
And many other things blasphemously spake they
against him.
The Bible says in verse 66, and as soon as it was day,
the elders of the people and the chief priests
and the scribes came together
and led him into their council saying.
And so we find that after the arrest there in the garden,
and we read about Peter's denial,
but the Bible told us in verse 54, that they took Jesus,
they brought him into the high priest house.
And we find that the record is given of Peter's denial,
but then the Bible tells us that the men that held Jesus
in verse 63, that they mocked him and they smote him.
And then they blindfold him
and they begin to strike him in the face and say to him,
prophesy, who is it that smote thee?
Do you see the scene?
I've actually been to the place.
I don't know that it's truly the place,
but it's the place that they believe
is the house of Caiaphas.
And you can visit it today in Israel, you can go there.
And when I went into that place,
we knew as we went in that it may not be the actual place,
but certainly there were many similarities
to it actually being the place
that was excavated and found.
And you went into this house
and you went down into the lower chambers
and you saw these places that were set up for torture.
And it's just truly what it was.
You saw the holes that they had in the rocks
where they would be able to tie prisoners up
and what they were able to do.
And then we literally stood in the pit
that was in that place.
And I remember singing hymns
when we were standing in that place
and remembering what happened that night.
And we begin to think about the suffering
before he even got to the cross.
And we find that he stands before the Sanhedrin
to end chapter number 22.
He's gonna go before Pilate.
And we find that he eventually is gonna be before Herod
and all these things that are taking place.
And we find that other gospel accounts tell us
of how they spit upon him and all that they did.
And I think about the suffering of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And I'm reminded this evening that he's God.
He's the God of the universe.
He's the one that has all power.
He's the one that loved us so much
that he humbled himself as Paul says
in the book of Philippians,
and became obedient unto death,
even the death of the cross.
The Romans, I'm told, as I study history,
that the Romans did everything that they could
to perfect the art of crucifixion.
And I know that that's a bad way to phrase it,
but that's the best way I know
based on the historical evidence
is they would do what they could
to bring an individual as close to death as possible
to give them the most suffering
that could possibly be endured by a human being.
Why?
Well, many times, even as the case was with Jesus,
they would be crucified publicly as an example.
As others would be able to pass by
and see the one that was being crucified
and understanding that they would never desire
for that to be their lot in life.
And that has quite an impact on behavior.
It really does.
And we find that before he ever got to that cross,
we read of these horrific things
that happened to the Lord Jesus Christ.
And notice if you will in verse 26,
and as they led him away,
they laid hold upon one Simon, a Cyrene,
and a coming out of the country.
And on him, they laid the cross
that he might bear it after Jesus.
And they there followed him a great company of people
and of women, which also bewailed and lamented him.
But Jesus, even in this place
of really being beaten and suffering
and all that he went through,
notice in verse 28 of chapter 23,
Jesus says, daughters of Jerusalem, weep not for me,
but weep for yourselves and for your children.
For behold, the days are coming
in the which they shall say,
blessed are the barren and the wombs that never bear
and the paps which never gave suck.
Then shall they begin to say to the mountains,
fall on us into the hills, cover us.
For if they do these things in a green tree,
what shall be done in the dry?
And there were also two other male factors
led with him to be put to death.
And we come to verse 33 that we read a moment ago
when they were come to the place which is called Calvary,
there they crucified him in the male factors,
one on the right hand and the other on the left.
The Bible tells us as we would consider the suffering
before the cross and then the suffering there on the cross
in verse 34, the Bible tells us,
then said, Jesus, notice in verse number 34,
father, forgive them for they know not what they do.
Isn't that a powerful statement?
Such power, such love, such grace, such mercy.
Father, forgive them for they know not what they do.
They parted his raiment and cast lots
and the people stood beholding.
The rulers also with them derided him saying,
he saved others, let him save himself.
If he be the Christ, the chosen of God.
And the soldiers also mocked him coming to him
and offering him vinegar and saying,
if thou be the king of the Jews, save thyself.
By the way, I'm thankful that Christ stayed on the cross.
Aren't you?
We find that as you begin to look at this,
it's interesting in verse 35,
it says that the people stood beholding.
As they begin to just watch and to see the,
I mean, he's beyond the ability to really recognize
as a man, the way that he'd been beaten
and all that he had suffered, his body broken,
his blood being shed.
We see that he suffered such great, horrific death.
We'll read about the subscription that was,
or the superscription that was above written
over him in the letters in verse 38,
Greek and Latin and Hebrew.
This is the king of the Jews.
Notice, if you will, if you skip down to verse number 44,
and it was about the sixth hour,
there was a darkness over all the earth
until the ninth hour.
The sun was darkened and the veil of the temple
was rent in the midst.
By the way, verse 45 is such a powerful truth
that gives us, as you study the book of Hebrews,
that access, a new and living way.
The veil was rent and twain.
In verse 46, and when Jesus had cried with a loud voice,
he said, Father, into thy hands I commend my spirit.
And having said thus, he gave up the ghost.
He died.
He said this, as John would record,
Eli, Eli, lama sabachthani, my God, my God,
why hast thou forsaken me?
You think about the physical suffering
that the Lord Jesus Christ endured on the cross of Calvary,
leading up to the cross of Calvary,
and you think about the pain that was inflicted,
pain beyond your ability or my ability to fully comprehend.
Beside all those things, the wrath of God was poured
upon him.
He made him to be sin for us, who knew no sin,
that we might be made the righteousness of God in him.
And you think about the truth of what was transpiring
at that moment in history.
The suffering.
He left the throne room of heaven.
He left all the glories to suffer.
And we need to be reminded as we observe the Lord's Supper, Jesus gives the instruction
to Paul.
Paul says, I received of the Lord that which I'm delivering.
And he said, as he goes back to that night and they observe that last supper there, and
we find that as you begin to look at the Lord's Supper, he said, this is my body which is
broken for you, this do in remembrance of me.
And then the cup and representing the blood in remembrance of me that we remember what
he suffered for me, for you.
It's overwhelming to truly just pause and just think about it.
I mentioned this on Wednesday evening.
Every once in a while in our lives, we can get kind of in a spiritual rut, kind of distracted
in life, kind of just mundane, monotonous, just going through the motions, whatever it
might be, however it is that you want to describe it.
And I said this, it would be good if you ever find yourself in that condition to run to
the Gospels and read the last few chapters of every book of Matthew, Mark, Luke, and
John, because it'll help you to be reminded of what Christ did for you.
I'm thankful that he was buried, that he rose, conquering sin, death, and the grave.
He's alive forevermore.
We read that this, as we look at 1 Corinthians 11, that as often as you eat this bread and
drink this cup, you do show the Lord's death till he come.
And so the resurrection is not specifically stated in 1 Corinthians 11, but it's definitely
inferred that we understand that he did rise again, and he is coming again, and we're thankful
for that.
So we understand this evening, as we're reminded in remembrance of me, we remember what he
suffered, but then we remember why he suffered.
I've mentioned it throughout the message this evening, but he suffered for me.
He suffered for you.
He died so that we might live.
We sing the song at times, it's been a while since we've had the opportunity to sing it.
It was for me.
And we begin to think about the truth of God's Word and the recognition of, yes, what he
suffered, but then putting ourselves in the place of understanding it was for me.
If you were the only person, if I was the only person on planet Earth, Jesus would have
died for you, because that's the only way that you could be redeemed to him.
He loves you so much.
And we recognize this evening Romans 5, 8, but God commendeth his love toward us, and
that while we're yet sinners, Christ died for us.
Look over to the book of Colossians, if you will, and I want to look at two verses, or
it's actually three verses, but two different portions of the book of Colossians.
Look with me first in Colossians chapter number one.
As Paul is writing here to these believers in Colossae, he gives them just a reminder
in chapter one and then again in chapter number two about this very subject in which we're
dealing with tonight.
These people were saved.
The Bible says in verse number three of Colossians 1, we give thanks to God and the Father of
our Lord Jesus Christ, praying always for you, since we heard of your faith in Christ
Jesus and of the love which you have to all the saints.
These are saved people, they've been born again.
And we understand that the Lord's Supper, in remembrance of me, the Lord's Supper's
an ordinance that's given to the local church to save people.
The Lord's Supper's not for lost people.
The Lord's Supper cannot save anybody.
There's nothing about the elements that change, that have any ability to save.
It was settled on the cross 2,000 years ago.
And we find that Paul, as he's writing to these saved people, he reminds them in verse
number 14 of chapter one, in whom we have redemption through His blood, even the forgiveness
of sins.
We find that as you look here at this verse of Scripture, it's so important that we understand
that we have redemption, but there's only one way to have redemption, and it's through
the blood of the Lord Jesus Christ.
We sang this morning, redeemed how I love to proclaim it, and actually we didn't sing
that this morning.
Is that what we sang this morning?
It's not what we sang this morning.
What did we sing this morning?
We sang some song about being saved.
We sang saved by the blood.
And I said this, there's only one way to be saved, and that's to be saved by the blood
of the crucified one.
And we find that as you look at the truth of God's Word, and by the way, many of the
modern translations like to mess with Colossians 1 and verse 14.
And what do they remove?
They remove the blood.
But without the blood, there's no forgiveness.
Without the blood, there's no remission.
And we find that he says, in whom we have redemption, and then he says, when he says
through his blood, you know what he's doing?
He's reminding them of Calvary.
He doesn't just say, in whom we have redemption, even the forgiveness of sins.
He reminds them.
He puts in the midst of this verse of Scripture through his blood.
Why?
Because it's a reminder of Calvary.
I can only be redeemed, and you can only be redeemed.
We can only be forgiven because of the blood that was shed at Calvary.
And even in reading Colossians 1 and verse 14, we're reminded back to Calvary and what
he did for us and how he shed his blood for us in chapter 2.
Notice with me in verse number 13.
The Bible says in chapter 2 and verse 13, and you, being dead in your sins and the uncircumcision
of your flesh, hath he quickened together with him, having forgiven you all trespasses.
Now, that's a wonderful verse of Scripture, the fact that we were dead in our sins.
Paul talks about it in Ephesians chapter 2 when he's writing to the church at Ephesus.
You hath he quickened.
We see the recognition here as well, hath he quickened together with him.
I was dead, and God gave me life, spiritually dead, on my way to a Christless eternity.
Why did he suffer?
He suffered so that I could be quickened.
He suffered so that I could be saved, so I could be born again, so I could be redeemed,
so I could be forgiven.
It says in verse 14, blotting out the handwriting of ordinances that was against us, which was
contrary to us, and took it out of the way, nailing it to his cross.
Praise God.
We sang it as well with my soul this morning.
And all of those verses are wonderful, but verse number 3, my sin, oh the bliss of this
glorious thought.
My sin, not in part, but the whole, is nailed to his cross, and I bear it no more.
Aren't you thankful for that?
We find that he says, blotting out the handwriting of ordinances that was against us, which was
contrary to us.
Listen, we were guilty, but no hope.
Why did he suffer?
He suffered so that we could be saved.
It says that he took it out of the way, nailing it to his cross.
He paid for it with his blood.
Wonderful truth.
This evening, as we prepare to observe the Lord's Supper, I've desired for me and for
you to just travel back to Calvary for a few moments tonight, to just be reminded what
Christ did for us, what he suffered and why he suffered, and that we'd have an appreciation
for our salvation, that we would, listen, the Lord's Supper is not something that we
just do because it's a religious rote-type process, no.
This is a time of great, really, soberness and just, we, yes, understand the process
of self-examination and evaluation and all those things, but I'm reminded of what Christ
did for me and what he did for you, what he did for all of those in the world, the just
for the unjust.
I don't deserve it.
You don't deserve it.
But aren't you thankful that someone told you?
As the songwriter said, by God's word, right?
Somebody took the Bible and told you, whether they quoted Scripture or had you read Scripture,
they told you about what Christ did for you.
Peer Kimberly played this morning, There is a Fountain Filled with Blood.
What a great song.
Tonight, and really it should be a reminder that we have every day of our lives, that
Christ suffered greatly so that I could live.
And he did it, just like the songwriter said, now I'm going to live for him, right?
why? Because I understand what He did for me. I understand how much He suffered for
me. And so I want to live for Him. If we have to suffer a little bit, remember we looked
at some of that this morning, the reality is that I'm going to live with Him forever.
Tonight, I hope that you appreciate what Christ did for you on the cross. And then as we journey
back before we look at 1 Corinthians 11, just in our minds for a little while tonight,
journey back to Calvary, nothing new, just a fresh reminder of how much He loves you
and how much He loves me and what He did for us. See, Hebrew says it this way, and I want
to close with this before we transition into 1 Corinthians 11, but Hebrew says it this
way in Hebrews chapter number 12. In verse number 2, the Bible says, looking unto Jesus,
the author and finisher of our faith, the Bible says this, who for the joy that was
set before Him, endured the cross, despising the shame, and is set down at the right hand
of the throne of God. For consider Him that endured such contradiction of sinners against
Himself lest ye be wearied and faint in your minds. See, for the joy that was set before
Him, He endured the cross. He did despise the shame. We understand that He's exalted.
He's sitting at the right hand of the Father at the moment. He's going to come back one
day and this evening for the joy. What was that joy? Redemption has been paid for. That's
why Jesus said, it is finished. It is finished. He paid in full and the plan was complete
and we can rejoice this evening as we go back to Calvary. Let's pray. Lord, we love You.
We thank You for loving us. We thank You that You've given to us this ordinance, the
Lord's Supper. We thank You that we can take and journey back to Calvary in our minds and
through the Scriptures. We understand what You suffered. We understand why You suffered.
God, I pray that You would help us to be grateful, mindful. Lord, help us to be fervent in sharing
this message with those that we come in contact with, many who are lost and heading to a Christless
eternity. Father, I pray that over the next few moments as we look further into this text
in 1 Corinthians 11 that You would just encourage us tonight. Help us as we examine ourselves.
Lord, help us to be clean. Help us to be right with You. Lord, we'll thank You for what You'll
do. For it's in Christ's name we pray. Amen.