Genesis chapter number three, if you will, Genesis chapter number three, we'll be looking
at verses one through seven this evening.
Genesis chapter number three, verses one through seven, and I'll give you a moment to turn
there, the title for the message this evening, Sin Entered the World.
Verse number one of Genesis three, the Bible says, now the serpent was more subtle than
any beast of the field which the Lord God had made.
And he said unto the woman, yea, hath God said, ye shall not eat of every tree of the
garden.
The woman said unto the serpent, we may eat of the fruit of the trees of the garden.
But of the fruit of the tree which is in the midst of the garden, God hath said, ye shall
not eat of it, neither shall ye touch it, lest ye die.
And the serpent said unto the woman, ye shall not surely die.
For God doth know that in the day ye eat thereof, then your eyes shall be opened, and ye shall
be as gods, knowing good and evil.
When the woman saw that the tree was good for food, and that it was pleasant to the
eyes, and a tree to be desired to make one wise, she took of the fruit thereof, and did
eat, and gave also unto her husband with her, and he did eat.
And the eyes of them both were opened, and they knew that they were naked, and they sewed
fig leaves together, and made themselves aprons.
As you understand, as we've studied through the book of Genesis up to this point, we spent
a couple of weeks looking at the second chapter of Genesis, and we understand that Adam and
Eve, as they spent time in the garden, it is not a specified period of time that God
gives us as to how long they were in the Garden of Eden.
As we study chapter number two, we do know that they were placed there by God.
The garden was specifically created by God and set there for a place that was prepared
for Adam and Eve according to verse number eight of chapter two.
We find that God planted that garden in that place for that purpose.
As we think about the period of time in which Adam and Eve lived in the garden, and it's
an unspecified period of time, we'd understand this evening as we'd read the text of Scripture
and getting into the third chapter of the book of Genesis, that it would lead us to
believe that the period of time was not very long that they spent in the garden.
The period of time was distinguished, as we looked at last week, as a time of innocency,
a time in which God created everything perfect, and it was that period of innocency.
It's understood, as we look at the third chapter of the book of Genesis, that evidently for
however long they had spent in the garden, they did experience fellowship with God.
You understand that in chapter number three, in verse number eight, it says, when they
heard the voice of the Lord God walking in the garden in the cool of the day, and so
evidently they had experienced fellowship with God during that period of time that they
were there in the garden.
You'll recall from our study over the last couple of Sunday evenings that Genesis chapter
number two tells us of many trees that were planted in the garden, but he mentions two
specifically by name in verse number nine of Genesis two.
It was the tree of life, and it was the tree of knowledge of good and evil.
These are the two trees that are mentioned specifically by name.
We know that the Bible tells us in verse number nine that God, out of the ground, made the
Lord God to grow every tree that is pleasant to the sight and good for food, and so there
are many more trees than the two that are specified by name, but we do know that the
tree of life and the tree of knowledge of good and evil were there in the garden.
We also know from our study of chapter number two that it's in Genesis chapter number two
where God records for us and reveals to us the very first command from God to man.
That command is found for us as we would look at the second chapter in verses sixteen
and seventeen where the Bible says, and the Lord God commanded the man, saying, of every
tree of the garden thou mayest freely eat, but of the tree of the knowledge of good and
evil thou shalt not eat of it.
From the day that thou eatest thereof, notice, thou shalt surely die.
As we understand Genesis chapter number two and the record that is given there in that
first command, we said that it was a simple command and there were also known consequences
that God gave with regard to that last part of verse number seventeen, thou shalt surely
die.
As we enter into the third chapter, we see as we've titled the lesson this evening, sin
entered the world, reminded of what the New Testament speaks about in Romans five and
verse number twelve concerning this sin entering into the world, and Paul puts it this way
in Romans five and verse number twelve with regard to the historicity and the accuracy
of that which we find in the Genesis record, he says, wherefore as by one man sin entered
into the world.
And then he says this, and death by sin, and so death passed upon all men for that all
have sinned.
And we find that Paul, in writing to those in Rome, he references back to this event
in the garden that we're studying this evening in chapter number three, when sin entered
the world.
Now as we look at the passage of scripture in Genesis chapter number three, if you're
taking notes this evening, I want you to notice the conversation recorded.
In verses one through five, we find that God records for us a conversation, the conversation
is between Eve and the serpent, the serpent of course is Satan.
We find that the Bible records for us this conversation and we understand as we've mentioned
already by way of introduction that this was a perfect environment.
We understand that God had created everything in perfection, in fact, in Genesis chapter
number one, remember in verse number thirty-one, it says, and God saw everything that he had
made and behold it was very good.
And we find that the creation week had ended, God gave us the record of the place in which
man would dwell, and in that place of perfection, for an unknown period of time they dwelled
there.
I would believe that it was a short period of time, and now the serpent who is more subtle
than any beast of the field, which the Lord God had made, Satan comes to tempt Eve.
We find that here as we would understand that Satan is there and in the garden and we'd
understand from the passage of scripture that this is the first temptation of mankind.
Now here's a question that's asked often and a question that we would seek to answer this
evening, though the answer may not please you because the bottom line is we don't know
for sure, but the question often asked is regarding Satan, when was he created and when
did he fall?
And many people ask that question, they try to pinpoint it as to a particular time.
There's some Bible scholars that have tried to pinpoint it to an exact day.
One in particular said it was the tenth day after creation.
I'm not sure how he arrived to his conclusion, but that's what he arrived to.
What we'd find this evening as we seek to answer that question, there are some things
that the Bible tells us in regard to Satan and the fact that he was created and all of
that sort of thing.
We know that he was created for over in the book of Ezekiel in chapter number 28, there
in that text of scripture, first of all let me mention this, as you're turning to Ezekiel
28, remember over in Exodus in chapter number 20 the Bible says that God made all things
in six days and he created all things in six days and so we would understand according
to the text of scripture as we look at Ezekiel 28 that Satan was created, he was not created
however as Satan, right?
We understand that he was Lucifer and that anointed cherub and we find here in Ezekiel
chapter number 28 beginning in verse number 13, the Bible says, thou hast been in Eden,
the garden of God.
Every precious stone was thy covering, the sardis, the topaz, and the diamond, the beryl,
the onyx, the jasper, the sapphire, the emerald, and the carbuncle, and gold.
The workmanship of thy tabards and of thy pipes were prepared in thee, notice this,
in the day that thou wast created and so we understand biblically that Lucifer was created.
You find that it says in verse 14, thou art the anointed cherub that covereth and I have
set thee so, thou wast upon the holy mountain of God, thou hast walked up and down in the
midst of the stones of fire, thou wast perfect in thy ways, notice this, from the day that
thou wast created till iniquity was found in thee.
By the multitude of thy merchandise they have filled the midst of thee with violence and
thou hast sinned therefore I will cast thee as profane out of the mountain of God and
I will destroy thee O covering cherub from the midst of the stones of fire.
As we understand the passage of scripture here in the book of Ezekiel we would conclude
that yes indeed Lucifer was created.
Now we also know this that the angels joined in praise when God created the earth.
Over in Job chapter number 38 the Bible would give us some indication in that passage of
scripture.
You remember as you're turning there that God begins to speak in Job 38.
Remember Job is seeking an answer from God and there's a period of silence and the time
in which his friends are telling him all of these things and of course he concludes that
they're miserable comforters and what have you.
But we get to Job 38 and we find that the Bible says, then the Lord answered Job out
of the whirlwind and said, but I want to draw your attention specifically to verses six
and seven where the Bible says this, whereupon are the foundations thereof fastened or who
laid the cornerstone thereof.
Of course God is revealing to Job that he is omnipotent, omniscient and he's sharing
his power there with Job and he speaks about creation there in verse seven.
verse number six and verse number seven notice when the morning stars sang
together and all the sons of God shouted for joy we look at verse number seven
we'd understand the reference here to angels that angelic host and Lucifer
being an anointed cherub we'd understand that when God is giving this answer to
Job with regard to the praise of when God created the earth we would
understand back from our study of chapter number one of the book of
Genesis that it was on day number three when God set the foundation the land and
the sea and all of those things and so we would conclude this evening that
certainly Lucifer and all of the angels they were created we know that
factually biblically and they were created in the early part of creation
week I cannot nail down an exact day I do not think the Bible clearly tells us
a specific day in which they were created we've studied chapter number one
and we do understand the things that God told us now it's also interesting that
people would say well when did he sin when did this war in heaven take place
this rebellion when Lucifer says it's recorded over in the book of Isaiah I
will be like the Most High and all of those things and we find that that sin
took place and he was expelled from the that position and of course becomes the
adversary of mankind and of God in whole we do not know exactly when this
took place however it would seem obvious that it was shortly after creation as we
look at the scriptures and we understand what God is giving us remember in
Genesis this record is provided to us I mentioned already this evening that as
we think about Genesis chapter number three and we think about the serpent
coming in tempting Adam and Eve I said that they did not live in the garden
very long in that state of innocency the reason that I conclude that is they had
no offspring right they were told be fruitful and multiply and yet there's no
record of any children being born in that stage of innocency and so
evidently it was a very quick process in which took place after this period
that's recorded for us in chapter number two and Satan rebels against God
and all that takes place and we find that then the temptation against mankind
comes in chapter number three as it's recorded for us here we understand that
there's some that have actually offered the opinion that they probably lived in
the garden for over a hundred years I don't think you can biblically come to
that conclusion based upon the fact that there were no children that were born in
that stage of innocency and we find that through Adam and Eve of course you
as you go through the text of Scripture you come to chapter four when you begin
to find about their descendants in that fulfillment of that command that was
given to be fruitful and multiply so getting back to the conversation I only
mentioned all of that because the Bible starts in verse number one now the
serpent was more subtle than any beast of the field where did he come from what
happened how did it happen all of those questions and we find that the record
that God gives us it just states it as being factual that this is what took
place and God did not see fit to give us the specific events dates and times in
which they took place but we are sure that this conversation that is recorded
in Genesis 3 verses 1 through 5 is a true historical account of when sin
entered the world I want you to notice with me what Satan says here in verse
number one notice first of all it says and he said under the woman yay half God
said you shall not eat of every tree of the garden and you find it in that very
first statement that he makes to Eve he's beginning to cast doubt upon that
which God has said and he's undermining the authority of God he says yay half
God said and we find that there in Genesis 3 and verse number one is the
initial attack upon the Word of God as it's been given to mankind remember God
instructed Adam and Eve in chapter number two we've studied that we look
through it and we find now that Satan is coming and he's undermining he's putting
seeds of doubt into the mind of Eve and he says yay half God said he doesn't end
there we find that as the conversation takes place because he said you shall
not eat of every tree the garden notice Eve in her response the woman sent him
to the serpent we may eat of the fruit of the trees of the garden you remember
that back in chapter number two in verse number 16 God said that of every tree
the garden notice thou mayest freely eat she continues in verse number three and
says but of the fruit of the tree which is in the midst of the garden evidently
obviously speaking about the tree of knowledge of good and evil that had been
forbidden we find that here's what she says God hath said you shall not eat of
it neither shall you touch it lest ye die it's interesting as to looking at
the response of Eve to Satan when he comes and says yay half God said you
shall not eat of every tree of the garden that she got partially correct
what it was that God said in chapter number two but it is interesting that
she ends verse number three by saying lest ye die as if it was a possibility
that that might take place when God in fact said at the end of verse over 17
thou shalt surely die man there's a there's a difference between thou shalt
surely die and lest there's a difference in what she says lest ye die notice here
that the serpent continues Satan continues he first says yea hath God
said notice in verse number four and the serpent said of the woman notice this ye
shall not surely die you shall not surely die so he's given he's cast the
doubt in verse number one when he says yea hath God said now in verse number
four he just outright contradicts that which God said in chapter number two God
said that you can eat freely of all of these trees but of the tree of knowledge
of good and evil he tells them thou shalt not eat of it for in the day that
thou eatest thereof thou shalt surely die Satan says in verse number four ye
shall not surely die can I tell you that Satan still works the same way
today he comes to the people of God and he says yea have God said and then he
says to us it's not gonna happen that's not really how it's gonna work that's
not gonna be the consequence that's not gonna be the that's how he works he's
undermining he's directly opposing that which God has said in his word you
notice that as you move forward in verse number five at the continuation of what
he says in verse four you shall not surely die notice what he says in verse
number five for God doth know that in the day that you eat thereof then your
eyes shall be opened and you shall be as God's knowing good and evil it's as if
Satan is seeking to convince Eve here according to verse number five that God
was withholding something from her that was good for her right see God knows
that in the day that you eat thereof that your eyes are going to be opened
and you're gonna be as God's he's making it appealing is he not he's going through
that process and saying God's keeping something from you listen we serve a God
who is gracious and merciful we serve a God who is a good God amen and he's good
all the time and we need to rejoice in the goodness of God and understanding
this evening that as Satan would come to tempt you to tempt me as we see sin
entering into the world in Genesis chapter number three we find that the
same tactic that is used here is used continuously by the adversary by the
enemy yea hath God said ye shall not surely die and then he tells Eve that
God is withholding something that's good for her he's seeking to entice her he's
seeking to tempt her we think about this temptation here and in these verses of
Scripture through this conversation that is recorded for us and we find that Eve
unfortunately did not get on the running shoes and go and find Adam and find out
what's going on and get that protection we find that the conversation was
entertained and there's this dialogue that goes back and forth and it's as if
here that Eve is there and she's just enamored with what's taking place and
you notice the response in verse number six and we see the conversation that
then reveals to us according to verse number six the course of sin the course
of sin notice in verse number six the Bible says and when the woman saw that
the tree was good for food and that it was pleasant to the eyes and a tree to
be desired to make one wise she took she took of the fruit thereof and did
eat and gave also under her husband with her and he did eat as we look at verse
number six and we see the course of sin we find that it begins with the eye
there when she saw it the Bible says when the woman saw that the tree was
good for food and we can think about and we'll look at a passage of Scripture in
1st John here in just a moment but we can think about the
the lust of the flesh.
And we see that here it continues and says,
and that it was pleasant to the eyes,
the lust of the eyes.
And then it concludes by saying
that it was a fruit that was a tree
to be desired to make one wise,
the pride of life.
We find here that this course of sin
that is mentioned here in Genesis 3
and verse 6, that she saw it,
she desired it.
Eventually, as we look in the text of Scripture,
the Bible says that she took of the fruit thereof
and did eat.
In 1 John 2,
the Bible would give us this truth
with regard to that which we've just mentioned
by parallel of what takes place here
in Genesis 3 and verse 6.
And we find that in 1 John 2
and verses 15-17,
the Bible says,
love not the world, neither the things
that are in the world.
Any man love the world,
the love of the Father is not in him.
For all that is in the world,
the lust of the flesh,
we noticed that right when she saw it,
the lust of the flesh
and the lust of the eyes,
it was pleasant to the eyes
is what we are told in Genesis 3
and verse 6,
and the pride of life.
It was desired to make one wise.
The Bible says it's not of the Father,
but is of the world.
And then it tells us this,
and the world passeth away
in the lust thereof,
but he that doeth the will of God
abideth forever.
As we notice the course of sin here
in Genesis 3 and verse 6,
we find that the action
that has taken place there
at the end of the verse of Scripture
where she took and ate,
that that is the result
of standing there,
having that conversation,
seeing it, and desiring it,
and eventually taking it.
It reminds me of the course of sin
even in the life of Achan
as you'd find in Joshua 7.
In fact, in Joshua 7,
God calls through Joshua,
Achan before him,
and there's a conversation
that takes place,
and Joshua says give glory to God,
and there's this conversation,
and Achan tells him,
Joshua in verse 21 of Joshua 7,
when I saw among the spoils,
he saw it,
a goodly Babylonish garment
and 200 shekels of silver
and a wedge of gold
of 50 shekels weight.
Then I coveted them,
that desire that he had,
and it says took them,
and behold, they are hid in the earth
in the midst of my tent
and the silver under it.
In Genesis 3,
when sin entered into the world,
we find this course of sin
that is mentioned to us
in verse number 6,
and we find that this is a course
that is often repeated
where we see something.
Oh, how important it is
that we're careful
with that which we look at.
That we understand the lust of the flesh.
That we understand the lust of the eyes.
That we understand the pride of life,
and that we're careful to guard
against those things.
That we would say,
get thee behind me, Satan.
That we would understand
that it's important that we know
what thus saith the Lord.
It's important for us to understand
that God is not trying to keep anything from us.
Too many people have the wrong idea
this evening in our society
as I have conversation
and interact with individuals,
and they'll say,
well, God wants me to be happy.
Can I tell you that's not
God's primary concern for you?
God's primary concern for you
is not that you're happy.
Can I tell you what leads to joy
is obedience, right?
What leads to joy is doing the will of God,
is doing what God has prescribed in His Word.
And this idea that,
well, God wants me to be happy,
and if it makes me happy,
then obviously God is for it.
No, my friend,
you need to go to what the Word of God says.
Amen?
You need to go and find what did God say
in His Word concerning that.
And God said to Adam and Eve,
notice the grace of God.
He says that of all the trees
that were there,
in verse number 16,
He says of chapter number two,
of every tree of the garden
thou mayest freely eat.
But there was one restriction.
Why is it that that one thing
that's restricted is something
that seems to cause us to stumble so often?
And how we'd understand
the consequence of sin,
and we'd see even here
in Genesis 3,
when sin entered the world,
that we'd understand the grave consequence
of this action that is here.
It's been recorded for us
so that we'd understand.
In verse number 6,
at the end of the verse of Scripture,
it says,
She gave also unto her husband with her,
and he did eat.
As we'd understand in the New Testament again,
we mentioned already from the book of Romans
in chapter number 5,
about Adam there
and sin entering into the world.
But Paul also says this over in 1 Timothy,
chapter number 2,
in verse number 14.
It's an interesting verse of Scripture.
And he's dealing with some things
with the church and roles in the church
and so on and so forth.
But he says here in 1 Timothy 2,
in verse number 14,
and Adam was not deceived,
but the woman being deceived
was in the transgression.
Eve wasn't, excuse me,
Eve was deceived,
but Adam was not deceived.
In 1 Corinthians 15,
in verse number 33,
excuse me, verse number 22,
God mentions this,
the apostle Paul, of course,
speaking to the believers in Corinth,
but we understand that he's speaking
about the resurrection
and speaking about the joy
of understanding the resurrection
because Christ is risen from the dead.
But he says this in verse 22
of 1 Corinthians 15,
for as in Adam, all die.
Why is it in Adam?
Because he took of it,
and of course we understand the seed
and what have you that has passed.
And we look here at what takes place.
He says, even so in Christ
shall all be made alive.
And we see in 1 Corinthians 15,
as well as Romans chapter number five,
the comparison between the first Adam
and the second Adam,
the Lord Jesus Christ.
And we find that as we look at that comparison,
that throughout the New Testament,
the event that we're looking at this evening
in Genesis chapter number three
is looked to as being factual,
historical event that took place.
This is not just some fable.
This is not just some story
that somebody came up with.
This is the actual record
of when sin entered the world.
And it's interesting
because if you understand
the first seven verses
of Genesis chapter number three,
it really unlocks for us
the rest of the Bible.
Because from Genesis chapter number three
all the way to Revelation chapter number 22,
what you begin to find
is what the consequences were
of this event that took place
in those first seven verses
and how it adversely affected mankind
and what God did to reconcile man to himself.
And from here all the way through the end,
you begin to look
and you begin to understand
that, listen, if Genesis three,
one through seven wasn't here,
a lot of it just wouldn't make sense.
Right?
Why?
Why did Jesus come?
Why did this happen?
Why did that?
Why the blood?
We have no idea.
But when we read these seven verses
and we understand the historical accuracy
of these verses
and we understand the way
in which the New Testament writers
often refer back to this event
that we're studying this evening,
we find that it was a catastrophic event
that caused much turmoil
and of course the death,
the spiritual separation from mankind
to the Creator.
I'm thankful that God is the Creator
often as we've studied here on Sunday evenings
through the book of Genesis,
we find and we've made reference
to the fact that not only is He Creator,
but He is Redeemer.
And it's important that we understand
the connection here this evening
because so often in our society this evening,
this thing of God being the Creator,
the truth of God being the Creator of all things
is being undermined
and what happens as you begin,
as you remove the Creator,
as you remove the account
that we're looking at this evening
of sin entering the world,
all of a sudden you have no need for a Redeemer.
But we indeed need a Redeemer.
Mankind needs to understand that truth
and the society in which we're living.
Listen, many people that we come into contact with
reminded of what the truth is in 2 Corinthians 4
that the God of this world
has blinded the minds of them that believe not.
There's much spiritual deception
that's taken place in our society today,
in our world as a whole
and we find that the truth of God's word
is so necessary that the light of the gospel
would shine in unto them.
And so we see the conversation,
we see the course of sin in verse number six.
Notice the cost of sin according to verse number seven.
The Bible says,
and the eyes of them both were opened
and they knew that they were naked
and they sewed fig leaves together
and made themselves aprons.
We find that immediately here
at the end of verse number six,
it says that she took the fruit thereof
and did eat and gave also unto her husband with her
and he did eat and the eyes of them both were opened.
What happened?
Their eyes were opened.
Remember, it's the tree of,
not the tree of life,
but it's the tree of knowledge of good and evil.
It was that tree that God said,
you cannot eat of that tree
and yet the woman through the temptation,
through the deception of the enemy,
through Satan, she saw it
and she understood that it was pleasant to be desired
and she took it and she ate it.
Their eyes are opened.
The Bible says that they realized that they were naked.
If you'll remember at the end of chapter number two,
we looked at the sanctity of marriage.
week, we understood that in verse number 25, the Bible says that they were both
naked, the man and his wife, and were not ashamed. But now their shame, because of
this nakedness, how do we know that? Because of their actions. Remember in
Genesis chapter number 2, there's still that stage of, or that state of
innocency. It's a perfect state, there's no sin that's entered in, but now in
chapter number 3, when that sin enters into the world, in verse number 6, their
eyes are open and they understand this, they realize this, and so what is it that
they did? They tried to cover their sin. Isn't that the natural process? We find that
they sewed fig leaves together and made themselves aprons. Really, the actions of
Adam and Eve, according to verse number 7, it was the works of their hands. And as
we go through chapter number 3, and we study over the next couple of Sunday
evenings, we'll find it to be understood at the end of the chapter, especially in
verses 21 through 24, that Adam and Eve would soon learn that their covering was
utterly inadequate. The works of their hands would not suffice. It was not
satisfactory. Amen? And we find that there was blood that was shed, for there were,
God made coats of skins and clothed them, according to verse number 21, and we
understand the indication of the shedding of blood according to that
verse of Scripture. We'll study that in more detail as we get to the end of
chapter number 3, but I want you to understand this evening, according to
verse number 7, that because of this sin that had entered in, they tried with the
works of their hands to cover themselves. It is utterly inadequate. Today, there are
people that are trying all sorts of things to cover their sin. The Bible says
that he that covereth his sin shall not prosper. Amen? There's only one
satisfactory, something that will satisfy the demands of a holy God, and
that is the blood of Christ. And we understand throughout the Old Testament
there was the blood of bulls and goats and so on and so forth that was shed,
seeking to show forth the Messiah who would one day come, and it was a shadow,
according to Hebrews 10, a shadow of good things to come. And it was through
the blood of Christ that was shed on the cross of Calvary that mankind could once
and for all understand the truth of redemption. We're not redeemed with
corruptible things, according to what Peter said, but we're redeemed with the
precious blood of Christ. And here we find in Genesis 3, verses 1 through 7, we
find here the high cost of sin. It was fellowship that was broken. You
understand that as you look into verse number 8 and you find that they're
hiding themselves from the presence of God, that fellowship that they had
enjoyed for whatever duration of time they enjoyed it was now broken because
of that sin. This evening, it's important for us to understand the cost of sin.
Someone said this, that sin will cost you more than you want to pay. I think that's
a pretty accurate statement, don't you? And this evening, as we look at Genesis
chapter number 3 and we see that conversation in those first five verses
and we find the course of sin, what a warning to us, because yes, we see the
cost of sin in verse number 7, but what a warning to us as to the work of the
enemy. Last week on Sunday morning, we dealt with neither give place to the
devil and we find here, as we mentioned several things about our adversary last
Sunday morning, but we find here again some of the tactics of the enemy.
Yea, hath God said. God wants us to know what he said, but Satan doesn't. Amen? God
wants us to be settled on what thus saith the Lord. He wants us to have a
working knowledge, if I could use that terminology, of his word. And we find
that he will flat-out deny what God has said. Ye shall not surely die. Well, it's
not gonna happen to me. I'm not gonna find myself in that place. Be not
deceived, right? The Bible is full of those types of statements. Be not
deceived. Be not deceived. What so ever man soweth, that shall he also reap. Amen?
It is a principle. It is a principle of God's word, sowing and reaping. By the
way, it's a positive and a negative principle. When we sow to the
spiritual, we'll reap of the spiritual. When we sow to the carnal, we'll reap of the
carnal. We understand that in Galatians 6. But here this evening, we find that he
then, at times, Satan, the adversary, will try to get us to believe that God is
trying to withhold something from us that's good for us. Can I tell you that
there was nothing from the tree that was mentioned here, the tree of
knowledge of good and evil, there was nothing from that tree that was good for
Adam and Eve. Amen? God was, God knowing all things, being
omniscient, being loving and merciful and gracious, God was trying in giving that
command. He was seeking to help Adam and Eve avoid that thing that would cause a
grave consequence. And this evening, God is not trying to keep something good
from you that you need. God is trying to protect you from something that will
hurt you. Amen? And we need to understand that from this text of scripture, sin
entered the world. As we continue through Genesis through over the next couple of
weeks, we'll look at some more of the judgments that are handed out and then
of course the work of God and in the lives of Adam and Eve at the end of the
chapter and that reconciliation that we would call it from those verses. Let's
pray together.