Exodus chapter 16, Exodus chapter number 16.
I'll read the first four verses by way of introduction
and we'll dig into the text this evening.
Exodus chapter number 16.
If you were here last week on Wednesday evening,
you'll recall that we examined part of Exodus chapter 9.
When we examined part of that passage,
it was dealing with the seventh plague.
And we talked about, as we looked at that portion of Scripture,
and we asked ourselves this question,
considered the thought, how do we respond to God?
God is faithful to give us truth,
and we find that even in that text of Scripture,
God gave truth to Moses.
He then delivers it to the people with regard to that seventh plague.
And it was very clear, man or beast that's in the field,
they're going to die when the hail comes,
and therefore, here's what you do, bring them in.
And we said that there were some that took heed,
there were others that regarded not the word of the Lord,
and of course, what happened?
Well, tomorrow, like God said, the hail came,
and any that were in the field died.
And we asked ourselves the question,
why would they respond that way?
And then we have to look ourselves in the mirror and say,
why do we respond sometimes in disobedience
to the clear instruction that God gives?
And we looked at that, dealing really with the Egyptians
and their response last week in chapter 9.
Look at chapter 16.
You may already be familiar with the text
just by mentioning it's Exodus 16.
It's the record that God gives us of manna.
And notice the Bible says in verse number 1,
And they took their journey from Elam,
and all the congregation of the children of Israel
came unto the wilderness of Sin,
which is between Elam and Sinai,
on the fifteenth day, the second month,
after their departing out of the land of Egypt.
And the whole congregation of the children of Israel
murmured against Moses and Aaron in the wilderness.
Does that please God? No.
Verse 3, And the children of Israel said unto them,
Would to God we had died by the hand of the Lord
in the land of Egypt, when we sat by the flesh pots,
and when we did eat bread to the full,
for ye have brought us forth into this wilderness
to kill this whole assembly with hunger.
Then said the Lord unto Moses,
Behold, I will rain bread from heaven for you,
when the people shall go out and gather
a certain rate every day, that I may prove them
whether they will walk in my law or no.
As we look at this text of Scripture,
we'll go down through verse number 28 this evening.
I've simply titled from verse number 4,
I will rain bread from heaven.
Tonight, as we look at this portion of Scripture,
we'll see how God's people responded to His instruction.
I believe this evening, and you've often heard me say it,
that our behavior really reveals what we believe.
We can say all day long that we believe X, Y, Z,
but the proof of what we truly believe is evidenced,
is demonstrated through how we behave,
through the things that we do.
We find that in the text of Scripture that is before us,
that God gives the record of this provision,
this manna from heaven.
Of course, we understand the Lord Jesus Christ,
and we won't have time this evening or Wednesday night
to deal with the truth of Jesus as being the bread of heaven,
the bread of life, and all of that.
But as we look contextually at Exodus 16
and really kind of continue the thought from last week
with how do we respond to God,
but then looking in this passage,
not at the Egyptians,
and we did ask the question last week,
this wasn't the first plague last week,
it was the seventh plague.
So they'd already witnessed the hand and power of God,
and yet, though it was the seventh plague,
there were some that still regarded not.
They didn't believe that it was actually going to happen.
Now we're looking at the children of Israel in Exodus 16,
and I want you to consider just a few things
by way of introduction this evening
when you consider all that they had witnessed firsthand.
They not only had the opportunity to see the ten plagues
and to experience the power of God through the plagues,
we understand that as we study the plagues
that there were even a portion of those plagues
where the Egyptians were impacted,
but the children of Israel were not impacted,
and God made that distinction,
and he said that he would on certain plagues,
and they had the opportunity to experience that.
Of course, we understand that they left Egypt
and they got to the Red Sea,
and what happens when they're at the Red Sea?
Well, very similar to what we read
in the text of Scripture by way of introduction
in Exodus chapter 16,
here they say,
you've brought us forth into the wilderness to kill us.
They had the same idea there.
It wasn't so much with hunger in that text of Scripture
as much as it was that there was the sea before them
and the Egyptians behind them,
but they still had and reached the same conclusion.
You brought us here that we would die.
There were not enough graves in Egypt, et cetera,
and so we find that the children of Israel,
they experienced being in that place,
and Pihahirath is where God led them to,
and then God miraculously parted the Red Sea,
and they witnessed that firsthand.
Not only did they see it with their eye,
but every one of them literally had to walk through
on dry ground.
Amen?
So they saw it, but they physically experienced it.
They walked through with walls of water on either side.
Can you imagine?
To see the power of God.
And then God closed up the waters,
and the Egyptians were destroyed.
And they were singing in Exodus 15
of all of God's greatness and His goodness
and all that He did,
and by the time you get to the end of chapter 15,
they find themselves in a place called Marah
where the water is bitter,
and what do they do?
They immediately complain.
And what does God do?
Well, He instructs Moses,
and He tells them take that wood
and throw it in that tree,
and the waters were made sweet,
and they were sustained.
Again, they got to see this.
And so as we look at Exodus chapter number 16
and we come to the place that we're at,
I want you to first see, number one,
the miraculous provision,
and we look here at the text
and we begin to see this miraculous provision,
and again, we've just went through
all that these people had experienced.
Can I say to you this evening
that we as the people of God,
we today not only have the opportunity
to read the entire canon of Scripture,
but we've been able to see God work
in our lives firsthand as well.
We sang this evening about God hearing
and answering prayer.
I hope tonight you've experienced
God answering prayer in your life.
I hope tonight you can look at your life
and you can see God's hand at work
and you can rejoice in what God has done.
We find that these children of Israel
that are here, this generation,
they've experienced all of this
wonderful work of God.
They've seen it firsthand.
They've experienced it,
but yet they come to a place
and they're hungry and they're murmuring.
The Bible says in verse number two
that the whole congregation
of the children of Israel
murmured against Moses and Aaron
in the wilderness.
It wasn't just a part of them.
It was all of them.
The whole congregation.
Can you imagine?
Oftentimes, when we talk about
spiritual leadership,
we'll reference the difficulties
in which Moses dealt with
on leading the children of Israel
and God adequately and appropriately
referred to the children of Israel
as being stiff-necked people,
and certainly they were.
Sometimes we can be stiff-necked too.
Amen?
Sometimes when we look at
the children of Israel,
we're real quick to be able
to criticize them
and to be able to look at
what they're doing and say,
how could they,
but then we stop short
of actually looking in the mirror
and saying, how does my behavior
actually mirror what they did?
And we look at the text of Scripture
and we see their complaining,
we see their murmuring,
and we find that God,
listen, our God is so gracious.
Isn't He so gracious?
The Bible says that
the children of Israel,
they complained in verse two
and verse three,
and they, in verse two,
it just simply summarizes
the fact that they murmured
against Moses and Aaron
in the wilderness,
and verse three kind of explains
in detail what they said,
and they were thinking back
to what they had
while they were in Egypt.
They quickly forgot
how they were crying out
while they were in Egypt,
were they not?
They were crying out for deliverance.
What did God say
when He showed up
and talked to Moses?
He said, I've heard their cry.
Amen?
So what do they remember in Egypt?
They only remember the good things,
quote unquote.
And so they're thinking,
they're saying, oh,
that we were back there,
and had they died
in the land of Egypt
when we sat by the flesh pots
and did eat bread to the full.
And then they're talking
about this hunger.
So what does God say
in verse number four?
Notice the miraculous provision.
God makes a promise
in verse number four.
Then said the Lord unto Moses,
Behold, I will reign bread
from heaven for you.
Now, I want you to just consider
for a moment
Moses hearing these words.
I will reign bread
from heaven for you.
And to begin to think
for just a moment,
we read and we understand,
and we've been taught
maybe for many different times
as we've walked
this Christian journey.
We understand manna.
We understand what God did.
But can you imagine Moses
hearing these words from God
when God says,
I'm going to reign bread
from heaven for you.
We could ask ourselves
the question,
how's that going to work?
How's that going to happen?
What's the process?
And we find that God's
making this promise.
The reality is that
God can do whatever
he wants to do
however he wants to do it.
The only thing that God is bound by is his word,
and he's the one that gave his word,
so he has put things within his word that would bind him,
but that's it.
We find that the unbelief of God's people,
often on the case of the children of Israel,
limited the Holy One of Israel,
but we find that God says,
"'I will reign bread from heaven for you.
"'The people shall go out
"'and gather a certain rate every day.
"'Notice this, that I may prove them
"'whether they will walk in my law or no.'"
And so we find this miraculous provision
that God makes this promise to Moses
and then to be delivered to the children of Israel,
and that God is going to do this thing.
We understand that it ended up lasting for 40 years.
Can you imagine?
Again, this is something that most of us
on a Wednesday night crowd,
we know about the manna.
We're like, yeah, yeah, manna.
This is miraculous.
God is providing for his people.
So we see the miraculous provision.
I want you to see number two,
the meticulous process.
We find in the New Testament,
in the book of 1 Corinthians,
that God tells us that our God,
he says that all things are to be done decently
and in order.
Our God is a God of order.
Our God is a God of detail.
If you read,
if you continue reading through the book of Exodus
and you begin to read about the tabernacle
and all of the explicit detail that is provided
with regard to the construction of the tabernacle,
I mean, it is extremely detailed.
You go throughout the scriptures
and you find that our God is a God of detail.
I mentioned on Sunday evening about worship,
and I said all that's called worship today
is not really worship,
and man oftentimes thinks they can approach God
on their terms,
but yet God has meticulously explained to us
in his word how we're to approach him.
And here in the text of scripture,
we find that there's a meticulous process
that they're to follow.
In verses four and five,
God gives a very general overview,
a summary if you will,
and then provides greater details in verses eight through 19.
Notice in verse five and six,
it says,
and it shall come to pass that on the sixth day,
they shall prepare that which they bring in,
and it shall be twice as much as they gather daily.
And so we notice that in verse number four,
it said that they should gather a certain rate every day
that I may prove them
whether they will walk in my law or no,
and it shall come to pass, verse five,
that on the sixth day,
they shall prepare that which they bring in,
and it shall be twice as much as they gather daily.
And so then in verses six and seven,
the Bible says that Moses and Aaron
said unto all the children of Israel,
it even,
then you shall know that the Lord hath brought you out
from the land of Egypt,
and in the morning,
then you shall see the glory of the Lord,
for that he heareth your murmuring against the Lord,
and what are we that ye murmur against us?
I want you to just on a side note this evening,
understand that in verse number seven,
God heard their murmuring,
and that in verse number two,
the Bible says that the whole congregation
of the children of Israel murmured against who?
Moses and Aaron,
but what does Moses say in verse number seven,
that he, God, the Lord,
he heareth your murmuring against the Lord?
Against the Lord.
We find that it says,
and what are we that ye murmur against us?
Moses understood his place,
and as he led the children of Israel,
he was simply following God's leadership.
And we come to verse number seven,
it says in the morning,
then you shall see the glory of the Lord,
or verse eight, excuse me,
and Moses said,
this shall be when the Lord shall give you in the evening,
flesh to eat,
and in the morning,
bread to the full,
for that the Lord heareth your murmurings,
which you murmur against him,
and what are we?
Your murmurings are not against us,
but against the Lord.
So in verses nine through 19,
we see that these details are being provided
for this meticulous process.
Again, this is a familiar passage of scripture,
many of us would know this,
we could answer the questions,
but I want you to look at it,
in verse nine, it says,
and Moses spake unto Aaron,
say unto all the congregation of the children of Israel,
come near before the Lord,
for he hath heard your murmurings.
And it came to pass,
as Aaron spake unto the whole congregation
of the children of Israel,
that they looked toward the wilderness,
and behold, the glory of the Lord appeared in the cloud,
and the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,
verse 12, I have heard the murmuring
of the children of Israel.
Speak unto them, saying,
at even ye shall eat flesh,
and in the morning ye shall be filled with bread.
And notice this,
and ye shall know that I am the Lord your God.
In verse 13, it came to pass
that at even the quails came up and covered the camp,
and in the morning the dew lay round about the host,
and when the dew that lay was gone up,
behold, upon the face of the wilderness
there lay a small round thing,
as small as the hoarfrost on the ground.
When the children of Israel saw it,
they said one to another, it is manna,
for they wist not what it was.
And Moses said unto them,
this is the bread which the Lord hath given you to eat.
This was the provision, the promise of verse number four,
I will reign bread from heaven for you.
This is the fulfillment.
This is the bread which the Lord hath given you to eat.
And then notice the details.
This is the thing which the Lord hath commanded.
So notice, in verse number 16,
Moses is making it very plain.
This is not my commandment to you.
This is what God has commanded.
And it's always important for us to understand
that Moses, he was a faithful minister.
Moses had been entrusted of the Lord
to take a message from God and to deliver to the people,
and Moses was faithful to do that.
We find that here, that as Moses begins to instruct them
and to provide them with the details,
he says that this is the thing
which the Lord hath commanded.
Notice verse 16, gather of it, of the manna,
according to his eating, an omer for every man,
according to the number of your persons,
take ye every man for them which are in his tents.
The children of Israel did so,
and gathered some more, some less,
and they did meet it with an omer.
Then he that gathered much had nothing over,
and he that gathered little had no lack.
They gathered every man according to his eating.
And so we find that Moses provides additional instruction
in verse number 19.
Notice very plainly, and Moses said,
let no man leave of it till the morning.
So we find that on day one through day five,
they were to collect,
they were to go gather enough manna for each day.
We find that he makes it very clear
that they're to keep none until the morning.
In verse 19, let no man leave of it till the morning.
And so we find, again, is there anything complicated
about these instructions?
It's a meticulous process.
We find that our God is a God of order.
Our God is a God of details.
And God says to the children of Israel through Moses,
here's the process, here's how you're to go out and gather.
Day one through day five, here are the instructions.
And so we find that in verse number,
skip down if you will,
and we'll look here at verse number 20.
Look at 20.
Notwithstanding, they hearken not unto Moses,
but some of them left of it until the morning,
and it bred worms and stank,
and Moses was wroth with them.
And we notice in verse number 21,
and they gathered it every morning,
every man according to his eating.
And when the sun waxed hot, it melted,
and it came to pass that on the sixth day,
they gathered twice as much bread,
two omers for one man,
and all the rulers of the congregation came and told Moses.
So notice in verse 22,
this is doing exactly what God had said in verse number five,
and it shall come to pass that on the sixth day,
they shall prepare that which they bring in,
and it shall be twice as much as they gather daily.
But there were some, the rulers of the congregation,
they came to Moses and they said in verse number 23,
this is that, and he said unto them,
so they brought the report,
this is that which the Lord hath said.
Tomorrow is the rest of the holy Sabbath unto the Lord.
Bake that which you will bake today,
and seethe that you will seethe,
and that which remaineth over,
lay up for you to be kept until the morning.
And they laid it up till the morning as Moses bade,
and it did not stink, neither was there any worm therein.
And so we find that as we would look
at the meticulous process,
and we'd understand these details,
and we'd understand that day six
is different than days one through five.
And I want you to consider with me
that as God gives this instruction,
and I want you to consider being the children of Israel here
in receiving this instruction.
Again, there's nothing confusing,
there's nothing complicated,
but we find that on days one through five,
if I gather enough just for today,
I'm not supposed to store it up,
I'm not supposed to let it stay until morning,
but then on day six,
I'm supposed to go out and gather twice as much,
and I am supposed to keep it until the morning
because I'm not gonna go gather on the Sabbath.
And again, if we lean on our own understanding,
I want you to consider those that did gather extra
and left it until the morning,
what happened?
Well, it bred worms and it stank.
That's what the Bible tells us.
So all of a sudden,
we can start leaning on our own understanding and saying,
well, if it happened on day three,
then how is it not gonna happen on day six?
Right?
We begin to insert our own thoughts
and our own reasoning and our own logic into,
and we try to go through the process of,
well, I know God said this, but.
I know this is what God said,
but you don't understand my situation.
but you don't understand my circumstances.
I know this is what God said,
but we're in 2025 and they said I had to do this
and this responsibility.
You understand what I'm saying this evening?
And so we come to the portion of scripture
and we find that on day six,
they were to have enough for two days.
And God had made it clear that they were to store it up and that it would not spoil and
they would have provision for that seventh day.
God knew what they needed and God would provide what they needed.
But they would not go out and gather on the Sabbath.
And so we find that there's a meticulous process that's laid out.
Sometimes when we go to the Bible, we look at the scriptures and say, they're so detailed.
And I think that's a good thing.
Because God provides for us as his people, what he expects for us to do.
What it is that pleases him.
You know, have you ever gotten some instructions and you've said, these things are not worth
the ink and paper that they used?
Because they're so vague.
I don't know.
I mean, I've taken instructions before and jokingly with Joseph, I've taken the instructions
And I've pulled them open something like this and I'll hold them like, well, maybe it's
supposed to be this way.
Like, cause it's just, it makes no sense.
And the reality is that when we come to the word of God, God gives us clarity.
God provides us with the details.
There's no, nothing vague within the text of scripture that we're looking at here in
Exodus 16.
And we find this meticulous process.
We could ask ourselves the question, could God have given them enough on day one that
they could have had it for the entire week?
Sure he could.
Could he have given it enough on day one that they could have stored it up for an entire
month?
Sure.
God could do whatever he wants, but he gave them a particular process and it was meticulous
and it was, it was detailed.
And God, as we look at the text of scripture, he was doing two things.
We notice in verse number 12, at the end of the verse, he says, and you shall know that
I am the Lord your God.
So God is helping to develop his people.
He's building their faith.
He's helping them to understand that he is able to provide for them.
He is able to meet their needs.
He knows what their needs are.
And though they're murmuring and though they're complaining and they're saying that they're
hungry, that God is able and he is proving to them that you shall know that I am the
Lord your God.
But there's a second thing that's taking place in the text of scripture and it really brings
us to our final thought this evening.
We look at the miraculous provision, the meticulous process, but I want you to notice number three,
the master's proving.
Notice back in verse number four, the Bible says, as this promise is given, then said
the Lord unto Moses, behold, I will rain bread from heaven for you.
The people shall go out and gather a certain rate every day.
And then notice this phrase, that I may prove them, that I may prove them, whether they
will walk in my law or no.
Yes, God was making it clear to them, you shall know that I am the Lord your God, according
to verse number 12.
But we find that within the text of scripture in Exodus 16, that God is proving his people.
I wonder this evening, there's some times in which God's proving us as his people, a
test, a trial.
Are we going to, notice when he says, whether they will walk in my law or no.
Will they trust me?
Will they obey me?
Will they follow me?
Will they lean on their own understanding?
Will they rely on some other means, some other, what will they do?
And we notice in the text of scripture, when we look at the master's proving, that he says
that I may prove them, and then notice, we looked at it a moment ago, but notice back
in verse number 20, that right on the heels of God saying through Moses, let no man leave
of it till the morning.
In verse number 20, the Bible says, notwithstanding, they hearken not unto Moses.
So when they hearken not unto Moses, truly, who were they not obeying?
God.
Right?
Well, we agree with that.
So they're not obeying God and the Bible says, but some of them, thankfully, not all of them
in verse number two, it was the whole congregation that murmured against Moses and Aaron and
God heard their murmurings.
He was not pleased with that, but we find in verse number 20, it says, but some of them
left of it until the morning.
So what does their behavior reveal?
Did they believe God or no?
Did they trust God or no?
What would be the motivation for keeping some, keeping extra, what would be the motivation?
Well, is it really going to be available tomorrow?
Is God really going to, is God going to really provide it tomorrow?
Am I going to go out there and is there going to be manna?
Maybe there's a motivation of, I really don't want to go out there and have to collect it
tomorrow.
It's hot.
It was hot today, wasn't it?
It's going to be hot tomorrow.
Say, man, I don't want to go out there and collect it.
I want the ease.
I don't know what all the motivations were, but we find that there were some that disobeyed.
There were some that kept it until the morning.
And I want you to notice, and again, you know this, but notice it says that it bred worms
and stank.
Now, could God have prevented that from happening?
We know that he could because he did on day six, correct?
But God purposefully, on days one through five, he gave them the instruction, you gather
enough for one day, and if you gather more and you store it up, you're not supposed to
do that.
So what happens?
Well, they wake up.
Can you imagine?
Have you ever opened up a package of something that's spoiled?
Have you ever opened up a package of flour or meal and there's worms in it?
Has anyone ever done that before?
It's kind of disgusting, is it not?
And you open it, have you ever had something that was moldy?
You had it in the cabinet somewhere and you maybe forgot about it and you go to open it
and you're like, oh yeah, we're not having that for lunch.
No way.
The Bible says that it bred worms and it stank.
Now, I want you to think about the immediate response of those people.
Do you think they would be interested in keeping extra tomorrow?
I wouldn't, right?
So God is proving them, he's letting them know that I am the Lord your God, but he's
also proving them whether they will walk in my law or no.
Listen, I'm thankful that God is gracious and merciful.
God didn't strike them dead for disobeying.
He just allowed that which they kept that they were not supposed to keep to spoil, to
breed worms and to stink.
In this evening, our God is long-suffering toward us, but I want you to understand that
our God wants us to walk in his ways.
He wants us to walk in his ways.
He wants us to obey him.
We ended our text last Wednesday evening by going to Acts and looking at the situation
with Ananias and Sapphira and the impact that it had on the church.
And I asked this question at the end of the service last Wednesday night, and I prefaced
it by saying I'm thankful that God's not working that way still today, but could you
imagine if people were still falling dead because they lied to God, could you imagine
how that would change our behavior?
I think it would have a huge impact on how we live day by day, on how we honor the Lord,
on how we pay very close attention to every jot and tittle, because every word is pure
and it's in there for a reason, amen?
God wants us to have it.
He wants us to know it.
And so we find that it bred worms and stank and Moses was wroth with them, and we find
that as we continue and we look at the master's proving, so we see on days one through five
that we don't know the number, but some of them disobeyed and they kept it till morning.
And then we come to verse number 25, and the Bible says that Moses said, eat that today,
for today is the Sabbath unto the Lord, for today you shall not find it, the manna, in
the field.
Verse 26, six days you shall gather it, but on the seventh day, which is the Sabbath,
in it there shall be none.
And I want you to notice in verse 27, and it came to pass that there went out some of
the people.
We saw that in verse 20, that some of them kept it until the morning, and verse 27, that
some of the people on the seventh day were to gather and they found none.
So we see in verse number 27, again, this process of proving, the master's proving,
so there were some that didn't believe that they were to gather twice as much on day six,
and that it would not spoil that God's provision for them for the Sabbath would be that they
would gather it on day six, and that they would store it up.
It says in verse 23, bake that which you will bake today and seethe that you will seethe,
and that which remaineth over, lay up for you to be kept until the morning.
And he tells them, eat that today, and verse 25, for today is a Sabbath unto the Lord.
Today you shall not find it in the field.
Now I want you to just use your sanctified imagination.
just for a moment.
And I want you to consider verse 27
as the Bible says that it came to pass.
So we all wake up on the Sabbath
and we all wake up that day.
And I want you to consider
as you use your sanctified imagination
that you look out of your tent door
and you see some people walking out in the field.
What are they doing?
Well, they're looking for manna.
But what are they finding?
They're finding nothing.
I'd hate to be one of the people
walking out there looking for manna.
Because not only does God know that I've disobeyed,
but a whole lot of other people know that I've disobeyed.
Amen?
See, sometimes the Bible says the deceitfulness of sin
in the book of Hebrews.
Sometimes you think you've covered your sin,
but the reality is that not only does God know about it,
but a whole lot of other people know about it too.
And that's just a sad situation.
Why?
Because God wants us to walk in his ways,
to walk in his ways.
We could look at the text of scripture
before us this evening,
and we could ask the question,
why does it have to be this way?
And I would simply say, because God said so.
God could have given any type of provision he wanted to,
he could have provided in any manner.
How did he provide for Elijah?
Well, he had the ravens come and feed him, right?
I mean, God can do what he wants to do,
how he wants to do it.
But we find in the text of scripture
that God is going to provide miraculously,
he's gonna provide for his people,
and he's gonna give them a meticulous process
on how they are going to go and to gather that provision.
While he's providing for them miraculously,
while he's detailed to them the process for gathering,
at the very same time, he's proving them.
He's proving them.
And the proving of them, the testing, the trying,
is whether they will walk in my law or no.
This evening, we don't go out and gather any manna.
But we're to walk by faith.
We're to walk in obedience to the truth of God's word.
We're to be doers of the word and not hearers only.
We're to take and apply truth into our lives.
We read the book of Ephesians,
and we find how that the Bible tells us often
in that book about walking and how important our walk is.
In fact, turn there, if you will, very quickly.
And I want you to see, we'll look at just a couple
of verses here in the book of Ephesians.
And I want you to see that in verse number,
chapter number four is where we'll look to begin.
But I want you to see in verse number one,
Paul is writing here to the believers in Ephesus,
those that have been saved,
those who have trust at Christ as their savior.
We read of that in the first three chapters.
We come to chapter four, and he says,
I therefore the prisoner of the Lord.
Notice what he says, beseech you that you walk worthy
of the vocation wherewith you're called.
God wants us to walk worthy.
God wants us to walk in obedience.
He tells them as we go to verse 17 in chapter number four,
he says, this I say, therefore, in testifying the Lord
that you henceforth walk not as other Gentiles walk
in the vanity of their mind.
I believe it was last year.
I'd have to look specifically in my notes
to see when it was that we did the series,
but we did a series here on Wednesday evening
of doing what we ought to do.
And there's a number of statements in the New Testament
that men ought to, that we ought to do this and do that,
and so on and so forth.
And we looked at a number of those things
from walk worthy, praise God,
and at the end of first Thessalonians,
at the end of second Thessalonians,
and we looked at all of those messages
of what is God telling us and how is he instructing us?
And God wants us to walk in his ways.
And he was proving the children of Israel in Exodus 16.
It's a passage of scripture that reveals to us the power
and the ability of our God to provide for his people.
But it's also a passage of scripture
in which it reveals to us that there are some that obey
and there are some that disobey.
And as quickly as we can look at the Egyptians
in Exodus chapter number nine from last Wednesday evening,
and we can look at their disobedience
and critique and criticize them,
we come now to Exodus 16 and we see that God's people,
after experiencing so many things,
they hear specifically the details, the process.
And yet, there were a portion that stored up
and they left it until the morning.
And then there were some that on the Sabbath went out
looking for manna.
And so this evening, we begin to look at our own lives
and we see all that God has done for us,
all that God has revealed to us,
not only in his word,
but what he's taught us in our own lives.
You know, the Bible says to whom much is given,
much is required.
Is that what the Bible tells us?
And I believe tonight that God has given us much.
And we begin to just live our lives
and make decisions based on buts.
I know what God said, but.
We're living on dangerous ground.
And God has long suffering to us
and I'm so thankful for his grace and his mercy
and his long suffering toward us.
But I want you to understand that the Bible says,
whom the Lord loveth, he chasteneth.
Whom the Lord loveth, he chasteneth.
He always does it for our good.
He always does it because he loves us.
But he does it because he wants us to walk in his ways.
He doesn't want us to lean on our own understanding.
He wants us to trust, to live by faith.
For 40 years,
children of Israel would have had to follow this process.
They would have to go out and gather up the manna.
You know, God was faithful to provide.
And God's been faithful to us.
He's never failed you and he never will.
He's never failed me and he never will.
And so this evening,
we look at this portion of scripture
and we see that God says that I may prove them.
Will we walk in his ways or no?
Will we obey him or no?
Tonight, I hope that our choice would be, yes, Lord, yes.
I wanna see those details,
the meticulous process, every jot and every tittle,
and I wanna obey all of it
because I want your blessing.
I want your blessing.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
Thank you for loving us.
Thank you for your word.
I thank you for the truth contained therein.
And as we can look at examples from the Old Testament,
we find that Paul said this
as he's writing to the church in Corinth,
that they were written as in samples to us
for our learning, for our admonition.
And Lord, I pray that we would take heed
to what we read in the Old Testament account
of the children of Israel and their behavior,
and that we would analyze and evaluate our own lives
and determine, are we walking in your way or no?
Lord, we know deep down,
we know your Holy Spirit convicts us.
You're so gracious to deal with us as individuals.
You're so long-suffering.
And I pray, God, that we would be responsive to you,
that we would just determine
that we're gonna live according to your word.
Bless our time of prayer.
We pray that through all that's said and done,
that we'd be glorified for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Amen.