schedule on Sunday, and then also the following Sunday
is Resurrection Sunday, Easter Sunday,
and a wonderful opportunity to be able to pass out
some of these invitations, let people know
that we're having special services.
7 a.m. sunrise service, 8 a.m. breakfast,
9 a.m. morning worship, and then we'll be done for the day.
So seven, eight, and nine, and while I was visiting
with Don this afternoon, someone came in the room
and I was actually reading scripture to him
as they walked in, and they apologized for interrupting,
and I said, that's okay, we're just reading the Bible,
and I was able to talk with her for just a moment,
and said, can I give an invitation to our church?
And I had some of these with us, and she said,
oh man, I need to get back to church,
it's been a long time since I've been at church,
and I said, well, Sunday's a good time to come back, amen?
And so give those out, people will come, Lord willing,
we'll look forward to an opportunity,
pray that we have good weather, and the Lord has blessed,
we've had some chilly sunrise services,
where people are covered up with blankets
and all that sort of thing, but we'll be right out
on the blacktop over here at 7 a.m.,
and sing some songs, look at the scriptures,
and it's always a wonderful time of fellowship.
If the weather is not cooperative,
we will pray somewhat quickly outside before we come inside
and just have the service here at 7 a.m.,
and so that will just all be dependent upon the weather.
Numbers 13 and 14, and we've been looking
at this portion of scripture, these two chapters,
over the last couple of weeks,
and this will be our final week
looking at these particular chapters
as we're dealing with the subject matter here in 2026
of a longing to see God work.
And I'm thankful that our God has done great things,
thou hast, we see that terminology
throughout the word of God, the things that God has done,
but we also know that he's still sitting upon his throne,
he's still alive and well, and he has all power,
he's got as much power today as he's ever had,
and he's just an amazing God,
and we have the opportunity and the privilege
to be able to serve him and to see him work,
and I'm thankful for what he's done,
but I'm thankful for what he's doing,
and it's a blessing to see God answer prayer
and work in hearts and lives,
and the growth of individual spiritual growth,
and it's just exciting to see how God is working.
We've understood as we've had this really thought
throughout 2026, we've understood that it is the unbelief,
the doubt of God's people that will limit God,
and the God who has all power,
the God who can do all things,
is limited when his people do not have faith.
In fact, we find that the book in Psalm 78,
the Bible says that they limited the Holy One of Israel,
it was because of their doubt and their unbelief
that they limited what God was going to do
or what God intended to do.
We find there in the book of Matthew
that the Bible says that Jesus
did not many mighty works there,
and it says this because of their unbelief.
It wasn't that, there wasn't a need,
it wasn't a fact that there were no one,
no individuals there that needed healing,
no, it wasn't that,
it was the fact that they did not believe.
And we understand that the disciples,
after they were there privately discussing
with the Lord Jesus Christ,
after he showed his power over that dumb spirit
and healed that man,
they said, why could not we cast him out?
And Jesus said, because of your unbelief.
And we've had the opportunity
to look at these two chapters in Numbers 13 and 14,
and the reason that we've come here
is because we see in these two chapters
the doubt and the unbelief of the people of God,
the children of Israel,
and we can look at this historical event in account
and we can learn from it
and we can apply truth in our lives.
And we said this as we began studying
this three-part kind of miniseries
is that the first thing we must do
is identify what causes doubt in my life,
what causes you, what causes me,
what causes us to doubt, to not believe God.
It's not because he's failed, amen,
because he never fails, he always is able,
he always does what he says he will do.
And so what is it that causes us to doubt?
We noticed as we've studied
through the portion of scripture,
it's when the people got their eyes,
those 10 bad spies as we refer to them,
as they got their eyes,
they said, nevertheless,
oh, the land, it's a good land,
nevertheless, there are walled cities
and there are giants there,
the people are strong and we are not able
and they reached a conclusion
based upon what they observed
and their doubt was impacting every area of their lives.
We said this, we wanna be able to see
what causes us to doubt,
but then we also wanted to understand
the consequences of doubt.
What are the consequences?
I said this last week that doubt and unbelief,
it's not benign, it's not something that's harmless,
in fact, it's extremely harmful,
not only does it limit God,
but it displeases God.
We've said that doubt and unbelief,
it's sin and it must be dealt with
and we understand that as we look
at this portion of scripture
that there were 12 spies that went out
and there were 10 that had unbelief,
that had doubt, but those 10
influenced the entire nation of Israel.
The Bible begins in chapter 14
by talking about in all the congregation,
in all the children of Israel,
because of 10 people that did not believe God,
we find that the entire nation
was ready to go back to Egypt.
Man, your doubt, my doubt,
it doesn't just affect me,
we don't live in a bubble.
Our doubt and our unbelief affects other people
and we dealt with that last week.
Today, as we look at this portion of scripture
and more into the 14th chapter,
I really wanna talk about how we can conquer doubt,
conquering doubt and how can we have greater faith?
How is it as we think about the disciples
and we've referenced in Luke 17,
where they say, Lord, increase our faith.
How is it that we can take the father
of that man that was healed,
that we mentioned that the disciples
had that private conversation with the Lord,
but yet that man said, Lord, I believe,
help thou mine unbelief.
How is it that we can be like the church
in Thessalonica when the Bible says of them
in the second letter that their faith
grow with exceedingly?
See, this evening, it's important
that each of us would be transparent with God.
He knows anyway, amen?
You can't deceive him, I can't deceive him.
You might be able to deceive your neighbor,
your spouse, your coworker,
but you can't deceive God.
In fact, you can deceive yourself.
Self-deception is the worst deception.
When you're not being a doer of the word,
the Bible says in that same verse,
deceiving your own selves.
And so we find that as we begin
to look at this portion of scripture
and try to figure out how can I conquer doubt,
the reality is I'm not gonna even care
to know how to conquer it if I don't acknowledge
that there are times in my life that I deal with doubt.
There are times in our lives that something happens,
and when that something happens,
it rattles us, it shakes us.
We're humans.
God knows our frame.
We're but dust.
He knows our frame.
And there are things that you will encounter in life,
there are things that I will encounter in life
that sometimes those things just shake us to our very core.
Sometimes it's a medical diagnosis.
Sometimes it may be something with regard
to financial difficulties, employment situations.
It could be something with children or grandchildren.
The list could go on and on.
But what I'm saying this evening
is that there are times in life
that something happens that just rattles us.
And it can cause us to have doubt
that just creeps in and rises up and can overwhelm us.
As we look at the portion of scripture,
I wanna focus specifically
on Joshua and Caleb this evening.
Beginning in verse number six of chapter 14,
the Bible says that Joshua,
it says, and Joshua the son of Nun
and Caleb the son of Jephunneh,
which were of them that searched the land,
rent their clothes.
Why is it that they responded in the way that they did?
Well, because they heard the people
complaining and murmuring.
They heard the people, those 10,
that said, we are not able,
and all the congregation is just murmuring
and they're complaining.
It would be better for us to have stayed in Egypt
and all of these things we've come here
and our children, our wives,
they're gonna be a prey
and let us go back to Egypt in verse number four.
And Joshua and Caleb hear all of this, they're there,
and they were part of that group,
those 12 that went in to spy the land.
And the Bible says that they rent their clothes
in verse seven, and they spake
unto all the company of the children of Israel,
saying, the land which we pass through to search it
is an exceeding good land.
By the way, the 10 spies acknowledged that as well.
They say that in verse 27 of chapter 13,
that it was surely it floweth with milk and honey,
and this is the fruit of it.
I mean, they saw the land, they say, nevertheless,
and they start looking at the obstacles,
but we find that Joshua and Caleb,
as they're speaking to the people,
they say that the land which we pass through to search it
is an exceeding good land.
And then notice in verse number eight,
if the Lord delight in us,
then he will bring us into this land and give it us,
a land which floweth with milk and honey.
Do you notice the perspective in verse number eight
of Joshua and Caleb?
They do not say that we are able,
they say that if God delights in us,
and by the way, what is it that causes God to delight in us?
Faith, belief, right?
The Bible says that without faith,
it is impossible to please him,
for he that cometh to God must believe that he is
and that he is a rewarder of them that diligently seek him.
And so this idea, if the Lord delight in us,
if God is pleased with us,
you know when God is pleased with us?
When we obey him.
When is God pleased with us?
When we trust him.
When we live by faith.
And so we find that Joshua and Caleb,
they try to still the people and they say,
if the Lord delight in us,
notice he will bring us into this land.
Joshua and Caleb did not have the perspective
that they would be the ones that would be able to conquer
and enter the land on their own merit,
on their own ability.
No, they recognized the promise of God.
By the way, in chapter 13 in verse number two,
it was God that said to Moses,
get these men together,
send them out to the land that I will give thee.
And I said this a couple of weeks ago,
that when those 10 spies said we are not able,
that it was never about them,
it was always about God.
It was always about what God promised.
And in your life and in my life,
it's always about bringing glory to God.
And we find here that he says,
if the Lord delight in us,
then he will bring us into this land
and give it us a land which floweth with milk and honey.
Notice verse nine,
only rebel not ye against the Lord,
neither fear ye the people of the land,
for they are bred for us,
their defenses departed from them,
and the Lord is with us, fear them not.
Fear had gripped their hearts.
What they saw impacted how they were responding.
They saw walled cities,
they saw mighty people,
they saw the sons of Anak, the giants,
and they said, we are not able.
They had their eyes on the wrong thing.
And so when we look at Joshua and Caleb here
and we understand what's taking place
and we see the perspective of these individuals,
I want you to understand this evening
that they had the same quote unquote facts.
They saw the same things,
but they kept their eyes on the Lord.
They recognized that God had given a promise.
They recognized that God was going to do
what God said he would do.
And so as we begin to think about Joshua and Caleb
and their perspective here in these few verses of scripture
and really contrast it with the other 10 spies
and looking at this idea of what causes me to doubt,
what are the consequences of doubt,
but then how can I conquer doubt?
It's very simple this evening,
there's nothing complicated about the message.
Number one, get into the Bible.
You say, well, I already know that.
You know how many people know that but don't do that?
You know how many times somebody faces a trial,
an obstacle, a difficulty,
and instead of running to God's word,
they run to people, they run wherever.
They don't run to the Bible.
So then faith cometh by hearing
and hearing by the word of God.
How am I gonna have my faith increase?
I need to get into God's word.
Someone said just yesterday,
I was overhearing a conversation
and someone was mentioning something about some obstacle
and what have you and the individual responded and said,
did they ever think about praying?
You know, sometimes we have this unique privilege of prayer.
And sometimes prayer is almost treated like a last resort
instead of a first response.
We try this, we try that, we do all these things
and we, oh, you know, maybe we should pray.
There's a priority placed upon prayer in 1 Timothy 2,
first of all, prayer and supplications,
this priority that's on prayer.
And so we get into God's word.
And as I get into God's word, here's what happens.
As I get into God's word, you know what happens?
I learn more about God.
Because it's God's word that reveals who God is.
How can I know God apart from God's word?
If we were to go around the room this evening
and ask for individuals to share testimony
or to make reference to some of the attributes of God,
the reality is that what you and what I know
to be true about God is only because we have this book.
How do you know that God is faithful?
Because God told us he's faithful.
No, he's demonstrated it.
How do we know that God has all power?
How do we know that God is holy?
How do we know that God is a God who forgives?
How do we know that he, you start going down the list
and you say, man, so when I get into the Bible,
what happens is I start learning more about God.
And as I'm learning more about God, guess what's happening?
My faith is increasing, why?
Because our God is great.
Our God is amazing.
There's no one like him.
There's nothing like him.
And we find that he alone is worthy.
And as we get to that place where our perspective,
our view, our understanding of God's greatness increases,
then my faith at the same time increases.
Because I know the all powerful God.
I know the one who knows all things.
And as I study the scriptures,
as I get into the word of God,
and as I just kind of meditate on who God is,
the reality this evening is I think
that if I were to poll each of you
as you came in here this evening,
if I gave John a task of having a clipboard there
and said, John, every time somebody walks in tonight,
I want you to ask them, is God great?
Yes or no?
I would hope that every single one of us
when you walked in would have said yes.
I would hope that not one amongst us would say no.
No, we know great is the Lord and greatly to be praised.
Right, but here's the reality.
As great as God is to you today,
he's far greater because you cannot comprehend
and I cannot comprehend how great our God is.
He's an infinite God and we're finite people.
My mind cannot possibly conceive how great our God is.
You just start reading Genesis chapter number one,
the record of the creation, wow.
Let there be light, there's light.
You read where the Bible says that he made the stars also.
I mean, just almost like it's an afterthought.
He made the stars also.
But then you read in the book of Psalms
and you read that the Bible tells us
that he calls all of them by their name.
Billions, you can't count them all.
And God just, it says, and he made the stars also.
And so when I get into the Bible,
when I get into God's word,
I'm learning more about who God is.
I'm learning more about what God's will is.
See, for these people in numbers 13 and 14,
what was God's will for them?
Well, God's will for them was to go into the land.
They did not fulfill God's law, God's will, excuse me,
because they got their eyes on the obstacles
and what happens sometimes is we do not run to the Bible
in the time of doubt and unbelief
and we have some obstacles that come.
Listen, I'm thankful that Nehemiah didn't give up
with the first obstacle.
I'm thankful that Paul didn't go back
after the first obstacle on the first missionary journey
and say, well, you know, I know the Holy Ghost
said separate unto me Saul and Barnabas for the work
whereunto I have called them,
but like, there's like, they don't want us there.
No, they just kept on going to the next town.
They just kept going preaching the gospel.
They knew what God's will was.
And for us this evening, as we get into the Bible,
as we get into the word of God,
we're able to understand what is God's will for me?
What is God's will for us?
What is God trying to do in this era of human history?
We find that as we get into the word of God,
we learn more about his works, his wonderful works.
Listen, when you read about the crossing of the Red Sea,
does it do anything for you?
Or is it just like a, yeah, I know that.
Really, we can take our own spiritual, like, temperature.
When we read the scriptures, is it alive to us?
Is it like, man, this is amazing, miraculous, God did this.
Or is it just like, yeah, I've read this, I know this,
like, but what about my, no, God's word
is supposed to build our faith.
And it will if we approach it properly.
We get to see God's works.
Get your, get into God's word.
Number two, get your eyes on Jesus.
We understand the truth of Hebrews chapter 12,
looking unto Jesus, the author and finisher of our faith.
And we understand the instruction
that we're to look to God.
And yes, as I mentioned a moment ago,
that Caleb and Joshua had the same facts
that the other 10 spies had, yet they believed God.
They determined to keep their eyes on the Lord.
They weren't so.
consumed with the walled cities,
they weren't so consumed with the sons of Anak.
No, they had their eyes on the Lord.
But I want you to understand this evening
that it's a choice.
Where you look in the time of a difficulty is a choice.
Listen to the words of the psalmist in Psalm 121.
I will lift up mine eyes into the hills
from whence cometh my help.
My help cometh from the Lord which made heaven and earth.
But the psalmist begins with those words, I will.
It's a choice.
I can keep my focus on my problems
and my problems just become greater and bigger
and more overwhelming because that's what my focus is.
Or I can say as the psalmist,
I will lift up mine eyes into the hills.
I will look to God.
I will put my eyes on the Lord.
Look in 2 Chronicles chapter 20.
Turn there very quickly.
And 2 Chronicles chapter 20 records for us an event
in the life of Jehoshaphat, king of Judah,
and several things going on here
in 2 Chronicles chapter 20
and the situation with the Assyrians
and just, I mean, all kinds of crazy things going on here.
And this is the victory here over Moab and Ammon
and what's going on.
And Jehoshaphat had experienced several things
throughout his life and his ministry.
He would, of course, face additional things as well.
But notice in verse four,
it says that he gathered these folks together
for what purpose?
To ask help of the Lord.
But then notice in verse number 12,
the prayer as we kind of dig in here
right in the middle of what's going on.
The Bible says this.
Oh, our God, wilt thou not judge them?
For we have no might against this great company
that cometh against us.
You ever feel that way?
Notice the next phrase.
Neither know we what to do.
You ever feel that way?
You say, no, I know everything.
You need help, honestly.
Because there are times that we are in ourselves,
we get into a situation where we say,
I don't know what to do.
Jehoshaphat's the king.
You know how many people are probably looking to him?
Hey, Jehoshaphat, what are we gonna do?
I don't know what we're gonna do.
I don't know what to do.
But notice the last statement of verse 12.
But our eyes are upon thee.
That's exactly where we need to be.
Lord, I don't know what to do.
Lord, this thing just happened.
Whatever this thing is,
whether it's the result of a doctor's appointment,
whether it's an employment situation,
a family situation, a relational thing,
whatever it is, that thing that rattles us,
that thing that shakes us to our very core,
that thing that's going to cause doubt and unbelief
to creep into our lives and overwhelm us,
that we have to come to the place where Jehoshaphat is
in 2 Chronicles 20 and verse number 12.
Lord, we don't have any strength,
we don't have any might against this great company,
and we don't know what to do,
but God, our eyes are on thee.
It's a choice that we make.
By the way, it's a whole lot easier
to get our eyes on the Lord
after we've spent time in God's word.
Amen?
They work together.
We spend time in God's word,
and then we get our eyes on the Lord.
Why?
Because I'm just in his presence.
We had on the bulletin Sunday morning,
the passage there in Psalm 16,
in thy presence is fullness of joy.
Man, what a blessing to think about
getting into the word of God
and getting our eyes on the Lord.
We find this, I would say,
that we need to rehearse the blessings.
Number three, rehearse the blessings.
We see it in verse number 11.
We've looked at this verse really each week
over these last three weeks.
It says, and the Lord said unto Moses,
how long, back in Numbers 14 and verse number 11,
how long will this people provoke me
and how long will it be ere they believe me
for all the signs which I have showed among them?
See, this evening, we have to understand
that as we rehearse our blessings,
as we do, as the songwriter said,
count your blessings, name them one by one.
As we rehearse our blessings,
what begins to happen in your life and in my life,
and even in the lives of others around us
as they hear us rehearsing the blessings of God,
it increases our faith.
Because what God has done is something
that I'm going to rejoice in
and it's gonna build my faith.
Why?
Because he's done these things,
he's proven himself, he's not gonna forsake me now.
This particular situation and trouble and trial and storm
is not too great for my God.
And I begin to rehearse those blessings.
It causes me to trust God in the moment.
In whatever I'm going through now.
Because in the moment, as I'm overwhelmed,
as I'm looking at the problem and the storm
and it's so great, as I take some time
after I've been in the word of God,
I get my eyes on Jesus and then I just begin to rejoice
and thank God for the things that he's done.
Man, it increases my faith.
Paul and Silas, what were they doing at midnight?
They were singing and praising God.
But let me talk about David for just a moment.
In 1 Samuel chapter 17,
and we referenced this very quickly a couple of weeks ago,
but in 1 Samuel chapter 17,
we find that David is obviously gonna do battle with Goliath.
He shows up and he asks this question,
is there not a cause?
And we find that David is having these interactions
with Saul and Saul is the king
and Saul says, you're not able, you're but a youth.
And this man, Goliath, well, he's a man of war
from since his youth.
And David begins to rehearse some blessings.
I said this two weeks ago that really God
is working to build our faith through our lives
as we deal with various obstacles
and he proves himself to us today.
And as we learn what we're supposed to learn today,
it's preparing me for the next trial,
the next battle, the next storm.
And so what was happening?
Listen, David doesn't just show up in 1 Samuel 17
and all of a sudden as a young man like,
oh yeah, I'm gonna fight Goliath, I'm gonna beat him.
No, there were some things that happened in David's life
where God was building his faith
and in the context of what we're dealing with this evening,
you know what David does when he's speaking to Saul?
He rehearses the blessings.
He says, if you pick it up with me here
in verse number 30, look in verse number 35
and I went out after, well, let me back up.
In verse number 32, and David said to Saul,
let no man's heart fail because of him.
Thy servant will go and fight with this Philistine.
Saul said to David, thou art not able
to go against this Philistine to fight with him,
for thou art but a youth and he a man of war from his youth.
And David said unto Saul,
thy servant kept his father's sheep.
There came a lion and a bear,
took a lamb out of the flock
and I went out after him and smote him
and delivered it out of his mouth.
And when he rose against me,
notice what David says, I caught him by his beard
and smote him and slew him.
That's pretty cool.
Amen?
Thy servant, verse 36, slew both the lion and the bear
and this uncircumcised Philistine shall be as one of them,
seeing he hath defied the arms of the living God.
Do you think David had faith here?
Absolutely he had faith.
What were all the other people of Israel doing, by the way?
Every time Goliath came out, they're hiding.
Fearful, right?
Am I right?
And David has faith.
Why does David have faith?
Well, he says, listen, as Saul, the king says,
no, you can't do this.
You are not able.
He says, let me tell you what happened
when I was taking care of my dad's sheep.
There was a lion and there was a bear.
What's he doing?
He's rehearsing the blessings.
Those things were faith builders in David's life.
Those things were opportunities for David
to see what God did.
We notice in verse 37, notice what he says.
David said, moreover, this is so important.
Please don't miss this.
In verse 37, David said, moreover,
the Lord that delivered me out of the paw of the lion
and out of the paw of the bear,
he will deliver me out of the hand of this Philistine.
Wow.
Listen, David knew that it wasn't in himself
that he got the ability to kill the lion and the bear.
The Lord that delivered me.
He acknowledged and recognized what God was doing
and how God was working and was building his faith
in those moments.
Did David know when there was a lion
that one day there'd be the giant Goliath?
No.
Did David know when there was the bear
that there would one day be the giant Goliath?
No.
But did God?
Sure he did.
And then when the day comes when there's Goliath there
and he's challenging and David is simply obeying his dad
and being there to deliver the goods
and he's ridiculed by his oldest brother
because of his.
His prideful heart is the accusation against him.
And David says, is there not a cause?
And then at that moment when Goliath is there,
David says, oh wait, there was a lion and there was a bear
and God was building my faith
and God was showing himself mighty.
And this uncircumcised Philistine shall be God.
He will deliver me out of the hand of the Philistine.
And so what happens?
Well, then David is, you know, let's give you some armor.
Let me give you these things.
And he's like, I haven't proved those things.
And he goes out and the Bible tells us
that when Goliath comes out against him
and he begins to curse him, David runs straight at him.
Why?
Faith in God.
When you rehearse the blessings,
it will increase your faith.
As you're reminding yourself what God has done.
God has been faithful.
God has never failed you.
He saved you.
He's given you so many things,
all things that pertain unto life and godliness.
We're seated in the heavenly places.
Man, he's given us a Bible, he's given us the Holy Spirit,
the earnest of our inheritance.
I mean, we just go on and on with so many blessings.
He daily loatheth me with benefits.
God has been so good to us.
The ability to see and to smell and to hear
and to walk and to talk.
And I mean, the ability to turn on a light switch,
the ability to sit in a heated room, the ability,
I mean, you just think about all of these blessings.
Somebody was sharing with me yesterday,
do you know what the poverty level is in the world?
I said, I have no idea.
I just don't know.
And they said, based on what I was told
and the research that was shown to me,
the poverty level in the world is $2 a day.
I guarantee you, all of us make more than $2 a day.
God's been good to us.
He's been so good to us.
And he's never failed us.
And we rehearse the blessings
and we come into a time of a storm
and we say, I didn't see this coming.
I wasn't ready for this.
But understand, God always knew about Goliath.
David, when he's facing the lion,
he doesn't know that Goliath is in the future.
When he's facing the bear,
he doesn't know that Goliath's in the future.
But God does and God is preparing.
That's why it's so important that we walk with God every day
and allow God to grow our faith
and to learn every day what we're supposed to learn.
Because that storm's gonna come
and if you've not properly prepared,
if you've not learned all that you're supposed to learn,
you're ill-prepared, right?
You ever get a test?
In high school, in college, university,
you get a test and you didn't study for it
and you say, man, I'm ill-prepared.
With a professor,
I did it when I was teaching that Bible Institute class.
I said, anyone know what this is?
And they said, I have no idea.
I said, that's what my professor used to do
when he was giving us a pop quiz.
I said, take out a piece of paper,
we're gonna have a pop quiz.
And those students looked at me like I was insane.
You know, one of those students didn't even turn in the paper
didn't even turn it in, ill-prepared, ill-prepared.
Number four, we need to get into God's word.
We need to get our eyes on Jesus.
We need to rehearse the blessings.
But I would say number four, we need to declare our faith,
verbalize it, like Paul did in Acts 27, I believe God.
I just believe God.
Yeah, but, no, I don't wanna hear any of the yeah, buts.
Nevertheless, no, no, I believe God.
I believe God.
I believe that what God has said, God will do.
I notice in our text in Numbers 14
that while Joshua and Caleb are talking to the people,
they say this, that the Lord, it says,
then he will, in verse number eight,
bring us into this land.
You know what they were doing?
They were declaring their faith.
They were verbalizing it.
They were saying publicly, not in these words,
but if I paraphrase it in a statement, I believe God.
He will bring us into this land.
And we find this evening that we look at verse nine
and he says, neither fear you the people of the land,
for they are bred for us,
their defenses departed from them,
and the Lord is with us, fear them not.
Listen, I'm thankful God is with us.
He will never leave us nor forsake us.
We find that there's great promises
that God has given to us.
Do you recognize that when the two spies went in
in Joshua chapter number two, when they go in
and they begin to search out the land,
and we find that in that interaction with Rahab
in Joshua chapter number two,
that the Bible reveals this to us,
that she says in verse number nine,
I know that the Lord hath given you the land
and that your terror is fallen upon us
and that all the inhabitants of the land
faint because of you.
You know what they were really fainting about?
Because of God, not because of the children of Israel,
because then she says this in verse number 10,
for we have heard how the Lord dried up the water
of the Red Sea for you when you came out of Egypt.
She then begins to talk about some things
that happened during the wilderness wanderings,
but Sihon and Og and what have you,
but understand with me that they heard,
listen, God was working and God was preparing
and Joshua and Caleb, they declared their faith,
they verbalized it, they said,
he will bring us into this land.
The Bible tells us in Psalm 118 in verse number six,
we see it in chapter 56 as well,
but in Psalm 118 in verse number six,
the Bible says this, it says, the Lord is on my side.
I will not fear what man can do unto me.
The Lord is on my side.
The Psalmist said it this way in Psalm 56,
he said it this way, let me get it here,
he says, in God have I put my trust,
I will not be afraid what man can do unto me.
It tells us that here in verse number nine,
the last phrase of verse number nine,
this I know for God is for me.
God is for me, the Lord is on my side.
Listen, I'm a child of God, I belong to him,
he belongs to me, you're his.
If you're saved tonight, you're his
and he has all power, he's got a plan for you,
he's got a purpose for you.
He which hath begun a good work in you
will perform it until the day of Jesus Christ,
Philippians one in verse number six.
God wants us to have faith, he wants us to live by faith.
If the Lord delight in us, how do we please God?
We obey him, we live by faith, we trust him.
We make that decision that I'm going to run
to the word of God so that my faith can be increased.
Why, because I wanna conquer doubt.
Something might happen in your life tomorrow,
something might happen in my life tomorrow
that will literally just shake us to our very core,
rattle us and it can be so intense
that we get our eyes off of the Lord because of this thing
but we must make the choice, we must make the decision,
I'm gonna run to God's word
and I'm gonna get my eyes on the Lord,
I'm not gonna be so focused on this thing.
Listen, I guarantee you tonight,
somebody walks in that back door
and drops a book on the ground,
all of y'all are gonna go look back there.
We get distracted so easy, something happens in your life,
you're walking with the Lord, you're having sweet fellowship
and then you get that call, you get that whatever
and it can rattle us and get our attention
but we have to say, no, no, I'm gonna get my eyes on Jesus,
I'm gonna make that decision, I'm going to make the choice
and exercise my will to trust God, to trust him
because God wants his people to believe him.
At times, if you're honest, doubt creeps up in our lives.
How's this gonna work out?
How are we ever going to?
I wasn't preparing for, I didn't see this coming
and doubt can start to creep in
and if doubt creeps in, doubt wants to take over.
Those weeds in the garden, they're not content
just having a little corner of the garden bed, am I right?
They want the whole thing, right?
Doubt wants to consume, take over.
Why?
Because faith pleases God, faith is what caused us
to step out, say I believe God, I wanna see God do something
because God is able, let's pray.
Father, we love you, thank you for loving us,
thank you for the privilege of being able
to study your word tonight.
I pray, Father, that you.
It would help us to conquer doubt in our lives.
Oh, it won't be a one and done.
We can conquer doubt today and something can happen tomorrow or next week
that will cause that doubt to creep in and we have to go through the process.
Lord, help us to stay in Your Word, to have our faith continuing to increase.
Help us, Lord, to believe You, to live by faith.
I pray that You'd bless our time of prayer.
Thank You again for the privilege, the opportunity to enter into Your presence.
You're a wonderful God.
You do great things.
Thank You that You hear us.
What a blessing to think that we can pray, God of the universe, and that You hear us,
that You're interested, that You answer us.
God, I pray that You'd bless and we'll thank You for it.
In Christ's name we pray, amen.