evening as we continue with this series on Wednesday evening, Walk Worthy, Please God.
And this is our 16th lesson.
And the Apostle Paul really has concluded this book with 14 concise pieces of instruction.
I'm not going to go back through beginning in verse number 12 and list all of them out
for you.
We have studied them and as you go through and you find, for instance, in verse number
14, there are several in one verse.
And so we find that all together, if you were to count them up, it's right at 14 pieces
of instruction that God gives to the church at Thessalonica through the Apostle Paul.
I believe this evening that the believers there at Thessalonica were well informed and
it was easy to understand what it was they were to do.
If they wanted to walk worthy, if they wanted to please God, we find that the book ends
really summarizing several things that have already been taught in the book, but just
kind of laying it out in this bullet point fashion.
Here's the instruction.
Here's what to do.
We understand and we've said it throughout the series that as we look at these particular
pieces of instruction, that there's some action that is required on the part of the believer.
There's something that I need to do.
There's something that I need to stop doing.
There's some action that is necessary, a response.
We find this evening, I often will pray that God would help us to be ready to receive the
word, but also that we'd be ready to respond, that we'd be doers of the word and not hearers
only.
We find that as they would have this understanding as to what it is that they are to do, it's
interesting because before closing the book, Paul provides two promises in the verse of
Scripture that we'll look at this evening that must be considered.
The two promises are in verse number 24, a verse of Scripture that God gave to me years
ago right after he was calling me to the ministry and he just brought my attention to this verse
of Scripture and has been a great source of encouragement to me over the years.
And we find that the Bible says this, faithful is he that calleth you who also will do it.
Begin to think about the instruction that Paul provides to these believers, to us by
way of preservation, God is giving us all of these pieces of instruction to close the
fifth chapter of the book of 1 Thessalonians.
And then after God tells us all of these things that we're to be engaged in, that the behavior
that would please Him, the behavior that would enable us to walk worthy, we're reminded
of these wonderful promises, faithful is he that calleth you who also will do it.
I think as we look at the truth of verse number 24, it reminds us in a greater sense of the
precious promises that God has given us throughout His Word.
You know the Bible is full of promises and it should encourage every child of God.
See we need to know them, we need to know the promises of God.
It's not enough for us just to sing about, standing on the promises of Christ my King.
I mean it's a wonderful song and we can sing it and we should and it's a blessing.
But the reality is that as a child of God we need to know the promises of God.
I believe that it's important, in fact I believe it's Scripture you can find where some of
God's people have done this, where we pray the promises of God, we pray Scripture.
We pray the promises that God has made.
You know that's what Nehemiah does when he hears what's taken place, he said, God you
said that if we, and that is what God said.
It's in Chronicles 7.14 during the establishment, the time of the temple being instituted and
all the dedication and we find during that prayer of Solomon that God gives that response
and then now here's Nehemiah all these years later hearing about all of the terrible report
and he prays according to what God had promised.
We need to know them, we need to pray them, we need to claim them, claim the promises
of God.
There's a little chorus, I think it's actually in our song book, every promise in the book
is mine, every chapter, every verse, every line.
And now you think about the promises, we claim the promises of God, then we should
share the promises of God.
I'm sure this evening that there's a promise that you're aware of that somebody else has
not yet maybe read it, they're not familiar with it, it's not something that's known to
them personally and we have the opportunity to share those promises.
This evening I've titled the message from this verse of Scripture, ponder the promises.
I picked the word ponder on purpose because it means this, it means to view with deliberation,
it means to examine, ponder the promises.
As we look at this verse of Scripture, number one if you're taking notes, really just simple
outline, simple thought tonight, but I think it has a profound impact not only in the lives
of the believers in Thessalonica as they originally would receive this truth, but I think for
us this evening and for countless millions of Christians throughout this church era,
note the promises.
Number one, note the promises.
The first one, God is faithful, God is faithful.
What an amazing truth of Scripture, what an amazing promise.
You know God is faithful, He's trustworthy, He's never going to fail you, He's never going
to recant on something that He's promised, that He's given, He's a faithful God.
We find that in the book of 1 Corinthians, turn back there if you would, and I want you
to look at a couple of references that Paul gives in this book of 1 Corinthians to the
truth of God's faithfulness.
In 1 Corinthians chapter number one, notice Paul is getting ready to write to a church
that's carnal, a church that's divisive, a church that's got all kinds of problems,
and it's interesting because he begins in verse number four by saying, I thank my God
always on your behalf.
Even as he's going to write a letter of correction, he begins by rejoicing in this first chapter,
and notice one of the reasons that he rejoices in verse number nine, God is faithful.
By whom ye were called unto the fellowship of His Son, Jesus Christ our Lord.
God is faithful.
He tells these believers in chapter number 10 and verse number 13, a verse that many
of us are familiar with, is at least part of the verse we often will quote, but in 1
Corinthians 10 and verse 13, the Bible says, there hath no temptation taken you, but such
as is common to man.
Then there's this statement, but God is faithful.
But God is faithful.
Who will not suffer you to be tempted above that you're able, but will with the temptation
also make a way to escape that ye may be able to bear it.
I've underlined in that great verse of Scripture so many wonderful truths for the child of
God, but I have just those four words underlined, but God is faithful, because it reminds me
of what I need to be reminded of.
God is faithful.
You know, there are times in your life that we're not faithful, that I'm not faithful,
that we fail.
No doubt you've been failed by some other human being at some point in your life and
you have failed someone else along the way, but God is faithful.
He's faithful.
And as Paul is writing to these believers, as he's giving to them, and we know it's under
the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God, but we find that as God is using the Apostle
Paul to minister to these believers and to instruct these believers with how they should
behave and how they should live so that they might walk worthy and please the Lord, we
find that Paul goes through all of this instruction and then he reminds them God is faithful.
God is faithful.
We find that his name is faithful if you're to look in Revelation 19.
We find that in the second letter that he, Paul, would pen to this church in Thessalonica,
2 Thessalonians 3, he reminds them again in verse number 3 of that book, but the Lord
is faithful who shall establish you and keep you from evil.
Wonderful song in our song book that we sing, great is thy faithfulness.
What a precious, precious song.
I know when we take favorites and we have opportunity, it's typically always selected
amongst the group.
I mean, somebody selects that song.
Why?
Because God is faithful.
It reminds us of that wonderful truth of Lamentations 3 that no doubt had impact on the songwriter
when he wrote that because the truth of Lamentations 3, great is thy faithfulness.
We understand in the book of Lamentations all that Jeremiah had experienced and all
that had taken place with regard to the nation of Judah, but yet even after all of that,
You can find God is faithful.
God is faithful.
By the way, God told them that's what was going to happen.
God told them that because of their sin and their wickedness that the Babylonians were
going to come and they were going to conquer and they were going to take captive the nation
of Judah.
And sure enough, it came to pass just as God had revealed not only through Jeremiah but
through many of His servants.
As I look in 1 Thessalonians 5, I see this truth that God is faithful, but as I notice
the verse of Scripture, in 1 Thessalonians 5 and verse 24, the Bible says, faithful is
he that calleth you.
No doubt it's a reference to God.
We mentioned in verse number 23 last week and the very God of peace dealing with the
subject of sanctification, sanctify you wholly.
And I pray God, your whole spirit and soul and body be preserved blameless under the
coming of our Lord Jesus Christ.
Faithful is he that calleth you who also will do it.
I think of this second aspect of this promise that I find here, these promises that I find
here in this verse of Scripture, not only is there a reminder, a promise to us that
God is faithful, but I believe number two that God is at work.
God is at work.
Faithful is he that calleth you who also will do it.
God is actively at work in the lives of His people.
We read through this portion of Scripture and we understand the responses that we are
to make with regard to our behavior, but we must recognize and we sought to incorporate
these truths throughout the process of studying this chapter that God is the one enabling
us.
God is working in us.
I can't do it on my own.
You can't do it on your own.
One of the most miserable things to try to do as a human being is to live the Christian
life in your own power.
You know, a lot of people say and a lot of people will make the claim that the most miserable
people in the world are lost people.
I disagree.
You know why I disagree?
I've met a lot of happy lost people.
I didn't say they had joy when Mark preached about that on Sunday night.
I just said they're happy.
I didn't say all of them are happy.
I just said I met some that are happy.
Haven't you?
They're lost.
They got no idea about eternity, but they're enjoying life right now.
You know who the most miserable person in the world is?
A Christian that's backslidden, a carnal Christian.
That's the most miserable person in all the world.
And we recognize this evening when we look at this verse of Scripture that God is at
work.
God is working.
You know, I believe that's probably why when somebody is not following the type of instruction
that we see here and they're leaving, departing, and they're trying to quench, they're not
following the leadership of the Holy Spirit in their lives, they're miserable because
God's working.
Conviction's a good thing, but it's a real good thing when it's heated, right?
You keep dealing with conviction after conviction after conviction and trying to suppress it
and suppress it and not deal with it and not deal with it.
It becomes miserable.
It really does.
But we look at this not from a negative perspective, but from a positive perspective.
Consider with me this evening that as these believers are receiving this instruction that
Paul goes through all of these concise bullet point type instructions and then says, God
is faithful and God is at work.
God is working in you.
I'm so thankful that I can't work for heaven.
Amen?
Let me say that again.
I'm so happy that I can't work for heaven.
You know why?
Because I'd never know if I did enough.
Am I right?
I become the authority.
I become the standard.
I'm the one that's going to…and it's a life of misery.
But I'm thankful to know that I'm saved by the grace of God, for by grace we are saved
through faith, Ephesians 2, 8, and 9, but you come to verse number 10, we are his workmanship
created in Christ Jesus, that we are to work and we are to live and to walk in good works.
The book of Titus deals with the subject of good works multiple times, never in the
perspective of salvation, but all in the response to our salvation.
The fact that I'm saved by the grace of God, it's to be worked out, it's to be evidenced
in my behavior, in my life.
James deals with good works.
Of course, there's been much confusion there with regard to the book of James, and James
is simply dealing with salvation from a fruit perspective, whereas Paul deals with it from
a root perspective.
He says, you say that you have faith, I'm going to show you my faith.
By the way, it's okay for people to see that you're saved.
Amen?
They ought to see that you're saved.
The message of your lips and the message of your life ought to be in agreement.
Amen?
That's why James says, hey, the fountain doesn't bring forth sweet and bitter at the
same.
No.
And so we find here this evening that this truth of God working in us and these believers
understanding as they get to the end of all of this instruction, they're reminded, yes,
this is your responsibility, but God is working in you.
He has called you and He will do it.
He will do the work.
Now, understand that it's not a situation where He will do it, where you just lay down
and just God's going to just miraculously do some kind of work.
No, we're actively seeking the Lord, we're in His Word, we're seeking to crucify the
old man and to walk in the Spirit, and God is at work in our lives, and He's enabling
us.
We think about that truth of His enabling grace, not just His saving grace, but His
enabling grace.
Look over to the book of Philippians, if you will.
I want you to look at a couple of verses of Scripture with me here.
In this book, Paul speaks of this work that God is doing within the lives of the believers,
and coupled together with this single verse of Scripture at the end of 1 Thessalonians
brings great joy to know that God is working.
Philippians chapter 1, verse number 6, that's what the Bible says, being confident of this
very thing, that He which hath begun a good work in you will perform it until the day
of Jesus Christ.
Isn't that a wonderful promise?
A wonderful truth that God is at work in your life, that God is working.
I'm thankful that He uses His Word, He uses the ministry of His Word, the Holy Spirit
uses the Word of God, and He's working in our hearts and our lives, and what a blessing.
Notice in chapter number 2, just a page or so over in your Bible, in verse number 13,
the Bible says this, for it is God which worketh in you both to will and to do of His
good pleasure.
I wonder this evening, when we look at a promise, we see too in this verse of Scripture this
evening that God is faithful and that God is working, He's working in our lives.
And I wonder this evening, what is the impact of God's promises?
We can note the promises, but then we must consider the impact of these promises.
How do the promises of God impact you?
If we look specifically at these tonight, we could ask how should these believers in
Thessalonica be impacted because of this reminder?
This evening, when we broaden the scope and look at a variety of promises throughout the
whole of God's Word, I wonder this evening, how does it impact you?
How do the promises of God impact you?
Well, number one, I would say this, these promises should cause us to rejoice.
It should cause us to rejoice.
I'm not always faithful, you're not always faithful, but God is faithful.
And though I might fail Him, let me rephrase that, and though I will fail Him, it's not
a matter of I might fail Him, we're going to fail Him.
We're not perfect, we're going to fail Him.
But God is faithful.
God is faithful.
That should cause us to rejoice.
It should cause us to rejoice greatly in being reminded of this wonderful, precious promise
that God has given us in His Word.
And so we find that these believers, that as they receive all of this information, again,
I want you to try to get into the mind, if you will, into the emotion of these believers
as they read this letter.
I believe that the original receipt of the letter, there'd be great excitement.
Amen?
Get a letter from Paul.
I mean, Paul was ministering there in Thessalonica.
He's concerned about them when he begins to write to them, and if we understand the context
of the letter and he's writing to find out how they're doing, he's concerned about them,
he loves them, and he's communicating these things to them in letter, in written form.
As they're beginning to read this letter, there's got to be a measure of excitement
and a measure of joy in their reading, in their reading, and they begin to read in that
fourth chapter, really a climatic type of a passage, if you will, with the return of
the Lord, the rapture of the church, I mean, how exciting.
Then they come to the fifth chapter, and all of a sudden, there's all of these, here's
what you need to do, here's what you need to do, here's your instruction, here are your
marching orders.
It can almost become a little overwhelming, all of these things that they're supposed
to be doing.
I don't want to, I don't want to warn them, actually I do want to warn them that are unruly
because that's fine, it's really not, but I'm just trying to get into the mind of, comfort
the feeble-minded, we'll let somebody else do that.
I don't want to deal with that.
I don't want to be bothered by supporting the weak.
You understand what I'm saying?
But Paul is giving all of this, rejoice evermore, pray without ceasing in everything, give thanks
for, this is the will of God in Christ Jesus concerning you, and all of these things that
they're to do, prove all things, hold fast that which is good, abstain from all appearance
of evil.
He says, faithful is he that calleth you, who also will do it.
All these promises would cause the believers to rejoice of knowing that God is faithful
and God is at work, and this evening I hope that for each of us tonight, we would rejoice
in the promises that God has given, that we rejoice, you know, sometimes we can look at
life and maybe with any type of task that we have in life, someone will assign you
a task to do, and you might ask the question, it'd be a valid question, how do I do this?
Just do it.
Isn't that helpful?
How can I do it in such a way that it would be right, it would be pleasing, it would be
acceptable?
I don't want to do it multiple times.
I don't want to do it to the way I think I should do it, and then you have a different
standard, a different expectation.
We come to the work of God.
We find that God lays out the work that we're to do, but then says, I'm working in you.
I'm enabling you to do what I've commanded you to do, and this is a precious promise
and a precious truth that should cause the believer to rejoice.
Not only should it cause the believer to rejoice, but I believe that the impact of these promises
really should give me hope, give me hope.
You know, we live in a world that does not understand the true definition of hope.
When we speak of hope from a biblical perspective, hope as we would refer to biblically, is not
wishful thinking.
No, it's a confident expectation based upon the promise of one who cannot lie.
Makes me confidently expectant.
I'm hopeful.
I have hope because I know Christ, because He's my God, because He's given me promises.
And we look at this verse of Scripture and we can understand that we should rejoice because
of these promises.
We should have hope because of these promises.
I believe that these promises should motivate us to continue.
We think about a theme that we have for this year in our church of continue.
Well, I'm telling you, when you look at a verse of Scripture like this, faithful is
he that calleth you who also will do it, that is a motivation to continue.
Why?
Because God is faithful and therefore we ought to strive to be faithful and we ought to know
that God is working in us and through us and He's seeking to bring to pass His perfect
will in our lives and in this world.
What a blessing to know the promises of God.
I believe also the promises should cause us to examine, to reflect.
I wonder as I look at this verse of Scripture and we focus really on the second aspect of
the promise, not the faithfulness of God, but on the God working in you aspect, faithful
is he that calleth you who also will do it, I wonder this evening as we take a look at
this verse and examine this verse and then look at our lives, do we truly see God working
in our lives?
Is there an absence in our lives of God being at work or can we actively put a finger on
things in our lives, say, here's where God's at work, here's what God is doing, here's
how God is growing me, here's how God is developing me, here's how God is maturing me, here's
how God is using me because God is working in me.
We ought to be able to look at our lives and we ought to be able to see some evidence
of God being at work, amen?
We sing a song with the kids, I feel like I say that a lot, God's still working on me.
How many of you know that little chorus?
I don't know all the words of it but something about he made the, you know, he created the
moon, the stars and all the universe and all this kind of stuff and he did, he made, I'm
not negating the truth of that, I just don't know the exact wording that it uses but he
is, he's creator God, he did all of that in just six days, Genesis record, amen?
I mean, Genesis 1 and 2, it's amazing but then the songwriter says, but he's still working
on me to make me what I ought to be, amen?
He's still working on us, he's still working in us and I hope this evening that when you
look at a verse of Scripture like this that it would cause us to rejoice and to have
hope and to continue but also to examine and say, is there evidence that God is working
in my life?
Do I see it?
Do others see it?
When God is working in our lives, we don't really have to manufacture it.
You know, there's a lot of times we try to manufacture things, we try to manufacture
the blessings of God, we try to manufacture the work of God, the moving of God.
There are people that try to, through various means of really manipulation through seeking
emotional type of processes and patterns, they try to manipulate circumstances, try
to manufacture something.
No, no, God is the sovereign God who we need to say, Lord, have your way in my life.
These believers in Thessalonica, if they're going to walk worthy, if they're going to
please God, they need to recognize that it's God that's going to do the work in and through
them.
Yes, they must be active, they have an active part in it but it's not an independent part
of it.
Does that make sense?
We are actively dependent upon the Lord.
We've got to do our part, abide in me, and I in you, right?
So we've got to do our part.
God didn't make you read your Bible today, He didn't make you come to church tonight,
I'm happy you did, He didn't make you, but we do our part and then God does His part.
It's amazing how that works.
I did my part this morning, I read my Bible and guess what?
God showed me some things.
He reminded me of some things as I was reading my Bible today because I opened it up and
I was reading it.
If I didn't read it, then He's not going to…does that make sense?
So we find this evening that we are actively dependent upon God but do you see His work
in your life?
Do you see His hand at work?
Let me ask it this way, do you long to see His hand at work in your life?
I mean, do we come to the place where we desire, Lord, we want to be that yielded and surrendered
vessel, that servant, Lord, that you can use?
I think of this, in fact I thought of it just as I made that statement, Psalm 119 verse
26, it is time for Thee, Lord, to work, for they have made void Thy law.
Can I tell you this evening that if that verse has ever been true in human history, and it
has been, and it was at the time of David writing it, can I tell you this evening it
is true tonight?
They have made void Thy law.
Is that not true?
It is time for Thee, Lord, to work.
He's promised.
that He's faithful. He's promised that He's at work. Do we see it? Do we long for it?
God, I want You to work in my life. I want You to be working and using me, not for me
to be recognized, but God, so that You would receive all the honor and the glory that is
due unto Your wonderful name, because He alone is worthy. He must increase, I must decrease.
And as He works in and through our lives, as we are those yielded vessels, then it will
be the case that we'll desire nothing more than for Him alone to be glorified through
whatever it is that He does. Let's pray together. Father, we love You. We thank You for loving
us. Ponder the promises. It's a familiar verse of Scripture. It reminds us that You're
faithful. Oh God, how thankful we are that You're a faithful God. We've experienced
Your faithfulness in our lives personally and corporately. God, we sing of Your faithfulness.
We rejoice knowing that You're a faithful God. Faithful is He that calleth You who also
will do it. God, You've called us. You've called us to live separated lives, holy lives,
pure lives, consecrated, Lord, for Your use, Your work. You've promised that You're working
in us. God, I pray tonight that this verse of Scripture would give us joy and peace and
hope and motivation to continue. God, I pray that for just a moment we do some self-examination,
be honest with ourselves before You, Lord. Is there any evidence of You working in our
lives? Is there anything that we can see, point to, that would show that You're at work?
Do we long, do we desire, do we invite You to work in our lives? Are we closer to You
today than we were yesterday, a week ago, a year ago? God, I pray that You'd help us
to be yielded and surrendered. I pray that You'd help us, Lord, to walk worthy and please
You. Bless our time of prayer. We thank You again for the privilege. I pray that You'd
be honored and glorified through all that's said and done. For it's in Christ's name we
pray. Amen.