Bible with you this evening, Hebrews chapter number 11,
and we'll be getting back to our series
that we've had here on Wednesdays for 2026,
dealing with the thought of seeing God work,
having a longing personally to see God do something great.
We understand, we have acknowledged
that God is still able, amen, and He is still able.
He still has as much power today as He's ever had,
and He has the ability, we said this,
that the only thing that hinders God
is our doubt, our unbelief.
And so as we begin to go through the scriptures
and deal with various aspects of having this longing
to see God work, and then we've ended up here
in Hebrews chapter number 11
and looking at these Bible characters that lived by faith.
And last time, two weeks ago, we looked at Abraham.
And I would say this tonight, that many of us,
I would say maybe most of us,
are familiar with the life of Abraham and Sarah.
There are several things about their lives
that if I were to ask you this evening
to give me some of the highlights
and some of the events that transpired,
you would be able to provide really kind of an overview
of the life of Abraham and Sarah.
So we find that in the passage
beginning in verse number eight, dealing with Abraham,
we noted as we studied those verses of scripture
what God revealed to Abraham.
We said this in Acts chapter number seven,
that as Stephen is preaching, he says,
"'The God of glory appeared unto our father Abraham.'"
And we don't know exactly all that God revealed to Abraham,
but we understand that whatever God did reveal to Abraham,
it was sufficient for Abraham to be able to understand
that Jehovah God was different than the idols
that they were familiar with in his homeland,
in the Ur of the Chaldees.
And so we find that after we dealt with how
or what God revealed to Abraham,
we then asked this question,
or we noted how Abraham responded to God.
And we tried to make the application
and challenge for our lives is how do we respond
to what God has revealed to us?
We have the complete revelation of God.
We have the complete canon of scripture.
We have everything that God wants us to have
and we need to respond, we ought to respond in faith.
As we look and move forward here in Hebrews chapter 11,
we come to verse number 11 and we see
that the scriptures begin to reference Sarah.
The Bible says this in verse number 11,
"'Through faith also Sarah herself received strength
"'to conceive seed and was delivered of a child
"'when she was past age.'"
Then notice this,
"'Because she judged him faithful who had promised.'"
Isn't that a great statement in God's word?
It says at the end of verse number 11,
"'Because she, Sarah, judged him, God,
"'faithful who had promised.'"
As we begin to think about the life of Sarah
and here if you're taking notes,
I've just titled the message,
Through Faith, Sarah, Through Faith, Sarah.
The others have been by faith
and whoever the character is,
but this evening, Through Faith, Sarah.
As we begin to consider what God is revealing to us
here in Hebrews 11 about her faith,
I think it's important to go back to the book of Genesis.
Go back with me to Genesis 11
and we'll be looking at a number of verses of scripture
here in the book of Genesis
to try to get an understanding of what's going on
in the life of Abraham and Sarah
and then to understand the statement
that is made in Hebrews chapter 11 about her faith.
We find that here in Genesis chapter 11,
notice in verse number 30, the Bible says this,
"'But Sarah was barren, she had no child.'"
At this point, we understand that God is revealing to us
and helping us understand.
This is something that was already known
by both Abraham and Sarah.
They understood this, they knew their condition
and we find that God is revealing to us
that she, Sarah, was barren.
In chapter number 12, in verse number one,
the Bible says, "'Now the Lord had said unto Abram,
"'Get thee out of thy country and from thy kindred
"'and from thy father's house
"'unto a land that I will show thee.'"
Notice verse number two,
"'And I will make of thee a great nation
"'and I will bless thee and make thy name great
"'and thou shalt be a blessing.'"
We understand that here in verse number two,
it's really the first reference with regard to this promise
that God gives with regard to having heirs
and understanding to have children
and we find that the promise gets a whole lot more specific
as we go through the pages of scripture,
but we find here that God is revealing
and letting Abraham know of his plan.
In chapter number 15,
if you skip ahead just a few chapters here,
in Genesis chapter number 15,
notice what happens in verse number one
after the victory that was recorded in chapter number 14,
we find that God appears to Abraham and he says,
"'Fear not, Abram, I am thy shield
"'and thy exceeding great reward.'"
What a blessing to understand
how God is seeking to encourage his servant
and Abram says back to the Lord,
notice in verse number two,
"'Lord God, what wilt thou give me?'
Notice this, "'Seeing I go childless
"'and the steward of my house is this Eliezer of Damascus.'
And Abram said, "'Behold, to me thou hast given no seed
"'and lo, one born in my house is mine heir.'
Behold, the word of the Lord came unto him saying,
"'Notice very plainly and bluntly,
"'this shall not be thine heir.'"
We find that Abraham after a period of time,
he comes and he's got an idea for the Lord,
I don't have any seed, I have no children
and Eliezer, why can't he be the heir?
And God again, plainly says,
"'This shall not be thine heir,
"'but he that shall come forth out of thine own bow
"'shall be thine heir.'
And he brought him forth abroad and said,
"'Look now toward the heaven and tell the stars
"'if thou be able to number them.'
And he said unto him, "'So shall thy seed be.'"
Chapter number 16 records the birth of Ishmael.
It starts in verse number one where Sarai, Abram's wife,
bear him no children and she gives the recommendation
about Hagar and we understand if you were to look
at the timeline that in chapter number 16,
it's about 10 years that has passed
since the promise was first given.
Now 10 years is a long time, amen?
To have received a promise and it not to be fulfilled
and you're not getting any younger,
it doesn't seem any more logical
and we find that 10 years and so we see,
we understand what happens in chapter number 16,
but then as we continue through the portions of scripture
and we'll look at chapter 17, 18 and 21
as we get through the message,
but I just wanna kinda lay the groundwork
that we understand where Abraham and Sarah are
in their lives.
And we find that as we come to chapter 17,
if you're taking notes, I'll give you the first point here,
the promise given, the promise given.
We read in chapter 17 in verse number 15,
the Bible says this,
and God said unto Abraham, ask for Sarai thy wife,
thou shalt not call her name Sarai,
but Sarah shall be her name be.
And I will bless her and give thee a son also of her,
yea, I will bless her and she shall be a mother of nations,
kings of people shall be of her.
Then Abraham fell upon his face and laughed
and said in his heart,
shall a child be born unto him that is 100 years old
and shall Sarah that is 90 years old bear.
And Abraham said unto God,
oh, that Ishmael might live before thee.
So Abraham is offered Eleazar in chapter 15,
now he's offering Ishmael here in chapter 17,
but I want you to notice the promise
and I chose to highlight verse 19 on purpose.
The Bible says in Genesis 17 and 19,
and God said, notice this phrase,
Sarah thy wife, what's the next word?
Shall.
Shall what?
Shall bear thee a son and then what does it say?
Indeed.
So two words that are really worthy of our consideration
here in Genesis 17 and 19,
where the Bible says that she shall bear thee a son indeed.
And the certainty of these words shall and indeed,
and God is seeking to communicate to Abraham the promise
and really give him a confidence and an assurance
of what God will do.
We find that he continues and says,
and thou shalt call his name Isaac
and I will establish my covenant with him
for an everlasting covenant and with his seed after him.
He then goes on to talk about Ishmael
and the way that he'll bless him and make him fruitful
and 12 princes shall he begat, so on and so forth.
But he says in verse 21,
but my covenant will I establish with Isaac,
notice again, which Sarah shall bear unto thee
at this set time in the next year.
So we find here in chapter 17
that God gives this promise very specifically.
There's no way for Abraham or Sarah
to misunderstand what is being communicated.
We find again, those absolute words shall and indeed,
and how blessed they are to receive that direct specific.
promise from God. As you go into chapter 18, I want you to
notice that in verse number 6 the Bible says,
And Abraham hastened into the tent unto Sarah, and he said,
Make ready quickly three measures of fine meal. Knead it,
and make cakes upon the hearth. And so Sarah is busy preparing
in chapter 18 and verse number 6. She's busy preparing and God
is having this conversation with Abraham and it tells us in
verse number 10 that he said, that's God speaking, I will
certainly return unto thee according to the time of life.
And lo, notice what it says, Sarah thy wife shall have a
son. The Bible says that Sarah heard it in the tent door which
was behind him. And so God reconfirms the promise that was
made in chapter number 12. Now understand, listen, the fact
that God reveals to us in chapter 11 and verse number 30
that Sarah was barren, God knew that. This was no surprise to
God. He was aware of it but yet even to a couple that had no
children, to a woman that was barren, He, God, makes a
promise that she shall bear a son indeed. And so we come and
we see the promise. It's not hard for us to understand or
comprehend the promise but we notice number 2, the problem.
The problem. Now allow me the time to kind of develop the
thought here with regard to the problem because we find that as
we look here in chapter number 18 that Sarah is hearing this
conversation again. She is in the house and she is preparing
the meal and she is doing those things and we find that she
hears that God says He is going to return and that she is going
to have a son. In verse number 11 of chapter 18 it says,
Now Abraham and Sarah were old and well stricken in age.
Notice this, and it ceased to be with Sarah after the manner of
women. It ceased. Again, God was aware of this. He is
revealing it to us. Verse 12, Therefore Sarah laughed within
herself. Here's what she says, After I am waxed old shall I
have pleasure, my Lord, being old also. As we look here and
we consider the problem this evening, the problem is
typically a result of our perspective. Understand here
that the problem, as I speak of the problem, Abraham and Sarah
both had an understanding of the reproductive process. They
understood how life worked. They understood the reproductive
process that God designed when He created humanity. And we
find that they knew, they were well aware of the fact of their
own condition. They were aware of the fact of their age. They
were aware of the fact that she was past the age of bearing
children. We begin to think about the problem. Again, the
problem is typically a result of our perspective. Because
what are we doing? We're looking at what we can see.
We're looking at what we can understand. We're taking and
falling into the trap of really violating the instruction of
Proverbs 3 and verse 5 where we're leaning on our own
understanding. And God says that we're not to do that. And
we find that here that the circumstances and the
situation in which Abraham and Sarah found themselves and
then they hear this promise. We find that before Sarah
laughed, Abraham laughed. Amen. Before Sarah offered to
Abraham to go into Hagar to have children, Abraham offered
Eleazar as the heir. Why do I say that? Well there are times
in which some individuals like to go to portions of
Scripture and like to be critical of Bible characters.
She laughed at the promise of God. Well before you get too
critical maybe you want to spend some time evaluating your
own life. You know what I'm saying? I think about it this
way. I said it to the group this morning. I'm really
thankful that God is not recording every day of my life
for everyone else to read about. Aren't you? You know what I'm
saying? It would be kind of humiliating, wouldn't it?
Because we don't always believe God. And we have so much more
than what they had. And we look here and we begin to
understand and we look at what's taking place. And yes,
the Bible says, trust in the Lord with all thine heart and
lean not unto thine own understanding and all thy ways
acknowledge Him and He shall direct thy paths. And we begin
to understand here where she laughed and understanding the
problem. Again it's a problem from their perspective. It's no
problem for God. It's a problem for them. And so as we look at
the problem and we begin to try to figure out as we put
Scripture and compare Scripture with Scripture, we find that
over there in Hebrews 11 it says, through faith also Sarah.
So my question would be this as we look through the portion of
Scripture this evening, when did Sarah's doubt turn to faith?
When did Sarah's doubt turn to faith? Remember several weeks
ago we looked at the man that said, Lord I believe, help
thou, help me, mine unbelief. Right? And we looked at that
and we talked about that and we said, listen God already knew
about that man's unbelief. God already knew about his doubt.
And so it was good for that man to acknowledge it and to pray
the way that he did. And so when we look at Sarah this
evening the Bible says, through faith also Sarah. So we
understand she had faith. So when did her doubt turn to
faith? As you look here in Genesis chapter number 18, we
find that after Sarah laughs in verse number 12, notice what
the Bible says in verse 13, and the Lord said unto Abraham.
Notice what God asks Abraham, wherefore did Sarah laugh?
Now here's what I believe. I believe that God asked Abraham
why Sarah laughed. Because Abraham had a responsibility
as being the husband to communicate to his wife what
God had promised. Abraham had laughed as well. We read it
earlier in chapter 17. But after Abraham laughed and God
restated the promise, God gave the token of the promise being
circumcision. And what did Abraham do? Well Abraham was
circumcised as well as Ishmael and all of those in his house.
And so at that moment that's where we see that Abraham
believed and had that faith that this was going to come to
pass. But Sarah has not yet been in that position. And so we
find that the Bible says that God asks Abraham, wherefore
did Sarah laugh? Saying, shall I of a surety bear a child
which am old? Now remember, I'm not reading anything into
Scripture. Back in chapter number 18 and verse number 10
the Bible says that Sarah heard it in the tent door which was
behind him. Sarah is not part of the conversation, but Sarah
is hearing the conversation. Are we tracking? So in verse
number 14 of Genesis 18 God is still speaking to Abraham, but
I believe Sarah hears exactly what God is saying. And here's
what God says, is anything too hard for the Lord? And then He
says this, at the time appointed notice I will return unto thee
according to the time of life and Sarah shall have a son. I
think it's at this moment in Sarah's life that her doubt
turned to faith. Because she hears, listen how gracious of
God to preface and to say before He just restates the
promise that I will return and she shall have a son, He says
is anything too hard for the Lord? Now that's precious and
we can look at that and we've often preached about that
thought and that subject that nothing is too hard for God.
Nothing is impossible for our God. But I want to this evening
help you to get into the shoes of Sarah because she's busy in
the home and she's preparing and she's doing those things in
the tent and God's having this conversation with Abraham, but
Sarah's hearing it and when Sarah hears it she laughs and
then she continues to hear and God says is anything too hard
for the Lord? At the time appointed notice I will, not I
might, I will return unto thee according to the time of life
and Sarah shall have a son. Again we looked in chapter 19
about those words shall and indeed and now we see I will
and shall and what a blessing those words are for us to grasp
hold of and understand and so we come to this place here this
evening where Sarah's doubt is
doubt, I believe right here is where it turns to faith. We look at what the
writer of Hebrews says in Hebrews 11, in verse number 11, the latter part of the
verse where the Bible says, because she judged him faithful who had promised. So
it says, through faith also Sarah herself received strength to conceive seed and
was delivered of a child when she was past age. Why? Because she judged him
faithful who had promised. The word faithful means trustworthy or worthy of
trust. That's what it means. And so when Sarah heard here what is being said in
verse number 14, again I believe that her doubt turns to faith and she judged that
the Lord is faithful, that he's trustworthy, he's made this promise and
it would come to pass. We're going to think about the truth here in Genesis chapter 18
and we understand this evening that the promise that we're dealing with is a
specific promise given to a specific couple, Abraham and Sarah. You can't claim
this promise, amen? It's not a promise for any of us to claim, it's a promise
that was given to Abraham and Sarah. And we find that throughout the pages of
Scripture there are some promises that are specifically given to individuals
such as this one that are not for us to try to apply in our own lives, but then
there are plenty of promises that absolutely are for our good and for our
benefit and for us to claim. We sing the song standing on the promises. What a
great song that is. As we remind ourselves of the promises of the Lord
in 2 Peter chapter number 1, notice Peter says this in verse number 4,
whereby are given unto us exceeding great and precious promises. Listen, God's
given us some wonderful promises and the question that we must ask ourselves
this evening is when does our doubt turn to faith? And we find in the text of
Scripture that for Sarah it took place when she heard the Word of the Lord. No
longer was Sarah dependent on on receiving the message from God through
Abraham. Are you tracking this evening? She's hearing it direct. What a blessing.
But can I tell you this evening, as a New Testament understanding of the
priesthood of the believer, you have direct access to God. You have a Bible.
You have the Holy Spirit of God. If you're saved this evening, that indwells
you and the Holy Spirit of God is our teacher and the Lord speaks to us
through His Word. And God wants us to believe Him. He wants us to have that
faith that we see in the life of Sarah and we can dig in and try to figure out
when did this happen for Sarah and I've tried to pinpoint it this evening but
then I want to look at my life and look at your life and evaluate our own lives
and say where's my faith? Well I want to hear an audible voice. Well Peter also
said we have a more sure word of prophecy. Amen? And Peter was the one that
walked with Jesus and in the context of what he's saying when he mentions the
truth that we have a more sure word of prophecy, he's just finished talking
about the Mount of Transfiguration. When they heard the voice of God and he says
but we have a more sure word of prophecy. Listen, the Bible is God's Word.
All scripture is given by inspiration of God. Amen? It's inspired. It's
preserved. And God said that He would preserve it to every generation. I had
somebody I was talking to the folks this morning there's an article just yesterday
about oh there's some missing Pauline letter that blah blah blah listen it's a
bunch of nonsense. Don't get distracted with that stuff man. When we're in Israel
we had somebody that after we went to the the museum there and they got the
Dead Sea Scrolls on display and so on and so forth and oh you know we get back
on the bus and there's this guy from New York he sat next to us for most of
the trip and he says so what do you think about the Dead Sea Scrolls you
know and he's all kind of and you know so and I'm like listen that's not how
God preserved His Word. Alright? When God said that He was going to preserve His
Word for every generation He didn't mean for 1,700 years it was going to be
hidden in a cave somewhere in Israel. Because guess what? That means
every generation didn't have it. Are you tracking? And so sometimes we can get so
caught up with academia and all these like oh listen to what this guy with a
PhD said and blah blah blah. No no no. What did God say? Because professing
themselves to be wise they became fools according to Romans chapter number one.
And we understand listen God has given to us He's recorded for us His Word and
He wants us to have faith. And Sarah had the opportunity to hear. She laughs
initially but then God says is anything too hard for the Lord? At the time
appointed I will and Sarah shall have a son. Hallelujah. And through faith also
Sarah. Why? Because she judged him faithful who had promised. This evening I
want you to understand that God's track record if we could use that terminology
this evening and I don't mean it in a in a in a negative sense but it's perfect.
God's never failed. He's never going to. God is trustworthy. Everything that He
has ever said He has He has completed. And we look here we begin to understand
the problem in the midst of the promise being given and we'll wrap up in just a
moment. And I want to ask you this evening where's the problem for us? What
keeps us from believing God? What keeps us from living a life of faith? What
keeps us from proving God? You understand what I'm saying? Because there was a problem
there and the problem was a result of their perspective. No, we're past age. I'm
barren. This isn't possible. But God said. So what do you do when in your
logic there seems to be an impossibility but you have a word from God? I'm not
talking about some crazy dream or vision. I'm talking about the Word of God. What
do you do? Do you believe God or do you believe yourself? Do you believe God or
when you make the decisions you know we live we're all the product of a culture
in a society a time in which we've been taught and we've been trained on making
decision trees and how to go through the process of making these decisions and
put all the pros on this side and all the cons on this side and blah blah blah
blah blah. I'm not suggesting that a decision tree is worthless or useless
and you never use it. I'm just simply saying when God's told us something it
doesn't really matter how many other things are on the sheet of paper. Does
that make sense? Because God said it and we're gonna believe God and we're gonna
approve God. The reality is that what God was promising to Abraham and
Sarah, note this, was something that only God could do. It was something that only
God could do. Don't you think Abraham and Sarah had tried to have children? Sure
they did. And when she continued to be barren Abraham says I have no children
and so Eliezer and Sarah says we have no children and Hagar and we have no
children. How about Ishmael? No, no. God promised something that only God could
do and God did. We have the benefit of reading about event that took place
thousands of years ago and being able to see the whole of the story and
understanding that when you come to Genesis 21 and number three in your
notes if you're taking notes this evening, the promise fulfilled. You come
to Genesis chapter 21 and there's two statements in verse number one that are
so precious. I personally, I underline, circle things in my Bible and if you're
in the habit of doing that I'd circle a couple of things here. In verse one of
Genesis 21 the Bible says and the Lord visited Sarah and noticed these words as
he had said. The Lord did unto Sarah notice as he had spoken. Those two
phrases as he had said and as he had spoken are so important for us to really
get hold of. What do I mean by it? Well God always does what he says he will do. He'll
never fail us. He wasn't going to fail Abraham and Sarah. The Bible says that
the Lord visited Sarah as he had said and the Lord
did unto Sarah as he had spoken, and it says in verse 2,
for Sarah conceived and bare Abraham a son in his old age
at the set time of which God had spoken to him.
Abraham, verse 3, called the name
of his son that was born unto him,
whom Sarah bared to him, Isaac.
God told him that in chapter 17, name of Isaac.
Now, here's a thought for you this evening.
What do you think the chatter around town was?
You ever think about that?
Do you think it was a secret that Abraham and Sarah
had a baby?
Listen, I've had strangers tell me
at different times in their lives about big events.
Strangers have told me about being engaged,
and I'm like, I'm thankful.
Praise the Lord for it.
I don't even know who you are, but great.
I'm expecting.
That's wonderful.
We had a baby.
Praise the Lord.
That's great.
I don't even know you, but it's great.
What I'm saying is that Abraham and Sarah, this
is a momentous occasion.
This was miraculous.
I think there are people that knew.
Why do I say that?
Well, because we mentioned several weeks ago,
months ago now, as we've talked about this thought of desiring,
longing to see God work.
And Psalm 109, 27 was a text that we
looked at a couple of months ago now at this point.
It says that they may know that this is thy hand,
that thou, Lord, hast done it.
That's what God did in Genesis 21.
He worked in such a way that no one could explain it away.
Amen?
And it says that Abraham circumcised his son,
verse number 4, Isaac being eight days old,
as God had commanded him.
And Abraham was 100 years old when his son Isaac
was born unto him.
And Sarah said, notice in verse 6 of Genesis 21,
God hath made me to laugh, so that all that here
will laugh with me.
When God asked Abraham in Genesis 18, why did Sarah laugh?
Sarah tried to deny it.
But now she acknowledges that she did laugh.
But we focus on the faith of Sarah and the fact
that God says, through faith also Sarah.
And what was the pivotal time in Sarah's life
when that doubt changed to faith?
Have you gotten into the book?
Have you heard the Spirit of God speak to you
through the word of God?
Do you have some promises that you can claim from God?
I mean, listen, it's not trusting in our own ways.
Listen, there's a way that seemeth right unto man, right?
But the end?
Not good.
Way of death.
But man, we have a Bible.
We have the Holy Spirit.
So then faith came with my hearing and hearing
by the word of God.
And Sarah heard the spoken word of God.
And it was pivotal for her.
And her doubt became faith.
So that when Hebrews 11 is being written,
the Bible says that through faith also Sarah.
And we get to see that she makes her way
into what we often refer to as the hall of faith chapter.
Why?
Because she judged him faithful who had promised.
This evening, how do you view God?
Do you judge him faithful?
Worthy of your trust?
Have you proved him?
Have you seen him do what he said he would do?
Because here Sarah is a great example for us.
Listen, we live life just like these Bible characters
live life.
We have trials and circumstances.
And we have things that we look at and we say,
but what about this?
And God says, this is no problem for me.
It's just a problem for you, right?
This situation was no problem for God.
It was just a problem for Sarah and Abraham.
And God says, isn't anything too hard for the Lord?
So I don't know what your problems are this evening.
And I don't use that word in a demeaning type of a way.
I don't know where our doubts are this evening.
But what I'd say to you is that typically, they're
a result of our perspective not being where it ought to be.
Because when we have a word from the Lord, do we believe him?
Do we believe him?
And it really just kind of boils down to that.
Do we believe God?
Do we judge him faithful, worthy of our trust, who has promised?
Listen, get in the Bible and get some promises.
I mean, study the scriptures and grab hold
onto some principles and some promises and just claim them.
Because God will not fail you.
And Sarah, Abraham, they got to see God do something miraculous.
And here we are thousands of years later reading about it.
Again, familiar to most of us about Abraham and Sarah.
But when we look at that pivotal moment in the life of Sarah,
when did her doubt become faith?
And for you this evening and for me this evening,
when does our doubt become faith?
We got to get into the book.
We got to hear the voice of God.
I'm not talking about an audible voice.
I'm talking about through the pages of scripture.
We hear the voice of God.
So you know what?
I'm going to believe God.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the example this evening of Sarah.
I thank you for that final statement.
She judged you faithful, worthy of trust.
She heard you speak those words that are recorded for us
in Genesis 18 and verse 14.
Is anything too hard for the Lord?
At the time appointed I will and Sarah shall have a son.
Oh God, thank you for ministering to Sarah,
for allowing her to hear those words
and for her to believe you, to trust you, to exercise faith.
God, I think about my life and our lives this evening
and I pray that you'd help us to be people of faith.
Help us to live by faith, Lord, to believe you,
to get into your word and allow your word to get into us.
God, that we'd know the promises and claim the promises,
that we'd see you work as only you can.
Thank you for loving us.
I pray that you'd bless the time of prayer
that through all that's said and done you'd be glorified.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Amen.