Genesis chapter 41.
In our last study, which was a couple of weeks ago, we looked at verse 1 through 32, here
through the 41st chapter of the book of Genesis.
And let me just give you a very brief overview of verses 1 through 32.
The Bible begins by sharing with us the timeline, it had been two full years since the butler
had been restored to his butlership, and of course the dream of the butler and baker in
Genesis chapter number 40 were interpreted by Joseph, and he gave them an interpretation.
The butler was restored to his butlership, the baker of course, he was put to death.
And we find that as we look at Genesis 41, beginning in verse number 1, we're told of
the timeline, so Joseph continued in prison for those two years.
We believe, although the scriptures are silent with regard to what was taking place during
those two years, he was faithful to his Lord, and he was doing that which he had been called
to do in that place, though he had been falsely accused and falsely imprisoned, he understood
that God was in control.
We find that the 41st chapter of the book of Genesis reveals to us a dream that Pharaoh
had, and Pharaoh had really two dreams, kind of he woke up after the first one, had a second
one immediately, and of course we understand that Joseph would then tell him that they're
really one, and we find that as Pharaoh awoke, he got woken up after that second dream, he's
very, just distressed with regard to all that was taking place, he calls the magicians
and all of the wise men in, in order to interpret the dream, but the Bible tells us there was
none that could interpret, and therefore Joseph was brought in with haste.
And Joseph was there in the prison, but it was during that time, in Pharaoh's great distress
that the butler remembers what had taken place a couple of years earlier, and at that recollection
he just rehearses those events to the Pharaoh, the Pharaoh sends for Joseph, he's brought
in with haste, and even though the matter was urgent, we find that the Bible tells us
that Joseph, he was, he shaved himself and he changed his raiment, then he came into
the presence of Pharaoh, and as he went into the presence of Pharaoh, Pharaoh says, hey,
I understand that you can interpret dreams.
And now think about Joseph being in this position, he's standing before the most powerful person,
probably in the world at that particular time, at least in that region, no doubt, he's
the Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, the ruler, and we find that he's brought there, and this
man says to Joseph, I understand that you can interpret dreams.
And Joseph says this, it is not in me.
And what a great testimony, he says, God shall give Pharaoh an answer of peace.
And we find that after he, Joseph gave that answer to Pharaoh, Pharaoh rehearses the dream,
Joseph gives an interpretation, and we find that Joseph, as he provided that, that explanation
to the Pharaoh, that the Pharaoh is impressed with what's taking place, we'll pick it up
in verse number 33 and look at the passage this evening.
The Bible says this in verse 33, now therefore let Pharaoh, this is Joseph continuing to
speak to Pharaoh, it says, now therefore let Pharaoh look out a man discreet and wise and
set him over the land of Egypt.
Let Pharaoh do this and let him appoint officers over the land and take up the fifth part of
the land of Egypt in the seven plenteous years.
And let them gather all the food of those good years that come and lay up corn under
the hand of Pharaoh and let them keep food in the cities.
And that food shall be for store to the land against the seven years of famine, which shall
be in the land of Egypt, that the land perish not through the famine.
The thing was good in the eyes of Pharaoh and in the eyes of all his servants, and Pharaoh
said unto his servants, Can we find such in one as this, a man in whom the Spirit of
God is?
And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, For as much as God hath showed thee all this, there is
none so discreet and wise as thou art.
Thou shalt be over my house, and according unto thy word shall all my people be ruled.
Only in the throne will I be greater than thou.
And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, See, I have set thee over all the land of Egypt.
And Pharaoh took off his ring from his hand, put it upon Joseph's hand, and arrayed him
in vestures of fine linen, and put a gold chain about his neck, and he made him to ride
in the second chariot which he had.
And they cried before him, Bow thee knee, and he made him ruler over all the land of
Egypt.
If you notice the statement there in verse number 41, when Pharaoh says to Joseph, I
have set thee over all the land of Egypt, I've used that for the title this evening,
I have set thee over all the land of Egypt.
As we dig into this passage of scripture, taking notes this evening, number one, the
plan explained.
As we find that the dream is given to Joseph, Pharaoh tells him what the dream is, and the
Lord gave Joseph the ability to interpret the dream.
God gave Joseph the ability to understand that this was really one.
He tells him that he showed it to him twice, according to verse number 28, what God is
about to do.
He showeth unto Pharaoh.
And we find that Joseph had the wisdom, the ability from God to be able to interpret the
dream, to explain to him that there's going to be seven years of great plenty, but it's
going to be followed by seven years of great famine, such as the land has never seen.
And we find that Joseph was given that ability from the Lord to provide this interpretation
to Pharaoh.
Not only was Joseph given that ability from God, but we find in our text of scripture
in verses 33 through 36, that God also gave Joseph the wisdom in order to provide counsel
to Pharaoh.
It wasn't enough that Joseph was just going to provide an interpretation and then kind
of shake his hand and say, good luck with that.
You got seven years of plenty, and you got seven years of famine, and I hope it all works
out for you.
No, we find that God gave him the ability to be able to interpret the dream, but then
also gave him the wisdom in order to provide counsel to Pharaoh.
I do not believe that Pharaoh had really any idea what to do with hearing this interpretation
with all that was taking place.
And Joseph outlines a plan with great wisdom.
He gives this plan to Pharaoh.
Here's what has to be done, and God had revealed, He tells him that what's going to take place
is going to be very grievous in verse number 31.
He tells him in verse number 32 that the dream was doubled unto Pharaoh twice.
It is because the thing is established by God, and God will shortly bring it to pass.
Now I want you to think about the distress that we could have in hearing something like
what Pharaoh has just received news of.
We find that it could cause great concern and distress, but then Joseph, even really
before Pharaoh has the opportunity to respond, Joseph gives the interpretation, but then
says in verse 33, now therefore.
Now based on the interpretation of the dream, what God has revealed to you, that which God
is going to bring to pass, yes, it's very grievous, but it's going to come shortly,
and there needs to be a plan, and Joseph explains this plan.
Notice with me, he tells him to look out a man, discreet and wise, and set him over
the land of Egypt, and so the first point of Joseph's plan that is explained to Pharaoh
is that there was a need for a wise leader.
Let me say this, it's important to have leadership.
God has established leadership.
We find in every institution that God has created, He's established leadership.
If you were to think about civil government, God has established leadership for civil government.
If you think about the home, God has established leadership for the home.
If you think about the church, God has established leadership for the church.
We do not want to follow the pattern in which is explained to us in the book of Judges,
where every man does that which is right in his own sight.
No, God has given leadership, and by the way, I'm thankful for leadership, I'm thankful
that God has allowed me to be in a place of leadership, but I'm thankful for the leadership
that God allowed me to sit under, and the leaders that God brought in my life that provided
leadership to me, and here we find that Joseph, in giving this plan to Pharaoh, he begins
by speaking about the importance of having a wise leader, and we find that he continues
to outline the plan to explain to Pharaoh what needs to be done.
Notice in verse 34, let Pharaoh do this, and let him appoint officers over the land
and take up the fifth part of the land of Egypt in the seven plenteous years, and so
during those seven plenteous years, not only a wise leader, but then obviously other people
that would serve in capacity of leadership, that that leader would delegate leadership
and responsibility to, appoint officers over the land, so that they could fulfill the responsibility.
Why?
Because one man couldn't do all of it by himself, amen?
It was not for Joseph, of course we know that he's the one that will become this leader,
but Joseph in of himself was not going to be capable to do all of it, and even as you
find the leadership that I just explained, when you think about the nation of Israel,
listen, God used Moses, but God gave Moses helpers, amen?
God calls pastors, but then God equips the members of the church to come alongside and
to help the pastor fulfill the ministry that God has given to that local church, and I'm
thankful that here, even as we see this plan that God has revealed to Joseph, and the wisdom
that God has given Joseph, he tells Pharaoh, let Pharaoh do this, do you see the confidence
of Joseph as he's explaining this plan, and remember, he was just in prison.
He didn't have a whole lot of time to think about what was going on and all this.
No, no, no, God was giving him wisdom,
and God was giving him leadership,
and he's speaking to Pharaoh, and he says,
these leaders are now in this place, these officers,
and what needs to happen is during those seven
plenteous years, they need to take up a fifth part.
20% needs to be gathered during those seven years.
They're gonna be seven years of plenty.
I mentioned this last week.
Often when there's years of plenty, what do we do?
We spend it up, we use it up,
because there's years of plenty.
It's just a normal idea of humanity,
and we find that this plan that is being explained
by Joseph is very specific with regard
to during those years of plenty.
By the way, this was important,
that 20% during those years of plenty
was taken and stored up, because listen,
once you get into the years of famine,
you can't say, I wish I would have.
Man, only if I had, it's too late.
Amen?
So God gives Joseph this wisdom,
and Joseph is explaining this to Pharaoh,
notice in verse 35, and let them gather all the food
of those good years that come,
and lay up corn under the hand of Pharaoh,
and let them keep food in the cities.
And so he gives them the instruction
for what to do with storing this food,
but then in verse 36, it says,
and that food shall be for store to the land
against the seven years of famine,
which shall be in the land of Egypt.
Do you see the confidence and the certainty of Joseph?
Listen, he understood the interpretation of the dream.
This is going to happen.
This shall come to pass, and it says this
at the end of verse number 37.
Notice what he says, that the land perish not
through the famine.
See, the result of a famine would bring death.
These seven years that would be very grievous,
they would bring death if there was not a plan
that was put in place.
And God gave Joseph the ability to interpret the dream,
but we find also that God gave Joseph the wisdom
to provide counsel to Pharaoh.
Can I help us this evening?
Our God is the omniscient God.
He is the all-wise God.
You believe that tonight?
He has all wisdom, and he says to us as his children
that if any lack wisdom, let him ask of God,
who giveth to all men freely and upbraideth not.
So we have the ability to receive the wisdom of God
for our lives, for the decisions that we face,
for the circumstances that we come in,
in contact with people and so on and so forth,
and we find that God will give wisdom.
Listen, when God gives us wisdom,
and often he gives it to us through his word, right?
His word gives us wisdom, and we find that
when he gives us wisdom in his word,
and we can have confidence,
just like Joseph stood with confidence
knowing what God had revealed to him.
We don't have to be intimidated.
Think about Joseph.
He was just in prison, and now he's standing before Pharaoh.
That could be an intimidating situation.
Could it not?
But yet Joseph, as we read the text of Scripture,
it seems as if he stands in the presence of Pharaoh
with confidence, and he says,
can you imagine that he says to Pharaoh,
let Pharaoh do this?
Here's what you need to do.
I just wonder if some of the people standing by
were like, who's this guy?
He's entered into the court with this level of,
but God gave him wisdom.
I don't think he was being disrespectful.
I don't think he was being out of line,
but he had the wisdom from God,
and he spoke with boldness.
Notice with me, the plan is explained,
but then, number two, if you're taking notes
in verses 37 through 39,
notice the perception of Pharaoh.
Notice with me the perception of Pharaoh.
Notice what he says.
Pharaoh said unto his servants.
So we don't know how many servants are there,
but this is a big deal.
The scene in Genesis chapter number 41 is huge.
Pharaoh is, I mean, he is troubled because of these dreams.
No one can interpret.
The Bible tells us that he calls for all,
in verse number eight, the wise men,
that they would come, and all the magicians,
that they would come to interpret the dream,
and none of them could interpret.
So this big crowd is there.
All of these wise men, all of these magicians,
the servants of Pharaoh are there,
and they're hearing and they're seeing this,
and the Bible says that Pharaoh says unto his servants,
notice what he says in verse 38,
can we find such a one as this is?
A man in whom the Spirit of God is.
You know, Pharaoh recognized
that there was something mighty different about Joseph.
He recognized through Joseph's behavior,
through his confidence,
through his countenance and his demeanor,
something's different about this fella.
He knew that he was in Hebrew,
for we find that it was said from the butler
in verses 10 through 12,
but specifically in verse number 12,
it says, and there was there with us a young man
and Hebrew servant to the captain of the guard.
And so that's really,
Pharaoh didn't know a whole lot about Joseph,
but he knew that he was a Hebrew,
and he knew that he'd interpret two dreams,
and now Joseph stands before him,
and this man, Pharaoh, says,
can we find such a one as this is?
A man in whom the Spirit of God is.
I like that.
I'm reminded of Acts chapter number four.
I mentioned a moment ago that wonderful truth
where Peter stands up and he says,
there's no other name under heaven given among men
whereby we must be saved, the name of Jesus Christ.
And they're being questioned
and they're being interrogated in Acts chapter number four,
because of the miracle that took place
in Acts chapter number three,
the lame man at the temple,
the gate beautiful that was healed.
And Peter says, listen, if you think it's in our name,
no, no, no, it's not in our name,
it's in the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth,
that this man is made whole.
And the Bible says that those that were interrogating,
they took notice of those men,
and they knew that they were unlearned and ignorant men,
but they had been with Jesus.
What caused them to have that conclusion?
They saw the boldness of Peter.
And here, Pharaoh says that this man, Joseph,
he says that the Spirit of God is in this man.
Can you imagine?
He recognized that what his wise men
and what these magicians could not do,
that God had revealed.
Because remember, Joseph said to Pharaoh
at the very beginning, it's not in me,
God shall give Pharaoh an answer of peace.
By the way, I would say to you this evening,
that if all God did was give Joseph
the ability to interpret,
it really would not have been an answer of peace.
Because if all he could do was interpret,
hey, there's gonna be seven years of plenty
and seven years of famine, good luck with that.
It's not an answer of peace.
But he says there's seven years of plenty,
seven years of famine, and here's the plan,
here's what you do.
That's an answer of peace.
And Pharaoh, the perception of Pharaoh is here,
he looks at his servants,
he says in verse number 39,
and Pharaoh said unto Joseph,
he now turns his direction to Joseph,
and he says, for as much as God
hath showed thee all this,
there is none so discreet and wise as thou art.
He was just in prison.
Pharaoh says, there's none.
There's none so discreet and wise as thou art.
Thou shalt be over my house,
and according unto thy word shall all my people
be ruled over, only in the throne will I be greater
than thou, verse 40.
And so we see that Joseph was the man for the task.
This is what Pharaoh understood.
Pharaoh, the perception of Pharaoh
is that he looks at his servants,
he then looks at Joseph, and he says,
you're the man, you're the man for this job.
You said that we're to look out a man,
discreet and wise, and set him over the land of Egypt,
and you're standing before me, you're the man.
We find the plan explained, the perception of Pharaoh.
Notice with me the promotion of Joseph.
The promotion of Joseph.
We read verse 40, the Bible says,
thou shalt be over my house.
Can you imagine, as those that were standing there,
witnesses, I mean, hearing the very words of Pharaoh
as they look at this man, Joseph, that was just in prison,
this Hebrew that was in a pit and sold into slavery,
a man that was falsely accused, that ended up in prison.
We find that Pharaoh, this powerful, prominent man,
he says, thou, Joseph, shalt be over my house,
and according unto thy word, notice what he says,
shall all my people be ruled.
Wow, I mean, that's amazing.
He says, only in the throne will I be greater than thou.
Pharaoh said unto Joseph, see,
I have set thee over all the land of Egypt.
And Pharaoh took off his ring from his hand,
and put it upon Joseph's hand,
and arrayed him in vestures of fine linen,
and put a gold chain about his neck,
and he made him to ride in the second chariot,
which he had, and they cried before him, bow the knee,
and he made him ruler over all the land of Egypt.
Can you imagine?
I mean, this is absolutely amazing.
Joseph is now second in command over all the land of Egypt.
Only in the throne would Pharaoh be greater.
He's given him, he's delegated authority to Joseph
that he, Joseph, would, according to his word,
word, he should rule his people. This is absolutely amazing. And I want you to notice that as
we look at this portion of scripture, we'll finish chapter 41 next week, but as we look
at this portion of scripture this evening and we see the promotion of Joseph and we
understand kind of what's taking place in the life of Joseph and we're coming to this
place and of course we'll continue to see the power and authority that God's given him,
but we find that Joseph, just a few chapters earlier, we find that he's in the pit. He
simply was sent out by his father to go get a report of his brothers to see how they're
doing and we find that as he's going, his brothers see him coming and they say, hey,
here comes this dreamer. Let's kill him. They put him in a pit. The Bible tells us they
could hear him crying, but they're eating and they're just enjoying life and then they
see some men coming, some Midianites, and they say, you know, let's sell him into slavery.
He goes to Egypt, gets taken out of that pit. He's in Egypt and man, when he gets to Egypt,
he's bought, he's there in the house of Potiphar, has great opportunities. He's really proven
that God is with him. It's obvious to Potiphar and he now has such responsibility in the
house of Potiphar and we find that he's falsely accused and then sent to prison. And after
a period of time in prison, we find that he's now in the palace. Can you imagine as you
travel and look at the life of Joseph from the pit to the prison to the palace? Many
times they say, well, we like the palace, but Joseph only got to the palace through
a prison, through a pit. And oftentimes we don't like the pit or the prison, but we say,
you know, I'm okay with the palace. I'm okay with that promotion. I'm okay with that situation.
But we find that we may not understand all the twists and turns of life and surely there's
plenty of them. We may not understand all that would befall us. We may not understand
why things are happening and why we're dealing with what we're dealing with, but we must
trust the Lord. We must recognize that God is sovereign and that God is in control and
that God is in command and that God worketh all things well, that God has a plan that
is beyond your ability and my ability to fully understand. And we begin to think about the
plan of God and begin to understand that often in our lives, until we get to the end and
look back, then we can say, oh, it all makes sense now. But at times when we're just walking
one step at a time, it might not make sense. What is going on? Why are we dealing with
this? Why am I in this place? But we find that Joseph was a man, no doubt, as we've
looked at his life and studied it for several weeks now, he was a man that trusted the Lord.
He was a man that continued to serve the Lord. He was a man that did and walked in integrity
and with great character. And now we find that Pharaoh stands and says that you're the
guy, you're the man. You said to look out a man that's discreet and wise and sent him
over the land of Egypt and I'm setting you. I have set thee over the land of Egypt, over
all the land of Egypt. I'm going to set before you this evening the truth that though Pharaoh
would say in verse 41, I have set thee over all the land of Egypt, though Pharaoh would
say in verse number 43 it would be said that Pharaoh had this idea that he made him ruler
over all the land of Egypt, I would submit to you this evening that it was God that put
Joseph in that place. And it was only God that could put Joseph in that place. I mentioned
this last week and it's important that we recognize and understanding the timing of
God that Pharaoh had a dream that none could interpret and I believe that, listen, that's
not the first dream Pharaoh ever had. In fact, I'm confident that during those two years
from the time that Joseph had interpreted the dream to the butler and the time that
the Pharaoh had no one to interpret, I am confident that Pharaoh had other dreams in
those two years. I can't prove it biblically, I can't take you to a verse of scripture,
but I believe this evening that Pharaoh had other dreams. And I believe that when he had
those other dreams there were plenty of times that the magicians and the wise men, they
came in and they provided an interpretation because that was the routine, that was what
they did. But God, as he was working and as he was bringing to pass his plan, we find
that Pharaoh has this dream that none can interpret. It was at that very time that the
butler says, I remember. And God's working his plan. You know, as we look at the Bible
we could prove, and I'll look at some verses here in just a few moments, that God is the
one that set Joseph in this place of leadership. But even before we get to those verses of
scripture to prove that it was God that put him in that place, I want you to understand
that Joseph understood that it was God that put him in that place. And I want you to understand
that Joseph, when he would speak to his brothers, if you continue to look through and to understand
what's taking place, and as Joseph would reveal himself to his brothers in chapter 45, turn
over just a few pages to Genesis 45, and for sure in several weeks we'll get to this portion
of scripture and we'll dig in specifically to all the details. But I want you to understand
something very important this evening, that Joseph recognized that it was God who brought
him to this place. And in Genesis chapter 45 he reveals himself to his brothers, we're
not going to deal with all the context of it, but in verse number 7 I want you to see
what Joseph says to his brothers. Notice in verse number 7 he says, and God sent me before
you to preserve you a posterity in the earth and to save your lives by a great deliverance.
Who does Joseph recognize that sent him before? God. Notice in verse number 8, so now it was
not who? It was not you that sent me, Heather, but God. Now, help me this evening, who was
it that sold Joseph into slavery? It was his brothers, the ones that he is speaking to
in Genesis chapter 45, the ones who did not recognize him initially, remember, and we'll
look at it over the next several weeks. They stand there in the presence of Joseph, he
knows who they are, but they don't know who he is. Of course, years have passed since
their last interaction, he's grown, he's 30 at the start of being promoted to that place,
they're 7 years of plenty, so he's 38-ish, somewhere around there, before they ever come
the first time, and we find that he recognizes them, they don't recognize him, he speaks
to an interpreter, so on and so forth, and so he says, though they understand they're
the ones that sold him into slavery, he says to them, it was not you that sent me, Heather,
but God. But God. Notice in Genesis chapter number 50, we see it there in Genesis chapter
45, but then we see in Genesis chapter number 50, now at this point, the family has moved
in, they had left Canaan, of course, Jacob hears of the fact that Joseph is alive, the
family comes, then Jacob will die, and after Jacob's death, the brothers are fearful, they
think that Joseph has just kind of been kind to them for a period of time because Jacob
was still alive, and now all of a sudden Jacob's dead, and so now we're in for it, and Joseph's
gonna get us back, and so on and so forth, and so they tell Joseph about what, you know,
before Jacob died, our father commanded, saying in verse 17, so shall you say unto Joseph,
forgive, I pray thee now the trespass of thy brethren and their sin, for they did unto
thee evil, and now we pray thee, forgive the trespass of the servants of the God of thy
father, and Joseph wept when they spake unto him. His brethren also went and fell down
before his face, and they said, behold, we be thy servants, notice in verse 19 of Genesis
50, and Joseph said unto them, fear not, for am I in the place of God, but as for
you, ye thought evil against me, but notice these words, but God meant it unto good, to
bring to pass as it is this day to save much people alive. Why did his brothers go to Egypt
in the first place? Well, because they had no food there either, because the years of
famine didn't just affect Egypt, in fact, they affected the whole world. And we find
that the brothers are only, had only survived and are only alive at this point because God
sent Joseph ahead. And Joseph had this perspective and understanding that yes, indeed, you meant
evil unto me, but God meant it unto good, to bring to pass as it is this day to save
much people alive. Now I don't know what happened for those two years in the prison, the scriptures
are silent to us with regard to the daily activities of Joseph for those two years,
but two years is a long time, and we find that as we look at the whole of the story
or the life of Joseph, we believe that as we look at the account that is given that
Joseph remained faithful. And in the midst of that prison, though Joseph may not have
understood how God was going to get him out of prison and what God was going to do with
him there and why he was even in that place, we find that now after looking back, Joseph
says, I see what God was doing all along. I see what God was doing all along.
See how God's hand was in all of this.
Now understand with me that as we live daily for God, we may not understand all the twists
and turns.
But I want you to understand that God has given us this book and He's revealed so much
to us about who He is and what His plan is that we just need to keep trusting the Lord.
We just need to keep trusting that He's in control and that He has a plan and though
I might not understand that He is God and He doeth all things well and He makes no mistakes
and we trust Him.
Listen, we have a whole lot more Bible than Joseph had.
Amen?
We got a whole lot more Bible than Joseph had.
And God has revealed some wonderful things to us in His Word that help us to understand
accounts even like the life of Joseph.
And He lived day by day.
Joseph did not know when he was in the pit that that was because one day he was going
to be in the palace.
He didn't know that.
He just had to trust God day by day.
If we're not careful, we read an account like the life of Joseph and we know the end.
We know that he ends up in the palace.
And so we read through the chapters of being in the pit and being in the prison and we're
like, yeah, yeah, but he's going to get to the palace.
But Joseph was living day by day just like you are and just like I am.
We had to just keep trusting God.
I said this two weeks ago.
I believe that if Joseph would have just thrown in the towel, if he would have just decided,
you know what, I'm going to just acclimate to this culture and I'm just going to mail
it in.
I mean, I've been forsaken.
I'm in this place and all of these things that are going on, I'm just going to be…
I don't think we'd ever read the account like we do.
But Joseph remained faithful.
Notice with me some verses of Scripture that teach us.
We think about the promotion of Joseph, that it really wasn't Pharaoh, no, it was God
that put Joseph in that place.
Notice in Psalm 75, Psalm 75, look what the Bible tells us in verses 6 and 7.
Look at just a few verses that will be done this evening.
Psalm chapter 75, in verse 6 the Bible says, for promotion cometh neither from the east
nor from the west nor from the south, but God is the judge.
He putteth down one and he setteth up another.
Do you believe that tonight?
I believe that God's in control.
I believe that God is in control.
And I believe that our duty is to seek God.
Our duty is not to seek a promotion.
It wasn't for Joseph to seek a path to the palace, it was for Joseph to simply seek God.
And it wasn't for Joseph to stand before Pharaoh and Pharaoh says, hey, I understand
that you can interpret dreams, yep, and I got a problem too, I'm in prison falsely accused
and if I help you, you help me.
Again, being fastidious, but you understand, sometimes that's how we roll in life.
Nope, Joseph said it's not me, God will give you an answer of peace.
Joseph wasn't seeking a position, he wasn't seeking a promotion, he wasn't seeking a place
there in Pharaoh's cabinet, no, he was simply seeking God.
He was seeking to honor God, to exalt God.
And here the Bible says that promotion cometh neither from the east nor from the west nor
from the south, but God is the judge.
He putteth down one and setteth up another.
Notice in Psalm 105, this here is an account that is given to us, really, if you read the
entirety of this psalm, provides lots of history with regard to the nation of Israel, the people
of God there, the children of Israel.
We find in verse number 17 that begins talking to us and sharing with us about Joseph.
Notice what the Bible says in verse 17 down through verse number 24 of Psalm 105, beginning
of verse 17, the Bible says, he sent a man before them, even Joseph, who was sold for
a servant, whose feet they hurt with fetters, he was laid in iron.
Until the time that his word came, the word of the Lord tried him, the king sent and loosed
him, that's Pharaoh, even the ruler of the people and let him go free.
He made him lord of his house and ruler of all his substance to bind his princes at his
pleasure and teach his senators wisdom.
Israel also came into Egypt and Jacob sojourned in the land of Ham and he increased his people
greatly and made them stronger than their enemies.
It was God that put Joseph in that place, it was God who was working, that was bringing
his plan to pass.
Notice the book of Daniel in the fourth chapter, if you will, in Daniel chapter number 4.
In verse number 17, jumping right in the middle here, but I want you to notice what the Bible
says in Daniel 4 and 17, the Bible says, this matter is by the decree of the watchers and
the demand by thy word of the holy ones to the intent that the living may know that the
most high ruleth in the kingdom of men and giveth it to whomsoever he will and setteth
up over it the basest of men.
Notice where it says that the living may know, that the most high ruleth in the kingdom of
men.
You know, there's a lot of people living today that think they're in charge, a lot of people
living today that think it's, am I right?
The Bible says in Daniel 4, 17, that the living may know that the most high ruleth in the
kingdom of men and he giveth it to whomsoever he will and setteth up over it the basest
of men.
Wow.
We've got a lot of pride in our nation.
I think we've got a lot of pride in our churches.
God resisteth the proud, but he giveth grace unto the humble.
Talks about the basest of men.
And he says that he wants the living to know that the most high, that God is the one that
rules in the kingdom of men.
God's in control.
Listen, just as much as God was in control in Daniel's day, God's in control today.
He says, pastor, things are going out of control.
Things are just going out of control.
No, no.
God's in control.
You say, well, I don't understand all of this.
You don't need to understand all of it.
Listen, so many people are trying to understand what's going to happen next week and next
month and next year and however long from now.
But I want you to understand that God told us that we're to redeem the time, redeem the
days that he's given to us.
We're to be understanding that our life is but a vapor that appears for a little time
and then vanisheth away.
And we need to be doing what God's called us to do right now.
Because God's in control.
God rules.
God reigns.
He's got it all under control.
Notice in the book of Acts, the testimony of Stephen in Acts chapter number 7, as Stephen
would rehearse this particular period of Israel's history, in these couple of verses of scripture,
of course, he preaches a powerful message in Acts chapter number 7.
It's a good Bible message that he preaches in Acts chapter number 7.
He knew the word of God.
It was a good Bible message, but it was not well received.
People stoned him because of the message that he preached.
We find in Acts chapter number 7 and verse number 9, notice part of the passage, he says,
and the patriarchs moved with envy, sold Joseph into Egypt.
Notice that phrase, but God was with him and delivered him out of all his afflictions and
gave him favor and wisdom in the sight of Pharaoh, king of Egypt, and he made him governor
over Egypt and all his house.
Listen, this evening, we just need to keep trust in the Lord.
I may not understand all the twists and turns.
You may not understand all the twists and turns.
We may try to answer some questions.
We may try to look at some things and analyze some things.
If you're analytical, if you're a problem solver, if that's your kind of personality,
you try to look at things and figure it out and try to provide answers and what have you.
But the reality is that there are times that we just simply don't have the answers.
And God just wants us to trust him.
He just wants to know, will you trust me with your life?
Will you trust me to do in your life what will bring the most glory to me?
Now think about that for just a moment.
What's going to bring God the most glory may not be what you think or what I think is the
most comfortable or convenient path.
And what is the question that we have this evening?
Am I willing to surrender all?
Am I willing to say, Lord, my life, my life, Lord, is yours to control?
That I don't need to understand all of the twists and all the turns and all the things
that happen because, God, I'm trusting that you're moving and you're working in such a
way that you will receive honor and glory.
And if that means that I have to go to a pit, if it means I have to go to prison, if I could
speak as Paul for just a moment, if it means I have to be stoned, if it means that I have
to be shipwrecked, if it means that I have to be beaten, if it means that I have to,
you fill in the blank, God, whatever is going to bring you the most glory.
Because, God, I trust you.
I trust you.
Joseph is set...
this prominent position over the next several weeks as we continue studying through the
book of Genesis. We'll continue to see how God is using this man, Joseph. Listen, God
will use you as well. God is no respecter of persons. He uses those who trust Him fully.
And He blesses. He moves and He works. And I mentioned this last week, two weeks ago,
when our greatest concern is God's glory, and there's no telling what God will do with
your life and my life. Because we simply want to live to bring honor and glory to His precious
name. Joseph, and God gave him wisdom to not only be able to interpret a dream, but to
give counsel to Pharaoh. Pharaoh had great perception. He said, who can we find better
than you? I mean, there's none else. And the promotion. God put Joseph exactly where
God wanted Joseph to be. Took some hard places, but he got to the place where God had for
him. And oh, how God is going to use Joseph. It's a testimony to, I mean, it's a blessing
to me to read the account of the life and the ministry of Joseph. And to be challenged,
God, would you help me? Would you help us to live in obedience and submission to you?
Let's pray together. Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. I pray that we
would truly tonight surrender all. Lord, that we'd say, as that songwriter said, my life,
Lord, is yours to control. No reservations. All in. Seeking only that you would receive
glory. Not concerned about our comfort or our convenience. Only concerned about your
glory. God, would you help us to live that way? Would you help us, Lord, to see you work
as only you can work? To bring souls to saving knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ. We know
that that brings glory to your name. God, I pray that you would guide and direct in
these few moments of invitation. Help us, Lord, to be sensitive to the leadership of
the Holy Spirit of God in our lives. Well, thank you for every decision that's made.
For it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Mary's going to play quietly on the piano. As she does, the altar is open.