Well, just a couple of more weeks of singing that song and the year will be over and it's
hard to believe, but we're at the end.
In fact, tonight is, we only have one more Wednesday night of regular church services
and then we have Christmas Eve service and then we have New Year's Eve service.
And so this and next Wednesday, our last normal Wednesdays of the year, Psalm 81, Psalm 81.
And if you have your Bible with you, turn there and we've been studying through this
Psalm now for a number of weeks and I hope that you have been encouraged and strengthened
just as I have.
I'm so thankful that God has given to us his word, his word has been preserved for us.
We know that it's profitable for us.
And as we've studied through this particular Psalm, we've learned many truths with regard
to the setting of the Psalm and how it would be used by the children of Israel.
But of course, being able to make application as we go through the Psalm as well.
Last week, we studied verses 8 through 10, Psalm 81 verses 8 through 10 last Wednesday
evening and as we studied those few verses of scripture, we discovered four things.
Number one, the Lord instructs.
Aren't you thankful that God gives us his instruction?
He gives us his word.
We say that the Lord not only instructs, but he warns and what a blessing to know that
the Bible contains instruction for us, but also contains warnings for us.
And we do well to take heed to the warnings, it is our benefit.
We're thankful that God would give us warnings and then God reminds us and what a blessing.
He reminded them of who he was and what he did for them.
And oftentimes as we read the scriptures, we're reminded of how wonderful our God is
and what a blessing it is to know him and how he's saved us and how he's made us his
own and what a privilege and blessing that is.
And then we said this, the Lord satisfies and I'm so thankful for the truth that he
said, open thy mouth wide and I will fill it.
And of course we understand, he says even at the end of verse number 16, and with honey
out of the rock, should I have satisfied thee?
And we see that the Lord satisfies all that thrills my soul is Jesus is what the songwriter
said.
And he is more than life to me.
Amen.
And in his presence is fullness of joy.
And what a blessing it is to know him.
We find that God graciously provided his people with this truth, with instruction, and he
was faithful to give the word and we understand that the word was available to them.
And we saw as we looked at this text of scripture in verse eight, he says, hear all my people
and I will testify unto thee, O Israel.
And he did just that.
We talked about the word testify.
It means to make a solemn declaration, whether verbal or written, to establish some fact.
It was to give testimony for the purpose of communicating to others, a knowledge of something
that was not known to them.
And God did provide them with truth.
We're going to look at verses 11 and 12, but before we do, I want to read to you and hold
your place there, but read with me, turn to the book of Deuteronomy, if you will.
Deuteronomy chapter 30, Deuteronomy chapter 30, I'm going to read a few verses of scripture
here as we get into the message this evening.
But we find that God graciously provided his word and he desired that his people would
hearken unto him.
In Deuteronomy chapter number 30 and verse number 11, notice what the Bible says here
in Deuteronomy 30, for this commandment, which I command thee this day, it is not hidden
from thee, neither is it far off.
Aren't you thankful for that?
He said, it is not hidden from thee, nor is it far off.
He says in verse 12, it is not in heaven that thou shouldest say, who shall go up for us
to heaven and bring it unto us that we may hear it and do it.
Neither is it beyond the sea that thou shouldest say, who shall go over the sea for us and
bring it unto us that we may hear it and do it.
But the word is very nigh unto thee in thy mouth and in thy heart that thou mayest do
it.
See, I have set before thee this day life and good and death and evil, and that I command
thee this day to love the Lord thy God, to walk in his ways and to keep his commandments
and his statutes and his judgments that thou mayest live and multiply.
And the Lord thy God shall bless thee in the land whither thou goest to possess it.
But if thine heart turn away so that thou wilt not hear, but shall be drawn away and
worship other gods and serve them, I denounce unto you this day that you shall surely perish,
and that you shall not prolong your days upon the land whither thou passest over Jordan
to go to possess it.
Verse 19, I call heaven and earth to record this day against you, that I have set before
you life and death, blessing and cursing.
Therefore choose life, that both thou and thy seed may live, that thou mayest love
the Lord thy God, and that thou mayest obey his voice, and that thou mayest cleave unto
him.
For he is thy life, and the length of thy days, that thou mayest dwell in the land which
the Lord swear unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give them.
We find as we look at this passage in Deuteronomy 30, as the people of God are preparing to
enter into the land of promise, that God is pleading with his people to hear and receive
the instruction to hearken.
He says in verse number 17, but if thine heart turn away, notice, so that thou wilt not hear.
And we come to Psalm 81, and as we continue studying through this portion of Scripture
in this evening, as we examine verses 11 and 12, we discover that the Bible tells us
that God's people hearkened not.
In fact, as you read verse number 11 in Psalm 81, it is a sad verse, a sad commentary with
regard to the heart of the people of God.
Notice with me in Psalm 81, verse number 11, the Bible says, but my people would not hearken
to my voice, and Israel would none of me.
So I gave them up unto their own heart's lust, and they walked in their own counsels.
Aren't those some sad verses of Scripture?
God provided for them everything that they needed.
God gave to them all of the instruction, all of the warning.
He gave them everything that they would need, and he was desirous that they would hearken.
He said in verse number 8, hear, O my people, and I will testify unto thee, O Israel, if
thou wilt hearken unto me in this evening, but my people, verse 11, would not hearken
to my voice.
I've titled the message this evening simply this, they hearkened not.
They hearkened not.
The word hearken, we reviewed this last week, but it means to attend or to regard, to give
heed to what is uttered, to observe or to obey.
As we look at these two verses of Scripture, it's important that we note, first of all,
as we look here at verse number 11, the Bible says, but my people.
I want you to focus on that with me just for a moment this evening, because God said to
them in verse number 10, I am the Lord thy God.
And we mentioned last week the blessed reminder that God gave to them in verse number 10 of
who he was to them, and then as he continues in verse number 10, what he did for them.
And we're reminded this evening that he is the Lord, our God, and in verse number 11,
he says, but my people would not hearken to my voice.
And when I think about the statement when he says, my people, God is not talking about
the Gentile nations.
God is not speaking about those other people groups of the world.
He says, my people.
I think about the New Testament truth, if we were to make a parallel, if you will, and
we were to look at this verse in verse number 11, it's not that God's talking about lost
people would not hearken to him.
He's saying, save people, my children, mine, the ones that I redeemed, the ones that I
paid for their sin debt, my people, those that call me Lord and master, my people hearken
not.
They would not hearken to my voice.
I think about the truth that there are times in our lives, no doubt you've experienced
it just as I have, that we can get bothered or annoyed with the behavior or the belief
of lost people.
We can see how they behave, we can see how they believe, and we can get annoyed by it,
we can get bothered by it, and how can they think that way?
How can they, and we understand, God's told us in 1 Corinthians 2 that the natural man
receiveth not the things of the spirit of God.
For their foolishness unto him neither can he know them because they're spiritually discerned.
And so even though we have that verse of Scripture, it doesn't prevent us at all times
from getting annoyed at some of the belief and behavior of lost people.
But I want you to consider this evening that just as Old Testament Israel, there are times
in which we as saved people don't hearken to the voice of God.
And he's not talking about the Gentile nations, he's not talking about all these other people
groups, he's talking about his people, the ones that he brought out of Egypt, the ones
that for all that time while they were in Egypt, they were crying for deliverance and
they were overwhelmed with all that they were facing, and we find that God brought them
out and God instructed them, but they would not hearken.
And so we find this evening that as we consider that he's talking about my people, that we
must make as we've even had really kind of the thought in recent messages of having that
own examination of our own lives.
How are we responding to what God has given to us in his word?
Because he's concerned about us as his people.
We notice how God describes the behavior of his people in verse number 11.
He says this, they would not hearken to my voice.
It wasn't that they did not have the truth.
It was not that they were unaware of what they were supposed to do.
It was not that God didn't send prophets, that God didn't have faithful men.
It was that they made a decision to not obey the voice of the Lord.
And they would not hearken to my voice.
Can you imagine the God of the universe, our God, creator God, he has provided all
things for us and he's given us good instruction and he sits there and he says, but my people,
they would not hearken to my voice.
No doubt if you have children, there've been times in which your children did not hearken
to your voice.
And as a parent, it bothered you.
And you made a decision that you would correct said behavior because they were to hearken
to your voice.
And even if you don't have children, you can kind of relate to that principle and that
application.
And we find that throughout the scriptures, the Bible talks about how God deals with us.
He chastens us and he desires that we would hearken to his voice.
But we notice as we go through the passage this evening that he's not going to force
us to.
He continues in verse number 11 and notice the phrase at the end of verse number 11,
in Israel would none of me.
You know, the idea that really this phrase is carrying is that they wanted nothing to
do with God.
I think about the truth when Jesus says in the gospels, why call us now me Lord, but
you do not what I say.
We begin to consider this evening that many times there's this idea, listen, the children
of Israel, they wanted deliverance.
Did they not?
I mean, you can go back, we can read, we can take the time to go back to the book of Exodus
and we can read of all that they dealt with and all that they were faced with and all
the struggles and trials and how they cried out, but they wanted the deliverance, but
they did not want to follow the Lord as Lord.
And we see sometimes the same thing happening in New Testament Christianity.
You find that there's individuals that you can talk to about the Lord and about their
need for Christ and salvation, and obviously there's nothing that we can do to get saved
as far as our works are concerned.
It's Christ alone.
If you try to mingle works with it, that's not true redemption.
We're redeemed through the blood of Christ, but you, how many times you see people and
understand, oh, they recognize, I can't, there's nothing I can do about that.
I'm going to die and go to hell.
I need to be saved.
But then you start talking to them about godly living and all of a sudden they don't want
a master.
Somebody said this, too many people today want a savior, but not a master.
Can I tell you this evening, I'm thankful that he's my savior and he's my master.
And by the way, he's a good master.
He's a good Lord.
The truth that he gives us, the instruction that he provides us with, it's for our benefit.
It's for our good.
We do well that we take heed thereunto, according to what he tells us in Psalm 19.
And so we find this evening that Israel is in this situation that God says, my people,
they would not hearken to my voice.
It wasn't that they couldn't.
It wasn't that they were unaware of it.
We just looked at the passage in Deuteronomy chapter 30.
God gave it to them.
He set before them the truth and he gave it to them and he pleaded with them, but he
gave them a choice.
And it says that Israel would none of me.
They wanted nothing to do with God.
I notice as we look at the text of scripture, the unfortunate consequences, according to
verse number 12, the Bible says this in Psalm 81 and verse 12, so I gave them up unto their
own hearts lust and they walked in their own counsels.
The consequences, the unfortunate consequences as we see in verse number 12, we notice that
the Bible says, so I gave them up.
That's what God says.
God's not going to force you to obey him.
He's not going to force you to get saved.
He's not going to force you to live for him.
He's just not going to force you to do it.
He wants you to.
It's best for us.
He will send warning.
You look at the nation of Israel, if we're to study their history, you can find that
he sent prophet after prophet, voice after voice that would come and give them a message
and call them to repentance and call them to obedience and call them to return.
God says, return to me repeatedly, but he doesn't force them.
He doesn't force them.
And the same is true for us this evening.
He doesn't force us.
You came to church tonight because you decided to.
You made a choice.
You read your Bible today because you decided to.
He didn't make you read your Bible.
He didn't make you come to church.
He's not going to make you give an offering or do like, it's a choice that we make, but
it's in our best interest to abide in him and to follow his word.
And so the Bible says, so I gave them up.
Notice, I mean, just think about the phraseology and consider with me the fact that God, how
difficult this passage of scripture is for us to really just wrap our mind around that
God loved them so much and God gave them all things.
He gave them everything that they would need, but they rebelled.
They were a stiff necked people.
That's how they're described.
God says, I gave them up.
I gave them up to what?
Notice what it says, unto their own hearts lust.
In other words, he let them do what they wanted to do.
He let them do what they wanted to do.
He says this in verse number 12, and they walked in their own counsels.
They didn't take the counsel that God had provided, the all wise God, the one who created
all things, the one that brought them out of Egypt.
I mean, think about it.
They could not, there was nothing they could do to get out of Egypt themselves.
God did for them what they could not do for themselves.
And then all of a sudden, we don't need God anymore.
We don't need, we don't want your instruction.
We don't want you to tell us what to do.
We don't want to follow your way.
And God gives them up to their own hearts lust, and they walked in their own counsels.
And we begin to think about the, obviously the tragic, unfortunate results, and we'll
see them next week as we finish out the chapter in verses 13 through 16.
But we just pause for a moment this evening, and we begin to look at this, and we understand,
listen, God will work, and God does a variety of things to call us back to himself, save
forcing us to.
He's given us a free will.
He wants us to live for him.
Notice if you will, turn to the book of Proverbs chapter 16.
As we consider these unfortunate consequences, the Bible says to their own hearts lust, and
they walked in their own counsels.
And look in Proverbs 16 if you will, and I want you to notice what the Bible tells us
in Proverbs 16 and verse number 25.
In fact, why don't we just back up.
Look at verse number two with me.
The Bible says this, all the ways of a man are clean in his own eyes.
But then notice this, but the Lord weigheth the spirits.
Commit thy works unto the Lord, and thy thoughts shall be established.
Notice verse seven, when a man's ways please the Lord, he maketh even his enemies to be
at peace with him.
That's something that God is able to do.
That's a result, a blessing, a miraculous provision that God gives to those that are
walking and living in a way that's pleasing God.
It says this in verse 25, there is a way that seemeth right unto a man, but the end thereof
are the ways of death.
The Bible says that he gave them up to their own heart's lust and they walked in their
own counsels.
We see that here it says there's a way that seemeth right unto a man, but the end thereof
are the ways of death.
You know, there are times in which we logically reason and we analyze a situation and we begin
to try to reach a conclusion and maybe based on some factors and whatever the criteria
is that we're using to reach our decision, but if we fail to take into consideration
the truth of God's word, we're going down a bad path.
Because it's not based upon your reasoning or my reasoning or our logic and what makes
sense and what's no.
Many times you find that God's ways, his ways are not our ways.
Amen?
And so sometimes you think the way up and you say, well, humble yourself.
You see these paradoxes, if you will,
within the scriptures, and you find here
that he says that the end thereof are the ways of death.
I think about the truth of Proverbs 3,
verses five and six, verses that many of us
could quote this evening, and the Bible says,
"'Trust in the Lord with all thine heart,
"'and lean not unto thine own understandings.
"'In all thy ways acknowledge him,
"'and he shall direct thy paths.'"
Those are verses that many of us tonight could quote,
but it's not about being able to quote
some verses of scripture,
it's about living the principle of the verses.
And we find that he goes through the text in Proverbs 3
and gives us a whole number of things
and areas in which we're to trust the Lord with,
and it's impactful and powerful for us,
and we find that that's exactly opposite
of what the children of Israel were doing
according to what we read in Psalm 81.
Proverbs 19, look what the Bible says in Proverbs 19.
In Proverbs 19, in verse number 21,
the Bible says,
"'There are many devices in a man's heart.
"'Nevertheless, the counsel of the Lord,''
notice those last three words,
"'that shall stand.'"
I mentioned this on Sunday morning
as we're going through the book of 2 Corinthians,
and we were looking there at that first section
of the 13th chapter as it wraps up,
and Paul's talking about,
I'm coming to you, this is the third time.
And as he's talking about,
listen, God's word doesn't change.
The counsel of the Lord, that shall stand.
And the Bible says that they walked in their own counsels.
They didn't walk in the counsel of the Lord.
Again, it wasn't a fact that they didn't know it
or that they didn't have it.
It's not that God didn't make it available.
It was just simply that they didn't do it.
They hearken not.
They chose not to listen to what God said,
to obey and submit.
They thought that there was a better way.
How many times have you heard somebody say to you
in some arena of life,
well, there's a better way to do that.
And sometimes we might sit back
and maybe the circumstances allow for us
to just sit back and let the individual find out
the hard way that the way that I tried to instruct you
is the way to do it.
And they think there's a better way
and we're gonna let them learn.
We're gonna let them find out
why we were doing it the way we were doing it.
And sometimes in life, if we're not careful,
we can look at the scriptures
and how many times young people have this perspective.
Well, that's kind of an outdated approach
or an outdated look.
And there's a better way to do this now.
We're in 2025, almost 2026, there's a better way.
No, God's way is the best way.
You can't improve on God's way.
It's just not possible.
Now, there are some things that we've been able to improve
on through the centuries.
And as you have technological advances
and you can improve in certain things.
And if you use the internet today,
I'm sure that you're glad you don't have the dial up
that we had in 1999 and all of the nonsense
of what was going on and all the do, do, do, do.
And the kids, they don't even know what that stuff is.
And you give them a rotary phone today
and they don't know what to do with it.
How do you dial this thing and so on and so forth.
There's advances, okay.
But that's just temporal things.
We start talking about eternal things.
You can't improve upon God's word.
God's word is perfect.
God's word not only is perfect,
but God's word, it's for all time.
The truth is that God's word is relevant
for every people in every generation.
We even looked on Sunday morning how that Paul
goes all the way back to the Old Testament law
to apply a principle to the believers there in Corinth
and how we see that all of God's word is applicable for us
and it's relevant to us.
And we understand that God has given to us his word.
As I look at Psalm 81 and I consider the truth
that God gives us with regard to this summary
of how his people responded and really the pleading
that God had for him that he says in verse eight
that hear all my people and I will testify
unto thee, O Israel, if thou wilt hearken unto me.
He told him in verse number 10 as we studied last week,
open thy mouth wide and I will fill it.
But then you notice, but my people would not
hearken to my voice and Israel would none of me.
So I gave them up unto their own hearts lust
and they walked in their own councils.
You know how destructive that was for the children of Israel?
It reminds me just reading these two verses of scripture,
it reminds me much of the period of the judges.
When the Bible says of that era of Israel's history,
every man did that which was right in his own sight.
That's what the scriptures tell us about the book of Judges.
And you'll find in the book of Judges,
this vicious cycle that's repeated in the book of Judges.
And it's that the people of God
wanted nothing to do with God.
They wanted to do their own thing.
They didn't wanna hearken to God.
They wanted to do what they wanted to do.
They wanted to go their own way.
They wanted to walk in their own councils
and do what they thought was best.
And then before long, they would face great opposition.
They would be under great oppression
and they would be really enslaved.
And then what?
Well, then they'd cry out to God.
Aren't you thankful that God's gracious and He's merciful?
I'm so thankful.
They would call out to God, they would cry out to God.
And for a little while after God would raise up a judge
and provide them with deliverance,
there was a time in which maybe
they would have a time of peace
and they would live in some level of obedience to God's word
but before long, you would find that cycle repeated again.
And as we begin to think about this commentary,
if you will, for Israel and for their history,
it saddens my heart.
I can't imagine the heart of God
and understanding I've given you this,
which is good for you, but you would not.
You wanted nothing to do with me.
So I gave you up and then God watches them
deal with all of the consequences of their own behavior.
All of the adversities that they suffered
because of their disobedience.
The Bible says that the way of the transgressor is hard.
God does chasten His children.
He chastens for the purpose of restoration.
And I'm reminded as we consider the truth for us
as New Testament believers,
as this is really a commentary of looking back
and stating about how they behaved.
I'm reminded of the truth for us of how we are to behave.
Look, if you will, over the book of 2 Peter quickly
as we close this evening.
And I want you to look at 2 Peter chapter one.
Yeah, chapter one.
And in 2 Peter chapter number one,
as we consider this evening,
this is the history
of Israel in Psalm 81.
The God of heaven is telling us what He provided for them,
what He did for them and how they responded.
The history is written.
Amen.
You're not gonna rewrite it.
You can't rewrite history.
People try to and they're continuously trying to,
but the history is there.
We can read the Old Testament.
We can see it.
But I want you to look at 2 Peter chapter number one
as we try to make application for ourselves
because Psalm 90 tells us that we live our days
our days are like a tale that is told.
And so you have a story and I have a story.
If we could look at our lives,
that's like a tale that's being told as we live our lives.
The story of your life and the story of my life
is being written right now.
And at some point, the story of your life
and the story of my life, there's gonna be history.
And I wonder, are they gonna say they hearken to God
or they hearken not?
In 2 Peter chapter one,
Peter is talking about an experience that he had.
In verse number 16, he says,
for we have not followed cunningly devised fables
when we made known unto you the power and coming
of our Lord Jesus Christ,
but were eyewitnesses of his majesty.
For he received from God the Father honor and glory
when there came such a voice to him
from the excellent glory.
This is my beloved son in whom I am well pleased.
And this voice, which came from heaven, we heard
when we were with him in the Holy Mount.
He's talking about the Mount of Transfiguration.
Peter, James, and John, they had the privilege
of being there and seeing and experiencing this.
But Peter goes on in verse number 19 and he says this,
we have also a more sure word of prophecy.
And then notice these next words,
where unto ye do well that ye may know.
And ye take heed as unto a light that shineth
in a dark place until the day dawn
and the day star arise in your hearts,
knowing this first that no prophecy of the scriptures
of any private interpretation,
for the prophecy came not in old time by the will of man,
but holy men of God spake as they were moved
by the Holy Ghost.
And so we find that Peter is saying, listen,
we heard the voice of God.
God. And he did. We go back to the Gospels and we can read it. We can understand.
Peter's referring to that great experience that he had at the Mount of
Transfiguration and he says, but we have a more sure word of prophecy. Listen,
there's people today that are looking for new prophecy, more prophecy,
something different. God's given us what he's gonna give us. Forever, O Lord, thy
word is settled in heaven. He's given to us all that he's gonna give us. He's
given to us the Bible. He's given to us the Holy Spirit. And here Peter says,
whereunto ye do well that ye take heed. And then he says this, he uses really
this analogy to help us to understand. He says, as unto a light that
shineth in a dark place. And I know I've used this example before as I've looked
at this passage of Scripture, but the reality this evening is if we were to
turn all of the lights off in this building tonight, it is dark outside.
We're to pull these shades and turn off all the lights, it'd be dark in here. I've
walked through here at night when it's dark and it's dark. And I guarantee you
that if we turned on a light somewhere in this sanctuary that everybody would
look to where that light is without even really thinking about it. It's just a
natural response. That that light would turn on and we'd all look at that light.
Have you ever been to the caverns? You ever go down there? And they take you
down there in that tour and you see all those great things that's so cool and so
neat and whatever. And then they cut the lights off, right? They turn them off and
they tell you to put your hand in front of it. You can't see it. Have you done it?
I've been down there and I'm like, I think I can see my fingers. And I can't
really, but I'm trying to get my brain to think I can see them, you know, and
whatever. And then all of a sudden there's a light and your eyes are
drawn to it. And Peter says in that same way, you do well, ye do well that you
take heed. What is that hearkening? It's hearkening. And God says of his people,
they hearken not. He's not talking about the Gentile nations. He's not talking
about lost people. He's talking about his people. And he says, my people, they would
not hearken to my voice. This evening, I hope that all of us would resolve. It's
not gonna be said of me, but I'm not gonna hearken to God's Word. God saved me.
He loves me. Everything that he's given to me is for my benefit. Every word of
this book is for my benefit. And I'm gonna take heed. I'm gonna
follow. I'm gonna obey. God, help me to follow you. Help me to obey you. Help me
to be a doer of your Word. Let it not be said of any one of us as it was of those
in Psalm 81, they hearken not to my voice. Let's pray. Father, we love you this evening.
We thank you for loving us. We thank you for giving us truth.