and I mentioned to you this morning that we'd be here
in Psalm 119, you see it in the bulletin,
and we're looking at verses nine through 16.
The 119th Psalm is a psalm all about the word of God,
it's all about the Bible, and you read through this psalm
and you find that the psalmist mentions many things
about his interaction with the word of God
and how he refers to the Bible in so many different ways
throughout this psalm and different declarations
that he makes that we find throughout the psalm
with regard to his relationship to the Bible
and the way in which he'll study it and learn it
and memorize it and so on and so forth, share it.
And so this evening, the psalm is broken up into stanzas,
and you can see that if you have a Bible
that has it outlined that way.
And so the first stanzas, verses one through eight,
we'll be looking at verses nine through 16,
which is the second stanza in this psalm,
and looking just at these verses this evening
specifically for the message,
of course, we'll reference other portions of the psalm,
but I want you to notice in verse number nine,
the Bible says a familiar verse of scripture,
wherewithal shall a young man cleanse his way?
By taking heed thereto according to thy word.
With my whole heart have I sought thee.
Isn't that a great statement?
With my whole heart I have sought thee.
Oh, let me not wander from thy commandments.
Thy word have I hid in mine heart
that I might not sin against thee.
Blessed art thou, O Lord, teach me thy statutes.
What a great desire.
Teach me thy statutes.
I wanna know your word.
Verse 13, with my lips have I declared
all the judgments of thy mouth.
I've rejoiced in the way of thy testimonies
as much as in all riches.
I will meditate in thy precepts
and have respect unto thy ways.
I will delight myself in thy statutes.
I will not forget thy word.
As we look at this psalm,
my focus is fixed on the latter statement
of verse number 10, when the Bible says,
oh, let me not wander from thy commandments.
What a great desire and prayer of the psalmist.
Let me not wander from thy commandments.
If I were to title the message this evening,
you see in the bulletin,
that's the phrase that I've picked
from these verses of scripture
to title our thought this evening,
the sermon for tonight.
Mr. Robert Robinson is the author of a familiar hymn.
It's the hymn, Come Thou Fount.
How many of you know the song?
You've heard it, you've no doubt,
you've had the opportunity to sing it
in a service at some point.
Many of us enjoy singing that song
and we're familiar with it.
And the third verse of that song says this,
oh, to grace, how great a debtor,
daily I'm constrained to be.
Let thy goodness, like a fetter,
bind my wandering heart to thee.
The songwriter said, prone to wander,
Lord, I feel it.
Prone to leave the God I love.
Here's my heart, Lord.
Take and seal it.
Seal it for thy courts above.
We're familiar with the song.
And that third verse is so powerful and so important.
It is said, it is documented,
that later in this man's life, Mr. Robinson,
he was riding in a stagecoach
and as he was riding in a stagecoach,
one of the other passengers in that stagecoach
was a young lady that started singing that hymn.
And as she began to sing the hymn,
she looked at him and she asked him,
what do you think about that song?
Not knowing that he was the man that authored the song.
He acknowledged that he was the author
and here's what he said.
I would give a thousand worlds if I had them,
if I had them, if I could feel now as I felt then.
It is said that he wandered in his later years.
He got away from the Lord.
He penned those words, prone to wander,
Lord, I feel it.
Prone to leave the God I love.
And he said, if I could,
if I had a thousand worlds that I could give,
I would give them if I could feel now how I felt then.
And the Psalmist says in verse number 10,
oh, let me not wander from thy commandments.
We spent all year studying through the book
of 1st and 2nd Timothy and we've had as our theme
for this calendar year continue.
We've had the opportunity to sing that theme song
as Pierre so adequately said this evening,
if you don't know it by now,
well, then you're not gonna learn it.
We only got a couple more times to sing it.
And the reality is that the song encourages us
with the same thought that we have from our theme
for this year that we find as Paul is giving
this instruction to Timothy, continue, continue.
But Timothy, as he gets to the end of his life
or Paul, when he gets to the end of his life,
he says to Timothy as we dealt with a couple of weeks ago
on Sunday morning, that he had finished his course.
And he had kept the faith and he had done
what God had instructed and called him to do
and he finished and the reality is that when we look
at this verse of scripture and we look
at the greater context, he says,
oh, let me not wander from thy commandments.
I hope that it would be a desire for every one of us
this evening that we would say, I don't wanna wander
from the commandments of the Lord.
I don't wanna get away.
And that word wander in verse number 10,
it carries with it the idea to err,
to stray or to go astray.
And to begin to think about those,
the temptations that we face, the enemy
that's constantly pulling us away
from what God has given us to do
and the work that he's clearly commanded us to do
and living in obedience to God's word.
And we must have our heart's desire, Lord,
as the psalmist said, let me not wander
from thy commandments.
As we look at this stanza, we find that it begins
with a question.
That question is then answered,
followed by both actions and resolutions.
And we'll mention the question in verse number nine
and then we'll look at the actions and the resolutions
that the psalmist gives us within this particular stanza
to help us understand the question
and really the answer, our response.
It says this, wherewithal shall a young man
cleanse his way?
You know, the Bible says much about our way,
our walk.
We find that here, even in this psalm,
in the first several verses, there's references
to the way of the individual.
Notice in verse number one,
blessed are the undefiled in the way
who walk in the law of the Lord.
Blessed are they that keep his testimonies
and that seek him how with the whole heart.
They also do no iniquity.
They walk in his ways.
We find that in verse number five,
the psalmist says, oh, that my ways
were directed to keep thy statutes.
What a desire.
That my ways were directed to keep thy statutes.
We understand that the question is asked
in verse number nine, wherewithal shall a young man
cleanse his way?
By taking heed thereto according to thy word.
The psalmist is rejoicing throughout this particular psalm
for the reality that he had the scriptures.
He had the portion of God's word that had been given.
He makes the statement forever, oh Lord,
thy word is settled in heaven in verse 89.
In verse 97, he says, oh, how love I thy law.
It is my meditation all the day.
He understands and he mentions how God's law
and how the testimonies and statutes
as he refers to them throughout the psalm,
he understands the impact that they have
on his life and on the believer's life.
Truly this evening, as we're told
in 2 Timothy chapter three, God's word is profitable.
God's word gives us the direction
and the counsel that we need.
God's word provides us with the truth that we need
as we travel through this world,
as we live this Christian life.
God's word is that lamp that he says
in verse 105 of this same familiar hymn.
He says, thy word is a lamp unto my feet
and a light unto my path.
I was talking even with someone yesterday
at the open house and we're talking about
just the path before us and I said,
well, remember, thy word is a lamp unto my feet.
It's a light and we find that truth in God's word
but we understand that that lamp that's for my feet,
that light for my path, that really God's word
provides that light for us to take that next step.
And really that's what we need to be concerned about
is what is the next step that I need to take?
What's the next step for me as I'm seeking
to follow the Lord, as I want my ways
to be pleasing in his sight?
What is that next step for me?
So often what happens is people wanna know
500 steps from now, what is going to be
and what my path is going to look like
but the reality is that we're not.
prepared for that far in advance.
Because we take one step at a time and we're stepping in the light,
and we're obeying the Lord, and we're following the direction that He provides us with,
then God gives light for the next step, and for the next step, and for the next step,
and we follow Him day by day, step by step, we walk with Him.
And what a joy.
And so we find that this question is answered by taking heed,
thereto according to thy word.
I'm familiar with the thought, if you turn over to the New Testament,
look over at what Peter says in 2 Peter, notice if you will,
as Peter is writing here and he's giving truth,
and Peter had the privilege of walking with the Lord.
He had the privilege of hearing the Lord Jesus Christ teach.
I mean, he heard Him with his own voice.
His own ears heard the voice of Jesus, and he heard Jesus teach,
and he heard Him preach, and we find that Peter,
not only did he hear the Lord Jesus Christ,
but Peter was privileged to go to the Mount of Transfiguration.
And in 2 Peter chapter 1, that's what he's referencing.
He's referencing that event, that experience that he had
when Peter, James, and John went up on the Mount of Transfiguration,
not only had they had the opportunity to hear the messages
from the Lord Jesus Christ, but on the Mount of Transfiguration,
they heard the voice of God.
And Peter is writing, and notice in verse 16 of 2 Peter chapter 1,
for we have not followed cunningly devised fables,
when we made known unto you the power and coming of our Lord Jesus Christ,
but were eyewitnesses of His majesty.
For He received from God the Father honor and glory,
when there came such a voice to Him from the excellent glory,
this is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased.
Notice in verse 18, in this voice which came from heaven,
what does he say? We heard. We heard.
When we were with Him in the holy mount.
But then notice what he says in verse 19.
We have also a more sure word of prophecy.
And then he says this, whereunto ye do well that ye take heed.
That you take heed.
Remember the answer to the question in Psalm 119 in verse number 9,
wherewithal shall a young man cleanse his way,
by taking heed thereto according to thy word.
And here Peter says, ye do well that ye take heed,
as unto a light that shineth in a dark place,
until the day dawn and the day star arise in your hearts,
knowing this first, that no prophecy of the scriptures
of any private interpretation, for the prophecy came not in old time
by the will of man, but holy men of God spake,
as they were moved by the Holy Ghost.
And I'm so thankful that all scripture is given by inspiration of God.
But the reality is just because we know what this book is,
just because we know the power of this book,
just because we know the fact that this book is profitable,
does not mean that we will necessarily take heed
to the truth contained within the book.
No, we ought to. Don't you agree?
I mean, we should.
We ought to say, well, that's what the Bible says,
and therefore I'm just going to do it because that's what God says.
But we're humans.
Sometimes we lean on our own understanding.
We try to figure out things.
Listen, there's your flesh and your spirit in enmity one with the other.
Amen? Have you found it to be the case?
Remember what Paul said in the book of Romans?
The things that I would, I do not. The things that I would not, that I do.
There's this great conflict.
And we find that the psalmist says,
by taking heed thereto according to thy word.
As we begin to look at this particular stanza within Psalm 119
and understand what the psalmist is desiring
and how he's approaching this,
I want you to look at these actions.
There's four actions followed by three resolutions.
And so really seven thoughts this evening,
but they'll be brief and we'll get through it.
And I want you to see the actions.
The first action is in verse number 10.
Because the answer to the question is by taking heed according to thy word,
he says, therefore, number one action is this in verse 10,
with my whole heart have I sought thee.
You know, God's not interested in half-hearted worship.
He wants our whole heart.
We referenced already back in verse number two
where the Bible says, blessed are they that keep his testimonies
and that seek him with the whole heart.
And so now the psalmist understanding the principle that is given in verse number two,
that those that would seek the Lord with their whole heart will be blessed,
he says this, this action that he's going to take with my whole heart,
have I sought thee.
I want you to think about seeking the Lord
and how important it is that we seek God,
that we seek his word.
We find that the Bible mentions,
as we begin to think about this idea of seeking the Lord,
seek ye first the kingdom of God, right?
That's what the Bible says.
So when you think about this idea of seeking the Lord,
and I think about Psalm 42,
and you might want to turn over there very quickly,
it's a psalm that you're familiar with,
but I want you to see what the psalmist says in Psalm 42
with regard to this idea of seeking the Lord,
and he says, with my whole heart have I sought thee.
And here's what the psalmist says in Psalm 42 in verse number one,
as the heart panteth after the water brooks,
so panteth my soul after thee, O God.
My soul thirsteth for God, for the living God.
When shall I come and appear before God?
The psalmist says in Psalm 63 in verse number one,
notice what the Bible says, O God, thou art my God.
Notice, early will I seek thee.
My soul thirsteth for thee, my flesh longeth for thee
in this dry and thirsty land where no water is.
I wonder, if we evaluate our lives,
how would we describe our seeking of the Lord?
How much are we in this idea that we find with the psalmist
that he's with my whole heart have I sought thee?
You know, when you get your heart into something, it's evident.
Have you not seen that in life? Have you not experienced that?
You know, we use the phraseology, they're going through the motions.
Have you ever seen something like that?
You say, their heart's not really in it.
And you can tell that.
And can I submit it to you this way?
You know when your whole heart's not in it too.
We do.
We know when we're just kind of coasting,
we're just going through the motions.
And God wants our whole heart.
Can I say it this way also?
God deserves our whole heart.
He deserves that we would say that I'm going to seek him with my whole heart.
I think about the truth of God's word,
and even in this psalm, in Psalm 119,
where the psalmist talks about really the treasures that he can have
and how he seeks the truths from God's word.
He says in verse 162 of the psalm,
I rejoice that thy word is one that findeth great spoil.
And you think about an individual,
and if you could think about someone that's searching for some treasure,
and they're searching with their whole heart,
I mean, they're all in. They're fully vested.
They're going to pull no stops.
I mean, they're all in to find that treasure.
Can I tell you that the Lord is far greater
than any treasure that you could find on this earth.
I was sharing with someone this morning on the way out.
They asked me a question that was a great question,
and I answered the question by quoting a verse of Scripture.
And I said, absolutely, as an answer to their question,
because the Bible says in His presence is fullness of joy.
And the question was this.
Have you ever had a time with the Lord
when you just feel like you don't want to leave?
You don't want to stop.
You've been praying, and you've been reading,
and you just feel like, I don't want to leave.
I'm having such revival, if we could use that word.
Yes, because in His presence is fullness of joy.
And the psalmist says, with my whole heart have I sought.
Notice the second action, if you will.
In verse number 11, the Bible says this.
Thy word have I hid in mine heart.
Have you ever tried memorizing Scripture?
Yes or no?
Is it easy or hard?
Hard.
You know it gets harder the older you get?
How many of you found that to be the case?
I mean, I'm just being honest.
These little kids, they can memorize verses pretty quickly.
And when we were younger, our minds were a little sharper.
We were maybe able to memorize things a little quicker as well.
But I want you to think about this idea
of hiding God's word in our hearts.
Sometimes I think we do a disservice for our kids,
and I've been guilty of it even during some VBSs
where maybe you give out some prizes and what have you
for memorizing these verses,
and oftentimes they're not truly memorizing the verses,
they're just reciting them.
And they just look, look, look, look, look, look.
Okay, I can tell you, for God's love of the world,
and they've got to say it so fast because they can't,
because it's going to be gone in a second, right?
No, no, no.
That's not the idea of hiding God's word in your heart.
When you hide God's word in your heart,
it's something that you're able to recall.
It's something that in that moment,
as I mentioned this morning from Matthew 4,
in that temptation moment that you can say,
as it is written, because you've memorized God's Word.
Can I tell you, when you see the psalmist saying,
thy word have I hid in mine heart,
that requires commitment, dedication, work.
It requires time.
There have been some that say,
well, it's just too hard to memorize verses.
You know there's a lot of hard things in life that we do?
Honestly, there are a lot of hard things in life that we do.
So just because something is hard,
when it comes to the Christian life,
doesn't mean we should shy away from it and say,
well, it's just too hard to memorize verses,
I'm just not gonna do it.
No, the psalmist is when I understand
that I need to take heed according to thy word,
I wanna hide God's Word in my heart.
I understand this evening that for many of us,
we have Bibles readily available.
I actually have seen, and you have as well,
I'm sure some reports of this year,
of just the record sales of Bibles in America.
I have seen reports of this calendar year,
and there's been many reports that I've seen
from various organizations that have been sending out
these articles about the number of Bibles
sold in the U.S. this year,
and how people are hungry for the truth.
I hope that's true.
Because thy word is truth, amen?
And we do live in a crazy world.
And I understand that we have a lot of Bibles available,
you have it on your phone, on a device,
you can listen to it, so on and so forth.
But I wonder tonight, and it's not likely
to happen in America, but we understand
that it's happened in a lot of places
around the world throughout history,
what would happen tonight if they came
and took all of our Bibles away?
You say it'd be a tragedy, I agree.
But how much of God's Word would you still have?
How much of God's Word would you still have?
I've read accounts of individuals
that were in communist-type countries
where the Bibles were confiscated,
they weren't allowed to have Bibles,
and how they just cherished every little verse
that they ever memorized,
and how important it became to them.
Someone wisely said, at times we don't appreciate
what we have until we no longer have it.
And I think that we've all been guilty of that
at some level in our lives, in some arena of our lives.
We think about the psalmist here, and he says,
thy word have I hid in mine heart.
Takes work, develop a goal.
For our church this year, we've had the opportunity
to have our church calendars
where there's a verse for every month,
and if you memorize the verses from 1 and 2 Timothy
throughout this calendar year,
you memorize 12 verses from those two books.
There have been some that have come to me
and they've said, pastor, can I recite the verses to you?
Do you know how encouraging that is to me?
And, oh man, I forgot that one,
I'm having a hard time with it, sorry, just be patient.
No, no, no, you're encouraging me, don't apologize to me.
Because the fact that you've been working on this,
and you've been working on this,
and you wanna tell me these verses,
that just blesses my heart.
Why, because it's good for you
to hide God's word in your heart.
This next year, our calendars are to be delivered,
hopefully this upcoming week,
and the new theme and the calendars that will be delivered,
again, you'll have opportunity to have a verse
for each month, the 12 more verses.
None of them are the same ones for 2024.
So if you keep doing that, you say a month of verses,
sorry, a verse a month, it's really not that hard.
Could be memorizing more than that.
We have a plan.
I use index cards.
You say, index cards, that's old school.
Yeah, it works, though.
They got all these new fancy technology things
to try to help you memorize things,
and they got these apps.
You know what the problem is for me?
I gotta use the app, and I just don't ever get to it.
But index cards, they sit on my desk,
and they're right there.
Sometimes people put them in the mirror,
and they put them on the whatever,
and they wanna have it in front of them.
Why, because they wanna memorize God's word.
It's a commitment that we're making.
It's this action that we're taking.
Notice in verse 13, he says,
with my lips have I declared all the judgments of thy mouth.
We see the third action that's listed here.
He says, I declared all the judgments of thy mouth.
And so here, the psalmist has not only,
and you see a progression.
The Bible says in verse 10 that with my whole heart
have I sought thee in verse number 11,
thy word have I hid in my heart.
And now in verse number 13,
I've declared all the judgments of thy mouth.
I mean, when I'm seeking God with my whole heart,
and I'm memorizing his word,
guess what starts coming out of us?
His word.
We start declaring the judgments of the Lord.
We start thinking and acting biblically.
Someone asks us a question,
and our answer to the question is a biblical principle,
a biblical truth to give the answer to the individual,
because we've been seeking God with our whole heart,
because we've been hiding God's word in our hearts.
And therefore, we're declaring his judgments.
What a joy.
You ever meet somebody, they say,
man, they talk biblical talk.
Do you understand what I mean when I say that?
I mean, that's good.
It's good.
You know, Baptist people were referred to
as being people of the book.
That's how we were referred to centuries ago.
By the way, it was intended to be a derogatory
type of a comment, that you're people of the book,
but I'm telling you, what other book
would you wanna have a commitment to,
I mean, than God's word?
To be known for, being people of the book.
Notice he says this in verse 14.
Not only did he declare all the judgments, verse 13,
but notice in verse 14, I have rejoiced
in the way of thy testimonies as much as in all riches.
So he says, I have rejoiced in the way of thy testimonies.
You know, when we're seeking God with our whole heart,
when we're hiding God's word in our heart,
we're talking about God's word, we're declaring it,
you know what we start doing, we start rejoicing.
It's a progression that we see in these actions
that the psalmist outlines when he's answering
this question that's asked to start verse number nine.
Wherewithal shall a young man cleanse his way?
By taking heed thereto according to thy word.
Okay, well then here's what I'm gonna,
here are the actions that I'm gonna take.
Understanding the answer to the question,
here are the actions that I'm going to take
so that I can have a way that's pleasing to the Lord
so that when God looks at my life,
God will be pleased with my life.
So when we find that there's four actions
followed by three resolutions,
I want you to see the first resolution in verse 16.
The Bible says, I will delight myself in thy statutes.
Verse 15, excuse me, the first one is in verse 15.
I will meditate in thy precepts
and have respect unto thy ways.
So the first resolution, the I will,
those are good statements, they're declarative resolutions.
He says, I will meditate in thy precepts.
What does it mean to meditate?
You know, the world today has an idea of meditation
that's different than what God's word means with meditation.
The world has an idea, this Eastern mindset of meditation,
of getting alone and kind of casting out
every thought from your mind
and getting in this kind of happy place or something,
I don't know, it's a weird kind of like void of thought.
That's not meditation.
When the psalmist says, I will meditate in my precepts,
it's that idea of it just continually
going through our minds,
we're just kind of just musing upon
the truth of God's word.
Have you ever walked away from your time with God?
Have you ever walked away from a church service
and just the truth of God's word
just was permeating your mind?
You're meditating on it.
There are times in which as I'm reading the Bible
and my daily devotions that I'll jot down
as I write various thoughts and things
that I'm jotting down as I'm reading my Bible
and there's sometimes Armando that I come to a place
I'm like, I don't really understand that,
I'm gonna jot that down
because I need to go back and figure that out.
You say, pastor, that happens to you?
Yeah.
None of us know it all, amen.
There are times in which it's like,
I gotta go figure that out and begin to meditate on it.
People have asked me over the years,
how long does it take to prepare a sermon?
It varies.
And one of the reasons that I have a hard time
telling you how long it takes to prepare a sermon
is because I just try to spend time just meditating on it.
Just letting it just get in my brain, in my soul.
The thought, the passage, the principle,
whatever it is that God's given me.
And he says, I will meditate.
Takes time.
But we're meditating on God's word,
on something that is pure and profitable and perfect
and it's been preserved for us and how blessed we are.
He says, I will meditate in my precepts,
a resolution, a determined statement that he makes.
He says in verse 16, I will delight myself in thy statutes.
I will delight myself in thy statutes.
You know, there are a lot of people
trying to delight themselves in a lot of different things.
But Solomon says, I'm gonna find joy
and I'm gonna find this delight in thy statutes.
Have you ever been reading the Bible
and something just kinda made sense to you
that you had maybe before not fully understood or grasped?
Maybe it was a thought, a truth.
Maybe you can remember when you first got saved
and you didn't understand something,
you're just reading the Bible for the first time.
So man, this is awesome.
Listen, God's word is a living book.
We oughta pray regularly that God helps us
to take a fresh approach to his word.
I'll be honest with you this evening,
as a pastor,
sometimes it's challenging with regard to,
I sit down to read the Bible and it's like,
I've preached through this book before.
I've taught through this before.
I've spent 50 weeks teaching on this particular book.
God, would you help me to approach it fresh?
Would you help me not to have my mind
wandering somewhere else as I'm just kinda reading?
No, God, I wanna hear from you.
Listen, I change my Bible out regularly
because I mark up my Bible
and I wanna read it without markings in it.
I got a new one sitting on my desk right now
that I'm just going through reading it
and the pages stick together and everything else
because it's brand new, drive me crazy.
And, but it doesn't have very many markings in it.
And actually this first time reading through it,
I didn't really put any markings in it on purpose
because what happens?
Well, I know me and you know you.
When I open my Bible and there's markings,
guess what my eyes wanna go to?
The markings.
It's like, oh yeah, that's a good truth
and then maybe I'm not.
And so I just want that fresh approach.
It's a living book and it brings us joy.
I remember, I didn't get saved until I was 17 years old.
I remember the first time I ever read
about the crossing of the Red Sea.
I'm telling you what, I was ready to swing on the rafters,
man, I was like, this is absolutely amazing.
I was in Bible college, I was a freshman in Bible college.
You didn't know about the Red Sea
and you're in Bible college?
Yes, I had no idea about the crossing of the Red Sea.
I was in Bible college.
And I remember sitting there, Tim,
and these students there, they're like,
come on, we heard this before, we know this.
And I'm like, this is awesome.
Because it is, because it is.
And if we're not careful, we can get kind of crusty,
kind of stale.
Do you understand what I'm saying?
Oh, how we take that fresh approach.
I will delight myself in thy statutes.
And then notice the last resolution
at the end of verse 16.
He says, I will not forget thy word.
Now that's perplexing to me.
You ever forget something?
Come on, don't look at, you ever forget something?
You say, I forgot something an hour ago, right?
Yeah, we forget stuff all the time.
Have you ever forgotten something that you said,
I'm not gonna forget this?
It's almost kind of like you jinxed yourself
when you say that, right?
You say, okay, I'm not gonna forget this.
And guess what you forgot?
This, whatever this was, right?
And you go and you say, I know I came in here,
have you gotten to the point where you go into a room
and you're like, why did I come into the room?
I knew I was coming to get something,
but I don't remember what I was going to get.
And then you do this, you leave the room
so that you can go back into the room
and you say, man, this is getting old.
Yeah, I know, I feel like, why is that happening?
And I know some of you look at me like I'm crazy
because you say, you have a great memory
and I do have a great memory,
but it's not as great as it was like 10 years ago.
And you say, pastor, just wait until you're my age.
I understand, I'm concerned.
But he says, I will not forget thy word.
How could he make such a statement?
How could he make that statement?
He's so purposed and so determined to seek God and his word
and he's going to make it his meditation,
he's gonna make it his delight.
It's gonna be so in him that he feels like
there's no way I could forget this
because it just becomes part of me.
I've read accounts of people that have various levels
of maybe Alzheimer's or dementia or whatever it might be,
but they can quote Bible verses.
I've read accounts.
And I could tell you this evening that, listen,
that person at some point in their life,
they had to absolutely saturate their hearts
and souls and minds with God's word.
And they might not remember who you are,
but they remembered verses of scripture.
It's amazing.
You can read accounts of people
that have had these experiences and it's awesome.
And the psalmist says, I will not forget thy word.
It's gonna be a constant reminder.
I'm gonna keep it in front of me regularly.
I'm gonna read it.
I'm gonna seek with my whole heart the Lord.
I'm going to seek his word.
I'm gonna hide it in my heart.
I'm gonna declare.
I'm gonna meditate.
I'm gonna rejoice.
And I'm not gonna forget.
Man, it's a wonderful resolution this evening.
When we answer this question in verse nine
and couple it with this thought in verse 10
that we use for our title tonight,
let me not wander from thy commandments.
I hope tonight that we'd say, I don't wanna wander.
The psalmist would say this in verse 67
of the same psalm, before I was afflicted,
I went astray, but now have I kept thy word.
I mentioned this morning
that I was reading through the book of Nehemiah.
I've been reading some other prophets recently.
You know, it's kind of interesting
when you see what the nation of Israel suffered
and how they responded.
Not all of them, but some of them.
And here the psalmist says, before I was afflicted,
I went astray, but now, so after the affliction,
have I kept thy word.
I would hope tonight that we would not have
to suffer affliction or suffer some great hardship
in order to seek the Lord.
But that we would truly just say, I wanna seek God.
I don't wanna wander from thy commandments.
No, I wanna walk with the Lord.
I wanna continue until the day of my departure,
whenever that is.
And so here's some thoughts from the psalmist.
Again, four actions, three resolutions,
that maybe tonight, as we examine our lives this week,
as we go through our lives and we say,
you know, these are some things
that I need to incorporate in my life.
I know if I'm seeking God with my whole heart or not.
I know if I'm hiding God's word in my heart or not.
I can go back and I can look at my life and say,
when was the last time I memorized a verse of scripture?
I said this to someone recently.
I can go in my life and I can look back and say,
when was the last time I shared the gospel with someone?
Not the last time someone, I was able to lead them to Christ
because that's God's business.
But our business is to give the gospel.
When was the last time I tried
to even share the gospel with someone?
I even cared enough to talk to them about their soul.
When's the last time I hid a Bible verse in my heart?
And as we evaluate our lives, as we begin to,
it is always this time of year,
you go into a new year and all those things,
good time for evaluation.
The psalmist says, I don't wanna wander.
I hope tonight we'd say, I don't wanna wander.
I wanna keep on keeping on,
keep serving God, living for God.
Let's take these actions and these resolutions
and apply them in our lives, shall we pray?
Father, we love you tonight.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for your word
and for the truth contained therein.
I pray God that you would help us
to be able to be students of your word
and Lord, to seek you with our whole heart,
to seek your word, Lord, to search the scriptures daily.
Lord, that we would hide your word in our hearts.
Lord, that we would be doers of the word,
that we would speak and declare thy word.
Help us, Lord.
I pray that you'd move and work
in this time of invitation as only you can.
And we'll be careful to give you the honor and glory
for every decision made, for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?