John chapter number two,
and thankful for the opportunity to continue
with this study that we have been studying this thought,
doing what we ought to do.
And of course, I've said it each week,
just because we know doesn't mean we do.
And this evening, we'll continue or we'll really
kind of conclude this particular mini series
within the series for the last five weeks.
This is part five tonight, we've dealt with this thought
of we ought to walk as Christ walked.
And it was within the greater theme or series
of doing what we ought to do.
But we come to first John two and verse number six,
and the Bible says, he that sayeth he abideth in him
ought himself also so to walk even as he walked.
And of course, as we've dealt with this subject now
for these last four weeks, tonight being part five,
we've discovered several aspects
and how with regard to how Christ walked,
how did he live during his earthly ministry?
I said that first John two, six,
really requires us as students of the word
to dig into the gospels and find out,
well, how did Christ walk?
If I'm supposed to walk as Christ walk,
then I must know how he walked.
And so we looked at a number of things already.
And we said that Jesus walked wisely, he walked humbly,
he walked purposefully, courageously.
Last week, we said that he walked compassionately.
And we looked at that truth from the book of Jude
and of some have compassion making a difference
and how we too are to walk and to live with compassion.
I've made this known that as we look
at these various aspects of how Christ walked
and then incorporating those things in our lives,
that it's not that we walk one,
they're not individual silos.
The reality is that as we walk, as we live our lives,
we're to live with compassion and with humility
and with purpose and so on and so forth,
all at the same time.
But we've looked at these as individual lessons
and looking at the example tonight,
I'm gonna deal with this subject
that Jesus walked obediently.
Jesus walked obediently.
Therefore, of course, we too ought to walk in obedience.
And obedience is a subject that we find
throughout the Bible and how important it is.
John chapter eight, as our manner has been here
over these last four weeks,
we're going to look at an example from the gospels
and then also a reference in the book of Philippians
in this particular case
of how the Lord Jesus Christ walked obediently.
And then as we prove that truth,
then we'll go over and begin to look at the truth
with regard to how we are to walk in obedience.
The reality is I preached this message on Sunday evening
with regard to the correction
that the church of Ephesus received.
And I said this, that when correction comes,
each individual has a choice.
How are we gonna respond to it?
Are we gonna obey it?
Are we gonna dismiss it?
What are we gonna do?
And when we think about the commands
that God has given to us,
we also recognize the fact that he's given us choice.
He's given to us free will.
You can obey, you can also disobey.
Now, we understand it's in your best interest,
it's in my best interest to obey.
It goes far better for us when we obey, don't you think?
And we see that throughout the scriptures.
We see it proven.
In John chapter number eight,
there's a number of things that are going on here
in this particular chapter.
We find that Jesus is here and I'm gonna jump,
there's no real easy place to jump in,
but I wanna look here at beginning in verse number 27.
The Bible says,
they understood not that he spake to them of the father,
then said Jesus unto them,
when you have lifted up the son of man,
then shall you know that I am he
and that I do nothing of myself,
but as my father hath taught me, I speak these things.
Now, it's interesting because when he would go to the cross
if you were to cross-reference
and look at other passages of scripture,
it's interesting that when they put him on the cross,
there were several things that were said.
Of course, he was mocked and he was ridiculed,
all that he was, the scourging and all that took place.
But after the Lord Jesus Christ said it is finished
and the veil was rent in twain,
there were some soldiers that said,
truly, this was the son of God.
And they recognized that truth.
And so we find that Jesus makes the statement
here in verse 28.
Notice in verse 29,
and he that sent me is with me.
The father hath not left me alone
for I do always those things that please him.
Now, it's interesting as we continue to see here
and understand the thought and the truth
that Jesus is giving, as he left the glory of heaven,
he, remember, he took on himself the form of a servant.
He came in human flesh.
He never stopped being God, but he was 100% God.
He was 100% man.
And we find that in that situation, he says,
I do always those things that please him.
Notice in verse 30, as he spake these words,
many believed on him.
Then said Jesus to those Jews, which believed on him.
Notice what he says to them.
If you continue in my word,
then are you my disciples indeed.
You think about this idea of continuing in my word,
it would have and carry with it that thought
of living a life of obedience,
a life that is consistent with the teachings of God's word.
Of course, we find that it's in this chapter as well,
in John chapter number eight,
that at the end of the chapter,
that Jesus is still speaking here
to these religious leaders.
And notice he says this in verse 51.
Verily, verily, I say unto you,
if a man keep my saying, he shall never see death.
And then said the Jews unto him,
now we know that thou hast a devil.
Abraham is dead, and the prophets,
and thou sayest, if a man keep my saying,
he shall never taste of death.
Art thou greater than our father Abraham, which is dead,
and the prophets are dead, whom makest thou thyself?
Oh, if they only knew how much greater he was than Abraham,
how much greater he is than Abraham.
We find that Jesus answered in verse 54 and said,
if I honor myself, my honor is nothing.
It is my father that honoreth me,
of whom you say that he is your God,
yet ye have not known him.
But I know him, and if I should say I know him not,
I shall be a liar like unto you,
but I know him and keep his saying.
Your father Abraham rejoiced to see my day,
and he saw it and was glad.
Now notice what they say in verse 57.
Then said the Jews unto him,
thou art not yet 50 years old, and hast thou seen Abraham?
And Jesus said unto them, verily, verily, I say unto you,
before Abraham was, I am.
What a statement of deity.
I mean, we find that here,
throughout the years, theologians and others
have had many things to say about this verse,
many that would attack the deity of Christ.
They would come to this verse,
and they would try to provide so many different angles
and aspects with regard to what Jesus was saying,
but we understand exactly what he was saying.
Furthermore, the Jewish people that he was speaking to
absolutely clearly understood what he was saying.
He was claiming that he is God.
Now, why is he claiming that?
Well, because he is, and we find that in verse 59,
they knew when he said, before Abraham was, I am,
the Bible says in verse 59,
then took they up stones to cast at him,
but Jesus hid himself and went out of the temple
going through the midst of them and so passed by.
Why did they wanna throw stones at him?
Well, because they were understanding
that he was claiming, he was telling them he is God,
and we find that in just a couple of chapters,
they would say, if thou be the Christ,
then tell us plainly, and he says,
I've told you, but you believe not.
And so we find that within the context
of all of these wonderful things taking place
in John chapter number eight,
that we find this statement where he says,
for I do always those things that please him.
I want you to think about the idea of walking in obedience,
and we see this example here, this declaration.
Turn to the book of Philippians, if you will,
and I want you to notice what the apostle Paul says
in Philippians chapter number two,
and this is a passage that is quite just a familiar passage,
a powerful passage, and we find that beginning
in verse number five of Philippians two,
the Bible says, let this mind be in you,
which was also in Christ Jesus,
who being in the form of God,
thought it not robbery to be equal with God,
but notice what the Bible says,
but made himself of no reputation.
Man, how different than so many today
that try to make a reputation for themselves.
They wanna be known of who they are
and what they've accomplished and so on and so forth.
Jesus is God, he left the glory of heaven,
and he made himself of no reputation.
Notice the Bible says, and took upon him
the form of a servant and was made in the likeness of men.
By the way, this is all necessary to redeem us.
Without this truth of the incarnation,
without this.
truth of Jesus, God in flesh, coming to this earth,
mankind could never be redeemed.
But we find that Jesus, the son of God, God in flesh,
the sinless one, he had to come and he came in this manner.
Notice it says in verse number eight,
in being found in fashion as a man,
notice these statements, he humbled himself.
Remember we talked about the very first week
that we were looking at this,
we dealt with two aspects that first Wednesday night,
wisely and humbly, that Jesus walked wisely and humbly
and he says he humbled himself.
He's God and he humbled himself.
So often we find ourselves being prideful
and we're fallen man that the only good that we have
is the good of God in us.
We are what we are by the grace of God.
Paul says, I know that in me that is in my flesh
well if no good thing, Paul asked this question
of the people at Corinth, he says,
what do you have that you didn't receive?
Well that's a sobering thought, that's a humbling thought,
that's a reality check and we find that the Bible says
that he humbled himself, notice this,
and became obedient unto death, even the death of the cross.
He became obedient unto death, even the death of the cross.
Why was he obedient to go to the cross of Calvary?
Well again, because it was for that hour,
that was the purpose, the whole reason
that Jesus came was to go to the cross
and we find that he was obedient.
By the way, aren't you thankful
that he went to the cross for you?
Aren't you thankful that he finished the course,
he finished what was laid out for him,
he said it is finished and I'm so thankful for that.
Now this evening, as we understand
that our savior walked in obedience
and we understand that he left us an example
that we should follow his steps,
then we too would say that we as the people of God
should walk in obedience, that our lives,
my life and your life should be marked
by obedience to God's precious word.
The reality this evening is that we find
that throughout the scriptures,
there's a premium that is placed on obedience.
It's not something to be neglected,
it's not something, well, it's not really a big deal.
No, God places a premium on obedience
and we find that as we study his word
that there's so many things that we need to be aware of
and so many different passages
that we could go to this evening.
We're gonna just look at a few
but I want you to think of this,
as Jesus said, I do always those things that please him.
And then I want you to think about this statement
in John chapter number two, the first miracle,
the marriage at Cana, when Mary says to the servants,
whatsoever he saith unto you, do it.
It's very interesting when we think about
this idea of complete obedience,
that we understand that for many of us this evening,
we probably have even today, this week,
there have been times in which we've been disobedient
to a command that God has given to us in his word.
We fall short, but we ought to be striving
to live a life that is marked by obedience.
Notice what the Bible says,
look at a few verses of scripture,
look at the book of Luke, if you will,
in chapter number six, Luke chapter number six,
and Brother Mark went to this text of scripture
in Sunday school this past Sunday
and I had so many thoughts going through my mind
as I had already prepared for this lesson
and several weeks ago, I actually thought
I was gonna teach this whole lesson in one Wednesday,
isn't that funny?
This is week number five, I prepared the whole thing
six weeks ago, thought I was gonna teach it in one week
and here we are five weeks later,
and but in Luke chapter number six
and verse number 46, the Bible says this,
what a powerful statement,
why call ye me Lord, Lord, and do not the things
which I say.
Isn't that a soul piercing verse of scripture?
I want you to think about the centurion
that came to Jesus and he came to Jesus
and he had a servant that was sick
and Jesus said, I'll come to your house,
but the centurion said, no, I'm not worthy
that you come to my house
and he said that he was a man under authority,
in other words, he had, being a centurion,
he had soldiers that were under his command
and here's what he said, he said this,
I say to this servant go and he goes,
I say to this servant do and he does
and so on and so forth
and I think about that truth
and the gospel of Matthew, Matthew eight deals with that
and you begin to think about the truth of that centurion
and Jesus mentions the faith of that man
and because he understood that Jesus could simply say
the words and he could heal a servant,
distance didn't matter, it was no problem for Jesus,
but I think about that man that was under authority
and from a human perspective,
he had authority over a group of soldiers
and he said come and they come,
go and they go, do and they do,
well, they obeyed, they understood what it was to obey.
I want you to understand this evening
that our God is so much greater than a centurion.
He's God and he bought you with his blood,
he bought me with his blood, he's my savior
and here the scripture say,
why call ye me Lord, Lord and do not the things which I say?
I said this before from the pulpit,
the reality is that many people today
are looking for a savior,
but they're not looking for a master.
They understand perhaps their need for salvation,
they understand that without Christ,
they're gonna spend eternity in the lake of fire,
that they cannot atone for their own sin,
but as far as having a Lord, a master in their life,
no, that's already occupied by them.
They're already gonna take that position,
there's no vacancy, if you will, for that office,
but the reality is that if he's my savior,
he must also be my Lord.
I believe it was D.L. Moody said,
if he's not Lord of all, then he's not Lord at all.
What a powerful statement and here we find,
I mean, it's a piercing question.
Why is it that we would call him Lord,
but then not do what he says?
The reality is that if we're going to have
and live a life that's marked by obedience,
then it requires for us to dig into the scriptures
to know what God commands of us, what he expects of us.
I cannot do what he commands of me to do
if I do not know what he's commanded me to do.
We find that the kings,
all the way back in the book of Deuteronomy,
though it was not God's plan that there would ever be kings,
God knew that there would be kings
and so he wrote for them instruction
and one of the things that they were supposed to do
there as the kings is they were to write for themselves
a copy of the law, that was what they were to do
and that would help them, you know,
the part of that is that they weren't
to multiply wives unto themselves.
How many of them multiplied wives unto themselves?
Maybe if they just wrote down the law
like they were supposed to, it would have kept them
from doing that which God specifically
prohibited them from doing.
But we find this evening that for many of God's people,
we don't even know what God expects of us to be doing,
we're not digging into the Bible,
we don't know the commands of scripture
and so how is it that we can obey him?
And so we find that just after this verse of scripture
in Luke 6 in verse number 46, he gives us the truth
with regard to the wise man and the foolish man
and we sing the song with the kids
and you're familiar with it and it's interesting
because in both of those individuals,
the reality is they heard the same message.
It wasn't an issue with hearing, it was an issue with doing
and can I tell you for many today,
it's not an issue of hearing, it's an issue of doing.
It's an issue of excusing why it's not necessary
for us to do that today.
Look at this passage, if you will, in the book of Ezekiel.
In Ezekiel chapter 33, Ezekiel chapter 33
and I want you to look at a few verses of scripture with me
even keeping in mind that passage in Luke 6
and we look back at the book of Ezekiel.
The book of Ezekiel is an interesting book.
We find that there's much truth that's given to us here
and God was going to send them, send Ezekiel.
You're there in chapter 33.
Let me just reference a couple of things in chapter three
and chapter three in verse number four
and keep your place in 33
but look at chapter three just for a moment
and look in verse number four
and he said unto me, son of man, go,
get thee into the house of Israel
and speak with my words unto them.
This is in verse five, for thou art not sent
to a people of a strange speech, of an hard language,
but to the house of Israel.
Not to many people of a strange speech
and of a hard language,
whose words thou canst not understand.
Surely, had I sent thee to them,
they would have hearkened unto thee.
Isn't that interesting?
God says to Ezekiel, I'm sending you to the house of Israel.
It's not a strange people with a strange language.
In other words, it's my people.
Ezekiel was in Hebrew and so he's going to go to his own people
and he says that if I had sent you to a people of a strange language
or a strange speech in hard language, that they would have hearkened unto you,
according to verse number 6, but the house of Israel, verse number 7,
will not hearken unto thee, for they will not hearken unto me,
for all the house of Israel are impotent and hard-hearted.
Wow.
You know, it's almost a situation here in Israel's history.
They had started with God.
Amen? They started with God.
And then they just kind of got off course.
They got some prosperity, they got some blessing,
and all of a sudden they didn't really need God anymore,
and they would need God when there was great opposition and oppression,
and they would call out to God, the period of the judges, and so on and so forth,
but eventually you find here they're in captivity.
And their hearts are so hardened.
God had sent prophet after prophet after prophet,
but they were just doing their own thing their own way.
God says to Ezekiel, if I had sent you to a different people,
they would have hearkened.
You know, it's sad, and I do not in any stretch of the imagination
try to connect Israel with the United States of America,
so please do not misunderstand what I'm going to say,
but I do think that there are principles that we can learn about a nation
and we can apply them broadly,
and we find that it's interesting in the United States of America
that today we're a nation that started with God.
You know, today there's a lot of people in America that just don't want to hear.
I'm serious.
A lot of people that just don't want to hear.
They're okay.
Not that there's not a work going on in America,
because God is working in America,
but I can tell you about mission field after mission field after mission field
where God is working in an amazing way.
Why? Because those people have a hunger for God.
It's amazing to me.
We notice not only that truth, but notice here in chapter 3,
and notice in verse number 22,
the Bible says, and the hand of the Lord was there upon me,
and he said unto me, notice God is speaking to Ezekiel.
It's a record that God gives us, and in verse number 22,
here's what God says to Ezekiel.
Arise, go forth into the plain, and I will there talk with thee.
Now let me ask you, is there anything difficult about what God told Ezekiel in verse 22?
I mean, it's pretty straightforward.
Arise, go forth into the plain, and I will there talk with thee.
So what if he decided not to go?
What if he decided to go but not to the plain?
God told him where to go and what was going to happen,
and I want you to see the obedience of Ezekiel in verse 23.
Then I arose and went forth into the plain,
and behold, the glory of the Lord stood there,
as the glory which I saw by the river of Chabar,
and I fell on my face.
I'm pretty confident this evening that Ezekiel was happy that he obeyed the Lord.
Amen?
But look at chapter 33, if you will, and there's so many things in between the two chapters,
so much content, but I want you to look at chapter 33 just for a moment,
and I want you to look at what God tells us beginning in verse 31.
In Ezekiel 33 and verse 31, the Bible says,
And they come unto thee as the people cometh,
and they sit before thee as my people,
and they hear thy words, so they hear.
But notice, they will not do them,
for with their mouth they show much love,
but their heart goeth after their covetousness.
And lo, thou art unto them as a very lovely song,
of one that hath a pleasant voice, and can play well on an instrument,
for they hear thy words, but they do them not.
So you see in verse number 31, the Bible says,
but they will not do them, they hear, but they will not do.
In verse 32, God kind of likens it to somebody
that would hear someone sing or play an instrument,
and he says, they hear, but they do them not.
Verse 33, and when this cometh to pass, lo, it will come,
then shall they know that a prophet hath been among them.
The problem here was not in hearing, but in doing.
That's the problem.
I'm sure that at some point in your Christian life,
you've left a service, a revival meeting, a missions conference,
a Sunday morning service, whatever service it was,
and God's Spirit spoke to you, you heard a message,
and you said, maybe you walked out and said,
man, that was a great message.
The reality is not in whether it was a great message or not,
it's what we do with the message.
It's not about hearing some, as it says in verse 32,
someone that can play well on an instrument,
someone that can wax eloquent, no.
It's about the Spirit of God speaking to me
and me responding in obedience.
Remember, never forget what God said through Samuel to Saul
in 1 Samuel 15 and verse 22,
to obey is better than sacrifice.
There's a lot of times in which we fail to obey,
even as Saul did in that passage of Scripture,
and of course he sought to excuse his disobedience,
and by the way, we're all good at that.
We're good at excusing our disobedience,
and we've become very good at it,
and the reality is that we need to come to the place where we say,
I just want to obey the Lord.
He's my Lord, so why would I call Him Lord
and then not do what He says?
If He's truly Lord, if He's truly Master,
if He is my Lord and my Savior,
then I ought to do the things that He tells me to do.
Again, I mentioned in John chapter number 2,
I want you to look at it in John chapter number 2.
In John chapter number 2 and verse number 4,
the Bible says, Jesus saith unto her,
Woman, what have I to do with thee? Mine hour is not yet come.
His mother saith unto the servants,
Whatsoever he saith unto you, do it.
I just wonder this evening of these servants
and all that they knew.
This was early on in the life and ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ.
This isn't the end of His earthly ministry.
This is the beginning of His earthly ministry,
and we find that these servants are there,
I don't know all of the details and all of the circumstances,
but I find that in the text of Scripture
that Mary says to these servants,
Whatsoever He, Jesus, saith unto you, do it.
And this evening, I would say that the counsel
that Mary gives to the servants in John chapter number 2
is good counsel for every one of us this evening.
Whatsoever He saith unto you, do it.
I'm sure that you're familiar, just as I am,
with the little catchphrase of the athletic company Nike,
just do it.
And the reality is that we see how they've used that
and so on and so forth, but I think about
the truth of God's Word in this verse of Scripture
where she says, do it.
You know, the reality is that we don't need to pray about obeying.
When God has given us a command in His Word,
it's not something that we pray about,
it's something that we do.
We simply obey Him.
There are certainly things that we must pray about
and we understand what those are,
but when it comes to the commands,
the obvious commands that God has given to us in His Word,
there's no need for us to pray about those things,
we simply do them.
There's no need for delayed obedience
in the life of a believer.
We must obey immediately, right away,
seizing the opportunity, not missing the opportunity,
but obeying the Lord.
This evening as we wrap up this mini-series
within this greater series of doing what we ought to do,
we find here this evening that Jesus,
He walked and left us an example
and I hope tonight that you could add,
and I mentioned this earlier on,
it's not an exhaustive list.
There's so many other ways as we study through the Gospels
that we see how Christ walked
and I'm thankful that He walked with courage
and with compassion and with honesty and with humility
and I'm thankful that He walked there with wisdom
and I'm thankful tonight for the example
that He gave us of walking in obedience.
And tonight I simply want to say this,
if we examine our lives,
we know what obedience looks like.
We know what it is when someone disobeys what we've said.
If you have children, no doubt there's been some time
in your life of rearing children
that you've given them some instruction
and they just failed to obey the instruction.
And sometimes you look at the children,
as I did many times,
over the years, and I would say,
there's now a consequence for the disobedience.
And you kind of look at it and say,
you know, it's really just so simple.
If you just obey, then you don't have to deal with this.
And every time over the years of rearing children
and dealing with that, every time I'd say those words,
it was like the Holy Spirit of God would say to me,
it's so easy, just obey.
God's made it plain.
He's given to us his word.
It's not a problem with hearing.
It's not a problem with having the word.
It's a problem in our own lives of doing it, of obeying.
And this evening, I hope that we could just make
a commitment before the Lord that, you know,
I'm gonna strive to live a life of obedience.
I'm just gonna obey God.
No questions asked, no, I'm not gonna take a poll
of what the world's doing and what's commonly accepted
and comparing myself amongst ourselves.
No, I'm just gonna make a determination
that whatsoever he saith, I'm just gonna do.
I'm just gonna obey God because to obey is better.
There's so many other verses that we could look at tonight
with regard to the subject of obedience.
It's an oft-discussed subject from this pulpit
from various passages throughout God's word.
Obedience, obedience, obedience.
And let these words ring in your heart.
Why calleth ye me, Lord, Lord,
and do not the things that I say?
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the opportunity that we have
to have your word and to know what you expect of us,
what you've commanded us.
I pray that you'd help us to be obedient, Lord.
Help us not to excuse disobedience in our lives.
Help us, Lord, to just make that commitment
that we're going to live a life of obedience.
I pray that, Lord, if you've put your finger
on some specific area in our lives tonight,
Lord, I pray that you'd help us to deal with that.
I pray that you would help us to seek you,
to seek to please you, Lord,
through all that we say and all that we do.
I pray that you'd bless our time of prayer.
We thank you for the privilege
that we have each Wednesday evening
to review updates from our missionaries
and to share requests of prayer
and to rejoice one with another of answered prayer.
And God, I pray that you'd bless our time of prayer tonight.
We pray that you'd be honored and glorified
through all that's said and done.
For it's in Christ's name we pray, amen.
All right, anyone need a prayer?