evening Genesis chapter number three be looking at verses 21 through 24 and I'll
give you a moment to turn there Genesis chapter number three be looking at the
last few verses here of chapter number three we've been studying the book of
Genesis now for about four a little over four months and we've thoroughly enjoyed
I know I thoroughly enjoyed the study I hope it's been a blessing to you and
this evening as we conclude this third chapter as you see in the bulletin this
evening I've adopted the title for the message from verse number 21
coats of skins coats of skins I'll read the passage of scripture get into the
message this evening beginning in verse number 21 it says this unto Adam also
into his wife did the Lord God make coats of skins and clothed them the Lord
God said behold the man has become as one of us to know good and evil and now
lest he put forth his hand and take also of the tree of life and eat and live
forever therefore the Lord God sent him forth from the Garden of Eden to till
the ground from whence he was taken so he drove out the man and he placed at
the east of the Garden of Eden cherubims and a flaming sword which turned every
way to keep the way of the tree of life as you know as we've studied the third
chapter of the book of Genesis we have found that it's in this chapter that God
records for us that sad event when sin entered into the world and we read
about the sin entering into the world in the first seven verses of chapter
three and then in the next several verses of chapter number three we see
how God is pursuing man he enters into the garden he's asked where art now and
we find that the the Lord is pursuing man and then of course last week as we
studied verses 14 down through verse number 20 we found that God's judgment
was announced and of course we understand that our God is the righteous
judge and there are consequences for disobedience he plainly said to Adam in
Genesis chapter number 2 in verse number 16 and the Lord God commanded the man
saying of every tree of the garden thou mayest freely eat but of the tree of the
knowledge of good and evil thou shalt not eat of it from the day that thou
eatest thereof thou shalt surely die and we read about the judgments that were
announced in verses 14 down through verse number 20 as we come to the last
few verses here of Genesis chapter number 3 I'm thankful this evening that
God would reveal to us once again his grace and his mercy I know that this
morning during the Sunday school hour we touched on some of the attributes of God
and then again during the morning service dealt with some of the
attributes of God and what a blessing it is to know that our God is indeed
gracious and merciful as we look at this passage of Scripture if you're taking
notes this evening I want you to see first of all notice what is provided
according to verse number 21 God lets us know what it is that he provides for
Adam and Eve the Bible says unto Adam also unto his wife did the Lord God make
coats of skins and clothe them as we notice what is provided in our text of
Scripture we are reminded of the fact that their coverings were insufficient
and the Bible tells us in verse number 7 after they partook of the forbidden
fruit after they disobeyed the commandment of the Lord we find that the
Bible tells us in Genesis 3 in verse number 7 and the eyes of them both were
opened and they knew that they were naked and they sewed fig leaves together
and made themselves aprons these aprons that they made in verse number 7 this
covering that was the works of their own hands this was inadequate it was
insufficient and we find that as we come to verse number 21 and the Bible
tells us that unto Adam also into his wife did the Lord God make coats of
skins and clothed them and so the works of their hands it was inadequate
insufficient and it pictures the works of their own hands as we mentioned in
verse number 7 and therefore God is going to provide them with coats of
skins as God would provide them with these coats of skins as mentioned in
verse 21 we would find that this now is a sufficient covering that which was
insufficient was replaced with that which is sufficient and of course it's
a picture we'll get to that in just a moment as we get through the lesson this
evening but as we think about the work of God and we think about this coat the
coats of skins that were provided we find that it would require an animal
sacrifice we find that in making these coats of skins there was an animal
sacrifice that was made no doubt with the blood being shed and once again
giving us that picture that we'll discuss at the end of the message this
evening that we touched on briefly last week as we looked at verse number 15 in
verse number 15 of Genesis 3 when God is announcing his judgment and he first
speaks to the serpent of course to Satan he says in verse number 15 I will put
enmity between thee and the woman and between thy seed and her seed it shall
bruise thy head and thou shalt bruise his heel and as we discussed that verse
of Scripture last week we talked about how that in verse 15 of Genesis 3 God
had announced really his plan for Jesus to come and to take the place of
mankind to shed his blood on the cross of Calvary and we find that as we would
come to verse number 21 that it's the start of that typology that you see
throughout the Old Testament of a an animal sacrifice in order to that blood
to be shed and the atonement that would be made typifying Christ who would one
day come we're reminded that the writer of Hebrew says in Hebrews chapter number
10 in the beginning portion of that text of Scripture he speaks about the law
having a shadow of good things to come but the law was insufficient the
Apostle Paul dealt with that quite in depth in the book of Galatians and we
find it over the book of Romans as well but in the book of Galatians he makes it
abundantly clear that the law could not save mankind in fact the law reveals
that man is sinful and in need of a Savior and so here we find the start of
this sacrificial process that would be typified throughout the Old Testament
this animal sacrifice blood being shed we could say this to this evening the
innocent for the guilty again a picture of the Lord Jesus Christ and we find that
the text of Scripture in verse 21 ends by saying and clothed them and God was
telling Adam and Eve that this is now sufficient covering for you this is the
path that that I am giving you and we find that even as we enter into the next
several passages of Scripture you come to chapter number four and you see the
offerings that are made and you understand that this communication that
God gave to Adam in chapter number three and the work that God did in making the
sacrifice and making these coats of skins that you would find that it was
evidently it was obviously I should say not evidently it was obviously passed
down and you see it in the sacrifice that was offered there in the fourth
chapter that we'll deal with next week by Abel we find that not only did God
provide them with a covering that was sufficient we notice what was provided
but I want you to notice also what is prohibited what it is that is prohibited
notice the language in verses 22 through 24 and notice what God says the Bible
says the Lord God said behold the man is become as one of us again we see again
that plurality and the deity of Christ the Trinity is in view and we've
mentioned that a few times already throughout our study of the book of
Genesis and we see the Trinity in view and he says behold the man has become as
one of us notice to know good and evil now man's understanding of good and evil
is different than God's understanding of good and evil God's understanding of
good and evil is from a perspective of holiness but man's perspective there of
good and evil is from his sinfulness and in that act that is described in
verses 1 through 7 of disobeying the Lord and taking of that forbidden fruit
it says and now notice this at the end of verse 22 lest he put forth his hand
and take also of the tree of life and eat and live forever therefore the Lord
God sent him forth from the Garden of Eden to till the ground from whence he
was taken notice with me as we consider that which is prohibited that entrance
into the garden is no longer permitted for Adam and Eve according to verse
number 23 we find that it was the Lord God that sent him forth from the Garden
of Eden now you'll recall with me as we've studied the second chapter that it
was this specific place that was designed by God for Adam and Eve and it
was in this specific place where the Bible tells us in Genesis 2 and verse
number 15 that the Lord God took the man and put him into the Garden of Eden to
dress it and to keep it and now God is removing man that he's created from the
garden but there is a good reason that God is removing Adam and Eve from the
garden and we find that yes the Lord was not only if we could look at this this
evening we looked at the judgments that were announced in verses 14 through 20
but really we could look at this as being an additional punishment that
they're banned from the Garden of Eden that they're no no longer permitted to
enter in and to dwell in that place that God had provided for them but we really
must understand this evening that this was an act of God's mercy being shown to
Adam and Eve and really to all of the human race and why is it that we'd say
that because we find that in chapter
number three and in verse number 22 that after God had announced that that man
now knows the the difference between good and evil you notice the latter part
of verse 22 he says this lest he put forth his hand and take also of the tree
of life and eat and live forever and so the mercy of God is in view here because
what God says is lest the people unless the man partake of the fruit and live
forever understanding this evening that to eat this fruit in a sinful condition
which is what they were in right sin had already entered the world and so now if
they partake of the fruit of the tree of life in that sinful condition they would
it would lead to eternal life in a fallen body now I'm thankful that God
has provided a better way aren't you see it was God's mercy that said I am going
to no longer permit we noticed what was provided but we noticed what is
prohibited it is no longer available for Adam and Eve or any of their
descendants to enter into the Garden of Eden and it was God's mercy on preventing
them from entering in lest they should partake of the fruit of the tree of life
and live forever in a fallen body God's provided a far better way we
understand the truth of the second birth as it's discussed in the New Testament
about being born again the second birth through the substitutionary atonement of
the Lord Jesus Christ which results not in eternal life in a fallen body but
eternal life in a glorified body in that wonderful Turner first Corinthians 15 if
you will just for a moment this evening and it's a chapter that many of us are
familiar with when we think about the resurrection and what a wonderful
chapter it is and it is the go-to passage of Scripture and we speak about
the resurrection we'll mention a few additional verses from this passage
later on this evening and so mark that spot there first Corinthians 15 because
we will come back but I want you to notice in verse number 52 here at first
Corinthians chapter 15 let me read verse 51 with it it says this first Corinthians
15 beginning in verse 51 behold I show you a mystery we shall not all sleep but
we shall all be changed in a moment and the twinkling of an eye at the last
trump for the trumpet shall sound and the dead shall be raised with it say
incorruptible and we shall be changed notice verse 53 for this corruptible
must put on in corruption and this mortal must put on immortality aren't
you thankful for that I'm thankful that God has provided a far better way and
God's infinite wisdom in his understanding being eternal he did not
want man to sin as they did in Genesis 3 and then partake of the the tree of life
and live forever in a fallen body but he says no I'm going to no longer permit
entrance into the Garden of Eden so that they cannot partake of that fruit so
that they will not live forever in a fallen body rather I will provide a far
better way the Lord Jesus Christ would come of course to earth as God and flesh
and he would go to the cross providing the the sacrifice necessary for man to
be born again and thus providing eternal life in a glorified body and what a joy
that is what a blessing that truth is we notice also according to verse number 24
as he says that he drove out the man notice so he drove out the man notice
what he did he placed at the east of the Garden of Eden cherubims and a
flaming sword which turned every way to keep the way of the tree of life not
only was God concerned with Adam and Eve specifically they're the only two human
beings that are on earth at this particular time there are no other human
beings Adam and Eve had not yet had any children we understand as we've mentioned
for several weeks now as we've studied the portion of Scripture that the period
of time in the Garden of Eden living in that state of innocence was a very short
period of time you find sin entering into the world we don't know it's not a
defined period of time biblically but we know that they were told to be fruitful
and multiply and there are no children that are born and so they did not live
in innocence for a lengthy period of time and we find that sin entered the
world then God drove Adam and Eve the only two human beings on all of the face
of planet Earth are driven away but God places at the east of the Garden of Eden
cherubims in a flaming sword which turned every way notice what it says to
keep the way of the tree of life so we find God's mercy made known to Adam and
Eve specifically but then we also see God's mercy being shown to their
descendants because you understand the Garden of Eden would not along with the
tree of life we understand that during the flood the Genesis flood that will
read here in just a short few chapters and we'll study through the flood that's
when the tree of life in the Garden of Eden is destroyed in the global flood
and so from the point of this chapter and the genealogy of the human race and
Adam and Eve all of their descendants up until Noah they are forbidden entrance
because these cherubims are placed there it'd be one thing for Adam and Eve to
know we can't go in there and we can't partake of that God has expelled us from
being able to enter there but God placed the cherubims there to prevent any of
the human race to enter in and partake of the tree of life and live forever in
a fallen body our God is awesome and we ought to thank God that he is omniscient
he has all wisdom and he has made a better way he has provided for us a far
better way it's interesting as you study the book of Hebrews it's kind of a side
note this evening but as you study the book of Hebrews you'll find that the
theme throughout the book of Hebrews is that Christ is better and you just begin
to read the book of Hebrews he's better he's better he's better and if you
compare him to anything and he's better he's superior because he is God in flesh
and we find that the the way of salvation the way that God has determined man to be
reconciled to himself is a better way than what Adam and Eve tried themselves
or which would have been a cut or that which would have been accomplished through
partaking of the tree of life the fruit of the tree of life there in a fallen state so
we find as we look at this passage of Scripture not only that which is provided
we notice that which is prohibited but I want you to notice this evening through
the remainder of our time notice what is pictured as we think about this passage
of Scripture just a few verses of Scripture but as we've mentioned
throughout our study the book of Genesis is the book of beginnings and the book
of Genesis unlocks so much of the rest of Scripture and without a sound
understanding a foundation built upon the book of Genesis it becomes
challenging for us to adequately interpret and understand the whole of
Scripture if you remove Genesis 3 from the Bible you just cut the entire
chapter out you remove all 24 verses it will be challenging for you to
understand much of that which is contained in the remaining chapters and
so we find that it's it's not simply an account a historical account of
something that happened with Adam and Eve though it is that this is a true
historical account of what happened with God's creation and with Adam and Eve
but we find that it also pictures for us the glorious picture that we find here
is the event of the substitutionary atonement the fact that Jesus Christ
would come as God in flesh and the perfect sinless Lamb of God would shed
his precious blood for mankind in order to be reconciled to God that's what is
pictured here in Genesis 3 verses 21 through 24 I mentioned to you to keep
your place in 1st Corinthians 15 and as I get back over there to 1st Corinthians
15 I want to read a verse to you from the book of 1st Peter and then I'll jump
into 1st Corinthians 15 and look at a few verses there but in 1st Peter 3 in
verse number 18 Peter said this for Christ also hath once suffered for sins
notice the just for the unjust that he might bring us to God being put to death
in the flesh but quickened by the Spirit and so we find the picture of the
substitutionary atonement that is given to us here in the book of Genesis in
chapter 3 verses 21 through 24 and as we look at the whole of Scripture study the
New Testament we can find this beautiful picture we can find the fulfillment of
this picture in the person of Jesus Christ in 1st Corinthians 15 in verse
number 45 the Bible says this and so it is written the first man Adam was made a
living soul now we've been studying about Adam and Eve right we've been
studying about the creation of mankind and the creation of the universe we've
studied and we see that at the end of creation day six God creates man and we
find that it's the crown of his creation and really the rest of Scripture deals
with how God as the Creator is going to interact with mankind human beings and
we find here that he Paul mentions to the believers in Corinth
the first man Adam was made a living soul but notice the remainder part of
the verse the last Adam was made a quickening spirit the last Adam is
Christ the Lord Jesus Christ and so we find here in 1st Corinthians 15 and
verse 45 the first man Adam we read historically we've been studying the
life of Adam and not really the life of Adam but the looking at the book of
Genesis and seeing the life of Adam but now we find that the references made to
the last Adam and that he was made a quickening spirit the Lord Jesus Christ
back up a few verses there in 1st Corinthians 15 and look at verse number
22 in verse number 20 I'll read that verse with it it says but now is Christ
risen from the dead and become the firstfruits of them that slept for since
by man came death who is that that's Adam right for since man came death by
man the Lord Jesus Christ he was born he took upon himself the form of a
servant remember you read Philippians chapter number two and you read about
the the incarnation of Christ and of course you can read the gospel records
came death by man came also the resurrection of the dead notice in verse
22 for is an Adam all die even so in Christ shall all be made alive so we
think about the first man Adam we can think about the curse and we can think
about judgment we think about the last Adam the Lord Jesus Christ we think
about life and blessing and the gift of God which is eternal life I'm reminded
of what Jesus said in John 10 in verse number 10 I am come to give them life
and if they might have it more abundantly and we find here that there's
a beautiful picture that is given to us in this passage of Scripture in Genesis
of the the substitutionary atonement turn once more over to Romans chapter
number five and we'll look at several verses in Romans chapter number five
this evening as we conclude we'll touch on a few other verses as well but I
want you to notice in Romans 5 looking at verses 12 really down through verse
number 21 the entirety of that last portion of Romans 5 and I want you to
see what the the Word of God teaches us with regard to this man Adam and the
Lord Jesus Christ notice in Romans 5 in verse number 12 wherefore as by one man
sin entered into the world who is that one man Adam you know that if you ask
that question to the general population today they probably have no idea if you
take and you just open up Romans 5 in verse number 12 and you ask him for as
by one man sin into the world who is that man that why I'm not criticizing any
ignorance what I'm saying to you is that in our society today we are have we
have a biblically ignorant society because we have a world that has sought
to undermine the authority of the Word of God and remove God's Word from the
public arena and therefore man is running around I read a poll this
morning it was ridiculous the number of people actually that were in the UK that
were that were polled and they were asked this question do you think there's
any meaning to life in the great the great percentage of those that were
pulled said we don't think there's any meaning for life sad remove the Word of
God we teach humanism and Darwinian ism and we teach evolution and all those
things and no wonder that people are running around saying yeah there's no
reason for life there's no purpose I mean and we find though that God's Word
gives us purpose is the person of the Lord Jesus Christ that gives us that
abundant life and so we find wherefore as by one man sin entered into the world
and death by sin notice and so death passed upon all men for that all have
sin we have inherited a sin nature and we are we sin because we are sinners and
that's how we were born verse 13 for until the law sin was in the world but
sin is not imputed when there is no law notice what Paul is saying in verse
number 13 well let me read verse 14 with it he says nevertheless death reigned
from Adam to Moses even over them that had not sinned after the similitude of
Adam's transgression who is the figure of him that was to come notice that what
he's saying here is that we don't have the law until Moses but sin was very
present throughout all of those generations between Adam and Moses
because as Adam would sin as we read in Genesis 3 then sin is passed on to all
mankind and we find that what Paul deals with in the book of Romans often is he
talks about the fact that because we have the law we are known to be sinners
because the law condemns us the law reveals to us that we are sinners but
Paul says before there was the law there was still sin because sin came through
the through Adam and through the transgression of God's commandment verse
15 but not as the offense so also is the free gift for if through the offense of
one many be dead much more the grace of God and the gift by grace which is by
one man Jesus Christ hath abounded unto many aren't you thankful for that we
understand this evening that the offense that is mentioned in verse
number 15 is the offense that is recorded in Genesis chapter number 3
when man Adam and Eve transgressed against the single commandment that God
had given them and we find here that he God is telling us yes there are many
that are dead it's passed upon all men but now let me reveal to you the grace
of God and the gift that comes from that grace verse 16 now and not as it was by
one that sinned so is the gift for the judgment was by one to condemnation but
the free gift is of many offenses unto justification for if by one man's offense
death reigned by one much more they would receive abundance of grace and of
the gift of righteousness shall reign in life by one Jesus Christ therefore as by
the offense of one judgment came upon all men to condemnation even so by the
righteousness of one the free gift came upon all men unto justification of life
for as by one man's disobedience many were made sinners so by the obedience of
one shall many be made righteous moreover the law entered the offense
might abound but where sin abounded aren't you thankful grace did much more
abound that as sin hath reigned unto death even so might grace reign through
righteousness unto eternal life by Jesus Christ our Lord and we find that
we can rejoice in the fact he says in just a few chapters in verse in chapter
number 8 in verse number 1 he says of these same same readers there is
therefore now no condemnation to them which are in Christ Jesus who walk not
after the flesh but after the Spirit but he speaks about the condemnation in
verse number 18 that as by the offense of one judgment came upon all men to
condemnation but we can rejoice in that righteousness of God that is offered and
the peace that we can have with God through the Lord Jesus Christ as he
mentions in verse number 1 of Romans 5 now as we think about the first man Adam
and the curse and the judgment we think about the last Adam the Lord Jesus
Christ and the life and blessing the eternal life that he offers I want you
to consider a few subject a few thoughts as we look back at Genesis 3
and just write down some notes this evening I'm going to reference a few
verses of Scripture but I want you to see this wonderful picture that is given
to us in Genesis chapter number 3 and how the Lord Jesus Christ took the place
of mankind and what he accomplished on the cross of Calvary in in purchasing
our redemption in verse number 17 through 19 we find in Genesis 3 that
God's judgment is announced to Adam in verse 14 he says to the serpent verses
14 and 15 verse 16 unto Eve but in verses 17 through 19 he speaks to Adam
direct you'll notice that in verse number 17 notice the last phrase in
sorrow shalt thou eat of it all the days of thy life in verse 18 he says
thorns also and thistle shall it bring forth today and thou shall eat the herb
of the field we can think about those thorns and thistles as the pain that
would be associated with work if you've ever dealt with thorns and thistles you
understand the pain that they can inflict and if you've never encountered
that we have some rose bushes over here and if you'd like to trim them next time
you can feel free but the reality is that we see sorrow in verse 17 we really
see pain in verse 18 notice in verse number 19 the last part of the verse of
scripture says for dust thou art excuse me for let me just read the whole verse
in the sweat of thy face shalt thou eat bread till thou return unto the ground
for out of it was thou taken for dust thou art and unto dust shalt thou
return he's speaking of death and so we see in verse 17 sorrow we see in verse
18 pain we see in verse 19 death I want you to remember that in Isaiah 53 the
prophet describes the Lord Jesus Christ Messiah who would come as a man of
sorrows a man of sorrows he says this and in Isaiah 53 in verse number 3 he
is despised and rejected of men a man of sorrows and acquainted with grief and we
hid as it were our faces from him he was despised and we esteemed him not
Surely he has borne our griefs and carried our sorrows.
Yet we did esteem him stricken, smitten of God and afflicted.
But he was wounded for our transgressions.
He was bruised for our iniquities.
The chastisement of our peace was upon him.
And with his stripes, we are healed.
All we like sheep have gone astray.
We have turned everyone to his own way.
The Lord hath laid on him the iniquity of us all.
He was oppressed and he was afflicted.
And he opened not his mouth.
He was brought as a lamb to the slaughter and as a sheep
before the shearers as dumb.
So he openeth not his mouth.
Mark would tell us and we can read it in the other Gospels as well
about that crown of thorns that was placed upon our Savior's head.
You think about the pain we get a little thorn in our finger
or on our arms as we're working in the brush and dealing with those things,
and we can think about the pain that could be inflicted.
In fact, we look here at the Savior and we think about the crown of thorns.
I mean, the very penalty or the judgment that is announced in Genesis three,
that these thorns and thistles would come as a result of the sin
that entered in the world.
And they take the crown of thorns and place it upon our Savior's head.
We're told in Hebrews in chapter two and verse number nine,
the Lord Jesus Christ, that he tasted death for every man.
We think about those three references of Scripture
in Isaiah 53, verses three through seven, in Mark 15, in verse 17,
in Hebrews two and verse number nine.
And we compare those statements about our Savior
and we compare them back to Genesis chapter number three.
And we find that he, the Lord Jesus Christ, that which was pictured
in those coats of skins, that substitutionary atonement
that is pictured all the way back there in Genesis chapter number three
and verses 21 through 24, it is fulfilled in the person of Jesus Christ.
I'm reminded this evening of the book of Revelation.
And what a wonderful place for us to finish our study of Genesis three this evening.
Look in Revelation chapter 21, if you will.
You'll remember, as we mentioned last Sunday,
as you're turning there to Revelation 21,
as we mentioned last Sunday evening,
we looked at that truth of Genesis 315.
And the fact that throughout all of the Old Testament,
you can read of so many events that are recorded for us
and we can read of those that would come to attack the seed
that God had promised his Savior, the Messiah,
to come through the seed, through the line of Abraham.
And you can find so many instances in the Old Testament
where it was thought that that line would be corrupted,
that that line would be destroyed.
Why? So that Messiah could not come.
But our God is greater than the enemy.
And we know that our God is victorious.
And we think about all of that in Genesis 3.
And from Genesis 3 to Revelation 21,
I mean, what a huge amount of Scripture.
And we see from the beginning to the end,
we see in all of the pages in between,
how God is interacting with his creation, with mankind.
And we find that sin entered the world in Genesis 3.
God gave us the picture of the substitutionary atonement
at the end of the chapter.
But I want you to notice in Revelation 21 here,
in verses 4 through 6, the Bible says this,
and God...
Now understand, the period of the tribulation is now completed.
The millennial reign of Christ is completed.
And the judgment seat of Christ has taken place.
And we're entering into that eternal state
as we come to Revelation 21.
It says, God shall wipe away all tears from their eyes.
And there shall be no more death,
neither sorrow, nor crying.
Neither shall there be any more what?
Pain, for the former things are passed away.
And he that sat upon the throne said,
Behold, I make all things new.
And he said unto me, Write, for these words are true and faithful.
And he said unto me, It is done.
I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end.
I will give unto him that is a thirst
the fountain of the water of life freely.
In verse 4, you find those three points
that I made reference of, the sorrow, the pain, and the death.
You find that it's mentioned in this verse of Scripture
that there would be no more death, nor sorrow, nor pain.
The result of the sin that entered the world
as it's recorded for us in Genesis 3,
we find that because of what Jesus Christ did on the cross of Calvary,
He says there's no more sorrow, death, or pain.
But I want you to look just a chapter further,
the final chapter of God's Word.
In Revelation 22, as we look at verses 1 through 5,
what a wonderful passage of Scripture it is.
The Bible says, He showed me a pure river of water of life,
clear as crystal,
proceeding out of the throne of God unto the Lamb.
In the midst of the street of it,
on either side of the river was there,
what is it? The tree of life.
Which bare twelve manner of fruits, and yielded her fruit every month,
and the leaves of the tree were for the healing of the nations.
Notice this in verse 3,
there shall be no more curse.
The throne of God unto the Lamb shall be in it,
and His servants shall serve Him.
And they shall see His face,
and His name shall be in their foreheads.
And there shall be no night there.
They need no candle, neither light of the sun,
for the Lord God giveth them light,
and they shall reign forever and ever.
Isn't that wonderful?
I mean, that just makes you want to go ahead and go, doesn't it?
I'm ready, Lord! Amen!
I mean, it says, this picture that God gives us
in verse number 1 and 2 of what we'd see,
but then He says there's no more curse.
He tells us that the throne of God unto the Lamb shall be in it,
His servants shall serve Him.
We're going to see His face in verse number 4.
We sing the songs, and Fanny Crosby wrote many of those songs
about seeing my Lord first of all, my Savior first of all,
and thinking about looking upon His face,
and we sang what a gathering that will be as a choir this morning,
and we sing what a day that will be as a congregational,
and we think about that when I see Him.
What a joyful, joyful truth.
It says, they shall see His face.
His name shall be in their foreheads.
We belong to Him.
There's no night.
It says that they shall reign forever and ever.
But I want you to notice, it says there's no more curse.
And I want you to notice that from Genesis chapter number 3,
it was in chapter 2 that we first read about the tree of life.
It was in Genesis chapter number 3 that they took of the tree of good and knowledge,
right, of the evil of good and knowledge, excuse me,
the tree of the knowledge of good and evil, I'll get it right,
and they partook of that fruit.
And then it's in Genesis chapter number 3 that God forbids entrance into the garden
lest man should eat of the tree of life.
We find that it's not until Genesis chapter,
with the flood, Genesis 6 through 8,
where the garden and the tree would be destroyed,
and now all the way in the eternal state in Revelation 22,
once again we read about the tree of life.
And what a blessing that is.
See, God has some better way.
His way is always better.
And as we look at Genesis chapter number 3,
we read a historical account of an event that happened in the life of Adam and Eve.
Adam and Eve are standing there after God pursues them when they're hiding,
and they have this conversation,
and Eve says, not me, it's the serpent.
And of course, Adam said, not me, it's the woman you gave me.
And God announces his judgments to the serpent, and to Eve, and to Adam.
And then God says, by the way, those coverings that you have are not sufficient.
I need to make you some coats of skins.
And in so doing, He gave us a beautiful picture of the substitutionary atonement
when Jesus Christ would come as man.
100% God, 100% man.
And He would take upon Himself the sin of the world.
The Bible says that He hath made Him to be sin for us who knew no sin,
that we might be made the righteousness of God in Him.
The just for the unjust, the substitutionary atonement.
Genesis chapter number 3, the coats of skins.
Let's pray together.