Thessalonians chapter number five kind of as a springboard this evening if you will and we have previously discussed as we've been studying through
The book of Genesis we've gone through the opportunity really to study the first eight chapters thus far and over the last several
Messages from the book of Genesis. We've dealt with the global flood really God gives us the
Record of what was going on with mankind leading up to the flood and the judgment of God upon his own creation
We find that God
Tells us that Noah found grace in the eyes of the Lord and we find that God then begins to give instruction to Noah with
regard to building the ark and all of that and what a blessing to read through and to see how God
Has given us typologies even through those Old Testament truths
We've mentioned repeatedly that the first eleven chapters and obviously we've only gone through the first eight chapters
But the first eleven chapters of the book of Genesis are under deep attack in our society today
and there is a desire of those in our culture in our society to undermine the Word of God and to seek to
Destroy the foundation is really what they're seeking to do because you find
That if you can destroy the truth that is given to us in Genesis 1 through 11
Then all of a sudden everything else in the Word of God becomes open to discussion
Because all of the references that you find throughout the scripture that would refer back to the Genesis account
They're not really true because Genesis didn't really it's not it's just a fairy tale kind of a thing and it just really kind of destroys
The whole thing and so they're seeking to undermine the authority of the Word of God and to destroy the foundation
I believe even as I said in Sunday school this morning
The reason that there's a departure from sound doctrine the reason in which the Bible is under attack is because mankind does not want to
be accountable to the Creator God and we find here that there are things that we see in our society today in our
climate today in our culture and in our
Dealing with all of the things around us that we look at things. We say how do we interpret these things?
You know that I've mentioned to you several times as we were just discussed the Genesis flood that it was a catastrophic
Event that had major geological and climatic effects the impact of the global flood
Was huge and we find that as we studied a few weeks ago. I had up on the screen
I'm not using PowerPoint this evening, but I had up on the screen a picture of the Grand Canyon and
Had a little question on there
Is this the result of millions of years as they would try to tell us?
That's what the situation was or is this a result of Genesis flood the flood of Noah's time?
I went through a number of things shared a number of things with you and one of the things that we discussed as we looked
At that is there are times in life that we look at things and scientists will come upon something and begin to look at it
But they didn't see it happen and then they begin to try to figure out
How is it that this could have happened they begin to offer theories? Well, I think maybe this happened like this
I believe so
We look at the Grand Canyon and we theorize and we come to the conclusion
There's a little bit of water over millions and millions and millions of years that carved out this Grand Canyon
or
It could be that the result of the global flood there was a whole lot of water
the earth was soft because of all of the rain and all that was upon the earth for all of those months and as God
caused the wind to come and the waters assuaged and went down continually that that is the impact of
the waters being abated and we looked at and shared a number of examples with you as to other
Canyons that you can find and see and you can look at wow that took place in six days that took place in
24 hours and we gave you illustration and examples of those things and I believe it's important that we see that
Now this evening as we begin to consider the idea of the Ice Age
It's something that's discussed often
But most people when I think about the Ice Age the only thing they know about the Ice Age is what some?
History channel some science some person has tried to tell them about the Ice Age
There's not a verse of scripture that says then there was an Ice Age. All right, it just doesn't exist. It's not there
However, we find that there is evidence and we'll look at some things here in just a moment that there was an Ice Age
I have you in first Thessalonians 5 I want to point out to you verse number 21
The Bible says this in in first Thessalonians 5 verse 21 prove all
things
Hold fast that which is good
Can I tell you that God and his word are good?
God is he he is eternal. Amen
He was there in the beginning
He's Alpha and Omega
He's eternal God and we find that he has provided us with a record and in the record that he has given us
He has provided all that he deems
Necessary for us to have and by the way, if that's all that he chose to give us then I believe that's all we need
Amen, and he's given us truth. The problem is not with what we see. The problem is in how we
Interpret what we see and that's an important point as we go through
The message this evening the problem isn't with what we see the evidence that we see that there was an Ice Age
that's not the problem the problem is how we
interpret what we see and
If we start with the Bible if we prove all things and we hold fast that which is good and we go to the Word
Of God we say we want to seek God and we want to seek God's face
I want to be able to interpret these things based upon the truth of God's Word now
We find that there are many that would give these in fact
Many scientists are on record as saying we really have no idea how the Ice Age came into effect
There's a lot of theories, but no one really knows that's pretty helpful. Is it not now?
they don't really teach it that way, but there's many that are on record of saying that and
The reality this evening is that they would give some of these theories that it took millions or billions of years in order for this
Snow and ice to accumulate
and all of these things to take place and so then all of a sudden you got this long age of the earth and you
Begin to influence and impact other aspects of Scripture and it becomes very problematic
Now does it really take millions and billions of years or does it simply take the right conditions?
And that is a question that has to be answered regularly as you approach these subjects and you have to understand we dealt with
a number of weeks ago when we dealt with the subject of the Grand Canyon with the idea of
the
Uniformitarianism and the idea that everything is going to take place everything that we can measure today has always taken place at that same rate
Well, the problem is that you you miss out on the catastrophic impact of the global flood
You don't take that into consideration
The problem that we find is that when there's something like Mount st
Helens that that explodes back in 1980 and all of the impact and effect of that you say, okay
There was a catastrophic event that changed how all of that landscape currently looks and there was a long-term
Effect upon all of those things as we looked at several weeks ago
And so when we begin to look at this subject of the ice age
We find first of all that there is in fact evidence of an ice age
Evidence exists that there's a nice age that there has been a nice age now
Most secular scientists would tell you that there's a nice age. They actually would tell you there are many ice ages
They're initially had the idea that there were three maybe four ice ages as they would call it
And then they said somewhere in the mid 70s into the 80s
They're like, oh, maybe they're actually like 20 or 30 ice ages and they just kind of bounce all over the place
And again, they really have no idea as to how this all happened
There's a lot of theories that exist but they kind of conclude they really don't know now the Bible as I've mentioned already by way
Of introduction does not say and then there was a nice age
However, when we examine the evidence again, it's not so much in what we see
It's how we interpret what we see as we examine the evidence of the ice age. We find that there are
glacial features that lie on top of sedimentary rock now if that is the case then that would be
Indicative of the fact that the ice age took place after the global flood
So it helps us to try to nail down the period of history in which the ice age took place now
Understand with me that the Bible in the record of the Bible and the people
That we find recorded in Scripture that until the Tower of Babel
As we'll come to in just a few chapters in Genesis chapter 11
It seems as if most of much of the earth's population stayed in a somewhat local area
We find that the animals got off the ark
they went there to replenish the earth and of course it was Noah and his wife his three sons and their wives that get
off the ark there to
Reproduce but it seems as if as you come to Genesis chapter 11
That they had stayed somewhat local and then of course the disbursement at the Tower of Babel
With that being understood
You would come to the conclusion that there's not a whole lot of things written in the canon of Scripture
With regard to the impact or the existence of the ice age because there weren't a lot of people around where the ice
A
Lot of people in fact, they they estimate that during the ice age about 30% of the land was covered with ice
Today, about 10% of the land is covered with ice.
Now if 30% of the land was covered with ice
is what they estimate.
Now there's some people that have these theories
that the entire earth was this ball of ice.
That doesn't even make sense.
Scientists agree that doesn't even make sense, okay?
So we can throw that theory out very quickly.
But if they say 30% of the land was covered
at the height of the ice age,
and today there's about 10% of it that's covered,
you would understand that there's not a lot of people
that are writing about the ice age or the impact
and all of that sort of thing
because of the population of the earth
and where people were during that particular time.
I want you to hold your place here in Genesis 8.
I will get there, I promise.
Turn over to the book of Job in Job 38.
You find that in Job 38 that God records for us
in this passage of scripture God's first speech to Job.
Now you remember if you study the book of Job
that Job is introduced to us as being a man
that walked with God and you understand all
that he encountered and then his friends
who were miserable comforters came
with the purpose of trying to encourage him
and there's all sorts of conversations
that go back and forth and speeches from his friends
and then Job's reply and so on and so forth.
We come here to the latter part of the book of Job
and we see that this, Job 38, is God's answer,
the first speech to Job.
It begins in verse number one,
then the Lord answered Job out of the whirlwind
and said, we don't have time to read the entirety
of the passage, I want to pull out four verses
of scripture for you.
Look in verse 22, the Bible says,
hast thou entered into the treasures of the snow
or hast thou seen the treasures of the hail
which I have reserved against the time of trouble
against the day of battle and war.
Skip down, if you will, to verse number 29.
The Bible says out of whose womb came the ice
and the orifrost of heaven, who hath gendered it?
The waters are hid as with a stone
and the face of the deep is frozen.
We find that even where Job was located
during the time in which he would have lived,
he would not have been necessarily in that 30%
of the earth that was covered with ice
but we do find that there is, it is interesting,
I believe that the verses here in Job
are at least worth considering
when we discuss the subject of the Ice Age.
So when we look at the Ice Age
and we begin to consider the evidence of the Ice Age,
we see it in our world today
and then we ask the question, how could this have happened?
If you're taking notes, I want you to consider
the conditions that are required for an Ice Age.
Now, these conditions that are required
are very rare conditions.
Science agrees, by the way, on these conditions
and though they give their theories
that don't even make sense
with regard to what the conditions would be,
we find that there are some specific requirements
in order for an Ice Age to take place.
Number one is that there would be cooler summers,
cooler summers.
In other words, what would have to happen
is the temperature, the global temperature
of the land area would have to cool during the summertime.
Now, in order for that to happen,
we begin to look at the word of God,
I know we're in eight, look back in chapter number seven,
if you will, just for a moment.
The Bible tells us in verse number nine,
there went in two and two into Noah into the ark,
the male and the female as God had commanded Noah,
verse 10 of Genesis seven,
and it came to pass after seven days
that the waters of the flood were upon the earth.
In the 600th year of Noah's life,
in the second month, the 17th day of the month,
the same day were all the fountains of the great deep
broken up and the windows of heaven were opened.
It then talks about the rain for 40 days and 40 nights,
but you understand that there was more than,
Noah's flood was more than just rain.
Yes, it was rain, but remember the deep was broken up,
you think about there's a lot of evidence,
we talked about it several weeks ago
of some of the volcanic activity that was taking place
during and after the flood.
And so in order for these cooler summers,
we know that there were many volcanoes
that were taking place that are very active,
you can look at several things within the strata
and look at various evidences of that.
And you would find that during that heightened activity
of volcanoes, that some of the ash and debris
would have filled the stratosphere, not filled it entirely,
but those particles would have been there.
And through that process, it would have reflected
some of the sunlight, which would decrease
the overall temperature of earth.
By the way, this isn't just something that a creationist
is coming up with to try to give an explanation
as to the ice age, science agrees that this is the case.
I have a printout here, I wanted to read it.
I got this from AccuWeather.com.
Last thing I heard, they're not independent
fundamental Baptist preachers, okay?
And AccuWeather, I have it on my phone,
they give you some good weather,
but meteorologists, you know, they get paid pretty well,
I understand, and they're wrong a whole lot.
But here's what AccuWeather says
with regard to volcanic eruptions
and the influence that they have upon global temperature.
Here's what it says, volcanic eruptions
can influence climate and global temperature.
Why?
Because of the gases and dust particles
spewed into the atmosphere during the eruption.
The small ash and aerosol particles
decrease the amount of sunlight
reaching the surface of the earth
and lower average global temperatures.
So if we know that was happening during the flood,
we understand all of that volcanic activity
that would take place, and it was taking place
for a lengthy period of time during and after,
you think about how that would have influenced
and really affected the overall temperature of the earth
and causing it to be cooler.
That's one requirement.
A second requirement is that there would need
to be an increase in moisture.
And so it's one thing to have cooler temperatures,
but if you have cooler temperatures and no moisture,
you don't really have this idea of an ice age
and have all this snow.
So you need to have an increase in moisture.
Now, warm ocean water would be the result
of all of this volcanic activity.
Think about all the lava,
and you think about all of the great deep.
We just read it in chapter number seven
and verse number 11.
The Bible says the same day were all the fountains
of the great deep broken up,
the windows of heaven were opened.
And so when all of that was taking place
and the fountains of the great deep were broken up,
that warm water or that lava
would cause the water temperature to increase.
Now, with water temperature increasing,
that increases the rate of evaporation.
Why?
Warm water evaporates quicker than cold water does.
The best temperature for evaporation is 212 degrees.
Why?
Because that's the boiling point.
If you boil water, you see that it evaporates quickly.
All right?
Scienceing.com says hot water evaporates faster
than cold water because the molecules of hot water
have more energy to escape the surface
and turn into a gas molecule.
Evaporation occurs when heat is applied.
It occurs especially fast.
Once water reaches 212 degrees Fahrenheit,
the temperature is known as the boiling point.
It stands to reason then
that if you're trying to make water evaporate,
it is necessary to apply heat.
Now, stay with me this evening
and understand what's taking place.
We're talking about the ice age.
We're thinking about how did this happen
and how can we look at the Bible
and examine the evidence and interpret the evidence
and come to a biblical conclusion
or do we have to believe these modern scientists
that there's millions and millions and billions of years
and then it messes up the whole timeline of the Bible
and really just kind of...
And so here's what happens.
Some Christians have no idea how to deal with it
and so they just avoid it.
And so somebody challenges us on the global flood
or, well, what about the ice age?
We're like, yeah, I have no idea.
I mean, I never...
Listen, I've never preached on the ice age before.
I've never heard anyone preach on the ice age.
No one taught it to me in Bible college.
We just don't talk about it.
So we allow people to give our children, our young people,
these ideas about ice age
and we allow these scientists with their degrees
and all of their vernacular
to go ahead and give their theories
and it kind of just,
we don't know how to interpret it with a biblical worldview.
So we see this increase in moisture.
If the evaporation levels would be increased significantly,
it would provide for that necessary moisture
because you need an increase of moisture.
It's one thing to have cooler summers,
but if you don't have the moisture,
you're not gonna produce the snow.
And you need to have those cooler summers, why?
Because when the snow falls,
you don't want it to melt in the summer when the sun...
You understand how this is working, right?
This kind of goes together,
these rare conditions that are required for an ice age.
There's also the need for a period of time
in order to accumulate the necessary amount of snow and ice
that would result in an ice age.
Therefore, those conditions are necessary
to last really several hundred years,
though scientists would like to tell us
that they need to last several hundred thousand years.
And that's why they begin coming up
with all of these 20, 30 different ice ages
as opposed to just one single ice age.
That's kind of interesting.
There's a...
Faith would know about this up there in Buffalo.
Lake affects snow, right?
Lake affects snow.
We hear about it.
In fact, I got a note on my phone this morning
about lake affects snow,
and I took a picture of it because it fit perfect
with what we're dealing with this evening.
And the reality is that what happens,
what causes this heavy snow
that we often refer to as lake affects snow,
it's when that cold air moves over the warm water.
And you have this increase of evaporation because of the warm water and it results in
some pretty major snowstorms.
And you see that to be the case and you find that when those conditions are in that situation,
that this is what the impact or the result of those conditions are.
So we understand that for this period of time, again, there would be this need for these
specific conditions.
Eventually, after the flood and after all that we read of in Genesis, in chapter number
8, in verse number 1, the Bible says that God remembered Noah.
Remember at the end of verse number 1 it says that God made a wind to pass over the earth
and the waters assuaged.
We talked about how in verse number 5 it says that the waters decreased continually.
Eventually the tops of the mountains were seen.
Noah then sends out the birds and of course he begins there with the raven.
It doesn't return.
He deals with the dove and there's a couple of journeys that take place.
And eventually the Bible tells us that Noah, at the end of verse number 13, removed the
covering of the ark and looked and behold the face of the ground was dry and in the
second month on the seventh and twentieth day of the month was the earth dried.
And then the Bible tells us that God spake unto Noah and told him that go forth of the
ark thou and thy wife and thy sons and thy sons' wives with thee.
And we mentioned as we studied that part of Genesis chapter number 8 that the earth in
which Noah and his family stepped upon was drastically different than what it was when
he got on the ark.
Because of all of the geological impact and influence it was a catastrophic event.
Now eventually, we talk about those specific conditions that are required in order to have
this ice age, eventually the volcanic activity would decrease and therefore the water temperature
would also decrease.
If you don't have the great deep kind of continuing to spew out lava, you don't have
all this volcanic activity, obviously you're going to have water temperatures that are
going to decrease.
You're also going to have less of those particles in the atmosphere that are going to reflect
or deflect the sun rays.
And so you're going to find that with the volcanic activity decreasing and the water
temperature decreasing that the result would be that the global temperature would increase
and the water temperature would decrease.
As you begin to think about that effect, you find that it would lead to less moisture and
more melting, right?
Because it's the reverse effect.
If you have warm water and you have reflected sun, because of all of those particles you
have cooler temperatures and you have more evaporation.
But as that process goes on for a period of time and you have less and less volcanic activity,
you have less ash up there, so there's more sunlight coming in.
Temperatures begin to rise, there's less lava being spewed into the water, thus the temperatures
of the water are decreasing.
You don't have as much evaporation and then you have more melting.
So the ice age begins to recede and no longer is it covering as much as it covers today.
We have 10% as I mentioned at the beginning.
Now I didn't do the calculations, I'm not a scientist.
I told you that this morning before we ever came back tonight.
But the reality is that there are some that have done all of these very sophisticated
calculations that I did read through and looked at them.
They made sense to me, but I didn't do the calculations and as they calculated the rates
of evaporation with specific temperatures of water versus the temperatures of the land
and blah, blah, blah.
And I'm not saying that to be disrespectful or to say that it's not worthy, but what they
conclude after all of their calculations is that for the ice age to take place as we would
look at the evidence and begin to evaluate those things, that it would take about 700
years total.
500 years for the ice to accumulate and about 200 years for the ice to decrease.
Now when we think about this, there's moraines and some other things that you see these indentations
and different things in rock that people look to and they say, oh look at these and this
shows evidence of multiple ice ages.
They fail to take into consideration the impact again of the global flood with all of that
water assuaging and all that was taking place and all of the impact there during that time.
So we find that though they would try to tell us it takes millions or billions of years,
if the conditions are right, in just 700 years, 500 years of accumulation, you could get the
amount of ice that is estimated to have covered the land at that time, and then of course
with that decrease over that final 200 years.
Now it's interesting because here's what evolutionary scientists would try to tell us.
They give this idea of a slow and gradual evolutionary scenario to explain the ice age,
but it cannot work.
Here's why.
They have these long age theories that involve a slowing down of the earth, sorry, a slow
cooling of the earth, but they do not come to the right conclusion that that's not going
to generate an ice age.
Why?
Because if the oceans are cooling gradually and the land is cooling gradually, by the
time everything was cold enough for enough snow to come that would not melt, then the
evaporation from the oceans would be insufficient to produce enough snow.
So what these scientists have concluded is that if that model were the proper model that
we follow, you would never have an ice age, you would just have a frozen desert.
Because everything would be cooling at that same time, and so you're not going to have
that evaporation, and you need all of that moisture, you need all of that in order to
produce this amount of snow.
So we look at those things and we see some things that we found here in the time of the
flood and all that was going on with that geological climatic impact.
The Bible says to prove all things.
I love it when we come to the scriptures and we conclude and we look at what God has given
us in His word, we look at some science stuff and we say, look, I don't have to be concerned
about what I see, it's how we interpret what we see.
We take and we start with the Bible and we can reach a conclusion that makes sense, not
only biblically but also scientifically.
Now I love it when there's some evidence of something in recent history that helps to
prove the point.
We don't need it, but it certainly is interesting to evaluate.
Some of those canyons that I showed you several weeks ago, they aren't necessary for me to
believe that the Grand Canyon was the result of the global flood, not millions and millions
and millions of years.
I don't need the evidence, but the evidence is kind of interesting when you get to see
it and say, well, what about this?
What about this?
You remember with some of those, the canyon, there was that tumbleweed where it kind of
blocked up the water and then they had to divert and there's a canyon there.
It's amazing.
And we looked at those things, but we find that there was something interesting that
happened back on July 15th.
By the way, that's a good day, right?
Is Natalie up here?
There she is.
July 15th, that's a good day, right?
But it was in 1942.
That's a little bit before you were born and even a little bit before I was born.
But on July 15th, 1942, what are we in in 1942?
We're in World War II, right?
And that's what we're in.
There is a secret U.S. Army air base in Greenland.
And at this secret U.S. air base in Greenland, on the morning of July 15th, 1942, there were
eight planes that took off.
There were six P-38 fighter planes and two B-17 bombers that were heading to a British
airfield.
They were not going to be able to make it all the way to this British airfield.
They were going to have to stop and take for fueling in Iceland.
And as they were going, as they began their journey, they encountered some very serious
weather, very adverse.
The weather was adverse.
They got word that they would not be able to land in Iceland in order to refuel.
And so they have a problem.
So what they decide to do is now they're going to turn back and they're going to go back
to the U.S. Army airfield in Greenland so that they can refuel there.
Well, as they're going through this process, the storm is getting worse and worse.
And now the airfield in Greenland says, we're closed.
You can't land here.
Well, what do you do?
If you have no fuel, you have nowhere to land.
I mean, you've got to make some decisions.
And so what we find is that due to this adverse weather and the need for fuel, they had to
crash land on Greenland's east coast.
And these eight planes crash landed, but there was a lot of snow.
And so they really, there was minimal damage to the aircraft.
The first aircraft had more damage than the others because the first aircraft put their
landing gear down.
And when they did, they hit the snow and they flipped and kind of was a problem.
But no real injuries to the pilot.
Everything was okay that way because of the amount of snow that was there.
And the other planes, as they noticed what happened, they said, we're not going to put
our nose gear down.
We're going to just belly land.
And they all landed.
They were safely landed.
Nine days after this situation, they were rescued from some dog sled.
This is history.
I mean, it happened.
Okay.
And they were rescued from some dog sleds.
And this was in 1942.
For a number of years, no one really thought about this, these lost squadron of aircraft.
It was a secret base on Greenland that they were going and so on and so forth.
And so we find that there were a couple of men, Patrick Epps and Richard Taylor.
and in 1980 they said you know what we're gonna go find those aircraft
because these p-38s are rare aircraft and they're worth a lot now I was just
born in 1980 so I don't remember this okay I had to look up and study history
but some of you like yeah yeah 1980 I remember that and here's what happened
these guys Epps and Taylor they literally thought that they were gonna
go and shovel a little bit of snow off of the wings put some fuel in those bad
boys and take off that's really what they thought and they said man these
things are gonna be intact this is perfect and so they go over there and
there's no evidence of any aircraft there's no let's try to clear off some
snow and we're gonna fly these things out of here no there's nothing so they
begin to investigate this was in 1980 when it took place this they led this
salvage mission it wasn't until 1988 eight years later when they actually
reached the first aircraft they had to use all kinds of sophisticated radar and
all sorts of things that were going on and eight years after they began this
salvage mission but lots of money by the way that they spent on this they
finally locate the first of these aircrafts they find this they use this
radar they discover these eight large shapes and they begin to get that first
plane do you know that that first plane was under 250 feet of solid ice 250 feet
of solid ice in less than 50 years you know when they got to those aircraft
they were just as they were when they landed there just as they were when they
landed proving that they did not sink in the ice but they were buried by the
snow and ice and so you think about that that in 50 years less than 50 years that
when they came and they finally found those aircraft that they're 250 feet
below solid ice intact it was built up year after or you know during that
process of all those by the way Greenland is not very green if you
didn't know that news flash okay we went out to dinner with our missionaries from
Greenland several years ago and as we went out to dinner with our missionaries
from Greenland several years ago the whole family was there and their whole
family was there the show family we have two families there now in Greenland but
this was with the show family specifically and we're not to eat or
eating and the waiters asked us some questions and we're talking I said well
you know I pastor a church and these folks are actually missionaries in
Greenland and do you know where Greenland is and that waiter it was
hilarious that waiter says oh yeah everything's so green and everything's
so nice he was as serious as he could be and those little missionary kids looked
at each other like what is this guy talking about like they were very
respectful they didn't say a word to that that guy but it was hilarious right
and so Greenland lots of snow up there lots of ice that accumulates very
quickly and so all I'm saying this evening is that when we look at the the
global flood and we begin to think about the impact of the global flood and again
as I mentioned by way of introduction not only would it have a geological
impact but the climatic impact of the flood all of these volcanoes and all of
these things that are taking place and how that would result in perfect
conditions for an ice age because you don't have as much of the Sun rays
coming through because all of those particles that are that are coming from
those volcanoes they're filling the stratosphere not filling it entirely as
I mentioned earlier but they're they're going into the stratosphere and they're
deflecting those rays and you find that the global temperature is decreasing in
fact when there are major volcanic activity that takes place even today you
find that locally and sometimes even on a wider scale it impacts the global
temperature it just does and science knows that and so when you think about
the increased activity and as much as was going on and you think about those
Sun rays being deflected you think about the warmer water that would evaporate at
a quicker rate because of the the the warmth of the water and it's perfect
conditions for that perfect storm you ever hear meteorologists say that these
are the perfect conditions for a perfect storm we hear people use that
terminology meteorologists when we live here on the East Coast they talk about
nor'easters right that's when we're gonna get the bad snow right and what
happens I don't know because I'm not a meteorologist but those low pressures
kind of meet and one comes from the South and one's coming from the West and
they super generate one another and it just produced a lot of snow though
that's when we get snow storms on the East Coast right I mean serious snow
storms I think it was in January of 2017 maybe 2018 what we got like 33 inches of
snow in just a what a day and a half does anyone remember that 36 I mean it
was insane my Kia Optima I couldn't see it I'm like I know that I parked there
but I cannot see my car it was completely buried in the snow and it was
a situation where it was just perfect conditions so you think about all that
was taking place after the flood and all of that geological and climatic impact
those were perfect conditions to result in an ice age and the theory of these
evolutionists that it took millions and millions and millions of years with all
of this very gradual cooling of temperatures both of the water and of
it doesn't even work scientifically but that's what they try to give us a theory
why because they don't want to believe this book that's really the that's
really the basis of it is they don't want to believe the book because if you
believe the global flood we talked to people when we were in at the Grand
Canyon back in 2000 and when do we go to the Grand Canyon 2011 I went to the
Grand Canyon and the guy was giving us all this speech about how all this stuff
happened I said well did you ever consider that maybe as the result of the
global flood Oh global flood they just dismiss it but why because they don't
want to recognize that this book is true and thus be accountable to the God of
the Bible in this evening listen we don't have to be afraid to talk about
the Grand Canyon we don't have to be afraid to talk about the ice age but it
doesn't have to be something that we need to be fearful of so I don't know
how to answer the questions just understand that the the global flood had
a major catastrophic climatic impact upon this world and we're going to go
from that perspective prove all things dig in dig into the scriptures look at
the science and show again it's not a problem with what we see it's a problem
with how we interpret what we see and they secular humanistic scientists like
to begin apart from God we must begin with God amen
it's absolutely imperative I don't know if it's gonna be next Sunday evening or
maybe the Sunday evening afterwards I don't like doing all this science stuff
every single Sunday evening but either next week or the following week I'm
gonna do a series or a lesson on dinosaurs why because that's another one
of those things that everyone wants to talk about dinosaurs and there's a lot
of Christians that just don't know how to talk about the subject do you know
that the word dinosaur is not in the Bible it's not you know why the Bible
was written before the word was invented the word dinosaur didn't even come
around until the 19th century seriously look it up and so because the word
dinosaurs in the Bible doesn't mean that dinosaurs didn't exist we know they
existed they didn't exist millions and billions of years ago they were created
on the same day that all the other animals were created day six right I
mean anyhow we'll get with that in a couple weeks but it's these are subjects
that we don't have to be afraid of we have the Word of God we have the truth
amen and we interpret things starting with God and knowing that he's given us
what we need in his word let's pray together