nights through this psalm. We did Psalm 25 for three weeks and then got into Psalm 81. And if
you were here last Wednesday evening, we actually really didn't do a whole lot of anything in Psalm
81. We gave an introduction to the psalm and understood that this particular psalm is a psalm
that was associated with the Feast of Tabernacles. And so for us to have a greater understanding
of this psalm as we would study through it, I thought it necessary to go back and to study
in the book of Leviticus and reference some stuff over the book of Exodus as well with regard to
the Feast of the Tabernacles. We also went over the New Testament and saw the Lord Jesus Christ
in John 7 there and so on and so forth, and introductory lessons so that we could gather
some understanding of this particular psalm. So this evening, we'll begin looking at the psalm,
looking at the first three verses this evening. Maybe you've heard it said, it's been said often
that the book of Psalms being referred to as Israel's songbook. And certainly there's truth
to that. Indeed, even still today, there are particular psalms or parts of psalms that we
still sing today. We probably don't sing it the same way that they did. Sometimes we look at it
and someone's put it to music and we'll sing it. And some of you know some of the psalms
that we'll sing. Psalm 48, great is the Lord. Psalm 19, the law of the Lord is perfect. And
there's several of them, just a couple of them quickly. But we know that this book has often
been referred to as Israel's songbook. And I'm thankful for the ministry of music and for the
gift of music. I would say this, that music is a gift from God to humanity. And we are, as humans,
we are musical people. And music ministers to the heart. And as we begin looking at this particular
psalm in these first three verses, we see this aspect of singing. Notice it says, sing aloud
unto God our strength, make a joyful noise unto the God of Jacob. Take a psalm and bring hither
the timbrel and pleasant harp with the psaltery. Blow up the trumpet in the new moon, the time
appointed on our solemn feast day. As we look at these three verses, I've simply entitled the
message for this evening as we get into Psalm 81, praise with song. And music, as I mentioned
already, is a gift from God to humanity. It's a means by which we are able to praise the Lord.
You think about the ministry of music, the purpose of music for us as we begin to look at
the content of Psalm 81, and even thinking about within the context of church and as believers,
the ministry of music. And I would say that music is part of life and culture. And you can go all
around the world and you can find music. It's very interesting. In fact, I would say this, I love
music. But you know something interesting, and you might be able to say the same thing,
I love music today, but I loved music before I got saved. It was a different kind of music,
but I love music. And the reality is that when I got saved, my music changed, but we are musical
beings. Music has great power, the ability of those that are writing songs to send forth a
message, not only through the lyrics of the songs, but also, of course, through the beat of the song,
etc., etc. And so we see some of those things. I'm not going to dive into all of that this evening,
but we understand that we're musical beings. Think about children. I mean, just little kids
in a nursery, you start singing songs and they respond to that. They are drawn to that. Why?
Because of this music. Why is it that so many of these videos and things that are so prevalent
today with regard to children and the music that is there, and just it's obvious that music is part
of our nature as human beings. I think about this, and we'll be in Psalm 81, but look over at Psalm 40
if you will. And I want you to notice what the psalmist says in Psalm 40, and we see a very
important truth because we speak about being musical people. And I shared with you already
that I loved music before I got saved, but my music has changed. And notice in Psalm 40, in
verse number one, I waited patiently for the Lord, and he inclined unto me and heard my cry. He
brought me up also out of a horrible pit, out of the miry clay, and set my feet upon a rock,
and established my goings. But notice in verse number three, and he hath put a new song in my mouth.
Even praise unto our God, many shall see it, and fear, and shall trust in the Lord. I would say
this, and you'd have to answer for yourself, but I would say that the music that I loved
before I got saved was not music that was praised to God. It wasn't. But it was music that I liked,
that I enjoyed. But after I got saved, God put a new song in my mouth, and God changed that aspect.
And I love music. I don't always sing on tune. We joke about it sometimes, about which key I'm going
to be in, and what happens when there's a key change. And I remember distinctly one time,
a few years ago, when we had a choir, and I was singing in the choir, and they decided that
it needed to be in a different key. And Miss Kimberly left this piano to go over here to this
one, so that it would transpose and put it in a different key. And so I asked for new music,
and Pierre looked at me like, what do you mean you need new music? I was like, well, if it's in a new
key, I got to have it, because this music is in that key. And I just, I don't understand everything
about music, but I love music. God's put a song in our heart. And you notice in Psalm 81,
that music is how this psalm begins. We mentioned last week about the Feast of Tabernacles,
and the aspect of praise, and what they would do, and how they were rejoicing for the harvest,
and what have you. And you see where the scriptures begin in this psalm with this
emphasis upon singing. Music is to praise God. It's to minister to our hearts. It's not
to entertain. That's not the purpose of music. We find that when we have special music in church,
when we sing hymns, and so on and so forth, when we speak about church music, there are times in
which people will give a hearty amen to a song, maybe that's being done with a special music,
that sort of thing. Maybe, as it happened, I think, two weeks ago, there were several people
that clapped at the end of a song. But that's not the purpose. It's not entertainment. It's
ministering. It's ministering to our hearts. There are times, I think it was even this past week,
that we put the words to the song up on the screen. Why? So that you can see the words. You
can read the words as the song is being sung. Why? So that it can minister to you. So it can minister
to me. And what a blessing to think about the ministry of music. As we begin to look in Psalm
81, and we learn some things about music, we notice that there are some truths here that God
gives us that are important. The first thing that we recognize is answering this question,
to whom do we sing? We find very plainly in verse number one, the Bible says, sing aloud unto God.
Sing aloud unto God our strength. And it continues, and make a joyful noise unto the God
of Jacob. They were singing to God. By the way, we have someone, and we have something to sing
about. Amen? Aren't you thankful when you sing a song about praising the Lord, living for Jesus?
We just sang it this evening. What a great hymn that reminds us of what he did for us, and how
we're to live for him. And as we sing the song, we're not just filling time. We're not just trying
to, we have to have this service schedule, and it has to be this way, and you have to include
this number of songs. No, it's ministering to us. The song service is part of worship.
Amen? The song service is not intended to be the time in which we're mingling, and talking,
and doing this, and checking this. And no, it's a time in which we're singing, and we're praising
God. And we're not only praising God, but through the song, as God would minister to our hearts,
and prepare us for the message that would follow. And we find that here, the Bible makes it very
plain that we are singing unto God. The psalmist is not giving instruction with regard to those
that would be gathered, that you're singing to them as being your primary audience. And yes,
when somebody sings here, there's an audience, the congregation, but we're singing to God.
And when you're singing to God, it makes all the difference. And we find this evening that
he makes it very plain that God is our strength, and he says at the end of verse number one,
unto the God of Jacob. And we understand, as we mentioned last week, this being a psalm that would
be relevant, and associated with the Feast of Tabernacles, and the emphasis there with being
unto the God of Jacob. Jacob, of course, becoming Israel, and so on and so forth.
But we find this evening that when we sing, we learn
learn some truth from Psalm 81 that we're singing to God.
Then we find not only who do we sing to,
but how are we to sing?
Notice in verse number one, sing aloud.
Sing aloud.
It then says this, make a joyful noise
unto the God of Jacob.
Now those two phrases, sing aloud, make a joyful noise,
are very interesting.
They really carry out the idea to sing out to shout.
That's what it means.
Listen, God's given us a song, God's given us,
we read Psalm 40, think about what he did for us
and how he delivered us and how he established our goings
and he's given us a reason to sing,
he's put a song in my mouth, in my heart,
and we find this evening that we're to sing out.
We're to not be shy about singing.
I like a church that sings out.
I feel like our church sings out and I like that.
I think part of that has to do, obviously,
with the personality of the leadership.
I think specifically the fact that Dean
is a very energetic song leader.
I think that helps a whole lot with congregational singing
and I appreciate the manner in which Dean
will lead congregational singing.
Why, because he wants to get us involved.
He wants to get us singing unto the Lord and singing out.
There have been times that I've visited churches
for revival meetings, missions conferences,
and I get into a church that has three, four, 500 people
and I sit there with my family
and we're gonna stand up and sing and I begin to sing
and all of a sudden I find out within about one measure
that I'm the loudest person in the entire section
in which we're singing or sitting, excuse me,
and I realize I gotta dial it back, I gotta tone it down
and I'm not being condemning, I'm not trying to be critical,
I'm just simply saying we got something to sing about.
Amen?
You think about somebody when they're talking.
You ever hear someone talk
and they're just talking real soft?
Listen, if you got something to say, say it.
Like, come on, I wanna hear ya.
And we sing out, sing aloud unto God our strength.
Make a joyful noise unto the God of Jacob.
And that phrase, a joyful noise,
often throughout the scriptures
is literally translated to shout.
To shout.
I'm thankful that we have someone
and something to sing about.
You think about singing Jesus Saves.
Isn't that a wonderful song?
Think about singing Jesus is a wonderful savior to me.
I mean, listen, you begin to sing that
and you're rejoicing and you're singing out, why?
Because the truth of that song
is not only bringing glory to God as we're singing to him,
but it's just ministering to our hearts.
The ministry of music.
Look over at Psalm 100 if you will, just a few pages over.
And it's a psalm also that deals much
with the idea of music and of course of giving thanks.
And I mentioned by way of introduction
that music is a means by which we praise the Lord.
And we find here in Psalm 100,
make a joyful noise unto the Lord all ye lands.
Serve the Lord with gladness,
come before his presence with singing.
If God tells us in his word,
this makes this emphasis and helps us to understand music,
I believe tonight when he says here,
serve the Lord with gladness,
come before his presence with singing,
God wants to hear us sing.
Amen?
God wants to hear you sing.
You say, well, I don't sing so well.
You're singing to God.
Amen?
And I understand those that are more musical,
I don't wanna be too silly about it,
but man, we're singing unto God.
And I understand the aspect of singing well
and the musical aspect on tune and so on and so forth.
I love it when these kids get up here and they just sing out.
Doesn't it bless your heart?
And think about little Zachary
and little Zachary is getting older,
but I mean, Zachary, man, he just, he sings out
and I love it.
And here's what, when I go and I preach chapel
at Christian schools,
and oftentimes when I've preached chapel
at Christian schools, they have you do both in one day.
You'd preach the elementary chapel
and then you got about a 15 minute break
and you preach the senior high chapel and it's amazing.
And those of you that have ever been
in a Christian school setting,
the little elementary school kids
that are singing in chapel,
man, they are singing.
And all of a sudden you get to the senior high,
junior high chapel and you're singing.
They're like, you can't, there's twice as many of them
and you can't hear them.
So you know what I started to tell the elementary kids?
Don't lose it in five years when you're up there.
Keep singing to God.
But all of a sudden they get so concerned
about what somebody else is hearing or I don't this.
We're singing to God.
Psalm 100, listen, God inhabits the praises of his people.
He likes it, he wants us to enter
into his presence with singing.
Verse three, know ye that the Lord, he is God.
It is he that hath made us and not we ourselves.
We are his people and the sheep of his pasture.
Enter into his gates with thanksgiving
and into his courts with praise.
Be thankful unto him and bless his name
for the Lord is good, his mercy is everlasting
and his truth endureth to all generations.
Don't you believe that the truth of verse number five?
The Lord is good, he's good all the time.
His mercy is everlasting, his truth does endure
and we're gonna praise him
and we're gonna praise him with song.
We find that in Psalm 81, not only does God teach us
in verse number one, how we're to sing
and to whom we're to sing, but we find that God
in verse two and three provides us
with the use of instruments.
And by the way, I'm thankful for those
that play instruments in our church
on Sunday morning and Sunday evening.
And they're typically in other places on Wednesday evening
and so we don't have them playing in here.
But on Sunday morning and Sunday evening
when they're playing their instruments,
man, it blesses my heart.
There have been times when Tim has been here
but not able to play his trumpet
and I say, you're not playing the trumpet today?
My lip, this, whatever, and I'm like, man, and I miss it.
Why?
Because I'm standing right here when we're singing
and he's blowing the trumpet right at me, amen?
And I love it.
The stringed instruments, isn't it beautiful?
It adds something to the music.
I'm thankful for the piano.
Aren't you thankful that we have piano players?
I can't play the piano.
You might be sitting there saying, I can't play the piano
but God has blessed us with piano players.
We have several in our church
and we are so thankful for each of them.
Why?
Do you know what it's like when you're singing a cappella?
Do you know how many churches don't have piano players?
Man, we're so blessed.
Look at what he talks about with regard to the instruments
in verse number two.
Take a psalm and bring hither the timbrel,
the pleasant harp with the psaltery.
Blow up the trumpet in the new moon
in the time appointed on our solemn feast day.
Listen, when they would sing,
the nation of Israel, very musical.
You think about all that they did
with regard to the tabernacle,
then the temple and all of the setting up
with regard to the music and the ministry of music.
And here the instruments are included in verses two and three
but remember Psalm 150, in fact, turn there.
And when you look in Psalm 150,
you'll see additional information given to us
about the use of instruments.
And we note the use of instruments in Psalm 150.
In verse number one, praise you the Lord,
praise God in his sanctuary,
praise him in the firmament of his power,
praise him for his mighty acts,
praise him according to his excellent greatness.
Notice in verse three,
praise him with the sound of the trumpet,
praise him with the psaltery and harp,
praise him with the timbrel and dance,
praise him with stringed instruments and organs,
praise him upon the loud cymbals,
praise him upon the high sounding cymbals.
Let everything that hath breath praise the Lord,
praise ye the Lord.
God wants to hear us sing.
God, I mentioned already, inhabits the praises of his people.
I believe as God would give music to his people,
we understand that that Lucifer fallen,
he was extremely musical.
If you look in the scriptures, you understand that.
And I believe that one of the things that he has done
is to corrupt music.
And so we find this evening that God wants us to sing
and he wants us to sing praise to his name
and we can praise him through song.
Listen, think about this.
When we talk about God wants to hear us sing,
when we introduce Psalm 81
and we see the way that this Psalm begins
and the aspect of it being associated
with the Feast of Tabernacles,
to sing aloud unto God our strength,
to make a joyful noise unto the God of Jacob,
we see this emphasis that's placed upon singing
and God wants his people to be singing.
He wants us to sing today.
Can I remind you of Paul and Silas?
Acts 16 and verse 25, it says this,
they sang praises unto God.
Amen?
Who do we sing to?
Well, sing aloud.
unto God our strength, make a joyful noise unto the God of Jacob. And it tells
us in Acts 16 and verse 25 that Paul and Silas sang praises unto God, but then it
says this, and the prisoners heard them. And the prisoners heard them. So you know
how they were singing? They were singing aloud. Amen? Because the prison... where
were they put? In the inner prison. Right? Is that what the Bible tells us in Acts 16?
They're put in the inner prison. But at midnight they're singing praises unto God and the prisoners
heard them. By the way, at midnight what are most people doing? I like to be sleeping at
midnight. I know some of you do not, but I like to sleep at midnight. Amen? They were
singing and they were singing aloud because the prisoners heard them. It's not this all
mellow kind of, Jesus is all the world to me. No, man, like we're singing out. Think
about this, Ephesians 5, we talk about the ministry of music for us today. Ephesians
chapter number 5, we'll get a passage in Ephesians, a passage in Colossians, as we see where this
psalm begins with this emphasis on music and this fact that we're to praise with song.
This evening I'm thankful that God saved me and that God put a new song in my mouth. And
I'm thankful today that my music is not the same music that I used to listen to. And my
music, listen, I want to listen to music that reminds me of how great my God is. I
want to listen to music that challenges me in my walk with God. And when I have, if you
were to sit in my office with me and you were to listen to some of the songs that I listen
to, they're songs that are doing exactly what I just said. They're reminding me of how wonderful
my God is and what He's done for me. And it's, man, it's just encouraging me and it's
ministering to me and it's strengthening me and it's just provoking me to go and to live
for Jesus. Ephesians 5, the Bible says this in verse number 18, and be not drunk with
wine or in his excess, but be filled with the Spirit. Now it's always interesting to
me that many times people say, I'm filled with the Spirit, but the Bible gives us really
evidences of what it means to be filled with the Spirit. Now we understand that we're commanded
to be filled with the Spirit. Being indwelled by the Spirit is what happens at the moment
of salvation. When I get saved, when you got saved, or when I said when I get, when I got
saved and when you got saved, when we trust that Christ is our Savior, the Holy Spirit
of God indwelled us. But the idea of the filling of the Holy Spirit of God is something
that changes. Why? Because we change. We're filled with self and we need to be emptied
of self. And just because I'm filled with the Spirit today doesn't mean I'm going to
be filled with the Spirit tomorrow. Just because I'm filled with the Spirit at 7.30 doesn't
mean I'm going to be filled with the Spirit at 8 o'clock, right? You're tracking. And
so we find that He says, but be filled with the Spirit. And here's some of the evidence.
Just like when you look at Galatians, when it talks about the fruit of the Spirit is,
don't say that you're walking in the Spirit, but there's no love, joy, peace, longsuffering.
No, that's the evidence. And here the Bible says, speaking to yourselves in psalms and
hymns, and it also says in spiritual songs, singing and making melody in your heart to
the Lord. Giving thanks always for all things unto God and the Father in the name of our
Lord Jesus Christ. You know, sometimes you might want to say, does it really have to
say always? Does it really have to say all things? Yes, because God is good all the time.
Amen? And He's worthy of our praise. We don't praise Him because our circumstances are good
all the time. We praise Him because He's good all the time. And it says, submitting yourselves
one to another in the fear of God. And so we find that in the context in which the Apostle
Paul is encouraging the believers in Ephesus. He's already established in the first three
chapters the fact that they're saved and their position is secure, is saved people. But now,
as he gets into chapter four and following, he's dealing with that practical aspect of what does
it mean now that you're a Christian? How do you live? How do you walk? The word walk is used
repeatedly in Ephesians 4, 5, and 6 because we're to walk a certain way because we've been saved.
And so when he talks about being filled with the Spirit, he lists these evidences and he lists
what is this going to look like? And it's interesting that verse 19 immediately starts
dealing with this subject of singing, of music. Speaking to yourselves in psalms and hymns and
spiritual songs, singing and making melody in your heart to who? To the Lord. To the Lord.
And what a blessing it is to be able to praise God through song. You know, just to be able to
have God remind you of a song and just allow it to minister to your heart as you go through maybe
a time of difficulty, as you go through whatever it is that you're facing and you're just, man,
God just ministers through song. I've mentioned this before and I think that it's essential to
understand and I don't claim to be a music scholar in any way, shape, or form. There's
much that I do not know about music and I readily admit that. But I do understand that we're all
different people and that when you start talking about right music, wrong music, that there's
really an idea of being able to look at a spectrum, if you will. And so there's right
music that might not be your style of music. Does that make sense tonight? It's not that it's wicked
music, it's still good music, it's still God-honoring music, but it may not be the exact
style that you like. In fact, if you were to think about some of, even some folks that have had the
opportunity to sing in our church, I think about when we had Pierre and Michael and Joseph and Tim,
I think, sang that four-men quartet. It was, that style of that was different than when some people
sing just a solo. But it doesn't mean that one's right and one's wrong. It's a different style. I
think they're both right. Again, if you could think about it linearly, like a spectrum, and
there's a section that, yes, this is bad, wrong music, this is bad, wrong music, but there's this
area that's going to be, this is really my style of music. This is really my style of music. I'm
sure you've heard, I remember hearing it years ago, of people comparing different Bible colleges
and their style of music. And that style of music from that Bible college is different than the style
of music from this Bible college. Are they saying that one's right and one's wrong? Well, some do
go that far to say that. I think if you go to some places, not only in the U.S., but even if you go to
some places around the world, you're going to find slightly different style of music. But it doesn't
necessarily mean it's wrong music. It still can be God-honoring, Christ-honoring music. In fact,
I think I've been to Israel. I know some of you have. The style of music in Israel is different
than the style of music that we have here in America. It just is. It's just different style
of music. The style of music in Kentucky? I'm not a bluegrass fan. Never was, right? But you
understand, there's just a different style. And I'm not, I would not say that just because the style
isn't what you say is your style, it doesn't mean it's wrong. There are some things that you can
look to, to be able to determine if something's right or wrong, and there are tests that we can
put forth, but we must be mindful of the fact that there's going to be within this spectrum,
if you will, that, okay, that's the style that I really like, but that's maybe a style that I
don't like. And it's important that we understand that there's an aspect of grace with that. And
there are lines in which you can go outside one side or the other, and it cross the line and be,
okay, this is not appropriate music. Yeah, but the words, speaking to yourselves in songs and
hymns and spiritual songs, singing and making melody in your hearts to the Lord. Again, when
you start getting into melody and harmony and all that sort of thing, I get kind of like, I'm
checked out, it's beyond my ability. But there's certainly an aspect that you can't just say, well,
just listen to the words. The words have to be appropriate, but there's other aspects of the
music that have to be appropriate as well. And so we have to understand that, but we also have
to have a measure of grace with that. And then look over at Colossians 3, if you will. We look
at Colossians 3, and notice what the Bible teaches us here as we continue to understand this aspect
of praise God with song and how they were given the responsibility in the opening verses of Psalm
81 to sing, to sing aloud unto God our God.
our strength, to make a joyful noise unto the God of Jacob."
Here in Colossians 3, as we find another local church being given instruction with regard
to church life and behavior and so on and so forth, we find that in verse number 16,
the Bible says,
"...let the word of Christ dwell in you richly in all wisdom."
Notice what the Bible says,
"...by teaching and admonishing one another in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, singing
with grace in your hearts to the Lord.
And whatsoever you do in word or deed, do all in the name of the Lord Jesus, giving
thanks to God and the Father by Him."
It's interesting as we look at verse 16 and 17 here within the context of this understanding
of singing, it says,
"...let the word of Christ dwell in you richly in all wisdom."
And then as it continues, it says,
"...teaching and admonishing one another in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, singing
with grace in your hearts to the Lord."
You know, our songs, according to verse number 16, are to teach and admonish.
The word admonish means to warn.
Now think about songs.
In fact, I asked this question on Sunday evening as we began the preaching time on Sunday evening.
We finished up the last hymn that we sang was Yesterday, Today, and Forever.
And I asked the question, what theology, what's the theological word that we use to describe
what we just sang about?
And Brother Mark said, immutable.
And that's true.
We talk about the fact that God is immutable.
He never changes.
So guess what?
We're singing a song, Yesterday, Today, and Forever.
We're singing a song that's teaching biblical truth.
And what a joy to have a hymnal, to have spiritual songs that are reinforcing the same teaching
that you would get from the Bible.
I'm not sure about you, but I know for me that when we sing songs, oftentimes I'm thinking
about passages of Scripture that are relatable to the particular psalm that we sing.
You're singing a song, a hymn, who is on the Lord's side?
I'm not sure what you think about when we're singing that song, but I'm thinking about
Moses.
Amen?
Why?
Because Moses says, he draws a line in the sand and said, who is on the Lord's side?
It's very interesting when you sing the hymns, when we sing through our hymnal, when you
have the opportunity to be able to say, I wonder what the songwriter was reading in
God's Word when God prompted them, led them to write the particular song that they wrote.
What was going on in their life?
What were the circumstances that they were facing?
What are the Bible truths that God was encouraging them with as they wrote that song?
And it's interesting when you begin to think that way, you're able to relate to various
passages of Scripture, and it's exciting.
I love singing, whosoever will, may come.
Right?
I mean, what a joy.
We sing that song.
I remember there's been a time when I've had the opportunity to be in a place where that
song was being led, and it was a congregational song, and so the congregation's singing it,
and there was somebody that was of a persuasion that it wasn't whosoever will.
And it was just kind of comical to begin seeing how they're singing whosoever will, but they
don't believe it.
But we believe for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved.
Aren't you thankful?
When you start singing about the fact that you're going to see Him face to face, what
does that do for you?
Does it encourage you?
Does it like cause you to think about, man, one day I'm going to say, this isn't just
a song that we just go through some motions and just, no, we're going to, it's a reality.
I'm going to see my Savior face to face.
Today that will be, amen?
You start singing these songs, you start thinking about the way that songs minister to us, and
what are they to do?
They're to teach us.
They're to admonish us, to warn us, and we find that here within the context of Colossians
3, yes, let the word of Christ dwell in you richly in all wisdom, but then he says, teaching
and admonishing one another in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, singing with grace
in your hearts to the Lord.
How many of you have tried to memorize a verse before, and it was so much easier when
you put the verse to some kind of song, right?
You put it to a little song.
When our children were at Heritage Baptist Church, they were, or Heritage Christian School,
they were part of the ODAC's Bible quiz team, and they had to memorize three chapters in
the book of Romans.
Joseph and Brianna, they had to memorize three chapters in the book of Romans, because that
was what they were doing for the Bible quiz, and so each of the kids on the team had certain
chapters that they were to memorize, and they were the ones that were supposed to be the
experts on that chapter, because they memorized it.
And I remember they had to memorize Romans chapter number one.
Now, if you've ever read Romans chapter number one, near the end of the chapter, it gets
all kinds of crazy with all the stuff that's going on, and Holly put some kind of song
to that thing.
She just made it up, just made up a song just with those words, and you know that Joseph
and Brianna, I think they were in fourth grade, third grade, and fifth grade, and they were
able to memorize, and I think if I called Joseph over here right now and said, hey,
can you sing that song with those words from Romans chapter one?
He would be able to do it.
It's amazing how our minds work, and so you get that song.
We were working on a memory verse last year with one of our memory verses for the month,
and as we were going through them last year, I was like, okay, is there a song that goes
with any of these verses, and there was one that I wasn't familiar with, but Kimberly
and Natalie sang it over in the fellowship hall, and they would sing it, and we would
learn it, and guess what?
It helped me to memorize that verse a whole lot easier.
Why?
Because it was with song.
And it's interesting as we think about the way that God has used the ministry of music.
Yes, it's been corrupted by the enemy, but we that have been saved by the grace of God,
God has given to us a new song, and I'm thankful for this gift of music, and I want the music
that I sing, I want the music that I listen to, I want the music in our church to glorify
God and to teach me, to minister to me.
I want to be reminded of biblical truth when I'm singing songs.
I want to be reminded of how great my God is when I'm singing songs.
When you begin to think about how He is able to deliver thee, and you sing that song, and
you're going through some difficulty and trial, and oh, how that song will minister to you.
And it's interesting.
I always find it interesting as we take the opportunity at different times during our
calendar year to take for people to give testimonies and to share favorites.
Just your favorite hymn, and we'll sing a verse of that favorite hymn.
And it's really amazing to me to see how God uses songs in people's lives, to minister
to them.
Sometimes the song that you might say is your favorite this week or this month or this year,
there might be a situation that you face, a different season in life, and God will use
a different song that will become your favorite at that moment.
Why?
Because you deal with different things, and so do I, and God uses those songs.
How often is it that many times in even a congregation the size of ours that you'll
have people that will pick the same song as their favorite?
I can almost guarantee every time that we take favorites that there's going to be a
certain number of songs that will be included.
Great is thy faithfulness.
It's one that's like, it's going, somebody's going to pick it.
It is well with my soul.
Somebody's going to pick it.
Amazing Grace, Brother Don is going to pick it.
Amen?
How many of you know that that's his favorite song?
Listen, he said, pastor, when I have my funeral, I already know we're singing Amazing Grace.
We're going to sing it 47 times.
I got it.
I understand, right?
Why?
It's his favorite song.
Because God uses songs to minister to us, but we're to sing unto God, and it's a form
of worship.
We're to sing aloud.
God's put a song in our heart and our mouth, and we need to sing praise to Him.
Remember, Paul and Silas, they sang unto God, and the prisoners heard them.
What an opportunity for them to be able to sing to their God in a very difficult circumstance
to be ministered to, but also to have an impact on others.
Praise with song.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
We thank You for the opportunity to be able to gather, and Lord, we thank You for the
ministry of music, the gift of music, and God, I pray that You would help us to sing
aloud unto our God, who is our strength, Lord, unto Thee.
Lord, help us to praise You, to make a joyful noise.
Lord, help us to have right music, have music that teaches us, that admonishes us, that
reminds us and reinforces to us Bible truth.
We thank You that we can pray together as a church family.
We thank You that You're a God who...
hears and answers. And I pray for these next moments, Lord, that You'd have Your will
and way. For it's in Christ's name we pray. Amen.
All right, Brother Fernando.