and this is our third message dealing with this portion of Scripture where Jacob is blessing his
sons. And the scene, we've dealt with it for a couple of Sunday evenings, of course, and the
scene is such that Jacob is preparing to die. He knows, in fact, at the end of this chapter the
death of Jacob is recorded for us. And we find that he calls his sons in and one by one they
stand before him and he issues some words, he makes some statements, some few, some that are
lengthier. We find that this evening we'll look at Joseph and we find that there's more said about
Joseph in this text of Scripture than any of the other sons and we'll notice that. But we find that
as his life is coming to an end that he has all of his sons there in his presence and they stand
before him one by one. I've mentioned as we've looked at this portion of Scripture several things
with regard to understanding the purpose of this, understanding the process by which they would go
through, understanding the prophetic aspect of several of the things that Jacob will say and
how that through Jacob's words we can see all the way down through the millennial with regard to
some of these statements that are made. And it's pretty awesome when you consider all of that and
the manner by which these blessings are given. Remember in verse 28 the Bible says,
all these are the twelve tribes of Israel and this is that their father spake unto them. And bless
them everyone according to his blessing he blessed them. Tonight we're gonna look at the final four
sons that are mentioned in the text of Scripture, Asher, Naphtali, Joseph and Benjamin. And so we'll
begin in verse number 20. The Bible says, out of Asher his bread shall be fat and he shall yield
royal dainties. Naphtali is a hind let loose, he giveth goodly words. And I'll read the rest of the
chapter or the rest of the verses as we go through the message this evening. As it has been the case
for the last two messages I've simply titled the message Jacob blesses his sons. This is part three,
the points are just the names of the sons. And so number one this evening is Asher from verse
number 20. Notice the Bible says his bread shall be fat and it says he shall yield, excuse me,
notice it says and he shall yield royal dainties. And so we see that as this word is given the
inheritance as we would look at the book of Joshua and understand the division of the land,
the inheritance for the descendants of Asher was the seacoast area that was north of Mount Carmel.
And we find that that was an extremely fertile area and we find that from that area there was
much that was produced because of that. In fact you find that even in Deuteronomy chapter 33 where
Moses is mentioning the tribes and mentioning various blessings with regard to them, we see
that there's also the fact that olive groves flourished in that particular area. And so as
the word is given here with regard to the yield of what they would be able to produce based on the
area in which they would inherit and inhabit, we find that that is the focus of that which is said
to Asher. We find that with Naphtali, the Bible says number two and we're moving quickly through
these first couple, it says Naphtali is a hind let loose and then notice it says this he giveth
goodly words. That's an interesting statement. We find that as you were to consider these two
traits, you think about a hind that's let loose, not only the speed but also the freedom if you
will when we see that phraseology that is given. And we also understand that here the Bible says
that he giveth goodly words. Some have surmised that from this you would understand that from
their tribe there would be some that would be good messengers because of their ability to deliver
message, the goodly words, but also the speed that would be referenced with a hind let loose. And we
don't really have any specific biblical examples of that with regard to an individual that was of
that tribe that would fit that category. But certainly as we look at these things that are
mentioned here, we do think of some things that were known to us. The Bible tells us in Judges
5 and verse number 18 that this tribe was known for their bravery and they were known for having
that tendency to as they would enter into battle to have that bravery. But I'm reminded this
evening as I look at these words that are mentioned to Naphtali and I think about that phrase he
giveth goodly words, I'm reminded of our speech. As we would seek to understand what's being said
here to Naphtali as he stands before him, we understand this evening that our words are
important. Our speech is important. I want you to look at a couple of verses with me. Look at Psalm
141 and in fact I mean we could look at so many passages tonight dealing with our speech and our
words and we find that the Bible gives us instruction with regard to our speech. But this verse here in
Psalm 141, God really laid upon my heart this week as I was preparing and looking through these
verses of Scripture. And notice what the Bible says to Psalm that's ascribed to David.
And the Bible says in verse number 3, set a watch, O Lord, before my mouth,
keep the door of my lips. Isn't that a good prayer? How many times have you said something and said,
I wish I didn't say that. Has it ever happened to you? I'm sure it has. We've all said something
out of reaction, out of haste and maybe some other emotion and we've regretted whatever it is that we
said. And here we find that the prayer of David is set a watch, O Lord, before my mouth, keep the door
of my lips. We find that Psalm 19 says let the words of my mouth and the meditation of my heart
be acceptable unto thee, O Lord, in thy sight. Right? And we understand the importance of our
words being acceptable to the Lord. Look over the book of James, if you will, and I'm going to read
several verses in James chapter number 3. James deals with really mature Christianity and those
that would be mature in Christ. And we find that here in James chapter number 3, he begins to deal
with the subject matter of the tongue. And he begins to deal and address our speech and as I
look at those words that are said with regard to Naphtali, goodly words that are referenced and how
our speech ought to be that which is acceptable in the sight of the Lord. Notice what James says
in James 3 and verse number 5, even so the tongue is a little member and boasteth great things.
Behold, how great a matter a little fire kindleth. And the tongue is a fire, a world of iniquity.
So is the tongue among our members that it defileth the whole body and setteth on fire the
course of nature and is set on fire of hell. For every kind of beast and of birds and of serpents
and of things in the sea is tamed and hath been tamed of mankind, but the tongue can no man tame.
It is unruly evil, full of deadly poison. That's a powerful statement that is made there.
You know, what we need is the power of the Holy Spirit to help us with regard to our speech.
Notice it continues, therewith bless we God, even the Father, and therewith curse we men,
which are made after the similitude of God. Out of the same mouth proceedeth blessing and cursing.
And then notice what he says, my brethren, these things ought not so to be. Doth a fountain send
forth at the same place sweet water and bitter? Can the fig tree, my brethren, bear olive berries,
either a vine fig? So can no fountain both yield salt water and fresh. And my attention is drawn
to verse number 10 when he says, out of the same mouth proceedeth blessing and cursing. And he says,
my brethren, these things ought not so to be. You know, our speech is extremely important.
Our words. With our words we can edify. In fact, we're commanded to do so in Ephesians 4.
We understand that with our words we can build people up. With our words we can tear people down.
Our words are powerful. We find that here the Bible says, he giveth goodly words. The account
in Genesis doesn't give us much information about Naphtali. We don't read much about several of
these. We've mentioned that over the weeks. And some have taken from this verse of Scripture that
it was Naphtali that delivered the message, that it was the spokesman that told Jacob that Joseph
was yet alive there in Egypt. I can't prove that biblically. But as Naphtali stood before Jacob,
one of the things that he says is, he giveth goodly words. And I wonder this evening if we
were to have someone give a testimony, if we were to stand before the Lord as we will one day,
we think about our speech and I wonder if it would be said that he giveth
goodly words. Our speech is appropriate, God honoring. And how important that is.
We find that not only do we see with regard to what the testimony that was given of him,
but we can make the application that we would be in that same position.
I'm going to skip down to verse 27.
and then we'll circle back and deal with Joseph
in verses 22 through 26.
And look down at verse 27, if you will.
Benjamin is then addressed, of course, the last one.
The greatest portion of scripture that's given is to Joseph
and I'm gonna spend majority of the time this evening
in that passage, but look in verse 27
as it deals with Benjamin, shall raven as a wolf.
In the morning he shall devour the prey
and at night he shall divide the spoil.
A warrior tribe.
We find that this is the only tribe,
it's very interesting, the only tribe
that would stay with Judah after the divided kingdom.
The 10 tribes of the north known as Israel,
the two to the south known as Judah,
but it's Judah and Benjamin that would be
the tribes of the south there.
And we find that from the tribe of Benjamin,
the first king, even though he wasn't from Judah,
it was the one that was chosen to be king of Israel
was Saul and he was of the tribe of Benjamin.
But we also find that the apostle Paul, of course,
Saul, before his conversion, he was from the tribe
of Benjamin as well.
We could look and mention some things
with regard to these individuals,
but we find there's not, again, a ton that's given to us
about this warrior tribe.
There's not much that we see with regard to Benjamin
within the Genesis record.
Of course, he is blessed by Joseph at the return
and is understanding his position there in Egypt
and what have you, but we find that the warrior aspect
is definitely in sight with regard to these words
that are spoken of Benjamin.
This evening, I wanna focus our attention on Joseph.
It begins in verse 22 and goes down through verse number 26.
More is said of Joseph to and about him than any other son.
I'm gonna read the entirety of these verses, 22 through 26,
and then we're gonna go back and dig through them.
Notice the Bible says, Joseph is a fruitful bow,
even a fruitful bow by a well,
whose branches run over the wall.
The archers have sorely grieved him
and shot at him and hated him,
but his bow abode in strength and the arms of his hands
were made strong by the hands of the mighty God of Jacob.
From thence is the shepherd, the stone of Israel,
even by the God of thy father who shall help thee
and by the Almighty who shall bless thee
with blessing of heaven above,
blessings of heaven above, blessings of the deep
that lieth under, blessings of the breast and of the womb.
The blessings of thy father have prevailed
above the blessings of my progenitors
unto the utmost bound of the everlasting hills.
They shall be on the head of Joseph
and on the crown of the head of him
that was separate from his brethren.
There's so much in these few verses of scripture.
It's amazing what is given to us in just a few verses.
I want you to notice several things
that we see about Joseph
and as we would seek to understand from his life
and then make application even in our own lives.
Notice in verse number 22 that Joseph was fruitful.
The Bible says that he is a fruitful bow,
even a fruitful bow, notice, by a well,
whose branches run over the wall.
Do you see the imagery that's provided of this fruitfulness
of what Jacob is speaking of when he speaks of Joseph?
And I think about the importance of being fruitful
and understanding that God has given us the truth
in our lives that we are to be fruitful people.
Look at Psalm one, if you will, a familiar Psalm,
a familiar passage of scripture,
but I wanna remind you what the Bible says here in Psalm one
as we consider this word that is given to Joseph from Jacob.
In Psalm one, in verse number one,
the Bible says, blessed is the man
that walketh not in the counsel of the ungodly,
nor standeth in the way of sinners,
nor sitteth in the seat of the scornful.
And the reality is that we need to be extremely careful
of the influences that we allow in our lives.
So many people, let him that thinketh he stand,
take heed lest he fall.
That's what the Bible says.
I can handle it.
No, you can't.
Amen?
You can't.
Your flesh is weak.
He says this, but his delight is in the law of the Lord.
And in his law, doth he meditate day and night.
And then notice what it says.
And he shall be like a tree.
That's what?
Planted by the rivers of water.
You remember over there in Genesis 49,
it said by the well.
That's the imagery that was used by Jacob.
And here we says that he's like a tree
that's planted by the rivers of water
that bringeth forth his fruit in his season.
His leaf also shall not wither
and whatsoever he doeth shall prosper.
And that's a wonderful promise that God gives us.
His delight is in the law of the Lord.
In his law, doth he meditate day and night.
And we find that the product,
what is produced by that is fruitfulness,
that he shall bring forth his fruit in his season.
We find that God is the one that allows us to be fruitful
and to bless and to prosper, make our way prosperous.
We find that in Joshua chapter number one
in verse number eight,
there's similar verbiage that is given
with regard to delighting in the law of the Lord.
Why is it that we're getting, digging into
and meditating on God's word so that we could do it?
Not so that we just know it,
so that we can answer some questions,
but so that we can apply it in our lives.
Notice over in John 15, if you will,
as we consider this truth of Joseph,
that Joseph was, he was fruitful.
In John chapter number 15,
we're reminded that Jesus is the true vine.
We understand that it's imperative that we abide in him.
We find in John 15, the Bible says,
I am the true vine and my father is the husbandman.
Every branch in me that beareth not fruit.
These are tough words, he taketh away.
And every branch that beareth fruit,
he purgeth it, why?
That it might bring forth more fruit.
I'm not an expert at these things.
I've never had a grove of trees
or any of that type of thing,
but I can read some things and I can understand some things
and the idea of purging and the purpose of that
to bring forth fruit, why?
Because the desire of having these trees
is to produce fruit, that's the whole point.
And so he's using this imagery here,
this analogy, if you will, and he says,
now you're clean through the word,
which I have spoken unto you, abide in me and I in you.
As the branch cannot bear fruit of itself,
except it abide in the vine,
no more can ye except ye abide in me.
I am the vine, you're the branches.
He that abideth in me and I in him,
the same bringeth forth much fruit,
for without me he can do nothing.
If a man abide not in me,
he is cast forth as a branch and is withered.
Men gather them and cast them into the fire
and they are burned.
If you abide in me and my words abide in you,
you shall ask what you will and it shall be done unto you.
Herein, notice this verse in John 15 and verse eight,
herein is my Father glorified that ye bear much fruit.
So shall ye be my disciples.
God wants us to be fruitful,
even as we see in the life of Joseph here,
the Bible says that as Joseph stands before Jacob,
and of course, the words that are spoken
as we've gone through this passage of scripture,
we understand that Jacob is speaking
and often there's a prophetic aspect,
and he says, Joseph is a fruitful bough.
He notices, he recognizes the fact that he was fruitful,
but I want you to notice in verse 23,
the next thing that we know with regard to Joseph
back in Genesis 49, is not only was he fruitful,
but Joseph faced opposition.
He faced opposition.
We know about it, we've studied it,
we've been familiar with the account of the life of Joseph.
It was at the very hands of his own brethren
that he faced this opposition,
and we find the Bible says the archers,
notice in verse 23, the archers have sorely grieved him
and shot at him and hated him.
We know that his brothers, they hated him so much
they could not speak kindly unto him.
We know that they were gonna kill him,
they put him in the pit,
they eventually sold him into slavery and all of that,
and we've studied that, we've understood that,
but we find that though Joseph was fruitful,
we also recognize that he faced opposition.
You know, the reality is that facing opposition
doesn't mean that we can't be fruitful.
We have an adversary, we have an enemy, we face opposition.
It's every time I try to do something for God,
it seems like there's, yeah, absolutely, there's opposition.
And you face that opposition because we have an enemy.
We see it in 1 Peter 5, verse number eight,
where the Bible talks about be sober, be vigilant
because your adversary, the devil is a roaring lion,
walketh about seeking whom he may devour.
We have an enemy.
You read about the accounts in Post-Exodus.
as they went back to Jerusalem to rebuild not only the temple but to rebuild the wall.
Man, they faced opposition at every turn.
We find here that Joseph, he faced opposition.
He was fruitful. He faced opposition.
I want you to notice in verse 24.
The Bible says,
His bow abode in strength, and the arms of his hands, notice this,
were made strong by the hands of the mighty God of Jacob.
You know what we learn as we look at verse 24?
That God was the source of his strength.
You understand, we cannot face opposition in our own strength.
We're not going to prevail in our own strength.
We find that as Joseph would face the opposition that he faced,
as he would deal with all the adversity that he dealt with,
that it was God who strengthened him.
As he was forgotten in prison for those two years,
two long years, it was God that was strengthening him
and it was Joseph that was living in the presence of God.
And we find this evening that it's imperative that we understand this evening
that the source of my strength and the source of your strength must be the Lord.
We sing the song about the arm of flesh will fail you.
And we found that to be the case.
The flesh is weak.
Be strong in the Lord and in the power of His might.
Ephesians 6 and verse number 10.
We wrestle not against flesh and blood.
Verse 12.
This battle that we're engaged in is a spiritual battle
and we need spiritual strength.
We need God to be our strength.
I'm thankful that He is my strength.
What a joy it is to rely upon Him.
And we find that here in verse 24,
God gives us this nugget of truth with regard to the life of Joseph
that his hands were made strong by the hands of the mighty God of Jacob.
I'm not sure if you've ever faced a situation in life
and from a temporal, physical perspective you say,
I just can't go on.
And you might not be able to in your own strength.
I'm thankful that God has promised,
but they that wait upon the Lord shall renew their strength.
Isaiah 40 and verse number 31.
What a great truth that God gives us strength.
It's not always talking about physical strength.
More times than not in the Scriptures when we talk about strength,
we're seeing the truth with regard to spiritual strength.
That we're being strengthened in our inner man.
Yeah, there's ways that you can go and strengthen the physical body.
There's various exercises that you can do
and you can work out these muscles
and you can develop and you can strengthen your physical body,
but as believers understand that we face opposition,
we better be busy strengthening the inner man.
Getting into the Word of God.
Allowing the Word of God to get into us.
Building up ourselves in the faith
and understanding the importance of being strong spiritually.
Notice it's interesting in verse 24.
I want you to see what God says.
It says,
But his bow abode in strength,
and the arms of his hands were made strong
by the hands of the mighty God of Jacob.
And then there's a parenthetical statement there.
It says,
From fence is the shepherd the stone of Israel.
Those are beautiful words at the end of verse number 24.
And we find that the mighty God of Jacob,
He is the shepherd.
We read Psalm 23, a Psalm that we're familiar with.
When David says, The Lord is my shepherd.
We read in John chapter number 10,
when Jesus stands and says, I am the good shepherd.
We find that it's the good shepherd that he giveth his life for the sheep.
And we understand the ministry that God reveals to us
in his working toward us as our shepherd.
The shepherd provides and protects.
The shepherd's presence brings a great peace and a great joy.
When there's an enemy,
when there's some danger that's nearby,
the presence of the shepherd brings a calmness and a peace.
I'm thankful that our shepherd, he said,
My peace give I unto thee.
Not as the world giveth, give I unto thee.
No, he gives us his peace.
And it's a peace that passeth all understanding.
So we note here that it says that the mighty God of Jacob
from thence is the shepherd.
But then notice it says the stone of Israel.
Often we recognize in the Old Testament
the reference to the Lord as being the rock.
And we see that reference over and over.
In fact, Moses makes statement of our rock is not like their rock.
And it's a big capital R versus a lowercase r.
And we understand the truth that we find.
But I want you to look over at 1 Peter 2, if you will.
And I want you to see this truth that God gives us
with regard to this reference of the mighty God of Jacob
not only as shepherd, but as stone.
Notice what the Bible says in 1 Peter 2.
In 1 Peter 2.
In 1 Peter 2, beginning in verse number 1, it says,
Wherefore, laying aside all malice and all guile
and hypocrisies and envies and all evil speakings,
as newborn babes desire the sincere milk of the word
that ye may grow thereby.
Then notice verse 3, if so be ye have tasted
that the Lord is gracious.
Oh, we sang about the grace of God this evening.
And I'm so thankful for God's grace and that God is gracious.
But notice what it says,
To whom coming as unto a living stone,
disallowed indeed of men, but chosen of God and precious.
Ye also as lively stones are built up a spiritual house
and holy priesthood to offer up spiritual sacrifices
acceptable to God by Jesus Christ.
Wherefore, also it is contained in the scripture,
Behold, I lay in Zion a chief cornerstone, elect, precious.
And he that believeth on him shall not be confounded.
Unto you, therefore, which believe, notice these words,
he is precious.
But unto them which be disobedient the stone
which the builders disallowed,
the same is made the head of the corner
and a stone of stumbling, even a rock of offense,
even to them which stumble at the word being disobedient,
whereunto also they were appointed.
And so we find that Christ is the living stone.
We find that Christ is the cornerstone.
We find that he is rejected.
In fact, we read that specifically in verse number seven.
Unto you, therefore, which believe, he is precious.
But unto them which be disobedient the stone
which the builders disallowed.
Again, being rejected, if you will.
And then in verse number eight, the fact that a stone of stumbling.
The Jews, there's a stumbling block.
And we find this evening that as we look at this verse of scripture
in Genesis chapter number 49,
that as God is allowing Jacob to speak to Joseph
and he's speaking to Joseph about his fruitfulness
and yes, the opposition,
but the source of his strength being the mighty God of Jacob.
And then he references from thence as the shepherd,
the stone of Israel.
Man, far-reaching prophecy.
Mention about our Savior.
What a blessing.
Notice as we continue through this portion of scripture
with regard to Joseph back in Genesis 49,
look at verse 25 with me.
In verse number 25, the Bible says,
Even by the God of thy father,
then notice these words,
who shall help thee?
You know, I'm thankful this evening that God is our helper.
I'm thankful this evening the Bible tells us
that he's a very present help in the time of trouble.
In fact, turn over, if you will, to Psalm 46.
I want you to look at that portion of scripture with me.
As we look at Psalm 46 this evening
and consider this precious truth,
we see the explanation that is given,
really the impact or the implication
of understanding this truth that is given
in verse number one and how it should impact
every believer.
Understanding that our God is our refuge,
that he is our help.
How does that impact us?
How does that cause us to deal with life
and the matters of life?
He said in verse number 25,
God shall help thee.
I'm thankful this evening that we can still claim
that wonderful promise that God the Lord,
he is my helper.
It says in Psalm 46 verse one,
God is our refuge and strength.
We noticed in verse number 24 of Genesis 49
that God was the source of his strength,
but then notice the end of the verse,
a very present help in trouble.
I like the way that God reveals this to us
because it's in the time of trouble that we...
need the help. And the Bible says that he's a very present help in a time of
trouble. And then I want you to notice the next verses, because as we look at
the next verses in Psalm 46, it really illustrates to us how the truth of who
God is to us as his people, that he's our refuge, our strength, and a very present
help. He is our helper. Notice the Bible says, therefore, based on my understanding
of who God is to me, therefore, will not we fear? Though the earth be removed, and
though the mountains be carried into the midst of the sea, though the waters
thereof roar and be troubled, though the mountains shake with the swelling thereof,
Now, verse number two and three describe some pretty catastrophic events. Do they
not? But the Bible says, therefore, will not we fear? Though all these things
happen. Why? Because the Lord is my helper. He's my refuge. He's my strength. He's a
very present help in trouble. What a joy to understand this evening that our God
is with us and our God is our helper. We read this truth in the New Testament, in
Hebrews chapter number 13. We often reference verse number five when he says,
I will never leave thee nor forsake thee. But we find the truth of verse number
six that is so important for us to be reminded of. The Bible says in Hebrews
13 and verse number five, let your conversation be without covetousness and
be content with such things as you have. For he hath said, I will never leave thee
nor forsake thee, so that we may boldly say, the Lord is my helper. And I will not
fear what man shall do unto me. What a joy to understand the position that we
have as believers that God is our helper. And we find that there in this portion
of Scripture, the Bible tells us that Jacob says, God shall help thee. I'm so
thankful this evening. I'm so thankful in my life, and I know many of you could
stand and give testimony this evening as well, how God has helped us. How God has
helped us. Why does the psalmist say in Psalm 121, I will lift up mine eyes into
the hills, from whence cometh my help. My help cometh from the Lord. And what is he
saying? Which maketh heaven and earth. He's the creator God. The creator God, the creator
of the universe, he's my helper, he's your helper. Isn't that wonderful? It's precious.
We find that it says, even by the God of thy father, who shall help thee. It continues
in verse 25, and by the Almighty. And then there's these words, who shall bless thee
with blessings. And then we see a variety of things that are mentioned. We note the
use of the word bless, or a form of that word in verse 25 and 26, and the blessings that
are given. And I consider this evening, the Bible says, who shall help thee in verse 25,
but also who shall bless thee. With blessings of heaven above, blessings of the deep that
lieth under, blessings of the breast and of the womb, the blessings of thy father have
prevailed above the blessings of my progenitors unto the utmost bound of the everlasting hills.
They shall be on the head of Joseph, and on the crown of the head of him that was separate
from his brethren. You know, I'm thankful this evening to be blessed. Can I tell you
this evening, God has blessed us with all spiritual blessings in heavenly places. We
read that in the New Testament. We find this evening, the blessings of God. He daily loadeth
us with benefits, is what the psalmist says. And we find this evening, that blessings come
in a variety of shapes, forms. You know, sometimes it's a great blessing when God says no. It's
a blessing when you say, but I was praying for that. God knows better what you need than
you do. Amen? And there's sometimes that God closes a door. You know that's a blessing
when God does that. It's a blessing when you say, but I look at it as a blessing when God
opens a door. Sure, it's a blessing when God opens a door. It's a blessing when God closes
a door. Blessings come in a variety of ways. Sometimes in our culture today, we have been
led to think a certain way with regard to what a blessing is or what a blessing should
look like. Can I tell you, sometimes things that might look on the surface to be negative
can be a great blessing from our God. Great blessing. This evening, we find that our God
is a God who blesses. We find this evening that the truth, and we could look at the book
of Deuteronomy, we could look at other portions of scripture, that there's a biblical principle
that we find throughout the scriptures that obedience leads to blessing. That disobedience
leads to cursing. We read that. In fact, Moses, as I said before you today, a blessing and
a curse. I mean, he makes it very plain, very straightforward. The blessing comes with obedience
and the curse comes with disobedience. We find that we're, as we look in the book of
Deuteronomy and you look at and compare various passages in the book of Deuteronomy, he tells
them just as we find in other portions, choose, make a choice. We find that Joshua says that,
choose you this day whom you will serve. I'm thankful this evening that our God is a God
that blesses. You know, I'm thankful to go to heaven. One day we're going to go there.
Do you know how many blessings he gives us along this journey of life? So many blessings.
There's so many songs that have been written about the blessings that God has given to
us and we are truly blessed. We find that Joseph, as we consider his life and consider
these statements, we find that not only would God bless as we see here and we understand
this, but we find that even in his life, you could look back and good times and difficult
times, God was at work. God was blessing. God was working. God was moving. This evening,
I hope that as we look here at the life of Joseph, and I know we dealt quickly with the
other three brothers, but we see that there's so much given to us here. I hope that we would
understand that he was fruitful and that we too are supposed to be fruitful, fruit
producing Christians. We must abide in Christ. We must understand that it brings glory to
God when we're fruitful, when we bear fruit. We're to bear much fruit. We find that just
as it's said of Joseph that he had opposition, that we too will face opposition. Don't think
that you're going to go through Christian life and never have any adversity. Jesus told
the disciples, they hated me, they're going to hate you. They're going to put you out.
They're going to kill you. They're going to think that they're doing some great thing.
The reality this evening is that we're going to face opposition, but we are on the winning
side. Isn't that wonderful? Have you read the book of Revelation recently? We're more
than conquerors. We win. Amen? Our future is bright. You say, pastor, do you see all
the headlines? Yeah, I see them. But Jesus is coming back. I belong to him. He is mine.
Hallelujah. We find that we will face opposition, but in that we must take refuge in knowing
that he, the mighty God of Jacob, is our strength. He's our strength. You don't have to do it
in your own power. In fact, you can't do it in your own power. One of the most frustrating
things in the Christian life is trying to live it in your own power. But God is our
strength. It was God that strengthened the hands of Joseph and he too will strengthen
us as we do the work that he's called us to do. God shall help thee. He's our helper.
You say, oh, I need help. Go to the Lord. He'll help you. He'll bless you. I'm so thankful
this evening that as we've looked for these last few weeks at these instructions, these
words that have been given from Jacob that we can understand contextually, but then we
can make application. Oh, from the tribe of Ephraim, the son of Joseph, came Joshua. We
know much about Joshua, do we not? A man that God used in a great way, a man that was faithful,
a man that led the children of Israel, that did what God had commanded him to do. From
the tribe of Manasseh, the other son of Joseph, we read of Gideon being from that tribe. You
think of Gideon. He's addressed first as being the mighty, mighty, mighty.
man of valor." How God used Gideon. What a blessing it is to know the Lord and understand
the work that He has for us. I hope that as we look this evening, even at Naphtali, that
we understand the importance of our words. You're going to speak a lot of words this
week. Are they going to be goodly words? Are they going to be words that build up, that
gratify, that bless the Lord, that are acceptable in the sight of the Lord? Because that's what
Jacob says. He says, he giveth goodly words. We ought to be known for giving goodly words.
Words that are appropriate and God-honoring. This evening we finish up this portion of
Scripture. We'll deal with, next week, the death of Jacob and enter into chapter 50 and
note the burial and what have you. We're nearing the end of our study of the book of
Genesis. I've greatly enjoyed it. It's been a real blessing and I hope that as we've looked
at these 12 sons and we understand the process and we understand all the purpose and some
of the prophetic aspect. I'm reminded of what I said the first night during the first message
from Genesis 49. It reminds me as I read Genesis 49 that one day each of us will stand before
our Heavenly Father, the beam of seat of Christ, the judgment seat of Christ and we're
going to stand before Him. Can I tell you this evening that that is a truth of God's
Word that not one of us will escape. No one is going to be able to stand with you, your
spouse, your parent, your child, your pastor. You're going to stand before Christ. I hope
that that's a sobering thought for you and I hope that with the understanding of that
truth tonight that we would live every day understanding that one day we're going to
stand before Him. And we take heed to the principles that God has given us that let
a man examine himself. What's the purpose of self-examination? Well, only because one
day we'll stand before someone else and give an account. This evening we see all the sons.
We saw some real positive things. We saw some negative things. We understand this evening
that we serve a great God, a gracious God, a loving God, a forgiving God and what a joy
it is to know Him and to serve Him. And I hope that God would use us, help us to be
fruitful in the face of opposition and difficulty. Listen, the opposition is growing every day.
It really is growing every day. But we are on the winning side. I hope that you take
great refuge in that tonight. Let's pray together. Father, we love You. We thank You for loving
us. We thank You for this passage of Scripture. Lord, You gave us these verses for a purpose
and God, we learn truth that we can apply in our lives. God, I pray that You would help
us to take these truths and Lord, that we would be doers of the Word. Lord, help us
to pray even as David did there in Psalms. Lord, to set that watch and to keep the door,
the gate of our mouth, our lips. Lord, help us to speak goodly words. As we think about
Joseph, help us, Lord, to be fruitful. Help us to abide in You. Lord, help us to depend
upon You, to be strengthened by You. We thank You for Your many blessings. God, You've been
so good to us. I pray that we'd live lives that are blessable. Lord, live lives that
are aligned with the truth of Your Word, living lives of obedience. God, I pray that
in this moment of invitation this evening that, Lord, You've worked in hearts and lives.
Whatever the verse may be or the verses, Lord, You've been able to speak to us as individuals
tonight. I pray that You'd have Your will in way. Help us, Lord, to be doers of the
Word and we'll thank You for it. In Christ's name we pray. Would You stand with me? Heads
are bowed, eyes are closed. Maybe the Lord used something this evening. Maybe even this
morning you didn't have an opportunity to respond. But God spoke to you through some
way today. Maybe just even through a song and you want to thank Him for His grace. Thank
Him that He's holy. As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.