this evening, the book of Acts.
The book of Acts.
And we'll begin in the 13th chapter this evening.
And I'll read just a couple of verses of scripture, we'll look at a number of other portions of
scripture as well.
But you'll be familiar with this text.
This is the record of the first missionary journey.
And I want to read just a couple of verses of scripture and then I'll give you the title
for tonight and look at some things here.
Acts chapter 13, beginning in verse number 1.
The Bible says this, now there were in the church that was at Antioch certain prophets
and teachers, as Barnabas and Simeon, that was called Niger, and Lucius of Cyrene and
Menaean, which had been brought up with Herod the Tetrarch and Saul.
Notice this in verse 2, it says, as they ministered to the Lord.
And it's good to be involved in ministry, it's good to be serving the Lord.
It's good to be using your spiritual gift for God's glory.
And every single one of us have a spiritual gift, and as we use our spiritual gifts for
God's honor and His glory, He blesses and uses us.
It says, as they ministered to the Lord.
And then notice this, it says, and fasted.
And we understand the importance of fasting, oftentimes it's something that's really missing
in our churches today.
In fact, I shared with someone not long ago that dietary intermittent fasting became popular.
I don't know how popular it is still now, but for a period of time there were more people
talking about intermittent fasting than they ever talked about spiritual fasting and the
aspect of biblical truth with regard to fasting.
But we see the Bible says, and they fasted.
And then notice the Holy Ghost said, I'm thankful for God's leadership, the Holy Spirit of God,
He gives leadership and direction.
Notice what the Lord says, the Holy Ghost says, separate me, Barnabas and Saul, for
the work whereunto I have called them.
And when they had fasted and prayed and laid their hands on them, they sent them away.
From verse number three, I want to just take that phrase and use it as our title this evening,
when they had fasted and prayed.
At this time, and I know his name is Saul, it will be changed here very shortly, but
I'll refer to him as Paul.
Paul was the one being sent out from the church in Antioch.
It was the first missionary journey.
And I believe that this church in Antioch, as we begin to understand some things about
the church, we see that they had an understanding of the privilege and power of prayer.
They're a praying church.
In fact, as we look at the text of Scripture, I believe that this church had placed an obvious
emphasis upon prayer.
And you know, it's an important thing when we understand the privilege of prayer, but
we also take and make a priority to pray.
And prayer is so vital.
And we find that as we look through Acts 13 and 14 that provide us with the account of
what happened on this first missionary journey, I believe that we could say this, God did
some amazing things.
God worked in miraculous ways.
God blessed and God used these men as they were separated for the work that God called
them to.
I believe that as you look at the text and you begin to see what's happened, there's
no doubt in my mind that God worked because His people prayed.
Because His people prayed.
God has ordained it that prayer moves the hand of God.
And that's just a biblical truth, a biblical reality.
As we study through the New Testament, we find that the Apostle Paul is enlisting fellow
believers, it seems at every turn, to pray for him.
We find that he obviously, the Apostle Paul, we can read of the prayers that he prayed
for those in Ephesus, those in Colossae, and others that he encourages them by telling
them that he's praying for them.
And he was a man of prayer.
He understood the importance of prayer, but he also understood the power of prayer in
having others pray for him.
And he asks many times for others to pray for him.
You may know the phrase, maybe it's something that you've heard at some point before, the
phrase, hold the ropes.
And that phrase became popular when William Carey, the missionary to India, made this
full statement.
He said, I will go down into the pit if you will hold the ropes.
And what he was communicating through that statement was that really an oft-repeated
part of that, hold the ropes, what he's communicating is that for him, he was going to go.
And for others, they were going to stay.
But those that were staying had a vital part in the ministry of what he would accomplish
or what God would do through him as they would engage in intercessory prayer, that they would
understand that it was not just that William Carey is going to India and he and his family
are going there and think that they have no part of the ministry, no, I will go as
you hold the ropes, as you pray on this end.
What a blessing to know that people are praying for you.
This evening, just as Paul enlisted prayer warriors, I want to not only personally but
as a representative of the group that's going to Idaho on Monday, I want to request your
prayers for us.
And I'm looking forward to the trip, I'm looking forward to what God will do, but I'm absolutely
convinced in my heart this evening that God will only work as the people of God are praying.
And as God moves in your heart and as you pray for those that are going, then God will
do a great work.
And here's the thing, for many of you, you will not get on a plane Monday morning and
go to Idaho with us, but you will have a vital part in that trip as you have an opportunity
to stay here and to pray for us.
And as we look at this truth throughout the New Testament, again, I started here in Acts
13, because here in Acts 13, the apostle Paul understood that the church in Antioch, it
says that when they had fasted and prayed and laid their hands on them, they sent them
away.
And so Paul understood that they were praying for him, and he sees what God does.
He experiences firsthand throughout chapters 13 and 14, he experiences what God is able
to accomplish and how God is able to work, and so therefore throughout the number of
writings that we read of Paul, often he's asking, would you pray?
Would you pray?
And so this evening I want to start and I want to look at a number of these.
Look in Romans chapter 15, if you will, in Romans chapter 15, and I want to note as we
look at each of these portions of Scripture, I want to note the request, but also some
details about the request, because each one is not identical.
We find in Romans 15 that the apostle Paul had a desire, obviously, to preach the gospel.
We start in the first chapter of the book of Romans where he says he's not ashamed of
the gospel of Christ, and he wants to go forth and to preach the gospel.
We find in verse number 30, notice what Paul says, now I beseech you.
We understand that to be strong language.
We use, we see that word used throughout the New Testament.
The word beseech really carries with it the idea of begging.
I beseech you.
What is it that Paul, at this point as he's nearing the end of the epistle, what is he
begging, beseeching the brethren to do?
He says, I beseech you, brethren, for the Lord Jesus Christ's sake and for the love
of the Spirit.
Notice this, that you strive together with me in your prayers to God for me.
So Paul is beseeching these brethren, and he's saying to them that you strive together
with me in your prayers to God for me.
We see this striving together idea that is given to us here in verse number 30, and how
that these would have an opportunity to pray for the apostle Paul as he would go forth
to preach the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
But he continues in verse number 31, notice that I may be delivered from them that do
not believe in Judea.
You understand that when we go forth, when you go to carry the gospel, when we go out
on Saturday mornings to knock on people's doors to tell them about Jesus, not everyone
is excited to see us.
Amen?
There are some that as we will go to Idaho that will not be excited that we're there
trying to preach the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ to them, and Paul encountered that
regularly throughout his ministry.
Some believed, and some did not.
And Paul had that experience, and Paul understood what it was to deal, we read even in that
first missionary journey of the persecution that he faced, and the opposition that he
dealt with.
And so he says, as he asked them to pray that I may be delivered from them that do not believe
in Judea, and that my service, which I have for Jerusalem, may be accepted of the saints.
And we believe that that has to do with really what we're dealing with on Sunday mornings,
with that offering that he was taking back, and he's praying that he would be able to
get that and accomplish really the idea when he says that my service which I have for Jerusalem
may be accepted of the saints.
not only that it would be a blessing to them,
but the idea of fulfilling a ministry obligation
and understanding that he had been entrusted with this.
And we started looking at it
in 2 Corinthians 8 a few weeks ago.
We'll continue this Sunday morning.
And we see that this is what Paul is referencing here,
that I may come, verse 32,
unto you with joy by the will of God,
and may with you be refreshed.
Now the God of peace be with you all, amen.
And so we find that as Paul is writing,
and of course, nearing the end of the epistle,
he's saying, I beseech you, pray for me, strive together.
I love the phraseology,
with me in your prayers to God for me.
And so we think about this,
strive together with me in your prayers to God for me.
The reality is that the group that's going to Idaho,
we also need to be engaged in prayer.
And then we're putting our feet to the ground
and we're going out
and actually doing the work of the ministry.
And he says that you strive together with me
in your prayers to God for me.
Not only are the ones,
not only is Paul praying for the ministry
that he's to be engaged in,
but he's enlisting others to pray for him and with him
as he's doing this ministry.
We find that as he writes to the church in Ephesus,
turn to the book of Ephesians in chapter number six.
And we know that on two occasions in the book of Ephesians,
we don't have time to reference it this evening,
but two prayers that Paul prayed
for the believers in Ephesus
are recorded in the book of Ephesians.
And you can read how Paul was praying for these believers
and it's so much deeper than just saying, I prayed for you.
He gives them the specifics of how he was praying for them.
And then as we come to Ephesians chapter number six,
and he deals with put on the whole armor of God
and he goes through the entirety of the armor of God
and he gets to verse number 18 and he says,
praying always with all prayer and supplication
in the spirit and watching there unto
with all perseverance and supplication for all saints.
And so we see from verse number 18,
the importance of praying one for another.
He says for all saints and being engaged
in intercessory prayer and how vital that is.
But you notice in verse 19 that he says,
and for me.
So now the apostle Paul,
as he's teaching these believers in Ephesus,
as he's already communicated to them,
how he was praying for them and he's teaching them
the importance of being engaged in prayer
and praying always in verse number 18 for all saints.
He says, and for me, let me give you
a personal prayer request.
Notice what it is.
That utterance may be given unto me.
That I may open my mouth boldly
to make known the mystery of the gospel
for which I am an ambassador in bonds
that therein I may speak boldly as I ought to speak.
Isn't that a great prayer request?
I mean, Paul, now think about the apostle Paul.
If there's someone in the New Testament
that you think of as having boldness to preach the gospel
and you were being given a question
in a Bible quiz type of a setting
and someone were to say,
who preached the gospel with boldness in the New Testament?
You may answer by saying Paul.
And I would say this, you'd be correct.
Paul preached with boldness.
You know why I think he preached with boldness?
Because people were praying
that he would preach with boldness.
And God answers prayer.
You know what happened in Acts chapter number four
when they heard all the threatenings
of the religious leaders?
And they went and they prayed and they said,
God, they didn't say, God, deal with the opposition.
They said, God, grant thy servants
that we may speak with boldness.
And you read just a few verses later
and the Bible says they preached with boldness.
God answers prayer.
And so Paul says, and for me,
that utterance may be given unto me
that I may open my mouth boldly
to make known the mystery of the gospel.
Listen, there are people when we go to Idaho
that have not heard the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And we need to have boldness.
And we ask that you would pray
that God would give us boldness,
but you shall receive power
after that the Holy Ghost has come upon you.
And you should be witnesses unto me
both in Jerusalem, Judea, Samaria,
the uttermost part of the earth.
We see that in Acts one and verse number eight.
And here we find that Paul says
that he wants to make known the mystery of the gospel.
What a great desire.
What a great reason to enlist fellow believers
in engaging in intercessory prayer.
Pray that I could speak the gospel with boldness
that I could make known the mystery of the gospel.
Notice in verse 20, he says,
for which I am an ambassador in bonds.
It's kind of interesting
that he would say all of this at the same time,
because he does not request
that they would pray for his deliverance from bonds.
He does not request that they would pray
for his deliverance from being in bondage.
No, that I would preach with boldness.
And Paul understood that God had a purpose.
And he says that therein I may speak boldly.
And then notice that phrase, as I ought to speak.
I would say to you and obviously to myself this evening
that each one of us, we ought to speak the gospel.
We ought to be able to give the gospel
of the Lord Jesus Christ
to those that we come in contact with.
And we ought to be walking in the spirit
that we have the boldness that God will give us
so that we could speak with clarity
and that we could make known the mystery of the gospel.
I think about those that were there in Athens
and they didn't know.
And Paul says that I'm gonna make him known,
him declare I unto you.
Who is it that he's referring to?
He says there's an altar to the unknown God.
And so I'm gonna make him known to you.
I'm gonna declare him to you.
Isn't that wonderful to know Jesus?
I mean, honestly, it's wonderful to know him.
And I mean, to know him personally and intimately
and to understand what he did for us
and what he wants to do for all people.
He's not willing that any should perish,
but it all should come to repentance.
It's absolutely wonderful.
And Paul wants to speak this.
Notice over in the book of Colossians, if you will.
And I know we're systematically going through
and looking at each of these references,
but you find that those believers in Rome
had been issued a letter from the apostle Paul.
All scripture is given by inspiration of God.
We understand that.
But Paul enlists those believers there to pray for him.
Paul then having a close relationship
with the church in Ephesus,
knowing after being able to minister there and serve there,
and he requests that those brethren,
that they would pray for him.
Now, as he's writing to the church in Colossae,
to these believers in Colossae,
the saints and faithful brethren as they're referred to
in verse number two of chapter one,
we understand by studying through this book
the apostle Paul, as you study the book of Colossians
and the rest of the New Testament,
Paul didn't know these people personally.
He had never personally met them.
He'd only heard.
As fact, as you look at chapter number one,
he says, since we heard of your faith in Christ Jesus,
who was it that told Paul about these believers in Colossae?
Well, it was Epaphras, who was their minister,
a faithful minister.
He's referred to that way a couple of different times.
And we find that Paul, he writes to them
and he tells them how he's praying for them.
He doesn't even know them personally,
but he's praying for them.
And then as he gets to the end of the book,
in chapter number four,
he's now going to enlist these believers in Colossae
that they too would pray for him.
Notice again, in verse number two of chapter four,
notice how it is that Paul asks these believers
to pray for him.
He says, continue in prayer,
and watch in the same with thanksgiving.
Now, we ought to understand
that there should be an emphasis on prayer.
And he places that emphasis in verse number two,
but then notice in verse three,
again, as it turns from prayer generally
and the importance of prayer
to a personal prayer request with all,
praying also for us.
For what?
That God would open unto us a door of utterance.
Do you believe this evening that God can open doors?
I believe that.
I believe that God can work.
And I believe that God does work.
And I believe that he can open doors.
I believe he can shut doors.
Amen?
And the reality is that Paul said
that there were many doors, many opportunities,
and there are also many adversaries
as he's talking to the church in Corinth.
And the truth of what he says there is known by us as well,
but he says that he wants these believers in Colossae
to pray for them, pray for us,
that God would open unto us a door of utterance.
You know, I wonder this evening,
how often do we pray this type of prayer?
That God would open doors.
We sometimes use the phraseology of a divine appointment.
And oftentimes when we use that phraseology,
we're recognizing the fact
that there were some circumstances.
beyond our control that God orchestrated
and God gave us this divine appointment
to be able to speak to somebody about Jesus.
Well, that's a door of utterance.
And notice what he says,
to speak the mystery of Christ,
for which I am also in bonds,
that I may make it manifest as I ought to speak.
Does it sound similar to what we read in Ephesians 6?
Sounds awful similar to what we read there in Ephesians 6
just a moment ago.
And we find that the Apostle Paul,
he's praying for these open doors.
You know, we desire for God to open up some doors,
not only here in Oakton and Vienna, Fairfax,
as we minister here,
as we desire to be the light in the community
that God has given us the opportunity to serve and minister.
And we need to be praying that God would give us open doors
and that God would use us as we go forth
and give us boldness.
But specifically this evening,
when we're looking at this idea of this trip
that we're taking on Monday,
that we're praying that God would open up doors,
that God would give us opportunities.
There's a church being planted, established.
And the reality is that the missionary,
I didn't do all of the research.
I haven't done all of the research.
I don't plan to do all of the research,
but he did all the research as he was seeking
where in Idaho he was gonna plant a church
and the need that was in that area
and the absence of gospel preaching churches.
And so there's a, based on what I've been,
what's been communicated to me,
there's a need for the gospel.
There's a darkness in that area
where there's no church that's shining forth
the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And so we need a door of utterance.
We need an open door of utterance.
We desire for God to do what we cannot do.
And guess what?
See, here's the amazing thing.
God does what we cannot do,
but God does not do what we can do.
See, God didn't choose to write the gospel in the stars
or on the stones or any other way.
He chose that we, as those that are saved
by the grace of God, would be the ones that go forth
and he'll open doors, he'll give us the boldness,
but we gotta open our mouth.
He doesn't do that part for us.
He empowers us to do it,
but at some point we gotta do it.
And so Paul says, pray for us,
that God would open unto us a door of utterance.
This evening, I ask for you also to pray for us
that God would open up a door of utterance,
that God would give us that boldness,
the opportunities and the boldness.
See, here's the thing.
If God doesn't open a door,
who are we gonna share the gospel with?
God's gotta open the door.
And then we gotta be ready to step in and do our part.
Amen?
Notice with me in the book of 1 Thessalonians.
We'll look at these final verses here,
1 Thessalonians and 2 Thessalonians,
the same church, obviously, the church in Thessalonica.
We find in 1 Thessalonians chapter five,
a very short verse, verse 25.
Brethren, pray for us.
That's pretty straightforward, is it not?
There's no specifics that are given here
in 1 Thessalonians, but when we go to the book
of 2 Thessalonians in chapter three,
we see the specifics of what Paul is requesting
that the believers in Thessalonica,
how they would pray for him, for them,
for those that are doing the work of the ministry.
He says, finally, brethren, in 2 Thessalonians three
in verse number one, finally, brethren, pray for us.
That the word of the Lord may have free course
and be glorified even as it is with you.
Now, I want you to pause just for a moment,
and I know I just had you in 1 Thessalonians
and I took you to 2 Thessalonians,
but I wanna take you back to 1 Thessalonians
because I think it's important that we see this
as you look in 1 Thessalonians chapter number two.
In fact, let's read chapter number one
and then get right into it because he says
that he's praying, he's asking these believers
to pray for us that the word of the Lord
may have free course and be glorified.
And then he says this, even as it is with you.
And so in chapter number one of the book
of 1 Thessalonians in verse number five,
Paul says, for our gospel came not unto you in word only,
but also in power and in the Holy Ghost
and in much assurance, as you know,
what manner of men we were among you for your sake.
Why did the gospel come that way?
Well, probably because people were praying
and God was working and God was answering.
Verse number six, and ye, and ye,
that's those that he's writing to
that had been saved in Thessalonica,
ye became followers of us and of the Lord.
Notice what it says, having received the word
in much affliction with joy of the Holy Ghost.
Now skip over to chapter number two, if you will,
in verse number 13 and notice that here,
the Bible says, for this cause also,
thank we God without ceasing.
What is it that's causing Paul to rejoice so greatly?
I mean, when you read those words
to thank God without ceasing,
what is it that Paul's rejoicing for?
It says this, because when ye received the word of God,
which ye heard of us, notice what he says,
ye received it not as the word of men,
but as it is in truth, the word of God,
which effectually worketh also in you that believe.
So that's the backdrop to what we read
in 2 Thessalonians 3 and verse number one,
when Paul says, finally, brethren,
pray for us that the word of the Lord may have free course
and be glorified even as it is with you.
Now think about this just for a moment.
Those believers in Thessalonica,
they knew the impact that God's word had in their lives.
They knew the power of God's word.
They understood the impact that God's word
had in their lives and as Paul would ask them to pray
and as he would make that statement,
even as it is with you, they could relate to that.
So now let me say it to you this way tonight.
Has God's word worked in your life?
Did the gospel make a difference for you?
Sure it has.
I mean, listen, the gospel radically changed my life.
Amen?
I'm not the same person that I was
before I got saved by the grace of God.
If any man be in Christ, he's a new creature.
Old things are passed away.
Behold, all things are become new.
And the reality is I'm not what I used to be
and thank God for that.
In God's word, listen, as newborn babes desire
the sincere milk of the word that ye may grow thereby,
strong meat belonging to them that are full age
and we understand that as we feast
on the truth of God's word,
all scripture is given by inspiration of God
and is profitable that we feast on God's word
and God's word works in us.
And so Paul says, would you pray
that the same way God's word has effectually worketh in you
that it would have that same impact on these
that we're ministering to?
Do you believe that it can?
I do.
I believe they can.
I was talking with brother Mark.
We were out door knocking a couple of weeks ago
and we had not had an opportunity
to go door knocking together for some time.
It just never worked out.
Just different teams and different things going on.
And he and I got to go out a couple of Saturdays ago
and we were knocking on some doors.
And as you're doing that,
you're having conversation as well.
And sometimes it's hitting the pause button
in between each house as you're talking and what have you.
And I said this to brother Mark.
I said, you know, it's wonderful
if God brings people to the church
that moved into the area,
they came from another good church and they come in
and man, they're already solid.
They've already been taught.
They just, man, they just can get plugged right in.
I said, but the reality is that
that's really not what church is all about.
Church is about reaching some people
with the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ
and then discipling them and teaching them
and training them.
As we find what Paul says to Timothy
as he's giving him the instruction
with the importance of taking and propagating the truth
and the things that thou hast heard of me
among many witnesses,
the same commit thou to faithful men
who shall be able to teach others also.
We've had some babies at our house
the last several weeks, grand babies.
And it's been exciting.
But can I tell you, they're messy.
And I'm not saying that in a negative way.
It's a joy, right?
It's wonderful, but it's messy.
Listen, sometimes when people are newly saved,
when people have not been grounded,
they may say some things that you're like, whoa.
But listen, God's word can work in their lives
just as it's worked in our lives.
I don't know about you,
but I can remember when I got saved.
And I can remember when I didn't know what I.
I know now.
Amen.
I can remember, we could put, I actually joked with
Brother Jeff that he should have done this in Sunday
school a couple of weeks ago, because we did it
during vacation Bible school that we challenged
all the kids, okay, who can say the books of the
Bible in order?
Genesis to Revelation.
You know what?
There are some little kids that got up and did it,
man.
They got right through it.
Praise the Lord.
And I told Brother Jeff, on Sunday, you get all those
adults and say, who can say the books of the Bible in
order, Genesis to Revelation, amen?
And the reality is that I remember when I didn't know
the books of the Bible in order.
I remember that.
I remember when I had no idea about the part in the
Red Sea.
Not a clue.
Now I could probably preach through Exodus 14 in my
sleep, basically.
And I'm not saying that pridefully, I'm just
simply saying God's Word has worked in my life.
And just as God's Word has worked in my life, it's
worked in your life, and it can work in other
people's lives.
Why?
Because God's Word is powerful.
He continues in verse number two, and that we may
be delivered from unreasonable and wicked men
for all men have not faith.
Hallelujah that he asked for prayer for that.
Safety from those that oppose.
Listen, there are those that are the enemies of the
cross.
He uses that phraseology in the book of Philippians.
They're the enemies of the cross.
We are in spiritual warfare, spiritual battle.
You know when the spiritual battle intensifies?
When you go out and preach the gospel.
Because the enemy doesn't like it.
I'm serious.
You get real active on preaching the gospel.
You get real active on trying to reach people with
the gospel, and the enemy doesn't like it.
And that spiritual warfare gets cranked up, and it
intensifies.
He says in verse three, but the Lord is faithful.
Aren't you thankful that God is faithful?
He said it this way in 1 Thessalonians to the same
church, faithful is he that calleth you who also will
do it, in verse 24 of chapter five.
And now we see that he says, but the Lord is
faithful who shall establish you and keep you
from evil.
And just as God would have an opportunity and an
ability to work in the believers in Thessalonica,
God can work in the lives of others as well.
This evening as we look at these five references,
these five examples throughout the New
Testament where Paul is seeking to enlist others to
pray on his behalf, he's trying to get these
believers, he understands the importance of prayer.
He understands as he first went out on that first
missionary journey that they fasted and prayed and
laid their hands on them and then sent them away.
And he got to see God do some amazing things.
But I believe that all the while, Paul and Barnabas,
they were praying as they went, but they also were
assured that there was a church back at Antioch that
was praying for them.
And they were, as William Carey would say, hundreds
of years later, hold the ropes.
And that's what they were doing.
And that's what I ask you this evening.
Will you hold the ropes?
Because we're going to go.
We're going to get on a plane on Monday morning and
we're going to go by the grace of God.
We'll get there safely and we'll have opportunity.
We already have it mapped out.
We have a quote unquote strategy for what we're going
to do.
Why?
Because if you don't have a plan, you're going to just
have disaster.
So we've made some plans on what we are going to do.
And our plan begins by saturating the area with
door hangers, letting them know that there's a church
that's starting, a church in the area.
We got 10,000 door hangers waiting for us.
Between the Pend Oreille, where the church will be,
and there's another town next to it that I wish I
could tell you the name of it, but it's not said like
it's spelled and I can't remember exactly.
I look at the spelling and I want to say it a
different way, but whatever the name of that town is.
And then there's Sandpoint to the southwest of where
Pend Oreille is.
And there's about 8,500 residential addresses that
are reachable in those areas.
We'd like to get them all hit, get all door hangers
on all those.
Why saturate it?
And then on Saturday, we're going to go back to those
neighborhoods that are closest to the church and
we're going to knock doors.
Hey, a few days ago, we left a flyer here letting you
know there's going to be a church planted.
And we just want to talk to you about the Lord and let
you know what he's done for us and what he can do for
you.
We got a plan.
But we need God's power.
Listen, corporations can come up with plans.
We try to have a plan, but we need God's power and we
need God's people to pray that God will do what only
he can do.
And then when we get back and on the 24th of August on
that evening service when we share a report with you and
are able to share with you what God did, then you can
rejoice with us.
Why?
Because you had a part because you were holding the
ropes.
And that's how this thing works.
And so this evening, when they had fasted and prayed,
we see all the examples.
And will you pray?
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the example that we see in the New
Testament.
We thank you for the request that is given over and
over.
And God, I pray that as we've sought to communicate
our burden and desire this evening, that we would
determine that we'll enlist and engage in prayer.
I pray, God, that you'd do great things.
I pray, God, that you'd work in such a way that only
you could receive glory.
I pray that you'd give us fruit.
I pray that souls would be saved and lives would be
changed.
I pray that the missionary and his family would be
encouraged.
I pray, God, that you'd give us safety.
I pray that you'd bless every aspect of this trip.
Thank you that we can spend some time at the
Wednesday evening prayer and Bible study to pray
corporately.
I pray that you'd bless our time and we'll thank you
for it.
In Christ's name we pray.
Amen.