with you this evening, Genesis chapter number 22 this evening, Genesis chapter number 22.
And I know that I've said it a couple of times, but I'm always thankful for the opportunity
to be in church on Wednesday evening.
And I remember as working in the corporate world and all the busyness of all that goes
on in a week and looking forward to that service on a Wednesday evening, seeking to be encouraged
and worship the Lord, fellowship with the people of God.
And so I always have loved the Wednesday night prayer meeting and looking forward to
what God has for us this evening.
The account recorded in Genesis chapter number 22 is a familiar account, and I would say
it's an impactful account.
It is the chapter in which God gives us the record of Abraham and Isaac on Mount Moriah.
It is this text where we find that if we could say it this way, Abraham faces the greatest
test of his life.
We have had someone said in years past, I'm not sure who it was, but someone wisely noted
that a faith that cannot be tested is a faith that cannot be trusted.
And I would say to you that Abraham had faith that endured a great trial, a great test here
in Genesis chapter 22.
Last time on Wednesday evening, we dealt with the name of God as it's given to us in Genesis
chapter 17, El Shaddai.
I am the almighty God.
That's what God says to Abraham as he appears to him after those 13 years between chapter
16 and 17.
And we find that God tells him, he reconfirms to him the promise with regard to the birth
of Isaac.
We looked at that last week.
We dealt with all of that.
Chapters 18, 19, and 20 deal with Sodom and Gomorrah, some things going on.
And we come to chapter 21 of the book of Genesis, and you find that it records for us the birth
of Isaac, that God did exactly what God said he would do.
And we can rejoice in that for every promise is true, amen.
And Peter says that they're exceeding great and precious promises, and indeed they are.
And I'm so thankful that our God has the ability to fulfill that which he promises.
We come to Genesis chapter 22.
We don't know exactly how much time has passed between chapter 21 and chapter 22.
We do not know.
The text does not tell us the age of Isaac here in Genesis chapter 22.
But we know that as we begin Genesis chapter 23, that the Bible tells us that Sarah, she
dies in this chapter, the beginning of the chapter, and she's 127 years old.
So that puts Isaac at 37 years old to start chapter 23.
And at the end of chapter 21, he's just four or five years old.
He's been weaned.
And so we don't know exactly how old he is.
Some have tried to pinpoint it, but I'm going to give you a real accurate estimation.
He's between five and 37.
And that's the answer that I'll give you this evening.
And there's a number of folks that have some ideas with regard to what the age might be,
but the text doesn't tell us exactly.
But we find here that there's a name that is given to us in verse number 14.
And it's actually an Abraham responding to all that has taken place.
And Abraham calls this place, this name, and it's a name that we will use with regard to
our God.
And that's interesting for all of the names that we've studied up to this point, we find
that God is giving to us the names that he's revealing.
But in verse number 14, and we'll look at the text in greater detail in just a moment.
But in verse number 14, the Bible says, and Abraham called the name of that place Jehovah
Jireh.
As it is said to this day in the Mount of the Lord, it shall be seen.
Jehovah Jireh, the Lord will see to it or the Lord will provide.
And this evening, the name that we're going to deal with is Jehovah Jireh.
Look with me at the text, if you will, and notice in really the first 13 verses, if you're
taking notes, the provision of God, the provision of God.
In these 13 verses, we note the faith of Abraham.
We note the obedience of Abraham.
His obedience and his faith is on full display here in Genesis chapter 22.
These first 13 verses, I mean, you want to see what it looks like to be obedient.
You want to see what it looks like to have faith.
I'm saying every day, living it out, this is what Abraham is doing.
It says in verse number one, and it came to pass after these things that God did tempt
Abraham and said unto him, Abraham, and he said, behold, here I am.
The word tempt means to test, to try, to prove.
That's what it means.
It says this in verse number two, take now thy son.
This is God speaking to Abraham.
Take now thy son, thine only son Isaac, whom thou lovest, and get thee into the land of
Moriah.
Now, if there was a period there, it'd be, we understand what God's saying, but there's
a semi-colon.
He's not completed the assignment yet.
The instruction is being given.
So we find that as we pause there just for a moment in verse two, that God is very specific
with regard to what he's saying, what he is instructing Abraham to do.
He says, take now thy son, thine only son Isaac.
Notice this, whom thou lovest.
The one that was just born in chapter 21, the one that after 24 years between the first
giving of the promise in Genesis 12 to what we looked at last week in Genesis 17, those
24 years without the fulfillment, but the fulfillment finally comes and it says it came
to pass after these things.
And God begins to speak to Abraham and he continues the instruction and notice in verse
two, and offer him there for a burnt offering upon one of the mountains, which I will tell
thee of.
Verse three, it says, Abraham rose up early in the morning, saddled his ass and took two
of his young men with him and Isaac, his son, and claimed the wood for the burnt offering
and rose up and went unto the place of which God had told him.
Then on the third day, Abraham lifted up his eyes and saw the place so far off.
And Abraham said unto his young men, abide ye here with the ass and I and the lad will
go yonder and worship.
Notice this phrase and come again to you.
We see his obedience in verse number three.
We find his faith in verse number five, where he says to those men, those servants, he says,
I and the lad will go yonder and worship.
Notice this and come again to you.
Larger place here, but look at Hebrews 11, if you will, very quickly.
And the subject matter this evening, I'm not really preaching through the whole chapter
and dealing with all of what God gives us.
We're going to get to that Jehovah Jireh, but I can't not mention anything about the
text.
And so I got to go through it here quickly.
But notice with me in Hebrews 11 in verse 17, the Bible says, by faith, Abraham, when
he was tried, this is what we're talking about in Genesis 22.
When he was tried, he offered up Isaac and he that had received the promises offered
up his only begotten son of whom it was said that in Isaac shall thy seed be called.
But notice verse 19, accounting that God was able to raise him up even from the dead from
whence also he received him in a figure.
That's spectacular faith right there.
See, we today, we understand we have the Bible and we can read of accounts where there were
miraculous resurrections of individuals, Elijah and Elisha and the ministry of the Lord Jesus
Christ.
And of course, our Savior rising, conquering sin, death, and the grave.
And he tells us that he is the first fruits, 1 Corinthians 15.
We understand, but we find that at the time in which Abraham is dealing with this in Genesis
22, he had not seen or read any of that, what I just mentioned.
He did not actually believe that God was able.
What faith, what faith that Abraham had.
See, God knew that Abraham had given promises and the promise that God gave to Abraham wasn't
just in having a son, but it was in a nation, it was in the perpetuity of that line.
And so we find that Abraham had great faith and he says to these men, he says, I and the
lad will go yonder and worship and come again to you.
And Abraham took the wood of the burnt offering and laid it upon Isaac, his son, and he took
the fire in his hand and a knife, and they went both of them together.
Notice this in verse seven.
I can't imagine as a father having this interaction that he has, but in verse seven, Isaac's speaking
to Abraham, his father, notice what he says, this is what Isaac says to Abraham.
He says, my father.
And he said, here am I, my son.
He said, behold the fire and the wood.
But notice this question.
Where is the lamb for a burnt offering?
Isaac knew that a lamb would be required.
Isaac understood.
And he asked the question.
We have the wood.
I mean, we have, we have most of what we need, but we're missing the lamb.
Notice the response in verse eight.
Abraham said again, we see the faith of Abraham.
He says, my son, notice this.
God will provide himself a lamb for a burnt offering.
So they went both of them together.
I believe verse number eight speaks really of a dual fulfillment.
Number one, that God would provide a substitute for Isaac.
Most importantly, that God himself would become our substitute, the Lord Jesus Christ, taking
our place, the Lamb of God, which taketh away the sin of the world.
I don't have time to deal with all of that this evening.
When I get to the name, we're dealing with the names of God in this study.
I preached Genesis 22 probably two years ago as I went through the book of Genesis, because
it took us like three and a half years to get through it.
But we see the faith of Abraham, and he says, my son, God will provide.
And can I tell you this evening, God did.
God did.
Not only did he provide for Abraham and for Isaac, but he's provided for us.
John the Baptist says, behold, the Lamb of God, which taketh away the sin of the world.
Hallelujah.
I'm so thankful that Jesus went to that cross, and he took my place, and he took your place.
He's our substitute.
We talk about the substitutionary atonement, what a blessed biblical doctrine that is.
We find that the Bible says in verse number nine, verse number nine, yes, and they came
to the place which God had told him of, and Abraham built an altar there and laid the
wood in order and bound Isaac, his son, and laid him on the altar upon the wood.
Remember, he believed that God was able to raise him up.
And we find in verse 10, Abraham stretched forth his hand and took the knife to slay
his son, and the angel of the Lord called unto him out of heaven and said, Abraham,
Abraham.
And he said, hear my.
Notice the message in verse 12, lay not thine hand upon the lad, neither do thou anything
unto him.
For now I know that thou fearest God, seeing thou hast not withheld thy son, thine only
son from me.
I've written in the margin of my Bible, I've often thought this as I've read through this
text of Scripture.
What is it that we're holding back from God?
Is there anything in my life, is there anything in your life that we're saying, God, you can
have all of this but not this?
God, I surrender.
We talked about on Sunday, I surrender all, is what that song was that we had for invitation
on Sunday evening.
And the reality is that for many times it might be that I surrender some, I surrender
most, but do I truly surrender all?
Is there something that we say, God, not that.
But Abraham was willing.
He didn't withhold anything from God, anything, wow.
Verse 13, Abraham lifted up his eyes.
The Bible says that he looked and behold behind him a ram caught in a thicket by his horns
and Abraham went and took the ram and offered him up for a burnt offering.
Notice this, in the stead of his son.
We see the provision of God in verses 5 through 13.
We note it, we've read through it, we see the dialogue, we see the obedience and the
faith of Abraham, we see the provision of God and what glory that is.
But as we see the provision of God, I want you to see in verse number 14, number 2, the
proclamation of Abraham.
Notice as Abraham experiences all that he experienced, can you imagine the emotions
in chapter number 22 in the life of Abraham?
Can you imagine the message as God comes to him in the beginning of the chapter and he
gives him the instruction to go and to do and he sets out and he's on this journey and
he's taking three days and he sees the place and all that's transpired, can you imagine
all of the emotions that this man has experienced in just a short period of time?
And after God provides, as we read in verse 13, we find that Abraham, I believe, with
great joy, recognizing the provision of God, rejoicing for the provision of God, that he
calls the place, the name of that place, Jehovah Jireh.
It's the only place you're going to find this word, this name, in the Hebrew Scriptures.
Obviously the truth of God being the provider, the one who will provide, the one who will
see to it, is seen broadly throughout the Scriptures, but we find this compound name
for God that Abraham in such joy, in a moment of great rejoicing, he calls the name of the
place Jehovah Jireh.
And notice it says, as it is said to this day, literally to the time of the writing
of the book of Genesis, the place that we're speaking about still carried with it that
name Jehovah Jireh.
Why?
Because God provided.
God worked miraculously and Abraham was moved with such gratitude and he was rejoicing and
he shares and he gives this name.
And you notice it says, in the mount of the Lord it shall be seen.
We think about this proclamation after the provision is given and no doubt we should
rejoice for God's provision, but as we've taken these names of God and we've sought
to try to make application for our lives and what is the significance of knowing the
name Jehovah Jireh, what is the significance of understanding that the Lord will see to
it, that the Lord will provide, what does that do for me?
What does that do for you today in 2025?
Well take your Bible and look at Matthew 6, if you will, and then we're going to look
at several areas in which we can see how our God provides.
Matthew chapter 6, it's a familiar portion of Scripture, in fact most of us tonight probably
could quote at least part of verse number 33, but seek ye first the kingdom of God.
Many of us could memorize or recite, rehearse much of that verse this evening, but I want
you to look at verse 32 along with it as we dig into this tonight.
Matthew 6 and verse 32, notice the Bible says, and after all these things do the Gentiles
seek.
Well what are those things?
Well if you don't, in verse number 31, they're saying, he says, therefore take no thought
saying what shall we eat, what shall we drink, wherewithal shall we be clothed.
He says for after all these things do the Gentiles seek, but notice this truth in verse
32, for your heavenly Father knoweth that ye have need of all these things.
Can I tell you this evening that the Lord is aware of your needs?
The Lord is aware of my needs.
He knows.
Not only does He know, not only is He aware, but He is able to provide for whatever that
need is.
We find that in verse 32 it says, your heavenly Father knoweth that ye have need of all these
things, it says in verse 33, but seek ye first the kingdom of God and His righteousness and
all these things shall be added unto you.
The truth tonight that the Lord is aware of what we need, but He's also able to provide
what we need is of great comfort to me.
When we begin to think about this truth of the Lord providing, we look at the familiar
passage of Scripture in Psalm 23, a psalm that most of us could quote this evening,
but it starts this way, the Lord is my shepherd, I shall not want.
The shepherd knows what the sheep needs, right?
You know, the sheep is not capable of taking care of his own needs.
The sheep needs someone to provide leadership and direction and so on and so forth, and
the shepherd has a great role and responsibility, and I'm thankful that our shepherd, the good
shepherd, the great shepherd, the chief shepherd, that he is my shepherd.
And this evening as we begin to think about this truth and we see the provision of God
and the proclamation of Abraham, I want you tonight to think just for the rest of the
time that we have before we go to prayer, I want you to think about God's provision
for you, God's provision for me.
I have eight things listed out that I want to highlight for you this evening, but I want
you to know that you could add to it, you could add to it, it's not an exhaustive list,
but God knows what we need.
Can I say this?
Oftentimes, it's going to be my first point of these eight thoughts, but oftentimes when
we think about the Lord will provide, Jehovah Jireh, even though contextually it has nothing
to do with finances, oftentimes when we think about provision and God providing, our minds
immediately go to finances.
But can I tell you this evening, you have a whole lot more needs than just finances.
We all do.
We have a whole lot more needs than finances.
There's definitely an understanding of the need for money to survive and to live and
so on and so forth, but God knows all about that.
We have things, we have needs that God can meet for us that money cannot buy for us.
So the first thought is finances, because I'm going to get that one out of the way so
that we stop thinking about it, amen, and so the first one is finances.
Look at 1 Chronicles chapter 29, if you will, 1 Chronicles chapter 29 being the Old Testament,
we'll be kind of bouncing back and forth here with a number of these, but I want you to
think about God's provision for you.
In 1 Chronicles chapter 29, David is ready to die and he's given a charge to Solomon
with regard to building the temple and all that God had put on his heart and all the
preparation that he did.
But I want you to notice what David declares in verse number 14 of 1 Chronicles chapter
29.
Notice the humility of David and the rejoicing of David.
Notice the perspective that David has that is a perspective that every one of God's people
must have today.
Notice it says this in verse 14 of 1 Chronicles.
29, but who am I and what is my people that we should be able to offer so
willingly after this sort? Then notice this perspective. For all things come of
thee and of thine own have we given thee. Listen, tonight understand that
everything that we have has come from God. He says for all things come of thee
and of thine own have we given thee. He says who am I, what is my people that we
should be able to offer this. I've often mentioned that the truth of 2nd
Corinthians that God loveth a cheerful giver. You study 1st Chronicles 29. I
think it's the best example in all the scriptures of what a cheerful giver
looks like. It's David. He gave of his own resources. He encouraged others to give,
to build a temple that he would never step foot in. He would never worship God
in that temple that would be built, but he gave sacrificially. He gave abundantly
and he recognized it was all because of God's provision. God can take care of us.
God knows what our needs are, but can I tell you you have greater needs than
finances. That's why I wanted to get that one out of the way. Number two, what does God
provide for us? He provides direction. You know we need direction in life. How many
times in your life you come to a place, you have the young people in here this
evening, the younger people, because we're all young people, amen, but the younger
people in here this evening and they seek, they need direction. What are you
going to do? What does God want you to do with your life? And all of these
decisions that are before them, listen, we need direction from God. It's a need
that we have, but the Bible tells us in Psalm 119 and 105, thy word is a lamp
unto my feet and a light unto my path. You know what God does for us? He gives
us direction. He gives us direction. He provides for you and for me the
direction, the lead us in a plain path, make it clear, trust in the Lord with all
thine heart, lean not on thine own understanding and all thy ways
acknowledge him and he shall direct thy paths. Is that not what the Bible tells
us in Proverbs 3, 5, and 6? And this evening we need direction. What do we do?
Where do we go? These decisions that are before me, I don't have the capacity. Why?
Because I don't know what's on the morrow. I can't see the future. Had a
great discipleship class today with Brother Fernando and we're talking about
several different things and one of the questions came up about what keeps so
many from surrender and submission and yielding and we talked about several
things that would prevent that in our lives and one being fear, fear of the
unknown. But you know the reality is that you don't know what's gonna happen
tomorrow whether you trust God or don't trust God. You don't know what's gonna
happen. You say, well this idea of surrendering over here, there's too many
uncertainties so I'm gonna go do this one because it's more secure and then
that one just falls all apart anyway. Because you don't know. You don't know.
We need God's direction. Number three, we need God's instruction. We need God to
teach us. David says, teach me, teach me. What a, having a teachable spirit. You
know it's important that we would have that humility and that ability to come
before the Lord and say, I need instruction. Lord, teach me. You know it's
a sad thing. So often we run into people, we have experiences in life where there
are people that do not have a teachable spirit. How do we know they do not have a
teachable spirit? Well they already know how to do everything. Have you ever met those
kind of people? I mean they just know how to do everything. Even though they've
never done it before, they've never read anything on it, but they know how
to do it. And the reality is that we need to come to God humbly and let God
teach us. Let God teach us. The Bible tells us in John 16 and verse 13 that
the spirit of truth was going to come and the Holy Spirit says he shall guide you,
he will guide you into all truth. He's the divine teacher. We need instruction. All
scripture is given by inspiration of God and is profitable for doctrine. For
doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for instruction in righteousness. That the man
of God might be perfect, throughly furnished unto all good works. We need
divine instruction from God. And God will provide it to us. He's given to us this
book. He's given to us the Holy Spirit who indwells us, who's the divine teacher.
And he'll instruct us. Can I tell you this evening, number four, we need peace. We need
peace. You know we live in a world where there's no peace. There's so much turmoil.
There's turmoil all around us. So many people have this idea that peace can only be found in
the absence of trouble. Can I tell you this evening, until we get to heaven, there's never
going to be an absence of trouble here on this earth. But when we get to heaven, there'll be an
absence of trouble. Amen? But can I tell you that you can have peace on earth. You don't have to
wait to get to heaven to have peace. You can have peace because peace is not found in the absence
of trouble. Peace is found in the presence of God. Jesus said this in John chapter number 15. He says
this. I mean, it's beautiful. John chapter 14, excuse me, he says,
peace I leave with you, my peace I give unto you. Not as the world giveth, give I unto you. Let not
your heart be troubled, neither let it be afraid. Great peace have they which love thy law, and
nothing shall offend them. He tells us these things in John 16 and verse 33, I have spoken unto you
that in me ye might have peace. In the world ye shall have tribulation, but be of good cheer, I
have overcome the world. We need peace. You know, the Bible describes in Philippians the peace of
God this way, it's a peace that passeth all understanding. What it seems like from the
temporal perspective that everything is falling apart and all the troubles and the trials, but we
can still have peace. Why? Because it's God's peace. And we need God's peace. Number five,
we need God's comfort. We need God's comfort. There's tribulation all around us. The Holy
Spirit is the comforter. But we know that the Bible tells us in 2 Corinthians, we dealt with
it in the beginning of the year. In 2 Corinthians chapter 1, the Bible tells us that our God is the
God of all comfort. And it tells us in verse number four of 2 Corinthians 1 that he comforteth us in
all our tribulation. He doesn't say that he removes all tribulation, but he says he comforteth us in
all of our tribulation. There's a great difference between removing the trouble and comforting us
through the trouble. Amen? We need that comfort. God is the comforter. We need his comfort. By the
way, all of these things are things that money can't buy. All of these things are things that
the world cannot provide, but our God can. Our God can. He can give you the direction that you need
for your life. Well, I went and talked to some counselors. There's wisdom in a multitude of
counselors. The Bible says that. But if you seek counsel, you better find a godly counselor because
you can find somebody that will tell you just about anything. Amen? You need instruction. You
need to go to God. Peace. No man can give you peace, but not only can no man give you peace,
no man can take your peace. He can't rob you of your peace. You have to forfeit it. So, I'm going to say,
all these people, man, they're… No, no, no. We have to forfeit it. We have to forfeit it. The comfort.
Number six, wisdom. Oh, how we need wisdom. We need God's wisdom. He's the all-wise God. He's
the omniscient one. And he says this in James 1, if any of you lack wisdom, let him ask of God,
who giveth to all men liberally and upbraideth not. What's the key in that passage, that promise? It's
acknowledging that you need wisdom. Because if you don't acknowledge you need wisdom, you will
never ask for wisdom. So many people think the key is asking for it. You're not going to ask for it
if you don't acknowledge you need it. And there's a whole lot of people that don't think they need
wisdom. They think they have it all figured out. Oh, would God help us to be humble? Would God help
us to understand we need? We talk Jehovah, Jireh, the God who will provide. He provides, yes, the
financial things. He provides the temporal things. Listen, the children of Israel understood, Moses
understood, that God can provide water from a rock. They understood that God could provide manna
from heaven. Elijah learned that God could provide through a raven. Right? God can provide all those
things, no problem.
I want you to think about these things tonight, the wisdom, the wisdom.
The days ahead of you, you don't know what you're going to encounter, but you need God's
wisdom.
I can't say every day because there may have been a day or a few days that I've missed,
but I endeavor every day of my life in the beginning of my day, God, I need your wisdom.
I need wisdom.
I don't know what I'm going to face today.
I don't know what's going to come up today, but God, you do, and I need your wisdom.
I need wisdom.
How about this one, number seven, encouragement.
You ever need encouragement?
I mean, just someone to encourage you.
I think Paul was glad for Barnabas.
Barnabas was an encourager, and I think Paul greatly appreciated the encouragement that
Barnabas provided.
But you understand that Paul was not, excuse me, Barnabas was not the only one that ever
encouraged Paul.
We find as you read through the scriptures that Paul received encouragement in 2 Timothy
chapter one and verse number 16, there's a reference to Onesiphorus and the Bible says
that he oft refreshed me.
The Bible tells us in 2 Corinthians in chapter number six about the coming of Titus and how
God comforts and how he used Titus to bring comfort and encouragement to Paul.
Listen, there are times in which you need encouragement.
There are times in which I preach the message in need of encouragement, and I said this
when I preached the message, today you might be the one doing the encouraging and tomorrow
you may be the one needing the encouragement.
Isn't that just how life works?
I mean honestly, today you might be the one calling someone, texting someone, writing
a note to someone to encourage them, but tomorrow you might need to be on the receiving end
of that.
God can encourage us.
He meets that need.
I said this earlier this year, one of the tools I think that is probably one of the
most often that our accuser of the brethren uses from his toolbox is that of discouragement.
There are a lot of discouraged Christians, a lot of people that are discouraged.
I think it's a tool that the enemy uses, but our God is able to encourage us as his people.
What a blessing to understand how God provides us with the encouragement that we need.
We have that encouragement comes through his word.
Have you been encouraged?
You read God's word?
Man, I have more than one occasion.
Just get into the Bible.
Sometimes God will use another brother or sister in Christ to encourage.
Sometimes it's that text message, that phone call, that email, that letter, that we don't
use letters too often anymore, but that letter, maybe that card that someone gives.
Maybe it's through preaching service.
Listen, we come to church and we can edify one another and we're supposed to, and we
find that we can encourage one another and we should, the encouragement that we need.
I save this one for the end.
You can add many things to the list.
It's not exhaustive.
In fact, I've added things as we've gone on tonight, but in my notes, number eight, it's
the greatest need of mankind, redemption, salvation.
We find in the book of Colossians in chapter one, and there's so many verses we could go
to, but for sake of time this evening, we'll just look at this single verse of scripture.
I alluded to it from Genesis chapter 22 when God, when Abraham says, my son, God will provide
himself a lamb.
The greatest need for humanity is redemption.
Your greatest need was to be saved.
The greatest need of anyone that you know is to be saved.
It's their greatest need.
And that need can only be met through the Lord Jesus Christ.
The Bible says in Colossians 1 and verse number 14, in whom we have redemption.
These words are important, through His blood, even the forgiveness of sins.
The only way to be forgiven without shedding of blood, there is no remission.
Is that what Hebrews tells us?
Blood is required.
Many of the modern translations today will remove the phrase in Colossians 1.14, through
His blood.
You can't have redemption, you can't have forgiveness if there's no blood.
Amen?
And Jesus Christ, the Lamb of God, He went to that cruel cross and He shed His blood.
Peter says we're not redeemed with corruptible things, silver and gold and so on and so forth.
No, we're redeemed with the precious blood of Christ.
Praise the Lord for redemption.
This evening, God's provision for us is abundant.
You say, but if I could just have a few more dollars I could do.
Think about all the things God provides for you that have nothing to do with dollars.
Nothing to do with dollars.
God is so good to us.
God meets our needs.
He knows what our needs are.
It's amazing how God works as we're sensitive to the leadership of the Holy Spirit and God
might prompt you, hey, so and so needs a call or a phone or a text, a card, something.
And you follow the leadership of the Holy Spirit.
Sometimes you have no idea how much of an encouragement and a blessing that is on the
other end.
Why?
Because they knew that they needed whatever it was that they needed and God used you as
a vessel, a tool to help bring that to pass.
Jehovah Jireh, my God will provide and He's capable of providing for, He is aware of and
He is able to provide for every need that we have.
And for that, our response should be one of great rejoicing.
Look at how good our God is.
He daily loadeth me with benefits.
That's what the psalmist said this evening.
Oh, we serve a great God.
He knows everything that we need and He's able to provide for it.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
Thank you for loving us.
God, there's so many other things that you provide for us and time simply won't allow
us to deal with all of it.
You give us rest.
Give us access.
Oh, Lord, we could go on and on.
We just thank you and praise you.
I pray that you'd bless our time of prayer.
Thank you for the privilege.
I pray that you'd work in hearts and lives and only you can and we'll give you the glory
for it's in Christ's name we pray, amen.