and know that our Savior lives, amen.
And what a blessing, I enjoy being able to get those
particular favorites from you.
We'll do Father's Day, we'll do the men
and have an opportunity to be able to do that.
And it leaves a little less time for preaching,
but many of the songs that we sing,
the great hymns of the faith,
they reinforce Bible teaching, amen.
And they instruct us and we're thankful for them.
And so I believe that we got a variety of messages
this evening as we had the opportunity to be able
to sing all of those wonderful hymns.
If you have your Bible with you tonight,
Psalm chapter number four, Psalm chapter number four.
And if you looked in the bulletin and on the back there,
the title for the message this evening
is from verse number seven.
The first phrase there,
thou hast put gladness in my heart.
And I'll read the entire Psalm.
It's not lengthy, just eight verses,
a Psalm that's ascribed to David.
And notice beginning in verse number one,
hear me when I call, oh God of my righteousness.
Aren't you thankful that he hears?
Praise the Lord, amen.
He says, thou hast enlarged me when I was in distress.
Have mercy upon me and hear my prayer.
Oh, you sons of men,
how long will you turn my glory into shame?
How long will you love vanity
and seek after leasing Selah?
But know that the Lord hath set apart him
that is godly for himself.
The Lord will hear when I call unto him.
Isn't that awesome to see the confidence?
He said in verse number one, hear me when I call.
But at the end of verse number three,
the Lord will hear when I call unto him.
Verse number four, stand in awe and sin not.
You know, we need to have a greater view of our God.
We need to see him high, holy, and lifted up.
And when we see him as he truly is,
it will have an impact on our lives.
We find that I actually preached a message,
I think it was last year,
as a direct connection as we look at the truth of God's word
between our view of God and then our sin in our lives
and how we need to see him for who he truly is.
Stand in awe and sin not.
Commune with your own heart upon your bed
and be still, Selah.
Offer the sacrifices of righteousness
and put your trust in the Lord.
There be many that say, who will show us any good?
Lord, lift thou up the light of thy countenance upon us.
Verse seven, thou hast put gladness in my heart
more than in the time that their corn
and their wine increased.
I will both lay me down in peace and sleep
for thou, Lord, only makest me dwell in safety.
We see this powerful statement in Psalm four
in verse number seven,
and I wanna consider just for a few minutes tonight
this thought, thou has put gladness in my heart.
The Hebrew word that's used here in verse number seven
for the word translated in English, gladness,
literally means joy.
In fact, 44 of the 94 times that that Hebrew word
is used in our King James Bible,
we find that it is translated joy.
And they're synonymous one with the other,
but we see here as the psalmist, David,
is making this declaration, this powerful statement,
thou has put gladness in my heart.
We recognize with me this evening
that David had an understanding that it was God
that put the gladness in his heart.
We see that he recognizes thou.
See, today when we think about gladness,
when we think about joy,
unfortunately there are times in which people
are trying to place their joy in a whole,
or find their joy in a whole host of things.
They think that the newest, greatest,
whether it's something you can purchase,
whether it's a position you can attain,
whatever it may be,
this thing is going to bring gladness in my life.
This thing is gonna bring joy in my life,
but we find that David says thou has put gladness
in my heart.
I'm thankful that Jesus is the source of my joy,
that he is my joy.
And we find here that he says thou has put gladness,
notice, in my heart.
Begin to think about this phraseology here
and begin to look at what David is saying,
and then you see the great imagery that David uses
at the end of the verse in order to really drive home
the point, if you will.
Notice he says more than in the time
that their corn and their wine increased.
So he's giving to us an example of a people
that would have great gladness and great joy
found in the fact that their goods had increased,
that they had their corn and their wine increased,
and because of that, they had gladness,
they had joy, and David says that the gladness
that God has put in my heart is greater,
it is more than in the time that their corn
and their wine increased.
We can understand the imagery that is used
and we can relate to it and we can understand this evening
the seriousness in which David is dealing with
when he speaks here about the subject of having joy
in his heart.
I wonder this evening as we begin to think about
the truth of this verse of scripture,
and I was mindful as I looked at this verse
of a little song that we sing with the Sunday school
children, I've Got Joy, and that little song,
if maybe you don't know it this evening,
it says I've got joy down in my heart.
Deep, deep down in my heart.
J-O-Y, down in my heart, deep, deep down in my heart.
Jesus gave it to me, and then notice this,
and nothing can destroy it.
Jesus gave it to me and nothing can destroy it.
I've got joy down in my heart,
deep, deep down in my heart.
And the psalmist declares here in Psalm verse number four
and verse number seven, thou has put gladness in my heart,
more than in the time that their corn
and their wine increased.
Let me ask you this evening, how's your joy?
Do you have gladness in your heart?
Do you have joy in your heart?
Galatians chapter number five, we'll look at a couple
of New Testament passages of scripture this evening.
Look in Galatians chapter number five,
and as you look there in Galatians five,
you're understanding that we're looking here
at the passage of scripture in which the apostle Paul
is giving the fruit of the spirit.
Understand that it says the fruit of the spirit,
it is not something that is plural,
the fruits of the spirit, it is the fruit of the spirit,
and as a having the fruit of the spirit,
here's how it's described, here's what it looks like.
Oftentimes, when we think about the importance
of walking in the spirit, in fact, you see it in verse 16
in the same text of scripture, this I say then,
walk in the spirit and ye shall not fulfill
the lust of the flesh, and we understand
that we're indwelled by the Holy Spirit of God
and we're to be filled with the Holy Ghost,
and what a blessing to understand
that as we acknowledge the biblical importance
of us being filled with and having the fruit of the spirit,
that there is biblical evidence that God gives us
for those who are truly filled with the spirit.
And so we find that here, the Bible says
the fruit of the spirit, notice in Galatians 5 in verse 22,
but the fruit of the spirit is love, joy, peace,
longsuffering, gentleness, goodness, faith, meekness,
temperance against such, there is no law,
and they that are Christ have crucified the flesh
with the affections and lust.
If we live in the spirit, let us also walk in the spirit.
Begin to understand the fruit of the spirit
as it's listed here in verse 22, again,
it's not fruits of the spirit, it's the fruit of the spirit,
and it's explained this way, the words are used
to help us understand when we're filled with the spirit,
we have the fruit of the spirit,
there's going to be love and joy and peace
and longsuffering and gentleness and goodness and faith
and meekness and temperance, it's going to be evidenced
in our lives, this is the fruit of being filled
with the spirit of God.
This evening, we understand that the psalmist says
that thou hast put gladness in my heart,
the fruit of the spirit, listen, you can try to work up joy
and gladness in your own life,
but it's going to just kind of fall short.
It's gonna be different than the gladness or the joy
that the Lord God Almighty can give you.
We find that some have had this idea that joy
or gladness is found in the absence of trouble.
In fact, many people try to live their lives
and if I could just get rid of these things,
then perhaps at that time, I could have gladness
and I could have joy, but I would submit to you this evening
that gladness, joy is not found in the absence of trouble,
but in the person of the Lord Jesus Christ.
In the very midst of great difficulty and trouble
and tribulation and difficulty, we can be joyful people
and we ought to be joyful people.
Did you notice in the Psalm there in Psalm four,
listen, there's some things that David's dealing with,
there's some things that he's facing,
but he says thou hast put gladness in my heart.
Doesn't mean that everything's gonna be perfectly fine
and you're never gonna have a trouble,
it's the fact that the Lord has put joy in your heart.
Notice in John chapter number 16, if you will,
John chapter number 16,
and I want you to see here what the Lord Jesus Christ
is saying to his disciples.
Of course, we understand that soon,
Jesus would go to the cross of Calvary.
He's speaking to his disciples and providing them
with truth that was so important for them to grasp
and hold on to in these days that would follow.
Right in the midst of the text of Scripture in John 16
in verse number 22, the Bible says,
and ye now therefore have sorrow,
but I will see you again and your heart shall rejoice.
And your joy, notice what it says, no man taketh from you.
Your joy, no man taketh from you.
It's almost as if we look at the text of Scripture
and understand what's taking place.
He says in verse 33 at the end of the discussion,
these things I have spoken in you that in me,
you might have peace in the world,
you shall have tribulation, but be of good cheer.
I have overcome the world.
And he says that your joy, no man taketh from you.
So then let me ask this question, how do we lose our joy?
If the Bible says that no man can take it from us,
then how do we lose it?
We have to forfeit it, amen?
We get our eyes on the wrong thing.
We get focused on maybe those temporal things.
We get focused on things that really don't matter
and we get all worked up and we really forfeit our joy.
Listen, this evening I've lived long enough
to know that there's some people that have lost their joy.
Amen?
There's some people that are just not joyful.
I'm not talking about the world,
I'm talking about God's people.
I'm talking about people that are saved, heaven bound.
I mean, people that have been born again, hallelujah,
we'll see Jesus one day.
We can lose our joy.
What is it that causes us to lose our joy?
If Jesus said that no man taketh it from you,
then it's something that we must forfeit,
that we make certain choices and certain decisions.
Listen, the Bible plainly said,
as we looked at it in Galatians chapter number five,
walk in the spirit and you shall not
fulfill the lust of the flesh.
He doesn't make us walk in the spirit though.
He tells us to be filled with the spirit
but he doesn't make us be filled with the spirit.
You can make a decision every day of your life
to be filled with self.
In fact, in the same text of scripture
in Galatians chapter number five,
when the Bible provides for us
what the fruit of the spirit is,
we find in the preceding verses that God lays out
what the works of the flesh are
and he tells us, here's how they're manifest
and you begin to see all sorts of evil
and terrible things in these characteristics
and the reality this evening is that
there's a possibility that some of God's people
have lost their joy.
We begin to evaluate our own lives,
examine our own lives and look at what the psalmist says
in Psalm four in verse number seven,
thou has put gladness in my heart.
And I wonder this evening, could you say as the psalmist,
thou has put gladness in my heart that I have that joy.
Could you say as that little song goes
that we sing with the kids in Sunday school
and in junior church and in vacation Bible school,
Jesus gave it to me and nothing shall destroy it.
Think about that.
That's a powerful little statement in that song.
Joyful people are praising people, amen?
Because if you have joy, you're gonna rejoice.
The outworking of joy is rejoicing
and therefore joyful people are praising people.
Can I tell you this evening, we have much to give thanks for.
We have so much to be thankful for.
I know that on Wednesday evening this past week,
I preached that message, my cup runneth over
and someone commented to me this morning,
I've been thinking about that phrase
throughout the last several days since Wednesday,
my cup runneth over.
Oh, what a great phrase to be mindful of
and to be thinking and meditating upon why,
because truly my cup runneth over.
My God daily loadeth me with benefits.
He's been so good to us.
We find that joyful people are praising people.
Let me say this,
joyful people are pleasant people to be with, amen?
This is a really simple practical truth, isn't it?
But joyful people are pleasant to be around, amen?
You like to be around joyful people?
Raise your hand if you wanna be around joyful people.
If you don't raise your hand, you're crazy,
you need some help, amen?
I'll try to sign you up for somebody to help you later,
but if you wanna be around miserable complaining people,
something's just not right.
You understand what I'm saying?
You get into a place and all of a sudden,
it's just miserable people and complaining people
and you're like, what is going on?
It's that old Eeyore syndrome, right?
Oh, bother.
Like just everything's just, no man, we're going to heaven.
Jesus is my savior.
He loves me.
He's given me all of these things.
I have a Bible.
I have the Holy Spirit that indwells me.
He's given me joy.
And David, he says, thou has put gladness in my heart.
So I wonder this evening,
again, we just have a few minutes,
but how's your joy?
Let me ask it this way.
Is it evident to those around you
that the Lord hath put gladness in your heart?
Here's what I truly believe.
I believe that when we have joy,
when we have gladness,
that other people are gonna know that.
You can't hide it.
Listen, what's on the inside comes out, amen?
And if you're filled with the Spirit
and you have that joy
and you have that perspective that David speaks of,
thou has put gladness in my heart.
Listen, those people that you come in contact with,
they're gonna say, man, look at this person.
They just have joy.
Then someone might say, how do you have the joy?
I mean, how is it that you just seem
to always be glad and joyful?
Listen, it's because of what my Lord has done for me.
Any of us can complain about anything.
Listen, there's a lot going on in our world
that we can complain about.
You can go down to the market,
you can go down to Costco
and you can find some people to complain with.
You know what I'm saying?
I tried to find a parking spot there yesterday.
I'm sure that I could have found some people
to complain with about trying to find a parking spot
on a Saturday at Costco.
But it's okay.
Thou has put gladness in my heart.
It is God that gives it.
So often we try to find that joy in other things.
Sometimes we try to find joy in people.
People will disappoint you.
Have you found that out?
Sometimes we try to put joy in maybe the things
that we have, the position that we hold.
Listen, all those things are fading, just passing by.
We sang to start the service this evening,
Jesus never changes, yesterday, today and forever.
And when I understand that He is my joy
and that He hath put gladness in my heart,
then I live as an individual that is rejoicing,
that's praising someone that others wanna be around.
Why?
Because joyful people are pleasant people to be around.
They really are.
And so this evening, just a simple brief challenge.
How's our joy?
Say, man, I've been, I just feel like I've lost my joy.
In fact, Brother Mershon, a number of years ago,
wrote an article that he titled Joy Thieves.
What is it that steals our joy?
And I said this as I looked at there at John 16,
something that we have to forfeit.
No man taketh it from you, we have to forfeit it.
And here's the reality this evening.
The world needs to see some of God's people
being filled with the Spirit of God and having joy.
Having joy, gladness.
David says, thou hast put gladness in my heart.
How's our joy?
Is it coming out through rejoicing, we're praising?
Do other people see it?
Just a simple thought this evening,
but I hope as we go throughout this week
that we'll be mindful that we're to be a joyful people,
a praising people.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for each song that we had the opportunity
to sing this evening.
And thank you for the messages that we received
through those great hymns of the faith.
Being reminded of the fact that you're coming again
and being reminded of the fact that you can do anything
and being reminded of the fact that you died for us
and that you rose conquering sin, death, and the grave,
that you live forevermore.
I mean, so many wonderful lessons and messages
that we were able to receive
through those songs this evening.
And now as we take just a few moments
to look at this statement of the psalmist in Psalm four,
God, would you help us to evaluate our lives?
Can we honestly say thou hast put gladness in my heart?
Am I a joyful person?
Do I have the fruit of the spirit
as evidenced in my life?
Do others recognize that I have that joy that you've given?
I pray, Father, that if we've come to the place
where we've kind of lost our joy,
God, would you help us to get it right this evening?
Lord, help us to change our perspective.
Lord, help us to see you for who you are.
Lord, help us to receive what you have for us
and to be able to be in that place
where we could say, as David did,
thou hast put gladness in my heart.
Help us to change our perspective.
I pray, God, that you'd work in hearts and lives
as only you can.
I pray that decisions would be made that would please thee.
Well, thank you for it.
In Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Just a brief invitation this evening.
Simple thought, thou hast put gladness in my heart.
More, he says, these people,
their corn and their wine increased,
but God, the gladness, the joy that you gave me
is more than that.
How's your joy this evening?
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.