And as we continue with this study of the names of God, I hope that you've been encouraged
and I hope that you've been blessed as we've had the opportunity to study these names.
This is our eighth lesson here on these Wednesday nights in this series.
I know Brother Mark filled in last Wednesday evening as I was down there in Florida, and
we were able to tune in via live stream and enjoyed the service.
I appreciate him being willing to fill in and certainly appreciate the challenge from
God's Word and desiring to serve the Lord with our lives as Elisha did, and so we praise
the Lord for that.
Exodus chapter 15, if you know about the section of the book of Exodus that we're in this evening
as we think about this name, we understand that the children of Israel, they were eyewitnesses
of God's great power.
They had been in bondage in Egypt, and while in Egypt, we know that God raised up Moses
and God called him and God told him to go stand before Pharaoh, and as he would stand
before Pharaoh, God would demonstrate His power, and oh, how He demonstrated His power,
so much so that the magicians and astrologers and wise men there in Egypt, they said, this
is the finger of God.
They recognized the power of God on display.
The children of Israel were eyewitnesses of this.
It was interesting, if you study the plagues, you'll find that for a number of them, there
was a distinction between the plague affecting adversely the people of Egypt but having no
effect whatsoever on God's people, and what a blessing to see the division and the separation
and to see the power of God, and we find that they were eyewitnesses of that.
We have the opportunity of reading it and being encouraged as we read it, being strengthened
in our faith, but they were eyewitnesses.
Can you imagine the impact, the influence that it should have had upon their lives?
We find that as they would leave Egypt land after that 10th plague, the death of the firstborn,
we find that they experienced deliverance from the Egyptians as they crossed over the
Red Sea, and God miraculously parted the Red Sea.
The Bible tells us that they went over on dry ground, and what a blessing to think about
God's power on display.
Not only had they witnessed those 10 plagues, but now they had the opportunity to experience
crossing the Red Sea, and again, the power of God on display.
Exodus chapter 15, that's recorded in the 14th chapter.
In the 15th chapter of the book of Exodus, for at least the first 21 verses here, we
find that there's a song of deliverance.
In fact, what was happening is the people of God were singing praise to God for what
He did.
Isn't that wonderful?
I think that's a great picture and understanding for us to rejoice in what God does, to take
the time to praise Him.
There are times in which we pray, and we pray God whatever the need is, and we say, well,
thank you for it.
I wonder how often do we thank Him for it when He answers, and here, the children of
Israel, they are rejoicing.
They were singing about God's power, and what a blessing.
Unfortunately, as the last verse concluded, they arrived in a place called Marah.
And as they arrived in this place called Marah, we find that it was in the midst of this great
difficulty that they would face, this first area after crossing over the Red Sea and experiencing
the power of God, and we find that in the midst of this difficulty, it's here that
God reveals to us and to the people of God, to Moses, this name, Jehovah Rapha, the Lord
who heals, Jehovah Rapha.
Notice with me, beginning in verse 22, and we'll read down through verse number 27, the
end of the chapter, and we'll look at this.
The Bible says this, so Moses brought Israel from the Red Sea, and they went out into the
wilderness of Shur, and they went three days in the wilderness and found no water.
When they came to Marah, they could not drink of the waters of Marah, for they were bitter.
Therefore the name of it was called Marah, and the people murmured against Moses, saying,
what shall we drink?
And he cried unto the Lord, and the Lord showed him a tree, which when he had cast
into the waters, the waters were made sweet.
There he made for them a statute and an ordinance, and there he proved them, and said," notice
what he says in verse 26, "'If thou wilt diligently hearken to the voice of the Lord thy God,
and wilt do that which is right in his sight, and wilt give ear to his commandments and
keep all his statutes, I will put none of these diseases upon thee, which I have brought
upon the Egyptians.'"
Notice this phrase, "'For I am the Lord that healeth thee.'
They came to Elam, where were twelve wells of water, and threescore and ten palm trees,
and they encamped there by the waters."
At the end of verse 26, you see that phrase, "'I am the Lord that healeth thee.'"
We get this name for God, Jehovah Rapha.
It's interesting, if you find throughout the Bible, there are many promises that God gives
us.
I'm thankful for every promise.
In fact, we sing, standing on the promises, and we understand the importance of knowing
the promises of God, Peter says, that are exceeding great and precious promises.
And we find that there are some promises in God's word that are conditional promises,
and some promises that are unconditional.
Most times, when you see those conditional promises, they'll follow a pattern similar
to this, "'If, then.'"
In other words, if you do this, then this is what will happen.
And we find, in a very positive sense here, in verse 26, notice the Bible says that God
says, "'If.'"
Do you see the word there?
"'If thou wilt diligently hearken to the voice of the Lord thy God, and wilt do that which
is right in his sight, not that which is right in your sight or in someone else's sight,
in the culture's sight, in the society's sight, no, in God's sight.'"
Where do we find out what's right in God's sight?
The B-I-B-L-E.
Yes, that's the book for me, right?
I mean, that's where we find out what is right in God's sight.
"'And wilt give ear to his commandments, and keep all his statutes.'"
Here's what God's going to do.
"'For I will put none of these diseases upon thee which I have brought upon the Egyptians,
for I am the Lord that healeth thee.'"
What a blessing and encouragement to the people of God for them to understand that God is
Jehovah Rapha.
We find that as God would make these declarations, we see it here in Exodus 15, he's speaking
about these physical diseases.
But I want you to think about the healing in a multiple type of areas this evening.
I want to look at a couple of verses of Scripture.
Turn over to 2 Chronicles chapter 7, if you will, and look at a few verses of Scripture
and then some examples of how this impacted the people of God and how it should impact
us.
In 2 Chronicles chapter number 7, you're familiar with this verse of Scripture, but I want you
to be reminded of what God says here in 2 Chronicles 7 and verse 14.
After the dedication to the temple, Solomon prays and God responds and says, "'I've heard
thy prayer,' and verse 12, notice what God says in verse 14, "'If my people, which are
called by my name, shall humble themselves and pray and seek my face and turn from their
wicked ways, then will I hear from heaven and will forgive their sin.'"
And what does he say?
Will heal their land.
He says that he'll heal their land.
He says in Exodus chapter 15, speaking about the diseases that were upon the Egyptians,
that he, the Lord, Jehovah Rapha, that he would put none of those diseases upon them.
Why?
Because he's the Lord that heals.
And we find that here in 2 Chronicles 7, there's this reference with regard to healing the
land.
Look in the book of Psalms, if you will.
In fact, there's so many Psalms that we could look to this evening to see the impact of
this truth.
But I want you to notice in Psalm 103, it's a precious psalm.
Some of you may even say that it's your favorite psalm.
It's just a wonderful truth that God gives us throughout the entirety of this psalm.
But the Bible begins, bless the Lord, O my soul, and all that is within me.
Bless his holy name.
Bless the Lord, O my soul, and forget not all his benefits.
Notice what it says, who forgiveth all thine iniquities.
Aren't you thankful that he forgives?
But then it says this, and healeth all thy diseases.
I believe tonight that God has the power to heal every disease.
He has the power to do so.
There are times in which he chooses not to heal a disease here upon this earth, but we'll
find as we get through the message this evening that ultimate healing always comes to the
people of God.
We find that here, this declaration, the psalmist rejoicing and blessing the Lord, praising
the Lord.
Why?
Because he understands this truth with regard to the aspect of God's nature, that he is
the God who heals.
Look at Jeremiah chapter 3.
Jeremiah's prophesying on the eve of Babylonian captivity.
This is hundreds of years, I mean, lots of history that's taken place between Exodus
15, when God announces that he is the Lord that heals.
And here in Jeremiah chapter number 3, and Jeremiah is dealing with a group of people
that are rebellious, a group of people that had forsaken the Lord, a group of people that
had forgotten the Lord.
The Bible says this, they forgot the Lord days without number.
The Bible says that they forsook the Lord.
The Bible then says this, they followed after idols.
Now we know that idolatry was prevalent within Israel's history.
You can read throughout their history and how prevalent it was that they would seek
after idols.
But here in Jeremiah chapter 3, notice what is said in verse 22.
2, God is speaking to his people through his prophet, it says this, return ye backsliding
children and I will heal your backslidings.
Behold, we come unto thee for thou art the Lord our God.
Now I want you to think about this truth of we sometimes will use that terminology of
backsliding and really this reference here in Jeremiah chapter 3 gives us some indication
with regard to God healing, what is he speaking of here, really a spiritual aspect, a spiritual
aspect and we can look at our lives as we examine our lives and determine where are
we in our walk with God, how close am I to God, am I closer to him today than I was yesterday
or a week ago or a month ago or a year ago or a decade ago, am I further, has there been
a time in my life that I was closer to God than what I am now, has there been a time
in my life that my prayer was more fervent than it is now, that my, you start filling
the blank and you start looking at that evaluation and examination and God says that he heals
not only diseases physically, not only a land that he has the ability to heal and by the
way he healed those waters at Marah, not only that but we find that when Elisha, there's
some water that there's death in the, well there's water that needs to be healed and
then there's pottage that there's death in the, God is able.
When I think about the spiritual aspect and how God is able to heal, to bring revival
in a life of an individual, to bring them back from where they came or to where they
had been, I think this evening as we look at this truth Jehovah Rapha, I wonder and
I ask this question, how should we respond to this revelation?
As God would reveal to his people that he is the Lord who heals, how should that impact?
How should that affect?
How should we respond?
I'm going to give you, and we're going to go quickly, I know it's Wednesday evening,
we try to get through and get into some prayer time but I'm going to give you four examples
this evening of responses that are appropriate responses, I mean that are exemplary for us
and the first one is of Moses and Moses, we're going to kind of be around in the Bible, it's
Bible study and so we're going to be flipping back and forth but go over to Numbers chapter
12 if you will.
In Numbers chapter 12 there's an event that takes place and we find that God had already
revealed to Moses in Exodus 15 as we looked at already that he is the Lord that heals
and here in Numbers chapter 12 Miriam and Aaron speak against Moses.
We find that there's some difficulty that takes place here and the reasoning for what
they're accusing Moses of is revealed to us but what I want to look at is in verse
number 10 where the Bible says, you know, the cloud departed from off the tabernacle
and behold Miriam, notice, became leprous, white as snow and Aaron looked upon Miriam
and behold she was leprous.
But I want you to notice what Moses does in verse 13, and Moses cried unto the Lord saying,
notice what he says, what is his prayer?
Heal her now, O God, I beseech thee.
Why did Moses pray for healing?
Because God told him, I'm the God who heals, amen?
We'd have no reason to pray for healing if we did not know that God was the God who heals.
Is that right?
And so God revealed to Moses in Exodus chapter 15 this name of his, Jehovah Rapha, the Lord
who heals, and later on down the road as they're still dealing with wilderness wanderings
and Miriam is leprous, white as snow, and Moses who had been spoken against, he cries
out to the Lord and he prays, heal her now.
I believe that Moses had faith that God could heal because he knew that God was Jehovah
Rapha.
Think about this in Nehemiah chapter number one, look at the example, a positive example
in the life of Nehemiah, in Nehemiah chapter number one, the post-captivity and all that's
taking place and Nehemiah's going to receive a report that is just discouraging with regard
to the affliction and reproach in Jerusalem and all that he finds out.
So what does this man Nehemiah do after receiving the report?
Well, he cries out to God, begins to pray.
We find that in verse number five, it says, and said, I beseech thee, O Lord, God of heaven,
the great and terrible God that keepeth covenant and mercy for them that love him and observe
his commandments, let thine ear now be attentive and thine eyes open that thou mayest hear
the prayer of thy servant, which I pray before thee now, day and night, for the children
of Israel, thy servants, and confess the sins of the children of Israel, which we have sinned
against thee.
Both I and my Father's house have sinned.
We have dealt very corruptly against thee and have not kept the commandments nor the
statutes nor the judgments, which thou commandest thy servant, Moses.
By the way, that prayer of repentance is an important aspect in every believer's life.
Sometimes what happens, if I sin, no, we did sin.
To confess means to say the same thing about, and we find here that he begins praying, confessing
the sins.
Notice what he says, not just of his brothers, but he says, both I and my Father's house
have sinned.
Verse 8, remember, I beseech thee, the word that thou commandest thy servant, Moses, saying,
if you transgress, I will scatter you abroad among the nations.
That's what God told Moses.
God told him, I'm bringing you in this land, but if you disobey me, I'm going to get you
out of this land.
Wow.
The Assyrian captivity, the Babylonian captivity is because of their disobedience.
Find in verse number 9, but if you turn unto me and keep my commandments and do them, though
there were of you cast out under the uttermost part of the heaven, yet will I gather them
from thence and will bring them unto the place that I have chosen to set my name there.
Now these are thy servants and thy people whom thou hast redeemed by the great power
and by thy strong hand.
O Lord, I beseech thee, let now thine ear be attentive to the prayer of thy servant,
to the prayer of thy servants who desire to fear thy name and prosper.
I pray thee, thy servant, this day and grant him mercy in the sight of this man, for I
was the king's cupbearer.
You know, it's interesting because in this passage of scripture, Nehemiah chapter 1,
Nehemiah is praying, he references about Moses in the text of scripture that we just read,
but we're also mindful of the fact that if you were to go back and read 2 Chronicles
chapter number 7, which we read a moment ago, where God said, I will heal your land, that
exactly what's happened in Israel's history is what Nehemiah is praying.
God, you said that if we disobeyed, this would be the consequence, and we find that it's
reiterated there in 2 Chronicles with God giving that instruction to Solomon after the
dedication of the temple, and we find that Nehemiah is saying, we're coming back to you,
we're praying, and we're seeking you, and what are they seeking for?
Well, deliverance for the opportunity to see the city rebuilt, et cetera, but also, I believe,
for healing of the land.
So what's not specifically said there, I think if you read it and you go back to 2 Chronicles
chapter 7, you see the connection beautifully as to why Nehemiah is seeking the Lord in
the manner in which he is.
What about Hezekiah, 2 Kings chapter number 20, look there, if you will, in the life of
Hezekiah, and we find that Hezekiah was a man basically known as being a relatively
good king, though the end of his life, it's unfortunate in a manner there that he was
given these additional 15 years, because unfortunately, in those 15 years, he didn't do what he should
have done.
It's very sad.
You know, somebody said this, and I think it's so important, it doesn't really matter
how you start the race, it matters how you finish the race, amen?
We find that Paul has that desire to finish his course.
He mentions that in Acts chapter 20, we find that Hebrews chapter 12, that we're to keep
our eyes on Jesus as we run our race, and He is the author and finisher of our faith,
and we must desire and long to finish well.
It won't happen on accident, we have to be purposed to do it, but here for Hezekiah,
and we talk about the fact that God is the God that heals, we find that here in verse
number one, notice this, in those days was Hezekiah sick unto death.
The prophet Isaiah, the son of Amos, came to him and said unto him, thus saith the Lord,
set thine house in order, for thou shalt die and not live.
Can you imagine receiving that word?
Can I tell you this evening, all of us are going to die one day.
We don't know when that's going to be.
We don't all get the message like Hezekiah did, amen?
So better be ready, better be ready.
Verse two, then he turned his face to the wall and prayed unto the Lord.
He says in verse three, I beseech thee, O Lord, remember now how I have walked before
thee in truth and with a perfect heart, and have done that which is good in thy sight.
And Hezekiah wept sore, and it came to pass after Isaiah was gone out into the middle
court that the word of the Lord came unto him saying, turn again and tell Hezekiah,
the captain of my people, thus saith the Lord, the God of David thy father, I have
heard thy prayer, I have seen thy tears, behold, was he saying, I will heal thee.
That's what your Bible says.
God says I will heal thee.
On the third day thou shalt go up unto the house of the Lord, and I will add unto thy
days fifteen years.
find that there's evidence given to help Hezekiah understand what God would do.
But I want you to understand this evening, if we look at these responses, why did Hezekiah
hear?
Why did he pray?
Well, God was the one that was able.
God is the one that is able.
New Testament believers, in James chapter number 5 and verse number 13, the Bible says,
is any sick?
Let him pray.
Why do we pray?
Why do we have in our prayer bulletins a section, sick or recovering?
Why is it that we pray for those that are not well?
Now understand with me this evening that we ought to be praying for those that need salvation,
those that need to be saved, and we have a section for salvation.
But the reality is that we pray, we see these responses of these individuals, and there
are many more that we could look to this evening.
Why?
Because God said, I'm Jehovah Rapha, I'm the Lord that heals.
Some negative responses.
I'll give you two of them this evening.
Ahaziah, 2 Kings chapter number 1.
Notice in 2 Kings chapter number 1, Elijah is the prophet of God.
We find that in this text, it's near the end of Elijah's ministry.
In fact, it's chapter 2 where he'll be caught up in that whirlwind with the chariot of fire.
We find in chapter number 1 that we're given this information with regard to Ahaziah.
Notice in verse number 1 of 2 Kings chapter 1, the Bible says, then Moab rebelled against
Israel, and after the death of Ahab, in verse 2, and Ahaziah fell down through a lattice
in his upper chamber that was in Samaria, and he was sick.
And he sent messengers and said unto them, Go inquire of, what does it say?
Baal Zebub.
Who is that?
That's an idol.
That's a false god.
Right?
Baal.
Baal Zebub, the god, little g, of Ekron.
Here's what he wants his servants, the messengers, to go and inquire of this false god, this
idol.
He says, Whether I shall recover of this disease.
Verse 3, But the angel of the Lord said to Elijah the Tishbite, Arise, go up to meet
the messengers of the king of Samaria, and say unto them, Notice what Elijah is supposed
to say to these messengers that are sent out from Ahaziah to go to a false god to find
out if he would heal, recover of his disease because he was sick.
The Bible says that here's what Elijah is to say to these messengers.
Is it not because there is not a god in Israel that you go to inquire of Baal Zebub, the
god of Ekron?
What is he saying here?
Listen, the Lord Jehovah, he is the god of the Hebrews.
He is the god of the universe.
He is the only true god.
And here God had revealed to the children of Israel before they ever entered the land
as they left from Egyptian bondage that I am the Lord that heals.
Why did God reveal that to his people?
Why did he preserve it for us in his word so that we would seek him in the times of
needing healing?
That we would not go seek other things or people or places, we'd seek the Lord.
I'm not suggesting this evening that we do not ever seek medical attention.
I'm simply saying there is a god in heaven that is able to heal.
He is the great physician.
And yes, he uses medical professionals and he's given them the abilities to be able to
have minds and understand things that are beyond my ability to comprehend.
And we thank God for that.
But we understand ultimately, and any good doctor would tell you that ultimately it's
not in them, it's in God.
This body is fearfully and wonderfully made.
No matter how long they study, we have medical professionals in our church, we have doctors
in our church, and no matter how long they study, there's always more to study, more
to learn, more to learn, more to learn.
The body is so intricate.
God can heal because God created this body and He knows everything about it.
We find this evening that Ahaziah, instead of going to Jehovah Rapha, instead of going
to the Lord who heals, instead of going to the prophet of God, he sends his messengers
to go seek after the god of Ekron, Beelzebub.
Let me give you the example of Asa, a negative response.
In 2 Chronicles chapter 16, Asa is given to us here in this account of what's going
on and we find that there are many things that we could say about Asa and there are
many things that we could, many good lessons that we could learn from his life.
We find at the end of his life, I want you to notice what the Bible tells us in 2 Chronicles
chapter 16, beginning in verse number 11.
The Bible says this,
And Asa slept with his fathers and died in the 140th year of his reign.
Two years of suffering if you look at the timeline between verse 12 and verse 13.
We find that, again, as I mentioned a moment ago, it's not that physicians are never to
be sought after, the reality is that the Bible plainly says that he sought not to the Lord.
We may need to go get medical attention.
I've gone, you've gone.
But ultimately my confidence and my faith is not in the ability of the doctor, it's
in God because he's the Lord who heals.
And I believe tonight that he has the ability to heal.
And let me say this as we close this evening, we think about this revelation that God gives
to the people of Israel there in Exodus chapter 15, I am Jehovah Rapha, I'm the God who heals,
I will heal you, and he has the ability to do that, but we live in a time in which every
single one of us have experienced, we've prayed for someone to be healed and we feel like
the prayer didn't get answered.
We feel like, why weren't they healed?
Well we find that there are times in which as we look even at our theme for this year
that God says to Paul as he prays, thrice, my grace is sufficient for thee.
For my strength is made perfect in weakness.
Is that not what 2 Corinthians 12 and verse 9 teaches us?
And so we find that this evening, if we think about the ministry, the miracles of the Lord
Jesus Christ, his power displayed over many diseased people to heal them.
But you know, there were many more in Israel during that day that had diseases that did
not receive healing.
And even those that received healing would one day die a physical death from something.
And this evening, there are times in which if we're not careful, we may get discouraged.
As we say, I believe that God can heal and I prayed fervently and God didn't heal.
Can I tell you this evening, that ultimate healing comes when this mortal shall put on
immortality, when this corruption shall put on incorruption.
The reality this evening is that we will face, unless the Lord Jesus Christ comes back in
our lifetime, and I hope he does, I believe that he will, but the reality is that if he
doesn't come back, then we're going to face death.
There's something, some health issue, something that's going to happen, and the reality is
that the ultimate fulfillment for us of how God heals is seen when this flesh is changed
in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye.
What a joy.
I referenced 1 Corinthians 15, but I want you to turn to Revelation 21, if you will,
and I want you to look at what the Bible says here in Revelation 21 as we conclude
this evening.
In Revelation chapter 21, in verse number one, the Bible says, And I saw a new heaven
and a new earth.
For the first heaven and the first earth were passed away, and there was no more sea.
And I, John, saw the holy city, new Jerusalem, coming down from God out of heaven, prepared
as a bride adorned for her husband.
And I heard a great voice out of heaven saying, Behold, the tabernacle of God is with men,
and he will dwell with them, and they shall be his people, and God himself shall be with
them and be their God.
Notice verse four, God shall wipe away all tears from their eyes.
There shall be no more death, that's what it says, neither sorrow nor crying, neither
shall there be any more pain, for the former things are passed away.
And he that sat upon the throne said, Behold, I make all things new.
And he said unto me, Write, for these words are true and faithful.
faithful. These words are true and faithful. God's word is true and faithful, and God's
is going to make all things new. He tells us that he's going to wipe away all the tears,
that there's going to be no more death, no sorrow, no crying, no more pain, no sickness
over yonder. Isn't that a wonderful thing? And I understand today that there are times
in which we deal with ailments. It doesn't mean that we don't believe that God can heal
or that God isn't able to heal. There are times in which God says, I want to teach you
a lesson through this. I'm going to, remember what the psalmist said in Psalm 119, it was
good for me to be afflicted. Why? Because then I learned thy statutes. There's some
things that you're only going to learn through the season of whatever God's taking you through.
There are certain things that we can learn as God takes us through something that we
cannot learn if God takes us around something. There are times in which God will take us
around something. Amen? The chosen of Israel, when they left, previous to what we read in
Exodus 15, in Exodus 14 when they left, God, actually it was in chapter 13, God didn't
lead them this way, he led them that way. Why? That way was more direct, but he said,
no, the people will faint because they're not ready for this. So he led them around
it. He didn't lead them through it, he led them around it. And in your life and my life,
sometimes God will heal and he will work miraculously and he will deliver us and take us around
something, but there are times in which he'll just give us his grace. I use the word just
and I really shouldn't have used that word because I'm so thankful for God's grace. And
his grace is sufficient. And in that moment, we get to learn things about God that otherwise
we'd never know about God. A dear mentor of mine said this to me a number of years
ago. He was laying flat on his back in a hospital bed, he was going to be out of the ministry
for months, had a major, major accident that had taken place and it was all the result
of tripping over a curb. And he said to me, he said, you know what? God knew that I need
this season. And God's teaching me some things in this season that I would not have learned
any other way. What is he saying? God could have healed him immediately. God could have
prevented that thing, but God allowed it and he went through a time of great suffering.
But he said, God's teaching me some lessons. I'm learning some things about God's grace.
One day, everyone that you know that you pray for that's dealing with some kind of
physical ailment, everyone that is experiencing some kind of physical ailment, one day, this
mortal shall put on immortality. I'm going to be changed, you're going to be changed,
we're going to have no more sickness, no more pain. Hallelujah. Praise the Lord for that.
This evening, never forget that he is the God who heals. Never forget this evening that
our response should be like Moses. Lord, heal her. Why? Because you revealed to me
that you have that kind of power. You know how we pray? I wonder this evening, when we
look at our prayer lives, are we praying in accordance with what God is really able to
do? What kind of prayer requests are on your prayer list tonight that only God can do?
That only God can do. And that only God will get the glory for. So this evening, he is
Jehovah Rapha. He is the God who heals. And we ought to rejoice in that. Let's pray together.
Father, we love you. Thank you for loving us. Thank you for revealing the truth in your
word. We know that the result of sin is death, physically, also spiritually. We thank you
for saving us. God will, unless you return, will face death here. Some even within this
room that have ailments, they've suffered. Some are suffering. We thank you that you're
the great physician, that you're the God who heals. I pray that it would be your will to
heal them, Lord, on this side of eternity, that, Lord, you would and we'd give you the
glory. I pray that in the cases in which they will not have that healing until they cross
over into eternity, that, God, your grace would be evidenced in their lives. That truly,
day by day, moment by moment, they would see and understand that your grace is sufficient.
Bless our time of prayer. I pray that you'd be honored and glorified. For it's in Christ's
name we pray. Amen.