Judges chapter number six, Judges chapter number six.
And for a few months now, we have been dealing
with the subject of looking on Wednesday evenings
at the names of God.
And we looked at Psalm 91 and also at Psalm nine.
And we saw from those two passages of scripture
that those who know the name of the Lord
will put their trust in the Lord.
And what a blessing to know that our God is faithful
and he is trustworthy.
And we've explained over these couple of months
of dealing with this subject.
In fact, we began in January,
so we didn't do it every Wednesday evening.
But we started January 29th,
and we've had the opportunity to look at a number
of the names of God that he gives to us in his word.
And we mentioned that God, he is infinite, right?
And we are finite.
We understand that he transcends us,
that his ways are not our ways, that he's far above
all that we could even begin to comprehend.
And so we find that through the Old Testament,
we find also in the New Testament,
there are many names that are ascribed to our God.
And through those names, he's communicating to us
certain aspects of his attribute, his character,
and helping us to be able to understand those things.
As we come to Judges chapter six this evening,
we'll look at a name that's given to us.
And that name, I'll read verse 23 and 24.
We'll grab some of the context
as we go through the message this evening.
But if you will look in verse 23,
the Lord said unto him, that's speaking to Gideon,
peace be unto thee, fear not, thou shalt not die.
Gideon thought that he would die.
He mentions that as we look at the text
and grab the context of it, because he says,
in verse number 22, I have seen an angel
of the Lord face to face.
So he thought he would die.
And the Lord said unto him, peace be unto thee,
fear not, thou shalt not die.
Verse 24, then Gideon built an altar there unto the Lord
and called it Jehovah Shalom unto this day.
It is yet an ophrah of the Abizurites.
And so as we look at this text of scripture,
God reveals to us a name that's mentioned really here
in its exact context, Jehovah Shalom.
And many of us, we are familiar with that word Shalom.
If you travel the Middle East, you'll hear in Israel,
you hear that very regularly as a greeting
and also as you depart from having conversation
with one another.
And so as we look at this name of God in verse 24,
I've just titled the message Jehovah Shalom.
And it means the Lord is peace.
And many of us are familiar with the life
and ministry of Gideon.
And we find that here as he builds this altar in verse 24,
that that's the name in which he gives the altar.
Let me share with you a definition of peace
that I really like.
And here's the definition.
And I really think there's two parts of the definition.
It really helps us to see the two aspects of peace
that we see within the scriptures.
But here's the definition, the tranquil state of a soul
assured of its salvation through Christ.
And this evening, if you have assurance of your salvation,
you have that peace.
There's a peace that comes with that.
I would say that that's describing for us peace with God.
And we see that phraseology in Romans chapter five.
We'll look at that in just a little while.
But then the definition goes on to say this.
And so fearing nothing from God and content
with its earthly lot of whatsoever sort that is.
And I think the second half of that definition
really is describing for us the peace of God.
And what a blessing to have peace with God,
but then we understand the peace of God.
We often make that reference in that distinction
as we go through the New Testament
and look at those various phraseologies.
And we'll look at a few of those things this evening.
But as we look at our text of scripture here this evening
and look at this name that God provides
and as this Gideon, as he builds this altar
and he names it Jehovah Shalom.
If you're taking notes this evening,
I want you to notice with me first of all,
the absence of peace, the absence of peace.
And we see it specifically, we'll look at two aspects
of this message as we go through with each of the points.
But I want you to see first the absence of peace
for Gideon and for Israel.
The Bible begins in chapter number six
and it says this in verse number one,
and the children of Israel did evil in the sight of the Lord
and the Lord delivered them into the hand of Midian
seven years and the hand of Midian prevailed against Israel.
Because of the Midianites, the children of Israel
made them the dens, which are in the mountains
and caves and strongholds.
And so it was when Israel had sown
that the Midianites came up and the Amalekites
and the children of the East, even they came up against them
and they encamped against them and destroyed
the increase of the earth till thou come unto Gaza
and left no sustenance for Israel,
neither sheep nor ox nor ass for they came up
with their cattle in their tents
and they came as grasshoppers for multitude
for both they and their camels were without number
and they entered into the land to destroy it.
And Israel was greatly impoverished
because of the Midianites and the children of Israel
cried unto the Lord.
That's the setting for Judges chapter number six
as we're introduced in just a few verses
past what I read there in those first six verses
were eventually introduced to Gideon,
the one who builds the altar and the verses
that we looked at by way of introduction.
But we find that as we look at the situation
that Gideon and Israel are dealing with,
that there's an absence of peace,
there's great turmoil, there's great conflict.
The Bible says that they entered into the land
at the end of verse number five to destroy it.
The Bible tells us that when they were trying to go forth
and it says, and when Israel had sown
and when they're coming to the place where they would reap
the Midianites and the Amalekites,
they would come and they would try to take
all of that substance.
And it says that they left no sustenance for Israel,
neither sheep nor ox nor ass at the end of verse number four.
And so what does Israel do?
Well, the Bible says they cried unto the Lord
at the end of verse number six.
And there's an absence of peace for Gideon
and for the people of God in this text of scripture.
We find that as we consider the truth
of an absence of peace and we see it contextually here
with the circumstances and situation
in which they're dealing with,
I would submit to you this evening
that there's an absence of peace with regard to humanity.
Generally speaking, the Bible says in Isaiah 48 in verse 22,
there is no peace, saith the Lord, unto the wicked.
And we see that repeated again in Isaiah 57.
And we find that the world,
as we would even understand in our own lives
and considering that definition
that we use by way of introduction,
that prior to salvation, I had no peace.
And the reality is that oftentimes we'll speak
of the time of before we trusted Christ
of having no peace and no hope and no direction.
And the reality is that humanity for lost people,
there is an absence of peace.
And you experienced that before you got saved.
If you're here this evening and you're not saved,
you don't know the Lord Jesus Christ, your personal savior,
you too at this moment would understand
that absence of peace.
And so many people are trying to find peace
in so many different areas.
They think that peace is found in the absence of trouble.
They think that if there could just be a,
my problems are dealt with,
but the reality is that having peace with God
only comes through the Lord Jesus Christ.
And we'll deal with that in just a moment.
But we see with humanity, I mentioned Isaiah 48,
but look at the New Testament, if you will,
the book of Romans.
We'll look at a couple of verses in Romans
and then also in the book of Ephesians.
Look in Romans first with me in chapter number five.
And again, dealing with this absence of peace,
Gideon experienced it.
The nation of Israel experienced it
in Judges chapter number six.
And we find that the announcement from the Lord
in verse 23 is peace.
And then he builds an altar and he names it Jehovah Shalom,
the Lord is peace.
And we find that in Romans chapter number five,
begin looking in verse number eight,
the Bible says, but God commended his love toward us
in that while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us.
Much more than being now justified by his blood,
we shall be saved from wrath through him.
For if when we were enemies, you see that?
When we were enemies, we were against God,
we were reconciled to God by the death of his son,
much more being reconciled, we shall be saved by his life.
And we talked about in the book of 2 Corinthians
in recent weeks, as we've studied through the book,
that ministry of reconciliation
and the fact that we have been reconciled
then is entrusted to us the ministry of reconciliation.
And what was the need?
Why was there a need to be reconciled?
Because we were at variance, we were at enemy of God,
we are sin separated us from God and we had no peace.
And there's an absence of peace.
We find in Ephesians chapter number two,
the Bible tells us and we'll look at this passage
a couple of times this evening,
I wanna look at just verses 11 and 12,
as we consider this thought of the absence of peace.
Notice what the Bible says in Ephesians two,
beginning in verse number 11.
He says, wherefore, remember, he's writing to save people,
the church at Ephesus is the church
that's being written this epistle.
He's writing to save people.
He talks about in the beginning of chapter number two,
about their conversion,
for by grace are you saved through faith.
He mentions in verse number eight,
just a couple of verses earlier,
but then he says in verse number 11,
wherefore, remember,
You know, there are times in which we, too, remember what we were, the state we were in before we got saved.
And notice what he says, that ye, being in time past Gentiles in the flesh, who are called uncircumcision,
by that which is called the circumcision in the flesh made by hands, that at that time ye were without Christ,
being aliens from the commonwealth of Israel and strangers from the covenants of promise,
having no hope and without God in the world.
The Bible doesn't specifically say in verses 11 and 12 that we have no peace,
but I do not believe that it's a stretch for us to say that there's an absence of peace prior to salvation,
for we find in just a couple of verses the Bible says that He is our peace in verse number 14,
and we'll look at that in just a moment.
But we find that as we look at this passage of Scripture and dealing with the name of God, Jehovah Shalom,
and the Lord is peace, and we see that Gideon and the people of Israel,
they were dealing with some real situations, circumstances where there was no peace,
there was turmoil, there was hostility, there was destruction, and they had no peace.
And then Gideon has this experience where the Lord appears to him and says,
Gideon, thou mighty man of valor, and Gideon is now thinking that he's going to die,
and the Lord says, peace, peace, and he makes that altar.
The Lord is peace, Jehovah Shalom.
See, for us this evening, we've experienced, if you're saved tonight, you've been,
you can recall when you were lost, and you can recall, you can know when you had no peace.
And the reality is that there's many that are around us today that there's still an absence of peace.
There's an absence of peace.
But I want you to consider with me the announcement of peace, the announcement of peace.
I've alluded to it already in Judges chapter 6, and we look back in the text.
I read the first six verses by looking at that absence of peace.
We find it as we continue reading in the text of Scripture.
I'll look here, look with me in verse number 12.
And the angel of the Lord appeared unto him and said unto him,
The Lord is with thee, thou mighty man of valor.
Gideon said unto him, O my Lord, if the Lord be with us, why then is all this befallen us?
And where be all his miracles, which our fathers told us of, saying,
Did not the Lord bring us up from Egypt?
But now the Lord hath forsaken us and delivered us into the hands of the Midianites.
And we understand, as Gideon is asking that, that they're not aware of the fact that
these are the consequences of their evil behavior,
the judgment that God was meting out to them because of their disobedience.
In verse 14, And the Lord looked upon him and said,
Go in this thy mind, and thou shalt save Israel from the hand of the Midianites.
Have not I sent thee?
And he, Gideon, said unto him, O my Lord, wherewith shall I save Israel?
Behold, my family is poor in Manasseh, and I am the least in my father's house.
And the Lord said unto him, Surely I will be with thee.
Thou shalt smite the Midianites as one man.
And he said unto him, If now I have found grace in thy sight,
then show me a sign that thou talkest with me.
Notice what Gideon requests in verse 18.
Depart not hence, I pray thee, until I come unto thee and bring forth my present.
And said it before thee, And he said, I will tarry until thou come again.
And Gideon went in and made ready a kid and unleavened cakes of an ephah flower.
The flesh he put in a basket, and he put the broth in a pot,
and brought it out unto him under the oak and presented it.
The angel of God said unto him, Take the flesh and the unleavened cakes,
and lay them upon this rock, and pour out the broth.
And he did so.
Then the angel of the Lord put forth the end of the staff that was in his hand
and touched the flesh and the unleavened cakes.
And there rose up fire out of the rock and consumed the flesh and the unleavened cakes.
Then the angel of the Lord departed out of his sight.
What an experience.
This is a faith builder for Gideon.
That's not really the focus of the message this evening.
But we find that God is building Gideon's faith.
And Gideon experiences this.
And notice the response in verse 22.
And when Gideon perceived that he was an angel of the Lord, Gideon said,
Alas, O Lord God, for because I have seen an angel of the Lord face to face.
And we find that the Lord says unto him in verse 23 that we read a moment ago,
and this is the announcement of peace to Gideon,
Is peace be unto thee.
Fear not, thou shalt not die.
So we find this announcement of peace.
What a great announcement this was.
As we consider the place where Gideon is, the absence of peace that they're experiencing in the land
with regard to the Midianites and all that's taking place.
But then even through this experience that he's having,
and he sees this fire rise up out of the rock and consume the flesh and the unleavened cakes,
he perceives that it was an angel of the Lord, and he just thinks he's going to die.
And the Lord, you see in verse number 23, it's L-O-R-D, all capitalized, Jehovah.
He says to him, Peace be unto thee.
What a great message. A message of peace.
The announcement that Gideon receives.
And Gideon responds to that announcement by building the altar and calling it Jehovah Shalom.
And what a blessing to see the impact, no doubt,
when God says peace, and then he names the altar that he builds Jehovah Shalom.
It was impactful.
This announcement to Gideon was an impactful truth that God was revealing to his servant.
But I want you to be reminded this evening that just as there was an absence of peace for Gideon and the people of Israel,
there was an absence of peace for humanity.
Just as there's an announcement of peace for Gideon, there's an announcement of peace to humanity.
Notice with me, if you will, in the book of Isaiah.
And I know that we're familiar with the verse of scripture, but I want you to see it.
In Isaiah chapter 9, and then we'll look over in the New Testament at a couple of passages as well.
Isaiah chapter number 9, a great prophecy that God gives to us.
And we see that in this passage there's, of course, just a messianic prophecy that's given to us that is so precious.
And look at with verse number 6, the Bible says,
For unto us a child is born, unto us a son is given,
and the government shall be upon his shoulder, and his name shall be called Wonderful, Counselor,
the mighty God, the everlasting Father, notice, the Prince of Peace.
Of the increase of his government and peace there shall be no end.
The Lord of David and upon his kingdom, to order it, to establish it with judgment, with justice,
from henceforth even forever, the zeal of the Lord of hosts will perform this.
And so we see that in verse number 6, as the name is given again,
even dealing with looking at the names of the Lord in this messianic prophecy,
that he shall be called Wonderful, Counselor, the mighty God, the everlasting Father, the Prince of Peace.
We're familiar, of course, with the account in Luke of the birth of Christ.
And as we look at that particular account, we know that in the announcement that is given,
the Bible says, Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace, goodwill toward men.
Jesus Christ, God in flesh, we understand the incarnation,
we understand his birth as it's recorded in chapter number 2 of the book of Luke.
And we find that now as we're thinking about and considering the announcement of peace
and the way in which there was this absence for Gideon and Israel, but an absence for humanity.
But then there's an announcement to Gideon and God gives an announcement to all of his creation
that the Prince of Peace, Messiah, is going to come.
The angels announce the birth and they say peace, and on earth peace, goodwill toward men.
But I also want to remind you of this.
Look at the book of Romans, if you will, in chapter number 10.
And as we consider the announcement of peace and just the privilege that we have,
you know, it's quite interesting as you study through the New Testament in particular,
you find many times that the Bible refers to God as the God of peace.
And he is the one that gives peace.
It is his peace.
Many people around the world, we see it even today,
we hear of it so often of peace agreements and treaties and all of these sorts of things.
And the reality is that true peace is found in the person of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And we find this announcement, notice in Romans 10, verse 13,
a familiar verse of scripture to us,
for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved.
How then shall they call on him in whom they have not believed?
And how shall they believe in him of whom they have not heard?
And how shall they hear without a preacher?
What's the preacher supposed to preach?
Well, he's supposed to preach the gospel,
going into all the world and preach the gospel to every creature.
We read that in Mark's gospel as the summary of the Great Commission is given.
And we understand that they went everywhere in Acts chapter number eight,
preaching the word.
What was it that they were preaching?
Well, they're preaching the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And so here it says, how shall they hear without a preacher?
How shall they preach, verse 15, except they be sent?
But I want you to notice in verse 15, the Bible says,
as it is written, how beautiful are the feet of them that preach,
what does it say?
The gospel of peace.
The gospel of peace and bring glad tidings of good things.
I understand that oftentimes as we try to engage in evangelism,
and try to preach the gospel,
that many people reject the message.
They do not believe that it's a gospel of peace,
that it's good tidings,
but we know the truth of God's word,
and we know that the gospel, it is,
as it's described here in Romans 10 and verse 15,
that it's the gospel of peace.
How can a man have peace with God?
How can a man, Job asked the question,
be justified with God?
How can a man have peace with God?
You know, the reality is that you find
throughout the centuries,
you can read accounts of individuals
making these types of statements of,
how can I have peace with God?
They come near the end of their lives,
and there's an absence of peace.
There's no assurance.
There's great turmoil,
and we find that they ask that question,
how can I have peace?
Then oftentimes, as I've heard many people say,
even to me, I've made my peace with God.
You ever hear somebody say that?
I've heard it far too often.
And anytime someone says to me,
I've made my peace with God,
I ask them if they can explain that to me.
What does it mean that you've made your peace with God?
How did you do that?
What was that process?
Help me understand.
Unfortunately, I've never had anyone
that has said I've made my peace with God
give me a good answer
with regard to what that means
to have peace, that they've made peace with God.
But we know from Romans 5
that there's only one way,
as I mentioned a moment ago,
to have peace with God,
and that's through the Lord Jesus Christ.
We don't bargain with God, amen?
We don't bargain with God.
God has set forth, here's truth.
Amen?
Here's the way.
We don't bargain with God.
So we find that there's this announcement of peace.
Can you imagine this evening,
as we think about Gideon in that circumstance,
in that situation,
how relieved he must have been
to have heard those words,
how impactful it must have been.
But then we think about humanity.
We think about that Messianic prophecy
in the book of Isaiah,
and to understand that Messiah,
Jesus was gonna come,
and one of the names that is ascribed to him
is this Prince of Peace.
We think about those in Luke 2
that heard the angels give the announcement of peace,
and then the privilege that we have,
those of us that have been saved by the grace of God,
to go forth and to preach the gospel of peace.
What a great privilege that we have.
To announce to people that have no peace,
where there's an absence of peace,
that we know Jehovah Shalom,
we know that the Lord is peace,
and we understand the truth of the entirety of the Bible
as we look from the old to the new,
and we see the Trinity provided to us,
and we understand that Jesus Christ,
God in flesh, that he came,
and he is our peace.
What a blessing.
So we see the absence,
we see the announcement.
Then I want you to consider with me
as we conclude this evening,
the assurance of peace with God.
The assurance of peace with God.
The word assurance carries with it
the idea of having full confidence.
We ask somebody, are you sure?
Have you ever go through a situation,
and I did this with Fernando,
kind of just messing with him a few weeks ago
on discipleship, and I told him,
I said, Fernando, when you pulled in,
there was a vehicle in the parking lot.
I said, did you see it?
And he's like, yeah.
I said, are you sure?
He's like, yeah.
And I said, Fernando, what kind of vehicle was it?
And he told me.
I said, what color was the vehicle?
And he told me, and I said,
are you sure that was the color?
And he's like, I mean, I'm pretty,
do you remember this?
He's like, you're kind of messing with me, right?
And I was doing it on purpose
to just kind of help him.
Listen, when we're talking about assurance of salvation,
nobody should be able to talk you out of assurance.
Amen?
For I know whom I have believed.
And we understand that whosoever shall call upon
the name of the Lord shall be saved.
We understand that God who promised eternal life,
he cannot lie.
And we have that assurance.
And I want you to understand this evening
as we look at the absence and the announcement of peace,
that we can have the assurance of peace with God,
having that full confidence.
You're there in Romans 10,
back up, if you will, to Romans chapter five.
And we mentioned in verses eight through 10 a moment ago,
but we see that the passage begins in verse number one,
therefore, being justified by faith,
we have peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ.
What a blessing.
I can remember when I did not have peace with God.
I can remember it.
I didn't understand all of the enmity
and that I was an enemy of God.
I didn't understand all of that,
but I knew I didn't have peace with God.
But now I have that assurance of peace with God.
And it's not in anything that I've done justified by faith.
He says, we have peace with God
through our Lord Jesus Christ.
Over the book of Ephesians,
and we looked at verses 11 and 12 earlier,
but look at verse 13 and following with me
in Ephesians chapter number two.
And I want you to,
as we try to package this together this evening,
as we consider Jehovah Shalom, the Lord is peace,
we begin to understand that there was in your life
a time of absence of peace,
and then someone announced to you the gospel of peace.
And now you're to have that assurance of peace with God.
And we find that in Ephesians two, beginning in verse 13,
remember in verses 11 and 12,
that at that time, remember in your past,
remember what you were having no hope without God,
but verse 13, but now in Christ Jesus,
ye who sometimes were far off
are made nigh by the blood of Christ.
Notice this phrase, for he, Jesus Christ, is our peace.
Praise God.
Who hath made both one and hath broken down
the middle wall of partition between us.
We're at enmity with God.
We're at variance with God.
Why?
Because of my sin, because of your sin.
It says in verse 15, having abolished in his flesh,
the enmity, even the law of commandments
contained in ordinances for to make in himself
of twain one new man, so making what?
Making peace.
And then he might reconcile both unto God
in one body by the cross,
having slain the enmity thereby
and came and preached peace to you,
which were far off and to them that were nigh.
And we rejoice, it says in verse 19,
now therefore ye are no more strangers and foreigners,
but fellow citizens with the saints
and with the household of God.
The book of Colossians in the first chapter,
we find that Paul mentions the same concept and idea
to the believers in Colossae as he's writing to them
about their position in Christ
and he's praying for them in the beginning portion
of Colossians one and he tells them in verse 14
of Colossians one, in whom we have redemption
through his blood, even the forgiveness of sins,
who is the image of the invisible God,
the firstborn of every creature,
for by him were all things created that are in heaven
and that are in earth, visible and invisible,
whether they be thrones or dominions
or principalities or powers,
all things were created by him and for him
and he is before all things and by him all things consist
and he is the head of the body, the church,
who is the beginning, the firstborn from the dead,
that in all things he might have the preeminence
for it pleased the father that in him
should all fullness dwell, then notice this in verse 20,
and having made peace through the blood of his cross,
by him to reconcile all things unto himself,
by him I say, whether they be things in earth
or things in heaven and so we see again,
he made peace, he provided that peace,
made it available to us, how?
Through the blood of his cross
and we now have that assurance this evening,
if you're saved tonight, when you pillow your head,
you ought to have that peace, peace with God,
that I know that I belong to Jesus,
that I know that I'm going to heaven
whenever I take that final breath
and what a joy to have peace with God,
to have the assurance that God hath said.
So often when you talk to people
about whether they think they're gonna go to heaven
when they die, so often you hear people talk about,
well, you know, I hope so, I think so
and I've done this and I'm doing this
and I'm trying this and so on and so forth
and the reality is that I'm thankful,
listen, that philosophy gives no peace,
it gives no rest because the question
is always lingering in the mind of the individual
of how do I really know if I've done enough?
How do I know if that bad thing I did
canceled out a lot of those good things
that I was doing and it makes the individual
the authority instead of the word of God
being the authority, this evening we can have peace.
have the assurance of peace with God,
not because of what we think or what we're doing,
but because of what God said in his word.
And what a joy this evening.
Now I want you to consider with me as we look in Judges 6,
and we're not gonna go back there,
but we find that that announcement is given
where the Lord says, peace, and fear not, thou shalt not die.
And then Gideon goes and he builds this altar
and he calls it Jehovah Shalom, the Lord is peace.
And when we understand this evening,
the absence, the announcement,
having the assurance of peace with God,
the reality is, as we mentioned the definition
by way of introduction this evening,
that peace is the tranquil state of a soul
assured of its salvation through Christ,
and that's peace with God.
But the definition goes on to say,
and so fearing nothing from God
and content with its earthly lot
of whatsoever sort that is,
that's the peace of God.
In this evening, if we have peace with God,
we ought to have the peace of God.
There's a lot of people today, save people,
that have peace with God.
There's a lot of turmoil.
They don't have the peace of God.
There's a lot of difficulty they're dealing with
and they don't have that peace,
that sweet assurance.
We're talking about the peace of God
that is described in Philippians four and verse seven
as the peace of God which passeth all understanding.
That opportunity where we allow,
as the book of Colossians says in chapter three
and verse 15, to allow the peace of God
to rule in our hearts,
that I'm not gonna be driven by emotions,
I'm not going to allow the circumstances,
the ups and downs, the valleys and the mountains
of my life to dictate that peace.
No, I have the peace with God,
but I have the peace of God
and I'm going to allow the peace of God
to rule in my heart.
We find this evening that Jesus gives us wonderful truth
in the gospel of John and we'll finish with this tonight
as we look at two verses in John.
Look at John 14 if you will.
And this is a favorite verse of scripture of mine.
I love how Jesus is speaking to the disciples here
before he would go to the cross
and we find that in these few chapters
in the book of John, he's giving them so much information
and we'll look at a verse here
and then at the end of this discourse,
really in chapter 16, we'll look at another verse,
but look at what the Bible says in John 14.
In verse number 27, notice what Jesus says.
Peace I leave with you.
But then I want you to get this.
He says, my peace, my peace, I give unto you.
Not as the world giveth, give I unto you.
Let not your heart be troubled, neither let it be afraid.
Jesus, God in flesh, he's told them
at the end of chapter 13,
he had told them plenty of times before that,
but he made it abundantly clear
that he's going to go to Jerusalem,
he's gonna be crucified, he's gonna go to the cross,
he's going to die, he's going to be buried,
he's going to rise again.
He says, let not your heart be troubled.
We understand the impact immediately
that this message and this discussion had on the disciples
and so he tells them to let not their heart be troubled.
He's giving them truth.
He tells them of things that will transpire and take place.
He tells them of sending the comfort of the Holy Ghost
and he says that I'm gonna give you my peace.
He's gonna continue in this discourse
in the gospel of John and in chapter 15,
he's gonna talk to them about the world hating them
and he's gonna tell them that if the world hates you,
you know that it hated me before it hated you.
He's gonna tell them that if the world,
if we were of the world, that the world would love his own.
He tells them in chapter 16
that whosoever killeth you
will think that he doeth God's service.
He's letting them know of some things
that are going to come but I want you to understand
how he ends this discourse in chapter 16 in verse 33.
He says these things in John 16 in verse 33,
these things, all of these chapters, 14, 15, 16,
really 13 through 16, these things I have spoken unto you
that in me ye might have peace.
In me ye might have peace.
Notice, in the world ye shall have tribulation.
Have you experienced it?
Sure you have, you live for any just a moment in time
and you know that in the world ye shall have tribulation.
But he says this, but be of good cheer.
I have overcome the world.
So the question this evening,
when we look at this name of God, Jehovah Shalom,
the Lord is peace and we see contextually
in Judges chapter six that there's an absence of peace,
there's an announcement of peace
and we find that Gideon responds to that
by building an altar and calling the name of that altar
Jehovah Shalom, the Lord is peace.
But we find that for humanity,
there's an absence of peace.
But there's an announcement of peace.
And we, as the ones that have peace with God
are entrusted to preach the gospel of peace.
To those who have no peace, we have the gospel of peace
to share with them, to give them
so that they can understand how they can have peace
with God and then we are to live
as those that have peace with God were to live
with the peace of God ruling in our hearts
because the Lord is peace.
And he said, I'm telling you all these things.
Listen, there's some hard things to deal with.
They're gonna hate you.
They're gonna kill you.
You're gonna deal with these things.
You're gonna face this opposition.
But he says, I'm telling you these things
that in me you might have peace.
Listen, peace, it is a lie.
There's so many people that have the idea
that peace is only found in the absence of trouble.
It's not true.
Peace is found in the person of the Lord Jesus Christ.
In the presence of the Lord.
You can have all kinds of turmoil
and chaos going on around you.
In the world, you shall have tribulation.
But in me, Jesus said, my peace give I unto you.
We can have that peace.
Listen, as the people of God saved, redeemed, reconciled,
the Lord is my peace.
The reality is that we ought to live in this world
as we deal with whatever we deal with
with allowing the peace of God to rule in our hearts.
Why?
Because my God's in control.
And my God doeth all things well.
He knows exactly where I am.
He knows exactly what's going on.
He knows exactly what I need.
And he is able.
He is able, amen.
We sing the song, he is able to deliver thee.
Every time we sing the song, I think about Daniel.
And then I'm reminded that he's able to deliver me
from what, from anything.
He's able.
Sometimes he chooses to deliver us through something
instead of from something.
And in fact, I've learned in my life
that when he delivers me through something,
I learn a whole lot more about who my God is
and how great he is when he delivers me through the storm.
Jehovah shalom.
The Lord is peace.
Do you have peace with God tonight?
You know for sure that heaven's your home.
You have peace with God.
If you do, are you allowing the peace of God
to rule in your hearts?
In me, you shall have peace.
The world, you're gonna have tribulation.
We see it, we understand it.
But are we allowing the peace of God
which passeth all understanding
to truly rule in our hearts?
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for your word.
We thank you for the fact that you are our peace.
God, if there's one that's not saved tonight,
I pray that you'd help them to understand
before they leave this place that they need to be saved.
There's no other way to have peace with God
except through the Lord Jesus Christ.
It's through the blood of his cross
that mankind, humanity, can have peace with thee.
Lord, for those of us that know you
as our personal Lord and Savior,
we would say that we have that assurance of peace with you.
Lord, help us to live each day
with the peace of God ruling in our hearts.
Bless our time of prayer.
We thank you for it.
We pray that you'd be honored and glorified