Chapter number one, verses 24 and 25,
will be the focus of our study this evening
as we study the days of creation.
I believe that we are continually reminded
of God's power and God's wisdom.
I am certainly thankful that we serve a God
who is omnipotent, that he has all power,
but in having all power, it's necessary also
that he has all wisdom, and he is omniscient.
We're thankful for that, and we see the harmony
of God's character even through creation
as we understand the power and wisdom of God.
We're reminded so often as we read the Genesis account
in the first chapter, and then even as we study
other portions of scripture that deal
with the creation account, how God said, and it was so.
It's so powerful to see in this chapter
how the Lord and the power of his word,
and what a blessing it is, and we, of course,
have made note throughout our study of the book of Genesis,
and still here in the first chapter,
as we've looked at creation, we've made note
of the word and that is used in this chapter,
and it helps us understand the successive nature
of the events that are recorded for us
to help us understand that God created everything
in six literal 24-hour days.
These were not ages or periods of time,
some undetermined length of time.
These were six 24-hour days, literal days.
We find that often he'll use that phraseology,
the evening and the morning were the first day,
the second day, so on and so forth,
and so we understand through the text of scripture.
It's also important to know that the Lord,
as he would speak to his people,
and as he would give them a pattern for their work week
and establish the Sabbath for Israel,
you'd understand that he would refer back
to the week of creation as being the example
that he speaks of because in six days he created all things,
but on day seven, he rested, and he used that pattern
for the nation of Israel to understand
that they too were to work for six days
and then rest on the seventh.
As we look at the sixth day of creation this evening,
we look at this passage of scripture,
really just looking at verses 24 and 25 this evening
because really there are two monumental things
that take place on day number six.
The first creative action, activity, if you will,
that takes place on day number six
is that of creating animal life,
life on earth proper.
Those animals that are mentioned in verses 24 and 25,
and we'll deal with that, land-based animals here
in just a moment throughout the evening tonight.
But the other monumental event that took place
on day number six was that God created man
and the crown of his creation,
and we will spend at least an entire service
dealing with that aspect of the sixth day.
In fact, we could look at just the statements
that are mentioned in the account of how God made man,
and we could spend a number of weeks
just in those few verses of scripture
and deal with so many of the issues
that we face in our society today
and how they're answered very simply
by understanding what God told us
in the very first chapter of his book.
And it's amazing how that we have thrown it out
as a society, as a culture,
and we have found ourselves in a mess
where people just can't seem to answer questions
that are so obvious, blatantly obvious,
and God's given us the record.
And so we'll spend at least an entire message next week
on that second activity that took place there
during the sixth day of creation.
So our focus here will be on the land-based animals.
It's interesting, even before we get into verses 24 and 25,
just to kind of rehearse, recap, if you will,
it's been a few weeks since we've been
in the book of Genesis and studying the days of creation.
We remember that on day number one there,
as it's recorded in verses one through five,
that God said, let there be light, and there was light.
We find that that was the energy
that God created in the beginning there.
And we find that on day number two,
he caused the firmament to be made.
And it says that he made the firmament,
divided the waters which were under the firmament
from the waters which are above the firmament, it was so.
And that was done on day number two,
according to verses six through eight.
As we continue looking through the days of creation,
we find that on day number three,
that God had formed the sea, the dry land, and plant life.
And we find that then on day number four,
the sun, the moon, and the stars.
And I know I enjoy saying this
because it's just powerful to me,
how that on verse number 16, the last five verses,
it simply says this, he made the stars also.
And there are billions and billions of stars,
and he simply records it as saying,
he made the stars also.
Isn't that amazing?
I mean, our God is so wonderful.
He transcends us.
We find that that's what we did on day number four.
Day number five, sea life and fowls,
as we studied in our last lesson,
and we understand how that he created those.
And then today, of course, getting into day number six,
land-based animals, and then as he made man.
But it's interesting as we think about the fact
that our God is a God of order and a God of plan.
We find that he formed the sea on day number three,
but then it was on day number five
that he filled it with life.
We find, again, that on day number two,
when he separated the firmament,
of course, the heavens from the heaven,
and so on and so forth, the waters were separated,
that he made the sky there,
as we would call it, as one of the heavens.
And we find that then he would fill it with life
on day number five.
And then we find that it was there on day number three
that he formed the dry land,
and it was there that the dry land appeared,
according to verses nine and 10.
And then on verses 11 and 12,
it talks about how there on day number three,
he brought forth vegetation.
Now that vegetation that was brought forth,
as we find here in the text of scripture,
is that that was the food source
for that which he would later create.
We find that he mentions that at the end of the chapter,
in verse number 30, it says,
unto every beast of the earth,
and every fowl of the air,
and to everything that creepeth upon the earth,
wherein there is life,
I have given every green herb for meat.
And it was so.
And then on day six, as we begin our study here,
we find that he made the land animals.
And so you see the order of our God,
how that as he's creating,
as we go through the chapter,
how that each aspect of the creation,
it's sustaining that would be created next.
And how powerful that is for us to understand.
In first Corinthians 14 and 40,
the Bible says let all things be done decently and in order.
And we understand that our God is a God of order,
even as we find here in the Genesis record of creation.
Verse 24, the Bible says this,
and God said, let the earth bring forth
the living creature after his kind,
cattle and creeping thing and beast of the earth
after his kind, and it was so.
And God made the beast of the earth after his kind
and cattle after their kind
and everything that creepeth upon the earth after his kind.
And God saw that it was good.
I'm reminded of a verse that we've referenced
on a number of occasion, Psalm 104, verses 24 and 25,
where the psalmist declares,
O Lord, how manifold are thy works!
In wisdom hast thou made them all.
The earth is full of thy riches.
So is this great and wide sea.
We're in our things creeping, innumerable,
both small and great beast.
And of course, we're reminded
of several other passages of scripture.
Psalm 19, the Bible speaks about,
the heavens declare the glory of God.
The firmament showeth forth his handiwork.
What a blessing it is to see here
how that God is revealing, once again,
his power and his wisdom.
Notice with me, first of all, the declaration, if you will.
In verse number 24, once again,
we see that oft-repeated phrase
throughout Genesis chapter number one,
where the Bible begins and simply says,
and God said.
We find that the power of his word, once again,
is evident here in the text of scripture.
And you notice that the Bible says,
and God said, let the earth bring forth
the living creature after his kind.
And so we find that God, he's created the earth.
We find in previous days of creation,
we've just rehearsed them and reviewed them.
And we understand that now, as he stands there,
as God is creating there in this first week,
he says, he speaks, and we see the power, again,
of his word in Psalm 33.
The Bible tells us there in verses six through nine,
a powerful passage of scripture.
And the psalmist declares, he spake and it was done.
The complete context of the quote there in Psalm 33,
in verse number six, it says, by the word of the Lord
were the heavens made, and all the host of them
by the breath of his mouth.
He gathered the waters of the sea together as in heap.
He layeth up the depth in storehouses.
Let all the earth fear the Lord.
Let all the inhabitants of the world stand in awe of him,
for he spake and it was done.
He commanded and it stood fast.
I think about the ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ,
and I think about the time in which
he's walking upon the earth,
and we see that he would reveal his power to his disciples,
and to obviously many of those within the land of Israel
during his life and ministry here upon earth.
And often through the study of the miracles,
you would find that the Lord Jesus Christ
was revealing his power,
and how often he would reveal his power
with just a spoken word.
Amen?
He does.
just simply say it. He just simply speak it. And as he would speak it, as he would
speak the words, you would see the power. I'm reminded there even as we look at
the creation and we find how that God would speak to His creation and His
creation always obeys the Creator. The only part of creation that does not
always obey the Creator is man. And we find that here God reminds us of the
power of His Word. This phrase is used throughout the passage of Scripture,
and God said. He spake and it was done. He said, let the earth bring forth. Notice
in verse 24, He says, let the earth bring forth the living creature after His kind,
cattle and creeping thing, and beast of the earth after His kind. And it was so.
We find that in verse number 25 that the Bible then says, and God made. He made the
beast of the earth after His kind and cattle after their kind and everything
that creepeth on the earth after His kind and God saw that it was good. As we'd
understand the context and what the Lord is dealing with as He's revealing to us
here His power and creation, we'd find that there in verse number 25 that God
is making, He is forming these land-based animals that we're looking at this
evening, and He's forming them from that which had been created earlier on. When
God created earlier on in the first few days of creation, we find that He uses
those elements that were created and now He's making the beast of the earth
after His kind, cattle after their kind, everything that creepeth upon the earth
after His kind, and God saw that it was good. And so we first see the declaration
of God. I'm thankful that God's power is revealed through His Word. I'm thankful
that God's declared some things to us, aren't you? I'm thankful that He's
declared the truth of creation, but I'm thankful that He's declared for us the
truth of redemption. I'm thankful that He's declared to us His love for us. We sang
in Sunday school this morning about my Savior's love, oh how marvelous, oh how
wonderful is my Savior's love to me. The reason that we know that is because He
declared His love to us, and He spoke, and we think about the spoken Word of God, the
power of His Word. We're thankful to have the written Word of God that we're able
to go to and read it and study it and memorize it, meditate upon it, and we're
able to understand and have the mind of the Lord, and we're able to have, as we
look at the Word of God, so often it is referenced, and God said, or thus saith
the Lord. And we find that God has recorded and given us His Word. Here in
the creation account, once again we're reminded of the declaration. I want you
to notice, however, as we think of these land-based animals, I want you to
notice the distinction that God makes in verses 24 and 25. He makes this
distinction, and really, in verses 24 and 25, He is speaking in broad terms or
categories that He would use in distinguishing the types of animals that
He's creating on day number six. Now we understand that there are charts and all
sorts of things that you could go to in science, and you could see how that man
has come up with all of these charts of families and species and so on and so
forth, but we find here that God has given us, in verses 24 and 25, on day
number six, the three broad categories, if you will, of that which He created of
land-based animals. Now we understand, and I mentioned this in a previous message,
and I think it's worth repeating this evening, that God is omniscient, He's
omnipotent, He's the one that did all of that which is recorded in Genesis 1, and
if He had chosen to give us every minute detail on how He did it, He certainly
could have. Amen? Because He did it. So He knows what He did, and He could have
given us every single detail of every single jot and tittle of all that He did
here in this week of creation. But the reality is that these first 25 verses
that are mentioned, they contain the record of all that was created other
than man. And then you see the crowning of His creation with man, and then you
start to see God's interaction with man throughout the whole of Scripture. And
you find, of course, yes, the fall of man early on in Genesis 3, and you understand
the plan of redemption that is given and provided for Adam and Eve, and then of
course the prophecies and so on and so forth, but you find that God is not
giving us every minute detail, not because He couldn't, but because He's
giving us what He wants us to have. And the emphasis of the Word of God is not
so much how did God make this certain little thing, but in God making man in
His image, by the way, the only thing that's been created in His image is
mankind, we find that God then shows us throughout the whole of Scripture how
man will interact with God. It's amazing. That's the focus of the Scriptures,
that's what God wants us to have, and we find that He does tell us that He
created and He provides for us that which He determines necessary for us to
have, but we find in these three broad categories that are mentioned or terms
that God uses, notice with me, we'll look at verse number 25, and God
made the beast of the earth after His kind and cattle after their kind and
everything that creepeth upon the earth after His kind, and God saw that it was
good. And so we find that in verses 24 and 25, the order of the three
distinctions or terms that He uses are slightly changed. It's still the same
three categories, but they're not in the same order, for in verse number 24, He
says, let the earth bring forth the living creature after His kind, cattle
and creeping thing and beast of the earth after His kind. And so in verse 24,
He deals with cattle, creeping thing, and then the beast of the earth, but in verse
number 25, He says, beast of the earth, cattle, and everything that creepeth.
There's no discrepancy there, I'm just sharing with you that it's
showing us that this is what God did. These are the terms that He used, the
categories by which He established. And so if we look there in verse number 24,
we see the first one that's mentioned when He says, let the earth bring forth
the living creature after His kind, cattle. Now, when He speaks about this
general term, it's a general term that broadly refers to any animal that would
be domesticated, used for various things. You find this term that's used throughout
the Pentateuch in a lot of references to not only dietary things, but also parts
of the law and offerings and so on and so forth. But we find that really when
He's speaking here and He uses this term, we could think of it in the terms of that
which would be domesticated. We find here this evening, as we think of all of the
land animals, there are certain animals. Now, I'm not a pet person, okay? If you're
a pet person, don't get upset with me. I'm just not. And I know there's some
people that are and some people that aren't. I'm not against you if you are, so
don't be against me if I'm not. But the reality, I'm just serious, amen? Praise
Tony's giving me an amen back there, right? And listen, the reality here, people
have been trying to give me dogs for I don't know how many years. And Doc will
joke with me every once in a while, but I got some friends that raise dogs and
kind of have it as a supplemental income thing, and I'm like, I got kids, man. I
don't need dogs, you know? But the reality is that I'm just not a pet person, but if
you are, that's not a problem. But there are certain things that you have as pets
and there's certain other things that you don't have as pets, right? Now, we
know there's some crazy people, amen? Some of us are crazy people, but there
are some crazy people that try to have things for pets that were never intended
to be pets, amen? Rattlesnakes were not intended to be pets. Praise the Lord,
amen? And then when those guys are trying to feed their snakes and they get bit
and they die, they want you to be sorry for them. And it's like, what were you
thinking, right? There's certain, so domesticated animals. So we're not going
to go through a list. There are thousands and thousands and thousands of species
of land animals. There's no way we could exhaust it this evening, but we find that
the broad categories that God would deal with, as he would use this word cattle
here in verse number 24, and again in verse number 25, keep in mind and have in
the thought of your mind those animals which would generally refer in broad
terms to those animals that we would consider domesticated animals. He then
says creeping things. I don't need to say a whole lot about creeping things, amen?
And y'all know what some creeping things are, right? And creatures that move on the
earth or at least very close to it. Again, it's a broad category and the number of
species is very broad that you could deal with of dealing with the creeping
thing. The reality is that most people don't like creeping things, right? I mean
most people are generally not going to be very favorable or fond of creeping
things. In fact, there are some screams and yells and all sorts of various sounds
that you will hear from people when there are creeping things around. And
it's interesting, even this afternoon as we got in the car to leave, one of our
children says, quick, a napkin! I need it now! And there was a creeping thing and
they didn't want the creeping thing near them and they quickly needed to have
some relief. And the other children, I won't mention who it was, but the other
two are saying, get it quickly, hurry! Right? Because they don't want it to get
away and then it's creeping somewhere else, you know what I mean? And so we find
here creeping things is mentioned as the second.
second broad category. Then the third category that God uses in the distinction here, he
says in verse 24, let the earth bring forth the living creature after his kind, cattle,
the creeping thing, and beast of the earth after his kind, and it was so. And so we find
here the third category that God uses, the beast of the earth. He uses it again in verse
25, and God made the beast of the earth after his kind, and cattle after their kind, everything
that creepeth upon the earth after his kind, and so we find that third category of the
beast of the earth. The category of animals, I would simply categorize it this way, that
are not typically domesticated. They don't fall in the category of cattle, they don't
fall in the category of creeping thing, and so it's those things that would not be typically
domesticated. As you read the word of God, you find in the book of Job in particular
that there are references to what we would call today dinosaurs. Now the word dinosaur
is not used, how many of you think about dinosaurs? People talk about dinosaurs, you hear it,
and they have all these far out outlandish ideas about dinosaurs, right? You hear this,
they're 56 million years ago, and all of these crazy things that are mentioned about dinosaurs.
Now, does anyone know why the word dinosaur is not used in the Bible? Does anyone know?
It wasn't a word when our English Bible was translated. The word dinosaur didn't come
into usage until the 19th century, okay? So you look in the Bible and you say, I want
to find dinosaurs, and I go over here and my teacher's telling me that there are dinosaurs,
and I'm seeing these findings and all of this, and they're showing us these dinosaurs
and they're huge and they're all this, but the Bible doesn't say anything about dinosaurs.
Well, it does. It just doesn't use the word dinosaur, because the word dinosaur wasn't
around when they translated the English in 1611. Of course, there have been revisions
since then with some spellings and that sort of thing to the King James Bible, but the
reality is that we're looking for the wrong word. Dragons and beast, and when God's speaking
to Job and he speaks about Leviathan, if you read all of that and you understand, he's
speaking about something that's like a dinosaur. Now, again, they didn't use that term because
the term was not in existence, and that's something for us to understand. And what happens
sometimes is the people that want to attack the word of God, they're going to come with
their attacks, and they're going to try to stump us, and they're going to try to cause
our faith to not be stable and cause us to be tossed kind of to and fro, and somebody's
going to come. It's not hard. Just because the word dinosaur isn't in the Bible doesn't
mean that God didn't make dinosaurs. Amen? And so just because God didn't tell us, again,
to go back to my point that I made by way of introduction, God didn't give us a list
of every single specific thing that he did or that he made. He puts these broad categories.
Why? That's not the emphasis that God wants us to be focused upon. Creatures, the land
animals that were created, the fowls that were created previously, the fish and the
sea life and the sun, the moon, and the stars, all of that, none of that was created to be
redeemed. None of that was created to have a relationship with God the way that man was
created, to have fellowship and relationship with God. None of that was created to be worshipped.
Right? God alone is to be worshipped. And what happens is because we don't see the word
dinosaur, it shakes our faith. Some young people are sitting in some science classes
in our school systems, and they're talking about dinosaurs, and the teachers are sitting
there thinking, yeah, how are you going to deal with that? It's very easy. God said on
day number six that he made the beast of the earth. Amen? And that's going to include dinosaurs.
I wouldn't want a T-Rex as a pet. Amen? Come on. But you understand what I'm saying.
And so we find here this evening, and I'll deal some more as we get through our study,
I'll deal some more with dinosaurs and go into more detail and give you some information
that I think will help you, that I've been helped by. But the reality is that we find
that God's just giving these distinctions, these three categories, on this first creative
work that takes place on day number six. Again, the most important aspect of day number six
is what we'll deal with next week when God says, let us make man in our image. And he
deals with so much there in that passage of scripture, and it's so powerful. I do want
you to make note of this. Notice how many times in verses 24 and 25 you see this phraseology,
his kind. Did you notice as we were reading? He says, notice specifically in verse 25,
and God made the beast of the earth, that was one category. What does it say? After
his kind. Then he says this, and cattle after their kind. And everything that creepeth upon
the earth, after his kind. And so God established the categories that he would use, these distinctions
that he would use, and as he would tell us in verse number 24 that he made these things
and God made this, he formed it, that he then says it's after his or after their kind. It's
repeated in each of these distinct categories that God would give us. This is a critical
truth that was first mentioned on day number 3 of creation. If you remember back to our
study several weeks ago on day number 3, that in verse number 11 and verse number 12, the
Bible says, and God said, let the earth bring forth grass, the herb yielding seed, and the
fruit tree yielding fruit after his kind. Whose seed is in itself upon the earth, and
it was so in verse 12, and the earth brought forth grass, the herb yielding seed, after
his kind, and the tree yielding fruit whose seed was in itself after his kind, and God
saw that it was good. So it was first mentioned on day number 3. Day number 1, there's no
reference of after his kind. Day number 2, there's no reference of after his kind. In
fact, not only on day number 1 and 2, but on day number 4, there's no reference of after
his kind. Why? Because those things that were created on day 1, 2, and 4 do not reproduce.
We find that on day 3, 5, and 6, God is creating that which will reproduce, and it's always
mentioned that it's after their kind. And it's so important for us to understand this
because when God mentions and repeats on day 5 and 6, he dealt with it on day number 5
when he talked about the sea life and the fowls, and he created them, and they were
to reproduce, they were to be abundant upon the earth, and it was always after their kind.
You can read it in verse 21, every winged fowl after his kind. And so we find here that
he then said, be fruitful and multiply, and of course he filled the waters with that sea
life, and of course the fowls, they brought forth abundantly according to the word of
God. And we find here that then on day number 6, he says once again, he uses this phraseology,
after their kind. I made this statement before, but it's worth repeating because it needs
to get hammered into our brains, we need to understand this because we're constantly
being just pushed and forced into this conversation in our society today when so many people want
to talk about evolution, and the reality is that the genetic code within the DNA allows
for a wide variation horizontally within kind. Okay? Listen, Jacob mastered this later in
the book of Genesis, did he not? He understood the principle that God established of that
which would reproduce after his kind, and really he made himself very wealthy because
of understanding it. We find that throughout history that we have these within kind, there's
cross-breeding that takes place and all of these things for these adaptations and this
wide variation horizontally, and it's within the kind, it's always within kind. In fact,
Brother Trell got a dog, and they got some kind of dog, I don't even know what kind of
dog it is, but it's a little puffball and it's supposed to be some kind of hypoallergenic
and it doesn't shed and it doesn't this and it doesn't that, and they were, what happened
is there's some dog breeders that went through this process of whatever they were doing and
trying to, these variations horizontally, but what the genetic code within the DNA does
not allow for is vertical evolution from one kind to another. It doesn't allow for it.
And so when we, when you speak to somebody that is of an evolution mindset, when they're
dealing with that Darwinism and all of that thing of evolution, they're saying that things
evolve vertically from one kind to a different kind. That's their premise. That's what they're
dealing with. But that's not what God told us, and in fact we don't see any of that,
there's no reference of it, there's no proof of it whatsoever, you can look through the
fossil records, you can look through everything, there is not one evidence of these missing
links that they speak of, but what you will find is adaptations. Because God, in the genetic
code of the DNA, now listen, I was studying DNA this week and I'm going to tell you, it
made my head hurt.
I'm not a doctor
praise the Lord
But I was studying some stuff about DNA. I was ready to pick up the phone and call doc
Like help me understand this stuff, but the reality is that it's so complex
that even the most
Advanced scholars today are really just scratching the surface of all that's within the genetic code of the DNA
But God created it that way amen and so he allowed for variations for adaptations
So you take certain kinds of animals and you take them to a certain?
Environment and all of a sudden over a period of time there will be
Adaptations because of the climatic influence on those particular kinds of animals. That's not evolution
Amen that's what God built into the DNA code for the
adaptation of his creation
based upon the climatic impact of where they would be and
And so there are certain you you read it you understand where people talk about hey
There we have this type of animal here, but it's not native to this part of the world
What happened somebody brought it there?
Right and they brought those
animals whatever kinds they were and it's obviously all different to pay depending on which island or which place you're speaking of and
You find that there were kings that had all sorts of wealth listen
Solomon brought all kinds of things into Israel
Right you can read about it
You can read about his fame and all that he brought in and the the the situation is that there are some kings some some
Emperors some rulers that conquered certain parts of the world and they wanted to bring certain types of animals to those
Places and now all of a sudden. They're a little different than they were from the place
They originated because of the adaptations
it's not evolution, and that's what some of the the the those that would
Suggest the the teaching and would be so forceful on this idea of evolution
They miss that that subject of the adaptations, I believe as I've mentioned several times
That it really isn't a matter of the intellect
It's more a matter of the will
When you're dealing with and we're looking at creation, and we're seeking to accept that which God has said we're coming
Approaching if you will the Word of God from the basis of this is what God said
And I'm going to accept it as such
Now as New Testament believers, we have the Holy Spirit of God who indwells us
And what and and as we think about the Holy Spirit of God?
He's the not only the author of Scripture, but he's the teacher of Scripture and guess what the Holy Spirit of God confirms within us
The truth of his word the Bible says in John that he will lead us into all truth
Amen and the reality is that when we approach the Word of God
we're understanding that that we're approaching it from a from a perspective that is a
Proper perspective, but Paul said this to the believers in Corinth, and it's so important for us to understand
He said the natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God
For their foolishness unto him neither can he not can he know them why because they're spiritually discerned and
So often when we have these interactions and we have these times in our lives when somebody will say oh
You're one of those creationist. You're one of those people that believe that God made all this stuff you believe in God
We have to understand that they're coming from a completely different
Worldview than what we're coming from and we we just going to take a step back
We need to be patient with it, but we also must understand. It's not just a matter of intellect
You cannot argue somebody into heaven
Okay, you can't and here's what happens
Here's why it's a matter of the will and of the emotion is
Because you can lay out all of the proof that you want to lay out and what people are gonna
Do is they're going to be willingly ignorant just like they were in the time when Peter was writing 2nd Peter 3 of
This there are willingly ignorant and what breaks my heart is people that do not want to know the truth
It's as if they have this mantra in life. Don't confuse me with the facts. I believe what I believe
I'm comfortable with my belief don't mess with me
But what you believe is false. You've been lied to you've been deceived
They don't want to they don't want it. I'm not saying they as in everybody
I'm not speaking in those absolute terms
But the reality this evening is that we have to understand it's not just a matter of intellect
Listen when we deal with these things when we understand the the truth of creation and we're dealing with
Defending our faith and we're speaking to people. We must bathe it in prayer
We must really understand this is a spiritual battle
This is not our weapons are not the same as their weapons
Amen, and we understand this evening that what we're dealing with is a spiritual battle a deceit
That has been
Planted there by Satan himself by the enemy and these people have been deceived and we must go in the power of God
We must bathe it in prayer
Because I can tell you this evening that the Holy Spirit of God
Has such a greater ability to convince somebody of truth than you or me or any other theologian
Amen and we just we have to take it from that. It's important for us to know what we believe
It's important for us to understand the creation account as it's been given
But it's important for us to understand that when we get into those conversations with people. They're spiritually
They're most of them. They're lost
They they don't have the Holy Spirit of God that's in dwelling them and we must bathe it in prayer
As we think about this first aspect of day number six of creation and we see that we conclude the first creative activity
By announcing look at what God says at the end of verse 24 in the end of verse 25
This is how God concludes this first poor
Creative activity of day number six. It says at the end of verse 24 and it was so
God said right that's how we started verse 24 and God said the end of the verse says and it was so verse 25
He ends it by saying this and God saw that it was good
We find here this evening that then in verse 26
He would say and God said and then we start that second creative activity
Of day number six where God creates man
It will be the focus of our study next week for at least next week
As we continue getting through the end of this first chapter. I hope this evening that as we understand, why is it that?
Obviously, it's important that we have the Word of God and that we understand what God has given us
But God's given us what we need to know
sometimes what happens in life is we are so we so occupy ourselves and I've been guilty of this myself we
Occupy ourselves to try to figure out things that God didn't tell us
to think that somehow if we arm ourselves with that information we could win an argument and
I found myself on more than one occasion
That it typically doesn't work that way and
We just need to be settled and grounded on what God has given us and here when he created the land-based animals
He gave three distinct categories
As how he would divide them and that's what he gives us there
In the the cattle the creeping thing and then the beast of the earth. Amen. Let's pray together Father