familiar to us this year that you still stand in awe
of how great our God is and what a wonderful blessing it is
that we have the Bible and that he has revealed himself
to us and there are plenty of people around this earth,
plenty of people around this county,
plenty of people around this town
that do not know how great God is
and what a wonderful privilege it is
that we can know the King of Kings and Lord of Lords
and know how great he is, amen.
And to be able to serve him, what a blessing.
And this evening, Psalm 85, we're gonna step away
from the book of Ruth for this evening
and really give a preparatory type of a message
leading into our revival meeting that will begin
Saturday morning with the men's prayer breakfast
and then Sunday through Wednesday.
And of course, this past Sunday morning,
I preached a message that was preparatory as well.
But as we look at Psalm 85 in verse number six,
just a familiar verse of scripture
and I'm gonna use this verse of scripture
really as a springboard this evening
and just titling the message, Revive Us Again.
And we sing that song and in fact,
we'll sing it during the revival meeting, Revive Us Again.
It's a familiar hymn to many of us
and we find that the psalmist says in Psalm 85
in verse number six, wilt thou not revive us again
that thy people may rejoice in thee?
I think about this idea of revival
and I mentioned this statement on Sunday morning
about being revival ready or being revival resistant.
And as we look at this thought this evening
of revive us again and really having the desire
that me, myself personally having the desire
and for me also having the desire
that each of you would have this desire
that we would be ready for revival,
we would be revival ready.
And you think about the idea of being ready for something
and you know what it means to be ready for something.
In fact, Juliana had a doctor's appointment yesterday,
everything went well and as she left the doctor's office,
they're just a few weeks away and the doctor said this,
pack your bags and be ready.
And all of you that have had children,
you understand what that means
and what the doctor was communicating
that at any moment you may enter into that period of time
referred to as labor and a baby is coming.
And so we don't know exactly the time
but the idea that the doctor was seeking
to communicate to Juliana and to Evan
was get your bags packed and be ready.
In other words, at three o'clock in the morning,
if it were to happen,
you don't wanna be trying to get your stuff ready
at that point, you gotta get going to the doctor.
And so I was of the persuasion when our children
were getting near to their due date,
when Holly was getting near to the due date,
I was of the persuasion that we had insurance
because it was the doctor's responsibility
to deliver the baby.
We did not have insurance
so that I could deliver the baby in the car.
so that I could deliver the baby at home.
We had insurance so that the baby could be delivered
at the hospital with the doctor.
And so therefore, I was ready to go.
When Holly says, I'm timing them and I'm saying, let's go.
Like, let's roll, right?
Let's go because we need to get to the doctor.
Now that took us to the doctor a few times prematurely
and we were sent home.
But when we think about being ready for something,
it means that we're prepared for it.
We're not just entering into something haphazardly,
we've planned for, we've prepared for.
And this evening, when we think about this idea tonight
of being revival ready, I mentioned on Sunday,
you're not going to experience revival
simply because there's a set of meetings
that have been placed on a calendar
and you've been encouraged to be here.
No, we're gonna have revival,
we'll experience revival personally,
and I pray corporately so long as we are ready for revival.
How can we be revival ready?
What is it that we can do?
What are some steps that we can take
simply this evening, four thoughts very quickly,
and we'll look at a number of portions of scripture
to begin.
Look over at First Corinthians chapter number 11
and we'll start here with this portion of scripture
that's a portion in which we regularly visit
when we observe the Lord's Supper.
And we're not observing the Lord's Supper this evening,
but we see in this passage of scripture
important instruction with regard to this idea
that we're dealing with tonight of being revival ready.
And if you're taking notes,
I would say number one, contemplation.
And the word contemplation literally means this,
it means the act of the mind in considering with attention.
So we're talking about contemplation,
I would ask the question when I say
that there ought to be some contemplation in our lives,
what is it that we're contemplating?
What is the object of our contemplation?
Well, it's our lives.
The Bible says in this portion of scripture
in First Corinthians 11 and verse 28,
notice the Bible says,
but let a man examine, what's the next word?
Himself.
You know what most humans like to do?
Examine other people.
It's a human tendency.
I would much rather have your life under the microscope
than my life under the microscope.
And you would like for someone else's life
to be under the microscope
than for your life to be under the microscope.
But the Bible says, but let a man examine himself.
Let a man examine himself.
And so we think about this idea of contemplation,
this idea, if you will, of self-examination.
What is the purpose?
We understand the object of our contemplation is our lives.
The purpose of our contemplation is to determine
whether or not my life,
whether or not your life is pleasing to the Lord.
See, the idea this evening of this thought of contemplation
is not really the idea of saying,
well, how do I compare to somebody else?
How is my life aligned to what maybe somebody else's life is
because the reality is that we find that here
in the church in Corinth,
they were encouraged in the second letter
that they are to not to compare themselves
amongst themselves.
This is foolish, this is not wise.
And we find this evening that the truth that we find
when we look at this idea of self-examination
is does my life please God?
Does my life please God?
Do my actions please God?
Do my thoughts please God?
Do my words please God?
I had this thought as I was just meditating
upon this message for this evening
and exactly what the Lord would want me to say.
And I had this thought and really quite honestly,
it was an extremely sobering thought.
And the thought was this,
what if in your life or in my life for the next 24 hours,
maybe the next 72 hours,
what if every action, every word,
and every thought were recorded and then played back?
How would you feel about that?
Would you be excited to come to the showing of your life
over the next 72 hours?
Probably for some of us, we might not show up
if we knew that every word that I spoke,
every thought that I had, every action that I took
was going to be for show, right?
But the reality is that what I say and what I do
and how I think is not for other people.
It's really for the audience of one, the Lord Jesus Christ.
How is, see, he sees everything.
He knows our thoughts.
You think about the truth of the Lord Jesus Christ
during his earthly ministry,
the gospels record on a number of occasions where he's there
and he knew their thoughts.
He knows our thoughts.
He knows what we're looking at,
what we've fixed our eyes upon.
The psalmist talks, or Job talks about,
I will set no wicked thing before mine eyes.
The psalmist speaks about putting a gate before our mouth.
Right, the psalmist says in Psalm 19,
let the words of my mouth and meditations of my heart
be acceptable in thy sight, O Lord.
Right, and so we think about that.
Sometimes we just, you ever hear somebody say,
I'm gonna give him a piece of my mind?
Be careful.
You know how easy it is to sin with the tongue?
Read the book of James, so easy.
And we grieve and quench the Holy Spirit of God.
And so this idea of contemplation,
this idea of self-examination that we are taking our lives
and we're putting them under the lens of scripture,
we're understanding that I'm not comparing my life
to your life, you're not comparing your life to mine
or to someone else, no.
We are looking at the truth of God's word
and saying, is my life pleasing, acceptable
in the sight of God?
I believe this evening that the process of contemplation
will humble us.
When I think about this,
and I'm not gonna have you keep turning there,
many of us know the verse of scripture,
but I'll reference it many times this evening.
In 2 Chronicles 7 and verse 14,
it's a verse of scripture that's often been used
in the context of revival.
And the Bible says, if my people,
which are called by my name,
the first thing is shall humble themselves.
You know what's a very humbling experience is self-examination.
I've often said this over the years, in fact, as we observe the Lord's Supper,
I probably mentioned about 80% of the time that we observe the Lord's Supper
that the process of self-examination requires two things. It requires
humility and it requires honesty. If we're not going to be humble
and we're not going to be honest about our self-examination, we're really kind of wasting our time.
We find that we desire to be revival
ready and therefore I must contemplate, I must have that
act of the mind in considering with attention
and truly examining my life. And so this evening, step one
in this process of being revival ready, contemplation, step number two
is confession. I believe this evening that the
proper result of contemplation will be
confession. Because as we consider with
attention our lives, as we examine our lives under the lens of Scripture,
as we truly stand and say, God, is my life
pleasing in your sight? My words, my actions, my thoughts,
are they pleasing in your sight? None of us are perfect. Amen?
And we know that man, I'm
thankful to be redeemed, but we still have a sin nature
and we understand this evening that when we go through that process of contemplation
and it leads us to that place of confession, we've been humbled
and then we confess our sins. We're familiar with 1 John 1
and verse number 9, if we confess our sins, he is faithful and just
to forgive us and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness. I'm so thankful
that we have a God who is ready to pardon, who is ready to forgive.
We understand this evening so much truth with
regard to the understanding of confession
and the importance of confession, but yet at times
if we're not careful, we'll act like we don't need confession.
That I really don't have anything. And then sometimes we'll say something like this,
Lord, if I have sinned, would you forgive me? Hold on a minute, it's
not if I have sinned. Amen?
We know that we have sinned. It's not this broad thing.
Confession means to say the same thing about. It means to agree with God.
When David confessed, when if you look in Psalm 51
and you read the confession of David, you find
that he is confessing. He is saying, this is wicked
what I've done. He says, against thee and thee only have I
done this wickedness. We find that he says, I acknowledge
my transgressions. It wasn't a situation of if I have sinned.
No, he acknowledged. He said, I know that I have transgressed
against the law of God. But isn't it a joy
to know that he's ready to pardon? He's ready to forgive?
The Bible tells us that God knows everything.
God knows everything. He knows our thoughts. He knows our words, our actions. He knows everything.
And so he knows that we've sinned.
He knew that, God knew that Rachel hid
the idols in the tent.
God knew that Adam and Eve sinned and were hiding in the garden.
God knew that Achan took of the accursed thing. God knew all of that.
Three examples that we find in the Bible where somebody tried to hide something, just simple
quick examples where they try to hide something. But God knew about it.
God reveals it to us in the pages of Scripture. The Bible says that he that covereth
his sin, notice these words, shall not
prosper. He that covereth his sin shall not
prosper. We try to hide something from God that he already knows about.
And he says, I will forgive you
so that you can have that restored fellowship. Now I'm thankful that my
sin and your sin, if we're saved, if we've trusted Christ as our Savior,
that I'm heaven bound and I'm thankful for that. My relationship
is settled because of my position
in Christ. But I would say to you this evening that sin in the life of a believer
hinders our fellowship with God. And truly this evening
I hope that our desire would be that there would be nothing in my life
that would hinder my fellowship with God.
This idea of confession is really a longing to be clean.
We read there again in Psalm 51 where he
says in verse number 7, purge me with hyssop and I shall be clean.
Wash me and I shall be whiter than snow. In verse number 10,
give me a clean heart, O God, and renew a right
spirit within me. I've said as I've looked at these verses before from this
pulpit, I have said that it's not an idea of just being cleaner.
It's the purpose of being clean.
Sometimes if we're not careful, we're content with cleaner.
We're okay with just being a little cleaner. We really don't want to go
as far as clean. And we find here
that this longing to be clean, that refusing to cover,
refusing to excuse. The Bible says in that portion
of scripture again in 2 Chronicles 7 and verse 14 that they shall humble themselves
and pray and seek my face. And then it says this, and turn from
their wicked ways. Turn from their wicked ways. Oh that
God would help us to be revival ready. I believe that
an approach in which we could take is contemplation.
It's going to take time. Examine ourselves.
And then confession. Lord forgive me. I'm thankful that he's
ready to pardon. He's gracious and he's merciful.
I think about this, not only contemplation and
confession, but I would say number three, cultivation.
The Bible speaks about our hearts as being soil. I mentioned this on Sunday morning.
We find that the Bible also refers to God's word
as being the seed. And I believe that
every week in our church the seed of God's word is preached.
I believe and I take very seriously the responsibility that
God has given me to preach the word. And I
believe that is my duty, my responsibility. I have heard
certainly throughout the years of folks that have visited or even watched on
live stream, why don't you deal with this and why don't you deal with that and why don't you share your
opinion on this. Because my opinion doesn't matter. I've got to preach the word of God
and God's, he said preach the word. Be instant in season, out of season,
reprove, rebuke, exhort with all longsuffering and doctrine. The time will come when they
will not endure sound doctrine, but yet it's the responsibility of a
pastor to preach the word. And I believe that this
week, not only do I believe that every time we have service that
God's word is preached, but this week, Brother Meshon, he's going to preach God's word.
I'm confident of that. Listen, if I didn't think he's going
to preach God's word, I wouldn't extend an invitation to him. I'm not
interested in inviting someone to come and stand behind this sacred desk
and gather together the saints of God for entertainment. That's not what
it's about. And so Brother Meshon is going to preach God's word and God's word
is seed and seed will be sown, but the question
and we use the point cultivation is because as the seed of
God's word is sown, what kind of soil
does it fall upon? If I want to have a
garden and I know we're near the end of the year for gardening and what
have you, but we have a garden out there. Someone mentioned the other day, they said,
man, your tomato plants are tall and they are. They're taller than Joseph. Now
something's taller than Joseph, man, that's tall. And we
find that those tomato plants, they're huge. And there was a lot
of work that went into cultivating that ground in order to prepare
the soil so that when the seed was planted that it would
produce some fruit. And we understand that. We understand
this evening the important aspect with regard
to agriculture and what have you. But I want you
to notice what the Bible says in the book of Hosea. Turn to the book of Hosea
if you will in chapter number 10. Hosea in chapter number 10
Daniel, Hosea, Joel, Amos
Obadiah try to help you there just a bit. And I
try to be a little bit more helpful than some that I have heard preached that always say it's between
Genesis and Revelation. And I always find that to be quite helpful.
And in Hosea chapter 10
and verse number 12, the Bible says this
Sow to yourselves in righteousness
reap in mercy. Notice what he says
break up your fallow ground for it is
time to seek the Lord till he come and reign righteousness
upon you. Verse 13, you have plowed wickedness, you have
reaped iniquity. You've eaten the fruit of lies because now there's trust
in thy way in the multitude of thy mighty men. And so we
understand that he's speaking here of sowing to ourselves in righteousness, reaping
in mercy. He speaks in verse 13 about that sowing and reaping. And we understand that's a law
that God has established. The Bible teaches us in the book of
Galatians this principle, this law of
sowing and reaping. Be not deceived. God is not mocked.
Whatsoever man soweth, that shall he also reap. Oftentimes
we are guilty of only looking at that verse of Scripture in the context
of the negative. But if you look at the context of Galatians 6
it's positive and negative because if we sow good seed, we
reap good fruit. Amen? And I'm thankful for that.
Preacher of yesteryear said unfortunately a lot of people go to
live their lives by sowing bad seeds six days out of the week and then they come
to church on Sunday and they pray for crop failure. And that's a silly way, I
mean it's a great analogy, it's a great illustration in a single
statement. That's not how we're to live our lives. We're to sow good seed and he
says break up your fallow ground. Have the heart, that process of
cultivation that we will decide this week, prior to entering into any of the
services, that we will decide I'm going to agree with God. I'm just gonna
agree with God. If God says that, that settles it. And I'm gonna
agree to be obedient to the Lord. We're gonna sing that little chorus, I'll say
yes Lord yes. We'll sing it before each of the messages. We will not sing our
theme song during the revival meeting. I've prayed about that this week and I
feel that it'd be appropriate to sing I'll say yes Lord yes, to your will and
to your way. I'll say yes Lord yes, I will trust you and obey. The song says this,
when your spirit speaks to me, with my whole heart I'll agree. And my answer
will be yes Lord yes. And that last part when it says when your spirit speaks to
me, I'm expecting, I'm anticipating the Spirit of God using the Word of God and
speaking to me and speaking to you. And I want to have that a heart attitude of
Lord, I'll say yes. Sometimes if we're not careful we look at the idea of maybe
having in our lives this time in which we'll use the terminology where man that
was conviction, that was convicting, that message was convicting, I was
experiencing conviction, stepping on my toes. Listen, that's a good thing. It's a
good thing. It's good for us when the Spirit of God is moving in our hearts
and our lives and He's challenging us and He's speaking to us directly
through His Word. Holly showed me this past week a little cartoon, whatever they
call them, memes. I don't even know what that means but she showed me
something that her mom sent her and there was someone searching through the
house frantically and this little cartoon meme thing and the caption said
I know that the preacher's got a camera in here somewhere because it
seems like every message he's preaching he must be watching my life. And the
reality is that's not the case. It's just God's Spirit uses God's Word and He can
speak to us and He can point out things in our lives and that's a good thing. I'm
thankful that God doesn't just leave us off to our own.
Yep, that's what you, is that what, that's what we do with our children. We call them
back. We try to set them in the right direction. We try to teach them the
way in which they ought to go. And so this evening we think about this idea of
cultivation, of having my heart prepared for God to speak to me, expecting that
God will speak to me. And then I would say this, there's a time of communion. The
reality this evening is that sometimes, I know that we live in a fast-paced world.
I really do. I mean we're busy. You're busy. I get it. I understand it. And if
we're not careful, we can just be so busy that we just totally live life thinking very
little about God and our need for Him because we're just so busy. But the Bible says be
still and know that I am God. The Bible talks about coming apart. The Bible speaks about
the importance of having that communion with the Lord. And I would encourage you this evening
that over the next several days that you carve out some time in your schedule to just have
some extra communion with God and just really get along with God. See, I believe tonight,
here's what I really believe. I believe we all could have revival before Sunday gets
here. I believe that. Why do I believe that? Because revival isn't something that's circled
on a date on a calendar. It's something that we can experience tonight. We can experience
tomorrow. We can have revival. And when we think about this idea of our busy schedules
and all that's going on, and I find, listen, I don't think that we're going to say, man,
I just, I don't think I should have read my Bible that much this week. I just don't think
we're going to say that. You know what I mean? We might say I shouldn't have been on social
media that much this week. I shouldn't have watched that much news. I shouldn't have watched
that many sports. I shouldn't have, there's a number of things that we may say I regret.
I shouldn't have spent that much time on that. But I don't think we're going to say I shouldn't
have prayed that long. I don't think we're going to say I shouldn't have read my Bible
that long. And so we're not going to regret those things. Remember the truth of 2 Chronicles
7, 14, and I've not dealt with it in its order as it's given, but the Bible says if
my people, which are called by my name, shall humble themselves, and then it says this,
and pray and seek my face. Pray and seek my face. That's this idea of communion. Seeking
the face of God. Prayer is work. I know I've said this before. I've been very transparent
about this from the pulpit before and I hope that no one has a negative response to this,
but I'm just being very transparent with you. It is easier for me to read my Bible than
to pray. I'm telling you, I can read my Bible for 10 times as long as I can pray. Honestly.
Prayer is hard work. It doesn't mean that I don't pray. I pray. Don't misunderstand.
Don't misinterpret what I'm saying. But prayer is work. Now some people, somebody might come
and say, man I can just pray for all day. God bless you. I wish I could. It's warfare.
It is spiritual warfare. But God says we're to pray. Seek his face. And this evening when
we think about this idea of how am I going to be revival ready? We're not just going
to show up. I've heard evangelists, missionaries that have said this. They've told me this
personally Brother Armando. They've told me to my face. I have shown up to churches for
special meetings and some people have greeted me and they've said, who are you? What are
you here for? Having no idea that there was a missions conference, revival meeting, special
meeting, just zero preparation whatsoever. We need to be prepared. And I believe that
as we have this idea of contemplation, Lord search me. This time of let a man examine
himself. It's a humbling experience. It will humble us. But contemplation will lead us
to confession. That we turn from our wicked ways. That we say God against thee and thee
only have I sinned. That thought that I had. That word that I spoke. I looked at that thing
and I shouldn't have. I read that thing and I shouldn't have. Whatever it might be. God
I've sinned. Would you forgive me? I don't want that thing to hinder my fellowship with
you. I truly want there to be nothing between my soul and my Savior. Then we have that time
of cultivation. Lord help me to have a heart. The soil that illustration is given in God's
word. That the soil would be ready for the seed. I mean that it would just be as the
seed of God's word is preached that it falls on good ground. Good soil that's ready to
receive it. We're ready to respond. It's going to require some communion with God.
Just some time that we carve out and we say Lord I'm going to spend some time with you
each day. Extra time. Really being serious about this thing. See I think today in America
I chatted with a man yesterday. He's a pastor in India. He's a pastor there for years. I
chatted with him yesterday. I hadn't seen him in over 20 years the last time I saw him.
We got to chat and catch up for a bit yesterday. When you think about some of the other countries
around the world and some of the approach, the seriousness if you will, the longing for
God. We read in the Psalms about the Psalmist saying I'm longing for thee. I fear that sometimes
in America Christianity has just been cheapened. If you can understand what I mean by that
because it's convenient. There's a measure with Christianity in America that it's comfortable.
I don't think it's going to stay like that for very long but it has been comfortable
and it's been somewhat convenient and it's been cheapened. Very rarely do we really have
to take up our cross. You understand what I'm saying? In this evening if we really want
to be serious about God's work in our life, we've got to spend some time with Him. Some
extended time with Him. Not just a...
quick little, thank you Lord for the day. But no, really spend time with them. Let's
pray together. Father, we love you. Thank you for loving us. I pray that we'd be revival
ready. Lord, would you prepare our hearts? We've prayed and asked that you would prepare
Brother Meshon and lead him to the messages to preach. And God, I believe that you will.
I believe that you'll answer that prayer. I pray that each one of us, Lord, would come
to each service, not only desiring to hear from you but expecting to hear from you. Lord,
that we'd come with hearts that are prepared to respond in obedience. Lord, I pray that
you do a great work. Even as I mentioned tonight, we could have revival before this meeting,
this special meeting even begins. I pray that you'd help us to take seriously the
importance of self-examination. I pray that that process of contemplation would lead to
confession in our lives. God, that we'd be honest and we'd be humble. I pray that you'd
move and work in hearts and lives. I pray that you would just be glorified. I pray that
you would not be content with status quo. I pray, Lord, that we'd long for you to have
that fullness of joy that's found in your presence, that we'd have that sweet communion
and fellowship with thee. We do thank you for the privilege of prayer. We pray that
you'd bless our time of prayer. I pray that you'd be honored and glorified through all
that we say and do. For it's in Christ's name we pray. Amen. Alright, if you have your prayer
bullets, does anyone need a prayer bulletin this evening?