Genesis chapter number 2 verses 1 through 3 will be our text of scripture for this evening.
I mentioned this morning that we finally finished Genesis chapter number 1, and it means that
we have 49 more chapters to go.
Praise the Lord, we're making progress, amen?
Jesus is coming again, and he's coming soon.
He may come before we finish the book of Genesis, amen?
Genesis 2 verses 1 through 3, the Bible says this, thus the heavens and the earth were
finished, and all the host of them, and on the seventh day God ended his work which he
had made, and he rested on the seventh day from all his work which he had made.
Verse 3 says God blessed the seventh day and sanctified it because in it he had rested
from all his work which God created and made.
The title for the message this evening is there from verse number 1, the heavens and
the earth were finished.
We have the great privilege of having in our Bibles the account of the week of creation,
and what a blessing that is.
There are so many in our world today that are asking these questions of where did it
all come from, how did it all begin, when did life start, so on and so forth, and we
have the word of God that tells us, that gives us the record of the week of creation.
What a blessing that is.
And as we study Genesis chapter number 1, we've said it often that the power and wisdom
of God is on display.
It is true, as we've mentioned many times throughout the study, according to Hebrews
11 and verse number 3, that it is imperative that we accept the record by faith.
I'm currently reading a book and I've not finished it so I cannot fully endorse it because
I've not finished the book, but the book is entitled, I Do Not Have Enough Faith to
Be an Atheist, and you've read it before, and would you recommend it?
Say it again?
Yeah, he was co-authored, he is one of them, and the reality is that, again, I've not finished
the book so I can't put my full stamp of approval on it because I've not finished it, but so
far it's been an excellent read, and the reality is that they talk about, oh, you have faith
in God.
They have faith in what they believe too.
Their faith is just misplaced, and by the way, it requires for them to have more faith
even than, see because the object of our faith is God himself, and God has declared, here's
what I've done, here's how I created, I said and it was done, he spoke and it was created,
it existed, and what a blessing to have the account of God's Word, and certainly the awesome
display of God's power and of God's wisdom should cause each of us as his children to
stand in awe of who he is.
That we study the first, many times, listen, most of us have read Genesis 1 countless times.
In fact, there are times when we start the new year that maybe we go to Genesis 1 and
we almost say, well, I've read this a hundred times, I already know, and we just kind of
go through it, but as we kind of just slow down a little bit and allow the truth of what
God is revealing to us, and to see his power and his wisdom, it results in us saying, what
a wonderful God, what a powerful God, what an all-wise God he is, and the psalmist speaks
of that in Psalm 33, in verse number eight, remember that on day number one, light or
energy was created.
On day number two, he separated it there and created the firmament.
It was on day number three that it was the sea, the dry land, and the plant life, and
we found that on day number four, it was the sun, the moon, and the stars, and we were
at the Creation Museum this past week, as well as visiting the Noah's Ark encounter,
and as we were there at the Creation Museum, we went into the planetarium, and I mean,
it was absolutely amazing as we sat in that theater, if you will, and we sat back in our
chairs, and we're looking at all of these things, and Holly was sitting to my right,
and as we were sitting there looking at all of these stars, and they were going through
all of the billions of miles, and light, I mean, just all of these numbers, and all of
this stuff, and I kind of whispered over to Holly, and I repeated those words that we
find in Genesis 1, in verse 16, he made the stars also.
It's amazing, and when we were sitting there in that planetarium, and just taking it all
in, and saying, this is just captured in a few words in Genesis' account, in Genesis
1 and 16, and he made the stars also.
It was on day four that he made the stars, the sun, the moon, and the stars.
On day number five, the sea life, and the fowls.
We find that on day number six, the land-based animals, and then the crowning moment of creation
when he created man in his own image, and what a blessing as we've studied through,
and we've had the opportunity to read, and to see all that God gives us.
We are reminded that these are six literal 24-hour days.
These are not periods of time, these are not long ages of creation, these are literal 24-hour
days.
We understand this, really, based upon the fact that the word and is used, the usage
of that word and, and giving that sequential idea of the events that are recorded.
But we also understand that at the end of each day, the Bible says the evening and the
morning were the second day, the third day, the fourth day, and we find that God gives
us there in that reading of Genesis chapter number one, the truth concerning these six
literal 24-hour days.
As we come to Genesis chapter number two in verses one through three, we find that
he says, thus the heavens and the earth were finished, and notice this, and all the host
of them.
If you're taking notes this evening, notice with me first of all that God declares his
creative work complete.
He says, thus the heavens and the earth were finished, and all the host of them.
It tells us in verse number three, and God blessed the seventh day and sanctified it
because that in it, he had rested from all his work which God created and made.
And so we find that he declares his creative work complete.
He says it is finished.
It is complete, not continuing, and that's important for us to understand as we look
at the Genesis account of creation, and we understand that God in his infinite wisdom,
he chose to create everything in six days.
Now, people argue about this all the time, and they have these circular reasoning arguments
of, well, couldn't he have done it in one day?
Sure, he's God, right?
He could do whatever he chose to do.
He could have created everything in a moment.
He could have taken years.
He could have done whatever he wanted to do, but what he did in his infinite wisdom is
he created everything in six days, and that's God's right to do it that way, by the way,
and he's God, amen?
And he told us exactly what he did.
And the real danger as we get into some of those arguments and some of those discussions
and that circular reasoning of what God can or cannot do, the problem is that we must
go with what God told us that he did, because we can sit around and we can say, well, yeah,
God could have done that, but he told us he did this, and so therefore we must take God
at his word.
That is the definition of faith, by the way, that we take God at his word.
We find that he created, as we've spoken about this many times throughout our study of Genesis
chapter number one, that God created each kind with the ability to reproduce, but we
also found that during the time of creation, and we discussed this on a number of occasions,
that the genetic code within the DNA allows for that wide variation horizontally within
the kind, but not for vertical evolution from one kind to another kind.
And here's the interesting thing.
When we think about that genetic code within the DNA and we think about the variations
horizontally, if you will, within the kind, we find that that is what allows for animals
to adapt to certain climates, as they would be moved from one climate to another climate
as some animals are transported from one area to another area.
You think about Solomon and all of his wealth and all of his wisdom and all of those things.
He brought in all kinds of animals and beings and what have you, and when we think about
the DNA code or the genetic code within the DNA and God creating those animals with that
ability to adapt, not to evolve, but to adapt, and it's built within the genetic code within
the DNA.
It is important also for us to remember that God is eternal.
And because God is eternal and because God is omniscient, he knows, and I think Alexis,
you mentioned it during your testimony, he knows the end from the beginning, right?
He is alpha and omega.
He's the first and he's the last.
He knows all things and therefore in those six days of creation, God in his infinite
wisdom, in the fact that he is eternal, he was able to create each of those kinds with
their genetic code built within the DNA, the ability to adapt and to thrive pre-flood
and post-flood.
Amen?
And that is an important thing.
for us to understand because a lot of times what happens is when you have
these evolutionists and they want to show you some of their quote-unquote
evidence and they want to talk about some of these things that they found in
some of the the fossils and in the fossil record as they like to refer to
the fossil record on many occasion you'll find that they'll mention some
things but really all you're seeing is the adapt the ability for those kinds to
adapt to the climate to the changes as we get further in our study the book of
Genesis when you study Genesis 6 7 & 8 and you see all that takes place with
the flood you will understand in a great way the the impact that the flood had on
the climate it was an amazing impact that was given through that flood and
the difference between pre-flood and post-flood is it's an amazing study and
so as we look here in Genesis chapter number one in Genesis chapter number two
as we come to this place where God says he's finished his work of creation we'd
understand that with his infinite wisdom and with the fact that he's eternal
that he was able to create all these kinds everything that he created that
they would have within their genetic code the ability to have those
variations horizontally based upon based upon climatic change and we find
here this evening that God declared that his creative work was complete and now
notice with me some verses of scripture let's go to the book of let's go to the
New Testament in the book of John we'll look at some Old Testament verses in our
next point this evening but I want you to look at some New Testament verses
with me go to John chapter 1 and as we look at this thought that God
declared his creative work complete that it was finished it was complete not
continuing I want you to understand from some of these verses that we'll look at
in the book of in the in the New Testament that again as we've mentioned
time and time again throughout this study of the book of Genesis and looking
at the record of creation that this idea of creation is not isolated to Genesis
the truth of creation is found it is scattered throughout all of the
scripture that God is the Creator Amen John 1 in the beginning was the Word and
the Word was with God and the Word was God who's the Word Jesus Christ verse
number 14 says and the Word was made flesh and dwelt among us and we beheld
his glory the glory is of the only begotten of the Father full of grace and
truth the Word is Jesus Christ he is the eternal Son of God Amen we find that
the gospel accounts they provide us with the record of his incarnation when God
took upon himself the the form of human human form and it says that in the
beginning was the Word the Word was with God and the Word was God the same was in
the beginning with God notice verse 3 all things how many things all things
were made by him and without him was not anything made that was made yeah he
declared there in Genesis chapter 2 in verse number 1 that the heavens and the
earth were finished he completed his work of creation here in John 1 we find
that Jesus Christ is is God in flesh of course the Word was made flesh and
dwelt among us but he is the eternal Son of God he is co-equal and co-eternal
with God the Father 3 in 1 the truth of the Trinity and it says all things were
made by him and without him was not anything made that was made turn to the
book of Ephesians in chapter number 3 we'll just look at about 5 or 6 verses
here this evening from the New Testament I only have two points tonight so we're
in good shape amen Ephesians chapter number 3 it doesn't mean that those
points are short but I do only have two points this evening Genesis excuse me
Ephesians chapter number 3 and verse number 9 the Bible says this and to make
all men see what is the fellowship of the mystery which from the beginning of
the world hath been hidden God notice this who created all things by Jesus
Christ turn over to the book of Colossians in chapter number 1 we've
looked at this verse a couple of times during our study but the Bible tells us
in Colossians 1 beginning in verse number 15 who is the image of the
invisible God the firstborn of every creature for by him were all things
created that are in heaven and that are in earth notice visible and invisible
whether they be thrones or dominions or principalities or powers all things were
created by him and for him and he is before all things and by him all things
consist amen the Bible continues in verse 18 he
is the head of the body the church aren't you thankful for that think
about that just for a moment the class tonight is not on the doctrine of the
church we're not dealing with ecclesiology this evening however it's
amazing to consider that the Creator God all that he says in verses 15 through
17 about all that he did and then it says by the way and he is the head of
the church amen he is the head of the body the church who was the beginning
the firstborn from the dead that in all things he might have the preeminence by
the way when we truly understand who he is it will not be a problem for us to
allow him to have the preeminence amen the problem is we get so twisted up in
our lives we get so twisted up by those things that are around us and you think
about the Sunday school lesson this morning that covetousness and that the
vanity and the the psalmist had said hey I want to obey I want to keep it until
the end prevent those things that covetousness and that vanity because I
know that those distractions are going to come when we truly understand who he
is and we have that knowledge of him and we desire to walk with him it's no thing
for us to say he's chief he is first place he is Lord of my life amen and we
find today the the great truth there that he is the creator of all things and
he is the head of the body the church over in Hebrews chapter 1 and then we'll
get over the book of Revelation and get into our next point this evening Hebrews
1 Hebrews is a great book I love the book of Hebrews I in fact I was praying
fervently last fall about preaching through the book of Hebrews this year
and God led me to the book of Ephesians instead and so I'll be praying again
about preaching through the book of Hebrews amen and I love the book of
Hebrews what wonderful truth God gives us there the Bible says in verse number
one of Hebrews 1 God who at sundry times and in diverse manners spake in time
past under the fathers by the prophets now think about that God used the
prophets in the old time you know we can read about the prophets and we can read
about their prophecies but notice in verse 2 half in these last days spoken
unto us by his son and that wonderful and he says here whom he hath appointed
heir of all things by whom also he made the world who being the brightness of
his glory and express the image of his person and upholding all things by the
word of his power huh when he had by himself purged our sins sat down on the
right hand of the majesty on high being made so much better than the angels as
he hath by inheritance obtained a more excellent name than they he is not only
the creator but he is the Redeemer amen and that's an important truth when we
come to the book of Genesis and we see the entirety of the first 11 chapters of
the book of Genesis and if we if we allow the naysayer to deny the account
of creation then we open up the door for them to deny his role as Redeemer it is
so imperative that we understand that truth this evening because what's
happened far too many far too many professing to be followers of Jesus
Christ have said well they have more evidence than we do which by the way
they don't amen and there they have more degrees they have more whatever and so
we're just gonna kind of give it to them and yeah maybe that is how it happened
and all of a sudden we have undermined the authority of the Word of God and on
what basis do I have to stand and say by Adam sin came into the world and death
by sin because of Genesis 1 can be questioned then certainly Genesis 3 can
be questioned amen and we find here that in Hebrews 1 1 through 4 that he speaks
about Jesus Christ as the Creator by whom also he made the worlds in verse
number 2 he says in verse number 3 that he's upholding all things by the word of
his power think about that but then it says this in the end of verse number 3
when he had by himself purged our sins sat down on the right hand of the
majesty on high you just skip over right there from verse 3 and go to Hebrews
chapter 10 and you'll have a great time in the Word of God rejoicing in what
Jesus Christ did on the cross of Calvary and how this man after one sacrifice for
sins forever he said it is finished when he was hanging upon the cross of Calvary
amen
And what a blessing and we find that he is creator and he is Redeemer
We're talking about the fact that his work of creation is complete notice in Revelation chapter 4 if you will
We'll look at chapter 4
Chapter number 10 and chapter number 6 14, but look at chapter 4 first Revelation 4 and verse number 11
Revelation 4 and verse number 11 and the Bible says this
Thou art worthy. Oh Lord to receive glory and honor and power
For thou hast created all things and for thy pleasure. They are and were
created
Go over to chapter number 10 if you will and look at verse number 6
Revelation 10 and verse 6
The Bible says this
The illustrious verse 5 with it and the angel which I saw stand upon the scene upon the earth lifted up his hand to heaven
And swear by him that liveth forever and ever
notice this who created heaven and the things that are that therein are and the earth and the things that therein are and
The sea and the things which are therein that there should be time no longer
We find once again the reference about the Creator God that he he said he swear by him that liveth forever
And ever who?
Created and then he talks about creating the heaven everything that's in the heaven the earth everything that's in the earth the sea and everything
That's in the sea. Amen. Turn over a couple of more pages chapter number 14. I
Can't hardly read my writing on this one. I hope I'm looking at the right verse
That's always a bad deal when you can't read your own writing. Amen
Revelation 14 in verse number 6
I saw another angel fly in the midst of heaven having the everlasting
Gospel to preach unto them that dwell on the earth and every nation and kindred and tongue and people saying with a loud voice
Fear God and give glory to him for the hour of his judgment has come and worship him
That made heaven and earth and the sea and the fountains of waters
There followed another angel saying Babylon has fallen has fallen the great city
Because she had made all nations drink of the wine of the wrath of her fornication
We notice that that loud voice of that one that was flying that angel in verse 7. This is fear God and
We find these as in give glory to him
For the hour of his judgment has come and worship him that made heaven and earth and the sea and the fountains of waters
he is the creator and
Here in Genesis chapter number 2 when we come to the the record here that God gives us of this seventh day
He says thus the heavens and the earth
were finished and
all the host of them
We find that he says on the seventh day in verse number 2
God ended his work
Which he had made he rested on the day on the seventh day from all his work
Which he had made and God blessed the seventh day and sanctified it because that in it
He had rested from all his work which God created and made
Notice as we look at this text of Scripture that not only does God declare that his creative work is complete
But we find as we look at verses 2 and 3 that God
Made a designation of the seventh day
Notice the designation of the seventh day in verses 2 and 3 he speaks about this seventh day and on the seventh day in each
of the
six days that are referenced in Genesis 1 1 through 31
The Bible tells us about the creative work that took place on that particular day
And it tells us in the more and the evening in the morning were the first day
We're the second day so on and so forth and we find that God reveals to us that
Which he did the work that he did on those particular days
but we come to the seventh day and we find that God said that his work was finished and
That he had ended his work and that he had rested from that
From his work which he had created and made and so we find this designation of the seventh day. Let me say this
It's important for us to understand this evening that God wasn't tired
Amen, he didn't need rest. He's God
Amen
He's not a God that is on a journey. He's not a God. That's asleep
That's not the God that we serve we find that Elijah is mocking the followers of Baal with that type of
terminology because of the fact that Baal wasn't answering them and they were pleading and pleading and he says he's on a journey maybe
He's asleep, right?
You're familiar with the text of Scripture over there in first Kings and we find here that God he did not need rest
He wasn't tired. He's God
But we must understand that in the designation of the seventh day that rather what God was doing was he's establishing a pattern
That he would refer to often for the nation of Israel now
We understand that we are not the nation of Israel
But we understand that as we look at this text of Scripture and we notice the pattern that God
Establishes that he worked he created on those six days and then we come to the seventh day
The work is finished
The work is completed and the Bible tells us that he rested on the seventh day from all his work
Which he had made notice with me some New Testament verses are assuming some Old Testament
References to this this thought of the seventh day and the designation thereof
Turn to the Exodus chapter number 16 if you will
Exodus chapter number 16 and I'll try to wrap up quickly here this evening in Exodus chapter number 16
You find the account of the children of Israel after they had gone through the Red Sea
They had crossed the Red Sea. They had worshipped the Lord
The Song of Deliverance has been sung they had no water at the end of chapter 15
God gives them water that water of course was
Bitter water and God told him what to do to make it drinkable and so on and so forth and we come to the 16th
Chapter and it's here in Exodus chapter number 16 that God reveals to us
The way in which he would
Sustain his people by the use of manna
Now we understand that if you would look at manna throughout the Old Testament that the people of God came to hate manna
They complained about manna
They said there's nothing to eat but this manna that we just ate right because they just got done eating it
But yet they say there's nothing for us to eat and God
Supernaturally provided them with this manna
It was miraculous how God gave them the manna and God establishes here in Exodus chapter number 16
We don't have time to develop all of it this evening, but we find that God
Gave them instruction for gathering. They were to gather each day, correct? And
They were not permitted to store it from one day to the next
Correct what happened if they did because there were some people that were just rebellious and they went out on day number one and they
Gathered more than they needed to
Anyway, and what happened?
Red worms it stank right and they learned their lesson quickly and they no longer went and gathered
But here's what God said that on this sixth day. What were they supposed to do?
Gather double why because you're not supposed to go out on the seventh day to gather now
What happens to those same group of rebels that decided on day number one that they were gonna gather twice?
It didn't work out
well for him at bread worms at stank and so on day number six, they didn't go and gather what they're supposed to and
They were a mess and really what happens is God was trying to teach them this principle of faith
If you obey me, yeah if on day number one you gather double it's gonna breed worms
But if you obey me on day number six and you gather double like I'm telling you to
It'll keep because I'm God
Isn't amazing his I mean, it's it's spectacular when you look at how God was proving himself and
Proving what he could do and how he could work the people that did not gather double on day number six
They went out on the morning looking for it. What's going on? There's nothing here
Yeah, we told you there was not gonna be anything
They didn't believe and
So God was establishing this principle and he was referring back to this thing of the Sabbath the seventh day
Notice this that the seventh day is listed here
And spoken about with regard to the gathering of manna prior to the law being given in Exodus 20
Right in Exodus 20 turn over there
If you will in Exodus chapter 20 verses 8 through 11 is where we see about the Ten Commandments in this commandment about the law
about the Sabbath
That's given to us in the Ten Commandments notice notice in Exodus 20 in verse number 8
Remember the Sabbath day to keep it holy
Notice what he says
Six days shalt thou labor and do all thy work
But the seventh day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God
In it thou shalt not do any work
Thou nor thy son or thy daughter thy man servant nor thy maidservant nor thy cattle nor thy stranger that is within thy gates
Now God could have stopped there, right? But notice what he says in verse number 11 for in six days
the Lord made heaven and earth the sea and all that in them is and
Rested the seventh day wherefore the Lord blessed the Sabbath
day and hallowed it. And so this is the pattern that God established in the week
of creation, right? And this is the reference that he's giving to his people
with regard to the Sabbath. Remember the Sabbath day to keep it holy. He gives
them the explanation of what they were to do, what they were not to do, and then
he gives them the example of what God did during the week of creation. He did
all the work in six days, but he rested on the seventh. Turn over just a few more
pages to chapter number 31, Exodus chapter number 31, and notice in verses
12 through 18. We'll read this text of scripture, I'll make a couple of
comments, and we'll close this evening. In Exodus 31 verses 12 through 18, the
Bible says this, and the Lord spake unto Moses saying, Speak thou also unto the
children of Israel saying, Verily my Sabbath, my Sabbaths ye shall keep. For
it is a sign between me and you throughout your generations that you may
know that I am the Lord that doth sanctify you. You shall keep the Sabbath
therefore, for it is holy unto you. Everyone that defileth it shall surely
be put to death. For whosoever doeth any work therein, thou shall, that soul shall
be cut off from among his people. Six days may work be done, but in the seventh
is the Sabbath of rest. Holy to the Lord, whosoever doeth any work in the Sabbath
day, he shall surely be put to death. Wherefore the children of Israel shall
keep the Sabbath, to observe the Sabbath throughout their generations for a
perpetual covenant. It is a sign between me and the children of Israel forever.
For in six days the Lord made heaven and earth, and on the seventh day he rested
and was refreshed, and he gave unto Moses when he had made an end of communing
with him upon Mount Sinai, two tables of testimony, tables of stone written with
the finger of God. And we find that God gives this pattern. The pattern is
established in Genesis 1 and 2, the first three verses into the second
chapter of Genesis establish this pattern of six days work and the Sabbath
a Sabbath of rest. Now let me say this, there are some today that are confused
about this subject of the Sabbath and the meaning of the Sabbath and so on and
so forth. We read there in Exodus 31 there's a sign forever between God and
Israel. We understand in New Testament Christianity that they worshipped on the
first day. Amen? And that's why we worship, that's why we worship, I mean
we're to worship the Lord daily, but that's why we gather together for
worship on the first day of the week and thus here today. And we find that
certainly there's some confusion among some with regard to that. We see it in
the book of John, chapter number 20, 21, you see reference to that. Paul mentions
it in 1st Corinthians 16 about on the first day of the week when you're
gathered together about the collection for the Saints and it's important that
we understand that. But God was setting forth a pattern in this designation of
the seventh day. As we look at the completion here of Genesis 2, 1 through
3, we find that God declared his creative work complete. Amen? And we find that he
designated that seventh day and he would use that designation that we find here
in Genesis 1 and into the first three verses of chapter 2 as reference for the
nation of Israel many times going forward with regard to the Sabbath and
their behavior with regard to their work week and how he would reference and give
as an example his work of creation. I am thankful this evening that God is the
creator and that his work is complete. And yes, in his infinite wisdom, in his
eternality, he was able to create these kinds with the ability within their
genetic code to adapt to certain climates and to see those horizontal, if
you will, changes and variations within their kind, but no allowance for any
vertical type of evolution from one kind to some other kind. And that's what God
did. And it's amazing when we look at the whole of Scripture, and I mean there's
so many other verses that we could look at this evening, but when we really go to
the Word of God and allow ourselves to read those verses and to see what God
has said and to simply stand in awe of who he is. He's a wonderful God and he
did it just like he said he did. Amen? And what a wonderful truth that he is
creator and I'm thankful this evening that he is redeemer as well. Let's pray
together.