32. Genesis chapter number 32. Genesis 32. I'm going to be looking this evening at the
latter part of the passage of Scripture of this chapter, verses 24 through 32. Last week
we had the opportunity to study the first 23 verses and we dealt with Jacob as he prepared
to meet Esau and obeying the instruction that the Lord had given him, Jacob was returning
home and the Bible tells us that he sent messengers ahead and as he sent those messengers
ahead they returned to him saying that we came to thy brother Esau and he's coming to
meet you and he's got 400 men with him. And of course that caused Jacob to have a measure
of concern because his last encounter with Esau was of course after he had stolen the
blessing and the deception and all that took place and Esau said I'm going to kill him
after I'm done mourning the death of my father. And of course mom told him to go away for
a short time, it turned into over 20 years and we find that Jacob then hears this information
and after hearing about Esau coming and having the men with him we find as we dealt with
last week that he seeks the face of the Lord and then he prepares a present for Esau and
strategically set up the camp. We're told in verse number 24 of our text of Scripture
that the Bible says this and he took them, sorry in verse 24, and Jacob was left alone.
Just pause there for a moment, we'll read the rest of the verse and down through the
end of the chapter in just a moment but I want you to think about all that's just taken
place as Jacob is seeking to obey the instruction that the Lord has given to return to the land
of his fathers and he comes to this place, he sends these messengers, he hears that Esau's
coming and the band of men that are with him and he's concerned, he's troubled, he has
this thought that Esau's going to do him harm, perhaps even killing his wives and children
and we find that Jacob is now in a position where the Bible says that he's left alone.
There's a little doubt in my mind that Jacob is full of concern. I believe that if I could
look in in this passage and thinking about Jacob and what we know about him, I would
say that even if this did not transpire the way that it does, that it would be some trouble
for Jacob to sleep this evening.
Ever have a sleepless night, just struggling with something, something's on your mind,
on your heart, something that you're concerned about and Jacob here, I believe that he was
full of concern and his reunion with his brother Esau drew near. The Bible tells us that when
he's left there alone, notice what the Bible says in verse 24,
And there wrestled a man with him until the breaking of the day.
That's a long night. The Bible says in verse 25,
And when he saw that he prevailed not against him, he touched the hollow of his thigh. The
hollow of Jacob's thigh was out of joint as he wrestled with him. And he said, Let me
go, for the day breaketh. And he said, I will not let thee go, except thou bless me. And
he said unto him, What is thy name? And he said, Jacob. And he said, Thy name shall be
called no more Jacob, but Israel. For as a prince hast thou power with God and with men,
and hast prevailed. And Jacob asked him and said, Tell me, I pray thee, thy name. And
he said, Wherefore is it that thou dost ask my name? And he blessed him there. And Jacob
called the name of the place Penuel. For I have seen God face to face, and my life
is preserved. And he passed over Penuel. The sun rose upon him, and he halted upon his
thigh. Therefore the children of Israel eat not of the sinew which shrank, which is upon
the hollow of the thigh unto this day, because he touched the hollow of Jacob's thigh, and
the sinew that shrank.
Now as we look at this passage of Scripture, I've titled the message Jacob's Encounter
with God. It was a long night. It was a life-altering night. You think about all that had transpired
in these hours that God records for us, and there's just a few verses of Scripture that
detail it for us, but I consider how this long night turned into a life-altering night
for Jacob. As we look at this text of Scripture, I believe that God gives us three specific
things that would serve as reminders in Jacob's life. By the way, we need reminders in our
lives. We need to be reminded of God's blessing, of God's goodness. It's good for us to set
up memorials. Obviously this isn't Memorial Day type of time of year. We're in February,
and we have Memorial Day as a nation in May, but we understand that throughout the Bible
as you read the pages of Scripture that often you will read of memorials that had been set
up. The purpose of being reminded of something so that some event did not lose its impact
upon the people, so that they would not forget about it. As human beings, we have a tendency
to forget. We have a tendency to forget the blessings that God has bestowed upon us. We
begin to deal with a particular storm and a difficulty in our lives, and we forget about
how good God has been and what God has done in our lives. We find this evening that as
we look at a number of, or as we could reference a number of memorials throughout the Scripture,
I believe here as we look at this text of Scripture, that in Jacob's life personally,
there are three things that would serve as a reminder, continual reminder to this man
of this night, his encounter with God. Notice with me as you look at the text of Scripture,
notice the first of these three reminders. The first is a name change, a name change.
The Bible tells us in verse number 26, and he said,
Let me go, for the day breaketh. And he said, I will not let thee go, except thou bless me.
In verse 27, it says, And he said unto him, What is thy name? And he said, Jacob. Now Jacob knew
that was his name. Just as I were to ask each of you this evening, what's your name? You know
what your name is. You've carried that name with you, and you know, you have an understanding. And
we find that Jacob answers the question. And he says that his name is Jacob. And I want you to
notice in verse 28, the Bible tells us that he said, Thy name shall be called no more Jacob,
but Israel. He'd had this name for a long time, his whole life up until this point. There's some
interesting data that you could look at to try to figure out about how old Jacob is at this
particular time. But he'd had this name, and you think about having a name change. You look
throughout the remainder portion of the book of Genesis, and you look back, and you begin to think
about how Jacob would be referred to. In fact, many times he's still referred to as Jacob. He's
not always exclusively referred to as Israel from this point forward. There are many times in which
he's referenced as Jacob, but you will find times in which he is referenced as Israel. I begin to
think about this passage of Scripture, and this reminder for Jacob, and the significance of this
name change. And as we begin to think about this, and I want you to think about how often you hear
your name. Someone asks you, what's your name? When Jacob would travel, when he'd go to Egypt,
and near the end of his life, hey, what's your name? And you think about the interactions that
we have, one with another. And I believe that any time that Jacob would say his name was Israel,
it serves as a reminder, a reminder of this night when his name changed. Anyone ever ask you how you
got your name? How'd you get your name? Sometimes we get our name, maybe it's just because our
parents liked the name, and there's really no good story behind it. But sometimes there's a
particular story behind it. I'm a junior, and obviously there's some level of significance
with being a junior, and the name that I bear being that of my dad. And several people have
asked us why we didn't name our son Christopher so that he'd be the third. Well, because Joseph is
my favorite Bible character. And so therefore, I desired that if God would give us a son,
that his name would be Joseph. And beside that, I don't like my middle name. But the reality is
that, you know, you talk about Julianna and Brianna, we really don't have any good reason
as to, there's no real thought behind it, except for Holly and I like the names. It was a good
thing we didn't have another girl, because we couldn't agree on another third girl's name that
ended with Anna. And she had one desire, I had a different, and then God gave us a boy, amen? And
so it all worked out. We talked to some people, and there's some real significance with their
name. And I want you to think about biblical times. I want you to think about other cultures and just
the opportunity within a number of cultures, even still to this very day, that there's much
significance with regard to their name. In here, the Bible says that thy name shall be called no
more Jacob, but Israel. For as a prince hast thou power with God and with men, and hast prevailed.
I think about the name change. What a reminder, a reminder for this man. I think about the
significance here, and obviously thinking about Israel, this new name that he would have,
and obviously thinking about the nation and all of the significance throughout the remainder of
Scripture and what have you. But as I begin to think about this significance of this particular
time in the life of Jacob, and I think about the truth that we've looked at in previous portions
of Scripture in the book of Genesis, where the old man and the new man. I begin to think about
Jacob and Israel, and thinking about this encounter with God, and thinking about
all of the significance.
This evening, this name change
would serve as a reminder
of what happened,
this encounter that he had with God.
I notice not only a name change,
but I notice a location.
I want you to note with me
in verse number one of Genesis 32,
the Bible says that Jacob went on his way
and the angels of God met him.
When Jacob saw them, he said,
this is God's host.
And he called the name of that place
Mahanim or Mahanaim,
however you want to say that.
And you see, though,
in verse number 30,
that the Bible tells us
that Jacob called
the name of the place Penuel.
I've seen God face to face
in my life that's preserved.
It's then referred to
in verse number 31 as Penuel.
And we find that the Bible tells us
that he passed over Penuel
and the sun arose upon him.
There's no more reference
about this particular place
in Jacob's life and Israel's life
that he ever visited this place again.
As you study scripture,
you're not going to find any references
to Jacob, Israel
with regard to this particular location.
But I do want you to think
about the significance
of naming this place.
And the Bible says
that he chose the name,
that he called the name of the place.
Now, you and I,
we don't typically have
the opportunity to name a city
what we want to name it.
Well, we don't have that privilege.
We don't have that opportunity
in the day and age in which we live.
But there were times in human history
when that has happened,
that people, as they would go
and they would settle
particular pieces of land
and they would go and and move out,
they would be able to name towns
and name cities.
And we find the significance of that.
You can read it throughout scripture
and other aspects and other people.
But here we find that Jacob,
because of the experience that he had,
because of this encounter with God,
because of all that had taken place,
this this long night
that was a life altering night.
The Bible says that
that his name was changed
and his his name would be Israel.
But the Bible says that
he named the place
and it's significant
what he named the place.
So that's what the Bible says.
For I have seen God face to face
and my life is preserved.
It's interesting, as we know,
the name that Jacob, Israel
would choose to name this place
and the significance of that name
and what Jacob would understand.
I begin to think about
in the life of Jacob
and any time that he would consider
a place that he's been.
And maybe even as we have opportunity
from time to time
to talk about travels
in different places that we've been.
I think that Jacob, Israel,
would hold this place
as a very special place
in his heart, in his life.
Why? Because of what happened there.
And he didn't just leave that place
and move forward
and go and meet his brother,
as we read in chapter 33,
the reunion that is mentioned there.
But we find that he took the time
and God took the time to record for us
that Jacob named this place.
So we see that there's a name change.
There's a location that is named.
But I really want to focus
on this last thought this evening.
I think it's the most significant
reminder in the life of Israel, Jacob.
The Bible tells us
that there wrestled a man with him
in verse 24,
to the breaking of the day.
It tells us in verse number 25.
And when he saw that he prevailed
not against him,
notice what the Bible says.
He touched the hollow of his thigh.
And the hollow of Jacob's thigh
was out of joint
as he wrestled with him.
It says in verse number 31
that as he passed over Penuel,
the sun rose upon him.
Notice what it says.
And he halted upon his thigh.
Talk about a name change, a location.
But I want you to think about a limp.
A limp.
The Bible tells us that he halted
upon his thigh.
The Bible tells us that God,
this no doubt a pre-incarnate
of Christ, a Christophanes, if you will.
We see that the book of Hosea
of references in the 12th chapter,
this particular encounter.
And we find here that Jacob,
though he asks the name,
the the Lord does not give him his name,
for we know that it's
you already know who I am.
Because he says in verse number 30,
as he names the place Penuel,
for I have seen God face to face
and my life is preserved.
Yet he'd asked him his name.
And we find that God
did not give him his name
for God had made it clear
who it was that wrestled with him that night.
And the Bible tells us
God touched
the hollow of his thigh.
And God tells us
that the hollow of Jacob's thigh
was out of joint.
And then he halted upon his thigh.
No doubt this limp
that Israel would have.
I would argue,
not sure that you could be dogmatic about it,
but I would argue that he had this limp
for the remainder of his days.
I want you to think about
the remainder of his days
and the limp that he would have
in the constant reminder
that that limp would provide
in Israel's life.
I want you to think about Israel
as he would walk from place to place.
You know, they didn't have automobiles.
They walked.
Occasionally they'd ride on animals, right?
They'd get a donkey or a camel
or whatever it would be.
But a lot of times
they walked from place to place
and had a limp.
And every time he'd walk,
every time he'd be thinking about that limp,
you're reminded
of this encounter that he had with God.
I want you to think about this.
You ever see somebody that has a limp?
Somebody that you know.
Maybe even somebody that you don't know.
You see him with a limp.
And maybe I know sometimes I do this in my own life,
especially if I know the person.
I'll say something like this.
What happened?
You ever do that?
You inquire.
Armando comes walking in here.
He's got a limp.
I said, Armando, what happened?
Can you imagine Israel?
What happened?
What does it immediately remind him
of this encounter that he has with God
and how God touched the hollow of his thigh?
And as I mentioned a moment ago,
I would argue that he had this limp
for the remainder of his days,
that he would be reminded
of what God did that night,
that encounter that he had.
The Bible tells us, turn to the book of Hebrews,
if you will, in the 11th chapter.
We know that Israel had an opportunity.
It lived for a number of years after this encounter.
Has a great reunion with his brother Esau in chapter 33.
We'll study that in the next couple of weeks.
And we find that eventually,
after a number of events transpire,
that he ends up going to Egypt.
We're familiar with that.
We understand what takes place.
It's the opportunity to be able to be there in Egypt
and he meets Pharaoh and he's in the presence of Pharaoh
and all of these things that take place.
But I think that for Israel,
this limp would serve as a reminder.
See, none of us like to limp.
It's kind of a hindrance to limp, isn't it?
You know what I mean?
Natalie came in this morning.
She hurt her ankle playing basketball yesterday.
She's got crutches.
Natalie, is it easy getting up and down the stairs
with those crutches?
No, it's more difficult, right?
You wanna get rid of the crutches, right?
But you're using the crutches because you're injured,
because you have a...
And so you think about Mr. Don,
you see him so often with a cane
and he's got that bad knee and he walks with that limp
and it's a hindrance.
He says to me often, he'll say,
if I could just get this knee replaced, I could run again.
But this limp, more than being a hindrance,
would be a reminder in the life of Israel.
The Bible tells us in Hebrews 11,
the great hall of faith chapter,
notice what the Bible says in verse number 21,
by faith Jacob, when he was a dying,
this is when he's in Egypt,
he blessed both the sons of Joseph and worshiped.
Notice what the Bible says,
leaning upon the top of his staff.
I know and I understand that many people would use a staff,
whether they had a limp or not,
but I think that this staff that Israel had
from this day forward served more than one purpose.
Helped give him stability because of this limp,
because of the fact that God touched the hollow of his thigh
and the Bible tells us that he blessed the sons of Joseph
and he was leaning upon that staff.
This evening, I wonder in our lives,
I wonder, are there some reminders that God has given us?
Are there some things in our lives
that we've set up as memorials?
I'm thankful that I've not had this kind of limp
that Jacob, Israel has in our text of scripture,
but wouldn't it be wonderful
if God would give us something like that,
that would serve as a constant reminder
of our encounter with God.
I'm thankful that God met with Jacob.
Jacob was there and he prayed as we mentioned last week
and he had gone through the process
of preparing the present to send to his brother
and strategically setting up the camp
and he was left there alone and he was left there alone,
there wrestled with him a man, pre-incarnate Christ.
And we find that this.
This particular encounter would change his life forever.
It was a long night, but it was a life-altering night.
What's your name?
Israel.
How did you get that name?
Can you imagine immediately the thoughts?
He didn't get it from his parents.
He wasn't named Israel at his birth.
He was Jacob, but his name was changed.
No longer shall your name be called Jacob, but Israel.
Where did that happen?
What happened to this place?
Actually I named the place, and I gave it a name that was significant because it was
at that place that I saw God face-to-face and my life was preserved.
Have you ever been to that place?
Have you ever been to Penuel?
Can you imagine?
Just think about Israel having these conversations.
You notice the limp everywhere you go.
You're not getting better.
It's not going to recover.
No, God's left me this way to remind me.
Think about the truth of 2 Corinthians chapter number 12.
We often think about the Apostle Paul.
The Bible tells us that he had a thorn in the flesh.
You read that passage.
Look over there just briefly, 2 Corinthians chapter 12.
Here's what the Bible tells us in this portion of Scripture, and I see the Apostle Paul as
he is seeking to have relief from this, and no doubt we each would probably pray the same
way that Paul prayed, that he would be delivered.
The Bible tells us in 2 Corinthians 12 and verse number 6, for though I would desire
to glory, I shall not be a fool, for I will say the truth.
But now I forbear, lest any man should think of me above that which he seeth me to be,
that he heareth of me.
And lest I should be exalted above measure through the abundance of the revelations,
there was given to me a thorn in the flesh, the messenger of Satan, to buffet me, lest
I should be exalted above measure.
For this thing I have assaulted the Lord thrice, that it might depart from me.
I don't blame him.
I don't think you would either.
But notice what the Bible says in verse number 9, the answer to this request.
The Lord said to him, My grace is sufficient for thee, for My strength is made perfect
in weakness.
Most gladly, notice what Paul says, most gladly therefore will I rather glory in my
infirmities that the power of Christ may rest upon me.
Paul had this thorn in the flesh as a reminder for him that God's grace was sufficient.
As a reminder to him, he says, most gladly therefore will I rather glory in my infirmities.
Notice in verse 10, therefore I take pleasure in infirmities.
Wow, he's glorying in infirmities and he's taking pleasure in infirmities.
We need to go back to school with Paul, amen, seriously, because typically that's not my
nor your response to infirmities.
In reproaches and necessities and persecutions and distresses, notice what he says, for Christ's
sake, for when I am weak, then am I strong.
From when I am weak, then I am strong.
This evening, when I look at the latter portion of Genesis chapter 32, this encounter that
Jacob has with God, it's a life-altering evening, it's a long night.
The Bible says they left alone, but they wrestled a man with him until the breaking of the day.
It's a long night, it's a life-changing night.
I wonder this evening, I know that our name hasn't been changed.
None of us have a limp as a result of the same thing that Jacob has dealt with, none
of us have named a city that I'm aware of, but I wonder tonight, are there some things
that God has done in your life, some memorials that you can think of, something that you
can set up and say, this is a reminder for me of what God has done for me, that I would
not get to a place where I forget who I serve, who He is, what He's done for me, that I would
not be exalted above measure, as Paul says in 2 Corinthians chapter number 12.
See, we need some memorials in our lives, and these three things are very tangible things
that God did specifically in Israel's life that serve as reminders, but each one of us
need reminders.
We need to be reminded of our time with God.
Do you remember the day that you got saved?
I hope you do.
So often when I talk to people about being saved, I encourage them to write down the
date.
I know that not all of us remember the date that we got saved.
Maybe no one encouraged you to write that date down, but I wrote the date down when
I got saved, someone encouraged me to do so.
And so I don't really celebrate in the same sense of using that word, but I twice a year
think about a birthday.
I have a physical birthday, it's in July, but more importantly, I have a spiritual birthday,
it's in August.
I know the date, my family knows the date, and on that day, they'll say, happy spiritual
birthday.
It's a blessing to me, it's a reminder for me, because on that day, my life changed,
my life changed.
You might not remember the exact day, but I hope you can remember the circumstances
surrounding.
You can think about, oh, that's when I met the Lord, my life changed.
And in a certain sense, He gave us a new name, because we identify with Christ.
When you trust in Christ, you're a Savior, you become a Christian.
Identifying with the Lord Jesus Christ, He is my Savior, I'm His child.
What a blessing.
I know that we don't walk around and say, my name is Christian, unless your name really
is Christian.
But I'll tell you one thing, when I meet somebody named Christian, I'll say, hey, that's a good
name.
Do you know what it means to be a Christian?
It's a great opportunity, it's their name.
In fact, anyone that I find that has a name that's a Bible name, say, man, that's a great
Bible name, do you know about them?
Well, I don't have any idea.
That's typically the response I get.
They were called Christians first at Antioch, that's what the Bible tells us in the book
of Acts.
And we bear His name because of what He's done in our lives.
And this evening, I hope that we would have, as we look at this passage, just a few verses
of an encounter that Jacob, who became Israel that night, had with God.
God gave him those reminders.
And for us this evening, I hope that you have some things that you can be reminded of, of
your time with God, that encounter when you trust that Christ is your Savior, oh, that
we never forget it, that we never lose sight of it, that we never get over our salvation,
that we would rejoice greatly in who we are in Christ.
We are new creatures, we've been transformed, we're heaven-bound in that wonderful...
Let's pray together.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
We thank You for the privilege that You've given us to study this portion of Scripture,
to look at the life of Jacob.
And this night, He's so concerned about so many things.
His reunion with His brother, Drunai, and you met with Him, You changed His name.
He named a place, and He left with a limp.
God, I pray, I believe this evening that Israel came to a place in His life where He had an
appreciation for that limp because of what it reminded Him of, appreciation for His name
because of what it reminded Him of.
God, I pray that You would help us this evening to have some memorials, some reminders in
our lives.
Thank You for meeting with us.
Thank You for saving us.
Lord, we thank You for the opportunity even this evening as we will observe the Lord's
Supper here in just a moment, the table of memorial, this due and remembrance of me is
what You said.
Lord, we're so thankful for the privilege, the opportunity that we have to observe the
Lord's Supper.
I pray that You'd meet with us in a special way these next few moments.
I pray that as we have a time of invitation that we would examine ourselves, that we would
be prepared spiritually for the observing of the Lord's Supper.
We pray that You'd move and work during these few moments of invitation as only You can.
We'll thank You for it.
In Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?