same passage last week on Wednesday evening if you were here and you'll
recall that we were looking at the great miracle that's recorded here. We looked
really at verses 17 through 27 and as we studied that portion of Scripture last
Wednesday evening I made it known that we would look at verses 28 and 29 this
evening and so here we are Mark 9 we'll be looking at verses 28 and 29. Last week
when we examine this miracle that's recorded here in Mark 9, we're reminded
there's a father that had a son and brought his son initially to the
disciples and brought a son to the disciples and desired that they
would cast out that devil and the Bible tells us at the end of verse number 18
they could not so therefore this man this man that was in great desperation
because of the circumstances and all that he was dealing with comes to Jesus
and he says to the Lord he says if thou can't do anything and we talked about
that last week that our God can do all things and what a blessing to know that
he said if thou can't do anything and he made two requests have compassion on us
and help us and what a blessing to know that our God is compassionate and that
he is a very present help at the time of trouble and we focused on that and the
Lord said back to that man if thou can't believe all things are possible to him
that believeth and the man in full transparency with tears makes a
declaration that we again focused on he said Lord I believe help thou mine
unbelief and so what did he do in that statement well really two things in that
full transparency he not only declared his faith I believe but he also declared
his doubt help thou mine unbelief and I said this last week that honestly if we
would look at the declaration of that man in verse 24 that many of us can
relate to that that we can understand that yes we believe God but then we have
that side of us that we look at the circumstances and sometimes the
mountains right in front of us are big and they're they're they're overwhelming
and we can have that that doubt that can creep in and so the Lord Jesus Christ he
demonstrates his power we find that the duff the the dumb and deaf spirit were
commanded not only to exit from this man but the Bible tells us that they
were that devil was to enter no more into him and what a blessing to think
about this great miracle and the power of the Lord Jesus Christ that was
displayed but we noticed that the disciples were part of this the
disciples were the ones that were first approached by this father and the
disciples were there as eyewitnesses they heard everything they observed
everything they were there throughout the process of this miracle and as we
come to verse 28 the Bible says and when he was come into the house his disciples
asked him privately why could not we cast him out and he Jesus said unto them
the disciples this kind can come forth by nothing but by prayer and fasting as
we look at this passage of Scripture I'm gonna preach a message that I've titled
if you want the title it's because of your unbelief because of your unbelief
and we'll look at it as we get into the message this evening but we find that as
we look here verses 28 and 29 and we have the the account fresh in our minds
we studied it last week if you were here I just very quickly rehearsed all that
transpired this great miracle but we find that we come to verses 28 and 29
and as we look at these verses I notice first of all if you're taking notes the
inquiry in verse number 28 God provides for us a record of the inquiry that
takes place who's the one who are the ones that are inquiring well it's the
disciples for we find that here the Bible says that his disciples asked they
inquired and we would say a couple of things number one it was a private
inquiry the Bible says that they asked him privately this was something that
maybe there was some uncertainty they didn't want anyone else to hear whatever
they come privately they get alone with the Lord by the way in the wonderful
thing to get alone with God and they're alone with the Lord Jesus Christ and they
they make this in inquiry and we find that not only is it private but it's
very direct notice the question that's asked in Mark 9 in verse 28 why could
not we cast him out it's a very direct question it's a very pointed question
and we find that as we look at the inquiry that is made here in Mark
chapter number 9 there's a reason that the disciples asked the question yes we
understand that in verse number 18 that the father brings the son and he brings
him to the disciples and it says very plainly at the end of verse number 18
that they should cast him out that was the desire that was the request of the
father but it says they could not but hold your place here in Mark chapter 9
and I want you to go back to Mark chapter number 3 go back to Mark chapter
number 3 there's a reason that they make the inquiry that they make and we come
to Mark chapter number 3 and it's not just because they were not able to it's
not because they could not it's because when we look at Mark chapter number 3 if
you notice in verse number 13 the Bible says that he speaking of the Lord Jesus
Christ mark 3 in verse 13 and he goeth up into a mountain and calleth unto him
whom he would and they came unto him and he ordained 12 so this would be that
same group of people and then the disciples these are the ones that are in
Mark chapter number 3 he calls them he's in this desert place a mountain the
Bible tells us in verse number 13 and he calls them he ordains them and notice it
says that they should be with him what a blessing it is to be with the Lord and
then it says this and that he might send them forth to preach their primary task
they would go out to preach and what a blessing we too have been given that
responsibility to go and preach the gospel but I want you to notice
specifically in verse 15 and to have power to number one heal sickness and
number two notice it says and to cast out devils so in Mark chapter number
three these disciples were called to the Lord those that he called we see he
ordained them he gave them their primary task of going forth to preach
and he said to them that they had power to heal sickness and to cast out devils
now I want you to keep that in mind as we're looking at this account in Mark
chapter number 9 because in Mark chapter number 9 the Bible says that the father
comes and they desire the father's desires that you would cast out the
devil and they could not thus they asked the Lord Jesus Christ privately in this
inquiry why could not we cast him out they knew what happened in Mark chapter
number 3 they understood that the interaction in Mark chapter number 3 but
yet in this moment they were not able to do this now think about this with me
this evening if someone were to come to you to ask you something that you knew
you did not have the power to do you would say you got to go you know if the
disciples knew they didn't have the power to do it they would say thanks for
coming but you got to talk to Jesus right but Jesus had said they had
authority or power not only to heal sickness but to cast out devils but in
the moment they could not so they make the inquiry why could we not like we
were there in Mark 3 we understood it but but when it came to it why could we
not do this so that gives us some understanding as to why they're making
the inquiry that they are and I would say this it's a good thing to do so
right it's a good thing if God's told us I'll use this example if God's told us
that were to be fruitful and we look at our own lives and we examine we say
there's no fruit in my life it's good for us to get alone with God and say God
why am I not fruitful right does that make sense and so we find here that they
come to Jesus privately and very direct or pointedly and they say why could not
we cast him out the inquiry now I want you to see number two the indictment the
indictment we don't see it here in Mark chapter number nine but one of the
beautiful things about the Gospels is that we have the opportunity to look at
parallel passages and events accounts that are recorded and at times it's no
contradiction it's no problem we find that these writers are writing from
different perspectives and they see different things they recall different
things and if you hold your place here in Mark 9 but turn over to Matthew
chapter 17 if you will and I want you to see it's the same miracle the same
account but I want you to see that in Matthew's account God gives us some
insight here that is helpful for us as we consider the indictment because they
ask the question now if you're gonna ask the question you better be prepared for
the answer amen search me O Lord okay be ready for what the results are so
they say why could not we cast him out we see it in Matthew 17 look in verse
number 18 and Jesus rebuked the devil and he departed out of him and the child
was cured from that very hour then came the disciples to Jesus apart and said
why could not we
He passed him out, you see it's the same parallel passages, Mark 9.
And Jesus said unto them, notice the words,
because of your unbelief.
Because of your unbelief.
Now Jesus is God, He cannot lie.
What Jesus says is true.
Amen?
So these disciples can't just disagree.
Say, no, no, that's not true.
No, Jesus said because of your unbelief,
so that means they had unbelief.
There was an issue in their heart.
And there was unbelief, there was doubt.
And Jesus is exposing that.
Let me say this, sometimes the truth is hard.
But God doesn't give hard truth to hurt His people.
God gives truth to help us.
If God did not tell them about their unbelief,
they wouldn't know what to do in order to have greater faith.
Does that make sense?
So God loves us too much to leave us undone, right?
And so they come to the Lord,
Lord, why could not we cast him out?
Because of your unbelief.
Sometimes that is hard for us to receive.
Sometimes we are in a situation
where we think more highly of ourselves than we ought.
We think, no, no, I have more faith than maybe I really have.
And Jesus says because of your unbelief.
Now think about it with me.
As these disciples were there and witnessed
all that had transpired in this great miracle,
they heard Jesus say,
if thou canst believe, all things are possible.
They heard the man say, I believe, help thou mine unbelief.
Now the scriptures don't tell us how they handled that,
how they responded to that, how that affected them.
But now when they're privately with Jesus
and Jesus is answering them for the purpose of helping them,
Jesus says because of your unbelief.
Can I tell you that God gives the truth because God loves?
We live in a time, we live in an era of history
where we see it so prevalent all around us
that in the name of quote unquote love,
people are being accepting and accommodating
and telling people everything's gonna be okay
because in the name of love, we don't wanna hurt you.
No, no, no, that's not love.
Jesus is giving the truth, though it may be hard to receive,
he's giving the truth because he loves them.
And he wants them, he desires for them to believe.
Remember, we looked at John 11 last week,
and in John 11, we dealt with the fact
that God wants us to believe.
Martha believed, if you had been here,
my brother had not died.
I believe you have the power to heal.
But the power to raise them from the dead after four days?
Right?
God wants us to believe.
So he pointedly gives this indictment
because of your unbelief, and it causes us
to understand something important
when we begin to consider the fact
that we too must examine our own selves.
We must examine our own hearts, our own lives,
and we must come to that place where we say,
Lord, is there unbelief in my heart?
Lord, would you, like this man says in verse 24,
help thou mine unbelief?
I want my faith to increase.
If I don't know that there's unbelief,
if I'm deceived, if someone's lying to me,
then how am I gonna grow in my faith?
And so Jesus loves them enough to give them the truth
in order to help them, and he says,
because of your unbelief.
I hope this evening that as we would consider
even that response that Jesus gives to the disciples
with regard to their inquiry,
that we too would come to the place
where we would desire to get into the presence of God
and God to truly search us and show us,
and show us why, because I wanna live a life
that's pleasing to the Lord.
I wanna have my faith increased.
We read the scriptures, the New Testament
in the gospels, it talks about,
shall the son of man find faith on the earth
when he returns?
Without faith, it's impossible to please him.
We've referenced that verse in Hebrews 11
in verse number six several times.
We find that the Bible tells us and teaches us
the just shall live by faith.
The Christian life is a faith life.
It's a believing God life,
and the reality is that God has never failed.
He's got a perfect track record, amen?
He's never failed you.
We've failed him more times than we can count,
but he's never failed us, and he never will.
He's trustworthy, he wants us to believe him,
he wants us to have faith,
and yet the disciples are in this place
when you peel it all back and you look at the root cause,
it's because of your unbelief, because of your unbelief.
We find not only is there an inquiry and an indictment,
but we find that there's insight
that's given to us in verse 29,
and I hope that as we look at verse 29
that God will help us and challenge us
from the insight that is given
in this simple verse of scripture.
We see it also in Matthew 17 and verse 21,
but if you look here in Mark 9 and verse 29
that Jesus said unto them,
"'This kind can come forth by nothing,
"'but by prayer and fasting.'"
Before Jesus said that in Matthew 17 and verse 21
and verse 20 after he tells them because of your unbelief,
he says, if you have faith, if you believe.
Remember, he had said to that man
that came to him that had previously gone to the disciples,
if thou can't believe,
all things are possible to him that believeth.
And so as we find here in verse number 29
as the scriptures kind of portray for us
and reveal to us and give us this spiritual insight
that there's an obvious link
between faith, prayer, and fasting.
There's an obvious link in the scriptures.
And we find that here when we would think about
where Jesus says that this kind can come forth by nothing,
but by prayer and fasting,
we would say this,
that prayer and fasting is evidence of our faith.
Because I believe God, I'm going to pray.
Because I believe that God hears and answers,
I'm going to pray.
I believe that he is able, therefore I'm going to pray.
I've often said that prayer is really,
prayer is such a privilege for us as the people of God,
but prayer is our greatest expression of dependence.
Not only is prayer our greatest expression of dependence,
but in a very real way,
it's also our greatest expression of faith.
Because I'm going to God and I'm praying
and I'm asking the Lord to do what only God can do.
And on Wednesday nights, we've been having this theme,
this thought of a longing to see God work.
And we find that here as Jesus cast out this devil,
the disciples make this inquiry privately
and they say, why could not we cast him out?
And the indictment is given because of your unbelief,
but then the insight that Jesus provides instruction,
if you will,
that this kind can come forth by nothing,
but by prayer and fasting,
we see the obvious link.
And we would say this,
we talk often about prayer,
we don't talk enough about fasting.
Fasting demonstrates seriousness.
When you fast,
it's not that you kind of, you know,
earn God's favor in some fashion.
It's really just revealing the fact
that we're serious about this.
And fasting also is an expression of humility.
Notice if you will, what the Psalmist said,
turn to the book of Psalms in Psalm 35.
And I want you to notice what the Psalmist says there
in Psalm 35 about this fasting
and what he did and how he described it here.
We'll just look at one verse here in Psalm 35
in verse number 13.
And notice what the Psalmist says,
but as for me,
Psalm 35 in verse 13,
when they were sick,
my clothing was sackcloth.
Notice what he says,
I humbled my soul, how?
With fasting.
I humbled my soul with fasting
and then notice what the scriptures say,
and my prayer returned into my own bosom.
There's always this connection in the scriptures
between prayer and fasting.
The idea of fasting is that I'm seeking
to demonstrate my seriousness
and I'm seeking to get closer to God.
And I'm seeking in that time of fasting
that I'm gonna spend that time in prayer,
in the presence of God,
getting close to the Lord.
And we find that here,
the Psalmist says that I humbled,
he says, I humbled my soul with fasting.
Let me remind you that the Bible tells us
that God resisted the proud,
but he giveth grace unto the humble.
We read that in James.
We read that in 1 Peter, and we find that principle
throughout the scriptures, and so we find
that the psalmist is saying part of this process
of fasting is also an aspect of humility.
We find in Ezra, turn over to Ezra, if you will,
in chapter number eight, and I mentioned this
to the group this morning, that Ezra chapter eight
in this passage that I'm going to read to you
is such a convicting passage of scripture for me
as I note what transpires and what's going on here,
and we find that in Ezra chapter number eight,
and it's just one example, we can look at a number
of examples in the scriptures of those that fasted
and look at some of the aspects of fasting,
but I want you to notice in Ezra eight in verse 21,
the Bible says, then I proclaimed a fast there
at the river of Ahava that we might afflict ourselves
before our God, notice what it says,
to seek of him a right way for us and for our little ones
and for all our substance, and so they were seeking
the Lord, they needed direction, they were trying
to get to Jerusalem, they needed the Lord's direction,
the Lord's provision, the Lord's protection,
and we find that Ezra says I proclaimed a fast there,
and as they're fasting, they're seeking the Lord,
we find in verse 22, God gives us great insight
with regard to the logic and thinking as to why
they took the approach that they did in verse 22,
it says for I was ashamed to require of the king
a band of soldiers and horsemen to help us
against the enemy in the way, why?
Because we had spoken unto the king,
saying the hand of our God is upon all of them
for good that seek him, but his power and his wrath
is against all of them that forsake him,
so here's what he's saying, we were in the presence
of the king talking about how great our God is,
and now we're gonna depart, and I'm ashamed to ask
the king for a group of people, soldiers and horsemen
to accompany us and to give us safe passage, why?
Because I've just got done telling him how our God
is able to do that, and so I'm not, I'm ashamed,
is what he says in verse 22, to require of the king
a band of soldiers, why?
Because I've told the king how good our God is,
and so what are we gonna do?
Well, we're gonna seek God's face,
and we're gonna fast, the seriousness.
In verse 23, it says so we fasted and besought our God
for this, and notice what it says, he was entreated of us.
God delights in answering prayer, and when he sees
the heart of his servants that is humbled
and that is serious in seeking him,
and we've demonstrated that through fasting,
not only through prayer, but prayer and fasting,
and we've demonstrated that, that seriousness,
God gives answer, notice as you look at verse 31,
the Bible says then we departed from the river of Ahava,
and so we find that there was a time of fasting
and a time of seeking God, and God answered,
and so therefore they departed, and the Bible says
right there in the middle of verse 31,
and the hand of our God was upon us,
and he delivered us from the hand of the enemy.
Isn't that awesome?
God did what only God could do.
God answered as they sought his face,
and the Bible says in verse 32, and we came to Jerusalem.
That was the desired end, if you will.
That was the goal, and God safely brought them there,
and we find that there's this revelation to us
with regard to the heart of the people
in prayer and fasting, and so as we look at this
in Mark chapter number nine, and we see and we unfold
what has transpired with this great miracle
that is recorded, and with the disciples
at some level perhaps we could say being perplexed,
why could not we cast them out?
Like you gave us the authority back there
when we were on the mountain with you,
and yet when the opportunity was here,
and when the situation was before us,
we were not able.
What happened?
Is it God's fault?
Never, never, it was because of their unbelief,
and God says that this kind cometh forth
by nothing but by prayer and fasting.
In Luke's gospel, we looked at Luke nine last week,
we're not gonna turn over there again,
but in Luke chapter number 10, the disciples
are rejoicing that the spirits are made subject to them,
and they come back to Jesus, they're all excited,
they're rejoicing, man, even the spirits
are made subject unto us, and Jesus says
in this rejoice not, rather rejoice
that your names are written in heaven.
It gives us a great insight and understanding there
with regard to how we're rejoicing.
They're not rejoicing in Mark nine, they're perplexed.
Why could not we do this?
Why could not we cast him out?
I want you to notice again in Mark nine in verse 29.
And I hope I can effectively communicate
this truth to you this evening.
As we look at this in verse 29, the Bible says
this kind can come forth by nothing,
notice again, but by prayer and fasting.
Is that what your Bible says?
Do you know many of the modern translations today
take out the word fasting?
Yours is missing, yeah?
I tell, yeah, okay.
Another reason to get a King James Bible, amen?
Praise the Lord, hallelujah.
Any opportunity I get, amen?
No, but here's the deal.
I want you to think about this, and I hope
I can effectively communicate this tonight.
Two things that are going on, I see.
Number one, the modern translations
remove the word fasting.
What do we know about the enemy?
Well, all the way back in Genesis chapter number three,
he attacks the word of God, right?
Yea, hath God said.
So all the way back then, and the enemy knows
the effectiveness of prayer, and by the way,
also of this truth of prayer and fasting.
And so therefore, the modern translations
are removing fasting, right?
That's problematic.
We're messing with God's word, number one.
I believe that the Lord Jesus Christ
said exactly what he wanted to say, amen?
There was no extra, every word of God is pure.
He said exactly what he wanted to say.
He said this kind cometh forth by nothing
but by prayer and fasting, and it's very particular
that he said that, and I want you to understand
something that the enemy is attacking God's word,
and he's attacking God's word in this area
where God's saying there's something about
prayer and fasting that's a demonstration
and expression of our faith that shows
how much we believe what God is able to do,
and then fasting is removed.
It's a problem.
But then I want you to think about this.
And I want you to answer this question.
Fasting, historically and primarily,
is fasting a spiritual discipline, I'll use that word,
or a physical discipline?
Well, what would you say, spiritual or physical?
Both, okay, you could say that,
but primarily and historically, it would be spiritual.
It's spiritual.
In fact, if you were to do any kind of a search,
and I did some searching in kind of the history
of some things, and you would find this,
that historically it says fasting
is primarily a spiritual practice.
Not only is it something within Judaism and Christianity,
but there are plenty of world religions
that practice fasting.
Okay, it's very common in a lot of religions,
world religions, so on and so forth,
and I don't mean to use Christianity as a religion,
we set that apart, we're in a relationship with the Lord,
but using that word very broadly,
it's primarily, historically, a spiritual practice.
It says this of biblical Christian fasting,
it's a deeply ingrained practice for seeking God.
It's oftentimes paired with prayer,
as we've seen as we've looked at some of these things.
But I want you to understand that as we would consider
this evening, this aspect, listen,
we're talking about a longing to see God work,
and the fact that we wanna see God work,
there was unbelief on the part of the disciples.
Jesus says this kind can come forth by nothing
but by prayer and fasting, and we hear a lot about prayer,
we hear little about fasting,
and what's happened in the last decade or so
is that fasting has predominantly been portrayed
as a way to lose weight.
Physical.
A way to lose weight.
You read it, you can look at it,
you can look up the statistics,
there are best-selling books that have been written
on the subject from 2012 to 2015,
that's what I said in the last decade plus,
gained great popularity through Silicone Valley
and through social media,
became one of the most searched trendy diets
by 2018 and 2019.
Why am I bringing that up?
I'm bringing that up for this purpose.
I'm not suggesting, I'm not gonna stand here
to this evening and say that fasting,
intermittent fasting can't help with dieting
and losing weight and so on and so forth.
I'm not trying to argue that.
What I'm simply saying is that we're living in a time
when the enemy has altered God's word.
but society has taken something that has primarily
been spiritual and made it physical to lose weight.
And here's my opinion and here's my experience.
I hear a whole lot more, even amongst God's people,
about the subject of fasting when it comes to dieting
than I ever hear about the subject of fasting
when it talks about getting alone with God.
And that's sad.
But that's my experience, that's what I see,
that's what I hear.
And let me say this, to be fair,
I mentioned to the folks this morning,
to be fair, Jesus says, Matthew chapter number six,
when you fast, don't go proclaim it like they do.
So I understand there may be people fasting
for spiritual reasons, but when's the last time
you heard a message on fasting?
I'm the preacher, I don't preach on it that often.
The reality, I can remember, I did a three-part series
on fasting on Wednesday night probably seven
or eight years ago, I could go look it up
to see exactly the dates, but it's something
that we don't preach on very often.
It's something that's not practiced
in a spiritual discipline.
To use that terminology, I hope you understand
what I'm trying to communicate with that this evening.
It's not a checkbox, I'm not meaning it that way,
but man, we got this thing going on in our lives
and we're serious, I want God, I want God
to give me clarity and direction and I need God
and I need to see God work and God says this kind
comes forth by nothing but by prayer and fasting
and we have modern versions that are removing fasting
so many Christians that are not using a King James Bible
don't even see the word, they don't even have
an awareness of it and then you have a culture
that is, I see advertisements all the time
for intermittent fasting.
If you're in this age to this age, you should be doing it
these hours and so on and so forth.
Diet, diet, weight loss, weight loss,
but primarily and historically, it's spiritual
to get alone with God.
Again, I'm not saying that you can't lose weight
by fasting, I'm not saying that, but I'm saying
that if a child of God is more interested in fasting
to lose weight than they are to fast to get alone
with God, there's a problem.
There's a problem and until we can identify the problem,
we're never gonna fix it.
Until the disciples could understand because
of your unbelief, they never are gonna fix it.
Right, if they didn't ask and if Jesus didn't tell them,
they never fixed the problem.
How many times we live in life and we have experiences,
maybe in the workplace, maybe even in church setting,
in family setting where somebody is doing things wrong
and they're not doing things the right way,
but no one has the courage to tell them.
No one has the courage to correct them.
No one has the courage to help them do it the right way
and here they are doing it the wrong way every single day
because no one's gonna tell them
because no one wants to offend them.
That's the kind of culture that we live in right now.
And the problem is that affirming someone's sin
is not love.
Affirming someone error is not love.
We are to speak the truth in love, absolutely,
and when I love someone, I wanna give them the truth.
Why?
Because I understand they're gonna stand up
for the Lord one day.
I'm not standing here this evening,
I hope you can understand, I'm not standing here
condemning anyone for fasting,
for physical dieting, weight loss purposes,
but what I'm saying is that if that's our primary goal
as Christians, we've missed it.
We've missed it because primarily fasting
is a spiritual discipline and here Jesus gives us insight
that's so important for us to really grasp this evening.
Why could not we cast him out?
They would not have asked the question
if they were not aware of the fact
that they were given power to do so.
Amen?
If I was never given power to do something,
if I was never trained how to do something,
I wouldn't be like, how did I not know how to do that?
No, I didn't know how to do it
because I didn't know how to do it,
like I'd never done it before.
Why could not we do that?
You gave us the authority, you gave us the power,
but we couldn't.
Why?
Because of your unbelief.
Is there unbelief in my life, in your life, in our lives?
And then we think about the subject of prayer and fasting.
Yes, we're not to go around and let everyone know
that we're fasting and we're not to go around
and announce it and look at me,
I fast twice a week, right, like the Pharisees
and so on, no, no, no, it's not the point, not the purpose.
But when I'm fasting, biblically, spiritually,
I'm taking and I'm going to demonstrate my seriousness,
I'm gonna take and let's just say it's a single meal.
Maybe I'm just gonna fast for a single meal.
I am going to get alone with God for that time.
I'm not gonna fast, I'm gonna skip that meal
so that I can go do these other things.
No, I'm gonna fast so that I can get with God.
And I'm gonna take that time and I'm gonna get serious
about seeking the face of God and getting close to the Lord.
And the Lord knows, he knows that this aspect of prayer
and fasting, that there's something that's revealed
through the practice of prayer and fasting
that's revealing our faith.
We're studying through the book of James.
The book of James is a good book, it's a great book,
it's part of the canon of scripture.
But throughout the book of James, you find something
that's interesting that many people have confused
over the centuries with regard to works and faith
and so on and so forth.
And James keeps making this statement
as we continue to get further into the book,
you have faith, show me your faith.
Because I can't see your faith except by your works.
Your works are the evidence of your faith.
And so what is it about our faith that is evidence to God
about through this aspect of prayer and fasting?
They had been given the power, but they really didn't believe
they weren't praying, they weren't fasting.
And Jesus confronts them, they obviously make the inquiry,
but Jesus gives the insight not only to the disciples,
but recorded in the scripture for us to help us,
to help us in our walk with the Lord.
And I wanna be one like the Church of Thessalonica,
when the Bible says that their faith groweth exceedingly.
I mean, when I examine my life, when you examine your life,
and I check, the disciples say in Luke 17,
I think it's verse three, Lord, increase our faith.
What a great prayer, what a great desire.
And then we see the Church of Thessalonica
where the Bible says that their faith increase exceedingly.
And man, I want my faith to be growing, I want my faith.
When I look at my life and I look back and I examine
last year, when I first got saved and incrementally,
how's my faith?
Do I believe God?
Am I in a situation where if I were in the storm
like Paul was, you read it in Acts chapter 27.
If I were in the storm, if you were in the storm,
and the Bible paints a picture for us where all hope
that they should be saved was gone.
I mean, they'd not seen the sun, the moon, the stars.
I mean, they were helpless and they were hopeless.
But God sent a message to Paul
that they were gonna be delivered.
You know what Paul does?
He stands up and he makes this three-worded statement.
I believe God.
And he followed it up by saying that it shall be
as it's been revealed to me.
And what's he saying?
God said we're gonna be delivered.
Oh, the ship's gonna be lost, but not one of our lives.
That's faith, that's faith, that's believing
that what God said was going to come to pass.
When everything around us says no,
when everything around us says hopeless, helpless,
you're just, I mean, there's no way out.
We haven't seen the sun, the stars,
we haven't seen the moon.
I mean, it's hopeless.
But God gave me a word.
And I'm gonna believe what God has said.
We live in a time, if we wanna look at our society,
we say, man, it's dark.
I mean, look at all the things that are going on.
People don't wanna hear.
No, no, listen, if God was done, we'd be in heaven.
I believe that.
And if there's no one else to get saved, we'd be in heaven.
There's still work to do.
We gotta believe it.
Believe the power of the gospel.
Believe the truth of God's word.
Believe that God is able.
He said because of your unbelief.
I don't want that to be the indictment on my life,
on your life, on our lives.
I want us to have faith.
Because we need to have faith to please God.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you tonight.
I thank you for loving us.
And I pray, Lord, that you would help us
to truly examine our own lives
as we look at a passage of scripture such as this.
Lord, that we'd consider the deception
of the enemy with regard to this area of fasting,
removing the reference for many of.
the modern versions and giving a perspective that is more physical in nature than spiritual
and has impacted many of your people, Lord.
God, I pray that You'd help us to just examine our own lives or to get alone with You privately
even as the disciples did in this passage and to ask the question and to be prepared
for the answer to have You search us, Lord, honestly, thoroughly, reveal to us, show us,
expose to us areas in which we need to grow.
We do thank You for the privilege of prayer.
We thank You for the missionaries that we support.
Thank You for just the opportunity to spend time in corporate prayer tonight.
I pray that You'd bless, You'd be honored and glorified, and we'll thank You for it
in Christ's name we pray, amen.
If you have your prayer bulletin with you, start on the back looking at some updates
for our missionaries and there's four of them this evening, we had a couple of shorter ones
and so we were able to get...