chapter number three, Genesis chapter number three, be looking in verse number
14 down through verse number 20 and let me read the text of Scripture we'll get
into it this evening. Genesis 3 beginning in verse number 14 the Bible says the
Lord God said unto the serpent because thou hast done this thou art cursed above
all cattle. And by every beast of the field upon the belly, upon thy belly,
excuse me, shalt thou go and thus shalt thou eat all the days of thy life. And I
will put enmity between thee and the woman, between thy seed and her seed, it
shall bruise thy head and thou shalt bruise his heel. Unto the woman, he said,
I will greatly multiply thy sorrow in thy conception, and sorrow thou shalt
bring forth children, and thy desire shall be to thy husband, and he shall
rule over thee. And unto Adam, he said, because thou hast hearkened to the voice
of thy wife, and hast eaten of the tree of which I commanded thee, saying, thou
shalt not eat of it. Cursed is the ground for thy sake, and sorrow shalt thou
eat of it all the days of thy life. Thorns also and thistle shall it bring
forth to thee, and thou shalt eat the herb of the field. And the sweat of thy face
shalt thou eat bread, till thou return unto the ground, for out of it was thou
taken. For thus thou art, and unto dust shalt thou return. And Adam called his
wife's name Eve, because she was the mother of all living. The third chapter
of Genesis, obviously, as we've mentioned throughout the first two
lessons that we've looked at this third chapter, this is our third lesson in
Genesis chapter number three, and we have mentioned that it's of significant
importance. In fact, without a proper understanding of the events that are
recorded in Genesis chapter number three, it would be very challenging for us to
understand the entirety of Scripture. It'd be difficult for us to understand
the remainder of what God has given us in His Word if we do not have a proper
understanding of Genesis chapter number three. In fact, if we erase Genesis
chapter number three from our Bibles, it'd be pretty confusing as you'd read
all of what God tells us concerning the promised Messiah and, of course, the
record in the New Testament of His coming and His death and His glorious
resurrection. And we find here the critical nature of Genesis chapter
number three. As we've studied this chapter up to this point, we've studied
in the first seven verses and read about the fall of man and, of course, that day
in which sin entered into the world and the significant impact that that had
upon the creation of God. And we'll discuss the judgments this evening as we
read this passage and study through here. It was encouraging two weeks ago as we
studied verses 8 through 13 and we had the opportunity to see not only the fall
of man but the pursuit of God. And I'm thankful that God pursued Adam and Eve
and though Adam and Eve responded to their sin and to their eyes being opened
by making for themselves aprons of sewing those fig leaves together, but we
find that they hid themselves from the presence of God amongst the trees of the
garden. And in the cool of the day, God came into the garden and God was
pursuing mankind. And I'm thankful for that. We referenced as we studied that
portion of Scripture, the truth that we find over in the book of Luke where the
Bible teaches us in Luke chapter 19 that the Son of Man has come to seek and to
save that which is lost. And I'm thankful that we have a seeking Savior. As we
continue looking at this passage of Scripture and we study that which is
before us this evening, we are going to review and look at the judgment of God.
We do understand this evening that He, God, is a righteous judge. And we
understand that there was a specific command that was given in Genesis
chapter 2 and we'll review that this evening as we make our way through the
text of Scripture. But we understand that God gave a specific command with a known
consequence for disobedience. And God is a righteous judge and as we study the
passage of Scripture, we do understand that there are consequences for
disobedience. If we could describe the text of Scripture, of course the title
for the message this evening, God's judgment announced, we find in the
passage of Scripture as God would deal with the serpent and then with Eve and
then with Adam, we'd find really what's outlined for us is the penalty for sin.
We know that the Bible says the wages of sin is death in Romans chapter number 6.
We know that God had given the truth to Adam in Genesis chapter number 2,
that the day that thou eatest thereof, thou shalt surely die. We find that it
was Satan that said, ye shall not surely die. And we dealt with that as we studied
the first portion of Genesis chapter number 3, but this evening as we look at
verses 14 through 20, we are reminded of the truth that God is a righteous judge.
And as you look at the passage of Scripture, you find first of all, if you
take notes this evening unto the serpent, we find that the Lord God speaks first
to the serpent. It was that serpent that we find in verse number 1 where the
Bible says the serpent was more subtle than any beast of the field which the
Lord God had made. And the serpent represents the enemy of God and man. The
serpent represents Satan himself, the devil. And we understand that the process
by which the devil in his subtlety comes into the garden and goes there to
tempt Eve. And we've studied that, we've looked at that, but you notice that God
says in verse number 14, and the Lord God said unto the serpent, because thou hast
done this. We understand that the attack of the enemy, and of course Satan is
against God and is against God's creation, and he had entered the doubt
into the mind of Eve by saying, yea, hath God said. And then saying that ye shall
not surely die, and giving the understanding to Eve that that which was
before her of the tree that was the forbidden tree, the tree of the knowledge
of good and evil, that it was that tree that was there. And she saw that it was
pleasant to the eyes, and she desired and took and did eat. And the Lord says,
because thou hast done this. Notice what he says in verse 14, thou art cursed
above all cattle and upon every beast of the field. So we find that the curse is
given to the serpent, and he tells him that he would be cursed above all cattle,
above every beast of the field. He then continues and says, upon thy belly shalt
thou go, and dust shalt thou eat all the days of thy life. It's interesting if you
want to hold your place here in Genesis in another book of Revelation, and we find
it on two occasions in the book of Revelation. Revelation chapter number 12,
first of all, and we'll look at a passage in chapter number 20, and we find that as
the Lord would give the description of the enemy of God and of mankind, the old
serpent, the Satan, we find that he refers to him in Revelation 12 in verse number
9. Notice the terminology that is used here, and the great dragon was cast out.
Notice that old serpent called the devil and Satan, which deceived the whole
world. He was cast out into the earth, and his angels were cast out with him. We find
in chapter number 20, in verse number 2, this is after the tribulation period and
the start of the millennial reign of Christ after the battle of Armageddon. The Bible
says in Revelation 20, in verse number 2, and he laid hold on the dragon, that old serpent,
which is the devil and Satan, and bound him a thousand years. And so we find that as God
is speaking to the serpent in verse number 14 of Genesis 3, that he's speaking to none
other but Satan himself. And we find that here in this text of Scripture, he issues
the curse, the penalty, the judgment. But I want you to notice that it continues in
verse number 15, as God is continuing to speak to the enemy of God and of mankind, Satan
himself. He says in verse number 15, and I will put enmity between thee and the woman,
between thy seed and her seed. It shall bruise thy head, and thou shalt bruise his heel.
This verse of Scripture is the first mention of the Gospel in all of the Word of God, and
what a blessing it is as we read that which God gives us here in Genesis 3, in verse 15.
The hatred, he says, that would be between thee and the woman, the enmity, he says, in
between thy seed and her seed. Notice the reference to her seed that is here in Genesis
3, in verse number 15. It is an obvious reference to a future descendant of Eve with no human
father. And we find that as we look at the text of Scripture that clearly in view is
the virgin birth of Jesus Christ, the promised Messiah. We find that the seed of course is
through the man, but here it says her seed, because of the virgin birth, the miracle of
the virgin birth, and of course the deity of Christ. And here we find that he says God
to the enemy, to the serpent, he says, I will put enmity between thee and the woman, between
thy seed and her seed. And what is given to us as a first mention in Genesis 3 and 15
of the Gospel we find carried out and mentioned throughout the various portions of Scripture.
In fact, this evening, turn to the book of Isaiah, if you will, and notice the prophecy
of Isaiah in Isaiah chapter number 7. We'll look at the fulfillment of course in the person
of the Lord Jesus Christ, God in flesh.
as it's recorded for us in Matthew 1.
But we find that in Isaiah 7 and verse 14,
the Bible says this,
therefore the Lord Himself shall give you a sign.
Notice what it says,
Behold, a virgin shall conceive and bear a son
and shall call His name Immanuel.
What a precious promise and a sign
that God mentions here that the Lord would give this sign,
and He tells, He's giving of course the affirmation
to that which we find in Genesis 3 and verse number 15
between thy seed and her seed.
Again, in view here,
the clear understanding of the text of Scripture,
the obvious references to the virgin birth of Jesus Christ,
and that there would be no sin nature
that would be passed down through the seed of man
through Adam, but it would be a sinless incarnation,
the miracle of the virgin birth.
Turn to the book of Matthew, if you will,
and look in chapter number one,
and what a blessing it is.
I'm thankful that we have the entirety of God's Word,
aren't you?
I'm thankful that we have the complete canon of Scripture,
that we can compare Scripture with Scripture,
and that we can find the prophecies that were given
and the fulfillments,
and we can have that opportunity to hold in our hand
the completed Word of God.
And what a blessing that is to us this evening.
In Matthew one and verse number 18,
it's a passage that we often deal with
when we speak about the time of year of Christmas,
but notice the Bible says in verse 18,
now the birth of Jesus Christ was on this wise,
when as his mother Mary was espoused to Joseph,
notice, before they came together,
she was found with child of the Holy Ghost.
Then Joseph, her husband, being a just man
and not willing to make her a public example,
was minded to put her away privileged.
But while he thought on these things,
behold, the angel of the Lord appeared unto him in a dream,
saying, Joseph, thou son of David,
fear not to take unto thee Mary thy wife,
for that which is conceived in her is of the Holy Ghost.
And she shall bring forth a son,
and thou shalt call his name Jesus,
for he shall save his people from their sins.
Now all this was done that it might be,
notice what it says, fulfilled,
which was spoken of the Lord by the prophet saying,
we just read this in Isaiah seven and verse number 14,
behold, a virgin shall be with child
and shall bring forth a son,
and they shall call his name Emmanuel,
which being interpreted is God with us.
Then Joseph, being raised from sleep,
did as the angel of the Lord had bidden him
and took unto him his wife and knew her not
till she had brought forth her firstborn son,
notice, he called his name Jesus.
We read this passage of Scripture in Matthew one,
and we can rejoice in the birth of our Savior,
that when the fullness of time was come,
that God did in fact send forth his son,
and we look at that truth
as Paul would mention in Galatians,
and it's all tied back to that which is stated
in Genesis chapter number three and verse number 15,
when God, the Lord God Jehovah is speaking to the serpent
and he's issuing the judgment,
and he says that because you've done this,
you're gonna be cursed above all the cattle,
above all the beasts of the field,
you're gonna go upon your belly,
the dust shalt thou eat all the days of thy life,
but then he continues and says it doesn't end there,
I'm gonna put enmity between thee and the woman,
between thy seed and her seed,
notice it says, so we see the birth of Christ, amen,
the fulfillment of what we find here in Genesis 315,
but notice it continues,
it shall bruise thy head and thou shalt bruise his heel,
it referring to her seed, the promised Messiah,
and we find that Jesus Christ,
as we see the phraseology,
bruise thy head and thou shalt bruise his heel,
on the cross of Calvary, the promised Messiah,
the Lord Jesus Christ would suffer, indeed he did,
but he would deal a death blow to Satan
and he would be defeated, amen,
and we find here that he says that what would happen
is that it shall bruise thy head,
that death blow, but we find that he then says
and thou shalt bruise his heel,
you think of the suffering of the Lord Jesus Christ
on the cross of Calvary,
you read any of the gospel records
and you can read of the time in which he was going
after he was arrested in the garden
and was going to the cross
and you see all that he suffered
and all that he dealt with,
but you understand that he willingly did that
and though he suffered
and though he had his heel bruised as it says here,
we find that in Hebrews 12, the Bible says,
looking unto Jesus, the author and finisher of our faith,
who for the joy that was set before him,
endured the cross, despising the shame
and it says this is set down at the right hand
of the throne of God
and what a blessing as we find in Genesis chapter number three
in verse number 15, all of this wonderful truth
concerning the plan of God.
Now you remember that God's plan
as we studied in Ephesians chapter number one,
you read it over in the book of first Peter as well,
that Jesus Christ is the lamb that was slain
before the foundation of the world
and you understand that none of these things
that have happened in Genesis chapter number three
took God by surprise.
God is omniscient, he knows all things,
he's eternal, he is alpha and omega,
the beginning and the end, the first and the last
and we find that here he issues the judgment
against the enemy of Christ and the enemy of mankind
and he says, here's what your judgment is
and by the way, he's going to give him
the truth of the gospel as we see it unfold
throughout the remainder of the scriptures.
It's amazing and really what we begin to find
in the latter part of Genesis three,
you see the sacrifice of the animals.
In Genesis chapter number four, you see sacrifice
throughout the book of Genesis
and then especially as you get into the book of Exodus
and you see the law being instituted
and you see sacrifice and sacrifice and sacrifice
and you read all of those things
and how the Passover lamb and all pointing
to the promised Messiah, the fulfillment of this promise
in Genesis three and verse number 15.
You come to the book of Matthew
and you come to the New Testament
and you see the fulfillment of Jesus not only coming
but living that sinless, perfect life
and going to the cross of Calvary.
You go to the book of Revelation
and you see the culmination of the defeat of the enemy
where the Bible says in Revelation chapter number 20
and verse number 10 that Jesus after that little revolt
that takes place there in Genesis 20
after the millennial reign of Christ.
Remember, Satan's loosed for a little season
and the Bible tells us in Revelation 20,
we read it in verse number two,
how that he would be cast into the pit there.
He's bound for a thousand years
but then he was loosed for a little season
according to verse number three
and it was just a little season.
I mean, that revolt did not last long
and he gathered all these folks
and in just a moment, God overthrew him, destroyed him.
The Bible says at the end of verse number nine,
and fire came down from God out of heaven
and devoured cast in the lake of fire and brimstone
where the beast and the false prophet are
and shall be tormented day and night forever and ever.
That's the complete fulfillment of the prophecy
in Genesis three and verse number 15
and it's amazing as you see it unfolded.
William Scroggie wrote a book
called The Unfolding Drama of Redemption
and it is a lengthy book.
It is a deep book in certain parts of the book.
It's a wonderful read
and certainly I believe in such a wonderful way
in titling that book as he's referring to the Bible.
It is the unfolding drama of redemption
and it is the truth here of what God said
in verse 15 of this chapter and issuing the judgment
and then you find the fulfillment of what the Lord would do
and how God would defeat the enemy.
Let me just give you a couple
of additional references here quickly
when we think about that statement
of bruising thy head versus bruising his heel
and yes, the Lord Jesus Christ suffered
upon the cross of Calvary but Satan was defeated.
Jot down if you will Colossians two in verse number 15.
Colossians two in verse number 15,
I'll just read these verses to you quickly
and that way we can get through the remainder
of the message this evening
but in Colossians two in verse 15,
the Bible says,
and having spoiled principalities and powers,
he made a show of them openly against us
which was contrary to us and took it out of the way,
nailing it to his cross
and we sang that song, that wonderful hymn this morning,
it is well with my soul and I love that third verse.
I mean the whole song is good, it's rich
but I love the third verse where it says,
my sin, oh the bliss of this glorious thought,
my sin not in part but the whole is nailed to his cross
and I bear it no more, amen?
And what a blessing and we find here that Jesus conquered,
he spoiled the usage here in Colossians two 15,
he spoiled principalities and powers,
he made a show of them openly,
triumphing over them in it.
In Hebrews two in verse number 14,
the Bible says this concerning that death blow
that was dealt to Satan on the cross of Calvary,
for as much then as the children are partakers
of flesh and blood, he also himself likewise
took part of the same, that through death
he might destroy.
By Him that had the power of death, that is the devil.
In 1 John 3 and verse number 8,
we find once again a reference to the victory
of the Lord Jesus Christ on the cross of Calvary
and of course His glorious resurrection.
In 1 John 3 and verse 8 it says,
He that committeth sin is of the devil.
For the devil sinneth from the beginning.
For this purpose the Son of God was manifested
that He might destroy the works of the devil.
Our God is victorious and He conquered sin, death,
and the grave and we find that ultimately
Satan will find himself in the lake of fire
to be tormented day and night forever and ever.
Moving on in the passage of scripture,
we find that first the Lord deals with the serpent.
He says under the serpent in verses 14 and 15.
In verse number 16 it's under the woman.
Under the woman, unto Eve.
Notice what He says here.
He said, I will greatly multiply thy sorrow
and thy conception.
In sorrow thou shalt bring forth children
and thy desire shall be thy husband
and he shall rule over thee.
We find that there'd be pain and sorrow
would be greatly multiplied in childbirth.
Now I'm thankful I've never given birth
and I never will but I have had the opportunity
and privilege to witness as Holly gave birth
to our three children and I said immediately
after the birth of Juliana that it's a good thing
that ladies were chosen by God to give birth
because for most of us men it would certainly
be a one and done, that's for sure
and we probably would tell our buddies
about the difficulty and what have you
but here in the judgment we find that He says
that He would greatly multiply thy sorrow
and thy conception.
In sorrow thou shalt bring forth children.
That's the first aspect.
I want you to notice what Jesus says with regard to this
in John 16 in verse number 21.
This is an amazing truth that I have witnessed personally
through the opportunity of seeing Holly give birth
and going through that process with her and by her side.
I remember the first time with Juliana
and we had gone through that Lamaze class
and all that stuff, you learn how to breathe
and all of that and I'm not sure if any of you did that
but I remember thinking that I would be a prepared husband
and I'd be ready to help her and I'd give her
all the right answers and it was just kind of a waste
of time to go to that class because basically
you just throw it all out the window
and I'm like honey you have to breathe
and the doctor's saying you gotta breathe
and I'm trying to demonstrate it for her
and I'm saying honey just squeeze my hand
and she's like no, no, no, you squeeze my hand
and I'm thinking I'm like fine, like I'm not in pain,
I'm okay, what am I gonna squeeze your hand for?
And it was just kind of a funny situation
and the pain that she endured of course
for those of you that have had children,
you understand that but notice what Jesus says
in John 16 and 21, a woman when she is in travail
notice hath sorrow because her hour has come
but as soon as she is delivered of the child
she rememberth no more the anguish for joy
that a man is born into the world.
It's amazing the joy that a mother would have
in holding that little baby right after birth
and how quickly some of those things
of what they had endured would pass by
because of the joy that they experience
in holding that newborn babe
and I remember well that situation
and we find here that part of the curse,
part of the judgment of God as it's outlined
in Genesis three is that God would,
that pain and sorrow, excuse me,
would be greatly multiplied in childbirth.
He also establishes the order in the home
here in verse number 16.
At the end of the verse of scripture
he says thy desire shall be to thy husband
and he shall rule over thee.
Now understand that that ruling over thee
is not in being some type of dictator
in that type of a situation
but we do find that God has established order
in the home as he has in every institution
that he has placed upon earth
and as he gives here the insight
as to what that order would be
as we study the New Testament,
we find more information that is given to us
concerning the order in the home
and about her desire and being to her husband
and that he shall rule over thee
and then we come to finally this evening,
number three if you're taking notes,
verses 17 down through verse number 19,
notice unto Adam.
So we find unto the serpent, unto the woman
and then verse number 17 through 19, unto Adam.
The Bible says this in verse 17
and then to Adam he said,
notice because thou hast hearkened to the voice of thy wife
and hast eaten of the tree
of which I commanded thee saying thou shalt not eat of it.
It's interesting because what God says to the serpent
is because thou hast done this.
What he says to Adam is because thou hast hearkened
to the voice of thy wife
and hath eaten of the tree of which I commanded thee
saying thou shalt not eat of it.
You don't see that he mentions that to the woman.
He just says unto the woman,
I will greatly multiply thy sorrow and thy conception.
But yet we find that with Adam he gives him,
he spells out for Adam what the offense is
and what he was guilty of
and reminds him of the command that God had given.
Back in Genesis chapter number two in verses 16 and 17,
as we studied the second chapter of Genesis,
we mentioned that this is the first command of God
in all of the word of God
and it says in verse number 16,
when the Lord God commanded the man saying
of every tree of the garden thou mayest freely eat.
But of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil,
thou shalt not eat of it.
For the day that thou eatest thereof,
thou shalt surely die.
You'll remember that it was in verse number 11
when God was pursuing Adam and Eve in the garden
that he asked the question first in verse number nine,
where art thou?
And he said that I heard thy voice in the garden.
I was afraid because I was naked
and I hid myself.
And then in verse number 11,
God says who told thee that thou was naked?
And then notice he says,
hast thou eaten of the tree whereof I commanded thee
that thou shouldest not eat?
The man said the woman whom thou gave us to be with me,
she gave me of the tree and I did eat.
We find that God is addressing Adam in verse number 17
and he says because thou has hearkened
to the voice of thy wife
and hast eaten of the tree of which I commanded thee
he's saying thou shalt not eat of it.
He wants Adam to understand that he had broken the command
that God had given.
We find that it says,
cursed is the ground for thy sake.
Notice in the end of verse 17 it says,
in sorrow shalt thou eat of it all the days of thy life.
Verse 18, thorns also and thistle shall it bring forth to thee
thou shalt eat the herb of the field.
So we see the sorrow that's mentioned in verse number 17.
We can understand that the thorns and thistles
can inflict pain as it's mentioned in verse number 18.
The work, the labor that is mentioned in verse number 19
and the sweat of thy face shalt thou eat bread.
And he says this till thou return unto the ground
for out of it was thou taken
for dust thou art and unto dust shalt thou return.
And remember that the Bible told us of the forming of man.
In Genesis chapter number 1 it says that God created man
in His own image and the image of God created He Him.
Male and female created He them in Genesis 1 and verse 27.
But it was in chapter 2 and verse number 7
that God gave us some additional insight
as to the creation of man.
And it says in verse 7,
And the Lord God formed man of the dust of the ground
and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life
and man became a living soul.
And here we find that in this judgment
that's announced to Adam,
that He tells him,
Cursed is the ground for thy sake
and in sorrow shalt thou eat it all the days of thy life.
Thorns also and thistles it will bring forth to thee.
Thou shalt eat the herb of the field.
He tells him about the sweat of thy face,
shalt thou eat bread.
And then He says this,
For out of it the ground was thou taken
for thus thou art and unto dust shalt thou return.
We'd understand this evening
that it was in Genesis chapter number 2
that the command was given
and God said in the day that thou eatest thereof
thou shalt surely die.
We understand that physical death
was not the immediate result of the sin
that entered in the world,
but there was death separation between God and man.
The spiritual death if you will
and man would then have to be reconciled to God
and we understand biblically speaking
that as you look in Romans chapter number 5
and you look at the New Testament
that we are born in our sins and our trespasses.
We are born physically,
but we must be born again
is what Jesus said to Nicodemus in John chapter number 3.
In fact, in Ephesians chapter number 2
He says in ye hath he quickened, right?
We were dead and we were reconciled.
We were made alive
and so we find that the Bible says
the wages of sin is death,
but the gift of God is eternal life
through Jesus Christ our Lord.
And we find here in the text of Scripture
that God would give the judgment
upon the enemy of God and of mankind,
Satan himself, the judgment
that's announced against the woman
and also against the man, against Adam.
But we can rejoice this evening
that in this text of Scripture
though the divine punishment is outlined,
we also have the opportunity...
opportunity to see the grace and mercy of our loving Heavenly Father. We
discover that the provision for mankind to be reconciled to God is also
announced. And that's what we spent time looking at in verse number 15 this
evening, because we find that it's there that God announces the plan of
redemption, the reconciliation of sinful man back to a holy God. As we look and
we'll study next week, and that ought to cause us to rejoice by the way, just
studying and looking at Genesis 3 and verse number 15 ought to cause every
child of God to rejoice and to see. And really if I could this evening just add
a little addendum to the message, it's interesting because in verse number 15
the judgment is issued and the the first mention of the gospel and all that would
be accomplished through the the promised Messiah coming to the earth, and you find
that the the scriptures contain so many references for us about the way that the
spiritual battle, the spiritual warfare, and how the the enemy Satan was seeking
to destroy the royal seed, he was seeking to destroy the seed by which Messiah
would come. And that's why there's so many battles in the Old Testament about
the Philistines coming against Israel and coming against Israel and coming
against Israel and seeking to destroy and to devour and to to go ahead and
corrupt the line that had been promised. And we find that as we study all of that
in the Old Testament begin to see, yes we can read of the the actual peoples that
were involved and we can read of the Hivites and the Amalekites and the
Philistines and all of these groups of people, but we have to understand that
what's happening is there's this spiritual battle that is raging in Satan
understanding that which had been pronounced in Genesis 3 in verse number
15 as it's recorded in our Bible that he sought to wage this war against the
God of heaven to destroy the line, to corrupt the line. And we can rejoice this
evening that he was unsuccessful. Amen? Because our God is greater. Amen? God is
omnipotent. He is the Lord God Almighty. He is the Lord God omnipotent. And we
find that though the the war was waged against God and against the seed, we find
that of course God prevailed and Jesus did come and Jesus fulfilled all that
would need to be fulfilled in order for man to be reconciled to God. Next week as
we can conclude Genesis chapter number 3, we'll have the opportunity to examine
the latter portion of this chapter and deal with, examine if you will, the coats
of skins that are mentioned in the latter part of Genesis 3 and understand
once again the prophetic impact of that which we find at the end of Genesis 3.
As I've mentioned so often as we've studied the book of Genesis and this is,
I don't know how many months we've been in it now, a few months, this is our 16th
lesson through the book of Genesis and as we've studied the book of Genesis I
have sought to, I guess, emphasize the importance of the book of Genesis
because the record that is given to us in the book of Genesis is under attack.
Yes, creation is under attack. Genesis 1 is under attack but we find that when
they attack Genesis chapter number 1 and they say there's no creator, there's no,
the man wasn't created in the image of God, so on and so forth, then what they
do is they begin to undermine all of the authority of Scripture and if you can
undermine the authority of Scripture in Genesis 1, it carries over to Genesis
chapter number 3. If God did not create man in his image, if man was not created
perfect in the image of God in a perfect environment and then man did not fall
and so on and so forth and if there's no creator, ultimately there's no need for a
redeemer and it's a huge problem that we find in our society today, the attack on
the book of Genesis. It's a precious book, it's the book of beginnings as it's often
been coined and as we dig into the book of Genesis and we find how God has given
us so many wonderful truths that would help us to properly interpret the whole
of Scripture. What a blessing that is. This evening I hope that even as we look
at the divine judgment that's been announced in this passage of Scripture
that we can rejoice in the provision for mankind to be reconciled to God as it's
mentioned in Genesis 3 and verse number 15. Let us pray together.