I'm just looking at a few verses this afternoon, and I told someone that I would be preaching
for about 45 minutes.
They said, well, you know, you could make it 30.
And I said, well, you know, I only have three verses for my text, but it doesn't mean we're
not going to go other places.
And anyhow, I do trust it'll be a blessing to you as we continue our study of the book
of Genesis.
I've thoroughly enjoyed studying the book of Genesis.
This is our 27th lesson from the book of Genesis, and it seems like we've been talking
about it for a long time of getting started with the series, and now we're going to be
concluding chapter number eight this evening.
As you, those of you that have been part of the study, as you know, Noah, as we were introduced
to him in chapter number six of the book of Genesis, he was a man that walked with God.
He had a great testimony.
The Bible tells us that he walked with God, and certainly the example of Enoch, of walking
with God, the two men that are first mentioned here in the book of Genesis that had that
testimony that they walked with God.
And the Bible tells us that Noah found grace in the eyes of the Lord in Genesis chapter
number six.
As we would consider the testimony of this man Noah, we find that during a time of great
wickedness and the corruption that had filled the earth, that Noah continued to maintain
a proper walk with God.
What a great example for us this afternoon as we would consider that even in the midst
of the world in which we live, that we can maintain a God-honoring testimony and we can
walk with God.
We do not have to be polluted or tainted by this world.
He has left us here in this world to be lights and to shine in the midst of a crooked and
perverse generation.
And I'm thankful for the testimony of Noah as we would consider the fact that he walked
with God, that he obeyed the Lord, we also must consider the obedience and the faith
of Noah.
He was a man that believed God.
God told him, here's what's going to happen.
I'm going to destroy the earth.
I'm going to bring rain.
I'm going to bring a flood.
And he believed what God told him.
God told him to build an ark and he moved and he did, he obeyed and he had faith that
God was going to do what God said he was going to do.
Off to repeat it in chapter six, seven and eight would outline for us, or really six
and seven, the obedience of Noah and that he did all that God commanded him.
So did he is how Genesis chapter number six concludes.
As you'll recall from last Sunday, as we looked at the eighth chapter of the book of Genesis,
we find that it's that time in which Noah and his wife and his three sons and their
wives are upon the ark.
And I made mention at the end of the message last Sunday evening, and we really kind of
focused on seeking to learn this valuable lesson of waiting on God to provide direction
in our lives.
And the direction was received.
Noah opens the door to the ark and he appears, he looks and it seems as if the ground was
dry, but yet God did not instruct him to get off the ark at that time.
I know that I made mention of the fact that many times as we would consider the waiting
on the Lord, waiting is something that most of us are not good at.
But yet Noah remained on the ark, he and his family and all of those animals until God
spoke to him and God said, now's the time to get off.
And what an important lesson for us to learn.
As we would consider that message and that truth, we then come to our text this afternoon
where the Bible tells us in chapter number eight and verses 18 and 19 that they all got
off the ark.
Noah went forth and his sons and his wife and his sons' wives with him.
Every beast, every creeping thing, every fowl and whatsoever creepeth upon the earth after
their kinds went forth out of the ark.
Now, this is the first time that they get off the ark in a year and 10 days.
That's a long time.
That's how long they'd been on the ark.
If you were to go back in chapter number seven and you would find when they got on
the ark and when God shut the door and you see the timeline all the way through chapter
seven into chapter number eight, you find that it's a year and 10 days that has passed
since they first got on the ark.
Now you consider with me this evening or this afternoon what it would be like to get off
the ark after you'd been on the ark for a year and 10 days.
Now they're going to step off the ark and they're going to take their first steps on
an entirely changed earth.
We had mentioned last week at the end of the message how the topography and the geography
of earth would have changed drastically from prior to being in the earth when they got
onto the ark and then all that took place through the flood and all of the destruction
and all of the change to the topography and the geography of earth.
And we find that they now step out onto this entirely changed earth.
I wonder this evening if we can kind of relate to Noah and his family.
I wonder what it is that, how we would feel.
I wonder how they felt getting off of the ark.
I wonder this evening what we would think about doing.
I know that as you take trips and you get on things, people say, the first thing I'm
going to do when I get off of or I get out of, you've heard people say that, right?
The first thing I'm going to do when I get off this airplane, the first thing I'm going
to do when I get off this boat, the first thing I'm going to do when I get out of this
car.
And we have these long journeys.
But for a year and 10 days, Noah and his family have been off the ark, excuse me, on the ark.
And they now get off the ark and God gives us a record of what takes place.
It's the subject matter that we'll be studying this afternoon.
In verse 20, the Bible says, and Noah built it an altar unto the Lord.
Noah built it an altar unto the Lord and took of every clean beast and of every clean fowl
and offered burnt offerings on the altar.
And the Lord smelled a sweet savor and the Lord said in his heart, I will not again curse
the ground anymore for man's sake, for the imagination of man's heart is evil from his
youth.
Neither will I against my any more every living thing as I have done while the earth remain
at seed time and harvest and cold and heat and summer and winter and day and night shall
not cease.
We find here in our text of Scripture, the title for the message, if you're taking notes,
Noah worshiped the Lord.
As we would look at this text of Scripture, I hope to be a blessing to you.
I want you to consider with me, first of all, worship as a priority.
Worship as a priority.
First things first, if you will.
They get off the ark, the Bible tells us in verse number 18, and Noah went forth and
his sons, his wife and his son's wives with him.
Every beast, every creeping thing, every fowl and what sort of creepeth upon the earth after
their kinds went forth out of the ark and Noah built it an altar unto the Lord.
The first thing they do when they get off the ark is they worship the Lord.
Worship as a priority.
Can I tell you this afternoon that our God is worthy of our worship?
The word originally in the English language carried with it the idea of worth-ship.
And you would understand that somebody is worthy of this worship and Jesus is worthy
of our worship.
Our God is a great God.
The word worship means to adore, to pay divine honors to, to reverence with supreme respect
and veneration.
And you think about our God, he is worthy of our worship.
I'm thinking this afternoon as I consider Noah and his family on that ark for a year
and ten days and I consider as they get off of the ark and I consider the ways in which
they begin to worship the Lord and the Bible tells us about the burnt offerings that they
bring upon the altar and we'll deal with that in just a moment.
But it's a priority that they're recognizing that God has given them the direction that
they needed, that God has given them the protection and kept them during that entire
process.
And the Bible tells us that he built an altar unto the Lord and notice it says, took of
every clean beast and of every clean fowl and offered burnt offerings on the altar.
Can I tell you this afternoon that this wasn't a quick process?
It was a lengthy process.
I'm thankful that we don't still have the temple that we have to take offerings to.
We don't have to make sacrifices and we'll get to that in just a moment as to the picture.
I'm thankful that we don't have to go and go through that whole process but the Bible
speaks in Hebrews chapter number 10 about those priests that stood daily ministering.
They would process offerings, sacrifice after sacrifice after sacrifice.
They would do that continuously and they would process these sacrifices, these offerings.
It could never take away sin.
It was a picture pointing to Messiah.
But we find that Noah and his wife and his sons and his wives, their wives, they get
off of the ark and the first thing they do, it says they took of every clean beast, every
clean fowl and offered burnt offerings on the altar.
So first of all to set up the altar, then the process of preparing the animals for the
burnt offering and the process of actually offering these animals.
This is a process.
See sometimes we get into this mindset in this day and age in which we live and the
convenience and everything happening so quickly, we kind of get into this like let's fit God
into our schedule.
It's a danger because we're such a busy society.
We have so many things going on and it's like, okay, I'm going to worship God but I'm going
to do it in five minutes.
I'm going to fit God in my schedule.
Can I tell you that God doesn't want to be fit in your schedule?
Amen?
Without him we can do nothing.
We understand who he is that we literally, every breath that we take is a gift from God
and we need to make worship a priority in our lives.
as a priority. The burnt offerings that are mentioned here in verse number 20,
this is the first mention of burnt offerings in the in the Word of God. We
understand that sacrifice and offering was something that was known as we would
study the book of Genesis as we have studied the book of Genesis. We found in
the fourth chapter those offerings, right, were brought and we understood we went
through that process with Cain and Abel and all of that and we find here that
there was an understanding. Remember that godly line of Seth and there was
some some sacrifice that was done on these offerings but now we find that the
Bible speaks about these burnt offerings. Later in the book of Leviticus, God would
give us further detail with regard to these burnt offerings and as we study
and we look in the book of Leviticus and understand the description that is given
to us, we find that those burnt offerings would enable an unholy people to
approach a holy God. It was a picture of atonement for sin and we're so mindful
this afternoon as we think about Noah getting off of this ark and we consider
the first matter of business is worship and he brings these offerings and he
offered burnt offerings on the altar and worship was a priority. Look over, if you
will, at Hebrews chapter number 10 and I want you to notice in verse number 12
what the Word of God tells us. It's that same passage of Scripture that I
mentioned earlier about those priests that would stand daily ministering and
we find that they were bringing those sacrifices that was just a picture. It
says that they offered year by year continually that they could never make
the comers there unto perfect. But we find in Hebrews 10 and verse number 12
speaking of the Lord Jesus Christ, God in flesh, the Bible says but this man after
he'd offered one sacrifice for sins forever sat down on the right hand of
God. You know, in the tabernacle there were a number of pieces of furniture. God
gives truth and gives the details with that, all of that instruction for
building and all that took place there in the book of Exodus. We find there's a
lot of furniture. There's no seat in the tabernacle. There was no place of rest.
There was no time in which the the priests were to sit down. No, they were
continually ministering and serving and making these offerings and what have you
and we find that here that as they get off the ark that worship was a priority.
Oh how we need worship to be a priority in our lives. That we adore the Lord. You
know that we worship him through our singing. We worship him through our
giving. You know giving is an act of worship. It is. And we could go on and we
could speak about our worship of God. Here's the truth in Exodus chapter 34
in verse number 13. We are told in that passage of Scripture this truth with
regard to worship. In verse number 14, excuse me, it says for thou shalt worship
no other God for the Lord who jealous is a jealous God. In Exodus chapter number
34. Now who knows what happens before Exodus chapter number 34? The golden
calf. Remember what took place? Moses is busy getting instruction from God
receiving the law and while Moses is getting the law the people are breaking
the law. They came to Aaron and they we find that they gave all that gold and
they they fashioned a calf and they begin to worship and we find that when
the covenant if you will is renewed in chapter number 34 the book of Exodus
that God very plainly says in verse number 14 thou shalt worship no other
God for the Lord whose name is jealous is a jealous God. He's worthy of our
worship. He alone is worthy of our worship. And we understand this afternoon
as we would look at Noah and his family coming off of that ark and we could
consider and we could give all kinds of ideas as to what we might want to do
after being on the ark for a year and ten days but we find that worship was a
priority. They got off the ark built an altar and brought these burnt offerings.
It was a process. It was not quick. The Bible doesn't tell us how long it takes. We know
it's a process. We're not interested in trying to fit God into our schedule. We
need to let God have his way and I'm not suggesting that we prolong things just
for the sake of prolonging something but we need to be sensitive to the leading
of the Holy Spirit of God. Allow God to have his way. Get into that spirit of
worship. He's worthy. Not only do we see worship that as a priority but I want
you to notice worship that pleases the Lord. This is important this afternoon.
This subject matter of worship is confused excuse me let me make let me
say it this way there are some in our society today that have confused the
subject of worship and we find that worship is a priority but it must be
worship that pleases the Lord. I said this in the morning service and I'll say
it again I mentioned to you that I would say it and that's this that not all that
they call worship is worship. Here in verse number 21 of Genesis chapter 8
the Bible says and the Lord smelled a sweet savor and the Lord said in his
heart I will not again curse the ground anymore for man's sake for the
imagination of man's heart is evil from his youth neither will I against my
anymore every living thing as I have done while the earth remaineth seed time
and harvest cold and heat summer and winter and day and night shall not cease
and we find that really in verses 21 and 22 following into chapter number 9 we
find the Noahic covenant as it would be referred to and we'll get into that as
we get further into our study but I want you to notice the beginning of verse
number 21 the Bible says and the Lord smelled a sweet savor this was pleasing
to God this act of worship worship as a priority these burnt offerings that Noah
brings upon this altar that he built this pleases the Lord and it is
absolutely important for us to understand this afternoon that our God
is a holy God and that we are to approach him as he has told us to
approach him we find that the Bible records for us about the strange fire
that was brought they were killed amen our God is holy and our God says that he
is worthy of worship but then he also tells us how to worship him in fact over
the book of John you don't need to turn there because I want you to go to some
of the Old Testament passages we're gonna look at turn over to the book of
Zechariah if you will I give you a moment to turn there Zechariah chapter
number 7 and as you're turning to Zechariah I'm gonna share with you what
Jesus said there in John chapter number 4 when he was speaking to the woman at
the well he said God is a spirit and they that worship him must worship him
in spirit and in truth God sets forth the way in which he is to be worshipped
and we must follow what he has said the book of Zechariah almost to the end of
the Old Testament we find that in Zechariah chapter number 7 in verses 4
through 6 that we see that the the indictment against the people and notice
what is said here in verse number 4 it says then came the word of the Lord of
hosts unto me saying speak unto all the people of the land and to the priest
saying when you fasted and mourned in the fifth and seventh month even those
70 years did ye at all fast unto me even to me and when you did eat and when
you did drink and not did not ye eat for yourselves and drink for yourselves
what's God saying oh well there was times in which they fasted but they
weren't fasting under the Lord people say I was fasting I was this in something
where they think that they're worshiping but God says no that wasn't worship that
was just some outward act that you were doing this wasn't true worship turn over
a few pages the book of Malachi if you will I'll read a lengthier passage of
scripture here in the book of Malachi in chapter number 1 in Malachi chapter
number 1 we find a final book of the Old Testament and here Malachi is
prophesying and the word of the Lord comes unto Malachi and what a blessing
to read obviously the captivity of the Babylonians already taken place and the
remnants already returned and what-have-you and we come to Malachi 1
in verse number 6 and it says this a son honoreth his father and a servant his
master if then I be a father where is mine honor if I be a master where's my
fear saith the Lord of hosts unto you Oh priest that despised my name and ye say
wherein have we despised my name notice where he says you offer polluted bread
upon mine altar and you say wherein have we polluted polluted thing in that you
say the table of the Lord is contemptible and if you offer the blind
for sacrifice is it not evil and if you offer the lame and sick is it not evil
offer it now unto thy governor will he be pleased with thee or accept thy
person saith the Lord of hosts you understand what's happening they're
bringing sacrifices bringing offerings but they weren't following what they
were supposed to bring supposed to bring an unblemished right they're bringing as
he says here in verse number eight you offer the blind you offer the lame and
the sick is this not evil in fact here's the illustration he gives take it to the
governor and see if it pleases him no you wouldn't take it to the governor
he's not gonna accept it
But you're bringing it to God
That's what's happening verse 9. And now I pray you beseech God that he will be gracious unto us
This has been by your means and he regard your person sayeth the Lord of hosts
Who is there even among you that would shut the doors for not neither do you kindle fire on mine altar for naught?
I have no pleasure in you sayeth the Lord of hosts neither will I accept an offering at your hand
You know God's saying don't even bring it but we're worshiping. No. No, you're not worshiping
it's not true worship all that's called worship is not worship and
Here we find that he says in verse number 11 from for from the rising of the Sun
Even under the going down to the same my name shall be great among the Gentiles and in every place
incense shall be offered unto my name and if your offering for my name shall be great among the heathen sayeth the Lord of
Hosts but ye have profaned it in that you say the table of the Lord is polluted and the fruit thereof even as meat is
Contemptible you said also behold what a weariness it is it?
And you have snuffed at it sayeth the Lord of hosts and you brought that which was torn and the lame and the sick
Thus you brought an offering should I accept this at your hand of your hand sayeth the Lord?
But cursed be the deceiver which
Hath in his flock a male and voweth and sacrifice unto the Lord a corrupt thing
Notice what God says for I am a great king sayeth the Lord of hosts and my name is dreadful among the heathen
He is king of kings and Lord of Lords. He is the Lord God omnipotent
He is worthy of our best
Amen, and they that worship him must worship him in spirit and in truth and God says look you're bringing these offerings
But this isn't true worship. You're going through the motions. You're doing these things, but this isn't true worship
Turn to the book of Matthew
Just several pages over the first book of the New Testament you find the book of Matthew in chapter number six
We were in chapter number eight this morning during our Sunday school hour
And I mentioned some reference to chapters five through seven with the Sermon on the Mount and I want you to notice in chapter number
six that God the Lord Jesus Christ gives some
Instruction and he gives us some insight with regard to the subject of worship, and he says this in Matthew chapter number six
Notice in verse number five when thou prayest do you think we can worship God in prayer?
Absolutely if we pray properly
Amen
Not all praying is worshiping God
How do we know that notice in verse 5 and when thou prayest thou shalt not be as the hypocrites are
For they love to pray standing in the synagogues in the corners of the street, so they're praying aren't they?
But it's really just a show
It's really just a show wasn't worship
Why notice what that says that they may be seen of men?
Verily I say unto you they have
Their reward what was their reward the rewards the applause of man? That's what their reward is and
Jesus says when you pray don't pray like that
Don't pray like that
Because that's not the type of prayer that is appropriate and proper prayer
We won't read through all the text of Scripture, but skip down and look at verse number 16. He says moreover when you fast
We mentioned the fasting over the book of Zechariah
again, he says be not as the hypocrites of a sound sad countenance for they disfigure their faces that they may
Appear unto men to fast verily I say unto you they have their reward
Jesus would teach about the subject matter of fasting and prayer and obviously the importance of both of those
subjects and he would teach about it and he would speak of it and
Throughout his ministry and we find here though that he says hey when you fast don't fast like they do don't fast like the hypocrites
Why what do they do? They just figure their face and they say, oh I'm fasting, you know
It's just so horrible
No, no
Don't do that. They're doing it to be seen of men. They have their reward. What's the reward the applause of man?
If that's all we're trying to get is the applause of man, then we do it in our flesh
Can I tell you there's a lot that's happening in the name of Jesus today even in this nation
That's nothing more than a work of the flesh. That's getting nothing more than the applause of man
But God says that's not worship
I'm not trying to be hard this this afternoon
I'm not trying to be critical of other people or ministries
But I'm trying to tell you this afternoon is that our God is worthy of worship and worship must be a priority
But it must be worship that pleases God
Our God is a thrice. Holy God
You look I challenge you you look in the Word of God you read and study this book when man comes in the presence of
God he falls flat on his face
Amen our God is holy and
The worship must be a priority, but it must be worship that pleases God
When Noah got off of that ark he and his family
They built an altar first thing they do
Build an altar
Bring those offerings the burnt offerings. It wasn't a how long's it's gonna take
No, no, they're worshiping God
You know really when when we get that heart when we're in that place or worshiping God the clock doesn't matter as much. I
Understand we all have schedules. I get it. I'm not saying that to say I want to preach longer any of that
Don't get nervous. Alright, but what I'm saying is that when we're truly in the presence of God
And we're worshiping him
Those things don't matter
because we're worshiping God and it's a priority and
Our worship when we're worshiping God and though in the means by which he set forth in his Word
It's got to be worship that pleases him
The Bible says they brought these offerings and it says there that the Lord smelled a sweet savor
Look over the book of Hebrews and we'll close with this and we're gonna be done Hebrews chapter 13, and I want you to see
Here in Hebrews 13 notice what the Lord says
in his Word
With regard to this subject of worship and something that pleases God in Hebrews chapter number 13 in verse number 15
Give you a moment to turn there
Worship must be a priority
Worship must please the Lord
All that is called worship today isn't true worship
Verse 15 of Hebrews 13
By him therefore let us offer the sacrifice of praise to God
Continually that is the fruit of our lips giving thanks to his name
But to do good and to communicate forget not for with such sacrifices. God is what does it say?
Well
Pleased does it please God when we praise him?
Absolutely. What about complaining? Does that please God not so much?
You read the Old Testament
They murmured and they complained and God was not well pleased. You can read it over and over
in fact
Paul would use the illustration of that murmuring and complaining in 1st Corinthians and he talks about in chapter number 10 of whom
God was not well pleased
But here we find just as the case was with those offerings that were brought by Noah
in Genesis chapter number 8 when they their worship pleased the Lord there was that sweet smell and
Here the Bible says that with such sacrifices God is well pleased
It tells us that we're to bring the sacrifice of praise to God
Continually that is the that is the fruit of our lips giving thanks to his name
This afternoon as we conclude the 8th chapter of the book of Genesis and we consider what happened when they got off the ark
I'm glad that God tells us
I'm glad we don't have to sit around and put on a
You know sanctified imagination say I wonder what they did after they got off the ark
They got off the ark the animals got off and the first thing they did was worship God
build an altar and brought burnt offerings
Worship is a priority and that worship pleased God. Oh
That we would please God with our worship that that he would see and be pleased. He would be well pleased
Amen, Noah worshiped the Lord. Oh that we too would worship God. He's worthy. He alone is worthy
All that we'd worship him. Let's pray together father. We love you. We thank you for loving us
thank you for the
Testimony that we get to read this afternoon of Noah and his family as they got off the ark
we thank you God for
The sacrifices that were made the worship that took place
You were pleased with it
God
As we look at some of these other examples this afternoon
Reminded in our own lives
How that worship must be a priority?
Worship that pleases thee I pray God that you would help us
Be well pleasing in thy sight I
Pray God that you would have your will and way here as we have a brief invitation
God that you'd speak to hearts move as only you can
Well, thank you for it. Would you stand with me heads about eyes are closed?
Jared's gonna play quietly on the piano and as he does the altar
Maybe you just want to come and worship the Lord for a moment.
Thanking Him for who He is, for what He's done for you.