Number two, deal with the topic here.
As you see in your bulletin, the sanctity of marriage
is the title for the message this evening.
That word sanctity carries with it
the idea of the quality of being holy,
and we understand, and we'll get through the message
this evening, that God is the one
who established marriage, amen?
And the record of Genesis 2,
as we've been studying the book of Genesis,
we find that this chapter, Genesis 2,
concludes with a beautiful record of the first union,
the marriage, if you will, between man and woman,
and here, God established the plan for marriage,
and we see that He is the overseer.
If you'd start with me and look at verse 22,
I know that the text specifically will be verses 24 and 25,
but let's get what's taking place here.
The Bible says in verse number 22,
and the rib which the Lord God had taken from man
made He a woman, and brought her unto the man.
And Adam said, this is now bone of my bones
and flesh of my flesh, she shall be called woman
because she was taken out of man.
Therefore shall a man leave his father and his mother
and shall cleave unto his wife,
and they shall be one flesh.
They were both naked, the man and his wife,
and were not ashamed.
We understand that it's chapter number three
where the fall of man is recorded,
we'll get into that over the next several weeks,
where sin entered into the world,
and so we carry at the end of chapter number two
that same state of innocence that we dealt with
last Sunday evening as we studied Genesis chapter number two
and we find life in the garden
and where God had prepared this place specifically
for His creation, Adam and Eve, for mankind,
we find that not only did He prepare it specifically,
He planted that garden in that specific place,
but He put man there in the garden.
And we dealt with several things last week
with regard to life there in the garden
and all that God would give us
concerning the attributes and the beauty and what have you,
but we come to the end of the chapter
and we find here that God begins to share with us
this union, if you will, this marriage between Adam and Eve.
You'll remember from verse number 22
as we pick it up in context,
that here the Bible tells us that God
is the one who brought Eve to Adam.
The Bible ends in verse number 22 and says,
and brought her, speaking of Eve,
unto the man, speaking of Adam.
And I'm thankful that here God was meeting
the need that Adam had.
It was a known thing.
God knew in His wisdom and His foreknowledge
and all of His omniscience,
He knew that man was not gonna be alone.
He was gonna make a help meet for him.
And here we find that God brings Eve to Adam.
We find also in verse number 23
that Adam had a clear understanding
that this which now stood before him
was different than anything he had ever seen.
Amen?
And if you look back and you remember from our text
in last week, in verse number 18, excuse me,
verse number 19, out of the ground,
the Lord God formed every beast of the field,
every fowl of the air, and brought them unto Adam
to see what He would call them.
And whatsoever Adam called every living creature,
that was the name thereof,
but there was not found in help meet for Adam.
And so all these animals go by and He names them
and God brought them to him.
Now in verse 23, Adam has an understanding
that I've not seen anything like this before.
This is bone of my bones, flesh of my flesh.
And it says that, he said, she shall be called woman
because she was taken out of man.
Now you recall that back in Genesis chapter number one,
when God told us the record in chapter number one,
day number six, as it's recorded for us
about the creation of mankind,
that He created male and female, created He them.
And one of the instructions that He provided them with,
according to verse number 28 of Genesis one,
was to be fruitful and multiply.
And here we find that God is bringing the two together.
He brings Eve to Adam.
And then the principle is established here
in verse number 24 that we'll look at this evening
when we think about the sanctity of marriage
where the Bible says,
therefore shall a man leave his father and his mother
and shall cleave unto his wife and they shall be one flesh.
As we would understand this evening,
it is important for us to recognize marriage,
that marriage is not the idea of man.
It is not the idea of government, amen?
It is God's plan.
It was God that designed marriage.
And as the designer, as the planner,
He has the right to establish the pattern
and He did here in Genesis two.
And it's important that we think biblically.
I often speak of that importance in our lives
and my desire as a follower of Christ to think biblically
and to be able to answer questions
not based upon what my opinion is, what your opinion is,
what the popular opinion of the society,
the culture in which we live,
what's gonna save my neck, so to speak,
what's gonna keep a crowd.
I mean, we could get into all kinds of mess
if we follow that pattern,
but how important it is that we think and act biblically.
One of the things that we say as Baptist people
and one of the distinctives as we would call them
is that we believe that the Bible is the sole authority
for faith and practice, amen?
The first distinctive that we speak of,
the Bible is the sole authority for faith and practice.
And so therefore, I'm not interested so much
in what the church fathers said.
You understand what I mean by that, right?
There are some that you can read
and they've written all sorts of things
and they've given their opinions
and even today there are denominations
that hold meetings and change position
based upon what the culture wants
and what is acceptable in the society in which we live.
That is contrary to what God tells us in his word.
And we are to be people that follow the book.
We are to be biblicist,
if I could use that term this evening,
and it's important that we would allow the plan that God,
the pattern that God established here in Genesis
to influence our thinking
with regard to this subject of marriage.
And Eve, of course, we find was brought to Adam,
as I mentioned, and now God in verse number 24
when he says, therefore,
what he's doing is he's providing future generations
with what his plan is for marriage.
Notice it says, therefore,
shall a man leave his father and his mother?
And so we understand that process of leaving.
And then there's an important word that is used.
It says, and shall cleave unto his wife.
That word cleave is an important word.
It means to stick to, to keep close,
to join to, follow close.
And we find that certainly this word
would be used later on by Joshua.
He speaks about cleaving unto the Lord.
And we see that at the end of the book of Joshua
and his challenge to the people
that he was called to lead prior to his death.
But we find here that God in establishing this principle,
this pattern of marriage,
he says you're to leave and then you're to cleave.
He says that the man and shall cleave unto his wife,
notice the last phrase,
and they shall be one flesh.
The bond and union of marriage
is clearly taught here in this text of Scripture.
And we find that it is God's plan
that one man be joined to one woman.
We find that his plan is right.
His plan is effective, amen?
And as we see in the plan of God,
as it's mentioned to us here in Genesis chapter number two,
we would find that God's wisdom clearly evidenced
through the plan, the pattern that he has established.
We find that the Lord Jesus Christ speaks of this
and gives authenticity to the text of Scripture
that we're looking at even here this evening
in the gospel record.
Turn to Matthew 19, if you will.
Hold your place here in Genesis.
We'll get back there eventually.
We will look at a couple of other verses of Scripture
this evening as well.
But in Matthew chapter number 19,
I want you to turn there
and I wanna read a few verses of Scripture to you.
And if you wanna jot down in your notes
not only Matthew 19 verses four through six,
but you could look at Mark's record of the same thing
in Mark 10 verses six through nine
when Jesus is answering the Pharisees
that were seeking to tempt him
about the law and they're tempting him specifically
about the subject of divorce and putting away one's wife.
And he says in verse number four,
Jesus is answering those religious leaders of the day.
He answered and said unto them, have ye not read?
Now we could just stop there just for a moment
and teach a whole lesson
about the importance of the Old Testament.
I am up to maybe above my forehead
on New Testament Christians
that say we don't really need the Old Testament.
That is a bunch of baloney.
The Old Testament was written for our instruction.
It was written for our admonition.
The New Testament tells us that.
In fact, many times when you read the life
of the ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ,
how often he refers back to the Old Testament.
You can look at the Apostle Paul.
and see how he refers back to the Old Testament when Stephen the first martyr
when he was preaching his message consisted so much of the truth of the
Old Testament that he was preaching the Old Testament is beneficial for us God's
preserved it for us and he says to these religious leaders by the way they were
familiar with the law they were experts quote-unquote of the law they had it
here they didn't have it in their heart but he says have you not read that he
which made them at the beginning made them what male and female that settles a
whole debate that's raging today doesn't it and I mean it's amazing and what's
going on in our society not only here in America but really in many places around
the world today with this gender fluidity thing that's going on and God
made a male and female and for over 6,000 years it's been pretty easy to
identify at the time of birth amen and here we find in verse number five it
says and said for this cause shall a man leave father and mother and shall cleave
to his wife and they twain shall be one flesh does that sound familiar to what
we just read in Genesis 2 in verse number 24 it's almost exactly word for
word what we read in Genesis chapter number 2 this is the Lord Jesus Christ
God in flesh he is God and he is speaking answering the Pharisees and he
says that from the beginning he made them male and female and then rehearses
and refers back to that which we find in our text this evening Genesis 2 and
verse number 24 and verse number 6 it says wherefore they are no more twain but
one flesh what therefore God hath joined together let not man put asunder and we
find that the Lord Jesus Christ would speak of this subject of marriage and he
would give authority to that which was established as a pattern all the way
back in Genesis chapter number 2 this evening as we embrace the plan of God
for marriage it will require us at the same time to it to reject some practices
in our world today somebody said this I was a great quote you can't love flowers
and love weeds if you love flowers you're gonna hate the weeds and what
they were trying to express through that statement was that if you have a flower
bed and you have all those flowers and you're trying to have the the curb appeal
and have that beauty to look at you don't want a bunch of thorns and
thistles and weeds right you gotta get some mixture and spray it on there right
the first time I went to visit Rick and Sally they're outside trying to kill all
their weeds why because they had beautiful flowers out there but the
weeds were coming and if we're not careful brother John what happens with
the weeds they overtake everything right and here we find that if we take that
statement that someone made that helps us relate to something physical and
temporal when we think about Bible teaching and Bible doctrine when we
embrace what God has said it will at the same time require us to reject other
theories other practices other ways in this evening when we think about this
truth of marriage and we think about the pattern that was established in Genesis
chapter number two I believe that within the the teaching of Genesis chapter
two you understand that Adam and Eve they did not have the responsibility of
leaving mother and father they're the first created beings and God brought
them together but from that point forward we find that he was
establishing this pattern that man would leave that man would cleave and that
they would become one flesh if we take the biblical definition of marriage and
we understand what God has said it will mean that we reject the practice of
polygamy polygamy is the practice that is not so popular still today though for
many centuries it was very popular in certain parts of the world in the
country if you will that is something that is still practiced and that's
having more than one spouse at the same time typically a male having multiple
wives females as their mates and we think of this and here's a subject the
reason why I bring up the subject of polygamy this evening is because many
people have the misunderstanding well the Bible records many Bible characters
that practice polygamy this is true and then you can read of many of the Bible
characters that had multiple wives at the same time however we must understand
this evening that just because the Bible records it doesn't make it right number
one nor does it mean that nor should let me say it this way nor should we
interpret the Bible recording something that happened as being God's stamp of
approval for it amen see we get a whole lot of trouble if we act that way if we
begin to interpret things well David had multiple wives and Solomon had multiple
wives and so therefore God must think it's okay no no that's bad
interpretation amen the Bible records a lot of things that aren't okay amen the
Bible records just because there are certain events that God would faithfully
record for us in his word doesn't necessarily mean that it's what his
design was or what he's approving and so it's very important that we understand
that when it comes to the subject of polygamy and now that's something that's
not super common today it does happen in certain parts of the country and of
the world there's this other practice and I've mentioned it before
sologamy and that's where you marry yourself and I really can't understand
it and it seems kind of weird to me I'm not sure what happens if you decide that
you want to divorce because you've only married yourself and here's what I
understand about sologamy it's something that is becoming increasingly popular
especially in Europe okay it's becoming increasingly popular and it's gaining
some traction even here in America and here's the interesting thing many people
will say this well it's not really illegal to marry yourself nor is it
really legal because it's not something that's ever really been practiced in
mass if you will and it's really this odd kind of thing of having that no one
is good enough and I'm the best for me and that sort of thing it's just kind of
a weird situation and but we would find that that would be something that we
would oppose when we take the truth of God's Word now something that's a little
bit more fresh maybe in our minds and that would be the subject of gay
marriage that's something that we see in our society today not today it's my
understanding that there are nearly 30 countries in the world but by the way
that's not very many as far as the total number of countries in the world but
there are about 30 countries in the world that have legalized the practice
of same-sex marriage of course the United States in 2015 made that
decision that we would legalize same-sex marriage as a nation that really began
as far as something being legal where a country was doing it back in 2000 so
it's something that's fairly recent as far as a government sanctioning that the
thing that we have to be careful of that I mentioned a moment ago really this
idea of marriage is not man's idea it's not government's idea right it's God's
plan it is God's pattern that he established and we find that he said a
man shall leave father and mother and cleave unto his wife and so it's very
clear in the Scriptures now here's what we have to be careful of when we'd
understand I'm gonna get into a couple other things here in just a moment but
something that I believe is important for us to note is that just because we
would reject something doesn't mean we have to be ugly about it amen we can
have the right position but at the same time have the right disposition it is
important that we stand upon the truth of the Word of God it's important that
we embrace what God says and what God's pattern is and that we would reject
false teaching with regard to the subject of marriage which is our subject
this evening but it doesn't mean that we have to be ugly about it you know there
are a lot of people in our society today as we would think about the fact that
they have been blinded by the God of this world right and certainly we
understand the wickedness of sin on so many levels but this evening it's
important that we understand that God's grace and God's mercy and we ought to be
in a position where we would gracefully try to share the truth of the Word of
God it seems as if to me that some of these practices specifically with the
idea of same-sex marriage is almost just becoming a popular cultural thing in our
society there are a lot of young people this evening that are being exposed to
this and being placed in a position of embracing it because it's just kind of
a cool thing to do now when you were a kid and I was a kid it wasn't the cool
thing right and we understand that from a cultural perspective and now because
all of this movement and all of this popularity and really the I say all of
it and really it's a very small percentage of our entire population but
we find that they talk real loud and they talk a lot but it's gaining
traction and it's influencing our young people it's influencing our young people
the point where they are in the in the school libraries and the public
libraries you are finding more and more children's books that are being written
not about a mother and a father and a standard structure for a home but about
this little whatever that has two daddies or two mommies and this sort of
thing and dealing with this and what are they doing they are bombarding the next
generation with this ideology and they're undermining the authority of the
Word of God it's important that we understand that listen the the liberals
understand that if they can get the mind of a five-year-old in 20 years they're
in really good shape because they got them I was sharing with somebody
recently how I don't hear it often but occasionally I'll hear a parent a
Christian parent say well you know I just can't tell my kids what to do I
just need to let them make their own decisions really where did you get that
idea the Bible says train up a child in the way he should go and when he is old
he will not depart from it that mean training is more than telling it's
teaching them and showing them and it's trained them in the way they should go
amen very specific very important for us to understand in this evening the world
is trying to get the minds of the young people and they're putting all of this
nonsense right in front of them I shared with some people personally I did not
say it from the pulpit but there's this little cartoon I've never seen it my
children have never seen it it's a little cartoon called Arthur and some of
you may have heard of it you may have been familiar with it I hope you haven't
let your children watch it and if you have maybe after I tell you this you
won't however this little story I don't know all of the details I did some
reading on it to understand what was going on but in this little cartoon
they're little rats is what they are from what I can gather and what was
going to happen is this one rat that is the teacher was going to marry his
partner who was a male and this was going to be the first episode of the new
season and I believe it was down in the state of Alabama was it in Alabama I
think was in the state of Alabama that the state of Alabama made the decision
that on public television they were not going to air that kudos to Alabama by
the way because they said we're not gonna put that on the public TV because
our parents in Alabama have come to trust us and we're not gonna but they
let their kids watch it without supervision and we're not gonna put that
in front of the kids I thought that was good for Alabama but you know the
liberals got involved in that situation is all kinds of nonsense and so what
what the public television system did is they put a rerun on for that time that
that episode will be they put a rerun on so that it could still broadcast Arthur
and so on and so forth then there was a Methodist Church in Alabama you heard
what I said right a Methodist Church a church I understand there's a lot of
things that we disagree I'm not getting into that this evening but a Methodist
Church in Alabama said we're going to have a viewing of that episode at our
facility and not only are we gonna have we're going to host we're gonna get the
rights to show it but afterwards we're going to have what you would call a
marriage reception to celebrate this stupid cartoon it doesn't even make
sense right but they were so much trying to support the agenda of the
left that they said if the state of Alabama is not going to show it on
public TV we'll get the rights and we'll show it at our facility then we'll have
a wedding reception and try to encourage people to come and participate what are
they doing they're trying to infiltrate the minds of the young people how
important it is that we teach the Word of God here's what God's Word says God
created male and female God said in the first marriage he took the woman Eve
and he brought her to Adam to the man and he gave the pattern therefore shall
man leave his mother and father and shall cleave unto his own wife and they
shall be one flesh and so we have to as we embrace this truth of what the
scriptures teach it would cause us to reject these things and I say that we
should reject those with compassion for some have just simply been blinded
they've been deceived by the enemy you understand as I preached about the enemy
this morning that I preached about the devil this morning he seeks to destroy
and he's determined and he wants to devour and yes we understand he's
defeated but we understand this evening that many have been led astray this
evening in addition to these ideas of marriage that should be rejected as we
embrace the plan that God has set forth in his Word I will also go on record to
say that the plan of God in Genesis would also teach us to reject the
following so many want to attack Bible-believing Christians as simply
being homophobic that's what they want to attack us as you just hate homophobe
or you just hate you know gay people and whatever you just hate that it has
nothing to do with that because when we understand the Bible teaching yes we
reject that but we reject polygamy that's heterosexual by the way not
homosexual but we we reject that we reject yes same-sex marriage but I
believe the Bible would teach us as we'd understand here in Genesis and the
pattern that God set forth that we would reject fornication what is fornication
by definition it is intimacy I'll use that word this evening and you
understand what I mean it is intimacy prior to marriage we find here that God
instituted this pattern he brought Eve to Adam they became one flesh the the
idea what's taking place in our society today this thing of fornication is
running wild in our society it is unbelievable what's happening in our
society with this idea of fornication it's sad it grieves my heart yes I'm
against abortion and I think we should be but I think we need to go deeper than
abortion and we need to start talking about fornication because that's where
it really that's the root of the problem not the entire root of the problem but
that is a main contributor to the problem of abortion and we find that the
Bible says to flee fornication look over in 1st Corinthians chapter number six
and notice what the Word of God says as Paul is writing to the believers in
Corinth now you understand in Corinth the there was a bunch of nonsense was
going on in Corinth as a city and the wickedness the temple prostitutes all
the things that took place and we find that the Apostle Paul begins to deal
with some of these things and he's dealing with some of this particular
subject and he deals with it by this by this way by saying in verse 18 of 1st
Corinthians 6 flee fornication it's pretty straightforward isn't it every
sin that a man doeth is without the body but he that committed fornication sinneth
against his own body it's interesting to me how people think they know more than
God you ever meet people to think they know more than God you try to share
with them a truth of the Word of God why are you against fornication because God
is amen here's what God said yeah but you don't understand how it helps me it
pleases me it whatever no no what you don't understand is God created you and
as the Creator he knows what's best for us and he said flee fornication amen and
so as a Bible believer it's not just that I want to stand on some soapbox and
deal with something that's taking place in our society today that everyone wants
to label us as being a particular something but I would say this evening
we're against fornication we're against it intimacy prior to marriage you can
reference in your notes there also first Thessalonians 4 in verse number 13 not
only are against fornication but we're against adultery what is adultery
intimacy outside of marriage the reality this evening is that I've been
Holly and I will celebrate 18 years of marriage here in August it is not
possible for me at this point or Holly at her point in her in our marriage to
commit fornication because it's it's a sinful act prior to marriage but we
could be guilty of adultery and that's the different use of the word biblically
and so that's the biblical definition of fornication intimacy prior to marriage
adultery is intimacy outside of marriage and so we understand this evening that
the even in the Ten Commandments in Exodus chapter 20 I believe it's in
verse number 14 it says thou shalt not commit adultery very plain very simple
look over in the book of Hebrews if you will in Hebrews chapter number 3 sorry
Hebrews chapter 13 Hebrews chapter number 13 marriage is the plan of God we
find that he defined it he set forth the pattern there in Genesis chapter number
2 he set forth the pattern for future generations and giving the instruction
in verse number 24 of that text of Scripture and here in Hebrew
13 and verse number 4 notice what the Bible says marriage is honorable in all
God is this why because it's God's plan that's what he set forth now we
understand you can look and we could speak this evening about first
Corinthians 7 where there are some that will not get married and that's totally
understandable and Paul deals with all of that and I'm fine with that I
understand that but this evening as we speak specifically about the the marriage
and about what God defined and described in the the pattern that he
set forth he says marriage is honorable and all in the bed undefiled but notice
this but whoremongers and adulterers God will judge that word whoremonger is a
word that the same Greek word is translated elsewhere in first
Corinthians 6 as fornication same word same Greek word and so when he's
speaking about whoremongers in this text of Scripture he's talking about
fornicators those that are involved in that sin that intimacy prior to marriage
and then he says and adulterers those that are guilty of intimacy outside of
marriage this is God will judge God will listen God is faithful God's gonna do
what he said he's gonna do and God has set up a plan and a pattern in this
evening I'm not seeking to be unkind I'm not seeking to be ugly toward any group
of people but the reality tonight is that when we embrace the plan of God it
requires us to reject some things from the society listen tonight let me just
break it down real simple for all of us to understand we believe that Jesus is
the only way to heaven you believe that tonight Jesus is the only way to heaven
there's no other name under heaven given among men whereby we must be
saved acts 4 and verse number 12 Jesus said I am a way no no the way amen the
truth and the life no man coming on father but by me so if I believe that if
you believe that this evening it requires us to reject the popular
opinion that hey as long as you're sincere and what you believe you'll make
it no I'm sorry sir I don't believe that I have to reject oh well if you're a
really good person to do really good things then God will send his favor and
he'll take you to heaven no that's not possible if righteousness came by the
law then Christ is dead in vain Galatians amen and so we have to when we
embrace Bible truth it's like drawing a line in the sand and say hey we're gonna
stand with God and with the Bible and here's what it here's where that may
puts us it's not that we're trying to be contentious it's not that we're seeking
to be contentious but we might listen there needs to be a voice that cries out
for truth and for righteousness this is right and that is wrong based upon the
authority of God's Word it's not my opinion it's not your opinion it's what
sayeth the Lord and that's so important that we come to that place and especially
today when we think about this subject of marriage you know that the the God's
plan for marriage in a in a male and a female in a home they become one and so
on and so forth it is that society that models and patterns itself after that
biblical model that will thrive no other society will ever thrive it's not
possible amen and so we understand this evening that we look at what the Bible
says and when there's some young people that have some difficulties
understanding all that they're being fed and all that they're being influenced by
by the way parents check what your kids are watching check what they're reading
it's everywhere it's insane how this movement has gained so much momentum so
quickly and how important it is that we would stand on the truth of the Word of
God so here's what God said here's what God's pattern is here's what God's plan
is and we can embrace the plan of God but it will require us to reject some
things at the same time God said as he gives us the record of this first union
between Adam and Eve he said that he brought her Eve unto the man and Adam
said as he looked there this is not anything I've seen before this is bone
of my bone and flesh of my flesh she shall be called woman because she was
taken out of man and God therefore gave the pattern therefore shall a man leave
his father and his mother and shall cleave unto his wife and they shall be
one flesh I'm thankful for God's pattern that he set forth in his Word and it's
not for man it's not for government to define it never has been amen God has
defined it God has given the truth with regard to marriage and it's just simply
our responsibility to embrace it let's pray together father we love you we
thank you for loving us thank you for the Word of God thank you for the truth
that's contained therein we thank you for the relevance of a truth that's
nearly 6,000 years old over 6,000 years old of the first marriage between Adam
and Eve and yet even this evening we would understand from this passage of
Scripture and this event that was recorded for us and been preserved in
thy Word the pattern that you set forth I thank you that Jesus during his earthly
reference back to this very first marriage as once again authenticating
and sharing with us the authority that the Genesis record has upon our lives we
ask God that you would help us with compassion to stand faithfully in a
culture that is progressively growing worse and worse and forsaking the
teaching and truth of thy Word I pray God that you'd have your will and way
over the next few moments of our time of invitation and we'll thank you for
what you'll do for it's in Christ's name we pray amen