chapter number 11, the 11th Psalm tonight.
And to be looking really at just a part of a verse tonight
from Psalm 11.
And I normally don't just take a part of a verse,
but we're going to over the next several weeks study
through the 11th Psalm.
And therefore we're going to break this up
and get these principles that God gives us.
We finished up our study doing what we ought to do.
And so we spent five or six months dealing
with various aspects that God gives us in the New Testament
of ought to statements.
And with the final one that we looked at for several weeks,
five weeks was walking as Christ walked,
because if we abide in him,
then we ought to walk as he walked.
And we looked at six different attributes
or characteristics of how Christ lived his life
and how we too as his followers should live our lives.
And then we'll transition.
The next study that we'll do here on Wednesday evenings
is going to be on the names of God.
And since I have been here as the pastor
on Wednesday evenings, when we transition,
and even in Sunday school,
most years we transition from one study to another.
I always take a Psalm and go through one of the Psalms.
And here we are in Psalm 11.
And I appreciate the Psalms.
They're such a blessing.
And there've been some years in my Christian life
that I have had and taken the approach
that every year as I'm reading through the Bible,
a couple of times through the Bible,
that I'll read the book of Psalms every month.
And I'll read five Psalms a day.
And that gets you through the book of Psalms each month.
And I'll tell you, it encourages you, it strengthens you.
And you need more than just the Psalms,
but the Psalms will encourage you.
And as we come to Psalm chapter 11,
there's only, as you note here,
there's only seven verses in this Psalm.
But I want you to know that a Psalm
that consists of just seven verses
will challenge us in so many ways.
And I hope that even as we begin the study this evening,
that we will be challenged in our walk with the Lord.
I'm gonna read the entirety of the Psalm,
and then really just go back to verse number one.
Notice the Bible says this in Psalm 11.
In the Lord put I my trust.
How say ye to my soul, flee as a bird to your mountain.
For lo, the wicked bend their bow.
They make ready their arrow upon the string
that they may privily shoot at the upright in heart.
If the foundations be destroyed,
what can the righteous do?
The Lord is in his holy temple.
The Lord's throne is in heaven.
His eyes behold, his eyelids try the children of men.
The Lord trieth the righteous.
But the wicked and him that loveth violence,
his soul hateth.
Upon the wicked he shall rain snares,
fire and brimstone and a horrible tempest.
This shall be the portion of their cup.
For the righteous Lord loveth righteousness.
His countenance doth behold the upright.
This evening, really the title for the series,
if you want a serious title, it's from the first statement,
which we'll be studying this evening.
In the Lord put I my trust.
And I'm gonna title the message this evening,
the Declaration of the Psalmist,
because what a declaration this is to start the Psalm,
where the Psalmist says in the Lord, put I my trust.
We're gonna think about this particular Psalm.
We don't know the exact circumstances,
but it's believed that most likely
David is fleeing from Saul.
And if you read through the book of first Samuel,
you'll read of that whole interaction
and the way in which David was running and fleeing from Saul
and Saul had made David his enemy continually.
And many believe that that may be the setting
of this particular Psalm.
Of course, there are times in which you look
at the life of David and he faced great difficulty
with his son Absalom as well in that whole situation.
And so as we look here at this portion of scripture
and begin to think about this subject,
in the Lord put I my trust, it's Bible study tonight.
And so I want you to look at a number of verses with me,
because on nine different occasions,
eight others than what we find here in Psalm 11 one,
the Psalmist makes that declaration.
I want you to read them with me.
Look at Psalm seven, turn and look at these verses
with me this evening, because I think it's so profound
that repeatedly the Psalmist makes this statement
about putting his trust in the Lord.
Notice in Psalm seven in verse number one,
oh Lord my God in thee do I put my trust,
save me from all them that persecute me and deliver me.
We read Psalm 11 one,
we'll be studying through the entirety of the Psalm.
Look at Psalm 16 in verse number one.
In Psalm 16, preserve me, oh God,
for in thee do I put my trust.
There are many Psalms, there are many verses
in which we read that I will trust him, I am trusting,
but I want you to notice the significance of him saying,
I will put or I put my trust.
Notice in chapter 25 of the book of Psalms,
we'll just walk right through several of these Psalms
this evening and look at what the Psalmist says
in Psalm 25 in verse number 20.
The Bible says this, oh keep my soul and deliver me,
let me not be ashamed, for I put my trust in thee.
Chapter 31 in verse number one.
In thee, oh Lord, do I put my trust,
let me never be ashamed, deliver me in thy righteousness.
Look at chapter 56.
You say, pastor, why do you keep saying these?
I want you to read them, I want you to see
how many times the Psalmist declares with those words,
in the Lord put I my trust.
In Psalm 56 in verse number four,
notice the Bible says, in God I will praise his word,
in God I have put my trust,
I will not fear what flesh can do unto me.
Skip down to verse number 11 of Psalm 56,
in God have I put my trust,
I will not be afraid what man can do unto me.
Chapter 71, we'll look at two more.
Psalm 71 in verse number one,
the Bible says, in thee, oh Lord, do I put my trust,
let me never be put to confusion.
And then in chapter 73, a Psalm of Asaph,
we find here in verse 28, Psalm 73 in verse 28,
but it is good for me to draw near to God,
I have put my trust in the Lord God,
that I may declare all thy works.
Why is it that we make time tonight,
why did I have you look at those verses of Scripture,
because I want you to understand tonight,
to put something, in this case trust
is what we're speaking of, is an act of the will.
It's an act of the will.
You must be, look, understand tonight,
you must be actively engaged to put something.
Does that make sense to you this evening?
I put my Bible here tonight, I didn't just drop it
and it fell where it fell, no, I put it here,
it was something that I purposed, something that I did,
and we find that here, speaking of the context tonight,
he talks about, in the Lord put I my trust,
this expression, in my opinion this evening,
this expression eliminates passivity.
This expression zeroes in on a deliberate decision
of an individual.
I am going to purpose, I'm going to decide,
I'm going to make the decision with my will,
an act of the will, that I am going to put,
I'm going to place my trust,
in the case of our study this evening, in the Lord.
We find that here, the psalmist is going to put
his trust in the Lord.
The word trust is an interesting word,
it means confidence, but it goes beyond confidence.
Here's what the 1828 Noel Webster's Dictionary says
for trust, reliance or resting of the mind,
on the integrity, veracity, justice, friendship,
or other sound principle of another person.
Now we know that we're not just speaking
of any other person, we see the definition
that's given of trust, and no doubt,
there's been a time in your life,
there's been plenty of times in my life,
where someone would say to me, or even I would say
to someone else, trust me.
Has anyone ever told you that?
Trust me, you can trust me on this one.
You've heard people say that, and there was a time
in our society in which there were many deals
that were brokered by just a handshake
in understanding the trust that you could place
in an individual, and you could trust their word,
and now you sign a contract that's 150 pages long,
and they still find ways to break it,
and the reality is that this evening,
when we're talking about this subject of trust,
this reliance, this resting of the mind
on the integrity, veracity, justice, friendship,
or other sound principle of our God,
he's trustworthy, he's trustworthy.
We find this evening that this declaration
of the psalmist, where he says in Psalm 11,
in verse number one, in addition to all the other places
in which we've read this evening,
he says, in the Lord put I my trust.
He deliberately put his trust in the Lord, his God.
We understand contextually, even as we look
at some of what's taking place, where he says in verse two,
that the wicked bend their bow, they make ready
their arrow upon the string.
We read at the end of verse number one,
where he says, how say ye to my soul,
flee as a bird to your mate.
and we'll deal with several of those things
over the next several weeks as we study through this,
but understand that the psalmist is dealing
with some very difficult days,
some very difficult circumstances that he's facing,
and he begins the psalm with this great declaration,
in the Lord put I my trust.
Again, it eliminates passivity.
It zeroes in on a deliberate decision of an individual.
You and I face things every single day.
And the question is, where do I put my trust?
Where do I put my trust?
Why is it, what is it that led to David,
the sweet psalmist of Israel,
saying and declaring in the Lord, put I my trust?
Well, look back, maybe on the same page for you,
a page back for me in Psalm 9,
and I want you to notice in verse number 10,
Psalm 9 in verse number 10,
notice what the Bible says in this verse of Scripture,
and they that know thy name
will put their trust in thee,
for thou, Lord, hast not forsaken them that seek thee.
There's great significance here in this verse of Scripture,
and it will be our next study on Wednesday evening,
as I mentioned a moment ago,
where we'll begin studying the names of God,
and here the psalmist says, and they that know thy name.
Listen, if you know who God is,
if you know the names that God has given to us
that describe his character and his attributes
and who he is, then it says here in this verse
that they that know thy name will put their trust in thee.
You've been in a situation where you've trusted
what someone said because of the character
of the individual, maybe somebody spoke up for them
and said, no, you can trust them, I know their character.
Well, we have a Bible that reveals to us
the character and attribute of God,
and it says here that they that know thy name
will put their trust in thee.
I'm afraid today that many of God's people
really do not know God in a deep, intimate way,
and therefore, they're not putting their trust in God,
they're putting their trust in other things,
maybe even themselves, because they really don't know,
intimately know, who God really is.
We find here that in Psalm 11,
the psalmist, why would he say this?
Well, because he knew the Lord.
David knew God.
David walked with God.
Was David perfect?
No, in fact, God records for us sin in the life of David,
and we see that, but we also see his response
and his brokenness and great truth
that helps us to be able to relate to an individual
that walked with the Lord, that sinned greatly,
but he repented and he had forgiveness and restoration,
and we see a man that knew the Lord
and he declared his trust in the Lord.
Not only do we know from Psalm 9 in verse number 10
that they that know, as it says here,
thy name will put their trust in thee,
but we find that we've been commanded,
we've been instructed throughout God's word to trust him.
In Psalm 4 in verse number 5,
the Bible simply says it this way,
offer the sacrifices of righteousness
and put your trust in the Lord.
I mean, it's a pretty straightforward command, is it not?
Have you ever told somebody, put that over there?
Now, what'd you mean by that?
Well, they had to have an act of the will
to go and put whatever the object was
in the place where you told them.
Is that correct?
And so they had to put it there.
Hey, go put those things away.
Hey, we understand the use of the word
and the act of the will.
It's not, again, it eliminates that passivity.
It's not just something's going to just happen.
No, I'm actively engaged in deliberately making the decision
that I'm going to put my trust in the Lord.
And the Psalmist instructs us,
commands us to do that in Psalm 4 in verse number 5.
Of course, this evening,
many of us could quote Proverbs 3, verses 5 and 6,
trust in the Lord with all thine heart.
Right, is that what the Bible says?
Lean not into thine own understanding.
Man, that's a hard one for many of us
if we'd be transparent this evening
because so often in our lives,
we lean on our own understanding.
And you understand tonight that God's ways are not our ways,
that he's far greater than we are,
that there are times when we go to the word of God
and we go to the scriptures
and we see the commands of the Lord and we say,
but this doesn't make sense, but this is what God says.
And we trust that God is going to do
what God says he will do,
that God will bless and that God will provide.
And we simply trust him
and not lean on our own understanding.
If you're analytical,
if you deal with as many people have been instructed
in so many different arenas in our society and our culture
of how do you make a decision
and you place all the pros here and all the cons here
and you kind of figure out what makes the best sense
and I'm gonna make a decision,
I'm gonna make that based on,
no, the reality is that if we're making a decision
that has some command that God has given to us,
it doesn't matter, you can take your pro and con sheet
and get rid of it because if God said it,
we simply trust him.
We simply, we make that decision
that I'm going to put my trust in the Lord.
We notice, however, throughout the scriptures
that many people and we too ourselves
can put our trust in different things.
Notice with me in Psalm 20,
just gonna kind of take a walk here
through some of these verses tonight
as we dig into this psalm
really as an introductory lesson tonight
to really get the concept and the idea
of what does it mean to put my trust?
Why is it that the psalmist makes this declaration
in the Lord put I my trust
and what are other things?
Why are people putting their trust in other places?
Notice in Psalm 20 in verse number seven,
what does the Bible say?
Chariots, some trust in chariots
and some in horses,
but we will remember the name of the Lord our God.
You know, there are some that place their trust,
they misplace their trust
here in chariots and in horses.
Listen, are there times in which we can study
in the Old Testament when Israel is facing battle
and if you look purely at the numbers of the enemy
and you look at the number of chariots
or you look at the types of chariots,
they have chariots of iron.
We see that where the sons of Joseph
make that declaration and they have chariots of iron,
but it doesn't matter if God said you trust the Lord.
You're not trusting in the chariots.
Well, I have more chariots than they do.
That's not the path in which God's people
are to go down in the way in which we make a decision.
No, I'm not trusting in my chariots.
I'm not trusting in my horses.
I'm trusting in the Lord.
Notice in Psalm 44, in Psalm 44,
and look at verse number six,
and then we're gonna backtrack into the Psalm,
but I want you to look at verse number six first
in Psalm 44 and verse number six.
Notice what the Psalmist says here.
He says, for I will not trust in my bow,
neither shall my sword save me.
You know what that reveals to me?
That some can trust in their bow.
For if he says, I will not trust in my bow,
then that means that there are some
that are trusting in their bow.
How is it?
That's their weapon.
That's their modern, that's the weapon of their day
when they would engage in battle,
and we find that the Psalmist says
that I will not trust in my bow,
neither shall my sword save me.
Look back, if you will, at verse number five.
The Bible says through thee.
Who's thee?
That's the Lord, that's who the Psalm is referring to here.
Through thee will we push down our enemies.
Through thy name will we tread them
under that rise up against us.
For I will not trust in my bow,
neither shall my sword save me.
Listen, were there times, are there examples
in which we can read of in which Israel,
the people of God, misplaced their trust
and they put it in their own power,
in their own might, in their military capabilities?
Remember what happened to Ai?
They had victory at Jericho,
but they forgot that it was God
that gave them the victory miraculously,
and they said, oh, Ai, it's kind of a small,
small, there's not that many people there.
I mean, we don't all have to go,
and there was sin in the camp.
There's a double issue going on there at Ai,
but we find that the Psalmist says I'm not gonna trust.
Listen, we, if we're not careful,
we can trust in the wrong thing.
We can misplace our trust.
Notice in Psalm 49, in verse number six,
notice what the Bible says here.
When we speak about this,
how we can put our trust in many things,
in Psalm 49, they that trust in their wealth
and boast themselves in the multitude of their riches.
Well, there's some people that put their trust
in their wealth.
In fact, there's a lot of people
that put their trust in their wealth.
You know what the Bible tells us about riches?
They make wings and they fly away.
That's what the Bible says.
And there's some that have lived through
and they've seen that economic decline,
and we can read of, in various times of history,
great economic crisis.
And we can speak, even as we deal with today,
as we face various aspects of inflation
and so on and so forth, with regard to.
our economy today, but we find that there's coming a day,
you read the book of Revelation during the tribulation,
where a day's wage is only gonna provide
for a day's ration of food.
Some place their trust in wealth or in riches.
Well, they think that, well, I can purchase what I need,
I can get, and it's a misplaced trust.
They that trust in their wealth and boast themselves
in the multitude of their riches, notice in verse seven,
none of them can by any means redeem his brother,
nor give to God a ransom for him,
for the redemption of their soul is precious,
and it ceaseth forever.
It's an interesting study.
If you take these verses and then go over
to 1 Peter chapter one and verses 18 and 19
and understand that we're not redeemed
with corruptible things, such as silver and gold
received from our vain conversation,
no, we're redeemed with the precious blood of Christ.
We find that there are some today, many today,
that are trusting in their wealth and their riches.
Turn to Psalm 118, if you will, Psalm 118.
Two verses of scripture here in Psalm 118,
verse eight and nine.
The Bible gives us a, it is better to statement.
Notice in verse eight, it is better to trust in the Lord
than to put confidence in man.
It's interesting that word put confidence,
the Hebrew word is the same word
that is translated primarily trust
in a hundred different passages.
It's not the same Hebrew word as the first trust
in verse number eight, it's actually two different words,
but we find that that word translated put confidence,
which by the way, it's not a wrong translation,
it's perfectly fine, but it's interesting to know
that it's like 103 times that Hebrew word
is translated trust.
And so what is the Psalmist saying?
It's better to trust in the Lord
than to trust or put confidence in man.
How many of you found that man will fail you, right?
How many of you found that God will fail you?
He won't, he won't.
The Psalmist knew that, that's why the Psalmist says,
it is better to put, to trust in the Lord
than to put confidence in man.
Notice in verse number nine, it is better to trust
in the Lord than to put confidence in princes.
Princes will fail you, but God will not.
And so he says, it's better, it's better.
Notice in Psalm 146.
Psalm 146,
it goes along with what we just read in Psalm 118
and verses eight and nine, but here in Psalm 146,
notice in verse number three,
put not your trust in princes nor in the son of man
in whom there is no help.
I want you to remember this evening
that the Bible tells us repeatedly
that the Lord is our helper.
The Bible tells us that our God is a very present help
in the time of trouble.
The Psalmist declares in Psalm 121,
I will lift up mine eyes into the hills
from whence cometh my help.
My help cometh from the Lord, which made heaven and earth.
And here we find that the Bible says
in this portion of scripture in Psalm 146 and three,
that there is no help,
what in the princes or in the son of man.
And so we find that our God is able to help us.
He has a very present help at the time of trouble.
We read Hebrews 13 and we read the wonderful promise
where it says, I'll never leave thee nor forsake thee,
but we rest in the fact that knowing that he will help us,
he will succor us.
That word means to help and he comes alongside
and what a blessing to understand the truth this evening.
And we find that as we look at these various passages
of scripture and look back at Psalm chapter number 11,
and we see this declaration that the Psalmist makes.
Again, I've emphasized and I've purposed this evening
to really zero in on that word put.
There are many other verses of scripture
that teach us this evening
on the importance of trusting the Lord.
There are many verses of scripture in fact,
that we'll look at next week that provide for us
what the results are for those that trust the Lord
and how God blesses and the rewards that we'll receive
by trusting him.
And we find that there are other declarations
in which God uses in his word with regard to trusting.
It's Job that says, though he slay me,
yet I will trust him.
And we find here this evening
that when we look at that little word put,
it's so vital, it's so significant for us this evening
because the reality is that when we face a circumstance,
when you face a scenario today,
when you face a scenario tomorrow,
when there's something that comes in your life,
when there's something that comes in my life,
when there's something that comes in our lives
collectively as a church, as a body of believers,
are we going to take and have this situation
when we look at this word put,
again, eliminating the passivity,
but zeroing in on the deliberate decision
that though all of these things are what the scenarios are
and here's what people are saying,
but I have purposed, I am determined,
I have put my trust in the Lord.
It's a decision that we must make.
And it's a decision that we make repeatedly.
It's a decision that you make on a regular basis
throughout the day.
You wake up in the morning and say,
I'm gonna trust the Lord today,
I'm gonna put my trust in the Lord,
and then you're gonna face a scenario,
you're gonna face a situation
in which you're going to be tempted to trust yourself.
You're gonna be tempted to trust some other means,
some other thing, but we find that in that moment
at that crosshair, we must say,
no, I put my trust in the Lord.
The Psalm in Psalm 11 in verse one says,
how say ye to my soul, flee as a bird to your mountain.
Have you ever heard anyone say that,
use the expression, I wish I could just fly away?
And I'm not talking about Southwest
and their little catch, you know, marketing tag.
I'm just talking about people that say,
I wish I could just fly away.
I wish I could just get out.
What do they mean by that?
I wish I could get out of the situation.
And here there's some people that are saying to David,
he says, he asked the question,
how say ye to my soul, flee as a bird to your mountain.
Can I tell you this evening
that there are times in which other people,
but there are also times in which maybe
you talk to yourself and say, I wish I could get away.
You ever talk to yourself?
Come on, we're not gonna, you know,
let's take you to the institution or anything
if you're talking to yourself.
I'm just, it happens, right?
You talk to yourself.
You can get yourself in a lot of trouble
when you start talking to yourself.
Start having a pity party.
I just wanna get out of here.
I just wanna, no, no, no.
He says, how are you saying that to me?
Listen, I have declared, I have put my trust in the Lord.
So no matter what comes, no matter what happens,
no matter what circumstance, no matter the difficulty,
the depth of the difficulty,
the people and what they're saying,
no, I have made this decision.
I have made the deliberate decision
and I am declaring for others to know
that in the Lord put I my trust.
And so in this evening,
the challenge is really simple for us.
As I mentioned by way of introduction,
that though the Psalm has just seven verses,
that there are many ways in which we'll be challenged
as we study these seven verses.
And tonight the challenge is this.
Can we declare as the psalmist did,
in the Lord put I my trust?
That I've made that deliberate decision
that no matter what comes my way,
no matter what the circumstances
and no matter what the other people are saying,
I have put my trust in the Lord.
Why?
Because the Lord is trustworthy,
because we know his name,
because we have this book that he gave us,
the Bible that reveals to us his nature and his character
and who he is and what he's capable of doing.
And I say, no, no, no, I'm not trusting in man,
I'm not trusting in princes,
I'm not trusting in my sword,
I'm not trusting in any of these things.
No, I'm trusting in the Lord
and I'm gonna put my trust in God.
And how important it is for God's people
to stand as David did in the midst of difficulty
and say in the Lord put I my trust.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you tonight.
We thank you for loving us.
God, I pray that you'd help us tonight.
I know that in a room, a crowd of any size,
there are difficulties that we face.
Lord, sometimes those difficulties
can bring discouragement in our lives,
can overwhelm us.
And God, I pray that tonight you would help us
from this half a verse of scripture
as we look at Psalm 11 one
and then coupled with so many other verses
of scripture tonight.
Lord, would you help us to be able to declare
as the psalmist did in the Lord put I my trust.
Understanding the importance of being actively engaged
in making that decision.
Understanding that you are trustworthy.
And though in our own human frailty,
we may be tempted to trust in other things.
things, including ourselves. Lord, I pray tonight that you would help us to put our
trust in thee. We thank you for the privilege of Wednesday evenings, not only being able
to study your word, but spend time together as a church family in prayer. And I pray God
that you'd bless our time of prayer tonight. I pray that you would help us, Lord, to exalt
and magnify you. Lord, help us to seek you. We thank you that you're a God who hears and
answers and that you're able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think.
We pray that you'd have your will and way, for it's in Christ's name we pray. Amen.