So, Genesis chapter number one, be looking here.
This is our second lesson on in the beginning and studying through the book of Genesis and
looking forward to that.
I'm going to put this back on in case they get it fixed, in case I move around.
I have a tendency occasionally to move around, I don't know if you've noticed that or not,
but just every once in a while.
Last Sunday night, though, I didn't move, I don't think, at all.
I stayed right behind the pulpit the whole time, and this probably will be about the
same tonight.
Definitely more teaching than preaching as we're dealing with some foundational things
here for our study through the book of Genesis.
Last week, of course, we looked at in the beginning and kind of dealt with why it is
that we should study the book of Genesis.
That sounds better, I'm going to try the lapel.
There we go.
Amen, it works now.
Praise the Lord.
Can you hear me?
You could hear me before, I'm sure, and anyway, Genesis chapter number one.
We looked last week at the foundation, why we should study the book of Genesis, the importance
of studying the book of Genesis, the foundation for all of the rest of Scripture.
This evening, before we dive into the specifics of Creation Week, I believe it's important
for us to acknowledge the truth that's declared in Genesis one and verse number one, that
it is God that created.
The title simply is going to be that this evening, God created, and looking here at
Genesis one and verse number one, unfortunately the origin of the universe and all that is
contained therein is regularly debated.
We find in our society that we live in and we think about the scholarly environment of
some of our schools and what have you and all of these theories that have been offered,
and oftentimes with those theories, what we find is that the biblical account of creation
is under intense, constant attack.
And we find here that in Genesis one and verse number one, it says, in the beginning, God
created the heaven and the earth.
We understand the account is given to us here in Genesis one, and as we look at the foundation,
the groundwork, if you will, for this study, I believe that it's important that we are
firmly grounded in the truth, that we understand that the teaching of the word of God regarding
the subject of creation is much deeper and broader than just the book of Genesis.
And we're going to look at a whole lot of Scripture this evening, so get your fingers
ready and we're going to move through the Scriptures and we'll get back here to Genesis
one in just a little while, but I want to share with you a number of verses throughout
the word of God that would declare to us, that would reveal to us the truth that God
created.
And then we're going to look at some theories, just a couple of them that are commonly offered,
and there are some, unfortunately, even under the broad category of Christendom, that have
bought into some of these false teachings and these false theories, and I'll share with
you this evening why it is that we reject those things.
At least that's my intent, we'll see how far we get.
Genesis chapter number six and verse number seven, notice here what is said, of course,
God speaking with Noah and getting ready to deal with the flood and all of those things.
In Genesis six and verse number seven, notice what the Lord said here in this text of Scripture.
And the Lord said, I will destroy man, what's it say, whom I have created from the face
of the earth, both man and beast and the creeping thing and the fowls of the air, for it repenteth
me that I have made them.
And so we find the declaration here in Genesis six, as God is giving the information concerning
the wickedness and the soon destruction because of that wickedness, that he says, I will destroy
man whom I have created.
He then goes through and talks about all of the others, the beast, the creeping thing,
the fowls of the air.
It says, it repenteth me that I have made them.
Passover, if you will, to Psalm, look at the book of Psalm, Psalm 90.
In the book of Psalms, we'll look at two passages here in the book of Psalms.
Psalm 90, we often think about this Psalm and we're mindful of the truth that is given
to us when Moses prays that truth and tells us the importance of numbering our days, teach
us to number our days that we may apply our hearts unto wisdom.
But here in Psalm 90, in verse number two, the Bible says this, before the mountains
were brought forth, or ever thou hast formed the earth and the world, even from everlasting
to everlasting, thou art God.
Not only does that deal with the fact that God created, but once again, it reinforces
that truth that we looked at last week, that our God is eternal.
Though he starts in Genesis 1, in the beginning, God has no beginning.
That's the beginning of time as God has created it and given for us a reference point of creation,
but our God is eternal.
He is alpha and omega, the beginning and the end.
Let's turn over to Psalm 102, just a few passages over in Psalm 102 and we'll look
at verse number 25.
Again, I want to lay the groundwork this evening.
There are so many that have attacked the writings of Moses in the first several chapters of
the book of Genesis, but we understand that the word of God declares throughout the word
of God that God created.
We see not only God making that declaration, we see the psalmist referring to it.
Again, here in Psalm 102 and verse 25, it says, of old hast thou laid the foundation
of the earth and the heavens are the work of thy hands.
Turn to the book of Isaiah, if you will, and what a powerful book, the book of Isaiah.
What a great prophet of God, a man of God who stood upon the truth and proclaimed righteousness
and preached to a people that did not repent.
And we find that in this particular book, Isaiah, we'll look at chapter number 42.
We'll look at a couple of verses here in the book of Isaiah and once again find that Isaiah
declares for us that it is God who created.
In Isaiah 42 and verse number 5, the Bible says, thus saith God the Lord, he that created
the heavens and stretched them out, he that spread forth the earth and that which cometh
out of it, he that giveth breath unto the people upon it and spirit to them that walk
therein.
Turn over just a couple of pages to Isaiah 45 and look at two verses here, verse number
12 and verse number 18, Psalm 45 and verse number 12.
The Bible says this, look at verse number 11 with it, thus saith the Lord, the Holy
One of Israel and his maker, ask me of things to come concerning my sons and concerning
the work of my hands, command ye me.
I have made the earth and created man upon it.
I even my hands have stretched out the heavens and all their hosts have I commanded, verse
18, for thus saith the Lord that created the heavens, God himself that formed the earth
and made it, he hath established it.
He created it not in vain, he formed it to be inhabited.
I am the Lord and there is none else.
That's good, I mean just praise the Lord.
He's providing for us the truth that God created, in fact even Satan himself is created
according to the book of Ezekiel in chapter number 28.
We find in this text of scripture that Satan himself has been created.
We understand that God created all things including the angels.
We understand that Satan Lucifer prior to his fall, he was an angel of course and he
lifted himself up with pride, said he would be like the most high and he was cast out
of heaven, but we find that in Ezekiel 28 in verse number 15, the Bible says this, thou
wast perfect in thy ways from the day that thou wast created till iniquity was found
in thee.
And even Satan himself, he's not eternal, Satan is not omniscient, he's not omnipotent,
he is not God.
I'm thankful that John tells us in 1 John in chapter number 4 that greater is he that
is in us than he that is in the world and God is victorious because he is creator and
Satan of course originally Lucifer, he was created even as we find here in Ezekiel 28.
Lest we think the references are only in the Old Testament and certainly we can look at
a number of additional verses this evening, turn to the book of Acts if you will, Acts
chapter number 17.
This is an interesting passage of Scripture for we find throughout the Old Testament,
Acts chapter number 17, we find that throughout the Old Testament, even leading up through
the Gospels, much of the reference that is given and much of the focus upon the nation
of Israel.
Of course we understand there are other references, other people groups and of course throughout
the Old Testament the interactions that God's people had with other groups of people, but
we find here in Acts chapter number 17 that Paul is going to go and he's going to preach.
The Bible tells us that he's going to Athens and it's interesting because we find some
of the foundation for some of this false teaching, some of that which underlies the philosophies
behind evolution is found in a lot of these pagan cultures and we think, you know, often
times we think about evolution and we think that it all started with Darwin and it really
didn't all start with Darwin.
We understand that if you look at many of the pagan cultures throughout the history
of the world, that there were many ideas about how the world came to be and so on and so
forth and we find here in Acts chapter number 17 that Paul, he was there, now you understand
that Paul was supposed to be resting.
The text of Scripture would tell us that after the
work at Thessalonica and Berea that they left Paul there and he was waiting but
he saw something that stirred him and moved him and what he saw was a city
that was wholly given to idolatry. That's how the city of Athens is described in
verse number 16 of Acts 17 and we find that Paul begins to share the gospel
with these individuals. He mentions through here about the way in which when
he stood on the midst of Mars Hill he's preaching, he speaks about all of the
altars that he observed during his time there because it was a city that was
wholly given to idolatry and he mentions that he sees this altar that had the
inscription to the unknown God in verse number 23 but I want you to notice what
Paul says here in verse 23 it says, for as I passed by and beheld your devotions
I found an altar with this inscription to the unknown God whom therefore ye
ignorantly worship him declare I unto you. And here's how he's going to
declare, here's how Paul is going to declare the Lord God Jehovah to these
people in Athens he says God that made the world and all things therein. Where
does he start? He starts with creation because he is creator. You understand
that he was creator before he's Redeemer from man's perspective we
understand God is eternal and his plan of redemption was determined before the
foundation of the world even as we discussed last week and looked at the
truth of that but we find here that Paul begins with this truth that God is the
creator he made the world and all things therein seeing that he is Lord of heaven
and earth he dwelleth not in temples made with hands and we find that Paul
would go through and he would preach a powerful message to these that were
there at Athens he continues preaching he eventually gets to the crucifixion
and the resurrection and there was a mixed response from the people in
Athens to the message that Paul preached but we see that where Paul began was
with the truth that God is the creator. Romans chapter number one we looked at
it last week we won't take the time to look there again this week but you can
mark it down Romans 1 verses 20 and 24 and really you could look at the
entirety of that passage and see the declaration that God is creator turn
over first Corinthians 15 if you will first Corinthians 15 just a few more
verses here you say pastor why are we taking so much time because it's so
vitally important that the foundation is secure that the foundation is firm
the reality is that there are people that are attacking are the core beliefs
that we have as as Christians concerning this thought this subject of creation
and what they're trying to do is remove God and so often you find that in their
attacks they will attack the truth that is given in the book of Genesis and tell
us for one reason or another that it's not trustworthy but I'm seeking to help
you understand this evening that it's a whole lot more than just confound to a
couple of chapters in the book of Genesis the truth that our God is the
creator is found throughout the Word of God and we cannot take these verses of
scripture and the truth that is given over and over and over and just set it
to the side and adopt some other theory concerning the origin of the earth and
first Corinthians 15 the Apostle Paul is speaking about the subject of the
resurrection and it's interesting because what Paul does and I've been
teaching through the book of first Corinthians those of you that are in
our the adult Sunday school class we dealt with this a few weeks ago but Paul
says in verse number 37 and that which thou sowest thou sowest not that body
that shall be but bare grain it may chance of wheat or of some other grain
he's answering the question that was asked in verse number 36 or that
possibly would be asked how are the dead raised up and with what body do they
come and the Apostle Paul begins to provide an answer for these believers in
Corinth and he goes through and it's interesting because as he's giving them
the answer to this question that could potentially rise he's sharing with them
truth regarding creation and he tells us in verse number 38 but God giveth it a
body as it hath pleased him into every seed his own body he says this in verse
number 39 all flesh is not the same flesh there is one kind of flesh of men
another flesh of beasts another of fishes and another of birds there are
also celestial bodies and bodies terrestrial but the glory of the
celestial is one and the glory of the terrestrial is another there is one
glory of the Sun another of the glory of the moon and another glory of the
stars for one star differs from another star in glory but what Paul's saying
here in this text of Scripture if you notice in verse 38 but God giveth it a
body it's God who is the creator and he's created all of these things and
then he tells them he leads into by laying this foundation something that
they could see that they could observe they knew that there was one kind of
flesh for man and a different for for for beast and for fish and so on and so
forth they knew that there was a difference between terrestrial and
celestial they knew that there was a difference I did that wrong celestial
and terrestrial he knew that there was a difference between the Sun and the moon
and the stars but they could not understand how that the natural body
would raise to be a spiritual body so Paul laid down that groundwork
declaring the truth that God is creator Ephesians chapter number three we'll
look at this verse in our study through the book of Ephesians but we find that
in Ephesians 3 and verse number 9 the Bible says this and to make all men see
what is the fellowship of the mystery which from the beginning of the world
have been hidden God look at this who created all things by Jesus Christ who
created all things by Jesus Christ we find in the book of Colossians in
chapter number one what a powerful truth that God gives us here in Colossians 1
concerning creation and the fact the the work of the Lord Jesus Christ it says in
Colossians 1 will begin in verse 15 speaking of Jesus the character it says
who is the character of Christ who is the image of the invisible God the first
born of every creature now you understand that as we would understand
what Paul is dealing with here in Colossi and giving this instruction you
understand that Jesus Christ came to this earth to manifest God to show he
says if you've seen me you've seen the Father right and that what Christ
declared and he's manifesting he's making it known he's revealing it and
listen when it says that he's the firstborn of every creature he's not
created he is the creator and that's important for us to understand because
Jesus Christ is eternal remember we dealt with that last week in the book of
Revelation when Jesus Christ himself said that he was the Almighty that he
was the Alpha and the Omega the first and the last the beginning and the
ending and we find here that it says in verse 16 for by him were all things
created that are in heaven and that are in earth visible and invisible now
notice it would have been sufficient for God to simply say for by him were all
things created all things but he goes further he says all things that are in
heaven all things are in earth it says this visible and invisible whether they
be thrones or Dominions or principalities or powers notice at the
end of verse 16 all things were created by him and for him and he is before all
things and by him all things consist and then it says this in verse 18 he is the
head of the body the church who is the beginning the firstborn from the dead
that in all things he might have the preeminence what a powerful passage of
scripture that we find here in Colossians 1 dealing with the creation
and the fact that he has created all things the book of Revelation will
finish there we'll look at two verses in the book of Revelation as we move
through laying the groundwork this evening Revelation 4
Revelation chapter before look at it with me in verse number 9 will read down
through verse number 11 it says this and when those beasts give glory and honor
and thanks to him that sat on the throne who liveth forever and ever the four and
twenty elders fall down before him that sat on the throne and worship him that
liveth forever and ever and cast their crowns before the throne saying look at
what they say in verse 11 thou art worthy O Lord to receive glory and honor
and power for thou hast created all things and for thy pleasure they are and
were created sounds often awful awful familiar to what we just read there in
Colossians 1 and verses 15 through 18 turn over to just a couple of pages over
to Revelation chapter 10 and we'll look here at one final verse of scripture
Revelation 10 in verse number 6 the Bible says and swear by him that liveth
forever and ever who created heaven and the things that are that therein are and
the earth and the things that therein are and the sea and the things which are
therein that
there should be no there should be time no longer remember he created time as
well right in the beginning we talked about that last week he created time
space and matter and we find here that it says that he created heaven and all
the things therein he created earth and all the things therein he created the
sea and all the things therein and we find that the Word of God we've looked
at a number of verses of Scripture this evening and I believe that beyond a
shadow of a doubt we can establish the foundation for this truth that God
created we must be we must have this firm foundation when the foundations are
being attacked when the enemy is attacking the very truth of God's Word
and who he is and his work of creation we must be able to stand upon the truth
of the Word of God and understand that it's it's found this is taught in in
many more places than just the book of Genesis notice not only do we understand
that God created and we establish that foundation but it's also important that
we know that this creation took place over six literal days 24-hour days now
this is another important aspect for us to understand and we'll look at a couple
of the objections and some of the theories that people deal with but just
a quick review of Genesis chapter number one go back there if you will and we'll
just look through we'll pick through a few verses of Scripture here this
evening to look at this truth that creation took place over six literal 24
hour days it's important that we understand this that this is a firm
foundation that we have you know there are theologians quote-unquote that call
themselves theologians that do not believe what we're sharing with you this
evening regarding the the creation being in six literal 24 hours days we find in
Genesis chapter number one in verse number five the Bible says in God called
the light day in the darkness he called night look at the last part it says in
the evening and the morning were what the first day verse number eight if you
look there it says and God called the firmament heaven and the evening and the
morning were what the second day you can follow this pattern you can see in verse
number 13 that it says this and the evening in the morning where the third
day you find that in verse number 19 the evening and the morning were the fourth
day you find in verse 23 and the evening and the morning worth a fifth day you
find in verse number 31 and God saw everything that he had made and behold
it was very good in the evening and the morning were the sixth day it says in
verse number one of chapter 2 thus the heavens and the earth were finished and
all the host of them and on the seventh day God ended his work which he had made
and he rested on the seventh day from all his work which he had made the
Hebrew word yom is the word for day that is used throughout Genesis 1 it's
actually used throughout much of the scripture and we find that this word
has with it carries within the context a literal 24-hour period of time a day as
we refer to it this evening now we understand I've mentioned this verse of
scripture last week in in the book of 2nd Peter chapter number 3 when the
Bible says and of course there were scoffers in the day saying where's the
promise of his return and so on and so forth and Peter said the Lord is not
slack concerning his promise as some men count slackness but as long
suffering to us we're not willing that any should perish but that all should
come to repentance in 2nd Peter 3 and verse number 9 and then Peter says this
to help the the believers to encourage them and to increase their faith that a
day is of a thousand years and a thousand years as a day now what he's
dealing with there in that text of scripture is helping the believers to
understand that though Christ has not returned he's outside of time he's
eternal and we're the ones that are confound by time and we're the ones that
are in this time but God is outside of time he's always present and we find
here this evening that when we look at that truth in 2nd Peter 3 in verse
number 9 it is an invalid Bible hermeneutic or interpretation to take
that principle that Peter deals with and bring it back here to Genesis and
say what was a thou it's like a thousand years no it's not true and we'll deal
with some of that in just a moment but I want you to understand that as you go
through this text of scripture that word yum is used repeatedly and it means a
24-hour period we see day one through day seven but notice also in Exodus
chapter number 20 in verse number 11 in Exodus chapter number 20 and verse
number 11 we find that here this is of course the record that God has given us
with regard to the the Ten Commandments and of course Moses had received these
commandments but I want you to notice that during the giving of that fourth
commandment concerning the Sabbath day really begins in verse number eight it
says remember the Sabbath day to keep it holy six days shalt thou labor and do
all thy work but the seventh day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God in it thou
shalt not do any work thou nor thy son nor thy daughter thy manservant nor thy
maidservant nor thy cattle nor thy stranger that is within thy gates then
notice the example that is referenced in verse number 11 for in six days the Lord
made heaven and earth the sea and all that in them is and rested the seventh
day wherefore the Lord blessed the Sabbath day and hallowed it now as we
read verse number 11 of Exodus 20 it is in perfect agreement with the account
that we just read in Genesis 1 through the beginning of chapter number 2 day 1
day 2 day 3 all the way through day 6 and then day 7 God rested and so God
sets forth this truth for the children of Israel regarding the Sabbath and he
tells them that they should work for six days and then they should rest on
the seventh and he says it is a pattern that would follow that of creation now
that's important for us to understand because that was a literal week for the
children of Israel correct they worked for six days literal and then they had a
seventh day that was a day of Sabbath a day of rest and we find that as God
would give that example and provide that for them you see the omniscience
of God the wisdom of God he could have created everything that fast he could
have he's God he chose to create it the way that he did to set forth the pattern
and he gives it there for the children of Israel this truth is repeated if you
want to jot the verse down in Exodus 31 and verse number 17 where the Bible says
this Exodus 31 and verse number 17 it is a sign between me and the children of
Israel forever speaking of the Sabbath for in six days the Lord made heaven and
earth and on the seventh day he rested and was refreshed again the pattern that
God set forth through the creation week now we look at the truth that God
created we see that it was six literal 24-hour days and then the question comes
to this what do we do when science seems to disagree with the biblical account
that's the question everyone wants to ask and here's what many people have
chosen to do is they choose to start with science and then interpret the
Bible that's not a good perspective we need to start with the Bible and then
interpret science amen and we don't listen we don't have to have all the
same degrees that some scientists have remember what it said in Romans 1
professing themselves to be wise they became fools and I'm not questioning
their intellect what I'm doing is saying they're not starting with God and what
they're seeking to do is they're seeking to ignore the Creator to get rid of God
they don't want to be accountable to God and we must always start with and stand
upon the truth of the Word of God we do not start with science and seek to
interpret the Bible those that have made that error have looked at some of
the evidence quote-unquote of the fossil record and some of the geological
questions that would arise from that we'll deal with some of those things in
the coming weeks and we'll look at those in great detail but what has happened is
some look at that evidence quote-unquote that is provided and say oh how do we
explain this and and it seems as if they're providing this mountain of
evidence against creation and therefore we must change our approach and we must
reinterpret the Bible three theories there are many more that we could deal
with but I'm just gonna deal with three this evening one is often referred to as
theistic evolution it needs to be refused and rejected what they say
basically is that the model in which evolution is viewed as God's method of
creation that's wicked I told listen there was somebody that questioned me
about this about five months ago what is it it's March four months ago somebody
questioned me about this not even in this state no one here would if I told
you who it was you wouldn't know who they are but they questioned me about
this thing of evolution and creation and they say and they're a person
professing child of God and they said well, how do you know how can you be so sure that God didn't choose to use?
evolution
Because I read the Bible
Like I mean, is that really that hard and here's the deal if God chose to use evolution
You know what? That means he lied to us in Genesis 1
That's a big problem
Because God is not a man that he should lie
Amen, if God chose and this is what I told the person listen if God chose to use evolution
Then my God would have told me that
Amen, but he didn't why because he didn't use evolution he created
Amen, and so we have to reject theistic evolution and there are people that call themselves
Theologians that want to use in and purport this theory and and try to
Offer it as as a model in which would make everybody happy
But it rejects what God said
Theistic evolution must be rejected
day age
Theory the day age theory
Some of you may have heard of this
It's a theory that has been given that's been offered in which the days of creation are interpreted
Figuratively as the ages of geology
It's really kind of a weird idea as to what they deal with and the reality is that most geologists don't even buy it
They they toss it out. They say it's not really valid because it doesn't fit their model either
But this day age theory, you know, there are some that interpret the Bible figuratively
They're always trying to spiritualize something and we believe that we ought to interpret the drop the Bible as it's given
Literally when God says and the morning and the evening were the first day
The morning and the evening were the first day
Amen, not some long age of geology
That's some figurative speech that God is using that maybe could encapsulate millions of years. No, it's a day. It's 24 hours
and
Then one that was given that some of you may have been
Familiar with in fact some of you
If you have a study Bible that you use in some of your study Bibles in Genesis 1 and 2
You may actually see in the notes of your study Bible this theory and it's called the gap theory
This theory
That's that's often referred to as the gap theory
It's an imaginary gap of time between Genesis 1 1 and Genesis 1 2
It's really not known how long that period of time is
But basically what the theory if I could boil it down and just give you it to you in a summary
Basically what they would teach is that the original earth that is mentioned in Genesis 1 in verse number 1
Was there for millions billions?
I mean you name how long it's been there and all sorts of things took place and what have you and then some
cataclysmic event took place and destroyed it and then
God recreated everything following the model that we have in Genesis 1 as we see it today, but that's not what God said
and
Here's the problem
See, I mentioned this before and it's so important that we understand because the gap theory again
It's one of these theories that was offered to try to I will use the word appease science
They sought to try to mesh the two. Okay. Well, you can believe in evolution
You can believe in that theory and we're gonna want to believe in this and so we wanted them to agree
And so we'll offer you these millions of years these billions of years. It's in this little gap between Genesis 1 1 and 1 2
Here's the problem all of these theories and we've only looked at three of them this evening
There are more that exists
But in all those theories there are long periods of time and in these long periods of time there is struggle
There is decay and there is death
This is a major problem for our biblical understanding
Because here's why God said that at the end of creation week that everything was good
Amen look at Genesis 1 1 1 with me again and look at verse number 31 in
Genesis 1 in verse number 31 the Bible says and God saw how many things?
Everything that he had made and behold it
What's it?
everything
It was very good
And the evening in the morning were the sixth day
So you're telling me that God is looking there at his creation on day six
He's looking at everything that he's created and he's looking at at man and all of that
Which he's created really literally standing upon
Just ages of decay and death and saying it's very good
No
See, here's the issue. There's no death until there's sin
Right. What what did the Bible tell us in Romans 5 in verse number 12 for by one man sin entered into the world and
death by sin
So if we remove the teaching of Scripture and we adopt some of these false theories that have been
suggested and have been
Offered to try to mesh the two worldviews
What happens is we begin to undermine all of the scripture and all of a sudden we have death
Before we come to the fall in Genesis 3
But the fall in Genesis 3 is what caused death and the day that ye eat thereof ye
shall
surely die
Right and we see that truth given to us in Romans 5 and verse number 12 as I quote it just a moment ago
What has happened so often as we look at this and kind of conclude this evening is the geological?
Geological questions from the fossil record have caused people to doubt what the Bible record says try to come up with some other
theory some other explanation
But instead of doing all of that and abandoning the very Word of God
We must stand upon the foundation of God's Word and very simply offer this
response is that the cataclysmic activity
That would give an an honest response and an accurate
Reference point to all of those geological
Geological questions can be found in the account that is given to us in Genesis 6 through 9. It's called the global flood
Amen, but what happens is they want to question the global flood as well
Because what they're trying to do is
very
Systematically tear our Bibles apart so that they no longer have to be accountable to God
But God's on his throne
Amen, he reigns
He is eternal and he has given us the truth
Concerning creation and I am so thankful for it. I'm thankful that we can stand upon the Word of God
There are some that would attack us. Oh, you're just too narrow-minded. Oh, you just don't understand
Oh, you just aren't smart enough. You haven't studied enough. I will provide for you over the next several weeks of studying
As we as we study through the book of Genesis
I will provide for you many references on how science proves exactly what God's Word says and
The scientists don't want to talk about it
They don't want to talk about it. Why because they don't want to be accountable to God
And this evening we find that the Bible not just Genesis
But yes in Genesis the Bible clearly teaches
God
Recreated and we must be firm on that position
We do not want to adopt any of these theories that have been provided that have been suggested that have been offered
We want to stand upon this is what God said and that settles it. Amen. Let's pray together father
We love you, but thank you