Hebrews chapter number 11, Hebrews chapter number 11 this evening.
And I have referenced, I believe, every single Wednesday of 2026 that I have been here.
And there's been a couple of Wednesdays where Brother Mark has filled in for me, which I
always appreciate his willingness to do that.
But every other Wednesday that I've been here for 2026, I think that I have referenced Hebrews
11 in verse number 6.
Without faith, it is impossible to please him, for he that cometh to God must believe
that he is, and that he is a rewarder of them that diligently seek him.
And we have referenced that verse through every service of this year.
We're one quarter through 2026.
Today is April the 1st, and so we have three months in the books.
And it's hard to believe that the first quarter of the year is behind us.
But here we are in the month of April, and as we've gone through on Wednesdays, both
in the morning, Wednesday morning prayer and Bible study, and in the evening, Wednesday
evening prayer and Bible study, we have, like the psalmist, we have expressed our desire
to see God work.
That's where we started in Psalm 119, it is time for thee, Lord, to work, for they have
made void thy law.
I preached the message, but I was hopeful that as I preached the message, it would not
just be a single voice that's pleading and expressing a desire to see God work, but a
corporate desire that we would, each and every one of us, we would desire to see God work
in our hearts personally, and in our families, in our church, in our community, in our country,
in our world.
And I believe this evening that God is at work.
I believe that.
You see God working, God saving people still.
He's still using the gospel, He's still answering prayer, He's still working in our lives.
I'm thankful for each day that I have an opportunity to open the Bible and read the scriptures
and God speaks to me, and it's a blessing and it's an encouragement that God indeed
is at work.
And we desire to see Him do greater works in these days in which we're living.
We find that as we have expressed our desire, we've also acknowledged the fact that God
is able and there's nothing too difficult for our God.
There's no situation, no problem, no individual that's too hard, that's too difficult for
our God.
We've acknowledged as well that the only thing that can limit our omnipotent God is my doubt,
my unbelief, my lack of faith.
And the reality this evening is that as we examine our own lives and as we've spent the
last few weeks looking at the subject of doubt in particular, we find that we often may have
to say as that man did in the gospel of Mark, Lord, I believe help thou mine unbelief.
And we may, like the disciples, have to get alone with the Lord Jesus Christ and hear
the Lord say to us, because of your unbelief.
And we've got to deal with that.
And so as we've had the opportunity to look at a number of passages of scripture and express
these things and understand these principles biblically, we now come to Hebrews chapter
number 11.
In Hebrews chapter 11, again, verse 6, a verse that I've quoted and referenced each Wednesday
throughout this calendar year, and it's often been referred to as the Hall of Faith chapter.
And some of you are familiar with Hall of Fame, and you can use that terminology, and
we know what that refers to here in America with regard to sports and what have you.
But we find that this portion of scripture has often been referred to as the Hall of
Faith chapter.
And I'd like to spend several weeks or months, however long it takes us to get through it
here, to really just walk through this chapter and to see what God does in and through his
people as they live by faith.
Faith is an action.
Faith simply defined as believing God, taking God at his word.
We might use the word trust, and that can express that same idea or concept of the word
faith.
And we understand this evening that as you look at Hebrews chapter number 11 here, that
you'll find that the Bible says in each of these records, by faith, and in the name of
the character, and then something that they did.
Their faith was revealed through their action.
What was it that allows for us to see their faith is their obedience to whatever God said.
Their response to whatever God had instructed or commanded.
And so you'll find that throughout this passage of scripture, you will find that by faith,
so and so did whatever the particular record is giving us of their behavior and their life
of faith.
If God says something once, it's important.
You believe that?
I believe if God says something once, it's important.
On four different occasions, and I'll reference, we're not going to go look at the verses,
but I'll reference them if you want to jot them in your notes.
The book of Habakkuk in chapter number 2 and verse number 4.
So Habakkuk 2 and verse number 4, and then three times in the New Testament, Romans chapter
number 1 and verse number 17, and then over in the book of Galatians, it's Galatians chapter
number 3 and verse number 11, and then right here in the book of Hebrews, Hebrews 10 and
verse number 38.
So on four occasions, Habakkuk 2 verse number 4, Romans 1 verse number 17, Galatians 3 verse
number 11, and Hebrews 10 verse number 38.
Mark, you started to word it right after I said Habakkuk 2.
What does it say?
The just shall live by faith.
Now do you think that God has that recorded for us four times in the scriptures because
he forgot that he said it the first time?
No.
There's an emphasis that is placed on this statement.
Why?
Because God's people, the just, are to live by faith.
The world, and before I got saved and before you got saved, all we could do is live by
sight.
But now we live by faith.
We find that the chapter begins this way in Hebrews 11, now faith is the substance of
things hoped for, the evidence of things not seen.
For by it the elders obtained a good report, through faith we understand that the worlds
were framed by the word of God so that things which are seen were not made of things which
do appear.
A great declaration with regard to the creation and the work of our creator and how he spoke
it all into existence and again, the truth of creation is not isolated to Genesis chapter
1 and Genesis chapter 2, the truth of creation is throughout the entirety of God's word.
Then we come to our text for this evening.
The Bible says in verse number 4, by faith Abel offered unto God a more excellent sacrifice
than Cain, by which he obtained witness that he was righteous, God testifying of his gifts
and by it he being dead yet speaketh.
So I've simply titled the message this evening By Faith Abel and so you'll know the titles
for all of the next messages on Wednesday, you just read through the text and you'll
see the by faith and whoever the next person is and that will be the title for the next
week's message and so next week, verse number 5, by faith Enoch, it's gonna be real simple
for you to know the text and the title.
And so we look at this and we see by faith Abel and it's interesting because what God
does here in Hebrews chapter 11 in this hall of faith chapter is he goes all the way back
to the very beginning, right?
Not with Adam and Eve but with Abel, Cain and Abel and he begins to reveal to us that
from the earliest days of creation of humanity, people were living by faith and even still
to this very day, we as God's people, the just, we are to live by faith.
And so we get a look at this portion of scripture in this verse and we must go back to Genesis
chapter 4 and so turn back there quickly if you will, Genesis chapter 4, we'll look at
verses 1 through 7 as we begin to understand what God is referring to when he says by faith
Abel offered unto God a more excellent sacrifice than Cain and so we read the record in Genesis
chapter 4 and we begin reading in verse number 1.
The Bible tells us this in Genesis 4 and verse number 1, and Adam knew Eve his wife and she
conceived and bare Cain and said, I have gotten a man from the Lord and she again bare his
brother Abel and Abel was a keeper of sheep but Cain was a tiller of the ground.
Now understand in verse number 2 there are two very different people, two very different
occupations but that has nothing to do with whether one would be accepted or one would
be rejected.
God's just simply giving us the truth of who these men were.
It says in verse number 3, and in process of time it came to pass that Cain brought
of the fruit of the garden.
ground, an offering unto the Lord. And Abel, he also brought of the firstlings
of his flock, and of the fat thereof." We'll pick it up in verse 4 in just a
moment, but I want you to notice in verse 3 and 4 the Bible tells us in process of
time. So we don't know exactly how much time has passed, but it says in process
of time it came to pass. And you read that Cain brought an offering and Abel
brought an offering. The details with regard to the offering are recorded for
us in verse 3. Cain brought an offering that was the fruit of the ground, and we
find in Abel in verse number 4 that it was a the firstlings of his flock. And so
we find the distinction with regard to the offering that was brought, and the
one that Cain brought, the one that Abel brought. As we begin to look at this, we
can ask ourselves the question, how did they know that they had to bring an
offering? Well, Adam must have communicated that to them. And who
communicated it to Adam? Well, God. God communicated to Adam, and Adam communicated
to his sons, and his sons bring this offering. Now you remember in Genesis
chapter number 3, the Bible records for us the the entrance of sin into the
world. And so as soon as sin entered into the world, the Bible tells us that Adam
and Eve, their eyes were opened, and they knew that they were naked. And what did
they do? They hid themselves, but they did something else. They tried to cover
their nakedness with fig leaves, right? And the fig leaves, that would have been
really the works of their own hands, and they're trying to cover their nakedness.
And so we find that God comes in into the garden there, and he begins to
call for Adam in the garden there, and we find that there's this
correspondence that takes place, and Adam very quickly says, it's the wife that you
gave me, the woman that you gave me, and she very quickly says it was the serpent.
So then God deals with the serpent, then he deals with the woman, and then he
deals with the man. And then something very significant happens at the end of
Genesis chapter number 3, and that's that God provides them with something else.
See, the fig leaves, the apron of fig leaves was not sufficient, so God
provided them a different covering. What did God provide for them? Covering of
skins, right, from an animal. And what had to happen in order for that
covering to be provided? Well, an animal had to be slain. That animal being slain,
that would have been the blood sacrifice, the blood offering that was made. And so
we find that in the garden, in Genesis chapter number 3, that there's this
record that God gives us, and he doesn't provide us with every single detail,
systematically how everything happened, but as you study the scriptures, we find
that the method by which Adam and Eve thought they could cover their
nakedness was insufficient, and God says that there's got to be an offering made
of blood, and you now have these coats of skin to cover, and it's the first example
that thousands of years before the Lord Jesus Christ would come to the cross and
shed his blood, that it was already pictured in Genesis chapter number 3.
And we find that there in Genesis chapter number 3, this truth was
communicated, no doubt, to Adam, and then to his sons, and his sons, in process of
time, they bring an offering. And so we see, first of all, as we consider by faith
Abel, I want you to see number one, that he offered. We see it here in verse
number 4, we referenced it in Hebrews 11 in verse number 4, by faith Abel offered
unto the Lord a more excellent sacrifice than Cain, and what was it that he
offered? Well, it says that he also brought of the firstlings of his flock,
and of the fat thereof. And the Lord, look at verse number 4, the end of the verse,
and the Lord had respect unto Abel, and to his offering. But unto Cain,
and to his offering, verse 5, he had not respect, and Cain was very wroth,
and his countenance fell. And the Lord said unto Cain, Why art thou wroth?
And why is thy countenance fallen? By the way, if God didn't love Cain,
and if Cain wasn't able to come to God in an acceptable way, there'd be no reason
for God to ever speak to Cain. But God spoke to Cain because God loved Cain,
for God so loved the world. And so we find that God speaks to Cain because he
sees that he's wroth, and his countenance had fallen, and he begins to speak with
him. And notice in verse number 7 what God says to Cain. He says,
If thou doest well, shalt thou not be accepted. And if thou doest not well,
sin lieth at the door, and unto thee shall be his desire, and thou shalt rule over him.
I want you to notice the two phrases that are mentioned in the beginning of verse
number 7. One of them is, if thou doest well, and then the second one,
if thou doest not well. So what is God communicating to Cain?
Well, there's a right way and there's a wrong way. There's an acceptable way and
there's an unacceptable way. Does that make sense? And so if thou doest well,
what does that mean? Well, you come by the way of blood offering.
We might say it this way as New Testament believers, you must come by the way
of the cross, right? There's no other way to be saved. There's no other way to have
redemption. The Bible says that, as we even referenced on Sunday morning,
that without the shedding of blood, there is no remission. And so we look here and
we find that God says to Cain, if thou doest well, shalt thou not be accepted.
In other words, he's saying to Cain, if you just come the way that I've
communicated to you, if you just come by faith, your offering reveals your faith,
then you'll be accepted. But if not, then sin lieth at the door. And so Cain had a
decision, Cain had a choice, just like Abel. Listen, this is a real text that
helps us understand, whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved.
This is not a situation of some Calvinistic teaching with regard to some
predetermined election. No, this proves to us very plainly in the very early pages
of Scripture that God says, if thou doest well, shalt thou not be accepted.
Aren't you thankful for that? And so we find that as we look at this offering
that Abel made, he offered, there's several things that I notice about the
offering. Number one, it was an offering that was made by faith. What was his
faith? Well, remember on Sunday, we talked about the law having a shadow of good
things to come. And we reference in Genesis chapter 3 and verse number 15,
where the Bible says, and I will put enmity between thee and the woman,
and between thy seed and her seed, it shall bruise thy head, and thou shalt
bruise his heel. And so Abel was putting faith in what God said. He was believing
that the way to come, the way to approach the Lord was with blood.
By the way, if you were to look and study later on as you go through the Scriptures
of the Old Testament, if you're to study the tabernacle, there's only one way to
get into the tabernacle. One entrance. And the first piece of furniture that you
come to, who knows what it is? The brazen altar. That's the first piece of furniture.
Why? Because a sacrifice is required. Blood is necessary. And so we find this
evening that this was an offering that was made by faith. By faith, Abel offered.
Notice, it was an offering that was made to God. Cain made an offering.
Abel made an offering. This offering that Abel made, he wasn't trying to be in
competition with his brother. No, he brought his offering to God, to the Lord.
When you live by faith, it's not so that somebody else might see, oh man, look at
their faith. No, I'm believing God and I'm living for God. The offering, the Bible
tells us, was a more excellent sacrifice. It was what God had prescribed. It was
according to the verbal word of God, what God had communicated. The offering was
accepted by God. The Bible plainly tells us in verse number 4 of Genesis 4,
and the Lord had respect unto Abel and to his offering. And so we find that it
was an offering that was accepted by God. It was an offering that was pleasing to
God. Remember, we said this in Hebrews 11 in verse number 6, and it's again a
verse that we've quoted all the way through the year. Without faith, it is
impossible to please him, for he that cometh to God must believe that he is,
and a rewarder of them that diligently seek him. So without faith, it is
impossible to please him. And so we find that he says, by faith, Abel. So he
offered a sacrifice, an offering that was pleasing to God. We're to live by faith.
And all the way back in Genesis chapter number 4, the first reference that we
have in Hebrews 11 of those individuals that are going to be recorded in the
hall of faith, those that are living by faith, is that by faith, Abel offered
unto God a more excellent sacrifice than Cain. Not only do we see that he
offered, but I want you to see number two, he obtained. The Bible says right there
in Hebrews chapter 11 in verse number 4, it says this, by which he obtained
witness that he was righteous, God testifying of his gifts, and by it he
being dead yet speaketh. Begin to think about this truth that he offered, but
then he obtained.
see that the verse says here that he obtained witness. Really, the idea of what's being
communicated here through this terminology and the verbiage that is used is his testimony
is in view. And by the way, when you live a life of faith, it's a testimony. In fact,
we have a reputation or a testimony whether we live by faith or not, but here, the context
of an individual that's living by faith, it says, by which he obtained witness. Notice
what it says, this testimony that he was righteous, that he was righteous. Begin to think about
that, begin to understand the teaching and we'd look at even this evening and discuss
our own, if we say that we've been declared righteous, we'd understand from a whole canon
of scripture perspective and a New Testament perspective that it's the imputed righteousness
of God that's been placed upon the account of us as individuals. Sinners saved by the
grace of God, it's not mine righteousness, it's the imputed righteousness of the Lord,
for He hath made Him to be sin for us who knew no sin, that we might be made the righteousness
of God in Him. And so we see that it says that he was righteous through this offering,
through his faith as he would make this offering on this day early on in human history, thousands
of years before Jesus Christ would come to the cross of Calvary, he was living by faith
and he had this testimony, he had this witness that he was righteous. And he was by faith
looking forward to one day, we know now as we look back on history, that would come thousands
of years later that Christ would come. We look back at Calvary, but we still look back
by faith, living now a couple thousand years after Calvary, but we still, it's still by
faith. Notice in the book of Romans, if you will, Romans chapter number 4, and let me
just say as you're turning to Romans chapter number 4, the only way to be declared righteous
is through faith, for by grace you're saved through faith. And it's all through faith,
it's not by works. And we see very plainly what's explained to us in Romans chapter number
4 with regard to Abraham. And if you look in verse number 1, the Bible says, what shall
we say then that Abraham our father as pertaining to the flesh hath found? For if Abraham were
justified by works, he hath whereof to glory, but not before God. And then notice this in
verse 3, for what saith the Scripture? It's always a good thing to make an appeal to God's
Word. Well this is my opinion, well this is what I think, well this is, no, no, no, what
does the Bible say? You know how many times I hear people take verses of Scripture out
of context? I mean all the time. I know I've used the illustration about over at the pizza
place where they put the tip jar out and they said, you know, money is the root of
evil or money is evil. No, no, no, the love of money is the root of all evil. And I had
to correct them on it because it just kind of bothered me. And I said, money is, you're
asking for money, you want tip, and you're putting a Bible verse on there that's not
even accurate. And people will quote verses of Scripture and they don't even know why
they're quoting it. The context in which they're using it. Well the Bible says that, you know,
God loved Jacob and he hated Esau. Do you know the context? It has nothing to do with
Genesis actually. It wasn't said in Genesis. It was actually said in Malachi and then repeated
in the Romans. But by the way, that was like two thousand years after the situation with
Jacob and Esau. And so you hear people that take verses out of context all the time and
they take, and so here's the appeal. What sayeth the Scripture? Let's go to the Bible.
What does God's Word say? So notice He says this, for what sayeth the Scripture,
Abraham believed God. That phrase is important. We'll see it again in verse number five, but
notice in verse three, Abraham believed God and it, his belief in God, was counted unto
him for righteousness. Now to him that worketh is the reward not reckoned of grace, but of
debt. But to him that worketh not, notice what it says here, but believeth on him that
justifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted for righteousness. So in verse number three,
it was Abraham believing God that was counted for righteousness. In verse number five, his
faith is counted for righteousness. Why? Because faith is believing God. Same thing. And so
we find that what God's telling us here is that the, the truth of Abraham and his righteousness,
it had nothing to do with circumcision. It had to do with his belief in God. Now circumcision
was the, the outworking, the evidence that he believed God. It was that stepping out
in, in the faith being revealed through the action. We find that there's many that have
taken issue with the book of James and were preaching through the book of James on Sunday
mornings. And I said this at the very beginning of the year as I preached that introductory
message with regard to the book of James, that there are many that have misunderstandings
about the book and so on and so forth. And I went through a number of those. And listen,
there's no contradiction between James and Paul. They're actually very complimentary.
In fact, James, he's talking about what's the evidence of your faith. You say you have
faith, show me your faith. How do we show our faith? Our works. The things that we do
are the evidence of our faith. But by the way, Paul said that we are his workmanship
created in Christ Jesus unto good works. Right after he said that we're not saved by works.
Right? In Ephesians 2, 8, 9, and 10. By the way, Paul says in the book of Titus, he says
that we're to be zealous of good works. Well, so there's no contradiction. It's a compliment,
a complimentary situation. And I said this on that first Sunday. It's as if, if you think
about it this way, Paul is dealing with the root while James is dealing with the fruit.
In the morning, it was prayer and Bible study session. Brother Ed's over there and I used
an example with him because he was there and it happened probably 13, 14 years ago. He
came here and he was helping me on a project. And he did that quite a bit back in those
days and always helping me with something around the church. And he came in here with
a ladder and it must've been a hundred year old wooden rickety rackety ladder. And I mean,
this thing was just, whew, man, it was not very, it didn't look very sturdy. And we're
working on something. And I think, I think we're actually working on some exit signs
and some emergency lighting. And he pulled that ladder out and I just looked at that
thing and I think he could read my mind, right? I'm like, there is no way I'm getting
on that ladder. Like I am, I am much heavier than he is. And that thing is not going to
hold me. And Mr. Ed says, oh, it's a good ladder. That thing will hold you. And I'm
like, nope, I am not stepping on that ladder. You know, the reality is that what would have
revealed that I really believed that that ladder would hold me as if I stepped onto
the ladder. Right? Does that make sense? Now I can stand there all day and say, I believe
it will hold me. But how do you know I believe that it will hold me is that I get on the
ladder. Does that make sense? And so here we find that the Bible talks about what he
obtained, his testimony, that it says that he was righteous. Now his righteousness was
not something that was a result of his works. It was his faith in the offering that he brought.
He brought the offering that he did because he believed what God said and he acted upon
what God said and thus brought this offering. And God says, yes, I accept that. Yes, I'm
pleased with that. Yes, that is a more excellent sacrifice. Why? Because you're operating in
the faith realm. Does that make sense? And so we're living by faith. We're desiring to
see God do great things. And we're desiring to see God work in great ways in our church,
in our families, in our lives individually. But we must live by faith. We must take God
at his word and our faith is revealed through our behavior. There was a man years ago that
crossed over Niagara Falls. He tightrope walked across Niagara Falls. Now that's just insanity
from my perspective, not something I would do. However, he decided that he would do that.
He tightrope walked across and he was successful. And he gets all the way to the other side
and he had a wheelbarrow with him and he had that thing, he pushed that thing. And
man, there's a group of people standing there waiting for him and he got there and they're
applauding him and they're excited for him and he made it across. And man, it's wonderful.
And then he said, how many of you think I can go to the other side? All of them. They
all believed that what they just saw him do coming from that side to this side that he
could do going back. And then he said, okay, one of you get in the wheelbarrow. You know
how many volunteers there were? Zero. By the way, if I were there and if you were there,
there'd probably still be zero. All right. So did they really believe? I mean, you can
argue it if you want, but the reality is that when we come to the faith life, living by
faith, we come to God. Listen, that man could have failed, but God's never going to fail.
God's never going to fail you. And so we just take God by, take God at his word. We just
live a life of faith.
And so we find that at the end of Hebrews 11 in verse number 4, to wrap it up this evening,
we notice this statement is made, and it's important that we grasp this as we finish
up this evening.
The Bible says at the end of the verse, and by it, by his faith, by his offering that
was an offering of faith that was a more excellent sacrifice, he being dead yet speaketh.
Cain didn't like the fact that Abel was accepted.
Can I say it this way?
Abel was killed because he lived by faith.
Abel was killed by his brother because he lived by faith.
There have been scores of people, perhaps millions of people throughout the centuries
that have been killed because they've simply lived by faith.
They lived by faith.
And what are we saying as we look at the text of Scripture?
We're saying this, that others may try to silence you.
Others might try to mock you.
Others may criticize you in whatever it might be when you live by faith, but we must acknowledge
and we must remember this evening that we are never forgotten by God when we live by
faith.
In our testimony speaks.
He being dead yet speaketh.
Jesus referenced Abel during his earthly ministry.
Now we read here in Hebrews 11 and throughout the centuries as we've had the complete canon
of Scripture, really as we look at it and we understand the human, the timeline, now
we are 6,000 plus years past the event that we're reading of this evening, but you're
speaking about a man that lived by faith.
He being dead yet speaketh.
I mentioned it last, I think it was last week, maybe the week before, about this year being
the 500th year anniversary of the Tyndale New Testament.
And William Tyndale had a desire that God's Word would be available to the common person
in the common language, English.
That was his desire.
And Tyndale was burned at the stake.
They tried to silence him because he simply tried to live by faith.
He wanted to get the Bible into the hands of the common people, the plow boy is one
that he referenced specifically.
And so we look at this text and we understand, listen, when we live by faith, we're not living
by faith so that somebody else could say, oh, look, they're a super faith person.
They have this, no, we're, he offered the offering to God.
We live by faith, we're living for God.
I'm seeking to just take God at His Word, believe God.
And Abel did that.
Abel believed what God said and Abel found, yes, he faced death, but he has a testimony
that still this evening speaks.
He obtained this witness, this testimony.
And this evening, remember that God is a rewarder of them that diligently seek Him.
Can I tell you this evening, the reward doesn't always come in a package the way that we might
think a reward would come.
You know, we have a Bible this evening.
Somebody said this, I heard him say it last week, every single person that's ever been
saved in an English New Testament of the Bible can look back 500 years ago and see the fruit
that came from William Tyndale's work.
That's phenomenal to think about it that way.
Absolutely phenomenal.
And so here we are this evening, we're saying, okay, so God is going to reward our faith.
That reward doesn't always look like something that we might picture in our mind as being
this award and being this reward, but we understand that God doeth all things well.
Remember, the psalmist said, it was good for me to be afflicted because then I learned
thy statutes.
And so not everything that we might look at as being a blessing or everything that we
might look at as being an unfortunate circumstance is really that.
Because we have tainted glasses and we find that God, he will reward our faith.
You say, yeah, but Abel died.
God allowed that to happen.
And he has a testimony that's still speaking today.
Because by faith, Abel offered unto God a more excellent sacrifice.
We don't have to worry about whatever the people are going to say.
We don't have to worry about whatever the consequences from man might be.
No, we just determined I'm going to live a life of faith because it's the life of faith
that pleases God.
And ultimately, my desire, your desire, our desire ought to be, I want to please God.
And without faith, it's impossible.
So what happens sometimes is we run around as believers thinking, I'm going to please
God, I'm going to please God, I'm going to please God, I want to please God with my life
and I'm trying to please God, but I'm not believing his word.
I'm not living by faith.
And God's already told us it's impossible.
But we're trying to do something that's impossible because we're leaning on our own understanding.
We say, well, I don't know how that, no, no, no, it's not about, it's just trusting God,
believing God by faith.
And so this evening we see by faith, Abel, he offered and he obtained.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you this evening.
Thank you so much for loving us.
I thank you for your word and I pray that you'd help us, Lord, help each one of us to
live a life of faith.
We see here in the life of Abel how he made an offering.
That offering was a more excellent sacrifice, but that offering was the result of his faith
in what you said.
God, you spoke the word and he acted in faith and he brought that offering and thank you
for that testimony.
Thank you that though he was killed, he being dead yet speaketh.
Thank you for his testimony.
God I pray that we'd have a testimony that would far outlive even our days upon this
earth, that we'd be people, men and women of faith, that God we would see and hear in
glory of the impact that that testimony would have on generations that would follow us.
We thank you for the privilege of prayer, even as we mentioned to start the service
this evening.
What a blessing.
Let's say it to the Lord in prayer and as we enter into our time of prayer this evening,
I pray that you would work, Lord, in each situation, that, Lord, you would just guide
us and direct us, help us, Lord, to please you and pray that you would work in a distinct
way and we'll thank you for it.
In Christ's name we pray, amen.
Let's turn to the back.