team this morning in your Bible, and to be looking the next few weeks at some messages
here from the life of Elijah. The Lord, I believe, as you look at his word, as we have
our theme for this year, great is the Lord and greatly to be praised. We understand that
the Lord has graciously revealed his greatness to us through his word. And we have examined
several portions of scripture this year in our quest to discover the greatness of God.
And I'm so thankful that God has given us a Bible, and not only has he told us that
he's great, but he's demonstrated his greatness for us. And we have the privilege of being
able to study a variety of portions of scripture and understanding, discovering the greatness
of God. As we move into the latter part of the year, we'll shift gears slightly and deal
with now that we've discovered God's greatness, it is important that we then declare God's
greatness, for we have a great God and he is to be declared. We mentioned this as we
started the year, that creation reveals God's greatness. And we said that through creation,
we see the power of God, we see the wisdom of God on display, and we find that God's
greatness is demonstrated, is revealed to us through creation. We spent a number of
weeks dealing with various aspects of creation, and what God's word tells us about creation.
And I'm so thankful that the creator God is also my helper and my deliverer, and he is
my redeemer. Obviously, as we get into the truth of redemption, begin to think about
the truth that the deliverance of God reveals his greatness. Again, you see his great power,
you see the fact that he's our great helper. We mentioned that inspiration reveals God's
greatness. We dealt with the inspiration of God's word. I'm so thankful that this is
not man's word about God, that this is the word of God. And the Bible says that all scripture
is given by inspiration of God, and what a joy and a blessing. Not only did we say that
inspiration reveals God's greatness, but preservation reveals God's greatness. It's a wonderful
thing that he inspired the originals, but we don't have the originals, but he promised
to preserve his word. And what a blessing to have the truth of preservation and to understand
this morning that we can have confidence in the book that we hold in our hands, knowing
that God has promised to preserve his word. And by the way, God cannot lie. He always
does what he says he will do, and he obviously used people. The Bible tells us that he exalts
his word above his very name, and he is obviously in his wisdom and in his grace and mercy,
he provided for us his word so that we could know him. And obviously we are without excuse
because he has given us his word. I mentioned this for a couple of weeks, that his love
demonstrates, reveals to us his greatness. We read about his great love, and I'm so thankful.
The songwriter said, amazing love, how can it be that thou, my God, didst die for me?
Amazing love, and God's love reveals to us just how great he is. The last couple of weeks
we've dealt with the truth of God's mercy, and God's mercy revealing his greatness. For
the next couple of messages, we'd like to examine how God's care for us reveals his
greatness. And we will consider some of the events from the life of Elijah, because I
believe that it so obviously reveals how God cares for his people. And God's care for us,
you think about the billions of people that are upon the face of the earth today, and
nearing eight billion people in population, and it is hard for us to wrap our mind around
that number. There are believers all around the globe. There are people all around the
globe that have trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as their personal savior, and we can rejoice
in that. We've had opportunity to meet believers, brothers and sisters in Christ from all sorts
of places. As you travel abroad, you have the opportunity, maybe not to be able to speak
with someone in the language that they speak, but you still have that bond in Christ, and
there's just something about that, and it's so precious, and it's so wonderful. And the
amazing thing about our great God is that he cares about you the same way he cares about
the someone on the other side of the globe, and every other person in between, all of
his children, he cares for us. And what a blessing to understand God's care, and I believe
that God's care for his children reveals just how great he is. As we look at the life of
Elijah, it's interesting, Elijah just comes on the pages of scripture, seemingly out of
obscurity. The Bible just declares in verse number one of 1 Kings 17, and Elijah, the
Tishbite. We don't have any reference of Elijah prior to this, obviously. From this
point forward, for a number of chapters, we'll read several things about the life and ministry
of Elijah, but from obscurity, it seems as if Elijah just comes upon the pages of scripture
in this particular time of history, in Israel's history, when Israel is far from God, when
Israel is just, Ahab is a wicked king, and we find that Elijah comes on the scene, and
notice the Bible says, and Elijah the Tishbite, who was of the inhabitants of Gilead, said
unto Ahab, as the Lord God of Israel liveth, before whom I stand, there shall not be dew
nor rain these years, but according to my word. That's a bold declaration. The boldness
of Elijah, it will not be the focus of our message this morning, but we know that Elijah
knew some things, he understood some things about God. He understood that God lives, that
God is a living God. He says this, as the Lord God of Israel liveth, notice what he
says, before whom I stand. When we stand and serve the Lord God Almighty, when we're going
in His power and in His might, we can stand before even the most wicked of kings, as
you see Ahab here, and we can deliver what thus saith the Lord. And we find that it was
God who was giving this instruction and this command to Elijah, and this particular message
of judgment that is delivered by Elijah to King Ahab. Obviously, Elijah, in obedience
to the Lord, delivering this message of divine judgment, we find that the Bible then continues
in verse number 2 and says, and the word of the Lord came unto him, Elijah, saying, notice
what the Bible says in verse 3, down through verse number 7, get thee hence and turn thee
eastward, and hide thyself by the brook Cherith, that is before Jordan. And it shall be that
thou shalt drink of the brook, and I have commanded the ravens to feed thee there. So
he went and did according unto the word of the Lord, for he went and dwelt by the brook
Cherith, that is before Jordan. The ravens brought him bread and flesh in the morning
and bread and flesh in the evening, and he drank of the brook. The Bible tells us in
verse number 7, and it came to pass after a while that the brook dried up, because there
had been no rain in the land. As we look at this portion of scripture this morning and
we consider God's care for his servant Elijah, and obviously God's care for us, I've titled
the message based on the portion of scripture where God says this in verse number 3, hide
thyself by the brook Cherith. Hide thyself by the brook Cherith. I would say this this
morning, that God's care, number 1 if you're taking notes, God's care is evidenced through
guidance. God's care is evidenced through guidance. Because God cares about his people,
he provides his people with guidance, with direction. And I think about the truth here
in the life of Elijah, as Elijah is standing there before King Ahab, king of Israel, this
wicked man, the Bible describes Ahab in verse number 33 of chapter number 16 this way, and
Ahab made a grove, and Ahab did more to provoke the Lord God of Israel to anger than all the
kings of Israel that were before him. And that's not really something to be proud about,
he is a wicked man, an ungodly man, and we find that Elijah is going to stand in his
presence in obedience to the Lord God Almighty, the Lord God of Israel that liveth, and he's
going to stand there and deliver a message of divine judgment. That message of divine
judgment, we understand that the impact of that judgment would be severe, and it would
be far-reaching. You find that Elijah would suffer from the consequences of this drought
that is announced in verse number 1 that says there shall not be dune or rain these years,
but according to my word. A drought is a very serious form of judgment. We find that the
impacts are quite severe and far-reaching. There are times in which we have in our lives
experienced maybe some windows where there's a couple of weeks without rain, and we begin
to see the impact on that even so quickly.
but can you imagine for years with no rain?
Years.
The impact would be severe,
the impact would be far-reaching.
But I find in the text of scripture,
as I mentioned that God's care is evidenced through guidance
that after Elijah delivers this message of divine judgment,
that the Lord came unto him and spoke to him,
according to verse number two,
and gave him guidance, provided him with direction.
The Bible says, get thee hence in verse number three,
and turn thee eastward,
and hide thyself by the brook Cherith
that is before Jordan.
Now it's interesting to me that as I look at the guidance
that God so graciously provides in verse number three,
revealing to us his great care for his servant,
that this guidance, this direction that is provided,
is clear and it's direct.
God was very clear in how he had given this instruction,
this guidance to his servant Elijah.
He didn't just say, hey, go eastward.
How far eastward?
To what place?
When have I arrived to the place where I'm to be?
No, we find that God very specifically,
he says, turn thee eastward and hide thyself
by the brook Cherith that is before Jordan.
He gave him a specific location,
he provided him with the exact guidance
that he would need.
This morning, if we'd be honest,
we each need guidance in our lives.
We need God's divine direction.
We need his leadership in our lives.
I'm thankful as you look at the Old Testament,
you begin to study the Old Testament
and the children of Israel during the time
in which they left Egypt in the wilderness wanderings,
you find that God graciously and supernaturally
led his people through some amazing means
in which he gave them guidance and clear direction.
It was a pillar of cloud by day
and a pillar of fire by night.
And it was so obvious.
And as the pillar of cloud would move
and the pillar of fire would move,
they would follow the leadership.
And even though they were following the leadership
of God Almighty, you would find that there were times,
many times in fact, that the children of Israel
would complain about the way
and what they discovered or found,
the hardships that they encountered.
And I will say this, that there are times
in which God is guiding us and leading us
and he may lead us directly into a time of difficulty.
It was God who told the disciples to get into the ship
and to go to the other side.
And as they obeyed the Lord, there was a great storm.
They were following the direction of God.
But in so doing, they encountered a storm.
And what was it that God was going to do?
He was going to reveal more of his attributes,
more of his power to his people.
And he was gonna deliver them through that.
And we find that God provides guidance.
And here for the servant Elijah,
God comes and speaks to him and gives him guidance.
I'm thankful this morning, unlike Elijah,
this morning we have the whole Bible.
We have the Holy Spirit of God who dwells within us.
If you've been saved this morning,
if you've trusted the Lord Jesus Christ
as your personal savior, the Bible tells us
that we are sealed with the Holy Spirit of God,
that our bodies, that we are the temple of the Holy Ghost
which is in us, which we have of God.
We understand that God provides us with guidance
and direction through his word and through his spirit.
And the direction is clear.
The guidance that God provides to Elijah is clear
and it is direct.
It is not difficult for Elijah to be able to understand
what it is that God is giving him the guidance
and it's not complicated.
Notice that with the guidance came a promise.
That's what the Bible says in verse number four
of 1 Kings 17.
The Bible says, and it shall be
that thou shalt drink of the brook.
And then notice this promise.
And I have commanded the ravens to feed thee there.
Do you think about the Lord God Almighty
providing guidance to his servant Elijah,
revealing to us his great care for his servant,
but we find also that he gave commandment to the ravens.
By the way, the ravens are God's creation.
It's interesting to me as you study through the scriptures,
you'll find that outside of humans,
God's creation always obey him.
I'm pretty confident that Jonah, the disobedient prophet
was thankful that that great fish was obedient to God.
Right.
And then the disobedient prophet
became an obedient prophet after his encounter
and after all that had taken place.
But we find here, notice he says,
God tells Elijah that there at this place Cherith,
the brook that God has given him the direction,
the guidance to go to this place.
He says, you'll drink of the water there,
but he says, I've commanded the ravens to feed thee there.
Now, the Bible tells us in Proverbs 3, 5, and 6,
that we're to trust in the Lord with all our hearts,
we're to lean not on our own understanding.
If you know anything about ravens,
and I'm thinking, I'm assuming that Elijah
knew some things about ravens,
that maybe there'd be reason to wonder how are the ravens,
like, how is this going to work?
We don't see anywhere in the passage of Scripture
that Elijah doubts or questions or even hesitates
at the command and the promise that are revealed to him.
And as we look at the passage of Scripture
and we see what's taking place
and we see God's care evidenced through guidance
this morning for his servant, for Elijah,
I'm so thankful, as I've mentioned already,
that today God continues to provide guidance
for his children.
Why does he guide us?
Why is it that he'd be concerned in your life,
in my life, in providing us with guidance?
Why would the God of the universe,
when you and when I are in a position in our lives
and we enter into the presence of God
and we're praying, we're saying,
God, I need your guidance, I need your direction,
God, would you please provide me with leadership?
Why does he, why?
Because he loves us and he cares about us.
I think about my children
and many of you have children this morning
and at some point you were a child.
As a child, you might ask your parents for some guidance.
You might seek the counsel of your parents
with regard to decisions that have to be made
and what have you and I'm always thankful,
it's a blessing to me when my children
will contact me for guidance.
You know, what's interesting now
is a parent of a married child
is the encouragement that comes
when a married child will contact you for guidance
because there's still a level of understanding,
of respect and the wisdom,
not that I'm saying that I'm some wise individual
but you understand what I'm saying.
And this morning, when you begin to think about
a child coming and seeking the guidance of a parent,
we understand that but we,
why do we give guidance to our children?
Why is it, listen, there are times in which
my children will say something like this
and it always bothers me when they say this.
They'll say, daddy, I know that you're busy
but and I say, no, no, no, no, I am not,
I don't ever want you to think I'm too busy for you.
I want them to come and to ask and why?
Because I care about them, I love them.
I wanna provide them with guidance
and our heavenly father who knows everything,
who knows the end from the beginning,
who is alpha and omega,
though you do not know what's on the morrow, he does
and he provides us with guidance.
He provides us with direction because he loves us.
I want you to think about a few verses of scripture
in the book of Psalms.
If you turn to Psalm chapter five,
look at just a few verses here in the book of Psalms
this morning, Psalm chapter number five.
Speaking of the truth of the guidance,
the leadership of God Almighty,
notice the prayer of the psalmist in Psalm five,
a psalm that is ascribed to David in verse number eight.
Notice what he says,
lead me, O Lord, in thy righteousness
because of mine enemies.
Notice what he says, make thy way straight before my face.
Make thy way straight before my face.
I'm mindful of what the psalmist will say in Psalm 27
in verse number 11 where the Bible says,
teach me thy way, O Lord,
and lead me in a plain path because of mine enemies.
How often in my life I pray
that God would make the path plain
and that God would make the path straight,
that God would give clear guidance and direction
as I seek his face,
and I believe that God is delighted
when we as his children seek his face for guidance.
Notice what the psalmist says in Psalm 27.
In Psalm 73, in verse number 24,
a psalm that is described to Asaph,
getting to the end of the psalm,
and it's so precious and powerful to see
the great contrast as to how he starts the psalm
and how he ends the psalm.
But notice in verse number 23,
the Bible says, nevertheless, I am continually with thee.
Thou hast holden me by my right hand.
Can you get the imagery here?
Can you see as a parent would hold their hand
of their child, and God is our heavenly Father,
and we as his children, and it says this,
thou shalt guide me with thy counsel,
and afterward, receive me to glory.
I hope that this morning, each of us would follow
the leadership and guidance of God
all the days of our lives,
and then he would receive us to glory,
that when we take that final breath here upon this earth,
that we enter into his very presence
and understanding that we've been guided
with God's counsel.
Where do we find God's counsel?
His word, his word.
Notice what the Bible says in Psalm 119,
a verse of scripture that is quite familiar to us
in Psalm 119, as we begin to consider the guidance
and how God's care is evidenced for his people
through his guidance, and I'm so thankful
that God provided guidance to Elijah,
but this morning, I must rest and understand
that he continues to provide guidance for me
and for you this morning in our lives.
Psalm 109 and verse 105, the Bible says,
thy word is a lamp unto my feet
and a light unto my path.
I'm thankful for the guidance that God gives
through his word, his counsel, his wisdom
that is contained therein.
I've said this often as I've counseled with individuals.
I've said this often as I've preached from God's word
that God will never lead you contrary to his word.
God will not lead you contrary to his word.
God will never lead you to do something
that contradicts a principle that he has placed
within this book.
God's guidance and God's leadership in your life
will always be consistent with what God says in his word.
Well, you don't understand, Pastor,
God's just guiding me to do this.
No, he's not, and I can say that
because of the authority of God's word.
Now, I understand that there are places
in which you can look to and you say,
well, God's guiding me to move to this place
or go to this place.
You're not gonna find a specific verse of scripture
that's gonna say, you know, so and so,
you should live in this place or do this thing,
but you understand that as we look to God's word
that God provides us with the guidance that we need.
We follow his leadership.
God's care for Elijah.
God's care for us this morning
is evidenced through his guidance.
Turn back to 1 Kings 17, if you will.
I would say not only is God's care evidenced
through guidance, but God's care is evidenced
through sustenance, through sustenance.
The obedience of Elijah is noted in verse number five
of our text of scripture, where the Bible simply says this,
so he, speaking of Elijah, went and did according
unto the word of the Lord.
Isn't that a wonderful truth, as God would record for us
the obedience of Elijah?
Listen, obedience is absolutely imperative.
As God would provide us with guidance and direction
in our lives, that we would submit to his leadership,
that we would obey the direction that he's given
to us in our lives.
Listen, if Elijah decided, well, Lord,
I know you tell me to go to the brook Cherith
and I know you tell me to go over there,
but I think I know better, I think I understand
the terrain and the situation better,
so I'm gonna go over to this place,
because in my mind, it's going to be better for me there.
No ravens are gonna show up there.
Why?
Because God said specifically at the end
of verse number four, and I have commanded the ravens
to feed thee there, there.
Every word is important.
He didn't just say, and I have commanded the ravens
to feed thee.
I have commanded the ravens to feed thee there.
Where's there?
The brook Cherith.
A specific location.
And the Bible tells us that Elijah is immediately obedient
to the word of the Lord, so he went and did a courting
unto the word of the Lord, and thank God
for the obedience of Elijah, for we find that
through his obedience that he sustained this,
through this period of time and the sustenances there,
we find that he receives a personal delivery
of both bread and flesh in the morning,
and again in the evening by the ravens.
This is absolutely amazing.
You say, I'm familiar with the portion of scripture.
I hope that you take a fresh approach
to God's word this morning.
I believe that if we took a servant
when we came in this morning and said what happened
at the brook Cherith, most of us, if not all of us,
would have said that Elijah went there and he drank
of the brook and the ravens brought him food.
We're aware of it, but I want you to see how God
is caring for his servant and how he's using the ravens
to bring each morning, notice what the Bible says
at the end of verse number five, for he went and dwelt
by the brook Cherith, that is before Jordan,
and the ravens brought him bread and flesh in the morning
and bread and flesh in the evening,
and he drank of the brook.
Can you imagine?
In my mind's eye, I see Elijah.
I mean, he goes to the place, Tim, where God told him
to go and he gets there, and on that first morning,
guess what?
Here come the ravens.
Look at this.
The ravens are, just like God said, the ravens are coming,
and sure enough, they bring, no, ravens are scavengers.
Ravens like to steal your lunch, not bring you lunch.
You understand what I'm saying?
Do you, I mean, am I telling the truth?
Ravens don't wanna bring you lunch, but God commanded them.
God commanded them, and God's creation obeys him,
and those ravens came there to the brook Cherith,
and they brought Elijah a meal, bread and flesh,
and the Bible says that he drank of the brook
in verse number six.
I don't know how long Elijah was at the brook Cherith.
I'm not sure of the length of time that he was there,
but for however long he was there,
each morning and each evening,
there was a personal delivery for Elijah
of bread and of flesh.
Isn't that amazing to you?
Does that not reveal to you God's care?
God knows what we have need of.
God created us, and the creator God knows
what we have need of, and we find that as God
would make this command, he'd make this promise
to Elijah, and he would command the ravens to feed him,
that Elijah sat in that place, and Elijah,
he experienced the blessing of God, the provision of God.
God's care was evidenced for Elijah
through this sustenance, this food that was provided.
I would say to you this morning that God is able
to sustain his children no matter the circumstances.
God is able, and though the circumstances there
in Cherith were, and in Israel, broadly speaking,
the circumstances were going to continue to deteriorate.
Why?
Because there's no rain.
There's no dew.
The judgment, the divine judgment of God is upon the nation
because of their wickedness, because of their idolatry,
because of their sin, and God is withholding
the rain from them, and we find that here is Elijah
over by this brook Cherith, and he's eating,
and he's drinking.
Because God cares about him,
and God's care is evidenced in his life.
You say, but pastor, the brook dries up.
I know.
And I would submit to you this morning
that God knew about that as well,
and God had a plan.
Listen, it did not surprise God when the brook dried up.
God knew that the brook would dry up.
Why?
Because there was no rain.
God knew, and God had a plan.
We'll look at the next message as God's care continues
to be evidenced in the life of Elijah and how God works,
but as we begin to think about God's guidance
and God's sustenance in the life of Elijah
and how it reveals to us and reminds us of the fact
that God cares about his servants,
I want you this morning to recognize
that God cares about you as an individual.
He cares about you.
I've heard people say, no one cares about me.
You ever heard anyone say that?
I've heard people say, no one loves me.
You ever heard somebody say that?
Should cause you to have a heart that's sorrowful
when you hear that.
somebody say that. Listen, I can tell them that God cares about them and God loves them.
As we look at God's word, we find this morning that God cares about us. Look over at 1 Peter.
I know it's a familiar verse, but I want you to turn there and I want you to see it in
your Bible this morning. And I want you to be reminded of this great truth that God gives
us in 1 Peter chapter number five. And then we're going to go to the book of Luke and
look at a couple of portions of scripture that I hope encourage you this morning, that
yes, we can look back to an Old Testament portion of scripture and we can rejoice in
knowing that God cares for his servants, that God cares for his people. But listen, it's
not just that God cares about Elijah. This morning, God cares about you personally. You
say, pastor, I'm going through a situation. I have this going on and I have all of this
turmoil and all of this uncertainty. God knows and God cares about you. And as you seek the
face of God and as you surrender to his lordship in your life, then he will provide you with
the guidance that you need. And as you follow him day by day and you trust him to lead you,
he will prove himself capable and worthy. Notice the Bible tells us in 1 Peter five,
again, a very familiar verse of scripture. The Bible says this, casting all your care
upon him. Why? For he careth for you. It's a simple verse of scripture. You've seen it
maybe on some artwork. You've seen it maybe on a mug or some other piece of everyday type
of item that we would use as a reminder to people. But I want you to see that God's word.
The Bible says all scripture is given by inspiration of God and is profitable for us.
And here, a very simple verse of scripture says this to the people of God, casting all your care
upon him. For he careth for you. What do we know about the people that Peter is writing to here in
the book of 1 Peter? Well, we know that there are people that are scattered abroad. We know
that there are people that are dealing with great adversity, of people that are dealing with great
persecution, of people that are trying to serve God under the time in which Nero is ruling and
what a cruel leader he was. And we find that they're dealing with all types of difficulties
and hardships and all these things that are going on. The Bible speaks of their sufferings within
the text of scripture. But Peter says, under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
casting all your care upon him. For he careth for you. What a precious truth of God's word.
Turn to the book of Luke, if you will, in chapter number 12. Luke chapter number 12. We look at a
few verses of scripture here in Luke 12 as we close this morning. The Lord Jesus Christ is
speaking. I believe in these two portions of chapter 12 that we'll look at this morning,
we're reminded of God's great care for us. As you're turning there to Luke 12, I thought it
was of interest and I wanted to reference the verse of scripture, though you do not need to
turn there. But in Psalm 147 and verse number 9, the Bible says that he, speaking of the Lord,
giveth to the beast his food and to the young ravens which cry. It's of interest to me that in
Psalm 147 and verse number 9, that God reminds us that he provides for the beast and for the
young ravens. But it was God who used the ravens to provide for his servant. Here in Luke chapter
12, notice what the Bible says in verse number 6. The Bible says in verse number 6,
are not five sparrows sold for two far things? And not one of them is forgotten before God.
It says this in verse number 12, but even the very hairs of your head are all numbered. Fear not,
therefore. Notice what he says, you're of more value than many sparrows. You're of more value.
I'm thankful that God has placed value on humanity. I'm thankful for the value that
God has placed upon humanity this morning as we think about the truth that we are valuable to God.
I've said this often, but it's worth repeating that we have value, humans have value for two
very obvious biblical reasons. One, because we're made in the image of God. If you remove the
teaching, the truth of creation, then man all of a sudden does not have value. If you follow
Darwinian evolution, man does not have value. But if you follow biblical creation, you understand
that God said let us make man in our own image, and he made them male and female, that you find
that man has value because we're made, created in the image of God. And the value of mankind
was demonstrated at a place called Calvary. When God in the person of Jesus Christ went to a cruel
cross, he bled and he died. He was buried and he rose again, but he paid a price because mankind
is valuable. We're not redeemed with corruptible things. No, we're redeemed with the precious blood
of Christ. And here we find that the Lord Jesus Christ, he speaks about the sorrow of the sparrows
that are sold and how that not one of them is forgotten before God. And then he says this,
can you imagine? We're familiar with this thought, this truth that is given in verse number seven,
where the Bible says even the very hairs of your head are all numbered. But I want you to think
about the original audience to this particular truth. I want you to think about Jesus teaching
and those that are gathered, and Jesus saying for the very first time that they heard this,
that the very hairs of your head are numbered. Now we know it, we've read it, we're familiar with it,
we've heard somebody say it before, and so we understand it. But I want you to think about
those original audience folks that were there when they first heard Jesus say this. Isn't that amazing?
That God knows the number of the hairs on your head? Have you ever tried to count the number
of the hairs on your head? Why would you try? I often joke that God has to subtract for me.
I'm not growing any new hair, I'm losing it. Holly's giving me a haircut the other day,
she said, honey, you're getting more gray. I was like, well, at least it's gray,
because it just keeps falling out. But the reality is that God knows the number of hairs
on your head. Now think about that. It's amazing. And he says this at the end, he says,
fear not, therefore ye are of more value than many sparrows. Skip down, if you would,
to verse number 22, here in Luke chapter number 12. Notice the Bible says in verse 22,
and he said unto his disciples, therefore I say unto you, take no thought for your life,
what ye shall eat, neither for the body what ye shall put on. The life is more than meat,
and the body is more than raiment. And then he says this in verse 24, consider the ravens.
Now, as I look here at the passage of scripture, I see where Jesus says to them, consider the
ravens, and you begin to think about the use of ravens in the Bible, and we know that Noah,
he sent out a raven, and it comes, it doesn't come back, and what have you, the dove comes back,
but the raven didn't. And you find here that now you think about Elijah and the ravens in 1 Kings
17 that we studied, and here Jesus is speaking to the disciples and he says, consider the ravens.
And he says this, for they neither sow nor reap, which neither have storehouse nor barn, and notice
these words, and God feedeth them. God feeds them. But then it says this, how much more are ye better
than the fowls? Listen, God created the fowls of the air. We can read the creation account in
Genesis chapter number 1, and we can understand that God created the fowls of the air, and we
understand that God cares for them, he feeds them, but he then says, as he gives this teaching to the
disciples, and he tells them that they can look at this earthly thought, this truth of the ravens,
and as they would consider the ravens, and here he says that God feedeth them, and then he says to
his disciples, how much more are ye better than the fowls? Now I want to remind you of a question
that the disciples asked to the Lord during a time in which they suffered in a great storm. I
mentioned earlier when I spoke about the guidance of the Lord, how that God provided the disciples
with guidance to get into a boat and go to the other side, and they encountered a storm. The
first time that happened, or that wasn't the first time that that situation happened, they were in
more than one storm there on the Sea of Galilee, but in one particular
instance when they're in a storm on the Sea of Galilee, it wasn't that Jesus sent
them without and then he comes walking on the water, it's that he's with them in
the boat. And as he's with them in the boat, they face this great storm and
Jesus is what? He's sleeping. Can you see the panic of the disciples as you read
the text of Scripture and they come to Jesus frantically and they awake him out
of sleep and they say this, Master, carest thou not that we perish? Oh no, Jesus did
care, he does care. And we find that he rebuked the wind and the storm, the waves
and there's a great calm. Here we find that God says to these same disciples, how much
more are ye better than the fowls? I'd say to you this morning that God, he cares about
you. His care is evidenced through his guidance. Say, man, I need some direction in my life.
I know the one that you need to seek. Say, the Lord knows everything, everything. He
is the all-wise God and he wants to provide you with guidance, direction in your life.
And then his care is evidenced through his sustenance. Here, God tells us that he feeds
the ravens. But in 1 Kings 17, God used the ravens to feed his servant. Isn't that amazing?
It's absolutely amazing to me to understand God's great care for us. The songwriter said
this, does Jesus care? Does Jesus care? If you were to read through the song, you would
see in that song great sorrow that was encountered by the songwriter. But as you read and you
get into the chorus of that song, yes, he cares. I know he cares. This morning, you're
dealing with some difficulties in your life, when you're dealing with some troubles, remember
God cares about you. He cares about you and he provides guidance and sustenance and it
reveals to us his greatness. He's able to care for each and every one of us, all of
the believers all over the universe, all at the same time, and provide you with guidance
in your life with where you are, while providing guidance in someone else's life over here
for where they are, guidance for this. It's amazing how great our God is and how personal
our God is. This morning, rest in knowing that God cares for you. We see it evidenced
in Elijah's life. I hope that you've experienced in your own life to know God cares. God cares
about me personally. Let's pray. Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. We thank
you for the opportunity to be gathered together to sing praise to your name, to open your
precious book. God, we thank you that you care about us, you care for us. God, I pray
that you'd help us to seek your face for guidance and leadership direction. I pray that we would
acknowledge this morning that we need your guidance. If we do not first acknowledge our
need for guidance, we'll never seek you for it. Help us to not lean on our own understanding.
Help us, Lord, to trust you and obey you. Help us to respond to the guidance that you
provide in the manner in which Elijah responded in immediate obedience. Lord, help us to know
that you care for us and you will provide sustenance. You will sustain us. No matter
the circumstances, no matter the situation, you'll provide for us. You know what we need.
You've made us. You've formed us. And your provision reminds us of your care. Help us
to cast all our care upon you, knowing that you care for us. I pray, Lord, that this morning
you'd help us to be, to rest in being reminded of your great care for us. I pray that you'd
move and work in hearts and lives. Maybe there's some that need guidance. They need
direction in their lives. Maybe there's some that, maybe they've said those words that
we mentioned a moment ago, no one cares about me. Maybe they feel like because of the storms
that are raging in their life, no one cares about them. God, would you help them to find
refuge in your great care. Help them to be encouraged this morning, to trust you and
to obey you. I pray that you'd move and work in hearts and lives as only you can. There's
one that's not sure of heaven. I pray that today be the day of their salvation. Well,
thank you for all that you'll do. For it's in Christ's name we pray.