I am thankful for the Word of God, I'm thankful for the truth that God has given us in His
Word.
Often, as we look at the Word of God, we find that God gives us, of course, truth that is
profitable for us.
The Word of God tells us that all Scripture is given by inspiration of God and is profitable.
We find that it's applicable in our lives.
I'm so thankful that God's Word is not just a book of theory, but it's a book of application.
We take the truth of God's Word and we put it into practice.
We say, as Baptist people, that the Bible, the Word of God, is our sole authority for
faith and practice.
And what a joy to have the Word of God.
The title for the message this morning is found in verse number 18 of our text of Scripture.
The Bible says, My little children, let us not love in word, neither in tongue, but in
deed and in truth.
I've titled the message this morning, Love in Deed and in Truth.
It's interesting, a recurring subject in the book of 1 John is that of brotherly love.
We find that John first visited this particular subject matter in 1 John chapter number 2,
verses 7 through 11.
We find, as the Holy Spirit of God would have directed him to speak on the subject of brotherly
love, we found in that text of Scripture in 1 John chapter number 2, that the reality
the test that was given, the evidence that was provided of our love for the brethren,
it was a, it revealed to us, it was evidence that we were abiding in Christ, that we were
walking in fellowship with Christ.
Remember, we mentioned that in 1 John chapter 1 and verse number 7, the theme for our year,
if we walk in the light as he is in the light, we will have fellowship one with another.
The blood of Jesus Christ, his Son, cleanseth us from all sin.
We find that John continues in 1 John chapter number 2, and he says in verse number 10,
he that loveth his brother abideth in the light.
And the evidence, the evidence of abiding in the light, walking in the light, is that
we love the brethren.
As we come to the third chapter of the book of 1 John, we see again that the subject of
brotherly love will be discussed.
We dealt with it just very briefly in a segue portion of verse number 10.
Last week we spoke about the sanctification, the growth of the child of God.
It says in this, the children of God are manifest and the children of the devil, whosoever doeth
not righteousness is not of God.
But then notice this as he gets into the subject matter of brotherly love, neither he that
loveth not his brother.
And now we see in verses 11 through 18 that he's going to deal with this subject of brotherly
love.
And here we discover that really, as we saw in chapter number 2, that it was an evidence
of fellowship with God, walking in the light, that here in chapter number 3 we discover
that loving the brethren, this brotherly love, is an evidence of conversion.
It's an evidence of conversion.
And what a joy to understand how God is giving us this truth with regard to brotherly love.
We find that this is not the last time that we will stop at this subject of brotherly
love as we study through the book of 1 John, for again in the fourth chapter, and really
into the very beginning of the fifth chapter, once again the Holy Spirit of God would prompt
John to write about this subject of brotherly love.
Now, the book of 1 John is only five chapters.
It's not that long of a book.
But yet we see the subject of brotherly love coming up time and time again.
I believe that the Holy Spirit of God is trying to get our attention with the subject that
is before us.
See, Satan is a master at deceiving.
He's a master of dividing.
We find that as we study the church in Corinth, there was so much division and envy amongst
them.
There were fightings and all sorts of things going on.
The strife that is mentioned, the spiritual immaturity of the church in Corinth.
And we find that Satan is trying to divide the church.
And we find that even now, as we look at this subject matter this morning, and we think
about the importance of brotherly love, we think about what God tells us about loving
the brethren, we find the significance of this subject and how we must avoid giving
place to the enemy when it comes to division.
And the enemy wants to divide, and he wants to destroy, and he wants to get church members
fighting against church members and all sorts of things.
But we must understand that we have fervent charity, one toward another.
That's what Peter says in the book of 1 Peter, under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of
God, that we have fervent charity, one toward another.
As we look at the subject matter this morning, in verses 11 through 13, if you're taking
notes, I want you to notice first, what is to be expected.
It's kind of interesting, as we go through the text of Scripture, he deals with the subject
of brotherly love, but there's an obvious contrast that is provided to us.
You'll recall in our message last Sunday morning, in verses 4 through 10, there was the contrast
that was provided there as well, as we looked at those that were doing righteousness versus
those that were not, and understanding that through their behavior, God is interested
in our behavior, that as we have been saved, as we have been born again, as we have been
declared righteous, that we are to live righteous lives.
And the contrast here in verses 11 through 18, as we find the contrast between love and
hate that is given to us, but notice what is to be expected.
In verse number 11, notice what the Apostle John says, under the inspiration of the Holy
Spirit of God, for this is the message that ye had heard from the beginning, that we should
love one another.
I would say this, love for the brethren is to be expected.
When we understand what the Lord Jesus Christ did for us, when we understand that we, at
that moment when we trusted Jesus Christ as our personal Savior, we were born again, and
we were born into the family of God.
We often refer to one another as fellow church members, as brother or sister, and we understand
that we are brethren, and it is to be expected that we would love one another.
And how do we do that?
We don't do that in our own power.
We do that through the power of the Holy Spirit of God, because of the love of God, because
of the fact that we have been loved, and He has shed His love in our lives.
We then, through the Holy Spirit of God, are able to love one another.
I'm not sure about you, but if you think back to your days prior to being saved, when you
were not converted, you probably did not have any desire to go to a church house, and you
probably had no love for the people of God.
But after we're saved, it's amazing how the Holy Spirit of God works in our hearts and
our lives, and how He gives us a love for the brethren.
We come from a variety of backgrounds.
We have different experiences and different upbringings, but one thing we have in common
is that bond that cannot be separated, and that is that Jesus Christ is our Savior.
And what a joy that is.
I've been to churches all over the place, and what a joy it is to be able to go to a
new location, to go to a new area, and to find a body of believers.
Brothers and sisters in Christ, people that I never have met before, but we can have love
one for another.
I remember when I was in Mexico, and dealing with some of those folks there in the church
where we were seeking to minister, and though I was in, I just had no ability to really
communicate with those people that we were seeking to worship with, they were translating
the service for us, because our Spanish was un poquito, and we just could not communicate.
But yet, there were some brethren that just wanted to just get close and have some fellowship,
in as much of a way as possible, with as few English words as they knew, and as few Spanish
words as I knew.
Try to have it, why?
Because we have this bond in Christ, we're brothers, we're sisters in Christ, and what
a joy.
And I believe that as we think about the truth of the Word of God, the teaching of the New
Testament, we understand that it is to be expected that as the people of God, we're
to love one another, we're to have love one toward another.
Jesus said this in John 13, if you turn back there, hold your spot here in 1 John, of course
John is the man that God would use to pen the Gospel of John, and the first, second,
third book of John, and the book of Revelation.
And we find that the apostle John is there throughout the Gospel of John, you will find
that he will refer to himself never as John, but as the one whom Christ loved, the one
whom Jesus loved.
And you think about the understanding that John had of the love that God had for him
personally, but John was there and he heard the teaching of the Lord Jesus Christ, and
he heard these words at the end of John 13, in verse number 34, Jesus said, a new commandment
I give unto you, that you love one another.
And then he says this, as I have loved you, that you also love one another.
By this shall all men know that you are my disciples, if you have love one to another.
It's interesting because John 13 begins by telling us about the Lord Jesus Christ and
His love.
Notice in verse number 1 of John 13, now before the feast of the Passover, when Jesus knew
that His hour was come, that He should depart out of this world unto the Father, having
loved His own which were in the world, notice this phrase, He loved them unto the end.
It's impactful.
And then John heard Jesus say that you love one another as I have loved you, that you
also love one another.
I believe that it's expected that we should have love one for another as we have trusted
Christ as our Savior as we're born again and adopted in the family of God.
It is to be expected that we have love for the brethren.
Notice not only back in 1 John chapter number 3 do we see to be expected as a love of the
brethren, I would say this as well, to be expected is hatred from the world.
Listen, we should marvel not, that's what it says in verse number 13, marvel not my
brethren if the world hates you.
We'll get to that in just a moment, but notice the example that is used in verse number 12.
He says this, that we're to love one another, he says, not as Cain who was of that wicked
one and slew his brother, and wherefore slew he him?
Because his own works were evil and his brother's righteous.
Isn't it interesting to you that in 1 John chapter number 3 we have a reference all the
way back to Genesis chapter number 4?
And really by the Holy Spirit of God prompting John to use this example of Cain and Abel
from the book of Genesis in the fourth chapter, we find that this gives confirmation of the
record that we have in Genesis.
And I'm so thankful, listen, you understand this morning that Genesis 1 through 11 is
under increased attack in our society today.
The world, the enemy is trying to undermine the authority of the Word of God, they're
attacking creation, they're attacking the flood, they're attacking those first 11 chapters
of the book of Genesis.
Why does that portion of Scripture find itself under such attack?
Well if you can destroy the foundation, you have nothing else to set on.
We find that they seek to destroy the foundation so that they can then question all sorts of
other portions of Scripture.
In fact, basically the end of their logic goes something like this, if God is not the
Creator, and the Word of God says that He is, but if God is not the Creator, then why
is it that we would even need a Savior?
And that's where that line of thinking leads to.
And it is a terrible deception from the evil one, but we find here in 1 John that there's
reference to Cain and Abel.
We're familiar with the passage of Scripture, and we find that the Bible says that, not
as Cain, who was of that wicked one, and slew his brother.
It's the first murder that is mentioned in all of the Word of God.
We find that it was a rock that was used to kill his brother.
We find that he sought to cover the blood.
We find that God came and said, where art thou, brother?
And he said, am I my brother's keeper?
But we notice from that very event in Genesis chapter number 4 that you can continue to
read throughout the Word of God, throughout the pages of history, in the newspaper reports
today of murder.
Of murder.
It's a tragic thing.
But can I tell you, you're never going to, as you think about this subject of murder,
and you see the reference here of this hatred, and you see what's happening with Cain and
Abel and the means by which it was used, you have to understand that the Bible says
who was of that wicked one and slew his brother.
Why?
Because his own works were evil and his brother's righteous.
Listen, you're not going to legislate righteousness.
You're just not going to do it.
You can outlaw anything you think that is a weapon that's going to bring some kind of
tragic end to another person's life, and somebody's going to find something to use to perform
that evil deed.
Why?
Because it's a matter of the heart.
It's a matter of the heart.
And that's why we say that Jesus is the answer.
That's why we say, listen, we are living in a generation.
We look around and we say, what is going on in our society?
What's going on in our world?
All of the evil that's taking place.
Day after day, you're reading of evil wickedness.
We have outlawed God in our communities.
We've told our young people that God does not exist.
We've told them that they came from nothing and really they're going to nothing.
We have undermined the word of God.
We have decreased the value of life.
And then we sit around and say, wonder why this is happening?
Really?
We need a return to God.
We need a revival.
We need an awareness of God.
There was a day in our history in the nation of the United States of America that you could
walk into the public places of our society, into the arenas of our public institutions,
of public schools, and see the Ten Commandments.
The Ten Commandments never saved anyone.
But I'm going to tell you what, when you read those Ten Commandments and you understood
something about God, it caused you to think a little bit about what your actions were
going to be, right?
And you think about the moral compass of our society.
We've gone off the deep end.
But look at what God says in 1 John chapter number 3 with regard to this evil, wicked
behavior of Cain.
It's because he was of that wicked one.
He was of that wicked one.
See, his works were evil, according to the end of verse number 12, and his brothers were
righteous.
It's interesting to me, do you understand that Cain was not an atheist?
He wasn't an atheist.
He tried to bring an offering to God, right?
You go back to Genesis 4.
He didn't deny God.
He came with the works of his own hands.
And God said, that's not acceptable, right?
He says to Cain, after Cain was wroth, he was angry, he says, God says to Cain, hey,
why are you angry?
Why are you wroth?
If thou doest well, shalt thou not be accepted?
You've got to come the right way.
What was the offering of Abel?
It was an offering of blood.
That was the right way.
That was the prescribed way.
Obviously, though we do not have all of the details in the Genesis record, God obviously
communicated effectively and completely to Adam what the right way was.
We see it in Genesis chapter number 3, after the fall, after sin entered into the world,
what did Adam and Eve do?
They tried to cover themselves with their own aprons, fig leaves.
God said, no, no, no, that's not going to be acceptable.
An animal had to be sacrificed so that skins could be provided, the leather would be provided
of a covering, and obviously the significance in the blood.
But notice, as he uses the example in verse number 12, and we see about the evil and the
hatred, notice what he says then in verse number 13, marvel not, that word marvel means
to wonder.
He says, marvel not, my brethren, if the world hates you.
You know, it's to be expected that the world would hate us.
I'm not suggesting that it's a delight.
I'm not suggesting that it should be something that we glory in, that the world hates us.
Most of us like to be liked.
But notice what Jesus said.
John, again, obviously would have heard these words, and he was used to pen them in John
chapter number 15 and verses 18 and 19.
Notice what the Lord Jesus Christ says.
These references in John 13 and John 15, these are just very soon before Jesus would go to
the cross of Calvary as he's sharing these truths with his disciples.
He says this in John 15 and verse 18, if the world hates you, you know that it hated me
before it hated you.
Notice what it says, if you were of the world, the world would love his own, but because
you're not of the world, but I have chosen you out of the world, therefore the world
hateth you.
Marvel not.
You say, pastor, this isn't very encouraging.
I understand, but it's true.
It's true.
You know why the world isn't going to love you?
Because they don't love your God.
That's really what it boils down to.
When you begin to think about the truth, listen, the gospel of Jesus Christ is confrontational.
The gospel of Jesus Christ confronts people with their need for the Savior.
And we find that here, what's to be expected, well, first, and the real primary aspect of
the text of Scripture is that there'd be love for the brethren, but understand this
morning that we should understand it to be expected that there will be hatred from the
world.
Listen, if the world loves us, there's probably something wrong, honestly.
If the world loves us, there's probably something wrong.
I've often said this with regard to the truth of separation.
The Bible says, come out from among them and be separate, saith the Lord.
You know what I found practically, is if we live holy lives and we live lives that we're
seeking to be pleasing to God, the lost, they're going to separate from us.
They don't like to be in the light.
They don't want to be in that presence, right?
And so, this morning, as we look at this, we know what's to be expected, but notice
number two, as we continue to move through the text of Scripture, verses 14 and 15, brotherly
love is an evidence.
It is an evidence of what?
Well, we said this in chapter number two, that it was an evidence that we were abiding
in Christ, that we were walking in the light.
This again is one of those birthmarks, if you will.
We've mentioned, as we've studied through the book of 1 John, that God gives us in this
book some birthmarks, some evidences of conversion.
That we can know.
that we've been born again, that we can look at this
and we can see the work that Christ has done in us.
Again, as we referenced in 1 John chapter number two,
we spoke about the fact how that, in verse number five,
but whoso keepeth his word in him verily
is the love of God perfected, and God is doing a work in us.
We spoke last week about the work of sanctification.
There was a word on sin, there was a word about our Savior,
and then there was a word about our sanctification
and how we're to be daily seeking to be like our Savior,
and we find here in the text of Scripture
that in verses 14 and 15, John is going to provide us
with this truth of knowing, having this evidence.
Notice what he says in verse number 14, we know.
Now I love, again, as we've mentioned many times
in the book of 1 John and really the whole of Scripture,
you read about God giving us these knowledge nuggets.
We know, he wants us to know.
He doesn't want us to be tossed to and fro
with every wind of doctrine.
He doesn't want us to be wondering day by day,
am I his child, am I not his child?
Can you imagine if every day your children had to wake up
wondering if they were your kids?
Can you imagine when you were growing up,
if every day growing up you had to wonder,
am I really their child?
It'd be a tough way to live.
How do I approach them?
But see, God wants us to know.
He wants us to have that security of our relationship
to him through the blood of Jesus Christ
and that we are his children.
Notice what he says, we know, to be confident of,
to have the assurance of, we know, what do we know?
That we have passed from death unto life.
What a great statement.
The truth of conversion, that we pass from death unto life,
that we were born again.
Ephesians, Paul mentions it this way
in the book of Ephesians.
He says, you hath he quickened who were dead
in trespasses and sins.
We were dead, but we've been made alive.
We've passed from death unto life.
And he says, we know that we've passed unto death,
that we've passed, in verse number 14,
from death unto life, why?
Because we love the brethren.
That's pretty straightforward, is it not?
We know, we have this confidence, this assurance.
We know what?
We know that we've passed from death unto life,
the conversion, what is the evidence
that we love the brethren?
Notice he takes it a step further
at the end of verse number 14.
He makes it abundantly clear.
He says, he that loveth not his brother abideth in death.
Wow, I just don't like that person.
You better check things out.
Amen?
Listen, the reality this morning
is that as we look at this passage of scripture,
we're acknowledging that God is giving us
this evidence of our conversion.
He says, listen, when you're born again,
the Holy Spirit of God lives within you.
It's amazing what happens at salvation.
In fact, when you got saved, when I got saved,
we probably really didn't understand everything
that happened in that moment of salvation.
There were certain things that we had to understand.
We had to understand that we were sinners,
and we had to understand that because of our sin,
there was a penalty, and that penalty is death.
We had to understand that we could never
earn our own salvation.
There was nothing we could do.
There were no works that we could do.
There was nothing that we could do to earn our own salvation
but Jesus Christ died for us.
He paid the price.
He paid it in full.
We, at that moment, understood that we were sinners
on our way to a Christless eternity,
and he is the Savior, and he loves me,
and he said that whosoever shall call upon
the name of the Lord shall be saved,
and we called out and said, Lord, save me.
Now, I didn't understand everything that happened
in that moment on August 31st, 1997 in my life.
I didn't understand that the imputed righteousness
of Christ, I didn't understand that.
I didn't understand the fact that I was immediately
at that moment that the Holy Spirit of God indwelled me.
I couldn't talk to you about the difference
between the indwelling of the Spirit
and the filling of the Spirit.
I didn't understand a lot of that stuff,
and neither did most of you.
But after we got saved, we began to grow,
began to learn, and I learned that that day
that I got saved that the Holy Spirit of God came into me.
The Bible says that if we're saved this morning,
remember Paul says, know ye not that your body
is the temple of the Holy Ghost which is in you,
which you have of God?
You're not your own, you're bought with a price.
Say, man, the Holy Spirit of God indwells me.
He's the earnest of our salvation.
We're sealed unto the day of redemption.
I didn't understand all of that,
but now as we look back and we see
and we understand salvation, the Holy Spirit of God
that indwells me is the same Holy Spirit of God
that indwells you if you've been saved,
and it's the Holy Spirit of God that allows me
to love as Christ loved.
It's the Holy Spirit of God that gives us
a love for the brethren.
I didn't have the Holy Spirit before I got saved.
I was dead, and he says here that this is an evidence
of your conversion.
We know, we're confident, we're assured of our conversion
that we've passed from death unto life.
Why?
Because we love the brethren.
I want you to understand here that John is not suggesting
that we love the brethren in order to pass
from death unto life.
Understand that.
Just like in 1 John chapter number two,
he's not suggesting that we keep his commandments
in order to know him.
He says in 1 John chapter number two and verse number three,
hereby we do know that we know him
if we keep his commandments.
He's not saying keep his commandments
and then you're gonna know that you're saved.
No, no, he's saying because you're saved,
because you've been born again,
you're gonna have this desire to keep his commandments.
And here in 1 John chapter number three,
he's not suggesting that we go around
and just try to love people.
I'm gonna love the brethren,
and that's going to be the way that I get saved.
No, what he's saying in this text of scripture
is that those that have passed from death unto life
will love the brethren.
That's an evidence of salvation.
It's amazing to me that Jesus said this.
We looked at it in John chapter number 13
as we looked at that text just a moment ago,
but remember in verse number 35,
Jesus said, by this shall all men know
that you're my disciples, what?
For your love one for another.
Now notice the difference between what Jesus said.
It's not something different that's a contradiction,
but notice the emphasis that Jesus places.
Jesus says, hey, listen, those people out there,
they're gonna know that we're his disciples
because we love each other.
That's impactful.
By this shall all men know that you're my disciples,
your love one for another.
But then John says, we know.
We know that we've passed from death unto life
if we love the brethren.
It's a self-administered test.
It's something that we look at in our lives
and we see, oh, thank God that he's given us
some evidences of salvation, some birthmarks of a believer.
And again, I can't explain it to you,
and you probably can't fully explain it to me,
but something happened after you got saved.
Listen, I never wanted to read this book
before I got saved.
I never went to church before I got saved.
Honestly, we didn't even go to church on Easter, man.
Honestly, we just didn't.
My parents are here, they can tell you.
I remember my dad coming home and saying,
we're going to church on Sunday.
We're doing what?
That was my response.
I was 12 years old.
We had other things we did on Sunday.
But then I got saved.
From the time I got saved until right now,
this moment, I can't think of one time,
I can't think of one time that I stayed home from church
just because I didn't want to go.
Honestly.
I'm not trying to pat myself on the back.
I'm just telling you that God gave me a love.
He did something.
I never wanted to go to church.
But then I got saved.
I'm going to do everything I can to get in the house of God
to hear the word of God,
to fellowship with the people of God.
I didn't love the brethren.
I didn't have any desire to,
but now I love the brethren.
Isn't it amazing?
I'll speak from my personal perspective.
Some of you have the same testimony.
I have a lot of relatives that aren't saved.
I have more in common with you
than I do with those lost relatives.
I have real fellowship with you
that I can't have with those lost relatives.
It doesn't mean that I don't love them.
It doesn't mean that I don't want to see them saved,
but it's just different.
He teaches about brotherly love.
It's an evidence.
We know that we have passed from death into life
if we love the brethren.
And what a blessing, or I shouldn't say if, because we love the brethren.
Let me quote it properly, because we love the brethren.
He says, he that loveth not his brother abideth in death.
Let me finish quickly this morning, number three.
We see brotherly love as an evidence, but notice how brotherly love is explained.
We're first reminded of the greatest example of love in verse number 16.
Most of us can quote John 3.16, for God so loved the world that he gave his only begotten
son that whosoever believeth in him should not perish, but have everlasting life.
First John 3.16 is a verse that I would encourage you to memorize.
John 3.16, first John 3.16.
Notice what the word of God says.
Hereby perceive.
You know what the word perceive means?
To know, to understand.
Hereby perceive we the love of God, because he laid down his life for us, and we ought
to lay down our lives for the brethren.
First we're reminded of the love of God.
I'm so thankful that God has declared his love to us in his word.
I'm thankful that God said that he loved the world.
I'm thankful for that declaration, but oh, how greatly we rejoice in the demonstration
of God's love, that he didn't simply declare it, but he demonstrated it.
We understand this in our lives.
We understand, listen, you can tell somebody you love them, but at some point your actions
are going to have to support your speech, right?
And we look here, and we look at the demonstration.
He says, hereby perceive.
This is how we know the love of God.
Why?
Because he laid down his life for us.
You remember the truth of Romans 5 and verse number 8?
But God commendeth his love toward us, in that while we were yet sinners, while we were
yet sinners, Christ died for us.
That's how God commendeth his love toward us.
And here we find that as we look at this verse of Scripture, and we're dealing with this
subject of brotherly love, and we're reminded of what John heard in John 13 and verse 34
and 35, as it's recorded for us, that Jesus says, listen, I give you a new commandment,
that you love one another as I have loved you, Jesus says.
And now we find that John, as he's dealing with, and he's getting ready to explain the
brotherly love, the example that the Holy Spirit goes to is the truth of the love of
God, the greatest example of love.
The Greek word would be agape love, that self-sacrificing love, a love that is God's
love.
And I'm so thankful to be a recipient of God's love.
I'm so thankful that, as Paul said, under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God
in the book of Romans, there's nothing that can separate me from the love of God.
Aren't you thankful for that this morning?
We're to keep ourselves in the love of God, according to the book of Jude, and we find
here that he says, hereby perceive we the love of God, because he laid down his life
for us.
Now he's going to begin the explanation of love, this brotherly love that he's dealing
with.
He begins at the end of verse 16 and goes through verse 17 and 18.
Notice what he says, and we ought to lay down our lives for the brethren, but whoso hath
this world's good, and seeth his brother have need, and shutteth up his bowels of compassion
from him, notice the question, how dwelleth the love of God in him?
That's a question to really ponder, to meditate upon.
He says, whoso hath this world's good, and seeth his brother have need, and shutteth
up his bowels of compassion from him, how dwelleth the love of God in him?
Notice the explanation in verse number 18, my little children.
Notice where he says love is not.
He says, let us not love in word, neither in tongue.
I would simply say that's our talk.
I don't think that it's suggesting that it's wrong to say I love you to someone, but what
he's getting at is what really is love.
Notice he says at the end of the verse, but, here's what love is, in deed and in truth.
Action, action.
And we think about the example that was used in verse number 16, the love of God.
He declared it, but then Jesus Christ went to that cruel cross.
What took our Savior to the cross?
The Romans?
The religious leaders that cried out, crucify him?
Ultimately, it was love because he said, I lay down my life in John chapter number 10.
He's the good shepherd and he lays down his life.
In fact, as we look at the text of Scripture, when you look at the crucifixion of our Savior,
we understood that it was love that took Him to the cross and it was love that kept
Him on the cross.
What an action.
What joy to know the love of God.
But then as the people of God, John says, here's how we're to love one another, not
just in talk, but in action.
Notice what James says.
Let's look at the book of James, if you will, in chapter number 2.
James chapter number 2, and I want you to look at verses 15 and 17.
He deals with the same scenario, really, that we see here in 1 John chapter 3 and verse
number 17, but notice here in James 2 and verses 15 and 17, 15 through 17, notice what
he says, if a brother or sister be naked and destitute of daily food, and one of you say
unto them, depart in peace, be ye warmed and filled, notwithstanding ye give them not
those things which are needful to the body, what doth it profit?
What a great question.
You see a brother or sister that's naked and destitute of daily food, and you say to them,
depart in peace, be warmed and filled, but you don't give them anything.
There's no action.
You have this world's good, is what he says in 1 John 3 and verse number 17, but whoso
hath this world's good, and seeth his brother have need, and shutteth up his bowels of compassion
from him, how dwelleth the love of God in him?
We're not to love, let us not love in word, neither in tongue, but in deed and in truth.
Notice what the book of Romans says, turn to the book of Romans, if you will, and we'll
close with this thought in Romans chapter number 12.
In Romans chapter number 12, see, the world kind of has this philosophy, and I'll use
the expression, I remember hearing it often as I worked in the corporate world, and I
don't know where the expression originated from, but, you know, it's kind of that idea
of, if you do this for me, I'll do something for you.
You know, you scratch my back, I'll scratch your back, kind of an idea.
And really, I've done favors for you, you do favors for me, and that's kind of how things
sometimes work, the motivation for certain things.
But notice here, in Romans chapter number 12, we deal with the love that we're to have,
this brotherly love that is described for us in the Word of God.
The Bible says this in Romans 12, in verse number 9, let love be without dissimulation.
Abhor that which is evil, cleave to that which is good.
Now, that word dissimulation is not a word that we use in our vocabulary every single
day, but really, just plainly, it means to have love that's without hypocrisy.
Let me say it this way, sincere.
Let love be without dissimulation.
It's a love that is to be sincere.
It's a love that's unfeigned.
It's a love that's without hypocrisy.
It's a love that expects nothing in return.
That's how we're to love.
I believe this morning that as we look at this passage of Scripture in 1 John chapter
number 3, verses 11 through 18, obviously, we know the wisdom of God.
We see all throughout the New Testament how often this subject of brotherly love comes
up.
It's recurring.
You can't deny it.
In the little epistle, this little letter, 1 John, five chapters, on at least three separate
occasions, he deals with the subject of brotherly love.
You read Jesus teaching about it.
You read John here.
We read of Paul teaching about it.
You read of Peter discussing it.
You read of Paul speaking to the church in Thessalonica about how they need to love one
another more and more that we increase in our love one for another.
We're taught of God.
We see the example of it.
Why is it recurring so often?
We need to be reminded of it, of our love one for another.
Why?
Because this is not something that's natural.
This is something that is supernatural.
This is something that is reserved to the individual that has been born again, that's
been saved by the blood of Jesus Christ.
This morning, as we look at this text of Scripture, and we're reminded of this statement that
we're to love in deed and in truth.
Not only do I know through the evidence that's mentioned in this
text of Scripture that I've passed from death unto life because I love the brethren, but
we also understand here in the text of Scripture when we couple it with John 13 that those
without will know that we're His disciples because of our love one for another.
Let me say this as I wrap it up.
It's easy for us to say we love the brethren, but I want you to notice how the Holy Spirit
of God takes it very specific in our text of Scripture in 1 John chapter 3 because sometimes
we can say we love the brethren and it be that plurality, right?
We love the brethren.
We love the people of God.
But notice how He brings it down to the individual in verse number 17, and seeth his brother
have need, and seeth his brother have need.
It's the individual.
We think about the love of God.
Listen, I'm so thankful that God loved me.
Aren't you thankful that God loved you?
When the Holy Spirit of God indwelled me and when He indwelled you, He gives us a love
for the brethren.
It's an evidence of salvation.
Oh, that we would increase more and more in this area of love.
I believe that God's given us a church where there's a genuine love one for another.
I believe it's evidence.
I've had people that have visited our church that have said this to me more than one time.
They've said this to me.
One thing that's really unique about your church is it seems like the people actually
care about each other.
Isn't that how it's supposed to be?
Because we love one another.
But let me say this, even as Paul said to the church in Thessalonica, we are to increase
more and more.
Love for the brethren.
Our love is to be in deed and in truth.
More than just talking, it's an action.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
How we thank You for loving us.
We thank You for the truth of Your precious Word.
We thank You for the subject matter that is before us this morning.
God, we thank You for the birthmarks, the evidences that You give us in Your Word with
regard to conversion.
God, as we think about this recurring subject, I pray that You'd help us to walk in the light.
Lord, help us to live lives that are pleasing in Thy sight.
God, help us to impact this world.
Help us not to marvel that the world hates us.
You've already told us that's to be expected.
Help us to love in deed and in truth.
Not just through our speech, but through our actions.
God, if there's one that's present that's not been saved, they don't know the Lord Jesus
Christ is their personal Savior.
They've never been born again.
If they were to die today, they have no idea what would happen.
Father, I pray that You would allow the Holy Spirit of God to convict that individual or
those individuals of their sin of Christ's righteousness of judgment to come, that they
would understand, they would perceive the love of God, that they'd understand that You
love them so much that You died for them.
You were buried and You rose again to pay for the sin of mankind.
Lord, if there's one that's lost, I pray that today they'd be saved, that we'd have an opportunity
to take a Bible and show them how they could know for sure that heaven's their home.
For every child of God, would You help us to be encouraged this morning through this
passage of Scripture?
Help us to evaluate our love for the brethren.
We pray that You'd move and work in this time of invitation as only You can.
I pray that each decision that is made would be sealed.
Lord, that we'd leave this place doers of the Word.
We'll thank You for the work that You'll do, for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would You stand with me?
At the end of our services, we have a moment of invitation for those visiting with us,
just so you understand what's taking place.
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
No one's forced to move or make any kind of decisions, but we do want to give you an opportunity
to respond.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano, and as she does, the altar is open.
Perhaps you want to come to this old-fashioned altar and just ask the Lord to help you in
this area.
Maybe you want to ask the Lord to, or thank the Lord for His love for you.
Maybe you want to thank the Lord for the love for the brethren.
Maybe you're not saved.
We'd love to take a Bible and show you how you can know for sure that heaven's your home.
But as Kimberly plays, the altar is open.