through 1st and 2nd Timothy on Sunday mornings.
Our theme is continue, but for Mother's Day,
we're gonna take a break from 1st and 2nd Timothy,
head over here to 2 Kings chapter number four this morning.
Mother's Day, of course, is a special day
that is celebrated on this, the 2nd May annually
here in the United States of America.
Anna Jarvis is credited as celebrating
the 1st Mother's Day, and that was back on May 10th, 1908.
And prior to then, there were some times
in which various pockets of populations
in the United States would celebrate
or acknowledge mothers on a special day.
But really, she is credited with celebrating
the 1st Mother's Day there on May 10th, 1908.
It was about five years later, on May 10th, 1913,
that the U.S. House of Representatives passed a resolution,
and that resolution, they called for all federal employees,
government officials, to wear a white carnation.
And they made that decree, or that resolution,
if you will, on May the 10th, 1913,
and they said that they were to wear the white carnation
on May 11th, 1913 in honor of Mother's Day.
It was the following year, on May 8th, 1914.
I give you all this information
just to let you know the importance of it,
but Congress passed a law designating
the second Sunday of May would be Mother's Day.
In that law, they also made a request for a proclamation,
and the very next day, then President Woodrow Wilson
issued a proclamation declaring
the first national Mother's Day.
And so that goes all the way back to 1914.
Of course, this is 2024, so 110 years ago
when it was made law.
The decree, if you will, the proclamation
by President Woodrow Wilson after the law passed Congress.
Today, there are over 50 nations in the world
that have a day in which they have on their calendars
an observance, a special day for observing Mother's Day.
It's not always on this same day
that we celebrate here in the United States of America.
There are a number of countries
that do have their calendar mirrored to our calendar
based on that proclamation,
but there are many other nations
that have some other time during the year.
But I'm thankful this morning, early this morning,
I sent my mom a text.
Of course, not able to see her today.
They're down in South Carolina.
I sent her a card in the mail,
and then I sent her a text this morning,
let her know that I love her and appreciate her
and all that she's done for me over the years.
And I am thankful for Holly,
and also let her know the appreciation that I have.
I hope that you, if your mother is still alive,
have had the opportunity to thank her today.
And if not, if you would do that,
many, no doubt, their mothers have passed on into eternity,
and that makes for a difficult day.
But the remembrance of all of those wonderful memories,
we certainly can rejoice in that
and thank God for the time that we're able to have.
As we come to 2 Kings chapter number four,
we're looking at the ministry of Elisha.
The ministry of Elisha is an exciting ministry,
one in which many of us are familiar with.
And as you begin the fourth chapter
of the book of 2 Kings,
we find that God gives us in the first seven verses,
it's not our text of scripture,
but God provides for us the record of the miracle
of the pot of oil.
Remember the widow woman,
she had a debt and her husband had died
and she had two sons.
And she went to the man of God, to Elisha.
She said, he asked this question,
what have you, what hast thou in the house?
And she said, not anything in the house save a pot of oil.
And God did a great miracle
and they gathered up all the vessels
and they filled from that pot of oil,
every vessel they could possibly find.
Elisha gave the instruction to sell,
pay off the debt, live on the rest.
What a wonderful miracle.
As we come to verse number eight,
the text of scripture in which we're looking at this morning
we are introduced to a family,
a husband and wife in the city of Shunem.
We do not know the name of this woman.
She simply introduced to us as a great woman.
In fact, often as we look at this text of scripture
in verses eight down through verse number 37,
she is often simply referred to as the Shunemite woman.
This morning, we'll take an opportunity to review her life
as it's revealed in this passage of scripture.
And I wanna note a number of characteristics
about this lady that would give us reason
as to why the Bible tells us that it was in this place
where was a great woman.
Notice with me in verse number eight,
the Bible says, and it fell on a day
that Elisha passed to Shunem where was a great woman
and she constrained him to eat bread.
And so it was that as off as he passed by,
he turned in thither to eat bread.
And she said unto her husband,
behold now, I perceive that this is an holy man of God
which passeth by us continually.
And I praise God for her perception and her spirituality.
The Bible says that she then makes this request
to her husband, she says, let us make a little chamber.
I pray thee on the wall and let us set for him there a bed
and a table and a stool and a candlestick.
And it shall be when he cometh to us
that he shall turn in thither.
At this point, they have no children.
We'll go through the text of scripture
and see the miraculous birth of their son.
But I want you to skip down, if you will,
to verse number 19.
I'll give you the title for the message
and we'll jump into the thoughts this morning.
In verse 18, it says, and when the child was grown,
it fell on a day that he went out to his father,
to the reapers, and he said unto his father,
my head, my head.
And he said to Elad, notice this, carry him to his mother.
And I've titled the message this morning,
carry him to his mother.
There's been many times in our lives
when our children would get injured.
I remember as a child, if I would get injured,
it was always mom that provided more care
and compassion than dad.
If I was injured as a child and I went to my dad,
he'd try to move the limb or move whatever
and say, it's not broken, son.
It moves just fine, just carry on, right?
And mom was the one that you would go to
to have compassion and some care and concern.
And in our home, it's the same way.
Oftentimes, I'll say, I'm not sure what to do about that.
Go see mom.
And here, this man says, carry him to his mother.
As we think about this passage of scripture,
we're gonna make our way through the entirety of it.
I wanna give you six thoughts this morning,
and I'm gonna be brief with each one.
Don't get overwhelmed with having six thoughts this morning.
But six thoughts this morning of characteristics
of this lady, this Shunammite woman,
as we refer to her as in this text of scripture,
that are great characteristics that lead to God telling us
that she is a great woman.
Number one, if you're taking notes,
I want you to note that she was caring.
She was a caring individual.
And I'm thankful for the care that we see
in this text of scripture.
The Bible says that Elisha would pass by
this particular place, and in verse number eight,
the Bible says that, so it was that as oft as he passed by,
he turned in thither to eat bread.
Why?
Because this Shunammite woman,
that's introduced to us in verse number eight,
that she constrained him to eat bread.
She was an individual that demonstrated care.
She was a caring individual.
In fact, Elisha says this in verse number 13.
Notice the Bible says, and he said unto him,
to Gehazi, his servant, he says to say unto her,
this Shunammite woman, behold, thou hast been careful for us
with all this care.
Begin to think about caring and being a caring individual,
and we find here in the passage of scripture
that no doubt the evidence is given to us
that she cared about Elisha.
Though the text of scripture does not tell us,
I believe that she cared for her husband.
As you look at verses eight through 11,
eight through 10, excuse me,
you find the interaction between this woman and her husband,
and I think that she had care for her husband,
and it then leads to having care for Elisha, the man of God,
and eventually would have care for her own son.
She has no son at the beginning of the text of scripture.
We're introduced to her as being this great woman,
this couple with no children,
but we find that Elisha makes the statement
in verse number 16 that thou shalt embrace a son.
We find that she did indeed have a child,
and that child was grown,
as we read already in verses 18 and 19.
We find that in verse number 20,
the Bible says that after the servant
had received the instruction to carry him to his mother,
after he's in the field there with his father,
and he says, my head, my head,
that it says that when he had taken him
and brought him to his mother,
he sat on her knees till noon and then died.
It's a sad verse of scripture as it ends,
but I see her care for her son
as he would come in from the field,
and he's got this perhaps something,
maybe heat stroke, some other injury maybe that took place,
and he's cried out for his head while he's in the field,
and he goes to the mom.
The servant brings him to his mother,
and she, the Bible says, that he, that son,
was there with his mother and sat on her knees till noon.
Maybe some of you here this morning,
you can remember as a child receiving the care on the knees.
of your mother.
And the reality is that God many times, and I know this morning that this is not, the
statements that I'll make this morning are not necessarily statements that are applicable
in every case, and I understand that.
But many times God has equipped mothers to have that caring heart and to demonstrate
that care, and we see it here in this Shunammite woman.
Not only do we see that she was caring, but number two, I note that she was generous.
She was generous.
You know, in our text of scripture, we see some evidence of this, but on the bulletin
this morning, the Bible says who can find a virtuous woman for her price is far above
rubies from Proverbs 31 and verse number 10.
The only woman called virtuous throughout all of the scripture is actually Ruth.
You find it in the book of Ruth.
But you'll find here that as we look through Proverbs 31 with regard to generosity that
is described in that text of scripture, that you'll see in 2 Kings chapter number 4 a lady
that was generous.
The Bible tells us, we've noted already in verse number 8 with regard to the provision
for the man of God, that she constrained him to eat bread.
The Bible says, so it was that as oft as he passed by, he turned in thither to eat bread.
Now we find that the Bible tells us that he passed that way regularly, and so this was
not just a one-time occurrence.
This was a regular occurrence, and she constrained him.
She was generous with her resources, constrained him to eat bread, and as oft as he passed
by, he turned in thither to eat bread.
Her generosity does not stop there.
We find that as we've read in verses 9 and 10, that she has this perception.
She's a spiritual lady.
She has this perception, and she says to her husband, this is a holy man of God.
And she has this understanding of who the prophet of God is, Elisha, and notice what
she makes this request in verse number 10, let us make a little chamber.
We find that really the idea of a prophet's chamber, we refer to that still to this very
day of using that phraseology.
When we built the parsonage, we put in the basement a prophet's chamber area so that
those that are traveling, missionaries and evangelists, would have the opportunity to
have a place where they could stay and have some refreshment time and what have you.
And so we find that she makes this request with regard to putting this prophet's chamber,
this little chamber.
She says, let us set for him there a bed, and a table, and a stool, and a candlestick.
And it shall be, notice the end of the verse, when he cometh to us, that he shall turn in
thither.
She was generous.
It wasn't an opportunity that she was going to allow to pass by.
She wanted to seize the opportunity that was before her, and though there's, as we look
at this text of scripture, this desire to be a blessing to the man of God, we find that
because of this, it resulted in the fact that Elisha would stay there.
That Elisha, as often as he would pass through that region, as he would travel throughout
the land of Israel, that he would come through and he would have a place where he could rest.
He would have a place of provision.
It was because of the generosity of this woman in Shunem.
We find that the Bible would tell us with regard to opportunities and the reality that
we're to do good as we have opportunity to do so.
In Galatians chapter number six, hold your place there, and I want you to see what the
Bible tells us.
In Galatians chapter number six, God gives us instruction, and we ought to be looking
for opportunities.
We ought to be looking for opportunities to do good, to be generous, to be giving.
We find that the Bible tells us in Galatians six and verse number nine, and let us not
be weary in well-doing, for in due season we shall reap if we faint not.
Then notice verse number 10, as we have therefore opportunity, let us do good unto all men,
especially unto them who are of the household of faith.
Though Galatians six was not written at the time of the ministry of Elisha, this lady
in Shunem did not have a copy of the book of Galatians, the opportunity presented itself
to her, and she seized the opportunity.
She had the opportunity to do something for the man of God, and she goes to her husband
and she says, let us do this, let's be generous, let's be hospitable.
And what a blessing, again, as we think about the man of God, Elisha, traveling, and I want
you to understand that not only would it be a blessing to Elisha because of her generosity,
but understand the way in which it would return to her and her family, because why?
Well, the man of God is there, and to have the privilege of having the man of God as
he would travel through to be at their place, at their residence, would be a tremendous
blessing and opportunity.
We've had the privilege, and I know that some of you have as well, over your time of serving
the Lord, to have meals with servants of the Lord, to have opportunities, perhaps, to have
servants of the Lord stay in your home.
Of course, with the Prophets Chamber, we have opportunity regularly to have missionaries
and evangelists stay in our home, and the opportunities of fellowship and the opportunities
of being able to be a blessing, I mean, they just abound, and it's such a privilege and
such a blessing.
I remember, I think back to the opportunity when we first connected with Brother Dan Hummel,
and of course, you know, our church is familiar with Beacon of Truth, and we do a lot with
them, and we had the opportunity at this point, about 15 years ago, to first meet Brother
Hummel, and it was at our church when we were in Pennsylvania, we were members of the church,
working a full-time job, had three little kids, and two, four, and six, I mean, we understand
what it was to be busy and to have schedules and all over the place and what have you,
but our church had a scripture assembly ministry, and it was in the evenings, and I remember
Dan Hummel standing up, we'd never heard about it before, and he stood up and he tore
one of the scriptures apart and showed how it gets assembled and showed the whole process,
and he said this, he said, anybody that's here can do something with this scripture
assembly.
It was the first time our church had ever done it.
He said, from the youngest to the oldest, somebody can do some job during the scripture
assembly, and so we had three little kids, as I mentioned already, and Joseph was just
about two years old, just a little tot of a kid, and we thought, well, I guess he said
everyone can do it, and so Holly and I talked, and we said, we're gonna go, and we went.
We were there each night of that assembly, and our kids did serve, they got involved,
but God allowed us, and Holly and I had the opportunity to chat, and we were able to take
Brother Hummel out and his wife and the team that was with them, it was a different group,
it wasn't Dan and Donna Stroop, it was a different couple, and we were able to take them out
for dinner after one of the assemblies, and we were just able to go out to pizza, it was
late, of course, work and school the next morning and all those things, it was gonna
be a late night, but at that place, through having that opportunity, God allowed our hearts
to be knit together, and we had such a blessed opportunity, and now I think about all these
years later, and to see the blessing of that, listen, as God would give you opportunity,
just as God gave this lady, this Shunammite woman is referred to her as this opportunity,
she seized it, she was generous, and God blessed.
I want you to notice, as we continue to read, in verse number 11, it says, and it fell on
a day that he, Elisha, came thither, and he turned into the chamber and lay there.
So he took advantage of the prophet's chamber that was made available as he traveled through.
The Bible says in verse number 12 that he said to Gehazi, his servant, call the Shunammite.
When he had called her, she stood before him.
Number three, if you're taking notes this morning, we notice not only that she was caring
and generous, but we notice number three, she was content.
She was content.
Notice what the Bible says.
She stood before him at the end of verse number 12, and in verse 13, it says that he said
unto him, so Elisha says to Gehazi, say now unto her, behold, thou hast been careful for
us with all this care, and then notice this question, what is to be done for thee?
What is thou be spoken for to the king or to the captain of the host?
What a great opportunity that is given to her as Elisha says to Gehazi, I will speak
on your behalf.
You have been so caring for us.
What is it to be done for thee?
Would you like us to stand before the king and speak for you or to the captain, the host?
And notice her answer, I dwell among mine own people.
She was content.
She said, I dwell among my own people, and he said, what then is to be done for her?
You see the heart of...
Elisha desiring to give and to be a blessing to this lady that had been so caring for him
and provided not only the bread, but also the dwelling place in that prophet's chamber.
And Gehazi answered in verse number 14, and he said,
Verily she hath no child, and her husband is old.
We find that though she was in this particular place of barrenness, that she did not seem
to be bitter by it.
She was content.
In fact, it says that he said, call her, and when he had called her, she stood in the door.
In verse 16, he said,
About this season, according to the time of life, thou shalt embrace a son.
Can you imagine her hearing these words?
She knew, the Bible tells us already, that she said to her husband in verse number nine,
I perceive that this is an holy man of God.
His ministry is going forth and he's traveling to and fro, and no doubt as we understand
and we're familiar with the life and ministry of Elisha, there's miracles that are taking
place and we find that on that day that he's there and he says to her, she's called back
into the presence, about this season, according to the time of life, thou shalt embrace a
son.
She had no child.
Not only had no child, but her husband was old, according to verse number 14.
And she says in verse number 16, at the end of the verse,
Nay, my Lord, thou man of God, do not lie unto thine handmaid.
It was almost beyond her ability to believe what had just been declared because she'd
known the circumstances that she had dealt with, but I believe that she was content not
only by her answer when it was asked, what is to be done for thee, that she says, I dwell
among mine own people, but even in the situation there with having no children, it seems as
if this Sunamite woman was a content individual.
She did not serve so that she could get something.
She did not perceive that Elisha was a man of God and that Elisha was a prophet of God
and that we're going to be generous and we're going to have him here so that we can get
something.
See, that's not the motive for giving and for serving.
We're content in what God has given to us and the opportunities that he has given to
us and the blessings that he will allow in our lives.
See if our motive for serving, God knows our motives, by the way, if our motive for serving
is so that I might get something out of it, then we have a wrong motive.
We have a selfish motive and we find that God does not bless that.
We live in a society today, in fact, many times, though it's not publicly known because
of legal ramifications and what have you, but many people say, well, I'll do this for
you if you do this for me.
And that's the way often things work in a society.
But here, this Sunamite woman, she was content.
She did not serve so that she could get something.
She was content.
You know, contentment is a great thing.
Many people in our society today are living lives of discontentment.
We think of the society in which we live in and we think that if I could just have more,
if I could just have this, if I could just, then I would be content.
The reality is that there were surveys done at this point, they're years ago when these
surveys were done, but they surveyed a group of people across every spectrum of income
level.
From the lowest income level to the highest, they just went through, they started, I think,
at $25,000 a year and they went up to like $250,000 a year and just looked at that category
of people and that income area.
And they went through and they gave, and they said, how much more would you need to be content?
You know, it was consistent that each earner in each of those categories said, you know,
if I could just have $10,000 more, I'd be, I'd be okay.
And that's what the one in the lowest income said and the one in the $250,000 income, they
all said the same thing.
There were options for them to select and it's, it's interesting.
We live in a society that, that really is designed to make you discontent.
We live in a midst of a generation of marketing and all sorts of things that, that really
the enemy wants you to be discontent.
But I want you to look at Philippians chapter number four.
As I think about the, the Shunammite woman and I think about her contentment as we see
in this passage of Scripture, I want to encourage you this morning to be content.
We find that in Philippians chapter number four, Paul is writing, and many of us would
be familiar with the fact that he's writing this church in Philippi and he's writing from
prison.
It was in the church, it was there in Philippi, in the city of Philippi where he was imprisoned
really when that church got a great start and he was ministering there.
Now many years later, he's writing back to this church under the inspiration of the Holy
Spirit of God from prison.
And he says in verse number 10, but I rejoiced in the Lord greatly that now at the last your
care of me hath flourished again, wherein ye were also careful, but you lacked opportunity.
And we understand even as we've looked at some of these thoughts already of being caring
and generous and content, we see some of this here even in this verse of Scripture.
In verse number 11, notice what Paul says, not that I speak in respect of want, then
notice the statement, for I have learned in whatsoever state I am therewith to be content.
I know both how to, how to be abased and I know how to abound everywhere and in all things
I am instructed both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to suffer need.
I can do all things through Christ which strengtheneth me.
I've often said to individuals and I've said publicly from this pulpit that I cannot say
as Paul said in verse number 11 that I have learned in whatsoever state I am therewith
to be content.
I'm trying to learn, I am learning in whatsoever state I am therewith to be content.
Maybe you're here this morning and you have the ability to say as Paul said, I have learned,
I am content no matter what the circumstances are.
But the reality is that as we grow in Christ, as we draw closer to the Lord, that we're
learning that subject of contentment, that disposition, that understanding that my God
shall supply all our need.
And he says that later on in this text of Scripture in verse number 19, and what a blessing
to consider that God is the one that can supply everything and he teaches us to be content,
to be content.
So many people today, they're not content with where they are in life.
They're chasing this and they're chasing that and they think if they could have that, that
it would just allow them to be content.
I'm going to tell you this morning that you need to learn to be content where you are.
Learning contentment.
God is in control.
God has a plan.
God has a purpose and God gives us exactly what it is that we need.
She was caring, she was generous, she was content back in 2 Kings chapter number 4,
number 4.
She was blessed.
The Bible tells us in verse number 16 that she hears Elisha make that declaration about
this season according to the time of life, thou shalt embrace a son.
In verse number 17, the Bible says, and the woman conceived and bear a son the season
that Elisha had said unto her according to the time of life.
What a tremendous blessing and she had been barren, but now she would be blessed with
a son and what a tremendous truth that we find in God's word with regard to the sanctity
of life and the preciousness of life.
We live in a society today in which they do not value human life and it's unfortunate.
We have just the progressive mindset with regard to abortion and a lack of understanding
of the sanctity of life.
In fact, there are many today that are being surveyed that are young aged people in their
20s and 30s and they will make statements such as this, I don't want to be inconvenienced
with children.
For anyone that's barren, that's a tragic statement to hear somebody say.
Children are not a burden, children are a blessing.
Children are work, amen?
Children are a blessing, not a burden.
We have this society that's grown up, this very, you know, the selfie generation, it's
all about them and it's all about their, what they want in life and they don't want
to be inconvenienced.
They don't want their life to be restricted in any way, shape or form because of children.
The birth rate in America has declined greatly.
If you look at it globally, you see that there's some other nations around the world that their
birth rate is way higher than what the birth rate of American citizens is and we see that
change that's going on in our society.
But this lady, she was blessed, she conceived and she bear a son and the Bible says in verse
18, when the child was grown, and I think about those formative years, we don't know
how old he is because we know that he's old enough that he goes out into the field and
he's there as his father is working in the field with the reapers and again, we don't
know the age of the son, we can make speculation.
And the Bible says that it has grown and I think about those formative years and I think
about that opportunity and about this Shunammite woman and the blessing of having a child.
Notice if you will, Psalm 113, we'll look at two Psalms, verses in the book of Psalms.
Look at first with me at Psalm 113.
God is the giver of life.
God is the sustainer of life.
I'm thankful that God is the author of eternal life.
Life is precious, but more important than being alive and breathing here this morning,
the most important thing is the spiritual life that is offered through the Lord Jesus
Christ.
The Bible tells us that there's a time to be born and a time to die.
The Bible tells us as an appointed unto man wants to die, but after this, the judgment.
And we understand the life and some people have the idea that life here on earth, this
physical life, is really all there is to it.
I mean, just live the best you can and get the most toys and I mean, just live it up
because this is all there is.
I'm sorry, but God tells us that there is eternity.
And the most precious thing is that God is the author of eternal salvation.
We find that He offers that eternal life.
You're here living this morning.
You have breath and life and none of us know how long we will have to live, but I hope
this morning you're sure of heaven.
You've trusted the Lord Jesus Christ, your personal savior and received the gift of life,
which is eternal life, or the gift of God, which is eternal life.
Notice here, as we think about the blessing of this Shunammite woman in Psalm 113 and
verse number nine, the Bible says, He, speaking of God, He maketh the barren woman to keep
her house, and to be a joyful mother of children, praise ye the Lord.
What a blessing.
In Psalm 127, in verse number three, a verse of Scripture that's familiar to many of us,
the Bible says, Lo, children are an heritage of the Lord, and the fruit of the womb is
His reward.
The Bible continues in verses four and five and says, As arrows are in the hand of a mighty
man, so are children of the youth.
Happy is the man that hath his quiver full of them.
They shall not be ashamed, but they shall speak with the enemies in the gate.
As we think about the children being an heritage of the Lord and speaking within the context
this morning of Christian families and Christian homes and understanding the blessing that
God would give to any of us to have children.
And understanding that God lends them to us, loans them to us for a season.
We have an opportunity to invest in them and to influence them and to instruct them and
to bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord.
The Bible says, As arrows are in the hand of a mighty man, so are children of the youth.
And you think about an arrow, and I'm not in archery whatsoever, I don't do well with
that sort of thing, but I do know a little bit about it, and that is that the arrow flies
in the direction in which you point it.
Is that accurate this morning?
The arrow is going to fly in the direction in which you point it or aim it.
Doesn't mean you're going to hit the target necessarily, especially speaking of me, but
the reality is that it's going to go in that direction as you aim it.
You know, we need to bring our children up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord.
We need to guide them and direct them.
Children have decisions ahead of them that are difficult decisions that are lifelong
decisions with regard to the decisions they make with regard to career, with regard to
family and all of those things, and how God has given parents an opportunity to invest
in them and to instruct them and to show them the way that they ought to go.
I mentioned this on Wednesday evening, but recently I have been confronted by a couple
of churches that have no pastors, and I've had some conversation over the last few days
with some other folks about trying to find, look, there's some churches that are ready
to just basically close down because there's no pastors, and there's some churches that
have been without pastors for extended periods of time that are just kind of hanging on by
a thread, if you will, and what do we do?
And I got correspondence yesterday from one individual that said, preacher, you know,
the problem is that there's a lot more churches looking for pastors than are our pastors
looking for churches.
It's a sad situation, what's going on in America.
It might be that God will allow us to have children and that God would call our children
to the ministry, not only pastoring, but missionaries.
We have, if you look at our board of missionaries, I'm thankful for the young families that we
have, but we have a lot of older families of missionaries as well.
They need to, we need to be raising up the next generation of servants.
We need to be praying to the Lord of the harvest that He would send forth laborers, children,
our inheritance of the Lord.
We need to rejoice in the blessing that we see here in this passage of Scripture.
She was blessed.
I want you to see that it turns, from a human perspective, in our text of Scripture in 2
Kings chapter 4, really to a tragic situation.
The Bible tells us, as we've read already, that He's there in the field with His Father,
that He went out to His Father, to the reapers, in verse 18, verse 19, it says that He said
unto His Father, My head, My head.
He said to the lad, carry him to his mother.
When He had taken him and brought him to his mother, He sat on her knees till noon and
then died.
Those are sad words.
I would say that as she was blessed, number five, she was broken.
There are periods of time in our lives of brokenness, periods of times in which we have
hearts that are heavy, that are overwhelmed, and verse 27, we'll get there in a moment,
but it says that her soul is vexed within her.
I don't know all that you're going through, I don't know the brokenness that anyone specifically
is dealing with, but understand that many people in our society today, many people in
our churches today, they're broken, they're broken.
I'm thankful that we serve a great God.
We serve a God who tells us that we can cast our burden upon the Lord, that we can bring
our care to the Lord, knowing that He cares for us.
I think about that song that we sang this morning, it's just like His great love, and
when we sang that song this morning, we had the opportunity to think about the words of
one of those, the third, I believe it was the third verse of that particular song and
understanding of His great love.
And it says, when life seems more than useless and I were better dead, I take my grief to
Jesus then, nor do I go in vain, for heavenly hope He gives, that cheers like sunshine after
rain.
There's some people that are broken, and here I believe that this circumstance in the
life of this Shunammite woman brought her to a place of brokenness, but I want you to
see what she does in her brokenness, because I believe that as we look and examine what
she does in her brokenness, what is revealed to us is her faith.
Her faith is evidenced through this period of brokenness.
Someone said this, a faith that cannot be tested cannot be trusted.
A faith that cannot be tested is a faith that cannot be trusted.
Listen, we serve the God of the universe.
You may be facing some situation, this Shunammite woman, she was facing a situation where her
son died.
In verse 21, the Bible says that she went up and laid him on the bed of the man of God,
and shut the door upon him and went out.
I want you to consider verse 21.
I'm assuming that this lad probably had his own bed.
I'm assuming that the boy, the son, had his own bed, but she does not take and lay her
son on his own bed.
I believe that she's rejoicing at this very moment in the fact that she said to her husband,
let's make this prophet's chamber.
And in that prophet's chamber, she calls it a little chamber, but she says, let us put
there, set there for him a bed and a table and a stool and a candlestick.
And we find that now when her son dies there upon her knees in verse number 20, that in
verse 21, she takes this body of her son and she lays him on the bed of the man of God.
The Bible tells us that she shut the door upon him and went out and she called unto
her husband and notice what she says in verse 22, send me, I pray thee, one of the young
men and one of the asses that I may run to the man of God, but then notice this and
come again.
I believe that she had every expectation.
Where was she going to run to in the moment of her crisis?
In the moment of her brokenness, what was she going to do?
She says, I need to get to the man of God.
I want you to understand in Israel's history at this particular time and the ministry of
the prophets, this was the place for her to run.
I'm thankful today with New Testament understanding and what Jesus Christ did on the cross of
Calvary and how he rent the veil and twain and he provided direct access for every child
of God.
If you're saved by the blood of Christ this morning, you have direct access to God almighty
and you can run to God.
In the moment of your brokenness, in the moment of your despair, in your heaviness, and the Bible says that she ran
She desired to run to the man of God and said I'll come again in verse 23
And he said notice what the husband says wherefore will thou go to him today?
It is neither new moon nor Sabbath, and she said it shall be well
It did not matter what the timing was there was an urgent circumstance
There was a need that she had in her life and though it was not a new moon though
It was not a Sabbath. She needed to get to the man of God
It's about a 25 mile journey
25 miles for us today well in northern, Virginia could take a while
but 25 miles
on a donkey
And notice what she says
She sat on an ass then she sat on an ass and said to the servant drive and go forward then notice this
Slack not thy writing for me except I bid thee. That's why she asked for one of the young men
Amen
because some of the old men couldn't go as fast as she wanted to go and so she called for one of those young men and
She said do not slack
Thy writing for me in other words there was urgency we need to get to the man of God
Verse
25 so she went and came into the man of God to Mount Carmel
It came to pass when the man of God saw her afar off that he said to cause a a servant behold
yonder is that Shunammite
You know he recognized her
Because she provided a place for him to dwell and he was there so often
And when she's coming even from a distance. He says to his servant Gehazi. He says the Shunammite
Shunammite
He then tells Gehazi run now
I pray thee to meet her and say unto her is it well with thee is it well with thy husband as well with the child
Notice the three questions is it well with thee is it well with thy husband is it well with the child?
Why was she running to the man of God?
Because in verse number 20 her son died
And Elisha says
To Gehazi
Run to her and ask her three specific questions number one is it well with thee number two is it?
Well with your husband number three is it well?
with the child and I want you to see her response it is
Well
It is well
Is that what you would expect
We sing the song
What a wonderful song it is
Almost always when we have favorites someone is going to pick it as well with my soul
and we know the story that
Really led to the writing of that song and the tragic fire of Chicago and the
descending ahead of a family in a
disaster on the seas where the the daughters are killed they drown and
Correspondences received back in Chicago
Saved alone
Just the wife made it across
And Horatio Spafford sat down as he took that journey across the sea and he asked
The captain of the ship as they got to around the area where the tragedy took place
If he could let him know where it was
And he sat down and he wrote the words of that song it is well
with my soul
It's amazing, you know what that is it's the grace of God
It is the grace of God
That would allow for us to say it's faith that we have in the God of the universe the one
Who spoke it all into existence the one who controls everything?
And we have the privilege of knowing him and serving him and because we know that he's a great God
And he do with all things well and because we've experienced the grace of God
We can say it is well it is well
When she came to the man of God to the hill she caught him according to verse number 27 by the feet and
Look at what Gahazi does but Gahazi came near to thrust her away and the man of God Elisha. He said let her alone
For her soul is vexed within her and then notice this and the Lord hath hid it from me and hath not told me
Elisha did not know
Many times the prophet of God would know ahead of time and God would reveal it supernaturally
But here Elisha does not know and then in verse 28. She said did I desire a son of my Lord?
Did I not say do not deceive me?
She did not even say in verse 28 that the son had died but notice in verse number 29
Then he Elisha said to Gahazi
Gird up my loins and take my staff in thine hand and go thy way if thou meet any man salute him not and if they
any salute thee answer him not again and
lay my staff upon the face of the child and the mother of the child said as the Lord liveth and as thy soul liveth
Notice this I will not leave thee and he arose and followed her
She was gonna stay with the man of God
How long do you need to stay in the presence of God?
When you're broken, you know what the wonderful thing is you can stay as long as you need to
You can stay in the presence of God
And he can help you
He can heal that broken heart. He can give you the grace
Remember he said to Paul my grace is sufficient for thee. Have you found it to be so in your life?
See we find it to be so when we go through that difficulty
Many times in life. There's there's very little growth without any
Adversity or difficulty many times in life. It's through that period of hardship that that God is developing us
Mary and Martha believed with all of their heart that Jesus could heal Lazarus
They sent to Jesus to say he whom thou lovest is sick
Why did they send for Jesus? Well because Jesus healed it the power over disease and they knew that
but Jesus tarried his
Departure and
both of those sisters
when Jesus arrives
They say this if thou hath been here
My brother would not have died. He still be alive. In fact the Jews that were there mourning as
Their custom would be when they heard Jesus wept. They said could not he
Who who made the man see that was blind they refer back to a miracle of a couple of chapters earlier
Could not he have healed him the answer is yes
But you know what? They didn't believe they didn't believe that he could bring him back from the dead
So Lazarus had to die
The morning the brokenness took place so that Lazarus
Would be in that tomb for four days and Jesus would say Lazarus come forth
He said to his disciples, I'm glad for your sakes that I was not there to the extent that you might believe
Brokenness
oftentimes leads to great growth
be in the presence of God
the Bible tells the verse 31 that Gehazi passed on before them and laid the staff upon the face of the child and there was
Neither voice nor hearing wherefore he went again to meet him and told him saying the child is not awake
He put the staff there
But there's no power in that the Bible says in verse 32 when Elisha was coming to the house behold the child was dead and laid
upon his bed
he went in therefore and
Shut the door upon them twain
Notice this he prayed unto the Lord
Is your first response to difficulty prayer
You know why Elisha prayed he saw Elijah pray, you know some of the power of prayer
He prayed unto the Lord
And he went up and lay upon the child and put his mouth upon his mouth and his eyes upon his eyes his hand upon
His hands and he stretched himself upon the child and the flesh of the child waxed warm
Then he returned and walked in the house to and fro and went up and stretched himself upon him in the
Child sneezed seven times and then notice this the child opened his eyes number six this morning finally
This Shunammite woman had the privilege to see God work
She had the privilege to see God work
What a unique privilege
She saw God work and giving her a son in the first place
But now we see that she she has the opportunity
personally to experience
the miracle working power of God Almighty
The Bible says that the child opened his eyes and he saw the Son of God
The Bible says that the child opened his eyes. So what happens Elisha calls Gehazi in verse 36 and said call the Shunammite
So he called her
And when she was coming unto him notice these words
He said take up
thy son
Then she went in and fell at his feet and bowed herself to the ground and took up her son and went out
We don't have time this morning but chapter number eight
We don't know the exact timing with all of these events in second Kings, but chapter number eight
Talks about the Shunammite
Woman and her son there was a seven-year famine. So at least seven years passes and the Shunammite
This giant woman and her son are referenced in chapter number 8.
God gave her opportunity to see her son grow and live.
I don't know how long, there's no more reference with regard to either one of them after chapter number 8,
but I find this morning, this great woman in Shunem, she was caring, she was generous, she was content.
I find that she was blessed, she was broken, and then she was privileged to see God work.
I think about that last point this morning, you know it's a privilege for us to see God work.
It's a privilege, unique privilege.
Do you long to see God work in your life?
Do you long to see God work in the lives of those that He's given you opportunity to,
if you're parents, to raise, if you're church members, to minister to, you want to see God work in their lives.
It's a privilege to see God work.
We've got to be in the right place if we're going to see God work.
You know what led to this Shunemite woman seeing God work in all the circumstances in which she did?
It started out by her being caring and saying, constrained him to eat some bread,
and then perceiving that this was a holy man of God and said,
we need to build a place for him to be able to stay so that when he passes through here, he'll stay here.
He could have stayed somewhere else, someone else could, but no, she had the opportunity and she seized it.
And because of that single decision, her generosity, her service, her care, she got to see God work miraculously.
I hope this morning that we would not allow opportunities to pass us by, that we would seize them,
that we'd be used of the Lord, that we would see God do great and mighty things.
It's God who said to Jeremiah, call unto me and I will answer thee and show thee great and mighty things which thou knowest not.
If you're broken today, can I give you hope in Christ?
Can I tell you that Jesus, He heals the brokenhearted.
What a wonderful, wonderful Savior we have.
If you don't know Him as your personal Lord and Savior today, today is the day of salvation.
This morning you say, I'm a Christian, I'm saved by the grace of God, but I got this burden, I'm broken over this situation.
Tell it to Jesus. Tell it to Jesus.
What a privilege we have.
What a friend we have in Jesus that we can go to Him knowing that He cares for us.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for the opportunity today to celebrate mothers.
Thank you for this Shunammite woman.
Lord, thank you for the characteristics that we could look at of her life.
Thank you for what you revealed to us.
I pray, God, that you'd meet needs this morning.
Maybe there's someone that's broken.
God, would you just help them to run to you, to get into your presence, to not leave your presence, to abide in you.
Lord, I pray that you would work miraculously in our lives, that we would seize the opportunities to serve you.
Not for something that we might be able to get, but Lord, that we would serve you because you are worthy of our service.
I pray that you'd move and work in hearts and lives as only you can.
If there's one that's not sure of heaven, it's our prayer that today would be the day of their salvation.
Well, thank you for all that you'll do, for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano.
If you're not sure of heaven, we'd love to take a Bible and show you how you can know for sure that heaven is your home.
If you're saved, then maybe you just need to come and talk to the Lord this morning.
Maybe there's something that's on your heart, you're broken, you're in need of God's care and God's grace.
Maybe God spoke to you through some other way this morning.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.