Prior to this text that we're going to be looking at,
the Apostle Paul gave instruction with regard to prayer,
and he said this in 1 Thessalonians 5, in verse number 17,
pray without ceasing.
And you know, prayer is a unique privilege.
We're so thankful for the fact
that our God hears and answers prayer,
and the fact that we have the privilege
to go boldly under the thorn of grace,
that access has been granted because of the sacrifice,
and of course the resurrection of our wonderful Savior,
and the fact that he ever liveth to make intercession
for us, but we know as the people of God,
we have this unique opportunity to pray.
And so Paul says in verse 17, pray without ceasing.
He continues to give them more instruction
over the next several verses,
and then we come down to verse number 25,
the text verse for tonight, and he says this,
brethren, pray for us.
It's a simple statement, really it's a concise verse,
just as we've looked at the instruction
contained within this latter portion
of 1 Thessalonians chapter five,
and really the bullet point type instruction
that God is giving to the church at Thessalonica
by way of preservation to every church
throughout the church age.
And so now Paul requests that the believers in Thessalonica
engage in the ministry of intercessory prayer
on his behalf, and I've titled the message this evening,
intercessory prayer, and he simply says,
brethren, pray for us.
Three thoughts this evening, and really the first couple
are pretty quick, and we'll focus most of our attention
on the third thought this evening,
but number one, if you're taking notes,
as we look at this passage in this particular verse
of scripture, I want you to see number one,
the simplicity of the request,
the simplicity of the request.
There's nothing complicated about 1 Thessalonians five
in verse number 25, nothing complicated whatsoever.
Brethren, pray for us.
It's a simple verse, it's a simple request.
We find that Paul knew that, well, excuse me,
they, the believers of Thessalonica,
they had the knowledge that Paul was praying for them.
And now Paul says, brethren, pray for us.
How is it that they knew that Paul was praying for them?
Well, Paul told them that he was praying for them.
Turn back to the first chapter, if you will,
of this epistle, and we find this to be the case
in many of the letters that God would use
the apostle Paul to write.
Of course, we know all scripture is given
by inspiration of God, but as Paul would minister
to these believers and churches and individuals
that he would write to, often, Paul will communicate
to them that he is praying for them.
Paul believed in prayer, Paul practiced prayer.
He did not simply instruct others to pray
while he himself sat on the sidelines.
I believe that Paul was a great prayer warrior
and that Paul was a man of prayer.
And we find that as he begins this letter
in 1 Thessalonians chapter one,
he says this in verse number two.
We give thanks to God always for you all.
Notice, making mention of you in our prayers,
remembering without ceasing your work of faith
and labor of love and patience of hope
in our Lord Jesus Christ in the sight of God and our Father.
We find that Paul, immediately upon penning this letter
to this church in Thessalonica, he immediately informs them
of the fact that he is praying for them.
We find that in the third chapter in verse number 10,
look at verse number nine with it.
In verse number nine of 1 Thessalonians three,
the Bible says, for what thanks can we render to God,
again, for you, for all the joy wherewith we joy
for your sakes before our God.
Now, Paul is writing this with regard to the report
that was brought back from Timothy.
It was a good report with regard to how the believers
in Thessalonica were doing.
He was concerned about their welfare.
He was concerned about their walk.
Why?
Because the enemy was attacking and they were suffering
with great tribulation and great difficulty
and oppression and opposition and so on and so forth.
And so Paul says that he's rejoicing.
But I want you to notice verse number 10.
The Bible says, night and day, praying exceedingly
that we might see your face and might perfect that
which is lacking in your faith.
Wow, Paul says to them in the first chapter
that we're giving thanks to God always for you all,
making mention of you in our prayers.
And then in chapter number three,
he mentions how that he's praying night and day exceedingly.
He says that the prayer according to verse number 10
is that they might see their face,
but also that they might perfect in them
that which was lacking in their faith.
They needed to grow spiritually.
By the way, I do not believe that these believers
in Thessalonica were offended by what Paul says
because they knew that Paul loved them
and Paul cared about them.
And Paul wanted to see them grow spiritually.
And so therefore for him to say,
there's some lacking in your faith,
he's not insulting them.
He's simply trying to encourage them
with regard to their spiritual growth.
And I don't believe for one moment
that they were offended by that.
And so we find that these believers in Thessalonica,
as we consider the simplicity of the request,
as we get to the very end of the letter,
and Paul says, pray without ceasing,
but then he says, brethren, pray for us.
Well, they already knew that Paul was praying for them.
And now they are given the simple request, pray for us.
Pray for us.
You know, prayer is a privilege
that is reserved for the redeemed.
Is a privilege that is reserved for the redeemed.
I believe the first prayer God ever heard me pray
was the prayer of salvation.
When I asked the Lord to save me.
And what a privileged prayer is.
We know that oftentimes, it's not as often today
as it was even when I was younger,
you would hear people say, pray for me,
or you're in our prayers.
And even thoughts with regard to broadcasting
and on the news and various things
with regard to tragic situations,
they would use that terminology.
And so often today, we hear people simply saying,
I'm thinking about you, or you're in my thoughts.
And there's an obvious transition, if you will,
with regard to people that they don't even understand
what prayer is.
But prayer is a privilege that is reserved for the redeemed.
That I have access to the very throne room of heaven.
What an amazing truth.
We see the simplicity of the request.
Number two, I would say this, the sincerity of the request.
Understand with me that as Paul writes these words
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
a simple request, brethren, pray for us,
I would say that it's also a sincere request.
This is not simply a cliche that would be used by believers.
Hey, I'm praying for you, hey, pray for me.
I don't think it was that situation
where it was just a cliche type of a statement.
I believe that Paul was sincere in this request.
Why was it that Paul was sincere?
Well, because Paul understood the power of prayer.
Paul understood that prayer moves the hand of God.
Paul understood that he needed brothers and sisters,
the redeemed of the Lord praying for him.
And Paul sincerely desired that God's people
would pray for him.
Just as he prayed for others,
this is a sincere plea for intercessory prayer.
Again, it's not just a cliche.
Sometimes we're good at these kind of cliches, if you will,
that we have used these terminologies
and I'll be praying for you
and maybe we don't even think anything about that
after we make that statement.
How sad that would be.
But Paul is sincere in his request.
We find here that Paul simply says, brethren, pray for us.
I wonder this evening as I think about the simplicity
and the sincerity of the request,
there's no real outline of prayer
that is provided in this portion of Scripture
as to how these believers were to pray for the Apostle Paul.
We find, and we'll look at a couple other passages here
in just a moment of where Paul provides some specifics
with regard to how to pray.
But for these believers in Thessalonica,
when they simply say, brethren, pray for us,
I know that they knew some things about Paul.
What did they know about Paul?
Well, they knew that he was a missionary.
They knew that he was traveling.
They knew that he was out preaching the gospel.
They knew that he faced much opposition.
They knew certain things about the Apostle Paul
which would help them be able to pray specifically
about those things, even though they're not outlined here
in the text of Scripture.
Brethren, pray for us.
Let me show you what Paul says to the church at Ephesus.
Turn back to Ephesians 6, if you will.
And I want you to notice the specifics.
that Paul gives to the church at Ephesus.
In Ephesians chapter number six,
Paul goes through the end of the chapter
dealing with the spiritual battle that we're engaged in,
and he talks about putting on the whole armor of God,
and he comes to verse number 18,
and he addresses the subject of prayer
to these believers at Ephesus,
and he says this in verse 18 of Ephesians six,
praying always with all prayer and supplication
in the spirit, and watching thereunto
with all perseverance and supplication,
then notice this, for all saints.
All right, this is the request of, listen,
as brothers and sisters in Christ,
we ought to be praying one for another, amen?
We ought to be upholding our brothers and sisters in prayer.
We remember it's been a number of years now
since Holly and the girls would sing that song,
but they would sing a wall of prayer.
Oh man, what a powerful song,
and how we need our brothers and sisters in Christ
to be praying for us, and he says for all saints,
but then I want you to notice in verse number 19
that Paul then says, and for me.
So Paul is going to get very specific
in verse 19 of Ephesians six
with regard to how he desired the believers in Ephesus here
to pray for him, and for me.
Notice what he says, that utterance may be given unto me,
that I may open my mouth boldly
to make known the mystery of the gospel,
for which I am an ambassador in bonds,
that therein I may speak boldly as I ought to speak.
Now, as we look at the request that Paul gives
to the believers in Ephesus,
I almost kind of scratch my head and say,
Paul is probably the most bold witness
that I can read of throughout the New Testament.
I mean, he's a man that goes from place to place,
and he enters into the city,
and he goes right into the synagogues,
and he begins to preach Christ,
reasoning with them out of the scriptures,
and I mean, he faces opposition,
and he faces difficulty, and he just keeps on preaching.
How does Paul have such boldness?
Well, we understand the Holy Spirit of God
gives us boldness, but I believe a great secret
to the boldness that Paul had in his ministry
was that he requested others to pray
that God would give them boldness.
I think about the disciples in Acts chapter number four,
when they're commanded not to teach or preach
in the name of Jesus any longer,
they'd already been in prison,
and they'd been threatened, and all of that,
and they said they prayed that God would give them boldness,
and if you look in the text of Scripture
in Acts chapter number four,
you find that they pray for boldness,
and then about a verse or two later,
they're speaking boldly the gospel.
Paul is a bold witness for the Lord Jesus Christ,
but he makes the request specifically to others,
to his brothers and sisters in Christ,
would you pray for me that I may open my mouth boldly,
that I may speak boldly as I ought to speak.
So guess what?
I think the believers in Ephesus
prayed that Paul would have boldness.
It just kind of makes sense if someone asks you,
would you pray for me specifically about this,
that you would pray about that.
So we see that Paul had boldness.
Notice in Colossians chapter number four,
he's writing to this group of people,
this church in Colossae, as we often refer to it as,
but you understand, the people in Ephesus knew Paul.
Paul ministered in Ephesus for a lengthy period of time.
When he writes back to the church at Ephesus,
just as he does to the church at Philippi,
he ministered to both of those churches extensively.
We find that Paul writing to the church in Thessalonica,
it was a limited amount of time
that Paul ministered to the church in Thessalonica.
The church at Colossae, they didn't know him,
they never met him personally.
Paul did not minister in Colossae.
Paul heard about this church in Colossae,
he heard about these believers,
he heard about their faith and about their walk.
We find that Paul did not know them personally.
It was through Epaphras, really probably the pastor
at the church at Colossae,
where Paul learned about these folks,
but Paul extensively tells them in the first chapter,
we don't have time to study it,
but in the first chapter of the book of Colossians,
he goes through how he's praying for them.
People that he never met physically,
that he never ministered to one-on-one,
but he's praying for them.
And then he says to them in Colossians chapter number four,
in verse number two, continue in prayer,
and watch in the same with thanksgiving.
Then notice, with all praying also for us,
that God would open unto us a door of utterance
to speak the mystery of Christ,
for which I am also in bonds,
that I may make it manifest as I ought to speak.
Paul doesn't give any specifics
to the church in Thessalonica in the first letter
with regard to how to pray for them.
He simply says, brethren, pray for us.
It's a simple request.
It's a sincere request.
Listen, when you ask somebody to pray for you,
you're sincere in your request.
There's a burden that you're carrying.
There's a challenge that you're facing.
There's an uncertainty in your future.
There's whatever the circumstance may be,
and you come to somebody and say, would you pray for me?
What are you revealing?
Well, you're revealing that you believe in prayer.
You're revealing that you believe
that God hears and answers prayer.
I believe that you're revealing that you believe
the person that you're speaking to practices prayer.
It'd be of no reason for me to ask somebody to pray for me
if I do not believe they're a person of prayer.
It just wouldn't make any sense.
But you ask someone to pray for you
because you believe that they believe in
and practice praying.
Just makes sense.
So we find this evening intercessory prayer,
the simplicity of the request,
the sincerity of the request.
But number three, I want you to notice
the supplication of the recipients.
When I speak of the recipients,
I'm speaking of those in Thessalonica
that received the request.
These ones that received the request,
brethren, pray for us,
and how is it that I could speak of this evening
of their supplication?
Well, what do you do when someone asks you to pray for them?
Do you pray for them?
I hope so.
That's how we would respond.
I'm supposed to say,
would you pray for me about this situation?
Now, there's a very practical aspect of this.
I know I have, and I'm sure that
if you'd be honest tonight, you have as well,
that someone's asked you to pray for them and you forgot.
You failed to do so.
Maybe you didn't jot it down.
Maybe you didn't just,
you thought you made that mental note,
and you found out that you don't remember
as well as you used to, right?
There was a, some of you might know his name.
He's with the Lord now, Dr. Lee Roberson,
a very well-known preacher.
Number of years ago, had a just Tennessee temple.
I mean, just a huge ministry college,
produced a number of preachers and pastors and missionaries,
a great man of God, and it was said of him,
I only ever met him once or twice.
He was probably close to 90 whenever I first met him,
and died shortly thereafter,
but the reality is that it was said of that man,
Dr. Lee Roberson, that anytime you'd ask him to pray for you
he would stop immediately, and he would pray for you.
Why did he do that?
Well, there's a huge ministry, a huge church,
lots of people, and a huge college, and lots of people,
and so he knew that there was no way he would remember
all of those people that had asked him
to pray about certain things,
so he made it a habit in his life.
I don't use the word habit in an inappropriate way
of it just being some religious exercise,
but he made it a practice in his life
that if someone were to say,
will you pray for me about this situation,
he would stop right then, and he would pray for them.
I think that's a good practice.
The reality this evening is that
as I look at this portion of scripture,
and I see this request,
I believe that the second letter gives us insight
with regard to the supplication of these believers
in Thessalonica, the recipients of this request.
Notice with me in 2 Thessalonians chapter number three,
if you will, in 2 Thessalonians chapter number three.
In verse number one, Paul says this,
Finally, brethren, pray for us.
That sounds awfully familiar to what we just read
in 1 Thessalonians 5.25.
Brethren, pray for us.
Here, it says, Finally, brethren, pray for us.
But notice verse number one contains some specifics
with regard to how he's now asking
these believers to pray for him.
That the word of the Lord may have free course
and be glorified even as it is with you.
Now, if you were to understand what Paul is referring to
when he speaks about the word of the Lord
having free course and being glorified
even as it is with you,
he had said to this same group of people
back in the first letter that he wrote to them
in the second chapter, in verse number 13,
he said that for this cause also thank we God
without ceasing because when ye received
the word of God which ye heard of us,
ye received it not as the word of men,
but as it is in truth, the word of God
which effectually worketh also in you that believe.
So, Paul is referring to the work
that God's word had in their lives
and he's saying that just as God's word
has been effective in your lives,
I want you to pray that as I minister,
as I take the word of God to other peoples
that God's word would have an impact
and an effect in their lives.
We mentioned, I said it even this past week
on Sunday morning, how that we are evidence
that the gospel works.
My life, your life this evening
has been transformed by the power of the gospel
and yet you have people today that say,
well the gospel just doesn't work anymore,
there's gotta be a new way,
there's gotta be some more effective.
No, the gospel is the power of God unto salvation.
We find this evening that as I look
at chapter three and verse number one
and I find that Paul is using these believers
as the example, look at how God's word
changed your lives.
You think about the way in which
they had been transformed by the power
of God's word.
What a joy.
It says in First Thessalonians one in verse nine,
you might want to just jot it down,
but it says how you turn to God
from idols to serve the living and true God.
Hallelujah.
That's because the gospel, it's because
the word of God was preached and proclaimed
and it impacted, it affected them.
So he continues in verse number two.
In Second Thessalonians three, verse one,
he talks about praying that the word of the Lord
would have free course and be glorified
even as it is with you.
Verse two, and that we may be delivered
from unreasonable and wicked men
for all men have not faith.
Wow.
What a statement.
The reality is that Paul knew what it was
to face opposition.
Paul knew what it was, seemingly at every turn,
to have someone or someones that were against him.
In fact, it was so intense that even when
he was in Thessalonica, the reason that
he was there for such a short time
is because the people that were opposing him
followed after him.
They would travel from one city to the next.
Why? Because they were opposing the work
that Paul was doing, how God was using him.
We find that he says he's praying for deliverance
from these unreasonable and wicked men
for all men have not faith.
We understand even still today that we live
in a wicked, a perverse generation.
We live, listen, Paul says this in the book
of Philippians that there are those
that are the enemies of the cross.
They're in opposition.
They stand against.
So he prays for deliverance.
Verse number three, but the Lord is faithful.
Aren't you thankful?
We looked at that last week in 1 Thessalonians 5, 24.
Faithful is he that calleth you who also will do it.
We find he says that the Lord is faithful,
and he is, praise God, who shall establish you
and keep you from evil.
But then I want you to notice verse number four.
And I spent all the time looking at those
first three verses, but I want you to see
that it's the climax, if you will,
for this particular point of noticing
the supplication of the recipients.
Notice what Paul says about these believers
in Thessalonica.
He says, and we, we have confidence
in the Lord touching you.
Notice that ye both do and will do
the things which we command you.
Now, I'm not going to take the time this evening
to look at all the things that he commanded them,
but I believe with regard to the subject
that we're studying this evening,
it's abundantly clear that one of the things
he commanded them to do was to pray.
And so notice what Paul says.
He says we have confidence.
We have confidence in the Lord touching you
that ye both do and will do
the things which we command you.
Don't you think that brought Paul great joy?
Knowing that the people that he was writing to,
the people that he was making this request to,
a simple, sincere request.
Brethren, pray for us that he had confidence
in knowing that they were going to do
and really, they already do and they will do
that which he has commanded them.
I believe that Paul knew there were some believers
in Thessalonica that were engaged
in the ministry of intercessory prayer.
I believe that when Paul was facing
some of the difficulties that he faced,
that God would encourage him
by knowing that there was an army of people
that were praying for him.
It's amazing so often we'll get
update letters from our missionaries
and they'll say something like this.
Your prayers are effective.
We can sense and see how God is working.
It's not to be spooky about it
or any kind of crazy thing about it,
but the reality is that prayer works.
Prayer works.
In the ministry of intercessory prayer
is an amazing ministry.
One of the things that's interesting is so often
we think about praying, if we're not careful,
prayer lives can consist more about me
and less about others.
I've said before and it's not something
that I practice often, but I have done it
on a couple of different occasions
where I like to pray out loud regularly.
That helps me stay on course.
It helps me not get distracted.
I'm talking to the Lord and he is present,
so it just helps me.
But on a few occasions I've recorded myself praying
so that I could listen back to see
really the content of my prayers.
You know it's far better for us to spend time
praying for others than being so consumed
about praying for ourselves.
We find that as we engage in the ministry
of intercessory prayer, one thing that is certain
is that if we're going to engage in the ministry
of intercessory prayer, we need to know,
and I don't mean in a nosy, inappropriate type
of a way, but we need to know what's going on
in the lives of our brothers and sisters in Christ.
If I'm going to pray, if I'm going to intercede
on your behalf, if I'm going to really
be that prayer warrior, I need to know
what I'm praying about.
I've often said that God blessed them prayers,
I couldn't care less to have them.
I don't know, you can't really substantiate the prayers.
God just blessed this person and blessed that person
and blessed, I mean blessed them real good
if you get a little Southern in you, you know.
What does that mean?
We end up beginning to pray specifically.
We got a note this afternoon from Brother Dewey Whitfield,
he'd been sharing with me throughout the week
about his wife's injury and the surgery that was upcoming
and not knowing exactly when they'd be able to have it
and we'd been praying throughout the week
and he sent me a text and said,
brother, they just took her back and we were having dinner
and we stopped right then and just prayed.
That's the unique privilege of prayer that at any time,
at any moment, for any reason,
and I was able to text him back and say,
brother, we prayed right now for your wife
and for this situation.
What a unique, I'm not patting myself on the back,
I'm simply saying that it's a unique privilege
that we can pray one for another
and be engaged in the ministry of intercessory prayer.
And you know, when we pray one for another,
we see this more, I believe, in Acts 13 and 14
when you study that first missionary journey,
the church at Antioch, no doubt,
was praying for the apostles.
So Paul, as they went out, Paul and Silas commissioned,
they go out, Paul and Barnabas, excuse me,
commissioned and they go out.
We find that as they would go on this missionary journey
that they travel to these cities,
but then they come back to the church at Antioch
and they call the church together.
And the Bible tells us in verse 27
that they rehearsed all that God had done with them.
You know, I believe tonight,
and I know I've preached from this passage of scripture
with regard to the first missions conference
of the local church,
and I really believe that's what that was.
And you find that there were some people
from the church at Antioch that were so excited
to be at that meeting,
to hear everything that was being told to them
that God had done during that missionary journey.
Why?
Because they were invested in prayer.
They were praying.
And through hearing what God did,
you know what they were receiving?
How God answered their prayers.
How God worked.
How God led along the way.
And the people that were saved
and the churches that were established.
And oh man, that caused people to rejoice.
It's just like when we have prayer letters
from our missionaries.
You know, when we have prayer letters
and we have opportunity to share the updates
and be able to share specific prayer requests,
and then when the missionaries send us another response,
another letter, another update,
and they have follow-ups with regard to the things
that they had asked us to pray about,
and then we get to see how God worked and what God did.
You know what?
If you're counted among those that were praying for that,
you rejoice greatly.
Because God answered your prayer.
Intercessory prayer.
Brethren, pray for us.
It's a simple request.
It's a sincere request.
But I believe that as we look at the next letter,
we see the supplication of the recipients.
They were people of prayer.
They engaged in intercessory prayer.
And through that, God worked and God blessed,
and the ministry of the Apostle Paul went forward,
and people heard the gospel,
and people were saved
because there were some believers praying.
What a blessing,
to be engaged in the ministry of intercessory prayer.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
How we thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the opportunity to study your word.
We thank you, Lord,
for the opportunity to engage in prayer.
And God, I pray that you'd help us to be people of prayer.
God, that we would pray one for another
as you've commanded us to do so.
Lord, I pray that you would bless
our remainder of our time this evening
as we receive these updates from our missionaries,
as we rejoice in what you've done,
as we take note of how we should pray.
I pray, Lord, that you'd be honored and glorified,
and we'll thank you for it.
In Christ's name we pray.
Amen.
Does anyone need a prayer bulletin this evening?
You did not get one?