God had revealed to him about the ministry.
In fact, we said there were seven things
that Paul recognized to be true
as you begin reading through 2 Corinthians,
chapter number four.
Of course, in chapter three,
he had spoken about the glorious gospel
and the contrast between the law and grace
and what a wonderful truth it is
that we have been given this ministry.
The ministry throughout these chapters
is explained to us various aspects of the ministry.
In fact, we would say this
as you come into the fifth chapter
in the next couple of weeks, we'll get there,
that it's the ministry of reconciliation
and what a joy to think that God has reconciled,
that we've been reconciled to God
through the Lord Jesus Christ
and then we have been given the opportunity
to participate in telling others
how they too can be reconciled.
We understand that as Paul recognized
these wonderful truths with regard to the ministry,
that it had a profound impact on him.
I would say this,
it should have a profound impact upon us as well,
that God would allow us to be used of him,
that God would allow us to serve him
and we find that the response that Paul gives
in verse number five, we preach not ourselves,
but Christ Jesus, the Lord
and we have an opportunity to be his ambassadors.
We'll see that in chapter five as well,
to be his witnesses as Acts five deals with,
we are his witnesses,
that he has given us that opportunity.
Paul was surrendered, I believe, as you study his life,
Paul was surrendered to the Lord.
I believe that Paul was a man, an individual
that was obedient to God's will for his life
and Paul came to that place where he said,
I am crucified with Christ.
Not only that, he says, I die daily
and Paul understood the importance of living for the Lord
and understood that one day he would stand before the Lord
and give an account for what he did
and he was consumed, I believe, as you study his life,
with desiring to do what God had called him to do.
We find that as we pick up this morning
in chapter four, verse number eight
and go through the end of the chapter,
as this fourth chapter of the book of 2 Corinthians
is concluded, we find that Paul now speaks
with a measure of transparency about the ministry.
In fact, as we look at the Bible,
it's so exciting to see how often we find
the writers of scripture and we know all scripture
is given by inspiration of God
but we understand that God used mankind,
he used men to write, to pen the words
and it's God's words but we find that
as you look at the book of Psalms,
there's such transparency among the Psalms
and you find that we can relate to that
and here in chapter number four,
I believe that Paul gets extremely transparent
with regard to the ministry.
We find that twice within the text of chapter number four,
once in verse number one and then again in verse number 16,
this phrase is used, we faint not.
We faint not.
You think about the theme of 2024 continue
and you think about the theme for this year
that God's grace is sufficient
and we find that those two things
really marry together quite well,
that we're seeking to continue to do
what God has called us to do
and that his grace, his enabling is sufficient for us
and Paul says we faint not.
We faint not.
It's interesting that in the midst of all
of the transparency that Paul will deal with
in second Corinthians chapter number four,
that that phrase is used twice.
We'll use it for our title this morning, we faint not.
It is a joy to experience the grace of God in our lives.
In fact, I know I said this on Wednesday evening,
I talked with Holly about it as well
and how the reminder, I think that for many of us,
we're reminded of certain biblical truths
through various means, maybe it's something that we see,
maybe it's a number that you see on a license plate.
I know Mark and I have talked about that in the past
and maybe God will give you a verse of scripture
and remind you of some truth
or maybe you're somewhere and you hear something
but oftentimes, I find that we'll be singing in our house
and this truth of God's grace is sufficient
has been such an important thing for me in my life
and I hope for you as well because we need God's grace.
His grace is amazing.
We sing the song.
I know every time we get near the 180s
that Brother Don says, why can't it be 187, right?
Sing Amazing Grace and it's such a wonderful song
and a wonderful truth.
God's grace is abundant
but he said that his grace is sufficient for me
and he said that his grace is sufficient for you.
I preached the very first message this year
that it's a promise that is explained
but it's a promise that must be embraced
and how important it is that we go through life
understanding the joy it is to experience the grace of God
as Paul fulfilled the will of God in his life,
I would say this, he had hardships.
He had hardships.
In fact, Job chapter 14 speaks of the man
that's born of woman is a few days and full of trouble.
He had hardships but I want you to understand this morning
that Paul had hardships but he had God's help.
I'm so thankful that Hebrews chapter 13
in verse number six reminds us
that we can have that confidence that God, he is our helper.
I'm thankful for Psalm 46
and in fact, if you study the entirety of Psalm 46,
it's amazing what the Psalmist says
but he speaks about in verse number one
how God is a very present help in the time of trouble
and you find that as the verses continue in Psalm 46
in verse two and three, the catastrophic events
that the Psalmist references in that Psalm
but yet he says, my God is a very present help
in the time of trouble.
Paul dealt with hardships but Paul experienced God's help
and what a blessing that is
as we look at the passage of scripture,
look at it in verse number eight, begin reading with me.
The Bible says this, we are troubled on every side
yet not distressed, we are perplexed but not in despair,
persecuted but not forsaken, cast down but not destroyed.
Always bearing about in the body,
the dying of the Lord Jesus,
that the life also of Jesus
might be made manifest in our body.
For we which live are always delivered unto death
for Jesus' sake, that the life also of Jesus
might be made manifest in our mortal flesh.
So then death worketh in us but life in you,
we having the same spirit of faith,
according as it is written,
I believed and therefore have I spoken,
we also believe and therefore speak,
knowing that he which raised up the Lord Jesus
shall raise up us also by Jesus
and shall present us with you.
For all things are for your sakes
that the abundant grace might through the thanksgiving
of many redound to the glory of God,
for which cause we faint not.
But though our outward man perish,
yet the inward man is renewed day by day.
For our light affliction, which is but for a moment,
worketh for us a far more exceeding
and eternal weight of glory.
While we look not at the things which are seen,
but the things which are not seen,
for the things which are seen are temporal,
but the things which are not seen are eternal.
This morning as we look at this passage of Scripture
and consider this thought, we faint not,
I want you to notice number one, the pressures.
The pressures.
Again, I mentioned by way of introduction
that the Apostle Paul is going to speak
with great transparency in this portion of Scripture.
In fact, in the book of 2 Corinthians,
he not only speaks here,
but he speaks again in chapter number 11
and again in chapter number 12
with great transparency with regard to the pressures
that he experienced.
We understand this morning that life is full of pressure
and here for just a few verses,
we have the opportunity to get a glimpse
into what the Apostle Paul experienced.
I would say this, that he had physical pressures.
He had emotional pressures.
I would say this, he had external pressures,
but he had internal pressures.
And begin to think about the pressures
that the Apostle Paul faced,
we find and we won't take the time to read it
in 2 Corinthians 11,
but in verses 24 through 28,
Paul lists out a whole lot of things that he suffered
and that he dealt with and those difficulties.
He ends it at the end of verse 28
and talks about that which came upon him daily,
the care of all the churches.
He says in the 12th chapter of the book of 2 Corinthians,
he says in verse number 14 and 15,
behold, the third time I am ready to come to you
and I will not be burdensome to you
for I seek not yours, but you.
For the children ought not to lay up for the parents,
but the parents for the children.
And here's what he says in verse 15,
I will very gladly spend and be spent for you,
though the more abundantly I love you,
the less I be loved.
He says to the churches in the region of Galatians,
Galatians chapter number four,
he asked this question, have I become your enemy
because I tell you the truth?
See, the Apostle Paul knew what pressures were.
He understood the pressures of ministry.
He experienced the pressures of ministry.
Paul is not speaking here about.
something that he read somewhere else from someone else.
He's speaking personally about what he experienced
and the joy as we look at here,
and I wanna make sure that it's packaged together
because I said by way of introduction
that there were hardships, but there's God's help.
And so we look first at the pressures
in which the Apostle Paul faced.
He says in verse number eight of 2 Corinthians 4,
notice he says this, we are troubled.
He says this, on every side.
We are troubled on every side.
To be troubled means to be afflicted.
It means to suffer persecution.
It means to be pressed hard upon.
And the Apostle Paul says that we are troubled
on every side.
Can you imagine, can you get in your mind this morning
a visual, if you will, of what the Apostle Paul
is seeking to communicate with regard
to the pressures of ministry
and understanding this thought of being troubled.
He says in verse number eight,
and we're just looking at the pressures at this point.
We'll look in just a moment at the counter
of each of these, but in verse number eight,
he says we are perplexed.
Ever been perplexed in life?
I mean, the idea of being perplexed
is to be without resources, to be in straits.
It carries with it this idea of not knowing
which way to turn.
Can I tell you that there are times
in which you might be perplexed,
and it's not because you don't know the leadership
of the Holy Spirit of God.
It's because you're concerned about the consequences
of the decision that you're going to make.
Let me say that again.
Being perplexed is not always because you don't know
the direction of the Holy Spirit of God.
Sometimes you're perplexed ministry-wise.
I'll speak as a pastor this morning.
You're perplexed because you know
that if you make the decision,
there's gonna be a fallout.
There's gonna be people that aren't gonna be happy.
You understand what I'm saying?
Sometimes it's not that you don't have the direction,
it's that you're concerned about the consequence.
We find that Paul says we're perplexed.
He says troubled on every side, perplexed.
He says this in verse number nine, persecuted.
Persecuted.
Literally, the idea is to put to flight.
The idea is to drive away.
Now, Paul knew something about persecution from both sides.
He knew what it was to be a persecutor, amen?
He went, he had the letters, he had the authority,
he had the power, and he knew what it was
to go and find any that were of that way.
But then he experienced greatly
what it was to be the persecuted.
Somebody's phone is ringing, amen?
Praise the Lord.
To put to flight, to drive away.
He says in verse number nine, notice he says persecuted,
and then he says cast down.
There it is again, hallelujah.
Put them on speakerphone.
Cast down.
It literally means to throw to the ground.
That's what it means, to be cast down.
Three times a charm, amen?
Praise the Lord.
Yeah, amen.
Call her out right there, amen?
Keep on preaching.
So to throw to the ground,
maybe you need to do that with that phone.
Cast down, amen?
But Paul says, as he's talking about the pressures,
he says troubled on every side.
He says perplexed, persecuted, cast down.
He's sharing his heart, he's sharing with transparency.
Listen, it's a false thing for someone to stand up and say,
there's not gonna be any pressures in life.
I mean, we got folks, we got people
that have all sorts of different backgrounds in our church
and all kinds of experiences, all different stages of life.
It'd be silly for a married couple to say to a couple
that's getting ready to get married and say,
there's no pressures in marriage.
No, it'd be silly to someone
that just recently had a newborn to say,
oh, there's no pressures in raising children.
There are pressures, there are difficulties.
And it'd be equally wrong for someone in ministry
to say someone else that's going into ministry,
oh, there are no pressures in ministry.
There are pressures.
I've been working with Fernando.
He announced his call to missions.
And it's changed the dynamic
of some of our meetings and discipleship.
And this week when we met for a couple of hours,
I shared with him, hey, listen, understand in ministry,
there's some difficulties.
He's getting ready to teach his first lesson.
You know what I told him?
I said, there's gonna be some that are gonna say
it's the best thing they ever heard.
And there's gonna be somebody else that asked you
what language you were speaking.
That's what I told him, because he speaks two languages.
But what was I trying to communicate to him?
Look, you can't please everybody.
I preached a message about a year and a half ago
on the audience of one, the audience of one.
Because you try to please everybody, you get crazy.
The pressures.
I read this little book a couple of Sunday,
actually three Sundays ago now.
Many of you know Don Sisk, just a simple book.
It's only like a half hour to read this book, if that.
It's like 85 pages, but just a small 85 pages.
Don Sisk was the director, he was a missionary in Japan.
He was a pastor for a number of years,
went to be a missionary in Japan,
and then was the director at BIMI for a number of years.
And so Don Sisk, I always thought it was kind of funny,
he wrote a book called Fourth Quarter.
And he used the parallels of the sports world,
if you will, in analogy.
So he wrote a book, Fourth Quarter,
how to serve God in the fourth quarter of your life.
It was a good book, I enjoyed reading it.
And then he wrote a book entitled Overtime.
Why did he write a book called Overtime?
Well, because he lived past 80, he's about 92 now,
and he's about 85, 86, and he wrote a book called Overtime.
And how to serve God in the overtime years.
It was a good book, I enjoyed reading it.
And I remember saying to Holly,
after he wrote that book Overtime,
I said, the only other sports analogy
I could think of is sudden death.
I can't think of another one.
And I said, sudden death must be the title of his next book.
But that'd be kind of weird,
because then he can't write the book,
because there was sudden death,
and we're just kind of joking about it.
And so here's the title of his newest book,
How to Stay in the Ministry Your Whole Life.
I like that better than sudden death.
And, but he wrote this little book,
and as I read this little book three weeks ago
on a Sunday afternoon, that book contained in it
some statistics about ministry.
Can I tell you this morning, it broke my heart
when I read the statistics about ministry.
Let me just share a few with you.
They say that 50%, 50% that begin pastoring
won't last five years.
They won't last five years, 50%.
Let me share this one with you.
Only 10% that start out pastoring retire as a pastor.
That means 90% along the way either die before retirement,
or they do something different.
That's a huge number.
Now, this statistic is in this book,
and I looked it up to try to validate some of these things,
and those two I could find easily
from a number of different sources.
But the one that's very concerning
is the number of pastors that leave the ministry
every month in America.
It's varied, so I'm gonna be transparent with you.
The lowest number that I saw was 250 pastors per month
leave the ministry.
The highest number I saw was 1,700 pastors per month
The consistent number that I saw was 1,500.
This book, How to Stay in the Ministry Your Whole Life
said 1,500 per month leave the ministry.
It's hard for us to wrap our minds around that.
But the reality is that we know,
we see some of this taking place where today
there are so many churches in America
that do not have pastors today.
There are churches that I know here in Virginia
without a pastor, and I mean,
it's not that they don't have,
there's no prospect for a pastor.
There's no one that they have lined up
to come be their pastor.
I talked with a friend on the phone on Wednesday,
and as I chatted with this ministry friend,
he shared with me that currently he's a missionary,
he's got a number of supporting churches
that don't have a pastor.
And he said, of the supporting churches
that I have without a pastor,
not one of them have even a prospect
of who would be their next pastor.
He shared with me accounts of men
that have worked diligently to try to find
their replacement with zero success.
It's a sad thing, it's a sad state
that we're dealing with, with our churches.
I don't believe that it's that God stopped calling.
I don't believe that.
Part of it is the fact that people
have stopped responding to the call.
But I think there's also a truth
of the pressures of ministry.
The pressures.
You look up some of the statistics,
they're wild, they blow your mind,
as to some of the pressures.
When you begin to think about.
about the Apostle Paul here,
and he's speaking again with great transparency,
and he says, look, there are pressures that we face.
There are pressures.
Listen, you're gonna face pressures in your life.
And what you're gonna find in your life,
you're never gonna make everyone happy either.
Amen?
You're not gonna ever make everyone happy.
Why do you think your pastor's gonna make everyone happy?
It's unreasonable, is it not?
Honestly.
I like this, I don't like that, I like that.
You know how it works.
And the reality is that Paul says there's great pressures.
But I want you to see number two.
With great pressures, there's great provision.
Praise the Lord.
It's not all negative, but there's a negative aspect.
I mean, there's reality, there's truth,
there's transparency.
And Paul says there's pressures,
but let me remind you that though there's great pressures,
there's great provision.
Why is it great provision?
Because it's God's provision.
And we find here that if we look
and we were to categorize it into two thoughts,
that the provision comes first in the form of God's grace.
The provision comes first in the form of God's grace.
And we're reminded of 2 Corinthians 12
and verse number nine that God's grace is sufficient.
That God's grace is sufficient.
And we find that in the text of Scripture,
we only looked at the pressures,
but notice in verse number eight,
as we go back and look at both sides of this,
that Paul says we are troubled on every side.
Then notice he says, yet not distressed.
I mean, we're troubled on every side,
but we're not distressed.
You know what it means not to be distressed?
It means to not be discouraged.
To not be discouraged.
Do you know that discouragement,
I shared this several weeks ago in another message,
but discouragement is one of the tools
that Satan uses most often.
It's a tool in the toolbox of Satan
that he loves to use to discourage people.
I know people right now that I could call on the phone
that were pastors when I started pastoring,
pastors that started after I started pastoring,
that are no longer pastors today.
You know what a lot of them say?
They're discouraged.
But Paul says, don't forget God's provision.
Yes, there are pressures, but oh, there's provision.
Yes, we're troubled on every side,
but we're not distressed, we're not discouraged.
Why?
Well, we'll get to the why at the end of the text
because he's got an eternal focus, not a temporal focus.
He's got a focus of pleasing God, not pleasing man.
And we find that he says we're not distressed.
He says, number two, in verse number eight,
when he mentions about we are perplexed,
but not in despair.
To not be, he says, we're not without hope.
He says this, we're not depressed.
You hear that word often used about depression.
I read a bunch of statistics this week.
I can't remember exactly the number, so don't quote me,
but it was about 45%, if I remember correctly,
of pastors that were surveyed that reported
they were depressed.
Let me ask you this, if the pastor's depressed,
how's he gonna lead the ministry?
If you're depressed, how are you leading your home?
You know what I'm saying?
It's a great number.
But Paul says God's provision, his grace.
Oh yeah, I'm perplexed, but I'm not in despair.
I'm not without hope.
I'm not depressed.
He says this in verse number nine, persecuted.
Oh yeah, we're persecuted, but not forsaken.
It means not to be abandoned.
It means not to be deserted.
Oh, I'm so reminded of the truth,
and I used it by way of introduction,
that there's hardships, but there's help.
And our God, it says in Hebrews 13, verse five and six,
at the end of verse five,
I will never leave thee nor forsake thee,
so that we might boldly say, the Lord is my helper.
I will not fear what man shall do unto me.
Listen, I'm not abandoned.
I'm not deserted.
There are times, loneliness, it's on the top list
of those that are talking, these pastors
that were interviewed and surveyed.
Oh, they feel loneliness, they feel,
no, no, the Holy Spirit's with us.
The Holy Spirit's with us, and as we look here,
and we see God's provision, we rejoice
in knowing that in the pressures,
there's also the provision, and this is true in your life
just as much as it's true in my life.
This is true in the lives of the believers
in the church in Corinth as much as it was
in the life of the apostle Paul.
And he says in verse number nine,
we're cast down, but not destroyed.
Cast down, but not destroyed, the idea, obviously,
to be killed or to be rendered useless.
I think Paul had a fear of becoming a castaway.
Mentioned in 1 Corinthians chapter nine.
Paul understood God had a purpose for his life,
and God understood he faced great pressures.
Again, the pressures that he faced,
there were physical pressures,
there were emotional pressures,
there were external pressures,
there were internal pressures.
And I think as you look at 1 Corinthians chapter number 11,
excuse me, chapter number, yeah, 11, verses 24 through 28,
I think it was the internal pressures
that affected Paul more than the external pressures.
I think it was the internal pressures.
I think about your own family, your own life.
When you got pressures internally in your home,
it's a lot harder to deal with
than when a neighbor's got a problem with you.
Am I right?
I think it was the internal that affected him the most.
But you know what Paul says?
Oh, there's all these pressures,
but there's God's provision, there's God's grace,
and God's grace is sufficient.
We continue reading, and we begin to see in verses 10,
down through verse number 15,
how Paul will continue to kind of expound
on what he's listed in verses eight and nine.
He says, always bearing about in the body
the dying of the Lord Jesus,
that the life also of Jesus
might be made manifest in our body.
Think about Paul.
I mentioned by way of introduction,
he says, I'm crucified with Christ.
He says, I die daily.
It's that constant reminder.
I said to Fernando on Thursday when we met,
I said, Fernando, you need to learn to be dead
to compliment and to criticism.
And he could tell you,
I'll tell you transparently right here.
Here's what I told him on Thursday.
For me personally, it's easy to be dead to compliment.
It's hard to be dead to criticism.
That's just me personally.
Some people are completely opposite.
They couldn't care less what you said about them.
They're dead to criticism.
It doesn't affect them one bit.
They don't give two thoughts about it.
But you start complimenting them,
and man, their head gets big,
and they get all kinds of puffed up.
We're all different.
Here's what I told Fernando.
You gotta know you.
What affects you?
How does it impact you?
But we need to remember that we're dead with Christ.
We're dead with Christ.
Notice verse 11.
For we which live are always delivered
unto death for Jesus' sake.
The life also of Jesus might be made manifest
in our mortal flesh.
So then death worketh in us,
but life in you.
We, having the same spirit of faith,
according as it is written,
I believed and therefore have I spoken.
We also believe and therefore speak.
He quotes back to the psalmist in Psalm 116.
And I'm so thankful that we've been given truth,
and then we speak the truth.
We have been, listen, in 1 John,
you read 1 John, chapter number one,
John starts out talking about we're his witnesses.
We're eyewitnesses of this.
And we speak what we have received
and what a blessing it is to know
that God would use us.
And we come to verse number 15.
I'll get to verse 14 here in just a moment.
But I want you to see verse number 15.
For all things are for your sakes
that the abundant grace
might through the thanksgiving of many
redound to the glory of God.
Now I want you to think about verse 15.
He speaks about all things are for your sakes.
Paul was a man that was surrendered.
He was yielded.
He understood for me to live as Christ
and to die as gain.
Paul says to the church in Philippi,
even after he makes that statement,
he says that it's more needful for you
that I'm here, why?
Because he understood that God was using him
to help them.
He understood that.
He understood the principle.
He understood the way that God designed it to work.
And he says all things are for your sakes.
And then he makes this statement
that the abundant grace,
think about that just for a moment.
We sing about God's amazing grace,
but we read and we talk about
as we get in the scriptures
about God's abundant grace.
Paul makes note in 1 Timothy
about how God's grace is abundant
and it was toward him
and how he trusted Christ as a savior
and he rejoices in the grace of God.
We can begin to think about the grace,
speaking of which,
we talk about the enabling grace,
the grace to serve God.
He gives us that grace.
It's abundant.
But notice what he says.
Might through the thanksgiving of many.
Now Paul's there just for a moment.
How thankful are we for God's grace?
But then we can ask ourselves this question.
How thankful are we in general?
We know the verses in everything give thanks
for this is the will of God
and Christ Jesus concerning you.
It says that through the thanksgiving of many,
down to the glory of God. You know when we give thanks, it pleases God. I'm being honest
with you this morning. When we give thanks, it brings glory to God, it pleases God when
we thank Him. You know what's so easy? To complain. To complain. Complain about everything.
I mean honestly, if we examine our lives, we complain about so many things. It's too
hot, it's too cold. I like this, I don't like that. This was, it was too loud, it was
too soft, it was too this, it was too that. You understand what I'm saying? You know what
the Bible says about complaining? The Old Testament word is murmur. I actually like
the word murmur more than I like complain. Because murmur just sounds bad. It does. You're
murmuring. Just carry something with it that just, that's probably not a good thing. Even
if you don't know the definition of the word and somebody says, stop murmuring. You're
like, hmm, that's probably, something's not right there. God heard their complaints and
it says this, He was not pleased. He was not pleased. You read the book of Numbers. God
was serious. There's some consequences. God miraculously provided manna. What do the people
say? I don't like this stuff. My soul loatheth. Come on. Am I telling you the truth this morning?
Come on. It was God's provision. I don't like it. Oh, that we were back in Egypt. Really?
Do you remember what Egypt was like? But is that not what they say? Sometimes we need
a reset. We need a reset. He says in verse number 15 that it would read down to the
glory of God. Just be thankful. Can I use a simple illustration this morning? I'm going
to say always, but I'm sure there are some times that I forget. I'm going to come down
for a minute, Fernando. Fernando's learned how to do the sound. I think it's great. He's
going to need that one day. Seriously. I know enough about that stuff to get everything
in trouble. I purpose every day to thank Holly for the meals that she makes. But can I tell
you something, Ron? They're not always my favorite meal. Listen for a minute. It's not
always my favorite meal, but I always thank her for the meal. You want to know one of
the things we had last night for dinner? Brussels sprouts. That's just a bad word, man. Brussels
sprouts. I do not like Brussels sprouts. In fact, there was a piece of a Brussels sprout
that got on my broccoli. It was contaminated. Amen? But you know what I did after dinner?
I thanked her for dinner. She labored for that. She worked hard for that. And I appreciate
it. But you know what I could do? I could complain about it. We're having this again.
Don't you know I don't like that? Now, that wouldn't work out real good for her along.
Am I right? But what do we do in church? Help me this morning. Help me this morning. What
do we do in church? Right? And I thank her because I appreciate it. I'm not saying that
because I want anyone to thank me. I already told you, a compliment doesn't bother me.
What I'm saying to you this morning is that sometimes we need a reset. We need a reset.
Paul talks about the pressures, but he talks about the provision. I preached a message
years ago on a Sunday morning from the book of Habakkuk. Somebody left here saying, I
can't believe he would preach up from Habakkuk on Sunday morning. Yeah. Yeah. And there was
a visitor here that morning, husband and wife, and they sent me an email and said, we've
been doing our devotions to the book of Habakkuk and that helped us so much. What I'm saying
to you this morning is that the pressures are real, but God's provision is real. We
see not only God's grace, but we see God's power. Notice with me if we're looking at
the provision and we note it from two aspects. Number one, the grace of God. Number two,
the power of God. We see in verse number 16, he says this, for which cause we faint
not. Paul, how is it that you can go through and experience all these pressures of life?
How can you have these pressures of ministry? How can you not be like John Mark and go back?
Because God's grace and because of God's power. He says, for which cause we faint not, but
though our outward man perish, can you imagine as we looked at verses 8 and 9 and all that
he explained, the outward man would perish, but he says this, yet the inward man is renewed
day by day. Brother Mark's Sunday school class this morning about the Holy Spirit, the work
of the Holy Spirit. And he went to Ephesians 3 and verse 16. I got it written in my notes
to go there. Because Paul, as he's praying for the believers in Ephesus, you know how
he prays for them that they be renewed with strength by the Spirit in their inner man.
And oh, we thank God for his power. We understand that the outward man might perish, but the
inward man is renewed day by day. How is it renewed day by day? Oh, if you're not in God's
Word, you have no idea how that happens. I'll be honest with you. If you're not doing devotions
regularly, if you're not in the Word of God, you're not having your inner man strengthened.
There's no, here's what I've learned in the Christian life, there's no just status quo.
There's no just staying in an idle position. You're either going forward or you're going
backwards. Honestly. You're either going forward or you're going backwards. And how is that
inward man renewed? It's renewed, notice what he says, day by day. Can I tell you this morning,
if you wait until the point that you're ready to faint, I can't do this anymore, and then
you're like, I need to be strengthened. Oh, God is able, but you're kind of late. You
need to be renewed day by day by day by day. And you go to it again and again and again.
Brother Jeff and I were talking when we're stapling and we're talking about some things
that we've just recently seen in God's Word as we've been doing our devotions and reading
and studying and it's like, man, there's things that God will point out. I've been preaching,
I've preached like 2,000 messages. I've preached through entirely like 25 books of the Bible
since I've been the pastor here, verse by verse, and yet every day, I don't, listen,
I don't go to the Bible just to find a sermon. I read this book every day of my life because
I need it. And the reality is that God will show me things, I'm like, man, that's really
good. Oh, God, I needed that today. Thank you for encouraging me with that truth. And
then maybe I'll have an interaction at some point later that day or that week and God
has prepared me for that interaction that I would have with a truth from God's Word
that can be shared with someone else. And he says the inward man is renewed day by day.
This morning, the pressures, the provision, but I want you to notice finally this morning
the perspective. The perspective. We know in verse number 14 that Paul had great confidence.
Notice how he begins verse number 14, knowing. Knowing. He doesn't say that he's thinking
that this might be the case. No, he says knowing. Listen, there's some things that God wants
you to know. We sang the song this morning to start when we all get to heaven, right?
Or was it The Roll is Caught Up Yonder? Which one did we sing? The Roll is Caught Up Yonder.
The Roll is Caught Up Yonder. Mr. Black, I think, is the one that wrote that song. And
he says this, when the roll is caught up yonder, I might be there. That's not what he said.
He said I will be there. Confidence. Confidence. Notice what Paul mentions that he knows in
verse number 14. Knowing that he which raised up the Lord Jesus. Hey, by the way, we serve
a risen Savior, don't we? Oh, we serve a risen Savior. He's alive. He rules. He reigns. He's
coming back one day. Hallelujah. And he says knowing that he which raised up the Lord Jesus
shall. Certainty. Certainty. Shall raise up us also by Jesus and shall present us with
you. Man, it's a beautiful picture that God gives us in one verse of scripture. And we
know, listen, this truth is that death has no power over us. If we've been saved by the
grace of God, we will, listen, Christ is the first fruits, 1 Corinthians 15, we will rise
again. And what a joy that is. And he says that he'll present us. I want you to think
just for a moment.
of the truth of the church.
The individual believers make up the church,
but the church is known as the body of Christ,
but also the bride of Christ.
And who's gonna do, who's gonna present us?
You read Ephesians chapter number five,
and you begin reading about the church
and the relationship between the husbands and wives.
And then you find that the Bible talks about
how husbands are to love their wives,
even as Christ loved the church and gave himself for it
in Ephesians chapter number five.
And he goes on to say this,
that he, Christ, might sanctify and cleanse it, the church,
with the washing of water by the blood
that he might present it to himself, a glorious church,
not having spot or wrinkle or any such thing,
but that it should be holy and without blemish.
Oh, what a day it's gonna be when we get to heaven.
I'm serious.
Heaven's gonna be a wonderful place.
Not everybody in heaven's gonna be thinking
the same way you think either.
I know we're gonna be glorified,
but there's some things that God's gonna straighten out,
I think.
But he says he's gonna present us.
Think about that this morning.
Paul said knowing, but then I want you to see
the focus of Paul, his perspective.
We're gonna read verse 18 and then go back to verse 17
in 2 Corinthians chapter number four.
Verse 18 says, while we look not at the things
which are seen, but of things which are not seen.
That's the focus of Paul.
Where's my focus, where's your focus?
Can I tell you this morning it's really easy
to look at the things that are seen?
It requires discipline to look at the things
that are not seen.
Requires discipline.
To have an eternal focus.
Oh, you gotta work on it.
Why, because the things which are seen,
those are things right in front of you.
Those things, those are the pressures.
Those are the difficulties, those are the distress,
that's what that is.
And Paul says, while we look not at the things
which are seen, but of the things which are not seen,
notice he says this, for the things which are seen
are temporal, but the things which are not seen
are eternal.
Oh, that God would help us to have an eternal focus.
An eternal focus.
Sometimes we get sideways about things here on Earth.
How many of you ever had a disagreement with your wife?
Don't raise your hand.
And afterwards, never?
He's coming to the altar this morning, amen?
He'd be the first one here before Kimberly
hits the first note, amen?
But here, listen.
Sometimes we have a disagreement with our wife
and it's over something so insignificant.
We're sideways with each other, problems.
And you sit down and say, what actually happened?
And you start figuring out and you're like,
that's kind of, shouldn't use these words,
but stupid, dumb, silly, whatever word you want to use.
Why?
See, sometimes we're just so temporally focused.
God says we need to get an eternal focus.
We look not at the things which are seen,
but the things which are not seen.
And we have to ask ourselves this morning,
where's our focus?
See, his perspective, the perspective of Paul
impacted how he responded to the pressures of life.
Can I tell you this morning that your perspective
is going to impact how you respond to the pressures?
You're gonna have pressures, I guarantee you.
And your perspective is going to impact
how you respond to those pressures.
And we find that here in verse number 17,
we see really the response of Paul
and it's all impacted because of the proper perspective
that he had and the Bible says,
notice what Paul says, for our light affliction.
Now, if you've ever read anything about the Apostle Paul
and you've ever read anything about the things
that he suffered, the pressures that he endured,
you would scratch your head on trying to figure out
why it would be termed light affliction.
He stoned and left for dead.
I believe God raised him up.
Listen, I mean, you begin to think about
all that Paul suffered and he says,
our light affliction, but then notice
it goes a moment further, he says,
or it goes a page further, he says,
which is but for a moment.
Now, when in Paul's ministry did he not suffer hardship?
You're gonna have a hard time reading in the Gospel
or in the book of Acts, reading through the epistles,
you're gonna have a hard time finding a time
in Paul's ministry where he wasn't facing pressures.
He says, but for a moment.
Why does he say it's for a moment?
Paul, it's your whole Christian life.
From the time you got saved to the time you were beheaded,
I mean, for all of it, you face pressures,
but it's just a moment, why?
Because I'm looking to eternity
and I'm gonna be with my Savior forever.
And it's just a moment, it's just light affliction.
By the way, what did our Savior suffer for us?
What did he suffer for us?
For the joy that was set before him, he endured the cross.
This word affliction in verse number 17
of our text of Scripture, the word troubled
in verse number eight is the root word
for that word affliction.
We're troubled on every side,
we're dealing with these afflictions.
This morning again in Sunday school,
Mark went over to Psalm 119, the psalmist says,
it was good for me to be afflicted.
Now, most of us would never say that.
Why, we don't like being afflicted.
Are we honest this morning?
You don't like affliction?
But the psalmist says it was good for me to be afflicted,
why, because then I learned thy statutes.
There's some things that we learn about God.
There's some things that we learn about God's grace
and about God's power, about God's purpose
through the times of affliction,
through the times of difficulty.
And Paul says, it's just light affliction,
it's just for a moment.
Then notice what he says, because he understands
that God is working to accomplish something great.
He's working to accomplish something
that would bring glory to his name.
Notice in verse number 17, he says,
for our light affliction, which is but for a moment,
worketh for us a far more exceeding
and eternal weight of glory.
Paul, beaten, stoned, shipwrecked.
Oh, God's working.
He's working something good.
He's working something great.
He's working something for his glory.
He's helping me to be conformed to his image.
It's wonderful, but it's all based on perspective.
Sometimes we get the wrong perspective in life.
Seriously, we just got a temporal focus.
We're just looking at things that don't really matter
in the big scheme of things.
There are eight billion people on this earth.
It's estimated that somewhere around six billion of them
are going to go to hell, the lake of fire.
Yeah?
I think that's low.
I think it's low.
I think it's more than that.
Multiple billions of people have never heard
the name of Jesus Christ.
And we want a church in Corinth.
I'm of Paul.
I'm of Cephas.
I'm of, have these divisions and these, seriously?
Seriously?
Paul says we got to get our perspective on heaven.
We got to get our perspective on eternity.
Every individual in Corinth,
every individual here this morning,
we're going to experience hardships.
We're going to experience hardships.
We're going to experience the pressures in life.
But through the hardships, the Lord is our helper.
His provision, His grace, and His power is enough.
It's enough.
We find, it's wonderful.
I turn over here to the book of 1 Peter,
in chapter number five.
In verse number eight, I'll read verse seven with it.
I wasn't planning to go here,
but it says, casting all your care upon Him,
for He careth for you.
And then it tells us in verse eight, be sober, be vigilant,
because your adversary, the devil, is a roaring lion,
walketh about seeking whom he may devour.
And then verse nine says,
whom resist steadfast in the faith,
knowing that the same afflictions are accomplished
in your brethren that are in the world,
but the God of all grace,
who hath called us unto eternal glory by Christ Jesus,
after that ye have suffered a while.
I don't know how long a while is, and neither do you.
You can look in any language you want to look in.
It is an unspecified period of time.
You can be the greatest Greek scholar
there's ever been to walk upon the face of the earth,
and a little while means a little while.
It's unspecified.
I don't know how long it is,
but you know what I do know?
God does.
God does, and I also know this, it's not forever.
It's not forever.
And he says this, make you perfect,
establish, strengthen, settle you to him,
be glory and dominion forever and ever, amen.
Listen, we need to allow the truth of God's word
to benefit our lives.
Allow his plan to change our perspective,
because the pressures are gonna come.
The provision will be there.
God will give it.
But your perspective and my perspective play a huge role in this thing. Play a huge role
in this thing this morning. Oh, that we'd get our eyes on glory, get our eyes on heaven,
on eternity. Let's pray. Father, we love you. Thank you for loving us. Thank you for your
word, the truth contained therein. God, I pray this morning that you would help us.
I don't know all of the pressures that your people are facing today. I don't know of the
pressures that have mounted, maybe that have caused some to be discouraged and depressed.
They've not experienced your provision. God, today would you help them to experience the
provision that you've given to them, your grace and your power. If we faint in the day
of adversity, our strength is small. It's not talking of physical, it's spiritual. God,
help us to be strengthened in the inner man day by day. Help us to have this proper perspective
of eternity. Oh, God, help us to not focus on the temporal things, but to focus on the
eternal things. Would you use us for your honor and for your glory? Would you move and work? Holy
Spirit, have your will and your way. Well, thank you for every decision that's made. For it's in
Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed. Kimberly's
going to play quietly on the piano, and as she does, the altar is open.