Jesus is coming, amen.
What a glorious thought.
One day we'll see our Savior face-to-face,
we'll be with Him forevermore, hallelujah.
If you're saved here this morning, that is a reality.
And I'm so thankful for that.
I had somebody tell me,
actually I've had lots of people tell me this,
you just can't know for sure
that you're gonna go to heaven.
I mean, no one can know for sure, it's just not possible.
And sometimes someone will tell me that
that also tells me that they go to church.
And they'll tell me the kind of church they go to,
they'll tell me some things about it.
And so I have an opportunity at that point to say,
well, listen, do you know about a guy named Paul?
He wrote a lot of our New Testament.
And they'll say, well, yeah, I heard about Paul.
Well, you know, Paul knew that he was gonna go to heaven.
I mean, he had confidence, he was certain,
he said that he was ready to be offered
at the time of his departure was at hand.
He knew that he was gonna receive a crown.
He said this, that it was better for him.
He said that he had this desire to depart,
to be with Christ, which was far better, hallelujah.
He knew and we can know too.
Aren't you thankful for that this morning?
What a blessing to be saved.
Aren't you thankful this morning?
If you're saved, man, you ought to rejoice,
rejoice every single day to know that heaven is your home.
Second Corinthians chapter number 12
and we're wrapping up our study.
We're getting to the end of the calendar year
and therefore we're getting the end
of the book of Second Corinthians.
We've been studying through Second Corinthians
on Sunday mornings all throughout 2025.
This is the 30th message that I've preached
here from Second Corinthians to say,
would you preach the other weeks?
Well, from other portions of scripture,
someone asked me last week, pastor,
why aren't you preaching from Second Corinthians?
Because the Holy Spirit told me
to preach from somewhere else, amen.
And I want to obey the Lord.
And so we dealt with a different passage last week,
but here we are back in Second Corinthians chapter 12.
And it's been a wonderful study, our theme all year,
God's grace is sufficient.
I hope, I pray that you have experienced that truth
afresh, anew in your life here in 2025,
that God's grace is sufficient.
And what a blessed promise that is.
It's not only a promise that's explained to us
in God's word, but it's a promise
that every child of God must embrace
in their personal life to know
that God's grace is sufficient.
Last time we were in Second Corinthians,
we were looking at verses 11 down through verse number 19.
And in that portion of scripture,
we talked about Paul's love for the Corinthians.
We're reminded that the Lord Jesus Christ,
before he went to the cross of Calvary,
would meet with his disciples
and he would tell them at the end of the 13th chapter
of the book of John, that he gave them a new commandment.
And that new commandment was that they love one another
as Christ loved them, that's how they were to love.
And he said, by this, by your love one for another,
shall all men know that you're my disciples.
We find that the apostle Paul would encourage the church
at Thessalonica with regard to this truth
of brotherly love.
And he said, you already know this,
you're already doing this, but I wanna beg you,
I wanna encourage you to increase more and more.
And in this particular passage,
Paul is sharing with the believers in Corinth,
reminding them of his love for them.
He says that the more he loved, that the less he was loved.
But it didn't stop him from loving.
He loved them as Christ loved.
And we said this, it is impossible for us to love
as we're supposed to love if we're not filled
with the Holy Spirit of God.
Because the Holy Spirit, the Bible tells us
that the fruit of the Spirit is love.
The first one that's mentioned there, love.
And we understand the Holy Spirit who indwells us
as we're filled with the Holy Spirit,
that he allows us to love as Christ loved.
And we're to love one another, and I'm thankful for that.
As we look at the end of chapter number 12,
we find that the apostle Paul is going to deal
with something that is absolutely essential
to be dealt with, and he deals with it in love.
Notice in verse number 20, in 2 Corinthians 12,
in verse 20, the Bible says this,
"'For I fear, lest when I come,
I shall not find you such as I would,
and that I should be found unto you such as you would not,
lest there be debates, envyings, wraths,
strifes, backbitings, whisperings,
swellings, tumults.'"
Verse 21, "'And lest when I come again,
my God will humble me among you,
and that I shall bewail many which have sinned already
and have not repented of the uncleanness and fornication
and lasciviousness which they have committed.'"
As we look at these two verses of Scripture,
I've simply titled the message this morning,
Sin Must Be Addressed.
For the last three weeks, Dean has selected a song
that goes so well with either a morning message
or an evening message, and it's so neat
to see how the Holy Spirit works.
I mentioned two weeks ago when that happened
that it was neat to see the Holy Spirit.
Last week on Sunday night,
I said that Dean's looking at my sermon notes.
He's coming into the office and he's checking my notes
and he's picking the songs, which he's really not.
But we sang last week,
How Great Thou Art in the evening service.
And then we spoke, we preached about the greatness of God.
Only God is great.
That was the title of my message.
And we just got done singing, How Great Thou Art.
It's so awesome.
Well, this morning, Sin Must Be Addressed.
And if you remember not the special song,
but the last hymn that we sang
as a congregation this morning,
Nothing Between My Soul and My Savior.
What an appropriate song to lead into a message
that as we look at verse 20 and 21 of 2 Corinthians 12,
that sin must be dealt with.
We find in verse 20 that he speaks about their carnality.
And he mentions a whole list of things
there at the end of the verse
and really representing the carnality.
We know much about the church in Corinth.
We know some of the things from the first book
that Paul writes to them.
But I want you to be mindful of this this morning,
that believers, those that have trusted
the Lord Jesus Christ as their personal savior
have this wonderful promise that we read
in Romans 6 and verse 14.
And it's this, that sin shall not have dominion over you.
That's a precious promise
that God has given to his children.
If you're saved, you've been delivered
from the penalty of sin.
Amen?
For the wages of sin is death,
but the gift of God is eternal life
through Jesus Christ, our Lord.
And if you're saved this morning,
if you've trusted Jesus Christ as your personal savior,
then you've been delivered from the penalty of sin.
However, I believe that you've also discovered
that you still have the old nature,
the flesh, the old man.
And you find that you still sin, right?
We look at the book of Ephesians,
we look at the book of Colossians,
and in both of those books,
the apostle Paul is writing to saved people.
And as he's writing to those saved people,
he gives them the principle of putting off the old
and putting on the new.
And we find that sin no longer has dominion over us.
We're saved, we're saved from the penalty of sin,
but we still have this old flesh, the old nature.
The Bible says that if you walk in the spirit,
you shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
It did not say that your flesh would not lust.
How many of you would like it if that's the way it worked?
It doesn't work that way
because God wants us to walk in the spirit.
And he says, it's a wonderful promise in Galatians 5,
if you walk in the spirit,
you shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
And we find this morning that the church in Corinth,
the apostle Paul expresses concern
here in these verses of scripture.
And we could look at this this morning
and understand that if you're not saved,
you have a sin debt that will send you to the lake of fire.
If you're not saved this morning,
you've never trusted the Lord Jesus Christ
as your personal savior,
you've never received the gift of God,
that means that you are condemned.
So what the Bible says,
the Bible says that you're condemned already.
And it's because of our sin,
the wages of sin is death for all have sinned
and come short of the glory of God.
And if you're lost this morning,
the sin that you must deal with is being saved
and allowing for the precious blood of Christ
to be placed upon your account.
We would look at the truth of earlier in this book,
2 Corinthians 5 and verse 21,
for he God hath made him Jesus to be sin for us
who knew no sin that we might be made
the righteousness of God in him.
We would use the term imputed righteousness.
And that's when the righteousness of God
is placed on your account and my account
at the moment of salvation,
and we're declared righteous,
we're saved from the penalty of sin.
And if you're here this morning and you're still lost,
you've never trusted Jesus Christ.
as your personal Savior.
Can I tell you this morning,
today is the day of salvation.
Can I tell you what Jesus said to Nicodemus?
He was a religious leader.
He was a man that knew a lot about God,
but he didn't know God.
He was a man that tried to keep all kinds of rules
and regulations, but Jesus said to him,
ye must be born again.
Religion can't save you.
Only Christ can save you.
Your good works can't save you.
And we can rejoice this morning in salvation,
but then we must understand,
listen, there's a false teaching that's prevalent today.
It's called antinomianism,
and it has this idea that you're saved,
and therefore you can just live however you wanna live,
because you're saved, you're going to heaven.
The Bible tells us in the book of Galatians
that we're not to use our liberty
for an occasion to the flesh.
And what we find this morning is that,
yes, I'm saved and I'm going to heaven,
and I can't do anything to keep my salvation.
I'm kept by the power of God.
He saved me.
He keeps me.
Hallelujah.
Praise God.
But I am to walk worthy.
I am to live a life that is pleasing to God,
and we find that throughout the New Testament,
there's many references with regard to dealing with sin
in the life of a believer,
and that sin must be addressed.
The reality is that as we look here
in this portion of Scripture
and understand what's taking place,
I'm reminded of a lesson that Joshua
and the children of Israel learned.
It was a hard, but I would say valuable lesson
that they learned at Ai.
And the lesson that was learned at Ai
was that there was sin in the camp.
And God said to Joshua that he was not going to fight
for them and be with them until sin is dealt with.
That's an important lesson.
It's a hard lesson, but it's a valuable lesson.
In fact, you don't need to turn there,
but I'll read for you Joshua 7 in verses 11 and 12
as God is speaking to Joshua.
Notice what God says,
"'Cause Israel hath sinned,
and they have also transgressed my covenant,
which I commanded them,
for they have even taken of the accursed thing
and have also stolen and dissembled also,
and they have put it even among their own stuff.
Therefore, the result, the consequence,
the children of Israel could not stand before their enemies,
but turn their backs before their enemies,
because they were accursed.
Then notice what God says at the end of verse number 12.
Listen carefully.
"'Neither will I be with you anymore,
except you destroy the accursed from among you.'"
God's serious about sin.
Can I say this this morning,
right at the beginning of the message,
God is never okay with sin.
He's not.
I'm thankful that God is long-suffering.
Amen?
I mean, listen, you need to rejoice
that God is long-suffering.
He's patient with us.
He gives us opportunities to repent,
and he gives us opportunities to amend our ways,
but God's never okay with sin.
Sometimes what happens is a person, a child of God,
misinterprets God's long-suffering as being God's approval,
and it's absolutely imperative
that God's people never mistake God's long-suffering
for God's approval, for God is never okay with sin,
and sin in the life of a believer must be addressed.
When I was preaching through 1 John a couple of years ago,
when our theme was walking in the light,
we, of course, dealt with that first chapter,
second chapter, dealing with sin in the life of a believer,
and I shared with you a quote that I had read somewhere
during the preparation for those messages,
and someone told the pastor,
sin's different in the life of a believer,
and the pastor said, yeah, it's worse.
Think about that for a moment.
See, the Bible says if I regard iniquity in my heart,
the Lord will not hear me.
The reality of 1 John chapter one,
and we'll look at a couple of things
as we get through the message this morning,
my relationship with God is settled.
I'm a child, listen, we believe in eternal security.
Once you're saved, you are kept by the power of God.
He gave us eternal life, not probationary life.
Aren't you thankful for that this morning?
I mean, listen, if we could lose it,
we'd have lost it right after we got it.
I can't earn it, and I can't keep it.
I'm kept by the power of God,
but I want you to understand this morning
that the Bible says that we have an advocate
with the Father, Jesus Christ the righteous,
and I'm so thankful that we can confess our sins
and we can have that forgiveness this morning.
Listen, it's important that we recognize
that sin, it doesn't affect my relationship with God,
but it certainly affects my fellowship with God.
D.L. Moody said it this way,
sin will keep you from this book,
or this book will keep you from sin.
You know, when you're not walking with God as you ought,
when you know you have sin in your life,
you don't wanna read the Bible.
You don't wanna pray.
You don't wanna be in church.
You don't want anything to convict you.
Why?
Because you know you got sin in your life,
and so sin will keep you from this book,
or this book will keep you from sin.
It's a very famous quote by D.L. Moody,
one that you've heard many times, no doubt.
So we're gonna think about this truth
of sin must be addressed.
If you're taking notes this morning,
number one, I would say this,
we must identify sin in our lives.
We must identify sin in our lives.
We cannot address or deal with sin
that we've not first identified.
I want you to notice in verse number 20,
the Apostle Paul, as he's writing
to the believers here in Corinth,
he lists out a list of things.
He says at the end of verse number 20,
lest there be debates, envyings, wraths, strifes,
backbitings, whisperings, swellings, tumults.
And so he lists these things.
We're not gonna deal with all of them in particular,
because I wanna get through the message this morning.
We're not gonna go through the list
and deal with all of it specifically,
but I want you to understand that the Apostle Paul,
dealing with all of these things,
and he's mentioned several,
and there are times in which we can speak about sin
and identifying sin, and we call sin what it is.
Listen, Joseph said this,
how then can I do this great wickedness and sin against God?
The evil wickedness of sin,
we must understand that this morning,
and we must identify sin in our lives.
This morning, begin to think about what is sin.
We could talk about sin being a transgression of the law.
Sin is someplace, sometimes it's sin of commission,
sometimes it's sin of omission.
It's the fact that I'm doing something
that God told me not to do, it's sin.
I'm not doing something that God told me to do, it's sin.
Can I tell you this morning, pride is sin.
We dealt with it not long ago,
as we looked at the passage in which Paul talked about,
"'Lest I be exalted above measure,'
at the beginning of chapter 12, and we talked about pride.
And the Bible says that God resisteth the proud,
but giveth grace unto the humble.
And the reality is that pride is a sin
that's so prevalent in our society today.
It's prevalent within our homes, our churches,
it's unfortunate, but it's a truth.
We find that there's many things
we could speak about this morning.
We could talk about our thought life.
We could talk about, think about the song that we sang,
"'Take My Life and Let It Be,'
and it goes through all of those elements.
And you think about your thought life,
you know, you can sin in your thought life.
Worry, you say, come on, preacher,
you're gonna get on my toes this morning.
The Bible says, be careful for nothing.
You say, I'm not worried, I'm just concerned.
You've just tried to spiritualize it,
that's all you've tried to do and excuse it.
The reality this morning is that when we don't trust God,
it's sin, it's sin.
This morning, I'm not gonna go through a whole list
of what is sin, but we wanna identify sin in our lives.
And I would say this this morning,
we can't deal with it until we've identified it,
but let me say this,
you must refuse to be oblivious or ignorant.
You gotta refuse to be oblivious or ignorant.
Don't have this kind of, well, I'm okay.
In fact, I got a little book in my office
that's titled, I'm Not Okay.
You know what the subject of the book is?
Pride.
It's a good little book and it's titled, I'm Not Okay.
And this morning, we must refuse to be oblivious,
we must refuse to be ignorant.
Sometimes what happens is we wanna examine the life
of someone else instead of examining our own lives,
because we can identify sin in somebody else's life
a whole lot faster than we can identify sin in our own life.
Why?
Because I don't wanna go through the process
of self-examination, but we must.
The Holy Spirit will convict us as we hear
and read the word of God.
Aren't you thankful for the ministry
of the Holy Spirit of God?
I'm thankful that God's given us a Bible
and you have an opportunity to read your Bible
every day of your life.
You have the opportunity to come in here
preaching from God's word four times a week.
And as you have an opportunity to hear
and to read God's word, the Holy Spirit of God
will take his finger, if you will,
and he'll poke right at you and right at me,
and he'll convict me.
He will identify sin in my life.
And in your life.
I think about the...
and Psalm 139 with that desire to have God search
and show him if there be any wicked way.
And the reality is that we must identify sin in our lives.
The Apostle Paul is going to write certain things here
with regard to understanding the context
and who he's writing to and what's going on there.
And I don't know what the list might look like
in your life or in my life,
but I know today that there's a reality
that sometimes we get too comfortable with sin.
You're a little apathetic, a little indifferent.
We just get comfortable with it.
This morning, we must identify sin in our lives.
Why?
Because sin hinders my fellowship with God.
You know, when you think about that song that we sang,
"'Nothing Between My Soul and My Savior',"
not of the least that would have that ability
to hinder my fellowship with God.
I wanna be able to be in that place
where I have that sweet communion with my God.
So after I identify,
so we must first identify sin in our lives.
Number two, we must then confess
and forsake sin in our lives.
You notice that I said confess and forsake.
We find this morning that the Bible is true
in 1 John 1 and verse number nine,
that if we confess our sins,
he is faithful and just to forgive us
and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness.
And we ought to rejoice in that wonderful promise
that God has given to us.
And I understand that his book ends, if you will,
to that wonderful truth of 1 John 1 and verse number nine.
God tells us this, that if we say that we have no sin,
we deceive ourselves and the truth is not in us.
He then says on the back end of the great promise
that if we confess our sins, that he'll forgive us,
that he'll cleanse us.
If we say that we have not sinned,
we make him a liar and his word is not in us.
We're gonna identify it
and then we gotta confess it and forsake it.
Respond with haste when the Holy Spirit convicts.
I think that's such an important thing.
See, sometimes we'll be reading our Bible,
sometimes we'll be in a message,
we'll hear the preaching of God's word
and we don't respond.
Can I tell you that's dangerous for the lost person
when they hear the gospel
and the gospel is preached to them
and they understand that they're a sinner
and they're gonna pay,
they're gonna go to the lake of fire because of their sin
and they don't respond
when the Holy Spirit is convicting them
and they get a hard heart.
I was talking to the teenagers this morning
in Sunday school about the importance
of having a tender heart.
And as God's people, we need to have a tender heart.
When the Holy Spirit convicts you of sin,
when the Holy Spirit of God throughout your day,
you know, I'm thankful that He indwells us.
You're in a situation where you say something to somebody
and it wasn't exactly true,
you weren't maybe meaning, intending to lie,
but the way that you answered the question wasn't truthful
and immediately the Holy Spirit convicts you.
What do you do?
How do you respond?
Do you respond with haste?
Do you deal with it?
Do you correct it?
Do you confess it as being sin?
You say, well, everybody lies.
No, no, no, it's not the right response.
I understand everybody does lie.
The Bible says all men are liars.
I understand that.
But it doesn't mean that God's okay with it.
Amen.
And the Holy Spirit will convict you.
You look at something that you're not supposed to look at.
Holy Spirit of God will convict you.
What do you do in that moment?
Respond with haste.
Yield to the Holy Spirit when He convicts.
Refuse.
Refuse to delay in responding.
Why, because refusing to, excuse me,
because in delaying what's happening
is you're gonna have adverse effects.
You're gonna have that hardened heart.
If you get that hardened heart
and you just kind of get comfortable with things
and all of a sudden it just doesn't maybe affect you
the way that it did before.
You know, there's some people
that have heard the gospel many times
and they've not been saved.
And the gospel's preached.
They hear the gospel and they just got a hard heart.
They just turn it off.
Their heart's been hardened.
This morning is God's people.
How's your heart?
Is it tender?
See, Paul's writing, listen, I said this,
I believe that Paul's saying these things in love.
By the way, if you truly love somebody,
you tell them the truth.
That goes way against our culture today.
Because our culture today says if you love somebody,
you let them be and do whatever they wanna be and do.
That's not love.
Amen?
Love is giving them the truth.
The Bible says in Ephesians that we speak the truth in love.
And we find here that Paul says that he loves them.
He says, I seek not yours but you in verse 14.
In verse number 15, he says,
I will very gladly spend and be spent for you.
Though the more abundantly I love you,
the less I be loved.
At the end of verse number 19, he says,
we do all things dearly beloved for your edifying.
Paul couldn't make them deal with their sin.
But he certainly wanted to encourage them to do it.
Why?
Because he understood the results, the ramifications,
what happens if they don't deal with their sin.
They miss out on the blessing of God.
They deal with the chastening of God.
I don't wanna be chastened by God.
I'm not interested in that.
But you know, God chastens his children.
And every once in a while, if you're saved,
you're gonna be chastened.
It's not always pleasant, but it's always for our good.
And this morning, we find that Paul then says
in verse number 21, unless when I come again,
my God will humble me among you
and that I shall bewail many which have sinned already
and have not repented of the uncleanness
and fornication and lasciviousness
which they have committed.
And so we see in verse 20, there's a list of items
that are mentioned beginning with debates.
And then we see in verse 21,
speaking about fornication, lasciviousness,
it's listed here and uncleanness is mentioned as well.
And so we begin to look at this
and we find that the Apostle Paul is saying,
listen, my desire for you is that you would be right.
Remember, the book of 1 and 2 Corinthians
is written to a church.
It's not written to a community.
This book is not written to the city of Corinth.
It's written to the church that's in Corinth.
And what do we know in the Bible about a church?
Well, a church is made up of people.
It's not a building.
This is where we have the privilege of assembling,
but you're the church.
We assemble together.
And to be a member of a church,
we look through the scriptures beginning in Acts 2
at the day of Pentecost.
We begin to look at the pattern
throughout the New Testament.
What does it mean to be a member of a church?
When he talks about the church,
well, somebody that's saved, that's baptized,
that they've voluntarily joined themselves together
for the purpose of pleasing God, exalting God
and carrying out the Great Commission.
That's the believer.
And so he's writing to save people,
but he's dealing here with the fact
that there needs to be repentance.
There needs to be this confession of sin
and forsaking of sin.
Understand this morning, again,
it's not that you need to get saved again.
You're saved and you're secure,
but it's that I wanna have God's favor.
I wanna have God's blessing in my life.
You know, it's amazing what we'll forfeit for sin.
And sometimes what happens is we never truly
consider what we're forfeiting
because we're looking at the pleasure of sin.
Hebrews talks about the pleasure,
there is pleasure in sin for a season.
The Bible also says that the way of the transgressor is hard.
It's hard.
I was teaching in Sunday school this morning
from 2 Kings chapter 23 to the young people
looking at kind of finishing up with Josiah.
And I ended the lesson this morning
by telling the young people, listen, I can't,
Josiah could not, he led them to make a covenant with God,
but he could not make them obey God.
I try to encourage those teenagers,
listen, I want you to live for God.
I want you to please God with your life.
I want you to obey God, but I can't make you.
But my heart is that I want you to, why?
Because it will be best for you.
You'll have God's favor.
Remember Deuteronomy, the Bible says that God said,
I give you today, I set before you today
a blessing and a curse.
And it's all based upon obedience to God's commands.
And this morning we must identify sin.
Once we've identified sin,
we must confess and forsake sin.
And then let me deal with this this morning.
Number three, if you're taking notes,
we must develop a plan to walk in victory.
We must develop a plan to walk in victory.
See, this morning, what I'm concerned about this morning
is sin in the life of believers.
We get comfortable with it, we just get used to it.
Everybody else is.
Remember a couple of chapters ago,
he said do not compare yourself amongst yourselves.
It's not wise.
And so how do we develop a plan to walk in victory?
I think it's key.
I think it's vital for each and every one of us.
Why?
Because when you have victory today,
when you confess, you identify sin in your life today,
you confess it and you forsake it,
it doesn't mean the devil's gonna stop tempting you.
You know what I found to be true?
He's gonna increase the attack.
He's gonna tempt you more.
He's not gonna stop coming and trying to tempt you.
He's gonna keep bringing it.
He's gonna increase the attack.
So how do we develop this plan of victory,
to walk in victory?
I would say this,
be honest about your area of weakness and vulnerability.
Be honest.
I would never do it in a public setting.
setting, but I think it would be important for each person to truly acknowledge, as we
talked about in our first point, identifying sin. Where am I weak? What's my weak vulnerable
spot? There are some things, listen, there are some believers that have no real temptation
with certain sin. It's just not something that affects them. They're just not, they're
not tempted by it. But then for other people, there's this type of sin that's a temptation
for them. And when you begin to look at your own life and you begin to be honest with yourself
and honest before the Lord and you humble yourself, you say, I want to identify, I want
to be honest about my area of weakness. Where am I vulnerable? I know my weaknesses. I've
sought to, to the Lord to be able to work in my life. One of my weaknesses, I don't
like problems. You say, neither do I. But sometimes we get problems, we can respond
a wrong way. We can respond in sin. Just a few weeks ago, something happened, and it
was one of those, are you kidding me kind of moments. You've ever had those in your
life and how could this happen? And I remember at the moment of hearing about what had transpired,
I remember beginning to immediately, you know how quickly you can kind of, your blood pressure
can rise. You understand? I'm trying to be transparent with you this morning. Okay. Are
you there? Some of you are shaking your head like you got it. Some of you are like, not
me. I'm an angel. I got my halo on this morning. Amen. Amen. But listen, it was just one of
those moments. And you know what the Holy Spirit, I'm telling you, as I walked out of
my office, like the Holy Spirit just had a conversation with me in the hallway and said,
do you really believe what you preach? You just got done preaching about any kind of
couple of things I just got done preaching about. And I said, Lord, I do. I believe what
I preach. And I just kind of had a moment in the hallway over there with the Lord to
just walk in the Spirit. Yes, it was a frustrating situation, but what could God do in that situation?
How could God grow me or use me? If I sinned in that situation, if I responded in a sinful
manner, would I have an opportunity to be able to talk to somebody about Jesus afterwards?
Are you tracking with me this morning? And we got to identify where are we vulnerable,
where are we weak? Listen, men, and I try to be careful when we're on Sunday mornings,
understand with me that pornography is an issue in our society. It is a major issue
in our society. If you have a weakness in that area of your life, you better make some
provision for that to protect against that. It's absolutely essential. Absolutely essential.
Because you say, well, I got victory today. Listen, I could tell you story after story
after story of people that I've worked with, people that I've counseled with that have
destroyed their homes, that have lost their careers, because they have a weakness that
they would not identify. It's a problem. And again, I'm not trying to go through all a
list of sin this morning, but I'm trying to say, we got to have a plan to have victory.
How am I going to develop a plan? I'm going to be honest about my area of weakness, my
area of vulnerability, and when I've identified that here, I'm going to avoid some things.
I'm going to avoid some things. I'm going to eliminate some things. Amen? Sometimes
you got to get rid of it. You know what Josiah did? He ground the graven images and the molten
images to powder. Sometimes you just got to destroy something. How many of you have ever
seen Fireproof? I'm not endorsing everything about Fireproof, but that guy, he went out
and he beat his computer with a baseball bat. Am I telling the truth? That's what he
did in the movie. And I know it's a movie, but it's a great example and illustration.
He's going to deal with that. And this morning, what I'm saying is that we need to, if we're
going to have a plan to walk in victory, if we're going to be living a life that's pleasing
to God, there's some things when we're honest about our area of weakness or vulnerability
that we're going to avoid. We're going to eliminate. We're going to restrict ourselves.
I've never, I'm just being transparent this morning. I've never tasted alcohol in my entire
life. There is zero about alcohol that tempts me. I've never tasted it. It stinks. I see
the results. I've been around people that are drunk out of their minds. Why would I
want that? I've never been tempted with it. But can I tell you, if you got saved out of
alcoholism, you ought not be even in a situation where it could be possible that you're going
to be having alcohol. Amen? It's quiet this morning. I'm trying to help you. Because it's
important that we develop a plan for victory. Because we have an enemy who wants to destroy
you. He doesn't want to just trip you up. 1 Peter 5, verse number 8, be sober, be vigilant
because your adversary, the devil, is a roaring lion, walketh about, seeking whom he may devour.
So we have to be honest about our area of weakness and vulnerability. We need to put
some things in place. Let me say this, number two, if you're going to develop a plan. Memorize
Scripture that directly addresses your area of weakness. I will set no wicked thing before
mine eyes. It's a really good verse of Scripture. When you begin to identify what your area
of weakness is, you go and find some verses of Scripture that deal with that particular
area of weakness and you memorize them. Wherewithal shall a young man cleanse his way? By taking
heed thereto according to thy word. Psalm 119, verse number 9. Verse 11, thy word have
I hid in mine heart that I might not sin against thee. That's Psalm 119 and verse number 11.
And so listen, memorizing John 3.16 is wonderful, but when you're tempted to look at something
that you shouldn't look at, you're not going to quote John 3.16. When you look at the time
when Jesus was in the wilderness and He was being tempted, in each temptation He responded,
it is written, and it was a verse that specifically dealt with the temptation. Look it up. It's
true. And what I'm saying this morning is that memorizing verses is important, but when
we're talking about this area of living a life of victory and developing a plan for
victory, you better memorize some verses that deal with your area of weakness and vulnerability.
And if you say, I don't know what that is, I got a problem with worry. I got a problem
with, you start filling in the blank, look up some verses. If you don't know, come, I'll
be glad to share some verses with you. Somebody came to me, one of the kids in church came
to me a year ago, year and a half ago, and said something about something that they were
struggling with and I said, I'll give you some verses and I wrote them out on index
cards by hand and gave them the verses, just to try to encourage that young person. Do
that. Hide God's Word in your heart. Stay in the book, number three. Stay in God's Word.
Stay in church. It is a good thing when God convicts us. It is a good thing when the Spirit
of God, sometimes we say, man, I think somebody shared the testimony on Tuesday night about
maybe getting their toes stepped on when they come to church sometimes, and it's that figurative
idea that the preaching, sometimes you might feel like the preacher's sitting in my lap,
I've never sat in any of your laps, but you kind of feel that way sometimes. Sometimes
people leave and say, preacher, that was just for me. And I say, you know what, actually
it was just for me. God, I needed that. I can't tell you how many people walked out
of church a few weeks ago when I preached that message, too busy for Jesus, and said
to me when they walked out, that was for me. I think God had you preach that for me. And
I said to many of them, it was really for me. It was for me. We get so busy in the work
that we forget about who we're working for. And what we find this morning is that we need
to stay in the book. We need to stay in church. When we're dealing with things in our life,
and those temptations are coming, sometimes what happens is we run away, but the thing
is we've got to draw closer to God. We've got to understand that He's a loving Father.
He loves us, and He cares deeply about us, and He wants us to have that victory. He's
given us all of the things that are necessary for us to walk in victory. Let me say this,
number four, when you're developing a plan to walk in victory, number four, be accountable.
Be accountable. Being accountable is so vital. Seeking counsel is having someone answer your
questions. Being accountable is answering somebody else's questions. There's a huge
difference between seeking counsel and being accountable. Being accountable is answering
somebody's questions. Hey, how have you been doing this week? And then you get real specific
about whatever the area of sin is. There's an accountability partner. How's this going?
How you doing with this? What's going on? And being accountable is answering the questions.
Answering the hard questions.
Being honest.
You know what I found?
Most people don't want to be accountable.
They just don't want to be accountable.
We're accountable to God.
We're responsible.
But we ought to be accountable to one another.
If you're married, be accountable to your spouse.
Be accountable.
If you're a child, be accountable to your parent.
If you're a single man, be accountable to a single man or to a married man, to a man.
Listen, a single man shouldn't be accountable to a single woman.
Amen?
And the reality is that we come to this, listen, there's sometimes we just get comfortable
with sin.
We got strife and contention and we just got used to it.
We just got comfortable with it.
We want to have a plan for victory.
Be accountable.
Be willing to answer somebody's questions.
Be willing to find somebody that you could confide in and say, listen, this is an area
of vulnerability for me.
This is an area of weakness for me.
I need help because I want to walk in victory.
I'm tired of living a defeated life.
God didn't save you to live a defeated life.
He saved you to live a victorious life.
But thanks be to God which giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.
And we find this morning that we have to have a plan.
It's not going to just happen by chance that you're going to have victory.
And let me say this, claim the promises.
I kind of got ahead of myself, but God's given us everything that we need.
I quoted already from Romans 6 and verse number 14, that sin shall not have dominion over
you.
Listen, claim that promise.
God's given us the victory.
Look at the Bible in Galatians chapter 5 and I mentioned this by way of introduction, but
I want you to look at it.
I want you to read it and understand what God is telling us here because the reality
is that we need to have a plan to walk in victory.
And it's such a blessed thing when we have victory.
We have victory.
You know how excited people get when they win a game?
You know how irritated they are when they lose a game?
I mean, just watch some of the sports on TV.
I don't encourage you to do that all the time, but I'm just saying you can see it.
We were sitting there on Friday and my brother-in-laws were sitting there and they wanted to see
one of the games.
We don't have cable anymore, so we're trying to figure out how to get the game and it was
on prime and so we were able to watch some of the game.
And I said to my one brother, we got a sister-in-law that, I mean, she bleeds green or whatever
she says, an Eagles fan.
And man, I said to my brother-in-law, I said, isn't it amazing how quickly they change?
To cheering, to booing, to cheering, to booing, I mean, it's just kind of, it's all based
on are they winning or are they losing?
When you have victory in the Christian life, there's nothing like it.
When you're walking in victory, and it's not because of you, it's because of God working
in you.
I know that in me, that is my flesh dwelleth no good thing, amen?
I know that the Bible says in John that without me you can do nothing.
The songwriter said it this way, the arm of flesh will fail you.
But thanks be to God which giveth us the victory.
Who shall deliver me?
I thank God.
You begin to look at these promises and you rejoice in what God has done for us in Galatians
5, in verse 16, this I say then, walk in the Spirit and ye shall not fulfill the lust of
the flesh.
I said it earlier by way of introduction.
It doesn't say that the flesh will not lust.
It says that ye shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
It's a promise that God has given to us.
You know, it's interesting to me that throughout the Scriptures, God gives us truth and he
provides us with evidences of that truth.
When you're filled with the Spirit, you're going to do certain things.
Look at Ephesians 5, 18 talks about what that looks like.
When you're walking in the Spirit, according to Galatians 5, verse 16, you're not going
to fulfill the lust of the flesh.
So if you say, I'm walking in the Spirit, and you're fulfilling the lust of the flesh,
you say, hold on a minute, it doesn't pass the test, amen?
You ever hear somebody say, I love Jesus, and they're out there living like the devil?
And they say, I love Jesus.
You say, hold on a minute.
You know what James says?
Out of the mouth, you can't, look, the water doesn't come forth with bitter and sweet,
right?
Amen?
And so we begin to think about how all these things, and we say, listen, the Bible says
I'm going to claim the promise, God says that if I walk in the Spirit, I'm not going
to fulfill the lust of the flesh.
Ye shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
Does it mean you might have to go pray more?
Does it mean you got, absolutely, depending on God.
I cannot do this in my own self, my own flesh.
My flesh wants to respond a certain way, right?
We're driving the other day.
This guy tried to, I mean, he almost ran me right off the road.
So I blew my horn.
I wasn't excessive.
Sometimes I'm just being honest.
Sometimes I wish I had one of them kind of horns because I just let them know.
And I try to, I'm working on it, amen?
And so I don't do that.
God's worked in my life.
I'm being honest.
Ten years ago, 15 years ago, 20 years, 25 years ago, man, but I just gave a little,
because I don't want to end up in an accident, so I just gave a little beep, and the guy
got mad.
I mean, he almost ran me over.
Give a little beep, he gets mad.
We come to a green light, he comes to a complete stop.
I mean, complete stop at a green light.
And Holly says, Holly says, she's never said this to me in her entire life, blow your horn
at him.
Hallelujah.
But I didn't.
I don't know what that guy was trying to do.
I know one thing, the enemy was trying to get me in the flash.
And I identified that.
And it's quick, it's amazing how little things...
I don't know what your area of vulnerability is.
I've shared some things transparently with you this morning.
I'm just telling you, we got to develop a plan.
How are we going to live a life of victory?
I don't want to live a defeated Christian life.
You know, as I look at Christianity in America, I feel like, and I'm not trying to be a judge,
I'm just simply saying I see a lot of defeated Christians.
I really do.
And that's not what God's plan is for us.
It's not just that we're holding on until we get to heaven, and listen, I'm looking
forward to get to heaven.
We can live a life of victory here, but sin must be addressed.
Paul in love says to these believers in Corinth, he says, I love you.
I'll gladly spend and be spent for you.
Everything that I'm doing is for your edifying.
And then he deals with this matter of sin, why?
Here's what I know.
I know that I'm saved.
And I know I'm going to heaven.
But I know that it's so sweet to enjoy fellowship with God here on earth.
And I want nothing between my soul and my Savior.
There's no sin, there is no sin that is worth having broken fellowship.
There is no sin worth having broken fellowship.
I'm just telling you this morning, there's nothing that's worth it.
In His presence is fullness of joy, Psalm 1611.
And I'm telling you this morning, as we examine ourselves, we've got to identify it.
We've got to be honest, humble, identify it, confess it, forsake it.
But then can I encourage you to develop a plan?
I gave you five thoughts, you can add to, move around, move, whatever.
But have a plan.
How am I going to have victory?
Because can I tell you this morning that you know you best, and you know your area of vulnerability
better than anyone else.
You just got to be honest about it.
And I'm so thankful this morning that God has told us that sin shall not have dominion
over us.
Remember this verse, I want to end on a really positive note.
Remember this verse, greater is He that's in you than he that is in the world.
And we can have victory.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you so much for loving us.
And God, I know this is something that I need, that we need.
God, that we'd get to the place where we deal with sin, address sin, identify, confess,
forsake, develop a plan to walk in victory.
And God, I believe this morning that the greatest need for every person is to be saved.
And if there's one here that's not sure of heaven, I pray that they would get that settled
this morning.
They'd come and give us an opportunity to take a Bible and show them how they could
know for sure that heaven's their home.
They would not leave here without 100% assurance that heaven is their home.
But for the believers this morning, I pray that they would truly believe that statement,
that there's no sin that's worth broken fellowship.
I don't want to forfeit my fellowship with you for anything.
And God, I pray that you'd help us to have that perspective.
Help us, Lord, to walk in the Spirit and claim that promise that we shall not fulfill the
lust of the flesh.
God, I pray that you'd move...
in work, at this time of invitation, as you've used your word already. Now help us, Lord,
to be doers, to respond in obedience. We'll give you the glory for what you'll do, for
it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Just a moment, Kimberly's going to play on the piano. If you're not sure of heaven this
morning, I mean you're not 100% sure if you were to die today, you'd go to heaven. Mark's
here. If you're a man, we'll take a Bible and show you how you can know for sure that
heaven's your home. Holly's over here. She'll take a Bible. If you're a lady, show you how
you can know for sure that heaven's your home. If you're saved this morning, I hope that
you would grasp that truth, that there's no sin that's worth broken fellowship, and that
you'd allow the Spirit of God to have His way in your heart and life. You'd be doers
of the word and not hearers only. As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.