2 Corinthians 2, we'll be looking at verses 12 down through verse 17 this morning and
finishing up this second chapter as we're studying through the book of 2 Corinthians.
And last week we looked at the preceding text of Scripture in verses 5-11 and in that passage
we dealt with the subject matter that Paul was giving this counsel to the believers in
Corinth and we titled the message forgiveness and the importance of understanding that this
one that had offended had responded to the church discipline.
They had, as we could look through the Scriptures and as best we can tell, they had repented
and God gave through the Apostle Paul instruction to this church with dealing with this individual
and to comfort him and to, well to forgive him and to comfort him and then to confirm
your love toward him.
It was the threefold process that God gave and Paul then said this at the end of verse
9 that he wanted to know whether they'd be obedient in all things.
See the matter was serious and Paul was concerned about the unity of the church in Corinth and
Paul understood that the church was a church, if you read the first letter, that was known
for its divisions and contentions and all that was going on.
It was a carnal church that the enemy was having his way and we find that the Apostle
Paul desired for these believers to be strong in the faith, that he desired that they would
grow in grace and knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ and they would not make
decisions that would make them vulnerable to the attack of the enemy.
As he ends in verse number 11, lest Satan should get an advantage of us for we're not
ignorant of his devices and Paul provided that counsel to the church and what good
counsel it is and as we continue through the text of Scripture we find in verse 12 he says,
furthermore, and so Paul is actually going to pick up a thought that he had kind of left
off for a period of time and begin to address again the situation with him not being in
Corinth as he had given them with regard to his travel plans and he says, furthermore,
when I came to Troas to preach Christ's gospel and a door was opened unto me of the Lord.
And what a blessing to just think about the truth of verse number 12 where Paul was traveling,
he had this purpose in his travel to what?
To preach the gospel because he understood that the gospel is the power of God unto salvation.
There's a man delivering Amazon packages on the same road that we were distributing literature
yesterday and I said, hey, you're delivering packages and I'm delivering the gospel here,
this is for you and he said, man, I love the gospel.
And we got to chat just for a moment and praise the Lord for that opportunity but we are the
bearers of the truth of the gospel and Paul said there was a door that was opened but
I want you to see that Paul dealt with situations and struggles just as we do and he said in
verse 13, I had no rest in my spirit.
There was something that was troubling the Apostle Paul, there was something that was
of concern to the Apostle Paul and I believe this morning that as we study the Bible that
God records certain things for us like this verse of scripture to help us understand that
Paul was a man like we are and he had the same struggles that we deal with and he said,
I had no rest in my spirit, why?
Because I found not Titus my brother and he had been looking for Titus and of course with
regard to the letter that had been sent to the church in Corinth and understanding how
would they receive and how would they respond and Paul was concerned about that.
That was a heavy thing on the heart of Paul and he could not find Titus and therefore
because of the inability on Paul's part to find Titus, notice what it says he did, but
taking my leave of them I went from Fence into Macedonia.
He went looking for Titus, now it's kind of interesting because then Paul's going to give
us some truth in the next several verses that will be the text in which we'll be studying
this morning but what Paul says in verse 12 and 13 triggers a thought in his mind about
the leadership of God and about the ministry that God had called him to that's literally
going to take the next several chapters of space in our Bibles before he gets back to
the meeting with Titus.
He doesn't actually reference him finding Titus until 2 Corinthians 7 verses 5 and 6
and so if you want to call it a parenthetical, it is a big parenthetical that Paul is about
to elaborate on the ministry and I'm so thankful that God called the Apostle Paul and that
God used the Apostle Paul and that we have the opportunity to be able to look at the
perspective and philosophy that God gives to us through these pages of scripture with
regard to the ministry.
Notice that Paul says this in verse 14, now, now thanks be unto God which always causeth
us to triumph in Christ and maketh manifest the savor of his knowledge by us in every
place.
As we look at this portion of scripture this morning, I want to preach a message that I've
simply titled Victory in Jesus and we're all familiar with that song, that song that we
sing, a familiar hymn, Victory in Jesus and I'm so thankful this morning that Paul experienced
victory and that we understand that we too are victors, we have victory because our Savior
is victorious, because he conquered sin, death and the grave, because he's alive forevermore,
because he rules and reigns and because he is victorious, then we as his people, as his
children, we too are victorious.
You know what I find in life?
Not every Christian lives victorious.
There's some Christians that are living defeated lives.
There's some Christians that are living like they're not victors, like they've lost.
There's some Christians that are not experiencing victory regularly in their lives.
Oh, they're experiencing defeat after defeat.
Can I remind you?
The Bible tells us that we're more than conquerors.
We're going to look at the verse in just a moment.
Can I remind you that the Bible tells us, as John is writing in 1 John, yes, we have
many things that we face, but greater is he that is in you than he that is in the world.
We are overcomers.
We are victors.
We're on the victory side.
We find here this morning that Paul is rejoicing because of this victory.
Notice he says, now thanks be unto God.
I mean, he's rejoicing.
And by the way, we ought to rejoice in the victory that is ours.
We ought to rejoice in the fact that we serve a God who is victorious, who always wins,
who is the victor, and he's our Savior.
I'm on the winning side.
How many of you know that song?
I don't know if you've heard that song before.
I never got to see or hear Curtis Hudson preach in person, and I didn't get saved until after
he went home to be with the Lord, but I've heard and read a lot of things about Curtis
Hudson.
And God used Curtis Hudson in a great way.
He was a pastor for a number of years, and then he was the editor of the Sword of the
Lord, and he traveled all around this country and abroad as well, and he would preach and
preach and preach, and God used him in a great way.
And I'm told, and I've heard audio, where he would start singing, I'm on the winning
side.
It is a great thing to know victory in Jesus.
As we look at the text of Scripture this morning and think about this thought for just a few
moments, consider with me, number one, the source of victory.
The source of victory.
It is imperative that we as the people of God acknowledge and always remember the source
of victory.
It says in verse number 14 very plainly, now thanks be unto God, which always causeth us
to triumph in Christ.
You don't have victory because of you.
You have victory because of Jesus.
And it's important that we understand the source of victory.
It's important that we acknowledge, see, when we acknowledge that He is the source of our
victory, that I can have victory in Jesus because of what He's done, then it helps me
to keep a humble perspective in life.
It helps me to stay reliant upon Him, and we find that throughout the Scriptures that
we're encouraged and we're reminded that He is the source of victory.
And we find that the Apostle Paul, notice how he says it, and I've read it already,
but it's so important to reiterate, now thanks be unto God.
Notice this, which always causeth us to triumph, literally to have victory in Christ.
Did you catch that little phrase, which always?
Listen, we ought to always be experiencing victory.
We talk about, we use the pass of the Old Testament from the book of Joshua to talk
about the picture, if you will, of the victorious Christian life.
and the desire that we have as the people of God
to have that victorious Christian life.
We don't want to live in defeat.
We don't want to live in discouragement.
We want to live in victory.
And we find that the source is Jesus.
Notice in Romans chapter eight,
and we'll look at a couple of verses of scripture here
that just no doubt you're familiar with them,
but it's important for us to see them
and understand that Paul, as he was a man
that experienced victory in his life.
In fact, I would say that Paul's life
was marked by victory.
Paul understood what it was to serve the conquering Christ
and understood that Christ was the source
of victory in his life.
In verse 31 of Romans eight, the Bible says this,
what shall we then say to these things?
If God be for us, who can be against us?
He that spared not his own son,
but delivered him up for us all,
how shall he not with him also freely give us all things?
Who shall lay anything to the charge of God's elect?
It is God that justifieth.
Who is he that condemneth?
It is Christ that died, yea, rather, that is risen again,
who is even at the right hand of God,
who always maketh intercession for us.
Who shall separate us from the love of Christ?
Shall tribulation or distress or persecution
or famine or nakedness or peril or sword,
as it is written, for thy sake,
we are killed all the day long.
We are accounted as sheep for the slaughter.
Nay, in all these things we are more
than conquerors noticed through him that loved us.
Who is that?
Well, that's Jesus.
Through him that loved us, for I am persuaded
that neither death nor life nor angels
nor principalities nor powers nor things present
nor things to come nor height nor depth
nor any other creature shall be able to separate us
from the love of God, which is in Christ Jesus, our Lord.
Paul understood what it was to face opposition.
Paul understood what it was to be ridiculed,
to be misunderstood, but Paul understood
he was on the winning side.
Paul understood that he had victory in Jesus.
He understood that though there would be circumstances
and situations that he would face,
he said, who, God is for us and so who can be against us?
He said, in all these things we are more than conquerors
through him that loved us.
He says this in 1 Corinthians chapter 15
as we consider that great passage of scripture
dealing with the resurrection
and oh, what a wonderful glorious truth it is
that Jesus is the first fruits,
that he conquered sin, death and the grave,
that he rose from that buried or that borrowed tomb
and he lives forevermore and what a blessing
to know the truth of the resurrection.
Remember that Paul in this passage of scripture,
there were some that were denying the resurrection
and they were uncertain of the resurrection.
He said, if Christ be not risen,
then our faith is in vain, our preaching is in vain,
but now is Christ risen from the dead.
I mean, it's an awesome passage of scripture
that proves the truth of the resurrection,
but we understand that with the truth of the resurrection
brings hope to God's people, for he's the first fruits
and I will rise and you will rise and what a blessing.
And he says at the end of all of this dealing
with this truth of the resurrection in verse 51
of 1 Corinthians 15, behold, I show you a mystery.
We shall not all sleep, but we shall all be changed.
See, here's the truth, we're not all going to die, why?
There's gonna be a generation that's going to be,
that's gonna be raptured out of here.
I hope it's my generation, amen, hallelujah.
It'd be wonderful, but we all shall be changed.
Notice, in a moment, the twinkling of an eye,
the last trump, for the trumpet shall sound
and the dead shall be raised incorruptible
and we shall be changed.
For this corruptible must put on incorruption
and this mortal must put on immortality.
So when this corruptible shall have put on incorruption
and this mortal shall have put on immortality,
then shall be brought to pass the saying
that is written, death is swallowed up,
what does it say?
In victory, hallelujah.
Oh, death, where is thy sting?
Oh, grave, where is thy victory?
The sting of death is sin,
the strength of sin is the law,
but thanks be to God,
which giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.
He giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.
He is the source.
It's not that I got the victory on my own,
it's not that you get, in fact, we can't.
We can't.
Your flesh will fail you.
The Bible says walk in the spirit
and you shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
You know why we're fulfilling the lust of the flesh?
Because we're not walking in the spirit.
The Bible truth in Galatians chapter five.
But he says, but thanks be to God,
which giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.
Notice in 1 John, I referenced already
the fourth chapter of 1 John,
but I want you to look at a couple of verses
there in the fifth chapter.
The Bible says, and as you're turning to 1 John five,
in 1 John four and verse four,
you're of God, little children,
and overcome them because greater is he that is in you
than he that is in the world.
I'm thankful that I am a child of God.
In fact, the third chapter begins
by talking about what manner of love
the Father hath bestowed upon us
that we should be called the sons of God.
What a blessing.
In chapter five of 1 John,
the Bible says this in verse number four,
for whatsoever is born of God overcometh the world.
And this is the victory that overcometh the world,
even our faith.
Who is he that overcometh the world,
but he that believeth that Jesus is the son of God.
We sing the song, faith is the victory.
Faith is the victory.
It's a familiar song that we sing.
It's found in this verse of scripture,
the truth, the biblical truth
that led the songwriter to write the song.
And we find that it says that we are overcomers,
that we are victorious, that we are conquerors.
The apostle Paul, as he begins writing,
and he mentions about this situation
where he was traveling and this opportunity came
as he went to Troas to preach the gospel,
the door was open, but he had no rest in his spirit.
And he was looking for Titus.
And then as he remembers how God brought all that together,
and even before he pens it in the seventh chapter,
he starts rejoicing in the fact
that God causeth us to victory.
He always causeth us to triumph in Christ.
We see the source of victory to begin verse number 14.
But then as we continue through the text
in 2 Corinthians chapter number two,
we find the scene of victory.
It's actually pretty awesome what the apostle Paul
begins to illustrate for us here.
Notice in the end of verse number 14,
and maketh manifest the savor of his knowledge
by us in every place.
For we are unto God a sweet savor of Christ
in them that are saved.
And in them that perish.
To the one we are the savor of death unto death
and to the other, the savor of life unto life.
He ends verse 16 in who is sufficient for these things.
I'll deal with that in just a moment.
But I believe in this passage of scripture
that the apostle Paul begins to reference something
that the people in Corinth would have been
very familiar with.
What is it that Paul references is the Roman triumph.
And in there, I believe that he references
this Roman triumph in order to assist the believers
in Corinth to understand the victory that we have in Jesus.
The Romans had this Roman triumph that would be given
really like a parade that would be given
to successful generals as they returned from their conquest.
And it was a big deal.
I mean, there was a lot of fanfare,
all sorts of things that were going on.
And when they would do this, they would bring with them,
of course, the soldiers that were fighting
with that Roman general, along with the captives
that they had taken, along with the loot
that they had brought back with them, the bounty,
along with, it is recorded, it is understood,
that the sons of the general, the one that had
that Roman triumph on his behalf because of his conquering,
that his sons would be there with him.
It's kind of an interesting picture.
Now, of course, we are so far removed
that we have to simply look at history
and begin reading and trying to understand.
But these people, these original recipients in Corinth,
they would have been very familiar.
Some of the things that they would do
is they would parade through the town.
They would have this incense that would be burned.
And it's interesting that he makes reference to that
with regard to the savor that is mentioned
in verse 14 and again in verse 16.
And he begins to.
to help the people of God understand the victory
that we have through Christ.
The scene of victory.
Christ is the victor.
And we as His people are walking along with Him.
But as many as received Him,
then gave He power to become the sons of God.
If you're saved this morning, you're a child of God.
And you're on the winning side.
We find that the Apostle Paul is making known here
this truth and helping us understand the scene.
Notice at the end of verse 14,
and maketh manifest the savor of His knowledge
by us in every place.
I'm thankful that God uses us
to make Him known in every place.
You know, we're to make Christ known.
That's what our job is.
That's what our duty is.
And we find that as we understand
that He always causeth us to triumph in Christ,
that He's making manifest,
making known Himself,
the savor of His knowledge,
notice, by us in every place.
Isn't it amazing that God would use us?
It's amazing that God would use us
to make Him known.
Those that know Christ are the ones
that can make Him known.
So that's kind of a simple statement.
It is, but you know how many know Him
that don't take any time to ever try to make Him known.
We can't expect a lost person to make Christ known.
He doesn't know Christ.
It's saved people.
I sent a text to somebody this week.
I don't know if they're saved or not,
but I had some interaction with them,
and I sent them a text,
and I said to them, I said,
I'd love to connect with you,
and I went through a number of things,
and then I said this.
I'd love to be able to sit down and talk to you
and let you know how Christ changed my life.
Why?
Because I can talk to that person personally
about what Christ did for me
and what He could do for them.
See, Paul says we're understanding this truth of victory.
We are more than conquerors through Christ,
and He's using us to make Himself known in every place.
Notice this in verse 15.
He says, for we are unto God a sweet saver of Christ,
and them that are saved and them that perish
unto the one, we're the saver of death unto death,
and to the other, the saver of life unto life.
Interesting verses of Scripture,
but the reality in verses 15 and 16
is we understand that the gospel is the power of God
unto salvation to every one that believeth,
but we understand that not everyone will believe.
Not everyone will believe.
John chapter one says He came to His own,
and His own received Him not,
but as many as received Him.
To them gave He power to become the sons of God,
even them that believe on His name.
Not everyone that hears the name of Jesus
is going to be saved.
You can read through the Old Testament.
You can think about New Testament truth.
You can look at lives throughout the pages of history.
You can look at even modern, our contemporaries,
and we can understand that not everyone
is going to accept the truth of the gospel.
We can understand that you can have children
that are raised in the same home,
with the same parents, with the same teaching.
You can have people that can sit in a church
with the same pastor, with the same preaching,
and you can take one that is going to accept it
and believe it and live it,
and you can take another one that says not for me, sorry,
but I want you to understand
that's because God gave man a free will.
God gave man a free will.
It is not God's will that any man should perish,
but that all should come to repentance.
We see that clearly throughout the scriptures,
and we find that God makes that known to us,
and we understand that,
and therefore, His sacrifice is sufficient
for all of humanity.
We can be absolutely confident
that when we share the gospel with an individual
and say to them that Jesus is the only Savior
and that He can save you,
we can understand that His atonement
and His sacrifice is still sufficient
to save sinners today.
I said to that young man yesterday,
right in the driveway as I talked to him,
I said, listen, for whosoever shall call upon
the name of the Lord shall be saved.
We believe it,
but I was confronted yesterday with the truth
that though that young man understood he was lost,
he understood that what he had believed for years
about his works getting him to heaven
was not true biblically,
and yet he was still not ready to accept Christ
as his Savior.
I can't make Him, and you can't make Him.
In fact, if we force them,
it's probably not really genuine,
and they're probably gonna die and go to hell
having a false hope until they die.
The reality this morning is that our God is victorious,
and we see this scene,
and we see the work that God is doing in every place.
I love the way verse number 14 ends,
in every place.
See, Paul had this passion to go to the regions beyond.
Paul had this passion to go into all the world
to be able to preach the gospel.
Why?
Because he understood that souls needed to hear the truth.
I said this back in December
as I considered some of the truth
from John 1, verses 11 and 12
about those that received Him not
and those that did receive Him,
that the reality is that there are far too many people
in our community today that do not even know
that they have a choice to receive Him or not.
They're not even aware of the very truth
that Jesus died for them and He loves them,
and we have an opportunity in every place
to make Christ known.
And as Paul would paint this scene for us,
reminded this morning of this truth,
look at Colossians 2.
I love this portion of scripture in Colossians 2,
dealing with the resurrection and all that Christ did,
and we find that His sacrifice was sufficient.
It says in Colossians 2, in verse 14,
blotting out the handwriting of ordinances
that was against us, which was contrary to us,
and took it out of the way, nailing it to His cross.
Man, hallelujah.
But then notice verse 15.
And having spoiled principalities and powers,
He made a show of them openly,
triumphing over them in it.
The devil was defeated at Calvary.
I believe that the devil thought
he was victorious at Calvary.
He did everything he could.
I mean, for centuries, he did everything he could
to destroy the line, the Messianic line.
He did everything that he could to corrupt the line.
You look at all the various aspects of the Old Testament,
you look at all these things that are going on,
and you find that Satan is trying to infiltrate
and to annihilate and to cause the fact
that Messiah would not be able to come.
But all of those plans were, they were just fruitless.
I mean, they could not.
I think about the events of Christ's life
and many times in which the religious leaders
sought to stone Jesus and kill Jesus
in a storm that was so violent
that the men who had been fishermen all their lives
said, Master, carest thou not that we perish?
But through all of that, Jesus was gonna go to that cross.
And in the Garden of Gethsemane,
as He's in great affliction
and dealing with all of that pressure,
I believe that when He prays,
to let that cup pass,
and when He says, let thy will be done,
I don't believe that Jesus was praying
for one moment to not go to the cross.
Because Jesus knew that He came to go to the cross.
He talked about it openly.
He knew that was necessary.
In fact, as you read Hebrews chapter number 12,
He went to that cross willingly,
understanding what would be accomplished
through that substitutionary atonement.
In verse number two, it says this,
excuse me, verse number, yeah, I'll use verse number two,
who for the joy that was set before Him endured the cross.
The joy that was set before Him.
He wasn't praying to get out of going to the cross.
I believe Satan was trying to kill Him in the garden
before He could ever get to the cross.
But He went to that cross,
and He was buried in that borrowed tomb,
and He rose, conquering sin, death, and the grave,
and our enemy was defeated once for all.
And according to Colossians chapter two,
God, the Lord Jesus Christ,
spoiled principalities and powers,
and He made a show of them openly.
triumphing over them in it.
I think Paul had the same thought in mind here
as he did in 2 Corinthians 2.
I'm reminded of 1 John 3 in verse number eight.
I'll read the verse for you
and we'll get back to our passage in 2 Corinthians.
But the Bible says this
in 1 John 3 in verse number eight.
He that committed the sins of the devil
for the devil sinneth from the beginning.
For this purpose the Son of God was manifested
that he might destroy the works of the devil.
We see the source of victory.
We see the scene of victory.
But as we go back to 2 Corinthians chapter number two,
I believe that we see the strategy for victory.
The strategy for victory.
Now, before you get too ahead of yourself,
I'm not being contradictory.
The source is Jesus.
But understand that if we want to experience the victory,
we must do it his way.
God's work must be done God's way.
It's a truth throughout the scriptures.
So vitally important.
We come to this passage and we find that in verse 16,
as we consider the strategy for victory,
that Paul ends the verse of scripture by saying this,
who is sufficient for these things?
Apart from Christ, none of us are sufficient.
He does not answer the question until the third chapter.
We'll look at it in more detail next week.
But notice in verse number five of chapter three,
not that we are sufficient of ourselves
to think anything as of ourselves,
but our sufficiency is of God.
Our sufficiency is of God.
Then notice what he says in verse 17.
As we think about this strategy here,
the Bible says that for we are not as many
which corrupt the word of God,
but as of sincerity, but as of God,
in the sight of God speak we in Christ.
You know what Paul's saying in verse number 17?
He's making a contrast and a distinction
between the ministry that Paul was engaged in
and the ministry that he's going to be speaking about
for several chapters now.
And what a joy it is, again,
to understand the philosophy and perspective
of ministry that is outlined in these chapters
in the book of 2 Corinthians.
But he's making this contrast and this distinction
between his ministry and the ministry of false teachers.
The ministry of those that were corrupting the word of God,
the ministry of those that were going out
and they were trying to use the scriptures
to say something that they did not say
in order to have some level of control over individuals
and in order that they might profit with all.
And Paul says, no, no, no, that's not me.
That's not us.
We don't corrupt the word of God.
We understand that Paul taught and was very plain
in giving the instruction of the importance
of preaching what?
The word.
He was not one that was going to try
to manipulate the word of God
and make it say something that it did not say
so that he might profit.
No, that was not his approach to ministry.
Why was that not his approach to ministry?
Well, because he stood before God.
Remember we talked about in our study
in chapter number one when you're misunderstood
and we talked about the fact that Paul
had this clear conscience, he examined himself,
he understood what it was to live in the presence of God.
He understood what it was to be accountable to God.
We find that Paul says, no, that's not how we do ministry.
In fact, when he's there
and during the first missionary journey,
if you read through the scriptures,
they're ready to make sacrifices on the behalf of Paul.
I mean, they're ready to worship Paul
and they're ready to get,
I think they could give Paul whatever Paul asked for
and Paul says, no, no, no.
I mean, I'm here to declare the real, the true God,
the living God, that's what I'm here for.
God used Paul to see many people saved.
God used Paul to see many churches established.
God used Paul to see people healed of infirmities
and all that took place.
And yet Paul never sought to benefit from those things.
He simply pointed people to Jesus.
And that's where you see the strategy.
Why was Paul, why did he,
why was his life a life that was marked by victory?
Well, he understood that the source of victory
is the Lord Jesus Christ.
And now thanks be unto God,
which always causeth us to triumph in Christ.
But he understood that there was an important aspect
of ministry and how we serve the Lord
and the victory that we can have.
And he says in verse 17,
we are not as many which corrupt the word of God,
but as of sincerity,
the reality is that we must live in full dependence,
as he said, who is sufficient for these things?
Not me, not you, our sufficiency is of God.
But we also understand that there must be integrity,
there must be sincerity.
What does God's word say?
That's what we're gonna live by.
Let God be true and every man a liar.
The Bereans are commended, why?
Because they search the scriptures daily,
whether these things be.
Listen, we're in a place where I encourage people
to read their Bibles.
We give you a daily reading Bible schedules,
we provide you with an admonition,
an instruction, an encouragement,
read the scriptures, dig in the Bible, read God's word.
If I was preaching something contrary
to what this book taught,
I wouldn't encourage you to read the Bible
because I'd be exposed as a fraud.
You know, there are some denominations historically
that would forbid their people from reading the Bible.
Why?
Because as long as they could keep a distinction
and a separation between them and the people,
they had a level of control.
You read it historically, I'm not making it up.
You can read it historically.
In fact, I made this statement years ago.
It was probably 12 and a half years ago, 13 years ago.
I was teaching right down here on a Wednesday evening
and I was teaching on sound doctrine
and I made this statement about denominations
that simply did not encourage people to read the Bible.
That was the terminology that I used.
And Marianne Cook came up to me after the service
and she said, pastor, I want you to understand,
it wasn't that they didn't encourage us,
they forbid us from reading the Bible.
She said, I remember as a little girl,
I remember mentioning in my school that I read the Bible
and I had my knuckles smacked with rulers.
Because I read the Bible.
No, no, we encourage you to read the Bible.
You need to read the Bible.
You ought to get a good Bible message from this pulpit
every time I open the Bible.
It's my job to feed the flock of God.
But what I give you from this pulpit
is not enough for you all week.
It's just not.
And Paul says that he understood at the end of verse 17
that in the sight of God, speak we in Christ.
Paul understood who the authority was.
Paul understood that he was in submission to God Almighty
and that God was the one that had called him.
He mentions it in chapter number one,
Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God.
And he understood that it was God who equipped him.
It was God who had taught him.
You read Galatians one.
This teaching that he was giving
was not something that he learned of many,
but he learned it by Jesus Christ,
of the revelation of Jesus Christ
is the way that he mentions it in Galatians one.
And the reality this morning is that he says,
in the sight of God, speak we in Christ.
That's a heavy statement if you're manipulating someone.
But if you're not manipulating,
if you're preaching with sincerity,
you're not corrupting the word of God,
you freely let people know,
listen, I'm doing this in the sight of God.
We know it's true whether you're corrupting or not.
God sees and knows everything.
But the reality this morning is that Paul says,
listen, this is the strategy for victory.
He's the source of victory.
I must live in full dependence upon him.
I must operate with integrity and with sincerity.
And I must trust him for the victory that only he can give.
Can remind you this morning
of two Old Testament passages of scripture.
Joshua chapter number seven and Judges chapter number seven.
Oftentimes we look at the book of Joshua as being,
again, as I mentioned earlier in the message this morning,
being a picture of the victorious Christian life.
And certainly it is.
I understand there's some hymns from old years
and there's some preachers from old years
that would say that the book of Joshua
is a picture of heaven.
I cannot disagree with that more
than I'm disagreeing with it right now.
It's not a picture of heaven
because there is sin in the book of Joshua.
There is no sin in heaven.
There is war in the book of Joshua.
There is no war in heaven.
It is not a picture of heaven.
You say, but so-and-so pastor said it was.
I'm sorry, okay?
This is not a picture of heaven.
It is a picture of the victorious Christian life.
You know what happens in the victorious Christian life?
You have victory,
but you have constant enemies coming after you.
You can have victory.
You know, the only defeat they had was an AI.
You study the whole book of Joshua,
the only defeat they had was an AI.
And I believe there's one main reason for that defeat,
but there's also a secondary reason.
The main reason is sin in the camp.
That's a great example for all of us.
If we're sin,
We're not going to have the victory that God has provided for us.
But we see also that there was a measure of self-dependence.
In Joshua chapter 7 and verse number 3, the Bible says that they returned to Joshua.
Joshua sent them out to go and to spy out, to check out what was going on, to view the
country according to verse 2.
And the Bible says that they come back and here's what they say, let not all the people
go up, but let about 2,000 or 3,000 men go up and smite AI, and make not all the people
to labor that thither, for they are but few.
Can I tell you, that was a mistake.
Sin in the camp is the primary reason for defeat.
But the secondary reason was self-dependence.
Joshua, don't make all of us go, I mean we can handle this one.
You know what happens in your life?
You start getting self-dependent.
You experience some victory.
You know what happened in the life, in the book of Joshua?
They had experienced some victory.
They experienced some victory.
You know what happens in your life when you experience victory?
All of a sudden you think, I can be victorious.
And I forget the fact that it was God who made me victorious.
I forget the source.
And I violate the strategy.
And I suffer defeat.
If you look through the Scripture, some of the most difficult days for God's people
were on the heels of victory.
On the heels of victory.
Why is that so?
Because it's when we become most self-dependent.
Look at what we were able to see done.
I mean, look at this.
This is awesome.
And we start thinking, we did this.
And then we enter the next one and we find out real fast.
Defeat.
See Joshua 7 is an important reminder for us.
Judges chapter 7, the life of Gideon, we're familiar with again, two passages that we're
familiar with.
I just want to remind you of what the Lord says to Gideon in Judges chapter number 7.
In verse number 2, the Bible says, and the Lord said unto Gideon, the people that are
with thee are too many for me to give the Midianites into their hands.
Why?
Why was it too many?
Lest Israel vaunt themselves against me, saying, Mine own hand hath saved me.
You know what a danger is for us?
We think we did it.
Forget the source.
Verse 7, the Lord said unto Gideon, by the 300 men that lapped will I save you and deliver
the Midianites into thine hand and let all the other people go every man unto his place.
You know what God did?
God gave them a victory that could only be explained as God did it.
There's no other way to explain it but to say God did it.
And that's what God wants in our lives.
He wants us to have victory, but He wants us to acknowledge as Paul did, we are more
than conquerors through Him that loved us.
But thanks be to God which giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.
You see, Paul was opposed, Paul was misunderstood, yet he knew victory came through Christ and
he was rejoicing.
He started the passage with thanks, with rejoicing.
He says, now thanks be unto God which always causeth us to triumph in Christ.
I wonder this morning, are you experiencing victory in your life?
Are you experiencing victory in your life?
I mean, day by day, you're experiencing victory.
You've seen the song, Victory in Jesus.
And we understand that one day we will see Him face to face and what a glorious day that
will be.
But understand with me here today, God wants you to be victorious today and tomorrow and
the next day and He wants you to have victory.
He's provided for you.
He is the source of victory.
He does not want His people to live defeated lives.
You say, but pastor, we have an enemy.
Yes, we do.
The Bible says that we can quench all the fiery darts of the enemy with that shield
of faith.
Is the Bible true?
Absolutely.
It's what it says.
The Bible says we're to take the sword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God.
We have victory through Jesus.
He's given us all that we need to have victory.
But what makes me so sad is I know so many Christians.
I know so many Christians that are living lives of defeat and yet victory is available.
Victory is available.
They're not surrendering.
They're not yielding.
They're walking in the flesh, not in the Spirit, and they're living defeated lives.
Can I tell you this morning, that's not what God intends for you.
He intends that you'd be victorious.
Victory in Jesus.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
I pray, God, that you would help each of us to regularly experience victory in our lives.
Or maybe somebody this morning, just living defeated, defeated lives, oh, God, would you
help them?
Would you help them this morning to understand that we're more than conquerors through Him
that loved us?
Would you help them this morning to understand the source of victory and the strategy, the
importance of surrender and dependence and integrity and sincerity?
We no longer would live defeated lives.
God, would you work in hearts and lives as only you can?
Maybe there's one that's not saved.
Maybe one day they need to come and ask the Lord Jesus Christ to be their Savior.
And I pray that you'd move and work in that life as only you can.
I pray that in these moments, that you would have your will and way, and we'll thank you
for it.
In Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Holly's going to play quietly on the piano.
As Holly plays, the altar is open.