of Joel. I understand when I made the announcement this morning that Joel was pretty excited
and actually I don't know if he was or wasn't, but preaching from the book of Joel, he seemed
like it was quite a surprise. And to be looking at the first several verses of this chapter,
it's quite interesting. The book of Joel is one of the oldest of the minor prophets and
it is written really predominantly, much of the context is dealing with Judah more than
Israel, but it's before the Assyrian captivity of Israel, it's before the Babylonian captivity
of Judah. In fact, the date of the writing is somewhere about 100, 110 years prior to
the Assyrian captivity of the nation of Israel. And so we find the age of this prophecy is
one of the first of the written prophecies we see here in the minor prophets. And it's
interesting when you begin to think about the content, we'll be just looking at the
first chapter, we're not studying through the book of Joel this evening, but it's interesting
for a theme throughout the book is the day of the Lord and really looking as far forward
from eschatology and looking at the tribulation of the day of the Lord and all of that. And
so it's quite interesting when you think about the eschatological calendar and how that one
of the oldest written prophets all the way through the day of the Lord. And what a blessing
and someone's phone is competing. Amen. I can talk louder than that Siri or whoever
that is. Amen. Ron's like, I am so sorry, but it's not my phone. Amen. And so this happened
to me many years ago, brother Ron, and I was in our church in Pennsylvania and I was sitting
right on the second row in our chair. It was kind of an auditorium where they kind of had
a, the center aisle was straight and then there were two side aisles and sitting right
over there. And Holly's phone started ringing and Holly was in the nursery and I was stone
cold, man. I didn't move. Ron was kind of like, how can I help you? I just kept on listening
to the preacher and I'm listening to the preacher and pastor says, he stops. He says, Chris,
is that your phone? No, sir. I mean, just, and he just, and Juliana's like, but daddy,
it's mommy's phone. It's not my phone. Amen. It is her phone. In this particular instance,
the two are not one, amen. But in any case, so I know, I know how it is, you know, it
doesn't matter what button you push. None of them seem to do anything, you know. But
Joel chapter number one will be the focus this evening. And you know, it's interesting
as you read the Bible in particular, thinking about the old Testament this evening, you
find periods of time in the record, in the history of the nation of Israel where there's
great rejoicing. And you see just amazing events and the rejoicing of the people, the
revivals in Judah. And you can read about the revivals and you can think about the rejoicing
and you find that there are times, no doubt, that the people of God had great joy. There
are times, however, that as you read through the old Testament, that you'll find that that
joy is missing. The joy's not there. And such is the case here in Joel chapter number one
as we're looking at what's going on here. In fact, we find that in verse number 12,
the Bible says this at the latter part, because joy is withered away from the sons of men.
And you read just a few verses down in verse number 16, notice what it says, is not the
meat cut off before our eyes? Yea, joy and gladness from the house is withered away.
Of our God. It's interesting even as I made comment this morning in Psalm 85 in verse
number 6 with the plea really for revival, that it's directly related to the subject
of rejoicing. Wilt thou not revive us again that thy people may rejoice in thee? The word
rejoice really, rejoicing is the outward expression of that inward joy. And we find as we begin
to look at this passage of scripture and consider from a national perspective as we get near
the end of the message, we'll deal with it from a personal perspective, but we could
ask the question, what is it that would cause the joy to wither away? And once we are able
to identify what it is that would cause the joy to wither away, we then ask the question,
is how can that joy be restored? Can the joy be restored? I'm thankful that the answer
to that question is yes, a resounding yes, the joy absolutely can be restored. And we
find that as we look at this portion of scripture, I'm mindful as we would make application this
evening in our own lives, I've often said over the years that really the most miserable
person that you'll ever meet is a backslidden Christian. You know, the most miserable person
is not the lost person. There are lost people that are miserable, but there are some that
don't even know that they're lost and what's all at stake. They just are completely blinded
to it. But you think about a saved person that's a backslidden. They know what to do.
They know what is right, but they're not doing right. They're not walking with God. They've
grieved and quenched the Spirit of God. The joy is missing from that person and they become
miserable. We find here in Joel, as we'll look at these first 14 verses, I've titled
the message, joy is withered away there from verse number 12. But I want you to notice
with me if you're taking notes, notice the situation. I'm going to read through and make
comment. The Bible says the word of the Lord that came to Joel, the son of Pethuel. Now
it's interesting as many of the prophets would begin and it speaks about the source of the
prophecy. It's the word of the Lord. This is God's word. And we understand all Scripture
is given by inspiration of God. And we find that He's now going to begin to describe for
us and help us to understand the situation in which they were dealing with. It says,
hear this, ye old men, and give ear all ye inhabitants of the land. Hath this been in
your days or even in the days of your fathers? I notice in verse number two, the uniqueness
of the situation. You find that this situation is so dire that the verse begins by asking
this question, or the book begins with asking this question, hath this been in your days
or even in the days of your fathers? I mean, what is about to be described here, the situation
that is going to be unfolded for us in this passage of Scripture, we see the uniqueness
of the situation. And the book says, has it been in your days or even in the days of your
fathers? You know, I think about our own nation and I think about some applications that we
can make and we see some things that are taking place in our world and in our society. And
we can say, has this ever happened in our days? Have we ever seen this magnitude of
problem? Has it been in our fathers' days? We know that the world has been wicked. We
understand that all the way back in the book of Genesis that Sodom and Gomorrah was destroyed
because of the wickedness of man. And even before that, we see the flood that God brought
upon the world because of the wickedness of man. But we see some things that are going
on and we begin to evaluate those things. And here in the timeline and the circumstances
and we find the uniqueness of the situation that Joel, under the inspiration of God Almighty,
says half this has been in your days or even in the days of your fathers. And then he tells
them this, tell ye your children of it and let your children tell their children and
their children another generation. And you think about the way in which the uniqueness
again of the situation that it was going to be so unique and it was going to be so intense
and such a dire set of circumstances that it would be something that would be talked
about for generations. That's pretty amazing. Notice in verse number 4, it says that which
the palmer worm hath left hath the locust eaten and that which the locust hath left
hath the canker worm eaten and that which the canker worm hath left hath the caterpillar
eaten. You see the level of destruction. Maybe we've handled one level of this situation
that's come and we've dealt with the palmer worm but now the prophecy says no, after the
palmer worm, whatever they've left, now the locust. And after the locust is done, then
the canker worm and then the caterpillar. And you see this progression and you see the
utter destruction. It's a unique set of circumstances, it's a unique situation, but there's utter
destruction and we find that this idea will continue to unfold for us in the next several
verses as we see the extent of the destruction. It's interesting that in verse number 5, it's
an interesting verse of scripture. The Bible says, awake ye drunkards and weep and how
all ye drinkers of wine. It helps us to really get a glimpse into the drunkenness that was
prevalent in those days and to see what was taking place. But notice what it says, because
of the new wine, for it is cut off from your mouth, the destruction that was coming, it
would destroy the vineyards, thus leading to no wine. And he's saying even to these
drunkards he's saying, awake! I mean, consider that this which you have been given to, that
because of the extent of this destruction that is coming, you're not even going to be
able to have your wine because it's going to be destroyed. The vineyards are going to
be destroyed. We find that in verses 6 and 7.
and also in v. 10 and 11,
we see the extent of the destruction.
Notice what it says,
"'For a nation has come up upon My land,
strong and without number,
whose teeth are the teeth of a lion,
and he hath the cheek-teeth of a great lion.
He hath laid My vine waste
and barked My fig tree.
He hath made it clean, bare,
and cast it away.'"
Notice, the branches thereof are made white.
V. 10,
"'The field is wasted.
The land mourneth,
for the corn is wasted,
the new wine is dried up,
the oil languisheth.'"
It says this in v. 11,
"'Be ye ashamed,
O ye husbandmen, how!
O ye vinedressers,
for the wheat and for the barley.'"
Why?
Because the harvest of the field is perished.
You see, the extent of the destruction,
the uniqueness of the situation,
the utter destruction that is revealed to us
in these verses of Scripture,
and we find that as we continue
really analyzing this passage,
you find that not only would they be affected personally,
not only would even those that were given to wine
be affected as it's mentioned in v. 5,
but tragically, even the offerings
in the house of the Lord would cease.
Why?
Because they don't have the production
in order to bring these offerings.
Notice it says in v. 9,
"'The meat offering and the drink offering
is cut off from the house of the Lord.
The priests of the Lord's ministers mourn.'"
Wow.
When you read these verses of Scripture,
you say, this is a bad situation.
I mean, this is dire.
In v. 12, it says,
"'The vine is dried up,
and the fig tree languisheth,
the pomegranate tree,
the palm tree, also in the apple tree,
and even all the trees of the field are withered,
because joy is withered away from the sons of men.'"
I want to consider as we think about
this description that is given to us
and we note the situation that is explained
in these verses of Scripture,
I would submit to you this evening
that no doubt this situation is the direct result of sin.
It's the result of sin.
Hold your place here in Joel
because we'll be back here in just a few minutes,
but go over to the book of Leviticus, if you will,
in the 26th chapter.
Leviticus 26.
It's just a little bit before 630.
There are 46 verses in this chapter,
and I'm going to be honest with you,
I don't know where to cut it off.
I'm going to read the entire thing
because it's necessary.
Because we're going to see that this situation in Joel
is the direct result of sin.
In Leviticus 26, I want you to notice
the positive nature of the first 13 verses
of this chapter.
If you were to divide it,
really you would divide Leviticus 26
in verses 1-13,
and then in verses 14 through the end of the chapter.
But I want you to notice what it says.
"...Ye shall make you no idols or a graven image,
neither rear you up a standing image,
neither shall you set up any image of stone in your land
to bow down unto it,
for I am the Lord your God.
You shall keep My Sabbaths
and reverence My sanctuary.
I am the Lord."
And then notice the first word of v. 3.
If.
That's conditional, correct?
If ye walk in My statutes
and keep My commandments and do them,
what's the first word of v. 4?
Then.
This is a classic if-then promise
in the Word of God.
There are several of them in Proverbs 2.
We see here in Leviticus
that there are several throughout the entire Bible,
but here in Leviticus 26,
a classic if-then.
If ye do this,
then God says,
God Almighty,
the Creator and Sustainer of the universe,
the Ruler of all things,
says,
here's what I'm going to do.
Your responsibility?
Walk in My statutes,
keep My commandments,
and do them.
Then, I, again, the Creator God,
I will give you rain in due season.
And the land shall yield her increase
and the trees of the field
shall yield their fruit.
Was that happening in Joel 1?
No.
Continue.
V. 5,
And your threshing shall reach unto the vintage,
and the vintage shall reach unto the sowing time,
and ye shall eat your bread to the full
and dwell in your land safely.
And I will give peace in the land,
and ye shall lie down,
and none shall make you afraid.
And I will rid evil beasts out of the land,
neither shall the sword go through your land.
And ye shall chase your enemies,
and they shall fall before you by the sword.
And five of you shall chase an hundred,
and an hundred of you shall put ten thousand to fight,
and your enemies shall fall before you by the sword.
For I will have respect unto you
and make you fruitful
and multiply you
and establish My covenant with you.
And ye shall eat old store
and bring forth the old because of the new.
And I will set My tabernacle among you,
and My soul shall not abhor you.
And I will walk among you
and will be your God,
and ye shall be My people.
I am the Lord your God,
which brought you forth out of the land of Egypt,
that you should not be their bondmen,
and I have broken the bands of your yoke
and made you go upright."
Isn't that awesome?
You say, man, I'm signing up for that.
Amen?
I want that.
I want verse 4 through verse 13.
Then, I want all of it.
I don't want part of it.
I don't want half of it.
I want all of it.
Amen?
I want the blessing of God.
I want God's favor.
I want God to walk among us.
I want God to be welcomed in my home
in our church
and to have that sweet communion and fellowship
that we spoke of this morning.
I want God's blessing.
It's dependent upon our obedience.
It's an if-then promise.
And verse 14 begins with this word,
but.
I would encourage you,
I have it in my Bible.
I have circled verse 3, if.
I have circled verse 4, then.
And I have circled verse 14, but.
If ye do this, then, God says,
not Moses says I'm going to do all these things.
No, God Almighty, the omnipotent,
omniscient God says I will do all these things,
but, verse 14.
And then you see that word again, if.
But if ye will not hearken unto Me
and will not do all these commandments,
and if ye shall despise My statutes,
or if your soul abhor My judgments
so that you will not do all My commandments,
and that you break My commandment,
notice, I also will do this unto you.
Now, I'm going to tell you,
you don't want to read verses 16-46.
You don't want any of it.
But God is gracious to tell His people
what the consequences are.
God was faithful to give the commandments, was He not?
Amen.
He is faithful to give His Word.
In Deuteronomy, we find that Moses says,
listen, His Word is not far off.
No, no, His Word is nigh unto thee.
I'm thankful that we have the Bible.
The Word of God.
And God says if you do this,
then I'm going to do this.
Praise God for the first part of Leviticus 26.
But if you refuse, if you disobey,
if you abhor, if you despise,
then He says in the same way,
the same promise,
the same magnitude of the promise of v. 4,
He gives in v. 16,
I also will do this unto you.
I will even appoint over you terror,
consumption,
the burning egg-yew
that shall consume the eyes
and cause sorrow of heart.
And you shall sow your seed in vain,
for your enemies shall eat it.
I will set My face against you,
and you shall be slain before your enemies.
They that hate you shall reign over you,
and you shall flee when none pursueth you.
And if you will not yet for all this hearken unto Me,
then I will punish you seven times more for your sins.
What's He saying?
I'm going to do these things,
and the purpose is to bring you back to Me.
Right? That you would return unto Me.
That chastening that we speak about as a believer.
Whom the Lord loveth, He chasteneth.
And we understand that not only in Proverbs,
that's an Old Testament and New Testament principle.
Whom the Lord loveth, He chasteneth.
And you find it in Proverbs.
You find it in Hebrews.
And you say, listen, God is doing something
to get our attention.
To bring us back to Him.
And He says, if I do all of these things,
and you still, for all of this,
it says, and if you will not yet for all this
hearken unto Me,
then I will punish you seven times more for your sins.
V. 19,
And I will break the pride of your power,
and I will make your heaven as iron,
and your earth as brass.
And your strength shall be spent in vain,
for your land shall not yield her increase,
neither shall the trees of the land yield their fruits.
And if you walk contrary unto Me,
and will not hearken unto Me,
I will bring seven times more.
seven times more plagues upon you
according to your sins.
I will also send wild beasts among you
which shall rob you of your children
and destroy your cattle
and make you few in number,
and your highways shall be desolate.
And if you will not be reformed by Me
by these things,
but will walk contrary unto Me,
then will I also walk contrary unto you
and will punish you yet seven times more
for your sins."
You say, we don't have to read anymore.
Really, honestly.
That's enough.
There's 20-plus more verses.
God is holy.
Notice v. 25,
And I will bring a sword upon you
that shall avenge the quarrel of My covenant.
And when you are gathered together
within your cities,
I will send the pestilence among you,
and you shall be delivered into the hand of the enemy.
When I have broken the staff of your bread,
men and women shall bake your bread in one oven
and they shall deliver you your bread again by weight,
and you shall eat and not be satisfied.
And if you will not for all this
hearken unto Me, but walk contrary unto Me,
then I will walk contrary unto you also in fury,
and I even I will chastise you seven times for your sins.
It's almost like if I could use this analogy,
God's just turning up the heat on the oven.
Right? You understand what I'm saying?
Why? Because God wants us to return to Him.
God's not doing these things.
He's not telling them this is going to be the consequence
because He's a mean, angry God.
No, He wants His people to return to Him.
And He's saying, here's what I'm going to do.
I'm going to make you uncomfortable.
I'm going to bring judgment.
I'm going to do these things.
And through these things,
it ought to be a wake-up call of,
man, I need to examine what's going on.
Why are we dealing with these problems?
Why do we have these troubles?
This is the hand of God.
And if you read it in 2 Chronicles 7,
which I touched on this morning,
and you read all that's taking place,
and really when you connect that with Nehemiah,
when Nehemiah prays,
Nehemiah is praying according to the Word of God.
Nehemiah says, God, You said that if we're in this condition
and we turn to You and we pray and we seek Your face,
that You will do this.
What's Nehemiah doing?
He's saying, God, I'm taking You at Your Word.
I am praying Your Word back to You
and this is what we're doing.
Notice in verse 29,
and you shall eat the flesh of your sons,
and the flesh of your daughters shall you eat.
You can read of that in 2 Kings.
The one woman boiled her son and they ate him
and the next woman was going to do it the next day
and they were going to eat him and she didn't
and it was a big problem for the king.
That's terrible.
Verse 30, and I will destroy your high places
and cut down your images
and cast your carcasses upon the carcasses of your idols
and My soul shall abhor you
and I will make your cities waste
and bring your sanctuaries unto desolation
and I will not smell the savor of your sweet odors
and I will bring the land into desolation
and your enemies which dwell therein
shall be astonished at it
and I will scatter you among the heathen
and will draw out a sword after you
and your land shall be desolate and your cities waste.
Can I ask you, did God do that?
Sure He did.
Babylonian captivity.
It's exactly what happened.
Why? Because for all of this, they returned not.
Verse 34, then shall the land enjoy her sabbaths
as long as it lieth desolate,
ye be in your enemies' land,
even then shall the land rest and enjoy her sabbaths.
That's why it was a 70 year captivity
for the nation of Judah in Babylon.
That's why Jeremiah, through the inspiration of God,
was preaching about 70 years.
And that's why Daniel understood in Daniel 9 or 10,
he understood by reading of the books
that 70 years were accomplished.
That 70 years was directly related
to what we're reading here in Leviticus 26
because of the land not having her sabbaths.
Verse 35, as long as it lieth desolate,
it shall rest because it did not rest in your sabbaths
when you dwelt upon it.
And upon them that are left alive of you,
I will send a faintness into your hearts
and the lands of their enemies
and the sound of a shaken leaf shall chase them
and they shall flee as fleeing from a sword
and they shall fall when none pursueth
and they shall fall one upon another
as it were before a sword when none pursueth
and you shall have no power to stand before your enemies
and you shall perish among the heathen
and the land of your enemies shall eat you up.
And they that are left of you shall pine away
in their iniquity in your enemies' lands
and also in the iniquities of their fathers
shall they pine away with them
if they shall confess their iniquity
and the iniquity of their fathers with their trespass
which they trespassed against me
and that also they have walked contrary unto me
and that I also have walked contrary unto them
and have brought them into the land of their enemies.
If then their uncircumcised hearts be humbled
and they then accept of the punishment of their iniquity,
then will I remember my covenant with Jacob
and also my covenant with Isaac
and also my covenant with Abraham
will I remember and I will remember the land.
You read Daniel's prayer in Daniel chapter number nine,
it's exactly related to what we're reading in Leviticus 26.
Verse 43, the land also shall be left of them
and shall enjoy her sabbaths
while she lieth desolate without them
and they shall accept of the punishment of their iniquity
because even because they despised my judgments
and because their soul abhorred my statutes
and yet for all that when they be in the land
of their enemies, I will not cast them away,
neither will I abhor them to destroy them utterly
and to break my covenant with them
for I am the Lord their God.
But I will for their sakes
remember the covenant of their ancestors
whom I brought forth out of the land of Egypt
in the sight of the heathen that I might be their God,
I am the Lord.
These are the statutes and judgments and laws
which the Lord made between him
and the children of Israel in Mount Sinai
by the hand of Moses.
I understand that as we look at the book of Joel
and I understand that as we look at the passage here
in Leviticus chapter number 26,
I understand the context
and I understand being written to Israel
and I understand that listen, America is not Israel.
I understand all of those things.
But the reality is that our God changes not.
The reality is that our God is a holy God.
The reality is that we have,
we understand that the righteous God
loveth righteousness and he will exalt a righteous nation
but he will bring low a sinful nation.
And we find that these principles,
these truths that we find in the word of God
are impactful and helpful for us to understand.
And so as we begin to evaluate what's taking place here
in the book of Joel in the first chapter
and we notice this situation that is unfolding for us
and we say, listen, somebody needs to wake up here.
Somebody needs to understand
that this is the judgment of God.
Righteousness exalteth a nation
but sin is a reproach to any people.
That verse does not say righteousness exalteth Israel
and sin is a reproach to Israel.
It says righteousness exalteth a nation
and sin is a reproach to any people.
Therefore, I believe that we can take
and apply the truth of Proverbs 14.34 in our own lives.
And we begin to think about this situation
and we begin to understand from Joel chapter number one
as we analyze and understand what's going on here,
we would conclude that this is the result of sin.
The result of sin.
I wonder, as we think about all of the things
that have taken place in our nation,
it seems as if there's a lack of a turning to God.
I remember, I shared this with somebody just a few days ago,
but I remember September 11th, 2001.
I remember exactly where I was.
Many of you do as well.
You remember that day and all that took place.
There's something interesting that happened after that day.
There were people looking for church houses to go to.
There really were.
There was an increase in church attendance
shortly after those attacks.
People that just wanted to go pray.
People that didn't go to church.
People that didn't pray, but because of the circumstances,
because of the situation.
But you look at what's happened
in the last 18 months in America,
not just with COVID, but with all of the stuff
that's gone on.
There are fewer people in church today,
by far, across the board, by far.
We see a nation that is saying,
what can we do to fix these problems?
What is the cause of these troubles,
global warming, or some other excuse, reason,
anything to not acknowledge the judgment of God?
America, I believe, is a nation
that is ripe for the judgment of God.
Do you understand that historically,
if you look at the nations of the world,
that our nation, though we have plenty of problems
and we've had plenty of problems,
our nation is unique compared to many other nations
in this world.
We have a lot of problems.
We are unique compared to many other nations
in this world, and we have been given a lot of truth.
We've been given a lot of truth, and to whom much is given, much is required.
There are people groups and lands across this globe as you would consider the need for missions,
there are people groups across this globe that do not have the light that we've had
in America.
And therefore I do not believe that they are in the same place of judgment that we are
in.
Certainly they're accountable, I understand that, I'm not making an excuse for those people
groups, but I'm simply saying to whom much has been given, much is required.
And we started with God, but we left God, right?
Israel started with God, and they left God.
You think about the prevalent sin of Judah and Israel throughout their history was that
of idolatry.
They had forgotten God, they had forsaken God, and they had followed after idols.
Could that not be the description of the land in which we call home?
And yet for all of this, it seems as if there's a lack of repentance, and a lack of truly
seeing that we need to turn to God.
God is the answer.
I don't have time, but in Amos chapter number four, maybe you want to jot it down.
In Amos chapter number four, God goes through a series of dialogue, and in quick summary
review He says there was famine, there was drought, there was blight, there was pestilence,
and there was destruction.
Yet for all of this have ye not returned unto Me, saith the Lord.
Read Amos four.
That statement of yet have ye not returned unto Me, saith the Lord is listed really after
each of those.
The famine, the drought, the blight, the pestilence, the destruction.
And then you come down to verse number 12 of Amos four, and it says, therefore, in the
very end of the verses, prepare to meet thy God, O Israel.
This is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of an angry God.
Our God is a consuming fire.
The situation in Joel 1 is, it's unique, it's utter destruction, it's dire.
Joy is withered away, but there's a solution.
We see the situation.
I want you to note the solution in verses 13 and 14 back in Joel 1.
The solution that was given in Leviticus 26 near the end of the chapter, as we mentioned,
is that turning back, that repentance, that acknowledgement of the sin, the iniquity,
the transgression, and turning back to God, a confession.
We see that in Daniel 9.
We see that in Nehemiah 1, where they're confessing, they're saying, we, God, have forsaken you.
God, we're coming back to you.
We want your blessing.
Notice in verses 13 and 14, the solution, gird yourselves and lament, ye priests, how
ye ministers of the altar, come, lie all night in sackcloth, ye ministers of my God, for
the meat offering and the drink offering is withholden from the house of your God.
We know as you read through the scriptures and you read about sackcloth, it's typical
of that of sorrow and repentance.
In fact, you see that in Jonah chapter number three, when the king of Nineveh, he declares
that they were going to be covered in sackcloth and ashes.
Why?
Because of a message from a prophet that was disobedient and God had to smack around and
get them to go into Nineveh, and the message was simple, yet 40 days and Nineveh shall
be destroyed.
Simple message, but passionate, no doubt.
You'd be passionate if you spent some time in the belly of a great fish too, amen?
They repented, they had revival.
Notice verse number 14, sanctify ye a fast, call a solemn assembly.
Notice what it says, gather the elders and all the inhabitants of the land into the house
of the Lord your God and cry unto the Lord.
It must begin at the house of God, according to what Peter tells us, and I believe that
as we look at a passage of scripture from the Old Testament such as this and we understand
what's going on and we note the situation and we note the solution, I trust that we
as the people of God would understand the need to return to God.
We'd understand that the answer in our world is Christ.
It's not more politics, it's not more red tape, it's not more vaccinations, it's not
more medicines, it's not more, it's not all those things.
It's God.
It's God, and we need to turn to Him.
We see this on a national level here and we've made some applications for what we've dealt
with, but I want you to think about the personal level.
Go back to Psalm 51 if you will.
We visited Psalm 51 this morning, I told you we'd be back tonight.
In Psalm 51, it's the psalm of repentance penned by David after the prophet Nathan.
With courage and boldness says, Thou art the man.
We find here in this passage of Scripture, as we mentioned this morning, we looked at
a number of the verses, but you find it begins in verse number one, Have mercy upon me, O
God, according to Thy loving kindness, according unto the multitude of Thy tender mercies,
blot out my transgressions.
Aren't you thankful that our God is merciful?
The loving kindness of God.
We go to Him on the basis of that.
He says, Wash me throughly from mine iniquity, cleanse me from my sin, for I acknowledge
my transgressions.
My sin is ever before me against Thee.
Thee only have I sinned and done this evil in Thy sight, that Thou mightest be justified
when Thou speakest and be clear when Thou judgest.
Behold, I was shaped in an iniquity, and in sin did my mother conceive me.
Behold, Thou desirest truth in the inward parts, and in the hidden part Thou shalt make
me to know wisdom.
Purge me with hyssop, and I shall be clean.
Wash me now, excuse me, wash me, and I shall be whiter than snow.
Make me to hear joy and gladness.
Verse 16 of Joel 1, joy and gladness were missing.
It says this, as we continue in verse number 8, that the bones which Thou hast broken may
rejoice.
Hide Thy face from my sins and blot out all mine iniquities.
Make in me a clean heart, O God, and renew a right spirit within me.
Cast me not away from Thy presence, and take not Thy Holy Spirit from me.
Notice verse number 12, restore unto me the joy of Thy salvation, and uphold me with Thy
free spirit.
Why is it that in verse number 12, does David cry out, restore unto me the joy of Thy salvation?
Shall I ask it this way, is there joy in knowing Jesus?
Is there joy in being saved?
Absolutely.
In his presence, Psalm 16, is fullness of joy, and we understand that he gives us joy.
It's a joy unspeakable and full of glory.
He says to the disciples when they come back, talking about all of the powers that he had
given them, and they're rejoicing in those things, and Jesus says, rejoice not in this,
but rather, rejoice that your names are written in heaven.
There's a new name written down in glory, and it's mine.
You remember when he got saved, and that joy.
David doesn't pray in Psalm 51, 12, restore me my salvation.
No.
You're saved, you're saved.
You're kept by the power of God.
But he says, restore unto me the joy of Thy salvation.
He lost his joy.
Why?
Well, you'd have to go back to 2 Samuel 11.
We don't have time tonight, because we read all of Leviticus 26.
But if you go back to 2 Samuel 11, and you read about the sin of David with Bathsheba,
the way in which he had Uriah the Hittite murdered, you will find why David lost his
joy.
And in one word, it's sin.
The same reason that the nation in Joel 1 was dealing with that utter destruction, sin.
And we find that David prays, restore unto me the joy of Thy salvation.
I'm thankful that our God is interested in restoration.
He's a restoring God.
And I'm thankful for the truth that God gives us in His Word with regard to His restoration.
It's interesting, as you continue to read down through Psalm 51, skip down if you will
to verse number 15.
It says,
down my lips and my mouth shall show forth thy praise." Notice what it says,
for thou desirest not sacrifice, else would I give it. Thou delightest not in
burnt offering. Now let me ask you a question, who ordained sacrifice and
burnt offering? God. That was God's institution. I mean, He ordained it.
Why is David saying that thou desirest not those things? Because God cares more
about your heart than He does about your offering. He cares more about your heart
than He does about those outward things. He says the sacrifices of God in verse
17 are a broken spirit, a broken and a contrite heart. Oh God, thou wilt not
despise. You can bring every offering you want, but if your heart's far from God, He
says that's not a sweet-smelling savor to me. Do good in thy good pleasure and
design. Build thou the walls of Jerusalem. Notice the then in verse number 19. Then
shalt thou be pleased with the sacrifices of righteousness, with burnt
offering and whole burnt offering. Then shall they offer bullocks upon thine
altar. Why is he going to be pleased in verse number 19, but he's not going to
desire them in verse number 16? Because there's a right heart. There's the
sacrifice that's mentioned in verse number 17 of that broken spirit, a broken
and a contrite heart. We talked this morning about that cultivation of the
heart. We find that God is able to restore unto David the joy of his
salvation. Why did he lose the joy? What was the cause of the joy from a
personal perspective? We looked at Joel in the the national perspective, but we
look at the personal perspective and we say, hey, believer, Christian, have you
lost your joy? Why? The cares of this world, the sin. I read something this
afternoon and it really convicted me. Here's what it said. You know what worry
reveals? Your lack of faith. I said, smack. What does worry reveal? Your lack of
faith. Well, thank you very much. I appreciate that. Stepped on my toes, just
stepped on my toes again. Joel 2, in verse number 25, we'll close with this.
What a great promise of God. I understand the context being more in a futuristic
perspective with the prophecy and view, but when David said in Psalm 51 12,
restoring to me the joy of thy salvation, we find that our God is a
restoring God. And in Joel 2 in verse 25, he says, I will restore to you the years
that the locust hath eaten, the canker worm, the caterpillar, and the palmer
worm, my great army which I sent among you. Who sent it? God. Well, it was because
of, no, no, God. God. In Joel chapter number one, when we were reading in verse
number four, we read about the palmer worm, the locust, the canker worm, and the
caterpillar. And we see here in verse number 25 of chapter number two, the
locust, the canker worm, the caterpillar, and the palmer worm. And God says, I will
restore to you the years that these things have eaten. Our God is a restoring
God. If your joy is missing, if your joy is withered away, you know that. There may
be some other people that know that too, quite honestly. It's hard to hide that
all the time. If your joy is gone, it's hard to hide that. You might get good at
it for a little while. It's hard to hide it. But I would submit to you this
evening that you know, I know, if my joy is missing. And what is it that took my
joy? Sin. Sin. And David says, restore unto me the joy of thy salvation. Oh, that God
would help us to understand, listen, we serve a holy God. I understand this message is not
the most popular message. I get it. Leviticus 26, they should read that in Congress every
day next week. It would be wonderful. Amen? Seriously. It might do us good if we read
some portions of God's Word, understanding that we serve a God who is holy. Judgment
must begin at the house of God. Oh, that we as the people of God would follow as David
did, as Nehemiah did, as Daniel did. Say, God, we've sinned. When's the last time we
wept over the sin of our nation? The wickedness that's so prevalent. I understand we complain
about it all the time. But when have we wept about it and confessed it? God, we live in
a wicked land. Wicked land. We really do. God is righteous. Righteousness exalteth the
nation, but sin is a reproach to any people. Let's pray. Father, we love you. We thank
you for loving us. Maybe there's one here as we think about it from a personal perspective
that their joy has been lost. Their joy is withered away. I thank you that you are able
to restore that joy. I pray that we'd be honest, humble with you tonight. And over
these few moments of our invitation that we would truly allow the Holy Spirit of God to
have His will and way. We live in a wicked world, amongst a wicked people. They need
to see the light of Jesus Christ in our lives. We need to shine bright. We don't need the
lens to be dirty. Help us, God, to be clean. We'll commit these times to you, for it's
in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me?