Genesis chapter 33, we had some extra specials tonight, I shared the situation there about
love thy neighbor, so you listen fast, I'm going to preach fast, amen?
And we got a fellowship over in the other room after the service, and a farewell fellowship
for Jared.
We're going to look at the entirety of Genesis 33 this evening, but it's only 20 verses,
and so not too bad, and trust the Lord to help us here.
I've titled the message, as you look at the back of the bulletin there, from verse number
11, the Bible says in verse 11, take, I pray thee, my blessing that is brought to thee,
because God hath dealt graciously with me, and because I have enough, and he urged him,
and he took it.
I'm telling the message this evening, God hath dealt graciously with me.
Of course, as we looked at Genesis chapter number 32, that long, life-altering night
that we studied a couple of weeks ago, we find the reunion between Jacob and Esau would
finally come to pass.
As we have noted, Jacob is quite concerned about this reunion.
We understand that Jacob has departed from Paddan Aram to go back to the land of his
fathers at the instruction, as a result of the instruction of the Lord.
God had given him the instruction to return, and Jacob was obedient to that instruction,
and we find that he's now going back, and he knows that he has to have this reunion
with his brother.
Of course, he had sent some men ahead in order to just prepare the way, and he found out
that Esau was coming with 400 men, and he was quite concerned.
And so, as we look at this text of Scripture, God records for us this account of this reunion
between Jacob and Esau, and we find that within the text that Jacob makes that great declaration
that God hath dealt graciously with me.
I believe that this evening that each one of us could agree with Jacob, and we could
understand that God has been gracious to us.
He's been so, so good to us, and what a blessing to know the Lord.
If you are taking notes this evening, number one, Jacob embraced his brother.
In verses one through four, we see the reunion recorded for us, and what an amazing scene
that God gives us.
I'm thankful that God has recorded these verses of Scripture, this event in the life of Jacob,
for it's certainly impactful.
First the Bible begins in verse number one, and Jacob lifted up his eyes and looked, and
behold, Esau came, and notice what it says, and with him 400 men.
Now he'd already known that in the beginning of chapter 32, he'd received that intel report.
The Bible continues, though, and says, and he, speaking of Jacob, divided the children
unto Leah, and unto Rachel, and unto the two handmaids.
Why did he do that?
Remember, he was concerned that Esau was going to kill him, and also kill his wives and children.
It says in verse number two, that he put the handmaids and their children foremost,
and Leah and her children after, and Rachel and Joseph hindermost, and he passed over
before them, and bowed himself to the ground seven times, until he came near to his brother.
And I love verse number four, for the Bible says, and Esau ran to meet him, and embraced
him, and fell on his neck, and kissed him, and they wept.
Isn't that a beautiful account of this reunion between Jacob and his brother Esau, and we
find that Jacob and Esau, there's an embrace.
It tells us in verse number four that Esau runs to meet him, and now Esau, the last that
we've heard of Esau with regard to his perspective of Jacob, is that he's going to kill Jacob.
He was angry over the blessing and all that had taken place, but we find that nearly 20
years has passed since that time, and we find this great reunion.
I believe that as we look at these few verses of Scripture that record for us this reunion
and this embrace between Jacob and Esau, it's a great example and a great picture of forgiveness
and reconciliation.
So often I've said over the years that two pillars of biblical Christianity, and it's
just two of many pillars of biblical Christianity, but two pillars of biblical Christianity are
forgiveness and reconciliation.
And I'm so thankful for the fact that we've been forgiven.
Isn't it wonderful to know the forgiveness of God?
The Bible says that with thee there is forgiveness.
Our God is a God that's ready to pardon, He's ready to forgive, and as the people of God
we understand something about forgiveness because we have been forgiven, and therefore
we are to forgive others.
The Bible says in Ephesians 4 and verse 32,
"...and be kind one to another, tenderhearted, forgiving one another, even as God for Christ's
sake hath forgiven you."
I didn't deserve to be forgiven.
It's God's grace and God's mercy that led to me being forgiven, and I'm so thankful
that God is rich in mercy, that God's grace is amazing and it's abundant, and this evening
we think about this truth of forgiveness, and then we think about reconciliation.
What a joy to understand the truth of reconciliation.
See, we've often spoken over the years, and yes, there's truth in the Bible with regard
to church discipline and dealing with sin and so on and so forth, but the purpose of
church discipline is not excommunication.
The true purpose of church discipline is reconciliation and restoration.
That's the idea.
Listen, God's people need to belong to a church.
The church is God's idea, it's God's plan, and God has instituted the church, and God
has given us instructions with regard to church discipline, and from time to time it's necessary
because of an offense and what have you, but the purpose is always reconciliation, restoration,
and we rejoice in that truth, the biblical truth of reconciliation and restoration, and
it's coupled there with forgiveness, and I'm mindful of what Galatians 6 tells us.
It tells us this, brethren, if a man be overtaken in a fault, ye which are spiritual, notice
what it says, restore such an one in the spirit of meekness, considering thyself, lest
thou also be tempted, and we think about that restoration, and back a couple of summers
ago, my dad preached through Psalm 23 on Wednesday evenings, and I want to remind you what the
Bible says in Psalm 23.
He says, he, speaking of the Lord being our shepherd, he restoreth my soul, and what a
blessing to understand this evening, and then to see this picture between Jacob and
Esau.
I mean, again, Jacob, why did he leave?
Mom said, hey, I've heard that Esau's going to kill you.
You need to go a little ways, and you need to get away for a little while so that his
anger will depart, and after 20 years, this reunion is given to us, and it's a reunion
that's sweet.
There's an embrace.
The Bible says that he ran to meet him, embraced him, fell on his neck and kissed him, and
they wept.
Isn't that beautiful?
I understand that as I look at this passage of Scripture, and I think about this event
that's been provided for us, this record that's been given, what a joy it is to have that
sweet communion and fellowship one with another.
There are individuals, believers, that have been at odds at one another for sometime years
and years and years, and they just dig in their heels, and they refuse to forgive, refuse
to have any level of restoration or reconciliation, and oh, that that would never be said of us
as God's people, that we'd understand that our God is ready to pardon, ready to forgive,
and because we've been forgiven, that we too are to forgive others, and we think about
this great example where Jacob embraced his brother.
Not only did Jacob embrace his brother, but number two, if you're taking notes, Jacob
explained God's blessing.
Jacob explained God's blessing.
He testified a little bit, begins in verse number five, he lifted up his eyes and saw
the women and the children and said, who are those with thee?
This is Esau asking Jacob about what he now sees, and Jacob responds and says this at
the end of verse number five, the children which God hath graciously given thy servant.
Then the handmaidens came near, they and their children, and they bowed themselves, and Leah
also with her children came near and bowed themselves, and after came Joseph near and
Rachel and they bowed themselves, and he said, what meanest thou by all this drove which
I met?
And he said, these are divine grace in the sight of my Lord.
Remember, we studied this in chapter 32 a couple of weeks ago, where he had prepared
that present and he sent those droves of cattle and livestock so that they would go, and he
was trying to appease his brother Esau, and in fact, it says exactly that in verse number
20 of chapter 32, and say ye moreover, behold, thy servant Jacob is behind us, for he said,
I will appease him with the present that goeth before me, and afterward I will see his face.
Peradventure, he will accept of me.
And so Esau says, hey, what is all of this that I see?
He sees the women and the children, he now references the droves of livestock, and it
says this in verse number 9, and Esau said, I have enough, my brother, keep that thou
hast unto thyself.
And Jacob said, nay, I pray thee, if now I have found grace in thy sight, then receive
my present at my hand, for therefore I have seen thy face, as though I
had seen the face of God, and thou was pleased with me."
Notice verse number 11.
I read it by way of introduction,
but notice it says,
take, I pray thee, my blessing that is brought to thee,
because God hath dealt graciously with me,
and because I have enough.
And he urged him, and he took it.
And he said, let us take our journey,
and let us go, and I will go before thee.
As we look at these verses of scripture,
really in verses five through 11,
we see that Jacob is explaining the blessing of God.
I want you to think about these 20 years,
and much of what we've studied,
and obviously it was a long time ago
that we're studying the time that he was there
in Paddan Aram, and all that took place,
but as we're familiar with the text of scripture,
and the record that God gives us,
we find that it is absolutely true
that during that period of time,
that Jacob experienced some hardship.
He experienced some difficulty.
There were some things, some circumstances
that were not what we might describe
as being favorable or desirable.
But we find that when Jacob and Esau have this reunion,
and after the embrace, and then Jacob explains
the blessing of God, I'm thankful that as I read
these verses of scripture in verses five through 11,
you know what you don't see?
You don't see any complaining.
You don't see Jacob saying to Esau,
listen, let me tell you how bad it was.
Let me tell you all the bad things that I experienced
when I was there in Paddan Aram,
and let me tell you how they weren't fair,
and how this happened, and that happened,
you don't read any complaining.
Not only do you not read any complaining,
but you find that Jacob didn't blame Esau
for anything that happened.
He could have been bitter at Esau.
Why did he leave in the first place?
Because Esau said he was gonna kill him.
And he leaves.
And sometimes when we experience some difficulties
and hardships, we're looking for someone
to put the blame on.
Sometimes that's what happens in life.
But I don't read that in Jacob's testimony.
I read that Jacob, as he's explaining what's taken place,
there's no complaining, there's no blame
that's being placed upon Esau.
I also recognize this.
Jacob doesn't take any credit for himself.
When Esau asks in verse number five,
when he says he looked up his eyes
and saw the women and the children and said,
who are those with thee?
And then in verse number eight, when he says,
what meanest thou by all this drove which I met?
Jacob doesn't say, yeah, it's been pretty good, man.
I really made it.
I mean, I went out there and I did all of this
and I, that's not what Jacob says.
There's no boasting.
There's no complaining.
There's no blaming.
There's no boasting.
We find that Jacob explains
and he declares the goodness of God.
He declares the goodness of God.
We find that in this text of Scripture
that he recognized it was God that had blessed him.
He recognized that it was God
that had graciously given him the children.
Notice in verse number five, he said,
the children which God hath graciously given thy servant.
When he speaks about the droves,
when the question is asked in verse number eight
and he speaks about the present,
he says in verse number 11,
take, I pray thee, my blessing that is brought to thee.
Why?
Because God hath dealt graciously with me
and because I have enough.
And he urged him and he took it.
Not only did he recognize that it was God
that had blessed him,
but Jacob was careful to give God the glory.
He was careful to give God the glory.
See, sometimes in our lives,
we might recognize that it's God that has blessed,
but there might be just a little part of us
that wants to have a little glory.
Sometimes that's the way it works.
But we find that Jacob is recognizing
it's God's good hand of blessing.
God hath dealt graciously with me.
I notice in the text of Scripture
that even as we've studied in Psalm 37
on Wednesday evenings,
for those that are part of that study,
we talk about the blessed and the righteous individual
that is referenced throughout Psalm 37.
And as we look at that text of Scripture,
the Bible talks about how the righteous,
how that they give and how that they are benevolent.
Why?
Because God is benevolent.
And so we find here, even within in Psalm 37, 21,
if you want to reference it,
it says that the righteous showeth mercy and giveth.
The righteous showeth mercy and giveth.
Why do they show mercy?
Well, because we've received mercy.
Why do they give?
Because God's given to us.
And so we find here that Jacob recognizes
the blessing of God, he gives God the glory,
but then he and himself, he wants to be a blessing.
He says, take I pray thee.
Notice the wording of verse number 11.
Take I pray thee, my blessing that is brought to thee.
God blessed me, and now I can be a blessing to someone else.
We sing the song channels only.
Being a channel, a conduit of God's blessing.
As God pours out the blessing,
it's not so that we can just gather as much as we can gather
and try to build bigger barns and so on and so forth,
but God's blessed us so that we can be a blessing.
I mean, this is great truth in the life of Jacob.
We find this evening that I believe each and every one of us
we'd be honest, God hath dealt graciously with me.
God's been so good to us.
Psalm 68 and verse number 19,
read just a few verses of scripture.
As we make some application in our own lives,
listen, God's been good to us.
So, so good.
We're so undeserving.
You know, there are times that we don't even thank Him
like we should.
He's still so good to us.
It's amazing how good God is.
Notice in Psalm 68, specifically look at verse number 19.
The Bible says,
blessed be the Lord who daily loadeth us with benefits,
even the God of our salvation, Selah.
You read that word Selah,
of course we've mentioned this before,
it's pause, meditate, think about this, chew on it.
Let the truth sink in.
But I want you to notice that middle phrase, if you will,
of this verse of scripture,
where the Bible says who daily loadeth us with benefits.
I like the wording.
I like how God gives us this picture
of just how good He's been to us.
He doesn't just give us a little bit of a blessing,
He loads us with benefits.
In my mind's eye, in my sanctified imagination,
I see kind of a wheelbarrow, if you will,
and you're trying to fill that thing up.
And I mean, you just get it as full as you can
because you want to make as few trips as possible
and man, it's just over
and you're trying to steer that thing.
Have you ever been there?
You ever done that before?
And then all of a sudden you put too much in it
and you tilt that thing over
and then you got a mess and you got to start over.
But in my mind's eye, I kind of,
that's how I like to think about God
who has daily loadeth us with benefits, with blessings.
With blessings.
We sing the song, count your blessings,
name them one by one.
I wonder how often we really in our lives
go through that discipline of counting our blessings
and name them one by one.
We're in such a fast-paced society.
I mentioned that when I spoke about loving our neighbor
and praying for them for a month
and sometimes that persistence wears off
because we're just an immediate satisfaction
kind of a society.
You wait too long at the,
wherever you fill in the blank
and you're like, hey, what's going on?
Come on, let's go, right?
And you think about that pausing.
Be still and know that I am God.
That's what he said.
We just take some time and say,
God, you've been so good.
Let me just start writing out all of your blessings.
All of your blessings.
I walked in my office this afternoon.
I'm sure you've done this before as well.
And sometimes you just do it by habit.
You walk into a room and the first thing you do
is just turn the light switch and then keep on walking.
You know, I walk in my office this afternoon,
I hit the light switch even though the light was on.
Just out of habit.
I just walk in the room and I bam
and it's like, oh yeah, it's already on.
I just kept on, it wasn't a senior moment.
It was just a habit.
That's at least my story and I'm gonna stick to it, amen.
But the reality is that sometimes
we just take it for granted.
I read that report about the Robinsons in Zambia
that for 12 hours a day,
they're gonna have no electricity.
Most of us wouldn't survive.
I'm just being honest.
Wouldn't have anything to power our cell phones
and this, that, and the other thing, it'd be a mess.
God's been so good to us.
So, so good.
Look in 1 Corinthians chapter four.
I need to move along here.
1 Corinthians chapter four.
Notice what the Bible says.
In 1 Corinthians chapter number four,
I'm gonna read a verse as you're turning there
from the book of James,
a verse that we're familiar with in James one and 17.
The Bible says every good gift
and every perfect gift is from above
and cometh down from the father of lights
with whom is no variableness, neither shadow of turning.
The book of 1 Corinthians in chapter number four.
In verse number seven, the Bible says this.
For who maketh thee to differ from another?
And then look at this question.
And what hast thou that thou didst not receive?
Now, if thou didst receive it, why dost thou glory as if thou hadst not received it?
Specifically as Paul is going to be dealing with the church in Corinth about spiritual
gifts, we find that there's certainly some reference there with regard to spiritual gifts
and understand the Lord gives as He wills.
But I want you to think about this truth broadly speaking.
What hast thou that thou didst not receive?
So often we have a wrong, a poor perspective when we think about life and we think, well,
I'm a self-made man, I got here, I did this and I did that and I worked hard, and so on
and so forth.
And the reality is that you may have worked hard and you may have studied diligently,
but it's God who gave you the ability to do that.
And so we have to dig deeper and dig deeper and find out, look, in Deuteronomy chapter
8 and verse number 18 it says this, but thou shalt remember the Lord thy God, for it is
He that giveth thee power to get wealth.
It's all God.
Remember the truth that Jesus gave in John?
He says, without me you can do nothing.
You go ahead and think you can do something without God, you're going to find out really
quick that you can't.
It's God's air that we're breathing.
It's only by God's grace right now that we're even here.
And we recognize here this evening that God has been so good to us and Jacob, after he
embraces his brother, he then explains God's blessing.
In the next several verses we read of the journey that takes place, there's a departure
that's documented and arrivals to different places.
Notice it says in verse number 12, back in Genesis 33, and he said, let us take our journey
and let us go and I will go before thee.
And he said unto him, my Lord knoweth that the children are tender and the flocks and
herds with young are with me and if men should overdrive them one day, all the flock will
die.
Let my Lord, I pray thee, pass over before his servant.
Notice this phrase, and I will lead on softly.
There's some wisdom in that.
It's not the duration of the message this evening.
But the thing of leading, and he says, I will lead on softly.
He understood the state of his flock, according to verse number 13.
By the way, Proverbs talks about that.
He understood the state of his flock and he said, look, it's not good for me to overdrive
them.
It's not good for me to become in a place where we're vulnerable.
And so he understood what was going on and he says, I will lead on softly, in the middle
of verse number 14, according as the cattle that goeth before me and the children be able
to endure until I come unto my Lord, unto seer.
You know, sometimes, this is a good truth for me, sometimes as leaders you get too far
out in front.
You got to lead on softly, carefully, understanding the importance of those that God has given
you the opportunity to lead, husbands, parents, leading your children.
Sometimes we can get crazy in our mind about why our kids don't get what they're supposed
to get and try to reason with them.
I was forever trying to reason with my kids before they could even begin to try to reason
And my dad would look at me and say, what are you doing?
What do you mean, what am I doing?
I'm parenting, amen?
They don't understand.
And he was probably right, there were times in which they just didn't understand.
Notice it continues in verse 15, and Esau said, let me now leave with thee some of the
folk that are with me.
And he said, what needeth it?
Let me find grace in the sight of my Lord.
So Esau returned that day on his way unto seer.
And Jacob journeyed to Succoth and built him a house and made booths for his cattle.
Therefore, the name of the place is called Succoth.
And so we don't look, as you look at the text of scripture, then in verse number 18, it
says, and Jacob came to Shalom.
Now there's probably a period of time between 17 and 18 that we don't know the duration
of time between those verses.
Many people have offered various opinions with regard to how long he was there in Succoth
according to verse number 17, before he went to Shalom, a city of Shechem in verse number
18.
And I'll leave that to be debated by the scholars, because I don't know the answer.
The Bible doesn't tell us, but it does seem like there's a period of time that takes place
where he was there in Succoth according to verse number 17.
But then in verse number 18, it says this, and Jacob came to Shalom, a city of Shechem,
which is in the land of Canaan, when he came from Paddan Aram and pitched his tent before
the city.
And here's where we get to our final point this evening.
We see that Jacob embraced his brother.
Jacob explained God's blessing.
And then number three, if you're taking notes tonight, Jacob erected an altar.
Notice what the Bible says after he comes and pitches his tent in this place.
In verse number 19, it says that he bought a parcel of a field where he had spread his
tent at the hand of the children of Hamar, Shechem's father, for 100 pieces of money.
And verse number 20 says, and he erected there an altar and called it El Elohi Israel.
I want you to think about the significance of this, and we find that it would certainly
be fitting that Jacob would erect this altar with all that he experienced and with all
that he knew, with all that had already, we've already looked at in Genesis chapter 33.
We find that he comes to this place, and he's going to be there, and he erects this altar
and he names it.
I want you to think about the significance, of course we've mentioned this in other portions
of Scripture, where the significance of a name, and how that Jacob in so doing, he had
the opportunity to name this altar whatever he really wanted to name the altar.
You read in the book of Joshua, and you don't need to turn there, but after the two and
a half tribes are going to depart and all that's taking place after the conquering
of the land that is given to us, we find that they were going to have an altar, they were
going to erect there, and they called it Ed, because it was a witness between them.
That's what it meant.
I remember teaching through that passage, and somebody came to me and said, what does
that mean?
It means a witness between them, that's what the Bible says.
But here we find that he says that he named this altar, he called it El Elohi Israel.
It means a mighty God is the God of Israel, a mighty God.
I want you to think about God's power, God's might.
Listen, I'm thankful this evening that our God is omnipotent.
I mentioned in Sunday school for those that were here this morning about the opposition
and how that the enemy is powerful, but he's limited in his power.
We serve the omnipotent God, the Almighty God.
Remember it was Abraham that first had that introduction from God when he said that his
name was El Shaddai, the Almighty God.
And here, as Jacob would set up this altar and he would give it a name, he says El Elohi
Israel, a mighty God is the God of Israel, and I'm so thankful that we serve a mighty
God.
He's great in power.
Jacob had experienced the power of God.
Jacob had witnessed in his life and an experience that he served a God who was mighty, was strong,
was powerful.
And this evening, I want you to understand that our God is all powerful.
The Bible says that the Lord God omnipotent reigneth, and I'm thankful that there's nothing
that's too hard for him.
The question that he asked Abraham all those years ago, millennia ago, he said, is anything
too hard for the Lord?
Still to this very day, there's nothing that's too hard for our God.
He's able.
We speak about prayer.
We take and claim promises, calling to me, and I will answer thee and show thee great
and mighty things which thou knowest not.
The truth of Ephesians, when he says that he's able to do exceeding abundantly above
all that we could ask or think, that's our God.
He's a mighty God, and he's able.
And after all these events in Jacob's life, when he comes to this place and settles down
and purchases this piece of property from the hand of the children of Hamar, we find
that he puts this altar in place, and he names it El Elohi Israel.
Mighty God is the God of Israel, and I'm thankful that still today we serve the mighty God.
What a mighty God we serve.
He's able.
You say, I got this problem.
I got this difficulty.
I got this.
God's able.
God's powerful.
We trust him, and we know that he'll give us the grace and the strength that is necessary
to go through whatever that he's allowed to come in your path or in my path.
He'll give us the strength for it.
I know there are times we say, well, this isn't what I would have chosen.
I get it.
But God says that his strength is made perfect in weakness.
When I am weak, then I am strong.
What a blessing to look at this passage of Scripture, to see a reunion, the embrace between
Jacob and Esau.
Isn't that precious?
And then the explanation that Jacob gives, listen, God has been so good to me.
Let me tell you what God's done.
He's been so gracious.
And then he sets up this altar, El Elohi Israel.
We serve a mighty God.
He's been so good to us.
Oh, that we would understand the importance of forgiveness and restoration, and that we
would lift up our voices and praise to our God, for he is worthy.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank You for loving us. We thank You for the account that You've given us this evening of this
reunion between Jacob and Esau and the events that followed. God, I pray that we'd be challenged
through this record tonight. Lord, that we'd be challenged in our own lives to
recognize that we've been forgiven and then to forgive.
Lord, I pray there'd be nothing between my soul and my Savior, but I also pray
that we'd have nothing between us as brothers and sisters of Christ, in Christ.
Lord, I pray that You'd help us to acknowledge Your good hand of blessing that's been upon us.
God, You've dealt graciously with us. You've been so good to us. I pray that You'd help us
to recognize Your strength, Your might, Your power. Help us to trust You and prove You.
I pray that in these few moments of invitation that You'd have Your will and way.
I pray that You'd move and work in hearts and lives as only You can.
We'll thank You for it. In Christ's name we pray.