which thou hast seen, the things which are,
and the things which shall be hereafter.
And chapter one is the first section,
chapters two and three is that second section,
the church age, the seven churches
that are being written to.
Those are literal churches that are in Asia Minor
at the time of the writing.
I believe that they're representative
of churches throughout the church age,
and we're still in that church age.
And then the things that shall be hereafter,
and we find that as we come to the fourth chapter,
it begins in verse number one,
after this, I looked and behold,
a door was opened in heaven,
and the first voice which I heard was,
as it were, of a trumpet talking with me,
which said, come up hither,
and I will show thee things which must be hereafter.
And immediately I was in the spirit,
and behold, a throne was set in heaven,
and one sat on the throne.
And he that sat was to look upon
like a jasper and a sardine stone,
and there was a rainbow round about the throne,
and it was in sight like unto an emerald.
And round about the throne
were four and 20 seats,
and upon the seats I saw four and 20 elders sitting,
clothed in white raiment,
and they had on their heads crowns of gold.
And out of the throne proceeded lightnings
and thunderings and voices,
and there were seven lamps of fire burning
before the throne, which are the seven spirits of God.
Notice verse six, and before the throne
there was a sea of glass like unto crystal.
In the midst of the throne and round about the throne
were four beasts full of eyes before and behind.
And the first beast was like a lion,
and the second beast like a calf,
and the third beast had a face as a man,
and the fourth beast was like a flying eagle.
The four beasts had each of them six wings about him,
and they were full of eyes within.
They rest not day and night,
saying, holy, holy, holy,
Lord God Almighty,
which was and is and is to come.
We find that this fourth chapter,
we'll read verses nine through 11 next Sunday evening
as we finish up with the fourth chapter,
but we find that here in Revelation 4,
God provides us with a glimpse
into the throne room of heaven.
What a scene it is.
And I just want you to think for just a moment this evening
that now we can only read about it,
but one day, one glorious day, we're gonna see it.
I want you to just let that sink in
for a moment this evening,
because it's beautiful to read Revelation 4 and 5
as God gives to us this glimpse
into the throne room of heaven,
and what a scene it is.
And we see as we've already been in the chapter
for a few weeks now,
and we've had the opportunity to speak about the rapture.
We've had the opportunity to speak about the throne.
And of course, the truth that I've said over and over
is what makes heaven heaven
is the fact that our Savior is there,
and for all of eternity will be in his presence.
And we find that we discuss,
we spent an entire service looking at the throne
and him that sat upon it.
And then we spent a week looking at the 24 elders.
And now we come as we continue
looking through this chapter,
and we're gonna see and focus our attention this evening
on these four beasts.
Unlike the 24 elders, these four beasts are not human.
And we'll look at how the scriptures reveal this to us
as we look at verses six through eight in particular.
I've titled the message simply this in heaven part three.
We did part one, part two, this is part three,
the final of this section in Revelation chapter number four.
And I want you to notice with me,
if you're taking notes this evening,
notice number one, how these four beasts are described.
As we look at the scriptures,
we find that the apostle John,
as he has an opportunity to be transported
into the throne room of God,
the Bible says that he heard that voice in verse number one,
and it said, come up hither.
And the Bible says that he was immediately in the spirit.
The Bible says that the voice said, come up hither,
and I will show thee things which must be hereafter.
And so we find that the apostle John is now writing,
he's providing for us a record of what he is seeing.
And of course, what he would hear
as he goes through this process.
And we find that as he's providing for us a description,
we have an opportunity to begin to see again
with our mind's eye what John had the opportunity to see.
We find in verse number six,
it says that before the throne,
there was a sea of glass like unto crystal.
And then notice it says in the midst of the throne
and around about the throne were four beasts.
So these are the four beasts
that we're going to focus our attention on this evening.
And we notice how they're described
beginning in verse number six.
It's also mentioned in verse number eight,
it says that they're full of eyes before and behind.
We read in verse number eight that it's described this way.
And the four beasts had each of them six wings about him.
Notice this, and they were full of eyes within.
And so we find in verse six and verse number eight,
this reference with regard to these four beasts,
with regard to them having these eyes,
and again, full of eyes before and behind,
full of eyes within.
We find that in verse number seven,
John will give the imagery with regard to these four beasts.
He says that the first beast was like a lion.
The second one was like a calf.
The third had a face as a man.
And the fourth like a flying eagle.
And we find that he is going to provide
this description for us.
And there are many that provide interpretations
with regard to what they think
and what they assume and what have you.
We find the final aspect of how he describes
what he's seeing in verse number eight
is that these four beasts, notice,
had each of them six wings about him.
And so we have the opportunity in verse six, seven, and eight
to read the description as John provides it to us.
And we know that all scripture
is given by inspiration of God.
And I believe that as you read
these few verses of scripture,
that the description reminds us
of some Old Testament passages of scripture
with regard to visions, one of Isaiah,
and one also of Ezekiel.
We'll start with Isaiah's vision.
If you hold your place here in Revelation,
we'll be back in just a few minutes.
But look over in Isaiah chapter number six,
and then we'll look over the book of Ezekiel.
We'll actually look at two passages in the book of Ezekiel.
But let's start in Isaiah chapter number six.
I actually referenced this passage of scripture
this on Wednesday evening.
And as we look at Isaiah chapter number six,
many of us are familiar with the passage.
And we find that Isaiah is writing,
and the Bible says in verse number one of Isaiah six,
in the year that King Uzziah died,
notice what the Bible says,
I saw also the Lord sitting upon a throne,
high and lifted up, and his train filled the temple.
So as we begin reading Isaiah six in verse number one,
we immediately are told that Isaiah sees this vision,
he sees the Lord, and the Bible says
that he sees him sitting upon a throne.
When we read Revelation chapter number four,
John, he's transported into heaven,
and immediately, what is he seeing?
The throne, and him that sat upon it.
And so we find that Isaiah, he sees this vision,
he sees the Lord upon his throne,
high and lifted up, his train did fill the temple.
Notice in verses two and three,
the Bible says above it, above what?
Well, above the throne, above the Lord,
as he saw the Lord sitting upon a throne,
stood the seraphims.
Each one had, what does it say?
Six wings.
Did we read that in Revelation chapter four?
We did, in verse number eight,
it said of those four beasts that they each had six wings.
We see that it says, and above it stood the seraphims,
each one had six wings.
With twain he covered his face,
and with twain he covered his feet,
and with twain he did fly.
Notice in verse number three,
the Bible says, and one cried unto another.
Now, we didn't read all of this,
we read it by way of introduction,
but we didn't read it just a moment ago.
And notice what these seraphims are crying.
The Bible says that they cried one to another,
saying, holy, holy, holy.
Is that what we read in Revelation chapter four?
We read that in verse number seven and eight,
as we read about this scene in heaven.
Holy, holy, holy is the Lord of hosts.
The whole earth is full of his glory.
Now, notice in Ezekiel chapter number one,
it's a little more lengthy of a passage
that we'll read in Ezekiel,
but we see in chapter number one,
as God provides for us this record of this vision
that Ezekiel has, and verse number,
we'll begin reading in verse number four.
Bear with me this evening,
it's a little lengthy of a passage that we'll read,
but I wanna catch all of it and see the vision.
And the Bible says in verse number four,
and I looked and behold,
a whirlwind came out of the north,
a great cloud and a fire enfolding itself,
and a brightness was about it.
And out of the midst thereof is the color of amber
out of the midst of the fire.
Verse five, also out of the midst thereof
came the likeness of four living creatures.
And this was their appearance.
They had the likeness of a man,
and everyone had four faces and everyone had four wings.
Now there's a distinction here.
These have four wings, not six wings.
And you just keep reading in verse number seven,
and their feet were straight feet,
and the sole of their feet was like the sole of a calf's foot
and they sparkled like the color of burnished brass.
They had the hands of a man under their wings
on their four sides,
and they four had their faces in their wings.
Their wings were joined one to another.
They turned not when they went,
they went out.
everyone straight forward.
As for the likeness of their faces,
they four had the face of a man,
the face of a lion on the right side,
and they four had the face of an ox on the left side,
they four also had the face of an eagle.
Thus were their faces,
and their wings were stretched upward.
Two wings of every one were joined one to another,
and two covered their bodies.
They went everyone straight forward,
whither the spirit was to go, they went.
And they turned not when they went,
as for the likeness of the living creatures,
their appearance was like burning coals of fire,
and like the appearance of lamps.
It went up and down among the living creatures,
and the fire was bright,
and out of the fire went forth lightning.
The living creatures ran and returned
as the appearance of a flash of lightning.
Now as I beheld the living creatures,
behold one wheel upon the earth by the living creatures
with his four faces.
The appearance of the wheels and their work
was like unto the color of a barrel,
then they four had one likeness,
and their appearance and their work
was as it were a wheel in the middle of a wheel.
When they went, they went upon their four sides.
They turned not when they went,
as for their rings, they were so high
that they were dreadful.
Their rings were full of eyes round about them four.
When the living creatures went, the wheels went by them,
and when the living creatures were lifted up from the earth,
the wheels were lifted up.
Whithersoever the spirit was to go, they went.
Thither was their spirit to go,
and the wheels were lifted up over against them,
for the spirit of the living creature was in the wheels.
When those went, these went,
and when those stood, these stood,
and when those were lifted from the earth,
the wheels were lifted up over against them,
for the spirit of the living creature was in the wheels.
Read those verses of Scripture and say,
what are you talking about?
What are you reading?
What are we looking at?
I've had people come to me from this passage of Scripture
and say, look, UFOs, Pastor.
I mean, UFOs right here, aliens.
No, no, no, no, you gotta keep reading the book of Ezekiel.
You can't just read chapter number one
and reach a conclusion based upon what you see here,
and we find that Ezekiel,
this is the record of his vision, these four creatures.
I'm not gonna go through all of it and pick through it,
but he's providing us with a record,
a description of this vision that he has,
but if you look in chapter number 10,
remember, no scriptures have any private interpretation.
We interpret Scripture with Scripture.
The best commentary on the Bible is the Bible, amen?
The reality is I've been asked,
hey, what commentaries would you recommend?
What should we say?
Listen, a commentary is simply
man's thoughts about God's words.
I'm not suggesting by making that statement
that we ought never use a commentary
or reference a commentary.
I'm just simply reminding each of us
that a commentary is simply man's words or thoughts
about God's words.
You have a study Bible.
Sometimes you can get messed up by reading the notes,
the footnotes of a study Bible.
Why?
Because it's just like what I mentioned there.
It's the idea of man's words or thoughts
about the Scripture.
Those notes are not inspired, but God's word is inspired.
Those words could have error,
but God's word is free from error,
and we can rejoice in understanding that.
Can I also mention this?
There are some things in the Bible
that are hard to understand.
That's just the truth of the matter.
Sometimes people have this idea,
well, I'm trying to make it easier to understand.
Whoever said that it's very easy to understand?
Amen?
God says of his own word
that there's some things that are hard.
What did Peter say?
As he's talking about Paul's writings,
he says some things that are hard to be understood.
And Paul says study to show thyself approved unto God,
a workman that needeth not to be ashamed,
rightly dividing the word of truth.
And so we find that as we look at this vision
in chapter number one,
we don't need to get all caught up into this,
oh, these UFOs and aliens and whatever.
Just keep on reading, and you come to chapter number 10,
and we find that in verse number,
I'm gonna just skip down to verse number 15.
The Bible says this.
And the cherubims.
The cherubims were lifted up.
Notice what he says.
This is the living creature
that I saw by the river of Shabar.
Well, where is that?
When is he talking about?
When did that happen?
Well, that's chapter number one.
We talked about, we read that passage of scripture,
and that's the vision.
And he says in chapter number 10
that the cherubims were lifted up.
This is the living creature
that I saw by the river of Shabar.
And when the cherubims went, the wheels went by them.
And when the cherubims lifted up their wings
to mount up from the earth,
the same wheels also turned not from beside them.
When they stood, these stood,
and when they were lifted up,
these lifted up themselves also,
for the spirit of the living creature was in them.
Then the glory of the Lord departed
from off the threshold of the house
and stood over the cherubims.
Verse number 19,
and the cherubims lifted up their wings
and mounted up from the earth and in my sight.
When they went out, the wheels also were beside them,
and everyone stood at the door
of the east gate of the Lord's house,
and the glory of the God of Israel was over them above.
Notice what he says again in verse number 20.
This is the living creature
that I saw under the God of Israel by the river of Shabar,
and I knew, I knew that they were the cherubims.
He didn't say, I think, he says, I knew.
How did God made that clear to him?
God revealed that.
We talk about revelation.
We understand that the canon of scripture is closed.
There's no more revelation in the sense
of what we would speak of here in Ezekiel,
but God made it clear to him.
And as he's writing, he says,
I knew that they were the cherubims.
So when we read Isaiah chapter number six
and we read Ezekiel one and 10,
we find that God gives us some glimpses
into the angelic world.
Now we understand some things about angels.
Number one, there are faithful angels
and there are fallen angels.
We understand that Lucifer, Satan,
he was an anointed cherub.
He, of course, because of his pride,
he's become Satan, the little G God of this world.
But there are some fallen angels that left the estate
when he fell, when he was cast out of heaven.
But then there are faithful angels.
There's a ministry of angels.
We understand this, that angels were created by God.
Amen, angels are created.
Not only are angels created,
but never are angels to be worshiped.
We find that Jesus is greater.
Hebrews talks about how he's greater than everything,
but he takes some time to talk about
he's greater than the angels.
And we find this evening that as we come
to Revelation chapter four,
and we notice how these beasts, these four beasts,
we notice how they're described,
that looking at the scripture here in Revelation four,
verses six through eight, and reading the description,
and then also comparing scripture with scripture,
I would say that these four beasts are seraphims.
That would be the position.
Now listen, there are people that say
it's four representations of the deity of,
or the glory of God, and each one representing
one of the gospels, and so on and so forth.
Matthew, Mark, Luke, John.
I understand some of the imagery there.
But we look here and we see that these four beasts
are mentioned again in chapter number five,
and they're worshiping the Lord.
They're worshiping the Lord here in chapter number four.
And when we look at, again, you may have a study Bible
that may say that they're cherubims,
but you look at the distinction between Isaiah and Ezekiel,
one has six wings, one has four wings.
Not trying to split hairs.
I'm just simply trying to give you my conclusion
as I study through the passage of scripture,
comparing scripture with scripture.
We notice how they're described.
We notice not only how they're described,
but number two, and really, I would say, more importantly.
Why do I say more importantly?
I'm not trying to negate everything I just said
with regard to how they're described
or trying to identify.
So many people wanna know, who are the four beasts?
Who are the four beasts, so on and so forth.
And the reality is that whether they're seraphims,
and some argue that they're cherubims,
and some would argue that, again,
they're imagery of the truth of who God is,
how he's portrayed, how Christ is portrayed in the gospels.
The reality is that what they're doing
is of great significance to us.
Because as we look in the passage of scripture,
we come to verse number seven and eight,
and we find, actually, just look at verse number eight.
The Bible says, and the four beasts had each of them
six wings about him, and they were full of eyes within.
Notice this first phrase.
It says, and they rest not day and night,
saying, holy, holy, holy,
Lord God Almighty, which was and is and is to come.
When we notice what they are doing,
we find that the Bible begins to tell us
how that they rest not day and night.
Can I remind you this evening that there is never a time,
There never will be a time that our God is not on his throne.
Amen?
Listen, they rest not day and night, they're around.
The Bible said, as we looked in verse number six, as he's looking at the throne, and before
the throne there was a sea of glass like unto crystal, and in the midst of the throne and
around about the throne were four beasts, the description is given, but then the Bible
says that they rest not day and night.
There's never a time, there never will be a time that God is not on his throne.
There's never a time, there never will be a time that God is not in control.
There's never a time, there never will be a time that God is not holy.
That God is not almighty.
That God is not eternal.
That he is not worthy.
And we find this evening, as we look at the behavior and what these four beasts are doing,
it reminds us of who our God is.
And it reminds us this evening, as it tells us, just that little phrase that they rest
not day and night.
I want you to get a glimpse into this throne room of heaven.
And again, tonight, all we can really do is read about it, and all we can really do is
in our sanctified imagination try to picture it.
But one day we'll be there.
And we'll see this same scene that John had the opportunity to see.
And for all of eternity, we, if you're saved this evening, you've been saved by the blood
of Christ, you're heaven born, you're born again, the reality is that we will be there,
we will see this and notice the Bible says that they rest not day and night, and then
notice what they're saying.
Number one, holy, holy, holy.
You think about the character of our God.
Our God is holy.
I want you to consider, it's first mentioned in the book of Leviticus with regard to God
saying to His people, be holy, for I am holy.
We find that God is teaching His people as He's brought them out of the Egyptian bondage
and He's preparing to take them into the land of promise, and He's revealing to them the
manner in which they are to behave and the fact that they're not to do after the things
that they saw in Egypt, nor should they do after the manner in which they'll see in the
land.
No, be holy, for I am holy.
We find that Peter will repeat that truth.
In fact, take your Bible and look over very quickly at 1 Peter, and I want you to see
in 1 Peter chapter number one, I want you to notice this thing of holiness is so important.
Brother Jeff was teaching this morning about the Nazarite vow and truly the word meaning
to be separated, and the separation, and we as God's people, we're to be holy because
our God is holy, and we find that these four beasts, what is it that they're doing?
Well, they rest not day and night, and they're saying, number one, they're saying, holy,
holy, holy, and 1 Peter chapter one in verse number 13, the Bible says, wherefore, girt
up the loins of your mind, be sober, and hope to the end for the grace that is to be
brought unto you at the revelation of Jesus Christ.
Notice verses 14 and following, as obedient children, notice this phrase, not fashioning
yourselves according to the former lust in your ignorance.
Listen, I'm not what I used to be.
I shouldn't desire to be what I used to be, amen?
I've been saved by the grace of God, I'm a new creature.
If any man be in Christ, he's a new creature, old things are passed away, behold, all things
are become new, and he says, not fashioning yourselves according to the former lust in
your ignorance, but as he which hath called you is holy.
So, be ye holy in, what does he say, all manner of conversation.
You know what that word conversation means?
It means your behavior, your lifestyle.
In every area of our lives, we're understanding the Holy Spirit of God.
If you're saved, if you're born again, the Holy Spirit of God indwells you, and your
body is the temple of the Holy Ghost, and we find here that he says, because it is written,
be holy, for I am holy, Leviticus.
Here we find that as Peter is writing to a group of people that are scattered abroad,
facing great persecution, all the difficulties that they're facing, the fiery trial as it
will be described later in this epistle, we find that Peter reminds the recipients of
the importance of holy living, holy living, separated.
When we look at the throne room of heaven, we find that these four beasts, what are they
doing?
Well, they rest not day and night.
Number one, they're saying, holy, holy, holy.
Our God is holy, and he expects for us to be holy.
Notice, not only do they say, holy, holy, holy, but the Bible says, Lord God Almighty.
Aren't you thankful that he's the Almighty God?
He is Lord of lords, he is King of kings, he has all power.
I think about the reference to Abram there in Genesis chapter 17, El Shaddai, I am the
Lord God Almighty, and we find here that these four beasts, that they rest not day
and night, and they're crying out, holy, holy, holy, Lord God Almighty.
I want you to be reminded this evening that our God has all power.
He is the Lord God Almighty.
And he, the Bible says that Jesus, he makes this declaration that I have all power in
heaven and in earth.
He didn't say I have most power, he didn't say I have some power, he said I have all
power.
And what a joy to understand that he says, but ye shall receive power after that the
Holy Ghost has come upon you.
And we find this evening that as these four beasts are there at the throne in heaven,
that what are they saying?
Holy, holy, holy, Lord God Almighty.
But then notice the last phrase, which was, and is, and is to come.
What are they referencing?
Well they're referencing the eternality of God.
He's Alpha and Omega.
He's the beginning and the end.
He has given to us this truth.
In fact, as we began reading and studying through the book of Revelation, we understand
that Jesus makes this declaration in chapter number one, in verse number four, John to
the seven churches which are in Asia, grace be unto you and peace from him, which is,
and which was, and which is to come.
Verse number eight, I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the ending, saith the Lord,
which is, and which was, and which is to come, the Almighty.
That's our God.
That's the one that we serve.
That's the one that loves us, that has a plan for our lives, that wants to use us for his
honor and for his glory.
He wants us to be that channel, that conduit that he can use to bring honor and glory to
his name.
The Bible says that these four beasts, referencing the character of God, holy, holy, holy, the
power of God, Lord God Almighty, the eternality of God, which was, and is, and is to come.
And I look here at this passage of Scripture and I begin to, to dig in and begin to look
at the scene in the throne room of heaven and we notice the throne and the scene that's
there and him that sat on it and we, we notice the twenty-four elders, the four and twenty
elders and we, we dealt with that a few weeks ago and then we come to these four beasts
and again the question so often that people ask is, who are they?
And I would submit to you this evening that the real question that we should focus on
is what are they saying?
And then we begin to examine our own lives and we say it of ourselves, what are we saying?
What are we saying about our God?
What do other people know about our God because of what we've said?
Are we saying as we would raise and use our voice, our lips, our tongue, are we, are we
speaking of the character of our God?
Are we speaking, are we saying how wonderful our God is?
He's holy.
He's righteous.
He's just.
Oh, he's love, absolutely.
He's gracious.
He's merciful.
On and on, he's long-suffering.
Aren't you thankful for the long-suffering of God?
This evening when we begin to think about and notice in the passage of Scripture what
these four beasts are saying, we really need to turn the, the focus of the passage on our
own lives and say what are we saying about our God?
Do we speak about his power?
What God is able to do?
Do we have that faith that my God is able?
You don't understand the circumstances.
No, you don't understand my God.
That kind of talk.
You know, you understand what I'm saying.
the faith that is built within us.
So then faith cometh by hearing
and hearing by the word of God
that we've read and we've spent time,
as the preacher mentioned this morning,
that we've been with Jesus,
that we have this proper view of who our God is
and what he's capable of doing.
And we understand this evening that he has all power.
There's nothing, zero, not one thing
that's too hard for our God.
Amen?
Do you believe that tonight?
Do we truly believe that this evening?
Nothing, as it says in Luke chapter number one,
is impossible with God.
Sometimes we sing that little chorus,
nothing is impossible.
And it's true.
Our God is able.
We are to be saying and proclaiming
what we know to be true.
We sang this morning, how great thou art.
You know, this morning when we sang that song,
the reality is that most, not all,
but most people within the walls of this building
already would agree that God is great.
In fact, most people within the walls
of this building this morning
could provide some level of answer
with regard to why God is great.
But you know who doesn't know that God's great?
The people out there.
You know how they're gonna find out that God's great?
If we talk about it.
You ever hear that little song, Let's Talk About Jesus?
It's a little chorus, Let's Talk About Jesus.
And the reality is that these four beasts,
they rest not day and night.
Holy, holy, holy Lord God Almighty,
which was and is and is to come.
Listen, do you believe that Jesus is coming?
I believe he's coming.
I believe he's coming soon.
What does that do for us?
Does it motivate us?
Does it cause us to have a greater zeal for the Lord
to do what we can do?
Listen, the reality is that once the trumpet sounds,
once we're out of here, once we take that final breath,
we're not gonna give one more dollar to missions
or to the cause of Christ.
We're not gonna pass out one more gospel tract.
We're not gonna share the gospel with one more person.
It's all done at that point for us.
Are we motivated?
I believe that we read the book of Acts the way that we do
because those disciples in chapter number one,
they saw the ascension of the Lord Jesus Christ
and they heard the angels say
that this same Jesus shall so come in like manner.
And they had no idea how soon or when he would come.
They had already asked,
is it now time that you'd restore the kingdom?
It's not for you to know, but here's what you need to know.
Here's your job, here's your duty.
And so this evening,
we'll begin to look at the passage of scripture.
And I've tried to give you an answer
of who they are based on the description,
but I want us to really focus on what they're doing,
what they're saying.
What is it?
How is it that others would describe your God, my God,
based on what they've heard us say?
How accurate of a description would they have
biblically speaking of God
if it's fully dependent on what they've heard us say?
Think about that just for a moment.
What do they know about our God?
Here's what Hebrews 13 says.
In fact, we'll hit this verse again
next Sunday evening as well as part of the message,
but it's such a powerful verse.
It's worth using multiple times
to let it sink into our minds and our hearts.
In Hebrews 13 and verse number 15, the Bible says this,
by him, therefore, let us offer
the sacrifice of praise to God.
What does it say?
Continually, let me just think about that continually.
And I understand we need rest
unlike those four beasts, the angels, we need rest,
but they rest not day and night.
You said, there's no way I could talk
about Jesus all day long.
I understand we have responsibilities
and so on and so forth,
but there's a lot of stuff we talk about.
There's a lot of stuff we talk about.
There's a lot of things that we talk about
that are temporal, temporary,
that really don't matter in the big scheme of things.
And the reality is that the Bible says
that we're to offer the sacrifice
of praise to God continually,
and then it describes it,
that is the fruit of our lips giving thanks to his name.
It said this way in 1 Thessalonians,
in everything give thanks,
for this is the will of God
and Christ Jesus concerning you.
So what is it that we're saying?
We see what the beasts are saying.
We see that they rest not day and night.
And they're saying, holy, holy, holy,
Lord God Almighty, which was and is
and is to come this evening.
We see how they're described,
but we see what they're doing.
And the question for us tonight is what are we saying?
What did we say last week about our God?
When that issue arose,
when that problem came in our lives,
what did we say?
This week, you say, I hope I don't have any problems.
Man that is born of woman is few days and full of trouble.
I don't like problems either, amen?
But the reality
is that even in the midst of the difficulties,
he is to be praised.
And can I tell you that in the midst of the difficulties
when we praise him in the manner
in which we're speaking about this evening,
it has a great impact on those around us.
Why?
Because they're expecting for us to complain and murmur
and woe is me and I don't understand
and I can't believe what else could go wrong
and so on and so forth.
This evening, when we get into the fourth chapter
in the throne room of heaven,
we see the throne, we see the four and 20 elders,
we see these four beasts,
but we notice tonight what they're saying.
And I hope that we would examine our own lives.
What are we saying?
What are we talking about?
Are we offering the praise of our lips to our God?
Continually?
Are we praising him?
Are we thanking him?
We're talking about how great he is.
I mean, when you think something is great,
you talk about it.
Amen?
If you've had a great meal, you talk about it.
A great experience, you talk about it.
Our God surpasses all of that.
All of it.
We ought to be talking about him, amen?
He is king of kings and Lord of lords.
He is the great, he is the Lord God Almighty,
the great I am.
And it is our job, our responsibility and our privilege
to talk about him, to lift up his name and praise him.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the privilege
of being able to study your word.
God, as we seek to make some application in our lives tonight
from this passage of scripture
and we see the challenge has been brought before us.
And God, I thank you for challenging my heart.
Lord, I pray that you would help us
to speak the things that we ought to speak.
That we would learn from this portion of scripture,
not only how these four beasts are described,
but Lord, that we'd be greatly impacted
by what they're doing.
Help us to examine our own lives.
Help us this week to say the things that we ought to say,
to speak of thee.
Lord, help others around us to know how great you are,
how powerful you are, how holy and righteous you are,
because we've opened our mouth and we've praised your name.
Would you move and work in these moments as only you can
we'll give you the honor and glory
for it's in Christ's name we pray, we just.