1 Timothy chapter number five.
Many of you know that we've been studying
through the book of 1 Timothy here on Sunday mornings
for the calendar year of 2024.
And once we're finished with 1 Timothy,
we'll go right into 2 Timothy.
Our theme for this year is continue.
And we see that thought and that theme throughout this book
and both books, 1 and 2 Timothy,
and we're very thankful for the opportunity
that we have to be able to study
this portion of scripture this morning.
This letter, as you know, those who have been here,
and for those of you that have not,
we'll get into the text this morning,
but this letter from Paul to Timothy
provides encouragement.
We all need encouragement, don't we?
And there are times in this life
that it can become overwhelming
and we need to receive encouragement.
We find that Timothy was left in Ephesus with a great task.
And that task was at times overwhelming.
He's dealing with false teachers
and all sorts of things that are going on.
And we find that God would use Paul to write this letter,
of course, under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
to give encouragement to his man,
to his servant to continue.
We find not only does this letter provide encouragement,
but it provides a warning.
And by the way, we all need encouragement,
but there are times that we all need warnings.
And I'm thankful that the Bible tells us
in the book of Psalms in the 19th chapter,
that by them speaking of God's word
and how thankful I am for the word
is thy servant warned.
And in keeping of them is great reward.
You have many things in your house today
that have warning labels on them.
You drive, you drove here this morning
and you saw various signs.
And at times you see warning about something that's ahead,
something that you're going to face.
And we find that there are warnings in life,
but God also in his word has provided us with warnings
and oh, how thankful I am for the encouragement.
Oh, how thankful I am for the warnings.
We also find that God gives instruction
and oh, how we need instruction.
I know that many of us men,
we've tried to put things together before
without the instructions.
And maybe we've come to a place
where we've gotten frustrated.
We thought what's going on?
Is it written in a different language?
Is it upside down?
Who wrote these instructions?
And we set them to the side and say,
we're gonna just do it ourselves.
And if you do it, like I do it,
you get to do it two or three times by yourself.
And find those instructions that you set aside
and realize humbly that I probably
should take these instructions
because whoever wrote them knows more than I do.
You know, God gave us a wonderful book.
He is the omniscient God.
He's the all wise God.
He knows more than all of us together.
And he has given us instruction in his word
and oh, how we need the instruction and how blessed we are.
Timothy was ministering there in Ephesus.
He had a great responsibility.
I mentioned already that the false teachers,
they were active and Timothy needed
to withstand their activity.
He needed to withstand their false teaching.
He needed to guide the members of the church
in the way that they ought to go.
We find that the members of that church
needed to understand how they were to properly behave
and also interact one with another.
We find that throughout this letter,
as we've mentioned in previous messages,
that God gives instruction for behavior in his house
and how we are to behave ourselves.
There is behavior that is appropriate
and there's behavior that's inappropriate.
I was at a conference this past week
and I was at that conference and they listed
right on all the instruction after you registered
to go to that conference.
It said, by the way, at the bottom of it,
it said, if you do this, this, or this,
you will be escorted immediately.
And I thought, well, there is behavior for this conference
that's appropriate and acceptable
and there is behavior for this conference
that is not going to be tolerated
and they put it right there in black and white letters.
If you do these things, you are out
and by the way, no refund.
And they weren't playing games.
And what I say to you this morning
is that the house of God is a sacred place.
It's a holy place as his people are gathered together
as we pray for his presence to be with us,
that we desire to worship him in spirit and in truth,
that there is behavior that is appropriate and acceptable
and there is behavior that is not well-pleasing to God.
And we find here this morning that through this book
that God has given not only encouragement
and warning and instruction,
we benefit just as Timothy did,
just as the church in Ephesus did,
we today benefit from all of these things.
And I'm thankful this morning
that the Lord is the head of the church, it's his church.
It's not my church, it's not your church, it's his church.
And he promises that he will build his church
and that the gates of hell shall not prevail against it.
By the way, that's a promise that's made in Matthew 16
that we can stand upon, that we can trust
and that we can rejoice in
and knowing that he is king of kings
and Lord of lords, he's on his throne.
We sang this morning, Jesus saves,
and what a joy to know that he does.
I wanna remind you that he's coming back again.
I don't know when he's coming,
but I'm looking forward to hearing the trumpet of the Lord.
Amen, in time shall be no more.
We're gonna go be with our Lord and savior.
He's the head of the church.
As the head of the church,
he has graciously instructed his church.
Not only the church here in Ephesus
that Timothy had the responsibility to lead and to guide,
but we find that God has providentially preserved his word
so that every church throughout the era
of the church history would have the instruction
so that we would know how we are to behave,
so that we would know how we're to interact one with another
so that we would understand how we can please the Lord.
I don't wanna be in a position as a church,
as an individual, as a family.
I don't wanna be in a position
where God would look at my life as an individual,
our home as a family, our church corporately,
and say, I am not pleased.
No, I long for God to be pleased with my life
and with us as a church.
I do not want, as you would read in the Old Testament,
Ichabod written that the glory of the Lord hath departed.
No, we serve a risen God.
He lives.
We sang it this morning.
And what a joy to know that he is the head of our church
and he has given us instruction
that when that instruction is followed,
it enables us to please him.
A few weeks ago, we started 1 Timothy chapter number five,
and the first section of this particular book
addresses relationships in the church,
and it deals with the senior saints and the younger saints,
and it deals with widows.
And we studied that portion of scripture
beginning in verse number one down through verse number 16.
We mentioned that the senior saints
are referenced as being the elder in verses one and two,
and that's not the office of the elder, the pastor.
That is just those that were older
that I've referred to as being senior saints.
You say, pastor, I'm a senior saint.
You figure it out.
I'm not going there, amen?
But the reality is that there are, in every good church,
a church that should have different ages
of people in the church.
There should be some senior saints,
but there should be some new believers.
And everywhere in between, why?
Because we're pressing forward for the cause of Christ
to reach a lost and dying world.
We find that the chapter concludes
beginning in verse number 17
down through the end of the chapter in verse number 25
with instruction regarding elders.
Now, this is the office of a pastor
that is being referenced.
You'll recall, maybe you were here several weeks ago
as we studied there in chapter number three,
and the Bible says, this is a true saying
in verse number one, if a man desire the office of a bishop,
he desireth a good work.
And we mentioned as we studied
through that portion of scripture
that God uses these terms in his word
of bishop and elder interchangeably,
and they refer to the same office that we refer to today
as being the office of the pastor.
And we find that the instruction is given
when he begins in verse number 17,
let the elders that rule well
be counted worthy of double honor,
especially they who labor in the word and doctrine
for the scripture saith, thou shall not muzzle the ox
that treadeth out the corn,
and the laborer is worthy of his reward.
Notice again in verse 19,
against an elder received an accusation,
but before two or three witnesses.
And so we find that in verse number 17,
and then again in verse number 19,
that he addresses in this section,
the elder, the pastor of the church.
I've titled the message this morning,
Honorable Elders, Honorable Elders.
I only have two points for you this morning,
but don't get excited.
That doesn't mean the message will be any shorter.
And the reality is that many of you take notes
and you get used to having three points
throughout the message.
This morning, we have two thoughts for you.
Number one, if you're taking notes,
the compensation for an elder,
the compensation for an elder.
I read verse 17 and 18.
Let me read them again for you.
The Bible says, let the elders that rule well
be counted worthy of double honor,
especially they who labor in the word and doctrine
for the scripture saith, thou shall not muzzle the ox
that treadeth out the corn,
and the laborer is worthy of his reward.
As we're gonna look at this passage of scripture again,
God is giving to the church at Ephesus
to Timothy as its leader,
instruction for behavior in the church,
that which pleases the Lord.
the Lord, that which does not please the Lord. He deals in the beginning of the
chapter the interactions between the senior saints, the younger believers. He
deals extensively in this chapter with widows, and then he comes to the subject
of dealing with the elders. He begins in verses 17 and 18 by dealing with the
compensation for an elder. Before we really deal with the compensation, I
want you to understand that the pastor has a responsibility. The responsibility
the pastor is dictated for us here. Notice the Bible says, let the elders
that rule well be counted worthy of double honor, but then notice the end of
the verse, especially they who, do you see the word labor? In word and doctrine. The
end of verse number 18, the laborer is worthy of his reward. The pastor has a
responsibility to labor in the word and in doctrine. It is my God-given
responsibility. When God called me to be a pastor, when God placed that call upon
my life, He gave me responsibility, and the responsibility is great. The
responsibility to feed the flock of God. What a joy that I have. I thoroughly
enjoy preaching and teaching God's Word. Sometimes, if we're not careful, we could
think that that's the only aspect of pastoring. It really is just the most
public aspect of the ministry of being a pastor, but we find that it's such an
important aspect. The pastor has a responsibility to labor in the word and
in doctrine. We find that it's so imperative that we understand this
morning that the pastor, that as I personally have the opportunity to
fulfill that role at Fellowship Baptist Church, that it is laboring in God's Word.
Someone asked me years ago, they came to me and they meant it as a compliment, and
they said this, pastor, those messages that you've preached have been very
helpful. I very much enjoy them. Are you getting them from a book? And I said, yes,
the Bible. And the reality is that I study, and I'm not patting myself on the
back, it is my God-given responsibility to dig into the Word of God and to
provide the flock of God with truth, with doctrine, that which is going to
help, that which is going to build up so that we might be sound in the faith.
That's my responsibility. That is a pastor's responsibility. We find that
that's not the end of the responsibility, but with regard to the context of what
we're looking at here, we find that he speaks about this laboring in word and
in doctrine. I like the fact that he uses the word labor because it is work. It is
work. And there are times I've been asked this question, how long does it take to
prepare a message? And the reality is that it varies. Sometimes a message can
come to you real quick. I mean, God just, man, He just gives...other times it is
just...it is work. And someone asked me, what do you do all week? I said, well, how
about you come and visit with me all week? And you can shadow me all week. It's
an open invitation. You can be with me. And then if you want to preach four
times next week, you go ahead and do it. You get to prepare four lessons next week.
And it's labor. Listen, I'm not interested in giving some cheap meal to our church.
I'm just not. The reality is that you can have, I think, about often this context of
feeding the flock of God. And I like home-cooked meals. I much prefer home-cooked
meals over frozen entrees. Amen? I like fresh home-cooked meals more than I like
leftovers. Now, I'll eat leftovers because I don't want to waste it, but I like it
when there's no leftovers. Why? Because that means there's another fresh meal
tomorrow. Amen? Joseph hates leftovers. I mean, he just...last...the week before they
went to camp, it seemed like every day we had leftovers. And Holly said, what do you
want for lunch? I said, I do not want any more leftovers. I am leftovered out.
Listen, this book is a living book. This Word will help you and it will help me.
And every time I come to the pulpit, I want to come with a fresh truth that God
has given to us with a measure of excitement. Why? Because this is God's Word
and it's a living book. This is not dead orthodoxy. This is not religion. And we
were knocking doors, Ronnie and I knocking doors, not yesterday, but last Saturday.
And some man says, well, you know, just to be honest with you, I'm not a religious
person. Isn't that what he said, Ronnie? And I said, well, sir, neither am I. And he
said, I don't believe you. He put his hand on his hip and he said, I don't believe
you. And I just introduced myself as being from the church. And he said, you've got
to be a religious person. Religion. I'm not interested in religion. I'm
interested in relationship with the Lord Jesus Christ. And what a joy to know that
he lives and he lives within me. And it's real. It's not just dead orthodoxy. And I
desire to fulfill the responsibility. I know. Listen, I'm not the greatest
preacher I don't ever claim to be, but I want to give God's Word. It's the
responsibility. But let me say this, not only does the pastor have a responsibility,
the church has a responsibility. He says in verse number 18, notice what he says,
for the scripture saith. This is a biblical truth. This is not just Timothy,
Paul's opinion that he's given to Timothy. He says, this is a, the scripture saith.
This is a biblical truth. By the way, when he uses this phrase and says, for the
scripture saith, he references really two verses of scripture. Thou shall not muzzle
the ox that treadeth out the corn, and the laborer is worthy of his reward. We're
not going to take the time, but if you went back to Deuteronomy 25 in verse
number four, and if you went back to Luke chapter 10 in verse number seven, those
are the two references that are given to us in verse number 18. And we find that
Paul, under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God, refers to both of those as
being scripture. And that's an important thing for us to understand. I'm so
thankful for the scripture, for the word of God, for thus saith the Lord. And so
what does he say? He says that the, in verse number 17, let the elders that rule
well be counted worthy of double honor, especially they who labor in the word and
doctrine. For the scripture saith, thou shall not muzzle the ox that treadeth out
the corn, and the laborer is worthy of his reward. We find that the pastor,
indeed, it's certainly to be noted that the pastor is not to be greedy, a filthy
lucre. The Bible gives that as a requirement in 1 Timothy 3. In verse
number 3, he again says it in 1 Peter chapter 5, in verse number 2. But we
understand this morning that the pastor must be compensated in order to provide
for his family. It just is what it is. Now, I'll be honest with you, this is one
of the hardest subjects for me to ever preach on. It really is. It's a difficult
subject, being the pastor of the church. This is an easy passage to preach from if
I'm preaching somewhere else, just to be honest with you, because it's a biblical
truth. Why do I say it's a difficult thing? Because people hear what they want
to hear. They receive what they want to receive. They think, assume what they want
to assume. And so let me be very clear this morning, before I say anything more,
I would like to say this. Fellowship Baptist Church has been good to us,
and I appreciate that. It's been a blessing to our family. But I want you to
understand that not all churches have this understanding, not all churches have
this perspective. I know churches right now that need pastors. In our state of
Virginia, our Commonwealth of Virginia, there are churches that need pastors.
You begin to talk to those churches, you say, well, what are you going to be able
to compensate them? Well, we just can't pay them. Well, how do you want somebody
to come and minister? What do you want them to do? Well, we can pay them $25,000.
Can you live on $25,000 a year? I'm just being honest with you. And it's one of
those things you begin to look at and you say, listen, the pastor, he has a responsibility,
but the church has a responsibility. And we understand that this is what God's plan is.
This is God's truth that He's given to us. Look at a few verses of Scripture with me.
Turn to the book of Romans, if you will. It's not just a truth that's just isolated here
to the book of 1 Timothy. Over the book of Romans, in chapter 15, we're going to look
at three other portions of Scripture very quickly this morning. And again, I've mentioned
already to preface it by saying fellowship after church has been good to us, and we've been blessed,
and I am thankful, and I appreciate the spirit and the attitude of our church family. But the
reality is that not everyone has this understanding. For generations, the idea of many churches was
that the pastor should be poor. That's just the reality. That was the perspective of a lot of
people. And the reality is that God has given a responsibility. Notice in Romans 15, in verse 27,
they have pleased them verily, and their debtors they are. Notice this,
for if the Gentiles have been made partakers of their spiritual things, notice what it says,
their duty is also to minister unto them in carnal things. So we see this distinction
between spiritual things and carnal things. The spiritual things, that's the responsibility of
the pastor. That's the responsibility of the leader of the church with regard to the office
of a pastor in the context of what we're dealing with, that we are to minister. Listen, they're
partakers of spiritual things, but then it says their duty is also to minister unto them in carnal
things. I've heard people say this over the years, well, the pastor can just go get a job.
He can, absolutely. But do you know how that changes the ministry of the pastor?
Honestly, it changes.
The pastor is working a full-time job somewhere else so that he can provide for his family.
By the way, he has a Biblical responsibility to provide for his family.
Amen?
He has a Biblical responsibility.
If he doesn't provide for his family, he's worse than an infidel.
We read that last time we were in 1 Timothy chapter 5, and so there's a Biblical responsibility.
Oh, well, the pastor can go to a job.
He can.
But if the pastor's working 40, 50 hours a week, how available do you think he is to
prepare messages?
How available do you think he is when you pick up the phone and say, hey, I have a ... And
you get voicemail.
You get no call back.
Why?
Because he's at work.
It's just the way it is.
I know a pastor friend down in the Richmond area, and he's pastor of the church for 27
years now.
But he shared this story with me, he's about to retire, and he shared this story with me
when he first got there to pastor.
They just flat out did not pay him like they should have or like they could have.
The finances were there.
It wasn't a matter of not having the ability, it was just that they chose not to.
And so after being there for about two months, he realized, I'm going in debt.
I can't cover the expenses of my family that's more expensive to live here than I thought
it was going to be.
And he put all these numbers together and he went and he had a meeting with the men
of the church after a Sunday morning.
And here's what he said, folks, I just want you to know, I'm going tomorrow to get a job.
He said, what do you mean you're getting a job?
Well, here's what you're paying me and here's what my expenses are and I just can't survive.
He didn't ask for them to pay him anymore.
He didn't demand that they pay them anymore.
He just simply said, I got to go get a job.
And then he asked this question.
He said, I just want to know how many of you could live here on that salary.
And they said, pastor, would you be dismissed?
And they decided that day that they were going to pay him like they should have, like they
could have, so that he didn't have to go get another job.
Here's the Lord.
But the reality is that it's a biblical responsibility, these carnal things, and it's a mindset that
sometimes people have, well, you can just go get a job.
Well, it affects the whole ministry.
There are some pastors that are bivocational, just the way it has to be.
And that's a sad situation when it has to be that way because you can't do both well.
First Corinthians chapter number nine, notice what the Bible says in this portion of Scripture.
In First Corinthians nine, Paul is writing to the church in Corinth, and he's giving
the same truth that he mentioned to those in Rome.
He says in verse 11 of First Corinthians nine, if we have sown unto you spiritual things,
is it a great thing if we shall reap your carnal things?
Again, he uses these two terms of spiritual and carnal.
He's not using the word carnal in Romans or here in First Corinthians as being a bad thing.
Like he says to them, you're carnal, you can't receive these things.
That's a negative connotation.
But when he's talking here, he's talking about the things that we need to live, to survive.
Most of you are not going to go to work for free, amen?
Most of you, when you got a job wherever you're working, you found out what you were going
to be compensated, amen?
You did.
I didn't.
I didn't ask the question.
When I came to pastor this church, I had zero idea what I was going to get paid.
I'm just being honest.
Those men that were here the day that I accepted the position, they can verify that.
I did not know.
Every year that I've been here, Doc was the treasurer for years, then Jared, and then
now Pierre, and Dean is one of our deacons, been a deacon since I've been here.
Every year, and these men, Jared's not here anymore, he moved to South Carolina, but they
can verify every year they would come to me and say, pastor, what do you need to make?
What do you need for a pay raise?
I've never answered the question.
Not one time.
When I worked in the corporate world, I got everything I could get.
I'm just being honest with you.
I negotiated.
It's different in the spiritual world, but the pastor still has needs.
Some of you have paid for college for your children.
Don't you think a pastor wants to pay for college for his children?
Again, don't take this as a negative to our church.
The church has been great to us.
It's a biblical truth that unfortunately there are churches today that they don't understand
it.
They think this, the pastor's just in it for the money.
There are some that are.
There are some that are, and it's terrible.
They ought not be in that position, but can I tell you because there are some that are,
it doesn't mean all are.
There are some that are laboring in the word and in doctrine, and they are, as we've titled
the message this morning, honorable elders.
In Galatians chapter 6, a third reference that God gives us with regard to this subject
matter, and we'll move right along.
Notice in Galatians 6 and verse number 6, let him that is taught in the word communicate
unto him that teacheth in all good things.
It's the same principle that we saw in the book of Romans, in the book of 1 Corinthians.
Now if you understand the book of Galatians, there's not a church in Galatia that's being
written to.
There are four churches in the region of Galatia that were established during the first missionary
journey.
Now we see it in 1 Timothy with regard to the instruction to the church and to Timothy
there in Ephesus, and so we find that this is a biblical truth, this is a biblical responsibility.
I've had the privilege of working with new pastors that are starting churches, and can
I tell you it's a difficult thing when you've got to start talking about money.
It's just complicated, it's difficult.
I didn't have any problem in the corporate world, but it's different in the church setting.
And I've talked to pastors, I said, listen, you are robbing your church of their God-given
responsibility to compensate you, because it is a God-given responsibility.
Well, we just want to support more missionaries.
It's great to support more missionaries, but you better take care of your pastor.
It's a responsibility that God has given.
So we see, first of all, the compensation for an elder.
Number two, I want you to notice in this passage of Scripture the conduct of an elder, the
conduct of an elder.
Now as we look at the rest of the text, beginning in verse 19 down through verse 25, we find
that God is going to deal with the conduct.
Now listen, the qualifications for an elder are detailed in 1 Timothy chapter 3.
We see them in the book of Titus as well, but we've studied them, and we said that the
qualifications are given.
These aren't just, we would like it if you had, no, these are qualifications, he must
be.
All right?
That's the verbiage that is used repeatedly.
And so we see the qualifications are outlined in detail in 1 Timothy chapter number 3.
In 1 Timothy chapter number 5, we find that we are provided with some practical instruction
regarding the conduct of an elder.
Let me remind you, I mentioned in 1 Peter chapter 5 in verse number 2, you don't need
to turn there, but it talks about filthy lucre or those that are there for lucre, but we
find that it also says in verse number 3 that the elder or the pastor is an ensample to
the flock, an ensample to the flock.
It's a sad thing this morning that there are some elders, even here in recent days,
that have been exposed for some great wickedness.
I know an elder, a pastor, that sat in a courtroom after he was charged with heinous crimes,
and he sat in that courtroom and he said this quote when he gave an answer to the judge,
I did not know I was breaking the law.
I will not tell you what the man was guilty of doing.
It is absolutely immoral and egregious, but he said to the judge, I did not know I was
breaking the law.
What was he referring to?
He was referring to the law of the land, but I want you to know he was breaking God's law.
Regardless of what the law of the land was, he was breaking God's law.
And listen, the Bible says in the book of Romans, hey, you that teach that you shouldn't
steal, do you steal?
No, it doesn't work that way.
The conduct of an elder is of great importance, and he is to be an example to the flock.
We see here in the text of Scripture a couple of things that we want to note.
Number one, an elder should pursue purity.
An elder should pursue purity.
And I'm going to say this at the end.
I'll say it now, I'll say it again at the end.
These truths that we're looking at with regard to the conduct of an elder are not just isolated
for elders.
Every child of God should pursue purity.
Because every man that hath this hope, what hope according to 1 John 3, that Jesus is
coming again, he maketh himself pure even as he is pure.
So this idea of pursuing purity is not just something that's reserved for the elder, for
the pastor of the church, but we find that all of God's people should pursue purity.
We see that, look in verse number 19, it talks about dealing with sin in verses 19 and 20.
Now, we understand that no person, pastor, elder, church person, no individual saved
by the grace of God person is ever going to reach a place of sinless perfection.
Amen?
And listen, I'm thankful this morning that I have been saved and I have been delivered
from the power of sin and from the penalty of sin, but I have not yet been delivered
from the presence of sin.
One day, one glorious day.
I'm going to go to heaven, and I don't know when that's going to be,
but I'm looking forward to going to heaven.
And guess what? There is no sin in heaven.
I am so thankful we will be delivered from the very presence of sin.
Actively right now, sin no longer has power over me.
Why? Because I've been saved by the grace of God.
I'm no longer bound by the power of sin.
Greater is he that is in you than he that is in the world.
But thanks be to God which giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.
Listen, it's not a valid thing to say, I just didn't have a choice.
No, you did have a choice.
Walk in the Spirit, and you shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
But we're never going to be sinless.
Okay? We're never going to be sinless.
But we find here that as we look at this passage of Scripture with this pursuit of purity,
it should be that our desire as we walk with Christ is that we sin less and less.
That we don't get comfortable with sin in our lives, for any child of God.
But especially as we look at the context here with regard to a pastor, an elder,
he says, then that sin rebuke before all that others also may fear.
Listen, the pastor is not above the law.
It should never be thought of that way. It should never be presented that way.
No, listen, how many of you, and I know we've got some police officers here, and that's fine.
I don't mean to offend you.
But the reality is, some of the times you get irritated with a police officer
that's going 95 miles an hour down the road, and then he wants to pull you over for going 72.
You're like, what's up with that?
Now, I haven't gotten pulled over recently, praise the Lord, so I'm not nothing.
But I'm just saying, it's frustrating. Why?
Because the police officer's acting like he's above the law. Right?
He has this little badge that he can show his body, and he can get away.
It doesn't always happen that way, but I'm saying it can be a frustrating thing.
The pastor is not above the law.
The pastor is more accountable to whom much is given, much is required.
And we find that a pastor, an honorable elder, he should be pursuing purity.
And we deal with sin. We see it in verses 19 and 20.
We find, notice in verse 21,
I charge thee before God and the Lord Jesus Christ and the elect angels
that thou observe these things without preferring one before another,
doing nothing by partiality.
Notice in verse 22, lay hands suddenly on no man,
neither be partaker of other men's sins.
Notice these three words, keep thyself pure.
Listen, there are some things that you need to do in your life.
There are some fences that you need to put up in your life to preserve purity
as you're pursuing purity.
A fence doesn't, it serves two purposes.
A fence is not just to keep you in.
You know how many young people have the idea that fences are just to keep you in?
I want to do, but my parents won't let me.
No, no, the fences, the warnings, they don't only just keep you in,
but they keep evil out.
And it's a blessing.
And here he says, keep thyself pure.
We mentioned already in 1 John chapter 3, verses 1 through 3,
we believe that Jesus is coming again, and if we have that belief,
we are to purify ourselves even as he is pure.
And so we find, notice in verse 24 specifically,
it says this, some men's sins are open beforehand,
going before the judgment, and some men they follow after.
Likewise, also verse 25, the good works of some are manifest beforehand,
and they that are otherwise cannot be hid.
What's he saying in verse 24 and 25?
Listen, sometimes you can see the wickedness from a mile away.
Sometimes people have gotten clever on how to cover it up.
But can I remind you of a secret?
It's really not a secret.
You can't cover anything from God.
You can try.
But Proverbs says, he that covereth his sins shall not prosper.
Shall not prosper.
Whoso confesseth and forsaketh, well then, they're going to find mercy.
Why? Because we have a merciful God.
We have a gracious God.
We have a God that the Bible says that with thee there is forgiveness.
Hallelujah.
I remember Rachel there in the book of Genesis.
She knew that she had the stuff in the tent.
What about as you look at Achan?
The troubler of Israel is referred to in the book of 1 Chronicles.
He knew that he had stuff in the tent.
He took of the accursed thing.
I want you to know that though they knew and they hid, that God exposed.
There's a truth in the book of Numbers that says be sure your sin will find you out.
The reality is that sometimes you can see it from a mile away.
Sometimes people are not really good at covering things up.
But you can't hide from God.
You can't hide from God.
God knows, he sees, he's everywhere present.
The reality this morning is that the truth of God being everywhere present
is a truth that causes me to have great comfort,
but it also should bring great conviction because he's everywhere.
He's with you.
And we're to pursue purity.
Not only pursue purity, but number two, when we talk about the conduct of an elder,
we should pursue purity.
We should reject partiality.
Reject partiality.
Notice what the Bible says in verse 21.
Really this idea of partial or being partial to someone
or this idea of partiality as being a respecter of persons.
And we're to be no respecter of persons.
Verse 21, it says, I charge thee before God and the Lord Jesus Christ
and the elect angels that thou observe these things,
notice, without preferring one another, one before another,
notice doing nothing by partiality.
This is a Bible word that's a good word.
We're to not be a respecter of persons.
A minister, a pastor, every child of God
ought to understand this morning that we are all made in the image of God.
Do you believe that this morning?
God is the creator.
And we have been made in his image.
And God so loved who?
The world.
Every person.
And we find that here, he says, let nothing be done by partiality.
And we're to reject partiality,
a word that's so often that would be used in our vernacular today is racism.
And we see it in our society.
We see the divide that it causes.
But I want you to understand as a child of God,
there should be no level of racism whatsoever.
Why?
Because we're all of one blood.
We're all made in the image of God.
We're all valuable in God's sight.
And we must understand this morning that it's absolutely imperative
that we look at the conduct of an elder
and we say not only is he to pursue purity,
but he is to reject partiality.
Not partial to anyone on any basis.
Amen?
That's the biblical truth.
By the way, it's not just a biblical truth for the pastor.
It's a biblical truth for every child of God.
Look at the book of Proverbs, if you will.
We're going to look at just a few verses.
We had a bunch more written down, but we're running out of time this morning.
I told you that two points didn't mean it'd be any faster.
Proverbs 24 and verse 23.
Notice what the Bible says in Proverbs 24 and verse number 23.
These things also belong to the wise.
It is not good to have respective persons in judgment.
Proverbs 28 and verse number 21.
We find again this truth restated.
It says to have respective persons is not good.
For a piece of bread that man will transgress.
We're to be no respecter of persons.
The book of James deals with it this way.
Turn to James chapter 2, if you will.
In the New Testament, the book of James.
And I want you to see in James chapter number 2.
And we will not have time to read the entirety,
the portion of Scripture, really verses 1 through 9.
I'll just read a few of these verses.
This idea of rejecting partiality.
The Bible says in James chapter 2 and verse number 1.
By the way, can I say this?
Jesus was counter-cultural.
What do I mean by that?
Do you know that the Jewish people hated the Samaritans?
They hated them.
They would not go.
They would not interact with.
They would not have conversation with.
They hated the Samaritans.
But Jesus in John chapter number 4 says,
I must needs go through Samaria.
He didn't go around Samaria
as was the standard behavior of the day.
He went through Samaria.
Why?
Well, there's a widow that he needed to meet.
The widow at the well.
By the way, it wasn't just the widow
because she went back
and she told all those people about Jesus.
And there was a great host of people that got saved
because Jesus went to Samaria.
And by the way, when he gave the Great Commission,
he said in the book of Acts,
and you shall be witnesses unto me,
after the Holy Ghost has come upon you,
you shall be witnesses unto me both in Jerusalem, Judea,
and where?
Samaria.
And under the uttermost part of the earth.
He was counter-cultural.
He loved all people.
Because they're all made in the image of God.
In James chapter 2 and verse number 1,
the Bible says this in verse 2,
For if there come unto your assembly a man with a gold ring
and goodly apparel,
and there come in also a poor man in vile raiment,
do you see the picture that's being painted?
You begin to see that one appears
to have some money and the other appears to be poor.
And he says, and ye have respect to him
that weareth the gay clothing.
Now understand that's the old English word of gay, okay?
It's not talking about the new way
that people are using that word, so just understand that.
And saying to him, sit thou here in a good place
and say to the poor, stand thou there
or sit here under my footstool.
Are ye not then partial in yourselves
and are become judges of evil thoughts?
Verse nine, he says this,
but if you have respect to persons, ye commit what?
Sin, that's pretty plain, isn't it?
I think it's not difficult to understand
that verse of scripture.
If ye have respect to persons, you commit sin
and are convinced of the law as transgressors.
You know that back in the book of Deuteronomy in chapter one
and again in chapter number 16,
it talks about not having respect of persons.
This is a Bible truth from the beginning to the end.
Our God has no respect of persons.
By the way, I'm thankful for that.
I'm thankful that our God has no respect of persons.
And we understand that the conduct of an elder
should be to pursue purity.
It should be to reject partiality.
Turn back to 1 Timothy chapter number five, if you will,
and we'll finish here with the matter of wine.
What an exciting subject, hallelujah.
1 Timothy chapter five,
notice what the Bible says in verse number 23.
It's dealing with the conduct of an elder.
In verse 23, I was gonna preach a whole message on this,
but we gotta get going through the whole of this book
and also the next.
But he says, drink no longer water,
but use a little wine for thy stomach's sake
and thine often infirmities.
Now, I wanna understand something this morning
as I begin to deal with this,
the conduct of an elder and addressing specifically
the matter of wine in this text of scripture.
There are two texts of scripture that often people will come
and they will present to someone
when they're trying to justify the use of alcohol.
One of them is this one.
The other is in John chapter two.
And here's what they say.
Well, Jesus turned water into wine.
And Paul told Timothy to drink a little wine.
And they'll use those two texts of scriptures
to justify their idea of drinking alcohol.
They forget that the Bible says
that we're to not look at the wine
when it moveth itself awry.
They forget to understand the truth
that wine is a mocker, strong drink is raging.
Whosoever is deceived thereby is not wise.
And so there's a whole host of scriptures
that people ignore when they try to justify something.
Here's what I've said for years.
If you wanna justify something,
you're gonna figure out a way to do it.
If you wanna do something bad enough,
you're gonna figure out a way to justify it and to do it.
That's just the reality of human nature.
But as I look at this passage of scripture,
there are, or this verse of scripture
with regard to the use a little wine,
there are two key things that must be acknowledged.
Number one, do you notice where he says,
drink no longer water?
Do you see it in your Bible?
He says, drink no longer water.
Now, why would it be that Paul is instructing Timothy
to drink no longer water?
Have you ever traveled somewhere
where the water is not sanitary,
the water is not safe to drink?
So there are, when I went to Mexico,
they said, listen, whatever you do,
do not drink the water.
They said, don't use the water to brush your teeth.
Don't use the water, use a,
we had to use water bottles to brush our teeth
and clean off our toothbrush.
They said, listen, it'll make you sick.
It's not good.
Don't drink it.
So I was really careful.
And we're, it was like the last day we were there.
We're in this big room
and there's different shower units in this room.
And the one pastor that's there, all of a sudden,
we're all in there and he says, oh no.
And he kind of hollers out like that.
We're like, what in the world happened?
We thought there's a snake in there or something,
you know, I have no idea what happened.
And he said, I just used the water to swish out my mouth.
I'm gonna be so sick.
And he was like paranoid, right?
Right away, I'm gonna be so sick.
And the reality is that there are places
you can still travel today
where the water's not safe to drink.
How much more back then?
Timothy is given this instruction, drink no longer water.
But then I want you to notice another key
in the verse of scripture.
He says, for thy stomach's sake
and thine often infirmities.
So there are two keys that are given to us here.
Number one, drink no longer water.
The water was not safe.
The water was causing some difficulties.
By the way, if you drink water that's not sanitary,
if you're traveling abroad
and you partake of water that's not sanitary,
you know what it does?
It adversely affects your digestion.
It makes you sick, all right?
So he says, not only drink no longer water,
but he says in verse 23, for thy stomach's sake
and thine often infirmities.
Obviously, Timothy was dealing with an ongoing issue here.
And with this ongoing issue,
there is a piece of instruction that is given.
What is that instruction?
But use a little wine, use a little wine.
Now it's important for us to understand,
and I'm gonna ask this question this morning.
We believe that God is the creator God.
Do you believe that this morning?
You believe that God is the creator?
Do you believe that God is omniscient,
that he knows all things?
I believe that this morning.
Do you believe that God is the author of the Bible?
He says all scripture is given by inspiration of God
and is profitable, right?
All scripture, not most of it, not some of it,
but all of it.
Do you believe this morning
that God is smarter than Google?
You laugh.
You laugh, why?
You know how many people say, look at Google,
or they'll bring you some kind of thing and they'll say,
well, Google said, right?
Google is the, come on,
they run algorithms for all that stuff.
I'm not smart enough to understand how it all works,
but I am smart enough to know this,
God is smarter than Google.
Amen.
Come on, you know it this morning.
He is the creator God.
Can I tell you what Google will tell you if you look up,
should I drink wine for my stomach?
Absolutely not.
It is the absolute worst thing you could do
if you have stomach issues is to drink alcohol.
It is the absolute, no doctor in their right mind
would ever tell you to drink alcohol
if you have stomach issues.
All right, Google knows that.
You go look it up.
I got screenshots of it on my iPad, all right?
So if your Google says something different,
I got screenshots, amen?
But I under, listen, I've studied this out.
I've studied this out for years.
I preached a message years ago
called the deceitfulness of alcohol.
It's still on our website.
You can go listen to it.
It's a whole message on it.
But the reality is that no doctor
is ever going to prescribe to an individual
that has stomach issues to drink alcohol.
Furthermore, there's a study.
It came out just a couple of years ago.
I didn't bring it with me.
It's on my desk.
But there's a study that came out.
I saw it on Fox News a couple of years ago,
and I said, man, this is wonderful.
And I printed that thing out, saved it,
and it said this.
It said no person under 40 years old
should ever drink alcohol.
There are zero health benefits.
You should be a total abstainer.
Now, can I tell you this morning,
that's not popular with all the beer manufacturers
and all the alcohol, why?
There's a huge industry.
Those people make lots of money, okay?
So those studies are not popular,
but they came out with it,
and I have the article printed,
and it says there is zero, not there's some,
there are zero health benefits to alcohol.
Now, if scientists and if medicine
and if Google can figure all that stuff out in 2024,
I submit to you this morning that the creator God,
who is the omniscient God, knows all things,
and he never in his word would have told Paul
to give Timothy alcoholic beverage for his stomach's sake.
Not a chance.
So if you wanna find a verse
that's going to justify your behavior,
you can't use 1 Timothy 5 anymore, amen, honestly.
It's just not a valid interpretation of scripture.
I have found, however, and you cannot find this online
where it has been something that has been verified,
but I did some research years ago,
and I found this to be the case.
I read it in a couple of studies.
There are others that have come out and said,
no, it's not true,
but I can tell you that we've practiced it personally,
and that is this, that pure grape juice
is actually a huge benefit if you have stomach issues.
In fact, there are some studies that have suggested,
and again, they say that they're not verifiable.
They have suggested that if you are exposed
to a stomach virus,
now, how many of you like stomach viruses?
Amen.
During that whole COVID thing,
everyone wanted to ask you about,
do you have this symptom, this symptom,
this symptom, this symptom,
and I was so like just wanting to mess with people
and say, man, I don't have any of that,
but I've been throwing up like crazy,
and I just got this,
because they didn't seem to care about
any of that sort of thing,
but I do not, Pierre, you know,
I hate the idea of a stomach bug.
It absolutely is the last thing I ever wanna have.
So as I was doing some study,
it said that pure grape juice can help,
and it can prevent, it can do all kinds of benefits
if you have gut things,
if you're exposed to some type of a stomach virus,
and so now in the man household,
anytime there's a stomach bug that goes around,
the first thing we do, get the grape juice.
I mean, the pure stuff, man,
and can I tell you, we have seen the benefit of it,
personally.
I'm not a doctor, I'm not a scientist,
I'm just an individual that did some study
and found out some things,
and I've suggested to other people.
My brother,
He said, man, the kid's got a stomach bug.
I said, you better go get some grape juice, man.
Just go get that stuff.
And it's helped us.
As I look at this passage of Scripture
and I find the conduct of an elder,
he says we're to pursue purity.
He says that we're to reject partiality.
And then he deals with the subject of wine
that's mixed right in the midst
of this whole text of Scripture.
But in the midst of speaking about wine,
we can assuredly say this morning
that there's no way that God Almighty,
the creator and the all wise God,
would have Paul tell Timothy to drink alcoholic beverage
for his stomach's sake.
No, the water was going to contribute further
to his stomach issues, his often infirmities,
and therefore drink no longer water.
But use a little wine for thy stomach's sake
and thine often infirmities.
I'm thankful that God has given us
every word of Scripture.
Listen, the Bible says that every word of God is pure.
See, God put all of verse 23 in there
so that we could interpret it properly
that Paul didn't just say, hey, don't drink any water,
but drink wine, period.
That would be open to all kinds
of different interpretations and understandings.
But he says, don't do it for this reason.
And when we understand that reason,
it helps us to come to a proper conclusion.
This morning, we look at this passage of Scripture
in 1 Timothy 5 and verse 17 through 25,
and we see that in this passage
it's dealing specifically with elders.
But I said to you a few minutes ago,
and I'll say it again, every child of God,
their conduct should be honorable.
It's not just honorable elders,
it should be honorable Christians.
That we live in such a way
that we bring honor and glory to our God,
that we are pursuing purity in our lives,
that we are rejecting partiality,
that we are understanding that there are things,
behaviors that are appropriate and pleasing,
and there are behaviors that are not appropriate,
they're inappropriate, they're displeasing.
As I mentioned to you at that conference,
they said, if you do any of these things, you're out.
No refund.
Can I tell you that the sponsors
and organizers of that conference,
they're not our audience.
God Almighty, the thrice holy God,
He is the one that we serve.
And oh, how our behavior should align biblically,
that we can thank God for the encouragement
that He gives us, we can thank God
for the warnings that He provides,
and we can thank God for the instruction that He gives.
Can I tell you this morning?
Instruction from God is only beneficial when it's applied.
It's not enough to know it, to hear it.
We must do it.
We must pursue purity and reject partiality.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the opportunity to be gathered.
Thank you for your word, the clarity of it.
And God, I pray that you would help us this morning
to submit ourselves to your word.
We know that you're the all-wise God.
We know, God, that you are holy and you're just,
and we thank you for the instruction that you've provided.
Help us, Lord, to pursue purity, to reject partiality.
Help us to live and walk in such a way
that you would be honored and glorified.
God, if there's one here this morning
that's not sure of heaven, God, I pray this morning
they'd come to this old-fashioned altar,
they'd allow us to take a Bible and show them
how they could know for sure that heaven's their home,
that they would not leave this place
without having 100% assurance that heaven is their home.
I pray, God, that you'd move and work,
that you'd be honored and glorified
through all that's said and done.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.