Acts 27, Acts chapter number 27, and as you're turning there, I'm going to read a verse from
the book of Deuteronomy.
We'll reference some other things in the Old Testament as we go through the message this
evening, but I'd like for you to be there in Acts chapter number 27, and I'm so thankful
for the Word of God and for the way in which it's changed my life, and I know that you
too could testify of the change that God has made in your life using His Word.
I want to read this verse as kind of a springboard into the message this evening from Acts 27.
The book of Deuteronomy is recording, rehearsing some of the history of the children of Israel,
and here's what is said in Deuteronomy 1 and verse number 32, yet in this thing ye did
not believe the Lord your God.
Yet in this thing ye did not believe the Lord your God.
I hope that it would never be said of us, individually or corporately, that we did not
believe God.
Amen?
I wouldn't want it to be said of me personally.
I wouldn't want it to be said of our family.
I wouldn't want it to be said of our church that we did not believe God.
Amen?
I'd much rather be known for believing God, trusting God, exercising faith in God.
Hebrews 11 reminds us that without faith, it is impossible to please Him, for he that
cometh to God must believe that he is, and that he's a rewarder of them that diligently
seek him.
Faith is simply taking God at His Word, believing that God will do what God said He will do.
Throughout this week of Vacation Bible School, we had a great week and we're thankful for
how God answered prayer and the opportunities to minister to these people, these young people
and their families.
I was especially pleased with the way in which the children were attentive to the lessons.
Of course, I taught the teen class, but as we would ask questions of several of the others
within the classes, you could tell that there was a level of attentiveness amongst the young
people as they were being instructed with regard to the subject matter at hand.
And as I mentioned to you last week, the theme of our Vacation Bible School was Mystery Island,
Discovering the One True God.
And as we would go through the lessons, and really the lessons were designed to discuss
various attributes of God, and we dealt with the fact that God is great, and He is.
We dealt with the fact that God is Almighty, and that He is able to do exceeding abundantly
above all that we ask or think, that He is omnipotent, He's omniscient, and He's omnipresent.
As we begin to understand that He's great and He's Almighty, it would lead us to a place
of standing in awe of who God is.
We dealt with the fact that He's the ruler.
I told our teen class that it is a settled fact that the Lord is the ruler of the universe,
and He rules in the affairs of mankind, that He is King of kings and Lord of lords.
There are times in which we may think what is going on and chaos seems to be prevalent
and prevailing, but yet we know that our God is in control.
He is ruler.
And I told the young people that if He is all that we've said that He is, and if He
is all that He has revealed to us in His word to be, and He is the ruler of the universe,
then who better to rule your life than Him?
You'll fail at ruling your own life.
Make a mess of it.
Amen?
All of us would.
We dealt with the fact that He is God with us, Emmanuel.
What a blessing to know that when the fullness of time was come, God sent forth His Son.
We understand that He sent forth His Son to go to the cross of Calvary to pay for the
sin of mankind to redeem us.
What a blessing.
We ended on Friday with this truth that God is trustworthy.
He is trustworthy.
You know, the reality is as I kind of meditated, I taught the lessons, and then as I ended
the week and kind of meditated upon all that I had taught and how I sought to influence
the young people that were in my class, the reality is that as you go step by step through
those days and you come to Friday and you come to that lesson that God is trustworthy,
that really that's the only conclusion that you reach after you understand all of who
He is.
When you understand that He is the Almighty God, that He is the Great I Am, when you understand
all that He's revealed to us in His Word regarding His person, it would lead you naturally
to a place of saying, He's trustworthy.
He's dependable.
Our God is faithful.
He always has been, by the way.
Amen?
He's never failed, and He's not getting ready to begin failing.
No one's going to ever overrun Him, dethrone Him.
It's not going to happen.
And as we look at Acts 27, and I visited this passage of Scripture with the young people
on Friday, and I want to develop it maybe a little bit more for us this evening.
As we look at this particular passage, we find that it's in verse number 9.
The Bible says, now when much time was spent, and when sailing was now dangerous, because
the fast was now already passed, Paul admonished them.
Notice what he said to them in verse number 10.
He said unto them, Sirs, I perceive that this voyage will be with hurt and much damage,
not only of the lading and ship, but also of our lives.
Nevertheless, notice verse number 11, nevertheless the centurion believed the master and the
owner of the ship more than those things which were spoken by Paul.
Because the haven was not commodious to winter in, notice this, the more part advised to
depart thence also, if by any means they may attain to Phinehas, and there to winter, which
is in haven of Crete, and lieth toward the south, west, and northwest.
Would you have noticed that phrase in verse number 11 when the Bible says, nevertheless
the centurion believed the master and the owner of the ship, notice, more than those
things which were spoken by Paul.
The title as you see in the bulletin today, the title for the message this evening is
this, who do you believe?
Who do you believe?
The reality is that everyone believes someone.
This centurion, he was going to place his trust, his confidence, he was going to believe
someone.
The reality is that the information that this man, this centurion received, was conflicting
information.
He had Paul on one hand saying, it's not safe for us to depart, it's not safe for us to
sail, it's dangerous, it's going to be wrought with danger.
And not only of the lading of the ship, but also of our lives.
And on the other hand, you have the master and owner of the ship saying, let's go.
You have the more part, as it says in verse number 12, you know what that means when it
says the more part advised, it means the majority.
The majority.
They say, no, no, it's good, it's fine, we're going to be able to make it.
The Bible says that the centurion, he is given this conflicting information, but he's got
to believe someone.
And who does he believe?
He goes with the majority.
He goes with the more part.
He goes with the owner and master of the ship, and they set sail.
As we go through the passage of Scripture this evening, we'll find that it was actually
a very poor decision on the part of this centurion.
But I want you to notice this evening that everyone believes someone.
Including you.
Including me.
You know that God wants you to believe Him.
God wants us to believe Him.
Do you think, as I read that verse of Scripture in Deuteronomy 1 and verse number 32, when
it says that they did not believe God, do you think that's what God wanted?
Well, no.
They absolutely, God absolutely wanted those people to believe Him.
This is really what Deuteronomy 1 is speaking of when you think about the children of Israel
and you think about their journey and all that had taken place.
I'm mindful of what the Word of God says in Numbers 14.
In Numbers chapter number 13, the Bible gives us the record of the spies going to spy out
the land.
And we find that in chapter number 13, the spies are selected and they're given their
instruction as with regard to what their task is.
We find that they depart and they go into the land as they had been instructed to do
so.
And they come back and we, several times this week, we were singing the song, 12 men went
to spy on Canaan.
And we're familiar with the text of Scripture and we know that the Bible teaches us that
there were 10 that came back with an evil report.
They did not believe God.
They did not believe that they were able
to go in and possess the land.
There were two, however.
Joshua and Caleb.
Joshua and Caleb, they believed
that God was able.
They believed that God could
give them that which God had promised them.
By the way, God had proven
to this group of people
many, many times,
over and over and over.
He'd proven His power and His might
and His ability.
These people had experienced
not only the plagues in Egypt
and what a wonder those were
as you begin to read in the book of Exodus
and read about the plagues
and you see the power of God on display.
You find that after the death of the firstborn
that they leave and God leads them
and they come to the Red Sea
and God parts the Red Sea
and they cross over on dry ground.
Miraculous.
Can you imagine being there
and experiencing that?
It was so impactful that the Egyptians,
they said, well, let us go as well.
We're going to pursue them.
Bad decision.
God had instructed the children of Israel
and God provided a way for the children of Israel,
but it was in the midst of the Red Sea
in which God destroyed the Egyptians
that sought to pursue after.
I mentioned this morning
that God knows what we need
and I mentioned about God
knowing that the children of Israel
needed water and they needed food
and we find that just after they crossed over the Red Sea
that as they're being led by God
that they come to a place
where there's bitter water.
Did God know that they needed water?
Sure He did.
Could God have led them to a different place?
Sure He could.
But He led them there.
It wasn't Moses that led the children of Israel
to that place.
It was God that led them to that place.
And God led them to a place
where there was bitter water.
They begin to murmur and complain
and Moses prays and God says there's a tree
and go put that tree in the water
and the waters were healed
and now they could drink the waters.
What a blessing to see how God blessed
and worked and provided.
And then in just a little while
God leads them again
and now they come to a place
where there's no water.
You say God don't you know that we need water?
Yeah He knows.
He's aware.
I think it's interesting
I actually said this to the young people.
God could have led them again
to a place that had bitter water.
What would you have done?
What do you think they would have done
if God took them to a place again
that had bitter water?
I think they would have looked for a tree.
They would have looked for a tree
that resembled the tree
that they put in the previous waters.
Why? Because that's human nature.
We just like to depend upon ourselves.
Right?
So what does God do?
He takes them to a place
where there's no water.
And then He supplies water from a rock.
These people had experienced
the power of God displayed
over and over and over.
And in Numbers 13,
they bring up this evil report.
In Numbers 14,
there's this great discourse that takes place.
And of course, Joshua and Caleb
are trying to steal the people
and get them to believe God
and to enter into.
And Caleb says this.
And in verse 7 it says,
and they spake in Numbers 14,
and they spake unto all the company
of the children of Israel,
saying, the land which we pass through
to search it is an exceeding good land.
If the Lord delight in us,
then He will bring us into this land
and give it us a land
which floweth with milk and honey.
Only rebel not ye against the Lord.
Neither fear ye the people of the land,
for they are bred for us.
Their defenses departed from them.
And the Lord is with us.
Fear them not.
Verse 10 is a sad verse of Scripture.
It says, but all the congregation
bade stone them with stones.
They're ready to stone them.
Simply because they say
we need to believe God.
In verse 11, God speaks to Moses.
And notice what the Bible says.
The Lord said unto Moses,
How long will this people provoke me?
And how long will it be
ere they believe me?
For all the signs which I have showed
among them.
You know, God wants His people to believe Him.
He wants you and He wants me to believe Him.
He wants us to trust Him.
He wants us to place our confidence,
our faith, our faith in Him.
It's interesting to me that we understand
and readily acknowledge the fact
that we cannot save ourselves.
Amen?
And so therefore, very few of us
have any trouble with fully trusting God
for our eternity.
Right?
Because we know there's nothing we can do about it.
But it seems like the God that we trust for eternity,
sometimes we have trouble trusting Him for today.
You ever notice that in our lives?
That we're trusting Him for eternity,
but we can struggle with trusting Him for today.
I believe that as we would look back to Acts chapter 27,
and if you are taking notes and consider the counsel
that the centurion received,
we already kind of dealt with it,
but you consider the counsel,
and we find that as these folks were getting ready to depart,
we understand there are 276 of them.
If you look at verse number 37,
you'll find the number, the head count if you will,
of those that are going to sail.
And these 276, they're there and they're waiting.
Are we gonna leave?
Are we not gonna leave?
What are we doing?
And the time to sail according to what Paul says
or what is given to us as kind of a backdrop,
that was now dangerous,
and we find that the counsel that was received
from the centurion,
there was a conflict within the counsel.
The reality is that this man was given counsel from Paul
that differed from what the owner and master of the ship said
that differed from what the majority, the more part said.
You know, today, we still get conflicting information.
We still get conflicting counsel.
That's why it's important that we have the right counselors.
The Bible says that there's safety
in the multitude of counselors,
but you better make sure they're the right counselors.
Amen?
Because the reality is that you can get
some wrong counselors and they can give you some bad counsel
and you can say, well, I counseled.
You understand that counsel is not just getting someone
to tell you what you wanna hear.
That's not counsel.
Dean has a little cartoon in the office,
in the finance office.
I don't know exactly how it says,
but basically people don't want your opinion.
They want their opinion coming out of your mouth.
And it's a cute little cartoon
and I've seen it several times over the years.
He's got another one that doesn't make any sense to me
because it says bacon doesn't make everything better,
but bacon normally makes things pretty good, you know?
But anyhow, the reality is that today,
today, you can find so much contradiction
in so many different voices that are trying to get you
to go in a particular direction.
And we find that in particular,
my thoughts as we look here at verse number 12,
it's interesting when it says,
the more part advised to depart.
You know, one of the dangers in our society today
is this idea of, well, the majority say.
Just because the majority says
doesn't mean the majority's right.
Have we not taught our children that, right?
We understand that, listen,
just because it's the number one result
on the Google search doesn't mean it's right.
In fact, if you're looking for some good truth,
you might not wanna look at the number one search
that's returned on the Google search
because they use all sorts of various metrics
and what have you to get that stuff to come up.
And you find that, listen,
the reality is there's so many voices
and it can be confusing.
Can you imagine being in the shoes of the centurion
in this particular passage of Scripture?
Can you imagine the pressure
and the responsibility of having to make the decision,
do we sail or do we not?
That's a big decision.
It's a lot of pressure.
It's one thing if it's just you taking a voyage
and you're by yourself
and maybe just a couple of folks with you,
but when there's 276 people
that are going to be sailing with you,
that is a big responsibility.
I understand that Paul is not God.
I understand that.
But Paul gives him counsel.
And he says, I'm going to believe these guys
instead of believing him.
We find that as we think about
the counsel that was received,
we think about the way in which he responded.
And as we notice that he responds
by believing and setting sail,
believing the most part, the more part,
the majority, believing the owner
and master of the ship.
The Bible says in v. 13,
and when the south wind blew softly,
supposing that they had obtained their purpose,
loosing fence, they sailed close by Crete.
Notice these next four words,
but not long after.
Not long after,
there arose against it a tempestuous wind
called Uroclidan.
The Bible says that the ship was caught
and could not bear up into the wind.
We let her drive,
standing under a certain island
which is called Clauda.
We had much work to come by the boat.
Which when they had taken up,
they used helps undergirding the ship
and fearing lest they should fall
into the quicksands.
Straight sail, and so were driven.
And we, being exceedingly tossed
with a tempest,
the next day lightened the ship.
They were tossing goods overboard.
It says the third day,
we cast out with our own hands
the tackling of the ship.
I wouldn't want to be in there for three hours.
Amen?
The third day.
Notice verse 20.
And when neither sun nor stars
in many days appeared,
and no small tempest lay on us,
notice this phrase,
all hope that we should be saved
was then taken away.
They're in a place where we could
literally say they were hopeless.
Hopeless.
I've never been in a storm like this
on the seas.
I just never have.
In fact, I never would like to be
on a ship in a storm like this.
Not really my desire.
I'm not interested in being
in the middle of the water
and not being able to see the sun
or the stars for days.
Not signing up for that.
But that's where they are.
Do you think for a moment
that this centurion wished
that he could have changed his decision?
Yeah.
Have you ever been in a place
where you say,
man, I wish I could change my decision.
I mean, can I go back?
Can I change that choice?
It was a bad decision.
But they're in the middle of the Mediterranean.
I mean, they're in the middle of a storm.
There's nothing you can do at this point
to change your decision.
It doesn't matter how much regret you have.
It doesn't matter how much you can say,
I wish I would have believed.
They could come to Paul and say,
Paul, you were so right.
I should have believed you, Paul.
Doesn't change the circumstances.
Doesn't change.
We find that they're hopeless.
And as we find them in that hopeless situation,
and we've considered the counsel
that was received,
and we consider how it is
that he responded to Centurion,
I want you to understand
that God is going to give us
a few verses of Scripture here
to help us be reminded
that believers,
followers of the Lord Jesus Christ,
that we are to believe God.
We're to believe the Lord.
There are times in which
the circumstances that we face
may seem to be beyond our comprehension
that we can't figure it out.
If you're analytical,
if you're of that kind of a mindset,
you like to be able to figure things out
and kind of see where things are going,
sometimes, it'll just drive you crazy.
Because we don't always see
how God is working.
Was God in control
when they arrested the Lord Jesus Christ
and took Him to the cross of Calvary?
Do the disciples think so?
They were confused.
In fact, Peter,
did he not try to stop
the Lord Jesus Christ from going?
Not so, Lord!
That's what Peter said.
He was as in much control at Calvary
as he was at creation.
As much control.
At creation in Genesis 1
when God said let there be light
and there was light.
And He had His power on display
and He was in full control.
He was as much in control at Calvary
as He was at creation.
Because God makes no mistakes.
And God knew what He was doing.
And the reality is that
the Lord Jesus Christ,
He had to go to that cross of Calvary
so that He could pay for your sin
and for my sin.
We understand that in the book of Luke
when God records for us
when those disciples are walking back
on the road of Emmaus
and they're downhearted.
I mean, they are struggling
and their countenance is sad
that Jesus comes along them
and is walking with them.
And He says,
why is it that your countenance is sad?
And they say,
are you just a stranger in Jerusalem?
You don't know what's happened?
They were going home
not because they thought
God was in control.
They were perplexed.
We thought it had been Him.
That's what they say.
What does Jesus do?
He begins to talk to them.
He starts with Moses and the prophets.
And He expounds unto them
all things in the Scriptures
pertaining to Himself.
And He's going to keep on going.
They get home.
And they say,
come on in.
Have a meal with us.
Stay with us.
And He broke bread.
Their eyes were opened.
And He vanished.
And they said,
did not our heart burn within us
when He spoke along the way?
And what did they do?
They got back to Jerusalem in a hurry.
They just walked over seven miles.
And now they're, I think,
running back seven miles
with a level of excitement.
He is risen indeed!
I mean, this is an exciting story!
It's not just a story.
It's truth.
It's history.
And listen, Jesus,
He went to that cross
we sang tonight.
He did it for us.
And He was in absolute control.
What did Pilate say
during the interrogation?
I know I'm backing up a few days
in the history of which I'm dealing with,
but when you back up
and you look at the interrogation,
Pilate says to Jesus,
don't you know that I have power?
Is that not what he says?
What does Jesus say?
Ha!
You only have the kind of power
I give you.
Right?
What did Jesus say?
John 10 we referenced this morning
about the Good Shepherd.
He says,
I lay down my life for the sheep.
No man taketh it from me.
He lays it down.
Listen, God is always in control.
In 2021,
in the midst of whatever chaos and confusion
you think we're living in,
God is in control.
And we as the people of God
must believe Him.
And we must trust Him.
Listen, God's Word still works.
You know that,
I said this to Holly this morning,
I said,
broadly speaking,
Christendom is in a mess right now.
The churches across the land,
things are going just crazy
what's going on.
In far too many,
not all,
listen, don't misunderstand
what I'm saying.
I'm not saying that
there's no good churches out there.
There are plenty of good solid churches
that are still standing for truth.
But you know that a lot of them
have forsaken this book.
And they've caved into the pressures of society.
And they begin to try to massage the Scriptures
to say something that they don't say.
And really, all they're doing
is 2 Timothy 4.
They're just itching, tickling people's ears.
And it's not going to change anybody.
It's not going to change anything.
Because God changes people.
We're not going to water down our message
and it be effective.
We're not going to employ our own
types of strategies and approaches
and our own methodology.
No, we need to follow God's methods.
And we do God's work God's way,
then we see what God is able to do.
It's far better to see what God can do
than to see what you can do
or what I can do.
Back in Acts 27,
Paul, the Bible says in verse 21,
but after long abstinence,
Paul stood forth in the midst of them
and said,
Sirs, you should have hearkened unto me
and not have loosed from Crete,
and to have gained this harm and loss.
But they couldn't change that, right?
change it. Notice verse 22, and now I exhort you to be of good cheer. I know
the verse doesn't end there, but can you imagine these guys listening to Paul? Be
of good cheer? We just got rid of all of our stuff, right? We haven't seen the Sun,
we haven't seen the stars for days. All hope that we should be saved is gone, and
you're telling us to be of good cheer? But that's what Paul says. But there's a
reason that Paul says it. Paul says this, be of good cheer, for there shall be no
loss of any man's life among you but of the ship. That's pretty encouraging. But
this isn't just Paul thinking this up on his own. This isn't some feel-good
preacher that just wants to put his arm around somebody and say everything's
going to be okay. Paul got a word from God. And the Bible tells us in verse
number 23 that Paul is going to rehearse this to these sirs that he references in
verse 21. For there stood by me this night the angel of God. Notice the way in
which he identifies whose I am and whom I serve. We talked this morning about
being mindful of our position. Aren't you thankful you belong to God? Now I belong
to Jesus. Jesus belongs to me. I am so thankful that I belong to Him. And Paul
says not only do I belong to Him but I serve Him. And here's what the angel of
God told me. He said this in verse 24, fear not Paul, thou must be brought
before Caesar and lo God hath given thee all them that sail with thee. These folks
were blessed because of Paul's presence being there. Because God says Paul you
need to appear before Caesar. And so I'm going to give all these other people
their lives too. You know God blessed Potiphar's house because of Joseph. Laban
understood that he was blessed because of Jacob. Right? These people are blessed
because Paul's there. By the way they ought to be happy that Paul got on the
boat. It says this, I love verse 25 of Acts 27. Wherefore sirs be of good cheer.
I have it circled in my Bible for I believe God. Now think about this. In the
midst, I mean it wasn't just the sirs that didn't see the Sun and the stars. Paul
didn't see it. Paul was in the midst of your Euclidean the same way everybody
else was. It wasn't that Paul was exempt from the storm. No, he was in the storm
with them. He was experiencing the same thing. He says be of good cheer. I believe
God. Notice what he says, that it shall be even as it was told me. Because God
always does what God says he will do. He always does. Remember when they came to
the tomb the angel said he's not here for he is risen. As he said. He always
does what he says. Our God is trustworthy. He's dependable. But the question is who
do we believe when we go to the Word of God and we read what God tells us in his
Word with regard to prophecy, when we regard to the end days, the times in
which we're living. Do we believe what God says? Do we believe that God is in
control? Do we believe that God's plan is coming to pass? Or do we fret and worry
and have fear and say everything's unraveling and everything's out of
control? No, no, no. We believe God. It's going to be. Listen, listen for the
trumpet. Jesus is coming. Amen. I don't know the hour. I don't know the day. But
it certainly appears each day. I mean, I know we're a day closer than we were
yesterday. But the reality is that, man, I said to Joseph yesterday we were
driving. I said, bud, listen for the trumpet, man. Jesus is coming. I believe
that he's coming. And here's why I believe he's coming right on time. I
understand that the Bible ends with, even so come Lord Jesus, right? And the
reality is that we might say, man, I wish Jesus would come today. And he could. But
you understand he's not coming on your timetable or on my timetable. He's coming
on his timetable. He's coming on time. He's not going to be early. He's not
going to be late. He's going to be on time. We find that Paul stands and says,
I believe God, that it shall be even as it was told me. Now I want you to
consider, as Paul makes this declaration, and I want you to consider that as we
would understand Paul standing in the midst of this difficulty, that he is
putting his full confidence in God. But you understand that he's putting
himself in a position where he's telling everybody else what God said. I mean he's
just, he's not in his little cabin by himself saying, I believe you Lord, I
believe you're going to deliver us. I'm just not going to tell anybody else because if
you don't, then you know I don't want to look bad. No, no. Paul believed God. It
wasn't like a, I believe you but I don't want to, I don't want to be wrong. No. He had
full confidence that what God told him, God was going to do. If you look through
the rest of the chapter, we don't have time this evening, I want to look at a couple
other passages, but if you look through the rest of the chapter you find that
they were delivered. They were delivered. The soldier's counsel was to kill the
prisoners according to verse number 42 and the centurion was willing to save
Paul, kept them from their purpose and commanded that they should not, that they
which could swim should cast themselves fast in the sea and get to land and the
rest, some on boards, some on broken pieces of the ship and so it came to pass
that they escaped, look at what it says, all safe to land. All of them. A mindful of
Hezekiah in the Old Testament. 2nd Kings chapter 18. We're going to run out of time this
evening but in 2nd Kings chapter 18, we're familiar with that which
happens during the reign of Hezekiah and during the reign of Hezekiah you find
that the Assyrians have taken Israel captive and they're seeking to now take Judah captive.
Sennacherib and Rabshakeh. Rabshakeh in particular is coming to the people of
Judah and it says in verse number 29, kind of jumping right in the middle here,
it says, well look at verse 28, then Rabshakeh stood and cried with a loud voice in the
Jews language and spake saying, hear the word of the great king, the king of
Assyria, thus saith the king, let not Hezekiah deceive you for he shall not be
able to deliver you out of his hand. You know that Hezekiah, I don't think he
ever believed that he could deliver the people. He knew that God could deliver
the people. There's a difference. Hezekiah is not standing up saying I'm
going to deliver you from the Assyrians. And you notice that the Bible says that
Rabshakeh as he's speaking with this loud voice in the Jews language that he
says this, hear the word of the great king, the king of Assyria. I want you to
hear the word of the king of kings and lord of lords, not the king of Assyria.
Notice verse 30, neither let Hezekiah make you trust in the Lord, saying the
Lord will surely deliver us and this city shall not be delivered into the
hand of the king of Assyria. Hearken not to Hezekiah, it says in the beginning of
verse number 31. But you understand that he continues and he says in verse 33,
hath any of the gods of the nations delivered at all his hand, excuse me, all
his land out of the hand of the king of Assyria? They were idols. They are false
gods. Of course they didn't deliver. We serve the true God, the king of kings and
lord of lords. The Bible says that the people held their peace and answered him
not a word for the king's command was saying answer him not. If you go through
and you find as you come into chapter number 19 of the book of 2nd Kings that
Hezekiah when he goes up to the house of the Lord and he spreads out the letter
that was sent and he prays and he understands that God is the creator and
he is and understands a lot of things about God and he he demonstrates here
for us in this passage belief in what God is able to do. You know the end of
the story tells us in verse number 34 of chapter 19 for I will defend this
city to save it for mine own sake and for my servant David's sake. They came to
pass that night that the angel of the Lord went out and smote in the camp of
the Assyrians and hundred four score and five thousand and they arose early in
the morning behold they were all dead corpses. So Sennacherib king of Assyria
departed and went and returned and dwelt Nineveh. His sons kill him in verse
number 37
I mean, we could go on and on this evening with examples in the Word of God of what our God is able to do.
And where people, the people of God are brought to a place of decision.
Are you going to believe God?
Or are you going to believe whatever's on the other side?
Whoever's on the other side?
It's best that we put our trust in God.
As believers, as the people of God, we are to believe God.
Trust in the Lord how?
With all thine heart.
I'll be transparent with you this evening.
The last part of Proverbs 3 and verse number 5 is hard for me and probably for you as well.
And lean not unto thine own understanding.
We struggle with that, do we not?
We're human.
That's why God said lean not on your own understanding.
In all thy ways.
And how many of your ways?
All.
Acknowledge Him.
And He shall direct thy paths.
Who better to direct your path and my path than the almighty, all-knowing God?
Amen?
This evening, when we understand who He is,
when we see Him in all of His glory,
when we see Him as Isaiah did in Isaiah 6, high, holy, and lifted up,
when we read of His attributes and the way in which He's described Himself,
but then the way in which He's displayed His attributes,
we stand in awe of who He is.
The psalmist said in Psalm 48,
Great is the Lord, and greatly to be praised.
And he ends that chapter with saying, after a whole host of things about how great God is,
that this God is our God.
Listen, He's trustworthy.
He wants us to believe Him.
He said in Numbers 14, when He speaks to Moses,
How long will it be ere my people believe me?
I hope He's not saying that today.
I hope that He's not looking at 2021 Christians and saying,
Aren't they believing me?
I've given them my word.
I've proven myself over and over.
Why won't they believe me?
And I'll finish with the verse that I started with,
Yet in this thing ye did not believe the Lord your God.
I hope tonight that it would never be said, of you or me or of us,
that we did not believe God.
That we'd come to a place in our lives where we say,
Bid me come to thee.
Because that's what Peter said when he saw Jesus walking on the water.
He believed. Amen?
I understand that Peter gets all kinds of criticism.
I understand that people talk about, well, he sunk.
He walked further than you did and I did and anyone else in that boat did.
Amen?
He's human.
But he believed God.
And he had enough sense about Him to say, Lord, help me, save me.
And then he walked back to the boat.
Tonight, we just didn't believe God.
I don't know in what area specifically in your life.
I know there's a lot of things going on in our world today.
I know there are a lot of voices that are trying to get your attention and my attention
and wanting to believe this thing and that thing.
But oh, if I could encourage you tonight to get into this book and believe God.
Yeah, but the fill-in-the-blank is saying whatever they're saying.
But what did God say?
What did God say?
Because I want to be on God's side.
Amen?
I want to believe God.
Let's pray. Father, we love you.
Thank you for loving us.
So many verses that I desired to get to this evening that I failed to do so.
The book of Psalms, the book of Proverbs,
admonition after admonition to put your trust in God.
To put your trust in God.
To believe is to trust.
To have faith.
I thank you tonight that you are trustworthy.
I thank you tonight that you've never failed.
God, I pray that you would help me in my life to believe you more.
Help us, God, to have confidence in knowing that you indeed are in control.
And that we can believe you.
Help us to have that peace that passes all understanding.
Help us to have the joy of the Lord. It's our strength.
I'm not sure exactly where this message applies in each individual's life that's present tonight.
But God, I pray that we'd be honest with you.
I pray that in the stillness and the quietness of the moment
that we'd truly allow you to have your way in our lives.
Help us to conquer doubt.
Help us to silence those voices.
Help us to run to you and to your word.
To trust you.
I thank you for what you'll do in the hearts of your people.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.