We're ready this evening to turn to a number of passages, and this is going to be a springboard
passage that we're going to start in here and look at a number of verses of Scripture
this evening.
As we really are going to enter into, this will be kind of an introductory lesson or
message on a series that we'll do on Wednesday evenings here for the next, I don't know,
six to ten weeks, something like that, and as the Lord would lead.
But the title for the message this evening, and really the title for the whole series
will be this, The Danger of Deception.
The Danger of Deception.
I believe this evening, well let's look at Mark 13, look at verses 5 and 6.
The Bible says here in Mark 13,
And Jesus, answering them, began to say, Take heed, lest any man deceive you.
For many shall come in my name, saying, I am Christ, and shall deceive many.
What a warning that is issued here in Mark chapter number 13.
You can read it in Matthew 24 as well, but you find that the Lord Jesus Christ in verse
number 5 says, Take heed, lest any man deceive you.
The word deceive means to cause, to stray.
It carries with it the idea of to lead astray or to lead aside from the right way.
It's also understood that this word deceive carries with it the idea of to lead away from
truth or to lead into error.
I believe that we are living in an age of deception.
As you just look around, I mean, you don't have to look far, I believe that in 2021,
we are living in an age of deception.
And as we acknowledge that there is a famine of truth in our land, and we at the same time
acknowledge that there's an onslaught of deception, we must take heed, as the Savior says in verse
number 5.
To take heed means to see, to discern.
It carries with it the idea of being on guard, to beware.
We find that throughout the Scriptures that God has given us the warnings that we need.
In fact, there are many times in which you read in the Word of God, beware, take heed.
God wants us to be aware of what's taking place.
He wants us to be aware of how our enemy operates and what he does.
And we understand that our enemy is a liar, amen?
He is the father of lies.
In fact, the very original work of Satan in the garden was that of deception.
We will not take the time to look back at Genesis chapter number 3, but I do want to
remind you what Paul says to Timothy in 1 Timothy chapter number 2.
Turn over there if you will, and we're aware that the Bible tells us in Genesis chapter
number 3 that the serpent was more subtle than any beast of the field.
And we understand that as Satan came in there to the garden, that he says to Eve,
yea, hath God said.
And then he continues on and he says, ye shall not surely die.
And we find that as Paul would reference this account in Genesis chapter number 3, as he's
speaking to Timothy and really dealing in verse number 14 with this very event, notice
what he says, and Adam was not deceived, but the woman being deceived was in the transgression.
When you think about that phraseology in verse number 14 with dealing with the subject
of deception and understanding that we're living in an age of deception, deception is
nothing new.
The enemy has sought to deceive from the very beginning.
Again, he's the father of lies.
There are some that would seek to distinguish between lying and deception.
The reality is that deception is lying, and there's a very discreet manner and some of
the words that are used with regard to that idea of deceit and the enticing words that
would be used and so on and so forth.
One of the greatest illustrations that I think of in the Word of God with regard to deceit
is that of the brothers of Joseph when they dipped the coat of many colors in blood and
they know exactly what's taking place and they know all that has transpired, for they're
the ones that did it, and they come back to Dad and they say, do you know whose this is?
What does Jacob say?
He says, it's Joseph.
Surely he's been devoured by a wild beast, and they allowed him to believe that, right?
They deceived him through that action.
This evening, if you're taking notes, I want you to note first of all the reality of deception.
The reality of deception.
Start with me in the book of Romans in the 16th chapter, and I want you to see again
this reality and this age of deception that we're living in.
In Romans chapter number 16, the Bible says this in verse number 17,
Now I beseech you, brethren, mark them which cause divisions and offenses contrary to the
doctrine which ye have learned, and avoid them.
Notice in verse 18, for they that are such, so those that are described in verse number
17, those that cause divisions and offenses that are contrary to the doctrine which ye
have learned, they're peddling some other teaching, some other doctrine.
He says, for they that are such serve not our Lord Jesus Christ, but their own belly,
and by good words and fair speeches deceive the hearts of the simple.
You notice that it speaks at the end of verse number 18 that they deceive the hearts of
the simple, but I want you to notice by what means it is that they deceive the hearts of
the simple.
By good words and fair speeches.
How many people today hear someone stand up that has oratory ability, and they stand up
and they're able to give some type of a presentation, they're able to speak, and they speak authoritatively,
and they speak on a subject, and they are able with their fair speech deceive the masses.
Notice in Ephesians chapter number 4.
Not only do we note here in Romans chapter number 16 that it's by their good words and
fair speeches, but it's interesting as to what we see that Paul says here in Ephesians
chapter number 4 with regard to these deceivers.
In verse number 14, the Bible says that we henceforth be no more children tossed to and
fro and carried about with every wind of doctrine by the slight of men and cunning craftiness.
Notice this, whereby they lie in wait to deceive.
You know, there are people that are literally waiting to pounce on the opportunity to deceive.
They lie in wait to deceive.
Again, we live in the age of deception, and we find that it's interesting within the context
of Ephesians chapter number 4, and we'll mention this near the end of the message, but you
find that in verse number 11 it says he gave some apostles and some prophets and some evangelists
and some pastors and teachers.
Why did God give?
Why did He call these individuals?
Why did He gift these individuals?
Why did He give them to the church for, in verse number 12, the perfecting of the saints,
for the work of the ministry, for the edifying of the body of Christ.
Notice till we all come in the unity of the faith, under the knowledge of the Son of God,
to a perfect man, under the measure of the stature of the fullness of Christ.
One of the responsibilities of the pastor, and you see that that office is given, it's
referenced in verse number 11, is to feed the flock of God.
One of the terminologies that is used to describe the office of a pastor is that he's the undershepherd,
and it's interesting if you were to do a study in the book of Ezekiel and you would notice
the reference to the shepherds as God would give an indictment on the shepherds and how
they were more concerned with themselves than with the flock that they were called to minister
to.
And we think about the responsibility to feed the flock of God, to be a good shepherd, and
not to replace the good shepherd, the Lord Jesus Christ, and not to try to take that
title away, but to fulfill the ministry and to feed the flock of God, to proclaim, to
propagate the truth, to preach the word.
Why?
So we understand there are those that lie in wait to deceive.
Notice in Ephesians chapter number 5.
Notice what he says here in verse number 6.
This is interesting.
It says this, let no man deceive you with vain words.
Now the idea of vain words are words that are empty or words that are void of truth.
But he says this, let no man deceive you.
So I'm puzzled as I begin to look at this admonition, this charge, if you will, from
Paul to the believers in Ephesus under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God, when
he says, listen, there are people that lie in wait to deceive you, but let no man deceive
you.
So we know, we understand that there are those that lie in wait to deceive that are anxiously
awaiting the opportunity to pounce upon the opportunity to deceive you.
That's what he says to the believers in the church at Ephesus.
And then he says this, but let no man deceive you.
Similar to what Jesus said when he said, take heed, lest any man deceive you.
And you think about that taking heed, you think about here where he says, let no man
Let no man deceive you that we're on guard,
that we're taking caution,
that we are discerning and aware
of what's going on,
that we can filter everything through
what this book says.
He says let no man deceive you
with vain words, with empty words,
with words that are void of truth.
It doesn't matter that they may
have good oratory ability.
We must understand that often
those that are seeking to deceive
will use those vain, those words
that are void of truth.
Notice in Colossians 2,
we're preaching through the book of Colossians
on Sunday mornings.
Our theme throughout this year
has been found in verse number 10,
that we are complete in Christ
and what a blessed truth and thought that is.
But we find, and I preached this passage
of scripture many months ago,
but notice what Paul says to these believers
in Colossians 2 in verse number four.
In this I say, lest any man should beguile you
with enticing words.
Now, the word deceive is not here,
but the word beguile literally means
to deceive by false reasoning.
So he says, let no man deceive you
in Ephesians 5 and 6.
And here we find that it says,
in this I say, lest any man should beguile you
with enticing words.
A few verses later in verse number eight,
he'll say, beware, lest any man spoil you
through philosophy and vain deceit
after the tradition of men,
after the rudiments of the world,
and not after Christ.
How is it that they beguile,
the Bible tells us in verse number four,
with enticing words.
These enticing words are words or speech
that is adapted to persuade.
It's purposeful.
Specious discord leading others into error.
That's the idea of enticing words.
You understand when someone's trying to deceive you,
when someone's lying to you,
they don't announce that they're seeking to deceive you.
Amen?
They use enticing words.
They use fair speeches.
They use vain words.
Notice in 2 Thessalonians chapter number two,
we see this again.
This is a recurring statement that we see
throughout the Word of God
with regard to this subject of deception.
And here in 2 Thessalonians two and verse number three,
again it says, let no man deceive you.
But I want you to notice that in Ephesians,
it says with vain words.
In Colossians, it says with enticing words.
But here we find in 2 Thessalonians,
he says, by any means.
I mean, he's making the truth to these believers
and for us this evening to understand
that we're to let no man deceive you
by any means for that day shall not come
except there come a falling away first
and that man of sin be revealed, the son of perdition.
Very quickly in the book of 2 Thessalonians,
Paul had been used by God to minister
in the city of Thessalonica.
He was only there for a short period of time.
And he wrote 1 Thessalonians
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God
to the believers at Thessalonica.
And then there was some group or individual,
we don't know for sure,
but someone sent a letter to the church in Thessalonica
claiming to be from the apostle Paul
that was giving them wrong information.
And Paul deals with that.
And he says, let no man deceive you by any means.
Listen, they're crafty.
Remember the enemy, he's more subtle
than any beast of the field in Genesis chapter number three.
And so we find that here, listen,
the reality is that there is deception
that takes place in our land that times, at times,
comes from those that even would claim
to have some measure of Christianity
and be perhaps in the large umbrella of Christendom.
And I understand that that's a large umbrella.
And there are many that would claim the term
or the word Christian and Christianity
that have never been born again.
And we understand the difference,
but we find here that that deception
comes from a variety of areas.
And here for the church in Thessalonica,
there was a counterfeit letter that was written
that was claimed to be written by Paul.
And he says, let no man deceive you by any means.
Notice in 2 Timothy chapter number three.
In 2 Timothy chapter number three,
the text of Scripture begins by saying,
this know also.
Again, I had made this statement on Sunday,
how thankful I am that God desires
for His children to be informed,
that we would not be ignorant,
that we would have knowledge with regard
to those things that we would deal with.
And he says, this know also that in the last days,
perilous times shall come.
We do not have time this evening
to look at all of the description
that is given to us with regard to the last days,
but I would like you to draw your attention
to verse number 13, where the Bible says this,
but evil men and seducers shall wax worse and worse.
Notice what it says, deceiving and being deceived.
So there are these evil men and these seducers
that are waxing worse and worse,
and they're engaged in deceiving,
but they themselves are also being deceived.
Deceiving and being deceived.
Again, the age of deception.
Notice in the book of Titus in chapter number one,
as we look at this particular book of Titus,
we find that here, God is calling and directing
that Titus would go and serve in Crete,
and Titus is referred to as just a great relationship
that he had with Paul, his son of the faith,
and mentions the same type of verbiage
that is referenced there to Timothy.
We find that he was there in Crete,
and he had a responsibility in Crete,
and it was to set an order,
according to verse number five,
for this cause left I thee in Crete,
that thou should have set in order
the things that are wanting,
and ordain elders in every city as I had appointed thee.
And so we find that Titus has this call of God
upon his life, he's there for a purpose,
and we find that purpose in verse number five,
but you find that in verse number 10,
notice what the scriptures tell us,
for there are many unruly and vain talkers and deceivers,
especially they of the circumcision,
referring to the Jews.
And we find here that there were many
that were in this place Crete,
and they were here,
and Titus had this responsibility of setting an order
and helping the church there to go forward,
and we find that there were many unruly,
that carries with it the idea of being disobedient
and vain talkers, again, we saw that reference in Ephesians
with regard to the vain words, they're void of truth,
and then he says, and deceivers.
Did you notice that it says there are many?
Do you know that Crete was not a very large place?
It's not a very large place.
But there were many.
There were many.
Let's look at 2 Peter chapter number two.
Look at the three verses that begin this passage of Scripture.
In 2 Peter chapter number two,
the believers that are being addressed in 1 Peter
are in need of encouragement.
We find that in the book of 2 Peter,
they're in need of instruction.
By the way, we find ourselves in both of those scenarios,
do we not?
Many times in our lives that we're in need of encouragement
and we're in need of instruction,
and I'm thankful that the Word of God
satisfies both of those needs.
It instructs us and it encourages us.
In verse number one of 2 Peter two, it says,
but there were false prophets also among the people.
That's a statement of fact based upon the Old Testament.
There were false prophets also among the people.
That was undisputed.
We understand you can go back to the Old Testament
and you can see the false prophets that existed
and all that took place.
It says here,
even as there shall be false teachers among you.
And he tells us that these false teachers who privily
shall bring in damnable heresies,
even denying the Lord that bought them
and bring upon themselves swift destruction.
And many shall follow their pernicious ways
by reason of whom the way of truth
shall be evil spoken of.
And through covetousness shall they with feigned words
make merchandise of you
whose judgment now of a long time lingereth not
and their damnation slumbereth not.
We see the conduct that is given as a description here
of these false teachers that would be among us.
And though the word deceive in our English language
is not listed here,
no doubt we find that it's through deception
that they bring in these damnable heresies
that are spoken of in verse number two.
It's through their deception.
that many would follow their pernicious ways.
And we find that it's referenced in v. 3
that through covetousness,
they shall with feigned words
make merchandise of you.
Feigned words. That's false words.
As we begin to look at all of these verses
of Scripture this evening,
I believe that it's very easy for us
to identify and acknowledge
that we're living in a time of deception.
That there is the reality of deception.
I don't like to be lied to. Do you?
I don't like to be deceived.
If I'm deceived, and then I find out,
man, it bothers me. Amen?
I don't like to be deceived.
And we find that God warns us
that there's going to be this deception,
this danger of deception,
and we see it so prevalent in our society today.
One of the things that bothers me so greatly
about this idea of deception
is that we're living in a society
in which they're very orchestrated
and they're very purposed
in their attempt to deceive.
And you know what they're doing?
They're deceiving the little ones.
They're targeting the youngest.
They're using the classroom
as a means of deception.
We find that we're living in a time
in a society in which
they are using the classroom
and they're using the teachers to deceive.
And these little children
are going to school,
and the people that we have
historically and traditionally
look to with some level of honor and respect
of filling a role of being teacher
that is respected and trusted,
now that person is deceiving.
It's crafty.
That's what we're dealing with.
And all of a sudden,
Johnny and Susie come home from school
and the parents have taught their children
to respect the authority
and to respect the teacher,
and the teacher's seeking to teach you
that two plus two is four,
but there are other motives
that are going on,
and you just begin to read about
the curriculum that's going on
in our society today,
and you begin to do some research
about the Department of Education
and all that's taking place,
and what you're going to find
is that there is an agenda
to deceive the masses
through the children.
By the way, this is nothing new.
You can study history
and find that this has happened many times.
They target the young minds of children,
and they stand up
with a certain amount of authority
and a certain measure of confidence
and they're persuasive.
And again, little Johnny and Susie
are sitting in the class
and they're supposed to listen
and respect the teacher.
Satan is working.
And then we try to preach the truth
of God's Word to them
and their mind is so filled with deception
that has been given to them
over and over and over again
by people that are in places of authority
that it's almost as if
there's no room for truth.
It is a dangerous situation.
That's why we as parents
must be involved
in the education of our children.
It is absolutely essential.
You know that if you read
the entirety of the Word of God,
that there's only one group of people
that were ever made responsible
for teaching their children.
Parents.
Cover to cover,
Genesis to Revelation,
there's only one group of people.
I understand that not everyone
can homeschool.
I understand that.
But I am suggesting
that everyone ought to be involved
in the education of their children
because our children are being deceived.
Do you know that it's a lot easier
for them to deceive your child
than for them to deceive you?
It's a whole lot easier.
And then all of a sudden
your kids are teenagers
and they have these ideas
and you say,
where did you get this from?
Years of indoctrination.
The danger.
Listen, it's a reality
that we're living in.
We see the reality of deception
quickly this evening.
The remedy for deception.
What is the remedy?
Well, we find that Jesus said,
take heed to have discernment,
to be aware, to see,
to be aware of what's going on.
But I believe that in one simple word,
the remedy for deception is truth.
It's truth.
We must know truth.
We must teach our children truth.
You read Deuteronomy 6,
I mean, when they're coming and going
and sleeping,
I mean, just every part of your day,
every opportunity,
you're giving truth,
you're giving truth.
It's reinforced.
I was chatting with someone
at the conference that we're at
there at the Beacon Rally
and we were speaking about
the great hymns of the faith
and we spoke and said
how one of the wonderful things
about the great hymns of the faith
is that they reinforce Bible truth.
And you can take these hymns
and our hymnal
and you could preach a message
through the words of those songs.
Why?
Because they're founded upon biblical truth.
One of the songs that we sang,
just a little chorus,
nothing is impossible with God.
How do we know that?
Because the Bible says it.
Amen?
And then you put it to words
and you start singing it
and then all of a sudden,
you're reminding yourself repeatedly
that nothing's impossible with my God
because He's omnipotent,
because He can do all things.
And so we find that we must know truth.
I mentioned already
in Ephesians 4
where He said they lie and wait to deceive.
The very next verse in verse number 15
says that we're to speak the truth in love.
Truth is always the answer to error.
Always.
And the problem is that
there is a lack of knowledge of truth
or a lack of courage to stand for truth.
Notice what Jesus said in John 8.
We're familiar with the passage of Scripture.
In John 8,
in verse number 32,
the Lord Jesus Christ said this,
and ye shall know the truth
and the truth shall make you free.
Jesus declared in the 14th chapter of the book of John,
I am the way, the truth, and the life.
As He prays before He would go to the cross
in John 17,
in verse number 17,
He says, sanctify them through Thy truth.
Thy Word is truth.
God has given us truth.
And truth is the remedy to deception.
For many, many years,
Baptist people had been referred to
and spoken of as being people of the book.
That's a good statement.
It did not originate as being complimentary.
We look into the history and understand the origins.
But it's a good statement when someone says
you're a person, the Baptists are people of the book.
Why do they reject what the state church says?
Because what the state church says
doesn't line up with what the book says.
So we stand on what the book says.
Amen?
And so we have to know the truth.
Where is the reality of deception?
We are living in an age of deception.
It's a reality.
And we can't put our head in the sand.
But there's a remedy, and it's truth.
And that's why it's so imperative
that we're in this book.
Amen?
God's given it to us.
What sad state we are in
when we don't know the truth
and we believe a lie.
He says, let no man deceive you.
How am I going to let no one deceive me?
I better know the book.
I better know the truth.
And when that deception comes,
I'm able to combat that with
here's what God says.
Here's what God's Word says.
And that's so essential in the age in which we're living.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
We thank You for Your Word.
I pray that over the next several weeks
as we examine various portions of Scripture
with regard to the subject of deception,
that You would guide us and direct us,
that You would help us.
Lord, I pray that You would help us
to be people of the book,
standing on truth.
Would You help us to not only know the truth,
but to have the courage to stand for truth?
We live in this age of deception
and the reality of deception.
deception is all around us.
I'm so thankful this evening that You've given us the remedy, that You've given us a perfect
preserved book as the answers that we need.
We pray that You'd bless our time of prayer, for it's in Christ's name we pray, amen.
Does anyone not get a prayer bulletin that needs one this evening?