I mentioned this morning that I'd be preaching from this passage of Scripture and
The title of the message is from verse number 12. I mentioned that this morning as well. Think it not strange
Think it not strange as we look here in first Peter chapter number four. I'm going to read the text of Scripture
We'll get into the message
But as you study the book of first Peter you will find and understand that Peter is seeking
to minister to those who are enduring trials and
There are people that have been dealing with much adversity and much opposition
In fact as you begin looking in the first chapter you find that he says to the strangers that are scattered throughout Pontus Galatia
Cappadocia Asia Bithynia and there's this disbursement amongst these followers of Christ and as he's writing to these of course
The Roman Emperor at the time is Nero and by the way, if you know anything about history
he was not very favorable towards God's people and
You will find that they were dealing with much adversity and much difficulty
And so God would use Peter to be able to send this letter
Of course as even as I mentioned this morning all Scripture is given by inspiration of God
But God gave the opportunity for Peter to write this letter
And of course, there are two epistles first and second Peter
That he was used to be the human penman of but if you notice in chapter 4 and verse number 12
The Bible says beloved think it not strange concerning the fiery trial
Which is to try you as though some strange thing happened unto you
but rejoice and as much as you are partakers of Christ's sufferings that
When his glory shall be revealed
You may be glad also with exceeding joy
If ye be reproached for the name of Christ
Happy are ye
For the spirit of glory and of God resteth upon you on their part. He is evil spoken of but on your part
He is glorified
But let none of you suffer as a murderer or as a thief or as an evildoer
Or as a busybody and other men's matters yet if any man suffer as a Christian
Let him not be ashamed
But let him glorify God on this behalf
For the time is come that judgment must begin at the house of God
And if it first begin at us
What shall the end be of them that obey not the gospel of God?
And if the righteous scarcely be saved where shall the ungodly and the sinner appear?
Wherefore let them that suffer according to the will of God
commit the keeping of their souls to him in well-doing as
unto a faithful
creator
Again, Peter is seeking to encourage these that are dealing with
Enduring these trials and we find that he gives them good information
I mean helpful truth that is revealed in this passage of Scripture and as I begin to dig into the fourth chapter
I think it would be
Necessary in the very beginning of this message to go back to the first chapter and look at a few verses
That he Peter gives these believers in in the first
Verses 6 through 9 of chapter 1 we notice some truth that is given at the onset of this letter
With regard to that which they are enduring that which they are dealing with notice in verse number 6
Again in first Peter chapter 1 beginning in verse number 6 wherein ye greatly rejoice
Though now for a season if need be you're in heaviness through manifold temptations
That is that the trial of your faith being much more precious than of gold that perisheth
Though it be tried with fire might be found unto praise and honor and glory at the appearing of Jesus Christ
Whom having not seen ye love in whom though now you see him not yet believing you rejoice with joy
unspeakable and full of glory
receiving the end of your faith even
The salvation of your souls
As being to look at the these two passages of Scripture and go back to the fourth chapter if you will of first Peter
I want you to note first of all the encouragement from Peter
I want you to know how that the Apostle Peter is going to encourage these
Believers that are enduring trials. They're dealing with opposition with difficulty
The adversity is real in their lives and Peter is going to be used of God to encourage them
As we walk through several verses here in first Peter chapter number four will make note as to how Peter is seeking to encourage them
Of course
He's building upon the truth that he gave them in the first chapter in those few verses that we just read
You note that he says that if for a season if need be
That you're in manifold or in heaviness, excuse me through manifold temptations
But he tells them that the trial of your faith being much more precious than gold that perisheth and we find that Peter is helping
these
Believers through the encouragement that he will provide them with he's helping them to develop a biblical perspective
and it is necessary for us as the children of God to have a
Biblical perspective when you begin to deal with
difficulties and begin to deal with
adversities and trials and you're
Enduring these hardships when you're looking. I mean you notice how Peter refers to it in verse number 12 of chapter 4
he says that this is a fiery trial a
fiery trial and if we have a
biblical perspective
With regard to the trials that we are going to endure as the people of God it
Absolutely will enable us to respond properly to those trials if we do not have a biblical
Perspective if we begin to deal with hardships and trials and adversities
The devil is going to work you over
He's gonna come and he's gonna say God doesn't really love you
God doesn't really care about you
And if God did love you, then this isn't gonna happen and you're not gonna have to deal with that
Get thee behind me Satan. Amen, because we need to develop a biblical worldview a biblical perspective
especially with regard to trials and
Adversity in these things that we would endure we understand if we were to read the whole of Scripture that you will find
That those that went before us those that sought to accomplish something for God those who are willing to go and follow
The Lord Jesus Christ they face difficulty. There's opposition. There's adversity along the path
But it does not mean that God has forsaken us. It does not mean that God does not love us. We must never
forget that God loves us with an
Unconditional love with an everlasting love we understand there's nothing that can separate us from the love of God
We understand that God knows listen Matthew chapter number 10 talks about the fact that he knows the the number of hairs upon your head
He's got a subtract for me
He might have to add for some of you, but the reality is that God knows everything about us and he loves us
And
Casting all your care upon him why he careth for you
God loves us and when we're in the midst of a trial if we do not have a
Biblical perspective it is very likely it is very possible that we respond
wrong to that trial to that adversity
So we find that as the as Peter is seeking to encourage these believers that through this encouragement
He's helping them to develop this biblical perspective
And and also not only to understand and to develop this biblical perspective
But also to recognize that God has a purpose in trials
See, sometimes we'd like to think that it'd be better if we could live through life with no adversity
If we could go through our entire life and never have a problem never have a trouble that it'd just be wonderful
God has a purpose in trials. Amen
Brother Mark preached about the storm last Sunday morning
And Jesus said let us go to the other side and he and I were talking on Wednesday a little bit about that
The reality is that Jesus as God
Being omniscient knowing all things he could have said let's not go yet because there's gonna be a storm
he told him to go right in the midst of knowing there's gonna be a storm and
The reality is that when we understand this evening that God has a purpose in trials
Could you imagine how different our Bible would be if there were no trials that the people of God faced?
It would simply be a book of theory
But it's a practical book
It's not just a theory that God is always with us
It's not just a theory that he's able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think
It's not just a theory that he's with us through whatever the the difficulty the trial the circumstance may be that he can deliver us
Through it. No, we have
passages of Scripture that we can run to and we can be encouraged by
Understanding that God did not simply declare that he's all-powerful, but he
Demonstrated that he's all-powerful. And if there were never any troubles if there were no problems if there were no adversities
How's God showing his power? It's just a book of theory
I'm thankful that the Bible is not just a book of theory. The Bible is a practical book. I'm thankful
that there are some young Hebrew boys
that were willing to go into a fiery furnace
that we read about in Daniel chapter number 3,
that they believed that God was able,
that they said to Nebuchadnezzar
in all of his power, in all of his ability,
they said, we're not going to bow down.
I mean, really, I'd love to have been there.
Nebuchadnezzar thinks he's going to do him a favor.
We're going to play the music again for you.
And they said, well, you can play it
until the cows come home, so to speak,
but we're not going to bow.
That's in the Hebrew somewhere.
But you understand that if that passage isn't there,
Nebuchadnezzar never says, there's no God like your God.
Without that trial, without that difficulty,
what about Darius in Daniel chapter number 6?
He says, I know your God's able to deliver thee.
Daniel, has your God delivered thee?
Yes, O king.
But Daniel had to go into den of lions.
Amen?
And we look through the Word of God,
and we find that Peter is seeking to encourage
these that are enduring trials.
And he says, listen, as I provide this encouragement to you,
I'm trying to help you to develop a biblical perspective
to recognize that there is a purpose in trials.
And look at what he says in 1 Peter 4.
Notice in verse number 12.
He says, beloved.
Now, that's good.
We mentioned already that God loves us.
So he refers to them in verse number 12, beloved.
And what a mindful thing that we are loved by our God.
And of course, the love that we have
as brethren, one for another.
He says, think it not strange.
Don't think this to be an odd thing, an unusual thing.
Think it not strange concerning the fiery trial, which
is to try you.
Notice what he says.
As though some strange thing happened unto you.
You know that you're not the first one to ever have a trial.
And you're not going to be the last one.
And most likely, the trial that you're in
isn't going to be the last one.
I mean, we know.
There are going to be trials.
There are going to be adversities, difficulties
that we're going to deal with.
And he says, don't think this to be odd or strange or unusual,
that this thing has happened unto you.
It's very interesting when I read
that verse in verse number 12.
And I think about the words of Scripture
and I begin to understand even that which others have said.
He says, as though some strange thing happened unto you.
Hold your place there and go back
to the book of Philippians, if you will.
And I want you to notice what Paul says here
in the book of Philippians.
Again, allow your mind to think about that phrase
when he says, happened unto you.
Do you ever wonder why this has happened to you?
I mean, maybe you're in the midst of something.
You say, I don't know why this is happening.
I don't know why this is going on.
I don't know why I have to deal with this.
Or maybe you say something like I say,
I don't have time for this.
Honestly, you ever have a difficulty and say,
I just don't have time for this.
This is not, I didn't plan for this.
Yeah, but God knew you needed it.
Look at what Paul says in Philippians one,
in verse number 12, but I would,
ye should understand, brethren,
that the things which happened unto me
have fallen out rather unto the furtherance of the gospel.
Paul's saying these things that have happened unto me.
The things that he was enduring.
He's writing the book of Philippians,
by the way, from prison.
He's saying the things that have happened unto me.
Remember, he says, Peter says,
as though some strange thing happened unto you.
Paul says there's some things that happened unto me,
but I want you believers in Philippi to understand
that those things that have happened unto me
have fallen out rather unto the furtherance of the gospel.
God has a purpose in it.
God has a plan in it.
And there are some times that things will happen
in our lives, and we need not to think
that it's some strange thing that's happened unto us.
Understanding that we serve a God who is sovereign,
that is all powerful, that is all knowing,
and He has plan and purpose in these things.
In verse 13 of 1 Peter 4,
notice the first two words, but rejoice.
If we'd be honest this evening,
when we're dealing with a fiery trial,
and I'm not sure that most of the trials
that any of us have endured
would qualify as being a fiery trial.
Maybe some, but not most.
But rejoice.
How often when we face a trial
is our first response to that trial to rejoice?
How often is it that we have that attitude
of Brother Caldwell's children to say,
I wonder how God's gonna work this time?
What faith?
This trial has come in my life,
and I wonder how God's gonna manifest His power,
how He's gonna demonstrate and reveal to me
His purpose, how He's going to develop me through this,
how He's going to use me to be able to influence
and impact others as a result of this trial.
But rejoice.
And as much as ye are partakers of Christ's sufferings.
Now you understand that suffering always comes before glory.
Amen?
Go back, if you will.
Well, let's just stay here in 1 Peter just for a moment.
We'll go back to chapter number two and look in verse 21.
It says, for even here unto where ye called,
because Christ also suffered for us,
leaving us an example that ye should follow His steps.
Here He says that we're to rejoice,
and as much as ye are partakers of Christ's sufferings.
Now, again, I want you to hold your place here
and look in the book of Philippians.
This is good.
It's good because it's Bible.
It's not good because it's coming from me.
God helped me, and I hope it helps you tonight.
In Philippians chapter number three,
I am guilty, even as I said this morning in James 5,
of often quoting the last part of the verse.
Here, I'm often guilty of quoting
the first part of the verse.
That I may know Him and the power of His resurrection.
I like that part, but Philippians 3.10 says
that I may know Him and the power of His resurrection
and the fellowship of His sufferings,
being made conformable unto His death.
What did Peter say about these trials,
this fiery trial that these believers were enduring,
that they were dealing with?
He says, but rejoice.
Why?
And as much as ye are partakers of Christ's suffering.
How in the world would we ever imagine
that our Savior suffered,
but yet we're not gonna deal with any suffering?
Amen?
Jesus said, if they hate you, they hated me first.
Right, is that what He said?
Don't be surprised by it.
And the reality is that we see that yes,
there's suffering, and suffering comes before glory.
Notice, if you skip back over to 1 Peter,
we're gonna get back to verse 13,
but look down to chapter five in verse number one.
The Bible says this,
the elders which are among you I exhort,
who am also an elder,
and a witness of what?
Of the sufferings of Christ.
And also a partaker of the glory,
what does it say?
That shall be revealed.
Is that future, present, or past?
Future, that shall be revealed.
Listen, there was a time for Christ to suffer,
and He did.
And He said in John 17
that He would receive the glory that was due, right?
That He enjoyed from the beginning,
from the foundation of the world.
But we find that, I've often mentioned
that the first time He came,
He came to pay for our sin, He came to suffer.
When He comes again, He's not coming to suffer.
He's coming in all of His glory, in all of His power.
I understand when you consider
the second coming of Christ,
there are two aspects of the second coming of Christ.
The rapture, followed by seven years of tribulation,
and then the return of Christ when He comes.
And you look at that, and you look in Revelation 19,
you begin to study that.
He is coming as the conquering King.
He suffered, and there's gonna be glory.
Listen, for us, do you understand that glory
is not necessarily something
that we need to long for here on this earth?
There's gonna be some suffering.
And I understand we don't like to suffer.
I don't like to suffer.
I like being comfortable.
If you don't, you should go talk to someone.
Honestly, I like to be comfortable.
But we're trying to develop a biblical perspective
and understanding that God in His...
omniscience. If need be, you have this trial, you have this difficulty, and
rejoice. But rejoice, notice back in verse 13, but rejoice why? In as much as you
are partakers of Christ's sufferings, that when his glory shall be revealed, again
future tense you see here in verse number or chapter 5 verse 1 as we
mentioned ago a moment ago, ye may be glad also with exceeding joy. Do you see
the words that are used? Glad, exceeding joy. Verse number 14, if ye be reproached
for the name of Christ, happy are ye, blessed are ye. You say man that's not
how I feel if I'm reproached for Christ. Again we're trying to develop this
perspective. Peter's trying to encourage these, listen these folks were suffering,
dealing with some serious trials. God's gonna use Peter to encourage them.
Verse 14, if you be reproached for the name of Christ, happy are ye, for the
spirit of glory and of God resteth upon you. On their part he is evil spoken of,
but on your part he is glorified. Notice verse 15, but let none of you suffer as a
murderer, as a thief, or as an evildoer, as a busybody in other men's matters. In
other words, look, if you're suffering because of some wrongdoing, don't try to
think that you're supposed to rejoice in that and glory God and all that. That's
a different kind of suffering. And Peter wants to make sure that these believers
understand that the suffering that we're speaking about is when you're suffering
for Christ because you're doing what you're supposed to do, not because of
some wrongdoing on your part. Verse 16, yet if any man suffer as a Christian, let
him not be ashamed, but let him glorify God on this behalf. Notice the truth of
verse 17 and following. He says, for the time has come that judgment must begin
at the house of God, and if it first begin at us, what shall the end be of
them that obey not the gospel of God? Begin to find here some truth with
regard to these trials and the purpose in these trials, and we understand that
he speaks about this judgment that must begun first at the house of God, and
really God would use these to purify and to purge the child of God. And that's
the work that God's doing through it, and it's a purifying work, it's a purging
work. He says, if it first begin at us, what shall the end be of them that obey
not the gospel of God? The reality is that the worst thing that we could
suffer here upon this earth is the worst thing we're ever going to suffer. We have
all of eternity with our Savior if we're saved, and what glory is going to
be. Do you know for a lost man the the greatest pleasure that they're ever
going to enjoy is the pleasure that they can have here upon earth? Because for all
of eternity there's going to be judgment. That's a sad truth and ought to motivate
us and convict us to share the gospel with a lost and dying world, because only
the pleasures of this world, that's the only pleasure a lost person is ever
going to know. You consider the the fiery trial for the believer and how the
fire will purify and purge, but you think about the unbelievers, he says at the
end of verse number 17, and what shall be the end be of them that obey not the
gospel of God? If the righteous scarcely be saved, verse 18, where shall the
ungodly and the sinner appear? We know the great white throne judgment tells us
if you read Revelation chapter number 20, and death and hell were cast in the
lake of fire, this is the second death. And that fire is a fire of judgment,
it's punishment, it's eternal judgment. Aren't you thankful that the second
death has no power over you if you've trusted Christ as your Savior? And we
find this evening that as we look at this trial and look at these situations
and we understand, let me read verse 19, wherefore let them that suffer according
to the will of God commit the keeping of their souls to him in well-doing as unto
a faithful creator. He is the creator of the universe and he is
faithful. And we are to commit, notice what it says, commit the keeping of their
souls to him in well-doing. We commit ourselves to him. I want you to think
with me this evening about a fire. You know that fire burns straw but purifies
gold. It burns straw but it purifies gold. You think about the sun. The sun will
melt the snow but harden the clay. Same sun. Think about a pot of boiling water.
You know they say that a watch pot never boils. We wanted a boiling pot this
afternoon quickly. Why? Because part of our lunch was going to be some noodles
that were going to go with our lunch. And those enriched pasta noodles, they're
hard, they'll break your teeth. But you put them in boiling water and what
happens to them? They soften. But you put an egg in boiling water and what happens?
It hardens. See, God will use a fiery trial in our lives and if our hearts
right and we have a right perspective, he'll develop us through it. He'll teach
us truth about him that we can only learn in the midst of that trial. I spoke
with a man on Thursday. I never heard his full story until Thursday. I had heard
parts of his story in the past and I won't get into all the details. But about
14 years ago he suffered a horrific tragedy in his life from man's
perspective. And he stood before us and he said, I had already been a Christian
at that point in my life. I had trusted Christ years prior. I had been walking
with God. If you were to ask me if I was trusting the Lord, I would say yes. I was
teaching Sunday school. But he came home from church on a Sunday and he faced a
horrific tragedy. And here's what he said. God became real in that moment. He said,
I grew closer to God as a result of that moment than I had ever been to God.
See, sometimes there are things that we can just learn about God in the midst of
a trial. If those fishermen, if Peter and James and John and the other disciples
that are on the boat, to go back to Mark's message from Sunday morning, if
there was no storm, would they have ever known that Jesus could calm the storm?
What did they say? What matter of man is this? That even the winds and the waves
obey? Is that not what the Scriptures say? Well, if they never see him do it, it's theory.
We serve a God of application, a practical, truthful God. We think about
the note, if you will, the encouragement from Peter. But now I want you to
consider with me the experience of Peter, lest we think that Peter is
speaking to these that are suffering and dealing with this fiery trial, and they
might sit back, as has been my case on more than one occasion, and say, well, you
just don't understand. People will say that to you. They do. Peter understood what he was
talking about. We understand it's Scripture, it's God's Word. But I want you
to consider the experience of Peter just for a few moments. Go back to the
book of Acts, if you will. There are times in which I've had people tell me when I've
sought to counsel them that I just have never experienced what they've
experienced, and therefore I'm not qualified to counsel them. I understand
what they mean by that. I've often responded to them, and I've said this,
that if my counsel is based upon the Word of God, then you have to take the
counsel of God's Word. Whether I have experienced the same hardship as you
have or not, what does the Word of God say? But Peter is encouraging some people
that are suffering, but he understood what it was to suffer. Peter had endured
some great difficulties. In Acts chapter number 4, of course, in chapter number 3
we don't have time to deal with it. Our time is running short this evening. But in Acts chapter number 3
there's a great miracle that takes place, and the lame man is healed. And in chapter
number 4, listen, there's a great difficulty that's going on here.
These religious leaders are all in an uproar and all that's going on, and they
don't like the preaching that's taking place. And in verse number 3, they laid
their hands on them. We understand Peter and John are the disciples that are
mentioned, the apostles in chapter number 3. They laid their hands on them, and they
put them in hold until the next day, for it was now eventide. And so with that
idea of being put in hold, they were put into the prison. And they're gonna bring
them out, and they're gonna find out all that was going on. And as you continue
reading through Acts chapter number 4, they're called before the religious
leaders, and Peter stands up with power and in the power of the Holy Spirit and
proclaims to them that it was not in his power, it was not in John's power. It was
in the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth that this man was made whole, and that
there's no other name under heaven given among men whereby you must be saved. I
mean, he just went ahead and laid it on them and gave them Bible truth, and they
didn't like it. So you keep on going through Acts chapter number 4 and verse
number 17, it says, "...but that it spread no further among the people, let us..."
the religious leaders,
straightly threatened them
that they speak henceforth to no man
in this name.
And they called them and commanded them
not to speak at all nor teach
in the name of Jesus."
Now you understand that this group
of religious leaders, they had power.
They were the same ones that had put them in war
the night before.
They had power. They had authority.
But Peter and John, they answered in v. 19
and said unto them,
whether it be right in the sight of God
to hearken unto you more than unto God,
for we cannot but speak the things
which we have seen and heard.
Praise the Lord.
Continue to go through the book of Acts
and you see if you were to skip down
in v. 29, it says this,
And now, Lord, behold their threatenings.
I don't know all that they threatened,
but we find that they said,
let us straightly threaten them
that they may speak henceforth to no man in this name.
I'm pretty sure that the threat was not,
if you preach in His name,
we're going to slap you on the hand.
I just don't think that was the threat.
You understand, this was a serious situation.
In fact, in chapter 5,
they're ready to kill these guys.
We'll get there in just a moment,
but notice in chapter 4 and v. 29,
what their prayer is to the Lord
in response to the threatenings
is that they would be granted,
it says, and grant unto thy servants
that with all boldness they may speak thy word.
They're dealing with a difficulty,
but they say, we want to continue going on.
We want to continue to preach and teach
in the name of Jesus
because that's what we're commanded to do.
Chapter 5.
Look in v. 18, if you will.
V. 17 tells us how they were filled with indignation.
This again is the religious leaders,
the high priest is there,
and the sect of the Sadducees,
and it says that they say in v. 18,
they laid their hands on the apostles
and put them in the common prison.
And I love this passage of Scripture.
It says, but the angel of the Lord by night
opened the prison doors and brought them forth
and said, go, stand and speak in the temple
to the people all the words of this life.
And then it says in v. 21,
and when they heard that,
they entered into the temple early in the morning
and taught, but the high priest came
and they that were with him
and called the council together,
the senate of the children of Israel,
and sent to the prison to have them brought.
But when the officers came
and found them not in the prison,
they returned and said,
the prison truly found we shut with all safety
and the keeper standing without before the doors,
but when we had opened,
we found no man within.
Where are they?
What's going on?
And then this one comes in v. 25,
it says, then came one and told them,
saying, behold, the men whom you have put in prison
are standing in the temple
and teaching the people.
Isn't that awesome?
I love it.
You skip down, look in v. 28,
the Bible says this,
as they now have Peter and John
back in their presence,
and they said, did not we straightly command you
that you should not teach in this name?
And behold, you have filled Jerusalem
with your doctrine
and intend to bring this man's blood upon us.
Then Peter and the other apostles answered and said,
we ought to obey God rather than men.
The God of our fathers raised up Jesus,
whom ye slew and hanged on a tree.
Him hath God exalted with His right hand
to be a prince and a Savior
for to give repentance to Israel
and forgiveness of sins.
And we are His witnesses of these things.
And so is also the Holy Ghost
whom God hath given to them that obey Him.
When they heard that,
they were cut to the heart
and took counsel to slay them.
It's getting more serious for the disciples.
Ready to kill them.
Gamaliel stands up and he says,
hey listen guys,
there's some other,
Jared and I were talking about this on Friday morning,
there's some other guys
that had come around here recently
and man their work just kind of fizzled out,
they had a little following
but nothing really came of it
and if this thing be a thing of men,
then it's just going to fizzle out.
But he says this,
if it be of God,
ye cannot overthrow it.
If God be for us,
who can be against us?
That's Bible.
That's just not some saying
that some person came up with.
We are more than conquerors through Christ.
Amen?
Notice as they agreed with Gamaliel,
God says in verse number 30,
let's look at verse 40,
and to him they agreed
and so just to understand context
it was these religious leaders,
they agreed with Gamaliel
that which he said
and when they had called the apostles,
look at these next three words,
and beaten them.
And beaten them.
They commanded that they should not speak
in the name of Jesus
and let them go.
And they,
now that's talking about those apostles
that were just beaten,
departed from the presence of the council,
what's the word in your Bible say?
Rejoicing.
What did Peter say in 1 Peter 4 verse 12 and 13?
He said look,
think it not strange concerning the fiery trial?
Verse 13 starts with these two words,
but rejoice.
Right?
But rejoice.
That's how he's encouraging them,
but that's what he did.
That's what he did.
The example,
notice this experience that he had,
it says here
that when they departed from the presence
of the council, verse 41,
they were rejoicing
that they were counted worthy
to suffer shame
for his name.
And by the way,
verse 42,
and daily in the temple
and in every house
they ceased not to teach and preach
Jesus Christ.
That's what got them in trouble in the first place.
Right?
Don't preach in his name,
don't speak in his name.
They said well,
you determine what you want to determine,
but this is what we're going to do.
Amen.
See Peter wasn't just trying to encourage
them from dealing with a fiery trial
without any experience himself.
He'd experienced
the opposition.
He had experienced
the trial.
He'd experienced the hardship.
And he rejoiced
that he was counted worthy
to suffer shame
for his name.
I spoke with someone yesterday
and as I had the conversation with the individual
he was sharing with me
some situation about some
believers from Russia that had
come over to the United States of America
and some of their assessment
of what the church in the United States of America
is like today versus what it's like
in Russia.
What are y'all scared about?
We had to meet underground and they're going to kill us.
Russia. That's what happens.
There's a
very well-known
account of a Russian preacher
that was
dealing with all sorts of
adversity and difficulty and
you know,
the enemy's wicked.
He just is.
The enemy is ruthless
and relentless.
And
in this particular situation
they had threatened this preacher in Russia
many, many times and
it just was like falling on deaf ears.
He just kept on doing what he was doing
and kept on serving God.
And so they got a couple
of his daughters.
They apprehended his daughters
and in his
presence
they're going to put hot irons in the ears
of his daughters and cause them to be deaf
permanently.
If he didn't stop.
I can't even imagine.
But you know what the daughters said?
Daddy?
Don't deny Jesus for us.
And those Russian men
stuck hot irons in the ears
of those young ladies.
Many years later
someone had heard that story
and was worshipping in that part
of the world and he noticed
as he was there that there was an interpreter
giving sign language.
And he went and spoke with them through the interpreter
and found out that they were the very daughters
of that preacher.
Still serving
God.
Still faithful.
Can you imagine?
Listen, there's some trials that we can face in life
but God is with us.
And the reality
is sometimes we just have to change our thinking.
We have this idea that
everything is going to be perfect in our lives.
No, the glory is
to come.
There might be some suffering
here. Our Savior suffered
greatly.
And there might be some suffering here.
I'm not interested in suffering.
But the reality
is that I better be prepared for it.
Because if I'm not
prepared for it, I'm certainly not going to respond
properly when it comes.
Acts chapter number 12 and we'll finish.
In Acts chapter number
Herod is on a
showing
his power
situation here. Of course by the end of the
chapter he's
killed by God and eaten by worms.
Didn't work out so well for Herod.
But here in the beginning
of the chapter, we find
that the record is given to us
about him raising his hand against
the devil.
church, it says in verse 1 of Acts 12, now about that time Herod the king stretched
forth his hands to vex certain of the church. What do the next words say? He
killed James. He killed him. He killed James, the brother of John with the sword.
And because he saw it pleased the Jews. I can't fully wrap my mind around that, I
can't think in that manner, but there's some people that hate God and hate God's
people. And it pleased them. So what did he do? He proceeded further to take Peter
also. What's he gonna do with Peter? The Bible tells us in parenthesis in verse
number 3, then were the days of unleavened bread. And when he had
apprehended him, he put him in prison, delivered him to four quarterians of
soldiers to keep him. Notice what it says, intending after Easter to bring him
forth to the people. What was he gonna do? He's gonna kill him. Peter therefore
was kept in prison, but prayer was made without ceasing of the church unto God
for him. This morning we talked about intercessory prayer, the power of prayer.
You guys are praying. By the way, I don't have time to go through the whole
account. When Peter's knocking on the door, they're still in there praying, and
Rhoda's like, he's here, and they're like, you're crazy. No, no, it's him. They
finally let him in. Look at verse number 6. And when Herod would have brought him
forth, the same night Peter was sleeping between two soldiers, bound with two
chains, and the keepers before the door kept the prison. Behold, the angel of the
Lord came upon him, and a light shined in the prison. He smote Peter on the side
and raised him up. He was asleep good, amen? I mean, seriously, he's sleeping
good. The peace of God. Arise up quickly, and his chains fell off from his hands.
I don't have time to read all of it. Look in verse number 17. He, Peter, beckoning
unto them with the hand to hold their peace, declared unto them how the Lord
had brought him out of the prison. He said, Go, show these things unto James
and the brethren. He departed and went into another place. This evening, as we
think about this passage of Scripture in 1st Peter, and the fiery trial in
which they were enduring, he says, think it not strange. Think it not strange. This
isn't something odd or unusual. Understand, as he had laid the foundation
in the first chapter, that wherein we greatly rejoice, though now for a season
if need be, ye are in heaviness through manifold temptations. These trials are
going to come in our lives, but we understand that through the
encouragement Peter is seeking to help these believers develop a biblical
perspective and to understand that God has a purpose, and that God's purpose is
not always for your comfort or mine. Do you believe this evening that God could
have allowed Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego not to go into the fiery furnace?
He could have prevented it. Listen, he could have killed Nebuchadnezzar before
Nebuchadnezzar could give the order to put those boys in the in the fiery
furnace. Could he not? He could have caused an earthquake that could have
destroyed that whole fiery furnace and caused great chaos and confusion. He's
God. He could do anything, but he let him go in. He let him go in. And then
Nebuchadnezzar says, how many did we put in there? Three. We put them in their
bound, and there's four walking around, and the fourth is like the Son of God.
And then he says, there's no God like their God. How are they gonna know what
our God is able to do? Sometimes it requires a trial, and in God's master
plan, sometimes it's okay if the trials come. I'll finish with a personal story. I
was looking through pictures last night to find out when it was, and it was
December 6, 2013. I remember the exact day because it was Holly's birthday. I
didn't remember the year. Not that particular year, her birthday was on a
Sunday, and after church went to Olive Garden. Went to Olive Garden, that's where
she wanted to go to have lunch for her birthday, and you know they ask if you
want soup or salad. Got the salad. I was eating salad, not even a crouton. That
would have been a good story, but it was just lettuce, and my tooth cracked as I
was eating salad. Salad. True story. And I paused, and I kind of was like, what in
the world? The kids and Holly, like what happened? I was like, my tooth just broke.
They're like, what? Yeah, my tooth broke. No pain, thankfully. I preached that
evening with no pain, but on Monday morning I went to the dentist. Now here,
just being very transparent, here was my attitude. I don't have time for this. I
don't have money for this. This is really not a good time. I'm being transparent.
That was my attitude. My attitude was not, I wonder how God's gonna use this. I'm
just being honest with you, and if you always think that way, you're my hero.
Honestly, I don't always think that way. I wish I did, but my thought was, I don't
have time for this, and I don't have money for this. The doctor comes in, does
his examination. He says, well, the good news is that we can save the tooth. The
bad news is that we're gonna have to have a root canal and a crown. My first
question was, not that's great that we can save the tooth. My first question was,
how much is that gonna cost? He said, well, you're a preacher, aren't you? He said,
I'll charge you for the crown, but I'll do the root canal as a professional
courtesy. That's what he said. He left the room to go take care of another patient
and to have the assistant get me prepared for the procedure, and I had
seen this assistant a number of times over the last, you know, the couple of
years before that on just routine visits. And she comes in and she says,
Mr. Mann, I know why you broke your tooth yesterday. I hope you could inform me.
That was my attitude. How do you know why I broke my tooth? And I'll never forget
what she said to me. She said, God sent you here. She said, I knew you were a
pastor. You'd been here before. She said, I've not been living for God. In fact,
I've been far away from God, and God's been dealing with me, and God sent you
here. And at that moment, I said, sorry, God. If you want to break my tooth in
order to put me in that place, that's a... and he allowed it to break with no
pain. Honestly, that was good. But what I'm saying is that we serve a God who is
able to do amazing things. And I had the opportunity to speak to that lady. Can I
tell you, I would not have just shown up to the dentist that day if I didn't have
a broken tooth. Why else would I go to the dentist? I'm not just gonna go show
up at the dentist tomorrow. It's not my plan, right? You go to the dentist because
you have a problem, or it's your routine checkup. But I went on that day because
God allowed something to happen that I looked at as being a difficulty, you know,
why do I have to deal with this? That woman, that hygienist, she said, I
know why you're here. God sent you here. That was... those were her... those were not
my words. Can I tell you this evening that I wish that I would always, every
time I face a difficulty in a trial, that I would have a perspective of, God, I know
you allowed this for a purpose. Who is it that you're gonna allow me to have an
influence, an opportunity? I'm not there yet. God's still working in our lives. I
try to have that perspective as I spend more and more time in His Word, and He
influences me and changes me than I did seven years ago. I think about that more
today than I did then. Why? Because I've learned more about God, and I've
understood God's master plan a little bit better. I don't see things from His
perspective, and neither do you. We only see what He allows us to see. But the
reality is that our God has a plan, and our God is able, and if we truly are in a
place where we say, my life, Lord, is yours to control, as the songwriter said,
if we truly are gonna say, I surrender all, if we truly are gonna say, I am
crucified with Christ, for to me to live is Christ, and to die is gain, then we're
saying to God, do with me what needs to be done in order to accomplish your
purpose and your plan, whatever that is. Often we speak about
those that are in the armed forces that would sign a blank check up to and
including death when they serve our country. You know, as a child of God, have
we really surrendered all? Have we really said to God, God use me however you see
fit, whatever you need to do to accomplish your purpose. God has a
purpose and a plan. Think it not strange. Amen? God's working. It's a lot easier to
see it afterwards than it is in the midst of it. Amen? It was easier for me
on Monday afternoon to see why I broke my tooth on Sunday than it was for me on
Sunday. It just was. Let's pray. Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. I
pray that somehow this evening you'd help one many amongst us. No doubt with
a group this size there are difficulties and trials that we're enduring. God, I
pray that you'd help us to have a biblical perspective, help us to
understand you have a purpose, help us to truly come to that place where we'd
say we are crucified with Christ, that we truly surrender all, that our lives, Lord,
are yours to control. I pray that you'd use us, you'd help us to respond properly
to the trials. We'd rejoice greatly. Would you move in our midst that decisions
would be made that would please thee. We'll thank you for all that you'll do
for us in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me?