Corinthians chapter number two.
We're looking through the end of this chapter
and the first few verses of chapter number three
this evening.
First Corinthians 2.14 through chapter three
and verse number three.
And this is an ask the pastor message this evening.
Several questions in fact were submitted
that reference some of the social and cultural matters
that we are facing today.
As believers we know that we are in the world
but we are not of the world.
And of course this morning the young people,
four of our teenagers, they sang a great song.
Until then, and then this world is not my home,
I'm just passing through, amen.
And what a blessing and how as they were singing that song
and I was thinking about the message
I'd be preaching this evening
and the fact that we would begin by reminding ourselves
that this world is not my home.
And I'm not home but I'm heading home.
We've often said that we're strangers and pilgrims,
read that in Hebrews 11.
We do also know that the Lord is omniscient
and in his omniscience he has left us here
as his representatives.
It could have been that at the moment of salvation
we'd immediately be transported to heaven
and to be with him forevermore.
But he chose that after salvation,
if any man be in Christ, he's a new creature,
old things are passed away,
behold all things are become new,
that's like Corinthians 5.17,
Dean shared that with the promises this evening.
But verse number 20 says, and we are his ambassadors.
And so those new creatures,
as we trust Christ as our savior,
until we are taken home to our glorious heavenly home,
we are his representatives, we are his ambassadors
and we have a mission and we've been given that mission.
We are sent into the world to be the light of the world.
And we find that the Lord Jesus Christ,
of course, as he's praying there in John chapter number 17,
he mentions this very truth with regard to his ministry
and finishing the work that he'd been sent to do.
But he says this, I have given them thy word
and the world hath hated them
because they are not of the world
even as I am not of the world.
I pray not that thou shouldest take them out of the world,
but thou shouldest keep them from the evil.
They are not of the world even as I am not of the world.
Sanctify them through thy truth,
thy word is truth.
And then he says this in verse 18 of John 17,
as thou hast sent me into the world,
even so have I also sent them into the world.
We have been sent into this world.
We find that the believers in Philippi were told this,
that we are to be blameless and harmless,
the sons of God without rebuke
in the midst of a crooked and perverse nation
among whom you shine as lights in the world.
And so we begin to think about the questions
that were submitted with regard to some of the things
that we're facing, social and cultural matters
that we're facing today.
We'd understand that many of the things
that we're facing today are the same types of things
that people have been facing for all of humanity.
And we find that there's certain aspects
where we could say, well, it's never been like this before.
Well, it has actually.
There have been some very evil times
throughout the history of mankind
and we can read of those in the pages of scripture.
We can read of those in history books
and we can find that we here in this country,
obviously, have understood some things
with regard to the founding of our nation
and the righteousness, perhaps, as we would refer to it as,
that really laid much of the groundwork
and then we begin to see that turning away
and it's challenging.
In fact, at times in our society
as we're seeking to live in this world,
we can become frustrated.
We can become overwhelmed.
We begin to think about living
in the midst of such craziness
and all of the things that are taking place
and it can overwhelm us.
It can very much frustrate us.
We begin to think about the day in which we're living
and beginning to think about some of these shifts
that are taking place in our culture
and some of the things that were specifically mentioned
in the questions that were asked.
I thought about this word that I think best describes
the day in which we're living and it's relativism.
Relativism.
And here's what the word means.
It really, and they refer to it as a doctrine.
Relativism is the doctrine that knowledge,
truth, and morality exist in relation to culture,
society, or historical context and are not absolute.
That's what relativism says.
And that I think really sums up
the day in which we're living.
Everyone has this idea that it's their perspective,
that it's their truth and my truth
and someone else's truth and all of this relativism
that is so prevalent in our society today
and you notice that it says it's the doctrine
of knowledge, truth, and morality.
And those three things are what specifically
are mentioned in the definition of relativism
and it says that those things only exist
in relation to the culture or the society
or the historical context.
And that there is no absolute truth.
Now that's a problem for us.
As Bible-believing Christians, that is a problem for us.
Why?
Because we believe that there's absolute truth.
And we believe that as we have this book,
the Bible, the word of God, and we have this
as our standard and that there are absolutes
and we begin to interact with people
that are persuaded of this idea of relativism,
it can become frustrating to us.
It can be overwhelming to us of how do I interact?
How do I answer the questions?
How do I have conversation
and how do I help them understand?
Furthermore, we find that when we come to the position
and come to the table with having an idea
that there are absolutes and that we are of the opinion
that the Bible is truth and it stands
and it stands forevermore and that God has given us
this book and we say as Baptist people
that the word of God, the Bible,
is the sole authority for our faith and practice.
And when we come to the table with that perspective,
we recognize that oftentimes we will be categorized
as being authoritarians.
We may be categorized as being dogmatic or worse.
And so what do we do in a world
where we're seeking to follow the teaching
that God has given us?
He's provided us with the Bible.
He's provided us with truth
and he's left us in this world to be lights.
And we deal with all of the relativism.
We deal with all of the cultural and societal changes
that we're facing and we're dealing with.
And we say it's just never been like that in my time.
I hear people say that often.
If my grandmother were to be,
we hear people make those types of references.
Well, guess what?
This is where we are.
And this is the world in which we're living right now.
And so we better understand some things biblically
of how it is that God would use us in this particular time
in order to make a difference.
So often what's happening in the midst of a time
in which the world is changing and all of this relativism,
that churches are folding.
What do I mean by folding?
Well, certainly there are churches that are closing down,
but I mean that they're abandoning the truth of God's word.
They're taking positions that are more neutral,
if you will, that are not so dogmatic
and not so authoritarian and not so black and white.
But the reality is that what the world needs is truth.
They need truth because truth will set us free.
See, the Bible talks about the false teachers.
Peter actually deals with it, that they promise liberty,
but they're entangled in bondage themselves.
Wow.
And we find here that as we begin to unpackage this time
in which we're living and try to answer these questions,
I've titled the message this evening Spiritual Discernment.
And oh, how we need discernment
in the day in which we're living.
But really, as I begin to look at the world
in which we're living and I look at this passage
of Scripture and I think in just six verses of Scripture
that God gives us some clear insight
as to some things that we must understand
as we're going to interact with people in a changing world
where their morality is relative
to whatever they think it should be,
that their truth changes from one time to another time.
I've mentioned this before.
We've heard the terminology of woke and cancel
and all of those types of things.
And one of the things that's interesting
is that people that were being canceled
or canceling other people a few weeks ago,
they're being canceled today.
It just, that's the, why?
Because there's no absolute.
And it's a huge problem.
As we look at the text of Scripture,
notice in 1 Corinthians 2 and verse 14,
the Bible says this.
But the natural man receiveth not
the things of the Spirit of God.
are foolishness unto him, neither can he know them, because they are spiritually discerned.
But he that is spiritual judgeth all things, yet he himself is judged of no man.
For who hath known the mind of the Lord, that he may instruct him?
But we have the mind of Christ.
Verse 1 of chapter 3, And I, brethren, could not speak unto you as unto spiritual, but
as unto carnal, even as unto babes in Christ.
I have fed you with milk, and not with meat, for hitherto ye were not able to bear it,
neither yet now are ye able.
For ye are yet carnal, for whereas there is among you envying, and strife, and divisions,
are ye not carnal, and walk as men.
We find that the Apostle Paul introduces a couple of terms in these few verses of Scripture
that are new as far as the church at Corinth is concerned with regard to the written communication
that Paul would provide them with under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God.
We find one of them is given to us in verse 14, the natural man.
That's the first reference that we see to this term.
We find also that he mentions in verse 15 about the spiritual, he that is spiritual,
and then he speaks of that in verse number 1 of chapter 3, that I could not speak unto
you as unto spiritual, and then this third term, but as unto carnal.
So we see that there are natural, spiritual, and carnal men.
I'm going to focus on two of those three this evening and hope to help us as we seek to
navigate the times in which we're living and standing upon truth, not abandoning the
truth of God's Word, standing firm on what thus saith the Lord, and being able to still
be the light that God has called us to be.
We begin to interact with those that we come into contact with.
I think that there are two things that we must really comprehend, and number one is
this, there's a matter of spiritual blindness.
There is a matter of spiritual blindness.
See the Bible tells us in verse number 14, as I've read already, that the natural man
receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God.
Why?
For they are foolishness unto him, neither can he know them, because they are spiritually
discerned.
Those, as we look in verse number 14, we find that the natural man is referring to the unregenerate
man, the unsaved man.
That's who's being referred to here in verse number 14 of chapter number 2.
And we find that the Bible says that the Spirit of God, if you look here, it says that the
natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God.
Why?
Well, because the Spirit of God doesn't dwell within them.
And so since the Spirit of God does not dwell within them, then He does not teach them the
Scripture in the same way that He teaches us the Scripture.
And so if something amazing took place at salvation, and actually a lot of somethings
that are amazing took place at salvation, that many of us did not understand all of
them on the day that we got saved.
But when you grow in grace and knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ and begin
to learn more about your salvation, it begins to, man, amaze us as to all that took place
on that day when we trust that Christ is our Savior.
And one of the amazing things that took place is the Holy Spirit of God indwelled us.
The Bible tells us that the Holy Spirit of God is the divine teacher.
In John 16 and verse number 13, the Bible plainly tells us as Jesus is preparing to
go to the cross of Calvary and He's giving the disciples some instruction with regard
to the days ahead and the ministry that they would have to fulfill.
He says this in verse number 13 of John 16, how be it when He, He's speaking of the Holy
Spirit, He refers to Him as the Spirit of truth.
We understand that He's referred to Him as the Comforter, even within the same context
of this passage with the instruction that He's giving, and He calls Him here the Spirit
of truth.
And He says that when He, the Spirit of truth, has come, notice what it says, He will guide
you into all truth.
For He shall not speak of Himself, but whatsoever He shall hear, that shall He speak, and He
will show you things to come.
I'm so thankful for the Holy Spirit of God, who is the author of Scripture, but also He
is the teacher of Scripture, and He indwells us.
But when we begin to think about this matter of spiritual blindness in 1 Corinthians chapter
number 2, and we begin to understand that Paul is saying, listen, the natural man receiveth
not the things of the Spirit of God, the Holy Spirit doesn't dwell within them, and therefore
the Holy Spirit is not teaching them, and here as we look at this truth and this matter
of spiritual blindness, what we must acknowledge this evening is that at times when we begin
to have these conversations with individuals in our society and in our culture that have
this completely different worldview, they've followed whole, completely and wholeheartedly
this idea of relativism and what have you, then we go to them and we seek to have interaction
with them, and our scriptural, spiritual argument is rejected.
Why?
Because it's foolishness to them.
They don't understand it.
The things that are contained within this book are spiritually discerned.
So when we begin to have a discussion with an individual that is not saved, this matter
of spiritual blindness, they are lost, it's the natural man, the unregenerate man, the
unsaved man, we begin to try to give them Bible passages to prove our position, and
then we beat our head against the wall because they don't understand it.
But you know what's amazing?
God told us that they wouldn't understand it.
The truth is that these that are categorized as being natural men, unsaved, unregenerate
individuals, they need to be saved.
The message for them is the gospel of Jesus Christ.
That is the message that they need.
And we find that in the same text of Scripture in John chapter number 16, when he speaks
about how the Holy Spirit of God, the Spirit of Truth would come and He would guide us
into all truth, if you look and you notice what's taking place with regard to His ministry
amongst the unregenerate, the natural man, it says in John 16 in verse number 8, speaking
of the Holy Spirit, the Spirit of Truth, the Comforter, that when He has come, He will
reprove the world of sin and of righteousness and of judgment.
Of sin, why?
Because they believe not on Me.
That's the unbelieving, that's the natural man, that's the unregenerate man, that's the
lost man, the unsaved man, and it says that He's going to the Holy Spirit of God that
when He comes that He will reprove the world of sin and of righteousness and of judgment.
Of sin, because they believe not on Me.
Of righteousness, because I go to My Father and you see Me no more.
Of judgment, because the Prince of this world is judged.
No doubt, if you've been in our services for any length of time, you've heard me make the
statement as I've prayed that the Holy Spirit of God would convict the lost of their sin,
of Christ's righteousness, and of judgment to come.
That's from John 16, verses 8 through 11.
And that is the ministry of the Holy Spirit of God toward this natural man, the unregenerate
man.
I'm not sure if you can remember when you were lost.
Some of us, we can remember when we were lost, we got saved later in life, and we can remember
when the individuals that we might interact with in that lost condition would try to share
biblical truth for us, and it just didn't make any sense.
And then you get saved, and you begin to hear the same Bible verses that maybe you heard
before, and it's like, oh, this makes sense now, because the Holy Spirit of God dwells
within you, and the Holy Spirit of God teaches you.
The Holy Spirit of God convinces you and confirms truth.
And for that, we ought to rejoice and we ought to be thankful, but what happens sometimes
is when we're dealing with those in our culture and our society that are shifting and moving
and they've adopted this philosophy of relativism, and their philosophical ideas are so foreign
to what we would believe and what we hold dear, and no, we say there are absolutes.
And I got 105 verses that I can give somebody and show them why, but they're lost.
They're lost, and they need to be saved.
This matter of spiritual blindness is so important for us as the people of God to understand.
In the book of 2 Corinthians chapter number 4, 2 Corinthians chapter number 4, the Bible
tells us of what the enemy is doing with regard to keeping people blinded.
2 Corinthians chapter number 4.
The Bible tells us in verse number three
that if our gospel be hid,
it is hid to them that are lost.
By the way, they're the ones that need it.
We sing the song, I love to tell the story.
And as we sing the song,
it talks about one of the verses
of those that have never heard, right?
Because there's so many that have never heard.
I love to tell the story to those that know it.
I mean, listen, we rejoice in knowing it,
but there's a world that's never heard
the wonderful story that Jesus saves.
And if our gospel be hid, it's hid to them that are lost.
Notice what the Bible says in verse number four.
In whom the God of this world, who is that?
That's Satan.
It's a little g.
The God of this world, Satan,
hath blinded the minds of them which believe not.
Lest the light of the glorious gospel of Christ,
who is the image of God, should shine unto them.
You know, Satan wants to keep people lost.
He don't want people to get saved.
And so this thing of spiritual blindness
is so important for us to understand.
In John chapter nine, we won't take the time to go there,
but there's a wonderful account of a miracle
that took place of the man that was born blind.
At the end of the text of Scripture,
after all of the interaction with the spiritual,
or excuse me, the religious leaders,
and this man, and his family, and all that takes place,
we find it at the very end
that when they're talking to Jesus, they say this.
Are we blind also?
They were not blind physically
as that man that was healed was blind physically,
but oh, they were blind spiritually.
And we find this evening
that this truth of spiritual blindness,
this matter of spiritual blindness is so imperative
for us as the people of God to understand.
We ask questions of how could somebody vote
the way that they vote?
How can they support the things that they support?
How can they stand for the things that they stand for?
Many times the answer is that they're lost.
They're lost.
If a blind person, physically blind person,
were to run their cart into you at Walmart,
you immediately upon being hit with the cart
may stop and be like, oh, did you?
And then you find out that they're blind,
and all of a sudden your interaction
with that person is going to change.
Why?
Because they're blind.
They didn't see you.
And you're going to have a measure of compassion
and understanding that they hit you with their cart
because they could not see.
But yet when it comes to spiritual matters,
it's as if we forget that we're interacting
with people that are lost.
They're unregenerate.
They're unsafe people.
They are referred to as being the natural man,
and they receive not the things of the Spirit of God.
Why?
Notice what it says.
Not only do they receive not the things
of the Spirit of God,
but it says that they are foolishness unto him.
Neither can he know them.
You know, it's amazing in Albania,
and some of you know some things about Albania.
The Hasaflux are missionaries that we've supported there
for a number of years.
Many years ago upon their original arrival into Albania,
I understand this as I've had interaction
and chatted with Brother Hasaflux over the years,
that basically the people of Albania would say
to be atheist and to be Albanian were kind of synonymous.
I mean, it was their identity.
If you were Albanian, you were an atheist.
It's just the way it was.
And unfortunately that land was just gripped in darkness
and all sorts of things were taking place.
And of course, Brother Hasaflux praised the Lord
for a man that is faithful, that God has used,
and people have been saved.
And it's amazing some of the things that have happened there
and some of the open doors and opportunities.
But it's interesting, he shared with me an account
where there was a professor that he was working with,
and that professor in Albania used the King James Bible
in college classes as an English textbook,
as an English textbook, but said he was an atheist.
This book isn't a textbook.
This book is a living book.
This book is profitable, it's precious.
And we find that the natural man,
he can't understand it, he can't discern it.
And the Bible says because they are spiritually discerned.
So often, and I'm guilty of it,
I hope that you could acknowledge
as you evaluate in your own life,
perhaps there's times that you're guilty of it as well,
you're having interaction with a lost person
and you're trying to prove your point biblically
and you're giving them Bible verses
and you're just not understanding
why they're not getting it.
And then we have to step back and say, they're not saved.
They're not saved.
They need the gospel.
And so we find that as we begin to think about interacting
with those in our culture and our society
and all the shift in worldview that's taking place,
we must recognize this evening
that there's this matter of spiritual blindness.
He continues in verse 15 of chapter two.
It says, but he that is spiritual judgeth all things.
You know that word judgeth and the word discerned
in verse number 14 are the same exact word.
They're used here.
It's the same Greek word.
And so we find that they're certainly appropriate
translation of what's taking place.
But he says that he that is spiritual judgeth all things.
Yet he himself is judge of no man.
Notice what the Bible says in verse 16.
For who hath known the mind of the Lord
that he may instruct him.
And then he says, but we have the mind of Christ.
So this is very interesting that he says
that we have the mind of Christ.
For we find that Paul would then say this
to the believers in Philippi in chapter two
in verse number five.
Let this mind be in you which was also in Christ Jesus.
Where do we get the mind of the Lord?
Right here.
This is where we get the mind of the Lord.
And so there are many times that people,
it was a fad that was going on.
And I guess it's different now what they say.
The question is, the fad that was going on,
what would Jesus do?
The WWJD thing that was going on was very popular.
And I guess now there's a spinoff of that
that he would love first is kind of what I understand
from some young people.
I saw some things, I'm like what does that mean?
And they explained it to me because I'm getting old
and don't understand all those things.
You guys ever get text messages with people
putting a whole bunch of letters together
and it's supposed to mean something?
You get those kind of things?
I'm like what in the world?
Anyway, rabbit killed it, we're going back.
And here's the deal though, we have the mind of Christ.
Most people, they ask the question, what would Jesus do?
The problem is that a lot of people have no idea
what Jesus would do because they never have gotten
into this book.
They're running around saying what would Jesus do
but they have no idea.
And so we find this evening that when we're interacting
with people, some of the source of our frustration
and the times in which we become overwhelmed
with trying to get people to understand our perspective,
we are dealing with lost people.
Number two, not only a matter of spiritual blindness
but as we continue into the third chapter
of 1 Corinthians, we find that there's a matter
of spiritual immaturity.
There's a matter of spiritual immaturity.
So there's a matter of spiritual blindness
but then there's also a matter of spiritual immaturity.
If I were to be transparent this evening,
this one's probably a little harder to deal with.
Why?
Because the person professes to be saved
and they may very well be saved.
I mean, obviously as we're speaking from the context
of the scripture, a spiritual immature person,
a carnal person, they're a saved person.
They're not categorized as being the natural man.
It's a separate category but dealing with that one
that professes Christ but is spiritually immature,
they are carnal, they've been just influenced
by the world and the culture and the society
and they've bought into all of the things
that the world is saying and they've discounted
the truth of God's word, it's challenging.
Just being very honest and transparent this evening,
it's challenging.
But we find that it is important for us to understand
that when we interact with people,
there will be some that we interact with
that are spiritually blind but there are some
that are spiritually immature.
It says this in verse number one of chapter three.
Notice what Paul is saying.
And I, brethren, he calls them brethren.
I mean, they're saved people.
He says, I could not speak unto you as unto spiritual
but as unto carnal, even as unto babes in Christ.
I think this is sad, don't you?
I think that Paul is having this heart here
of there's so many things that I wish I could say to you,
that I wish I could give you but I understand
that those things are meat and I have to give you
a milk diet.
He says that in verse number two.
I have fed you with milk and not with meat.
Why?
for hitherto ye were not able to bear it, neither yet now are ye able." And so they
were just spiritually immature people. They were not growing as God had
designed it to be that they would be growing in their faith, and they're
spiritually immature. And Paul says that when I came, when I'm writing to you,
when I seek to minister to you, I cannot do it as unto spiritual, but I have to do
it as unto carnal, as babes in Christ. He says in verse number three,
for ye are yet carnal. And then he describes what that carnality, how it's
going to play out. He says, whereas there is among you envying and strife and
divisions, are ye not carnal and walk as men? The envying, the strife, and the
divisions that were prevalent in the church in Corinth were a direct result
to their spiritual immaturity. And that spiritual immaturity, unfortunately, does
not allow people to receive the meat of the Word of God. Notice what is said over
in Hebrews chapter number five. In Hebrews chapter number five, we find that
here the Lord is giving us truth with regard to those that are in the same
category as being spiritually immature. And in Hebrews chapter number five, and
beginning in verse number 11, notice what the Bible says. Of whom we have many
things to say, and hard to be uttered. Why? Why were these things hard to be
uttered? Seeing ye are dull of hearing. I don't want to be in that category. He
says this, for when for the time ye ought to be teachers, ye have need that one
teach you again, which be the first principles of the oracles of God. And it
becomes such as have need of milk, and not of strong meat. Now think about this
in verse number 12. Some have asked me this question over the years. When is it
that somebody should be a teacher? I really don't know the answer to the
question, but no doubt under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
the human penman to the book of Hebrews knew that it was time that these people
that he's writing to should be teachers. Your spiritual journey and your
spiritual growth is, every single one of us will grow at a different pace, but we
ought to be growing. And the writer of Hebrews under the inspiration of the
Holy Spirit of God says, for when for the time ye ought to be teachers,
ye have need that one teach you again, which be the first principles of the
oracles of God. Now listen, we have to understand this evening that it's not a
problem that a believer needs the milk of the Word. That's where we all
begin, on the milk of the Word. The problem is when we ought to be having
meat and we're still on a milk diet. That's the problem. And we find here,
listen, I'm thankful that I'm not on a milk diet anymore. Aren't you? I mean,
praise the Lord. Can you imagine if all you had was milk? That'd be horrible. I
hate milk. I mean, unless it's with cookies or donuts or something, and then
it's just double bad. I am thankful physically that I'm not just on a milk
diet, but spiritually. God uses that same analogy and illustration for us to
understand, listen, there is the meat of the Word. He says this in verse 13, for
everyone that useth milk is unskillful in the word of righteousness, for he is a
babe. Again, we all start with the milk. It's necessary. The Bible says this in
1 Peter 2 and verse number 2, as newborn babes desire the sincere milk of the
Word that ye may grow thereby. There's a, when you begin to have
discipleship, when you begin to have some teaching of some new believers, you want
to start with a good foundation. You want to begin to give them the milk of the
Word of God. And why? Because it helps that growth, and it helps them to grow as
babes in Christ, to gain that spiritual discernment that they need. Oftentimes
I've had people say to me, I've tried reading the Bible and I just don't
understand it, and I don't get this, and I get to this portion of the Bible, and
it seems to be that they always say Leviticus. I'm not sure what's wrong with
Leviticus, but everybody seems to say they get to Leviticus, and they just
can't get through. And I try to encourage some new believers, listen, read the book
of John. Start in the book of John. I don't send them the first Chronicles. I
save that for Blake to read on Christmas Eve. But you understand why we want
them to grow, give them some milk of the Word. And we find that here, they
then, as they grow, that milk, it says that everyone that useth milk, that
everyone that useth milk is unskillful in the word of righteousness, for he's a
babe, but strong meat belonging to them that are full age. Even those who by
reason of use have their senses exercised to discern both good and evil.
Now this is a very difficult point to really be able to say with absolute, and
that is when is somebody in a position where they're truly a babe in Christ and
growing, and they're on the milk of the Word, and when is somebody spiritually
immature? That's gonna vary, and it's not as easy as it is when you deal with the
natural man, the spiritual blindness. But the reality this evening is that when we
begin to look at this situation in Corinth and look at what's taking place,
and of course if you do any study whatsoever with regard to the the city
of Corinth and the wickedness and the culture and all that was taking place,
you will find that no doubt they were living in times in which there was
similar types of situations that we deal with even today. They would use the term
to describe someone that was living in a wicked, immoral life, whether they were
in Corinth or around the region of Corinth, they would refer to the
individuals that would be living an immoral life as living like a Corinthian.
That's how bad it was in Corinth. And so they're living in that time, and Paul is
saying, listen, I have some truth that I want to give you, but you can't get it
yet because you're spiritually immature. And there are times when we begin to
deal with the culture in which we're living in, begin to deal with the things
in which we're facing, that there are times in which we're dealing with people
that are lost, they're the natural man, there's the matter of spiritual
blindness, but then there are times in which we're dealing with people that are
just spiritually immature. We find that I mentioned already about 1 Peter 2 and
verse number 2, as newborn babes desire, this is the cereal milk of the Word, that you
may grow thereby. We find that over in 2 Peter 3 and verse number 18, the
Bible says, but grow in grace and knowledge of our Lord and Savior, Jesus
Christ. And so we understand this evening and we can say with absolute
certainty that it is God's plan and God's design for His children to grow.
It is not God's plan or God's design that His children would remain babes in
Christ, that we would remain spiritually immature. No, His plan and His desire is
that we would grow in grace and knowledge of our Lord and Savior, Jesus
Christ, that He gave us the Bible so that we could grow, that we could have
that spiritual discernment, so that we could look at things in our culture and
our society, that we could look at the things that we face in our lives and the
the things that come our way, and we can have the spiritual ability to process
those things and respond to those things. I've often said as I read Psalm 119, what
a wonderful psalm it is, and you think about all that the psalmist says about
the Word of God and how wonderful it is and how precious it is and so on and so
forth, that our desire ought to be, as the psalmist declares, that we would think
and act biblically. It requires that we grow spiritually, and so when we begin to
think about and we begin to have these interactions of meeting people and
seeking to interact with them, and of no doubt the conversations come up about,
hey, did you hear this and did you see that and did you hear about this thing
over here, and those conversations no doubt take place in our lives. People
bring things up to us. What do you think about? Did you hear about? You get those
kind of conversations, and so what do we do? How do we deal with those people that
we're interacting with when we have a belief that the Bible is the absolute
truth and that this thing of relativism is nonsense because there is absolute
and there is absolute truth, there is right and wrong, there are morals and
immorals, there's a right way to behave and there's a wrong way to behave, and we
find that God has given us His Word and He's outlined those things for us. So
what do we do? Well, I believe that as we deal with those, that if we could
categorize them as being spiritually blind, we say, let's get back to the
the gospel. Do you know how many times I've had conversations with people trying to, I'm
saying lost people, because I've had conversations with lost people, and I begin to try to give
them the gospel, many times, many times they'll ask questions that have absolutely nothing
to do with the gospel. They want you to go over here and talk about this, and they want
to come over here and talk about this, and all of these things that are away from the
gospel. And so often what I do is I say something like this, you know what, that is a really
good question, and I will answer that, but let's look at this first. Why? Because I want
to get to the point of the gospel because they need to be saved. They're not going to
understand, why do you believe the way that you believe? Well, here's all the verses that,
they're not going to get it. They're the natural man, they receive not the things of the spirit
of God. They're foolishness unto him, neither can he know them. Why? They're spiritually
discerned. And so we need to get back to the gospel, get back to the gospel, get back to
the gospel. And we need to be very direct about it. We need to be disciplined. Sometimes
what happens if we're not careful is somebody will ask us a question that will distract
us or detour us from really the main point, and we feel like we have to answer that question
so that we don't seem like we don't know. Because we wouldn't want them to think that
we're ignorant to that particular question, or that we're unlearned, or whatever the case
may be. No. So we think we've got to answer all these questions. No, no, no. We have to
be disciplined to stay on track with the gospel. What about those that are spiritually immature?
Well, I've learned, I am learning, maybe I should say, that'd be a better way to put
it. I am learning that it is important that we meet them where they are and then teach
them the truth within the pages of this precious book. And we go systematically and we try
to teach them, here's what the Bible says. But listen, before I'm going to take them
and show all them these things about what the Bible says, I must be able to teach them
what the Bible is. Does that make sense? Because before I tell them what the Bible
says, I need them to understand what the Bible is. Because if they don't understand what
the Bible is, then it doesn't matter what the Bible says. Because if they don't believe
that the Bible is the authority, that the Bible is God's Word, that the Bible, all Scripture
is given by inspiration of God, if they do not believe that this book is divinely inspired
and supernaturally preserved, if they don't have confidence in this book, then I can take
them to all the verses of what it says, but it really doesn't help. Why? Because they're
still stuck on what the Bible is. You know how many people think that the Bible is just
man's Word? Tons of people. They think that the Bible is man's words. I read an article
last week about an individual that used to be a pastor, now is an author, visits churches
to try to encourage them. You know what he says about the Bible? He says, the Bible is
not the Word of God. The Bible is simply man's words about God. Well, if that's really
the truth, then we just, I mean, what's the point? If it's just man's words about God,
then that doesn't do anything for anybody. But we find that this book, see, I have to
start, I have to build a foundation, right? I've never built a house, I'm not going to
build a house, you don't want me to build a house, but I do understand some things about
building a house. If you're going to build a house that's going to stand, you better
spend some time on the foundation. If you don't spend time on the foundation, you're
going to have problems, right? And so therefore, when I begin to deal with somebody that would
fall within this category of being spiritually immature, I do not need to judge them for
their spiritual immaturity, no, rather I'm going to try to teach them. I'm going to meet
them where they are, I'm going to help them to grow in grace and knowledge of our Lord
and Savior Jesus Christ. Well, that's just your opinion of what the Bible says. That's
just your interpretation of what the Bible says. But again, we must get back to starting,
that's why when I have discipleship classes, I always start with the Word of God, always
the foundation. Because everything that we're going to look at as a Baptist, we say the
first point of Baptist distinctives is this, that the Bible is the sole authority for faith
and practice. You know, there's a lot of people, a lot of groups of people that say they believe
the Bible. But they only believe the Bible if it aligns with their experience. They only
believe the Bible if it aligns with what a church father said or something else. So they
really don't believe that it's the sole authority for faith and practice. And so therefore,
I must begin there with the basics and say, here is what the Bible is. And then when I
can get somebody to agree that the Bible is inspired and preserved and profitable and
all that the Bible is, then I can say something like this, can we agree that we are going
to agree with God? We're going to go to God and His Word and we're going to see what God's
Word says. And if we can agree that this is God's Word and it's inspired and it's preserved
and this is the standard, we can get somewhere. But if we don't have that foundation, you
can beat your head upon the wall. I've been there. I have. I'm just telling you. And seemingly
get nowhere. Why? Well, because they really didn't believe that this book is what you
believe this book is. And so you're talking on two different wavelengths. Does that make
sense? Because I have a belief of what this book is and so therefore when I turn to a
verse of Scripture and say, bam, that's what the Bible says, then I'm thinking they're
at the same place I am with regard to what they believe the Bible is. And then all of
a sudden I find out they don't really believe the Bible is what I believe the Bible is.
And so we can avoid a lot of frustration. We can avoid a lot of difficulties in our
own lives as we have these types of conversations when we acknowledge that there's a matter
of spiritual blindness and there's a matter of spiritual immaturity. And I'm going to
seek as I interact with those individuals to be able to meet them where they are and
give them what they need. Paul said, I have some things I wanted to tell you, but I can't
because you're not spiritual, you're carnal. Basically that's what he says in 1 Corinthians
chapter number 3 verses 1-3. And so we find that he says there in Hebrews 5, there's some
things that I want to tell you. They're hard to be uttered. Why? Because you're dull of
hearing. Because in the time that you ought to be teachers, you're actually having need
that somebody teach you. And so we find that there was an understanding on the part of
the spiritual leader of the person that had a certain amount of spiritual awareness and
a spiritual discernment to know, here's how I need to approach this particular subject,
this particular matter. See, it's really not unlike other fields of life. If you're going
to teach somebody how to do certain things, whether you're going to teach them how to
put up drywall, you're going to teach them how to paint, you're going to teach them how
to lay carpet, you're going to teach them how to lay tile, you're going to teach them
how to play the piano, you've got to start where they are. Right? I come to Holly and
I say, teach me the piano. I want to play a hymn next Sunday for a special. I'm ready
to go. It ain't going to work. That's not where I am. So she's going to have to take
me to the, like, level one book. Is there something below level one? Just one hand at
a time, just a few notes, maybe the letters of the keys on the notes, because I don't
know what, do you understand what I'm saying? Why? Because that's where I am. And that's
where she would have to have the discernment as a teacher of, I'm not ready to put this
piece of music in front of you because you're not able to do it. And so this evening, we
can avoid a lot of frustration and a lot of difficulty in our lives when we interact with
people. We get so frustrated. Why don't they see it like we see it? Well, it might be because
they're spiritually blind. They need Jesus. They need to be saved. It may be because they're
spiritually immature. They might be saved, but maybe no one's ever taken and taught them
the truth of God's Word.
Maybe no one has taken the time to invest in them and give them some discipleship and
teach them, and we just have an expectation in our mind that, well, they've been around
for a little while, I mean, they know a lot of these things, whatever, and so they must
be at this level, and then we find out, no, they're really not.
But it's not that we would insult them or criticize them, it's that we would seek to
help them to grow in grace and knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.
I think about that truth in Acts 8, the Ethiopian eunuch is standing there, or sitting there
up in the chariot, and he's reading from Isaiah 53, you're familiar with the passage of Scripture.
God takes Philip and brings Philip over to him and says, go up to the chariot.
You know what Philip asks that man?
He says this, he said, understandest thou what thou readest?
And his response is so important for us to understand.
He says this, how can I except some man teach me, guide me?
Wow, what a great truth.
And so you know what Philip did?
He got up in the chariot and he preached Jesus.
Because you know what the Ethiopian eunuch, he said, man, is this guy talking about himself,
the prophet Isaiah, or is he talking about some other man?
He's reading Isaiah 53, he's talking about Jesus.
And so what does the Ethiopian eunuch need to understand?
He needs to understand Jesus.
So Philip gets in and he preaches Jesus, and then he sees water and says, can I get baptized?
If you believe, thou mayest.
What do you do?
He said, I believe that Jesus is the Christ.
Stop the chariot, baptize them.
It's awesome.
But never forget that he said, how can I except some man should teach me?
There's some people that we interact with that they just need somebody to teach them.
First what this book is, then what this book says.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for your Word.
We pray, God, that you would help us to be students of the Word.
I pray that you'd help us to grow in grace and knowledge of our Lord and Savior, Jesus
Christ.
I pray, God, that you would help us as we interact with those in our culture, so many
that have adopted this worldview and philosophy that is counter-biblical, this idea of relativism
that is so prevalent.
And God, I pray that you would help us to stand upon the truth of thy Word.
I pray that you'd help us to have the right position and also the right disposition, help
us to understand that people need Jesus, they need to be saved, and help us to understand
the importance of growth, spiritual growth and development.
I pray, Lord, that you would help us ourselves to be students of the Word.
Help us, Lord, to be used for your honor and for your glory.
And I pray that you'd bless as we have this time of invitation, we ask that decisions
would be made that would please thee, and we'll thank you for it, in Christ's name we
pray.