and certainly appreciate it and trust it's been a blessing to you. In our last
message we entered into the third chapter of the book of Colossians and
as we did we mentioned that the book would turn and be a little more
practical in nature if you will and so thankful that God's Word is practical
amen it's to be applied in our lives were to be doers of the word and not
hearers only. We find that as we entered into this third chapter of the book of
Colossians that we were immediately faced with these three verses that
encourage us to be mindful of our position in Christ and I'm so thankful
for the salvation of these believers in Colossi that Paul is writing to and I'm
thankful this morning to know that heaven is my home and that I have been
adopted in the family of God that I understood that I was a sinner in need
of a Savior and that Jesus Christ is the only Savior he said there is he
said I am the way the truth and the life no man cometh unto the Father but by me
I'm thankful that I can understand as the Word of God teaches us that we are
secure in Christ our position is so vital and we understand that the
believers in Colossi were encouraged to be mindful of their position and then
they were encouraged to be mindful of their pursuits and when I understand my
position it has an impact and influence on what I pursue we find that in our
lives today in our world in our society that people are pursuing all sorts of
things and we find that as the people of God we are to be pursuing Christ and
we're to be pursuing godliness we're to hunger and thirst after righteousness
and what a blessing to be mindful of these two wonderful truths that we find
here in Colossians 3 verses 1 through 3 we understand that this epistle was
initially delivered to the believers in Colossi approximately nineteen hundred
and sixty years ago that's a long time ago and it was delivered to these
believers nineteen hundred and sixty years ago but the truths that are
contained therein are still applicable and relevant for us today in fact I
bring up specifically the time frame of the writing of the book of Colossians
because as we approach a verse number four which will be our text for this
morning we find that this truth that was being referenced the event that was
being referenced and given to these believers in Colossi has not yet taken
place though we have full confidence that it will take place we find that as
we look at the Word of God and we study the Bible we would come away with the
understanding that the Bible is a gift from God I'm so thankful for the Bible
I'm thankful that God has given us His Word and as I consider the Word of God
and there are many things that we could say this morning about the Word of God
but we'd understand that God's Word is precious it's precious it's more
valuable than gold or silver or rubies or precious stones is more valuable than
any of those things for the Word of God is eternal and it's a precious book and
we ought to view it and understand it as being precious we understand that
this book that we hold not only is it precious but it's powerful it's powerful
listen the Word of God had the power to change your life and to change my life
and I'm thankful that God says that His Word is alive it's quick and it's
powerful and it's sharper than a two-edged sword I'm thankful for the
power of the Word of God and when we understand the the power of God's Word
it helps us understand why the admonition throughout the New Testament
is to preach the Word why because the Word of God is powerful we find that
this book that we hold in our hands it's preserved I'm thankful that God Almighty
who is eternal that He has given the promise to preserve His Word His Word is
forever settled in heaven and He said that He's given us His Word and that
He'll preserve it from this generation forever and I'm so thankful that we have
a preserved Word of God that we can have the confidence when we go to the
Word of God to know that this indeed is the Word of God it's profitable it's
profitable hasn't God's Word helped you in your life the Bible says that of
itself that it's a lamp unto our feet that it guides us and it leads us we
understand that Paul as he's writing to Timothy he says that all Scripture is
given by inspiration of God and he says that it's profitable and he lists
several things that it's profitable for and we understand this morning that God's
Word is profitable but I also understand this morning that God's Word is
prophetical the prophecy of God's Word we find that as you study the the whole
of God's Word and we understand that as we look at the truth of God's Word that
God is eternal is no beginning and no end he created time he's outside of time
and yet he has provided us a book that records for us all of the history of
mankind that he wants us to have and as we look at this verse of Scripture in
Colossians 3 and verse number 4 and we will unwrap the eschatological truth of
this verse but there's a parenthetical statement that deserves our attention
notice with me in Colossians 3 and verse number 4 the Bible says this when Christ
who is our life shall appear then shall ye also appear with him in glory if you
have your bulletin today you've already seen that the title for the message is
when Christ shall appear we know that he came the first time and we're awaiting
his second return we find that as we look at the Word of God and we
understand the truth that is contained herein that I mentioned that there's
this parenthetical statement that deserves our attention if you're taking
notes I would simply point out this morning number one there is a distinct
perspective there's a distinct perspective the Apostle Paul is he's
writing to the believers in Colossae not only would he impart truth to these
believers but we find that just as the cases with many of the epistles that
Paul was used as the human penman to author that he would also share with the
believers that he would write to his own perspective and he would share many
things about his own life we find that this man Paul he was converted on the
road to Damascus and God changed his life and God called him and God placed a
specific calling upon the life of Paul and we find as we read throughout the
Word of God that you would find that God gives us the record of many of the
accomplishments if you will of the Apostle Paul and how God used Paul for
his honor and for his glory and what a blessing to read about and study the
life of Paul then you understand that Paul himself had the perspective that he
was the chief of sinners you understand that Paul understood that that in his
flesh dwelleth no good thing the Apostle Paul understood that he was what he was
by the grace of God but as he shares his perspective and I believe it's a
distinct perspective here in our text of Scripture this parenthetical statement
notice what he says in verse number four when Christ notice the phrase who is our
life Wow I mean that's a simple yet impactful statement in fact I believe
this morning that if you're not careful as you read the Word of God that you
could quickly pass over such a statement no doubt when we read the Bible there
are times in which we'll have various things going on and distractions would
persist and we would find that perhaps we miss something here and there or
maybe we have the busyness of our day in our schedule when we read a little too
quickly if you will and we can miss simple statements in the Word of God but
how impactful this statement is when Christ who is our life I believe that
this statement here in verse number four ought to stop each and every one of us
in our tracks and cause us to evaluate can I say as Paul said that Christ is my
life can you say as Paul said could the believers in Colossae say as Paul said
he Christ is our life the reality is that he is the one who gives life it is
only by God's grace that you're living at this very moment but we also
understand that is only through God that he gives eternal life the Bible says in
Romans chapter number six that the gift of God is eternal life aren't you
thankful for the gift of God it's through Jesus Christ our Lord because he
went to that cross of Calvary we sang about the cross this morning and how he
went to that old rugged cross and he bled and he died to pay for the sin of
mankind to pay for your sin and my sin the reality is that we're all sinners
and sin requires a payment and as I shared with someone just recently
there's only one payment that's acceptable for the sin of mankind and
that is the precious blood of the Lord Jesus Christ you can't work your way to
heaven you can't give enough to get to heaven there's nothing you can do in of
yourself to get to heaven it's all in what Jesus did on the cross of Calvary
and he has given us eternal life the reality is that in John chapter number
10 in verse number 10 the Bible says that he came as the Good Shepherd and he
gives life and he gives life to the world
He gives it more abundantly.
What a blessing and what a joy
to have the abundant life.
Some of you remember what life was like
before salvation.
You remember what life was like
and the reality is that life now
as a child of God is so much better,
is so much different than what we had
prior to being a Christian.
No longer am I living just for the here and now.
I get to enjoy the blessings of God here and now,
but the reality is that I'm heaven bound
and I have this life that He's given me.
And when I understand that He's given life,
when I understand all of the blessings
that He's bestowed upon us,
and we find that Paul makes this statement
when Christ, who is our life.
I wonder this morning,
can we make in honesty before the Lord,
can we make that statement?
The reality is that I believe that even still today,
people continue to use this expression
that is used here in this verse of Scripture.
My life is baseball.
Baseball is their life,
or this thing is their life,
or maybe a parent says of a child,
they're my life,
or a spouse says of their spouse,
they're my life.
We understand the statement.
People use it still to this day.
What does this statement mean?
What is it that we would understand
when someone would say of their child
that's so enthralled with a particular aspect
of maybe it's a sport
or maybe it's some type of activity,
and the parent would say,
as they would observe their child,
and maybe there's an onlooker,
and they would say,
well, you know, that's just their life.
What do they mean by that?
What does that Paul means by this statement?
I believe that we would understand it
to be used to designate someone
or something that would have preeminence in our lives.
And can I submit to you this morning
that there's only one person
that should have the preeminence in your life
and in my life,
and that is the Lord Jesus Christ.
When Paul says when Christ,
who is our life,
it's the Lord Jesus Christ
that deserves that place of preeminence
in your life and in my life.
And we find that Paul understood that
because of his conversion.
You understand that Christ was not his life
in the same sense that we would look at this statement
prior to his conversion,
just as Christ was not your life
prior to your conversion.
If you can look back before you were saved
and you could think of maybe some pursuits
and some things that you were seeking after,
and someone would say of you,
this is their life,
this is their pursuit,
this is what is preeminent in their lives.
In fact, there are times in which
you can speak to people and you know
that if you get on a certain subject or topic
that you've found the thing that is their life.
Because they just can't stop talking about it.
I wonder,
is Christ our life?
That we get talking about the Lord
and we just kind of can't stop talking about Him.
Because of how good He is
and all that He's done for us.
Remember what Paul said in 2 Corinthians 5
and verse 15 holds your place here
in the book of Colossians, if you will.
And I want you to notice what Paul says
here in this passage of Scripture.
Paul understood what the Lord did for him
and he says this in 2 Corinthians 5,
and that He died for all.
It's a universal truth that the Lord Jesus Christ
died for the sin of mankind.
For all.
It says this, that they which live
should not henceforth live unto themselves,
but unto Him which died for them
and rose again.
What a great truth.
When Christ, who is our life,
notice in Colossians 1 and verse 18,
and we studied this several months ago
as we studied through the first chapter
of the book of Colossians,
when Paul gives this great section
with regard to the Person of Jesus Christ
and what magnitude we find in this text
and how beautiful it is,
but we find in verse 18 that he says this
of the Lord Jesus Christ,
that He is the head of the body of the church,
who is the beginning, the firstborn from the dead,
that in how many things?
All things.
He might have the preeminence.
Listen, I don't expect Christ to have
the preeminence in the life of an unbeliever.
Do you?
No, they're lost.
In the life of a child of God?
Someone that's been born again?
Remember, Paul's writing to the saints
and faithful brethren in Christ
which are at Colossae according to v. 2
of chapter 1,
and as I understand my position in Christ
and I understand what He's done for me,
and I understand that in all things,
not in some things, not in most things,
but in all things,
He must have the preeminence.
And Paul says when Christ,
who is our life,
that's a simple yet impactful statement.
I'm going to read to you the words of a song.
Mr. Thompson, Mr. Will Thompson
penned the words to this song.
It's number 100 in our song book.
The title of the song is
Jesus is all the world to me.
Listen to what Mr. Thompson said.
My life, my joy, my all.
He is my strength from day to day.
Without Him, I would fall.
When I am sad, to Him I go.
No other one can cheer me so.
When I am sad, He makes me glad.
He is my friend.
Jesus is all the world to me.
My friend in trials sore.
I go to Him for blessings
and He gives them o'er and o'er.
He sends the sunshine and the rain.
He sends the harvest, golden grain.
Sunshine and rain, harvest of grain.
He is my friend.
Jesus is all the world to me
and true to Him I'll be.
Oh, how could I this friend deny
when He's so true to me.
Following Him, I know I'm right.
He watches o'er me day and night.
Following Him by day and night,
He's my friend.
The final verse of this wonderful hymn,
Jesus is all the world to me.
I want no better friend.
I trust Him now.
I'll trust Him when life's fleeting days shall end.
Beautiful life with such a friend.
Beautiful life that has no end.
Eternal life, eternal joy.
He's my friend.
Mr. Thompson started this hymn by saying,
Jesus is all the world to me.
My life, my joy, my all.
This man was saved by the blood of Christ.
And he understood that Christ,
who is my life,
He's my all in all.
He's everything to me.
Without Him, as the songwriter said,
I will fail.
I will fall.
Remember, it was the Lord Jesus Christ
in John 10, I referenced a moment ago
when He said that I give them life
that they might have it more abundantly,
that He says just a few verses after that,
that without Me, ye can do nothing.
I'm so thankful this morning
for this distinct perspective
that is shared with us
in Colossians 3 and verse 4.
It's a parenthetical statement,
but oh, how impactful it is.
This morning, can we, as Paul said,
and as he sought to encourage
these believers in Colossae,
can we say that Christ is our life?
Notice as we continue to go
through this fourth verse of Colossians 3,
not only is there a distinct perspective,
but there is a declared promise.
I'm thankful for the promises of God's Word.
In fact, we sing about standing on the promises.
It's Peter that says that He's given us
exceeding great and precious promises.
I'm so thankful for the promises of God's Word.
I mentioned to you earlier
by way of introduction
that this book of Colossians
was written nearly 1,960 years ago,
and yet the promise that was given
to these believers in Colossae
that many years ago
still stands true to this very day.
The event has not yet taken place,
but we have full confidence
that in what God has said He will do,
that He indeed will do.
He will bring it to pass.
Remember that Jesus said
to His troubled disciples
when they were nearing the time
of Christ going to Calvary
and Jesus had given them much instruction
with regard to those events
that would unfold in the days ahead.
He says to them in John 14,
let not your heart be troubled.
You believe in God, believe also in Me.
In My Father's house are many mansions.
If it were not so, I would have told you.
I go to prepare a place for you.
And then He makes this statement
in v. 3,
and if I go and prepare a place for you,
I will come again and receive you unto Myself
that where I am, there ye may be also.
There were scoffers during the first century.
Peter deals with them.
There are scoffers that continue today
that say where is the promise of His return?
But as Peter would say to those scoffers
as he would respond to their attacks,
he would say this,
the Lord is not slack concerning His promise,
but is longsuffering to us, Lord,
not willing that any should perish,
but that all should come to repentance.
I'm thankful that we serve a...
who cannot lie. I'm thankful this morning that we serve a God who is not slack
concerning his promise, aren't you? I mean he's never failed and he's not planning
to. We serve the God of the universe and as we look at this declared promise, we
find that the Apostle Paul says this, when Christ, who is our life, shall appear.
I like that word shall. It's certain. He doesn't say when Christ might appear or
we think he is going to, he could appear. No, no, he shall appear. He's coming. He
says this, then shall ye also appear with him in glory. You know the study of
eschatology is fascinating. The study of end times. We find that our God, as I
mentioned earlier, he is eternal so he is able to provide us with a timeline that
stretches from creation to eternity. In fact, as you study the Word of God, he
gives us insight even to events prior to creation for the Bible tells us that
Jesus was the Lamb of God slain before the foundation of the world. And we find
that our God is outside of time. It's sometimes hard for us to understand
because we are contained within time and everything is time, time, time,
time. We're just so controlled by time. But God is outside of time and he's
given us this great truth here and we find that as we study eschatology that
we have the opportunity to study the prophecy that God's given as we begin to
think about specifically eschatology with dealing with the prophecy of end
times or future events that we'd find that the Word of God gives us much
truth. Here, as we examine this verse of Scripture, I believe that you would
conclude that the event of prophecy that's being addressed here is the
second coming of Christ and not the rapture of the church. We understand that
oftentimes we speak about the second coming of Christ and we can use the word
kind of interchangeably or the phrase interchangeably to talk about two
distinct events on the prophetic calendar. We find that there is a
prophecy, an event on the prophetical calendar of the rapture of the church.
But then we also find that there's an event on the prophetical calendar in
God's Word that deals with his second coming, the second advent, if you will. We
understand that he came the first time just as he said. When the fullness of
time was come, God sent forth his Son and he's gonna come the second time right
on time. He's not gonna be a moment late. He's coming just as he is supposed to
and we find that this event that's mentioned here in Colossians 3 and verse
number 4 really is dealing with the truth of Revelation 19 and not with
1st Thessalonians 4. Now I hope over the next few moments that I can unpack and
help understand something in about 20 minutes that could take hours of
discussion. So I hope that someone told me I talk fast. I try to slow it down a
little bit, but sometimes I got to talk fast because we got a lot to cover. And
so I'll talk fast if you listen fast. I'm just I'm not gonna go any faster than I
was. But listen, when we look at Colossians 3 and verse number 4, notice
the word when the Bible says this, when Christ shall, notice this word appear. When
Christ shall appear. The Bible is very specific. Every word of God is given to
us and we're thankful for every word of God. They're pure words. And here Paul
says when Christ shall appear. The word appear means to make actual and visible.
It means this, to become manifest. Now it also says this, that when Christ who is
our life shall appear, notice, then shall ye also appear with Christ in God. Now
specifically who is Paul speaking to? The ye are the believers in Colossae. We find
that by extension when we understand the prophecy and the promise that is given
here, that ye also includes me. It includes you, the believers, the people
that have been saved by the blood of the Lamb. If you're here this morning and you
have a 100% confidence that heaven is your home, not because of anything that
you've done, but because of what Jesus Christ did on the cross of Calvary, then
ye means you. Because when Christ shall appear, it says this, then shall ye also
appear with him in glory. Yes, specifically he's speaking to believers
in Colossae, but they're saved the same way we're saved. And when we become part
of the Bride of Christ, we can join in on the promise that is given. Now
understand with me that as we look at this word appear and understand
that it says that we also shall appear with him in glory, we could ask this
question, when does this happen? When is it that this happens? You'd understand
that this is not speaking of the rapture, for that event happened
suddenly, and believers are caught up to meet the Lord in the air. In fact, as we
look at the truth of the rapture of the church, the Apostle Paul, as he's
speaking to the believers in Corinth in 1 Corinthians 15 and verse number 52,
describes that event of the rapture of the church in this manner, in a moment, in
the twinkling of an eye. In a moment, in the twinkling of an eye. And we find that
he's discussing in 1 Corinthians 15 the rapture of the church when we are going
to be caught up and to meet the Lord in the air. 1 Thessalonians chapter 4
deals with it in great detail. We find that as we look at that truth in
1 Thessalonians 4 and verse number 13 through 18, and he gives the truth with
regard to the rapture of the church, Paul then describes it this way in
chapter 5 and verse number 2, that the day of the Lord shall come as a thief in
the night. And so we find here that as we would understand the truth of the
rapture, and we'd understand the terminology that is given that in a
moment, in the twinkling of an eye, as a thief in the night, that that's the
rapture. Listen, it's going to happen so quickly. As Brother Sommerdorf mentioned
last Sunday morning as he spoke about the rapture of the church, no one's
going to be able to say, oh man, he's coming and let's do this, that, or the
other thing. No, it's gonna happen just like that. Actually faster than that. And
we're gonna be gone. What a joy. Looking for the upper taker, not the undertaker.
Amen? That's what Brother Mershon always says. And the reality is that we
understand that Jesus is coming again, but oftentimes we speak out on coming
again, we're focused upon the rapture of the church. And that's okay, that's the
next event on the prophetic calendar. Jesus is coming again. We're gonna be
raptured out of here. But he's not going to make himself manifest, he's not gonna
make himself actual or visible in that particular coming, because he's gonna go
in the air. We're gonna meet him in the air, it's just gonna be like that, just
that quickly, and we're gonna meet him in the air. And so here is Paul speaks to
the believers in Colossians, he says, when Christ, who is our life, shall appear,
then shall ye also appear with him in glory. So again, when does this event
happen? We find that at the second coming of Christ, when he comes and comes all
the way to earth, that what happens, the Bible reveals to us in Revelation 19,
we'll look at it in just a moment, that we come with him. We come with him. Not
only do we come with him, but the host of the heavenly angels come. I mean, it's
gonna be a serious situation. Amen? Listen, he came the first time as a babe, and he
came the first time to die for the sins of mankind. But when he comes again, he's
coming to rule and to reign. The Lord God omnipotent reigneth. And he's not coming
as a babe in the manger, he's coming as the conquering King of kings and
Lord of lords. And we find that as we look at Revelation 19, that as that event
is given to us in detail, that not only will we return with him, but then
the battle of Armageddon ensues, and then we find that the millennial, the literal
millennial reign of Christ begins. He will rule and reign for a thousand years
upon the earth. And by the way, we'll rule with him. Isn't that awesome? Look at
Revelation 19 with me, if you will. Now remember, this is the context in which
Paul is sharing with these believers with regard to the when Christ shall
appear. Then shall ye also appear with him in glory. And find in Revelation 19,
beginning in verse number 11. Revelation 19, beginning in verse number 11, the
Bible says, and I saw heaven opened. Behold, a white horse and he that sat
upon him was called Faithful and True. Oh, we could speak for a long time just upon
those two names that are ascribed to our Savior. He's faithful. Aren't you thankful
for the faithfulness of God? He's dependable. He's trustworthy. Listen,
remember this promise that's given to the church in Colossae 1960 years ago.
Why is it that we still have confidence and certainty in this promise? Because
he's faithful. He's outside of time. We can sit around and say, where is the
promise of his return? I mean, he said he was gonna come. And in that same passage
of Scripture in 2nd Peter 3, the Bible tells us that a day is as a thousand
years as a day. To God, why? Because he's outside of time. Notice, he's faithful.
he's faithful, he's true, and in righteousness he doth judge and make war.
His eyes were as a flame of fire, and on his head were many crowns, and he had a name written
that no man knew but he himself, and he was clothed with a vesture dipped in blood, and
his name is called the Word of God."
Remember the truth of John 1, in the beginning was the Word, the Word was with God, the Word
was God.
The Word was made flesh and dwelt among us in verse number 14, and here his name is the
Word of God.
Notice verse 14, and the armies which were in heaven followed him upon white horses,
clothed in fine linen, white and clean.
Aren't you thankful for that?
Listen, it's not those filthy rags, it's not my own righteousness, I'm clothed in the righteousness
of God Almighty.
Because the Bible tells us that he hath made him to be sin for us who knew no sin, that
we might be made the righteousness of God in him.
Verse 15, and out of his mouth goeth a sharp sword, and with it he should smite the nations,
and he shall rule them with a rod of iron, and he treadeth the winepress of the fierceness
and wrath of Almighty God, and he hath on his vesture and on his thigh a name written
King of Kings and Lord of Lords.
Wow.
And he shall appear, then shall ye also appear with him in glory.
These two events that we often refer to and sometimes use interchangeably with regard
to the return of Christ or the second coming of Christ, when we begin to understand the
truth of prophecy and we'd study eschatology and the Word of God, and we begin to understand
that these two events are separated by seven years.
We understand Daniel's prophecy in Daniel chapter number nine.
I don't have time to unfold all of this, but I hope to whet your appetite enough that you'd
go back and read and study, and I could give you the truth in a summary format this morning
that will help us to understand what God desires for us to understand.
I know there's some people that say, I want to know when he's coming.
You're not going to know.
You can study the Bible and come up with all the numerology you want to come up with and
come up with it.
God says, no man knoweth the hour.
Jesus said, in fact, to his disciples before he ascended to heaven, when they asked him
in Acts chapter number one, now at this time restore again the kingdom to Israel, and he
said it is not for you to know the times or the seasons which the Father hath put in his
own power, but ye shall receive power after the Holy Ghost has come upon you, and ye shall
be witnesses unto me both in Jerusalem and in all Judea and in Samaria and unto the uttermost
part of the earth.
What are we saying?
You have a job, and your job is not to worry about the date on the calendar that I'm coming
back.
You just know that I am coming back, and here's your job, here's your duty, your responsibility
until I should return.
And so we begin to study prophecy and we begin to understand what's taking place.
We look at these two events prophetically, the return of Christ, looking at the rapture
of the church and his second advent, his second coming, we find that there's a separation
of seven years.
I believe this morning that in order for us to properly understand prophecy, it is absolutely
essential that we properly understand Israel and the church.
There is a grave mistake in which people do not properly understand the distinction between
Israel and the church.
I read with me clearly this morning that the church is not Israel.
We're not Israel.
We're not spiritual Israel.
Israel is Israel.
And by the way, if you read in Romans chapter number 11, and we don't have time to develop
all of that either, but if you read in Romans chapter number 11, he's talking about Israel
in verse number 25.
He says, for I would not, brethren, that ye shall be ignorant of this mystery, lest ye
should be wise in your own conceits.
Notice what he says, that blindness in part is happened to Israel until the fullness of
the Gentiles become in.
He just talked to them about the way in which the Gentiles were graft in and all that was
taking place.
Why?
Because Israel rejected Messiah.
And that wasn't a surprise to God, by the way.
He knows everything.
And Israel rejected Christ as being Messiah, and therefore the Gentiles were graft in.
The mystery of the church is that the church is distinct from Israel, and it's made up
of Jew and Gentile together that are saved by the blood of Jesus Christ.
We're a completely separate entity.
Notice also in Romans chapter number 11, in verse number 29, the Bible says, for the gifts
and calling of God are without repentance.
You know what he's speaking about?
He's speaking about all of those promises that he gave to Israel in the Old Testament.
The promises to Abraham and to the Jewish people and saying of those promises that the
gifts and calling of God are without repentance.
In other words, just because they turned on God doesn't mean that God's not going to fulfill
what he's promised them.
Do you remember the Abrahamic covenant?
Abraham was sound asleep when God passed through, signifying that the Lord passed through
twice and signifying that these promises were not conditional.
They were not dependent upon Israel or Abraham, certainly responding in a certain way, but
they were dependent upon God.
We understand in the Word of God that there are some conditional promises.
Oftentimes conditional promises in the Word of God look like this.
If then, if my people, which are called by my name, shall humble themselves and pray
and seek my face and turn from their wicked ways, then will I hear from heaven and heal
their land.
That's what the second Chronicle 7 in verse number 14.
Proverbs chapter number 2, you look through the passage of Scripture, there's a whole
host in just the first 10 verses of if then promises.
We find that there are if then promises, but then there are unconditional promises.
God says here of Israel that the gifts and calling of God are without repentance, and
so Israel is distinct from the church.
When we understand that truth, it helps us to understand prophecy.
When we blur that truth and we try to make the church spiritual Israel and we try to
do all of these things and spiritualize the text, then we get all kinds of sideways and
messed up on understanding the truth that God has given us in his Word.
I often have referred to it in this manner, and I don't do a lot of cooking and baking
and that sort of thing, but I often refer to it in this manner.
If we could use an illustration this morning of one that would be cooking, and perhaps
you're making a dish and you're preparing this elaborate meal, and there's a particular
sauce that needs to go with that dish, and you have to do some things in the beginning,
but then that sauce is not necessary until the very end of the cooking process.
And what you do with that sauce is maybe if we could use this terminology, you put
it on the back burner.
It's still maybe simmering a little bit, you've got it on super low heat, it's still kind
of simmering, but it's not forgotten about, it's not discarded, but it's not in focus
right now because there are other things to tend to.
And you're preparing that meal and you're dealing with that meal and you're putting
all of the other ingredients together, and then you come to the end and you've got to
take that sauce and bring it back to the front again.
If I could use that analogy in explaining to you this way, that in a similar manner,
God, because Israel rejected Messiah, He put them on the back burner.
It's not that Jews can't be saved today.
Jewish people can still be saved today.
Paul, in fact, says, my prayer in God to Israel is that they might be saved in Romans 10 and
verse number 1.
There are Jewish people that can be saved, but they have to be saved the same way that
you and I are saved.
They can't just say, well, I'm Jewish and so therefore I'm okay.
Doesn't work that way.
So for a season, the church age, a period of time that's not defined in years, God has
put Israel on the back burner and He's dealing with the church.
The church, the bride of Christ.
And as He deals with the church, we find the church age, we find the epistles and all
that's given to us as the church, all of our responsibilities as the bride of Christ.
But then at some point, the bride of Christ is gone and Israel comes back on the burner.
And so what happens when we understand, again, the truth and the distinction between Israel
and the church, it also assists us, it's important that we would understand why.
What is the purpose of the tribulation?
The purpose of the tribulation is to deal with Israel again.
In fact, Jeremiah says it this way in Jeremiah 30 and verse number 7, he says that it's the
time of Jacob's trouble.
The time of Jacob's trouble.
So the church is raptured.
In fact, if you read the book of Revelation, you read throughout just the chapters of the
book of Revelation, you look at chapters 2 and 3, he's dealing with the seven churches
in Asia.
And then guess what?
In chapter number 4, John's caught up, right?
The Bible tells us in Revelation 4 and verse number 1, after this
I looked and behold a door was open in heaven and the first voice which I heard
was as it were of a trumpet talking with me which said come up hither and I will
show thee things which must be hereafter." I believe that's the rapture right there.
The rapture of the church. The church age, chapters 2 and 3, all of the
churches are being addressed. Those seven literal churches that existed that also
represent the church age as a whole. We find that then John, he hears
that voice as a trumpet talking. Notice what it says, that a door was opened in
heaven. Come up hither. And so we understand the purpose of the
tribulation and we understand that God now once again is going to deal
specifically with Israel. It's the time, it's a time of Jacob's trouble and as he
deals with Israel specifically during those seven years of tribulation there's
going to be, as you continue to read through the book of Revelation, you see
the sealed judgments and you see the the trumpet judgments and you see the
vile judgments and all these judgments that take place and it is a time in
which God's wrath is poured out upon mankind. And he's helping Israel to
understand that he indeed is the Messiah. And so what's the focus, what's the
purpose of the tribulation? It's Israel. It's Israel. And so as we begin to
understand Colossians 3 and kind of come full circle to what Paul is saying
to these believers, he says, when Christ who is our life shall appear, then shall
ye also appear with him in glory. So we find that here in this verse of
Scripture that he would be speaking about the second coming of Christ, the
second advent, that event that's dealt with in Revelation 19. Remember in
Revelation 4 he said that he saw the door in heaven open and in Revelation
19 and 11 it says and I saw heaven opened. Heaven opened so that the church
could ascend and then heaven opened because they're coming back. Amen?
Revelation 4 and 1 and Revelation 19 and 11. And in between those two events is the
tribulation. The tribulation. We find that as we look at the Word of God and he says
that he shall appear and then we and ye shall, excuse me, then shall ye also
appear with him in glory. The fact of the matter is that, listen, when you look at
the timeline and the distinction it wouldn't make a whole lot of sense. Some
people teach that there's a pre-tribulation rapture, some a mid-trib
and a post-trib, and you look at those various schools of thought and many
times you'll find that there's a misunderstanding of Israel in the church.
I'm not trying to be unkind or mean but I'm just simply saying that that's
really what the root problem is and you find that it'd be kind of interesting
those that would teach a post-trib, how are we going to appear with him if we're
it just it doesn't line up and so when you look at all of the scripture and you
interpret all of the scripture the way in which it's to be interpreted, what God
said, not trying to spiritualize anything, not trying to change anything, but here's
what God has said. And when we look at this promise, I want you to just consider
in closing this morning, the motivation of this promise. It's not really a point,
I only had two points this morning, but I want you to think about these believers
in Colossae and I want you to think about you this morning and as I think
about my own life, we say when Christ who is our life shall appear, then shall ye
also appear with him in glory. You think about the comfort of this truth, you
think about the motivation of this truth. Listen, I'm not just living life for
whatever we can gain here. We have this sure promise that gives us confidence,
that gives us certainty, that this life is not all that there is. Listen, there
are people today that live and they walk upon this earth and they think, oh man
this is all there is to life, just live life to the fullest and whatever. I mean
the one who has the most toys wins and all that sort of thing, but the reality
is that, listen, my focus is way beyond that. Way beyond that. Because I'm
gonna come back with Christ. And if you're saved this morning, you're gonna
come back with Christ and you're going to rule with him. Isn't that amazing? Wow. If
you're not saved this morning, you say preacher, I have no idea what you're
talking about. I've never been saved, I've never trusted the Lord Jesus Christ
as my Savior. If I were to die today, I have no idea what would happen. Could I
encourage you this morning to trust Christ? Paul said it this way, today is
the day of salvation. Listen, no man knoweth what a day would bring forth.
Boast not thyself of tomorrow is what Proverbs says. We find this morning that
if you're not saved, that event, the rapture, is gonna take place and you'll
be left behind. If you've heard the gospel, if you're here this morning, you're
watching live stream, you've heard the gospel. God says that you'll believe a
lie. You'll believe a lie. The Bible tells us that after that Millennial reign of
Christ, there's this event called the Great White Throne Judgment. The Bible
tells us that the dead, small and great, are gonna stand before God. They're gonna
be judged. The Bible says that if you've not been born again, that you'll be cast
in a lake of fire. This is the second death. Prior to that truth in Revelation
20, for those that would be ruling and reigning with Christ during his
Millennial Kingdom, the Bible says that the second death has no power on us
because we've been born again. Could I encourage you this morning to let
someone take a Bible and show you how you could know for sure that heaven's
your home? Oh, I would beg of you not to leave here without knowing for
sure that heaven is your home. 24 years ago, I guess it was, when I understood
that I was a sinner in need of a Savior and that Jesus Christ was the only
Savior. I understood that he died for me and he paid for me what I could not pay on my
own. And I placed my faith and trust in the finished work of Christ at Calvary
and he gave me life. He gave me abundant life. He gave me eternal life. And my
desire, even as Paul says, my desire is that he, Christ, would be my life. I'll be
honest with you this morning, I don't know that I can stand here with as much
assurance as Paul did and say he is my life. But I want him to be. I want him to
have preeminence in my life. And I hope that you do as well. And then as we
consider this promise. Listen, he's going to appear. Don't get bogged down with
what's going on in our world. Just know that we're on the winning side.
Curtis Hudson used to sing the song all the time. We're on the winning side. I've
read the back of the book and we win. Amen. We're on the winning side. This
distinct perspective and then we find this this promise when Christ shall
appear. Let's pray. Father we love you. We thank you for loving us. We thank you for
your word and the truth contained therein. We pray God that you would help
us to honor you and glorify you through all that we say and all that we do. I
thank you God for your word and for the truth contained therein. If there's one
that's not sure of heaven, oh God would you please help them today to understand
their need for Christ. For those that have been born again, would you help us
God to understand the truth and the teaching of your word with regard to
prophecy, eschatology. Help us Lord to keep our focus on those truths and not
to get discouraged or bogged down in this world. Would you bless our time of
invitation that decisions would be made that would please thee. Well thank you
for what you'll do for it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me
heads are bowed, eyes are closed. I'm gonna have a moment of invitation when we give
you an opportunity to respond to the Word of God. Perhaps this morning you're
not sure of heaven and you'd like to have someone take a Bible and show you
how you can know for sure that heaven's your home. Perhaps this morning you have
some other area of your life in which the Lord has spoken to your heart and
you want to come to this old-fashioned altar and you want to pray and ask God
to help you. As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.