11 is where we will begin this morning, 1 John 4,
beginning in verse number 11.
Notice what the word of God says here
in our text of Scripture,
beginning there in verse number 11.
Of course, last week we looked at verses seven through 10,
and this subject matter of loving one another
is a recurring thought,
not only through the book of 1 John,
but really through the New Testament.
And we find that it begins here in verse number 11
of 1 John 4.
The Bible says,
If God so loved us, we ought also to love one another.
It's pretty simple, isn't it?
I mean, very straightforward
with regard to the simplicity of the argument here
in understanding how we are to behave ourselves.
We are to be like Christ, amen?
And I'm so thankful to be the recipient of his love.
We dealt with that in great extent last week
of what a joy it is to know that God loves us.
Notice in verse 12,
no man hath seen God at any time.
If we love one another, God dwelleth in us,
and his love is perfected in us.
Hereby know we that we dwell in him and he in us,
because he hath given us of his Spirit.
And we have seen and do testify
that the Father sent the Son to be the Savior of the world.
Whosoever shall confess that Jesus is the Son of God,
God dwelleth in him and he in God.
And we have known and believed the love
that God hath to us.
God is love, and he that dwelleth in love
dwelleth in God and God in him.
Herein is our love made perfect
that we may have boldness in the day of judgment,
because as he is, so are we in this world.
There's no fear in love,
but perfect love casteth out fear,
because fear hath torment.
He that feareth not is made perfect in love.
We love him because he first loved us.
If a man say, I love God and hateth his brother,
he is a liar.
For he that loveth not his brother whom he hath seen,
how can he love God whom he hath not seen?
In this commandment have we from him
that he who loveth God love his brother also.
The title of the message this morning
from verse number 11, we ought to love one another.
Obviously, we understand that the New Testament
provides us with valuable instruction
as we consider the thought that is before us again
this morning of loving one another
and this truth that we are to love one another.
The reality is that there are times
in which we know what we ought to do,
but we don't do it.
Isn't that true?
There's a lot of things that we know that we should do
that it would be right for us to do,
but sometimes we struggle with actually doing
that particular thing.
And so we find that as we look at the New Testament,
I am thankful for the instruction that God has given us
with regard to the subject matter that is before us,
and I'm also thankful this morning for the examples
that God has given us in the scriptures
with regard to those that have taken the instruction
and applied it in their lives,
that they were doers of the word and not hearers only.
We often mention and I often pray
as we open up our services,
I pray as I read my Bible daily,
I pray, God, would you open down mine eyes
that I may behold wondrous things out of thy law.
I also pray, speak, Lord, for thy servant heareth,
and I pray this, Lord, help me to be a doer of the word
and not a hearer only.
We find that the New Testament provides us with instruction,
but we also have the privilege of seeing those
that have applied such instruction in their lives.
We'll look at a couple of individuals
at the end of the message,
but I want you to consider by way of introduction
this morning, the church in Thessalonica.
The church in Thessalonica, if you were to go back
and look at 1 Thessalonians 4, verses nine and 10,
in those verses of scripture,
the believers in Thessalonica at this local church,
they are commended for their love one for another.
We find that Paul tells them that as he commends them,
he is understanding, as he's evaluated,
and he's heard of their love that they have one for another,
but after commending them, he then challenges them
with this thought in verse number 10,
that ye increase more and more.
In other words, don't be content or satisfied where you are
with regard to the subject of loving one another,
of this subject of brotherly love,
but increase more and more.
It's exciting, as you would read
the book of 2 Thessalonians,
and you would go in the first chapter,
the introductory of that particular book,
you find that in verse number three,
that as Paul is writing back to this church,
he commended them and then challenged them
with regard for their love one for another.
He then says this in 2 Thessalonians one,
in verse number three, he says,
their charity, love, of every one of you all
toward each other, listen to this word, aboundeth.
It aboundeth.
If you look up that word aboundeth,
it means to super abound.
I like that word.
And you think about this love that they had one for another.
Paul says, listen, I'm gonna commend you
as he's writing that first letter to them
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God.
He says, I commend you because you're loving one another,
but I wanna challenge you that you increase more and more.
And then as he writes again,
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
that second letter, he says, listen, I'm rejoicing.
I'm thankful because your love, your charity,
one for another, it aboundeth.
Wow, that's exciting.
That's a group of believers that received instruction
and applied instruction.
They lived, they were doers of the word
and not hearers only.
As we look here in the book of 1 John
and we begin to, again, address the subject matter
that is before us of loving one another
and understanding that we ought also to love one another
as we're told in verse number 11,
I want you to consider just a couple of thoughts
this morning.
Number one, if you're taking notes,
why should we love one another?
Number one, because of his love toward us.
Because of his love toward us.
I will not preach the entirety of the message
that I preached last week
because I spent a significant amount of time
dealing with the subject matter last week
that we are the recipients of the love of God
and I'm so thankful that I can rejoice on a daily basis
that God loves me.
I tell him every day, God, I love you
and I thank you for loving me
because I understand that I love him
as it says in verse number 19,
because he first loved me.
And I'm so thankful for the love of God.
And notice in verse number 11,
the Bible says if, the understanding is since,
God, notice what it says, so loved us.
Thankful.
As you think about that little word so,
you think about the significance
and you think about the way in which he is telling us,
we see it in John 3 in verse 16 as well,
for God so loved the world.
And he says here, beloved, if God so loved us,
we ought also to love one another.
Reminder of being a recipient
of the wonderful love of God.
You notice in verse number 16,
that the Bible declares there
that God is loved but prior to that,
notice as he begins in verse 16,
it says and we have known and believed
the love that God hath to us.
It's interesting, he starts,
he mentions it often and in fact,
just very quickly look at the fourth chapter
and just look at the kind of the separations
as I preach these messages in verse number one,
he begins by addressing them as what?
Beloved.
In verse number seven, he addresses them as beloved.
In verse number 11, he addresses them as beloved.
Understanding that we are the recipients
of the love of God.
We love him because he first loved us.
He is the initiator.
And we ought to rejoice in that this evening,
this morning and when we think about this truth
of we ought to love one another, why?
Because I have received God's love.
We're mindful of the truth and we speak about forgiveness
and I'll mention a little more about forgiveness
as we get through the message this morning
because we're going to end with a number
of really applications, practical points
on how we can love one another,
but we're reminded for the basis of us forgiving one another
is the fact that I've been forgiven.
We can read that in Ephesians four in verse number 32.
And so why is it that I'm going to love one another?
Why is it that we understand,
yes, we've been commanded to do so,
but we've been the recipients of the love of God.
Therefore, to love one another.
Notice not only because of his love toward us,
but I want you to think about this
as we dig into the passage of scripture this morning
because of his love through us.
Not only his love toward us, but his love through us.
Hold your place here in 1 John
and go to the book of Romans if you will.
In chapter number five, we're gonna look at a couple
of verses of scripture dealing with this subject
of the love of God through us.
I'm thankful for his love toward us,
but I'm thankful for his love through us.
He mentions in the text of scripture in 1 John
and we'll go back there in just a moment
about the Holy Spirit, the Spirit dwelling within us.
And I'm so thankful for that truth of the word of God.
In Romans chapter number five,
notice it begins in verse number one,
therefore being justified by faith.
By the way, that's the only way to be justified.
He says we have peace with God
through our Lord Jesus Christ.
I am so thankful for having.
peace with God. I'm thankful for the peace of God that passeth all understanding that I have as a
child of God, but what a joy to know that I have peace with God, and the only way to have peace
with God is through the Lord Jesus Christ. You ever hear somebody that says at the end of their
life, I've made my peace with God? You ever hear somebody say that? I've heard people make that
statement before. What do you mean by that? Because biblically speaking, there's only one
way to have peace with God, and that's through the Lord Jesus Christ. Listen, we don't have a
conversation and make a deal with God. We just don't. God's given us the truth, and we must obey
it. Notice in verse number two, by whom also we have access by faith into this grace wherein we
stand and rejoice in hope of the glory of God, and not only so, but we glory in tribulations also.
There's a whole message right there. Knowing that tribulation worketh patience, and patience
experience, and experience hope, and hope maketh not ashamed. Notice what he says, because the love
of God is shed abroad in our hearts, how? By the Holy Ghost which is given unto us. You know that
I can't love people the way I'm supposed to love people apart from God loving through me,
and neither can you. You ever hear somebody say, I love them, but I don't like them?
That's just being fleshly and carnal. I'm being honest.
It's flesh and carnal. You've heard people say that. I have to love them.
If the Holy Ghost is in you, and He is, if you've been saved, the Bible tells us that the Spirit
dwelleth within us. Amen? The indwelling of the Holy Ghost. What a wonderful truth
of the Word of God. And the Bible tells us here in this verse of Scripture in Romans 5,
in verse number 5, that the love of God is shed abroad in our hearts by the Holy Ghost which is
given unto us. On Sunday evening, Galatians chapter number 5, if you will, Galatians chapter
number 5, Steve made mention of this particular verse in Galatians 5, in verse number 22, as the
Bible begins to describe the fruit of the Spirit, it begins with what? Love.
Love, joy, peace, longsuffering, gentleness, goodness, faith, meekness, temperance against
such, there is no law. But we find that as we are walking in the Spirit and not fulfilling the lust
of the flesh, when we are having that fruit of the Spirit, then we have love. You know what's
interesting? It doesn't say the fruits of the Spirit. It's singular. It's something, when you
talk about the fruit of the Spirit, you can't go through the list and pick and choose which ones
you think you have because the fruit of the Spirit is, and this is how it's described, love,
joy, peace, longsuffering, you have all of it. So, if somebody says, well, I have the fruit of
the Spirit, I just don't love people. No, no, no, you don't have the fruit of the Spirit
because it's love, joy, peace, longsuffering. Sometimes we divide those up and we look at them
as being fruits, plural of the Spirit, but the Bible says fruit of the Spirit. This is how it's
described, love, joy, peace, longsuffering, etc. We can use descriptive terms all the time to
describe something or someone, and we use a variety of terms to describe it. Maybe a food,
maybe a house, a car, whatever it might be, an individual. We can use a number of different
terms to describe that person. It doesn't mean that as we're describing that singular item with
maybe a variety of terms that it's multiple items that we're describing. No, it's the same item,
but we're using multiple terms to describe it. We understand that. We do it all the time.
We find here the fruit of the Spirit is love. Notice with me as we go back to the book of 1 John,
it's all of those things that are mentioned, but we find that it begins with saying that
the fruit of the Spirit is love, and I'm so thankful of His love not only toward me,
but His love through me. Notice with me as I begin to think about the love of God through us,
I begin to think about the fact that it is powerful. Notice in verses 12 down through
verse number 16, notice how the Word of God tells us, no man hath seen God at any time.
If we love one another, God dwelleth in us, and His love is perfected in us. And He's going with
this recurring theme about the truth that God dwelleth in us. He says in verse 13,
Hereby know we that we dwell in Him, and He in us, because He hath given us of His Spirit.
Aren't you thankful for that wonderful truth? Listen, that's what makes His love powerful.
It's His love. It's His love through us. Here's somebody say, I just can't love them. You can't,
but God's love through you will enable you to love them. Notice in verse number 14,
He says, And we have seen and do testify that the Father hath sent the Son to be the Savior of the
world. Isn't that wonderful? When you think about the truth of verse number 14, that they were
eyewitnesses and they do testify. We have seen and do testify. Testify of what? That the Father
hath sent the Son to be the Savior of the world. That's our responsibility. We've understood the
truth, and we are to testify. It says this in verse 15, think about the wording here,
Whosoever shall confess that Jesus is the Son of God, God dwelleth in him, and he in God.
You can't buy the Holy Spirit. You accept Jesus Christ as your personal Savior. You acknowledge
that He is God, and then He gives us. It's the earnest of our inheritance. The Holy Spirit is
the earnest of our inheritance, and we receive the Holy Spirit of God, the Holy Ghost, and God
dwelleth in me. Notice what He says in verse 16, And we have known and believed the love that God
hath to us. God is love, and he that dwelleth in love dwelleth in God, and God in him.
We find that when we think about the love of God toward us, we rejoice. Then we think about God's
love through us, that it's powerful. Think about this. Not only is it powerful, but it's impactful.
His love through us is impactful. We can think of it from a couple of different perspectives.
We can think of it from the perspective that we'll deal with in just a moment on others,
but I want you to think about contextually here the impact of God's love in our lives personally.
As His love is operating through us, notice what the Word of God says in verses 17 and 18.
Interesting verses of Scripture. The Bible says, Herein is our love made perfect,
that we may have boldness in the day of judgment. Do you notice that statement?
That we may have boldness in the day of judgment. You know, most people in the day
of judgment do not have boldness. They have fear in the day of judgment. But notice it continues.
It says, Because as He is, so are we in this world. We're to be like Him. We know that one
day, and we'll look at it in just a moment, we will be like Him, but we're to be like Him now.
Listen, we're to be following the pattern, the example that Christ gave us,
and He loved. Remember John 13, He loved until the end.
When Judas comes in to betray Jesus with a kiss, he says, Friend.
Notice verse 18, There is no fear in love, but perfect love casteth out fear,
because fear hath torment. He that feareth is not made perfect in love.
Contextually, as we look at verses 17 and 18, we begin to see how that as we follow the instruction
that God has given us that we're to love one another, the loving one another is God's love
through us. It's not us conjuring up this love in of ourselves. It's not us trying to
work something up. No, it's God living in us, and God flowing through us. And as we're loving like
He loved, as we're like He is, we have confidence. It says in verse number 17, it says that we may
have boldness in the day of judgment, because as He is, so are we in this world. And we can
have that confidence. We can have, we can understand the impact of God's love through us.
It's interesting, as you would look at a contrast between 1 John 4, 17 and 18, and back over to 1
John chapter 2. The Lord just brought this to my mind this morning. I was actually shaving this
morning, and I was thinking about the message that I was going to preach, and God brought this thought
to my mind with regard to this contrast between 1 John 4, 17 and 18, and 1 John 2 in verse 28,
because He says that I was just meditating. These verses of Scripture in verse 17 and 18 are
interesting verses of Scripture, powerful truth of the Word of God, that we would have boldness
in the day of judgment. But notice the contrast back in 1 John 2 in verse 28. It says,
And now, little children, abide in Him, that when He shall appear we may have confidence, notice what
it says, and not be ashamed before Him at His coming. Wow. There are some that will be ashamed
before Christ at His coming. It's just a sad truth of the Word of God and a sad truth of humanity.
There will be some that will be ashamed before Him at His coming. But I'm thankful this morning
that we can have that confidence. Notice what it says, little children, abide in Him. So, what's
the evidence of abiding in Him? Well, when we're looking at 1 John 4 and these verses of Scripture
of loving one another, I'm walking in communion with my Lord. We've been singing all week,
or all year, excuse me, our theme song, I walk and I talk with the King. What a joy,
walking in the light as He is in the light. Remember, as we mentioned all the way back
in the beginning of the year of that theme that we have, and we'd be mindful of considering the
truth that as I walk in the light as He is in the light, that I have fellowship with Him.
But the Word of God says,
we have fellowship one with another.
Yes, we have fellowship with him,
but we also have fellowship one with another.
We're abiding in him as we're living as we ought to live,
he says, because as he is in verse 17 of 1 John 4,
so are we in this world.
Listen, we are to be his representatives.
People are to see the love of Christ through us
as we live here on this earth.
Is it true as you look at the life and ministry
of the Lord Jesus Christ,
as you trace the steps of the Lord
through the gospel accounts,
is it true that you see the love of God?
Absolutely.
You see his love on display.
Again, not only did he declare it, but he displayed it.
And we find that here it says,
because as he is, so are we in this world.
We understand that he then tells us
in 1 John 3, speaking about the return
of the Lord Jesus Christ,
that he says in verse two, beloved,
now are we the sons of God,
and it doth not yet appear what we shall be.
But think about the now versus the shall be.
What are we now?
I understand that we still have the old nature, the flesh,
and there's enmity.
You read Galatians 5.
We looked at verse number 22, the fruit of the spirit.
Verses 16 and 17, walk in the spirit.
You shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
And you get into the fact of verse 17,
the flesh and the spirit,
they're at enmity one with another.
The works of the flesh are manifest,
and he lists them all out.
And then you get into the fruit of the spirit.
And think about this.
We know what we are now.
And we know, as he says in 1 John 4, in verse number 17,
that as he is, so are we in this world.
Listen, we're not gonna be in this world long.
Amen?
This world is not my home.
I'm just passing through.
That's what the songwriter said.
And what a wonderful little chorus that is.
When we think about the fact
that we're just strangers in pilgrims, amen?
I'm not home, but I'm going home.
Glory, hallelujah.
This world is not my home, but as I'm here,
listen, I understand that now, as I'm here,
that I'm his ambassador.
I'm his representative.
I am his witness that people are to see Christ in us.
And as we're loving one another,
that impact that it has for us,
that we can have that confidence,
that we can have that boldness in the day of judgment.
Why?
Because we're doing what we're supposed to do.
We're abiding in him, and we're living,
if I could call it this, we're living the Christ life.
You say, well, that's being awfully prideful.
You know what Paul said in 2 Timothy chapter number four?
Under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God, by the way,
he said this, I am now ready to be offered
the time of my departure is at hand.
I have fought a good fight, I have finished my course,
I have kept the faith.
Paul is not being prideful.
He's completed what God's called him to do.
And then he says this, again, being mindful of the truth
that it's under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
he says, henceforth, there is laid up for me
a crown of righteousness.
Well, that's awfully prideful of you, Paul,
to think that you're getting a crown.
It's not prideful.
God said there are crowns, and Paul understood
that his obedience would lead to,
he's gonna receive a crown.
And he says this, not for which the Lord,
the righteous judge, shall give me at that day,
and not to me only, but unto all them also
that love is appearing.
You can have a crown of righteousness as well.
Wonderful.
And so again, back to 1 John chapter number three,
we find that he says that we are the sons of God,
it doth not yet appear what we shall be,
but we know that when he shall appear,
we shall be like him, for we shall see him as he is.
Isn't that wonderful?
Thinking about that glorified state
that this mortal shall put on immortality,
that this corruption shall put on incorruption,
and we can just rejoice in understanding
the glory of heaven and all that will take place,
but we understand that while we're here,
we're to be like him.
When he shall appear, I'm gonna be like him, glorified,
but now as I'm living this life here on this earth,
I am to be like him because as he is,
so are we in this world.
We're to be like Christ.
And his love through us is impactful in our lives,
it gives us a boldness, it gives us a confidence,
it enables us not to be ashamed at his appearing.
Not only is it powerful and impactful,
but I believe that as we look at the word of God,
and we consider our love one toward another,
and we consider his love not only toward us,
but through us, that his love through us is observable.
It is observable.
Notice, if you will, in verse number 20,
verse 19, we've read before,
we love him because he first loved us,
what a precious truth of the word of God,
but then look at what he says in verse 20.
If a man say, I love God, and hateth his brother,
he is a liar.
Again, that's strong language.
It's the word of God.
Throughout the book of 1 John,
we have found many times where God is telling his people,
you can say whatever you wanna say,
but here's the evidence, the proof,
of what you say being true.
If a man say, I love God, and hateth his brother,
he's a liar.
The evidence, the litmus test, if you will,
and today we have people, I've mentioned about the truth,
and we see it in chapter number five,
we've seen it in John, we've mentioned it many times.
If you love me, keep my commandments.
People say, I love God, I love Jesus,
and they're not obeying the word of God.
Here he says, if you love God,
but you hate your brother, you're lying.
So if you hate your brother, you don't love God.
It's observable, notice what he says here.
For he that loveth not his brother whom he hath seen,
how can he love God whom he hath not seen?
In this commandment, have we from him
that he who loveth God love his brother also?
Wow.
It's observable.
We find that Jesus said this in John 13,
in verse number 35, we're familiar,
as we've mentioned last week, verse number 34,
with the new commandment that Jesus gave,
but then he says this, by this shall all men know
that you are my disciples if you have love one to another.
You know, the church in Corinth
didn't do so well at that, did they?
There were divisions and schisms and all sorts of things,
but you know when you begin to really study
the book of 1 Corinthians in particular,
begin to study the people there at the church in Corinth,
you know why there were divisions and schisms
and all those going in?
Because they were carnal.
The Bible tells us that Paul says,
I can't write unto you as being spiritual,
but as carnal, as babes.
And so the love of God wasn't flowing through them,
they were at opposition and enmity one with another.
Listen, the world should see in us,
and they will know that we are his disciples
by our love one toward another.
It's observable.
So we begin to think about the love of God toward us,
and his love through us,
and we've had this recurring thought
that we ought to love one another.
So what is, this morning,
as we kind of finish up the message,
what are some practical ways,
what's some application that we can take in our lives,
and look at the word of God,
and say, here's how we practically fulfill
the instruction that we've been given to love one another.
I'm gonna give you three thoughts this morning
on how biblically we can love one another.
Notice the Bible tells us in Ephesians five
that we are to walk in love,
in Ephesians five, in verse number two.
I wanna give you examples of a couple of men.
I'm not gonna go to the book of Philemon,
I just talked through the book of Philemon
on Wednesday evenings.
But in verse number five,
the book of Philemon describes Philemon as a man
that loved the Lord and loved all the saints.
I want you to think about that.
It's consistent with what we're reading here in 1 John.
That if you love God, you're to love one another.
If you say that you love God,
but you hate your brother, you're a liar.
And so the Bible says of Philemon
that Paul is saying, I've heard about your love
that you have, not only your love, but your faith.
And the love, as he describes it, he says,
which thou hast toward the Lord Jesus and toward,
notice what it says, all saints.
Not just the ones that you connect with best,
but love toward all saints.
Why?
Because we're brothers and sisters in Christ.
Amen?
And we find, it's very interesting, by the way,
it's awesome how God works,
but God is really, in this book of Philemon,
he's setting Philemon up for Onesimus.
You love all the saints, and now Onesimus is a saint.
Love him.
Amen?
Because you love all the saints.
But he didn't me wrong, he's forgiven.
Love him.
Powerful truth.
But I want you to look at the book of 3 John, if you will,
and I want you to look at what the Bible says
about a man by the name of Gaius.
And then I'll give you three points
on how we can practically apply in our lives.
What does it mean to love one another?
How is that observed?
How is that practiced?
in our lives. New Testament truth that we'll look at, three truths that we'll
look and examine, but look at what the Bible says here in 3 John, only one
chapter here, but begin looking at verse number five. We know that he's writing to
the well-beloved Gaius according to verse number one. Notice in verse number
five, he says, beloved thou doest faithfully whatsoever thou doest to the
brethren and to strangers. Well, that's a high commendation, is it not? Notice he
continues, he says, which have borne witness of thy charity before the church.
Understand the word charity is synonymous with the word love. In fact,
the Greek word that is translated charity is actually translated love more
times in the New Testament than it's translated charity. It's the same Greek
word, and you find here that he's speaking of this love of this charity
that Gaius has, and he says that he doest whatever he does, he does it
faithfully, and he says this not only to the brethren but to the strangers, which
have borne witness of thy charity. Notice what it says, before the church. So in
your mind's eye, see what's happening as John is writing to this Gaius, this
well-beloved Gaius. He says to Gaius, he says, listen, there are people that have
stood up and give testimony before the church of your love for the brethren.
Isn't that awesome? Because it was what? It was observable. It was God's love
working through Gaius. He had been a recipient of the love of God, he had been
saved by the very grace of God, and he now, as the Holy Spirit of God would
indwell him, he's now loving that love of God working through him. It impacted his
own life, it was observable. They gave testimony, continue in verse number six,
which if thou bring forward on their journey after a godly sort thou shalt do
well, because that for his name's sake they went forth taking nothing of the
Gentiles, we therefore ought to receive such that we might be fellow helpers to
the truth. And we find that Gaius understood it, he was allowing the Lord
to work through him, and what a great testimony of this man Philemon, and then
of this man Gaius, and we see the truth of the church in Thessalonica that we
used by way of introduction this morning, and now we look at these two individual
believers that were loving one another. It says of Philemon, just a couple of
verses later in that text of Scripture, how the bowels, the emotions of the
brethren were refreshed by him. Wow. So how do we do it? Three simple thoughts
this morning on how do we love one another. Number one, pray for one another.
Pray for one another. Go to the book of Philippians, if you will. I want you to
look in the first chapter, and I want you to see what the Apostle Paul says to
this church in Philippi as he's writing to them and seeking to not only
instruct them but to encourage them. And we come to Philippians chapter number
one, and I want you to notice what Paul says in verses three and four. In
Philippians chapter number one, beginning in verse number three, the Bible says,
"'I thank my God upon every remembrance of you, always, and every prayer of mine for
you all, making request with joy.'" So is Paul praying for the believers at
Philippi according to verses three and four of Philippians 1? Sure he is. He says,
"'I thank my God upon every remembrance of you,' he says, "'always, and every prayer of
mine for you.'" He doesn't just say, "'and every prayer of mine,' and leave it blank. No,
he's praying for them specifically. But why is he praying for them? Notice in
verse number 17, even assorry, verse number 7, here in Philippians 1 and verse
number 7'even as it is mean for me to think this of you all,' notice this next
phrase, "'because I have you in my heart.'" Because I have you in my heart. Because I
love you. Because I have you in my heart, I have you in my head. And that's why I
thank God on every remembrance of you, and that's why I'm praying for you. He
continues in verse number 7, "'inasmuch as both in my bonds and in the defense
and confirmation of the gospel, ye all are partakers of my grace. For God is my
record, how greatly I long after you all in the bowels of Jesus Christ.'" Wow. Why is
Paul longing for them? Man, because he has them on his heart. He loves them. He loves
these believers in Philippi. And because of his lovelisten, we say, we're to love
one another. Okay, so if I love you, what does that mean practically? It means I'm
praying for you. That's an expression of my love, of your love, one for another, is
that we're praying one for another. You know, sometimes it ought not be the case, but sometimes
people seem to not appreciate prayer in the sense that theyyou might tell somebody
you're praying for them, but they really are looking for something in their mind that's
more than prayer. You know the greatest thing I could ever do for anyone is pray for them?
To pray for them. As we invest time in prayer, I've sat in situations over the years, I promise
you, and I would never go into details, but I have sat in situations over the years that
it would have been so much easier for me to give somebody a check and tell them to get
out of my office than for me to spend time with them and for me to pray with them and
for them. It would have been so much easier to just write them a check and say,
hallelujah, goodbye. I'm not being unkind by saying, I'm just saying it'd be easier.
And some people would rather have a check because they think it's something that's
more significant that's going to help them. But the greatest thing we could ever do for
anyone is give them our time, and then if we're giving them our time by praying for them,
what a great investment of our time, what a great evidence of our love for them,
that I'm investing my time with the Lord in prayer on your behalf. Wow. Paul says,
you're in my heart, so I'm praying for you. I long to see you. Listen, if there's somebody
that you long to see, it's not because you don't like them. He longs to see them because
he loves them. Notice not only do we pray one for another. I would say this, New Testament
truth with regard to the practical application of what does it mean to love one another? It
means that we serve one another. It means that we serve one another. Go to the book of Galatians,
if you will, in the fifth chapter. Galatians chapter number 5. Galatians 5 and verse number
13, this idea of serving one another. You know, we live in a time and an era where people would
rather be served than serve. Do you agree with that this morning? We live in a time,
we live in an era where people would rather be served than serve. But as New Testament believers,
as we understand this truth of loving one another, notice what Galatians 5 and verse 13 says,
for brethren, ye have been called unto liberty, only use not liberty for an occasion to the flesh.
Notice what he says, but by love serve one another. By love serve one another. He says,
for all the laws fulfilled in one word, even in this, thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself.
I'm going to read to you a verse from the book of Hebrews in the sixth chapter. You don't need to
turn there. But in Hebrews chapter number 6 and verse number 10, the Bible says, for God is not
unrighteous to forget your work and labor of love, which you have showed toward his name,
in that ye have ministered to the saints and do minister. He's not talking about here of their
service to God, although that's important and that shows that we love him. But he says of your work
and of your labor of love, and how is that known? He says in that you have ministered to the saints
and do minister. So, not only past tense, have you ministered, but you're actively ministering. Glory.
That's because we love one another. Think about the Lord Jesus Christ in John chapter number 13,
a wonderful passage of Scripture that deals with not only the love, but also the humility of the
Lord Jesus Christ being a servant. It's in that text of Scripture in John 13 where Jesus washes
the feet of the disciples. The lowest of low tasks that could be given to anyone, and Jesus
washes the feet of the disciples. Yes, we see his humility, but we see that he's a servant. He's a
servant. It begins in John 13 by saying he loved them until the end.
And it ends in John chapter number 13
by Jesus saying,
a new commandment have I given you
that you love not as yourself,
but you love as I have loved.
So if we're going to love one another,
if we're going to apply the truth
that we've been studying,
that we've been reviewing,
that we've been confronted with,
it will look like prayer.
It will look like service.
And then let me say this,
there are many others.
But number three,
forgive one another.
Forgive one another.
From the book of Ephesians,
if you will,
in the fourth chapter,
I referenced a moment ago,
verse 32,
and I told you we'd come back to it.
I did not read the verse.
But I want you to look here
in Ephesians chapter number four,
verse two and verse number 32,
with this subject of forgiving one another.
In Ephesians four and verse number two,
the Bible says with all lowliness
and meekness with long suffering
for bearing one another in love.
And he goes through all sorts of things
that we're to do
as we study through this chapter.
And then of course,
you come to the end of the chapter,
he's dealing with put off,
put on,
and that principle of walking in the spirit.
And he comes to verse number 32,
and he says,
and be kind one to another.
Notice this word,
tender hearted,
forgiving one another,
even as God for Christ's sake
hath forgiven you.
Let me ask you this morning,
are you thankful that you've been forgiven?
Wow.
So thankful to be forgiven.
You know,
the people that should have no problem with forgiveness
are the ones that have been forgiven.
Honestly.
We've been forgiven.
Listen, I didn't earn,
I didn't deserve forgiveness.
God offered me forgiveness,
even though I didn't deserve it.
Because he loved me.
For his God who is rich in mercy,
a God who loved me with great love,
he offered me forgiveness.
I didn't deserve it.
And we're to forgive one another.
Notice what the Bible says in 1 Peter chapter number four.
We'll close with this verse of scripture this morning,
as we consider the practical application.
What does it look like to love one another?
Well, if we're gonna love one another,
we're gonna pray for one another.
If we're gonna love one another,
we're gonna serve one another.
we're gonna forgive one another.
In 1 Peter chapter number four,
in verse number eight,
notice how he says,
and above all things have fervent charity among yourselves.
For charity shall cover the multitude of sins.
Let me try to, as best I can,
quickly explain this verse of scripture.
It does not carry with it the idea
that charity sweeps sin under the carpet.
You're never gonna find that in the New Testament.
But the idea is that as God would forgive them,
then I have charity love
that I'm going to forgive them as well.
Charity covereth the multitude of sins.
It's not a situation where I love them,
so I'm gonna let them do whatever they wanna do.
They can sin and it's just all okay,
and so on and so forth.
No, there's gonna be judgment for that.
God, listen, God is a righteous God,
but he's a loving God, and God forgives.
And I'm so thankful that he forgives.
And as we have fervent charity one with another,
accordingly it says in 1 Peter four in verse number eight,
then he says that charity covereth the multitude of sins.
That's a wonderful truth of the word of God.
I'm so thankful that as you read the book
of 1 Corinthians and 2 Corinthians,
that Paul addresses a sinful situation
in the book of 1 Corinthians,
a situation that was so egregious
that he says it's not even named amongst the Gentiles.
Wicked behavior that's taking place
in the book of 1 Corinthians.
Evidently, as you read the book of 2 Corinthians
and you see what's taking place,
evidently that man got right with God.
You know what Paul tells those believers in Corinth?
Forgive them.
And then just after that, he talks about the fact
that we're not ignorant of Satan's devices.
Oh, he'd love to use bitterness to harm you and to divide.
But Paul says, that brother was forgiven,
then you forgive him.
You look at the difference between 1 Corinthians
and 2 Corinthians on dealing with that brother,
I mean, hey, deal with it.
Don't sweep it under the rug, deal with it.
But as they got it right and they had forgiveness,
then you too offer forgiveness.
See, we're to have fervent charity, one toward another.
If we're going to love as we ought to love,
we ought to love one another.
It's one thing to know it,
it's another thing to practice it and to do it.
We see God's love toward us and how we ought to rejoice.
We see God's love working through us.
It's not my love, it's God's love through me.
And God is the one that enables me to love.
It's a powerful love because it's God's love.
It's perfected in us, the Bible says.
It's a love that's impactful.
It helps me to have that opportunity
to have boldness and confidence because as he is, so am I.
It's observable.
If you say that you love God but you hate your brother,
you're a liar.
It's observable.
By this shall all men know that you're my disciples.
What is this?
You're loved one for another.
But then practically, okay, we understand,
but how do we do it?
Where's the rubber meet the road?
Three New Testament truths.
Pray, pray one for another.
Listen, if you say that you love somebody
but you're not praying for them,
I would personally recommend you evaluating that
because Paul said you're in my heart
and that means you're in my mind
and that means you're in my prayers.
Serve one another in love.
God's not gonna forget our service of love,
our labor of love as you did minister
and as you continue to minister and then forgive one another.
Three practical ways that our love one for another
is evidenced in our daily lives.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the precious word of God.
We thank you for the instruction that you've given us.
We thank you for your love toward us.
As we think about the message this morning,
we're thankful for your love through us.
And God, I pray that you would help us
to love one another as we ought.
Help us to apply the truth in our lives.
Help us to be doers of the word and not hearers only.
Maybe there's one that's never trusted Christ
as their savior.
Oh, how we would rejoice in their salvation.
Maybe this morning someone needs to come
and just thank you, Lord, for your love toward them.
God, maybe this morning we need to come
and ask you to help us to love as we ought to love.
That we'd abide in you,
that we'd walk in obedience to your commands,
to your ways, that we would be like you.
That we would love as you love
because it's your love working through us.
I pray that you'd have your will and way
in these moments of invitation.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you?