13, and this morning we'll be looking at verses 7 through 17 from this passage of Scripture,
Hebrews chapter number 13.
And last week we looked at the first six verses of Hebrews 13, and we dealt with the behavior
of a believer, or of the believer, and we come now to this next section, and really
this is going to be a part one, part two for the next two Sunday mornings.
We would look at this passage and really finish up the book of Hebrews, and typically I am
scrambling to finish the book in which we are preaching from on Sunday mornings through
our themes, and this year I was sharing with Holly last night, I was planning to preach
from somewhere else for Thanksgiving, and I began to just meditate upon the last portion
of Hebrews 13, and very familiar with the truth in verse number 15, in fact it's where
we get our title for the message, where the Bible says,
"...by Him, therefore, let us offer the sacrifice of praise to God continually, that is, the
fruit of our lips giving thanks to His name, but to do good and to communicate, forget
not, for with such sacrifices God is well pleased."
And from verse number 15, we've derived our title, Our Lips Giving Thanks to His Name.
Again, it will be a part one, and I was very familiar with this truth in verse number 15,
but we were ended last week in verse number 6, and I was kind of feeling like I was a
week off, you know, how do I go to verse 15 and then next week go back, and began to really
just meditate over the portion of Scripture that is before us this morning, and obviously
we are very familiar, most of us I would say, understand the biblical principle of giving
thanks, and we're familiar, no doubt, with the Old Testament children of Israel and their
constant murmuring, and how that often we would look to and see that sin of complaining
and murmuring, and we would obviously critique them, and understand that we're to learn from
their just bad behavior, poor behavior, and we're to give thanks.
You read through the book of Psalms, and often you are reading and confronted with the way
in which we would praise and give thanks to our God and how wonderful He is.
Of course, we have been given instruction with regard to giving thanks as New Testament
believers in everything give thanks, for this is the will of God in Christ Jesus concerning
you.
And sometimes we can have difficulty in that everything part, right, and we say, well,
there are certain things that it's easy to give thanks for, but in everything, that's
a little bit challenging, that's a little bit difficult, but we understand that we serve
a God who is sovereign, who is good all of the time, and we know, as we look at the truth
in Romans chapter 8, that we know that all things work together for good to them that
love God, to them who are called according to His purpose, and so we are to give thanks
in all things.
And as we look at this portion of Scripture, and again, as I meditated on these verses
and began to really just spend time in this last section of Hebrews 13, I went through
and the Lord revealed to me ten particular things in which the children of God, the child
of God, should rejoice.
Ten reasons to rejoice in verses 7 through 25.
A couple of weeks ago on a Wednesday evening, I had ten points, and promptly realized after
the second point that there was no possible way I would get through all ten in one evening,
and so therefore, on the fly, I broke that message into two.
Well, I learned from past experience, and therefore, this morning, part one, we're only
going to look at the first five of these ten reasons to rejoice that we find as we
conclude Hebrews and looking at this thirteenth chapter.
Notice with me in verse number seven, the Bible says this, remember them which have
the rule over you, who have spoken unto you the word of God, whose faith follow, considering
the end of their conversation.
As we begin digging into the portion of Scripture, we notice in verse number seven the first
reason for us to rejoice, and that would be this, number one, for spiritual leaders.
We find in verse number seven, the Bible says, remember them which have the rule over you,
who have spoken unto you the word of God, and then it says, whose faith follow, considering
the end of their conversation or their life, and we understand, even as the Apostle Paul
would have written to the church in Philippi, and he spoke to them about the things that
they had heard from him, but also the things that they seen in him do.
The reality is that spiritual leaders, we ought to give thanks for the spiritual leaders
that God has brought into our lives.
In verse number 17, the Bible says, obey them that have the rule over you, and submit yourselves.
Notice what it says, for they watch for your souls, as they that must give account, that
they may do it with joy and not with grief, for that is unprofitable for you.
Can I tell you this morning that verse number 17 is a heavy verse of Scripture.
It deals with one of the responsibilities of spiritual leaders, and that is that we
watch for your souls, and the Bible says they must give account, I mean, that is a weighty
truth of the word of God, and we find that the Apostle Paul, no doubt, as he would consider
spiritual leaders and spiritual leadership, he mentions about all of those things that
come upon him, and all of the outward things that he dealt with, and then he says this,
and the care of all the churches which comes upon me daily.
We think about spiritual leaders, we're familiar with the Old Testament, we understand how
God would lead his people, the children of Israel, and how he used men, he used leaders,
we can think of Moses as being a leader for the children of Israel, we can think of Joshua,
we can think of the period of the judges, and of course the prophets and the priests,
and we can think about that spiritual leadership that they would provide, of course, during
that particular era.
As New Testament believers, we understand this morning that the church is God's idea.
The church is not man's idea, someone did not decide at some point in history, you know,
I think we ought to have a church.
The church is God's idea, God ordained the church, and he also instructed how a church
is supposed to operate.
He's given us in his word the truths with regard to the polity, the leadership of the
church, the ordinances in the church, the offices in the church, all of those things
we find that God has given us in his word.
And so we find that the church is God's idea, it's been ordained by God, and he has established
spiritual leadership.
I want you to turn back, if you will, to the book of Ephesians in chapter number 4, and
I want you to notice what Paul says to the believers here in Ephesus as we would think
about this truth of giving thanks, one, the first reason from this portion of Scripture
for which we should rejoice and thank God, give thanks to the Lord is for spiritual leaders.
In Ephesians chapter number 4, the Bible says in verse number 11, and he gave some apostles
and some prophets and some evangelists and some pastors and teachers.
Notice what it says, for the perfecting of the saints, for the work of the ministry,
for the edifying of the body of Christ.
I know that this morning it's a little bit awkward, if you will, to be the pastor and
speaking about giving thanks for spiritual leadership or spiritual leaders, because I
am one.
However, I am thankful for the spiritual leaders that God put in my life, and as I began to
meditate upon this truth in Hebrews 13 and verse number 7 and verse number 17, and begin
to dig in and to see that the first of these reasons to rejoice, as we conclude Hebrews
13, is to give thanks for the spiritual leaders, I'm mindful of the very first pastor that
I ever met, that I ever remember meeting and having any amount of influence in my life,
was a man by the name of Rodney Paddock, and he was a pastor at Grace Baptist Church in
Jacksonville, North Carolina, and that's the church where my parents got saved.
And I remember he had a little Sunday school class in the back of the property in a little,
really like a little modular type trailer, if I remember correctly, and it was a new
believers class, and I remember for Sunday school that my parents would go into that
class and they would be instructed and they'd be taught, and Pastor Paddock was a man that
loved the Lord, he was a man that gave his life to influence others and to instruct them
in the Word of God, and what a great ministry he had.
Brother Paddock is with the Lord today, and he went home to be with the Lord many years
ago, but the reality is that there's still a church there that, to the best of my knowledge,
the last time I visited Jacksonville, North Carolina, and stopped by the church, I had
the privilege of meeting some of the folks there, and they have had a worldwide impact
through missions, because of the influence in the military, and of course in and out,
and so on and so forth.
A man that was a spiritual leader, I didn't get saved under his ministry, but man, he
influenced my parents and he instructed them, and I'm thankful for a man like Rodney Paddock.
I'm thankful for a man like Palmer Sean, he was my pastor, you understand that he's been
here as an evangelist, he's in evangelism now, but God used Palmer Sean in my life,
and he was a spiritual leader.
As I was a senior in high school, just after I got saved, we began going to his church,
and as we were there at his church, it began to grow, and he took an interest in me, and
he began to encourage me and instruct me, and I felt like the Lord was calling me to
the ministry, and I didn't know what that meant, what that all looked like, and I remember
Brother Mershawn as a spiritual leader, coming and giving guidance and counsel and direction
and all.
So, even to this day, I still contact Brother Marshawn.
He's a spiritual leader in my life.
I could go on and I could mention other names
of spiritual leaders that God has given in my life,
and no doubt in your life,
you've had some spiritual leaders
that God has allowed you to be influenced by,
and we need to rejoice and thank God
that in His wisdom, in His plan,
not only did He ordain a church
and the church, but we find that He established
the leadership for the church,
and spiritual leaders, we ought to give God glory
and thanks for the spiritual leaders.
Think about this.
We see in Ephesians 4 that the Bible says
that He gave some apostles, some prophets,
some evangelists, and some pastors and teachers.
He tells the purpose for the perfecting of the saints,
for the work of the ministry,
for the edifying of the body of Christ,
and how blessed we are.
You know, there are churches all across the world,
and really, as we think about our nation,
as the United States of America,
there are churches all across this nation
that do not have spiritual leadership.
They're lacking pastors.
The office is vacant.
There are pastors that regularly resign.
I read statistics as you go through this year,
in 2020, and all of the things
that have been accompanied with this pandemic,
and they estimate that at least one quarter
of those in spiritual leadership will resign
by the end of the year.
That's sad.
There are churches, listen,
I remember preaching in churches just after Bible college,
and being in churches and not having pastors
and inquiring from them how long it had been
since they'd had a pastor.
Two years, three years, four years.
Oh, man.
Then you have some that are in the office,
but they're not fulfilling the office.
They're not preaching the Word of God.
They're not doing what God had instructed in His Word.
Notice what Peter says.
You don't need to turn there,
but in 1 Peter 5, in verse number two,
Peter says, feed the flock of God.
He's speaking to the elders.
In verse number one, he tells us that,
the elders which are among you I exhort,
whom also an elder, the spiritual leaders.
It says, and a witness of the suffering of Christ,
sufferings of Christ, and also a partaker of the glory
that shall be revealed, feed the flock of God,
which is among you, taking the oversight thereof,
not by constraint, but willingly,
not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind,
neither as being lords over God's heritage,
but being in samples to the flock.
You remember that the early church,
in the book of Acts, as they were dealing
with various things that were accompanying the growth
and all that was going on,
and in Acts chapter number six,
there begins to have some internal uproars, if you will,
and we find that the disciples,
they say that they weren't gonna leave
the Word of God to serve tables.
Now, not that they were above the fact of serving tables,
but they said that they were gonna give themselves
continually to prayer and to the ministry of the Word,
the responsibility to feed the flock of God,
and I would say this morning that as we look at Hebrews 13
and begin looking at these reasons to rejoice,
that it begins with identifying spiritual leadership
and thanking God for spiritual leaders.
Number two, if you're taking notes back in Hebrews 13,
look in verse number eight, the Bible says this,
Jesus Christ, the same yesterday and today and forever.
Reason number two to rejoice,
not only for spiritual leaders,
but number two, for the immutability of Christ.
I'm so thankful for the truth of the Word of God
with regard to this teaching that our God changes not.
The Bible says the same yesterday and today and forever.
You understand that everything around us changes.
Sometimes the changes are rapid, are they not?
Sometimes the changes are not the changes we had hoped for
or were looking toward,
but the reality is that we can rejoice in the fact
that we serve a God who does not change.
He is the same yesterday and today and forever.
Obviously, even as you look at the way
in which the verse is articulated,
you would find not only the immutability of God,
but the eternality of God,
the eternality of Christ that he is forever.
And what a joy to think about the truth of the immutability
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
Notice here in Hebrews 13,
the truth that says Jesus Christ,
the same yesterday and today and forever.
In Malachi chapter number three,
we find that the prophet of God is there
and he's prophesying, he's ministering,
and God is laying out some charges
and some indictments against his people.
And in verse number six of Malachi chapter number three,
notice what God says.
I am the Lord.
I change not.
Therefore, ye sons of Jacob are not consumed.
Aren't you thankful that our God does not change?
I've often said as I've meditated
and mentioned the truth,
the doctrine of the immutability of the Lord Jesus Christ,
how that it should cause us to rejoice greatly,
for we would be in a real terrible situation if God changed
and we didn't know how to approach him
because he changes from generation to generation,
from life to life.
And man, it'd be challenging, it'd be difficult,
but we understand that our God changes not,
the immutability of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And I hope this morning that as you begin to think this week
as we celebrate Thanksgiving
and we think about the principle of giving thanks
and praising God,
that we would find even here in Hebrews 13,
some real good reasons for which we should rejoice.
Number one, spiritual leaders.
Number two, the immutability of Christ.
Number three, back in Hebrews 13, I would say this,
we need to rejoice for the Word of God,
for the Word of God.
I'm so thankful for God's Word.
I mean, honestly, this morning,
as we think about this book that we hold in our hands,
you must understand that there are many people
that have gone before us that gave their lives
so that we could hold this book in our hands this morning.
You didn't have to give a whole lot of anything.
Maybe somebody even gave you the Bible
that you hold in your hands.
Maybe you purchased the Bible.
Maybe you have a real nice Bible
and you paid 100 or $150 for that Bible,
but you can go down to the dollar store
and get a Bible for a dollar.
In fact, if you need a Bible, we can give you a Bible.
We've mentioned that over the years.
We have Bibles downstairs.
And I remember a lady that came here a number of years ago.
She was just walking down Oakton Road
and she was from China.
And she saw the cross atop our sign
and then saw the cross on top of the fellowship hall.
She came walking up the driveway
and you could tell that she was just inquiring
as to what this building was.
And by seeing the cross,
she had assumed it was a church.
And Holly and I were here.
In fact, we were in the fellowship hall having lunch.
And we saw this lady walking up the driveway
and didn't know who she was
and went out and asked if she needed some assistance.
And she asked, is this a church?
And she was here because her daughter
was going to be going to school locally
as an exchange student.
She came into our church.
She said, can I come in and see?
And I said, absolutely, you can come in.
And she came here into the sanctuary in our auditorium.
And as she was standing in here
and she saw the cross here
and she was just kind of taking it all in.
And then back then there wasn't coronavirus.
And so we had Bibles in our pews.
You don't have Bibles in the pews anymore,
but there were Bibles in the pews.
And she saw one of the Bibles next to the hymnals.
And she said, is that a Bible?
I said, it is.
Can I see it?
I said, sure.
She said, I've never held a Bible before.
I've never seen a whole Bible before.
That's what she told me.
Mark, she was standing about two rows behind
where you're sitting this morning.
And she stood right there and Holly was standing with me
right here as we're talking to her.
And she just held onto that pew Bible.
And I said, would you like one of your own?
And you thought I'd give her a billion dollars.
I'm serious.
She said, really, I could have one?
I said, well, I'm not gonna give you that one.
I'll give you another one.
And I went downstairs and got a Bible
and brought it up to her.
At that time, Holly and the lady were standing
in the foyer chatting.
And she grabbed that Bible from me and she hugged it.
I mean, it was precious.
But this morning, see, we gotta give thanks
for the Word of God.
I mean, when you were getting ready
to leave the house this morning,
you probably grabbed your Bible to bring with you.
You're going to church to bring my Bible.
And I hope that you had some time this morning
before you came to church to open up your Bible
and read the Word of God
and that we understand how precious this book is,
that we understand this morning
that there are countless people around the globe
that do not have a Bible that they can go and open and read.
But yet God has seen fit to bless.
And we have the Word of God.
Notice in our text in verse number nine,
the Bible says this,
"'Be not carried about with divers in strange doctrines,
"'for it is a good thing that the heart
"'be established with grace, not with meats
"'which have not profited them
"'that have been occupied therein.'"
You say, pastor, where do you see the Word of God?
Well, the reality is that the Bible says
it is a good thing that the heart be established with grace
right after it says,
be not carried about with divers in strange doctrine.
And therefore I say, I need to give thanks
for the Word of God because of the Word of God
that is the source of sound doctrine.
I would be carried away with all sorts of false teachings
and strange doctrines if it were not.
for this book.
And so would you.
Why is it that we can travel to places around the globe?
Why is it that missionaries can go to places around the globe and they can find in various
groups of people strange, diverse and strange doctrines?
Because they don't have the Bible.
They don't have spiritual leaders that are teaching the Word of God, that are feeding
the flock of God from the Word of God.
I've often thought, I've said it probably a half a dozen times already this morning
about turning in your Bible, take your Bible and turn to the book of Hebrews and turn over
to this passage and so on and so forth.
There are people that do not have a Bible that are sitting in a church this morning
that have one person, the spiritual leader that has the Word of God.
He can't say turn in your Bibles.
We find that the Word of God is the source for sound doctrine.
All scriptures given by inspiration of God is profitable for doctrine.
I'm so thankful for the Word of God.
I'm thankful that because of the Word of God, not only is it the source of sound doctrine,
but we find that it says it is a good thing that the heart be established with grace.
I'm thankful that it establishes our heart.
That word established means to make firm or to make sure.
I mean to be established, not to be tossed to and fro with every wind of doctrine.
No, to understand what thus saith the Lord, to have the Word of God.
Remember Paul often says as he's ministering to those that God would give them the opportunity,
he says, but I speak the Word of God to you and I would not have you be ignorant brethren
and so on and so forth.
And he's giving them the Word of God, why?
So that their hearts could be established, so that they could have some stability in
their lives.
They would not be tossed to and fro.
That's why it's so important that we understand this morning the preciousness of this book
and that we have it in its right place in our lives.
As Baptist people, we've often been referred to as people of the book.
By the way, that's a good thing.
Amen?
And we find that we look at the Word of God and as Baptist people, if someone were to
say what distinguishes you as a Baptist, many times our first answer would be that the Bible
is the sole authority for faith and practice.
What do we mean by that?
It's our final authority.
It's our only authority.
You can find religious organizations all over the world that say they believe the Bible,
but you would understand as you would dig in and you'd begin to evaluate and investigate
their teachings and their denominations, that the Bible is just one source.
It is not the source.
They look to some other writings, whether it's religious writings.
They look at various church fathers, if you will, and all of these things, and we say,
no, no, the Bible is our authority.
If what a theologian of yesteryear said lines up with the Word of God, I'm okay with it.
But if what a theologian from yesteryear said doesn't line up with the Word of God, then
we must side with God and His Word.
We say, sorry, man is fallible, but God is infallible.
And we look at the Word of God and we find in verse number nine that it is the source
for sound doctrine, that it establishes our hearts, that it helps us to have surety of
what it is that we believe.
When someone comes and asks you, what do you believe about this, and what do you believe
about that, and why do you do this, man, it ought to be that we can go to the Word of
God and share, here's why we do the things that we do, because here's what God said.
Verse 22, notice the Bible says this, and I beseech you, brethren, suffer the word of
exhortation.
Notice what it says, for I have written a letter unto you in few words.
What's it referring to?
Well, this very book of Hebrews that we've been studying all year.
This is the letter that he's referring to.
And we look here, and I look at verse number 22, and of course, we're reading this and
understanding that this is part of the canon of Scripture.
This is the Word of God, but it had been written, it had been sent to these Hebrew, these Jewish
believers in the first century.
And I would say this, as I begin to think about the Word of God and the preciousness
of God's Word, and the reason that we ought to thank God for His Word, not only that it's
the source of doctrine and establishes our hearts, but it's available.
I've already mentioned by the story I gave you from the lady from China how that we ought
to rejoice that it's available to us.
I want you to notice what God says to the children of Israel back in the book of Deuteronomy,
if you will, in chapter number 30.
We find in Deuteronomy chapter number 30 that Moses is speaking here to the children of
Israel, giving them direction, and they're soon going to be entering into the land of
promise.
And as we look at Deuteronomy chapter number 30, we find out some important truth with
regard to the availability of the Word of God.
In verse number 10, the Bible says this in Deuteronomy 30 and verse number 10,
"...if thou shalt hearken unto the voice of the Lord thy God to keep His commandments
and His statutes," notice what it says, "...which are written in this book of the law."
You understand that the Pentateuch, the first five books of the Bible, Genesis, Exodus,
Leviticus, Numbers, and Deuteronomy, this is the book that he's referring to.
You find in Joshua 1 and verse number 8, this book of the law, "...shall not depart out
of thy mouth."
And we see that he talks about the laws and the statutes, the commandments that are written
therein.
Notice in verse 10, "...and if thou turn unto the Lord thy God with all thine heart,
with all thy soul, for this commandment which I command thee this day," notice what it says,
"...it is not hidden from thee, neither is it far off."
Aren't you thankful that God didn't hide it from us?
He made it available.
Again for us as being here in the United States of America and speaking English, that we have
the English Bible that's available to us, and how we ought to rejoice in the blessing
of God and giving us the Word of God, it's not been hidden from us.
Notice in verse number 12, "...it is not in heaven that thou shouldst say, Who shall go
up for us to heaven and bring it unto us, that we may hear it and do it?
Neither is it beyond the sea, that thou shouldst say, Who shall go over the sea for us and
bring it unto us, that we may hear it and do it?
But the Word is very nigh unto thee, in thy mouth and in thy heart, that thou mayest do
it."
You know one of the sad things when you think about the Word of God and the availability
of the Word of God and even thinking about the preciousness of God's Word and how we
ought to thank God for His Word, one of the things that's sad when we think about the
Word of God and speak about the Word of God is how often it's neglected.
How often it's neglected by people that profess to be believers.
You know there are statistics that are done all through the years and often you find that
there are many that are asked the question that profess to be Bible believers and they're
asked, have you ever read the Bible in its entirety?
And it's a very small percentage of people that say yes.
Oftentimes the Bible is neglected even by the very people that claim to believe it.
And that's a sad thing because God has given it to us that we would know it and that we
would do it.
And this morning as we look here in Hebrews chapter 13 and begin to focus upon the fact
that my mouth, our lips giving thanks to His name and we have reasons to rejoice and
the text of Scripture provides these believers with a number of them.
And this morning we say, listen, I need to give thanks to God.
My lips need to give thanks to His name.
Number one, for spiritual leaders.
Number two, for the immutability of Christ.
Number three, for the Word of God.
Number four, back in Hebrews 13, Lotus and verse number 12.
But let's read verse 10 through 12.
The Bible says in verse number 10, we have an altar whereof they have no right to eat
which serves the tabernacle.
For the bodies of those beasts whose blood is brought into the sanctuary by the high
priest for sin are burned without the camp.
So he's referring back to the Old Testament.
You can look in the book of Leviticus and see those things he's referring to.
Of course, often as we've studied through the book of Hebrews, we have found that the
writer regularly goes back to the Old Testament, that which these original recipients would
have been very familiar with.
And then notice in verse number 12, wherefore Jesus also, that he might sanctify the people
with his own blood, suffered without the gate.
Number four, if you're taking notes this morning, the fourth reason to rejoice is for the substitutionary
atonement of the Lord Jesus Christ.
The fact that He went to the cross for you.
He took your place.
He paid a debt that I could never pay.
Amen?
I mean, He took our place.
We can go back and we can think about the text of Scripture that record for us the trial
and the mockings and all that took place when Jesus was going to be led astray to go to
the cross of Calvary.
We understand that the Bible prophesies about the death that Christ would suffer and the
fact that Messiah, the Lord Jesus Christ, when He came that first time, He would come
as that suffering Lamb, if you will, to go to be that Lamb of God that would take away
the sin of the world.
And we find that through the trials, remember, as He's standing there and the accusations
are given, there was another one by the name of Barabbas.
And Barabbas was rightly imprisoned and Barabbas was going to be put to death.
You'll recall with me that there were three crosses.
There were two for the thieves.
one on either side of the Lord Jesus Christ and that third cross no doubt
would have been for Barabbas if you look through the text of Scripture and you
understand what's going on Barabbas was there and as you look at all that's
going on and Pilate is speaking to the the Jews that are bringing the
accusations and he says I find nothing worthy in this man of death they had
this tradition that they released one at this time and who is it that you'd
like for me to release Jesus or Barabbas what do they say release Barabbas Jesus
crucify him they cry out multiple times and I think about Barabbas I don't know
if you've ever thought about Barabbas but I wonder how much he knew about what
was going to happen and the the fate if you will of his own life and the
punishment for his own crimes but then he was released and Jesus hung upon that
cross he didn't hang on the cross just for Barabbas he hung upon the cross and
shed his precious blood for you and for me and for all of mankind the Bible says
that God hath made him Jesus to be sin for us who knew no sin that we might be
made the righteousness of God in him we think about the substitutionary atonement
the fact that he took our place oh how we ought to rejoice this morning it we
sing about being saved I'm washed in the blood and so thankful at the cross even
as we sang I remember singing that song a number of years ago at the nursing
home there was a man from another country that was there with his wife and
he was fine his wife was not well and we sang that song at the cross and he
in all sincerity and he was steeped in a false world religion and he asked me
this question what is meant by cross at the cross what do you mean by that we
had sung the song and he heard the words but he did not understand see this
morning when we sang at the cross you had an understanding of what we were
singing about you understood that we were singing about that old rugged cross
on which Jesus Christ took your place and my place but this individual had
never even understood what is it that you mean at the cross and I had the
privilege of taking a Bible and sitting with this man and sharing with him what
is meant that the significance of the cross that Jesus Christ God in flesh
hung in shame and shed his precious blood so that you my friend could be
saved I wish I could tell you he trusted Christ he didn't at that moment and we
had future opportunities to continue to plant seed in and water and he never
trusted Christ his wife passed on and he did not stay at the nursing home after
that because he'd been there to visit with his wife but this morning as the
people of God I hope that we would rejoice in the substitutionary atonement
Revelation chapter number five turn over there if you will and Revelation
chapter number five and the scene in heaven that is given to us in Revelation
4 and 5 in particular is just a I mean a majestic scene I mean you begin to read
Revelation 4 and 5 and if that doesn't make you excited I'm not sure that
anything could make you excited and you read about that you read about what
we're going to experience and what heaven is going to be like and the way
in which we're going to rejoice and praise our God forever and ever and he's
worthy of it amen and the Bible tells us here in Revelation chapter number five
in verse number eight when he had taken the book the four beasts and four and
twenty elders fell down before the Lamb having every one of them harps and
golden vials full of odors which are the prayers of saints notice in verse
number nine and they sung a new song saying thou art worthy to take the book
and open the seals thereof for thou was slain and hast redeemed us to God by
thy blood out of every kindred and tongue and people and nation and has
made us unto our God kings and priests and we shall reign on the earth what a
joy as we think about the the song that is being rehearsed here in verse number
nine thou art worthy why for thou was slain and has redeemed us to God by thy
blood what a joy we sing about redemption and we sing about redeemed
how I love to proclaim it redeemed by the blood of the Lamb listen when we
really understand redemption when we really understand what Christ has done
for us we ought to love to proclaim it amen why because the reality is that
when we understand redemption properly that we've been reconciled to God
because of the blood of Jesus Christ that no longer am I going to spend
eternity in the lake of fire but I have a home in heaven I mean that's amazing
it's miraculous what he's done for us and how we ought to rejoice in the the
reality of the substitutionary atonement of the Lord Jesus Christ I
often mention about reading the gospel records of the life and ministry of the
Lord Jesus Christ but as you conclude each of the Gospels you'll read about
the crucifixion the burial and the glorious resurrection I'm so thankful
that he rose conquering sin death in the grave when you read about the
substitutionary atonement when you read about the death of Christ on the cross
of Calvary I wonder how it impacts you wonder how it impacts me I wonder how
much how often it should be a daily occurrence perhaps multiple times in the
day that we thank God for our salvation that we thank God for the substitutionary
atonement because if he didn't go to that cross and pay that price we'd be
hopeless and helpless amen I mean just hopeless but praise God he went to the
cross he paid the price he declared it is finished this morning as we look here
at Hebrews 13 we're reminded of the substitutionary atonement as it tells us
here in verse number 12 wherefore Jesus also that he might sanctify the people
with his own blood suffered without the gate we see in the next few verses this
truth about rejoicing it says let us go forth therefore into him without the
camp bearing his reproach for here we have no continuing city but we seek one
to come by him therefore let us offer the sacrifice of praise to God
continually that is the fruit of our lips giving thanks to his name but to
do good and to communicate forget not for with such sacrifices God is well
pleased it pleases God when we praise his name we find the Bible says in verse
number 15 by him therefore let us offer the sacrifice of praise to God what's
the next word continually right I have it circled in my Bible it's a constant
reminder to me that this is something that were to do continually this is not
something that we do once a year at Thanksgiving right there are some people
that have that idea that oh it's Thanksgiving we need to give thanks no
no as the people of God were to give thanks continually we have so many
reasons to rejoice and I believe that as we look at this chapter and we see these
ten reasons to rejoice and just looking at the first five this morning that it
helps us to understand that we're to give God thanks continually you
understand that as we've looked at these particular truths this morning these
reasons to rejoice spiritual leaders that's something that God has ordained
that God has given the instruction established spiritual leadership we
think about the immutability of Christ is there anything that's going to change
that I mean in its own word it changes not right I mean he's immutable he
changes not so can you not give thanks continually when you think about the
fact that our God changes not he's immutable it doesn't matter what your
circumstances are today or tomorrow or next week or next month there's a reason
to rejoice when we're mindful of the fact that the that our God changes not
that is immutable the third thing that we looked at the Word of God is anything
gonna change it I mean they might try to outlaw it in fact I read just this
past week how that there's some countries over in Europe that have upped
the ante so to speak on hate speech and you preach the Word of God and you're
gonna find yourself in jail in a number of those nations why because they're
they're saying the Bible is hate speech listen this book gives freedom it's sin
that that that bounds us that that binds us remember that Paul said that sin shall
no longer have dominion over you this book frees it gives liberty there are
people that try to outlaw it but can I tell you it's never gonna be outlawed I
mean I don't care what they say they're not gonna change it forever Oh Lord thy
word is settled in heaven amen I mean we got the book that's reason to rejoice no
matter what your circumstances are no matter what your challenges are I'm
rejoicing in the Word of God we find the fourth thing that we're just looking at
now the substitutionary atonement I mean it's a fact it's a reality it happened
Jesus died for you reason to rejoice I mean we think about this idea of
continually I think what happens so often and I know I've said this with
regard to the the truth of Psalm 150 where we are to praise God not only for
the things that he does but for who he is see sometimes I fear that
And even in my own life, but I think generally speaking, we are typically led to give thanks
based strictly upon our circumstances, the things that are going on.
But when we learn to rejoice in who our God is and what He has done, we will never lack
reason to rejoice.
Because though all the difficulties and all of the opposition that we might deal with,
we're looking at some things that are settled.
We're dealing with some principles and some reasons to rejoice that no one can change.
Number five, if you're taking notes, we've looked here that we're to rejoice for spiritual
leaders, we rejoice for the immutability of Christ, for the Word of God, for the substitutionary
atonement, and number five, for our home in heaven.
I'm so thankful for the reality of heaven.
Notice what the Bible says here in verse number 14.
For here, we have no continuing city, but we seek one to come.
Does this not remind you of what we've read earlier in the book of Hebrews?
Remember back in chapter number 11, in verse number 13, when the Bible said these all died
in faith, not having received the promises, but having seen them afar off and were persuaded
of them and embraced them and confessed that they were strangers and pilgrims on the earth.
The Bible talks about the fact that they were looking for a better city, and it says
in verse number 14, for they that say such things declare plainly that they seek a country
for truly, if they had been mindful of that country from whence they came out, they might
have had opportunity to have returned, but now they desire a better country that is in
heavenly, wherefore God is not ashamed to be called their God, for he hath prepared
for them a city.
Here in Hebrews 13, in verse number 14, it says for here we have no continuing city,
but we seek one to come.
You remember as we finished chapter number 12 a couple of Sunday mornings ago and looked
at verses 18 through 29, I titled the message, The Finish Line, and we spoke about the contrast
that is given there in Hebrews chapter number 12 between Mount Sinai and Mount Zion, and
the fact that we have this finish line for the believer, as New Testament believers,
this reality, this certainty of heaven.
I think this morning about our home in heaven, we sing about heaven, and we speak about the
role being called up yonder and when we all get to heaven and those sorts of things, but
daily in our lives do we daily remind ourselves that, listen, this world is not my home.
I'm just a passing through.
I'm a stranger in a pilgrim.
I have a home reserved for me in heaven.
And what a joy that is, how it helps us to keep our eyes upon the Lord Jesus Christ,
understanding our finish line.
Think about what Jesus said to the disciples in Luke chapter number 10.
These disciples had been given instruction in Luke chapter number 10 to go out.
They had been given instruction as they were to leave with regard to the ministry that
they were to be engaged in, and they come back, and they come back returning with joy.
In verse number 17 of Luke chapter number 10 tells us about how they returned.
Verse number 1 tells us about how they were sent.
And then verse number 17 says, and the 70 returned again with joy.
They're rejoicing.
They're returning with joy.
Notice what they said.
Lord, even the devils are subject unto us through thy name.
Why?
Because greater is he that is in you than he that is in the world.
The name of Jesus is a powerful name.
Amen?
We find here that the Bible says, and he said unto them, I beheld Satan as lightning fall
from heaven.
Behold, I give unto you power to tread on serpents and scorpions, and over all the power
of the enemy, and nothing shall by any means hurt you, notwithstanding, and this rejoice
not.
You say, wait a minute.
This is what they're rejoicing in.
And Jesus is giving them an important truth.
He says, rejoice not that the spirits are subject unto you, but rather rejoice.
Why?
Because your names are written in heaven.
Your names are written in heaven.
I see these folks returning with joy.
Now, in your mind, I mean, a group of 70 people, that's a pretty good-sized group of people.
I mean, it's not a huge group, but I mean, 70 that are coming, I mean, you're going to
notice them, right?
And you see these 70, they come and they're rejoicing.
In my mind's eye, my sanctified imagination, I see them coming.
They're not coming like this.
I mean, that's not coming rejoicing, right?
They're coming excited.
They're talking about what they've experienced.
They're talking about what they had just seen, and they're rejoicing.
They come back with joy.
Jesus says, listen, I want you to have joy because your names are written in heaven.
I wonder this morning, how often do we have joy just because we're reminded that our names
are written in heaven, that we have a home in heaven?
I mean, we just live like we're supposed to as Christians, right?
This world's not my home.
People look at you sideways.
They think you're crazy.
I told you about the guy in the bank.
He looked at me, and things were bad.
I can't remember the exact circumstances, but some things had happened in our world
that were really just kind of troubling at that particular moment that week.
He looked at me, and he is just a grumpy old man.
You've met grumpy old men, no doubt, amen?
You know what I mean.
Your mind probably already got an image when I just said grumpy old man, right?
He's just a grumpy old guy.
He's just standing there, and he was just doing his business, and he was just not happy
and very matter of fact.
He kind of looked at me and kind of like, what is this guy doing?
I said, how are you, sir?
I knew he wasn't doing well, and normally, I'm wiser than that.
What do I mean?
Well, normally, I don't like asking people how they're doing when they don't look so
good because I don't need their sob story.
You ever ask somebody how they're doing, and they just kind of dump a big old truck of
problems on you?
You're like, why did I ask him, right?
But I was in the bank.
I wasn't going to be there long.
I said, how are you doing?
He said, how are you?
I said, I'm absolutely wonderful.
That's Mr. Don Curry, by the way.
If you talk to Don Curry, I mean, every single time you ask him how he's doing, in the hospital
bed.
Brother Don, how are you?
I'm absolutely wonderful.
It's encouragement.
That's what he says.
You know.
You've met him.
You've talked to him.
Absolutely wonderful.
And I said, absolutely wonderful.
He said, you're lying.
That's what he said to me.
The man in the bank, he said, you're lying.
I said, I'm not lying.
I mean, that's kind of funny, right?
I'm like, I'm not lying.
He's like, how could you be absolutely wonderful?
I said, because I'm going to heaven.
And he kind of changed his countenance.
He said, you're dying?
Not that I know of, right?
I mean, like a little bit every day, I guess, technically, right?
But like, I don't think I'm dying today.
Like I'm not taking my final withdrawal kind of a situation, you know?
But the reality is that it could have been the day of my death.
You don't know when you're going to die.
I don't know.
And I said, well, I don't think I'm going to die today.
But I might.
But one day, I am going to die.
Because the Lord Jesus Christ took my place on the cross of Calvary, and he made it possible
for me to be redeemed, I placed my faith and trust in the finished work of Christ.
He told me that the gift of God is eternal life through Jesus Christ, our Lord.
And I accepted the gift of God, and I'm going to go to heaven when I die.
And he just looked at me like he had never heard something like that before.
I offered him a gospel tract.
He probably had not.
I think Mark just kind of had that idea.
He probably had not ever heard that.
A lot of people that never heard that truth.
And I offered him a gospel tract, and he took it.
He told me he'd read it.
Never heard from him.
I've never seen the man again.
But what I'm saying to you this morning is that, what if we lived our lives like that
every day?
I'm going to heaven, man.
Listen, I understand there are some days that we all live under the circumstances, right?
I get it.
But these disciples, these 70 that are returning with joy, I wonder if we had joy in our lives
the way they did just because our names are written in heaven.
And I say just because, really, that's an amazing reality, that I'm going to go to heaven
when I die.
I don't know when it's going to be, but I have that hope, that certainty.
Again, it's not a hope like the world would use the word hope.
We often have spoken to people, and if you were to die today, are you 100% sure you'd
go to heaven?
I hope so.
Well, they don't mean it the way we mean it.
We talk about the blessed hope.
I mean, it's an assurance.
It's a certainty.
Why?
Because of what Jesus said.
We find that he said this in John 14, let not your heart be troubled.
You believe in God, believe also in me.
In my Father's house are many mansions.
If it were not so, I would have told you, I go to prepare a place for you.
And if I go and prepare a place for you, I will come again and receive you unto myself,
that where I am, there you may be also.
Man, hallelujah!
I'm going to go to heaven one day.
I mean, this world is not all there is.
Sometimes we live like it, right?
I mean, let's be honest and transparent.
We get so distracted by the things that are going on in our world that sometimes we're
not mindful of the fact that this world's not my home.
I'm going to heaven.
You know what Paul said to the believers in Philippi?
He tells them in Philippians chapter number three that their citizenship, their conversation
is in heaven.
In Philippians 3 and verse number 20, he tells them this, for your conversation is in heaven.
From whence also you look, we look for the...
Savior, the Lord Jesus Christ. My citizenship is in heaven. Remember, the
Lord told us this, we look at it in 2 Corinthians chapter number 5, that we
are ambassadors. What is an ambassador? It's a representative. See, this world is not
my home. I'm in the world, but I'm not of the world. Why? Because I've been saved.
I've been born again. And because I'm in the world, but not of the world, that
makes me an ambassador, and we are to be good ambassadors. We're to be His
representatives, and our citizenship, our conversation, is in heaven. We're seated
in heavenly places. The book of Ephesians deals with that truth. This morning, as we
think about this week of Thanksgiving, in no doubt there are many things you could
give thanks for, but as we look at Hebrews chapter number 13, and examine
the first five of these reasons to rejoice, I hope this morning that you'd
be encouraged when you leave here and say, listen, I know the world's
crazy. Amen? I've seen the things that are out there in the news. The world has
lost its mind. The world's crazy that we live in, but I'm thankful for spiritual
leaders. I'm thankful as we look at Hebrews 13, not only for spiritual
leaders, but I'm thankful for the immutability of Christ. Oh, all the things
around us are changing, but our God's the same, yesterday and today and forever.
The Lord says in Malachi, I am the Lord, I change not. I'm thankful for the Word of
God. It comforts me. Oh, it convicts me, but it comforts me. I'm thankful that I
can just grab my Bible and read it, and just be encouraged. You know, you get a
little bit discouraged, you see the things are going on in the world, you just get
into the Bible. You just read about the plan that God has and how he's revealed
it to us. Meditate upon who he is. I'm thankful this morning for the
substitutionary atonement, that Jesus took my place. The cross reminds us of
that. By the way, the cross is empty. Why? Because he didn't stay on the cross. He
was buried and he rose in victory. He's seated in heaven. He ascended, as Acts
tells us and shows us. And then this morning, I'm thankful for our home in
heaven. This road is not my home, and it's not your home either. The wise man says in
Ecclesiastes that man goes to his long home. Every man goes to his long home.
Eternity, right? Every person's gonna die. As believers this morning, if you've
trusted Christ, you can rejoice that heaven is your home. And this morning, we
got some reasons to rejoice that nobody can change them. There are settled
reasons. We think about all the things that are changing. I say, listen, I'm gonna
rejoice in these things. Next week, we'll look at the next five. Let's pray
together. Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. Thank you for the Word
of God. We've mentioned this morning that that's one of the reasons that is given
here in Hebrews 13 for which we should rejoice, that we have the Word of God. It
establishes our hearts. It's the source of sound doctrine. It's available to us,
and I'm so thankful that we can go to the Word of God this morning. And we can
examine your Word and discover these reasons for which we should rejoice. Our
lips giving praise to your name. Lord, we know that you're pleased with our praise.
And I pray this day that you would help us to rejoice as we should, to praise you
as we should, to know that you're worthy as we travel this earth, as we think
about the chaos and the confusion. I pray, God, that you'd help us to have a joy
unspeakable, full of glory. Help us to rejoice greatly. The joy of the Lord is
our strength. I pray, God, that you'd help us to choose to focus upon these reasons
that no man can change. And help us to rejoice greatly. I pray, God, that you'd
bless the time of invitation, that you'd help us to make decisions, to be more
mindful of praising you and rejoicing in these things that you've done for us and
provided for us. God, if there's one present on our property or watching via
livestream that they do not know you as personal Lord and Savior, this truth of
the substitutionary atonement, they've never understood how that you took their
place. You suffered and bled and died, buried and rose in victory so that we
could be redeemed, reconciled to God. If there's one in that condition this
morning, I pray that today would be the day of their salvation. Lord, I pray that
the Holy Spirit of God would work as only he can, that we'd be doers of the
Word and not hearers only. I pray that you'd bless the time for us in Christ's name, we pray.
Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed. Kimberly's gonna play
quietly on the piano and as she does, the altar is open. Maybe this morning you
just need to get along with God and thank him for some of these very things
that we looked at. Maybe there's some other things that God's impressed upon
your heart that you just want to thank him for. As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.