And I know if you looked at the bulletin,
you said, that's not what the bulletin says.
It says Nehemiah.
And I was planning to preach a message
from the book of Nehemiah.
And I think maybe if the Lord would allow,
I'll preach that message next week,
but God just didn't give me a piece about it yesterday
and led me in a different direction.
And so I trust to be a blessing to you this morning.
Acts chapter number 13,
I've titled the message simply this this morning,
why missions?
Why missions?
And on occasion, I've been asked that question,
why missions?
I think that some have inquired
simply because they've never been taught
and they have a genuine interest in learning
and understanding why we would place
an emphasis upon missions.
Others, I believe they are interested in understanding
perhaps a philosophy or a perspective
and their inquiry with this question,
why missions really would lead to an evaluation personally
on why it is that we have such an emphasis upon missions.
It has been said, people have said this in the past,
that missions is the heartbeat of God.
I like that statement.
God is interested in reaching people
with the gospel of Jesus Christ.
We understand that He's given us a mandate.
He's given us a responsibility
to preach the gospel to every creature.
Why?
Because He desires for human beings
to know the way of redemption.
And we understand this morning
that as you study the word of God
throughout the whole of scripture,
you'll find, especially in the Old Testament,
many references to this,
that all the earth may know,
that all the world may know
that there's a God in heaven.
And we find this morning
that as we study the New Testament,
we find the fulfillment of the Old Testament prophecies
in the person of Jesus Christ,
that Jesus Christ came,
He lived a perfect and sinless life.
He went to that cruel cross.
He was buried and He rose,
conquering sin, death, and the grave.
He ascended to heaven.
He lives forevermore.
He's coming again.
And He's given us a responsibility
that while we're here,
we tell somebody about Jesus.
And we find that as we answer this question,
why missions?
Some have said that missions is the heartbeat of God.
And I like that statement.
Others have made this statement
that missions is the lifeline of the church.
And I like that as well
because the church must place an emphasis
upon what God has given us to do.
We must take seriously the responsibility
that God has given us.
Some have asked it this way.
Why is it that we'd have a missions conference?
Why is it that we'd have missionaries come
and present like we have this morning?
Why is it that families like the Hector family
and like the Ballou family
that we heard an update on this morning
that they too are on the road of deputation
seeking to raise support?
Why would someone sell their house?
Why would they live in a camp trailer
and travel the country?
Why would they go from church to church
to raise support,
to share the call that God has placed upon their lives,
to fulfill a call that God has given them?
Why would they do that?
Some have asked this.
Why is it that we would give of our personal finances
to support missions?
We begin to ask several of these types of questions
and I believe the list of questions could go on and on,
but you get the point this morning.
And as we think about answering this question,
why missions?
I'll give you three thoughts this morning,
but the reality is that the list could be far greater
than just three thoughts that I'll give you this morning.
But I want you to fix your attention
for just a few moments here in Acts 13,
and then we'll be in a number of passages this morning
as we answer this question, why missions?
In Acts chapter number 13,
we really are breeding of the church in Antioch here
in the first missionary journey.
And we see what God is doing and how God is working.
Of course, we know that the Lord Jesus Christ
gave the command with regard
as we often refer to it as the Great Commission.
He spelled it out very plainly in Acts 1 in verse number 8,
that it was to be in Jerusalem and all Judea, Samaria,
and the uttermost part of the earth of the world.
And we find that it was there not until Acts chapter number 8
Brother Hector mentioned it
in a Sunday school message this morning,
that after the persecution intensified,
they were scattered abroad
and they went everywhere preaching the word they fulfilled.
In fact, if you read Acts chapter number 8,
you begin to read how that they went into Samaria.
Well, that's where God told them to go.
You begin to read there
as you continue through the book of Acts,
how the gospel is going forward.
And of course, this first missionary journey
in Acts chapter number 13 is recorded for us.
There are a couple of more in the book of Acts,
but I wanna focus our attention here
for just a few moments on these five verses
and answering this question, why missions?
Notice the Bible says in verse number one of Acts 13,
now there were in the church that was at Antioch
certain prophets and teachers as Barnabas and Simeon
that was called Niger and Lucius of Cyrene and Manan,
which had been brought up with Herod the Tetrarch and Saul.
So we find right away in verse number one,
that there's a local church in Antioch,
praise God for the local church.
And this local church was doing
what God had called them to do.
We find there were there, they were gathered,
there were prophets and teachers,
they're teaching the word of God.
The Bible says in verse number two,
as they ministered to the Lord
and what a blessing to serve God,
what a joy and privilege it is to serve our master,
the King of Kings and Lord of Lords.
They were serving, they were ministering,
the Bible says and fasted.
Notice in verse number two,
the Holy Spirit, the Holy Ghost said,
separate me Barnabas and Saul for the work
run to I have called them.
So we find that Saul, of course,
his name during this particular journey will change to Paul
and we begin to see how that God has called,
he's placed a specific call
upon the lives of Paul and Barnabas.
And in the Holy Ghost, the Spirit of God says,
separate me for what purpose?
For the work where unto I have called them.
The Hector family is doing what they're doing
because God has called them.
The Ballou family is doing what they're doing
We could go through the list of all of the missionaries
that God has privileged us to partner with
and they're doing what they're doing
because God has placed a call upon their lives.
It's not good enough if mom and dad were to say,
hey, I think you should do this
or if the pastor were to stand up and say,
I think you should do this.
The reality is that God Almighty calls people
to serve him in this capacity
and God makes it clear that he's called them.
Notice it says, and when they had fasted and prayed
and laid their hands on them,
notice this, it says, they sent them away.
The church in Antioch, the body of believers
at this local church, they send Paul and Barnabas
to fulfill the mission that God had given them.
We find that it says, so they, verse number four,
being sent forth by the Holy Ghost,
departed from Solution, from thence they sailed to Cyprus.
And that when they were at Salamis, notice this,
they preached the Word of God.
We just heard from Brother Hector.
You're not going there for politics
or for any other purpose.
He's going there because of a person.
That person is Jesus Christ
and he's going to preach the Word of God,
to preach the Gospel.
Why?
For it's the Gospel that's the power of God
unto salvation, amen?
It's the Gospel that we've been called to proclaim.
And we understand that Paul says this
unto the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God
in 1 Corinthians 15, the Gospel is this,
the death, burial, and glorious resurrection
of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ,
that he did all of this according to the Scriptures.
That's what the Bible says in 1 Corinthians 15.
And I'm so thankful for the Gospel.
I'm thankful that someone gave me the Gospel
and I'm thankful that we have the privilege
of giving the Gospel to someone else.
In fact, just this week, I was at a meeting on Thursday,
but on Tuesday, I received a phone call
from a man that pastors here
in the Commonwealth of Virginia.
And he pastors in a place called Snowville
in the middle of nowhere, down past Roanoke.
And he's in a little, little place,
but he is the father of Sarah Wagar
that was here back in August visiting with us,
the Wagar family, and they're missionaries in Micronesia.
And she called and said,
hey, dad, we're at this church up in Northern Virginia
and guess who the pastor is?
He's Chris Mann.
And he says, Chris Mann, I know that name.
Well, that man is Tony Hart
and he was a member of the church back in 1992
where my dad got saved down in Jacksonville, North Carolina.
And he and his family spent 10 years in Spain
and now he's pastoring here in Virginia.
And not only did I get to talk to him
on the phone on Tuesday,
but I got to see him at a meeting on Thursday
that we were both in attendance for.
And I got to sit next to him and chat with him
and just kind of rejoice in what God is doing.
And he looks at me, now Tony is just kind of a small guy.
He's a short fella and very trim.
And he says, man, last time I saw you,
I don't think you were much bigger than I am.
And man, it's so exciting to see how God works.
Listen, God uses the gospel to change lives.
He said, I never would have imagined,
I never would have thought that you were pastoring a church,
that you're serving the Lord, but that's how God works.
Because someone shared the gospel, amen?
And the gospel has the power to change lives.
And so we see that the Bible says in verse number five,
they preach the word of God.
in the synagogues of the Jews,
and they had also John to their minister."
We will not take the time to read
the entirety of chapter 13 and 14,
but we find that it's in these chapters
that we read about the ministry there,
that first missionary journey.
If you read the book of Galatians,
you will find that the book of Galatians,
unlike some of the other books in the Scriptures,
it will say that it's written
unto the churches of Galatia.
Why has it said that?
Because it was the region of Galatia
where this first missionary journey took place,
and there were multiple churches that were planted.
As you would look through chapter 13 and 14,
you'll read that they went to Antioch and Pisidia,
Iconium, Lystra, and Derbe.
And in each of those places,
there were churches established, by the way.
In each of those places,
Paul and Barnabas were chased out of town
because they didn't like there were some
that were in opposition to the work of God.
Opposition is nothing new.
There are people that oppose the Gospel.
And people that oppose the work of God.
It's so exciting as you go to the end of chapter number 14
that you get to this portion of Scripture
and you find the Bible tells us in verse number 26,
and then sailed to Antioch.
That's where we found them in the beginning of Acts,
chapter number 13, they're in Antioch.
And now at the end of chapter number 14,
they sail back to Antioch.
Notice it says from whence they had been recommended
to the grace of God.
Notice this phrase, for the work which they fulfilled.
Isn't it exciting to hear about people fulfilling
what God has given them to do?
And then it says this in verse 27,
and when they were come and had gathered
the church together,
they rehearsed all that God had done with them
and how He had opened the door of faith unto the Gentiles
and there they abode long time with the disciples.
I often have referred to this portion of Scripture
at the end of Acts 14 as the first missions conference.
It's the first missionary journey
and now it's the first missions conference
where they come back and they report on the work.
By the way, I think the people at the church in Antioch
were interested in hearing what God had done.
Why?
They were invested, they were praying for
these missionaries that were sent out from them.
So we read Acts 13 and we understand
that when we begin to think about this question,
why missions, we would understand that missions is biblical.
Missions is not the idea of some of the,
you'll read about some of the missionaries
and their father of modern missions and what have you.
Some people will give those terminologies or those titles
to some of these great men of God that served a great God
that fulfilled what God had called them to do.
But I want you to understand this morning
that missions is God's idea.
Just like the local church is God's idea,
man did not sit around and say,
you know, I think we should have this thing
called the church.
It is God that instituted the church.
It is God that has instructed the church
and we find that he's given the mandate
that the church is to reach the world and he uses missions.
So why is it that we'd have missions?
Let me give you three thoughts this morning
on answering this question, why missions?
Number one, because of the command of our Lord.
Understand this morning that this must be our primary reason.
The primary reason that we would give to,
that we would support missions,
that we would have missions conferences
and support missionaries and what have you,
the primary reason is out of obedience
to the command of our Lord.
We understand that this is primary.
We understand that if we get our eyes off of the fact
that we're seeking to obey the command,
that the secondary reasons will fail
to continue to motivate us
because it must be that we have our eyes on Jesus
and that we understand that we're doing this
because of the command of our Lord.
I've knocked on doors before
because God has commanded us to do so
and people weren't so excited to see you there.
If I'm doing it because I think
there's gonna be a warm reception,
after just a little while I'll stop doing it.
But the reality is that when we're mindful of the command,
listen to what Jesus said in Matthew chapter 28.
We're familiar with the Great Commission.
I'll just read it from Matthew chapter 28,
but we find that it's referenced in each of the Gospels
as well as the book of Acts.
In Matthew chapter 28, beginning in verse number 18,
Jesus, after His resurrection, He says this.
Beginning in verse number 18 of Matthew 28,
and Jesus came and spake unto them saying,
all power is given unto me in heaven and in earth.
Isn't that encouraging?
We serve the Lord God Almighty.
He is the omnipotent God.
He has all power.
And then He says this,
go ye therefore and teach all nations,
baptizing them in the name of the Father
and of the Son and of the Holy Ghost,
teaching them to observe all things
whatsoever I have commanded you.
And lo, I am with you always,
even unto the end of the world.
Amen.
What a blessing to know the command that God has given.
And what a blessing it is that as we read this command
that He tells us really as bookends to the command
that He has all power.
And then He says, I'll be with you.
And that's encouraging.
That helps us to understand
that we're not going in our own power, our own might,
but we're going in the power of God Almighty.
And we find here that He gives us this promise
and He gives us this command.
And we understand that obedience is necessary.
The Bible tells us this,
as we would think about this command of our Lord,
it is a matter of obedience.
And Jesus said this in John 14 and verse number 15,
if you love me, keep my commandments.
And so we answer the question, why missions?
We must first acknowledge the command of our Lord.
And we must understand that this is our primary reason
and that it is a matter of obedience.
Paul says this in 2 Corinthians 5 and verse number 20,
that we are His ambassadors.
We find that the disciples will stand up
and they'll make it known that we are His disciples.
We are His witnesses.
And we understand this morning
that we have the command of the Lord.
And not only is it a command
that must be obeyed, a matter of obedience,
but I want you to think about it this way as well.
It is a matter of opportunity.
You know, it's an opportunity that we have
to obey the command that Christ has given.
And I think about the opportunity,
I think about the privilege that is ours.
And I want you to notice what Paul says
to the believers in Thessalonica
in 1 Thessalonians chapter number two.
And it's in this passage of scripture,
God leads Paul to word this in a certain way
that I think is so encouraging
when we think about the opportunity
that is before us to obey the Lord.
And this morning, when we think about this truth
and we think about the benefit that we have
of having the word of God
and how thankful we are for God's word,
but the reality is that He has given us
the word of God to be obeyed.
We're told in 1 Thessalonians 2,
beginning in verse number one,
for yourselves, brethren, know our entrance in unto you
that it was not in vain.
If you were to go back to Acts 17,
we will not take the time to do that,
but if you were to read the first three verses of Acts 17,
you'll find that God records there
the entrance into the city of Thessalonica.
And it's during this missionary journey
that is Paul and they're going there
and they're ministering.
And he says, you know, brethren,
you're aware of our entrance in unto you
that it was not in vain.
But even after that we had suffered before
and were shamefully entreated,
as you know, at Philippi,
that refers back to Acts 16,
we were bold in our God to speak unto you
the gospel of God with much contention.
I'm thankful for the way in which he tells us
in verse number two that they were bold in our God
to speak unto you the gospel of God with much contention.
You understand that Paul makes the request
specifically to the church at Ephesus
that they would pray that he would have boldness,
that he would speak the word with boldness.
And we find that he says that they were bold.
Notice in verse number three,
for our exhortation was not of deceit,
nor of uncleanness, nor in guile.
Notice how he states this,
but as we were allowed of God
to be put in trust with the gospel,
even so we speak.
Can you think about that just for a moment?
We were allowed of God to be put in trust with the gospel.
Paul says this in 2 Corinthians chapter number four,
that we have this treasure in earthen vessels.
We've been entrusted.
We are responsible.
We're to be good stewards.
That's why Paul says before he ever says
in Romans one and verse 16,
that I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ
for it is the power of God unto salvation.
He says prior to that,
he says not only am I ready,
but he says I am debtor.
I am indebted.
Why?
He understood that he had been entrusted with the gospel.
He was given this opportunity.
He was allowed of God to be entrusted with the gospel.
And then he says, even so we speak,
not as pleasing men,
but God, which triumph our hearts.
You know, there's a number of people that have gone astray
because they try to please men.
A lot of preachers have gone astray
But we have the responsibility to please God.
You ever try to talk to somebody about the gospel
and they don't want to hear it?
Why?
Because the message that you're trying to share with them
isn't pleasing to them.
It's confrontational.
It's contentious.
It's not pleasant.
when you've got to sit down and tell somebody that they're lost because they're sinners
and they're on their way to a Christless eternity in the lake of fire. A lot of people don't
respond well to that. They want you to tickle their ears. They want you to tell them something
that's going to make them feel good and increase self-esteem and so on and so forth. But the
reality is if you don't understand you're lost, you're never going to understand that
you need a Savior. We find that he says that we came not seeking to please men, but to
please God. And God tries the hearts. I want you to think about this as we think about
the church in Thessalonica. It's not a perfect church. There is no perfect church, but the
church in Thessalonica is a model church. It is a good church. And it's from them. If
you were to go back to the first chapter, you would find that the Bible says in verse
number 7 of chapter 1, so that ye were in samples to all that believe in Macedonia
and Achaia, for from you sounded out the word of the Lord, not only in Macedonia and Achaia,
but also in every place your faith to God were to spread abroad, so that we need not
to speak anything. This is missions. They go to Thessalonica in Acts 17 on a missionary
journey and they preach the gospel and people get saved. A church is established and from
that local church, they're preaching the gospel. Really, if you were to read verse
number 8 of 1 Thessalonians 1, it's almost as if Paul is saying, you worked us out of
a job. Because everywhere we went, they'd already heard because you were faithful to
give the truth. Glory to God. Listen, their labor was not in vain. They went. It was a
matter of opportunity. Yes, it's a matter of obedience, but you know, we have opportunity.
How long do opportunities last? Sometimes just that long. Someone said this about opportunities.
They're easier seeing as they pass us by than as they're coming toward us. How many times
we've missed an opportunity? As we have opportunity, Paul uses that phrase actually at the end
of the book of Galatians in chapter 6 and verse 9, he says, and let us not be weary
and well-doing for in due season we shall reap if we faint not. As we have therefore
opportunity, let us do good unto all men, especially unto them who are of the household
of faith. Now, I understand the application here, those that are of the household of faith,
but I want you to ask this question this morning by way of application when we think about
this verse of Scripture when he says, let us do good unto all men. The greatest thing
we can do for anyone is tell them about Jesus. That's the greatest thing we could ever do
is tell them about Jesus. I understand that people are hungry and people need various
things and they have various needs and we get contacted regularly and if we get so focused
on temporal needs and dealing with those temporal situations and never tell them about Jesus,
they're going to die one day and they're going to enter into a Christless eternity. Do good.
The greatest thing I can do for anyone is tell them about Jesus. Number one, why missions?
Because of the command of our Lord. Number two, why missions? Because of the condition
of the lost. Because of the condition of the lost. John chapter 3 and Brother Hector was
in this passage this morning. I'm just going to mention a few things. If you were in Sunday
school you heard him give a lesson. It was a great lesson and really the idea of his
lesson this morning, the title, Fuel for Souls. And then we asked this question, why
missions? And we look at John chapter 3, we find that Jesus is speaking to a religious
man by the name of Nicodemus. He was a Pharisee. He was a ruler of the Jews. The Bible tells
us in verse number one, you find a man that is religious. He knows stuff about God and
there's some people today that have the idea in our world today just knowing about God
is okay. I believe there's a God. It's not enough. The Bible tells us in the book of
James that the devils believe and tremble. When Jesus walked upon the face of the earth,
many times when He encountered those that were demon-possessed, you would find that
those demons would say, have you come to torment us before our time? They knew that He was
the Son of God. It's not enough to just believe mentally. The idea of believing scripturally
when we read about that truth that you're there in John 3, but in John 1 it says, but
as many as received Him to them gave He power to become the sons of God, even to them that
believe on His name. That idea of believing is believing understandingly and receiving
Him as our personal Savior. It's not just a mental exercise of believing that there
is a God. We find that this religious leader, this Pharisee named Nicodemus, he comes to
Jesus by night and Jesus answers him. The question that he asks, he says, we know that
thou art a teacher come from God, for no man can do these miracles that thou doest except
God be with him. And Jesus responded and said, verily, verily, of a truth of a truth I say
unto thee, except a man be born again, he cannot see the kingdom of God. Immediately
what Jesus does is He deals with the condition of Nicodemus. He's lost. He's religious, but
he's lost. And we find that as He deals with the condition, Nicodemus doesn't understand.
He hears this phrase of being born again and he asked a very, really pertinent question.
He says this in verse number 4, how can a man be born when he's old? Can he enter the
second time into his mother's womb and be born? He did not understand what this meant
that you must be born again. And Jesus says in verse number 7, marvel not, well, verse
number 6, that which is born of the flesh is flesh and that which is born of the Spirit
is Spirit. He says in verse number 5, I say unto thee, except a man be born of water and
of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God. Marvel not that I said unto thee,
ye must be born again. Here's what Jesus is saying to Nicodemus. Listen, everyone here
this morning has been born of water. Every single person. Medically speaking, when you
understand physiological birth and so on and so forth, we're born of water. Every one of
us. But some may not have been born again, being born of the Spirit. If you're here this
morning and you're breathing, you're living, you've been born of water. But being born
once isn't enough. Nicodemus was born once, but Jesus said you must be born again. Why?
Because there's a condition that you have and the condition of the lost is that they're
dead in their sins and their trespasses. We're going to look at that in just a moment in
the book of Ephesians. But he says you must be born again. Born of the Spirit. He says
marvel not at this truth. See, Jesus loved Nicodemus enough to tell him the truth. You've
been born of water, but you need to be born of the Spirit, Nicodemus. You need to be born
again. Listen, being born again is not being baptized. There's some churches that teach
that. Being born again is not going through some class and saying some things and giving
some money and going some place. No, no, no. That's not being born again. Being born again
is when we understand that we're lost and that Jesus is the only Savior. And we recognize
that without him we'll spend eternity in the lake of fire and that he loved me so much
that he died for me. And we say we want to receive that free gift, that eternal life
that he offers. And the Bible says that we're born again. The Bible uses the word that we're
quickened. We're made alive. It's exciting to be born again. Listen, if you've only been
born once, you've only been born of the water, you need to be born of the Spirit. You need
to be born again. See, to be born once is to die twice. Because the Bible talks about
physical death. The Bible also talks about spiritual death. We'll look at that in just
a few moments. But to be born twice, being born of the water and being born of the Spirit,
is to die but once, die a physical death. That's the point when a man wants to die.
But after this, the judgment is what the Bible says in the book of Hebrews in the ninth chapter.
So I want you to understand that Jesus is giving Nicodemus the truth. We read that portion
in the beginning, but then the portion that Brother Hector read, verse 15, that whosoever
believeth in him should not perish but have eternal life. Notice verse 16, probably one
of the most commonly known verses in all of the Bible, for God so loved the world that
he gave his only begotten Son, that whosoever believeth in him should not perish but have
everlasting life. You understand that God's greatest attribute is not love. Yes, he loved
the world. The Bible tells us that. But his greatest attribute is holiness. We sang this
morning, holy, holy, holy. Our God is holy. And because He's holy, He's just. And there's
divine judgment. But He loves His creation. He loves humankind. And so He says, I loved
you so much that I sent my Son. See, because there had to be justice. So God so loved the
world that He gave His only begotten Son. What is He speaking of? Well, in verse 14,
He talks about Moses being lifted up in the wilderness, even so must the Son of Man be
lifted up. Jesus would go to the cross of Calvary. And Jesus would be the Lamb that
was slain before the foundation of the world. He would be the sacrifice. And He says that
He gave His only begotten Son that whosoever believeth in Him should not perish but have
everlasting life. Notice what it says in verse 17, for God sent not His Son into the world
to condemn the world, but that the world through Him might be saved. Why? Because we were condemned
already. He says that in verse 18.
He that believeth on him is not condemned,
but he that believeth not is condemned already,
because he hath not believed in the name
of the only begotten Son of God.
And this is the condemnation,
that light has come into the world,
and men love darkness rather than light,
because their deeds were evil.
And so we find here that he's saying, listen,
again, understanding this word believe,
it's not just a mental recognition
that Jesus walked upon the earth, that Jesus is God,
it's receiving him as your personal Savior.
Notice what the Bible says in verse number 36
of John chapter number three.
He that believeth on the Son hath everlasting life,
and he that believeth not the Son shall not see life,
but the wrath of God abideth on him.
Someone wrote a track, I actually believe it was
Dan Hummel that wrote the track,
I know that Beacon sells it, or has it available.
What do I have to do to go to hell?
Nothing.
Because we're already lost.
The condition of the lost.
He that believeth not the Son shall not see life,
why, for the wrath of God abideth on him.
He that believeth not, according to verse number 18,
is condemned already.
Notice in Ephesians chapter number two,
and as you're turning to Ephesians two,
let me just reference a couple of verses
that you're familiar with from the book of Romans.
The book of Romans in chapter three in verses 10 and 23,
the Bible tells us, as it is written,
there is none righteous, no, not one.
None.
You say, well, I'm a pretty good person.
Who are you comparing yourself to?
Your neighbor, co-worker?
The standard is God, His holiness.
The reality is that there's not a man upon the earth
that sinneth not, except for Jesus Christ, who was perfect.
He who knew no sin was made sin for us.
The just for the unjust.
But every single human being is guilty of sin.
It's a universal condition.
And I'm thankful that there's a remedy for that condition.
His name is Jesus.
And we find here that in Ephesians chapter number two,
the Bible says, and you hath He quickened
who were dead in trespasses and sins.
That word quickened is made alive.
I mentioned this just a moment ago
as I referenced this verse of Scripture,
but it says you were dead in trespasses and sins.
Dad, I was rehearsing with Tony what you heard that day
when you were walking through that building
when Kurt Branch said, there are a lot of dead people
in the world that are just waiting to die.
And Brother Tony remembered who Kurt was
and asked me for his contact information.
He said, man, that's a good statement.
I said, yeah, and as soon as my dad heard it,
he said, man, what does that mean?
And my understanding is that that man said
there are a lot of people that are dead spiritually
that are just waiting to die a physical death.
And at that moment, my dad's testimony is right here.
He said, that's me.
I'm dead spiritually,
and I'm just waiting to die a physical death.
He knew just that much of a testimony of a witness.
God used his word.
It says this in verse number two,
wherein in time past you walked
according to the course of this world,
according to the prince of the power of the air,
the spirit that now worketh in the children of disobedience.
Notice what this says, among whom also we all
had our conversation in times past.
Listen, Paul's including himself.
Why?
We all had this condition, the condition of the lost
is that we are sinners separated from God Almighty.
We are dead in our trespasses and sins.
And he says, we all had this conversation in times past
in the lust of our flesh, notice,
fulfilling the desires of the flesh and of the mind.
And we're by nature, the children of wrath, even as others.
And I have in box, I don't have it circled
because I don't do circles real good.
So I got a box around it.
And if I draw circles, I start crossing out words
and then I can't read it from the pulpit
and it gets real messy.
And so I got a square around it.
These words of verse number four, but God,
I'm so thankful for God,
who is rich in mercy is what the Bible tells us
in verse number four.
Notice where it says, for his great love,
wherewith he loved us.
Oh man, I was dead in my trespasses and my sins,
but he quickened me, he made me alive.
I was born again on August 31st, 1997.
I know what my birthday is, just like many of you know
what your birthday is, right?
July 15th, 1980, someone said on Thursday,
just as a side note, it's a rabbit trail,
I'm gonna kill the rabbit.
And here's what the guy said.
He said, man, this happened in 1976
and some of you guys were just toddlers.
I looked back at the guy and said, I wasn't even alive yet.
I'm not gonna be able to say that a whole lot longer.
This guy here, brother Hector, he's only 27.
He started telling me his wife was born
when I graduated high school.
You start feeling old.
And so I got to remember that I'm not that old.
But anyhow, listen, July 15th, 1980
is when I was born of water, physically.
But August 31st, 1997, that's the most important day
because that's when I was born again.
I was born of the Spirit.
Jesus said, you must be born again.
And I thank God for that date.
I thank God that someone told me to remember the date
and to write it down.
And Holly's not here this morning.
Joseph's doing sound, Brianna's over here.
But on August 31st, you know I get a little message
from Holly and from the kids and they say,
happy spiritual birthday.
In fact, Brianna and Juliana just had
their spiritual birthday on Thursday of this past week.
We sent them a text, happy spiritual birthday.
This is when I was born again.
God, who is rich in mercy with his great love,
wherewith he loved us.
Listen, the condition of mankind.
Paul says this in 1 Timothy 1 and verse number 15.
He says, this is a faithful saying
and worthy of all acceptation
that Christ Jesus came into the world
to save sinners of whom I am chief.
You say, well, I'm just gonna try to be a good person.
Well, just a little while later in Ephesians 2,
the Bible tells us you can't be a good person
to get to heaven.
Doesn't work.
Titus 3 tells us it's not by works of our righteousness,
which we have done.
We find that the only payment that's accepted
for our eternal security for salvation through Jesus Christ
is the blood of Jesus Christ.
That's it.
I'm gonna just be a good person.
You can't.
It's not possible.
You can be as good as you think you can be.
And at the end of the day, it's still not accepted.
You say, well, that's not fair.
God is God and he made the rules.
And it's right here in the Bible.
Amen?
And this morning, we understand why missions,
number one and primary, because of the command of the Lord.
Number two, secondary, because of the condition of the lost.
I wanna say this, number three,
because of the coming of our Lord.
You know, Jesus is coming and he's coming soon.
No man knoweth the hour.
I hear regularly people say, in fact,
on Thursday I was at a pastor's meeting
and I heard a number of people use this term
about God tearing his coming.
Listen, Hebrew says that he will not tarry.
He's gonna come right on time.
He knows the time, we don't know the time.
But let me say this, and there's a number of verses
that we could look at.
I'm just gonna look at one passage in Acts 1
in verses eight through 11.
I'm gonna look at this passage
because I think it's so instrumental
on why we read the book of Acts the way that we do.
The impact that this passage of scripture had
on the disciples.
In Acts chapter number one, in verse number eight,
remember they were asking him about whether it was time
that he would set up his kingdom.
He tells them in verse number seven,
it's not for you to know the times or the seasons
which the Father hath put in his own power.
Verse eight, but ye shall receive power
after that the Holy Ghost has come upon you,
and ye shall be witnesses unto me both in Jerusalem
and all Judea and Samaria
and unto the uttermost part of the earth.
And so Jesus makes that statement,
he speaks those words, and the Bible says in verse number nine
and when he, Jesus, had spoken these things,
while they, the disciples, beheld, he was taken up
and a cloud received him out of their sight.
This is the record of the ascension of Jesus Christ.
Now I want you to think about this event
in the lives of the disciples
and how impactful it would be.
That Jesus is there speaking to them,
he'd already gone to the cross of Calvary,
he had been buried and had risen from the dead,
we find that he's been ministering there 40 days,
he's interacted with the disciples,
and now he gives them the great commission
and as he's speaking the words,
he begins to ascend out of their sight.
Man, that's powerful.
It's impactful.
The Bible says, and while they looked steadfastly
toward heaven as he went up,
and I know I've said this before
as I've read this passage of scripture,
but you and I'd be standing there
looking steadfastly toward heaven as well.
Amen?
He was just talking to us
and now he's ascended out of their sight
and you're just standing there
looking steadfastly up into heaven.
And while they were looking steadfastly up into heaven,
the Bible says two men stood by them in white apparel,
these angels, they say this in verse number 11,
Ye men of Galilee, why stand ye gazing up into heaven?
Notice this, this same Jesus,
which has taken up from you into heaven
shall so come in like manner
as ye have seen him go into heaven.
Man, Jesus is coming back.
And we find that the disciples, listen,
they heard Jesus say this during his earthly ministry
in John chapter number 13
after he'd washed the feet of the disciples
and he'd given them instruction,
he gives them the command that they're
love as he loved and we find that he gives them that new commandment their
hearts are troubled after they find out he's gonna go to the cross and he says
let not your heart be troubled you believe in God believe also in me and
John 14 in verse number one he continues in my father's house or many mansions if
it were not so I would have told you I go to prepare a place for you and if I
go and prepare a place for you I will come again and receive you unto myself
that where I am there you may be also and now they heard that from Jesus and
now they hear from the angels that the angels say hey listen this same Jesus
he's coming back what was the last command that they heard Jesus give go
and preach the gospel you know why I think we read the book of Acts the way
that we do because they heard Jesus coming back and Jesus gave him a command
you shall receive power after the Holy Ghost come upon you you shall be
witnesses unto me both in Jerusalem Judea Samaria the uttermost part of the
earth and so we find that you read the book of Acts and you come to the place
as brother Hector mentioned this morning where they turn the world upside
down before it ever says that chapters before it says you have filled Jerusalem
with your doctrine why Jesus is coming back I want to do
what he's calling me to do I want to fulfill I want to be obedient to the
command that he's given me and we find that we read the book of Acts and now
we're nearly 2,000 years past the writing of Acts chapter number one and
we find that the truth is still today that Jesus is coming back and I want
you to think about this when you think about the the rapture of the church
listen the the James 5 tells us that that the reality is that the coming of
the Lord draweth nigh James 3 excuse me 2nd Peter 3 and verse number 9 says hey
listen those of you that are saying where's the promises of his coming
listen the Lord is not slack concerning his promise but he's long-suffering to
us were not willing than any should perish but that all should come to
repentance and we find that at the time I want you to consider this very quickly
this morning that when the rapture of the church takes place I want you to
think about what happens and I can't go through all of the eschatology of what
happens but I just want to give you a couple of thoughts number one we're out
of here amen the church the bride of Christ is
removed if you read first Thessalonians 4 verses 16 and 18 specifically you find
that the Bible tells us of the rapture of the church we are caught up to ever
be with the Lord that only causes to rejoice greatly but immediately upon the
rapture of the church not only is the church removed but that's the start of
the seven-year tribulation period we don't have time to get into all of it
this morning but I want you to understand that at the start of that
seven-year tribulation that there are many things that are going to happen we
find that the book of Revelation reveals to us about the hundred and forty-four
thousand that will proclaim the truth the Bible reveals to us about the two
witnesses that will proclaim the truth and we know that there are people that
will be saved during the tribulation but as you understand and you interpret
scripture with scripture you will find that primarily Jesus is dealing with
the Jewish people the state of Israel during the tribulation his church is
removed and here's what the Bible tells us the lost people who rejected the Lord
Jesus Christ will remain upon this earth at the rapture the church is removed if
you've heard the gospel if you've never trusted Jesus Christ as your personal
Savior you will be left there's a popular I've never seen it I've never
read it but there's a popular series called left behind and it deals with a
lot of that stuff again I've never read it or watched any of it but the reality
is that people will be left behind and here's the reality from second
Thessalonians 2 is that those people that heard the gospel and rejected they
will believe a lie and they will not be saved you say all I'll deal with that
later first of all you never know when you're gonna die second of all you never
know when Jesus is coming back he come back today he can biblically speaking he
could come back today there's no other prophecy that has to be fulfilled before
Jesus returns come back today let me read to you a second Thessalonians 2
second Thessalonians chapter number two I want to read these verses to you and
it's so sobering the Bible says this in verse 10 and with all deceivableness of
upright and unrighteousness excuse me in them that perish because they receive
not the love of the truth that they might be saved and for this cause God
shall send them strong delusion that they should believe a lie that they all
might be damned who believed not the truth but had pleasure in unrighteousness
believe not the truth what is truth Jesus is truth he said I'm the way the
truth in the life the Word of God is truth he's given us truth the gospel is
truth we find this morning the coming of the Lord draweth nigh listen I don't
know the hour or the day but why missions because there's a world that
needs to hear the gospel there are people that the population the world is
nearing what 8 billion people now there are people that have never heard the
name of Jesus they've never heard the message that we proclaim our brothers
going to a place there in Guatemala where there's over 80,000 people in the
best that they know there's no gospel preaching church a land of 17 million
people with seven church planters do the math that's all I mean you got to
reach 2.7 million people each Jesus coming back listen our lives are short
James said this way what is your life it's but a vapor that appears for a
little time and then vanishes away the wise men of the book of Proverbs in
chapter 27 and verse number one he gives the council to boast not thyself of
tomorrow why we know not what's on tomorrow and then I want to remind you
what Paul said in 2nd Corinthians 6 and verse number 2 what a great verse of
Scripture and 2nd Corinthians 6 and verse number 2 we think about this
truth of why missions and we think about the coming of the Lord Paul says for he
saith I have heard thee in a time except in the day of salvation of I suckered
they behold now is the accepted time behold now is the day of salvation
there's no time to delay listen this family the Hector family they want to
get to Guatemala you heard him in Sunday school those of you that are here and
they want to get to Guatemala why they want to do what God's calling to do
they're on deputation and God will develop them and teach them lessons
during deputation that they would not be able to learn otherwise they'll have the
opportunity to minister to people that they would not have been able to
minister to otherwise our church being one of that groups of people why do we
place an emphasis on missions why do we have every week brother Michael comes on
Sunday morning and gives a missions update why do we take the time to put
three missionary updates on the back of our prayer bulletin every week why do we
invest our dollars personally as a church to missions because of the
command of the Lord because of God's command primary he said if you love me
keep my commandments it's a matter of obedience but it's also a matter of
opportunity we have opportunity with the freedom to do it right now why
because of the condition of the lost we don't have time this morning to read
Revelation 20 verses 11 through 15 but it records for us the great white throne
judgment my opinion it's probably the saddest verses of all the Bible because
the Bible concludes in verse 15 and says they were cast in a lake of fire this is
the second death and whosoever is not found written in the book of life they
were cast in a lake of fire this is the second death and it's sad they say how
do I get my name in the book we can read through the scriptures about references
in the book of Philippians in the book of Luke about the book our names are
written in heaven through accepting the Lord Jesus Christ as our personal Savior
a songwriter said there's a new name written down in glory and it's mine oh
yes it's mine right that's what the songwriter said this morning first and
primary the command of the Lord second the condition of the lost number three
the coming of the Lord listen Jesus is coming soon we can do everything we can
to obey the command that he's given and that we'd serve God like they did in the
book of Acts with a motivation to please our God understanding that we've
been allowed of God to be entrusted with the gospel what a privilege let's pray
together father we love you how we thank you for loving us this morning the
message why missions primarily to a saved person but God I understand this
morning that there may be someone here someone that's tuned in via live stream
that's never trusted Jesus Christ as their personal Savior they've never been
born again oh they're alive they were born once they were born of the water
they've never understood this truth that we're dealing with this morning you must
be born again and God I pray that if there's one Lord
lost, that you would convict them of their sin, of Christ's righteousness, of judgment
to come.
They'd understand that today is the day of salvation.
They would get it settled.
They would accept that free gift.
The Bible says the wages of sin is death, but the gift of God is eternal life through
Jesus Christ our Lord.
Oh, that they'd receive the gift, they'd be saved.
Father, I pray for every child of God.
Lord, I pray that you'd help us to understand why missions.
Why should we go?
Why should we pray?
Why should we give?
Why should we cross the street to be a missionary, to tell someone about Jesus?
Help us to be aware of and live daily with the truth of your command.
Understanding is the primary reason.
Help us to be mindful of the condition of the lost.
Lord, help us to recognize that soon you are coming.
Once you come, once the rapture of the church takes place, no longer will we have an opportunity
to share the gospel with anyone.
For all that will be there will be there because their names are written in the book.
When the role was called up yonder, the songwriter said, I will be there.
He had confidence, certainty, because he had trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as his personal
Savior.
He'd been born again.
Oh, God, I thank you for the privilege that we have to have a small part in missions,
to be involved in what you're doing globally.
I thank you for the Hector family who surrendered to the call that you've placed upon their
lives.
And God, I pray that you'd use them mightily.
I pray that you'd move and work in these few moments of invitation.
Lord, that we would be responsive to your spirit this day.
And we'll thank you for every decision that's made, for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Amen.