and this is message number two,
and we are, Lord willing, gonna get through
verses four through eight this evening.
Revelation one, verses four through eight.
I'm gonna read the passage of scripture,
dig right in this evening.
The Bible says, beginning in Revelation one,
in verse number four,
John to the seven churches which are in Asia,
grace be unto you and peace from him which is
and which was and which is to come,
and from the seven spirits which are before his throne,
and from Jesus Christ who is the faithful witness
and the first begotten of the dead
and the prince of the kings of the earth,
unto him that loved us and washed us
from our sins in his own blood,
and hath made us kings and priests unto God and his Father,
to him be glory and dominion forever and ever, amen.
Behold, he cometh with clouds,
and every eye shall see him,
and they also which pierced him,
and all kindreds of the earth shall wail because of him,
even so, amen.
I am Alpha and Omega,
the beginning and the ending,
saith the Lord which is and which was
and which is to come, the Almighty.
This evening I've titled the message,
Get Your Eyes on Jesus,
and I want you to remember,
as I mentioned last week by way of introduction,
that the original recipients of this book of Revelation
were facing great adversity and persecution.
Domitian was the ruthless emperor,
and those that refused to worship him,
remember he gave that decree,
he claimed that he was to be worshiped as Lord and as God,
and we find that those that refused to bow to him,
they faced really grave consequences,
and we find that in the midst of that setting,
in the midst of all the turmoil
and the persecution and the difficulty,
I want you to notice that as we begin in verse number four,
the Bible says, John to the seven churches which are in Asia,
notice this, it's a familiar greeting
that's penned throughout the New Testament,
grace be unto you and peace.
This is so important that we understand
at the very onset of this particular study
and understanding that in the midst of great difficulty,
of great adversity and persecution,
that the Lord sends this message to his people
about grace and about peace.
It's very interesting when you consider
the content of the book of Revelation,
it's a book that really is full of judgment,
it's a book that's full of turmoil,
but yet we find here on the beginning
of this entrance into this book,
he says grace and peace.
I want you to be mindful this evening
and rejoice in the fact that in the midst
of all that is going on around us,
that we have been given the grace of God.
The grace of God, we sing Amazing Grace,
I know it's Mr. Don's favorite song
and we think about that wonderful song Amazing Grace
and Paul mentions how that God's grace
is abundant and it is and we understand
that I am what I am by the grace of God
and we have been given grace.
By the way, I'm thankful that the Bible tells us
that our God is a gracious God.
Not only has he given us grace,
but we find in the verse it says and peace.
Again, in the midst of great turmoil and difficulty,
adversity and all that's going on,
we find that he grabs our attention
and speaks of these two attributes, grace and peace.
I'm thankful in the midst of turmoil,
we can have the peace of God,
which passeth all understanding.
In the midst of facing a ruthless,
just wicked ruler, these people,
the original recipients, they could be mindful
of the fact that God has extended grace,
right, grace is saved through faith
and God's been gracious to us
and we find that they also can be reminded
of the peace that God gives.
I mentioned this morning in John 14 in verse 27
that Jesus said, my peace give I unto thee.
I'm thankful that it's his peace.
I'm thankful that it's a perfect peace
and it's a peace that passeth all understanding.
It's interesting as we look at these few verses
of scripture this evening, I really appreciate
the opening passage because I believe
it grabs our attention and it presses us
to get our focus off of our circumstances
and to get our eyes on Jesus.
It's amazing when you begin reading this book
and you notice in these first few verses,
of course we studied verses one through three last week,
but verses four through eight and how still
in the introduction really of this book
that the reader, the recipient of this book
is really implored to get your eyes on Jesus.
It's really easy for us at times
to live under the circumstances.
It's really easy for us to get overwhelmed
with all the things going on in our world
and going on around us and the troubles
and the trials and the difficulties that we face,
but the reality is that we need to get the same message
that these recipients received and that God has preserved
so that we would receive it again this evening as well
and that is to get our eyes on Jesus.
I'm thankful that he's the author
and the finisher of our faith.
We find in the text of scriptures,
we deal with the subject of get your eyes on Jesus.
If you're taking notes, number one,
I want you to recognize his person.
Recognize his person.
There's no doubt as we read these verses of scripture
that the Trinity is in full view.
We find that the text of scripture,
as we mentioned last week in verse number one,
it's the revelation of Jesus Christ
and we find that as we look at these few verses
of scripture that yes, the Trinity is in view
and I'm thankful for the truth
and the teaching of the Trinity.
However, we see this portrait, if you will,
of our Lord and Savior, the Lord Jesus Christ
and we begin to see some things with regard to who he is
and we get our eyes on who he is,
we find that he is eternal.
The Bible says here in verse number four
and again in verse number eight
and really verse number four is referencing the Father
if you're going to track the Trinity aspect
of what's being spoken of here
and verse four is speaking of the Father
and it says, from him which is and which was
and which is to come.
We find though that in verse number eight,
when it's speaking about Jesus,
he says, I am Alpha and Omega,
the beginning and the ending, sayeth the Lord,
which is and which was and which is to come, the Almighty.
I'm thankful that our God is eternal.
I'm thankful that he is, he was and he is to come.
I'm thankful this evening that John, of course,
as he's writing, as the human penman writing this book,
he was extremely familiar with the eternality
of Jesus Christ.
In John chapter number one, we're reminded
of what John penned in the Gospel of John.
In John chapter number one,
we know that the Bible says in the beginning
was the Word and the Word was with God
and the Word was God.
He tells us in verse number 14
that the Word became flesh and dwelt among us.
But I want you to notice specifically
that in verse number 15, John the Baptist is speaking
and it says that John bear witness of him
and cried saying, here's what John the Baptist said,
this was he of whom I spake, speaking of Jesus,
who that cometh after me is preferred before me, why?
For he was before me.
Now, if you understand the scriptures,
you understand that John the Baptist is older physically.
He was born first and then Jesus was born.
But John the Baptist is able to say in verse number 15
that he was before me, why?
Because he's eternal.
We find that in verse number 30 of John chapter number one,
this reference is made again.
This is he of whom I said, after me cometh a man
which is preferred before me, for he was before me.
But then I want you to notice in John 17
John is recording this prayer of the Lord in John 17.
No doubt there are times in which people reference
this phraseology, the Lord's Prayer,
and they really are referencing the model prayer.
When the disciple said, Lord, teach us to pray
and Jesus said, here's how you pray.
Our Father, which art in heaven, hallowed be thy name.
That's the model prayer.
That's not the Lord's Prayer.
Really, John 17 is the Lord's Prayer.
We find that in John 17, Jesus knowing
that his hour was come and he's praying.
And it says in verse number one, it says,
these words spake Jesus and lifted up his eyes to heaven.
And he said, Father, the hour has come.
Glorify thy son that thy son also may glorify thee.
Look at verse number five with me, if you will.
It says this, and now, O Father, glorify thou me
with thine own self, with the glory which I had with thee
before the world was.
So as we begin looking at the book of Revelation
and we're seeing the revelation of Jesus Christ
and we find that we're to recognize his person
and understand who he is, he reveals to us
the eternality of himself, the fact that he has
no beginning and no ending.
He says in verse eight, I am Alpha and Omega.
He says, I am he that was and is and is to come.
And what a joy.
I want you to notice number two,
when you consider recognizing his person,
I want you to notice that he's faithful.
He's faithful.
Look at verse number five.
The Bible says I'm from Jesus Christ,
who is the faithful witness.
Let me say this just very briefly
as a interruption in thought.
If you look at the end of verse number four
and from the seven spirits which are before his throne,
that's where you see the Holy Spirit reference.
As I mentioned, the Trinity is in view.
When we begin to think about verse number five
and Jesus is referred to.
being the faithful witness.
I'm thankful that Paul declares it this way
in 1 Corinthians 1 and verse number nine
by simply saying God is faithful.
I'm thankful for Paul as he's writing to the church
in Thessalonica in 1 Thessalonians 5 and verse number 24.
He says faithful is he that calleth you
who also will do it.
I'm thankful this evening that our God is faithful.
One of the songs that we sang on Friday evening
at the memorial service for Alexis' mom,
Ms. Susan was Great is Thy Faithfulness.
And I know that every time we kind of go around
and have opportunity for favorites
and we have on Mother's Day the ladies get to pick a song
and on Father's Day the men get to pick a song
and then on our prayer, praise and pie
we'll sing a whole lot of songs
and every once in a while
we'll have other times of favorites
and it just seems to me that almost every single time
Great is Thy Faithfulness is one of the songs
that is requested by someone from our congregation.
Why?
Because our God is faithful.
Our God is faithful and he is true.
We find that in Revelation 19 and verse number 11,
notice with me the way that this is articulated here.
This is when Christ comes back to earth
and we'll reference this in just a few moments again.
But it says in verse number 11 of Revelation 19,
and I saw heaven opened and behold a white horse
and he that sat upon him was called what?
Faithful and true and in righteousness
he doth judge and make war.
I'm so thankful that our God is faithful.
He's trustworthy, he's dependable,
he's never failed, he never will.
I'm thankful this evening that his faithfulness
is not dependent on my faithfulness.
Aren't you thankful for that?
You know why?
There've been times that we have, I have failed the Lord
but I'm thankful that he never fails.
He's faithful, he's faithful.
And here in verse number five it says
and from Jesus Christ who is the faithful witness.
We find also as we consider his person this evening
that in verse number eight we are revealed
that he says at the end of the verse
that he is the almighty.
I want you to think about the name
that he ascribes to himself here
at the end of verse number eight.
He says that I am Alpha and Omega.
He's the beginning and the ending.
He says which is and which was
and which is to come the almighty.
Omnipotent, ruler of everything.
That's what it means, that's what it means.
I'm reminded of the truth in Genesis chapter 17
when Abram has a visit from the Lord
and we find that God reveals himself to Abraham
as being El Shaddai is the Hebrew word, the name of God
and it means that he is the almighty one.
I'm thankful that our God is the almighty God.
He has all power.
There is nothing that's outside of his control.
We spoke of that some this morning
at the end of the message
and we find here again as we begin to think
about the people that are being written to originally
but then we understand that throughout church history
that as God has chosen to providentially preserve this book
and to allow us tonight to have the book of Revelation
that we need to get our eyes on Jesus
and we need to see who he is.
We need to understand that our God is eternal,
that he is outside of time,
that he knows the end from the beginning,
that he is faithful,
that he always does what he says he will do.
We can trust him.
I made this statement a few times this morning.
We are either gonna believe God or we're not.
We ought to believe him, he's faithful
and then we see that he is almighty.
Aren't you thankful that you know who he is?
I mean in just a few verses of scripture
all of a sudden if our attention is drawn to Jesus
and recognizing his person,
we're reminded about that peace
that he spoke of in verse number four
and we're reminded of the fact
that really it's gracious of God to reveal his person to us.
I'm thankful this evening
that I don't have to try to figure out God on my own.
that I don't have to rely on my own resources.
I don't have to go and try to figure out
who God is, God has given me a book
and in this precious book he has told me who he is.
There's a lot of people that don't know who God is
because they're trying to define God outside of the Bible.
We find that here this evening when we see him exalted,
when we get our eyes on Jesus,
we remember his person,
all of a sudden we're focused on who he is
and our attention is not so much on the circumstances
and the difficulties in which we're facing.
We see number one this evening, recognize his person,
number two, remember his passion.
In verses five and six,
we find that the Lord gives us truth
with regard to his passion, his work.
In verse number five,
his death and resurrection are clearly seen
and in verse number five the Bible says,
and from Jesus Christ who is the faithful witness,
notice in the first begotten of the dead
and the prince of the kings of the earth,
we find that as we look here
and see that the Bible continues in verse five
and says unto him that loved us
and washed us from our sins in his own blood.
So we find that in verse number five
that the death and resurrection of the Lord Jesus Christ
are in clear view and we must remember that.
We must remember what he did for us.
We must understand this evening that he rose from the dead,
conquering sin, death and the grave.
He is alive forevermore.
He makes that declaration later
at the end of chapter number one
and I'm so thankful that I serve a risen savior.
I'm so thankful.
Listen, we're all gonna face death
and we have placed our faith in the one
who has conquered death.
And the Bible tells us in Hebrews chapter number two
that we no longer have to have the fear of death.
Why?
Because our God has conquered death.
Oh death, where is thy sting?
Oh grave, where is thy victory?
But thanks be to God which giveth us the victory
through our Lord Jesus Christ.
First Corinthians 15, you read the whole chapter.
I mean, you see the resurrection in that chapter
like you see it nowhere else in the Bible
in one condensed area and what a joy this evening to know.
But look at the text here.
It says in verse number five at the end,
unto him that loved us.
You know why he went to the cross?
Because he loved us.
The Bible says in John three in verse 16,
a verse that many of us are familiar with.
In fact, it's John again that penned those words
that Jesus spoke to Nicodemus.
Nicodemus comes to Jesus and he says,
we know that you're a ruler, a teacher,
that you have done these things
and I mean, they're convinced of it
and Jesus speaks to him about the need of being born again.
And then we go through the text of scripture
and we come to verse 16, a verse that is so familiar,
so precious, for God so loved the world
that he gave his only begotten son,
that whosoever believeth in him should not perish
but have everlasting life.
Aren't you thankful for that verse of scripture?
For God so loved the world.
We find that in John three in verse 16,
it tells us that precious truth here
in Revelation one in verse five,
it says unto him that loved us.
We're reminded that in John 13 in verse number one,
at the end of the text that Jesus will speak
about loving one another as he loved them.
But he says in John 13 in verse number one,
it says this, having loved his own,
which were in the world, he loved them unto the end.
I'm thankful tonight that there's nothing
that can separate me from the love of God.
I'm thankful for that.
It caused us to rejoice in that.
He loved us, he continues to love us.
Notice in first John, again, as we reference
various passages that God used the apostle John
to pin with the similar subject in first John three
in verse number 16, by the way,
it's an interesting study to see John 316
next to first John 316, for the Bible says
in first John 316, hereby perceive we the love of God.
How is it that we perceive the love of God?
Because he laid down his life for us
and we ought to lay down our lives for the brethren.
He laid down his life for us.
John talks about in John chapter number 10,
Jesus says I am the good shepherd.
And he says that the good shepherd,
what does the good shepherd do?
He gives his life for the sheep.
See, no one's gonna take it from him.
In fact, even while he was on the cross of Calvary,
you understand that the Bible says
that he gave up the ghost.
He gave up the ghost.
He laid his life down as a sacrifice,
as the sacrifice that was required
to pay for my sin and your sin and the sin of the world.
No man takes it from him.
He says in John 10 that he not only
is gonna lay his life down,
but he's gonna take it up again.
He speaks of the resurrection right there
in the same passage of scripture.
And what a joy to know that he did.
Listen, the disciples,
if you read through the gospel accounts
after the announcement of the resurrection,
there's all kinds of confusion.
They run and they're troubled
and they don't know what's going on.
And then they remember,
oh, this is what Jesus was telling us about.
And they remembered.
Listen, this evening,
we have to be reminded of the truth that God loved us.
And his love is what sent him to the cross of,
Calvary, he gave up the ghost,
he willingly laid down his life.
Remember, Pilate was so confused
when they said that he was dead already,
typically because of the circumstances
at that particular time,
and what they did to the thieves
is they broke the legs so that they would die quickly.
They tried to make crucifixion
as long as they possibly could
to make it as torturous,
and also to cause others to be walking a straighter line
because they don't want to end up in that same position.
And we find that Pilate said he's dead already,
yeah, but the Psalms said that no bones would be broken.
The Bible's awesome.
And we find that 1 John 4 and verse number 10,
the Bible says, herein is love,
not that we love God, but that he loved us
and sent his son to be the propitiation for our sins.
This evening, when we begin to remember his passion,
we recognize his person, but we remember his passion,
we remember all that he suffered there at Calvary,
all that he suffered leading up to Calvary,
all that he endured on that cross,
and we understand it's because he loved us.
It's because he loved us.
But then the Bible says this in Revelation 1
and verse number five,
not only unto him that loved us,
but it says, and washed us from our sins in his own blood.
This reveals to us the cleansing work of Calvary,
the fact that we needed to have that blood.
We sang this evening about the blood
and what a great song to start our service this evening,
singing about the blood.
And we find that this evening,
the truth that I prayed that without the shedding of blood,
there's no remission, we have forgiveness,
redemption through his blood, even the forgiveness of sins.
And he washed us from our sins in his own blood.
You know, the reality is that all of us have sinned
and all of us must have the blood applied.
We sing the song, we didn't sing it this evening,
we sing the song, are you washed in the blood?
You know it?
Are you washed in the blood?
It asks questions in the soul, cleansing blood of the lamb.
And every time we sing that song,
at that point right there, I say this, yes, I am.
You say, why do you say that?
Because I want to, amen.
Because the spirit led me to, amen.
Because I am saved by the blood of the lamb.
And when it says, are you washed in the blood
and the soul cleansing blood of the lamb?
I say, yes, I am.
I am saved by the blood of Christ.
By the way, there's no other way to be saved, amen.
It's the only way to be saved.
Are your garments spotless?
Are they white as snow?
Are you washed in the blood of the lamb?
It's a great song.
And we find here that as the book of Revelation
is being given to us in these introductory statements
before the messages even come to the churches in Asia
that we'll read and we'll study the details of them,
we find that he's telling us that these messages,
that these letters are coming from God
and we must get our attention on him.
We must get our eyes on our Lord
and we must understand that he is eternal,
that he is almighty, that he is faithful.
We must understand that he loved us
and that he washed us, he cleansed us.
And then we see in verse number six,
the beginning of the verse, notice what he did.
After we got saved, it says that he hath made us kings
and priests unto God and his father.
You know, that's a privileged position that he gave us.
You know, it's a joy to be said that I'm a child of God.
I'm a child of the king, amen, we sing the song.
And the reality is that I've been adopted, hallelujah.
I'm a child of the king.
And we find this evening the truth
that I'm joint heirs with the Lord Jesus Christ,
that he calls me his son.
Remember John one in verse number 11,
he came to his own, but his own received him not.
But verse number 12, but as many as received him
to them gave he power to become the sons of God,
even to them that believe on his name.
It's a joy.
I think about the Old Testament.
I believe it's 2 Samuel chapter nine, Mephibosheth.
And Mephibosheth was the son of Jonathan
and Mephibosheth was crippled
and Mephibosheth could do nothing for himself.
But David the king, he wanted to show kindness
to the house of Saul, that's what the Bible says.
He wanted to show kindness to the house of Saul.
And he said, is there any yet alive?
And someone told him, there's this one Mephibosheth,
the son of Jonathan down in Lodabar.
He says, call for him.
And Mephibosheth is brought there
because he's crippled and he comes there
and he's concerned.
I believe that he thought,
I believe that he believed he was gonna be killed
because that was so common in the age,
the era in which those events took place.
You know what David says?
I'm gonna make you as one of the king's sons.
You're gonna sit at my table.
I'm gonna give you all the provision.
He gave him land.
And you say, why would he give him land?
The man is crippled.
Well, he gave him servants to go with the land
because Mephibosheth himself couldn't take care of the land
so he gave him all the provision.
And he said, you're gonna sit at my table
as one of the king's sons.
Man, it's awesome to read that passage of scripture.
And what a great picture it is
that I have been made a child of God.
He says specifically here in verse six,
that he hath made us, notice kings and priests,
begin to understand the fact that this gives us
the opportunity and the privilege to be able to serve him.
You think about that truth of the priesthood of the believer
in 1 Peter chapter two,
just a few pages back in your Bible,
we notice in this portion of scripture,
the truth of the priesthood of the believer.
The Bible says in verse number nine
in 1 Peter chapter two,
but ye are a chosen generation,
a royal priesthood and holy nation,
a peculiar people that you should show forth
the praises of him who hath called you out of darkness
into his marvelous light,
which in time past were not a people,
but are now the people of God,
which had not obtained mercy,
but now have obtained mercy.
Aren't you thankful?
He's made us a priest.
You know that we can serve him.
We can bring him the offerings.
We can enter into his presence.
Hebrews 13 in verse 15 talks about bringing continually
the sacrifice of the praise of our lips
and what a joy to know that we can serve him
because of how he's made us a king and a priest.
We find that we can serve him now,
but we also see the truth here that is further developed
as we go through the book of Revelation
that will serve him during the millennial reign
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
Jesus is literally gonna reign for a thousand years.
And by the way, someone asked a great question this morning.
They said, I know that you mentioned
that Jesus is gonna reign for a thousand years,
but can you help me understand that?
Because God said that a thousand years is a day
and a day is a thousand years.
Is it really a thousand years?
And I said, yes, it is.
And here's why.
He's speaking to us from our perspective of time,
not his perspective of time.
Isaiah talks about the one that dies at a hundred
is gonna die like a child.
And so obviously a thousand literal years
as we would calculate time.
And so we find that he's gonna rule and reign,
but he says that he's made us kings and priests
and we're gonna rule and reign with him.
It's further developed as we get into chapter 20
of the book of Revelation in verses one through six.
And we'll get there in about five years, I guess,
according to brother Hummel,
but we'll get there and we'll study and we'll see
what that looks like in the millennial reign of Christ.
But what a joy to be able to serve him today,
to have that position.
See, that's what he did for us.
I notice in first Peter chapter two in verse number 10,
I read it just a moment ago,
but I noticed where the scripture said,
which in time past were not a people,
but are now the people of God.
I hope that just that simple thought
from that portion of verse number 10
encourages you tonight.
Because before salvation, we were not a people.
We were lost on our way to a Christless eternity.
But thankfully, the Lord Jesus Christ took our place.
We need to remember the work that he did,
remember his passion.
Number three, recall his promise.
In verse number seven, notice with me,
the Bible says this,
"'Behold, he cometh with clouds and every eye shall see him
"'and they also which pierced him
"'in all kindreds of the earth shall wail because of him.
"'Even so, amen.'"
We find here in verse number seven,
the Bible says, "'Behold, he cometh.'"
It tells us that every eye shall see him.
It also tells us they which pierced him would see him.
That's speaking about the Jews or Israel as a nation.
And we find that here in verse number seven,
it's important that we understand this evening
that the obvious reference to Christ's return here
is when he returns all the way to the earth
at the end of the tribulation.
Let me very quickly try to help us understand this idea
or the teaching, the biblical truth
with regard to the return of Christ.
There's really two aspects to the return of Christ.
He's going to return in the air,
according to 1 Thessalonians chapter number four.
And when he returns in the air,
the Bible says that we which are alive,
the dead in Christ shall rise first,
then we which are alive.
and remains shall be caught up together with him,
and we're gonna meet him in the air,
and we're gonna be with him forever.
He's not gonna come all the way to earth
at that first time, he's just gonna come in the air.
And by the way, it seems clear,
we'll look at a few verses here in just a moment,
that not every eye is gonna see him.
In fact, 1 Thessalonians chapter number five,
and verse number two says that he's coming
like a thief in the night.
The Bible says in a moment, the twinkling of an eye,
which is faster than you can blink, 1 Corinthians 15,
that's how he's gonna return at that point.
But then, in that event, which we refer to as the rapture,
why don't we use the word rapture?
People come and say, well, the rapture's
not even in the Bible, that's because
they're looking for the word rapture.
Do you know that the word dinosaur
is not in the Bible either?
Does that mean there are no dinosaurs?
I read something this week that said,
science proves the Bible wrong,
because dinosaurs aren't in the Bible.
Come on, man, the word dinosaur didn't even
come into existence until the 19th century.
How's the word gonna be in the Bible
if it didn't even exist?
Right, and they're like, well,
let's not talk about the facts.
But the reality is that, listen,
the fact that the word rapture is not there
doesn't mean there's not a rapture,
because the word caught up means rapture.
If you study the Greek and you understand it,
that's what it means, it means to be caught up,
to be raptured, all right?
We find here that that's what's going to start
that seven-year period of time
that we refer to as the tribulation,
and that will be taking place here on earth.
Remember I mentioned to you last week
that when you study the book of Revelation,
there'll be scenes in heaven and scenes on earth,
and they sometimes just go back and forth,
these scenes that we find throughout the book of Revelation,
and so we find that really, to begin chapter number four
of the book of Revelation is where we see
the rapture of the church really taking place,
and John being escorted into heaven.
You see in chapters two and three
the references of the letters to the church.
After that point, no longer do you see
any reference to the church until chapter 19,
and in chapter 19, the reference that you see
with the church is the saints,
and we're coming back with him, okay?
So when we look at this and we see this reference
in Revelation one and verse number seven,
and behold, he cometh with clouds,
and every eye shall see him,
this is referring not to the rapture,
but to the end of the tribulation
when he returns all the way to earth,
and he's gonna literally set his foot down,
and we see, we're gonna look at Zechariah here
in just a moment, and we find that this event
is fully developed or more fully explained
as we get to the book of Revelation in the 19th chapter.
We find that we read verse number 11,
and then you continue from there, and you see that,
but look back at the book of Zechariah, if you will,
very quickly, I wanna look at two verses of scripture
in the book of Zechariah.
The easiest way to find Zechariah is to find Matthew
and then go backwards to Malachi
and backwards again to Zechariah, all right?
So if you're struggling, that's the easiest way to find it,
at least the easiest way I have learned to find it.
Zechariah chapter number 12, look at verse number 10.
The Bible says, and I will pour upon the house of David
and upon the inhabitants of Jerusalem,
the spirit of grace and of supplication,
and they shall look upon me whom they have pierced,
and they shall mourn for him as one mourneth
for his only son, and shall be in bitterness for him
as one that is in bitterness for his firstborn.
Now, here's where we see about they're gonna look upon him
who they pierced, and we see that in Revelation 1
in verse number seven, but now skip over to chapter 14,
if you will, and look at verse number four.
The Bible says this, and his feet shall stand in that day
upon the Mount of Olives.
How many have ever stood on the Mount of Olives?
All right, some of you stood there.
I remember standing on the Mount of Olives,
and I remember as I stood there, we sat up,
there's a little place where you can sit up there
and oversee, and I mean, you can, it's amazing
as you look over the valley and you see the Temple Mount
and all that you see, and at the bottom,
between the Temple Mount and the valley,
you see the Garden of Gethsemane, I mean, it's amazing.
It's a treacherous walk down that walkway there,
very, very, very steep, but the reality is that
when I stood there, you know what I thought?
One day, Jesus is coming back, and he's gonna put his foot
right here on the Mount of Olives.
It's what the Bible says, and it says in verse number four,
which is before Jerusalem on the east,
and the Mount of Olives shall cleave in the midst thereof
toward the east and toward the west.
It's gonna literally split it open.
The Bible says, and there shall be a very great valley,
and half of the mountain shall remove toward the north,
and half of it toward the south.
So I stood on the Mount of Olives, and I thought about this.
In fact, we read the passage of Scripture.
It's gonna happen, but that's gonna happen
in Revelation 19, is the timing in the book of Revelation.
So here in Revelation one, when here John is speaking
about the fact that the Lord cometh,
he's speaking specifically about Revelation 19
when he comes at the end of the tribulation,
but we must rejoice and recall the promise that he gave,
even as John is mindful in John 14,
as he had the privilege of writing those words,
let not your heart be troubled.
If you believe in God, believe also in me.
In my Father's house are many mansions.
If it were not so, I would have told you.
And then he says this, I go to prepare a place for you,
and if I go and prepare a place, I'll come again
and receive you unto myself,
that where I am, there ye may be also.
And he said, I come again.
I will come again.
Remember, he's the faithful witness, right?
Verse number five is the faithful witness.
He said, I will come again.
John says this in 1 John chapter number two.
We mentioned John 14 and 1 John chapter two
in verse number 28, the Bible says,
and now little children abide in him
that when he shall appear, not if he shall appear,
but when he shall appear, he's coming.
We may have confidence and not be ashamed
before him that is coming.
If it tells us this, then we know that it is possible
that some could be ashamed of him that is appearing.
Verse 29, if you know that he is righteous,
you know that everyone that doeth righteousness
is born of him, chapter three and verse one.
Behold, what manner of love the father hath bestowed upon us
that we should be called the sons of God.
Really, that goes right back to verse number six
and five in Revelation that he loved us
and washed us from our sins in his own blood.
Therefore, the world knoweth us not
because it knew him not.
Beloved, now are we the sons of God.
And it does not yet appear what we shall be,
but we know that again, when he shall appear,
we shall be like him for we shall see him as he is.
And every man that hath this hope in him
purifies himself even as he is pure.
In Acts one, so John had the privilege of hearing Jesus say
in John 14 and then recording,
let not your heart be troubled.
And that verse, those verses that I quoted for you
a moment ago, he had the privilege of recording for us
first John 2, 28 down through chapter three
in verse number three about the return.
But then John had the privilege of standing
in Acts chapter number one when he watched Jesus ascend
back up into heaven.
And as John was part of that group that stood there
as Jesus ascended back up into heaven,
he heard the angel say, why stand ye gazing up into heaven?
This same Jesus, which has taken up from you into heaven
shall so come in like manner.
What a joy, what a joy.
Listen, we need to recall this promise.
We don't know when he's coming, but we know that he is.
I said this last week, imminent and immediate
are not the same thing.
The reality is that when God gives us the teaching
in his word of the imminent return of Christ,
it really is a precious, God has all wisdom, all right?
And sometimes he just lets us get a little bit
of his wisdom, but he has all wisdom.
And with having all wisdom, he knew that he could give
this teaching of the imminent return of Christ
and every generation of believer would live,
understanding that it could happen in their time.
It's amazing.
Jesus didn't give us the day.
The disciples were asking in Acts chapter one,
he said, it's not for you to know.
We just gotta be busy about the work
that he's given us to do.
And so this evening, what's the result?
When we get our eyes on Jesus, we take the thought
of this message tonight, get your eyes on Jesus.
When we recognize this person, when we remember his passion,
when we recall his promise, when we're focused upon Jesus,
what is it that will be the result?
Well, look at the end of verse number six.
To him be glory and dominion forever and ever, amen.
Listen, when you get your eyes on Jesus,
you know what you start doing?
You start worshiping him.
You start praising him.
Why?
Because you're seeing him for who he is.
You're getting your eyes on Jesus.
You're not so focused on all the circumstances of life,
all the things going on around us.
Can I tell you this?
Even there's a lot of things pulling for our attention.
A lot of voices in the world,
a lot of things that are trying to get us distracted.
I preached a few weeks ago on Sunday morning
about a good soldier not being distracted.
And here we find that if we get our eyes on Jesus,
we can rejoice in knowing who he is,
what he has done for us, and what he is still going to do.
He's coming back for us.
Someone said this to me this morning.
They said, I don't know a whole lot of things,
but one thing that I do know
is that whether I have to live through some difficulties
and I die a martyr, or if I just live in peace and freedom
and I just die of old age,
I know is I'm going to see Jesus. Hallelujah. I understand, I'd rather die just of old age
and not have to go through all the tribulation and all the difficulty, but the Bible says
that we'll face persecution, yea, all those that live godly in Christ Jesus shall suffer
persecution. I really think tonight that we need to be prepared for it. I'm going to preach
a message in just a couple of Sunday mornings of preparing for persecution. 1 John chapter,
or excuse me, 2 Timothy chapter number 3. You say, you really think it's going to happen?
I don't know, because I'm not a prophet in that sense of foretelling, but I can foretell
what the Bible says, and the reality is we better be prepared for it. Amen? When we look
at these people that we're facing under Domitian's rule, terrible, terrible times, grace, peace,
why? Because we get our eyes on Jesus. And we recall, we recall His promise, that last
point that we dealt with, we remember His passion, that what He did for us, and then
we recognize His person. And we just see how lovely and how wonderful He is. And what will
happen is we'll begin rejoicing to Him be glory and dominion forever and ever. Amen.
Let's pray. Father, we love You. We thank You for loving us. We thank You for Your Word
tonight. We thank You for the truth of it. I pray, Lord, that You would help us to get
our eyes on Jesus. Lord, we understand that we're living in a difficult time. We have
all sorts of things going on around us. And Lord, we pray that You would just work in
our hearts and lives, that You would help us, Lord, to take the truth of this short
portion of Scripture, Lord, that we'd get our eyes on You. Move and work in this time
of invitation as only You can, and we'll give You the glory for it. In Christ's name, we
pray. Would You stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed. Kimberly's going to play
quietly on the piano.