written 39, and it's interesting that we would sing that song that we just sang
about our all being on the altar, and I hope when you sing, what a privilege it
is to sing, but the ministry of music, the place that music has in worship, and as
we sing songs, it's not just some kind of filler, and it's an opportunity to
worship the Lord and how the the Spirit of God speaks to our hearts through the
words of these wonderful hymns, and I'm so thankful for the old hymns of the
faith, and praise the Lord for it. Psalm 139, be looking at verses 23 and 24 this
evening. I intend that the message will be a little shorter this evening, and
we'll spend an extended amount of time in prayer this evening, and Psalm 139, I
want to draw your attention to these two verses of Scripture. The Bible says,
Search me, O God, and know my heart. Try me and know my thoughts, and see if
there be any wicked way in me, and lead me in the way everlasting. Many of us are
familiar with this text of Scripture. In fact, we often sing the song that is
titled, Cleanse Me, and it's interesting, that song that is in our hymnal, number
57, J. Edwin Orr penned the words of that hymn in 1936, and his testimony is that
he penned those words during an intense movement of the Holy Spirit at the
Easter Revival Convention in New Zealand. He goes on to say, for some time it was
in 1936 that the words to that song were penned, he said, for some time prior to
this Easter campaign, an attitude of unusual expectancy had been prevalent
among those people. Prayer meetings spread throughout the city with much
fervency, and intercession led to widespread confession and reconciliation
among the believers. Great numbers of unconverted students professed faith in
Christ. The next night was given over to testimony with singing such as one
expects in heaven. The revival news soon spread throughout all of New Zealand. Dr.
Orr reports that as he was leaving New Zealand, four Aborigine girls approached
and they sang a beautiful song for him. It was a Morai song of farewell, and he
heard the tune of that particular song and loved the tune, and he was so
impressed with the beauty of this Polynesian melody that soon afterward he
wrote new verses to the tune on the back of an envelope. The text was based on the
familiar words of Scripture that we just read this evening. Search me, O God,
and know my heart. Try me, and know my thoughts, and see if there be any wicked
way in me, and lead me in the way everlasting. If you're taking notes and
you'd like a title this evening, I've simply entitled the message, Search Me, O
God. As we look at this and dig right in this evening, I want you to notice with
me that the psalm is a psalm that is ascribed to David, and so the sweet
psalmist of Israel has been used of the Lord to write this psalm, and we see that
as we note the the verses that end this psalm, I believe, number one this evening,
that it was a personal plea. I'm impressed by the personal nature of what
we find here in the text of Scripture, and it's important for us to understand
the personal nature of these verses of Scripture, in that we are aware of the
importance of us also having a personal desire, such as what is expressed by
David here in this prayer. We notice the use of pronouns. In fact, in two
verses of Scripture, he uses the word me four times. He uses the word me four times.
That personal nature of this prayer, this plea, he says, search me, O God, and
know my heart. We see the personal nature of it, and this evening, as we think about
the aspect of these familiar words of Scripture, and we think about the
prayer of the psalmist, and the understanding of the personal nature of
what we're dealing with this evening, I would like, as I've approached the
passage, and as I would seek to share some thoughts with you this evening, that
we, too, would take a personal approach to the subject matter that is before us. In
just a short period of time, we were planning to have a revival meeting, and
what a joy to be able to have a special meeting on our calendar on an annual
basis. And obviously, this year, many things have been adjusted on the calendar,
and many things have been removed from the calendar, and we're not having the
evangelist that we intended to have that was originally scheduled, actually, a
couple of years ago. But the Lord knows, and the Lord's in control of those
things, and I'm looking forward to those that will be with us. And I find this
evening, this personal aspect of approaching and entering into church
services regularly, or even as we have special revival meetings, that we'd
understand that I'm desiring that God would work in my life, that God would
search me, that God would show me, that I understand that it's important if we
could figuratively, this evening, have in our minds this idea that we stand and we
draw a circle around ourselves and say, God, work within the circle. Work in my
life. Do something in my life. And we see the personal nature. He says, search me, O
God, and know my heart. We're familiar with Jeremiah 17, but I remind you what
Jeremiah records for us here in this familiar passage of Scripture. In
Jeremiah 17, in verse number 9, the Bible says, the heart is deceitful above all
things, and desperately wicked. Who can know it? In verse number 10 of Jeremiah
17 says, I, the Lord, search the heart. I try the reins, even to give every man
according to his ways, and according to the fruit of his doings. We understand
that the Bible teaches that the heart is deceitful. We understand this evening
many things with regard to deceit. We understand that the enemy of the
brethren is a deceiver, right? And we understand the nature of those that
would try to deceive us, but the reality is that at times in our lives we can be
deceived. We can deceive ourselves. Self-deception. We find here that the
Lord answers the question when the verse ends, who can know it? I, the Lord,
search the heart. And that's what we see here, that the plea of the psalmist, the
plea of David, is search me, O God, and know my heart. Notice what he says, try me
and know my thoughts. And we understand this evening the importance of bringing
into captivity every thought to the obedience of Christ. We see that truth in
2nd Corinthians 10 and verse number 5, and Paul gives the admonition to those
that he's writing to in Philippi, there in Philippians 4 and verse number 8, with
regard to the things that were to think on. And he says, finally, brethren, what
sort of things are true, what sort of things are honest, what sort of things are just,
what sort of things are pure, what sort of things are lovely, what sort of things are
of good report, if there be any virtue, if there be any praise, think on these things.
Now, we understand this evening as we approach this passage of Scripture and
we take this familiar passage of Scripture, that the psalmist is taking
this personal approach. I remember, I don't know all the words to the song, but
there was a little chorus that we sang with kids years ago in a junior church,
children's church type of a setting. It's me, it's me, it's me, O Lord, standing in
the need of prayer. I think it goes something like, not my brother, not my
sister, but it's me, O Lord. And I think about that little chorus and that little
song that we'd sing, and I think about the words of the psalmist here in
understanding that David is saying, God, I'm interested in you searching my heart,
I'm interested in you knowing my heart and trying me and knowing my thoughts.
See, there's a danger that we face in not really accepting the personal nature of
these particular verses of Scripture. What I mean by that is there are times
in which we think that we're really praying and really hoping that God works
in somebody else's heart and life, that God really shows them the error of their
ways. We get kind of concerned about that. The Pharisees, they were really good at
that, were they not? I'm going to read to you what the Pharisee says in Luke 18,
jot it down if you will, in Luke 18 verses 10 through 12. The Bible records
for us about two men that went up into the temple to pray. The Bible tells us
that the one was a Pharisee and the other was a publican. The Pharisee begins
to pray in verse number 11 of Luke 18, and it says, the Pharisee stood and prayed
thus with himself, God I thank thee that I am not as other men are. Extortioners,
unjust, adulterers, or even as this publican. I fast twice in the week, I give tithes
of all that I possess. The publican, according to verse number 13, sending afar
off would not lift up so much as his eyes into heaven, but smote upon his
breast saying, God be merciful to me a sinner. It says this in verse 14, I tell you
this man went down to his house justified rather than the other. For
every one that exalteth himself shall be abased, and he that humbleth himself
shall be exalted. I believe there's interesting insight to us in verse
number 14 with regard to the importance of humility. What is going to lead me?
What is it that led the psalmist David to say what he says in Psalm 139 verses
23 and 24, to say search me O God and know my heart, try me and know my
thoughts, that personal plea. What was it? I believe that there's a level of
humility, a level of humility. And there's a recognition of I'm desiring that God
works in my heart, in my life. We find that Peter, if you'll recall with me at
the end of the book of John, in chapter number 21 after they go fishing, and we
find that the Lord shows up on the shore and he says, have you caught
anything? Do you have any meat? And they say, no we've caught nothing. And Jesus tells
them to cast the net and they would find and they have a great host of multitude
of fish that they bring in. And Peter then after they come to the shore and
they come and dine and they enjoy fellowship with the Lord, the Lord Jesus
Christ begins to interact personally with Peter. Begins to ask him a series of
questions. Do you love me? And we recognize those truths that are there
and we find that the Lord then gives some instruction and revelation with
regard to the end of Peter's life and the death that he would die. And Jesus
says this, Peter follow me. You'll probably recall that John was there as
well. And Peter says to the Lord Jesus Christ after he hears those words, follow
me, in verse number 21 he says, well what about this guy? He says, Lord and what
shall this man do? What's he concerned about? He's concerned about John, right?
And Jesus says, if I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee? Follow
thou me. Really learn about that. Learn about some personal responsibility. One
day we're gonna stand before the Lord Jesus Christ. And you're not gonna stand,
you're gonna stand by yourself, amen? You're gonna give an account. And we find
the personal nature of this and the importance. The Bible tells us that
there in Corinth there was some problems that were going on. Part of, I mean
obviously there's a whole list of problems are going on in Corinth, but in
2nd Corinthians the Bible reveals to us that they were comparing themselves
among themselves. And the Bible says that this is not wise. See there's a danger in
us being able to look at other people and looking at how I'm maybe comparing
myself among ourselves, but the standard is not some other believer. The standard
is the Lord Jesus Christ and the Word of God. And so we find that the personal
nature of this plea is revealed to us in the use of the pronouns and the fact
that he says, search me, know my heart, try me, know my thoughts. And this evening
this is a prayer that we need to pray. This is a place in which we need to get
alone with the Lord and say, God we want you to search us, me personally. Yes, I
want God to work collectively, but I must be careful to understand the importance
of the personal nature of this plea from David here in Psalm 139 verses 23 and 24.
Notice I believe not only was it personal, I believe it was passionate. I believe
that David really desired for God to search him. I believe that David was
passionate in his prayer. We see many things about David. There are much that
we could discuss with regard to his life and we could go through a whole host of
things and see some passion in the way that he rejoiced, the way that he sought
the Lord. I believe here as he's praying, I believe that there's a level of
passion. It's interesting to me as you read the entirety of Psalm 139 that the
psalmist had an awareness of God's omniscience and omnipresence. Notice how
he begins the psalm in verse number one of Psalm 139. It says, O Lord, thou hast
searched me and known me. He begins the psalm with the acknowledgement of God's
omniscience, that God knows everything, but yet he concludes the psalm by saying,
Search me, O God, and know my heart. Try me and know my thoughts. Amen? But he starts
the psalm by saying, Thou hast searched me. In understanding, knowing, recognizing
the fact that our God is omniscient, you understand this evening that as we
consider the prayer of David at the end of the psalm, it was not only that he had
an awareness that God knew these things, but we see in this prayer, in these words,
that he desired for the Lord to search him and to know him and to try him and
to see if there be any wicked way in him. That desire on the part of the
psalmist to say, God, I want you to search me. See, it's one thing for us to
recognize that God knows everything. He does. When Adam and Eve were hiding in
the garden, did God know where they were? Of course he did. When David thought that
he did everything that he could within his power to cover his tracks, did God
know what he had committed? Surely he did. That's why he sends Nathan and says, Thou
art the man. Right? We can't hide anything from God. But there's something
interesting to me about the prayer of the psalmist here, is that the
knowledge of God knowing everything, but then the invitation to that all-knowing
God to come and search me. See, it's one thing for a child to know that their
parents have the ability to go in and to search the bedroom and to search under
the bed and in the closet and wherever they want to search to be able to find
whatever it is that they want to find, but it's another thing for the child to
say, I invite you in to look. Do you understand the difference? See, God knows
everything and He knows our hearts. He knows if there's wickedness in us. He
knows our thoughts, but yet we find that the psalmist is inviting God in. He's
desiring, I believe, with passion for God to do this work in his life. I think it's
very encouraging to see the perspective of David and also for us to understand
the importance this evening of having a similar heart attitude. How many times
throughout the Gospels do we read of the interactions of the Lord Jesus Christ
with those to whom he ministered, and yet Jesus would say that he knew their
thoughts, and they marveled. I mean, they didn't know. How does he know what we were
thinking? He knows your thoughts. He knows my thoughts, but it's a different thing
when we say, Lord, we want you to search us and we want you to know and try, and
that invitation that we extend, I believe that we only are going to extend that
invitation when we have that measure of humility. I believe that we'll only
extend that invitation when we have that process of self-examination. When we go
through the process of what we read of in 1 Corinthians 11 that we often read
and reference during the time of observing the Lord's Supper, and we
understand that it's a table of examination, but let a man examine
himself. We find that because the heart is deceitful, that we say, Lord, now we
want you to search me in case I have deceived myself. I find that it's a
personal plea, it's a passionate plea. I believe it's a purposed plea. There's a
purpose in this plea, in this prayer, and it's exciting. Notice what he says in
verse number 24, and see if there be any wicked way in me, and lead me in the way
everlasting. You know what I believe the purpose is? The purpose is to be right with God.
Amen? And lead me in the way everlasting. Lord, I want you to search me, I want you
to try me, I want you to know me, I want you to see if there's any wicked way in
me. Reveal that to me so that you then lead me in the way everlasting so that I
can be right with you. The idea of nothing between my soul and my Savior. The idea
of having that sweet communion with our Lord and Savior. The purpose of
David praying the prayer, the purpose of the plea that we read, is that I want to
be right with my Savior. I want to be right with God. God, if there's anything wicked
in me. See, we look at verse number 21 and 22. It's interesting, the verses leading
directly into the prayer that finishes the psalm. He says, do not I hate them, O
Lord, that hate Thee, and am not I grieve with those that rise up against Thee. I
hate them with perfect hatred. I count them mine enemies. Then he says, search me, O
God, and know my heart. Try me and know my thoughts. See if there be any wicked way
in me and lead me in the way everlasting. In the very context of what he's saying
in verses 21 and 22, he's saying, but God, I want it to be a righteous thing. I don't
want it to be a carnal thing. The reality this evening is that there are times in
our lives when we think, well, and in fact, even as you speak with lost people and
you confront them with their need for the Savior, on many occasion I've had
people say, well, I've never murdered anybody. Well, I mean, that's a good thing
that you never murdered anybody, right? I've never committed, and they might list
something that they think is a big sin in their minds. You know, it's interesting
that when the Lord in the epistles, and you can read various portions of
Scripture, when He's giving instruction to His people about the importance of
our walk, I think of Ephesians specifically, and you think about the
latter half of the book and really dealing with chapters 4 and 5 and
looking at all of the things with regard to our walk with the Lord and how we
walk, how we behave. You know what He deals with? He doesn't deal with don't
murder people. He doesn't deal with don't commit adultery. He doesn't deal, no, He
says, tell the truth. Don't lie. He says, be angry and sin not. Right? He says, let
not the sun go down upon your wrath. The things that He says in Ephesians 4 and
5, the instruction that He's given, the importance of our walk, see, sometimes we
overlook some of those things in our own lives because we're so concerned about
some bigger things. We fail to realize that they're causing my walk with my
Savior to be hindered. And sometimes we're too busy looking at someone else
and looking at someone else's problem, someone else's sin, someone else's... and if
I can find someone that's doing something worse than I am, it can somehow
make me feel okay. But the psalmist says, search me. Search me, O God, and know my
heart. Try me and know my thoughts and see if there be any wicked way in me and
lead me in the way everlasting. Why? Because I want to be right with God. I
want to have that proper fellowship with God that is possible. It's
going to require some humility to pray a prayer like this. It's going to help us
to recognize the importance of taking that personal approach. God work in my
life. As we prepare for revival, I honestly don't have many times to
preach between now and then with regard to messages of preparation. We have an
outdoor service on Sunday evening. We have an Awana ceremony awards on
Wednesday evening a week from now. And I want to encourage you that as we prepare
spiritually for this revival meeting, yes, we pray broadly, corporately, that God
would work in the midst of his people. But I wonder this evening how many of us
will say, as the psalmist said here in Psalm 139, God, I'm the one that needs
you to work in my life. Lord, I want to be thoroughly right with you. I'm
not concerned about what somebody else is doing and how somebody else is
behaving and how somebody else is acting. I just, God, I want you to work in my life.
You know what the beautiful thing is? If everyone takes that approach, God works
amazing ways, right? But if everybody's taking the approach of, man, I hope you
work in that guy's life, I hope you work in that person's life, and then we miss
what God has for us. Search me, oh God. Let's pray. Father, we love you. We thank
you for loving us. We thank you for this brief thought this evening. From this
familiar passage of Scripture, it is my prayer tonight, personally, you'd work in
my life. Lord, I pray that somehow this evening this familiar passage of
Scripture has helped someone. I know that you helped me. Lord, I pray it is my
desire that you'd work corporately in our midst. God, I long to have you work
in my life personally. God, I repeat these words of the psalmist and desire that
you would work in my life. Thank you for the privilege of prayer. We thank you for
the power of prayer. And I pray as we gather here at the church house and pray
together, you'd bless and work. I pray for our families that are tuned in via
livestream. Oh Lord, I pray they would not hustle to some other activity, but
they spend time in prayer, understanding the importance and the power of prayer.
We thank you, even as we began our service this evening, that you're a God
who does answer prayer. We pray that you would be honored and glorified and we'll
thank you for it. In Christ's name we pray, amen. Let me share some updates with
you in our prayer bulletin. I want to start first with the insert.