with you, Revelation chapter number six, and looking at the couple of verses there in Revelation
chapter number six, verses three and four will be our text for this evening, and we'll read that,
get into the message this evening. Of course, we started as we're studying through the book
of Revelation, this is actually message number 26 through the book, and we've tried to get through
verse by verse and studying what God has given to us here, and Revelation chapter number six begins
recording for us the opening of the seal judgments, and a couple of Sunday nights ago we
looked at the first seal being opened in verses one and two, and this evening we'll look at the
second seal being opened in verses three and four, and notice the Bible says in verse three,
and when he had opened the second seal, I heard the second beast say, come and see,
and there went out another horse that was red, and power was given to him that sat thereon
to take peace from the earth, and that they should kill one another, and there was given unto him
a great sword. Before we get into the message this evening, as far as looking at what God gives us
here in Revelation six verses three and four, let me provide for you a couple of introductory
thoughts. In chapter number one of the book of Revelation, the Bible says this, the revelation
of Jesus Christ, which God gave unto him, noticed to show unto his servants things which must shortly
come to pass, and he sent and signified it by his angel unto his servant John, who bear record of
the word of God, and of the testimony of Jesus Christ, and of all things that he saw. Notice in
verse three it says, blessed is he that readeth, and they that hear the words of this prophecy,
and keep those things which are written therein, for the time is at hand, and so God has given to
us the book of Revelation, and the Bible plainly tells us in verse number one to show unto his
servants things much which must shortly come to pass, and we find that as we read the book of
Revelation that we're studying much with regard to eschatology, the doctrine of end things, end times,
and we're seeking to understand what God has revealed to us in his word. It is important for
us to understand, however, that we cannot get so focused on eschatology or end times that we fail
to do what God has given us to do here upon the earth, and we find that we've been given marching
orders. Keep your place in the book of Revelation, but if you would turn back to the book of 1 Timothy,
and I want to read just a couple of verses to you from the book of 1 Timothy with regard to
this understanding of why it is that we are to be diligent to preach the gospel, the good news
of Jesus Christ, amen? And we find that we have the responsibility to do that, and we understand
that God has given to us in his word the responsibility, the privilege of being his
representatives. Paul says this in 1 Timothy chapter number one, in verse number 15, this is a
faithful saying and worthy of all acceptation that Christ Jesus came into the world, notice what it
says, to save sinners of whom I am chief. We understand that his name shall be called Jesus,
right? He's going to forgive his people of their sins, and we understand that he was born to die,
and even at the announcement of the birth of the Lord Jesus Christ, we hear of peace and glad
tidings, and what a joy to understand that he shall be called Wonderful Counselor, the Mighty
God, the Everlasting Father, the Prince of Peace, and as we begin to understand the responsibility
that we have to preach the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ in the second chapter of the book of
1 Timothy, in verse number four, the Bible says, who will have all men to be saved, and to come
unto the knowledge of the truth. It is the will of God for humans to be saved. It's the will of
God for those that are saved to preach the gospel to all the world, and to understand that God is
not slack concerning his promise, as some men count slackness, but is long-suffering to usward,
not willing that any should perish, but that all should come to repentance. As we begin to
understand the preaching of the cross, the preaching of the gospel, a message of peace,
a message of how to have peace with God. Have you ever heard somebody use the phraseology,
I've made peace with God, and sometimes you might hear somebody say that, and the reality
is there's just one way to have peace with God, and we understand that the Bible tells us in the
book of Romans, in chapter number five, in verse number one, therefore being justified by faith,
we have peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ, and understand that we've been given
the responsibility to preach the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ, so that people would know
how they can have peace with God. Not only that they can have peace with God, but we understand
that as the people of God, if you've been saved by the grace of God this evening, that not only do
you have peace with God, but the Bible tells us that he's given to us his peace, and he said that
in the world you shall have tribulation, but in me you have peace. We understand that he's told us
in his word that he's given to us the peace of God which passeth all understanding, and the book
of Colossians tells us that we're to allow the peace of God to rule in our hearts.
Why do I say all of this by way of introduction? Because as we look at the book of Revelation,
and we understand what God is revealing to us, there will come a time, and we don't know
the day nor the hour, but the rapture of the church is going to take place, and I don't know
when the rapture is going to take place, and neither do you, but the reality is one day the
trumpet of the Lord shall sound, and we find that when that day comes, things are going to change,
not only for us, and what a glorious change it's going to be. We which are alive and remain shall
be caught up together in the clouds to be with the Lord. Man, listen, we're going to be with
him for all of eternity. Hallelujah. I mean, if you're saved this evening, that's an exciting
truth and reality of God's word, but I want you to understand that chaos is going to take place
on this earth. We looked last time on the first two verses of Revelation chapter six, and
we understood that first horse and the rider that sat upon the horse, that that is Antichrist,
and that's the rise of Antichrist. Revelation six is the start of that 70th week of Daniel.
We refer to it as the tribulation. As we begin to think about the 70th week and all that will
take place, and we can rejoice that we won't be here, hallelujah, but we find that there's going
to be chaos. Look at second Thessalonians, if you will, and I'm just going to read a couple of
verses, then we're going to get over to Revelation chapter six and look at our text this evening,
but I want you to understand the importance of what God has given for us to do today.
We find in second Thessalonians chapter number two, really, if I had time, we'd read the first
12 verses, but let me just read a few of them. In verse number seven, the Bible says,
For the mystery of iniquity doth already work. Only he who now letteth will let until he
be taken out of the way. That's the ministry of the Holy Spirit, the restraining power
of the Holy Spirit. The Holy Spirit indwells the people of God in this time, in the church age,
and if you're saved this evening, the Holy Spirit of God indwells you, and we understand the
restraining power of God. The mystery of iniquity doth already work, but there's this restraining
that's taking place, and until he be taken out of the way. How is the Holy Spirit, the restrainer,
taken out of the way? Well, at the rapture, that's what takes place, and we find here in verse number
10, the Bible says, And with all deceivableness of unrighteousness in them that perish,
notice, because they receive not the love of the truth, that they might be saved.
And for this cause, God shall send them strong delusion that they should believe a lie, that they
all might be damned who believe not the truth, but had pleasure in unrighteousness. Listen, that's a
sad reality of what's going to happen during the tribulation, and we find this evening that once
the rapture of the church, pictured in Revelation chapter number four, we studied and we understood
in Revelation chapters two and three, the seven churches in Asia, and all of the messages that
were given to those churches, and the content of those messages, and we come to chapter four,
and we see that picture where John hears, as it were, of a trumpet talking with him, Come up hither,
and the
Picture the rapture and we find that the church
is no longer mentioned after the end of chapter three
until chapter 19 when we come back with the Lord
at the end of the tribulation
and we have the battle of Armageddon.
And of course thereafter will be
the millennial reign of Christ
and he'll establish that in chapter number 20.
But we find that when the rapture takes place,
listen, you're not gonna tell another person about Jesus
and about their need to be saved.
We're gonna be out of here.
But there are gonna be countless billions of people
that are quote unquote left behind.
I don't use that phrase to follow after the book series
or the videos that were used with that title
but understand that many people will be left behind.
And it's going to be utter chaos upon earth.
And we find that immediately when you look
at the sealed judgments in chapter six,
remember chapter four and five
are like kind of this parenthetical if you will
where God gives us a view,
the scene in the throne room of heaven.
And we find that as we come to chapter number six,
he begins to reveal to us the sealed judgments
that are being opened.
Now there are some that would give the idea
and I mentioned this several weeks ago
with regard to different perspectives
of the timing of the rapture and when it will take place
that they do not believe that the sealed judgments
are part of God's wrath.
And they somehow try to deal with it
that it's just part of the tribulation
that man has dealt with throughout history and what have you
and they would coin a phrase
that it is a post-tribulation pre-wrath rapture
which really is just a mid-trib rapture perspective.
And why do I say that?
Well I say that because as you begin looking
at chapter number six and you begin to see what's happening
and let me say this,
some of those other positions that are out there,
some of those people are extremely combative
about their positions.
And they wanna fight with people and so on and so forth
and I'll just say as a friend of mine said
that just recently retired from the pastor,
he said if you wanna believe in a mid-trib rapture,
a post-trib rapture,
I just hope God lets you live through the tribulation
and that'll be fine.
And the reality is that we don't take the position
out of some escape mentality,
but we take the position
because we believe it to be biblical.
Here's the question.
If indeed the sealed judgments are not part of God's wrath,
then why is it that Jesus is the only one
that can open the seals?
It's a question that must be answered
because we find that if it's just the tribulation
and the persecution that the church has endured
from its inception and it's just more of the same,
they'll take a verse such as what we find
as Paul is writing to Timothy
in 2 Timothy chapter number three,
yea, all those that live godly in Christ Jesus
shall suffer persecution.
And we find that the tribulation of the book of Revelation
is much different than what we read
when we read of that persecution,
even of the tribulation that Jesus speaks of in John 16
and verse number 33.
And so we find that yes, the church,
when you study the book of Acts,
you can see the persecution.
You can see from its very beginning days
the way that the church faced opposition.
And we find that God has always blessed
and God has always provided
and God is with his church.
He told us that I will build my church
and the gates of hell shall not prevail against it.
And we find that as we begin to look in chapter number six
and we begin to understand what's happening,
that this is the wrath of God
being poured out upon the earth.
We must also make the distinction
as we have in previous messages
and went to great lengths
to be able to establish the biblical truth
and looking at various portions of scripture
that there's a great difference
between the church and Israel.
It is important that we do not
adopt some replacement theology.
It is important that we understand
that the church and Israel are distinct
and that God has a distinct purpose
for the church and for Israel.
In the time of the tribulation,
remember in Daniel's prophecy,
unto thy people and unto thy holy city.
And so we find that there's much biblical truth
that God has given to us with regard to this tribulation.
And as we begin to think about the tribulation
and we're reminded that even as we study prophecy
and even as God said in Revelation chapter number one,
that he's showing us things
which must shortly come to pass.
And even though he tells us,
blessed is he that readeth
and they that hear the words of this prophecy
were reminded in the words echo in my mind
that we're to redeem the time,
that we are to occupy till he come.
And we find that time is going so quickly
and we find that the coming of the Lord
draweth nigh as James would say.
And we see various things happening around us,
not that we're looking for signs,
but it reminds us and it gives us this evening
when we read a portion of scripture
like we're gonna study here tonight,
it reminds us of the work that is before us.
Souls are dying.
People are truly that die without the Lord Jesus Christ,
they are truly going to spend eternity in a lake of fire.
Wow, that's sad.
We preached this morning about talk is cheap
from James chapter number two.
You say you have faith, show me your faith
because true faith works.
And we look here at the second seal being opened
and John continues to provide his readers
with this eyewitness account.
We find that John hears and it says in verse number three,
and when he had opened the second seal,
I heard the second beast say, come and see.
And John hears, he hears that invitation to come and see,
he's an eyewitness of what God is revealing to him
and then he begins to write and to report what he saw.
Now remember, the he in verse number three
and when he had opened the second seal,
remember, that is the Lord Jesus Christ.
Remember in chapter number five,
there was this question, who is worthy to open the book?
Remember, John, he was weeping and he wept much, why?
Because he said that there was no one found to open
but yet one of the elders in Revelation five
in verse number five said, weep not.
Behold, the lion of the tribe of Judah,
the root of David hath prevailed to open the book
and to loose the seven seals thereof.
And we find in verse number one of chapter six,
and I saw when the lamb opened one of the seals
and then in verse number three,
and when he had opened the second seal,
and so the Lord Jesus Christ, the one who is victorious,
the one who has redeemed us by his own blood,
the one who has commissioned us to go forth
and to preach the gospel to a lost and dying world,
he's opening these seals.
Now again, as we begin to understand
that whether the seals are part of the tribulation,
God's wrath, it's interesting for us to note that yes,
it is Jesus that's opening these seals, it's God's wrath.
In fact, when you begin to look
and we won't get there until a couple of weeks,
but in chapter number six, when the fourth seal is open,
a fourth part of the earth is going to be killed.
Now there's going to be plenty that will die
before that fourth seal is opened,
but we find that if the fourth seal were open
and the population were as it were today,
that's two billion people that would die in the fourth seal.
This is like nothing that's ever been seen on earth before.
And by the way, these are the seal judgments.
You still have the trumpet and the bowl
or vial judgments that will come,
and we're just at the very beginning of the tribulation.
Chaos, confusion, all sorts of things
are going to be taking place here upon earth.
And it ought to motivate us to tell somebody about Jesus.
I'm not saying that everyone you tell
about Jesus is going to listen.
about Jesus is going to be saved,
but someone who knows the truth, how does it affect us?
I've asked people this question before.
If you were just a quote unquote good citizen
and you knew that there was some kind of threat
at a local establishment where there were a number
of people that were gathered and people
were going to tragically lose their lives
and you were aware of, you sat in the coffee shop
and overheard people talking about their plan,
you would call someone and you would let
someone know, why?
Because the threat seems credible.
Whether it's just talk or what it is,
you hear it and you're gonna report it
so that somebody with authority can go and investigate
and try to figure out what's going on.
I heard just this past week of a planned mass shooting
at a school that was thwarted because of some investigation
that was taking place and there were three
middle school students that were planning
to carry out some tragic school shooting.
And guess what, there's some people that heard about
and reported and they were able to seemingly
keep that from happening.
Can I tell you that it's not a perceived threat
that the rapture's going to happen.
It's not a perceived threat that the tribulation
is going to happen, this is God's word.
And how does it affect us?
How does it motivate us to tell somebody about Jesus?
And we notice here as we look at what John is reporting
and as John is giving to us this second of four horsemen
that's revealed, it tells us in verse number four,
and there went out another horse that was red.
And so in the first of the seals that are open,
we find that it begins to reveal to us
about the white horse and he that sat on him had a bow
and we began to identify who the rider
on that white horse is.
And we understand that's anti-Christ
and we understand that the Bible says
that he went forth conquering and to conquer.
But remember, he had a bow, but he had no arrows.
And we talked about the fact that he would conquer
through peace.
We talked about the fact that Daniel's prophecy
reveals to us that there will be this peace treaty,
this agreement that is made
between the anti-Christ and Israel.
And we find that that's going to happen,
that's that first seal.
But when we come to the second seal,
this next horse, a red horse,
and it's often been defined and categorized
in one word as war.
And we find the Bible says,
notice what the Bible says in verse number four,
and there went out another horse that was red.
The Bible says, and power was given to him
that sat thereon.
Now we're gonna get through the whole verse,
but let me just pause at that moment.
And let me just give you some thoughts tonight.
Number one, I want you to notice what the rider is given.
We're just simply talking about preaching
about the second seal open tonight.
And we notice number one, what the rider is given.
And the first thing that he's given
according to verse number four is the Bible says,
and power was given to him that sat thereon.
Now I want you to understand something about this power
that was given to this rider.
We could argue with regard to who gave the power
to this rider, but ultimately,
if you go far enough down the path,
you would have to acknowledge that it's God
who gave him the power.
Amen?
Let me take you over, hold your place here,
but look in John chapter 19, if you will.
In John chapter number 19, the Lord Jesus Christ
is getting ready to go to Calvary.
And he had given the instruction to his disciples
about what would happen when he went to Jerusalem.
And in chapter 18, he's arrested.
He's before Pilate and all that takes place.
And we find that the people are crying out
to crucify Jesus.
And Pilate is in this situation where he said a few times,
I find no fault in him.
And we come and we're looking here in John chapter 19.
And the Bible tells us, and pick it up with me
in verse number five, then came Jesus forth
wearing the crown of thorns and the purple robe.
And Pilate saith unto them, behold the man.
When the chief priests, therefore, and officers saw him,
they cried out saying, crucify him, crucify him.
Pilate saith unto them, take ye him and crucify him
for I find no fault in him.
The Jews answered him, we have a law.
And by our law, he ought to die
because he made himself the son of God.
That's because he is God, amen.
And that's one of the reasons that the Jews hated him.
Every time he proved his deity, they were ready to kill him.
They rejected Messiah.
He came to his own and his own received him not.
We read in verse number, let's look here in verse number eight
when Pilate, therefore, heard that saying,
he was the more afraid and went again into the judgment hall
and saith unto Jesus, notice, whence art thou?
But Jesus gave him no answer.
Now, there's a reason for that, I believe.
Previously, a question was asked
and Pilate didn't stick around long enough
to get the answer and now he's afraid
and all that's transpired and Jesus gives him no answer.
In verse number 10, notice what Pilate says to Jesus.
Speakest thou not unto me?
Knowest thou not that I have power to crucify thee
and have power to release thee?
Now, Pilate thought he had some kind of power.
Now, legitimately, he had been given some power, amen.
There was power that was vested in him from the authorities
and we understand that as he has this perspective
of the power that was vested in him,
that he thought that he, and he says,
I have power to crucify thee and I have power to release thee
but notice what Jesus says.
As Jesus will help us to set the record straight
and understand the way in which God's world works,
he says in verse number 11, Jesus answered,
thou couldest have no power at all against me
except it were given thee from above.
Therefore, he that delivered me unto thee
hath the greater sin.
What is the Lord saying to Pilate?
He's saying, yep, I have given you the power.
You could have no power at all against me
except it were given thee from above.
Now, remember, Jesus has all power.
He said, as he ascended to heaven,
all power is given unto me in heaven and in earth.
He is the Lord God omnipotent.
There's nothing too hard for him
and so as we come to the second seal
and we notice what the writer is given,
the Bible says that there's power, power was given to him.
Ultimately, that power that was given
to this second horseman, this second rider
on this red horse was given to him by God.
Now, what does that reveal to us?
It reveals to us that God is in charge, amen?
Listen, this is not just more of the same
and the enemy working and just kind of doing his thing
and this is just more persecution and opposition,
but it's not yet the wrath of God.
God is the one that's opening the seals,
but God is also the one that's giving the power
to this particular, as it says here,
to this particular horseman and what is it?
It says at the end, and was given unto him a great sword.
So we find that what was given to the rider
is power and a great sword.
Now, the Antichrist in verses one and two,
we find that he had a bow, but he had no arrows
and he went forth conquering and to conquer.
And so we notice what the rider is given.
He's given power and he's given a great sword,
but then we notice, number two, what the rider does.
Notice the Bible says that the power was given to him
that sat there on, notice that phrase
in the middle of verse number four,
to take peace from the earth.
To take peace from the earth.
That's what the rider does.
We've said that this second horseman,
this red horse, as we find here,
this second seal, that it's summarized
in one word being war.
And we find the Bible says to take peace from the earth.
Understand that the earth there,
that word means the earth as a whole.
The word means the inhabited earth,
the abode of men and animals.
This is not that peace is just being taken
from some particular geographic location,
some small part of the earth,
but we find that the Bible says
that to take peace from the earth.
No doubt there's been many conflicts
throughout even the last hundred years in our human history
and throughout the last couple thousand years
and even beyond that, if you study human history,
you study the Old Testament and all the wars
and all of the battles and all of those things.
But we find that the Bible says
to take peace from the earth.
Not every country on the face of the earth
was involved in the world wars.
There were certain countries that were affected greatly
while others seemed to be not fazed at all.
But yet we find that the Bible says
to take peace from the earth as a whole,
the inhabited earth, the abode of men and animals.
Animals, let me say this about peace.
Peace is something that mankind desires.
I said this when I mentioned about the deal
that the Antichrist will make according to Daniel 9
and that pact, that agreement that will be made,
a peace treaty as we've often referred to it as.
Listen, there are many things
that mankind will do to get peace.
Why, because peace is desired.
We just want peace, we just want peace.
But it's gonna cost you this, I just want peace.
People want peace at home and they're willing
to compromise on things at home because they want peace.
They won't hold to certain standards
and certain positions, why, because I want peace.
I don't want the turmoil, my kids are teenagers
and they're kinda pushing back and I don't wanna,
and I just want peace at home.
Am I right?
Think about it on a world stage, people just want peace.
People are crying right now about the prices of fuel
and they just want peace, just make it end,
whatever's necessary.
I'm not trying to get political this evening,
I'm just simply saying that during the tribulation,
there's gonna be peace taken from the whole,
and by the way, it's God that gives the power
for that to happen.
Peace is desired.
In the next seal, we'll notice, and even as we go through
studying the tribulation and all that takes place,
in the next one is famine and obviously an impact of war
and all that sort of thing, but eventually it comes
to the place where you have to have the mark of the beast
and you're gonna buy, trade, buy or sell,
trade, whatever you're gonna do.
You know what, there are gonna be people lined up.
Why, because I'm hungry, because I this, I whatever,
and if I need to get that mark, I'll get that mark,
that's what they'll do.
Peace is desired, peace is fragile, peace is fragile.
I mean, we see it even in our daily lives, do we not?
We see it around us, we understand the fact
that peace is fragile, we understand that peace
comes from God, we mentioned already that we're to preach
a gospel message, a truth of the good news
of the Lord Jesus Christ, of mankind having peace with God
and then those that have peace with God
having the peace of God.
Peace comes from God.
If you understand and you read over in Isaiah,
the Bible talks about the evil, the wicked,
they have no peace, they have no peace.
We find that here as we notice the activity,
the behavior of this writer and what he does,
the Bible says that he has the power
to take peace from the earth.
Then we notice number three, the resulting chaos.
The Bible says this in verse number four,
and there went out another horse that was red
and power was given to him that sat thereon
to take peace from the earth
and that they should kill one another.
There was given unto him a great sword,
that they should kill one another.
The chaos as peace is removed.
And understand that if you study in Ezekiel 37 and 38,
I'm not saying that this indeed is Gog and Magog,
there's two references to Gog and Magog,
one that takes place after the battle of Armageddon
in Revelation chapter number 20,
but there's also a Gog and Magog in Ezekiel 37 and 38
that takes place somewhere in the beginning stages
of the tribulation.
Because what happens if you read Ezekiel 37 and 38,
and you understand that Gog and Magog
and how that's all formulated and all that happens,
it's after the Valley of Dry Bones,
it's after the regathering and all of that,
and you find that what happens
is they come against Israel, against the holy city
when there's a perceived peace, right?
When there's a defenseless city, an unwalled city.
You can read it and you can see what the Bible says there
in Ezekiel 37 and 38.
And after that destruction, by the way,
it's gonna take them seven years
to dispose of all of the weaponry that's used.
And it's kind of interesting when you line all of that up.
We understand here that the Bible says
that they should kill one another.
It's kind of interesting that when you begin
to look at some of the battles, even in the book of Joshua,
and then as you go forward and look at some of the battles
of Israel and some of their continued foes
throughout the era of the kings,
that there were many times in which the enemy
would have chaos that would take place
and they would kill each other.
And here we find this chaos that is taking place,
this resulting chaos.
We find that there's no value or regard for life.
Peace is taken from the earth.
As we look at this and we see the second seal
and we say, okay, I got it.
I understand what's going to happen.
I understand that there's going to be this first seal
and the Antichrist is gonna come.
He's riding on a white horse
and he's gonna go forth to conquering and to conquer.
And he's gonna do it through peace because he has no bow.
And then the second seal is open and there's a red horse
and he's given power from God to take peace from the earth
and they're gonna kill one another.
We don't know how many are gonna die.
Again, we know that during the fourth seal,
it will be one fourth part of the earth.
We don't know the numbers here with regard
to how many will be killed in this war
and all that as they kill one another,
but it's gonna be absolute chaos.
No regard for life.
You think about some of the things that we see
in kind of isolated moments today.
Some of the tragic, listen, I just saw today
about a shooting in Louisiana.
Eight people were killed.
And it was some kind of started out
with some kind of domestic violence dispute.
I don't know all the details.
I'm not the news people.
I just simply got an alert on my phone
and you see a little bit about that.
Listen, I don't wanna make light of that,
but when you start talking about what's gonna happen
during the tribulation, it's exponentially greater.
It's beyond what we can even really fathom.
It's gonna be horrible, horrible.
And so why do we study prophecy?
Why does God tell us this?
Why does he reveal these things to us?
Why is it that he's given to us the book of Revelation
just so that we can sit around and debate eschatologies,
just so we can sit around and as quote unquote
Bible scholars debate the deeper things of Christianity?
No, he gives it to us so that it would motivate us
to the work that God's given us to do.
Listen, I have loved ones that are lost.
I have loved ones that are lost.
They've rejected the gospel.
That means that they'll be here during the tribulation
unless they get saved beforehand.
That means that if they do not,
there's gonna be a lot of saints
that get saved in the tribulation,
but for these are a lot of people
that get saved tribulation saints that we read of
and we'll study that as we go through.
But we begin to understand that here
as we look at what's happening.
Listen, for some of those loved ones
that have heard the gospel and rejected,
if we believe what 2 Thessalonians says
that I read just a moment ago,
God's gonna send them strong delusion.
They're gonna believe a lie.
They're not gonna get saved.
How does it motivate us to not only share the gospel,
but how does it motivate us to pray for people to be saved?
I'm thankful that I'm going to heaven.
Don't, I mean, listen, I am so thankful.
But let me just remind you of what Paul says.
Let me finish with this, Romans chapter nine and 10,
and we're only gonna read a couple of verses
in each of these chapters.
But I hope with having the truth that God has given to us
and understanding what we're studying
through the tribulation and studying these great judgments
that are being poured upon earth from God
as he's opening up these seals
and his wrath is beginning to be poured out.
In Romans chapter nine, Paul says,
"'I say the truth,' in verse number one,
"'in Christ I lie not, my conscience also bearing me witness
"'in the Holy Ghost, that I have great heaviness
"'and continual sorrow in my heart, why?
"'For I could wish that myself were accursed from Christ
"'for my brethren, my kinsmen according to the flesh.'"
In chapter 10, in verse number one, he says,
"'My brethren, my heart's desire and prayer to God for Israel
"'is that they might be saved.'"
We find that Paul said this in Acts chapter number 20,
in verse number 31, he said,
"'By the space of three years, I cease not to warn everyone
"'night and day with tears.'"
But he said in verse 26, before that, he said,
"'I am pure from the blood of all men.'
And I believe that as you read that reference
that Paul makes of being pure from the blood of all men,
and Paul, no doubt, being a scholar of the Old Testament
and understanding and being trained
in the way in which he was,
you could think about the truth of Ezekiel
and being called to be a watchman.
And God tells Ezekiel that the responsibility of the watchman is to give warning.
What those that are warned do with the warning is between them and God.
But if the watchman fails to do his job, then blood would be required.
Paul says, I'm pure, or I'm clean from the blood of all men.
He said, I cease not to warn day and night with tears.
Why?
Because Paul understood the truth of heaven and the truth of hell.
The lake of fire.
And as we study the book of Revelation, we're just reminded of what's going to happen.
And we can sit around and say, well, I'm not going to be here, hallelujah.
But who do you know that will be here?
That God's given you, placed you in a particular spot, with a particular knowledge of the truth
to be that voice.
If they reject, at least they heard.
Amen?
And then you are clean from that responsibility.
But I just wonder this evening, how does it motivate us to tell?
How does it motivate us to pray?
These things are going to happen.
It's not a perceived threat.
It's an absolute reality of what's going to happen during the tribulation.
Let us pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
And yes, we desire to be good students of thy word.
We desire to properly interpret scripture, to compare scripture with scripture.
We want to be biblical.
But God, we don't want this knowledge to simply puff us up or to enable us to have some theological
debate.
God, I pray that it would motivate us and stir us to tell people about Jesus.
Time is short.
You told us to occupy until you come, to redeem the time.
Lord, I pray that you would help us tonight to understand what will happen, but to allow
that reality to move us.
I pray that in the moment of invitation that you'd have your will in way.
Would you help us, Lord, to just respond as you've spoken?
Help us to be doers of the word.
We'll thank you for it.
In Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
We're going to have a moment of invitation.