uh... the opportunity that we have to look at this portion of scripture i
appreciate
church members who are
uh... on
q with what we're doing
and uh... what i mean by that will someone came in this morning as a
pastor i thought you are a pretty second print in chapter five verse number twenty
but i see
on the bulletin here the appreciation thing is the
as young person again
but here's why i was encouragement to me why
because it's two weeks ago that i was a second in chapter five and someone
remembered hallelujah amen
and someone said i thought we had a look at that we did but god wouldn't let me
get away from it just yet
to look at verse twenty one lord will do that next week verse twenty one's a
favorite verse of scripture just a wonderful truth
that god gives us but let me read to you to remind you second reading of chapter
five inverse twenty
a couple of weeks ago we look at verses eighteen through twenty
and uh... during that uh... message uh... two sundays ago
as we looked at this portion of scripture look at those three verses of
scripture we talked about really two thoughts number one
the privilege that is ours to be
an ambassador
then we said this only is it a privilege
but then we talk about what the purpose was was the purpose of being an
ambassador
and uh... we look at those two points specifically but we look at chapter five
verse number twenty one a read it for you again
the bible says this in second contains five verse twenty now then
we are ambassadors for christ
as though god did beseech you buy us
we pray you in christ's stead
be reconciled
to god
we noted from this passage of scripture that being an ambassador requires that
we're active not passive
we said this also that being a
uh... an ambassador of the lord jesus christ is more
than simply sharing a gospel tract with someone i said this i'm all for
giving out gospel tracts we have them in the back we order them regularly i i do
it's something that we should do
and there are times in which only we may be able to do or the only thing we may
be able to do is give a gospel tract
uh... a waitress an attendant somewhere at the the clerk at the store
et cetera et cetera
uh... and we may not have the opportunity to engage them in
conversation
but i said this and i didn't mean it to come across in a
uh... in an unkind way but just the reality is this we have not been called
to be god's marketing agents
that's not what god called us to be
god called us to be his ambassadors
and i preached that message two sundays ago and
god just again as i mentioned a moment ago wouldn't let me get away from the
thought and then took me to proverbs thirteen and verse seventeen
and the bible says in that passage of scripture in that verse a wicked messenger
falleth into mischief but then the end of the verse says this as often you find
in the book of proverbs a contrast
in a single verse of scripture the bible says this in proverbs thirteen and verse
seventeen
but a faithful
ambassador
is health
a faithful
ambassador
is health
as we look at the message this morning we look at this passage of scripture i've
titled the message a faithful
ambassador and i want you to think about this this morning
as we look at this verse of scripture the bible says now then
we are ambassadors for christ who is the we
well the we
is all of those that have been redeemed that have already been reconciled we
cannot we've been given the purpose
we've been given the ministry of reconciliation
but those that have been given the ministry of reconciliation are those
that have already been reconciled to god
we have been reconciled remember verse seventeen therefore if any man be in
christ
he is a new creature old things are passed away behold all things are become
new
paul experience that in his own life he experienced the power of the gospel
as he got saved and god changed his life
and he expected that those that he was writing to in the church in corinth
just as he had
had the opportunity to preach the gospel there that they too
uh... after trusting christ as their savior that they
were these new creatures they had that
uh... experience in their own lives and so paul as he says now then we plural
are ambassadors for christ paul understood
as he writes in many of the uh... letters that he writes to churches and
even to individuals
that his office was that of an apostle
he understood that
but we find that he also understood is through the the holy spirit giving him
the words to write all scriptures given by inspiration of god
that he was an ambassador for christ but he does not say to the church in corinth
uh...
and an ambassador
he says we
are ambassadors
in the question that god just kept bringing to my heart and my mind
as i was looking at this passage of scripture is this and really
if you wanted to use a subtitle for the message this this morning i said
the the title is a faithful ambassador but a subtitle might be this
what kind of an ambassador
are you
ask the question personally
see the reality this morning is that we are ambassadors
but can i say to this morning that we could be
good ambassadors
or we could be bad ambassadors
there are some people that
bill the the role we talked about the appointments of being an ambassador for
the united states going to a particular nation and country there are some that
fail
in their responsibility
and they have to be recalled and replaced
right we we see that
the reality this morning is that we are ambassadors but the question is
what kind
of an ambassador
am i a faithful ambassador
am i a slothful ambassador
you start filling in the blank all these thoughts and questions
so this morning as we consider the thought a faithful ambassador
and looking at the truth that we are ambassadors it's like this
the apostle paul says as he's writing to timothy in second timothy chapter
number two
he tells him to be a good soldier
and i said this last year as i preach through the book of first and second
timothy
the reality is that we're all soldiers if you're saved by the grace of god
at that moment of salvation you were enlisted
into the lord's army
and the question
is not am i a soldier the question is am i a good soldier
i don't want to be content with just being a soldier
paul says to timothy he doesn't use these words but he says to be a good
soldier i don't want you to just be a soldier i want you to be a good soldier
of the lord jesus christ
and when i think about this truth of being an ambassador this morning
the bible says in proverbs thirteen and verse seventeen a faithful
ambassador
is health
and we can look at that from a variety of applications this morning but i want
to specifically look at it
from the perspective of being an ambassador
as we find in second corinthians chapter five in verse number twenty
with the purpose
of fulfilling the ministry of reconciliation
how is that health
well because we're taking the gospel of the lord jesus christ
to an individual that is at variance with god because of their sin
and we have the opportunity to go
and to plead with them
to be reconciled to god
and it brings health it brings
salvation it brings
uh... this miracle of being born again and what a blessing
a faithful ambassador
so this morning i want you to consider number one if you're taking notes
a plea
for faithful ambassadors
i see first of all a plea
uh... a sub point there from our loving savior
a plea from our loving savior
I want you to go back to the book of isaiah if you will
in isaiah chapter number six we find that isaiah
uh... after the king had died
uh... he sees the lord he sees god high holy and lifted up the king was
Uzziah
and he finds that it was in that year that that
isaiah gets this vision
we read of the vision
in isaiah chapter number six and
many of us would be familiar with it but i want to read just to grab the
context here in verse number one
the bible says in the year that king Uzziah died
i saw also the lord
sitting upon a throne
high and lifted up and his train filled the temple by the way
we need to get that kind of glimpse of god
we need to see god in his rightful place he's not the man upstairs he's not
no no he is god
he is the holy
god the creator of the universe yes he loves me and yes he says
uh... that that he is
uh... all sorts of things to us with regard to his
uh... his relationship to us and i'm thankful for that
but all we must have a high view of our god
verse number two above it stood the seraphims each one had six wings
with twain he covered his face and with twain he covered his feet and with twain he did fly
and one cried unto another and said holy
holy holy
is the lord of hosts
the whole earth
full of his glory
the post of the door moved at the voice of him that cried and that
house was filled with smoke then said I
woe is me for I am undone see when we see god in his rightful place you know
what happens
we see ourselves in our rightful place
you know what the best
antidote if you will the best remedy for pride
is seeing god in his rightful place
place, because all of a sudden you start seeing God in His rightful place, it'll humble you
in a moment.
Isaiah says, woe is me, woe is me, for I am undone because I am a man of unclean lips
and I dwell in the midst of a people of unclean lips, for mine eyes have seen the King, the
Lord of hosts.
Then flew one of the seraphims unto me, having a live coal in his hand, which he had taken
with the tongs from off the altar, and he laid it upon my mouth and said, Lo, this hath
touched thy lips, and thine iniquity is taken away, and thy sin purged.
And then notice verse 8.
This is where I see, we talk about this plea for faithful ambassadors, and I see it first
from our loving Savior.
Here in verse number 8, we find that the verse of Scripture that many of us are familiar
with from this text, also I heard Isaiah's recounting what he hears, the voice of the
Lord, and here's what God said, Whom shall I send, and who will go for us?
I would say to you this morning that it's the Lord Jesus Christ that while He was during
His earthly ministry, when He saw the fields, He prays and He says this, He tells His disciples
to pray to the Lord of the harvest.
Why?
For the harvest is plenteous, but the labors are few.
There's a plea for faithful ambassadors.
We are ambassadors, but there's a plea for faithful ambassadors.
The wise man in Proverbs, he tells us that a faithful ambassador, what he brings is health,
and we find this morning that as ambassadors of the Lord Jesus Christ, that is a position
that we have.
It's a position of privilege, as I preached two weeks ago.
Whom shall I send, and who will go for us?
Do you hear the plea of our loving Savior?
He gave us the Great Commission, we're familiar with it, we understand the responsibility
that has been ours, the privilege that is ours, and we see this plea of our loving Savior.
We see it here in Isaiah 6, and Isaiah responds with those words, Here am I, send me.
You know the amazing thing is Isaiah did not even know what the task would be at the time
of surrender.
You know why?
He saw God in His rightful place, and it really didn't matter what the task was, if God was
looking for a volunteer, He said, Here am I, send me.
God went on to tell them in the next several verses through the end of the chapter what
His responsibility would be, and then also told them that the people wouldn't listen
to Him.
Isn't that encouraging?
See sometimes what happens is we think, oh, well, we're going to go do this because everyone
wants to hear it, and then somebody doesn't want to hear it, and you get discouraged.
No, we do it because of obedience.
We do it because that's our position.
We are His ambassadors, and a faithful ambassador bringeth health, and there's a plea for faithful
ambassadors.
The Lord Jesus Christ in Luke 14, as He's speaking there, He says, Go out into the highways
and hedges and compel them to come in.
Compel them to come in.
We see a plea for faithful ambassadors, first from our loving Savior, but number two, we
see a plea for faithful ambassadors from a lost sinner, from a lost sinner.
Turn to the book of Luke, if you will, and I referenced the passage in chapter 14, but
I want you to look at Luke 16, and I want you to understand here, we see the plea of
our loving Savior, but then we see a plea from a lost sinner.
In Luke chapter 16, God gives to us the account here of the rich man and Lazarus.
Many of you would be familiar with it.
The Bible tells us in verse number 22, And it came to pass that the beggar died and was
carried by the angels into Abraham's bosom, and the rich man also died and was buried.
And in hell he lift up his eyes, being in torments, seeth Abraham afar off, and Lazarus
in his bosom.
The Lord Jesus Christ spoke more about hell.
Hell's a real place.
I understand today there are people that try to deny the existence of hell.
They talk about annihilation and all this sort of thing, and no, listen, hell is a real
place.
And then the Bible tells us this, that death and hell are cast in like a fire.
This is the second death in Revelation chapter 20.
It's a real place, and it's not a place I've had people tell me as I've talked to them
about needing to be saved, they say, oh, I know I'm going to hell, I'm going to go and
party with my buddies.
No, you're not.
It's a place of torment.
It's a place of separation.
And the worst thing about hell is that you're separated from God for all of eternity.
We find that here, that he's in this place of torment, this rich man, and the Bible,
listen, he didn't go to hell because he was rich, by the way.
People don't go to hell because they're rich.
The Bible says the wages of sin is death.
Amen?
And we know that death is not physical death, it's spiritual death.
And we understand that we must be redeemed, we must be reconciled, we must be born again.
And if you're not born again, then you go to hell, eventually the lake of fire.
If you're saved by the grace of God, you go to heaven.
Praise God, my conversation, my citizenship is in heaven.
I belong to him.
We sang, blessed assurance, Jesus is mine, oh, hallelujah.
But we see this plea from this lost sinner.
Notice in verse 24, and he cried and said, Father Abraham, have mercy on me and send
Lazarus that he may dip the tip of his finger in water and cool my tongue, for I am tormented
in this flame.
Notice initially his request is for himself.
His request is to have some level of comfort in this place of torment, but Abraham responds
in verse 25 and says, son, remember that thou in thy lifetime receivest thy good things
and likewise Lazarus evil things, but now he is comforted and thou art tormented.
And beside all this, notice in verse 26, between us and you, there is a great gulf fixed so
that they which would pass from hence to you cannot, cannot, neither can they pass to us
that would come from thence.
So I want you to understand, listen, there's no place where you can go just for a little
while and you're going to, no, no, no, this, this teaching, this false teaching of purgatory,
it's not in the Bible.
It's on the Bible, all right?
When you die, there's two places that you can go for all of eternity and the reality
is that you can't change from one to the other.
It's impossible.
Your fate is sealed.
That's why it's so important what you do with Jesus today.
That's why in chapter six of second Corinthians, Paul will say today is the day of salvation.
That's why in Proverbs, the wise man says, boast not thyself of tomorrow.
Why?
We don't know what a day is going to bring forth.
That's why James says, what is your life?
It's a vapor that appears for a little time and then vanisheth away.
How many of us can look back at our lives and be like, man, look at how quick life went.
Look at how quick life went.
Listen, some of us are at the age where previously in our lifetime we thought the age that we're
currently at was old.
And now we try to convince everybody that it's still young.
Amen?
Life goes so quickly.
All of a sudden, this lost sinner, his plea changes dramatically.
In verse 27, then he said, I pray thee therefore, father, that thou would ascend him to my father's
house.
What's significant about this rich man now pleading for someone to go to his father's
house?
Well, see, this man, according to verse 28, had five brothers.
He had five brothers.
He says, for I have five brethren, that he, Lazarus, may testify unto them, my five brothers.
Why?
Lest they also come into this place of torment.
There's a plea from our loving Savior, but there's a plea from a lost sinner.
This lost sinner, God gives us the opportunity to see this interaction, to understand this
interaction, and this man, all he is concerned about at this very moment in his life, of
course his life has ended, he's in hell, but at this moment as God gives us this record,
all he's concerned about is his five brothers.
Why?
He doesn't want them to come there.
He's in hell.
He's in the torment.
He understands that there's a great gulf fixed that you cannot pass from one to the other,
and he says, then send him to my father's house, because I have five brothers.
I don't want brothers to come here.
Notice what the Bible says, Abraham saith unto him, they have Moses and the prophets,
let them hear them.
What does he say?
They have the word of God.
Let them hear them.
Last week, Luke 24, what did Jesus do?
Well, starting in Moses and all the prophets, he declared unto them all the things pertaining
unto himself.
Now we find that Abraham says they have Moses and they have the prophets, and notice in
verse 30, this rich man, he says, nay, father Abraham, but if one went unto them from the
dead, they will repent.
I believe that he's sincere in what he's saying.
He truly believed.
reality. That's not how God chose for it to work. God didn't, He's not, listen, the
angels don't proclaim the gospel. He did not, He did not design it so that
people would rise from the dead and go tell people and they'd see this great
miracle. No, He commissioned us to be His ambassadors. And this rich man is
pleading, a plea for faithful ambassadors. He wants this man to go. Why? Because he
doesn't want his brothers to go to hell. Can I tell you this morning, though you
might not be able to hear their voices, there are billions of people on this
earth that need a faithful ambassador. They need somebody to go and tell them
that Jesus is the way. But sometimes what happens is our mind can't fully
wrap around the billions of people. So let me make it real personal. There are
people in your neighborhood that need a faithful ambassador. There are people in
your neighborhood, there might be some people in your family that need a
faithful ambassador. Some people in your neighborhood, some people in your office,
where you work. Some people, you understand what I'm saying, because
sometimes we look at the billions and we think how in the world we're gonna
reach the billions. But it just starts sometimes with crossing the street, with
talking to somebody at the office, talking to a family member. There's a
plea for faithful ambassadors. We see it first from our loving Savior, but then we
see it here in Luke 16, from a lost sinner. And Abraham says in verse 31,
if they hear not Moses and the prophets, neither will they be persuaded, though one
rose from the dead. You know how much that encourages me this morning? Here's
why it encourages me, because we have the power of the gospel. Sometimes we think,
well, if God would do some miracle, they would just believe. If God would do, no,
no, no. We got this book. This book is powerful. And Abraham says, if they won't
hear this, they're not gonna believe even if they see some great
miracle. So this morning, a faithful ambassador. I asked the question, what
kind of an ambassador am I? A plea for faithful ambassadors. Number two this
morning, the pattern of faithful ambassadors. What is the pattern? Why is it
that someone would say, why do we read in Proverbs 13, this verse of Scripture
about a faithful ambassador's health, what is it about their behavior, the
pattern of their life, that would cause someone to identify them as being a
faithful ambassador? So this morning, if we're looking at what kind of an
ambassador am I, and we're trying to determine am I a faithful ambassador,
there's certain characteristics, if you will, certain attributes about your life
and my life that should be present, the pattern of a faithful ambassador. What's
a faithful ambassador look like? Well, I believe that we see it first in the life
of the disciples. Look in Acts chapter 8, if you will. In Acts chapter number 8, we
see the faithfulness of these disciples here in this really highest point of
persecution. As we've read through the book of Acts from the first chapter till
now in chapter 8, as you understand all that's going on, this height of
persecution there in Jerusalem, it was a great persecution. The church was
scattered abroad because of this, and all the believers of the church. Now, the
thing that's interesting about Acts chapter number 8 is that the leaders of
the church, well, they stayed in Jerusalem. It was the people that were
scattered abroad. And the Bible says this in verse number 4 in Acts chapter number
8, therefore they that were scattered abroad went everywhere, what does the
Bible say? Preaching the word. You know what a faithful ambassador does? They
seize the opportunities. So, well, God's just not giving me any opportunities. Are
you praying for him? You know, sometimes what's interesting about opportunity,
sometimes they're hard to see. What do I mean by that? Well, at the moment it's
hard to see the opportunity, and afterwards you might see the opportunity
and say, man, I missed that opportunity. See, they seized the opportunity. They
went everywhere. Listen, they were facing great persecution, hardship, difficulty.
They could have left from Jerusalem, and they could have decided to do a whole
host of things because of the great persecution that they suffered, because
they had to leave. They could have complained, and they could have protested,
and they could have, but you know what they did? They went everywhere preaching
the word. They're faithful ambassadors. Can I tell you that as you look at this
portion of Scripture in Acts chapter number 8, it's in this passage where you
find the gospel gets into Samaria, the place where they would probably least
like to go. God was at work, and I'm thankful that I can look at this example,
a pattern of faithful ambassadors. They seize the opportunities. I believe that a
prayer, something like this, God, would you give me opportunity today? Would you
give me opportunity this week to speak to somebody about you? I believe that's
a kind of prayer that God would delight in answering. Amen? You say, well, I'm
praying for a Corvette. I'm not sure that's a prayer that God delights in
answering, but he delights in answering the prayer of would you give me an
opportunity to be your ambassador, your representative, to pray them, to plead
with them, to be reconciled to God, because that's the purpose of an
ambassador. I pray, God, would you give us an opportunity? And we seize the
opportunity. I see it in the life of Matthew. Turn back to Matthew chapter 9,
if you will. In Matthew chapter 9, God gives us the opportunity to read of the
calling of Matthew. Matthew was a publican, not very well liked. Amen? Tax
collector, that's what a publican is. And here's the deal. They were representing
the Roman Empire, and they could exact whatever they wanted to exact, and
whatever they got extra than the Romans required, they got to keep for themselves.
They were not well-liked people. But Jesus calls Matthew. Matthew's life has
changed. He becomes a disciple of the Lord Jesus Christ. We see it here, notice in
verse 9, and as Jesus passed forth from the fence, he saw a man named Matthew
sitting at the receipt of custom. He saith unto him, follow me. And he arose
and followed him, and it came to pass, as Jesus sat at meet in his house, in the
house, we know from Luke 5, it was Matthew's house, and it tells us that
behold, many publicans and sinners came and sat down with him and his disciples.
Again, Luke 5 tells us that it was the house of Matthew, and it tells us that
it was a great feast. When the Pharisees saw it, they said unto his disciples, why
eateth your master with publicans and sinners? Why did the Pharisees say that?
Well, because they were so, they weren't, I mean, they were so far above. They were
blinded. Jesus heard that in verse 12, and he said to them, they that behold
me, not a physician, but they that are sick, but go and learn what that meaneth.
I will have mercy and not sacrifice, for I am not come to call the righteous, but
sinners, to repentance. Why don't I bring us to this passage of Scripture to talk
about the pattern of faithful ambassadors, because I want you to see
not only seizing the opportunity from the disciples in Acts chapter 8, but I
want you to see the length by which Matthew went through. Sometimes it's going
to cost you something to be a faithful ambassador. The Bible tells us that he
opens his house, and there's a great number of people there. What was the
purpose? Was it just to have a party? No. Jesus was there, and Jesus went to talk
to these. They came and sat down, and we find that these are there, this great
company, and begin to look at Matthew, and I think about his passion, if I could
say that this morning, that after he rose and followed Jesus, you know what his
desire was? Were for others to see and meet and know who Jesus is. I referenced
it from after preaching at the youth rally a couple of weeks ago. Brother
Jeff mentioned this morning in Sunday school as well, but the reality is
that David says in Psalm 34 and verse number 8, oh taste and see that the Lord
is good, and why does he say that? Because he experienced the goodness of God, and
therefore he wanted others to experience the goodness of God. Matthew had his life
changed because of Jesus, and so now what does Matthew want to do? He wants others
to meet Jesus. I told that man Carlos yesterday that I met at his front door. I
said, listen, I just want to tell you what Jesus did for me and what he can do for
you. Why? Because Jesus is the Savior of the world. He is the one that is the way,
the truth, and the life. And this morning we begin to think about this. Listen,
there may be times that it's an inconvenience for us, quote unquote. It
may change our schedule. It might require us to take somebody and have coffee or
take somebody and have lunch. Why? Because I want to do the work of being
an ambassador. I want them to know that I truly care about them. Why? Because I want
them to be reconciled to God. I want them to go to heaven when they die, and it may
cost us something. It may cause us to have to get out of our
comfort zone. You know, we all have a comfort zone, don't we? We all have a comfort zone.
And Mary requires to get out of our comfort zone. Sit down with somebody and
ask them some questions about where they're from.
Take a little interest in their life. Why? So they can have that opportunity to be able to
share the gospel with them. To be able to share the gospel with them. Building those relationships
to be able to share the gospel. Being careful not to allow them to influence you. We've got
to be careful of that. But the reality is that we find in Matthew that after he met the Lord and
begins following him, it says that he has this feast at his house. I've invited people to my
house that are lost. I've gone and taken people to lunch. I was sharing with someone in our church
just this past week. I sat at their house and they were having some work done and they were
asking about the individual, how I met him and so on and so forth because I had given them the
recommendation. And I said, you know, this guy, he came to church a couple of times. He did some
work here and had opportunity to be able to talk to him a few times and what have you. And then I
took him to lunch one day. I sat there for a couple hours with him at lunch. Share the gospel with him.
And he grew up a different world religion and he was still kind of looking at that path, but he knew
the truth. And we chatted and he didn't get saved. I wish he did, but he didn't get saved. And I told
him this when he left that meeting. I said, listen, you ever got questions? You know, I'd love to be
able to connect with you again, so on and so forth. And just a couple of years later after that,
he had a relative die. I get a text on my phone from this guy saying, hey, would you pray for me?
He's still not saved, but you're trying to reach people, trying to reach people. Listen, I fail
more times than I do it the right way. But the reality is that sometimes it, I often say Ronnie
goes to Walmart to meet people and I don't. I go to get in and get out. But sometimes it's
a change in our schedule that God will allow us to be that faithful ambassador,
that we seize the opportunity, that we're willing to pay the price of being a faithful ambassador.
We look at the life of the Apostle Paul. He's writing. Look at Romans chapter one, if you will.
Look at a few verses in the book of Romans. He's writing to the church in Corinth and he says, we
are ambassadors. We are ambassadors. We find that the Apostle Paul understood what it was to be an
apostle, but he also understood what it was to be an ambassador. And now as the Apostle Paul is
writing to these believers in Corinth and he says, we are ambassadors for Christ. And he explains to
them the privilege and the purpose. And we now look at this truth of what does it mean to be a
faithful ambassador? The plea is provided to us, but the pattern, and we see in the life of
the Apostle Paul in verse 14 of Romans chapter one, he says, I am debtor, both to the Greeks
and to the barbarians, both to the wise and the unwise. Why does he have this perspective of being
indebted? Why is it that he looks at this from this perspective that I am debtor? What did he owe
to these individuals? Was it that he went through his whole life borrowing from people and he was
indebted to everyone? No. It was that he had been entrusted with the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And what was entrusted to him was not just for him. It was to be for all people.
Just like when we read in the account of the announcement of the birth of the Lord Jesus
Christ and they bring those good tidings, those glad tidings of great joy, that the reality is
that he says unto you, but to all people. Paul says, I'm debtor. Why? Because God gave me something
that really, yes, it saved my soul, but it's for you, to tell you about how much God loves you and
that he'd save you. So then what does he say in verse 15? So as much as in me is, I am ready
to preach the gospel to you that are at Rome also. I wonder this morning, are we prepared
to be a faithful ambassador? Could we say that we're ready when that opportunity comes, that
we're ready to seize the opportunity, that we're prayed up and we have the power of the Holy Spirit
of God, that we have the opportunity to be able to go to the book, the Bible, and be able to give
the truth of God's word? Why? Because the Bible gives clarity. The Bible is God's word and it's
profitable and it gives clarity and people will have their objections and they'll have their
comments and they'll have their thoughts from whatever religious background they have. But
the reality is we say, what does God say? What does the Bible say? And Paul says, as much as
in me is, I am ready to preach the gospel. And then he says in verse 16, for I am not ashamed
of the gospel of Christ, for it is the power of God and the salvation to everyone that believe
it, to the Jew first and also to the Greek. The reality is that in our lives, the pattern of
a faithful ambassador is that we should not be ashamed. We see a tire with the idea, bumper
stickers, other things of I am not ashamed or unashamed and what have you, and the reality is
that there are times in our lives, if we'd be honest, that we might find ourselves in a circumstance,
in a situation where we might not say that we're ashamed. We might use the word I'm a little
embarrassed or I'm a little, you know, I'm just kind of, I'm not a people person. I don't like to
talk and I just kind of, but what did we do? We failed to seize the opportunity.
And Paul says, I'm not ashamed of the gospel. Listen, I've had so many people reject and
get angry. I've had people cuss at me and whatever, tell me they're going to call the
police on me, so on and so forth. That's all fine. You know, it's not my job. It's not my
responsibility to see them trust Christ. Some plant, some water, God gives the increase.
And I don't have to be ashamed about what I know to be true because they disagree with me.
I don't have to be ashamed of it. Amen? That's my God. He's my Savior. He's my Lord.
He's my everything. Would you be ashamed of your wife or your husband? Would you be ashamed of your
children? If you're sitting there with a, if somebody says, is that your wife? And you just
kind of, no, you should, that would be terrible. Would it not? How much more wonderful is our
Savior? You say I have the best wife in the world. I'm glad you think that. I'm being sincere. I'm
glad you think that. Every husband ought to think that they have the best wife in the world. Amen?
But I want you to know that as Joy Clemens sang from this pulpit, somebody reminded me of that
this past week, he is more than wonderful. He's more than your mind can conceive. Our God is so
great and I should not be ashamed of him. A faithful ambassador is going to seize the
opportunities. They're going to go out of their way. They're going to allow for their schedule
to be interrupted. Pay a price. They're going to be unashamed. We find that in the book of Romans,
Paul says in chapter 9 and chapter 10, he makes these statements about having this desire and
this heaviness that his brethren, his kinsmen, according to the flesh, speaking of Jewish,
other Jewish people, that they would be saved. Notice in Romans chapter 9 and beginning in verse
number one, he says, I say the truth in Christ, I lie not, my conscience also bearing me witness in
the Holy Ghost that I have great heaviness and continual sorrow in my heart. Why? For I could
wish that myself were accursed from Christ for my brethren, my kinsmen, according to the flesh.
Notice in chapter 10 in verse number one, brethren, my heart's desire and prayer to God for Israel is
that they might be saved. Notice what Paul is saying. In chapter 9 and chapter 10, Paul has
this heavy heart. Listen, Paul was going to heaven. There's no doubt that if you read
the New Testament, there's absolutely no doubt that Paul had confidence in his conversion.
There's absolutely no doubt that the Apostle Paul knew to be absent from the body was to be
present with the Lord. He knew that he was going to heaven. In fact, he says of the believers in
Philippi that he was in a straight betwixt two. What was the straight betwixt two? Having a
desire to part, to be with Christ, which is far better. And he had said to the same church in
Philippi, those believers, for me to live as Christ, but to die as gain. Why? Because I'm
going to heaven. But Paul had this burden for others to be saved. Can I tell you that a faithful
ambassador should have a burden, a burden for people to be saved, to come to the truth of
salvation, to the knowledge of the Lord Jesus Christ. You should have a burden, a burden.
I preached before, I mentioned a few weeks ago, I didn't preach the message, but I referenced
the message where the man of God wept. Paul served and ministered with tears. He had a
burden for people. And I wonder, as we think about this truth of a faithful ambassador,
we ought to have a burden.
I know that in our prayer list that we have a list for salvations on Wednesday evening
and we have names on there.
But I wonder, you know who the best person is to pray for those people?
Is the one that put the name on the list.
You know why?
I don't know who most of them are.
But you do.
And whoever else is reading our prayer bulletin, they don't know who most of them are.
Because you put them on the list.
And you should have a burden for lost people.
Why do we go out and try to share the gospel?
Well, because we're commanded to do so.
And that's the number one reason.
We go out of obedience.
But can I tell you that we ought to have a burden.
We have a burden.
Habakkuk had a burden.
Paul had a burden.
In Romans chapter number 15, notice what Paul says nearing the end of this book.
Romans chapter 15 and verse 19.
In Romans 15 verse 19, through mighty signs and wonders by the power of the Spirit of
God so that from Jerusalem and round about unto Illyricum, I have fully preached the
gospel of Christ, yea, so I have strived to preach the gospel now where Christ was named
lest I should build upon another man's foundation, but as it is written to whom he was not spoken
of, they shall see, and they that have not heard shall understand.
We don't want to take the time to look at Romans 10 when Paul says, how shall they hear
without a preacher?
Listen this morning, we see that there's a plea for faithful ambassadors.
First from our loving Savior, then from a lost sinner.
We see there's a pattern for faithful ambassadors.
But I want you to see finally this morning, and we'll make it quick.
Chapter three this morning, a prize for faithful ambassadors, a prize for faithful ambassadors.
This morning as I begin to think about this truth and the understanding that one day I'll
see my Savior face to face, what a glorious day that will be.
But I would submit to you this morning that outside of your own salvation, the greatest
privilege of a Christian is to see a lost sinner bow their head and trust Christ as
their personal Savior.
Is absolutely glorious to have that opportunity.
If you've ever had that opportunity, you know how wonderful it is that God would allow you
to be the vessel.
You can't save anybody, I can't save anybody, Jesus is the Savior.
But He chose to use us as His ambassadors, and there's a prize.
The Bible speaks about crowns, and we understand this truth, but we look this morning and we
begin to understand the privilege of telling someone about Jesus.
And then when someone bows their head and their heart and they accept the Lord Jesus
Christ as their personal Savior, I mean, hallelujah, it is absolutely wonderful.
It's the greatest experience outside of your own personal salvation, your own personal
conversion that I believe you can have as a Christian.
It's awesome when you would have the privilege of seeing that.
When we begin to think about this prize, I would say that there's a two-fold aspect of
the prize for faithful ambassadors.
The first aspect would be that we're pleasing our Savior today.
We're pleasing our Savior today.
If you're a faithful ambassador, then God is pleased with you.
We find that it is true that as we live our lives that we can live in such a way that
is pleasing to Him, and we understand that we can live in such a way that God is not
well-pleased.
And I believe this morning that having God's favor upon us and God being pleased with us
is a great reward.
I pray for God's favor.
But you understand that God's favor comes to those who are living in obedience.
I'm thankful that the Bible says the goodness of God leadeth to the repentance.
But the reality this morning is that God's hand of favor, His good hand of favor is upon
those that are living a life of obedience.
The second aspect of this prize for faithful ambassadors is seeing fruit in eternity.
I want you to understand this morning that as a faithful ambassador, again, it's God
who gives the increase.
But I would argue that if you're not actively planting and watering, you're probably not
going to be the one that's going to see the increase, even though God's the one that gives
it.
So as you're engaged in that ministry of giving and being a faithful ambassador, what joy
to think about seeing fruit in eternity.
I'm talking about being in heaven.
Listen, the most wonderful thing about heaven is seeing our Savior.
In fact, if our Savior's not there, it's not heaven.
That's what people talk about the streets of gold and listen, what makes heaven heaven
is the presence of our Savior.
We understand that this morning.
But can you imagine having the privilege of seeing someone else in heaven for all of eternity
because God allowed you to be the vessel to share Christ with them?
That's awesome to think about that, that there'd be others in heaven.
Listen, if you've ever led someone to Christ, if you've ever had the opportunity to see
I can think if I can see images in my head right now of people that one day I will see
in heaven, that God allowed me.
I'm going to see a lot of people in heaven, but there's some people that I'm going to
see that God let me personally be involved in seeing them saved.
That's awesome.
In 1 Thessalonians chapter 2, notice what Paul says as he's writing to this church.
It's a church that Paul had the privilege of being able to go and preach the gospel
in the city of Thessalonica and people got saved and there's great persecution and opposition
and all those things going on.
But now as Paul is writing back to this church in Thessalonica, notice what the Bible says
in verse 19, and we're catching the very end of this chapter in the thought here, but
notice he says, for what is our hope or joy or crown of rejoicing, notice this, are not
even ye in the presence of our Lord Jesus Christ that is coming, for ye are our glory
and joy.
You know what I think Paul had in his mind as he's writing, obviously in the inspiration
of the Holy Spirit of God, I believe that he had in his mind and in his heart as he's
writing these verses that there are going to be people that he has the privilege of
seeing in glory because they got saved.
Why did they get saved?
Because the gospel is the power of God unto salvation.
But how did they hear?
They had to have a preacher.
Paul understood he was an apostle, but he understood he was an ambassador.
And Paul went to Thessalonica and he went there and he preached the gospel and people
got saved.
God used him as the instrument, as the vessel to give them the gospel.
And Paul says, you're our glory and our joy.
I wonder this morning, is there anyone in your mind that you can see at this moment
that you'll see in heaven?
Because God allowed you the opportunity to share the gospel with them and they got saved.
I hope that there's several that you can see.
The prize for faithful ambassadors.
I'm going to remind you of a song.
We read some of it a few weeks ago when Brother Gardner was here on that Sunday night.
The title of the song is, Have I Done My Best for Jesus?
But I just want you to think this morning about the first two lines of the chorus for
that song.
Of course, as we sing the songs, we sing the verse and then the chorus, the verse, the
chorus, the verse, the chorus, the chorus is sung repeatedly.
The first two lines of the chorus of that great hymn are this.
How many are the lost that I have lifted?
It's what the songwriter wrote.
The second line says this, how many are the chained I've helped to free?
I can't save anyone and neither can you.
But God chose to use us.
And here's the reality this morning, if you're saved by the grace of God, if you're saved
by the grace of God, you're an ambassador.
If you're not saved this morning, you need to be saved because you're lost and like the
rich man in Luke 16, you're going to spend eternity in a lake of fire because of your
sin.
It's not because God doesn't love you, it's because of your sin.
The wage of sin is death.
God loves you so much that He sent Jesus to die for you, to pay for your sin so that you
could be saved and He wants you to be reconciled.
But this morning, if you're saved, you're an ambassador.
The question is this, what kind of an ambassador?
am I? And only you can answer the question. Only I can answer the question for myself.
What kind of an ambassador am I? Because the wise man under the inspirational Holy Spirit
of God in Proverbs said, a faithful ambassador bringeth health. Oh, that God would help us
to be faithful ambassadors. Let's pray. Father, we love you this morning. We thank you for
loving us. We thank you for the truth of your word. And God, I pray that in these moments
of invitation that you'd have your will in way. God, I've made it clear already the questions
that ought to be pondered. So now we trust you to work in hearts and lives as only you
can. If there's one lost, I pray they'd come. We could take a Bible and trust Christ today.
I pray for those that are saved. We are ambassadors. What kind of an ambassador am I? Lord, have
your will in way. Work as only you can. We'll thank you for it in Christ's name, we pray.
Would you stand with me? Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano. As she does,
the altar is open. If the Lord spoke to you this morning, the altar is open. Do business
with God.