pairing, and I certainly appreciate all of the hard work,
and appreciate Ron and Mady doing the decorations.
They were here late last night finishing up,
and always appreciate them doing the decorations
here in the church, and certainly thankful,
as I mentioned, Brother Ron is traveling,
and he's heading down to Georgia.
Take your Bibles.
I know I have Acts chapter 20,
but I want you to start in the book
of 1 Corinthians chapter number nine.
We're gonna look at a few passages of scripture
before we find our way to Acts chapter number 20
this morning, and so eventually we'll get there.
Last week, we had the opportunity,
as we gathered together, to be challenged
to evaluate our service to the Lord,
and we considered this thought last week.
For the audience of one, we must remember
that our service is indeed for the audience of one.
It's for the Lord Jesus Christ,
and that at the same time, we understand
that it will have an impact on many,
and I begin to think about that truth,
and as we examined that portion of scripture last week,
and really understanding that God has called us
to be his servants, and what a great privilege it is
to serve the Lord, that we singularly are seeking
to serve Christ for the audience of one,
but there are many that will be impacted by our service.
There are people that are watching us,
people that are observing us, people that will be influenced
and impacted by our service, may I say it this way,
or lack thereof, amen, and people are watching,
and people are certainly seeing the example
that we are setting, and our service is
for the audience of one, it's for the Lord Jesus Christ,
seeking to please him alone, but many will be impacted.
I believe that as you study the New Testament,
you would agree with me that the Lord used
the apostle Paul in a variety of ways.
In fact, as you read through the New Testament,
you'll find that God chose to record many details
about the life of Paul.
We had the privilege of reading through the book of Acts,
we'll be in Acts chapter number 20 here shortly.
We had the opportunity to read in the book of Acts
various aspects of the missionary journeys
that God allowed for the apostle Paul to go on.
We find that as we read the New Testament books
that God would use several of them,
the human penman, he would use Paul to pen those books,
and through those books, we have the opportunity
to not only learn about the ministry of the apostle Paul
and how he was ministering to others and encouraging them,
but also we have the opportunity to evaluate
his own service to the Lord.
And we find that as we study the New Testament,
and again, as we have the opportunity to study
the life of the apostle Paul in the New Testament,
I believe this morning, truly, the apostle Paul
served for the audience of one.
He served the Lord Jesus Christ.
He was not interested in pleasing certain groups of people,
as he would go from place to place and minister.
He was serving the Lord Jesus Christ
for the audience of one.
I believe truly this morning
that the apostle Paul had the desire,
in fact, we'll see it in Acts chapter number 20,
that he would finish his race, his course with joy,
that he would hear, well done thou good and faithful servant
and that he would finish what God had called him to do.
I believe that he had that aspect or that perspective
for the audience of one,
but it's obviously clear, abundantly clear,
as you read through the New Testament,
that his service not only was pleasing to God,
but it has impacted generations of believers.
Not only those in the first century that knew
and Paul ministered to them personally,
but for centuries now, we've had the complete canon
of the New Testament, of God's word,
and we have the New Testament, and as we study,
as we dig into the New Testament, still to this very day,
the life and service of the apostle Paul
is impacting scores of believers,
and for that, we ought to be thankful.
You think about your life,
and obviously, as God gives us life,
it's just but for a moment.
James says it this way, what is your life?
It appears for a little time and then vanisheth away,
and we understand that to be true.
We understand the brevity of life,
and as we begin to think about the brevity of life
and thinking about how God would use us in our lifetime
to serve him and to impact individuals,
but then to consider that God will allow our lives
after we leave this earth
to continue to impact generations.
That's amazing, and that's certainly something
that God can do in and through each of our lives.
As we look at a few of these passages
starting in 1 Corinthians 9,
I believe in these few passages that we're gonna read
as we lay the groundwork for getting
to Acts chapter number 20,
that really in these portions of scripture
starting in 1 Corinthians 9,
God provides us with a record
of really Paul's approach to serving the Lord.
What was it that shaped the ministry of the apostle Paul?
What was it that gave him the framework,
the philosophy of ministry, if you will?
Why is it that we speak of and look at the New Testament
and see the service of Paul
and say this is commendable and noteworthy
and exemplary, his service to God?
Well, I believe that God gives us some insight
as we'll see in a few of these passages.
Notice in 1 Corinthians 9, in verse number 23,
the Bible says this,
Paul is speaking to these believers in Corinth,
and he says, and this I do for the gospel's sake.
If you were to look back into the chapter,
you find verse number 16
about the responsibility of preaching the gospel
and that God had called him to this,
and he says, this I do for the gospel's sake,
that I might be partaker thereof with you.
Know ye not that they which run in a race run all,
but one receiveth the prize.
He says this, so run that ye may obtain.
That phrase is the phrase that I've used
for our title of our message this morning,
so run that ye may obtain.
He says in verse 25,
and every man that striveth for the mastery
is temperate in all things.
Now they do it to obtain a corruptible crown,
but notice we, an incorruptible.
I therefore so run, not as uncertainly,
so fight I not as one that beateth the air,
but I keep under my body and bring it into subjection,
lest that by any means, when I have preached to others,
I myself should be a castaway.
That idea is really to be useless or of no value,
and Paul is saying, I do this for the gospel's sake,
thinking about the audience of one,
but also that I might be partaker thereof with you,
the impact that it would have on many.
And he says, this I do, this is my approach,
this is how I'm serving the Lord, why?
Because I'm running that I might obtain.
So run that ye may obtain.
He tells that to the believers at Corinth,
but Paul himself, I believe,
is seeking to serve the Lord in that manner.
A familiar verse of scripture to us is Galatians 2,
if you turn over to that portion of scripture
in Galatians chapter number two,
and we find that Paul gives this great climatic statement,
if you will, with regard to his view of his own self
and his ministry to the Lord
and understanding his place of service.
He says in Galatians 2 in verse number 20,
I am crucified with Christ.
Nevertheless, I live.
Yet not I, but Christ liveth in me,
and the life which I now live in the flesh,
I live by the faith of the Son of God who loved me
and gave himself for me.
The Apostle Paul was living the crucified life
as we've often referred to it as,
and we find that he was all in,
he was surrendered to the Lord,
and we begin to think about his surrender
and his service to Christ and how he understood.
And again, as we begin to look at these few passages
to develop and understand the framework,
the approach that the Apostle Paul
to have in his service to the Lord,
it will help us as we too serve the Lord.
The book of Philippians,
just a few pages over in your Bible,
Philippians chapter number three.
In Philippians chapter number three,
we really could read verses four through 14,
but for sake of time, I want you to jot that passage down
so that you could read the entirety of it.
For sake of time, I'm gonna pick it up
in verse number 11 down through verse number 14.
But again, notice the approach
that Paul has in serving the Lord.
He says this in verse number 11 of Philippians three,
if by any means I might attain
unto the resurrection of the dead,
not as though I had already attained,
either were already perfect.
In other words, I have not arrived,
neither have you, neither have I.
He says, but I follow after,
if that I may apprehend that
for which also I am apprehended of Christ Jesus.
Brethren, I count not myself to have apprehended,
but this one thing I do,
forgetting those things which are behind
and reaching forth unto those things which are before.
I press, do you see the imagery that God gives us
as Paul is sharing his approach to ministry?
I press toward the mark
for the prize of the high calling of God in Christ Jesus.
He's not being, if it's convenient, if it's comfortable.
No, he says, I'm pressing toward the mark,
so run that you may obtain.
He shares that in First Corinthians nine.
He says here in Philippians three
that he is seeking and following after the Lord.
He wants to apprehend that
for which he was apprehended of Christ.
He wants to press toward the mark
for the prize of the high calling of God in Christ Jesus.
One day, each of us will stand,
if you're saved this morning,
if you've trusted the Lord Jesus Christ
as your personal Savior,
you will stand at the judgment seat of Christ.
And I'm looking forward to the opportunity,
Lord willing to hear, well done,
good and faithful servant, and to receive crowns of service.
Remember, it's God who has enabled us,
who has equipped us, who has called us,
but then he rewards us for serving him.
It's an amazing truth of God's word.
And I hope this morning that each of us
would have that understanding
that when I stand before the Lord,
that I would not have that wood, hay, and stubble
that will be burned up,
but that we'd have that silver, gold, and precious stone
that we would serve the Lord acceptably,
that we would serve him faithfully.
And we find here that the Apostle Paul,
this is what he's doing.
He's pressing toward the mark.
Again, if you would think about the imagery,
you see someone who is constant and consistent.
Notice one final passage, 2 Timothy chapter four,
before we get to the book of Acts.
In 2 Timothy chapter number four,
it's a familiar portion of scripture.
Paul, this is the last letter
that God would use the Apostle Paul to pen
before he would be martyred for the faith.
And he's writing it to his son in the faith.
He's writing it to Timothy.
He's seeking to influence and instruct
and to encourage Timothy to continue to serve the Lord
and to finish his course, to finish his race.
But Paul says in 2 Timothy four and verse number six,
for I am now ready to be offered.
So Paul's ministry has come to an end.
It's come to a conclusion.
He understands that the time of his departure is at hand.
It was not just that he was going to depart
from a particular location in that his ministry
in that locale was completed.
No, it was that he was going to go home.
Remember, he said in 2 Corinthians,
to be absent from the body is to be present with the Lord.
Paul understood that this was the end
of his earthly ministry, the end of his earthly life.
He would soon face a martyr's death.
He says, the time of my departure is at hand.
But notice he says, I have fought a good fight.
I have finished my course.
I have kept the faith.
Oh, that God wouldn't allow each of us
at the end of our lives to be able to say
what Paul says in verse number seven,
that it would not be, I wish I would have.
If only I would have, if I could change this.
No, I don't want to have those types of regrets.
And we see that Paul, he was not perfect,
but he was a man who was surrendered to the Lord.
He was a man who was committed to serving Christ.
And he says, I have fought a good fight.
I have finished my course.
I have kept the faith.
Notice verse number eight, henceforth,
there is laid up for me a crown of righteousness.
Remember, we said in First Corinthians nine,
he says, they run to obtain a corruptible,
but we an incorruptible.
He says, so run that ye may obtain.
And Paul had this, this isn't pride,
but he has this confidence that there is laid up for him,
for me, a crown of righteousness.
There are five crowns that are mentioned
in the New Testament.
We won't take time to deal with that this morning,
but this is one of the five.
He says, a crown of righteousness,
notice, which the Lord, the righteous judge,
by the way, he is a righteous judge,
shall give me at that day.
But notice the end of the verse.
And not to me only, but unto all them also
that love his appearing.
So this morning, just as the apostle Paul
could have confidence of receiving this crown,
as he said that he was pressing toward that mark,
he wanted to receive that well done.
And we find that he says,
there is a crown of righteousness that the Lord,
the righteous judge, shall give me at that day.
So this morning, as we begin to think about our service
to the Lord, as we consider last week's message
for the audience of one,
we understand that God has called us
and God has equipped us and we're serving the Lord,
but it will have an impact on many.
I look to Acts chapter number 20.
And in Acts chapter number 20,
we have the opportunity to see and to read
of an interaction between the apostle Paul
and the church leaders of the church at Ephesus.
The apostle Paul, historically,
at this particular time in his life,
in Acts chapter number 20, he's on his way to Jerusalem.
And as he's heading towards Jerusalem,
he's really going and traveling with haste
because he's desiring to be there at the day of Pentecost.
And because of that, he would not have opportunity
within his schedule to stop in at Ephesus
and have any interaction with those church leaders.
So what does he do?
He calls for those church leaders to meet him.
And here is the conversation that God records for us
between the apostle Paul and the church leaders at Ephesus.
And in this particular portion of scripture,
this few verses we're gonna look at this morning,
I believe that God gives us four aspects of Paul's service
that would be helpful for each of us today
to be able to apply in our own lives.
Notice the Bible says, beginning in Acts chapter number 20
and verse number 17, and from Miletus,
he sent to Ephesus and called for the elders of the church.
And when they were come to him, he said unto them,
and so Paul was addressing these church leaders.
He's going to share personal testimony of his own ministry,
but then he's gonna encourage them
with regard to their service to Christ
and their time that they have to minister.
And he says this in verse number 18,
ye know from the first day that I came into Asia
after what manner I have been with you at all seasons,
serving the Lord with all humility of mind
and with many tears and temptations,
which befell me by the lying in wait of the Jews,
and how I kept back nothing that was profitable unto you,
but have showed you and have taught you publicly
and from house to house, testifying both to the Jews
and also to the Greeks repentance toward God
and faith toward our Lord Jesus Christ.
And now behold, I go bound in the spirit unto Jerusalem,
not knowing the things that shall befall me there,
save that the Holy Ghost witnesses in every city
saying that bonds and afflictions abide me.
Verse 24, but none of these things move me,
neither count I my life dear unto myself,
so that I might finish my course with joy
in the ministry which I have received of the Lord Jesus
to testify the gospel of the grace of God.
And now behold, I know that ye all among whom
I have gone preaching the kingdom of God
shall see my face no more.
Wherefore, I take you to record this day
that I am pure from the blood of all men,
for I have not shunned to declare unto you
all the counsel of God.
So verse 27 concludes Paul sharing at that point
his testimony of his service and rehearsing to them.
He's going to continue making some references,
but now he's addressing them,
these leaders of the church at Ephesus
with regard to their service.
Verse 28, take heed therefore unto yourselves
and to all the flock over the which the Holy Ghost
hath made you overseers to feed the church of God
which he hath purchased with his own blood.
For I know this, that after my departing
shall grievous wolves enter in among you,
not sparing the flock, also of your own selves
shall men arise speaking perverse things
to draw away disciples after them.
Therefore, watch and remember that by the space
of three years, I, again he's speaking
about his own ministry, cease not to warn everyone
night and day with tears, and now brethren,
I commend you to God and to the word of his grace
which is able to build you up and to give you
an inheritance among all them that are sanctified.
I have coveted no man's silver or gold or apparel,
yea, ye yourselves know that these hands
have ministered unto my necessities
and to them that were with me.
I have showed you all things, so laboring
you ought to support the weak and to remember
the words of the Lord Jesus, how he said
it is more blessed to give than to receive.
Notice verse 36, and when he had thus spoken,
he kneeled down and prayed with them all.
So Paul addresses these believers,
these church leaders from Ephesus,
he calls them and they meet together,
and within this passage of scripture,
there's great truth that is revealed to us,
but I find four specific aspects of Paul's ministry
and how it is that in verse 24 he could say
that I might finish my course with joy,
and the ministry, notice, that I have received
of the Lord Jesus, he's given each of us a ministry.
Your ministry differs than Paul's ministry
and your ministry probably differs
than the person sitting around you,
but God has equipped us and he's called us
to serve him and Paul says I desire to finish
my course with joy, understanding that this ministry
has been given to me and trusted to me
by the Lord Jesus, and we find that he's able
to say at the end of his life, I have finished,
I've kept the faith, I've finished my course,
and he knew that there was a crown of righteousness,
so he says, and I believe that he believed this
for himself in First Corinthians nine,
so run that ye may obtain, he's saying that
to the believers in Corinth, he says it to himself,
probably to others as well, and understanding
this morning that Paul served the Lord,
if you're taking notes, number one,
he served the Lord humbly, humbly, he was a humble man.
Humility is necessary in our service to Christ.
It's absolutely essential.
Notice the Bible says in verse number 19,
serving the Lord with all humility of mind
and with many tears and temptations,
which befell me by the lying in wait of the Jews.
Humility in service to the king is absolutely essential.
It's absolutely essential.
Why do we say that?
Well, because the Bible tells us
that God resisteth the proud,
but giveth grace unto the humble.
As we serve the Lord Jesus Christ,
we understand that it is he that has called us,
it is he that has equipped us, he has enabled us.
Paul said that he was thankful that God enabled him
and that he put him into the ministry,
and we find this morning that as Paul
is serving the Lord as we get some insight here
in Acts chapter.
20 with regard to his manner of service, we find that he served the Lord humbly.
Listen, this morning, it's essential. Notice in Philippians chapter number 2,
notice what Paul says as he's speaking to these believers in Philippi. Of course,
he's addressing there in Acts chapter number 20 the church leaders of Ephesus,
but I want you to see what Paul says about humility. As we look here in
Philippians chapter number 2, he says this in verse number 3 of Philippians 2,
let nothing be done. Now, if he says let nothing be done, that's pretty
all-inclusive, is it not? And so that certainly would include our service to
Christ. He says let nothing be done through strife or vain glory, but in
lowliness of mind let each esteem other better than themselves. Look, not every
man on his own things, but every man also on the things of others. But then we find
in verse number 5, there's this great truth that Paul gives to these believers
at Philippi and to us by way of preservation. The Bible says let this
mind be in you, which was also in Christ Jesus. You know, he is, the Lord Jesus
Christ is God. He's God. God in flesh. The beginning was the Word, and the Word was
with God, and the Word was God. Amen? And the Word became flesh and dwelt among us,
tabernacled among us, John chapter number 1. And you see, and obviously there's a
variety of passages of Scripture that prove the deity of Christ. We celebrate
this time of year on our calendars, the Incarnation, the fact that God came to
this earth, and we find the deity of Christ, that He is God. Where is He that
is born? King of the Jews. They bowed down and worshipped Him, is what the Bible
tells us. Why? Because He's God. But He was humble. He humbled Himself. Now think
about that just for a moment. We're to serve the Lord humbly as Paul did, but we
find that Paul makes this approach an appeal to the church at Philippi. He says
let this mind be in you, which was also in Christ Jesus. In verse number 8, he
says, being found in fashion as a man, he humbled himself and became obedient unto
death, even the death of the cross. Why? So that he could pay for your sins and
mine. And he humbled himself. He's the Creator God. You read John 17, and you
read about the glory that He had with the Father, and eternity passed, and yet
He left the glories of heaven, the splendor of heaven, to come to this
sin-cursed world so they could die for us. As we serve the Lord, we must also
serve Him humbly. We must understand this morning that it is easy for us to become
prideful. It is easy for us to become full of ourselves and to think that we're
something, but reality is that we're just sinners saved by grace. I'm thankful to be
a saint. I'm thankful that Christ is in me, and I'm in Him, and I'm thankful that
I'm heaven-bound, but we must serve the Lord with humility. First Peter says it
this way, that we're to be clothed with humility, and then a reference
that we see not only in First Peter 5, but also James 4, for God resisted the
proud and giveth grace to the humble. This morning as we serve the Lord, we
must serve Him humbly. Let me say this morning that Paul was a servant. He says
that I was serving the Lord with all humility of mind. We must not only serve
the Lord humbly as Paul did, but number two, we must serve the Lord
compassionately. Compassionately. Someone said, I'm not sure who it is, we've used
this phrase before, but often you'll find in life that people don't really
care how much you know until they know how much you care. No doubt you've heard
that at some point in your life, and we find that the Apostle Paul was a man who
served the Lord with compassion. He served the Lord compassionately. I would
understand this morning that even as our Lord was humble, our Lord too was
compassionate. Matthew 9 and verse 36 tells us that the Lord, He saw the
multitudes and He was moved with compassion. Why do we say that the
Apostle Paul served with compassion? Why did he serve the Lord compassionately?
Well, notice in verse 19 it says, serving the Lord with all humility of mind, but
notice, and with many tears. Skip down and look at verse 31. It says, therefore
watch and remember that by the space of three years I ceased not to warn everyone
night and day with what? With tears. Why Paul? Why do you have tears, Paul? Well,
because Paul understood the fact that every person that he came into contact
with was going to spend eternity in the lake of fire if they did not trust the
Lord Jesus Christ as their personal Savior, and he was compassionate. He
cared about people. I mean this statement as we studied on Wednesday nights going
through the book of Ruth, how that we learned from Boaz that he was a man who
took interest in individuals. He was a man who stopped even in the busyness of
his life and all the responsibilities that he had to be able to care
about people. And this morning we see that Paul was a man that served the Lord
compassionately, compassionately. You know, sometimes we get branded as not being
compassionate, not really caring, but the reality is that we should be the ones
that care the most because we know the truth. As I begin to think about the
truth of compassion and the importance for you and for me this morning to be
compassionate in our service to Christ, we're mindful of the fact that we are
seeking to reach individuals that have been influenced. Listen, they're lost. The
God of this world has blinded the minds of them that believe not. When we think
about sharing the gospel with people, we understand that we at times we're called
to minister to people that oppose themselves. Paul speaks of that in 1st
Timothy and that we're to do it with meekness, the Bible says. And here we find
that Paul, he's serving the Lord compassionately. We begin to think about
the ministry of the Apostle Paul. We begin to look at the impact that Paul
had and how God used the Apostle Paul to not only bring honor and glory to Christ
and he's serving the Lord Christ as a singular focus for the audience of one,
but generations of believers have been influenced and impacted by the ministry
of the Apostle Paul. So what is it about his approach to ministry that is
exemplary for us that we could say that too is the manner by which we should
serve the Lord? Because if he served the Lord and he pleased God, and if he served
the Lord and he made an impact, then I can learn from his approach to service and I
can adopt in my own life how I too can serve Christ so that I can be pleasing
to the Lord and so that I can impact. Does that make sense? And so we find that
he served the Lord humbly, he served the Lord compassionately. Look if you will
in 1 Thessalonians chapter number 2. Often we've said as we've studied through
the New Testament that there's no perfect church. By the way, this church is not a
perfect church. There are no perfect churches, but we serve a perfect God.
We have a perfect book. Amen? We're imperfect people, but we have a perfect
God and a perfect book and we seek to do all things in honor and glory to our God.
There's no perfect church. The church in Thessalonica is a model church,
no doubt. As you look throughout the New Testament, you have the opportunity to see
a number of different churches. You'll find that some churches are not model
churches. The church at Corinth is probably the top of that list of this is
not a model church. There's some things you can learn about their behavior and
their actions of not to do, not to incorporate in your ministry. But when we
think about the church at Thessalonica, we find that they're a model church and
there's much about this church that we can have the opportunity to say there's
some things that we can learn and apply from our lives. But as we think about the
church in Thessalonica and we think about their influence in the place that
they have of being a model church, we find that within the content of this
first letter that Paul reveals to us his compassion, his compassionate
approach. When he comes to Thessalonica, just like as he had gone to other cities
during his ministries, during his missionary journeys, it was often met
with some contention. It was often met with opposition. We find that such was
the case even in Thessalonica, but we find that the Bible tells us, notice in
1 Thessalonians 2, in verse number 5, the Bible says,
Isn't that a great verse of Scripture?
Paul, you were handling the Word of life, you were handling the Word of God, you were
handling eternal matters. Yes, but I was compassionate. I came in humbly. Notice
it says that we sought not glory in verse number 6, nor of men sought we glory,
neither of you nor yet of others. And we find that he was humble, but he also says
that he came in and he was gentle among them. And then he uses this imagery that
we find at the end of verse number 7 that's so impactful, where the Bible says,
Even as a nurse cherisheth her children. And Paul says that was our approach to
ministry. We're compassionate. Verse number 8, So being affectionately desirous
of you, we were willing to have imparted unto you, not the gospel of God only, but
also our own souls. Why? Because ye were dear unto us.
I wonder this morning, as we evaluate our ministry and our service to God,
I wonder, are we serving Christ humbly?
I wonder this morning, are we serving Christ compassionately?
Are there people in your life and in my life that know that we care about them?
That we're gentle, that they know that they're dear unto us?
Listen, I'm not suggesting that we change our message.
I'm not suggesting that we compromise on what thus saith the Lord,
because God's word is true, and we must stand on the precepts of God's word,
and I believe ultimately that being loving is speaking the truth.
It is not very compassionate of me to see somebody that's opposing themselves,
that's living in disobedience, that's following after whatever they're following after,
and me to just put my arm around them and say,
love you man, everything's going to be okay.
That's not really love, would you agree this morning?
But I can put my arm around them and say,
listen, can I share with you the truth of God's word?
It's amazing when we begin to think about the power that God has given us in His word,
and the power of compassion.
Listen, when people understand that you actually care about them, that you love them,
that we can show the love of Christ.
By the way, you can't do that in your own power, in your own flesh.
You can only do that through the power and work of the Holy Spirit of God.
It's the only way to do it.
And we love people, and we show that compassion.
What a blessing to think about Paul's ministry and his service.
We see in Acts 20 that he served the Lord humbly, he served the Lord compassionately.
Let me say this, Paul served, number three, Paul served the Lord passionately, passionately.
You know, I'm thankful for some passionate people.
I remember one time somebody saying to me, this is probably 11 years ago,
I've been here for almost 12 and a half years, probably 11 years ago.
And it was a teenager, Luke is probably a little bit older than you.
But I remember he just struggled coming to church, and I was trying to talk to him.
And he said this, he said, well, the Bible's just boring.
That's what he said to me.
I said, well, let me ask you this.
Do you think that I think the Bible's boring?
Oh, no, I don't think you think the Bible's boring.
I mean, you're like passionate about this stuff.
That was, I was glad to hear that.
Why?
Because the Bible's not boring.
And what that young man saw was somebody that actually believed what they were preaching.
They're passionate about it.
You've met people that are passionate.
We joke sometimes with the Fesdections that everything that Zachary does, he does with
all of his being.
Pierre, amen and amen, right?
I mean, he's all in.
I got pictures of Zachary.
When he's throwing water balloons at VBS this past year.
And I mean, I don't know who took the picture, but I mean, it captured perfectly in one shot
all of the passion of Zachary.
Listen, we ought to be passionate in our service for Christ.
People ought to know that we truly believe the message that we're proclaiming and that
we're passionate about it.
Notice in verse number 20 of Acts 20, the Bible says this.
Why do I say that Paul was passionate?
Well, it says that in how I kept back nothing that was profitable unto you.
Now, can I pause just for a moment and can I tell you this morning that we have been
called to deliver a message that is profitable to people that often do not know that the
message is profitable?
Do you understand what I just said?
God has called us to deliver a message that is profitable to people who often do not know
that that message is profitable.
But still, we're called to proclaim the message.
He says that he held back, I kept back nothing that was profitable unto you.
Notice as you look at verse 21, he says, testifying both of the Jews and also to the
Greeks, repentance toward God and faith toward our Lord Jesus Christ.
He's preaching this message of salvation, and he's preaching it, I believe, with passion.
As you look at the Apostle Paul, as he travels from one town to the next town to the next
town, from one city to the next, he's facing opposition and he's facing persecution, and
yet he's going in and he's preaching, and I believe, with passion.
We find that in verse 29 and 30, he gives us some insight as he's giving the instruction
to the church leaders of Ephesus with regard to their ministry and feeding the church of
God.
He says this in verse 29 and 30, for I know this, that after my departing shall grievous
wolves enter in among you, not sparing the flock, also of your own selves shall men arise
speaking perverse things to draw away disciples after them.
Therefore, we should be passionate about our ministry.
Listen, do you want, think about the imagery, as you understand the Bible gives us the imagery
that we're sheep, he's the shepherd, the pastor has been called as an under-shepherd,
if we could use that terminology, and he says that there are going to be some grievous wolves
that are going to come in and they're not going to spare the flock.
We've got to be passionate.
Can I tell you this morning that the other side is passionate?
The other side is passionate?
They're passionate about what they believe.
They're passionate, and sometimes we just sit on the sidelines and serve God with passion.
Listen, compassionately, but with passion.
I'm thankful that God's given us truth.
I'm thankful that I know the truth and I can be passionate about it.
Notice this interaction.
If you turn to Acts 26, we're going to jump right in the middle of the context of the
passage of Scripture, but so that we can understand what's happening, Paul is giving a defense
here before Agrippa.
He's given a defense before Festus already and Felix and what have you, and he's had
this opportunity, and he's standing before and giving testimony, and here in Acts 26,
he's standing before Agrippa.
And as he's standing before Agrippa, again, we won't take the time, we don't have the
time to go through all that Paul is speaking to him, but he's preaching, he's giving
the truth about his own testimony of salvation and conversion, and notice if we jump in at
verse number 24, and as he thus spake for himself, so Paul is preaching, I mean, I think
he's preaching with passion, he's sharing the truth with Agrippa, and others are there.
The Bible says that Festus stands up with a loud voice.
Notice it says, Paul, thou art beside thyself.
Much learning doth make thee mad.
Crazy.
Festus is in opposition to what Paul is saying, but I think that as Paul was standing there
before Agrippa and that group of dignitaries that were gathered, that Paul was speaking
with passion.
I believe that Festus was under conviction, no doubt Agrippa too will be under conviction
as we look here at this text of Scripture, but we find that Paul, he says in verse number
25 as he responds to Festus, he says, I am not mad, most noble Festus, but speak forth
the words of truth and soberness.
And we ought to be passionate about it.
Listen, there are still people today, believe it or not, that are passionate about the football
team in Washington.
I don't know how many years they've lost for.
I don't know that they've ever had a winning record since I've lived here, all right?
I remember when I first moved here, and I'm not a huge sports fan.
I liked sports a whole lot more years ago than I do now, but the reality is that when
I first moved here, there were people, okay, what team are you going to follow?
And we don't have a real big population of folks in our congregation that are really
avid sports fans, but there are people, I don't even know if Washington's playing at
home or away today, but there will be people at the game today that will color themselves
in paint that spent way too much money to go and buy a ticket.
They're going to sit there, if it's local, they're going to sit here in nasty weather,
and they're going to be passionately cheering for a losing team.
Am I right?
Should we not be passionate for our cause?
Should we not have passion as we proclaim the message that Jesus is Lord?
I remember sitting in England, Liverpool, England.
I love the Clemens, great friends, missionaries that we've supported for years.
They've sat at our table, great friends.
But I remember Joseph was there.
He's the only one in the auditorium that was there with us.
I remember serving and getting there for that Sunday at Breck Road Baptist Church,
and I remember going in there and we stood up to sing.
Man, I was ready to sing like we sing here.
And within the first two verses, I found...
Not two verses, two measures.
I found out that no one was singing anywhere near as close to what my volume was.
And I kind of had to tone it down and had to kind of...
And it's very formal.
That's just their worship, very formal.
And I remember talking to Brother Clemens.
He said,
English people aren't very passionate.
And I'm not criticizing Brother Clemens.
Don't misunderstand my point.
And it's very, this is just how we worship.
That's fine.
But I said to Brother Clemens, I said, well, how do you describe when they're watching
what we call soccer, they call football?
Because they're a bunch of maniacs for unpassionate people.
And I don't use the word maniac in a negative way.
I mean, they're passionate, and so often, we as God's people, we lack passion.
Paul stands and says, I'm not mad, I'm not crazy, but I'm speaking forth the words of
truth and soberness.
For the king knoweth, in verse 26, of these things, before whom also I speak freely, for
I am persuaded that none of these things are hidden from him, for this thing was not done
in a corner.
Saying Agrippa, believest thou the prophets, I think he was passionate in his question
to Agrippa.
I know that thou believest.
And Agrippa responds and says, almost thou persuadest me to be a Christian.
And Paul says, I would to God that not only thou, but also all that hear me this day were
both almost and altogether such as I am, except these bonds.
Paul's passionate.
We must serve the Lord humbly, we must serve the Lord compassionately, we must serve the
Lord passionately.
Finally, number four this morning, we must serve the Lord faithfully.
We must serve the Lord faithfully.
Notice back in Acts chapter 20, the Bible says in verse number 20 that he went, notice
it says, and how I kept back nothing that was profitable unto you, but have showed you
notice and have taught you publicly and from house to house.
He was faithful to preach in the square, but also to go and meet people where they
are.
And he proclaimed, he served, he taught publicly and house to house.
Notice in verse 26, and really, I believe this morning, we don't have time to get into
all of it, but I believe that in verse number 26 that Paul is making a direct, I mean, straight
line back to Ezekiel's book when God says that he sent Ezekiel to be a watchman.
And that if you warn the people and they don't respond, then you're free.
You're not guilty of their blood, but if you fail to warn them, then their blood is on
your hands.
We don't have time to develop all of that, but Ezekiel 3 and 33, you find that God makes
that declaration.
Paul would have known the Old Testament extremely well.
And so in verse number 26, he says, wherefore I take you to record this day that I am pure
from the blood of all men.
That is a powerful statement under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God.
That's just not me or you saying, listen, I will be honest, I am not free from the blood
of all men.
There are more times in my life that I like to admit that I have failed to share the gospel
with someone.
More times than I like to admit.
You missed the opportunity.
Not sensitive to the Holy Spirit of God.
More times than I like to admit.
But Paul, he was faithful.
That's what the Bible says in verse number 31, therefore watch and remember that by the
space of three years, he says this, for three years, I ceased not to warn everyone night
and day with tears.
You want to talk about someone that was exhausted physically?
I think Paul could say, that's me.
Many of us, we don't really know what it means to be tired.
You say, pastor, I beg to differ.
But understand, he said, I ceased not for three years.
And this isn't the only three years of his ministry, by the way.
This is what he's speaking to about the ministry there in Ephesus, in Asia, as he says Asia
Minor, as he says to these church leaders from Ephesus that gathered together, and he
says for those three years, I ceased not to warn everyone night and day with tears.
God's called us to be faithful.
He said in verse 24, none of these things move me, neither count I my life dear unto
myself, so that I might finish my course with joy, and the ministry which I have received
of the Lord Jesus to testify the gospel of the grace of God.
And then he's able to say, I have finished.
He was faithful.
He was faithful unto the end.
The Bible tells us, moreover, it's required in stewards that a man be found faithful.
There's a lot of things that a lot of us can't do but all of us can be faithful.
Not all of us can play the piano.
Not all of us can preach.
Not all of us can disciple.
Not all of us can, you just start filling in the blank.
Not all of us can sing.
Not all of us can lead music.
Not all of us can work in the nursery.
Come on, not all of us, you just keep doing the blank, but all of us can be faithful.
We can be faithful, be faithful.
I'm thankful that our God is faithful.
We're a faithful God, but he's called us to be faithful and we're to serve God faithfully.
I think about Noah.
I was praying here this morning and just praying over the message and God brought to my Noah.
He was faithful to do a work, but he was faithful to preach.
He was a preacher of righteousness, the Bible tells us, and he was faithful.
And I tell you this morning that your faithfulness and my faithfulness should not be dependent
on results.
Why do I say that?
Remember last week, for the audience of one, for the audience of one, I'm faithful because
I'm serving Christ.
I'm serving the Lord.
There are no results.
You think about some of the great missionaries that we look to today, Adam Jetson, Hudson
Taylor, others, that they went to these places and they had no converts.
They had no people that were flocking to Christ to hear their message.
Some of them went years without a convert, but they were faithful.
Why?
For the audience of one.
I remember reading of William Carey, the Bible says, or the Bible, the book that I was reading
on William Carey mentioned that for a number of years he had no converts, but he was faithful.
I mean, dealt with opposition after opposition, difficulty after difficulty, but some years
after his life there were over 100,000 believers in that place where he was called to minister
that all of them could singularly trace their spiritual heritage back to that one man.
It's amazing.
He was faithful.
Look at Hebrews 13 in closing this morning.
Hebrews 13 in closing, listen, God's called each of us to serve the Lord.
He's called each of us to serve Christ.
What a privilege.
What a privilege to serve the Lord.
In whatever capacity it is, it's a privilege to serve the Lord.
However He's equipped you, however He's called you, it's a privilege to serve the Lord.
One day we're going to give an account for what we did with how He's equipped us.
The Bible tells us in Hebrews 13, verse 20 and 21, I want you to see these verses as
we close.
The Bible says, now the God of peace that brought again from the dead our Lord Jesus,
that great shepherd of the sheep through the blood of the everlasting covenant.
Notice where it says, make you perfect in every what?
Good work.
To do His what?
To do His will.
Working in you, aren't you thankful He's working in us?
That which is well-pleasing in His sight through Jesus Christ to whom be glory forever and
ever, amen.
For the audience of one, last week's message, this week's message, so run that ye may obtain.
As we evaluate our service to God, listen, we serve a great God.
All year we've been talking about how great He is.
And He's great, but He's worthy of our service.
He's worthy of our work, our good work.
And He's equipped us, He's enabled us.
This morning we see in the life of Paul and how often we can say, man, look at, look at
the Apostle Paul, look at how, what he did for the Lord, look at how God used him.
Well, it's because he was surrendered, because he was set focused on pleasing the Lord.
And how did, how did Paul serve and how should we serve?
Well, he served the Lord humbly.
It is absolutely essential that we serve the Lord with humility.
He served the Lord compassionately.
People knew that he cared, he loved them, they were dear unto him.
He served the Lord passionately.
He was proclaiming the words of life and he served the Lord faithfully.
Until his very last moment, he said, the time of my departure is at hand, but I have fought
a good fight.
If God has you here, He has a purpose for you.
And we're to do good works, we're to not again to be saved or to stay saved, but because
we are saved, we get to serve Him.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
Thank you for the privilege of knowing you.
If there's one here that's not sure of heaven, God, I pray that today they'd be saved.
Lord, I pray for each child of God that we would evaluate, examine our service to thee.
Lord, that you'd help us to serve you humbly, compassionately, passionately, and faithfully.
Lord, help us to do all that we do for the audience of one to please you, Lord, singularly.
But understanding that our service to thee will have an impact on many.
Help us, Lord, to serve you as we ought.
I pray that you'd move and work in our midst as only you can, that decisions would be made
that would please thee and we'll thank you for it in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand?