for the opportunity to preach through the book of Colossians here in this calendar year.
And I have been encouraged and strengthened, and what a blessing to have the Word of God.
Amen.
And it's interesting, I was sharing with someone just this morning, and had been sharing with
my family earlier in the week, how that when you look at these truths in the Word of God,
how applicable they still are for today.
And we understand that the Word of God is the living Word of God, and it's written by
the eternal God, and therefore it is relevant for every people group.
It's relevant in every era of human history.
And there are some that think that the Bible is outdated, it needs to be updated, or whatever.
They'll say, well, it's not relevant.
It is so relevant.
And we find that as we dig into the Word of God, that God will give us truth that is applicable
and relevant in the day in which we are living.
If it were true in Paul's day and Peter's day, and we know that it is, that there were
false teachers that were active, we would say assuredly this morning that false teachers
continue to be prevalent.
We understand that as we look at the passage of Scripture, as we look at the end of chapter
number one of the book of Colossians and then get into chapter two, we find that the apostle
Paul had shared with these believers in Colossae, and we've studied it, how that really the
philosophy of his ministry.
What was the ministry that God had placed him in, that God had called him to?
It was to preach Christ, it was to warn every man, and it was to teach every man for the
express purpose of being able to present every man perfect in Christ Jesus.
What a great summarized statement of the ministry.
Not only the aspects of ministry, but the purpose of ministry.
As we studied last week, and you look at the first few verses of Colossians 2, we find
that Paul then is revealing to these believers in Colossae about this great conflict that
he has, not only for the believers in Colossae, but for those in Laodicea and for all of them
that had not seen his face in the flesh.
And as we studied last week and we dealt with that great conflict, we said we understood
that Paul had such great concern and care for these believers that the way in which
he described that care and concern was a great conflict.
What was it that caused this great conflict in the life of the Apostle Paul?
Nothing other than these false teachers that were active, not only in Colossae, but we
find in Laodicea and in many other regions in which the gospel had gone forth.
And Paul has this great conflict and he desires to warn these believers in Colossae.
We, of course, understand as he summarized the ministry to preach Christ, warning every
man and teaching every man, and we find that the Bible tells us this in Psalm 19 and verse
number 11,
"...moreover by them," by the Scriptures, the law of the Lord is what is being referred
to in that portion of Scripture.
He says this, "...moreover by them is thy servant warned, and in keeping of them,"
the Scriptures, "...there is great reward."
We looked a couple of weeks ago at the truth in 1 Corinthians 4 and verse number 14 when
Paul said,
"...I write not these things to shame you, but as my beloved sons, I warn you."
I warn you.
He's giving, extending this warning in order to protect these believers from these false
teachers and from this teaching that is going forward, and we find that then, after giving
a warning, he seeks to teach every man.
Why is it that he's seeking to teach?
Well, as we said last week, spiritual growth is the most effective defense against false
teaching.
I mean, when you know what the Word of God says, when you have been settled and grounded
in the faith, when you've grown spiritually, not that you ever come to a place of arrival
because we'll find even as we study through the text this morning, it is a continual process
of growth, of spiritual growth, that when you are growing spiritually, you are able
to defend the truth of the Word of God and the false teachers, their teaching and their
philosophies just kind of fade away under the truth of the Word of God.
We find that it was there that Peter said in Acts 6, dealing with some of the things
that were taking place there at the church in Jerusalem.
He speaks about him and the others, that they would give themselves to prayer and the ministry
of the Word.
I'm thankful that God has given us the Word of God, and I'm thankful that He has instructed
us to teach and preach the Word of God, and what a blessing it is for us to have the Word
of God.
This morning we'll be looking at Colossians 2, verses 4 through 7.
The Bible says this,
And this I say, lest any man should beguile you with enticing words.
For though I be absent in the flesh, yet am I with you in the Spirit, joying and beholding
your order, and the steadfastness of your faith in Christ.
As ye have therefore received Christ Jesus the Lord, so walk ye in Him, rooted and built
up in Him, and established in the faith as ye have been taught, abounding therein with
thanksgiving.
If you're taking notes this morning, I've titled the message from verse 7, rooted and
built up in Christ.
Rooted and built up in Christ.
This is a great declaration with a great passage of Scripture, and as we study through it this
morning, I want you to take note, number one, note how Paul cautions these believers.
Again, we mentioned that in chapter number one, when he describes the ministry that God
had called him to, he says,
Warning every man.
And we find that in verse number four, Paul is going to begin this aspect of ministry
of issuing a warning, cautioning the people of God.
We find that the truth that is really started in verse number four will continue and be
more developed even in verse number eight, as we'll study next Sunday morning.
But we find that this danger that Paul is dealing with and the caution that he's giving
to these believers is exposed in verse number four.
He's exposing the tactic of the enemy.
He's dealing with what they need to be careful of and how they need to be cautioned.
We've often mentioned throughout the last several weeks how that we have grown accustomed
as human beings of receiving warnings, of receiving caution.
And we see it on various items that we purchase, the various places that we go, caution, and
you'll see warning.
And those things are there to grab our attention and to help us take heed.
In fact, in verse number eight, it's not really, we're going to look at it in its entirety
next Sunday morning, but the verse begins with this wonderful word, beware.
Now when you see the word beware, you should take heed.
I mean, it gets your attention, amen?
And I remember as a child and even still today, if I'm out door knocking and visiting in the
neighborhoods and there's a fence and there's a sign that says beware of dog, I am taking
literally that warning that is posted on that fence.
Why?
Because I've gone into gates before and there's been a big dog that's come around the corner
and so therefore I'm taking heed to the warning and often what I will do is I will take that
gospel tract or that John and Romans and I will twist it up and stick it in the fence
and say, I hope they'll grab it and read it.
That's just what I do.
Why?
Because there's a warning that's given.
There's certain things that you keep away from your children, chemicals that perhaps
you clean with.
There are warning labels on those things.
There are cautions.
And so here Paul is going to issue a caution to these believers in Colossae and as he's
issuing this warning, you understand that Paul is seeking to help these believers.
He loves them.
He's not warning them so that they would forsake truth and follow him.
No, he's warning them because the deceivers, the false teachers are active among them and
Paul loves them and Paul wants to give them the truth.
This here in this passage of Scripture, you notice that he begins in verse number 70 and
says, and this I say.
Why is he saying this?
Well remember in the previous passage that we studied last week, he says I have this
great conflict for you and therefore because of this great conflict that I have and we
understood as we studied the passage and looked at the whole really of the message of the
book of Colossians that it was these false teachers that resulted in Paul having this
great conflict.
He says therefore I'm saying this to you, lest any man should beguile you with enticing
words.
That word beguile and it carries with it the idea of deception by false reasoning.
Deception by false reasoning.
And he says this, he uses this phraseology with enticing words.
You know the reality is that if they would teach the truth of the word of God, they're
not going to beguile you.
But they have to use these enticing words in order to beguile you.
Why?
This deception by false reasoning.
And these enticing words are speech words
that are adapted to persuade.
It's specious discourse leading others into error.
That's what enticing words.
That's the idea of this truth
that Paul is giving to these believers in Colossae.
And so he's telling them,
listen, I want you to understand
the way in which these false teachers
are going to operate.
They're going to come in
and they're going to seek to beguile you
with these enticing words.
It's not something that's just captured
in the book of Colossians.
I want you to hold your place here
and look over to the book of 1 Timothy if you will.
We'll look at a few verses here this morning.
In 1 Timothy 4, we'll see this truth given here
that Paul is instructing Timothy,
his son in the faith.
And we understand if we could use the analogy this morning
that in a spiritual type of a manner,
the Apostle Paul is seeking to pass the baton to Timothy.
He understood that Timothy was his son in the faith.
He understood that God had called Timothy
and commissioned Timothy,
and Timothy was like-minded.
And so in the book of 1 and 2 Timothy,
Paul is investing in instructing Timothy
to take the next leg of the race, so to speak.
And in 1 Timothy 4, the Bible says this,
Now the Spirit speaketh expressly,
that in the latter times,
some shall depart from the faith,
giving heed to seducing spirits
and doctrines of devils,
speaking lies in hypocrisy,
having their conscience seared with a hot iron,
forbidding to marry,
and commanding to abstain from meats
which God hath created
to be received with thanksgiving of them
which believe and know the truth,
for every creature of God is good,
and nothing to be refused
if it be received with thanksgiving,
for it is sanctified by the Word of God in prayer.
And I want you to notice,
so Paul is instructing,
he's giving Timothy really a warning here
and an understanding of what's going to happen.
And then notice the charge
that is issued in verse 6.
If thou, Timothy,
if thou put the brethren
in remembrance of these things,
thou shalt be a good minister of Jesus Christ,
nourished up in the words of faith
and of good doctrine,
whereunto thou hast attained.
In the book of Titus,
you turn over just a few pages,
and you find in the book of Titus,
again, Paul will refer to Titus
as being a son in the faith,
and we find that Titus again
is given this responsibility
to go into Crete,
and we find that as he would go there,
that he would set things in order
that were wanting.
He was to ordain elders in every city,
and Titus had a responsibility.
And Paul is seeking to instruct Titus
and to help Titus to understand.
And throughout the book of Titus,
you will find a number of references
to this terminology,
sound doctrine.
Sound doctrine.
Understanding the truth of the Word of God.
Notice what he says in Titus 1.
In v. 10.
Let me read v. 9 with it.
"...holding fast the faithful word
as he hath been taught,
that he may be able by sound doctrine
both to exhort and to convince the gainsayers.
For there are many unruly
and vain talkers and deceivers,
especially they of the circumcision."
That referring to the Jews,
we understand that terminology
throughout the New Testament.
And if you look and you understand
really contextually what's happening
throughout the New Testament era
and the propagating of the truth of the gospel,
remember in Acts 15,
they had to have a meeting,
a council at Jerusalem,
as it would be referred to.
Why?
Because there were some Jewish people
that were saying to the Gentiles,
unless you're baptized,
excuse me, circumcised
after the manner of Moses,
you cannot be saved.
Well, that's not true.
Paul deals with it extensively
in the book of Galatians.
And here we find that
as he's instructing Titus,
he's saying, listen,
there are going to be people that come
that are vain talkers and deceivers.
What is Paul saying
to these believers in Colossae?
He's saying, listen,
I'm writing to you,
lest any man should beguile you
with enticing words.
Peter says this in 2 Peter 2.
In 2 Peter 2 verses 1-3,
I've referenced this portion of Scripture,
but we'll read all three verses
here this morning.
The Bible says this,
Peter says in verse number one
of 2 Peter 2,
but there were false prophets
also among the people,
even as there shall be
false teachers among you,
who privily shall bring in
damnable heresies,
even denying the Lord that bought them
and bring upon themselves
swift destruction.
And look at what it says in verse two.
And many shall follow
their pernicious ways,
by reason of whom
the way of truth
shall be evil spoken of,
and through covetousness
shall they with feigned words
make merchandise of you
whose judgment now of a long time
lingereth not
and their damnation slumbereth not.
The feigned words are false words.
Here in Colossians 2,
he says with enticing words.
And we find that the Bible tells us
that many shall follow
their pernicious ways.
Listen, that's a sad reality.
These false teachers,
they gain a following.
Why? Through their false teaching,
through their enticing words,
through their speech
that is adapted to persuade.
Leading others into error.
And we find that Paul
is issuing this caution
to the believers in Colossae
that they would understand
that these false teachers
are among them.
It's one thing to understand
that there are false teachers among us,
but it's another thing to understand
how they operate.
And so Paul is seeking
to not simply announce
to the believers in Colossae
that there are false teachers,
but to take it a step further
and say here's how they operate.
Here's what they're seeking to do.
They want to beguile you.
They want to deceive you
to use this deception
by false reasoning.
Now, I don't like being deceived.
Do you?
Have you ever been deceived?
You've ever been lied to?
It bothers you.
I don't want to be lied to.
I don't want to be deceived.
We find that they will,
these false teachers,
their seeking,
their goal is to beguile you.
Can you see the contrast
between what Paul said
to the believers in Colossae
in chapter 1?
What was the goal of his ministry?
To present you perfect
in Christ Jesus.
You couldn't be more opposite.
Paul says I'm preaching Christ.
I'm warning every man.
I'm teaching every man
so that we might present every man
perfect in Christ Jesus.
But these false teachers,
they're seeking to beguile you.
To deceive you by error.
By false reasoning.
We find that it's so important
that the people of God today,
we need wisdom
and we need discernment.
Oh, how we need discernment.
Paul says this,
I believe that the Apostle Paul
wrote the book of Hebrews
and in Hebrews 5,
you don't need to turn there,
but in verse number 14,
really we don't have the time
to look at verses 11 through 14,
but we find that they were not growing
as they should be growing.
They should have been teachers,
but the Bible says
they were dull of hearing.
And here's what Paul says
in Hebrews 5 in verse number 14,
but strong me belongeth to them
that are of full age,
even those who by reason of use
have their senses exercised
to discern both good and evil.
You understand this morning
that a false teacher
doesn't show up on your doorstep.
A false teacher doesn't
come sit at your table.
come through the doors
of this congregation and say,
just so everyone knows
I'm a false teacher.
I mean, it'd be really easy
if they did that.
Just so you know,
I'm here to beguile you.
No, they don't do that.
They don't do that.
That's not how they operate.
And we need discernment.
Oh, how we need discernment.
This morning as we think
about the passage of Scripture
and we speak about the way
in which it's relative
in our world today,
we're dealing with false teachers today
that are so prevalent.
We made the statement last week,
I made the statement
that we think about false teachers
that they are persistent
and they are persuasive.
And they are.
That's how they work.
They'll keep,
if they see that
there's an opportunity,
there's some progress
that they have been able to make,
they're going to be persistent.
And oh, how they're persuasive.
And Paul says, I want to caution you.
It's interesting.
They'll change words.
We've mentioned before
how that they will use our vocabulary,
but not our dictionary.
They'll use a terminology
that perhaps we're familiar with,
but they mean something
entirely different.
It's important that we ask the question,
what do you mean by that?
Someone I gave a gospel track
to just recently,
and they said,
oh, I'm a Christian.
What does that mean?
How did you become a Christian?
Can you explain that?
that to me? Because the reality is that it's easy to say I'm a Christian. What
does it mean? Has there been a time in your life that you were born again, that
you recognize you're a sinner and needed the Savior, and that Jesus is the only
Savior? Have you been born again? You understand. I gave a gospel tract to
someone yesterday. He said, Catholic? No, sir. A follower of Jesus Christ. And he
said, oh. But the reality is that they'll use our vocabulary, a different
dictionary, but then they'll do this. They'll change this book. They will
change this book. This book is authoritative. This is the Word of God,
and it is this book that must alter the behavior and the belief of any child of
God. We do not come up with our own ideas, with our own thoughts, and say, well,
we'll just change the Bible. No, no. It doesn't work that way. The Bible changes
us. Amen? Because the Bible is the Word of God for all scriptures given by
inspiration of God. It's not for me to change it. It's not for me to alter it.
It's not for me to say, well, it really doesn't mean this, or it doesn't mean
that. Listen, if somebody has to start being real creative in their explanation
of the Word of God, I'd be careful. The plain sense of the text of Scripture,
that's why it's important to, and you'll see through some of you that have been
here for the the duration of me pastoring here, some that are newer, I
preach expository messages almost extensively only. Why? Because we want to
get the Word of God in context. I'm trying to cherry-pick a verse from here
and there and make it say something that it really doesn't say. He cautions
them. I want you to notice, not only back in Colossians 2 do we find that Paul
cautions them, but I want you to know how Paul commends them. In verse number 5, we
find that Paul is extending to them this commendation. He is commending them, and
it's interesting. He begins by saying this in verse number 5,
For though I be absent in the flesh, we understand, we've made it clear
throughout our study of the book of Colossians, that Paul has never met these
people in the flesh. They've never met him. He heard about these believers
through Epaphras. The Bible reveals that to us in chapter number 1. We know that
there was a relationship between Paul and Epaphras, and we find that Epaphras
was the spiritual leader at the church at Colossae, and it was through this man
that Paul understands the things that are taking place in Colossae. This man
brought back a report. You'll remember in the book of 1 Thessalonians that Paul
shares with the believers in Thessalonica how that he couldn't go
back to Thessalonica. He administered there for a period of time, but he had to
depart, and he wanted to know their estate, so he sent Timothy, and he sends
Timothy to Thessalonica to get an update, to get a report of how they're doing, and
Timothy brings that back. That's how Paul understood things that were going on
there in Thessalonica. In Colossae, he understands these things through
Epaphras, and he says, though we're separated by distance, I've not seen you,
I'm absent in the flesh, notice what he says, yet am I with you in the Spirit.
Then notice this next word in verse number 5, joying, joying, and beholding
your order, though he was separated from these believers by distance, yet he is
joying. The word means to rejoice greatly. Now, can you see Paul? He's in prison,
right? He's writing the book of Colossians from prison, and when he hears
about these believers in Colossae, when he receives this report from Epaphras,
and he hears about what's going on, and as he's praying for them, remember he
says in chapter 1, I'm praying for you always. He's praying, and he's thanking
God for them, and he's praying they would understand the truth, and he's seeking
the minister, and as he's writing this letter that we refer to as the book of
Colossians, he says that he's joying. I wish in my mind's eye I can see it, but I
wish, oh, how wonderful it would be to see the spirit of Paul in that prison cell.
He's rejoicing greatly. Paul, you're in prison. Yeah, but I'm thinking about those
believers over in Colossae, and oh, how excited he was to hear, oh, he was
troubled by the false teachers that were active, but he was excited about the
report that he received, and he says this, that he was beholding your order. It's
really the first reason, if you will, for which Paul was joying, that he was
rejoicing greatly, and he says he's beholding your order. The idea of this
phraseology really is a military idea. It really carries with it the idea of an
orderly and organized army. Now think about that. We sing songs about the Lord's
army, a Christian soldier. We understand that Paul says, and as he's writing again
to Timothy in 2nd Timothy chapter number 2, that to be a good soldier of
Jesus Christ, and Paul is looking at this church in Colossae through his
spiritual understanding and that which Epaphras has brought to him, and he
says, I'm beholding your order. You're like an organized army. I like the
imagery. I like the use of the words and the understanding within the context of
the language, and they would have understood exactly what it was that Paul
was sharing with them. He says not only am I beholding your order, but he says
this at the end of verse number 5, and the steadfastness of your faith in
Christ. By the way, your faith is only as good as the object of your faith. He says
the steadfastness of your faith in Christ. I spoke with someone this week
extensively, and I spoke to them about salvation being by grace through faith,
and he said, well I have faith, and I said, I understand that you have faith, but
what is your faith in? He began to give me an answer, and I said, listen, your faith
is only as good as the object of your faith. Who's your faith in? He says the
steadfastness of your faith in Christ. The word steadfastness carries with it
the idea of firmness. As believers, we're to have the steadfastness of our faith
in Christ, that we understand that Jesus gave the instruction to the
disciples before he ascended to heaven, not only to go and preach the gospel to
every creature, baptize them, and to teach them all things whatsoever I have
commanded you, and that we would have this steadfastness. When you think about
faith, really the idea here, the body of doctrine and truth by which we hold dear
as the people of God. Jude commends those that he's writing to, that
they are to contend for the faith. So Paul, as he has received this report
from these, or from Epaphras with regard to these believers in Colossae, he really
likens these believers to an orderly army of disciplined soldiers that are
making a solid front against the enemy. I like the imagery. You think about the
Roman soldiers, and the Roman Empire, and the advancement, and really the
understanding that these people would have had about that Roman army, and how
they would enter into battle. Listen, if you're gonna go into battle, you don't go
in all kind of confused, and man, some people are going over there, and some over here,
and some over here, and we're all disorderly. Man, that's a recipe
for disaster. Remember, as we studied last week in the first few verses of
Colossians chapter number two, he spoke about the fact that they would be knit
together in love, and we spoke about unity. Endeavoring to keep the unity of
the Spirit is what he says to the believers in Ephesus, and we find that
Paul is saying, I am rejoicing greatly, and he issues to these
believers, he commends them for their order, and for their steadfastness, or the
steadfastness of their faith in Christ. We find that he cautions them, we note
that he commends them, and then number three this morning, we note how Paul
challenges them. Here's the wonderful thing, as though Paul was rejoicing
because of their order, and their steadfastness, or the steadfastness of
their faith in Christ, Paul understood that he had to issue this challenge, that
they did not get comfortable where they were, that they did not just sit by
and stagnate. See, the reality is that in the Christian life, we must continue to
march forward. We need to be careful about becoming apathetic, indifferent.
Apathy is so dangerous. We can come to a place where we feel like I've kind of
gone as far as I think I need to go. Oh, beware. Be careful. It's interesting, in
like fashion, Paul extends a challenge to the believers in Thessalonica when he's
speaking to them about brotherly love, and he says, I know that you do it, but
I'm challenging you to abound more and more. Don't get comfortable. Press on.
Hebrews 6 has the idea, you don't need to turn there, but in Hebrews chapter number
six, right after we read that passage in chapter number five about their dull of
hearing in the
There's a need for them to grow in their faith,
in their walk with God.
He tells them, let us go on
unto perfection.
Remember, Paul is seeking
through the teaching of the Word of God
to present these believers perfect
in Christ Jesus.
And so how does Paul challenge
these believers in Colossae?
How is it that Colossians 2
would challenge me,
would challenge you this morning
in verses 6 and 7?
What is the challenge for us?
We receive the caution.
We understand there are false teachers around.
Listen, they're prevalent.
I've been dealing with things
in recent weeks
that are so very relevant
to this subject of false teachers.
It's prevalent in our day.
We need to be cautioned.
Oh, it's good that we have the Bible.
It's good that you're in church.
It's good that you have sought
to grow spiritually.
But we find this challenge
that is being issued to these believers,
and I believe to us this morning as well,
notice when he issues this challenge,
it's regarding their walk in v. 6.
As ye have therefore received
Christ Jesus the Lord,
so walk ye in Him.
It's interesting as you look at the truth
in the book of Galatians
and you understand how those people
were led astray.
And you can read through it
in Galatians 1.
And they began in the faith
and they're going to continue in the flesh.
And Paul is really issuing
this state of confusion, if you will.
How is it that you begin this way
and then you try to go on this way?
And we find that Paul is saying
to these believers,
and the Word of God is saying to us this morning,
as ye have therefore received
Christ Jesus the Lord,
this morning, if you've been born again,
you've trusted Jesus Christ
as your personal Savior,
if I were to ask you this morning,
are you 100% sure
that heaven is your home?
I asked a man that question this week
and he said, if you put it that way,
I mean, he kind of did that number.
And I said, well, I'm not interested
in knowing if you're 95% sure.
It's not good enough.
Well, how could anyone know?
I'm glad you asked.
Let me show you what the Word of God says.
We find, look, there's a stink bug, man.
I saw all you guys looking at it
and it got my attention, amen.
As long as that thing stays there,
Juliana will be happy.
But if that thing goes down there,
you guys are in for a treat, amen.
And as you have therefore received
Christ Jesus the Lord,
if you've been saved,
you've trusted Christ as your Savior,
notice what Paul says,
so walk ye in him.
This truth of having a walk with the Lord,
this truth of having communion with the Lord,
what a blessing.
And what a unique opportunity that we have
to walk with God, to commune with Him.
I don't know how many of you
are reading the daily devotional
that we distributed to you this year,
but we distributed a daily devotional.
If you didn't get it and you want one,
we have plenty of other copies,
but it's called A Daily Word.
And if you read the devotional thought
from Friday evening,
it went through and it went through
all of these things that you're going to do
in your lifetime if you add all the minutes together.
Did anyone read it?
Okay, some of you read it.
And it's kind of interesting.
It was March 5th.
I'm going to go ahead and just read some of it.
And here's what it talks about.
It says this,
the average American will spend six months
sitting at stoplights.
And Julianna and Brianna said, what?
Every minute they add up, right?
And you go through and you look through
and it talks about five years waiting in line.
And I said, yep,
that's probably going to be a little bit longer for me
because I always find the long lines to wait in.
And you ever do that at the grocery store?
You think, man, there's only one person here.
We're in shape.
And then they're like, no, I don't want that.
And I don't want this.
And I think I'm, yeah.
And then it says that you're going to spend one year
looking for misplaced objects.
Some of you say, no, that's very underestimated, right?
I'm going to spend a lot more than one year
looking for misplaced objects.
But anyway, it goes on.
It says this, you're going to eat.
You're going to spend six years eating.
Yeah, I like that.
You had all those minutes up.
But then it says this,
what would the number be if you added up all the time
you have spent with God so far in your life?
If you didn't read it, I'd recommend you read it.
Honestly, it's convicting.
How long do you spend with God?
We spend all this time doing all these other things.
And here's what the excuse is that most people use.
I just don't have time.
You have the same amount of minutes today
that anybody else living has.
It's how we use our time.
And the reality, and I'm not sure of the study
that was behind all of that,
but I know that there are several things you can Google
and see how many minutes the average person per day
spends on this and the average lifespan,
and just calculate it out.
I think it said six years eating,
and we calculated as a family last night
that if you spent one hour with God a day for 50 years,
it would equate to two years.
So we're gonna spend four times, three times, excuse me,
as more time eating than we are walking with God,
if you spend an hour a day.
Can I tell you this morning,
most people don't spend an hour a day with God.
We just don't.
And what I'm saying is that he says here,
as you have therefore received Christ Jesus the Lord,
so walk ye in him.
Continue this, listen, salvation is more
than just a fire insurance policy.
It's more than just keeping you out of the lake of fire.
We get to commune with the God of the universe.
We get to walk with him.
Jesus says this in John chapter number 10,
I've come to give you life
and that you might have it more abundantly.
Man, the abundant life in Christ,
it comes through our fellowship and our walk with him.
And as we walk with him, guess what?
We're less likely to be beguiled with enticing words.
Why?
Because I'm walking with him.
If somebody brings something and says,
well, this, that, and the other thing,
it's like, well, actually the Bible says right over here.
Let me share this with you.
Somebody asked me this week,
is that just something that you assume
or is that really what the Bible says?
That's a great question, by the way.
It's a valid question.
Because the reality is that we say
that the Word of God is the sole authority
for faith and practice.
So if you believe something and you say something,
you better have some Scriptures to back it up.
And if you have some Scriptures to back it up,
don't listen to what some false teacher says.
He challenges them with regard to their walk.
Listen, if you're saved,
if you've received Christ Jesus the Lord,
so walk ye in Him.
Notice verse number seven, regarding their growth.
We understand the two are related one to the other.
He says in verse number seven,
rooted and built up in Him,
and established in the faith.
Let's look at these three references
and uses of these words that Paul uses.
Number one, he references really an agricultural type
of a word when he says rooted.
Rooted.
Rooted in Christ.
You think about a plant that is rooted.
Have you ever tried to get some weeds out of the garden?
And man, those things got a root this long
and you say, what in the world?
We're rooted in Christ.
Here's the question, are we a mighty oak?
Or a tumbleweed?
How many of you know what tumbleweed is?
How many of y'all have driven in the West Coast
and you've seen tumbleweed?
Driving in the state of Nevada,
very limited number of people in the state of Nevada.
Little pockets of people all over,
but you could literally,
we have spent time when I lived in Nevada,
I could drive for three or four hours
and never see another human being.
You can't do that.
You can't drive three or four seconds in Northern Virginia.
Amen?
I'm being serious.
You can drive hours.
I mean, if you break down, you're in trouble, man.
It's a desolate place.
You had to be more careful of the farmers
that had their fence break that the cow
was on the middle of the road.
Or the tumbleweed that would regularly blow out
in the middle of the road.
You're driving 70, 75 miles an hour
and those tumbleweed come blowing across the road.
It's a dangerous situation.
Why do they blow around so easily?
They're not rooted.
And so Paul uses this agricultural analogy, if you will,
and he says that we're to be rooted in Christ.
And then he uses an architectural analogy
when he says built up.
So you think about this being rooted in Christ,
being firm, having the idea of being thoroughly grounded.
Remember, the Bible says this
in 2 Timothy chapter number three,
when the word of God talks about the scriptures
being given by inspiration of God,
that they're profitable for doctrine, for reproof,
for correction, for instruction in righteousness,
that the man of God may be perfect, throughly firm.
unto all good works.
We find that if you were to read Psalm 1,
and you read about the blessed man,
that's a picture of someone that is grounded.
And he's firm.
And then he uses this architectural analogy
of being built up.
This idea of a constant increase
in Christian knowledge.
The fact that we're continuing to build
upon the teaching of the Word of God.
Not looking for other teaching.
Not looking for some kind of new teaching.
But seeking to know this book.
You know, if you read your Bible today,
and you read that same passage of Scripture
a month ago, a year ago, a couple of years ago,
God probably used that passage today
in your life different than He did before.
Is it because it's a different passage?
No. It's because you have different circumstances today
than you did the last time you read it.
And God will reveal something to you
in that passage that perhaps you had not seen before.
As a pastor, as a preacher of the Word of God,
I preach multiple times a week.
I'm talking to people all the time.
And there are times that I will preach a message
from a passage of Scripture,
and later that week, I will in my personal devotions
read that same passage of Scripture
and say, man, I wish I had seen that
before I preached.
Because that was really good.
Why didn't I see that?
It's a living book.
And we just continue to build up.
He says rooted.
That agricultural analogy
of being rooted in Christ.
That firmness being thoroughly grounded.
The idea of being built up.
The architectural analogy
of a constant increase in Christian knowledge.
And then He says established.
Notice back in Colossians 2 and verse 7.
Rooted and built up in Him.
We've said in Christ.
We understand that Him is referring to Christ.
We understand that contextually.
And so we want to be rooted and built up in Christ.
And then He says established in the faith.
Established.
Make firm.
Having something that is established.
It's not gonna waver.
It's not gonna change.
You understand today that our world is changing?
Amen?
It's changing so much,
they don't even know what's going on.
I'm being honest.
Our world has lost its mind.
That's what happens when you get rid of truth.
When you set truth aside, anything goes.
The cancel culture that we're living in,
those people that are canceling somebody else today,
they're gonna be canceled tomorrow.
It's all relativism.
But we got this book.
That's truth.
And we're established in it.
Listen, I'm not mad at somebody
because they disagree with what I believe.
I'm really not.
But I'm not gonna be swayed to believe what they believe
just because there's some pressure.
Because I wanna please Christ.
I wanna please God.
And so we have to be established.
Established in the faith.
Look at what He says.
As ye have been taught.
And I believe that's important.
We go back to Colossians one and we dealt with this
on our very first message on the book of Colossians
when he, Paul, is addressing these believers
and he's speaking about how they were giving thanks
and rejoicing for them, praying for them.
He says in verse number seven,
as ye also learned of Epaphras, our dear fellow servant,
who is for you a faithful minister of Christ.
These people in Colossae, these believers,
they had been taught.
And Paul says, as he's writing to them
and he's challenging them with regard to their walk,
with regard to their growth,
he says being rooted and built up in him,
established in the faith as ye have been taught.
Don't go looking for some other sources.
You've been taught by a good minister, a faithful minister.
And therefore, listen, I know I dealt with this
so I don't wanna repeat all of it,
but what's a faithful minister?
What's a good minister?
Someone that teaches the book.
Feed the flock of God,
that's the responsibility of the pastor,
the truth in 1 Peter chapter number five.
And we desire in our church through the ministry
that God has given me to teach the word of God.
Not my opinions, not my ideas,
but to teach the word of God, to teach the truth.
And we find that he says, as ye have been taught,
notice this truth in 2 Timothy chapter number two.
We used to have these words on our hallway
as you would walk down the stairs
to the Sunday school classrooms.
We painted and therefore those words are no longer there,
but we need to get those reprinted
so that we can put them on the wall again.
But in 2 Timothy chapter number two and verse number two,
the Bible says this, let me read verse number one with it.
Thou therefore my son,
be strong in the grace that is in Christ Jesus.
In the things that thou hast heard of me
among many witnesses,
notice these two words, the same, the same.
Commit thou to faithful men
who shall be able to teach others also.
The same, why?
Because truth doesn't change, right?
Paul says, I've given you this truth, Timothy.
I have given you the truth, I have taught you,
it's been among many witnesses
and you now, Timothy, take the same,
the same body of truth and teach others.
Again, as I mentioned earlier,
as we looked at 1 Timothy chapter number four,
Paul is, if you can think of it this way,
he's passing the baton.
In 2 Timothy chapter number four, Paul says,
look, the time of my departure is at hand.
So who's going to run the next leg of the race?
Paul says, Timothy, the same things that I've taught you,
the same, commit thou to faithful men
who shall be able to teach others also.
The truth of the Word of God.
The people in Colossae, the false teachers,
they were looking for some new truth.
There is no new truth.
We have the full canon of Scripture.
We have the whole Bible.
We're not looking for new revelation.
We just need to study the book that God's given us.
Amen?
People so busy looking for something new,
they haven't even read this.
Honestly.
Colossians chapter number two, notice what he says.
Think about this truth,
when he says, as you have been taught,
and then he says this, abounding therein.
Abounding therein.
With thanksgiving, this idea of abounding,
really you get this idea,
if I could use the analogy of maybe a river,
and abounding would not be a trickling stream,
but a mighty river.
Abounding therein with thanksgiving.
So Paul, as he is going to challenge them,
he challenges them with regard to their walk,
with regard to their growth,
and with regard to their thanksgiving.
To their gratitude.
With regard to their gratitude.
He says, with thanksgiving.
You know, this morning, it would be helpful for us
as the people of God,
just as it would have been helpful
for these believers in Colossae,
to thank God for truth.
You know how blessed you are to have a Bible?
Honestly.
Really, I can't honestly say without thinking,
because oftentimes I think about it
just because of how I have understood
other parts of the world,
and have come to understand that.
But most times, we will say,
as a preacher of the word of God,
take your Bibles and turn to.
It's just kind of a habit kind of thing.
Why?
Well, number one, because I'm preaching from the Bible.
I'm not just giving you my thoughts or ideas.
Number two, because you have a Bible,
and therefore you can turn to the Bible.
There are people groups all across this globe
that do not have the word of God.
We send missionaries to places
in which they do not have members of a congregation
that have their own Bible
that they can take home with them.
All over the globe.
But you have a Bible.
Are you thankful for it?
I mean, he says this in Colossians 2.
He says, with thanksgiving,
abounding therein with thanksgiving.
Listen, we need to be thankful.
We preach this passage of scripture in Hebrews 13
at the end of last year about some 10 things to rejoice.
It's a two-part series.
One of those things was rejoicing,
not only in truth, but rejoicing for spiritual leaders.
Someone that would stand up and preach the Bible.
We live in a time and a day and age
that there's not a whole lot.
I mean, there are people that are preaching.
Thankfully, there are faithful preachers
of the word of God.
But you understand that you can find a lot of places
around this country in America
where you're hard-pressed to find a faithful church
that preaches the word of God.
That's sad.
It's sad.
So Paul is saying to these believers,
how's your gratitude?
Every day, are you thanking God for the spiritual blessings?
Are you thanking Him because you have a Bible?
Oh, how blessed we are to have the word of God,
that I can go to the Bible.
Listen, when you need direction,
you seek the face of God through His word.
It's a lamp unto our feet.
It's the word of God that helps us to grow
and be established.
And so Paul says, listen,
I want to caution you. I want you to understand not only are the false
teachers active, but here's how they work. Here's how they operate. When you know
how the false teacher operates, it gives you an advantage. It really does. To
defend against it. To understand, what do I need to do? Okay, if they're active and
this is how they operate, they're going to seek to
beguile me with enticing words, therefore I must be rooted and I must be built up
in Christ Jesus. Why? Because that's the defense. I'm not going to be beguiled. I'm
not going to be deceived because I've been established in the faith. I have
grown spiritually. So after he he cautions them, he commends them, and then
he challenges them. For us this morning, I wonder how is our how's our walk with
God? As you have therefore received Christ Jesus the Lord, so walk ye in him. If we're
to add up all the time in this last week, in this last month, in 2021, that we've
spent with God, how many hours would it equal? That's not a question that I want
you to answer me. I want you to ask yourself, how's my walk with God? Are we
growing spiritually? I'll say this, if you're not walking with God, your
spiritual growth probably isn't that great because our spiritual growth is
the the outflow, the result of our walk with him. Are we growing? Are we thankful?
Thankful for truth. Thankful that God would, I mean, the privilege that is ours
to have the truth. What a joy. It comes with great responsibility. But this
morning, I hope that as we look at this passage and we see how Paul was
addressing these believers in Colossae, that we would find that it's for us
today in 2021. It's for you. It's for me. That we would receive the word of caution.
Oh, it's good to receive commendation, but let's not get stuck on the
commendation. Let's look at the challenge as well, that we continue to grow, to
develop in our walk with Christ. Because the false teachers, they're active.
They're active. And they're seeking to beguile you, to deceive you. So they're
seeking to do. You say, no, absolutely. Satan doesn't want you to serve God. And
if you're saved this morning, he'll do everything he can to keep you from
serving God. If you're lost, you've never trusted Christ as your Savior, he'll
bring plenty of false teachers into your life to keep you from trusting Christ.
How do we know that? 2 Corinthians 4. The God of this world has blinded the
minds of them that would believe not, lest the light of the glorious gospel
should shine in unto them. How does he do that? False teaching. It's what he does.
It's how he operates. I'm so thankful for the Word of God. I hope this morning that
we'd receive a challenge just as these believers in Colossae received. Shall we
pray? Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. We thank you for the truth
that you've given us and thy word for this portion of Scripture and how
applicable it is in our lives even today. Oh, how mindful I am of the help that
these believers in Colossae must have received as they were reading and
digesting the truth contained within this book of Colossians. I pray this
morning that you would help us. Lord, if there's one that's not sure of heaven, I
pray the Holy Spirit of God would convict them of their sin, of Christ's
righteousness, of judgment to come. Lord, I pray for each believer. Would you help
us to walk with you? Help us, God, to grow, to be rooted and grounded in Christ,
rooted and built up in Christ. I pray, Father, that you would help us to be
prepared individually and corporately as a church to contend for the faith,
understanding that the best defense for false teaching is spiritual growth, that
we would, as Paul said of these believers in Colossae, he says, beholding your order,
steadfastness of your faith in Christ, that we too would be like that organized
army, setting a firm defense against the attack of the enemy and the false
teaching that is so prevalent today. Help us, God. Work in lives, have your
will and way, for it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me? Heads
are bowed, eyes are closed. Kimberly's gonna play quietly on the piano, and as
she does, the altar is open. I'm gonna come and pray down here at this altar.
You want to pray in your seat? Would you let the Lord have his way
in your life today? If you're not sure of heaven, we'd love to take a Bible and
show you, like, you know for sure that heaven is your home. Maybe you need to
grow, maybe you'd be honest with the Lord about your walk, and you say, Lord I
need, I need to grow. I need to walk with you. As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.