Exodus chapter number 40, and this will be the text for our study this evening, Exodus chapter
number 40. I'll read a verse of scripture to you, give you the title, and get into the message this
evening. In Exodus 40, we're going to look at verse number 33. Eventually we'll cover the entire
chapter. I want you to notice in verse number 33 that he is speaking of Moses. It says,
And he, Moses, reared up the court round about the tabernacle and the altar and set up the hanging of
the court gate. Notice this phrase, So Moses finished the work. That's the title for the
message this evening. So Moses finished the work. We'll look at the entire 40th chapter of the book
of Exodus this evening. The work being referenced here in Exodus 40 is that of the tabernacle.
As you're aware, in the latter part of the book of Exodus, God had provided very specific,
detailed instruction with regard to the tabernacle. I mean, he provided the exact
dimensions. He provided the prescribed materials, everything about the tabernacle. The instruction
is given. We find that Moses would receive that instruction as he's up on the mount,
and as he's receiving that instruction, he's given all of the truth about each piece of furniture.
Again, the specific dimensions, the materials that are to be used, and with regard to even the
priest and their garments and all of that. And we find that as they come down off the mount,
as Moses comes off the mount, that he finds that the children of Israel, of course,
they had broken the command. You read in the 33rd chapter of the book of Exodus, 32nd chapter,
sorry, about the breaking of the law, the situation there with the sin of the people,
the golden calf, and all that takes place. And you look throughout just after the covenant being
renewed, and you begin reading in chapter number 35 of the book of Exodus, and you see
the implementation, the construction, the following of all of the instruction that had been given
while Moses was there on the mount. And we think about just the precise instruction that God would
give, and as we come to the 40th chapter of the book of Exodus, we find how that the very end of
the chapter records for us how that the glory of the Lord filled the tabernacle. Can you imagine
being there? Can you imagine the sight that it would have been? Can you imagine the experience
as the Bible tells us in verse number 34, then a cloud covered the tent of the congregation,
and the glory of the Lord filled the tabernacle. As we read verse number 34 of Exodus chapter number
40, we notice that the verse begins with the word then. It's interesting as we understand that
there were some things that took place before then in verse number 34. We find that then is
described, the event there of verse number 34 is described for us, but then comes as a result of
what had previously been explained in detail in chapter number 40. The result is that, or the
truth is that we want then. We want then. We want the result that is mentioned in verse number 40.
We want to see the glory of the Lord fill the tabernacle, if you will, if we're looking at the
contextual message here this evening, and we understand that which is taking place in Israel's
history, they want that. The then is desired. In our lives this evening, many times we would say
we want then. We want the blessing of the Lord. We want God's favor. We want God's glory to be seen
in and through the work of the ministry. But the reality is that then comes after a whole lot of
other stuff takes place. Then doesn't just happen. It's not just a chance type of a thing.
We notice throughout the text of Scripture, go back to verse number one, if you're taking notes this
evening, I just want you to notice some phrases that are used here in the passage of Scripture,
and that which is recorded for us that gives us great insight as to what is found at the end of
the chapter, the result that is desired. As you take notes, I want you to notice the phrase,
and thou shalt. Notice in verse number one, the Bible says, and the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,
now God is speaking to Moses, and what a blessing to understand that our God is faithful and that
he has faithfully provided the instruction that is necessary. The Bible tells us of the timing.
On the first day, the first month, shalt thou set up the tabernacle of the tent of the congregation.
And then notice from verse number three all the way down to verse number 15, every verse begins
with the phrase, and thou shalt. Notice verse three, and thou shalt put therein the ark of the
testimony and cover the ark with the veil. Verse four, and thou shalt bring in the table and set
in order the things that are to be set in order upon it, and thou shalt bring in the candlestick
and light the lamps thereof, and thou shalt set the altar of gold for the incense before the ark
of the testimony and put the hanging of the door to the tabernacle, and thou shalt set the altar
of the burnt offering before the door of the tabernacle of the tent of the congregation,
and thou shalt set the laver between the tent of the congregation and the altar,
and shalt put water therein, and thou shalt set up the court round about and hang up the hanging
of the court gate. Verse nine, and thou shalt take the anointing oil and anoint the tabernacle
and all that is therein, and shalt hallow it and all the vessels thereof, and it shall be holy,
and thou shalt anoint the altar of the burnt offering and all his vessels and sanctify the
altar, and it shall be an altar most holy, and thou shalt anoint the laver and his foot and
sanctify it, and thou shalt bring Aaron and his sons into the door of the tabernacle of the
congregation and wash them with water, and thou shalt put upon Aaron the holy garments and anoint
him and sanctify him that he may minister unto me in the priest's office, and thou shalt bring his
sons and clothe them with coats, and thou shalt anoint them as thou didst anoint their father,
that they may minister unto me in the priest's office, for their anointing shall surely be an
everlasting priesthood throughout their generations." Now, I read those verses of Scripture. We're not
going to take the time to go through and dissect each piece of furniture that is mentioned in
the specific instruction, but I want you to understand that as we read these first 15 verses
of the book of the 40th chapter of the book of Exodus, we find that God is giving specific
instruction. God did not tell Moses, go make a tabernacle and put some furniture in it. No, God
said, I want you to make a tabernacle, and here are the dimensions of the tabernacle, and here's what
you use to make the tabernacle, here's the way that it's to be set up, here are the pieces of
furniture, and by the way, it's a brazen altar, but here's the dimensions of the brazen altar, here's
how you're going to make it, here's what you're going to do, here's the material to use, and then
there's going to be a laver, and here's what you do, and I mean, it was very specific and very
detailed as to all of the instruction. We find that as you come to the end of chapter number 39,
that all of the work, Bezalel, I mentioned this morning briefly how that God had equipped Bezalel
and Aholiab for the work that God had for them to do here, but if you read the end of chapter 39,
the Bible says, according to all the Lord commanded Moses, so the children of Israel
made all the work, and Moses did look upon all the work, and behold, they had done it as the Lord had
commanded, even so had they done it, and Moses blessed them, and so we find at the end of chapter
number 39 that they completed the work as far as all of the construction aspect was concerned.
Moses inspects it, he says, yep, everything's been made according to the commandment of the Lord,
and now God comes in the first 15 verses of the book of the 40th chapter and tells Moses,
here's what you need to do, and thou shout, and thou shout. I mean, you see the specific
instruction that is given. I'm so thankful that God's given us a pure Bible, the entirety of
God's Word, that He has given us the instruction on how we're to live our lives and what it is
that we're to do, and we find that throughout the Word of God, God has given us specific
instruction. God wants us to be informed people. If Moses did not follow the direction that the Lord
gave, then Moses was responsible for that and would be held accountable for that, and God
graciously gave him the specific instruction, and then God would hold him accountable for what He
did with it. The reality is that God has given us His Word today, and what a blessing it is, and we
know that we'll be held accountable for what is written within this book. I'm thankful that the
Word of God has been preserved for us and that we can indeed agree with what Paul said in 2 Timothy 3,
that this book is, in fact, a profitable book. And as Peter mentioned, you do well that you take heed
thereunto. It's in our best interest to obey the Word of God. We see that there are some in our
society today that just despise the idea that the Word of God is the way to go, and it's not.
of God would have commandments in it
that would say,
Thou shalt, or thus saith the Lord.
I for one am thankful that God has spelled it out.
I'm thankful that God has given us
a clear Word.
Amen?
It's challenging when somebody says,
hey, here's a task for you to do.
Go do it.
And you're like, well, what do you want me to do?
How do you want me to do it?
And they don't really give you any direction.
They don't really give you any instruction.
And you go and you start the work,
and then they come along and say,
no, no, no, you're not doing it right.
Are you kidding me?
Like that's what you feel like saying, right?
Like I asked you and you gave me
no instruction, no direction,
and now you're telling me I'm not doing it right.
It's frustrating.
That's not the case with God.
God's told us.
And thou shalt.
I like the fact that God has given us
specific instruction.
I like the fact that He's laid it out for us.
I understand the truth of the individual soul liberty.
And I understand all of those truths
within the New Testament,
but the reality is that with that
individual soul liberty comes
individual responsibility and accountability.
And I'm so thankful that God has given us His Word.
I believe that Moses,
if he were able to share with us this evening,
if we were able to speak with him
and ask him, are you happy Moses?
Are you pleased that God gave you
the specific instructions?
I think Moses would say absolutely.
Because he didn't have to think about
how something was going to be done.
He just simply had to follow
what God gave him to do.
We see this phrase,
and thou shalt.
Notice with me as we continue through
the 40th chapter,
that you now will see this phraseology.
It won't be consistent throughout all of the verses
in the same manner in which we found
the and thou shalt,
but I want you to notice that you'll see this.
Thus did Moses,
and you'll see this phrase,
as the Lord commanded Moses.
Notice in verse 16.
Thus did Moses,
according to, circle the word, all,
that the Lord commanded him,
so did he.
Moses didn't just say,
well, that part's not really important.
We can skip that part.
No, no, he did all.
He understood that God took the time
to give him the specific instruction,
and every single detail that God gave him
in v. 3-15 was important to be followed.
It was not, well, this one we can take it or leave it.
This one, you know, I don't really like that.
It's going to take too much time to do this thing,
and so we'll just skip it.
No, the Bible says,
Thus did Moses, according to all
that the Lord commanded him,
so did he.
Notice v. 17.
And it came to pass in the first month
in the second year,
on the first day of the month.
By the way, if you look at v. 2,
on the first day of the first month,
shalt thou set up the tabernacle.
It says in the first month,
the second year on the first day of the month,
that the tabernacle was reared up.
So Moses is following the timeline
that had been given in v. 2,
and then we find that the Bible begins
in v. 18, really down through v. 33,
recording for us the way in which Moses fulfilled
that which God told him to do.
In fact, in these verses of Scripture,
there are seven times specifically
where these words are written,
As the Lord commanded Moses.
Notice in v. 18.
And Moses reared up the tabernacle,
and fastened his sockets,
and set up the boards thereof,
and put in the bars thereof,
and reared up his pillars.
And he spread abroad the tent
over the tabernacle,
and put the covering of the tent
above upon it.
Notice this phrase,
As the Lord commanded Moses.
V. 20,
And he took and put the testimony into the ark,
and set the staves on the ark,
and put the mercy seat above upon the ark.
And he brought the ark into the tabernacle,
and set up the veil of the covering,
and covered the ark of the testimony,
As the Lord commanded Moses.
V. 22,
And he put the table and the tent of the congregation
upon the side of the tabernacle northward
without the veil,
and he set the bread and order upon it
before the Lord,
As the Lord commanded Moses.
And he put the candlestick and the tent
of the congregation over against the table
on the side of the tabernacle southward,
and he lighted the lamps before the Lord,
As the Lord commanded Moses.
And he put the golden altar
and the tent of the congregation
before the veil,
and he burnt sweet incense thereon,
As the Lord commanded Moses.
And he set up the hanging
at the door of the tabernacle,
and he put the altar of burnt offering
by the door of the tabernacle
of the tent of the congregation,
and he offered upon it
the burnt offerings and the meat offering,
As the Lord commanded Moses.
V. 30,
And he set the laver between the tent
of the congregation and the altar,
and put water there to wash withal.
And Moses and Aaron and his sons
washed their hands and their feet thereat,
when they went into the tent of the congregation,
and when they came near unto the altar,
they washed,
As the Lord commanded Moses.
And he reared up the court round about
the tabernacle and the altar,
and set up the hangings of the court gate,
so Moses finished the work."
We read these verses of Scripture
and we see the obedience of Moses.
We find that Moses was faithful
to obey the commandment of the Lord.
We've often mentioned over the course
of many lessons in the book of Joshua
that we've been studying during this pandemic
and various messages throughout
the last several weeks,
even as we looked at the life of Ezra,
that he prepared his heart to seek the law of the Lord
and to do it, right?
And to teach in Israel statutes and judgments.
Ezra 7 and verse number 10.
We find that there is throughout the Scripture,
throughout the entirety of Scripture,
there is an obvious importance
that God places upon obedience.
We sing trust and obey.
We sing songs, I will obey.
We talk about the importance of obedience.
We talk about the fact that we're to be doers of the Word
and not hearers only.
Well, here, if we were to sum up
that which is given to us in verses 16 through 33,
we would simply be able to summarize
these verses of Scripture by saying,
Moses obeyed.
He did what the Lord told him to do.
We find that he was only able to obey
because he had been given the instruction.
God had faithfully given the instruction,
but then it was up to Moses to obey that instruction.
You know, as we look at the Word of God,
we can say with certainty
that God has given us His Word.
We have the Word of God.
It's one thing to have it.
It's one thing to know it.
It is entirely different to obey it.
To be a doer of the Word.
See, it's interesting.
The passage of Scripture reminds me,
when I think about obedience,
it reminds me of a truth in John 2.
Turn to the book of John, if you will,
and look at the second chapter with me.
And in John chapter number 2
is the first miracle that's recorded
in the life and ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ.
It's the miracle at the marriage of Cana.
We're familiar with that which takes place.
And as we look at John chapter number 2,
the Bible tells us as we begin the passage of Scripture
that in the third day,
there was a marriage in Cana of Galilee
and the mother of Jesus was there.
Notice in verse 2,
and both Jesus was called and His disciples to the marriage.
When they wanted wine,
the mother of Jesus saith unto Him,
they have no wine.
Jesus saith unto her,
Woman, what have I to do with thee?
Mine hour is not yet come.
It's interesting in this first miracle
at the marriage of Cana,
you begin to see this subject matter
that runs throughout the entirety of the book of John
with regard to the hour.
And Jesus would often refer to the fact
that the hour has not come
and He says,
Mine hour is not yet come.
He understood the purpose
in which He had come to this sin-cursed world.
He understood that He would live a perfect sinless life,
that He would go to the cross of Calvary
to pay for the sin of the world,
that He would be buried in a borrowed tomb
and that He would rise in victory on the third day,
conquering sin, death and the grave.
It's not until John chapter number 17
that you read where Jesus says,
Mine hour is come.
There are many references
between John 2 and John 17
of the hour,
but it's not until that time in John 17
that Jesus says,
Mine hour is come.
But notice this truth in John chapter number two
in verse number five.
Notice what Mary says to these servants.
His mother saith unto the servants,
notice this,
whatsoever he saith unto you, do it.
I like that verse.
The mother of Jesus, Mary,
she says to Jesus about the problem
in verse number three,
she saith unto him,
they have no wine.
And we find that the mother, Mary,
now turns to these servants
and she says to the servants,
whatsoever he saith.
He saith unto you, do it.
See, I remember hearing this phrase
when I was young.
Yours is not to reason why.
Just to do or die.
Some of us are familiar with that phraseology.
And I believe, I guess,
from at least my perspective,
I never have researched it,
but in my mind, contextually,
it's a military thing.
You don't need to question why.
Yours isn't to reason why.
It's just to do or die.
Just do it because I said kind of a situation.
You know, the reality when we come
to the commandments of the Lord,
that's absolutely how our response should be.
Just do it.
Whatsoever He saith unto you, do it.
You think about the miracle there in John 2,
and you think about what happens.
It's interesting, we don't have time
to go through the entirety.
It's not really the subject matter
by which we're studying,
but we find that what was the instruction
that Jesus gave,
fill the water pots with water.
And the Bible just simply says in v. 7,
and they filled them up to the brim.
They didn't question.
They didn't have some long debate
as to, well, is that really what we're supposed to do?
Is that really going to work?
No, no, no, they just did it.
V. 8, Jesus then said to them,
draw out now and bear it
unto the governor of the feast.
And they bear it.
There's no questioning.
There's no discussion.
They just did it.
They heard what Mary said.
Whatsoever He saith unto you, do it.
We come to v. 9 of John 2,
and the Bible says when the ruler of the feast
had tasted the water that was made wine,
and knew not whence it was,
look at this phrase, this parenthesis.
It says, but the servants which drew the water knew.
Isn't that good?
See, they heard Mary say
whatsoever He saith unto you, do it.
When we go to the Word of God,
we just need to have a hard attitude of obedience.
You know, there's a phraseology,
a logo, just do it,
within the sports arena.
We come to the truth of this thought
in John 2, do it.
Just obey.
And that's exactly what we see Moses doing here
in Exodus 40.
And thou shalt.
And, I mean, just repeated, repeated, repeated, repeated.
God has given specific instruction
and then the Bible says,
thus did Moses,
as the Lord commanded Moses.
Then, verse number 34.
I submit to you this evening
that you do not get then
if you skip as the Lord commanded Moses.
It's not going to happen.
And thou shalt.
What happens between and thou shalt
and then is obedience.
And you only get then if you obey.
And that's what Moses did.
Moses obeyed.
Then, the result of the behavior,
the event that is recorded,
the Bible says,
then a cloud covered the tent of the congregation
and the glory of the Lord filled the tabernacle.
And Moses was not able to enter
into the tent of the congregation
because the cloud abode thereon
and the glory of the Lord
filled the tabernacle.
And when the cloud was taken up
from over the tabernacle,
the children of Israel went onward
in all their journeys.
But if the cloud were not taken up,
then they journeyed not until the day
that it was taken up.
For the cloud of the Lord was upon
the tabernacle by day
and fire was on it by night.
But of all the house of Israel
throughout all their journeys,
I want you to focus this evening
on the truth in v. 34-35.
Then, the glory of the Lord
filled the tabernacle.
It really is the desired result, is it not?
See, we want the blessing of the Lord.
We find this representing
the presence of the Lord.
We understand in the Old Testament
as we'd study about the children of Israel
and the tabernacle
the truth of the Holy of Holies
and the very presence of God.
Of course, represented by the cloud by day
and the pillar of fire by night.
But we find here that on this moment,
can you imagine, the Bible says,
so Moses finished the work,
then a cloud covered the tent
of the congregation,
and the glory of the Lord
filled the tabernacle.
What a glorious sight it must have been.
Then, is the result of the first 33 verses.
And really specifically,
the result of v. 16-33.
Because God gave the instruction,
but the instruction had to be followed.
I'm mindful of the truth
in the book of 2 Chronicles 5.
If you turn over there just quickly
this evening and notice,
in 2 Chronicles 5,
as we read this portion of Scripture
and see how the glory of the Lord
would fill the house of God.
Of course, the tabernacle there
during the ministry and life of Moses,
it was David that had the desire
to build the temple.
And you remember that David had that desire
to build a temple.
And Nathan initially said,
go and do all that was within thine heart.
But that same night,
the Lord appeared to Nathan and said,
no, no, no, it's not for David
to build the temple.
And we find that Nathan faithfully
went back to David and delivered the truth
as to what David was to do.
And you can read about the Davidic covenant
and all that takes place
in that portion of Scripture.
And we find that David made it his purpose
to prepare for the building of the temple.
He understood that his son Solomon
would build the temple.
And we find that he gave liberally
and he encouraged others to give,
to store up all of that
which would be necessary
to build the temple.
And we come to 2 Chronicles
and we read about all that is taking place.
We don't have time to look at all of it
this evening, but you find that
chapter 2 reveals to us
some of the preparations that took place.
And you find that in v. 4,
the Bible says,
behold, I build a house to the name of the Lord my God.
We find that he says in v. 5
of 2 Chronicles,
and the house which I build is great.
Why?
For great is our God above all gods.
We find that he says that,
I love the phraseology that is used
in v. 9 of chapter 2.
He said, even to prepare me timber and abundance
for the house which I am about to build
shall be wonderful great.
And you find this information that is given
and then you read about the construction
in chapter 3 and chapter 4
just as you would read of the construction
of all of the elements with regard to the tabernacle
and those chapters leading up to
Exodus chapter 40.
But we come here to 2 Chronicles 5
and we see about the dedication.
It says in v. 1 of chapter 5,
thus all the work that Solomon made
for the house of the Lord,
notice this phrase, was finished.
What did we read about Moses
there in Exodus 40 and v. 33?
So Moses finished the work.
We find here,
the Bible says that Solomon,
that the work that he did,
that the house of the Lord was finished.
We find that in v. 13,
skip down if you will and look there,
it says it came even to pass
as the trumpeters and singers were as one
to make one sound to be heard
in praising and thanking the Lord.
And when they lifted up their voice
with the trumpets and cymbals
and instruments of music
and praised the Lord saying,
for He is good,
for His mercy endureth forever,
that then, you see the word then.
We saw that in Exodus 40
in v. 34,
for then the house was filled
with a cloud, even the house of the Lord.
So that the priests could not stand
to minister by reason of the cloud.
Notice, for the glory of the Lord
had filled the house of God.
Solomon will speak to the people.
We see that his prayer of dedication
is recorded as we move into chapter 6.
And you come to chapter 7
and you see how that prayer of dedication
and all of the sacrifice is recorded.
And you find the Lord replying to Solomon
and telling him that He's heard his prayer
But we think about the glory
of these chapters in 2 Chronicles
and how they mirror that which we read
in Exodus 40.
Something that is consistent
in both of these events
is the fact that the Bible says,
then this happened.
And it's after the obedience.
See, Solomon obeyed that which had been
instructed of him to do.
And we find that Moses,
to go back to our text of Scripture
in Exodus chapter number 40.
that we're studying this evening,
we find that Moses was a faithful minister
and Moses was an obedient servant of the Lord.
He did that which the Lord commanded.
This evening, what a sight it would have been
both at the tabernacle and at the temple.
Amazing.
We think this evening of our own lives.
We think of the blessing of God.
We understand that our bodies now,
according to the New Testament,
the temple of the Holy Spirit,
the Holy Ghost which is in us,
which we have of God,
we're not our own according to 1 Corinthians 6, verses 19 and 20.
We find that God desires to bless His people.
The psalmist said that He daily loatheth me with benefits.
We find that we want then.
We want the blessing.
We want the desired result.
But sometimes where we mess up
is in that in-between area.
We understand, and thou shalt.
We understand the desired result.
But sometimes we have difficulty with the do it.
Obey it.
Follow it.
As the Lord commanded Moses.
See, sometimes we're guilty of leaning on our own understanding.
Sometimes we're guilty of saying,
well, is that really still applicable today?
Is that really still something we have to do today?
Is that something?
And we just kind of mess things up.
And then we find ourselves in a place
where we're not obedient like we're supposed to be,
and we're not getting the desired result,
and we're wondering what's going on.
And God's saying you've got to do it My way.
I think it's interesting.
I understand some people could have an issue with it.
And if you do, just remember that I didn't say it.
J. Vernon McGee did,
and I'm not trying to hide behind his quote.
But I did think it was kind of interesting what he said.
I can find fault with what he said as well.
It's not a perfect statement.
But J. Vernon McGee, I think on one particular occasion,
it probably happened many times
because he's said interesting things
during his time in ministry
that would reveal times of maybe frustration and annoyance.
But I think it was one of those particular times.
And some people were really challenging him on,
do we really have to do that?
And why does it have to be this way?
And why do we have to do those things?
And J. Vernon McGee said something to this effect.
He said, listen, God made the world
and God's world is God's way.
And so if you want to do things your way,
go create your own world and figure it out.
I thought it was kind of comical.
And really what's J. Vernon McGee saying?
He's saying God is the creator.
And he is the one that has given us the instruction book.
He's the one that has revealed to us,
faithfully delivered to us,
what pleases Him.
So ours is not to argue over the content of this book.
Ours is simply to do it.
Moses didn't have to take some time and say,
well, does it really matter
if it's placed on the left side of the holy place
or on the right side of the holy place?
Does it really matter if it comes before or after?
No, no, he just had to do what God told him to do.
And God had a reason for the placement.
And it's God's desire
and it's God's right to say what He wants to say.
He's God.
And all we have to do is obey.
And we put it in those terms that seem so simple.
Doesn't it?
I mean, it really does, right?
I remember so many times as a parent
saying to the kids when they were younger,
it's so simple.
Just obey.
And I would say it countless times.
What is hard about this?
Just obey.
Just do what I said.
Just about every single time I ever said that,
it's as if the Holy Spirit of God
was whispering in my ear,
it's so easy.
Just do what I say.
I've given you my word.
Just do it.
And so many times in our life,
we struggle with obedience.
We make it sound easy.
But there's challenges.
We've got this flesh.
We've got this reasoning.
And this evening, when we look at the
40th chapter of the book of Exodus,
we see a glorious conclusion.
Then, the glory of the Lord filled the tabernacle.
And you read of this glorious event.
It's a result of Moses obeying completely
what, and thou shalt what God said.
And this evening, if we want then,
we better start doing.
We need to take heed to John 2 and verse number 5.
Whatsoever he saith unto you, do it.
Just do it.
Just determine that we're going to obey
the word of God.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
Would You help us, Lord,
to be doers of Your Word and not hearers only?
Lord, would You help us
to not approach Your Word
with the thought of disagreeing
and disputing, questioning?
Help us to have that attitude of Moses
as we read in this passage of Scripture,
and thou shalt.
Thank You, Lord,
for giving the instruction.
Thank You for being faithful
to deliver to us Thy Word,
just as You did to Moses.
Lord, thank You that the Bible records for us
that Moses did as You commanded.
He obeyed.
Thank You for the result.
Then, the glory of the Lord filled the tabernacle.
Lord, help us daily,
moment by moment,
to obey You.
To walk in the Spirit so that we would not
fulfill the lust of the flesh.
To approach Your Word on a daily basis
with that thought,
whatsoever He saith unto You, do it.
God, that You would help us
to have the attitude of the psalmist.
Lord, teach me Thy ways.
And then help me to walk in Thy ways.
Help us to fulfill that which we read of in James,
that we would be doers of the Word
and not hearers only.
Work in hearts and lives as only You can.
Use us, Lord, for Your honor and glory.
We'll thank You for it.
In Christ's name we pray.