course finished up the 12th chapter a couple of weeks ago and we took a couple
of lessons to get through Genesis chapter number 12 and as we finished up
the latter part of Genesis chapter number 12 we had the opportunity to look
at verses 10 through 20 and as we looked at that passage of Scripture we found
that Abram of course had followed the direction of the Lord and had gone to
the promised land to the land of Canaan we refer to it as the promised land and
he arrived in the land of Canaan in the first section of Genesis chapter number
12 of course they had left the Ur of the Chaldees went to Haran and then down to
Canaan the Bible told us in Genesis chapter number 12 that there was a great
famine it was a grievous famine and Abram left with him and his wife and
all that they had lot in his all of the cattle all of the herds all that they
had and they went to Egypt and we found that the Scriptures told us in those 10
verses at the end of Genesis chapter number 12 how that Abram and all that he
had went down into Egypt and we made some interesting under just really
interesting truth that is given to us here in Genesis chapter number 12 with
regard to the demonstration of God's power and the ability for our God to
work through all situations and of course Abram sought to lean on his own
understanding and convince Sarah to say Sarah I at the time that she was his
sister and so on and so forth but God demonstrated his power and protect it
Sarah I and protected Abram and we find that our God is able amen and we don't
have to rely on our own understanding in fact the Bible tells us that we're to
trust in the Lord with all of our hearts that we're not to lean on our own
understanding and what a blessing it is when we see God work and when we have
the opportunity as we did at the end of Genesis chapter number 12 to see what
God is able to do I finished the passage by asking this question did we
learn a lesson I asked if Abram learned a lesson but we know that he repeats
the same mistake later on in the book of Genesis but I wonder this evening and I
asked the question two weeks ago did we learn a lesson did we learn that our God
is able I believe as I mentioned in that particular message that if Abram would
have walked right into Egypt and said yes she is my wife God would have
protected her because our God is able he didn't have to come up with some scheme
and devise some story and I understand that in his mind he justified it because
of the fact that he and and Sarah I were half sisters and so or half siblings and
so on and so forth but we understand that our God is able he is able to do we
understand as we have the New Testament principles in Ephesians 3 that he's able
to do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask her think that's the God
that we serve and we find that after the events unfold at the end of Genesis
chapter number 12 that Pharaoh says to to Abram in verse number 19 why sets now
she is my sister so I might have taken her to meet a wife now therefore behold
thy wife take her and go thy way and the Bible tells us that Pharaoh
commanded his men concerning him and they sent him away and his wife and all
that he had and we enter chapter 13 the fact the passage will be studying this
evening and the Bible says this and Abram went up out of Egypt he and his
wife and all that he had and a lot with him into the south and Abram was very
rich in cattle and silver and gold and he he went on his journeys from the
south even to Bethel under the place where his tent had been at the beginning
between Bethel and AI under the place of the altar which he had made there at
the first and there Abram called on the name of the Lord and lot also which went
with Abram had flocks and herds and tents the land was not able to bear them
that they might dwell together for their substance was great so that they could
not dwell together notice in verse number eight if you will the Bible says
this and Abram said unto lot let there be no strife I pray thee between me and
thee between my herd men and thy herd men for we be brethren now I'd like to
preach a message this evening and really we're gonna look at the entirety of
Genesis 13 that I've simply entitled from verse number eight let there be no
strife let there be no strife as we look at the passage of Scripture and we see
how that Abram would now depart from Egypt he and his family and all that he
had you find that there in verse number one the Bible says that Abram went up
out of Egypt he and his wife notice this and all that he had and lot with him
notice in verse number two the Bible says that Abram was very rich in cattle
and silver and gold we found that in verse number 16 of Genesis 12 the Bible
told us that Pharaoh entreated Abram well for her sake and he Abram had sheep
and oxen and he asses and men servants and maidservants and she asses and
camels and we find that God had blessed Abram and as we consider the passage of
Scripture that is before us and we look at these first six verses if you're
taking notes I want you to notice with me his walk notice the walk of Abram I
want you to consider he had been in the land of Canaan he had been in the very
place where God had promised him to go and as he had gone to that place as he
arrived to the place where God had instructed them and led him to be he
endured difficulty there was a famine I said this is I was speaking to a
missionary friend just on a day or two after I preached the message two weeks
ago here from Genesis chapter number 12 I said the God of the universe I think I
mentioned it during the message as well but the God of the universe he is
omniscient he is omnipotent we find that he knows all things he knows the end
from the beginning he is Alpha and Omega and we find that God Almighty had
directed Abram and his family to travel to arrive in this place when there would
be a famine no doubt in my mind that God could have led Abram to arrive when
there wasn't gonna be a famine no doubt in my mind that God because he's
omnipotent he has all power he could have prevented the famine but you
understand that he led him to arrive when there was gonna be a famine see God
he works in our lives to develop us to help us to trust him and to see what he's
able to do I think about the disciples and how that Jesus said to them get on
the ship and go across the sea knowing that they were going to encounter a
storm by the way he's the same God that could say peace be still and calm the
storm but yet he did not prevent the storm from happening he wanted to show
his power we find that Abram made the decision I mentioned it last time as we
looked at chapter number 12 he made that decision to depart the land that God had
led him to and because of that famine he goes down to Egypt and we find that he's
there throughout the scriptures we find that Egypt is a picture of the world and
we find that he Abram and his family and all that he had they go down to Egypt
and there he has the opportunity to see God work he was fearful that that his
life would be taken because of Sarai and her beauty and the fact that Pharaoh
would take her and yet it was that very Pharaoh that said here take your wife
and be gone we find that he now is going to journey back to the place where
God had originally led him to there in the place of Cain and we found all the
way back in Genesis chapter 3 11 how that God spoke to Abram and gave him
that direction to leave the earth the Cowdys they could not travel across the
Arabian Desert for many reasons and so they had to go northwestward as they
would go to Haran and then they would leave her on and then go down to Canaan
and we find that now this man Abram and all that he has they're now going to
journey and the Bible tells us in verse number three as we think about his walk
and the Bible says that he went on his journey from the south even to Bethel
notice what it says unto the place where his tent had been at the beginning
between Bethel and Ai you notice that as we studied the 12th chapter then in
verse number eight that the Bible tells us that he removed this unto a mountain
on the east of Bethel and pitched his tent having Bethel on the west and Ai on
the east and there he built it an altar unto the Lord and called upon the name
of the Lord and we see the walk of Abram and we see as they would travel and
journey and now they're leaving that place they're leaving Egypt and they're
walking they're journeying back to that land of promise the land that God had
led them to we find that the Bible tells us in verse number four under the place
of the altar which he had made there at the first and there Abram called on the
name of the Lord will come back to verse number four at the end of the message
and make reference there again but I want you to see what the Bible tells us
about lot here in verses five and six and about what's taking place the Bible
says this that the that law also which went with Abram had flocks and herds and
tents now we find that there was a level of blessing that God had poured out not
only upon Abram but upon law as well and we find that they were receiving and
enjoying the blessing of the Lord and the Bible tells us in verse number six
that the land was not able to bear them.
As we would think about the increase of possessions,
it led to a shortage of land.
And we find that the Bible tells us
that the land was not able to bear them,
that they might dwell together,
for their substance was great,
so that they could not dwell together.
I want you to just for a moment
consider as Abram would leave Egypt
and he's following the Lord
and going back to Canaan.
That's a good walk.
As you would walk back to the place
where God had initially led him
as God was giving him that direction.
Of course, we know that Stephen,
as he is preaching in Acts 7,
he makes note of Abram
and his entrance into the land of Canaan
and the dwelling there
and all of the blessing.
And so, we find that now Abram
is back in the place where he's supposed to be.
I'm so thankful that our God is gracious.
I'm so thankful that we can walk with Him.
We spoke about Enoch this morning.
And we spoke about the fact
that he walked with God.
He pleased the Lord.
And we see that in Genesis 11
and verses 5 and 6.
And what a joy.
And now we see that Abram,
as he is walking back,
and I believe that during this journey,
no doubt there were some things
that he would contemplate.
There's some things that he's considering
as he's returning.
And he's experienced some blessings
and he's seeing the rich blessing
that the Lord poured upon him
and upon his nephew Lot.
We find not only his walk,
but I want you to notice number 2
in verses 7-13.
I want you to notice his wisdom.
Notice his wisdom.
In verse 7, the Bible tells us
that there was a strife
between the herdmen of Abram's cattle
and the herdmen of Lot's cattle.
Now, we understand that as we look
at what's taking place here
and we see the cause of this strife
that's revealed to us in verse 6,
the Bible says that the land
was not able to bear them.
And we see that because of their increased goods
and substance that the land was insufficient
and we find that there's this problem
and it results in this strife
and the herdmen of Abram
and the herdmen of Lot,
they have this strife.
And notice what the Bible says
at the end of verse 7,
and the Canaanite and the Perizzite
dwelled then in the land.
Now, we will not take time
to develop all of it,
but we had discussed during the time
in which Noah would make his
prophetic statements how the Canaanites
would be the dwellers of that particular land,
and we see here that the Bible says
that the Canaanite and the Perizzite
dwelled then in the land.
There's a couple of observations
that I make from that statement of Scripture.
Number one is this,
that there are others that are living there.
I think about when Jesus told them
to get on the ship and the Bible says
that there were other little ships.
You know that you're not the only one
going through a storm in life.
Amen?
There were other little ships.
There were other ships on the sea.
There are other folks that are dealing
with difficulties,
and so there's other people in this land,
but one thing that I notice
is that the Canaanite and Perizzite,
these people groups that are mentioned,
they now are witnessing this strife
between the herdmen of Abram
and the herdmen of Lot.
Brethren, it ought not be
that the world would see the people of God
engaged in strife.
Amen?
And that's what we see that's happening.
We see that here,
as there's this strife that's taking place,
no doubt that Abram has a measure of wisdom
as we see as he begins to respond to Lot
and he gives them these options,
and we find it in verse 8
that Abram said unto Lot,
let there be no strife.
Let there be no strife, I pray Thee,
between me and Thee
and between my herdmen and Thy herdmen.
Notice what he says,
for we be brethren.
And we find that Abram,
as he would respond properly
to this problem that is here,
we understand in life
that there's no doubt
that we're going to face problems.
We're going to face difficulties and challenges.
Can I tell you that the enemy,
he seeks to cause division.
He seeks to set people at variance
one with another.
He seeks to divide
and to cause schisms within the body.
That's what the enemy wants to do.
And we find here that Abram responds
and he says,
let there be no strife, I pray Thee,
between me and Thee
and between my herdmen and Thy herdmen,
for we be brethren.
For we be brethren.
I notice that as we would look
at the response of Abram here
and we're noticing the wisdom of Abram
that we will understand
and easily recognize this evening
that if we're going to resolve
the problems that we face in life,
that we are going to need the wisdom of God.
And the thing that's wonderful
is that God says that He'll give us wisdom.
We can have His wisdom.
We don't have to rely upon our own
way of thinking and our own solutions to problems.
We can have the wisdom of God.
I want to keep your spot here,
but turn to the book of 1 Kings if you will
in chapter 3.
And we're familiar with the passage of Scripture
here in 1 Kings 3
and what's taking place.
And you find that Solomon is now
the king of Israel
and he is now sitting and reigning
and his father David of course,
a great king,
and now Solomon,
the third king of the nation of Israel,
Saul, David, and now Solomon.
And he's reigning
and he's real early on here in his reign.
And the Bible tells us
that the Lord appears to him.
And as the Lord appears to him,
in verse 5 it says,
in Gibeon, the Lord appeared to Solomon
in a dream by night
and God said,
ask what I shall give thee.
Can you imagine?
I was reading just recently
through the Gospel records
and how Herod said to ask what you want of me.
And of course, the whole situation
with the head of John the Baptist.
You think about Ahasuerus
when he says to Esther,
ask what you will up to the half of my kingdom.
And here, the God of the universe
appears to Solomon in this dream
and He says, ask what I shall give thee.
And we find that Solomon responds
in verse 6,
and Solomon said,
Thou hast showed unto Thy servant David,
my father, great mercy,
according as he walked before Thee
in truth and in righteousness
and in uprightness of heart with Thee.
And Thou hast kept for him
this great kindness
that Thou hast given him a son
to sit on his throne as it is this day.
Do you see in verse 6
the humility of Solomon?
The recognition of the goodness of God
in his life and the blessing
and the mercy that God has shown,
the favor that God has shown?
You see it in verse 6.
Notice as he continues in verse 7,
And now, O Lord my God,
Thou hast made Thy servant king
instead of David my father.
And I am but a little child.
I know not how to go out or come in.
And Thy servant is in the midst of Thy people
which Thou hast chosen a great people
that cannot be numbered
nor counted for multitude.
Give therefore Thy servant
an understanding heart to judge Thy people
that I may discern between good and bad
for who is able to judge this
Thy so great a people?
I love what the Bible tells us in verse 10.
And the speech pleased the Lord.
That Solomon had asked this thing.
Solomon said give me understanding.
Give me wisdom
to be able to lead and judge Thy people.
Notice the text of Scripture
in 1 Kings 3, beginning in verse 16.
We don't have time to deal with all of it,
but down through verse 28
is the first opportunity for Solomon
to display this wisdom
that God had supernaturally given him.
And we find that there's this situation
with a child that died in the night
and the one mother says,
no, the dead child's yours.
And the other one says, no, the dead child's yours.
And so on and so forth.
And the Bible says this in verse 22,
And the other woman said, nay,
but the living is my son
and the dead is thy son.
And this said, no.
But the dead is thy son
and the living is my son.
Thus they spake before the king.
Verse 23, Then said the king,
the one saith, this is my son that liveth
and thy son is the dead.
And the other saith, nay,
but thy son is the dead
and my son is the living.
Apart from the wisdom of God,
you're going to have a real hard time
figuring out whose son is who.
Who's telling the truth?
What's going on here?
In Solomon, he says bring me a sword.
Can you imagine?
Again, we're familiar with this,
but put yourself, inject yourself here
in the passage of Scripture.
The king said, bring me a sword.
And they brought a sword before the king.
And the king said, divide the living child in two
and give half to the one
and half to the other.
What?
Who would think of that?
Then spake the woman whose the living child was
unto the king in verse 26,
for her bowels yearned upon her son.
And she said, oh my Lord,
give her the living child
and in no wise slay it.
But the other said,
let it be neither mine nor thine,
but divide it.
What?
Solomon had his answer.
This wisdom that was on display,
the Bible says,
then the king answered and said,
give her the living child.
living child and in no wise lay it she is the mother thereof and I want you to
notice in verse 28 the Bible says in all Israel heard of the judgment which the
king had judged and they feared the king for they saw that the wisdom of God was
in him to do judgment we need wisdom listen we live in a crazy world and we
don't need earthly wisdom which is not what we're speaking of the scene we're
talking about that heavenly wisdom that wisdom that comes from the omniscient
God who made this promise in James 1 in verse number 5 if any man lack right if
we lack wisdom let him ask of God who give it to all men liberally in a
braided knot and we find that in that passage of Scripture one of the things
that I have determined that is so essential for us is that the Bible says
if any man lacked the problem is that we have to recognize that we lack it so
that we ask for it but too often we don't have the kind of humility that
Solomon had see Solomon had the humility to say God's asking me what I want I can
ask him whatever I want and Solomon says you've been so good to me God you've
blessed me you've done all of these things you've shown mercy and all that
you've done I need wisdom Solomon wasn't full of himself he wasn't prideful
by the way I believe this evening that a prideful individual is not going to
recognize their need for wisdom they're not gonna ask for wisdom because they
don't think they need it they think they already have it amen and so where does
it begin it begins with that level of humility with us recognizing Lord I need
your wisdom and I'm praying I believe that you said I'm asking in faith I
believe that you said that if we ask that you'll give it so God I need your
wisdom by the way if you're asking God for wisdom you better get in the book
because he's gonna use his word to give you wisdom amen you're not gonna just go
to sleep at night and bam you're gonna have all this wisdom all right you need
to get in the word that's how God's gonna give it to you that's how he's
gonna provide that wisdom to you and we notice the wisdom back in Genesis
chapter number 13 the wisdom of Abram here in the passage of Scripture he says
let there be no strife in verse number 8 for we be brethren look at what he says
in verse number 9 is not the whole land before they separate myself I pray thee
from me notice that Abram makes this proposal to Lot and he says this if thou
will take the left hand that I will go to the right or if thou depart to the
right hand that I will go to the left he gives Lot the choice he makes the
proposal and he says to Lot listen here's how we need to solve this problem
it's not good for us to be in this situation where we have too much
substance the land is not adequate to support all of us and we need to be able
to separate because we need to have no strife between us it's a lot here's the
deal you choose where you want to go if you choose to the right I'll go to the
left if you choose the left I'll go to the right we find that the Bible tells
us that Lot makes the choice in verses 10 through 13 it's recorded for us that
Lot lifted up his eyes and beheld all the plain of Jordan that it was well
watered everywhere before the Lord destroyed Sodom and Gomorrah even as the
garden of the Lord like the land of Egypt is now comest unto Zoar then Lot
chose him all the plain of Jordan and Lot journeyed east and they separated
themselves the one from the other it says this in verse 12 Abram dwelt in the
land of Canaan and Lot dwelt in the cities of the plain and pitched his tent
towards Sodom it won't take long before he is in Sodom and the discussion of the
slippery slope of the decision of Lot will be detailed as we continue to
journey through the book of Genesis in fact it's in chapter 14 and verse 12 the
Bible tells us that he lot dwelt in Sodom and before long he'll be at the
city gate we find that he made this poor decision but we find that that decision
again separate from we're dealing with with Abram we see the wisdom of Abram
want you to consider with me he says let there be no strife let me make a New
Testament application if I can turn the book to Philippians if you will in
Philippians chapter number two as we look at the New Testament Church and we
look at the books of the Bible in the New Testament that are written to
churches and we find that these a number of these epistles are written to these
bodies of believers we understand that there in the church in Corinth there was
much division and strife and all sorts of things going on the church in Corinth
is known for being a carnal church Paul says that it's reported amongst you that
there's these divisions and stripes he said I believe it and we find that he
addresses those things and here in the book of Philippians I want you to notice
in verse number one of chapter number two Paul says this to the church in
Philippi if there be therefore any consolation in Christ if any comfort of
love of any fellowship of the Spirit if any bowels and mercies to fill ye my joy
notice what he says that you be like minded having the same love being of one
accord of one mind let what is the next word nothing that's a pretty significant
word is it not I mean it excludes everything right let nothing be done how
through strife or vainglory but in lowliness of mind let each esteem other
better than themselves look not every man on his own things but every man also
on the things of others he says let there be no strife he says this let
nothing be done through strife or vainglory we see that Abram says let
there be no strife why for we be brethren and Paul says of the believers
in Philippi he says let nothing be done through strife or vainglory we
understand this subject matter of vainglory it's the the individual
attention that is somebody wants and they want to be right they want to be
first they want to be recognized whatever the situation is and we find
here he says let nothing be done on those terms let there be no strife let
there be no vainglory he says this as we go through the passage he says look not
every man on his own things but every man also on the things of others we
speak about the importance of being a servant we speak about the importance of
recognizing the opportunities that God would give us to be a blessing to others
too often we get our eyes on our own lives my problem my situation my issue
my whatever and we might miss opportunities to be able to be a
blessing to be used of the Lord in somebody else's life because we're too
focused on me we're too focused on self and notice the example that Paul gives
in verse number five let this mind be in you which was also in Christ Jesus so he
uses the Lord Jesus Christ is the perfect example of this instruction is
giving here and we're familiar with the passage of Scripture here in Philippians
chapter number two he says let this mind be in you which was also in Christ Jesus
who being in the form of God thought it not robbery be equal with God he is God
incarnate the Lord Jesus Christ we understand that he says in John 17 that
that he experienced that glory that he had from the beginning he was going to
finish the work we understand that in John chapter one as John the Baptist is
there who by the way physically speaking is older than the Lord Jesus Christ
Elizabeth gave birth to John the Baptist before Mary gave birth to the Lord Jesus
Christ and we find that John the Baptist says that he is before me he is
preferred above me and we find that he's understanding the eternality of the Lord
Jesus Christ and he's God incarnate and he comes it says here in verse 7 but made
himself of no reputation and took upon the form of a servant was made in the
likeness of men have you really stopped and considered the truth of what the
Lord Jesus Christ did for us and leave I mean we understand Calvary and what a
blessing and how grateful we are we think about this truth that he left the
the glory of heaven Paul said it this way as he's speaking to the church in
Corinth and in 2nd Corinthians 8 in verse number 9 he says for you know the grace
of our Lord Jesus Christ that though he was rich yet for your sakes he became
poor that ye through his poverty might be rich verse 7 but made himself of no
reputation and took upon him the form of a servant was made in the likeness of
men and being found in fashion as a man he humbled himself and became obedient
unto death even the death of the cross wherefore God also hath highly exalted
him and given him a name which is above every name that at the name of Jesus
every knee should bow things in heaven things in earth things under the earth
that every tongue should confess that Jesus Christ is Lord to the glory of God
the Father Paul says let nothing be done through strife or vain glory Solomon the
one that we mentioned his wisdom that was on display in first Kings chapter
number three he tells us in the book of Proverbs that by pride comes contention
by pride comes destruction we find that here is we would look at the truth of
of Genesis chapter number 13.
And as we look at the life of Abram
as it's traced here in these verses of Scripture
and these events that are unfolding in his life,
he was walking with the Lord.
He was returning back to the place where God had led him.
But we find that there's a problem again.
Remember, there was a problem in Genesis chapter number 12.
There was a great famine.
And now there's a problem.
There's strife between his herdmen and Lot's herdmen.
And the wisdom of Abram is on display
in how he addresses that problem
and how he deals with that.
We have the privilege of tracing
the steps of the life of Abraham.
And we have the privilege of being able
to see much Scripture that is given to us.
And as we would analyze and look at the Scriptures,
we would have the opportunities
to see the way in which he lived his life
and how we can learn lessons as we live our lives.
We need wisdom.
We're going to have problems.
We need God's wisdom.
Not only do we see the walk and wisdom of Abram,
but I want you to notice his worship.
It's interesting how that in Hebrews 11,
this morning we dealt with the walk of Enoch
and we dealt with the worship of Abel.
And here we see the walk of Abram
and the worship of Abram.
But I want you to notice the Bible tells us this
in verse number 13,
and then we'll get right into verses 14 through 18
and look at the worship of Abram.
But notice what the Bible says,
but the men of Sodom were wicked and sinners
before the Lord exceedingly.
And again, that's the place in which Lot had chosen
and pitched his tent towards Sodom.
But now the Lord is going to speak to Abram.
Isn't that encouraging?
I understand this morning, this evening,
I said this morning twice already, man alive.
I didn't sleep well last night.
I'll blame it on that.
But the reality, I had an hour nap this afternoon
in my office.
I woke up and I really didn't know where I was.
It was amazing.
Amen.
And praise the Lord.
I put that recliner back and I was out.
And anyway, the Bible says that the Lord said unto Abram,
see God audibly spoke to his servants.
And sometimes people today say,
I wish God would audibly speak to me.
You have this book.
This is the voice of God.
This is God speaking to us as His people today.
By the way, I understand that as we go through life,
that it's very easy for us to say,
well, I wish that was my situation.
I wish I was over there.
I would exchange these problems for those problems.
Probably if you did, you'd find out that you made a mistake.
Sometimes we say, man, I wish I lived in that era.
I wish I lived during that time.
I wish I had the experience of what these folks had.
Listen, I'm thankful to live in 2020
and to have the whole Bible.
What a blessing.
And we find that God in His wisdom has allowed us,
ordained us to be alive today.
And so we have this truth of the Word of God
and we have the very voice of God.
We have the words of God.
And here the Bible says the Lord said unto Abram,
I wonder this evening, when you read your Bible,
when you attend a church service like this,
are you listening for the voice of God?
Are you looking for God to speak to you?
Do we come with that expectation,
with that anticipation when we enter
into our time of devotion on a daily basis?
When we come to a church service,
are we coming expecting that God is going to speak to me?
Are we coming anticipating saying, Lord, I'm listening?
It's like Samuel, right?
When he goes to Eli, you've called.
No, I didn't.
He comes again, you call, no, I didn't.
He says, here's what you do.
Next time you hear it, say, speak, Lord,
thy servant listens, hears.
See, are we listening for the voice of God?
I had the privilege this week of speaking to someone
who I best could describe the conversation
as an individual who's hungering and thirsting
after God and after righteousness.
Can I tell you, those are exciting conversations.
When someone just, I mean, two hours
and 20 minutes pass like that.
Why, because it's like, tell me something else.
Give me some more truth.
Show me this.
I mean, they're hungering and thirsting
after the word of God.
I love it.
It's great.
And I wonder in our lives, is it just a box that we check?
Read my Bible today, went to church this morning,
went to church tonight, went to the revival meeting,
checked the box.
Are we coming to listen for the voice of God?
God, speak to me.
The Lord spoke to Abram.
And notice what the Lord said in verse 14 and following.
The Lord said unto Abram after that lot
was separated from him, lift up now thine eyes
and look from the place where thou art.
Northward, southward, eastward, and westward.
In other words, he says, look everywhere,
in every direction.
From the place where you are, look in every direction.
That's what God tells him.
And then God says this.
For all the land which thou seest,
to thee will I give it and to thy seed forever.
That's a great promise, is it not?
The promise of God to Abram with regard to the land.
We find that it's not only the land, but it's the seed.
We find that he says that the land which thou seest,
to thee will I give it and to thy seed forever.
And I will, notice where he says,
I will make thy seed as the dust of the earth
so that if a man can number the dust of the earth,
then shall thy seed also be numbered by the way.
We're familiar with Abraham and Sarah.
Now, Abram and Sarai, do they have any seed?
No!
Sarai, the Bible tells us in chapter number 11,
she's barren.
And yet, God is giving this promise
about the blessing, not only of the land, but the seed.
By the way, they're both elevated in years, shall we say?
But God's making a promise.
Can I tell you this evening
that when God makes a promise, it's sure.
We can stand upon it.
We sing the song, by the way, standing on the promises.
I cannot fall, right?
The songwriter says.
And we think about the promises of God.
Peter says that they're exceeding precious,
great and precious promises.
We get into the word of God and we study it and we say,
God, you have some promises for me today.
He does.
Look for them.
Search them out.
Reclaim them.
The promises of God.
He says, I'm gonna give you a land.
I'm gonna bless your seed.
Notice in verse 17, he continues,
God speaking to Abram and says,
arise, walk through the land in the length of it
and in the breadth of it, for I will give it unto thee.
We're speaking about the worship of God.
We're noticing the way in which Abram
would worship the Lord.
But in verses 14 through 17, we're really seeing
the way in which God is speaking to Abram.
But the response of this promise,
the response to this promise,
the response of Abram is to worship the Lord.
To worship the Lord.
We see in verse number 18,
it says, then Abram removed his tent.
The idea of that phraseology that we find
in verse number 17, God's instruction was,
arise, walk through the land in the length of it
and the breadth of it, for I will give it unto thee.
And so the idea of then Abram removed his tent
is that he began to journey and moving his tent with them
as he was going through the land.
And he's moving and he's taking, making progress,
following what God said in verse number 17.
And he kept moving along the way, staking his claim,
believing the promise of God.
Faith.
And it says this,
and came and dwelt in the plain of Mamre,
which is in Hebron, and notice,
and built there an altar unto the Lord.
It is said on a number of occasions about Abram
that he built an altar unto the Lord.
We read it on a number of occasions in chapter number 12.
We read in chapter 13 and verse number four
how that he came to the place which he had made there
at the first and there that altar that he made.
Remember in verse number three,
it says that he came to a place where his tent
had been at the beginning between Bethel and Ai.
And we find that there he had built that altar.
And here the Bible says in verse number four
that Abram called on the name of the Lord.
He did that back in chapter number 12
as we found record of that in verse number eight.
And now we see in chapter number 13 and verse number four
and in verse number 18,
there he built an altar unto the Lord.
He's worshiping the Lord.
See, Abram is living during the era of Israel's history
where there is no tabernacle.
That's not gonna come for a long period of time.
There is no temple that's even further out in the distance.
And so what did Abram do?
Built an altar.
By the way, that's what Noah did after he got off the ark.
We spoke about that this morning as well.
that he built an altar and he called upon the Lord and he's worshiping the Lord.
So we think about the promises of God and we think about
the way in which God is giving and speaking to Abram
here in this passage of Scripture in verses 14 through 17.
The natural response is to worship the Lord.
To worship Him. This evening as we would take the passage of Scripture that is
before us and we would consider the walk and the wisdom and
the worship of Abram, I wonder as we walk with God,
are we daily walking with Him like we should be? Are we in the place where
we're supposed to be? Are we asking God and depending on God
for the wisdom that we need for the the problems that we face in life?
There will be problems. There are problems.
Right? We need God's wisdom and we see that Abram, we notice his
wisdom on display here in the passage. But how thankful I am for how the
Lord spoke to him. You understand that God didn't speak to Lot in this
fashion, in this manner. See, Lot chose something based upon
sight. He lifted up his eyes and he saw this and he...
By the way, he's pitched towards Sodom. We said already that the men
of that city were wicked and sinners before the Lord exceedingly.
He'd soon be influenced by them. But as Abram made that decision, he made
that proposal and he told Lot, you choose and I'll go the
other way. And then the Lord spoke to him. He says,
look at every direction. I'm going to give you this land. I'm
going to bless your seed. And what does he do? He
worships. Can I tell you this morning? Oh man, this
evening? Can I tell you tonight? Listen, three times. Man, alive.
Can I tell you this evening? That we need to worship God.
Listen, when you approach the Word of God and He speaks to you
and He gives you some promises, oh would you just worship Him?
You know, what a joy it is to just get in His presence for a little while.
Not necessarily to ask for anything. Just to worship Him.
Just to praise Him for who He is. Just to thank Him for giving you a Bible.
For giving you a church where you can go and
hear the Word of God. For giving you an opportunity to receive
the promises of God. To be in a place where you've been
aware of who He is. How He's revealed Himself to you.
Oh, you just get in His presence a little while and you begin to
just get filled with God and stand in awe of who He is.
You begin to worship. It's amazing how you find yourself in that place and
how God will bless. And how God will come and commune with
you. And how He will meet the needs of
each of us, His people. He's a God who is able.
This evening we see that Abram, the passage finishes with him
worshiping. With him worshiping the Lord. Building an altar.
We see his walk. We see his wisdom. We see his worship. This evening, oh that we'd
walk with God. Oh that we'd ask God, recognize that we
need His wisdom. Get into the book and worship Him. He is
worthy of our worship. Let's pray. Father, we love you.
We thank you so much for loving us.
We thank you for who you are. You are the Lord God Omnipotent.
El Shaddai, the Lord God Almighty. In just a little while,
in Bible history, from the place where we are this evening, you will reveal
yourself to Abraham as El Shaddai, Lord God Almighty.
We thank you that you've given us your Word.
And then on a regular basis, as often as we please, we can
enter into your presence. Dig into your Word.
Commune with you.
The thought of that calls us to rejoice.
That we could be in your presence. We thank you that you spoke to Abraham.
We thank you this evening that we have the entirety of the Bible and that you
still speak to us today. And God, I pray that you'd help us to
listen for your voice. I pray that you'd help us to
enter our daily time with you in each church service that we attend.
Anticipate and expecting that you're going to speak to us.
Help us to receive and claim the promises. Help us, Lord, to worship you,
for you are worthy of our worship.
Lord, I pray this evening that we've been challenged and encouraged by the
opportunity to study these events in the life of Abraham.
Perhaps there are some this evening that have some
problems that they're facing in life. They need your wisdom.
God, would you help us, as Solomon did, to humble ourselves.
To recognize that you are the all-wise God and that you've promised to give us
wisdom if we simply ask.
Help us to humble ourselves and to acknowledge our need.
And God, we trust you to give us the wisdom that we need to
navigate this life and to address problems that will arise. I pray, God, that
you would work in hearts and lives that decisions would be made that would
please thee and we'll thank you for it. Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed,
eyes are closed. Holly's going to play quietly on the piano.
As she does, we'll have a time of invitation, opportunity for you to
respond. Maybe you just want to thank God. Maybe
you want to ask him for wisdom. Maybe there's some problems you're dealing
with in life.
And you just want to come and worship the Lord a little bit this evening.
Thank him for speaking to you. Thank him for
allowing you to enter into his presence. As Holly plays, the altar is open.