It's been great this week, hasn't it?
And thank you to you who have prepared
and then sung the music.
I think sometimes we're very careful to appreciate
those who teach and preach and things like that.
And sometimes we forget that the amount of work
that goes into preparing the music
that so blesses our heart.
So for all of those of you that come early
and all of those of you that prepare through the week
and then present those beautiful songs to us,
they bless my heart.
I'm grateful for that and thank you for it.
Well, let's take our Bibles tonight
and would you turn with me to Ephesians chapter three.
Aren't you glad I didn't say Psalms?
I do know there's a New Testament, okay?
Ephesians chapter three.
Two verses as our text, verses 20 and 21.
There the Bible says,
"'Now unto him that is able to do exceeding abundantly
"'above all that we ask or think
"'according to the power that worketh in us,
"'unto him be glory in the church by Christ Jesus,
"'throughout all ages, world without end, amen.'"
Let's pray.
Father, we're grateful for this evening
that you've given us.
We're thankful for the rain.
Lord, we appreciate the blessing of that.
We pray now that you would speak to our hearts
as we gather together.
We're here because we do desire to know your word,
to be instructed from it.
And Lord, we confess to you
that we desperately need your spirit's help
in discerning its truth and how to apply it to our lives.
So would you use this time, minister to our hearts,
teach us, convict us where we need to be convicted,
encourage people.
I pray in Jesus' name, amen.
When the Israelites came up out of Egypt,
they came up shouting.
They were rejoicing.
They had been crying out to the Lord for years and years
because of the bondage that they found themselves in.
Living in Egypt in the end was far different
from when they went into Egypt.
And the taskmasters demanded great effort from all of them
and there was great cruelty
in the effort that they demanded.
And so when God finally worked,
and I shouldn't say it that way,
when God did work and the plagues were accomplished
and Pharaoh was convinced by the mighty power of God
to let his people, God's people go,
it was amazing what took place
and just seemed like a moment.
They were out of bondage and coming out
to what they had known to be or had heard to be
the promised land.
Not only were they coming out free people,
but the Egyptians had been moved
to shower them with great treasures.
And they weren't coming out poor shepherds.
They were coming out with great riches
from perhaps the wealthiest
and most affluent kingdom on earth at that time.
They were bringing their herds with them.
I've heard all kinds of estimates
of how many was in their number,
but I don't think it's at all an exaggeration
to say that there were at least a million people
marching up out of Egypt,
carrying the treasures of Egypt
with all of their families and all of their flocks
and all of their herds, and they were rejoicing.
They were following God's will
and God was leading and God was blessing.
And in God's will and by God's hand,
God marched them right down to the shores of the Red Sea.
And all of a sudden when they are confronted with a sea,
and by the way, it wasn't the Reed Sea,
it was the Red Sea, it was a real sea.
And there was no way, they weren't shipbuilders,
they weren't engineers of that nature.
And when they realized that they could not go forward,
my goodness, their joy turned to real anger.
And sometimes when we get angry, it turns to blame.
And these same people that had been singing
are now crying out to Moses,
"'Because there were no graves in Egypt,
"'hast thou taken us away to die in the wilderness?
"'Wherefore hast thou dealt thus with us
"'to carry us forth out of Egypt?
"'Is not this the word that we did tell thee in Egypt,
"'saying, let us alone, that we may serve the Egyptians?
"'For it had been better for us to serve the Egyptians
"'than that we should die in this wilderness.'"
Now can I remind you,
that's not what they were saying in Egypt.
They weren't saying, oh, Moses, leave us alone.
We love it here.
We love the lash on our back.
We love being in bondage.
We love not having freedom to live our lives as we want.
They were begging to be delivered.
But now they stand at the shore of the Red Sea.
If they turn to their right, basically to their right,
they're going to find the wilderness of Sinai,
the wilderness of sin.
God's going to eventually lead them through that.
But right now, there's no way in their own strength
and intellect they can negotiate that wilderness.
If they go to the left,
they're going to soon encounter a place called Migdal.
Migdal was the largest fortress of the Egyptian army
outside of the palace of the capital city.
And bearing down upon them with great fervor and furor
is the entire Egyptian army.
And they are now using that new engine of war,
the iron-wheeled chariot.
And Israel begins to realize we're caught, we're trapped.
There is nothing we can do.
We can't go forward.
We can't go back.
We can't go to the right.
We can't go to the left.
And I love in that moment that God speaks to Moses.
Says, Moses, talk to him.
Here's what he says, fear ye not.
Aren't you glad in the most horrific circumstances
God speaks to us and says, fear ye not.
I've got this.
Fear ye not.
Stand still and see the salvation of the Lord,
which he shall show you today.
For the Egyptians whom you have seen today,
ye shall see them again no more.
You see, the Israelites' great problem was this.
They were boxed in.
And they thought their greatest problem
was that they had the sea in front of them,
Migdal to their left, Wilderness to their right,
the army of the Egyptians to their rear.
But their greatest handicap was that their perspective
on life was contained in the box of their own abilities.
In other words, because they could not perceive
how to get across that ocean,
because they knew no way to go through a wilderness,
no way to get through the army at Migdal,
they had no clue how to vanquish
that army coming up behind them.
Because of that, they ascribed to the Lord,
well, there must not be any way.
If we can't figure it out, there must not be any way.
And then Moses, by the direction of God,
raises that staff.
And you know what happens.
That sea begins to divide.
I used to, in my heart, think that it would divide
about, oh, 20 or 30 feet.
And then I read a book and got to thinking
about a million people with flocks and herds
going across that.
And I think that thing may have been a mile wide.
And if God wanted it to be two miles,
it was two miles wide.
And in my mind, a wind comes down
and dries that seabed out.
And all of Israel and all of their possessions,
everything, crosses over on dry ground.
Let me stop and say this clearly.
Pastor, do you believe that was really true?
Yeah, I believe that was really true.
I believe God really did that.
And they cross over and they get to the other side
and the Egyptian army is now on them
and they see that gateway to the ones
that they're pursuing.
And they come down into that ocean
and God just closes it up.
I don't relish in the loss of life,
but I acknowledge the power of God.
And I'm sure over on that far seashore,
there was an Egyptian deacon.
I mean, an Israelite deacon saying,
I thought that's what God would do.
I kind of knew that's what God, no you didn't.
I'm just saying to you that God is able to do what you and I cannot even conceive of him doing.
And we need to rearrange our thinking and allow God to be God and believe that God can be God
in our lives. Sometimes it's easier to believe that God can be God and do great things in somebody
else's life, but God can be God and do great things in our life. Don't limit what God can do.
Three thoughts tonight, very quickly, well I won't make that promise.
The great possibilities of our God, the great poverty of our minds,
and the great purpose of our lives. Here we go. Consider with me for a moment
the great possibilities of our God. Go back to verse 20. Now unto him that is able.
Let me shorten that. God is able. You believe that? I do. I find it comforting to say,
but can be honest with you, sometimes saying it does not translate into my life living it.
Believing that God is able. That word able is a very interesting word. Probably you've heard it.
It is the Greek word dunami. And I took elementary Greek almost 50 some years ago,
and so I am a scholar. I am an expert on the ancient language. No I'm not,
but I got a strong concordance on my computer and I love to look up words.
And I'm told, I don't know, I'm not scholarly enough to know if it's true, but I'm told that
word denotes great power, and we took it literally from the Greek over to our language,
from dunami to dynamite, because it speaks of great power. If you read Mr. Strong, and I suggest
you do sometimes, Mr. Strong says it means simply this, literally, to be possible. The word dunami
means to be possible. I think we can understand it this way, with God to whom everything is
possible. I think the Bible even says that. I want you to understand that we serve a supernatural
God. Our God is not bound by the laws of nature. Our God created the laws of nature.
And anytime God wants to suspend the laws of nature or transcend the laws of nature,
God can make that choice. It is His prerogative, because God is a supernatural God. We,
like the Israelites, sometimes make God natural like us. God is not natural like us. He is a
supernatural God. There was a day when God sent His angel to a young lady in Israel.
She was a godly young lady, pure. She had a desire to be a servant of the Lord, to be used of the
Lord, and God was going to use her. And so God came and sent the angel to her, and the angel
said to her, Mary, you're going to have a baby. And not in a sinful, doubting way,
but in a wonderment way, Mary says to the angel, well, you don't understand.
You see, Mr. Angel, there's a biological process whereby men become daddies and
mommies become mommies. And I have not entered into that process, so I think maybe you found
the wrong Mary, because it wouldn't be possible for me to have a child, because I have not been
with man. And I love the angel. God's Word, He says back to her, the Holy Ghost shall come upon
thee, and the power of the highest shall overshadow thee. Therefore also that holy thing
which shall be born of thee shall be called the Son of God. And behold, thy cousin Elizabeth,
she has also conceived a son in her old age, and this is the sixth month with her, who was called
barren. For with God, nothing shall be impossible. Mary, I know you've got honest questions.
I know there's confusion in your mind, so let me explain it to you. Here's what's going to happen.
The Holy Ghost is going to come upon you, and the Holy Ghost is going to overshadow you.
And because our great and supernatural God may choose to do as He pleases, the Holy Ghost is
going to put in your womb a child. Not a child conceived by a human father, lest he have a sin
nature, but a child conceived, if you will, in the mind of God. And God is going to place that in your
womb. And then in an amazing process, He's going to overshadow you, and that child is going to grow
as a child normally grows in your womb. And when you come to full term, you're going to give birth
to a baby boy that has not got the seed of man, but is the seed of God, because He's going to save
people from their sins. And Mary said, okay. You say, preacher, we think you're pushing the limits
tonight. You got us crossing an ocean on dry ground, and now you're telling us you believe
that a virgin can conceive and bear a son? Yes. Do you actually believe that, preacher? Yes.
Can you explain it to me, preacher? Yes. The Holy Ghost is going to come upon her,
and going to overshadow her. And those are God's words. And by faith, I trust what God,
and only God can do. And He says to Mary, hey, just in case you wonder about the power of God,
God's going to do it that way with you. But you do remember your cousin Elizabeth up north,
don't you? Well, God's also done something marvelous in her life. Her and her husband,
who are both way past childbearing age. Hey, your cousin Elizabeth is with child six months,
because God can do what God wants to do, because God is able. And you and I need to stop being so
academic, and so intellectual, and so careful about being misunderstood or perceived,
that we limit God to what we think we can do. God is able. Do you believe that tonight?
Can God do the miraculous in your life? Can God do the miraculous in this church?
Can God do the miraculous in America today? Can God do the miraculous in a culture that is so
far away from Him? And I'm simply here to remind you that sometimes we've got to remind
ourselves about the great possibilities of our God. He is a supernatural God.
Let's deal with this. The poverty of our minds. Again in verse 20,
Now unto Him that is able to do, to do what? Exceeding abundantly above all that we ask
or think. God's ability and possibility are infinitely above mine. It is above my asking,
but to be perfectly honest with you, it's above even what I can think and imagine.
One of the goals of our lives ought to be to think like God thinks, because we will never ask
like God wants us to ask, until we think like God wants us to think.
Have you ever thought about in the Word of God, how many times God reveals to us
that our thinking is so different than His thinking? Think about a few thoughts,
or about a few places. He reveals to us that there's a definite difference between His thoughts
and our own. In Isaiah 55, you don't have to turn there, I know you're familiar with these.
For my thoughts are not your thoughts. Every once in a while I'll stop and I'll say to people,
I had an amazing realization today. And they'll say, why? And I'll say, I realized God is smarter
than me. I have that realization many times a day, do you? God is smarter than me. His ways
are higher than my ways. His thoughts are higher than my thoughts. And I've got to acknowledge
in my life that God sees and perceives and thinks of things that are above me.
He says this to me in James 4,
ye lust and have not,
ye kill and desire to have and cannot obtain,
ye fight and war, yet ye have not because ye ask not.
Why don't we ask?
Will ye ask and receive not because ye ask amiss,
that ye may consume it upon your lusts?
You know who I love?
Me.
I really like me.
And I think you probably really like you.
And sometimes I'm so myopic that I view life just from me.
And it's all about me.
It's all about what I think I need.
It's all about what I think I want.
It's all about what I think I deserve.
And what God is saying,
he's not saying you're a lustful man
who's having lustful thoughts.
He is saying you're so wrapped up in your own desires
that you can't see beyond what you perceive.
You can't see beyond what you can think.
You can't see beyond what you want.
And you don't ask right because you're so prone
to asking for just the way you see it
and just what you want.
He says, have this confidence.
If we have in him,
that if we ask anything according to his will,
he heareth us.
And if we know that he hear us,
whatsoever we ask,
we know that we have the petitions
that we've desired of him.
Well, what a pursuit in life
to come to the place where we understand,
where we know,
where we come into alignment with God's will.
What a prayer life
when we come into alignment with God's will.
He challenges us to have the mind of Christ.
Wow.
Let this mind be in you,
which was also in Christ Jesus.
What is that?
Several years ago,
when I went to Bible college,
I was a married student.
There was a number of married students
and I'm just like everybody else.
It was just so busy.
You would go to class.
You would take a few minutes to study
or go to the library.
You'd go to work.
You'd go home.
You'd have an hour.
You'd go to bed.
You'd get up and rinse and repeat
and do it over and over again.
There wasn't a lot of time for fellowship.
You just had to get it all done.
And there were a number of us
that were in that boat.
One particular,
a man who we sat together in a number of classes.
Our families had fellowship sometimes,
a few times over the year,
two, three that we were together.
But we developed a friendship
without a lot of fellowship.
And when we graduated,
he went the way of the mission field.
I went the way of pastoral here in the States.
And we maintained contact.
When I started a church,
he was one of the first two or three missionaries
that we took on for support,
though he did not come home
because he was wrapped up in the work.
He didn't take a furlough for nearly 20 years.
He called me one day and he said,
hey, I'm taking a furlough.
And I thought maybe I'd come
and show your people who I am.
You know, you've been supporting us 20 years.
And I said, man, when you get here,
what a wonderful thing.
Come to our conference.
While you're here,
we're gonna spend some time together.
And you and I'll just make some time to get away.
We're gonna just rehearse to each other
all what God has done in 20 years.
And so they did come
and had a wonderful conference.
We found time to get out to breakfast.
And I only take people to the finest restaurants.
And so we went to IHOP.
And we're sitting there at IHOP
and we're enjoying each other
and telling each other what God has done.
And ever seen somebody
and you know the wheels are turning,
but there's no connection being made?
And I looked at him and I said,
Jack, if you don't see anything you like here,
we can, there's another fine restaurant
across the street, Waffle House is right over there.
We can go there.
He said, no, it's not that.
He said, I have for 20 years
been thinking in Spanish.
And he said, I'm struggling coming back
and just in a couple of weeks thinking in English.
And he said, for the life of me,
I can't figure out what rooty tooty fresh and fruity is.
I said, Jack, absolutely nobody knows
what rooty tooty fresh and fruity is.
It comes out different every time.
But in that moment, in that moment,
the Holy Spirit spoke to me.
And he said, you know what your problem is, Mike?
You have thought in Edwards for so long
that you're gonna have to retrain yourself
to think in Jesus.
Now, I'm not trying to be funny or cute in that.
I'm just saying to you that one of the pursuits
of our lives has to be to allow the Word of God
and the Spirit of God retrain, renew,
to be not conformed to the world, but to be transformed.
And one of the passions,
one of the zealous passions of our life must be,
God, I want to see it your way.
I want to see it your way.
And not long after that revelation,
I looked up into the face of God
and I said something like this.
I won't quote it, but I said something like this.
God, how can I do that?
I'm locked in me.
How can I change it all?
How can I make it think different?
How can I see it different?
How can I accomplish that?
How can I get the mind of Christ in Edwards?
And I'll tell you, God showed me something,
and I want to show it to you tonight.
Notice this.
If you mark your Bible, verse 20 says this.
Now unto him that is able.
We've already defined that word as dunami, to be possible.
To do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think
according to the power.
If you circle that word, circle it
and draw a line back to able,
because they're the same root word.
They're the same root word, dunami.
Now here, I want you to notice this.
That worketh, where?
In us.
God says, and I love this,
I won't take the time to show it to you,
but that word worketh, you're familiar with that.
It's the Greek word intergeo.
If we went up into James chapter five,
you would see this sentence.
You would see the effectual fervent prayer
of a righteous man availeth much.
That's the same word that is translated effectual fervent.
Here's what God is saying.
There is an effectual fervent power.
There is an effectual fervent possibility
already working in you.
It's not something I have to summon up.
It's not something I have to make happen.
It's something I have to surrender to.
God help me to see that.
It's already working in me.
How do I have the mind of Christ,
grit my teeth and say, I will think like Jesus.
No, you won't.
You can't.
But when we got saved, back in 1975,
84, 29, I've got some heritage people here,
so I'll say it.
No, I won't say it, nevermind.
I got saved in 1975.
I was there in the living room of my house,
opened the Bible and called out upon the Lord to save me.
And I'm not trying to be mystical
and I'm not trying to be silly.
But in that moment, man, something very,
very important happened to me.
I didn't realize it then.
I didn't fully understand it then.
I didn't fall down at foam in my mouth.
I didn't levitate and hover over the sofa.
I didn't have some ecstatic experience.
But the Spirit of God, when I called upon the Lord
and said, I am a sinner and I need you to save me,
and he did save me, the Spirit of God pierced my chest,
came into my heart and took up residence in my heart
so as to make me able to become
what Christ wants me to become,
to think like Christ and to have the perception
and the discernment of Christ.
It's not instantaneous, but it is possible.
Years ago, my wife and I moved in from the country
and we moved back into town, if you will,
and we had a lovely home.
And if you don't know my wife, but if you did,
you would know that she is a person
that everything has to be in its place.
And we had moved that day and somebody called
and said, they were being very kind,
they wanted to drop a meal off to us
so that she didn't have to worry about cooking a meal.
Meals are very important to me.
And when they called and said, hey, we're 20 minutes away,
we're dropping off a meal, there were boxes in her house
in places that boxes shouldn't be.
And so she said to me, we gotta straighten this place up.
I said, we're moving.
No, no, we have to straighten this place up.
And so I said, okay, you straighten this floor up.
I'm gonna go downstairs.
I'll move some stuff out of the way.
I'll take the sweeper that's down there.
I'll vacuum the carpet.
We'll make it as presentable as we can.
And I went downstairs and, you know, I don't know about you,
but the good vacuum sweeper is on the first floor
at our house.
The one that's ready to go to sweeper heaven
is on the basement.
And I went down and I'm unwrapping the cord,
getting ready to sweep.
I'd move some boxes.
The phone rings.
I go over.
I answer the phone and it is an issue
and I have to take care of it.
About 15 minutes it takes me on the phone.
Ooh, the people are getting close.
I go back.
I'm gonna sweep.
I'm gonna get this done.
I'm gonna be a good husband.
I hit the switch and nothing.
I said to myself, why are we moving a broken vacuum sweeper?
So in a very loving way, I called up to her
and I said, why did we move this?
It doesn't even work.
And honestly, this is a life-changing moment
in our marriage.
She calls back down the steps.
Did you plug it in?
And I said, does she think I'm a moron?
Did I plug it in?
Oh.
Isn't that a great story?
It has nothing to do with the message.
It's the exact picture of us.
The power is there and we never plug in.
The spirit of God resides in our heart
with the effectual fervent power
to allow us to be transformed,
to allow us to see it like God sees it.
And we spend so much time not surrendering,
not walking in the spirit,
not being submissive to the spirit,
not surrendering to the spirit.
So much time in my life is spent grieving the spirit.
Well, I'm good at grieving the spirit.
I'm good at saying the wrong thing
and thinking the wrong thing and doing the wrong thing.
And I grieve the spirit.
I'm good at that.
I'm not so good at walking and surrendering
and submitting to the spirit.
Sometimes I'm even fearful we quench the spirit.
We resist him so much.
We just say, no, I'm not gonna allow you
to do that in my life.
No, it's just who I am.
It's what we said about the approved sin.
We can just literally quench the spirit
when our every effort should be,
let me be surrendered to the spirit.
Let me be submissive to the spirit.
God, as I read your word, when I see truth,
I will be submissive to that truth.
I'll ask your help to apply that
and to make me to appropriate that.
God, I want to think like Jesus thinks.
And it's not something I've got to figure out.
You've already prepared the power to do it.
And just as Mary could be overshadowed
and the Holy Spirit come upon her,
I'm not talking about silly stuff.
I'm not talking about false spiritual movements.
I'm talking about the precious spirit of God
who resides in our heart, who has come to teach us,
to bring all things to remembrance.
He's come to convict us.
Sometimes, I don't know about you,
but sometimes we can resent conviction
when in truth, we ought to appreciate
every time God speaks to us.
I always marvel that people can say,
well, I was moved, but I didn't move.
Well, I think if God loves me and cares enough about me
to care about my life and he comes
and taps me on the shoulder and speaks to me,
I think there's just one word back to the spirit of God.
Yes, show me, help me, I'll do it.
I want to be obedient to you.
God says, listen, you have the power within you.
It's not of you, it's not yours.
It's the spirit of God.
But God wants to change who we are.
Christians live their whole lives unchanged
or barely changed from the time they're saved.
Man, there ought to be a marked difference in us.
I won't say it over again,
but those things ought to begin to fall off of us,
those worldly things in our life.
And yes, we progress and we become more and more Christlike
and we come to that place in our life
when we're dealing with the really hard stuff,
but it ought to be falling off.
We ought to have victory in our lives.
Can I ask you a question?
When was the last victory in your life in overcoming sin?
When's the last time you even thought
you had one you needed to overcome?
We've become so professional at going to church,
we're not sure we need the Holy Spirit.
Because we compare ourselves one to the other
instead of comparing ourselves to the Lord.
God says, I can help you think like me.
I can help you pray like I want you to pray.
And you can see things that exceed anything you thought
could be done in or through your life.
When's the last time God did something so marvelous
in your life, so marvelous in your home,
so marvelous in your marriage,
so marvelous in your career,
so marvelous in your testimony
that it was just obviously God doing something?
Now, let me give you the last thought.
Not only the poverty of our minds, but get this,
the great purpose of our lives.
Notice what it says in verse 21.
Unto him be glory in the church by Christ Jesus
throughout all ages, world without end.
We live in a world where an awful lot of preaching
seems to indicate that God exists
to just do good stuff for us.
God exists so that we never have to go through pain.
God exists for us so that we never have to suffer want.
God exists for us so that we never face a problem
or have to climb a mountain or cross a deep river.
God exists for our good.
That may be comfortable, popular preaching.
It is not biblical.
God does not exist for our good.
We exist for God's glory.
Now, God is always good in all that he does,
but do not get that equation backwards.
God does not exist for our good.
We exist for God's glory, and then God adds this.
Literally, he says, I want to get glory through your life,
through the church, throughout all ages.
I puzzled for what that means,
but let me try to explain two ways.
I think, first of all, it means that God wants to get glory
from our lives in all the ages of our life.
I think little children can glorify God,
and I think we ought to be attentive
to teach them to glorify God.
I think teenagers, I don't think the teenage years
are years to sow wild oats.
They do come up, you know.
I don't think teenage years are years to spend in self
and wrapped up in self.
I think the teenage years are for glorifying God.
I think the young, busy years of moms and dads and children
where everybody's got a schedule,
everybody's got a million,
I think God wants to get glory out of young families.
I think God wants to get glory out of empty nesters.
I think God wants to get glory out of old folks like me.
I don't think there's ever a day in our lives
where we can say, well, you know,
I'm not too concerned about what God wants
or can do in my life.
I think God's very concerned about every day.
And every day in my life, there should be a passion.
There should at least be an interest
of how can I glorify God today?
I think it also means this,
that God wants to get glory every age of this world.
Did you know that God did the impossible in creation?
He just spoke it into existence.
Did you know that God did the impossible for Noah?
Did you know that God did the impossible for Abraham?
That God did the impossible for Moses and Israel.
God did the impossible for Mary.
God did the impossible for Paul,
for Peter, for John.
God did the impossible in giving his word.
God did the impossible until about 1920.
And then remember God stopped doing the impossible. Did He? No, but we decided God
was dead. And we decided that our technology was greater than God. I'm here
to tell you that God still wants to get glory today. And God is still able to do
the impossible today. More than any other time of my ministry, I am seeing people
not giving up on church, but giving up on the concept of God doing anything great.
We'll go to church. We'll bring our families to church. We'll hunker down. And
you know, we'll make a few ministry, we'll do some outreach, and I'm
glad for all of that. Please don't misunderstand me. I'm not trying to be
critical or ugly. But I'm saying, when did we decide God can't send revival? When
did we decide that God can't change our culture? When did we decide that God
can't use us to impact our neighborhood or to impact our community? When did we
decide? I'll tell you when we did. When we decided that we couldn't see God
doing anything but what we could assume He could do. We wrapped God up in our
little box and we said, God, I appreciate you. I appreciate what you've said, but
God, I don't think there's any way we can do that. I'll be done in two minutes, but
here's what I'm here to tell you. Stop putting God in your box. Stop limiting
what God can do. There's people in here tonight that have children that are away
from the Lord or grandchildren away from the Lord. We make some semblance of
praying for them, and we would love to see them get right with God. But I think
a lot of people have decided, well, that may be in somebody else's life, but my
son is too far gone, or my grandchild is too far gone, and it's just not gonna, I
mean I'd love to see it, but you know. Stop it. Stop it. Get on your face before
God and call out to a supernatural God who can involve Himself in your child
or grandchild's life and change their heart. Stop limiting God. Well, I wish we
had a marriage that, you know, God was really in our marriage, but you don't
know my husband. Oh preacher, you don't know my wife. Stop it. Stop telling God
what He can and cannot do, and get on your face before God and say, God help me
to see more. Help me to see, help me with your mind to understand that you can
impact, and start pouring out your heart to God and saying, God change my home,
change my marriage. God could never change my work life. It's miserable. I
hate it. I hate every day of my life. I don't like my boss. I've got a, you
preacher, you've never had, you've been the boss, you've never had a boss. Stop it!
Stop thinking that God cannot change it. Get on your face, and if it's one time,
five times, ten times a day, pour your heart out to God like Hannah did, even if
they think you're drunk, and beg God, change my circumstance. Is God able? Is
it possible? A little girl came to me one time and said, preacher Moore, anything I
want a husband. I got two granddaughters looking for husbands. Sometimes they'll
say, I don't think I'll ever find. Stop it! Stop it! I'm not telling everybody to
look for a husband here. I'm just saying, stop telling God what he can't do. People
in here bound by a sin just hold you. You've tried so many times to, in your
own strength, oh, I'm gonna stop, I'm gonna, and then you're back. Preacher, I'll just have to live
with it. I can't change. I'll do all I can, but I, I'm always gonna be caught by that.
I'm always, stop it! Stop limiting God. God is supernatural. God is not bound by
laws. God is not bound by our limits. God is not stuck in our box. We have got to
start thinking like God wants us to think, because He can do exceedingly,
abundantly, above all that we can ask or think, and we let a world go to hell
because we don't think we can impact it. We're just a little church. We can never
grow a lot. Stop it! Stop it! They stood at that Red Sea, get this numbed
done, where God had brought them. You see, when God wants to get glory out of our
lives, sometimes He puts that big deal problem right in front of us, and they
were gonna complain about it, and they were gonna fuss about it, but they were
gonna die at the edge of that sea until Moses said, hush up, look at what God can
do, and he raised that rod, and the problem could be solved. The child could
come home to the Lord. The spouse could change. The boss could change. The
finances could change. Your health could change. Your perspective could change. If
we beg God and walk with God and ask God, God, do what only you can do. God is not
finished. God's not done. My challenge to you tonight is this. Be one of those who
walk with Him. Ask big things. Stop it. Stop it. What's a big thing in your life?
What's something you'd love to see and you'd love God to do, but I'm kind of
stuck here at the shore. I don't think God could stop it. Ask God. Would you pray
with me? God, help us to see not silliness, not wildfire, not charismatic
emotionalism, but help us to appreciate who you are. It is you who said there's
nothing impossible with you. It is you who have put that fervent power working
within us in the Holy Spirit. It is the Holy Spirit that can change our attitude,
can change our perspective. It is the Holy Spirit that can help us to have a
vision to see what can be done. It is the Holy Spirit who can pray for us and
pray with us and teach us to pray. It is the Spirit of God that can enable us as
we submit to Him and walk in Him. It is the Spirit of God that can help us see
what only God can do in answer to our prayers. We pray small prayers. We pray
for little things. God, help us to be people who just ask God to do exceeding
abundantly above all that we can think or imagine even. And God, may we see
victory in people's lives, lives of people we love. May we see victory in the
lost that surround us. May we see victory in our church. May we see victory
on our job, in our finances, in our health, in our homes, because we start to ask you
to work. We walk with you. I wonder how many tonight would say, Preacher, here's
the truth. I'm not trying to pry. I would not try to be personal. Preacher, there's
something in my life that I would really, really like to see made right. I'd love
to see God work, but I've just kind of grown over the years.
thinking, well, that just can never happen.
But tonight, I'm committing myself to pray and ask God to do what sometimes seems to
me to be impossible to be done.
Would you slip your hand up and just say, God, I'm telling you, I'm praying for that.
God bless you.
We've all got stuff where we just think it's beyond hope and help.
God says, I brought you there so that I could show you how mighty I could work on your behalf.
Ask him for big things.
He wants to get glory through our lives.
So, Father, you've seen hearts, many of these things, very personal things, no doubt.
Lord, I pray that you would work.
And I pray that as we surrender and submit to your spirit and seek his face and seek
to be transformed through your word by his work, that we will be able to pray according
to your will and pray with the mind of Christ and see what God, who can do the impossible,
can do in the circumstances we care about.
Help us, Lord, I pray in Jesus' name.
Amen.
I want every head bowed, every eye closed.
You can stand quietly to your feet.
Why don't you spend some time with the Lord tonight and say, Lord, I'm asking you, would
you help me with this?
As the pianist plays, why don't you just take a few moments?
Lord, it's between me and you, but I'm asking you, will you work in this thing I'm asking
you to work?
It's so big.