some folks visiting with us this morning.
Patricia's joining us again,
and Rob is here with us as well,
and certainly thankful for folks that are visiting.
Good to see the Salgados this morning,
and looking forward to seeing Emery.
I'm sure he's getting nice and big,
and good to see you folks this morning.
Nehemiah chapter number six,
and we'll be looking at this portion of scripture.
Let me just give you a little bit of background
before we get into the passage this morning.
Of course, as you know,
Judah had been taken captive by the Babylonians,
and after that captivity,
we understand that they spent 70 years in exile
before Cyrus came to the throne,
and Cyrus made a decree that the Jewish people
could return to the land of their homeland,
to the city of Jerusalem particularly,
and we find that it's in the book of Ezra
that God records for us and provides for us
the details regarding the return,
and obviously the building of the temple
is found in the book of Ezra,
and you can read and study and see all that God does,
revival, and so on and so forth,
and we find that as we come to the book of Nehemiah,
that it's in that same time frame,
obviously several years after Ezra and that group,
that original group had returned to Jerusalem,
and many years later, we find that Nehemiah
in chapter number one is found in Shushan,
and he's serving the king Artaxerxes,
and we find that he's in that place,
and he's the cupbearer for Artaxerxes,
and chapter number one tells us
that he has some correspondence with Hanani,
and the specifics of that correspondence
dealt with the situation in Jerusalem.
He asked specifically, how are things in Jerusalem?
Give me a report as to what's going on there,
and we find that Hanani delivers to Nehemiah this report
with regard to the great affliction and the reproach.
He tells him that the wall of Jerusalem
also is broken down,
and the gates thereof are burned with fire,
and we find that Nehemiah, as he received that report
after that correspondence with Hanani,
we find that he was very burdened
for the situation in Jerusalem.
We find that he immediately went to God in prayer,
and he began to seek the face of God,
and we find that chapter number two tells us
that he was in the presence of Artaxerxes,
and prior to this particular event,
he had not been sad in the presence of Artaxerxes,
but Artaxerxes could see in his countenance
that he was sad, and he said, what is it?
This is nothing more than sorrow of heart,
and we find that Nehemiah reveals to the king
that which he had heard and understood,
and permission is granted for Nehemiah to return.
As you read the rest of chapter number two,
you find that Nehemiah gets back to the city,
and he, on his own, upon arrival,
he goes and he views the city,
and he's taking everything in,
and he's seeing firsthand exactly what Hanani
had described to him in that correspondence
in chapter number one,
and we find that Nehemiah then issues a challenge
to the people of God, those that were there,
and he tells them, let's rise up and build.
The good hand of the Lord is upon me.
And he understood there was a work to be done,
and we find that immediately upon the challenge
being issued in Nehemiah chapter number two,
the opposition also is there.
I mean, immediately upon Nehemiah saying,
let us rise up and build,
the Bible tells us that Sanballat and Tobiah
were there ready to oppose the work of God.
Chapter three, four, and five provide us for a record
not only of those that were there
in chapter number three extensively,
but chapters four and five reveal to us
the work that is being carried on
and the opposition that they're facing.
When we come to chapter number six specifically,
we find that I believe that the enemy begins
to really up their game, so to speak.
And we find that as we look at chapter number six
and dive into this passage this morning,
I'm trusting that God will help to equip
and strengthen us as the people of God,
even as the enemy would seek to derail us.
We find that it's here in chapter number six
in verse number one.
It says, now it came to pass
when Sanballat and Tobiah and Geshem the Arabian
and the rest of our enemies heard
that I had builded the wall
and that there was no breach left therein,
and though it says there are parentheses
at the end of verse number one,
though at that time I had not set up
the doors upon the gates,
notice verse two, that Sanballat and Geshem
sent unto me saying,
come, let us meet together in some one of the villages
in the plain of Ono.
But they thought to do me mischief.
If you've already looked at the back
of the bulletin this morning,
the title is found here in verse number two
for our message this morning.
They thought to do me mischief.
That word mischief is often translated as evil.
Not that mischief is a wrong translation of the word,
but it's synonymous,
and we understand that it's translated various ways,
but the mischief that was intended to be done
against Nehemiah and those that were doing the work,
they had evil intentions against the man of God
and the work of God.
I believe that as we look here
at this passage of Scripture,
there's some things that we need to learn
if you're taking notes, number one,
we need to learn to recognize the enemy.
We need to learn to recognize the enemy.
Now understand that by this time,
I mean, Nehemiah had been working
and Nehemiah had been enduring some opposition,
adversity, and hardship,
and we can read of that in chapters,
really the end of chapter two,
three, four, and five,
really four and five capture a lot of it, most of it.
And so we find that by this time,
Nehemiah had been very familiar
with who his enemies were.
In verse number one, in fact,
the Bible says that it came to pass
when Sanballat and Tobiah and Geshem the Arabian,
notice what he says,
and the rest of our enemies.
And so Nehemiah at this particular time of his ministry,
he was able to easily identify who his enemies were.
But I want you to understand
that though the opposition to the work of God
began immediately,
I find that as I read Nehemiah chapter number six,
that we discover that the enemy
is increasing their deception.
See, Sanballat and Tobiah were constantly
in chapters four and five coming and saying things,
let us join with you,
and if a fox goes up on it, it's gonna crumble,
and I mean, all of the ridicule
and all of the things that they said.
But now in chapter number six,
the level of deception increases exponentially.
And it's important as we study
through chapter number six this morning
that we find that Nehemiah was able
to consistently recognize the enemy.
Can I tell you this morning
that the enemy doesn't always show up
by saying, I'm your enemy.
In fact, it's very rare
that an enemy would show up that way, right?
And so we find that as we look at this passage of Scripture
that the deception is increasing.
Remember what the word of God says
in the book of Ephesians in chapter number six,
and we studied this book a few years ago in its entirety,
but we find in Ephesians chapter number six
in verse number 10,
Paul says this to the believers in Ephesus,
finally, my brethren,
be strong in the Lord and the power of His might.
Put on the whole armor of God
that you may be able to stand
against the wiles of the devil.
That word wiles, it carries with it
the idea of deceit, deception, craftiness, tricky.
Remember that it says of the serpent
in Genesis chapter number three,
that he was more subtle than any beast of the field.
We find that it's in verse number 12
of the same passage in Ephesians six
that Paul says that we wrestle not against flesh and blood,
but against principalities, against powers,
against the rulers of the darkness of this world,
against spiritual wickedness in high places.
I believe that as we look here in Nehemiah chapter number six
it reminds me as we think about the deception increasing
and we think about the attacks
in which Nehemiah would deal with
the opposition to the work,
it reminds me of what we read back in the book of Numbers
under the counsel of Balaam.
Remember that Balaam could not curse the people of God.
Though Balak wanted him to,
we find that it was through the counsel of Balaam
that he encouraged the people of God to corrupt themselves.
You can read that in Numbers 31 and verse number 16.
We also find that it's very similar to what you read of
in the book of Joshua in the ninth chapter
with the deception of the Gibeonites.
And we find that our enemy is going to consistently
and regularly increase the deception
because he's our enemy.
Understand as we look at this point this morning
that we need to learn to recognize the enemy,
we need to understand the objective of the enemy.
I mean, ultimately their objective is to destroy the work.
And that's what they'd like to do.
But I believe that the enemy, though he understands,
and we'll look at some promises at the end of the message
this morning, the work of God will march on.
I believe that where he finds great satisfaction
is in hindering the work of God.
Hindering the work of God.
That's exactly what the enemy had been trying to do
in chapters four and five.
And now in chapter number six,
we find that the enemy recognizes
that the building is continuing to go on.
I mean, the wall is near completion.
It says that the doors had not yet been set up upon the gates,
but we find that they're nearing completion.
And so the enemy is going to elevate and increase
the level of deception.
And they're going to come and try to hinder the work.
So what do they do?
We understand what their objective is,
but look at what the method is that's employed in Nehemiah
chapter number 6.
First, we find in verses 2 through 4
that there is a request for a meeting in one of the villages.
The Bible says in verse number 2,
come let us meet together in some one of the villages
in the plain of Ono.
Notice what Nehemiah says, but they thought to do me mischief.
And so they desired to have this meeting.
No doubt, I believe that if this meeting would have taken place,
they would have sought to intimidate Nehemiah
from continuing with the work.
I believe that really another plan of these individuals
was to get Nehemiah distracted from the work,
remove him from the work he was doing.
Notice what he says in verse number 3,
and I sent messengers unto them saying,
I am doing a great work so that I cannot come down.
Why should the work cease whilst I leave it and come down to you?
See, the enemy wants the work to cease.
He wants to hinder the work.
And so let's remove Nehemiah.
And Nehemiah was used by God in an amazing way
to lead these people that are rebuilding the walls.
And so the enemy is coming and trying
to get the leader to be removed and to go to this meeting
that they set up in this plain.
Notice what the Bible says that after Nehemiah sent messengers
unto them, that in verse number 4,
the Bible says, yet they sent unto me
four times after this sort.
And I answered them after the same matter.
The enemy is persistent.
We often can use the word that he's relentless.
We find the enemy in his persistence.
We find it on four times this first option
of having Nehemiah leave Jerusalem
and go into one of these villages, this place
in the plain of Ono, so that they could have this meeting
and seek to cause the work of God
to cease, to hinder the work of God,
to intimidate the man of God.
But it did not work.
So we notice method number 2 in our passage of Scripture
in verses 5 through 9.
We find that they send an open letter.
An open letter.
You know, really what they're doing here
is they're lying about the motive of Nehemiah.
They're slandering the name of Nehemiah.
They send an open letter so that it can be read
by more than just Nehemiah.
In the previous section, the first approach
in seeking to have him meet, the Bible
says that verse 2, that Sanballat and Geshem
sent unto Me.
So they go directly to Nehemiah.
They want a meeting with you over here.
Now we find in verse number 5 that it says,
then sent Sanballat his servant unto Me
in like manner the fifth time with an open letter
in his hand, desiring that others
within the city of Jerusalem would read this
and they would have the opportunity
to influence other people.
And look at what the letter says.
Verse 6, wherein was written,
it is reported among the heathen,
and Gashemus saith it, that thou and the Jews
think to rebel, for which cause thou buildest the wall,
notice this, that thou mayest be their king,
according to these words.
So what are they saying?
Nehemiah, you want to be the king.
You have selfish motives.
You're coming in there and you want to be the king.
You want to be the leader.
And you want to be the king in verse number 7.
And thou hast also appointed prophets
to preach of thee at Jerusalem, saying,
there is a king in Judah.
And so this is the attempt, the way in which the enemy is
going to try to deal with this now in this open letter
and seeking to influence others to rebel against Nehemiah
and seeking to undermine the character of this man.
There is a king in Judah, verse 7,
and now shall it be reported to the king according
to these words.
Come now, therefore, and let us take counsel together.
So here's what they do.
They say, we know this is what you want to do.
And they're trying to influence, but not only
in influencing the others, but they're now saying,
we're going to go to the king, Artaxerxes.
And we're going to tell him that you
are going to rebel against him and you want to be the king.
Now, Nehemiah had a good relationship with Artaxerxes.
He was his cupbearer.
In chapter number 2, you see the interaction.
And we find that the enemy is seeking,
through various levels of deception,
as they would elevate.
It's not now just Sanballat and Tobiah that are coming
and trying to attack Nehemiah.
They give these invitations, and now they send this open letter.
Let's get some other people riled up against them.
Let's have the influence of the people
so that he would not be able to continue the work.
We find that not only that, the third level of deception
that we find is recorded for us in verses 10 through 14.
Look at what happens now.
Again, the enemy continues to elevate
the level of deception.
It says afterward, in verse number 10,
I came unto the house of Shemaiah, the son of Deliah,
the son of Mehedabiel, who was shut up.
And he said, let us meet together in the house of God,
within the temple.
And let us shut the doors of the temple.
Why?
For they will come to slay thee.
Yea, in the night will they come to slay thee.
So now this fellow says to Nehemiah,
Nehemiah, they're going to come kill you.
The only place that you can find refuge is in the temple.
Now that would've been a problem for Nehemiah
to go into the temple.
It seems very obvious through the passage of scripture
that the recommendation was to go into the holy place.
He wasn't permitted to go into the holy of holies.
And it was as if the enemy now, notice what the Bible says,
that Nehemiah replies and says, look at verse number 11.
Should such a man as I flee, and who
is there that being as I am, would go into the temple
to save his life?
I will not go in.
And lo, notice this word, circle it, underline it,
I perceived, I perceived that God had not sent him,
but that he pronounced this prophecy against me,
notice this, for Tobiah and Sanballat had hired him.
What level of deception.
The influence that they had these enemies,
the way in which, and we'll notice
at the end of the passage, they infiltrate.
And they now get this man, according
to what we see in verse number 10,
to come and to say to Nehemiah that he, this is Shemiah,
as we notice in verse number 10, Shemiah says, hey listen,
they're going to come and kill you,
and so you need to go over here and hide yourself,
protect yourself.
It's where you'd find refuge.
And we find that really their intent,
as Tobiah and Sanballat had hired him,
notice what it says in verse number 13,
therefore was he hired that I should be afraid and do so.
Do what?
Go into that place that he was not permitted to go into
and sin, and that they might have matter for an evil report
that they might reproach me.
Oh, the enemy is, he's crafting.
Hey listen, Nehemiah, they're going to kill you.
They're going to come at night and they're
going to kill you.
The only place you can find refuge
is in the place where you're not permitted to go.
But if you go in that place, then you'll have refuge.
You'll have safety.
But in going to that place, they then
are going to say, oh, you went to where
you weren't supposed to go.
You sinned.
Now they can bring up an evil report
and they can bring reproach against Nehemiah.
It's crazy, but that's how the enemy works.
We see it right here in Nehemiah chapter number 6.
Notice how they, at the end of the passage in verses 17
through 19, notice their approach of infiltration,
as I have referred to it as.
We find that verse 17 says, moreover, in those days,
the nobles of Judah sent many letters unto Tobiah.
The nobles of Judah.
They're sending letters to Tobiah.
Who's Tobiah?
He's the enemy.
Notice what it says.
And the letters of Tobiah came unto them.
So these fellows are corresponding one
with another.
Verse 18, for there were many in Judah, many, sworn unto him.
Why?
Because he was the son-in-law of Shekeniah, the son of Arah.
And his son, Johanan, had taken the daughter of Meshulam,
the son of Berechiah.
So through these relationships, through his wife
and his daughter-in-law, he's now infiltrated.
And he has the ear of the nobles of Judah.
And they're corresponding one with the other.
It tells us in verse number 19, also,
they reported his good deeds before me
and uttered my words to him.
And Tobiah sent letters to put me in fear.
The enemy is tricky.
He's deceitful.
And he has no morals.
He's relentless, and he's ruthless.
And he will do whatever is necessary to hinder
the work of God.
of God. Whatever. Because He's evil. And this enemy, these enemies, we see that
when they were not able to be successful in the end of chapter number two, the
first approach was, hey, let us join you. Verses chapters four and five, all of the
ways in which they sought to cause the work of God to hinder, and now in chapter
six we see the level of deception rise exponentially. They hire a man that's
supposed to be a priest. They infiltrate the ranks of the nobles of Judah
through relationship so that they can have influence. Wow. And I want you to pay
particular attention to how the enemy would use fear. It's very interesting in
this passage of Scripture how the enemy will use fear. Notice in verse number
nine. Verse eight, I didn't read verses eight and nine, we'll get to that in just a
moment, but it says in verse eight, Then I sent unto him, saying, There are no such
things done as thou sayest, but thou faintest them out of thine own heart. For
they all, notice what it says, made us afraid, saying, Their hands shall be
weakened from the work, that it be not done. Now therefore, O God, strengthen my
hands. So the first reference to fear or being afraid is in verse number nine,
They all made us afraid. Notice verse number 13, Therefore was he hired that I
should be afraid and do so. So we find in verse number nine this thing of fear, we
find in verse number 13 this thing of fear, and at the end of verse number 18,
19, excuse me, it says, Also that reported his good deeds before me and uttered my
words to him, and Tobiah sent letters to put me in fear. You know why the enemy
uses fear? Because the enemy uses fear, and I believe that when he can make the
people of God afraid, he can cause us to do things that otherwise we would not do.
Don't keep doing this work because here's what we're gonna do, we're gonna
kill you, we're gonna imprison you, we're gonna do this, we're gonna do that, and
I'm afraid, right? They said in verse number 13, He was hired to tell me that
they were gonna come and kill me so that I would be afraid and do so, go into the
place where I was not permitted to go. And so the enemy is gonna use fear, the
enemy continues to use fear, and the enemy uses fear, and I believe that as he
would make people afraid, that he can be successful, at least in his
objective, to hinder the work of God. To hinder the work of God. I'm afraid to do
this, I'm afraid to do that, I'm afraid to go here, I'm afraid to go there. And the
work of God is hindered because of fear. And here in Nehemiah chapter number six,
on three occasions we find that the enemy specifically, the four methods are
outlined, I would submit to you that even though the Bible doesn't say in the
first four verses of chapter number six that they were trying to make him afraid
in that meeting as well. I mean, when he says that they thought to do mischief to
me, or they thought to do to me mischief, obviously they were trying to make him
afraid. So the enemy wants to cause the people of God to be fearful so that the
work of God would be hindered, so the work of God would cease from going
forward. And so this morning, I believe that as we look at Nehemiah chapter
number six, the first reality, the first thing that we need to learn is we need
to learn how to recognize the enemy. And I submit to you this morning that it's
not always easy to recognize the enemy. Look at the methods that are used in
this portion of Scripture, the extent in which the enemy would go to deceive you,
to deceive me. We find that we need to learn to recognize the enemy. Number two,
we need to learn to resist the enemy. We need to learn to resist the enemy. Notice,
you can hold your place here Nehemiah, but I want you to be mindful of what
James says in James 4 and verse number 7. In James 4 and verse number 7, the
Bible says this, submit yourselves therefore to God, resist the devil, and he
will flee from you. That's a great promise of God's Word, is it not? Listen,
before you resist the enemy, you need to submit to God. That's the formula. Submit
to God, submit yourselves therefore to God, resist the devil, and he will flee
from you. As we submit ourselves to God and we're filled with the power of the
Holy Spirit of God, then we have the ability to be able to resist the enemy,
and we have the promise that the enemy is going to flee. See, the devil don't
want to mess with the Lord. He wants to mess with you, in your flesh, because he
can be successful. Amen? I want you to notice on the four methods that were
employed in Nehemiah chapter number 6, I want you to notice how Nehemiah
responds to each of those situations, but before we look at that specifically in
Nehemiah chapter number 6, I want you to note that Nehemiah was a man of prayer.
Nehemiah is a man of prayer, and I believe that that's such a key for us to
see how that he had the level of perception and discernment to be able to
recognize the enemy in chapter number 6, because he was a man of prayer. He's
submitting to God. He's a man of prayer. Notice in Nehemiah chapter number 1, we
don't have time to read the entirety of it, but in verse number 4 is when you
begin to see where Nehemiah prays. It goes all the way through the end of
chapter number 1, there in verse number 11, but notice what it says in Nehemiah 1
in verse 4, and it came to pass when I heard these words that I sat down and
wept and mourned certain days and fasted and prayed before the God of heaven.
Listen, I'm glad that he wept and I'm glad that he mourned, but had he not
fasted and prayed, we may not see the same results that we see here in Nehemiah.
We find that, yes, we can weep for our nation, we can mourn for the report that
we hear, but we better seek the face of God. We need a revival of prayer. We find,
again, I don't have time to read the entirety of the next verses, read it
later, but through the end of verse number 11, we find that Nehemiah is
praying, and what a great prayer it is. A prayer of intercession, a prayer of
confession, the sins of the people. I mean, he's serious in his prayer. We find
that in Nehemiah chapter number 2, after Artaxerxes sees that he has nothing
more but sorrow of heart, and he says to him, you know, what do you want? And look
at verse number 4, then the king said unto me, for what dost thou make request?
And then notice the last part of verse number 4, so I prayed to the God of
heaven, and I said unto the king, to start verse number 5, can I tell you that it's
not always the length of your prayer? Notice the scene in Nehemiah chapter
number 2. Artaxerxes says, hey, I notice your countenance. This is nothing more
than sorrow of heart. What is it that you request? And before he answered the king,
it says that he prayed to God. What a great truth. Nehemiah's a man of prayer.
Not only there, notice in chapter number 4. Chapter number 3 deals with the work
being assigned and all of the people that were there, and chapter number 4,
again, the work being attacked and all that's going on. Notice in verse number
8 of Nehemiah 4, the Bible says, and conspired all of them together to come
and to fight against Jerusalem and to hinder it. Nevertheless, verse number 9 of
Nehemiah 4, we made our prayer unto our God and set a watch against them day and
night because of them. What's the response? Pray. He's a man of prayer. In our
chapter, in Nehemiah chapter number 6, the chapter in which we're studying this
morning, we find that in verse number 9, the last phrase of the verse says,
Now therefore, O God, strengthen my hands. I mean, that's a short prayer, is it not?
But he was a man that communed with the Lord. He was a man of prayer. And so when he's
facing this situation and they're trying to weaken their hands, they're trying to
discourage them and cause them to be feared so that the work would be hindered, we find
that Nehemiah prays, Strengthen my hands. In verse number 14, we find that he
prays, it says, My God, think thou upon Tobiah and Sandalit, according to these
their works, and on the prophets Noadiah and the rest of the prophets that would
have, the prophetess Noadiah, excuse me, and the rest of the prophets that would
have put me in fear. Another reference to fear. We find that Nehemiah was a man of
prayer, but how did he deal with the methods? How did he deal with the attack? Well, number
one, they invited him to go to one of the villages in the plain of Ono, and I would
say this, that Nehemiah rejected the invitation. He rejected the invitation. Sometimes we ought
to say no. I've often said from Nehemiah chapter number 6, they invited him to Ono,
and he said, Oh no, amen. I ain't going there. I'm not leaving the work. Why should
the work cease? Why should it be hindered? No, I'm not going. We've got to learn how
to say no. Amen? Well, but they invited me, and they're going to think I'm going to...
Learn to say no. Amen? Honestly. No appearance of evil. Sometimes they're inviting you to
go to that place so they can slander you, like they were trying to do to Nehemiah. Right?
Not only did he reject the invitation, he refuted the claim. In the claim of verse 6
and 7, in that open letter...
was that Nehemiah wanted to be the king.
He refuted that.
V. 8, he says,
"...then I sent unto them, saying,
there are no such things done as thou sayest,
but thou faintest them out of thine own heart."
You're just making this stuff up.
No truth to what you're claiming whatsoever.
He refuted the claim.
He resisted the suggestion.
When the man comes, Shemaiah,
and says, hey, you need to go into the temple.
These are going to come and kill you, slay you.
He resisted that suggestion.
He was able to have perception.
And I believe that in v. 12
when he says, lo, I perceived,
it's that level of having that discernment
that only God gives.
And say, no, I'm not permitted to do that.
And notice what he says in v. 11.
I mean, think about it.
He's saying they're going to come.
In the night will they come to slay thee?
At the end of v. 10.
And notice what Nehemiah says in v. 11.
Should such a man as I flee?
Think about what he just prayed in v. 9.
Oh God, strengthen my hands.
Nehemiah, they're going to come kill you,
and then I run in fear.
No, no, no.
I just prayed that God would strengthen me.
Should such a man as I flee?
And who is there that being as I am
would go into the temple to save his life?
I will not go in.
I like his resolve.
I believe that Nehemiah remained steadfast.
As we think about that infiltration
that was mentioned in v. 17-19
and the relationship of Tobiah
with the nobles of Judah
through his wife and his daughter-in-law,
and all of the letters that would go back and forth,
I believe that Nehemiah, he remained steadfast.
I mean, no doubt it was a constant bombardment.
No doubt it was a regular thing.
I mean, they're sending letters back and forth
and they're seeking to cause him to be afraid,
but I find that Nehemiah was a man
that remained steadfast.
For us as New Testament believers,
get our eyes on the Lord
and just continue to march forward
to do the work that God has called us to do.
We find that number one,
we need to learn to recognize the enemy,
to be able to identify the enemy.
And it's not always easy.
We need discernment
to try the spirits, as John says.
To know that we're engaged
in spiritual wickedness in high places,
the spiritual warfare that is taking place
in our society still even today.
It is raging.
Oh, how we need the discernment of God
to be able to recognize, identify the enemy.
And then we need to learn how to resist the enemy.
It starts with submitting ourselves to God.
Being a man of prayer like Nehemiah.
Seeking the face of God.
Praying daily,
God, would You help me to have
the discernment as I go throughout my day
to be able to identify,
to recognize the enemy
and to see how the enemy would like
to hinder the work that You're doing in and through me.
We learn how to resist.
Number three this morning,
I believe that we need to learn how to rejoice
in the work of the Lord.
We notice verses 15 and 16.
I would say this as we would look at these verses.
Thinking about the truth of rejoicing,
I am so thankful for the truth
that greater is He that is in you
than he that is in the world.
We are on the winning side.
Have you read the book of Revelation?
We win! Amen?
You say, it's not looking so good.
Look to Jesus.
Don't worry about all this craziness.
They're trying to hinder you.
They're trying to stop you.
They're trying to hinder the work of God.
Say, listen, we're on the winning side.
We win!
Jesus is the victor.
Amen?
Satan is already defeated.
He already knows his demise.
Revelation 20 and verse 10,
that old serpent,
he's cast in the lake of fire
and he will suffer and be tormented
day and night forever and ever.
Amen?
Curtis Hudson used to sing often.
I never had the privilege of meeting
or being in a meeting with Dr. Curtis Hudson.
In fact, he went home to be with the Lord
when I was just a little infant.
But I read many things about him
and often he would preach
and he would preach and he would sing.
I'm on the winning side.
Amen?
Rejoicing.
Notice the first four or five words here
of verse number 15.
So the wall was finished.
Isn't that good?
The wall was finished.
In the twenty and fifth day
of the month Elu,
in fifty and two days.
Of course, those that would like to attack
the authenticity and the accuracy
of the Word of God
would say of this verse,
it's impossible that it could be done
in fifty-two days.
Listen, with God,
nothing shall be impossible.
Amen?
They had a lot of people.
If you go back and read through
the entirety of chapter number three
and you read of all of the people
that were working
and all the things that were going on
and you think about the size of the work,
you also understand that the Babylonians
did not utterly take down
every single piece of the wall.
And you understand, listen,
you put God into the equation,
it changes everything.
Amen?
And they finished the wall.
Not only did they finish the wall,
and I understand you don't really see
much rejoicing here,
but I think that there was rejoicing
on the part of the people of God
as they finished the wall.
But when we're rejoicing in the work of the Lord,
we know in verse number 16
that even the enemies had to recognize
that the work was wrought of God.
Notice what the Bible says in verse number 16.
And it came to pass
that when all our enemies heard thereof
and all the heathen that were about us
saw these things,
that they were much cast down in their own eyes,
for they perceived that this work
was wrought of our God.
Listen, when even the enemy recognizes
this is the work of God,
that's what I want to see.
Amen?
I want to just be a church
that's so submitted to God,
that's so just steadfast
in the work that God has called us to do,
that even the enemy would say,
that's the work of God.
Do you remember when Moses and Aaron
were dealing with Pharaoh?
The plagues?
The book of Exodus?
And I mean, the land of Egypt
was just tattered and torn.
It was just destroyed through those plagues.
In the beginning,
what is it that Pharaoh did?
Well, after they saw a miracle by Moses and Aaron,
he called his magicians.
Said, hey guys, you do the same thing they just did.
And they do.
I never could understand
when Pharaoh has his cronies bring more frogs.
Does that make any sense to you?
They had frogs everywhere.
In the bed chamber, in the oven,
and they were everywhere.
And he's gonna have his boys bring more frogs?
It don't even make sense.
But that's what he did.
But eventually,
you go through that passage of scripture,
those chapters in the book of Exodus,
and even the magicians come to Pharaoh and say,
this is the finger of God.
This is the finger of God.
These enemies.
Do you think the enemies wanted to recognize
that God did this?
No, but there was no other explanation.
They came to this place
where they're cast down in their own eyes.
They're defeated.
We did everything we could do.
I mean, it was a full court press.
We pulled out all the stops, all the tricks.
We hired people and we tried to deceive
and we did everything.
And the work was finished.
The work was finished.
Let me share with you this morning
a few promises from the Word of God
for us as the people of God.
Go to the book of Matthew, if you will.
In Matthew chapter number 16.
You believe the Bible this morning?
Every word, amen?
Every word of God is pure.
So thankful for the Word of God.
We sing, we didn't sing it this morning,
but we sing standing on the promises, amen?
Peter says they're exceeding great and precious promises.
Paul says that we can be confident
in the promises of God.
In Him, they're yay, amen?
Listen, what God says, He will do.
Notice Matthew 16.
It's right in the midst of the portion
in which Jesus asked the disciples,
whom do men say that I, the Son of Man am?
Then He says, but whom say ye that I am?
See, because the answer that they say
that you're John the Baptist,
you're one of the prophets, Jeremiah, Isaiah, someone else,
that wasn't the right answer.
So Jesus says, whom say ye that I am?
And Peter stands up in boldness and declares,
thou art the Christ, the Son of the living God.
He's the Messiah.
He's the promised one.
He's God in flesh.
And we find that Jesus then gives a promise
in verse number 18.
I say also unto you,
that thou shalt not be deceived by any man,
but by the Son of Man,
and by the Son of Man,
to thee that thou art Peter, and upon this rock I will build my church, and the gates
of hell shall not prevail against it."
Now we know that verse.
I want you to turn there and look at it because I want it to impact us today.
Jesus said, I will build my church.
It's not our church, it's His church.
And He said, I will build my church.
And He said, furthermore, the gates of hell shall not prevail against it.
Does that mean they're not even going to try?
They've been trying from the beginning.
In Acts chapter number 3 and 4, you see the persecution intensify.
In chapter number 8, it goes to a whole other level.
And you find the promise though of God Almighty that the gates of hell shall not prevail against
it.
I'm so thankful for that.
Listen, there's going to be a day when God's done with the church.
And that's when we get to go to be with Him, amen?
The church is the organism that God is using during this particular time of history.
And He's using the church and He says, I'm going to build it and the gates of hell shall
not prevail against it.
Look here at the book of Romans in chapter number 8.
I just want to share a few promises with you to encourage you this morning.
As we think about the enemy, even as Nehemiah would face an enemy, and even still today
as we face an enemy that would seek to, yes, their ultimate desire is to destroy the work,
but they want to hinder the work.
They want to do anything they can to hinder the work of God.
Romans chapter number 8 and verse number 31, what shall we then say to these things?
If God be for us, who can be against us?
I want to be on God's side, amen?
Notice what he says in verse number 37, nay, in all these things we are more than conquerors
through Him that loved us.
More than conquerors.
I've already said we're on the winning side.
What a joy, what a blessing to be victorious, to be conquerors.
Listen, for too long now the church has acted as if we have no power.
The church has laid down and allowed the enemy to just keep on marching.
The church has said we shouldn't get involved with these things, we shouldn't talk about
these things, we're going to keep it to ourselves.
No, no, we're to go forth and make a difference, amen?
We're on the winning side.
We go in the power of the Lord God Almighty.
And if God be for us, who can be against us?
You say, well I have a whole list of people that are against us.
Yeah, I do too.
But with God, we're a majority, amen?
Look at 1 Corinthians 15.
We mentioned that one of the ways in which Nehemiah resisted the enemy was that he remained
steadfast.
We find in 1 Corinthians 15 in verse number 58.
Another familiar verse of Scripture.
Verse 57 says, but thanks be to God which giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus
Christ.
Therefore, my beloved brethren, be ye steadfast, unmovable, always abounding in the work of
the Lord.
Why?
For as much as ye know.
Every word of God is for you.
He didn't say for as much as you think, for as much as we hope, for as much as you know
that your labor is not in vain in the Lord.
Listen, when we go in the power of God Almighty and we're going forth into the battlefield
and we're giving the truth of the Word of God and we're battling over the souls of men,
you can understand that our work is not in vain in the Lord.
God is working.
God uses His Word.
He promises to do so.
You say, well I just don't see how God is working.
You just remain steadfast.
See, sometimes what we know has to supersede what we think.
We look at the surface and we say, I think this isn't working.
I think I'm not making any progress.
I think it's just, no, no, we know that our labor is not in vain in the Lord.
I think about what Paul said in Romans chapter number 8.
You don't need to turn there, but when we talk about all things work together for good
to them that love God, it starts out with, and we know, because sometimes when we're
in the midst of something, we might sit there and say, how is this going to work for good?
What we know has to supersede what we think.
And he says here that we know that our labor is not in vain in the Lord.
Philippians chapter number 1, Paul is writing to this church, he's in prison.
This church had communicated with him many times.
They gave, they were a precious group of people to Paul.
Paul says they're a precious group of people to him, prayed for them.
I mean, the beginning of chapter number 1 of the book of Philippians is just powerful
to see the relationship that they had, the love.
And notice what Paul says to these believers in Philippians 1 and verse number 6, being
confident.
Don't you like that word?
That's a good word.
Being confident of this very thing, that he which hath begun a good work in you will perform
it until the day of Jesus Christ, being confident.
Listen, this morning, as we look at Nehemiah chapter number 6, and it happened 2,500 years
ago, just about, and you think about the events and the situation that Nehemiah dealt with,
do you see that things have changed somewhat, but the basics of the spiritual warfare that
we deal with, it remains the same, 2,500 years.
Oh, we have different technology now, thankfully we have some modern conveniences now, right?
But the enemy, still working today in the same way that he was 2,500 years ago, and
he wants to deceive you, and he wants to deceive me, and one thing that he uses is fear, fear.
When we look at these promises of God that we've looked at in the New Testament, and
we are mindful that over and over that God says to his people, fear not, be not afraid.
Over and over and over we read those words in this precious book.
I'm mindful of the truth of Hebrews 13, in verses 5 and 6, the Bible says in Hebrews
13 verse 5, let your conversation be without covetousness, and be content with such things
as you have, completely different message in that portion of verse number 5, but notice
what he says at the end of verse number 5, for he hath said, I will never leave thee
nor forsake thee, isn't that precious?
But you know what the result of that understanding is, is verse number 6, so that we may boldly
say the Lord is my helper, and I will not fear what man shall do unto me.
Why is it that you do not have any fear?
Because the Lord is my helper, the Lord is my helper, and he said I'll never leave thee
nor forsake thee.
Remember Psalm 121, I will lift up mine eyes unto the hills, from whence cometh my help?
My help cometh from the Lord, notice this, which made heaven and earth.
Now how did he make it?
He spoke and it was so, amen?
The wonder of creation, God said and it was so.
The power of creation, and he's my helper, he's your helper, he's Nehemiah's helper.
How could Nehemiah continue with all that was going on?
I mean day after day after day, the work being opposed and all of the adversity, he's a man
of prayer.
He learned how to recognize the enemy.
He learned how to resist the enemy, and I believe that as we look at the completion
of the wall, we rejoice in the work of God.
This morning I pray that God would help us to recognize the enemy and to resist the enemy
and to keep on keeping on.
One day it's all going to be over, whether it's by death or by rapture, it's going to
be over.
But until then, oh that God would help us.
to just press on and say, look, I'm not looking for some cave to run to and hide in.
I'm not.
People want to move to Idaho and wherever else they want to move to, we're 16 miles
from the White House.
Oh, man, we're in the thick of it, amen?
Come on.
They're legislating all kinds of wickedness, but we are on the winning side.
And we say, we want to, we want to recognize the enemy.
Sometimes it's real easy.
Other times it takes great levels of discernment that only God can give us, and oh, that we
would resist and see God work and do what only He can do, amen?
I'm glad Nehemiah didn't give up.
Can you imagine?
Well, it's just too hard.
We just kind of, boys go home, close down shop, we're not going to continue this.
They don't want us to do it.
No.
They were persistent.
They just kept on, kept on, keeping on.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
Thank You for loving us.
Thank You for this passage, and though the events occurred over 2,000 years ago, we see
such similarities of what we deal with today.
Oh, how we need perception, discernment, to be able to recognize and identify the enemy.
We understand the truth that You have given to us in Your Word with regard to resisting
the enemy, and I trust that You would help us to follow the pattern, the discipline of
Nehemiah that we see in Nehemiah chapter 6.
Help us this morning to leave this place encouraged because of the promises that You've
given us in Your Word.
We're thankful for the good work that You have started.
We know that You will complete it.
We know that You said that You would build Your church, and the gates of hell shall not
prevail against it.
Lord, I pray You'd help us to be a people that are fully surrendered to You, a people
that are yielded, that would allow You to do what only You can do, that even the enemy
would have to look at it and say, the Lord did that.
Oh, God, we pray that You'd work in that way.
Use this time of invitation as only You can to convict and to convince and to change we,
Your people.
That we might go out of here with a revived focus and a resolve to serve You faithfully.
It's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Jared's going to play quietly on the piano, and as he is playing, the altar is open.
Come to this old-fashioned altar, make your seat an altar.
Would you submit to God, surrender to God?
Let God use you.
Ask Him to help you to have that ability, that discernment to recognize and identify
the enemy.
As Jared plays, the altar is open.