16. As I mentioned this morning, I'm so thankful for the Word of God and thankful that we're able
to have a copy of the Word of God and that we're speaking with someone this week and sharing with
them some of the ministries that we've done here at the church over the years and discussing the
Bible assembly campaign and the opportunity to assemble scriptures. And we've not been able to
do that in 2020, but look forward to being able to get engaged with that ministry once again.
And what a blessing to be able to see the Word of God go around the world. In your Bible this
evening, Genesis chapter number 16, we'll be looking at the entire chapter, Genesis 16,
looking at verses 1 through 16. And let me read the first verse. We'll dig into the scriptures
this evening. The Bible says, Now Sarai, Abram's wife, bare him no children. And she had a handmaid,
an Egyptian, whose name was Hagar. If you look over in verse number 15 of our text,
the Bible says, And Hagar bare Abram a son. And Abram called his son's name, which Hagar bare,
Ishmael. And Abram was fourscore and six years old when Hagar bare Ishmael to Abram.
If you're taking notes this evening, I've simply entitled the message, The Birth of Ishmael,
The Birth of Ishmael. The content of Genesis 16 reveals to us the humanity of Abram and Sarai.
As we think about the passage that we studied over the last few weeks in Genesis chapter number 15,
and just the powerful truth that God gave us, and the way in which God came and spoke to Abram,
and the conversation that they had, the dialogue, if you will, back and forth. And Abram receives
the promise of the Lord, and the promise with regard to the seed, the promise with regard to
the land, as we looked at last week. And we look at that Abrahamic covenant, as we often refer to
it as, and what great truth is provided to us in Genesis chapter number 15. And we enter into
chapter number 16, and I believe that as we look at this passage, it is very possible that we can
examine this chapter with a critical eye. It is possible for us to, in fact, any portion of
Scripture, but especially this passage of Scripture with regard to the study that we've been doing
through the book of Genesis, it is possible that we enter into with that critical eye, and we critique
the behavior, the decisions of those. And at the onset of the message this evening,
there are bad decisions that are made in Genesis chapter number 16, but as we look at the passage,
I think that it's possible that if we examine the Scriptures with a critical eye, and we just
examine Genesis chapter number 16 with accusing and critiquing the decisions of Abram and Sarai,
that it is very possible that in doing so, we may miss the lessons that God has for us to learn
from studying the event that is before us. I think most of us would agree this evening
that I'm glad that my life story hasn't been written down and recorded for generations of
people to read. The reality is that there are certain aspects of our lives, no doubt,
that have been recorded. There are times in which while I'm preaching, maybe I say something
in a twisted way. I put the words in the wrong order or something, and then that's recorded,
and somebody can go back and look at it. But I think about Abram and Sarai, and I think about
the way in which their life and many of the events of their life are recorded in the pages of
Scripture. And they've been viewed, and they've been studied for generations of people. Not only
Abram and Sarai, many other of the characters in the Word of God. And we know that the only perfect
person is God. The Lord Jesus Christ came and lived a perfect and sinless life. And as we look
at Genesis chapter number 16, I believe that the record reveals to us the humanity of these
individuals. The fact that they deal with some of the same difficulties that we deal with.
Listen, we're not always as patient as we ought to be. Amen? We don't always have the faith that
we ought to have. We don't always live in obedience to the commands that God has given us.
And if we're not careful, we can, with a critical eye, look at a passage of Scripture such as this
one and say, they should have done this, and they should have done that. And I understand, we'll
share some of those things this evening. But all my prayer tonight as we look at this passage is
that we would learn from that which is recorded, and we would be able to make good decisions in
our own lives. As we're going to dig into the passage and look at the entirety of the chapter,
I do think that it's important to really dissect verse number one just for a moment as it helps to
set the scene as to that which would unfold in Genesis chapter number 16. Notice with me,
the Bible begins and tells us, Now Sarai, Abram's wife, bare him no children. Now this is a recurring
statement or theme throughout the Scriptures with regard to our first introduction to Abram and
Sarai. In fact, if you go back to Genesis chapter number 11, and you find that as God would provide
us with the history of Abraham and the generations of Terah as they begin in verse number 27,
the Bible tells us in Genesis 11 and verse number 30, But Sarai was barren, she had no child.
The Bible tells us, even as we studied the 15th chapter of the book of Genesis over the last few
weeks, that Abram said in verse number 3 of Genesis 15, Behold, to me thou hast given no seed.
And of course, God's response when Abram says that one born in mine house is mine heir,
God said to him, This shall not be thine heir, but he that shall come forth out of thine own bowels
shall be thine heir. We come to chapter number 16 and we once again are reminded of this situation
in which the Bible tells us that Sarai, Abram's wife, bare him no children. Now the Bible continues
to go on and it introduces us to someone that is her handmaid. It says, And she, Sarai, had
a handmaid. Notice this, an Egyptian whose name was Hagar. I'm not sure how often you have really
considered the content of Genesis 16 or how much time you've spent at really trying to figure out
where did this Hagar come from. We know the Bible says that she's an Egyptian, but I would encourage
you just for a moment to turn back to Genesis chapter number 12. You'll recall with me in Genesis
chapter number 12, as God had called Abram to leave the Ur of the Chaldees, as it is mentioned
at the end of chapter 11, the beginning of chapter number 12, that as they get into the land, as they
get to that place where God had promised them to go, it tells us in verse number five, And Abram
took Sarai, his wife, and Lot, his brother's son, and all their substance that they had gathered,
and the souls that they had gotten in Haran, and they went forth to go into the land of Canaan,
and into the land of Canaan, they came. And we find that in verse number 10, the Bible says that
there was a famine in the land. If you remember, as we studied this portion of Scripture, that we
spoke about the plan of God and how God and his wisdom and knowledge that he led Abram and his
family to go to this place at this time, and yet as they arrive, they encounter this famine. And
the Bible tells us that Abram went down into Egypt to sojourn there, for the famine was grievous
in the land. Of course, we understand that while Abram and Sarai and Lot and those servants that
he had went down into Egypt, that the Bible tells us that Abram's greatest concern was for his wife
Sarai, and he said, Tell them that you're my sister, because they're going to see you, and
they're going to see that you're beautiful, and they're going to kill me for your sake.
We find that God miraculously took care of Sarai and Abram, and God dealt with Pharaoh. We studied
this a number of weeks ago, and we find that the Bible tells us that Abram and his wife and his
family, they leave in verse number one of chapter 13, it says, and Abram went up out of Egypt,
he and his wife and all that he had, and Lot with him into the south. I do not believe that I can
prove it biblically that Hagar became a handmaid during this particular trip, but it certainly
seems to be the case. And we find that it's important for us to understand that even the
decisions that we make, and in this particular context as we look at a timeline, that it will
perhaps have consequences later on down the road. And we find that even here in Genesis chapter
number 16, that will be a recurring thought throughout the message this evening. But we find
that the Bible introduces us not only or reminds us of the situation of Sarai being barren, having
no children, but also the Scriptures introduce us to this one named Hagar, who was an Egyptian.
Now, as we dig into the passage, I want you to notice first of all, if you're taking points,
the reasoning of Sarai. In verse number two, God gives us a glimpse into the reasoning of Sarai.
The Bible says in verse number two, and Sarai said unto Abram, Behold now the Lord hath
that restrained me from bearing.
I pray Thee, go in unto my maid.
It may be that I may obtain children by her."
As we begin to think,
and we'll read verse 2 in just a moment,
as we begin to think about the reasoning of Sarai
and we see her perspective in verse 2
in this beginning section of this verse of Scripture,
that she goes to her husband
and she says she identifies
what has already been well known.
We know that she's barren.
We know that Abram had already spoken to God
in chapter number 15 about having no seed.
And we find that she says to her husband,
the Lord hath restrained me from bearing.
Now look at the logic, the reasoning, if you will.
She says, I pray Thee, go in unto my maid.
It may be that I may obtain children by her.
As we would think about the thought,
the reasoning, and the perspective,
I would say that it was one of sight and not of faith.
I would say that when we look at what's taking place here,
that what is being said was something that was legitimate
with regard to the society in which they lived.
It was certainly something that had taken place
and something that they were aware of
that she, as being barren,
could have children through her handmaid.
And we find that she's going to,
with this reasoning and this logic,
she's going to bring this idea to Abram.
And I want you to just stop and think for a moment.
I want you to consider with me
that as we think about the situation
and we think about all that Abram and Sarai have dealt with,
I want you to consider with me
that it's been 10 years since they left the Ur of the Chaldees.
that when they received that call,
when Abram received that call in chapter 12,
that he had received the fact
that God would make of thee a great nation,
I will bless thee and make thy name great.
He goes through and he gives them these promises,
and of course, they're repeated throughout the Scriptures.
At that particular time, Abram is 75 years old.
By the end of chapter 16,
we'll find that Abram is 86 years old.
And so there's a period of just about 10 years that goes by.
And after 10 years of waiting,
and after 10 years of not having any children,
we find that it's come to the place
where it's adversely affected the reasoning of Sarai.
She begins to have a sight answer to the problem
instead of a faith solution to the problem.
I think that when we would evaluate our circumstances
and our situations that we face,
I would wonder this evening
as we have decisions that we have to make,
what is it that we go through as a process?
What is it that we begin to evaluate?
Where does the promise of God
lay within our decision-making process?
See, the reality this evening
is there are times in which many of us
have not waited 10 years for God to do something.
10 years is a long time.
10 years is a very long time.
They're older, they've heard this promise,
but she's barren.
She's had no children.
They look at society and they see
that this is a practice that is accepted.
And so she begins to, in her mind,
as we think about her reasoning,
she comes to this conclusion.
Again, I believe it's the wrong conclusion,
but I wonder this evening,
can we relate a little bit with Sarai?
Can we, instead of criticizing her,
try to learn from her?
I'm not in any way suggesting
that she made a good decision.
She didn't, it was a terrible decision.
But there are times in which we make terrible decisions
and we've not waited 10 minutes for God.
10 years is a long time.
The Bible tells us that she says,
I pray thee, go in unto my maid.
It may be that I may obtain children by her.
I wonder how many different ways
we could apply the thought this evening
from this passage of Scripture
and how there are times in which
we try to take matters in our own hands.
That we try to manipulate circumstances
or to build something.
We're not waiting on God.
We know that God's promised to work.
We know that He's given us promises
that I'm gonna build the church
and He's given us a pattern,
a plan, if you will, on how to reach the world
with the Gospel of Jesus Christ.
But I wonder, have we stuck to the plan?
Are we doing what God said?
Or do we just kinda, you know what?
That's not working and we're tired of waiting.
And see here, Sarai, it's a terrible decision.
Again, I wanna repeat that.
I wanna make sure that we understand this evening
that I'm not saying that this is a right decision.
I'm simply suggesting this evening
that I can understand how someone
could make a wrong decision
when our reasoning is getting messed up.
When we're looking at it by sight
and not by faith.
When we say, I look at my own resources,
and again, they're stricken in years,
when we say, this is not happening.
I'm barren and maybe you can have a child in this manner.
Maybe it is that I would obtain children by her.
See, this evening, instead of criticizing Sarai,
I wonder if we would evaluate our own lives
and decisions and ask ourselves,
how much patience and faith do we have?
How much patience and faith do we have
on waiting on the promises of God?
In allowing God to work
in a way that only He will work?
In a way that would only bring honor and glory to His name?
We see the reasoning of Sarai, number two.
If you're taking notes at the end of verse number two
and down through verse number four,
I want you to notice the response of Abram.
The response of Abram.
Again, the reasoning of Sarai was not good reasoning,
and the response of Abram is not a good response.
At the end of verse number two, it says,
and Abram hearkened to the voice of Sarai.
And Sarai, Abram's wife, verse three,
took Hagar, her maid, the Egyptian,
after Abram had dwelt 10 years in the land of Canaan,
and gave her to her husband, Abram, to be his wife.
And he, Abram, went in unto Hagar, and she conceived.
When she saw that she had conceived,
her mistress was despised in her eyes.
We see, first of all, in verse number two,
we think about the response of Abram.
It begins by him hearkening to the voice of Sarai.
He hears what Sarai says,
and we understand what's been recorded here
in Holy Scripture for us.
I'm not sure if there's been other discussions
that have taken place between Abram and Sarai.
We know that every conversation that they have
has not been recorded in Holy Scripture,
and I'm not sure, during that 10-year period,
how difficult it was.
I do know, however, that in chapter number 15,
that God, as he speaks to Abram,
and then as Abram speaks back to God,
that Abram voices a similar situation when he says,
behold, to me thou hast given no seed.
This was not a secret.
This was something that perhaps
had come up in conversation many times,
and now she's gotten this solution.
She's had this answer.
Abram, God has not allowed me to have children.
The Lord hath restrained me from bearing,
and here's the solution.
And Abram hearkened to the voice of Sarai.
Verse number three records for us
the way in which the decision was made
and verse number four tells us
about the way in which Abram went in unto Hagar
and the consequence of that decision,
the fact that the Bible says,
and she conceived.
So we begin to consider the response of Abram
and it's just kind of a short point this evening.
I wonder this evening how often it is
that we respond to those
that have had improper reasoning.
See, the reality this evening
is that there are times in which
an individual as Sarai in this particular case
has reasoning that is not appropriate reasoning
and it requires a response.
Abram has been called of the Lord
as we find throughout the Scriptures
that he is to be the head of the home,
he is to be the spiritual leader in the home,
and there are times in which
the response to bad reasoning
does not need to be one of just hearkening to it.
And we find that this response of Abram
is a wrong response.
He hearkened to the voice of Sarai.
I want to focus this evening on our last point
and the results of their decision.
The results of their decision.
And really, it will take the remainder of the chapter,
but I want you to hold your place here
and I want you to turn over to the New Testament
and the book of Galatians
before we really dig into these results.
I want you to consider...
what God tells us in Galatians chapter number 6.
We visited this morning, verse number 10,
as we were dealing with the subject this morning,
this mortal shall put on immortality,
this mortal must put on immortality.
We talked about the opportunities that we have now,
and we looked at verse number 10,
but I want to draw your attention this evening
with regard to the subject matter of Genesis 16,
to Galatians 6 and verses 7 through 9.
The Bible says in verse number 7,
be not deceived, God is not mocked.
For whatsoever a man soweth, that shall he also reap.
God has established in His word a law
of sowing and reaping.
The reality is that we see this law in nature,
we understand the principle, the law
of sowing and reaping, if you want to have a harvest
of corn, you sow some seed, and after some time
of taking care of that seed and watering,
and so on and so forth, as the time would go forth,
you will reap a harvest of corn.
The principles are many.
You reap what you sow in like fashion.
The reality is that oftentimes you reap more than you sow.
And we find here that the Bible continues
in verse number 8, for he that soweth to his flesh
shall of the flesh reap corruption.
But he that soweth to the Spirit
shall of the Spirit reap life everlasting.
I'm thankful this evening that though oftentimes
when we speak about the law of sowing and reaping
that we would speak of it in a negative context,
the reality is that there's a positive side to it as well.
If you sow some good seed, you'll reap some good fruit.
You sow bad seed, you're gonna reap some bad fruit.
I'm thankful that the principle, the law has these two sides
and we understand this evening this truth.
And then notice in verse number 9,
and let us not be weary in well-doing,
for in due season we shall reap if we faint not.
The reality is that it's not often
that we reap as soon as we sow.
Now there are times in which we will obviously,
when I think about the decisions that we make,
there might be some immediate consequences.
When we really think about the law of sowing and reaping
and we understand this evening
that if I want to have a harvest in the fall,
that I need to be busy about doing some work in the spring
and preparing and cultivating
and getting the seed out of the barn
and all of the things that I need to do
in order to ensure a harvest.
I don't decide at harvest time,
hey, I better get that seed out of the barn.
No, there's just not enough time.
It's not gonna happen.
It's not gonna work.
In fact, there are many fruit trees
that take years to produce fruit.
You don't just decide,
I think I wanna have some apples in my yard next year.
I'm gonna go buy an apple tree.
You're not gonna have apples next year.
Just not gonna work.
And so we understand this evening
that principle from nature and that law.
And in our lives, we understand,
as we'll look at this passage of scripture,
a couple of impacts of these decisions,
the results of their decision.
We've noticed their reasoning.
We've noticed the reasoning of Sarai,
the response of Abram.
Now let's look at the results of their decision.
There were, if you're taking notes,
number one, there were some immediate consequences.
The Bible says at the end of verse number four
that her mistress was despised in her eyes.
As I would begin to consider this evening
the immediate consequences,
I would say that verses five and six,
really verse four, five, and six,
reveal to us some of the domestic relationships
that had some immediate consequences
to the decision that was made.
The reasoning led to a response,
and then there are some results.
And the Bible says in verse number five, notice,
and Sarai said unto Abram,
my wrong be upon thee.
I have given my maid into thy bosom,
and when she saw that she had conceived,
I was despised in her eyes.
The Lord judged between me and thee.
Now all of a sudden, there's domestic dispute going on.
There's problems at home.
There's contention between Sarai and Hagar.
There's contention between Abram and Sarai.
And we look at what's happening.
We find in verse number six that Abram said unto Sarai,
behold, thy maid is in thy hand.
Due to her is it pleaseth thee.
Notice what it says.
And when Sarai dealt hardly with her,
she fled from her face.
The Bible, as it uses that word, dealt hardly,
it means to deal harshly with her,
and she fled from her face.
Now this situation has gone downhill very rapidly.
Sarai has some reasoning,
and it's revealed to us in verse number two.
And she comes to this place in her life
and she's reasoning through what's going on.
And she says, I have no children.
And she goes to her husband, to Abram,
and she says, I pray thee, go in unto my maid.
It may be that I may obtain children by her.
And maybe she did not expect things
to work out the way that they did.
The reality is that there are times
in which in our lives we make decisions
and we don't think the consequences
are gonna be what they are.
I didn't see that coming.
I didn't think it was gonna work that way.
I didn't think she was gonna respond that way
or he was gonna do this.
And here we find that Abram hearkened to Sarai.
He goes in unto Hagar.
She conceives, and the Bible says
that when she saw that she had conceived
that her mistress was despised in her eyes.
There becomes this contention between Sarai and Hagar.
And then Sarai goes to Abram and says,
my wrong be upon thee.
And we find that now Sarai, as Abram would say to her
in verse number six, thy maid is in thy hand,
do to her as it pleaseth thee,
that now Sarai will deal harshly, hardly with her.
And now Hagar flees.
As a side note, dealing with the consequences
of the results of the decisions,
we see that in verses number seven through 11,
that God reveals to us the situation
with Hagar fleeing and the angel of the Lord
appearing to her.
But I want you to think this evening
when we think about the results of the decision
that there were some immediate consequences.
In verse number seven, the Bible says,
and the angel of the Lord found her
by a fountain of water in the wilderness,
by the fountain in the way to Shur.
As we would look at Bible geography,
we would understand that what's happening here
is the Bible would describe for us in verse number seven
where the angel of the Lord found Hagar.
She was heading back to Egypt.
She was from Egypt.
She was an Egyptian.
We mentioned that in the beginning of the text of Scripture
at the beginning of our message this evening.
And now as the angel of the Lord would find her
in the wilderness by the fountain in the way to Shur,
that she's heading back to Egypt.
Now it's interesting that as we begin to look here
as Hagar would depart and set out to return to Egypt,
that the angel of the Lord appears to her
and in so doing as we read these few verses of Scripture,
I believe that we see many of God's attributes on display.
I believe that we see the sovereignty of God.
I believe that we see the grace of God,
the omniscience of God, the eternality of God.
All of these things were in view here
in these verses of Scripture.
And notice with me in verse number eight,
he said, Hagar,
Sarai's maid, whence camest thou?
And whither wilt thou go?
And she said, I flee from the face of my mistress Sarai.
The angel of the Lord said unto her,
Return to thy mistress and submit thyself under her hands.
Now that's pretty direct instruction, is it not?
The angel of the Lord comes and gives direct instruction.
Now Sarai was the one that had dealt hardly with Hagar
and Hagar's response to that was that she fled from her face
and now the angel of the Lord appears
and the angel of the Lord refers to Hagar
as being Sarai's maid and says to her,
you need to return to thy mistress
and submit thyself under her hands.
Notice in verse number 10,
and the angel of the Lord said unto her,
I will multiply thy seed exceedingly
that it shall not be numbered for multitude.
And the angel of the Lord said unto her,
Behold, thou art with child,
and shalt bear a son,
and shalt call his name Ishmael,
because the Lord hath heard thy affliction.
The name Ishmael means God shall hear.
We find that here in these verses of Scripture again,
as God would pursue the angel of the Lord
goes to where Hagar is as she's fleeing,
we'd see the grace of God.
We'd understand the omniscience and eternality of God
when the angel of the Lord says to her
that she is with child and that she shall bear a son.
When he says to her in verse number 10,
I will multiply thy seed exceedingly
that it shall not be numbered for multitude.
In verse number 11,
the angel of the Lord tells her of the name
that she shall call her son.
And notice in verse number 12,
and he will be a wild man.
His hand will be against her.
against every man and every man's hand against him,
and he shall dwell in the presence
of all his brethren."
This is where we transition from
those immediate consequences
that we read of in verses 4-6,
and now begin to look at some long-term consequences
of our decisions.
You know, the reality is that there are times
in which we make decisions
and there are some short-term consequences
and maybe they're not very comfortable,
they're not desirous, and we deal with them.
And sometimes we don't really even consider
what the long-term consequences may be.
But here in the text of Scripture,
we see that there are long-term consequences
that are revealed to us.
The first aspect is we find in v. 12,
the Bible says he, speaking of Ishmael,
will be a wild man.
The idea is that he would be unruly and stubborn.
We find the Bible then tells us in v. 12
that his hand will be against every man
and every man's hand against him,
and he shall dwell in the presence
of all his brethren.
We could look this evening not only
of the immediate descendants of Ishmael,
but we could find as we look historically
of the Arab nations that are the descendants of Ishmael,
and we could find how that even here
in Genesis 16,
there's this understanding of the turmoil,
the hostility, and the contention
that would be in their future.
That their hand, as it says in v. 12,
he will be a wild man,
his hand will be against every man,
and every man's hand against him,
and he shall dwell in the presence
of all his brethren.
This evening, if you're to study through history,
you'll find that exactly what God says here
in Genesis 16, in v. 12,
with regard to the descendants of Ishmael
has been seen throughout human history.
And we find that these are
what I would consider this evening,
this is a long-term consequence
to a decision that was made.
When you think about the time of Abram,
I mean thousands of years of human history
have passed, and we still see the consequences today
of this decision that is recorded
in Genesis 16.
We find the Bible continues in v. 13,
and she called the name of the Lord
that spake unto her.
Thou, God, seest me.
For she said,
Have I also here looked after him
that seeth me?
Wherefore, the well was called
Lehei Roy.
Behold, it is between Kadesh and Berid.
And Hagar bare Abram a son,
and Abram called his son's name,
which Hagar bare Ishmael.
And Abram was fourscore and six years old
when Hagar bare Ishmael to Abram.
As we see in v. 14,
bare Lehei Roy,
that name of the well,
it means the well of him that liveth
and seeth me.
And I think that's quite interesting
as we understand this evening
that our God lives,
and our God sees us.
And He knows what we're dealing with.
He knows what we're experiencing in our lives,
and certainly there is comfort
in understanding that.
As we look at these results of this decision
that is recorded in Genesis 16,
again, I believe it's very easy for us tonight,
it's very easy for me in my study time
to just go to chapter 16 of the book of Genesis
knowing the content of what's going on
and just beginning by,
let's attack Abram and Sarai.
Look at all the bad decisions they made.
I can't believe they did this
and so on and so forth.
But I took a step back
as I was studying the portion of scripture
and I began to deal with the reasoning
and looking at what's taking place
and asking and evaluating in my own life
how patient am I on waiting on God?
How much faith do I have when I wait on God?
It's easy for me to look at the results
of the decision that was made
in Genesis chapter number 16
and critique the decision that was made,
but the reality is that there are decisions
that I make and there are decisions that you make
that we don't know what the full consequences
are gonna be.
They're outside of our control.
There are immediate consequences,
but then there are long-term, far-reaching consequences.
And I would challenge you this evening
that as we look here at Genesis chapter number 16
and we consider the content of what God gives us
in this passage that we would be aware of the fact
that Abram and Sarai were human beings
and their humanity is on display
and the reality is that we all are human beings
and we are dealing with difficulties
and there are times in which somebody
might enter into our life and bring us some reasoning
that is not sound logic reasoning.
And if we're not careful, we can respond to that
and make some decisions that are not proper decisions
that will have some negative consequences.
Because there's principle in the Word of God law
with regard to sowing and reaping.
You understand this evening, no doubt,
that every decision that we make has consequences.
I read a humorous story this afternoon,
it really wasn't much of a story,
it was just a little clip and it was quite humorous
where someone was observing,
this of course was not in 2020, it was many years ago,
but they were observing that during this time of year,
the two most popular books at a bookstore
are the cookbook and the diet book.
And they were making fun of the fact
that you're trying to find out how to cook the food
and then trying to find out how to lose the weight
from eating the food.
And the reality is that every decision
that we make has consequences.
I mean, we understand that in the little things in life,
but sometimes we make decisions
that have far-reaching consequences,
long-term consequences.
I don't think Abram and Sarai
had any idea that thousands of years
after the decision that was made in Genesis 16
would still be having consequences today.
I just don't think they even considered that.
Many times in our lives, perhaps as parents,
we make decisions and perhaps we do not fully consider
the long-term impact and influence
that those decisions could have in our children,
in our grandchildren, because we're making decisions
and consequences are results of decisions.
Holly often has said to me over the years,
I'm not sure where she first heard it,
but it's not that it's a very unpopular
kind of a thought or saying, it's well-known,
but what one generation does in moderation,
the next does in excess.
Begin to think about the consequences of our decisions
and what it is that we allow in our own lives
and what it is that we allow to be permitted
and so on and so forth and how those things
are going to impact a future generation.
And here in this passage of scripture,
we see the reasoning of Sarai,
poor reasoning, poor reasoning.
But before we get too critical on Sarai,
before you examine her life and criticize,
would you take a step back and evaluate your own life
and say, how's my reasoning?
Do I trust God?
Am I patient on waiting for God
to do what God said He would do?
Am I displaying, demonstrating faith in my life?
We see the response of Abram, poor response.
But again, before we, with a critical eye,
come and attack Abram for not being the man
that he was supposed to be and not opposing the idea
that was brought forth,
I wonder if we take a step back and evaluate.
What happens when someone comes to you
with some bad reasoning and gives you a suggestion
and idea, hey, we could handle it this way,
we could do it this way.
Are we willing to stand up with a measure of sound logic
and reason and a measure of faith and say no?
God had given a promise to Abram.
Abram, he responds to this reasoning of Sarai
and then we see the results.
I don't think for a moment that Abram and Sarai
thought about the far-reaching consequences,
but I would suggest to you this evening
that I don't even think they considered
the immediate consequences.
I don't think they thought it would work out this way.
Oh, maybe that Sarai would have children through Hagar,
but not that it would have this level of effect and impact.
That it would cause that immediate contention
within the home, if you will.
And this evening, I just wonder if instead of critiquing
and criticizing and attacking,
if we would just simply take a step back
and evaluate our own lives and say,
how are we doing when we are facing with difficulties
and the decisions that we have to make?
How's my reasoning?
How's my faith?
How's my patience?
We see this evening in Genesis 16, the birth of Ishmael.
Father, we love you and we thank you for loving us.
We thank You for the privilege
of being able to once again open Your Word.
And Lord, I hope this evening
that not one person has misunderstood
what I've sought to communicate this evening.
In no way, shape, or form am I commending
or saying that what was done
was understandable or appropriate.
These are poor decisions that were made
and this is chapter number 16.
God, I simply desire tonight
to learn from that which is recorded
in this passage of Scripture,
and that we as Your people today
would not just sit by and criticize,
but that we'd step back and evaluate.
Cause our reasoning.
Help us to be mindful this evening
that our decisions have consequences.
There are times in which we can sit back many years
and look at the consequences and wonder,
how did this ever happen?
To give an honest answer,
we'd have to dig and dig and dig
to go all the way back to that decision
that led to those consequences.
Help us, Lord, to have faith.
Help us, Lord, to believe You.
Help us, Lord, to be patient.
I know that as Your children,
it's one of the hardest things that we do
is waiting on the Lord.
I pray, God, that You'd help us to endure.
I pray that You'd work in hearts and lives,
have Your will and way as only You can,
for it's in Christ's name we pray,
Amen.