Revelation chapter number 2, be looking at verses 12 through 17 as we deal with the church
in Pergamos.
And we'll be looking here at these few verses of scripture.
The city of Pergamos was located about 45 miles north of Smyrna.
Of course, it's been a few weeks since we've been here on a Sunday night looking at the
book of Revelation.
We've had a couple of other evenings and different things going on on Sunday nights, but it's
been almost a month actually since we've been in the book of Revelation.
And so the last study was on the church in Smyrna, verses 8 through 11, and this city
of Pergamos is located at 45 miles or so north of Smyrna.
The city was known for pagan polytheistic religion, including emperor worship.
And so it was a real exciting place to live.
All sorts of idolatry and wickedness and lots of religion, quote unquote.
Of course, no true, the lack of true gospel preaching was limited.
Obviously the church in Pergamos is there, but there's much false teaching, false religion
and all that was going on.
The city was known, it's believed that parchment type paper was first used here in the city
of Pergamos.
That's just kind of an interesting thought or fact.
It's also reported, if you were to study through history, that this city had a library
quite extensive that had about 200,000 volumes.
And so we're going to think about this as in the first century, we're going to think
about a library with 200,000 volumes.
It's pretty significant.
And so we find that as we look at this text of scripture, we see a little bit about what's
going on in the city and what they would be aware of.
But we understand as we're looking at the book of Revelation and these letters that
are written to the churches, the idea is not so much to study the cities and know too
many things about them specifically, but to look at the evaluation that God gives of the
individual churches.
I'm thankful that the Lord Jesus Christ is the head of the church.
It's his church and he loved the church and gave himself for it.
He purchased it with his own blood according to Acts chapter 20.
And we find that he is the head of the church and he's writing, having John write these
letters to the church as he's giving an evaluation.
And we know immediately as we have with the previous two letters, how the Lord is described
for us.
We noticed in the first letter to the church at Ephesus that it talked about the Lord Jesus
Christ, that he that holdeth the seven stars in his right hand, who walketh in the midst
of the seven golden candlesticks.
And then to Smyrna, these things saith the first and the last, which was dead and is
alive.
But notice now in verse number 12, the Bible says, and to the angel of the church in Pergamos
write, these things saith he which hath the sharp sword with two edges.
We mentioned in chapter number one, as we looked at the great description that is given
of the Lord Jesus Christ, about the fact that he's described in so many amazing ways
and understanding that he has a name, the word of God.
We looked at Revelation 19 and we looked at a number of those things.
And now we find that it says, he which hath the sharp sword with two edges.
Immediately my mind goes to Hebrews chapter four and verse number 12.
If you want to just very quickly look at that verse of scripture and notice what the Bible
says in Hebrews 4 and verse number 12, as we consider this introductory statement.
And here in Hebrews 4 and verse 12, the Bible says this, for the word of God is quick.
It means it's alive.
I'm thankful that God's word is a living book.
The Bible says, for the word of God is quick and powerful and sharper than any two edged
sword.
And notice it says, piercing even to the dividing asunder of soul and spirit and of the joints
and marrow and as a discerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart.
That's a powerful verse of scripture.
And we find that the Lord Jesus Christ, as he's having John pen this letter to the church
in Pergamos, he says, he which hath the sharp sword with two edges.
It's not dull.
It's sharp.
The word of God is quick.
It's powerful.
It's a living book.
And the Lord Jesus Christ has a name according to Revelation 19, the word of God.
And so we look here and begin to look at this evaluation of the church.
I want you to note number one, how they flourished.
Notice as we look at that familiar statement, I know thy works.
We've read that of the church at Ephesus.
We've read of the church in Smyrna.
We'll read it in each of the churches.
And we see here that in verse number 13, the Lord says, I know thy works.
You understand this evening that there's nothing that you can hide from God.
There's absolutely nothing that you can hide from God.
Adam and Eve tried to hide from God.
How'd that work for them?
It didn't work.
David tried to hide some stuff from God.
How'd that work?
Well, he told Nathan all about it.
And Nathan stood before David and said, thou art the man, right?
And we can go on and on and we can understand this evening that God knows everything.
Listen, he knows your motives.
He knows the thoughts that you have, that he knows everything about us.
He knows our works.
He knows why we do the things that we do.
And it says here, I know thy works and where thou dwellest.
That's how he describes the place Pergamos, even where Satan's seat is.
And thou notice, as we look at this verse of scripture and look at how they flourished,
it says, and thou holdest fast my name and has not denied my faith.
Even in those days where in Antipas was my faithful martyr who was slain among you, where
Satan dwelleth.
As we look at verse 13 and begin to think about how they flourished, I want you to consider
a few thoughts here with regard to the church in Pergamos and what they were doing and how
they were being used of the Lord.
Number one, they were a light in a dark place.
They were a light in a dark place.
It says that where thou dwellest, even where Satan's seat is.
Sometimes we can get sideways over the place where God has us, maybe being a wicked place,
an ungodly place, but the reality is that God has put us in this world, though we're
not of the world, and he's called us to be a light.
The book of Philippians in chapter two and verse number 15, the Bible says that you may
be blameless and harmless, the sons of God, without rebuke in the midst of a crooked and
perverse nation among whom you shine as lights in the world.
Jesus said that we're to let our light shine.
We understand, we sing the song with the kids, this little light of mine, I'm gonna
let it shine.
I'm not gonna let Satan blow it out, I'm not gonna hide it in a bushel, no, I'm gonna let
it shine till Jesus comes, and we sing all those verses with the little kids and we understand
the importance of being that light.
And here, the church in Pergamos, they were living in a wicked, pagan, idolatrous, polytheistic
society, and yet they were shining as a light.
What a great example for us, what a great reminder of the importance to continue to
shine the light of the gospel.
We find that not only were they a light in a dark place, but the Bible says that they
held fast his name, notice it says, and thou holdest fast my name.
I'm thankful that even in the midst of a pagan society, even in the midst of idolatrous
worship that we can hold fast the name of Jesus.
Jesus indeed is the sweetest name I know, and we ought to lift high the name of the
Lord Jesus Christ, we ought to not be ashamed of the name of the Lord Jesus Christ.
He's my savior, and I love him, and he says to this church that thou holdest fast my name,
verse number three, and hast not denied my faith.
Can you understand just for a moment as we begin to think about this church in Pergamos
and the city and the idolatry and the wickedness and the emperor worship and how if you did
not follow their religious practices, they would literally make your life miserable.
They would try to make it so that you cannot survive.
Not so that you cannot thrive, but literally so that you cannot even survive.
You must follow their rules.
You must do as they tell you to do, and yet we find that this church, they did not deny
the faith.
They did not deny the faith.
Can you imagine the pressures?
The overwhelming pressures that they would face in society, but yet we find that here
the Lord Jesus Christ, as he's giving this evaluation, he says that you're shining in
this dark place, that you're holding fast my name, that you've not denied my faith,
and then notice he says, even in those days wherein Antipas was my faithful martyr, who
was slain among you where Satan dwelleth.
It's interesting that he said at the beginning of the verse, even where Satan's...
C is, and at the end, where Satan dwelleth.
But he talks about this fact that they were faithful
in the midst of great persecution.
He says in those days, can you imagine
the church in Pergamos?
I mean, they obviously knew the events
surrounding the death of Antipas.
They would be familiar with all that had transpired,
and as the Lord says that even in those days
where in Antipas, my faithful martyr
who was slain among you,
could it be that some within the church,
not only brothers and sisters in Christ,
but perhaps even family members,
they're being reminded of being faithful unto death,
being faithful unto death.
And here the church was flourishing in these ways,
and we can rejoice in that, and we can take note,
and we can say, okay, God knows our works,
and it's good that God would acknowledge
and God would recognize that here's some things,
here's some areas where you're doing
what you're supposed to be doing,
but we understand as we continue through the text,
not only how they flourished, but number two,
we know how they faltered.
We see in verse 14 and 15 in these two verses,
and in verse number 14 specifically,
notice the Bible begins,
but I have a few things against thee.
These are words that are no doubt difficult to receive.
These are words that given an evaluation,
you do not wanna hear.
I have a few things against thee.
Remember as we looked at the church in Ephesus,
the Bible said, nevertheless, I have somewhat against thee
because thou hast left thy first love.
And we find here that he says,
but I have a few things against thee.
Notice what he mentioned specifically.
The first thing that he mentioned specifically
is the doctrine of Balaam.
It says this in verse number 14,
because thou hast there them that hold
the doctrine of Balaam,
who taught Balak to cast a stumbling block
before the children of Israel
to eat things sacrificed unto idols
and to commit fornication.
Now it's kind of interesting
because here in Revelation chapter two
in verse number 14,
it refers to this situation
as being the doctrine of Balaam.
In second Peter chapter two in verse number 15,
the Bible refers to it as being the way of Balaam.
And in Jude verse number 11,
the Bible refers to it as being the error of Balaam.
But here we find that God refers to this teaching,
this doctrine, and he refers to it
as being the doctrine of Balaam.
And there were some there that held,
it says that thou hast there
them that hold the doctrine of Balaam.
So if we find that Jesus is referencing
to this church in Revelation,
this church in Pergamos about this doctrine of Balaam,
we ought to know what that is.
Begin to read about that in Numbers chapter 22 through 25.
We won't read all of that obviously,
but turn back if you will to Numbers chapter 25.
Numbers chapter 25, and I want you to notice some things.
In beginning in chapter 22,
we won't have time to go through it,
but we find that Balaam is called
in order to curse the people of God.
We find that he blesses the people of God,
he does not curse them.
And there's some very important things
that we learn through that process.
But we come to chapter 25,
and it's here in chapter 25
that God tells us what the children of Israel did.
And then it's not until chapter 31
that the Bible gives us the reason
by which they did what they did in chapter 25.
So we're gonna read in chapter 25
what the children of Israel did,
then we're gonna go over to chapter 31
and understand the counsel that Balaam gave.
In chapter 25, in verse number one,
the Bible says,
and Israel abode in Shittim,
and the people began to commit whoredom
with the daughters of Moab.
And they called the people
unto the sacrifice of their gods,
and the people did eat and bowed down to their gods.
And Israel joined himself unto Baal Peor,
and the anger of the Lord was kindled against Israel.
Now those are interesting verses of scripture
when you're reading through the dialogue
and you're reading about Balaam being called by Balak
to curse the people of God,
and he cannot curse them, and he blesses them,
and Balak is beside himself.
And you go through chapter 22 and 23 and 24,
and you're reading all of these iterations
of what's going on,
and you're reading even in chapter 24,
in verse number 10,
it says that Balak's anger was kindled against Balaam.
Why?
Because this was not what he brought them here for.
And then all of a sudden,
you start reading chapter 25,
and you say, what happened?
What is going on?
How is it that they committed whoredom
with the daughters of Moab?
How is it that they're eating the sacrifice of their gods,
and they ate, and they're bowing down to their gods?
What in the world?
And you look at chapter 31,
and God gives us insight here in verses 15 and 16
with regard to the counsel of Balaam.
And notice what the Bible says
in numbers 31 in verse 15,
"'And Moses said unto them,
"'Have you saved all the women alive?
"'Behold, these caused the children of Israel,
"'through the counsel of Balaam,
"'to commit trespass against the Lord
"'in the matter of Peor.'"
And there was a plague among the congregation of the Lord.
In verse 16 of numbers 31,
it's referring to that event that we just read
in chapter 25, verses one through three.
And we find that God reveals to us
that it was through the counsel of Balaam.
Let me share something with you
that I think is vitally important
that we understand this evening.
You understand tonight that the enemy, our enemy,
he cannot curse us.
God has blessed us.
We are blessed.
We are the people of God.
We are the children of God.
He cannot curse us.
But you know what he can do?
He can do the same thing that Balaam did
in giving this counsel.
Since the enemy cannot curse the people of God,
he sought to corrupt the people of God through compromise.
And here's what happens.
Because of the corruption and the compromise,
the curse comes.
Because of the compromise and the corruption,
Balaam could not curse the people of God.
Why?
Because they had been blessed by God.
But he gives them counsel to do something
that was in violation to God's law
that would bring forth the judgment of God.
Do you get that tonight?
He could not curse them.
What did Balaam want?
Balaam wanted them to be destroyed.
Balaam says, I can't do it because God's blessed them.
But you know what?
If you corrupt them,
because notice what the Bible says at the end
of verse number three in chapter 25,
the Lord was kindled,
the anger of the Lord was kindled against Israel.
Why was God's anger kindled against his people?
Because they corrupted themselves.
Because they violated the truth of God's word.
You know, no one can make you sin.
But when you sin, you forfeit the blessing of God.
And you deal with judgment.
And so there's this doctrine of Balaam
that's going on here in the church in Pergamos.
There were some that held to this doctrine of Balaam.
And it all has to do with compromise and corruption.
And as we look at the connection between verse 14 and 15,
we see what's happening here in Pergamos
as we begin to understand how they began to falter.
And there's compromise and there's corruption
because not only the doctrine of Balaam,
but in verse 15 of Revelation two, the Bible says,
so hast thou also them that hold the doctrine
of the Nicolaitans, which thing I hate.
Now, in the city of Ephesus,
according to chapter two in verse number six
here in Revelation,
we read of the deeds of the Nicolaitans.
But now we're reading of the doctrine of the Nicolaitans.
And I understand that it's a different city,
it's a different place.
But I want to remind you of the biblical truth
from Galatians five, nine,
that a little leaven leaveneth the whole lump.
You know, sin is a slippery slope and so is compromise.
You begin to just compromise a little bit here
and a little bit there,
and you change and blur the line here and there.
And before long, it just kind of spirals out of control.
Compromise is a dangerous thing.
And so we find as we begin to think about
this sect, if you will,
that were referred to as the Nicolaitans,
it's believed that this was a sect of individuals there
that advocated.
for this thought of what we refer to as antinomianism.
This idea of antinomianism is really this idea
that we have a license to live however we wanna live.
That we're saved by grace
and therefore we can just do whatever.
I mean, forget about the standards.
Not only do we lower the standards,
but man, we should just eliminate the standards altogether.
But I wanna remind you what Paul said in Romans chapter six.
He said, should we sin that grace may abound?
What's the answer?
God forbid.
Is that not what Paul says
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God
in Romans chapter six?
And so we find that here when we look at this situation
of the faltering church in Pergamos
and we find that they were flourishing.
I mean, they did some things good,
but there were some people within the church.
There were some in verse number 14,
because thou hast there them that hold the doctrine of Balaam
in verse number 15,
so has now also them that hold
the doctrine of the Nicolaitans.
And so there were some within the congregation,
not all of them,
but there were some within the congregation
that were holding to this doctrine of Balaam,
that were holding to this doctrine of the Nicolaitans.
And can I share with you this evening
that they don't just hold it to themselves,
they begin to influence other people.
They begin to peddle their doctrine.
They begin to try to find others to share this with.
And we find that as we're looking at this church
in Pergamos and we're looking at what's happening,
that we have to be so careful
when it comes to this idea of compromise.
It's absolutely imperative that we resist compromise.
It doesn't mean that we do not seek to do various things
just because maybe something's new or whatever it may be,
but the reality is that we do not wanna forfeit
the blessing of God in order to appease
some group of people.
And as we look here at this text of scripture
and begin to think about where they were located,
and then even beginning to try to make some application
for us this evening,
we understand that the temptation
will always exist to compromise.
The temptation will always exist to compromise.
I have followed up with visitors
that have come to our church over the years.
I've been here for 13 and a half years.
I've followed up with countless visitors.
And there's been some visitors that I've gone to
and we've sat with and we visited with,
and they say, well, if you just change that position
on the King James Bible, we'd come back to your church.
Sorry, we're not gonna change our position
on the King James Bible so that you would come
to our church.
If you just get some different music,
if you just do this, if you just do that,
the reality is that there's always a temptation
to compromise.
And here's what happens, it can almost become pragmatic
where we get that idea that, well, if we do this,
if we just kind of lower this,
if we change this a little bit,
then we'll be able to reach more people.
And so we wanna reach more people,
and so therefore we're going to falter on this area here
because we wanna reach more people.
And there's always a temptation to compromise.
It always exists.
It exists in your home.
It exists with your family.
It exists with your children.
There's always a temptation to compromise.
How do we resist compromise?
How do we avoid compromise?
Not that we just wanna stay in some era
of we're just not willing to be up with the times
or whatever it may be.
No, we don't wanna compromise.
There's a difference.
I'll use the word relevant.
I use it appropriately this evening.
There's a difference between being relevant
and compromising.
We put electricity in our building
because it's actually kind of comfortable.
It's not really a compromise.
By the way, that was done well before any of us were here,
but I'm thankful that it was done, aren't you?
Come on.
I'm thankful for indoor plumbing, right?
Aren't you?
Especially on a night like tonight.
You gotta, yeah, come on.
I mean, just be, that's not the same as compromise.
So how do we resist it?
How do we avoid it as a church, as a family?
What do we do?
We have to know the truth of God's word.
And we have to be students of the word of God.
We have to commit ourselves to following the principles
that are contained within God's word.
Here's what God's word says,
and here's how we're gonna go.
And here's the reality is that you'll be pushed
and I'll be pushed.
And there are times in which we look to the truth
of God's word and we desire that we want to stay true
to God's word.
We make that commitment that I wanna be true
to the principles that God has laid forth in his word,
and we wanna follow the way of the Lord.
But there's always gonna be a temptation to compromise.
In a city like Pergamos, with all that was going on
and all the pressures that a church would face
and all of the tribulation that they were dealing with,
the persecution that they were facing,
I think it could kind of be easy to be like,
yeah, let's just kind of bend a little bit right here.
Let's just kind of, but no, we don't wanna do that.
And here the Lord says, I have a few things against thee.
Why?
Well, because there are some that have,
they hold to the doctrine of Balaam.
There are some there that hold the doctrine
of the Nicolaitans.
And so he gives, as he's evaluating the church,
and even as we've mentioned for our own church this evening,
though Fellowship Baptist Church in Oakton
is not in Revelation two or three,
we take these passages of scripture and we say,
what would God say of us?
How would God evaluate us?
Well, in each of the churches that God corrects,
he also gives them counsel
to be able to correct their course.
I've termed it this way, number three tonight,
the formula for revival, the formula for revival.
The Lord exposes our failures,
those areas where we're faltering
as we see in verse 14 and 15.
So that we would address it, so that we deal with it.
See, because we can deceive ourselves.
We can sit back and say, man, everything's going great.
But no, the Lord steps in and he gives an evaluation.
He provides the truth with regard to where we stand.
And then he provides the formula for revival.
Notice in one word in verse 16, repent.
Repent.
You know what every church
and what every believer needs to do is agree with God.
To agree with God.
We're not gonna argue with God.
We're not gonna say, no, that's not how it is.
No, that's not true.
That's a bad evaluation.
No, God's way is true and God's word is true.
And what God says is fact.
And he says, repent.
You must change your mind,
which will result in a change of direction.
You must return to the Lord's way and refuse compromise.
There's no middle ground here.
It's repent.
God's way is always right.
100% of the time.
God's way is perfect.
And so what we must do is align our thinking
with God's thinking.
The pragmatic approach says, but we're trying,
look, we're trying to reach more people
or we're trying to do this or we're trying to do that.
And God says, repent.
Do God's work God's way.
No compromise.
Notice the or else in verse number 16.
He says, repent or else I will come unto thee quickly
and will fight against them with the sword of my mouth.
You think God is serious about his church?
I believe he is.
He loved the church and he gave himself for it.
The church is the bride of Christ.
The church is the greatest organism.
I like to use that word, not organization
because it's living.
The church is the greatest organism on the planet earth.
It's the pillar and ground of the truth.
And the Lord Jesus Christ is serious.
And he says, repent.
And if not, or else I will,
notice he says, I will come unto thee quickly.
God will give us a little space to repent.
I'm thankful for God's grace and his mercy
and his long suffering.
But he says, here's the evaluation.
Change your way.
He doesn't say, here's the evaluation
and we'll come back in a year and reevaluate.
No.
here's the evaluation, repent, get it straight, get it right. And he says this
or else I will come unto thee quickly and will fight against them with the
sword of my mouth. I begin to think about that. So often we rejoice in the
promises that God gives, if God be for us who can be against us. Aren't you
thankful for that wonderful promise? But I'm reminded this evening that as
Jeremiah was prophesying to the people of Judah and they send and they say
will God fight for us? He says no, God's gonna fight against us. Why was God
gonna fight against his own people? Because of their disobedience, their sin,
their idolatry. And I don't want to be in a place where where it would be that
God would fight against with the sword of his mouth. Those people, those groups
that were in the church that held to the doctrine of Balaam, to the doctrine of
the Nicolaitans, they had to be dealt with. It had to be addressed. There needed
to be repentance. These letters that God gives to these churches, they're serious.
Why? Because God's church is precious and God is concerned about the holiness of
his people and the holiness of his church. The church is not a club. It's the body of
Christ and we're to follow God's way. And the Bible says in verse 17 as we
end each of these letters in the similar fashion, the consistency in each
of them, I know thy works. But also as we read in verse 17, he that hath an ear, let
him hear what the Spirit saith unto, remember, the churches, plural. I believe
that these seven churches that are addressed, this letter would go and they
would read not only their own evaluation, but they would read the evaluations of
the others. Why? Because he that hath an ear, let him hear. Listen, I can learn
from the evaluation that God gives us, but we can learn from the evaluation that God
gives another church. And here, as we have Revelation 2 and 3, there are seven
churches that we can learn from. And God has preserved it for all of church history
so that we could have these letters, so that we could learn the lessons that we
need to learn, that we could be aware of the danger of compromise, that we could
understand how that the enemy wants us to corrupt, he wants us to disobey so that
we would be judged, so that we would lose the good hand of God's favor in our
lives, in our ministry. And he says this, to him that overcometh. I've mentioned in
the previous lessons, as we look at that phrase in these particular letters, that
that's the one that is victorious. I'm thankful even for the truth, and we sang
about this the other night in 1 John chapter number 5, where the Bible says in
verse number 4, for whatsoever is born of God overcometh the world, and this is the
victory that overcometh the world, even our faith. I'm thankful that we are more
than conquerors through Christ. I'm thankful that we are on the winning side,
that we're victorious. But we understand that as we look here at this thought of
being victorious and dealing with the instruction, the counsel that God has
given, that he provides here. Remember to the church in Smyrna, he said, he that
overcomes shall not be hurt of the second death. What a blessing to know that I'm
saved by the grace of God. I'm on, I'm born again, I'm on the winning side, and
the second death hath no power over me, according to Revelation 20. But here I
want you to notice that God says three things to the one that's victorious, that
overcomes. It says that I will give to eat of the hidden manna, of the hidden
manna. It's kind of interesting phraseology. We're familiar with manna in
the Old Testament. We're familiar with how God miraculously sent bread from
heaven to feed his people, and how if they took up too much on a particular
day, that it would breed worms, and it would stink, and it would spoil. But then
on a particular day, because they would not go out on the Sabbath, they would
have to gather twice as much. And even in so doing, it did not spoil, it did not
rot, it did not stink, did not breed worms. And so we're familiar with the manna of
that God sent from heaven to feed his people, but now we look here and the
Bible says that I will give to eat of the hidden manna. I believe that
God is referring here to the spiritual provision through his word. Let me say it
this way, I believe what God is telling us is that his word is sufficient. His
word is sufficient. Let me say it this way, because he's dealing with compromise,
he's dealing with the the doctrine of Balaam, the doctrine of the Nicolaitans,
and there's this idea that there is something that I might gain through
compromise. But can I tell you that you're not going to gain anything
through compromise. God's word is sufficient, and God has given to us his
word, and we must follow what he's given to us. We must take the truth that he's
provided to us, and we must stand on the truth, and we must live the truth. I don't
need, I am not going to gain anything through compromise, and neither will you.
I think the result of compromise in most cases would be regret, would be
regret. Because you know when you compromise, it doesn't take too long
before you start seeing the fruit of the compromise. When we begin to see the
fruit of the compromise, that's when the regret sets in. So this evening he says
to him that overcometh will I give to eat of the hidden manna. Notice this, and
we'll give him a white stone. It's kind of interesting, and there's not any clear
100% dogmatic kind of position here, but I believe that this white stone, you look
at some historical things, and there's really a number of ideas with regard to
the significance of a white stone. But I think what really makes the most sense
as you look here, and you see what the Lord is saying, is it would represent
pardon and forgiveness. Oftentimes someone that was acquitted of a crime in
this era, they would be given a white stone to show that they were pardoned.
I'm thankful this morning, this evening, excuse me, that I have been
pardoned. I've been forgiven. Think about the truth of being forgiven. I'm
forgiven forever. I don't have the guilt, the weight of that guilt of my sin. Why?
Because I've been forgiven. And if you've been forgiven this evening, you
understand as well the significance of that, and what a blessing it is. And he
says that I'll give him a white stone. But then he says this, and in the
stone a new name written, which no man knoweth, saving he that receiveth it. I
know that we sing that song, there's a new name written down in glory, and it's
mine, oh yes it's mine. We begin to look at this phraseology and thinking about
that white stone representing pardon and forgiveness, but then also noticing where
the Bible says that, and in the stone a new name written, which no man knoweth,
saving he that receiveth it. You know that in some parts of the world, even
still today, but certainly throughout history, when someone came to Christ, they
would literally change their name. And it still happens today, especially in
some countries of certain religious, world religions, where they have names
that are associated very closely with their particular world religion. They
come to Christ and they'll change their name. Why? Because it's a new identity.
Begin to think about this, and of course in our culture, most of us would not ever
consider having a change of name because of coming to Christ, but the
reality is that we do have a new name. I now belong to Jesus. God is now my
Father. Amen? But as many as received Him, to them gave He power to become the sons
of God. Listen, I've been adopted into the family of God. Aren't you thankful for
the truth of adoption? Now here's something that's amazing. I've never gone
through the process of adoption personally, but I know people that have
personally. You know what happens after they go through the process of adoption?
There comes a day. You know what happens in that day? They get a new name. Yeah? They
get a new name. And I know some folks that
that the process is lengthy.
And unfortunately in America today,
the process is expensive, that process of adoption.
But I know folks, relatives and a close pastor friend,
even here in Virginia,
that have gone through this process of adoption
and they get so excited about that day
that they'll go to the courthouse
and everything will be made official
because there's this lengthy period of time.
And yes, we've had our daughter in our home
for however long we have,
but now it's the day that it's gonna be official
and the name has changed.
To what name?
Well, to the name of the parents,
the new parents, the adopted parents.
And I think about the truth that God gives us in his word
when he talks about being adopted in the family of God.
He's given us a new name, a new identity.
I think this evening about the wonderful truth
that as believers, as Christians,
our identity is in Christ.
Our identity is in Christ.
Yes, we can talk about our family name.
Yes, we can talk about our citizenship
and so on and so forth.
But the reality is that first,
the primary identity for each child of God
is that I'm a Christian.
I belong to Christ.
And he says,
not only will I give him to eat of the hidden manna,
I'll give him a white stone
and then the stone a name written,
which no man knoweth,
saving he that receiveth it.
I wonder if you remember when you first got saved
and maybe somebody said something like this to you,
now you're a Christian.
Now you're a Christian.
And I don't know if that was said to you
or what significance it would have had immediately.
But as you look back and you begin to understand that,
it's significant.
I'm a Christian.
What does it mean to be a Christian?
We use the word in the New Testament, saint.
One who is in Christ and whom Christ dwells.
Wow, it's amazing.
I remember when my dad got saved.
Here's what some of the people said.
Well, Chris got religion, it will wear off.
No, he got a new name.
He got saved, he got born again.
And you know what?
Other people may not have understood
that new name Christian, but he understood.
And tonight, when we acknowledge the fact
that we've been saved by the grace of God
and we've been pardoned and we have forgiveness
and we have a new name that's written,
that I am a Christian and the world may not understand that.
The world might think, oh, that just means you're religious.
No, it doesn't mean I'm religious.
I told a man I was knocking on his door
and he answered the door.
I think Tim, maybe Ronnie was with me knocking door.
And he said, oh, I don't like religion.
I said, neither do I.
And he looked at me like I was crazy
because I had just announced
that I was from Fellowship Baptist Church.
I don't like religion, why?
Because religion condemns.
It's a relationship with the Lord Jesus Christ
that gives life and purpose.
And we understand it tonight,
but notice it says, which no man knoweth saving he
that receiveth it.
You try to explain to lost relatives and lost coworkers
what Christ did for you and they don't get it
because they don't have it.
Does that make sense?
And we get it because we have it.
And we can rejoice tonight.
Listen, the church in Pergamos, they were doing some things.
They were a light in a dark place.
They were faithful.
But there was some compromise that was creeping in.
There was some corruption that was coming in.
And Jesus says, hey, listen, repent.
It's there.
I know it.
I see it.
I'm telling you, there are some that are there
that hold the doctrine of Balaam
and the doctrine of the Nicolaitans.
And if you don't repent, I'm gonna come and judge.
This evening, as we evaluate the church in Pergamos,
we can take this admonition in charge
and we can say, hey, listen, we need to keep on doing right
and we need to know the principles of God's word
so that we can resist and avoid compromise
so that we can continue to have the blessing of God
upon our lives individually, in our families
and in our church so that God would be glorified.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for your word.
I thank you for this letter, the church in Pergamos.
I thank you, God, for what you have revealed
to us through it.
And I pray that you'd help us to take heed.
I pray that tonight, Lord, you would help us
to evaluate and examine our own lives
in light of this letter to the church in Pergamos.
Lord, help us as we acknowledge tonight
that the temptation for compromise will always exist,
but God, help us to stay true to you and to your word.
Help us, Lord, to resist and avoid compromise
so that we might continue to have the blessing of God
upon our lives.
Well, thank you for every decision made
for it's in Christ's name we pray, amen.