And as you're turning to the book of 1 Thessalonians,
you'll be mindful that the Lord allowed the Apostle Paul
and his team to travel to the city of Thessalonica.
It was during the second missionary journey
in which God allowed them to go to this particular city.
And we find that as they arrived to the city,
we find the work that was done.
And if you were to read Acts chapter number 17,
you'll have an opportunity to read the record
that God gives us of their entrance into that city
and their preaching of the gospel.
And we understand that as we read the passage
in Acts chapter number 17,
that the time that they were able to spend
in the city of Thessalonica was brief.
It was cut short from a human's perspective, if you will,
due to the opposition to the gospel.
We understand that on this second missionary journey,
there were some that even as Paul and his team
arrived in Thessalonica,
there were some from other cities
that did not like the message
in which they were preaching that would come
and cause problems for Paul and his team
there in the city of Thessalonica.
And we know that every time you attempt
to do a work for God, there will be opposition.
And they face that opposition,
but it's interesting and exciting to understand
that just after a brief period of time
in the city of Thessalonica,
that a church was established.
And we find that that church was established.
And as you examine the communication
that God allows Paul to give to this church
that's part of the canon of scripture,
we understand all scripture is given by inspiration of God.
As you study 1 and 2 Thessalonians,
and really in particular as our focus today
will be on the book of 1 Thessalonians,
you have the opportunity to really see
the way in which Paul and the believers in this church
had a close relationship.
God allowed them to have a bind,
one with another to have this just tight relationship.
And we find that as we look at the book of 1 Thessalonians,
I'm mindful this morning, and you know as well
that this book is written to a local church.
It's written to a body of believers.
And it is written from,
understood under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit,
but it is written from a church leader,
from the Apostle Paul.
And we find that as Paul is writing this,
and he would reveal to us through various means
the relationship that they held.
I'd like to use an expression that he uses
in 1 Thessalonians 2 and verse number 11 this morning,
and really will serve as our title.
Look there at 1 Thessalonians 2 and verse number 11.
The Bible says, as ye know,
how we exhorted and comforted and charged every one of you,
then notice this phrase,
as a father doth his children.
As a father doth his children.
As we look at that phrase and understand that again,
as I mentioned during our announcement time this morning,
that we'll have a part one this morning,
and a part two this evening,
having the same title,
as a father doth his children, part one and part two.
As we begin to look at this short book,
we will find, and I know there's a lot more
than what we'll look at today,
but for sake of getting through it in one day,
and two messages,
I'd like to examine five principles
that I believe if we would implement these five principles,
that it will lead us to reaching the ultimate goal
that is noted in verse number 12 of the same chapter.
Paul says at the end of verse number 11,
as a father doth his children,
then notice what the ultimate goal is,
that ye would walk worthy of God,
who hath called you unto His kingdom and glory.
You understand that children are not going to
just by chance walk worthy of God?
New believers are not going to, by chance,
walk worthy of God.
And as we examine the passage of Scripture
both this morning and this evening,
and really we're gonna look at the entire book,
and kinda just look at a variety of verses
throughout the book of 1 Thessalonians,
take an overview if you will.
As we look at this book
and think of this truth this morning,
I want us to look at it from two perspectives.
Number one, from a father to a child.
That parental relationship,
we don't know and we find here that Paul,
as he would use this expression,
as a father doth his children,
he's not explicitly giving instruction
in the book of 1 Thessalonians to dads
on how they are to work and minister to their children.
Though the Bible contains much information about parenting
and much truth is contained therein,
we find that Paul is writing to a church.
But he says in this same manner,
as a father doth his children,
this is how we were ministering.
What a great truth.
And I find that not only would we look at it this morning
from the perspective of a father to a child,
but I'd encourage you this morning
to look at it from a mature believer to a growing believer.
A mature believer to a growing believer.
You understand this morning that you may be here
and you say, I'm not a father, turn off the preacher.
No, no, no, no.
The word of God is applicable for all of us.
And we find that the principles
that we'll look at this morning,
as we would examine them from these two perspectives,
I believe it will help us.
And as we begin to look at the passage,
I just have two thoughts for you this morning,
and then we'll look at three thoughts this evening.
But if you're taking notes,
number one, first principle
that I believe we need to implement in our lives,
number one, impart biblical truth.
Impart biblical truth.
As Paul arrives into the city of Thessalonica,
as the word of God would give us the record of that
in Acts chapter number 17,
we find at the end of verse number two
that the Bible says this,
that he reasoned with them out of the Scriptures.
And the importance of imparting biblical truth,
oh, it's always been important,
but we find in the day and age in which we're living,
in the hour in which we're facing this morning,
oh, it is imperative that we, as the people of God,
would impart biblical truth.
It was not necessary for Paul
to enter into the city of Thessalonica
and share his own opinions.
It was not necessary for him to come there
and try to make them what he was.
No, he went there and he imparted biblical truth.
The book that we hold in our hands this morning
is the word of God.
It's a living book.
The Bible is quick and powerful
and sharper than any two-edged sword.
We understand this morning
that there are some that do not like the Bible.
There are some that would like to outlaw
the truth of God's Word
and to say that if you were to preach or teach
or even just share a truth from the Word of God
that it could be constituted as being hate speech.
But the Word of God is truth.
The Word of God is powerful.
And we must impart biblical truth.
Notice if you turn back to the book of Psalms,
and we're gonna look at a number of verses
and then make our way back to the book of 1 Thessalonians
and look at what Paul is doing
with these believers in Thessalonica
and be mindful of the truth that he says,
as a father doth his children,
practically speaking,
Psalm 19 as you're turning there,
practically speaking as Paul is ministering
to these believers in Thessalonica,
it is that second of the relationships that I mentioned
that we'd like to look at it from these perspectives.
It's a mature believer to a growing believer.
We find this morning in Psalm 19
what a powerful passage of Scripture
beginning in verse number seven.
The Bible says this,
the law of the Lord is perfect.
Converting the soul,
the testimony of the Lord is sure,
making wise the simple.
The statutes of the Lord are right,
rejoicing the heart.
The commandment of the Lord is pure,
enlightening the eyes.
The fear of the Lord is clean,
enduring forever.
The judgments of the Lord are true
and righteous altogether.
Notice verse number 10,
more to be desired are they than gold,
yea, than much fine gold,
sweeter also than honey in the honeycomb.
I wonder this morning,
how do we value the Word of God?
Is it more precious to us than gold?
Yea, than much fine gold?
Notice in verse number 11 of the same passage,
the Bible says,
moreover, in addition to the truth
that's already been given,
moreover, by them, by the law of the Lord,
by the Word of God,
is thy servant warned.
And in keeping of them,
there is great reward.
Psalm 119, on two occasions,
and really, you can look at the entirety of Psalm 119
and see the value of the Word of God
and the importance of imparting biblical truth,
but I'll take just two verses from Psalm 119 this morning.
Verse number 72,
notice what the psalmist says here
in Psalm 119 in verse number 72.
The law of thy mouth is better unto me
than thousands of gold and silver.
I love the expression of the psalmist.
I mean, he understood the value of the law of the Lord,
of the truth that we have in our hands this morning.
Verse 127, the psalmist says here,
therefore, I love thy commandments above gold,
yea, above fine gold.
We have a society.
in which their value system is different than our value system or at least it
should be amen our value system should differ from the value system of the
world in which we live and we think about the preciousness of the Word of
God and we think about the importance of imparting biblical truth the reality
this morning is that we have the opportunity to impart truth to a future
generation as fathers to impart truth to your children as mature believers to
impart truth to growing believers and oh how important that we're engaged in this
work certainly there are people that buy gifts and we like to shower our children
with gifts and show them nice things and that's wonderful but if it's in place of
giving them the truth of this book it's not what we're supposed to be doing
impart biblical truth the the wise man Solomon notes in Proverbs 23 and verse
23 buy the truth and sell it not I mean get understanding get wisdom you see it
all throughout the book of Proverbs and oh how precious the Word of God is in
Proverbs chapter number 30 the Bible speaks about the Word of God being pure
oh I'm so thankful for the Word of God Jesus Christ before he went to the cross
of Calvary he said sanctify them through thy word thy word is truth John 17 and
verse 17 as we look back to the book of First Thessalonians I want you to notice
several references in this chapter in this book with regard to the Apostle
Paul's relationship in his imparting of biblical truth to these believers in
Thessalonica and as he would write back to them this first letter we understand
there's a second letter that we hold as well that we can read and study from but
I want you to notice how that the Apostle Paul when he's writing under the
inspiration of the Holy Spirit this first letter this epistle back to the
church the believers in Thessalonica that he is rehearsing for us how he
imparted biblical truth we understand that the record in Acts tells us that he
reasoned with them out of the scriptures but here in First Thessalonians in
chapter 1 look at verse number 5 the Bible says this for our gospel came not
unto you in word only but also in power and in the Holy Ghost and in much
assurance as ye know what manner of men we were among you for your sake and you
became followers of us and of the Lord look at this having received the word in
much affliction with joy of the Holy Ghost when he says that they received
the word will notice as we continue to go through this book that he's very
clearly referring to the Word of God to the scriptures to that which he had
imparted to them and he says that they received the word in much affliction but
with joy of the Holy Ghost see they were dealing with some trials and some
difficulties I mentioned already by way of introduction the way that those folks
came into the city of Thessalonica and they were not happy that Paul and others
were going and sending forth the Word of God in fact it's in that passage of
Scripture in which they make the accusation the charge that these that
have turned the world upside down have come hither also they were preaching the
Word of God they were imparting biblical truth in chapter 2 in verse number 2
notice the Bible says but even after that we had suffered before and were
shamefully entreated notice this as you know at Philippi we know what happened
at Philippi in Acts chapter 16 you can read of that and that's what happened
just before they come to Thessalonica Paul and Silas remember they were
imprisoned and God worked miraculously and they had suffered and they had been
entreated shamefully entreated but notice where he says in verse number 2
we were bold in our God to speak unto you the gospel of God with much
contention though they had suffered though they had been shamefully
entreated though they dealt with opposition and difficulty Paul was
absolutely 100% confident of the importance of the need of imparting
biblical truth and he said though this cost me though I suffered for this when
we came to this new city when we came to you in Thessalonica we were bold in our
God to speak unto you the gospel of God with much contention to give the Word of
God we find in verse number 9 look down of the same chapter it says for you
remember brethren our labor and travail for laboring night and day because we
would not be chargeable unto any of you notice we preached unto you the gospel
of God verse number 13 for this cause also thank we God without ceasing
because when you received the Word of God which he heard of us you received
it not as the Word of men but as it is in truth the Word of God which
effectually worketh also in you that believe what a great verse of Scripture
Paul says to these believers he said that we thank God without ceasing by the
way we ought to be thankful when people receive biblical truth yes we're
thankful for the opportunity to impart impart biblical truth but when somebody
receives that biblical truth we begin to see people be doers of the word and not
hearers only people that begin to implement the Word of God in their lives
how it should bring joy to our hearts how it should cause us to rejoice and
thank God he says here because when you receive the Word of God which he heard
of us see Paul understood that God was using him and others that were there on
that missionary journey to impart this biblical truth and God will use you to
impart biblical truth as well yes fathers to your children but what about
the mature believer to the growing believer and by the way wherever you are
in your walk with God there's someone that's not as far along in the journey
that you can invest in and you can impart truth in you know why some people
kind of get forgive me why some people kind of get cranky because they're not
doing anything they just kind of get cranky you ever meet somebody that's
cranky man we get to impart truth biblical truth listen you can find
somebody that's not as far along on the journey as you are the importance is
that you're on your journey and you're walking with God and you're making that
progress and you come alongside someone else and you invest in them and you
impart biblical truth Paul says that you received it listen I'm thankful that
they were bold to preach the Word of God I'm thankful that even though they faced
opposition they still went forth and imparted biblical truth the church at
Thessalonica we've often mentioned over the years and many Bible commentators
will make the same observation that this church in Thessalonica is not a perfect
church because there's no such thing as a perfect church but this church in
Thessalonica is a model church you can find a lot of things in this book first
Thessalonians even in second Thessalonians that show how this is a
model church and see Paul as we read here in verse number 13 he said you
received the Word of God which you heard of us he said you received it not as it
is not as the Word of men but as it is in truth the Word of God now notice the
last phrase which effectually worketh also in you that believe this morning
would you be able to testify that God's Word has worked in your life would you
be able to stand up and say listen let me tell you how God's Word has changed
me let me tell you how God's Word has helped me in fact perhaps you were
reading your Bible this morning I hope you were and as you're reading your
Bible this morning God was helping you as you're reading his Word and as you're
getting fed and you're nourishing on the truth of God's Word this past week if
someone were to come to you and I mean stand face-to-face with you and say to
you today hey what did God show you from his Word this week would you have an
answer see we don't do that a whole lot because we don't want to embarrass
people or we don't want to be embarrassed mark you're laughing it's
right though isn't it when's the last time somebody came up to you and said
hey what's God teaching you in his Word how's God working in your life this week
because his Word effectually worketh in you which also believe in this morning
if you can testify that God's Word has has worked in you and it's made a
difference in your life then guess what it will work in somebody else's life and
you can look at somebody else you say oh they don't want the Word of God just
look at them just whatever listen God's Word is powerful and we claim the
promise of the Word of God that it will work it effectually worketh also in you
that believe this morning impart biblical truth oh it's imperative we are
living today in a society that could be described as being biblically ignorant
but if we'd be honest you know who's responsible for that the church you know
why Paul said that the church is the pillar and ground of the truth impart
biblical truth it's a it's a it's a truth a principle that that spans time
it was truthful for Paul and for
He's a believer in Thessalonica, but it's important it's truthful for us today.
Impart biblical truth.
Notice chapter number four.
In chapter number four, we're going to see kind of some of the specifics of biblical
truth that Paul gave.
Sometimes we like to speak in generalities, and sometimes the Word of God gets real specific.
Further in chapter number four, notice what he says, furthermore then, we beseech you
brethren and exhort you by the Lord Jesus that as you have received of us how you ought
to walk and to please God, so you would abound more and more.
When he speaks there in verse number one of you have received of us how you ought to walk
and to please God, he's speaking of the imparting of biblical truth.
They have received it.
The apostle Paul and his team, they went in there and they ministered and they served
and they gave the truth, and now he says, you have received of us how you ought to
walk and to please God.
And he says this, so you would abound more and more.
Notice this in verse number two.
For ye know what commandments we gave you by the Lord Jesus.
For this is the will of God, even your sanctification, that ye should abstain from fornication.
That every one of you should know how to possess his vessel in sanctification and honor,
not in the lust of concupiscence, even of the Gentiles which know not God, or even as
the Gentiles which know not God, that no man go beyond and defraud his brother in any manner,
because that the Lord is the avenger of all such, as we also have forewarned you and testified.
For God hath not called us unto uncleanness, but unto holiness.
Be therefore that despiseth, despiseth not man, but God, who hath also given unto us
his Holy Spirit.
Notice in verse number 11, and that you study to be quiet and to do your own business and
to work with your own hands as we commanded you.
Verse 12, that you walk honestly toward them that are without, that you may have lack of
nothing.
Skip over to chapter number 15, or chapter 5 if you will.
Look at verse number 15.
Actually look back up in verse number 14, this is now we exhort you brethren, warn them
that are unruly, comfort the feeble minded, support the weak, be patient toward all men,
see that none render evil for evil unto any man, but even follow that which is good, both
among yourselves and to all men.
Rejoice evermore, pray without ceasing, in everything give thanks, for this is the will
of God in Christ Jesus concerning you.
Watch not the spirit, despise not prophesying, prove all things, hold fast that which is
good, abstain from all appearance of evil.
The very God of peace sanctify you wholly, and I pray God your whole spirit, soul and
body be preserved blameless unto the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ.
He says, faithful is he that calleth you, who also will do it.
Brethren, pray for us.
And all the brethren with an holy kiss, I charge you by the Lord that this epistle
be read unto all the holy brethren, the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you, amen.
He got into some specifics, did he not?
We don't have time to develop all of it this morning.
But I want you to understand that he's imparting biblical truth.
He's saying, listen, God has given us the word and he's taught us how we're to live
and how we're to behave ourselves and what we're to do and what we're to avoid and he
gives them biblical truth.
And then he says this, in chapter number 5 and verse number 27, I charge you by the Lord
that this epistle be read unto all the holy brethren.
Why?
Because we want to keep imparting biblical truth.
Does that make sense?
We just keep giving the Bible, just keep preaching the Bible, just keep teaching the Bible.
I was talking to a pastor friend not long ago, and as we were talking, we were just
discussing some of the different studies that we're doing and some of the different
teaching and preaching and going through books and various studies and so on and so forth.
And we were just chatting and the conversation came up.
And for those of you that maybe somebody's watching that's an evangelist, I don't know
why they'd be watching, but they would maybe take offense to this.
But the pastor said something to the effect about how evangelism preaching is different
than pastoral preaching.
And sometimes as a pastor, you preach a passage of scripture and then someone says, hey, four
years ago you preached that same text of scripture.
And they'll say something to that regard and so on and so forth.
And we were just chatting and having some good fellowship about it and talking about
different studies and what have you.
And here's what he said to me, and it was so profound, it's just a simple truth, but
it was impactful.
This man's been in the ministry for about 20 years longer than I've been in the ministry.
And he said this.
He said, when that happens in my ministry, I always just simply think this thought.
When everyone sitting in the congregation obeys everything that I've preached, then
I'll stop preaching it.
And I said, you know what?
That's pretty good.
It's pretty good.
Because we're to be doers of the word and not hearers only.
Amen?
Listen, we never stop imparting biblical truth.
We got to keep giving it and keep giving it and keep giving it.
Not only as fathers to our children, but as mature believers to growing believers.
You say, well, I'm not a mature believer.
Well, you're a growing believer somewhere further down the road than someone else.
Amen?
Number two this morning, not only do we impart biblical truth, but number two, we model biblical
truth.
We model biblical truth.
Someone said, the message of your life has a far greater impact than the message of your
lips.
The message of your life has a far greater impact than the message of your lips.
I would say this this morning, that it's absolutely necessary that the message of our lips be
modeled in our lives.
That as we would impart biblical truth, that we also are living biblical truth.
That we're modeling that truth that we're teaching, that we're giving.
It's interesting, Paul says this in Romans chapter number two, as he's really giving
an indictment against the Jews in this passage of scripture.
He says this in verse number 21 of Romans chapter number two.
He says, what a great series of questions.
Thou therefore which teachest another, teachest not thyself.
It's a good question, is it not?
Thou therefore, Romans 2 verse 21, which teachest another, teachest not thyself.
Thou that preachest a man should not steal, dost thou steal?
That would be hypocritical, would it not?
Listen, don't steal, and then you're stealing.
Hypocrisy.
Verse 22, thou that sayest a man should not commit adultery, dost thou commit adultery?
Thou that abhorrest idols, dost thou commit sacrilege?
And so just in these two verses of scripture, he's giving a series of questions, and basically
what he's telling us as we study here and look at these verses of scripture, listen,
the message that we preach, the truth that we impart, we ought to be living that.
We ought to be modeling that.
How often we've heard people give testimony of someone that gave them some instruction,
and as they were giving the instruction, were violating the same instruction that they were
giving.
How impactful do you think that instruction is?
Don't do this while I'm doing it.
How far do you think that's going to go?
Not very far, right?
And so we find that it is imperative that we impart biblical truth, but it's just as
imperative that we model biblical truth.
Notice here in the book of 1 Thessalonians, as we've mentioned that we're going to kind
of take a survey here through this book, we looked at chapter 1 and verse number 5 earlier,
but look at it again with me.
In 1 Thessalonians 1 and verse number 5, Paul was faithful to impart biblical truth, but
we find also that he was faithful to model biblical truth.
It reminds me of the principle in Proverbs 23 and 26 when it says, my son, give me thine
heart and let thine eyes observe my ways.
I wonder this morning how many of us could really say to somebody, watch my life and
just do what I do.
Not in a prideful, arrogant way, but in a manner in which, listen, as best as we are
able, through the power of the Holy Spirit, through yielding to him, through walking in
the Spirit, not fulfilling the lust of the flesh, that we could say to somebody, just
model my behavior.
Paul said to the believers in Corinth, be followers of me, even also as I am of Christ.
Paul was following the Lord Jesus Christ.
Was he perfect?
No.
But he says, the things that you see in me do.
He's modeling biblical truth.
Notice in verse number 5 of 1 Thessalonians 1, it says this, for our gospel came not unto
you in word only, but also in power and in the Holy Ghost and in much assurance.
Notice this phrase, as ye know what manner of men we were among you for your sake.
Listen, these people in Thessalonica, they saw Paul and the others.
They observed what they were doing and how they were living.
And as we look at the truth of this brief time that Paul was able to minister among
these believers, not only was he imparting biblical truth, but he was
modeling biblical truth. And you think about the impact of the ministry
in Thessalonica and why, roughly, it appears as you read Acts 17, three weeks,
it was three Sabbath days that they reasoned together with them. How in the
world could a church be established and all of these things be done, and writing
back to these believers and encouraging them, instructing them,
because it was a message that was not lips only, it was a message that was
modeled by the life as well. Great impact. When you look at the testimony of the
Apostle Paul, you see a man that would go forth and boldly preach the Word of God,
but he lived the Word of God. Here in chapter number two, look down at
1 Thessalonians 2 and verse number 7, the Bible says this,
but we were gentle among you, even as a nurse cherisheth her children. Again, he's
saying to these believers in Thessalonica, listen, you know how we
behaved ourselves, you know how we acted, you know what we did. The reality is that
in chapter number three, he talks about, you remember. Listen, he's writing to
people that he ministered to. He can't pull the wool over their eyes. He's saying
to them, you know how we behaved ourselves, you know how we were gentle among you, even
as a nurse cherisheth her children. Look down, if you will, at verse number 10 of
1 Thessalonians 2, verse number 10. He says, ye are witnesses, and God also. Wow,
that is a weighty statement. Ye, believers in Thessalonica, that's who he's
writing to, right? Paul and Silvanus and Timotheus under the church of the
Thessalonians, verse number 1 of chapter 1. He says, ye are witnesses, and God also.
How wholly and justly and unblameably we behaved ourselves among you that believe.
Wow, what a great testimony. It's on the inspiration of the Holy Ghost, right? The
Word of God. And Paul says, listen, ye are witnesses, God also. God knows all things.
God sees all things. He says, and you understand what our behavior was. You understand how
we behaved ourselves among you that believe. He says, as the words that would be used to
describe their behavior, wholly, just, and unblameable. Wow. That's a fantastic testimony.
He says, not only did we impart biblical truth, but we modeled biblical truth. We didn't
just tell you to not do these things or to do these things, but we lived the Word of
God. We find here in verse number 11, he says, as ye know, we've used this as our title
this morning, the last phrase, but notice the phrase again. He says in verse 10, ye
are witnesses. He says in verse number 11, as ye know, how we exhorted and comforted
and charged every one of you as a father doth his children. This morning, to the dads, do
your children see you model biblical truth? Do your children observe you living a life
pleasing to God, a life that matches the message of your lips? But to the mature believer,
I wonder are there some growing believers that look at your life and see, this is someone
that gets it. This is someone that's doing it, that they're obeying the Word of God.
They're living the Word of God. I wonder this morning if we could make some of these same
statements that Paul makes. See, as we begin to think about this truth this morning, these
two principles, if you will, that we impart biblical truth, that we model biblical truth,
and keeping in mind all the while what that goal is, the goal is that ye, those that you're
ministering to, would walk worthy of God. And in order for me to achieve that goal,
in order for me to see my children, in order for me to see some younger growing believers
walk worthy of God, I need to be imparting truth and I need to be modeling truth, biblical
truth. It's absolutely imperative. We notice the example of Paul. Of course, we're looking
at it here in the book of 1 Thessalonians. But I want to remind you, if you turn back
in your Bibles just a few pages to Philippians chapter number 4, I want to remind you what
Paul said to the believers in Philippi. Again, Philippi is the city that he was able to enter
into and minister amongst before he got to Thessalonica. And we can read of the record
of this ministry in Acts chapter number 16. And as Paul, under the inspiration of the
Holy Spirit of God, would write back to the church in Philippi, he gives them great instruction.
He's writing from prison. He's talking about rejoicing evermore. Rejoice in the Lord,
O Lord, and again I say rejoice. By the way, Paul was rejoicing, even in his circumstances,
in his difficulties. I wonder this morning, as you think about the message of the book
of Philippians, rejoice, rejoice, rejoice. I wonder this morning about that Philippian
jailer when the book of Philippians was written and he read it. And he was the one that had
put them fast in the prison. But he heard them sing praises unto God. The Philippian
jailer got saved. He said, what must I do to be saved? Believe on the Lord Jesus Christ.
Amen? And we find that that Philippian jailer was saved. But when Paul is saying rejoice
in everything, rejoice in the Lord, O way, I believe that that Philippian jailer, he
could say, you know, in the terrible circumstances that Paul was in, he was rejoicing. He's
writing from prison. He says in the first chapter, the things that happened to me have
happened for the furtherance of the gospel. He's rejoicing. But notice what he says in
verse number nine of Philippians 4. Those things which ye have both learned and received
and heard. Now those first three phrases of verse nine would be our first point this
morning, impart biblical truth. Ye have received it, you've learned it, you've received it,
you've heard, but notice the last phrase, and seen in me do. The God of peace shall
be with you. Those things which I've imparted unto you, those things that you've learned,
you've received, and you've heard, but those things that I modeled, that you've seen in
me do. Have you ever been in a place where maybe you or maybe someone else that was in
your presence, your company, had a child that behaved in a certain manner that was embarrassing?
The parent, maybe you were in the situation, or maybe it was another parent, says, I don't
know where they learned that. You ever been in a situation like that? You say, well, if
I could be honest with you, I could probably help you understand where they learned that
from. Amen? Because you know what children do? They model the behavior they see. I'm
not saying 100% of the time, forever of their lives, but many times children model that
which they see. We impart Biblical truth, but we model Biblical truth. Listen, the example
of Paul is great, but we have a greater example, and that's the Lord Jesus Christ. Acts 1 says
this of the Lord Jesus Christ. Notice what the Word of God says in Acts 1. We'll be finishing
here in just a moment with this truth of the example of our wonderful Savior. Luke is writing
here and the Bible says this in Acts 1, in verse number 1, the former treaties have I
made, O Theophilus, of all that Jesus began, notice what it says, both to do and teach.
This morning we acknowledge and understand that Jesus is the master teacher. Many times
when we read the Gospel accounts, we don't even see all of what He was teaching, but
we'll maybe just read a phrase of He was preaching or He was teaching. He's the master teacher.
Nicodemus comes to Him by night. He says we know that thou art a teacher sent from God.
And we find that as we look at the truth that God gives us in His Word of the Gospel records
and we understand that these truths are given to us as the life and ministry of the Lord
Jesus Christ, that it was both to do and teach. It was imparting truth, but it was
also modeling truth. And Jesus says this, and of course we know that He is perfect and
that He is the perfect example. He says in John 8, in verse number 29, for I do always
those things that please Him. I do always those things that please Him. This morning
Jesus is our example. Peter says that Christ left us an example that we should follow His
steps.
And as we examine this morning, and we'll visit again this evening, the book of 1 Thessalonians,
with this thought in mind, as a father doth his children, and looking at it from really two
perspectives, from fathers to children, but then from a mature believer to a growing believer.
I'd ask you this question this morning in closing, or these two questions in closing this morning,
to whom are you imparting biblical truth? To whom are you imparting biblical truth?
If you don't have an answer for that question, I would encourage you to find someone to impart
biblical truth to. I would challenge you not to be satisfied with a no one answer,
because we ought to be imparting biblical truth. If you can't remember the last time that you've
had an opportunity to share biblical truth and impart it to someone, I would encourage you this
morning to ask God to help you to impart biblical truth. And then I wonder this morning, how are we
doing in the area of modeling biblical truth? How many people do we want to see observing our lives?
Can we say, as Paul said, that the things that you've seen in me do? I was teaching the teens
a couple of weeks ago, and I use really as a springboard verse of Scripture by which we'll
study throughout several weeks with the young people, this truth from 1 Samuel 16. And I won't
get into all of it, but Saul's dealing with an issue where he has an evil spirit that's troubling
him. And his counselors say, here's what we've got to do. We've got to find a man that can come in
and play, and man, this is going to be great. And they just go, okay, find him. And one of the
servants answered and said this in 1 Samuel 16, 18, just jot it down, and we can go back and read
it later. He says, behold, I have seen a son of Jesse, the Bethlehemite, that is cunning and
playing, and a mighty, valiant man, a man of war, prudent in matters, a comely person, and the Lord
is with him. You know what I told the young people on Wednesday evening? Same thing I'm going to tell
you now. I'm not sure that David even knew who this servant was. I'm not sure that David knew
the servant was watching him, observing his behavior. You know what I told the young people?
When somebody says, I'm watching you, we can behave a certain way,
because we know somebody's watching us. I don't think David knew that this servant was watching
him. When they said, go find a man, and that servant says, I've seen, I've seen a son of Jesse,
a Bethlehemite, and here's how he describes him. Wow. People are watching you. People are watching
me. A lot of people watch me. Seriously. I'm being honest, man. I'm not saying that pridefully,
I'm just saying, with a position comes just certain things come along with it.
But you know, people are watching you. That person at work, that person in your neighborhood,
we need to find somebody to impart biblical truth to, but we need to make sure we're modeling
biblical truth. First two principles. Three more tonight. Come back tonight.
Challenge you to come back. I really believe this morning that as we look at this, just an overview
of First Thessalonians, there's a lot more. I had a lot more in my notes that I could give you
principle-wise, but five of them that I really believe will go far if we implement them in our
lives to being able to see some people walk worthy of God. You know why? It's not going to happen by
chance or by accident. We have the purpose to impart and then model biblical truth.
Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. We thank you so much for the opportunity to gather
together, to honor fathers on this day, to rejoice in our relationship with you through the Lord
Jesus Christ. I'm challenged personally through the message of First Thessalonians,
the message from the perspective in which we've looked at it this morning.
God, I pray that we would not soon forget that which we've heard.
I pray that we'd truly allow the Holy Spirit of God to examine us. As we read in the end of First
Thessalonians 5, quench not the spirit. Grieve not the spirit, Paul says in another portion of
Scripture. Oh, God, I pray this morning that we'd be sensitive. We would not grieve nor quench
the Holy Spirit of God, but that we would be doers of the Word,
that we would understand the importance of imparting biblical truth.
If we're not imparting biblical truth, God, would you help us to recognize the need
and to engage in seeking earnestly to find someone that we can impart biblical truth to?
God, help us always to model biblical truth,
understanding that you see us at all times. There are many people that are observing us
and we don't even know. As a man of yesteryear said, sometimes the only Bible a lost man will
ever read is the life of a believer. How much truth, biblical truth are we modeling? Oh, God,
help us. Help us to do business with thee. Well, thank you for the work that you'll do. We pray
that you'd be glorified through every decision, for it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand
with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed, no one's looking around. Kimberly's going to play
quietly on the piano. Maybe this morning you want to come to this old-fashioned altar. Maybe you
want to ask God to help you to impart biblical truth. Maybe you need to ask God to help you to
model biblical truth. However it is that God may have worked in your heart and life this morning,
would you allow God to have his way? The altar is open as Kimberly plays.