We looked at this verse last week.
We're going to run over to the book of 1 Corinthians as soon as I read this verse.
And if you want to just start in 1 Corinthians, that's fine.
I'm just going to read Matthew 4 and verse 19 quickly and then get right into the message
this evening.
The Bible says this in Matthew 4 and 19, and He saith unto them, Follow Me, and I will
make you fishers of men.
I said this last week that our job is to follow Christ, and as we follow Him, He does a work
in us.
He said, I will make you fishers of men.
And no doubt as we yield ourselves to the Lord, as we allow Him to do a work in us,
we have to have a part in that, allowing Him to do the work.
But He said to the disciples that I will make you fishers of men.
And what a joy to know, to experience the work that Christ does within His people.
The Bible says that if any man be in Christ, he's a new creature.
Old things are passed away.
Behold, all things are become new.
We understand that we're to be conformed to the image of His dear Son.
We understand that we're to be like Christ, and He's doing a work in us.
We sing the song with the children often.
He's still working on me, and to make me what I ought to be.
And I wonder this evening if we would allow God to have His way that we could say that
we're following Christ, and He's making us fishers of men.
First Corinthians chapter 1, we're going to look at chapter 1 and 2 before we get into
the message this evening with some points, just some applicable type of thoughts for
you tonight.
But we understand, after looking at the message from last Sunday evening, that we should share
the gospel.
It is important that we understand our responsibility, not only our responsibility, but the privilege
that God has given us to be His spokespeople, to be His representatives.
And what a joy that is.
Next week we're going to go through the particular verses that we will use as we're seeking to
share the gospel.
Before we do that, however, I believe that it's important for us to understand how we
can get to the most important subject.
In other words, like, let me say it like this, often in life we can have conversations with
individuals and never actually talk about the Lord, yet alone address the subject of
the gospel.
And we can have conversations with people, we can maybe have the intentions that I want
to be able to share the gospel with this individual and we begin talking and we talk about sports
and we talk about the weather and we talk about politics and we talk about whatever
we talk about and the conversation ends and we walk away and we say, I never even shared
the most important thing that I could possibly share with that individual, never even bringing
up the subject.
As we look in the book of 1 Corinthians in chapter 1, I want you to see what Paul says,
and I'm going to read not the entirety of the chapter, but I'm going to read the last
portion of chapter 1 and into the beginning portion of chapter 2.
And I'm going to pick it up in verse number 15, the Bible says, lest any man should say
that I had baptized in my own name and I baptized also the household of Stephanas, besides I
know not whether I baptized any other.
Notice verse 17, for Christ sent me not to baptize, but to preach the gospel, not with
wisdom of words, lest the cross of Christ should be made of none effect.
Now remember that statement at the end of verse number 17, it's important for us to
recognize this, not with wisdom of words, lest the cross of Christ should be made of
none effect, not with wisdom of words.
Verse number 18, for the preaching of the cross is to them that perish, notice what
he says, foolishness, but unto us which are saved, it is the power of God.
It's the same message, but to those of us that have been saved by the grace of God,
that we've been saved and we know that heaven is our home, the preaching of the gospel is
the power of God.
But to a lost person, it's foolishness.
And God does a work, and it's the work of the Holy Spirit, not only in the life of the
individual that's saved, that's sharing the gospel, but in the life of the individual
that's hearing the gospel.
You understand you cannot use wisdom, the words that are of wisdom, to try to get somebody
saved.
No, the Holy Spirit of God has to do a work.
The Holy Spirit of God, His job, according to John 16, one of His ministries is to reprove
the world of sin and of righteousness and of judgment to come.
And we read that in John 16.
And so we find that the preaching of the cross is to them that perish, foolishness.
I've heard people that have mocked the gospel, they've mocked it, it doesn't make sense to
them.
They criticize it, and it's foolishness to them, but I want you to understand that it's
still the gospel that we're supposed to preach.
He said in verse number 17, for Christ sent me not to baptize, but to preach what?
To preach the gospel.
What is the gospel?
Well, the gospel, very simply, is the death, burial, and resurrection of Jesus Christ.
It is the good news.
Verse 19, for it is written, I will destroy the wisdom of the wise and will bring to nothing
the understanding of the prudent.
Where is the wise?
Where is the scribe?
Where is the disputer of this world?
Hath not God made foolish the wisdom of this world?
Do you remember what Romans 1 says, professing themselves to be wise, they became fools.
Verse 21, for after that, the wisdom of God, the world by wisdom knew not God.
It pleased God by the foolishness of preaching to save them that believe.
Verse 22, for the Jews require a sign and the Greeks seek after wisdom, but we preach
Christ crucified.
To the Jews, a stumbling block, and unto the Greeks, foolishness.
But unto them which are called, both Jews and Greeks, Christ, the power of God, and
the wisdom of God, because the foolishness of God is wiser than men, and the weakness
of God is stronger than men.
Isn't that encouraging?
Verse number 25, praise the Lord.
Verse 26, for ye see your calling, brethren, how that not many wise men after the flesh,
not many mighty, not many noble are called, but God hath chosen the foolish things of
the world to confound the wise, and God hath chosen the weak things of the world to confound
the things which are mighty, and base things of the world, and things which are despised
hath God chosen, yea, and things which are not to bring to naught things that are.
Why?
Why did God choose to work this way?
Why is it that God has revealed to Paul and now to the church in Corinth the way in which
he, God, is going to work?
Notice verse 29, that no flesh should glory in his presence, that no flesh should glory
in his presence.
It's all about Christ.
And we find that it says, verse 30, but of him are ye in Christ Jesus, who of God has
made unto us wisdom and righteousness and sanctification and redemption, that according
as it is written, he that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord.
It's a work that God does, not a work that you do, it's not a work that I do, it's a
work that God does, but God uses his people.
And when we're humble and we're understanding of how God works, it's amazing how God would
use us when we yield ourselves, when we follow him and we're walking in humility, we are
clothed with humility, as Peter says in 1 Peter 5, that we are able to see God do a
work in and through us and use us as instruments in his hand to reach others with the gospel.
Chapter two, notice in verse number one, and I, brethren, when I came unto you, came to
you, came not with excellency of speech or of wisdom, declaring unto you the testimony
of God, for I determined not to know anything among you save Jesus Christ and him crucified.
And I was with you in weakness and in fear and in much trembling, and my speech and my
preaching was not with enticing words of man's wisdom, but in demonstration of the spirit
and of power, that your faith should not stand in the wisdom of men, but in the power of
God.
Does this mean when we read the end of chapter one, the beginning of chapter number two,
does it mean that we should not be prepared, does it mean that we shouldn't go through
any preparation?
No, it doesn't mean that.
It simply means we must be more dependent on the Lord and the Holy Spirit than we are
on our preparation.
We understand that Ezra, the Bible describes him as being a ready scribe.
The Bible says in Ezra 7 and verse number 10 that he prepared his heart to seek and
to do and to teach in Israel statutes and judgments, and so he sought the Lord.
He was a ready scribe.
And you know it's interesting because what happened in the life of Ezra, if you were
to read beyond chapter seven and verse number 10 and you continue to read through the passage
of Scripture in the seventh chapter, you know what you find is that Ezra then had opportunity
to teach because he was a prepared, he was a ready scribe.
But we must recognize this evening that we're not going to see souls saved and lives changed
because simply or completely in our preparation, we must be dependent on the Holy Spirit of
God.
Seek to go with the words of wisdom, as he says in verse number four of chapter number
two, my speech and my preaching was not with enticing words of man's wisdom, but in demonstration
of the spirit and of power.
Why?
That your faith should not stand in the wisdom of men, but in the power of God.
Far too often, Christians have tried to win arguments instead of simply sharing the gospel.
And it's a grave danger that we make in trying to win arguments or argue somebody into heaven.
You can't argue anyone into heaven.
You know, there are times in which you could see and no doubt there's many of them that
are available that you could look at videos and what have you, where you can find a lost
person that is left in a position of not being able to give an answer.
In other words, if you were to rule from a perspective of who won the debate or who won
the argument, you would say, and side with the Christian.
But the lost person still didn't get saved.
So what's the goal?
Is the goal to win the debate, win the argument?
Or is the goal to see souls saved and lives changed?
And so we must understand, again, it's not saying that we should have no preparation,
it's just what is our approach when we're seeking to share the gospel with an individual?
Do we want that individual to look at us and say, wow, look at how much they know?
Can I tell you, if that's your goal, you're very unlikely to see anyone trust Christ as
their savior.
Because what's on display is you want people to see how well versed you are and how much
you know and how many answers you can give.
Look over, if you will, we looked at verses chapters one and two, turn over to chapter
number nine, if you will.
And I'm going to give you some more from here, and then I have a list of seven things,
and I'm just going to touch through them quickly, not going to spend a ton of time on them,
but really how it is that we can approach the subject of sharing the gospel and being
able to accomplish what we're seeking to accomplish.
In 1 Corinthians chapter number nine, in verse number 16, the Bible says, for though I preach
the gospel, I have nothing to glory of.
Isn't that a great perspective?
You know, the apostle Paul was used of God to see a number of churches planted, to see
a number of people come to Christ.
But he says, for though I preach the gospel, I have nothing to glory of, for necessity
is laid upon me, yea, woe is unto me if I preach not the gospel.
For if I do this thing willingly, verse 17, I have a reward, but if against my will a
dispensation of the gospel is committed unto me, what is my reward then?
Verily, that when I preach the gospel, I may make the gospel of Christ without charge,
that I abuse not my power in the gospel.
For though I be free from all men, yet have I made myself servant unto all, that I might
gain them more.
Now, Paul's going to say some things in the next few verses that are important for us
to understand how he's approaching this.
In verse 20, it says, unto the Jews I became as a Jew, that I might gain the Jews.
To them that are under the law is under the law, that I might gain them that are under
the law.
To them that are without law is without law.
And this I do for the gospel's sake, that I might be partaker thereof with you.
Now, we have to understand that as we look at verses 20, really 19 down through 22, and
look at what Paul says, and he summarizes it in the end of verse number 22, that I am
made all things to all men, that I might by all means save some.
This is not a verse, this is not a proof text that you go to, to prove compromise, to prove
ecumenical movement, and so on and so forth.
Paul is not saying that I'm going to abandon the truth of God's word so that I might be
able to try to reach somebody with the gospel, no.
He's saying that I don't want to be the stumbling block, I don't want to be in the way of anyone
being saved.
Does that make sense?
And so I'm going to become all things to all men, I'm going to try to seek to reach as
many people as I possibly can with the gospel, I don't want to get in the way, I don't want
to be the hindrance to an individual being saved, I'm going to go and preach the gospel.
And he says, and this I do for the gospel's sake, I said this last week, it's worth repeating
as we look at this portion of scripture, if you're saved by the grace of God this evening,
you're going to heaven, amen?
You believe that tonight?
If you're saved, you're going to heaven.
If you never lead somebody to Christ, or if the person you're working with doesn't trust
Christ, you're still going to heaven.
But the reality is that we want others to go to heaven with us.
We understand, listen, the alternative is the lake of fire.
It's not a good alternative.
Somebody said this, they said it this way, you must really hate people to not be willing
to tell them the truth of the gospel.
And that was just a very raw way in which the individual said it, but it really was
so impactful the way that they said it, because the reality is that if we know the truth of
the gospel, if we fail to share the gospel, and we're not taking advantage of the opportunity
that God gives us as he's put us into our path, crosses with that individual, then we
have this responsibility.
And if we don't give them the gospel, what is it that we don't understand?
What is it that we're fearful of?
Most times we're afraid of rejection, we're afraid that someone's going to get upset with
us.
I mentioned last week, there are times in which we shy away and we're fearful because
we may not know the answer.
Well, remember the verses that we looked at tonight in chapter one and two of 1 Corinthians,
you do not need to know every answer.
You are not going to know every answer.
And if you wait until you think you know every answer to try to share the gospel with someone,
you will be surprised that someone will ask you a question that you didn't prepare to
answer.
That's the way it works.
People come up with some really hypothetical, crazy, off the wall things.
They'll start talking to you about aliens, they'll start talking to you, I mean, they'll
just talk to you about all kinds, I'm telling you the truth.
Tim and I stood at a door three months ago and this, I can't even tell you what the guy
was talking about.
He was all over the board, man.
He was just, he was out there and he was just trying to get us distracted from being able
to share the truth of the gospel.
Remember the God of this world, little G, God of this world, he hath blinded the minds
of them which believe not, lest the light of the glorious gospel should shine in unto
them.
If our gospel be hid, it is hid to them that are lost.
And so if I desire, if I understand this evening that I should share the gospel and I say,
I want to be able to get to the subject.
I've been in so many cases, I've been in so many situations where I've just never been
able to actually get to the subject that I want to get to.
What are some practical ways?
What are some things that we can do to try to get to the gospel?
Let me say this.
Some of what I'm going to share with you tonight is really the context of, especially the first
point dealing with a door to door kind of a situation where you're knocking doors.
You understand when you go and knock a door, if you've never done it before, and I'll tell
you this just from practice, every time I do it, brother Mark, the first one is the
hardest one.
I don't know how you feel about it, but that first one, there's this kind of like emotion
that builds up in you of like, oh, what's going to happen?
What are they going to say?
And you say, but you're the pastor.
I'm a person.
I'm a human being.
Amen.
And that first door is always the hardest door.
And so this first thought, number one, if you're taking notes, how is it that we're
going to approach people with the gospel?
I try to encourage people, especially with door to door, is to be observant and find
some common ground.
You're knocking on a stranger's door.
They don't know who you are.
You don't know who they are.
They don't know you from anyone.
And here you are standing at their door, knocking at their door.
Now today, things are quite complicated.
I've shared this with some folks, and I feel like we need to try to be as creative as possible
and still within the bounds of scripture, but you know, it's very complicated today.
I would say probably 85% of the doors that we have knocked on in the last few months
have these fancy ring doorbells or some type of doorbell that's a smart doorbell.
They can see you and you can't see them, and they just don't come to the door.
They just have no interaction with you, or they'll come over the little thing and say,
can I help you?
And you say who you are, and they're like, just leave it at the door, right?
They're not interested in having conversation.
So if you can have conversation, if someone comes to the door and you're able to have
that conversation, I try to encourage people to be observant as they're even approaching
the door and find some common ground.
Ronnie and I were knocking doors a couple of weeks ago, and I noticed that on the porch
of the home that we were approaching, there was a flag that I did not recognize.
Now there were three flags on that particular home, and as the person came, I said, hey,
listen.
I said, I don't recognize that one flag.
I know the American flag, but what's that other flag?
And they got all excited.
Why?
Because it was the flag of their homeland.
It was the flag of their country, and they began to tell me about their flag and where
they were from.
I just was simply trying to find a common ground to try to bring the wall down a little
bit, if you understand what I mean.
If you've never knocked doors, you might not be able to understand what I mean.
to understand how that works,
but you're talking to a complete stranger.
They don't know, they think you have an agenda.
Why are you here?
What are you trying to get?
I mean, it can be really a difficulty,
and so I try to find some common ground.
Many times, if I find that there's a flag
that is a branch of the service,
I'll make a comment about, hey, did you serve in the,
fill in the blank, the Army, the Air Force,
whatever it is, thank you for your service.
And then very quickly, I mean,
that's just a quick kind of statement,
try to find some common ground.
We had some visitors that came for Easter
that we, Joseph and I, knocked their door
the day before Easter, and they came on Easter Sunday,
Resurrection Sunday, and we went to their door.
They had a little rock on their front porch that said,
you've entered Eagles territory,
and the Philadelphia Eagles, the emblem was there.
And so what did I do?
I said, hey, listen, I said, are you guys Eagles fans?
You're down here in Virginia, and you're fans of the Eagles?
And Carter's like, yeah, it doesn't matter
where you live, you can be an Eagles fan, amen?
And he's their big Eagles fan.
And I just tried to get a little common ground.
I don't wanna spend a ton of time there,
I don't wanna have a long discussion,
but I wanna find a little common ground
so that I can have some further conversation.
So then, very quickly, after I find a little common ground,
I would say number two, clearly introduce yourself.
Let the people know who you are, where you're from.
Don't shy away from the fact that you're
with Fellowship Baptist Church, that you're with the church.
They need to know who you are, why you're there.
You begin to kind of have that introduction personally,
and no one else would have this situation.
But me, I never introduce myself as the pastor, never.
I always introduce myself as Chris.
I don't, I never introduce myself as the pastor.
We were knocking doors down in Fairfax,
and after about six or seven minutes of talking to this guy,
he said, oh, you're the pastor?
And he ran over and turned his music down
and then shook my hand and was all,
and he was all, the whole, changed his whole demeanor.
And so I try to just be careful.
I just want, look, I'm just a person.
And I just introduce myself, I introduce whoever's with me.
And these are the first couple of points here, again,
with regard to if you're out and you're trying
to share the gospel with people that you don't know.
All right, if you're having some common ground,
it's a neighbor, it's a coworker,
obviously these points are not points
that would be applicable with regard
to that particular situation.
But now getting back to how it is
that we get to the subject of the gospel,
I believe it's important that we, number three,
ask questions, begin to ask some questions.
Oftentimes, I will begin asking someone
about their church background.
Many times today, people will say, I don't go to church,
I don't have any church affiliation,
and I'll maybe ask them something like this,
well, did you ever go to church?
Well, yeah, I went to church when I was a kid.
Oh, that's great, what church did you go to?
I'm asking questions, I'm showing, number four,
genuine interest, but I'm trying to get some information
so that I know how to give the conversation
or how to guide the conversation.
Can I say this, when you're asking those questions
and it goes hand in hand with showing genuine interest,
make sure that you're listening to the answers.
Get their name, use their name.
And when you get the answers to the question,
make sure that you let them know
that you're tracking with them
and you're having this interaction with them.
The reality this evening is that as we're asking
those questions and showing that interest,
we're gaining some level of being able to insert the gospel
and take the conversation to where we want it to go.
And so the thought that I have, number five,
again, if you're taking notes, stay on topic
and lead the conversation of the gospel.
Lead the conversation of the gospel.
Now, how does this work?
How is it that we have these interactions?
Many times I've been in situations
where I'm never able to actually get to the gospel.
The conversation, the person's not interested,
they don't give you but like four seconds,
they just don't wanna have it.
And so how do I get the topic?
How do I lead the conversation to the gospel
if I'm seeking to share the most important message
that I could ever share?
I'm going to take those opportunities
when it comes to asking about church,
if they say anything about church attendance.
Many times I've said something like this,
well, listen, it's important to go to church,
it's commendable to go to church,
but most importantly is knowing for sure
if you were to die that you'd go to heaven.
And you say, man, you just bring up the subject of death.
Listen, I'm there to share the gospel.
And the reality is this, every person
that we come in contact with is going to die.
Now, let me say this, it's not a comfortable subject.
You know, a lot of people, according to the scriptures,
Hebrews 2, they have a fear of death, right?
And so they don't like talking about
what they're afraid of, does that make sense?
But Ecclesiastes says this,
that it's better to go to the house of mourning
than to the house of feasting.
Why?
It's the end of all men.
Listen, every one of us,
unless Jesus comes back while we're still alive,
they're gonna have a funeral service
and it's gonna be ours.
We're gonna die.
Can I tell you that during COVID,
it was actually really easy to talk about this.
It really was, I'm not kidding.
It was amazing.
I had people approaching me during COVID.
Hey, you gave me one of them gospel tracks before,
like, what's gonna happen?
You try to, what an opportunity.
Because so many people were concerned
about dying from COVID.
And I would say to people repeatedly, repeatedly, repeatedly,
there are more people dying from all kinds of other things
than there are dying from COVID.
And the reality is that you have, listen,
I said this to our local representative
that sits on the board here in our Providence district.
I said, listen, the chances of you or me dying from COVID
are pretty low given all of the information that we have,
but there is a 100% chance we're gonna die.
We're gonna die.
And so I try to get to that subject.
I don't wanna be really unkind about it,
but the reality is that if we're going to share the gospel,
we have to get to the point of sharing the gospel.
We have to be purposed.
I'm not just trying to stand and shoot the breeze,
with some person that I don't know
and just talking about some team
or some activity or something.
No, I've come, Christ Jesus according,
remember what Paul said there in 1 Corinthians 1.17,
for Christ sent me not to baptize, but to preach the gospel.
He said, but we preach Christ crucified.
And so we have this responsibility to go
and to preach the gospel,
to give the truth of Christ's death,
his burial and his resurrection.
And so we wanna lead the conversation to the gospel.
Sometimes I'll be able to ask somebody with that question,
hey, are you 100% sure if you were to die today,
you'd go to heaven?
You know, many times people say, nah, I mean, not 100%,
but like maybe 80%, 90%.
And that always makes me kind of chuckle internally.
I never chuckle externally,
but I kind of wonder in my own mind,
what is it that makes you think 70%, 80%, 90?
Like, how do you figure that, right?
Like what is the equation that you're using
to reach your conclusion?
I don't ask that question in that manner,
but many times I'll say this, well, how do you know?
How do you know?
What am I doing?
I'm getting them to give me an answer.
Because when they give me an answer,
it enables me to be able to know where to go scripturally.
What verses am I gonna give them?
Where am I gonna begin?
As I begin to, and we'll look at verses next week,
I'm being able to share those verses.
And all of this, I know that I'm spending a lot of time
going through this, but the reality is this is just,
I mean, just a very quick time.
You have a moment of opportunity
to be able to get to this point.
And so then I have number six, if you're taking notes,
I think I've shared all of them up to this point,
but I dealt with it last week.
Number six would be this, share your story.
I said this last week, make it personal.
What did Christ do for you?
How did Christ change your life?
If you are tracking with me this evening,
I've not yet said one thing
about inviting somebody to our church.
Do we want people to come to our church?
Sure, absolutely.
I'm thankful for every visitor
that comes through these doors, I am.
We follow up with them.
We have meals with them, our family does.
We try to reach them, try to follow up at their homes.
I mean, we do all sorts of things to try to reach people.
But the reality is that we're not just simply
trying to get people to come to a church.
We wanna share the gospel with people.
And we wanna be able to get to the gospel.
I said this last week, but it's worth repeating.
As soon as you make the emphasis on visiting church,
that individual that you're speaking to
already has a predetermined idea about church.
They already have something in their mind
that they believe about church.
Whether it's positive or negative,
whether it's an experience that they've had as a child,
whether it's an experience of a family member,
whatever it might be.
My grandfather, when my dad was going
to South Carolina, Parris Island,
to go to boot camp, and then afterwards
he was stationed in North Carolina because of COVID.
Every Marine goes down there after they get to Paris Island
and he's there and they were talking about churches.
And my grandfather, who I do not think at that point
in his life ever, ever stepped foot in a Baptist church,
said to my dad, beware of the Baptists
because they handle snakes.
I'm telling you the truth, man.
Now you know me, I wouldn't be a Baptist
if we handled snakes, amen?
And I hate snakes, I am not handling snakes.
I have zero idea where my grandfather got that idea.
Now I know there's some boys over in West Virginia
that handle snakes and some of those boys
got bit by rattlesnakes.
I don't understand what's wrong with them,
but that's what they do.
They don't understand Mark 16 and that's fine.
The reality is that my dad was told that.
Now let me fast forward.
That was like in 1977, 1978 that my dad was told that.
My dad was told that.
It was in 1992, so you do the math, right?
14 years, go by, and in 1992 my dad hears somebody
that says there are a lot of dead people
in the world that are waiting to die.
My dad doesn't understand what that means.
He inquires and he says, the man says,
well, there are a lot of people that are dead spiritually
that are just waiting to die a physical death.
And at that moment, my dad was under conviction.
We're going to church.
My mom says you go to your church, I go to my church.
I'm sitting there as almost 13 years old
and I'm like wait, hold on.
You don't have a church and you don't have a church.
What are you talking about?
You go to your church and I'm going to my church.
We didn't go to church.
I'm telling you the truth.
We never went.
We didn't even go to church on Easter and Christmas.
We just didn't go to church.
So what do they do?
Well, my dad went to the Methodist church
and my mom went to the Catholic church.
One time.
My dad went to the Methodist church, I think twice.
My mom went to the Catholic church.
I remember going to the Methodist church
and to the Catholic church and I remember it being empty.
There was just no gospel given.
There was no truth given.
It was very strange and I remember my dad
going back to that worker, that young Marine
and saying where do you go to church?
You know what he said?
Grace Baptist Church.
Do you know one of the first thoughts
that went through my dad's mind when he heard that?
What his dad told him 14 years earlier.
So you know what my dad did?
He went on a Wednesday night by himself.
He didn't take my mom and he didn't take me or my brother.
He went by himself to see what the situation was.
You know the preacher that night?
Rodney Padat was his name.
He preached a message on hell on a Wednesday night.
My dad sat in the back row and he would say
if he was here that he was under so much conviction
that his knuckles were white by holding on
so tightly to the pew.
He went back the next Sunday and he got saved.
Everybody has an idea when they hear church.
I'm thankful that my dad didn't avoid going
to a Baptist church because of what he was told
but there was no grounds for what he was told.
It was just some kind of hearsay.
People have an idea about church.
I'm not there to just simply say come to our church.
I'm there to preach Christ.
Can I share my story?
Can I tell you what Christ did for me?
Can I tell you how he changed my life?
There was a day in my life where I had no hope.
I had no peace.
I had no joy.
I was going down a road to nowhere.
In fact, I was going somewhere.
I was heading for a Christless eternity.
There's a song, then Jesus stepped in.
Oh, hallelujah, that he saved me.
He changed my life.
We get to start there and sharing your story
with that individual.
Let me say this as we wrap up this evening.
So we wanna get to sharing the gospel.
I'm gonna go through next week all the verses
and then we're gonna actually have an opportunity
to say it's gonna be very different.
It is gonna be a different Sunday night service.
After I go through the message next week,
it's gonna be a shorter message.
You're gonna get to put to practice some of what we learned.
We're gonna do it right here in church.
We're just gonna find somebody
and just go ahead and share a story
and go through it and be able to give a presentation.
We'll turn off live stream early and be able to do that.
Why?
Because we wanna put into practice
what we're trying to learn.
So we will get into all the verses.
Many times people refer to it as the Roman's road.
You've heard that terminology
and memorizing the Roman's road.
And certainly those are good verses.
I oftentimes start in John 10 personally
because the good shepherd, he gave his life for the sheep
and that we, according to verse number 10,
might have life more abundantly.
And I like to start there,
but we'll look at all those verses next week.
But let me say this to finish up tonight.
This is probably one of the most important things
I could say as we look at this subject matter
with regard to trying to share the gospel.
Number seven, if you're taking notes,
leave the door open for another opportunity.
Leave the door open for another opportunity.
The biblical principle, turn to 1 Corinthians, if you will,
and the third chapter.
So many times, if we're not careful,
we can go so far
that we turn that individual off
from any further conversation,
not only with us, but possibly with anyone else.
I suggest this evening
that as we look at 1 Corinthians chapter three,
that Paul understood a principle
that is important for us to understand.
They were saying in Corinth,
according to 1 Corinthians three and verse four,
I am of Paul and another I am of Apollos,
are you not carnal?
Who then is Paul and who is Apollos,
but ministers by whom you believed,
even as the Lord gave to every man.
We're just ministers, just ministers, servants.
Verse six, I have planted, Apollos watered,
but God gave the increase.
So then, verse seven, neither is he that planteth anything,
neither he that watereth, but God that giveth the increase.
Now, he that planteth and he that watereth are one,
and every man shall receive his own reward
according to his own labor.
Notice this, verse nine,
for we are laborers together with God.
You're God's husbandry, you're God's building.
Remember, Jesus said, follow me
and I'll make you fishers of men.
We are laborers together with God.
But the principle here in 1 Corinthians three
that I think is so important
as we conclude this thought tonight
is that some plant, some water,
but God gives the increase.
God may use you on that first interaction
to simply plant the seed of the gospel.
And when you leave the door open,
it gives opportunity, number one,
for the Holy Spirit of God to work in that individual's life
and then for someone else to come along and water
and God gives the increase.
I do not want to, listen, the gospel is offensive,
but I don't need to be offensive.
The gospel's offensive, but I don't want to be offensive.
And I want to leave that door open.
I have given open invitations.
If you've ever gone door knocking with me,
you could stand here and say it.
You've heard me say it.
I have given countless invitations
to individuals to give me a call and let's have coffee.
Over and over and over.
I'm trying to leave the door open.
I'm trying to, hey, can I come back and follow up?
And I might stop back by,
especially if it's a good contact.
I want to give the opportunity,
give the Holy Spirit opportunity to work
and to understand I don't want to be the reason.
I don't want to be the hindrance,
not only for me not having another opportunity,
but somebody else having an opportunity
and going and sharing the gospel with that individual.
I don't know about you, but I know I can say for myself,
I did not get saved the first time I heard the gospel.
I didn't.
Maybe you're here tonight
and the very first time you ever heard the gospel,
you got saved and that's wonderful.
But I think for many of us,
we'd say we would testify that it wasn't the first time
that I heard the gospel that I got saved.
So what does that mean?
Well, it means that there were second and third
and fourth opportunities that someone came
and God was working and the water was being applied
and praise God.
And I want to give that open door of opportunity.
Let me say this.
Even when somebody doesn't give you a chance
to get anywhere near what we dealt with tonight,
I do two things.
I always try to leave them with either a gospel tract
or one of our brochures that has the gospel.
And I always do something like this.
I say, listen, I completely understand you're busy
or whatever.
Would you do me a favor?
Would you just make a commitment to read this?
There's some Bible verses in here
and I just want to know if you would read them.
Then I try to quote a verse of scripture.
The verse of scripture will vary
based upon the particular conversation
that I had with the individual.
But I like to quote a verse of scripture, why?
Because God uses his word.
And so I want to use, I want to take an opportunity,
even if somebody says, no, I'm not interested.
If they say, no, I don't want that.
If I'm gonna offer them a tract or an invitation,
I still oftentimes will quote a verse of scripture
so that there's some piece of God's word
that is given that the Holy Spirit can use.
You know that God's word is powerful.
powerful. And with just one verse of Scripture, I believe it with all my heart tonight. I
believe that somebody that I talk to, somebody that you talk to, but we leave one verse of
Scripture with, I believe that that single verse of Scripture can keep them up at night.
And really wondering, what's going to happen when I die? The Holy Spirit's using His Word
in the heart of that individual, bringing conviction. That's what He does. And that's
a work that we can't do, but God has given us the tools to be able to do that, and He
does a work as we use His Word. It's not in the wisdom of man's words. It's in the power
of God's Word. I'm not going to a door trying to win an argument. I'm not trying to argue
somebody into heaven. No, I simply want to share the gospel. You know, there have been
some times that I've had to say, the example that I used when Tim and I, I don't know what
that guy was talking about. Eventually, after a few minutes, I just said, hey, listen, I
appreciate your time. You have a wonderful day. If you'd read those things, I'd love
to be able to get in touch with you again. I'm not going to sit there and try to argue
with the guy on his doorstep for how long am I going to argue with him. He's not going
to change my mind. I'm obviously not going to change his mind. And so, I just need to
go and move on. Does that make sense? But I want to try to leave the door open. I never
would insult somebody. I would never attack them and what they believe. No, I want to
leave a door open this evening. If we're going to share the gospel, we say, I understand
that I want to, the responsibility, the need to share the gospel. I got to have some kind
of a plan. How do I get there? Because there's far too often that we can have discussions,
conversations, intending to share the gospel, but never actually getting to it. And we leave
the meeting, we say, no, it was a good meeting, it was nice, it was a friendly conversation,
but we actually never got to the gospel. I went to lunch with our neighbor, and he is
a different world religion, and I went desiring to share the gospel with him. Can I tell you,
it was challenging for like the first 15 minutes. How am I going to, like, there's no crack
opening. We're just eating lunch and talking, and he was just talking about any subject
he could think of to really try to keep the conversation busy and avoiding what he probably
knew I wanted to talk to him about. He knew I was the pastor of the church. He's our neighbor.
And after about 15 minutes or so, I was able to, there was a statement that was made that
was able to get into the gospel. You know, that man, he didn't trust Christ that day,
but can I tell you for sure, he knows the truth of what God's Word says. And that's
our duty. Our duty is not to make somebody get saved. That's the work that God does.
But we do have a responsibility to tell them. Ezekiel, he's called to be a watchman. The
watchman has a responsibility. The response of the individuals that are warned is outside
of his responsibility. If he warns them and they ignore, well, he's not responsible. But
if he fails to warn them, then God holds him responsible. This evening, we have to make
sure that we're purposed as we seek to give the gospel. And don't just leave conversations
and say, well, I wish I would have been able to. No, we got to be purposed in it. We got
to be kind and compassionate and loving and show the grace and mercy of God and leave
that door open for future opportunities. Let's pray. Father, we love you tonight. We thank
you for loving us. We thank you for your Word. We thank you for the example of Paul. As we've
looked at these portions of Scripture in the book of 1 Corinthians, and God, I pray that
you'd help us to be determined to preach the gospel, that we would understand that
you've given us this responsibility. Help us not to go seeking to win arguments and
display our superior knowledge. No, God, help us to go in humility and love, genuine concern
for our soul. And I pray, God, that you would use us, that we would see fruit, fruit that
would bring honor and glory to thy name. I pray, Lord, that as we go throughout the remainder
of this week and, Lord, as you would give us opportunities, that you would help us to
seize them. And God, we'd see you do a work. Well, thank you for it in Christ's name, we
pray.