is memorizing verses, singing the song,
and what a blessing.
I'm thankful for the blood that was shed for me,
and the blood that was shed for you.
We all have a sin problem.
All men are born sinners in need of the only savior,
the Lord Jesus Christ.
And I am so thankful that someone gave me that message
and told me that I could go to heaven,
not because of anything I could do,
but all because of what Jesus had already done.
Isn't that wonderful?
And so many today are trying to do all sorts of things
to try to get to heaven,
and it's never gonna work because Jesus already did it,
and we just accept that free gift of eternal life.
Certainly thankful for the opportunity
to open up the Word of God, Acts chapter number 12,
this morning.
Hold your place there,
and then turn over to Acts chapter number one.
Before we get into the text of scripture, Acts chapter 12,
we're gonna kinda walk through the book of Acts
and look at a number of references,
and then land in Acts chapter number 12.
As you know, over the last several weeks,
we have been in 1 Timothy chapter number two,
and our theme for this year is continue.
We're preaching through 1 and 2 Timothy on Sunday mornings,
and here we find ourselves in the book of Acts.
The reason that we're in the book of Acts this morning
is because in 1 Timothy chapter two,
as we've looked at for the last few weeks,
we have addressed the subject of prayer
and how important prayer is.
We find that there's a priority in 1 Timothy two
and verse number one that is placed upon prayer.
We understand the importance of having some,
the importance of understanding the place of prayer,
the privilege of prayer,
and we understand that this morning.
We recognize that prayer
should be a vital part of our lives.
It's a unique privilege for every child of God
to go to the throne of grace and to seek the Lord
and to obtain favor and grace and help in time of need.
We find that prayer is not a mere religious exercise.
It's not rote religion.
It's not memorized prayers.
No, we are communing with our heavenly father.
What a unique privilege that is
that we can enter into his presence.
I believe that as you study the book of Acts
and the reason that we're taking
and looking at the book of Acts this morning,
we'll get back to 1 Timothy,
but as we look at the book of Acts,
we read of the church in the first century.
As you read of the first century church
and you have an opportunity to see
all that was accomplished as the Lord Jesus Christ
was working in and through them,
you find statements such as this,
that they filled Jerusalem with their doctrine.
You find statements such as this,
that they turned the world upside down.
And as you look at the advancement of the gospel,
as you study the book of Acts
and you see how the gospel there in Jerusalem
goes throughout the entire known world
and as God is using the disciples
and multitudes of people are being saved
and how God is at work,
you begin to look at these amazing accomplishments,
but you cannot ignore the reality
that the first century church is a praying church.
The first century church is a praying church.
I'm sure that you've probably heard
at some point someone speaking about,
we're in the 21st century, get with the times,
we need to be a 21st century church and so on and so forth.
And I'm thankful for the modern conveniences that we have
and that we're sitting in a room this morning
that has many of those modern conveniences.
But understand with me this morning
that the church needs to really be a first century church,
not a 21st century church.
The church today needs to be not an entertaining church,
but a praying church.
And unfortunately, all across our world
and all across our land in America,
you have assemblies that are taking place
where it's not much more than entertainment.
It's mindful of what C.H. Spurgeon said
a couple of hundred years ago
that they would be entertaining the goats.
That's exactly what's happening all across our land.
And the church needs to be a praying church.
As we look in Acts chapter number one,
we're gonna take a walkthrough, if you will.
And I want you to see,
as we look at the early church that's a praying church,
you see all of the great accomplishments
and how the gospel went forth
and churches were established and missionary journeys
and souls saved.
And I mean, multitudes of people that were saved.
And man, it's exciting.
But a vital part of all of that is prayer.
They're a praying church.
Paul says that first of all, prayers and supplications,
the priority, the emphasis on prayer.
Jesus said, my house shall be a house of prayer.
Here in Acts chapter number one,
notice in verse number 14,
the Bible says these all continued with one accord
in prayer and supplication with the women
and Mary the mother of Jesus and with his brethren.
So you see that there,
just after the ascension of the Lord Jesus Christ,
that's recorded for us in verses nine through 11,
Jesus goes to heaven after he'd walked upon earth,
after his resurrection and teaching and giving instruction.
And we find that he ascends to heaven
and the Bible says these all continued
with one accord in prayer and supplication.
In verse number 24, the Bible says, and they prayed.
Notice what they prayed.
They said, thou Lord, then notice this phrase,
which knowest the hearts of all men.
Aren't you thankful that you serve a God who's omniscient?
Aren't you thankful that you serve a God
who knows all things?
And the disciples as these are gathered here,
these that are praying 120, they're praying
and they say, God, we're praying to you
and you know the hearts of all men.
God knows your heart this morning.
Motives matter.
God knows your heart.
The Bible tells us the heart is deceitful
and desperately wicked.
Who can know it?
In the very next verse of Jeremiah 17,
that's verse nine and verse 10 says,
I, the Lord, I try the heart.
He knows our hearts.
Notice what they pray.
It says, show whether of these two thou hast chosen.
You know what they're praying for?
They're praying for divine direction.
They're praying, they don't wanna get in the way.
They don't wanna make their own decision, their own choice.
They're praying that God who is omniscient,
who knows all things, who knows the hearts of all men,
that God would give them divine direction.
Aren't you thankful today
that we can still pray that prayer?
We can still go to God.
Listen, there are many times in my life,
I think if you'd be honest this morning,
there are many times in your life
where you just don't know what to do.
You can't figure it out.
You don't have the ability to understand
and you pray for that wisdom.
The Bible says, if any man lack wisdom,
let him ask of God who gives all men liberally
and prayeth not.
We find here in Acts one, the praying.
Notice in chapter two in verse number 42,
after the day of Pentecost and over 3,000 are saved
and what an exciting day this is
in the early church history and looking at the start.
And we find that in verse number 42,
the Bible says this, and they continued steadfastly
in the apostles doctrine and fellowship
and in breaking of bread and in prayers.
Prayer was a central vital part of the early church.
The early church is a praying church.
Notice in chapter four in verse 31,
we're not looking at every reference
with regard to prayer in the book of Acts,
but I wanna highlight many of these.
Why?
Because I wanna prove a point this morning.
In Acts four, we find that the disciples
are dealing with the religious leaders
and it's in this text of scripture
where Peter stands up with great boldness and says,
"'Neither is there salvation in any other,
"'for there is none other name under heaven given among men
"'whereby we must be saved.'"
What a great declaration of the gospel
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And we find that in this setting and in this meeting
and in this really trial, if you will,
as they're being interrogated,
that they are told by the religious leaders
that they are no longer to speak in the name of Jesus.
We find that hearing that rebuke
from those religious leaders,
what they do well, they go to prayer.
The Bible says in verse number 24,
that when they heard that Peter and John
come back and deliver to the company,
to the disciples, to the church, if you will,
what the religious leaders said,
and it says that they lifted up their voice to God
with one accord.
They begin to pray.
They begin to seek the face of God.
Notice what they say in verse 24,
"'Lord, thou art God,
"'which hast made heaven and earth and the sea
"'and all that in them is.'"
Aren't you thankful that when you pray,
you're praying to the creator God?
Praying to the God that said,
let there be light, and there was light.
Praying to the God that we read in Genesis chapter number one
and God said, and it was so.
He not only is omniscient,
that he knows the hearts of all men,
as we see in Acts chapter number one,
but here as we see the praying church,
that they understood that he's omnipotent,
that he has all power,
and given the circumstances that they're facing,
giving that rebuke that they've received,
they now go to God in prayer,
understanding that prayer is a privilege,
but understanding that God hears and answers prayer.
And they say, you're God, and you're the creator.
Notice in verse 31,
and when they had prayed,
you know what's interesting,
what they prayed was that God would give them boldness.
Singularly, that is their prayer request
in this text of scripture.
They did not pray for deliverance,
that God would judge the religious leaders,
that God would, no,
they just.
simply prayed for boldness.
In the midst of this threat, we've heard what's been said,
God, would you grant us boldness?
What a great prayer request.
And it says in verse 31,
and when they had prayed, the place was shaken
where they were assembled together
and they were all filled with the Holy Ghost
and they spake the word of God with boldness.
God answered prayer, why?
Because we have a God who hears and answers prayer.
We have a God who at any time,
we can go before that throne and we have that access
and we can seek his face.
In the early church, they're facing a situation,
they're facing some opposition
and we find that they go to God and God answers.
We notice in Acts chapter number six,
notice what's happening in Acts six,
contextually, just very quickly,
the threat from without the, if you will,
the persecution from without is recorded
in Acts four and five and now all of a sudden
in chapter number six, there becomes some stirring within.
The enemy is trying to attack from without
but the enemy is attacking from within.
And we see that in Acts chapter number six.
And so what do they do in Acts six?
Well, they pray.
Because the early church was a praying church.
And what did the church do?
Well, when they had a difficulty, they prayed.
When they had something that they're dealing with,
they prayed, notice in Acts six and verse number four,
this is what the disciples, the apostles say,
Peter here and he says,
but we will give ourselves continually to prayer
and to the ministry of the word.
If you skip down to verse number six,
it says whom they set before the apostles
and when they had prayed, they laid their hands on them.
This is really the deacons that we read of here
in Acts chapter number six that are appointed
over these matters that are being dealt with.
And we find the central focus of prayer
in Acts chapter nine after the conversion of Saul.
At that time, his name is Saul.
Of course, we know him and it often referred to him
as Paul, the apostle, the apostle to the Gentiles
and what a great man of God.
But in Acts chapter nine, he's persecuting
and he's got authority, but he meets Jesus, hallelujah.
And he gets saved, he gets born again.
And we find that as he gets saved and he says,
Lord, who art thou?
He says, Lord, what wilt thou have me to do?
And God's gonna use a man.
The man that he's gonna use is Ananias.
And Ananias, of course, we're not gonna deal
with the entire text, but Ananias has some concern
because he's heard about this man, Saul
and he has a testimony that goes before him,
this reputation, if you will.
But notice what God says in Acts chapter nine
in verse number 11, as the Lord answers Ananias,
the Bible says, arise and go into the street
which is called Strait and inquire in the house of Judas
for one called Saul of Tarsus,
notice, for behold, he prayeth.
Saul's saved for just, I mean, just a short period of time
at this particular time in history.
And what's he doing?
He's praying, he's praying.
And in Acts chapter number 12, excuse me, Acts chapter 13,
we're gonna deal with Acts 12 as our text this morning,
but notice in Acts chapter 13,
this is the first missionary journey.
The church at Antioch, they're gonna send forth
the first missionaries and we find that in verse number three
of Acts 13, the Bible says, and when they had fasted
and prayed and laid their hands on them,
they sent them away.
By the way, I believe that throughout the duration
of this missionary journey that the church was praying
for the missionaries because at the end of Acts 14,
when they receive word that the missionaries are returning
to deliver a report, the church shows up
and the church is there and they get to hear what God did.
I believe this, that they get to hear
how God answered their prayers,
how God used Paul and Silas on this, Barnabas, excuse me,
on this missionary journey and how God worked
and they have the opportunity to hear
in Acts chapter 14 and verse 23,
before they return to the church at Antioch,
these missionaries, they go back to the churches
that were established, four of them established
on this first missionary journey.
In Acts 14 and verse 23, it says,
and when they had ordained them elders in every church
and had prayed with fasting, they commended them
to the Lord on whom they believed.
In Acts chapter 16, we find that the Bible,
as they arrive in Philippi, now again,
as they receive the direction of the Lord
to go into Macedonia and during
this second missionary journey,
the Bible tells us here in Acts chapter 16 and verse 16,
and it came to pass as we went to prayer.
It's a central part of the local church.
It's a central part of the first century church.
In Acts chapter 20 and verse number 36,
notice what the Bible says.
As Paul is going to depart, he's called folks together
so he could deliver them a message.
He called for the leaders of the church at Ephesus here
in this particular text, and we find
that as he gives them instruction
and gives them a charge in verse 36, it says,
and when he had thus spoken,
he kneeled down and prayed with them all.
And they wept sore and fell on Paul's neck and kissed him.
Could you imagine the scene here
as they had this prayer meeting before Paul would head?
Where's he going?
Well, he's heading to Jerusalem.
That's why he called for the leaders
of the church at Ephesus to meet him there,
and he's on his way to Jerusalem,
and we find that they have this prayer meeting.
In chapter 21 and verse number five,
the Bible says, and when he had accomplished those days,
we departed and went our way,
and they all brought us on our way with wives and children
till we were out of the city, and what did they do?
Before they left, it says,
and we kneeled down on the shore and prayed and prayed.
We could look at more examples this morning,
but I hope at this point,
after reading this number of verses,
that you would agree with me
that the early church was a praying church,
that you would agree this morning
that the early church believed in,
but also practiced prayer.
You know, a lot of people can believe in things,
but never actually do it.
We believe in the power of prayer,
but how often do we pray?
How often do we pray?
Do we only pray when there's an urgent matter,
or are we people of prayer?
The Bible says that we're to pray always.
Pray without ceasing, in 1 Thessalonians.
Be dealing with that this Wednesday evening, actually.
Begin to look at this early church
and understand the fact that they believed in
and practiced, they believed in prayer,
individually and corporately.
You know, it's a blessing to be able
to go to God on your own.
There's one God and one mediator between God and man,
the man Christ Jesus.
I'm thankful that any time, at any place,
for any reason, I can go to God in prayer, and so can you.
You don't need some intercessor.
You don't need to have some mediator.
No, Jesus Christ is our mediator,
and we go to the Father through the Son,
and what a blessing to understand that truth.
We find this morning that though we can gather,
or we can individually go to God in prayer,
we understand the emphasis as we look here
in the book of Acts, that prayer is not just individual,
but it's corporate, corporate prayer.
Turn over to Acts 12.
I asked you to begin there,
and we're gonna look at this text of Scripture.
For some, it's a familiar passage of Scripture.
We're gonna go through this passage of Scripture
here this morning, verses one through 19,
and I wanna look at a praying church.
In Acts 12, in verse number one,
the Bible says,
Now about that time Herod the king stretched forth his hands
to vex certain of the church,
and he killed James, the brother of John, with the sword.
And so we see the opposition again.
We see what's taking place,
and we see the death of James at the hand of Herod.
The Bible tells us in verse number three,
and because he, that's speaking of Herod,
saw that it, what's it?
Well, the killing of James,
this opposition that he led in this persecution,
this martyrdom, that it pleased the Jews.
The Jews are pleased at what's taking place.
The Bible says in verse number three
that he proceeded further to take Peter also.
James has been killed, according to verse number two,
and Herod, he says,
Man, this has pleased these people.
So guess what?
I'm gonna take Peter also.
Peter's a great leader in the church,
and so the Bible says that these then,
at the end of verse number three,
were the days of unleavened bread.
So God gives us insight with regard to the timing,
with regard to when this happened,
and it says when he had apprehended him.
And so we find that Peter is apprehended by Herod,
according to verse number four,
and Herod puts him into prison.
It says he put him in prison
and delivered him to four quaternions of soldiers
to keep him.
Notice, intending after Easter
to bring him forth to the people.
When he's gonna bring him forth,
you know what he's gonna do?
He's gonna kill him.
That's what he's gonna do.
Because of what was going on,
he had killed James,
and the timing wasn't right to kill Peter,
but he saw that it pleased the Jews,
and so he says.
So I'm going to apprehend Peter and I'm going to incarcerate Peter so that I can kill Peter.
He delivers him to these soldiers and he's kept in ward.
He's in prison.
But I want you to notice verse number 5.
The Bible says Peter therefore was kept in prison but prayer was made without ceasing
of the church unto God for him.
We see in verses 1 through 4, really verses 1 through 5, the situation.
If you're taking notes this morning, notice the situation with me.
And here's what I want you to understand this morning.
The church, the early church, the first century church, they had situations the same way every
church, every individual has situations.
You're a family, you have situations, you have circumstances, you have difficulties
that arise.
You're a church family, you have situations, you have things that you deal with.
As an individual, we have situations, matters, circumstances that we deal with.
And as we look here in Acts chapter number 12, we find that in the first five verses
that God allows us to have an insight and understanding, if you will, to the situation
that the church faced.
We mentioned already that in Acts chapter number 4, they were facing a different situation.
The situation was a threat that you no longer can speak in the name of Jesus.
So, at the circumstances that are presented in Acts chapter number 4, what did they do?
Well, they went to prayer.
And here in Acts chapter number 5, as God reveals to us the situation, we see that it's
a serious matter.
I want you to think about, we're reading this as historical documentation.
This is an accurate historical account that God has given to us.
But I want you to think about being in this church.
I want you to think about being there and understanding what's taking place.
And I want you to consider with me this morning that you're in a situation and you've seen
James killed.
And you understand the power and the authority that Herod has, and you see that the Jews
are pleased with it.
And by the way, these are the same Jews that in chapter number 4 were saying, you can't
speak in his name any longer.
And they're pleased that Herod is now putting them to death.
And Peter, Peter is taken, he's incarcerated.
Peter's a leader of the church.
By the way, the enemy knows how to work.
The enemy knows how to work.
But I'm thankful that the church had been given some instruction, the church understood
some things, the people, they understand the importance of prayer, they see the circumstances,
they see what's taking place.
And in this situation, I want you to put yourselves there.
I want you to think about being there.
How would you feel?
What would your response be?
See oftentimes we'll use little catch phrases, if you will, cliches, that prayer should be
our first response and not our last resort and those types of things.
But the reality this morning is that in many of our lives, prayer is not our first response.
And there are many times in our lives that we lean on our own understanding that we try
to figure out how we can change the circumstances, how we can maybe manipulate the circumstances.
How can we get Peter out of here?
And maybe this morning if we're in this situation and collectively this is our church and we're
dealing with this situation and we have a meeting and we say, okay, we gotta come up
with a plan.
How are we gonna get our pastor, our leader out of prison?
What are we gonna do?
What are some things that we can do?
We begin to brainstorm, we begin to come up with ideas and we're gonna have this covert
operation and someone's...
Sometimes that's how we think.
Sometimes that's how we behave.
We lean on our own understanding.
We're trying to figure things out ourselves.
Listen, we're all guilty of it.
We've all been there.
We've all had situations.
We see the situation of the early church.
We understand in Acts 12 the stakes are high.
Peter is going to be put to death.
Herod is not playing games.
What do we do?
How do we respond?
I'm thankful for the privilege of prayer.
I'm thankful for a praying church because we see the situation but then we see the supplication
and really begins in verse number five and as we go through the text of Scripture, notice
the Bible says, therefore, Peter therefore was kept in prison.
But I want you to notice what the Bible says, but prayer was made notice without ceasing
of the church unto God for him.
You know how the church, the early church, the first century church, you know how they
respond to the situation?
They prayed.
They said, we gotta have a prayer meeting.
We gotta have a prayer meeting.
This is urgent.
By the way, I think a lot of people showed up for the prayer meeting.
They believed in prayer.
You know, that's fine that you're going to gather over there, but I'm just going to pray
at home.
No, there's something about corporate prayer.
They got together and they prayed.
We see in verse number six, this is when Herod would have brought him forth, Peter, what's
he bringing him forth for?
What's the purpose?
Well, to kill him.
And the Bible says the same night Peter was sleeping between two soldiers.
By the way, what a great picture of the peace of God.
Amen?
God tells us about a peace that passeth all understanding.
Jesus said, my peace I give unto thee, not as the world giveth give I unto thee.
He said, my peace, I think about the peace of God.
And Peter, he saw that James was killed.
He knew what Herod's purpose and intentions were.
And we find that Peter is asleep between a couple of soldiers.
The peace of God.
Listen, I don't know what you're dealing with this morning, but I know the peace of God.
Peace does not mean the absence of trouble.
See, there's a lot of people that think that they could just have peace if all of their
troubles would go away.
Peace is not found in the absence of trouble.
Peace is found in the person of Jesus Christ.
He is our peace.
And the Bible tells us, commands us in the book of Colossians that we're to let the peace
of God rule in our hearts.
You know what that means?
That's an action we have to take.
Why?
Because sometimes we're dealing with situations where chaos wants to rule in your heart.
Where doubt wants to rule in your heart.
God says let the peace of God rule in your heart.
Wow, hallelujah, for the peace of God.
He's sleeping.
And the Bible says in verse number 6 that He's bound with two chains in the keepers
before the door kept the prison.
And so again in your mind's eye if you can see the situation we're told of four soldiers
in verse number 4 and what's happening is Peter is in this cell and he's got two soldiers
that are chained to him and then there are two soldiers that are watching guard at the
door.
You think Herod was serious?
You think he wanted to make sure he was going to be able to fulfill his desire in killing
Peter?
Absolutely.
He puts everything in place that he could.
By the way it reminds me of what happened a little while earlier with the Lord Jesus
Christ and they came to Pilate and they said, they called our Savior a deceiver and how
terrible that is.
But they say we know what this deceiver said before he died.
He said that he was going to rise again and so we want you to set a watch and make it
sure.
And Pilate said you have it, set it as sure as you can and they did everything they could.
But guess what?
The stone rolled away.
Hallelujah.
The grave it could not keep him.
They did everything they could.
But Christ rose conquering sin, death and the grave.
And here Herod he makes every preparation possible to keep Peter secure within this
particular prison cell and we find that he's got two soldiers that are chained to him.
He's got two soldiers that are outside of the cell door and the Bible says in verse
7, and behold the angel of the Lord came upon him and light shined in the prison and he
smote Peter on the side.
I like it when it says that.
You ever have to smite someone to wake them up?
Amen?
I remember Elijah, he's here this morning.
We were at camp several years ago.
You guys were just junior campers and his cousin went with us and his cousin wouldn't
get up one morning and he said I got it and he went in there and he just smacked that
young man and woke him up.
Got him out of bed.
Amen?
And I wasn't going to get away with that but Elijah took care of it and that young man
got up out of bed.
Amen?
And the Bible says here that he smote Peter on the side and raised him up saying arise
up quickly.
Notice the Bible says that his chains fell off from his hands.
And the angel said unto him gird thyself and bind on thy sandals and so he did.
And he saith unto him cast thy garment about thee and follow me.
And he went out and he followed him and wist not that it was true which was done by the
angel but thought he saw a vision.
You ever dream at night and your dream might be so vivid that you think it's real?
I mean Peter's in a position here where he almost thinks he's dreaming, he's having a
vision.
And I want you to see that in verse number 10 it says and when they were past the first
and the second ward they came unto the iron gate that leadeth unto the city, notice what
it says, which opened to them of his own accord.
They went out and passed on through one street.
forthwith the angel departed from him." You say, that's just not possible. You don't know
the God that I know. He's the God of the impossible. He's the God of the impossible. He said, nothing
is too hard for me. How did the gate open? God opened the gate. That's what God can do.
I want you to understand why all of this is taking place. The church is praying. The church
is praying. They're in a prayer meeting. They don't know at this moment as we're reading
the text of Scripture, they don't know what's happening in the prison cell. They don't know
that Peter was asleep between two prison guards and that the angel of the Lord came and smote
him and the chains fell off and he's walking. They don't know that. They're praying. They're
praying. I don't know exactly what they're praying. All of us can use our sanctified
imaginations and we can be creative to think of different things that they might have been
praying. But I'm not sure that any of them prayed that God would you just smite them
and cause those chains to fall off and just open the gates and let them. I don't know
that they prayed exactly that way. But that's why we take and cherish the prayer promise
that God gives us in Ephesians 3.20, now unto him that is able to exceeding abundantly above
all that we ask or think. I don't know if I were, now that we have the record of Acts
12, we may pray this way. But without the record of Acts 12, we may not pray in that
same regard, but we have a God who's able to do exceeding abundantly above. And we find
that as the church is having this prayer meeting and we see that God is working again, they
do not even know what God is doing and how God has answered their prayer. We find in
verse number 11 that when Peter was come to himself, now think about that. He's been smitten
by the angel of the Lord to wake up and to get out of that prison. He goes out and I
mean the doors open and the gate opens and the Bible says in verse number 12, when he
came to himself. No, this isn't a vision. No, this isn't a dream. No, this is reality.
I'm delivered. I'm not in that cell anymore. Man, hallelujah. The Bible says in verse 12,
here's what he said. Now I know of a surety that the Lord hath sent his angel and hath
delivered me out of the hand of Herod and from all the expectation of the people of
the Jews. He says this in verse 12, and when he had considered the thing, he came to the
house of Mary, the mother of John, whose surname was Mark. Now notice this, where many were
gathered together praying. The Bible told us in verse number 5, but prayer was made
without ceasing of the church unto God for him. And the Bible tells us that after God
heard their prayer, after God was working miraculously, after he's answered their prayer
and he's delivered Peter in such a miraculous way as we've read the text of Scripture, that
Peter considers the thing and he says, I'm going to go over here to this particular house
and he goes, and the Bible tells us that there are many that are there praying. They're
gathered together and they're praying. It's an all-night prayer meeting. An all-night
prayer meeting. What a blessing. You know, there was a time in our nation's history that
our churches had all-night prayer meetings. There are some that still do today, and I'm
thankful for that. An all-night prayer meeting. By the way, I don't think it's a prayer meeting
is a bad idea. We need prayer. We need to be a praying church. We have a one-hour prayer
meeting on Wednesday evening. And I don't mean to insult anyone, but I said this a few
weeks ago, you have a one-hour prayer meeting and half the people show up. Our actions speak
louder than our words. What do we believe about prayer? We're a praying church. We
go to a conference every year in July. We're just at a retreat for a pastor retreat. We
go to a pastor's conference. Completely different. I mean, as far from one end of the spectrum
to the other are these two meetings that we go to. But this meeting that we go to in July,
it's a pastor's conference. Super, super busy schedule. Lots of preaching and all sorts
of instructional classes and different things that we go to. And it's an exciting time.
But that church up there, it's where Breonna's going to college right now. That church up
there in preparation for that pastor's conference, they have an all-night prayer meeting. Leading
up to that all-night prayer meeting, they have a 24-hour prayer thing that's going on
where they're not gathered at the local church, but they have people that sign up for certain
times of the day and they're praying. They have time slots. I'm going to pray from 2
to 3 a.m. I'm going to pray from 7 to 8 p.m., whatever the times are. And they have that
set up. And then they finish that week of those prayer meetings and people praying individually
at certain times and they come together and they have an all-night church prayer meeting.
God hears and answers prayer. Prayer is a unique privilege as a child of God. I fear
this morning that prayer is neglected in our society today. It's probably 25 years ago
now. It was actually 26 years ago now. I've told this story before, but 26 years ago my
dad was doing a men's prayer breakfast and he was teaching at that men's prayer breakfast.
He was teaching on prayer and he went to a Bible bookstore. He'd only been saved for
a short time. He was going to a Bible bookstore to try to pick up a book on prayer in order
to be able to use some things and teach on the subject of prayer. And as he was looking
in that Christian bookstore, he found a book that was titled, How to Pray, in nine minutes
and 59 seconds. And really what was communicated even through the title of that book was really
indicative of the society, the culture that we live in. We want everything to be right
now. Prayer is work. Prayer is labor. How many of you know the song, Sweet Hour of Prayer?
Sweet Hour of Prayer. I've said this before as well. Unfortunately in the 21st century,
it's as if we've exchanged a sweet hour of prayer for just a little talk with Jesus.
And that's another song that you may be familiar with. Sweet Hour of Prayer. Sweet Hour of
Prayer. It's interesting to me in Acts chapter number 12 that Peter is in prison. The church
is assembled, as the Bible tells us here, at the house of Mary, the mother of John.
And they're assembled there and praying. And Peter's in prison. They don't know what's
going on with Peter. And Peter doesn't know all that's going on there. But he comes to
the house. And in verse number 13, the Bible says, As Peter knocked at the door of the
gate, a damsel came to hearken, named Rhoda. And so Peter is there knocking at the door
of the gate. And Rhoda comes to answer, I don't know the time. We find that as you
look throughout the text of Scripture, that the Bible would tell us that Peter is there.
He's sleeping. He's in between those soldiers and all that's taking place. And we find that
he's knocking at the door. And in verse number 14, it says, And when she knew Peter's voice,
how many of you ever had somebody knock at your door, especially at an unexpected time,
an unexpected hour, you're not expecting someone, someone knocks and you might say something
like this. We have rings today. I get it. But maybe, if you can think back a few years,
you say, who's there? Any of you remember that? One day I'll be preaching in 25 years
and I'll use something like that. And young people are going to look at me like, why would
you say who's there? Just take out your phone and look at your da-da-da-da, right? I mean,
you understand what I'm saying? But many of us still today, we can recall saying, who's
there? The Bible says that when she knew Peter's voice. You ever been in a situation
where you can know who the person is just by hearing their voice? You know their voice.
You're familiar with their voice. And she knew the voice and notice what the Bible says.
She opened not the gate for gladness. That always makes me laugh when I read verse 14.
But it says that she ran in and told how Peter stood before the gate. I see this young lady,
this damsel. I don't know her specific age, but she's so filled with excitement. She's
so overjoyed that she doesn't open the door. She goes and runs and tells those that are
praying. Remember, they were gathered together praying. They weren't sitting around watching
something. I know they didn't have TV, but they're not sitting around playing games and
doing whatever. No, they're praying. They're praying. And Rhoda says that Peter stood before
the gate. Notice the response. It says in verse 15, and they said unto her, Thou art
mad. Crazy. Crazy. You ever pray and God answers and you just can't maybe believe it?
God likes to answer that way, by the way. Prove His power. They say, Thou art mad. But
notice what it says. But she constantly affirmed that it was even so. Then said they, It is
His angel. But Peter continued knocking. Think about the persistence of Peter. He just continued
knocking. I'm not sure how long the conversation took. I'm not sure.
of all the interaction, but the Bible says that he continued knocking there and the Bible
says that when they had opened the door and saw him, they were astonished. They were astonished.
Listen, I understand sometimes today we may act like and we may pretend that we're not
astonished when God answers prayer because we know that God is able to. Listen, when
God answers in a great way, you'll be astonished. Your faith will be increased. You will have
joy. It's not that you were praying with unbelief. It's not that you were praying with doubting.
You're just astonished to see what God was able to do because God often works in such
a way that would cause his people to stand in awe of who he is. And that's what I believe
happens here. Notice what happens in verse 17. They were astonished. I'm not sure how,
what they said, but in verse 17 it says, but he beckoning unto them with the hand to hold
their peace. I think there were a lot of questions. There was some, you ever, I mean, what's going,
Peter, what happened? How did you? I think that's what happens. That's what I would be
wondering. Peter, what happened? How did you get here? And it says that he was beckoning
unto them to hold their peace. And then notice the Bible says he declared unto them how the
Lord had brought him out of the prison. And he said, go, show these things unto James
and to the brethren. And he departed and went to another place. Obviously there's a, it's
a different James. It's not the James that was killed at the beginning of the text. But
we find here that, that Peter, the verse 17 is a short verse. But what we read from verse
six down through verse number 11 is what Peter's rehearsing to them. What God did.
Because it says that he declared unto them how the Lord had brought him out of the prison.
Isn't it exciting when God answers prayer? In verse 18 it says, now as soon as it was
day, there was no small stir among the soldiers that was become, what was become of Peter.
Can you imagine the soldiers when they awakened? I mean, if you were chained to Peter and you
opened your eyes and Peter wasn't there, how would you feel? Knowing that you're going
to have to give an account, by the way. Maybe you'd ask the two guys that were watching
the door, hey, what happened to Peter? Did you see him leave? What's going on? I mean,
could there be confusion? A level of concern? Stress? It says, there was no small stir
among the soldiers. Verse 19, and when Herod had sought for him and found him not, he examined
the keepers and commanded that they should be put to death. He went down from Judea to
Caesarea and their abode. Why did he command that they be put to death? Because they had
a prisoner that was no longer there. It was a serious consequence. I want you to understand
this morning that God is able to work in such a way, not only would He cause us to rejoice,
but the lost people are able to sit there and say, I don't know how this happened. Previously,
if you look in Acts 4 and Acts 5, those that were apprehended, they weren't there. Where
are they? Well, they're preaching. How'd they get there? God delivered them. This morning,
I said it in the beginning of the message, the 21st century church, we need to stop trying
to be an entertaining church. We need to be a praying church. A praying church. This morning,
as we look at the admonition from 1 Timothy chapter 2, and we've studied it the last several
weeks, Paul makes it very clear in the inspiration of the Holy Ghost, I exhort therefore that
first of all, supplications, prayers, intercessions, and giving of thanks be made for all men.
You skip down to verse 8, it says, I will therefore that men pray everywhere, lifting
up holy hands without wrath and doubting. As you study the book of Acts, you say, man,
how did they accomplish everything that they accomplished? Well, there are several keys
I believe that God gives us as we study the book of Acts. They were filled with the Spirit
of God. They believed in imminent return after they saw Him ascend and heard the angel say
He's coming back. But I want you to understand they were a praying church. And God hears
and answers prayer. God delights in showing Himself mighty. And we, we need to be a praying
church, individually and corporately. A praying church. I believe this morning, this book,
there are many prayer promises that God gives us. Many accounts of God's people praying
and God answering. What we need, we need to see God work. It is time, the psalmist said,
for thee, O Lord, to work. You know what moves the hand of God? The prayers of His
people. The prayers of His people. This morning, just like the book of Acts and the first century
church was a praying church, we today, in 2024, we need to be a praying church. A praying
church. Let's pray together. Father, we love You. We thank You for loving us. We thank
You for the privilege of being able to have a Bible, to be able to study Thy Word, to
go through and to see how You worked and what You did. Lord, we stand in awe of reading
this account in Acts 12. For some this morning, they've heard it before. For others, perhaps,
this morning is the first time they ever heard this passage of Scripture. They heard about
the persecution, but they heard, as you think about the situation there that the church
was facing, and they had the opportunity to hear about the supplication, the church praying.
You working and answering and delivering miraculously. God, how we stand in awe of
who You are. I pray this morning that we would respond, just as we've been ready to receive.
God that You would challenge us in our own personal lives, corporately that You would
challenge us with this area of prayer. That as the early church is characterized as being
a praying church, the Fellowship Baptist Church in Oakton would be characterized as
being a praying church. God, we believe this morning that You hear and answer prayer. And
I pray that that belief would be evidenced in our behavior because what we do speaks
louder than what we say. God, I pray that our families, that their children would see
their parents' belief in prayer. Prayer is a vital part of our lives. I pray that in
these moments of invitation, if there's one that's not sure of heaven, they do not know
with 100% confidence that heaven is their home. And I pray that we'd have an opportunity
to take a Bible and show them how they could know for sure that heaven's their home. God,
I pray for every child of God. Would You help us to be responsive this morning? We'll give
You the honor and glory for all that You'll do. For it's in Christ's name we pray. Would
You stand with me? At the end of each of our services, we have an invitation where we give
you an opportunity.