what a great truth and we're looking forward to going through that passage of Scripture on Wednesday nights here over the next several weeks this
morning if you have a Bible with you turn to the book of 1st John if you will
1st John chapter 3 and some of you are already in Colossians expecting for us to be in Colossians this morning
You'll have to just keep turning further in the New Testament get to the book of 1st John and of course many of you know
I hope that none of you have forgotten that today is Valentine's Day
And it's kind of interesting as we think about the the special day that is on our calendar today
We understand there are many that will seek to express their love through various means in fact I read this morning
that in the United States of America the projected expenditure on
Valentine's Day is
22 billion dollars
that's a lot of money and
Some of you may have contributed to that fund right you went and got some flowers
you got a card you got maybe some chocolate and
purchasing those things and
we understand the way in which we would seek to
express our love and
The thing that's interesting and we understand the truth of the book of Ephesians
The Bible says that husbands that were to love our wives
The Bible says that were to love our wives in the same manner in which Christ loved the church and gave himself for it
And as we think about the the day today
Valentine's Day on the calendar
And many will seek to express love again
22 billion dollars nearly that's the projected expenditure
I'm not sure why they projected to be lower because last year it was
27.4 billion and so they've projected it to be lower this year
But needless to say that's a lot of money that will be spent by individuals seeking to express their love
And we find that as we would think about the subject matter of love as
certainly as the people of God we must reflect upon the love of God and
We think and we understand the Bible teaches us much about God's love and I'm so thankful
For the truth that God gives us with regard to his love for us as
We think about the love of God
We understand that the price that was paid to express his love for us
Far exceeds any dollar value we could ever put
That we would deal with here in our country because it was with the precious blood of Christ
We're not redeemed with corruptible things such as silver and gold, but we're redeemed how with the precious
Blood of Christ as of a lamb that was slain from the foundation of the world is what Peter tells us and I'm so thankful
For that truth often we sing with the children Jesus loves me this I know
For the Bible tells me so and what a blessing to sing that song
One of the great hymns that we sing is a hymn that's entitled Jesus loves even me
Jesus loves even me. I am so glad that Jesus loves me
Jesus loves even me the songwriter said there are wonderful things that he reads in the Bible
But the dearest of them is this that Jesus loves me. And so if you're taking notes this morning
I've simply entitled the message Jesus loves you and you know, there's a
truth to that statement that would cause us as children of God to rejoice greatly and we understand what that means and we
Understand the significance of that statement when someone says to you that Jesus loves you it causes you to have
Just a great
Comfort in knowing and recognizing being reminded of that truth
However, there are many in our world today that do not know the love of God
They do not understand
What it is that is meant when the Word of God says for God so loved the world that he gave his only begotten
Son that whosoever believe it than him should not perish, but have everlasting life. They don't understand
The full nature of the love of God in 1st John 3 in verse number 16 often
We can quote John 3 16 is of great interest that 1st John 3 16 is very similar to John 3 16
The Bible says this as John the Apostle is writing under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God
Notice what he says hereby
perceive we the love of God
Because he laid down his life for us
Because he laid down his life for us and we ought to lay down our lives
For the brethren want to focus on the first portion of this verse of Scripture this morning
Hereby perceive we the love of God
Because he laid down his life
For us that word perceive is an interesting word. The word means to know or to understand
It means to have knowledge of to perceive to have knowledge of and in John says hereby
Perceive we the love of God
Because he laid down his life for us
brother Michael told us how that they were gonna have a
meeting there in the Gambia and how that the
Preacher was gonna preach on the deity of Christ and what a great subject matter. What a great truth and we've dealt with
Often in in the recent weeks and months about the Lord Jesus Christ and that he is God and God in flesh and what a
blessing to
understand the truth of the
Incarnation and the deity of Christ and the eternality of Christ
In fact, we started the book of Colossians last Sunday morning
we dealt with the subject matter of the exalted Christ and how
Wonderful he is and you find in this text of Scripture see there are many today that still deny the fact that Jesus is God
They're okay with saying that Jesus is a prophet a teacher a good man
So on and so forth, but we find that Jesus is God
The Apostle Paul as he's preaching and teaching and he goes to the city of Thessalonica. He says that this Jesus is
The Christ the Messiah the anointed one the promised one but notice here
there are many portions of Scripture that you can go to to acknowledge and understand the
The the deity of Christ and the fact that he is God notice what is said here pot hereby perceive
We the love of God because he laid down his life
for us who was it that went to the cross of Calvary Jesus Christ, he is God and
That's just a side note for free this morning. But there are some that still
Have difficulties with that question that Jesus asked to the disciples
Whom do men say that I the son of man am
they said some say that you're John the Baptist one of the prophets so on and so forth and
Peter with great boldness and courage stands up after Jesus says but whom say ye that I am
Thou art the Christ the Son of the Living God
And it's amazing to me
How many in our society today in our world?
Continue to have confusion with regard to the person of Jesus Christ
and we know that's because of the enemy the evil one and
We find here the truth of the deity even revealed to us in this verse of Scripture
If you're taking notes this morning, I want to point this
Truth out number one to be confident of God's love for you
We need to be confident of God's love for us
The word confident means to have full belief
It carries with the idea of being fully assured positive without suspicion I
like this definition from the 1828 Noah Webster's dictionary, it says this having an
excess of assurance
to be confident having an excess of assurance to
have full belief to be fully assured and persuaded to be
Confident of the love of God as we would look at the passage of Scripture here in 1st John 3 in verse number 16 the
Word of God tells us that this is how we can know or understand to have knowledge of the love of God hereby
Perceive we the love of God because he laid down his life for us
We find that throughout the Word of God his love is declared for us
And I'm so thankful that God has declared his love for us in his word
But he goes far beyond simply declaring his love for us. We find that he demonstrated his love for us
We know the verse of Scripture in Romans 5 in verse number 8 where the Bible says but God
Commended his love toward us and that while we were yet sinners Christ died for us
You understand this morning that we do not deserve the love of God
You cannot earn the love of God. The truth of God's Word is that he loves you
You can't earn it
There are people trying to earn God's love
It's not anything of us that would cause God to love us. We were at enmity with him
Amen, but it's because of God's character in God's nature
It's because of the truth that John reveals to us even in this book in 1st
John 4 in verse number 8 again in verse number 16 of that same chapter. The Bible says God is
Love God is love
We know that there's much confusion about that subject matter this morning in the world in which we live and I do not seek
To spend a ton of time on that part or that aspect of things this morning
But we do understand there's confusion amongst the general populace with regard to what it means that God loves you
There are many today that would take that statement and they would say well
Well, God is love and that means I can do whatever I want to do because God is love.
And that's not truly what it means.
See, God's love, I know I've often said this, but it's certainly worth repeating.
The love of God is best described not as being permissive, but being protective.
It's a protective love.
It's not a permissive love.
If you love your children, you seek to protect them.
You don't just simply permit your children to do whatever they want to do because you
love them.
That'd be nonsense.
And God loves us, and we need to be confident of God's love.
The Bible says that God is love.
The Bible says this in 1 John 4, in verse number 19, we love Him, why?
Because He first loved us.
God doesn't love us because we loved Him.
We love Him because He loved us.
And the reality for some of us this morning, we can understand that there was a time in
which we were probably ignorant of God's love.
There was a time in which maybe for some they grew up in a Christian home and they grew
up in a church environment and they sang from the youngest of age, Jesus loves me, this
I know.
And they had understood the fact that God loves them.
And when I would have the opportunity, and even still today, if we have a vacation Bible
school and I'm leading songs and kind of overseeing the vacation Bible school, when we sing that
song I'll say to the children, can you tell me a verse that would prove that?
Because the song says, Jesus loves me, this I know, for the Bible tells me so.
It's important that the children understand that Jesus loves them is not based solely
upon my word or me telling them, it's based upon the truth of God's word.
And no doubt one of the little children will say, John 3, 16, for God so loved the world,
and it causes my heart to rejoice that they understand that truth.
But for some of us that did not grow up in that type of environment, maybe there was
a time that we were ignorant of the love of God.
We didn't know that God loved us.
We didn't understand what that meant.
We find that we love Him because He first loved us.
Paul in closing the book of 2 Corinthians is writing to that group of believers.
He refers to the Lord as being the God of love and peace.
It's interesting for in the book of 2 Corinthians he begins that book by speaking about, in
the first chapter, about the fact that He is the God of all comfort, and He is.
And then he closes the book by reminding the believers in Corinth that He is the God of
love and peace, and He is.
It's His nature.
It's who He is.
He's just.
We understand that truth and understand the way in which those particular attributes coincide
one with the other in perfect harmony because God is perfect.
Just to remind you of what Jesus said to the disciples often, turn back to John 13
if you will, often we are mindful of this truth in John 13 when the Lord Jesus Christ
would give this new commandment, and we often speak about the love that we're to have one
for another as the people of God, as the children of God.
And what a blessing to understand that Jesus said, by this, by our love one for another,
shall all men know that ye are my disciples.
The love that we have one for another.
But I want you to notice what He says in John 13 and verse 34.
A new commandment I give unto you, that ye love one another, and then look at this phrase,
as I have loved you, as I have loved you, that ye also love one another.
He says to the disciples, as I have loved you.
If you look over in chapter number 15, a few pages over in verse number 12, again He
repeats this truth.
He says, this is my commandment, that ye love one another as I have loved you.
See, this truth this morning of being confident of God's love for you is important.
To have that full assurance, to have that excess of assurance, and we understand that
when we're fully assured, that when we have no suspicion about God's love for us because
we're confident, it's based upon the truth that's found in the Word of God.
God is not a man that He should lie.
He's given us, He's declared for us, He's demonstrated to us, His love for us.
I want you to understand this morning, think about this, John, the Apostle John, he was
confident that Jesus loved him.
He was confident that Jesus loved him.
In fact, many of you know this, but look back, if you will, still in the book of John,
we'll look at a few more verses here in the book of John, go back, if you will, to chapter
number 13.
You were there in chapter 15, I'll just go back a few pages to John chapter number 13.
You'll be mindful that the passage of Scripture begins, I'll just read the end of verse number
1, that it says this, He loved them unto the end.
If you're familiar with the book of John, you'll understand and be mindful of the fact
that it's in this passage of Scripture in which Jesus will wash the feet of the disciples.
And He teaches them a lesson, He gives them that lesson with regard to service, and then
we come down and we continue to go through the chapter and we come to verse number 23.
In the Bible, look at verse 22, it says, then the disciples looked one on another, doubting
of whom He spake.
What was it that He said?
Well, Jesus said in verse 21, verily, verily, I say unto you that one of you shall betray
me.
Verily, verily, of a truth of a truth, one of you shall betray me.
And the disciples begin to look at one another, they're doubting of whom it was that Jesus
spake.
And look at verse 23, now there was leaning on Jesus' bosom, one of His disciples, notice
this phrase, whom Jesus loved.
Whom Jesus loved.
You know that the apostle John, if you study through the entire book of John, you'll find
that he does not refer to himself as John.
He refers to himself as the one whom Jesus loved.
Isn't that precious?
He was confident that Jesus loved him.
I don't believe there's any doubt in his mind, he had that full assurance.
He was fully persuaded, why?
Because he heard what was said, but he also was walking with the Lord Jesus Christ during
his earthly ministry, and no doubt, on more than one occasion, the Lord would express
his love, and the Bible says that this man, John, he refers to himself as the one whom
Jesus loved.
We see it in chapter number 20.
In chapter number 20.
Think about this, in verse number 1, it was the first day of the week, and here comes
Mary Magdalene early to the tomb, and of course it's after the crucifixion and burial.
The Bible says that she seeth the stone taken away from the sepulcher.
It says in verse number 2, then she runneth and cometh to Simon Peter, and to the other
disciple whom Jesus loved.
The other disciple whom Jesus loved.
Who is that other disciple?
John.
The other disciple whom Jesus loved.
And saith unto them, they have taken away the Lord out of the sepulcher, and we know
not where they have laid him.
We find that as we go through the passage of Scripture, we understand the great day
that that was, and then we come to the end of the chapter, and we see that Jesus of course
appears to his disciples as they're gathered together, and you come to the 21st chapter,
it's in that chapter in which it's Peter that says, I go a fishing, and they say unto him,
we also go with thee.
And Jesus is going to show up.
They're out there on the boat, and they're going to try to fish, and of course the Bible
says that they caught nothing.
If you have some time to study between this passage of Scripture and the previous record
in which there was the draft of fishes when Jesus told them after a night of toiling and
catching nothing, he says, cast out into the deep for a draft of fishes, and Peter says,
Lord we've toiled all the night, nevertheless at thy word, and he let down the net, there's
such a great catch, and here Jesus calls and says, have you caught anything?
And they say, no, we've caught nothing.
The Bible says here in verse number seven, well let me back up, because in verse number
five it says, then Jesus saith unto them, children, have ye any meat?
They answered him, no, they'd caught nothing.
Verse six, he said unto them, cast the net on the right side of the ship, and ye shall
find.
They cast therefore, and now they were not able to draw it for the multitude of fishes.
Therefore that disciple whom Jesus loved saith unto Peter, it is the Lord.
Now when Simon Peter heard that it was the Lord, he girded his fisher's coat unto him
for he was naked and he did cast himself into the sea.
We find that a little while later after the Lord was speaking to Peter and asking Peter,
do you love me?
And going through that portion of Scripture, and Jesus tells him in verse 19 to follow
me, and Peter in verse number 20, it says, then Peter turning about, seeth the disciple
whom Jesus loved following."
See, we could look at a number of other passages
in the book of John,
but not only was John confident,
but the other disciples.
I mean, Mary Magdalene goeth to Him
that the Lord loveth.
And we find that John had this confidence,
this assurance of God's love for him.
I believe this morning that Paul
was confident that Jesus loved him.
In fact, we find that often Paul would preach
about the love of Christ.
Often, as he would minister to those
that God would give him the opportunity
to minister to,
he would speak about the great love
of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.
The love of God.
In Galatians 2, oftentimes we will recite
this verse of Scripture
and speak about the importance of living
the crucified life, if you will,
and understanding that we have
been bought with a price
and we're to glorify our Father
who is in heaven.
And we find that Paul,
as he would make this declaration here
to the believers in the region of Galatia,
he says this in Galatians 2,
I am crucified with Christ.
Nevertheless, I live.
Yet not I, but Christ liveth in me.
And the life which I now live in the flesh,
I live by the faith of the Son of God
who loved me.
Who loved me.
And gave Himself for me.
What did John say in 1 John 3
and verse 16?
Hereby perceive we the love of God,
because He laid down His life for us.
And Paul says here in Galatians 2
and verse 20 that He loved me
and gave Himself for me.
In the book of Ephesians in chapter 2,
Paul is beginning the passage
speaking about the condition of all mankind
being lost,
being separated from God
because of our sin.
Being dead in our trespasses and sins.
But you notice in Ephesians 2
and verse 4,
the Bible begins with these two words,
but God.
But God,
who is rich in mercy,
notice this,
that His great love
wherewith He loved us.
I believe this morning
that we need to be confident of God's love for us.
I believe this morning that
John was confident that Jesus loved him.
I believe this morning that Paul was confident
that Jesus loved him.
I wonder this morning,
how confident are we
that God loves us?
Are there times in which we doubt
the love of God?
Are there times in which
we are lacking that certainty?
I believe this morning that we need to be confident.
Remember, that word that John uses,
hereby perceive,
it means to know or understand,
to have knowledge of,
and it lends itself to being confident of something
because I know it
and I can have assurance of it.
I can be confident of it.
I wonder this morning as we think about
the Apostle Paul preaching about the love of God.
Certainly, he was convinced
and he was confident in this truth.
Thus, he proclaimed the message.
And what a great message it is.
I want to go over to the book of John
in the 11th chapter.
As we think about this really
as a first point,
but almost we can look at it as an introduction
because I want to look at the
really, we can't look at the entire passage
for sake of time,
but I want to look at John 11.
And if I were to give some outline points,
if you will, to the message this morning,
I'd say number one,
that we're to be confident of the love of God for us.
But then I'd say this, number two,
never allow circumstances
to cause you to doubt the love of God.
Never allow circumstances
You understand this morning
that the enemy wants you to doubt the love of God.
He does.
The enemy wants you to look at your circumstances
and look at the things that are taking place in your life
and perhaps some hardships that you're dealing with,
perhaps some adversities that you're facing in life.
And the enemy wants to whisper in your ear,
God doesn't really love you.
Because if God really loved you,
He wouldn't do this, that, or the other.
But we need to this morning,
see, we're confident of God's love,
and we need to never allow circumstances
to cause us to doubt that love.
What God has declared,
what God has demonstrated,
we can't let doubt creep in
and overcome what has been declared in the Word of God.
We see in John 11,
the reality is this passage of Scripture
is a really exciting passage of Scripture.
It's in this passage
that Jesus stands at the tomb of Lazarus
and says, Lazarus, come forth!
I mean, what a powerful passage of Scripture
is John 11.
But I want you to notice some things
in this passage that I hope will help us.
Because we find that we are to be confident
of the love of God,
but we find that there are times
in which our circumstances can be adverse.
There are times in which we deal with hardships in life.
And here in John 11, I want you to notice,
the Bible tells us about Lazarus being sick.
And notice in v. 3,
it says this,
therefore his sisters,
we know those are Mary and Martha,
the sisters of Lazarus,
and they are going to send to Jesus,
if we understand what's taking place here,
in v. 2, it says,
it was that Mary which anointed the Lord with ointment,
wiped His feet with her hair,
whose brother Lazarus was sick.
And so, Mary and Martha,
the sisters of Lazarus,
they sent unto Him.
Him is Jesus,
we understand as it begins saying this,
Lord.
And so they send to Jesus,
and I want you to notice what they say.
Behold,
He whom thou lovest is sick.
Now, could they not have just said,
Lazarus is sick?
Right?
In fact, they could have simply said,
our brother is sick.
Jesus knew who it was.
Jesus knew the family.
But when they send to Jesus,
I love the expression.
They say, Lord,
behold,
He whom thou lovest is sick.
Now I believe, without being able to go through
the entire passage of Scripture this morning,
that Mary and Martha probably had the thought
that because Jesus loved Him,
that Jesus was going to come and heal Him.
Because when Jesus arrives,
the first response of Martha and Mary
is that if you had been here,
He would not die.
Look at it and you can read the whole passage
and you can see that.
And so I believe that in their mind,
they understood who Jesus was.
No doubt they had heard of and seen miracles.
They knew what He was capable of doing,
for they expressed, they say,
if thou hadst been here,
my brother had not died.
What does that communicate to us?
That Jesus could have healed him.
So when they send to the Lord,
they say, Lord,
behold,
He whom thou lovest is sick.
And then the Bible tells us in v. 4,
when Jesus heard that, He said,
this sickness is not unto death,
but for the glory of God,
the Son of God might be glorified thereby.
Notice v. 5.
Now, Jesus loved Martha and her sister.
That's Mary and Lazarus.
It's interesting as I look at the passage of Scripture,
that Mary and Martha were confident
that Jesus loved Lazarus.
No doubt.
He whom thou lovest is sick.
They knew, they understood,
they had confidence that Jesus loved their brother.
And then we find in v. 5
that the Word of God reveals to us
that Jesus indeed did love Mary and Martha and Lazarus.
We understand there are times in which we can quote John 3.16
and we can speak about the fact that God so loved the world,
but when we really take and make it personal
that God loves me as an individual.
He knows everything about you.
He knows everything about me and He still loves me.
And He still loves you.
Isn't that amazing?
It's amazing.
Those things that perhaps you'd hope
that no one else ever knew about you.
He knows.
And He still loves you.
Here, the confidence of the sisters,
Mary and Martha,
that Jesus loved and then the declaration
where the Bible tells us that Jesus did love them.
We understand that personally.
We find that as you would continue
to walk through the passage of Scripture,
Jesus would say,
look in v. 6 before He makes this statement,
when He had heard therefore that He was sick,
He abode two days still in the same place
where He was.
Now what would you desire?
An immediate departure.
You are not looking for a divine delay.
You're looking for an immediate departure.
Amen?
From Jesus two days.
It wasn't that He didn't receive the message.
It wasn't that He didn't know what was going on.
It's that He's God.
And He says, I have a plan.
I have a purpose.
I'm going to accomplish something here.
We find that after this delay,
it says that He said to His disciples,
let us go into Judea again.
And the disciples of course were concerned
because the Jews had sought to stone Him
and so on and so forth.
And we understand that if you go
through the entire book of John,
His hour was not yet come,
though it's not said specifically here.
But we know that when His hour was come,
that He would lay down His life.
But notice in v. 11,
these things said He,
and after that He saith unto them,
Our friend Lazarus sleepeth.
But I go that I may awake him out of sleep.
The Bible says that His disciples said,
If he sleep, he shall do well.
I mean, we heard that He was sick too.
And oftentimes, somebody says if you're sick,
get some rest.
And Jesus speaks plainly to them.
They did not understand
what Jesus was communicating to them.
And the Bible says in v. 13,
Howbeit Jesus spake of His death,
but they thought that He had spoken
of taking rest and sleep.
And then Jesus said unto them plainly
in v. 14, Lazarus is dead.
Lazarus is dead.
And in v. 15,
I cannot develop all of this.
I've preached from this passage of Scripture before
and focused more upon the truth of v. 15
than I have upon the love
that we're focusing on this morning.
We find in v. 15, the Bible says,
I am glad for your sakes that I was not there.
I was glad for your sakes that I was not there.
For the intent ye may believe.
Nevertheless, let us go unto Him.
You know, there are some times in your life,
there are some times in my life,
there's a situation that's recorded here
in the lives of Mary, Martha, and Lazarus
in which God is seeking to do something great.
And He's seeking to stretch us
and grow us and develop us.
And in those circumstances,
because of our human nature,
we can sometimes feel isolated.
Sometimes we can feel overwhelmed.
And we can come to the place
where the enemy at that moment
will come and say,
Jesus doesn't really love you.
We believe this morning He can do anything.
He could heal this man from a distance.
He could have immediately went.
He could have prevented this.
But you understand this morning
that as we look at the passage of Scripture,
that it wasn't because He didn't love them.
He's trying to develop them.
If you'd been here,
you wouldn't have died.
Fast forward, if you will,
to the passage of Scripture
in v. 32,
when Mary was come where Jesus was
and saw Him,
she fell down on His feet saying unto Him,
Lord, if Thou hadst been here,
my brother had not died.
The same words that Martha spoke earlier
in the passage of Scripture.
When Jesus therefore saw her weeping
and the Jews also weeping
which came with her,
He groaned in the Spirit and was troubled.
Those Jews that were there,
it was a very custom, cultural thing
that would take place.
The death of a loved one
where some folks would come
and they would be the mourners.
And they would weep and mourn
and so on and so forth.
And the Bible says in v. 34
that Jesus said,
where have you laid Him?
And they said unto Him,
Lord, come and see.
And then the Bible says here in v. 35,
Jesus wept.
And then the Bible says this in v. 36,
Then said the Jews,
these mourners that were there,
Behold, how He loved Him.
And this morning,
the truth of God's love
and being confident of God's love
will bring us to a place
where we're never going to allow
circumstances to cause us
to doubt the love of God.
Because I'm confident that God has declared
and He's demonstrated,
hereby perceive we the love of God
because He laid down His life for us.
And we find here in the passage of Scripture
that there were some of those Jews
that also said in v. 37,
Could not this man,
speaking of Jesus,
which opened the eyes of the blind,
and you would look back in John 9
and see that great miracle.
And the Bible says,
have caused that even this man
should not have died.
Even these Jews that were mourning,
they acknowledged the love
that Jesus had for this man Lazarus,
but they also acknowledged the fact
that Jesus could have prevented his death.
But remember what He said back
in the 15th verse,
I'm glad for your sakes that I was not there
to the intent you may believe.
Jesus will stand at that tomb.
And He says, take ye away the stone.
In v. 39.
Of course, there's an objection.
He hath been dead for four days
and surely by now he stinketh.
Jesus said, roll back that stone.
In v. 43, it says,
when He thus had spoken,
He cried with a loud voice,
Lazarus, come forth.
And the Bible says,
he that was dead came forth,
bound hand and foot with grave clothes.
And his face was bound about with a napkin.
Jesus saith unto them,
loose him and let him go.
And I want you to notice in v. 45,
the Bible begins with this word, then.
Then.
Many of the Jews which came to Mary
and had seen the things which Jesus did,
what's it say?
Believed on Him.
Then.
They already believed that He could heal them.
Martha believed it.
Mary believed it.
The Jews believed it.
But because of that divine delay of Jesus,
now He's dead for four days
and He calls Him forth out of the grave.
Then they believed
because they saw this great miracle.
Remember, the Bible said in v. 4
that this sickness is not unto death
but for the glory of God
that the Son of God might be glorified thereby.
In John 9, the passage that deals with the blind man
that was healed,
the Bible says that the disciples asked Him,
saying, Master, who did sin?
This man or his parents who was born blind?
And Jesus said neither hath this man sinned
nor his parents,
but that the works of God
should be made manifest in him
so that God would be glorified.
And we find in this passage of Scripture
that the Bible begins
as this particular event, if you will,
is recorded for us.
It begins by Mary and Martha
sending to Jesus and saying,
Lord, behold, he whom Thou lovest is sick.
And then the Bible says a couple of verses later
that Jesus loved Martha and her sister
and Lazarus.
Even the Jews that were there as mourners,
they say, behold, how He loved him.
You know, it's very possible that a circumstance like this
could cause someone to doubt the love of God.
It could.
Because the enemy wants you to doubt the love of God anyway.
The enemy wants you to doubt everything that God said.
How do we know that?
Yea, hath God said.
Is that not how it started in the garden
in Genesis chapter number three?
Right?
Yea, hath God said.
Why is it that people struggle
with their confidence of their salvation?
Because people want to doubt.
Because the enemy wants to cause someone to doubt
what God said.
I don't know who it was.
I don't remember.
But a theologian of yesteryear said,
never put a question mark where God put a period.
I like that.
It's a simple statement.
But how true.
Listen, this morning, circumstances will change.
Circumstances will change.
Have you found it to be so?
Circumstances change.
Sometimes you feel like life is a roller coaster.
Right?
And oftentimes when you're up at the top
and things are going great
and you're on the mountaintop, so to speak,
and man, the blessings are flowing
and it seems like everything's going well,
typically at that time the enemy doesn't come whispering,
saying, God doesn't love you.
Oh man, because you ain't going to doubt God's love
when things are going wonderful.
But it's when that valley comes into play.
That roller coaster, if you will,
I hate roller coasters, by the way.
way, but that roller coaster, so to speak, comes down. I have to take Advil before I
go into the theme park, and then I take some with me so that later on I can take some more.
But the reality is that when you're in that valley, when those circumstances are challenging,
when it seems like everything's falling apart, when it feels like no one's near and no one
cares, the enemy's going to come. The enemy's going to say, you still think God loves you?
You still think that? Oh, be confident of it. Never allow circumstances to cause you
to doubt the love of God. Never put a question mark where God has put a period. Hereby perceive
we the love of God, because He laid down His life for us. It's settled. He loves you.
He loves me. Circumstances are going to change, but God's love remains constant. Circumstances
will change, but God's love remains constant. Romans 8, look there at that great passage,
if you will. In Romans chapter number 8, Paul gives us a phenomenal declaration with
regard to the love of God. I'll begin reading in verse number 31. The Bible says this in
Romans 8 in verse number 31, what shall we then say to these things? If God be for us,
who can be against us? He that spared not His own Son, but delivered Him up for us all,
how shall He not with Him also freely give us all things? Who shall lay anything to the
charge of God's elect? It is God that justifieth. Who is He that condemneth? It is Christ that
died, yea rather, that is risen again, who is even at the right hand of God, who also
maketh intercession for us. Look at this question in verse 35. Who shall separate us from the
love of Christ? Those circumstances. Who shall separate us from the love of Christ? Shall
it be tribulation, or distress, or persecution, or famine, or nakedness, or peril, or sword?
Perhaps if we had time this morning to go through each one of those words that are mentioned,
we could find how in those circumstances, someone might feel like they've been separated
from the love of Christ. The enemy wants you to think that. As it is written in verse 36,
so that's why Paul is going to give us an answer, for thy sake we are killed all the
day long, we are accounted as sheep for the slaughter. Nay, in all these things we are
more than conquerors, notice this, through Him that loved us. And then notice the language,
for I am persuaded. Don't you like that word? I use the word confident in our message this
morning as our points, and again that word has the idea of being fully persuaded, fully
assured of, being positive, without suspicion, having an excess of assurance, and Paul says,
for I am persuaded that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor
powers, nor things present, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other
creature shall be able to separate us from the love of God, which is in Christ Jesus
our Lord. The question of verse number 35, who shall separate us from the love of Christ?
Paul gives an answer in verse 38 and 39, he says, I am persuaded, if I could summarize
it, nothing, nothing, no other thing, no other creature, nothing can separate us from the
love of God, which is in Christ Jesus our Lord. This morning, when we're confident of
God's love for us individually, like John was, like Paul was, when we have that confidence
that God loves us, that we are fully persuaded and assured of, that we have that excess of
assurance that, as John said, hereby perceive we the love of God, because He laid down His
life for us. When I'm confident of God's love, I'm probably going to share that message
with more people, because I'm confident of it. Amen? If you're doubting it, if you're
not even sure that God loves you, you probably ain't going to tell anybody else that God
loves them. Right? Anyone ever ask you for a recommendation for dinner? I want to go
to a place, you know, where would you recommend? I was thinking about, it's Valentine's Day,
I was thinking about taking my wife to such and such place, and you've been there before,
and it was not very good. And what do you say? Well, I mean, maybe I'd go somewhere
else. You know, I don't know that I would go there. Why? Because you're not persuaded,
you're not confident yourself. So you're not going to make the recommendation that somebody
else goes there. But if you've been there, man, that was the best fill-in-the-blank I've
ever had. I mean, the steak there, the chicken parmesan, wherever you're going, it was great.
See, this morning when I am convinced of God's love for me, and I'm assured that what He's
done for me, He could do for others. Listen, our God is no respecter of persons. The Bible
plainly teaches us that. He's no respecter of persons. And I can go, and I've had, I
know I've shared already, I had more people this week, I had two, one on Friday, one yesterday,
and I said, man, I like your mask. Jesus loves you. I hate wearing that thing. I really
do. I don't like wearing a mask. I wear it as little as I possibly have to. But if I'm
going to have to go into an establishment and wear it, man, I want it to have a message
that someone's going to read. I was at Costco on Friday. The lady at Costco, she's the cashier,
and she's starting to help the fellow that's in line in front of me, and she looks back
to just see if the lane there was filled up or whatever, and she saw my mask, and she
stopped dead stream in what she was doing, forgot about the guy who was in front of her
and said, I like your mask, where'd you get it? They probably won't let me wear it here,
but I'm going to wear it everywhere else. That's what she said to me. And the guy yesterday,
said, man, I like your mask. See, I've had some opportunities to talk to people because
of that, but I can tell them that God loves them. I can tell them of the love of God.
I'm confident in the truth. I'm confident. And we need to be careful never to allow circumstances
to cause us to doubt the love of God. There's some circumstances that we can face that are
just, from human perspective, very challenging. When the doctor says the diagnosis is fill
in the blank. When the employer says, I'm sorry, but you got to make some cuts. I mean,
whatever the difficulty is, the reality is that there's something that can happen in
your life that's a difficulty that for somebody else, it doesn't even really faze them. And
then something happens in your life that seems to crush you, that somebody else just, it
is what it is. I mean, no big deal. We're all made up different. But when those circumstances
that are adverse come, would you understand this morning that circumstances are going
to change, but God's love is constant. There's nothing that can separate us from the love
of God. As many today will celebrate this holiday, spend nearly $22 billion on cards
and chocolate and flowers and whatever else. I hope this morning that we'd be reminded
of the love of God. Jesus loves you. What a precious truth that we find in the Bible.
We need to go through every day of our life, being confident of that. Maybe it'd be good
to refer to ourselves like John did. The one that Jesus loves. Isn't that good? Because
man, we're reminded every day and confident. God loves me. He loves me. Let's pray together.
Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. Thank you for your word. Simple message
this morning, but your word is powerful. And I know how the enemy works. I know that the
enemy would like to cause the people of God to doubt the love of God. Especially when
those circumstances are overwhelming, challenging, adverse.
And God, I pray, even as we've picked through a little bit of John 11, would You help us
to never doubt Your love.
Never put a question mark where You put a period.
We'd have that confidence, that full assurance.
We thank You for the truth of Your Word that reveals to us the love that You have for us.
I pray that if there'd be one that's never trusted Christ as their Savior, they've never
fully understood this truth that God loves them.
He demonstrated that love by sending His Son to die upon the cross of Calvary.
God in flesh paid with His precious blood a debt that could in no other way be paid,
that debt being sin.
I pray the Holy Spirit of God would convict sinners, convince them of their sin of Christ's
righteousness of judgment to come.
For us as the people of God, would You encourage us this morning through this truth?
Would You help us to, with confidence, declare this truth to others?
I pray that You'd have Your will in way in these few moments of invitation, for it's
in Christ's name we pray.
Would You stand with us?