And the book of Hosea, chapter number 2.
Before we get to the second chapter, I'm going to give some introduction here
to the book of Hosea.
And the question specifically is from the second chapter,
a reference in verse number 15 specifically.
But really, instead of just jumping right into that verse of Scripture,
give a little bit of a background, if you will, to the book of Hosea.
I believe the book of Hosea is a fascinating book.
Hosea was a prophet that had a long ministry
and specifically he was ministering to Israel.
When we refer to Israel in that context, it's the ten tribes of the north.
He's ministering well after the divided kingdom.
And we find that after the divided kingdom,
there's Israel to the north, Judah to the south.
And this man, Hosea, was called of the Lord to minister,
to prophesy to the ten northern tribes, the tribe of Israel.
We find that Hosea 1.1 provides for us the timing of his ministry.
The Bible says in Hosea 1, in verse number 1,
the word of the Lord that came unto Hosea, the son of Berei,
in the days of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah.
So God helps us understand who's reigning in Judah
during the time of Hosea's ministry,
though his ministry is specifically predominantly to the northern tribes,
not to Judah.
And then it tells us, and in the days of Jeroboam,
the son of Joash, king of Israel.
Now, it's important that we understand the history that God provides us
in the book of 1 and 2 Kings.
Of course, in 1 and 2 Chronicles as well, there are two Jeroboams.
This is Jeroboam II.
This is not the first Jeroboam,
when it first had a divided kingdom of Jeroboam and Rehoboam.
But we find this is Jeroboam II,
and it's important that we understand that.
It tells us that he is the son of Joash.
He's the king of Israel.
He, Jeroboam II, reigned for 41 years.
In 2 Kings, chapter number 14,
maybe hold your place here in Hosea and turn over to 2 Kings 14
just for a moment, if you will, by way of introduction,
as we get kind of the background, if you will,
for what's taking place during the ministry of Hosea.
In 2 Kings, chapter 14, in verses 23 through 29,
God provides us with the record here of the time
in which Jeroboam II is reigning in Israel.
Notice the Bible says in 2 Kings 14, in verse 23,
In the fifteenth year of Amaziah, the son of Joash, king of Judah,
Jeroboam, the son of Joash, king of Israel, began to reign in Samaria.
Samaria is the capital, if you will, of the northern tribes,
whereas Jerusalem would be the capital of Judah.
And it says that he reigned 40 in one year.
So notice in verse 24,
And he did that which was evil in the sight of the Lord.
By the way, every king of Israel did that which was evil in the sight of the Lord.
After the divided kingdom, you have, of course,
Saul, David, and Solomon, a united kingdom for 120 years.
After that, there's this divided kingdom.
There's no good kings in Israel. Zero.
We find that in Judah, there are periods of time in which there are good kings.
In fact, there are seasons of revival.
And because of that, Judah is not taken captive
for about 115, 120 years after Israel was taken captive.
Israel, of course, taken captive by the Assyrians and Judah by the Babylonians.
And we find here that he did evil in the sight of the Lord.
Notice it says that he departed not from all the sins of Jeroboam,
the son of Nebat, who made Israel to sin.
Now, as it says it here, it helps us in verse 24
to remember the fact that there are two with the name of Jeroboam.
And it's interesting because the first one that is mentioned
at the end of verse 24, who's the son of Nebat,
it says, who made Israel to sin.
Now, remember, his reign, he was concerned that the people
were going to go back to Jerusalem, that they were going to go back to Judah.
It was going to weaken his ability to be the king.
And so what did he do? Well, he instituted his own form of worship.
He made it convenient for the people.
Oh, you don't have to go all the way to Jerusalem.
It was a counterfeit.
They set up in Dan these worship idolatrous situations there.
And we find that throughout the book of 1 and 2 Kings,
often you will read the phrase that he did,
speaking of whoever the king is, according to the sins of Jeroboam.
And you read that regularly.
And what it's referring to is go back to the first Jeroboam
and read what he did, and they followed that pattern.
Notice in verse number 25,
Now, understand that Jonah went to Nineveh.
What was Nineveh?
Nineveh is the capital of Assyria.
The Assyrians, they were the ones that eventually would come
and take captive Israel.
But remember, Jonah goes in preaching a message of
in 40 days you're going to perish, you're going to be destroyed.
Why? Because of their wickedness.
And they repent. There were several things that were taking place.
And here in verse 25, when it talks about he, Jeroboam II,
restored the coast of Israel from the entering of Hamath
under the Sea of the Plain, this was a quote-unquote
positive thing with regard to the nation,
its borders, its boundaries, and that sort of thing.
So what is it doing?
Well, it's giving the people of Israel some sense of security.
Some sense of we're okay.
I mean, look at what's happened.
He's restored the coast of Israel.
So these prophets that are prophesying judgment that's going to come,
well, look, we've fortified this.
We've restored the coast of Israel.
And so it's an interesting situation there in verse 26.
For the Lord saw the affliction of Israel, that it was very bitter,
for there was not any shut up, nor any left, nor any helper for Israel.
And the Lord said not that he would blot out the name of Israel from under heaven,
but he saved them by the hand of Jeroboam the son of Joash.
So there was some positive that was taking place there.
Now, it's not spiritually positive, but we see God's grace and God's mercy.
Verse 28, Now the rest of the acts of Jeroboam,
and all that he did in his might, how he warred, and how he recovered Damascus
and Hamath, which belonged to Judah, for Israel,
are they not written in the books of the Chronicles of the kings of Israel?
And Jeroboam slept with his fathers, even with the kings of Israel.
And Zechariah his son reigned in his stead.
We find that here as we look at this portion of Scripture in 2 Kings,
it helps us to get a little bit of the background, if you will,
of what's happening during the time in which this man Hosea is prophesying
to the northern tribes of the ten northern tribes we refer to as Israel.
Now, if you are interested in reading something
that will help you kind of get just a broader understanding, if you will,
of what's taking place during the time.
Hosea and the prophet Amos are contemporaries.
They're prophesying at the same time to the same people
during the same situation, and we find that both of those books,
Hosea and Amos, they're contemporaries,
and it makes for good reading to read those two books together
in order to see a broader picture, if you will.
Now, we understand that here the Bible says back in Hosea chapter 1,
so we get the setting, we understand what's taking place
with regard to the time of the writing.
In verse number 2 it says,
The beginning of the word of the Lord by Hosea.
Notice the Bible says, And the Lord said to Hosea,
Go take unto thee a wife of whoredoms and children of whoredoms.
Notice the end of verse number 2.
I'm not going to deal with the first part of the verse so much
because of what's going on in the question tonight,
but we see that God gave Hosea this command.
Hosea obeys the command.
It was an illustration that God was using to show
the relationship between God and Israel
and how Israel was treating God.
And so we find at the end of verse number 2 it says,
For the land hath committed great whoredom,
departing from the Lord.
And so we find the indictment is given in verse number 2.
If Israel was guilty, I would refer to it as being spiritual adultery
and God's judgment would soon come.
However, we find that God loves His people
and we understand that God made a covenant with Abraham
and that that covenant will be fulfilled.
And I say all of that so that we could understand
as we get into the second chapter
and deal specifically with the question this evening,
it's important for us to have this understanding
of what's taking place,
who's being ministered to,
what the context of this particular promise is in chapter number 2.
And so we find that the Bible says that the land hath committed great whoredom.
The land itself, the dirt, can't commit great whoredom.
It was the people of Israel.
They had been given the truth.
They had been given the truth with regard to the one and only God.
only God, and they consistently and regularly were guilty of idolatry.
It was over and over and over again.
You find the idolatry not only of Israel, but of Judah as well, and we find that here
God says that he's going to bring judgment because of their wickedness.
Now let me say this, as you hold your place here in the book of Hosea, understand this
evening that God's people still today can be guilty of spiritual adultery, and the chastening
of the Lord is sure.
Hold your place here and look at the book of James, if you will, and keep your fingers
busy tonight.
We're going to look at several passages of Scripture as we seek to make application as
we go through this portion of Hosea this evening.
In James chapter number 4, the Bible tells us in verse number 4, I hear some pages, I'll
give you a moment.
James 4 and verse number 4, you adulterers and adulteresses, know ye not that the friendship
of the world is enmity with God?
Whosoever therefore will be a friend of the world is the enemy of God.
That's pretty strong language.
That's God's Word.
Very straight, very clear.
And so we find this evening that just as Israel, and so often we can criticize Israel, but
if we're not careful we can also imitate their behavior, and we can be guilty as James says
ye adulterers and adulteresses, and we find he says, and John says this in 1 John 2, love
not the world, neither the things that are in the world.
We know that the Bible says that the world passeth away, and we understand that truth,
but he that doeth the will of God abideth forever.
And so we find here this evening that this sin, if you will, this idolatry, this spiritual
adultery, this whoredom that's referred to here, he says that these individuals, they
are guilty, and because of their guilt they would face judgment.
By the way, we find that in the Pentateuch, as you study throughout the instruction that
God gives to his people Israel, God made it abundantly clear that if you do this, here's
the blessing.
If you do this, here's the judgment.
I mean, over and over we find that God made it crystal clear to his people, we dealt with
it a little bit in Sunday school this morning, about the choices.
The consequences to your choices and to my choices are not always known, but our choices
always have consequences.
At times, however, the consequences of our choices are crystal clear, and God says I
have a blessing for you, and I set before you a blessing and a curse.
A blessing if you obey, a curse if you disobey.
And we find this evening that the children of Israel were guilty, and therefore they
would face judgment, but I'm thankful that our God is long-suffering, I'm thankful that
our God is merciful, I'm thankful that our God is loving, and we look at that here in
this portion of Scripture.
Here's the question that was posed in Hosea chapter 2.
The question reads this way, what is the meaning of the valley of Achor for a door of hope
in Hosea 2 and verse number 15?
We'll begin reading with me in verse 14, we're going to look at the context here as we've
already dealt with the introduction, kind of understand the setting, look at verse 14
if you will.
The Bible says in Hosea 2 and verse 14, therefore behold, I will allure her and bring her into
the wilderness and speak comfortably unto her.
And I will give her her vineyards from thence, and the valley of Achor for a door of hope.
And she shall sing there as in the days of her youth, and as in the day when she came
up out of the land of Egypt.
And it shall be at that day, saith the Lord, that thou shalt call me Ishi, and shalt call
me no more Bally.
For I will take away the names of Balaam out of her mouth, and they shall no more be remembered
by their name.
And in that day will I make a covenant for them with the beast of the field, and with
the fowls of heaven, and with the creeping things of the ground.
And I will break the bow and the sword and the battle out of the earth, and will make
them to lie down safely.
And I will betroth thee unto me forever, yea, I will betroth thee unto me in righteousness,
and in judgment, and in lovingkindness, and in mercies.
I will even betroth thee unto me in faithfulness, and thou shalt know the Lord.
And it shall come to pass in that day, I will hear, saith the Lord, I will hear the heavens,
and they shall hear the earth.
And the earth shall hear the corn, and the wine, and the oil, and they shall hear Jezreel.
And I will sow her unto me in the earth, and I will have mercy upon her that had not
obtained mercy.
And I will say to them which were not my people, thou art my people, and they shall say, Thou
art my God.
As we look at this text of Scripture, there are several things that are important for
us to know as we seek to answer the question, what is the meaning of the Valley of Achor
for Dor of Hope?
There's some interesting statements that are made, some insightful statements that are
made that help us to understand what the promise is here in Hosea chapter number two.
Number one, I want you to notice this, and it's not really points, it's just more of
a lecture type of a message this evening, but let me give you something to note down
there in your notes.
I want you to notice the phrase, that day.
You see it in verse 16, you see it in verse 18, and you see it again in verse 21.
So three times in this passage of Scripture, God speaks about that day.
Notice in verse 16, it says, it shall be at that day.
In verse number 18, it says, and in that day.
And then in verse number 21, it says, and it shall come to pass in that day.
And so we find that as we look here at this truth at that day, and notice that phraseology
repeated, it gives us insight to be able to understand this promise, the Valley of Achor
for Dor of Hope.
Now understand in verse number 17, it talks about removing idolatry.
The nation of Israel and idolatrous people, by the way, they're still in rebellion to
God as a nation, and we find here that we look and it says, I will take away the names
of Balaam out of her mouth, and they shall no more be remembered by their name.
I mean, this removal of idolatry in verse 19, it talks about God's faithful love, though
his people had been disobedient and rebellious.
It talks about in loving kindness.
I'm so thankful for that word, loving kindness.
It's repeated throughout the Old Testament over and over and over.
You find in verse 16, God gives us this truth with regard to these two names.
He says that thou shalt call me Ishi, and that means husband, and no longer Balaam.
That means owner or Lord.
Not Lord, the big capital L, but like the master, the owner in that general sense.
And so think about what God is saying, the relationship.
It's going to be this situation of no longer an owner, a master, but like a husband.
And again, understanding the context of what God said to Hosea to go and take thee a wife
of whoredoms.
And in fact, I preached on this.
That was a question that was asked in another Ask the Pastor.
Why did God have Hosea do that?
Go back and listen to that message, and that's the whole content of that message, not the
content of this message based on this specific question.
But we find that God gave that instruction to Hosea again as an example of what was going
on in Israel.
So we find that the Bible says in that day.
Now keep that in mind, and we're going to get to some more about that in just a moment
as we seek to answer the question more deeply.
Now Achor, as it talks about in verse number 15, the valley of Achor.
What is this?
Is this a familiar place?
Is this something that would be known?
Well, absolutely.
Achor, it means trouble or disturbance.
And we understand that this is the valley where Achan and his family were stoned, alright?
So this is something that was well known to the children of Israel as a place, as a location.
And when you would speak of the valley of Achor, it would immediately be in their mind
that this was a place of trouble or disturbance because of the history, because of what took
place.
And we find that that would immediately come to their mind.
Achor, even as the Chronicles tell us that Achan is the troubler of Israel.
Turn back to Joshua chapter 7, if you will.
I want to remind you of the context of this, and in fact, many of us this evening that
are not native, we're not Israelites, we're not Jewish, but we understand the Old Testament,
the accounts, and we're familiar with Achan.
We're familiar with the situation at Ai, and we understand what happens.
What did he do?
Well, he was guilty of taking the accursed thing, taking that which he was not to take,
that which was to be given to the Lord.
And we find that in chapter 7, they suffer defeat, and 36 men lose their lives, and Joshua's
beside himself.
He doesn't know what's going on.
And God says,
Sin in the camp.
And this is amazing to me
that God says this in v. 12,
"...therefore the children of Israel
could not stand before their enemies,
but turned their backs before their enemies."
Why? Because they were accursed.
"...Neither will I be with you anymore,
except you destroy the accursed from among you."
God is serious about sin.
You think you can live in sin
and have the blessing of God.
You're foolish.
God is long-suffering.
God is gracious. God is merciful.
But understand with me this evening
that God is just.
Amen? God is just.
And we find here that through a series of events,
we find that God brings the tribes
before Joshua, then the families,
then the households, then man by man.
And I can't imagine being Achan.
He knew that He had taken the accursed thing
and as it was narrowing down
and the circle is getting smaller
and smaller and smaller,
and He's going to be exposed.
The Bible says that in verse number 20,
that Achan answered Joshua and said,
indeed, I have sinned against the Lord God of Israel
and thus and thus have I done.
We find that the Bible tells us,
I'm going to just skip through
so that we can get to the phraseology.
But in verse number 25, Joshua said,
why hast thou troubled us?
The Lord shall trouble thee this day
and all Israel stoned him with stones
and burned them with fire
after they had stoned them with stones
and they raised over him a great heap of stones
unto this day.
So the Lord turned from the fierceness of his anger.
Wherefore, the name of that place was called
the Valley of Achor.
Notice it says unto this day.
Now, when you read that in the book of Joshua,
I read that today in 2024,
it doesn't mean until this day
that that heap of stones is still there unto today.
But what it means is under the time of the writing.
All right, so that heap of stones,
just like the memorials that we read of
in the beginning of the book of Joshua,
when he said they're here unto this day,
you could literally still go to Gilgal
and see the memorial that was set up.
You could literally still go to the place
where they crossed over Jericho.
There was that, that evidence was there
unto the day of the writing.
And so we find where it says
the Valley of Achor unto this day.
Again, this is well known to the children of Israel.
It was a place of trouble and judgment.
But as we find in Hosea chapter number two,
the Bible says in all of this indictment
and all of this wickedness and the spiritual adultery,
the judgment that would come,
God says the Valley of Achor for a door of hope,
for a door of hope.
Now, though judgment would come and judgment was certain
and though judgment had come to Achan
and therefore it had the name,
that valley named the Valley of Achor,
we know that the Bible says here in verse number 15,
that one day that Valley of Achor
would be known as a door of hope.
Now, hope is an interesting word.
Hope is a word that I like.
The word hope biblically means a confident expectation,
something that we can be sure of,
something that we can rest in,
something that we can have that confidence in,
that confident expectation.
And I want you to think about this just for a moment
and then I'm gonna get back to Hosea chapter number two,
but I wanna take just a little bit of a detour,
if you will, and talk about hope just for a moment,
because the Bible says that the Valley of Achor
for a door of hope.
And I want you to think about
if I could make an application this evening for us
with this idea of judgment and hope.
Can I do that with you this evening?
Take your Bibles and go to Ephesians chapter number two
and I want you to see what the Bible says
in Ephesians chapter number two.
As we think about our own selves
and here in the book of Hosea,
obviously we're dealing with the nation of Israel,
but I want you to think about ourselves
and I want you to think about the truth
that we were dead in our trespasses and sins
before we were saved by the grace of God, amen.
And I want you to understand that the Bible tells us
here in Ephesians chapter number two,
notice in verse number 11,
wherefore remember that ye being in time past Gentiles
in the flesh who are called uncircumcision
by that which is called the circumcision
in the flesh made by hands.
Now that's obviously the distinction
between the Jews and the Gentiles,
the uncircumcision and the circumcision.
But notice in verse number 12,
it says that at that time ye were without Christ.
Do you remember when you were without Christ?
I hope you do.
I remember when I was without Christ.
I remember when I was lost.
And notice what the Bible says,
being aliens from the Commonwealth of Israel
and strangers from the covenants of promise,
what does it say?
Having no hope and without God in the world.
Do you remember when you had no hope?
You didn't have the confident expectation
that heaven was your home.
You didn't have that sweet assurance,
that blessed assurance that we sing of,
knowing that I am his and he is mine.
We had no hope, no hope.
But I want you to understand that in Christ no longer,
it says in verse number 13,
but now in Christ Jesus,
ye who sometimes were far off are made nigh how
by the blood of Christ for he is our peace.
And I'm so thankful for that,
but I want you to keep this idea of hope.
And we find in Ephesians chapter two,
it says that we had no hope.
Turn to the book of first Peter, if you will.
First Peter, and I want you to see what God tells us here
as Peter is writing to those that are facing great levels
of persecution under the hand of Nero,
the ruthless, wicked emperor of Rome,
hated God's people.
We find that as they're scattered abroad
that Peter is used of the Lord to write to them,
to encourage them.
We find in verse number three, notice what the Bible says.
Blessed be the God and father of our Lord Jesus Christ,
which according to his abundant mercy
hath begotten us again unto a what?
Lively hope.
By the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead
to an inheritance incorruptible and undefiled
and that fadeth not away reserved in heaven for you
who are kept by the power of God through faith
and to salvation ready to be revealed in the last time.
I went from having no hope to having a lively hope.
Isn't that amazing?
No hope, lively hope.
Because of what Christ did on that cruel cross
and the offer of salvation, the gift of God,
which is eternal life.
But I want you to consider a third thought this evening
with regard to this subject of hope.
Turn to the book of Titus, if you will,
and chapter number two.
As believers, no longer are we in that position
of having no hope.
However, I would submit to you
that there are countless billions of people
on planet Earth today that have no hope,
that are in that condition of Ephesians two in verse 12,
they're without Christ and therefore they have no hope.
We have a lively hope.
We don't only have a lively hope,
but I want you to see what the Bible says
in verse number 11 of Titus two.
It says this, for the grace of God that bringeth salvation
hath appeared to all men,
teaching us that denying ungodliness and worldly lusts,
we should live soberly, righteously and godly
in this present world, looking for that blessed hope
and glorious appearing of the great God
and our Savior, Jesus Christ.
I have a lively hope, but I have a blessed hope.
Amen, aren't you thankful for that?
And I think about what God has done for us.
I think about how God in his grace and his mercy,
that he is our peace and that he took an individual.
If I use myself as the example this evening,
he took a lost sinner that had no hope
and he saved my soul and he gave me a lively hope
and I now have the blessed hope that one day
my Lord is gonna come back.
It's absolutely phenomenal.
And it's important that we think about that this evening.
God placed it upon my heart as I was preparing
to answer the question this evening
and just rejoicing in my preparation of yes,
looking at what's going on with Israel here in Hosea two
and the promise, but then thinking about my own life
and that I had no hope and he says,
the Valley of Achor, a place of trouble,
a place of disturbance, a place that was known for judgment
would be a door of hope.
I'm thankful that God, Jesus Christ took the judgment
for me and for you.
Did he not?
He hung upon that cruel cross and he suffered
and he bled and he died so that those who had no hope
could have a lively hope, could have the blessed hope
that one day our God's coming back
to receive us unto himself.
What a blessing that is.
Back to the portion of scripture here in the book of Hosea,
notice what a great promise this is
for the nation of Israel.
We understand, however, that this promise
is still in the future.
Israel as a nation is still in a state of disobedience
and rebellion, we understand that, we see that,
we understand that the Bible teaches us
that because of their rejection of the Lord Jesus Christ,
blindness, spiritual blindness has come upon
the nation of Israel.
Now it is possible that Jewish people can be saved,
but they have to be saved the same way as anyone else.
Listen, it is heresy, there are people
that are internet preachers, that are famous television preachers that say if you are Jewish
you're going to heaven, period.
That is false.
That is not what the Bible teaches whatsoever.
The Bible says that the gospel is the power of God unto salvation to everyone that believeth
to the Jew first and also to the Greek.
He came to his own, but his own received him not.
They cried out, crucify him.
Is that not what happened?
And we find that because of their rejection, they're in this state of disobedience.
There's this spiritual blindness that has happened to them, but there are still promises
that were made to Israel and those promises are as certain as they've ever been.
And we understand the full picture from God's perspective.
We're living in time and sometimes that's the difficulty is that we're living within
the boundaries of time and what's going on and it's hard for us sometimes to take that
step back and try to get the perspective of God.
Understand I said it this morning that this prophecy that is still going to be fulfilled
is already 2,700 years old.
This man Hosea was, listen, the nation of Israel was taken captive in 722 B.C.
The prophecy took place before the captivity.
Jeroboam is reigning.
Jeroboam did not enter into the captivity.
It was his descendants that were taken captive.
It was not Jeroboam.
So it's at least 2,700 years old plus however long it was prior to the captivity or prior
to the death of Jeroboam.
So we understand that, but the reality is that God's promises are sure.
We sang this morning, standing on the promises of Christ my King, right?
We sing and we thank God for the promises and we come to a passage like this and we
say, well what does this mean?
When is this going to be fulfilled?
What is the meaning of this?
The valley of Achor, this place of judgment, this place of trouble and of disturbance is
going to be a door of hope?
When is this going to happen?
How is this going to happen?
Is it going to happen?
And let me say this, it is absolutely going to happen.
Why?
Because God said so.
Now you can fight with God, but I'm going to tell you like Gamaliel said to those Sanhedrin
leaders in Acts chapter number 5, if this thing be of God, you're wasting your time.
You might as well just submit to God and understand that God has a plan, amen?
And God's plan is perfect.
God's plan is perfect.
You say, I don't like God's plan, you've got to change your perspective, amen?
Some of you laugh, I'm being serious.
You know how many people say it's not fair that the person in Africa, the person in Australia,
the person in Asia, the person in North America, South America, wherever, up in the barren
cold wilderness of the northern territories, they've never heard of Jesus and I can't believe
that they would go to hell.
Well, what are you doing about it?
You know how many people I've heard make that, and I can't believe, how could a loving God,
well, He commanded us to go to hell.
So all of a sudden we're bringing a charge against God while we're being disobedient
to God.
How does that work?
That's a messed up mindset, is it not?
So what we find here in the text of Scripture is that it will happen.
I believe we can understand when it's going to happen.
The key, as I said early on in the message this evening, is that phrase, that day.
That day.
It's repeated three times in just a short period of time here in these verses, and what
does it mean?
In verse 16, 18, and 21, what is it that's being referred to?
What does God mean when He says at that day, in that day, at that day?
So let me help us, and we don't have time to develop all of this this evening, but let
me tell you of two phrases that you'll find throughout the Bible.
You hear this phrase, the day of Christ and the day of the Lord, all right?
Those are phrases that you're going to come across as you study the Scriptures, as you
read the Scriptures, and both of those, day of Christ and day of the Lord, they're really
referring to the same period of time.
The seven-year period of tribulation is what that's referring to.
The day of Christ is really concerning itself with the heavenly events, whereas in the day
of the Lord is concerning itself with the earthly events.
So there are going to be things that are taking place on earth during the seven-year tribulation,
the day of the Lord, while at the same time, there will be things, events taking place
in heaven, the day of Christ.
They're not two different time periods, they're the same time period, but they're referring
to events from a certain perspective.
Heavenly events, earthly events.
I want you to remember that the seven-year tribulation is referred to as Jacob's trouble.
So what is God going to do?
Well, Israel is in rebellion.
Israel is in rebellion to God to this very day as a nation, they are in rebellion to
God to this very day, and therefore they're having spiritual blindness, the judgment,
so on and so forth.
But during the tribulation, all of a sudden what's going to happen is God is going to
once again deal with Israel primarily.
That's His plan.
So the church is going to be raptured because God's no longer dealing with us as the church.
We've been saved, and He's going to deliver us from that wrath and all of those things.
And by the way, we're going to study the book of Revelation, but I've heard many people
say, well, I believe in a mid-trib rapture because it's pre-wrath.
Have you ever read Revelation 6?
I mean, as soon as the seals begin to get open, the wrath of God is being poured out.
And if you read that as being not wrathful, I'm confused.
And so the reality this evening is that we look at and we see, what is the purpose of
the tribulation?
Why is there going to be a tribulation?
And it's for the nation of Israel.
You see the 144,000 witnesses, 12,000 from each tribe, the two witnesses that come.
What is God doing?
He's dealing with Israel.
He's calling them back to Himself.
You read in Romans where it says, and this is where people, the heresy comes in, where
it says that all Israel shall be saved.
That doesn't mean that every Jewish person is saved.
It means after the tribulation and all of what is going to happen, that at that point
when the millennial kingdom begins, all of Israel shall be saved.
Those that trusted in the true Messiah, the Lord Jesus Christ, because of the tribulation
and all that's taking place, all Israel shall be saved.
That's what it means.
And so we find that when we look here at, in that day, at that day, the repeated phraseology
in Hosea 2, when is it going to happen?
Well, the day of Christ, the day of the Lord, that seven-year period begins with the rapture
of the church.
The clock begins.
Three and a half years, I mean exactly three and a half years, the abomination of desolation
is going to take place, the midpoint of the tribulation.
Daniel speaks about it.
Jesus speaks about it.
Paul speaks about it.
It's going to take place at that time, and we find that he's going to violate the peace
treaty, the Antichrist will, all of that stuff that's going to happen, and then there's going
to be three and a half more years.
Then there's going to be the battle of Armageddon.
Jesus is coming back.
He's coming back with his saints, hallelujah.
That's the next time, Samantha, I'm going to ride a horse, amen?
And hallelujah, I rode a horse down in Tennessee a few years ago, and we're planning a trip
to Tennessee tomorrow, and I said, one thing we're not doing is riding horses, amen?
I did not really enjoy myself too much, and it was not terrible, but it was not something
I'd like to do again, but I'm going to ride a horse when I come back with Jesus, amen?
And hallelujah, it's not going to kick me off.
It's not going to cause me trouble, and I rejoice in that, but the reality is that when
we come back, we find that Christ returns with his saints, and what does he do?
He establishes his millennial kingdom, the millennial reign of Christ.
It's a thousand years that Jesus Christ himself is going to sit on the throne of David.
He is the rightful heir to it, and he is going to rule and reign in righteousness.
The Bible gives us so many insights to regard to the millennial reign of Christ, those which
we cannot look at this evening in their entirety, but I do want you to notice here in the text,
the text of Scripture that the Bible talks about in verse 15, how she shall sing there
as in the days of her youth and as in the day when she came up out of the land of Egypt,
and you think about that imagery and the understanding of the hope and the joy that they would have
because of that.
He's going to remove idolatry in verse 17 and verse 18, and in that day will I make
a covenant for them with the beast of the field and with the fowls of heaven and with
the creeping things of the ground.
It's interesting.
God speaks about the way in which the bear and the lion and the lamb, excuse me, they're
going to be together, and that doesn't happen today, playing on the whole of the asp.
I'm not messing around with serpents today, man, especially deadly ones, venomous ones,
and you find that God's going to restore during that millennial reign really to the way it
was restored.
really pre-flood, pre-judgment.
Jesus is gonna rule and people will still die.
We're not gonna die
because we're gonna come back and rule and reign with him.
We've already gone through that situation,
either the rapture or death here.
But we find that here in Hosea,
it talks about the covenant that he's gonna make
with the beast of the field and all of that in verse 18.
In verse 19 and 20, he talks about that betrothal
and that relationship that he gave hint to
in verse number 16 with regard to the names
that not Bali, but Ishi.
And we find here that God gives this promise.
So when we read the book of Hosea,
we read all of the judgment,
we see all of the indictment that comes on Hosea,
excuse me, on the nation of Israel
through the prophet Hosea because of their idolatry,
because of their wickedness, their spiritual adultery.
We find that in the midst of the judgment,
the prophecy of judgment, the indictment upon the nation
that God gives them a promise.
The promise is not yet fulfilled,
but one day it will be that the Valley of Achor,
a place known, it's a place of judgment,
trouble, disturbance will be a door of hope.
And that's the promise that God gives to his people
in Hosea chapter number two.
And we find that that day will come.
We don't know exactly when it's gonna come,
but I'll say this, it's at least seven years away.
How do I know that?
Well, because we haven't started the tribulation yet.
The tribulation seven years.
And so it's at least seven years
before the millennial reign will begin.
And that's when the Valley of Achor
will be known as a door of hope.
I'm thankful this evening to have hope.
I had no hope one day.
Now I have a lively hope.
I have the blessed hope.
I hope this evening you have hope.
You have hope because you know Jesus.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for your word, the truth contained therein.
I pray God that you would help us to understand your plan.
Lord, no doubt we covered a lot of material this evening
and looked at a large swath of time.
God, we're thankful that you have a plan.
We're thankful that you're gracious, merciful God.
Lord, we're thankful for this promise
that you gave to Israel as a nation.
We're thankful for the reality that we have
as your people, as your children.
To have hope.
And God, I pray that you'd help us to live every day
with the understanding and the reminder
of that blessed hope that today could be the day
that you come back.
God, help us to be found faithful.
Help us to be found occupying, redeeming the time.
I pray, Father, that you'd help us to be encouraged
that you have a plan.
Help us, Lord, to submit to you.
We'll thank you for it, in Christ's name we pray.