passage of scripture. I hope that as we examine this portion of scripture this
morning that we would be challenged. I trust that we'd be encouraged as we look
at this familiar passage, but also that God would challenge us. I'm mindful of
some New Testament truth. If you look in, you're there in Daniel, but I consider
the truth with regard to the Apostle Paul speaking to the church in Ephesus.
What's funny, Steve? You're good? Okay, I thought something, Jim's taking his thing
like this, so I didn't know if something was going on behind me. And in Ephesians, of
course, the Apostle Paul is encouraging the believers in Ephesus with regard to
their walk with God. Of course, the foundation in the first few chapters is
established with regard to their relationship to God through the Lord
Jesus Christ, and then he addresses their walk, and he comes to the final chapter
in the book of Ephesians, and as he gets to the latter part of that chapter, he
begins to talk about the spiritual warfare in which were engaged. And in so
doing, he begins to challenge the believers in Ephesus to stand, and he
tells them that they are to be strong in the power of the Lord, and we find that
as we would examine and consider the admonition, if you will, that the Apostle
Paul gives to the church at Ephesus and to the believers there, and he tells them
not only be strong in the power of the Lord, but he tells them to put on the
whole armor of God, and he says this, that you may be able to stand against
the wiles of the devil. He then tells them we're not engaged in some sort of
wrestling match, some sort of fleshly carnal battle. No, it's a spiritual battle
in which we are engaged in. And we begin to think about the, really, the admonition
that Paul gives to these believers as he's instructing them, and I find this
morning that each generation will face unique pressures to bow or to conform to
the current ideologies. We find that we're living in a particular era in
which we, as this generation, we are facing certain pressures to bow, to
conform to the ideologies that exist, and we find that each generation is going to
face such circumstances. The believers that Paul is referencing and ministering
to in Ephesus, they had their own set of circumstances that they faced, and they
had to stand in the power of God, and they had to be willing to yield
themselves to God. They had to be willing to walk in the Spirit so that they
would not fulfill the lust of the flesh, and we find that for the passage of
Scripture that we're going to look at this morning in Daniel 3, we find that
these three Hebrew children that we often are familiar with, Shadrach,
Meshach, and Abednego, these fellas, they faced unique circumstances with regard
to the pressures of their day, and we find that they were willing to stand. If
you've already looked at the bulletin on the back, the title for the message this
morning is really a question, and the question is this, are you willing to
stand? Am I willing to stand? Again, each generation is going to have its
opportunity to face the pressures and the ideologies that exist within that
particular society and culture, and the question is whether or not the people of
God will stand. We find that as we look at a passage like Daniel 3, we rejoice
greatly in understanding what takes place, and we're familiar with the
passage of Scripture, and we say, man, this is wonderful, look at how God worked,
look at what God did, but it's because there were some people of God that
stood, that were willing to take a stand no matter what the pressures were,
no matter what the consequences were that they would face, they were willing
to take a stand, and the question is we look through history, not only biblical
history, but we look at modern history and look at the church history through
the ages, and you can find individuals and groups of people that stood for
truth, and I wonder this morning, I wonder in our generation who among us would be
written about that we were willing to stand, that we might encourage a future
generation in like fashion as we have been encouraged by those who have gone
before us that were willing to take a stand. As we notice in our passage of
Scripture here in Daniel 3, let me just read some verses, we'll get into
the message. I'm gonna try to look at all 30 verses, and notice in verse number
one the Bible says this, Nebuchadnezzar the king made an image of gold whose
height was three square cubits and the breadth thereof six cubits. He set it up
in the plain of Dura in the province of Babylon. We understand that Nebuchadnezzar
is the king of the Babylonian Empire, we understand that he has great power, we
find that as you look at the history with regard to this kingdom and you'd
understand the power in which this man had when he's going to put up this image
of gold, this 90-foot image, and he's going to give some requirements that
we'll look at in just a few moments, you understand that he had power to make
happen what he said would happen. And as we look at the passage of Scripture
and we consider the question, are you willing to stand? I want us to consider a
few things. Number one, consider with me the circumstances these men faced.
Consider the circumstances they faced. Now admittedly, right from the beginning
this morning, we understand that the circumstances that are faced in Daniel
3 are different than the circumstances that you will face, they're different
than the circumstances that I will face, they're different than the circumstances
that Paul faced and the believers in Ephesus faced, but each generation is
going to have a set of circumstances, some ideologies that are in opposition
to God's Word that we're gonna face. And here in Daniel 3, we find as we've read
in verse number one that this golden image is set up and in verse 2 it says
then Nebuchadnezzar the king sent to gather together, notice, the princes, the
governors, and the captains, the judges, the treasurers, the counselors, the
sheriffs, and all the rulers of the provinces to come. For what? They were
gonna have this dedication, it says, to come to the dedication of the image
which Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up. Then, in response to this edict, if you
will, that was made, it says the princes, the governors, and captains, the judges,
the treasurers, the counselors, the sheriffs, and all the rulers of the
provinces were gathered together under the dedication of the image that
Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up. And they stood before the image that
Nebuchadnezzar had set up. Then, and Harold cried aloud, to you, notice, it is
commanded, O people, nations, and languages, that at what time you hear the sound of
the cornet, flute, harp, samba, psaltery, dulcimer, and all kinds of music, you
fall down and worship the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the king hath set up.
Now, here's where it gets complicated for these three Hebrew children. We find that
Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, they've already been taken into Babylon. Of
course, Nebuchadnezzar and the Babylonians would conquer Judah, and we
find that these fellows, along with Daniel, they were in captivity. They're
there in Babylon. If you read the first couple of chapters, you see in which the
way in which they were sought to be indoctrinated. In chapter number one, you
read about the indoctrination program that the Babylonians had for those that
they would bring in, and you find that here, this Harold cries, listen, the
instruction, the command was clear. It was not ambiguous whatsoever, but the command
violated a greater command, and that was a command that God had given. And we find
that as here, these men would hear this instruction, as this Harold would cry
aloud and say, here's what is required of you. You're gonna hear the music play, and
when that happens, you fall down and worship. Worship an image? Yes, fall down
and worship. And we find that as the music would play, as they would prepare
for this, that not only was the command known, but the consequences were known. We
find that in verse number six, the Bible says, and whoso falleth not down and
worshipeth shall the same hour be cast in the midst of a burning, fiery furnace.
The stakes were high. The situation, the circumstances that they faced were
serious. We find that the stakes are high. They understand the command that is
given. Again, this command is not ambiguous. It's extremely clear. We've
created this image. We've set up this golden image, and we're gonna have some
musicians play some music, and you're going to bow and worship. And if not, in
the same hour, the burning, fiery furnace. Can you imagine the predicament that
these men are in? Can you imagine as they're in this situation, and we find
that just as we look at the circumstances, we find that these
pressures that they faced, again, different than the pressures that we
would face. We understand that the pressures are varied, but we would
understand also that they're certain. We will face pressures. We are facing
pressures. And we find that as we look here at this passage of Scripture that
says in verse number 7,
"...therefore at that time when all the people..."
heard the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sakhba, psaltery, and all kinds of music,
notice the next three words, all the people, the nations and the languages
fell down and worshipped. What did they do? They worshipped the golden image that
Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up. Whether it was out of this, of course, we
understand as you'd look at the Babylonian Empire and look at their
culture and society, an idolatrous people, a people that served a
multiplicity of gods, and we find that there's some that would be bowing
down in worship because it was just custom in their culture. There are others
no doubt that did this out of fear. They understood the circumstances, they
understood the consequences, and they said, I'm not going to a burning fiery
furnace. I understand that Nebuchadnezzar has the power to fulfill that which he
said would be the consequence. These people bow down and they worship, but in
verses 8 through 12 we are introduced to people that we have become familiar with
as New Testament believers, to these three Hebrew children that were willing
to stand. The Bible says in verse number 8,
Wherefore at that time certain Chaldeans came near and accused the Jews. They
spake and said to the king Nebuchadnezzar, O king, live forever! Thou, O king, hast
made a decree that every man that shall hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp,
sakhba, psaltery, and dulcimer, and all kinds of music, shall fall down and
worship the golden image. And whoso falleth not down and worshipeth that he
should be cast in the midst of a burning fiery furnace. They knew what
had been commanded. They repeated to the king the edict that he had put forth, and
they say, There are certain Jews, in verse number 12, whom thou hast set over the
affairs of the province of Babylon. Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. These men,
O king, have not regarded thee. They serve not thy gods, nor worship the golden
image which thou hast set up. And we ought to say, Amen! They took a stand. And we
find that the stand is taken in verse number 12. These certain, these Jews are
accused by these that are mentioned in verse number 8, these Chaldeans that come
to Nebuchadnezzar. Hey listen, there's some guys over here that they didn't bow
down. They didn't follow what you told them to do. So Nebuchadnezzar, he's not
real pleased with hearing this news. And the Bible tells us in verse number 13
that in his rage and fury, he commanded to bring these fellas into his presence.
Can you imagine? I mean listen, I understand this morning that most all of
us, you could probably tell us the account. But I just wonder this morning
if you can put yourself in the shoes of these fellas. I'm talking about not
understanding that they're gonna come out of the fiery furnace. I'm talking
about understanding that you didn't bow. You took a stand. You stood for what was
right. And then the king says, bring them here. And you're being marched into the
presence of this particular time of the most powerful human being on the face of
the earth. And he's furious. And he has all this power. And he says, as he
approaches these men coming to his presence, he says this in verse
number 14. Is it true, O Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, do not ye serve my gods,
nor worship the golden image which I have set up? Now, if ye be ready, that at
what time ye hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbutt, psalter, and
dulcimer, and all kinds of music, ye fall down and worship the image which I have
made well. But if you worship not, ye should be cast the same hour into the
midst of a burning fiery furnace. Notice the question that ends verse number 15.
And who is that God that shall deliver you out of my hands? Do you see the pride
of Nebuchadnezzar? I mean, you look and you understand what Nebuchadnezzar is
saying. And he's saying, almost if I could paraphrase it, I'm gonna give you
guys another chance. Maybe you didn't fully understand what I had commanded.
Maybe you didn't understand the consequences, and you violated it the
first time. So now I'm gonna give you another opportunity. And we're gonna play
the music again. And if you bow well. You know, a lot of people are looking for
well. A lot of people are looking for comfort and ease, and just kind of go
with the flow. You know what I mean? How is it that we can just kind of make our
way through this crazy society? I'm gonna tell you, we're gonna have to stand. We're
gonna have to stand. This world has lost its mind. There's no more moral code of
standard that is based on anything that is close to the Word of God which we
believe and preach. We find that we're living in a really, as some have tried to
coin it, a post-truth type of an era in which truth is just relative. It's your
truth, and it's my truth, and it's their truth. I'm sorry to tell you, but the Word
of God is truth. The Bible says, Thy Word is truth. Jesus Christ said, I am the way,
the truth, and the life. And we find that we have truth. Listen, I'm not trying
to be ugly with anyone. I'm not trying to cause myself to have enemies. I like
people to like me. Do you like having enemies? Come on. I want people to like me.
But I'm much more concerned with God being pleased with my life. Because we're
gonna stand before him one day, and these guys, they hear the King. So we're
gonna give you another chance. Can you imagine in that moment? Can you
imagine the pressures in that moment? Three of you, the most powerful man on
the earth at that particular time, humanly speaking, and he says, here's what
we're gonna do. We're gonna play the music. In your sanctified imagination, can
you hear the music playing and see those men stand? They just stand. Wow,
what circumstances they faced. I want you to consider the confidence they
displayed. We consider the circumstances really in verses 1 through 15, and the
next few verses, verses 16 through 18. I want you to consider this confidence in
which they displayed. I believe that they had confidence in what God was able to
do. The Bible says in verse number 16, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego answered
and said to the king, O Nebuchadnezzar, we are not careful to answer thee in this
matter. If it be so, you understand what they're saying? If what you just told us
is gonna be what's gonna happen, if that's gonna happen, we want you to know
something. Our God, whom we serve, is able to deliver us from the burning fiery
furnace. And, by the way, he will deliver us out of thine hand, O king. I wonder
this morning, how much confidence do we have in what God is able to do? Honestly,
how much confidence do we have in what God is able to do? We understand that
Paul says to that same group of people in Ephesus, now unto him which is able to
do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think. We know that the
Scriptures are, throughout the entirety of God's Word, revealed to us. They're
full of example of what God is able to do. We find that the questions are asked
when God stands before Abraham, and he says to Abraham, I am the Lord God
Almighty, El Shaddai. He says, Abraham, and just a little while after he reveals
himself in that manner, he says, is anything too hard for me? Oh, do we have
confidence in what God is able to do? Are we in a place where we're willing to
exercise that faith that is revealed here in these verses of Scripture? Oh, the
great confidence. Listen, if you've seen God work, if you've read this book and
you've allowed this book to influence and impact your life, and you let the
Word of God build your faith as it says it will, we find that we can have great
confidence in what God is able to do. So I don't know how God's gonna do it.
I don't think they knew how God was gonna do it either. They just believed
that God was able. Notice what they say in verse number 18. But if not, I believe
what they're saying here is if he doesn't deliver us out of the burning
fiery furnace, they knew that he would deliver him out of the hand of the king.
They knew that God was able to deliver him from the burning fiery furnace. But
if not, be it known unto thee, O king, can you see them standing here? It's similar
to what we read of the the disciples in the book of Acts when they're standing
before the Sanhedrin and they're saying, we understand that you told us that we
can't preach in his name, we understand that you've told us that you're gonna
beat us and imprison us, and so on and so forth, but we must
obey God. And we find here that they say that we will not serve thy gods, nor
worship the golden image which thou hast set up. I mean, they were
confident. They were courageous. They had purposed. They had resolved. We are not
going to bow. I believe that Nebuchadnezzar could have played the
music until today, and they were not gonna bow. You understand? They just,
they were resolved. They were determined to obey God. See, you
understand this morning that what led to their confidence, and not only do we
see that they had confidence in what God could do, but we understand they had
confidence in what God had said. You know, the truth is God had given command, and
we find even as you look at the Ten Commandments, thou shalt have no other
gods before me. We find that it's in Leviticus 26, in verse number one, that
here God says, ye shall make you no idols nor graven image, neither rear you up a
standing image, neither shall you set up an image of stone in your land, to bow
down unto it, for I am the Lord your God. I believe that the confidence that is
displayed here really reveals to us a walk that they had with God, an
understanding that they had of the Word of God, and the decision that they were
making was not an emotional decision. It was not a situation of like, hey, we're
just not gonna stand so we could be different. No, it was a decision that was
based upon biblical principle, and when you make a decision based upon biblical
principle, the biblical principle isn't gonna change. It doesn't matter who's in
the White House, it doesn't matter who controls the government, it doesn't
matter what border we're in, what land we live in, God's Word, based upon the
principles contained therein, when we make decisions in that fashion, it's just
not gonna change. We are not going to bow to your God. We're not gonna do it. I
believe that not only does it reveal that they had a personal walk with God, I
believe the depth of the walk that they had with God, I believe it also reveals
to us that there was a level of preparation. You understand that in order
to stand, we better be preparing to stand, because when those
pressures come, when the consequences, when the bar, the stake is raised as high
as it is here, if we've not prepared to stand, we're probably gonna bow. We're
gonna justify it somehow in our minds. Everybody else is doing it. You probably
said that as a teenager like I did. Why can't I do that, mom? Why can't I do that?
That everybody else is doing it. I think I only said that a handful of times,
honestly, because each time I said that, they said, okay, tell me who's doing it,
and it was just like, mmm, everybody. But you understand. Notice what the wise man
says, Solomon, Proverbs 24. Notice what he says in Proverbs 24 and verse number 10.
What a great truth that God gives us here in this verse of Scripture. The
Bible says in Proverbs 24 and verse number 10, if thou faint in the day of
adversity, thy strength is small. Can I tell you this morning that the day of
adversity is gonna come? It's gonna come. It's not talking about physical strength,
however. See, we wrestle not against flesh and blood, as I referenced in Ephesians
6 this morning by way of introduction. We wrestle against spiritual wickedness in
high places. And here he's not speaking about our strength being small, meaning
that our physical strength is small. Remember, Paul said, in my weakness, then
I'm strong. Why? Because his strength is made perfect in weakness. And we find that
as we would look to the Word of God and we'd understand the importance of being
strengthened in the inner man, that we walk in the Spirit, that we have the
boldness that only comes as a result of being filled with the Holy Spirit of
God. And we find that these men, I believe that as we look at this passage and
consider this example, that these men, they had had this confidence, and it's
confidence in what God could do, it's confidence in what God had said. I
believe that it reveals to us that they had a close walk with God, and they had
prepared. They had prepared for this day. I don't know that you say, so they knew
it was going to happen? I'm not saying that they knew exactly what was going to
happen, just like you don't know exactly what's going to happen. But there's this
preparation as we walk with God. And when that day of adversity comes, we're
walking with God, our inner man has been strengthened, and we're able to stand. Not
in our own power, but in the power of God. And we're able to stand. We see the
confidence that was displayed. I want you to consider with me, as we continue
through this passage of Scripture, I want you to consider number three, the
communion they enjoyed. The communion they enjoyed. It's really interesting as
you look at verses 19 through 26, and we understand again, as we're familiar with
the passage of Scripture, that these men find themselves in this fiery
furnace. But I want you to consider for a moment the communion that they enjoyed.
The reality is that the Bible says that the stakes were so high, Nebuchadnezzar
is so furious. I mean, can you imagine the embarrassment of Nebuchadnezzar? I mean,
you know his pride, we've already discussed it. And now all of these people
are there, and they bring these three before him, and he says, here's what's
gonna happen, you're gonna bow. And they just stand. They just stand. It says that
Nebuchadnezzar was full of fury in verse number 19. The form of his visage was
changed. See, I believe in verse number 13, when it says that he was in his rage
and fury that he brought him before him, but he's offering them another
opportunity, and we're gonna play it again, and you're gonna bow, and it's
gonna be well. And when they don't, he's full of fury. His visage was
changed against Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. Therefore he spake, he
commanded that they should heat the furnace one seven times more than it was
wont to be heated. He commanded the most mighty men that were in his army to bind
Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, and to cast them into the burning fiery furnace.
So he heats it up seven times hotter than what it was going to be set to, and
he finds the mightiest within his army to bind these men. It was so hot that the
men were slain that threw these three into the fire. Notice in verse 21, then
these men were bound in their coats, their hosen, their hats, their other
garments, and were cast in the midst of the burning fiery furnace. Therefore,
because the king's commandment was urgent, and the furnace exceeding hot, the
flame of the fire slew those men that took up Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego.
And these three men, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, fell down bound into
the midst of the burning fiery furnace. But then Nebuchadnezzar's a stone-eyed.
He's astonished as to what happens. The Bible tells us in verse number 24 that
he rose up in haste, and he speaks to his counselors that are there, and he
asked this question, did not we cast three men bound into the midst of the
fire? They answered and said unto the king, true, O king. I mean, he's in a
position where he's looking at what he's seeing, and he's saying, hey listen,
wasn't it three? And weren't they bound? Yes, true, O king. You've not lost your
mind. Yes, that's what we did. He answered and said, lo, I see four men loose. He
says they're loose, and they're walking in the midst of the fire, and they have
no hurt. And the form of the fourth is like the Son of God. I want you to
consider the communion that they have.
They enjoyed communion with God in a way that I don't know we can fully
comprehend, because it was their obedience to God that led to the fire.
It was their obedience to God that led to the fire. And they go in bound seven
times hotter. The men that cast them in are killed. The king says they're walking
around. I mean, can you imagine King Nebuchadnezzar looking at this like,
what is going on? How is this even possible? Remember what he said in verse
number 15, who is that God that shall deliver you out of my hands? See, he
thought he had all this power, and he thought that if he raised the
stakes high enough, you're gonna bow.
I've heard people say this,
everybody has a price.
I hope you don't have a price.
I hope that there's not some stake
that the enemy could raise it to
and you say, okay, enough is enough.
I'm just going to do what you want me to do.
I'll bow if you want me to bow.
I'm not going in that furnace.
It says in v. 26,
then Nebuchadnezzar came near
to the mouth of the burning, fiery furnace
and spake.
Can you imagine?
In my mind's eye, the people are still there.
It was in that same hour.
And he's talking to these guys.
Now maybe there's some that are deep in the crowd
and they've not heard what was just asked
of the counselors.
And they see the king walk over there
and he's talking.
Now, if you were an observer,
you saw the three men die that cast them in.
Who's he talking to?
Surely they're dead, right?
As an observer.
And it says here that he spake
and he said,
Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego.
Notice what he says.
Ye servants of the Most High God.
Come forth and come hither.
Then Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego
came forth in the midst of the fire.
I can't even imagine being an observer
and seeing those boys walk out.
What is going on?
Right?
And they come walking out.
I don't know how long
they were in the burning, fiery furnace.
I don't think you do either.
It doesn't seem that it was extremely long
that they were there in the burning, fiery furnace.
But they spent more time in that burning, fiery furnace
than you did.
Or than I have.
And it was because they were willing to stand.
That they went in that burning, fiery furnace.
And the reality is that as we look at this,
and we think about the communion that they enjoyed,
we find that the psalmist says that in Thy presence
is fullness of joy.
Jeremiah, of course, he's prophesying
on the eve of captivity.
And in fact, Jeremiah's prophesying
when the Babylonians have besieged the city
and he sees them all around.
He understands what's going to happen.
But God gives word after word to Jeremiah.
And in here, in Jeremiah 42 and v. 11,
the Bible says,
be not afraid of the King of Babylon,
of whom you are afraid.
Be not afraid of Him, saith the Lord,
for I am with you to save you
and to deliver you from His hand.
Jeremiah 42 and v. 11.
Don't be afraid of Him.
The One you're afraid of, don't be afraid of Him.
Why? Because I'm with you.
I'm with you.
Man, they had some communion with God.
We understand that as we look at the truth
of the New Testament,
Jesus said in Matthew 28
before His ascension,
all power is given unto Me.
He gives the great commission.
And He says, lo, I am with you always.
Hebrews 13 and v. 5,
a precious promise of the Word of God.
He will never leave thee nor forsake thee.
When we understand the truth of v. 6,
He is my Helper.
Therefore, who or what am I going to fear?
The psalmist said in Psalm 121,
I will lift up mine eyes unto the hills.
From whence cometh my help?
My help cometh from the Lord
which made heaven and earth.
He is my Helper.
He's your Helper.
And here, these men,
they find themselves in the fiery furnace,
they find themselves enjoying some communion with God.
Can I tell you this morning that
if you're going to stand and if I'm going to stand,
we may face some consequences.
But can I tell you,
God will be with you.
And you'll have seasons of communion
that are sweeter than you've ever enjoyed
any time before.
I think about Paul and Silas
when they were in prison.
They were cast into the prison fast,
locked away.
But man, they were singing, were they not?
Singing to God, they were having communion with God.
See, this morning,
I believe that we better prepare to stand.
And I believe that as I look at a passage like Daniel 3,
that I'm encouraged.
This is an encouraging passage of Scripture.
It's exciting.
To read the account, this isn't some fairy tale.
This is God's Word. This happened.
And not only does it encourage us,
I believe it should challenge us.
Because am I willing to stand?
Are you willing to stand?
I mean, when the stakes are like they were for these three,
are we willing to stand?
In closing, I want you to consider
some consequences of their stand.
I want you to consider with me a few things
as we look at the remainder of the passage.
I want you to, just for a moment,
consider how this experience
impacted their own lives.
Can you imagine?
Listen, when you see God work,
when you see God do something miraculous,
it has an impact in your life.
Do you think that these men
talked about this experience?
I mean, I do.
I don't have any Bible to prove it to you.
But I see these guys talking about
there was a time that we were in the burning fiery furnace.
Let me tell you what happened.
Can you imagine the generational impact
maybe to their grandchildren
as they would sit and talk about what God did?
Man, it had an impact in their lives.
But in verse 27, I want you to notice
how this experience impacted the lives
of the princes, the governors, the captains,
and the king's counselors.
Notice what it says in verse 27.
Again, to get back to the context,
Nebuchadnezzar has come close to the mouth
of the burning fiery furnace.
He says to these men,
ye servants of the Most High God,
come forth, and they came hither.
They came forth out of the midst of the fire.
It says in verse 27,
and the princes, governors, and captains,
and the king's counselors,
being gathered together,
notice these three words,
saw these men.
They saw it.
They were eyewitnesses of these men
walking out of the burning fiery furnace.
And it says,
upon whose bodies the fire had no power,
nor was a hair of their head singed,
neither were their coats changed,
nor the smell of fire had passed on them.
How many of you have ever been to a bonfire?
How many of you, when you got home,
smelled like bonfire?
How many of you have ever grilled?
And you try not to touch the flame,
but those little hairs get singed up.
Right?
These men were in the midst
of the burning fiery furnace.
And all these fellows that were there,
the princes, the governors, the captains,
the king's counselors,
they see these men walk out,
and they're not bound anymore.
The fire had no power on them.
They have not a hair singed.
And they don't even smell like fire.
Now that would cause those guys
to kind of like, what is going on?
Right? I mean, seriously.
You remember back in the book of Exodus,
when Pharaoh said something similar
to Moses about who is your God?
God, through a series of events,
the plagues as we refer to them as,
revealed who He was.
The power that He has.
So much so that the counselors of Pharaoh
said this is nothing more than
the finger of God.
Nebuchadnezzar says,
ye servants of the Most High God,
come out!
And all of these idol-worshiping Babylonians
see these men walk out with no hurt.
I don't think any of them were lining up
to go in it to see if their gods could deliver.
Do you?
Nuh-uh.
What an impact,
as we think about the consequences
of their stand.
Listen, when you stand,
there are going to be some consequences.
There's going to be some impact in your life,
in my life.
But in the lives of others around us,
they see what God is able to do.
They see that it's not just a theory.
You know, this book is so much more than theory.
To walk with God is not just a theory kind of thing.
It's real life.
God is really able.
God delivers.
God works.
And we find that this experience
not only impacted these men personally,
it impacted those in leadership around the king,
but it also impacted Nebuchadnezzar.
Verse number 28, it says...
this. He spake and said, blessed be the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego who
hath sent his angel and delivered his servants. Now stop there, we're gonna read
the rest of it in just a moment. But you notice that this man Nebuchadnezzar, he
said, who is that God that shall deliver you out of my hand? And we find that now
he says, ye servants of the Most High God, and he says, blessed be the God of these
men, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, who has delivered his servants, but notice
what he recognizes, that those servants that were delivered, that they first
trusted in him. We sing trust and obey, for there's no other way to be happy in
Jesus, but to trust and obey. Why is it that we should trust God? Because he's
faithful, because he always does what he says he will do. We find that God, as the
children of Israel are given the assignment to go into the the land of
promise, and Moses sends out the spies, and they come back with the evil report,
and Joshua and Caleb are seeking to influence the congregation to go and
believe God, and they were ready to stone those guys. God says, how long will it be
are my people believe me? Trust me, that we have confidence in God. See, it says
that this man, Nebuchadnezzar, he recognized that these servants were
delivered, but it was a result that they trusted in him, and then notice this, and
have changed the king's word, and yielded their bodies, that they might
not serve nor worship any God except their own God. It impacted Nebuchadnezzar.
He said, these guys trusted in God, they yielded their bodies. It's interesting if
you were to go and maybe jot it down in your notes to read Romans 6 about who we
yield ourselves to. We are to yield ourselves unto the Lord, and we find that
these men, they yielded themselves. It's interesting if you look in Romans 6
and you read the references with regard to the word yield or yielded, it's the
same Greek word that is used in Romans 12 when he says that you would present
your bodies a living sacrifice. Same exact Greek word. So, yielding and
presenting our bodies to God, and see what God is able to do. He said, I'm not
interested in signing up for all that. I don't want to be a martyr. Neither do I.
I mean, honestly, I don't want to face, I don't want to go to prison. I don't want
to do any of that stuff, but we got to stand. We got to stand. We have to be
resolved. The pressures are only going to continue to increase. Listen, we have the
Word of God, and the Bible says that in the last days, perilous times are going
to come. They're here. Evil men and seducers are going to get better. No, they're
going to wax worse and worse, deceiving and being deceived. Is that not what the
Word of God says, tells us? Clearly, God gives us the instruction. We find that
really as we look at the consequences and we see the impact upon these groups
of people, I want you to understand that God was glorified, and that's what it's
all about. It's not really about us saying, oh, look at these guys. They were
so bold to stand for God. I'm thankful that they were, but God was glorified. It
says in verse 29, therefore, I make a decree. Now, he started the chapter by
making a decree that everybody bow down to his image, and now he makes a decree
at the end of the chapter that every people, nation, and language would speak
anything amiss against the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego shall be
cut in pieces, and their houses shall be made a dunghill. Why? Because there is no
other God that can deliver after this sort. God was glorified. Then the king
promoted Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego in the province of Babylon. God was
glorified. You know, it's interesting to me. We think about the consequences. You
know, it's been some 2,600 years since this event took place, and we're still
talking about it. 2,600 years. That's a long time, and we're still receiving
encouragement from some individuals that were willing to stand. They're willing to
stand. They just simply said, listen, I can't do this. I cannot be influenced by
your ideologies. I will not bow. I will not conform because I have a higher
authority. I have a higher authority, the highest authority, and one day I'm gonna
stand before him. So are you. The question, however, as we think about this event, we
think about the title of the message this morning, are you willing to stand?
Am I willing to stand? Can I fill you in? It's easy to stand in here. It is. You
take a stand in here, man, we cheer you on. Amen! But we got to be willing to
stand out there. Out there. In a lost and dying world, they need to see that our
God is real. It's not just a theory. You know, they don't think much of our God.
They really don't. They curse him. They hold their fist against him. They need to
see that our God is real. Do you believe this morning that God is still able to
work? I don't know that there's gonna be a burning fiery furnace. Again, the
circumstances, the pressures are different for every generation, but we're
facing some pressures today, and there's a movement today to cause you and to
cause me to bow, to conform, to we can't talk about this, we can't talk about
that, we can't go there, we can't go here. And they want a silence. They want us to
be ashamed. I've said that a couple of times the last few weeks because of our
theme for our missions conference. I am not ashamed. And this morning, are we
willing to stand? Are we willing to stand? I'm encouraged by Daniel 3, but
really more than being encouraged, I'm challenged. Because I look at these three
guys, they didn't have all that we have. We got the whole book, but they had a
real close walk with God that caused them to have some some strength and some
resolve spiritually to say, I understand the stakes. I heard the command. Yes, I
heard the music, but I'm not gonna bow. It's not gonna do it. Are you willing to
stand? Let's pray. Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. Thank you for
your Word. I thank you how that we can go to your Word and be encouraged, and at
the same time be challenged. I thank you for the challenge that Paul gives the
believers in Ephesus, and how that we can look at this event that happened 2,600
years ago, and see some men that stood. We understand and acknowledge readily
this morning that we're facing pressures in our society, in our culture, to bow
and to conform to the ideologies. God, I pray that you would help us to walk in
the Spirit. I pray that you'd help us to put on the armor, that we would be able
to stand in the evil day. Would you help us this morning to let you have your
will and way in our lives? Help us to truly yield ourselves to thee. We pray
that you'd be glorified through every decision, and we'll thank you for it.
Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed. It's our custom to have
an invitation at the end of our service in order to give you an opportunity to
respond to how God may have spoken to you through His Word. Kimberly will play
quietly on the piano. As she does, the altar is open. You don't want to come to this
old-fashioned altar. Maybe you want to make your seat an altar, but would
you let God have His way in your life? As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.