second Kings chapter number eight as we continue studying the life of Elisha and
as we now move on into this eighth chapter of course we've spent several
weeks over the last several Wednesdays we've been in chapter number seven last
week we took a week off from the life of Elisha looked at a passage of scripture
with the life of Ezra and what a blessing that was and this evening as we
get into chapter number eight we will see once again that Elisha has an
interaction with the woman from Shunem and you'll remember this woman from
Shunem based on our study of second Kings chapter number four is several
really probably several months ago now when we studied the fourth chapter of
the book of second Kings and we dealt with the ministry of Elisha and how God
was working and of course he would pass through Shunem it would go through there
on a somewhat regular basis the Bible says that he passeth continually through
that place and so the woman at Shunem she spoke with her husband and she said
we need to make a little chamber and so they had a construction project and we
often refer to a prophet's chamber we use that terminology and we really see
that it comes from what we see here in second Kings chapter number four and
Elisha had testified of the care in which he received each time he would
pass through that place not only having a place in which to stay but also the
great care in which he received we find that the of course through the passage
of scriptures you interact with the lady at Shunem you find of course that they
had no children and Elisha announces that they'll have a son and what a
wonderful day that must have been they have a son and then he's out working
with his dad one day in the field and the boy dies and of course the woman
from Shunem there's no name given she goes to find the man of God and Elisha
sends Gehazi up ahead and long story short that boy is raised from the dead
and then we get into chapter 5 really the end of chapter 4 and 5 6 7 you
don't hear anything about Elisha having any interaction whatsoever with the lady
from the woman from Shunem and her family and now we come to chapter number
8 and the Bible says then spake Elisha unto the woman notice how it's referred
to here whose son he had restored to life so of course we know through the
description that is given here in verse number one as to the woman that God is
referring to that Elisha is going to have this interaction with of course as
I've mentioned there's been a number of events that have transpired over the
past a few chapters of dialogue that we read in the Word of God and we don't
know exactly how much time has passed not only from the last interaction to
this we don't know how much time passed between the end of chapter number 7 the
beginning of chapter number 8 we just know that the dialogue goes into this
interaction that is recorded here we do know that in just a few verses of
Scripture seven years of famine is covered and it's amazing how sometimes
you can read super lengthy portions of Scripture and there's just a brief
amount of time that passes and other times there's just a couple of verses
and several years can pass and so we find that the Bible says then spake
Elisha unto the woman whose son he had restored to life saying arise and go
thou in thine household and sojourn wheresoever thou canst sojourn notice
for the Lord hath called for a famine and it shall also come upon the land
seven years if you're taking notes this evening the Lord hath called for a
famine that is the title for the message adopted right from verse number one for
the Lord hath called for a famine it's interesting in the Word of God as you
often will find references to God's of course judgment upon his people and you
find that in the Word of God periods of famine most what most times are
representative of divine judgment periods of drought you remember we first
find Elijah we first began to study in first Kings chapter number 17 to the
life of Elijah what do you see he's calling for that drought right there's
not going to be neither rain nor dew except at my word and we find that three
and a half years passed and why it was the wickedness of Ahab and Jezebel and
we find that as we move here into the life of Elisha and we have some
understanding of the the the reign of Jehoram and his wickedness and we find
that the Bible tells us that he cleaved under the sins of Jeroboam the son of
Nebat and of course we dealt with many of those things but we find that here as
we enter into the eighth chapter of the book of 2nd Kings that once again there
is divine judgment upon the house of Israel because of their wickedness I'm
thankful that our God is righteous and that he is the righteous judge and we
find that he in righteousness indeed executes judgment and we find that he's
given truth throughout the entirety of the Word of God with regard to his hand
of blessing and his time of judgment the reality is that most of us I think if
all of us are in our right minds we would say that we would much rather have
times of blessing than times of judgment amen and but we find that the
blessing comes as a result of obedience and honoring the Lord and so we find
here that as we look at the passage of scripture I want you to see the
declaration of Elisha the declaration really recorded for us in the first two
verses here of chapter number eight we see that it's simply this the Lord hath
called for a famine not only does he declare that there is a famine that is
coming but we find that he tells he specifies the period of time that that
famine would be upon the land we find that it says that it shall come also
come upon the land seven years that's a lengthy period of time we can look back
to the life of Joseph we don't have time this evening to study all of that but
you can think about the seven years of plenty in the seven years of famine that
are dealt with there in the life of Joseph when he was in Egypt and so on
and so forth and you can read the passages of scripture and even in a time
when they had purposefully planned during the seven years of plenty for the
famine that would come if you read the passages of scripture in the book of
Genesis you can see how difficult that period of famine really was and we find
that as we come here to second Kings chapter number eight we read the
declaration of Elisha we see the power and sovereignty of God I'm thankful this
evening that our God is sovereign that he is in control of all things and we
find that Elisha's declaration is this for the Lord hath called for a famine
see there are some that would like to of course deny the existence of God there
are some that would say that God exists but he's really not in control of
anything he kind of has taken a step back from his creation if you will but
we understand that our God is intimately involved with the affairs of mankind we
can read throughout the whole of scripture we can see the hand of God you
can read a book like the book of Esther and you can find that though the name of
God is not mentioned throughout the ten chapters of the book of Esther oh how
you can see the hand of God at work in superseding over the affairs of man and
what a blessing to know that our God is in control that he is sovereign that he
does have all power we find that in this declaration that there was some
instruction that would be given to the woman from Shunam we find that the Bible
says that then speak Elisha unto the woman he was faithful to deliver this
message to this woman and he said here arise and go notice thou and thine
household and sojourn wheresoever thou can sojourn for the Lord has called for
a famine and it shall also come upon the land seven years it's interesting we
look at the declaration of Elisha here in verse number one and you see what
he's announced and who he's announced it to the specifics of that judgment but
it's also interesting to see the response is recorded in verse number two
and really what you're seeing is the obedience of this woman and her
household and we see her response it seems quite evident that she believed
the man of God Elisha had proven to be a man of God Elisha had proven that he
spoke the word of the Lord as I've mentioned many times through the life of
Elijah you see him using that terminology with quite regularity thus
saith the Lord you don't find that quite as often with Elisha though you find
references of it but you know that he's speaking the word of the Lord he is a
faithful prophet and when he comes to this woman and he gives this declaration
she immediately responds with obedience I like that I believe that's exemplary
for us I believe that there is within the response of this woman there is a
lesson for each of us to learn on the importance of obedience and this
obedience of this woman was immediate consider she was going to leave
everything that she knew she was gonna leave her land she was gonna leave that
which was familiar to her notice it says and the woman arose and did after the
saying of the man of God and she went with her household and sojourned in the
land of the Philistines seven years now seven years a long time in some regards
seven years
It seems like it just kind of goes by fast.
But seven years, really, that's a long time.
And we find that she immediately responds
with obedience.
It says that she arose
and she did after the saying of the man of God.
She and her household.
And they went and dwelt in the land of the Philistines
for seven years.
We see the declaration of Elisha.
Notice number two,
discussion with the king.
It's amazing as you look at what happens.
Again, we find that verse number two
describes for us her departure from Shunam
and her arrival into the Philistines' land.
And you come to verse number three
and it says,
and it came to pass at the end,
excuse me,
and it came to pass at the seven years end.
And so just like that,
we've gone right through the seven year period of famine.
We don't know.
God doesn't give us all the details of all that happens
and so on and so forth.
But we do know that the famine has now ended.
And so what happens,
the woman returns.
It says that the woman returned
out of the land of the Philistines.
So she returns after seven years.
And the Bible tells us
that she went forth to cry unto the king
for her house and for her land.
As I've referred to this as the discussion with the king,
we find that she went to make a petition to the king
for both her house and her land.
And she'd been gone for seven years.
But now she's coming back
and she's making this request,
this plea if you will.
And she's seeking to have a discussion with the king.
But it's interesting because the Bible tells us
that though she's interested in having this dialogue,
this discussion with the king,
that the king is actually in the midst
of a discussion already.
The king is having a discussion with Gehazi.
We've not heard about Gehazi for a lengthy period of time.
It was at the end of chapter number five
when we last heard about Gehazi.
Remember he was the servant of Elisha.
And we find that Gehazi was there
for many of the miracles
that God would perform through Elisha
during his earthly ministry.
And you find that Gehazi was there
and he saw God work.
And there in chapter number five
when you read about the healing of leprosy
from Naaman and all of that situation,
remember Gehazi decided that he wanted something.
And so he chased after Naaman
and the host that came from Syria.
And as he returned, he says,
I didn't go anywhere.
And of course, he's stricken with leprosy at that point.
And the Bible tells us
there's actually some interesting division
from biblical scholars.
Some would say that the events in chapter number eight
would reveal that Gehazi no longer had leprosy.
I would disagree with that.
And here's why in the end of chapter number five
in verse number 27,
the Bible says that the leprosy therefore of Naaman
shall cleave unto thee and unto thy seed forever.
And he went out from his presence a leper as white as snow.
So I don't believe that he was healed of his leprosy
nor do I believe that the events in chapter number eight
preceded what we read of in chapter number five.
I think this is a proper chronological order
of the events in the life of Elisha
and that which happens.
In fact, when you come to the end of chapter number eight,
you really start to see the latter years of Elisha
and some of the announcements that he makes,
I believe, and I'll just give it to you for further study.
If you go back to the book of Leviticus
in chapters 13 and 14,
you'll find how that the priest were to investigate
those that thought they had or did have leprosy.
And they were to go through the process
of how they would go forth
in identifying those individuals,
but also in announcing them clean.
And if you read the portion of Scripture,
if they were completely white with leprosy,
they were clean.
And so if you look here in 2 Kings five and verse 27,
it says, and he went out from his presence,
a leper white as snow.
And it's very interesting as you look at what happens again
back in Leviticus,
and really you got to read all of the entirety
of both of those chapters.
But I'll read one verse for you in Leviticus 13
and verse number 13.
It says, then the priest shall consider and behold,
if the leprosy have covered all his flesh,
he shall pronounce him clean that hath the plague.
It is all turned white, he is clean.
I love the Bible.
You study passage with passage
and you interpret the word of God.
And you begin to see that this Gehazi
is in the presence of the king.
Now, he no longer is the servant of Elisha,
but now he's somehow having this discussion with the king.
And we find that as he's talking with the king,
it's amazing.
And again, you see the providence of God.
You see the hand of God at work.
This woman from Shunem,
she had received the message from Elisha.
She departs the land because of the famine.
She comes back after seven years
and she desires to have this discussion with the king
to make her petition,
to have her land and her home restored.
And as she enters in,
she interrupts a discussion that's already taking place
between the king and Gehazi.
Look at what the discussion is.
And the king talked with Gehazi,
the servant of the man of God saying,
tell me, I pray thee.
Notice what he asked to know.
All the great things that Elisha hath done.
Isn't that interesting?
The king says, I wanna know about the works of Elisha.
The Bible tells us in verse number five,
that it came to pass as he, that's Gehazi,
was telling the king how he had restored
a dead body to life.
So he's talking, now listen,
there are many miracles of Elisha.
In fact, the Bible records twice as many miracles of Elisha
than you find of Elijah.
And it seems quite interesting
as you think about the double portion and what have you.
But we know that there were many, many miracles
that God performed through the prophet Elisha.
And as this discussion, this conversation is taking place,
Gehazi is speaking about how this dead body
was restored to life.
It says that, behold, the woman
whose son he had restored to life
cried to the king for her house and for her land.
Isn't that awesome?
I mean, just think about the timing, right?
I mean, just we could say from our human perspective,
what are the chances?
It's not chance, it's providence.
And we find here that Gehazi said,
my Lord, O king, this is the woman
and this is her son whom Elisha restored to life.
Isn't that amazing?
You think about the timing.
Elisha said, the Lord's called for a famine,
you need to get out of here.
You and your household, go.
Sojourn wheresoever you can sojourn.
It's gonna be here for seven years.
And she leaves.
She obeys the instruction of the man of God.
And she goes to the land of the Philistines
and she's there for seven years and she returns
and now she's gonna make the petition
that she could have her home and her land restored.
And as she walks in to speak with the king,
Gehazi is telling the king about this miracle.
And then says, in fact, that's her.
Can you imagine?
I mean, it's pretty neat, right?
I mean, talk about the proof, the evidence.
We see the declaration.
We see the discussion.
Notice in verse number six, number three,
the decree, the decree of the king.
It's interesting as we read verse number six
that it begins really, it says,
and when the king asked the woman, she told him.
What a nice, simple way to let us know
that the account is confirmed.
Now, can you imagine being the king?
Can you imagine being Gehazi?
Can you imagine being the woman?
I mean, put yourself in any of the shoes
of the people that are there.
I mean, to be the woman from Shunem,
to show up and to think,
man, they were just talking about us.
To be Gehazi and had just been sharing with the king
about this great miracle and then here she comes.
To be the king and hearing this
and then man, here's the evidence right in front of me.
And so the Bible says that when the king asked the woman,
she told him, the account is confirmed.
I'm not sure of how much dialogue they had.
I'm not sure of what details perhaps
the king might've wanted to know.
But you remember that on that particular day
as it's recorded for us in 2 Kings chapter number four,
when her son died, the Bible says that she went up
and laid him on the bed of the man of God
and shut the door upon him and went out
and she then tells her servant,
she says that she called unto her husband and said,
send me, I pray thee, one of the young men
and one of the asses that I may run to the man of God
and come again.
And he said in verse number 23 of chapter number four,
wherefore wilt thou go to him today?
It is neither new moon nor Sabbath.
And she said, it shall be well.
And she gets on the,
she says that they saddled the ass
and said to the servant, drive and go forward.
Slack not thy riding for me except I bid thee.
And they go quickly to the man of God.
And we find that she answered Gazi and said it is well.
And then we know the account and we see what happens.
And Elisha came into the house in verse 32
and the child was dead.
He was upon the bed.
And we find that the Bible tells us in verse number 33
that Elisha prayed, he prayed unto the Lord.
And then in verse number 36,
he calls for the Shunammite and he said,
Take up thy son.
It's the very account that's being discussed with the king
here in 2 Kings 8, verses 4 and 5.
We find that this account is confirmed.
This was not just some story that Gehazi was telling.
This was not some make-believe fairy tale type of thing.
No, this was truth of an event that happened.
And I'm so thankful that we have the truth of the Word of God.
I'm so thankful that we can rehearse the miracles of God
and we can rehearse what God has done in our lives
and the lives of others.
We can look at the record of God's Word
and we can understand that they are confirmed.
These are not fables.
They're not stories.
So often you hear me use the phraseology, a Bible account.
I don't believe it's sinful to use the phraseology,
a Bible story.
But sometimes when we read stories to our children
that are these fairy tale type of stories,
and all of a sudden we're going to say,
okay, let me tell you a Bible story.
Sometimes it's difficult for a child to differentiate.
This is a Bible account.
This is something that happened.
We find that the account is confirmed in verse number 6,
and then notice that her request was granted.
It's a decree that the king makes.
The Bible says,
so the king appointed unto her a certain officer saying,
Restore all that was hers and all the fruits of the field
since the day that she left the land, even until now.
I'm not sure how the discussion would have gone
if Gehazi wasn't rehearsing these things to the king.
We could speculate.
We could sit around and come up with our theories
as to how the king would respond to this woman,
whether he would just dismiss her from his presence
or what he would do.
But you find that this woman was obedient to the man of God,
to the declaration that was made with regard to the famine,
and God no doubt had instructed Elisha
to deliver this message to the Shunammite woman,
and she believes and she responds in obedience
and she leaves,
and now when she returns and makes her petition
for her home and her land to be restored,
we find that the Lord's timing being perfect,
these events just as they are,
and the king makes this decree.
He sends an officer and says,
restore, notice what he says,
restore all that was hers,
notice, and all the fruits of the field
since the day that she left the land,
even until now.
What a blessing.
What a great result.
We see through these six verses,
we're reminded of the power of God.
We're reminded of His sovereignty
that He is in control of the affairs of mankind.
And the reality this evening is that
the woman could ask 105 questions
about why she should leave,
where she should go,
what she should do,
what's gonna happen to my house,
what's gonna happen to this,
she could ask all those questions,
but she just obeyed.
She just obeyed.
And this evening,
we learn valuable lessons from this account in Scripture.
We learn the lesson of obedience.
We learn the lesson of trusting the Lord
and knowing that He is able to do
even what we might not see happening.
I'm not sure what her expectations were
leading into that discussion.
Sometimes we make a request expecting to be denied,
because our faith is little.
I'm not sure what her expectation was going into it,
but all I can say is that
as I look at this passage of Scripture,
I am reminded that God's timing is perfect.
And what a blessing to be able to see
these types of accounts
and to be encouraged in our own walk with God
on the importance of following God and obeying God
and seeing God work as only God can work.
This evening, we see the Lord hath called for a famine.
God's aware of the things that take place
within the affairs of mankind.
God is not far off in a distant land somewhere
where He's unaware of those things that are happening.
He's a gracious, merciful God.
He's long-suffering,
but we find that He is a righteous God.
He is the righteous judge.
And this passage begins with the announcement
of that judgment, the Lord hath called for a famine.
In a time such as that,
you are reminded of the importance
to turn your attention to the Lord,
to consider your ways.
You find the prophets often said, consider your ways.
Consider your ways.
How important it is even as we live in such a time.
I mean, when you look at a global pandemic,
I know it's not a famine,
but if you deny that God is in control
and that He is over these things,
you can see God's hand.
Listen, it is time for man to seek the Lord.
I disagree 100% with what some of the folks
in our nation have said.
There have been some, I won't name names,
there have been some that have been on public television
that have said this is beyond the power of God.
Baloney.
God's in control of all things.
It's amazing how just a little tiny virus
could cause such a global situation.
Oh, that man would turn their eyes upon the Lord.
See, we're dealing with something that pales in comparison
to what will happen during the tribulation.
You read the book of Revelation.
You read all of those judgments, 21 of them.
I mean, it's gonna be serious.
This evening, in the time in which this Shunammite
was living, there was gonna be a famine.
The Lord had called for a famine.
Righteous judgment.
She obeyed the Lord and she was divinely protected.
Can you imagine that?
In the land of the Philistines.
There's a whole nother message
we could develop right there.
But she was divinely protected by God.
And then she comes back, the timing is perfect,
and she's restored all of her things.
Isn't that amazing?
We serve a great God who's able to do
exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think.
He's able to take care of his own.
Amen?
And we trust him and we follow him.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you this evening.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for your word, the truth contained therein.
I pray, God, that you'd encourage our hearts tonight.
Help us to be mindful of the fact
that you indeed care for your own.
That you're able, no matter the circumstances,
to take care of us as your children.
And for that, we rejoice.
We thank you that you have all resources.
Lord, we look forward to the day
in which we'll be able to spend eternity with you.
We are looking for the return of the Lord.
We know that it draweth nigh.
God, I pray that you'd help us to be faithful
and obedient to you.
Thank you for the testimony of the Shunammite.
Thank you for the faithfulness of Elisha.
Lord, I pray that you would use us.
Help us to glorify thee in our lives
and we'll thank you for it.
In Christ's name we pray.
Amen.