We'll turn tonight to Isaiah in chapter 41.
Isaiah in chapter 41.
And verse number, for the sake of time tonight,
we'll just read from verse 17 down to verse 20.
Isaiah 41, reading from verse 17 down to verse 20.
We'll hear God's word this evening.
When the poor and needy seek water, and there is none,
and their tongue faileth for thirst,
I, the Lord, will hear them.
I, the God of Israel, will not forsake them.
I will open rivers in high places,
and fountains in the midst of the valleys.
I will make the wilderness a pool of water,
and the dry land springs of water.
I will plant in the wilderness the cedar, the shitar tree,
the myrtle, the oil tree, and I will set in the desert
the fir tree and the pine, the box tree together,
that they may see, and know, and consider,
and understand together that the hand of the Lord
hath done this, and the Holy One of Israel hath created it.
Amen.
And we know the Lord will bless the reading of his word
tonight.
Let's just pray together briefly before we look at God's
word.
Almighty God, we turn to thee.
The arm of flesh will fail us.
We dare not trust our own.
But we do tonight put on the gospel armor.
And we do watch unto prayer.
And we do ask thee, Lord, as we've been singing,
make us ready for the coming of the Lord Jesus.
And Lord, we thank thee for thy word tonight.
We thank thee for this church, for the pastor and this church.
And we pray you bless him and his family,
and bless each member of this congregation here this evening.
Or may they know thy presence in a very real way.
May you speak to us, encourage us in the things of God.
We pray that thy spirit would speak tonight
through the preaching of the word.
We pray that, Lord, hearts would be surrendered to thee.
And we ask this in Jesus' name.
Amen.
The book of Isaiah is found here in the middle of the Bible.
And in my country, we say Isaiah.
I know here it's Isaiah.
And so you have to forgive me if you don't understand what I'm saying.
You just have to nod along, OK?
But the book of Isaiah is found in the middle of the Bible.
And oftentimes, people call it the mini Bible.
There are 66 books in the Bible.
And there are 66 chapters here in Isaiah.
And if you were to read from verse chapter number one
down to chapter number 39,
you'd find much of the first part of Isaiah
to be all about woe and difficulty and cursing.
And then you get to chapter 40,
and you find the first word of chapter 40 is the word comfort.
Because that's the New Testament, some people say,
when the Lord Jesus Christ will come.
Comfort.
And he did come.
And he has come.
And he has brought great comfort to men and women around the world.
Here we are in Isaiah chapter 41 tonight.
And the Bible has told us in the book of Isaiah
that judgment is coming
and that judgment will come to the people of God
because they, particularly in Isaiah,
have fallen into idolatry.
If you read Isaiah 40 in verse 18,
the Bible says this,
to whom then will you liken God?
Or what likeness will you compare unto him?
And there are many people in the time of Isaiah
who were making their own God.
And the Lord says, the nations are like a bucket.
And the Bible tells us that there were people
who were making all kinds of gods.
And then the Bible says in verse 21,
have you not known?
Have you not heard?
Have you not been told you from the beginning?
Have you not understood from the foundations of the earth?
It is he that sitteth upon the circle of the earth.
And so the Bible message of Isaiah really
is to behold our God, to look to God.
And I just want to draw your attention tonight
with God's help to a little expression here
that I believe Isaiah is giving by the Holy Spirit
to the people of God, the true people of God
who are living in captivity.
And it's found here in verse number 17.
Look with me there if you can.
Just a little expression and it says this,
I the Lord.
And I want to speak tonight with God's help
just simply about that thought, I the Lord.
That is what the whole world just needs to see.
But can I say before the world can see it,
you have to see it.
Before the world, before this community can see
I the Lord in their life,
it has to begin with us, doesn't it?
And so I want to begin there with God's help.
And I want you to see this evening
that the work of God begins really with the Lord.
It doesn't begin with me.
It doesn't begin with you.
I didn't choose for myself to go to the country of Wales.
I'm an Englishman and an Englishman likes his own castle.
That's what they say, isn't it?
Or castle.
They like their own castle.
But I didn't choose to go to where God chose.
And I want to say to you my friend this evening,
if we were to sum up our lives, it should be this.
I the Lord.
It's all about him, not about you.
It's not about what you can do,
it's about what he can do through you.
Isn't that an encouragement tonight?
It's all about God.
And that takes the pressure off us, doesn't it?
We were going out soul winning yesterday.
And sometimes we can get a little bit depressed
and discouraged because nobody answers the door.
Maybe that happens, I know that happens here
because your pastor said that,
but it happens sometimes where we are in Wales.
Nobody answers the door, nobody's interested.
Listen, it's not about you or about me.
It's about the Lord and what the Lord's doing.
And I just want to look at this text tonight.
Here were people who were in captivity
and they needed to see the Lord.
You need to see the Lord.
I need to see the Lord.
It's all the Lord tonight.
And let's just look at this very quickly.
The Bible tells us this expression, I the Lord,
or just the word I is found in this text six times.
Look at verse 17, I the Lord will hear them.
I the God of Israel will not forsake them.
Verse 18, I will open rivers.
Then through verse 18, I will make the wilderness.
Verse 19, I will plant.
Look at verse number 19, I will set.
This whole chapter, this whole section
that we're going to look at tonight
isn't really about man, it's about God.
And when you have a high view of who God is
and what he's doing,
then that changes everything for you, doesn't it?
So here is our text this evening.
The first thing I want you to notice
is that here are a people who are dwelling,
this is a prophecy obviously,
but are dwelling amidst captivity,
who have nothing, but they have the Lord.
Notice of their condition.
The first point this evening is this really,
I the Lord hears.
Notice their condition.
When the poor and needy seek water.
Now we could spend a whole sermon tonight
talking about those two names, couldn't we?
Poor and needy.
Poor meaning afflicted, wrecked, weak, humbled.
I wonder tonight, have you ever been humbled in your life?
Have you got to a place where God has taken
everything away from you apart from himself?
These people, they were poor,
but not only were they poor, look at it,
they were needy, they were in want, they needed help.
And do you know, the Bible tells us
who's the first person who hears the cry
of the poor and needy?
It isn't Isaiah.
Who's the first person who's heard the cries
of those in Africa tonight, or those in America,
those on your own street who are desperate
for the word of God?
Who is the one that hears their cry?
It's I the Lord.
Before you ever go and reach someone with the gospel,
God is already seeking them, isn't that wonderful?
It's all I the Lord.
It all begins with I the Lord, isn't that wonderful?
And look what they're looking for.
Very basic provision.
When the poor and needy seek water.
Now we live in the Western part of the world, don't we?
Western civilization.
And England isn't much different,
you may be surprised to say this,
but England's much, much different than America.
We have taps just like you do here and all those things.
I remember one time I met someone who said,
do you all have internet in England?
We do.
And we have taps just like everyone else does.
We're a Western civilization.
Water is a very basic need, isn't it?
And here were people who were reduced to nothing.
They had absolutely nothing.
They didn't even have water.
Look what they were seeking for it.
They were looking for it.
Can you imagine just for a moment here this evening,
being in this part of the world
and not having the provision of water?
Having no tap to turn on,
having no bottle to drink out of the fridge
of cool, refreshing water.
But this isn't talking about physical provision.
I want to apply this spiritually.
There are many people around the world today who do not have what you have.
They don't have the freedom to worship God like you do.
They don't have a gospel preacher like you do,
who takes the Word of God and preaches it.
And can I tell you, the country that I've come from
is full of history of men and women like that.
But today, the sad reality is,
there are many people that don't have spiritual water.
We have people in our church, in our video, we showed it to you,
who travel 50 miles one way and 50 miles the other way on a Sunday
just to come to worship with people
who love the Word of God being preached as it should be preached.
Can you imagine that?
50 miles one way with five children in the car,
and 50 miles back, they stay all day?
That's how serious people were for the Word of God.
And here are people tonight, and they haven't got water,
there is none, their tongue's failing for thirst,
they begin to get desperate, then God hears them and steps in.
And I tell you tonight, the sad reality is,
we don't really ever see the Lord until we really need to see Him.
Until we start to get desperate for God.
Do you know the danger of living in a country like the United Kingdom,
in a country like America, I'm assuming tonight, I'm a guest here,
but is that we can get so comfortable with everything,
we don't realize we need God.
We're so used to the mechanics of Christianity even,
we're so used to the blessings of coming into a meeting
and going out again and doing that Sunday after Sunday,
we forget one key thing, we need God.
We need the Lord.
And that's what these people were reduced to.
They were reduced to people who were hopeless, who were helpless,
listen, they didn't have water.
They were seeking water, they couldn't find it.
But I, the Lord, stepped in.
Isn't that wonderful?
Look what it says here in our text in verse 17.
They thirst, their tongue's failing for thirst,
but I, the Lord, will hear them.
Can I tell you, in the nation of Wales,
there were Christians, a group of five people in a little town
called Welshpool, who were desperate for God
to do something with their chapel building.
And they didn't contact us first, God heard them.
And that's always the way it works, isn't it?
You may be here tonight, and you may need to know this,
I need to know this, listen,
what we really need is God to do something, not us.
Do you know, in the United Kingdom,
you can't convince anyone to be a Christian as it were.
It's hard, it's difficult, people are stubborn to it.
People don't want anything to do with the Lord things,
and maybe it's the same here.
What do we need?
We need what Isaiah needed, we need I, the Lord,
to open the hearts and the eyes of the hearts of the men and women of the people,
and God is doing that.
He hasn't changed.
He's the same yesterday, today, and forever.
And just as people are poor and needy,
listen, it's a good place when a nation gets poor and needy,
because then I, the Lord, works.
And maybe in this church tonight,
maybe I can encourage you by saying this,
listen, God is doing something in your location, in your locality.
He's hearing the cries of the poor and needy.
He's hearing the cries of the men and women
who don't know the way in their life,
and I, the Lord, is hearing them.
And as you follow Him, He'll lead you to those very people.
Isn't that wonderful?
I, the Lord.
Listen, when man fails, when everything's gone,
listen, this is what happens in the time of Isaiah,
he hears.
That's what we need, isn't it?
That's what we need.
He hears them.
And notice, look at verse 17.
I will hear them, and I will not forsake them.
What a wonderful verse.
God hasn't finished with America.
God hasn't finished with the United Kingdom.
God is still hearing His people,
just as He was in the days of Isaiah.
He's not given up.
He's not forsaken.
What's He doing?
He's sitting on the cloud, as it were, of heaven,
the throne room of heaven,
and He's hearing His children pray, even tonight,
revive us again, and He's moving.
That's the Lord I know.
There's an old lady in our church.
She lives about 40 miles, 40 minutes, rather, away from us.
She's in her 80s.
She's lost her mind.
She wouldn't want me to say that,
but you don't know her.
Her mind is gone.
I get myself in trouble.
And she's a sweet Christian lady.
Her parents were missionaries to an island somewhere,
and she grew up in a Christian home.
She's recently lost her husband,
and she's been going through a very difficult time.
And you can sit with this lady.
We go and visit with her, and you can sit with her,
and she'll ask you the same question over and over again.
But you know one of the most encouraging things
from a visit with this dear lady is this.
She says, there's one verse God has never let me forget.
Every time she quotes it to me,
I will never leave thee, nor forsake thee.
She said, God hasn't let me forget that verse.
Why?
Because I, the Lord, hears the cry of the poor and needy,
and He moves.
So the first thing this evening is this.
I, the Lord, hears.
But notice this very quickly this evening.
I, the Lord, will.
The Lord does four things in this text for His people.
Can I tell you, God is still working for His people.
It's wonderful when you see the Lord working in a church,
isn't it?
But it's even wonderful when you see Him working in individuals.
People who come in from outreach, from the doors.
People you never met.
Someone somewhere gave them a tract,
and you don't even know who they are,
and here they are today.
God has done something.
It's wonderful when God's working like that.
Now let's just hear with me.
God says He'll do four things for these people.
Look at verse 18.
He says, I will open.
Then He says in verse number 18, I will make.
Then He says in verse number 19, I will plant.
And then He says in verse number 19, I will set.
Four things God has promised to do.
Now all these things, can I tell you,
are surrounding the location that the children of Israel
were in at this time, this remnant.
They were in the wilderness.
They were in a desert.
They were in a dry land.
Could I apply that maybe this evening spiritually?
Maybe you feel sometimes you're in a desert.
I know it doesn't feel like a desert around here,
but maybe sometimes you feel spiritually I'm in a desert.
Nobody's interested in the things of God.
Nobody's responding to when we go out on the doors
or when we do this or when we do that.
They felt like they were in a very dry season.
Notice what it says.
I will open rivers in high places.
I will make the wilderness a pool of water.
You know what God is doing here?
God is doing something in difficult places.
Aren't you thankful tonight that I, the Lord,
is able to move in the most hardest places in the planet Earth?
Do you know where the church they believe is growing the most this evening?
It's in places like China, North Korea,
where everyone is saying it cannot be done.
It shouldn't be done.
God is working.
He's doing the impossible.
Notice some of the things that he does that are impossible.
It says in verse 18,
I will open rivers in high places.
Now, I'm not an expert tonight,
but I don't think that rivers often flow in high places.
And then if you look at verse 18,
I will make the wilderness a pool of water.
I'm not an expert tonight,
but I know that water and wilderness don't often go together.
And then at verse 18, I'm not an expert again.
I'm just an Englishman,
but I don't think that a dry land can become a spring of water.
What's God doing here?
He's doing impossible things
in a place where no one says it can be done.
You need to believe that for your area tonight.
There may be people that come and say,
this isn't the Bible Belt of America.
Nothing can happen.
Listen, rubbish.
I know that's the wrong word here, but I'm going to use it anyway.
God is at work.
He can do anything.
Is there anything too hard for the Lord?
Is there anything impossible with him?
No.
He can do anything.
Look what it says in verse number 18.
I will.
If God says he will, no one can stop his will.
Isn't that wonderful?
Look what it says.
I will open.
I will make.
I will plan.
I will set.
If God is determined to do something,
there isn't anyone who can stand in our God's way.
That's the Lord.
I know. You may be here tonight and there may be challenges ahead of you. There may
be difficulties ahead of you. There may be hard things ahead of you. There may be
challenges. How are we going to do this? We don't have the resources. We don't have
the ability. Listen, I the Lord, if He is with you, nobody can stand against you.
Isn't that wonderful? That's what the Lord said to Joshua when he became the next
man in line after Moses. You remember that? He says, I will be with thee. No man
will be able to stand against. Can you imagine being Joshua in Joshua's shoes?
Can you imagine what it must have been like to be the next in command after Moses and
then become Moses' replacement? The weight of responsibility that would have fallen
upon his shoulders and yet he said this, I'm with you, Joshua. And listen, I
want to tell you tonight, I don't know the circumstances and the difficulties
that you're going through this evening. Maybe as a family of God here or even
as an individual, the situations you're facing, but I know this, I the Lord will.
He will. He does the impossible. He really does. We've seen it in our little
bit part of the vineyard. God has done impossible things in our part of the
world. There was a man a number of years ago who came from a little town about
25 miles or so from where we are, about 40 minutes away. His name was Robert
Germain Thomas. You may have heard of him. He had a burden to go into the Lord's
work. He was ordained as a minister of the gospel and that day it was a very
Christian place where he was living in Wales at that time and minister came to
him one day and said, well, where are you going to go? What town of Wales are you
going to be? He said, I'd like to take the gospel to the outermost parts of the
world and he went. I believe the first place he went to was China. He arrived in
China and as he was there in China within a year his wife who he just
married had passed away. She died. He then felt like, how can I go on? And so he
stopped working in the ministry and he got a job with languages, part of the
Chinese office there. He was a translator and as he was there he came
across people who were making their way across the sea from North Korea. At the
time it was called the Hermit Kingdom and they made their way
across secretly to come and trade. They weren't allowed to do that. It was illegal.
They didn't like that in the Hermit Kingdom. North Korea or Korea as we know it
now, North Korea now, and these people came and they met this man, Robert
Germain Thomas, and they began to speak to him and he began to realize
these people spoke a different language and he offered them a copy of the
Chinese scripture. They said, where did you get that? He said, I have many of these
Bibles. And he would go on secret mission trips with these two, a couple of people
from the Hermit Kingdom, and he would deliver the scripture secretly. He'd go
in and out, in and out. Eventually one day he had this burden. He wanted to go into
the Hermit Kingdom and he wanted to give the Bible to the leaders and he had this
desire and this American captain kind of used him and he went in and it all went
a little bit wrong. The Hermit Kingdom thought they were attacking them and so
they began to open fire upon these people and so he got off the boat and he
began to throw as many copies of God's Word as he possibly could. He got onto
the shores of the Hermit Kingdom. There was a man there and if you met someone
who was an outsider, you were compelled to execute them on the spot. Robert
Germain Thomas stood on the shores of Korea and he said, here's a Bible. It's
just a Bible. The man from the Hermit Kingdom took his sword and he executed
him on the spot. What they did in those days, the leaders took the trophies of
their victims and they took the Bible, didn't really know what it was, and they
tore it apart and they took the pages and they put them on the wall of the
house, of his house, sort of a wallpaper decoration. One by one the locals began
to come in and read the Scriptures and people were converted. Years went on and
so they tell us the kingdom was overthrown and years later someone came
in and talked to this person and he said, how did you hear the gospel? He told them
the story of this man who'd come, Robert Germain Thomas from Wales. And that
building that was the man's house then became the church. What I'm saying to
you tonight is this, I the Lord does impossible things. Look what he does, I
will open rivers in high places, I will open valley, I will open fountains in the
midst of a valley, I will make the wilderness a pool of water. God is doing
that even in this part of the world, isn't he? Listen, this place is a pool of
water in a dry land, isn't it? This place is an open river in a high place. Men
don't think they need God, but you be faithful because you are a river that
people need. God's doing it. Notice what else God does it very quickly in verse
number 19, I will plant in the wilderness the cedar, the shitar tree, the myrtle
tree, the oral tree, I will set in the desert the fir tree and the pine tree
and the box tree together. What God does, he takes a wilderness place and he fills
it with trees, with decoration as it were. That's what the gospel does, isn't it?
The gospel when it saves someone, changes a community and now instead of it being
a dry boring wilderness, see now there's life, now there's spiritual life, now
there's testimonies of God's grace in a dry land. Who did it? I the Lord. Notice
with me very quickly verse 20 and then we'll be closed. That they may see and
know and consider and understand. It's interesting, God says he'll do four
things and verse 20 tells us that those who see what God does, they see four
things. They see, they know, they consider, they understand together, meaning this
that they're all in agreement, it's not just one man who said it, all of them
are in agreement. They look at what's been done and they say this, look at
verse 20, that the hand of the Lord has done this. Can I tell you in the work of
God that's really all we need is the hand of God. It's not about what you do
or I do, it's really not about what we're doing in Welshpool, Wales or in
Bilth, Wales, it's really this, what's God doing? Can I tell you I believe with all
my heart the hand of the Lord has opened water, wells, springs in dry lands and he
can do it here too. Wouldn't it be wonderful if churches were replanted in
this part of the world, in buildings that were being closed where there were only
five people? The same story could be there too, why? Because it's the Lord, he's
doing it. If I can encourage you tonight, that would be my simple encouragement
would be this, this is where the people of God were encouraged, they would step
back and look and they'd say look what God has done and that's all you need. You
just need to live for the I the Lord. You don't need to live for the approval of
men. You sometimes, maybe I'm wrong to say this, but being on this sort of short
deputation whirlwind of, I don't even know if you call it deputation, if you
call what we're doing deputation really, people have said it's not really
deputation because you're only here for for two months. But one thing sometimes
this is challenging for us is that we, you might think this is a bit too weird
for me to say, but sometimes we challenge, the challenge we have is we want to be
liked by people, you know, we want we want people to like us, we don't want
people to think well I can't believe we let them come in here, you know what I
mean? But you know it's really not about us, we don't want you to see us, we're
not interested in our name, we want I the Lord to do something and if the Lord
uses us this evening, perhaps in a small way to be an encouragement to you, praise
God. I the Lord has done it. Let's pray together. Oh our God we thank thee for
what thou art doing and may we be encouraged simply tonight as thy people
this is the Lord's doing. It is marvelous in our eyes. Oh Lord use thy word this
evening to encourage thy people not to look at their circumstances but to look
at their God. In Jesus precious name, Amen.