this portion of scripture this morning.
And we, of course, last week started a mini-series
on preparation for revival.
And in the message last Sunday morning,
I sought to establish the need for revival.
We looked at the book of Nehemiah in the first chapter,
and we understood that Nehemiah requested a report,
he received a report, and his response
is really what we focused upon,
and how he responded to the report that he'd received.
And I sought to provide you last week
with a report on the church in America.
And as we began to look at a number of statistics last week,
I believe that it was quite evident
that we are in need of revival.
I said this, and it's worth repeating,
no longer should we shift the focus
upon another group, another denomination,
another whatever you want to label somebody as,
in order to expose their sin or their failure.
But rather, we must desire the light of God's Word
to be focused upon us as individuals,
and in our local church,
and acknowledge the need for revival.
We mention this, that revival, a very simple definition,
is God bringing His people back to spiritual health.
We understand that as we acknowledge
the need for revival,
that we could sit here this morning,
and we could say, okay, we acknowledge,
we understand, we agree with the truth
that we need revival, now what?
Thus, we've titled the message this morning,
The Pathway to Revival.
And I want you to understand
at the very beginning of the message this morning
that the pathway to revival,
there are many hindrances to that pathway.
We find that there are many things
that will cause the people of God
to even perhaps acknowledge the need,
but never step foot on the pathway to revival.
Maybe they consider the cost,
and they say the cost is just too great.
They're not really willing to change things.
They're not really willing to pay what the cost is
to truly have revival.
The hindrances to revival are many.
We find that the enemy does not desire
for the people of God to be revived.
He is perfectly content and satisfied
with God's people being apathetic and indifferent.
He is absolutely just perfectly fine
with the church of God in America being comfortable.
God never called us to comfort.
In fact, He said,
"'Yea, all those that live godly in Christ Jesus
"'shall suffer persecution.'"
We find that we look at the church of the Laodiceans
referred to there in Revelation chapter number three,
and they were a church that was,
man, they were comfortable.
They had everything that they needed, quote unquote.
They were apathetic and they were indifferent.
They had this perspective that they had need of nothing,
and really even the Lord,
because the Lord was on the outside of the church
that He bought with His blood, knocking.
This morning, as we think about the pathway to revival,
we consider the hindrances that are there,
and we understand that there'll be great difficulty,
but I hope this morning that we've acknowledged the need
and we've determined that I wanna get
on the pathway to revival.
Revival is for the individual.
Let me say this, revival is a work of God.
It is God bringing His people back to spiritual health.
It is a work of God Almighty, and the psalmist said this
in Psalm 85 in verse number six.
He says, "'Wilt thou,' speaking of the Lord,
"'wilt thou not revive us again?'
It's a work of God.
We cannot manufacture the work of God.
We ought not ever seek to manufacture the work of God.
We simply desire that God would work,
and this morning, we understand that revival
is a work of God.
I would say this, we're in a place and a position
in our lives and in our nation where we come to a place
of being desperate to see God work.
We're desperate to see God work.
The psalmist said this in Psalm 119 in verse 126.
He said, "'It is time for thee, Lord, to work,
"'for they have made void thy law.'"
Think about that phrase.
It is time for thee, Lord, to work.
We are desperate to see God work.
We are desirous to see God work,
and as we think about this pathway to revival,
as we seek to embark on this pathway,
and we draw our attentions to what the prophet of God
said in Hosea 10 in verse number 12,
it's a familiar verse of Scripture,
but I want you to notice in verse number 12 of Hosea 10,
notice what the word of God says.
"'Sow to yourselves in righteousness,
"'reap in mercy, break up your fallow ground,
"'for it is time to seek the Lord,
"'till He come and reign righteousness upon you.'"
Of interest to me in this particular verse of Scripture
is that little phrase in the middle of the verse
where it says, "'For it is time to seek the Lord.'"
We mentioned that the psalmist declared in Psalm 119
in verse number 126, "'It is time for thee, Lord, to work,'
but here the prophet of God is saying to the people of God
that it's time for you to do some things.
And yes, revival is the work of God,
but we ought to be in a position where we are prepared
for God to send revival.
And as we look at this particular passage of Scripture,
I'm gonna go a little bit out of order
of how it's actually worded here in verse number 12,
but I want you to notice as we think about this truth
of the pathway to revival, I seek to get,
I embark upon this journey, this path to revival,
I must first of all, I would say this,
it is time to plow, it's time to plow.
Notice the verse of Scripture,
it says this in the middle of the verse there,
"'Break up your fallow ground.'"
Break up your fallow ground.
We understand the agricultural analogy
that is being used here by the prophet of God,
and we find that as he's using this agricultural analogy
that he's seeking to establish spiritual truth,
oftentimes in the Old Testament,
you'll find that the people of God
had hearts that were hardened,
they had hearts that were not prepared for the word of God,
they were resistant, they were stiff-necked,
they were rebellious,
and we find that their heart was not right with God.
They would go through the motions many times,
and they would bring their sacrifices,
and they would say that we fasted,
but God's saying, listen, I'm concerned about your heart.
Your heart is far from Me.
And we find that as we look here
at this phrase of Scripture where the Bible says,
break up your fallow ground,
and we begin to think about the importance of our heart
being ready to receive the truth of the word of God,
being ready to receive the seed of God's word.
We understand as we, again,
speak of the agricultural analogy
that is here in this verse of Scripture,
we planted a garden this year.
And there's never been a garden in the place
where we've planted a garden,
at least not for a long, long time,
if there ever had been.
And there was a lot of work to get that ground prepared.
There was a lot of labor that had to go forth.
There were, Joseph and I, he's smiling up here
because he was the one that was there with me working,
and I mean, it was labor, it was work.
Why?
Because I couldn't just go out there
and throw down some seeds and expect
that they would take root
and they would produce some level of fruit for us.
No, the ground had to be prepared.
The ground had to be plowed up.
There was work that needed to be done.
By the way, I couldn't just start with plowing.
I mean, there was a lot that had to be done
in preparing that soil.
And then once the preparations were completed,
we could then plant the seeds, plant the plants,
and then reap a harvest.
But we understand this agricultural analogy,
and we begin to think about our own hearts
and desiring that we'd have hearts
that are tender toward the things of God.
Look over, if you will, in the book of 2 Chronicles
in chapter 34.
In 2 Chronicles chapter 34, God speaks to us
about one of the kings of Judah,
and really, Josiah here in this passage of Scripture,
what a great man of God,
what a great leader for the nation of Judah,
the great revival that took place under his leadership.
We find that it's in this portion of Scripture
in 2 Chronicles 34 that God gives us
some insight to the man Josiah.
And of course, we know that he was just a boy
when he began to reign.
And he began to reign during a time in Judah's history
of great wickedness and great depravity
and idol worship.
And we find that now, Josiah comes to the place
and he gets busy and he begins to serve God.
And by the way, we ought never overlook
the youth in our church.
I was praying this morning,
I was sitting here on the platform,
I got some sunburn, so I was sitting, not kneeling.
And, but God's okay with that, amen?
And I was sitting here praying early this morning,
and I was praying for each one of you
by name this morning and praying that God would work
in our hearts and in our lives.
And I began to pray for the young people
as they sit.
near the front and I began to pray that God would use them
and maybe they would be the catalyst
that God would use to bring some revival.
It was just a little lad that gave his lunch
to the Lord Jesus Christ.
And sometimes if we're not careful,
we can despise little things, we can despise young,
but we find here that while he was young,
he began to, as he had a heart for God,
he began to do the work of God.
And the Bible tells us in verse number 14
of 2 Chronicles 34 that he had given the instruction
with regard to the work and to repair the house of the Lord
and it says that when they brought out the money
that was brought into the house of the Lord,
Hilkiah the priest found a book of the law of the Lord
given by Moses.
And Hilkiah answered and said to Shaphan the scribe,
I have found the book of the law in the house of the Lord.
And Hilkiah delivered the book to Shaphan
and Shaphan carried the book to the king.
This is Josiah and it brought the king word back again
saying all that was committed to thy servants, they do it.
And they have gathered together the money
that was found in the house of the Lord
and have delivered it into the hand of the overseers
and the hand of the workmen.
Then Shaphan the scribe told the king saying,
Hilkiah the priest hath given me a book.
And notice the Bible tells us in verse number 18
that Shaphan read it, the book that was found
in the house of the Lord before the king.
We know the book, the Bible tells us in verse number 14
that the book that was found was of the law of the Lord
given by Moses.
And we find that he's using the word of God.
He's beginning to read the word of God to the king.
Now the king has already been doing some great things,
has he not?
I mean, he's already given some instruction
with regard to repairing the house of the Lord
and so on and so forth.
In fact, in the very carrying out of those instructions
is where they find the word of God.
Shaphan begins to read the word of God.
I'm thankful this morning that God's word is powerful.
No doubt this man had a heart that was prepared to receive.
We see in verse number 19 it says,
and it came to pass when the king heard the words
of the law that he rent his clothes.
You say, well, that's not very kingly.
God's word impacted him.
The Bible says that the king commanded Hilkiah and Ahiakim,
the son of Shaphan and Abdon, the son of Micah,
and Shaphan the scribe and Esaias, servant of the king,
saying, go inquire the Lord for me
and for them that are left in Israel and in Judah
concerning the words of the book that is found.
For great is the wrath of the Lord
that is poured out upon us
because our fathers have not kept the word of the Lord
to do after all that is written in this book.
You find that not only did he hear the word of God,
but he responded to the word of God.
He responded in humility and in brokenness,
and he begins to give instruction
with regard to inquiring of the Lord
to determine what it was that would transpire
because of the rebellion, because of the sin of the people.
And I want you to skip down, if you will,
in verse number 26, and it says,
and ask for the king of Judah,
speaking here again about Josiah,
who sent you to inquire of the Lord.
So shall you say unto him,
thus saith the Lord God of Israel
concerning the words which thou hast heard.
Then notice verse 27, because thine heart was tender,
because thine heart was tender,
and thou didst humble thyself before God
when thou heardest his words against this place
and against the inhabitants thereof,
and humblest thyself before me,
and didst rend thy clothes and weep before me,
I have even heard thee also, saith the Lord.
He says, behold, I will gather thee to thy fathers,
and thou shalt be gathered to the grave in peace.
That's a huge blessing for Josiah.
He says, neither shall thine eyes see all the evil
that I will bring upon this place.
He was spared from that.
Isn't that amazing?
And upon the inhabitants of the same,
so they brought the king word again.
And so you notice that because of his response,
it says, because in verse 27, thine heart was tender.
And that was the key, having that tender heart,
it then led to his humility before the Lord
when he heard the words of God.
And the Bible tells us that he did rend his clothes,
but he also wept before the Lord
according to verse number 27.
And we find how he responded with that heart
that was tender.
Begin to think about our heart
and breaking up that fallow ground again.
This time to plow in order that we would have our hearts
prepared to receive the seed of God's word.
You know, on a daily basis,
we need to ensure that our hearts are prepared
to receive the truth of God's word.
We come to the house of God,
we've been praying before each of our services
and really focusing in that prayer time,
that corporate prayer time at the start of our services
that God would move and work in the midst of our service.
It's not a time to pray for the folks that are sick
or the folks that are traveling,
but God in this hour, would you move?
Would you work?
Would you help my heart to be ready to receive
that I might respond to the word of God?
That we enter into the house of God
with a level of anticipation and expectation
that God has a message for me,
that God has truth for me.
By the way, we should enter our time of prayer
in Bible study every day with that same perspective.
That we open our Bibles in the mornings
or whenever it is that you might read your Bible
and you open the word of God and you say,
God, would you speak to my heart?
Speak, Lord, for thy servant heareth.
Lord, open thou mine eyes
that I may behold wondrous things out of thy law.
Teach me, Lord.
Help me to respond, Lord,
that I might be a doer of the word and not a hearer only.
That our hearts would be ready.
Our hearts would be prepared.
We find that the psalmist speaks of this.
It's interesting, Psalm 51
is the great psalm of repentance of David.
Of course, after his sin there with Bathsheba and Uriah.
And it's interesting because a couple of times here
in this portion of scripture,
he speaks about a clean heart and being clean.
And notice with me in Psalm 51 in verse number 10.
Notice as David is praying,
and if you were to read the entirety of the psalm,
you see his acknowledgement of his sin
and his confession of his sin
in the beginning of this chapter.
And we come to verse number 10 and he says,
create in me a clean heart, O God,
and renew a right spirit within me.
He had said this in verse number seven,
purge me with hyssop and I shall be clean.
He now mentions specifically creating me a clean heart.
There's something about this phraseology
when David is praying and he's saying,
I want a clean heart.
I don't want a dirty heart.
I don't want a hard heart.
I want a clean heart.
I heard David Gibbs make this statement
that too often the people of God
are content with being cleaner, but not being clean.
The reality is that if you gave me a dirty glass,
and so that's dirty, I need a clean one,
and you just kind of wish it around with some water
and then put it back and say, well, there you go.
It's cleaner than it was.
It might be true, right?
It may be cleaner than it was,
but I'm still not interested in drinking my water
or my sweet tea from that particular glass.
I'd prefer that my glass is clean.
You ever go to a restaurant and you got a fork that's dirty?
Some people just take that fork that's dirty
and they just take out the napkin
and they just kind of,
no, man, I want a clean one, amen?
I don't want it to just be a little cleaner.
I don't want just the hard stuff plucked off,
you know what I'm saying?
You ever been in a restaurant and you had that happen?
Come on, man, I want it clean.
Joseph wants to bring his own, amen, right?
He wants to just bring his own silverware.
He's not interested in eating off something
that somebody else ate off of.
And listen, create in me a clean heart.
Not just cleaner, but clean.
Think about that.
The heart, plow, it's time to plow.
Break up your fallow ground.
Notice what he says in verse 17.
The sacrifices of God are a broken spirit,
a broken and a contrite heart.
Oh God, thou wilt not despise.
Notice how he describes it in verse 17
as a broken and contrite heart.
David, in this particular psalm,
he's broken over his sin.
By the way, it should not just be the consequences
of our sin that should cause us to be broken.
It should be the fact that we've offended a holy God.
Against Thee and Thee only have I done this wickedness.
Have I sinned?
I've done this evil in Thy sight.
And sometimes if we're not careful,
we can be broken over the consequences of our sin,
but not really broken over the fact
that we've offended a holy God.
This morning, we find that the instruction of Hosea
to these that he's writing to
contains with it this admonition
to break up your fallow ground.
It's just time to plow.
If we're gonna get on this pathway to revival.
We've acknowledged the need for revival.
So, okay, we acknowledge, we agree,
we wanna get on the path,
we wanna embark on this journey.
Starts with the heart.
Plow up.
Break up your fallow ground.
Notice number two, it's time to plant.
It's time to plant.
You know, it really doesn't do a whole lot of good
to plow up agriculturally,
if we're speaking of the agricultural analogy
that's being used here
in this passage of Scripture in Hosea 10.
It doesn't do a whole lot of good to plow
and break up the fallow ground and then leave it, right?
Some of you know, with our garden this year,
I started a little bit early,
earlier than I was supposed to,
and I was trying to get that thing ready,
and then I broke my finger,
and then I couldn't do anything.
I couldn't grab the shovel, I couldn't grab the rake,
I couldn't grab the rototiller, I couldn't do anything.
And so guess what started to happen in that place
that we had put apart to prepare for a garden?
Some things started growing in it,
and they weren't things that I planted in it, right?
Those things were weeds.
Isn't it amazing how quickly those things can grow?
And all of that work that then had to cease,
you started to see all of this stuff creep in.
And see, when we break up our fallow ground,
when we plow, then it's time to plant,
it's time to get the seed, the seed of God's Word.
We see that the Bible says here in Hosea 10,
in verse number 12,
sow to yourselves in righteousness, reap in mercy.
We understand that sowing and reaping is a law of nature.
We understand that God has given throughout His Word
this truth of sowing and reaping,
and we see it in nature, we see it in our own lives,
and we find here that it's necessary, it's important,
it's imperative that we are sowing good seed.
He says, sow to yourselves in righteousness.
And then what are you gonna reap?
He says, reap in mercy.
It's a great contrast that we see in verse number 13.
It says, ye have plowed wickedness,
ye have reaped iniquity.
What a contrast in verse 13 from verse number 12,
as the instruction is being provided to the people of God
with regard to the procedure that they're to follow,
not only of breaking up that fallow ground,
but it's time to plant, it's time to sow that good seed.
Notice in the book of Galatians, again,
we're familiar with this text of Scripture.
There's great truth here with regard to this principle
of sowing and reaping in Galatians chapter six,
verses seven and eight.
And we look at what is given to us here
in this New Testament epistle.
We find that Paul, under the inspiration
of the Holy Spirit of God, begins by saying,
be not deceived.
You will find that type of terminology on occasion
throughout the Word of God.
You'll find throughout the Word of God at times
where you'll see beware.
And I find in my own life, personally,
as I come to a verse of Scripture that says,
be not deceived, my antenna, so to speak,
kinda is a little bit more in tune with what's going on.
Why?
Because the reality is that if God prefaces
what He's going to say with be not deceived,
the reality is that many must be deceived
with this thinking.
And so he says, be not deceived.
God is not mocked.
What sober man soweth, that shall he also reap.
Be not deceived.
God is not mocked.
It's a law that God has established.
He gives further insight to this truth
in verse number eight.
He that soweth to his flesh
shall of the flesh reap corruption.
Now, I hope that we're not interested
in that first part of verse number eight.
I don't wanna reap corruption.
Do you?
No, thank you.
Well, so he that soweth to his flesh
shall of the flesh reap corruption.
Now, we like that word shall when it's in Romans 10, 13.
For whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord
shall be saved.
And then we say something like this,
it doesn't mean that you might be saved,
doesn't mean that you could be saved.
Man, it is certain, it is absolute, you shall be saved.
And then all of a sudden we read the same word
somewhere else and we say, well.
God says he that soweth to his flesh
shall of the flesh reap corruption.
That's negative, but look at the positive
at the end of verse number eight.
But he that soweth to the spirit
shall of the spirit reap life everlasting.
He then says, let us not be weary in well-doing,
for in due season we shall reap if we faint not.
You know, it's possible to become weary,
begin to see things that are taking place in our world
and begin to think that maybe our efforts
aren't really worth it.
The reality is that right now we're at a place
where we're hollies out there picking tomatoes
almost every day.
But you know, that didn't happen overnight.
There's a truth of sowing and reaping
that it's not immediate.
And he says in verse number nine,
let us not be weary in well-doing,
for in due season we shall reap if we faint not,
that we persevere, that we continue on.
And we think about this truth of this sowing
to yourselves in righteousness and it's time to plant.
It was J. Vernon McGee that made this statement.
He said, unfortunately, in his experience
that too many of God's people would spend six days a week
sowing seeds of wickedness and then they'd show up
to church on Sunday and they would pray for crop failure.
You just let that sink in just for a moment.
He said for six days they would sow seeds of wickedness.
Then they'd show up to church
and they'd pray for crop failure.
But God says be not deceived.
God is not mocked.
Whatsoever man soweth, that shall he also reap.
And we find this morning that as we begin
to think about this process, this pathway to revival,
it starts with preparing my heart,
breaking up our fallow ground,
having a heart that is tender and ready to receive
that as we open the word of God.
By the way, let me say this.
We don't need to wait until September 18th to have revival.
Revival is not something that's just on a calendar.
We have a revival meeting that's on the calendar
on September the 18th or the 21st
and we have a special guest speaker that's coming.
But the reality is that you, we can have revival.
I can have revival today.
We can have that revival in our lives
where God has brought his people,
he's brought us as individuals back
to that place of spiritual health.
We begin to plant those good seeds.
Begin to plant so to the spirit,
as he says in Galatians 6 and verse number eight,
so shall of the spirit reap life everlasting.
You say, well, I'm just not seeing any of the results.
Takes time.
You don't plant today and reap tomorrow.
Now, sometimes the fruit comes faster than other times.
In fact, if you're to plant some fruit trees,
they take a whole lot longer to produce fruit
than some vegetables,
vegetable plants that you can plant, right?
And we see those laws in nature.
And so we find here that it's time to plow
back to Hosea 10, it's time to plant.
Let me say this, it's time to pursue.
It says this in verse number 12,
for it is time to seek the Lord
till he come and reign righteousness upon you.
I want you to notice that phrase when he says,
it is time to seek the Lord, the idea of pursuing the Lord.
I would say this, that there are many things
in our world today, many things in your life today,
many things in my life today that are competing
for our attention, competing for our pursuit, right?
A lot of things.
But we must be laser focused on pursuing our God.
I mean, laser focused.
There are a lot of distractions,
a lot of things that are gonna come
and try to gain our attention to pursue this
and pursue that and pursue this thing over here.
And oftentimes when we're pursuing those things,
we find that those things are just temporal things.
They're things that just fade away.
And it could be our lifelong pursuit.
And we find out that it doesn't bring the joy
or happiness that we thought it would bring.
How many people have had that testimony?
In fact, Holly was asking me last night,
there was a, we were talking a little bit
about college football and she asked me this question.
She said, well, how many of these college players
actually make it to the NFL?
And I said, it's probably about 1% or less.
She said, are you kidding me?
She said it was a lot higher than that.
But I mean, if you do the math, you just figure it out.
It's one or less percent.
I didn't do a Google search.
Google knows everything.
But I just kind of did the math in my head
and tried to figure it out.
But you.
Just work how they are.
She said, so why are they doing this?
That's what she asked me.
She doesn't understand sports a whole lot, right?
And doesn't like sports a whole lot.
But that was her question.
And the reality is that we could ask ourselves
the question of ourselves.
Why am I pursuing what I'm pursuing?
Why am I doing what I'm doing?
And we think about this truth this morning
of seeking the Lord, of pursuing Him,
and understand there are all sorts of things
that will vie for our attention,
that are competing for our pursuit,
that I must be laser focused on pursuing the Lord.
And let me say this this morning,
we are not pursuing the blessings.
We're pursuing God.
There's a great difference.
So often what happens if we're not careful
is we begin to lead and live our lives in such a way
that maybe we're just seeking the blessing,
maybe we're just seeking the blessing from God
instead of seeking God.
I'm thankful for God's blessing,
but you understand this morning
that God is worthy of our pursuit
without regard of the blessing.
He is worthy.
Let me say it this way,
He's worthy of our service
without the blessing of our service.
Amen?
And if we're not careful,
there are times in which we think maybe
that we could manipulate the hand of God,
that if I do these certain things,
if I do this certain thing,
that it means it's going to result in this way.
And the reality is that God is sovereign
and God has a plan and God has a purpose.
And it doesn't, we cannot manipulate God,
but we must still live in such a way
that we're pleasing God.
Does that make sense this morning?
Because when I want to please God,
listen, this morning, God is good.
Was God good in the life of Job?
Sure he was.
But did Job lose everything?
Yeah.
But God was still good.
Was God good in the life of,
we can begin to enlist all sorts of people.
How about Paul and Silas?
They're on a missionary journey.
Bringing the gospel to Philippi.
Right?
They're serving God.
They're doing what God's called them to do.
And then they get beaten.
They get imprisoned.
You say, yeah, but the,
the Lord sent an earthquake and delivered them.
I understand.
But they still got beaten and imprisoned.
That's more than I've gotten.
How about Isaiah?
If you read the book of Hebrews in the 11th chapter,
the hall of faith chapter that we often refer to it as,
we see great triumphs in Hebrews chapter number 11.
And we can look at Hebrews 11
and we can read of those triumphs
and we can read of, by faith,
this particular hero of the faith did this
and this one did this and this one did this.
But we come to the end of Hebrews chapter 11
and we read what the Bible says
and others, in verse 36,
had trial of cool mockings and scourgings.
Yea, moreover, of bonds and imprisonment.
I mean, it's exciting to read about Daniel
in the den of lions.
Exciting to read about Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego
in the fiery furnace.
But you read of these others,
the Bible says in verse 37, they were stoned.
They were stoned.
Think about Stephen in Acts chapter number seven.
Was Stephen not doing what he was supposed to do?
No, man, he was preaching.
And he was preaching a powerful message.
The people were under conviction.
They lashed out at him, they stoned him.
Others that were stoned, notice this,
they were sawn asunder.
History would tell us that Isaiah faced such a death.
The prophet Isaiah saw God high, holy,
and lifted up, preached faithfully.
Listen, we're not pursuing the blessing.
We're pursuing God.
And as we pursue God, it is within his sovereign right
on what he allows to happen in our lives
and how he will use those circumstances in our lives
for the purpose of bringing glory and honor to himself.
John 11 in our Sunday school lesson this morning.
And the reality is that as we seek God,
that we understand that we're seeking and serving him.
He is worthy, he is God Almighty.
Can you imagine that the God of the universe
would even allow us to seek or to serve him?
If we seek him with all of our heart,
he should be found in us.
You think about that, that we can have that communion
with God Almighty as we seek him, as we seek him.
Notice what the psalmist says,
turn to Psalm chapter 42, if you will.
Look at the analogy that the psalmist uses here,
and this is a great truth,
and I hope that, one, that we could look at our own lives
and we could say, yes, it's in this manner
that I want to seek the Lord and to pursue my God.
And we find that in Psalm 42, is this not on?
Jim's back there telling me this is not on.
Somebody's gonna put some bad batteries
in my thing up here.
Dean, is that you?
Dean's not even in here, amen.
I'm gonna change the batteries real quick.
Stand by, commercial break.
Jim?
No, no good?
Pulpit mic.
Just use the pulpit mic, amen.
All right, we'll get rid of this thing,
and let me just use the pulpit mic.
That means I can't move.
All right, Psalm 42, look at verses one and two.
The Bible says this.
As the heart panteth after the water brooks,
so panteth my soul after thee, O God.
My soul thirsteth for God, for the living God.
When shall I come and appear before God?
Notice the imagery of verse number one of Psalm 42.
As the heart panteth after the water brooks.
You think about the imagery that is used here
in an animal that has not had the quenching of its thirst,
an animal that's running and desiring,
and it says, as the heart panteth after the water brooks,
so panteth my soul after thee, O God.
Have you ever been thirsty?
Have you ever been hungry?
You know, in America, we say we're hungry.
We just ate like a few hours ago.
You know what I'm saying?
Your kids sometimes will say, I'm starving.
Your husband sometimes will say,
all the ladies, I'm starving, what's for dinner, right?
And we, listen, the reality is that
we've not really known hunger, most of us, right?
Like some in the world have known hunger.
You ever been in a position where you're just,
you feel like you're parched, you just need a drink.
You just need something to quench your thirst.
The psalmist says, in that manner,
that's how I am pursuing God.
So panteth my soul after thee, O God.
When's the last time, I just need God's word.
It doesn't matter what else is going on.
I just need God's word.
Because when we need that drink,
when we need that sustenance,
there's something that comes in to distract us
and we say, hold on, I need to do this first.
I need a drink.
I just wonder of our pursuit of God.
How are we longing for God?
When we get up on Sunday morning
and we get to go to church today,
we get to fellowship with the believers today,
we get to worship God today,
we get to hear from the word of God,
God has a message for me.
Man, I can't wait to get there.
Because I'm longing for God.
My devotions daily, what is it that would distract us
from seeking God and saying, I'm pursuing God.
I just want to get into his word.
I just want God to show me and reveal himself to me
and help me.
And I'm longing for that.
We find that here as we begin to think about
this seeking the Lord, this pursuit of God,
again, being laser focused and understanding
how desperately we need him.
A missionary from Asia came to the United States
several years ago and said, I don't know the missionary.
I don't know the pastor that gave the story.
But I read that after being in the United States
for a few weeks, the pastor that had kind of
took him around and introduced him to some friends
and tried to raise some support in different things,
the pastor inquired what he thought
about the American church.
And this man from the other side of the world said,
I'm amazed at how much you can accomplish without God.
And that stunned the pastor.
He said, all of your programs, all of your,
and he just began to listen.
He said, I'm not trying to criticize.
I'm just giving an answer to the question that you asked.
I'm amazed at how much you can do without God.
But the reality is that if we understand biblically
without him, we can do nothing.
And what needs to happen in our lives when we think about this pursuit of God is we must
come to a place where we recognize how desperately we need God.
And with that same level of desperateness of seeking that drink to quench a thirst or
that sustenance to quench a hunger pain, that we say spiritually, I have that level of desperation
to seek God, to minister to my spirit and to my soul.
I need God.
And I'm seeking God.
I'm not just seeking a blessing from God, I'm seeking God.
Paul said this in Colossians 3, if you then be risen with Christ, seek those things which
are above, where Christ sitteth on the right hand of God.
Set your affection on things above, not on things of the earth.
For you're dead and your life is hid with Christ in God.
The kingdom of God is not going to advance by our church becoming filled with men.
But can I tell you for a long time, that's really been our goal.
Our goal in our churches for a number of generations has been we've got to fill the church house,
fill the church house, fill the church house.
And I'm not saying that that's a bad goal, reaching people with the gospel.
In fact, he told us in John 15 in the same passage where he said that without him we
can do nothing, he said, herein is my father glorified that you bear much fruit.
So we understand that God is glorified as we bear fruit.
But the reality is that the kingdom of God is not going to advance just by our churches
being filled with men, but by the individuals in our churches becoming filled with God.
And as we as individuals in our churches are filled with God, the result of that is that
we'll be reaching people with the gospel.
The result of that is that the church house will be filled up.
But that's not the number one goal.
The number one goal is that I'm filled with God.
Be filled with the spirit.
We spoke of that last Sunday evening and the importance of that truth.
There's a great contrast in Hosea 10 as we wrap up this morning.
In Hosea 10 verses 12 and 13, there's a great contrast between those two verses of scripture.
And we find that the contrast is provided to us and we find that really in verse number
12, the prophet of God is telling them that they need a different path than the one in
which they've journeyed on.
The path in which they've been on is given to us in verse number 13 and he says, no,
you need a different path.
And as we would begin to consider and really conclude this message this morning on this
preparation for revival miniseries, this pathway to revival, we must look at the contrast here.
He says, sow to yourselves in righteousness, reap in mercy, break up your fallow ground
for it is time to seek the Lord till he come and rain righteousness upon you.
Notice what they have been doing.
Ye have plowed wickedness, ye have reaped iniquity, you have eaten the fruit of lies
because thou didst trust.
Notice these words, in thy way, thou didst trust in thy way in the multitude of thy mighty
men.
Solomon said, under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God in Proverbs 3, that we're
to lean not on understanding, right, we're to trust in the Lord with all of our hearts.
And here the word of God tells us that they were trusting in their own way.
They had plowed wickedness, they had reaped iniquity, they've eaten the fruit of their
lies, they had had a trust, a confidence in the multitude of their mighty men.
And we find that here the prophet of God, Hosea, is saying, look, you need to change
your course, you need to get on a different path.
If you desire that God would come and rain righteousness upon you, then you need to change
your course, you need to change your path.
As we consider this morning the pathway to revival, we recognize, acknowledge the need
for revival.
If you weren't here last Sunday, you listened to the message, I believe that it was quite
obvious that there's a need for revival.
And again, it's not just that we point at another denomination, another group of people
and say, look at them, look at all their, no, no, the light of God's word shines on
us.
Say, God, I need revival, God, we need revival.
When we acknowledge that need, what's the pathway to revival?
Three thoughts this morning, it's time to plow.
It's time for God to work.
I agree with the psalmist in Psalm 119, 126, but the prophet says, well, there's some things
that you need to do.
Number one, you need to plow, break up your fallow ground, plant, sow to yourselves in
righteousness.
And then we need to pursue, seeking God, not just for a blessing, but seeking God because
he's worthy of our pursuit, because he's a good God, he's a great God.
We're pursuing him.
Next week, we'll have our third message on this thought of the preparation for revival
and ask ourselves this question, am I revival ready?
It'll be wonderful.
Come to church next week already having revival.
I preach a message, are you revival ready?
Man, we're not revival ready, we're having revival, amen?
Because revival is when God brings his people back to spiritual health.
This morning, I don't want to just be cleaner, I want to be clean.
Preparation for revival, the pathway to revival, there are hindrances, there are hindrances,
many hindrances.
But I hope that we'd clear the hindrances out and say, I'm going to get on that path.
Let's pray together.
God, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you, God, for the opportunity that you've given us to gather together.
We thank you for your word, for the truth of your word.
God, we pray that you would, in these few moments, these quiet moments, Lord, of invitation,
I pray that the Holy Spirit of God would move in hearts and lives.
You'd take your word and minister as only you can.
I pray that we take the time to respond, that we would not leave here just by checking
a box and filling a requirement, quote unquote, but God, that we truly let you have your way.
We'd get on this pathway to revival, help us to have hearts that are tender, ready to
receive the seed of your word.
Help us, Lord.
We need you.
Pray that you'd work as only you can, for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano, and as she plays, the altar is open.
Come and ask the Lord to just respond to God, however he's spoken to you this morning.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.