As he's writing to these believers in this region of Galatia. He said this in Galatians 2 in verse number 20
I am crucified with Christ
Nevertheless, I live yet not high but Christ liveth in me
He says this in the life, which I now live in the flesh
I live by the faith of the Son of God who loved me and gave himself
for me
the Apostle Paul said to the believers in Corinth and second Corinthians 5 in verse number 15 and that he died for all that
They which live should not henceforth live unto themselves
But unto him which died for them and rose again
I'm so thankful for the privilege of living for Jesus and giving our heart to him
Colossians chapter number two this morning if you have your Bible there with you
Colossians chapter number two, I will be preaching through the book of Colossians this year
But as you know, if you've been here for any length of time each year
I choose an annual theme for our church as I seek the Lord for direction
I ask him and I desire of him to provide me with direction
That will lead me to a theme that will encourage
strengthen and
Challenge the members and attenders of Fellowship Baptist Church. It's hard to believe but it's true
nonetheless that this is
Entering now into our tenth year of being the pastor here at Fellowship Baptist Church and we came in August of
2011 and
each
Calendar year that we have had the privilege and opportunity to serve as the pastor of this great church
We've had a theme in
2012 our theme was standing on his promises
We sing the song about standing on the promises and we had as our theme in
2012 standing on his promises and we had the privilege
During that particular calendar year to study on Sunday mornings. It was certainly more of a topical
Study and we went through and we studied
various promises from the Word of God and I'm so thankful that our God has given us exceeding great and precious
promises as Peter said it and
What a joy it is to be mindful of the promises of God and to claim the promises of God in
2013 I preached through the book of Esther and the theme for that year was for such a time as
This for such a time as this and as we had the opportunity and privilege
To preach through the book of Esther and we understood that God gives us opportunity and how we must seize that opportunity in
2014 I preached to the book of John and
Dealt with that great statement of John the Baptist in John 3 in verse number 30. He must increase
It's all about Jesus and we understand that the entirety of that
thought in that verse as he must increase and I must decrease and so we taught through preached through the book of
John in
boldness to speak thy word
This was part one of the book of Acts and we studied through the first 12 chapters the book of Acts in
2015 and
We saw how that the disciples of the Apostles there the early church how they faced much opposition and much
difficulty and they faced threats and
Imprisonment and beatings and all sorts of things that they endured and how they prayed that God would grant them
Boldness to speak thy word and how we
understand even still today how we need the boldness of the Holy Spirit of God to speak the Word of God in
2016 we finished up the book of Acts
We picked up in Acts 13 and went through the end of the book and we taught and had our theme that year. I
believe God
How important it is and that we would stand as Paul did in Acts 27 and make that declaration
I believe God and
We see throughout the latter part of the book of Acts the way in which the missionary journeys in the church
The gospel went forward. What a blessing in
2017 increase our faith another one of those topical type of studies as we went through the year the calendar year of
2017 really we focused upon those things that God would give us in his word
that would be as I often referred to it that year as faith builders and
How God would increase our faith the disciples said to the Lord Jesus
During his earthly ministry. They said Lord increase our faith and we to
Understand that it's important that we live by faith. We understand the Word of God says without faith
It is impossible to please him
but he that cometh to God must believe that he is and a rewarder of them that diligently seek him the just shall live by
faith and
We're to walk by faith live by faith and so we throughout
2017 focused upon those
Various truths of the Word of God that would cause us to have our faith increased in 2018
counter blessings
the psalmist said he daily loatheth me with benefits and
I believe that each of us could echo the words of the psalmist and say in our hearts and lives today
That he has daily loatheth us with benefits God has been so good to us
And it's important that we count our blessings. We understand the song count your blessings name them one by one and
it will surprise you what the Lord hath done and
so often we can find ourselves in a natural state of complaining or murmuring and looking at the
Circumstances and the adversities that we face but how we must focus our attention upon counting our
blessings in 2019 be strong in the Lord and I taught preached through the book of Ephesians and how important it is that we
Understand that we're engaged in spiritual warfare and that spiritual battle
continues to rage even today and how we must put on the whole armor of God and we must be strong in the Lord in
the power of his might and I had the privilege of teaching and preaching through the book of Ephesians last year as I
Mentioned in the beginning of our service this morning
The book of Hebrews what a great book Christ is better
He's superior better than what better than anything better than everything. He's superior. He's better and
We understand that as we study through the book of Hebrews and had that as our thought our theme looking unto Jesus from the 12th chapter
Of the book of Hebrews and how important it is for us as the people of God
To not be focused so much upon the circumstances of life
But to have our eyes upon our Savior to look to Jesus
The author and finish of our faith that we would lift up our eyes unto the hills from whence cometh our help
Understanding and knowing with assurance that our help cometh from the Lord which made heaven and earth
I'm so thankful for the truth
of that theme and how it encouraged and
strengthened and challenged me personally last year and
this year
complete in Christ
complete in Christ in Colossians 2 in verse number 10 the Apostle Paul and we're going right in the middle of a
Discussion that he's having with these believers in the in Colossi and the Bible says and ye are
Complete in him which is the head of all
principality and
Power Lord willing and with the help of the Lord we will study through the book of Colossians this year
We will not start this morning in Colossians 1, but we will
Go through exegetically through the book of Colossians and study verse by verse
But this morning we will consider this statement from this verse of Scripture as we will use it for our theme for this calendar
year in
2021 we understand that as the Word of God says you're complete in him
We've used as our theme complete in Christ
The hymn is very obvious that it's Christ
If you look back in verse number 5 the Bible says for though I be absent in the flesh
Yet am I with you in the Spirit joining and beholding your order and the steadfastness notice of your faith in Christ as
Ye have therefore received Christ Jesus the Lord
So walk ye in him and who in Christ Jesus the Lord
rooted and built up in him who's him Jesus Christ and
Established in the faith as ye have been taught abounding therein with thanksgiving
Beware lest any man spoil you through philosophy and vain deceit
After their tradition of men after the rudiments of the world and not after Christ
for in him Christ dwelleth all the fullness of the Godhead bodily and
ye are
complete in
Him Christ, which is the head of all principality and power
complete in Christ
This morning as we study and kind of share our heart and the theme for this year
I would just ask a few questions by way of delivering this message this morning
And so if you're taking notes, the first question is this what does it mean to be complete in him?
What does it mean when the Apostle Paul says to these believers in Colossae and ye are?
Complete in him when we have as our theme for all of this calendar year
Complete in Christ when you walk into the sanctuary and you see on the banners
Complete in Christ when you look in your Bible and you have your bookmark and it says complete in Christ
when you look at your church calendar,
when you go to our website
and you see this thought of complete in Christ,
and we ask ourselves this question,
what does it mean to be complete in Him?
What does it mean to be complete in Christ?
Well, we'd have to answer that question
by going all the way back to the book of Genesis.
In Genesis chapter number one,
if you take a moment and hold your place there
in the book of Colossians
and turn back to the book of Genesis, if you will,
and obviously on Sunday evenings,
I am preaching and teaching through the book of Genesis
and we're made our way to the 17th chapter.
And so we've made some progress
over the last couple of years
studying through the book of Genesis.
And here we find in Genesis one in verse number 27,
the Bible says this,
so God created man in his own image.
In the image of God created he him,
male and female created he them.
We understand the truth of creation.
We've spent much time developing
the teaching of the word of God.
And we've said often that the truth
and the teaching of creation
is not isolated to the book of Genesis.
You find the truth of creation
all throughout the word of God.
And we understand that we are created in the image of God.
What does that mean?
Well, we understand that God is the Trinity,
we use that word, the triunity,
God the Father, God the Son, God the Holy Spirit.
These three are one, the triunity or the Trinity
as we would refer to it as.
And we'd understand that as man has been made
in the image of God,
that we as human beings, we are a trichotomy.
And what we mean by that is we are body, soul and spirit.
When God made Adam and God made Eve,
he made them in the image of God.
They had a body, a soul and a spirit.
They were made perfect.
And we find that the Bible tells us
as we would look just a few chapters later
in Genesis chapter number three,
that sin entered into the world.
We understand that God had given a simple command.
And he said to Adam in verse number 16
of Genesis chapter number two,
and the Lord God commanded the man saying,
of every tree of the garden thou mayest freely eat.
But of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil,
thou shalt not eat of it.
For in the day that thou eatest thereof,
thou shalt surely die.
In Genesis chapter number three,
the serpent, Satan himself,
enters the pages of Scripture.
And the Bible tells us in Genesis three
in verse number one,
now the serpent was more subtle than any beast of the field
which the Lord God had made.
And he said unto the woman,
yea, hath God said,
ye shall not eat of every tree of the garden.
And we understand I will not take time
to go through the entirety of the passage.
But the Bible tells us in verse number six,
and when the woman saw that the tree was good for food
and that it was pleasant to the eyes
and a tree to be desired to make one wise,
she took the fruit thereof and did eat
and gave also unto her husband with her and he did eat.
The Bible says that the eyes of them both were open
that they knew that they were naked
and they sewed fig leaves together
and made themselves aprons.
Now God is not a liar.
He's not a man that he should lie.
And he said in verse 17 of Genesis two,
that in the day that thou eatest thereof,
thou shalt surely die.
But we understand as we follow
and trace the pages of Scripture,
that Adam and Eve did not die physically
on that particular day.
They died spiritually.
And we'd understand that the Bible tells us
that death entered into the world.
And if we leave the pages of Scripture
here in Genesis chapter number three,
and we go over to Romans chapter number five,
and we find that the Bible tells us in Romans five
in verse number 12,
wherefore as by one man sin entered into the world
and death by sin,
and so death passed upon all men for that all have sinned.
Now at the birth of the children of Adam and Eve
and all other human beings that have ever been born
upon the face of this earth,
apart from our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ,
have been born with a sin nature.
We have still body, soul, and spirit,
but we are dead in our sins and our trespasses.
The Bible tells us this truth
as we look at the book of Ephesians.
Notice with me in Ephesians chapter number two,
as Paul is writing to these believers in Ephesus
and dealing with this thought
of being dead in our trespasses and sins,
we'd understand this morning
that lost individuals are dead spiritually.
The Bible says in verse number one of Ephesians two,
and you have he quickened
who were dead in trespasses and sins.
And so quicken, that means to make alive.
And we understand that as saved people,
we've been born again,
and therefore we would be complete in Christ,
but we'd understand as we look at this truth of Scripture
that lost people,
if Paul is saying to these folks in Colossae
that you're complete in him,
then we would understand it's possible to be incomplete.
Amen?
It's a pretty simple thought, a pretty simple truth,
but if someone says that that's complete,
I have completed the puzzle,
I put the last piece in the puzzle,
that means it was incomplete until that piece was put in.
And as human beings, if we are not saved,
we are incomplete.
We have body, soul, and our spirit is dead.
We are dead in our sins and our trespasses.
In fact, it is this very truth
that God used to convince and convict my dad
of his need for a savior.
It was a man that was sharing the gospel
with another coworker, and he said this,
there are a number of people in this earth,
there are a number of people that are living,
but they are dead, walking around,
and they're just waiting to die.
And he used this terminology
and he went through this whole thing,
and my dad understood at that particular time
that he was alive physically, but dead spiritually,
and he was going to die a physical death at some point,
but of course, he was dead in his trespasses and sins.
Now, if we understand this thought of being complete in him,
we'd ask the question, what does it mean
to be complete in him, to be complete in Christ?
It means that we'd be born again.
Do you remember the words of Jesus to Nicodemus
in John chapter number three,
and verse number three and verse number seven?
And I just got it straight what the man said,
there are a lot of dead people walking around
that are just waiting to die.
And that was the exact quote that the man used,
it was the witnessing to the coworker,
my dad heard that, a lot of dead people
walking around waiting to die,
dead spiritually waiting to die a physical death.
But Jesus said this to Nicodemus,
we know that Nicodemus came to Jesus by night,
and Jesus said to Nicodemus in verse number three
of John three, verily, verily, I say unto you,
I say unto thee, excuse me,
except a man be born again,
he cannot see the kingdom of God.
And then he says in verse number seven,
marvel not that I said unto thee,
ye must be born again.
The word complete in Colossians two in verse number 10,
the verse that we're using as our theme verse for this year,
if you turn back to that portion of Scripture
of Colossians, the word complete means to fill to the full,
to cause one to abound.
I like this statement or this definition
of this word complete,
to make complete in every particular,
to render perfect, to render perfect.
And so we've answered the question,
what does it mean to be complete in Him?
We then ask this question, number two,
if you're taking notes this morning,
why did Paul tell them, these folks in Colossae,
why did he tell them that they were complete in Him?
Very simply stated, because they had been born again.
Turn back, if you will, to Colossians one,
and notice with me in verse number two,
how Paul would address these folks in Colossae.
The Bible says in verse number one,
Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God,
and Timotheus, our brother.
To the saints and faithful brethren in Christ,
which are at Colossae.
You understand that in verse number two,
that Paul would refer to these individuals
that he's writing to in the book of Colossians,
these individuals in the city of Colossae,
that they are saints and faithful brethren in Christ.
A saint, as we've mentioned in times gone by,
is one who is in Christ, in whom Christ dwells.
And you will find that throughout the Scriptures,
there are many books of the Bible
that are addressed to the saints in Ephesus,
the saints here in Colossae.
And we find that they notice, as the Bible continues,
notice with me in verse number four,
it says this,
since we heard of your faith in Christ Jesus,
and of the love which you have to all the saints.
We read already in verse number five of Colossians two,
where the Bible says at the last statement of that verse.
the steadfastness of your faith in Christ. And so we find that these
recipients of this book, if we were to understand this morning, the book of
Colossians is being written to believers, is being written to those that have been
born again, those that have been saved, and that is why the Apostle Paul is saying
to them in Colossians 2 and verse number 10, and ye are complete in him. We
understand what it means to be complete in him, and we understand why Paul would
tell them that they are complete in him, is because they've been saved, they've
been born again. Back in the book of Ephesians, as we've referenced Ephesians
2 and verse number 1, the fact that you were dead in your trespasses and sins,
and you hath he quickened who were dead in your trespasses and sins. In Ephesians
2 and verse number 4, the Bible says, but God who is rich in mercy for his great
love wherewith he loved us, even when we were dead in sins, hath quickened us
together with Christ. By grace you're saved, and hath raised us up together and
made us sit together in heavenly places in Christ Jesus, that in the
ages to come he might show the exceeding riches of his grace and his kindness
toward us through Christ Jesus. For by grace are you saved through faith, and
that not of yourselves, but of the gift of God, not of works lest any man should boast.
For we are his workmanship created in Christ Jesus unto good works, which God
hath before ordained that we should walk in them. We understand there's only one
way to be saved, and that's through the blood of the Lord Jesus Christ. We sing a
song, one way God said to get to heaven, Jesus is the only way. And we understand
this morning that Jesus himself proclaimed, find the way, the truth, and
the life. No man cometh unto the Father but by me. We understand that Peter, as he
stands up there in Acts chapter number 4, and as they're being questioned about
the man that was healed in Acts chapter number 3, and all the stir and uproar
that was taking place because of that great miracle, that Peter stands up and
he testifies and he says there's no other name under heaven given among men
whereby we must be saved. What is that name? That's the precious name of Jesus.
And these believers here in Colossae, they had been saved by the blood of
Jesus Christ, they had been quickened, they had been made alive, and therefore
Paul is saying to them, ye are complete in him. You're complete in him. Not really
a third point, but a question that we'd ask at this point in the message this
morning, are you complete in him? Have you been born again? Could it be said of you?
I mean, would be a possible... we understand that all Scripture is given
by inspiration of God. Paul was the human penman that was used to write the book
of Colossians, but really we find that it's the Word of God, and God is saying
to these believers that you are complete. Why? Because you're a believer, because
you've trusted Christ. These individuals in Colossae, they're saved, they've been
born again, and this morning, are you complete in Christ? Have you been born
again? Have you trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as your personal Savior? I'm not
asking if you know about him. I'm not asking if you know some truth from
the Word of God. I'm not asking if you can recite some things, and some words,
and some maybe even quote some verses of Scripture. I'm asking this morning, has
there been a time in your life, has there been a day in your life where you
understood that you were a sinner, that you were incomplete, that you were dead
spiritually, that there was a great price for that sin, and that's death. The
second death, as the Bible says, in the lake of fire. You understand that Jesus
Christ, because of the love of God, died in your place. He went to that cruel
cross. He bled and he died. He was buried in a borrowed tomb. He rose in victory,
conquering sin, death, and the grave. And the Bible says, for whosoever shall call
upon the name of the Lord shall be saved. There was a time in your life when you
said, I understand that I'm a sinner. I understand that there's a penalty for
breaking the law of God. I understand that God in flesh, the Lord Jesus Christ,
died for me. And I placed my faith and trust in the finished work of Christ at
Calvary. And you were born again. You may not remember the exact date. I seek to
encourage those that God has allowed me to minister to, and to lead them to a
saving knowledge of the Lord and Savior Jesus Christ, to remember the date in
which they trusted Christ, the date in which they were born again. I encourage
people in that thought or that way because I was encouraged in that way. And
so I remember that it was on August 31st, in the year 1997, when I placed my faith
and trust in the finished work of Christ at Calvary. And I'm so thankful that on
that day, I was made alive. So thankful that on that day, I was born again. And I
didn't understand that that day on that moment, I didn't understand all that that
meant. But I understand as I read the scriptures, and I understand that as we
look specifically at this truth this morning, from this thought in Colossians
2, that I am complete in Him, in Christ. What a joy. What a blessing. This morning,
if you say, I'm not complete. I've never trusted Jesus Christ as my personal
Savior. I'm incomplete. Yes, we've been made body, soul, and spirit, but I've
never been born again. I'm dead in my trespasses and sins. Can I tell you this
morning that Jesus saves. We sing about it. We proclaim the message. In fact, as
we preached and taught through the book of Hebrews, we're mindful of that truth
in Hebrews 7, in verse number 25, where the Bible says, wherefore He is able also
to save them to the uttermost that come unto God by Him, seeing He ever liveth to
make intercession for them. He is the Savior of the world. We sang this morning,
what a wonderful Savior, and He is. The songwriter said, He's a wonderful Savior
to me. It's another song in our hymnal that we sing. He's a wonderful Savior to
me, and as we think about the truth and the thought of these two great hymns of
the faith, the reality is that I can say from a personal perspective that He,
Jesus, is a wonderful Savior, and that He is my Savior. He's a wonderful Savior to
me. This morning, if you can't say that, if you don't have that peace and that
confidence, can I tell you this morning that He wants to save you. He loves you, and
He wants to save you, and you can be born again today. Would you trust Christ? We've
asked two questions. Number one, what does it mean to be complete in Him? Number two,
why did Paul tell them, these folks, these individuals in Colossae, that they
were complete in Him? Because they had been born again. Finally, this morning I
would ask this question, how should this truth impact you? How should this truth
impact the believers in Colossae? Again, as we will throughout this calendar year
study through the book of Colossians, beginning in Colossians 1.1 in our next
message, and going all the way through the end of the fourth chapter, it's not a
very long book, but we will make our way through the book of Colossians in this
calendar year, and it will probably take us most of the year to get through the
book, but as we find and as we will spend time at a later date studying in great
detail the second chapter of the book of Colossians, I want you to notice how the
second chapter of the book of Colossians begins. It says this in verse number one,
for I would that ye knew what great conflict I have for you, and for them at
Laodicea, and for as many as have not seen my face in the flesh. So Paul reveals
to these believers that he's writing to in Colossians 2 in verse number one, that
he has a great conflict for them and for the believers in Laodicea, as we find in
verse number one, and he's not yet seen them. We'll mention that as we study
through the book about the relationship between Paul and these believers and so
on and so forth, but as we go through and begin to study the second chapter, and
I'll just make a couple of statements this morning on understanding how this
truth should impact you, how it would impact these believers in Colossae, I
want you to understand that Paul is saying to them, as we've mentioned
already in verse number six, notice in Colossians 2 in verse 6, as ye have
therefore received Christ Jesus the Lord, so walk ye in him. We've often used
this verse of Scripture to say, listen, if you've been born again, if you've
received Christ Jesus the Lord, you're to walk in him. In fact, as we studied
through the book of Ephesians a couple of years ago in 2019, we had the
opportunity to look at our position in Christ and then how that position
in Christ impacts our walk with him. And of course, there in the book of Ephesians,
there are several different aspects in which...
Paul addresses the believers in Ephesus about their walk.
And here in Colossians, he tells these believers,
you've received Christ Jesus the Lord,
so walk ye in Him.
Notice what he says in verse 7.
Rooted and built up in Him,
and established in the faith as you have been taught,
abounding therein with thanksgiving.
And what a great picture
of what the Christian life is supposed to look like.
That we are rooted and built up in Him.
That we are established in the faith.
That we're not tossed to and fro
with every wind of doctrine.
That we're not easily influenced by the false teachers
that are so prevalent in the day in which we live.
We understand as we would study the book of 2 Timothy,
as we'd study the book of 2 Peter,
as we'd look through various portions of the New Testament,
we'd understand that the Bible reveals to us
that there will be false teachers.
There are false teachers.
And Peter says, just as there were false prophets
in the Old Testament,
there would be false teachers
in the age that we refer to often as the church age.
And we see it to be true.
We do not have to be tossed to and fro
with every wind of doctrine.
We can be this picture that is seen in verse 7,
that we are rooted and built up in Him.
Established in the faith.
Notice, as you have been taught,
it reminds us of the importance of teaching the Word of God.
It reminds us of the importance of discipleship.
The Great Commission.
That we're to go into all the world
and preach the Gospel to every creature.
But the Bible tells us that we're to see Him saved
and see Him baptized and then see Him discipled.
That we would teach them all things
whatsoever I have commanded you.
That's what Jesus said in Matthew 28.
And as we would consider the importance
of discipleship and teaching,
that people, the people of God
would be grounded and settled and rooted and built up.
Then notice verse 8.
Paul says, beware.
Now it's interesting to me,
whenever you see a warning label
on some product that you purchase,
a sign on some road that you're traveling,
on some gate that you're seeking to enter,
there will be warning signs.
Beware of dogs is a sign that you may see
as you would enter into someone's gate.
You ought to take heed to that warning.
Beware. Danger ahead.
As you're driving, there's a curve,
there's a this, whatever it might be.
Out west, beware of falling rocks.
Many places you can drive out west
and rocks will just fall onto the highway.
You need to be careful.
In the pages of Scripture,
God gives us some warnings.
Could I tell you this morning that it's important
that we take heed to the warnings
that God gives us in His Word?
And here's where we find really
the impact of this truth.
He says, beware,
lest any man spoil you
through philosophy and vain deceit.
After the tradition of men,
after the rudiments of the world,
and not after Christ.
Can I tell you, as we note here
in this text of Scripture
that these believers were being hit
with philosophy and deceit and tradition,
they're given this warning in v. 8.
Beware, lest any man spoil you
through these processes.
And we'll study as we deal with Colossians 2
in greater detail at a future time.
We'll discuss some of the things
that were prevalent during this particular time
in this particular region.
Some of the false teaching
that would be influential,
possibly influential,
in the lives of these individuals.
And Paul is warning them
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God.
And he's warning them,
and then he's encouraging them.
It says, for in Him dwelleth
all the fullness of the Godhead bodily.
In who? In Christ.
Dwelleth all the fullness of the Godhead bodily.
In other words,
we don't have to look for anywhere else,
anything else in Him in Christ.
Dwelleth all the fullness of the Godhead bodily.
And the continuation in v. 10,
ye are complete in Him,
which is the head of all principality and power.
And so as we understand the warning in v. 8
and the encouragement in v. 9-10,
specifically in v. 10,
the thought that we've used for our theme this year
that we are complete in Christ,
that you're complete in Him,
we would say this,
that this truth would impact us.
It would give us a peace.
It would give us a rest.
I'm complete in Him.
These philosophies and this vain deceit
and these traditions,
I don't need to get caught up in those things.
I don't need to get twisted up
and sideways over those things.
No, I understand my position in Christ.
I understand that I'm complete in Him.
The reality is that lost people,
those that are not complete,
we said in the beginning of our message
that if He's saying you're complete in Him,
then it's obviously possible to be incomplete
and that would be a lost person.
Can I tell you that we have witnessed,
we have observed, in fact,
some of us even that got saved later in life
tried to fill that void with something else.
Because we knew we were incomplete.
And we see, we observe people
that try to fill that void,
that emptiness with something.
And they find that nothing ever satisfies.
That nothing gives you that completeness.
Why?
Because the only thing,
the only person that satisfies,
the only person that can bring that completeness
is Christ.
It would not work to go back
to the illustration that we used
in the beginning of the message this morning
about that 500 piece puzzle
that you get to number 499
and there's one piece missing.
And you've looked high and low,
you've searched everywhere,
you cannot find it.
It would not work to simply go find
a piece from a puzzle in the closet
from some other puzzle
and try to force it in.
No.
It's not going to work.
You need that piece
that specifically goes to that puzzle.
In fact, there are times in which
our family has set up a table
and would work on a puzzle.
And there are times in which
I would jokingly go by and say to Holly,
oh, that piece goes right here.
And you could try to force it as much as you want,
but if it's not the right piece,
it's not going to work.
And if we could use that simple illustration
and example this morning
and put it to a spiritual truth
that we find here in the book of Colossians,
only Jesus satisfies.
The only way to be complete
is in Christ.
You're not going to find
completeness in riches,
in wealth or fame,
in possessions,
in position.
No.
Those things leave man wanting
because nothing will satisfy like Jesus.
See, this is how God designed it.
Remember, we're a trichotomy.
Body, soul, and spirit.
Because of sin, there's death.
And the spirit needs to be quickened.
The only way for that to take place
is through the blood of Christ.
And this morning, as I understand
the things that these believers
in Colossae would face,
and even the things in which
the believers throughout the ages would face,
that we understand this morning
our place and our position in Christ.
That we'd understand there's nothing else that I need.
That I find my acceptance in Him, in Christ.
That I find and understand this morning
that I am complete in Him.
It gives me a peace
that passeth all understanding.
It gives me a rest
that is almost beyond description.
This morning, as we think about the subject of peace,
we understand that there's only one way
to make peace with God.
According to Romans 5, in verse 1,
therefore being justified by faith,
we have peace with God
through our Lord Jesus Christ.
It's good for us to have peace with God,
but there's only one way to have peace with God
is through the Lord Jesus Christ.
Salvation.
And these believers are being encouraged.
Ye are complete in Him.
Oh, you've made peace with God
and now you have the peace of God
that passeth all understanding.
This morning, this year, in 2021,
as we are reminded throughout the year,
complete in Him, complete in Christ,
as we sing the theme song...
complete in thee, that we'd understand that our identity and our acceptance is
in Christ. Many times in life people seek to describe themselves, to identify
themselves, and I wonder as the people of God, you know the best way for us to
understand our identity first and foremost is that we are children of God.
I'm a child of the King, the songwriter said, and what a joy to know the Lord
Jesus Christ is our personal Savior. And this morning, if you've been saved, I
would say to you that you are complete in Him, but I would challenge you this
morning to allow that truth to impact how you live daily, to understand that
your acceptance, that your identity is not found in people, positions,
possessions, wealth, status. No, no, I'm complete in Him, and I can have a peace
and a rest because I understand my acceptance in Christ. That we would not
be influenced by philosophy, vain deceit, tradition, the rudiments of the world, as
the Bible says there in verse number eight, that we would be rooted and built
up in Him, understanding that we're complete in Him. This morning, if you've
never trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as your personal Savior, I would say to you
this morning that today is the day of salvation. That's what Paul said. We
understand that our life is but a vapor. We understand the wise man said in
Proverbs that we know not what a day would bring forth. Paul said today is the
day of salvation. And if you've never trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as your
personal Savior, in the same thought of this message this morning, I would say to
you that you're incomplete. You need to be saved. And if you would trust Christ
as your Savior today, you would be complete in Him, complete in Christ. What
a joy, what a blessing. I look forward with great excitement and anticipation to
preaching and teaching through the book of Colossians this year. I trust that God
would use the study through this great book to encourage, strengthen, and
challenge each and every one of us. Let's pray. Father, we love you. We thank you
for loving us. We thank you so much for the Word of God and for the truth
contained therein. We thank you that you have given us all things that pertain
unto life and godliness. We thank you that as believers, as the children of God,
that we can understand that we are complete in thee. God, I pray that this
Bible truth would have a profound impact on every believer within our congregation.
Father, I pray that if there'd be one under the sound of my voice that's never
trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as their personal Savior, I pray that today would
be the day of their salvation. I pray that the Holy Spirit of God would
convict them of their sin, of Christ's righteousness, and of judgment to come. I
pray, God, that they would get it settled and then understand that because of
their salvation, they too would be complete in Christ. Would you have your
will and way over these next few moments of invitation? Work as only you can, and
we'll thank you for it. In Christ's name we pray, amen.