their care for us, most hospitable, and we're so grateful.
I thank you this morning, but I will thank you again
as you're opening to Romans chapter eight.
Thank you for the lovely home we have while we're here.
I jokingly said to Pastor Mann that our two days
might just be extended to six months.
We're so comfortable there, but thank you very much.
You are certainly a great blessing to us.
Thank you for your very faithful support
and for very substantial gifts, offerings,
given to the ministry, not only for the Bible efforts,
but for the church planting efforts.
You have come through truly in Herculean fashion
this last year, and we are very, very grateful for that.
So please continue to keep those things in prayer.
Our message tonight is called to convey,
called to convey.
We're gonna start with one reading.
There are actually three readings,
and they are the only three times you find the phrase
love of Christ in the Bible.
Love of God is a more common expression,
but this specific phrase, love of Christ.
And so let's begin with Romans chapter eight,
those wonderful, climactic, mountaintop verses
at the end of that chapter.
Romans chapter eight, verses 35 to 39.
And I don't even recall from this morning
if it's the practice of the church or not,
but if you're able, would you stand with me
for the reading of God's word,
then we'll make a prayer and be seated.
Romans chapter eight, verses 35 to 39.
Let's just read those all together.
Who shall separate us from the love of Christ?
Shall tribulation, or distress, or persecution,
or famine, or nakedness, or peril, or sword?
As it is written, for thy sake we are killed
all the day long.
We are accounted as sheep for the slaughter.
Nay, in all those things we are more than conquerors
through him that loved us.
For I am persuaded that neither death,
nor life, nor angels, nor principalities,
nor powers, nor things present, nor things to come,
nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature
shall be able to separate us from the love of God
which is in Christ Jesus our Lord.
Father, I thank you for the reading of your word.
I thank you that we live in a country
that is still free, that we can gather
and worship you, and praise you, read your scriptures,
and speak freely of your son, our savior,
the Lord Jesus Christ, and the salvation
that is available to us through him.
We thank you for it.
As I often pray, Father, but never as a vain repetition,
may your spirit and your word have free course
in the moments to follow.
For we know this word has the power
to bring the lost to Christ.
It has the power to bring the backslidden
back into right relationship,
and it has the power to bring the saint
who's walking with you into a closer,
sweeter fellowship with you.
May your word accomplish its purposes,
I pray in Jesus' name, amen.
Thank you, you may be seated.
Who shall separate us from the love of Christ?
As I read this, and this is that great
mountain peak passage in the book of Romans.
You remember the book of Romans, of course,
starting from chapter one and going
all the way to chapter eight,
beginning in the depth, in the dark depth
of the sin of man, beginning in chapter one,
exposing the depth of the sin of the heathen,
and going on into chapter two,
and exposing the hypocrite and the Hebrew,
and concluding in chapter three
with the first crescendos you find
in the book of Romans of how the whole
of humanity is without excuse, is sinful.
There is none righteous, no, not one,
for all have sinned and come short
of the glory of God, and then it continues
all the way from chapter one to chapter eight,
the most doctrinal book of the Bible,
building on the doctrine of salvation,
of salvation imputed and salvation imparted,
and it gets to, all the way up to chapter eight,
we'll go from the depth, let's look
at that depth for a couple minutes,
because the contrast might help us
to even appreciate more the height
that we reach by chapter eight.
Of course, chapters nine to 11
deals with a national question,
after all those doctrinal chapters,
and chapter 12, I beseech you, brethren,
by the mercies of God, et cetera,
present your bodies a living sacrifice,
deals with all the practical stuff
built on that doctrine, but it starts
with the depths of the sin of mankind
and brings us to what we just read.
We'll come back to that in a minute,
but think about the depths of it.
Romans chapter one, just to pull
a few of those verses out,
it speaks in verse 18 of all ungodliness
and the unrighteousness of men.
It tells us in verse 19, they are without excuse.
It tells us in verse 21, they glorified Him not as God,
neither were thankful,
but became vain in their imagination
and their foolish hearts was darkened.
I would love to read each part in each phrase,
because one builds upon another upon another,
exposing the utter sinfulness of man
and how far he has fallen.
It says God gave them also,
also gave them up to uncleanness
through the lust of their own hearts.
I'm in verse 24, to dishonor their own bodies
between themselves.
In verse 25, it tells them they worshiped
and served the creature more than the Creator.
It tells us in verse 26 that they had vile affections.
It says in verse 28 that God gave them over
to a reprobate mind.
And verses 29 to 32 gives one area of sin,
one sin after another after another
in one of the deep sin lists.
That's the condition of the lost.
It's the condition we were all in
before somebody who was called to convey
the love of Christ came and conveyed it to us.
If you're saved tonight,
just praise God for your salvation.
As you may say, well, a lot of those sins weren't me.
You read through that whole sin list.
And then if you start looking at that and saying,
well, I kind of grew up in a good home
and I was kind of a moral person,
then go on from chapter one to chapter two
and see thou that judgest.
And continue on until you get to those crescendo
I mentioned.
What's the plural of that musician?
Crescendi?
Yeah, when you get to them in Romans chapter three
and look at those things and see,
wow, I stood guilty before God
in the same category in the depths.
But because of salvation, hallelujah,
I'm all the way up to the heights.
Called to convey.
Think of a conveyor belt, will you?
For a few moments as we try to have a word picture.
See, I believe this very much,
that after we got saved,
God left us here for a purpose.
And a central part of that purpose
is this idea that we're called to convey
the love of Christ.
I mean, why not once we got saved
and baptized, instant glory?
Why would we be kept in a sinful body
on a sinful earth after that we got saved?
We're called to convey the love of Christ.
There will be a day that will come
when the rapture will occur
and every born-again person
indwelt by the Holy Spirit of God
will be removed, will be taken,
will be caught up together
to meet Him in the air.
And the Holy Spirit will be removed
for that seven-year tribulation.
And the sinful, fallen condition of man
in the heart of the unregenerate
with vile affections will have at it.
And the devil will have at it.
Praise God.
We'll be elsewhere.
Think about what He lifted us from.
And so how can we be recipients
of that glorious salvation?
How can we sing saved, saved
and not convey it?
Think of a conveyor belt.
You go to the grocery store
and you put your groceries on there
and you put the plastic bar between you
and the person in front of you
and maybe there's someone behind you
and it conveys, it moves,
it transports your goods
from one place to another.
You think of a factory,
an assembly line for Emmy and me,
we would always think of
a carousel bringing our luggage.
2017, we came up after many, many hours
in a plane and many hours of layovers
and none of our luggage was there.
And I don't particularly want to greet
my family straight out.
After all those hours,
I like to freshen up.
But we had no clothes,
we had no nothing.
We watched that conveyor belt
conveying everybody else's luggage,
moving it from one place to another
and we had nothing
and got greeted by our family members.
Jimmy, you're home, you know, New Jersey.
I've been waiting.
I'm waiting to talk to you, give me a big hug.
When a conveyor belt doesn't convey what it's supposed to,
oh, to think that we would have no Christians here tonight
who would be like that conveyor belt,
not conveying what is needed for the person
on the other end of it.
We came this time and we got all our luggage, praise God.
I was so happy, I was so excited.
I ran to get our luggage off,
but I had the pouch right here
so I can get the two of them and be He-Man.
I don't want my wife, I love her.
I loved her even before the message this morning,
but I got to love her a little bit more after that.
And I had the pouch.
And I went to the conveyor belt to get them
and my pouch went,
and it's a big U-shaped post right next to me
that I kind of hid into as I tried to grab both bags.
The passports, the COVID documentation,
all the things we need to get through there
and not be quarantined or stopped or sent back
were all of a sudden in a place I couldn't get to them.
And this big old boy wasn't gonna get up
on that conveyor belt and go with the luggage
and try to reach in there.
And I was about to say, Emmy, and I thought, no, no, no.
If I do that, I'll be Pastor Man's illustration
of a husband who doesn't love his wife.
And so I got this security person and asked him,
can you please help me?
That little black and white pouch in there is my life.
And so he got up on there and he went through it once
and had to come around again before he could actually get it
has nothing to do with the sermon,
but I thought I'd just mention that.
I wasn't quite ready to receive those bags.
In fact, I not only lost the pouch,
I didn't get the bags until the next time around,
but that conveyor belt kept conveying the bags
until I was ready to receive them.
And so I would just say, church, we are called to convey,
whether that's in the Samoan Islands,
way out in the middle of the South Pacific.
I like this map of the South Pacific
because it shows Pacific Ocean on both sides.
I could put two marks on that map to show where we are.
But whether the love of Christ is conveyed
all the way out to tiny little islands on Samoa
or right here in your area,
I would say every one of us is called to convey.
And so the idea tonight, the challenge tonight,
the message tonight is let us be superb conveyors
of the love of Christ.
And I got thinking about that and I said,
you know, there are three times that particular phrase.
One of my very favorite hymns is the love of God.
That's just, oh, that fourth verse, that poetry of it.
Just such a beautiful hymn.
But I caught my attention for the first time last month,
love of Christ, and I got looking at it.
And I found, as I studied the three passages,
I found three different aspects of what
will make a person to become a superb conveyor
of the love of Christ.
And so those are the three we're gonna look at.
The first one, I'll put them in the form of questions
for us tonight.
Number one, am I confident in the love of Christ?
See, a person who is confident in the love of Christ
is a superb conveyor of it.
When you love something and you're confident in that,
you will brag about it.
You go to a good restaurant.
The Smiths took us to The Lazy Dog
when they sent me the email when I was up in New Jersey
and they said, we're gonna go to a restaurant
called The Lazy Dog.
I thought, hmm.
The name doesn't exactly sell it,
but they said it was good.
And several other people told me it was good.
And we went there and they told me
what was good on the menu.
And we had a great time and I enjoyed the food.
And they've been there a couple times.
And you know, if you go to a restaurant a few times
and the food's really good,
you'll be confident to talk about it, amen?
You'll be confident to tell someone about it.
I'm not gonna go and say,
well, I don't know if I'm intellectual enough
to talk about how great the restaurant is
or I'm too fat to go up to somebody
and start talking to them about how great the restaurant is.
No, I've gone there.
The waiter was good.
Or in our case, the waitress.
The food was good to this.
And I've gone there two, three, four times.
And every time they got it right.
And I'm not worried what you think.
I'm too short.
I'm too tall.
I'm too.
I hope the point is coming through.
Because many people say,
I don't feel confident enough to go out throwing
to pass out tracks to talk about the Lord.
I don't have this, I don't have that.
I'm not gifted.
I'm not this, I'm not that.
If you're so confident in the love of Christ,
it'll just ooze out of you.
A salesman knows that if he's got a junky product,
it's hard to sell.
He's gotta lie or cheat or steal or exaggerate
or try to convince you to need something you don't.
But a salesman who has a great product
that will change your life, that will really help you,
boy, he can sell that to you all day long.
How about us?
Are you that confident in the love of Christ?
I'm not talking about self-confidence.
You know, when I get up to preach, I preach.
I probably look kinda confident,
but it's not self-confidence.
I'm not a confident guy.
I go around with my shoulders sagging.
I'm worried about what they think about my appearance
and I have this self-consciousness stuff going on
and I over-apologize.
I'm just not one of those people
who carries himself with a lot of self-confidence.
But when I'm up preaching, I'm not preaching gym.
I'm not trying to convince you about gym.
I'm getting up to preach the word of God
and I have absolute confidence in the word of God.
And when I wanna preach to somebody who might be lost,
I have absolute confidence of the love of Christ for them.
I could get the focus off of gym.
It's funny that I'm saying that while the focus is on him,
but you get my point.
Look at the passage.
Now, come back to the end of Romans chapter eight.
Come back to the mountain peak with me.
Read it, come back to it often.
Go visit.
You don't have to go look for some mountain
with a wizard on top.
Go to Romans chapter eight and read that.
It's a fantastic question with a fantastic answer.
Who shall separate me from the love of Christ?
I tell you, that'll take care of you.
You've been abused, you've been abandoned,
you've been this, you've been that.
Life has been hard on you.
You just go to the mountain and say,
none of that stuff separates me from the love of Christ.
He loves me.
His Calvary love is so great.
He loves me when I'm at my lowest.
He loves me when I am at my weakest.
He loves me when I messed up, when I failed,
when I stumbled, when I fell,
when I've denied him three times.
Go tell Peter and the disciples.
And Peter, two beautiful words in the Bible.
I get confident in his love.
Who shall separate us?
Tribulation, et cetera, et cetera.
I don't need to read that.
But if you just stop at verse 36,
you're gonna be messed up.
Are you with me tonight, church?
We're back in Romans chapter eight.
I hope we have time to get to the other two passages
because they're fantastic too.
But this one, who shall separate us from the love of Christ?
It says in verse 36, as it is written,
for thy sake we are killed all the day long.
We are accounted as sheep for the slaughter.
And there's a period there.
But I wanna beg of you not to stop at that period
and keep reading on.
Church, let me say this tonight.
Never, ever, ever cast yourself as a victim.
You are a victor.
I know the world in which we live in.
Yes, it's waxing worse and worse.
Yes, I could gripe all day long about the mainstream media
and about the politics of this and these things going on
and the freedoms that are stripped.
I can talk to you about the events
that were commemorated yesterday
that speak of a hatred for this country and attacks on it.
I could speak of current events
and I could whine all day long.
And you know what?
Too many Christians are doing exactly that.
Their social media is filled with things
about this person and that person
and this politics and that politics.
Where's the love of Christ?
Let's flood, if any of you are on social media,
flood those things with the love of Christ and stop whining.
It's so hard to be a Christian now in these days.
America used to be a Christian nation,
but now we're going down
and I don't think we could ever have revival.
And all day long, we are accounting a sheep
for the slaughter, period, full stop, done.
Please read the next word.
The first word in the next verse, what does it say?
Nay.
No, that is not the perspective on the mountaintop.
That is not the perspective when you have come
and learned of salvation and you've begun to understand
how it was imputed and how it's imparted
and how it's expressed through you
and how you have the spirit of God dwelling in you.
Nay.
And all these things and peril and tribulation
and this and that and attacks.
We are more than conquerors.
That kind of love gives me confidence.
Amen.
That kind of love gives me confidence
even when the news reports and the Supreme Court decisions
and the what and the what and the this
and the rigged election and the what and whatever.
However your politics are oriented
and all that kind of stuff, nay.
And all this, we are more than conquerors.
Are you that confident in the love of Christ?
See, that gets your eyes off yourself.
That gets you not worried about confidence in yourself.
self-confidence. Paul said, he doesn't count any of that, he has no confidence in the
flesh, but his confidence in the love of Christ is great. How about ours? You get
so confident, I'm going through depression, but he still loves me. I'm
going through a broken home, I'm going through this situation, I'm going through
that situation, whatever it may be, but in one thing I can be absolutely confident.
Nothing, no one shall separate me from the love of Christ. The devil is a liar
from the beginning and he will attack that all day long, but you could stand
firmly wherever you are and say, I am confident in the love of Christ. Nay, in
all these things we are more than conquerors through him that loved us, for
I am persuaded, I have been convinced absolutely, and therefore I have absolute
confidence that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, etc., nor
height, nor depth, etc., shall be able to separate us from the love of God. So in
this section it begins with the love of Christ and then it goes down to the love
of God which is in Christ Jesus our Lord. You cannot be a superb conveyor of the
love of Christ if you're not confident in it. Place your confidence there and it
will just come flowing out. Please do not think this is a sloppy agape message, oh
the love of Christ and I just think about the love of Christ and I'm just
gonna go around all day long and give smiley tracks, just joking pastor, and
just talk about the love of Christ and it's all fluffy and and gooey and agape.
Oh praise God it is sweet and it is wonderful. But the next passage we're
going to look at is in 2nd Corinthians chapter 5. 2nd Corinthians chapter 5, I
want to start up at verse 9 and lead up to verse 14 and even include verse 15. So
number one, am I confident in the love of Christ? If I am, I'm positioned to be a
superb conveyor. Number two, am I constrained by the love of Christ? Are
you constrained by the love of Christ? Look at the passage with me,
wherefore we labor that whether present or absent we may be accepted of him for
we must all appear before the judgment seat of Christ that everyone may receive
the things done in his body according to that he hath done whether it be good
or bad knowing therefore the terror of the Lord. Let me stop for a second. I'm
looking at this and I'm seeing in verse 9 labor, work. I'm seeing in verse 10 the
judgment seat of Christ. I'm seeing in verse 11 the terror of the Lord. I'm
looking at the context that leads up to the Apostle Paul saying to the
Corinthians, for the love of Christ constraineth us. Well I kind of prefer the
newer versions because they say compelled and that's easier to understand and I
think it's a better word. It compels us. No it's not. Constrained is absolutely the
word. It's the word that means being pressed in on every side. It's the word
that refers to a ship trying to get through a narrow strait and it must stay
right in its lane to get through without being harmed. It's the word that means
armies pressing you on every side. It's the word used for, and this is the word
picture I want to park on for a minute, it's the word used for a cattle or a
sheep shoot. Have you ever seen one of them where they run all the cattle
through it and it's like these barricades or these fences and there are
these paths they have to go through. It's time to take the cows to go to graze
because they need to be fed. Flip open that one they go that way. It removes the
distractions and it provides the direction. The love of Christ
constraineth us. And see if you have a sloppy, non-biblical, theologically weak
view of the love of Christ, it's just something we receive and it makes us
feel good and I'm glad I'm saved and going to heaven. Give me the remote. If
you have a shallow view of the love of Christ, you won't be a superb conveyor of
it. You may say, oh I'm so confident. I know for sure. I know for a fact. Someone
knocks on my door to ask me, do you know if you died today you'd go to heaven? I
absolutely know it because I said the prayer and got saved. And that's the
whole depth of the love of Christ. They haven't begun to experience the love of
Christ. The Apostle Paul said, for the love of Christ constraineth us. Does it
constrain you? Well, does the love of Christ remove a whole bunch of
distractions and provide direction? Bring the sheep through. No, send them over
there to graze. No, send them this way because this is the time to shear their
wool, can be beneficial and helpful to people and clothe people and protect
people. And they've run through that. See, if you have this sloppy type of thing
and you don't have the experience of the love of Christ constraining you, you're
not a superb conveyor of it. And so we have the local New Testament Church and
what does the preacher try to do? He's not preaching do this, do this, do this to
build an empire. The preacher isn't preaching that to make you a good
little Christian girl and a good little Christian boy and to have all these
rules to follow. And if you do enough of them, you might please God. The love of
Christ, nothing's going to separate you from it, but it will constrain you. It
will remove you from certain things you used to watch. It will remove you from
certain things you used to listen to. It will block off certain associations you
used to participate in. It will constrain you. Does the love of Christ have a
constraining influence in your life? And that's why I went to the verses up above.
It says, for we labor, wherefore we labor that whether present or absent, etc. The
love of Christ constrains us to serve. See, I've been called to convey and I can
convey the love of Christ because I'm so confident in it, but it takes work.
Amen? You can't have this mentality, well, I hope they extend the unemployment a
little bit longer so I could stay home more because I'm making more at home
than if I went to the workplace. That's not a good way to convey. You are not a
superb conveyor of the love of Christ if you're the laziest person in your
workplace. Well, it's just a government job, you know, you can get away with this
and that, and I don't want to work too hard and get the others in the office
upset with me. You're not a good conveyor. Your conveyor belt isn't working. Amen?
Christian people ought to be the hardest working people because they're
constrained. So wherefore we labor that whether present or absent, we may be
accepted of him, for we must all appear before the judgment seat of Christ.
Time prevents me from turning to the passage, but you know it. Well, you will
be judged as a believer. We know unbelievers, different judgment
altogether, white throne. We don't need to talk about it. But we'll be judged at the
bema seat of Christ for our works, what we've done in the body, whether it's good
or bad, we'll be judged. Is it wood? Hay? Stubble? Etc. That's something that ought
to grip the mind of a Christian and say, I know that I'm saved, I know I'll never
be judged for my sin. That judgment was settled for the believer by the love of
Christ on Calvary. But I will face a judgment for my works, for what I do, for
how I serve him. And don't make your pastor or someone else beg you to get in
his employ. Say, the love of Christ will constrain me. I don't have to worry about
how confident I am I can do it. I will just be available and I'll get plugged
in for the cause of Christ, because the love of Christ constrains me to do that.
And that's something to think about. What will the love of Christ constrain you to
do? And what will it constrain you from doing? I'm not the Holy Spirit. I'm a
preacher. But the Holy Spirit can point out to you exactly what things he wants
to constrain you from doing. He may just be wanting to reorganize your time
management. He may just be saying you don't need to go down the Facebook rabbit
hole for an hour at a time. He may just be saying you don't need to binge watch
this program because everybody else is. He might be saying to someone you don't
need to be on the video game or the this or the that that much time. You need to
be plugged in for the cause of Christ, because this world is populated with
people who need the love of Christ. What will he constrain you from doing that is
filling your time? I remember Edgar says in Proverbs chapter 30, remove far from
me vanity and lies. Oh Lord remove far from me empty empty things that have no
impact on eternity.
Remove those far from me, the idea of let me fill my time with things that are useful for the cause of Christ.
Are you a superb conveyor of the love of Christ?
We'll go to our third point.
Do I comprehend the love of Christ?
Would you turn to this beautiful reading in Ephesians chapter three with me?
Ephesians chapter three, verse 14 to 19, our last passage, our third time, going in order of appearance in the word of God of the love of Christ.
One of the beautiful times where the Apostle Paul prays for one of the churches.
Here he says, starting in verse 14,
For this cause I bow my knees unto the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ,
of whom the whole family in heaven and earth is named, that he would grant you according to the riches of his glory.
Oh my church, how I want to park there and ponder that.
Time doesn't allow but come back to that.
The riches of his grace, the riches of his glory, the riches of his mercy.
Oh, those are wonderful thoughts to ponder.
But he said that he would grant you according to the riches of his glory to be strengthened with might by his spirit in the inner man.
That Christ may dwell in your hearts by faith, that ye, being rooted and grounded in love,
may be able to comprehend with all the saints what is the breadth and length and depth and height.
I would recommend that you underline all four of those dimensions.
And say, do I comprehend the love of Christ?
See, you will be a superb conveyor of the love of Christ if you are absolutely confident in it,
that nothing can separate you from it.
You will be a superb conveyor of the love of Christ if you allow the Spirit of God to give you direction,
constrain you from going in certain directions and doing certain things,
and directing you in certain paths.
And you will be a superb conveyor of the love of Christ as you increase in your comprehension.
My wife can teach a rock to read.
She's incredible at what she does with those kids, and she's teaching them to read in English,
but she knows that she could teach them from a very young age to be little automatons,
to be little robots just reading, and it could sound good.
Jane and Spot went to... whatever.
And they could just say it, but she knows questions, questions, questions, comprehension questions,
because they could read it and not know what they said.
Bob threw Jane the ball.
What did Bob do?
Bob went home.
They could answer something that has nothing to do with what they read,
because they don't have comprehension.
And she works on them, and she works on them, and she works on them,
so that they're not only reading, but they're comprehending,
so that by the time they even get to first grade, they can read those simple sentences
and understand what they're reading and build on that.
And she's done incredible work with it.
I remember back when I was an English teacher,
I was teaching the pre-college class in American Samoa,
and I knew that these students, if they came to the United States to university,
they wouldn't be ready, and so I started having them read things
that would be a real challenge for them,
and we had deer time, drop everything and read.
And I started giving them Dickens and stuff that was above,
and they had to have a dictionary, and they would read,
and then afterwards we would talk about it,
and they would moan, groan, gripe, and complain.
Oh, Mr. Jim, I don't understand what I'm reading.
I can't get this.
Just read it.
If you don't know a word, get the dictionary out.
We'll talk about it afterwards.
This is deer time.
No talking.
And I did that day after day, and the tension kind of built,
and built in one wonderful day.
Pai, sitting in that corner of the classroom,
it was silent as anything, and she said,
Mr. Jim, Mr. Jim, I read the whole page,
and I understood the whole thing.
That's a teacher moment.
I want to say to you tonight,
I might steal a couple extra minutes,
because we have to scratch the surface on this.
We need Christians in the pews,
on the streets, in the community,
who have a high level of comprehension.
We don't need just first grade level of comprehension,
even third or fifth grade.
We need to be high school.
We need to be college.
We need to be post graduates.
We need people who are PhDs in the love of Christ,
where your understanding is increasing.
We will never fully comprehend this side of heaven,
the height, the depth, the breadth,
the length of the love of Christ.
But we could keep going up.
And the more you comprehend it,
oh, the more you'll share it.
You'll just long for people.
Even if we don't take the kindergartner
and expect them to be reading on university level,
we're fine with Bob.
Bob is big.
And somehow they have a hard time with the Bs and Ps,
so they mess that up.
Pop is pig.
And we have to teach him the B and the P sound.
You get some funny things that come out.
I remember the radio announcer back then,
it was some years ago,
but he would always say,
President Push.
I said, what was President Push we heard about day after day?
It was the Bs and Ps.
But you don't go to the kindergartner
and expect them to have law degrees or medical degrees
and be able to read things at that level.
Oh, but you want them to be able to start reading
and add to it more and more.
If you really want to begin just a little bit
to understand these four dimensions,
go back to Ephesians chapter 2
and start looking.
There are four dimensions given.
I'm not going to do them in the order that they say in that verse.
They say breadth, length, depth, and height.
Let's start with the depth.
This will be very easy because we already read Romans chapter 1
and pulled out all those things.
But look in Ephesians chapter 2.
And you hath he quickened made alive
who were dead in trespasses and sin,
wherein in time past
ye walked according to the course of this world.
See, all three enemies.
There's the world.
According to the prince and the power of the air.
There's the devil.
And the spirit that now worketh in the children of disobedience,
among whom also we had all our conversation
in time past in the lust of our flesh.
Oh, look at those three enemies.
Look at the hopeless soul
who's dead, dead in their trespasses and sins.
The Calvinists like to take this passage and distort it
and say that the person has no involvement whatsoever
in responding, so the implication is
why go out and give a track and try to lead them to the Lord.
No, they're dead like Adam and Eve were dead when they were cast away.
They were dead in their spirit.
And when you're dead in your spirit,
the three enemies, the internal, the external, the infernal enemy
have their way with you
and keep you apart from God
and you're in the depth and you're helpless.
Oh, but that there would be people who would come
and convey the love of Christ
and that the Holy Spirit can work from the outside
and you could be quickened and made alive again.
I want you to think, Christian,
just for a few moments tonight about these dimensions.
Think about how deep he reached.
Think of the depths of his love.
He who was seated in the heavenly places.
He in the Godhead.
He who is complete said,
I'll go to a sin-cursed earth.
I'll walk those dusty roads.
I'll walk among those men who are sinful
and receive everything they throw at me.
A wine-bibber and a drunkard
and the piercing and the crucifixion.
The lies, the false witness.
I'll go among them.
You will begin to comprehend the love of Christ
when you start to think of how deep he reached
to pull you up.
I can only scratch the surface.
My time is really up in one minute,
but I'm going to steal five more.
Amen.
Oh, he reached deep.
Now think about the heights.
Just keep reading.
I can't not read verse 4.
My goodness.
But God, hallelujah,
is rich in mercy for his great love
with where he loved us.
Even when we were dead in sins,
hath quickened us together with Christ.
For by grace are you saved.
Now see the height in verse 6.
And hath raised us up together
and made us to sit together in heavenly places.
That moment that he reached down
and you who were dead in trespasses and sins,
he quickened.
He lifted you as high as you can go.
Amen.
He brought you to be seated in heavenly places.
If you want to ponder that,
go to Isaiah chapter 6
and look at the throne.
Look at them saying,
Holy, holy, holy.
And see how high that is and say,
I'm seated there already
in my position.
Hallelujah.
Go to Revelation chapter 1
and see Christ revealed in his glory.
Not in his robe.
Not in his dusty sandals
that they have to clean his feet.
But see him in Revelation chapter 1
and then go to Revelation chapter 4
and chapter 5
and see that glorious,
exalted,
Seen and realized the love of Christ
has such height that He brought me up to that.
I was meant to go to the deepest, farthest place
separated eternally from God.
Oh, but Christian who is saved,
who shall separate us from the love of God?
You start to grow in your comprehension
of the depth of His love
and how low it reached
and how high it brought you.
Oh, and now think of the length of it.
Look still in verse 6, now into verse 7,
that in the ages to come,
He might show the exceeding riches of His grace
and His kindness toward us through Christ Jesus.
Oh, the love of Christ is long.
I've had people stand before an altar
and say, I do,
as I married them, but they didn't.
It lasted a while, but they didn't.
I've had in my own life experience
a biological mother who just left,
tore me up as a child.
That's the one who's supposed to love you
all the way through.
That's not a self-pity party.
That's the love of Christ.
Amen.
But there is love in this world,
even love that we might think
ought to be most reflective of that love,
but it's not.
You could have a friend that you've poured yourself into
in friendship and loving devotion
to this person as a friend,
and then something happens
and the relationship is broken,
never to be repaired.
Not so with the love of Christ.
It's long that in the ages to come,
that throughout eternity,
He's lifted you so high,
and that love of Christ lasts forever.
We shall forever in heaven
be the envy of angels
because of our redemption
and our exalted position.
Have we made it to sixth grade yet?
Can we get our comprehension level?
Maybe let's get up to high school.
And how about the breadth?
See, I really, really appreciate this church.
I'm not just buttering anybody up.
I really appreciate what this church has done for me
over the last few years
that we've been partnering together.
The faithful support, the prayers,
the encouragement, the huge gifts,
the belief in what God is doing
through such people as us.
I really appreciate Jennifer coming out
on the missions trip
and seeing our work firsthand
and being there.
And the truth is,
I would like to take you as a church
and hug you.
I'd like to embrace you.
I'd like to reach around all of you.
And some of you are like, uh-uh.
And then we see how sweaty you are right now too.
That's a double uh-uh.
I thought I heard Scooby.
That's what I thought I heard.
But church, I don't have that embrace.
But you keep reading in Ephesians 2,
and that wall of partition was removed.
And His embrace reached to the worst.
Even with vile affections
that burned in their lust
one toward another,
working that which is inseemly.
His embrace reached every single one of them.
Those who worship the creature
more than the Creator.
If they just but turned
and received His love.
Oh, what a reach.
To the uttermost parts of the earth.
And then He went to the other side.
And He took the Hebrew.
He took the one who they thought
they were just in the pocket of the divine,
judging everyone else,
but they were lost too.
And He said in those verses,
it's the same thing,
that if thou shalt confess
with thy mouth and believe
in the Lord Jesus Christ.
For whosoever,
whosoever,
what an embrace.
His arms, the breadth,
we would say width,
of His love is so great.
What if we said right here tonight,
oh Lord,
I will grab onto the love of Christ
with such confidence
that it cannot be shaken.
And when I doubt myself
and I doubt my circumstances
and I doubt this and I doubt that,
I will not doubt the love of Christ.
I will go to the mountaintop
of Romans chapter eight.
What if we said tonight,
Pastor in just a second,
I'm gonna just ask you to come
and take the whole invitation.
What if tonight,
the Holy Spirit spoke to you
and someone would say,
oh, Holy Spirit of God,
constrain me from this
or to do that.
We need missionaries in the Samoan islands,
but there are just not enough people
who are so constrained
by the Spirit of God,
by the love of Christ to go.
I'm convinced of that.
I'm not saying it's one of you,
could be.
What if you would say tonight,
oh Father,
oh Spirit of God,
increase my comprehension
for all the education.
Some of you may have an education
in advanced degrees and professions
and you may be very knowledgeable
in law and medicine and engineering
and this or that.
But you would say,
the most important degree I want
is a full comprehension
to the measure I can
this side of heaven,
of the love of Christ
so that I can be a superb conveyor.
Father, we thank you, Lord,
for your word.
We thank you that you would even allow us
to be vessels to convey your love.
And I pray, Father,
that you would do that work
that only you can do.
In Jesus' name, amen.
Amen, would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
We're gonna play quietly on the piano.
What a great challenge
from the word of God.
I'm so thankful for the love of Christ.