We'll be looking at verses 3 through 6 this morning.
And as we look at this passage of Scripture, we'll see the first use of one of the words
that I mentioned several weeks ago that is a common, frequently used word throughout
this book.
In fact, in four times in these four verses of Scripture, the word no is used.
And I mentioned, and I'm so thankful that our God wants us to be informed, amen?
He does not want us to be ignorant.
He doesn't want us to be unlearned.
He wants us to know some things, and as we look at His Word, we know that He's given
us truth for the purpose of knowing truth, and I'm thankful that the truth will make
us free.
I'm thankful for the power of the truth to sanctify us, to set us apart.
I'm thankful that God, in His Word, has given us these revealed truths that He desires for
His people to know.
As we look at this particular passage of Scripture here this morning, I would say this.
There's one truth that God wants His children to know that we'll examine this morning, and
that is this, that indeed we are His children.
Let me say it a different way, maybe.
The Lord desires for us to be secure in our salvation.
What a blessing it is to know that we're saved, amen?
And not to have this difficulty of going through life and wondering from day to day, moment
by moment, circumstance by circumstance, do I belong to the Lord or not?
Am I saved or am I not?
And what a terrible way to have to live life, and I'm thankful that my salvation is wholly,
completely dependent upon God, amen?
And as I place my faith and trust in the Lord Jesus Christ and His finished work on the
cross of Calvary, He gave me eternal life.
That is the gift of God.
He said, I know my sheep, they hear my voice, they follow me, I give unto them eternal life,
and they shall never perish.
Peter says that we are kept by the very power of God, and I'm so thankful for the truth
that God has given us in His Word with regard to security.
You know, the reality is that mankind, human beings, and God, of course, is the Creator,
so God knows every detail about us, wouldn't you say that's accurate?
God knows every single detail about us.
In fact, the psalmist says that He knows our frame, He knows that we're but dust.
He knows us, and He knows that one difficulty, one area of need for mankind is that of security.
It is a need that is shared amongst mankind is being secure.
You think about relationships and being secure in your relationship with your spouse, and
you think about securities, and certainly we take measures in our lives to provide security,
to give security, but I'm thankful with regard to this subject matter of salvation
that God, understanding who we are, understanding our frame, knowing that we have this basic
need of security, that He gives us the truth in His Word that we can be secure in our salvation.
As we look at this passage of Scripture, we'll mention many things with regard to the security
that is given, but I want to draw your attention to verse number 6, give you the title, and
we'll get going this morning.
The Bible says this in verse number 6.
We will be looking at verses 3 through 6, but just look at verse 6 with me for a moment.
He that saith he abideth in him, speaking of the Lord Jesus Christ, he that saith he
abideth in him, ought himself also so to walk, even as he walked.
Our theme for this year is found in verse number 7 of 1 John, chapter number 1.
If we walk in the light as He is in the light, we have fellowship one with another.
In the blood of Jesus Christ, His Son cleanseth us from all sin, and here in verse number
6 of chapter 2, we see this subject matter of our walk again being mentioned, and we
are to walk as He walked.
Walk as He walked.
We'll use that as our title for the message this morning.
I believe that God gives us in His Word several references throughout the Scriptures of evidences
of salvation, and I like to refer to them as being birthmarks of the believer.
And this morning, we will see the first of these birthmarks that are mentioned in the
book of 1 John, and as we look at this passage of Scripture, we see that really God gives
us in verse number 3 what I would refer to as being a litmus test.
It is provided for us in verse number 3.
Notice it says, and hereby we do know that we know Him.
Here's the test.
Here it is right here at the end of verse number 3, if we keep His commandments.
If we keep His commandments, what is it that this test reveals?
Well, it says, and hereby we do know that we know Him.
And so the test, the litmus test that is given is if we keep His commandments, but what it
reveals to us is that we know Him.
It does not say that we know about Him, but it says that we know Him.
There is a great difference in knowing about Him than there is in knowing Him.
Would you not agree?
Many of us this morning, there are some famous people that we could list off their names,
and we could ask the question, do you know this individual?
And many of you would say, oh yeah, I know, I know.
You don't know him or her.
You may know about him or her, many of those figures that we could mention this morning,
but I'm thankful that as we look at the Word of God and the passage that is before us this
morning, the Word of God says, and hereby we do know that we know Him.
How do we know that we know Him?
If you keep His commandments.
If we keep His commandments, verse number three.
Now understand, no one has ever been and no one will ever be saved by keeping His commandments.
Amen?
We're not saved by works.
We understand the Word of God is abundantly clear that we are not saved by our works,
and so this is not telling us that this is the mode or means by which mankind is saved,
for no one's ever been saved and no one will ever be saved by our works,
but He says that here's how we know that we know Him if we keep His commandments.
As we think about this passage of Scripture this morning,
and we understand the birthmark of the believer that is before us,
and we consider the litmus test of if we keep His commandments,
I want you to notice, if you're taking notes this morning, number one,
note the behavior of the possessor.
The behavior of the possessor, the one who possesses eternal life,
the one who has trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as their personal Savior,
and we'll look at verses five and six in order to really look at the point.
We'll come back to verse number four here in just a moment,
but notice in verse number five, the Bible is referring to that one who is a possessor.
The Bible says,
But whoso keepeth his word in him verily is the love of God perfected.
Hereby know we that we are in Him.
Again, we see that word know.
God wants you to know that you're saved. Amen?
He says in verse number three,
Hereby we do know that we know Him.
In verse number five, He says,
Hereby know we that we are in Him.
To be in Christ is a phrase that is used throughout the New Testament.
To be in Christ.
You think about the picture in the Old Testament of Noah in the great flood,
and security was where?
It was in the ark.
It was only those eight that were in the ark that would be spared destruction
through the flood and through God's righteous judgment upon His creation.
And we find here that the Bible says that we know Him again in verse number three,
not knowing about Him, but knowing Him.
And then in verse number five,
Hereby know we that we are in Him.
To be in Christ.
We find here that it is important,
and if I could make just a note this morning before we get too far into the passage,
from a language perspective,
a perspective that is given to us here in verses four and five,
it's a principle that is important for us to understand,
and that is the verb tense of the word keepeth.
In verse number four, you'll see that it says,
He that saith, I know him, and keepeth not.
And then in verse number five, you say,
But whoso keepeth his word.
And so that word keepeth is used in both verses four and five,
and it's the first occasion in the book of 1 John
where the verb tense is of significant importance.
And we'll see this again as we travel through this book,
especially again in chapter number three,
not getting ahead of myself,
but focusing here on the passage before us.
It is important to understand that this word keepeth,
the verb is conjugated in the present tense,
thus indicating an ongoing action.
And it's important for us to understand that
as we'll look at the passage,
and it will help us to keep in mind
this note of language principle, if you will,
with regard to the verb that is used
in the tense of the word keepeth.
And so as we look at this passage,
I want you to notice in verse number five,
when we think about the behavior of the possessor,
Notice what the Word of God tells us here
in v. 5.
"...but whoso keepeth his word..."
Notice this phrase.
"...in him..."
In that individual, in that possessor,
in the one that's keeping His Word.
Notice it says,
"...in him, verily, truly,
is the love of God perfected."
When we note the behavior of the possessor,
we must first look at and acknowledge
the internal work that God is doing.
I'm so thankful that God's doing a work
on the inside.
Amen?
God is working in the lives of His children.
And you think about the internal work
of the possessor,
and the Bible describes it in v. 5
that in Him, in this one that is the possessor,
"...in him, verily, truly,
is the love of God perfected."
Don't think about the work that God is doing
on the inside.
The reality is that I can't see
what God is doing on the inside,
and you can't see what God is doing
on my inside.
There is a truth that is given in 1 Samuel 16
with regard to the choosing of David
to be the king of Israel.
And first, Eliab stands before Samuel.
And remember, he's the firstborn.
And Samuel immediately has this thought,
surely, he is the one.
Right?
And God says, no.
He's not the one.
Don't look on his appearance,
or on his countenance.
He says that God sees the inward.
Man sees the outward,
but God sees the inward.
Both the inward and the outward are important
as we'll look at our message this morning
and acknowledge that truth,
but I want you to consider first of all
that before there's any external,
there's an internal work that God is doing.
As we trust that the Lord Jesus Christ
is our Savior,
if you think about the behavior of the possessor,
if you think about your own life,
if you are in Christ,
if you have trust that Christ is your Savior,
and you begin to look back at your time
of being saved from that moment
that you trust at Christ until today,
without regard of how long that has been,
but as you look at your journey with Christ,
can you not see,
can you not identify and testify this morning
of God's internal work?
His love is perfected, the Bible says.
The love of God is perfected in that one.
Now as you think about the work
that God is doing on the inside,
no doubt that work is eventually
gonna be seen on the outside.
Is that fair?
Amen?
So there's an internal work that's taking place
and God is working.
His love, think about the love of God.
Nothing can separate us from the love of God.
Aren't you thankful for that?
We sang this morning in Sunday school
a couple of songs,
one of them, Jesus Loves Me, This I Know.
For the Bible tells me so.
Aren't you thankful for the love of God?
And His love is perfected in us,
and as we think about the love of God,
and we think about the work that He's doing in us,
and we think about the internal work,
we ought to be grateful for that.
We ought to rejoice in that.
We ought to invite that work to continue to take place.
Amen?
God, continue to speak to my heart.
God, continue to work in my life.
God, continue to show me areas in my life
where I need to change so that I might be more like You,
so that I might please You,
so that I might walk in a manner
in which is honoring and pleasing in Your sight.
God, continue that internal work.
We find not only the internal work of the possessor
or in the possessor,
but I want you to think about the external evidence.
As I mentioned, that work that is being done on the inside
will eventually be seen on the outside.
When you think about David in 1 Samuel 16,
you think about David being anointed in that great truth
that God gives to Samuel in 1 Samuel 16 in verse number seven
with regard to God seeing the heart,
man looking at the outward appearance.
You would find this truth that God says to Samuel
that man looketh on the outward,
but the Lord looketh on the heart.
Remember, God had told Samuel and Samuel told Saul
that God had selected a man that was after his own heart,
but we see the external evidence in the life of David,
for there's a servant that comes to Saul
just a short time later in 1 Samuel 16 in verse number 18,
and here's how he describes David.
He describes him as being a son of Jesse the Bethlehemite
that is cunning and playing, a mighty valiant man,
a man of war and prudent in matters and a comely person,
and the Lord is with him.
I want you to understand that God saw the heart of David,
but this unnamed servant saw the external evidence
of the work that God had done in David's heart.
As we look at our lives
and we look at this passage of scripture
in 1 John chapter number two,
and we think about the behavior of the possessor,
and yes, that internal work
where truly the love of God is perfected,
we see the external evidence.
Notice in verse number three of 1 John chapter number two,
the Bible says this,
and hereby we do know that we know him,
if we keep his commandments.
So in verse number three,
you see that it's the external evidence
is that we keep his commandments.
In verse number five, what is the external evidence,
but whoso keepeth his word?
I would argue that that's synonymous,
keeping his commandments and keeping his word.
There is a similarity there
between those two statements that are given,
the litmus test that is provided
as we mentioned in verse number three,
and we find that he says that he keeps his commandments,
he keepeth his word,
and then in verse number six,
notice he talks about abiding in him.
He that saith he abideth in him.
Does your mind not rush back
to the gospel of John in the 15th chapter
when Jesus and John is there
and Jesus says, abide in me, right?
He uses that great example,
that great truth that we see in nature
that the branches cannot sustain their own life,
but the branch is dependent upon the vine, right?
I am the vine, you're the branches.
Is that not what Jesus said in John chapter number 15?
And he says, abide in me,
and now John who walked with the Lord Jesus Christ,
who heard the Lord Jesus Christ,
remember he testified in the first chapter of this book
how that he was an eyewitness.
His ears had heard, his eyes had seen,
his hands have handled of the word of life,
and he speaks about the one that says he abides in him.
Now, it's interesting that in verse three and five,
there's nothing about saying anything,
it's just the external evidence,
and here in verse number six, he says,
he that saith he abideth in him,
notice what it says,
ought himself also so to walk even as he walked.
Walk as he walked.
Peter says it this way in 1 Peter chapter number two
and verse number 21,
that Jesus left us an example
that we should follow his steps.
And as we think about this truth of the external evidence
and the behavior of the possessor,
there's an internal work that is taking place,
but that internal work is manifested through our behavior,
through the actions that we take,
the external evidence is that this one
that is a possessor
is going to keep the commandments of the Lord,
he keeps the word of God, he walks as he walked.
The thought of this word keep is that of obedience.
The word literally means to attend to carefully, to observe.
I like the first definition, to attend to carefully.
You know, it's so important
that we carefully examine the word of God
and that we understand what God desires of us.
If we're going to follow the admonition
that Paul gives the believers in Ephesus
that we are to prove what is acceptable
in the sight of the Lord,
to prove what God is pleased with,
we must attend to this book carefully.
And as we give our attention carefully to the word of God,
I'm not just brushing through and skimming over.
I don't read this book like I read any other book.
There are some, you ever read an article,
you ever read a book and you kind of just skim through it
and you're like, man, I'm not going to,
maybe I didn't even finish reading it.
There's some books that I have in my library,
some that I've gotten rid of,
that I started reading and never finished them.
I just didn't feel there was,
it was just not getting anything, right?
It was just not helpful.
There's some books in my library that I've read
and I've reread and I've reread
because they've been helpful.
There's some books that I've read once
and I've never read them again.
But this book, this book is not like
any of those other books.
This book is a book that I long to deep dive into
and to attend to carefully, why?
Because this book tells me the mind of God.
It tells me the behavior for the saint.
It tells me what is pleasing in His sight.
And as we understand the importance of observing,
of keeping, of attending to carefully His Word,
He says,
is that this one that is a possessor,
the behavior of the possessor,
yes, there's the internal work that God is doing,
but the external evidence is that
He keeps His commandments,
He keepeth His Word,
He walks even as Christ walked.
This morning as I've examined
and thought about this passage of Scripture,
I've considered this idea,
this thought as to why it is
that people would obey.
You know, the reality is that we understand
the society in which we live,
a society that has been,
and I understand that we have some real problems
with our judicial system today,
but has been historically set upon laws
and legal precedents.
And laws are important for any society.
Anarchy is bad, amen?
Laws are important.
When we think about obedience
and we think about why it is that we obey,
I would submit to you this morning
that we as the people of God obey
for a different reason than some others
may obey other laws and other things.
I think about biblical times
and the writing of the Word of God,
and no doubt there were some
that would serve in capacities
of being servants or slaves,
and they had to obey because it was required.
Obedience was required.
The penalty for disobedience was severe,
often up to including death.
You think about the severity of that.
I think about this,
there are times in which people will obey
because it's necessary.
Slightly different than being required,
though there's a similar thought there,
but I think about maybe the aspect of an employee.
That they obey the rules, if you will,
the guidelines of the particular company
in which they work for
out of necessity for this purpose
that it's a duty that I need to keep my job.
And if I'm going to keep my job,
then I'm going to have to obey these guidelines,
these, you guys have an employee handbook?
You know, you get those things
and there's an expectation of obedience to those things.
And if you wanna work at a particular company,
then you've signed on and you're going to determine
that you're going to, out of necessity
in keeping your job, you're going to obey those things.
When I went to Bible college, they gave us a handbook.
And then they told us in that handbook,
some of you guys that went to Bible college
or Christian college,
you know about this demerit system thing, right?
And this offense equals these demerits
and so on and so forth.
And there was some motivation
in obeying some of those things
because of wanting to stay out of trouble
and not get the demerits.
But I would say this, as a child of God,
as a possessor of eternal life,
because of that internal work that God is doing
in my heart, in my life,
the reality is that I desire to obey God.
I want to obey God.
I have the understanding that there is great joy
and there is great delight in obeying my master,
my savior, my Lord.
When we understand that difference in perspective,
remember what John would have heard Jesus say in John 14,
in verse number 15,
if you love me, keep my commandments.
Within this same book,
turn over to 1 John 5, if you will.
And I want you to see what the word of God says here
in 1 John 5.
Notice in verse number three,
with regard to obedience,
he says this, for this is the love of God,
that we keep his commandments.
And then notice this phrase,
and his commandments are not grievous.
Listen, for us as the people of God,
because of what we've mentioned,
the true possessor of eternal life,
we know that we know him,
the internal work that is going on,
the love of God that is being perfected in us,
the Holy Spirit of God who now indwells us,
the truth that we are the temple of the Holy Ghost,
which is in us.
And we understand all of those realities
that God has given us in his word,
then I, as a possessor of eternal life,
this gift of God,
there ought to be a desire in my heart to obey God.
I just want to obey him.
I delight and I joy in obeying my savior.
As a child, those, all of you have been a child, amen?
Amen?
I know it's deep for Sunday morning, amen?
Some of us have had children.
You know, there comes a point in your life
when your obedience to your parents changes
from a have to to a want to.
There should be, right?
And you think about if you can evaluate your life,
and perhaps you can remember that time in your own life
where it transferred from being I have to do
what my parents tell me to do
to I want to do what my parents tell me to do.
And I'm not saying that it would be 100%
all of the time across the board,
but the reality is that there comes a place in our lives
we understand in relationship where that transition happens.
And I would say as we think about the heavenly truth
and the reality that he's my heavenly father
and I'm his child, that I want to obey him.
I desire to please my God.
As we look at the passage of scripture
with the understanding, as I mentioned,
by way of introduction of the verb tense
of that word keepeth, and the greater context
of 1 John into the beginning of the second chapter,
the end of the first chapter with the whole truth
of confessing our sin, understanding that we're not to sin.
Remember, he says in verse number one,
my little children, these things write unto you
that you sin not.
That ought to be our goal.
That ought to be our desire.
But when we sin, we can rejoice that we have an advocate,
Jesus Christ the righteous, amen.
And what a blessing to know that we have the advocate.
And so when we understand the verb tense
and we understand the greater context
of this passage of scripture,
we would understand that when he says in verse number three
that we keep his commandments,
when he says in verse number five,
whoso keepeth his word, when he says in verse number six
that we ought to walk even as he walked,
that he is not saying that it's going to be
perfect obedience, completely sinless.
Rather, the possessor is going to have
that humble, obedient response
to the commandment of the Lord.
That we understand, listen, there's going to be a time
that we don't, even though we're possessors,
where we don't keep his commandments, amen?
You've sinned, right?
We know, listen, if you say I never sinned,
you better go back to 1 John chapter number one.
Go back a couple weeks and listen to the message, amen?
Because the word of God says you're lying.
You've deceived yourself.
You make him a liar.
The truth is not in you, right?
Is that not what 1 John one tells us?
So we know the word of God tells us
and experience tells us that we have,
at times after we trusted Christ as our savior,
a possessor of eternal life,
there has been a time where I did not keep his commandment.
Doesn't mean I'm not saved.
No, no.
What's the, when we think about the passage of scripture
and the truth that God is revealing to us here,
it's not that if you mess up one time
that you must not be a possessor.
It's that we have this attitude towards the word of God
to the commandments of the Lord
that I have this humble, obedient response
to the commandments of the Lord,
and my life is given this evidence
of living a life of obedience,
that that's the pattern that is set forth,
that there is a pattern of obedience.
We said that the verb tense would indicate
that ongoing action, the obedience to keeping his word.
When the word of God is disobeyed in the life of a believer,
the Holy Spirit of God convicts us, amen?
And as that conviction comes in our life,
and some people say, I don't like conviction.
You ought to like conviction.
Conviction's a good thing, amen?
The word of God, my Bible tells me,
and your Bible tells you that whom the Lord loveth,
he chasteneth, amen?
It's an evidence, it's a birthmark of a believer
that God deals with us as children,
and he convicts us, and he chastens us,
and what's our response to that?
We're a possessor, that internal work is taking place,
and it's evidenced in a life of obedience.
Again, he's not giving the idea
that it's perfect, complete obedience
and living a sinless perfection type of reaching that goal,
but there's this pattern of obedience.
I believe that the next point that we look at
will help us fully come to the conclusion
of this passage of Scripture.
Notice with me, not only the behavior of the possessor,
but I want you to notice in verse number four, number two,
if you're taking notes, the behavior of the professor.
And when I say a professor,
I'm not talking about your college professor,
but I'm talking about the one that professes
to be something that he is not.
The reality is that the Word of God begins in verse number four, he that saith.
I would say this, man can profess anything, can he not?
Man can profess anything.
Let me say it this way, talk is cheap.
Amen?
Talk is cheap.
Man can say whatever he wants.
In fact, you found, as we looked at the end of chapter number one, that there were many
references as to he that saith.
If we say, the phrase was repeated there three times.
Here we find in verse number four, he that saith, I know him.
Now remember, the litmus test is given in verse number three, that you know, that you
know him, why?
We keep his commandments.
The internal work of verse number five, that God's love is being perfected in us, that
it's evidenced in the external by our obedience and our walk, and we're walking even as he
walked.
We find that the professor in verse number four, the one that says, he professes, I know
him.
But notice what it says, and keepeth not his commandments.
He has no regard for the Word of God.
There's a disobedience, this individual really, if they're just a professor, if they simply
say that they know him, but they've not actually received him, they are not a possessor of
eternal life, the Holy Spirit is not working within them, that internal work is void.
It's not there.
There's no internal work, and therefore, their behavior is marked by disobedience.
Their behavior is marked by disobedience.
They don't care what God's Word says.
The Holy Spirit of God is not living within them.
They're not saved.
Now, they say that they know him, but the evidence is not there.
In fact, the evidence is on the contrary.
It says that he keepeth not his commandments.
Notice what God says.
This person is a liar, and the truth is not in him.
You say, man, that's hard language.
It's the Word of God.
God's Word is very direct.
There are people that can profess that they know him, but the evidence does not support
their profession.
There's no internal work that's taking place.
They've never truly trusted Christ as their Savior, and the external evidence is that
on the contrary, that they actually are not a possessor, that they've simply professed
something.
And the Word of God tells us that in this life of this individual that keepeth not his
commandments that they are a liar, and the truth is not in him.
Let me illustrate it this way.
As we mentioned about in our previous point with the possessor in the external evidence
of keeping the Word of God and keeping the commandments and obeying, the reality this
morning is as we look at this professor and we understand that it says that he keepeth
not his commandments, you know that even occasionally a lost person will obey a truth of God's Word.
The one that wants to deceive you, the one that's crept in unawares, according to Jude
1, that individual that's crept in unawares, they will try to put on this facade of obedience
and even the professor, even the lost person occasionally will obey a commandment of the
Lord.
But the pattern of obedience is missing.
Someone said it this way.
You think about hypocrisy and you think about this one in verse number 4, he that saith,
I know him and keepeth not his commandments is a liar and the truth is not in him.
Again, it's not the individual that occasionally will obey a command of the Lord.
The reality is this, again, someone made this reference, I thought it was quite appropriate,
that even a broken clock tells the right time twice a day, right?
That's pretty easy for us to understand.
A broken clock tells the right time twice a day.
You say, well, not if it's military time.
I understand.
Amen, for all you military folks out there, amen, I understand.
But I want you to understand this morning, when we think about the truth of verse number
4, believe that it helps us understand the truth of verses 3, 5, and 6.
In verse number 4, we see that it's saying that he that says, but he keepeth not his
commandments, though there's the occasional time in which they may obey a principle or
a truth from the Word of God, it does not make them a possessor.
In like fashion, there will be a time in the life of the possessor where we don't perfectly
keep his commandments.
It doesn't make us lost, right?
You follow?
Does that make sense?
And so it doesn't make us lost if there's that occasional sin in our life, that occasional
time in which we have not kept the commandment of the Lord.
What God is doing for us here in this passage of Scripture, when we think about this truth
and this litmus test, as I've used the analogy from the beginning of the message this morning
that is given to us in verse number 3, the question that we could ask ourselves at the
conclusion of the message this morning is this, what does the test conclude?
This test, I do not believe this morning, though I preach the Word of God and though
I preach the truth, the reality is that this is a test that you self-administer, that you
examine your own life.
And then as you examine your own life and as you begin to understand, listen, God wants
you to know that you belong to Him.
Many of us have children.
Those of us that have children, do you not want your children to know your love for them
and that they belong to you?
That they would be secure in their relationship physically with you as parent to child?
Sure you do.
You don't want your child to come running up to you as just a little toddler and kind
of push them off and go somewhere else.
No, no, you want them to know that there's a relationship, there's security.
You want your children to be able to come to you and to know that they are secure in
their relationship, right?
In like fashion, God wants us to be secure in knowing that we belong to Him, that we
are in Him.
And so He provides us throughout the book of 1 John, really throughout the Word of God.
There are many passages that you could go to, but I believe that as you go through the
book of 1 John, you'll find many ways the approach that is given to us by God in this
book, this short epistle, is that God says, you can say whatever you want to say, but
here's the test.
Don't say that you love God and hate your brother.
Because if you hate your brother, you don't love God, right?
We'll get to that in a little while.
And He uses these tests throughout the book of 1 John to help us truly evaluate why.
Well, one truth that we find in the Word of God, and He mentions it in 1 John 1, is that
we can deceive ourselves.
Now, I want you to consider that just for a moment as we close up this morning and we
think about this.
The devil is a liar, is he not?
And the devil is a deceiver, correct?
He uses deception all the way from the beginning, right?
And if we know that he's a deceiver, and we know that he's a liar, he wants to deceive
you, and we know that there's a danger in deceiving ourselves, God graciously provides
us with some test that we can administer so that we can know and not be deceived.
Isn't that awesome?
When you think about the wisdom of God, and you think about the love of God, and God says,
I want you to know that you know.
I don't want you to be tossed to and fro.
I don't want you to not have this knowledge.
And He says, hereby we do know that we know Him, that we keep His commandments, that we
keep His Word, that we walk as He walked.
The focus this morning is not so much on the professor.
The behavior the professor has given to us in verse number 4, the one that professes
to know Him but keepeth not His commandments, that person's a liar.
The truth is not in him.
As just a moment of speaking to one that perhaps would fall into that category, I would submit
to you that you must make sure that you are born again.
It's not just a lip service profession.
Evaluate the evidence in your own life.
Am I a professor or am I a possessor?
Do I possess eternal life or do I just profess to know Him?
What does my life conclude as I look at the test?
What is it in my life that I am a professor or am I a possessor?
life as a believer, see, the reality is that as a believer, as I mentioned a few moments
ago, we ought to have a desire, a want to, with regard to obedience to the Word of God.
We agree that this book is God's book.
It's God's Word.
Amen?
We agree on that.
You sit in a church this morning that has as its authority this book.
The Word of God is our sole authority for faith and practice.
And I've often said over the years that we must agree to agree with God, that we go to
the Word of God and we agree with what God says.
And as a believer, as a possessor, that internal work that is taking place, and the Holy Spirit
of God is working in my life and in my heart, and I read the Word of God in my daily devotions
or as I come to a church meeting and I hear the preaching and the teaching of the Word
of God, that I'm taking that truth and I'm saying, how do I apply that truth in my life?
How do I become a doer of the Word?
I want to keep His commandments.
Oh, by the power of God, with the help of God, would you help me to walk in obedience?
Would you help me to submit to that truth?
Would you help me to live out that truth in my life?
And that's the response of the possessor.
We continue to desire the internal work.
God, keep working in my life.
Keep showing me.
Keep revealing to me.
Help me, God, by Your power and Your strength to obey Your Word.
We look at our lives and we say, man, this possessor, he's keeping the Word of God.
He's keeping the commandments of the Lord, and the external evidence proves the profession
that I'm in Christ, that I'm in Him.
And this morning, I'm so thankful that God has given this first of several that we will
discuss over the year of a test, a birthmark of a believer.
Our life is to be evidence of that work that God is doing in us.
As we take a moment at the end of our service to examine our own lives and say, how am I
doing in this area?
Am I keeping His commandments?
Am I walking as He walked?
Do I know His commandments?
This morning, walk as He walked.
Walk as He walked.
Many years ago, I don't think it's too prevalent today, though it may be.
Some could correct me if I'm off on this, but I think it was a while ago.
Again, it's still occasionally tossed around, but it was very prevalent years ago, and that
was that little, what would Jesus do?
Right?
You remember everyone's wearing these little wristbands, WWJD, and run around with this
idea of what would Jesus do?
Sadly, I would say that oftentimes, we don't even know what Jesus would do because we don't
know this book.
And it's more than just wearing some paraphernalia, it's having that internal work where God's
Holy Spirit is working in my life and revealing truth to me.
And as I walk in the light, and I walk as He walked, that I follow His steps, the example
that He gave us, that truly, we could follow that question of what would Jesus do?
Because I'm walking in the light, our theme, and I'm walking as He walked.
The life of a believer should be marked with obedience, amen?
It really should.
Marked by obedience.
There should be a pattern of obedience in your life and in my life.
Again, no one ever has been and no one ever will be saved by keeping His commandments.
John's not talking about salvation of how to, he's talking about the possessor of salvation.
And here's how you know, that you know Him, if we keep His commandments.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
We thank You for the Word of God.
We thank You for this truth that has been revealed to us in this passage of Scripture,
this birthmark of a believer, this security that You want us to know.
I'm so thankful that You know that we have this need as human beings, a need to know
that we are secure, a need of security, and You have provided within Your Word many examples
of how we can know that we know You, that we are in Christ.
This one that is before us this morning, I pray that You'd help us to evaluate our lives.
I trust that those that are gathered here this morning are possessors, that, God, You're
doing a work internally in each of us, that the evidence is seen on the external.
There may be one that the Holy Spirit may have convicted this morning, they're just
a professor, there's never actually been a time in which they've been born again.
If that would be You this morning, I trust that You would respond to the invitation that
the Lord extends, whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved, that
You would receive the gift of God, which is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord,
and no longer would You be just a professor, that You would be a possessor of eternal life.
For each one that's here that's accepted the gift of God, that's saved. God, I pray that
our lives would be marked by obedience, that our heart attitude would be one of submission
and obedience as we come to Your Word. In fact, that we would read Your Word daily with
the purpose of obedience. We think of Samuel when he said, "'Speak, Lord, for Thy servant
heareth,' hearing with the purpose of obeying." David, the example in 1 Samuel 16, God knew
his heart. That unnamed servant of Saul observed the external evidence of what God knew to
be done internally. God, I pray that'd be our testimony this morning, that our lives
would clearly indicate that we belong to You and that we are a possessor of eternal life.
Thank You for the work that You do in us. God, help us to have that desire for You to
continue by Your power and with Your help that we would be doers of the Word, that we
would keep Your commandments. Would You work in these few moments of invitation? Help us
to respond as You've spoken to our hearts, and we'll thank You for it. Would You stand
with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed. Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano.
As she does, the altar is open. Maybe this morning you want to come and just thank God
for the internal work that He's doing in you. Thank Him for salvation. Maybe this morning
you want to come and ask Him to continue to reveal to you, to help you to walk in obedience,
to keep His commandments. Not sure how the Lord may have spoken to your heart this morning,
but as He has, would you respond as Kimberly plays, The Altar is Open?