to 2 Timothy chapter number two.
And we've been dealing with this series
throughout the calendar year of 2024 of continue.
It's our theme for this year.
And as Pierre mentioned,
it's October is right around the corner
and it's hard to believe we're nearing the end.
And I've mapped out,
not completed each message for the rest of the year,
but every time around September and October,
I have to map out to make sure
I'm gonna have enough Sundays to finish up
what it is that we're going to have for our theme.
And so I'm excited about what God has in store for us
and praying about a theme for next year.
And my target date typically is October 1st
to have all of that ready to roll.
And so you pray that God will give wisdom and direction,
but I'm thankful for this series,
first and second Timothy, the thought of continue.
No doubt we live as we come to the third chapter
in a few weeks in a time of being the last days,
perilous times as they are described for us.
And we see all kinds of things going on in our world
and turmoil and so on and so forth,
but we serve a God who is on his throne,
who has a plan, who do with all things well,
his way is perfect, amen.
And I am thankful to know him as my personal Lord and Savior
and thankful for the opportunity
that we have to serve him as soldiers in the Lord's army.
When you trust at Christ as your personal Lord and Savior,
you were enlisted in the Lord's army
and praise the Lord for that truth.
And we find that God gives us in this passage
in second Timothy chapter number two,
really the entirety of the chapter,
much information with regard to being not only a soldier
in the Lord's army, but a good soldier.
And that's been the thought for a few weeks now
here on Sunday mornings.
I'm not content.
I don't wanna be content.
I don't want you to be content with just simply saying,
I'm a soldier in the Lord's army.
No, I wanna be a good soldier.
We find that within the text of scripture,
there are five characteristics that God gives us
that would cause a soldier to be referred to
as being a good soldier.
And we see that in verse number three,
thou therefore endure hardness
as a good soldier of Jesus Christ.
The Christian life is a spiritual warfare.
We find that the battle is raging
and too many soldiers in the Lord's army
are ill prepared for the battle.
And that's just the reality.
That's just the way it is.
And it's unfortunate, but it's the truth.
And we must preach the truth.
We must analyze and be able to examine
and to honestly evaluate where we are individually
and where we are as a church locally,
but then also the body of Christ broadly speaking.
It seems as if I made this comment to someone yesterday
when we were going apple picking,
but it seems as if some in our society today
that are saved by the grace of God,
they're enlisted in the army of the Lord's army
that they enjoy being a soldier,
but simply want no part of combat.
Now think about that just for a moment.
They're happy to be a soldier.
They're happy that they're saved.
They're happy that they're going to heaven,
but they really don't want any part of combat.
They don't want to be engaged in the battle.
They don't want to be in the spiritual warfare,
but we understand that Paul says to the believers
in Ephesus in Ephesians six,
that we're to be strong in the Lord
and the power of his might.
He says in verse number 12,
that we wrestle not against flesh and blood,
but against spiritual wickedness in high places.
And we see that we understand I've made known for years now
when we look at our society
and we look at the problems and all that's taking place.
Many people try to say that we're dealing with cultural war.
We're dealing with this social war, so on and so forth,
but really we're dealing with spiritual warfare.
It takes on many shapes and forms.
It's called a number of different things,
but we understand as Bible believers
that it is a fight between evil and good.
And we understand that it's a spiritual battle.
We must come into the spiritual battle
prepared for combat, being strong in the Lord.
And we find that as we have that desire
that we would be a good soldier of Jesus Christ
refusing to be content with average.
You know, there are a lot of people today
that are just okay with status quo,
just kind of, I'm getting by, I'm making it, I'm average.
And I hope that that would not be our place
of being content there,
but that we would strive for excellence
in the Christian life,
that we would strive to be in a place
where God would be pleased with us,
that we would honor and glorify him,
that truly it would be said of each and every one of us,
not only that we're a soldier,
but we're a good soldier of Jesus Christ.
We looked at in the first lesson
that a good soldier endures hardness.
We noticed that in verse number three.
I read it a moment ago,
thou therefore endure hardness
as a good soldier of Jesus Christ.
Two weeks ago, we dealt with the first part
of verse number four,
that a good soldier avoids distractions.
The Bible says, no man that woreth
and tangleth himself with the affairs of this life.
The distractions will vary.
The distractions are abundant,
but we know that our enemy, he is a master deceiver,
and he distracts us in so many ways.
There's so many distractions around us,
and we must be focused on the Lord Jesus Christ
and on the work that he has for us
because we are engaged in spiritual warfare.
We can no longer afford to be distracted.
We can't be, as I said two weeks ago, asleep at the wheel.
We must be alert.
We must be vigilant.
Remember what the Bible says
in 1 Peter chapter number five, in verse number 80,
it says, be sober, be vigilant.
Why?
Because your adversary,
we're engaged in spiritual warfare,
as a roaring lion walketh about,
seeking whom he may devour.
He wants to destroy your life.
He wants to devour you.
Here's what I'm thankful for.
He has no power over me with regard to going to heaven.
He can't take my salvation.
Hallelujah.
I am kept in the hand of God, amen.
But you know, he wants to destroy our lives.
He wants to destroy our testimonies.
He wants to destroy our effectiveness.
He wants to devour you, your spouse, your children.
He wants to devour.
And so we find that the Bible says, be sober, be vigilant.
And we find here that this soldier, this good soldier,
number one, he endures hardness.
Number two, he avoids distractions.
This morning, we'll look at the remainder
of verse number four.
The Bible says that he, that good soldier
that's referenced in verse number three,
that he may please him.
Who's him?
Well, that's the Lord Jesus Christ.
That is our savior who hath chosen him to be a soldier.
Again, when you got saved by the grace of God,
you were enlisted in the Lord's army.
You didn't get saved and then make a decision.
You know, do I want to sign up
to be in the Lord's army or not?
And you know, I'm gonna evaluate.
No, no, when you got saved, whether you knew it or not,
now you do, you were enlisted in the Lord's army.
That's his plan.
He hath chosen you to be a soldier.
And notice the Bible says that he, that soldier,
that good soldier may please him, the Lord Jesus Christ,
who hath chosen him to be a soldier.
So this morning, as we note the third characteristic
of a good soldier, I would say this,
they seek to please their master.
A good soldier seeks to please their master.
I made the statement on Wednesday evening,
too many people that are saved,
they are interested in having a savior,
but not a Lord or a master.
They want a savior.
They want to go to heaven when they die,
but they really don't want a master.
They don't want Jesus to be Lord of their lives.
What do I mean by that?
Well, they want to just do what pleases them.
They want to live their life.
They want the benefit of heaven, so to speak,
but they want to do whatever it is
that they want to do here on this side of eternity.
They want to live to please themselves.
We all know people that are living to please themselves.
We know, by the way, where that ends.
We know the futility of it.
We know that it brings no real true peace and joy,
that it's empty, it's vain, but we find this morning
that the good soldier, he is going to seek
to please his master, understanding
that not only is Jesus my savior,
but he is my Lord and my master.
By the way, he's a good Lord.
He's a good master.
His commandments are not grievous, amen?
Some people look and they try to attack the scripture
and they say, well, you know, the Christian life
is just a whole list of do's and don'ts.
If you look at it that way, you have missed
the whole point of the relationship
that you have with the Lord Jesus Christ,
and are there things that he tells us not to do?
Sure.
Are there things that he tells us that we should do?
Absolutely, but if you have children,
you have a list of things that they should do
and they should not do.
Why?
Because you love them.
And God as our Lord and our master and our savior,
he's given to us in his word truth
that helps us understand how we can please him.
Note this, you don't need to turn there.
I'm gonna read the verse for you,
but in 1 Thessalonians 2 and verse number four,
the apostle Paul is writing to this church
that he had the privilege of going
and preaching the gospel to.
He says, but as we were allowed of God
to be put in trust with the gospel,
even so we speak.
Notice where he says, not as pleasing men.
but God, which trieth our hearts.
It ought to be the desire of every child of God.
It ought to be the desire of every saved,
blood-bought child of God to please their master.
We find that a good soldier, according to verse number four,
it says that he may please him
who hath chosen him to be a soldier.
Let me ask you, I'm gonna ask two questions this morning
as we deal with the subject matter.
Number one, if you're taking notes,
can I, can you, can we please the Lord?
You ever found yourself in a situation
where you found like, or you felt like
you found yourself in a situation
where you had a desire to please
maybe an employer or somebody else,
but you found yourself, I don't know how,
I feel like I cannot please this person.
It seems like everything I do is wrong.
You ever been there, you feel that way?
And I'm sure that at some point in life,
a teacher, a professor, a coworker, an employer,
whoever it might be, that we have felt that way,
but we find that we come to the scriptures
and we come to the truth that is before us this morning,
we can rejoice in knowing that I can please the Lord.
You can live your life, I can live my life,
we can live our lives in such a way
that the Lord Jesus Christ would be pleased with us.
And by the way, he's revealed to us in his word,
we'll deal with that in just a moment,
but we wanna answer the question, can I?
There's some people that go through life and they say,
well, I can't please God anyway.
Well, you can please God.
And it is absolutely possible,
we see it in 1 Thessalonians 2,
where Paul says that he's seeking to please God,
not pleasing men, but pleasing God.
If the apostle Paul understood that he was able to serve
in such a way that he could bring honor and glory
to his savior to please his Lord,
then we understand this morning
that we too can please the Lord.
In 1 Thessalonians 4, in fact, turn over there if you will,
we find that Paul gave his testimony in the second chapter
with regard to his entrance into and how he recognized
that he had been privileged to preach the gospel,
but he was seeking in doing so to please God
because he understood that that was pleasing in his sight.
But notice as he's writing in chapter number four
to these believers, these in Thessalonica,
he's encouraging them with regard that they too
can please the Lord with their lives.
In verse number one of 1 Thessalonians 4,
the Bible says, furthermore then,
we beseech you brethren and exhort you by the Lord Jesus,
that as ye have received of us,
notice how ye ought to walk and to please God,
so ye would abound more and more,
for ye know what commandments we gave you by the Lord Jesus.
And so as Paul is writing here
to these believers in Thessalonica,
not only did he tell them in the second chapter
that he was living and behaving in such a way
that he would please God, not men,
that he would please God,
that then he tells these believers
that they have received truth.
He mentions that truth in verse number two
as being the commandments that they gave Paul
to these believers in Thessalonica,
notice, by the Lord Jesus.
These weren't commands that just Paul was making up
and adding these things.
No, Paul was giving the commands
as the Lord had given the commands.
And he says this, that you've received them.
Well, you've received, you've been instructed
on how ye ought to walk, and then notice the phrase,
and to please God, so ye would abound more and more.
And so we find that the Apostle Paul
is saying to these believers in Thessalonica,
listen, you can please God with your life.
And I've given you the instruction, God has enabled me,
God has allowed me to be the individual,
the mouthpiece, if you will,
that brought this truth to you
so that you would know how you can please the Lord.
And then he ends it by saying this,
so you would abound more and more.
Live your life to please the Lord, why?
Because it's possible.
Notice the testimony of the Lord Jesus Christ, if you will,
in John chapter number eight.
Turn back, if you will, to John chapter number eight.
Now, we know that Jesus is God in flesh,
and what a blessing to understand that command
or that truth, and we find that Jesus, as God,
he left his throne in heaven,
he came to this sin-cursed world,
he lived a perfect, sinless life,
and he went to the cruel cross so that we could be saved.
And what a joy that is to know.
But he makes this statement in John chapter number eight,
and what a great truth.
The Bible says, and he that sent me is with me,
the Father hath not left me alone,
for I do always those things that please him.
I want you to think about your life,
and I want you to examine, as I have,
and I wonder today, now obviously we understand
that Jesus is God, he's perfect, and we are not,
but I wonder if we would evaluate our lives,
I know that we could not say that I do always
those things that please the Lord,
because we are sinners and we fail,
but I wonder if there's more things that we do in our life
that please him than not.
If we truly evaluate our lives,
if we look at our last days that we've walked on this earth,
as we look at the last few days,
did I please the Lord with how I walked?
Did I please the Lord with the things that I said?
Did I please the Lord?
Because I can please God, I can please him.
And Jesus says, I do always those things that please him.
There's a man in the Old Testament,
we'll look at the testimony of this man
in the book of Hebrews, in the 11th chapter,
if you'd turn there just for a moment,
Hebrews chapter number 11.
We think about this great hall of faith chapter
and how God has given to us the testimonies
of those that live by faith.
And by the way, the Bible tells us
the just shall live by faith.
We are to take God at his word, to believe him,
God is pleased when we live a life of faith,
and we'll mention that in just a few moments,
but look here, in Hebrews chapter 11,
in verse number five, God tells us about a man
by the name of Enoch.
And the Bible says that Enoch in verse number five,
by faith Enoch was translated that he should not see death.
Notice and was not found because God had translated him
for before his translation, he had this testimony
that he pleased God, that he pleased God.
Isn't that a simple testimony, but so powerful.
I mean, it's just a simple statement.
Enoch pleased God, praise the Lord, that he pleased God.
He lived in such a way, and by the way,
we understand historically, if you were to go back
to Genesis five, just on the eve of Genesis six
and the great global flood and all that would take place.
And obviously the Bible tells us that Noah found grace
in the eyes of the Lord, but the reality is
that he was living, Noah was, during a time
of great wickedness, and Noah was able to walk with God
and please God and find grace in the sight of God.
But so was Enoch as we look in the fifth chapter,
again, all of those things of wickedness
that were going on, and Enoch had this testimony
that he pleased God.
Now understand this isn't Enoch writing about himself.
This is God writing about Enoch.
And I wonder today if God were to write about your life,
if he were to write about my life,
if he would sum up our testimony in the same way.
They pleased me.
They lived in such a way that they, see because we can.
We can please God.
We can please him with our lives.
The record that we see in these few verses of scripture
answer the question with great certainty
that absolutely we can live in such a way
that God is pleased.
If it's true that we can live in such a way
that God is pleased, it's also true
that we can live in such a way that God is not pleased.
Amen.
And our behavior matters to God.
There are some people that have the idea, antinomianism,
if you've heard about the subject, the terminology,
they believe, they teach that you're saved by grace,
you can kind of just live however you want to live,
and you're just gonna go to heaven when you die.
And the reality is that I'm thankful
that salvation is eternally secure,
that I can't work for my salvation,
nor can I work to keep my salvation.
But the Bible does tell us that if any man be in Christ,
he is a new creature, old things are passed away,
behold, all things become new.
The Bible tells us that we are his workmanship
created in Christ Jesus unto good works.
We find that the Bible tells us as James deals with it,
and he deals with the fruit of salvation,
not so much as Paul deals with the root of salvation.
He says, you say that you have faith, show me your works.
Your works prove your faith.
And we understand that to be true.
James is not complicating the situation
and expressing that there's some way
that you can be saved by your works.
No, he's simply saying that if you are saved,
it will be evidenced in how you live, amen.
And we find this morning that if we,
understand that God has saved us, if we have that goal and that desire, that we
would please Him who has chosen us to be a soldier, that we would desire to please
Him, but understanding this morning that I can. It is a goal that can be
achieved. There are times in life where you might think, well, I've set these
goals and these goals are just not attainable. And oftentimes in the
beginning of a calendar year, I'll challenge people about setting spiritual
goals for the upcoming year and dealing with various things with regard to Bible
reading and prayer time and witnessing opportunities and so on and so forth. And
why? Because we want to have, if you don't have a goal, you just just go through
life aimlessly, helplessly, hopelessly. You just, you just have, you're just no
direction. But set some goals. I've encouraged people this way. Listen, don't
set your goal to read the Bible for three hours a day if you're not reading
it for three minutes a day right now. Why? It's just not attainable. It's not
realistic. If you're reading your Bible for two hours and 30 minutes a day right
now and you say, you know what, I want to read it for three hours a day, praise the
Lord. It's a, it's an attainable, it's a, it's a goal that is possible. This truth
that is before us this morning, I'm thankful that we can please God. And it's
not a moving target. It's not something that's just like, oh, I don't know what to
do. I don't know how to do. Is it even possible? Yes, it's possible. And we answer
the question, can I? And now we answer the question number two, how can I please
God? It's important that we understand that we can, but then we get to the, to
the nuts and bolts, if you will, of how can I? I understand that I'm, I can, but
now how do I do it? Well, there's two important principles that I'd like to
consider and then kind of jump into some thoughts, practical application, if you
will. And the first one is a truth that we find in Romans chapter number eight.
Look in Romans chapter number eight, if you will. Now understand that as we got
saved, that, that our spirit, we were made alive. We were quickened. Ephesians
two talks about those of us that were dead, that we were quickened, we were made
alive. And at the moment of salvation, Galatians describes it this way, that,
that there's this battle between our flesh and our spirit. The Bible says that
they're at enmity, one against the other. And we understand the great promise of
Galatians five, that if we walk in the spirit, we shall not fulfill the lust of
the flesh. It'd be wonderful from a human perspective, but we understand and we
submit ourselves to the plan of God. We, sometimes we say, man, I wish that we
just didn't have this flesh anymore. But at the moment of salvation, it was just
eradicated. And I understand the positive idea of that, but that's not how God
chose it to be. And we still have the flesh with the carnal desires and the lust
of the flesh is still there, but the Bible says that if I walk in the spirit,
I will not fulfill the lust of the flesh. He gives me power. He gives me victory.
And we understand that. And so when we look at the truth that's before us in
Romans chapter number eight, I want you to consider this vital principle as we
seek to answer the question, how can I please the Lord? Understanding that I can,
but now how? Notice verse number eight, so then they that are in the flesh, notice
what it says, can not please God. Now, do you know what it is when you're in the
flesh? I'm asking, do you know as a Christian, as a child of God that's been
saved for a period of time, do you know in your life personally what it is when
you're in the flesh? Can you feel it? Can you understand the feeling that you get
when you're like, I'm in the flesh right now? And sometimes you say, I want to be
in the flesh for a minute right now. No, you should stop right there and you
should pray and you should confess and you should, but we're all humans. I'm just
I'm trying to be helpful this morning because we all deal with the flesh and
you let somebody say something to you, do something to you, and all of a sudden you
can, that old man can revive in a moment. Yes, the principle is true that we're to
put off and put on, put off the old man, put on the new, and what great truth we
find in Ephesians and Colossians with regard to doing that. But you understand
that Paul said, I am crucified with Christ and I die daily, and even if you
do that, in a moment's time that old man can be revived. And you can be in the
flesh in a hurry. Am I right? And the Bible says in Romans 8 and verse number 8,
that if we're in the flesh, we can not please God. We cannot please God. So we
ought not walk in the flesh. We ought not walk according to the former lusts and
desires. We need to walk in the Spirit. It's an important principle that we
understand as we seek to answer the question, how can I please the Lord? I
understand that I can, but then how can I? We must recognize that if we're in the
flesh, we're not going to be able to please God. We're not going to be. Why?
There's a great contrast. It's amazing, in verse number 6, if you look at just a
few verses up, it says, for to be carnally minded is death, but to be
spiritually minded is life and peace. There's a great contrast that we find. We
mentioned in Hebrews 11 and verse number 5, the testimony of Enoch, but verse
number 6 says that without faith it is impossible to please Him, for they that
believe, they that come to God must believe that He is and that He's a
rewarder of them that diligently seek Him. And so we find here that this idea
of walking in the flesh, and we know what it is, we've experienced it, and we know,
and we know the fact that they're at enmity, the flesh and the spirit, one
against the other, but we must understand this morning that if we're going to live
in the flesh, if we're going to mind the things of the flesh, we're not going to
please God. He's not going to be pleased with our lives. The second important
principle is found in Ephesians chapter 5. Notice with me in Ephesians chapter
number 5, and it's an important truth that is a simple verse of Scripture that
gives us great work to do. Why do I say that? Well Ephesians 5 in verse number
10 says, proving what is acceptable unto the Lord. That word acceptable is also
translated in our Bibles as well-pleasing. So we find that what is
acceptable to the Lord is pleasing to the Lord, and we find here that it says
proving what is acceptable unto the Lord. What does it mean to prove something? What
is the process that's being done here? There's this process of proving. It was
often used in metalworking, and getting an element, silver was very common.
They would go through that process of purifying the silver. They're proving it.
They're getting out all of the things that need to be taken out and
withdrawn, and they're purifying, and here we say proving. It's that work, and
we dig into the Scriptures, and we're seeking to prove what is acceptable unto
the Lord. What is well-pleasing to God? Well in our journey of doing this, as we
have the opportunity to go through and to study the Scriptures, we have many
examples that God has given us with regard to things that please Him and
things that do not please Him. In fact, there's a great example of something
that does not please Him. We mentioned already in Romans 8 about walking in the
flesh, but notice, if you will, in 1 Corinthians chapter number 10. In 1
Corinthians chapter number 10, the Bible tells us, as God is using Paul to
minister to these believers in Corinth, and he's going back to the Old Testament
and says, in fact, in the text of Scripture that the things that were
written aforetime are written for our admonition. I'm so thankful that God
chose to preserve the Old Testament. The Old Testament, listen, all Scripture is
given by inspiration of God. That means from Genesis 1-1 to Revelation 22-21, amen?
All of it is inspired by God, and it is profitable. So I don't, a certain
portion of the Scripture, I don't like reading. You ought to get that right with
the Lord, amen? Because it's God's Word to you, and He has preserved it for a
reason, and Paul says it was written for our admonition. The things that he
mentions in the text of Scripture are all events that took place with regard to
the children of Israel. I'm not going to deal with the particulars that are
given to us in verses 6-10, but I do want you to notice in verse number
5, notice what the Bible says,
"...but with many of them God was not well pleased." Now, he doesn't say, but with all
of them. He says, but with many of them. That means that there were some that
pleased the Lord, but there were some, many, that did not please the Lord, and it
says, "...for they were overthrown in the wilderness." He gives us the examples. In
fact, in verse number 6, it says, "...now these things were our examples." Now,
examples we are to learn from. We benefit from examples. We benefit from
reading these truths that are mentioned in the Old Testament from here in 1
Corinthians 10. We go back and we read them, and we learn from them, and if God
says that with many of them He was not well pleased, that ought to get my
attention, and ought to get your attention.
attention. Why? Well, because their behavior did not please God. And if their
behavior did not please God, then I better be careful that I'm not acting
and behaving in that way. Does that make sense this morning? If I find that the
Scriptures say that this is pleasing to the Lord, then I find, okay, that behavior
is pleasing to God. I ought to be doing that thing, whatever that is. So this is
that proving what is acceptable unto the Lord, that we're digging into the
Scriptures, that we're working, that we're proving, that we're finding. Okay, what is
it that was not pleasing? Well, we'll make one comment here. There was idolatry. We
understand idolatry is not pleasing to God, amen? It's a pretty simple one.
It's one that many times now John finishes 1st John by saying, my little
children, keep yourself from idols. Sometimes we're fooled in America to
think we don't have idols because we don't have little statues in our house
and we don't have these little wooden figurines and we don't bow down to them.
And so in America, we think we don't have idols. We have plenty of idols in
America. Plenty of idols in America. Work, money, sports. I mean, we could just go
status, position. I mean, you just go on and on. We got idols. The Bible says in
Colossians 1 that in all things He, Christ, must have the preeminence. Amen. He is
first. He is the one that has that place of preeminence. But we see idolatry is
mentioned, fornication is mentioned. Notice, if you will, just verse number 10.
It says, neither murmur ye, as some of them also murmured and were destroyed of
the destroyer. Now, what does it mean? We don't use the word murmur too often, but
I actually like the word murmur. It just sounds bad. You say to somebody, you're
murmuring. It almost could be offensive. But no, we just, we complain. We use that
word. It really means the same thing. You know, the children of Israel, they were
often guilty of complaining, of murmuring. And we find that the truth of God's Word
is that this is one of the things that are specifically mentioned here in 1
Corinthians chapter number 10 that did not please. He says, with many of them God
is not well pleased. One of the things that they were doing was murmuring. They
were complaining and God was not pleased with it. You know, we're good at
complaining. We really are. We're good at criticizing the children of Israel for
complaining. But then right after criticizing them for complaining, we
complain. Listen, people complain about it's too hot, it's too cold, it's too this,
it's too that. The food is too this, it's too that. This person asked for that. I
mean, we can find things to complain about and complain about and complain
about. In Numbers chapter 21, the Bible says that the people spake against the
Lord and He sent fiery serpents. They were complaining about God's provision
for them. In that verse specifically, they were talking about the fact that they
hated manna. God miraculously provided manna. But in chapter number 11 of
Numbers, the Bible says, and when the people complained, it displeased the Lord
and the Lord heard it and His anger was kindled and the fire of the Lord burned
among them and consumed them that were in the uttermost parts of the camp. Now
Numbers 11.1 is a convicting verse of Scripture because the Bible says when
the people complained, it displeased the Lord. But then it tells us this, and the Lord
heard it. God hears our praise, but He also hears our complaints. And oh, would it be
said that He hears us praise Him far more frequently than He hears us
complaining. But not only did the Lord hear it, not only was the Lord displeased,
but the Bible says that His anger was kindled. His anger was kindled. I don't
want God to be angry with me. I don't want God to be angry with my family. I
don't want God to be angry with our church. I don't want to be complaining. No, I want to
learn from that example that is referenced in 1 Corinthians 10. We go
back to the Old Testament and we learn. So this truth of proving what is
acceptable unto the Lord. We can please God, but then how can I please the Lord?
The two vital principles, I need to dig into God's Word so that I can prove what
is acceptable unto the Lord. I need to understand that if I'm in the flesh, I'm
not going to please Him. Children are commanded to obey their parents. And in
Colossians 3.20, it says that in so doing, they are pleasing the Lord. So it's a
simple verse of Scripture, a simple principle that we find again as we're
studying and proving what is acceptable unto the Lord, that we find that God says
in Colossians 3.20, children obey your parents and all things for this is well
pleasing unto the Lord. And we find that we have children that disobey. They're
not just disobeying their parents, they're disobeying the Lord. They're not
just displeasing their parents, they're displeasing the Lord. And so we
find that again, going through this process of proving what is acceptable,
that helps us to understand not only that I can, but how can I please the Lord?
Let me give you three ways very quickly as we close this morning. Three ways that
we can please our Master. Three ways that we can please our Master. Number one,
living a life of faith. Living a life of faith. What does it mean to live by faith?
So often we use the terminology and it seems as if there are times in which we
talk about living by faith and it seems like this mystical kind of an idea
of what does it mean to live by faith? You hear people say, well, just step out
by faith. You ever heard somebody say that? And it's as if you're just
gonna step off into nothing and you're just stepping out by faith. And they use
that kind of, listen, it's not this mystical idea of living by faith. Living
by faith and living a life of faith is trusting God, is taking God at His word,
that what God says, God will do, that God always does what He says He will do, that
God is, as we sang this morning, a faithful God, that He's never failed, that
He never will fail, that He provides and He supplies the needs for His people. We
find that in Hebrews chapter number 11, a verse that I mentioned a moment ago, in
verse number 6, the Bible says, but without faith it is impossible to please
Him. So what do we learn from that? We learn that we better live by faith and
when we do it pleases God. You think about many instances in the Word of God
where people lived by faith, where people took God at His word, that they believed
that what God said, God will do, how God was pleased with them and how God did
the miraculous, that listen, as Noah stood, excuse me, as Moses stood on the
bank of the Red Sea and he believed God, that God said, raise up your arm with
that staff and that rod, that He would part the Red Sea, that as Moses
believed God and he acted in faith, he took God at His word, then God did the
rest. Because God always does what God says He will do. When Abraham went out,
not knowing whether he went, but he went out believing God, God says that it was
by faith that he went. You can read through Hebrews 11 and you can read of
all of these that that triumphed greatly through faith, but you'll understand
this vital principle that all of them simply took God at His word. We think
about Elijah when he prayed fire from heaven. What a great passage of Scripture.
The book of 1st Kings, we read it, we rejoice in seeing this great power of
God on display, but you'll notice something when when Elijah prays, he says
that I've said all this at thy word. It's a little phrase that gives us such
insight to what was happening there in that moment as Elijah was simply
believing God. He was acting in faith. And the Bible says that without faith it is
impossible to please Him, for he that cometh to God must believe that He is,
and that He is a rewarder of them that diligently seek Him. And we find here
this truth, how do I live by faith? How do I walk by faith? How can I take God at
His word? Well, the Bible says, so then faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the
word of the Lord, of the Word of God. Listen, your faith is not going to be
increased and you're not going to live by faith if you're not spending time in
this book, because faith comes, is produced by hearing the truth of God's
Word. When we hear of all of the great triumphs of our God, when we hear of His
character, of His attributes, of who He is, of what He's capable of doing, it causes
me to have faith to believe. You think about the many miracles when the Lord
Jesus Christ walked upon the face of the earth, and how He would speak about,
thy faith hath made thee whole. I think about the man, Ronnie, often mentions the
individual that says, Lord, I believe, help thou mine unbelief. It was believing that
God is able, that God was able, that He was able to do it.
will do, and when I read those truths of God's Word, when I'm saturating my mind and my heart
with who my God is and what my God has done, it increases my faith.
A question is asked that's a piercing question with regard to the return of the Lord.
Will he find faith on the earth?
I wonder.
We're to live by faith, not by sight, but by faith.
Well, I just need to be able to figure all this out, and I need to be able to see it
all before I...
That's not living by faith.
It's just believing God.
God said he would provide.
God said that he would bless.
God said that he would be who he says he will be, and we just believe him, and we live a
life that is marked by faith, that pleases the Lord.
God is pleased when we trust him, when we believe him.
Do you like people to believe you?
Sure you do.
We like people to believe us.
We like people to trust that what we say we will do, that we will do, that they can have
confidence.
God is pleased when we trust him, when we believe him, when we take God at his Word.
Paul stood up with great boldness and said in Acts 27, I believe God.
I believe God.
God gave him a great promise in that passage of Scripture, and he believed that God was
able.
Though the circumstances didn't look like it, he said, I believe God.
Notice number two.
Not only can we please God by living a life of faith, we live a life that's marked by
praise.
I mentioned about complaining a few moments ago that it displeased the Lord, but notice
that when we praise the Lord, that it pleases the Lord.
In Hebrews 13 and verse number 15, we started out this morning by reading a few verses of
Scripture from the book of Psalms and Psalm 34, and I made this statement that our God
is worthy of our praise.
He alone is worthy of our praise.
And we find here in Hebrews 13 and verse number 15, it says, by him, therefore, let us offer
the sacrifice of praise to God continually.
That is the fruit of our lips giving thanks to his name.
I believe that God is pleased when we praise him, that God, he inhabits the praise of his
people.
We're to come before his throne with thanksgiving.
We're to enter into his gates with praise and with thanksgiving.
Why?
Because our God is worthy, and we're to offer continually to our God the fruit of our lips,
the giving thanks to his name.
And that in any situation, in any circumstance that you find yourself in in life, that God
is still on the throne and he's still good.
He is good all the time, and he is worthy of our praise.
In the most difficult of days, we can still lift our voice and praise the Lord.
Why?
For he is.
He is.
He is holy.
He is just.
He is righteous.
He is omnipotent, omniscient, omnipresent.
He is almighty.
He is.
You keep filling in the blanks.
He's all those things and more.
When I learn to thank him for who he is and praise him for who he is, then my circumstances
don't matter so much because God is.
Paul and Silas, they were in prison.
They'd been beaten, but they sang praises unto God at midnight.
In the midst of that prison cell, in the midst of that difficulty, they knew that God was
still worthy of their praise.
A life that pleases the Lord, not only a life that's marked by faith, a life that's marked
by praise, but a life that's marked by giving, by giving to the Lord.
You know, so often when we approach the subject of giving, people get nervous and they get
worked up and they reach various conclusions, but understand that giving is part of the
Christian life.
We worship God through our giving.
We speak about that often.
We take up an offering.
It's not that somebody is trying to get, no, it's that we get to give to God.
We get to worship God.
We get to give to God.
Notice the book of Philippians, if you will, we're going to look at two passages very quickly
in the New Testament.
The children of Israel, by the way, had the privilege to give to the building of the tabernacle.
And as they gave, and the Bible regularly mentions, and we'll look at this in the book
of 2 Corinthians as well this morning, the Bible often mentions about willing offering,
willing.
And they gave so much that it was said, hey, the people bring too much, they don't need
to bring anymore.
Praise the Lord.
They were willing.
They were privileged to be able to give.
Notice in Philippians chapter four, in verse number 16, the Bible says, for even in Thessalonica
ye sent once again unto my necessity, not because I desire a gift, but I desire fruit
that may abound to your account.
But I have all and abound, I am full, having received of Epaphroditus the things which
were sent from you.
And then notice how Paul describes the offering that was sent from these believers to him
for the work.
He says that it was an odor of a sweet smell, a sacrifice acceptable, well-pleasing to God.
For some reason, there's been this stigma, if you will, with regard to speaking on the
subject of giving, that pastors shy away from it, that church people think the pastor's
just trying to get something, and the reality is that no, it's Bible.
It's Bible.
And God says that he is well-pleased when we give.
Listen, we're not just tipping God, we're giving to God out of a heart of love and obedience.
And God is pleased with it.
By the way, our giving not only pleases God, but it's also an evidence of our faith.
That we believe, if we just start with the tithe and just mention the tithe for just
a moment, that we believe that God will do with 90 percent more than what could be done
with 100 percent.
It's believing God.
It's just taking God at his word.
That God said that you've robbed me in the book of Malachi, where have we robbed thee?
In tithes and offerings.
And he said that prove me is what he said in Malachi chapter 3.
And what would he do?
Not only would he bless them, but he would also rebuke the devourer for their sakes.
Our God is able, and it's a matter of faith, it's a matter of obedience, but it's pleasing
to the Lord.
Notice the people in 2 Corinthians chapter 9, and I have to hurry here, 2 Corinthians
chapter 9, in verses 6 and 7, the Bible says this, in 2 Corinthians 9, it's interesting
if you, I don't have time, but if you want to go back later this afternoon and read chapter
8, you'll notice that the very people that he's speaking of in chapter 9 that we're giving,
that they were in deep poverty, but yet they gave.
And he says this, that they first gave of them their own selves to the Lord, and then
of their substance.
But notice in 2 Corinthians 9 in verse 6, the Bible says, but this I say, he which soweth
sparingly shall reap also sparingly, and he which soweth bountifully shall reap also bountifully.
Now we understand this from a perspective of agriculture, do we not?
If you plant a bunch of seeds, you're going to expect to have a big crop.
If you plant just a few seeds, you're going to expect to have a smaller crop.
You're not going to plant a few seeds and think that you're going to have an abundance
of crop, right?
We understand agriculturally, but he's making the application here to our giving, whether
we're giving sparingly or whether we're giving bountifully.
Notice in verse number 7, every man according as he purposeth in his heart, so let him give.
But notice what it says, not grudgingly or of necessity, for God loveth a cheerful giver.
It's a wonderful truth that we find here.
We mentioned in Philippians chapter number 4 that God is well pleased with this, with
our giving.
But here in 2 Corinthians 9, the Bible says that God loveth a cheerful giver, that the
perspective is not this that I'm giving grudgingly or of necessity.
It's not that I have to, it's that I get to.
It's that God blessed me and God has enabled me to give back to him.
God is pleased with that.
Why?
Because we're honoring him, we're exalting him, and he's pleased.
This morning we've answered the question that yes, indeed, I can please God.
And then we've considered some ways in which we are able to please him.
How can I do it?
Okay, I understand that I can, but then how?
You continue to apply the principle of Ephesians 5, 10 to your life and prove what is acceptable
unto the Lord, and you'll find a number of reasons.
I've given you three simple thoughts this morning on how we can please God, but understand
the Bible is full of examples of how your behavior and my behavior can please our God,
and that we would have this idea, we'd have this perspective that we find in 2 Timothy
2 and verse number 4, that I want to please my master, a good soldier.
Not only does he endure hardness, not only does he avoid distraction, but he has as a
goal to please his master.
This morning as we examine our lives, I hope that we would examine our lives in such a
way that we would determine whether our behavior pleases the Lord.
Are there adjustments that need to be made?
Are there areas in our life where, if we're honest and if we're humble, as the Holy Spirit
of God searches and proves, that would say, you know, there's some areas that are not
really well.
well-pleasing to the Lord, then make the adjustments.
There's some things that need to be adjusted.
I made this statement on Wednesday evening.
It's a silly thing for us to go to the truth of God's word
and to be confronted with truth
and then to not apply it, to not make adjustments,
to not say, you know what, that's something that I need,
that's something I need to incorporate in my life.
No, we come to the place where we say,
listen, I want God to be pleased with my life,
and if adjustments are necessary,
then by God's grace and with God's help,
I'll make the adjustments so that my life can be pleasing
so that we could have the testimony of Enoch.
He pleased the Lord.
He pleased God.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Lord, this morning, the challenge is simple.
Are we living in a manner that pleases you?
We acknowledge that our behavior can please you
and our behavior can displease you.
We've looked at three simple thoughts.
The Bible is full of examples.
The list is by no way, no means exhaustive.
Your word has plenty of examples for us.
And I pray that you'd help each of us to have as our goal
that we want to be a good soldier
and that a good soldier has as a goal to please his master.
And I pray that you'd help us this morning
to live our lives in such a way that you'd be pleased.
Help us to examine.
Help us to adjust.
There's some things that we're doing
that are not pleasing your sight.
Would you help us to confess them and forsake them?
There's things that we're not doing that we should be doing.
Lord, help us to be obedient.
Help us to be doers of the word.
Help us, Lord, to live a life
that is well-pleasing in thy sight.
Well, thank you for the work that you'll do.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed.