She made it back safely on Monday evening.
And so we thank the Lord for that.
And she just has a few more weeks
and then she'll be done her first year.
It's hard to believe, but continue to pray for her,
pray for Kiademe.
She also has just a few weeks left
until she's finished with her first year.
And it's hard to believe how quickly time goes.
And we're thankful that both Kiademe and Brianne
are doing well.
Thank you for praying for them.
First Thessalonians chapter five this evening,
First Thessalonians chapter number five.
We started in verse number 12 about three months ago now.
And we've been studying through these instructions
that God gives to the church there in Thessalonica.
And he begins with, we beseech you.
And then of course he transitions in verse 14.
We exhort you and we find that as we've read through
and studied these particular instructions,
that we would say that the closing section of this book
is packed with powerful truth.
And I would call it profitable instruction.
We understand that God's word is profitable.
We understand that the second Timothy chapter three
in verse number 16 tells us that all scripture
is given by inspiration of God and is profitable.
It tells us what it's profitable for,
but this is profitable instruction.
And we find that every New Testament church
should have a desire to walk worthy and please God.
That of course has been the title for this series
over the last 13 weeks.
And this evening as we examine two verses of scripture,
we've been spending, really in verse 14,
we spent several weeks looking at each phrase.
And then over the next several weeks,
we've kind of just dealt with one verse per week.
But this evening, verse number 20 and 21
really tie together and establish a single truth
that needs to be understood.
And really, I believe that the scriptures are clear
that we are to be sound in the faith.
We find that God has desire for his children
and for his churches to be sound in the faith.
That word sound means to be healthy.
It means to be free from any mixture of error.
You will find the phrase there in the book of Titus
of being sound in the faith.
You'll find in the book of Titus
and the book of 1 Timothy
and a number of other books as well,
where they'll use the word sound doctrine
and that which is free of any error, mixture of error.
And so we find that God desires for his people,
his churches to be sound in the faith.
As you read the pastoral epistles,
as you read the letters that are given
to the New Testament churches,
such as this one to the church at Thessalonica,
you will know that there is an emphasis placed
on the importance of being settled, grounded,
and established in the faith.
And that's what God wants for his people.
He doesn't want us to be tossed to and fro.
He doesn't want every time some new thing comes up
for us to be swaying back and forth
and we're over here and we're over there
and we don't know what.
No, he wants us to be settled and grounded
and to have that solid foundation.
And so God provided us with his word
and we believe the Bible is the sole authority
for faith and for practice.
And so I'm thankful that God has given us his word.
We understand that the church in Thessalonica
and many of the churches, as we look at the churches
that are written to here in the New Testament,
they did not have the entire Bible
like we have this evening.
And so we understand that God,
during that foundational period of time
that we often refer to as the early church age,
in the first century, that God had established
that there would be some apostolic sign gifts,
that there would be some truth
with regard to some spiritual gifts
that would be for that era of time.
And we see really that here,
as we look at this portion of scripture,
that he's dealing with part of that,
but we find that it's been preserved for us this evening
and it's applicable for every church
throughout the church age.
We have the whole Bible and we ought to be thankful for that
and here in these two verses of scripture,
I believe that God provides his people
with a simple formula that will enable
individual believers and churches
to be sound in the faith.
Notice what he says in verse number 20,
despise not prophesying, verse 21,
prove all things, hold fast that which is good.
Really, those three statements are going to serve
as our three points for an outline this evening.
And so number one, verse number 20,
despise not prophesying,
as I've titled the message this evening,
sound in the faith.
How can we be sound in the faith?
How could this church, the church in Thessalonica,
how could they be sound in the faith?
How could any church be sound in the faith?
Maybe we can ask this question as well this evening.
Are there churches that are not sound in the faith?
Obviously, the answer is obvious to that question.
There are an abundance of churches
that are not sound in the faith.
How can we make that statement this evening?
Well, because what they teach and what they practice
doesn't align with the book that God gave us, the Bible.
And I'm so thankful for that little song that we sing,
so often with the children in Sunday school, the B-I-B-L-E.
Yes, that's the book for me.
I stand alone on the word of God, the B-I-B-L-E.
And God's given us the authoritative word,
and that is certainly reason to rejoice.
But we find first this evening, despise not prophesying.
So we have to understand,
as we look at this verse of scripture,
what is it that Paul is referring to?
What are these prophecies, if you will,
these prophesying that Paul is referring to
when he says despise not prophesying?
Well, we have to understand this evening
the ministry of prophets.
What is the ministry of prophets?
Well, prior to the New Testament being completed,
we find that prophets would speak
direct revelation from God.
Now that the Bible is completed,
we find that there are no longer prophets
in the sense of speaking direct revelation from God.
For the Bible, the canon of scripture is closed.
Now we could look at a preacher and say,
some might use that terminology,
that they're forth telling, they're giving truth.
But the reality is that that office of a prophet,
when Paul was speaking here about despise not prophesying,
we must understand what the New Testament teaches us
about the ministry of prophets.
Understand also this evening that prophets,
apostles and prophets,
were the foundation of the local church.
We understand that Jesus Christ is the cornerstone.
The prophets and the apostles are the foundation.
And then we find that Peter refers to,
we see in the book of Ephesians as well,
that we are lively stones.
We're like the bricks of the structure of the church,
if we could think about it in that image this evening.
And so look back, if you will, to the book of Ephesians,
and notice what God tells us about prophets.
And it helps us to understand what Paul is dealing with here
in the church in Thessalonica,
when he says despise not prophesying.
It's Ephesians chapter two.
Look, if you will, with me at verse number 20.
Now, obviously we're jumping at the end
of a text of scripture,
and he's talked already about their new position in Christ,
because these people have been saved by the grace of God.
And he says this in verse number 20,
and are built upon the foundation
of the apostles and prophets,
Jesus Christ himself being the chief cornerstone.
So Jesus Christ is the chief cornerstone,
and the apostles and the prophets,
according to verse 20, are the foundation.
If you look back in verse 19,
he talks about our position in Christ
and of the household of God.
And again, seeing in verse 21,
in whom all the building fitly framed together,
groweth unto a holy temple in the Lord,
in whom you also are builded together
for an habitation of God through the spirit.
And so we find this evening in Ephesians 2.20,
this truth that the apostles and the prophets
are the foundation of the church.
Look in chapter three, if you will, in verse number five,
the Bible says this, which in other ages,
he's talking about this mystery,
which in other ages was not made known
unto the sons of men, as it is now revealed
unto his holy apostles and prophets by the spirit.
And so this is God's revelation, again,
as we would speak about the ministry of prophets
before the completion of the New Testament,
that they would speak direct revelation from God.
And so he gives us this truth
in verse number five of chapter three.
Again, look over in chapter number four, if you will,
in verse number 11, and we really could read down
a few verses, we'll read verses 11 through 14,
and notice the various offices that are spoken of here.
In Ephesians four, in verse number 11,
it says, and he gave some apostles.
Now, if you look back in the text, in verses seven and eight,
you talk about the gifts that he's given to every man
and understand that he here.
is referring to God, he gave some apostles
and some prophets and some evangelists
and some pastors and teachers.
So what was the purpose that God gave these offices?
He equipped the church with these offices.
Notice in verse number 12,
for the perfecting of the saints,
for the work of the ministry,
for the edifying of the body of Christ,
till we all come in the unity of the faith
and with the knowledge of the Son of God
unto a perfect man,
unto the measure of the stature of the fullness of Christ,
that we, notice this, henceforth,
be no more children tossed to and fro
and carried about with every wind of doctrine
by the slight of men and cunning craftiness,
whereby they lie in wait to deceive.
And so understand that false teachers,
they're very subtle in their approach.
Understand that they're lying in wait to deceive.
This is the revelation that God has given us
with regard to their craftiness.
He says, by the slight of men, every wind of doctrine.
And obviously there were false teachers
that were prevalent in the early church age,
just as there are today.
We find that in the Old Testament, there were false prophets.
We can read of all of those things.
And so we find that we understand
prior to the completion of the New Testament,
what was the ministry of a prophet?
Well, to give the word of God,
that direct revelation from God.
So here, Paul is saying, despise not prophesying.
There are gonna be some that come in
that are going to speak to you the truth.
Despise not prophesying.
We find that it doesn't end there.
We'll look at verse 21 in just a moment.
But let me just say this,
because as we look at this passage of scripture
and understand that we today are not in the same position
as the church at Thessalonica.
The church in Thessalonica didn't have a whole Bible.
We have a whole Bible.
So what is the ministry of a prophet?
Well, apostles and prophets are no more
in the sense that they were
at the writing of the New Testament.
And so therefore, we find that after the completion
of the New Testament, here's what the New Testament says.
In 1 Corinthians chapter 13, in fact, turn there,
because I want you to see it.
In verses eight through 10, notice what the Bible says,
and it deals with tongues as well
as we read the portion of scripture.
But I want you to see what it says
with regard to prophecies.
In 1 Corinthians chapter 13, in verse number eight,
of course, many of you know, 1 Corinthians 13,
people refer to it as what?
The love chapter, it's about charity.
And he says in verse number eight, charity never faileth.
But whether there be prophecies, they shall fail.
Do you see that?
It then goes on, it says whether there be tongues,
they shall cease.
Whether there be knowledge, it shall vanish away,
for we know in part, and we prophesy in part,
but when that which is perfect is come,
then that which is in part shall be done away.
And we find that as we look here
and we think about Peter, excuse me, James,
talking about in James chapter number one,
the perfect law of liberty,
and that we're to be doers of the word and not hearers only.
He talks about the one that looks into the mirror
and he uses that illustration
and he looks into the perfect law of liberty.
So when the word of God is complete,
as we see in verse number 10,
they didn't have the complete New Testament
or the complete Bible, we now do.
And so he says that these things that are in part
shall be done away.
Notice in verse number eight,
it says whether there be prophecies,
notice they shall fail.
Now, is that a statement that is absolute?
They shall fail, that's what's going to happen.
What does the word fail mean?
It does not mean that the prophecies
aren't going to come to pass.
So you think about the Old Testament,
when there's a prophet, if a prophet is known,
whether they're a true prophet or a false prophet
was whether or not their prophecies came to pass, right?
That was a test that was given of Old Testament prophets.
This is not what that word fail mean.
It doesn't mean that somebody made a prophecy
and it did not come to pass, it failed.
No, this word fail means to cause to cease,
to end or to be done away.
So what is he revealing to us?
Well, prophecies in the sense of speaking
the direct revelation from God,
as we see prior to the New Testament being completed,
that after the New Testament is completed,
after the Bible is completed, then prophecies shall fail.
They're going to cease.
We don't need them anymore.
God's given us the Bible.
He's given us the whole canon of Scripture
and therefore no one is speaking
any direct revelation from God.
God has given his complete revelation in his word.
Does that make sense this evening?
So then he says, whether they be tongues, they shall cease.
I just had this conversation
at the dinner table this evening.
Somebody came up with, somebody sent a note to Juliana
about some speaking tongues situation.
We began to talk about it.
And I said, the question that people have to answer
is that the Bible says they shall cease.
When?
When, when are they gonna cease?
Well, according to the text, as you read through the text,
when that which is perfect is come,
that's when they're going to cease.
So we look here and we find, again, there are people today,
there are groups of churches you can go to
that still would believe in prophecies
and they would believe in speaking in tongues
and yet they don't follow the biblical pattern
or the biblical instruction that's been given.
And we find here this evening that God is very clear
in his word, as we can go Scripture with Scripture,
comparing Scripture with Scripture,
what it is that they had the responsibility of receiving
and how for every church throughout the church age,
how we would deal with this.
Again, they did not have a complete Bible,
so therefore God was still giving his word
through prophecies, through prophesying,
as we would see in this text of Scripture.
Therefore, as we look at ourselves today
as a New Testament church
and looking at having the complete canon of Scripture,
we do not need any office of a prophet.
There's no longer prophesying in that sense.
Absolutely, it is true today that God still uses evangelists
and pastors to preach his word.
That's why Paul says to Timothy in 2 Timothy 4,
preach the word.
That's why we find that as you look at the entirety
of Ephesians 4, verse number 11,
he talks about apostles, prophets, evangelists,
pastors and teachers.
And we see again that the foundation of the church
was laid Jesus Christ, the chief cornerstone,
the foundation, the apostles and the prophets.
And so we find that the first thing that is given
to the church in Thessalonica is despise not prophesying.
If I could look at that and try to apply it
for us this evening,
I would say that when the word of God is being preached,
we ought not despise it.
We ought to accept the truth of God's word.
And in fact, we ought to desire to hear the word of God
being proclaimed.
We ought to make sure that we're in a place
where the word of God is being proclaimed.
We don't go somewhere, we don't go find a church
based on wanting to know what kind of ministries
or programs do you have and what do you have for this
and what do you have for that
and where do you take the teenagers during the summer
and this, that and the other thing.
And there's a lot of people that that's what they look for
in finding a church.
And they don't really have as a primary factor
how the preaching is handled.
But I would say that first and foremost,
we better be concerned with the preaching of God's word
and we should despise not the preaching,
despise not prophesying is what he says
to the church in Thessalonica.
Now notice as we move on verse 21,
number two, if you're taking notes,
he says prove all things, prove all things.
What does it mean to prove?
It means to test or to examine.
It means to scrutinize.
It means to determine if a thing is genuine.
All right, so that's what the word means, prove.
So here he says prove all things.
So I want you to think about the church in Thessalonica
and I want you to think about this despise not prophesying.
But there are false prophets, there are false teachers.
So when somebody is coming and they say,
I have a prophecy from the Lord, I'm gonna prophesy.
All right, despise not prophesying
but coupled together prove all things.
And so how is it that we today
are going to prove all things?
How is it that they could prove all things?
Well, we find that they obviously
had the apostolic authority of Paul and Peter and John
and so on and so forth.
But we noticed something in the church at Berea.
So look over at Acts chapter 17, if you will.
And we often reference the Bereans.
And we talk about the behavior of the Bereans
when it came to Paul going there and preaching the word.
Now we find that here Paul was only there
for a very short time.
In fact, he went to Berea because
of being run out of Thessalonica.
And that's where the chapter begins in Thessalonica
and then he's run out of there
because of all of the turmoil and opposition.
It says in verse number 10.
And the brethren immediately sent away Paul and Silas
by night unto Berea, who coming thither
went into the synagogue of the Jews.
Isn't that awesome?
Paul was so concerned, everywhere he went
to preach the truth of the gospel, to let it be known,
and so he finds himself being carried over to Berea
because of the opposition in Thessalonica,
and he goes into the synagogue of the Jews,
and he goes in to teach and to preach.
We find that in verse number two,
it says this was his manner,
and he reasoned with them out of the scriptures,
and so look in verse number 11,
the Bible says these, those in Berea,
these were more noble than those in Thessalonica,
in that they received the word,
notice what it says, with all readiness of mind.
But notice, and searched the scriptures daily
for what purpose, whether those things were so.
So Paul comes and he's reasoning with them
out of the scriptures, this is his manner
according to verses two and three,
when he gets to Thessalonica,
so we could easily assume, and I think properly assume,
that when he gets into Thessalonica,
he does the same thing.
And so in verse number three of the text,
it says, opening and alleging that Christ must needs
have suffered and risen again from the dead,
and that this Jesus, whom I preach unto you, is Christ.
And so I believe that Paul went to Berea
with the same message, and so they received the word
with all readiness of mind.
They weren't despising prophecies, prophesying,
and so they received the word with all readiness of mind,
but then it says they searched the scriptures daily
whether these things were so.
How do we prove all things?
How could the church in Thessalonica prove all things?
Well, they did have the Old Testament,
and they were able to go,
and they were able to prove all things.
Of course, the apostolic authority,
as I mentioned a moment ago,
but then I want you to think about
the ministry of the Holy Spirit.
Now, again, we have the whole canon of scripture,
and what a blessing that is,
but we understand the ministry of the Holy Spirit.
The Bible tells us in the Gospel of John
that he will guide us into all truth,
lead us into all truth.
That's a ministry of the Holy Spirit of God,
and I'm thankful that the Holy Spirit,
at the moment of salvation, indwells every believer.
Those that were saved in Thessalonica
when they got saved,
they got the Holy Spirit just like we do.
So the Holy Spirit of God lives within them.
Have you ever heard something or read something
and just something didn't sit right with you,
and you didn't really know what it was?
Is the Holy Spirit not,
the Holy Spirit was not confirming what you were hearing.
Has that ever happened?
You start reading the wrong book,
you start listening to the wrong person on YouTube
or wherever it might be,
and all of a sudden something's being said,
there's some kind of, and you're like,
eh, something's not right here.
The Holy Spirit's giving you this uneasy feeling
that there's just not something right.
And then you go to the Scriptures and you trust the Lord
and ask the Holy Spirit to guide you into all truth
as he promises to do so.
Again, John 14 and verse number 26,
the Bible says this in that portion of Scripture,
"'But the Comforter, which is the Holy Ghost,
"'whom the Father will send in my name,
"'he shall teach you all things
"'and bring all things to your remembrance,
"'whatsoever I have said unto you.'"
And then in chapter 15, excuse me,
chapter 16 and verse number 13,
the Bible says this,
"'Howbeit when he, the Spirit of truth, is come,
"'he will guide you into all truth,
"'for he shall not speak of himself,
"'but whatsoever he shall hear,
"'that shall he speak,
"'and he will show you things to come.'"
And so we have those promises from Jesus
with regard to the ministry of the Holy Spirit of God.
And so as the people of God today,
when we look at this admonition,
this really, if you think about it,
as I mentioned already,
this formula for how an individual believer or a church
could be sound in the faith,
we are to prove all things.
Go to the Bible and ask the Holy Spirit
to commune with your spirit.
Look over at 1 John chapter four,
and I'm gonna read all of the verses
where I've actually turned there.
I just referenced John 14 and 16,
but look at 1 John chapter four, if you will.
In 1 John chapter number four,
notice how we begin this chapter.
It says, "'Beloved, believe not every spirit.'"
But what's the admonition?
"'But try the spirits, whether they are of God.'"
Because many false prophets are gone out into the world.
Did God know that there would be false teachers
and false prophets?
Sure He did.
So what did He do?
Well, He gave warning and instruction to His people
on how they are to try the spirits and prove all things.
And so He tells them in verse number two,
"'Hereby know ye the Spirit of God,
"'every spirit that confesseth that Jesus Christ
"'has come in the flesh is of God.
"'And every spirit that confesseth not
"'that Jesus Christ has come in the flesh is not of God.
"'And this is that spirit of antichrist,
"'whereof ye have heard that it should come,
"'and even now already is it in the world.'"
Now, we know that one day during the tribulation
that the antichrist is going to show up,
but the spirit of antichrist is already working.
We see that, we know here it's already in the world.
And then He says, "'Ye are of God, little children,
"'and have overcome them, because greater is he
"'that is in you than he that is in the world.
"'They are of the world, therefore speak they of the world,
"'and the world heareth them.
"'We are of God.
"'He that knoweth God heareth us,
"'he that is not of God heareth not us.
"'Hereby know we the spirit of truth
"'and the spirit of error.'"
This simple statement in verse number 21,
prove all things, it reminds us of the importance
of knowing the word of God and walking in the spirit.
Listen, there's a lot of stuff out there today.
There's a lot of preachers on the internet.
I'm not gonna suggest that every one of them is wrong,
because there's some good ones out there.
But I'm telling you, prove all things.
That's what the Bible tells us
as part of the formula.
Listen, there's a lot of books out there,
a lot of books that you can get your hands on,
and sometimes those books have false teaching in them.
There might be a couple of good things,
but then there's some bad things in them,
and you gotta be really careful to prove all things.
What does the Bible say?
We gotta know the word.
And so Paul says, if we're going to be sound in the faith,
and that's the goal, then we must despise not prophesying,
prove all things, and then notice how he ends verse 21,
hold fast that which is good.
Now, when we see that word hold fast,
it means to keep secure, or to keep possession of.
And you think about keeping possession,
keeping firm possession of something.
He says, hold fast that which is good.
So once you have received, and once you have proven,
then hold fast.
I've had people ask me before, are you open-minded?
Well, I can only be as open-minded
as God's word allows me to be, amen?
Listen, I'm not open-minded
that there's another way to heaven, amen?
And people can say, oh, you're closed-minded,
you're narrow, you're this, you're that.
Listen, the Bible says that Jesus is the only way,
does it not?
And so once we have received the word,
and once we have proved, then we hold fast.
You know, so many people today are saying,
we should change, we need to change this and change that,
and become more accommodating, and try to,
listen, we gotta hold fast to the truth.
What truth of God's word are you willing to let go of?
I don't wanna let go of any of it,
because God gave it to us
so that we could walk worthy and please him, amen?
And so we find this evening that he says,
hold fast to keep firm possession of, to keep it secure,
that when you have received the word,
they received it through prophets
that would speak direct revelation of God,
we receive it today through our own personal Bible study,
through preaching, as God has given the responsibility
of evangelists and pastors to preach the word,
we receive it, then we prove it,
go home and search the scriptures,
and then we hold fast, we hold fast.
It's funny as you look at the,
it's really the word funny
is probably not the appropriate word,
it's of great interest when you talk to folks that wanna,
why aren't you more open-minded
about this than to the other thing?
And you begin to share with them truth,
and you show them,
here's why I've come to the position that I've come to.
And you can go to verse, after verse,
after verse, after verse,
I mean, that's proving all things.
It's having a biblical foundation.
And it's so imperative that we as the people of God
are biblically based.
We notice that this truth that he says, hold fast.
that which is good." Notice what he says. I want you to see two passages in
closing this evening. Look back in Philippians chapter 4 if you will, and I
want you to see what Paul says to the church at Philippi. In Philippians
chapter 4, and then we're gonna look at what Paul says to Timothy, his own
son of the faith, and 2nd Timothy. So we'll notice here in Philippians 4
what he says to the church at Philippi. Notice in verse number 9 of Philippians
4, "...those things which ye have both learned and received and heard and seen
in me do, and the God of peace shall be with you." So Paul is saying to this
church in Philippi that there are some things that you've heard from me. Yes, you
have learned them, you've received them, you've heard them, you've
seen them in me. You need to do them, and he talks about the God of peace being
with them. This is giving us the idea, the understanding, that when we hold fast
that which is good, it's not just that we have a head knowledge of this is what
we believe. No, we also practice what we believe, that we're to be doers of the
Word. Amen? Listen, the Bible has been given to us, yes, to help us to
establish truth, that which is right, that which is wrong, that which is good,
that which is evil, to understand the plan of God. God's given us so many
wonderful truths in His Word, but understand that He's not given it to us
just so that we can have some superior level of knowledge. He's given it to us
so that it would impact our behavior, so that it would change the way that we live.
And so we find this evening that Paul is mentioning there to the church at
Philippi, but now I want you to see what he says to Timothy in 2nd Timothy
chapter 2. Notice what he says in 2nd Timothy chapter 2, and then we'll be
done this evening, but notice here, it's a great verse of Scripture that we've
often used with regard to the work, the ministry of discipleship. In 2nd Timothy
chapter 2, he says, Thou therefore, my son, be strong in the grace that is in Christ
Jesus. Notice verse 2, In the things that thou hast heard of me among many
witnesses, the same. Commit thou to faithful men who shall be able to teach
others also. This verse of Scripture gives us the truth of generational
influence. It shows to us not only Paul being the one teaching Timothy, but then
Timothy investing in others, faithful men that would be able to teach others. We
see multiple generations that are covered in verse number 2 of 2nd
Timothy chapter 2, but I want you to see this connection here. He says, The
things. Do you see it? And the things. That's what he says to begin the verse,
That thou hast heard of me. Now, the things, that's a simple
statement that includes a whole lot of teaching, okay? The things that thou hast
heard of me among many witnesses. Paul had instructed Timothy. We find the
writings that God gives Paul to write to Timothy. Obviously, all Scripture is given
by inspiration of God, but we find that then he says, Notice these words. You see
the things, but then notice this, the same. Do you see them? He says, In the things
that thou hast heard of me among many witnesses, the same. Commit thou to
faithful men who shall be able to teach others also. So when he says the same,
what is he referring to? Would it be a stretch for us to say, The same things
that you learned of me, that's what you're to teach others. That's what he's
saying. The same, right? Why? Well, because when we receive the Word and we prove
the Word, we hold fast. We hold firm and we teach that same truth to a future
generation. We teach that same truth to our children and to our grandchildren
and beyond. Why? Because it is the truth that changes lives. It is this book. God
told us, as we think about it, he says, Thy Word is truth, right? Sanctify them by
thy Word. Thy Word is truth. We find that he tells, Jude gives this charge, that
we're to earnestly contend for the faith that was once delivered to the
saints. Not that we look for something new. No, we've received already. We have
proven and then we hold fast. And when we take that simple formula that's given to
the church in Thessalonica in chapter 5, verses 20 and 21, three statements,
despise not prophesying, prove all things, hold fast that which is good, then we are
on the way to being sound in the faith. And God wants his individual children and he wants
his churches to be sound in the faith. He's given us his Word. He's given us his spirit.
He's equipped the church with pastors and evangelists and given them a charge to preach
the Word. And as we receive the Word and we prove through the Word, then we hold fast.
Look, I'm thankful that I don't have to be tossed to and fro with every wind of doctrine.
Amen? It's easy. Listen, I used to, going home from Bible college, I used to listen
to a certain person on the radio the summer of my freshman year in Bible college. And
I listened to this fella on the radio try to sharpen myself. He would take calls,
Harold Camping, any of you remember him back in the day? And he set dates for the return of Christ
and all kinds of crazy stuff. But I'd listen to him. And here's why I would listen to him,
because I would try to sharpen myself and he'd begin to give answers. And I'd say,
that's wrong because of this. The Bible says this. I'm driving down the highway and I'm
trying to recall verses of scripture that I'm trying to, why? Because I'm trying to be sharp
to understand what does the Bible teach? And sometimes he would deal with certain things
and I'd go and have to look it up. And why? I'm trying to prove. And I was trying to do that so
that I could be equipped, so that I could be in a position of being able to defend, earnestly
contend for the faith. We need to be very careful this evening, not looking for anything new.
God's given us all that we need. There are people out there running around trying to find some new
revelation, while at the same time they're not even doing what God has revealed to them in His
Word. What a shame. What a sad situation. This evening, he says, despise not prophesying,
prove all things, hold fast that which is good. What a great formula to be sound in the faith.
Let's pray. Lord, we love you. We thank you for loving us. Thank you for the Word. I pray that
you'd help us to be strengthened. Lord, help us to be settled and grounded. Help us, Lord, to
be firm in our position. Help us to be biblical. Bless our time of prayer. We'll thank you for it
in Christ's name we pray. Amen. Let's start in the back with the prayer updates for our
missionaries. Brother Kim, Sermon Lord in China, anyone need a...