feeling well today, and so you pray for Norma Jean,
and then pray for Miss Mauna as well.
I don't know, she's normally here,
and so she's not here this evening.
We'll follow up and see if she's doing well,
but I would like for you to pray for Miss Mauna as well,
and we're thankful to the Lord for the privilege of prayer.
The book of Ephesians this evening,
Ephesians chapter number six,
and we have now for a number of weeks here
on Wednesday evenings have had the opportunity
to study this subject matter of doing what we ought to do.
Doing what we ought to do,
and as we've had this opportunity
to study these passages of scripture in the New Testament
that speak about the things that we ought to do,
we understand that God has given us this truth,
and we ought to apply it in our lives.
Knowing what we ought to do
doesn't immediately make it the case
that we do what we ought to do,
and so as we study through these things,
we wanna be challenged and allow the Lord
to have his will and way in our lives.
I find it fascinating and insightful
to read Paul's request for prayer
as it's recorded here in Ephesians chapter number six.
Previously in this book as he's writing to this church
that God allowed him to have an opportunity
to minister to these precious souls for a number of years,
and the ministry there and the opportunity
to be able to influence them,
and he encouraged them previously in the book of Ephesians
by revealing to them how he was praying for them,
and he doesn't just simply say I'm praying for you,
but he explains to them on two separate occasions
here in the book of Ephesians
how specifically he is praying for them,
and I'm sure that was of great encouragement
to the believers when they received this letter
and they understood how the apostle Paul
was praying for them.
Now as we come to the last part of the chapter of the book
in Ephesians six verses 19 and 20,
Paul makes a request for prayer,
and again, it's fascinating and insightful
as you read his request that is given
to the believers at Ephesus.
Notice in verse 19, he says, and for me.
Now he mentions in verse 18 about prayer
and the subject is dealing with praying for all the saints,
but then in verse 19, he says, and for me,
and so he's gonna deal with the specific prayer request
that he is submitting, if you will,
to the believers at the church at Ephesus.
Notice as we think about this
that there are times in which we submit prayer requests.
We have a prayer bulletin weekly,
and Holly updates that,
and sometimes you give a prayer request
verbally in the service
as we have the concluding part of our service for prayer,
and you say would you pray for so on and so forth,
and whatever that request is,
you can make the request in writing,
you can send an email,
you can send a text, and you give that request,
and we understand, and now Paul,
as he's writing to these believers in Ephesus
here in Ephesians 6, he says, and for me in verse 19,
so he's going to give them
a specific personal request for prayer,
that utterance may be given unto me
that I may open my mouth boldly
to make known the mystery of the gospel.
So in verse number 19, he gives the truth
with regard to what he's asking prayer for,
and he says that utterance may be given unto me,
and then notice that I may open my mouth boldly,
but not just to say anything,
not just to have boldness to speak
on whatever platform that he's desiring,
whatever soapbox, if you will,
that he's desiring to speak on,
whatever cause it is that he's trying to promote,
no, that I may open my mouth boldly
for what purpose to make known
the mystery of the gospel.
Notice in verse 20, for which I am an ambassador in bonds,
that therein I may speak boldly,
and then here's the statement, as I ought to speak.
And so we find that the apostle Paul
has this understanding that he ought
to speak the gospel with boldness.
I've titled the message tonight,
if you're taking notes,
that we ought to proclaim the gospel.
We ought to proclaim the gospel.
As I consider just the opening thoughts
of Paul making this request to these believers in Ephesus
and the way in which I stated
that it's both fascinating and insightful
to read how Paul is praying for them,
but also how he requests prayer,
it leads me to a place of being mindful
of the fact that we ought to analyze our prayer list.
We ought to analyze what it is that we're praying for.
What significance of things are we praying for?
What plane, if you will,
are there more temporally focused or eternally focused?
And as we analyze our prayer list,
and also not only analyzing our prayer list,
but reviewing what we request prayer for,
we find that there really is anything
that Paul could have submitted here
to the church at Ephesus for prayer,
but he asks specifically that he would be given,
that they would pray that he would be given this boldness
to be able to speak the gospel.
Why?
Because he knows that he ought to be speaking the gospel.
Now, this is always an interesting passage of scripture
to me here in Ephesians 6, verses 19 and 20,
because honestly, as I read the New Testament,
and as I analyze the life of the Apostle Paul,
he is a man that is probably the most active proclaimer
of the gospel in the New Testament.
He's the one that's traveling from place to place
on these missionary journeys,
and he's proclaiming the gospel,
he's making known Christ,
he's sent over to Athens in order to get some rest,
if you will, because of all the things
that have transpired, and there, as he sees a city
that's wholly given to idolatry, what does he do?
He's stirred, and he goes,
and he seeks to make Christ known to them,
and we find that Paul was extremely active.
In fact, think about what Paul says in Acts chapter number 20
as he's writing or speaking to these leaders
of the church at Ephesus.
In Acts chapter number 20,
he's had the leaders of the church at Ephesus
meet him as he's on his way to Jerusalem,
and as they meet there in Acts chapter number 20,
he imparts to them some important things.
We won't look at the entirety.
We're gonna zero in on one particular statement
that he makes with regard to the subject this evening
of we ought to proclaim the gospel,
and notice what he says in verse number 31.
Therefore, watch and remember,
and so there's something that Paul did
that he's calling to their remembrance
that by the space of three years,
I ceased not to warn everyone night and day with tears.
So Paul, as we look in Acts chapter 20,
his testimony is such, especially with the testimony
that he has with the believers in Ephesus,
that he ceased not to warn for a period of three years.
What is the warning?
Well, it's giving the gospel.
He's warning them about judgment to come
and about the need to trust Christ,
and he says that he was doing it with tears.
Notice he says night and day with tears.
So the apostle Paul had an understanding.
His understanding was that he ought
to speak boldly the gospel.
Why is it, what is it that he understood about God
and about God's plan that led him to having this belief
that he ought to speak the gospel,
to proclaim the gospel with boldness?
Well, let me give you just a couple of thoughts
this evening.
If you're taking notes, number one,
I believe the apostle Paul understood the command of Christ,
the command of Christ.
You say, yeah, we know this.
We can rehearse the great commission.
Can I say this?
And with all sincerity,
knowing the great commission isn't the same
as fulfilling the great commission, amen?
Knowing, again, what I said,
as we've looked at this series here on Wednesday night,
knowing what we ought to do doesn't mean
we're actually doing what we ought to do.
And so the ability for us to quote the great commission,
to know the places within God's word
where the great commission is contained
does not mean that we personally are actively speaking,
proclaiming the gospel as we ought to be.
We find that there's, of course, the gospel,
the great commission is given in each book of the gospels,
Matthew, Mark, Luke, and John.
It's given in the book of Acts as well.
Probably the simplest form,
the one that is most widely memorized is Mark 16 and 15,
and we're to preach the gospel to every creature.
And we understand that.
We understand this evening the importance
of that portion of scripture and the simplicity
with regard to what Jesus says there.
And of course, he says it in different ways
in each of the gospels as is recorded for us,
but he says that we're to go into all the world
and preach the gospel to every creature.
Now, going into all the world starts
by just going across the street.
Is it not true?
I was speaking with someone yesterday
that was a freshman there at the college.
In fact, as we were in the hotel
and I was down and had some breakfast
and there weren't too many people down there
and a young man comes and he asked
if the seat was available and he sat there
and he opened his Bible and so I kind of assumed
that maybe he was preparing to go to the college
because he sat down and opened his Bible
and he was of that age and I inquired
and sure enough he's going to be studying
and he began to ask me questions and what have you
and I was sharing with him and I can't give you
all the details, it would take too long,
but the reality is one of the statements
that I made to him is that where we have
the privilege of ministering here in Northern Virginia
that literally the world is in our backyard
and we see that, we understand that,
we see how that the opportunities are before us
and truly sharing the gospel, proclaiming the gospel
begins by simply taking that step
and engaging with an individual.
You don't have to cross an ocean,
you don't have to get on an airplane or a boat
in order to go and proclaim the gospel to someone.
Acts 1.8, but you shall receive power
after that the Holy Ghost has come upon you
and you shall be witnesses unto me
both in Jerusalem, Judea, Samaria,
the uttermost part of the earth
and remember the disciple said this,
we are his witnesses.
We have it, that portion of Acts 5
is on the wall above our track rack
to remind us that we are his witnesses
and if we have the truth and I believe we do,
listen, if I didn't think it was true,
I'd just go do something different, right,
but I believe it's true and we have it
and therefore we ought to give it.
I want you to consider the life of Paul though
when we consider the command of Christ,
notice if you will over in Acts 26.
Notice what he's saying here,
he's standing before King Agrippa
in this closing section of the book of Acts,
we find that Paul has given his testimony
before several leaders and here he's standing
before Agrippa and others that are there,
Festus is going to tell him that he's crazy,
he's mad because he's there in the audience as well,
but notice in Acts 26 and verse 15,
the Apostle Paul is rehearsing his conversion testimony
and his experience of coming to Christ
as we read of it in Acts chapter nine
and I'm gonna pick it up in verse 15,
he says and I said, who art thou Lord?
And he said, I am Jesus whom thou persecutest.
But then notice verse 16, but rise and stand upon thy feet
for I have appeared unto thee for this purpose,
to make thee a minister and a witness
both of these things which thou hast seen
and of those things in the which I will appear unto thee,
delivering thee from the people and from the Gentiles
unto whom now I send thee to open their eyes
and to turn them from darkness to light
and from the power of Satan unto God
that they may receive forgiveness of sins
and inheritance among them,
which are sanctified by faith that is in me.
Isn't that a great mission that God communicated
to the Apostle Paul at this time in his life,
he saw, he's just converted, he says, who art thou Lord?
What wilt thou have me to do?
And we find that Jesus gives him this revelation,
he tells him that he's gonna send him
as a witness of these things.
He tells them that as he goes and he preaches,
it's going to be so that their eyes,
that they could be turned from darkness to light,
from the power of Satan unto God,
that they may receive forgiveness of sins.
This is what we get to do when we proclaim the gospel,
this is what we're doing,
we're giving somebody the greatest news.
I understand that sometimes they don't receive it that way,
but Paul understood this,
he understood the command of Christ.
I want you to notice, I stopped reading in verse 18,
but I want you to look at what it says in Acts 26,
in verse 19, look at what Paul says,
whereupon, O King Agrippa, notice what he says,
I was not disobedient unto the heavenly vision.
Paul considered this thought and this practice
of proclaiming the gospel a matter of obedience,
obedience to Christ, and he says to Agrippa,
I was not disobedient unto the heavenly vision.
He says it this way to the church in Corinth
in 1 Corinthians chapter nine,
he's speaking to them about the privilege
that he has to be involved in the gospel ministry,
and he says this in 1 Corinthians nine in verse 16,
for though I preach the gospel,
I have nothing to glory of,
for necessity is laid upon me, yea,
woe is unto me if I preach not the gospel.
And he says in verse 23, and this I do for the gospel's sake
that I might be partaker thereof with you.
I think about the apostle Paul
and a man that surrendered and yielded
to proclaiming the gospel,
but yet a man that when he submits a request for prayer
to the church at Ephesus,
what is it that he requests prayer for?
That he would have boldness,
that he would open his mouth to speak with boldness
as he ought to speak.
Wow.
He understood the command of Christ.
Not only do I believe that the apostle Paul
understood the command of Christ,
number two, I believe that the apostle Paul
understood the certainty of eternity.
See, for us this evening,
if we're going to come to this place
that we would preach and proclaim the gospel as we ought to,
that we would say as the apostle Paul
that I may open my mouth boldly
to make known the mystery of the gospel,
that I would speak as I ought to speak,
that we understand the command of Christ,
but we also must understand the certainty of eternity.
The wise man said in Ecclesiastes 12 in verse number five
that man goes to his long home.
I shared with someone recently,
and I said, listen, no matter how many years we live
here upon this earth,
it's really only that long in light of eternity.
We sometimes think about, oh man, 70, 80, 90, 100 years,
it's such a long time, not compared to eternity.
It's just that long.
What is your life?
It's but a vapor that appears for a little time
and then vanisheth away.
It's like a shadow.
How long does your shadow stick around?
Not long, not long.
And so we find that the wise man,
he says that man goes to his long home.
Hebrews nine in verse 17 says,
as is appointed unto man wants to die, but what?
After this, the judgment.
So we believe this evening in the certainty of eternity,
do we not?
Every single person that I come into contact with,
every single person that you come into contact with
is going to have an eternity somewhere.
We believe that.
Biblically, we believe that.
The Bible teaches us,
and we'll look at it from our perspective
with regard to save people first
in 2 Corinthians chapter number five.
See, Paul understood this.
Why is it that he says,
as I have an opportunity to submit a request for prayer
to these believers at Ephesus,
what is it that I'm gonna ask them to pray for me?
Well, he says that I would speak as I ought to speak
the gospel with boldness.
This evening, he understood the command of Christ,
but he understood the certainty of eternity.
Notice in 2 Corinthians chapter number five,
he begins the chapter by saying, for we know.
There's some things that we know, amen,
because God has revealed them to us.
There's a lot of people that you can talk to
that you can go around this room and say,
well, nothing can be certain.
No, no, no, there are some things that can be certain.
There are some things that we know,
and we can be assured of, and we can have confidence in,
and we can stand on them, and we can speak with authority,
not because we are the authority,
but because God is the authority.
And we find that in 2 Corinthians five,
he begins in verse number one, for we know.
Notice as we skip through the passage,
look at verse number four, he says,
for we that are in this tabernacle do groan,
being burdened, not for that we would be unclothed,
but clothed upon that mortality
might be swallowed up of life.
I love 2 Corinthians five four,
and the verbiage that God uses
in how mortality will be swallowed up of life.
It's like the verse of scripture, no doubt,
had an impact and an influence on D.L. Moody
when he said, when you read that I'm dead,
just remember that I'm more alive than I've ever been.
Why?
Because mortality will be swallowed up of life.
He says in verse number eight, for we are confident,
I say, and willing rather to be absent from the body
and to be present with the Lord.
He tells them in 1 Thessalonians chapter four,
that I'm giving you this by the word of the Lord.
He's teaching them about the rapture,
and he's teaching them about the certainty of the rapture
and the eternity that we'll have,
those that are saved by the grace of God
that we will have with our Savior,
and so shall we ever be with the Lord.
Aren't those wonderful words?
In fact, they're followed up with these words,
wherefore, comfort one another with these words.
And so Paul had an understanding of the command of.
And by the way, that's the priority, the order that I'm giving you these thoughts this evening,
not that the list that I'll provide you with tonight is an exhaustive list on why we ought to proclaim the gospel,
but three thoughts on why we ought to proclaim the gospel.
But our number one motivation ought to be to obey Christ.
That we could stand before someone like Paul stood before Agrippa and say,
I was not disobedient unto the heavenly vision.
No, I didn't have a heavenly vision like Paul did, and neither did you,
but I had a revelation that's recorded in God's word that I have a personal responsibility,
and so do you, to proclaim the gospel.
And by the way, Paul is bound at this point, he's going to go and have to appeal to Caesar and all that's taking place,
and Caesar said, what have you, because of what? Because he's preached the gospel.
But he says, I've not been disobedient to the command of Christ.
But then we see the certainty of eternity that everyone that we know is going to spend forever somewhere.
So we find for the believer the confidence that we have in heaven, Revelation chapter 20.
We're familiar with the passage of scripture, it's a sad portion of scripture.
I do not enjoy reading the last of several verses of Revelation chapter 20.
I'll just read verses 14 and 15 this evening,
but it's a sad section of God's word that describes for us the great white throne judgment.
The Bible says in verse 14, in death and hell, we're cast in the lake of fire, this is the second death.
And whosoever is not found written in the book of life was cast into the lake of fire.
We have to come to a place where we truly believe what God says in his word,
and allow it to impact our behavior with regard to the subject of proclaiming the gospel.
See, mankind, humanity, they have one of two destinations for eternity.
Heaven or the lake of fire.
We believe that this evening.
The Bible plainly teaches that.
The Bible does not teach, as some denominations teach, as some organizations teach,
that there's some holding place, there's some in-between place,
that if you weren't quite good enough, you can kind of spend some time there
so that you can be refined enough to be able to go to heaven,
or so that your loved ones might be able to pray or really to pay for you to be able to...
No, that's not what the Bible teaches.
The Bible's very plain that there's just one of two eternal destinations for humanity.
And when we truly understand the command of Christ, we ought to proclaim the gospel.
When we understand the certainty of eternity, we ought to proclaim the gospel.
Number three, when we understand the condition of humanity.
The condition of humanity.
What do I mean by that?
You mean, pastor, that the society today is real bad?
Listen, mankind's been real bad for 6,000 years.
I mean, listen, if you go back, I understand that oftentimes we will say something like this.
It's never been as bad as it is today.
And the problem with that statement is we really don't know history.
Because the reality is that the world was so bad
that God destroyed it with a flood in Genesis chapter 6.
Sodom and Gomorrah were so wicked that God rained fire and brimstone upon them.
There are periods of time throughout Israel's history, as you can read,
just in the historical content that God gives us in the Bible of great periods of wickedness,
of offering their children to false gods on altars.
I mean, just wickedness.
I understand that because of the era in which we're living
and because of the availability to news and so on and so forth,
that it just seems like it's just worse than it's ever been.
And certainly things are getting worse and worse.
But it didn't just happen in this generation that mankind became depraved.
Amen?
We believe that mankind is born sinners.
And that's the condition of humanity.
The condition of humanity.
Romans 3 and verse number 10, as it is written,
there's none righteous, no, not one, for all have sinned
and come short of the glory of God.
Verse 10 and verse 23, we are familiar with these verses of Scripture.
In fact, if we were to ask this evening, can you quote some of these verses,
many of us could quote these verses.
We know them, we're familiar with them, we believe them.
But the reality is that at some point the belief of those verses
have to impact the behavior of God's people.
Romans 5 and verse number 12, a verse that we're familiar with
with regard to the entrance of sin into the world
and how sin passes from one generation to the next.
It says,
Wherefore, as by one man sin entered into the world, and death by sin,
and so death passed upon all men, for that all have sinned.
So we find this evening that there's this condition of humanity.
Notice how Paul explains it to the believers in Ephesus and Ephesians,
chapter number 2, as Paul is giving to them this truth
with regard to the condition of humanity.
And for us to be able to recognize that we were in the same boat,
we were in the same condition, and now we're simply saved by the grace of God.
In Ephesians chapter 2, in verse number 1, Paul says this,
And you hath he quickened, who were dead in trespasses and sins,
wherein in time past ye walked according to the course of this world,
according to the prince of the power of the air,
the spirit that now worketh in the children of disobedience,
among whom also we all had our conversation in times past.
How many of us? We all had our conversation in times past.
This was our condition.
And so it says,
In the lust of our flesh, fulfilling the desires of the flesh and of the mind,
and were by nature the children of wrath, even as others.
As we begin to think about the truth of Ephesians chapter 6
and the request that Paul makes,
and in this request revealing to us what we ought to be doing,
because no doubt if Paul understood that he ought to be proclaiming the gospel,
then every child of God ought to recognize that we too should be proclaiming the gospel.
How is it that we proclaim the gospel?
Well, it's varied.
As a church, we have organized times of being able to go out and share the gospel.
And why is it that we have organized times of being able to share the gospel?
Why is it as a church that we have these Saturday mornings
and we go out and we use maps and we try to reach our community?
Well, we want to with purpose and on purpose and systematically and strategically,
we want to reach our community with the gospel.
We want to be in a place where this is, as we often use the analogy,
our church is a beacon of hope, is a light in this community.
By the way, there's a lot of hurting people in our community.
There are people every day that are dealing with disease,
they're dealing with divorce, they're dealing with just various levels of dispute
and the number of calls that our law enforcement receive on domestic violence
is so regular in our society, in our community.
The number of attempts in our community of suicide is alarming.
You say, no, not in Fairfax County. Absolutely in Fairfax County.
A lot of people that can make things look pretty nice on the outside,
but the reality is that they need Christ.
And God's placed us here as a light.
We know that the enemy seeks to deceive and to keep blinded,
but God's people need to have this understanding that Paul has
as he communicates to the believers in Ephesus,
and we this evening need to come to the place where we say,
you know what, I ought to proclaim the gospel.
As a church, we want to systematically and strategically share the gospel.
We have gospel tracts available in our tract rack.
Every time that you come in and go out of our sanctuary,
the opportunity to take gospel tracts so that you can have a place
and being able to share the gospel with someone.
There are unique ways. We dealt with it on Sunday nights just a few months ago
with regard to how to share our personal testimonies
and the opportunities that God gives.
And we've got to be purposed in it because we understand these truths.
We understand that we've been given a command.
We've been given a command.
When a command is given, there's really only two options,
obedience or disobedience.
There's really no middle ground.
God. We understand the certainty of eternity, that every person that we come in contact
with is going to spend forever in one of two places. And the condition of humanity reveals
to us that most of those that we come in contact with, because of understanding the statistics,
they've never even heard the gospel, that means most people are still lost and therefore
on their way to the Christless eternity in the lake of fire. And as we understand these
truths, see, I said this to someone recently, I said, you know, I have zero desire, I don't
want to see anyone go to the lake of fire. Listen, if we truly understand tonight, these
three simple truths, how could we look at anyone and not have a desire to share with
them truth? Why? Because they're not going to believe us? It's okay. Jesus said just
shake off the dust and go to the next person. Our job is not for whether or not they believe
us. Our job is not for how they view us. Ron and I were knocking doors and we were in the
neighborhood over there where Magnus and Alexis live and we're knocking doors and so we purposefully
knocked on Alexis's door. Why? Because man, at least somebody's going to be nice to us this
morning. Amen. And we knocked on her door and she answered and she sure enough, she was gracious and
nice. And she said to Ron and I, she said, now did you guys go to this house over here? And she kind
of told us what house she was talking to. She's like, because I've really been trying to work on
that. And I said, well, no, we haven't gotten there yet, but that's going to kind of be our last stop
and where we parked and where we started the kind of that's where we're going to end. And we go over
there and Ron, if you remember, that was kind of the worst door of the day. But it doesn't mean we
don't continue to go because our job is not on how they respond. Our job is on whether we proclaim
the gospel. That individual can kind of slam the door in our face and kind of throw up his hands
as he did. Like, I can't believe you're here from the church. But one day he's going to stand before
God. But one day I'm going to stand before God. And according to the book of Ezekiel, the watchman
doesn't give an account for whether the people respond to the warning. He gives an account on
whether he gave the warning. And I believe that's what Paul is referencing in Ephesians chapter,
or excuse me, Acts chapter 20. When he's talking to those leaders of the church at Ephesus,
he makes at least two, maybe more, but obviously two direct comments that correspond to the truth
from the book of Ezekiel with being a watchman. Paul knew the Old Testament. He was aware of the
truth that God had communicated, and he knows that the watchman, if he does not warn, then he's
responsible. But if the watchman warns, he's not responsible for the response of those warned. So
Paul says, what am I doing? I'm warning every man night and day with tears for a space of three
years. But yet when he writes to the church at Ephesus, he says, would you pray for me that
utterance may be given unto me that I may open my mouth boldly to make known the mystery of the
gospel for which I am an ambassador and bonds that therein I may speak boldly as I ought to speak.
This evening, I don't think any one of us, any one of you would disagree that we ought to proclaim
the gospel. It's our duty. Very practically, if we don't tell, if we don't proclaim the gospel,
who's going to? We can't, we can't, look, the false teachers, the false world religions,
I'm thankful that there are some other churches, even here in Fairfax County,
that preach the gospel. Many of those churches, the pastors are friends, and I thank the Lord
for them. But you know what the statistics would tell us here in Fairfax County? The last time I
looked at the population of our county, coupled with the number of churches in our county that
preach the gospel that I'm aware of. Now, I understand there may be some that are preaching
the gospel that I don't know, I'm not aware of the church and what have you, but that I'm aware
of doing some research, the ones that are preaching the gospel, that if every church in our county
reached 10,000 people a year, the churches that I know of that are proclaiming the gospel, it would
take us about 11 years to reach everybody in our county one time. You know what the reality is?
We're not reaching 10,000 people every year, and most of those other churches aren't reaching
10,000 people every year either. But 10,000 people a year, it still takes 11, you know how many people
in our county are going to die in 11 years? If we don't tell them, who will? We ought to proclaim
the gospel. Number one, there's a command. Number two, there's the certainty of eternity. And number
three, there's the condition of humanity. Let's pray together. Father, we love you. Thank you for
loving us. Thank you for giving us the opportunity to be your representatives, your ambassadors. I
pray God that you would use us, help us to have a renewed commitment to obey this great commission
that you've given to us. Help us to speak with boldness, help us to proclaim the gospel. We
thank you for the privilege of prayer. I pray that you would bless the remainder of our service,
for it's in Christ's name we pray. Amen. Does anyone need a prayer bulletin this evening?