of the faith and I'll say this it is obviously a smaller room and so you
sound better singing over here amen and what a blessing and we're thankful for
the opportunity the book of Acts this morning and we're gonna be in Acts
chapter number 12 Acts chapter number 12 this morning and this past week I know
for many of us has been an extremely busy week and I understand that we're
busy people generally speaking there's a lot going on in our lives we live in one
of the busiest places in America and just seems like always going and coming
and sorts all sorts of things going on but some weeks at times just seem to be
a little extra busy than normal and of course starting the renovation project
and various things going on memorial service and what have you just an
extremely busy week and in times of busyness we have to be more purposed
with our schedules in times of busyness we have to be more purposed with our
schedules perhaps something gets rescheduled or perhaps something gets
canceled altogether and in the midst of the busyness and especially this week
the Lord graciously reminded me of the priority of prayer because sometimes if
we're not careful in the midst of busyness we begin to remove things that
ought not be removed amen and in the midst of all of that God just graciously
reminded me of the priority of prayer in fact someone wisely stated this there is
nothing on your calendar today more important than prayer there is nothing
on your calendar today more important than prayer through this the Lord led me
to Acts chapter number 12 and to look at this portion of scripture and there's
times in which I've said over the years of the way in which a song will match so
perfectly with the message and how the Lord orchestrates all of that and God did
something this week that gave some confirmation with the subject of prayer
and Holly makes the bulletins each week and she puts in the bulletins and she
gives it to me for review and what have you and this week again because of her
traveling and all the things going on she had the bulletin basically ready
without the sermon titles and the songs for today she had everything else ready
to go and I sent her an email and she was sitting over there on the other side
of the office and she got the sermon titles and she started laughing and she
said I love it when God works that way and if you noticed in the bulletin today
on the right hand side let us pray for each other and that little picture and
image there she has never used in a church bulletin until this week so it
was not just a use that it was something that recycled or what have you is the
first time and that was just an encouragement to me and I hope an
encouragement to you as well as you look there in the bulletin and we look at
Acts chapter 12 I'm simply titled the message this morning a praying church a
praying church we find here in Acts chapter 12 and I want to just look at
two verses and then we'll look at the entire text as we get through the
message today but in verse number five the Bible says Peter therefore was kept
in prison but then notice the end of verse number five it says but prayer was
made without ceasing of the church unto God for him in verse number 12 of Acts
12 the Bible says and when he that's Peter had considered the thing he came
to the house of Mary the mother of John whose surname was Mark where many were
gathered together praying the subject of prayer is such an important subject in
fact I've shared with people over the years that prayer is work prayer you're
engaging in serious spiritual warfare when you get engaged in prayer why
because the enemy doesn't want us to pray the enemy knows that prayer moves
the hand of God the enemy understands the importance and the priority on
prayer and we find that prayer is work prayer requires us to be purposed it
requires us to put a priority on prayer and to understand the importance and we
read through the scriptures and we have so many wonderful promises that God has
given to us with regard to prayer and the invitation and what he's capable of
doing but I'm sad to report that oftentimes prayer is neglected by God's
people in fact as you look through the scriptures you begin to understand the
significance of prayer you begin to study some of the prayers of those that
are recorded in the scriptures man it's encouraging to see how the people of God
got serious about seeking the face of God and then had the privilege of seeing
the hand of God respond to the prayers of his people awesome we always have
hope because there's God you look at circumstances you look at situations
and you think that it's so dim and so difficult but God and I'm thankful that
we have the privilege of prayer as we begin looking at this portion of
scripture I'm actually going to go all the way back to Acts chapter 1 and the
first thought this morning if you're taking notes number one the pattern
established the pattern established I want you to understand that the first
century church was a praying church the first century church was a praying
church we find that there are many times today that people are saying hey we need
to become a 21st century church and we have all sorts of activities and all
sorts of programs and various things that fill our calendars but the reality
is that prayer is essential we can mark off a lot of things from our church
calendar from our personal calendar there are things that we can remove in
their things that we can cancel but we must not neglect the area of prayer we
find in Acts chapter 1 notice if you will after the ascension of the Lord
Jesus Christ we find in verse number 14 that the Bible says this these all
continued with one accord in prayer and supplication with the women and Mary the
mother of James and with his brethren we find here after Jesus ascended to
heaven that they get together and they come to that room and they're they're
praying in chapter number two in verse number 42 the Bible tells us after the
day of Pentecost and after the 3,000 professed faith in the Lord Jesus Christ
and they were baptized follow the Lord and believers baptism the Bible says in
verse number 42 and they continued steadfastly in the Apostles doctrine and
fellowship and in breaking of bread and in prayers we find that the early church
the first century church was a praying church in chapter number four they're
facing some difficulties they're facing some persecution they're facing some
threats and we find that they've been commanded to no longer speak the name of
Jesus but Jesus had told them go ye into all the world and preach the gospel to
every creature and we find that after they heard the threats and they heard
all that was taking place and after they had endured some hardship we find that
in Acts 4 in verse 23 it says in being let go they went to their own company
and reported all that the chief priest and elders had said unto them and when
they heard that notice what it says they lifted up their voice to God with one
accord and said Lord thou art God which has made heaven and earth and the sea
and all that in them is and you can continue reading there and see the
prayer of that early church in response to the the difficulty in which they were
facing and what am I saying here this morning I'm saying that the early church
was a praying church there's a pattern that's established we've read a couple
of verses in chapter number 12 notice in chapter 13 when the church in Antioch is
there and God is working but God is going to move and call and separate and
there's going to be the first missionary journey and the gospel going forward
through those means we find the Bible tells us in Acts 13 in verse number 2 as
they ministered to the Lord and fasted the Holy Ghost said separate me Barnabas
and Saul for the work we're into I have called them and when they had fasted and
prayed and laid their hands on them they sent them away you could continue to
read through the book of Acts and you can find the first century church was a
praying church you can find that as the Apostle Paul is writing to those that he
ministered to whether it's a church or an individual that Paul often not only
shares with them how he's praying for them but he also requests that they
would pray for him we find in first Thessalonians chapter 5 it says it very
simply this way
Brethren, pray for us.
There are other times in which the Apostle Paul
gives more specific details with regard
to the matter in which he's desiring
the individuals to pray for them.
The word of the Lord would have free course
that he mentioned some specific prayer requests,
but we find that very generically he says,
brethren, pray for us.
The first century church, the first century believers,
they believed in prayer.
And there is a pattern that is established.
And why is it that I seek to establish this truth
this morning before we enter into Acts 12?
Because I want you to understand something very important.
In Acts chapter number 12,
they didn't pray because of the problem.
They were a praying church, amen?
You know what happens often is we pray
because we have a problem.
Something happens in your life,
something happens in my life,
something goes awry, it doesn't go like we planned
or we thought, we get that phone call,
that bad news, whatever it may be,
and all of a sudden we say, you know, we should pray.
They don't pray simply because of the problem.
Now, yes, they pray because there's a problem,
but they were a praying church.
It wasn't something that was new to them.
It wasn't something that was odd for them.
No, they were a praying church.
We find that as we come to Acts chapter number 12
and we see that there's this pattern established
that the first century church was a praying church,
we find as we look at the text here,
the peril explained, number two, the peril explained.
We find as we begin reading in Acts chapter 12,
the Bible says in verse one,
now about that time Herod the king
stretched forth his hands to vex certain of the church.
And so we find right in the beginning
of reading this chapter in verse number one
that Herod, this man that had some power,
he had limited power, but he had some power,
and we find that he has this power,
and the Bible says that he stretched forth his hands
to vex, the word means to oppress,
it means to afflict, it means to harm.
This is ill intent, this is what this man Herod
is seeking to do, he's lifting up,
stretching forth his hands to vex certain of the church.
The Bible continues to tell us in verse number two
that he killed James the brother of John with the sword.
It's pretty serious.
Time of great peril.
We find that the church is facing this persecution,
and by the way, it's nothing new for God's people
to face persecution.
It's nothing new for God's people to face opposition.
And we find here in the text of scripture
that this behavior of Herod,
the Bible tells us that it pleased the Jews.
We find that he raises, he stretches forth his hands
to vex certain of the church,
and he kills James the brother of John with the sword,
but then in verse three it says,
and because he saw, Herod observed the response
of the people to what he did,
and the Bible says because he saw it pleased the Jews.
It pleased the Jews.
And so what does he do?
Well, the Bible tells us in verse number three
that he proceeded further to take Peter also.
The Bible says then were the days of unleavened bread,
and when he had apprehended him, he put him in prison,
delivered him to four quartarians of soldiers to keep him.
Notice what it says,
intending after Easter to bring him forth to the people.
He was gonna kill him.
That's what he was gonna do.
The peril is explained to us.
We begin to look at the situation,
we begin to notice what's taking place here
in these verses of scripture,
and begin to see the seriousness
of what God's people are facing.
And we understand that God is sovereign,
but God has allowed these things
that we read in Acts chapter number 12 to unfold.
He allows his people to face this opposition
that they're facing.
And we look at the text and we see what's taking place,
and you say, why?
Why is it happening this way?
Why is it that this man is able to have
this kind of power and authority?
Why is it that God's people are suffering?
Listen, we're engaged in spiritual battle.
We are engaged in spiritual battle.
Amen?
Some of these same Jews here were the ones
that obviously descendants of,
and even some of the very people that probably cried out,
crucify him, speaking of the Lord Jesus Christ.
You understand that there's an enemy.
The enemy's alive and well.
Now, the enemy doesn't have unlimited power,
but we do have an enemy.
And it's interesting, hold your place here,
but look in Ephesians chapter six, if you will,
and in Ephesians chapter number six,
we often speak of, and we should,
about the armor of God,
and putting on the whole armor of God,
and being strong in the Lord, and the power of his might,
and we understand that we wrestle not
against flesh and blood,
and those are all important truths
that we understand from Ephesians chapter number six.
But after the Lord, through Paul,
has Paul pen these words,
and he goes through each of the pieces of armor,
you find that it ends in verse 18,
this way, praying always,
with all prayer and supplication in the spirit,
and watching thereunto with all perseverance
and supplication for all saints.
Every one of us, as we come together as an assembly,
brothers and sisters in Christ,
but then we leave this place and we go our separate ways,
and we're facing a battle.
We're facing the opposition,
and we need to not only be prayed up ourselves,
but we need to have our brothers and sisters in Christ
praying on our behalf,
because we do have an enemy.
We are engaged in spiritual warfare.
This is not a playground.
Have you found that to be the case?
It's not a playground, it's a battleground.
There is evil,
and evil, it seems at times that it's prevailing.
You ever think that way?
Listen, God is on his throne.
Don't get discouraged.
Don't let up your hope and think, oh, it's no, no, no, no.
God's on his throne, and by the way,
not only is he on his throne,
but he told us what to expect in these last days.
He informed us so that we would understand
the things that we would encounter
and the oppositions in which we would endure,
and he provided us with that information.
He instructed us with how to deal with it.
On the heels of telling us that evil men and seducers
shall wax worse and worse,
deceiving and being deceived, he says, but continue thou.
But continue thou.
I mean, keep on going.
Keep on serving the Lord, why?
Because we are on the winning side.
Because victory in Jesus is true, amen?
Because we have a God who hears and answers prayer.
We have a God who is able to do exceeding abundantly
above all that we ask or think,
and we find that God has given to us
this great privilege of prayer,
and we need to be a praying church.
It's important that we pray personally,
but it's important that we come together corporately
and we pray as a church, as a body, as a family.
Prayer, prayer's important.
In fact, Paul says it this way as he's writing to Timothy,
if you notice over in the book of 1 Timothy,
in chapter number two, in 1 Timothy chapter number two,
in verse number one, the Bible says this.
I exhort therefore that, tell me those next three words.
First of all.
Now what does that mean to you?
Kind of an order of priority?
Yeah, is that how you would take it?
He says, I exhort therefore that first of all,
supplications, prayers, intercessions,
and giving of thanks be made for all men,
for kings, and for all that are in authority,
that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life
in all godliness and honesty.
And then it says in verse three,
for this is good and acceptable
in the sight of God our Savior.
First of all, sometimes we just complain.
Amen?
First of all, we complain about those in leadership.
We complain about those things that are going on around us.
But the Holy Spirit of God moved Paul to write,
I exhort therefore that first of all,
supplication, prayer.
intercessions and giving of thanks be made for all men. I'll be honest with you
this morning if we're honest with God most of us are guilty of disobeying this
portion of Scripture. A praying church, a praying church. I've noted already I said
it to you in the in the last point when we established the or we noticed the
pattern that's established there throughout the book of Acts the early
church the first century church was a praying church it wasn't the crisis that
led them to pray oh yeah they prayed about that but they were praying church
they believed in the power of prayer they had seen God answer prayer and by
the way the more you pray the more you will pray why is that because you see
God work you see God answer you see God respond and guess what that does it
encouraged you to keep on praying you say I don't when you when you read the
Bible when you get something out of the Bible when God speaks to you and shows
you something what do you want to do you want to read it more not less right
because God's speaking to you God's working and God's revealing truth and
the Spirit of God is is communing with your spirit and leading you into all
truth and you you want more not less I see God answer and I want to pray more
why because God is able and God can and God will we see God work the natural
response for these people in Acts chapter 12 I believe as we look at the
pattern in those few verses that we look to the natural response for them was to
pray it was to pray when you looked at in Acts chapter 4 it's interesting
because when they prayed in Acts chapter 4 they did not pray that God would deal
with those religious leaders by by punishing them by doing it no they just
prayed that God would give them boldness they told us not to speak and so God
give us boldness to speak hallelujah that's how we ought to pray look at it
if you will back in Acts chapter 12 we see the pattern established we see the
peril explained but then we see number 3 this morning the that God's power is
explained God's power is demonstrated the Bible tells us in verses 3 and 4
what Herod did with Peter and Peter obviously had a prominent role in the
church and we understand that this man Herod was intending to kill him and we
look in verse number 5 and the Bible says Peter therefore was kept in prison
but God tells us what the other believers were doing but prayer was made
without ceasing of the church unto God for him Wow they had a prayer meeting
have you ever been part of an all-night prayer meeting it was a thing of
yesteryear it was a thing that happened often I still have preacher friends that
in their churches they have all-night prayer meetings it's not a bad thing
it's a good thing but it's something that's kind of faded away and it's kind
of been replaced with all sorts of other things on our calendars we begin to look
and we understand that here the Bible says that prayer was made notice where
it says without ceasing we understand the timing as we look here at the text
of Scripture because Peter's gonna be sleeping here in just a few moments and
as you look through what's happening and you see where the the church is
assembled in and I get it that those all-night prayer meetings they can be
difficult they can be challenging as your body you're trying to be
disciplined to be engaged in prayer when your body wants to sleep and whatever
else is going on but we see that there was a matter here that required that
they get a hold of God the early church did not come together and say okay
what's the plan what are we gonna do to break Peter out hey Bart you got some
tools go get those things and Ron you go get this thing over here and you get
no they just prayed they weren't trying to figure out how they could do
something why because they acknowledge that they could do nothing they could do
nothing but pray and let me say this that's the greatest thing they could do
but sometimes we have that wrong perspective all I can do is pray as if
it's insignificant as if it doesn't matter as if it here's the deal someone
said this prayer is not an escape from our responsibility no prayer is our
response to God's ability now think about that prayer is not an escape from
responsibility it's not a situation that we take this oh I'm just gonna pray
about it as if it's I'm not taking my responsibility to escape from my
responsibility no it's how I respond to God's ability and here's a real question
for us as we examine our own hearts and our own prayer lives is really this how
big is God could I submit to you this morning that your prayer life and my
prayer life truly reveals how big we think God is what's on your prayer list
what's on my prayer list that that is something that only God can do that
would it reveal the faith that we have in God's ability because our prayer is a
response to God's ability the Bible tells us in verse number five that
they're praying and verse number six notice the Bible says this and when
Herod would have brought him forth the same night Peter was sleeping between
two soldiers bound with two chains and the keepers before the door kept the
prison do you see the length in which they went through to make sure Peter
wasn't getting out I mean it's pretty amazing isn't it when you think about
Herod and the Jews and all the the the folks there that would have this
perspective and they they had him there he was sleeping between two soldiers he
was bound with two chains and then there's keepers at the door of the
prison they're trying to keep that thing sure they're trying to make sure
that Peter's not getting out you know what Peter's doing Peter sleeping it's a
whole nother message but that's the peace of God that's the peace of God
that passeth all understanding to be in the midst of something like that and
just go ahead and go to sleep I think the song anywhere with Jesus and one of
the verses says anywhere with Jesus I can go to sleep amen and every time we
sing that song I think of Acts 12 and Peter sleeping between a couple of
soldiers and the Bible tells us that it was that night Herod was gonna bring
them forth and in verse 7 notice it says behold the angel of the Lord came upon
him Oh God's about to do something miraculous God's about to work in a way
that only God could get the glory God is responding to what we read at the end of
verse number five that prayer was made without ceasing of the church and to God
for him and they're praying and God is working and God sends an angel by the
way the angels have great power 175 85,000 I think it was that were killed
there during the situation with Hezekiah in one night I mean amazing and we find
here that God is going to send an angel the Bible says an angel of the Lord came
upon him and a light shined in the prison and notice what it says he smote
Peter on the side that always makes me laugh Peter was sleeping good man I mean
he was sleeping he has sound asleep and the Bible says that this angel of the
Lord smote him on the side raised him up and here's what he said arise up quickly
and here's the first miracle and his chains fell off from his hands now think
about it I mean these chains they obviously were used in this capacity for
you know keeping prisoners and they were no doubt well-made and they made sure
that they were in good condition before they used them but God the Bible says
the chains they just fell off from his hands did you imagine I mean Peter has
to come to himself he thinks he's seeing a vision as we keep reading here through
the passage but the notice the Bible says the angel said unto him gird thyself
in verse number 8 bind on thy sandals why is he girding himself why is he
binding on his hands because they're getting ready to get out of there and
they would gird their loins as they were getting ready to go somewhere and
especially when they were going with haste and the Bible says gird thyself
and put on bind thy sandals and so he did and he say then to him cast thy
garment about thee and follow me and he went out and followed him and wist not
that it was true which was done by the angel but thought he saw a vision oh it
was true Peter was getting out of there because God was working because God was
responding to prayer because his people responded to the ability that they knew
God had and that's chapter number four when they prayed
And we looked at that we didn't look at the whole prayer, but they begin praying and they start out their prayer by praying
Acknowledging the fact that our God is creator
He said let there be light and there was light I
Talked to a man yesterday, and I asked him if he had a church that he attended
He said no my wife goes to the Methodist Church, but I don't go to church
And I said oh man, that's unfortunate, and I I knew he was from somewhere else
I didn't know where he was from and I said well
What's your background, and he said I'm from the west part of Indian
I said that's great and begin to chat with them, and he said well. I'm an atheist
And I said really and he said yeah
And he was a younger fella
And he was very I just felt the Spirit of the Lord giving me Liberty to have
Conversation with them, and I said now listen you seem like a smart guy I
Said you got an Apple watch on your wrist right there. How'd that thing get made you said well somebody made it
I said really I said looks like you're going to your car
How'd that thing come together? He said well somebody made it. I said and you think that we just evolved and
He just kind of looked at me
And I said what do you do for a living he said well, I'm a computer programmer
I said really I said so you write code
He said well
I kind of manage people now, but I used to I said well
Why don't the computers just do it themselves why didn't it just happen and he just looked at me?
And I said sir. I said do you really believe that?
There's no God
you really believe that this all just
Happened as intricate as we are
The design of humanity
the design of the planet where we're located and just a
Little further from the Sun and we'd freeze a little closer to the Sun and we'd burn up
I mean you think about all of these things listen. It's not some random chance. We serve the Creator God
And that's how they approached him in Acts chapter number four they said when they lifted up their voice
they said thou Lord thou art God which has made heaven and
Earth and the sea and all that in them is
Listen when we understand the truth of who we serve and we understand his ability it changes our prayers
Because God is able God is able
So we find that as we come back to Acts 12 and look at verse 10 Peter again in verse number 9
He thought he saw a vision, but as they continue there
It says and when verse 10 they were past the first and second Ward
They came under the iron gate that leadeth under the city now understand this word Ward
This word Ward it means a guard or a watch it's people persons that are keeping watch
That's what it is. So they come to the first but not just to the first and then to the second
So how many there were some soldiers in the cell?
there were some soldiers outside of the cell there was a ward and then there's a second Ward and
Peters Gerd on his loins and put on his sandals and he's walking out
It's pretty awesome
That's the God we serve
He's able
And we find that the Bible says in
Verse number 10 as we continue reading there
They come to that iron gate that leadeth under the city notice where it says which open to them of his own accord. I
I
Mean God just had that thing open up. Can you imagine I mean, this is awesome
The Bible says
That they went out and passed on through one Street and forthwith the angel departed from him
Verse 11 when Peter was come to himself
I don't know if you ever have those moments in your life where you kind of come to yourself
Something's happening you just kind of I mean Peter's in this situation and he's like it's real like and I mean he's standing there now
He's not in the prison anymore. The angel of the Lord's departed and he stand there no more chains on him
He's he's able to go forth and the Bible says that when he has come to himself
He said now I know of a surety
that the Lord has sent his angel and hath delivered me out of the hand of Herod and from all the
Expectation of the people of the Jews. What did Peter acknowledge? Well immediately when he came to himself
He acknowledged God did it
By the way, that's how God wants to work
God always wants to work in such a way that the only thing we can say is God did it
Gideon as an example
If I give you the victory
With that number of people you're gonna think it's because of your might that you got the victory, right?
So I'm gonna dwindle it down. Anyone want to go home go home
Bunch of people left
Gideon you still have too many actually God. I'm really outnumbered. I mean that was the reality of it
But God said I'm gonna give you victory with how many with 300
So that no one
Could misunderstand that it was God who gave the victory and we notice here
that after Peter acknowledges and he says I know of a surety I love that phraseology because
There's this confidence that Peter has that God did this
That God was working and the Bible says that when he had considered the thing
So, I don't know how long he's standing there and I don't know how long he's considering the thing
But for however long it is he's considering what's transpired
And the Bible says that he came to the house of Mary the mother of John
Whose surname was Mark where many were gathered together
Praying so all of a sudden Peter shows up to the very house where the prayer meetings taking place
He comes to the very house where the Bible told us in verse number five
That prayer was made without ceasing of the church unto God for him and they're there praying and as they're praying
They don't know that God's already delivered. They don't know that God's already answered
They don't know that God has already worked, but they're just praying
And Peter shows up exactly where they're praying
The Bible says in verse 13 and as Peter knocked at the door at the gate a damsel came to hearken
Named Rhoda now again, there's some pretty hilarious parts of this text of Scripture
And here's another one of them and this one Rhoda she comes and the Bible says in verse 14
When she knew Peter's voice now, there's some people that you know their voice
Amen you hear somebody speak. Sometimes people have very distinct voices and sometimes they can be a little bit like man
Is that so-and-so or so, you know, maybe maybe got but man
There's a a distinction that some people have in their voice and here this one Rhoda
She knew that it was Peter's voice and he's knocking
Now the Bible tells us in verse 14 that she opened off the gate for gladness
That she opened off the gate for gladness now again, let him in. No. No, she's so excited
She opened it not for gladness and she runs back in the Bible says she ran in now that reveals to me something about her
excitement
Amen, you think about those?
Folks that were there at the the the empty tomb they ran they had gladness
They had joy and we find here that she runs in and the Bible says that she told how Peter stood
before the gate
Verse 15 it says that they said unto her thou art mad the word mad means crazy
Thou art mad
They were praying
But they lacked some faith
Some of them did
Some of them lacked faith on
Wednesdays, we've been talking about this thing of faith and doubt and all that we've gone through in 2026 and looking at all of this
importance of living by faith and
That man that Jesus said if thou remember he came and he said if thou can't do anything
have compassion on us and help us and
Jesus said if thou can't believe all things are possible
To them that believe and that man said I believe help thou
mine unbelief
He was honest. He was transparent. By the way, the Lord already knew that
Amen, God already knows
And so here we find that the Bible says that they said thou art mad, but she verse 15
Constantly affirmed that it was even so then said they it is his angel and
All the while. Here's what Peter's doing
It's hilarious
She runs in and she says Peter's here. No, you're mad. You're crazy, and she's constantly affirming
No, I know it's Peter. I heard his voice
Okay, we're not gonna convince her that she didn't hear his voice. So we'll just tell her it's his angel
And all the while Peter's knocking the Bible says in verse 16
But Peter continued knocking and when they had opened the door and saw him notice where it says they were
astonished
When's the last time
When's the last time God's astonished you with an answer to prayer?
I mean literally, you saw God do what only God could do.
You didn't understand it. Maybe the circumstances frustrated you.
But you prayed. And you asked God to work and He did.
And the Bible says that they were astonished. I like that.
I like it when God works that way.
The Bible says that He, verse 17, beckoning unto them with the hand to hold their peace.
Now, in my sanctified imagination, here's how I see it working out.
Peter comes in, they're astonished, and I think that...
You ever been in a situation where 20 people try to talk at the same time?
I think they all want to know, how did you get here? What happened? Who let you out?
I mean like, just bam, bam, bam, rapid fire. Questions are coming.
Peter, tell us what happened. And He, the Bible says, beckoning unto them with the hand to hold their peace.
And the Bible says that He declared unto them, notice what it says, it's important.
Declared unto them how the Lord had brought Him out of the prison.
He began to provide for them an account of what had transpired.
What He experienced. How that it was the Lord that brought Him out of the prison.
And we find that Peter, he gives glory to God. He acknowledges that it's God.
By the way, we just read the account. What else was he going to do?
He couldn't say, I was able to get these guys to go to sleep, and I snuck out. No.
He knew it was God.
I covertly got through the first ward and the second ward. No.
God did something miraculous.
You know, when all those guys were coming after Elisha, and his servant was scared to death,
Elisha says, God opened his eyes.
There's more with us than with them.
And then he prayed that God would cause them to be blind, and then Elisha leads them to Samaria.
Right? That's what God can do.
And here we find that Peter says, go, show these things unto James and to the brethren.
And he departed and went into another place.
Now, the story continues. The account continues.
And now we have this couple of verses that provide us with a record of the other side, if you will.
And so we've read in these verses of Scripture, the side of the church, the side of Peter,
and all that had transpired and how God delivered.
But remember that as we started reading in verse number six, it says,
And when Herod would have brought him forth, what is he going to bring him out for?
He's going to bring him out to kill him.
The Bible says in verse 18, as we pick up the account from the opposite perspective,
it says, Now, as soon as it was day, there was no small stir among the soldiers.
Notice what it says, what was become of Peter.
Now, can you imagine being one of those soldiers? Can you imagine?
I mean, listen, it was a very important job.
It was a job that if you lost a soldier, if someone escaped, you would lose your life.
I mean, it was a very important job. There were very high stakes.
And we find that the Bible says there was no small stir among the soldiers.
What was become of Peter?
They woke up and Peter wasn't there.
They woke up and the chains were laying on the ground.
Amen. I mean, because the Bible said that he told him to stand up and the chains fell off.
And so there's no idea that I would have.
There's no idea that you should have, that somehow those chains were taken.
No, they were laying there.
And there's no small stir.
I mean, I think the guards inside the prison had a conversation with the guards outside of the prison doors.
I think those guys had a conversation with the ones that were in the first ward and the second ward.
And they're trying to figure out what happened.
Can you imagine?
It's hilarious.
Trying to figure it out.
Were you sleeping? No, I wasn't sleeping.
Did you see? No, I didn't see.
What happened? How did this happen?
How did this happen?
I ask that question all the time.
It's how my brain works.
Something goes wrong. How did this happen?
I want to get to the root cause. How did this happen?
And these guys are trying to figure it out.
And the Bible says in verse 19,
And when Herod had sought for him, now they knew that Herod was going to come for them.
They knew what was going on.
And now Herod, the Bible says, sought for him and found him not.
He examined the keepers and commanded,
notice what it says, that they should be put to death.
And he went down from Judea to Caesarea and there abode.
Shortly thereafter, Herod would die.
In the next few verses, you read of that.
It's not the point of the message this morning.
But we find that here, as we look at the other side of the account,
listen, the unbelievers are going to stand in disbelief.
How did this happen?
Listen, that's how I want God to work.
I wanted to leave them in a situation where they could,
they have no explanation.
I remember standing up in testimony, I said, give glory to God.
Our God did this.
Our God worked in this way.
Because this is what God is able to do.
Someone said this, and I think it's convicting for sure.
I think it's important for us to consider this thought.
The pulpit, so that's why I say it's convicting,
because this quote is straight at me.
The pulpit of this day is weak in praying.
The pride of learning is against the dependent humility of prayer.
A few chapters earlier, turn there, if you will, in Acts 6.
I said this in the beginning of the message this morning.
There is nothing on your calendar today that is more important than prayer.
In Acts 6, there's a problem in the church.
The church was growing, there were some people being neglected,
there was too much work to be done, not enough workers to summarize.
I want you to notice in the text of Scripture, the Bible says in verse 2,
that the twelve called the multitude of the disciples unto them and said,
here's what they said,
it is not reason that we should leave the word of God and serve tables.
Now understand with me in verse number 2,
that the approach and the perspective of the apostles
was not that it was below them to serve tables.
That's not the idea.
Servant leadership is biblical.
And it's not that it's below them to serve tables,
but they said this, that we should leave the word of God and serve tables.
Their job, preach the word, be instant in season, out of season,
reprove, rebuke, exhort with all longsuffering and doctrine.
We find that the Bible says in 1 Peter 5, feed the flock of God.
The job of the pastor, if I can use today's terminology,
is to be a man of prayer and of the word.
Amen?
And it's not that serving tables is below,
it's that I can't allow serving tables to interfere with my priority
of the word of God and prayer.
Does that make sense?
And we find in verse number 3, it says,
Wherefore, brethren, look ye out among you,
seven men of honest report, full of the Holy Ghost and wisdom,
whom we may appoint over this business.
So what was their solution?
What was God's solution to the situation?
Well, there were going to be some people in the church
that were going to rise up and help with the other responsibilities.
Does that make sense?
There's some things that needed to be taken place,
and there's some work that needed to be done.
And so they're going to find these men and the credentials, if you will,
men that were of honest report, men that were full of the Holy Ghost and wisdom,
and they would be appointed over this business.
And notice in verse number 4,
But we will give ourselves continually to what?
To prayer and to the ministry of the word.
Can I tell you this morning, the enemy would like nothing more
than for the pastor or the religious leader
to leave the ministry of prayer and the word
and get caught up with all kinds of other things.
Why?
Because if the pastor's not praying and the pastor's not laboring in the word,
then the pastor can't fulfill his God-given responsibility.
Does that make sense?
Someone years ago, and I'm not saying this
to get somebody to have this conversation with me today,
but someone years ago heard on a Wednesday evening,
through conversation, it was not something that I announced in the pulpit.
They just heard from conversation that I had been planning to cut the grass that week.
And here's what they said to me on the back door as they left.
the back steps right over here.
They said, pastor, you let me know what time to come
and I'll cut the grass because you can preach, I can't.
You don't need to be out there cutting grass.
I can cut the grass.
Praise the Lord.
Again, I'm not saying that so that somebody
would have that response this morning.
I'm simply saying the early church had a priority on prayer.
The early church understood
that there's an emphasis on prayer.
You'd be amazed.
And I'm not just speaking from my experience.
I'm talking about the experiences of other pastors
that I've been able to have conversations with.
You'd be amazed at how many things
members of churches will ask pastors to be engaged with
that have nothing to do with the ministry of prayer
or the word of God.
The pulpit's weak in praying
because the pastor is looked at as the one
that's responsible for doing X, Y, and Z.
And there's only so much time.
Somebody said this.
I just finished reading a book just last night.
It's the book that I referenced a few weeks ago
that said you must remember that God is omni-everything
and you are omni-nothing.
I love the quote.
Joseph said, you've used that twice in two services.
I like it.
It was a good reminder for me
because I'm omni-nothing.
But here's what the writer went on to say.
We as pastors, we are not an unlimited resource.
We're not.
We're not God.
And so the reality is that we look at a passage
of scripture like Acts 12.
Peter's the one that's speaking here
or at least one of them.
He's often the spokesman and we don't know for sure
that he's the one speaking in Acts 6
but it would make sense that he was
as one of the apostles, always the one speaking up
in all the other instances that we have
and we find that he's now the one in prison
but the church is praying.
The church is praying and God works.
This morning I simply asked the question
why and when do we pray?
If we honestly evaluate our lives,
if we evaluate our church,
would it be said of us that we're a praying people,
that we're a praying church?
Do we believe in the power of prayer?
It's one thing for us to walk around
and say I believe in the power of prayer
but our behavior reveals what we really believe.
I know I've said this before and I don't say it
to try to increase the attendance on Wednesdays.
I say it because it's true.
The midweek prayer and Bible study
in our churches in America today
is the least attended service of the week.
That tells us a little bit about what we think about prayer.
Does it not?
Listen, God convicted me
and I hope God would convict all of us
because prayer is so important.
Prayer is so vital and our God hears and answers prayer.
Why and when do we pray?
Is there a pattern of prayer in your life,
in my life, in our church that we're a praying church?
When's the last time we've been astonished
because we've seen God do what only God can do?
We said kind of like Hezekiah.
Lord, here's what they've said.
Laid out the letters before God.
God, it's the truth.
They've done everything that they said they've done
to all the other nations but you're God.
You're God and God worked because Hezekiah prayed.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
Thank you so much for loving us.
I thank you for the privilege of prayer.
I thank you for the power of prayer.
I thank you that the early church was a praying church.
Praying church is made up of praying people.
God, I pray that we'd be a people of prayer.
So often prayer is easy to talk about,
it's easy to sing about, it's easy to preach about
but praying is work.
Distractions can abound.
Busyness can distract us.
God, I pray that you'd help us to be a praying people,
a praying church.
Would you have your will and way in the hearts and lives
of those that are present this morning?
God, do a work in our hearts.
A work that would not soon be forgotten.
A work that would bring forth fruits
because God, prayer is our response to your ability
and we know that you can do everything.
There's nothing too hard for thee.
We commit these moments to you.
Pray that you'd have your will and way
for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
I know we don't have the same kind of altar in here
that we do in the other room
but maybe this morning the Lord spoke into your heart
through the preaching of his word,
convicted you at some level.
Kimberly's gonna play.