as the same, commit thou to faithful men
who shall be able to teach others also.
And I'm thankful for faithful men.
I'm thankful for my dad, of course, Father's Day.
Sent him a message early this morning.
I'm thankful that when I was just almost a teenager,
12 years old, almost 13,
that my dad trusted Christ as his savior.
Somebody cared enough about him to share the gospel.
Wasn't even really sharing the gospel with him directly,
but with another co-workers who's in the Marine Corps
and overheard that conversation.
And just a couple of weeks after that,
he trusted Christ as his savior.
And I'll tell you, my life changed after that
because dad said, we're going to church.
And I began to go to church and hear the gospel.
It was a number of years before I got saved,
but I'm thankful to be able to report
that my dad's still serving the Lord today.
And that is a blessing and an encouragement to me
and thankful for the faithful men of our church.
And often I pray that God would give us men,
that God would give us faithful men,
those that would serve the Lord faithfully,
that we could run the race and serve the Lord.
Thankful for the examples of those that have gone before us.
If you have your Bible with you this morning,
Isaiah chapter 38 is where we'll be looking at.
Isaiah chapter number 38.
And of course, it is a great responsibility.
It's a great blessing,
but also a great responsibility to be a father.
And I remember with great clarity
when Holly made known to me
that she was expecting our first child.
And I remember that, and I would say it this way,
that there was a flood of emotions that overwhelmed me.
And some of those that I could specifically say,
joy, excitement, but I'll be honest with you,
there was a little bit of fear
and a little bit of uncertainty
and the weight of the responsibility
of being a father and having children.
And I remember Holly sharing that with me.
Now our kids are 23 and 21 and 19, all adults,
but just a blessing to be able to have the privilege
and the responsibility to have children.
We know that children are an heritage of the Lord
and it's a blessing.
And we're very thankful.
One of the greatest responsibilities as a Christian father
is noted in a phrase here in the book of Isaiah
in the 38th chapter.
I want you to look at verse 19.
I'm gonna quickly go through the entire chapter
by way of introduction,
but I'm gonna just read verse 19 to begin here.
And the Bible says this,
the living, the living, he shall praise thee
as I do this day.
Notice the last phrase of verse 19,
the father to the children shall make known thy truth.
What a powerful declaration, a powerful statement.
And as Christian fathers,
we understand the great responsibility
that is given to us here in this verse of scripture.
No doubt as fathers,
there are many valuable lessons
that we can teach our children.
And I've had the, again, opportunity to have three children
and we're very thankful for that.
Many lessons that you try to teach your children,
you teach them to have good manners
and you teach them to behave a certain way
and you teach them various things about finances and life
and so on and so forth.
But honestly, this morning,
at the top of our list as Christian fathers
should be to teach them about God,
to teach them about God and to make known thy truth.
Here in Isaiah chapter 38,
there's an interaction that takes place
between King Hezekiah and the prophet Isaiah.
Now, Hezekiah was basically a good king.
There are many good things that you can read about Hezekiah
and as you look at this particular chapter,
we find that the Bible says in verse number one,
in those days was Hezekiah sick unto death.
And Isaiah the prophet, the son of Amos,
said unto him and said unto, sorry, let me back up.
came unto him and said unto him, notice where he says,
thus saith the Lord, set thine house in order
for thou shalt die and not live.
And we understand through the interaction
that takes place here that Hezekiah
would be granted 15 years of additional life.
But let me say it this way,
it did come to the point one day
in Hezekiah's life that he died.
The Bible says as it appointed unto man wants to die
and after this, the judgment,
I don't know when I'm gonna die,
you don't know when you're going to die,
but we understand the truth of God's word
with regard to this.
But think about this interaction
as the prophet of God, Isaiah,
comes and says to the king, Hezekiah,
thus saith the Lord, here's the message from God,
you're gonna die.
Notice he says, set thine house in order
for thou shalt die and not live.
And we find that the Bible tells us
that Hezekiah turned his face toward the wall
and prayed unto the Lord and said,
remember now, O Lord, I beseech thee
how I have walked before thee in truth
and with a perfect heart,
and have done that which is good in thy sight.
And Hezekiah wept sore.
Then came the word of the Lord to Isaiah saying,
go and say to Hezekiah, thus saith the Lord,
the God of David, thy father, I have heard thy prayer,
I have seen thy tears.
Notice, behold, I will add unto thy days 15 years,
and I will deliver thee in this city
out of the hand of the king of Assyria,
and I will defend this city.
And this shall be a sign unto thee from the Lord
that the Lord will do this thing that he had spoken.
Behold, I will bring again the shadow of the degrees,
which has gone down in the sundial of Ahaz,
10 degrees backward.
So the sun returned 10 degrees
by which degrees it was gone down.
In verse number nine, the Bible says this,
the writing of Hezekiah, king of Judah,
when he had been sick and was recovered of his sickness.
And so starting in verse number nine,
down really through verse number 20,
we find that Hezekiah begins to reference some things,
to write some things, to acknowledge some things
that he knew to be true.
And he talks about praising,
and he talks about various things,
but I want you to notice,
and for sake of what we're looking at this morning,
I want you to notice near the end of this writing,
near the end of this declaration,
in verse number 19, he says,
the living, the living, he shall praise thee
as I do this day.
And then notice, these are the words of Hezekiah,
the father to the children shall make known thy truth.
He knew something that was extremely important.
Unfortunately, in Hezekiah's life,
the son that would be born after
this particular circumstance was a man
by the name of Manasseh.
Manasseh was 12 when he began to reign,
and he was a wicked man.
And it doesn't necessarily say that,
that doesn't mean that Hezekiah didn't teach him.
We don't know all of the details,
but what I'd say is that Hezekiah recognized
an extremely important truth that's necessary
for each of us to understand this morning,
that somebody, someone needs to make God's truth known
to the next generation.
And as we look at the context,
and we think about this day being Father's Day,
that here it specifically says,
the father to the children shall make known thy truth.
Can I tell you this morning by way of introduction,
that it's every believer's responsibility
to make known the truth of God's word.
We just recently had our missions conference,
and obviously preaching and being challenged
about the idea of going forth
and preaching the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
We understand the fullness of the Great Commission
is not simply to preach the gospel.
The fullness of the Great Commission
is to preach the gospel.
The Bible says that we're to go
and we're to preach the gospel to every creature,
but we find that we're to baptize them,
and then notice this,
to teach them all things whatsoever I have commanded thee.
The idea of discipleship,
the idea that we're to go forth and make disciples.
And so this morning, the truth that is before us
this morning is for every single one of us.
We have a responsibility to make God's truth known
to those that are coming behind us.
We understand there's a time to live,
there's a time to die.
We understand that there's one generation that passes away,
and there's another generation that comes.
We can look through the Bible,
we can look specifically in the Old Testament
and understand many things
with regard to the nation of Israel,
and we can see a nation that's living and serving
and has good leadership,
and then another generation rises up,
and there's always another generation.
We look in the New Testament,
begin to think about the leaders,
the spiritual leaders of the church
and how the Lord had instructed them to teach
and to disciple a future generation.
I'm thankful that Paul had the opportunity
to pass the baton to Timothy.
to instruct Titus and to leave him in Crete
that he would set in order the things
that were wanting there.
Begin to think about the ministry
and the idea of making God's truth known
to the next generation.
From that verse of Scripture,
I've simply titled the message this morning,
Make Known Thy Truth.
When we talk about thy truth, that's God's truth,
not your truth.
That's God's truth,
and we have to understand that we're making known
the truth of God's word.
I'm thankful this morning that Jesus said,
I am the way, the truth, and the life.
No man cometh unto the Father but by me.
Thankful that Jesus said this,
sanctify them through thy word.
Thy word is truth.
And just a little while after that,
Pilate stood before Jesus and asked what is truth?
And truth embodied stood right before him
and yet he didn't stick around long enough to get an answer.
I am thankful this morning
that we have the truth of God's word.
I'm thankful that we have a Bible that's dependable,
that we can look to.
It's all scriptures given by inspiration of God.
It's been supernaturally preserved for us
and we're so thankful that we have a Bible,
that we have the truth before us.
So we're gonna think about this idea
of make known thy truth.
Just a few thoughts for you
and we'll be looking at various parts
of the Bible this morning.
But number one, if you're taking notes,
a plea for influence.
A plea for influence.
Look over at the 71st Psalm, if you will.
Psalm 71.
We're gonna look at a few verses here
in the book of Psalms this morning
and we'll eventually get into the New Testament.
But I want you to see here in this Psalm,
a plea for influence.
And we begin to understand,
there are some that say,
well, I just don't have any influence.
There's some that say, I wish I had influence.
But here we see the heart of the Psalmist
having this plea, this earnest desire,
this yearning to have influence.
The Bible says in Psalm 71 in verse number 18,
notice the Bible says,
now also, when I am old and gray-headed,
oh God, forsake me not,
notice the rest of the verse,
until I have showed thy strength
unto this generation
and thy power to everyone that is to come.
Do you see the heart of the Psalmist here
in Psalm 71 in verse 18,
this plea for influence.
He recognized his condition.
He recognized that he was old and gray-headed
and he recognized that there was still
within him this drive,
this desire to be able to influence.
He makes this plea.
He says, oh God, forsake me not
until I have showed.
Now that's an interesting word.
That word means to tell.
It means to make known, to declare.
We're talking about make known thy truth.
And here the Psalmist says,
oh God, forsake me not
until I have showed thy strength
unto who?
Unto this generation
and thy power to everyone
that is to come.
Listen, there's some young people
in our church this morning.
There's some young people
that need to know the truth of God's word.
They need to know that our God is faithful.
They need to know that our God is all powerful.
They need to know that our God hears
and answers prayer.
I mentioned to Ms. Barbara this morning
how good it was to see her in church
and how it's exciting to see
how God answered prayer.
And she said, it's important.
It's what she said.
It's important for God's people
to see that God hears and answers prayer.
And I agree wholeheartedly.
Listen, it's important that our young people
in our church, that the generation
that's coming behind us,
that it's not always talking about
what God used to do.
It's not always about the past
and the God of the past.
But no, here's what God's doing today.
Here's how God's answering prayer today.
Listen, there were two people on Sunday night
in our Spanish ministry
that trusted Jesus Christ
as their personal savior.
To God be the glory.
The gospel still works, amen.
And souls are still being saved.
Just a few weeks ago,
Tiani trusted Christ as her savior.
And we got some people that are giving
and they're going to Bible college
and training for the ministry.
They've surrendered to missions.
Listen, God is at work.
And we need to ensure that we have
the plea for influence.
Oh God, would you give me this opportunity?
Would you give me this opportunity
to influence, to make known
thy strength, thy power, thy truth,
as Hezekiah said to a future generation.
We think about this plea.
We think about this idea of declaring
and telling and making known.
Let me say this, a few things about this plea.
If you're going to plea,
you're gonna ask God,
you're gonna seek the face of God for influence.
Let me tell you that it needs to be active
and not passive.
Active and not passive.
We need to be actively engaged
in influencing a future generation.
What can we do?
How can we actively be involved?
It's not a passive thing.
Well, we don't believe in that idea
of lifestyle evangelism.
Now the reality is that they ought to see
that there's something different about you,
but we also got to open our mouth
and tell them what it is.
Amen.
And we got to be active.
And we find that it's important
with this idea of influence,
that is to be active, not simply passive.
Let me say this.
It is to be purposed and not accidental.
Listen, I'm thankful for the accidental moments,
if you will, of opportunities to influence,
but we need to be purposed.
We need to have purpose
that we're going to seek these opportunities.
I'm pleading for influence
and I'm gonna be purposed to look for
and seize those opportunities to influence.
Again, there are times in which something might happen
and circumstances may evolve in such a way
that man, I didn't think that this was gonna happen today,
but I have this opportunity for influence.
Praise the Lord for that.
But it's gotta be purposed.
It's gotta be purposed.
Let me say this.
If we're gonna have influence,
we need to be present and not absent.
You know, we have a real problem in our nation today
of absent parents.
It's their studies that are out there.
You can read them.
You can see all the statistics
and we understand this reality that we're facing.
We're talking about being present, not absent.
Can I say this?
What I mean by being present is being actively engaged,
not just physically there.
You know, you can be present, but not really be present.
You can be here this morning in this building,
present in attendance,
but be completely somewhere else in your mind
and completely miss everything that's taken place.
Amen?
You can be at home with your family
and we got these little phones and listen,
I know there's a lot of good things about these phones,
a lot of evil things about these phones as well,
but can I tell you, if the whole time you're home,
you're on your device, you're not really present.
You say, pastor, I don't like the preaching.
Amen?
Listen, here's the reality.
Look, there's some places that have,
how many times have you gone to a restaurant
and you sat down and you saw a family sitting down
and every single person at the table was on their device?
Have you seen it?
I've seen it time and again.
They're having family time.
Oh yeah, they'll tell you.
Chick-fil-A at one point,
I know other places have done this.
They put little boxes on their tables
and they say, put your phone in there
so that you can spend some time together
when you come and eat at our establishment.
That's not a bad idea.
My mom started doing this.
She'd go to restaurants, she'd leave her phone in the car
when she went into the restaurant.
Why?
This can be a distraction, but not just at a restaurant.
You come home from work, I understand we're busy.
Listen, I get phone calls all the time
and I'm not saying that to say stop calling me.
I'm just simply saying, I get phone calls
and I get text messages and I get emails
and I get all kinds of things,
but what I'm saying is that there's some times
that we gotta be unplugged and say,
hey, I'm gonna be present with my family.
Amen?
Listen, you can scroll.
Listen, people are having problems with their wrist
and their thumbs because all they do is scroll.
I'm telling you, man, you look it up.
There's some statistics out there,
some things that are happening.
And you can get on these social media sites
and you can scroll indefinitely and just scroll.
You know what your phone does now?
Your phone tells you how much time
you've spent on which app.
And you say, yeah, I don't pay attention to that.
Maybe you should.
Because when I talk about being present,
I'm not just talking about a physical presence,
I'm talking about being actively engaged
and your family knowing that you're there,
that you're present.
You're asking questions, you're finding out.
Listen, if we're gonna have a plea for influence,
how do we influence those that are closest to us?
Man, I gotta know what's going on in their life.
Who are their friends?
What's going on?
How was school?
So on and so forth.
I wanna know, amen.
A plea.
The psalmist, oh God, forsake me not
until I have showed thy strength
unto this generation and thy power
to everyone that is to come.
What a great desire.
This morning, we need to have a plea for influence.
Not only a plea for influence, but I'd say this,
a passion to influence, a passion to influence.
See, it's one thing to have a plea
and pray, God, would you give me an opportunity,
but then there's a different thing
to have a passion for it.
See, here's the reality.
Those watching us know what we're passionate about, amen?
They know, listen, you talk to somebody for a little while,
you get some conversation with them
and you begin to find out real quickly
what they're passionate about, why?
Because what you're passionate about, you talk about, right?
And so we find here, if we have a passion to influence,
then we're gonna look for and seize those opportunities
that God will give us.
See, we're having this plea, God, would you give me
the opportunity to influence,
and then I have this passion to influence.
And listen, I understand it might not always come
at a convenient time.
It might come that your children ask you a question
and it's just not convenient, it's been a long day at work,
lots of things going on, things on your mind.
Listen, it's an opportunity.
And here, let me tell you this, if you don't answer them,
they're gonna go somewhere to get an answer.
And you know where they're gonna go for the most of them today? They're gonna go
to the Internet. I used to say go to Google, but now they got chat GPT and all
this other stuff, right? And they're gonna look there, and you know what they're
gonna believe? They're gonna believe what they read on the Internet. How many of
you know this morning that everything on the Internet isn't true? Show
me your hands if you know that to be the case. That everything on the Internet is
not true. Listen, there's some young people that think that everything they
read on the Internet is true. It's just not the case. Everything you read in this
book is true. Come on! We need to get our face in this book, amen? And we need to
understand thy word is truth. Listen, this Bible is never gonna lead you astray.
This Bible is truth. You can go and you can ask questions on Google and chat GPT
and whatever other thing you, Gemini, so on and so forth, and I'm telling you, you
need to go to the Bible, but as those that are influencing, understand. When
someone asks you a question, if you don't take the time to answer, they're gonna go
somewhere to get an answer. They're gonna go somewhere, and it's so readily
available today. Listen, back in my day, you had to go find the Encyclopedia
Britannica, 26 volumes or however many it was. How many of you remember the
Encyclopedia Britannica? Come on! These young people are like, what? They don't
even print it anymore. They don't. They stopped printing a long time ago. Why? Because it
wasn't worth their time and money to print it because no one was buying it.
Wikipedia kind of took care of that situation, but listen, what I'm saying to
you this morning is that we need to have a passion to influence. Look at Psalm 145.
Psalm 145, and we're gonna look at a couple of examples here of a passion to
influence. In Psalm 145, it's a psalm that's ascribed to David, and notice with me,
we'll read the first several verses of Psalm 145, and then we'll look over the
book of Proverbs and see a testimony of Solomon that really will go hand-in-hand
with this aspect of David here in Psalm 145. In Psalm 145, in verse number one,
notice the Bible says, I will extol thee, my God, O King, and I will bless thy name
forever and ever. Every day will I bless thee, and I will praise thy name forever
and ever. Listen, it's a good thing to praise the Lord. He is worthy. Amen? He's
to be exalted and to be magnified. Listen, that's part of influence, by the way,
when we're exalting the Lord and we're praising Him every day, and we're talking
about how good God is, how great God is. It's making a difference. It's making an
impact when you begin to praise God, even in the storms of life, in the trials, and
the difficulties. You say, God's at work. God knows what's going on. Listen,
that's influence. He says in verse number three, Great is the Lord, and greatly to
be praised, and His greatness is unsearchable. Notice in verse four,
one generation shall praise thy works, what's it say? To another,
and shall declare thy mighty acts. I will. He didn't say, I might.
He didn't say, when it's convenient, I will. He said, I will speak of the glorious
honor of thy majesty and of thy wondrous works. Listen, you'll find somebody that
wants to hear it. Amen? He says, I'm going to speak. You say, well,
people don't want to hear. Find a new audience. Find somebody else to talk to.
Amen? Listen, we need to be able to influence. The Bible said, and we'll look
at it in just a moment, I've already quoted it once, but the Bible says,
the things that thou hast heard of me among many witnesses, the same commit thou
to faithful men shall be able to teach others also. Listen, there's some people
out there that need your influence. We've got to have a passion to influence.
And he says, I will speak of the glorious honor of thy majesty and of thy wondrous
works, and men shall speak of the might of thy terrible acts, and I will declare
thy greatness. Do you see the passion of the psalmist, of David here? He says,
I will, in verse number five, speak of the glorious honor of thy majesty.
He says, in verse number six at the end, I will declare thy greatness.
Listen, it's a blessing to talk about how great God is. There's no one like Him.
No one like Him. Amen? Listen, you need to get filled up on how great God is.
And when you get filled up on how great God is, you can't help but just talk about
how great God is. If you had a great meal last week, if you had a great experience
at some place, some establishment, you write reviews and you talk about how great
that place was, and this server, and that server, and this meal, whatever.
Listen, it's about time that we start saying, I will declare thy greatness.
There's no one like our God. He's absolutely amazing. And we find that the
more you begin to study His word, the more you begin to search out His greatness,
the more you find, as he said in verse number three, that His greatness is
unsearchable. Listen, we're just barely scratching the surface. Listen,
I know that God is great, but He's greater than my mind can conceive.
He's greater than my words can be able to articulate to you this morning.
That's how great our God is. As great this morning as God is in your mind,
I tell you He's greater, far greater. The Bible says that He's infinite.
We're finite. We cannot fully understand Him. His ways are not our ways.
His thoughts are not our thoughts. Amen? And we find that we've got to have this
passion to influence. Listen, I don't know. I normally don't watch soccer.
Don't let that be offensive to you. Amen? Joseph said to me last night,
how can you watch a game that spends 90 minutes and it's zero to zero?
There should be some scoring. Amen? And I agree with him. Amen?
But it's the World Cup, and I kind of got sucked in a little bit,
watched a little bit of the games and what have you, the US won.
And I don't even know when the next game is, all that sort of thing.
But listen, there's some people that are passionate about their team. Am I right?
I mean, they put on all kinds of paraphernalia to cover the colors of their
country, and they're up there screaming and yelling, and they're doing all the
things that they're doing. They got passion. Can I tell you,
at some point, it really doesn't matter who wins what match.
It doesn't matter how many points they have and what group.
It doesn't matter who scores what. It doesn't matter who wins the World Cup.
Listen, it's all temporal. It's all temporal. I'm not saying that if
you're a fan, if you're into it, that's your thing. I get it. It's fine.
But what I'm saying is it's temporal. It's fading. It's going to pass away.
Shouldn't we be passionate about something that's eternal? Amen?
Listen, that guy scores a goal, and the fans go crazy, and they're just all...
Joseph said, why are they so excited? It was zero to zero.
How many watched the game last night? The Curacao or whatever it was, right?
They never, never made it before. Smallest nation population to ever make it
to the World Cup, and they're celebrating. And Joseph's like,
why would you celebrate zero-zero? I said, because they actually get a
point for that. He said, how do you get a point for that if you didn't score any
points? We don't understand soccer real good, amen? But here's the reality.
They're passionate. Listen, it's time for God's people to be passionate
about influencing a future generation. Can I tell you the kids,
the young people in our church, they need to know that we're serious
about who God is and about what God's able to do, that we have a passion.
Listen, they ought to know that we're more passionate about God than anything else.
Amen? We are more passionate about God than anything else.
Nothing else comes close. We're passionate about the Lord.
Look in Proverbs 4, if you will, just a few more pages over in your Bible,
Proverbs 4, here Solomon is speaking. Of course, God is using him to pen the book
of Proverbs. And the Bible begins in verse 1 of Proverbs 4,
hear ye children the instruction of a father, and attend to no understanding.
Solomon says, for I give you good doctrine, forsake ye not my law.
Notice in verse 3, he says, for I was my father's son, tender and only beloved in
the sight of my mother. Notice these next four words that begin verse number 4,
he taught me also, and said unto me, let thine heart retain my words,
keep my commandments, and live. He says, get wisdom, get understanding,
forget it not, neither decline from the words of my mouth, forsake her not,
she shall preserve thee, love her, and she shall keep thee.
Wisdom is the principal thing, therefore get wisdom, and with all thy getting,
get understanding. Exalt her, and she shall promote thee.
She shall bring thee to honor when thou dost embrace her.
She shall give to thine head an ornament of grace, a crown of glory,
shall she deliver to thee. Verse 10, hear, O my son.
Now, this is Solomon speaking to Rehoboam. Hear, O my son, and receive my sayings,
and the years of thy life shall be many. I have taught thee in the way of wisdom.
I have led thee in right paths. If I can, in verse number 4,
replace those pronouns this way, David taught Solomon.
In verse number 11, Solomon taught Rehoboam, right?
It's David teaching Solomon, it's Solomon teaching his son, Rehoboam.
And what a blessing to think about this idea, this passion and influence in Solomon
under the inspiration.
of the Holy Spirit of God makes it clear to us that He taught me also. David was actively
involved. We read already there in Psalm 145 how he had a passion to influence. I will
declare. I will speak. And now we find that Solomon says, He taught me also. He taught
me. What a blessing to think about that. David was the king. David was not a perfect man.
We understand the scriptures record for us things about David to show his humanity and
to show various aspects of his failures. But we find that the Bible tells us that David
was a man after God's own heart. David did a lot of good things, great things. God used
him in an amazing way. David had great faith. David had passion to influence and God used
him. And God used him not only to influence his own son, but then even as Solomon took
that instruction and then instructed his son. Some of us here this morning are grandparents.
What a blessing. And we have two grandchildren. We found out just recently that number three
is going to be another boy. And so that's a blessing. Another grandson. Amen. And we
begin to think about these ideas. Listen, it blesses my heart to hear little Nova sing
Jesus loves me, this I know. I used to sing that song with Juliana. So you try to influence
one generation and the next generation is going to be influenced as well. I like to
sing with Nova. I like to read and to teach. I was telling you not long ago, we had one
of these little books. I don't know where we got it from, but I said, forget that. It's
a little children's Bible story that was taking things all kinds of sideways. I don't know
who wrote it, why they wrote it, but I said, let's just read the Bible. Amen. And I begin
to share with her truth about David. And I was just kind of, I didn't even get my Bible.
I was just sharing with her truth about David. And she said, more Papa, more. And man, that
just blessed my heart. See a passion to influence. See the greatest thing that we can teach a
next generation is truth about God. Truth about God. So I taught my son how to shoot
a basketball. Praise the Lord. I played basketball with Joseph. Taught him how to hit a baseball.
Praise the Lord. How to kick a soccer ball. I didn't teach him that. Teach him how to
do certain things. Amen. But, but here's what I want you to understand. Those things are
all temporal. What matters most is teaching, influencing about God. Notice with me, not
only do we see a plea and a passion, but I want you to see what is the number three,
the purpose of influence. What is the purpose of influence? Well, I've already quoted the
verse. You don't need to turn there. Second Timothy two and verse number two, Paul is
standing there writing to Timothy. Paul understood that soon he would face a martyr's death.
And he says to Timothy, the things that thou hast heard of me among many witnesses. Notice
this. He says the same, not something different, not something new. No, no, no. The same commit
thou to faithful men who shall be able to teach others also. I'll be 46 in just a few
weeks. I still consider that to be a young man. Now soon, I'm not sure when it's not
going to be a young man anymore. And my kids are already telling me it's the, it's your
late forties. And I said, listen, this is how it works. All right. Early forties are
40, 41, 42, 43. Mid forties are 44, 45, 46. Late forties are 47, 48, 49. And they said,
no, no, no. Late forties is 46. I disagree. And I still say I'm in my mid forties. Amen.
But here's the reality. Here's my heart, my goal. I don't know. Ronnie asked me, do you
want to, are you going to pastor until you're 80? I have no idea how long God's going to
give me. But you know what my heart's desire is, is that there's a church here that stands
for the truth of God's word when I'm gone. Whether that's that I'm gone tomorrow or in
25 years, my goal is that God's people will continue to march forward with the truth of
God's word that we have influenced a next generation. Listen, I tell you often as the
children come up here, they sang on Wednesday evening. What a wonderful blessing to hear
the little, the younger children in our church sing during our missions conference. And listen,
that's the future of our church. Amen. That's the future of our church. Zachary is going
to be our song leader. Amen. And praise the Lord. You get a big old smile up there. He
don't need a mic. He's like me. Amen. He just got a booming voice. Praise the Lord. But
what I'm saying is that that's the future of our church. The purpose of influence is
so that we would take that baton, that truth, and we'd give it to a next generation. You
know what they would do? They do the same thing that we're doing and they would influence
the next generation. He said in the book of Jude, it was needful for me to write unto
you. And he talks about the fact that there were some men that crept in unawares of this
false teaching and so on and so forth. And he tells them that they would earnestly contend
for the faith that was once delivered to the saints. I'm thankful that we have a Bible
and that we, listen, you know there are people that died so we could have a Bible today.
There are people that have died so we could have a Bible today. We can go and get a Bible
so easily today but it's not always been that way. We're blessed by those that have gone
before us. And we think about this purpose of influence. Look at Ephesians chapter 6
if you will. Ephesians chapter 6 and then we'll come back to the Old Testament and look
at a passage of scripture there. Ephesians chapter 6. Notice what the Bible says here
in this portion of scripture. And parents, if you have little children you no doubt would
like to teach your children some of these verses. And one of the first ones that we
taught our children to memorize was Ephesians 6 and verse number 1. Children, obey your
parents and the Lord for this is right. Amen. And we try to teach them that verse. They
need to understand that. But I want you to notice a little bit down the passage in verse
number 4. The Bible says this, and ye fathers, and ye fathers, provoke not your children
to wrath, but bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord. See this is where
that real weighty responsibility comes into the picture. The word nurture is instruction
which aims at increasing virtue. That's what it means. The word here in admonition to bring
them up in the nurture and admonition. It's gentle reproof. It's counseling against a
fault. We live in a time and a generation and for some of us here this morning we've
spanned a couple of generations and you can kind of see some of the differences. But I
want you to understand that there's a generation today that's more interested in being friends
with their children than being parents to their children. I'm not saying that parents
and children shouldn't have good relationship. But what I'm saying is that we are their parents.
A responsibility to bring them up in the nurture that's giving instruction what aims at increasing
virtue and in the admonition. Counseling against faults. Telling them when they're wrong. Gentle
reproof. Listen, part of being a parent is correcting. Part of being a preacher. Preach
the word. Be incidences and odysseys and reprove, rebuke, exhort with all longsuffering and
doctrine. It's part of it. Amen. And it's understanding the purpose of influence. In
Psalm 78, you don't need to turn there. In Psalm 78 verses 4 through 7 God gives us some
instruction with regard to the purpose of influence with regard to the nation of Israel.
And Psalm 78 really is just an amazing passage of scripture that covers so much of Israel's
history. But in the beginning verses of that particular chapter we find that there's really
revealed to us the purpose of influence. In verse number 4 of Psalm 78 the Bible says
we will not hide them from their children. Showing to the generation to come the praises
of the Lord and his strength and his wonderful works that he hath done. For he established
a testimony in Jacob and appointed a law in Israel, which he commanded our fathers
that they should make them known to their children. Remember as we read in Isaiah 38
he said the father to the children shall make known thy truth. And here in Psalm 78 in verse
number 5 the latter portion that they should make them known to their children that the
generation to come might know them even the children which should be born who should arise
and declare them to their children. We see some phrases in verse number 6 the idea of
to know them to know what? Well we read in verse 4 and 5 to know the truth of who God
is of the instruction that God has given to set their hope according to verse number 7
that they might set their hope in God and not forget the works of God but keep his commandments.
This is the purpose of influence. Listen I want to see as John says it this way in 3
John just one chapter in verse number 4 and here's the way John says it. I have no greater
joy than to hear that my children walk in truth. Now I understand that that's not specifically
talking about biological children. There's often times even as Paul would refer to Timothy
as his son in the faith, to Titus as his son in the faith and we begin to think about this
idea of those that would walk in truth. John in the first epistle, 1 John he'll write often
about little children. He'll use that phraseology and so now
He says, I have no greater joy than to hear that my children walk in truth.
You know, what a blessing if we think about the aspect of biological children.
If God has blessed you with children, there's no greater joy than to see your children walk
in truth.
To see them get saved, trust Christ as their Savior, to follow the Lord in believer's
baptism, to surrender their lives to the Lord, to live for Christ.
And there's no greater joy.
But can I tell you this morning, when we think about the household of faith, if you will,
and you think about those that are coming behind us, a future generation, as John would
say, listen, I have no greater joy than to hear that my children walk in truth.
I've been told recently about some young people, I'm talking about in a public school that
took some gospel tracts from our church and were passing out gospel tracts.
Man, that makes me want to jump off, like just go crazy.
And I'm not that kind of a fanatic, but I'm telling you what, that gives you some reason
to shout.
Amen?
I remember what it was to go to public school, I went there my whole life.
And man, it's a different thing today than it was then.
But man, we go forth, listen, when I hear about people come and say, man, I was sharing
the gospel with somebody at work, I was doing, man, it caused me to have great joy.
Why?
Because you're walking in truth.
You're walking in truth.
And what a joy.
Here's a question, as we think about this passage of scripture from Isaiah that we just
took that phrase and kind of jumped from there and begin to look at this idea of making known
thy truth and the fact that there's a future generation that's coming behind us.
Listen, they're confused.
There's so much confusion in our world today.
They're teaching kids in kindergarten that you can't know if you're a boy or girl.
I mean, that's just nonsense.
Amen?
It's just nonsense.
Everything's relative, this, that, and the other thing.
Listen, there's so much confusion in our world today.
But there's a generation, if you do some research and you look at it, there's a generation between
the ages of like 18 and 25 that are sick of it.
They're just absolutely sick of it.
And so there's got to be something better than this.
Sadly to report, you know where they're going?
They're going to a lot of the Catholic churches, Anglican churches.
You just look it up.
It's what's happening.
You know why they're going there?
Because they see an institution, quote unquote, that has lasted through the centuries.
That's their reasoning.
That's their logic.
I've read extensively on it.
I've seen many things about it.
And I'm telling you, it's happening.
We're seeing it.
Can I tell you, they're not going to get truth there.
They're not going to get truth there.
But they're sick of it.
They're sick of all the things that are taking place in our society today.
You know what they're doing?
They're looking.
They're searching.
They're seeking.
Listen, we've got to be actively involved in influencing.
Because I'm telling you, if you look at those denominations, if we can use that phrase,
their attendance is going like this.
They're seeing a spike.
Listen, they're dusting out the pews that they haven't been dusting out in a long time.
This is what they're saying.
Because there's a generation that's sick of it.
They've been lied to, and they've been lied to, and they've been lied to.
We have the truth.
We need to have this plea for influence.
God, would you give me the opportunity to influence?
To be actively engaged.
To be present.
To be purposed.
God, would you give me a passion to influence?
Would you help those that are observing me to know that I'm serious about the truth of
your word, that I have a passion.
We sing the song, a passion to reach the lost.
Oh God, give us a passion.
And then we see the purpose.
How sad.
I've had experiences where I've knocked on doors of individuals that are just a generation
away from someone that was a Baptist deacon, a Baptist preacher, and you knock on their
door and they have no clue about salvation, raising their kids, they don't even know anything
about the Bible.
You say, how does that happen?
Somewhere along the line there was a lack of influence.
Let me understand that every man has their own decision.
Every man has their own choice.
But I want you to understand that we need to be actively engaged.
Let me ask this question.
It's a question I've had a hard time getting away from in the last couple of weeks.
How much would our children know to be true about God if we were their only instructor?
Before God ever established the church, he established the home.
The home does not replace the church.
Excuse me, the church does not replace the home.
The church is an institution that God has ordained and instructed and he's using.
But the responsibility of training children has always been and will always be the responsibility
of the parents.
God established the home well before he established the church.
The church comes alongside and aids in that instruction, in that bringing up.
It's what the church does.
Pastor, my kid's a mess, it must be your problem, it's not my problem.
I'm just simply saying, no, no one said that to me, I'm just saying you read that kind
of thing.
What I'm saying is how much would our kids, how much would our kids know to be true about
God if I were their only instructor?
I'm thankful for the Sunday school teachers, I'm thankful for the junior church workers,
I'm thankful for those that are actively engaged, church leaders, church members that
are actively engaged in instructing.
Praise God for that.
But understand, the responsibility is ours.
And it's a weighty responsibility.
But God will help us and God will give us all that we need to fulfill what he's called
us to fulfill.
Oh, that God would help each of us this morning.
Again, it's Father's Day, so some application of fathers, but we think about the truth broadly
speaking that we as believers are to make known God's truth to a next generation.
Oh, that God would give us a passion to do so.
Let's pray together.
Father, we do love you this morning.
We thank you so much for loving us.
We thank you for the word of God and for the truth that's contained therein.
God, I pray that you would help us to be passionate about the truth of thy word.
I pray that those that are observing our life and our behavior would know that there's nothing
that even comes close to our passion.
But this passion that we have for you and for your truth to make it known, God, help
us to be engaged actively.
I pray, Father, that you'd be with each one that's here this morning.
I pray that you'd help us to recognize the opportunities that you've set before us.
God, some of us have children.
Some of us have grandchildren.
Some of us, Lord, do not have children, but Lord, there's someone to influence.
I pray that you'd help us to walk so close to thee, to be so filled with thy power and
with thy spirit, to be so filled with your goodness and your greatness that we can't
help but talk of all thy wondrous works to declare thy greatness to another generation.
Help us, Lord.
I pray that you'd move and work in the moments of invitation as only you can, and we'll thank
you for every decision.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with us?