Colossians chapter number two.
We'll finish up this particular chapter this morning
and really kind of make it, if you will,
halfway through the book
and certainly have enjoyed the book of Colossians.
Of course, we took a number of weeks,
really several months off with some other things
that we're dealing with and preaching through
and I got back to the book of Colossians
last Sunday morning.
And last week was message number 10.
We looked at verses 11 through 15
and we dealt with that statement
that he made in verse number 14,
nailing it to his cross.
Aren't you thankful for what the Lord Jesus Christ
accomplished for you at the cross of Calvary?
And how wonderful to know that you're saved,
that you're heaven bound, amen?
And we're so thankful for that.
Verses 16 through 23 will be the focus
of our message this morning.
If you've looked at the bulletin,
you'll note that the title for the message
is Traps of False Teaching.
And I'll say this, there are many traps of false teaching.
The false teachers are deceptive,
they're active and we find it, of course,
that these false teachers were active here in Colossi.
We dealt with this many months ago
when we really were dealing with the introduction
to the book of Colossians and dealt with
some of the false teachers that were prevalent,
what have you.
The way in which Paul began the second chapter,
speaking of that great conflict that he had for them,
not only for those in Colossi,
but also for those that were in Laodicea
and he had this conflict for them
because he understood that these false teachers
were active.
I do not think it would be inappropriate
for me to say today that false teachers
continue to be active.
And we know that the Apostle Peter's,
he's writing to those that he's writing to
in the second letter, second Peter,
he deals with false teachers,
he deals with their characteristics and so on and so forth
and he makes this truth, this statement to these believers
and he talks about how there were false prophets
in the Old Testament and that there will be
false teachers today.
And we know that to be the case,
you can read through the Old Testament
and you can read of the false prophets that existed
and the way in which they gave false messages
to the people of God,
but I'm thankful for the true prophets of God.
I'm thankful for those prophets of God
that stood and delivered the message from God Almighty
to the people that he called them to minister to
and you can read through the Old Testament
and you can read of these prophets
and of their courage and of their faith
and what a blessing to know that they were faithful
to God Almighty.
So we are not ignorant this morning
of the attacks upon truth.
We understand this morning that the enemy
has been in opposition to the truth
from the very beginning.
The fact of the matter is that all the way back
in the book of Genesis in the third chapter,
we find that Satan, the serpent,
who's more subtle than any of the beasts of the field,
he says, yea, hath God said.
He's questioning the Word of God.
He's undermining the authority of God's Word
and then he continues on and he says this,
ye shall not surely die.
But we understand that God had given truth
and no matter how the enemy will seek to oppose truth,
that truth marches on, that truth stands
and I'm thankful for truth and that we,
this morning, have the truth of the Word of God.
I believe this morning that it would be fair to say
that the methods employed by false teachers
have been varied.
Their methods are varied.
The reality is that this reminds us
of the importance of being grounded in the truth
because the methods, listen, we're not ignorant
of his devices, Paul says that in 2 Corinthians,
but we do find that the methods,
the means in which are employed by these false teachers
will vary from generation to generation
and it reminds us of how vitally important it is
that we would be grounded on the Word of God
and the truth of God's Word.
I have often said that the answer to error is always truth.
The answer to error is truth.
We find that a preacher of yesteryear,
he made this statement,
error cannot flourish where sound doctrine holds sway.
Error cannot flourish where sound doctrine holds sway.
Why?
Because we know the truth
and we know the truth of the Word of God
and we're sound in the doctrine
and therefore when the false teaching
and the false teachers try to come in,
we're able to stand upon the truth of the Word of God
and that false doctrine cannot, it will not,
that error will not flourish.
I think about the admonition that Peter gives
at the end of that second letter
that I mentioned a moment ago.
Hold your place then in the book of Colossians if you will
and look to 2 Peter chapter number three.
And as you would do a survey of the book of 2 Peter,
you'll find that he deals with these false teachers
and their condemnation
and he deals with the characteristics of these individuals
and he's seeking to encourage
and instruct the people of God.
It's interesting how he ends
this particular epistle.
Notice with me in 2 Peter three in verse number 17.
He says,
Ye therefore, beloved,
seeing ye know these things before,
notice this warning,
beware lest ye also being led away
with the error of the wicked
fall from your own steadfastness.
But what does he say?
But grow in grace
and in the knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ
to Him be glory both now and forever.
Amen.
We understand that Peter had earlier said
in the first epistle to the same group of believers,
he says to them in 1 Peter two in verse number two,
as newborn babes desiring the sincere milk of the Word
that ye may grow thereby.
The false teachers are going to be active.
They're going to use, employ their methods.
They're going to seek to deceive.
And we understand that here in Colossians chapter number two,
the apostle Paul really will deal with three traps
of the false teachers,
three aspects of false teaching, if you will,
in these particular traps.
We know that Paul has sought to give truth
to these believers.
And we know that Paul is warning these believers.
Remember, as he mentioned to these believers
in the first chapter in verse number 28
of chapter number one of the book of Colossians,
he says,
whom we preach, speaking of the Lord Jesus Christ,
warning every man and teaching every man in all wisdom.
Why?
That we may present every man perfect in Christ Jesus.
As we look at these false teachers that are active
and we understand what Paul is dealing with,
as I've mentioned already this morning
by way of introduction,
false teachers continue to be active today.
I would say this,
I believe that their influence reaches further today
than it ever has.
Why is that?
Well, because we have this thing called the internet.
And as good as the internet can be
and as helpful as the resources can be on the internet,
you understand that that internet,
that platform is being utilized
for bad reasons and causes as well.
And we don't even need to get into all the sin
and the wickedness that exists on the internet,
but you think about the false teaching
and how easy it is for someone to go into Google
and to just type in some type of a search
and have all sorts of results and responses come.
And people sometimes have this attitude.
Well, it must be true because I read it on the internet.
Beware, amen.
There is much false teaching that exists on the internet
and the false teachers have been able
to broaden their influence exponentially
because of the internet.
And it's so vital that we as the people of God
acknowledge that danger and set our heart
to seek the law of the Lord
to understand the truth of God's Word.
This morning, look at verse number 16.
The Bible says,
let no man therefore judge you in meat or in drink
or in respect of an holy day
or of the new moon or of the Sabbath days,
which are a shadow of things to come,
but the body is of Christ.
Let no man beguile you of your reward
in a voluntary humility and worshiping of angels,
intruding into those things which he hath not seen,
vainly puffed up by his fleshly mind
and not holding the head
from which all the body by joints and bands
having nourishment ministered and knit together
increaseth with the increase of God.
Verse 20.
Wherefore, if ye be dead with Christ
from the rudiments of the world,
why, as though living in the world,
are ye subject to ordinances,
touch not, taste not, handle not,
which all are to perish with the using
after the commandments and doctrines of men,
which things have indeed a show of wisdom
and will worship and humility
and neglecting of the body,
not in any honor to the satisfying of the flesh.
Trap number one, if you're taking notes,
the trap of legalism.
Verse 16 and 17 deals with the trap of legalism.
And legalism is a dependence upon moral law
rather than on that personal faith
in the Lord Jesus Christ.
It is a dependence upon moral law.
It's a dependence upon that outward.
It's really the idea of adding works to grace
and understanding that there's something
that I must do in order to gain.
the favor of God. You understand that we were dead in our sins and our trespasses
and he hath quickened us, he made us alive. We find that Paul really, it's of
note, and we'll mention it many times throughout the message this morning, but
it's of note that he tells them in verse number 10 and we've used it for our
theme this year, ye are complete in him. And we find this trap of legalism and we
find that Paul begins in verse number 16 by saying, let no man therefore judge
you. He's gonna list some things particularly that he's speaking of, but
we find that judgment is a prevalent factor within the scope, if you will, of
legalism and thus Paul begins by using this phrase, let no man therefore judge
you. Now the message this morning is not on judging or on judgment, but you
understand that the truth of God's Word is that we are to judge all things. We
understand that people say, judge not lest you be judged, that's a Bible truth
as well, and the reality though is that with the judgment that we would speak of,
if we are to engage in judgment, it is to be based upon the truth of the Word of
God. And we understand here that as these individuals, these legalists, if you will,
if we can use that phraseology, we find that the reference here, and understand
in the first century there is a really interesting period of time,
transitional period of time that's taking place, and Jews are saved and
Gentiles are saved, and the church, this mystery that's made up of Jew and
Gentile, and you think about this transitional period of time and
really some difficulties, and it was a great opportunity, if you will, for these
false teachers to pounce on it, and for these false teachers to come in, and you
understand that false teachers are opportunistic. They're going to seize the
opportunity that presents itself in order to propagate their false teaching
and to deceive as many as they possibly can. We find here that as these
references that are given in verse 16 and 17 with subject to this trap of
legalism, they have obvious reference to the Old Testament law. We find that it's
interesting, and we'll look at verse 16 in more detail here in just a moment, but
it's interesting that as Paul says, let no man therefore judge you in these
things, and we'll look at it in a moment, notice what he says in verse 17, which
are a shadow of things to come, but the body is of Christ. Remember last year we
preached through the book of Hebrews, and what a great truth that God gives us in
Hebrews chapter number 10, one of my just favorite passages of Scripture when
the Bible begins in verse number 1 of Hebrews 10, and says, for the law having a
shadow of good things to come, and not the very image of the things, can never,
with those sacrifices which they offered year by year continually, make the comers
thereunto perfect. Talks about the blood of bulls and goats, and it should not
take away sins, but we find that as we enter and go further through the text of
Scripture in Hebrews 10, that the Bible says, but this man, speaking of the Lord
Jesus Christ in verse number 12 of Hebrews 10, after he'd offered one
sacrifice for sins forever, sat down on the right hand of God. I'm so thankful
for the Lord Jesus Christ. And we find that false teachers, the reality is that
as you would boil things down and look at all of the false teachers that are
prevalent, they all err within the scope of how they deal with Christ. And
looking at, listen, we understand that Christ is sufficient, that the sacrifice
that he made on the cross of Calvary satisfied the demands of a holy God, and
he is all we need, and we find that here the Old Testament, it's a shadow of
things to come, but Christ has come, and Christ has fulfilled the law. And we find
here that these legalists, they're judging people, notice in particular in
verse number 16, in meat or in drink or in respect of a holy day or of the new
moon or of the Sabbath days. Notice with me this truth that is given here in the
way in which they're judging, and I want you to hold your place here in Colossians,
and we have the benefit this morning of having the entire canon of Scripture. And
by the way, that is a huge benefit. You understand in the first century, these
believers in Colossae, as they're receiving this letter, they don't have
the same benefit that we have this morning of turning here and turning
there and looking at this passage and looking at that passage and comparing
Scripture with Scripture, but we have that benefit and that blessing, and we
find that as we look at the whole of Scripture that we're able to determine
the mind of the Lord and we're able to easier, it becomes easier for us to
identify false teaching. Notice with regard to meat, notice over in 1st
Timothy chapter number 4, turn over to that passage if you will, and notice what
Paul is saying to Timothy here in this portion of Scripture. He's dealing here
again with these false teachers and talking about those that would come in
and just the way in which they speak lies and hypocrisy and so on and so forth.
But as we look here in 1st Timothy chapter number 4, it says in verse
number 3, forbidding to marry and commanding to abstain from meats which
God hath created to be received with thanksgiving of them which believe and
know the truth. For every creature of God is good and nothing to be refused if it
be received with thanksgiving for it is sanctified by the Word of God and prayer.
I'm thankful for this passage of Scripture. Listen, dietary things have
changed, pre-flood, post-flood, the law, after the law, the fulfillment of the New
Testament, the fulfillment of Christ and the law in the New Testament. You see
here, he says every creature of God is good and nothing to be refused if it be
received with thanksgiving, and I'm thankful for the truth of the Word of
God. They were judging in meat, not only in meat, in drink. There's a very simple
verse of Scripture that we know in 1st Corinthians 10 and verse number 31,
whether therefore you eat or drink or whatsoever you do, what does it say? Do
all to the glory of God. Amen? Think about this thing of holy days. It's mentioned
in verse number 16 of Colossians chapter number 2, and you
think about the reference here again as I've mentioned this transitional period
in the New Testament and understanding the way in which these Jews that would
have been saved and part of the church, this mystery, the Jews and Gentiles as
one body of believers, and you think about these false teachers and they're
judging with respect to holy days, new moon, the Sabbath days. I just finished
reading through the book of Leviticus again, and you read through the book of
Leviticus and you read all about their feast and all about the various aspects
of the Jewish calendar and how they had their Sabbaths and how they had all of
their feasts and so on and so forth, and there were three times in a year in
which all the males were to present themselves, and you just look at how
their calendar operated and how it was focused upon those things, and we
understand that if we look again at what he says in verse number 17, which are a
shadow of things to come. Listen, when you study all of the truth of the Old
Testament, you begin to look at those feast days and all of the sacrifices and
all of those truths that are given, you find that they point to the Lord
Jesus Christ. The typology is rich when you study through the tabernacle and you
study the various pieces of furniture and the materials that were used for
construction, and you see how it points to Christ in typology. It's beautiful, but
it was a shadow. And so Christ has come and Christ has fulfilled the law, and
these folks are judging and they're bringing their judgment, and Paul says,
let no man therefore judge you. Notice what the Bible says in Romans chapter
number 14 with regard to this truth of this last phrase there in verse number
16 with regard to the trap of legalism. And in Romans chapter number 14, in verse
number 5, many still turning, give you a moment there, Romans 14 and verse number
5. I learned something on Wednesday night in the message. Actually, I learned
many things in the message. I've enjoyed the study through Psalm 23, but I heard
someone say, hey, don't start reading until I get there. And then my dad used
what Brother Ken Sparks used during the youth rally, say amen when you get there.
And the problem is some people are gonna get there faster than other people, but
the reality is that I'm thankful. It's always good to hear the pages of God's
Word turning, amen. I'm mindful when I hear that of the people, some of our
missionaries that we support, that they can't say to their folks, take your Bible
and turn to, because they don't have Bibles. Side note, back to Romans 14, verse
number 5. Notice what he says, one man esteemeth one day above another, another
esteemeth every day alike. Let every man be fully persuaded in his own mind. And
again, dealing with the transitional nature. Listen, the reality is that the
Sabbath was a sign for the Jews. It was a specific instruction that
was given to the Jews as a nation, the nation of Israel. And we understand that
as you study the book of Hebrews, and we did that last year, and you understand
the Sabbath of rest that we have, that rest in Christ. And what a blessing to
have that rest in the Lord Jesus Christ.
He is Christ.
And we find here that these folks
were coming in and they were judging
and they were dealing with
these new believers
and they were seeking to trap them
in legalism.
I want to share a few additional verses of Scripture
with you while you're here
in Romans 14.
Look, if you will, at verse 13.
It says,
"...let us not therefore judge one another any more,
but judge this rather,
that no man put a stumbling block
for an occasion to fall in his brother's way."
And this really is a great segue verse
to what Paul deals with
with the believers in Corinth
with regard to the subject of becoming
a stumbling block.
And the reality in which this could be,
especially in this first century
within the church
and all of the transitional nature
of that which was going on,
it was very possible for those
to engage in behavior
that could potentially be a stumbling block.
Look over, if you will,
1 Corinthians 8.
Notice here what Paul says
to this church in Corinth.
Now, the church in Corinth
had lots of difficulties.
And they were, of course,
dealing with many attacks
and there was division and discord
within the members,
within the ranks of the church.
And Paul is seeking to give them instruction
and seeking to help them
and calling them to spiritual maturity
and growth.
He says this in 1 Corinthians 8,
beginning in verse 8,
"...but meat commendeth us not to God.
For neither if we eat are we the better,
neither if we eat not are we the worse.
But take heed, lest by any means
this liberty of yours
become a stumbling block to them
that are weak.
For if any man see thee
which hast knowledge,
he that eateth meat in the idol's temple
shall not the conscience of him
which is weak be emboldened
to eat those things which are offered to idols?
And through thy knowledge
shall the weak brother perish
for whom Christ died.
But when ye sin so against the brethren
and wound their weak conscience,
ye sin against Christ.
Wherefore, if meat make my brother to offend..."
Notice what Paul says,
"...I'll eat no flesh while the world standeth,
lest I make my brother to offend."
So there's this aspect that Paul deals with
and really in the first century here
dealing with this subject of stumbling block
and not causing others to be offended
and so on and so forth,
understanding some that are weak in Christ
and they're babes in Christ
and trying to help them and encourage them
and bring them along in their spiritual journey
and their growth and their walk with Christ.
And we find that Paul deals with this subject
and really the idea of becoming a stumbling block.
He gives further information to this.
We mentioned already in Romans,
but look in 1 Corinthians 10,
just turn over a few pages if you will.
Notice the way that he mentions it here
in verse number 23 of 1 Corinthians 10.
I believe that this was a life principle
that helped guide decisions not only for Paul,
but perhaps as we would implement in our lives as well.
It would be helpful.
Look at what he says,
"...all things are lawful for me,
but all things are not expedient."
All things are lawful for me,
but all things edify not.
And just having that understanding
and that awareness of how the actions
that we may engage in would affect,
impact someone else,
especially with regard to a younger believer.
And so we find that Paul gives much truth
within the Word of God
with regard to the liberty that we have,
with regard to the way in which Christ has set us free.
We're not to use our liberty as an occasion to the flesh.
He deals with that in Galatians chapter number five.
But we understand that these individuals,
these legalists,
and he's speaking of this trap of legalism here
and this dependence of moral law.
You understand the law cannot save.
If the law could save,
Paul deals with that in Galatians as well.
if righteousness came by the law,
then Christ is dead and vain.
Amen?
And so the law cannot save.
It's the law that condemns.
It's the law that says,
guilty.
And so they're saying,
we're going to follow these moral laws
as opposed to this dependence
or this understanding of this personal faith
in the finished work of Jesus Christ
on the cross of Calvary.
Peter makes an interesting claim,
and you don't need to turn there,
but it's interesting because
some of these false teachers
and really all of them to a degree
have this focus
as we'll look at these three traps this morning.
But Peter says this,
while they promise them liberty,
they themselves are the servants of corruption.
You know, there are false teachers who say,
well, if you do this,
it's going to bring this level of liberty.
It's going to bring this level of awareness
and knowledge and so on and so forth.
And Peter says, listen,
they promise liberty,
but they themselves are the servants of corruption.
We find that we must be grounded
upon the truth of the Word of God.
Avoid the trap of legalism.
This false teaching fails to recognize
that the Lord Jesus Christ fulfilled the law.
It fails to recognize the fact
that what Jesus Christ did on the cross of Calvary
was sufficient to pay for the sin of mankind.
Listen, you can't help Christ pay your sin debt.
Amen?
By the way, you ought to be happy about that.
He didn't pay a portion and say the rest is up to you.
No, no. He said, it is finished.
It is finished.
And we are complete in Him.
What a wonderful truth of the Word of God.
The trap of legalism, number one.
Number two, the trap of mysticism.
The trap of mysticism.
We see this in verses 18 and 19.
And really, these mystics,
they would have this idea
that spiritual apprehension of knowledge
is inaccessible to the intellect,
that it may be obtained
or it must be attained
through contemplation and self-surrender.
And it's very interesting
when you think about mysticism
and obviously some of that which still exists today
and even here in the first century.
We find what it talks about here in verse 18 in particular
how that they intrude into those things
which He hath not seen,
vainly puffed up by His fleshly mind
and this mystic kind of perspective.
And notice what Paul says to begin verse 18
just as he began verse 16,
let no man therefore judge you.
Notice what he says here in verse 18,
let no man beguile you of your reward.
And it says in a voluntary humility
and worshiping of angels.
But think about that phrase,
let no man beguile you of your reward.
The idea of this particular word,
it's interesting, it's only used here,
this Greek word is only used here in verse 18.
We find that the English word beguile
is used in verse 4 of our text of Scripture,
but it's a different Greek word
with just a slightly different meaning.
But here the idea of this word beguile
is to defraud or beguile of the prize of victory.
Really, he says beguile you of your reward
in a voluntary humility and worshiping of angels.
Intruding, notice what he says,
into those things which he hath not seen,
vainly puffed up by his fleshly mind.
They begin to talk about these things.
They begin to speak about the way
in which they've attained some level
of spiritual awareness and knowledge
because of that which they have engaged in.
He speaks here in verse 18
of this worshiping of angels.
You understand that angels are mentioned
all throughout the Word of God,
but never, never are angels to be worshiped.
Not one time in all of the Word of God
are you to worship angels.
Never.
You're not to worship angels. Why?
Because you worship God.
You worship God.
There's no worshiping of angels.
In fact, as you read throughout the Word of God
and you read of angels and you read of their ministry
and their ministering servants
and so on and so forth,
and we're so thankful for the ministry of angels
that God in His knowledge created in angels,
that they are created beings.
He is the Creator.
He created these angels,
and you find that angels worship God.
They don't receive worship.
Remember reading the book of Revelation
and John is going to worship?
No, no, no, no!
Worship God!
Amen.
He is worthy of our worship.
This thing of worshiping angels,
in fact, some of them they would seek
to have really this idea of this contemplation
and self-surrender and it says there
that they're vainly puffed up by this fleshly mind,
but it also says this voluntary humility.
They almost have this perspective
that we're not good enough to worship God,
so we're going to start by worshiping angels.
And they would try to convince people
to engage in this worshiping of angels.
We're not to worship angels.
Never has it been commanded in the Word of God
to worship angels.
And we finally begin to get into this
really dangerous situation.
You're on dangerous ground
when you get into this mysticism stuff.
And we find that they get into this
and they begin to, as it says,
that they intrude into those things
which they know not.
Why is it, if we would begin to think about
the failure on the part of the mystics
in this idea of mysticism,
I believe that the answer is given to us
in verse 19 as to why,
where they've gone astray,
where they've missed it.
We said of the legalists
that they missed understanding
that Christ and His payment was sufficient.
Here in this text of Scripture,
thinking about mystics,
where they missed it
is that they failed to put Christ
in His proper position.
Notice verse 19.
It says,
and not holding the head.
Is that?
the capital in your Bible?
Why?
Because speaking of Christ,
do you remember what Paul said
back in chapter 1?
It might be on the same page for you.
It's a page different for me.
But look back if you will.
Remember the great discourse
that Paul gives in Colossians 1
on exalting the Lord Jesus Christ.
And he says in v. 15,
who is the image of the invisible God,
the firstborn of every creature.
For by Him were all things created
that are in heaven, that are in earth,
visible and invisible,
whether they be thrones or dominions
or principalities or powers.
All things were created by Him and for Him.
And He, Christ, is before all things
and by Him all things consist.
And He is the head of the body,
the church, who is the beginning,
the firstborn from the dead,
that in all things,
He might have the preeminence.
You understand that the Lord Jesus Christ
when He gave the promise to Peter
with regard to the church,
He said, I will build My church
and the gates of hell shall not prevail against it.
Why did He make the statement that way?
Because it's His church.
He's the head of it.
Paul deals with this here in Colossians.
He deals with it in other portions of Scripture.
He deals with the believers in Ephesus.
And we understand the truth
of the headship of the Lord Jesus Christ
that He is the head.
Listen, when you don't have Christ
in His proper position,
things get messed up.
Not only in church, but in your life.
In your home. Right?
Christ has to have that proper position.
We had wall art in our home
in Manassas where it said
Christ is the head of our home.
And He is.
And we understand that He's the head of the church.
Notice it says,
"...and not holding the head,
from which all the body..."
Remember, the church is represented
in the book of 1 Corinthians, Romans as well,
"...as being a body of believers,
from which all the body, by joints and bands,
having nourishment, ministered,
and knit together,
increases with the increase of God."
Listen, when we worship God
as we're supposed to,
when we have the Lord Jesus Christ
in His proper position,
as He is entitled to,
we find that He provides us
with everything we need.
We don't need to intrude into these things
that they know not of.
We don't need to get into this mysticism
kind of a situation.
And you begin to think about these
that have experienced and they've dabbled
in some of this mysticism kind of stuff,
and they begin to talk about,
well, you have this experience,
and you begin to look at some maybe
of the charismatic type movements
that would be fallen into these traps of mysticism,
and they begin to have this perspective
of unless you experience the same thing
that I've experienced,
then you've not attained some level of spirituality.
But if I'm complete in Him,
what does complete mean?
Are there more levels of spiritual attaining?
No, I'm complete.
Yes, it's true that I'm to be sanctified,
and I'm to be walking with Him,
and I can be closer to Him as I abide in Him,
but there's not this mysticism kind of stuff
that's going on.
I shared the illustration many years ago,
but I remember knocking on a door
and giving an invitation,
trying to share the Gospel with an individual
as I was out door knocking,
and as I was door knocking on that particular day,
I think Juliana was actually with me.
It was many, many years ago,
and we think, and she was just real young,
and this lady answered the door,
began to have a conversation with her,
and she said something like this.
I asked her if she knew for sure that heaven was home,
and she said, absolutely.
And now, you don't get that too often
when you go door knocking,
and with that level of certainty, right?
And I said, man, that's wonderful.
Can you tell me how, I mean, when'd you get saved?
How do you know for sure heaven's your home?
And without any hesitation and 100% convinced,
she said this, I've spoken in tongues.
That was her answer.
And then she said this,
are you sure that you're going to heaven?
And I said, yes, ma'am.
And she said, oh yeah, when did you speak in tongues?
That was her measuring rod.
That was her standard by which you determine salvation.
Now, how does that work with the Word of God?
It doesn't work.
And the reality this morning
is that this mysticism stuff is dangerous.
Notice the danger here that Paul mentions
in 2 Corinthians 11.
Keep your place here in Colossians.
We'll get back there in just a moment,
but I want you to really see
the depth of the danger of this mysticism.
In 2 Corinthians chapter number 11,
Paul says this in verse number 13,
for such are false apostles.
Again, we're talking about false teachers.
We're talking about the traps of false teaching.
Paul deals with three of them in Colossae
that were prevalent, legalism.
Now we're looking at mysticism.
Notice what he says here in verse 13
of 2 Corinthians 11, for such are false apostles,
deceitful workers, transforming themselves
into the apostles of Christ.
But notice verse 14, in no marvel,
for Satan himself is transformed
into an angel of light.
Therefore, it is no great thing
if his ministers also be transformed
as the ministers of righteousness
whose end shall be according to their works.
That's a grave warning, is it not?
The dangers of mysticism are serious.
And we find here that as we would understand
the truth of the word of God,
and we'd understand that as we look
at this passage of Scripture,
and we see the danger that Paul speaks of
with even Satan himself transforming himself
into an angel of light, here's the catch.
Here's the truth of the word of God
is that John says this in 1 John 4,
Beloved, believe not every spirit,
but try the spirits, whether they are of God,
because many false prophets are gone out into the world.
And then he says this,
Hereby I know you the Spirit of God.
Every spirit that confesseth that Jesus Christ
is come in the flesh is of God.
Where do they err?
They err with regard to the person of Christ.
And we find here that these mystics,
they fail to put Christ in his proper position
as being the head.
And Paul warns the believers in Corinth
that listen, don't marvel at this.
It's not a great thing if his ministers
transform as the ministers of righteousness.
And so be careful.
And John says, listen, we need to try the spirits.
Believe not every spirit.
Try the spirits.
How do we try them?
The word of God.
Remember what I say in the beginning,
the answer to error is always truth.
Why did the believers in Berea get commended?
Who knows?
Why were they commended?
Mark?
They searched the Scriptures daily.
Who was preaching to them?
The apostles.
And they're searching,
and they're trying to find out, is this true?
Listen, the work of the Bereans,
the work of us as a believer,
Paul says this, that we're to be students
of the word of God.
Study to show thyself approved unto God.
A workman that needeth not to be ashamed,
rightly dividing the word of truth.
Listen, we need to be settled and grounded
in the word of God.
And when these mystics and their approach
that is given here in chapter 2, verse 18,
with regard to that which they were engaging in,
it was important that you try the spirits.
And that you beware.
Let no man beguile you of your reward.
I'm thankful that Christ is the head of the church.
I'm thankful when you think about legalism
that Christ's atonement,
that His payment on the cross of Calvary
is sufficient for the sin debt of mankind.
And He's the head of the church.
Danger number three, verses 20 through 23,
it's the trap of asceticism.
Asceticism is a severe self-discipline
and evidence of all forms of indulgence
for religious reasons.
In your mind, as you think about the one
that would be really taken up in this trap of asceticism,
you would think about a monk.
But you know, you can never deal with the flesh
with the flesh.
It doesn't work.
And so sometimes these monks,
they try to go to these monasteries
and they're gonna get away from everything that's evil.
But they take their flesh to where they're going.
And guess what?
The flesh is at enmity with the spirit.
Is that not what the book of Galatians says
in the fifth chapter?
And so the reality is that if our flesh
is at enmity with the spirit,
we can get rid of every toy and every gadget
and everything and go to some secluded place,
but I take my flesh with me.
I take my flesh with me.
And so before long, I'm gonna have all kinds of problems.
Right?
Because we've got our flesh.
And it's at enmity with the spirit.
I believe that as we look at these verses of scripture
that the failure on the part of
of these that would be in the trap of asceticism
is that they fail to recognize
what our position is in Christ.
And really, when there's a failure
to understand our position in Christ,
it leads to being enslaved.
It leads to being enslaved.
Paul says this, and you don't need to turn there,
but just a reminder as we begin to look at these verses,
that Paul says this in Galatians 5, verse 1,
stand fast therefore in the liberty
wherewith Christ hath made us free,
and be not entangled again with the yoke of bondage.
Listen, if I've been made free,
if I've been set free by the truth,
why do I wanna be in bondage again?
And here it's this failure of recognizing
what our position is in Christ.
Notice how he begins verse number 20.
In verse number 16 and 18,
when he talks about these first two traps,
he says, let no man therefore judge you.
Let no man beguile you.
But notice how he begins verse number 20.
Wherefore, if ye be dead with Christ
from the rudiments of the world,
why, as though living in the world,
are you subject to ordinances?
If you are in Christ, if you be dead with Christ,
if you have been, notice the reference really,
I believe, is back to the text that we studied last week
in verses 11 through 15,
when he talks about the way in which we were quick
and we were made alive and what Christ did for us
on the cross of Calvary.
There's a reference, no doubt,
when he talks about ye be dead with Christ
from the rudiments of the world.
Remember, it was back in verse number eight
of Colossians 2 that Paul says,
beware lest any man spoil you
through philosophy and vain deceit
after the tradition of men,
after the rudiments of the world,
and not after Christ.
And so Paul says, listen, if you're dead with Christ
from the rudiments of the world,
why, as though living in the world,
are you subject to these ordinances?
Now, it's also interesting when he mentions
this word ordinances at the end of verse number 20,
it makes my mind circle back to what we read
in verse number 14 last Sunday morning,
where the Bible says blotting out
the handwriting of ordinances that was against us.
And it was against us.
You read the law, guilty, right?
Just don't even read all of the law,
the 630 plus aspects of the law,
just read the 10 commandments.
Which one among us could stand up and say,
I've kept them all?
No.
And Jesus says, listen, we talk about thou shalt not kill.
Jesus says, if you hate your brother,
it's like you killed him.
Thou shalt not commit adultery.
If you think upon a woman to lust after her,
you've committed adultery in your mind.
Well, that takes it to a whole nother level.
Does it not?
Seriously.
It's not, I didn't do the act.
Okay, Jesus comes along and makes sure
we're all understanding that we're condemned.
Right?
So there's only one word when we stand up against the law.
Guilty.
But Jesus, thank God for what he did
on the cross of Calvary.
He blotted out the handwriting of ordinances
that was against us, which was contrary to us,
and he took it out of the way,
nailing it to his cross.
And so therefore, Paul says, listen,
if you've been born again, if you're a child of God,
why are you gonna be subject to these ordinances?
And then he kind of lists them.
Touch not, taste not, handle not,
which all are to perish with the using.
Notice the end of verse number 22.
After the commandments and doctrines of who?
Men.
Not after God, but after men.
You know, the Pharisees.
Man, they were a fine group of people, were they not?
Whew.
Vipers.
I mean, Jesus went after those guys.
They had so many man-made additions
to what God had already said in his word,
they couldn't fulfill what they were trying
to make other people fulfill.
And here we find that Paul says this trap of asceticism,
that this severe self-discipline
and this avoidance of all forms of indulgence
for these religious reasons
that it's going to take you to some level
of attaining some spirituality
that could be attained no other way,
be careful of that trap, why?
Because you're complete in Christ.
You're complete in Him.
Verse 23, it says this,
which things have indeed a show of wisdom
and will worship and humility and neglecting of the body,
not in any honor to the satisfying of the flesh.
You think about those same people
that I mentioned a moment ago, those Pharisees,
and how did they pray?
Man, they wanted everybody to hear them pray, right?
What did they do when they fasted?
Hey, listen, Ryan, just so you know, I'm fasting today,
so just, I just want to make you know that.
Don't invite me to go to lunch with you
because I'm fasting today.
What did Jesus say?
You have your reward.
What's the reward?
The praise of men.
Did you hear them pray?
Did you hear their fasting again?
You have your reward.
It's the praise of men.
This idea of these, a show of wisdom and will worship
and humility, neglecting the body.
Remember, when the Pharisee and the Publican were praying,
what's the Pharisee?
I thank God that I'm not like him.
Is that not what the Word of God tells us?
The Publican.
He said, have mercy, I'm a sinner.
And so we see here this morning
that as we look at these three traps
that were prevalent here for the believers in Colossae,
the trap of legalism, the trap of mysticism,
the trap of asceticism,
that in each of these particular situations
that they would deal with,
they needed to have truth given to them.
And they needed to understand that we must keep Christ
in his proper place.
Listen, the truth of legalism there
when he talks about a shadow of things to come,
but the body is of Christ.
I'm thankful that we have the real thing,
not just a shadow.
How many of you have ever seen a shadow?
You know what a shadow is, right?
So let's just use, Michael, you're sitting up here,
and James and Wyatt, and Alice is too little for this,
but you're walking out this evening,
and James or Wyatt, they see your shadow.
Why do they see your shadow?
Because you're there.
Now what kind of sense would it make for James or Wyatt
to go try to hug the shadow
if dad is right there?
Right?
I'm not chasing the shadow of the law.
It was a shadow of good things to come,
and it pointed to Christ, but Christ has come,
and he's our savior.
And we understand that he is sufficient,
that he satisfied all of the demands
to pay for the sin of mankind.
Listen, he's the head.
He is the head.
And in all things, he must have the preeminence.
We gotta keep him in his rightful place.
And if we don't have him in his rightful place,
things get messed up.
We find here with the last truth,
they fail to recognize what our position is in Christ.
I'm so thankful to be a child of God,
adopted in the family of God,
to be joint heirs with the Lord Jesus Christ,
to understand that I have reserved in heaven for me
an inheritance that's incorruptible, undefiled.
It fadeth not away.
It's reserved in heaven for me.
What a blessing to know that any time
I can go directly into the throne room of God
because of Jesus Christ,
because of what he did for me, what he did for you.
And this morning, we need to be careful
of the traps of false teaching.
I understand that they may vary for us today
and dealing here with these in Colossae,
but some of these traps that exist today,
we need to be careful.
We need to try the Spirit.
Don't believe it.
Well, he's a preacher and he's got this many followers.
I mean, he must be right.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
Be careful.
We must grow in grace and the knowledge
of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ.
And that growth comes through a proper walk with God.
Yes, we're to abide with him, in him,
and we're to walk with him.
And yes, the word of God does give us instruction
of things that please him and things that do not please him.
But we understand that we are complete in him.
And what a wonderful truth of the word of God.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the word that you've given us,
this precious Bible.
And God, we thank you that you've given us truth.
And even as we referenced earlier this morning
of Romans 8, the truth shall make you free.
I'm so thankful to have been given the freedom
that Paul spoke of in Galatians chapter number five,
and have no desire to be entangled again.
and any kind of bondage, I pray that you'd help us to take heed to the
warning and instruction that was given in this portion of Scripture for these
believers, and to understand that today the false teachers are still prevalent,
and they're still seeking to propagate their teachings, and they're still
seeking to trap, to take captive as many as they can. Help us to know the truth, to
stand for truth. If there's one that's been influenced and impacted by false
teaching, at whatever level it may be, oh God, would you help them and deliver them
from that at this very hour. Help us, God, to run to you and to your word. May it be
that you have your rightful position in our lives, and that we
understand that we are complete in you. If there's one that's not sure of heaven,
they've never been saved, but yet they're in our midst today. They've not had that
handwriting of ordinances that was against them. They've not had it blotted
out. They've not had it nailed to the cross. They're still dead in their
trespasses and sins. Oh Holy Spirit, we pray that you would convict of sin, of
Christ's righteousness, and of judgment to come. They would make a decision before
they would leave this place, to place their faith and trust in the finished
work of Christ at Calvary, understanding that today is the day of salvation. Help
us, God, do a work in our lives, and we'll thank you for it. Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed. Kimberly's going to play quietly on the
piano, and as she does, the altar is open. You can come to the old-fashioned altar,
you can make your pew an altar, but as she plays, the altar is open. Let's allow
God to have His way in our lives.