of Judges, I mean the Old Testament, Judges chapter number 13, this morning, Judges chapter
number 13, and with each passing year, I realize personally what a great honor and responsibility
it is to have children.
And I remember not long ago someone asked me this question, what is the hardest stage
of parenting?
And I said, the one that you're actively in.
Sometimes people think, well I can't wait until these kids get older, and then they
get older and it's a whole new dynamic, I can't wait until these kids fill in the blank
and it's a whole other dynamic, but when they leave the house, it's a whole other dynamic.
Those of you that have had each of those stages, you understand, you also understand how quickly
time goes, you wonder when they're going through that, we often refer to it as terrible twos
kind of a time, you say, when is this ever going to end?
And then you just seemingly blink an eye and they're teenagers, and then they're beyond
teenagers, and it's quite amazing, and I understand it's a great honor, great responsibility
to have children.
The Bible teaches us that children are inherited to the Lord, and the fruit of the womb is
His reward.
I can still remember with clarity, and it's not that long ago, but I can still remember
quite vividly when Holly told me that she was expecting our firstborn.
Of course that's Juliana, at the time we did not know whether it would be a boy or girl,
and so we remember that, I remember that day, and I remember her sharing that with me, and
I'll be honest with you, I had some mixed emotions immediately upon hearing that news,
I had some mixed emotions.
For one, I was excited, and I was thankful for the fact that God was blessing us with
a child.
But at the very same time, I was nervous and fearful.
Why?
Because I was aware of the great responsibility that it was to have children and to raise
children to follow the admonition that's on the front of the bulletin this morning, bring
them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord.
And I remember thinking a couple of thoughts, really all at the same time, and I wondered
something like this, am I gonna know what to do?
I wondered something like this, am I really ready for this?
And I remember looking at Evan, November of, I guess it was, she was born last year, 2023,
so November of 2022, and I remember looking at Evan and saying, are you sure that you're
ready to be a father?
And he said, oh yeah, and I said, oh my.
I think they're watching livestream this morning, but I thought to myself that when I found
out that we're having our firstborn, I immediately recognized I don't know that I'm ready for
this.
But you know what I learned through the years?
If you depend upon the Lord and you trust the Lord for the wisdom and the direction
that only He can give, that God will guide and God will direct and God will help.
The Bible teaches us that He's a very present help in the time of trouble, and He teaches
us in His Word that if we recognize that we lack wisdom, that if we ask that He will give
wisdom.
And we'll reference that verse of Scripture as we go through the message this morning,
but the reality is that we come to Judges chapter number 13 this morning, and as we
come to this passage of Scripture in our text this morning, Manoah and his wife had no children.
We do not know their ages, but we do understand that the Bible tells us that Manoah's wife
was barren.
She had no children.
But she received this announcement, she received word that she would have a son.
If you begin reading with me in Judges 13 and verse number 1, the Bible says, and the
children of Israel did evil again in the sight of the Lord, and the Lord delivered them into
the hand of the Philistines forty years.
And now as God gives us in verse number 1 the backdrop of what's going on in Israel
broadly speaking, the text of Scripture goes in to verse number 2 and begins to share with
us a particular family in Israel.
As we look at this text of Scripture, it says there was a certain man of Zorah of the family
of the Danites whose name was Manoah, and his wife was barren and bare not.
And the angel of the Lord appeared unto the woman and said unto her, Behold now, thou
art barren and barest not.
Notice this, but thou shalt conceive and bear a son.
We're going to look at the whole chapter, but I want you to skip down to verse number
8, if you will, and look at what the Bible says.
Then Manoah entreated the Lord and said, O my Lord, let the man of God which thou did
send come again unto us, and teach us what we shall do unto the child that shall be born.
Skip down to verse number 12, Manoah said, Now let thy words come to pass.
How shall we order the child, and how shall we do unto him?
If you've looked at the bulletin this morning, I've titled the message really from verse
number 12 of our text, How Shall We Order the Child?
How shall we order the child?
As we look at the text of Scripture and we think about Father's Day, and we understand
the great responsibility that it is to raise our children, I look at this question that
is asked of Manoah, and I look at this text of Scripture, and I find that God gives us
some instruction that is helpful.
Regardless of what stage you are in life, and quite honestly, whether you're a father
or not here this morning, the truth from Judges chapter number 13 is applicable to you and
will be helpful in your life as we look at this interaction between Manoah, his wife,
and the Lord.
Now, taking notes, number one this morning, there is a recognition of deficiency.
There is a recognition of deficiency.
In general, general terms this morning, human beings, especially men, if I could add that,
and all the ladies will appreciate it, they have a really hard time recognizing their
deficiencies.
Human beings in general.
We have a hard time recognizing our deficiencies.
The fact of the matter is that God warns us many times in His Word about pride.
He warns us not to think more highly of ourselves than we ought.
He tells us that pride destroys, that pride, only by pride cometh contention.
He tells us that He resisteth the proud, and yet we continue to have difficulties in the
area of pride.
The Bible teaches us that we as Christians are to be clothed in humility, that we're
to humble ourselves in the sight of the Lord, but we find, generally speaking, we have difficulties
recognizing our deficiencies.
Unfortunately, this difficulty has a way of leading to even more difficulties in our lives.
We recognize, we fail to recognize that we have a deficiency, it's difficult for us to
acknowledge that, and because we do not recognize our deficiencies, it leads to more problems,
it leads to more difficulties and more trials in our lives.
And we find that this morning, that when we consider this idea of recognizing our deficiency,
or a recognition of deficiency, is that what happens when we fail to recognize that pride,
not only does it displease the Lord, but many times in our lives it leads to living independent.
Independent of God, and independent of the help that we can get from God, and if we're
not careful, when we go through life, if we fail to recognize the deficiency, we live
in a society that wants to puff ourselves up, to think that we know more than we really
know, to think that we're capable of doing more than we're really able to do, that we
don't need, but the reality is that we do need.
We're a needy people.
There's a short book that I read years ago, in fact, I gave it to several of our men at
that time, and it was a really short read, you could probably read it in 20 or 30 minutes,
and the book was titled, I Am Not Okay, and it was all about pride, and the reality is
that here in our text of Scripture, we find that there was a recognition of deficiency
on the part of Manoah.
I believe that though, if we fail to recognize our deficiencies, it leads to independent
living, that when an individual recognizes their deficiencies, it reveals humility,
and it leads to dependent living.
Listen, we, I understand that so often we speak about, I have my rights, I have my,
I'm independent, so on and so forth, but when we think about the Christian life, the Christian
life must be lived in dependence on the Lord.
In fact, Jesus said it this way, I am the vine, you're the branches, and He says this,
without me, ye can do nothing.
We must abide in Him.
Before we ever will follow that path, we must recognize our deficiencies.
As we look at the text of Scripture, I find that this man, Manoah, when he receives the
word from his wife with regard to the interaction that she had, that he recognized his deficiencies.
Why do I say that?
Well, because number two, if you're taking notes, there's a request for direction.
There's a request for direction.
I would submit to you this morning that no one is going to make a request for direction
unless they first recognize their deficiency.
Amen?
You're not gonna ask for help.
You're not gonna request direction.
if you think you got it, if you think you can handle it,
if you think you know the way,
you're not gonna ask for help.
I remember when we made the decision to drive,
well, we didn't really make the decision,
the Marine Corps changed duty stations for my dad
and we were driving from New Jersey to Nevada.
And that was back in the day,
not only did you not have cell phones,
but you didn't even have those little Garmin GPS things,
you had the Rand McNally maps, amen?
You guys remember using those?
And it was, you'd look at the page
and then on the right-hand side,
it would say joins to page number or map number 41
and you'd flip on over and sure enough,
page 41 was the continuation of the map
and I sat in the front seat of my dad's truck
and I was the navigator.
We had never driven across country before,
I mean, what a trip.
And I remember the very first day,
we were gonna stop in a town in Pennsylvania
to visit with my aunt and uncle.
And we were gonna stop there and visit with them.
And I'm gonna tell you, my dad,
we had two vehicles going,
my dad and I were in the pickup truck
and my mom and brother were in the minivan behind
and we drove around that little town about seven times.
And we just kept driving around and around and around
because my dad knew where we were going.
He knew where we were going.
And I'm like, dad, I'm pretty sure
we crossed these railroad tracks like six times already.
I'm pretty sure that's the same convenience store
that we passed.
I'm pretty sure we've been here.
Finally, my dad pulls into a little convenience store
and guess what he does?
He asks for directions.
But before he asked for directions,
he had to recognize that there was a deficiency,
he didn't know where he was going.
And he had to ask for direction.
Here in our text of scripture,
Manoah, because he recognized his deficiency,
he makes a request.
And the request is a request for direction.
Can I submit to you this morning
that whether you're a father, whether you're a mother,
whether you're a husband, a wife, a child,
a single individual, whoever you are,
whatever your stage is in life,
whatever your position is in life,
you need God's direction.
You absolutely need God's direction.
You can't navigate life on your own.
You can try.
You're gonna find that you're gonna take
a lot of wrong turns, a lot of troubled paths.
The Bible tells us that the steps of a good man
are ordered by the Lord.
The Bible tells us that God will lead us in a plain path.
He'll make the directions, he'll provide us with a way.
The Bible tells us that we're to trust in the Lord
with all of our hearts,
that we're not to lean on our own understanding,
but we're to acknowledge him.
He says that he will direct our paths.
This morning, I don't care what your stage of life,
what your arena of life is today,
you need God's direction.
Manoah recognized that he needed direction.
He makes that request, why?
Because he's never been a father before,
because he never had children.
He didn't know what to do, how to do,
and because he recognized his deficiency,
he made this request for direction.
We read it already in verse number eight,
but notice, the Bible tells us,
then Manoah entreated the Lord.
And notice what he says,
oh my Lord, let the men of God which thou did send.
Now we'll get to this in just a moment in our final point,
where we spend most of our time this morning.
We find that Manoah's wife received the announcement
before Manoah did.
Manoah's wife shares that information with Manoah,
so then Manoah says, send again.
It says, oh my Lord, let the man of God
which thou did send come again unto us.
For what purpose?
To teach us what we shall do
unto the child that shall be born.
Very interesting, there's a measure of faith
with regard to the announcement that was made
when the angel of the Lord appeared there to Manoah's wife,
and it says, thou shalt conceive and bear a son.
Now Manoah, as he received that communication from his wife,
he says, teach us what we shall do
unto the child that shall be born.
He expected that the child would be born,
but he made a request for direction.
We read in verse number 12,
where the Bible says that Manoah said,
now let thy words come to pass.
How shall we order the child,
and how shall we do unto him?
I've often said that God is the creator.
He is the one that gave life, amen?
He is the one that has ordained the relationships in life.
He is the one that has instituted marriage.
He is the one that instituted the home.
He is the one that instituted the church.
He is the one that instituted government.
He is the creator.
He is the sustainer, but he's also the instructor.
In each of those arenas in life,
we find that God, he did not just institute marriage
and not provide any direction for marriage.
He did not institute the home
and not provide any instruction for the home.
No, we find that what God instituted,
God also gave instruction for.
As we've studied through the book of 1 Timothy
here on Sunday mornings,
we have discovered throughout that book
that God instituted the church,
that Christ is the head of the church,
but there's so much instruction for the church.
How do we behave as God's people?
How do we function?
How do we operate as a church?
And it's important for us to understand
and to take that information, that instruction,
and to apply it.
The same is true in the home.
The same is true in your family.
The same is true in your life.
How do I order my steps?
How do I know what to do?
How do I know what pleases God?
How do I know what displeases God?
You better get into this book.
Many people, unfortunately, are trying to live life,
even, sadly, some of the people that profess
to know Christ as their savior
are trying to live life apart from the instruction
that God has provided.
They might read other books on parenting.
They might read other books on how to be a good husband
or a good wife or how to be a better me
or whatever the book might be that you wanna read.
But the reality is that God has given us
valuable instruction in this precious book.
And we find that here, that Manoah,
he makes this request, what do we do?
How do we do?
We don't know what to do.
His request reveals to us his deficiency.
Look over the book of James, if you will.
Hold your spot there in Judges.
We'll be back in just a moment.
But I want you to see in James in chapter number one.
It's a verse of scripture that we could quote,
many of us, I could quote it for you this morning,
but I want you to look at it.
Why?
Because I want you to see it.
I want you to underline something in this text of scripture
in James chapter number one and verse number five.
It's a familiar verse of scripture.
Again, many of us could quote at least a portion
of this verse of scripture this morning.
But the Bible says this, if any of you,
I like the way that it says that
because really that's inclusive, amen?
If any of you lack wisdom,
let him ask of God.
Now who is God?
Well, God is the creator, he's the sustainer.
We also understand this when we understand who God is,
that he has revealed himself to us
as being the all wise God.
We often use the theological term that he is omniscient,
that he knows all things.
He has all wisdom.
I'm thankful that he has all power.
I'm thankful that he's everywhere present,
but I'm thankful this morning that our God,
my God, my father, he has all wisdom.
And he says to me, and he says to you as his children,
if any of you lack wisdom, let him ask of God,
notice what it says, that giveth, giveth what?
Well, giveth wisdom to all men liberally
and upbraideth not, and then notice this,
and it shall be given him.
Now here's an important truth
with regard to this text of scripture.
It ends with a great promise.
It shall be given him.
To who?
To the one who asks.
Who's the one that's gonna ask?
The one that recognizes that they lack, amen?
If any of you lack, see that's really, in my opinion,
the key to this verse of scripture,
if any of you lack wisdom.
So often we go through life never acknowledging,
never recognizing that we lack wisdom,
therefore we never ask for wisdom,
therefore we never get wisdom.
If God has made us a promise, and by the way,
does God fulfill his promises?
All of his promises, we can be sure of.
They are yea in him, and we can rejoice in that,
and we can understand.
We sing about standing on his promises
and claiming the promises, and we ought to,
but the reality this morning is that this great promise
in James one and verse number five,
so often is not fulfilled.
filled in your life or my life because I don't ask.
Because you don't ask.
Why don't we ask?
Because we don't recognize that we need it.
We think we can handle it.
Then all of a sudden, something big comes in your life.
And you say, oh man, this one right here,
like I need wisdom on this one.
I'm gonna go seek God because,
can I submit to you this morning
that you need God's wisdom every day of your life?
It's not just for the quote unquote big things.
For every day of your life, you need God's wisdom.
You need to live dependent upon him.
And so we find in our text of scripture in Judges 13
that there's a recognition of deficiency
which leads to a request for direction,
which leads to, as we go back to Judges 13,
and really the primary focus of our message this morning,
there is a robust directive.
I'm thankful that God answers the prayer,
the request that is given of Manoah
here in Judges 13.
He asks the question, he makes the request,
teach us what we shall do unto the child that shall be born.
How shall we order the child and how shall we do unto him?
And we see the request is made,
but we can rejoice this morning
that there is a robust directive that is given.
God does not simply say to us,
hey, do your best, good luck, figure it out.
No, he gives us direction.
He provides directives.
Have you ever been assigned to do a task
and not instructed on how to do it?
It's frustrating.
You say, how do I do this?
And maybe a foreman, a boss, someone else says,
figure it out.
Okay.
And then you figure it out.
And you did it wrong.
And they say, that's not how you're supposed to do it.
Well, I asked you how I was supposed to do it
and you didn't tell me.
It can be frustrating.
See, here in our text of Scripture,
God graciously provides direction
because Manoah requested direction.
Notice with me in verse number 23,
Manoah makes the statement in verse 22,
Manoah said unto his wife,
we shall surely die because we have seen God.
But his wife said unto him,
if the Lord were pleased to kill us,
he would not have received a burnt offering
and a meat offering at our hands.
Neither would he have showed us all these things,
nor would as it at this time
have told us such things as these.
I want you to notice two statements
at the end of verse number 23.
Manoah's wife said that he showed us all these things.
And then we see that it says also,
told us such things as these.
The directive is given contextually
in our text of Scripture.
If you turn back to the beginning of the chapter,
we read through verse three by way of introduction.
Pick it up in verse number four.
We find that the announcement is made
at the end of verse number three,
that thou shalt conceive and bear a son.
In verse number four, this is the initial instruction
that is given to Manoah's wife.
It says in verse number four,
now therefore beware, I pray thee,
and drink not wine nor strong drink,
and eat not any unclean thing.
For lo, thou shalt conceive and bear a son,
and no razor shall come on his head.
For this child shall be a Nazarite unto God from the womb,
and he shall begin to deliver Israel
out of the hand of the Philistines.
We find the Bible says that the woman came
and told her husband, saying,
notice what she says in verse number six,
the man of God came unto me,
and his countenance was like the countenance
of an angel of God, very terrible.
But I asked him not whence he was,
neither told he me his name.
But he said unto me, notice now in verse number seven,
Manoah's wife is going to share this announcement
with Manoah.
It says in verse number seven,
but he said unto me, behold, thou shalt conceive
and bear a son, and now drink no wine nor strong drink,
neither eat any unclean thing,
for the child shall be a Nazarite to God from the womb
to the day of his death.
Then Manoah, after hearing this news,
we've read verse eight a couple of times,
but after hearing the news from his wife,
he cries out, he says, he intrudeth the Lord,
and said, O my Lord, let the man of God,
which thou didst send, come again unto us,
and teach us what we shall do unto the child
that shall be born.
And God hearkened to the voice of Manoah,
and the angel of God came again unto the woman
as she sat in the field.
But notice Manoah, her husband was not with her.
So what does she do?
The woman made haste and ran,
and showed her husband, and said unto him,
behold, the man hath appeared unto me
that came unto me the other day.
Manoah rose and went after his wife,
and came to the man, and said unto him,
art thou the man that spakest unto the woman?
And he said, I am.
And Manoah said, now let thy words come to pass.
How shall we order the child,
and how shall we do unto him?
In verse number 13 and 14,
now the angel of the Lord is gonna speak to Manoah,
and give this instruction,
this robust directive that we see.
Says the angel of the Lord said unto Manoah,
of all that I said unto the woman, let her beware.
She may not eat of anything that cometh of the vine,
neither let her drink wine or strong drink,
nor eat any unclean thing.
All that I have commanded her, let her observe.
In verse 15, the Bible says that Manoah said unto
the angel of the Lord, I pray thee,
let us detain thee until we shall have made ready
a kid for thee.
The angel of the Lord said unto Manoah,
though thou detain me, I will not eat of thy bread.
And if thou will offer a burnt offering,
thou must offer it unto the Lord.
For Manoah knew not that he was an angel of the Lord.
And Manoah said unto the angel of the Lord,
what is thy name?
That when thy sayings come to pass,
we may do thee honor.
And the angel of the Lord said unto him,
why askest thou thus after my name,
seeing it a secret?
So Manoah took a kid with a meat offering
and offered it upon a rock unto the Lord.
And the angel did wondrously,
and Manoah and his wife looked on,
for it came to pass when the flame went up toward heaven
from off the altar that the angel of the Lord
ascended to the flame of the altar.
Manoah and his wife looked on it
and fell on their faces to the ground.
But the angel of the Lord did no more appear to Manoah
and to his wife than Manoah knew
that he was an angel of the Lord.
And here's where he says that they'll die.
In verse 22, Manoah said unto his wife,
we shall surely die because we have seen God.
But his wife said unto him,
if the Lord were pleased to kill us,
he would not have received a burnt offering
and a meat offering at our hands.
Neither would he have showed us all these things,
nor would as at this time have told us
such things as these.
And notice verse 24,
and the woman bare a son and called his name Samson.
And the child grew and the Lord blessed him.
And the spirit of the Lord began to move him at times
in the camp of Dan between Zorah and Eshtol.
As we look at this text of scripture,
we see again contextually the answer to the question,
the request that's made for direction
that God provides the directive.
He had already provided to Manoah's wife
in verses four and five,
and then his wife faithfully communicated to him
in verse number seven.
But then at the request of Manoah
in verses 13 and 14,
the angel of the Lord came and delivered this message
to Manoah to give an answer to the question.
I submit to you this morning that as we consider
this as being Father's Day,
that as fathers that we are to bring our children up
in the nurture and the admonition of the Lord,
that we have a responsibility to seek the face of God,
to understand even as here Manoah says,
how shall we order the child?
Lord, teach us what we shall do unto the child
that shall be born.
This morning, each of us need God's direction,
but just for a few moments and by way of closing,
let me share some truth with you
with regard to taking an application
from this text of scripture for fathers
on how we are to order, how we are to teach,
how we're to train, how we're to raise our children.
Turn back to the book of Deuteronomy, if you will.
In the sixth chapter, Deuteronomy chapter number six,
beginning in verse number one,
it's a familiar passage of scripture.
As we look at this passage of scripture,
we find that God had provided Israel with instruction
with regard to the home life and the responsibility
to teach and to train the children that would be born.
In verse number one in Deuteronomy six,
the Bible says now these are the commandments,
the statutes and the judgments
which the Lord your God commanded to teach you.
Notice this phrase that ye might do them
in the land whither you go to possess it.
God did not give the commands
so that we could just know them,
but he gave the commands
so that we would apply them and do them.
We find that in verse number two,
it says that thou mightest fear the Lord thy God
to keep all his statutes and his commandments
which I command thee,
thou and thy son and thy son's son,
all the days of thy life
and that thy days may be prolonged.
Now we understand as we look through Israel's history,
there are many times even as we found
there in our text of scripture in Judges 13
where they were not obedient
to the commands that God had given.
In fact, they were evil, they were wicked,
they did wickedly in the sight of God
and therefore judgment came
as we started the 13th chapter of the book of Judges,
it was the Philistines that brought great persecution,
if you will, to the children of Israel.
Israel for 40 years according to that text of scripture.
In verse three it says,
Hear therefore, O Israel, and observe to do it.
You see again a focus on doing,
that it may be well with thee,
and that ye may increase mightily
as the Lord God of thy fathers hath promised thee
in the land that floweth with milk and honey.
Hear, O Israel, the Lord our God is one Lord,
and thou shalt love the Lord thy God
with all thine heart, with all thy soul,
and with all thy might.
And these words which I command thee this day
shall be in thine heart.
By the way, if it's not really in your heart,
your kids know it.
If it's not really in your heart,
the people you're trying to minister to,
the people you're trying to influence,
to reach, to teach, they know it.
They know it if it's not really in your heart.
See, the command first in Deuteronomy chapter number six
is to the individual, the importance that we receive,
that we do, that it's in our hearts.
And then we find in verse number seven,
and thou shalt teach them.
Teach them how?
Teach them diligently unto thy children,
and shalt talk of them when thou sittest in thine house,
and when thou walkest by the way,
and when thou liest down, and when thou risest up,
and thou shalt bind them for a sign upon thine hand,
and they shall be as frontlets between thine eyes,
and thou shalt write them upon the post of thy house
and on thy gates.
Listen, the idea in verses six, eight, and nine
is not so that it would just be for outward show.
It's not something that we just have these phylacteries.
By the way, the Jewish people were guilty of that.
They still are guilty of that today.
Many times during the life and ministry
of the Lord Jesus Christ,
he'd say to some of the religious leaders,
you don't even know what this means.
What's he talking about?
They'd have scripture written on their person.
They'd have it attached to their robes,
and they'd have it,
and they didn't even understand what it meant.
The idea is not for outward show,
but it's to be that continual reminder
of what the Lord has said
so that we would apply the truth in our lives,
and we find that here in this text of scripture
that God says, first of all,
before you're ever going to effectively
teach your children, you must be doing it yourself.
Can I tell you this morning
that if we can step back from the role
and the attention on fathers here this morning,
and we just say, in whatever place you have of ministry,
whatever opportunity God would give you
to influence someone,
can I tell you that you must be doing
before you start teaching?
You don't want to be accused and guilty of hypocrisy.
Hypocrisy.
The leaven of the Pharisees.
They weren't doing.
And this morning, we find that there's an emphasis
that's placed here, and after we have received,
and after we're doing,
then we're to teach diligently to our children
or to whomever it is that we have influence over.
And by the way, I believe this morning
that every one of us has some sphere of influence.
Can I tell you this morning,
and I'm not picking on anyone in particular,
I'll use my own children as an example
that are here this morning,
but can I tell you that there's some young boys
in our church that look up to Joseph?
They do.
There's some young ladies in our church
that look up to Brianna.
They have an opportunity to influence
some of the younger kids in our church
that you and I might not have the same opportunity
to influence.
All of us have a sphere of influence.
It doesn't have, well, I'm not a father,
I'm gonna shut this message down.
No, no, no, be careful.
Because each of us have a sphere of influence.
There's somebody that's watching you.
I'm gonna preach on that tonight.
I hope you'll come back.
The reality is that we find that God gives this,
yes, he answers the prayer, the request of Manoah,
but I want you to understand that biblically,
as we consider in our own lives,
and I make the appeal to you this morning,
listen, you must recognize your deficiency.
You must make a request for direction.
And then you find that God has given a robust directive.
He has given truth in his word.
And as we seek him, as we understand that we lack wisdom
and we've asked God for wisdom,
he takes us to his word and his Holy Spirit
that indwells us is our teacher
and he teaches us his word.
And he helps us to be able to have that influence
and to be able to give the truth
that we're commanded to give.
Turn to the book of Proverbs, if you will,
in the fourth chapter.
Proverbs chapter number four.
We're gonna look at the first few verses
of this text of scripture in the fourth proverb.
We find that here, of course,
we understand that the book of Proverbs
from a human perspective is Solomon
writing to his son, Rehoboam.
And we find that as this text of scripture in chapter four,
it's really a generational text.
It says, hear ye children the instruction of a father
and attend to no understanding.
Beyond it being just the human relationship
of Solomon teaching Rehoboam,
we understand that spiritually it is God, our father,
who's giving us direction and instruction.
We find it in verse number two,
it says, for I give you good doctrine,
forsake ye not my law.
For I, Solomon speaking, was my father's son,
tender and only beloved in the sight of my mother.
Who's his father?
David, of course.
And it says in verse number four,
it says he taught me also.
So David gave some instruction to Solomon.
By the way, at the end of David's life,
you can read it in both 2 Samuel and 1 Kings,
you can read the instruction that is given
from David to Solomon.
We find that David makes this,
excuse me, Solomon makes this statement
that he taught me also.
It says, and said unto me,
let thine heart retain my words.
Keep my commandments and live.
Get wisdom.
Where do we get wisdom from?
From God.
Get wisdom, get understanding.
Forget it not, neither decline from the words of my mouth.
Forsake her not, and she shall preserve thee.
Love her, and she shall keep thee.
That's wisdom.
Verse seven, wisdom is the principal thing.
Therefore, get wisdom, and with all thy getting,
get understanding.
Exalt her, and she shall promote thee.
She shall bring thee to honor when thou dost embrace her.
So shall give, she shall give to thine head
an ornament of grace, a crown of glory.
Shall she deliver to thee.
Notice verse 10.
Hear, O my son, and receive my sayings.
Can I pause there just for a moment?
There's a difference between hearing and receiving.
You can hear me this morning,
but you don't have to receive anything I'm saying.
You can hear your parents, you don't have to receive.
You can hear from God,
but he's not gonna make you receive it.
Isn't that a scary thought?
He loves you so much that he gives you truth.
He gave us a Bible.
He gave you a preacher here this morning
to preach the Bible,
but he's not gonna make you receive it.
There's a difference between hearing and receiving.
You ever had somebody, are you hearing me?
Are you listening to me?
They make a distinction between hearing and listening.
You ever have somebody, you're giving them instruction,
maybe a little child, and they're hearing.
It's not that they're deaf.
They can hear you.
They're just not listening to you.
Hearing and receiving.
He says, hear, O my son, and receive my sayings.
The years of thy life shall be many.
I have taught thee in the way of wisdom.
I have led thee in right paths.
I wonder this morning if we could say
that I have taught thee in the way of wisdom.
I have led thee in right paths.
I hope that we could.
Whether you have children or not,
to the people that you're influencing,
I wonder could we make that statement,
could we say that this morning,
that I have fulfilled my responsibility.
I have given the truth.
I have no control over how you receive it
or what you do with it,
but I do have a responsibility to give it.
Proverbs 22, a familiar verse of Scripture,
in verse number six, the Bible says this.
I believe it's one of my dad's favorite verses of Scripture.
The Bible says in verse number six of Proverbs 22,
train up a child in the way he should go.
When he is old, he will not depart from it.
Can I tell you this morning,
there's this philosophy that's seeking
to influence our culture that says something like this,
just let your kids figure it out.
Can I tell you that God said train them?
He didn't give you this hands-off approach of,
look, they're gonna just figure out life on their own.
No, you've been given a God-given responsibility
to train them.
Can I tell you that training requires more than telling?
Telling them is not training them.
Training them takes work, takes commitment, dedication.
It takes sweat, blood, tears to train someone.
Here in the text, train up a child,
notice, in the way he should go.
Teaching them the ways of the Lord,
teaching them what thus saith the Lord,
teaching them what pleases God and what displeases God.
By the way, what you do not know, you cannot teach.
What you do not know,
No, you cannot teach.
If someone came in here and said,
Pastor, can you teach me?
And they named some language.
I don't know any other language.
I don't even know English real good.
But you understand, if you don't know it,
you can't teach it.
So you better have a close walk with God.
That's why in Deuteronomy 6,
it starts with the individual
receiving and doing and having in your heart,
because then you can begin to teach.
To train up the involvement that is required.
We cannot, we can no longer think
that training our children
is the responsibility of the school.
What a tragic situation that would be.
Can I also say to you
that it's not the responsibility of the church?
It's not the church's responsibility
to train your children.
Now, I will say this,
the church should come alongside of you
and help you in the process of training your children.
But the church has not been given the responsibility.
The parents have been given the responsibility.
Ephesians chapter number six,
the verse of scripture that's there
on your bulletin this morning
that we quoted by way of introduction,
and ye fathers, provoke not your children to wrath,
but bring them up in the nurture
and admonition of the Lord.
This admonition, this command to bring them up.
Listen, your kids, the young people in our church,
they need direction.
Can I tell you this morning,
there is a world out there
that is standing by waiting
to give your kids all kinds of direction.
And I would submit to you
that most of that direction
that they want to give your children
is in direct opposition to the instruction
that's given in this precious book.
But they're waiting to do it.
Oh, there are people online
that are waiting to instruct your children.
There are people that are ready,
they're ready to give false teaching,
false instruction, false worldviews.
Wouldn't have a biblical worldview.
Bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord,
the involvement that is required.
There's a great connection between Proverbs 22
in verse six and Ephesians six and verse number four.
As we look at the passage of scripture this morning
from Judges, and we look in the chapter
and the situation there between Manoah and his wife
and receiving this announcement in Judges 13
with regard to the fact that though they had no children,
that they would soon have a child.
There's a recognition on the part of Manoah
of his own deficiencies.
I don't know what I'm doing.
Do you ever feel like that in life?
You say, I don't want to admit it.
I know, because we have a hard time admitting it.
There are times in lives, listen,
there's some times that God will bring you to a place
that he'll bring you to the end of yourself
so that you recognize you need him
and you can no longer do it.
You should no longer desire to do it
in your own power and your own strength.
Manoah recognized his deficiencies.
He recognized and therefore he made a request.
I wonder this morning, how often do we request of God
to provide us with direction in our lives?
Yes, within the context of this message this morning,
specifically to fathers on training their children
and bringing them up in the nurturing
and the admonition of the Lord
and running to the word of God to receive the directive
that God has provided us with, absolutely.
But what about where you are in your life?
Regardless of who you are,
with regard to your responsibilities,
your position in life, you need God's direction.
I said this on Wednesday evening
to end our missions conference.
I said this, there was a great emphasis
throughout the conference,
but especially there on Wednesday evening, of surrender.
And I said this, surrender can be a fearful thing.
But surrender is the most freeing thing
when we're surrendering to God.
When we, listen, I don't want people to think I don't,
listen, God knows your deficiencies.
He knows my deficiencies.
It's best for us to acknowledge them
and seek him for direction.
There are times in my life
that I'll say something like this when I pray.
God, I have no idea what I'm doing.
I have no idea what needs to be done.
I have no idea what the next step should be.
God, I need your direction.
God, you promised in your word
that you would give me direction.
Can I tell you this morning,
I've prayed that prayer in the context of parenting.
I've prayed that prayer in the context of pastoring.
I've prayed that prayer in the context
of just being a Christian.
God, I need your help.
I'm thankful that he's a very present help
at the time of trouble, that he will give us what we need.
And he said, he promises to you,
he promises to me that he will give us wisdom,
that he'll give us the direction.
But the person that receives the direction,
the wisdom is the one who asks.
The one who asks is the one that recognizes
that they lack and they need it.
This morning, we see a great example
in the life of Manoah in Judges 13,
an example that is applicable to every one of our lives,
how desperately we need God
to provide direction in our lives.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the opportunity
that you've given us to gather today.
We thank you, God, for the freedom that we have
in this nation that we can openly worship thee.
I pray, Father, that you would work in hearts and lives.
If there's one here this morning that's not saved,
God, I pray that they would understand
how much you love them.
That you sent your only begotten son,
the Lord Jesus Christ, God in flesh,
to come to this sin-cursed world to die
on a cruel cross to take their place,
to pay their sin debt,
was buried and rose, conquering sin, death, and the grave,
alive forevermore, soon to return.
God, I pray that the individual that's not trusted you,
that today, before they leave,
they would trust Christ as their Savior.
They could leave here knowing that heaven is their home,
that, God, you are their Father,
that they are your children.
I pray, Father, that you would work in the hearts and lives
of your people this morning,
regardless of our lot in life, where we are in life,
whether we have children or not,
whether we're even married or not.
God, we need your direction.
These young people, from the youngest to the oldest,
in our midst this morning, we need your guidance.
We need your direction.
God, I pray that you'd help us to acknowledge,
to recognize our deficiencies,
and to be dependent upon you,
to refuse to live independently,
to refuse to try to navigate our own path,
but, God, that we would rest in thee,
and that we would trust thee.
I pray that you'd move and work in hearts and lives
as only you can.
We pray that every decision that's made would be sealed,
and, Lord, that you'd be honored and glorified,
for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's gonna play quietly on the piano,
and as she does, the altar's open.
Maybe this morning you need to come
and just recognize your deficiencies.
Wherever you are in life, you have some deficiencies,
and you need God's help, you need God's direction.
Maybe it is specifically with regard to parenting,
to raising the children, whatever it is that God has done.
However God's spoken to your heart,
as Kimberly plays, the altar is open.
Please visit www.charlesboyk-law.com to learn more.