Beautiful music, I appreciate it, it's sung well and appropriately done, very good.
I was surprised this morning, I was not included, I'm not going to be here for the apple picking
trip.
I want you to know that I am an apple connoisseur and an apple snob.
I literally eat an apple every day of my life and if you get the opportunity when you go
out to the orchard, if they have ambrosia, go pick some ambrosias.
If you like crisp, sweet apples, look for Envy and go buy or get some Envy apples.
Now if you want to know more about apples, see me after the service, okay?
I honestly, I just finished a book on Johnny Appleseed and there really was a Johnny Appleseed
and he was a great man and his vision was that some of the settlers going over the mountains,
the pioneers, were so poor, so impoverished just to get to where they were going that
they would have no good food supply or it would be difficult for them to do.
He literally planted orchards all through the Appalachians, the Alleghenies, the Blue Ridge,
so that as they went, they could take twigs and branches and then replant and his vision
was if they did that everywhere this side of the Mississippi, at least people would
have some good fruit and some good food for their life.
So there are and were some good people with a good vision to be kind and helpful to others.
Alright, that's the nicest I'm going to be all morning, alright?
I'm going to preach now.
It is an absolute privilege and honor to be here.
Pastor, thank you for this opportunity and invitation.
Thank you for being here and I'm looking forward to what God is going to do in our midst.
I'm asking God to speak to me, help me as much as I'm asking for God to speak to you
and help you.
Having said all that, Psalm 31 this morning, Psalm 31.
And for our text, though we'll look at other verses, we're going to begin reading in verse
14, Psalm 31 and verse 14.
And there the Bible says this, David speaking under the inspiration of the Spirit of God,
But I trusted in Thee, O Lord, I said, Thou art my God.
My times are in Thy hand.
Deliver me from the hand of mine enemies, and from them that persecute me.
Make Thy face to shine upon Thy servant, and save me for Thy mercy's sake.
Let's pray.
Father, we're very grateful for the opportunity to be together this morning.
We thank You for Your Holy Spirit.
I pray that He this morning would take Your Word and speak to our hearts through it.
Lord, we're gathered here because we know we need to hear from You.
And I pray that You would accomplish that.
I ask You to encourage people.
I pray that You would instruct people.
But I also pray that You would convict and challenge us.
And Lord, where You see something in our life that needs to be strengthened, changed, would
You convict us about that and then help us to accomplish what You want.
I pray especially for those that may be here this morning in our presence that have never
trusted Christ as their Savior.
God, would You expose to them their great need.
Beyond their need, would You reveal to them how much You love them and how much You desire
to save them.
So Lord, work in all of our hearts.
Help us, we pray.
In Jesus' name, amen.
Here's my question to begin the message.
In verse 14, David says, but I trusted in Thee.
Why is David saying he's in a place where he has to bring attention to the fact that
he's trusting in the Lord?
Well the answer is in verse 9.
Have mercy upon me, O Lord, for I am in trouble.
The trouble that David is in and the word that he uses is not indicative that it's a
difficult moment but it'll pass.
No, he is in real trouble.
We're not sure if this is from the time of his life when Saul was chasing him.
We suspect and I agree that it is probably written around the time where Absalom has
rebelled and David is being cast out of his palace, cast out of his city.
Deceitfully, Absalom has asked leave, to go to leave the city.
He's gone to Hebron, taken Hebron, taken that fortified city, raised an army and is now
marching back towards Jerusalem.
There are people that are making decisions that are certainly terrible decisions for
David.
They're forsaking him.
They fear that Absalom's army is stronger than anything David has.
David is aging and David is feeling forsaken.
Notice what he says in verse 10.
For my life is spent with grief, my years with sighing, my strength faileth because
of mine iniquity, all my bones are consumed.
I was a reproach among all my enemies but especially among my neighbors.
Now I read that just so that we understand this is a deep moment of trouble in David's
life and he is really concerned about what is going to happen to him, happen to his family.
It is a serious moment into which he interjects this, but I trusted God.
Why did you trust God David?
Because my times are in His hands.
David realized what you and I realized, that one of the realities of our lives in this
world is that we experience seasons of stress.
We experience seasons of trouble.
We're surrounded by difficult moments, difficult times, problems if you will.
In our nation today, who cannot realize the difficulty of the moment we're in, the social
unrest.
Not only is there social unrest, political unrest, there's economic uncertainty.
Who knows what interest rates are going to do?
Who knows what this is going to have, what this bubble is going to bust?
It's always a question of what's going to happen.
We've lived through a pandemic, now we're back into seasons of war.
What's going to break next?
Where will there be strife and killing next?
There's situations specific to our own lives.
Jobs change.
Things in our circumstances of health change.
There's just always this possibility of a season of stress.
Have I encouraged you yet?
We'll get to it.
That's why David said, man, we live in this ever-changing sea.
We live where we just don't know what tomorrow's going to bring.
I had someone say to me, they said, preacher, it just seems like everything is as hard as
it can be.
Sometimes we feel like that.
I noticed in the last song that we sang, a guy said, man, I feel like I'm dead.
But then Jesus comes and rolls the clouds away.
We understand that Jesus always knew where we were and always knew what we needed.
We're not the first generation to face stress and trouble.
I doubt that many have faced all that David faced in his life.
As a young man, he had to face and kill a bear and a lion and a giant.
As a young king, Saul was determined to kill him.
He had a kingdom to manage.
He was surrounded all of his days as king with wars and fighting.
He had a very difficult family situation, some of his own making.
But my point is this, that in life, if you and I think that it is always a fairy tale,
it is not so.
And how is it that we as believers today, how do we manage these seasons of stress,
these seasons of difficulty, and it comes back to the statement that he trusted in the
Lord because his times, David's, were in God's hands.
And I want you to know that though we are not fighting giants and killing bears and
lions and we're not kings of kingdoms, we are people who live on God's earth and we
do face the seasons of difficulty in our lives.
lives and one of the great things that you and I must come to understand is that we can
trust that God is our God and our seasons, our lives are lived in God's hands.
Notice those two things with me today.
Number one, my times.
David's life and our lives are definitely marked by change and instability.
That word that David used for times is a word that indicates seasons or changeableness.
I'll speak more about that in a moment.
But I just want you to recognize this morning that our lives are lived in seasons.
Let me try to illustrate it.
Several years ago, I was born an infant, more than several.
And in infancy, I was completely helpless.
If my mother and father had not provided for me, had there not been a gracious God, I couldn't
have survived.
But you know what?
I grew out of that age of infancy and I became a toddler.
And I was such a precious toddler.
You know the season of being a toddler.
It's a challenging season.
But you know what?
We grow out of being toddlers and we become juniors.
And as juniors, the world is exciting and life is exciting and mom and dad are great
and it's a wonderful season of life.
But we grow out of being juniors and we become teenagers.
And we then understand that it's our job to teach mother and dad how they're to live and
how life is supposed to be.
But we grow out of being teenagers.
And then those truly wonderful years come normally where we find that one that God has
made for us and we're going to share a life with them.
And then we grow out of that season of newlyweds to become young parents.
And it's a challenging season, but it's also one of the greatest seasons of life as we
see those children born into our homes.
And then that season comes of being an empty nester and we don't know what we're going
to do, how we're going to survive.
And then we find out it's a pretty good deal.
And then after being empty nesters, we become seniors and we're almost back to infancy.
Think about it.
You have a point preacher?
Yeah.
We live our lives in seasons.
And they come and they go.
They stay for a while and then we move on to something else.
And some of them are incredibly precious and some of them are incredibly difficult.
David one day was sitting on a hillside tending sheep, creating wonderful psalms and hymns
about the Lord and creation.
But the next moment in life, he's called down to the house.
He stands before Samuel, the judge, the prophet, and he's anointed king.
One moment he's a hero with his foot on Goliath's chest, but the next he's dodging a spear from
King Saul.
The next moment he's a king in Hebron and then Jerusalem and living in a palace.
But the next he's an outcast being chased by his own son.
I'm simply saying that we don't know what tomorrow holds and we're not guaranteed that
tomorrow is a sweet season.
Here's the truth, we're going to pass through some wonderful times, but we're also going
to face some truly difficult times in our lives.
One of my favorite things as a pastor, preacher, was when a young couple would have a child.
And we had a very young congregation and I was often, I did way more weddings than funerals.
And I remember going to the hospital one time and this young couple, he was a Marine and
his wife, they had just had their first child.
And he and I were standing off to the side and she was over in a rocking chair in a little
blue blanket and a little blue beanie, you know, and she was rocking her new little boy.
And the husband and I, we were talking about, I'm quite sure, serious things, maybe football.
And I overheard the wife and she was so softly, she could have cared less about us.
Her attention was that little baby.
And I heard her say something like this, I don't ever want this moment to pass.
I just always want you to be in my arms and my little baby and my little boy.
And I overheard her say that and down inside me as a fundamental Baptist preacher, I wanted
to turn to her and say, well sister, that baby's going to grow up.
It's not always going to be like this.
They're going to grow up and they're going to love somebody else more than you and leave
you.
Aren't you glad I fought the urge to say that?
But that was the truth.
Because life's always moving.
It's always moving.
It never stays the same.
And sometimes we just want to reach out to the Lord and say, leave it here.
Stop moving it.
Stop letting the world turn.
I remember my grandma used to watch her show.
It was a soap opera called As the World Turns and it followed the lives of these people
and they got old and they had problems and they had good days and bad days.
And I began to recognize it was not something you might want to watch, but it was mighty
true in what it said.
The world keeps turning and we never know what tomorrow brings.
But sometimes what tomorrow brings is not easy and not pleasant, but it's part of what
God is allowing and doing in our lives.
I am so thankful that in those seasons that are moving and ever-changing, mine are lived
in the hands of God and so are yours.
Think about that with me for a moment.
David's times may have been unstable.
David's life may have been ever-changing, but David's God was stable and unchanging.
Think of words that he used.
He described God as a rock, as a fortress, as a house of defense.
In other words, man, everything is swirling about me, but God never moves.
God never changes.
One of the attributes of God that is so precious to me is that God is immutable.
We often talk about God being omniscient and it's a wonderful truth that God knows everything.
God knows everything about me and God knows everything I need.
God is omnipresent.
I am so thankful God is present with us this morning.
My wife in Charlotte, I'm glad God is present with my wife and with my son as he stands
to preach this morning.
I'm glad that God is present with every missionary.
I'm glad God is present with my kids and grandkids scattered across the country.
God is ever-present.
God is omnipotent.
There's never anything that we face that God cannot care for, God cannot take control of.
All things are possible for God.
And we know those omnis, but sometimes we're not as careful to appreciate that God is immutable.
And as everything swirls around us, God is the same that he's always been.
And God's truth is the same as it's always been.
His mercy endures forever.
He is exactly today what he was yesterday and tomorrow when my life changes, he will
exactly be what he was today.
He never changes.
Now let me mention two aspects of that that's important for us.
God is not only immutable, God is sovereign.
Sometimes we're a little bit afraid of that word sovereign.
It's a wonderful word and a wonderful truth.
The word David uses for times is the same word that Daniel uses, and I won't have you
turn there for the sake of time.
But it's the same word that Daniel uses when he says this, Daniel answered and said, blessed
be the name of God forever and ever, for wisdom and might are his.
And he changeth the times and the seasons.
He removeth kings and setteth up kings.
He giveth wisdom unto the wise and knowledge to them that know understanding.
Our world seems to be utterly chaotic.
But I want you to understand that in the midst of our chaos as we see our world, God is absolutely
in control.
Nothing takes God by surprise.
God is not sitting on the edge of heaven hoping it works out.
God knows exactly where he is taking planet earth.
And by the way, God knows exactly where he is taking you and I.
God is God in the future.
God is God in the past.
God is God in the present.
And God is sovereign over all men.
God knows who he is going to raise up and allow to rule.
But God knows when he's going to take them down
and let someone else rule.
This world is not moving by the manipulative hand of man.
It is moving by the settled story of God.
And it is coming to the place where God is bringing it.
Hey, good news, Jesus is coming again.
We may not like every aspect of how it is coming there,
but it is coming there under God's control.
And sometimes we get so frustrated
and we get maybe so frightened because of the moment,
but you and I must understand
that our times are in God's hands.
And he is a sovereign God moving history his direction.
But let me also say this, God is also a personal God.
Aren't you glad of that?
God is not just some foreboding force.
God is not just some unknowable power.
God is personal.
I love what David says in verse 14.
Thou art my God.
I am so thankful this morning
that I can say God is my God.
I am his son.
I did not get saved as a child.
I wasn't raised in a Christian home.
I have wonderful parents.
Please don't hear me saying that they were not good people.
They were wonderful people.
And dad got saved at 63 years old.
Mom got saved.
My brother got saved and through a series of events,
I got saved, my wife got saved, praise God for it.
We were 23 years old, young parents when we got saved.
And I regret, as long as I live,
I regret that the first 23 years of my life
were not lived under the purposes
and the understanding of who God was.
But I am grateful for this, that I know the dividing line.
I am grateful that I know what it was to live without him
and then to understand my need of him and to be saved
and now to have lived knowing him and him knowing me
and to have the consciousness that I know where I was.
I know how God spoke to me.
I know what my need was and I called out to him to save me
and it's all been different because thou art my God.
What a joy.
He is a personal God.
You see, God is both transcendent and imminent.
What do you mean by that, preacher?
I mean that God is big enough, so big,
that he rules the universe.
But he is so personal that he met with me
in that wonderful apartment I have that you have provided.
He met with me this morning.
50 years in to knowing him, he met with me
and showed me truth from the word of God,
spoke to me about my life.
That's who my God is.
He's big enough to run the universe.
He's big enough to choose kings and put kings down.
He's big enough to control the chaos of this world,
but he's personal enough to meet with me,
to care about my knee hurts.
Would you please feel sorry for me this week?
He's personal enough to know my needs, my heart.
What a God we serve.
You say, well, preacher, if he's so big
that he can run the universe and so sovereign
that everything is planned out and so personal
that he knows where I am, knows what I need,
knows where he's taking me, then I have no part?
Oh, no.
That's where David put this, verse 14.
But I trusted in thee.
It's God's job to run the universe.
It's God's job to be personal and direct me,
but it is my job to trust him.
You see, personal trust in a personal God
and a sovereign God gives us the inner stability
when everything else around us is in upheaval.
In the middle of this chaotic world
where God knows what he's doing, but I don't,
my job is to trust him.
Trust him.
Now, there are times when we trust the Lord
in the middle of the storms and the bad seasons,
the difficult seasons of life,
where we wonder, is God doing anything?
Is God there?
God always is there.
And sometimes when we're in the ship with God
and we cry out, master, carest thou not that we perish,
he rises from the hinder part of the ship
and he walks up and speaks and the waves cease
and the storm stops and we say, oh God, you love me.
It's so wonderful.
But there are other times when we say, Lord,
there's a storm.
And he chooses to let your Clydon blow.
And the storm blows so hard that the ship breaks up.
But in the midst of that storm, God speaks to us
and says, hey, you're going to make it through here
and you're gonna lose the ship, but not your life.
And I know where you are and what you need.
And by the way, when you get cast into the water,
I'm gonna bring a board by.
And you can snatch the board and make it to land, Paul,
but I'm not gonna stop the storm.
And by the way, Paul, got another tough event on the land
because you're gonna make a fire
because you're cold and I'm gonna let a snake bite you.
But Paul, I'm sovereign.
I'm gonna take the venom out and you're not gonna die.
Now, if I were Paul, I'd have said,
let's stop short of the ship breaking up.
Let's stop short of the snake.
And that's when God says, no, no, no, no, understand this.
Paul, your times, they're in my hands.
And I'm doing something that you can't see.
I'm doing something bigger than you can imagine,
but I've got you.
And your job is to trust me in the middle of that storm.
Let me make two observations and I'll be done.
Number one, the time to prepare for trouble
is before you're in it,
especially in the matter of salvation.
If you're here this morning
and you can't point to that time in your life.
Now, not everybody has to know a date.
Not everybody has to know the exact moment
the clock struck when you got saved.
But being born again is an important moment.
We may not know what time it was or what day it was,
but when we get saved, we're acknowledging to the Lord
that I'm a sinner.
And my sin has broken any relationship with you.
And if I bear my sin, you can't be in the presence of sin.
And if I bear my own sin,
I can never come into your presence.
And God answers back, but I've remedied that
because I sent my son to earth
and my son loving you so much
went to a cross at Calvary
where all sin was poured out on him.
And instead of me forsaking you,
instead of you not being able to be in my presence,
I forsook my own son.
My God, my God, why has thou forsaken me?
And in that moment, sin was judged and sin was paid for
and the price of sin, the penalty of sin was paid.
My son died.
And if you'll look to my son,
and see, that's a conscious act, isn't it?
That's not something we're given from our parents.
That's not something that we just grow into.
It's a conscious act.
I don't know what day, I'm not sure what time it was,
but I remember hearing the gospel somehow
and I remember that moment in my life,
maybe alone after the service,
maybe alone after someone had talked to me,
maybe alone after I had read something.
I remember that moment in my life
that I acknowledged what God said was true.
My sin separates me from you.
And I can't change that.
And I acknowledge that you sent your son, Jesus,
who died in my place.
And if I will simply look to what you did for me
and receive that gift,
acknowledge my need as a sinner
and acknowledge the work of your son.
on the cross at Calvary in a transaction
I'll never understand fully until I get to heaven.
My sin is paid for in what Jesus did
and Jesus' righteousness, the Bible word,
is imputed to me and I now bear the righteousness of Jesus
as he bears my son and when God looks at me,
he no longer sees sinful Mike Edwards,
he sees the righteousness of Jesus
and on the basis of that transaction,
I can get in heaven, I can be present with the Lord forever.
Hey, that's a conscious moment of decision in our lives
and if you're here this morning
and you've never had that moment in your life,
I'm telling you it's available to you today.
God didn't stop doing that in 1950.
God didn't stop saving people that way in 2000.
God is saving people like that in 2025
and he is here and it's a decision that you've gotta make,
oh, not to save yourself
but to receive what God has already done.
Let me move on quickly.
I'm also saying that the time to prepare for trouble
is before it happens for believers.
Sometimes in the good seasons of life, I'll speak for me,
sometimes in the good seasons of life,
I forget that there may be a difficult season coming.
I just think life will always be like this.
It'll always be okay but it won't always be okay.
This body will wear out, fortunes change,
things move in and out of our lives
and sometimes in the good, easier seasons,
you know what I do?
I forget how desperately I need the Lord
and I become a little too confident in myself
and then the crisis hits.
And I'm saying to you, there's never a day that we live
that we don't desperately need the Lord.
There's never a day that we walk and work
and go through life where we don't need to call out
to the Lord and be absolutely dependent on him
and may you and I be very careful
that we do not live our lives thinking we can handle it
and then that season comes.
I'd say secondly this,
though we may at times be overwhelmed, God never is.
And you and I must practice trusting the Lord.
In the good seasons but also in the difficult seasons.
David was writing psalms when it was just
a beautiful hillside with him and his sheep.
David was singing and praying those psalms
when Absalom was at the gate.
What are you saying, preacher?
I'm just saying that psalms and trusting the Lord
are not just for the easy or the hard seasons,
they're for every season.
And we will have a season where we're overwhelmed.
You say I don't think for my life, ooh, you will.
God is never overwhelmed, hang on to him.
In the few times that we went to the ocean
when my children were small, I would go purposefully
because I wanted my kids to know a couple of things.
Number one, I wanted them to know how little they were
in scope of creation, how small they were.
I wanted them to see the grandeur of that ocean
and just sense it.
One of the things that I always did was,
I'll pick Chris out, he's my pastor now.
I pick him up and I would start to walk into the ocean
and they were mesmerized by it.
They thought it was the greatest, coolest thing
in the world.
And I would walk out and they, daddy, this is cool.
Maybe they're two and a half, three years old.
And they thought it was neat.
The water's cold, because that's when we go,
and it's hitting my ankles and I'm freezing.
I take another couple of steps out and now it's up
to my waist and I'm going, ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh,
because it's cold.
But he thinks it's cool, what are you doing, dad?
Like that.
I kept walking.
By the way, all the time my wife is back on the shore,
that's far enough.
But I want to show them something.
We step out a little further and now the water's
hitting their legs.
And I always notice something about all three of my kids.
When the water started hitting their legs,
they tightened their hug.
They held on to me.
But in all three of my children, I'd notice something,
that when I took another couple of steps
and the water got up to their chest,
they actually pushed away.
You know why they pushed away?
They pushed away because for a moment,
they had decided that their dad was insane.
And they couldn't stick with him.
And they had to take control.
And they had to get themselves back to mommy
who really loved them.
That's a silly story.
But I have observed that in so many believers' lives.
That they trust the Lord until they really have
to trust the Lord.
And when trust the Lord is no longer just a phrase,
no longer just what I'm supposed to say,
when trust the Lord means I abandon it all to him.
I trust him with my life.
I trust him with my family.
I trust him with my job.
When it just says, thou art my God,
my times are lived in my hands,
wherever you want to take me,
whatever you want to do with me,
however you want it to come out,
I simply trust you, Lord.
That's a big step.
And sometimes even as believers,
we can push away and say, I'll take this now.
I'll take control.
I'm done.
Let me say this.
If you're here this morning and you're unsaved,
God loves you.
And whether you realize it or not,
you need him really bad.
Take a look at this world.
Take a look at where it's going.
And understand that it is moving in God's way.
Can there be revival?
Of course.
But I'm telling you, ultimately this world ends
in the destruction of one called Antichrist.
I don't know when.
I sense sooner than later.
I know Jesus is coming again.
And I'm telling you that season is real
and that season is coming.
And this is your opportunity to take Christ as your savior.
But believers, I'm saying to you,
I hope you're in a good season today.
But they are seasons and they will change.
And there are hard things out there.
And you want to be as surrendered and as close
in your walk to the Lord in this good season
as you'll wish you were in that difficult season.
And with everything moving and all the things we see,
I am so glad that my times are lived in God's hands.
Thou art my God.
And when the doctor tells me, and it's bad news,
but I trust it in thee.
And when that boss makes the announcement,
when that financial crisis comes,
when the next pandemic is here, when everything,
but I trust it.
And I'm telling you, I'm telling you,
but I trust it in thee.
The greatest phrase for any believer's life
is to have learned to say and mean,
I trust it in thee because my times are in thy hand.
Would you pray with me?
Father, we're grateful for this morning
and for this opportunity.
And I pray just now that you would speak
into the hearts of believers here today.
There may be some who are experiencing
very difficult seasons right now.
Lord, would you remind them that their times
are lived in your hands, that the season
they're experiencing now is not a surprise to you.
It's not a mistake.
It is something you've allowed because you're sovereign.
And every season has a time, it has a purpose.
You know what you're doing and your purposes
for your children are always good.
And Lord, would you remind them that in this difficult season
you're personal, you know where they are,
you know how they hurt, you know what they need,
you know what their fear is.
You know what they're going through.
You know what their fear is.
And you'll walk alongside them.
May they cry out to you as David did
in this difficult season, but I'm trusting in thee.
Pray for them.
And those who are in a good season of life, may they be reminded that the season changes.
It's always moving.
And now is not a time to be independent of the Lord.
Now is not a time to take control.
Now is a time to be appreciative of where the Lord has you and in preparation for where
the Lord may be taking you.
To grow closer to Him.
To become more dependent in this sweet season.
And I pray for unbelievers.
For men and women who are in this room, oh they're not vile people.
They're here because they care about you.
They want to know something from you.
I pray that you would speak into their lives.
If they can't find that spot in their life, well don't try to create it out of nothing
in their past.
But if they can't find that moment where they consciously made a decision, I'm a sinner.
I need Christ.
I need what He did for me.
And to call out upon the Lord, for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall
be saved.
In this moment they could call out to the Lord and know that they're saved.
And know that you are their God.
So Lord we give you these things and we ask you to work.
Just before I conclude my prayer, I wonder if there might be one that would say this
morning, preacher I'm here this morning.
I can't point to that conscious decision in my life.
I just don't know it's there.
And by an uplifted hand, I wouldn't call your name if I knew it.
I will in no way embarrass you.
But I simply am asking, would you let me pray with you?
I'll pray in a way that is not identifying you.
But I'm not sure I've made that conscious decision, but that troubles me.
And I'm interested in getting that settled in my life.
Would you slip your hand up where I could just pray with you?
Preacher I can't point to the place in my life where I've made that conscious decision
for Christ.
Is there one?
Can I pray with you?
I wonder if there might be some that would be here today that would say, preacher I'm
in a pretty difficult season of life.
And I'm going to cry out to the Lord today, I know Lord that things are moving by your
hand.
But Lord, I'm fearful in this season.
And I'm asking you, will you speak to me and encourage?
I'm calling out, I'm trusting you, thou art my God, but it's a difficult season of life.
And I'm asking, will you take my hand?
God bless you, I see that hand.
God bless you, I see that hand, others.
God bless you.
It's a difficult season.
Many of you, the majority are here and it's a good season of life.
It doesn't mean it's problem free, but it's a good season of life.
But it might have occurred to you during the message, you know, I've not been as careful
in this good season in being prepared for the ones that are yet coming.
Maybe there's some strengthening in my spiritual walk.
Maybe there's some strengthening I need to employ for my family.
And God, I know that you've got me in a good season.
I know you're my God.
I know I trust you, but Lord, I've just been kind of realizing here, I need to be strengthening
for the seasons that come and I need to be purposeful about it.
Just by an uplifted hand.
God's spoken to me in that way, that I've been a little bit independent of the Lord
in this sweet season.
God bless you.
Many, many.
Now Father, you've seen our hearts, and Lord, the important thing is that we deal with you.
With what you've spoken to us about.
We rejoice that our times are lived in your hands, but Lord, help us to be sensitive servants
as we walk with you.
If there's one here that isn't saved, they are in a crowded room that loves them, cares
about them, would rejoice in their decision.
We'll take a Bible and show them how they can be saved.
We pray in Jesus' name, amen.
Would you quietly, heads bowed, eyes closed, would you stand to your feet?
Pianist is going to play, and if God's spoken to you, you want to spend a moment with the
Lord at the altar, would you come?
If you're here and you're not sure you've made that conscious decision, we will help.
Would you come?
Well, I'm in a difficult season.
Help.
It's okay.
It's okay to be in the difficult season.
It's okay to ask for His help.