Number one, how appropriate as we were singing our last song, our last congregational song,
it fits so well with the message for this evening.
And the song title is, You're All on the Altar, and I hope that as we were singing
this evening that we were meditating upon the words of that song, how thought-provoking
and soul-searching the words of this particular hymn are.
And the title of the message this evening from the book of Philippians is this, Who
Are You Living For?
And Philippians 1 and verse number 21, the Apostle Paul says, For to me to live is Christ
and to die is gain.
And I simply ask the question in our message title this evening, who are you living for?
C.T.
Studd said, Only one life will soon be passed.
Only what's done for Christ shall last.
I'm mindful of one of my Bible college professors, and he had a successful career as an engineer
prior to his salvation and call to ministry.
And he'd been working for a number of years and had been dealing with, of course, he trusted
Christ as a Savior and dealing with the thought of ministry for a number of years after that,
still working faithfully in the corporate world and had a successful job and career.
And as he was struggling with the thought of serving the Lord full-time and working
in the ministry as a pastor, he felt the Lord was calling him to the ministry and he was
just dealing with that process.
And if you have felt the call or you've been called, you might understand some of what
that struggle might look like.
And he was dealing with several of those things, and it was a particular occasion as they were
rolling out some new machinery that he had the opportunity to help design.
And as he had worked and helped design that machinery, and they had a big, just a ceremony,
if you will, ribbon cutting and all of these sort of things, and as they would get rid
of the outdated old system, they brought the new system in, and it was a day in which
to be celebrated.
It was a day to be really full of just accomplishment and rejoicing as to what was able to be accomplished.
But as he had been struggling for a period of time at that particular moment in his life
with regard to serving the Lord full-time in the ministry or to continue in that path
as he had been on, he was really struggling.
And all he could consider on that particular day was that at some point, whoever had put
that existing machinery in there, they probably had a similar type of a ceremony and celebration
as they brought in the new and did away with the old.
And now, however long later, he was part of that new group.
And he knew this, that at some point, his design, the machinery, that would be replaced
by something new, something better, something faster, more efficient, so on and so forth.
And I believe that, as I recall sitting in classes with this particular professor and
hearing his testimony on a regular basis and understanding this quote from C.T.
God, how powerful it is.
And it is true that as we live our lives, that we are to live for eternity, in light
of eternity.
No, God doesn't call everyone to the ministry.
God doesn't call everyone to serve as a pastor or missionary or evangelist.
But we do find that he does give us the responsibility to live our lives for Christ.
Whatever we find ourselves, whatever capacity it is that we find ourselves in, we understand
that God has placed us in that place for a purpose.
And yes, some of those purposes might be to provide for our families and so on and so
forth.
And absolutely, that's true.
But we find that ultimately, God has us in the places that he has us so that we could
be light, so that we could be his representatives in those places.
There are people that you come into contact with, there are people that I came into contact
with when I worked in the corporate world for many years that my pastor would never
meet.
It just never was going to happen that my pastor would ever sit down and have lunch
with some of the colleagues that I had when I worked in the corporate world.
And it's unlikely that I'll probably have lunch with some of your colleagues.
And so God has placed you there.
God had placed me in that particular setting with an opportunity to be a representative
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
We find that the Bible teaches us very plainly and very clearly the truth of the brevity
of life.
I think that C.T.
Studd was really capturing that idea, only one life, he says this, will soon be past.
And the Bible teaches us the truth of the brevity of life.
And the fact that the Bible says in James that our life is like a vapor that appeareth
for a little time and then it vanisheth away, and we can consider the brevity of life and
understand those truths, and we know as believers that we've been given the responsibility to
redeem the time and to understand that these days that God has given us to dwell here upon
the earth are few and we have opportunities that will soon be past.
The song that we sang this evening is, You're All on the Altar, and we think about this
song and if we answer the song with the answer of, yes, my all is on the altar, then there
will be no question who it is that we're living for.
Seems pretty obvious that if our all is on the altar, then we are living for Christ.
We're not living for self, we're living for Christ.
As I think about the song and I think about some of what we've dealt with even in recent
days as we've studied the book of Joshua, and we dealt with the first lesson there at
the end of the eighth chapter when they made those offerings, and we spoke about how they
offered burnt offerings and they sacrificed peace offerings upon that altar when Joshua
built the altar according to what was commanded by Moses there in Deuteronomy in chapter 27,
and we find the fulfillment.
And if you watched that particular Joshua lesson, you understand that I gave application
to how we as New Testament believers, we are to offer, give our bodies as a living sacrifice.
Paul mentions that in Romans chapter number 12 in verses 1 and 2, and it's a powerful
passage of scripture where Paul says, I beseech you therefore, brethren, by the mercies of
God that you present your bodies a living sacrifice, holy, acceptable unto God, which
is your reasonable service, and be not conformed to this world, but be transformed by the renewing
of your mind that you may prove what is that good and acceptable and perfect will of God.
As we think about the truth and the challenge, if you will, that Paul presents to the believers
in Rome when he says, I beseech you therefore, brethren, by the mercies of God that ye present
your bodies a living sacrifice, Paul was not giving them a challenge to do something that
he had not already done.
Yes, it was true that Paul was challenging the believers in Rome that they were to give
and they were to make their bodies a living sacrifice unto the Lord, but we understand
that Paul would give this declaration in Galatians 2, in verse number 20, where he would speak
of his own personal testimony, and he says, I am crucified with Christ.
Nevertheless, I live, yet not I, but Christ liveth in me, and the life which I now live
in the flesh I live by the faith of the Son of God who loved me and gave himself for me.
I believe that as you study the Scriptures, as you study the New Testament, you will find
that the Apostle Paul is one of the greatest examples of a man who was absolutely surrendered
to the will of God.
There are others, no doubt, that we could look to and we could see their example of
how they lived for the Lord and how they served the Lord and how they were crucified
with Christ, but as you trace the steps of the Apostle Paul, beginning in Acts chapter
number 9, after his conversion, of course, he's called Saul, and that passage of Scripture,
his name would then later be changed to Paul, and we've come to refer to him as the Apostle
Paul.
And we find that as you study his life and you trace his steps during those missionary
journeys, he was a man that was absolutely surrendered to the will of God for his life.
He was living for Jesus.
We sing that hymn, by the way, Living for Jesus.
What a great hymn that is.
And we think about the importance of living our lives.
That song that we would sing is a powerful song, but it's a convicting song.
See, that's one of the things that I love about singing the old hymns.
When we sing those songs, we are confronted with truth.
We are thinking about the words, and as we sing those songs, it's not just that we're
seeking to fill up some time and space in our services.
No, the songs are intended to convict us.
In fact, there are times in which, if we'd be honest this evening, we could have an invitation
after the song.
service. I think about one of the hymns that we sang last Sunday morning, I
surrender all. I surrender all. Man, that's a convicting song. And when we're
singing it, I wonder if we're really realizing what we're singing. I surrender
all. Not some, not most, but all. We know that our songbook is full of wonderful
songs that are thought-provoking, convicting songs. See, the Apostle Paul
had no problem declaring who he was living for. We find that he says to us
here in this passage of Scripture that is before us in Philippians 1 and verse
number 21, he says, for to me to live is Christ and to die is gain. I want you to
capture some of the, really, the context of what the Apostle Paul is saying. Back
up, if you will, to the twelfth verse of chapter number one of the book of
Philippians, and we could look at the first eleven verses and see the
greetings and the place that the people at Philippi had in the heart of the
Apostle Paul and his love, care, and concern for these believers at Philippi.
And we can rejoice in that relationship that had been established through the
missionary journey, the second missionary journey, when the Apostle Paul had the
privilege of being able to serve in that community. We believe that the book of
Philippians was written somewhere between 10 and 13 years after his first
arrival in Philippi in that ministry. Of course, the book of Philippians is a book
in which we can speak about rejoicing and joy, and he tells us in the fourth
chapter, a verse that is extremely familiar to many of us, in verse number
four, rejoice in the Lord always, and again I say, rejoice. Paul's writing from
prison, yet he's telling him about rejoicing. Isn't that wonderful? We find that
Paul begins in verse number 12 to capture the context of that great
statement that is made in verse number 21. Notice what he says,
but I would ye should understand, brethren, that the things which happened
unto me have fallen out rather unto the furtherance of the gospel. We could spend
the entirety of our time this evening just focusing on the truth of verse
number 12 and how the Apostle Paul had a proper perspective of his life. He
understood the sovereignty of God. He understood what we spoke about this
morning, remembering that the Lord is still on his throne and God is in
control. And the Apostle Paul says, there's something that I understand
about my current circumstances, but I want you to understand it as well. I
don't want you to be ignorant of these things, I want you to be aware. He said, I
would ye should understand, brethren, notice what he says, that the things
which happened unto me have fallen out rather unto the furtherance of the
gospel. There are times in which we can look at our circumstances and we can say,
woe is me, look at how unfortunate these things are, and look at all of these
things that I'm dealing with. But the Apostle Paul said, no, these things that
have happened have happened for the furtherance of the gospel. And he says
this in verse 13, so that my bonds in Christ are manifest in all the palace
and in all other places. Notice what Paul's saying. He's saying, I have
opportunities to share the gospel with people because of my circumstances that
otherwise I would not have had. That's a good perspective on life. I hope that
this evening, as we look at the book of Philippians and just review a few of
these things, that we would be challenged by the perspective of the Apostle Paul,
and we find that he speaks about the opportunities that the Lord would give
him given his current circumstances. And in the last part of the book of
Philippians, in chapter 4 and verse 22, he says this, all the saints salute you,
chiefly they that are of Caesar's household. What a blessing. There are some
people that got saved because Paul was in that place. Verse 14, and many of the
brethren in the Lord, waxing confident by my bonds, are much more bold to speak the
word without fear. Some indeed preach Christ, even of envy and strife, and some
also of goodwill. The one preached Christ of contention, not sincerely,
supposing to add affliction to my bonds, but the other of love, knowing that I am
set for the defense of the gospel. What then? Notwithstanding, every way, whether
in pretense or in truth, notice, Christ is preached, and I therein do rejoice, yea,
and will rejoice. For I know that this shall turn to my salvation
through your prayer and the supply of the Spirit of Jesus Christ, according to
my earnest expectation and my hope, that in nothing I shall be ashamed, but with
that with all boldness as always, so now also Christ shall be magnified in my
body, whether it be by life or by death. For to me to live is Christ, and to die
is gain. I notice as we look at the passage of Scripture, a commitment that
the Apostle Paul had made. I do not believe that Philippians 121, as we've
quoted it often, and maybe some of God's people over the years have used this
verse as maybe a life verse, if you will, and certainly it's an appropriate life
verse. It's appropriate for us to say, for to me to live is Christ, and to die is
gain, and we see the truth in this verse of Scripture with regard to the
life that I'm now living, that I would live this life for Christ, and that when
I, as Peter said in 2 Peter 1, put off this my earthly tabernacle, that I'll be
with Christ, that I will have that gain, and to die is gain. He goes on to mention
about the struggle that he was dealing with. He says in verse 23, I'm in a
strait betwixt two, having a desire to depart and be with Christ, which is far
better, and so Paul was assured of his salvation. Paul was absolutely confident
and to be absent from the body is to be present with the Lord. He knew that
truth. He proclaimed that truth, but Paul says, for to me to live is Christ. It's
not a cliche. It's a commitment. Every day of my life, I want it to count for Christ.
For to me to live is Christ, and to die is gain. I believe that there are some
things that Paul constantly remembered in his life that led him to making such
a commitment. If you will, just turn over with me to a couple of passages. We'll
just look at a couple. Look in 1 Corinthians chapter number 6. We'll look
at one in 2 Corinthians, and then we'll be back to the book of Philippians, but
notice in 1 Corinthians chapter number 6, in verses 19 and 20, again a familiar
passage of Scripture to us, but I believe that some of these things that Paul
often preached were things that he meditated upon himself and things that he
recalled on a regular basis. You find that as you study the life of the
Apostle Paul, I believe that I could say with accuracy that he never got over the
fact that he was saved. I don't think he ever forgot what happened on the road to
Damascus. You find that as he would stand before many and give his testimony that
he refers back to that day, and all that was taking place, and how he had been
saved, and what joy filled his heart and his life knowing that he belonged to
Jesus. In 1 Corinthians 6 and verses 19 and 20, he says to the believers in
Corinth, he says, what? Know ye not that your body is the temple of the Holy
Ghost, which is in you, which you have of God? And notice where he says, and ye are
not your own, for you're bought with a price. Therefore glorify God in your body
and in your spirit, which are God's. See, Paul understood the price that was paid
for his redemption. To redeem means to buy back. We speak about the truth of
redemption throughout the Scriptures, and we find if you were to study the first
chapter of the book of Ephesians, you would look at the plan of redemption and
you would see the price for redemption, and that is the precious blood of Christ.
We find that Peter deals with that truth in 1 Peter chapter 1, that we're
not redeemed with corruptible things such as silver and gold. No, we're redeemed
with the precious blood of Christ. We find that Ephesians goes on to deal with
the proof of our redemption, the fact that the Holy Spirit of God indwells us,
and we see here in this passage how that the Apostle Paul connects those
things. He says that our bodies are the temple of the Holy Ghost. He tells us two
very important things. Number one, we're not our own. You go through life and you
hear people say, I'm my own man. I do what I want to do. I'm my own, you know,
whatever, and the reality is that as God's people, we're not our own. We've
been bought with a price, and that price is the precious blood of our Savior, God
in flesh, Messiah, the Lord Jesus Christ. If you were to read the gospel accounts
and read the end of each gospel account, Matthew, Mark, Luke, and John, and read the
account of the
of the crucifixion,
you will see the price that was paid
for your redemption.
And I would submit to you
that the Apostle Paul,
as he would consider this commitment
when he would say for me to live as Christ
and to die as Gain,
he would understand,
he would have this knowledge
of the fact that he was not his own,
that he was bought with a price,
and he concludes,
since I'm not my own,
since I was bought with a price,
therefore, the natural conclusion
that we reach based upon that truth
is that we are to glorify God
in our bodies.
He says this,
therefore, glorify God in your body
and in your spirit which are God's.
He would say there in 1 Corinthians 10
and verse 31,
you don't need to turn there,
but he says,
therefore, whether you eat or drink
or whatsoever you do,
do all to the glory of God.
In 2 Corinthians 5,
what led to the commitment?
Because I see in Philippians 1 and verse 21,
I see a great declaration
that the Apostle Paul would make there
in that passage of Scripture,
but I find more than just a declaration,
I see a commitment daily
that I'm going to live for Christ.
I believe the truth here
in 2 Corinthians 5,
I preached on this passage of Scripture
several Sunday mornings ago.
He reconciled.
And we find that in verse 14
of 2 Corinthians 5,
the Bible says,
for the love of Christ constraineth us
because we thus judge
that if one died for all,
then we're all dead.
And then he died for all
that they which live
should not henceforth live unto themselves,
but unto him which died for them
and rose again.
Those of you that have received
any sort of correspondence from me
over the years,
know that 2 Corinthians 5
and verse 15 is a verse
that I put in emails,
letters, cards,
whatever that I send out.
This verse of Scripture
has had a profound impact upon my life.
I mentioned the song that we sing,
Living for Jesus,
and we find here
that in the verse of Scripture,
he says in that he died for all
that they which live
should not henceforth live unto themselves,
no, but unto him which died for them
and rose again.
So often, I think in our culture,
we've been given this mindset
and this perspective of
what are you going to do with your life?
Young people hear it all of the time.
My children are getting older.
And 13, 15, and 17,
it's hard to believe,
Juliana had her birthday last week,
turned 17.
She's gonna be a senior in high school.
And as such,
will be asked the question
hundreds of times.
She's already been asked the question
plenty of times.
What are you going to do?
We remember,
those of us that were seniors in high school,
we remember being asked that question.
Even before you're a senior,
you get asked,
what are you gonna do?
Where are you gonna go to college?
What are you gonna do with your life?
So on and so forth.
And I have submitted to many over the years
that a better question is not
what do I want to do with my life,
but what does the Lord want me to do with my life?
As the people of God,
as people that understand redemption,
as people that understand the truth of the Word of God,
we ought to make this commitment that Paul made
for me to live as Christ and to die as Gain.
And what is it that the Lord wants me to do?
Again, not every person will be a missionary
or a pastor,
but we have to understand
what does God want with my life?
We know through the revealed will of God
that He wants us to live for Him.
He wants us to live for Him.
He doesn't want us to live for self.
He wants us to live for Christ.
We find there in the book of Philippians,
I mentioned that we'd get back there in just a moment.
Look, we're looking at the first chapter.
Look at chapter number three.
In chapter number three,
the Bible gives us some truth
with regard to the life of Paul
and some of the things that he deals with.
And he says in verse number four,
though I might also have confidence in the flesh,
if any other man thinketh that he hath whereof,
he might trust in the flesh, I more.
Circumcised the eighth day,
the stock of Israel of the tribe of Benjamin
and Hebrew of the Hebrews is touching the law of Pharisee.
Concerning zeal, persecuting the church,
touching the righteousness which is in the law,
blameless, verse seven.
But what things were gained to me,
those I counted loss for Christ.
Yea, doubtless, and I count all things but loss
for the excellency of the knowledge of Christ Jesus,
my Lord, for whom I have suffered the loss of all things
and do count them but dung,
that I may win Christ and be found in him,
not having mine own righteousness, which is of the law,
but that which is through the faith of Christ,
the righteousness which is of God by faith,
that I may know him and the power of his resurrection
and the fellowship of his sufferings,
being made conformable unto his death.
If by any means I might attain
unto the resurrection of the dead,
not as though I had already attained,
either were already perfect, but I followed after.
If that, notice where he says,
I may apprehend that for which also I am apprehended
of Christ Jesus.
Brethren, I count not myself to have apprehended,
but this one thing I do,
forgetting those things which are behind
and reaching forth unto those things which are before,
I press toward the mark for the prize
of the high calling of God in Christ Jesus.
Paul says, for to me to live is Christ
and to die is gain.
He made a commitment.
Again, this is not some sort of cliche.
It's a commitment that Paul made.
I believe that as the recipients
of this wonderful letter that we call
the book of Philippians,
that as they received and read,
I believe that many within the congregation
of the church at Philippi,
they would agree with what Paul is saying.
They had the privilege of seeing his life and ministry
and they would understand exactly what he was meaning
when he said, for to me to live is Christ
and to die is gain.
I believe that in that phraseology
and in that statement,
that there's not only a commitment,
but there's also a level of conviction
upon the people that are reading
the truth that's been given.
Could I say that?
I wonder as the believers in Philippi
receive the letter and they read it for the first time,
I wonder if any amongst them would say,
I wonder if I could say that.
I wonder if I could say that,
for to me to live is Christ and to die is gain.
There's a level there of conviction
when you read about the commitment that was made.
And I wonder this evening,
if any had had that thought on whether or not
they too could make that comment,
if they could make that declaration.
I wonder this evening,
if there were some that were saying,
I need to be in that place
where I could make the same commitment
that the Apostle Paul made,
for to me to live is Christ.
Can I tell you that you would never regret
living for Christ?
Remember the quote that we started this evening
from C.T. Studd,
only when life will soon be passed,
only what's done for Christ will last.
It's interesting as we look at the commitment
of the Apostle Paul and we see what he says
and really the focus of our message this evening
is dealing with what led to that commitment
and the commitment itself.
But I want you to notice in the book of Philippians
in the second chapter,
I want you to see a contrast that the Lord gives us.
And as we look at this contrast
in Philippians chapter number two,
beginning in verse number 19,
I want you to see what the Apostle Paul says.
Now remember, he's writing from prison
and he tells them in verse number 19,
but I trust and in Philippians two in verse 19,
but I trust in the Lord Jesus
to send Timotheus shortly unto you,
that I also may be of good comfort
when I know your state.
So we understand the Apostle Paul
had had communication with the believers in Philippi,
they sent and communicated with him.
If you read the fourth chapter,
you see their involvement in his ministry and what have you,
but you find here that the Apostle Paul
had an interest in knowing the state of the flock,
knowing the state of the church in Philippi.
He himself was not able to go and just travel
and go over there to Philippi
and find out how things were going.
So he would send Timothy in his place.
It's interesting as you kind of on a side note,
as you notice often throughout the epistles
that the Apostle Paul is concerned
about those that God allowed him to minister to.
He speaks to the believers in Thessalonica.
We looked at 1 Thessalonians 2 last Sunday morning
and you look in the passages there
in the book of 1 Thessalonians
and you see that Paul was going to send Timothy
to find out how they were doing.
He was concerned for them.
He says this in 2 Corinthians,
you don't need to turn there,
but chapter 11 and verse 21,
he says beside those things that are without,
that which cometh upon me daily,
the care of all the churches.
The Apostle Paul wanted to know their state.
So he's going to send Timothy, verse 20,
notice what he says in Philippians 2 and verse 20,
for I have no man like minded
who will naturally care for your state.
And then notice this truth in verse 21,
for all seek their own.
not the things which are Jesus Christ.
But ye know the proof of Him
that as a son with the Father,
He hath served me in the gospel."
Verse 22 is a testimony of Timothy.
He's going back and speaking about
the testimony of Timothy.
That's why he's going to send Timothy to them
because of the testimony that he has.
But I want you to notice the contrast
between what Paul says in Philippians 1
and verse 21 of himself.
For to me to live is Christ
and to die is gain.
And what he says of those in Philippians 2
and verse 21,
for all seek their own,
not the things which are Jesus Christ's.
What sad commentary is given
in Philippians 2 and verse 21?
I've asked the question this evening,
who are you living for?
We sang the song as our final
congregational song.
I love it when it works this way.
I didn't ask Holly to pick songs this week.
I mean, I asked her to pick them,
but I didn't tell her which songs to pick.
She just picked the songs.
And she told me what they were.
And honestly, the only thought that I had
wasn't so much with what songs they were,
but the fact that we had at least
one patriotic song this morning.
And I didn't give much thought
to the songs and which order they were in
and all of those things.
She was handling that.
And I appreciate her doing that.
And as we turn to that last hymn this evening,
I didn't realize until we got up here
until we were singing our theme song,
I didn't realize that the last hymn
that we would sing tonight
is, You're All on the Altar.
And as we sang that song,
and actually when Jared was still
leading the theme song as we were singing it,
I was thinking how appropriate
is, You're All on the Altar,
and I'm preaching a message,
who are you living for?
And if we can sing that song
that we sang this evening,
and we can say, yes, my all is on the altar,
then the answer's obvious.
I'm living for Christ.
For me to live is Christ,
and to die is gain.
I don't want to be categorized
as those unnamed people
in Philippians 2.21
that Paul concludes of them
that they seek their own
and not the things which are Jesus Christ's.
I'd rather stand understanding
what the Lord has done for me,
understanding that I'm not my own,
I've been bought with a price.
And being able to stand and say
for me to live is Christ,
to die is gain.
Does it mean that I'm going to be perfect
or you're going to be perfect?
Absolutely not.
But it means that every day
we make a conscience decision
that today, I want to live for Jesus.
It's not about me.
I'm not crucified with Christ.
I have followed the call
that was issued in Romans 12.
I beseech you therefore, brethren,
by the mercies of God,
that you present your bodies
a living sacrifice,
holy, acceptable unto God,
He says, which is your reasonable service,
that I could say,
for to me to live is Christ,
and to die is gain.
Who are you living for?
Father, we love You
and we thank You for loving us.
We thank You that You
have a perfect plan.
And in that plan,
You sent Your Son,
the Lord Jesus Christ,
to come to this incursed world
to live a perfect, sinless life,
to die, to be buried,
to rise in victory,
to redeem us.
We know that that plan of redemption
was a plan that was determined
before the foundation of the world,
that Jesus is the Lamb of God
that was slain
before the foundation of the world.
We know that as we study
the book of Ephesians,
that the text of Scripture
is dealing with the how of salvation,
not the who of salvation,
and for that we rejoice.
And God, I pray that as Your people,
those of us that have been redeemed,
as we sing,
redeemed how I love to proclaim it,
redeemed by the blood of the Lamb,
Lord, that we would understand
that we're not our own,
that we've been bought with a price,
that we could say I am crucified with Christ,
that we could say with Paul,
for to me to live is Christ,
and to die is gain.
Living for Jesus, Lord,
that's our desire,
that our lives would count for Christ,
that You would enable us
to make an impact upon eternity,
and we'll thank You for it.
During this time of invitation,
would You move in hearts and lives,
would You alone be glorified?
We'll thank You for what You'll do,
for it's in Christ's name we pray.