meeting is just a place on a calendar. Just because we hold a revival meeting
doesn't mean that God is going to change us or that there's going to be revival.
But I do believe that revival meetings are important because they mark a time
in our lives where we can say to the Lord, speak to me. Where we give God the
opportunity because we are opening the Word and we are looking at Scripture and
we can say, please use this time to work in my life. The other thing I would say
about revival is this. I spend a lot of my time looking at the world and
critiquing the world and finding all that there is in the world that is going
wrong and being done wrong and doing wrong and all of that. I'm a fundamental
Baptist preacher. I can see the wrong in anything and bring it out. But you know,
a time like this in our lives, these meetings are less about us examining the
world and more about making sure that we give God the opportunity to examine us.
Because the truth is, revival doesn't start in the world. It doesn't start in
the halls of Congress. It doesn't start in the White House. It starts in me.
And so I pray with that spirit and with that understanding, you'll look to this
message tonight and just allow God to speak into your life. I am saying very
clearly at the beginning of this message that I'm asking God to do the same thing
in my life. I'm not scolding you. I'm not trying to be harsh in my preaching. I'm
trying to be honest with myself and allow the Holy Spirit to have time to
look at me. And my prayer is that you'll do the same thing. Having said that,
turn with me to Hosea chapter 7. Now Hosea hangs around with Daniel. And if
you find Daniel and go one more, you'll find Hosea. Hosea chapter 7. And we're
going to begin our reading in verse 8. Hosea 7 and verse 8. And there the
scripture says this. Ephraim, he hath mixed himself among the people. Ephraim
is a cake not turned. Strangers have devoured his strength, and he knoweth it
not. Yea, gray hairs are here and there upon him, yet he knoweth not. And the
pride of Israel testifieth to his face, and they do not return to the Lord their
God, nor seek him for all this. Ephraim also is like a silly dove without heart.
They call to Egypt, they go to Assyria. When they shall go, I will spread my net
upon them. I will bring them down as the fowls of the heaven. I will chastise them
as their congregation hath heard. Woe unto them, for they have fled from me.
Destruction unto them, because they have transgressed against me, though I have
redeemed them, yet they have spoken lies against me. And they have not cried unto
me with their heart. When they howl upon their beds, they assemble themselves for
corn and wine, and they rebel against me. Let's pray and ask God's help. Father,
we're so grateful for this time that you've given us tonight. I thank you, Lord,
for these that have gathered and sang, and just the blessing the music is. I
thank you for those that are listening by the way of livestream. And Lord, we
understand this is not how we would have chosen to do this meeting or to meet
together, but it is what you've allowed, it's what you've given us, and so we're
grateful for that. And we pray that, Lord, you would use these moments in our life
and use your word and speak to us. Lord, we are so quick to complain, we are so
quick to indict the world, and it is indictable. But Father, what about
ourselves? And the truth is, if the world is ever going to see you, they're going
to have to see you through our testimony, through our lives. They're going to have
to hear our words, and our words will need the influence of a right life and
fellowship with you. And so I pray that we would think about these things
tonight, not looking at our brother or sister, not looking at those in the world
which we so easily condemn, but looking at ourselves. I pray it in Jesus' name.
Amen. I want to preach tonight on this thought. I have a lot of experience with
this. Gray hairs. If you notice in verse 9, again, it says, strangers have devoured
his strength, and he knoweth it not, yea, gray hairs are here and there upon him,
yet he knoweth not. A lot of times in the Bible, perhaps most of the time in the
Bible, when you hear gray hairs, you see that phrase or something akin to it, what
we're talking about is the wisdom that experience brings, the blessing that
age can be, because it allows us to have experienced those things and understood
their blessings or consequences, and then be able to communicate to younger
people what they need to know and how they should react if they face that same
situation. And by the way, we live in a generation where gray-headed, the hoary
head, is disrespected. It's almost as if it's old, you throw it away, when in truth,
biblically, there is tremendous wisdom and blessing in hearing the advice of
those that are older than us, and those that have experienced life, and we are
just getting ready to experience it. But to be honest with you, in our passage
tonight, gray hair is not referring to the blessing of age and wisdom, it's
referring to something quite different, and in our text tonight, it is
referring to decay. The gray hair not only can demonstrate wisdom from
experience, it's gray because it is in a process of decay. I hate to admit this
about myself, but I can't do what I used to do, and just about everything on
me hurts at one point through the day. My good friend, Dr. Don Sisk, told me one
time, he said, Mike, after 70, if you wake up and something doesn't hurt, you didn't
actually wake up. And I think there's truth to that. You know, no matter how we
try to put it off, here's the truth. Each and every one of us were born to die, and
and our journey through this life is a journey that takes us from dust back to
dust. And I'm not trying to be discouraging to you tonight, I'm trying
to be realistic with you that our lives are going to experience decay, and
the truth is, the day is going to come, if Jesus does not come first, that I'm
going to die, and I'm going to be in the presence of the Lord through that
experience of death. And I can take vitamins, and I can try to eat
better than I do, and do all that I can to prolong it and to keep
strength in it, but I don't care what I do, and I don't care what vitamins I take,
I am decaying and moving towards death. Are you encouraged yet? No. But what is
true of my physical life does not have to be true of my spiritual life. And I
can be as vibrant and as vital for God the day that he takes me home as I was
the day that he saved my soul and put something in me that I'd never
experienced before. I may not be able to do all the things in ministry that I
once could do, but I can have influence, I can make a difference, I can be used of
the Lord up until the very day that he takes me out of this world. And I know
that you feel the same way that I do. I don't want to be a statistic, I don't
want to be
one of those people who used to. I don't want to be one of those folks
who once had a ministry, or once cared about the way I lived my life, or once
cared about the influence of the Spirit in and through my life. I want to have a
fire and a passion for serving the Lord until God takes me out. And to be honest
with you, if I'm going to do that, then I am going to have to pay attention to what
Hosea speaks to the nation of the northern nation of Israel about in this
passage. Because he says, Israel Ephraim, and understand Hosea was a prophet to
the northern kingdom of the ten tribes that had their capital in
Samaria, and God is trying to reach out to them. God is trying to bring them home
and bring them back, and Hosea preaches to them, and he says to them, Ephraim,
Israel, I see something about you, and what I see about you is that there are
gray hairs of decay in your spiritual life, and you're not even aware that
they're there. You know that you and I can be the very same way. What we so
easily see in others, we don't see in ourselves. What we so easily condemn in
others, we barely recognize in ourselves. And I think this message tonight will
confront us with the gray hairs, the spiritual gray hairs that are in our
life. Let me give four of them to you. Number one, there is what Hosea
identifies, as I call it, the gray hair of false testimony. The gray hair of
false testimony. I take you to verse 8. Ephraim, he hath mixed himself among the
people. Ephraim is a cake not turned. Again, Ephraim is referenced to the ten
tribes who were the nation of Samaria, or Israel, if you will, and Hosea
preaching to them says, listen, you know what you are, Israel? You know what you
are, Ephraim? You are a cake not turned. Now let me unpack that just a little bit.
In Bible times, in these days, they did not have convection ovens. They didn't
have our wonderful appliances in our kitchens that circulate the air so
that no matter where that loaf is placed, it has an even heat all around it.
They had, if they were wealthy, they had a stone oven. If they were not wealthy,
they had a hot rock or maybe a cooking pot of some kind. And when they fashioned
that loaf and were going to cook that loaf for their family or for their shop,
it was attendant upon them that one person, the baker, be there to constantly
turn that stone. Because there wasn't circulating air, it was extremely hot on
the stone and much, much cooler all around it. If you put that in there and
didn't pay attention to it, you had a very lovely brown bottom to the loaf. But
when you opened that loaf or cut into that loaf or bit into that loaf, you
found that what looked done on the bottom was mush on the inside, and it was
not worth eating. It couldn't be eaten. And what Hosea is saying to Israel is
this, you are not on the inside what you profess to be on the outside. You may
have a brown crust that looks inviting, but when we get inside you, when we get
into the heart of Ephraim, we realize that the appearance is not what is
actually going on inside. And I fear for our churches, I fear for Christians
today. We have been affected by wanting to look good and satisfied if people
think we are something, even if we are not actually that something in our
hearts. I want people to think I'm a good man. I want people to look at me and
think, boy, that's a guy who really loves the Lord. I want to be well thought of.
Hey, have you ever noticed our social media? Nobody ever shows their bad day.
Everything is about their good day. Everything is about the good part of
their lives, and it is very rare for them to portray what the rest of life
actually is. We have in our news right now this tragic case of this young lady
who was found murdered after being on this cross-country trip with her fiance.
I don't understand the parenting that would allow that, but they allowed that,
and every picture that they posted on their social media was a picture of
absolute perfection. It was just joy. It was everything you would have ever
dreamed, and I'm sure that people that looked at it, young people especially,
said, man, someday I'd like to have that. And then the veneer is pulled back, and
we find out that there's fighting, and tears, and anger, and anger to the point
where this young lady is murdered. And so all I'm saying is, is that what it
appeared to be was not what it actually was, and I have a great fear that we have
churches across America, even churches like our churches, where people are
satisfied to be well thought of and have a good appearance, even if the heart is
not the picture as presented on the outside. I had in our church that I
pastored for so long, my office was on the second floor, and I had a window that
looked out over the parking lots. And one of my favorite things, it's strange,
but one of my favorite things was just to watch families come to church. I'd
watch them drive in, they'd get out of the car, the husband would have his Bible,
the wife would have three car carriers, and 12 kids, and nine Bibles, and bags.
You know, I'd go down and preach on men helping their wives. But one thing I
observed for months, and it was a man who would pull into the parking lot, the very
front, his family would get out, no problem, they would come in the front
door, and he would walk all the way down the parking lot, all the way around to
the back door, and come in the back. It didn't matter if it was a hundred and
five degrees, it didn't matter if it was ten below, it didn't matter if it was
sunshine or rain, he did the same thing every Sunday. And I thought, that's so
strange. And so one day, naive, innocent me, I went to him and I said, why do
you let your family off, park there, and walk all the way around? And here's what
he said to me, well preacher, you just have to understand that so-and-so is a
greeter at that front door, and I don't like him. And there's just something
that we've got between us, and I just don't want to look at him, I don't want
to shake his hand. And I thought to myself, you sing in our choir, you say
amen when I preach. And here's the truth, I know it's not the greatest sin in all
the world, I know it may not in our hearts and minds compare to what this
young man we think has done to this young lady, but it is a picture of what
we so often are. We profess to be right with God, we profess to be walking with
God, we profess to be close to God, and we do the right things, and we sing the
hymns, and we know the words, and we carry a King James, and we say amen where we're
supposed to say amen, and we come to three to thrive, we do all of that stuff,
and we carry garbage in our heart, and wonder why we don't have revival, and
wonder why we don't have influence to win people to Christ. That's an example.
It could be a thousand things. Every Saturday morning at our church, we had
men's prayer meeting at 730. I don't think everybody has to do that, it's what we did.
And as part of that, I would take my boys when they were old enough to go, and we
would get in the car, and we'd go to prayer meeting, they would pray with
other men, pray with me, pray with boys. I just wanted to have the experience of
praying with good men. And after prayer meeting was over, we'd have donuts and
coffee, and we'd go back home, and on our way between the house and the church was
a 7-eleven. And everybody knows what's in 7-eleven, slurpees and coffee are in
7-eleven. So when we would go home, I'd stop almost every Saturday and say, guys
get get a candy bar, get a slurpee, I'll get a cup of coffee, and I'll take you
home, and then I'm gonna...
gonna go soul winning.
But outside that 7-Eleven, there was a perfect oak tree.
It reminds me a great deal of this oak tree
sitting down in front of the parsonage.
And I would take my boys when they had their slurpees
and I had my coffee, just, there was a picnic table
over there and we'd sit down for just a moment.
I can remember 25 times saying to my boys,
hey guys, your dad wants to be like this oak tree.
I wanna be strong, I wanna be a place where people
can have refuge, where they can feel secure.
I wanna be symmetrical, I just wanna be strong
like this oak tree.
And then I'd say, guys, I want you to be strong
I'll never forget one morning, we came around the corner,
there'd been a windstorm.
And the windstorm or the lightning had hit that tree
and it had split four different directions
and there was nothing inside the bark.
It was rotten to the core.
Well, I pulled my car in that place and called my assistant,
said I won't be at men's prayer meeting this morning,
I gotta take care of something with my boys,
please take that.
And I pulled them over, we went over to that tree
and not angrily, but I said to them, guys,
I don't ever want to be like this oak tree.
And I never want you to be like this oak tree.
I don't want to be one of those who sets themselves forth
as something they are not.
I want it to be real.
I want it to be real on the outside
and I want it to be real on the inside.
I want you to know that what your dad says he is.
And that's the kind of man I want you to be.
I'm not trying to be harsh.
But I'm telling you, our churches are filled with people
that are satisfied to carry a grudge,
that say amen to portions of the scripture
that they have no intention of being obedient to
in their lives, that understand what the Bible says
about the home and have no sense of instituting
those things in their home, in their lives.
And it's a gray hair.
And I'm telling you that when we are satisfied,
you say, well, preacher, everybody has something.
Yes, we do.
All of us have something in our lives
that isn't the way it should be.
My fear is this, is that when we are satisfied
for it to be that way,
when we will come into church, when we will hear preaching,
when we will sense from the Holy Spirit
that he wants us to deal with that,
and our reaction is, this is just how I am.
And we're willing to stay that way.
You say, well, preacher, I've been saved 30 years.
I've been saved 40 years.
Hey, listen, to accept without caring sin in our lives
is not a sign of maturity.
It's a sign of backsliding, of being away from the Lord.
And so I say to you, Hosea looked at Ephraim
and he said, you're not what you say you are.
You give the appearance of one thing on the outside,
but when I get into there, you're not worshiping Jehovah.
You're chasing idols.
You're as pagan as the ones that live around you,
but you're trying to present yourself
as God's people, Jeroboam.
The gray hair of false testimony.
Here's number two.
Not only the gray hair of false testimony,
but the gray hair of a fruitless life.
Look at verse nine again.
Strangers have devoured his strength.
He knoweth it not.
Yea, gray hairs are here and there upon the face of the earth
and gray hairs are here and there upon him,
yet he knoweth not.
What an arresting statement that is in verse nine.
Strangers have devoured his strength and he knoweth it not.
Can I help us understand that a consistent theme
in the word of God is that the loss of God's power
is rarely obvious and violent.
It is more often a subtle process of decay.
We just let it happen.
Or we go through the motions.
We continue to do what we used to do.
We just don't have the influence that we used to have.
Samson stood up one day after having for years
thrown off his attackers.
Oh, he had led a loose life.
He had been disobedient to parents,
disobedient to the Lord,
but he just assumed that he could always
throw off the attackers.
But one day he stood up and he didn't, he wist not,
he didn't even know the spirit had departed.
King Saul remained king long after God
had removed his hand.
That's startling to me.
He was king.
He commanded the armies,
but God had long ago anointed another to be king
and God's hand had been removed from Saul.
Oh, he went through the motions, but the power was gone.
Did you know that it was a full year
from David's sin with Bathsheba
before Nathan the prophet came in and confronted him
and David admitted, I am the man.
You're right.
And for a full year, he kept singing his Psalms.
And for a full year, he kept going to worship at the temple.
And for a full year, he paraded before his armies.
And for a full year,
he acted like the sweet singer of Israel.
And all the time during that year,
what the Bible tells us is he was eaten up inside.
But he went through the motions.
I'm just telling you that Ichabod was written
over the temple long before services stopped in the temple.
The truth is we're able to go through the motions.
I wonder how many Sunday school lessons are taught
with no real sense of God's power and God's blessing on.
I wonder how many sermons are preached in pulpits
where there is no true sense of God's power and blessing.
Hey, listen, I know how to write three points in a poem.
I know how to do this and do this.
I can go through the motions.
But going through the motions
does not bring the power of God.
And here's the truth.
If we're going to see where we are,
it is not in the sense of, do I do what I used to do?
It is in the small things that only we notice in our heart.
Let me tell you two things.
How do you tell if the influence and the power
of the Spirit is slipping out of your life?
Two things.
Number one, you'll begin to notice
a lack of appetite for what is good.
You'll begin to notice that your appetite
for what is good is changing.
I think I was telling preacher today,
I remember when I first got saved
and I was finding verses like John 3.16.
I know this may be amazing to you,
but as a 23-year-old man, I never saw it.
I never knew it.
And I found it and I thought, the world's gotta know this.
They don't know this.
And I would go into the factory and I would tell people,
hey, God so loved the world,
and they'd look back at me and say,
yeah, yeah, everybody knows that preacher.
We learned that in Sunday school.
They would call me Preacher Edwards.
I can remember every time I opened the Word of God,
God would speak to me.
God would show me something.
I can remember when I would pray and be startled,
startled when God answered exactly what I asked him to do.
And I ask us tonight,
when's the last time God showed you something
in his Word for you?
When's the last time there was that sweet desire
to meet with him over his Word
and to tarry with him in prayer?
When's the last time, not generally speaking,
but specific to your life that you can say,
hey, God showed me this.
God spoke to me about this.
God did this in answer to my prayer.
You'll notice that the services of church
are not near as exciting as they once were.
As a matter of fact, they almost have to be endured.
Well, I remember when I got saved,
and I keep saying that like I don't now.
I am passionate about preaching, not just my preaching.
But I see so many folks who were on fire
for a year or two or three,
and then you look at their life as they move down the road,
and now it's as if,
when are they gonna get done?
You say, well, preacher, everybody's.
got stuff to do. I realize everybody's got stuff to do, but I'm telling you
there was a time in your life when you didn't look at your watch. There was a
time in your life where you hung on every word. You say, well, for good
preachers, you're just not a good preacher. Hey, it's God's Word. And I'm
asking you, you know, we've been in a strange time of history. You know what my
great fear is? That folks have gotten used to not going to church and they
think, well, I can sit here and be comfortable. I'm not faulting you. I know
that this is a special circumstance in this church. Please don't hear that as
condemnation. But across America, folks, probably around 70% of people have come
back to church. There's 30% of people that may use COVID as an excuse,
but are not motivated enough to come back to church. You know what that is?
That is a gray hair. You say, well, I've heard preaching for a long time, preacher.
Oh, so you've matured to where you don't need it? Because the Apostle Paul said, I
remember him saying something like this, that he had not yet apprehended that
for which he was apprehended, and he was pressing toward the mark. And there was
no time in that great man's life where he said, I'm gonna put it in neutral, and I
don't need much anymore. Complacency is overtaking our churches. And I'm
suggesting to you that if you have a sense of that in your heart, that's not
growth. That's a problem. And ask God's help to deal with it. Service is forsaken.
People don't sing anymore. Soul winning? What's that? Witnessing? That's something
you do in a foreign country. Hey, not only do we start to lose our taste for
that which is good, we start to gain a taste for that which is bad. We become
content with a lower standard of Christian living. The shows we would have
never watched, we now watch. The things we would have never chuckled about,
sometimes we think, well, maybe that's a little funny. We become flippant about
faithfulness. We become flippant about sin. We become indifferent to conviction.
And I'm just asking you, take a look at your heart. Don't look at me. Don't look
at someone else. Don't think about your husband, or your wife, or your kids, or
your parents. What about you? And has there been that subtle change in your
love for that which is good, in your disdain for that which is evil? And if so,
admit it to yourself, and ask the Spirit of God's help, help me to pluck that gray
hair. Here's number three. The gray hair of callousness. Look at verse 10.
And the pride of Israel testifieth to his face, and they do not return to the
Lord their God, nor seek him for all this. God spoke to them. They knew what God was
saying to them, but their pride would not let them get it right. And so God could
speak, and what used to be convicting to them was no longer convicting to
them. You see, sin makes us insensitive. And one of the greatest fears I have for
our country, oh you say, well it must be this party, or that party, oh it must be
this bill, or that bill, must be this election, or that election. No! The
greatest fear I have for our nation is we are becoming churches of dry eyes and
empty altars. Dry eyes, empty altars. You say preacher, I used to when you would
preach on that, boy God would get a hold of my heart, and I was under conviction.
But to be honest with you preacher, I've heard you preach on that so much, and
I've heard a lot better preachers than you preach on that, and to be honest with
you, it used to bother me, but it doesn't bother me. Oh, you've matured? No. When we
can ignore the convicting hand of the Holy Spirit, that's not maturity. So often
people will say to me, hey you know preacher, I've served, and I've done this,
and I've done that, I've done it for years, let somebody else do it for a while.
That is not growth in your Christian life! And may God touch our hearts, and
help us to see that whether we're sitting in our living room, or family
room, or kitchen table listening to this on livestream, or whether we're sitting
in this room tonight, or wherever we are, that if the Holy Spirit of God will come
down and and love us so much, that he will walk this aisle, or come to our aisle,
and speak to our heart, and say that's you, you've grown calloused. You don't
want to go forward because you don't want anybody to think less of you. That
takes us back to the first one, where we want everybody to think we've got it
squared away. When we know we don't, and we know in our heart that we're
disappointing, we're not pleasing to the Lord in some area in our life, and oh my,
when God's Holy Spirit will speak to us that way, there is but one answer that
should come from us, yes God, yes God, yes God. And I don't care who sees it, and I
don't care who knows it, God you're right, I'm not where I used to be, I'm not where
I once was, and I've become comfortable with being away from where I
used to be, and need to be, and I don't want to be troubled with it, and that's
exactly where Ephraim was, and so God would speak to him, and speak to him, and
speak to him, and their pride would be a stone face, and their heart was callous,
and they would not respond. There's a fourth hair, a gray hair, notice it in
verse 11, Ephraim also is like a silly dove without heart, they call to Egypt,
and they go to Assyria, the hair of silliness.
Hosea says, you ever seen a dove? A dove is always flitting around, very nervous,
always flitting around, going from this, to this, to this, to this, to that, and you
know what Christians, I think in our day, could be described as, as silly. You see,
I think so many have come to the place where our callousness has, has not allowed
God to speak to us, and so we sense that we're not where we are, ought to be, we
sense that we don't have the influence, we don't have the same measure of the
Spirit's power and influence that we once had, and you know what that must be?
That must be the preacher's fault. He looked at Ephraim and he said, you, you're
God's people, and you are looking for help from Egypt. What is wrong with your
thinking? You are running to Egypt because you need help, because you're
under attack, and you're asking, where is it? When did you start doing that? Do
you remember when you came to me and I answered and deliver you? Not only did
they go to Egypt, they went to Assyria. Hey Assyria, can you help us? You know why
they did that? Because they had no communication with the Lord. And today I
see it in churches all across America, preacher. You know what we need? We need a
new style of music, that's what we need. If we had a new style of music, the
Spirit would descend upon this place and, whoo, we'd have a full house, it'd be
great. Hey preacher, you know what we need? We need a new version of the Bible,
because we need a Bible that we can read and, and in our words, hey preacher, you
know what we need? We need a new you. Yeah. Preacher, you just don't feed us.
Preacher, you just don't this. On and on and we go from this, to this, to this, to
that, and you know why? Because we don't come down here. Because the altar is no
longer the answer to our hearts. Because repentance and getting right with God
is no longer the answer. Notice what he says in verse 14, they have not cried
unto me from their heart. Oh, they howl on their beds, they assemble themselves for
corn and wine, but they rebel against me.
me. Now I'm finished but here's my point. These things are progressive. When we are
willing to be on the outside to appear to be something we are not really on the
inside, I'm telling you it's the first step to a fruitless life. A life where we
become contented with doing less, with being less, with caring less about the
good and entertaining more of the evil. And then it leads to a callous life
because we no longer want to be bothered. Well we'll go through the motions, we'll
do what we do because we want people to think we are solid Christians and we
want people to think we are involved and we've got it all squared away but we
just notice that we're not bearing fruit like we once did. Our devotions
aren't deep like they once were. Our heart is not seeing answered prayer like
it once did and and we notice that we're becoming okay with that. We're just not
tore up about not having that close walk with the Lord and I'm telling you before
very long we think the answer is somewhere else and it's someone else's fault. I don't
know about you, I suspect I do, that you think exactly like I do in the sense
that I don't want to be a statistic. I don't want to be that one who once
walked with God but now does not have power with God or influence with God. I
don't want to be that one who once had a heart that sought him and wanted to
know him and wanted to be changed from the inside out. I don't want to go to
where I'm just complacent and I'm satisfied with where I am and feel no
need to change. No, I want to be the kind of person that is always watching me. I
want to watch me and Holy Spirit I'm giving you entrance to my life and I'm
asking you will you expose to me those gray hairs that will lead to a place
where I am somebody who used to, where I'm somebody that you could have used
but not now. I don't want to get to the place where I don't have influence
for you and and where I'm just one of those guys, you know, he says he's a
Christian. God help us to see that revival does not start in Congress.
Revival doesn't even start in this church. It starts in me. It starts in my
heart when I'm willing to say to the Lord, you're right and there are things
that need to be adjusted in my walk with you and I don't care who thinks of ill
of me. I don't care if it dashes somebody's concept of who I am. I know
I'm not what I need to be. I'm not saying I'm in deep sin. I just know I've moved
and it's not growth. Would you pray with me?
Fathers, we come to you tonight. I pray for everyone in this room. I pray for
everyone who is so patiently and graciously listened to me on live
stream and I pray that you would right now, Holy Spirit, speak to us. Would you
speak to us about the grudge that is in our heart, the bitterness that we hold,
the anger that no one except those who are closest to us sense and hear? Would
you talk to us about the things that we think no other eyes see but our hearts
are even now convicting us about? We do them in the dark. But Father, they come
between you and us and we want to be well thought of and we we try to keep
the image and the appearance up, but in our hearts we know we're not where we
need to be. And Lord, we know that in our bearing fruit, not only souls, but in our
becoming Christ-like and bearing the fruit of the Spirit, we are not where we
once were. And Lord, if we're complacent and satisfied to stay there, we'll build
callous upon callous upon callous upon our hearts. And where once we could be
convicted and where once we had a tender heart, we'll become scoffers. We'll
kind of chuckle that, yeah, I used to get upset about that. And think we have grown,
think we've become more mature, when in truth we've just become hardened. And
there'll be a day when we need you. There'll be a day when we wish we had the
influence we once had, the relationship, the closeness. But we might well become
silly and think that it's somebody else's fault or think if we could just
add something from the world to our lives. That would be the answer. We just
need to go to a new church, one that thinks like we do. So Lord, if there's
going to be revival, it needs to start in hearts like ours, in weeks like this,
where we just give you the time to speak. And so I pray for every heart in living
rooms and dining rooms, wherever they are, Lord, would you touch their heart
right now and help them to get up out of that chair, perhaps kneel and make their
sofa, their altar. I don't care if their wife will have questions or their husband
will have questions, tell them the truth. Something between me and you. Nothing
between is what we sing. Do we mean it or is that a false appearance? Lord, I pray
that you would speak to our hearts about our changing appetite for that which is
good. And God, break our hearts about our changing acceptance of that which is
evil. Most of all, God, I pray that you would pierce our hard, calloused hearts.
What a privilege it is to have the Spirit of God care enough about us that
he would speak to us. So Lord, would you work in this preacher's heart? Everything
I said tonight can be true in my life. And would you change us? I pray in Jesus'
name, amen.