and I'm gonna read just a couple of verses of Scripture
here in the book of Ephesians,
and then we'll look at a number
of other portions of Scripture.
But here in the book of Ephesians,
really starting in chapter number five in verse number 22,
but if you're not careful,
if you start there just dealing with the family structure,
you miss a great key that God gives us,
and that key is provided in verse number 18
of the fifth chapter of the book of Ephesians.
The Bible says,
and be not drunk with wine wherein is excess,
but be filled with the Spirit.
If you're saved by the grace of God this evening,
the Holy Spirit of God dwells within you.
The Bible teaches us that at the moment of salvation,
we are indwelled by the Spirit of God.
He is the earnest of our inheritance,
and what a blessing to understand the truth of God's word
with regard to the indwelling of the Holy Spirit of God.
The reality is that at the moment of salvation,
the Holy Spirit of God indwelled us,
and we got all of the Holy Spirit that we ever will get.
The problem, however,
is that as we walk this journey called the Christian life,
there are times in which self gets too absorbed,
and we are filled with self
and not filled with the Spirit.
I cannot be filled with self
and filled with the Spirit at the same time.
I must be emptied of self.
I must be dead.
I die daily.
I am crucified with Christ.
I must die to self
and then be filled with the Spirit of God,
and we find here that the Apostle Paul
writing to the believers in Ephesus
before he starts dealing with, in verse 22,
the family structure,
he talks about the importance
of being filled with the Spirit.
In verse number 22, he begins with the wives.
Wives cannot be the wife
that God has given them the instruction to be
if they are not filled with the Spirit of God.
Husbands are addressed next,
and husbands cannot be the husbands
that God calls us to be
if we are not filled with the Spirit of God.
The Bible tells us husbands
that were to love our wives as Christ loved the church
and gave himself for it.
What love that God has given,
and then he gives the instruction
that husbands love their wives in like manner.
How convicting that is.
I can't do it in my own strength and my own power.
Neither can you.
We must be filled with the Spirit of God.
We come to the sixth chapter,
and you understand that the chapter divisions,
verse divisions are put there
for the ease of finding portions of scripture.
You find that as you come to the sixth chapter,
it now begins to address children.
The Bible says this in verse number one.
One of the first verses we ever taught our children
to memorize, by the way,
children, obey your parents in the Lord,
for this is right.
Why is it that we had our children memorize that verse
as one of the first verses that they ever memorized?
Because we wanted them to understand
that when they obeyed mommy and daddy,
they were obeying God, amen?
Because God said, children, obey your parents in the Lord,
for this is right.
Verse two, the Bible says, honor thy father and mother,
which is the first commandment with promise,
that it may be well with thee,
and that thou mayest live long on the earth.
These words, honor thy mother,
obviously within the context,
each time we read it, it says honor thy father and mother.
But as we think about this Mother's Day,
and we think about these words, honor thy mother,
these words can be found in both the Old Testament
and the New Testament.
We find that these words were first spoken by Moses.
God had given him the instruction, of course,
to speak to the children of Israel.
I'm reading through the Bible for a second time this year.
I finished up the book of Leviticus this morning,
and I was encouraged as I was reading the last part
of the book of Leviticus this morning,
and how often God speaks to Moses,
but then commands Moses, say to the children of Israel.
And you find that Moses was a faithful minister of the Lord.
Moses received the word that God gave,
and then Moses faithfully gave the word to the people
that he was called to lead.
He could not make them obey it,
he could not make them follow it,
but he did, he fulfilled his responsibility
in giving the message to the people
that he was called the minister to.
We find that God had given him the responsibility
of delivering this message of honor thy father,
honor thy mother.
We find that it's first given in the book of Exodus
during the 10 commandments in Exodus 20 in verse number 12.
Again, we find in the book of Deuteronomy,
now understanding the times of the Old Testament
and understanding the audience, if you will,
right after the Egyptian bondage,
the Exodus, as we read of in the book of Exodus,
obviously we understand that after that great deliverance,
God was moving and working and gave the 10 commandments.
And then there was a matter of disobedience
on the part of the children of Israel,
and they did not enter into the land
for fear of the inhabitants of the land.
They did not trust the Lord.
And so there were 40 years of wanderings,
and we find that after that generation died
that would not be permitted to enter in,
that now Moses is called to instruct the group of people
that would enter into the land.
And as you read the book of Deuteronomy,
you find that it's in that book
that now Moses is addressing this group of people
that would actually enter into the land of promise.
They would inherit that land, inhabit that land.
And we find that in Deuteronomy 5 in verse number 16,
this same truth is given once again.
So we find in Exodus 20, we find again in Deuteronomy 5,
and then we find in the gospel records,
if you were to read through the gospels,
that Jesus Christ himself, God in flesh,
he speaks these words, honor thy father and thy mother.
Now we find in the text that we're looking at this evening
in the book of Ephesians,
the apostle Paul writing to this church,
this church in Ephesus, this important instruction.
See, we sang tonight, oh Lord, send a revival
and let it begin in me.
Is that what the song said?
That's what the songwriter said.
And we find that there's definitely biblical truth to that
with regard to the individual.
And see, if our land,
if our church is ever gonna have revival,
it begins with individuals having revival.
And then we find that there's revival in the home.
And what a blessing to think about
this portion of scripture.
We're not studying through all of it,
beginning in chapter five, verse 18,
through chapter six, verse number three,
but we find that there's the possibility
to have revival in our homes.
We started last week in our new Sunday school class,
that marriage class that we started last week,
and we'd invite you to come.
We'll have our next week, our second lesson.
And we have the opportunity to examine the scriptures
and understand what God designed for the marriage.
And what a blessing to understand
that not only did God institute marriage,
but he gave instruction for marriage.
And I said this last week, that marriage is a journey.
It is a journey that is to be enjoyed, not simply endured.
Unfortunately, there are a lot of people today
that we know that you work with,
that maybe your family, you have family members,
you have friends that are enduring marriage,
not enjoying marriage.
We find this evening that there's the possibility
for revival in our home.
It requires that each individual be filled
with the spirit of God and follow the instruction
that God gives.
As we zero in this evening on this thought
of honor thy mother, I have just a few thoughts for you.
And really, I want the young people
to really pay attention this evening.
And obviously, the truth of God's word
is applicable for all of us.
But I especially want the young people
to be extremely attentive this evening.
And I hope it'll be a blessing and encouragement to you.
Number one, if you're taking notes,
it's a principle to obey.
We find that the Bible says honor thy father and mother.
And of course, with it being Mother's Day,
focusing on that particular aspect of honor thy mother.
We can read those words and we can understand
that the principle is a simple principle,
honor thy mother.
But if we're really serious about it,
we can say, okay, how do I do that?
I want to do that, but how?
Practically, how can I honor my mother?
Well, I'm glad that you've asked.
Turn to the book of Proverbs.
And I want to give you two practical tips.
Of course, we could give much more information this evening,
but I want to give you two practical tips
from the book of Proverbs.
Proverbs chapter number one,
I've taken a few verses of scripture
and just really boiled them down
into two thoughts this evening
with regard to these practical tips.
Proverbs chapter number one,
how can I obey this principle?
There's a principle that is given,
instruction, honor thy mother.
How can I obey that, practically speaking?
And if you want to take and consider these two thoughts,
the first one would be this, forsake not her instruction.
Forsake not her instruction.
You know, I'm thankful for the instruction
that mothers give.
I'll say this as I mentioned it this morning,
that not every statement that I'll make this evening,
just like not every statement that I made this morning
would be applicable to every circumstance or situation.
Obviously, there are some people that have mothers that are lost, and they do not follow
the precepts or the instruction of God's Word, and so on and so forth.
And so we understand that, but I'm speaking from a context of a biblical perspective.
And if you look in Proverbs 1 and verse number 8, notice what the Bible says, My son, hear
the instruction of thy father.
But then it says this, and forsake not the law of thy mother.
Many times, if you were to think of Old Testament times with regard to life and family life
as we study through the scriptures, and in fact, for many centuries of human civilization,
it was the case.
Obviously, we live in a different era today, but it was a typical situation where the husbands
and fathers would be out working while the mothers would be caring for the children in
the homestead, if you will, and providing that instruction and giving at the, at her
knees, even we mentioned that this morning, the instruction to her children.
We see here that the scriptures say, forsake not the law of thy mother.
Over in chapter 6, notice what the Bible says in Proverbs 6 and verse number 20, again,
it's the same command.
It's interesting that we read of this same thing in chapter 1, and we read it again in
chapter 6.
Do you think that the wise man, that God, ultimately as the author of this wonderful
book of Proverbs, he wants us to understand this truth?
It says, My son, keep thy father's commandment and forsake not the law of thy mother.
It goes on in verse 29, 21, and says, bind them continually upon thine heart and tie
them about thy neck.
When thou goest, it shall lead thee, when thou sleepest, it shall keep thee, and when
thou awakest, it shall talk with thee.
For the commandment is a lamp, and the law is light, and reproofs of instruction are
the way of life, to keep thee from the evil woman, from the flattery of the tongue of
a strange woman.
There are many that have given testimony with regard to how the prayers of their mother,
the instruction of their mother, how it influenced them, and even in various circumstances in
which they found themselves, it was as if they could hear their mother speaking the
words of instruction to them.
And it says here in the text of scripture, to forsake not.
How do I forsake not that instruction?
Well, it says in verse 21, to bind them continually upon thine heart and tie them about thy neck.
And we think about the imagery that is provided to us in verse 21, and no doubt when still
even today, there are some that would have understood during the time of the Lord Jesus
Christ that they would actually put scripture verses on their being, on their person, and
yet they would not even understand because Jesus would point to them and say, understand
us now, go find out what this means.
We find this evening that there's great imagery here, but the reality is that we must know
and receive that instruction.
Forsake not the instruction.
It's a great way to honor thy mother.
Think of this in the book of Proverbs, again, a number of verses of scripture, but the second
thought, a principle to obey with regard to practical tips on how to honor our mothers
would be to walk in wisdom.
The book of Proverbs is a book of wisdom.
In Proverbs 10, I want you to look at a number of verses here, three different verses we'll
look at with regard to this truth of walking in wisdom.
The Bible says this in Proverbs 10 and verse number 1, the Proverbs of Solomon.
Notice a wise son maketh a glad father, but then notice what the Bible says, a foolish
son is the heaviness of his mother.
We know we honor our mother by walking in wisdom.
It's a heaviness, the Bible says, a foolish son is the heaviness of his mother.
In chapter 15 and verse number 20, the Bible says this with regard to this truth of walking
in wisdom, a wise son maketh a glad father, but a foolish man, notice what it says, despiseth
his mother, a foolish son.
What does he do?
He despiseth his mother.
In chapter 23 of the book of Proverbs, we'll look at a few verses there.
We find that here in this text, the Bible tells us in verse number 23, Proverbs 23 and
verse 23, by the truth, sell it not, also wisdom and instruction and understanding.
The father of the righteous shall greatly rejoice, and he that begetteth a wise child
shall have joy of him.
Thy father and thy mother shall be glad, and she that bear thee shall rejoice.
You know, a mother rejoices as their children walk in wisdom.
A way in which a child can honor their mother is to walk in wisdom, to not forsake the instruction,
to walk in wisdom, to apply the principles in their lives, to honor their mother.
We see that there's a principle to obey, but there's also a promise to receive.
If you note the truth back in Ephesians chapter 6 and verse number 2, the Bible tells us to
honor thy father and mother, but then there's that parenthetical statement where the Bible
says which is the first commandment with promise.
If you were to go back to Exodus 20 and again to Deuteronomy 5, you'll find exactly what
the Apostle Paul says here in verse number 3 with regard to the promise to receive.
When we honor our father and mother, when we honor our parents, notice this promise
that is given, a two-fold promise that says, number one, in verse number 3, that it may
be well with thee.
Then it says this, and that thou mayest live long on the earth.
The first commandment with promise, in Exodus chapter 20 and verse number 12, when Moses
gives the first reference of this command, this instruction, it says that thy days may
be long upon the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.
In Deuteronomy 5 it says that thy days may be prolonged and that it may go well with
thee.
You know, the reality is that God, as we as children, as you look here at this, children
obey your parents and the Lord for this is right, honor thy father and mother, which
is the first commandment with promise, that as children obey and honor their parents,
they're obeying and honoring the Lord, and the Lord blesses that.
The Lord blesses obedience, it's a principle that we find throughout the whole of Scripture.
As we walk in obedience, God blesses.
And he says that it may be well with thee and thou mayest live long on the earth.
What great promises.
You think about the way that God references this, the first commandment with promise,
the promise that is directly attached to the commandment.
What we do with the commandment depends on, or what we do with the commandment dictates
the promise that is received.
And so we find that here, even in Ephesians chapter number six, Paul reiterates this biblical
truth from the Old Testament.
As we think about the simple thoughts of these verses of Scripture, it's important this evening
that we not simply deal with a principle and a promise, but number three this evening,
and finally, I want you to see that there's a warning to heed.
A warning to heed.
Turn to the book of Proverbs, if you will, in the 30th chapter, and I want you to see
what the Bible tells us.
In Proverbs chapter 30, verses 11 through 14, God says there is a generation.
Each verse starts that way.
And I want you to see what God tells us.
We're going to read the entirety, all four of those verses, and then focus in on verse
number 11 with regard to our subject this evening.
In verse number 11, the Bible says there's a generation that curseth their father and
doth not bless their mother.
There's a generation that are pure in their own eyes and yet is not washed from their
filthiness.
There is a generation, oh, how lofty are their eyes and their eyelids are lifted up.
There is a generation whose teeth are as swords and their jaw teeth as knives to devour the
poor from off the earth and the needy from among men.
As we look at verse number 11, the Bible says there's a generation that curseth their father
and doth not bless their mother.
No doubt throughout human history there have been many a people, individuals, that have
been guilty of cursing their father and not blessing their mother, of disobeying the command
that's been given with promise to honor thy father and mother.
There's been a number of folks.
We can read even in the Old Testament in the Pentateuch of those that disobeyed and
they suffered greatly for it.
I mean, they were put to death for their disobedience.
We find as we look at the generation in which we're living and the society in which we're
living, it seems to be more and more commonplace for children to disobey, for children to curse
their father and refuse to bless or to honor their mother.
You see it all around us.
I made this statement last Sunday morning in our Sunday school class.
You see all of these things that are going on on campuses around the United States of
America, which is absolutely just ridiculous what's going on in our college campuses today.
But all of those 20-something-year-olds that are up there doing all that they're doing,
you know what, they were the four-year-olds that were standing in Walmart stomping their
feet, throwing a fit, and getting their way.
Now they're 20-something-year-olds and they think that that's still how they're to behave.
No one's told them otherwise.
No one's holding them accountable.
It's a problem.
We find that we live in a time in which people, unfortunately, and obviously, again, it's
not everyone.
I'm thankful that there are those that are honoring their fathers and their mothers that
are living in obedience.
But we find that there is a generation, listen, I understand what it is.
There comes a time in the life, and I think it's more prominent with boys and young men,
we get to that place of being 16 or 17 years old and we think we just know everything.
We got it all figured out and we're smarter than our parents and so on and so forth.
And when we're 15, 16, 17 years old, we think mom and dad don't know anything about what
they're talking about and what have you.
And then when we're in our 20s, we kind of have that idea, well, maybe mom and dad weren't
as dumb as I thought they were.
And then when we're 30 or 40, we're like, you know what?
Mom and dad had a lot of wisdom.
They really knew what they were talking about.
Did any of you go through that cycle when you were 15, 16, 17?
Ron's like, no way, I never went through that, yeah.
Amen, right?
And listen, it's something we go through, and I'm not sure what's wrong with us, but
it happens.
But there's a warning that God gives us.
Notice in chapter 20 of the book of Proverbs, those that would refuse to honor father and
mother.
Remember, it's the promise, the first commandment with promise.
It's the promise of thy days being long, that it may be well with thee.
We find in Proverbs chapter 20, notice what the Bible says in verse number 20, whoso curseth
his father or his mother, notice what the Bible says, his lamp shall be put out in obscure
darkness.
That's a scary verse.
Amen?
Whoso curseth his father or his mother.
What is the principle tonight from Ephesians 6 that we find first in Exodus that is repeated
by Jesus?
We find that it's honor thy father and thy mother, but we find that here the Bible says
there's a generation that curseth their father and doth not bless their mother.
And it says of the one whoso curseth his father or his mother, his lamp shall be put out in
obscure darkness.
Notice chapter 30, I know we kind of bounce back and forth, but go back to chapter 30
just after we read of those statements of the generations.
I want you to look at verse number 17.
Proverbs 30 and verse number 17, the Bible says, the eye that mocketh at his father and
despiseth to obey his mother, the ravens of the valley shall pick it out and the young
eagles shall eat it.
That's pretty serious imagery, is it not?
I mean, it's pretty straight to the point.
There's a man by the name of Jerry Ross, he wrote some books and ministered amongst
teenagers for quite some time, and it said, I heard the story firsthand, I was not there
to see it happen, but I'm told that Jerry Ross was preaching at a teen camp type of
a summer camp setting, and he was preaching, he was preaching from this passage of scripture
in Proverbs chapter 30.
And he'd just finished up preaching and he ended with verse number 17 about the eye that
mocketh at his father and despiseth to obey his mother, the ravens of the valley shall
pick it out and the young eagles shall eat it.
And the story, as it was conveyed to me, after he'd completed the message and after they
had a time of invitation, they dispersed to go and do various activities that they were
going to do, and just within a few moments they heard some screeching cries and hollers
from up the road, and one of the young people that sat in that auditorium and listened to
that message that was despising and cursing their parents literally was attacked by birds
just moments after preaching this message, and the birds were attacking and plucking
at the face.
And it was told to me personally that that took place, now that's, I think about the
other couple hundred teenagers that were there, man, I'd get right in line, amen, I mean seriously.
But the reality is that when we read the warnings that God gives in His Word, it shouldn't
be that we have to experience something, that we have to see someone else experience something,
it should be that we simply accept what God has said as being truth and saying, look,
I don't want to be in that position, I don't want to have my candle be put out in obscure
darkness, no, I'd rather that this commandment that was given, which is the first with promise,
that I would honor my father and my mother.
How do we do it practically?
We must not forsake the instruction, we must walk in wisdom.
This evening I'm thankful, my mom, of course she's watching this evening online, they don't
have evening service there and she's watching, and my mom wasn't saved when I was real little,
she saved me when I was a teenager, but I'm thankful for the opportunity in those teenage
years and even still today to know that she prays for and she wants to give that godly
advice and counsel.
I think about Holly and obviously the opportunity that she's had as my wife and mother of our
children to be able to teach our children biblical instruction and provide them with
truth.
And listen, sometimes children, if you're not careful, you think you know more than
you really do, you think you're wiser than you really are, and God says honor, honor
thy mother.
Don't have those consequences that we see here with the warning that is given, no, determine
I'm going to obey.
I'm thankful that God has given us this instruction as we think about revival this evening and
revival in our homes.
It's not just mom and dad that need to be walking in the Spirit and filled with the
Spirit of God, it's the children too, children that need to be filled with the Spirit of
God and walking in wisdom, walking in the light.
So often today we have where families are turned upside down, what do I mean by that?
Well the children are running the show, you see it, you see it all the time.
Where the parents aren't really the parents, it's the children that are calling all the
shots, the children are manipulative through their actions and their behavior and what
they do and they stomp their feet and they say what they say and they're going to throw
their fit until they're, well if you don't stop I'm going to do this, how many times
you hear somebody say that and they never follow through?
Maybe it ought not be that children are running the show, mom and dad are the responsible
parties in order to raise and to bring up their children in the nurture and admonition
of the Lord, but children do have a great responsibility.
This evening maybe you need to thank God for your mom, maybe you need to tell her how thankful
you are for her, maybe there's some areas in your life where you've not honored your
mom, maybe some of the young people, I know we don't have a lot of young people here this
evening but maybe there's some that God would be just speaking to you tonight and saying
hey, how are you doing with this area?
Take heed to the principle that God gives, take heed to the warning that God has provided,
honor thy mother.
Let's pray together.
Father we love you, we thank you for loving us, thank you for your word, we thank you
for the opportunity to be here this evening and for the opportunity to sing wonderful
songs, hymns, to be challenged and comforted and Lord we thank you for your word and we
thank you for this commandment with promise, the first commandment with promise and God
I pray that you'd help, especially our young people this evening, Lord they would honor
their parents, they would walk in wisdom and obedience Lord that they would obey, Lord
that they would be used of thee, I pray that you'd help parents to fulfill their God-given
responsibility.
Lord I pray that we'd have homes that are honoring to thee, Lord that we'd see revival
in our homes that would lead to revival in our church, that would lead to revival in
our nation.
I pray that you'd move and work, God if there's one that's been disobedient, disrespectful,
not following the principles that you've given forth in your word, I pray tonight that they
would take heed to the warning.
I pray God that you'd work in their heart and draw them back to yourself, help them
Lord to correct their behavior, to be aligned with the principles of your word.
Well thank you for the work that you'll do, for it's in Christ's name we pray.