39 tonight, Genesis chapter 39, and last Sunday evening we started looking at
this portion of Scripture
and we only made it through the first six verses and so this evening we'll
look at verses 7 through 19
here in the 39th chapter of the book of Genesis
and let me just remind you very quickly as we began studying this portion of
Scripture last week
and we noted the fact that the Bible tells us that the Lord was with
In verse number 2 of Genesis 39, the Bible says the Lord was with Joseph
again in verse number 3
of our text of Scripture, the Bible says that his master, that's Potiphar,
he saw that the Lord was with him. If you skip down to verse number 21, the
Bible says again
after he, Joseph, was accused and then imprisoned
the Bible tells us in verse number 21, but the Lord was with Joseph
and showed him mercy and gave him favor in the sight of the keeper of the prison
and then notice in verse 23, the fourth time in this chapter where the Bible
says
the keeper of the prison looked not to anything that was under his hand because
the Lord was with him and that which he did the Lord made
it to prosper. I'm thankful for the testimony of Joseph
I'm thankful for a man that though he was sold into slavery, his brothers
despised him, were going to kill him and then sold him into slavery
We understand as we begin reading even at the end of the 37th chapter and then the
beginning of the 39th chapter of the book of Genesis
that he's purchased by one named Potiphar who was an officer of Pharaoh
captain of the guard and we find as we studied last week in the first six
verses of our text of Scripture that Joseph
we saw him as Joseph the overseer
and we had the opportunity to be able to study through this portion of Scripture
to be able to understand how God's hand of blessing
was upon Joseph and we understand that that was a direct result
of Joseph's behavior of him living a life that was pleasing
to the Lord. This evening as we pick it up in verse number seven notice the
Bible says this and it came to pass
after these things. Now remember there was a period of time we mentioned
with regard to how long Joseph was there in the house of Potiphar he served
faithfully
it was at least 10 years that he was there serving
if you look at the details of dates with regard to events that take place here in
the book of Genesis
and we find that after these things when everything in the house of Potiphar was
left into the hands of Joseph
remember the Bible said at the end of verse number five that the blessing of the Lord was
upon all that he had in the house and the field
in verse number six says and he Potiphar left all that he had in Joseph's hand
and he knew not all he had save the bread which he did eat
and Joseph was a goodly person and well favored and it came to pass after these
things verse number seven
that his master's wife cast her eyes upon Joseph
and she said lie with me
but thank God for these words in verse number eight
he refused. The Bible says
and said unto his master's wife behold my master wanteth not what is with me in
the house
and he hath committed all that he hath to my hand
there is none greater in this house than I
neither hath he kept back anything from me
but thee because thou art his wife
notice this statement how then can I do this great wickedness
and sin against
God. It came to pass in verse 10 as she spake to Joseph notice
day by day that he hearken not unto her to lie by her
or to be with her. It came to pass about this time that Joseph
went into the house to do his business and there was none of the men of the
house
there within and she caught him by his garment
saying lie with me and he left his garment
in her hand and fled and got
him out. We will make note with regard to the text down through verse number 19
but this evening
we see part number two the Lord was with Joseph the
particular aspect that we're gonna deal with from this passage this evening last
week we saw Joseph
the overseer tonight we see Joseph
the accused. Joseph the accused
what I'm thankful for as I look at this passage of scripture several things that
are
of great importance and significance to us as Bible believers
and understanding the impact of this account
in our lives and how it helps us but as we look at the entirety of Genesis
chapter 39
next week we'll have a missionary but the following Sunday I'll deal with the
final part of this passage of scripture
and we'll deal with Joseph the prisoner and as we
kinda look at the entirety of the chapter we look at Joseph the overseer
Joseph the accused and Joseph the prisoner
what we learn and what we find out is that God is with him
in each of those times of his life and that brings great encouragement to me as
a child of God
because there are times in which circumstances will take place in your
life and in my life
that are maybe beyond what we would think is our human control
but yet God promises that he'll be with us
as we look at this particular portion of scripture in dealing with the fact that
Joseph
the accused we see in verse number 7 and 10
where the temptation is recorded the Bible tells us that she says in verse
number 7
lie with me this is the initial temptation
that takes place and we find that the Bible tells us that he refused
but I want you to see that in verse number 10 the Bible tells us
that it came to pass as she spake to Joseph day
by day there was an initial temptation and then there was continued
temptation
and we find that in verse number 12 the final record of this temptation where
she sees
and decides that she's going to seize the moment
that there's no one else in the house in this final temptation comes when she
catches him by the garment
and she says lie with me we begin to think about the temptation in looking at
this particular
text of scripture and what's given to us and we understand that as human beings
we too will be tempted as we
live this life and the reality this evening as we think about the Lord Jesus
Christ the Bible tells us in the book of Matthew and again in the book of Luke
that he was led in the wilderness by the spirit he was tempted
of the devil and we find that that temptation came
to the Lord Jesus Christ and temptation will come in your life it will come in
my life it comes in Joseph's life
and we see the record of this temptation it's interesting
as you look at Luke's gospel account the Bible speaks about the devil leaving
for a season and that's quite interesting to me because
oftentimes when we face temptation in our lives you may face temptation today
and you may have victory today but you can rest assured that the enemy is gonna
come again tomorrow
and he's gonna come next week and he's gonna come the week after that
and we find that in certain aspects of our life as we've experienced the
Christian journey
the enemy just tries to beat us
down he tries to find that weak moment that time of being vulnerable
if you will and we find that it's so vitally important that we understand
this evening the importance of walking
in the spirit why because God tells us in the book of Galatians
that if we walk in the spirit we will not fulfill the lust
of the flesh something that is true for each and every one of us this evening is
that even
if we are born again if we've trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as our Savior we
still have
the flesh we still have the old man
and those tendencies of the old man those
the fleshly desires and that's why the Bible teaches us in the book of
Ephesians and again in the book of Colossians that we're to put off
and then put on and what a great principle that God teaches us
but we see the temptation recorded many of us would be familiar with the truth
the first Corinthians 10
in verse number 13 turn over there with me and look at this portion of scripture
again you might be able to memorize it but I wanna have us read it this evening
and gather tonight from this portion of scripture
as we look at the life of Joseph but then also make application for
our own lives notice what Paul says to the believers in Corinth under the
inspiration the Holy Spirit of God
with regard to this truth of being tempted and first Corinthians 10 in
verse 13 notice what the Bible says
there hath no temptation taken you
but such as is common to man
but I want you to notice those next statement those next words the Bible
says but God
is faithful aren't you thankful that we serve a God who is faithful
and we sang last week we made mention on Wednesday evening about being thankful
for God's faithfulness
but notice specifically within the context
what Paul highlights with regard to the faithfulness of God
within the subject matter of this temptation
that you will face that I will face the Bible says that God is faithful
who will not suffer you allow you
to be tempted above that you are
able but notice this but will with the temptation
also make a way to escape
that you may be able to bear it I've written in the margin of my Bible
two things next to the word
to this verse of scripture, number one, God is faithful.
Number two, look for the escape route.
Look for the escape route.
Because the Bible tells us that God with the temptation
also he will make a way to escape.
You know what happens sometimes is unfortunately,
mankind is not looking for the escape route.
In fact, there's too often that mankind is looking
to satisfy the desires of the flesh.
And we find this evening that as we look at Genesis 39
and we look at Joseph the accused,
and we see the temptation recorded,
he was a man that though 1 Corinthians 10, 13
was not written as we have it in the Bible today,
we understand that the principle forever,
O Lord, thy word is settled in heaven.
And Joseph was a man that lived and understood.
Listen, there was an escape route and he got out.
He refused and he got out and what a blessing.
Notice, as we think about the temptation being recorded,
we look at the response of Joseph.
And it's given to us in three aspects as we look here
in verse number eight, the Bible says that he refused.
Now I'm thankful for his refusal.
I'm thankful that he initially as this temptation comes
and it unfolds in this period of time
in which Joseph has served in the house of Potiphar.
And the Bible simply states he refused.
Praise God for that.
And I'm thankful that he recognized the position
that he had, but more than recognizing the position
that he had, more than recognizing what Potiphar
had entrusted him with, because he mentions those things.
Look in verse number eight, he says,
behold, my master wanteth not what is with me in the house.
And he had committed all that he hath to my hand.
He understood that his master Potiphar had entrusted him.
He was Joseph the overseer.
He was the man that had all of this power and this control,
but he also says there is none greater in this house
than I in verse number nine.
Neither hath he kept back anything from me, but thee.
Why?
Because thou art his wife.
And so Joseph understood, he recognized as he refused
the request of Potiphar's wife to lie with me,
he recognized the fact that his master had entrusted him
with this great power.
He recognized his position within the home,
but I want you to understand that those weren't
the most important things that he recognized.
Those are recorded for us, and it's important
that we understand, listen, there are some places
in some circumstances in life where maybe a position
that an individual holds will keep them
from committing some particular act of sin.
Why?
Because it would look really bad for that position.
I understand we're living in a time where it seems
as if it's not that bad anymore, and people just kind of,
well, everyone's doing it, and so on and so forth,
but there was a time in our nation's history
where there was some level of respect
with particular offices that people would not,
because of an office, commit certain things.
But I want you to understand this evening
that just because you recognize an office,
a position that you have, is not the greatest thing.
The greatest thing is what he says
at the end of verse number nine.
Notice the statement, how then can I do
this great wickedness, and notice what he says,
and sin against God.
You know what Joseph understood?
He realized the awfulness of sin.
He understood as he was being tempted and he refused,
and he gives this response as it's recorded
in verses eight and nine.
He says, how then can I do this great wickedness
and sin against God?
I wonder this evening how mindful we are
when we commit some act of sin,
of recognizing that it's a sin against God.
Sometimes if we're not careful,
we can kind of sugarcoat our sin,
we can kind of call it, we want to use terminologies
that are not too offensive because we want to make sure
we still feel good about ourselves,
but the reality is that sin is awful,
it's wicked, and it's against God.
And here this evening, as we look at the statement of Joseph
I am just looking at where this is with regard
to the dialogue within the book of Genesis,
and thinking about the contrast between Joseph
here in Genesis 39 and Judah in Genesis chapter 38.
Now remember, we studied a few weeks ago
in Genesis chapter number 38, the wickedness of Judah,
and we talked about his private and his public wickedness
and all that was going on and that God knows about,
but Judah was in a position where he thought
that he could kind of get away with this sin.
Judah kind of thought that he was in a position
where he could make decisions and he could have
that pleasure of sin for a season, if you will,
and that no one's really gonna find out.
But Joseph, on the other hand, says how can I do
this great wickedness and sin against God?
This evening I believe that what we really need
in our churches and our nation is understanding
this truth of the awfulness of sin.
And sin is deceitful.
The Bible talks about in the book of Hebrews
the deceitfulness of sin.
And we find here this evening that Joseph refuses,
he realized the awfulness of sin.
And I want you to look at Hebrews 13, if you will.
Again, hold your place there in Genesis,
we'll be right back, but look over in the book of Hebrews,
if you will, in the 13th chapter.
And I want you to see again, as we have the privilege
of having the whole canon of scripture
and we can look at and we can see the truth
of what God has given us and we can see it illustrated
even here in the life of Joseph,
a man that is living a life that is pleasing
and honoring to the Lord.
In Hebrews chapter 13, so often we'll quote verse five
in verse number six, but I remind you that the Bible says
in verse number four of Hebrews 13,
marriage is honorable in all and the bed undefiled.
But the Bible says that whoremongers and adulterers,
God will judge.
That word that's translated in our King James Bible,
whoremongers is a word that's also translated
in other portions of scripture, a fornicator.
And so we see that here in Hebrews 13 in verse number four,
the truth of fornication and adultery are both exposed
as being evil, wicked, that God will judge.
You know what's sad today?
Fornication and adultery has just become commonplace
in our nation.
Sad.
No doubt if we were to take a survey this evening
of asking this simple question,
do you know someone that has been engaged
in the sin of fornication or adultery?
I would say the majority of us would say,
I know someone that's been involved in that sin.
That's sad.
You know what's even worse?
It's become commonplace in God's house.
And you say, how could that be?
Because we've forgotten to recognize the awfulness of sin.
We've given our place, we've dealt with
and we've begin to be influenced by a culture,
by a society that says, hey, do what you want,
live how you want and do what makes you happy
and so on and so forth.
And listen, that's a lie from the pit of hell.
This evening, we see that Joseph,
he refused why he recognized,
he realized the awfulness of sin,
but then I want you to see that he ran.
The Bible says that it came to pass in verse number 10
that she spake to Joseph day by day
and he hearkened not to her, to lie by her, to be with her.
They came to pass about this time
that Joseph went into the house in verse 11
to do his business.
There was none of the men of the house there within.
She seizes the opportunity,
says that she caught him by his garment.
She says, lie with me.
And notice what the Bible says,
that he left his garment in her hand and fled
and got him out.
I'm thankful for Joseph's response in running.
Some have noted that he lost his coat,
but he retained his character.
And that coat that he lost in verse number 12
would cause him some difficulty in the next several verses
with regard to the accusation
that is brought against Joseph by the wife of Potiphar.
But I want you to see that it was far better
for him to lose a coat than to lose his character.
And we find that the Bible says that he fled.
God tells us, Paul writes to Timothy
both in the first and second letters
that he writes to Timothy in 1 Timothy chapter six.
And in 2 Timothy chapter number two,
he speaks about fleeing, fleeing youthful lust,
fleeing fornication.
Sometimes we've just got to,
like the Patch the Pirate song says,
put on your running shoes, amen.
And some of you little kids,
you know that Patch song, put on your running shoes,
get out, why?
Because God is faithful to provide a way to escape.
1 Corinthians.
10, 13.
And sometimes the way to escape
is that you gotta put on your running shoes
and you gotta flee.
The Bible says that he fled and got him out.
Praise the Lord.
For a man that facing this continued temptation
that came day by day and day by day,
that he continued to have that spiritual strength
to refuse and to stand for what was right
and to recognize the awfulness of sin.
The Bible tells us as we would again,
contrast his behavior even with others
within the pages of Scripture.
I'm reminded this evening of King David,
a man that the Bible says is a man after God's own heart.
A man who when he was to be in battle,
carried in Jerusalem a man that observed Bathsheba
washing herself, bathing herself.
And he says, get her for me.
The servant of David says, is not this Bathsheba?
Notice the Bible says the wife of Uriah, the Hittite.
She's a married woman, David.
You know what that was?
That was God faithful.
Putting up a bright sign of no, David, stop.
And David refused and said, get her, bring her to me.
Listen, each of us are gonna face temptation in our lives.
You may have faced temptation already today.
You're gonna face temptation tomorrow.
There's something that comes to your mind
as we're looking at this portion of Scripture.
I don't know what the temptation is.
You know how cunning the enemy is?
Is that the temptation in your life
is gonna be different than the temptation in the life
of somebody a couple of rows from you
and different than mine and so on and so forth, why?
Because the Bible gives us as we look at the truth
of who our God is, but also how our enemy works,
that he's crafty and he's cunning.
And the Bible tells us, look,
he's going to tempt you in areas
where you're most vulnerable.
We can think about using the terminology
where somebody will, maybe they're trying to eat
a little bit more healthy and they'll say,
oh, that doesn't even tempt me
because it's not really the kind of dessert
that they really like.
You've ever heard somebody use that kind of phraseology?
And then all of a sudden,
you bring their favorite dessert into the room
and all of a sudden they're tempted, right?
And the fact of the matter is that the dessert
that tempts you might not be the dessert
that tempts me and vice versa.
But with sin, it works the same way.
You have certain weaknesses and it's those weaknesses
where you have that the enemy is going to try
to exploit those and that temptation is going to come.
That's why it's so vitally important
that we be strong in the Lord and the power of his might.
Put on the whole armor of God.
Why?
Because those fiery darts are gonna come
and we'll be able to quench all the fiery darts
of the wicked.
And we find here this evening that he becomes the accused
because of his behavior, because of his refusal.
It says in verse 13, and it came to pass
when she, Potiphar's wife, saw that he had left his garment
in her hand and was fled forth that she called
unto the men of the house and spake unto them saying,
see, he, speaking of Potiphar, hath brought in in Hebrew,
speaking of Joseph unto us to mock us.
He came in unto me to lie with me
and I cried with a loud voice.
Now, is she telling the truth?
She could not be further from the truth.
That's what she says.
You know, sometimes people are gonna lie about you.
And there's nothing you can do about it.
You know what happens sometimes when people lie about us
and we don't want to defend ourselves.
And I understand that.
But you know, Joseph was in a position
where he wasn't able to defend himself.
The Bible says that she gives this story,
this lie to the men that came in after she cries.
It says in verse 15, it came to pass when he heard
that I lifted up my voice and cried
that he left his garment with me and fled and got him out.
And she laid up his garment by her until his Lord came home.
That's Potiphar and she spake unto him
according to these words saying,
the Hebrew servant which thou hast brought unto us
came in unto me to mock me.
Now, if you're the husband,
how do you feel when you hear that?
Yeah, you're enraged?
Yeah, angry?
Guess what?
Potiphar has some power.
The Bible tells us that he's an officer of Pharaoh.
He's captain of the guard.
The Bible tells us that he hears this,
which she says in verse 17,
it says that she spake unto him according to these words
saying, the Hebrew servant which thou hast brought unto us
came in unto me to mock me.
And it came to pass as I lifted up my voice and cried
that he left his garment with me and fled out.
And it came to pass when his master heard the words
of his wife, which she spake unto him saying,
after this manner did thy servant to me
that his wrath was kindled.
And what does he do?
Verse 20, and Joseph's master took him
and put him into the prison,
a place where the king's prisoners were bound.
And he was there in the prison.
Now, as we look at this portion of scripture
and we see what's taking place and Joseph the accused,
we learn some very valuable lessons about temptation
that you will face, that I will face
and how we need to respond to that temptation
because the temptation is gonna come.
And it comes in a variety of forms.
There are times you can do a simple internet search
for something extremely innocent that you're looking for.
And all of a sudden things come up on your screen.
Has it happened to you?
Sure it has.
What is going on?
What do you do?
How do you respond?
What kind of controls do we have in place?
See, sometimes we talk about the importance
and I think we should talk about the importance
of having controls in place for young people
and what have you, but understand temptations don't stop
when you turn 18, they don't stop when you turn 30 or 40
or 50, they continue to come.
And it's important that we're accountable
and that we live a life that is pleasing the Lord
and we learn how to respond to the temptation
that we always are looking for the escape route.
And here in this passage of scripture,
Joseph is falsely accused and he ends up in prison.
But I would submit to you and it will be a continuation
to next week as we've looked at this chapter now
in this three part series, I would submit to you
that God is at work in Joseph's life.
God's at work.
There are times in your life and in my life
that there are some circumstances that come in our life
we say, I didn't do anything wrong.
Joseph didn't do anything wrong.
He is faithful.
He responded exactly, I mean, if you want a case study
on exactly how to respond to temptation,
this is your chapter.
Outside of the Lord Jesus Christ, this is your chapter.
And he ends up in prison.
But God was at work.
God was at work.
You know why?
It's through Joseph being in a prison
after being falsely accused that God will bring Joseph
into contact with the butler and the baker
and God's plan will continue to unfold
in the life of Joseph.
And here's the thing, many of us this evening
have read the entire book of Genesis.
Many of us this evening, we know what happens
in the life of Joseph.
But at this moment in Joseph's life,
he knew that he was falsely accused.
He knew he did nothing wrong and he ends up in prison.
But he continues to serve God.
He continues to be faithful.
And the Bible tells us that when he's in prison,
the Lord is with him.
This evening, it's far better,
Peter talks about it, when we suffer for righteousness,
when we, listen, if we do wrong and we suffer for it,
that's on you.
But blessed are you, happy are ye
when we suffer for righteousness.
This evening, it's far better to retain your character
and your integrity and live a life that's pleasing
and honoring to the Lord.
That accusation comes, the temptation came,
but Joseph, he's got a testimony that stands
that we look to in the word of God
and we say, look at this man of God.
Look at an example of someone that dealt with temptation
properly biblically and then see what God did in his life.
This evening, Joseph the accused,
listen, you're gonna face temptation.
Sometimes you do the right thing.
You refuse it.
You recognize the evil wickedness of it.
You run and maybe you'll be falsely accused,
but before God, you can retain your integrity,
your character, and we can thank God
that God, he keeps a good record book.
He knows, and it'd be far better
to be able to stand before him knowing
that we can stand with our integrity and innocency,
that we have looked for that escape route.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
Thank You for loving us. Thank You for Your Word. Thank You for the truth of Your Word.
I pray that this evening as we consider the temptation of Joseph and the accusation that's
brought against him, Lord, I pray that You'd help us in our lives. No doubt, each and every
one of us, we face temptation. God, I pray You'd help us to recognize that You're faithful.
God, that You'd help us to look for that escape route. God, thank You that You're a God of
grace and mercy, forgiveness. We sang grace that's greater than all of our sin. Maybe
there's some that have failed in this area. They've given in to the temptation. They've
committed the sin. God, I pray that tonight they would confess it, find forgiveness with
Thee. Lord, that they'd have restored fellowship with Thee. Why? Because You're a God who's
ready to pardon, ready to forgive. We have an advocate with the Father, the Lord Jesus
Christ. Lord, I pray You'd help each of us, Lord, to walk, live in such a way that we
would please Thee. We'll thank You for what You'll do. For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?