chapter number 15 this morning and I'll be looking at the last portion of this
wonderful passage of Scripture be looking at verses 51 through 58 1st
Corinthians 15 verses 51 through 58 I'm so thankful for the Word of God and
God's Word has changed my life and I know that many of you would testify this
day that God's Word has had a profound impact in your life as well and I'm so
thankful for the truth contained therein I'm thankful that as I go to the Word of
God that God will use his Word to comfort me he'll use his Word to
convict me and he has no doubt changed me through the truth that is revealed
to us in his precious book the Bible 1st Corinthians 15 looking at verses 51
through 58 the Bible says this behold I show you a mystery we shall not all
sleep but we shall all be changed in a moment in the twinkling of an eye at the
last trump for the trumpet shall sound and the dead shall be raised incorruptible
and we shall be changed for this corruptible must put on incorruption and
this mortal must put on immortality so in this corruptible shall have put on
incorruption and this mortal shall have put on immortality then shall be brought
to pass the saying that is written death is swallowed up in victory Oh
death where is thy sting Oh grave where is thy victory the sting of death is sin
the strength of sin is the law but thanks be to God which giveth us the
victory through our Lord Jesus Christ therefore my beloved brethren be
steadfast unmovable always abounding in the work of the Lord for as much as you
know that your labor is not in vain in the Lord I want to draw your attention
to the last phrase of verse number 53 we'll use this for our title this
morning and the last phrase this mortal shall put on immortality if you're
taking notes simply that phrase this mortal shall put or must put on
immortality as we think about first Corinthians 15 we know that this
chapter is known as the resurrection chapter in the Bible in fact as we
consider the truth of the resurrection of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ we
would say this morning that the resurrection of Jesus Christ is the
cornerstone of our faith we understand this morning that as the people of God
that we ought to rejoice greatly in this Bible reality that Jesus Christ conquered
sin death in the grave and rose in victory we had the opportunity this
morning to sing some songs about the incarnation the birth of our Lord and
Savior Jesus Christ and we understand that he was born to die that he came to
this earth with a purpose with a mission if you will and that was to go to the
cross of Calvary to pay for the sin of mankind and he fulfilled that which his
purpose was and he went to that cruel cross and he bled and he died he was
borrowed buried in that borrowed tomb but he rose in victory and as we look at
first Corinthians 15 we find that not only should it cause us to rejoice but
it gives us hope we find that Paul systematically in this passage of
Scripture teaches the believers in Corinth the truth regarding the
resurrection and then I believe that as we look at the section that we'll be
focusing on this morning he challenges these believers to live for the Lord in
the present we find that the Bible tells us in verse number 20 but now is Christ
risen from the dead notice and become the firstfruits of them that slept in
verse 22 the Bible says first in Adam all die even so in Christ shall all be
made alive and we find that it causes us to rejoice it gives us hope and
expectation if you will and what joy that should bring to the heart of every
believer as we really fix our attention upon the reality of what God gives us in
this wonderful chapter and really we find that it's throughout the scriptures
but here in one chapter the evidence that is just systematically given with
regard to the the event as it's given with the resurrection and the impact of
that truth on the believers if you're taking notes this morning I just have
two points for you but that doesn't mean that the service will be any shorter and
sometimes you can have 10 points and it's a kind of a concise thing and
sometimes you can have two points and it's just as long as if you had 10 but
if you are taking notes number one this morning the certainty of the promise the
certainty of the promise notice with me in verses 51 through 57 I've read it
already but I want you to take note of some of the verbage that is used some of
the words that God uses in this passage of scripture that reminds us of the
certainty of this promise notice in verse number 51 the Bible says behold I
show you a mystery notice we shall not all sleep but notice what it says but we
shall all be changed I like that shall that's a good Bible word it's not a
think it meant many of us it might happen it could happen no this is a
certainty we shall all be changed notice it says we shall not all sleep in other
words what he's referring to is that not every believer will die prior to the
rapture of the church as we compare scripture with scripture and we
understand the truth the first Thessalonians chapter number four the
Bible says but they which are alive and remain shall be caught up together with
them in the clouds to meet the Lord in the air and we understand that the we're
not going to prevent them go before those that had died in Christ and here
as Paul is giving the truth of the believers in Corinth he says we shall
not all sleep not every single believer will die a physical death prior to the
rapture of the church but know with certainty be assured of this we shall
all be changed he says in verse number 52 as we think about the certainty of
the promise it says in a moment and the twinkling of an eye at the last Trump Oh
how we eagerly await the trumpet of the Lord the Bible says for the trumpet shall
sound this isn't a hope so kind of an idea of this is just a Christianity a
Christian doctrine that gives some people some kind of excitement no no this
is a Bible reality a truth of the Word of God that the trumpet shall sound the
Bible says and the dead shall be raised incorruptible and we shall be changed
as you notice how many times in verse number 52 the Bible says shall again the
certainty of this event and the certainty of this promise the Bible says
in verse number 53 he now begins to use this word must for this corruptible must
put on incorruption and this mortal must put on immortality we've used that as our
title this mortal must put on immortality it is it is going to happen
it must happen and as we look in verse number 54 it continues so when this
corruptible shall have put on incorruption and this mortal shall have
put on immortality then shall be brought to pass the saying that is written death
is swallowed up in victory now notice with me in verses 51 through 53 he's
giving us the certainty of the promise and he's speaking about this event
that's going to happen in a moment and the twinkling of an eye at the last
trump but the trumpet shall sound and the dead shall be raised incorruptible
and we shall be changed this corruptible must put on incorruption this mortal
must put on immortality then he says this so when this corruptible shall have
put on incorruption when it happens because it's so certain that it's going
to happen why because God has said it this isn't the Apostle Paul just trying
to have a rah-rah session with the church in Corinth and trying to get them
emotionally charged no this is the Word of God and the certainty of the promise
is that when this happens notice the impact is going to be brought to pass
that the saying this saying death is swallowed up in victory and then we read
verse 55 and 56 Oh death where is thy sting see the sting of death is removed
because of the promise that we read in verses 51 through 54 notice at the end
of verse number 54 death is swallowed up in victory so then as a believer we find
that verse 55 says Oh death where is thy sting because death is swallowed up in
victory why because of the truth of 1st Corinthians 15 the resurrection of Jesus
Christ the the hope of every child of God remember as we studied through the
book of Hebrews this year in Hebrews chapter number 2 the Word of God gives
us this precious truth with regard to those that would fear death and the
Bible says in verse number 14 and verse number 15 with regard to this truth and
notice in Hebrews 2 and 4 verse 14 for as much then as the children are
partakers of flesh and blood he also himself likewise took part of the same
that through death he might destroy him that had the power of death
That is the devil.
Notice v. 15.
"...and deliver them who through fear of death
were all their lifetime subject to bondage."
But when we understand the certainty
of the promise that is before us
in 1 Corinthians 15,
and we look at this latter portion of this chapter,
and we see what is going to happen,
the Bible tells us that death
is swallowed up in victory,
and thus we say,
O death, where is thy staying?
O grave, where is thy victory?
I'm thankful that if I am to die
prior to the rapture,
that I will be buried in some tomb somewhere,
but that's not the end of the story.
Amen?
I know how D.L. Moody used to say
that one day you're going to read in the papers
that D.L. Moody has died.
Don't believe it.
Don't believe it for a moment
because on that day,
I'll be more alive than I ever have been.
Yesterday, a great hero of the faith,
Dr. Henry Morris III,
went home to be with the Lord.
But here's the amazing thing.
Though he served and had such an impact
upon Christianity in our generation,
and he fought and contended
for the truth of God's Word
with regard to the Genesis account
and the truth of creation,
that today, he's in the presence of his Savior.
Why?
Because he took his final breath yesterday,
and then he went to be with his Savior.
O death, where is thy victory?
O, excuse me, thy sting.
O grave, where is thy victory?
Notice what it says in verse 56.
The sting of death is sin.
Why is that?
Because the Bible says the wage of sin is death.
Remember in Genesis chapter number three,
prior to Genesis chapter number three
and in the third chapter of Genesis,
we read of the fall of man,
and we find that prior to that,
that God in chapter number two
gave instruction to Adam
with regard to the fruit of the tree
that they could not partake of.
He said that in the day that thou eat thereof,
thou shalt surely die.
What did the enemy say?
Thou shalt not surely die.
He lies to him.
He says in Genesis chapter number three,
yea, hath God said.
And then he says, ye shall not surely die.
Well, the Bible tells us that
that's when death entered into the world.
In Romans chapter number five,
you can read the portion of Scripture
as by one man, that's speaking of Adam,
sin entered into the world,
and death by sin.
And so here as we read verse number 56,
the sting of death is sin.
The reality is that we have death in the world today
because of sin.
That's the result.
That's the consequence of a decision
that was made in Genesis chapter number three
to disobey the single command of God.
And we have people today that say,
why would a loving God allow these things to happen?
Why is it that people die and all of these things,
disease and all that we deal with?
The reality is it's a consequence of sin.
Death is the result of sin.
We understand that.
The wages of sin is death.
Now we understand that there's a physical death
and there's also a spiritual death.
The Bible refers to the spiritual death
as the second death.
Now I'm thankful that as a child of God,
that the Bible also speaks about birth
and being born again.
There's a physical birth,
but there's also a spiritual birth.
And one person said this, a theologian of yesteryear,
to be born once is to die twice.
But to be born twice is to die once.
What do you mean by that?
Well, if you're only born once physically,
you're gonna die twice.
You're gonna die a physical death,
but then you're gonna die a spiritual death
because the Bible says that the wages of sin is death.
And we understand in Hebrews chapter number nine
that the Bible teaches us,
as it appointed unto man once to die,
and after this, the judgment.
And the Bible speaks about the second death.
You can read in Revelation chapter 20
and chapter number 21,
and you read about the second death.
But you also understand on the flip side of that,
to be born twice is to die once.
I was born physically.
I have a physical birthday, just as each of you do.
I was born physically on the 15th of July in the year 1980,
and that was my physical birth date.
Then I was born again on August 31st, 1997.
And the Bible says that those of us that have been born again
that the second death has no power over us.
To be born twice is to die once.
I'll die a physical death,
but I'm not gonna die a spiritual death.
I'm gonna live forevermore with my Savior.
What a wonderful truth of the word of God.
And we find that, yes, here in the passage,
it says the strength of sin is the law.
Remember, Paul says,
I had not known sin if it were not for the law,
because the law told me thou shalt not covet,
and therefore I knew that I was sinning
because I was coveting, Romans chapter number seven.
And you can find throughout the word of God
that this saying that he's referring to
because of this promise, the certainty of this promise,
the reality of what's going to happen,
but again, verse number 54,
bring it all back into context.
So when this corruptible shall have put on incorruption,
again, it's going to happen,
and this mortal shall have put on immortality,
then shall be brought to pass the saying that is written,
death is swallowed up in victory.
And then we read verse number 57,
but thanks be to God,
which giveth us the victory
through our Lord Jesus Christ.
See, He went first.
He is the firstfruits.
When we talk about the resurrection,
as we referenced in verse number 20,
again in verse number 23 of this great chapter,
and we find that we can thank God
for the victory that He has given us
through the Lord Jesus Christ.
Now when I think about the certainty
of this promise this morning,
I would say this,
the promise encourages my heart.
I hope it encourages you this morning
when you consider the promise that is before us
in verses 51 through 57,
and you begin to think about heaven,
what a joy it is when we have the opportunity
to speak about the reality and the certainty of heaven,
and man, it encourages us.
Miss Joyce comes in here so often
and speaks about heaven.
When I see my Savior,
and she speaks in terms of just great encouragement,
not only the encouragement,
but the joy and the peace
that this promise brings in the life of the believer.
I would say this,
the promise influences my expectations.
I mean, I have an expectation
that one day, one glorious day,
I'm gonna see my Savior face to face.
This life is not all there is.
We're here right now,
but remember, we're pilgrims and we're strangers.
We're just a passing through.
This world is not my home.
Praise the Lord.
I believe this morning,
when we think about this promise,
I would say this morning without hesitation,
without doubt,
that this promise that is before us
has influenced believers through the centuries.
Many have found great encouragement,
joy, and peace through the promise
of what we're looking at this morning.
Of course, we could look at a number
of additional portions of Scripture
and compare Scripture with Scripture,
but we find this morning
that these believers throughout the centuries
have been greatly influenced by this promise.
I want you to think about what Paul said.
Of course, God used Paul to write 1 Corinthians 15,
but I want you to consider a few portions of Scripture
and consider how this promise,
the certainty of this promise,
influenced the Apostle Paul.
Look over, keep your place there in 1 Corinthians 15.
We'll be back in a moment.
Look over at 2 Corinthians 5.
2 Corinthians 5.
I want you to, we'll pick it up in context.
I wish we could look at the entirety
of 2 Corinthians 5.
What a powerful passage of Scripture.
The Bible says in verse number five,
now he that hath wrought us for the self,
same thing as God,
who also hath given unto us the earnest of the Spirit.
That's the proof of our redemption.
You can compare that with Ephesians 1,
verses 12 through 14,
and the truth of God's Word,
the moment of salvation,
the Holy Spirit of God indwells every believer of God,
and what a blessing that is.
Verse six, therefore, we are always confident,
knowing that whilst we are at home in the body,
we are absent from the Lord.
Notice what he says in verse number seven,
and keep this thought for our final point this morning.
He says we walk by faith, not by sight.
Verse eight, we are confident, I say, and willing,
rather to be absent from the body
and to be present with the Lord.
Do you think Paul understood the certainty of the promise?
Sure he did.
Do you think Paul was encouraged?
Do you think he was influenced
by the certainty of the promise?
Remember as he's writing to the church in Thessalonica,
as he's giving them word with regard
to the coming of the Lord,
he says, I'm not sharing my opinion,
I'm not sharing my perspective,
I'm giving you the Word of the Lord.
He finishes that passage by saying,
comfort one another with these things.
And what comfort it brings in our hearts,
notice in the book of Philippians, if you will,
in Philippians chapter number one,
Paul is, of course, privileged of God
to minister in the city of Philippi.
He's now writing back to these believers
that he had the opportunity to do so.
opportunity during his second missionary journey to lead to Christ and influence
greatly and he's speaking about the current crisis in his life but he's
helping them understand that these things that have happened unto him have
happened under the furtherance of the gospel what a great perspective by the
way and as he's speaking to them in this first chapter I want to draw your
attention to what he says in verse number 23 he says for I'm in a straight
betwixt two what was it that had this man of God in this complex a situation
he says I'm in a straight betwixt two sometimes we're in that position maybe
there's a decision before us and we say man I don't know what to do well let me
reveal to you as you probably already know what it was that caused this
conflict for the Apostle Paul why he would say that he's in a straight
betwixt two having a desire to depart and to be with Christ which is far
better and this promise that we're looking at this morning that this mortal
must put on immortality this had a profound impact in the life of the
Apostle Paul he says I'm in a straight betwixt two what's wrong Paul what's
going on in your life well I have a desire to depart to be with Christ which
is far better notice what he says nevertheless to abide in the flesh is
more needful for you you know what he understood he understood that the what
the wise man in the Old Testament Solomon recognized there's a time to be
born and there's a time to die and what he recognized is that God the giver and
taker of life was not ready for Paul to go to be with Christ why because there
was still ministry to be done here upon this earth and he says nevertheless to
abide in the flesh is more needful for you God was still using the Apostle Paul
not only to minister broadly and to minister where he was and he reached
people with the gospel in Rome as he was in prison we understand that as we read
the the entirety of this book but we understand that he would be used of God
to pen this book to influence these believers so he says listen I have a
desire to go and be with Christ to be with my Savior which is far better but
God's not done with me here it's more needful for you that that I abide in the
flesh and he understood God's work and God's plan notice with me in 2nd
Timothy chapter number four as we kind of take a quick survey if you will
through the life and ministry of the Apostle Paul and think about the
ministry that God had given him in the way in which the promise that is before
us had influenced his life and had brought him encouragement had given him
an expectation had brought joy and peace within his life he's writing to his son
in the faith here in 2nd Timothy chapter number four and he says this in verse
number six for I am now ready to be offered I would argue with you that he
was ready in Philippians 1 he says I have a desire to depart he was ready but
it wasn't time notice now what it says and the time of my departure is at hand
God had revealed that now Paul would leave this temporal life this earth and
he would go to his long home as Ecclesiastes say he would enter into
eternity he says this in verse number seven I have fought a good fight I have
finished my course I have kept the faith henceforth there is laid up for me a
crown of righteousness which the Lord the righteous judge shall give me at
that day and not to me only but unto all them also that love his appearing as we
think about the Apostle Paul penning these words to the church in Corinth
back in first Corinthians 15 the passage in which we're studying this morning as
we consider God using this man to pen these words and understanding the
influence that he would have upon the believers in Corinth broadly speaking
believers throughout the centuries because of the fact that it is
preserved Word of God and the influence and impact in my life today I'm mindful
of some of the things that Paul says later on past first Corinthians 15
remember in 2nd Corinthians chapter number five he said that we walk by
faith not by sight why because we're still in this tabernacle we're still in
this flesh he says here in verse number seven I have fought a good fight I have
finished my course I have kept the faith why what is he referring to he's
referring to his life his journey with Christ if we could tie all of this in
with the book of Hebrews our study throughout 2020 we would say that the
challenge to the believers that were being addressed in the book of Hebrews
those first century believers was to continue don't return don't go back to
Judaism why Christ is superior Christ is better and you need to continue and
there's a charge that is given to those individuals remember in Hebrews chapter
number six he says therefore leaving the principles of the doctrine of Christ let
us go on unto perfection we're mindful in chapter number ten that the just
shall live by faith but if any man draw back my soul shall have no pleasure in
him but we are not of them who draw back unto perdition but of them that believe
to the saving of the soul we read through Hebrews chapter number 11 that
great hall of faith chapter and we read of those that went before us that were
faithful that that ran their race that finished their course and we find that
he's speaking of all those individuals and then we find that he begins chapter
number 12 by saying now let us lay aside every weight and the sin which
doth so easily beset us and let us run with patience the race that is
before us so we think about the certainty of the promise and how it
causes us to rejoice I want you to think about our conduct in the present our
conduct in the present I'm so thankful for the certainty of the promise I mean
honestly this morning the reality and the certainty of heaven thrills my soul
when we sing about those great hymns of the faith when we see Jesus when we see
him face-to-face and when we all get to heaven and all of those wonderful hymns
that we sing about heaven and it thrills my soul but I understand that that
promise is certain but there's a present and I understand this morning
that as I rejoice in the certainty of the promise that I must also understand
my conduct in the present how does this truth that has been laid before us
that's been given to these believers in Corinth what is the application as we
come to verse number 58 we find that it begins with a therefore he says therefore
my beloved brethren he's gonna give them this application if you will the impact
of this truth in the lives of these people this morning life should truth
should impact your life the Bible tells us that were to be doers of the word not
hearers only we find that we at times have had that little chorus that we
would sing I'll say yes Lord yes to your will into your way why because
God's Word is to influence my conduct in the present I'm thankful for the
certainty of the promise but what about my conduct in the present as we begin to
dissect a very familiar verse of Scripture in verse number 58 and we
begin to see what Paul is saying and we compare that with what Paul said of
himself in in 2nd Corinthians 5 and also over there in Philippians 1 and in
2nd Timothy chapter number 4 I believe that this is impactful for us today
notice what he says therefore my beloved brethren be steadfast unmovable always
abounding in the work of the Lord for as much as you know that your labor is not
vain in the Lord believer child of God there's a certain promise of eternity
that this mortal shall put on immortality but until that day serve God
until that day live for him see we find that he says be steadfast and unmovable
really those two words kind of carry the similar idea of being firm of being
settled of not wavering he says this always abounding notice where he says in
the work of the Lord we're engaged in the work our conduct in the present
we're engaged in the work we're look notice when he says always abounding I
like the imagery that we see in that verse of Scripture that God is blessing
the work we understand the truth of what Paul would say earlier to these
very believers in the church in Corinth with regard to the ministry in the
gospel that some plant and some water but God giveth the increase that we are
laborers together with the Lord and we find that he says always abounding in
the work of the Lord notice where he says for as much as you know now the the
Word of God in so many various places gives us the the certainty of what God
wants us to know he doesn't want us to be
to be ignorant of things.
He wants us to know some things.
And he says this within the context
of what we're dealing with.
For as much as you know,
notice that your labor, again,
he said that we're always abounding
in the work of the Lord.
We're engaged in God's work.
He says, for as much as you know,
that your labor is not in vain
in the Lord.
What a great truth.
What a great perspective.
What a great reminder for these believers
with regard to the conduct in the present.
What is my conduct?
What is it that I'm supposed to be doing?
Listen, we're not just going and finding
some sort of cave to hide in
until Jesus comes.
No, we're to be engaged in the work of the Lord.
Onward, forward, Christian soldier.
I mean, we march by faith.
The Bible tells us that with regard to the church,
and I'm so thankful that the church
is not man's idea.
You understand that the church is God's idea.
And Jesus Christ Himself said,
I will build My church
and the gates of hell shall not prevail against it.
It's not that we're in some kind of defensive position.
We're to be on the offense.
We're to be going onward and forward in faith.
Faith is the victory.
1 John 5.
And we find that He says,
as you would consider with me this morning,
our conduct in the present.
Here are some things.
Listen, be certain of the promise.
Allow the promise of the mortal
putting on the immortality
to encourage you and to influence you
and to give you those heavenly expectations
and to bring you that joy
and to give you that peace.
But understand that in the present,
it should have an impact on you.
You know this morning,
there are some things that I can do today
that I can't do when this promise is fulfilled.
When this mortal shall put on immortality,
there are things that I no longer will be able to do.
And such is the case for you.
There are just things you won't be able to do.
There's a whole lot of things you won't be able to do.
And I'm not going to give you an exhaustive list.
I'm obviously not going to deal with the sinful things
that you won't be able to do anymore.
But I want to speak to you about a few things.
I want to give you a challenge as we conclude this morning
to really consider,
yes, the certainty of the promise,
this mortal must put on immortality.
It's going to happen.
But until then,
there are some things that I can do.
Shall I say there are some things I must do
that I cannot do later?
When this promise is fulfilled,
I no longer will have the opportunity.
With that thought in mind,
I want to share with you a verse of Scripture
before I give you three areas
in which I would like to draw your attention to.
And that truth is in the book of Galatians.
In Galatians 6,
the Word of God gives us
a powerful truth
that is so pertinent to the subject
in which we're dealing with this morning.
In v. 10,
we will deal with this passage this evening as well.
But we'll be looking at v. 7-9.
But in v. 10 of Galatians 6,
the Bible says this,
as we have therefore opportunity.
You know that you have opportunities today
that you will not have in glory.
It's just the way it is.
As we have therefore opportunity,
let us do good unto all men,
especially unto them
who are of the household of faith.
And so we understand contextually
what he's dealing with
with regard to their interactions
with one another.
He deals with that really
in the first five verses of chapter 6
and really bearing one another's burdens
and so on and so forth.
And we see about this truth in v. 10.
But I want you to focus upon the thought
in the beginning of the verse of Scripture
as we have therefore opportunity.
You have opportunity today
that you might not have tomorrow.
We understand that our opportunities
change every day,
but I'm speaking in light of the promise
of the mortal shall put on immortality.
There are things that you can do
as a believer on this earth
that you cannot do when you're in heaven.
Number one, live by faith.
Live by faith.
What did Paul say in 2 Corinthians 5?
We mentioned it a moment ago
as we looked at that portion
and we spoke about the fact that he says
to be absent from the body
is to be present with the Lord.
But in v. 7 of chapter 5,
in the book of 2 Corinthians,
he says, for we walk by faith,
not by sight.
The just shall live by faith.
We understand the call upon the people of God
to live by faith.
But you understand
that you can only live by faith now.
Because when this mortal
shall put on immortality,
then we shall see Him.
And that's a glorious truth.
I mean, it's a wonderful promise.
I mean, we spoke about the certainty of the promise
in the beginning of our message this morning
and how it encourages us
and how it brings us joy and peace
and what blessing that is.
But you understand today
that we're to live by faith.
Then we shall see Him.
It's no longer going to be living by faith.
And so what opportunity do we have to live by faith?
Only while we're still in this body.
While we still have this earthly tabernacle.
Because when this mortal
shall put on immortality,
no longer will I be able to live by faith.
You know that it pleases God when we live by faith.
We understand that.
Hebrews 11 and verse 6.
But without faith,
it is impossible to please Him.
For he that cometh to God must believe that He is,
and that He is a rewarder of them
that diligently seek Him.
God is pleased when His people live by faith.
But as we consider the promise this morning
and then we consider our conduct in the present.
See, Paul says this is going to be the future.
This is going to happen.
This is a certain promise.
But now let's talk about your conduct in the present.
Because we're not with Jesus yet.
I'm glad one day I'm going to be with Him.
And if you've trusted Christ as your Savior,
you're going to be with Him too.
But what's our conduct in the present?
Are we living by faith?
Are we believing God?
Are we trusting God?
Are we taking Him at His Word?
Are we proving Him by living by faith?
Or are we faithless?
The reality is that the Word of God speaks
in this manner with regard to faith.
Shall the Son of Man find faith upon the earth?
Speaking about His return.
See, He speaks about the great faith that He saw
of those that He interacted with,
the Lord Jesus Christ during His earthly ministry.
But there were times in which He even said to the disciples,
how is it that you have no faith?
Right?
Where's your faith?
You saw all these things,
you experienced all these things,
and now where's your faith?
See, I can only live by faith today
when I have this earthly tabernacle.
This mortal shall put on immortality.
And then, I shall see Him.
And I will not be able to live by faith.
Number two, share the Gospel.
Share the Gospel.
We understand this morning that as the people of God,
we've been commissioned by God Almighty
to preach the Gospel.
The authority of God Himself.
In Matthew 28, all power is given unto Me
in heaven and earth.
And then He says to go and to preach the Gospel.
We understand that each Gospel book,
Matthew, Mark, Luke, and John,
each Gospel record, including the book of Acts,
give us the commission of God Almighty
to preach the Gospel.
Go ye into all the world
and preach the Gospel to every creature.
Paul said, woe is unto me
if I preach not the Gospel.
I wonder this morning,
with what level of enthusiasm do we have
to obey the Word of God?
God Almighty.
With regard to sharing the Gospel.
See, when this mortal shall put on immortality,
then, those that we will be with will know Him.
You're not going to walk the streets of glory
and share the Gospel.
Why?
Because death and hell will be cast in a lake of fire.
The Bible tells us that the only ones
that will enter into heaven
are those that have been saved,
that have been washed in the blood of the Lamb.
So there's now no need then,
when this mortal shall put on immortality,
I don't need to share the Gospel with anyone.
Because they're all saved people.
Amen?
So now.
the time to share the gospel. Now is the time to obey the command, the commission.
Why? Because this mortal shall put on, must put on, immortality. It's going to
happen. And by the way, you don't know when it's gonna happen, and I don't know
when it's gonna happen. But the truth and the certainty of the promise that
excites us, that encourages us, Paul says, therefore, based upon this truth, let me
talk to you about right now. Let me talk to you about your conduct in the present.
Let me talk to you about your service for God. That's going to happen. The
mortal will put on immortality. The corruption will put on incorruption. But
until then, what are you doing for God? How are you serving Christ? Number one,
live by faith. Number two, share the gospel. Number three, give to the Lord.
What do I mean when I speak about giving to the Lord? Well, treasure is in there,
but that's the third thought. Number one, give them your time. You know, time
will be no more. You can't give of your time when you're in heaven. I mean, you
can't give them your talents. You can't give them your treasures. And the
reality is that while I'm here, while this mortal is still mortal, while I
still am breathing and living, while I still have this earthly tabernacle, I can
give to the Lord. I can give of my time. I can give of my talents. I can give of my
treasure. But there's coming a day when this mortal shall put on immortality, and
I'm not going to be able to give of my time or my talents or my treasures. And
so we understand this morning that this is a great truth of the Word of God, the
promise of His, the certainty of His promise, and we think about the way in
which it encourages us as the people of God. But what about our conduct in the
present? There are some things that you can do. There are some things that I can
do, that I have opportunity to do, that I can only do while I'm here on earth. I
can't do it when I get to heaven. You know, it's interesting, the wise man says,
I wasn't gonna read this, but I feel that it's appropriate to do so. Look at what
the wise man says in Ecclesiastes 2. It wasn't that I wasn't gonna read it
because it didn't fit or whatever. I just didn't know that we'd have time to go
here. But notice what Solomon says in Ecclesiastes chapter number 2. Of course,
we understand that he's looking at earth, he's looking at life, this side of
eternity, and the vanity of vanities, and so on and so forth. But I want you to
consider this thought. In Ecclesiastes chapter number 2, in verse number 17
through 19, this is, therefore I hated life, because the work that is wrought
under the sun is grievous unto me, for all is vanity and vexation of spirit.
Notice what he says in verse 18. Yea, I hated all my labor which I had taken
under the sun. Why? Because I should leave it unto the man that shall be after me.
What's he saying? I can't do anything with it after I die. Notice verse number
19. And who knoweth whether he shall be a wise man or a fool? Yet shall he have
rule over all my labor wherein I have labored, and wherein I have showed
myself wise under the sun. This is also vanity. You know, Solomon understood
something. There's a time to be born, a time to die. He's gonna mention that in
chapter number 3. But even prior to that, he's noticing, listen, life under
the sun, life on this side of eternity, I'm gonna die one day and I
have no control over those things. There's no more that I can do with that.
I think about the nation of Israel. We understand that in the book of Malachi,
they're under a great indictment for many things that they're doing. Turn to
the book of Malachi, if you will. I want you to think about this truth that God
has given with regard to the responsibility that we have to give
unto the Lord. We have the opportunity to give, yes, of our time and our talents and
our treasures. And we think about the privilege that is ours. Listen, giving is
part of worship. When we fail to give, not only are we robbing God, but we're not
worshiping Him in the way in which He is worthy to be
worshiped. Can I share something with you this morning? God doesn't need
your money. He doesn't need my money. But in God's wisdom and in His design, He
said, give. Give and it shall be given unto you. See, He set forth this
principle, this walking by faith, this believing God and giving. Notice in
verse number 7 of Malachi chapter number 3, even from the days of your
fathers you're gone away from mine ordinances and have not kept them.
Return unto me and I will return unto you, saith the Lord of hosts. But ye said,
wherein shall we return? Notice verse 8. Will a man rob God? Yet ye have robbed me.
But ye say, wherein have we robbed thee? God says in tithes and offerings. Can I
tell you this morning with all sincerity, I'd never want to be accused of robbing
God. Wow. And I hope this morning that you would not in any way shape or form want
to be accused. Let me say this, they weren't just accused of it, they were
guilty of it, of robbing God. I don't want to rob any man, but I especially
don't want to rob God. He says, you've robbed God. Ye say, wherein have we robbed
thee? God says in tithes and offerings. Why? Because God knows everything. God
knows. It says, you're accursed with a curse for you have robbed me. Even this
whole nation. Wow. So not only were they guilty of robbing God, but now they're
cursed with a curse. That's pretty serious. So what's the remedy? Verse 10.
Bring ye all the tithes into the storehouse, that there may be meat in
mine house. Notice what he says, and prove me now herewith, saith the Lord of hosts,
if I will not open you the windows of heaven and pour you out a blessing, that
there shall not be room enough to receive it. Now in my mind, and maybe
you're different than I am, but I seek to, as we look at Psalm 119, I like to think
and act biblically. I don't do it all the time, but I try to immerse myself
so much in the Word of God that I just think biblically. Again, I'm not
there, I haven't arrived, but I love God's Word and I want God's Word in me. And when
I read this verse of Scripture, in verse number 10, when he speaks about, if I will
not open the windows of heaven, immediately my mind goes back to the
life and ministry of Elisha, when he talks about the the famine in the land
and he tells them, hey there's gonna be meat, there's gonna be plenty, there's
gonna be grain, and so on and so forth. And the man, the officer at the
gate, he says, might this thing be if God were to open the windows of heaven? And
Elisha says, you're gonna see it and hear of it, but you're not gonna partake of it.
You remember those leprous men? They go out there, they're in that quandary. I
mean, if we stay here, we're gonna die. If we go back over there, we're gonna die. I
mean, we have no food. If we go to the Assyrians, I mean, it's possible that
they would spare us. What happens? They go and they find the tents empty, but all
the spoil is there, but the soldiers are gone. And they had plenty. I'm wondering
this morning, if when the children of Israel, who were very familiar with their
history, read this verse of Scripture, their mind raced back to the event that
I'm referring to. You could look back in 2 Kings chapter number 7 and read of
the event and read of what happens. And that man says, the one that leaned, whose
hand the king leaned, answered the man of God and said, if the Lord would make
windows in heaven, might this thing be? And he said, behold, thou shalt see it
with thine eyes, but thou shalt not eat thereof. And if you go to the end of the
passage, you see that the Bible says that the people went out and spoiled the tents
of the Assyrians in verse number 16. So a measure of fine flour was sold for a
shekel, two measures of barley for a shekel, according to the word of the Lord.
You understand that before that, they were to the point where they were
killing their own offspring because they were starving. I can't even comprehend.
And God says to these people that were robbing him, they were guilty of robbing
him, wherein have we robbed thee in tithes and offerings? You're under a curse. He
says, therefore, here's the remedy. Bring ye all the tithes in the storehouse. He
says, prove me in the passage, prove me now herewith, sayeth the Lord. If I will
not open you the windows of heaven and pour you out a blessing, that there shall
not be room enough to receive it. And I will rebuke the devourer for your sakes,
and he shall not destroy the fruits of your ground, neither shall your vine cast
her fruit before the time in the field, saith the Lord of hosts. And all nations
shall call you blessed, for you shall be a delightsome land, saith the Lord of
hosts. As we think about this passage of scripture within the context of what
we're dealing with this morning, with our conduct in the present, listen.
there's something I can give to God today of my treasures, of my tithes, and
my offerings for the work of the Lord. You understand that David, prior
to his death, he gave from his own resources in order for the temple to be
built. A temple that he would never step into, a temple that he would never
worship God from, but he gave of his own resources. But when he died, he no longer
would have the opportunity to do those things. And so this mortal must put on
immortality. When we think about this truth of giving of our own resources to
the Lord, and we think about the the indictment against these people in
Malachi 3, and we think about the promise that God has given, I'm mindful of how
the prophet of God said, hey you're working to earn this money, but you're
putting it in bags with holes. Why? Because you're robbing me. But God says
if you prove me, if you do the right thing, if you live by faith, if you give
to the Lord, I'm gonna bless, and I'm gonna rebuke the devourer. Listen, I want
the blessing of God, and I want God to rebuke the devourer. And so this morning
we think about our conduct in the present, and we think about a few
examples of things that I can do while I still am in this earthly tabernacle. I
can live by faith. Then I shall see him. I can share the gospel. I can give. But
when this mortal shall put on immortality, those opportunities are gone.
Can't do it anymore. I'm gonna read you a poem. Many of you perhaps have heard it
before. C.T. Studd wrote this poem, Only One Life. Two little lines I heard one
day, traveling along life's busy way, bringing conviction to my heart, and from
my mind would not depart. Only one life till soon be past. Only what's done for
Christ will last. Only one life, yes, only one. Soon will its fleeting hours be done.
Then, in that day, my Lord to meet, and stand before his judgment seat. Only one
life till soon be past. Only what's done for Christ will last. Only one life, the
still small voice, gently pleads for a better choice, bidding my
selfish aims to leave, and to God's holy will to cleave. Only one life till soon
be past. Only what's done for Christ will last. Only one life, a few brief years.
Each with its burdens, hopes, and fears. Each with its clays I must fulfill,
living for self or in his will. Only one life till soon be past. Only what's done
for Christ will last. When this bright world would tempt me sore, when Satan
would a victory score, when self would seek to have its way, then help me, Lord,
with joy to say, only one life till soon be past. Only what's done for Christ will
last. Give me, Father, a purpose deep, in joy or sorrow, thy word to keep. Faithful
and true, what e'er the strife, pleasing thee in my daily life. Only one life
till soon be past. Only what's done for Christ will last. Oh, let me love with
fervor burn, and from the world now let me turn, living for thee and thee alone,
bringing thee pleasure on thy throne. Only one life till soon be past. Only
what's done for Christ will last. Only one life, yes, only one. Now let me say,
thy will be done, and when at last I'll hear the call, I know I'll say, t'was
worth it all. Only one life till soon be past. Only what's done for Christ will
last. I believe this morning there's a child of God, the promise that is before
us, it's certain. This mortal must put on immortality, but I wonder how it's
impacted my conduct for the present. See, I don't believe that as a child of God I
would lay upon my deathbed and regret living by faith. I don't think I'd lay on
my deathbed and regret sharing the gospel. I don't believe that I would lay
upon my deathbed and regret giving to the Lord. But I'd say this, there are many
people that have taken their final breath, that laid upon their deathbed,
and they said, I wish, I wish I would have done more. I wish I would have lived by
faith. I wish I would have shared the gospel with more people. I wish I would
have given of my time, my talents, and my treasures. And with regret they lay upon
that deathbed. Not saying I regret doing living for God, no, I regret not doing
more. And when we understand the certainty of this promise in 1st
Corinthians 15, it's designed to impact our conduct in the present. I'm looking
toward that day when I see my Savior face to face. Listen, it's closer now
than it's ever been. I'm a day closer to eternity and so are you. And that's a
certain promise. But I wonder about our conduct in the present. Oh, would God help
us to live by faith, to live for him, understanding as this man of God
from yesteryear said in this poem, only one life will soon be passed. Only what's
done for Christ will last. Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. Thank you
for the Word of God and the truth contained therein. I thank you for the
privilege of having the Bible. Thank you for the challenge that you've given to
me in my own life. I pray that you've used your word this morning to challenge
the folks that have watched, tuned in, been part of our service today. God, that
we would surrender our lives and our wills to you. That your word would impact
our perspective with regard to eternity and also with regard to this life. I'm so
thankful for the promise that this mortal must put on immortality. But as I
meditate upon those things that I no longer will be able to do, I wonder how
that promise has impacted my current conduct, my conduct in the
present. Lord, help me to live by faith. Help me to share the gospel. Help me to
give. Lord, help me to serve you acceptably. I pray that you would move
and work in the lives of your people. Lord, that decisions would be made today,
decisions that would please thee, decisions that would cause us to be
conformed to the image of Christ. Would you help us today to have a high level
of enthusiasm to obey the Word of God, God Almighty? Well, thank you for the work
that you'll do, for it's in Christ's name we pray.