2 is where we'll be this morning. Elizabeth's sister's here again as well, so good to see you.
James chapter number 2, be looking at verses 1 through 13. I'm just going to read the first
verse. We'll dig into the message this morning. Notice in verse number 1 of James chapter number
2, the Bible says, My brethren, have not the faith of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Lord of glory,
with respect of persons. Now, I love the way that James, under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit
of God, because we know all scripture is given by inspiration of God, but I love how verse number
1, this second chapter, and we know the chapter divisions are added later, but he says, My
brethren, speaking to these believers, these saved individuals, these Jewish saved people, he says,
have not the faith of our Lord Jesus Christ. By the way, that's the full title of our Savior,
the Lord Jesus Christ, but then it says this, the Lord of glory. Aren't you thankful to know
Jesus as your personal Lord and Savior, to know that he is the Lord Jesus Christ, God in flesh,
the promised Messiah, the one who was promised and foretold throughout the Old Testament, fulfilled
all the prophecies, came, suffered, and bled, and died, rose, conquering sin, death, and the grave,
is alive forevermore. One day he's coming back, and what a glorious day that will be, and he says
he's Lord of glory, and then he says this, with respect of persons. Now, remember, as we've started
citing the book of James here in 2026, and we're several weeks, months in at this point, we find,
and it's important for us to be reminded of the fact that the book of James is extremely practical
in nature. Remember, James is seeking to encourage the brethren to do what? To live out their faith.
The idea that you have faith, and we'll get into this as we continue through the book, and there's
really no contradiction between faith and works. We find that they're complementary, not contradictory,
and he says that if you have faith, it's evidenced by your works, it's seen in your behavior, and so
we find that he's encouraging the brethren to live out their faith. The spiritual, or the goal,
is spiritual maturity. I said this in the very first week of this calendar year, not all who grow
old grow up. Now, that's not just true in the physical realm, that's true in the spiritual realm
as well, and we're looking for that spiritual maturity. Remember, the Apostle Paul, as he ends
2 Corinthians 13, the passage that we ended with last year, looking at our theme, God's
grace is sufficient, starting through the book of 2 Corinthians, he tells the people at
Corinth, the believers in the church in Corinth, he says that he was praying for their perfection, their
spiritual maturity, and then he tells them to be perfect, to go strive forth for that spiritual
maturity in your life. And by the way, you're as mature spiritually as you really want to be. You've
spent as much time with God last week as you really wanted to, and what a blessing to have access,
direct access to the throne room of heaven, that we can come boldly before the throne of grace to
worship him and to exalt him and to bring our petitions before his throne. We find that he also
gives us a Bible and we have the opportunity to read and study and to grow. He says this,
as newborn babes desire the sincere milk of the word, why that ye may grow thereby. The church in
Corinth was not a church that had spiritual maturity. In fact, Paul says, I can't speak to you
the way that I want to speak to you. I can't give you the truth that I want to give you. Why?
Because you're carnal, you're babes, and the reality is that the goal is spiritual maturity.
Now it says there at the end of verse number one, with respect of persons, we'll find within the text
in verse number four, it says, are you not then partial in yourselves? And then you find again in
verse number nine, if you have respect to persons. And so throughout the passage here, really the
thought, the subject that's being dealt with is this idea of partiality, to be partial, to be
partial. The Greek word that is used here is to be discriminant, to prefer one, to be partial or to
have partiality, is to be biased to one party, to be inclined to favor without reason. Really it springs
from the will and the affections rather than from a love of truth and justice. We find that there's
an aspect here where it deals with respect of persons and partiality, that it's based often on
class status instead of character. Let me say this, what we believe is revealed by how we behave.
And God's word has the answer for every situation that we face in life. And God's word is the
authority and we find that as we come to the word of God, that God's word has principles contained
therein that can be applied in every arena of our lives. You may not find a particular bible
verse that will say, thou shalt not and fill in the blank, whatever it might say. But if you find
and you prove all things and you prove what is acceptable unto the Lord, then you gain biblical
principles that are applied into everyday situations so that you can please the Lord.
And so this morning, you've already seen probably on the bulletin, but I've titled the message this
morning, Partiality Condemned. Partiality Condemned. Number one, if you're taking notes, we see it in
verses two and three. We'll circle back to verse number one at the end of the message, but notice
number one, partiality explained. In verses two and three, James, again under the inspiration of
the Holy Spirit of God, is going to use an illustration to ensure that his audience will
understand the subject. And by the way, this illustration that is used in verses two and three
is both clear and relatable. It is something that each of these original recipients, but also
throughout the history of the church, we've been able to read verses two and three and say, I get
it. I understand what James is speaking about. I understand what God is confronting us with,
the subject of respective persons or partiality. So notice partiality explained in verse number two,
it says this, for if there come unto your assembly, and so I'm going to pause there,
your gathering, right? The church, ekklesia is the Greek word for church, and it means assembly.
Here, they would probably, this word actually is dealing with the synagogue and obviously Jewish
people and kind of through that transition, understanding their assembly, their gathering.
And so we find that he says, for if there come unto your assembly, a man with a gold ring
in goodly apparel, and there come in also a poor man in vile raiment. And so we find that verse
number two illustrates for us these two individuals that could be at the opposite end of the spectrum,
if you will, economically. And we find that these two individuals enter into the same assembly.
It's not two different assemblies, it's into the same assembly. And one comes in, and it's really
the outward appearance that is dealt with in verse number two. And we find that the outward
appearance will have an impact upon the onlookers, upon those that are gathered in that assembly.
They see these two individuals that enter in, and the one is a man, as it says in verse number two,
with a gold ring in goodly apparel. And so we find that immediately it would be, listen,
I understand the truth of 1 Samuel when God is speaking to Samuel about not choosing Eliab
as the king. And God says, no, don't look at his outward appearance. Why? For man looketh on the
outward, but God looks at the heart. And I'm thankful for that truth. But there's really two
truths in that passage of scripture that are important for us to understand. One is that God
sees your heart. Number two is man can only see the outward. I can't see your heart. I can only
see the outward. But let me say this, the outward is a reflection of the heart. Amen? And that's why
we're talking about what we believe is evidenced in how we behave. And we find that this individual
comes into the assembly and you find that he has a gold ring and he's got this goodly apparel. And
so immediately it would be obvious to all of those that are there with regard to this individual.
But then there's another one that comes in and it says that this is a poor man in vile raiment. I
mean, there's nothing goodly about his attire. There's nothing that would cause you to think
this is a man of means, an individual that has some level of wealth or riches. And we find that
this again, it's very clear, it's very relatable. But then we notice as the illustration progresses
into verse number three, notice what James says, and ye, so again, the word
He is plural, right?
He's talking about the assembly.
So those that are already there, the brethren,
that's who he's talking to, the believers,
my brethren, verse number one.
So ye have respect to him that weareth the gay clothing
and say unto him, sit thou here in a good place.
And then you say to the poor,
stand thou there or sit here under my footstool.
Now, the actions that are described in verse number three
reveal to us that each of these individuals
that are illustrated in verse number two
receive a very different reception, amen?
And so if we could illustrate this
and kind of play this out this morning,
we're here and we're gathered and we're in assembly
and somebody walks in and man, they are just dressed
and they have what looks like on the outward.
Man, they're a person of means, of wealth, of whatever.
And all of a sudden, it's a disregard for others
that are there and we just go and me,
oh, come sit, I'm gonna give you this place to sit
and I'm gonna put you in this place
and I'm gonna highly esteem you.
But then there's somebody else that comes in
and not dressed the same way and we just ignore them.
We just have no time for them.
We say, stand thou there in the corner.
The illustration is pretty easy to understand, is it not?
It's very clear.
It's very relatable as to what's going on
and we find that here what's happening
in verses two and three is that partiality
is being explained.
It's a desire for God to help his people
to understand what partiality looks like, why?
Because most people, if they're confronted
with being partial, are gonna deny it.
I'm not partial.
There's no partiality.
And so what does he do?
Well, he first starts by explaining
what partiality looks like and here's what it looks like.
Now, let me say this.
Within the context of James chapter number two,
partiality here in verses two and three,
as it's explained to us, is really based
upon economic status.
Let me say it this way.
The assumption of economic status.
The reality is that the one that was dressed
with the gold ring and the goodly apparel,
he could have spent everything he had
to look good on the outward and had nothing else.
And the one that had vile raiment
or that which was not outwardly impressive,
that one could have lots of means.
The idea is that there's partiality
that's based on perceived economic status.
Can I say this to you today?
That still happens to this very day.
Partiality based on economic status
continues to this very day.
In various places, in various arenas,
but we find that it still happens.
Let me say this.
Partiality explained in James two,
as it's illustrated in verses two and three,
is based on that perceived economic status,
but that's not the only way that partiality
is actually practiced or evidenced.
We find that there can be partiality
based on religious affiliation.
Happens all over the world.
All over the world.
There are people that are partial,
that are respecters of persons,
based on religious affiliation.
And they have a different religion,
and therefore they're partial to someone else.
They're prejudiced towards someone else.
And so we see it economically.
We see it religiously.
We also would say this.
We see it politically.
There's definitely the ability to be politically partial,
that we would have that danger.
We see it in our country today.
I mean, we see it not only here in America,
but all over the world.
There's great divide when it comes to political things.
In this nation at this time,
I'm not sure that we could be any more divided
than we really are.
And here's what I need to be careful of,
and here's what you need to be careful of,
is to know, listen, I'm thankful to be an American,
but my citizenship is in heaven.
Amen?
Regardless of someone's economic status,
regardless of someone's religious affiliation,
regardless of someone's political party affiliation,
that's someone that I'm supposed to reach
with the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
Amen?
And we understand that.
Let me say this, and it's probably one of the most prevalent
in America, means of partiality, and that's based on race.
And it's something that we just face.
We just deal with it.
We just, look, the scriptures deal with everyday living.
Amen?
And so we see that partiality is explained,
and we find that these things happen,
and you see this taking place.
Now, let me say this.
When you live in certain countries,
and I've had the opportunity to travel to some places,
not many, as some of you have traveled
much more extensively than I have,
but you go to some places in the world,
and race is not a factor with regard to partiality.
Why?
Because they all have the same amount of pigment
in their skin.
They all look exactly the same,
but there's still partiality.
Y'all don't like it this morning.
Come on, there's still partiality.
You go to India, there's partiality in India.
You go to many of the African countries,
there's partiality.
Everyone can look exactly the same on the outward,
but there's partiality, and it's based on
either economic or religious primarily.
All right?
You come to America, America is a country of immigrants.
Amen?
For every one of us, unless you're Native American,
every one of us has somewhere in our history
where our ancestor came to America.
Amen?
And there was a process, whatever that process was,
you have the, maybe if you know your family's history
and what have you, you know where they came from,
you know why they came.
My ancestors didn't come for a good reason,
they came because they were in trouble where they were,
and they came here, and it's just, you know,
all kinds of different stories.
But being a nation that's a nation of immigrants,
it's really easy to be able to be partial based on race.
We're talking about partiality being explained,
but we're not gonna stop there
because we see partiality explained,
and then we see partiality exposed.
So let me say this, as we continue through the text,
we find that the explanation is given in verses two and three
but then look at verse number four.
He says this, he's gonna expose it.
He says, are ye not then partial in yourselves
and are become judges of evil thoughts?
So he explains what partiality looks like,
he uses this illustration that's very clear
and very relatable, two people enter in,
very opposite ends of the spectrum,
perceived spectrum of economic status,
and there's a different reception,
very different reception for each one of them,
and therefore, he explains it but then he exposes it
and he says, are ye not then partial in yourselves
and are become judges of evil thoughts?
Look at verse number six, but ye have despised the poor.
Do not rich men oppress you
and draw you before the judgment seats?
So verse six is kind of an interesting verse
because he tells them that they're despising the poor
through this respecter of persons, through this partiality,
they're despising the poor and then he says,
by the way, do not rich men oppress you
and draw you before the judgment seats?
So the very ones that are oppressing you,
the very ones that are bringing you
before the judgment seat, now you're respecting them
and what's he doing?
He's exposing it, he's exposing the error of their way,
he's exposing, why?
Because the action is going to reveal
what's truly in the heart of the individual.
The action is going to reveal what is truly
in the heart of the individual.
And let me say this, when we begin to think about
what's happening here and we understand, again,
contextually that here, my brethren,
and we established it pretty consistently
throughout James chapter number one,
that James is writing to these Jewish believers
that are facing persecution
as we study through the book of Acts,
we see all that's taking place,
but these Jewish believers, and let me say this,
and please, I'm gonna be careful how I say it,
but I believe it's an accurate statement biblically,
the Jewish people were extremely partial.
Okay, when Jesus, and we're gonna get there
at the end of the text, when he said,
I must needs go through Samaria, that was a big deal.
The Jewish people, they despised Gentiles.
In fact, referred to them as being dogs, right?
Is that biblical?
We read it, we read the history, we read the interactions,
and so we see it biblically,
and so we find that this was something
that would have been part of maybe,
if we could say, even their culture
and what they were used to.
But if any man be in Christ.
He is a new creature.
Old things are passed away.
Behold, all things are become new.
Amen?
And so we find that what's happening here
is James is exposing
in the individuals that he's ministering to
this subject of partiality.
He's explained it, but now he's exposed it.
We find that Jesus not only went there to Samaria,
but we find that he said
specifically in the book of Acts
when he gave the Great Commission.
You read the other events
or the other records of the Great Commission.
Go ye into all the world and preach the gospel
to every creature.
That's all-inclusive, is it not?
That's every single people group.
We understand that, but understand
how he said it in Acts.
Jerusalem, Judea, Samaria,
and the uttermost part.
I'm thankful. Listen, every word of God is pure.
And he specifically said Samaria. Why?
Because I believe, it's just my belief,
I believe that many of those Jewish believers
would have very conveniently skipped Samaria
and still thought they were carrying out
the Great Commission.
Are you tracking this morning?
Listen, God's word is applicable in everyday life.
I know it's not the most popular message to preach,
but the reality is that this is what we live with.
This is what we deal with, and God's word
is the instruction that we need.
How many of you watched a football game?
This past year, or in the past several years,
and you'll see in the end zone
written there, end racism.
Have you seen it?
Come on, I've seen it.
I don't even watch that much football, and I've seen it.
Can I tell you that the world and their philosophies
are never going to end racism?
It's only when we take the truth of God's word
and apply it appropriately that partiality,
and I don't really truly, I think partiality
is the right biblical word to use,
because partiality, again, can be evidenced
in multiple types of ways.
Again, economic, religious, maybe political,
and then also through race,
but we find that he's exposing this,
and again, think about our own heart.
Listen, your heart's deceitful.
Amen?
Our hearts are deceitful.
Listen, I've walked up to some houses
to knock doors,
to proclaim the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ,
and in their yard,
they have a sign that says,
everyone's welcome here,
except for me.
Why?
Because they don't like the message that I'm bringing.
I'm just being transparent with you this morning
and trying to help us understand
how this thing really works.
And what I'm saying is that
you can put any sign in your yard that you want to,
you can make any motion or movement
that you want to make,
but really what ends partiality
is biblical Christianity.
Biblical Christianity
is the answer to partiality.
By the way, Jesus is the answer to everything.
What we need in America is God.
Amen?
People get in all this kind of,
we need this candidate, we need this one,
we need that one.
No, we need God.
Our hope is not in the White House,
it's not in Wall Street,
it's in God's house.
We need revival.
We need to see God do a work
that only God can do.
And I believe that He wants to.
I believe that He's able to.
If God's people would just get serious about it,
about being that channel only that we sing about,
that God would use us for His honor
and for His glory,
that we would recognize that it's all about Jesus,
it's nothing about me.
I mentioned this on Wednesday evening,
and I'm continuing to read the book,
and he's mentioned it several times,
our God is omni-everything
and we are omni-nothing.
We need God.
Now God will work through us,
praise the Lord,
because I am a branch.
But the branch needs to be attached to the vine.
Hallelujah.
And we find, listen,
the answer is always the Bible.
And so we look at this,
it's explained, it's exposed,
but let me say this,
finally, partiality expelled.
Partiality expelled.
God's word has the answer,
we must search the scriptures
in order to apply biblical principles
to our daily living.
Notice, if you will,
back in verse number five,
in James chapter number two,
in verse number five,
he says this,
Hearken, my beloved brethren,
hath not God chosen the poor of this world,
rich in faith,
and heirs of the kingdom
which He hath promised to them
that love Him?
Listen, I'm thankful this morning
that my salvation was not dependent
on any kind of status that I had.
My salvation is simply in the fact
that I was a sinner in need of a Savior.
I've said this many times from this pulpit,
there's only two categories of people
in all the world.
There are saved people
and there are lost people.
Period.
End of story.
The world wants to categorize.
Why?
Because the world wants to divide.
Deceiving and being deceived,
that's what happens through this whole process.
And God's word gives the answer.
And we're talking about partiality being expelled.
And so listen,
my salvation and your salvation
was not based upon any status that you had.
I'm thankful
that God loved an old sinner like me
and like you.
And He adopted me into His family.
And He made me join heirs with Jesus.
I mean, hallelujah, man.
Praise the Lord.
Salvation is something wonderful.
If any man be in Christ,
he's a new creature.
I quoted that verse a moment ago.
And it's so important that we recognize
what we have in Christ.
He says in v. 7,
look there, it says this,
Do not they blaspheme that worthy name
by the which ye are called?
Speaking about those rich men in v. 6.
And then v. 8.
If ye fulfill the royal law
according to the Scripture,
thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself.
Ye do well.
Can I tell you this morning
that the world truly can't define love
the way that God does?
Listen, the world misunderstands love.
The world thinks that love
is like some coddling and accommodating.
Listen, love gives truth.
Love speaks truth.
God loves us,
so He tells us that we're sinners
in need of a Savior.
He doesn't love us and say
just do whatever you want to do
and we're going to accommodate whatever.
No, He loves us,
so He gives us the truth.
And we find here He says,
Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself.
Ye do well.
We understand the appeal to the Old Testament.
But think about what Jesus said.
Jesus changed the whole dynamic.
Why?
Because when Jesus came
and you start looking at His teachings,
you find that Jesus started dealing with the heart,
not just the outward.
You know what a lot of those
Jewish religious leaders were good at?
The outward.
The rabbis, the Pharisees, the Sadducees,
still to this very day,
they're very good at the outward.
If you've ever taken a trip to Israel,
I have.
I've been there.
They're very good at the outward.
But Jesus starts dealing with the heart.
Do you remember?
He says if you commit adultery,
well that was the idea of the Pharisees,
the religious leaders.
But if you think on a woman,
you've already committed adultery in your heart.
Now all of a sudden God's dealing with the heart.
Amen?
I've never murdered anyone.
Yeah, but if you've hated your brother
in your heart.
Oh, now it's coming.
Right?
And so we see what's happening.
Jesus then says this in John chapter number 13
that we're to love how?
As Christ loved.
Can I tell you this morning,
it is impossible for a lost person
to love like Christ loved.
And it's impossible for you to love like Christ loved
unless you let him love through you.
The love of God is shed abroad by the Holy Spirit,
Romans chapter number five,
that indwells us.
I'm so thankful for the indwelling
of the Holy Spirit of God.
He tells us, he commands us,
but then he enables us.
And so we see here in verse number eight
this wonderful truth,
and we find that he says in verse nine,
but the contrast here,
here's what you should do,
but here's, he's already exposed it
in the previous verses.
He says, if you have respect to persons,
notice these three words,
ye commit sin.
We don't like dealing with sin,
but we have to.
We have to.
Listen, partiality is sin.
Partiality is sin.
And unless you believe that,
you're never gonna deal with it.
It's never gonna be expelled.
And we find that it says in verse number nine,
but if you have respect to persons,
ye commit sin
and are convinced of the law
as transgressors.
Verse 10, for whoso shall keep the whole law
and yet offend in one point,
he is guilty of all.
And so you think,
I got everything else squared away,
I just got this little thing going on,
you're guilty of all.
He says in verse number 11,
for he that said,
do not commit adultery, said also, do not kill.
Now if thou commit no adultery, yet if thou kill,
thou art become a transgressor of the law.
So speak ye, and so do, as they that shall be judged
by the law of liberty, for he shall have judgment
without mercy that hath showed no mercy,
and mercy rejoiceth against judgment.
So let me, as we deal with this idea
of partiality being expelled, listen, he says,
if you have respective persons, ye commit sin.
What do we do when we are confronted with God's word
about sin in our lives?
Well, we can really do one of two things.
We can quench the spirit, we can despise the prophesyings,
and we can just try to cover our sin.
But the scriptures tell us,
whoso covereth the sin shall not prosper.
Or we can accept the truth of God's word
and agree with God that what God calls sin is sin.
And what do I do?
Well, I confess it and I forsake it.
First John 1.9, if we confess our sins,
he is faithful and just to forgive us,
not only to forgive us our sins, but to cleanse us.
Aren't you thankful for the wonderful promise
that we have in First John 1.9?
And so we have to agree with God, the idea of confessing.
It's not this idea, Lord, if I sinned.
Stop it.
You know you sinned, right?
How many times do we do that?
God, if I'd sinned at all, if I did anything, stop.
He knows, listen, he searches the hearts, he knows.
You might be able to deceive yourself,
you might be able to deceive your spouse,
you might be able to deceive your parents,
but you are not gonna deceive God.
Amen?
And so what do we do?
Well, we confess it and we forsake it
and we have forgiveness and we find
that how can partiality be expelled?
Again, I've said it and I'll say it again,
the answer to partiality is biblical Christianity.
That's the answer.
Notice, if you will, back,
we're gonna look at a couple of Old Testament principles
and then look at the New Testament evidence of that.
Look in the book of Leviticus, if you will,
and the principles that we're gonna look at
are really with regard to our God.
And look in Leviticus 19,
and we'll look at Deuteronomy as well,
and then we'll jump over to the New Testament.
Look in Leviticus 19, if you will,
and as you're turning there, look at verse number 15.
Leviticus 19 and verse number 15,
by the way, he told them in verse number two,
ye shall be holy, for I the Lord your God am holy.
Verse 15, ye shall do no unrighteousness in judgment.
Thou shalt not respect the person of the poor
nor honor the person of the mighty,
but in righteousness shalt thou judge thy neighbor.
Listen, God is no respecter of persons,
and God's people should be no respecter of persons.
In Deuteronomy chapter number 10,
notice what God is saying here to this generation
that would be the ones that would enter into
and possess the land.
In Deuteronomy 10, in verse 17,
by the way, in verse 16, he tells them,
circumcise therefore the foreskin of your heart
and be no more stiff-necked.
Jewish people, especially in the New Testament,
are so concerned about the outward circumcision,
but Jesus says, circumcise the foreskin of your heart.
Why?
Because it's the heart of the matter.
He says in verse 17, for the Lord your God
is God of gods and Lord of lords, a great God,
a mighty and a terrible, which regardeth not persons
nor taketh reward.
He doth execute the judgment of the fatherless and widow
and loveth the stranger and giving him food and raiment.
Love ye therefore the stranger,
for you are strangers in the land of Egypt.
I'm thankful that God is no respecter of persons.
Listen, you're not gonna make a bargain with God.
I don't care how much money somebody has,
I don't care how much prestige, power, position,
you're not gonna bargain with God.
We sing it with the kids.
One way God said to get to heaven, Jesus is the only way.
No other way, no other way, amen?
He said, I am the way, the truth, and the life.
No man cometh unto the father but by me.
You're not gonna bargain with God.
Look in the book of Acts, if you will, chapter number 10.
We're gonna walk through just a couple of verses here
in the book of Acts, and I want you to see
some of these truths that God gives us
with the early church, and again,
this early church was given the responsibility to go
and to preach the gospel to every creature,
and we find that they were to go
and they were to have that opportunity
to be able to give forth the truth of God's word,
and what a blessing.
In verse number 33, it says,
immediately therefore I sent to thee,
and thou hast well done that thou art come.
This is Cornelius talking as he called for Peter to come,
kind of catch the context, if you will,
and he says, now therefore, we are we all here
present before God to hear all things
that are commanded thee of God,
and so to catch the entire context,
in Acts chapter number 10, we find that God gives,
Cornelius is a man that's praying.
He's religious, but he's lost,
and God allows for a vision and says, go send for Peter,
tells him where to go, who to send for,
all the details, and at the same time,
God's working in Peter's heart.
Peter sees this vision, and he says, not so, Lord.
I've never had anything unclean,
and all the things that are happening,
again, who's Cornelius?
Well, that's a Gentile.
Peter, Jew.
Amen?
There's a conflict between Jews and Gentiles,
and what happens?
Well, we find that here, Cornelius says,
here's what's happened.
He rehearses, he says, and we're all here,
ready to hear from you.
By the way, that's a great opportunity.
I had that happen one time at a funeral.
I'm telling you, man, it was a memorial service
at some guy's house.
I didn't know him, they didn't know me,
and it was a military member that their dad passed,
entered into eternity, didn't know anything
about their religious background whatsoever,
but Holly's cousin was in the Marine Corps as well
and said, would you be a blessing to that family?
I pulled up.
I didn't know if I was getting out of there.
I didn't know what was going on.
I pulled up, went into that house,
and they said, hey, hey, hey, the preacher's here.
Let's listen.
And the whole place, man, I'm like, let's go.
Praise the Lord, amen?
And I felt like Paul when they said,
if you have anything to say,
yes, I have something to say, amen?
And man, it's a great opportunity.
And so what does Peter do?
Notice what Peter says first in verse 34.
Then Peter opened his mouth and said,
of a truth I perceive that God is no respecter of me.
Of persons.
By the way, if you read chapter number 11,
when Peter comes back to the Jews,
those of the circumcision,
oh, brother, they're not happy with Peter.
Oh, they're not happy with Peter.
But then Peter rehearses everything
and Peter gets to the end of it.
And Peter says this.
He tells them that as he began to speak
that the Holy Ghost fell on them as on us at the beginning.
And he begins to share with them.
And so what do they conclude
when they heard these things?
Verse 18, they held their peace and glorified God saying,
then hath God also to the Gentiles
granted repentance unto life.
Hallelujah.
Why, I'm a Gentile.
Praise God.
But Peter had to acknowledge something very important.
God is no respecter of persons.
And he acknowledged that
before he ever preached the gospel.
It was important for him to,
it's recorded for us so that we would understand
this truth as well.
Look in chapter 15, if you will.
In Acts chapter number 15.
What's happening here?
Well, this is the council at Jerusalem.
In Acts chapter number 15,
there's all kinds of things going on.
And what's happening?
Well, they tell us right in the beginning,
it says this, that if you're not circumcised,
except you be circumcised after the manner of Moses,
you cannot be saved.
And there's some Jewish people
causing some problems for Paul,
where he's gone on that first missionary journey
in the cities, sorry, the region of Galatia.
Those four churches that were established,
those Judaizers are coming
and all these things are happening.
And they have this council at Jerusalem.
Paul is not having it.
Why?
Because he understands that there's nothing
that gets added to grace.
Grace alone, faith alone, Jesus alone, amen.
It's not Jesus plus anything.
It's not Jesus and my circumcision,
Jesus and, no, no, no, no.
Because they were saying,
except you be circumcised after the manner of Moses,
ye cannot be saved.
But Paul was preaching a gospel that didn't include
go be circumcised after the manner of Moses.
It was believe on the Lord Jesus Christ
and thou shalt be saved.
Hallelujah.
And so what has happened here in Acts chapter 15,
notice in verse number nine, the Bible says this,
and put no difference between us and them,
purifying their hearts by faith.
Who's the us, who's the them?
The Jews and the Gentiles.
That's who it is.
And so we find in chapter 17,
notice what the Bible says in Acts chapter 17.
Now we come to, as Paul is continuing here,
his missionary journeys and he's going forth
and we find that he's been there,
he's kinda kicked out as we find to start the chapter
in Thessalonica, Berea, and he's kinda ushered out
and he's there and the Bible says
that he was waiting for them and he's at Athens
and his spirit was stirred in him.
Why?
I don't know.
that was wholly given to idolatry.
He says that he goes forth and he sees
all of these particular images and he finds this
where it says that he has this inscription
as he passed and beheld your devotions,
I found an altar that said this to the unknown God
whom therefore you ignorantly worship.
He says him declare I unto you.
He preached Christ.
And notice what he says in verse 26.
Well, I'll read verse 24 because he says
he's declaring God unto them.
He says in verse 24, God that made the world
and all things therein.
We know what God he's talking about, right?
Amen?
Jehovah, our God.
We find that he's speaking here.
He's making it abundantly clear.
They have a city wholly given to idolatry,
all of these false little G gods.
And he says the one that you're ignorantly worshiping,
I'm gonna declare him unto you.
He is the God that made the world in the beginning.
God said, praise God, the power that was displayed
in Genesis chapter number one.
And we find that here he says he made the world
and all things therein,
seeing that he is Lord of heaven and earth,
dwelleth not in temples made with hands,
neither is worship with men's hands
as though he needed anything,
seeing he giveth to all life and breath and all things
and hath made, what does it say?
Of one blood, all nations of men
for to dwell on all the face of the earth
and hath determined the times before appointed
and the bounds of their habitations.
I'm thankful for the truth of God's word
that expels partiality.
When you truly understand the Bible
and you truly understand biblical Christianity
and you have your faith, your belief impact your behavior,
it will expel partiality.
That's what will happen.
And we find that Paul says that he's made
the God who created all things,
the God who is the creator,
the God that needs nothing,
the God who is the self-sufficient one,
that he hath made of one blood all nations of men
for to dwell on all the face of the earth.
Can I tell you this morning it's the enemy
that wants to divide.
It's the enemy that gives lies and divisions
and all these types of things
and we find that it's God that gives clarity.
In the book of Romans we find that in chapter two
in verse number 11 that God tells us once again
that our God is no respecter of persons
and aren't you thankful again
that he is no respecter of persons.
In chapter 10, Romans chapter 10,
we're so familiar with verse 13
for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord
shall be saved and I'm thankful for that
but in verse number 12 it says this,
for there is no difference between the Jew and the Greek
for the same Lord over all is rich
unto all that call upon him.
You can't take the gospel to the wrong address.
Amen?
You just can't do it.
God desires for all men to be saved.
He's not willing that any should perish
but that all should come to repentance
and we find here this partiality expelled.
Let me just read for you in Revelation chapter number five
and I hope as we're gonna circle back to verse one
and be done but look in Revelation chapter five
just very quickly before we circle back to James chapter two
and finish up the message this morning.
In Revelation chapter five in verse number eight
and I just preached through this
a couple of Sunday nights ago,
three weeks ago I believe it was.
It says in verse number eight,
when he had taken the book and the four beasts
and four and 20 elders fell down before the lamb
having every one of them harps and golden vials
full of odors which are the prayers of saints.
Notice verse number nine.
And they sung a new song.
By the way, this is a scene in heaven, amen.
It's what this is in the throne room of heaven.
Verse nine, and they sung a new song saying,
thou art worthy to take the book
and to open the seals thereof
for thou was slain and has redeemed us to God by thy blood.
Notice this, out of every kindred and tongue
and people and nation.
Hallelujah.
Heaven is gonna be a wonderful place.
Yes, because Jesus is there,
but I want you to know that all the redeemed
throughout all the world and throughout all the ages
are gonna be gathered together
in that beautiful, wonderful place.
And hallelujah.
Listen, I'm excited about how the Bible
gives us instruction for daily living.
What a blessing.
Notice he said this in James two in verse number one.
He made this appeal to these that he's writing to
and to us as well by way of preservation.
He says, my brethren,
have not the faith of our Lord Jesus Christ,
the Lord of glory, with respect of persons.
What is he saying there?
Listen, you say that you follow the Lord Jesus Christ.
You say you're a disciple of his.
You say that you have that same belief,
that same body of teaching.
You have the faith of our Lord Jesus Christ,
he says this, my brethren,
have not the faith of our Lord Jesus Christ,
the Lord of glory, but notice, with respect of persons.
He's gonna take that finger
and deal with something very specific
that we've dealt with through the whole message this morning
the subject of partiality.
And why does he make an appeal back
to the Lord Jesus Christ?
Because as I've already noted to you
in John chapter number four,
and we'll finish there this morning,
but look in John chapter number four.
Listen, everything, every single thing
that our God has ever done has been on purpose.
He makes no mistakes, there's nothing that's done
without an understanding and a knowledge of why.
Listen, there are times, have you ever done something
and somebody said, why do you do that?
And you're like, I have no idea.
Have you ever done something and said,
that was a bad, like I wasn't thinking.
Joseph got some candy, and I'm trying not to eat candy,
and he got some candy, he had three bags of candy
on our island in our kitchen.
And I said, bud, what is this?
He said, that's a bad decision.
Yes, it was, and it tasted good.
I didn't eat all three bags, but I did try it.
And I said, man, it's better if it's not here, amen?
But that was, it was a funny response, a bad decision.
Listen, Jesus always did with purpose, on purpose.
He moved with purpose.
In John chapter number four,
you're familiar with the passage.
He says this in verse number four,
and he must needs go through Samaria.
I'm sure you've heard the passage.
You're familiar with it, but let me just,
in case you're not, the Jewish people in that day
would go out of their way to avoid Samaria.
They would go around.
They would make their journey longer,
more exhausting, more difficult,
because they would not go through Samaria.
Why?
Because the Jews hated the Samaritans.
Jesus deals with it right here.
They hated the Samaritans.
But I want you to understand that Jesus loves everyone.
And as God's people, partiality is expelled
by biblical Christianity when we live like Jesus.
He said, y'all are claiming to be like Jesus,
but you have partiality in your heart.
It ought not be.
I'm gonna explain it, I'm gonna expose it,
and then I'm gonna tell you how to have it expelled.
Get rid of it.
It's sin.
Confess it, forsake it.
He says as you go through the passage of Scripture
that he meets a woman at the well.
By the way, this woman was living with somebody
that wasn't her husband, had had five husbands,
but God loved her.
And God revealed himself to her
in this journey, in this interaction.
The disciples had left to go get some food,
and they come back and they see Jesus
talking to the Samaritan.
What is going on?
This is not normal, this is not our practice.
But we find that through the text,
and I'm just gonna try to summarize it quickly,
we find that she recognizes because Jesus says to her
in verse 26, I that speak unto thee am he.
Well, what did she ask?
She said, the woman saith unto him,
I know that Messiah's cometh.
He is the Messiah, he is the Lord Jesus Christ.
So what does she do?
She gets all excited and she runs home.
Says, come, let me show you a man
that told me all things ever I've done.
And then as they're coming, we find that Jesus,
the disciples come back, and she brings these people,
and as Jesus is speaking to the disciples,
catch the context in verse 35.
Jesus says, say not ye, there are yet four months,
and then cometh the harvest.
Behold, I say unto you, lift up your eyes
and look on the fields, for they are white already
to harvest, and it tells us that there's a great number
of Samaritans that are coming to where Jesus is,
and I believe that Jesus said, look, there's a harvest.
Talk about those Samaritans coming.
Listen, the gospel's for every single person.
Why do we support missionaries all around the world?
Because the gospel's for every single person.
Every person, God died for, and He loves, and He wants the gospel to go forth.
Do you believe that this morning?
I believe that.
James is dealing with something that's taking place at the congregation in the assembly.
And he says, let me, I'm going to give you an explanation to try to expose this for you.
I'm going to give you something that's very clear and relatable.
Two people walk in, very opposite ends of the spectrum from your perspective, and here's
how you behave, and your behavior reveals a heart problem, partiality in your heart.
It's sin, and it must be dealt with.
I think if James came and said, you guys are partial, then we're not partial, not here.
He says, let me show you what it looks like.
Listen, let God search our hearts.
There should be no partiality in any of our hearts.
Amen?
Zero.
Because the answer to partiality is biblical Christianity.
And if we really believe what this book says, and we're going to live it out, there will
be no partiality.
Amen?
To God be the glory.
I'm thankful for the example of the Lord Jesus Christ.
I'm thankful for all those portions of Scripture that we can look to, and we say, listen, heaven's
going to be a wonderful place because it's going to be so diverse.
By the way, let me just say this.
Our congregation is so diverse, and I love it.
I think it's awesome.
In fact, I was with Brother Somerdorf, and we had breakfast together, and he said, he
invited somebody to church, he said, their church is like heaven.
He said, because, and he explained to me later, he said, every tongue, every nation, every
tribe, listen, that's what the church is supposed to look like.
Why?
Because there's two groups of people, saved and lost.
Saved and lost.
I believe it.
We live it out.
Partiality will be exposed when we live out biblical Christianity.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for your word.
God help us to be honest this morning before you.
God search us.
Our hearts can be deceitful.
We know that.
They're desperately wicked.
God help us to expel partiality from our lives, if any of us are guilty this morning.
Help us to acknowledge this sin, to deal with it, confess it, and forsake it.
Lord, help us to love as you loved.
Help us to serve as you serve.
Lord, help us to live out our faith that what we believe would be evidenced in how we behave.
Would you work in hearts and lives, God, as we've heard your word this morning, we've
read your word this morning, God help us now to respond to your word that we'd be doers
and not hearers.
Well thank you for all that's done, for it's in Christ's name we pray.