our responsibility to share the gospel,
but also our approach or how we are going
to follow this process of fulfilling
what God has given us to do.
Last week, specifically, we talked about
how we can purposefully engage people with the gospel.
Matthew 4, 19, Jesus said,
follow me and I will make you fishers of men.
And this is part three.
I mentioned last week that oftentimes,
and what we're gonna do this evening
is go through all the verses
and share the verses that we would use
when we're speaking to somebody about the gospel.
I mentioned last week,
I made a reference to the Roman's road.
It's a popular term that many of us
might be familiar with someone using that term.
And the reality is that we believe
in the power of God's word, amen.
We believe that God's word is powerful
and we believe that God's word is profitable
and we believe those truths
and therefore we must use the Bible.
God's words are much more powerful than my words.
And so anytime I have an opportunity to speak with someone,
I like to be able to share some verses.
There are times in which you might be able to open a Bible
and be able to show them some verses
and read along with them,
but we really need to commit some verses to memory
that we would be able to share with them
and be able to use the sword of the spirit,
which is the word of God
and be able to share the truth with them.
And sometimes in the very beginning of the conversation,
I like to share John 14, six.
It's a great verse of scripture that Jesus said,
I am the way, the truth and the life.
No man cometh under the father, but by me.
And oftentimes I will use that verse of scripture
as an introduction kind of a verse,
getting right into it
and being able to share with them Christ.
And another verse of scripture that many people,
even in our spiritually, scripturally ignorant society,
John 3, 16 is a verse of scripture
that I have found over the years that people,
sometimes they know it, they're familiar with it,
they've heard it.
For God so loved the world
that he gave his only begotten son,
that whosoever believeth in him should not perish,
but have everlasting life.
And I wanna get those verses in.
Why?
Because God can use his word.
So even if my interaction with the individual
ends at that moment,
there's no opportunity to be able to go any further,
they're not interested, whatever it might be,
I've at least had an opportunity to share
some of God's word with them and God can use that.
The Holy Spirit uses the word.
And so what a unique opportunity.
Now, let me say this, oftentimes what happens
before I get into the verses of scripture,
people have this idea that I need to be well-versed
and trained so that no matter what the individual's
religious background is, I will know what they believe
and be able to counter that with Bible argument.
Can I tell you, that's just an approach
that doesn't work real well.
And why doesn't it work real well?
Because what happens far too often
is you begin having an argument
instead of sharing the gospel.
I will say this, Ronnie and I were knocking doors yesterday
and I was on the opposite, the receiving end of that
where the individual that we were talking to
made assumption about what we believe
because we're Baptist and he categorized us
and made some statements that just were not true.
And I know how that made me feel by hearing that
and now we were able to have a very good conversation
and it was profitable to an extent,
but the reality is that there was some mischaracterization
on the part of that individual because of some assumption
or something that he had heard somewhere
with regard to what we as Baptist people believe.
And pretty much he categorized Baptist
in the same category as any Protestant.
And he said this, he didn't use these words,
but basically what he said is that Protestants,
they just believe they can interpret the Bible
however they want.
That's not what I believe is a problem.
And first of all, we're not Protestants,
so I had to correct that misunderstanding.
We were never part of the Catholic church
and therefore we cannot be part of the Reformation
and the Protestant movement.
But needless to say,
I wasn't trying to have that discussion.
The reality is that we don't believe
that we can just interpret a passage of scripture
however we want, isogete it and just come up with some,
but the reality is that he had some truth
that he had experienced in his life
of seeing that how is it that one denomination
can take a passage of scripture
and interpret it a certain way,
and another denomination take the same passage of scripture
and interpret it a different way.
And that's an experience that he's had,
and so therefore he just makes this conclusion.
It is far better, instead of us trying to go
into the situation and take it from the approach of,
oh, they say they're fill in the blank,
whatever the religion is or the denomination is,
and that means here's what I'm gonna begin to say,
it's far better that we ask them and get information.
Remember last week one of the things I said
was ask questions, make inquiry.
Because when you begin to ask them,
then you're not just being able to make assumption
based on what a denomination teaches.
I have found this over the years.
Most people that you come in contact with
if you've done any amount of study,
you know more about what their denomination believes
than they do.
All right, unless, there are exceptions to the rule,
but rule of thumb, my experience,
years and years of knocking doors
and interacting with people,
I know more about what they supposedly believe than they do,
and the reality is that it's far more effective
to have them share with you what they believe.
I try to deal with the subject of going to heaven.
That's what we're most concerned about.
If you were to die today,
are you 100% sure that heaven is your home?
And that's what I'm trying to get to, why?
Because death is something that all of us
are going to face.
And so the question is, are you 100% sure?
Now, I've had repeatedly people look at me and say,
well, I mean, not 100% sure,
but you know, I'm fairly confident.
You know, I think so, I hope so, that sort of thing.
And so even if they say I'm 100% confident,
here's my response, that's wonderful.
Can you tell me how you know that?
And then guess what I'm getting?
I'm getting from them what they believe.
So now I understand from them personally,
not from whatever their religious background is
in making some level of assumption
that they must believe this,
because no, they're telling me what they believe,
and therefore I understand
where I should focus my attention on.
Most times, almost every religion of the world
teaches a work-based salvation.
All right, if you boil it down right there,
so there's two main issues.
Number one, they don't accept that Jesus Christ is God.
All right, that's one issue, most of the cults.
All right, the second issue is they believe
that salvation is somehow attained through our good works.
And sometimes it's a mix of faith and works,
but there's works included.
And so when we understand as they share those truths
with us, remember the power of your personal testimony.
I talked about that two weeks ago,
about making it personal.
So what do I do?
Well, there are times when I have an opportunity
to share my testimony, and I'll say something like this.
Now, I was never part of any kind of denomination.
We just didn't go to church as a child,
but here's what I kind of believed.
And I don't know, Brother Armando, where I got this,
where I picked it up from, but it's just kind of,
if you asked me prior to going to church
and hearing the gospel, if I were to go to heaven
when I die, I probably would have said, I hope so.
I think I had a pretty basic understanding
that there's heaven and hell,
and I didn't know a whole lot about anything more than that,
but I think I would have said, I hope so.
And if you asked me how I would have known,
I had in my mind this idea of really this big scale,
if you will, and it's good versus bad,
and if I've done more good than bad,
then I'm gonna make it.
That was kind of my idea, my thought.
And so I live life for a number of years thinking
that if I could be a good enough person
that somehow I could make my way to heaven.
Now, the problem with that is it's not biblical.
There's a lot of people that think that.
So as I'm sharing my testimony,
because I know my testimony,
I am able to, and I'm encouraging you
to know your testimony so that you can do the same thing,
is you can focus on certain aspects of your testimony
that will be able to, it's your testimony.
They can't argue with you
that what you're saying isn't true.
You're gonna say, listen, you know what?
There was a time in my life that, man,
I thought the same way.
I thought, man, if I could just be good enough,
if I could do enough good, man, I could make it to heaven.
But you know, I was reading the Bible.
Somebody shared Bible truth with me,
and I found out that the Bible says,
for by grace are you saved through faith.
Do you see how I just went right into a verse of scripture,
Ephesians 2, eight and nine,
and it says specifically, not of works,
lest any man should boast.
And I realized when I read that scripture,
when somebody shared that verse of scripture with me,
that I could not get to heaven by my own works.
I could not be good enough to get to heaven,
that if I could be,
then I would have reason to boast.
Look, I made it and you didn't.
But the reality is that it's not works, merit, salvation.
For by grace are you saved through faith.
It is all Jesus.
Amen.
Paid in full.
I know many of you this evening will not remember this.
Many of you will though.
There was a time in our society
before credit cards were as prevalent as they are today,
that there was a thing called layaway.
And some of you remember layaway.
And layaway was real popular at Kmart.
And some of you don't even know what Kmart is.
And Kmart had these things called blue light specials.
How many of you remember those, right?
You'd be in Kmart and they'd have blue light special,
aisle number whatever, right?
And my mom's mom was a Kmart fanatic, man.
She loved that place and she was all about layaway.
And my understanding is how layaway works
is you put the items that you want,
you put it in there and you put a little bit
of down money on it and then they keep it.
And then you have to go back in
and you have to keep on paying on it
and so on and so forth.
And then eventually you get the product
if you pay for all of it.
Now they just let you take a credit card
and pay however many percent your credit card has.
And you take the product with you
and you pay for it for,
hopefully you pay it off right away.
But if you don't, there are people that are paying
for the same pizza they ate 13 years ago
and they're still paying for it
because they just keep on racking up the credit card.
Our nation is in trouble with that.
But the reality is that that's not how salvation works.
Jesus didn't just make a down payment.
He paid it all.
And there's nothing I can do,
there's nothing anyone can do to earn salvation.
We are unworthy but because of his grace.
And so we try to get to that point.
So if you are interested in being able to learn
about some world religions and various denominations,
it's certainly, there's no benefit to it,
but it can present itself in a dangerous situation
where we become armed with information
and think, oh, we can win this argument.
Again, I've said it multiple times the last two weeks,
we're not trying to win arguments.
It's not about winning an argument.
Someone said, I met somebody
and they said that they were Pentecostal
and I didn't know what to say to them.
Somebody told me that just about three weeks ago
after doing door hangers.
And you know what I said to them?
I said, all you had to say is, oh, that's great.
Are you sure that you're going to heaven when you die?
And they'd probably say yes.
And then you'd say, okay, how do you know that?
And then they would give you an answer
based upon what they believe.
Now, I have an understanding
of what they probably would say,
but I don't wanna make the assumption for them.
I want them to tell me.
Does that make sense?
And so we're trying to have this conversation.
And then as I get into the gospel,
I'm gonna share the verses with you.
I'm not gonna read all the verses.
I'm gonna reference them so that you can jot them down.
If you need to be able to get a copy of these later,
please let me know.
I'll be happy to share them with you.
But the first thing when we're interacting with somebody
and we wanna be able to share the gospel with them
and lead them to Christ,
sometimes, here's what I say.
If they say, no, I don't know.
I say, listen, if I could take just a few minutes
and show you from the Bible, from God's word,
how you could know for sure that heaven is your home,
would you be willing to take a few minutes
and look at what God says in his word?
And then at that point,
I'm able to get into the verses of scripture.
And the first point that someone has to recognize,
number one, is they have to recognize that they're a sinner.
Listen, if we don't start with the acknowledgement of sin,
then there's no need for a savior.
Okay, so we have to acknowledge, we have to begin,
as it is written, Romans 3.10,
there's none righteous, no, not one.
Romans 3.23, for all have sinned
and come short of the glory of God.
So we begin there in the book of Romans,
Romans 3.10, Romans 3.23,
Romans 5.12 deals with the same thing
that while God demonstrated his love toward us
or commended his love toward us
and that while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us.
And so we deal with that truth
of the reality that we are sinners.
Now, it is important when you share
those verses of scripture,
the Bible says for all have sinned
and come short of the glory of God.
Does that mean you?
Ask that question.
Does that mean me?
I've said to a lot of people like, man, that means me.
When I wasn't the pastor, I said,
does that mean the pastor at the church?
Absolutely, it means the pastor of the church.
For all have sinned and come short of the glory of God.
The only one that has not,
that ever lived a life that was sinless
is the Lord Jesus Christ because he's God in flesh.
All other humanity has been guilty of sin.
Here's my experience.
No person I've ever spoken to
had a hard time acknowledging that they were a sinner.
Now they might say, well, I'm not really that bad.
I'm like, I didn't ask it what extent you're a sinner.
I just asked if you're a sinner, right?
Thou shalt not lie, all right?
Bear false witness.
The Bible says all men are liars, right?
Is that what it says?
And so the reality is that it is certain
that almost everyone you talk to you say,
have you ever told a lie?
You just deal right there, right?
And so most people will acknowledge that they're a sinner.
They don't have a hard time acknowledging that.
Number two, recognize you're a sinner, number one.
Number two, and before you go to number two,
you have to make sure they're tracking with you.
Make sure, hey, listen, you've already gotten their name.
David, do you believe that you are a sinner?
Yes, I believe that.
Okay, number two, they have to recognize
or realize that there is a penalty for sin.
There's a penalty, there's a consequence.
Most people, by the way, understand
and can relate to the fact that there are consequences
for breaking the law.
I oftentimes will talk about if someone goes out
on the highway and they are going excessively fast
and they pass a state police officer,
a county police officer, whoever it might be,
and they put the lights on and they get pulled over,
there's a consequence for their breaking of the law.
It's something that people can relate to
and they can understand.
So a sinner, all of humanity, has broken God's law.
And so therefore, we are guilty
and there is a penalty for sin.
Romans 6.23, for the wages of sin is death.
The wages of sin is death.
The rest of the verse, but the gift of God
is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord.
I oftentimes, when I'm at this particular point,
I stop at for the wages of sin is death.
I'm not gonna deal with the entirety of the verse yet.
I'm just gonna deal with that first point.
Why?
Because I want them to recognize and to accept the truth
that the wages of sin is death.
What does that mean?
Hebrews 9.27 is an important verse of scripture.
It goes out of the book of Romans,
but Hebrews 9.27, as it is appointed unto man,
wants to die, but after this, the judgment.
All right, and here's what I do.
Oftentimes, and I don't use my full Bible,
I use the New Testament,
but I hold my New Testament like this
so that they can read the verse, all right?
Now, I have these verses memorized,
and so I'm able to make sure if they read it wrong,
I'm like, hold on a minute, it's 9.27.
Make sure you're looking at that verse
and be able to make sure that they're getting it,
and that way, they're reading it for themselves.
I don't like just quoting all the verses to them.
Why?
Because I want them to see that this is God's word.
I mean, I could just rattle off
whatever I wanna rattle off,
and they don't know.
Now, the Holy Spirit can still use it if it's God's word,
but I want them to see this is God's word,
and God's word is authoritative,
and we deal with the fact that there's a penalty for sin.
So what is that penalty?
That penalty is death, for the wage of sin is death.
What is death?
What does it mean?
Well, it's not just a physical death,
but most importantly, it's a spiritual death.
That's the wage of sin.
Separation from God for all of eternity,
and death and hell, Revelation 20, verses 14 and 15,
we're cast in a lake of fire.
This is the second death.
Most people, when you talk to them about death,
all they really can think of is physical death.
They don't really have an understanding of spiritual death
or separation from God for all of eternity,
and so it's important that we deal with that,
and so then I'll ask somebody,
okay, so I understand that you believe that you're a sinner
and that there is a penalty for sin.
You are guilty, and the wage of sin is death.
Yes, I believe that.
I'm gonna make sure that they get it,
that they agree before I go to the next step,
and I often will say something like this.
Now listen, that's bad news, but the good news is coming.
You have to deal with the bad news
before you can deal with the good news,
because again, if you just start in Romans 10, 13,
for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord
shall be saved, it's a great verse of Scripture,
but why do I need to call?
If I don't know that I'm a sinner,
if I don't understand the penalty for sin,
what is the reason to call for a savior?
And so we deal with that truth, those first two thoughts
of the fact that you're a sinner
and that there is a penalty for sin.
Number three, realize, accept the truth
that Jesus died and rose again to pay for your sin,
to pay for your sin.
Romans 5, 8, but God commendeth his love toward us
and that while we're yet sinners, Christ died for us.
And I'm so thankful, the truth of 2 Corinthians 5, 21,
for he hath made him to be sin for us who knew no sin,
that we might be made the righteousness of God in him.
He took my place on the cross of Calvary.
He took your place on the cross of Calvary.
He paid a debt that he did not owe,
because I owed a debt that I could not pay, amen.
And I'm so thankful that he paid that debt.
How did he pay it?
Well, through his blood,
when he was hanging there upon the cross of Calvary.
his death, and then, of course, it's important
that we deal with the resurrection,
because that's proof that he is who he says he is
and that his sacrifice was acceptable,
and we look at the truth of the resurrection.
You could look at any of the gospel records.
I recommend Matthew 28, verses five and six,
because it's very concise, and you can just look
at those couple of verses, and so you deal with that,
and so you get to the point that, listen,
even though you're a sinner,
and even though there's a penalty,
a consequence for your sin, God loved you so much
that he took your place.
He paid for your debt.
He went to the cross of Calvary to pay for your sin
so that you could have eternal life,
and that's when you get to this thought,
really, this last thought,
is accept his free gift of salvation.
The Bible says in Romans 6, 23,
we read the first part in the second acknowledgement
of realizing that there's a penalty for sin,
for the wage of sin is death,
but the Bible continues that the gift of God
is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord.
I oftentimes will give the opportunity
to make a comparison between what is a wage
and what is a gift.
I love the fact that those two words are used,
because a wage is not a gift, and a gift is not a wage.
They're not the same thing.
A wage is something that we earn.
Most people that you talk to, they know what a wage is.
They go to work, they get paid,
they understand what a wage is.
They also understand what a gift is.
And if I say to someone, and I've used the illustration,
if I, hey, listen, my vehicle's dirty,
I need you to wash it for me,
and if you wash my car, I'll give you 30 bucks.
Nowadays, it's gotta be like probably 70 bucks, right,
because it's inflation, just everything's more expensive.
And is that a gift or is that a wage?
Well, that's a wage, like I gotta wash your car
before you give it to me, right?
Yeah, it's a wage.
But if I just hand you something,
whether it's money or something else,
and say, there's nothing you need to do for this,
it's just, I just want you to have it, it's a gift.
Now, the reality is that someone had to pay for the gift.
Right?
If you get a gift for Christmas,
you get a gift for your anniversary,
you get a gift for your birthday,
someone had to pay for that gift.
In this context, understanding that the gift of God
is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord,
he paid for the gift.
Now, something interesting about a gift
is that you have to accept it or receive it.
In our culture, it's not common
that gifts would be rejected,
but it certainly is a possibility.
Unfortunately, I've had people,
as I've gotten to this point even,
that have said, you know, I'm okay.
And it just makes my head spin.
Because I'm like, so you're rejecting the gift of God,
which is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord.
Now, I can't make them accept it,
and you can't make them accept it.
The Bible is very clear that salvation is a person,
an individual's decision that they have to make
to accept the Lord Jesus Christ as their personal Savior.
So, how do I get this gift?
How do I receive this gift?
If we look at Romans chapter number 10,
verse number 13, I mentioned it a couple of times
already this evening,
for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord
shall be saved.
What a wonderful verse of Scripture.
I've often said to people,
how do you call upon the name of the Lord?
Well, you pray.
You pray, and you acknowledge that you're a sinner.
You acknowledge that Christ is the only Savior,
that you're guilty as a sinner,
that there is that penalty,
that Christ is the only Savior,
and you accept that free gift of eternal life,
and you trust Him as your personal Savior.
I shy away from leading someone in a prayer.
I try to encourage people to pray themselves,
but there are times in which you may have
to lead somebody in a prayer.
They maybe don't know exactly what to say.
I always try to get them to pray out loud, all right?
Can you pray silently?
Absolutely, but I like them to pray out loud,
and Romans 10, verses nine and 10,
the Bible says that if thou shalt confess with thy mouth
the Lord Jesus, and shalt believe in thine heart
that God hath raised Him from the dead,
thou shalt be saved.
For with the heart man believeth unto righteousness,
and with the mouth confession is made unto salvation.
Now, with everything that I've shared this evening,
there's not one place that it says,
if you wanna go to heaven, go to church.
If you wanna go to heaven, get baptized.
If you wanna go to heaven, take the Lord's Supper.
If you wanna go to heaven, give to the church.
It's not there, it's not biblical.
There's only one way to heaven,
it's through the Lord Jesus Christ.
Now, if I'm saved, I should be baptized.
If I'm saved, I should give to the local church.
If I'm saved, I should attend the local church.
We understand those things, but that's not how I get saved.
I get saved through the Lord Jesus Christ,
through His death, burial, and glorious resurrection,
accepting Him as my Savior.
So I know I went through those verses
somewhat quickly this evening,
but that's kind of an outline
of how you would step-by-step go through it.
If there's no opportunity,
if the individual's like, you know what,
I'm not interested, I don't have time,
it's really busy, it's whatever,
get off my property, whatever they say.
If you have an opportunity
to at least share a verse of scripture,
it's the same, really, John 14, six is one
that I, it's just a go-to verse for me.
I'm the way, the truth, and the life.
No man cometh unto the Father but by me.
And I'll quote that sometimes in the very beginning.
If I don't have an opportunity, I quote it as well.
Hebrews 9, 27, as it's appointed unto man,
wants to die after this, the judgment.
And these are verses that we can be able to share with people
they might not even know that you're sharing
or quoting a Bible verse,
but the reality, as I mentioned last week,
is that we leave that conversation
and we can pray that God will use His word
to convict that individual.
The Holy Spirit, the Bible teaches us in John
that His ministry with regard to lost man
is to convict them, to convince them of three things,
of sin, of judgment, and of Christ's righteousness.
And so of sin, of Christ's righteousness,
and of judgment to come.
And so we understand that as we're able to share God's word,
as we're able to give the truth of God's word,
the Holy Spirit can use that.
All right, so I mentioned this last week.
Joseph, you can turn off live stream.
Goodbye to the live stream audience.
We're not gonna.