Evening, Genesis chapter 50, and tonight we'll be looking at verses 15 through 21.
Genesis 50, 15 through 21.
In the midst of our text this evening, Joseph makes a statement that is quite familiar to
many of us.
In fact, part of Genesis chapter number 50 is often quoted by God's people.
The part that's often quoted is,
Ye thought evil against me, but God meant it unto good.
That's not the whole verse, but that's the part that often is quoted.
I've used that part of the verse or part of that statement, God meant it unto good, as
our title for our message this evening.
As you recall from our message last Sunday evening, Jacob's final request, we understood
that the request was given, the request was granted after Jacob died at the end of chapter
49.
We find that the process of mourning was fulfilled, and then Joseph and his brothers,
they took a journey in order to bury their father, Jacob, in the place specifically that
he had given to them that he desired to be buried.
The Bible told us in verse 14, as we finished up the text last Sunday night, that Joseph
returned into Egypt.
He and his brethren and all that went up with him to bury his father, and after he had buried
his father, so they now returned to Egypt, Jacob, as we mentioned, was buried according
to his desire, and I think that the trip back to Egypt brought some mixed emotions to Joseph's
brothers.
As we begin our text of Scripture this evening, beginning in verse number 15, we see that
God gives us immediately some insight with regard to the conversation that takes place
amongst Joseph's brothers.
Notice in verse 15, the Bible says, "...and when Joseph's brethren saw that their father
was dead, they said, Joseph will peradventure hate us, and will certainly requite us all
the evil which we did unto him.
They sent a messenger unto Joseph, saying, Thy father did command before he died, saying..."
This is all fabricated, you understand that.
This is not actually what Jacob had commanded.
It says, "...so shall you say unto Joseph, Forgive, I pray thee now, the trespass of
thy brethren and their sin.
For they did unto the evil, and now, we pray thee, forgive the trespass of the servants
of the God of thy father.
And Joseph wept when they spake unto him, and his brethren also went and fell down before
his face, and they said, Behold, we be thy servants.
And Joseph said unto them, Fear not, for am I in the place of God.
But as for you, you thought evil against me, but God meant it unto good, to bring to pass
as it is this day, to save much people alive.
Now therefore, fear ye not, I will nourish you and your little ones.
And he comforted them and spake kindly unto them."
If you're taking notes this evening, I want you to notice, first of all, the concern of
Joseph's brethren.
The concern of Joseph's brethren.
For many years, Joseph's brothers lived knowing what they had, how they had sinned against
their brother, the evil that they committed against Joseph.
They lived for many years trying to suppress all of that.
And we understand that as they went into Egypt, they did not recognize Joseph.
But on that first entrance into the country of Egypt to find sustenance for their families,
we find that Joseph recognized his brethren.
We find that it was a series of events that transpired with them needing to take another
journey into Egypt, and eventually Joseph would reveal himself to his brothers.
And we've made note, as we've studied through the portion of Scripture, that when Joseph
had the opportunity to reveal himself in Genesis chapter 45, that his brothers, they were troubled
at his presence.
Why is it that they were troubled at his presence?
Well, they knew all that they did, and they understood that now Joseph standing in this
place of authority and power, they were fearful of what Joseph would do.
And Joseph called them near to himself and he comforted them.
And the Bible says in verse 5 of Genesis 45, now therefore be not grieved nor angry with
yourselves that ye sold me hither.
Then notice he said, for God did send me before you to preserve life.
He said, for these two years hath the famine been in the land, and yet there are five years
in the which there shall neither be earring nor harvest.
And again in verse 7, and God sent me before you to preserve you a posterity in the earth
and to save your lives by a great deliverance.
Then notice verse number 8, so now it was not you that sent me hither, but God.
When we studied through Genesis 45, we made note with regard to the perspective that Joseph
had, and certainly had a proper perspective on life and understanding all that had transpired.
As we come to Genesis chapter number 50, obviously many years have passed, it's in Genesis 46
that Jacob and the family all go into Egypt, and we understand that the Bible tells us
that Jacob was there for 17 years in the land of Egypt.
To the best of our knowledge, biblically speaking, what is revealed to us, there's
no time during those 17 years that anything with regard to past history is ever dealt
with.
It doesn't seem, it's never brought up in the dialogue that we read in the account of
the book of Genesis.
We find that there's 17 years there, all of those 17 years are not notated daily what
took place, but we do not have in Scripture of any record of these item, or these events
being discussed.
We find now that Jacob dies, Jacob is buried, and the brothers are concerned.
As we note the concern of Joseph's brethren, we see in verse number 15 what they thought.
Notice with me again, the Bible says that they recognized that their father was dead,
so here's what they think, here's the conclusion that they reach.
In verse number 15 they said, Joseph will peradventure hate us, and will certainly requite
us all the evil which we did unto him.
They almost have this perspective, if you will, that Joseph has dealt kindly with us
over these past 17 years that we've lived in Egypt solely because of the fact that Jacob
was alive.
And because of dad's presence, because of dad being here, Joseph really didn't say anything,
he didn't do anything with regard to the evil that we did unto him.
So they begin to think as they're journeying back to Egypt, imagine with me on that journey
back to Egypt, and knowing that you've just buried your father, and they have this belief
that now Joseph is going to requite them all of the evil which they did unto him.
They're concerned.
We find that they devise a plan.
We notice what they thought, but then we see what they did.
They send a messenger with a message.
It seems as if, as you look at the text in verses 17 and 18, that they're there in the
presence of Joseph as this message is being delivered to Joseph.
And basically as Joseph is receiving this message, it reveals again to us the measure
of concern that these brothers have with regard to what would happen to them, revenge
if you will, because dad is gone.
And they acknowledge the evil that they did to Joseph.
So here's the message that they give the messenger to deliver in verse 17.
Forgive, I pray thee now, the trespass of thy brethren and their sin.
For they did unto thee evil.
And now we pray thee, forgive the trespass of the servants of the God of thy father.
We find that they were seeking forgiveness.
They were seeking that they would not have retribution, that there'd be no revenge, that
there'd be no penalty if you would for that which they committed against Joseph.
And it's interesting because all the way back in Genesis 45, we mention the beautiful picture
of forgiveness.
We noted as we've looked at the names even of Joseph's children and how he mentions about
the way that God made him forget and God had blessed him, and understanding the fact that
Joseph was aware of God's plan.
Joseph was not allowing bitterness to have any place in his heart.
He was not angry with his brothers.
In fact, he forgave them and he had this restored relationship with them, but their concern
was that it was just kind of because dad was still there.
Now that dad's gone, how's Joseph really going to treat us?
But I want you to see that it was true forgiveness that Joseph had forgiven his brothers long
before this event in Genesis chapter 50.
In fact, the Bible says that Joseph wept when they spake unto him.
Joseph had already forgiven his brothers.
We mentioned about the beautiful picture of forgiveness.
We mentioned in previous messages with regard to the danger of bitterness, and in fact,
there are many people today that deal with bitterness and they have bitterness in their
heart.
And the reality is that Joseph was a man that he had learned to forgive.
His brothers, they were concerned.
The Bible tells us that.
brothers after the messengers deliver the message and Joseph weeps that his brethren
they went and fell down before his face and notice what they say, we be thy servants.
We be thy servants.
They were concerned it would be far better for them to live and be the servants of Joseph
than to die for the evil which they had committed so many years prior.
So we note the concern of Joseph's brethren but I want you to note number two, the confidence
of Joseph.
In verses 19 and 20 we see a man who has great confidence.
Confidence in himself?
No, confidence in his God.
By the way, we ought to be confident knowing that our God is in control.
We ought to be confident knowing what God's plan is and that God has a plan that is greater
than any of us individually and that God will bring to pass that which he desires to
bring to pass and the process by which he chooses to bring those things to pass is completely
up to him and within his control.
We find that Joseph says this in verse number 19, he said unto them, fear not for am I in
the place of God.
I begin to think about the confidence of Joseph and I notice in verse number 19 that Joseph
knew who he was and he knew who God was.
I'm thankful to know who God is.
Aren't you thankful to know that God is on his throne, that God is sovereign, that God
is a good God?
We ought to know what our place is.
Joseph is not in the place, he is not God, he understands that God is far greater than
he is.
We think about what Isaiah says as God is making it clear, your ways are not my ways
and your thoughts are not my thoughts.
God transcends us.
We find here this evening that as we look at verse 19 that Joseph is understanding not
only who he is but he understands who God is.
I wonder this evening, do we have a proper view of who God is?
Do we see God in his rightful place?
Do we see God high, holy and lifted up?
Do we really believe that God is in control?
Do we really believe that God makes no mistakes?
Do we really believe that God's ways are perfect?
Because all of those things that I just mentioned are biblical truths that we find within his
word.
But the reality is that at some point in your life and in my life, the Bible truths need
to be lived out in our daily lives.
It cannot be that we only say that God is good when things are going according to the
way that we want them to be.
It cannot be that we can say that God's way is perfect so long as it aligns with what
my way is.
No, God's way is perfect.
God truly makes no mistakes.
Do you believe that this evening?
I believe that.
And we find that Joseph had to understand this, this perspective, but he had great confidence.
And I wonder this evening how we do, how do we fare in the trials and the difficulties
in life and all that we deal with?
What is our confidence level with regard to understanding who God is?
Understanding that God has a plan.
See, my life is in God's hands and your life is in God's hands.
There are a lot of times in our lives that we might think that we're in control, that
we may think that we can go through life and we have the ability to manage various levels
of processes, but the reality is that our God alone is in control of all things.
Joseph continues to demonstrate his confidence in the Lord in verse number 20.
He says, but as for you, he looks at his brothers.
He says to them, ye thought evil against me.
Is that a true statement?
Absolutely.
They hated Joseph.
They could not speak peaceably unto Joseph.
They conspired to kill him and then chose to sell him into slavery instead of killing
him.
And Joseph says, ye thought evil against me.
And it could be in your life and in my life that we've had circumstances and situations
where people have thought evil against us.
They have planned and desired to cause great heartache and pain in your life.
But notice that Joseph does not end by simply exposing the evil intent of his brothers.
He continues and says, but God meant it unto good.
Can I tell you this evening, this is not a cliche.
This is a man who has great confidence in knowing intimately his God, in knowing the
ways that his God works and understanding the fact that our God is a sovereign God,
that He is in control of the affairs of mankind.
And we find that as we come to a text of Scripture like this, that the Bible says, but God meant
it unto good.
And He continues to bring to pass as it is this day to save much people alive.
If you think about the statement that is made in Genesis chapter 50 and verse number 20,
and you understand all that we have studied throughout these many weeks of looking at
the life of Joseph, we understand that all of those things that transpired were coming
to that very point where God would allow Joseph to have an audience before Pharaoh to interpret
a dream that could otherwise not be interpreted by any magician or any other wise man within
Egypt.
And Joseph not only was able by the grace of God and the ability of God to be able to
interpret the dream, but then give to Pharaoh a plan that would result in much people being
saved alive.
Otherwise, the great famine that would follow, the great years of plenty, would have had
a devastating impact on the population, not only in Egypt, but most especially in Canaan.
And so Joseph, when we know the confidence that he has in this text of Scripture, it
causes us to rejoice.
Why?
Because we can have confidence in who our God is.
We can be confident in knowing the plan that God has for your life and for my life.
Listen, Joseph did not have the Bible like we have the Bible.
You think about all that we have in this precious book and all that God has revealed to us,
that would help us to have confidence in knowing the plan that God has for us.
I want to draw your attention to two New Testament passages of Scripture.
First is in Romans chapter number 8.
Anytime you think of this passage here in Genesis chapter 50, often we would couple
it with the truth that we find in Romans chapter number 8.
It makes good sense to go from Genesis 50 to Romans chapter number 8 and to see the
connection between these two verses of Scripture.
Joseph makes this great declaration revealing his confidence that he has in his God.
And we find that Paul writes, and he says this in Romans 8 and verse 28, and I like
the first words, and we know.
I'm not sure how often I've heard Romans 8.28 quoted without quoting it completely.
So often I've heard Romans 8.28, all things work together for good.
But the Bible says, and we know.
That's powerful.
How is it that we know?
Well, because God has revealed to us in His word, His character, His nature, who He is,
the plan that He has.
Does it mean that we're never going to have a difficult day?
No, it does not mean that whatsoever.
But we find that as we come to Romans chapter 8 and verse 28, the Bible says, and we know
that all things work together for good to them that love God, to them who are the called
according to His purpose.
What a precious verse of Scripture.
You say, well, this right here looks like a mess to me.
I don't know how anything good is going to come out of it.
You just keep trusting the Lord.
You just keep doing what's right, and you let God be God.
And do you think Joseph, for two years, he's left in the prison, right?
Forgotten.
But God's timing was perfect.
God's plan was coming just as He had designed it to come.
We find that the Bible tells us that we know.
Do you have the confidence today, tonight, as you face the uncertain times that you face
in your life, that we face in our lives collectively, corporately, as a people, as a nation?
So often you will hear people make statements about various things.
And so long as the things are positive or to their liking,
they'll make statement with regard to God being in control
and God put that person there or God did this.
But when it doesn't fit what they want it to be
or what they think should be,
all of a sudden it's not God who put them there.
God is sovereign.
God is in control.
I can't tell you how many times, and I hate to bring it up,
I don't like dealing with so many political type of things
and you know that, but I can't tell you how many times
I heard we're getting ready to have another election cycle,
get ready for all of the rhetoric again.
But our hope is not in the White House.
You understand that?
Our hope is in Jesus.
Amen?
But so many people talking about stealing an election,
this, that, changing, so on and so forth.
Listen, God rules in the affairs of mankind.
And even if all of that stuff happened,
God allowed it to happen.
We either believe God's in control or we don't.
Plain and simple.
You can't have it that God's in control
so long as everything goes the way that you want it to go
and then all of a sudden God must not be in control
when it doesn't go the way that you want it to go.
Amen?
God's in control.
By the way, I'm thankful that God's in control
because God, he knows all things.
He is the only one that should be in control.
And we ought to readily allow him to have control.
Joseph had great confidence.
Let me take you to another New Testament verse of Scripture.
In 2 Corinthians chapter five,
we speak about having confidence
with regard to the affairs of life
and to the events that would transpire in your life
and in my life as we see it in Joseph's life
here in Genesis 50, as he's looking back
at those evil things that his brothers did to him.
But he says, God meant it unto good.
God had a plan.
God had a purpose.
God is sovereign and my life is in the hands of my God.
But I want you to notice when we think about
this subject of confidence,
I want you to see what Paul says
in 2 Corinthians chapter five with regard to confidence.
We sang this evening about the truth of Calvary.
We sang this evening about blessed Redeemer
and what a wonderful Redeemer he is.
We sang this morning, it's a song that asks a question,
are you washed in the blood,
the soul cleansing blood of the Lamb?
I often will say in the chorus of that song,
when it says, are you washed
and you hold it out in the blood,
I'll say, yes, I am kind of as a repeat, if you will.
I don't know what the right musical term is,
but man, I'm thankful to be washed in the blood,
to know that I've been saved by the grace of God.
Notice what Paul says with regard to his position in Christ
beginning in verse number one of 2 Corinthians five.
Notice these words, for we know.
Now, we made note of Romans eight and 28
and we talked about the start and we know.
Here, Paul says, for we know.
Notice what it says, that we know,
that if our earthly house of this tabernacle were dissolved,
what does he mean by that?
When we die, to make it real plain and simple,
that this earthly house of this tabernacle were dissolved.
We have a building of God
and house not made with hands, eternal in the heavens.
For in this, we groan earnestly,
desiring to be clothed upon with our house,
which is from heaven.
If so be that being clothed, we shall not be found naked.
For we that are in this tabernacle do groan, being burdened.
Not for that we could be unclothed, but clothed upon.
Notice what he says, that mortality might be swallowed up
of, what does it say?
Life, not swallowed up of death, of life.
Because he's talking about being saved
and having confidence of being saved.
Verse number five, now he that hath wrought us
for the self, same thing as God,
who also hath given unto us the earnest of the spirit.
If you look at Ephesians one, we don't have time to go there
but we find that the Holy Spirit of God
is given to the child of God at the moment of salvation
and he is the earnest of our inheritance.
We talk about being, that we have been indwelled
by the Holy Spirit of God.
But verse six says, therefore, notice this,
we are always, do you see the word confident?
Knowing that whilst we are at home in the body,
we are absent from the Lord.
For we walk by faith, not by sight.
What's he saying here?
Well, listen, as long as we're in this body,
we're absent from the Lord.
I'm not in heaven in his presence, I'm here.
Now we understand that God is everywhere.
We just talk about the omnipresence of God
but we see that he says we walk by faith, not by sight.
But then notice the contrast, he says,
that we're confident in verse number six,
that if we're here in this body, in this tabernacle
that we have, that we're absent from the Lord.
But then notice verse number eight.
We are confident, I say, and willing,
rather to be absent from the body
and to be present with the Lord.
Wherefore, we labor that whether present or absent,
we may be accepted of him.
So verse number eight is a verse that we often will quote
in 2 Corinthians chapter five, verse number eight,
to be absent from the body is to be present with the Lord.
But we know that Paul says that we are confident,
not only confident, but he says willing,
rather to be absent from the body
and to be present with the Lord.
We talk about the confidence of Joseph
as we see in Genesis chapter number 50.
I wonder this evening, two aspects of confidence
in the life of a believer.
Number one, are you confident that God is in control
of the affairs of your life?
Are you confident of that this evening?
That God rules, that God reigns, that God is in control,
that God has a plan, that God's way is perfect,
that God makes no mistakes.
You know who often messes it up?
The person you look at in the mirror.
We're the ones that mess it up, amen?
But I wonder tonight, are you confident of heaven?
To be absent from the body is to be present with the Lord.
This was confidence.
Paul starts the fifth chapter of 2 Corinthians,
for we know, a confidence.
Listen, so often I hear people,
as I talk to them about their soul and about heaven,
well, I hope so.
I hope I could make it.
I hope I could be good enough.
I hope I could, listen, we can know,
and I know most of you do.
I'm thankful this evening for the confidence that we have,
that we'll see Him face to face,
go through life every day with that measure of confidence.
To be absent from the body is to be present with the Lord.
I don't know when I'm gonna die.
You don't know when you're gonna die,
but we know that death could take place at any moment.
Right, we know that.
People die, I don't know, I can't remember
what the numbers are, it changes all the time,
but people around the globe, I mean, every second,
20 people die or something, it's a crazy number.
It's crazy how many people die every day.
We need to be confident of heaven.
If you don't have that confidence,
oh, we love that today would be the day of your salvation.
We note the concern back in Genesis 50,
the concern of Joseph's brethren.
We note the confidence of Joseph.
Notice finally with me this evening, number three,
note with me the compassion of Joseph.
I love verse 21.
I see the compassion of a man who'd been wronged.
Sometimes even as believers,
sometimes we have a hard time treating people nice
that treat us nice, yet alone,
somebody that doesn't treat us very nice, amen?
But Joseph had been wronged,
but he understood that God was in control,
that you meant it unto evil, but God meant it unto good.
God had a plan.
His plan was to bring to pass,
as it is this day, to save much people alive.
And God has me, had me exactly where I was supposed to be.
And we find that he responds to his brethren
in verse 21 with a great measure of compassion.
They say, behold, at verse 18, we be thy servants.
And Joseph says, fear ye not.
In verse 21, then notice what he says.
I will nourish you and your little ones.
Wow, what compassion?
I mean, we read that previous in the account of Joseph
when dad was still alive back in Canaan
and Joseph was gonna send his brothers
to go bring his dad back and he says,
come back and I'm gonna take care of you
and I'm gonna nourish you.
But now dad is gone, dad has died.
The brothers think surely he's gonna requite us
for the evil that we did unto him
and we're gonna be his servants.
We'd be better to be a servant than to die
and this is a bad thing and dad is gone
and we don't know what's gonna happen.
And Joseph says, fear not.
I will nourish you and your little ones.
Isn't that precious?
To think about the compassion that Joseph has towards his brothers.
It says in verse 21 that he comforted them.
I don't know, the Bible doesn't give all the specifics as to how he comforted them, but
it seems as if he comforted them through more than just words because the next statement
tells us that he spake kindly unto them and maybe as he did in chapter 45, he drew them
near to himself and he comforted them, perhaps he embraced them and he hugged on them, if
you will, and we find that he comforted them and then the Bible says that he spake kindly
unto them.
I made mention earlier, but we find that in Joseph's life that even his brothers, that
they hated him, according to Genesis 37 and verse number 4, that they could not speak
peaceably unto him.
And now Joseph, as he speaks these words to them of, fear ye not, I will nourish you and
your little ones, he comforted them and he spake kindly unto them.
What a beautiful picture of compassion and forgiveness, a man that understood who God
is and who he is, understood that God has a plan and God's plan is perfect and sometimes
as we've seen the life of Joseph, God allowed Joseph to see the plan, to understand what
God was doing.
You know, at times in your life and in my life, we may not fully understand what God
is doing, maybe years before we understand what God is doing.
It may not be on this side of eternity that we find out what God was doing and how God
was working and why God was working how he was.
But we must rest in the fact that we understand that God is sovereign and God is good.
God has a plan.
I noticed that phrase that he spake kindly unto them.
The New Testament were given some, actually throughout the scriptures, but the New Testament
couple of verses were given some instruction with regard to our words.
In Ephesians chapter 4, turn there quickly if you will, we'll look at two verses and
be done.
Ephesians 4, it's a passage of scripture that deals with the put off and put on principle.
We find that God addresses our speech in verse 29, he, Joseph, spake kindly unto them.
In Ephesians 4 and verse 29, the Bible says, let no corrupt communication proceed out of
your mouth, but that which is good to the use of edifying, that it may minister grace
unto the hearers.
What a great verse of scripture that we can use our words to build up, to edify.
That we can use our words in such a way that it ministers grace unto the hearers.
Have you ever heard someone speak kindly?
Speak graciously?
That's how we are to speak.
Colossians 4 and verse number 6 says, let your speech be always with grace, seasoned
with salt that you may know how you ought to answer every man.
Let your speech be always with grace.
That's a great piece of instruction that's given to us with regard to our speech, seasoned
with salt, that you may know how you ought to answer every man.
This evening we see the compassion of Joseph.
He tells them to fear not, he tells them that he will nourish not only them but their little
ones and he comforted them and then he spoke kindly unto them.
This evening, just as Joseph demonstrated grace and compassion, we too as the people
of God need to be a compassionate people, a people that show grace, kindness.
The Bible speaks of our Savior that he is a God who is moved with compassion.
As we note here in this text of scripture, we see Joseph's response.
The boys, the brothers, as they travel back from burying dad, they're concerned.
What's going to happen now that dad is gone?
I mean, surely Joseph is going to, I mean, he's going to requite us for the evil that
we did unto him.
I mean, this is a bad situation for us and they devise this plan.
They thought that something bad would happen to them and so they have these messengers
go and offer these words that Jacob spoke before he died with regard to forgiving and
they offer themselves as being Joseph's servants.
Joseph says, no, no, no.
He weeps before them.
He says, I know who God is and I know who I am and I know that God is a gracious God,
a sovereign God and I know that God has a plan and I am confident that God was at work.
Though ye meant it unto good, excuse me, unto evil, God meant it unto good.
God was at work.
Listen, God's at work in our lives.
We may not always see exactly how God is at work.
You may think tonight, man, I got a mess.
What do you mean God's at work?
Just go back and read the life of Joseph.
There were times in his life where, I mean, he didn't know what was going to happen on
the next day.
He didn't know that he was going to go from the prison to the palace.
He didn't know that.
He was just daily walking with God, trusting the Lord and he had confidence that God was
in control.
This evening, do you have confidence that God's in control of your life?
Have you placed your life in His hands?
Allow Him to have His will and His way.
Lord use me for your honor and for your glory.
Do in me what you see fit.
I trust you, Lord.
I have confidence that you're a good God and you do all things well.
We spoke of that confidence of heaven in 2 Corinthians 5.
Tonight, I don't want you to leave here without having confidence that heaven is your home.
Not hoping, but knowing, knowing.
Spoke with a man at his door a few weeks ago and as I spoke to him at his door, he said,
well, yeah, I mean, I want to go to heaven.
I hope I go to heaven.
I mean, he kind of gave the impression that doesn't everybody want to go to heaven.
He said, I just don't know.
I'm trying to figure all that out.
I'm just hoping that I could get to heaven.
I said, well, you don't have to hope, you can know, you can have confidence that heaven
is your home.
Not because of anything that you do, but all because of what Jesus did.
Isn't that wonderful to have that kind of confidence?
Joseph demonstrates great confidence in this text of Scripture and then he's compassionate.
Oh, that God would help us as His people to be a compassionate people, to speak with grace,
to speak kind words, to edify, to build up, to encourage, to minister grace unto the hearers.
God would help us to be compassionate people.
What a great picture that we see in the life of Joseph of how we as believers should behave.
He didn't have anything like we have with regard to the whole canon of Scripture and
yet he lived a life that was exemplary.
We still today study it and see from this man's life how we ought to live our lives.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the life of Joseph.
We thank you, God, for this portion of Scripture that reveals to us the concern that his brothers
had but then, Lord, we see the confidence and the compassion of Joseph and God, I pray
that you'd help us to live with the kind of confidence that Joseph had, Lord, help
us to know that you're in control.
We believe what you've told us in your word and I pray that you would help us to live
every day with that measure of confidence.
Help us to be compassionate people.
God, if there's someone here tonight that's not sure of heaven, I pray the Holy Spirit
of God would work and draw that individual to you, Lord, that they might be saved.
I pray that you'd move and work as only you can and we'll thank you for it.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano.