special music this morning, I didn't want you to be afraid that I was going to sing
this morning, thus I shared with you my experience yesterday in kindly declining the opportunity
even there yesterday, but I will spare you this morning as well.
First Timothy 2, verses 4 through 7, and thankful for God's Word, the Bible says this,
Who will have all men to be saved, and to come unto the knowledge of the truth?
For there is one God, and one mediator between God and men, the man Christ Jesus, notice
verse 6, who gave himself a ransom for all, to be testified in due time, whereunto I am
ordained a preacher, an apostle, I speak the truth in Christ, and, lie not, a teacher of
the Gentiles in faith and verity.
In the midst of this exhortation on prayer, remember he begins in verse number 1, I exhort
therefore that first of all supplications, prayers, intercessions, and giving of thanks
be made for all men.
And then as we looked at it last week, the Holy Spirit of God zeroed in on this truth
for kings and for all that are in authority.
I hope you prayed for our leaders last week, and I mentioned to you that I jotted down
the names.
One person contacted me for the websites that I referenced, and they said, well, that just
added 12 names to my prayer list, and I said, well, praise the Lord.
And I prayed for our leaders this week by name, and I hope that you have as well.
And we find that in the midst of this exhortation that God gives us on the subject matter of
prayer, right in the midst of it we find that God reveals His will for humanity.
Often we hear people talk about God's will.
No doubt you've mentioned at some point the will of God or God's will, and we understand
what we mean by that.
And I am thankful that God has preserved His word for us so that we can know His will.
See, this morning we do not have to reach our own conclusions regarding the will of
God.
We go to the Word of God, and we understand that in the Word of God, God has revealed
to us who He is, who we are, and what His will is for humanity.
Knowing the will of God will impact how we behave.
Knowing the will of God will impact our worldview.
You know, there are people today, they talk about your worldview and seeking to influence
your worldview or shape or mold your worldview.
They'll use that type of terminology.
Listen, it's the Bible, it's the will of God that should mold and shape our worldview.
And we find that as we look at this passage of Scripture, it seems very obvious to me
that knowing the will of God will influence how we pray.
Right in the midst of the exhortation on prayer, it's almost like it's a parenthetical statement
in verses 4 through 7, and in the midst of this exhortation on prayer, God reveals to
us His will for humanity, why?
Because God's will will influence how we pray.
Knowing the will of God influences your prayer life and my prayer life.
Hold your place here, let me read to you 1 John chapter number 5.
In 1 John chapter 5, many of us are familiar with verse number 13, and speaking about the
assurance of salvation and what a precious verse that is.
But in 1 John chapter 5, in verse number 14, the Bible says this, and this is the confidence
that we have in Him, that if we ask anything according to His will, He heareth us.
And if we know that He heareth us, whatsoever we ask, we know that we have the petitions
that we desired of Him.
And so we find that in 1 John 5, 14, we have this truth of we're to pray according to the
will of God.
And so in the midst of this exhortation on prayer, God reveals to us His will for humanity.
I've titled the message, as you see in the bulletin this morning, God's will for humanity.
As we look at these few verses of Scripture, I want to share three thoughts with you this
morning from this portion of Scripture that I believe God is giving us that will help
us shape our worldview, influence our behavior, and influence our prayer lives when we understand
this is God's will.
With me this morning, notice number one, if you will.
God's will is for lost people to be saved.
Have you ever prayed or have you ever heard someone pray, Lord, if it would be your will,
would you save them?
No, you don't need to pray that way.
We know that it's God's will.
God does not arbitrarily save them.
They have to accept the gift that He offers.
But we can be confident this morning that it is God's will that lost people are saved.
Why do we go and preach the gospel?
Why do we pass out gospel tracts?
Why do we, well, because we know it's God's will for lost people to be saved.
Remember this morning, there are two groups of people in the world.
There are people that are lost and there are people that are saved.
As you boil it all down, if you look at it all, you come to the very end of it, you say
there are two groups of people in the world, saved people and lost people.
Those of us this morning, I'm in the category of being saved, amen?
I've been saved by the blood of Christ.
Heaven is my home, no doubt about it.
Jesus is mine, I am His, hallelujah.
I am so thankful for the truth of salvation.
I've been born again by the Spirit of God through the blood of Christ.
Praise the Lord for knowing that you're saved.
But remember, for every one of us this morning that are saved, there was a time that we were
lost.
So everyone that's in that category of being saved, at one point you were in the category
of being lost.
And if you say, no, I was born saved, you need to be saved.
You need to be born again, amen?
On the authority of God's Word, why?
Because you're not born saved, you're born lost.
You're born at enmity with God.
In fact, Ephesians chapter number two explains that in great detail with regard to we all
had our conversation in times past.
We all were in that same condition of being lost.
But we notice here in this portion of Scripture, in verse number four, notice what the Bible
says in 1 Timothy 2 and verse number four, who will have, notice what it says, all men
to be saved and to come unto the knowledge of the truth.
Why do I say this is God's will for the humanity when we look at God's will for lost people
to be saved?
Because it says, who will have all men to be saved.
Now it doesn't mean that all men are going to be saved.
It simply means that his will is for all men to be saved.
There's not one person that can stand at the great white throne judgment of God and say,
you were not willing to save me.
Not one person can stand there and say that.
No, Jesus died for the world.
In fact, look at verse number six, who gave himself a ransom.
What does it say?
For all.
For how many?
And we see in verse number four, who will have how many men?
All men.
Verse number six, who gave himself a ransom for how many?
For all to be testified in due time.
And so we find in verse number four, and again in verse number six, this word all that is
so important for us to understand.
And we find that God says that he will have all men to be saved.
He gave himself Jesus Christ when he hung upon the cross of Calvary.
He was paying for the sin of humanity.
He was paying for your sin, and for my sin, and for your neighbor's sin, and for your
parents' sin, and your children's sin, and your…
He was paying for the sin of mankind.
By the way, we find that Calvinism with its teaching of unconditional election and a limited
atonement are exposed as being false teaching by these simple verses of Scripture.
I want you to understand this morning, and I know it's not popular, but it's biblical
that this idea of Calvinism is creeping into our churches all across this land.
It's creeping into our Bible colleges, into our seminaries, and it's creeping into the
pews and into the pulpits of America.
It's a problem.
The reason that it's a problem is because Calvinism doesn't align with the Bible.
And let me tell you, you can go to the internet and you can find a lot of Calvinistic preachers.
You can find a lot of them that align with Calvinism.
And the problem is that the Bible teaches something different.
The Bible doesn't teach unconditional election.
The Bible doesn't teach limited atonement.
We're not looking at all of the tenets, if you will, of Calvinism, but in just three
verses of Scripture, those two tenets are exposed as being false teaching.
And we find that what happens is Calvinists have to get very creative, and they say, well,
all doesn't really mean all.
You'll hear that repeatedly.
When you look at Ephesians chapter number one, understand with me this morning, we do
not have to be afraid of the Word that God uses in His Word.
Look at it actually with me in Ephesians 1.
We don't have to be fearful of this.
We do not have to be fearful of using the Word predestinated.
God's Word uses that Word.
But we have to be afraid of the Word that God uses in His Word.
have to understand the context of what God uses it with.
In Ephesians chapter one, notice the Bible says
in verse number three,
blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ
who hath blessed us with all spiritual blessings
and heavenly places in Christ.
Notice verse four.
According as he hath chosen us in him
before the foundation of the world,
that we should be holy without blame before him in love.
So we look at the idea of the choosing.
Again, they'll use that idea of unconditional election.
He says that he chose us in him
before the foundation of the world.
Don't get afraid.
Don't think this is unconditional election
because he says that we should be holy without blame.
That is God's will for God's people.
Those that get saved is that we would be holy
and without blame before him in love.
Notice in verse five,
having predestinated us unto the adoption of children,
notice what it says,
by Jesus Christ to himself
according to the good pleasure of his will.
What happens in Ephesians one
is they use the word choose and predestinate it
and they run with Calvinism.
But the problem is that Ephesians one
is not talking about the who of salvation.
Not at all.
Ephesians one is talking about the how of salvation.
You know, Tim, what God determined
before the foundation of the world,
he determined there's only one way to be saved.
That's through Jesus Christ.
That's why Peter is able to say
that Jesus is the lamb that was slain
before the foundation of the world.
Amen?
Because God predetermined,
he predestined the how of salvation.
It would be through Jesus Christ.
By the way, if you look at the Old Testament,
you look at so many things that happen in the Old Testament,
what's happening is it's a, really,
it's a spiritual war that's going against
trying to destroy the messianic line
so that Jesus can't come.
But greater is he that is in us.
Listen, God is omnipotent.
We have an enemy who's powerful,
but God is all powerful.
And Messiah came.
Aren't you thankful?
And he went to the cross
and he shed his blood for all of humanity.
And God's will, we can say with confidence this morning,
that God's will is for lost people to be saved.
And the truth, don't be afraid of Ephesians 1.
Don't be afraid of Romans 9 and 10.
We don't have to fear it.
We just have to understand what God is saying in his word.
And he's saying, listen,
there's only one way to be saved, through Jesus Christ.
Notice with me, though,
that it's not just this portion of scripture
that reveals to us God's will for lost people to be saved.
Take your Bible and turn over.
Well, actually, you're probably still there
in 1 Timothy chapter two.
Look at chapter one just for a moment.
We mentioned this passage of scripture a few weeks ago.
And look at verses 15 and 16.
In 1 Timothy one, verses 15 and 16,
notice what Paul says,
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God.
This is a faithful saying, a truthful saying,
and worthy of all acceptation.
What is this saying?
Well, that Christ Jesus came into the world
to save sinners.
Amen?
Then he says this, of whom I am chief.
Now, notice verse 16,
how be it for this cause I obtain mercy
that in me first Jesus Christ
might show forth all longsuffering
for a pattern to them,
which should hereafter believe on him
to life everlasting.
In Ephesians one, the same portion of scripture,
we're not gonna go back there,
but it says later on in chapter number one,
in whom you trusted after you believed.
And so they heard, or after you heard,
they heard the truth of the gospel,
Paul comes in and preaches,
and they believe it, they accept Christ,
and they're born again.
They're adopted in the family of God.
And so we find that Paul says
that Christ Jesus came to save sinners,
of whom I am chief,
and then there's this pattern
for those that would believe on him
to life everlasting.
By the way, if you look at verse 16,
and really carry out the thought of it,
he has us in mind.
Because we heard and we believed,
if you're saved here this morning,
the truth of 2 Peter chapter three in verse nine.
Maybe you wanna jot it down.
The Bible says that the Lord
is longsuffering to us, word,
not willing that any should perish.
It begins, the Lord is not slack
concerning his promise to us, word,
as some men count slackness.
What are they talking about?
Well, some say, no, he's not gonna come back.
Where is the promise of his coming?
That's how 2 Peter three,
with those scoffers and mockers,
and that's what's being dealt with.
And then Peter says,
the Lord is not slack
concerning his promise to us, word,
as some men count slackness.
But what?
He's longsuffering to us, word.
Notice, not willing that any should perish,
but that all should come to repentance.
But I want you to see it in 1 John chapter two.
Turn over there if you will.
In 1 John chapter two,
as you're turning there,
I wanna remind you of a familiar verse of scripture
that many of us could quote this morning,
and that's John 3, 16.
For God so loved, what?
The world.
For God so loved the world that he, what?
He gave his only begotten son,
that whosoever, don't you like that word?
Whosoever will may come.
We sing the song.
What a wonderful song it is.
Whosoever shall believe.
Right, what are they gonna have?
Everlasting life.
For God so loved the world that he gave
his only begotten son,
that whosoever believeth in him should not perish,
but have everlasting life.
So again, when those that would follow
the tenets of Calvinism would say,
well, all doesn't really mean all.
It just means all of the elect.
So then when you say, well, John 3, 16 says,
for God so loved the world,
they say, yeah, it doesn't really mean world
as in including everybody.
It just means the elect world.
But I want you to notice what the Bible says in 1 John.
I love God's word.
The best commentary on the Bible is the Bible.
And in 1 John 2, it's a precious truth
that God gives us in verse number one,
that Jesus is our advocate.
Praise God for that.
And it says this in verse number one,
my little children, these things have I write unto you,
that you sin not.
And if any man sin, we have an advocate with the Father,
Jesus Christ, the righteous.
Notice what it says, and he, who is he?
Well, Jesus Christ, our advocate.
And he is the propitiation for our sins.
Literally the truth of the covering, the blood,
the atonement, the mercy seat is in view,
he satisfied the demand for sin, the penalty.
So he is the propitiation for our sins.
Now, John is writing in 1 John to save people, amen?
He's writing to save people.
So he says, he is the propitiation for our sins.
Now, we believe that this morning,
but we believe that God's will is for all people to be saved,
that God's will is for lost people to be saved.
Notice what he says, and not for ours only,
but also for the sins of the whole world.
I'm thankful this morning that God's will
is for lost people to be saved.
Why am I thankful for that?
Because I used to be a lost person, amen?
And God saved me by his amazing grace.
And what a blessing.
And I want you to understand this morning,
as I mentioned by way of introduction,
knowing the will of God will shape our worldview.
It will impact our behavior,
but it will also influence our prayer.
It's this parenthetical statement
in 1 Timothy chapter two,
in the midst of an exhortation on prayer,
that God reveals his plan, his will for humanity.
And the first aspect is for lost people to be saved.
How does that influence my prayer life?
Paul says this in Romans chapter 10.
I think it's a great example for us to know
as we think about how this parenthetical statement
of giving to us God's will for humanity
in the midst of an exhortation on prayer
reveals how knowing God's will influences my prayer life.
Here's what Paul says in Romans 10 in verse one.
Brethren, my heart's desire and prayer
to God for Israel is that they might be saved.
So that's a prayer request,
that's a prayer of Paul's
that's influenced by knowing the will of God.
Amen?
And so when we look at this portion of scripture
this morning and we make application for our lives,
we know that God's will is for lost people to be saved.
But how has that influenced me?
If I know that it's God's will for lost people to be saved,
then I ought to be active in sharing the gospel.
Amen?
It means that I ought to be praying for people to be saved.
Because knowing the will of God influences my prayer life.
Notice with me number two this morning,
not only is God's will for lost people to be saved,
but number two, back in 1 Timothy chapter
number two, God's will for lost people to be saved.
God's will is for saved people to grow spiritually.
God's will is for lost people to be saved,
but then God's will is for saved people to grow spiritually.
We find in our text of scripture, again,
in 1 Timothy chapter two,
notice what the Bible says in verse number four,
who will have all men to be saved,
but then it says this,
and to come under the knowledge of the truth.
And then verse number five, again,
I'm thankful for this wonderful promise or truth
that God reveals to us.
Notice it says, for there's one God
and one mediator between God and men,
the man, Christ, Jesus.
This exposes the teaching
that you have to go through some priest to get to God.
I'm thankful that we are priests of God
and we can go direct access to the throne of heaven.
That is an amazing privilege, by the way.
And when we look at verse four and five,
and we consider the thought this morning
that God's will is for saved people to grow spiritually,
we understand two aspects here
of that growing in the knowledge of the truth.
It says, and to have to come
unto the knowledge of the truth.
Where do I get that from?
Well, God's word is truth.
He says, sanctify them through thy word.
Thy word is truth.
And so we understand that we're to grow by this book
and this book will grow us up in our faith,
but we also understand the aspect,
according to verse number five, of prayer.
Prayer.
You know, as you grow spiritually,
you're gonna learn more about this book
and you're gonna grow in your prayer life.
And those things work together.
In fact, we sing a song with our children in VBS
and in Children's Church.
Read your Bible, pray every day,
and you'll grow, grow, grow, right?
Many of you have heard the song.
Maybe you've had the opportunity
to hear us sing it at some point,
but we sing that with the children.
Why?
Because we understand that reading and praying,
reading God's word and praying
helps us to grow spiritually.
And it is God's will for lost people to be saved,
but then not to just, okay, I'm saved.
No, now God's will for you
when you leave the category of being lost
to going into the category of being saved,
God's will is for you to grow spiritually.
We know that here from 1 Timothy 2,
but notice with me a few other verses of Scripture.
Turn over to Hebrews 5, if you will.
Hebrews 5, and really,
this is an interesting passage of Scripture
where Paul speaks to these.
I believe Paul wrote the book of Hebrews.
The Bible college answer is God wrote it
because all Scripture is given by inspiration of God.
People debate over it,
but I believe Paul was the human penman.
But the reality is that here,
and then also in 1 Corinthians 11,
two times the verbiage isn't used here,
but it's as if Paul is saying
he uses this verbiage in 1 Corinthians 11.
I praise you not.
Like, I'm not commending you for this.
This, in fact, I'm speaking really to your shame.
What is it that he speaks of?
Well, notice with me in Hebrews 5 in verse number 11.
He says, of whom we have many things to say
and hard to be uttered.
Why are they hard to be uttered?
Well, not because I don't understand them,
not because I don't know how to communicate them,
but because ye are dull of hearing.
So Paul says, this is difficult
because we have many things to say,
we have many things to teach you,
but you're dull of hearing.
And notice in verse number 12, he says,
for when for the time you ought to be teachers.
That means that they'd been saved for a while.
They'd left the category of being lost and being saved
and they're to grow spiritually.
He says, in the time that you ought to be teachers,
ye have need that one teach you again,
which be the first principles of the oracles of God.
There becomes such as have need of milk
and not of strong meat.
And that reminds us of the truth of 1 Peter 2
in verse number two.
The Bible says, as newborn babes,
desire the sincere milk of the word
that ye may grow thereby.
And so listen, it's not a bad thing
to need the milk of the word.
That's where we all begin.
But I'm so thankful.
Physically, I'm thankful I'm not still on a milk diet.
Hallelujah.
But spiritually, we ought not be on a milk diet.
We're to grow.
Amen.
And so he says, notice he says,
that ye have need of milk and not of strong meat.
Notice verse 13, for everyone that useth milk
is unskillful in the word of righteousness,
for he is a babe.
But strong meat belongeth to them that are of full age,
even those who by reason of use
have their senses exercised to discern both good and evil.
Now here's the amazing thing spiritually.
You don't have to be saved for a certain period of time
in order to be a mature Christian.
So physically speaking, there are certain things
that a baby cannot eat.
They have to be on a milk diet for a certain period of time,
and then everything they eat is pureed.
Isn't that awful?
I mean, honestly.
I am not interested in eating baby food.
Julianna's been feeding some baby food to Nova.
No thank you.
I've not offered to taste it.
I don't wanna smell it.
I like my food the way I eat it, amen.
But physically, Nova can't handle the piece of chicken
that I eat or the green bean that I eat, right?
She can't handle it.
And so there's a, we understand that physically,
but spiritually, you can be mature
and not be very quote-unquote old in the Lord.
Why do I say that?
Well, because you're as close to God,
you're as mature spiritually as you really wanna be.
We, this past week, we've read our Bibles
as much as we've really wanted to.
We've prayed as much as we've really wanted to.
We've engaged, listen, it's a desire that we have,
that we wanna grow.
He says, as newborn babies, desire,
this is the same miracle of the word,
that ye may grow thereby.
But then we are to grow beyond that.
We're to get into the meat of the word of God.
We find that 2 Peter 3, in verse number 18,
here's what God says, and it's a great ending
to the book of 2 Peter, but grow in grace
in the knowledge of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ.
To him be glory, both now and forever, amen.
You know what the best remedy is for false teaching?
Spiritual growth, spiritual growth.
Because when you grow spiritually,
when you get into this book, when you grow,
you can expose false teaching.
You can identify false teaching.
You can see it, because you're growing spiritually.
And so we find that God's will, number one,
is for lost people to be saved,
but God's will, number two,
is for saved people to grow spiritually.
So just as we made application with the first truth,
we make application with the second truth.
What are we doing personally to grow spiritually?
How, maybe I can ask it this way,
what are we doing to help someone else grow spiritually?
What are we doing to help somebody else grow spiritually?
You know, Nova can't feed herself right now.
If you can't feed yourself right now,
somebody, you have, you've broken something,
you have a, but she physically cannot
feed herself right now.
You know, the reality is that spiritually speaking,
there's some babes in Christ that need a mature brother
or sister to come alongside and help them to grow.
You ever know the phrase, we use it,
they're spoon-fed, right?
Why, because they can't feed themselves.
So I don't know where you were when you first got saved,
but I know when I first got saved,
I didn't know anything about this book.
I didn't know where to begin.
I didn't know what, I didn't know anything.
And so I'm thankful that there were some spiritual leaders
in my life that came alongside
and helped me to grow spiritually.
By the way, that's the fulfilling of the Great Commission,
not only to preach the gospel and to baptize them,
but to disciple them.
And we find here that we are to be engaged in ourselves.
What are we doing to grow?
Don't be comfortable and content with where you are.
The Christian life is very interesting.
There really is no time that you're stagnant
in the Christian life.
You're either going forward or you're going backward.
Seriously.
Don't be content with where you are.
Desire, as Paul, I think about Paul.
For many of us, in 1 Timothy, he says,
I'm the chief of all sinners.
But for many of us, we have Paul in our minds
as this great Christian,
and he certainly was a man that followed God.
He's a man that we can learn much from.
But you know what Paul says in Philippians 3?
That I may know him.
He wasn't content with where he was.
He wanted to grow more.
He wanted to learn more about his Lord and his Savior.
Not only did we say that we should be engaged
in seeking how God's will, how has it affected my behavior,
but we said it should affect our prayer lives.
It's within this exhortation on prayer
that God reveals his will for humanity.
And I want you to understand
that in Ephesians chapter number three,
Paul is praying for the believers in Ephesus.
In Ephesians chapter number three,
as Paul is praying for the believers in Ephesus,
it's very interesting because Paul is praying
that these believers in Ephesus
would be strengthened spiritually, that they would grow.
Notice with me, beginning in verse number 14 of Ephesians 3.
See, Paul is praying for these believers in Ephesus
according to the will of God.
And it says in Ephesians 3 and verse 14,
for this cause I bow my knees unto the Father
of our Lord.
Lord Jesus Christ, of whom the whole family in heaven and earth is name, that
he would grant you according to the riches of his glory, notice, to be
strengthened with might by his Spirit, where? In the inner man. Listen, we need
to be praying that way one for another. So often our prayer requests one for
another are physical, but we need to be praying spiritually for our brothers and
sisters in Christ. We, listen, we're engaged in spiritual battle and
spiritual warfare, and we need to be strengthened in our inner man. We find
that he says that Christ may dwell in your hearts by faith, that ye, being
rooted and grounded in love, may be able to comprehend with all saints what is
the breadth and length and depth and height, and to know the love of Christ,
which passeth knowledge, that ye might be filled with all the fullness of God. Why
is Paul praying this way? Well, because he understands God's will is for saved
people to grow spiritually. Paul has grown, and Paul says, I want these
believers in Ephesus to grow spiritually, so I'm praying for them. He prays for the
believers in Colossae in Colossians chapter number one. Now it's interesting
because in Ephesians chapter 3, Paul had a personal relationship with these
people. He knew the people at the church at Ephesus. He had ministered there, but
now when we come to the book of Colossians, Paul did not minister there.
He did not. God didn't use Paul to start the church in Colossae, but he heard
about their faith, and what does he do? He begins to pray for them. And notice with me
in Colossians 1, how does Paul pray for these believers in Colossae? Well, in
verse number 9, it says, for this cause we also, notice what he says, since the day
we heard it, do not cease to pray for you, and to desire that ye might be filled
with the knowledge of his will and all wisdom and spiritual understanding, that
ye might walk worthy of the Lord unto all pleasing, being fruitful in every
good work, and increasing in the knowledge of God. I won't read the rest
of the prayer, but this is biblical praying. And it's praying according to
the will of God, because God's will is not simply that lost people are saved,
but God's will is that saved people grow spiritually. We ought to be praying. You
know, sometimes, you know, God uses a variety of things to grow us. Some things,
sometimes, God uses the things that we dislike the most to grow us. Amen?
Sometimes, God will put somebody in your life to grow you. The person that you
want to get, you understand what I'm saying? They bother you. God says, I'm
helping you grow. The psalmist says in Psalm 119, it was good for me to be
afflicted. I don't know about you, but I don't like affliction. But he says, it's good
for me, because then I learned thy statutes. I grew. Listen, David, he was, he
was displeased when Uzzah touched the ark and he died. But you know what
happened in that tragedy? David grew. David grew. He found out we better do
God's work God's way. And guess what? When they brought the ark the second time,
when they took it out of the house where it was stored for three months, they did
it the right way. They did it God's way. And so we find here that we're to pray
God. Listen, sometimes we pray someone's dealing with a trial and affliction and
we pray for them in that trial or affliction, which is great, it's
commendable, but don't stop too short. What do I mean by that? Well, maybe you need to add
this to the prayer. God, in that, would you help them to grow spiritually? Would you
help them to learn more about you? That's praying biblically. So God's
will, when we understand it, it impacts our behavior. It influences our worldview, but
it also influences how we pray. We see that Paul says, I'm praying for my
brethren that they would be saved. Why? Because he understands God's will is for
lost people to be saved. We find that Paul is praying for those in Ephesus and
those in Colossae that they would grow spiritually, that they'd be strengthened, they would
have knowledge. Why? Because he understands that God's will is for saved
people to grow spiritually. Number three in our text of Scripture in 1st
Timothy chapter 2, I want you to see number three. God's will is for saved
people to share the gospel. God's will is for saved people to share the gospel. You
understand that lost people can't share the gospel? Why? Because they don't know
the gospel. In fact, when there was one that was possessed that said of Paul that
these are the men that show us the way of salvation, we find that Paul said, get
that, cast the demon out. Why? Because it was the wrong vessel. It was the right
message, but the wrong vessel. Notice back in our text in 1st Timothy chapter 2,
the Bible says in verse number 6, who gave himself a ransom for all. We
already mentioned that in our first thought this morning, that it is God's
will for lost people to be saved. But then notice the end of verse number 6, to
be testified in due time. The idea of this phrase here is that he would, the
Lord Jesus Christ, would be testified by those that know him at the appropriate
time. You know, God gives us opportunities, and we better be ready to share Christ,
to speak of the hope that lieth within you. Notice in verse number 7, Paul makes
the application personally to himself, where unto I am ordained a preacher and
an apostle. The office that he had was that of being an apostle, but he was
commissioned, just as each of us are commissioned, to be preachers of the
gospel. We find that Jesus said that we're to go and preach the gospel to
every creature. By the way, in Acts chapter number 8, at the height of the
persecution of the church in Jerusalem, they're scattered abroad because of the
persecution, and the Bible says, and they that were scattered abroad went
everywhere preaching the word. You know what's interesting about that? The
church leader stayed in Jerusalem. It was the people that went out and preached
the gospel, that preached the word. There's only so many people I come into
contact in any given week. There's only so many opportunities that I have to
preach the gospel. It is my duty, but it is your duty. Why? Because it is God's
will for saved people, not only to grow spiritually, but for saved people to
spread the gospel. We see, he says, that I am ordained a preacher and apostle. I
speak the truth in Christ and lie not, a teacher of the Gentiles in faith and
verity. And so we find that it is our responsibility, we understand this
morning, that God's desire is for his people to share the gospel. In Acts
chapter 5 in verse 32, we're not going to turn there, but the Bible says of the
disciples, they say this, we are his witnesses. By the way, it's a good way
for us to refer to ourselves. We are his witnesses. We are the ones that God has
entrusted to take the gospel to a lost and dying world. And we know that Paul
said, I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ. Why? For it, the gospel of Christ,
is the power of God unto salvation. Remember again, to everyone that
believeth. Why everyone? Why does he use that phrase? Well, because God's will is
for lost people to be saved. For all men. He gave himself a ransom for all. So
therefore, Paul is able to say that the gospel is the power of God unto
salvation to everyone, to any man, any person that would place their faith and
trust in Christ. And so we find that the Bible tells us in 2nd Corinthians
chapter 5 and verse number 20 that we are his ambassadors. It's kind of a
special title that God gives us as being his ambassadors. I read an account
recently of a, I don't remember exactly the name of the individual. I should have
jotted it down. I thought I remember it, but I can't remember the name of the
individual. But he was in charge of the government office in which the
ambassadors would leave from there, from the United States, and they'd go to
whatever country they were going to. And the first question that this individual
would ask as they would come into his office and they were preparing for
departure to go fulfill their duties as ambassador, is he would say this, what
country do you represent? And almost every single time the individual being
asked would answer the country that they were going to. And he would say, no, you
represent the United States of America. You are going to that foreign nation to
represent America. So what are we as ambassadors? Well, this world is not my
home. You know, as you can say, the Bible speaks about in Ephesians chapter 3
that our citizenship is in heaven. Amen? We sing, this world is not my home. I'm a
pilgrim. I'm a stranger. Hebrews chapter 3, 11. And the reality this morning is
that we are ambassadors. Why? Because our citizenship is in heaven. We have
citizenship here on earth, but we are ambassadors here. We are his
representatives. Our kingdom is heaven. Aren't you thankful for that, by the way?
What a unique opportunity that we have to be his witnesses, to be his
ambassadors. And we find that truth in Acts 5 and verse 32, in 2 Corinthians 5
and verse number 20.
We could take the time this morning to look at the Great Commission as it's given in Matthew, Mark, Luke, John, Acts.
You see it over and over. God's will is for those that are saved to share the gospel, to spread the truth of the good news.
It's the greatest message that's ever been told.
But so often we shy away from sharing the gospel, and I'm guilty of it just as much as anyone else is,
because we're concerned of how it's going to be received.
God never gave us the responsibility of how someone responds to the message that we give.
In fact, the instruction of the Lord Jesus Christ is when they don't listen to you, just shake off the dust and go to the next place.
Is that not true?
So our duty, we find, is that we would understand the will of God.
In the midst of this, we've made application throughout the message this morning,
but we find with this third thought that God's will is for saved people to share the gospel.
The question this morning is how has that truth of knowing this morning God's will is for us to spread the gospel, to share the gospel,
how has that impacted our behavior?
Someone asked this very simple question.
Who gives out tracts?
Do you know the answer to that?
The one that has them.
Have you ever been in a situation where you thought the Holy Spirit of God was prompting you to give a tract and you didn't have one?
Can I tell you something really frustrating?
I say it's frustrating because I was in Bible college.
When I was in Bible college, you had to wear a shirt and tie every day to class.
You had to wear a coat to chapel.
That was just the dress code.
That's what we had to do.
And so I wore a shirt and tie every day to class, and just as I still do today, I had gospel tracts in my pocket.
I like wearing dress shirts.
I don't wear them all the time, but I like wearing them because it's an easy place to keep a gospel tract.
While I was in Bible college, I had students that made fun of me for carrying gospel tracts around.
Can you just kind of shake your head and say, seriously?
I mean, isn't that what we're supposed to do?
Try to share the gospel.
I understand that it doesn't end with just sharing a gospel tract, but there are some times where the only thing you might be able to do is share a gospel tract.
The person that's helping you at the counter is working a job.
And integrity would say that they have to be a good worker, right?
And you can't take 30 minutes of their time to try to share the gospel with them.
While the line backs up and they're—that's not right.
So, all you might be able to do is say, can I share this with you?
And I often say this, the content of this changed my life 25 years ago.
Will you read it?
I try to get them to give me a commitment that they'll read it.
They have to answer the question.
Now, some of us have all been to the same place, all being in Fairfax, where the person likes to take them and rip them up in your face.
It's happened multiple times to several of our members.
You know, it doesn't make me mad, it makes me sad.
It makes me sad.
Something happened in that man's life, and I don't know what it is, but he's mad at God.
He's not really mad at me.
He's not mad at the other members of our church that have had that happen.
Some have shared it with me.
Have you ever given a tract?
Have you ever been to Aldi?
I have been.
Have you ever given a tract?
Yep, I know who you're talking about.
He followed me out the door and said, you're sure this is for me?
Yeah.
Right in my face.
It just broke my heart.
I'm not mad at him.
He's rejecting Christ.
But how has the truth of God's will, that saved people to spread the gospel, to share the gospel, how has it impacted your behavior and my behavior?
How has it influenced my prayer life?
Those are the two questions we've asked with each point this morning.
Let me share with you again Paul's example.
We've used that for the first and second point.
I'll use it again for this third point this morning.
Look at Ephesians chapter 6.
I want you to see what Paul, it's very interesting that Paul, God allows for the prayers of Paul to be recorded in a number of portions.
There's a few times in which we read of Paul requesting prayer.
One of them is very basic where Paul simply says in 1 Thessalonians 5, brethren pray for us.
There's no specific details with regard to the prayer request.
But the example in Ephesians chapter 6, I want you to see this morning because we're going to look at Colossians as well and we'll be done.
But notice in Ephesians 6, notice what the Bible says in verse number 19.
He talks about in verse number 18 about the importance of praying.
But then he says in verse number 19, after he says pray for all saints, but he says and for me.
So Paul is giving the believers of Ephesus a personal prayer request in Ephesians 6.
And here's what the request is.
That utterance may be given unto me.
That I may open my mouth boldly to make known the mystery of the gospel.
For which I am an ambassador in bonds that therein I may speak boldly as I ought to speak.
I know I've asked the question before but it begs to be asked again in this portion of scripture.
Paul requesting for boldness.
Is not Paul one of the most bold witnesses that you see as you read the New Testament?
I mean he stands in boldness before those in authority and he preaches the gospel.
But he asked people to pray for boldness.
That he would open his mouth and speak what he was supposed to speak.
The gospel.
That may be some insight as to how Paul was so bold.
He had people praying for him to be bold.
That was his request.
In Colossians chapter number 4 he says this in verse number 2 of Colossians 4.
He's speaking to these believers of Colossians.
He's already said how he's praying for them.
Now he's saying pray for me.
Continue in prayer.
Verse number 2 of Colossians 4.
And watch in the same with thanksgiving with all.
Praying also for us.
What's the prayer request?
That God would open us a door of utterance.
Can I say it in this phrase?
That God would give us an opportunity.
And then he says this.
To speak the mystery of Christ.
For which I am also in bonds that I may make it manifest.
Notice what he says.
As I ought to speak.
So Paul, understanding the will of God, has his behavior impacted.
How do we say that?
Well, Paul gets saved.
He understands that it was God's will for him to be saved.
He acts nine.
But then Paul is engaged in discipleship and helping people to grow.
Paul then is sharing the gospel.
Why?
Because that's God's will.
But his prayer life was influenced by these three thoughts that are given to us of God's will for humanity in 1st Timothy 2.
He prays for people, lost people, to be saved.
He prays for God's people, those that are saved, to be strengthened and to grow spiritually.
He prays that God would give him boldness.
And he asks others to pray that he would share the gospel as he ought.
So I simply ask this morning.
How has knowing God's will for humanity, God's revealed will, how has it impacted our behavior?
And how is it influencing our prayer life?
Because in the midst of an exhortation on prayer, God seemingly gives us this parenthetical statement and says,
let me reveal to you my will for humanity.
Number one, it's for lost people to be saved.
Number two, it's for saved people to grow spiritually.
And number three, it's for saved people to share the gospel.
I hope this morning that God's will impacts us.
Impacts our behavior and influences our prayer lives.
Shall we pray?
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for your word.
I thank you this morning that we do not have to reach our own conclusions with regard to your will for humanity.
That we can go to the written, preserved, inspired, preserved word of God.
You have communicated to us what your will is for humanity.
God, I pray this morning that we would be impacted and influenced by these truths.
If there's one that's not saved, I pray this morning they'd understand that it's your will for them to be saved today.
Today is the day of salvation.
Maybe for some that are saved, they're just kind of floundering around.
They're not really growing spiritually.
God, would you help them to recognize this morning that your will is for them to grow spiritually?
It's not enough to just be saved.
I mean, yes, they're going to heaven.
But God, you want them to grow in grace and knowledge of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ.
God, would you help us to recognize this morning that your will is for us to share the gospel?
Would you help us to evaluate our lives and honestly, sincerely desire to be used of them?
me, to share the wonderful message of the gospel with those that we come in contact
with.
I pray that in these moments of invitation that you'd move and work as only you can.
We'll be careful to give you the honor and glory for all that you'll do for it's in Christ's
name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano and as she does the altar is open.