on chapter number two, and we're looking at verses one and two today.
And the title for the message, if you look at the back of the bulletin, Jesus, Our Advocate.
And we'll get to that great truth here in just a few moments and what precious truth
it is.
I want you to notice as we begin looking at this passage of Scripture, the Bible says,
my little children, these things write I unto you that ye sin not.
And if any man sin, we have an advocate with the Father, Jesus Christ, the righteous.
And he is the propitiation for our sins and not for ours only, but also for the sins of
the whole world.
As we begin this passage of Scripture, you'll know it's a very interesting introduction,
if you will, a greeting, the verbiage in which is used in verse number one, my little children.
I do not believe that this phrase, this greeting would be one of insult, rather one of encouragement.
We find that at the time of the writing of the book of 1 John, this epistle, we understand
that John is the last of the apostles that is still living.
He's an old man by this particular time, and we find that the enemy has been at work.
The false teachers have infiltrated into the churches, and John is being used of the Lord
to provide instruction.
And when he uses this phraseology, my little children, really he's communicating to these
believers not only his care and his concern for them, but his love for them.
And you think about the communication of this greeting, my little children, understanding
that at salvation we're born again, and you'd understand the truth of being babes in Christ
and thinking about this phraseology of these that are younger in their faith than what
the apostle John would be.
He's of course walked with the Lord Jesus Christ.
He testifies in the opening statements of 1 John chapter number one that he is an eyewitness
of these things, and he provides this eyewitness account.
We find that he says that his ears have heard, his eyes have seen, his hands have handled
of the word of life, and he provides this great record, and as he's speaking to these
that are younger in their faith, my little children, he is encouraging them, and he's
communicating to them his great love and care and concern for them.
We find it's also of note, we've mentioned in our previous messages, that in verse number
three, and again in verse number five, you read the phrase, declare unto you.
In verse number three it says, that which we have seen and heard declare we unto you,
and in verse number five of chapter number one it says, this then is the message which
we have heard of him and declare unto you.
And so we've noted the fact that John is a faithful messenger.
He has faithfully, is faithfully communicating that which he has been instructed to communicate.
We also find that it's interesting that here in verse number one of chapter two, there's
a phrase that was mentioned in verse number four.
That phrase is this, write unto you.
Notice in verse number four, and these things write we unto you, that your joy may be full.
In verse number one of first John chapter number two, he says, my little children, notice,
these things write I unto you.
We'll see it again in chapter number five, but we find that John is communicating the
word of God to the people of God, and as he's communicating to them, no doubt the
truth that is being communicated is powerful, life-changing truth.
I'm so thankful for the word of God and the power that it has to change lives, and I'm
thankful for the way in which our last message in verses five through 10 of first John one,
the truth that was revealed there in that passage, really we begin to see in verse one
and two of chapter number two how that truth is played out, how it applies practically
in our lives.
If you're taking notes this morning, I only have two points, but don't get excited.
They're two very long points, amen?
And so bear with me on the two points this morning.
Number one, if you're taking notes, an appeal to the believer.
An appeal to the believer.
I want you to notice, he says, my little children, in verse number one of chapter two, these
things write I unto you, notice this appeal, that ye sin not.
Wow.
What an appeal to the child of God, to the believer.
We've stated in previous messages, in fact, I mentioned it last week, and we find that
the text before us in verses five through 10 of chapter number one clearly teaches us
that we will never reach a place of sinless perfection in this mortal body.
One day, one glorious day, this mortal, this corruption shall put on incorruption and this
mortal shall put on immortality, and we understand that we will no longer have this flesh, but
while we walk upon this earth and we have this mortal body, we have the flesh.
So we will not reach a place of sinless perfection, however, the appeal to the believer is here
that ye sin not.
Now think about that and understand with me, I would say it this way, that it's not a truth
of reaching a place of sinless perfection, but the reality is that as the people of God,
I should sin less as I walk with Him.
Amen?
As we grow in our walk with the Lord Jesus Christ, as we walk in the light, as He is
in the light, I ought to be sinning less and less as I'm in His presence.
Have you ever been driving down the highway?
I've spent many hours on the highway in recent days, and it's always interesting when you
pass one of those individuals that's sitting in the median upon the highway and all of
a sudden everyone feels the need, they are compelled to follow the speed limit.
The guys that were passing by you and changing lanes and driving erratically, all of a sudden
they see the presence of a law enforcement and they decide they ought to get things contained
and follow the law.
The reality is that when we understand that we're walking in the light as He is in the
light, we're having fellowship with Him, and we're living daily in the presence of God,
it ought to impact our behavior.
Amen?
It ought not be that we live and just casually sin and just go through this process as a
believer freely sinning.
In fact, I believe this morning that the enemy, our enemy, has twisted two very powerful
biblical truths that greatly hinder the effectiveness of God's people today.
Here's what those two truths are, I believe, and we see it here as he says that ye sin
not.
First of all, I would say this, the enemy, our enemy, Satan, has taken a wonderful Bible
truth and he's twisted it, and I believe that it hinders our effectiveness, the first
of which is the grace of God.
The Bible tells us in Jude 4, and just a few pages over from 1 John, it's a short letter,
only 25 verses here in the book of Jude, but you find that the Bible tells us in Jude 4,
for there were certain men crept in unawares who were before of old ordained to this condemnation,
ungodly men, notice what the Bible says, turning the grace of our God into lasciviousness and
denying the only Lord God and our Lord Jesus Christ.
I am so thankful for the grace of God, aren't you?
We sing about His amazing grace.
We understand that His grace is amazing, it is abundant, and I'm thankful that I'm saved
by His grace, that I'm able to serve by His grace.
I'm thankful, the truth that God has given us in His Word with regard to His grace, but
you see here that the Bible says that they've turned the grace of our God into lasciviousness.
That word lasciviousness is not a word that's very commonly used today, but it's a word
that means unbridled lust.
It's a word that carries with it the idea of just doing whatever it is that you want
to do.
We've turned, they, the enemy, has twisted the truth of the grace of God, and here we
find that it says in Jude 4 that they've turned the grace of God into lasciviousness.
Think about this truth.
Go over to Romans 5 if you will, and look at this passage and how it's dealt with in
Romans 5, the last portion of the, really the last verse and into the sixth chapter
of Romans 5 and into verse chapter number 6.
Notice Romans 5 in verse number 21.
Notice what it said, that as sin hath reigned unto death, even so might grace reign through
righteousness unto eternal life by Jesus Christ our Lord.
So there's this contrast that's being made in the fifth chapter about the sin and the
entry of sin and the effect of sin, but then the contrast made with the gift of God and
the life that God gives through His Son and the crucifixion on the cross of Calvary and
how that all men are affected by the sin of Adam and were all sinners, but because of
the death of Jesus Christ, that righteousness now is available to all men, and what a joy
that we find in this portion of Scripture.
But notice what is said in the beginning of chapter number 6 and verse number 1.
What shall we say then?
When we consider this sin versus the grace of God, what shall we say then?
Notice what it says, shall we continue in sin that grace may abound?
So I know that God is gracious.
The enemy has twisted this powerful Bible truth that God is gracious.
He's turned it into lasciviousness, this unbridled lust.
God is gracious and it's deemed our effectiveness, it has hindered our effectiveness.
It's really deemed us to be ineffective because we believe the lie of the enemy.
Well God is gracious.
Should we say that we should continue in sin that grace may abound?
What's the answer?
God forbid.
How shall we that are dead to sin live any longer therein?
The idea is not that, well, I want to experience the grace of God so I'm going to go out and
live all this sin so that I can experience the grace of God.
That's not the idea.
But there are people today that have twisted the idea of God's grace and it renders us
ineffective because God does not use dirty vessels, amen?
And we find that it's rendered us ineffective and the enemy has been very just subtle in
his approach and his attack.
And I would say that not only the truth of the grace of God, but really contextually
with what we look at in 1 John, back in 1 John I would say this, the forgiveness of
God.
Aren't you thankful for God's forgiveness?
I'm thankful that he is faithful and just.
Amen?
Aren't you?
Aren't you thankful that with him there is forgiveness, that he is ready to pardon, he
is ready to forgive?
I'm so thankful for that truth.
But the reality is that there are people today, the enemy has peddled this idea and twisted
the truth of not only the grace of God, but the forgiveness of God, that it almost gives
the believer when they've been affected and impacted by this wrong teaching, that it gives
them this free car, get out of jail free kind of an idea that I can go and sin and
live however I want to live because God's going to forgive me.
And it renders us ineffective.
In 1 John 1 and verse number 9 is a powerful truth, we looked at it last week, if we confess
our sins, he is faithful and just to forgive us our sins and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness.
But when we find here that we understand this truth, it's not so that we just go out and
sin and live however we want to live and say, well, God is gracious and he's going to forgive
and so I can just do what I want to do.
Look at the appeal in verse number 1 of 1 John 2, after the instruction is given in
the first chapter with regard to the fellowship and what have you, we find that he says, my
little children, these things write I unto you that ye sin not.
It's not the mentality that God is gracious and that God will forgive and therefore I
have this license and I can go do whatever I want to do and then I know I can just confess
it and he'll forgive me.
That's a wrong theology.
That is a bad hermeneutic.
The reality is that the truth of God's grace and the truth of God's forgiveness ought to
bring us to the place when we understand all that he's done for us and we understand all
that he is to us, that we say, I want to sin less and less and less.
Getting to the point, again, we're never going to reach that place of sinless perfection,
but when we look and evaluate our lives, we say, I sin less today than I sinned yesterday.
Amen?
Why?
Because I'm walking in the light.
I'm walking in his presence.
The question, see the reality is this, the believer should not sin freely because of
these great Bible truths.
No, rather the believer should strive, should make it their goal that they sin not.
Amen?
Seems as if at times we get so influenced by our culture.
The church has always been called to influence the culture, but we find that there's always
been an influence from the culture upon the church.
There are times in which our sin is justified and excused and made light of.
Everyone does it.
It's just the acceptable thing.
But the reality is that as I'm walking in the light and I'm walking with Christ, the
appeal to the child of God, the appeal to the believer in 1 John 2 is that we sin not.
Can I sin less?
Is it even possible?
If so, how?
I would say three very quick things this morning on answering the question when the appeal
is that you sin not, I would say this, yes, indeed, I can sin less as I walk with Christ.
And one way is what we found in verse number 7, and I've mentioned it already, is that
we walk in the light, that we walk in the light.
You know, the reality is that throughout the Scriptures, there are many times in which
we find, in fact, a perfect, great example of it is in Joseph's life that he was living
in the presence of God.
And when Potiphar's wife saw that there was no one in the house and she saw that this
was the perfect opportunity, I believe that Joseph understood that God was present.
When we learn to walk in the light as He is in the light and we learn to live in that
realm and live in that close fellowship and communion with Him, it will impact how we
live our lives, and we should sin less.
Let me ask you, parents, do your children behave a certain way when they know that you
are there in their presence?
Sure they do.
Just as the illustration that I mentioned a moment ago with regard to the police officer
sitting in the median of the highway.
There are people that obey the speed limit whether there's a police officer present or
not, but there are others that just because of the presence of law enforcement, it will
change their behavior.
And as we understand that human trait and we understand that reality, it is such that
as I walk in the light as He is in the light, everywhere I go, my God is with me.
Man, that's going to affect how I live my life, and it will lead to a place of sinning
less.
Amen?
Number two, not only walk in the light, but stay in His Word.
Remember last week we belabored the point where the Bible told us in verses 6, 8, and
10 of chapter number 1 that they were saying this, but the reality was something different.
In verses 8 and 10, the Bible says that the truth is not in us and His Word is not in
us.
The Bible says in John 17 and verse number 17, sanctify them through Thy Word, Thy Word
is truth.
This book, as D.L.
Moody said, and I often quote, will keep us from sin, or sin will keep us from this book.
And how important it is that we stay in His Word.
There was a direct correlation in verses 8 and 10 between that deception and all that
was taking place within the lives of those individuals with an absence of the Word of
God.
How I must stay in the Word.
And then I would say this, that I must walk in the Spirit.
The Bible tells us in Galatians 5 and verse number 16, if you walk in the Spirit, ye shall
not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
I'm thankful this morning that God has given us freedom from the bondage of sin.
And that when John gives this appeal to his readers, and by way of preservation to us
this morning, that the Bible says, I say unto you, I write these things unto you, that ye
sin not, that this is an appeal that we must take and we must respond to.
And as we evaluate our lives, we say, I want to sin less and less as I walk with Christ.
And it's possible.
Listen, it's not this excuse of the devil made me do it.
Amen?
Honestly.
That we begin to understand the truth of what God is giving us here, and the importance
of this appeal to the believer.
We note the appeal to the believer.
Number two, if you're taking notes, I want you to understand an advocate for the believer.
There's an appeal to every believer, but I'm so thankful, and it should cause us to rejoice
greatly that we have an advocate.
The Bible says this, my little children, these things write I unto you, that ye sin not.
Then notice the next phrase, and if any man sin, now, we try to sin not, we are walking
in the light as he is in the light, we're in his Word, we're abiding in the truth, we're
abiding in him, we're walking in the Spirit, but the reality is that you have flesh and
I have flesh, and guess what?
We sin.
Right?
Have you found it to be the case?
You say, I'm going to do everything I can not to sin tomorrow, I'm just going to stay
in bed all day.
Well, you forgot about redeeming the time.
Right?
Listen, we can put parameters in place, but the reality is that we have this flesh, and
as we have this flesh, the flesh at, listen, is at enmity with the Spirit, Galatians 5,
right?
In our own Christian experience.
has taught us, has revealed to us, that yes, we should have that desire, we should
respond to that appeal, that I sin not, but I'm so thankful that when I sin, I
have an advocate. What wonderful Bible truth is given to us here in this
portion of Scripture. I want you to notice how our advocate is described. The
Bible says, and if any man sin, we have an advocate with the Father. Notice this
description, Jesus Christ the righteous. Aren't you thankful that he's righteous,
perfectly just, he's without sin. The Bible continues with this description in
verse number two. I want you to see that it says this, and he is the propitiation
for our sins. Notice this, and not for ours only, but also for the sins of the
whole world. I'm so thankful that Christ paid the price for the sin of mankind,
and he is the propitiation for our sins, and also for the sins of the whole world.
It says in 1 John 4, in verse number 10, turn over just a few pages, it says
here in his love, not that we loved God, but that he loved us, and sent his son to
be the propitiation for our sins. That word is a word, again, we mentioned
lasciviousness earlier, this word propitiation is a word that we may not
use very often. It's a word that is something that we use theologically
more than maybe in our everyday vernacular, but when we think about this
word, it means the satisfaction. It means that Jesus Christ satisfied the
demands of God. He paid for the sin. It's also interesting because it really
relates to the Old Testament truth of the mercy seat. In fact, the same Greek
word is used in Hebrews 9 and translated as mercy seat. When you think about that,
you begin to get that picture in your mind of the mercy seat, you'll be
familiar with the tabernacle, as God had given instruction to Moses to build this
tabernacle, and all of the details, the pattern that was provided, and you'll
find that there was the outer court, and then you come in and there's the holy
place, right? And you find that within the holy place is the Holy of Holies. When
you go into that Holy of Holies, by the way, it's only to be entered on the Day
of Atonement one time per year, and you would find that there was there, in that
Holy of Holies, the Ark of the Covenant. The Ark of the Covenant had originally
three items within it. The law, it had the pot of manna, and it had Aaron's bud,
or Aaron's rod that budded. We find that, as you would think about the law, and
you'd think about that Ark of the Covenant, you would find that really we
could refer to that as being a throne of judgment. We're guilty. But perfectly
placed upon the top of that Ark of the Covenant is what? The mercy seat. The
mercy seat. And it perfectly, completely covers the Ark of the Covenant, and what
was a throne of judgment now becomes a throne of grace. Why? Because the blood
would be applied once a year, and you would find that as that blood was
applied, that you would find that atonement had been made, and what joy
that is, and now that throne of judgment becomes a throne of grace. And as we see
here, that the Bible describes our advocate as being Jesus Christ the
righteous, but also reveals to us that He is the propitiation for our sins, the
sacrifice of Jesus Christ on the cross of Calvary, His burial, and His glorious
resurrection. Listen, it was sufficient, and it was complete in satisfying God. We
ought to rejoice greatly in that truth. We find that as we would consider the
description that is given to us in these verses of Scripture with regard to our
advocate, we would find that the description proves to us that Jesus is
indeed perfectly qualified to serve as our advocate. By the way, He's the only
one that's qualified to serve as our advocate. Not only is He perfect and
without sin, the fact that He is Jesus Christ the righteous, but also understand
that He made the accepted payment for the sin of mankind. There's a, I believe,
as we've mentioned before, there is a false teaching that seems to grow in
more prevalence today. In fact, it's creeping its way into many of our Bible
colleges today. It's creeping its way into many of our Baptist churches today,
and we see it growing in its allure, and really the appeal of this false teaching
is really one of intellect. And here's what I would say. Verse number two helps
us so much with this false teaching. It's this false teaching. No doubt you've
heard of Calvinism, and part of Calvinism teaches that there is a limited
atonement. In other words, they would say that Jesus only died for certain people,
His atonement was limited. The Bible, however, tells us here that He is the
propitiation for our sins, and not for ours only, but also for the sins of the
whole world. Isn't that so precious? John 3 and verse number 16, a verse that we
commonly quote and understand, "...for God so loved the world that He gave His only
begotten Son, that whosoever believeth in Him should not perish, but have everlasting
life." And we must be careful about this subject and this teaching of Calvinism.
This isn't the only area in which they err, but you would find, and I'm not
seeking to be prideful or to get in arguments with people, people that watch
online, I'm sure, man, they'll send me emails and what-have-you, but the reality
is that the Bible teaches that Christ satisfied the sin for all of mankind.
His payment satisfied the requirement, not for our sins only, but also for
the sins of the whole world. That ought to cause us to rejoice. Listen, if you
understand this morning your place in human history, you'd understand that
you're one of the whole world. Amen? And you understand that Jesus died for you.
The song that they sang this morning, what a precious song. Aren't you thankful
that when you can hear the words of that song that you can identify and say, yes,
Jesus died for me. Praise God. Hallelujah. What a Savior. As we think about the
description that is provided of our Advocate, we then could ask this question,
not only how our Advocate is described, but notice with me the work that our
Advocate does. So precious as you'd really think of and understand this word
Advocate as really being the fact that He's our defense attorney. And really as
we look at this passage of Scripture, these verses here in verse 1 and 2, and
understand the truth that is being communicated to us, it is a perfect
illustration of what we find in 1 John 1 and verse number 9. If we confess
our sins, He is faithful and just to forgive us our sins and to cleanse us
from all unrighteousness. But how is that practically applied? How does that work?
What does it look like? The reality this morning is that in order to adequately
explain these verses of Scripture, I believe that we, in our mind's eye, must
enter into the courtroom. I'm thankful this morning that I've never been in the
courtroom standing on trial. Amen. I got called to jury duty once, so I got a
little bit of experience. We have some within our congregation that are
attorneys, lawyers, that have work in law enforcement and have experience being in
the courtroom, and so they might be able to relate a little better than some of
us, but no doubt we each have some level of awareness of what happens in the
courtroom. And as we enter into the courtroom in our mind's eye this morning,
if we can imagine the judge being God the Father, and He sits in His rightful
place as being the judge, and you find that the accuser is there. Who's the
accuser? Well, according to Revelation 12 in verse number 10, it's Satan. He is the
accuser. He is the accuser of the brethren, and he's there in this courtroom,
but I'm thankful that there's also our advocate, Jesus Christ the righteous. And
then there we stand, the accused, the defendant. And we stand in this courtroom,
and from your perspective, and I'll just come down here this morning so that I
can kind of look the same way you are. If I can get a picture of a courtroom, the
judge is here in the center. He's sitting upon the bench there, and perhaps at a
table over here is where I'm seated as the defendant, and I have my defense
attorney, Jesus Christ the righteous, standing by my side. And then over here
at this other table, there's the prosecutor, the accuser of the brethren,
Satan. And we find that as we're there in that courtroom, it's quite
different than what we might imagine in a court of law today upon earth.
Because our defense attorney, Jesus Christ the righteous,
He's actually not seeking to prove our innocence.
Why?
Because we're guilty.
A defense attorney, if you were thinking about in a court of law today,
and you were thinking about sitting in a courtroom and hiring a defense attorney,
and you're going to hire this one,
they're going to be on your side as your advocate to try to prove your innocence.
The accuser, the prosecutor, is seeking to prove your guilt.
Right? Is that how it works?
And the accuser, the brethren, he stands up in all of his terribleness,
and he accuses us of whatever the sin might be.
And as he accuses us, the accusation is made, and we know that we're guilty.
And Jesus Christ the righteous stands up,
and He does not seek to provide some level of proving innocence,
declaring on the behalf of us, the defendant,
some way in which we can have the case fall in our favor as being declared innocent.
No, the reality is that forgiveness requires guilt.
Do you know that?
Forgiveness requires guilt.
A court does not pardon an innocent man.
There's no need for a pardon. You're innocent.
Our defense attorney, can you imagine in your mind today,
as you think about Jesus Christ, our advocate, Jesus Christ the righteous,
that He stands and He says,
Father, He's guilty.
He's guilty. Guilty as charged.
Now, what do you think the prosecutor does?
Oh, man, this is wonderful. They're not even trying.
But then He says this, I paid the price.
I paid the price.
I satisfied the requirement that would be placed upon this one because of their guilt.
And in that courtroom, and in that setting,
as we think about this passage of Scripture illustrating for us so wonderfully,
the work that our advocate does,
that we find that Jesus Christ the righteous, our advocate,
He does not seek to defend us and to prove our innocence.
Rather, we find that He confirms our guilt,
but reminds the judge that the penalty has been paid.
It's satisfied. Isn't that wonderful?
And when you understand the portion of Scripture that is before us,
it ought to cause us to rejoice greatly.
To know that we have the perfectly qualified advocate,
Jesus Christ the righteous, His qualification is given to us,
and we find that He's standing there.
And the truth for every believer this morning,
for every single one of us is that, listen, we do sin.
Yes, the appeal is that you sin not.
But the reality is that we sin, and when we do,
we have an advocate.
We have an advocate.
And the accuser of the brethren is defeated every time.
Isn't that awesome?
He's defeated every single time.
When we look at the passage of Scripture and really find the truth of verse 9,
and how that is practically applied,
and the outworking of that truth as it's given to us in verses 1 and 2 of chapter 2,
I am thankful that as I confess our sins again,
an acknowledgment of the guilt.
I mentioned last week as we closed our passage of Scripture,
we closed our message last week,
it's not a desire or a seeking to excuse or to cover or hide our sin.
No, it's an acknowledgment of our guilt.
But what joy that He says that if we confess our sins,
He is faithful and just to forgive us our sins,
and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness.
As I thought about this passage of Scripture,
meditated upon the truth contained herein,
I could not help but think of a court of law in our land today,
and we understand that we do not have perfect justice in our system today,
but I think about being a guilty sinner as I am, and as you are.
You know how hard it'd be to find a defense attorney?
Charges have been brought against you.
You look up on Google,
I need a defense attorney, here's what the crime is,
here's what the situation is,
I need to have an attorney that's going to help me in this particular area.
And you have that opening phone dialogue with that attorney,
they begin to ask you about the charges that have been brought against you.
They begin to ask you what happened and the circumstances and so on and so forth,
and then ask you what happened,
and you simply say, I did everything that I'm charged with.
Well, that's going to be a tricky job for the defense attorney.
He's going to try to enter some kind of plea,
he's going to do whatever he can do to try to lessen charges, so on and so forth.
I'm guilty.
And our advocate says, I know you are, but I paid the price.
I paid the price.
And that old serpent, the accuser of the brethren, the prosecutor,
he brings those accusations against you and against me.
But we must be mindful that in that courtroom, we have an advocate.
And he's our defense attorney.
And as we determine in our lives that I'm not going to cover, excuse,
I'm not going to hide my sin, guilty as charged.
But Jesus paid for it.
And he is my advocate.
If you're saved this morning, he's your advocate.
I wouldn't want to enter the courtroom without an advocate.
Amen?
The Bible tells us of a great white throne in Revelation 20, verses 11 through 15.
Those are not saved people.
They do not have Jesus Christ the righteous as their advocate.
And the sentence is given out in what is it?
The lake of fire, the second death.
Right?
But for us this morning, if we're saved, if you've trusted Jesus Christ,
you're a savior, man, he is our advocate.
And he's our defense attorney, never seeking to argue our innocence,
but simply stating guilty but paid.
And that should cause us to rejoice greatly.
Listen, this morning as we look at these two verses of Scripture,
let us beware of the false teaching that seems to be prevalent in our society today.
Not just today, but for all of church history,
where the enemy has twisted the powerful biblical truth of the grace of God,
and the reality of the precious truth of the forgiveness of God,
in leading the people of God to thinking that they can sin freely
and live however they want to live because God's grace is abundant
and because God will forgive, and so just do what you want to do,
live how you want to live.
No, the grace of God is not to be answered with,
what shall we do then, shall we continue in sin that grace may abound?
God forbid.
And John says, I'm writing these things unto you that ye sin not.
That we come to that place as we walk in the light,
as we feast upon His Word, as we walk in the Spirit,
that we're sinning less and less every day as we walk with Him.
That should cause us to, that appeal that is given,
should cause us to respond with examination.
To really, listen, if an individual has this idea that they can just go and live
however they want to live and just sin and sin and sin and just build up,
they really have to evaluate whether they're in the faith.
There's a man that I met many years ago, probably at this point,
probably close to 25 years ago, and he was living like the devil.
That's just being plain.
And he was boasting on a Sunday night after church, I wasn't saved,
it was in Jacksonville, North Carolina, young Marines,
they were outside talking and this guy was just bragging about all the sin
that he was involved in.
And I remember as a young teenager hearing this guy talk about this wickedness,
and here's what he followed up with it by saying this,
but I got saved and so I got my corner of heaven.
And I wasn't even saved at that point, but I thought,
that just doesn't seem right.
Right?
Just doesn't seem right.
The appeal is that we sin not, that we sin not.
It should cause us to reflect and respond with examination.
God's given us all of the tools necessary.
if I can use that phraseology to enable us to no longer be bound by sin, amen?
But then we should rejoice in this truth that there's an advocate for the believer, because
though my goal and though my aim, my ambition is that I would sin not, I'm going to sin,
and so are you.
You ever have a child that wants so desperately to please you as a parent, and then they fail,
they mess up.
Man, it can destroy them, just crush them, they're just so disappointed about them being
a failure and a disappointment to their parent, but you provide that way back for them, right?
And as we think about the reality is that though my goal and my aim is that I would
sin not, that when I sin, it does not lead to utter defeat.
But I understand and I acknowledge that I have an advocate, and all I must do is confess
that sin.
Yes, I'm guilty, it was wicked what I did, what I thought, what I said, God, would You
forgive me?
Listen, we ought to keep a short sin account with God.
What renders the believer so ineffective today is the way in which the enemy twists
these wonderful truths of the Word of God.
And you have people sitting in churches all across the world today that have been influenced
by some false teaching, and we've been rendered ineffective, and that's sad.
Listen, I want God to use me, I want God to use you.
He uses clean vessels, amen?
Not perfect.
I understand my standing, I'm perfectly justified in my standing, amen, 100%.
His righteousness has been imputed upon my account, amen?
2 Corinthians 5 verse 21, I am so thankful for that.
But practically, practically, I'm not perfect, and neither are you.
But we desire to be clean so that God can use us, amen?
There's an appeal to the believer that you sin not, but how we ought to rejoice that
we have an advocate.
There is an advocate for the believer, Jesus Christ the righteous, let's pray.
Father, we love You.
How we thank You for loving us.
God, I pray that if there were one present today that's not sure of heaven, that they
would understand how they could be saved.
Father, I think of this message, no doubt, starting out with my little children being
written and being delivered to save people.
I pray that as we examine that appeal, that we'd respond with examination and truly desire
to sin not.
As we walk with You, that we would be able to see in our lives that we sin less today
than we did before, because we're walking in the light.
And when we sin, would You help us to remember that we have an advocate?
Help us not to go about to try to prove our innocence or argue our innocence.
Help us to humbly acknowledge, confess our sin, knowing that it's been paid for and that
You promise to forgive.
Thank You for this wonderful truth.
Help us not to be influenced by false teaching.
Help us not to live thinking that we have a license to sin and live however we want.
Help us to have that desire to be a clean vessel fit for the Master's use.
Would You move and work in hearts and lives as only You can.
We'll be careful to give You the honor and glory for all that You'll do.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would You?