And turn in the word of God the book of Colossians and we'll be studying this year through this book as we had our introductory
Message last week looking at our theme from Colossians chapter 2 in verse number 10
When paul said to these that he's writing to in colossi and ye are complete
In him complete in christ complete in him
And as we dig into this book in the first chapter, we'll be looking at verses 1 through 8 this morning colossians
Chapter number 1 looking at verses 1 through 8
If you are taking notes in that new sermon notebook that you picked up yesterday
you will
Want to title the message this morning to the saints
At colossi to the saints
At colossi the bible says this in verse number one of colossians 1 paul
An apostle of jesus christ by the will of god
Timotheus our brother
And so we find right in the beginning of this book that god gives us the human penman to the book of colossians
And that being the apostle paul you understand that he says an apostle of jesus christ
Notice what it says by the will of god and the apostle paul understood that he was what he was by the grace of god
He understood the calling
That god had placed upon his life and he understood
Uh the great responsibility that he had
Uh, and what a joy and what a blessing to see a man who was yielded to the holy spirit of god
a man that was used to cause the
Instruct people and to uh be involved in the cause of christ moving forward
The bible says in timotheus
Our brother, we know that paul had a close relationship with timothy
Often even as you find he would refer to timothy as being his own son in the faith and you understand
They traveled and journeyed together. They ministered alongside one another and paul
invested in timothy and paul
instructed timothy and uh
We find that of course the bible would help us to understand the human penman and the human authorship
We understand that all scripture is given by inspiration of god and this is the word of god
But god would use paul humanly speaking to pen these words
The bible says in verse number two of colossians one to
The saints and faithful brethren in christ which are at colossi
Grace be unto you and peace from god our father
and
The lord jesus christ we will go down through verse number eight this morning in our study
But as we kind of give some background information to this church here this group of believers in the city of colossi
We would understand geographically that the city of colossi was located roughly a hundred miles east of ephesus
and as we would begin to think about the geography and we'd understand some things and
with regard to the city of colossi this ancient city that was
Uh very
Involved in trade and what have you at the time of the writing?
As paul is now addressing this group of believers. We'd understand that the
City had kind of already
Had its its highest days if you will it was a city in decline because of some
Changes with trade routes and so on and so forth, but we find that this city
Was was roughly a hundred miles east of ephesus
We understand when we think about the geographical location
Of this particular city of colossi that paul spent an extended period of time in ephesus
and the bible would tell us that during
the time that paul was in ephesus if you
Hold your place here in colossians and turn to the book of acts in the 19th chapter
And god is giving us some information here
In the book of acts with regard to the missionary journey and all that god would use paul and those that accompanied him
to accomplish for the cause of christ
The bible would tell us that while he spent this extended period of time in ephesus
That the gospel threat spread throughout asia
in fact
You will understand and keep your place there in acts 19, but you'll understand that in acts chapter number 16
when they were seeking the will of god with regard to
Taking the gospel forward the bible tells us that they were forbidden to the holy ghost
To preach the word in asia in acts 16 in verse number six
Though they had endeavored and desired to go to that region and it was when they were in ephesus as it's recorded in acts 19
Notice in verse number 10 the bible says this and this continued by the space of two years
What was it that continued the teaching of the word of god?
The instruction that paul was giving to those and the bible says so that all they
So that all they which dwelt in asia, excuse me heard the word of the lord jesus
both jews and
greeks now
As we notice acts 19 in verse number 10 and the bible tells us so that all they which dwelt in asia
Heard the word of the lord jesus both jews and greeks and we understand
That when the bible refers to here in acts 19 in verse number 10 to asia
Is speaking about that region that we would refer to as asia minor and we'd understand that the gospel was going forth
That paul was instructing the believers there in ephesus and people were hearing the gospel and they were taking the word of god
uh into their communities and into their
neighborhoods if you will and they were spreading forth the gospel
And the bible tells us that all they which dwelt in asia heard the word of the lord jesus both jews and greeks now
That's encouraging to me because that's the model that god has set forth. That is the plan
That jesus has established that the gospel would go forth into all the world and we find
That with colossi being a hundred miles roughly to the east of ephesus
That it is certainly possible that during the earthly ministry of the apostle paul in ephesus though
He himself never traveled to colossi
That we would understand that the gospel spread forth
And no doubt people in the city of colossi had the privilege of hearing the gospel
As I mentioned just a moment ago the apostle paul never personally ministered in the city of colossi
He did not know these believers
personally
In fact, if you read verse number one of chapter two the book of colossians
The bible says for I would that ye knew what great conflict I have for you and for them
At laodicea and for as many as have not seen my face in
The flesh the apostle paul never ministered personally in colossi. He did not know
By name the individuals that he's writing to in the book of colossians
It's interesting for as we look at other books of the bible that god would use the apostle paul to write
There are many times in which you see the personal influence and you find
The names of individuals that are
Referenced and you can go back to the book of acts and you can read about the time and ministry
Of the apostle paul amongst those very people that he's writing back to and that's not the case here with the book of colossians
however
As you read the book of colossians, you really get the sense you understand
the love and
Concern that paul had for each of these believers
Now that's encouraging to me. In fact, it is a challenge to me to see how the apostle paul had such
uh, just a desire
Uh for these believers in colossi believers that he never even met
But believers that he heard about their testimony. He received from epaphras this
Uh this report this testimony and paul has this love and genuine concern for these believers
And you find that as you read through and study the book of colossians
There will be some names that you recognize
Apaphras is one of them and we'll mention that as we go through the message even this morning
But as you get into the end of the book of colossians, you'll see a couple of additional names
In which you will recognize from some of the other writings of paul
uh and and some of the names of the individuals that are referenced in the book of colossians and so
As we look here and we think about this man epaphras the bible tells us
That he was a faithful minister
and
The individual that informed paul about the group of believers here in colossi
Look down at verse number seven in colossians one. The bible says as you also learned
Of epaphras our dear fellow servant who was for you a faithful minister
of christ
As we begin to think about the
geography if you will
Of colossi you begin to think about the way in which paul learned about this group of believers in colossi
It was through the testimony of epaphras that would bring this report
And paul would be informed and he would be aware that there's a group of believers in this city in colossi
that were
Assembling and growing and serving and what a blessing that must have been to the heart of the apostle paul
Unfortunately as we find throughout the history of the church
Here even in colossi we would find as we read through the book of colossians
That false teaching had crept in we understand the bible teaches us that there will be false teachers
We understand today that as we live in 2021
That there are many false
false teachers that abound.
It is so vital that we understand
that we are settled and grounded
in the truth of this Book.
How thankful we ought to be
as New Testament believers
that we have the complete canon of Scripture
and that we can go to the Word of God
and we can understand what
thus saith the Lord.
But these believers in Colossae,
there were some false teachers
that had crept in.
Now you understand.
When false teachers come into an assembly,
they do not wear a name tag
that says, I'm a false teacher.
They do not announce broadly
to the people that they're seeking
to come in and assemble with
and influence that they are false teachers.
No, as Jude would say it,
they creep in unawares.
They try to fly under the radar, if you will.
We have often said during the time of ministry here
that God has given me that false teachers,
one of the ways in which they operate
is that they will use the same words that we use.
They will use our vocabulary.
The problem is that they have a different definition.
They mean something entirely different
than we would mean by the very same words
that we would speak.
And it's so vitally important
that we are so grounded in the truth of this Word.
It was an unfortunate set of events
that led to this false teaching
creeping into the church in Colossae.
But how thankful I am
that the Lord would use His Word
to correct the false teaching
and to properly instruct the believers in Colossae.
I'm thankful that Epaphras was there,
a faithful minister of Christ.
Oh, what a blessing it is.
Even last year as we studied through the book of Hebrews
and we mentioned in Hebrews 13,
those 10 things that we ought to be thankful for,
that we ought to rejoice in.
And we mentioned about spiritual leaders
and how thankful we should be
for those that would be called,
that would be referred to as a faithful minister of Christ.
Someone who would stand up
and faithfully proclaim the truth of the Word of God
without compromise.
The Bible says that those that are preachers,
those that are pastors,
that were to preach the Word,
the instant in-season, out-of-season,
reprove, rebuke, exhort,
with all long-suffering in doctrine.
We understand that the time will come
when they will not endure sound doctrine,
but our responsibility is to preach the Word.
It may not be popular.
In fact, we're finding the closer we get
to the return of our Savior,
that it's becoming less and less popular.
But oh, I'm thankful for Epaphras,
who was a faithful minister of Christ,
who was engaged in helping these believers in God
through allowing Epaphras to communicate with Paul,
would then, under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
use Paul to send this letter,
the book of Colossians,
to properly instruct,
to correct that false teaching
and properly instruct these believers.
Oh, how thankful I am for the Word of God.
I'm thankful that the Word of God,
as I've referenced already this morning,
that passage in 2 Timothy 3,
that all Scripture is given by inspiration of God.
The Bible says,
and is profitable for doctrine,
for reproof, for correction,
for instruction in righteousness,
that the man of God may be perfect,
throughly furnished unto all good works.
I know I've said it often.
It's worth repeating.
We need more of this book, not less.
There's a popular movement within our world today
of we need less preaching.
We need less teaching.
We need more entertainment.
No, we need the Word of God.
In your life, in my life personally,
I need more of God's Word.
We've just now entered into the second week
of a brand new year.
I hope that you've made the decision
that in 2021 that you're going to read the Bible
more than you did in 2020.
That you're going to dig in.
That you're going to allow the Word of God
to impact and influence your life
to have its work and its way in your life.
We need more of God's Word, not less.
Someone said this,
that thumbprints in the Bible
are more important than footprints on the moon.
And I like it.
Because we need the Word of God.
Let me clarify, I am not simply saying
that you read it as fast as you can
to say I read the Bible ten times this year.
If you could, that's wonderful.
I endeavor annually, personally,
to read the Bible through several times.
But I would say to you,
as I've said to many people personally,
the quality is more important than the quantity.
To truly allow the Word of God to get into you.
That we truly determine that we're going to be
doers of the Word and not hearers only.
In this book of Colossians,
when it was originally sent
from the Apostle Paul to this group of believers,
oh, I'm sure it was a great encouragement
as we'll find as we read through
and study through this book,
to hear how Paul,
though they may have heard of him,
they never met him personally,
how he says, I'm praying for you.
And then he tells them how he's praying for them.
I mean, just the encouragement
that these believers would receive.
But then the instruction that they would receive
to correct that false teaching.
I'm so thankful that God's given us
the Word of God.
I believe that these original recipients,
the day in which they originally received
this letter that we refer to
as the book of Colossians,
that there was excitement.
That there was joy.
I mean, this was a big deal
that we've received a letter from Paul,
the Apostle.
I believe they were excited about it.
They understood that it was the Word of God.
They're going to set it aside.
I'll get to it later.
No.
They want to know the content of this letter.
I believe that it was impactful in their lives.
As we notice as we study through
this first several verses of Colossians 1,
I want you to notice with me,
number one, how they were described.
Notice how these believers
are described for us.
The Bible tells us that Paul's writing to them
in verse 1, but then notice the description
in verse 2.
The Bible says, to the saints.
To the saints.
We understand.
We've even titled the message this morning
to the saints at Colossae.
It will say, and faithful brethren in Christ,
which are at Colossae.
I'm so thankful for this word saint.
I would say to you this morning,
even as I mentioned a few moments ago
by way of introduction,
that there are those today
within the broad category of Christendom
that would use the word saint,
but they have a different definition.
They mean something entirely different
than what the Bible means
when the Bible uses the word saint.
The word saint.
It means holy one.
It means those who have been saved.
It means those who have been redeemed
by the blood of the Lamb.
A real good definition for saint is this.
One who is in Christ
and in whom Christ dwells.
A saint.
One who is in Christ
and in whom Christ dwells.
We find that Paul,
as he would write to the believers in Ephesus,
that he says to them
in v. 1 of Ephesians 1,
Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ
by the will of God,
to the saints, which are at Ephesus.
When he's writing to the believers in Philippi,
another church in which he had
the opportunity to minister to
and had the privilege of being able
to serve alongside,
he says here, Paul and Timotheus,
the servants of Jesus Christ,
to all the saints in Christ Jesus
which are at Philippi
with the bishops and deacons.
And then here in Colossians 1,
in v. 2, to the saints
and faithful brethren in Christ
which are at Colossae.
Oh, I'm so thankful for the recognition
at the very beginning of this book
that we'd understand that Paul
is writing to believers.
He's writing to people that have been born again.
To people that are saved.
They're referred to as saints.
One who is in Christ,
in whom Christ dwells.
Oh, what a blessing.
I want you to notice that not only
does he call them saints,
but he says, and faithful brethren.
Faithful brethren.
I love the description
of these believers in Colossae.
Saints and faithful brethren.
Faithfulness is to be commended.
It seems as if as we would go through life
and we'd understand various influences
of our culture and our society,
that it would seem as if by and large
the importance of faithfulness
has kind of not been where it needs to be.
But I would submit to you that as the people of God,
that faithfulness is to be commended.
We understand that God says
faithfulness.
This is required that stewards,
1 Corinthians 4 and verse 2,
that it's required in stewards
that a man be found faithful.
We understand that Solomon
in the book of Proverbs
would express the value of faithfulness.
The Word of God is full of examples
of both men and women
who were faithful.
They were faithful.
I'm so thankful that our God is faithful.
He is faithful.
In fact, we sing,
great is thy faithfulness.
You begin to think about the faithfulness of God.
I hope this morning that when your mind
would reflect upon the faithfulness of God
that you'd be encouraged
to know that our God is trustworthy
and dependable.
God is faithful.
But we find that these believers in Colossae,
that they are being referred to
as being faithful brethren.
Faithful.
I'm thankful for the faithfulness
of the people in Colossae.
The way in which they're described.
Paul says,
grace be unto you and peace from God our Father
and the Lord Jesus Christ.
Notice in v. 3 of Colossians 1,
we give thanks to God
and the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ
praying always for you.
We are going to use v. 3
in a future message
to begin to look at the prayer
that Paul records really
for these believers in Colossae.
In v. 9-14, he lets them know
how he's praying for them specifically.
But what a joy when you see
how the Apostle Paul is saying
to these believers in Colossae
that he is thankful for them,
that he's praying for them.
Notice in v. 4,
since we heard of your faith in Christ Jesus
and of the love which ye have to all the saints.
Paul heard about their faith in Christ Jesus.
He heard about their conversion.
He heard that they had been born again.
As you continue to look,
you find that the Bible would reveal to us
how the Gospel got there
and they believed.
It says in v. 5,
for the hope which is laid up for you in Heaven,
whereof ye heard before
in the word of the truth of the Gospel,
notice where it says in v. 6,
which is come unto you
as it is in all the world,
and bringeth forth fruit
as it doth also in you,
since the day ye heard of it
and knew the grace of God in truth.
I'm so thankful for the testimony
of these believers in Colossae
for the way in which they are described.
I'm thankful for their salvation.
I'm thankful that one day,
I mean, we'll have the opportunity
of seeing these believers in Colossae
that were redeemed.
They've been saved.
The Bible says that the dead in Christ shall rise first.
And what a joy for all of eternity
to be with the saved, the believers.
It says that it's come unto you.
What has come unto you?
The word of the truth of the Gospel.
Notice where it says,
as it is in all the world.
The job of New Testament believers
is to preach the Gospel to every creature,
to go into all the world
and preach the Gospel to every creature.
I'm thankful that the Bible
would rehearse for us
and provide us with a record
of how the Word of God,
the Gospel of Jesus Christ
went in all the world.
Notice where it says in v. 6,
right in the middle of the verse,
"...bringeth forth fruit."
You know, this is a great promise
that we need to hold dear to our hearts.
The Bible says that the Gospel
bringeth forth fruit.
We understand that Paul said this in Romans 1
in v. 16 that he's not ashamed
of the Gospel of Christ,
why? For it is the power of God unto salvation.
And we find that we're to preach the Gospel
to every creature,
but we notice here in v. 6
that the Bible says that the Gospel
brings forth fruit.
The Gospel.
It brings fruit.
See, the seed of the Gospel
needs to get out of the barn.
There's no point in keeping the seed of the Gospel
in the barn. No.
There's a lost and dying world
that needs the Gospel.
And the Gospel brings fruit.
It produces fruit.
It is the power of God unto salvation.
It is the means that God has determined
that we would preach the Gospel to every creature.
And he says that it doth,
it says this,
"...and bringeth forth fruit
as it doth also in you."
So, understand with me
what Paul was saying to these believers in Colossae.
Understand with me personally
if we were to understand that I've been saved,
you've been saved,
you've trusted Jesus as your personal Savior,
and you can take the truth
of this passage of Scripture
and apply it in your own heart
and your own life,
that I've received the Gospel.
I've believed Jesus Christ.
I've trusted Him as my personal Savior.
I've been born again.
I can be referred to as a saint
because I am in Christ
and Christ dwells within me.
And we find here
that it brought forth fruit in me.
And it gives me the confidence
that it has the ability
to bring forth fruit in others.
What did the Gospel do for you?
Aren't you thankful that someone
didn't look at you and say,
yeah, I don't think the Gospel can work for them?
I think we'll go somewhere else.
They don't look like they're interested.
Oh, I'm thankful
for the power of the Gospel in my life.
I'm thankful for the fruit
that it's brought forth in my life.
But I'm encouraged as I read verse 6
as the Bible tells me,
listen, it doth also in you,
it brought forth fruit in me,
but it's gone not only to me,
it's gone into all the world.
And it bringeth forth fruit.
This morning, I hope that we'd be challenged
by the thought of v. 6.
Yes, as we are encouraged
by the way in which these believers
are described,
that we would be challenged
that the Gospel would go forward
and that it would bring forth fruit.
You say people don't want to hear.
Says who?
By the way, our job has never been
to make people hear.
Our job has been to give the Gospel.
To just go forth
and preach the Gospel to every creature.
And we can have the faith
and the confidence
that it will bring forth fruit.
This is God's way.
And shall I say this morning
that God's way works.
God's way needs not improvement.
God's way needs not to be updated.
God's way just needs to be worked.
We just need to do it.
We just need to do what God said.
So often,
we can sit around in these little group sessions
and have these conversations.
Periodicals are written.
Seminars are held.
How to church growth.
Reaching a community.
We just need to do what God said
and just preach the Gospel.
We notice not only how they are described,
but I want you to notice their love displayed.
Notice their love displayed.
Go back with me to verse number four.
I want you to pick up on what Paul says
that he heard from Epaphras
because it's obvious that he,
if you look in verse number eight,
who also declared unto us your love in the Spirit.
So Epaphras was the man that God would use,
the servant of the Lord that God would use
to be a faithful minister there in Colossae,
but also to bring word to Paul
about this group of believers.
And Paul says in verse number four,
since we heard of your faith in Christ Jesus,
what a blessing to hear about their faith,
their salvation.
But notice what else he heard.
And of the love which ye have to all the saints.
We notice how these believers are described,
but we also notice their love displayed.
The love which ye have to all the saints.
Again, in verse number eight it says,
who also, speaking of Epaphras,
declared unto us your love in the Spirit.
Hold your place here in the book of Colossians
and turn back to the book of John
in the 13th chapter, if you will.
And I know that it's a familiar verse
of passage of Scripture.
In fact, on Wednesday evening,
as we dealt with John 14,
this past Wednesday evening,
I made some reference to John 13.
But I want you to notice what Jesus says.
Read the verses with me.
In John 13, in verse number 33,
Jesus says this.
Let me back up to verse 31 and catch it in context.
The Bible says,
therefore, when He was gone out,
Jesus said, now is the Son of Man glorified
and God is glorified in Him.
When it says there in verse number 31,
He was, therefore, when He was gone out,
that's speaking of Judas Iscariot.
Of course, if you look back
into the preceding text of Scripture,
you'll see how that He was the one
that would, of course, betray the Lord Jesus Christ.
And it says in verse 32,
if God be glorified in Him.
but God shall also glorify Him in Himself
and shall straightway glorify Him."
Verse 33,
"'Little children,
yet a little while I am with you.
Ye shall seek Me,
and as I said unto the Jews,
whither I go ye cannot come.
So now I say to you,
a new commandment I give unto you,
that ye love one another,
as I have loved you,
that ye also love one another.
By this shall all men know
that ye are My disciples,
if ye have love one to another.'"
Isn't that a powerful passage of Scripture?
Jesus says,
"'A new commandment I give unto you,
this new commandment is that you love one another,
as I have loved you.'"
You think about the love of God.
You think about the love of the Lord Jesus Christ.
It says that He loved Him unto the end.
He loves us with an unconditional love.
He loves us with a sacrificial love.
And here the Bible says that we're to love one another.
And then Jesus says this,
"'By this shall all men know
that ye are My disciples.'"
Do all men know that we are the disciples of Christ
by observing how we love one another?
I mean, we look at the church in Corinth
and it's full of divisions
and all kinds of difficulties
that they're dealing with.
I mean, I'm of Paul, I'm of Cephas,
I'm of Apollos,
and there's divisions and there's carnality.
Surely the love of Christ
was not undisplayed by those believers in Corinth.
But Jesus said that we're to love one another.
He said this is the way in which men are going to know
that you're My disciples if you have love one to another.
The church in Thessalonica,
turn to 1 Thessalonians 4 if you will.
The church in Thessalonica
had been properly instructed
and they understood this truth of brotherly love.
Of loving one another
as Jesus commanded in John 13.
Paul would write to this group of believers
in 1 Thessalonians 4 in particular.
And I want you to notice with me
in v. 1 of 1 Thessalonians 4,
the Bible says,
"...furthermore then, we beseech you, brethren,
and exhort you by the Lord Jesus
that as ye have received of us
how ye ought to walk and to please God,
so ye would abound more and more."
See, these believers in Thessalonica,
they were being instructed.
And specifically,
they're being taught about brotherly love
in verses 9 and 10.
If you skip over and look at those verses,
look at what the Bible says
as Paul is continuing to instruct these believers.
He says, "...but as touching brotherly love,
you need not that I write unto you.
For ye yourselves are taught of God
to love one another.
And indeed, ye do it toward all the brethren
which are in all Macedonia."
Isn't that a great testimony?
Paul says to these believers in Thessalonica,
he says, I want you to understand
that we've taught you how you've received of us
how you ought to walk
and how you ought to please God.
And it pleases God when we obey Him.
And as we look here in this subject
of brotherly love,
Paul says, I don't need to really write this unto you
because you know you're taught of God
to love one another,
and indeed, ye do it toward all the brethren
which are in all Macedonia.
What a joy and what a blessing.
What a great testimony
this church in Thessalonica had
with regard to brotherly love
and with loving one another.
But notice what he says.
But we beseech you,
the end of verse 10,
but we beseech you, brethren,
that ye increase more and more.
Don't get comfortable with where you are.
Increase more and more.
I mean, what a joy.
I often hear about folks
that would say of our church,
even though 2020 was a different kind of a year,
we didn't have as much opportunity for fellowship
and so on and so forth,
but I often hear over the years
of folks that would say
the genuine concern and love
that the believers,
that the members of the church
have one for another.
Praise the Lord.
That's how it's supposed to be.
Amen?
We love one another.
In 1 Peter 4,
in verse 8,
Peter says this,
and above all things,
have fervent charity among yourselves.
Have fervent charity among yourselves.
John would say in 1 John 4,
now understand that John was there
in John 13 as we read that portion of Scripture
where Jesus gave that new commandment.
The Apostle John was there.
And now many years later,
God would use the Apostle John
to pen the book of 1 John.
And in 1 John 4 and verse 7,
the Bible says,
Beloved, let us love one another,
for love is of God.
And everyone that loveth is born of God
and knoweth God.
Let us love one another.
You see, as I go back to the book of Colossians,
and I notice in these first few verses
of this book that we're going to study
throughout this year,
and we'll get through all of it,
and as we get through the book of Colossians
and we're introduced to these believers
in Colossae,
when we have the privilege of understanding
what Paul heard of them,
how he received from Epaphras
this word about these believers
over in this city of Colossae,
and he heard about their conversion.
He heard about their position in Christ.
He heard about the way in which
the Gospel got to their city
and how there were many that trusted Christ.
And they were there,
and we see how they're described,
but we notice what is displayed,
their love that is displayed.
He says,
And of the love which ye have
to all the saints.
To all the saints.
I think it's interesting that it says
to all the saints.
Because it's not supposed to be like,
well, I love them,
but that one over there
is kind of difficult to deal with.
They kind of rub me the wrong way.
Our personalities kind of throw that out.
We're to have love one for another.
By the way, we should be happy
that not everybody is exactly like we are.
Amen?
Because if everybody is exactly like you were,
if everyone is exactly like I was,
whoo, it'd be a rough place.
Honestly.
Sometimes I annoy myself.
And if everybody else was like me,
it'd be problematic.
God's made us all different.
We're to love all the saints.
The Bible says that Paul heard of their faith,
but it also shows us of their love
that was displayed.
And of the love which ye have
to all the saints.
How are we doing?
I hope that we're following
the instruction of Christ in John 13.
I hope that when people would observe us,
they'd say, man, they love each other.
They love each other.
And it's genuine.
Notice with me,
not only how these folks in Colossae
are described,
not only do we notice their love being displayed,
but I notice in these first few verses
of Colossians 1,
I notice that they had been discipled.
They'd been discipled.
Notice with me in verse 7,
two phrases in this particular verse of Scripture.
The Bible says,
as ye also learned of Epaphras.
Now, Paul calls him our dear fellow servant.
You understand that Paul and Epaphras,
they have the opportunity.
As you read the book of Philemon,
you'll see some reference to Epaphras
there in the book of Philemon.
We won't take time to turn there,
but you see that Paul refers to Epaphras
as our dear fellow servant.
But you notice that the Bible says,
as ye, speaking of the believers in Colossae,
as ye also learned.
That's the key word I want you to focus upon that.
They have learned of Epaphras.
Notice what it says,
who is for you a faithful minister of Christ.
Now, someone that is a faithful minister,
there's some criteria that would go along
with that terminology.
You understand that there's a reference
to a good minister, a faithful minister.
Listen, Paul was not just throwing out
accolades to Epaphras.
This is the Word of God.
What made this man a faithful minister?
What made him a good minister?
Well, hold your place here in Colossians.
Turn to the book of 1 Timothy, if you will.
I'm glad that you asked the question this morning,
and you'd be interested.
in knowing why is Epaphras,
why is it that he's referred to
as a faithful minister of Christ?
Well, Paul says this in 1 Timothy 4.
I won't take the time to read the first five verses,
but I would encourage you to read
as the Bible gives us some interesting truth
with regard to the description
of the latter times
in which we're living, no doubt.
But notice verse 6 of 1 Timothy 4.
If thou... who's he speaking to?
He's speaking to Timothy.
That's who the book is written to.
He says, if thou put the brethren
in remembrance of these things,
thou shalt be a good minister
of Jesus Christ,
nourished up in the words of faith
and of good doctrine
whereunto thou hast attained.
The Apostle Paul says, listen,
you need to do these things,
and as you would do these things,
and as you would put them,
the people that you've been called to lead
and minister to,
as you would put them in remembrance
of these things,
then you would be acknowledged
as being a good minister of Jesus Christ.
We understand that Paul gives instruction.
He does not use the specific terminology,
but in 2 Timothy 4,
when he says to Timothy,
I charge thee therefore before God
and the Lord Jesus Christ,
who shall judge the quick and the dead
at His appearing in His kingdom,
preach the Word,
be instant in season, out of season,
reprove, rebuke, exhort with all longsuffering
in doctrine, for the time will come
when they will not endure sound doctrine,
but after their own lusts shall they
heap to themselves teachers
having itching ears.
They shall turn away their ears from the truth
and shall be turned unto fables.
But watch thou in all things,
endure afflictions,
do the work of an evangelist,
make full proof of thy ministry.
Paul says to Timothy,
you're going to be a good servant,
a good minister, a faithful minister,
preach the Word.
Peter says this to the individuals
that he's writing to in 1 Peter 5.
We find that the focus
of this particular few verses
to look at what we're focusing on here
this morning in this passage of Scripture
is that he's speaking to the ministers,
to the pastors, to the leaders of the church.
Notice with me in verse 1 of 1 Peter 5.
The elders which are among you I exhort,
who am also an elder
and a witness of the sufferings of Christ
and also a partaker of the glory
that shall be revealed.
Notice what he tells these elders,
these pastors, these leaders,
these spiritual leaders.
He says,
feed the flock of God which is among you,
taking the oversight thereof,
not by constraint, but willingly,
not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind,
neither as being lords over God's heritage,
but being in samples to the flock.
Notice this,
and when the chief shepherd shall appear,
ye shall receive a crown of glory
that fadeth not away.
Now, verse 4 encourages me
as a pastor,
as one that would take this responsibility
that has been placed upon me,
being called into the ministry
and God enabling me.
The Bible says that when the chief shepherd shall appear,
I'm thankful that the chief shepherd's coming back.
But the Bible says,
ye shall receive a crown of glory
that fadeth not away.
Can I say that everyone that calls themselves a pastor,
everyone that fills the office of elders,
is not going to receive this reward?
Why? Because they're not feeding the flock of God.
They're not being a faithful minister.
They're not being a good minister.
I long to please God.
I long to be a faithful minister,
a good minister,
one who feeds the flock of God,
that fulfills the responsibility,
that would have the testimony of Epaphras
here in Colossians 1 and verse 7.
A faithful minister of Christ.
But we're noticing how they had been discipled.
They had been discipled, no doubt, by Epaphras.
This faithful minister of Christ.
We understand that the Great Commission is our mission.
The Great Commission is our mission.
As a local New Testament church,
we have our marching orders.
We're not waiting for instruction from Heaven
on what we're supposed to do.
He's already given us the instruction
in the Word of God.
The Great Commission is our mission.
Oh, we need to have focus upon what our mission is.
What happens with businesses,
with corporations over the years,
you can see where they lose their focus
of what their mission is.
Most companies, most corporations,
entities, they have a mission statement.
What's the purpose of their mission statement?
To communicate what their purpose is.
To communicate what their mission is.
At times, if they're not careful,
they can get distracted, detoured.
They can lose focus of what their real mission is.
Can I tell you that the enemy wants to distract us
as the people of God from what our mission is?
He wants us to get caught up in all kinds of things.
He wants us to get detoured and distracted
by all sorts of things that are going on in our world today.
But we must refocus upon what our mission is.
And the mission for the local church
is the Great Commission.
Notice that the Great Commission,
as we would speak about it,
we would understand that discipleship
is a vital part of this mission.
I'd invite you to look over to Matthew 28
as we conclude this morning.
We notice how these folks are described.
We notice their love that's displayed,
but we also take note that they had been discipled.
The Great Commission is our mission,
and discipleship is a vital part of that mission.
In Matthew 28 and verse 18,
Jesus came and spake unto them.
This is after His death, after His burial,
after His resurrection,
just prior to the ascension of Jesus Christ.
He's giving instruction to His people,
His followers, and He says,
all power is given unto Me
in heaven and in earth.
Notice this,
Go ye therefore and teach all nations.
What are we to teach them?
The Gospel.
The death, burial, and resurrection of Jesus Christ.
Baptizing them in the name of the Father
and of the Son and of the Holy Ghost.
Baptism always follows salvation.
We do not believe in infant baptism.
We believe in believer's baptism by immersion.
After you have accepted the Lord Jesus Christ
as your personal Savior,
that you follow Him in believer's baptism.
It pictures the death, burial, and resurrection
of Jesus Christ.
It shows that we're to be dead to the old self
and rise to walk in newness of life.
See, there is a proper mode of baptism,
but there's also a proper candidate for baptism.
Remember the Ethiopian eunuch
when he says there in Acts 8,
here's water, what doth hinder me to be baptized?
And I'm so thankful that Philip was able to say
with great confidence that if you believe
with all thine heart, thou mayest.
He said, I believe!
And he said, stop the chariot,
let's get this guy baptized, amen?
So the Great Commission teaching all nations,
giving the Gospel.
Number two, baptizing.
Number three, verse number 20,
teaching them.
Who's them?
That's the converted people.
The people that have been saved.
The people that have been baptized.
Teaching them, notice what the Word of God says,
to observe all things,
whatsoever I have commanded you.
And lo, I am with you always,
even unto the end of the world.
Amen.
Far too often,
the Great Commission stops at verse 19.
Discipleship ministry of a local church
is imperative.
It's key.
That believers are discipled,
that they're taught to observe all things
whatsoever I have commanded you.
It's the responsibility of the leadership
of the church to provide discipleship,
that teaching.
Oh, discipleship happens from the pulpit
as the Word of God is taught and preached.
Discipleship happens in classrooms.
Discipleship happens having coffee.
Discipleship can happen in a number of ways.
As the Word of God is given and instructed,
and a person, an individual that has been saved
sits and hears and receives the instruction.
And as they receive that instruction,
they're to be doers of the Word,
not hearers only.
And we see how the Word of God
would spread forth
and how the cause of Christ would move forward.
I'm so thankful that Jesus has promised
to be with us as we go to fulfill
this Great Commission.
But as I look at the church in Colossae,
I notice that they had been discipled.
They had been taught.
As you also learned of Epaphras,
our dear fellow servant,
who was for you a faithful minister of Christ.
I'm thankful that Epaphras taught
Word of God. But you know, these believers had to show up to receive the
instruction. Amen? He could have discipleship class. Hey, we're gonna have
discipleship class on Tuesday night at whatever time. Who's gonna show up?
There's a desire to learn, a desire to grow. I want to know the Lord Jesus
Christ. I want to be discipled. I want to be instructed. This morning, as we're
introduced to these believers in Colossae, we learn a little bit by way of
introduction of where the city was and some of the things that were going on.
But I want you to notice how they were described. Saints. Faithful brethren. I
want you to notice their love that was displayed. How that they loved all the
saints. And then I want you to notice that they were discipled. They were
growing. They're being taught. Oh, that God would help us to be encouraged by
reading about this church in Colossae. Oh, that God would help us to be challenged
in our own walk with Christ. Have you been saved? Perhaps there's one that's
tuned in this morning that's never trusted Christ as their Savior. You
couldn't be referred to as a saint or a faithful brethren, but today is the day
of salvation. The gospel brings forth fruit. Jesus died for you. He was buried
in a borrowed tomb and he rose conquering sin, death, and the grave. And
the Bible says, for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved.
Maybe today you need to be saved. This morning we're challenged by the love for
the saints, the love for the brethren. Maybe this morning we're challenged by
our discipleship. How are we growing? Are we involved in discipleship? Are we
eager to learn, to be discipled, to be taught the Word of God? The saints at
Colossae, let us pray. Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. We thank you
for the book of Colossians. Thank you for this group of believers in Colossae where
the gospel reached and souls were saved. It brings forth fruit. The gospel does.
We're challenged by that truth. We're challenged to give the gospel, to preach
the gospel. I pray that you'd work in hearts and lives as only you can over
the next few moments of invitation. God, help us to be doers of the Word and not
hearers only. If there's one that needs to be saved, I pray that today would be
the day of their salvation. The Holy Spirit of God would convict them of
their sin, of Christ's righteousness and of judgment to come. God, I pray that
you'd help us to long to be like thee, to know thee, to grow in our walk with thee.
Have your will and way in these few moments, for it's in Christ's name we
pray. Amen.