you will, and in the book of Nehemiah, and looking at this portion of Scripture, Nehemiah
chapter number 4, and as we get to that passage of Scripture, I want to remind you of something
that the Apostle Paul said as he was ministering there to the believers in Corinth.
Of course, we understand that God allowed the Apostle Paul to minister in Corinth for
an extended period of time, and during that time of ministry, a church was established,
and then God would use Paul to write two letters back to this church, instructing
them with regard to their walk with the Lord, and of course, with various things within
the church, but Paul mentioned this in 1 Corinthians 16, in verse number 9, he said,
For a great door and effectual is opened unto me, and then he ends the verse by saying this,
And there are many adversaries.
There are many adversaries, and this evening, I want to preach a message that I've entitled
There Are Many Adversaries, but we're going to look at Nehemiah chapter 4 with that thought
of what Paul said in 1 Corinthians chapter number 6.
The reality is that for most of us, it is easy to acknowledge that we have an enemy.
The Bible declares that we have an enemy, and we understand that the enemy, that we
are engaged in spiritual battle, it's not flesh and blood that we wrestle against, but
spiritual wickedness in high places, and we understand that truth, and we understand that
throughout the scriptures, that the Lord has given us a number of accounts to help
us understand how the enemy operates.
As we have the opportunity to read much of the accounts, or many of the accounts, I should
say, in the Old Testament, that as we read those accounts, we have the opportunity to
get insight as to how the enemy is working.
It's not simply a lesson in history, though it contains an accurate historical record,
and as we look at the accuracy of the historical record, if we end there, we miss the spiritual
application, and so it's imperative for us to understand that God's not simply giving
us the history, though he is.
He's giving us truth to help us understand the way that the enemy operates, and really,
it enables us to be better equipped for the battle.
As we look at Nehemiah, we're going to be in chapter number four, and I want you to
understand some things that are taking place as we get into chapter number four this evening.
Obviously, we've not been studying through the book of Nehemiah, and we're jumping in
chapter number four, and so just briefly, I want to give you some information.
Nehemiah, of course, was not in Jerusalem at the beginning of the book.
As it's being written, the people of God had been carried captive already at this particular
time in their history.
Of course, a remnant was returning under the decree of Cyrus, and we understand that as
we look at the passage of Scripture, that in the very first chapter, that God gives
us some insight as to the concern that Nehemiah has for his home country.
The reason we know that he's concerned is because he inquired, and he made inquiry as
to what was going on, and he received a report, and part of the report that he received, according
to Nehemiah 1 and verse number three, is that the wall of Jerusalem also is broken down,
and the gates thereof are burned with fire.
As we go through the book of Nehemiah, we begin to see the work that is taking place
on rebuilding the walls.
We understand that it's in the second chapter that Nehemiah makes his petition, if you will,
to King Artaxerxes with regard to going and fulfilling the work that God had called him to.
We read in chapter number three, if you were to read the entirety of the chapter, you begin
to see how the rebuilding of the walls and the workers are assigned, and as you go through
the passage, you'll find at the beginning of verse number two, and many of the verses
thereafter will say, and next unto him, and then it will name some people, and they were
working on this part of the wall, on this particular gate, and then next unto him there
was this group of people, and so on and so forth, and so we kind of see what's happening.
Even before we get to the fourth chapter, at the end of chapter number two, we're made
aware of some of the opposition.
They're named by name at the end of chapter number two.
The Bible tells us in verse number 19, but when Sanballat the Horonite and Tobiah the
servant, the Ammonite, and Geshem the Arabian heard it, they laughed us to scorn and despised
us and said, what is this thing that ye do?
Will ye rebel against the king?
I love the response that is recorded for us in verse number 20.
It says, then answered I them and said unto them, the God of heaven, he will prosper us.
Don't you like the faith of Nehemiah?
He said, therefore, we his servants will arise and build, but ye have no portion, nor rite,
nor memorial in Jerusalem.
The workers are assigned, and we come to chapter number four, and the Bible begins in verse
number one, and it says this, it came to pass that when Sanballat heard that he builded
the wall, he was wroth and took great indignation and mocked the Jews.
As we enter into the fourth chapter, we find that the Bible would give us the record that
he, Nehemiah, is saying that the enemy, Sanballat in particular, that he heard that we builded
the wall.
Can I tell you that the enemy is content if we're not making progress?
You're not going to mess with us if we're not doing anything.
But when you try to do something for God, you begin to have some opposition.
You begin to deal with the enemy opposing the work of God.
As you take notes this evening, I want you to consider first of all with me the plan
of the enemy.
We find that the enemy, the plan is revealed throughout the passage.
We'll go through a number of verses here.
You find that in verse number one, the Bible says that they mock the Jews.
There are times in which the enemy will mock the people of God, will mock that which we're
seeking to do.
And we find that it says in verse number two, and he spake before his brethren in the army
of Samaria and said, what do these feeble Jews?
Will they fortify themselves?
Will they sacrifice?
Will they make an end in a day?
Will they revive the stones out of the heaps of the rubbish which are burned?
Now Tobiah the Ammonite was by him and he said, even that which they build, if a fox
go up, he shall even break down their stone wall.
Mocking them.
They're going to build a wall, but if a little fox were to climb upon it, it's going to fall.
We see the enemy, they have a plan.
Notice in verse number seven, as we continue to kind of dissect what's going on here, it
says it came to pass that when Sanballat and Tobiah and the Arabians and the Ammonites
and the Astrodites heard that the walls of Jerusalem were made up and that the breaches
began to be stopped, notice, then they were very wroth.
So what do they do?
They conspired, all of them together, to come and to fight against Jerusalem.
Notice where it says, and to hinder it.
Now it's interesting, as we note the progression that is made here, you find that the enemy
seeks to really discourage the work from even going forward.
The enemy seeks to come and mock and use the verbiage that is used here, these feeble Jews,
and talking about that even if they build it, if a fox were to go up on it, it's going
to break down their stone wall, and the enemy seeks to discourage us right on the onset
of even trying to do anything for God.
And when that discouragement doesn't cause the people of God to stop, we find that we
come to verse number seven and we see the plan further develop, because here's what
they heard.
They heard that the walls of Jerusalem were made up and that the breaches, notice, began
to be stopped.
How did they respond?
Then they were very wroth.
So now they have to increase their attack.
They need to do something else.
They need to go to level two, if you will.
I mean, if the mocking and that verbal opposition that is recorded for us in the first three
verses, if that works, then the enemy doesn't even have to expound any energy, effort, they
don't need to come and fight, they don't need to do anything.
But we find that they heard that the work was going forward.
It wasn't complete, but it was going forward.
So guess what the enemy does?
We need to go to the next step.
We need to increase our attack.
And we find that they are conspiring, notice in verse number eight, all of them together
to come up and to fight against Jerusalem.
It says, and to hinder it.
It's interesting as we move forward through the plan as it's revealed to us that yes,
the enemy wants to hinder the work, but their ultimate goal is not to simply hinder it.
They want the work to cease.
And we see that very obvious in verse number 11.
It says, and our adversary said, they shall not know, neither see, till we come in the
midst among them and slay them, and notice what it says, and cause the work to cease.
It's interesting to me as I know in verse number 11, really the approach of the enemy.
You notice that they say, they shall not know, neither see, till we come in the midst among
them.
We find that we would speak in the New Testament.
we understand some truth with regard to
Jude makes this statement
only one chapter in the book of Jude,
but we find that he says this
in v. 3,
that it was needful for me to write unto you
and exhort you that you should earnestly contend
for the faith which was once delivered unto the saints.
Why?
For there are certain men crept in unawares.
We're familiar with the terminology
that it's a wolf in sheep's clothing.
We're understanding the way
in which the enemy is deceitful
and the enemy tries to come in
and seeks to identify themselves
as being maybe one of us,
of seeking to deceive us through their approach.
Remember, the apostle Paul said
to the believers in Corinth in 2 Corinthians 11,
in v. 13,
he says, for such are false apostles,
deceitful workers,
notice what he says that they do,
transforming themselves
into the apostles of Christ.
And no marvel.
For Satan himself is transformed
into an angel of light.
Therefore, it is no great thing
if his ministers also be transformed
as the ministers of righteousness
whose end shall be according to their works.
John says that we're to try the spirits.
We find here that the enemy,
the adversaries as they're noted
in v. 11,
that they say,
here's what we're going to do.
They're not even going to know what happened.
They shall not know, neither see,
till we come in the midst among them
and slay them and cause the work to cease.
You see the progression in this plan
as it's really revealed to us.
And I know we've skipped around
because we're going to go back
and catch those verses that we skipped,
but you notice the plan of the enemy
that it begins with some mockery.
It begins with seeking to just simply
discourage you from ever getting off
the starting block, so to speak.
And then we find that they say
we're going to go and fight against them.
And we find that they want to hinder the work.
And then we find that really ultimately
their goal is to cause the work to cease.
The enemy's not satisfied with simply hindering the work.
They want it to cease.
I'm thankful for the promises of God.
I'm thankful for Matthew 16 when Jesus said,
I will build my church and the gates of hell
shall not prevail against it.
I'm thankful for biblical promises that we have
with regard to the work of God,
the work of Christ and how we can prevail.
But we must be mindful that the enemy,
that there are many adversaries
and the enemy has a plan in his plan.
Remember what Peter said.
I mentioned the very beginning of the message
that it's easy for most of us
to acknowledge that we have an enemy.
And we find that Peter says this
and understand that Peter understood.
Remember in Luke, it was Jesus when He said to Peter,
He said, Peter, Satan hath desired to have you
that he may sift you as wheat.
But then He gives them some encouragement.
He says, but I have prayed for thee.
I've prayed for thee.
And He says, when thou art converted,
strengthen thy brethren.
And God would use Peter to write first and second Peter.
And we find there in 1 Peter 5
that Peter begins to encourage
and strengthen the brethren
by reminding them that we have an enemy
and that He walketh about seeking whom He may devour.
We note, first of all, the plan of the enemy.
We note, number two, the prayer of God's people.
What a great response to the enemy.
To go to God in prayer.
Sometimes I feel as if in many of our lives,
throughout the history, I guess maybe, of our churches,
sometimes we have not fully acknowledged
the true power of prayer.
And we find here that the Bible says in verse number four,
after the mockery that we read of
in the first three verses of Nehemiah 4,
the Bible says,
Hear, O our God, for we are despised.
And turn their reproach upon their own head
and give them for a prey in the land of captivity.
I like how they prayed.
I like how they responded to that which the enemy was saying
and how the enemy was angry, of course, and mocking.
We find that they pray to God
and they say turn their reproach upon their own heads.
Give them for a prey in the land of captivity.
Notice in verse number nine,
after the enemy conspired all of them together,
according to what we read in verse number eight,
we find that in verse number nine,
the Bible says,
Nevertheless, we made our prayer unto our God
and set a watch against them day and night because of them.
We find that they were steadfast in prayer.
They understood the importance of seeking the face of God
and understanding what God is capable of doing.
We understand the many prayer promises
that God has given us in His Word.
We often quote those prayer promises.
We find that James would put it this way,
that the effectual fervent prayer
of a righteous man availeth much.
Prayer changes things.
Our God delights in answering prayer.
By the way, He delights in answering specific prayer.
We find they prayed specifically.
They not only prayed,
we find that they set a watch against them day and night
because of them according to verse number nine.
And we notice that as we look at the plan of the enemy,
we look at the prayer of God's people,
I want you to notice as we move through the text,
the power of God.
In verse number 12, it says,
It came to pass that when the Jews which dwelt by them came,
they sent unto us ten times.
Now, think about that.
Ten times.
I mean, the persistence of the enemy is noted.
From all places, whence ye shall return unto us,
they will be upon you.
Therefore said I in the lower places behind the wall
and on the higher places,
I even set the people after their families
with their swords, their spears, and their bows.
And I looked and rose up and said unto the nobles,
unto the rulers, unto the rest of the people.
So Nehemiah stands up, he's looking, he rises.
He says to the nobles, the rulers,
and the rest of the people,
notice what he says.
Be not ye afraid of them.
Remember the Lord, which is great and terrible,
and fight for your brethren, your sons and your daughters,
your wives and your houses.
And it came to pass when our enemies heard
that it was known unto us,
and notice what the verse says,
and God had brought their counsel to naught.
That we returned all of us to the wall,
every one unto his work.
At the end of verse number 20,
well, let's read the entirety.
It says in what place, therefore,
ye hear the sound of the trumpet,
resort ye thither unto us.
Our God shall fight for us.
Remember what Nehemiah said
as we made note of it at the end of chapter number two,
once those enemies were first revealed to us.
It's interesting, as Nehemiah gets into the city,
it says in verse number 11 of chapter two,
so I came to Jerusalem, I was there three days,
and we find that he begins to examine and go through
and begin to, I guess, get a report, if you will,
of what was going on,
and we find that he then reveals
what it is that God has put in his heart.
It's recorded for us in verses 17 and 18.
The enemy is made known,
and remember, Nehemiah answered them and said,
the God of heaven, He will prosper us.
So we've got to remember the power of God.
See, where we focus in the time of our adversity,
that we understand that our God is the Lord God Omnipotent
and that He reigns and He rules,
and we find that Nehemiah says,
be not ye afraid of them.
Remember the Lord, which is great and terrible.
We find that he's reminding them,
yes, we understand there's an enemy,
we understand they have a plan,
we understand what's going on,
but no, God brought their counsel to naught.
Why? Because we prayed.
We saw what God is able to do.
And he reminded them,
at the end of verse number 20,
our God shall fight for us.
We find many times, especially in the Old Testament,
it's noted the battle is the Lord's.
The battle is the Lord's.
And yes, we are to go in the power of God,
be strong in the Lord and the power of His might,
put on the whole armor of God,
and we understand that we are soldiers
and we are called to be engaged in the battle,
the spiritual battle that's taking place.
We acknowledge our enemy and what he seeks to do,
but we must understand that we go not in our own power,
but we go in the power of God.
The songwriter said the armor of flesh will fail you.
The songwriter was accurate in understanding that truth.
Remember, it was the Apostle Paul,
he said, I know that in me that is in my flesh
dwelleth no good thing.
He said this, he said, the things that I would, I do not.
The things I would not, that I do.
I mean, he understood the struggle
and all that goes with it,
but he said that the Lord would give victory,
that we are conquerors,
more than conquerors through Christ.
We see their enemy.
They have a plan.
The people of God pray.
The power of God is noted.
And I want you to notice as we conclude the chapter,
note the persistence of God's people.
The Bible says at the end of v. 15,
notice what it says after it tells us
how God brought their counsel to naught,
that we returned all of us to the wall,
every one unto his work.
See, God had a plan and a purpose
for this work that is recorded for us,
this historical account that is given to us
in the book of Nehemiah,
the rebuilding of the walls.
Remember, we revealed to you there
in the beginning of the book of Nehemiah
how that he inquired and he received word
that the people, yes, they were in great affliction
and reproach, but the wall of Jerusalem
was broken down.
The gates were burned with fire.
And as we begin to look at the work
that God had given Nehemiah to be engaged in,
it was to do this work.
He tells us there in chapter 2
that the people, they had a mind to work.
And what a blessing to understand
how they got back to the work.
It came to pass in v. 16,
from that time forth,
that the half of My servants wrought in the work
and the other half of them held
both the spears, the shields, the bows,
the habergens, and the rulers
were behind all the house of Judah.
They which builded on the wall
and they that bear burdens
with those that laid it.
Everyone with one of his hands
wrought in the work
and with the other hand held a weapon.
Can you see it in your mind's eye?
There was an enemy.
An enemy was seeking to cause the work to cease.
That was their goal.
And so they prayed and they were persistent.
They got back. They persevered.
They got back into the work.
They were going to move forward.
They understand there was an enemy.
And so, Nehemiah devises this plan
and they're working and they have
everyone with one of his hands wrought in the work
and with the other hand held a weapon.
The Bible says that the builders,
everyone in v. 18,
had a sword girded by his side
and so builded.
And he that sounded the trumpet was by me
and I said unto the nobles and to the rulers
and to the rest of the people,
the work is great and large
and we are separated upon the wall
one far from another.
In what place, therefore, you hear the sound of the trumpet?
Resort ye thither unto us.
Our God shall fight for us.
Notice v. 21,
so we labored in the work.
And half of them held the spears
from the rising of the morning
till the stars appeared.
Likewise, at the same time, said I unto the people,
and everyone with his servant
lodged within Jerusalem,
that in the night they may be a guard to us
and labor on the day.
So neither I nor my brethren
nor my servants nor the men of the guard
which followed me,
none of us put off our clothes,
saving that everyone put them off for washing.
I want to note something that's interesting
as to the work that they're engaged in.
Now, we're engaged in a work
that's a different work than the work
that they're engaged in.
We're not building a wall.
And that's not the work that we're doing.
We have a work to do.
Amen?
And remember, Paul said that we are
laborers together with God.
We're to put our hand to the plow.
We're to be engaged in the work of the Lord
and the service of the King.
And what a blessing it is to be able
to be engaged in the work that God is doing
and to be a co-laborer,
to labor together with God.
And we understand that as we're engaged
in this work that God has given us,
that we have a task to do
and that we have an enemy.
Many adversaries, Paul said,
we have an enemy that would like to hinder us,
that would like to cause the work to cease,
but we prevail, we persist,
we continue to move forward.
And we note that the Bible tells us
something interesting in verse number 18.
And he that sounded the trumpet was by me.
And then it tells us in verse number 20,
in what place therefore ye hear
the sound of the trumpet,
resort ye thither unto us,
our God shall fight for us.
And it reminds me as I would make
spiritual application this evening
and begin to think about our own lives
and the ministry that we're engaged in
and the work that we're doing,
I'm thankful that even as we look here
and he says that there were all of these people
that we're building,
and he says that the work is great and large,
and we are separated upon the wall
one from another in verse number 19.
The work that we're engaged in is a great work.
It's the Lord's work.
We're not building a wall,
but if we could make the application this evening,
I am thankful that there are local churches
all around the globe
that are seeking to do the work of the Lord,
that understand that our responsibility
is to preach the gospel of Jesus Christ.
It's the only hope for mankind.
The only hope.
And we preach the gospel
in every place that we can go.
It works on every continent of the world.
It works for any people group around the globe,
and we preach the gospel of Jesus Christ,
and we are engaged in that work.
Now, I'm thankful.
Listen, the reality,
yes, there are churches that are closing.
There are churches that are faltering
and so on and so forth,
but there are good churches around the globe.
There are good churches here in our county.
There are good churches in Virginia.
There are good churches in the United States of America.
There are good churches all around the globe.
We're all engaged in the same great work.
We're not all together in the same place,
but we're all engaged in the great work.
And here's the reality
that we're engaged in the work until when?
Until the trumpet of the Lord shall sound.
Amen?
Remember, at the end of the church age,
there's this wonderful thing that we call the rapture.
Some people criticize the rapture
because they say the word's not in the Bible.
Well, the word means caught up.
And the Bible tells us in 1 Thessalonians 4,
for this we say unto you,
by the word of the Lord,
that we which are alive and remain
unto the coming of the Lord
shall not prevent them which are asleep.
For the Lord Himself shall descend from heaven
with a shout, with the voice of the archangel,
with what?
With the trump of God.
And the dead in Christ shall rise first.
You know what Nehemiah said?
There's one that's near me with a trumpet.
And when the trumpet sounds,
everyone retreats together to this place
and the Lord's gonna fight for us.
And we find here that they were to be engaged in the work
until they heard the sound of the trumpet.
And I tell you, we're to be engaged in the work
until we hear the sound of the trumpet.
The songwriter said,
I don't know who wrote the song.
We've sung it many times.
Listen for the trumpet.
Jesus is coming.
And He is.
But we're not just sitting around
doing nothing waiting to hear the trumpet.
We're to be engaged in the work of the Lord,
redeeming the time.
Why?
For the days are evil.
Can we not see that the days are evil?
Oh, that we'd put our hand to the plow
and get engaged in the work,
understanding what God has for us.
And we're just working until we hear the trumpet.
And when the trumpet of the Lord shall sound,
man, we're going to heaven, amen.
The rapture of the church.
We're out of here.
Starts the seven year tribulation.
By the way, when you think about that understanding
prophetically of the book of Revelation,
you see all that takes place.
It's there in Revelation chapter number four,
chapters two and three deal with the seven churches in Asia.
The letters are written.
All of the information is given to those churches.
Yes, they were historical, literal churches
that were in those locales.
The message that is given to those churches
is applicable for churches even still today.
And it's important that we're mindful of the message.
But in chapter number four of the book of Revelation,
we find the Bible tells us that John, he heard a voice.
And the Bible tells us that the voice that he heard
said this, come up hither.
Begin to look at the passages in Revelation
that are recorded after this event.
Begin to speak about the tribulation period.
How God is working.
And how God is bringing His people Israel
to a place of acknowledging who He is as the Messiah.
We don't have time this evening to get into
all the eschatology.
But I want you to understand from the book of Nehemiah
in the fourth chapter,
I want you to be encouraged this evening.
You say, how can we be encouraged with a title
like there are many adversaries?
I thought the same thing as I was preparing, amen?
But the reality is that we can be encouraged
because we're more than conquerors in Christ
or through Christ.
We can be encouraged because we have a work
to be engaged in.
And the work that we're engaged in is a great work.
And when the work that we're engaged in,
when Jesus is gonna come,
He's gonna come with the trumpet is going to sound.
We read there in 1 Thessalonians chapter number four,
but we find also there in 1 Corinthians chapter 15,
behold, verse 51, I show you a mystery.
We shall not all sleep, but we shall all be changed.
In a moment, the twinkling of an eye,
at the last trump, for the trumpet shall sound.
The dead shall be raised incorruptible
and we shall be changed.
For this corruptible must put on incorruption
and this mortal must put on immortality.
Can I tell you, if I can put myself in the place of Nehemiah,
if I can put myself into the dialogue
of chapter number four of the book of Nehemiah,
they're working and they're working.
And if there's a group of people that come over
and come to where Nehemiah is,
Nehemiah says, what are you doing?
You didn't hear the trumpet sound, did you?
You stay engaged in the work.
The trumpet didn't sound.
But when he said that the one that sounded the trumpet
was Biden.
me. And so if there was a need for them because of the fact that there was a
level of vulnerability from a physical perspective because the work was great
and large they were separated upon the wall far from one another that if they
needed to all retreat and come to one place that Nehemiah would give the
signal and the trumpet would sound. And that's when they're all supposed to come
back to that place. And so if they start trying to retreat and get out of the
work and just want to be near Nehemiah and he says no no no go work. The trumpet
hasn't sounded. And for us New Testament believers as we understand if we could
make an application this evening listen the trumpet hasn't sounded. There's some
people out there trying to tell you that the return of Christ already took place
they needed to read their Bibles again. Amen.
Jesus listen the rapture hasn't taken place he hasn't returned yet. He's coming.
The return of the Lord draweth nigh. He's coming. We'll hear the trumpet. The
Bible tells us that we'll ever be with him. What a blessing. But until the
trumpet sounds we got to work. We got to work. The work that God's given us is a
great work. It's the work of preaching the gospel to every creature. Think about
that. 7 billion almost 8 billion people on our earth. A lot of people. It's a
great work. We continue to send people out. We continue to go out into our
community and around the world to do the work of God. When the work or excuse me
when the trumpet sounds we're gone in a moment twinkling of an eye. The work is
finished. Until then redeem the time. Get engaged in the work of the Lord. There
are many adversaries. He wants you to quit. He really likes you to just not
even get engaged in the work. Just be on the sidelines. Say yeah I don't know if I
want to get engaged in that. It's too too difficult, too hard, too whatever. No no.
We say we we've been enlisted in the army. Last week we looked at Archippus
right. He is a good soldier. A fellow soldier. What a blessing. Oh that God
would help us to be engaged in the work of the Lord. Father we love you. We thank
you for loving us. We thank you for the Word of God. The truth contained therein.
I pray God that you would help us to understand the historical account that
is given to us. I'm thankful to report that in chapter number six the book of
Nehemiah that it records for us that the walls were finished. What a blessing. Oh
the enemy continued to fight and to oppose and used different tactics. People
were persistent under the leadership of Nehemiah as he followed you as they
prayed. God we thank you for your power. We thank you for bringing it to pass.
Lord I pray as we consider an application for us this evening that
we'd understand that we're engaged in a work and it's a great work. It's an
honorable work. It's the greatest work to be able to give the gospel of Jesus
Christ which is the power of God unto salvation to everyone that believeth.
Lord I pray you'd help us to be faithful until the trumpet of the Lord shall
sound. We thank you for the truth that Jesus is coming and indeed we are
listening for the trumpet but I pray that you'd help us to be faithfully involved
in the work you've given us to do that we'd redeem the time. Understand that the
days are evil. Use us God in such a way that eternity would be impacted and you
would be glorified. Well thank you for it in Christ's name we pray. Amen.