And we were in the Old Testament and this morning back to our study through the book of 1st Timothy.
And our theme for this calendar year is continue.
We find that in 1st and 2nd Timothy we see many references to the idea of continue.
And the Apostle Paul is being used of the Lord to write to his son in the faith, Timothy,
and to encourage him to continue, to continue to do the work of the ministry,
to continue to do what God's called him to do.
And what a blessing.
I'm thankful that God gives us the strength and he gives us the truth that we need
in order to continue to endure.
Listen, we'll face opposition, we'll face adversity,
but with God's help and by God's grace we can continue to do what God has called us to do.
As we look this morning in 1st Timothy chapter 4,
I plan to preach through the entire chapter, the 16 verses here.
I'm going to read just a couple of verses and we'll get right into it this morning.
In verse number 1, notice the Bible says,
The nature of God is good and nothing to be refused if it be received with thanksgiving,
but sanctified by the word of God in prayer.
Notice verse 6,
If thou, Timothy, if thou put the brethren in remembrance of these things,
thou shalt be a good minister of Jesus Christ,
nourished up in the words of faith and of good doctrine,
whereunto thou hast attained.
I want you to look at verse 16.
It's actually our memory verse for the month of May if you've been working on it.
The Bible says,
Take heed unto thyself and unto the doctrine.
Continue in them, for in doing this thou shalt both save thyself and them that hear thee.
As we look at this passage of Scripture,
I've titled the message this morning this,
How is your diet?
If you look at verse number 6,
the Bible says right in the middle of that verse,
that we'll be nourished up in the words of faith and of good doctrine.
As you note the title for the message this morning,
you may immediately think of your physical diet,
and you might think of its nutrition level.
However, this is church, and I'm not a dietician.
Amen.
Praise the Lord for that.
I'm a pastor.
God's given me the responsibility of preaching the word of God,
and we find that God's word,
and here in this text of Scripture,
when I ask how is your diet,
I'm not referring to your physical diet.
I'm referring to your spiritual diet.
God likens his word to food,
and our text, as I've read already twice now in verse number 6,
speaks about being nourished up in the words of faith and of good doctrine.
1 Peter 2 and verse number 2 says,
As newborn babes desire the sincere milk of the word,
that ye may grow thereby.
We understand that as God would liken his word to food,
and even in that truth in 1 Peter 2,
he gives the understanding as newborn babes,
if you're saved this morning,
praise God for your salvation through the Lord Jesus Christ.
If you're not saved this morning,
you don't know that heaven is your home.
Today is the day of salvation.
It could be the day of your second birth.
We find that those that are born again,
we are babes in Christ.
You grow in your Christian life.
I've now had the privilege of knowing the Lord
and walking with the Lord for some 20, almost 7 years,
and I praise the Lord for that.
And the reality is that when I first got saved,
and when you first got saved, you were a babe.
I hope you're not still a babe, amen,
unless you just got saved recently.
Why?
Because we're to grow in grace and knowledge
of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.
And he says in 1 Peter 2,
As newborn babes desire what?
The sincere milk of the word,
that ye may grow thereby.
You know what babies need?
They need milk.
And he refers to the milk of the word,
but we find that in Hebrews 5 and verse 14,
God says this,
But strong meat belongeth to them that are of full age,
even those who by reason of use
have their senses exercised to discern both good and evil.
I'm thankful that there's the milk of the word,
but I'm thankful that there's the meat of the word.
You know, the more you, the longer you have been saved,
and the more you read the Bible,
and the closer you get to the Lord,
the more you find out how deep this book really is,
and the treasures within God's word,
and I'm so thankful for it.
As we think this morning about this question
that I've used to title the message this morning,
How is your diet?
As we look at this passage of scripture,
we see that there's some things that we ought to receive,
but there's some things that we ought to reject.
And we understand that as we look at this passage of scripture,
there's a continuity that is given throughout this portion
of God's word that helps us understand
the importance of our spiritual diet.
It's very interesting to me that when this book was written,
of course, in the first century,
the technology that is available today
was obviously not available then.
And even as the Apostle Paul would be used of God
to give this instruction and to provide this warning,
and to help the people,
Timothy and those that he's ministering to in Ephesus,
to understand the importance of receiving certain things
but rejecting other things,
how much more today we need the truth
of this portion of scripture.
I'm thankful this morning that God's word is perfect,
it's preserved.
I'm thankful that it's profitable.
I'm thankful that it is a book
that just goes beyond our ability
to fully understand the depths of the truth of this book
and the fact that it does not need to be updated.
No, we just need to follow the instruction
that God has given us.
It's a book that's been given for every people
throughout all of time because its author is eternal.
And what a blessing to understand that truth
and to comprehend it this morning.
And so if we're taking notes this morning,
we ask the question, how is your diet?
I'm going to give you a couple of thoughts.
Number one, you must be selective.
You must be selective.
What do I mean by that?
Well, not everything that is available
is to be consumed by the child of God.
Just because something is available,
just because something has a Christian title
doesn't mean that it should be consumed
by the child of God.
Understand this morning that there are many books,
that there are many pamphlets,
that there are blogs and videos,
and you think about the YouTube videos
that are available today,
and you look at all the blogs,
and I mean just so many things that are available
that would have a Christian title to them
that may have some catchphrases in them
that may at first appearance look to be
something that you could consume.
But I want you to understand this morning
that not everything that is available
is to be consumed by the child of God.
Not everything that's available
See, there are some things that are unhealthy.
There are some things that are unhealthy.
Notice what the Bible says in verse 1.
It says,
Now the Spirit speaketh expressly.
Notice what it says,
that in the latter times,
some shall depart from the faith,
and they're giving heed to seducing spirits.
Understand that we're engaged in spiritual warfare,
spiritual battle.
Listen, it is Satan, the enemy of God,
the enemy of God's people,
that said in Genesis chapter number 3,
Yea, hath God said.
It's the enemy, Satan, that in Genesis 3 says,
Ye shall not surely die.
And he continues to manipulate God's word,
and he continues to cause doubt and confusion,
and these demons, these fallen angels,
these false spirits,
we find that it says,
giving heed to seducing spirits.
Notice, and doctrines of devils.
It says this in verse 2,
Speaking lies and hypocrisy,
having their conscience seared with a hot iron,
forbidding to marry,
and commanding to abstain from meats,
which God hath created to be received with thanksgiving
of them which believe and know the truth.
And so we find that there's a warning that's given.
There's a couple of examples in verse number 3
of what these false teachers would teach
and this danger that is lurking.
We find that in verse number 7,
we speak about that which is unhealthy.
Notice what God says in verse 7,
But refuse profane and old wives' fables,
and exercise thyself rather unto godliness.
As we begin to think about that which is unhealthy,
see, the appearance of something doesn't determine
whether it's healthy or unhealthy.
In fact, there are many books that can be written
that have really nice graphics,
and I mean appealing titles,
and yet the content is not healthy for God's people.
There are those, listen, you understand
that the people that are false teachers
that are following what we see here,
that we as God's people are to refuse and to reject,
they do not begin their blog,
they do not begin their video by saying,
by the way, I'm speaking...
They're making lies and hypocrisy just to put it out there.
They don't start out that way.
No, they're deceptive, they're crafty,
they're seeking to lead astray
with craftiness and deceitfulness,
and we find this morning that we must be selective
because there are some things that are unhealthy.
In 1 Timothy chapter number one,
turn back a couple of pages,
and I want to remind you of what God revealed
in this first chapter that we studied many weeks ago now,
and we find that in verse number four,
notice what God says.
Neither give heed to fables and endless genealogies.
Notice what they do, which minister questions
rather than godly edifying, which is in faith, so do.
So they minister questions, they give this doubt.
They cause people to say, well, yeah, how could that be?
Listen, God says that he is a god of the impossible.
God is the one that created everything.
He is the one that sustains everything.
We must understand that as we look at the pages
of this book, and we'll mention some more about this
in just a moment, that God's word is powerful,
and it is truthful, and everything that it records
is accurate.
You say, well, I just don't understand how that could be.
It goes against the laws of he created.
He is God, amen?
And so guess what happens in a lot of these videos
and these blogs and these books, they minister questions.
They simply try to put a little doubt
in the mind of a believer, in the mind of an individual
that will destroy their entire understanding
and cause them to have no confidence whatsoever
in this precious book.
Why is there so much attack in Genesis one through 11?
Why are there so many that have attacked
the creation account, the flood account?
Why constant bombardment on those particular passage
of scripture?
Well, because if you can undermine, if you can discredit,
if you can discredit the first several chapters
of the book of Genesis, you've destroyed
the entirety of the Bible.
Because if God can't be trusted in what he said
in Genesis one, and what he said in Genesis two,
and what he said in Genesis three, and four, and five,
and six, and so on and so forth,
then how can we trust John 3.16?
Oh, but we want to trust John 3.16,
because for God so loved the world that he gave his own,
and if you don't believe that verse, sure you do.
But you can't have a redeemer without a creator.
He is creator, and he is redeemer.
And we rejoice in that.
Listen, there are some things that are unhealthy.
There are some things that the child of God
must simply refuse.
They must reject.
Let me say, I'm not gonna read that,
I'm not gonna watch that, I'm not gonna be influenced
by that, why?
Because it's unhealthy.
It's not good for me.
God said, without faith, it is impossible to please him.
For he that cometh to God must believe that he is,
and that he's a rewarder of them that diligently seek him,
in Hebrews 11, in verse number six.
Listen, we believe this book by faith.
Someone said, you mean to tell me that you believe
a whale swallowed Jonah?
Yeah.
And a preacher said this in response,
if God's word told me that a Jonah swallowed a whale,
I'd believe it, too.
Amen?
Why?
Because God's word is truth.
God's word is truth.
There's some things that are unhealthy.
In 1 Timothy 1, 4, we see how it ministers questions.
Notice in verse six, the Bible says,
from which some having swerved,
notice this, have turned aside unto vain jangling.
I love the way that that phrase is recorded for us
and really translated for us.
And it has this idea of useless talk.
Sometimes you listen to these,
and I hope you're not listening to them,
but you come across something,
and it's just vain jangling.
It's just useless talk.
It's just ministering questions.
It's not edifying.
It's not building up.
It's not honoring God.
It's not building up your faith.
We find that there's some things, again,
that we as God's people must simply refuse.
We must be selective.
Why?
Because there's some things that are unhealthy.
We must be selective.
Why?
Because there's some things that are healthy.
I'm thankful for God's word.
I'm thankful for resources that are available
that are helpful, that are healthful,
that God uses to build up our faith.
Notice the Bible says, we read already in verse number three,
notice the end of the verse.
The Bible says, to be received with thanksgiving,
notice this, of them which believe and know the truth.
I'm so thankful for truth.
We live in a world today that really, in many cases,
they don't want to know truth.
They don't want to be confronted with truth.
They don't want to acknowledge that God is who he is
and that he's given a Bible that is truth
because if they acknowledge that,
then they're accountable to that.
And so man wants to, quote unquote, create their own truth.
They want to say, well, that's your truth.
This is my truth and everything becomes relative.
But what I would submit to you this morning
is that there is truth and it is absolute truth.
Jesus, who is the way, the truth and the life,
stood before Pilate and Pilate says what is truth,
but he didn't stick around long enough to get an answer.
And how sad that is.
Jesus said, before he went,
before that interaction with Pilate,
he says this, sanctify them by thy word.
Thy word is truth.
Truth stands on its own.
Truth is powerful.
It's transforming.
I'm so thankful for truth.
And he says to those that know the truth,
that believe and know the truth,
what is the truth reference?
Well, he talks about that they forbid to marry
and command to abstain from meats.
But what is the truth knowing in verse number four,
for every creature of God is good
and nothing to be refused
if it be received with thanksgiving.
Hallelujah.
Praise God.
Amen.
You know, there've been some dietary restriction changes
throughout the scriptures.
You think about pre in the garden
and then you think about pre flood
and then you think about post flood
and then you think about the dietary restriction
in the book of Leviticus.
And then you come to the New Testament
and God says that everything
can be received with thanksgiving.
Hallelujah.
Glory to God.
For it is sanctified by the word of God in prayer.
But then notice this,
as we think about that which is healthy
and we understand what it does for us
and how it encourages and edifies and builds us.
In verse number six, notice what the Bible says.
If thou put the brethren in remembrance of these things,
what things?
Well, obviously he's not returning
to the doctrines of devils in verse number one.
He's not speaking about the lies
and hypocrisies of verse number two.
No, he's talking about the truth.
And if you, Timothy,
if you put the brethren in remembrance of these things,
in other words, as he will say in 2 Timothy 4,
preach the word.
Timothy, if you're faithful to teach the truth,
if you're faithful to give the word of God,
notice that you put the brethren
in remembrance of these things.
Thou shalt be a good minister of Jesus Christ.
Thou shalt be the desire of every pastor,
every spiritual leader.
And it says, nourished up in the words of faith
and of good doctrine where unto thou hast attained.
I'm thankful for the truth of God's word
and it continues to help us understand
that that which is healthy.
In verse seven, it says, but refuse,
again, that which is unhealthy,
profane and old wise fables.
But what do you do?
Rather, unto godliness.
For bodily exercise profiteth little.
But godliness is profitable unto all things,
having promise of the life that now is
and of that which is to come.
Now, verse number eight's a very interesting
verse of scripture.
Bodily exercise profiteth little.
There's a truth there that it is profitable,
but it ought not be the primary concern.
You know, we live in a culture today
that puts a greater emphasis on the external
than they do on the spiritual,
on the physical versus the spiritual.
They spend hours in a gym trying to sculpt muscles
and whatever and have whatever type of health
they think they can have while they ignore the spiritual.
God is not saying in this verse of scripture
that you shouldn't exercise,
that you shouldn't have any bodily exercise.
He's simply helping us to understand
that bodily exercise profiteth little.
It's temporary.
Amen?
But, notice, godliness is profitable unto all things,
having promise of the life that now is
and of that which is to come.
And understanding this work of studying the scriptures,
of growing spiritually, of feasting upon that
which is healthy, of being in God's word.
Listen, I hope this morning that you don't spend
more time.
physically working out than you do spiritually feasting on God's Word.
There needs to be a balance. There needs to be a balance. Well, the doctor told me that I need to
exercise.
Well, listen, God says to study. God says that we're to read it and to know it and to
memorize it.
People say, man, I just can't memorize any verses. It's just too hard for me. You know
why, Ms. Lorraine? It takes work!
Right? She says to me, she's been a blessing all year. I don't mean to point her out, but
all year she's been a blessing with this memory verse campaign that we're doing of each month
having a verse as a church.
She comes to me and she's called me and said, can I quote the verse to you? She comes in
and says, can I quote the verse to you? At scripture assembly, she says, I'm going to
start in January and I'm going to give, and just help me with the first word and we'd
get through it. And man, that's a blessing to my heart. But why? It's work. It's work.
It's work.
She says this in verse 9, this is a faithful saying and worthy of all acceptation. For
therefore we both labor and suffer reproach because we trust in the living God who is
the Savior of all men, especially of those that believe.
Now this verse, verse number 10, is a unique verse, a great verse. You know, there's a
teaching of election and predestination and Calvinistic ideas that there's only, Jesus
only died for certain people and so on and so forth. Well here we find that the Bible
promises that He's the Savior of all men, especially of those that believe. What does
He mean by that? Well obviously we know that all men aren't saved, but His sacrifice and
His payment for sin is enough, is sufficient for all of humanity. Praise God. Hallelujah
for that truth.
We find that earlier Paul had said this in verse number 15 of chapter 1, this is a faithful
saying and worthy of all acceptation. What is it? That Christ Jesus came into the world
to save sinners, of whom I am chief. But how many are sinners? For all have sinned
and come short of the glory of God. And He came into the world to save sinners. His payment,
His blood was sufficient, it's satisfied, and it's available to all mankind. The Bible
says this, that the Lord is not slack concerning His promise, speaking about His return as
some men count slackness, but is longsuffering to us, word, not willing that any should perish
but that all should come to repentance. Calvinists have a hard time getting around the word any
and all. They start redefining terms and they start manipulating scripture and so on and
so forth. And I love taking them to 1 John chapter 2 where the Bible says that we know
that He is the propitiation for our sins, hallelujah, He's writing to save people, but
not for our sins, only for the sins of the whole world. Hallelujah. In fact, God speaks
about false teachers and says that they deny the truth, they deny the one that died for
them, that paid for their sin. These verses reveal to us that the child of God must be
selective. There are things that are unhealthy, things that are healthy. So we understand
that physically speaking. There are some things that are unhealthy for you. You say, but they
taste so good. Listen, the devil's crafty. He'll make it sound good. He'll make it look
good. But it's unhealthy. It's unhealthy. There might be some things you need to cut
out of your diet. There might be some things that you say, well, I can handle it. No, you
can't. You can't. It starts messing with your brain. It causes doubt, confusion, uncertainty,
all of a sudden you're not believing what God has said. See, we talked about that which
is unhealthy and how it ministers questions, and it's referred to as being vain, jangling,
useless talk. Well, that which is healthy, it will build you up. Notice what the Bible
says in the book of Colossians. Turn over quickly, if you will, to Colossians chapter
number 2. In Colossians chapter 2, in verse number 6, the Bible says that the devil's
purpose is this, is he have therefore received Christ Jesus the Lord, so walk ye in him.
And then notice this, rooted and built up in him, established in the faith, as he have
been taught, abounding therein with thanksgiving. But you know, it's followed with another warning.
But, in verse 8, beware, lest any man spoil you, how, through philosophy and vain deceit,
after the tradition of men, after the rudiments of the world, and not after Christ. That which
is healthy is going to build you up. That which is healthy will give maturity and stability.
Turn back to the book of Ephesians, if you will, and look at the fourth chapter, Ephesians
chapter number 4, because that which is healthy is going to build you up. That which is healthy
is going to give maturity and stability. Again, we understand some of these principles when
we think about a physical diet. We're speaking this morning about a spiritual diet. I want
to be built up. I want to have that spiritual maturity. I want to have that spiritual stability.
It's only going to come as a result of having, being selective and having a healthy spiritual
diet. In verse number 14 of Ephesians 4, the Bible says that we, henceforth be no more
children tossed to and fro and carried about with every wind of doctrine by the slight
of men and cunning craftiness, notice this, whereby they lie in wait to deceive. But speaking
the truth in love may grow up into him in all things, which is the head even Christ.
Listen, you want to have that stability? You want to have that maturity? You've got to
be selective in your spiritual diet. There's some things that you ought to receive. There's
some things that you ought to reject, you ought to refuse. You say, listen, I'm going
to be selective with my spiritual diet. I understand that not everything that is available
is to be consumed by the child of God. We must examine the source. Examine the source.
Listen, you ought to know the author. You ought to know some things about what the author
believes. You ought to know who's putting the videos out there and what they believe.
And listen, say, well, I can believe, you know, we believe certain things that are consistent.
Be careful, because sooner or later what's going to happen, you start filling, you continue
to fill your mind with those things, it's going to have an impact. It's going to have
an influence. You say, well, if I believe this that they said, they were so convincing
in what they said over here, and I didn't believe it when I first started. But now all
of a sudden I understand where they're coming from. Be careful. We must examine the source.
We must know. Listen, what do they believe? If they don't believe in creation, if they
don't believe that God is the creator, if they don't believe that He died for all people,
if they don't believe that Jesus is the only way to heaven, if they don't believe, we could
just keep going through the fundamentals of the faith. Listen, don't fill your mind with
it. It ministers questions. It's vain jangling. We find this morning that Paul says to Timothy
in the second letter, we're not going to turn there and look at it, but you can reference
it in 2 Timothy 3 and verse number 10, Paul makes this statement, but thou has fully known
my doctrine, manner of life, purpose, faith, longsuffering, charity, and patience. I like
that he says, you have fully known my doctrine and manner of life. You ought to examine the
source. You know how many people today, when we talk about physical diet, are looking at
the labels? I mean, they're examining, they want to know where did this thing come from,
what's going on with it, what's the source? Why? Because they want to, I only want to
put healthy things in my body. And then they're a Christian and they go and listen to terrible
false teaching. You say, what's going on here? You examine the source with regard to
the meat that you're going to eat, but you don't even care about the stuff you're listening
to? It's dangerous. And Paul gives a warning. He says we have to be selective. When it comes
to our spiritual diet, when we ask ourselves how's our diet spiritually speaking, we must
be selective. Number two, I took a long time on number one, but we'll get through it. Amen.
Number two, you must, you must be scriptural. You must be selective, but you must be scriptural.
See, in verse number three of the Bible says, them which believe and know the truth. I've
already made mention of the fact that we're thankful for God's truth, for God's Word,
but I want you to understand this morning that this Bible is like no other book. God's
Word is like no other book. This book, the Bible, we must refuse reading it like we would
read any other book, because it's not like any other book. It's unique in the fact that
its author is divine, its content is true. We accept it by faith. God said it, that settles
it. So often we've read and we've seen, and I know that bumper stickers aren't quite as
common or popular today as they once were, but you'll remember perhaps, those of you
that are old enough, the bumper sticker or maybe today the meme that says, God said it,
I believe it, that settles it. I submit to you this morning that whether you believe
it or not doesn't really matter, because if God said it, that settles it.
that settles it. Amen? I think about the disciples in Acts when the
religious leaders are fighting against and Gamaliel stands up and says, listen,
if this thing be of God and you try to fight against him, it's like you're
fighting against God. Yeah, that's exactly what you're doing. Listen, God gave us a
perfect book. He gave us a pure book that is preserved, that is precious, that is
profitable, that is powerful, a book that we have in our hands this morning that
is like no other book. Listen, I have books in my library that you can have. I
don't care, but you can't have my Bible. You can't have my Bible. My kids could tell you
they're older now. When they were little, still they don't carry my Bible. Could
they? Yeah, they're old enough, they're big enough, but when they're little kids, man,
they didn't carry my Bible. You say, well, that's kind of, listen, I was, I didn't
want them dropping it and drawing in it. I came home from work one day. I was
working at Sikorsky and Juliana got a hold of a page in Exodus and wrote all
over it. Man, I had to go take a break. I was like, whew, I gotta calm down for a minute, right? I was
at a pastor's meeting on Tuesday. I tell you the truth, I'm protective about my
Bible. I was at a pastor's meeting on Tuesday and I left my Bible in the pew
of the church. Why did I leave it in the pew? Because we're going over to have
lunch and guess what? I don't want anything spilling on my Bible. Because
I'm messy and I'm gonna spill? No, the guy next to me might spill something. Amen?
There might be a kid at the table. I leave my Bible in the church so I know
where I left it. I know where it is. It's in safekeeping and I'm there and I'm
fellowship and I'm getting ready to leave and I'm talking to Pastor Mike
Reed. I'm talking to him and some lady comes walking through. Anyone know whose
Bible this is? I'm like, whoa, that's my Bible. Careful. And she's like, oh, I just
wanted to bring it to you. And I'm like, thank you very much. Just trying to, just
wagging it around, right? Listen, the Bible is a precious book. You say, Pastor, you're
gonna get a new one. I understand but it's my Bible. It's my Bible. I love the
Bible. I love the Bible. This book is like no other book. It has absolutely changed
my life. And those of you here this morning that have read this book, you
know that this book is like no other book. You know the impact and the
difference that this book has made in your life. I'm reading through the Bible
for a second time right now. I personally like to read in Genesis and go through
Revelation and start back in Genesis and go to Revelation and start back. That's
just what I like to do. Near the end of the year, depending on what the time of
the month is when I finish Revelation for a, whatever the time is that I
finish it in that calendar year, depending on the number of days or
months left in the year, I might just read the New Testament and then I'll
start on January 1st in Genesis 1. It's just what I do. The last few days I've
been reading Leviticus. Right now I'm reading Deuteronomy. It's exciting. I know
that numbers is in between those two books. I understand that. But I bring up
Leviticus because so many people criticize the book of Leviticus. Let me
give you just a moment of insight with regard to the book of Leviticus. The book
of Exodus is exciting because it records for us how God delivered His people out
of Egyptian bondage. And it's exciting to read the book of Exodus. I had regularly,
I admit that. I willingly admit that the book of Exodus is exciting. I mean, you
start reading about the Red Sea, you read about all the plagues, you read about the Red Sea,
man, it's exciting. You end the book with the tabernacle being reared up and the
presence of God being there. I mean, it's exciting. You come to the book of Leviticus, you start
reading all this stuff. You say, what in the world is going on here? Two quick takeaways.
Number one, Moses was a faithful minister. God gave Moses truth for the people and Moses
delivered the truth to the people. But let me tell you what the book of Leviticus is really
all about. See, God got His people out of Egypt. But in the book of Leviticus, God has to get
Egypt out of His people. And for those of us that are saved here this morning, I don't know
when you got saved, but Egypt is a type of picture of the world. And I don't know how much world you
had in you before you got saved. But you know what Christ is trying to do? He's trying to get the
world out of you. You know what He says? Be holy for I am holy. We're in the book of Leviticus. He
says, here's what I want you to do. Here's how I want you to behave. I don't want you to do what
you saw in Egypt. I don't want you to do what you're going to see in the land. I want you to
do what I'm telling you to do because I'm your God. Don't skip it. It's powerful. It's helpful.
By the way, the Old Testament was written for two things according to the New Testament. Number one,
our learning. Number two, our admonition. The Bible is one complete book that's made up of
66 individual books, but its theme is consistent, written over a period of 1,500 years, 40 different
people. I mean, it's amazing. Why? Because all Scripture is given by inspiration of God. It's
God's Word. It's God's book. And we understand this morning that we should not, we must not
consume that which deviates from the Bible. We must remember that there are some things that must
be refused. John says this in 1 John chapter number 4 and verse number 1, Beloved, believe not
every spirit, but try the spirits whether they are of God, because many false prophets are gone out
into the world. This morning, we must be selective, but we must be scriptural. Where God's Word puts
a period, don't put a question mark. When God said it, it settles it. Sometimes, well, I just got to be
able to figure it out. Listen, His ways are not our ways. His thoughts are not our thoughts. If you
could figure out God, then you don't need God. I'm thankful that God has allowed us to know Him,
and we continue to desire to know Him, but I've submitted this to you on more than one occasion,
that the reality this morning is that as great as you think God is today in your life, He is far,
far greater than your mind could even imagine. You say, but I know that God is great. Yes, so did
David. And then he said this, that His greatness is unsearchable. That's Bible. Psalm 135, Psalm 145.
I know that the Lord is great. His greatness is unsearchable. You say there's a contradiction. No,
no contradiction whatsoever. I submit to you this morning, I know that God is great,
but does it mean I know everything about Him that I can explain it? No,
because His greatness is unsearchable, and we come to Him by faith. Amen? Man.
Man is not perfect. God is perfect. Man is fallible. God is infallible. Have you ever
said something and you said it wrong? Sure you have. I have said things when I've preached and
said, no, no, I didn't mean it that way. Let me rephrase that. Why? Because sometimes we get,
your mind gets thinking faster than your tongue can go. Now my tongue can go pretty fast,
but sometimes my mind goes faster. And you might say something, you might have it in the reverse
order or whatever it might be. Listen, God is perfect, and His Word is perfect. We think about
our spiritual diet, it's got to be selective and it's got to be scriptural. And we see,
number three this morning in closing, when we understand, when we evaluate our spiritual diet,
it must be selective, it must be scriptural, but the result is going to be this, you will be sound.
If you're selective and if you're scriptural, you will be sound. You will be sound. What do I mean
by the word sound? Well, we understand that God says in His Word many times, He talks about sound
doctrine. When He uses that word sound, He uses that to refer to that which is healthy,
or that which is free from any mixture of error. In verse 11 it says, these things, back in 1
Timothy chapter number 4, these things, we read that in verse number 6, where He said,
if you put the brethren in remembrance of these things, now in verse number 11, these things,
command and teach. He then says this, let no man despise thy youth. It's kind of interesting
because Timothy wasn't necessarily a very young man at this particular time, but he was definitely
younger than others. He says, let no man despise thy youth, but be thou an example of the believers
in word and conversation and charity and spirit and faith in purity. Now I want you to just pause
for a moment and look at verse number 12. God says, let no man despise thy youth. And He tells
them what to do in being an example and what have you. And oftentimes we think about this in the
context of, you know, a younger person. Timothy wasn't specifically younger, probably in his 40s
actually. And that is kind of young, amen, I'm in my 40s, kind of young. But the reality is this,
today, if I could make an application and not be doing any
service to the Scriptures, here's what I find what happens today. People will say something
like this, well, you just don't have a degree. You're just not as smart as we are. I mean,
I got a doctorate in some kind of whatever science and some kind of whatever. You know
what Romans 1 says, professing themselves to be wise? They became fools. Am I saying
that everyone that has a Ph.D. is a fool? I'm not saying that. Don't misquote me. What
I'm saying this morning is that God's wisdom and earthly wisdom are two very different
things. Two very different things. You know what happens sometimes? The intellectual movement
causes people to not accept this book by faith because intellectually they just can't. And
then they start trying to, well, you're just not very smart. I'd rather be biblical than
smart. Am I against education? No, I have a degree. I've taken other classes and I've
done different things over the years. But you know what? My confidence is not in my
degree. My confidence in that book, the Bible. Do you know, can I share a secret with you?
There's some people that taught me things when I got that degree that were contrary
to what that book says. You know why? Because they're men. They were wrong. They got it
wrong. You know what? As you study Scripture and you compare Scripture with Scripture and
you're a student of the Word, you're like, well, actually that's really not what the
Bible says. Actually the Bible says this, being sound. He says in verse 13, till I come.
Remember, Paul was planning to come to Ephesus to be with Timothy and Timothy was left there
just as Titus was left in Crete and he had a job, he had a mission, he had a ministry
to do. And Paul said in verse 15 of chapter number 3, if I tarry long. He's writing these
things in verse number 14 and he says that if I tarry long that thou mayest know how
thou oughtest to behave thyself in the house of God which is the church of the living God,
the pillar and ground of the truth. And so Paul has this plan, if you will, to go and
to be there, but he says in chapter number 4 in verse number 13, till I come. So I don't
know when I'm coming, if I tarry long my plan is to come, but till I come, notice, give
attendance to reading, to exhortation, to doctrine. That's what you need to be focused
on. Obviously, contextually, it would be with regard to the Scriptures. Remember Paul in
2 Timothy, he says, listen, bring me, what, especially the parchments. You know what he's
referring to? He's talking about the Old Testament Scriptures. There's a missionary that was
going to the field and he was going to Africa and the journey was challenging. It was about
120 years ago and as he's going into the inner parts of the jungle, the journey was challenging
and difficult and he started with all kinds of materials and things he was going to take
as he was planning to go and reach a tribe and minister there and he had all these books,
his library with him and the journey was treacherous, the journey was challenging and little by
little he decided, you know what, I don't really think I need this book and I don't
really think I need this book and I'm going to leave this behind because I can't make
the journey with all of these books and eventually, you know what book he got there with? One,
the Bible. The Bible. Because there's one book I can't part with. See, Paul says, till
I come. We don't know when he was going to come. He said, if I tarry long, give attendance
to reading, exhortation to doctrine. Neglect not the gift that is in thee which was given
thee by prophecy with the lying of the hands of the presbytery. Timothy was called into
the ministry, called by God, validated through the spiritual leaders. He then says this in
verse 15, meditate upon these things. Again, we see another reference to these things.
Those things that are healthy. Those things that are true. Notice where he says, give
thyself, notice where he says, holy to them. I'm not going to give myself holy or partially
to the truth that I, these things that I know and then partially to this other stuff because,
you know, I want to be open-minded. You hear that phrase today. It's common. You know,
you just got to be open-minded. You got to be, no, no, no. I got to be biblical. I got
to be biblical. I don't need to be open-minded. I need to be biblical. If God said it, this
settles it. Right? And in Sunday school this morning, in the marriage class, we were reading
some passages of scripture, the book of Genesis, the book of Matthew, and we read the portion
that says in the beginning, God made them male and female. I don't have to be open-minded
about it, and neither do you. Amen? The world's confused. You know why the world's confused?
Because they have an unhealthy diet. God's people shouldn't be confused. You know what's
really confusing to me is when you see a church that has crazy flags flying on it and crazy
statements on their marquees and all this stuff. Why? Because they've been given the
truth and they've forsaken it. Why? Because they want to be accepted? They want to be
politically correct? I'd rather be biblically accurate. Amen? You say, Pastor, this is your
tread on some thin ice. I know. I understand. But it's God's Word. There's no compromise
on God's Word. Listen, one day, I'm going to stand before Jesus, and so are you. I don't
want to stand before Him and be like, well, you know, the pressures of the culture and
all that. No! God said it. And if you are selective and you are scriptural, you will
be sound. It might not be that you're popular, but you'll be sound. Notice, give thyself
wholly to them that thy profiting may appear to all. And then verse 16, take heed unto
thyself. We'll see again a reference to this in chapter number 5. We'll keep it in a couple
of weeks. In verse 22, keep thyself pure. He says, take heed unto thyself and unto the
doctrine. Continue in them. Don't go looking for other stuff. Continue in what God has
said. Continue in them, for in doing this thou shalt both save thyself and them that
hear thee. Who are those that hear thee? Well, Timothy was ministering in the church at Ephesus.
And so as he's preaching, he's a pastor and he's ministering in the church at Ephesus,
we found out in verse number 6, putting the brethren in remembrance of these things, it
would be that he's a good minister and nourished up in the words of faith and of good doctrine.
And we find that in verse 16, he says, continue in this. Take heed unto thyself and unto the
doctrine. Continue in them, for in doing this thou shalt both save thyself and them that
hear thee. Listen, it's not talking about saving and salvation, being saved from the
penalty of sin and going to heaven. That's not what verse 16 is talking about. You know
what 16 is talking about? Being saved from the false teachers. Being saved from, as it
says in verse number 4, those that are seducing spirits and doctrines of devils, speaking
lies and hypocrisies. Listen, if you're built up in the faith, if you have a healthy diet,
you're going to be saved from that stuff. Delivered from it, not having all of that
confliction in your mind and in your spirit about what is, no, God gave us His Word. I'm
so thankful this morning. But I ask you, how's your diet? How's your diet? There's so much
that's available today. So much that's available today. You may get emails, you may receive
periodicals, whatever it is that you receive. You go on YouTube and you just start looking
at videos of this preacher or that preacher. Well, pastor, they must be right. They have
like 450,000 this and they got all this whatever. And, man, they had this video viewed 2.7 million
times and your video's only been viewed two times and, you know, blah, blah. Give me a
Who are they? What do they believe? Examine the source. Be selective. Be careful. Listen,
not everything that's available today is to be consumed by God's people. There are many
false prophets. There are many false teachers. And they're lying in wait to deceive. They
want to confuse you. They minister questions. They don't give answers. They minister questions.
This will put a little doubt in your mind. And that little doubt begins to grow. It can
mess with you. Don't put a question mark where God's put a period. Take God's Word as God's
Word and believe it. God commends through Paul the church at Thessalonica in 1 Thessalonians
because when they received the Word of God, they received it not as the Word of men.
but it's the Word of God. And he says this, which effectually worketh in you that believe.
See they received it as it was the Word of God, not as the Word of man, but as the Word
of God. And God's Word effectually worketh in you. Be selective, be scriptural, and the
result is that you will be sound. You'll be sound in the faith. Let's pray. Father, we
love you. Thank you for loving us. Lord, if there's one not saved, I pray that today they'd
trust Christ as their Savior. We know that you died for all, that you love all, that
you offer forgiveness and how thankful we are for that. God, perhaps this morning there's
some that, if they'd be honest, their spiritual diet is not healthy. They've been reading
and watching and consuming those things that minister questions, that are vain jangling,
that are causing confusion and concern. Lord, they need to have a change of diet, some things
that must be refused, rejected. Lord, I pray that you'd help us to have a diet that is
healthy, spiritually speaking, that will build us up, that will result in stability and maturity,
that we'd be sound in the faith. I pray that you'd move and work in hearts and lives as
only you can. Well, thank you for these moments of invitation. For it's in Christ's name we
pray. Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed. We'll have a moment of invitation.
If you're not sure of heaven, we'd love to take a Bible, show you how you can know for
sure that heaven's your home. Maybe God spoke to you this morning just very directly. Maybe
there's some things in your diet that are unhealthy that you need to deal with. You
need to confess it to the Lord and say, I'm not going to consume these things anymore.
Maybe you just want to come and pray and ask God to help you to have a diet that is healthy,
to keep you protected from those unhealthy things. As Kimberly plays, The Altar is Open.