Corinthians chapter number 12, 13 this morning.
Chapter number 13, almost to the end of the book
and this week and next week
and then we'll have one final message to end the year.
Of course, there's a Sunday in between
that'll have a opportunity for a Christmas message
on the 21st and thankful for the book of 2 Corinthians.
It's been a blessing to me and I trust to you as well
and dealing with this thought,
the theme throughout the year, God's grace is sufficient
and I was so blessed yesterday.
Someone shared with me that they had memorized the verses
and working on memorizing the verses
and I hope that you are as well.
If you memorize all the verses, 12 verses for the month
or for the calendar year of 2025,
you have 12 verses on grace
and last year was 1st and 2nd Timothy
and someone was able to share with me all the verses
from last year all the way through
and got a couple kind of at the end of this year,
they're still working on, but I was blessed and encouraged
and I was challenged in my own brain to try to remember
what was the memory verse in June of 2024?
Hello and praise the Lord.
That was an encouragement to me, it was a blessing
and we're to hide God's word in our hearts
and what a blessing and it takes work.
It's not easy, it takes work, it takes discipline,
it takes review and so I am thankful for that.
I wanna encourage you to be memorizing the verse
this month, 1st Peter chapter four and verse number 10.
As every man hath received the gift,
even so minister the same one to another
as good stewards of the manifold grace of God.
I'm so thankful that God has given to us spiritual gifts,
he's given us his grace and we are to be good stewards
and what a blessing and some of you told me this morning,
I got the verse, should I recite it to you?
And I said, save it for tonight
and we'll do that this evening
but we're looking forward to it.
Back to 2nd Corinthians, of course we understand
over the last couple of weeks as we've studied
through chapters 11 and 12 that the circumstances
and really the criticisms that were surrounding
the writing of this book of 2nd Corinthians
resulted in the apostle Paul defending himself
for much of these last two chapters.
We read it in chapter 11 and chapter 12
and we find that in chapter 12 and verse number 11,
he says, I am become a fool in glorying,
ye have compelled me and this was something
that was necessary, he mentions that I,
for I ought to have been commended of you
for in nothing am I behind the very chiefest apostles
though I be nothing.
And the apostle Paul has spent time
in these two chapters 11 and 12 really writing
as a response to the circumstances and to the criticisms
that surround the writing of this particular letter.
The false teachers were there and all that was taking place
and how they had attacked the apostle Paul.
I was thinking yesterday as I was just kind of meditating,
actually I guess it was Friday evening,
just meditating on many of the New Testament books
and churches that were established
and you think about the work of the missionary journeys,
you think about the importance of planting churches
but something that I was just kind of meditating on
Friday evening was this thought that as many churches
as were established, as much of the instruction
that they had received, you know there were false teachers
that came in every single one of them
and you find the prevalence and just the attack
of the false teaching and the way in which many
of those churches were destroyed and how sad it is
and I'm thankful that the faith was delivered to us.
If you think about the book of Jude
and we have the truth of God's word
and there have been a line of faithful followers
of Christ for which I'm thankful
but we're reminded of those false teachers
that are so prevalent.
As the epistle closes, we find that the apostle Paul
in that section in chapter number 12
reminded the people at Corinth, the believers there
of his love for them.
We find that he confronts them about sin.
We dealt with that last Sunday morning.
Sin must be addressed and we dealt with that.
It will continue into the 13th chapter
and we find that now he will issue to them a challenge.
It's interesting to me as we come to the last chapter
of this particular book and I think about
the original recipients, no doubt I think about myself
and I think about you as we've studied
through this entire book, what do we do with it?
What do we do with what we've read and what we've learned
and what we've heard preached and what do we do?
How do we respond?
But I think for a moment of these original recipients
to these believers in the church at Corinth,
I wonder as we consider this letter that was sent to them,
what would they do with it?
Would they ignore the message?
Would they say, well, that's nice?
Would they embrace the message?
Would they take to heart that which was shared with them
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God
and would they be doers of the word,
applying and embracing the truth?
And here's the conclusion that I reach,
just as the fact is for the original recipients
such as the truth for us this morning, it's our choice.
It's your choice what you do with what you hear, amen?
It's absolutely our choice.
It was their choice as individuals.
I'm sure that within the church at Corinth,
I can't prove it but I would assume understanding humanity
that there were some within the church
that embraced the message that said, you know what?
There's truth there that I need
and I need to apply these things and I need to do this
and I need to be a doer of the word
as we look at the truth in James one.
And there were probably others that said,
that was really nice that Paul wrote that.
And there are others that said,
you know, I don't agree with that.
That's just Paul's and there's always a mixed response.
It was true when Jesus taught, was it not?
There were some that he said were wise.
Why?
Because they did, they applied the truth.
There were some that he said were foolish.
Why?
Because they dismissed that which he taught.
And so just as the case for these original recipients
there in Corinth, they had a responsibility
to do with what they heard,
such as the case for us this morning,
as we've considered all that we've looked at
this calendar year, as we've studied through this book.
I would say this, that the Apostle Paul
is a good spiritual leader.
He does this in the 13th chapter,
he brings them to a place of decision.
It's always important.
It is my goal and when I preach, when I teach,
my goal is always to bring people to a place of decision.
Does it always mean that people are gonna make a decision?
Yes.
I shook my head no, but the answer is yes.
Why?
Because no decision is a decision.
No response is a response.
Amen?
And the reality this morning is that
as we look at this text of scripture,
I'm gonna read the first five verses,
we're gonna deal with the first 10,
and then we'll look at verses 11 through 14
in the next message.
But notice here's what Paul says,
beginning in verse number one,
this is the third time I am coming to you.
In the mouth of two or three witnesses
shall every word be established.
I told you before and foretell you
as if I were present the second time
and being absent now, I write to them
which heretofore have sinned and to all other
that if I come again, I will not spare.
Since you seek a proof of Christ speaking in me,
which to you word is not weak, but is mighty in you.
For though he was crucified through weakness,
yet he liveth by the power of God.
For we also are weak in him, but we shall live with him
by the power of God towards you.
Notice verse five, examine yourselves,
whether you be in the faith, prove your own selves,
know ye not your own selves,
how that Jesus Christ is in you,
except ye be reprobates.
We'll look at the text all the way through down in verse 10
as we get through the message this morning,
but I've titled the message from verse number five there,
examine yourselves, examine yourselves.
As we consider this portion of scripture
and really this challenge to these believers in Corinth
and Paul bringing them to a place of decision,
I find first of all, if you're taking notes,
I want you to notice the reminder.
In the first four verses of this text of scripture
that I just read for you,
Paul reminds them of a few things.
Number one, he reminds them that this is not the first time
that he's come to them.
He tells them in verse number one,
this is the third time I am coming to you.
And then he says this at the end of verse number one,
in the mouth of two or three witnesses,
shall every word be established.
It's very interesting there in verse number one
that the Apostle Paul references back
really to Deuteronomy chapter 17
with a principle from the Old Testament law
that in the mouth of two or three witnesses.
And what's interesting to me
as he's writing to this church in Corinth
and he's writing to these New Testament believers
is the truth that the Old Testament
is still beneficial for us.
And there are applications of principles
that must be applied in our lives.
We find that there are some today
that have this perspective
that we don't need the Old Testament,
but we find that the Apostle Paul
writing to New Testament believers
in the city of Corinth and the church in Corinth,
he references to them and applies a principle.
that comes directly from the Old Testament law.
And I'm thankful that God has given us
the whole canon of scripture,
that we have the preserved word of God,
and that we can go to the Old Testament
and we can understand principles
that are still appropriate for us to apply
in our lives today.
He tells them that he, in verse number two,
he says, I told you before.
Now I think about this,
as the Apostle Paul is reminding them,
he tells them in verse one, this is the third time,
but then in verse number two, he says,
I told you before and foretell you as if I was present.
So he's writing to them and he's writing them,
he's told them already, he's writing to them,
telling them the same thing
that he would tell them when he arrives.
So what's the reminder?
Truth doesn't change.
Truth remains.
And the Apostle Paul, the message that Paul is delivering
to these people, to these believers in Corinth,
was not gonna change.
It had not changed because there was a period of time
that lapsed between the first, the second, the third,
or even as he would come,
he says that he's giving them this truth.
He mentions that he's absent
and he's writing to them in verse number two.
And he says, I write to them which heretofore have sinned
and to all other that if I come again,
notice what he says, I will not spare.
See, they were looking for some level of strength.
They mentioned that Paul was weak
and they were looking for strength
and the Judaizers had influenced this thought process
in the minds of the believers in Corinth
to have this perspective of the Apostle Paul
that he was this weak individual,
but Paul mentioned and he'll mention it again
at the end of our text that we're looking at this morning
that he's ministering to edify not to destroy.
But he says, I will not spare.
We mentioned a few weeks ago,
as we've looked through these texts of scripture
as the Apostle Paul is writing to these believers
that if he needed to be stern, he could be stern.
If he needed to stand and to call out sin
that he would be willing to do so.
I think about Nathan, the strength that was required
for Nathan to stand before David, the king,
and to say thou art the man.
And I believe that that's really what Paul is saying here.
He's not gonna be ugly and nasty,
but he's gonna call out sin.
He's going to address sin.
He's going to confront individuals.
Why?
Because we're to live our lives pleasing to God.
We're to walk worthy.
We're to please God.
And we find here that the Apostle Paul,
he's reminding them that the message doesn't change.
It's interesting if you were to go back
to the book of Jeremiah,
and we don't have time to do that this morning,
but the king at one point comes to Jeremiah and says,
is there a word from God?
It's kind of comical because Jeremiah had been given a word
to the king of Judah and to the people of Judah
consistently, and here comes the king saying,
is there a word from God?
And you know what Jeremiah says?
Yep, the same word that I've been telling you.
God's word is settled.
God's word is true.
In the principles that are being given
to the believers in Corinth,
through the writing of this letter,
and through the previous in the book of 1 Corinthians,
and in Paul's ministry there,
God's word is settled.
And I'm thankful for that.
I'm thankful that our God changes not.
He's immutable.
He's the same yesterday and today and forever.
And what a blessing to understand that.
And so Paul reminds them that this is not the first time
he references that Old Testament law principle
and applies it with regard to his addressing
to these believers in Corinth.
He reminds them that the message does not change,
that truth is consistent.
He reminds them of the crucifixion.
Notice, if you will, in verses three and four,
he says, since ye seek a proof of Christ speaking in me,
which to you word is not weak, but is mighty in you.
Again, that's the reference that's been consistent
in the last couple of chapters that we've mentioned
that they're influenced by those Judaizers.
And then notice what he says in verse number four.
For though he was crucified through weakness,
yet he liveth by the power of God.
We know that he's referring to the Lord Jesus Christ,
and we understand that as you look here
at that first section of verse number four,
and you begin to understand the crucifixion,
and you can understand the power of the resurrection.
I'm so thankful that we serve a risen Savior,
and I'm thankful that though there were some,
remember, even those that mocked the day
that Christ was crucified, that they said,
if you're the Christ, come down.
You had power to save others, save yourself, right?
This is the message that many of these mockers were giving,
but I understand that Jesus Christ stayed on that cross
because he was paying for your sin and for my sin.
And I'm thankful that he stayed on the cross.
I'm thankful that though he could call legions of angels,
that he chose to endure the cross, why?
For the joy that was set before him,
according to Hebrews chapter number 12.
And I'm thankful this morning
that Paul is going to reference, listen,
you speak about this weakness and this power,
you think about the weakness of the crucifixion,
but the power of the resurrection.
And then he says this, for we also are weak in him,
but we shall live with him by the power of God towards you.
Now, this is interesting that Paul says this
in the end of verse number four,
because really Paul is referencing back
to that promise that God had given him in chapter number 12.
Remember that the apostle Paul besought the Lord thrice
that this thorn would depart from him.
And God said, my grace is sufficient for thee,
for my strength is made perfect in what?
In weakness.
You know, oftentimes in your weakness
is when you become most dependent.
I mean, we speak of that spiritually,
and that's the purpose of the message, obviously,
is to look at the spiritual aspect of that.
But you think about physically, if you're weak physically,
you are dependent on someone else
or something else to help you, why?
Because you're weak physically, spiritually.
Paul says, or God says to Paul,
that my strength is made perfect in weakness.
I mentioned as I preached through that portion of scripture
a few weeks ago, how thankful we ought to be for the thorns.
Why?
Because the thorns keep us humble.
And if we're not humble and we're prideful,
that means God resists us.
Remember, God resisteth the proud,
but giveth grace unto the humble.
And Paul says, as he's reminding these believers in Corinth,
he's setting the table, if you will,
and he starts with the reminder,
notice number two, if you're taking notes,
notice the demand.
Notice the demand.
It's very simple in verse number five, examine yourselves.
And this is not just a suggestion.
It's not just a recommendation.
It's really a demand that the apostle Paul
is placing upon the believers in Corinth.
Now again, whether they do it or not is their choice.
How they respond to the message is up to them.
But the reality is that the apostle Paul,
it's interesting as God would lead him to write,
he says, examine yourselves, whether ye be in the faith.
And then he says this, notice, prove your own selves.
Know ye not, notice again, your own selves,
that Jesus Christ is in you, except ye be reprobates.
But I trust, verse number six,
that ye shall know that we are not reprobates.
Now, as the apostle Paul gives this demand
to these believers in Corinth,
I'm interested in knowing all that's taking place here
in understanding this morning
that these believers in Corinth
had spent much time examining Paul.
They had spent much time putting Paul's life
under the microscope.
They had spent much time criticizing
the things of the apostle Paul.
He said he was gonna come to us,
his yea is not yea and his nay is not nay.
He said he was gonna come and he didn't,
but he did say, if the Lord will.
Well, they just forgot that little part.
And what I'm suggesting to you this morning
is that the apostle Paul,
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
we find that the demand is examine yourselves.
Stop examining Paul and start examining yourself.
That's what the church of Corinth,
that's the message that the believers in Corinth
needed to receive.
And with the same level of intensity, if you will,
with the same rigor that they would put
the apostle Paul through as they were examining his life,
that they ought to put themselves to the same level,
to that same level of intensity.
Don't give yourself a pass.
You weren't given Paul a pass.
Be as strict with yourself as you were with the apostle Paul.
Think about that this morning.
Examine yourselves.
We observe the Lord's Supper and in 1 Corinthians,
we find that the instruction is given,
let a man examine himself.
And we find that often as we consider the truth
of this idea of examination,
that there's obviously a desire on the part of many people
to examine others instead of themselves.
But he says examine yourselves.
And I think about the truth that's given here
with regard to examining yourselves.
Turn back if you will.
will, to 2 Corinthians chapter 5, why is it that Paul's saying examine yourselves?
See, what happens in life is we can get so busy examining the lives of other
people and spend little time examining ourselves, but you know you're gonna
stand before God individually. Paul told them this in 2 Corinthians chapter 5
in verse number 10, for we must all appear before the judgment seat of
Christ. You're gonna stand before God one day. I'm gonna stand before God one day.
If you're lost here this morning, you've never trusted Christ as your Savior,
you're gonna stand at the great white throne judgment, and I would tell you
this, today is the day of salvation. You don't want to stand at that judgment
because the only verdict at that judgment is that you'll be cast in a
lake of fire. That's it. There's no other outcome. If you're a subject at the
great white throne judgment, the only outcome is to be cast in a lake of fire
forever and ever. The judgment seat of Christ, the Bible tells us that we can
receive rewards or we can suffer loss. We can look at it that Paul talked to
them in the book of 1 Corinthians about this subject of the judgment seat of
Christ, the bema seat of Christ, and we find that there are crowns that can be
received, and we find that the Apostle Paul, he's saying to these believers in
Corinth here, to these, really all of them, there are some that are there that he's
writing to, and he's saying, examine yourselves. Examine yourselves. Why? You're
gonna stand before Christ one day. I'm beginning to think about this text and
understanding the demand that God has placed upon his people, and we see it
specifically for the believers in Corinth in both letters that Paul writes
about this, let a man examine himself, and how important it is that we would take
heed. How important it would be for the believers in Corinth to take heed. Listen,
don't get so busy as those in Corinth were doing examining someone else and
not considering your own life. There are some people that are lost that just want
to examine the lives of other people, and they want to examine, well look, that
person claims to be a Christian, and they do this, this, and this, and they behave
this way. Hey listen, get your eyes off of them. If you get your eyes on Jesus, the
one who is perfect, the one who is sinless, the one who loves you, the one
that died for you, that's what we need to get our eyes on. And sometimes lost
people, they'll begin to look at everyone else, well this person did this, and this
person did this, and this person claims to be a Christian. Listen, you're gonna
stand before God one day, and if you're lost, it's not gonna be a valid excuse to
stand at the great white throne judgment and say, well, you know, there were some
frauds, there were some really bad examples of Christians that were in
my life, and therefore I resisted it, and I... Invalid. Invalid. It's unfortunate
that that happens and that that might be your experience, but the reality is that
Jesus left us an example, a perfect example, and yes, we as believers are to
follow in his steps, but I want to encourage you this morning that sometimes
lost people, they get so concerned looking at other people, well I'm better
than they are, I'm not as bad as them, I've never killed anybody. I hear that so
frequently, and I'm like, I'm glad you haven't killed anybody, I mean that makes
me encouraged that you haven't killed anybody, but that's not really the litmus
test, that's not the single factor that determines heaven or hell. It's
whether you receive the Lord Jesus Christ as your personal Savior, or you
reject. He came to his own, his own received him not. And so as we look
here, we see that idea of lost people, but then obviously the book of Second
Corinthians is written to the believers at the church in Corinth, but here's
something that's important that we understand as we look at these verses of
Scripture, and it's something that we understand this morning, that listen,
everyone that sits in a church isn't saved. Everyone that sits in a church
isn't saved. I'm not trying to make anyone think they're not saved this
morning, but if the Holy Spirit of God would convict your heart that you've not
trusted Christ as your Savior, then today is the day of salvation, but this idea of
examine yourselves. Listen, going to church and even, I sit in a good church
that preaches the gospel, I sit in a church that uses the right Bible, that
has the right standards, whatever it might be, that doesn't save anybody. It's
a personal decision that every individual has to make. Can I tell you
this morning that I sat in a church for about three years that was a good church,
I mean a solid church, a church that preached the gospel week after week
after week, and I was lost. I sat in that church for three years without trusting
Christ as my Savior, but praise God on that one morning I recognized I needed
to be saved and I trusted Christ as my Savior 28 years ago now. You can sit in a
church and be lost. I did it. He says examine yourselves whether you be in the
faith. Prove your own selves. So the word examine and the word prove, they're very
closely associated one to the other, and he says no. So you think about these
three words, examine, prove, know, all personal, your own selves. He says how
that Jesus Christ is in you. That's about salvation. And then he says this,
accept ye be reprobates. Now that word reprobate is an interesting word and
really the idea as we see it used three times in our text of Scripture this
morning is this idea of not being approved or not passing the test. So
what's the purpose of examining ourselves? What's the purpose of proving
ourselves? What's the purpose of knowing ourselves? Well, whether we be in the
faith. Am I truly saved? Have I been born again? Have I had that experience, and not
that it's an experience, but if I had that day in my life where I recognized
that I was a sinner and Christ was the only Savior and I trusted him as my
personal Savior. Can I explain to you this morning that you're not becoming
saved. You are saved on a particular day. The Bible says you must be born again.
It's a moment. I often say this, that salvation is the miracle of a moment. Now
sanctification, it's the process of a lifetime, but salvation, it's the
miracle of a moment. And there was a day in my life, and I don't know the exact
time, I just know the exact day, that I recognized that I needed to be saved. I
was born again. Hallelujah. Holly's birthday was yesterday. She was asking
her mom on the phone last night, what time was I born? And I thought it was
kind of an interesting question, and I was waiting for the answer. And my
mother-in-law has seven children, and she's part of that group
that's in the senior saints, amen? I'm not trying to be critical, I'm trying to be
careful, but I thought, I wonder how she's gonna answer that question. She's
gonna remember what time, and she hesitated for a few moments, and then
Holly said, 3.06 a.m.? And my mother-in-law said, yes, that's what time it was. And I
just kind of chuckled, right? But listen, we were all born at a
certain time, physically, right? There's a time of birth on your birth certificate,
right? And the reality is that you were born again at a moment when you
trusted Christ as your Savior. And so this idea of being a reprobate within
the context is here, is not passing the test, not being approved within the fact
that, listen, I'm a fraud. I might know how to say what I need to say, I
might be able to come into the place and look the part. I talked to the teens this
morning about pleasing God with their lives and walking worthy, and I said this,
the Bible says, walk worthy of God. It doesn't say walk worthy of a teacher, a
parent, a pastor. No, walk worthy of God, and guess what? You can deceive a teacher
a parent, a pastor, but you can't deceive God. It's impossible. And so this process
of examination, listen, you've spent so much time examining the Apostle Paul, how
about you examine yourself? You ever been in a situation where you feel like you're
under the microscope? People often speak, and I don't say this in a pity kind
of a way, just something that's been, there's actually been books written with
this kind of a title, is living in a fishbowl. They talk about people that are
spiritual leaders, and you kind of live in a fishbowl, a fish tank, where
everyone's always looking at you, and always looking at you, and I get it. If
you're in any place of leadership, that often is the case, but I want you to
understand that as they were examining the Apostle Paul, and Paul wasn't really
too concerned about them examining him, but he said, listen, you need to examine
yourselves. You know why Paul, I think, really didn't, it didn't affect him
greatly that they were putting him under the microscope, because Paul put
himself under the microscope. See, Paul examined himself, so if someone else was
going to come in and examine him, it really didn't affect him too much, it
didn't bother him too much. Why? Because he had already examined himself, he'd
already got along with God, he already had lived in seeking to please the Lord
with his life, and he wanted to live a life, in fact, he says it this way in Acts
24 and verse 16, and herein do I exercise myself...
to have always a conscience void of offense
toward God and toward men.
And so the Apostle Paul lived that way,
but he's saying to these believers in Corinth,
stop examining me, examine yourselves.
Whether you be in the faith, prove your own selves,
know your own selves, how that Jesus Christ is in you.
Aren't you thankful, Christ in me, the hope of glory.
Listen, when you got saved, the Bible tells us
the Holy Spirit of God indwelled you at that moment.
You're sealed unto the day of redemption
with the Holy Spirit, and what a joy, and what a blessing.
And you need to know that you know that you know
that heaven is your home.
Examine yourselves, whether you be in the faith.
And so Paul gives this demand to these believers
here in Corinth, he reminds them,
but then he gives to them a demand.
He says in verse six, but I trust that you shall know
that we are not reprobates.
You know, I believe that what Paul's kind of hinting
towards here in verse number six, you've examined me
and you're probably gonna keep examining me
and you're gonna find out that I passed the test.
Not pridefully, not arrogantly, listen,
I'm not saved because of anything I've done,
I'm saved because Jesus Christ saved this lost sinner.
Amen?
And so when he's talking about being in the faith
and having the truth of being born again,
Paul says, listen, I know you've examined me,
I know you're gonna keep examining me,
but you're gonna know that we are not reprobates.
We have passed the test.
Then I want you to notice the concern.
As we wrap up in verses seven through 10,
the Apostle Paul once again is going to share his heart
with these believers in Corinth and really his heart
for the believers in Corinth.
And we find the concern of the Apostle Paul
in verse number seven and eight, he's concerned
for their deeds, for their actions,
for those things that they do.
Notice in verse number seven, he says,
now I pray to God that ye do no evil.
He had mentioned in verses 20 and 21 of chapter 12
about the dealing with sin, that sin must be addressed.
He mentioned in verse number two about those that have sinned
and we find here that he says that I pray to God
that ye do no evil.
You know, this is a concern that the Apostle Paul has
for these believers in Corinth, those that are born again,
those that are saved.
Listen, my desire, our desire is that you would walk worthy,
that you would do no evil.
Notice he continues in verse number seven,
not that we should appear approved,
but that we should do that which is honest,
though we be as reprobates.
He's saying not only concerning their deeds to do no evil,
but to do that which is honest.
You know, Christians ought to be honest people.
Amen?
I mean, how terrible.
I understand that we live in a society
in which honesty and transparency
is not the norm any longer.
I know I've never lived in the days,
but I've heard about people
that made huge agreements on handshakes.
Transactions that were done,
business transactions on handshakes.
And now we have documents that are pages,
dozens and hundreds of pages long,
and lawyers involved on all sides,
and all of those types of things.
And listen, there was a day and age
in which honesty was appreciated
and was something that was really looked up to.
That you should do that which is honest.
You know, Paul says to the believers in Philippi,
I mentioned last week about the put off
and put on principle,
and the fact that we're to walk worthy.
And Paul said this to those,
I think I said Philippi, Ephesus,
in Ephesians chapter number four, five, four.
He tells them about the putting off and putting on,
and he tells them this in verse 25 of Ephesians four,
"'Wherefore, putting away lying.
"'Speak every man truth with his neighbor,
"'for we are members one of another.'"
Putting away lying.
So Paul says here, I pray to God that you do no evil,
that you should do that which is honest.
This is Paul's concern for their deeds,
for their actions, for those things
that they're going to do.
But then as we transition here,
notice he says in verse eight,
and we're gonna get back to verse number eight
as we wrap the whole message up,
but he says this,
"'For we can do nothing against the truth,
"'but for the truth.'"
Can I tell you this morning,
you're not gonna change God's mind.
You're not gonna change God's truth.
You're not going to.
God's truth is settled.
You're not gonna change it.
In verse nine, it says,
"'For we are glad when we are weak,
"'and you're strong in this also we wish,
"'even your perfection.
"'Therefore I write these things being absent,
"'lest being present I should use sharpness,
"'according to the power which the Lord
"'hath given me to edification and not to destruction.'"
So as we unpack verses nine and 10,
I believe that Paul's concern here
for the believers in Corinth is for their growth,
their spiritual growth.
He mentions again at the end of verse number 10
about the power that God gave him,
but that power was given to him for edification,
to build up,
to see somebody grow in their walk with Christ,
not to destruction.
We find that he mentions in verse number nine,
notice at the end it says,
"'In this also we wish,
"'even your perfection.'"
That word wish really carries with the idea of a prayer,
this desire that Paul has for them,
and as we think about the growth here,
he says in verse number nine,
"'Even your perfection.'"
He says in verse number 10 about edification,
and I begin to think about the two uses of these words here
of that which is perfection and also the edification,
and really what Paul is referencing here
is for their spiritual maturity.
That they would be equipped.
The word perfection at the end of verse number nine
is an interesting word.
It's a word that was very familiar
that was used in a multitude of scenarios.
It was a word that these believers
would be able to relate to
in a number of different arenas of life, if you will.
We understand that it's Bible, that it's scripture,
that Paul is writing to these,
and that he's concerned about their spiritual growth,
their perfection, that spiritual maturity,
but we find that the term, the same exact term,
would be used within the medical field,
and within the medical field,
it would be used to have this idea of setting a broken bone.
I don't know if you ever had a broken bone,
and it needed to be set,
and when I broke my pinky, it was a displaced fracture.
They thought they were gonna have to do surgery.
I really didn't want to have to have surgery,
and they were able to get that thing to be corrected
because it was a displaced fracture,
but it had to be set.
Thankfully, it wasn't too awfully painful
going through that process,
but I understand some people that have had broken bones,
and they have to be set, it's a painful process.
And so it means, within that medical use of the term,
to set a broken bone,
within the nautical world,
it would mean to outfit a ship for voyage.
And within military usage,
it would mean to equip an army for battle.
So you think about those usages,
and again, it's a word that all of these folks
could easily associate with and understand
what Paul is saying to them
when he says that this also we wish,
even your perfection, your spiritual maturity,
your equipping, the idea that Paul is concerned
for them spiritually, why?
Because he knows that they're gonna stand before Christ,
and he's concerned for them.
Why is it that Paul mentioned in chapter number 11,
that which cometh upon me daily,
the care of all the churches?
Why did Paul care so much about the people
that God had allowed him to minister to?
Because he understood that those people
were gonna stand before God one day,
and he wanted them to walk worthy,
he wanted them to please God,
he wanted them to be able to stand
and to give a good account.
I think about what we read in the Gospels.
Well done, thou good and faithful servant.
And Paul is concerned about their spiritual maturity,
and we ask ourselves the question this morning,
how is it when we begin to think about this perfection
and the spiritual maturity, what does it look like?
How is it accomplished in the life of a believer?
Look, if you will, at Hebrews chapter 13.
We're gonna look at a few passages
as we wrap up this morning,
but I want you to consider this final really concern
that Paul has for these believers.
In Hebrews 13, we read about the same idea
of this perfection and the work that God is doing in you.
I'm thankful for the song that we sing with the children.
God's still working on me to make me what I ought to be.
Aren't you thankful?
Listen, when the Lord works in your life,
when he's ministering to you,
when he's using his word to grow you,
we ought to rejoice in that.
Can I say this, and I don't say this
in order to try to manipulate some type of response,
but can I say this?
It's not a bad thing to visit an altar in a church.
It's actually a good thing to visit an altar in a church.
Somebody mentioned to me not long ago
how that it was so perplexing to them
because they've been in different parts of the world,
and they've seen churches,
and they've seen people respond
where an altar will be completely packed,
and so many people responding and yet,
oftentimes in America,
you don't see that same level of response.
It's almost as if people have had this idea
that going to the altar is just for the really,
like really bad people.
No, it's for all of us to respond to God
and to let, why?
Because God's working in us and it's a blessing.
Notice where he says in Hebrews 13,
this idea of spiritual maturity,
being equipped for this perfection.
It says in verse 20 of Hebrews 13,
now, the God of peace that brought again from the dead,
our Lord Jesus, that great shepherd of the sheep
through the blood of the everlasting covenant.
Notice what he says,
make you perfect in every good work to do his will,
working in you that which is well pleasing in his sight
through Jesus Christ to whom be glory forever and ever.
Amen.
Aren't those two very good verses of scripture?
To understand in verse 20 that our God
is the God of all peace
and we read that in 2 Corinthians chapter number one,
we find that he continues to speak about the resurrection
and we serve a risen Lord
and what a blessing to know that our savior is risen
and he is that great shepherd of the sheep
and he's doing a work in us
and I'm thankful for that work that he's doing
and you must evaluate your own life
and I preached this several months ago
from the book of 2 Corinthians.
How is God moving in your heart?
What is God doing in your life?
How have you grown this year and this month?
I mean, what is God doing in my life?
How am I growing?
What changes have I seen?
What has God put his finger on?
How have I responded?
Because he's working,
it says that he would make you perfect in every good work.
Notice what it says, to do his will, not to do my will.
You know what I find?
The closer we get to God, the more we walk with God,
the more we wanna do his will.
The less my will really matters
because we all have a will.
We all have a will.
But we find that it says to make you perfect
in every good work, to do his will.
Notice, working in you.
I hope that you never get over the fact
that Christ would work in you.
You know, I'm thankful the apostle Paul,
the Bible talks about when he saw a city
that was wholly given to idolatry,
that he was stirred up in his spirit.
You know, God uses his word to stir up his people.
He stirs us.
But what happens when he stirs us?
Do we respond?
Do we, see, Paul didn't just get stirred and just stay there.
He got stirred and he went and he preached.
Amen?
We find that it says that he's working in you,
that which is well-pleasing in his sight.
This is that spiritual maturity that Paul's speaking of,
that concern that he has for those believers in Corinth,
even your perfection, that spiritual maturity.
See, God is working in us and it's a joy.
And all of it is so that God would be glorified.
We see that at the end of the verse, in verse 21,
through Jesus Christ, to whom be glory forever and ever.
Amen.
You know, as you grow in Christ, as I grow in Christ,
as I have that spiritual maturity,
as we're walking and abiding in him,
you know who's glorified?
Christ, the Lord.
Not me, not you.
It's God who receives the glory.
Look at what God has done.
Someone looks at you and says some word of compliment
and they look at you and they begin to try
to maybe give some glory and say,
listen, not I, but Christ.
It's Christ that works in me and through me
and I give God all the glory for that.
And it's a great joy.
So we understand as we look at this spiritual growth
that the apostle Paul is concerned with,
these believers in Corinth and even their perfection
and we say, what does this look like?
How is it accomplished?
How does God accomplish this?
Well, notice, if you will,
in 2 Timothy chapter number three.
In 2 Timothy chapter number three,
we get instruction as to how God accomplishes this
in the lives of his people.
What does God do?
How does God do it?
Notice, Paul is writing to those believers in Corinth.
He mentions a couple of times within our text of scripture
that he's writing to them.
He said, I mentioned it as we've gone through
the text of scripture.
He says it in the beginning in verses one and two.
He talks about writing to them.
He talks about it again in verse number 10.
Therefore, I write these things being absent.
And so we find that he's writing to them
and then we notice in 2 Timothy chapter three in verse 16,
all scripture is given by inspiration of God
and is profitable for doctrine, for reproof,
for correction, for instruction in righteousness.
And then notice, there's no period at the end of verse 16.
Right?
It's a colon.
For what?
Notice it says that the man of God may be,
what does it say?
Perfect, throughly furnished unto all good works.
How does God, how is this accomplished in your life?
This spiritual growth, this perfection
that the Apostle Paul is speaking about,
what does it look like, but then how is it accomplished?
It's accomplished through his word.
God's given to us his word and as we read his word,
as we study his word, as we read his word
and hear his word and we do his word,
we apply it in our lives, it's profitable for us
and it says that the man of God may be perfect,
throughly furnished unto all good works.
How are you gonna become spiritually mature?
How am I gonna become spiritually mature?
Remember, as he's writing to the church in Corinth
in the first book, he says, I can't write unto you
as unto spiritual, but as unto carnal.
I'd like to say, he has a desire to teach them some things,
he has a desire to tell them some things,
but he can't, why?
Because they can't receive it.
In fact, he says in verse two of chapter three
of the first letter, I have fed you with milk
and not with meat, for hitherto you were not able
to bear it, neither yet now are you able.
But what's the idea?
Well, the book of Hebrews talks about having
that spiritual, that meat of the word
and what a joy to understand that God has given to us.
Listen, there was a time in which they should have had meat
according to Hebrews in chapter number five,
for when the time ye ought to be teachers,
ye have need that one teach you again,
which be the first principles of the oracles of God
and it becomes such as have need of milk
and not of strong meat, verse 13 of Hebrews five,
for everyone that useth milk is unskillful
in the word of righteousness, for he is a babe.
But strong meat belongeth to them that are of full age,
even those who by reason of use have their senses exercised
to discern both good and evil.
So how does God accomplish this in the life
of the believers through his word?
I'm so thankful to have a Bible this morning.
I'm so thankful that God has given to us
all things that pertain unto life in godliness.
I'm thankful that the Holy Spirit of God indwells
and works, confirms in our hearts the truth of his word.
And that we can go to his word and we can understand,
he says, that this was his desire.
We wish even your perfection, this spiritual growth,
this spiritual maturity, and God uses his written word.
Paul desires, I believe, that they would respond properly
and that they would respond before he comes.
Go back to 2 Corinthians 13 as we wrap up this morning
and I want you to notice Paul's concern
as he mentions really concluding here in verse number 10.
He says, therefore, therefore I write these things
being absent, lest being present I should use sharpness
according to the power which the Lord hath given me
to edification and not to destruction.
Paul had mentioned a couple of chapters earlier
about the edification versus destruction
and he references it again here in this verse.
But I find that as Paul is writing in verse number 10
that I really see that Paul is expressing to these believers
that he desires that they would respond
through the written letter.
That he doesn't have to come, right?
He says, therefore I write these things being absent,
lest being present I should use sharpness.
You know what I think Paul's desire was?
Is that he would show up.
He intends to go and visit the church in Corinth.
That's his intention, and that when he gets there
he finds they.
They've accepted everything, and they've responded, and they're doers of the Word.
And all those problems that he thought he was going to have to address, it's like, man,
they accepted the written Word, and they did it.
Wouldn't that be awesome?
That's Paul's desire, is that that's how they would respond, that they would take the letter.
Again, he's bringing them to a place of decision.
Examine yourselves.
He's bringing to place a decision of, listen, take what I've written to you and apply it.
Do it.
Because his desire when he arrived was not that he would have to use sharpness, that
he would not have to be mighty as he spoke of in verse 2 and verse number 3, but that
he would have that opportunity to be able to see a group of believers that have already
accepted and responded.
He says this in verse 8, I told you that we'd wrap up with it, for we can do nothing against
the truth, but for the truth.
See, what was it that would be the source, if you will, of evaluating would be God's
Word, the truth.
We're judged by the truth, by God's Word.
Amen?
So we're judged by.
So we find that as Paul would write to these believers and he would explain to them that
truth has been given, he says, listen, you can do nothing against the truth, but for
the truth.
What is he saying?
If you're living right, if you're doing right, if you're taking the truth and applying it,
you don't have to really worry about the examination.
You don't have to be concerned about it.
Why?
Because you've embraced the truth and you've responded to the truth.
And somebody says, why are you doing that?
And you're able to say, well, right here over in this chapter, here's what I've understood
God to say in His Word and this is why I'm doing what I'm doing.
This is why I'm behaving the way I'm behaving.
This is why I'm living the way that I'm living.
And I can take the Bible and I can, does that make sense?
We said the Bible is the sole authority for faith and practice.
And so Paul's saying, listen, you can do nothing against the truth, but for the truth, you're
not going to change the truth.
God's truth is settled.
And yet we find that as we're going to be judged by the truth of God's Word, that if
we're living according to God's Word, we don't have to fear that judgment.
We don't have to fear that exam.
I remember when I was in the corporate world, and some of you can relate to this, in the
corporate world and they would have audits.
And audits was always a time in which people were so, so, so overwhelmed, so concerned
about the audits.
And I used to think this, and maybe I'm just naive and whatever, but I used to think this
when it came to audit season.
If you were doing everything right, you don't have to really worry about the audit.
Does that make sense?
If you're doing business the way you're supposed to do business, if you're following the regulations
that you're supposed to follow, the audit is a hassle.
It takes time, but I don't have to be afraid of it because I did what I was supposed to
do.
The COO of our company stood in my office one day and used all kinds of profanity and
all kinds of demands, and he demanded that I do something.
And I said, I ain't doing it because it's not following our regulations.
And I'm accountable.
I wasn't trying to be an insubordinate employee or whatever, but I knew that that fellow wasn't
going to be the one held accountable for doing what he was demanding that I do.
And if I did what he demanded that I do, and then there was some kind of repercussion for
it, he was going to be nowhere to be found.
You understand what I'm saying?
So I sent him.
You say you sent him.
He was so much higher than I was pay-wise and all that kind of thing.
And I said, you really need to go talk to that department over there, and once they
do what they're supposed to do, then I'll be glad to do my part.
I'm just using a simple, silly analogy to say, listen, if you're doing business the
way you're supposed to do business, you don't have to fear the audit.
If you're living the way that you're supposed to be living, you don't have to fear the judgment.
You don't have to fear it.
Because we're doing what we're supposed to do.
We're walking.
Paul says that I exercise myself.
This was something that he did to have always a conscience void of offense before God and
man.
He wanted to live a life that was pleasing to God, to walk worthy.
We sing the song, nothing between my soul and my Savior.
And how important it is that we live that way every day.
If you're lost this morning, today's the day of salvation.
Stop examining everybody else and saying, well, they don't this, and they don't that,
and they don't, why would, no, no, no.
You're going to stand before God one day, and you need to be saved.
Today is the day of salvation.
But for every child of God, take the instruction that Paul gives, examine ourselves.
How am I doing?
Am I living according to God's Word?
Am I taking the truth of God's Word and applying it in my life?
Am I truly a doer of the Word?
Is there spiritual growth and maturity in my life?
Can I see in my life today some measure of spiritual growth from a year ago, from two
years ago, from three years ago?
Where has that growth gone?
Have I got kind of stagnant, if you will?
Have I got kind of, do you understand what I'm saying?
We examine ourselves.
And it's so vital and so important.
Paul was concerned about them.
He loved them.
He wanted them to be able to stand and to give a good account before the Lord.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
We thank You for the truth of Thy Word.
And I pray that this morning You would help us, Lord, to be doers.
That we'd respond, Lord, in obedience.
That we would take the truth of Your Word and apply it, Lord.
That we'd not leave here just hearing only, but that we would leave here doing.
I pray, Father, that You would work in the hearts of those that may be here that are
not saved.
Lord, help them to get their eyes off of everybody else and to understand their own personal
situation and their need for Thee.
I pray in this moment, Lord, that people would respond and that, God, You would have Your
will and way in our lives.
We'll thank You for it.
In Christ's name we pray.