week is the better way to put that and they indicated that here's how I feel
when I'm in church and it's cold and it was a group text message and Holly
promptly responded back with a an emoji of a sweaty person saying and
this is how pastor feels when he's preaching and I was quite comical and I
have said for years I do not set the thermostat to what it would cause me to
be comfortable because all of you would be very much freezing and I said it to
try to accommodate as many within the middle group as I can you don't want my
dad controlling the thermostat that's for sure and it will be freezing and so
anyhow it is not helpful having all these windows and doors open but we
understand to increase some airflow and so Lord willing we won't have to do that
too much longer Proverbs chapter number 13 this evening I'm going to tell you
right from the beginning we're not going to be here long I'm going to use a
couple of verses from the book of Proverbs as really a springboard if you
will and then go look at a passage of scripture that we will deal with in more
detail but I want to start here in Proverbs chapter number 13 and this
evening if you're taking notes I've simply entitled the message choose your
companions wisely choose your companions wisely as we understand the
world in which we live we understand that there are many voices and there are
many ways in which we're influenced it's important I would say that it's
imperative that we would acknowledge this truth and then actively work to
ensure that we manage those influences the things that we hear the things that
we see the people that are influencing our lives there are many voices can I
tell you that we're engaged in spiritual battle warfare I've mentioned this many
times over the years but we understand the battle is raging we understand that
there are many that have an agenda there are many that are seeking to cause chaos
and confusion and that's the tactic of our enemy by the way our God is a God of
order the enemy is all about chaos and confusion and division we find that as
we look here and we think about those that are influencing us often we speak
about the importance of us actively being engaged in influencing others the
reality is that there are people that are influencing us as well and we
better be careful that we control that we manage how we're being influenced the
sources of information that we're reading the places where we're hearing
certain things we need to be careful notice what the wise man says in
Proverbs 13 in verse number 20 he that walketh with wise men shall be wise but
a companion of fools shall be destroyed that's a powerful verse of Scripture I've
titled the message choose your companions wisely we need to be careful
who we associate with we see that in this particular verse of Scripture he
that walketh with wise men shall be wise but a companion of fools shall be
destroyed look over at a New Testament verse of
Scripture keep your place there in the book of Proverbs if you will but look
over at the book of 1st Corinthians in chapter number 15 you know it's
interesting there are many pithy sayings if you will if we could use that
terminology that abound in our world and if you do some level of research and
study you'll find that many of them have a foundation upon some biblical truth
it's quite interesting when you do some of that studying and you've heard about
the whole good Apple bad Apple analogy and all of that sort of thing and we
find here in 1st Corinthians 15 and verse number 33 notice what it says be
not deceived now if a verse of Scripture starts out by saying be not deceived we
ought to pay attention we'll understand that the the writer of course we
understand the inspiration of the Scripture we understand that God is
seeking to give us some truth that no doubt it is possible shall I say common
that we would be deceived over the particular matter that is to be
discussed he says be not deceived evil communications corrupt good manners evil
communications corrupt good manners if I could give you just a brief overview of
some of that which is going on in the church in Corinth we understand this in
the 15th chapter near the end of the book but we understand as we do an
overview study as we do a detailed study through the book of 1st Corinthians that
the church in Corinth was a carnal church the church in Corinth was a
church that had divisions and all sorts of problems they were a carnal church
and the Apostle Paul said to them I can't really speak to you as unto
spiritual I got to speak to as carnal as babes and we find that as we go
through the book of 1st Corinthians and we'd study all that's going on and we
find that the Apostle Paul gives them many valuable truths in the first six
chapters and then he begins to answer questions that they shared with him he
begins chapter number seven speaking on this regard now concerning the things
that you've written they asked some questions about some things and really
if we begin to understand some of what's happening in Corinth and we'd
understand the wickedness in the city of Corinth and we'd understand some of
those things we would conclude that the church in Corinth was being influenced
by the culture it has always been the plan of God that his church influences
the culture not that the culture influences the church and we find that
in Corinth they had it backwards they were dealing with things where the
culture the society was influencing the church instead of the church
influencing the society or the culture I would say that in many regards today as
you look around the landscape of America you would find that there are many
churches that have been influenced by the culture that have been influenced by
the society that we live in when we are the ones that are to be influencing the
culture we're the light of the world the salt of the earth we have the truth of
the gospel and so we understand as we'd speak about the subject of choosing your
companions wisely that we have to be careful who we associate with notice
this as well that who and what we listen to notice what the Proverbs says the
wise man notes in Proverbs 19 in Proverbs chapter number 19 the things
that we listen to who and what we listen to it's an interesting process that you
should go through as you begin to listen to certain people it's a good thing to
do some research and find out what they really believe it's a good thing to find
out what their worldview is are they addressing subject matters from a
biblical worldview a biblical perspective or not you begin to just
hear some things I often have said that false teachers one of the things that's
so dangerous about false teachers is that they use our vocabulary but they
don't use our dictionary they'll say some of the same words that you've heard
though they'll use some of those catchwords but they mean something
entirely different because they use our vocabulary but not our dictionary and we
find that it's important for us to understand who and what we're listening
to and to ensure that we're not being adversely influenced by some that we
ought not be influenced by notice what Proverbs 1927 says cease my son to hear
the instruction that causeth to err from the words of knowledge it is
possible that we could hear the instruction that would cause us to err
from the words of knowledge and so what is it that Solomon says cease my son
don't listen to that stuff don't be influenced by those things I mentioned
that there are many voices today and we see them we hear them I shall say loud
and clear I mean there's a lot of voices out there today and we got to be careful
on how we're being influenced consider this truth from the New Testament and
then we'll get to our passage that I want to dig into and really dissect
this evening but go to Philippians 4 we're familiar with the verse of
scripture in Philippians 4 in verse number 8 being familiar with the verse
does not mean that we practice the verse amen being familiar with the verse
doesn't mean we practice the verse finally brethren
Whatsoever things are true,
whatsoever things are honest,
whatsoever things are just,
whatsoever things are pure,
whatsoever things are lovely,
whatsoever things are of good report,
if there be any virtue,
and if there be any praise,
think on these things."
Alright, there's a filter test
that needs to be applied.
We begin to hear things.
We want to understand,
does it pass the Philippians 4.8 test?
Does this information that is being given to me,
that's being spoken to me,
or through some written means,
does it pass the test of Philippians 4.8?
It would be a good idea for us to practice that.
Putting the filter on. Amen?
God gave it to us for a reason.
Listen, you want to know what kind of things to think on?
These things.
Can I tell you that, really,
and I know I said this way early on
with the whole pandemic and everything that was going on,
so many listening to news and watching news,
and I'm not saying that we shouldn't have
any level of information,
but the reality is that
I gave somebody a formula,
I said for every 20 minutes that you watch or listen to the news,
you ought to spend an hour in the Bible.
I don't know where I got that percentage kind of situation,
I just came up with it,
but what I was trying to convey was that,
man, we need the truth of God's Word.
You sit around and you listen to these people all day long,
talking all their stuff that they're spewing out.
I sat in the hospital room one day,
visiting with someone,
and we actually had to be confined to the waiting room.
It used to be that you could go to a hospital
if someone was having surgery and you could wait for them,
you could go back there,
and I got these passes that basically let me go anywhere in the hospital
until COVID-19, I can't go anywhere near the hospital.
And of course, things are relaxing now,
but it used to be that you could go in there
and as a pastor, I could go in and pray,
and I could wait and I could get in,
it didn't matter if it was visiting hours or not,
I had passes to be able to get in.
And I remember on one particular occasion,
someone's having a heart cath,
and I sat with the family there in the waiting room,
and there was this show on, I'm going to be honest with you,
I've never watched the show in its entirety,
but the show was called The View.
And it was on in the lobby,
and it was loud, and it was obnoxious,
and I wanted to throw something at the TV.
And I wasn't even watching it.
But the stuff that was spewing out of the mouths
of those people on that talk show was ridiculous.
And unfortunately, there were a whole host of people
that were sitting there watching it,
otherwise I would've just gone over and turned the thing off.
But it was loud, and it was obnoxious.
And we just overheard some of it.
Listen, some people that are listening
to that junk every single day, man, it's messing them up.
Amen?
Some people watching online
might send me some emails later, amen.
It'd be all good, amen.
It's the one thing that's interesting about online,
you never know who's watching, right?
And that's okay, I stand by it, amen.
It's junk.
And can I tell you that the networks are full of that stuff.
And you got these talking heads,
and you got these people,
and if we're not careful as to not only
who we associate with,
but also who and what we listen to,
how it influences us, how it affects us,
how it messes with our worldview.
And all of a sudden, we find ourselves saying some things
that we've actually never done any research on,
and we've never validated the truth of,
you know, and there are people
that say things that aren't true.
You know that?
Years ago, there was a commercial about the,
you know, how do you know that?
I read it on the internet,
and the idea of the commercial
was that everything on the internet is true.
You understand that's not true.
Just because you find it on the internet
doesn't mean it's true.
By the way, many of those search engine companies
run algorithms that put up search results
that they want to put up.
I told you when I was preaching through the book of Genesis
and dealing with Noah's flood,
because we're still preaching through the book of Genesis,
it'll be a while,
but dealing with Noah's flood in particular,
you type in Noah's flood,
and you're gonna get a whole lot of stuff about it
being some fairy tale kind of a situation,
because the algorithms are written
to promote those things first.
Look at Psalm 1.
This is where I want to go this evening.
Psalm chapter number one.
I believe the principles in mind from Proverbs 13 and 19
with regard to choosing your companions wisely,
I believe we see in the first three verses
of the first Psalm evidence of someone
that took the principles that we looked at
and lived by them.
Now, the reality is that many of us
are familiar with Psalm 1.
It's a very familiar passage of Scripture.
In fact, many of us have probably memorized the first Psalm,
and we could stand up and quote it,
and sometimes I fear that what happens
with a passage of Scripture
that has a high level of understanding
that we're extremely familiar with it
is that sometimes we can miss things,
because we simply, oh yeah, I know that.
I know that account.
I know that situation.
I know what happens.
And the reality is that,
especially if you've been saved for any length of time,
if you read your Bible regularly,
you must always be careful to keep it fresh.
What I mean by that is that we don't just get into autopilot.
That we ask the Lord, show me something,
teach me, minister to me.
And we have had the opportunity, personally speaking,
I've read passages of Scripture,
I've preached passages of Scripture
that I've gone back to weeks later,
months later, years later,
and I've read again,
and man, I didn't understand that before.
I didn't see that before.
And God's Word is a living book.
And we must not allow the holy to become common.
In Psalm 1, notice the Bible says,
blessed is the man that walketh not
in the counsel of the ungodly,
nor standeth in the way of sinners,
nor sitteth in the seat of the scornful.
Notice it says, but,
his delight is in the law of the Lord,
and in his law doth he meditate day and night.
And he shall be like a tree planted by the rivers of water
that bringeth forth his fruit in his season.
His leaf also shall not wither,
and whatsoever he doeth shall prosper.
Just gonna look at the first three verses this evening.
If you're taking notes, number one,
I want you to notice how this man acts.
Notice how he acts.
We often would look at this as being the blessed man.
Blessed is the man.
And I want you to notice two things
with regard to what God tells us,
with regard to his action from verses one and two.
Number one, if I could summarize verse number one,
I would summarize it this way.
Get out of the world.
Just get out of the world.
We are in the world, but we are not of the world.
Isn't that what Jesus said in John 17?
That's what he said.
And the reality is that if you read John 17,
and by the way, that's the Lord's Prayer,
you understand that as he's going through there,
and as he's praying, notice this,
he says in verse number 15,
I pray not that thou shouldest take them out of the world,
but that thou shouldest keep them from the evil.
You know what that means?
There's evil.
Amen?
We live in an evil world.
And it says, Jesus, he says,
I'm not praying that you should take them out of the world,
but that thou shouldest keep them from the evil.
They are not of the world, even as I am not of the world.
Sanctify them through thy Word.
Thy Word is truth.
And so we find as we look at verse number one
and summarize the thought of verse number one,
it would simply be this, get out of the world.
Get out of the world.
Stop allowing the world to influence you.
Look at what the Bible says.
Blessed is the man.
Look at the progression.
Number one, that walketh not in the counsel of the ungodly.
He walketh not in the counsel of the ungodly.
He's understanding that there's some influences,
there's some counsel.
He's not gonna walk in that direction.
It's interesting as you begin to see the progression
of the verse of Scripture,
that the Bible says that he walketh not
in the counsel of the ungodly.
Notice number two, nor standeth in the way of sinners.
You start walking in that way.
Before long, you start standing amongst them.
You've been walking,
and now you're standing,
and you're getting more influence.
You're hearing more.
More of that world is being put on you
and the thoughts of the world.
And we find, listen, the enemy...
Something about Satan.
He's a liar.
He's a liar. Right?
So you think that as a liar
and as a deceiver,
he's going to package that thing
as well as he possibly can.
And what happens here is we find
the Bible says,
"...blessed is the man that walketh not
in the counsel of the ungodly,
nor standeth in the way of sinners..."
Then notice this progression.
"...nor sitteth in the seat of the scornful."
So from walking, to standing, to sitting.
You think about Lot.
Lot and Abraham have a discussion.
There was some contention among their herdsmen.
Right?
Choose the land. What does Lot do?
He sees it.
He says, I want that land.
Initially, he just pitches his tent toward Sodom.
Before long, he's living in Sodom.
Before long, he's sitting at the gate.
He lost his family.
The Bible says in the New Testament
that this righteous man vexed his righteous soul.
Can you imagine?
How'd that happen?
You just start facing the wrong direction.
You just start walking with the ungodly.
You start standing and hearing
and being influenced.
Sitting in the seat of the scornful.
I think about the way in which,
and I won't read the quote to you this evening.
I've read it before.
If you'd like to have it,
I'll be glad to send it to you.
But the reality is that the enemy
has taken our classrooms in America
to use them as a platform
to promote their agenda.
It's a known fact
that they're seeking to promote their agenda.
The Darwinian evolution, the humanism,
and all of the things that are going on.
And we find that in the classrooms
across America,
this stuff is being taught.
We find here the blessed man.
We notice how he acts.
Number one, get out of the world.
Don't allow those things to influence you.
Be careful.
Remember, choose your companions wisely.
Understand the truth of influence.
Get out of the world, but number two,
get into the Word.
Get into the Word.
I read already in John 17,
he talked about the fact that
he's praying not that we'd be delivered from the world,
that we're in the world,
but we're not of the world.
And then he says,
sanctify them through Thy Word.
Thy Word is truth.
So we get out of the world,
but we must get into the Word.
Notice the actions in verse 2.
There's this contrast as the verse begins
with the word,
but His delight is in the law of the Lord.
That word delight carries with it
the idea of taking pleasure in.
If reading the Bible is a chore,
if reading the Bible is a checkmark
on a book somewhere,
if that's reading the Bible,
if that's kind of the approach,
that's not really delighting in the law of the Lord.
Delighting in the law of the Lord is when,
so let me use this maybe simple analogy.
There are certain foods that perhaps you eat
because they're good for you.
Some of those green vegetables.
My dad always, as a child,
as I would have and I never ate them
and to this day, I don't eat them.
My mom likes them.
Beets.
I think they taste like dirt.
If you like beets, that's up to you.
That's fine.
I just don't like them.
And my dad would cut those things up on his plate
and he'd say, oh, these are so good.
And he was lying every second of the way.
He's just eating them because supposedly
there's some benefit of eating them.
There are other things,
cheese steaks, cheeseburgers, pizza,
you know, all that kind of stuff,
like I don't have to force myself to eat it, right?
Like it's just good.
Somebody mentioned to me today
about eating Brussels sprouts.
Ugh, Holly likes those things.
I can't stand them.
Dean's ready to go eat, amen?
But what I'm saying is that
when I look at the way in which the terminology is used,
but his delight is in the law of the Lord,
it's not this thing of I have to read my Bible.
It's not this thing of let me make sure
I check this box because I want to read.
No, no, I'm delighting in it.
This is God speaking to me.
God's love letter, if I could use that analogy
to us as His people.
Listen, there was never a time that Holly,
when we were dating,
would give me a note or a letter
that I was not anxious to read.
I'm being honest.
She'd leave a note in my box in college,
and it didn't matter if I was running
a little bit late to class or whatever.
I want to read it.
I want to know the content of it.
I never just kind of tucked it away somewhere
and well, I'll see what that says later.
No, it was never my,
it just wasn't.
You guys remember when you were dating?
See, today they got all this technology, right?
We used to actually write notes
like on paper with pen.
Imagine that, right?
And you were anxious to read it.
And there were times in which
maybe I was going to go on a trip.
I remember going to a national preaching conference
down in North Carolina and we were dating
and she gave me some notes and she said,
now don't read them until...
What do you think you want to do?
Armando, you want to read it, right?
Because this is from the person that I love,
the person that I'm planning to marry.
This is a love note.
Amen?
This is God's Word.
God loves us.
And He gave us this book.
And we ought to delight in the law of the Lord.
Oh man, I get to read my Bible.
It's not a chore, it's a delight.
In times in which we're reading our Bible
and say, man, I can't believe that much time went by.
I understand we have other things to do in life.
I understand we have jobs
and various things that we have to tend to
and kids that are running around
that need some breakfast.
And I get it, right? I understand.
What I'm saying is that
the picture that we get here
of this delighting in the law of the Lord
is taking pleasure in it.
I can't wait until I can read my Bible.
If you're morning,
I personally like to read in the morning
after I have my coffee.
Holly likes to read in the morning
as soon as her eyeballs open up.
I'd close my eyeballs and go back to sleep.
So I don't do it that way.
I like to get some coffee and I like to read.
Occasionally, something happens.
Somebody's in the hospital.
Something weird happens.
And your time with God gets interrupted.
You're a mom and a child wakes up
before they're supposed to.
Whatever it might be.
For me, that time got interrupted.
I can't wait until I can get back
to my time with God.
My delight in the law of the Lord.
I'm not patting myself on the back.
I'm just simply saying,
when we look at the imagery
that is given to us,
when we understand what's taking place,
listen, if you can watch some news network
longer than you can read God's Word,
we need to do some examination.
Amen?
Let's just be transparent with one another.
If we can watch the news for a couple hours a day,
but we can only read the Bible
for a few minutes a day,
not only is there a problem,
but there's going to be greater problems.
His delight is in the law of the Lord.
Look at what it says.
And in His law,
doth He meditate day and night.
No doubt, as we look at this passage of Scripture
and we consider the actions of this blessed man
and we see that he's getting out of the world
and he's getting into the Word,
we find that he's meditating
to dwell on anything in thought,
to muse upon it.
Throughout the Psalms, you'll see
that little word often used,
selah.
It's good for us to meditate on the Word of God.
It's good for us to just let the Word of God
just be in our minds and stew over it
and just saturate our minds.
He combines our souls with the Word of God.
It says day and night.
No doubt in my mind that here in Psalm 1,
there's some connection to the truth in Joshua 1.
I preached a message on this
as we went through the series early on
in the book of Joshua.
Joshua 1 and verse 8.
When God says to Joshua,
this book of the law shall not depart out of thy mouth,
but thou shalt meditate therein day and night.
Why? Why, Joshua, should you meditate in this law,
in this book of the law day and night?
That thou mayest observe to do according to all
that is written therein.
For then, then is after, right?
For then, thou shalt make thy way prosperous,
and then, thou shalt have good success.
I made the statement this morning
that oftentimes we want the result
without the process.
We want the then, but we don't want the process.
We want to have our way being prosperous.
We want the good success,
but we might not want to follow
the instruction that is given.
And I find here that the Word of God
is the delight of this man,
and not only does he take pleasure in it
and have it as being his delight,
but the Bible says that he meditates in it
day and night.
Day and night.
Think about that.
Really, the idea is we're meditating day and night,
that throughout the day,
the truth of that which I have read
is on my mind.
I wonder how often,
as we read our Bibles in the morning,
I wonder how often we think about
what we read as we go throughout the day.
It's really on our mind.
Like we're really meditating on it.
It's really affecting our behavior that day.
That we really ask the question,
how is it that what I read today
can be put in practice in my life today?
We find that the first two verses of Psalm 1,
we note how he acts.
In verse number 3 of Psalm 1,
we note how he abounds.
Notice what the Bible says,
and he shall be.
Like, there's an analogy that is given to us,
a picture that is describing
the way in which this man
that is the blessed man,
how he will abound.
He shall be, notice,
like a tree planted by the rivers of water.
In your mind, no doubt,
as you think about the imagery that is given
in verse number 3 of Psalm 1,
we have the image of strength and stability
as this tree that is planted
by the rivers of water.
This tree that as we go through
the progression of verse number 3,
we'll understand that it flourishes.
We understand that it's fruitful
and so on and so forth.
But we get that picture immediately
of some stability and some strength.
Remember as we started that series
and we didn't get very far into the series
in the book of Titus,
and we titled our series in the book of Titus
Grounded and Settled.
And the reason really the thought
of the book of Titus
and what Titus was commissioned to do there
in Crete is he would go and ordain
and set in order the things that were wanting.
And we understand all that he was responsible for doing.
And we get this picture of being
grounded and settled.
The Bible tells us in Colossians 1
and verse number 23,
if you continue in the faith,
grounded and settled,
and be not moved away from the hope
of the Gospel which ye have heard
and which was preached to every creature
which is under heaven,
whereof I, Paul, am made a minister.
And we see here in this picture
in verse number 3,
this tree that's planted by the rivers of water,
this strength and stability.
But the Bible doesn't end there.
The Bible says this in verse number 3,
that bringeth forth His fruit,
and then notice this,
in His season.
You know that fruit trees have seasons.
And we would see here
that the understanding as we would begin
to see what's happening,
that bringeth forth His fruit in His season,
that it's not only fruitful,
but it's at the right time.
The reality is that there's some times
that we're not on the same time schedule
that God's on,
but it's our time schedule that's wrong,
not God's.
Because God's time schedule's perfect.
And the reality is that we look here
and we see this One that is referred to
as blessed as the man,
and we see His actions, His behavior.
He's getting out of the world.
He's getting into the Word.
And we know how He abounds.
He's like a tree.
The strength and the stability.
But He's fruitful.
And He's fruitful in His season
at the right time.
We find that the Bible then makes this statement,
His leaf also shall not wither.
It's interesting.
If you were to think about the area
in which the psalmist lived.
You would think about the terrain.
Now, I've never been to Israel.
I've seen some pictures.
I know many people that have,
and I hope one day to be able to get there.
If I don't get there,
I'll see the New Jerusalem at least.
Amen.
And the reality, however,
is that if you do a little study
and what have you,
you could find out
that as you look at the imagery
of verse number three,
this tree that's planted by the rivers of water
and how important that is
for the sustainability of trees
in that particular region.
And as you would deal with periods of drought
and not having water,
and you could see how because of the heat
and because of all of those things,
you could see some leaves that wither.
Some leaves that wither.
See, why is it that His leaf also shall not wither?
Well, if I could use the analogy
that He's plugged into the right source, right?
He's gotten out of the world,
He's gotten into the Word,
and He's receiving that sustenance spiritually
from the Lord through His Word,
and we begin to see how He abounds
and we begin to see the way
in which this is described for us
in verse number three.
And really, we're getting a good picture.
I mean, this is a positive thing.
This is a result that is desired.
Amen?
And then it ends in verse number three
with whatsoever He doeth shall prosper.
Whatsoever He doeth shall prosper.
Oh, so you mean I can do whatever I want to do
and I'm going to prosper?
No, no, no, no.
You missed all of the message.
You missed it all.
Because what we're going to do
is we're going to do what we have found
that God wants us to do.
And when we're doing what God wants us to do,
then God is going to bless that effort and that work,
and we might not be prosperous
from a world's perspective,
but we must understand that God's definition
of prosperity and success differs greatly
than the definition of the world.
There are some that have this idea
that I'm a success if I end my life
with a certain amount of money
and a certain amount of goods
and all of these sort of things.
The reality is a child of God.
I'm just wanting to hear,
well done, thou good and faithful servant.
Amen?
See, many people,
as we look to the truth of the Word of God
and we understand what God's Word has told us
and we find here that He says,
whatsoever He doeth shall prosper.
When I'm getting out of the world,
when I'm getting into the Word
and I'm delighting in the Word
and I'm meditating on the Word
and I'm no doubt because of those actions,
I'm obeying God and I'm following God's plan,
this blessed result of verse number three
is evident in my life
and we begin to see God working.
Psalm 37,
the Bible says trust in the Lord
in verse number three and do good.
So shalt thou dwell in the land
and verily thou shalt be fed.
Notice this,
delight thyself also in the Lord
and He shall give thee the desires of thine heart.
How many of you have ever heard a child of God say,
God said He'll give me the desires of my heart
and they forgot the whole first part of the verse?
Right?
God didn't just say,
I'll give you the desires of your heart.
heart. He said, delight thyself also in the Lord and he shall give thee the desires of
thy heart. Notice thine heart. Notice verse five. Commit thy way unto the Lord. Trust
also in him and he shall bring it to pass. See, when I delight myself in the Lord, here's
what happens. His desires become my desires. And if his desires are my desires, then guess
what? He's going to give me the desires of mine heart. Why? Because they're his desires.
Does that make sense? And so often we've taken things and we've pulled and we've picked and
we've taken and we've come to a completely different conclusion. We've got people running
around doing their own thing, doing whatever they want to do and saying, well, God said
he's going to bless me. What is your description of blessing? Just because you have a good
salary doesn't mean God's blessing you. In America, we look at it that way sometimes.
Biblically speaking, that is not in any way, shape or form the reality of whether God's
blessing someone or not. God promised to provide for us and I'm thankful he does.
Most of us have probably, at least not in recent years, have had to pray for our daily
bread. God's been good to us in this nation. I mean, he's been real good to us. And if
we're not careful in kind of promoting some of those ideas, we'd have a hard time being
able to take that same type of teaching to some of these other third world countries
around the world where, by the way, the Word of God works and is truth. Right? This thing
of the prosperity gospel and all these things that are promoted, it's not biblical. I'm
thankful that God chooses to bless and that God chooses to bless some with wealth and
that's perfectly fine. I'm not opposed to it whatsoever. But we have to understand that
as we look here in the passage of scripture in Psalm chapter number one, and we kind of
bring full circle back to our thought this evening of choosing your companions wisely.
Listen, if we're not careful this evening, we're going to be influenced by some people
in our world. We're going to be influenced by some things that we're hearing and we're
reading and it's going to cause us to go on a path completely different than what this
book teaches. And we have to understand that there is a battle that is raging and there
are many voices out there. As I thought about that truth of many voices being out there
and understanding what's happening in our world today with all of these negative influences
and all of these people that are teaching this teaching that is foreign to the truth
of the Word of God. And we find that we'd ask ourselves, see, there are times that people
come that grew up in a church and they come and they say something like this. Well, I
just don't believe that anymore. What changed? What happened? I've had the opportunity on
a few occasions to actually sit down and talk to some people and find out, do a little digging
and find out what happened. One man in particular, I remember like it was yesterday, I knocked
on his door. It was a Saturday morning. And I began to speak to him about the Lord. Somebody
is grilling. It smells good. Amen. Somebody smell that? Yeah, you better shut that door.
Amen. Or bring some over. The man that answered the door began to just exchange some simple
conversation. I told him who I was, where I was from and so on and so forth. And I asked
him if he was sure if he or did I go to heaven. He kind of chuckled. Can't know that. I began
to quote some verses of Scripture to him. And I'll never forget when I quoted John 14
verse number six, I said, Sir, Jesus said, I am the way, the truth, and he said, and the life. No
man cometh unto the Father, but by me. He said it. He finished the verse. It kind of took me back.
Okay, this guy, he knows some stuff. We had an extended conversation. And through that
conversation, I found out how he grew up, the church that he grew up in, what he had been
taught, etc, etc. I said, man, what happened? He told me where he went to college. I had some
understanding of the university that he went to, and some of the secular influence that he would
be exposed to at that particular school. I didn't have a ton of information on that, but I did have
some understanding of it. And I began to inquire. So what happened? Well, I sat in this class and
began to name these classes that he sat in, and how that the professor systematically tore apart
his worldview and presented him with some other perspective than this perspective, and how it just
totally destroyed his faith. It was sad. I had the opportunity to meet with that man probably four or
five times over the course of maybe four months. And it did not matter what verse of Scripture I
went to, it didn't matter what I said to this man, he was in fully with that ideology. And it was so sad.
I had thoughts, probably not the same way I think I'm now, with regard to how his parents must have
felt, how his pastor must have felt from when he was a young child. I'm not suggesting that we can
force anybody to have a certain worldview or what have you, but the reality is that that person made a
decision to be influenced by some that had a completely different worldview. And unfortunately, they did not
have a firm enough grounding themselves to be able to withstand that. That's not the truth for everyone.
There are some people that can go to some places and read some things, and they have enough spiritual
foundation that they can handle it. But you better be careful. You better be careful. Apologetics is such an
important truth, an area of study of being able to defend the truth and contend for the faith that's been
delivered. And we find that there are many influences. And we have to be careful of who we associate with. We
have to be careful of who and what we listen to. Because before long, we hear enough of that stuff. And it's just, I
mean, it is just permeating our society. I mean, the young children are being set in front of TVs that are showing
programs that are indoctrinating them as toddlers. It's happening. And then we wonder why they don't believe, why they
fall away, why this happens and why that happens. Oh, we need to be careful. We need to be careful that we protect, that we
manage how we're being influenced. And it would be a good exercise for us to not only know Philippians 4.8, but to
exercise Philippians 4.8. And so I'm going to put this in practice in my life. I'm going to be careful. And I am going to
protect how I'm being influenced. And I'm going to get out of the world purposefully. And I am going to get into the Word. And
we better have right proportions. We better understand how important it is. And sometimes we can say, well, I just want to be
informed. Be careful. Be careful who you're listening to. Be careful how that stuff is affecting you. And we have the truth of God's
Word and how powerful it is to transform our lives and to give us all the answers that we need for life. Lord, we love you. We thank you
for loving us. We thank you for the counsel of the wise man here in Proverbs, both in chapter 13 and 19, as we've used these
verses as a starting point to get there to the blessed man in Psalm 1. God, we're thankful for the opportunity to observe his
action and then to see how he abounds. God, I pray that you would help us this evening.
Lord, there are so many pieces of information that are so readily available to us.
Most today have technology at their fingertips.
We can look up anything, we get alerts all the time, we're being influenced by so many
different areas.
God, I pray that you would help us to manage how we're being influenced, who we're being
influenced by.
Lord, help us to get out of the world and to get into thy word.
We thank you for the power of your word.
Lord, I pray that you would help us to think and behave biblically.
Help us to be grounded and settled.
Work in our hearts and lives and we'll thank you for it.
In Christ's name we pray, amen.
Would you stand with me?
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano.
Maybe this evening there are some things that you've been exposed to that are influences
that you need to repent of, let's just be honest.
Maybe this evening you just want to pray and ask God to help you to be aware of the influencing
that is taking place and that God would help you to be protected from being adversely influenced.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.