the passage of scripture there with those four leprous men
and the decision that they made after they had that great discovery
and we praise the Lord for that and then this evening we're gonna look here at
Acts 14
and again dealing with the idea leading into our missions conference just a week
away
and actually less than a week if you consider the Saturday
banquet dinner and then of course Sunday morning service and what have you
and we're looking forward to all that God has in store for us
as you study the Bible you'll find as I mentioned this morning the
theme of missions you understand that to have
the heart of God is to have a heart of missions you find that the
lifeblood of a local church is its missions program
I believe so strongly
on the importance of missions and involvement in missions
I'll say this I really appreciate
and not that I have a lot of experience with any
other organization but I appreciate the way that we as independent Baptist
churches handle missions and having relationships with our missionaries
and having them come in and we can hear their presentations and what God has
called them to do
and we can interact with them we can pray with them and for them
they come back and they visit us and so on and so forth and I really appreciate
that
and I know that there are some groups that do not follow that same pattern I'm
not criticizing or what have you I just really appreciate
what I've had as a heritage of missions I appreciate
the emphasis that our church places
on missions and I have purposed
since the day that I arrived at Fellowship Baptist Church that we would
on purpose and with purpose have an emphasis on missions
and there was already a strong missions program here at our church when we
arrived and I'm thankful for that
and my desire was with the Lord's help and by the grace of God to
see that go even further
and to have a greater impact on reaching the world with the gospel
and by God's grace I believe that we've been able to see that accomplished we've
picked up we've almost doubled the number of missionaries that we supported from
when we first arrived
and we have missionaries all over the world
you give liberally and I appreciate that I'm thankful that our family
personally we have an opportunity to give to missions yes to
to tithe and to give of our offerings but to give specifically to missions to
know what God is
going to do in the world with taking the gospel
I've appreciated anew the opportunity in the last couple of years to participate
on missions trips
I had the opportunity by myself to go to Mexico back in 2017
and came back with a burden not only a greater burden for missions but for our
church to be able to take missions trips and we're all planning to do one in
2020 and of course COVID came and
that all got messed up and so we're able to do that last year by going to Panama
got a trip planned this year
and we're just excited about missions and I think there's something about
being able to go to the field
and to be able to see personally be able to interact with individuals that are
serving
what God is doing but as you study the the New Testament you'll see
how God was working to take the gospel to the known world
we understand that it was the plan of the Lord that the gospel would go forth
to the whole world and he was going to use people to do that
we find that as we look at the beginning of the book of Acts and you begin to see
what's happening in the church in Jerusalem in a growing church a
thriving church
but they weren't spreading out they weren't taking the gospel anywhere and
there was persecution that came and at the
height of that persecution we find that they were scattered abroad and Acts 8
tells us that they that were scattered abroad went
everywhere preaching the word it's important that we know
that those individuals that were scattered abroad according to Acts
chapter number 8
I have you there in chapter 14 hold your spot there and turn back to chapter 8
but I want you to see that as we look at this passage and see what's taking
place
that those that were scattered abroad they were not the leaders of the church
the leaders of the church in Jerusalem stayed in Jerusalem these were the
people that had been saved that have been
saved by the grace of God and it tells us in verse number one as you look
here
and Saul was consenting unto his death and at that time there was a great
persecution against the church which was at Jerusalem
and they were all scattered abroad throughout the regions of Judea and
Samaria then notice this phrase
except the apostles every word of God is pure
he's given us all the details that we need and he specifically included
in the canon of scripture that those that were scattered
except the apostles then you look at verse number four
therefore they that were scattered we see who they were in verse number one
they were scattered abroad notice they went everywhere
preaching the word it is the responsibility of
every child of God to be ready to give an answer for the hope that lieth within
them
to be able to stand up and speak up for Jesus Christ
and we find that that's what happened so after that scattering in Acts chapter
number 8 they end up the Gospels going forth
and we find that it's reaching to a further region
and then we come to Acts chapter 13 and that's where we begin to read about the
first missionary journey
that's how we refer to it the first missionary journey there's a second and
a third
and we look in Acts 13 and 14 and we read of this first missionary journey
and we understand that the church in Antioch it was a local church
just like our church it was a local church it was located in Antioch
and we understand there's some significant things about the church in
Antioch they were first called Christians
in Antioch right we see that we understand that
and we find that the church in Antioch it was a church that was doing the work
of God I mean they were
discipling people people were being taught and trained and people were
growing
the Bible tells us they were praying church the Bible tells us that they
fasted
we see that they were a church that that God was pleased with
a church that had the hand of God upon them
and then God shows up the Holy Spirit moves
and says separate me Barnabas and Saul for the work whereunto I have called them
and this is where we begin to see this first missionary journey
in this church the church in Antioch they played a significant role
as the gospel went throughout the region of Galatia
we find that as the church was there in Antioch
these men went out they were sent from the church the entire church didn't go
to the region of Galatia
but they were engaged and involved and they played a significant role
they did not have the kind of communications and technologies that we
have today
that we can receive emails and phone calls and voice messages and
video chats they didn't have that kind of technology
but I believe that this church in Antioch was a church that was
faithful a church that was invested in this ministry that God
called Barnabas and Saul this work that he had called them to
I believe that they faithfully prayed for Paul and Barnabas as they were on
this missionary journey
for the Bible tells us in Acts 13 and verse number 3
and when they had fasted and prayed and laid their hands on them
they sent them away I don't think they stopped praying
when they were sent away I think they continued they endured in prayer they
continued
in prayer and we find that as the gospel went into the region of Galatia
that as you go through these two chapters in chapter 13 and 14
you'll find that there was an established work
in Antioch and Pisidia there was a work that would be established in Iconium
in Lystra and in Derbe there are these four cities
in the region of Galatia when you read the book of Galatians
you find that it's not a church in Galatia it's to the churches in the
region
of Galatia a lot of times we talk about some of these
epistles the church at Ephesus the book of Ephesians the church at Philippi the
book of Philippians so on and so forth
we look at the book of Galatians it's written to those churches in the region
and those churches were established during this first missionary journey
it's so rich it's so important that we see
how God is working in what God is doing
as we come to the end of chapter 14 and begin to look at our passage this
evening
for just a few minutes I want to consider the end of the missionary
journey
as it's recorded to us in Acts 14 as we deal with this subject matter look
what God has done isn't it exciting to see God at work
I mean honestly in your life personally
in the life of a church the life of a missionary it's exciting
to see what God is doing I'm encouraged regularly
we on purpose provide updates of our missionaries we put the
the summaries of the prayer letters on our prayer request or our prayer sheet
every single week why because we want you to know how to pray for
and then to rejoice with the missionaries as God is doing a work
understand that God uses people he uses people
God is the one doing the work but he uses people
and we have the opportunity to know who some of these people are
that are going forth that are taking the gospel
when we have in our
bulletins every week. These are the missionaries of the week. You're reminded
this is where they're serving. This is what they're dealing with. What was the
last update? Our letters are in the back so that you can go and look at them. We
give you a directory. Why? Because we want you to have that personal connection
with the people that God is using. And just like the church in Antioch knew
Paul and Barnabas. They knew them. They labored together and now Paul and
Barnabas are being sent out. And we come to the end of chapter 14 and notice the
Bible. I'm going to begin reading in verse 21. In the bulletin I put as the
passage for verses 25 through 28. But let me just grab it in
context here. In verse 21 the Bible says when they had preached the gospel to
that city and had taught many they returned again to Lystra and to Iconium
and Antioch. So they go back kind of in reverse order if you will to each of the
places where they had previously been administered. Notice what they're doing
in verse 22. Confirming the souls of the disciples and exhorting them to continue
in the faith and that we must through much tribulation enter into the kingdom
of God. And when they had ordained them elders in every church and had prayed
with fasting they commended them to the Lord on whom they believed. And after
they had passed throughout Pisidia they came to Pamphylia and when they had
preached the word in Perga they went down into Adalia. And then notice in
verse 26 and when in Fence sailed to Antioch. Notice from whence they had been
recommended to the grace of God for the work which they fulfilled. As we look at
this passage of scripture just for a few minutes this evening we see the follow
up but then we start to look and we see in verse 26 that the Bible says they
sailed to Antioch not Antioch and Pisidia. Antioch where notice from whence
they had been recommended to the grace of God. The church that we're reading of
in the beginning of chapter 13 this is where they're going. If you're taking
notes notice number one they returned. Very simple they returned. They returned
to the place where they started. They returned with a purpose. They returned to
this place but I want you to understand that in verse 26 the Bible says from
whence they had been recommended to the grace of God. Notice this phrase for the
work which they fulfilled. They returned but only after they completed the
assignment. There's something about finishing. There's something about
finishing. Fulfilling. And we find that God had called them to a work and in Acts
chapter 13 in the beginning of the passage when they receive that call it
simply says separate me Barnabas and Saul for the work whereunto I have
called them. And God's called each and every one of us to a work. God's got a
plan and a purpose for every single one of us and it's absolutely vital it's
important that we seek to fulfill what God has called us to do. That we would
understand that we're yes we use the analogies the Bible uses the analogies
of a race that we're running as we think about running the race and and
finishing our course as Paul would say at the end of the book of 2nd Timothy
and we understand I want to finish well. I want to finish strong. None of us know
when the finish line is going to come for any of our lives for we understand
that death could come at any moment. The the rapture could come at any moment but
they returned after they completed the assignment and they returned to the
place where they were sent out of. Now I think that this return again they
didn't have all of the technology that we have today. There was not as many
opportunities as we have today with planning so far in advance and
understanding timing and all that sort of thing. They obviously had means of
communications. They had people that would go forth and deliver messages and
etc. But we find that word was received that they were returning. That had to be
exciting. Don't you think? The church in Antioch they didn't know how long Paul
and Barnabas were going to be gone. They didn't know exactly what they were going
to be doing but they were praying. I believe that they were invested in the
work. They may not have received many updates throughout the process of the
work because again of the the lack of communication means of communication but
we find that now that these men that God had separated and called the ministry
they're going to return. So we find that they return. I mentioned that they
returned with a purpose. Not only number one they returned, number two they
reported. They reported. Notice the Bible says this in verse 27. It says, and when
they were come and then I want you to catch this phrase, and had gathered the
church together. And had gathered the church together. They didn't have
livestream. They didn't have recordings that someone could watch at a later
time. They assembled. The church is supposed to assemble. Amen? I'm thankful I
mentioned this morning that we're able to watch livestream when we're on
vacation. There's a place and we have it if people are sick, people are
traveling, whatever. But I want you to understand that church is an in-person
situation. Amen? It is. There's no livestream that they had. There was no
I'm gonna go catch it on YouTube later because it's recorded. No. The church was
gathering and if I'm gonna hear I better be present because the only way I'm
gonna hear is if I'm there. I made the statement this morning about Brother
Jeff's Sunday school class. I think it's the third time I've said something about
it this morning or today and I said this as I started to use borrow his
illustration that he ended the class with. If you missed Sunday school, I'm sorry. You
missed it. Like it's not recorded in Sunday school. You just missed it. And
that's unfortunate. Why? Because there was the Word of God going forth that's to
help us. And we find here that the church, they gathered. The Bible tells us that
after the church gathered that when they were come and had gathered the church
together. And by the way, I don't think it was probably real hard for them to get
people to come to the place where they gathered. I don't think they had to twist
people's arms and manipulate them and try to persuade them. Man, they were
invested in the work that was going on. And they find out that Paul and Barnabas
are coming back. I want to be there. I want to hear. And so they reported. The
Bible says, notice the words of verse 27, they rehearsed all that God had done
with them. That's a simple statement that is full, power-packed statement.
They rehearsed. Notice that little word all. Isn't all such a small word but so
inclusive? I mean they rehearsed all. You ever heard like, I looked everywhere. I
did. No, no. They rehearsed all. They shared the details. They began to explain
what God, notice again, all that God had done with them. We are co-laborers with
God. We are workers together with God. God is the one that does the work. Some
plant, some water, but God gives the increase. And we find here that what a
service this must have been. The people from the church at Antioch, when they're
gathered together, they're now hearing from the lips of Paul and Barnabas how
God answered their prayers. They're hearing from Paul and Barnabas how God
was working and what God was doing. They heard of some of the persecution. If you
read through chapter 13 and 14, you find that they're chased out of the cities
and they're faced with persecution, but yet God is working. And they got to hear
that. They got to hear how their prayers were answered, how exciting it must have
been. This evening you could read Acts 13 and 14 in about 12 minutes. It's about how
long it will take you to read it. I think the service was longer than 12 minutes.
We read it, but as they're explaining it, in my mind, look, if you want to preach
next week, well, it's the missions conference the following week, just let me know. You
can then have your spiritual imagination. But I think when they gather together and
they're there and they're hearing, I think they're getting into some details, maybe
some questions asked, maybe some, like, exciting stuff. And I think that they were in a hurry.
You know, sometimes, especially here in Northern Virginia, we get in a hurry. We get in a hurry.
Everything is so... Kenny Baldwin, a friend of mine, he says this. He says, we don't go
to church to get out of church. We go to church to get something from God. And I understand
that we have to be somewhat time sensitive. I understand some of those things and the
culture that we live in, but we can't put God on a timeline. Amen? And they get to church
and they're hearing what God... I don't think anyone's, Paul, our roast is, no, like, give
me more. I often think about it when a... And I don't watch anywhere near as many sports
as I used to when I was younger, but I used to watch sports a whole lot longer or a whole
lot more often.
But it was always interesting when a game went into overtime, most times people don't
turn off the game and leave.
That's when they're on the edge of the seat, like that's when it's serious, right?
And so sometimes we think about church like they went and they were receiving, they were
excited, why?
Because they were invested, they were praying, they sent them out.
They had questions, they were able to hear what God was doing.
You don't want to miss it, you don't want to miss hearing how God is working and what
God is doing.
And the Bible says that they gathered the church together, they rehearsed all that God
had done with them and how He, God, had opened the door of faith unto the Gentiles.
Don't you think that was exciting?
I mean, I read Acts 13 and 14 and I get excited reading it.
I read the Bible and I get excited about reading how God is working and what God is doing and
I'm reminded that if God did it then, He can still do it today.
He says, I am the Lord, I change not.
He says, I'm the same yesterday, today, and forever.
Listen, if God has done working, then we're out of here.
But we're still here and so we understand that God is still at work.
God still has a plan and a purpose and we have opportunity to be involved in what God
is doing and we find this local church at the end of the missionary journey that they're
gathered together, these missionaries, they return and then they report to the church
all that God did.
That's why I titled the message, Look What God Has Done.
Isn't it exciting that we can look and see, look at what God has done.
Not what we've accomplished, but what God has done because God can do so much greater
than what we can do.
We can make a mess of things in a hurry, but God doeth all things well and God is able
to do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think.
Do you believe that tonight?
I believe that.
I believe that God is able.
I believe that God still wants to save souls.
I believe that there's people in Northern Virginia that still need to be saved by the
grace of God.
I believe that.
I believe there's people all around the world.
There's people in Guyana.
There's people in Switzerland.
Those are the two countries that are missionaries that are going to be here this week, this
upcoming week.
That's where they're going.
They're raising money to go to those two fields.
There are people there that need the gospel and I believe that as those missionaries are
surrendered and yielded and as churches like ours and others that will support them hold
the ropes and pray for them, I believe that God will do a work and then we can rejoice.
We can see how God has provided buildings and how God has saved souls and how God has
added to the church and people have been called to the ministry.
They're training and they're being sent forth and I had interaction this week with Brother
Marzouk.
They had their college graduation and there are people, they went to that field, what,
10 years ago now, and they started a church.
They've had 600 people in their church and they have a Bible college where they're training
people that are graduating to go out and plant churches, hallelujah.
That's exciting.
In just a few weeks, I'm going to have the opportunity by the grace of God and I'm so
thankful for the opportunity to stand in a church building in Belgium and preach a dedication
service for a church there that we prayed, we gave, and God did the work.
That's awesome.
Look what God has done.
They returned, they reported, and I'm going to say this, they rejoiced.
No, the text doesn't expressly state that they rejoiced, but I believe they did.
I think if you read this, I don't see how you could get around the fact that there was
rejoicing going on.
It doesn't expressly state that there was rejoicing, but I believe that the natural,
the appropriate response to all that was reported by Paul and Barnabas when they returned would
be to rejoice, to give God the glory, because as God is being exalted, look at what, notice
what God has done, how He, God, opened the door.
And there, it says in verse 28, they abode long time with the disciples.
There was a period of time in which they were there before they moved on.
And we find that as we look at this text of scripture, there was rejoicing.
You know one of the things I love about the missions conference?
I told you that it's this mix of revival meeting, but also this missions conference emphasis
of missions.
There's rejoicing.
Why?
Because you're hearing these reports.
You're hearing what God has done.
These are new missionaries for us.
We don't support any of them that are going to be here.
Typically, I try, as I plan, to have the keynote speaker be someone that we already support.
This year, we don't support any of the families that are going to be with us already.
They're all brand new to us.
However, we find that we'll get to hear what God has done.
The man that's the keynote speaker, Brother Jim Moore, he pastored for about 45 years.
He's been going to all these countries and visiting all these missionaries as an international
representative and he's going to be able to share with us some things that God is doing.
The missionaries that are raising support, they haven't been to the field yet for their
first term, but they've had survey trips.
They've been able to experience what God has done on the road of deputation, how God has
opened doors and how God has blessed and provided.
All of that is to God be the glory.
Guess what we do?
We rejoice.
Listen, when the Brown family was here a few weeks ago, it's a family that we've supported
since they were on deputation.
Now, after a couple of terms of work in Cambodia, we get to hear what God is doing.
We get to see pictures of a church and people and we rejoice.
Why?
Look what God has done.
Look what He's doing.
In just a few weeks, I'll be in Belgium, but Brother Jared Clement will be here.
It's pretty awesome, actually.
He was at our house a few weeks ago and he sat at our table and we chatted and we fellowshiped
and we rejoiced and he was sharing stuff with me and showing me blueprints of what they're
looking at doing with the building and he's showing me video and, man, I've been there.
I've been to Breck Road Baptist Church.
Personally, physically, I've been there.
I love the Clements.
God connected us and, man, they've been on the field faithfully.
I think they're nine, ten years that they've been there in England.
They're up in Liverpool and God's doing a great work.
They were here and they shared with us on the day that they were here, the last time
they were here, about a new opportunity to buy the pub that was next to their church
building and God worked all of that out miraculously.
And now to see the video of what God's doing and we sat at the table until like 1230 in
the morning, man.
We're just rejoicing.
It's like, man, tomorrow's an early morning but we're just excited.
And then he found out that we're going to Ireland and to Belgium and he's like, man,
I want you to come to England when you're there.
Like, you're just right there.
When are you going?
And I said, the dates.
And he's like, I'm going to be in America.
He's like, we're coming home for one month.
We haven't scheduled one meeting.
And I said, good.
Put us on the calendar for June 22nd.
I said, because I'll be preaching over there and you can preach here.
And he said, I'll do it.
And so guess what?
He's going to be here on June 22nd and I've already seen the video that you're going to
see.
If you don't rejoice, you're not paying attention.
I'm just being blunt because I've seen the video.
If you don't rejoice, you're not paying attention or you're not invested.
But when you see what God's doing, man, how can you not rejoice?
We serve a great God.
We really do.
And we have the opportunity to be involved in what God is doing.
It's hard for me to fully comprehend that, that the God of the universe, who doesn't
need me, who doesn't need you, has chosen in His infinite wisdom to use us, to allow
us to be the hands and feet of Jesus, as many have referred to.
That we can be co-laborers with God.
I preached that just a few weeks ago from 2 Corinthians 6.
We are workers together with Him.
Man, what a privilege.
And we get to do this.
We have a missions conference coming up.
I'm excited.
I love it.
I really do.
It's a lot of work.
It's a lot of preparation.
It's a lot of work behind the scenes.
We show up for the services, but we're doing stuff with the missionaries throughout the
days, all the things.
But I love it.
We get to Thursday, Friday, man, we're wore out, but we love it.
You come every night.
You work every day.
I get it.
It's a commitment, but it's worth it because we get to see what God is doing.
We get to say, you know what?
I can have a part in what God is doing.
Praise the Lord.
Look what God has done.
They returned, they reported, and they rejoiced.
I think there was great rejoicing.
I don't think anyone was eager to leave.
I really don't.
You know, sometimes I sit back and I think about our church.
We end church, we end the service, and like 45 minutes later, half of us are still here.
And I'm like, man, I could have preached a little bit longer.
But I love it.
Why?
Because we're fellowshipping, we're rejoicing.
That's what it's about.
And here, when I look at this passage, I think, man, that is what the work of God is all about.
Being invested and then rejoicing when we get to hear what God has done.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you so much for loving us.
We thank you, God, for your word and for the truth of your word.
We thank you for the part that we can have in missions.
God, I pray that you would prepare us this week spiritually.
Lord, that we would be in a place where we are ready for what you have for us.
I pray, God, that you would move and work, guide and direct.
And we'll thank you for all that you'll do.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Amen.