14, Proverbs chapter 14, and then I also want you to get your place in Nehemiah
chapter number 1.
Proverbs chapter 14
and then we'll be over primarily in Nehemiah chapter number 1 this morning
and looking at this portion of Scripture as you know and I mentioned even during
the announcements this morning
that in just a few days America will celebrate 250 years
and what a milestone celebration and we're obviously
as Americans we're excited about that. You've seen things all over the place
with regard to 250
and obviously there's the DC Gospel Outreach, Brandon and Anna are here this
morning and
I've been told by others, Kevin and Barbara were down there, it's amazing how
many people are down there
passing out literature and asking if they'd pray with you and etc.
And you see it all over the place, America's celebrating 250 and it's
certainly a milestone and we're thankful it will be celebrated.
Several people said, are you going to go to DC on July 4th? No.
Absolutely not, amen. I have no interest whatsoever
in being down there with all the other millions of people that will be down
there.
I am personally of the persuasion that watching fireworks on the TV is
perfectly fine and acceptable. Now no one else in my family agrees whatsoever
but they're not the one that is always hot and sweating and dealing with
driving through the traffic of all the other people
and but so we'll go somewhere probably to watch the fireworks but I'd be
content in my air-conditioned living room, amen.
And especially if you looked at the forecast this week it's going to be
triple digits most of the days this week
and so we are certainly thankful for this milestone but I want you to
consider
that approximately 2,700 years before the Declaration of Independence was
signed
the Lord moved Solomon, we know all scriptures given by inspiration of God,
holy men
of old spake as they were moved by the Holy Ghost and
2,700 years roughly before the signing of our Declaration of Independence
Solomon penned these words in Proverbs 14 and verse 34
righteousness exalteth a nation
but sin is a reproach to any people in fact on the front of our bulletin this
morning
you see a part of Proverbs 14 34 that first part
righteousness exalteth a nation. I've often pondered the words of this
particular
verse of scripture I've always found it quite interesting
that the truth or the principle that God gives us here in Proverbs 14 and verse
is applied broadly. We find here that
Solomon of course if you begin to think about when he's writing and
what his particular position is he's king of Israel
and as king of Israel he's king of a nation, of a people
and God had had it set up that it was a theocracy but of course
the people said we want a king, we want to be like the other nations and you had Saul,
David, and Solomon as kings of a united kingdom. After the reign of Solomon it
becomes a divided kingdom and you have
Israel to the north and Judah to the south and
you find here that the verse of scripture again every word of God is
pure
and God chooses his words purposefully
I said to some young guys just this past week I said listen
we're not always master communicators but God is and God always says exactly
what he means to say and he always means
exactly what he says and here
he did not say righteousness will exalt Israel
but sin will be a reproach to Israel no he uses the terms broadly if you will
righteousness exalteth a nation
but sin
is a reproach to any people and we see that word nation and we see that word
people and we understand again
the application of the principle of the truth that is given to us here
in Proverbs chapter 14 in verse number 34
and it's an important principle that is foundational for us to understand this
morning
listen the Bible tells us that the righteous God loveth righteousness
we understand this morning that God is in control of the affairs of mankind and
he is the creator and he is the sustainer and I'm thankful to be an
American I'm thankful to be here in this nation and I'm thankful
to be alive in the era that will celebrate our 250th anniversary
I'm not yet 50 so I wasn't alive during the 200th anniversary but
some of you were and some of you remember that and
and so I'm thankful but I wanna be clear this morning
that before being an American I'm a Christian and it's important that we
understand our identity in fact we live in a
era of human history where there's so much with regard to identity and
identity politics and identity just broadly whatever category you want to
deal with
and it's important that we understand this morning
if you've been saved by the grace of God if you know for sure that your sins have
been forgiven and you're heaven-bound
that first and foremost you are a Christian
that happens to live in America
and I'm thankful to be an American but I understand there's Christians all over
planet earth and I'm thankful for those Christians all around the globe I'm
thankful for souls that have been saved missionaries that go out to plant churches
and we find here this important principle
in whatever land we may find ourselves now we're in America so we understand
the application and we'll
be able to deal with some of that and so we see again about 2700 years before the
signing of our Declaration of Independence we see
that God moved Solomon to pen these words
I want you to understand again if you can think about a timeline
from the time that Solomon wrote these words if you fast forward about 500
years
and I asked you to be in Nehemiah chapter number one and look there Nehemiah
chapter number one
this is approximately 500 years or so after
the writing of Solomon there in Proverbs chapter 14 in verse number 34
righteousness exalteth a nation
but sin is a reproach to any people that's what the Bible says that's the
principle that is given in Proverbs 14 in verse number 34
and so Solomon wrote those words and about 500 years later
we read this I'm gonna read verse 3 we're gonna look at the first seven
verses of Nehemiah 1 but look at verse 3
and they said unto me the remnant that are left of the captivity there in the
province notice what it says
are in great affliction and what does it say
reproach what did the Bible say in Proverbs 14 in verse number 34 righteousness
exalteth a nation
but sin is a reproach to any people
and here the people tell Nehemiah
that they're in great affliction and
reproach and reproach the wall of Jerusalem also is broken down
and the gates thereof are burned with fire
as we look at this portion of scripture in Nehemiah chapter number one I hope
that God will help us
to learn some important principles begin reading with me in verse number one the
Bible says the words of Nehemiah
the son of Hakaliah and it came to pass in the month
Chislu in 20th years I was in Shushan the palace that Hanani one of my
brethren
came he and certain men of Judah and I asked them concerning the Jews that had
escaped which were
left of the captivity and concerning Jerusalem
and they said unto me the remnant that are left of the captivity
there in the province are in great affliction and reproach
the wall of Jerusalem also is broken down the gates thereof are burned
with fire and it came to pass when I heard these words that I sat down
and wept and mourned certain days and fasted and prayed before the God of
heaven
said I beseech thee O Lord God of heaven
the great and terrible God that keepeth covenant and mercy for them that love
him
and observe his commandments aren't you thankful
to know some things about the character and nature of God
I'm thankful that Nehemiah when he went to God in prayer as he begins praying in
verse number five
he knew who God was he knew who he was praying to there are certain
aspects with regard to the attributes of God that Nehemiah was aware of
and he prays according to the character of our God
in verse number six let thine ear now be attentive
and thine eyes opened thou mayest hear the prayer of thy servant
which I pray before thee now day
and night for the children of Israel thy servants and confess the sins of the
children of Israel
which we have sinned against thee both I
and my father's house have sinned
we have dealt very corruptly against thee and have not kept the commandments
nor
the statutes nor the judgments which thou
commandest thy servant Moses
as we look at this portion of scripture understanding the principle of
Proverbs chapter 14 in verse number 34
righteousness exalteth a nation but sin
is a reproach to any people as we look here at Nehemiah 1 verses
1 through 7 I want you to notice first of all with me this morning
the request the request I want you to notice specifically
that Nehemiah in chapter number one he talks about the timing
he talks about who he is in the timing he's the son of Hacaliah came to pass
in the month
Chislew in the 20th year and he talks about where he
was, not only who he is, but where he was. He was in Shushan the palace, according
to verse number one. But in verse number two, things kind of change, if you will,
because the Bible talks about this man Hanani. He refers to him as one of my
brethren, and he says he came. Notice it says that Hanani, one of my
brethren, came, he and certain men of Judah. But then notice this, when we
think about the request, the next three words there, I asked them. I asked them.
Now Nehemiah was about a thousand miles away, and he's in the palace as the
cupbearer of Artaxerxes. That's where he is. He's not really close to Judah
proximity-wise. He's about, again, a thousand miles away. It's a great
distance, and you begin to think about even the journey, the trek to go there,
and how challenging it would be, and how difficult it would be. But though he had
been, because of the captivity, because of the Babylonian captivity, and all that
had taken place, though he had been removed from Israel, from Judah, we find
that as we look at verse number two, and we note the request, I would say it this
way, that though he was a thousand miles away, though he was in the palace, though
he was the cupbearer of Artaxerxes, he had enough concern to ask about his
homeland. And I want you to understand that I believe Nehemiah here, he did not
want some sugar-coated kind of an answer. I believe that he wanted to know the
truth with regard to the situation that was there in the homeland. And he asks
specifically in verse number two, I want you to see that he asked two things. He
asked about the people. He asked about the people. It says, and I asked them, notice,
concerning the Jews that escaped, which were left of the captivity. He was, he
wanted to know about the people. How are the people? And then he says, and concerning
Jerusalem, the people and the place. That's what he's asking about. Can I tell you that
the most significant out of the request is inquiring about the people, because
people is what really matters. We sang during the missions conference on Sunday
evening, people need the Lord. We understand that as we go forth and seek
to give the gospel to a lost and dying world, as we provide you with gospel
tracts and opportunities and avenues, and as we have new move-ins and all sorts of
other opportunities, door-knocking, etc., to get out. Why? Because the people are the
people that Christ died for. The people, the condition of the people, that's what
matters most. And we find that Nehemiah, before he asks about the place, now he
does ask about the place, but we see specifically that he inquires, he makes a
request to his brother Hanani and these other men. He asked them, he wanted to
know, how are they doing? How are the people? How's the place? And as we think
about the request, and sometimes we're just content to be in our little silos, so
to speak, and don't really want to know all the things that are going on, you hear
sometimes people will use the phraseology of people having their head
in the sand. And we understand what that kind of communicates, and the fact that
they're not aware of things that are taking place around them. And we find
that though Nehemiah, separated by a great distance, in a place that he's in
the palace, and he's the cupbearer. By the way, the position of cupbearer was not, I
mean, you think about it, kind of mixed emotions thinking about it, because you
could, if someone tried to poison the king, you were probably the first one to die,
because you're the cupbearer, but you also are in the palace, in the presence
of the king, right? And so it's kind of one of these, like a comfortable kind of
a situation, but there's also a great level of danger that's associated with
it. And you understand that to be a cupbearer, you had to have a great
testimony, you had to have high integrity. Why? Because your position was extremely
vital and important, and we find that here, this man is in that position, but
he cares. But he cares. See, sometimes if we're not careful, we can think about
where we are in life, and all the things that we have, and things are going well,
and here's what this situation is, and we might forget about understanding
broader what's going on around us. What about the people around us? And we see
the request, and I want you to note with me number two, the report. We see these
phrases, when we think about the request, the Bible says in verse number two, I
asked them, and then you see when you consider the report this morning in verse
number three, you'll read this phrase, they said unto me. They said unto me. Why
did they say what they said? Well, because he asked. Because he asked. You notice in
verse number two, the Bible says that Hanani, one of my brethren, came, he
was an incitement of Judah. It doesn't say that they came and just gave this
report. It says that he asked them, he inquired, he made the request, he showed a
measure of interest to understand what was going on, and that's just taking
enough time to care. You know what I mean? Sometimes we get so busy that we don't
even ask somebody how they're doing, and what's going on in their life, and we're
just kind of going through our own life, and woe is me maybe, and look at all of
my problems, but we find that he asked, he made that inquiry, he made the request,
and so we see the report, they said unto me. Now in verse number three, the Bible
says, and they said unto me, the remnant, so notice that they begin to answer
about the people first. The first request was about how are the people, and then
about the place, and it says the remnant that are left of the captivity there in
the province, notice what the Bible says, they're in great affliction and reproach.
Great affliction and reproach. You begin to think about the testimony of these
men, they had been there, the Bible says that they returned, that they came, in
verse number two, they had been there in Judah, and they come with this eyewitness
account, this report, the word reproach means to be a shame or disgrace, and we
find here that the Bible says that they're in great affliction and reproach.
Not a great report, but an honest report. Not a great report, but an honest report.
By the way, I'm glad that these men didn't just say, oh everything's good,
everyone's fine, because they weren't. The situation that's explained here in
Nehemiah chapter number one is serious. They were in not just affliction, but in
great affliction. They were dealing with reproach. Notice as the Bible continues
to go forward and begins to provide us with an answer with regard to not only
the people, but then concerning Jerusalem, the place, it says the wall of Jerusalem
also, notice what it says, is broken down. The wall represented a measure of safety.
The wall was something that people would look to and understand, again, being Jewish
and having that ancestry and having been there and knowing all that takes place,
and you find that Hanani and these men that came from Judah, that they say the
wall, the wall of Jerusalem is broken down. The gates thereof, notice what he
says, are burned with fire. The report was provided to them. It was an honest report.
It was a dim report, if you will, and I want you to consider just a few things.
Why were they in this condition? Why is it that we read that the Bible says that
they were in great affliction and reproach, that the wall of Jerusalem was
broken down, that the gates were burned with fire? Why is that? Well, we don't have
to reach a conclusion or make some assumption based on our own interpretation.
The Bible tells us exactly why they're in the condition that they're in. We read
already the principle in Proverbs 14 and verse 34, that righteousness exalteth the
nation, but sin is a reproach to any people. Hold your place here in the book
of Nehemiah and look over to the book of Lamentations, if you will, in Lamentations
chapter number 1. Jeremiah, Lamentations, and then Ezekiel, just to kind of help you
out here this morning. Lamentations, notice what the Bible says in Lamentations
chapter 1. Now, Jeremiah is the human penman of the book of Lamentations. We
understand that the Babylonians had just taken captive the nation of Judah, and
Jeremiah had been preaching that. He'd been preaching about judgment that was
coming. Why was the judgment coming? Because of the sin. They would be in 70
years of captivity. The Bible makes it extremely clear that there'd be a
remnant that would return, and Jeremiah preaches, and he's faithful, and guess
what happens? They hate Jeremiah, by the way, because he's preaching faithfully,
and he's dealing with all sorts of opposition and difficulty, and yet
Jeremiah is faithful. And then we come to the book of Lamentations to lament, and
to begin to think about many things in this particular book of Lamentations, and
to consider the heaviness, and the weeping, and all the things. But I want
you to notice in verse number 8 of Lamentations chapter number 1, notice
what the Bible says in verse number 8.
Jerusalem hath grievously, what's it say? Sinned. Grievously sinned. Therefore, she
is removed. All that honored her despise her, because they have seen her nakedness,
yet yea, excuse me, she scytheth and turneth backward.
Jerusalem hath grievously sinned, therefore she is removed.
We won't take the time this morning, but maybe you jot it down in your notes.
Leviticus chapter number 26, and if you'd go to that chapter and if you'd read through
that chapter, you'll find that God provides the children of Israel through Moses a bunch
of promises.
In that passage, he deals with promises based on obedience and what they could expect to
receive as they obeyed the Lord and as they walked with God and how God would bless them
and how God would provide for them and all that God would do protecting them, etc.
And God provides them with this promise, with these promises there in Leviticus chapter
number 26, and we find that as you read through the chapter that there's a distinction that
takes place and you read through it and you find that after he deals with all of these
blessings and all these things that will come to pass, he says if you walk in my statutes
and keep my commandments and do them, then I will do this.
Chapter 26, verse 3 and verse 4 all the way down.
But then you come to verse 14 and it says, but if you will not hearken unto me and will
not do all these commandments and if you shall despise my statutes or if your soul abhor
my judgments so that you will not do all my commandments but that you break my covenant,
then God's going to do all these things.
In fact, in Jeremiah it's quite interesting because the people in Jeremiah's day, Jeremiah's
prophesying, he's preaching, his message never changed, amen?
But yet there were times they came to him, in fact secretly the king comes to him and
he says, hey listen, we don't want anyone to know that I'm coming to you, alright, don't
tell anyone.
Do you have a word from the Lord?
Yeah, the same word I've always had, judgment's coming.
You're going to be destroyed, you're going to be taken captive, right, is that what happens?
And they want someone to itch, tickle their ears and give them something that they want
to hear and Jeremiah never changed his message.
In fact, there was a time in which they came to Jeremiah and said, hey, is God going to
be with us?
Is God going to help us?
And Jeremiah says, no, God's going to fight against you.
Now that's not very encouraging.
Why was God going to fight against them?
Because Israel, Jerusalem have grievously sinned.
And judgment was coming.
Listen, the righteous God loveth righteousness.
Righteousness exalteth a nation, but sin is a reproach to any people.
And we find as we begin to look at this passage of scripture and yes, understanding historically
the timing of it and who's being spoken about, but when we understand the principle with
regard to the truth in Proverbs chapter 14 and verse number 34, that that principle can
be broadly applied to any nation because righteousness exalteth a nation and sin is
a reproach to any people.
And so we find that they receive this report and we understand the reason that they find
themselves in the condition that they do, that there's great affliction, that there's
reproach.
The wall is broken down.
The gates are burned with fire.
And we find here that they had sinned grievously.
What lessons can be learned?
Well, we look back to history and you can learn many lessons from history.
Unfortunately, there are those that study history and are bound to repeat the same mistakes
that have been recorded for us in history.
We find not only that, but you'll find that there are revisionists that try to rewrite
history and they try to change things.
And we see that even in our nation today.
We see how that they're trying to change things and all that's taken place.
But what I want you to understand that we have here before us a really an example of
this principle from Proverbs chapter 14 and verse 34.
There's a request that is made and then the report is given.
And just for a moment this morning, I want you to consider just a few things about our
nation because the Bible says that sin is a reproach to any people.
God has been good to America.
Is America perfect?
Absolutely not.
But there are still people from all over the world that want to be in America.
They risk everything to come to this nation.
It's true.
And for all of our failures and for all of our sins, God has been good to this nation.
And often here, maybe even this week, you'll sing the song, God bless America.
Can I tell you we need to start thinking about it this way, America bless God.
Amen?
God has blessed America.
But can I tell you that God has told us in his word and he's given us principles that
we look at in his word that judge, listen, our God is just.
He is a just and righteous God.
And if God judged his people, Israel and his people, Judah, and we see what's taken
place, listen, God help us to come to a place that we acknowledge the sin of our nation
and our need for repentance and our need for revival.
We find here that as we begin to think about just a few things, listen, today in America,
we are a nation that is marked by immorality, immorality.
I mean, the moral compass of our nation is so out of just kilter.
It's amazing.
It's unfortunate how the moral compass is just so messed up.
But you know why that is?
Because this book has been removed from the public place.
This book, listen, when you sat in a classroom, when you saw posted on various places in the
public arena, the Ten Commandments that had some impact on the individual, whether they
believed them or not, they saw that that was what God said.
Those were God's commandments.
It impacts morality.
A nation that's marked by immorality, do you know in America every year the number now
is about 1.1 million abortions in our nation annually.
That's the reported number.
Who knows what the, God knows what the actual number is.
I don't know and you don't know.
The reports don't tell us.
15,000 murders in America every year.
We understand the truth that evil men and seducers shall wax worse and worse, deceiving
and being deceived.
Begin to think about these things that have taken place in our nation.
Listen our nation, we have pride at the highest level.
Pride at the highest level.
The President of the United States last week, two weeks ago at the G7 Summit made the statement
that without him Israel would not exist.
From a biblical perspective that is absolutely absurd.
Absolutely absurd.
Pride.
It's what it is, it's pride.
I was reading through the book of Daniel this morning, maybe it would be a good thing for
some of our leaders to read through the book of Daniel because Nebuchadnezzar was the most
powerful man on earth at that particular time.
Look at this Babylon that I've built and I've made and he's on the field like a wild beast.
And at the end of the chapter, you know what he says?
God is able to abase.
You know what the Bible says?
God tells us that pride, in the book of Proverbs, that pride brings destruction, that pride
brings contention.
Amen?
The Bible's true.
The Bible says this, God resisteth the proud but giveth grace unto the humble.
Listen we need some humility, we need some humility.
We're a prideful nation, prideful and God resisteth the proud.
We have this idea, this mentality in America that we've, you know, I'm a self-made man,
I've pulled myself up by my own bootstraps and I do, listen, I'll be looking in John
chapter 15 this evening but Jesus said without me you can do nothing.
You think about the abuse and the murders and the fornication and pornography and covetousness
and idolatry and you just list all of these things, listen, these are the things that
are permeating our nation.
39.2 trillion dollars in debt, wow.
I can't even fathom the number.
All the zeros.
Listen, our nation's in trouble.
I love America but I'm a Christian before I'm an American and I love America but I look
to the Bible and I see that the scriptures say that righteousness exalteth the nation
but sin is a reproach to any people.
There's no asterisk in your Bible that says accept the United States of America.
Amen?
Sin is a reproach to any people.
And as we look here at the text of scripture and we see the request, I ask them, we see
the response that they said unto me, I want you to consider with me, sorry, the report,
the request and then the report number two they said unto me and then notice the response
of Nehemiah.
In verses four through seven.
and we see number three, if you're taking notes,
the response.
Notice with me the words, it's so powerful to see
the way that Nehemiah responds to what he hears.
And again, he only heard the report because he made inquiry.
He receives from Hanani and these certain men of Judah
this report because he asked, because he made a request.
How are the people and how is the place?
And he cared enough to know.
And we find the Bible says in verse number four,
that came to pass when I heard these words.
Notice the words that described for us
the response of Nehemiah.
It says that I sat down, number one, and wept, and wept.
I believe this morning that Nehemiah understood
with great clarity why the people were in the condition
that they were in.
I believe that he was well aware of the fact
of the principle that we've read in Proverbs chapter 14
in verse number 34, that sin is a reproach to any people.
I believe that Nehemiah understood,
even as he would hear Jeremiah preaching
and all that would take place,
I believe he had an understanding
of why the people were in the condition that they were in.
Great affliction and reproach.
The Bible says that he wept.
You know, it's interesting if you study
through the scriptures and you begin to think
about those that wept.
Jesus wept a couple of different times.
One at the tomb of Lazarus,
and another is he talks about weeping over Jerusalem.
We think about Jeremiah.
We refer often to him as the weeping prophet.
We think about the prophet of old,
the man of God, Elisha.
He wept.
You think about the apostle Paul.
The Bible says of the apostle Paul
that he ministered day and night with tears,
the Bible says in Acts chapter number 20.
The Bible says that Nehemiah hears this report.
When I heard, when I heard these words,
I sat down and I wept.
I wonder when's the last time we wept
about the condition of our nation.
I mean, just wept.
Not having our head in the sand,
not having a sugar-coated report
that everything's good.
Oh, did you see the stock market?
Did you see this?
It's higher than it's ever been.
We got the greatest.
No, no, I'm talking about the condition of the people,
the hearts of humanity.
I'm talking about that.
Listen, we're in a place today in America,
and I understand, I already mentioned
about the debt of our nation.
I think our economy could crash in a moment.
I just believe that.
I find that we are living in a time and a place
that we're increased with goods
and have need of nothing like the Laodiceans.
We have so much, we've been blessed so much,
but it's made us so apathetic and indifferent.
And just as long as I have whatever
and my portfolio looks good and everything.
Listen, I'm telling you,
we gotta think about the condition of humanity.
What shall it profit a man if he gained the whole world,
but loses his own soul?
Mark eight.
See, we're in a place where some of God's people,
we need to weep.
We see what's going on around us.
He says, I wept, notice what it says, and mourned.
And mourned.
It means to grieve, it means to lament.
And we see that he uses these two words
to describe his response after receiving the report.
He wept and mourned, it says certain days.
Listen, this wasn't just for a 30 seconds.
This wasn't that some motivational speaker
stood before him and gave him some emotional,
draw the heartstrings and kind of an emotional moment,
and then just, no, for certain days.
This was impactful when he heard the report.
Somebody said this to me years ago.
They took a missions trip,
and they went to a place that might be
maybe described as being a third world country.
And they said, you know,
one of the things that I walked away with
is I understood that America's in the same place
that they are, but we can cover it up.
We can cover it up.
It's like putting paint on some rotted wood.
Right, you just kind of,
you get a house that's falling apart,
and someone comes in and flips that thing,
and they just put some new drywall up,
but they put it to some rotted four by four,
or two by fours.
It's not gonna help real good.
It's gonna be a problem.
See, we can put paint on it.
We can cover it up.
But the heart, the condition of souls of humanity,
souls are dying.
The response, he said, I wept, I mourned certain days,
and then notice it says, and fasted and prayed
before the God of heaven.
He fasted and he prayed.
Fasting is associated with this idea
of really demonstrating to God our seriousness.
I said this a while ago as I preached on a Wednesday
about this kind cometh forth by nothing
but by prayer and fasting,
that unfortunately, in many of the modern translations,
that word fasting is removed,
and we see the attack of the enemy with regard to fasting,
but then we find even in our modern day
how that fasting has been presented
as being primarily a physical thing,
not a spiritual thing.
So many people that are fasting for diet purposes
of losing weight and having this intermittent fasting
and so on and so forth,
and I'm not criticizing you if you're doing that.
I'm just simply saying that the primary use
of the idea of fasting is spiritual,
and it reveals that I'm gonna deny myself
and why, because I'm showing God the seriousness
of my heart, and he says that he fasted and he prayed,
and we begin to look here.
We find these words that are given to us
in verse number four, wept, mourned, fasted, prayed.
In verse number six, you see the word confess, confess.
As we continue to read in context
and we understand what Nehemiah says
as we find in verse number four
that he fasted and prayed before the God of heaven,
in verse number five, I beseech thee.
Can you think about the word beseech?
We often use it in context of Romans 12, and we should,
because in Romans 12, the apostle Paul says,
I beseech you, therefore, brethren, by the mercies of God,
and we talk about how Paul is pleading
and shall I say begging,
and here we find that Nehemiah begins to pray.
He says, I beseech thee.
Do you see the seriousness, the anguish of soul,
if you will, as he's seeking the Lord?
Why?
It's because of a report that he heard about his homeland.
It's because of the understanding
that sin is a reproach to any people.
We find that here, he says,
I beseech thee, O Lord God of heaven.
Aren't you thankful to know him?
What a blessing to know that he is the Lord God creator.
He's the creator of all things,
and it says the great and terrible God.
Notice it says that keepeth covenant and mercy
for them that love him and observe his commandments.
Now, let me say this, in verse number five,
we're thankful that he keepeth covenant
on the positive side,
but his promise to bring judgment is just as sure
as his promise to bring blessing.
The promise of Proverbs 14, verse 34a
is just as certain as the promise of Proverbs 14, verse 34b.
What do I mean by that?
Righteousness exalteth the nation.
That is a promise that is certain and sure.
Sin is a reproach to any people.
He says in verse six, let thine ear now be attentive,
that eyes open, that thou mayest notice what he says,
hear the prayer of thy servant,
which I pray before thee now.
Notice what it says, day and night.
He was persistent.
Again, this was not as you see in verse number four
when it talks about certain days,
and now in verse six, day and night.
This is not just some emotional response
to some rally cry that he hears.
This is not just some momentary kind of a thing.
Listen, there are times
in which you can get emotional responses.
We don't need to respond emotionally.
We need to respond biblically.
What do I mean by that?
Well, again, to reference the book of Daniel,
there are some guys that are gonna go to a fiery furnace,
and they made a decision based on principle.
What was the principle?
Thou shalt have no other gods before me.
They're not to bow down before any images.
And Nebuchadnezzar, hey, I'll make this big old statue.
When you hear the music, bow down.
Hey, they didn't bow down.
Their decision was not an emotional decision.
Their decision endured even though he comes and says,
I'm gonna give you another opportunity.
And even though they say, okay, heat that thing up,
and we're gonna send you in.
Listen, they never changed.
Why?
Because their decision was based on biblical truth.
And therefore, that decision can endure.
That decision will last.
And we find here that Nehemiah, he's in this position,
and the Bible says certain days in verse number four
and verse number six, day and night.
So he's praying, and notice how he prays.
He says, which I pray before thee now,
day and night for the children.
of Israel, thy servants, and confess the sins of the children of Israel, which we have sinned
against thee. Both I and my Father's house have sinned." You know what Peter said? Judgment
must begin where? At the house of the Lord. Amen? That's what he said. Sometimes we come
to the place where we can point at, look at all their sin. But what about our sin?
What about our sin? Nehemiah says, I confess the sins of the children of Israel, which we,
includes himself in there, which we have sinned against thee, both, now makes it really plain,
both I and my Father's house have sinned. Can I say this at this moment? I'm so thankful that
our God is gracious and merciful. I'm so thankful that with thee there is forgiveness. That's what
the Bible says about our God. I'm thankful for the wonderful promise in Acts 1, excuse me,
in 1 John 1, in verse number 9, when the Bible says that if we confess our sins, he is faithful
and just to forgive us and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness. Praise God. I'm thankful for
1 John chapter 2, in verse number 1, where the Bible says that we have an advocate with the
Father, Jesus, Christ Jesus, the righteous. Man, I'm so thankful to have an advocate with the
Father. You've heard me say this before, the idea of an advocate, a defense attorney. Listen,
it's not that he's pleading our innocence. He's simply saying, yes, they're guilty, but I paid
for it. Praise God. Confession. By the way, if we say that we have no sin, well, 1 John 1 deals
with that in two areas. He says, if we say that we have no sin, then we are, the truth is not in us
and we make him, God, a liar. So we look here and we see the confession. We see the response
of Nehemiah. He wept, he mourned, he fasted, he prayed, he confessed. Notice in verse 7,
we have dealt very corruptly against thee and have not kept the commandments nor the statutes
nor the judgments, which now command us thy servant, Moses. It's kind of interesting in
verse number 7, where he says that we've dealt very corruptly against thee. And again, you understand
he confesses the sin. He uses the word multiple times in verse number 6, confess the sins of the
children of Israel, which we have sinned against thee, both I and my father's house. And we find
it's sin that is a reproach to any people. We find that he says that we've dealt very corruptly
and it's there in Lamentations, as we read a moment ago, that Jeremiah says that Jerusalem,
that listen, it was a, it was a situation in which they were disobedient and they had sinned and
they had sinned grievously. And I want you to understand here that as Nehemiah is responding,
he references what they did. They've not kept the commandments nor the statutes nor the judgments,
which now command us thy servant, Moses. We looked at Leviticus 26, or I referenced it
in Leviticus 26. Listen, Nehemiah understood the Old Testament, understood the principles
and he's confessing this response. I see the response of Nehemiah. It continues in verse 8.
Remember, I beseech thee the word that thou commandest thy servant, Moses saying,
if you transgress, I will scatter you abroad among the nations. That's exactly what was
happening or what had happened, the condition that they find themselves in verse 9. But if you turn
unto me and keep my commandments and do them, though there were of you cast out under the
uttermost part of the heaven, yet will I gather them from fence and will bring them unto the
place that I have chosen to set my name there. Now, these are thy servants and thy people whom
thou hast redeemed by thy great power and by thy strong hand. Oh, Lord, I beseech thee. He uses
the word again. Let now thine ear be attentive to the prayer of thy servant and to the prayer of
thy servants who desire to fear thy name and prosper, I pray thee, thy servant this day and
grant him mercy in the sight of this man, for I was the king's cupbearer. And even as you enter
into chapter number two, as he gets into the presence of the king, we find the Bible tells us
that he had the sorrow of heart and he had not been sad in the presence of Artaxerxes previously.
Listen, this had a great effect on him. It impacted him greatly. I would say of the response this
morning that it's both appropriate and exemplary. It's an appropriate response. When you hear about
the condition to weep and to mourn and to fast and to pray and to confess, it's appropriate.
It's exemplary. Something for us to learn about the response of Nehemiah in Nehemiah chapter
number one. I wonder this morning, again, Nehemiah is dealing with his own homeland.
He's dealing with the situation there with Israel and Judah in particular and the captivity and the
all that's going on. But I wonder this morning, as we look around our land, again, I'm thankful
to be an American. I understand this week, momentous occasion, 250 years.
But America's in trouble, spiritually. Spiritually. These guys are out there, DC Gospel Outreach,
trying to reach the folks that are there in DC, reach our nation's capital.
There are what, 360 million people in America, roughly?
We need to duplicate not only what they're doing there in DC Gospel Outreach, but we need to be
doing that all, because people all around us, they need to be doing that. They need to be
all around us. They need the Lord. People are dying. Listen, we can get mad. We can get mad.
Get angry. You know what some people do when they respond, when they begin to think about what's
going on and they hear the report and they see what's going on? We don't see this in Nehemiah's
response, but you know what they could do? They can begin to complain. Complain. Listen, there's
a lot to complain about, quote unquote, in our nation. But you know complaining isn't going to
change anything. It's not going to change a thing. You can complain all you want. Some people,
they decide to get involved in political activism. We're going to go march and go do this and go do
that. And listen to what Jesus said, go preach the gospel. Go preach the gospel. I'm not saying
that it's a sin to be involved in some type of political thing. I'm just simply saying that's
not what he's called us to. He's called us as his people to preach the gospel to every creature.
Listen, it's the gospel. It's the Lord Jesus Christ and it's the gospel of Jesus Christ that's
going to change this nation. Nothing else. So many people have eyes on what's going on at the state
house, the White House, the stock market, at Wall Street, all these. Listen, the hope of America is
in God's house. That's the hope of America. We need to recognize, we need to think about what's
going on in our homeland. How does it affect us? How does it impact us? Do we even care?
Do we even care? Because sometimes we can get so caught up in man, as long as I'm comfortable and
as long as things are okay in my little bubble, then just don't mess with me. Just let me just
live life and let me just enjoy life. We can get there. I'm thankful to be an American,
but if God judged his people Judah, he'll bring judgment to us as well.
And I believe this. I believe he already is judging our nation. I believe that.
He judges through leadership. He does. He does. Complain about the leadership in this commonwealth.
Can't believe people voted for. Listen, it's God's judgment. I just believe that. I just believe that.
It's God's judgment. And God's removing his hand and we, listen, people all week this week, God
bless America, they're going to sing it. It's going to be a great song. It's going to be a great
God bless America. They're going to sing it. It's going to be on the TV. You're going to see it at
different parades and different things, but America bless God. We need to turn to God.
We need a group of God's people that will get serious like Nehemiah did. Weep. Oh, that we'd
weep again. We'd truly see the condition of our nation. Say, God, how will you use me? Pray,
confess, confess your sin. Listen, it's easy for us to look at all the problems of everybody else.
I've said it all so often. We'll have the Lord's supper tonight. It says, let a man examine
his neighbor. Nope. It's not what it says. If you got a wrong translation, it might say that,
but it says, let a man examine himself. Let a man examine himself.
It's a lot easier to examine someone else.
It doesn't hurt as bad or examine somebody else, but he said, let a man examine himself.
And oh, that we'd take the example of Nehemiah, Nehemiah chapter number one, that principle,
that righteousness exalteth the nation, but sin is a reproach to any people.
I'm thankful to be an American, but America's in trouble. And it's up to us as the people of God
to respond in an appropriate way. Let's pray.
pray. Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. We thank you for your blessings,
your good hand of blessing that's been upon us, individually, corporately, as a church,
even as a nation. Lord, you've been good to us. We have to acknowledge that. God, just
as we'd say of Judah and this text of Scripture, we acknowledge this morning the sin in our
land, the sin in our lives, personally. And God, I pray that you'd help us to respond
appropriately, to see the example of Nehemiah, to be moved by the truth and principle of
thy word, not just looking for emotional responses. God, help us to see revival in this land,
knowing the only hope of America is the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ. Would you use us,
help us to be vessels that are meat for the master's use, clean and easily to be used.
I pray that in the time of invitation that you'd have your will in way. We'll thank you
for it. In Christ's name we pray. Would you stand