after number three i'm not sure when the food's going to be here
uh... but i know one thing that's a blessing is when you have lunch on the
property after the service you have a little bit of liberty to preach a little
longer
and when you haven't reached in as long as i haven't reached then you take that
liberty if you will
uh... i got four points this morning and so we'll get through it but uh... lunch
is going to be provided here on the property
and so i trust that you will pay attention throughout the end of the
entirety of the message i trust to be a blessing to you
first samuel chapter three is a a familiar passage of scripture here in the
beginning
of the book of first samuel of course we know that the lord graciously answered
the prayer of hannah
we read about the first chapter of uh... in first samuel chapter one we read
about the life of hannah
and of course her husband el cana and the bible tells us that hannah
was barren
she had no children
we find that though she was barren she earnestly sought the lord
and i'll say this she plainly made a request she asked for a son she's very
plain in her request to the lord
and uh... we find that as we study the whole of scripture the bible says ask
and you shall receive
and uh... you have not because you ask not you have not because you ask amiss
and
we understand some of those truths with regard to prayer but we find that hannah
very plainly seeks the lord and prays earnestly
for a son
god answers her prayer
and we know that the result of that answer is the birth of samuel and we
know that
uh... the name samuel in fact hannah states this in first samuel one in verse
number twenty
uh... the reason why she named him samuel because i have asked him
of the lord
you may remember that as hannah prayed
for a son that her prayer also included a promise
a vow if you will that she would give him unto the lord
all the days of his life
i'm thankful to report that
god answered the prayer of hannah
and hannah
she fulfilled the vow that she made to god
and samuel ministered in shiloh with eli and we find that the
word of god will tell us as we begin first samuel chapter number three
uh... the first several verses give us really a setting for our message this
morning
notice the bible says this in first samuel three in verse number one
and the child samuel ministered unto the lord before eli
the word of the lord was precious
in those days
notice what the bible says there was no
open vision
you're familiar with that truth in proverbs twenty nine in verse eighteen
where there's no vision
the people perish
and that's not speaking about having a vision for a
a land or a people or so on and so forth that's regarding
the giving of god's word we understand all scripture is given by inspiration
of god
the bible says that the word of god was precious in those days
there was no open vision and it came to pass at that time
when eli was laid down in his place and his eyes began to wax dim
that he could not see
and ere the lamp of god went out in the temple of the lord
where the ark of god was
and samuel was laid down
to sleep
we find several things here in the first three verses of first samuel chapter
one
we find that samuel was serving god it says that he ministered unto the lord
before eli in verse number one we know that the
uh... scriptures tell us as i mentioned in verse number one that there was no
open vision that the word of god was precious in those days
the bible also tells us that eli was going blind he could not see
according to the end of verse number two
and the bible tells us something interesting in verse number three
that the lamp of god went out in the temple of the lord you know that was to
burn continually
the responsibility of the priest were to ensure that the oil was
put into those lamps so that they would burn continually
and we find the bible says that the lamp of god went out in the temple of the
lord where the ark of god was
and the bible tells us now that samuel
he went to sleep
and what a setting that god gives us for our text this morning
we focusing primarily on verses four through eleven you see in your bulletin
this morning
that the title of the message and really this is the short title is speak
the full title if you want the full title would be
as we find in verse number nine
speak lord
for thy servant
speak
lord
for thy servant
notice this morning if you're taking notes i want you to know the persistence
of the lord
in verses four through eight
god gives us the record
of his calling to his servant samuel
we would find as i've noted this morning the persistence of the lord
and we find that the lord desires to speak to samuel i'm thankful this
morning to report that god still desires to speak to his children
that god desires to speak to you
and to speak to me in fact if you've read your bible this morning already
uh... the lord spoke to you through his word i was
finishing up in reading this morning
in the book of nehemiah and reading the the truth of god's word
and how the lord minister to my heart personally several hours ago as i was
reading that portion of scripture and i'm thankful this morning
uh... for the persistence of god in the life of samuel notices we
understand the setting
uh... that that eli he's going blind he cannot see
uh... he's elderly we find that samuel was ministering before the lord
and we find that samuel goes to sleep and the bible says in verse number four
that the lord called samuel
the lord called samuel
and he answered samuel answered and said here am i and notice what he does
he ran unto eli and said
here am i
for thou callest me
this is a natural response i mean if you would understand the
the setting and all that was taking place and you consider the
uh... the frailty of eli and you consider the
the responsibility in the ministry of samuel and you find that samuel hears
his voice called
samuel what is the natural thing for him to do is to run to eli to say here am i
you've called me
and eli says
i didn't call you
notice in verse number five and he said
i called not
lie down again
and he went
and lay down
but verse number six says this notice the phrase in verse number four that the
lord called samuel in verse number six
and the lord called
yet
again
the persistence of god
the bible says he called yet again samuel
and samuel arose and went to eli
notice what he says here am i
for thou didst call me
and he answered i called not my son
lie down again
now at this point i'm not sure exactly all of the side story of what's going on
and uh... the the mind of samuel the mind of eli
uh... but i can imagine samuel as he
rose up that second time and he knows that he heard his name called and
he runs into where eli is and he says
you've called me
here am i he says i didn't call you
and samuel probably thinks he's going crazy right like what's going on
uh... i know that i heard my name called
he says lie down again at the end of verse number six that's eli's instruction
to samuel
the bible tells us in verse number seven now samuel did not yet know the lord
neither was the word of the lord yet revealed
unto him
again we see the persistence of the lord in verse number eight
the bible says the lord called samuel again
the third time
he arose and went to eli and said here am i
for thou didst call me
now i wonder again
uh... it may be the the
uh... tone of samuel of
trying to convince eli i know that you've called me
but now as we look at this text of scripture and we find uh...
the persistence of god and the
the way in which he desires to speak to his servant we read again in verse
number ten
in the uh... the first phrase this is the lord came and stood
and called as at other times
samuel
aren't you thankful for the persistence of god
the fact that he desires to speak to us we
have his word and we would say this morning that we have the complete canon
of scripture we have all that god desires for us to have been
in this book we find
the answers to the problems that we would face in life and
we find that it's in this book that we
uh... have the opportunity to hear the voice of god
what a blessing it is that god desires to speak to us and
we find that
uh... it is true this morning that we
we read many things
we listen to many things
but i wonder this morning how much time do we spend reading this book
how much time do we spend in the word of god
i have a library full of books i'm not suggesting this morning
that you should not read
uh... any other book but the reality
is that this book is a precious book it is a profitable book
and it is certainly important that we spend time in the word of god
so many people uh... they they desire to i want to be a good husband will read
the word of god because god is the one that created the home
god is the one that gives the instructions on
and how to be a good husband.
I want to be a good wife.
Then go to the Word of God
and find out what God says
about being a good wife.
I want to be a good father,
a good mother, a good son,
a good daughter,
a good church member,
a good pastor.
The Word of God has all of that in it.
And what a blessing that God desires
to speak to us.
Sometimes we'll spend more time
reading a self-help book,
reading a leadership book
from some human penman,
reading some book on parenting
from someone that has written that book.
Again, I'm not suggesting
that those aren't good resources,
but we must read this book.
And we must recognize this morning
that God desires to speak to you.
I understand that He speaks to us
through His Word.
And I understand that He may not be
calling us this morning
in the same fashion in which He called Samuel.
Here it's recorded in 1 Samuel 3.
But I wonder this morning,
are there times in your life
in which perhaps you've had a season,
a dry season if you will,
where you've not spent time
in the Word of God on a daily basis?
And the Holy Spirit of God,
He's calling you
and He's giving you that thirst
and that desire for the Word of God.
Perhaps there's a time in which
you've not been able to attend church regularly.
You've not had the opportunity
to sit under the preaching
of the Word of God
and you have a longing
and you have a desire
to hear the Word of God.
To hear the voice of God.
We find the persistence of the Lord.
I'm so thankful that as we look
at 1 Samuel 3,
that the Lord was persistent
in His calling of Samuel.
Notice not only the persistence of the Lord,
2, notice the perception of Eli.
In verse 8, we find that it was the third time
in which the Lord called Samuel
and Samuel arises and goes to Eli
and says, here am I for thou didst call me.
And you notice the end of v. 8,
the Bible says,
and Eli perceived that the Lord
had called the child.
I'm thankful for the perception of Eli.
I'm thankful that as we would look
at this text of Scripture
and we'd understand what's taking place
and we'd understand the role of Eli
and the call that God is giving to Samuel,
that Eli, of course, Samuel goes to him
each time assuming that it was Eli
that was calling.
There was some need that Eli had.
There was something that had happened
and Eli needed the assistance of Samuel.
Thus, Samuel would run to Eli,
but that's not what was taking place.
It was the Lord who was calling Samuel.
And the perception of Eli
is given to us here in v. 8.
It says that he perceived
that the Lord had called the child.
Now I know the perception of Eli,
but I want you to understand
that Eli then gave good counsel.
I'm thankful for the counsel that Eli gives.
In v. 9 of our text of Scripture,
after Eli perceived that it was the Lord
that called Samuel,
he then gives some instruction,
some counsel, if you will, to Samuel.
And he says this,
Therefore Eli said unto Samuel,
Go, lie down.
Now he had already told Samuel that
on a couple of occasions, had he not?
He had told him in v. 5,
he says lie down again.
Again in v. 6, lie down again.
But now when Eli perceived
that it was the Lord that called the child,
the instruction, the counsel
that Eli will give Samuel changes.
It's not simply go lie down.
But notice the Bible tells us in v. 9,
Go lie down, and it shall be,
if he call thee, that thou shalt say,
Speak, Lord, for thy servant heareth.
So Samuel went and lay down in his place.
As we think about the perception of Eli,
and we think about the counsel of Eli,
what great counsel that he gives to Samuel.
He tells Samuel to hear the voice calling him,
Samuel, Samuel, and if he shall call thee again,
here's what you need to say.
Don't come running to me,
I'm not the one calling you,
but say, Speak, Lord, for thy servant heareth.
Speak, Lord, for thy servant heareth.
The Bible tells us that Samuel went and lay down
in his place.
We've noted already in v. 10,
that the persistence of the Lord is recorded for us
where the Bible says that the Lord came
and stood and called as at other times,
Samuel, Samuel.
We note the persistence of God.
We note the perception of Eli.
But now I want you to note the posture of God's servant.
The posture, the attitude, the position, if you will,
of the servant of the Lord, that being Samuel.
Notice the Bible tells us that the Lord came
and called us at other times and said,
Samuel, Samuel.
And notice in v. 10, the last phrase of the verse,
then Samuel answered, Speak, for thy servant heareth.
I'm so thankful for the response of Samuel
in this passage of Scripture
that he took heed to the counsel that he received from Eli.
And of course, as we note that God calls again
and says, Samuel, Samuel,
and we find the posture of God's servant,
and we understand that here in the text of Scripture,
it helps us to understand the relationship, if you will,
that he indeed is Lord and we are his servants.
You know, it's a tremendous blessing
that he would speak to us.
It really is.
You know, there are some people in our world today
that are motivational speakers,
that make lots of money giving speeches,
and people pay lots of money to go listen to somebody talk
on some subject and so on and so forth,
and they desire to hear the words of this individual.
We could think of Solomon and all of his wisdom
and the way in which the Queen of Sheba traveled
to hear the wisdom of Solomon,
and we can understand those things,
but you understand that the omniscient, all-knowing God
has given us a book, and he desires to speak to us.
And our posture should be one of speak, Lord,
for thy servant heareth.
We should have that desire to hear the voice of God
as we read the pages of Scripture
to understand that it's God's Word.
And he desires to speak to us.
This word heareth, when the Bible says speak,
for thy servant heareth,
that word carries with it the idea of hearing, listening,
but also with the purpose of obedience,
the idea of hearing with a view of obeying.
Now that's a good understanding of us
as we dig in and understand really
what Samuel is saying here.
Speak, Lord, for thy servant heareth.
I wonder this morning when we go to the Word of God,
when we come to the house of God,
when we are listening and reading the Bible ourselves,
when we're hearing the preaching of the Word of God,
are we saying speak, Lord, for thy servant heareth?
This hearing that is focused on,
that has the view of obedience,
that we would be doers of the Word and not hearers only.
I'm mindful of the truth that we find
within the Word of God where David will say in Psalm 86
and verse number 11 as he's praying,
and what a great psalm of prayer.
He says, teach me thy way, O Lord.
I will walk in thy truth.
That's the desire to hear the teaching of the Word of God,
to hear the words of God with a purpose of obedience,
with a mind of walking in thy truth.
I want you to note Psalm 119, if you will.
What a wonderful passage of Scripture, Psalm 119.
If you turn over to that passage, if you will,
hold your place there in 1 Samuel 3.
Of course, we're familiar with Psalm 119,
the longest chapter in all of the Bible,
a text of Scripture that is dedicated
to the very Word of God.
And I want you to know how the psalm begins
in verse number one.
Blessed are the undefiled in the way,
notice this, who walk in the way of the Lord.
Who walk in the way of the Lord.
The idea of hearing the Word of God
with the purpose of obedience.
Why is it that we would say, speak, Lord,
for thy servant heareth.
I want to hear God speak,
and I purpose to obey what God says.
We find here that as we would consider
the truth of God's Word,
and the focus of these two psalms,
and of course we could look at a number of truths
this morning, but I want you to think in your mind,
you don't need to turn there,
but in Luke chapter number 10,
God records for us an event in the life
of the Lord Jesus Christ when He's at the house
of Mary and Martha, and we find the Bible says
that Mary, that she was also sat at Jesus' feet
and heard His Word.
And heard His Word.
The idea, again, of that particular Word
there in Luke 10 and verse number 39.
of heard or hear is to attend to,
to consider what is or has been said
to understand.
She sat at the feet of Jesus
and heard His Word.
I note back in 1 Samuel 3,
as we take note of the posture
of God's servant,
and I note the end of v. 10,
he says,
Speak, Lord, for Thy servant heareth.
And then I want you to notice
the first few words of v. 11.
And the Lord said...
Isn't that sweet?
I mean, the first three times,
Samuel does not know that it's God
that's calling him to speak to him
and he runs to Eli.
And Eli says, I've called thee not.
On that third encounter,
Eli perceives that it was the Lord
that called Samuel.
And he says, when you hear his voice again,
if he were to call to you again,
say, Speak, Lord, for Thy servant heareth.
And Samuel goes back to his place
and Samuel hears again,
Samuel! Samuel!
And he responds by saying,
Speak, for Thy servant heareth.
And the Bible says,
the Lord said to Samuel.
Wow!
Sometimes we say, well,
He's just not talking to me.
Are we saying, Speak, Lord,
for Thy servant heareth?
Are we responding?
Are we entering our time
in the Word of God
by saying, Lord, I want You to speak to my heart.
I want You to teach me Thy truth.
I commit, I resolve to walk in Thy ways.
Lord, show me things that I need to do.
Show me things I need to stop doing.
Lord, speak, for Thy servant heareth.
I want you to note that this is first of many times
for Samuel when he heard the voice of God.
When God spoke to him.
We won't have time to go through all of them,
but I want you to quickly go through several chapters
here in 1 Samuel with me.
And I want to just note some of these verses of Scripture
in which God speaks to Samuel.
We notice in verse number 11,
the Lord said to Samuel.
Notice in verse number 19,
the Bible says, and Samuel grew,
and the Lord was with him
and did let none of his words fail to the ground,
fall to the ground.
Excuse me, verse number 21,
and the Lord appeared again in Shiloh,
for the Lord revealed Himself to Samuel in Shiloh
by the Word of the Lord.
Let's move over to chapter number 8, if you will.
Of course, we're familiar with the text of Scripture
in verse number 8,
where the people of God wanted a king.
And the Bible tells us that the thing displeased Samuel,
but in verse number 7 of 1 Samuel 8,
the Bible says, and the Lord said unto Samuel.
God's speaking to Samuel.
God's giving Samuel truth.
God is revealing to Samuel what is taking place.
He says, hearken unto the voice of the people
and all that they say unto thee,
for they have not rejected thee,
but they have rejected me,
that I should not reign over them.
Notice in chapter number 9.
In verse number 15, this is very interesting.
This is when Saul is coming,
and they're going to go to the man of God, to Samuel.
And the Bible says in verse number 15,
now the Lord had told Samuel in his ear
a day before Saul came, saying,
notice what God tells him,
the day before Saul comes,
tomorrow, about this time,
I will send thee a man out of the land of Benjamin,
and thou shalt anoint him to be captain
over my people Israel,
that he may save my people
out of the hand of the Philistines.
For I have looked upon my people
because their cry is coming to me.
And when Samuel saw, notice,
the Lord said unto him,
behold, the man whom I spake to thee of,
this same shall reign over my people.
The day before Saul even arrives,
God speaks in the ear of Samuel
and tells him that Saul's going to come,
and that he is to anoint this one to be king over Israel.
Notice in chapter number 15,
just picking a few here,
where the Bible tells us that the Lord spoke to Samuel
in chapter number 15,
the partial obedience of Saul
with the situation there with the Amalekites,
and the Bible tells us in verse number 10,
then came the word of the Lord unto Samuel saying,
and God's going to give Samuel some truth
with regard to the rejection of Saul
being king over Israel.
You find in chapter number 16,
that the Lord said unto Samuel,
how long wilt thou mourn for Saul?
Seeing I have rejected him from reigning over Israel,
fill thine horn with oil,
and go, I will send thee to Jesse the Bethlehemite,
for I have provided me a king among his sons.
Of course, the Bible as you're familiar with,
the passage of Scripture in verse number six,
that the sons of Jesse are to come,
and he looks upon Eliab and said,
surely the Lord's anointed is before me.
But notice verse number seven,
but the Lord said unto Samuel.
Aren't you thankful that God spoke to Samuel?
Because when he sees Eliab,
he says, surely this is the one.
But God spoke to Samuel.
And God said to Samuel, this isn't him.
He says, look not on his countenance
or on the height of his stature,
because I have refused him.
For the Lord seeth not as man seeth,
for man looketh on the outward appearance,
but the Lord looketh on the heart.
One by one, the sons of Jesse pass by.
And God says, no, no, no.
Aren't you thankful that God spoke to Samuel?
Aren't you thankful that Samuel learned to say,
speak, Lord, for thy servant heareth.
The Bible tells us that they come to a place
and the Lord hath not chosen any of these,
and He asks the question to Jesse,
are here all thy children?
And He tells them that David the youngest,
of course, He doesn't even give his name
in verse number 11, but He says,
there remaineth yet the youngest,
and behold, he keepeth the sheep.
Then the Bible says in verse number 12,
as David appears, it says,
and he sent and brought him in,
and now he was ruddy and with all of a beautiful countenance
and goodly to look to,
and notice this phrase, and the Lord said,
and the Lord said, arise, anoint him, for this is he.
Then I want you to notice the response.
Remember, speak, Lord, for thy servant heareth.
The word hereth carries with it that idea
of hearing with a view of obeying.
Samuel had this consistency.
When God spoke to him in chapter number nine
and said, hey, Saul's gonna come
and I want you to anoint him, did he?
He did.
He obeyed the Lord.
And here, in chapter number 16,
we notice the Bible says that the Lord said,
arise, anoint him, for this is he.
Then, verse number 13, Samuel took the horn of oil
and anointed him in the midst of his brethren.
The Spirit of the Lord came upon David
from that day forward.
So Samuel rose up and went to Ramah.
I've taken this few minutes to look
through these verses of Scripture
to see that here in chapter number three
was the first of many times in the life of Samuel
when the Lord spoke to him.
And I want you to consider with me
as we look back in 1 Samuel chapter number three,
I want you to note the content
of God's message to Samuel in our text
and how the content of what God is going to say to Samuel,
how that it pertains to what God was going to do
really was a message of impending judgment.
God was graciously giving His servant
information regarding future events, right?
Look at it back in 1 Samuel chapter number three.
I'm so thankful that Eli had the sense,
the perception to say to Samuel,
it's not me that's calling you,
but God is calling you.
And when you hear him call,
say, speak, Lord, for thy servant heareth.
And I'm thankful for the obedience of Samuel
that he says when he hears Samuel, Samuel,
he says, speak, for thy servant heareth.
And the Lord said to Samuel,
notice in verse number 11 back in 1 Samuel three,
behold, I will do a thing in Israel.
Now, is he telling him of something
that he's already done?
No.
He had the Pentateuch.
He had the book of Moses.
The Scriptures were available.
And there was some truth that was there for him
that if he wanted to read about some of those events,
he could have read of some of those events.
But God says, as God's speaking to Samuel,
I will do a thing in Israel.
I will do, future tense,
something that's going to happen.
And God is graciously revealing information
to his servant regarding future events.
Notice it says,
at which both the ears of everyone
that heareth it shall tingle.
In that day, I will perform against Eli
all things which I have spoken concerning his house.
When I begin, I will also make an end.
For I have told him that I will judge his house forever
for the iniquity which he knoweth
because his sons made themselves vile
and he restrained them not.
And therefore, I have sworn under the house of Eli
that the iniquity of Eli's house shall be forgiven.
house shall not be purged with sacrifice nor offering forever."
The Bible tells us in verse number 15,
And Samuel lay until the morning, and opened the doors of the house of the Lord.
Samuel feared to show Eli the vision.
I want you to consider with me this morning as we note the posture of God's servant,
the way in which he says,
Speak, for thy servant heareth.
And I want you to note the content of what God's message is to Samuel here in this text
of Scripture with regard to future events and God revealing to his servant what he was
going to do.
And I want you to think about what we have in the pages of Scripture.
You know, God is Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end, the first and the last.
He is outside time.
He transcends us.
He has all wisdom and all knowledge.
He is the Lord God Omnipotent, and He rules and He reigns, and He has a plan.
I understand sometimes we live in the midst of the chaos and confusion in which we're
dealing with in our world today, and there's all sorts of things going on, and we could
look as if things are falling apart, but I believe wholeheartedly that things are falling
in place.
And I find that as we read the pages of God's Word, that He has graciously given us information
regarding future events.
"'Speak, Lord, for thy servant heareth.'"
I don't have time to turn to each of the passages, but I want you to hear these verses of Scripture.
Maybe you can jot them down to look at later, and this is just a few verses of sampling
in 2 Thessalonians 2.
In verse number 7, Paul says to the believers in Thessalonica, "'For the mystery of iniquity
doth already work.'"
Can I tell you that it's working?
The mystery of iniquity is working.
It doth already work.
Notice in 2 Timothy 3, in verse number 1, that Paul says, "'This know also.'"
God wants His people to know some things, and Paul is giving this truth to his son in
the faith, Timothy, and he says that in the last days, perilous times shall come.
That word perilous, it means troublesome, dangerous, harsh, or fierce.
He says, Timothy, I want you to know something.
I want you to have knowledge of this truth that in the last days, perilous times shall
come.
He tells them a few verses later in 2 Timothy 3, in verse number 13, "'But evil men and
seducers shall wax worse and worse, deceiving and being deceived.'"
John tells us this in 1 John 4, in verse number 1, that many false prophets are gone
out into the world.
You can read 1 Timothy chapter number 4.
You can read 2 Peter chapter number 2.
You can read the short book of Jude, and you can find in each of those passages of Scripture
that God is giving us a description of false teachers.
He's letting us know, He's informing us of how these false teachers are going to operate
and what they're going to do.
He's giving us this information.
And then I want you to turn to the book of Revelation, and I want you to look at the
way in which this book begins, and understanding with me that as we look at this passage of
Scripture in 1 Samuel 3, when Samuel says, "'Speak, for thy servant heareth,' that we
know the posture of God's servant and the way in which he desires to hear what God has
for him, and God reveals to him the content of the messages with regard to future events,
that which would come to pass in Israel.'"
And we can read and understand that it did come to pass, just as God said that it would,
and we can have confidence that everything that God has told us, God will do.
Revelation 1.
Notice what the Bible says in verse number 1.
"'The revelation of Jesus Christ, which God gave unto him,' notice this, "'to show unto
his servants things which must shortly come to pass.'
And he sent and signified it by his angel unto his servant John.'"
The book of Revelation, the very first verse tells us that it's the revelation of Jesus
Christ, it's not the revelation of John, it's the revelation of Jesus Christ that was given
to John, and the Bible tells us that it was given, notice the phrase right in the middle
of the verse, "'to show unto his servants things,' notice this, "'which must shortly
come to pass.'"
Now, I understand shortly, from our perspective, is different than God's perspective, amen?
Because with God, a day is a thousand years, and a thousand years is a day, according to
2 Peter chapter number 3.
We're stuck in time, and we have this weird perception of things that are short or long,
so on and so forth, but we find that the key here, for me, is that the Bible says that
he wants to show these things unto his servants, and then he says, "'which must shortly come
to pass.'"
And for some reason, we're fooling ourselves to think that we're never going to deal with
what God tells us is going to happen in the future.
We may be the generation that lives through some of these events that take place, we often
speak of desiring to be the generation that's raptured out of here, that hears the trumpet,
and we're raptured out of here, well then guess what, there's a whole lot of stuff that
has to happen, it's just the way it is, and God's given us that truth.
He's revealed to us in his word, things which must shortly come to pass.
We've noticed, as we've looked at 1 Samuel chapter number 3, the persistence of God,
we've noticed the perception of Eli, the posture of God's servant, Samuel, and I want you to
consider as we close this morning, a principle for today.
Consider with me a principle for today.
As we look here in Revelation chapter number 1, and we see that the Bible says that God
is going to show unto his servants things which must shortly come to pass, I want you
to just for a moment give some attention to chapters 2 and 3 of the book of Revelation.
As we find in this portion of Scripture, in these two chapters, that on seven occasions
this phrase is repeated, he that hath an ear, let him hear.
He that hath an ear, let him hear.
What did Samuel say?
Speak, for thy servant heareth.
The intent, the idea of hearing with a view of obedience, of obeying, we find here that
this word hear, when it says in Revelation 2 and 3, he that hath an ear, let him hear,
it's to attend to, to consider what is or has been said, to understand.
It's that same Greek word that was used back in Luke chapter number 10, when the Bible
speaks of Mary who sat at the feet of Jesus and heard his word.
Notice in Revelation 2, in verse number 7, as God is speaking to the church at Ephesus,
the Bible says he that hath an ear, let him hear.
I'm not going to read the entirety of these verses.
I want to give you a principle, and I hope that it all wraps up and makes sense to us
this morning.
He that hath an ear, let him hear.
He says to the church at Ephesus, to the church in Smyrna, skip down to chapter 2 in
verse number 11, he that hath an ear, let him hear.
The church at Pergamos in chapter 2 in verse number 17, he that hath an ear, let him hear.
The church at Thyatira in chapter 2 in verse number 29, he that hath an ear, let him hear.
The church in Sardis in chapter number 3 in verse number 6, he that hath an ear, let
him hear.
The church in Philadelphia in chapter 3 in verse number 13, he that hath an ear, let
And the church of the Laodiceans, I want to read three verses as we consider what he says
to this church.
It is not called the church of Laodicea, it is called the church of the Laodiceans.
And there is a distinction there, by the way.
Notice it in verse number 14, and unto the angel of the church of the Laodiceans write.
But notice with me in verse number 20 of chapter number 3, behold, I, who is speaking, Jesus.
These are the letters that are given to the churches in Asia, these seven churches.
This is the church of the Laodiceans.
Behold, I stand at the door and knock.
If any man hear my voice and open the door, I will come into him and will sup with him
and he with me.
To him that overcometh will I grant to sit with me in my throne, even as I also overcame
and am set down with my father in his throne.
Then we see this repeated phrase in verse number 22, he that hath an ear, let him hear.
He that hath an ear, let him hear.
Notice with me in verse number 20 as we've read the verse of Scripture, that the Bible
says behold, I stand at the door and knock.
The imagery that is given to us here in this text of Scripture is that the church of the
Laodiceans.
that the Lord Jesus Christ is on the outside of his church. You understand
that the church is the pillar and ground of truth, but the church is his church.
Remember Jesus said in the book of Matthew, I will build my church and the
gates of hell shall not prevail against it. We understand that the church
according to Acts chapter number 20 that Jesus Christ bought it with his own
blood. We understand the Bible tells us that husbands are to love their wives
even as Christ loved the church and gave himself for it in the book of Ephesians.
And we find here that God owns the church, the Lord Jesus Christ, he
instituted the church, and here in chapter number three, a church that is
full of goods. The Bible says that this is how God describes them.
Excuse me, this is how they are described here. Notice it says, because thou sayest,
this is what they say of themselves, I am rich and increased with goods and have
need of nothing. And God says, but you know not that thou art wretched,
miserable, poor, blind, and naked. They're having a little club. It's the church of
the Laodiceans. And the imagery that God gives us in verse number 20 is that
Jesus is on the outside of his church and he's knocking. He's knocking on the
door of the church. And the Bible says, then I stand at the door and knock. You
notice that God does not force himself in. You remember when Peter was knocking
on the door when they were praying for him in Acts chapter number 12?
Rhoda was excited, wasn't she? But she forgot to do something. She forgot to
open the door! Right? She says, it's Peter! He's knocking on the door! What did they
say? You're mad. You're crazy. That's what they say to her. It's his spirit. And she's
like, no! He's knocking! And eventually they open the door and Peter's able to go in and
he tells them some things. He shares how God had miraculously answered their
prayers and delivered him from prison. Read it in Acts 12. Here we find that Jesus is
knocking on the door of his church and as he's knocking there, he says, I stand at
the door and knock. Notice what it says, if any man hear my voice, notice, and open
the door. Would you allow me this morning to make an application from what we see
in 1 Samuel chapter number 3 when Samuel is there and he's hearing the voice of
God and he hears Samuel and he runs to Eli and says, here am I! You've called! And
Eli says, I haven't called you. Go back to sleep. Go back to bed. And Eli goes back
to bed and he hears, excuse me, Samuel goes back to bed and he hears Samuel and he
runs into Eli again and says, you've called! Here am I! I haven't called you. Go
back to sleep. And on that third time, Eli perceives it's the Lord. And he says,
Samuel, when you hear it again, here's what you need to say. Speak, Lord, for thy
servant heareth. What good counsel. We find that Samuel followed that counsel and the
Lord came that fourth time and said, Samuel, Samuel. And he said, speak, for thy servant
heareth. And the Lord said unto Samuel. It tells us here in Revelation chapter number
3 and verse number 20 that if any man hear my voice and open the door, notice what it
says, I will come into him and will sup with him and he with me. You know, he desires to
have fellowship with you. He desires to speak to you. In fact, he's waiting for you to enter
into his presence to invite him to speak to you. To say as you would get into a quiet
place and open up the precious Word of God and as you open this precious book and you
say, Lord, open thou mine eyes that I may behold wondrous things out of thy law. But
Lord, would you speak for my servant heareth. I mean, I want to know who you are and I want
to know what you've done. But I want you to speak to me. I want you to show me how to
be a better father, a better mother, a better husband, a better wife, a better son or daughter,
a better church member, a better pastor. God speaks to me. God gives us instruction on
all of those things that I just mentioned. Maybe you want to be a better employee. Maybe
you want to be a better employer. God speaks about those things as well. We say, God, speak
for thy servant heareth. We go to the Word of God. And as we make application this morning
and look at this principle for today, we can rejoice in understanding that still to this
very hour, God is desiring to speak to His servants. Are you hearing the voice of God?
Are you spending time in this precious book? Are you allowing the Word of God to permeate
into your soul? To impact your behavior? To have faith in what God has said? To understand
that He has given us, He has taught us things that must shortly come to pass. That just
as He revealed to Samuel in 1 Samuel chapter number 3, these things concerning future judgment
that would come upon the house of Eli, that God has given us in His Word truth regarding
future events. And we go to His Word and we say, speak for thy servant heareth. But
that attitude is critical. It is a critical attitude that we have that we come to God
and we say, Lord, would you speak to me? Would you give me truth? And would you help me to
respond to that truth? Would you help me to be a doer of the Word and not a hearer only?
Would you help me to put in practice that which you've given me in your Word? I don't
just want to soak it all in. I want to be a conduit. I want to learn the Word of God.
I want you to teach me some things and then I can share that with others. And I can have
an understanding of the times in which we're living. See, God has graciously given us His
Word. But He doesn't make you read it. No one's going to force you to read the Bible.
Now maybe if you're a child here this morning, you say, my parents forced me to read the
Bible. Be thankful for that. Honestly. Because they would help you to develop a walk with
God. I'll never forget the day in which I sat in our house in Manassas and when our
children were younger, of course we'd read the Bible to them. And we still to this day
have family devotions together, all of us. And we would encourage our children as they
got a little older to read the Bible for themselves. And learn to read the Bible. Learn to study
the Bible. One year for Christmas, one of our children, they would come to me regularly
and ask me, what does this word mean? What does that word mean? It was encouraging to
me. It's encouraging when my children say, I was reading the Bible, what does this mean?
Right now we've done various things in our family devotions, but right now as a family,
each month we're reading through the book of Proverbs, individually. Today is August
8th, and so we'll be reading Proverbs chapter number 8 individually. And we have family
devotions tonight. We each will share, what did God show you? How did God speak to you
through Proverbs 8 today? And undoubtedly, Tim, somebody's going to say, that was my
verse! Because God used that verse in their life. And undoubtedly, I want to go first,
I want to go first, can I go first? Because I don't want anyone to take my verse, that
kind of a thing. But it's exciting. We're trying to help them, but I'll never forget
when I was sitting on the couch in Manassas and we'd ask the children, did you read your
Bible today? And I remember Joseph was walking upstairs one day, and I was sitting there
in the living room, and many of you were at our house in Manassas, and you know the layout.
And he kind of, as he would walk up the stairs, he could see right where I was sitting. And
he looked at me and he said, hey daddy, did you read your Bible today? You know, I was
thankful to be able to say, yes I did. And to share how God had spoken to my family.
God had opened my heart that day. But can I tell you this morning that we shouldn't
just read our Bibles because somebody might ask us if we read our Bible today? God wants
to speak to you. He wants to speak to you. He's given you this perfect, preserved Word
of God. It's profitable for us. It's a probing book. Amen? It's a piercing book. It's a
proving book. And we get into it and we say, speak Lord, for thy servant heareth. Oh, would
you teach me truth from your Word? I'm so thankful you've given it. But the principle
that we look at this morning is just as God was seeking to speak to Samuel, today God's
desiring to speak to you. Maybe you're saying, man, it's been a long time since I've heard
the voice of God. Maybe I've neglected reading the Word of God. I think it was Brianna and
her testimony a couple of weeks ago after coming from camp and maybe it was one of the
other days.
teenagers. I don't remember for sure. I didn't jot it down. But they made a
statement about one of the things that Pastor Michael Jones said during his
message that many believers respect the Bible. Have any of you said that? And that if any of
us were to throw the Bible on the ground, oh what's going on? You know we respect
the Bible. And that pastor said at teen camp that many of God's people respect
the Bible, but only a few read the Bible. Statistics come out every year. I've
never been called and asked, so I'm not sure who has been polled. But statistics
are coming out all the time of how often people that claim to be followers of
Jesus Christ read their Bible. You know there are very few in the whole of
Christendom, however you want to cut that up and dice it up, that have ever
read the Bible cover to cover. God wants to speak. God desired to speak to Samuel.
God had something to tell Samuel. But Samuel had to say, speak Lord for thy
servant heareth. This morning, oh that a whole bunch of us would just say, speak
Lord for thy servant heareth. I don't want to just go through the motions of
checking a list of, I read my Bible today, but I desire that God would speak to me.
Give me truth. Help me in my walk with Him. Speak Lord for thy servant heareth.
Let's pray. Father, we're so thankful this morning for your Word, the precious Bible.
We sing songs about the Bible. We claim to believe the Bible. We have discussions with
people about the Bible. God, we're so thankful that you've given us this book and that you
desire to speak to us. And I pray that this morning, in the quietness of the moment, that
you would help us as your servants to respond in the same fashion in which Samuel responded.
And we would say, speak Lord for thy servant heareth. As we consider the message to each
of the churches in Asia, there in Revelation 2, in verse number 3, he that hath an ear,
let him hear. You stand at the door and knock. If any man will hear and open, oh God, I pray
that we would enjoy that rich fellowship with you around your Word and in prayer. Speak
to our hearts. Give us confidence in what thy Word says. Help us to understand those
things which must shortly come to pass. We pray, God, that if there'd be one that's present,
not sure of heaven, it's our prayer that today would be the day of their salvation. For each
of us that have trusted you as Lord and Savior, I pray that we'd have a renewed commitment
with regard to our walk with thee, specifically with regard to our Bible reading. As we look
at this Old Testament account and make application in our lives today, that we'd be challenged
and that we would say, speak Lord for thy servant heareth. Would you move and work as
only you can, and we'll give you the glory for it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you
stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed, no one's looking around. Kimberly's
going to play quietly on the piano. Give you an opportunity to respond, an invitation.
Maybe you want to make your pew an altar. Maybe you want to come to this old-fashioned
altar. Maybe you just need to come and say, as Samuel said, speak for thy servant heareth.
Renew that commitment, desiring, understanding that God desires to speak to you, but desiring
to hear from him. As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.