If you will, and turn to the book of Philemon, and be looking at just a verse of Scripture
here from the book of Philemon.
And I won't be dealing with the whole thought of that which is developed here in the book
of Philemon.
There's only one chapter, so turn to chapter number one, amen?
And we'll look here at just a verse of Scripture.
I hope to be a blessing to you this evening as we think about this truth that is given
to us.
The Apostle Paul had the privilege to serve in many regions during his ministry.
In fact, as you trace the steps of Paul, if you begin to look through the book of Acts
and trace the missionary journeys, the first, second, and third, you begin to see the regions
in which God enabled and allowed the Apostle Paul to serve and to minister.
And along the way, he had the opportunity to meet a whole lot of people.
And he had people that he was able to meet that, of course, were the enemies, the opposition,
those that opposed him.
And occasionally he mentions those folks, but there are a lot of people that he had
the opportunity to serve God with.
And as he would serve and as he would minister in various regions, God would allow him to
have those relationships established.
In fact, as you read through the New Testament, and you have the opportunity to read many
of the books that God has allowed the Apostle Paul to be the human penman of, that you have
the privilege of reading of several of those names that are mentioned.
In fact, you can look at the end of many of the epistles and see where the Apostle will
mention people by name, specifically.
Sometimes he gives us some information about them.
Sometimes there's not a whole lot that's given to us, but names are provided.
It's interesting if you were to read Romans 16, that is an especially lengthy portion
of Scripture with a lot of names that are provided of these people that God allowed
the path of the Apostle Paul to cross with and to serve alongside of.
And of course, in many cases, to minister to them, but also to minister along with them.
The name Archippus is found both here in the book of Philemon.
It's also found over in the book of Colossians.
And we'll look at both passages of Scripture this evening.
Notice in verse number one of the book of Philemon, the Bible says, Paul, a prisoner
of Jesus Christ, and Timothy, our brother, unto Philemon, our dearly beloved and fellow
laborer.
And he says this, and to our beloved Athia and Archippus, our fellow soldier, and to
the church in thy house, grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus
Christ.
Right in the beginning of the letter, we find that God gives us an understanding as to the
time of the writing of this short letter that is sent, of course, to Philemon and also to
Athia and Archippus, as it's mentioned in verse number two.
As we would consider the timing of the letter, he says that Paul, a prisoner of Jesus Christ.
We understand many of the epistles we would refer to as the prison epistles, and this
letter, along with the book of Colossians that we'll reference this evening as well,
they were both written, they're both referred to as these prison epistles that were written
around the same time from the same location during Paul's first confinement there in Rome.
And so we understand a little bit of background about what God is giving us with regard to
the timing of the writing and who he's writing to.
We're not going to deal with really the thought and the full message of the book of Philemon.
In fact, if you go back and read through it, you'll see a beautiful picture that is given
to us with regard to this one on Onesimus and all that took place and how in the past
he was unprofitable, but now he's profitable.
Why?
Because he's been saved.
And great message, but not the message for this evening.
The message for this evening, we're going to focus on this one, Archippus.
Notice the Bible tells us, and we're going to use it for our title this evening, look
at it, it says, and to our beloved Athia, and Archippus, our fellow soldier.
Archippus, our fellow soldier, is the title for the message this evening.
I want you to notice, first of all, if you're taking notes, notice how this man is identified.
We've read it there in verse number two, he's identified as a fellow soldier.
I like that terminology.
I like the picture that you get in your mind when you read that description, that identifying
name title, if you will, that is given.
The Bible says, now, and Archippus, our fellow soldier.
It's interesting to me that the title, if I could use that terminology this evening,
of fellow soldier, that the Apostle Paul only refers to two people in all of the Scriptures
with that title.
We read about being a good soldier, and so on and so forth, and we'll reference some
of that this evening, but there are two people specifically that he mentions as being fellow
soldiers.
We notice in the first verse of Philemon, that as he speaks about Philemon, he uses
this terminology, our dearly beloved and fellow laborer.
I'm thankful that he was a co-laborer, a fellow laborer, and in that word is used, we find
that Paul says there in the church in Corinth, as he's ministering to them, of course, the
divisions and schisms and all that was taking place in Corinth, and I'm of Paul, and I'm
of Cephas, and I'm of Apollos, and so on and so forth, and Paul says, we're just laborers
together with God.
And in chapter number three of 1 Corinthians, what a great perspective to have.
But this title that we find here that is given as an identifier, if you will, for
Archippus is fellow soldier.
It is used also of speaking of Epaphroditus.
Turn back to the book of Philippians, if you will, in chapter number two of the book of
Philippians.
Now, Epaphroditus was a man we believe most likely the pastor of the church there in Philippi.
He speaks about him as being a companion in labor, my brother, but notice in Philippians
two, in verse number 25, it says, yet I supposed it necessary to send to you Epaphroditus,
my brother and companion in labor, and fellow soldier, but your messenger, and he that ministered
to my wants.
It's commonly believed that as the church at Philippi collected this offering to assist
the apostle Paul, that it was taken, delivered to Paul by the hand of Epaphroditus, and he
took that as the messenger of the church, he brought that offering to the apostle Paul,
and then Paul would deliver this letter back to the church at Philippi by the hands of
Epaphroditus.
And we find here that he's referred to as fellow soldier.
And again, it's Epaphroditus and this one, Archippus.
It's interesting because this title reveals to me the fact that they were engaged in battle.
You immediately get in your mind when you read that title, that term that is ascribed
to Archippus here, the way in which he's identified, we see this fellow soldier, he's engaged in
the battle.
The battle that he's engaged in though is a spiritual battle.
And the reality this evening is that each and every one of us are engaged in a spiritual
battle.
We see this spiritual battle, this spiritual warfare that Paul speaks of to the believers
in the book of Ephesians there as they're ministering in the city of Ephesus and that
church that is there and ministering and serving.
And Paul tells them, listen, we are engaged in spiritual warfare.
And the reality is that if you have any sense about you, and I don't say that to be condescending,
you can obviously, without hesitation, identify today that we're in the midst of spiritual
warfare.
I mean, the spiritual battle that is raging.
And we find that this man, Archippus, not to say that others weren't fellow soldiers,
but it's interesting that there's just a couple of people that are given, that are spoken
of in this term.
You find often that the Apostle Paul, when he speaks about Timothy, how does he refer
to Timothy?
My son in the faith.
He refers to Titus in like manner.
In fact, he speaks of Onesimus in that fashion as well.
But we find that there's a purpose.
We believe that every word of God is pure.
And the Bible says that all Scripture is given by inspiration of God.
And God led the Apostle Paul to use this term, this title, in identifying this one, Archippus.
Now, the reality is that Paul had spoken to Timothy about the importance of understanding
our place as being a soldier and what it means to be a good soldier.
Notice if you will, over in 2 Timothy chapter number 2, I'm going to draw your attention
quickly this evening to just the first four verses of this passage of Scripture.
And I want you to just get the instruction that Paul is leaving for Timothy, of course,
by way of preservation for us as well to this day.
He says this in verse number 1 of 2 Timothy 2,
Thou, therefore, my son, be strong in the grace that is in Christ Jesus.
The things that thou hast heard of me among many witnesses, the same commit thou to faithful
men who shall be able to teach others also.
He says this, Thou, therefore, endure hardness as a good soldier of Jesus Christ.
He says, No man that woreth and tangleth himself with the affairs of this life, that
he may please him who hath chosen him to be a soldier.
Who's that?
Well, that's the Lord.
Amen?
You trust that Christ is your personal Savior.
You are enlisted in the Lord's army.
Amen?
You became a soldier of Jesus Christ.
We find that we sing the song with the kids about being in the Lord's army, right?
And we have fun with singing that.
We sing.
songs about onward Christian soldier right and we understand some of the
songwriters that have taken up on this thought of being a soldier and this is
an analogy an illustration that is used to help us understand this this
Christian life that we're living in this battle in which were engaged in and Paul
says to Timothy that that you might be a good soldier that you may please him who
have chosen him to be a soldier wonder this evening as we would think about
this title that is given to Archippus in our text of Scripture the way in which
he is identified I wonder this evening if someone would say of me if someone
would say of you there are fellow soldier a fellow soldier I wonder this
evening if we understand really the the spiritual warfare in battle that we are
engaged in the truth of Ephesians 6 is a powerful truth that we must be
mindful of on a regular basis we spoke of course of the theme for 2019 be
strong the Lord I preached to the whole book of Ephesians we belabored the point
but it's good to be reminded of the fact that we're engaged in spiritual warfare
and we wrestle not against flesh and blood we're to put on the whole armor of
God by the way that's not a one-and-done situation that is an everyday
sometimes you might have to go put the armor on again because something
happened as you were engaged in battle and you you have to understand the
importance of this battle that we're in and Paul says as he refers to this one
this co-laborer but more than that a fellow soldier we notice how he's
identified I want you to notice over the book of Colossians how he is instructed
the book of Colossians gives us some some information at the end of the book
again I mentioned how that many times I said this by way of introduction that
you get to the end of some of these epistles that God allowed Paul to be the
human penman of and you see a reference to a number of individuals people that
he served and ministered to people that he served alongside of and we find that
beginning in Colossians 4 and verse number 7 is where you begin to see a
number of those names that will be mentioned throughout the end of this
particular passage of Scripture names that Paul mentions we get down to verse
number 17 and it says this notice and say to Archippus so so this is this
interesting to me because really he says just catch it in context notice in verse
number 7 all my states shall take a kiss declare unto you who is a beloved
brother and faithful minister and fellow servant the Lord verse 9 with Onesimus a
faithful and beloved brother who's one of you they shall make known unto all
things which are done here we see that he mentions about others he goes through
and he speaks of them favorably and about their labor and their service but
when he comes to verse number 17 and he's going to speak about Archippus he
says and say to Archippus there's some instruction that I want to make sure it
gets delivered to this one this fellow soldier that's engaged in the battle
there's some instruction that I want to make sure it gets to him see with the
other folks that are mentioned there's not necessarily a piece of information
that is to be given to them as much as there's a description as to how they're
engaged in the work and what they're doing and their faithfulness and we
notice that Paul says this notice what he says we're gonna break the statement
down number one he says take heed to the ministry now we're going to pause
right there I know that's not the fullness of the thought but we're just
gonna pause there for just a moment and this idea of taking heed to to discern
to understand to have a knowledge of and he says take heed but notice what he
says he could have stopped again every word of God is pure take heed to the
ministry notice how it's described which thou hast received in the Lord now let
me ask you do those words that are given after ministry don't you think
those are important words he didn't just stop take heed to the ministry he says
take heed to the ministry which thou hast received in the Lord I think about
the message that would be delivered I believe that the recipients here would
have faithfully taken and delivered this message and say to archivist okay here's
the message for you it's been contained and preserved for us so that we can read
it and be encouraged by it and be challenged by it but we find that as he
would receive those words when when it says take heed to the ministry and then
which thou hast received in the Lord it's the Lord that calls us to the
ministry it's the Lord that equips us for the work of the ministry it's the
Lord who enables us we find that as we would understand the truth of spiritual
gifts within the the Church of God and we'd understand how the Holy Spirit of
God gifts each individual believer as he will amen and he's the one that gives
you and equips you for the work of the ministry for the the work that God has
called us to now this one archivist he may have had a particular position
there's some that have the idea that he may have been a pastor of a church and
whatever the particular ministry may have been that he was engaged in we find
that the Apostle Paul in delivering this message of taking heed to the ministry
which now has received in the Lord is reminding him that he had been called by
God they've been given this ministry by the Lord I think about the words of Paul
when he says this and and you can just let me read the verse to you but in
first Timothy 1 in verse number 12 Paul says and I thank Christ Jesus our Lord
who hath enabled me for that he counted me faithful putting me into the ministry
see Paul understood that he was called by God in fact as you read through many
of the epistles and that that Paul was the human penman for you'll find that he
references the call that God has placed upon his life in those introductory
statements in fact here in first Timothy 1 in verse number 1 Paul says
this he says Paul an apostle of Jesus Christ by the commandment of God our
Savior and Lord Jesus Christ which is our hope we find that Paul understood
something about the ministry he understood that he was called by God and
now as he's giving this word to archivist is he giving this instruction
he says take heed to the ministry which thou hast received in the Lord then
notice this last phrase that thou fulfill it that thou fulfill it see
whether this man quit or was just simply tempted to quit is really not certain in
fact the only two verses of Scripture that we have specifically about this
man archivist or the two that we've looked at this evening Philemon one
verse number two and here in Colossians 4 and verse number 17 theologians of
yesteryear have spun theories about whether or not he quit the ministry and
got off track and so on and so forth the reality is that we don't know factually
biblically speaking but I can tell you this that when you're engaged in
spiritual battle when you're a fellow soldier there's some things that come in
your life that cause you to consider walking away quitting giving up is it
worth it and Paul whether this one archivist whether he was just facing
this time of maybe difficulty and discouragement maybe he was tempted with
the idea of not continuing it's just not worth it it's too challenging it's too
difficult you don't know what I've had to deal with again we don't know all of
that but Paul having obviously under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit but
having an understanding of this man and in writing this and giving this
instruction he says that thou fulfill it the importance of completion the
importance of finishing the importance of understanding that that we that as we
serve God that we're serving God and that as we run our race we're not
running our race to compete against one another we're running our own race and
as we're running our race our goal is to finish in fact Paul said this to the
believers that he is writing to in the region of Galatia of course there's been
many things that had taken place and the Judaizers that came in and all of the
false teaching and he asks him this question he says ye did run well who did
hinder you that you should not obey the truth in Galatians 5 and verse number
7 I love the testimony of the Apostle Paul you come to the book of 2nd
Timothy chapter number 4 of course we're familiar with the passage of Scripture
we understand how that he's writing to to Timothy and he begins to share this
testimony of course he's given Timothy these final words of instruction these
words of instruction by the way are are really summed up in in this idea
continue continue I mean if you read the third
chapter of the book of 2 Timothy,
you begin to read about the perilous times
that shall come,
and Paul starts it this way by saying,
this know also.
Remember, Paul often as he writes,
he will speak of,
you know, I would not that you be ignorant, brother.
I want you to know something.
I want you to be informed of something.
And here he says to Timothy,
this know also,
then the last days perilous times shall come.
And by the way, he begins to go through
and to explain some of these things
and give some descriptions
as to what would be endured
and what would be experienced.
He tells them in v. 12,
yea, and all that will live godly in Christ Jesus
shall suffer persecution.
Can I tell you that the persecution
in which the first century believers
faced and endured
is different than anything any of us
have ever experienced.
He says evil men and seducers
shall wax worse and worse
deceiving and being deceived.
Then notice what he says in v. 14.
But continue.
But continue thou in the things
which thou hast learned and been assured of,
knowing of whom thou hast learned them.
And he goes through and he begins
to give this charge to Timothy
to continue.
Yea, these things are going to happen.
We're going to face opposition.
We're in a battle.
We're in spiritual warfare.
You're a fellow soldier.
I know sometimes in the battle it gets hard.
I know sometimes in the battle
it gets overwhelming.
That thou fulfill it.
Continue.
Be faithful.
The Scriptures speak about being faithful unto death.
Being faithful unto the end.
Paul says this.
He gives him the charge in v. 1 of chapter 4
about preaching the Word of God.
He says in v. 2,
Preach the Word, be instant in season,
out of season, reprove, rebuke, exhort,
with all longsuffering and doctrine.
He tells them, hey, the time's going to come
when they're not going to endure sound doctrine.
Right?
Why?
Because after their own lusts
shall they heap to themselves teachers
having itching ears.
We see this stuff.
I mean, this is where we live.
He says in v. 6
as we get to the point of Paul's testimony,
he had given this instruction to
this one archipis, he says,
Take heed to the ministry which thou hast received
in the Lord, that thou fulfill it.
And Paul's personal testimony is given to us
in v. 6-7 of 2 Timothy 4,
where I am now ready to be offered.
The time of my departure is at hand.
I have fought a good fight.
I love it.
I have finished my course.
I have kept the faith.
We're familiar with the verses of Scripture.
We reference them often.
But I want you to really think about
the testimony of Paul.
And I want you to think about
the instruction that he's given
here in Colossians 4 and v. 17
as he's closing this book,
as he's closing, and he mentions
several people by name,
and he goes through many different attributes
of these people and what they were engaged in
and what they were doing, but he says,
And say to archipis,
Take heed to the ministry
which thou hast received in the Lord,
that thou fulfill it.
Archipis, don't give up.
You're a fellow soldier.
I know you're in the battle.
Sometimes when you're in the trenches of the battle,
like I've never been a soldier
in the U.S. Armed Forces of any branch,
but I can only imagine.
You read some of those stories
about some of the wars that our nation
has been engaged in throughout our history.
If you're a history buff
and you've read accounts of battles
that have taken place in other portions
of the world history,
and you begin to see what's happening,
and you think about those fellow soldiers,
and you think about some of the things
that they experienced,
some of the difficulties in which they endured,
and Paul says,
Archipis, take heed to this ministry
which you've received in the Lord,
that thou fulfill it.
I hope this evening
that sometimes when we're engaged in the battle,
we can become overwhelmed.
By the way, if you watch too much news,
you're gonna be overwhelmed in a hurry.
I'm just telling you.
You're gonna be overwhelmed in a hurry.
The enemy wants to get your mind.
It really does.
Can I remind you that we're on the winning side?
We're more than conquerors in Christ,
but thanks be to God which giveth us the victory
through our Lord Jesus Christ, amen?
We're fellow soldiers.
By the way, I think about this term.
It's been said by many throughout the history,
really, of Christianity
where, I shouldn't say the entire history,
the recent history, I guess I should say it that way,
that far too often as a soldier,
as a fellow believer is wounded
that we kick our own wounded.
It ought not be that way, brethren.
We're fellow soldiers.
We wanna encourage them that thou fulfill it.
See, because you have a race that you're running,
and as we run our race,
we're not competing with one another.
We're simply striving to please him
who's called us to be a soldier.
And what a blessing.
To think about this really obscure Bible character,
archivist, we don't know a whole lot about him,
but Paul says, I wanna get a message to him.
Again, I don't know all of the circumstances
surrounding this man's ministry
and all that he was dealing with,
but can I tell you today,
that I get reports, I get phone calls,
I read articles about people in the ministry
that quit every single day.
Hundreds.
It's sad.
I don't know the reason for all of them.
There's no way I could.
I don't know the real reason for many of them,
to be real honest with you.
But I do know this.
I've heard people say something like this.
It's just too much.
It's too hard.
I had one man, I tried to encourage him,
and I used this terminology.
He was ready to quit.
I mean, he had dealt with a bad situation.
And I said to this man, as I spoke to him on the phone,
I said, listen, brother, you're at a crossroads.
Don't be discouraged.
Keep your eyes on Jesus.
He's got a plan.
We don't understand all this mess
that you're dealing with right now,
but we know that the enemy's at work.
Keep your eyes on Jesus,
and just understand that you're at a crossroads.
Here's what his words were.
He said, no, I'm at a dead end.
It hurt.
Because his perspective was, I'm done with this.
It's too much.
And that's exactly what the enemy wants to do.
Right?
That's what he wants to do.
And so Paul says, deliver this message to Archippus.
He's a fellow soldier.
That's how he's identified, but he's instructed.
Take heed to the ministry which thou hast received
in the Lord, that thou fulfill it.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
God, we thank you for your word.
Lord, we know that we're engaged in spiritual battle
and spiritual warfare.
Lord, we know that you've given us in thy word
truth with regard to the last days
and the things that will endure.
God, I pray that you'd help us to be strong
in the Lord and the power of his might.
Help us, God, to understand that we need
to put on the whole armor of God.
Help us to understand that we wrestle not
against flesh and blood.
The weapons of our warfare are not carnal.
They're spiritual.
Help us, God, to understand that you
have called us to be a soldier.
Help us to be a good soldier.
Help us to fulfill.
To finish.
To complete our race.
I pray that you would work in each heart,
in each individual.
Lord, help us to just keep our eyes on Jesus.
We know that the enemy is ruthless, relentless.
He's walking about seeking whom he may devour.
But God, we're on the winning side.
More than conquerors through Christ.
Thank you for the victory that is possible
only through the Lord Jesus Christ.
Work in hearts and lives.
Help us, Lord.
We'll thank you for it.
In Christ's name we pray, amen.