Genesis chapter number 14, and be looking at verses 17 through 24 this evening, Genesis
chapter number 14, and be looking at verses 17 through 24.
If you're taking notes this evening, I have titled the message, Abram Met Melchizedek.
There's actually two kings that he meets in this particular text of scripture.
He meets the king of Sodom, and he also meets Melchizedek, the king of Salem.
And as we look at the passage of scripture, we'll be reminded from looking at the first
section of Genesis chapter number 14 last Sunday evening, that the Lord provides us
with a record of a battle that took place in the Vale of Sidon.
As we spoke about that particular battle, and we looked at the verse, really verse 1
through 16 last Sunday, and we began to understand the size of this battle, the seriousness of
this battle, we dealt with the fact that they took Lot.
Lot, of course, at that particular time, was dwelling in Sodom.
No longer did he just have his tent pitched toward Sodom, he's now living, dwelling in
Sodom.
And we find that the Bible tells us that they took Lot and all of his goods, and of course
at that time, Abram became involved in this particular battle.
And the Bible gives us this truth in verse number 16, it reveals to us that Abram had
complete victory.
They returned all the goods, Lot, his goods, the women and the people.
Notice the Bible says, speaking of Abram in verse number 16 of Genesis 14, and he brought
back all the goods, and also brought again his brother Lot, and his goods, and the women
also, and the people.
We learned two important lessons last week as we looked at those first 16 verses.
One lesson we learned from the life of Lot, and that was that we need to be careful of
our influences.
We need to be careful of the way in which we begin to allow ourselves to be exposed
to wickedness and become desensitized to wickedness, and the way in which the enemy works, and
we spoke about that last Sunday evening.
We also learned a lesson from the life of Abram, and we spoke about the fact that he
was engaged here in a physical battle, but we are engaged in a spiritual battle.
We look at the fact that Abram had complete victory in this physical battle that he was
engaged in, and we only can have victory in this spiritual battle as we go in the power
of the Lord, as we put on the whole armor of God, as we understand that we wrestle not
against flesh and blood, but against spiritual wickedness in high places.
We sought to learn those lessons last week, and as we look further into the 14th chapter
of the book of Genesis and really finish it up this evening, and we look at the record
of these meetings that Abram has, I believe, again, that we find here within the pages
of Scripture some very important lessons for us.
Notice in verse number 17, the Bible says,
And the king of Sodom went out to meet him, who's him, it's Abram, after his return
from the slaughter of Shador Laomer, and of the kings that were with him, the valley
of Shavah, which is the king's dale.
And notice verse 18,
Melchizedek, king of Salem, brought forth bread and wine, and he was the priest of the
most high God.
And he blessed him, and said,
Blessed be Abram, of the most high God, possessor of heaven and earth.
And blessed be the most high God, which hath delivered thine enemies into thine hand.
And he gave him tithes of all.
The king of Sodom said unto Abram,
Give me the persons, and take the goods to thyself.
And Abram said to the king of Sodom,
I have lift up mine hand unto the Lord, the most high God, the possessor of heaven and
earth, that I will not take from a thread even to a shoelatchet, and that I will not
take anything that is thine, lest thou shouldst say, I have made Abram rich.
Save only that which the young men have eaten, and the portion of the men which went with
me, Aner, Eshgal, and Mamre, let them take their portion.
As we look at this text of Scripture, I want you to notice with me, first of all, if you're
taking notes, the significance of the meeting.
It's very interesting as we look at the passage of Scripture, and I read the entirety of it
this evening so that we'd kind of get a flow of what's taking place, but it's very interesting
that as you begin reading this portion of Scripture, that you find in verse number 17
that the Bible says that the king of Sodom went out to meet him after his return from
the slaughter.
We find that the Bible tells us that this king of Sodom, he goes out with the express
purpose of meeting Abram.
Abram is coming back from a great victory.
We've already dealt with that in our previous study as we looked at the first 16 verses
of this chapter, and we find now that the king of Sodom comes and he desires to meet
with Abram.
Now, it's interesting, we understand if you go back to chapter number 13 and look at verse
number 13, that the Bible says that the men of Sodom were wicked and sinners before the
Lord exceedingly.
Now we do not know a whole lot about this king of Sodom, in fact his name is not even
provided to us in the text of Scripture, but we do find that if he is the king of such
a wicked people, that it would not be too far of a stretch to say that he himself was
wicked.
Amen?
And so we find that this wicked man, this king of Sodom, he's coming and he has this
desire to meet with Abram, but right as we're looking at the passage of Scripture, we find
that the king of Salem, Melchizedek, first meets with Abram.
The Bible tells us in verse number 17 that the king of Sodom goes out for the purpose
of meeting with Abram, but as we look at the passage, the Bible says in verse 18, and Melchizedek,
king of Salem, brought forth bread and wine.
You do not see any more reference to the king of Sodom until verse number 21.
And so God divinely orchestrated this meeting and the timing of this meeting so that Abram
would be properly prepared to have this meeting with the king of Sodom.
Before he would meet with the king of Sodom, he meets with Melchizedek, the king of Salem.
You note in the Scriptures the intent of this king of Sodom, and you note as we get into
the passage and start reading in verse number 21 and following the purpose of his desire
to meet with Abram, but you find that this one, Melchizedek, almost slips in, if you
will, if we could use the picture this evening, he slips in just ahead of the king of Sodom
and he has a time of meeting with Abram.
And it's so significant to see this meeting that takes place.
We, of course, as we studied through the book of Hebrews, we spent some time several weeks
ago, actually a couple of months ago at this point, dealing with Hebrews chapter number
seven and looking at Melchizedek.
If you turn over, hold your place here in Genesis 14, and turn over to the book of Hebrews,
if you will, I just want to make a few statements from Hebrews chapter number seven with regard
to this one, Melchizedek.
As I mentioned as I preached through Hebrews chapter number seven, really if Hebrews did
not give us some insight, there's a verse of scripture in Psalm 110 in verse number
four, but really this meeting in Genesis chapter number 14, for some of us, maybe we would
just briefly read over it and not really hold too much significance in our minds, but we
find that this was a significant meeting and then we see how that Melchizedek is an Old
Testament type of Christ.
Notice in verse number one of Hebrews seven, the Bible says, for this Melchizedek, king
of Salem, priest of the most high God, who met Abraham returning from the slaughter of
the kings and blessed him, to whom also Abraham gave a tenth part of all.
First being by interpretation, notice, king of righteousness, and after that also king
of Salem, which is king of peace, without father, without mother, without descent, having
neither beginning of days nor end of life, but made like unto the Son of God, abideth
a priest continually.
You remember that we find in the scriptures that as we would be reading the book of Hebrews
and studying the portion that this text is found in, that the writer of Hebrews is presenting
the Lord Jesus Christ in his priesthood as being superior to that of the Levitical or
the Aaronic priesthood.
And as we begin to see that he's of a greater, a higher order, he's after the order of Melchizedek,
and we saw and studied in this passage and begin to see the descriptive terms that are
given in these first three verses of Hebrews chapter number seven.
Now go back to Hebrews chapter, or excuse me, to Genesis chapter number 14, and notice
here in the text of Scripture what God tells us about this meeting.
We see some of the description, we find here that he was, he's the king of Salem according
to verse number 18, the king of Salem, which many believe to become Jerusalem later, and
the king of peace.
We find at the end of verse number 18 it says that he was the priest of the Most High God.
Remember that he was a priest and king.
We speak about the Lord Jesus Christ being prophet, priest, and king.
And we find that this Melchizedek, he was a king and he was a priest.
And we notice the meeting, and I want you to consider the fellowship that they had here
at this meeting.
In verse number 18, Ismael...
Melchizedek kind of cuts off the king of Sodom
and comes to meet with Abram.
The Bible tells us in v. 18
that Melchizedek, notice it says,
Melchizedek, king of Salem,
brought forth bread and wine.
Bread and wine.
As we begin to think about the fellowship
that they would enjoy here
at this particular meeting,
and we think about the significance
of these two items that are mentioned,
the bread and the wine,
and we understand the significance
of these elements biblically,
we begin to think about as New Testament believers
and begin to consider the way
in which God has given the church
the two ordinances,
that of baptism and the second is the Lord's Supper,
and we think about the Lord's Supper
and how we have the bread and the wine.
We understand that contextually,
and we've spent entire message on this in the past,
that it's unfermented wine.
You can always find in the Scriptures,
contextually, whether it's speaking
of an alcoholic beverage
or the fruit of the vine.
And here as we begin to see this
and we understand the picture biblically
and the typology and the significance,
how the bread, remember what Jesus says
is we would consider the Lord's Supper
and we'd consider the instruction of Paul
in 1 Corinthians 11,
the bread, why?
For the body of the Lord Jesus Christ
that's broken.
The wine or the juice, why?
For the blood of the Lord Jesus Christ,
His perfect blood that was shed.
And we begin to see how that even
in Genesis chapter number 14,
with this meeting with Melchizedek,
this Old Testament type of Christ,
how that they have this wine and this bread
and how significant that is
to how the Old Testament looked forward to Calvary.
See, we think about the Bible
and we understand that as we look at the Bible
that yes, there is much history
that is contained within the Old Testament.
In fact, as we've studied throughout
some of these pages of Genesis,
as you study throughout various books
of the Old Testament,
you see the historical nature of these things.
But we understand that the theme of the Bible
is redemption and the main character
of the Bible is the Lord Jesus Christ.
And we find that the Old Testament
is pointing to the day in which Messiah would come.
And these Old Testament Bible characters,
by faith, they looked forward
to the day that Messiah would come.
And here we see even in the meeting
that Abram had with Melchizedek,
how that he brought forth this King of Salem,
this Old Testament type of Christ.
He brought the bread and the wine.
What fellowship they must have enjoyed.
I notice not only the significance of this meeting
because of the fellowship,
but I consider the instruction
that Abram received during this meeting.
I want you to notice in verse number 18
that the Bible says that he was the priest
of the Most High God.
You see that phrase, the Most High God.
You notice again in verse number 19,
the Bible says that he, speaking of Melchizedek,
blessed him, speaking of Abram,
and said, blessed be Abram.
Notice again, you see the phrase of the Most High God.
Possessor of heaven and earth.
You see in verse number 20,
and blessed be the Most High God.
You find in verse number 22,
as Abram is now responding to the King of Sodom,
he says, I have lift up mine hand
unto the Lord, the Most High God.
The Possessor of heaven and earth.
That term, the Most High God,
or that name, it's really a compound name,
El Elyon, it's a Hebrew word.
It's really the first mention in all of the Scriptures
of this name of God, the Most High God.
And you find that as Melchizedek would meet with Abram
and he begins to give some instruction,
he greets him in the name of the Most High God.
Now think about the impact and understand,
as we have the Scriptures,
and perhaps you can think back to the time
in which you first came to Christ
and first began discipleship
and learning the Scriptures
and how you would read of maybe in theology
of the names of God and the significance
of the names of God
and how God through His names reveals His character.
Well, think of Abraham, Abram here,
his name's not yet been changed,
but you think of Abram as he's receiving these greetings,
he's receiving this instruction,
and the Bible says that he speaks to him
in this terminology, the name, the Most High God.
I want you to know this evening
that he is the Most High God.
There's none like him.
And Abram, in this meeting,
remember I mentioned by way of introduction
that God divinely orchestrated the meeting
and the timing of the meeting
that Abraham would be prepared properly
for the meeting that he would have with the King of Sodom.
And we find that there's some fellowship,
but I see the instruction
and I find how that Melchizedek comes to him
in the name of the Most High God.
Notice he continues and says this in verse number 19,
the possessor of heaven and earth.
God is the owner.
He is the possessor of heaven and earth.
Now again, I want you to consider
the significance of this truth
and understand the impact that this revelation
would have upon Abram in this particular moment in his life.
And maybe for some of us this evening,
we say, yeah, we know that he's the Most High God.
Yeah, we know that he's the possessor of heaven and earth.
Do we live like it?
Do we live like he's the Most High God?
Do we live like he's the possessor of heaven and earth?
And here Abram is now receiving this revelation
and he's understanding more about this God
that he's followed and he's serving.
And we understand that God had called him
as you look back in Genesis 11,
and he called him out of the earth of Chaldeas
and Abram is following him
and he's learning more about this God that he's serving.
He says he's the Most High God.
He says he's the possessor of heaven and earth.
Exodus 9, look at a few verses of Scripture with me if you will.
In Exodus 9, we're right in the midst of the plagues
in Egypt land.
In fact, in this particular text,
we're looking at the seventh plague, that of Hale.
We won't read the entirety of it,
but I want you to see how that God would use Moses
to help Pharaoh and the Egyptians
understand that the earth is the Lord's,
that He is the possessor of heaven and earth.
Look at verse 29 of Exodus 9.
The Bible says,
God said unto him,
as soon as I am gone out of the city,
I will spread abroad My hands unto the Lord.
And the thunder shall cease,
neither shall there be any more hail,
that thou mayest know
how that the earth is the Lord's.
God is revealing His power
through the plagues,
and of course, we understand contextually
of what's happening in Egypt land
and how Pharaoh had that perspective.
I don't even know who your God is.
And God begins to reveal Himself
and God demonstrates His power through these plagues.
And now, as Moses is going to depart
after this seventh plague,
he says, I'm gonna leave the city,
I'm gonna spread my hands unto the Lord,
and the thunder's gonna cease,
there should be no more hail,
that you, Pharaoh, that you may know
how that the earth is the Lord's.
We find in the book of Deuteronomy,
chapter number 10,
it was important for the children of Israel
to understand this truth.
We find that here in the book of Deuteronomy
as you would look at the entirety of the book
and the preparation for the people of God
as they would go in to possess
the land of promise,
and Moses, of course, would not be permitted
to lead the people of God
into the land of promise,
and we understand, however,
that God would use Moses to prepare them
for the entrance into the land of promise.
We understand that they would face
a great number of difficulties,
there would be opposition
as they would enter into the land of promise,
and throughout the book of Deuteronomy,
God is using Moses to encourage the people,
to equip the people, to prepare the people
for that which they would face.
Notice in verse number 12 of Deuteronomy,
chapter number 10,
and now, Israel, what doth the Lord thy God
require of thee?
But to fear the Lord thy God,
to walk in all His ways,
and to love Him, and to serve the Lord thy God
with all thy heart and with all thy soul,
to keep the commandments of the Lord
and His statutes which I command thee this day
for thy good.
You understand it's for your good.
It's for my good.
Amen?
Notice verse 14.
Behold, the heaven and the heaven of heavens
is the Lord's thy God.
The earth also with all that therein is.
God is the owner.
He is the possessor of heaven and earth.
The psalmist declares in Psalm 24,
in verse number one,
we find that he will make this declaration
with regard to this truth
that we're looking at this evening.
The earth is the Lord's and the fullness thereof,
the world, and they that dwell therein.
Paul would later say in the book of 1 Corinthians
in chapter number 10,
as he's speaking here to this carnal church
in the New Testament.
We find that he's giving them some instruction,
and he says to them in 1 Corinthians 10,
in verse number 26,
for the earth is the Lord's and the fullness thereof.
In verse number 28,
but if any man say unto you,
this is offered in sacrifice unto idols,
eat not for his sake that showed it,
and for conscience sake,
for the earth is the Lord's and the fullness thereof.
Now understand with me as we go back
to Genesis chapter number 14,
that God is preparing Abram for this meeting
that's going to happen between he and the king of Sodom.
And before he's ever going to have this meeting
with the king of Sodom,
there's this meeting with the king of Salem, Melchizedek,
and there's some fellowship that takes place.
There's some instruction that is given.
He says, listen,
I come in the name of the most high God, El Elyon.
He says to him that he is the possessor of heaven and earth.
And then back in Genesis chapter number 14,
notice in verse number 20,
the Bible says,
and blessed be the most high God,
notice this, which hath delivered thine enemies
into thy hand.
What's Abram being instructed on?
It was God that gave the victory.
We mentioned that last week as we studied
the portion of Scripture in Genesis 14,
verses one through 16.
And we dealt with the fact how that Abram,
after he was made aware of the situation
that Lot had been taken,
that he takes his trained servants, 318,
according to verse number 14,
and pursued after them and he smote them.
But we find that as we look at the passage of Scripture
and God gives us some insight
as to this victory that was wrought on this day,
that the Bible says that it was God that gave the victory.
It was the most high God,
the possessor of heaven and earth.
It was this God, Abram, that you're serving,
that you're following.
It is He which hath delivered thine enemies into thy hand.
See, Abram had to understand
some things with regard to that
which he had experienced.
You know, it is possible that we could have victory
and we somehow get full of ourselves.
Begin to think that it was something in our power,
it was something in our approach,
it was something in our wit
that allowed us to have the victory.
In fact, if you were to look at the book of Judges
and you would understand that
which takes place with Gideon
and you understand that in Judges 7,
very interesting insight that God gives us
with regard to the battle that Gideon would be
the human instrument that God would use
to go against this great host.
And we find that in verse number 2 of Judges 7,
notice what God says to Gideon.
It says,
The Lord said unto Gideon,
the people that are with thee are too many.
They are too many for me to give
the Midianites into their hands.
Now you understand, at this particular time,
even with the number of people that Gideon had,
he was still far outnumbered.
But God says, Gideon, you have too many.
I cannot give you the victory
with this number of people and here's why.
Lest Israel vaunt themselves against me,
saying, mine own hand hath saved me.
So what does God say?
He says, I'm gonna make it such
that the only thing that you can explain
is that God gave us the victory.
I'm going to decrease your numbers so significantly
that there would be no other explanation
for the victory that I'm going to give you
than to say God did it.
See, God understands.
He's the Creator.
He's made us and He understands
that we sometimes as human beings
can get to the place that we get
a little full of ourselves.
And we think that we've accomplished something,
that we've done something.
And Jesus said, without me, you can do nothing.
In John 15.
And so Abram in this meeting with Melchizedek
as they are having this meeting,
we find that he's receiving some instruction.
He's gaining a better understanding of who God is.
The Most High God, the Possessor of Heaven and Earth.
He's gaining a little bit of a greater understanding
of what God does.
Not only who He is, but what He does.
By the way, it's good for us to continually
allow ourselves to be developed in our understanding
of who God is and what God does.
It's important for us to understand theology.
It's important for us to understand
the God that we serve
and that we would be students of the Word of God,
that we would be instructed through the pages of Scripture,
that we would understand the way in which God works.
And here, Melchizedek in no uncertain terms
lets Abram understand that it was God
that delivered thine enemies into thy hand.
The battle that took place,
remember it was four kings with five.
It was a pretty serious battle that took place.
And those kings from the east that came in
that weren't too comfortable
or too excited about the fact
that those other kings had rebelled,
they came in and cleaned house.
And Abram, with the help of God
and his 318 servants,
went and recovered all.
And God allowed Melchizedek.
He orchestrated that this meeting would take place
so that Abram would understand
that he would gain this greater awareness of the fact
that it's God that gives us the victory.
It was God that delivered thine enemies into thy hand.
I think about the many battles
that you can read of throughout the Scriptures.
I think about battles in which
the kings of Judah encountered the enemies.
The kings of Israel encountered the enemies.
And you can see very distinctly
the hand of the Lord
in providing and delivering
and giving the victory.
And here, Abram is given this truth.
We not only consider their time of fellowship,
their time of instruction,
I want you to consider the blessing.
In verses 19 and 20,
the Bible says at the beginning of v. 19,
and he blessed him.
Melchizedek blessed Abram.
And then we find that in v. 20,
it says that he, Melchizedek, says,
and blessed be the Most High God.
We notice the response of Abram
to these blessings that are mentioned.
He says, blessed be Abram
of the Most High God,
possessor of heaven and earth.
Blessed be the Most High God
which hath delivered thine enemies into thy hand.
And look at the end of v. 20.
And He gave him tithes of all.
We see again, as we've mentioned already,
that there's a few first mentions.
The book of Genesis is a book of beginnings.
And so, obviously, as you study
through the book of Genesis,
you see a number of first mention principles.
You find the first mention of El Elyon,
the Most High God.
You see the first mention of the possessor
of heaven and earth.
Now we see the first mention of tithes.
We notice in Hebrews 7,
if you hold your place there in Genesis
and turn back over to the portion in Hebrews,
you find that God speaks of this
in Hebrews 7 as well.
He's speaking about, of course, Abraham
and his interaction with this Melchizedek,
the king of Salem.
This reference in Genesis 14,
the historical account that is given to us there.
And we understand, again,
as we read the book of Hebrews,
these Jewish believers in the first century,
we understand how they would hold Abraham
in high regard.
And the greatness of Abraham.
He was Father Abraham.
We find that in verse 4 of Hebrews 7,
it says, now consider how great this man was
unto whom even the patriarch Abraham
gave the tenth of his spoils.
And verily they that are of the sons of Levi
who receive the office of the priesthood
have a commandment to take tithes of the people
according to the law that is of their brethren,
though they come out of the loins of Abraham.
But he whose descent is not counted from them
received tithes of Abraham
and blessed him that had the promises.
It says in verse number eight in here,
men that die receive tithes,
but there he receiveth them
of whom it is witnessed that he liveth.
And as I may so say,
Levi also who receiveth tithes
paid tithes in Abraham.
So we begin to see in Genesis 14
this record of Abram giving tithes of all
to Melchizedek, this king of Salem again,
this Old Testament type of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And we begin to understand the teaching
throughout the Scriptures with regard to giving
and understanding that giving
is a form of worship.
We need to be careful when we understand
the truth of giving
and we understand the blessedness in giving
and understand that God in the New Testament,
it says that He loves a cheerful giver.
That we'd understand that we worship our God
through our giving.
And here, Abram recognizing the blessing
and recognizing that which he's dealing with here
in the passage of Scripture,
we find that he gave tithes of all.
So, we look at the significance of this first meeting.
This meeting with the King of Salem.
This one Melchizedek.
We begin to understand how that God in His wisdom is preparing Abram for this second
meeting that we find was intended really to be the initial meeting.
Remember in verse number 17, the King of Sodom went out to meet him after his return.
But God orchestrated it so that first, the King of Salem, this Melchizedek, has a meeting
with Abram.
And now, Abram is properly prepared for the meeting that will take place with the King
of Sodom.
We mentioned about the significance of the meeting.
I want you to think about as we look at the latter portion of this chapter, number two
in your notes, the subtlety of the enemy.
You understand the enemy is subtle.
In fact, we're told in Genesis chapter 3, when we understand the events that are recorded
for us with regard to the Garden of Eden and sin entering into the world, that the Bible
tells us of the serpent in verse number 1 of Genesis 3,
Now the serpent was more subtle than any beast of the field which the Lord God had made.
And He said unto the woman, Yea, hath God said, Ye shall not eat of every tree of the
garden.
And we find that He came with great subtlety.
We understand that the Bible tells us that our enemy, in Ephesians chapter number 6,
we're told that we're to be strong in the Lord and the power of His might, put on the
whole armor of God, that we might stand against the wiles of the devil, the subtlety of the
devil, the deceitfulness of the devil.
We find in 1 Peter 5 that Peter is giving admonition to those that he is speaking to,
that he's ministering to with regard to the enemy.
And he says he's walking about seeking whom he may devour.
But Paul gives us this great truth in 2 Corinthians 2 in verse number 11, when he says that we
are not ignorant of his devices, speaking of the enemy.
And the reality is that we, as we study the Word of God, as we begin to study the events
that God has preserved for us in this precious book, we are able to be informed and aware
of how it is that the enemy works.
Why would we speak this evening about this meeting with this king of Sodom and entitle
it, describe it as being the subtlety of the enemy?
Well, I want you to really, in the very beginning, consider the timing of this meeting.
We look at the purpose as we get into the text, but I want you to consider, as we think
about the subtlety, this man, this king of Sodom, he comes with an offer right after
a time of great victory.
See, there are times in which we experience great victory and we experience the blessing
of God, and perhaps our guard can be down.
Because we're experiencing that victory.
In fact, as you study the kings of Israel and Judah, and you would find at times in
their lives that they would experience victory, and shortly thereafter, they would suffer
great defeat.
We need to be careful in time of blessing and time of victory.
And we notice here that the king of Sodom, if you look in verse 17, it says that he went
out to meet him after his return from the slaughter of Shador, Laomer, and of the kings
that were with him.
Now remember, in verse 16, he brought back all the goods.
He brought his brother-in-law and his goods and the women and the people.
There's great victory that had been taking place.
And here comes the king of Sodom.
And he's going to come with an offer.
He's going to come, and we really see the subtlety of the enemy, and we begin to notice
what's taking place.
Notice in verse number 21, we look at his proposition.
It says this,
And the king of Sodom said unto Abram, Give me the persons, and take the goods to thyself.
Give me the persons, and take the goods to thyself.
I've already made mention that this king of Sodom no doubt was a wicked man.
When we understand the way in which God describes for us the people of Sodom, the men of Sodom,
that they were wicked and sinners before the Lord exceedingly, we very easily can conclude
that this man that was the king of Sodom was a vile, wicked man.
And this king of Sodom comes to Abram just after he's experienced great victory.
And he's brought all of these things back.
He's returned all of these things.
And he's come back.
And here the king of Sodom, but before he can hear the proposition of the king of Sodom,
God allows the king of Salem to first have a meeting with Abram.
And God in that meeting that Melchizedek has with Abram reveals more of his person, reveals
more of his plan.
And we find that Abram is therefore prepared for the meeting with Sodom.
And when this man, this king of Sodom, gives this proposition, he says,
Give me the persons, and take the goods to thyself.
Then Abram is able to come to a place where he understands, I don't need what you're offering.
Why? Because I'm serving the great God, the Most High God,
who is the possessor of heaven and earth.
This wicked king of Sodom, I don't need thy goods.
You do understand that he says, Give me the persons, and have the goods.
He's concerned about the people, this king of Sodom.
He's not so concerned about the goods, he's concerned about the persons.
And we understand that no doubt, even at the end of this chapter,
as Abram would give a response to the king of Sodom,
and he would say, No, thank you, that he would return.
But we find that Lot would go back to Sodom.
If the king of Salem, Melchizedek, is a type of the Lord Jesus Christ,
I would say this evening that the king of Sodom is a type of the devil,
is a type of the enemy.
He's wicked, exceedingly vile.
And he comes and he makes this offer, this proposition.
And I love the way in which Abram responds in verse number 22 and 23.
The response continues into verse 24,
but I want you to see what is said in verses 22 and 23,
and really grasp with me this evening how this meeting with Melchizedek
properly prepared Abram for the subtlety of the enemy.
It says this,
Abram said to the king of Sodom,
I have lift up mine hand unto the Lord.
The Most High God, the Possessor of heaven and earth.
Now let me ask you this evening,
where is it that Abram discovered that he was the Most High God?
Where was it that Abram discovered that he was the Possessor of heaven and earth?
Look no further than the meeting that he had with Melchizedek.
The instruction that he had just received.
As Melchizedek comes, and it's the first mention that we see in verses 18 and 19
when Melchizedek says the Most High God,
that he is the priest of the Most High God,
that he's coming and he says,
Blessed be Abram of the Most High God, Possessor of heaven and earth.
This is the first mention of these titles for God in all of the Bible.
And now Abram's response to the king of Sodom
is that I have lift up mine hand unto the Lord,
the Most High God, the Possessor of heaven and earth.
Abram was able to answer in the manner in which he did
because of that meeting with Melchizedek, the king of Salem.
Because of the instruction that he received.
The preparation that God was giving Abram
to be prepared for the subtlety of the enemy
when the enemy would come and say,
Hey, just give me the people, you can keep all the spoil.
And Abram says, Actually, I have my eyes on someone greater.
Actually, I have my eyes on something better.
I'm serving the Lord, the Most High God, the Possessor of heaven and earth.
We know him later as the King of kings and Lord of lords.
We find that Abram, I'm so thankful as I look at the passage of Scripture
that God orchestrated this meeting with Melchizedek and Abram, aren't you?
You begin to see how God is working and orchestrating and preparing.
And Abram says, he continues in verse 23,
that I will not take from a thread even to a shoelatchet.
And that I will not take anything that is thine,
lest thou shouldest say, I have made Abram rich.
The Scriptures already tell us on a number of occasions
that God had blessed Abram.
We read of the blessing of Abram as he goes down into Egypt,
as he returns from Egypt.
We read about how God blessed Abram.
And we come to this passage and we see
that there were three hundred and eight...
trained servants from his own house that went out to battle.
God's blessing and favor had been upon Abram,
but we find that the enemy comes,
and the enemy gives this proposition, he gives this offer,
and because of the meeting that Abram had with Melchizedek,
the picture, the type of the Lord Jesus Christ,
the King of Salem, and the instruction that was received,
he's prepared for this meeting,
this offer that the King of Sodom would give.
You know that in the New Testament,
actually turn there.
Look over at Matthew, if you will,
in chapter 4.
Hold your place there in Genesis.
We'll get back.
In Matthew 4, this is the account of
the temptation of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ.
The Bible says this in verse 1,
Then was Jesus led up of the Spirit
into the wilderness to be tempted of the devil.
When He had fasted 40 days and 40 nights,
He was afterward and hungered.
And when the tempter came to Him,
he said, If Thou be the Son of God,
command that these stones be made bread.
But He answered Jesus and said,
It is written,
Man shall not live by bread alone,
but by every word that proceedeth
out of the mouth of God.
Then the devil taketh Him up into the holy city
and setteth Him on a pinnacle of the temple.
Notice what he says,
If Thou be the Son of God, cast Thyself down,
for it is written,
He shall give His angels charge concerning Thee,
and in their hands they shall bear Thee up,
lest at any time Thou dash Thy foot against a stone.
Jesus responds, It is written again,
Thou shalt not tempt the Lord Thy God.
The devil taketh Him up into an exceeding high mountain
and showeth Him all the kingdoms of the world
in the glory of them.
That's where I want to focus on here.
The offer.
It says to him in v. 9,
And saith unto him,
All these things will I give thee
if thou fall down and worship me.
Then saith Jesus unto him,
Get thee hence, Satan,
for it is written,
Thou shalt worship the Lord Thy God
and Him only shalt thou serve.
Then the devil leaveth Him,
and behold, angels came and ministered unto Him.
Luke tells us that they departed for a little time.
The devil departed for a little time.
Let me submit to you this evening
that as Satan would tempt the Lord Jesus Christ,
God and flesh,
no doubt this evening,
he would bring a temptation in your life as well.
He wants to make you an offer.
I've heard many missionaries have shared this.
In fact, you even hear it occasionally
within our own borders of our own nation
that every man has their price.
Abram said, I'm not interested.
I don't want your goods.
I don't want what you're offering me.
And I find it interesting
that as the Lord Jesus Christ
in Matthew 4
responds to each of these temptations
of the devil,
He says, it is written.
We find that that no doubt is a pattern for us
as we go into spiritual battle and warfare.
It is imperative that we know the Word of God
so that we can respond with the Word of God.
We understand in Ephesians 6
that it is the sword of the Spirit
which is the Word of God.
And we find that Jesus says it is written.
In essence,
what we find in the response of Abram
in Genesis 14
is that he has received this revelation
about who God is
and about what God does,
and as he receives this revelation
through this meeting with Melchizedek,
when the King of Sodom comes
and makes this offer,
in essence, he's saying,
it is written.
I understand that it's not yet been written.
Moses would write it.
But in essence, he's saying,
I understand this revelation
that has been given to me.
I have my eyes on the Most High God,
on the Possessor of Heaven and Earth.
I don't need your goods.
I'm not going to take any of those things,
not from a thread, even to a shoelatchet.
I'm not going to take any of that,
lest thou should it say,
I have made Abram rich.
What discernment Abram has
in this passage of Scripture?
How did he get the discernment?
No doubt, it comes from spending time
and walking with the Lord.
No doubt, in our text of Scripture,
it's a result of that meeting
with the King of Salem, Melchizedek.
That Old Testament type of Christ.
He continues in v. 24
to finish out the passage.
He says,
save only that which the young men have eaten,
and the portion of the men which went with me,
Aner, Eshgal, and Mamre,
let them take their portion.
But Abram is in a place
where he is completely dependent upon the Lord.
It's interesting, in Psalm 57,
you don't need to turn there.
I'll just read to you very quickly
what the psalmist declares in Psalm 57
in verse 2.
He says,
I will cry unto God Most High,
unto God that performeth all things for me.
Psalm 57 and verse 2.
This evening, as we look at this encounter,
this meeting,
we begin to see the significance of the meeting
with Melchizedek, the King of Salem.
We begin to see the subtlety of the enemy
and seeing the approach of this King of Sodom.
I submit to you this evening
that we need to get our eyes on the Lord.
Looking unto Jesus has been our theme all year.
But as Abram is given this information,
it has a profound impact upon his life,
and it enables him to be prepared
for the subtlety of the enemy.
Unfortunately, we read far too often
of casualties in the Christian life.
In fact, Paul says he's writing to the people in Galatia,
the region of Galatia.
He says, you did run well.
Who did hinder you?
We find that throughout the lives of God's people
and as we journey this Christian life,
the enemy is going to come.
He's going to tempt you.
He's going to try to distract you.
He's going to try to get your eyes on something else.
He's going to try to make a deal with you.
To make an offer with you.
I mean, by the way, Abram,
you're the one that brought all this back.
I mean, it's only right that we give this to you.
I know the Scriptures don't say that,
but can you imagine in that time frame?
Historically?
The pressure?
But see, Abram was looking far beyond
what any earthly king could offer him.
He says, King of Sodom, no thank you.
No thank you.
I'm serving the Most High God,
the Possessor of Heaven and Earth.
Oh, that we'd get our eyes on the Lord.
Oh, that we'd have those times of meeting with the Lord
so that we could be properly prepared
for when the enemy comes and seeks to tempt you
and seeks to make a deal with you.
I say, not today.
No thank you.
I serve the Lord God Almighty.
He is King of kings and Lord of lords.
There's nothing that you can do for me.
There's nothing that you can give me
that He can't do.
I'm serving God.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
I thank You for this text of Scripture,
the significance of what we see transpire,
and how that this King of Sodom
set out to meet with Abram
as he would return from this great victory.
And yet, in Your wisdom,
You orchestrated it so that Melchizedek,
the King of Salem first,
had a meeting with Abram.
And in that meeting, Abram was prepared
to deal with the subtlety of the enemy.
God, would You help us tonight
to acknowledge the importance
of spending time with You and Your Word,
that we'd have the spiritual discernment
that only comes from You,
that we'd have that wisdom that You promised to give,
that we'd be aware of the devices of our enemy,
the tactics, the subtlety.
Lord, that as we learn more about who You are
and about what You do,
we just get so in awe of who You are,
that there's no offer that could come our way
that would cause us for even a moment
to become distracted.
As we serve the Lord God Almighty,
the Most High God,
the Possessor of heaven and earth,
I pray this evening that You'd speak to hearts.
Challenge us.
Help us to make some decisions tonight.
Lord, perhaps maybe there's some
that have had the enemy come in subtlety.
Seek to distract them.
Oh Lord, would You help them.
Perhaps tonight, there are some that need to make a commitment to spend more time with You,
to make that a greater priority so that they could be properly prepared
for the day in which the enemy does come.
Work in only the way You can.
We pray that You alone would be glorified, for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would You stand with me?