Online and happy birthday to brother John and he is not 40. Amen. I don't know exactly his age, but he is not 40
I can guarantee you that happy birthday, brother
John 2nd Chronicles chapter number 20 2nd Chronicles chapter number 20 in your Bible this morning as you know throughout the year
Here in 2020 our theme has been looking unto Jesus
We systematically studied through the book of Hebrews and as we studied through the book of Hebrews
Of course, as you know as you've been with us, we finished up last Sunday and what a joy
To that it was for me
I hope it was a joy for you to study through the book of Hebrews and to be encouraged to be challenged to be strengthened
And as we study the Word of God
We know that the Bible tells us that faith come of my hearing and hearing by the Word of the Lord of the Word of
God and I'm so thankful that through studying the Word of God that our faith is increased and we serve a wonderful Savior
Amen, and I know I've shared this before with you that several
in the places in which we go we have to wear masks and all that sort of thing and so I
purchased a couple of masks that have
Some some some sayings on them. One of them says Jesus loves you
and one of them says Jesus saves and I get occasionally some people that look at me and
Say I like your mask
I appreciate that message and then I have other people that look at me like I want to tear that mask off your face and
The thing that's amazing and I thought about this week
I had some of those that just kind of looked at me funny this week with either of those masks on and I thought this
The reality is that Jesus does love you and I you don't have to believe it
but I wish you would and
I'm so thankful to know the love of God and to know the truth of the Word of God as they were singing the song
That we can trust his word. It will not fail
Amen, and what a blessing to know the truth of the Word of God to have the privilege of studying the Word of God
And as we've had for our theme and obviously all of these
expressions throughout the book of Hebrews how Christ is superior he's better and he is and
The the believers there that are being addressed the original recipients. They are being
Just the evidence is is just so
Convincing I mean it's an
overwhelming amount of evidence to prove that Jesus Christ is superior and how important it is for us as the people of
God as we go through life as we journey life that we turn our eyes upon the Lord that we seek his face that we
understand that though the things around us may be confusing there may be
Conflict and contention and chaos and all of those things that our God is in control
Our God is sovereign and we need to look to him this morning
I've asked you to turn to 2nd Chronicles chapter number 20 and we're gonna look at verses 1 through 30
As we examine this passage of scripture that records for us an event from the reign of Jehoshaphat
He's king of Judah. And if you know some things about Jehoshaphat, we understand this morning that if we were to categorize
Kings of Judah and say there were some good kings and there were some bad kings
Jehoshaphat I think would fall in that category as being basically a good king
obviously, not everything in his life is is worthy of emulation of
Exemplary conduct so on and so forth. He actually made a couple of really bad decisions in 2nd Chronicles chapter number 20
He's really just following a really bad decision in which he made affinity with Ahab
That will not be the content of what we'll study this morning
but we find that as we come to the 20th chapter of 2nd Chronicles that we have this opportunity of
Reading an event in the life of Jehoshaphat that I think will help us as we're able to relate to this
Individual to this man that yes, he was the king of Judah
But he was facing a great difficulty look at it in verse 1 with me
the Bible says it came to pass after this also that the children of Moab and the children of Ammon and with them other
Beside the Ammonites came against Jehoshaphat to battle
Then there came some that told Jehoshaphat saying there cometh a great multitude
Against thee from beyond the sea on this side Syria and behold
They be in hazes on Tamar which is in getting look down at verse number 12
If you will and the Bible says this Oh
our God
Will thou not judge them?
For we have no might against this great company that cometh against us
Neither know we what to do
But our eyes are
upon
thee
This morning. I want to preach a message that I've simply titled from the end of verse number 12. Our eyes are
upon
thee our eyes are
Upon thee sometimes I think as we look at the declaration in verse number 12, we can relate we have no might no strength
no power
Given the circumstances the situation which we're facing. In fact, we might say as Jehoshaphat said we don't even know what to do
But here's what we're doing. Our eyes are upon
Thee notice with me as we study through this passage of Scripture number one
If you're taking notes consider the dilemma Jehoshaphat faced
He faces a dilemma, of course, we know what dilemmas are problems trials difficulties
Those things that we wish we didn't have to deal with quite honestly those things that come into our lives that we say
It'd be better if we didn't have to deal with this right now. I don't have time for this. It's not a good season
It's whatever and we have these dilemmas these trials these
Times of difficulty that we face in our lives and we find that Jehoshaphat is facing such a dilemma
I want you to understand. This isn't the first time this man ever faced a dilemma
This isn't the first time there was ever any type of military campaign that he would be involved with and yet we find that in
This particular text of Scripture the severity of this dilemma
Reveals to us great truth that I hope would be a help to us
We find as we've read already in verses 1 & 2
that the children of Moab and the children of Ammon they form a
Coalition and they come and they've already crossed the Bible tells us in verse number two that someone came to tell Jehoshaphat
There was a messenger that brought this message
They've already come this great multitude against thee from beyond the sea of this side Syria
and we find that they were coming no doubt for the purpose of attacking and
Conquering they weren't coming to just bring kind greetings
They weren't coming to try to have a little brief skirmish and then just let's go home
No, they were coming to attack and to conquer and no doubt. This was a very serious situation
We find the Bible says in verse number two notice how this coalition is described as a great
Multitude we find that Jehoshaphat himself while he's praying in verse number 12
He will refer to this great multitude as a great company
And then we find in verse number 15 of our text of Scripture that the Lord
Gives answer and the the Prophet is speaking to Jehoshaphat and God says be not afraid nor dismayed
by reason of this great
Multitude and so when we look at the passage of Scripture and we see that can and we consider the dilemma in which
Jehoshaphat was facing we understand here this morning
It's a great multitude. It's a great company
It wasn't just that the messenger described this coalition in this manner
The messenger describes as a great a great multitude
Jehoshaphat says it's a great company and God says it's a great multitude. You know, there are times in our lives that we can
Embellish the difficulty in which we're dealing with. Amen. We can look at something and say this is the biggest trial
I've ever faced in my life and sometimes we get to the other side of it
We say, you know, it really wasn't that bad or we face something more difficult and say, you know
That thing that we faced really was just a walk in the park and we find here
however, that it was not a situation in which
Jehoshaphat is simply
Embellishing his dilemma God calls it a great multitude this great coalition
That is coming against Jehoshaphat king of Judah
And of course the people of Judah now understand with me as we look at the passage of Scripture how this dilemma
Impacted how it affected
Jehoshaphat as we begin reading verse number three, the Bible says and Jehoshaphat
feared
You ever fear the things that you might face? I understand the Bible's full of fear not fear thou not
We studied as we've been studying through the book of Genesis
We will finish up the 15th chapter of Genesis this evening
But when you began Genesis 15 in verse number one, we find that God in that memorable greeting to Abram
He says Abram fear not
But there are times in our lives as human beings that we fear
It's an emotion that we have and there are times in which we fear in
Jehoshaphat here in 2nd Chronicles chapter number 20 in verse number 3 when he's faced with this dilemma
We find that the Bible tells us that he feared
the the
Important thing that we need to know as we study this passage of Scripture this morning is how is it that we respond?
in time of fear
How is it that we respond with dilemmas that we face in time of difficulty in time of trial?
When we have that fear, how does it does it cripple us?
Does it cause us to just begin to make all sorts of decisions that that are not appropriate?
Decisions we find that the fear that Jehoshaphat
experiences in this passage of Scripture
caused him to seek God.
And I mean, that's powerful.
It's such an imperative truth
for us to grasp this morning
because v. 3 says that Jehoshaphat
feared and set himself to seek the Lord
and proclaimed a fast throughout all Judah.
Fasting in the Word of God
as we've mentioned throughout the years
is a sign of really the seriousness
of the individual seeking the Lord.
He's not only seeking God through prayer,
but he's proclaimed this fast.
Why?
Because they're serious about what's going on
and through this prayer,
this seeking and this fasting,
they're demonstrating their seriousness
with regard to the situation.
And so we find that the fear
that Jehoshaphat would experience
because of this dilemma
properly drove him to the Lord.
Sometimes we get to the place in our lives,
and I understand that even as we studied
in Hebrews 13 just a few weeks ago,
when we understand that our God is with us,
He said, I'll never leave thee nor forsake thee.
And then we can say that we're not gonna fear
what man can do unto us.
Why?
Because God is my helper.
But even though we understand that biblical truth,
I would submit to you this morning
that there are times even as the people of God
that circumstances will invade your life
and invade my life that will cause us
to respond with fear.
But what do we do in that time of fear?
Oh, we seek God.
And we begin to have Him remove those fears, right?
Because we're focused upon Him
and we're seeking Him
and we're seeing how He will work
in and through the situation.
So number one, we consider the dilemma.
Number two, notice the declaration of Jehoshaphat.
Over the next several verses,
we find this response of Jehoshaphat to this dilemma.
And as we begin to just dissect,
really verses three through 13,
and begin to look at this prayer
and this proclamation, this declaration,
as I have termed it,
we find that not only is it impactful for us
as the people of God,
but I would submit to you this morning
that it's exemplary.
It's a great example for us to begin to see the fact
that this man, Jehoshaphat,
though he's the king of Judah,
he's facing a serious situation.
It's a real dilemma in which he is facing.
The nation is in a situation
in which they are now going to seek God
because of this coalition that's been formed.
And I want you to notice the response.
We see in verse three, as I've already made note,
that he sought the Lord and proclaimed a fast.
It continues in verse number four.
And Judah gathered themselves together
to ask help of the Lord.
Even out of all the cities of Judah,
they came to seek the Lord.
There's really a couple of things
that I noticed in verse number four.
Number one, I noticed the influence of King Jehoshaphat.
I noticed that King Jehoshaphat,
in verse number two,
as he received word about this coalition
that was formed against them,
and he understood the purpose
in which they were coming to attack and to conquer,
that Jehoshaphat proclaimed a fast around all Judah.
And the Bible says that Judah gathered themselves together.
This man was an influential leader
in the nation of Israel, appropriately so.
He's the king.
He should have influence, amen.
And we find that he's influencing these people,
the children of Israel, the inhabitants of Judah,
to seek God.
And we find that the Bible tells us in verse number four,
even out of all the cities of Judah,
they came to seek the Lord.
What were they seeking?
Well, the Bible tells us they were asking help of the Lord.
And, you know, I'm so thankful that the Lord is our helper.
There are times in which, in our life,
we feel like we can handle the circumstances,
the situations, the dilemmas that come into our lives.
We feel that we have the ability to handle this thing,
but we must find ourselves as the people of God
to understand how important it is
that we are dependent upon the Lord
and that we ask Him for help.
You ever in a situation where you are just
so reluctant to ask for help,
yet there's help that's just close by?
And maybe you just work and work and work
and you try to figure something out
and you're just working, working, working
and toiling and rowing,
as the Bible talks about the disciples.
They're toiling and rowing.
You know what I mean?
I mean, in my mind's eye, I see it, right?
They're rowing as hard as they,
and they're not going anywhere.
Jesus came by and they invite him on the ship.
And guess what?
They're on the other side.
It's amazing.
So we just ask God for help.
He is our helper.
The psalmist declares, help, Lord.
And there are times in which
that's exactly what we need to do.
And they sought the Lord for the express purpose
of asking help of the Lord.
Look at verse number five,
as we continue looking through here.
And we understand that in these next few verses
of scripture, really in verses five through 11,
that as Jehoshaphat is praying,
that as we read these words,
we find that it's revealing to us
the knowledge that he has of God and of his word.
I would submit to you this morning
that it's imperative as us, as the people of God,
to be people of the book,
that we know the God of the Bible,
that we know the word of God.
Listen, when we understand that he's able to do
exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think,
when we understand that he said,
call unto me and I will answer thee
and show thee great and mighty things
which thou knowest not,
when we understand the promises of the word of God,
it will cause us to run to him for help.
We've been singing our theme song since June
from Psalm 121.
I will lift up mine eyes unto the hills
from whence cometh my help.
My help cometh from the Lord,
which made heaven and earth.
When I understand that he said,
let there be light and there was light,
when I understand that he created everything
out of nothing that he said and it was done,
man, it causes me to understand
that he's able to help me
and he's able to help you.
Notice in verse number five,
the Bible says that Jehoshaphat stood
in the congregation of Judah and Jerusalem
in the house of the Lord before the new court
and said, this is where the prayer begins,
oh Lord God of our fathers,
art not thou God in heaven
and rulest not thou over all the kingdoms of the heathen
and in thine hand is there not power and might
so that none is able to withstand thee.
Notice in verse number six that he, Jehoshaphat,
understands that our God is sovereign
and that he is omnipotent.
You understand this morning as we consider
the event and the life of Jehoshaphat,
but even as we begin to make application
for our own lives today and think about
the dilemmas that we face,
maybe as individuals, maybe as families,
maybe as a church, maybe as a nation,
we begin to see the dilemmas that we face
and we must recognize this morning
that the word of God reveals to us
that our God is sovereign,
that our God is the omnipotent God
and that he reigns, that there is nothing
that's too hard for him.
And we find that Jehoshaphat, as he's praying,
he's recognizing that again, it reveals to us
his knowledge of who God is.
In verse number seven, art not thou our God?
You notice the personal relationship.
He's our God.
Aren't you thankful for that?
It says here, who didst drive out the inhabitants
of this land before thy people Israel
and gavest it to the seed of Abraham thy friend forever?
We find that God has worked mightily
on the behalf of his people
and here Jehoshaphat would rehearse
that which had been really the understanding
of the start of the nation of Israel
and the promise to Abram as we'll be studying
even this evening in Genesis chapter number 15
and we've studied over the last several passages
of scripture in the book of Genesis
with regard to the promise that God gave to Abram
and as we notice here that Jehoshaphat
is aware of those things.
He's aware of the mighty acts of God.
I wonder this morning, how often do we rehearse
what God has done?
When we face a dilemma, when we face a difficulty
and we go to God in prayer,
I wonder how our faith is encouraged, increased.
I wonder how our fear is decreased
when we just rehearse what God has done.
When we're mindful of the mighty acts of our God.
Our God is amazing and he's done some amazing things
and he's recorded for us in this precious book
so many amazing miracles that are impactful for us
as the children of God.
In your life and in my life, God has worked miracles.
God has answered prayer in your life
and that encourages you.
He's seen you through the storm before
and it caused you to have great comfort
and great confidence and faith knowing
that he's with you even in the midst of the trouble,
the dilemma that you're facing today.
We find that the prayer continues,
notice in verse number eight,
and they dwelt therein and have built thee a sanctuary
therein for thy name saying,
if when evil cometh upon us as the sword,
judgment or pestilence or famine,
we stand before this house and in thy presence
for thy name is in this house
and cry unto thee in our affliction,
notice this last phrase,
then thou wilt hear and help.
Jehoshaphat knew that that's what God had said.
You look at the declaration, the proclamation,
the dedication of the temple under the reign of Solomon
and you read all of that, which is taking place,
obviously the building of the temple,
you get into 2 Chronicles.
6 and 7, and you read the prayer of Solomon into all the activities and
festivities, if you will, that surrounded the dedication of the temple, and then
how God answers, I've heard thy prayer, is what God says to Solomon in chapter
number 7, and we find that within the context of those chapters that Jehoshaphat
is mindful of that promise, and he's saying, here's what we're doing. You said
if when these evil things come, that if we come to this place and if we cry unto
thee in our affliction, that you will hear and help. Therefore, based upon what
you have said in your word, God, we're here asking you for help. Amen? And listen,
if you don't know the Word of God, you're not gonna know that you can go to him
for help, right? And so we find that Jehoshaphat, with facing this dilemma,
with dealing with this difficulty, his knowledge of who God is, but also his
knowledge of what God has said, that God wants to be your helper. Listen, we
understand the psalmist has declared this throughout the Psalms, and we've
studied many of them as we've had the opportunity to speak about the truth
that our God is our helper, and we think about this truth, you don't need to turn
there, but in Psalm 46 and verse number 1, the psalmist declares God is our
refuge and strength, a very present help in trouble. He's not only able to help,
he's available to help. Have you ever known somebody that's able to help, but
they just don't have any availability? You need help with a project, and you
know so-and-so can help you, because they have the know-how, but they're just
simply not available. They're busy, they have other appointments, they have other
tasks that they're working on. That never happens with God. He's a very present
help in the time of trouble. It's interesting what the psalmist continues
to say in Psalm 46 and verses 2 and 3. He says, therefore, based upon our
understanding that God is our refuge and our strength and a very present
help in trouble, will not we fear, though the earth be removed and though the
mountains be carried into the midst of the sea, though the waters thereof roar
and be troubled, though the mountains shake with swelling, thereof,
selah. That word selah in the book of Psalms is a precious word. It means to
stop and meditate and muse upon and allow it to sink in. Someone over the
years, many people have asked me how much of the Bible should they read every day
and that sort of thing, and kind of developing a Bible reading program and a
schedule and so on and so forth, and I've often told people that the
quality of your time with the Lord is of more importance than the quantity of the
number of verses or chapters that you read. There are times, and I hope that
you've experienced this as a child of God, there are times that God will arrest
your attention upon one verse of Scripture and you just simply don't get
any further than that one verse. But oh, you had a hallelujah time with the Lord
on that day, you understand what I mean. And the reality this morning is that we
can, when we look at the the psalmist and we say, selah, listen, we stop and we
meditate and we think about this, we say, listen, this is impactful truth. And see,
Jehoshaphat, back in 2nd Chronicles chapter number 20, he knew that God had
said this. What was it that caused him, in light of the dilemma, in light of the
difficulty that he was facing, why is it that he proclaimed this fast? Why is it
that he sought the Lord? Why did he bring the people? Because he knew that God said
that if you seek me, I will hear and I will help. What did the songwriter say in
the song that the the girls, Holly and Julianne and Brianna, played for us?
His word will not fail you. It won't. God is not a man that he should lie. Every
promise of God in him is yea. These promises are exceeding great and
precious promises. And we find that this man, Jehoshaphat, what a great
example for us. He's saying, in simple faith, his actions are saying, I believe
you, God. And here's why we're here. Continue, look in verse number 10,
And now, behold, the children of Ammon and Moab and Mount Seir, whom thou wouldst
not let Israel invade when they came out of the land of Egypt, but they turned
from them and destroyed them not. Behold, I say, how they reward us to come to cast
us out of thy possession, which thou hast given us to inherit. In verses 10 and 11,
not only does it reveal to us again more of the knowledge that Jehoshaphat has
of the historical events, but it also reveals to us the transparency of
Jehoshaphat. You know, did God already know this? Sure he did. Our God is
all-knowing. He's omniscient. He already knew what they were facing. He already knew
those that were gathered against. He knew about this great company, this great
multitude. But you understand that there's something beneficial for us, as
the people of God, to be transparent with God and to just pour our heart out to
him and say, God, here's the specific issue that I'm facing. Here's
the specific difficulty, dilemma, that I'm dealing with in my life. For Jehoshaphat,
in this text of Scripture, specifically, the dilemma is that there's a coalition
that's formed against them, Moab and Ammon and others along with them, and
they're coming to attack and conquer. So what does Jehoshaphat do? I'm being
transparent with God. Here's my problem, God. Hezekiah, when the Assyrians
come in, Rabshakeh's coming and telling them, as the representative of
Sennacherib, he's coming and saying, here's what we're gonna do, here's what
we're gonna do, and letters were written. What does he do? He goes and he lays it
out before the Lord. God, here's what they're saying. Not only is it what
they're saying, what they're saying is true. They've conquered all of these
surrounding nations. They do have great power, but God, you're the Lord of the
universe. These other nations, they serve false gods, but we serve you. Hezekiah
lays it out before the Lord. And I would say to you this morning, as we look at
this passage of Scripture, and we've made note that it was a—not only do we
see that through this impactful event, it's exemplary. We find that we're in
that place of, hey, let us get before the Lord and just pour our heart out to God
and just be honest with God. He knows anyway, but there's something beneficial
about us saying it to God and just letting him know. We continue as we find
that he's stated the problem, and we see this declaration as we read for—by way
of introduction for our title this morning, but look in verses 12 and
13 again with me. Oh our God, wilt thou not judge them? For we have no might
against this great company that cometh against us. I find in that first
statement that is there, and he continues by saying, neither know we what to do,
that it's a recognition of their inability. You know that requires
humility. In your pride and in my pride, we want to figure that we can take care
of it. We got this. We can handle this. But the reality is that when we find in
this declaration in the first, really two-thirds of verse number 12, that
Jehoshaphat is in his declaration, he's recognizing his inability. We have no
strength, we have no might, we have no power against this great company. We're
saying, we're just—we're not fit for this battle. We're not able. And furthermore,
we just flat-out don't know what to do. Have you ever been there? You just don't
know what to do. Sometimes—and I'll be very transparent with you—sometimes I
pray to the Lord in these type of terms, and I say, Lord, I'm not smart enough to
know how to figure this thing out. You just need to make it extremely plain and
clear to me, because I'm just not smart enough. He said, I can't believe—you're not smart
enough either, amen? Seriously, we don't know the end from the beginning, but we
know the one who does. So would it not be foolish of us to think that we can
handle all of our problems? No. We go to God and say, I don't know what to do. And
that's what Jehoshaphat does. He says, we don't have the power, the might, we don't
have the ability, and we don't know what to do, but our eyes are upon thee. What a
precious statement. Our eyes are upon thee. This, as we would say that it was a
recognition of their inability in the first part of the verse, we'd say in the
latter part of the verse that it's a declaration of their dependence. John 15,
we find that Jesus teaches the disciples, and of course for us to have the
understanding of that teaching, that without Him we can do nothing. The
songwriter said, I need thee every hour, and I know I've often said not to try to
one-up or correct the songwriter, but the reality is that we need Him every second
of every minute of every hour. We need God. And here the the King of Judah, He
says, our eyes are upon thee. In the dilemma that you're facing, we know the
dilemma that Jehoshaphat is facing, it's historical record, it's for us to be able
to examine, but God's Word is given to us, not just for a history lesson, God's
Word is given to us so that we can apply in our own lives. What's the dilemma that
you're facing? What's our difficulty that we're dealing with today, and have we
come to the place of declaring our inability and declaring our dependence
upon God? God, our eyes are upon thee. All year, look
unto Jesus. Turn your eyes upon Jesus, they sang this morning. We've just
gone through and began to understand the significance and the importance of us
trusting God. Listen, He is the author and finisher of our faith. He is just, I mean,
He's amazing. And as we begin to see how that Jehoshaphat would make this
declaration, we find in verse number 13 that all Judah stood before the Lord
with their little ones, their wives, and their children. Oh, how important verse
number 13 is. Can I submit to you this morning that husbands, your wives need to
know that you're trusting God. Parents, your children need to know that you're
trusting God. Listen, our families need to understand that we are seeking God.
Their little ones, their wives, their children, the families were there. They
were gathered together in seeking the Lord, and we find the power of that, and
the importance of that. Listen, why is it we have people that are writing books
and dealing with all of this sort of thing, how that we're losing a
generation in our churches, and can I tell you that for the most part they're
right, we are. Why? Somewhere we've lost it. There's been a disconnect. And the
reality is that here in verse number 13, when we think about this influence, when
we think about the the setting and all that was taking place, and how important
it is for the children to know that we are seeking God for help, that we're
dependent upon Him. Not only do we consider the dilemma, and notice the
declaration as we finish up the passage of Scripture this morning, I want you to
rejoice in the deliverance of the Lord. I know that our time is kind of, I took too
long on 13 verses, but let's look at verse 14 down through verse 30. Then upon
Jehaziel, the son of Zechariah, the son of Benaiah, the son of Jael, the son of
Mattaniah, a Levite of the sons of Asaph, came the Spirit of the Lord in the midst
of the congregation, and he said, Hearken ye, all Judah, and the inhabitants of
Jerusalem, and thou, King Jehoshaphat, thus saith the Lord unto you. Now that's
exciting, because the Lord is answering their prayer. Remember what he said in
verse number nine, that then that will hear and help, and God is answering the
prayer. He's heard the prayer of his people, and Jehoshaphat has influenced,
and he's led the nation of Judah in seeking the face of God, and now the
Lord is speaking, the Lord is giving an answer. Notice what he says in verse 15,
Be not afraid nor dismayed by reason of this great multitude, for the battle is
not yours, but God's. Oh, how we could focus so much of our time upon that last
statement of verse number 15. The battle is not yours, but God's. We find this
morning that we are engaged in spiritual warfare. We see it so evidenced in our,
just the day and age in which we're living, we see it all around us,
the evidence of this spiritual warfare, this spiritual battle that we're engaged
in, and we understand that we must recognize that it is a spiritual battle.
We wrestle not against flesh and blood, against spiritual wickedness in high
places. That's what Paul says to the believers at Ephesus in Ephesians
chapter number 6, and we are to be strong in the Lord and the power of his
might. If God be for us, who can be against us? We are more than conquerors
through Christ, but thanks be to God which giveth us the victory through our
Lord Jesus Christ. Listen, what a joy to know that God is the Lord God omnipotent
and that he rules and reigns, and we are, as the songwriter said and Dr. Curtis
Hudson often sang, we are on the winning side. What a joy that is. It says in verse
number 16, tomorrow, go ye down against them. Behold, they come up by the cliff
of Ziz, and ye shall find them at the end of the brook before the wilderness of
Jerul. Now, I'm thankful God didn't stop there and just tell him where he's gonna
find them, but he continues and gives him more information. Verse 17, ye shall not
need to fight in this battle. Set yourselves, stand ye still, and see the
salvation of the Lord with you. O Judah and Jerusalem, fear not, nor be dismayed.
Tomorrow, go out against them, for the Lord will be with you. We notice several
things in verse number 17. We find that he says, stand ye still and see the
salvation of the Lord. We are mindful of that truth when Moses says to the
children of Israel as they were to cross over the Red Sea, stand still and see the
salvation of the Lord, and then they're told to go forward and they cross over
on dry ground. We find here that he says here that they're not to fear on two
occasions. In verse 15, again in verse number 17, he says, fear not, nor be
dismayed. He tells them again, and what a great reminder for us to be aware of the
presence of God, for the Lord will be with you. The Lord will be with you. Verse
18, and Jehoshaphat bowed his head with his face to the ground, and all Judah and
the inhabitants of Jerusalem fell before the Lord, worshiping the Lord. And the
Levites, and the children of the Kohathites, and of the children of the
Korhites, stood up to praise the Lord God of Israel with a loud voice on high, and
they rose early in the morning, and went forth into the wilderness of Tekoa. And
as they went forth, Jehoshaphat stood and said, hear me, O Judah, and the
inhabitants of Jerusalem. Believe in the Lord your God, so shall you be
established. Believe his prophets, so shall you prosper. And when he had
consulted with the people, he appointed singers unto the Lord, and that should
praise the beauty of holiness, as they went out before the army, and to say,
praise the Lord, for his mercy endureth forever. It's interesting as you look at
verses 18 through 21, and really the first statement, verse 22, that we'll
look at in just a moment, you see the rejoicing. It's impactful. Before the
actual deliverance, they're rejoicing in what God is going to do. Why? Because
they're so certain that what God has said he was going to do, that he will do,
that they can rejoice before it even happens. That's amazing. It's also
something that we should do in our lives. It reminds me of what Paul tells
the believers in Philippi, in Philippians chapter number 4, and verse number 6, and
often we quote the verse of Scripture, but we find here that the Bible says, be
careful for nothing but in everything by prayer and supplication, with thanksgiving.
Let your requests be made known unto God. And here in verses 18 through 21, the
people are worshiping the Lord. They're praising the Lord. We find that
Jehoshaphat again stands up in verse 20, and he says, believe in the Lord your
God. Have faith. Believe what God has said. In verse 21, they're there and they're
praising the beauty of holiness, that they're praising the Lord and the beauty
of his holiness, and it says, praise the Lord for his mercy endureth forever. And
notice verse 22, the beginning of the verse, it says, and when they began to
sing and to praise, the Lord set ambushments against the children of Ammon
Moab and Mount Seir. You understand that God loves to receive our praise. He does.
And they're praising God before they find the coalition dead. They soon are
going to find the coalition dead, but their rejoicing precedes the evidence of
what God said he would do. Why? They had faith. They just believed that God was
going to work, that God was going to do what he said he was going to do. We find
in verse 22, he sets the ambushments. It says that at the end of the verse, which
were come against Judah, and they were smitten. We see the response as we
consider this final point of rejoicing in the deliverance of the Lord. We see
how the Lord responds, but we also see the rejoicing of the people of God. And
then we read of the victory. The Bible ends verse 22 by saying, and they were
smitten. Notice in verse 23 and down through verse number 24, the record of
the defeat of this coalition. It says, for the children of Ammon and Moab stood up
against the inhabitants of Mount Seir, utterly to slay and destroy them. And
when they had made an end of the inhabitants of Seir, everyone helped to
destroy another. And when Judah came toward the watchtower in the wilderness,
they looked unto the multitude, and behold, they were dead bodies fallen to
the earth, and none escaped. Verse 25, and when Jehoshaphat and his people came
to take away the spoil of them, they found among them an abundance both
riches with the dead bodies and precious jewels, which they stripped off for
themselves. Notice this, more than they could carry away. And they were three
days in gathering of the spoil, it was so much. That reveals to us in verse
number 25 a couple of things. Number one, it reveals to us the size of this
coalition. Remember, the messenger said it was a great multitude. Remember,
Jehoshaphat says it's a great company, and God, through the prophets, says it's
a great multitude. We find that it reveals to us that as Jehoshaphat had
rightly proclaimed to the Lord, we don't have any might against this great
company, we don't know what to do. The Bible tells us in verse number 25, there
was so much spoil that they couldn't carry it away. There weren't enough of
them to carry away the spoil. Furthermore, it took them three days. It says that, and
they were three days in gathering of the spoil, it was so much. Sometimes God will
bring you to a dilemma, a difficulty.
that's just absolutely 100% beyond anything you could even imagine doing.
Why? Because that's when God gets the glory. That's when God gets the glory. We
understand that in the life of Gideon. We speak about it often. God says to Gideon,
nope, if I give you the victory with that many people, you guys are gonna say you
got the victory. So I need to bring it down. Just tell them if they don't want
to fight, go home. And a bunch of them went home. You understand they were
already outnumbered before the army was decreased in size. Vastly outnumbered.
God says if they don't, if they want to go home, they don't want to fight, let
them go home. Why'd all those rascals go home? Because they knew they were
outnumbered. We're going home. And then God said it's still too many. Here's what I
want you to do. And we know the account. We know what, Judges 6 through 8, read the
chapters. And you can see all that God does. But what God is doing is saying,
listen, God works in these moments of impossibility so that he would be
glorified. So that it's not explained as, well, that was the the wisdom and might
of the King Jehoshaphat. He set this great plan in order, and he did this, and
he did that, and let's lift up King Jehoshaphat. No, no, no. King Jehoshaphat
said to the people, I don't know what to do. He said that to God. But the people
were there. Oh, but the leader, the king, is supposed to make it make it so
everybody thinks he knows what he's gonna do. Sometimes the leader doesn't
know what he's gonna do. And a good leader depends upon God. Because you
understand that even though someone's a leader, it doesn't make them have
infinite knowledge as God does. We're still human beings. And we find here that
Jehoshaphat, he's not gonna receive any glory for this victory. The people of
Judah aren't gonna have any any kind of glory for this victory. They didn't
do anything. Nothing. They just simply went and collected the spoils. When they
arrived, they were all dead. God had worked on their behalf. Notice with me,
not only was it a complete victory and the spoils are gathered, but they
returned to Jerusalem. In verse number 26, on the fourth day, they assembled
themselves in the valley of Barakah, for they, excuse me, for there they blessed
the Lord. Now, that's an important statement. Again, they were praising
God beforehand, but then don't forget to praise God afterwards as well. Amen?
They praised him before, but then when they actually experienced the victory
and got it, they blessed the Lord. Therefore, the name of the place, the same
place, was called the Valley of Barakah unto this day. I think that as we read
that statement throughout the scriptures, and especially you read it in the book
of Joshua in particular, unto this day, I think there's great significance in that
because I'm mindful of when the event took place and then when the record was
written and then reread, that unto that day it was still called the Valley of
Barakah, and what a great teaching tool and an opportunity of influence to say,
let me tell you what happened. How did this place get its name? You ever think
about that when you travel? You travel places, you begin to travel the world,
what's the significance of this town? How did this town get its name? How did this
place get to be called this? Well, in the Valley of Barakah, let me tell you what
happened. There was a coalition, I'm not going to reveal or I'm not going to
recite everything I just said, but you understand, right? What a great
opportunity. Verse 27, then they returned, every man of Judah and Jerusalem and
Jehoshaphat in the forefront of them, to go again to Jerusalem, how? With joy. How
did Jehoshaphat start in verse number three? With fear. With fear. But it was an
honest situation. Sometimes we can say, I'm not afraid, but inside you know you're
afraid, right? And here it says they returned with joy. Why? For the Lord had
made them to rejoice over their enemies. They came to Jerusalem with psalteries
and harps and trumpets under the house of the Lord. In your mind's eye, can you
see them returning? I mean, honestly, in your sanctified imagination, they're not
walking back like this, oh man, it was a long trip and I'm just, man, they're
coming back excited. I mean, they're rejoicing in what God has done and how
God has worked. And this was a time to exalt and magnify the Lord God Almighty
and they're returning with psalteries and harps and trumpets under the house
of the Lord. It's a big deal. And I think the people that were left back in
Jerusalem when they went out, the ones that were there, right? The wives and the
children. Can you imagine how they were feeling upon the return of the men as
they were coming back? And they're coming back with the spoils, but they're coming
back rejoicing. In verse number 29, the fear of God was on all the kingdoms of
those countries when they had heard that the Lord fought against the enemies of
Israel. So the realm of Jehoshaphat was quiet, for his God gave him rest round
about. In verses 29 and 30, I notice in this passage the impact upon the
surrounding people groups, the surrounding nations. Can I tell you this
morning that when God works, not when we try to manufacture God working, but when
God works, people take note of that. The world understands. You understand that
during the revival ministry of many of those great evangelists in the beginning
of the 20th century of this nation, that there were people in communities that
feared those evangelists coming to their communities. Why? Because they knew that
the liquor stores and liquor places and the saloons and all of those places, all
of the places of ill report, they're gonna shut down. Because somebody's gonna
come in there, they're gonna preach the gospel, and people are gonna get saved,
scores of people are gonna get saved, and it's gonna change the town. They were
fearful of it. Why? They were taking note of what God was doing and how God was
working. And I would submit to you this morning that as we put ourselves in the
position as Jehoshaphat did and the nation of Judah did, they say, we don't
know what to do, but our eyes are upon thee. We're looking to you. We're trusting
you, God, in this moment of difficulty, in this dilemma that I'm facing. I'm trusting
you, and I'm asking you to work in such a way that you alone will be glorified.
People are gonna notice, and it's important for us to give glory to God.
Don't take this, yeah, well, you know, I figured it out. He didn't figure anything
out. Amen? Jehoshaphat didn't know where to go. In fact, God told him when to go
and where to go. He didn't leave anything open to Jehoshaphat's own figuring it
out. And this morning, as we think about this great passage in 2 Chronicles 20,
this event in the life of Jehoshaphat, I hope that we leave with more than just a
history lesson. I hope that we leave with saying, our eyes are upon thee. I understand
in a group of people, really of any size, there are dilemmas, there are
difficulties, there's opposition, there's problems, but our God is able to help.
And we must declare, as Jehoshaphat did, our eyes are upon thee. Our eyes are upon
thee. I'm looking unto my Savior, understanding who He is, understanding
what He's done, understanding what He's promised, and I'm saying, God, would you
work? I was reading this morning in my own personal devotions to the book of
John, and once again, it's a familiar verse of Scripture, but once again, my
attention was focused upon that great declaration of John the Baptist in John
3 in verse 30, he must increase and I must decrease. Listen, it's all about God
being glorified. And as long as you're trying to figure out your own problems,
and as long as you're trying to have somebody recognize how smart you are to
figure out all of your dilemmas in life, God's not gonna be glorified. And we
need to just simply come in simple faith and obedience and say, God, I don't have
the might, the strength, or the power. I don't have any idea what to do, but
here's what I'm doing. My eyes are on you. I'm seeking you. I'm asking you for help.
And God is a very present help at the time of trouble. And he says, here's what
I want to do for you. Here's how I'm gonna work on your behalf. And he gives
us the victory. And then we say, thanks be to God which giveth us the victory
through our Lord Jesus Christ. Our eyes are upon thee. Father, we love you this
morning. We thank you for loving us. We thank you for the opportunity to be
gathered together this morning for the purpose of worship. We thank you for the
opportunity to study this passage of Scripture, to be reminded of this
historical event during the reign of Jehoshaphat, king of Judah. I believe this
morning in my own life that this record of 2 Chronicles 20 is impactful. It's
exemplary. The purpose of studying your Word is not to simply have a better
grasp or understanding of historical events or timelines, though we gain that
understanding. It's that we might be doers of the Word and not hearers only.
That we might take the truth and apply it in our lives. And I pray this morning
the Holy Spirit of God has moved and worked the lives of your people. No doubt
there are dilemmas that we face. I pray that we would respond as Jehoshaphat
did and declare our dependence upon thee, would cause us to then rejoice in your deliverance,
to exalt and magnify your name.
Understand this morning that the dilemmas that we face are quite different than that
which was faced by Jehoshaphat and the nation of Judah on this particular day, but dilemmas
nonetheless.
God we pray that you'd be exalted in our lives.
There's one that does not know you as their personal Lord and Savior, it's our prayer
today that they would allow us to take a Bible and show them how they could know for sure
that heaven is their home.
They would not leave this place without knowing for sure of their eternal destination.
I pray that decisions would be made that would please thee during this time of invitation.
For it's in Christ's name we pray, would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed, no one's looking around.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano and as she does, I'd invite you to respond
to the Lord.
You can use your pew as an altar, you can come to this old-fashioned altar, but let
the Lord have His way in your life.
Be a doer of the word and not a hearer only.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.