Well, again, it's an honor to be here and thank you for being here.
And I pray that together we can learn a lot this week and that I can be a blessing.
You've already been a blessing to me.
Thank you so much.
Take your Bible, if you would, and turn to 2 Corinthians 10.
While you're turning there, I have to make this comment.
I don't know how many years I've known Joe.
Joe left.
I guess, oh, he's back there, okay.
But honestly, he was probably six or seven years old when we first met, and he was about
to my knee.
And now, many years later, I don't make it to his knee anymore.
And I only see him every couple of years now, and I just stand amazed at how the Lord
is prospering him in his height.
Now, the Lord is working with me in a similar way.
It's just this direction.
So I love Joe.
Amen.
Take your Bible, 2 Corinthians 10.
Let's notice in verse 14, Paul speaking, for we stretch not ourselves beyond our measure
as though we reached not unto you.
For we are come as far as to you also in preaching the gospel of Christ, not boasting of things
without our measure, that is, of other men's labors, but having hope when your faith is
increased that we shall be enlarged by you according to our rule abundantly, to preach
the gospel in the regions beyond you, and not to boast in another man's line of things
made ready to our hand, but he that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord.
Let's pray.
Father, we're grateful for this time you've given us to be together.
We're thankful, Lord, for this church and for the testimony of this church, their love
for missions, their concern for the world and for the need of lost souls to know Christ.
Lord, it is a valid question to ask ourselves, do we care?
Do I care?
Thank you for that message and song.
And we ask you now, Holy Spirit, this is your word, we are your people, and I pray that
you would do what no preacher can do.
Would you speak to the heart of every individual, expose to them their need and expose what
your word wants us to understand, convict us and help us, I pray.
In Jesus' name, amen.
I'll make an obvious statement, the world is immense, isn't it?
Sometimes I just ponder how big, not only geographically, the world is, although that's
astounding, and to me amazing that with modern travel we can cover thousands and thousands
of miles in hours instead of weeks and months, as it once was.
But I'm also always amazed at the size of the world and the sheer population.
I am told, and I don't know, but some people say there are as many as 8 billion people
on planet earth.
To be honest with you, I get lost after a hundred, so I don't know what 8 billion is,
but I know that it's an incomprehensible number by one individual.
I think of how large it is in diversity, how many languages are on planet earth, how many
people groups are on planet earth.
And then to understand that probably a third of them have not only never heard a clear
presentation of the gospel, some of them have never even heard the name of Jesus.
And when I think of how large it is, then I'm amazed by this thought, that as large
and as diverse as all the peoples and cultures and languages are, there is one name by which
every one of those souls must come to for salvation, and that is through Jesus Christ.
There aren't many ways.
There aren't many names.
Languages don't change the need of a soul.
Language doesn't alter the need of a soul.
Culture doesn't change what every soul needs.
Every soul needs the Lord Jesus Christ.
When I think about how immense the world is and how great God's love for every individual
is, then I come to this thought as well.
I'm somewhat embarrassed about how small my world is.
Many days and too many ways and too many days I live my life concerned only about the three
foot circle that is around me.
What impacts me?
What is in my day that day?
What's my need without ever giving a real thought to what the need of this world is?
I'm challenged when I read about men like the Apostle Paul and passages like we're looking
at this morning, to be a man like Paul who lived beyond his world.
That's my message this morning, living beyond our world.
Two times in the verses we read, Paul uses that word under the inspiration of the Spirit,
but he said he wants to go beyond his measure.
He wants to preach in the regions beyond where he is.
I think he alludes to the fact that he lives beyond his means, and I'll be very careful
to explain that in just a few moments.
But I think in every one of our lives, every one of our hearts as believers, there ought
to be a sense, a burden to live beyond who and where we are.
I don't mean to be negative in my preaching, but folks, we find ourselves living, I believe,
in the most narcissistic generation that has ever populated planet earth.
It is all about me.
It is, we don't live the we life, we live the me life.
And even believers have to purposely, intentionally break out of that and say, Lord, help me to
see beyond me.
And like the Apostle Paul, be willing to live beyond our measure.
Be willing to live beyond reaching, beyond our border, even living beyond our means.
And if those things I want to talk about for a few moments this morning, I want you to
think about what Paul means when he says he lived beyond his measure.
Look again at verse 14, for we stretch not ourselves beyond our measure, as though we
reach not unto you.
Understand this, that there were times, often, when the Apostle Paul and the church at Corinth
had kind of an adversarial relationship.
The people at Corinth did not like Paul's authority, I suppose they didn't like anyone's
authority over them, and sometimes they chafed at what Paul demanded of them or said to them
or preached to them.
And at this moment, what they're feeling, what they're saying is, Paul, you're challenging
us to reach a world.
You're challenging us to take the gospel to every creature.
But Paul, don't you understand we have our own problems?
Don't you understand, Paul, here at Corinth, we've got issues here.
In our lives, we have issues here.
You just keep telling us to reach beyond and reach beyond, and Paul, you're a dreamer.
You're dreaming if you think the gospel can go to every place in the globe and everybody
ought to hear.
And I love what Paul's answer is to them.
In essence, he says, we reached you.
We reached you.
You see, there's always been people who would doubt whether the gospel could ever go from
Jerusalem to Samaria.
I mean, the gospel is meant for Jerusalem.
But you know what?
God intended it to go beyond Jerusalem, and he had to send some persecution to get it
done.
But they did take the gospel to Samaria, and you know what?
Samaritans did get saved.
And not only did it go to Samaria, well, maybe it could go to Samaria, because they've
got some linkage to the Jewish, the Hebrew culture, but it could never go to Gentiles.
But it did go to Gentiles.
It went to Antioch, and the people at Antioch had a great revival there and saved.
A great church was established at Antioch among Gentiles, and by the way, it became
the model church for modern missions there in Antioch.
And by the way, that's where they were first called Christians.
I'm just saying there's always been people who said it couldn't be done.
There's always people who said it could never jump an ocean, but the gospel did jump an
ocean.
It jumped the Aegean, and Paul took the gospel to Philippi, and Thessalonica, Berea, Corinth,
and oh, by the way, we sit
in this room this morning because the gospel jumped
another ocean.
It jumped the Atlantic Ocean.
And we are the recipients of the truth of the Word of God
because there is no barrier or border that
can stop the Word of God.
And you and I ought to live with that thought that, yeah,
God can do more than I understand.
God can do more than I can anticipate.
God can do something.
Listen, if you are concerned just
about the measure of what can be done in the life
or through the life of Mike Edwards,
I assure you not much.
But if you pour the Spirit of God and the will of God
into a surrendered Mike Edwards, much can be done.
Fellowship Baptist Church is a spot
on a map in Fairfax County, Virginia.
But pour the Holy Spirit in Fellowship Baptist Church,
and you'd be amazed at the measure of what
God could do in reaching an entire world.
Because it is not our measure that is the difference.
It is God's measure working through us.
Now unto him that is able to exceeding abundantly
above all that we ask or think, according
to the power that worketh in us.
God is able to do exceeding abundantly great things
through us in this place if we will see and trust and believe
that God can work in us.
The Apostle Paul was a man who lived beyond his own measure,
his own ability.
He was a man that was willing to live beyond his own borders.
I love what he says in verse 16.
He wanted to preach the gospel in the regions
beyond you.
One of the greatest political questions
we face in our nation today is who and how
do we allow people to come into our country,
both legally and illegally?
To be honest with you, that's a question for other minds
than mine.
The great question that our church ought to be pondering
is not who comes in.
It ought to be how do we get our folks to go out?
How do we get people to see the great need
of reaching this lost world?
Paul was a man who was interested in going beyond,
in reaching beyond his border, if you will.
He was saved around 42 AD.
That's a long time ago.
He spent some silent years in the desert
being taught of others and being taught of the Lord
specifically.
Around 46 AD, he began preaching, traveling the world,
preaching the gospel.
And for the next 15 years, he traveled by foot.
He traveled by ship.
He was supported by others, but also when needed,
worked as a tent maker.
He preached in cities.
He preached in villages.
He preached both in season and out of season.
He preached in Jerusalem.
He preached in North Africa.
He preached in Asia Minor.
He preached in Greece, the islands
of the Mediterranean, Italy, and even
in the capital of the Roman Empire itself,
he preached the gospel in Rome.
And I believe if he would have had
modern means of transportation, Paul literally
would have reached his entire known world.
He preached to Jews, but he also preached to pagans.
He preached to paupers and kings,
to anyone that would listen, to include those who
kept him in chains in prison.
There was no border.
There was no barrier that could keep him out
if it was the Lord's will that he go.
He literally lived the Great Commission.
When we read Regents Beyond You, sometimes we
think, well, that's an interesting phrase,
but we forget the life that Paul led to accomplish that.
And I don't know about you, but what that creates in my heart
is not necessarily a guilt. It creates in me
a question of, what do I do?
What's my commitment to reach a lost world in the way
that Paul reached it?
As I was studying for this message,
I noticed that phrase, Regents Beyond.
And in one of the commentators I read,
he said there's no way to really quantify Regents Beyond,
because it depends on where you are.
But he said the best way to understand Regents Beyond
is this, still further, still further.
And I was so struck by that.
Can I tell you one of the fears of my life?
Here's one of the fears in the heart of Mike Edwards.
I've been saved since 1975.
I've been in ministry soon after.
I have studied my Bible.
I have preached.
I have been part of programs.
I've won souls.
I've prayed.
You say, are you boasting?
No, I'm just telling you.
I've been at it for a while.
And can I tell you one of the fears
and one of the dangers in my life?
To come to the place where I think I've done enough.
To think that I've learned enough.
To think that I've studied enough.
To think that I've given of myself enough.
To think that I've given enough.
To think that there's nothing else for me.
To think that someone else should share the burden.
To think that someone else should do the work.
Hey, I hope that God gives me the grace
for every day of my life to say there is still further I can go.
There is still more that I can do.
There is still someone I can reach.
There is still more of my heart to surrender to the Lord.
And may God help all of us to guard our hearts
against being content with what we have done.
There is still more that I can give.
There is still more that I can sacrifice.
There is still more that I need to grow in in my life still further.
One of my heroes of the faith is a man named C.T. Studd.
What a name.
And C.T. Studd, it won't mean much to us,
but in the early 1900s, C.T. Studd was a great cricket player.
I mean, it was a very big deal.
He was a professional cricket player.
He made a big mistake.
One night he was invited to a moody rally, and he went.
And he got saved.
And when he got saved, all of a sudden cricket
wasn't as important to him.
And long story short, he became a great missionary,
giving up that career and all the notoriety that went with it
and served in many places across the globe.
But he knew how to turn a phrase.
And let me just give you two of them.
He said once, some want to live within the sound of a church
or a chapel bell.
I want to run a rescue shop within a yard of hell.
Now, that's a phrase, and that's a preacher,
and we do stuff like that.
But I love that sentiment, that I'm not
content to just be in the comfortable place.
I'm not content to just take the easy way, that I want to go
and I want to be used of the Lord.
And if it takes me into the uncomfortable place,
into the inconvenient place, then Lord, so be it.
There is still further I can go.
He said this, if Jesus Christ is God and died for me,
then no sacrifice can be too great for me to make for him.
What a heart.
How do you get there?
How do we care about a lost world, a lost world
that we have no contact with in many ways?
Can I add this?
A lost world that often repulses us.
A lost world that when we see their culture,
when we see the degeneracy of what they do and how they live,
hey, I'm talking about our culture.
And then across the globe, how do I have that heart help me?
How do I care about them?
How do I see them and feel compassion?
How do I make myself willing to be sacrificial for them?
I remember this, that but for the grace of God, that's me.
But for the grace of God, I would be what they are.
And only by the grace of God was I pulled from that fire.
And I must remind myself of this,
that God loves every single one of them.
I don't know about you, but sometimes I
want to go to West Virginia and buy 300 acres or more
in the deepest, darkest holler you've ever seen.
I want to go all the way back in that holler at the front of it.
I want to build a gate and a wall.
I want my wife, my three kids, my seven grandkids,
and both my friends, I want them to be in there
and seal that gate and say, leave us alone.
But that is not our purpose.
And those people that often we are repulsed by their behavior, God's Son died for them.
And they are as valuable to God as you and I will ever be.
You and I have to see not with our eyes, but God's eyes.
The songwriter put it this way, and forgive my voice.
Let me see this world, dear Lord, as though I were looking through your eyes.
A world of men who don't want you, Lord, but a world for which you died.
Let me kneel with you in the garden, blur my eyes with tears of agony, for if once
I could see this world the way you see.
I just know I'd serve you more faithfully.
I need to go still further.
Third, I would say this.
We need to live beyond our means.
Boy, I want to be careful how I say that.
You have never met a tighter man than me.
I do not live beyond my means, but I do have faith.
And I ask God to increase my faith.
I love what Paul says in verse 15, not boasting of things without our measure, that is of
other men's labors, but having hope.
When your faith is increased, that we shall be enlarged by you according to our rule abundantly.
What is Paul saying?
Paul is writing this to a local church, and he's saying, you're my hope.
You're my hope.
The Sadarskis are here this morning.
We are their hope.
God has called them to go to Poland, a needy, needy, dark field.
It will be a hard, hard work.
They don't have the means to get there by themselves.
They are here because we are their hope.
And you know what they're praying?
They are praying that our faith is enlarged.
They're praying that our hearts are touched, that we see the need, that we look beyond
our comfort zone, that we look beyond our convenience, that we look beyond our own needs,
and we see a world, a world of people dying without Christ, not knowing the gospel.
And they are praying that our faith is enlarged.
Why?
So that we can support them to go to Poland to preach the gospel to people who need to
know Jesus Christ.
And Paul is saying, that's my prayer.
My prayer is that your faith is increased.
I would remind you that I think the Lord's favorite kind of giving is sacrificial giving.
I think the Lord loves it when His people see the needs of others and make a decision.
I will put my comfort aside.
I will put my convenience aside so that I can give so that their need can be met.
You say, why do you think the Lord loves that?
Well He proved it.
He gave His own Son.
He looked on our need and saw that there was no way that our need could be met other than
His Son coming and dying in our place, being the sacrifice for our sin, paying the penalty
for our sin, and then in a transaction that I won't fully understand until I get to heaven,
when I come to the cross and I believe what Jesus has done for me on the cross at Calvary,
and I ask Him through His work to be my Savior, my sin goes on Him and His righteousness comes
on me.
And when God looks at me, He no longer sees my sin.
He sees the righteousness of His Son, Jesus.
My goodness, Jesus gave His life for us, and then God looks at us as believers and says,
They have a need?
Is there any way that you would be sacrificial and meet their need?
There was a day when Jesus said to His disciples, let's go observe people giving.
That ought to sober us.
Let's go watch people give.
And they went down to the women's court of the temple, that's where the benevolence offerings
were given.
And it's very interesting, the boxes that were used were a box and it had a long metal
flute that opened up, and you would come by and you would drop your coins in and they
would rattle all the way down, and then the priests would come and take those and distribute
them to people that had great needs.
And it's there that Jesus stood with His disciples and He observed the people giving.
There was a custom, it's an ugly custom, but people who wanted to be seen and wanted to
be appreciated and praised who were giving large amounts would actually hire people to
run before them and even trumpeters to blow trumpets to gather a crowd so that they could
be observed in giving huge amounts.
And so, you know, like your pastor does.
And so they heard the trumpets blowing, they saw the people coming, the oors and the aars,
and men would come by and they would drop great amounts into these boxes and ooh, aahs,
the coins would tinkle down into the box and then after they were properly appreciated
they would pass off and all that was done and kind of in the trail of all this Jesus
notices a little lady.
And she's coming all by herself and there's no trumpets blowing and there's no oors and
aars.
As a matter of fact, nobody even cares that she's there because most people think, well,
she probably should be receiving from the box, not giving to the box, but she has two
mites and she drops those two mites into that box and Jesus says something to His disciples
that is absolutely shocking to Him.
He turns to them and He says, this little widow, she's given more than all the rest.
And the disciples look at, Lord, you saw the coins go in, you heard the noise that they
made and her little two mites barely made a tinkling sound as they went down.
There's no way she gave the most.
And then He explained a principle that you and I need to understand.
You see, she gave the most in this sense.
The men that came by gave out of their abundance.
What's that mean?
It means they gave what was comfortable to give.
They gave what they knew they could do without.
They gave what they knew they could replace.
They gave what was convenient to give.
And the difference between them and her was, Jesus says, she gave all she had.
Now the point is not the only way we please the Lord is to give all we have.
We can.
But the point is this.
The Lord loves and respects when people will say to themselves there's a greater need.
There's a greater good.
And even if it makes me a little bit uncomfortable, and even if it makes a little bit inconvenient,
to give to meet that need is greater in eternity and will be greater in my life than can be
imagined.
That's what I challenge you with this morning.
The Apostle Paul says go beyond.
Go beyond your measure.
God can bless and use us.
Have a vision for beyond your borders.
See that world.
Be brokenhearted for that world.
And then he says this, sacrifice.
Go beyond what is comfortable.
Go beyond what is convenient and you say, well, what will happen?
God will bless.
God will provide.
You see, too often I think we lead our lives timidly.
We offer only out of our abundance or that which is convenient to offer.
We truly love the Lord.
I'm not suggesting we don't,
and I think we even see the need.
It's just that bit too far.
One last, well, two last.
Never believe a preacher when he says finally.
There's seven more finales coming, but quickly.
My favorite story in the word of God
is Elijah and that widow.
And God says to Elijah, Elijah, I want you to leave,
I want you to go up, and this widow is going to sustain thee.
Now, can I tell you, in a Baptist preacher's heart,
and I am alluding to Elijah as a Baptist preacher,
we do not want to be sustained by widows.
We want to sustain widows.
And so this is a completely difficult situation,
but Elijah is told and Elijah obeys,
and Elijah goes up and knocks on the widow's door
and says, hey, the Lord has sent me,
and you're to take care of me,
and what do you got to eat?
That's the Edwards version.
And she says, well, to be honest with you, Mr. Prophet,
all I have is enough barrel in the meal
and enough oil in the cruise
to make my son and myself a little cake.
My plan was a good one.
We were going to eat those and die.
And Elijah says this, make me a cake first.
Could you have said it?
I mean, the words would have choked in my throat,
but it's what God told him to do.
Sometimes people will say to me,
you're preaching on giving, you're preaching on sacrifice.
I know, not because it's what I would choose to preach on,
it's because God put it in here.
And he says, make me a cake first.
And here is the most amazing part of the entire story.
She has the faith to do it.
And she makes that cake and sits down there,
and the Prophet sits down at that table.
And if you think it was hard for him
to ask her to make the cake,
now he eats it in front of them.
And then says, go make yourself a cake.
You just ate it.
She goes to that barrel.
And you know what's in it?
Enough.
Enough for her and her son.
You know what's in the cruise?
Enough oil.
Hey, you know what's there tomorrow?
Enough.
You know what's there the next day?
Now, if you knew my heart and how weak my faith was,
I would say to the Lord, would you just fill it up?
Every day I come back and there's enough.
I'm just saying to you that God loves
when people obey his word and are willing to sacrifice.
And then God, beyond their measure,
can work in their lives and do great things.
Great things.
Thousands of years later,
we're still talking about a lady
who had the faith to give what God wanted her to give.
And she never did without.
One last.
1904, a young man graduated from high school.
His name was William Borden.
And Borden, if you recognize that name,
if you're my age, you remember Elsie the cow.
And that was Elsie the cow of the great Borden dairy,
food, all that process and all that.
And William Borden was going to be the heir
to all of that business.
He was gonna be a very wealthy man.
As a graduation gift from high school,
his parents gave him a trip around the world.
That's what you got, isn't it?
Yeah, a trip around the world.
And his dad wanted to broaden his business horizons,
wanted him to really get a feel for what it would be
to be a tycoon of the world, you know.
And just a part of the story,
Mrs. Borden was a saved lady,
had taught her son the word of God, he knew the Lord.
And on this world tour,
instead of getting his visions for business broadened,
God called him to be a missionary.
And when he came home from the trip,
he told his dad, hey,
God has called me to the mission field.
He had seen a certain people while he was in China,
the Kanzu people, and God had laid a burden on his heart
to reach the Kanzu people.
Oh, his dad was upset.
I sent you to learn how to be a businessman.
He finally came to the place where he thought,
well, we're gonna send you to college,
you'll lose this silliness.
You'll understand that business is the way to go.
They sent him to Yale University, don't advise that now,
but back then, when he got there, he became an evangelist.
He started leading Bible studies,
led his roommates to the Lord,
founded the mission in New Haven,
leading people to the Lord.
He just never lost the fervor.
When he graduated, he followed through on his promise.
Now, one interesting thing, the Kanzu people,
though they lived in the Mongolia region,
were Arabic-speaking people.
And so to reach them, he had to learn the Arabic language.
And he, after graduation, went to Cairo to learn Arabic
so that he could go to Mongolia to reach these people
while in Cairo.
25 days after he was in Cairo,
he contracted spinal meningitis.
Today, it's a dangerous disease, but we can work with it.
We have antibiotics.
They didn't have antibiotics then that could do it,
or certainly not in Cairo.
30 days after he arrived in Cairo, he was dead.
Oh, the Chicago papers, what a waste!
Wasted life!
They found his Bible.
He was a journalist.
And in his Bible, this young man had written these words,
no reserves, no retreats, no regrets.
No regrets.
He had purposed to live his life in God's hands.
And though it did not pan out the way that he thought,
he gave his life for the cause of the Lord,
and he had no regrets.
With this, I'm done.
I lived 23 years without knowing the Lord.
I regret 23 years that were not given to the Lord
in my life.
I don't want to finish my life with regrets.
I wanna make the choices that God wants me to make.
I wanna do the work that God wants me to do.
I wanna be the man that God wants me to be,
because I don't wanna stand before the Lord and say,
ah, I knew what you laid on my heart,
but again, the songwriter would put it this way.
By and by, when I look on his face,
beautiful face, thorn-shadowed face,
by and by, when I look on his face,
I'll wish I had given him more,
more, so much more,
more of my life than I ever gave before.
By and by, when I look on his face,
I'll wish I'd given him more.
Nobody will stand there and say,
boy, do I regret getting that burden for missions.
man, do I regret being in that conference
and having my heart to,
boy, do I regret not taking more of the money that I had
and not giving it to the cause of missions,
but we could have gone to Disney World.
Nobody will say that.
All of us will wish we had given more,
we had done more, we had surrendered more,
we had lived for him more.
That's why moments like this are important.
When we make choices about who we will be,
how we will live, what we will give,
how will we allocate the resources
that he's so blessed us with,
no reserves, no retreats, no regrets.
Would you pray with me?
Father, we thank you for these few minutes you've given us
and we come to this moment of invitation
and we ask you to please make it clear to us
what you want us to do.
Lord, you have so blessed us abundantly.
And sometimes we turn our eyes away
from the needs of the world
when really you want us to look deeply.
God, would you touch our hearts
and would you help us to.
purpose this year to be more willing to sacrifice, more generous in our giving
for the needs of others? Would you help us to see that it's the example that you
set? God, I pray for those who are here that you would have them to lift up
their eyes and see the need. Maybe you're calling their life to be one of those
that go. Whatever it is, I pray that you would burden us to see beyond ourselves,
to go beyond ourselves, to be willing to be used of you in a great way, giving,
praying, going. I pray for that one here that may not know Christ as their Savior.
I pray, Lord, that you would help them to see that even today, if they will confess
their needindeed, we are sinners, we know itand that the provision of the
cross is there if they will call upon Jesus to be saved. For whosoever shall
call upon his name shall be saved. Lord, I pray you'd burden their heart. Now work
in us, change us, and help us to see it, I pray. Just before I conclude my prayer, I
wonder if there'd be one or two that would say, you know, Preacher, God has
spoken to my heart.