And if you look at the back of the bulletin, the title for the message this morning,
in Horeb, God made His greatness known.
God had worked miraculously and rewarded the faith of the parents of Moses.
We read that in Exodus chapter number 2.
It will not be the content of our message this morning,
but we understand that there were some difficult times
in which were taking place there in Egypt,
and the leadership of Pharaoh as a wicked man, and all that was taking place.
And God blessed and rewarded the faith of the parents of Moses,
and Moses was spared death, and Moses had the opportunity to be raised
there in the home of Pharaoh in just an amazing set of circumstances.
And then as you continue reading through the book of Exodus,
you'll find that through a series of events,
as we come to chapter number 3, he's ended up in Midian.
In fact, as you begin reading chapter number 3,
you'll note that the Bible tells us that he was at the backside of the mountain,
and he came to the mountain of God, even Horeb, the backside of the desert, excuse me.
Notice what it says there in verse number 1,
Now Moses kept the flock of Jethro his father-in-law, the priest of Midian,
and he led the flock to the backside of the desert,
and came to the mountain of God, even to Horeb.
Maybe sometimes you feel like, not physically,
but you feel like, emotionally, that you're on the backside of the desert.
You feel like it's a lonely place, a deserted place,
and you might feel like you're in that situation,
but we find, as we've used for the title this morning,
that in Horeb, God made his greatness known.
Before we dive into the passage of Scripture in Exodus chapter number 3,
I want you to jot down a couple of references, and I want to read the verses to you.
I'm not going to even turn there myself,
but in Psalm 106 and verse number 8,
listen to what the psalmist says.
The psalmist says this in Psalm 106 and verse number 8,
Nevertheless, he saved them for his namesake.
We must always recognize it's for God's namesake, it's for his glory,
but notice the last phrase of Psalm 106 and verse number 8.
It says this, that he might make his mighty power to be known.
I'm so thankful that he is all-powerful,
and I'm so thankful that he works,
and he has recorded for us in the pages of Scripture
his wonderful works, his acts,
and through those we find that he's made his mighty power to be known.
Then I want you to listen to the words of Moses
as they're found in Deuteronomy chapter 3 and verse number 24.
We find that as we're beginning to look here in Exodus chapter number 3,
that this is the beginning of really our introduction to Moses
and to the ministry that God would call him to.
Of course, we read of him in chapter 2 specifically.
The first time we begin reading of him is birth and all that takes place,
but really the interaction with God
and the work that God would have for Moses,
we begin here in chapter number 3.
But I want you to think about Moses at the end of his life.
In Deuteronomy chapter number 3, in verse number 24,
here's the testimony of Moses.
Listen to what he says.
Oh, Lord God, thou hast begun
to show thy servant thy greatness and thy mighty hand.
I want you to think about those words just for a moment.
I'll read the rest of the verse here in just a second,
but think about what he says.
Thou hast begun to show thy servant thy greatness and thy mighty hand.
Now, this is the same Moses that saw God do amazing things.
I mean, we read through the pages of Scripture
and the record of the life and ministry of Moses,
and we read of some amazing miracles of the power and might
and greatness of God on full display,
but Moses says, you've just begun to show me, I'm your servant,
you've just begun to show me thy greatness and thy mighty hand.
Why? Well, because God's greatness is unsearchable.
We know that the Lord is great.
It's our theme this year.
We've been preaching on the greatness of God
and how his greatness is revealed to us.
But I want you to understand that this morning,
I hope that you have a greater view of who God is today
than you did last week and that you did last month
and that we continue to see that he's greater than I even imagined.
And as we go through life and we draw closer to God,
we see that he's greater and he's greater.
But the reality is that his greatness is unsearchable.
He continues and says,
for what God is there in heaven or in earth
that can do according to thy works and according to thy might?
The answer is none.
All the false gods of the lands and all of those false deities that exist,
we find that there's none like our God, Jehovah God, the God of the Bible.
And I'm so thankful that God has revealed himself to us.
And as we think about the life of Moses
and we think about this place as he's in Horeb,
that God made his greatness known there in that place,
even as it's described as the backside of the desert.
I mean, he had fled.
You think about the circumstances that led to Moses being in this place.
But we find that God made his greatness known.
If you're taking notes this morning, notice with me, first of all, the great scene.
In verses 1 through 14, we see this great scene that God gives us insight to.
It tells us in verse number two,
And the angel of the Lord appeared unto him in a flame of fire out of the midst of a bush.
And he looked.
Behold, the bush burned with fire, and the bush was not consumed.
Verse three,
And Moses said, I will now turn aside, notice what he says,
and see this great sight, why the bush is not burnt.
We find that this great scene begins with this burning bush.
And Moses sees this bush is burning with fire.
And as it draws his attention, he notices that the bush, however, is not consumed.
No doubt he had seen a bush burn at some point in his life,
and no doubt he'd experienced that.
But he'd never experienced seeing a bush burn, but not being consumed.
And he says, I'm going to go figure out what's going on.
Let me, I will now turn aside and see this great sight, why the bush is not burned.
And this great scene that we see here begins in verse number four with a great encounter.
It's a great encounter. Notice the Bible tells us in verse number four,
And when the Lord saw that he turned aside to see,
God called unto him out of the midst of the bush and said, Moses, Moses.
Now, can you imagine?
I mean, I understand that for many of us, we're familiar with this passage of scripture.
But this morning, I want you to think about Moses.
He's on the backside of the desert. He's in Horeb.
He's taking care of this flock, and he's there, and he sees this burning bush.
And he says, well, that's kind of strange. It's kind of odd.
That bush is not consumed. I can tell that it's burning with fire, and fire consumes things.
Amen? That's what it does.
He says, I'm going to turn aside. I'm going to see what's going on here.
And as he comes over, God sees that he comes, and God calls him, Moses, out of the bush.
Can you imagine?
I mean, this is a great encounter.
And we find that the Bible says that Moses says, here am I.
Verse 5, and he said,
Draw not nigh hither.
Put off thy shoes from off thy feet.
For the place whereon thou standest is holy ground.
What made it holy? The presence of God.
Not Moses, not the bush, not even the place.
It was that God was there.
And God's presence in this place, that's why I call it a great encounter,
because Moses has this encounter with God.
No doubt he had heard from his mom as he was growing up,
and before she had to turn him back over to the daughter of Pharaoh to continue to raise,
she had heard, no doubt, about God and about the people of God.
And we find now, however, that he has this encounter with God,
and he's told to take his shoes off because the place was holy ground.
Moreover, verse 6, he says,
Moreover, he said, I am the God of thy father,
the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob.
And Moses hid his face, for he was afraid to look upon God.
He recognized in the presence of God.
What an encounter.
You know, I'm so thankful that we can enter into his presence.
The Bible says that in his presence is fullness of joy.
The Bible tells us that we're to come boldly into the throne of grace.
In fact, in that last verse of End Can It Be,
it sings about that boldly I approach the throne.
But it's not on our own merit that we can come boldly into the presence of God.
It's not because of any good thing in us.
No, it's because of the Lord Jesus Christ made a way.
He is the way, the truth, and the life.
And he said, no man cometh unto the Father but by me.
And we find that he made a way.
He's our great high priest.
He ever liveth to make intercession for us.
And when he was crucified,
that veil that separated the holy place from the holy of holies
was rent in twain from the top to the bottom,
granting access.
What a blessing.
And we find that Moses is here, what a great encounter.
But we find that the great encounter carries with it
as we continue to read, there's a great task.
I'm gonna skip down to verse number 10.
We'll come back to verse number seven
here in just a moment.
But I want you to note with me, in this great scene,
we see this great encounter, but we see a great task.
Notice in verse number 10, the Bible says,
"'Come now therefore,' notice what God says to Moses,
"'and I will send thee unto Pharaoh,
"'that thou mayest bring forth my people,
"'the children of Israel, out of Egypt.'"
This is a great task.
I mean, it's overwhelming as to the task
that God is assigning to Moses.
In fact, as we continue through the message this morning,
we'll see that there are some excuses
that are offered by Moses as to why
he cannot fulfill the task.
And as we think about this great task,
this great task that God has given to us this morning
that is mentioned to us in verse number 10,
I want us to be mindful of the fact
that God has given each of us a great task.
He's given us a task, not the task
that Moses had to bring his people out of Egypt,
but we find that he's given us the task
of taking the glorious gospel to a lost and dying world,
to a people that are dead in their sins
and in their trespasses, to a people that are bound
in their sin, a people that many times have no idea.
Many have not heard the name of Jesus
in the context of the scriptural understanding
of who Jesus is.
So often as you read the book of Acts,
you find that the comment will be made
specifically with Paul, how he would speak.
Peter says it as well, that he presents Jesus as the Christ.
And what is the significance of that?
Well, they knew the man Jesus,
the people that they're writing to,
the people that they're ministering to,
they were aware.
Remember, he says these things were not done in a corner.
You're aware of this, you've seen this,
you're witnesses of these things.
Speaking of the miracles of Jesus
and the life and ministry of Jesus,
but he says this Jesus, this man that you know,
he's the Christ, he's the God man,
he's the Messiah, he is God in flesh.
There's some people that know about Jesus in our society,
but they don't know the Jesus of the Bible.
What a great task that God has given us
to be his ambassadors, his representatives,
to take that glorious message, Jesus saves.
What a blessed truth.
We find that as we look here,
there's not only a great encounter and a great task,
but there's a great promise.
In verse number eight, notice what the Bible says.
It says this, and I am come down to deliver them,
his children, out of the hand of the Egyptians,
and to bring them up out of that land
unto a good land and a large
and unto a land flowing with milk and honey.
Who's gonna continue unto the place of the Canaanites
and the Hittites and the Amorites,
the Perizzites and the Hivites and the Jebusites.
But notice with me in verse number eight,
God had given, we read in verse number 10,
I kind of have gone in a different sequence
for purpose of getting to the point this morning,
but we find that God has commissioned,
has given this great task to Moses in verse number 10,
but who is it that's going to actually do the work?
It's God.
God says in verse number eight,
when we think about this great promise, he says,
I am come down to deliver them
out of the hand of the Egyptians.
It is God that is going to do the delivering.
And I think about this truth
as we make some parallels this morning
in our own lives and our own responsibilities to God,
that he's given us a great task,
but he's not told us to save anyone.
You know why?
We can't.
I can't save anyone.
You can't save anyone.
You know who does the saving?
Jesus Christ, the savior of the world.
Paul says, this is a faithful saying
and worthy of all acceptation
that Christ Jesus came into the world
to save sinners of whom I am chief.
When he says that it's a faithful saying,
it's a true saying.
This is the purpose.
Jesus says himself, I am come to seek and to save
that which is lost.
I'm so thankful that, listen,
I'm thankful we don't have to do the saving.
God says some plant, some water,
but God gives the increase.
It was not Moses that was gonna deliver
the children of Israel from the hand of Pharaoh
and from the Egyptians.
It was God that was going to do that,
but God was going to use a man.
Isn't that interesting?
Let me ask you this.
Could God have delivered the children of Israel
from Egypt without Moses?
I mean, he could have just caused an earthquake
to take place and consume all of those Egyptians
and then, man, the people are free to go,
but he chose to use a man.
That's very similar today.
God chooses to use us.
I don't fully understand why he would use us,
but honestly, it's amazing that he would use us.
They would give us and trust to us the gospel
and then tell us, go and tell them.
It's not your job to save them.
It's just your job to tell them.
What a joy, what a blessing, what a privilege.
Not only we think about the great promise
that God says I am come to deliver them,
but notice with me in verse number 12.
Notice the second aspect of this great promise.
God says this, certainly I will be with thee.
Aren't you so thankful for the presence of God?
God says to Moses,
I'm gonna deliver the children of Israel.
By the way, I'm sending you to do it,
to be the man that I'm going to use,
and I'm gonna send you to Pharaoh,
but I want you to know that I'm gonna be with you.
Wow.
Reminds me of the promise of Matthew 28,
verses 18 and 20.
He said that we're to go into all the world
and preach the gospel, right?
And he tells us there in that passage of scripture,
I am with thee, I am with thee.
What a joy and what a blessing to know
that as we go to seek to fulfill this great task
that God has given us,
that we have this promise that it's God
that does the saving,
and it's God that's promised to be with us.
I'm not alone.
I have God with me.
What a blessing.
But I want you to notice in this great scene,
and probably what makes it such a great scene
is our great God.
Our great God.
Notice with me how God reveals himself to Moses
in this portion of scripture.
The Bible tells us initially in verse number six
that he says to him,
I am the God of thy father, the God of Abraham,
the God of Isaac, the God of Jacob.
And Moses hit his face for he was afraid to look upon God.
And as God continues to reveal himself to Moses,
notice what he says to him in verse number seven.
The Lord said, I have surely seen the affliction
of my people, which are in Egypt
and have heard their cry by reason of their taskmasters,
for I know their sorrows.
I want you to notice from verse number seven
that God is speaking to Moses in the past tense.
In other words, he's speaking to Moses
about what he knew took place.
And we find that God in making it known to Moses
in this fashion, I believe,
that God is revealing to Moses that he's eternal.
He's the God of the past, he's the God of the present,
and he's the God of the future.
He has no beginning and no ending.
I am alpha and omega is what God says.
And we find that as we look at this portion of scripture
that God says to Moses,
I have surely seen the affliction of my people,
which are in Egypt.
I have heard their cry.
Listen, I'm thankful that God knows.
I'm thankful that God knows.
I'm thankful that he's eternal.
Notice as we continue reading, he says,
and I am come down to deliver them.
He's heard what took place in days and in time before,
but he says, I am come down now.
He's the God of the present.
And then he says, to deliver them, future tense.
God can speak authoritatively about the future
because God holds the future in his hand.
He knows all things.
See, God is outside of time.
We are bound by time.
Everything is time, time, time, time, time.
I'm running out of time this morning.
I'm gonna borrow from Brother Lennon from last week.
I was joking with some people about that.
Man, he got done.
I said, I'm not even on my second point by now.
What's going on, you know?
And don't get used to it, amen?
But your roast wasn't even done last week when you got home.
You know what I'm saying?
I mean, it was so early.
But look, he's the God of the past,
the present, and the future.
God's revealing this to Moses.
See, Moses is having this encounter with God.
And what makes it such a great scene
is that God is revealing himself to Moses.
I said, I've titled in Horeb, God Made His Greatness Known.
And God is revealing to Moses that he is the eternal God.
He is the God of the past, the present, and the future.
I want you to notice that he says.
In verse number 14, let me back up in verse number 12 as he says,
I will certainly be with thee, and this shall be a token unto thee that I have sent thee,
when thou hast brought forth the people out of Egypt, ye shall serve God upon this mountain.
Notice in verse number 13, Moses said unto God,
Behold, when I come unto the children of Israel, and shall say unto them,
The God of your fathers hath sent me unto you, and they shall say to me,
What is his name?
What shall I say unto them?
Oh, verse 14, what a precious verse.
And God said unto Moses,
I am that I am.
And he said, Thus shalt thou say unto the children of Israel,
I am hath sent me unto you.
This is, we'd often refer to as God's proper name, if you will, Jehovah.
Jehovah. He's Jehovah God.
And he reveals himself to Moses,
I am that I am.
Tell them, I am hath sent thee unto them, or sent me unto you.
We find that this word, this proper name of God, Jehovah, the great I am,
it carries with it the idea, helps us understand,
that he is the self-existent one.
He has no beginning and no end.
He's the self-existent one.
I'm mindful of what Jesus said,
as he's interacting with the religious leaders in John chapter number 8.
And as he's interacting with those religious leaders,
and they're questioning him and saying,
We don't know who you are, but we know who Abraham,
and we know who Moses, and we'd be the followers of them, and so on and so forth.
And Jesus is graciously interacting with them.
At the end of the text of the scripture, he says,
Before Abraham was, I am.
Wow. What a powerful declaration.
Understanding that Jesus is God.
And we find here that in verse number 14,
this truth of our great God and how he's revealed himself to Moses,
and we see this great scene.
As we continue studying here through this portion of scripture,
I want you to see not only the first thought here of this great scene,
but number two, if you're taking notes, three great signs.
Three great signs.
Notice in verse number 15, God said moreover unto Moses,
Thus shalt thou say unto the children of Israel,
The Lord God of your fathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac,
and the God of Jacob, hath sent me unto you.
This is my name forever, and this is my memorial unto all generations.
Go, and gather the elders of Israel together, and say unto them,
The Lord God of your fathers, the God of Abraham, of Isaac, and of Jacob,
appeared unto me, saying, I have surely visited you,
and seen that which is done to you in Egypt.
And I have said, I will bring you up out of the affliction of Egypt,
unto the land of the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Amorites, the Perizzites,
the Hivites, and the Jebusites, unto a land flowing with milk and honey.
And they shall hearken to thy voice, and thou shalt come,
thou and the elders of Israel, unto the king of Egypt.
And ye shall say unto him, The Lord God of the Hebrews hath met with us.
And now let us go, we beseech thee, three days' journey into the wilderness,
that we may sacrifice to the Lord our God.
Notice verse 19.
And I am sure that the king of Egypt will not let you go.
No, not by a mighty hand.
God, again, knows the future. He knows what's going to happen.
There's a difficulty, I think, about Moses
and some of the excuses that he offers in the next several,
in chapter number four as we begin to continue looking here.
We find that God said, Pharaoh's not going to let you go.
No, not by a mighty hand.
But notice what he says, and I will stretch out my hand
and smite Egypt with all my wonders,
which I will do in the midst thereof.
And after that, he will let you go.
God begins to show his greatness to Moses here in Horeb.
We find in Egypt, he's going to continue to demonstrate his great power.
In verse 21, it says,
I will give this people favor in the sight of the Egyptians,
and it shall come to pass that when you go, you shall not go empty,
but every woman shall borrow of her neighbor and her that sojourneth in her house
jewels of silver, jewels of gold, and raiment.
You shall put them upon your sons and upon your daughters,
and you shall spoil the Egyptians.
Notice the excuses begin, and think about this truth of these three great signs.
Beginning in verse number one of chapter four,
the Bible says that Moses answered and said,
But behold, they will not believe me, nor hearken unto my voice.
For they will say, The Lord hath not appeared unto thee.
Moses was concerned that the people would not believe him.
The people would not believe that God had appeared to him.
The people would not believe that God had given him this message.
And we find that Moses begins this objection,
and we find that the Lord answers him in verse number two
and gives us this first of three great signs.
Notice what it says, the Lord said unto him,
What is that in thine hand?
And he said, A rod.
I want you to think about this.
God will use us for his glory if we surrender.
Somebody said this years ago, preacher of yesteryear,
God's not looking for ability but for availability.
God will equip those who are willing to be used for his honor, for his glory.
His strength is made perfect in weakness.
You know, the best place for us to be as the people of God is to say,
I'm just not able.
Because then we're most dependent.
Without me you can do nothing is what Jesus said.
The danger comes in the life of a believer when we think,
I got this, I can handle this.
God says, you need me.
The songwriter said, I need thee every hour.
I've often made the comment about that song,
and I don't seek to criticize the songwriter,
but the reality is I need him every second of every minute of every hour.
Without him we can do nothing.
We're but dust. We're frail.
But he is mighty.
And God says to Moses, what's in your hand?
He said, a rod.
Notice what God does this first sign, the rod of Moses.
In verse number three it says that he said,
And he cast it on the ground and it became a serpent.
And Moses did exactly what I would do.
And Moses fled from before it.
He had some wisdom, didn't he?
Can you imagine taking that rod and throwing it on the ground and it becomes a serpent?
I mean, this is his rod.
Right?
This isn't a rod that he went and picked up somewhere.
God didn't say, go over there and pick up that rod and then it became a serpent.
He said, what's in your hand is his rod.
By the way, you know what a shepherd had?
He had a staff, a rod.
It's what they carried with them.
So this is what he had.
And God said, take that and throw it on the ground and he does.
Thank God for his obedience.
I mean, just immediately obeyed.
And then he flees from it.
And again, I'm with Moses.
And I have a hard time with verse number four.
I'm just honest with you.
The Bible says that the Lord said unto Moses, put forth thine hand and take it by the tail.
Lord, you want me to do what?
I'm just being transparent with you.
I would have had a really, really hard time with this.
I hate snakes.
Terrible.
He says, go and take it by the tail.
Again, what does Moses do?
The Bible says he put forth his hand and caught it.
And it became a rod in his hand.
I know that we're familiar with this.
Can you imagine?
I mean, God's making his greatness known.
He says to Moses, take that rod that's in your hand and throw it down.
And now it becomes a serpent.
And you pick it up again and it becomes a rod.
God's making his greatness known.
God says this in verse number five, that they may believe that the Lord God of their fathers,
the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, hath appeared unto thee.
And then the Lord says this, furthermore unto him, put now thine hand into thy bosom.
This is the second of these great signs.
He says, put now thy hand into thy bosom.
And he put his hand into his bosom.
Now again, Moses is obedient immediately.
God says, put your hand in.
And the Bible says that when he took it out, behold, his hand was leprous as snow.
You know what your hand looks like.
He put it in, it was fine.
Brings it out and it's leprous as snow.
Wow.
Verse seven, he said, put thine hand into thy bosom again.
He put his hand into his bosom again and plucked it out of his bosom.
And behold, it was turned again as his other flesh.
Isn't that amazing?
It's amazing.
God's given him these three great signs.
The rod, his hand.
Leprous, puts it in again, brings it out and it's whole.
number 8, the Bible says, and it shall come to pass, if they will not believe thee, neither
hearken to the voice of the first sign, that they will believe the voice of the latter
sign.
And then he gives them a future sign, then we look at these two that God gave him immediately
here in this objection when he said, the people aren't going to believe me or hearken unto
me.
And God gives them the sign of the rod and of his hand.
And then in verse number 9, he tells them this, and it shall come to pass if they will
not believe also these two signs, neither hearken unto thy voice, that thou shalt take
of the water of the river.
So now he's talking about the water at the Nile when he'd go to Egypt, and he tells them
that you take the water of the river and pour it upon the dry land, and the water which
thou takest out of the river shall become blood upon the dry land.
Wow.
We know the plagues, the water turned to blood, and we see that God's giving this third sign
that we see here.
And the Bible says that Moses, even after hearing these things, he said unto the Lord
in verse number 10, O my Lord, I am not eloquent neither heretofore nor since thou hast spoken
unto thy servant, but I am slow of speech and of a slow tongue.
The Lord said unto him, what a great question, who hath made man's mouth?
Who hath made man's mouth?
What's the answer?
God.
He's the creator.
Or who maketh the dumb or deaf or the seeing or the blind?
Have not I the Lord?
And he says, now therefore, go.
Now therefore, go, and I will be with thy mouth and teach thee what thou shalt say.
Moses, as he continues to have some struggles here, we find that there's these signs that
have been given, the rod in his hand, and then God promises them that if they don't
believe you for those things, you take some of that water from the river there, the Nile,
and you pour it out, and it will become blood on the land.
We find that though in the midst of some struggles, we find that Moses goes.
Notice in verse number 18, the Bible says that Moses went and returned to Jethro, his
father-in-law, and said unto him, let me go.
I pray thee and return unto my brethren, which are in Egypt, and see whether they be
yet alive.
And Jethro said unto Moses, go in peace.
That was the first step for Moses.
Before he would ever stand before Pharaoh and say, let my people go, he had to stand
before his father-in-law and say, let me go.
He stood before his father-in-law, Jethro, and he said, let me go.
He told him where he was going to go and why he was going to go, and we see that Moses
is given the answer from Jethro, go in peace.
I want you to notice at the end of verse number 20, the Bible tells us that Moses took the
rod of God in his hand.
God had given him that instruction in verse number 17.
He said, and thou shalt take this rod in thine hand, wherewith thou shalt do signs.
Take the rod.
I love how verse number 20 refers to it as the rod of God in his hand.
We find that Moses, and we'll skip down just a few verses for sake of time, we find that
as you come to verse number 28, the Bible says that Moses told Aaron all the words of
the Lord who had sent him and all the signs which he had commanded him.
And Moses and Aaron went and gathered together all the elders of the children of Israel,
and Aaron spake all the words which the Lord had spoken unto Moses.
Notice it says, and did the signs in the sight of the people, and the people believed.
Isn't that a precious four-word statement?
People believed.
Those signs that God gave, these three signs that we're speaking of, they were impactful
in the lives of the people.
They believed.
And notice it says, and when they heard that the Lord had visited the children of Israel
and that he had looked upon their affliction, then they bowed their heads and worshipped.
What a great response to what they had understood.
Now for those of you that are familiar with the portion of the book of Exodus that we're
looking at here, you understand that things did not immediately just turn good and man,
they just were released and they went.
No, they faced some real difficulty.
In fact, Moses gives the testimony that since I've come to Pharaoh that you've not delivered
this people.
In fact, it's just become worse for the people.
There's a responsibility to obey.
See God began here in Horeb.
Moses made the statement at the end of his life, O Lord God, thou hast begun to show
thy servant thy greatness in thy mighty hand.
And we've got to think about Moses and his life and all the way back here in this first
encounter that he has with God in Horeb.
And how God in Horeb made his greatness known to his servant.
There's a burning bush, this encounter that God reveals to us where this great scene and
this burning bush and it's burning with fire but it's not consumed and through that series
of events as we've looked at, God makes himself known to Moses and he gives a task but he
promises to be with him.
God gives him these signs.
God begins to reveal his greatness to Moses.
Moses goes on as we would look at his life and its totality.
We see that Moses, many of us would say is a great hero of the faith.
Begin to think about Moses and you talk about people that have Bible characters that become
favorites and if there was one Bible character to be your favorite, for some Moses would
be on their list.
But it all started in Horeb when God made his greatness known.
This morning, God wants to make his greatness known to you.
He wants to reveal to you who he is through the pages of this book.
He wants you to know who he is.
He wants you to know that he is the great God, he is Jehovah God, the self-existent
one, the God of the past, the present and the future.
He wants you to know that he is the savior of the world.
He wants you to know that he's giving you a task and you begin to think about all of
these things and how God reveals his greatness to us and what's our response to that?
Our response to God revealing his greatness ought to be obedience.
We understand that Moses, just as we could relate to, he's got some difficulties there
but God, they're not going to listen but God, I'm not eloquent and so on and so forth and
certainly there are times in which we too offer excuses to God but at the end of the
day Moses was obedient.
Moses went to Jethro and said, let me go.
And Jethro says, go in peace.
And then Moses goes and he meets Aaron and they meet with the elders and they call the
people and they tell him.
Praise the Lord.
But what caused him to go was that God revealed his greatness to him in Horeb.
Because of this encounter with God that we read of in this portion of Scripture in Exodus
chapter number 3, it changed the course of Moses' life.
No longer would Moses be on the backside of the desert but Moses would now and over the
next several, I mean, pages of Scripture.
Who is it that we look to over and over and over as the human leader that God would use?
Moses.
Wow.
God revealed his greatness and Moses responded in obedience.
I thought of this as we were singing that song this morning, And Can It Be, I mentioned
this a little bit even yesterday during our men's prayer breakfast, you know, when we
truly understand all that our God has done for us, all that he is to us, our response
ought to be one of obedience.
And can it be?
Amazing love, how can it be?
That thou, my God, shouldst die for me.
But what's my response to that?
When he's revealed to me his greatness that I live for him, that I live for him in obedience.
And we read in the life of Moses over chapters and chapters of God's Word all that God would
use him to do and how God would continue to reveal his greatness to him, but it started
in Horeb when God made his greatness known.
This morning, I hope you see God in all of his glory, hope you see God for who he is.
He's a great God, greatly to be praised, and he is deserving of my everything.
What's in your hand, God, you can have it, you can have it.
God just wants us to surrender to him.
If you've never been saved, if you've not trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as your personal
Savior, let me say as Paul said, today is the day of salvation.
Jesus Christ is the Savior of the world.
We talked about the task that he's given to us as his people, those that have already
been saved.
We sang the first song, are you washed in the blood?
What does it mean to be washed in the blood?
It means to be saved.
I can't save myself, not by works of righteousness, which we have done.
According to His mercy He hath begotten us, for by grace we are saved through faith, and
that not of works is the gift of God, not of works lest any man should boast."
Jesus said, I am the way, the truth, and the life.
No man cometh unto the Father but by Me.
This morning, if you can say, I've been washed in the blood, and I hope you can, then let's
live for Jesus.
Be willing to do whatever He's called us to do.
Lord, I'm yours, because you've showed me your greatness.
If you've not been washed in the blood, you do not have 100% confidence.
If you deny today that heaven is your home, you say, Pastor, I'm trying to do the best
I can.
I have people tell me that all the time.
In fact, just a couple of weeks ago, I had somebody say, I'm doing good.
I said, what happens if your good isn't good enough?
He said, well, I'll do better.
That's what he said to me.
I said, what happens if better isn't good enough?
He said, well, I'll do whatever is better than better.
That's what he said.
I said, the reality is this.
We're not redeemed with corruptible things, but with the precious blood of Christ.
The only payment for your sin and for my sin is the blood of Christ, and it's sufficient.
It satisfies the demands of a holy God.
If you've not been saved today, today is the day of salvation.
If you've been saved, let's live for Jesus.
Let's see Him in His greatness, as Moses did, and say, Lord, I'll go.
I don't know how I'm going to do it, but you promised to be with me, and you actually promised
to do the work, and God, just use me.
I'm just yielded and surrendered.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for your precious word.
We thank you for the life of Moses.
As we think about his life, we thank you, God, for this event, this encounter that is
recorded in Exodus chapter number 3, the record of where you in Horeb made your greatness
known to your servant.
God, we're thankful that you're a great God.
We thank you that you do all things well.
God, if there's one present this morning, one that's tuned in via live stream that's
never been saved, they've never trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as their personal savior,
they do not have 100% confidence that heaven is their home, oh, God, I pray that you'd
move and work in their hearts and lives this morning.
I pray, God, that you would convict them of their own sin, of Christ's righteousness and
of judgment to come.
God, I pray for every believer that's here this morning.
I pray, Lord, that you would stir us up.
Lord, that we'd see you in all of your greatness.
Like Moses, we would be surrendered and yielded, that we'd go.
Lord, that we'd be willing.
I pray that you'd use us, God, for your glory.
Would you move and work in these few moments of invitation?
Have your way, Lord, for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me as our custom is at the end of our service, we have an opportunity
for you to respond.
If you're not sure of heaven, we'd love to take a Bible and show you how you can know
for sure that heaven is your home.
Maybe the Lord just spoke to your heart in some particular way this morning through his
word and you just want to come and pray and ask God to help you.
There's a specific need, something specific that God dealt with.
As Kate plays, the altar is open.