number 21, John chapter number 21 this evening, and we'll use this passage of Scripture as
a springboard into our message this evening.
I said 21, sorry, John chapter number 20, John chapter number 20, and look with me,
if you will, at verses 28 and 29, John chapter number 20 and verses 28 and 29, and the context
in which we're dealing with in this particular portion of Scripture is after the resurrection
of the Lord Jesus Christ, and He, of course, made Himself known, He appeared to many, and
the Bible tells us in verse number 19 of John chapter number 20 that the same day evening,
being the first day of the week when the doors were shut, where the disciples were assembled
for fear of the Jews, came Jesus and stood in the midst and saith unto them, Peace be
unto you.
We find that Thomas was not there, according to verse number 24, the Bible says, but Thomas,
one of the 12, called Didymus, was not with them when Jesus came.
And they told them, they told Thomas about seeing the Lord, and he said that he would
not believe, and so on and so forth, but you find that in verse number 26, it says, and
after eight days again, His disciples were within, and Thomas with them, then came Jesus,
the doors being shut, and stood in the midst and said, Peace be unto you.
Then saith He to Thomas, Reach thither thy finger, and behold My hands, and reach hither
thy hand, and thrust it into My side, and be not faithless, but believing.
The text that I wanted to use this evening is our springboard here in verses 28 and 29.
Notice what Thomas says in verse number 28, and Thomas answered and said unto Him, My
Lord and my God.
Jesus saith unto him, Thomas, because thou hast seen Me, thou hast believed.
Blessed are they that have not seen, and yet have believed.
Last week, we examined Matthew chapter number 16, and we looked at that question that Jesus
asked the disciples, Whom do men say that I am?
And of course, we looked at that passage of Scripture, and I mentioned this last week,
that the question that was asked by Jesus to the disciples is just as important today
as it's ever been.
The confusion of the people that we find in Matthew chapter number 16, remember the disciples
say, well, some think that you're John the Baptist, or Isaiah, or Jeremiah, or one of
the prophets, and there was confusion amongst the people with regard to who Jesus is, who
He was, and we find that that confusion still exists today.
We understand that Paul said to the believers there in Corinth in 2 Corinthians chapter
number 4 that the God of this world hath blinded the minds of them which believe not, and we
have the responsibility of preaching the gospel and giving the gospel, and we understand that
we must know who Christ is, but we must be able to speak to those that we come into contact
with with regard to who is Jesus.
We understood that though there was confusion amongst the people, that Peter answered with
great confidence, and he proclaimed, thou art the Christ, the Son of the living God.
And what a powerful declaration that we see by Peter in that text of Scripture.
And I think about this as I see Thomas' response in verse number 28, when Thomas says, my Lord
and my God.
And when we understand who Jesus is, when we study the doctrine of Christ as we've entered
into as of last Wednesday evening, and we think about the person of Christ and who He
is, God in flesh, if I were to title the message this evening, and I'm sure it's going to be
a two-part message, I would simply entitle it this, Jesus is all the world to me.
And there's a song with that title, Jesus is all the world to me, and the songwriter
said this, Jesus is all the world to me, my life, my joy, my all.
He is my strength from day to day, without Him I would fall.
When I am sad, to Him I go, no other one can cheer me so.
When I am sad, He makes me glad, He's my friend.
Jesus is all the world to me, my friend in trial sore.
I go to Him for blessings, and He gives them o'er and o'er.
He sends the sunshine and the rain, He sends the harvest, golden grain.
Sunshine and rain, harvest of grain, He's my friend.
Jesus is all the world to me, and true to Him I'll be.
Oh, how could I this friend deny, when He's so true to me.
Following Him I know I'm right, He watches o'er me day and night.
Following Him by day and night, He's my friend.
Jesus is all the world to me, I want no better friend.
I trust Him now, I trust Him when life's fleeting days shall end.
Beautiful life with such a friend, beautiful life that has no end.
Eternal life, eternal joy, He's my friend.
And I would echo what the songwriter said in that song that I just read.
Jesus is all the world to me, I'm so thankful.
The word of God reveals to us who Jesus is, and
that we have been privileged as believers to be in a place where
someone at some point brought the gospel to us.
Whether you're the first believer in your family or
whether your parents were introduced to the gospel or your grandparents or
however far you dig down, someone brought the gospel to your family.
And you have the privilege of knowing through this precious book who Jesus is.
And what a blessing because there are countless numbers of people around
the globe that are blinded with regard to the question, who is Jesus, who is He?
Not only are those that are blinded, but we find that in a world where there are
over 7 billion people, a percentage of them have never
even heard the name of Jesus, yet even hearing the gospel.
And how privileged we are, and we find that Thomas is my Lord and my God.
Jesus says, because thou hast seen me, thou hast believed.
And then think of this, the latter part of verse number 29.
Blessed are they that have not seen and yet have believed.
I've not seen him, but I believe the record that he has given us, and
I am so thankful for the word of God.
Why is it that Jesus is all the world to me?
Well, I'm sure there's plenty of answers that we could give to that question, but
I've tried to categorize it into five particular areas this evening.
And I know that I won't get through all of them, so
this will be a multi-part series, but let's look at this.
Number one, why is Jesus all the world to me?
Because of who he is, because of who he is.
He's God, he's God in the flesh.
We think about this, look over in John chapter number one, and
we'll be all over the scriptures this evening.
And looking at a number of portions, and seeing what the word of God tells us.
Notice in John chapter number one, a very familiar portion of scripture.
In verse number one, the Bible says, in the beginning was the word, and
the word was with God, and the word was God.
The same was in the beginning with God.
All things were made by him, and
without him was not anything made that was made.
You notice in verse number 14, the Bible says, and
the word was made flesh and dwelt among us.
And we beheld his glory.
The glory is of the only begotten of the Father, full of grace and truth.
Look at the book of Philippians, if you will, in chapter number two.
Philippians chapter number two, and
look at verses five through 11 of this portion of scripture.
Philippians chapter number two, beginning in verse number five.
Let this mind be in you, which was also in Christ Jesus,
who being in the form of God, thought it not robbery to be equal with God, but
made himself of no reputation, and took upon him the form of a servant,
was made in the likeness of men.
Being found in fashion as a man, he humbled himself, and
became obedient unto death, even the death of the cross.
Wherefore, God also hath highly exalted him, and
given him a name which is above every name.
The name of Jesus, every knee should bow of things in heaven, and
things in earth, and things under the earth.
And every tongue should confess that Jesus Christ is Lord,
to the glory of God the Father.
In the book of Hebrews, and of course,
we studied through the book of Hebrews this calendar year.
But we find that in Hebrews chapter number two,
that the Bible tells us how that the Lord Jesus Christ,
he came in the seed of Abraham.
It says in verse number 16 of Hebrews 2, for
verily he took not on him the nature of angels, but
he took on him the seed of Abraham.
And so we begin to understand this evening who he is.
We understand the answer that Peter gave to that question that was asked last week.
Whom do men say that I am?
And we find that there were some that said John the Baptist, and
others that were given as answers.
And Peter says, thou art the Christ, after Jesus then says, but
whom say ye that I am?
Thou art the Christ, the son of the living God.
And we find the word of God teaches us we could read about, study the incarnation,
and understanding even the portions of scripture that we've just read.
But when we consider who he is, we must consider his humanity.
The humanity, he took upon himself the form of a man.
He came in the likeness of men, put upon himself the form of a servant,
came in the likeness of men.
And so we think about his humanity, we could ask this question,
how do we know what evidence do we have with regard to the humanity of Christ?
In Matthew chapter number four, in verse number two,
the Bible tells us that he was hungry.
We find that, of course, it was after the
the time of fasting and the Bible says and when he had fasted 40 days and 40
nights he was afterward and hungered the Bible tells us in the book of John in
the fourth chapter you remember the situation where he said that he must
needs go through Samaria and he meets the woman at the well and in John
chapter 4 verses 6 & 7 the Bible tells us that he was thirsty we find that
Jesus in Mark chapter number 4 he's in the ship and the Bible says that he was
asleep in the in the hinder part the the back part of the ship why he was
tired and so we see those revelations to us in the Gospels with regard to the
humanity of Christ that he was a man and he had to come in the likeness of men so
that he could die in our place so that he could provide the sacrifice that
would be acceptable for our redemption so we see his humanity but we also see
his deity and just as we'd say that he was tired remember when he woke up as
they came and they were the disciples were just concerned and I see them kind
of rushing in and saying master carest thou not that we perish what does he do
he goes out and he rebukes the wind and the waves and says peace be still and
there's a calm and he demonstrates his power we think about the truth if you
would turn to the book of Mark chapter number two and notice with me I don't
have time to read the entirety of the portion of Scripture but in this passage
of Scripture we find that Jesus in thinking about considering not only his
humanity but his deity that he is God that he forgave sin we referenced this
portion briefly a few weeks ago but you'll understand that Jesus was there
and he told this man that thy sins be forgiven in verse number five this was
the man that his friends were concerned about his condition he was one that was
sick of the palsy and they brought him in through the roof because there were
so many people they couldn't get in and Jesus saw them and saw this man and said
thy sins be forgiven thee and those that were sitting around those religious
leaders the scribes in particular in verse number seven they say this who can
forgive sins but God only who can forgive sins but God only you know I
can't forgive you of your sins you can't forgive me of my sin but God is
the one that forgives we find that throughout the Old Testament we find the
reference that our God is ready to pardon ready to forgive with thee there
is forgiveness and what a blessing to understand that we find in first John
chapter number one that if we confess our sins that he is faithful and just to
forgive right to cleanse us from all unrighteousness and what a blessing to
understand they say who can forgive sins but God only and so Jesus says at the
end of verse number eight why reason you these things in your hearts and then
as he's there talking in verse number ten he says that you may know that the
Son of Man hath power on earth to forgive sins he sayeth to the sick of
the palsy I say unto thee arise and take up thy bed and go thy way into thine
house and immediately in verse number twelve that man arose took up his bed
and went forth the Bible says that they were all amazed and glorified God saying
we never saw it on this fashion and so he forgave sins why because he's God we
see his deity we see that he raised the dead of course we could look at a few
examples in the Gospels my mind races to the one that's probably the most
familiar to us in John the the Gospel of John in chapter 3 11 you remember that
Lazarus was sick and we look at the passage of Scripture we find that he
Jesus was made aware of the sickness of Lazarus and he comes and they were
saying things such as this if you would been here if you would have been here my
brother wouldn't have died they believed that Jesus was able to heal Lazarus of
his sickness why well there were many that were healed throughout the life and
ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ the disciples had witnessed those things and
Jesus here did not go he tarried his departure there was a delay in his
leaving why for the glory of God for the work for the fact that he says to the
disciples early in the passage that they would would be just encouraged that they
would grow in their faith he says that he was glad for their sakes that they
were that he was not there to the intent that you may believe and not only did
Mary and Martha understand that if Jesus had been there he could have
healed Lazarus but there were some that were gathered there that were Jews that
were lamenting the death of Lazarus and after Jesus wept these Jews say it's
recorded in verse number 37 they say amongst themselves could not this man
which opened the eyes of the blind have caused that even this man should not
have died the miracle that had taken place back in John chapter number nine
with regard to the healing of the man that was born blind was fresh on the
minds of these Jewish people and they say after Jesus wept they said well if
he had been here I mean he healed the man that was born blind certainly he had
the power to have healed this man so that he did not die but Jesus purposed
and he did not go to heal him why because he was gonna raise him from the
dead he'd been dead for four days you remember the response the pushback if
you will that was received when he said that they should move the stone and you
find that he says take away the stone in verse number 39 and there's just a level
of objection if you will for Martha when she says by this time he stinketh he had
been dead four days but Jesus will proclaim in verse number 43 with a loud
voice Lazarus come forth the Bible tells us that he that was dead came forth
bound hand and foot with grave clothes and his face was bound about with a
napkin Jesus saith unto them loose him and let him go Wow what an amazing truth
of the Word of God we find that there were many that responded in believing
because of what they had seen and we think about this why is Jesus all the
world to me because of who he is he's God we see his humanity throughout the
Gospels we see his deity that he is God in flesh notice with me not only because
of who he is but because of his mighty power think about the power of Christ we
understand as we read the Word of God and we've mentioned about the attributes
of God that our God is omnipotent that he has all power the Lord God omnipotent
reigneth and what a blessing to read through the Word of God and to see the
power of God demonstrated and of course it's declared for us many times we see
during the life and ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ of his great power his
mighty power I'll list a number of things we see number one his power over
demons look in the book of Luke if you will and chapter number eight and I'll
give you the entire portion of which you could go back and read I won't have time
to read the entirety of these portions of Scripture but in Luke chapter number
eight in verses 26 through 39 you'll read about the account in which Jesus
had crossed over the lake and they'd gone over the sea there and they went to
the country of the Gadarenes and as they're there they meet this man that is
possessed with a demon and the Bible tells us in verse number 27 that he had
devils a long time and wear no clothes neither a boat in any house but in the
tombs and Jesus will ask him in verse number 30 what is thy name and he said
legion because many devils were entered into him we find that Jesus demonstrated
his power over the demons in fact the demons they know who Jesus is James says
that the devils believe in tremble in verse number 28 we say that we see that
it says when he saw Jesus he cried out fell down before him and with a loud
voice said what have I to do with the Jesus thou son of God most high I
beseech thee torment me not and Jesus will rebuke these demons and heal this
man and of course we find that he's then clothed in his right mind sitting at the
feet of Jesus being instructed the people that were there in the city they
besought him to depart from them they wanted him to leave because of all that
had taken place and this man was begging the Lord to be able to go with him it
says in verse number 38 that he besought him that he might be with him
but Jesus sent him and said that he was to be a testimony in his own community
there and to show them how great things God hath done unto thee and the Bible
tells us that he went his way and published throughout the whole city how
great things Jesus had done unto him and so when we think about the mighty power
of God we see the power of Christ over demons over disease we've mentioned
already some reference with regard to the way in which our God is able to heal
we mentioned John chapter 9 with the man that was born blind you think about
John chapter number 5 I've often looked at John chapter number 5 and in
reference that portion of Scripture is when the impotent man meets the
omnipotent God and that man was lame and Jesus asks him a question in John
chapter number 5 and it's a he'd been there for 38 years he had this
infirmity for 38 years and Jesus says in verse number 6 wilt thou be made whole
now we understand that if you had an infirmity for that period of time and
someone came and asked you if you wanted to be made whole you would answer
absolutely notice in verse number 7 it says the impotent man answered him sir I
have no man when the water is troubled to put me into the pool but while I am
coming another step at that
down before me, Jesus saith unto him,
rise, take up thy bed, and walk."
Can you imagine?
38 years, impotent.
He's there at the pool of Siloam,
the Bible talks about in the first several verses,
again, we don't have time to look at all of it,
but we find that he had desired to be healed
and yet had no hope or no expectation,
and Jesus comes and says,
will thou be made whole?
And he says, I have no one to let me in,
and Jesus says, rise, take up thy bed, and walk,
and immediately the man was made whole
and took up his bed and walked.
On the same day was the Sabbath,
of course he received some just negative response
from the Jews because of that,
but this is a miraculous demonstration
of God's power over disease.
I think about the woman with the issue of blood.
She spent all of her living with going to the physicians
and trying to find some way to be healed
of this problem that she had,
and she spent all of her substance and yet was no better.
She said this, and she knew that Jesus was coming that way,
she said, if I could just touch the hem of his garment,
and the people were thronging him
and all the things that are going on,
and she touches the hem of his garment,
and of course Jesus says, who touched me?
The disciples kind of look around,
and what do you mean who touched you?
And he knew that virtue had been departed,
and she came and he said, thy faith hath made thee whole,
and she was immediately healed.
The power of our God, the power of Christ
demonstrated over demons, over disease, over death.
We mentioned it already in John chapter 11,
and you see his ability to raise them from the dead.
We find that he, of course, the Lord Jesus Christ,
he conquered sin, death, and the grave,
and we understand this thing of death.
In fact, I believe that even as we've gone through 2020,
I know that I've mentioned a number of times
that there are a number of people in our world
that are more aware of their mortality
than perhaps had been the case prior
to what we've been dealing with here in 2020.
In fact, it's given some very unique opportunities
of witness for a number of years.
I was at the pastor's conference yesterday,
and for a number of years,
and I was talking to some people
about the fact that we've always said,
hey, if you were to die today,
are you 100% sure that you'd go to heaven?
We understand the certainty of death,
but what a joy to know the reality,
the certainty of heaven,
and as was pointed out, man wants to die,
but we find that Jesus,
not only did he raise people from the dead,
but we understand that he conquered sin,
death, and the grave,
and someone said this,
when we think about death for a believer,
it's simply a doorway to enter,
to leave this life and enter that life,
and what a blessing to think about the reality of heaven
and being with our Savior for all of eternity.
Over nature, number four, over nature,
because of his mighty power,
in Mark chapter number four,
turn over and look at that passage, if you will, with me,
and this is just a powerful passage of scripture.
I referenced it a moment ago
when I spoke about the fact that he was asleep
on a pillow in the ship,
but notice with me in verse number 35,
the Bible says,
the same day when the evening was come,
he saith unto them,
let us pass over unto the other side,
and when they had sent away the multitude,
they took him even as he was in the ship,
there were also with him other little ships,
and there arose a great storm of wind,
and the waves beat into the ship
so that it was now full,
and he was in the hinder part of the ship,
asleep on a pillow,
and they awake him and say unto him,
master, carest thou not that we perish?
And he arose and rebuked the wind and said unto the sea,
peace, be still,
and the wind ceased,
and there was a great calm,
and he said unto them,
why are you so fearful?
How is it that you have no faith?
And they feared exceedingly and said one to another,
what manner of man is this,
that even the wind and the sea obey him?
He's God.
And we find that as we look at this portion of scripture,
again, it's a familiar portion of scripture.
In fact, if you've been in church for any length of time,
I'm sure if you were in Sunday school as a child,
you probably heard a Bible account,
a teacher that taught about Jesus calming the sea.
And it's a familiar Bible account,
but I hope this evening that maybe we could put ourselves
with the disciples just for a moment into that ship
and see how fearful they were with regard
to the certainty of tragedy
because of the storm that had raised up,
and they were fearful,
and they said, master, carest thou not that we perish?
And I mean, to see the Lord Jesus Christ walk out
and to say, peace, be still,
and immediately there was a calm.
That's amazing.
And sometimes I believe that one of the dangers for us
as the people of God and the longer that we walk
with the Lord is sometimes these things
can just become commonplace.
Oh yeah, we know about that.
We know that he calmed this.
But we think about the power of our Lord.
Why is it that I would say Jesus is all the world to me?
Number one, because of who he is.
He's God.
Number two, because of his mighty power.
And I think about the power of God.
Listen, it is unlimited.
He can calm the storm in your life.
He can calm the seas that are raging in your life.
And we think about the power of God over disease
and sickness and all of those things.
And we understand this evening that when we live here
in this 21st century and we're dealing
with all of the difficulties and adversities
that we deal with, that we must be mindful
of the mighty power of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ.
He says this before he would ascend to heaven
in Matthew chapter 28.
Look over there with me.
We'll finish with this portion of scripture
as we think about the mighty power of the Lord.
And we think about this.
Of course, we often reference the Great Commission
and we should because it is the responsibility
of the child of God to proclaim the gospel
to a lost and dying world.
Jesus came in verse number 18 of Matthew 28
and he spake unto them.
And notice what he says.
All power is given unto me in heaven and in earth.
He didn't say some power.
He didn't say most power.
He said, all power is given unto me in heaven and in earth.
Notice in verse number 19, it says,
go ye therefore and teach all nations,
baptizing them in the name of the Father
and the Son of the Holy Ghost,
teaching them to observe all things
whatsoever I have commanded you.
And lo, I am with you all way,
even unto the end of the world, amen.
I mean, this passage of scripture
has so much great truth in it.
But as we focus upon the mighty power of the Lord,
we see that he says to these disciples,
he will soon be, if you look at the timeline
and you look at Matthew 28
and you couple it with Acts chapter number one
and giving the last of the Great Commission,
then the Ascension, you can read Luke 22 as well
and kind of see what's going on there with this record,
excuse me, Luke 24, and see the Ascension of the Lord.
And these disciples would hear the Lord Jesus Christ say,
all power is given unto me in heaven and in earth.
Go ye therefore and teach all nations.
And he gives that Great Commission.
And so he kind of, the book ends, if you will,
of the Great Commission.
On the front end of it is the fact that he says,
all power is given unto me.
On the back of the commission, he says,
I am with you all way, even unto the end of the world.
Now think about that.
We have this responsibility, this commission to go,
but the Lord in his declaration and giving this commission,
he says, I have all power and I'll be with you.
Isn't that precious?
Why is Jesus all the world to you?
I hope that you would say, as the songwriter said,
Jesus is all the world to me.
And I have three more reasons that I'll give you next week
as to why he is all the world to me,
but when we start this and evaluate the scriptures,
I would say number one, because of who he is,
and number two, because of his mighty power.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for the word of God.
Thank you for the truth that is given to us in thy word
with regard to the life and ministry
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
I thank you for the truth of the incarnation,
for the truth of your word with regard
to the purpose of Christ's birth,
that it was prophesied and it was fulfilled.
And we find that the purpose was to go to that cruel cross,
to suffer and bleed and die.
We thank you for the opportunity to look
at these portions of scripture this evening
with regard to the person of Jesus Christ,
with regard to the power of Jesus Christ.
God, I pray that our hearts have been encouraged
in these few moments of studying thy word,
to understand that you indeed are God
and that you do possess all power
and that you've promised to be with us.
I pray that we would go in the power
of the Holy Spirit of God.
And I pray that we would walk with thee.
Lord, even as we sang these wonderful songs this evening,
as you're all on the...
an altar living for Jesus.
Oh, when we understand who You are,
when we can answer that question
that we examined from Matthew 16 last week,
and when we can understand
that You're all the world to us
because of who You are,
because of the things that You've done,
because of what You continue to do
and how You continue to work,
that we would live for You.
That we would seek to please You and honor You
through all that we say and do.
Lord, we ask that You'd bless our time of prayer.
We thank You for the privilege of prayer.
We thank You that You're a God
who hears and answers prayer.
We pray that You'd meet with us
and bless our time.
For it's in Christ's name we pray, Amen.