And last week, we had the opportunity to study
in the Old Testament, we're in the book of Isaiah,
and we noted how Hezekiah trusted the Lord
in the midst of great adversity.
And if you were here last week,
we looked at that situation,
and Hezekiah believed the record of creation
that God had given.
He knew that God was the creator God,
and he knew that the creator God was his helper.
And we mentioned last week,
as we studied the passage of Scripture there in Isaiah
with regard to the time of Hezekiah's reign there
and the attack or the threat of the Assyrians,
we find that he responded to that great adversity
with fear, excuse me, with faith,
and with dependence on God alone to help.
Faith conquered his fear.
No doubt, there were opportunities
for the people of God, Judah,
to have fear with regard to the threats
and all that had taken place.
The Assyrians were the world power
and had conquered many a people group,
but Hezekiah was a man of faith.
Hezekiah was a man that believed God,
that trusted God, and he knew that God alone
was able to help.
He knew that there was nothing that he could do
and of himself.
It was all through the power of God the creator
that was his helper.
Judah, of course, as we finished up last week,
was miraculously delivered,
and the Assyrians were defeated.
This morning, as we look here in Acts chapter number four,
I wanna look at what takes place here with the disciples.
We understand that at this particular time in history,
as we look at this account in Acts chapter number four,
that the Lord Jesus Christ had lived
his perfect, sinless life.
The record of the life of Christ
is provided through the gospels.
We find that he, of course, had gone
to the cross of Calvary.
He had bled and died.
He had been buried in a borrowed tomb,
and he rose, conquering sin, death, and the grave.
We find that the book of Acts records for us
in the first chapter his ascension to heaven,
and before he ascended to heaven,
he gave instruction to his disciples,
to those that would carry on the work of the Lord
with regard to what we refer to as the Great Commission.
That work, as the disciples were seeking to fulfill
the work that God had given them to do,
was met with serious, I would say intense, opposition.
We find that many times we begin to read
through the book of Acts, and as you continue
through the first several chapters of the book of Acts,
you read of that opposition to the work of God.
We've mentioned many times over the years
that God's work is continuously met
with opposition, with adversity.
Just because we're doing what God's called us to do
doesn't mean that it will be void of any interference
or any opposition.
In fact, often we find that that opposition comes greatly
as we're seeking to follow the Lord.
The fourth chapter of the book of Acts,
we're looking this morning, beginning in verse number 23,
but the beginning of this chapter begins
by revealing to us how Peter and John were held in prison.
They were held in prison overnight
because of what had taken place in Acts chapter number three.
There was a great miracle that took place
with that man that was lame,
that laid at the gate beautiful, and he was healed,
and that gave opportunity for Peter to preach the gospel,
and many people trust that Christ is their savior.
5,000 besides the women, and you look
at what's taking place there,
and you look at the growth of the early church,
and you find that the religious leaders were not happy
with what was going on, and we find that those
that believed according to verse number four
the number of the men was 5,000,
and as we begin Acts chapter number four,
they were held in prison overnight,
they're released, and then they're interrogated,
and there's all sorts of questions that are asked
as to what's going on, and we find that Peter stands,
and he preaches the gospel once again,
and the religious leaders are not happy
with what's taking place.
The religious leaders, they cannot deny the miracle
of Acts chapter number three, but they desire
that this would spread no further.
So what do they do?
They begin to threaten the disciples.
We find that the threat is recorded for us.
Look, if you will, in verse number 17 of Acts four,
as we make the, set the scene, if you will,
for the passage that we're going to look at this morning.
In verse 17, it says, but that it spread no further
among the people, let us straightly threaten them.
They speak henceforth to no man in this name,
and so this was this conference that they had
as they conferred amongst themselves,
according to verse number 15,
and they come up with their plan,
and their plan is to threaten the disciples,
and they call the disciples to them in verse number 18.
It says that they called them and commanded them
not to speak at all nor teach in the name of Jesus.
So this is a major problem because Jesus told them
to go and preach the gospel to every creature,
and the religious leaders are threatening the disciples,
and they're saying, listen, we're commanding you
not to teach or to even speak in the name of Jesus.
It tells us that Peter responds in verse 20 and says,
for we cannot but speak the things
which we have seen and heard.
I'm thankful for his boldness.
It says in verse 21, so when they had further threatened
them, they let them go, finding nothing
how they might punish them because of the people,
for all men glorified God for that which was done.
It tells us that the man in Acts chapter number three
was about 40 years old on whom this miracle
of healing was showed.
So we find that they commanded them in verse number 18,
and Peter responds in verse 20,
and then they threatened them again
before they released them, and we come to verse number 23
as our passage for our study this morning.
The Bible says, and being let go,
and so these disciples are released
from the religious leaders.
They've just heard the threat.
They've just been commanded with regard to not speaking
or teaching in the name of Jesus.
They've already spent one night in prison,
according to Acts four at the beginning of the chapter
in verse number three.
We find that now they're released and being let go.
They went to their own company and reported all
that the chief priest and elders had said unto them.
And when they heard that, they lifted up their voice to God
with one accord and said, Lord, thou art God,
which has made heaven and earth and the sea
and all that in them is.
Who by the mouth of thy servant David has said,
why did the heathen rage?
And the people imagined vain things.
The kings of the earth stood up and the rulers
were gathered together against the Lord
and against his Christ for of a truth
against the holy child, Jesus, whom thou hast anointed,
both Herod and Pontius Pilate with the Gentiles
and the people of Israel were gathered together
for to do whatsoever thy hand and thy counsel
determined before to be done.
And now, verse 29, and now, Lord, behold their threatenings.
And grant unto thy servants that with all boldness,
they may speak thy word by stretching forth thine hand
to heal that signs and wonders may be done
by the name of thy holy child, Jesus.
When they had prayed, place was shaken
where they were assembled together.
They were all filled with the Holy Ghost
and they spake the word of God with boldness.
Last week, the title for our message was
The Creator God Is My Helper, part one.
This morning is part two.
The Creator God Is My Helper.
The religious leaders let the disciples go as we've read
and we see that they come and they give this report
to their own company.
It tells us in verse 23 that they being let go,
they went to their own company.
And you can think about this reunion
and this gathering that took place
and the disciples after Acts chapter number three,
these Peter and John, they're imprisoned overnight
and they're before the religious leaders
and they're hearing those threats
and these of their own company are in a different location
and now Peter and John reunite with them.
And the Bible tells us in verse 23
that they reported all that the chief priests and elders
had said unto them.
So we find that as Peter and John would leave the place
of standing before these religious leaders
and hearing the threat and the command
and all that was contained within that conversation,
we find that they come and they give a report,
they debrief the others,
they let them know what the circumstances are
and what has transpired.
And we find that as we're looking at our text of scripture
this morning and we see this opposition,
we see this adversity,
I want you to notice first of all this morning,
if you are taking notes, notice how they respond.
Notice how they respond.
I believe this morning that their response is consistent
with the response of Hezekiah
that we studied last week in Isaiah 37.
And we find that what they do in verse number 24
is so important for us to grasp
and to understand this morning
that they hear what's taking place.
Peter and John heard it firsthand,
they report it to their own company,
they're aware of the threat of the command
that has been issued by the religious leaders.
By the way, these religious leaders had great power.
They had great authority.
They didn't have all authority.
They didn't have all power.
There is one that has all power and all authority, and his name is Jesus.
And that's who these disciples were serving, and that's who these disciples were seeking
to preach Jesus.
And we find that these that had some power and some authority would not cause the disciples
to cower in fear.
They would not cause the disciples to doubt the power and authority of their Lord and
Savior Jesus Christ.
Rather, we find that their immediate response to the situation is to go to God in prayer.
You know, God answers prayer.
It's a statement that's so easy to make, it almost can become a cliche if we're not careful.
But the reality is that prayer is a great privilege for the child of God, that at any
moment, for any reason, you have direct access to the God of the universe.
He told us that we're to come boldly unto the throne of grace.
He said to us, call, and I will answer thee.
And you think about the privilege of prayer, and here in the context of this great adversity
dealing with the opposition and the threats that came forth, we find that when they heard
that in verse number 24, they lifted up their voice to God with one accord.
They didn't get together and figure out how they were going to overcome the Sanhedrin.
They didn't get together and see how they could elect other people in power that might
be able to…
No, they went to God in prayer.
That was their immediate response, was to go to God in prayer.
See, prayer must be our first response.
Prayer cannot, it should never be our last resort.
We understand that God answers prayer, that God works and God moves, and we find here
that as they go to God in prayer, we notice, just as we did with Hezekiah, what it is that
they recognize.
Notice in verse number 24, the Bible says that they lifted up their voice to God with
one accord, and notice what they said, Lord, thou art God.
Recognize who He is.
But then they say this, which has made heaven and earth and the sea and all that in them
is.
I've said so often that the record of creation is not isolated to Genesis.
It seems as if the opposition would like you to think that the record of creation is only
found in the book of Genesis in the first few chapters, but the reality is that the
truth of creation is found throughout the entirety of the Word of God.
We find here that these disciples, they understood that the Creator God was their God.
They understood that He spoke and it was so.
That as we studied several weeks ago, as we looked at the truth of creation and how creation
reveals the greatness of God, He said, let there be light, and there was light.
It's amazing.
So often when we begin to think about creation and the power that's on display, the wisdom
that's on display with the record of creation, and we can stand and we should stand in awe
of who God is because He is the Creator God, but we must understand that God gave us the
record of creation, yes, so that we could understand the origin of man and we could
understand that He is the Creator, but then He ties it all together for us and lets us
understand this morning that He is our God, that He is our Helper, that when we understand
the power and the wisdom of creation and we understand all that was displayed through
creation that He is my God and He is my Helper.
So the disciples were facing serious opposition here.
Just as Hezekiah and Judah were facing serious opposition from the Assyrians, but we find
that in both cases, Hezekiah, and here are the disciples, they recognize that their God
is greater.
They understand and they recognize that He is the Creator of all things and that nothing
is too difficult for Him.
Thou art God which has made heaven, earth, sea, and all that is in them, all that in
them is.
Wow.
See, we need to be mindful of the truth that the Creator God is our Helper.
Sometimes we face big problems.
We face difficulties.
We've referred to, in these last two weeks, great adversity.
There are times in which we face great adversity, but our God is greater.
Our God is able.
He's able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think.
There are times, even as we mentioned in our Sunday school class this morning, that we
try to take matters into our own hands, that we try to scheme and devise and figure out
how we can do something instead of recognizing that the Creator God that spoke it all into
existence, that He's able to do far better than we are.
We look here at this passage of Scripture and we know how they respond, and I wonder
this morning in my life, and I wonder this morning in your life, how do we respond in
times of great adversity?
When we face difficulties, when we face problems, when we face that opposition, how is it that
we respond?
Do we immediately go to God in prayer?
Do we immediately remind ourselves that our God is the Creator?
See, sometimes we come to this place, and the disciples could have as well, because
this body, this religious body that they had just stood before, this Sanhedrin, these men
had great power.
The same men that delivered Jesus to Pilate to be crucified had great power.
They were the ones that imprisoned Peter and John the night before.
They had power.
And sometimes today we look at certain authorities and think, look at the authority or the power
that they have, and fail to recognize and remember that our God has all power.
He has all power.
And by the way, just as Jesus said to Pilate, remember what Pilate said, I have the power
to release you?
And Jesus said, listen, you need to understand something, Pilate, he didn't say it that way.
The only power you have, the power that I let you have.
And those that are in places of power are there because God has allowed them.
And by the way, that means if you like the person in power or not, amen?
Because God is sovereign.
You know, sometimes the leadership that a nation has is judgment upon that nation.
You can't just think, oh, the leader that I like is there because God put him there.
No, no.
People are in power because God's allowed them to be in power.
And we find, though, that their power is limited while His power is unlimited.
He's the Creator God.
And that's the response of these disciples and how the truth of who God is influenced
the manner in which they responded to their adversity.
That's why it's so important to be in this book.
That's why it's so important for us to understand who God is.
And we find that we know God through His Word.
God has revealed Himself to us through the pages of this book.
We could sit here this morning and we could take testimonies this morning.
We could have every single person that's here this morning stand and give testimony.
Why do you say that God is great?
Why do you think God is great?
And everything that we could say because of His great mercy, because of His great love,
because of His great power, because He delivered here, because He did this, all that we know
about God is found in the pages of this book.
And God gave us this book so that we would know how great He is, so that in the time
of adversity, in the time of difficulty, we could respond by not saying, oh, did you hear
what they said?
Did you hear?
Do you know who my God is?
Do you know what He's capable of doing?
Remember thinking about this, kids at the playground have conversations occasionally
about how their dad is stronger or better than your dad.
They have those kind of conversations.
You know what the Bible tells us?
Our rock is not like their rock.
Who's it referring to?
Our God.
And I'm so thankful this morning that our God is greater and we find that they respond
properly.
And for us this morning, how we respond to great adversity really reveals what we know
and believe about God.
When we face great opposition, we face great difficulty in opposition, how we respond reveals
in great measure what we know and believe to be true of God.
We find how they respond, but then I want you to note in our text.
of Scripture, what they requested.
I want you to notice, they pray, and in verses 25 through 27, they speak about the truth
that had been revealed in the Old Testament, reference to Psalm 2, with regard to the heathen
raging and the kings of the earth standing against the Lord, and so on and so forth.
And you find in verse 27 and 28, speaking about the Lord Jesus Christ and how He would
He was, of course, determined to go to the cross of Calvary.
And then we come to verse 29, and that's where we really see what it is that they requested.
In verse 29 and verse number 30, and when I begin to note their request, when I notice
that they respond by prayer, but then when I look at their prayer and examine and study
their prayer and zero in on what they requested, I'm impressed.
I'm challenged by what they requested.
Honestly, their request in this passage of Scripture, I believe, is both commendable
and exemplary.
I don't know that I would have prayed the same thing that they prayed.
I'll be honest with you.
He's the creator God.
My prayer might have been like this, God deal with them.
You heard what they said, deal with them.
That's not what they prayed.
It says this in verse 29, and now, Lord, behold their threatenings.
Do you remember Hezekiah, what he did?
He took that letter from Rabshakeh, went into the house of the Lord, and he laid it out
before the Lord.
And here the disciples, they say, Lord, you've heard, behold, their threatenings.
But notice what they request, and grant unto thy servants, that with all boldness they
may speak thy word.
Wow, that is commendable, that is exemplary.
See, they prayed that God would give them boldness in the face of adversity.
They did not pray that God would eliminate the adversity.
They prayed that though the adversity is there, God would give us boldness.
I want you to recall with me that James and John, not too long before this particular
account, desired to call fire from heaven like Elijah did.
Turn back, hold your place here in action, turn back to the book of Luke, if you will.
In chapter number 9, I want to read this passage of Scripture to you here in Luke 9,
because this did not take place that long before the text of Scripture in which we're
reading this morning.
In Acts chapter number 4, they say, Lord, behold their threatenings, but God, our request
is that you'd give us boldness to speak thy word.
In Luke chapter number 9, in verse 51, the Bible says, and it came to pass, when the
time was come that he should be received up, he steadfastly set his face to go to
Jerusalem and sent messengers before his face, and they went and entered into a village of
the Samaritans to make ready for him, and they did not receive him, because his face
was as though he would go to Jerusalem.
And when his disciples, James and John, saw this, they said, Lord, wilt thou that we command
fire to come down from heaven and consume them, even as Elijah did?
Can you imagine referring back to Elijah back in 2 Kings chapter number 1?
Did that happen?
Sure it did.
You remember the final servant that came?
He understood the first two companies, man, they got consumed with fire, so he approached
Elijah differently than the first two did.
But we come now and we find that James and John here in verse number 54, they say to
the Lord, Lord, wilt thou that we command fire to come down from heaven and consume
them, even as Elijah did?
But he turned and rebuked them and said, ye know not what manner of spirit ye are of.
Notice what he says, for the Son of Man has not come to destroy men's lives, but to save
them.
They went to another village to save them, to save them.
How would they be saved?
The preaching of the gospel.
How is anyone saved?
Through the blood of the Lord Jesus Christ.
There's only one way to be saved, it's the Bible way.
Jesus is the only way.
No other way, no other way.
Jesus said, I am the way, the truth, and the life.
No man cometh unto the Father but by me.
Peter had just proclaimed in this same very passage in Acts chapter number 4, neither
is there salvation any other.
Only in the name of Jesus, he says, notice in verse number 12, neither is there salvation
any other.
For there is no other name under heaven given among men whereby we must be saved.
So Peter understood the gospel had to go forward.
He understood that there were some people, even within that group of that religious crowd,
that needed to be saved.
They needed to hear the gospel.
Those that were opposing, those that were threatening, that were commanding do not teach
or preach in the name of Jesus, Peter and John and the disciples and those that were
gathered together, they understood that they had been commissioned to preach the gospel
and that the gospel is the power of God unto salvation.
And so when they pray, when they make their requests, listen, they respond by prayer.
They understand that God is the creator and that he is their helper and they recognize
this great truth and they say, God, would you give us boldness in the midst of this
adversity?
Isn't that commendable?
Exemplary.
In the midst of this time of threats, God, we need boldness.
It says in verse 30, by stretching forth thine hand to heal and that signs and wonders may
be done by the name of thy holy child, Jesus.
We've been studying the book of Acts in our adult Sunday school class or the family Sunday
school class, excuse me.
We'd studied the miracles of Christ for a lengthy period of time through the gospels.
As we came to a conclusion of that particular study, we dealt with the fact of what Mark
16 and verse 20 says, that they went forth and preached everywhere, the Lord working
with them and confirming the word with signs of following, amen.
Here they're praying in that same understanding that God would grant them boldness.
You know, God is able to give you boldness in the midst of adversity, in the midst of
opposition, in the midst of all that's taking place in our lives and our world.
As we look at the disciples here in Acts chapter 4 and we see their response to those
that were opposing the message, you know there are people that are opposing the message still
today.
You understand that.
There are all sorts of things that are going on in our world today.
It seems like there's not a day that goes by in which you're not finding or hearing
about how there's someone in power, some place of authority where they're trying to silence
the people of God.
We need boldness to preach the gospel.
See because the Lord has come to save people.
And as we understand that salvation is only through the Lord Jesus Christ, there's only
one way to be saved.
As I mentioned a few moments ago, we understand that what they must hear is the gospel of
Jesus Christ.
The Bible says, for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved.
That's a wonderful promise of God's word in Romans 10 and verse 13.
But the Bible continues and says, how then shall they call on him in whom they have not
believed?
They're not going to call on him if they don't believe him.
And then it says, how shall they believe in him whom they've not heard?
How shall they hear without a preacher?
That's what the Bible says.
How shall they preach except they be sent as it is written, how beautiful are the feet
of them that preach the gospel of peace and bring glad tidings of good things, but they've
not all obeyed the gospel for Isaiah saith, Lord, who hath believed our report?
So then faith cometh by hearing and hearing by the word of God.
If you take that passage of scripture in Romans 10 and verse 13 through 17, we understand
the great importance that is before us of being able to preach the word of God with
boldness, to preach the gospel.
The world in which we're living, they need to be saved.
The answer is Jesus.
But in order for them to be saved, they need to have some of us that have some boldness.
That boldness needs to come from the Lord Jesus Christ.
Listen, I'm not going to be bold in my own power.
I'm not, neither are you.
We have the power of the Holy Spirit of God.
We notice how they responded.
How do we respond in times of great adversity?
Do we remember that God is the creator, that He's our helper?
To respond in faith, believing that He is able.
What is our request?
request. The request of the disciples is not to eliminate the opposition. Sometimes we
think that'd be great, but the request of the disciples is to empower His people, that
we may speak Thy word. How with boldness. Notice, finally this morning, what they received.
In verse 31, we read the response to the prayer that was prayed by these that were gathered
together. And the Bible tells us when they had prayed, the place was shaken where they
were assembled together. It tells us that they were filled with the Holy Ghost. And
then notice the end of verse 31, and they spake the word of God with boldness. Wow.
What a scene. What a blessing. Their desire, as it's reported through the record of the
prayer that they offered to the Creator God, was that they would have boldness to speak
the word of God. And we find that God answered the prayer and God empowered them for the
task. I'm so thankful that God still today will empower us for the task that is before
us. See, so often we just forget that we're His representatives. Sometimes our identity
is kind of skewed because the highest part of our identity is that I'm a follower of
Jesus Christ. And when I understand that I'm His representative, when I understand as Paul
would say in Galatians, I am crucified with Christ. Nevertheless, I live, yet not I, but
Christ liveth in me. The life that I now live in the flesh, I live by the faith of the Son
of God who loved me and gave Himself for me. Begin to understand living that crucified
life and understanding that, listen, I'm just His representative. I'm just here to go in
the power of the Holy Spirit of God and just speak the word of God with boldness. Not worried
about what somebody thinks about me. Sometimes that really is a hindrance in our lives. What
are they going to think about me? They're going to think I'm crazy. They probably already
do. But seriously, sometimes we get so caught up in what somebody's going to think about
me or how they're going to respond to me that we fail to recognize who we really are. Notice
what Peter had said previously to these religious leaders. In verse number 20, for we cannot
but speak the things which we have seen and heard. You know that word, cannot. It's as
if it's just oozing out of them and they can't help it. Does that make sense? It's
the overflow. And we find that the disciples here, they're saying, God, we need Your power
in order to fulfill the task that You have given us. This morning, we need God's power.
So many people today talking about becoming a 21st century church. I understand we live
in an advanced age and we live in a time of great advancements with technology and all
sorts of things. I mean, don't get me wrong, I'm glad that we have electricity and heat
and all that stuff today. I'm thankful for that. But really, we talk about doing the
work of God, we need to become a first century church. Fully relying upon the Lord. Understanding
the commands that He has given us to go and to preach the gospel to every creature and
that we must go in His power and I must have His boldness. God, help me to understand why
You've placed me here. Why have You given me the sphere of influence that You have?
It's to be Your representative, to be Your ambassador, to be the light in this dark world.
And the disciples, they got it. They didn't pray for the opposition to be removed. They
prayed for boldness in the midst of adversity. Last week, when we looked at Hezekiah, Judah,
the nation in which he was ruling and reigning as king over, they're faced with great adversity.
Sennacherib and Rabshakem, the Assyrians. You know, God delivered them from the Assyrians.
An angel of the Lord came out, we read it last week, and 185,000 were slain. One night.
God delivered them from the Assyrians. This week, as we look at the disciples, God delivered
them through the opposition. By the way, the opposition didn't stop at the end of Acts
chapter 4. You continue to read, the opposition just intensified. They call them in Acts chapter
5, and they're like, did not we command you? Almost as if to say, did you not understand
what we said? Were we not clear? And yet, ye have filled Jerusalem with your doctrine.
That's what they say in Acts chapter 5. Peter, in that passage, he says, we ought to obey
God rather than man. In that passage, they were threatened some more, and they were beaten,
and they left rejoicing that they were counted worthy to suffer shame for His namesake.
Last week, the enemy was eliminated. 185,000 killed, Sennacherib goes back, his own sons
kill him. We read it. This week, however, the opposition remains. But God's people
are empowered. God's people are empowered to fulfill the task. We've often referenced
Psalm 121, verses 1 and 2, where the psalmist says, I will lift up my eyes into the hills.
From whence cometh my help? My help cometh from the Lord, which made heaven and earth.
Last week with Hezekiah, he faced great adversity, but he understood that the Creator God was
his helper. This week, we look at the disciples. They face opposition, adversity, threats,
commands, but they understood that the Creator God is their helper. And I want you to notice
what the psalmist says in Psalm 146. Look over and we'll finish here with this passage
of Scripture in Psalm 146. Oh, indeed, creation reveals to us the greatness of God, His great
power, His great wisdom. We see it throughout the pages of Scripture. You can walk out this
afternoon and you can see the beauty of creation. Look at your own body and see how God has
formed us, fashioned us, how each of our members work. Just stand in awe of our God, but never
forget that He's your helper. Yes, He's the Creator, but He's your helper. Notice in Psalm
146, verse number 1 says, "'Praise ye the Lord! Praise the Lord, O my soul! While I
live will I praise the Lord. I will sing praises unto my God while I have any being. Put not
your trust in princes, nor in the Son of Man, in whom there is no help.'" How often are
we guilty of verse number 3? Putting our trust in someone or something else. Sometimes
putting our trust in ourselves. I got this. I can handle this. I need to do something.
No, no. He says, "'Put not your trust in princes, nor in the Son of Man, in whom there is little
help.'" No, no. He says, no help. "'His breath goeth forth, he returneth to his earth, and
that very day his thoughts perish.'" But then notice verse 5 and 6. "'Happy is he that hath
the God of Jacob for his help, whose hope is in the Lord his God.'" The word happy is
often also translated as blessed. He says, listen, don't trust in these things, but happy
or blessed is the one that has as his help the God of Jacob for his help, whose hope
is in the Lord his God. Notice verse number 6, "'Which made heaven and earth, the sea,
and all that therein is.'"
verse, which keepeth truth forever."
Did you notice the words of verse number 6, which made heaven and earth, the sea, and
all that therein is?
Does that not sound awfully familiar to exactly what the disciples prayed in Acts chapter
number 4?
Did they have the book of Psalms?
Absolutely.
They had the book of Psalms.
They did not have the whole Bible as we have the whole Bible today.
But in Acts chapter number 4, when they went to God in prayer, they said, Thou art God
which hast made heaven and earth and the sea and all that in them is.
He is the man.
Blessed is the man, or is he, that hath the God of Jacob for his help.
Listen, this morning, we're blessed because the Creator God is our helper.
And we must never forget that.
Listen, I'm so thankful that He's the Creator, that He's given us the truth with regard to
the origin of man and the universe and all of those things, and He's told us how He did
it.
It's amazing when you think about creation, but how does it affect me personally in my
everyday life?
The Creator God is my helper.
The Creator God is your helper.
This week you face opposition.
This week you face adversity.
This week you face a difficulty.
And you say, listen, my God's the Creator.
He spoke it all into existence.
He upholds it all by His power.
There's nothing too hard for Him.
And this, whatever this is, is nothing for God.
My God is able.
How do we respond in times of great adversity?
I hope this morning, over these last several weeks, as we've looked at the greatness of
God as revealed through creation, and then we apply it to our everyday lives that the
Creator God is my helper, I hope that as we face difficulties in life, and I know that
we will.
I know that we will.
Some are in the midst of great trials at this very moment, but the Creator God is your helper.
And that ought to cause you to rejoice greatly.
And you must recognize that you're happy or blessed because the God of Jacob is your helper.
So often we want this thing to help me, or this person to help me, or this…God is my
helper.
God is my helper.
The psalmist said, vain is the help of man.
So often, I need help.
The psalmist said, help, Lord, understanding that He is the Creator.
This morning, I hope that you've been encouraged by Hezekiah and by the disciples, and that
you, this morning, can say personally that the Creator God is my helper.
He's your helper.
Say, but you don't understand what I'm dealing with.
He spoke it all into existence.
You understand that?
He said, and it was so.
He made the stars also.
What a statement.
He spent a whole week on that.
And He's your helper.
He's my helper.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
We thank You for the truth of Your Word and the power of Your Word.
We pray, God, that You would help us this morning to be encouraged and to be strengthened
through what You have revealed to us in Your precious Word.
We thank You for the response of Hezekiah.
We thank You, God, for the response of the disciples.
Though they face great adversity, they responded in faith, they responded with understanding
that You are the Creator God and that You are our helper.
I pray, Father, that You would help each and every one of us, Lord, as we have examined
these portions of Scripture, to be encouraged, to be strengthened.
Lord, help us to fully depend upon You.
Father, I pray that if there's one here or one that's tuned in via live stream that's
not sure of heaven, I pray that they'd trust Christ today.
They'd understand that He is the only Savior.
I pray for the one that's facing adversity, difficulty, many, Lord.
I pray that You'd help us, help us to have faith and confidence in knowing that the Creator
God is our helper.
We pray that in these moments of invitation that You'd move and work as only You can.
I pray that decisions would be made that would please me.
We'll thank You for the work that You'll do, for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed, no one's looking around.
As our manner is, we'll have an opportunity for invitation, invite you to respond.
Maybe this morning you're dealing with some great adversity or opposition.
You need to come to this altar and ask God to help you.
Maybe you've been looking to other people or other sources for help.
Maybe you need to ask God to forgive you for that.
Ask Him completely.
The Creator God is our helper.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.