Key to that truth is verse number one,
the Lord is my shepherd.
I'm thankful that he is the good shepherd
and he gave his life for the sheep
according to John chapter number 10.
I'm thankful that he's the great shepherd,
the chief shepherd, he's coming back, hallelujah.
But what a joy to know that the Lord is my shepherd.
And if you don't know that this morning,
I want you to know that he wants to save you,
he wants you to know for sure that heaven is your home,
he loves you and he died for you,
you cannot pay for your own sins,
he paid for them on the cross of Calvary
and it's not his work plus your work,
it's his work alone and we're so thankful
for that Bible truth.
All of that was free as a result of the song this morning.
Second Corinthians chapter number eight
is the passage that we'll be preaching through this morning,
and as you have a moment to turn there in your Bibles,
I wanna remind you from this chapter
in Second Corinthians chapter number eight,
we started the chapter by noting the example
of the churches of Macedonia.
We find that the Apostle Paul is going
to really commend these churches for their giving
and the Bible tells us that these were in deep poverty,
however, they gave sacrificially.
The Bible reveals to us that they gave of their own selves
and what a great truth for each of us
to acknowledge this morning that we surrender all,
that we recognize that I'm bought with a price
and therefore I belong to God and we find here,
the Bible said in verse number five,
but they first gave their own selves to the Lord
and unto us by the will of God
and we notice that example of the churches of Macedonia
and then the Apostle Paul in the next text of scripture,
he then challenges the believers here in Corinth,
the main recipients of this book of Second Corinthians
and he challenges them to abound in this grace also.
That was the term that we adopted and used
as a title for a message in verse number seven,
that you abound in this grace also
and what the Apostle Paul was saying
to the believers there in Corinth
is that you're doing these things,
that you abound in everything in faith and utterance
and knowledge and in diligence and your love to us,
but he says that see that you abound in this grace also
and we dealt with the subject
about talking about the importance
of being complete in Christ, being mature believers,
not doing this and leaving this undone
and not doing this and leaving this undone,
but doing all to the glory of God
and by the way, the only way that we can accomplish that
is through the spirit of God who works in and through us,
he enables us to do what he's instructed us to do
and we find that the chapter concludes here,
Second Corinthians chapter eight,
this chapter concludes with the record
of the offering being delivered.
However, this morning before we get to that portion
and finish up the chapter,
I believe that we come to a statement
regarding the character Titus
that is worthy of our pause and examination.
We find that Paul pens a letter to Titus,
it holds the name of that book of Titus,
just a few chapters and there in that particular letter,
Paul refers to Titus as my own son after the common faith.
We find that the apostle Paul and Titus
had a close relationship
and Titus was dear to the heart of Paul.
In fact, in Second Corinthians chapter number six
and we studied this several weeks ago,
what we found in chapter seven and verse number six,
the Bible says, nevertheless,
God that comforted those that are cast down,
comforted us by the coming of Titus
and we spoke about that portion of scripture
in Second Corinthians chapter seven,
how that God used Titus to bring encouragement
to Paul and to others
and we find that as we look at our text this morning
in Second Corinthians eight, verses 16 and 17,
it is worthy of our pause and examination.
Notice the Bible says this, but thanks be to God.
Isn't that awesome how Paul starts that section?
He starts with this note of praise and what a blessing.
We ought to be a people that praise the Lord.
We're to enter into his gates with thanksgiving, amen.
We're to be a cheerful, joyful, thankful people
and everything give thanks for this is the will of God
in Christ Jesus concerning you
and God is good all of the time.
It doesn't mean that our circumstances are always good.
It doesn't mean that we always have everything
the way that we'd like for it to be,
but we know that God is always good
and Paul says, but thanks be to God.
Notice what he says, which put the same earnest care
into the heart of Titus for you.
For indeed, he accepted the exhortation,
but being more forward of his own accord,
he went unto you.
In verses 16 and 17, I note these statements
that are made about Titus
and I've simply titled the message this morning,
how is God working in your heart?
How is God working in your heart?
The title requires for us to pause and reflect
and to be able to answer,
how is God working personally in your heart?
How is God working in my heart?
Is God working in your heart?
Is God working in my heart?
As we notice this text of scripture
in just a couple of verses,
we notice, first of all, what Paul recognized.
Notice what Paul recognized.
It's given to us in verse 16.
He says this, but thanks be to God,
which put the same earnest care
into the heart of Titus for you.
Paul recognized two things according to verse number 16.
What he noticed first of all,
was he noticed how God was working.
He noticed that God was at work.
And by the way, can I encourage you this morning
that you could understand and recognize this morning
that God is always at work.
God has a plan and God's plan includes God's people
and God is at work.
And here in the text of scripture,
we find that the apostle Paul is recognizing God's work,
not in his own life, but in the life of Titus.
So we find that he notices how God was working,
but he also recognizes who God was working in.
He recognized specifically that God was working
in the heart of Titus.
I hope this morning that you've recognized in your own life
when God is working, when God is stirring
and God is doing something in your heart,
the reality is that we can also notice
when God is working in someone else's life.
This morning, I'm thankful that God works in
and through individuals.
Our God is a for God so love the world kind of God.
He loves all people, all humanity,
but we understand that this truth that God loves me,
that he's interested in me,
that he's interested in working in your life personally.
I'm thankful for what God was doing
in the heart of the apostle Paul,
but we pause here just for a moment this morning
to acknowledge as Paul does,
he recognizes that God was at work.
We find that Paul, we notice first of all,
what he recognized, we then notice how he rejoiced
and I mentioned it my way of introduction,
but he starts in verse 16, but thanks be to God.
Paul is rejoicing.
Paul gave thanks to God for working in the heart of Titus.
The reality is that as God is working in the heart of Titus
and Paul recognizes this work that God is doing,
he recognizes that it's God that's doing the work
and that it's Titus, the person in whom God is working
and that causes Paul to rejoice.
I wonder this morning, how often do you thank God
for working in your heart and your life?
How often do you pause and rejoice and say,
thank you God for speaking to me.
Thank you God for convicting me.
Sometimes we think of conviction as a bad thing,
but the reality is that when the spirit of God
uses the word of God to convict the people of God,
that's a good thing and we ought to rejoice
and we ought to thank him.
But then I wonder this morning,
Paul's not rejoicing here
because God was working in his heart,
although we know that God worked
in the life of the apostle Paul,
but he's rejoicing here because God was working
in the heart of Titus.
And I wonder this morning,
how often do we as the people of God
recognize God's work in the hearts of others
and then thank God, rejoice for what God is doing
in the heart of others.
See, the reality is that as we see this verse of scripture
and we see this truth revealed to us
that Paul, there's no competition here,
there's no jealousy here.
Remember the church in Corinth
in the first chapter of the first book of Corinthians,
God reveals to us about divisions
and envyings that were in the church.
In those divisions and envyings,
as you study through the book of 1 Corinthians,
oftentimes what we would be able to acknowledge
that much of it was the result of spiritual gifts.
And you find that these divisions and these envyings
that were taking place there in the church in Corinth
that was causing for a church to not be unified,
it was causing for a church not to accomplish
what God had intended for that church to accomplish.
But here, when we come to 2 Corinthians.
Paul is not jealous that God was working in the heart of Titus.
No, Paul is rejoicing that God's working in the heart of Titus.
Why? Because God is working in the hearts of His people.
And the Apostle Paul had an understanding of what God was doing
and how God works and he recognized it, but then he rejoiced.
He thanked God.
Listen, this morning, the work of God requires all of God's people.
The Bible tells us about the church and the Bible uses a number of analogies
to describe the church to us, but one that is used even here to the church in Corinth
in 1 Corinthians is that of a body.
And oftentimes we talk about a church body and we'll use that phraseology
and we understand this morning that as we would look at that portion of Scripture
in 1 Corinthians and understand that each one has their spot,
their position, their responsibility, and when they all come together
and do what God has called them to do as individuals,
that God alone is glorified and that the community is impacted for the glory of God.
See, the truth is that Paul understood he wasn't on an island to his own,
as an individual, to do everything.
No, Paul understood that God's working in the heart of Titus.
And what a joy to understand what Paul recognizes in verse 16
and how Paul rejoices in verse 16.
But then we notice in verse 17 how Titus responded.
Number three, notice how Titus responded.
Notice the Bible says,
for indeed, then notice this phrase,
he accepted the exhortation.
He accepted the exhortation.
You know, it says that, but being more forward of his own accord, he went unto you.
And so we find that in verse 17 when we look and couple the truth together in verse 16
that God was working and it says that he put the same earnest care
into the heart of Titus for you.
God did that.
That wasn't something that Titus just worked up on his own.
That wasn't something that Paul on his own just put that into the heart of Titus.
No, Paul recognized it's God that's doing the work.
And then the Bible says, for indeed, he accepted the exhortation,
and it reveals to us, but being more forward of his own accord, he went unto you.
I begin to look at this response of Titus,
and the reality is that as God is moving and God is working,
there's different responses that people can have to God's leadership.
There's the opportunity that people have.
See, when God is working and God is moving, we can resist.
We can rebel against.
Amen?
I know it's not comfortable, but the reality is that we see it throughout the Scriptures.
There are those that resist God's work in their life.
There are those that rebel against God's work.
There are those that they know the prophet of God would stand before the people
and give proclamation, and they would do exactly the opposite of what God had instructed them to do.
And then we see, as we note here in this text of Scripture, that Titus responds.
He accepted the exhortation.
I believe that this phrase, accepted the exhortation, reveals to us a couple of things about Titus.
Number one, it reveals to us that he was sensitive, that he was sensitive.
I wonder this morning, how sensitive are we to the leadership of God in our hearts and lives?
When we come to church, are we coming with an expectation of hearing from God?
Are we coming anticipating that God has a message for me as an individual,
that God desires to work in my life to do something in my heart?
See, that's how we ought to come to church.
In fact, when I pray for you each Sunday morning, and I sat in my office and prayed for each of you by name this morning,
and I pray that God would work in hearts, I pray that you would come,
and I often pray this way, a few hours before the church service is even going to happen,
God, would you help them as they wake up this morning to have hearts that are prepared
and hearts that are ready to receive, not the message from me as the messenger, but the message from God.
Because it's God's word that is preached. The preacher has the responsibility to preach the word.
And God, the Holy Spirit, will take the written word of God and speak to the hearts of God's people.
And he'll do something in your life.
But we've got to be sensitive. We've got to be sensitive.
You know, it's possible that you can enter into your own personal time of devotions.
It is possible that you can enter into a church service with a heart that is hardened,
with a heart that is distracted, with a heart that is not ready.
I mean, it's break up your fallow ground kind of a situation,
and if you've ever planted a garden, if you've ever had the opportunity to do something like that,
there's some work that has to be done to the soil after a cold winter and all that takes place
before you can just drop some seed and expect a harvest.
And our hearts are the same way.
We've got to have hearts that are sensitive, that are prepared to receive what God has for us,
that we're asking God, that we're pleading with God.
God, would you speak to me? God, would you illumine the scriptures to me?
Would you show me something I need to do, something I need to stop doing?
God, speak to me. Put something in my heart.
He was sensitive. But I also noticed that he was submissive.
For indeed, it says, he accepted the exhortation, but being more forward of his own accord, he went unto you.
Sensitivity is important. I shall say it's necessary.
But sensitivity without submission is only going halfway.
We need to have a heart of submission.
God, I'll do what you want me to do.
God, you put something in my heart, and by your grace, with your help, I'll do what you've put in my heart to do.
That I have that heart of submission.
Yes, it's absolutely necessary that we're sensitive to the leadership of the Holy Spirit of God in our hearts and our lives,
but sensitivity without submission is not the full picture that we're looking for.
And we find here in the text of Scripture that he was sensitive, but he was also submissive.
This morning, it's altogether possible for us to hear the voice of God speaking to us through the word of God,
and then rejecting it, not being submissive to it.
Saying, no thank you. I don't want to do that. I'm not interested in doing...
And it caused our heart to be hardened. It caused us to be hardened.
Submission is such an important aspect of the Christian life.
Submission to God and to his will and to his word.
See, the reality this morning is that far too often we desire, your old man desires to reign in your life,
to be the ruler of your life, to do what is most comfortable for you to do.
We have to wave that white flag of surrender.
We have to be willing to surrender to the lordship of Christ in our lives that we'd say, yes, Lord, yes.
I will do what you've led me to do.
When you put something in my heart, when you speak to me through your word, Lord, I'm going to obey.
I'm going to do what you've called me to do.
We look at this passage of scripture, these two simple verses,
and I had planned to preach all the way through verse 24 this morning,
but God just kept bringing me back to verse 16 and 17
and to this thought about God putting something in your heart, and I could not get away from it.
So I figured that I better follow the leadership of the Holy Spirit of God
and just deal with these two verses of scripture this morning.
And then I begin to evaluate my own life and ask you this morning to answer some questions
as we seek to make application from this portion of scripture, just two verses.
How is God working in your heart?
Throughout the scriptures we find that God places an emphasis on the heart.
He places an emphasis on the heart.
We find many times in the Old Testament in particular that God will tell us
and speak to us about various things that were taking place of the children of Israel
and how yes, there were times in which they would go through the motions
of bringing offerings and sacrifices and doing what they were commanded to do,
but their heart was far from Him.
They were just simply going through the motions.
Dead orthodoxy.
That's all it is, going through the motions.
Checking a box.
I read my Bible, I went to church, I did this, I did that.
That is dead orthodoxy.
And God says many times of the children of Israel that He didn't want their sacrifices,
but He's the one that ordained the sacrifices.
He's the one that instructed them to bring them.
But He says, I want your heart.
I want your heart.
We find that there are some in the Old Testament that are referenced as being those
that served God with a perfect heart.
We find that there are some that God tells us that they served God but not with a perfect heart
or not with their whole heart.
You ever watch somebody do something?
engaging in some activity and you say, they did that half-heartedly.
You ever hear that term or use that term and we know what that means, we watch somebody
do something and their whole heart's not into it, they're not completely wholly given to
whatever it is.
And the reality is that as believers, as followers of Jesus Christ, we ought to serve God with
our whole heart.
We ought to desire that God works in and through our lives and that we're submissive, sensitive
and submissive to his leadership and we find that in the Bible that God tells us that he
alone searches our hearts.
He knows our hearts.
You know that he knows the motives behind the things that we do.
He knows.
In Jeremiah chapter 17, we often reference in verse number 9, but I want you to notice
in Jeremiah, I'll read verse 9 with it, but I really want to place the emphasis in Jeremiah
17 on verse number 10 this morning because in verse number 9, it's an oft-quoted verse
of Scripture speaking about the heart.
The Bible says in Jeremiah 17 in verse number 9, the heart is deceitful and desperately
wicked.
Who can know it?
And we're familiar with that verse of Scripture and we understand that we can have a deceived
heart.
In fact, James says that if we're not doers of the word but hearers only, that we've deceived
our own selves.
We find that here he says that our heart is deceitful and desperately wicked.
Who can know it?
But I want you to notice in verse number 10 what God says, I, the Lord, search the heart.
I try the reins, even to give every man according to his ways and according to the fruit of
his doings.
Reminded of Jesus in Revelation chapter number 2 that the Bible says that he is the one that
searches the hearts.
We're mindful of the psalmist who says, search me, oh God, and know me.
Why is he saying that?
Because the reality is that God knows our hearts.
We look through the Scriptures and we find the importance of the heart.
Some have said it this way, the heart is the heart of the matter.
The heart of the matter is the heart and it's a matter of the heart and they use that back
and forth and how important that is.
The heart of the matter is a matter of the heart and what is God doing in your heart
this morning?
What is God doing in my heart?
How is God working in your life?
Paul recognizes, he sees that it's God that put this into the heart of Titus, put what?
This same earnest care for the believers in Corinth and for others that were going to
receive this offering and we find that Paul is mentioning about this work of God and he's
rejoicing and he's acknowledging how Titus accepted, he responded.
This morning, how's God working in your heart and my heart?
Notice a few verses, if you will, from the book of 2 Chronicles.
I use these few chapters because God gives us some very important truth with regard to
the heart.
2 Chronicles chapter 16 is where we'll begin and we'll look at three verses of Scripture
as we kind of just walk our way through a few verses here in the book of 2 Chronicles.
We're Old Testament, 2 Chronicles chapter 16 and I want you to notice, again, the Scriptures
place an emphasis on the heart and as we look here at these few verses of Scripture, I believe
that God reveals some things to us about the kind of heart that God works in.
See, I asked the question by way of title this morning, how is God working in your heart?
What kind of heart is God working in?
You ever think about that for a moment?
A heart that's sensitive, a heart that's submissive, that's the kind of heart that God's working
in and we find this morning in 2 Chronicles chapter 16, notice what the Bible says in
verse number 9 and I'm jumping right in the middle of a context here of a situation with
Asa as he was reigning and all that was going on, but I want you to notice the truth that
is mentioned in verse number 9, for the eyes of the Lord run to and fro throughout the
whole earth to show himself strong in the behalf of them, notice what the Bible says,
whose heart is perfect toward him.
Therein thou hast done foolishly, therefore from henceforth thou shalt have wars.
You know, as the man of God stood up, Hanani, and verse 7 is the man that's saying this
to the king, to Asa, the king of Judah, and the Bible tells us that Hanani gives, delivers
faithfully this message and notice the response of Asa in verse number 10, then Asa was wroth
with the seer.
You know, the reality is that Asa's heart was not right with God, Asa's heart was not
right with God and God brought forth a man of God, a seer, a prophet, Hanani by name,
to confront the king of Judah and to deliver this message and you know what Asa did?
He got mad at the preacher, that's what Asa did.
The Bible says he was wroth with the seer, not only did he get angry with him, but he
put him in prison.
You know, there are times in which if our heart's not right with God and yet the word
of God is going forth and the word of God is being proclaimed and we're being confronted
with the truth of God's word, we're going to do one of two things, we're going to get
right or we're going to get mad.
We're going to get right or we're going to get mad.
And here Asa got mad, he got wroth and he put him in prison.
We're told of Ahab who was a wicked king of Israel that Jehoshaphat comes along and he
made affinity with him which is a whole other message to be able to preach and the disastrous
decision that Jehoshaphat made with that situation, but the reality is that he brings these prophets
to inquire on whether they should go to battle and of course all the prophets are false prophets
and they're all saying, yeah, go to battle and Jehoshaphat has enough sense about them
to say, is there not a prophet of the Lord?
And there's one man by the name of Micaiah and Micaiah was a man that was a faithful
prophet of the Lord, but here's what Ahab says of him.
He hates him.
Why?
Because he never says anything good about me.
But you understand this truth about Ahab that the Bible says that he was the most wicked
king of Israel.
When he confronts Elijah, he confronts him as being the troubler of Israel, but the reality
is that it was Ahab's sin and wickedness and his idolatry that caused so many problems
for Israel, Micaiah.
As he comes to give word, he's really kind of threatened, hey listen, you know that all
the other prophets have given good word.
He says, I've seen them as sheep scattered.
What was he saying?
The king's going to be killed.
That's what the prophecy was.
And Ahab was so scared.
You know what he did when he went into the battle?
He told Jehoshaphat, you dress as the king and I'm going to dress as a normal guy.
Yeah, you read it.
But you know what happened?
Ahab was killed.
He was killed in battle.
Here Asa, his heart wasn't right with God and God sent a prophet, a seer, a man of God
to confront him and he got mad and put him in prison.
Look in chapter 17 if you will, Jehoshaphat, I was just talking about him a moment ago,
but look here if you will in chapter 17, 2 Chronicles 17, look in verse number 3, and
the Lord was with Jehoshaphat.
Listen, I'm thankful this morning that as a child of God that the Bible tells us that
he'll never leave us nor forsake us, amen?
But I want you to understand that we're told that we're to abide in him, we're to abide
with him, we're to walk with him.
We understand this morning that as we look at this portion of Scripture and we begin
to understand that God is with Jehoshaphat, it's because of the behavior, the heart of
Jehoshaphat, because of the character of this man, and the Bible says that because
why he walked in the first ways of his father David and sought not unto Balaam.
Praise the Lord for a man that was willing to walk with God, to obey the commandments
of God.
It says that he sought to the Lord God of his father and walked in his commandments
and not after the doings of Israel.
Verse 5, therefore the Lord established the kingdom in his hand and all Judah brought
to Jehoshaphat presence and he had riches and honor and abundance and then notice verse
number 6, and his heart was lifted up, notice what it says, in the ways of the Lord.
You know, that's a good way for a heart to be lifted up.
Oftentimes our hearts are lifted up in pride, in our own ways.
In fact, we find that through the Scriptures that when the Bible tells us about Uzziah
that he was a man that was helped of the Lord until his heart was lifted up.
He got a little bit prideful and we find that he was marvelously helped until he was strong
in verse 16, but when he was strong, his heart was lifted up to his destruction.
That's Uzziah in 2 Chronicles 26 verses 15 and 16.
But here we find that Jehoshaphat, that his heart was lifted up.
in the ways of the Lord. Moreover, he took away the high places and groves out of Judah."
I wonder this morning, is our heart lifted up in the ways of the Lord? I mean, truly
seeking the face of God and desiring that God would do in and through us what only God
could do. Again, we're looking, we're trying to examine what kind of heart does God put
something into? Because the Bible says of Titus, that Paul rejoiced, he gave thanks
to God. Why? Because God put the same earnest care into the heart of Titus for you. It was
God that put that care in the heart of Titus. And God is no respecter of persons, hallelujah.
And we find this morning that as we look at the text of scripture in 2 Corinthians chapter
number 8, we say, what is God doing in my heart? We see what God was doing in the heart
of Paul and then specifically the heart of Titus, but what is God doing in my heart?
If God's not moving and working in my heart, is there a reason? Is my heart lifted up with
pride? Is my heart hardened toward God? Do I have some bitterness that's crept into my
heart? Do I, what's, is there some sin in my life? What is it that's choked out, if
you will, God working in your heart and my heart? We find that this man, Jehoshaphat,
his heart was lifted up in the ways of the Lord. I want you to consider 2 Chronicles
chapter 34. Notice with me, this is nearing the end of the time of Judah as a nation.
Just shortly hereafter, they'll have a few more kings, but it's really just on the eve
of Babylonian captivity and they will soon be carried away, but we find that the last
real revival, if we could call it that, that took place in Judah's history is here during
the times of Josiah. Josiah was a king, he reigned, the Bible tells us he was only 8
years old when he began to reign, he was young, but the Bible tells us that he had a heart
for God. It's very interesting because we find that there were some, some tragic things
that happened between the reign of Jehoshaphat and now the reign of Josiah. And we see some
of those tragic things happening with the idolatry and the Baal worship and all that
was taking place in Judah, and we find that now as Josiah comes and he begins to reign
as the king of Judah, that we understand some things that had happened. Notice in verse
number 7, the Bible says in 2 Chronicles 34 and verse 7, and we had broken down the altars
and the groves and had beaten the graven image into powder and cut down all the idols
throughout all the land of Israel, he returned to Jerusalem. And so we find that there's
work that's being done, they're cleansing, in verse number 5, he burnt the bones of the
priests upon their altars and cleansed Judah and Jerusalem. And we begin to see what's
happening, he has a heart, in verse number 8, the end of the passage, to repair the house
of the Lord, his God. You know, it's a sad thing, but the temple that had been built
had been desecrated. They brought in false images. And all sorts of wickedness had taken
place and Josiah is seeking to cleanse. And the Bible says in verse number 14, and when
they brought out the money that was brought into the house of the Lord, Hilkiah the priest
found a book of the law of the Lord given by Moses. Well, hallelujah, the word of God.
Aren't you thankful for a Bible? And the Bible says in verse 15, and Hilkiah answered and
said to Shaphan the scribe, I have found the book of the law in the house of the Lord.
And Hilkiah delivered the book to Shaphan and Shaphan carried the book to the king and
brought the king word back again saying, all that was committed to thy servants, they do
it. I want you to notice, it says in verse 17, and they have gathered together the money
that was found in the house of the Lord and have delivered it into the hand of the overseers
and the hand of the workmen. Then Shaphan the scribe told the king saying, Hilkiah the
priest hath given me a book. And notice these words, and Shaphan read it before the king.
And Shaphan reads the book, the law of Moses, the Pentateuch. And the Bible says that it
came to pass in verse 19, when the king had heard the words of the law, that he rent his
clothes and the king commanded Hilkiah and Ahiakim, the son of Shaphan and Abdon, the
son of Micah, and Shaphan the scribe and Asai, a servant of the king saying, go and inquire
of the Lord for me and for them that are left in Israel and in Judah concerning the words
of the book that is found. For great is the wrath of the Lord that is poured out upon
us because our fathers have not kept the word of the Lord to do after all that is written
in this book. When Josiah heard the word of God, he had a heart that was tender. In fact,
in just a few verses, look if you will at verse number 27, the Bible tells us that because
thine heart was tender and thou didst humble thyself before God when thou heardest his
words against this place and against the inhabitants thereof and humblest thyself before me and
didst rent thy clothes and weep before me, I have even heard thee also saith the Lord.
You know, Josiah has a desire for others to hear in verse number 30, verse 29, then
the king sent and gathered together all the elders of Judah and Jerusalem and the king
went up into the house of the Lord and all the men of Judah and all the inhabitants of
Jerusalem and the priests and the Levites and all the people great and small, notice
what it says, and he read in their ears all the words of the book of the covenant that
was found in the house of the Lord. His heart was tender. Can I tell you their examples?
We won't take the time this morning, but Jeremiah gives a word and God gives a word to Jeremiah
and he tells his strollman, his stride, to ride on a stroll and he takes it and the Bible
tells us about the king taking a pen knife and cutting it and throwing it in a fire.
The Bible tells us of Jesus, the master teacher, the God in flesh, that when he taught we sing
the song, the wise man built his house upon the rock and the foolish man built his house
upon the sand, but in context of those portions of scripture and that song that we sing with
children so often, the Bible is referring to the one that hears and submits to versus
the one that hears and disobeys. Here's what? Here's the word of God. Because Jesus was
teaching and he taught and he said some heard and obeyed and some heard and disobeyed and
the ones that obeyed are likened unto a wise man and the ones that disobeyed are likened
unto a foolish man. This morning, just because God's word is preached, just because you go
to a church where God's word is preached doesn't mean that your heart is right with God. I'm
not saying of anyone in particular that your heart's not right with God, but I'm simply
saying as we evaluate our own lives, how is God working in my heart? What is God doing?
Is God doing anything in your life, in your heart? Is he stirring you up? Is he working?
God wants your heart. Solomon is the human penman to the book of Proverbs, but we know
that not only could you look at a human father writing to a human son, but we find that the
truth of the book of Proverbs is that God is speaking to us as his children. He says,
my son, give me thine heart. God wants your heart this morning. I believe this morning
that if he has your heart, he'll have all of you. If he has your heart, he'll have all
of you. Seek him with your whole heart. Seek his word with your whole heart. Don't just
go to portions of scripture that you already are familiar with and you think, well, this
is going to encourage me or this is going to not ruffle my feathers, this isn't going
to convict me or step on my toes. No, we need the whole counsel of God. We need all of it.
Let me remind you of what Psalm 119 says. You can turn there if you'd like. In Psalm
119, we read in this lengthy chapter a portion of scripture that is so powerful about God's
word and how precious God's word is. But as we begin reading, the Bible says in verse
number one, blessed are the undefiled in the way who walk in the law of the Lord. Notice
verse two, Psalm 119 and verse number two, blessed are they that keep his testimonies
that seek him, what's the Bible say? With the whole heart. Skip down if you will, look
at verse number ten. With my whole heart have I sought thee. Oh, let me not wander from
thy commandments. Thy word have I hid where? In mine heart that I might not sin against
thee. This morning we could look at more verses, verse after verse after verse of how important
our hearts are to God.
We see that Paul, as he's in the midst of writing to the church in Corinth about this
grace-giving, about this offering, he commends the churches of Macedonia, and he says they
were in a great affliction, deep poverty, but they gave sacrificially, they gave liberally,
they gave of their own selves.
And then he, Paul, is going to challenge, after commending the churches of Macedonia,
he's going to challenge the believers in Corinth that they would abound in this grace also,
that they would be complete, mature, that they would not leave one part undone while
they're doing another.
And we find that we receive that challenge, and then as he's going to report about the
sending of the offering and all that takes place, we find that in the midst of that,
he pauses just for a moment to thank God for what God did in the heart of Titus, and
how God put into the heart of Titus the same care for you.
And I ask the question this morning, what is God doing in your heart?
What is God doing in my heart?
Is God working in our hearts?
Are you sensitive to His leadership?
Are you desiring, as you spend time with God daily in His Word, are you desiring that
God would speak to you?
Are you responding in obedience?
Because I found in my life that as we respond and we obey, that God continues to work and
God continues to do something in our hearts.
If God reveals something to you, if God puts something in your heart and you resist it,
if you rebel against it, don't expect God to keep putting more things on your heart.
It's those that are sensitive that have submitted that God continues to work.
You know, it's a wonderful thing when God works in the heart of an individual.
It's a wonderful thing when you know that God's put something in your heart.
It's a wonderful thing when you know that God's done it, that God's moving and working
and He's stirring you up and He's doing something in your heart.
It's a wonderful thing to be able to see in the lives of others, as Paul does in the life
of Titus, that God is at work, that it's God that's doing it.
I'm going to close this morning with a statement from Nehemiah.
In Nehemiah chapter number 2, we find that we do not have time this morning, but chapter
1, he receives a report of all that's gone on and how the condition of the city.
He weeps and he mourns and he fasts and he seeks the face of God.
Chapter number 2, he's before the king.
He was the king's cupbearer.
The Bible says that the king recognized his countenance being sad and the king noted that
it was nothing else but sorrow of heart.
God works in the heart of the king, granting Nehemiah opportunity to go to Jerusalem.
We come to verse number 11.
The Bible says, so I came to Jerusalem and was there three days.
In verse number 12, notice what the Bible says, I arose in the night, I and some few
men with me.
Notice what it says, neither told I any man what my God had put in my heart to do at Jerusalem.
Neither was there any beast with me save the beast that I rode upon.
They go forth and they begin to see, to take note of what's going on there in the city.
You find in verse 17, the Bible says, then I said unto them, ye see the distress that
we are in, how Jerusalem lieth waste and the gates thereof are burned with fire.
Come and let us build up the wall of Jerusalem that we be no more a reproach.
Then I told them, notice what it says, then I told them of the hand of my God which was
good upon me, as also the king's words that he had spoken unto me, and they said, let
us rise up and build so they strengthen their hands for this good work.
See, in the beginning in verse number 12, he knew that God put something in his heart.
He took those men on a journey first, and he showed them what was going on, and then
he spoke to them, and he told them, and he revealed to them, and it says that he told
them in verse 18, of the hand of my God which was good upon me.
He had referenced that in verse number 8, according to the good hand of my God upon
me.
See, Nehemiah knew God put something in his heart, and he put something in his heart that
he could have no rest until he fulfilled what God had put in his heart.
I just wonder this morning, what's God doing in your heart?
How's God moving in your life?
What is God doing?
Can I tell you this morning that the hour is late?
There's much work to be accomplished for the cause of Christ.
There's a world that needs to hear that Jesus saves.
The Bible tells us that Jesus gave this prayer request.
He said that the harvest is plenteous, but the labors are few.
Pray therefore the Lord of the harvest that he would send forth laborers into his harvest.
There's a work to do.
And what's God put in your heart?
How's God using his word?
How's the spirit of God using the word of God in your heart as a child of God?
Because if you're saved this morning, you're a child of God.
And if you're a child of God this morning, we're saying saved, saved.
And can it be?
Hallelujah.
I'm so thankful that I'm saved by the grace of God.
If I'm a child of God, that means God my Father wants to work in my heart, and he wants to
work in your heart.
And as we quickly this morning just look at a few examples of what kind of heart does
God work in?
We ask ourselves the question, what is God doing in my heart?
Yes, I understand that Paul is referencing what God is doing in the heart of Titus, but
this morning I'm not asking you to look at somebody else's life to evaluate what God's
doing in their heart.
I'm asking you this morning to evaluate your own life and say, what is God doing in my
heart?
Is God working?
And I hope that this morning we can say He is and here's how He's working.
And if not, I would encourage you, do business with God.
Listen, if God's not working in your heart, if God has worked in your heart at some point
and then He's not, you long for God to work in your heart.
You want that.
You want God to be using His Word to challenge you and convict you and change you and give
you that burden.
So what is God doing in your heart?
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
God, I pray this morning the Holy Spirit would take the Word of God and work.
It's not for any individual to come and tell me necessarily what You're doing in their
heart, but God, for us each individually to examine ourselves.
Are You working?
How are You working in our hearts?
I pray that in this moment of invitation, if there's one that's lost, that's not sure
of heaven, that today they would come forth, have a Bible that we could take and show them
how they could know for sure that heaven is their home.
And then God, I pray for Your people, those that are saved, God, maybe there's some here
that say, to be honest, God's not really working in my heart.
I've not spent time with Him in His Word as I should.
I have a hard heart.
I have a bitter heart.
God's not working.
We need to get that right with God this morning so that once again He could work in your heart
and your life.
Maybe this morning you know how God is working.
You could articulate it clearly.
Maybe this morning you need to come and just thank God that He's working in your heart.
Don't take it for granted.
Praise Him for it.
Rejoice that He's working.
God, I commit these moments to You.
I pray that You'd move and work as only You can.
We'll give You the glory for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would You stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano and as she does, the altar is open.