of Psalms will be in Psalm 23.
And if you've already looked at the back of the bulletin,
you'll see that we're doing part one and part two
for this morning and this evening.
And looking at this very familiar Psalm,
of course, Psalm 23 is probably just as familiar
as the song that we just sang, Amazing Grace.
In fact, I've been to a number of funerals over my life
where even not being a church funeral
like what we would have here,
many times people still will use that song, Amazing Grace,
and still reference Psalm 23.
It's very familiar to us.
But I hope this morning that even though
this is a familiar Psalm,
that God would help us to be attentive
and really get a truth that God has for us.
The Bible says this beginning in verse number one.
I'm not gonna preach through the whole Psalm,
but I wanna read the entire Psalm
at the beginning of the message this morning.
The Bible says,
The Lord is my shepherd, I shall not want.
He maketh me to lie down in green pastures.
He leadeth me beside the still waters.
He restoreth my soul.
He leadeth me in the paths of righteousness
for his namesake.
Yea, though I walk through the valley
of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil
for thou art with me.
Thy rod and thy staff, they comfort me.
Thou preparest a table before me
in the presence of mine enemies.
Thou anointest my head with oil,
my cup runneth over.
Surely goodness and mercy shall follow me
all the days of my life,
and I will dwell in the house of the Lord forever.
The song that we just sang in this Psalm
goes so well together.
I didn't pick the songs, Dean always does,
but it's always a blessing to me.
And you have those weeks when they just
go together so well.
And this morning as we look at this particular Psalm,
again a very familiar Psalm,
it's full of powerful truth
and really not part of the message,
but certainly important to deal with.
Notice in the very beginning of this Psalm
that the psalmist, the human penman
that God used to write the Psalm is David.
And the Bible says, the Lord is my shepherd.
And I want you to just think about that truth
just for a moment this morning.
He is the shepherd, he's the good shepherd,
he's the great shepherd, he's the chief shepherd.
But notice that David says, the Lord is my shepherd.
And that possessive truth that we find
in this particular Psalm,
he says the Lord is my shepherd.
And I wonder this morning,
how many of us could say,
I'm not gonna ask you to raise your hands,
but how many of us could say this morning with David
that the Lord is my shepherd?
Not just that he is the shepherd
or the good shepherd and so on and so forth,
but the Lord is my shepherd.
I would say to you this morning,
there's only one way for the Lord to be your shepherd.
And that's through accepting him
as your personal Lord and savior.
In John chapter number 10,
and we'll actually look at some of those verses
this morning, the Bible teaches us
in that portion of scripture
that Jesus is the good shepherd.
And the good shepherd layeth down his life for the sheep.
And he says this in verse number 27,
as you go through the end of that chapter,
he says this, my sheep hear my voice
and I know them and I give unto them eternal life
and they shall never perish.
And so it's interesting as you compare
those two portions of scripture
that here, David says the Lord is my shepherd.
There, Jesus says, my sheep hear my voice.
And this morning, I hope that you have assurance
that Jesus is your shepherd,
that the Lord is your shepherd.
We'll deal with a few things
as we get into the message this morning.
And if you're not sure of that, man,
we'd love today for you to have that level of confidence.
But I want you to see as we look at this psalm
at the bookends by way of introduction,
the last statement of this psalm in verse number six says,
I will dwell in the house of the Lord forever.
And I want you to understand there is a great connection
between verse number one and verse number six.
The truth of verse number one,
the Lord is my shepherd is the basis
for the truth in verse number six,
that I will dwell in the house of the Lord forever.
You cannot this morning say that I will dwell
in the house of the Lord forever
if you do not know the Lord as your shepherd.
And we find that there's a great connection
between verse one and verse six
and so many wonderful truths that are packed in between.
But I'm thankful this morning
that I will dwell in the house of the Lord forever
because the Lord is my shepherd.
We think about this even the terminology.
Someone sent me a text this week
and it was kind of interesting the way
that the text kind of worked even with this thought here
from verse number six.
Notice it's the house of who?
It's the house of the Lord.
The Lord is there.
And that's what makes heaven heaven
is the fact that Jesus is there.
And what a tremendous blessing.
But we think about this particular psalm
and so many rich truths that are contained within this psalm.
But I really wanna focus our attention this day,
this morning and this evening
on that last phrase in verse number five
where the psalmist says, my cup runneth over.
My cup runneth over.
The imagery of this statement is beautiful.
No doubt in your mind and in mine
when you read that statement, my cup runneth over,
you think about the abundance,
you think about the extra, if you will,
and you find that this imagery
of this single statement of God's word,
it reveals to us the goodness of God
in the lives of His children.
And certainly this morning,
I believe that every one of us would agree
that God has been abundantly good to us,
that God has blessed us beyond measure,
that even as I prayed this morning,
as the psalmist says, that the Lord hath daily,
He's daily loadeth me with benefits.
It's not just He's sprinkled them upon us,
no, He's loaded us with benefits.
And what a blessing.
I'm sure at some point in your life,
I've heard it often in my life
that you've heard somebody speaking about the idea
of whether an individual is an optimist or a pessimist.
How many have heard people talk about this before?
And oftentimes what they'll use
is they'll use a metaphor of a cup of water.
And in using that metaphor,
they'll say, are you a half full
or half empty kind of a person?
You've heard that before.
And they use that terminology,
they use that metaphor in order to try to help us determine
are you an optimist or a pessimist?
And we've heard that and people have used that,
but I would submit to you this morning
that as a child of the King,
I'm thankful this morning that my cup's not half full,
my cup's not half empty, my cup runneth over.
My cup runneth over.
And this morning, as we see the psalmist boldly declaring
and making the statement as our minds are fixed this week
on the subject of Thanksgiving and we have this holiday,
listen, it's not just that we'd sit around
and fill ourselves with all of these particular items
that find themselves on the menu of Thanksgiving.
It's not that we'd sit around and just watch football
or have family time and that sort of thing.
No, we must recognize the giver of all good gifts.
And surely each of us this morning
should be able to say my cup runneth over.
My cup runneth over.
This morning and this evening,
I want to provide for you 10 reasons,
10 biblical reasons that every child of God
should say my cup runneth over.
My cup runneth over.
Number one, if you're taking notes, my shepherd loves me.
My shepherd loves me.
I hope that you never get over that.
I sang this morning, one of the songs
that we sang in Sunday school this morning
was Jesus loves me.
What a precious, precious truth of God's word.
The songwriter of that particular song
said Jesus loves me, this I know.
It's not a hope so, it's not a think so,
it's not I hope Jesus, no, I know that Jesus loves me.
Why?
For the Bible tells me so.
And I'm so thankful that God and his word
has declared to us his love for us
and he's revealed to us his love for us.
And we find this morning that our shepherd,
my shepherd, my shepherd loves me.
Nothing can separate me from the love of God,
which is in Christ Jesus.
Look at a few verses of scripture with me
and have your hands ready this morning.
We'll look at a number of scriptures this morning.
But notice in John chapter number three,
and I want you to read it this morning.
For so many of us this morning, we could quote John 3.16.
It's a very familiar verse of scripture.
But I want you to read it this morning and look at it.
I want you to allow the Lord to use the word of God
to impress upon your heart and to encourage you this morning
with this truth that God loves you.
You know, there's some folks in our world today
that they feel like they're not loved.
They feel like no one loves me, no one cares about me,
no one knows.
Listen, I'm thankful this morning
that no matter what's going on in your life,
no matter what trial you're facing,
no matter what hardship we're enduring,
that we can rejoice and we can say my cup runneth over.
Listen, just if this was the only point today,
my cup runneth over because God loves me.
That's enough, but there's so much more.
The 10 reasons that I'm gonna give you
between this morning and this evening, it's not exhaustive.
We could go on and on and on.
But this morning, look at John 3.
The Bible says this in verse number 16.
For God so loved the world
that he gave his only begotten Son
that whosoever believeth in him shall not die.
who believeth in him should not perish, but have everlasting life.
Notice verse 17,
For God sent not his Son into the world to condemn the world,
but that the world through him might be saved.
You know, we were condemned already.
But I'm thankful this morning because the Lord is my shepherd
and because my shepherd loves me that I no longer,
there's no condemnation for those who believe
and praise the Lord for that wonderful truth.
And we find here this morning that the Bible says,
For God so loved the world.
And someone says, well, you don't understand what I've done.
God does, and he still says that he loves you.
Praise God for that.
Because at times, if we'd be honest,
we're not very lovable.
Amen.
But God loves you and he loves me.
My shepherd loves me.
Romans five and verse number eight,
a verse that's very familiar to us.
And the Bible says there that God commended his love toward us.
And that while we were yet sinners,
Christ died for us.
And I think about the demonstration of God's love.
He declared it, but he demonstrated it.
And he said, I loved you so much that I died for you,
that I took your place.
And we find that that was his demonstration of his love.
But I want you to look at Romans eight.
And it's the passage that a lot of times we'll go to
when we think about the love of Christ
and how thankful we ought to be this morning
that my shepherd loves me.
In Romans chapter number eight and verse number 35,
the question is asked,
who shall separate us from the love of Christ?
We'll read all the verses,
but I'm thankful this morning that the answer is nothing.
There's nothing that can separate you
from the love of Christ.
The Bible says,
shall tribulation or distress or persecution
or famine or nakedness or peril or sword,
as it is written, for thy sake,
we are killed all the day long.
We are accounted as sheep for the slaughter.
Nay, in all these things, we are more than conquerors.
Notice, through him that loved us.
Notice what the writer says, Paul, the human penman.
He says, I am persuaded.
I am persuaded of what?
That neither death nor life nor angels nor principalities
nor powers nor things present nor things to come
nor height, nor depth,
nor any other creature shall be able to separate us
from the love of God, which is in Christ Jesus, our Lord.
I hope this morning that you would say my cup runneth over.
Why? Because my shepherd loves me.
My shepherd loves me.
There's some times in your life that the enemy might,
he's the accuser of the brethren, by the way.
He might whisper in your ear that God doesn't love you.
If he really loved you, he wouldn't, listen,
nothing can separate us from the love of God.
The songwriter said, this I know, Jesus loves me.
This I know.
Why? For the Bible tells me so.
He didn't say because my circumstances tell me so.
He didn't say because my feelings tell me so.
He said, because the Bible tells me so.
And our emotions and our feelings and our circumstances
do not dictate to us what is truth.
It is God's word that reveals to us what is truth.
And so number one this morning,
why would I say my cup runneth over?
Because my shepherd loves me.
Number two, not only because my shepherd loves me,
but my shepherd died for me.
My shepherd died for me.
It shows me the love of God,
but it also reveals to me as I think about the love of God,
demonstrate it through the fact
that the Lord Jesus Christ died for me.
It shows me the value that he's placed upon my life
and upon your life.
He loved you so much that he was willing to die for you.
You say, pastor, why did Jesus have to die?
Well, because sin had to be paid for.
The Bible says that the soul that sinneth, it shall die.
And we find that the Bible tells us
that the wages of sin is death.
And we find this morning that all have sinned
and come short of the glory of God.
Every single one of us that are sitting here this morning
have sinned.
We are guilty before a holy God.
Every one of us.
You say, well, I'm not as bad as,
I don't care if you're not as bad as, you're guilty.
And by the way, it's funny how we always try
to find somebody worse off than we are
to compare ourselves to,
when we wanna try to make ourselves feel like we're good.
But we're all guilty.
Some of us this morning,
we've trusted the Lord Jesus Christ, our savior,
so we are saved sinners.
Amen?
We are heaven-bound sinners.
But this morning, when we understand the truth
that Jesus died for me, my shepherd died for me,
we find in John chapter number 10,
and I want you to look in John 10.
It's a powerful passage of scripture.
In fact, between this morning and this evening,
we're gonna look at a number of verses
from John chapter number 10
and how the correlation, the connection
between Psalm 23 and John 10,
it's so obvious and so powerful.
And we find that here,
Jesus begins in verse number one of John 10,
and he says, verily, verily,
this is of a truth of a truth.
God's word is truth.
Jesus Christ himself is truth.
And he says this, I say unto you,
he that entereth not by the door into the sheepfold,
but climbeth up some other way,
the same as a thief and a robber,
but he that entereth in by the door
is the shepherd of the sheep.
I'm thankful this morning the Lord is my shepherd.
And we mentioned that already,
but we find that as we look through
this portion of scripture,
that not only is Jesus going to declare to us
that he is the shepherd, that he is the door,
but you find that he's going to reveal to us
that as our shepherd, he took our place
and he died for us.
In verse three, to him, the porter openeth
and the sheep hear his voice
and he calleth his own sheep,
notice his own sheep by name,
and leadeth them out.
And when he put forth his own sheep,
he goeth before them and the sheep follow him,
for they know his voice.
And a stranger will they not follow,
but will flee from him,
for they know not the voice of a stranger's.
It says this, this parable spake Jesus unto them,
but they understood not what things they were
which he spake unto them.
And this happened often during the earthly ministry
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
He would teach and there would be some uncertainty
as to what is the meaning,
what is the message that he's seeking to teach us.
And so what does Jesus do?
Well, he gives more explanation.
And I'm thankful that he's a loving,
gracious, patient God.
And you go to God's word and there are times
in which we don't understand
and we can say, Lord, would you help me to understand?
And here, notice what Jesus says to them
after they understood not according to verse number six.
He says, verily, verily, I say unto you,
notice he makes it very plain,
I am the door of the sheep.
All that ever came before me are thieves and robbers,
but the sheep did not hear them.
I am the door.
By me, if any man enter in, he shall be saved
and shall go in and out and find pasture.
Notice the contrast in verse 10 for the thief,
cometh not but for to steal and to kill and to destroy.
I am come that they might have life
and that they might have it more abundantly.
I am the good shepherd.
Notice what he says,
the good shepherd giveth his life for the sheep.
Why does my cup runneth over?
Because my shepherd died for me.
He died for me.
I was guilty.
You were guilty.
We deserve death.
Not only do we deserve physical death,
but we deserve spiritual death.
And really, that's what's being spoken of
when the Bible says the wage of sin is death.
It's yes, death is the result,
physical death, the result of sin,
but the wage of sin is that second death,
that spiritual death.
And here, the Bible says that the good shepherd
giveth his life for the sheep.
He did for me and he did for you
what we could not do for ourselves.
And he died for us.
He took our place.
And we sing the song sometimes at Christmas time,
sometimes at Easter, about it was for me.
And it was for me that he went
and he went to that cross and he died an awful death.
And I'm so thankful that he didn't stay dead.
He went to a borrowed tomb
and he rose conquering sin, death, and the grave.
He's alive forevermore.
But we find this morning that my shepherd died for me.
Notice in verse number 15, it says this,
"'And the Father knoweth me, even so know I the Father,
"'and I lay down my life for the sheep.'"
He says this, "'And other sheep I have,
"'which are not of this fold, them also I must bring,
"'and they shall hear my voice,
"'and there shall be one fold and one shepherd.
"'Therefore doth my Father love me, why?
"'Because I lay down my life, then I might take it again.'"
Notice the powerful truth in verse 18.
"'No man taketh it from me.'"
He said, but then the Romans arrest him
and no man taketh it, he lays it down.
He went willingly to that cross.
He suffered all that he did willingly
so that you and I could be redeemed.
Notice this is in verse 18,
"'But I lay it down on myself.
"'I have power to lay it down
"'and I have power to take it again.
"'This commandment have I received of my Father.'"
If you were to look at the record of the crucifixion,
Pilate was so confused
when he heard that Jesus was dead already.
Why?
Because of the timing.
But remember, Jesus said it is finished
and he gave up the ghost is what the Bible tells us.
And he laid down his life for us.
He died for us because he loves us.
And we find this morning
that why should we live through life?
Why should we walk through life?
And echo the words of the psalmist
that my cup runneth over.
Listen, this idea of my cup is half full or half empty
is nonsense for the child of God.
we ought to be my cup runneth over kind of people
because my shepherd loves me and because my shepherd died for me.
He did for me what I could not do for myself.
I remember it was just over a year ago
that I stood in the very place there in Israel
where I had the opportunity, and I thank the Lord for it,
to be in the place where most likely Jesus,
when he was arrested and kept overnight
with the situation at Caiaphas' house and all that took place,
and to be able to see and to remember
being in the Garden of Gethsemane and all that took place
and thinking about all that my Savior endured for me
and going to the place Golgotha, the place of a skull,
and thinking about that place where my Savior died for me.
But then seeing there's an empty tomb
because he rose, conquering sin, death, and the grave.
Listen, this morning, my faith is not based on being at that place.
My faith is in a person and in the truth of God's Word.
You may never have the opportunity on this side of eternity
to be able to be in Jerusalem and see those places personally,
but I tell you this morning that I'm so thankful
that God's given us the truth in his Word, that he died for us.
It is a settled fact of history.
It is a biblical truth that Jesus died for me.
Notice with me 1 Peter 3.
Notice this wonderful truth that God gives us
when it could impact you and me this morning to go through life.
Listen, my shepherd died for me.
In 1 Peter 3, in verse number 18,
the Bible says,
For Christ also hath once suffered for sins.
He suffered on that cross.
I want you to notice the emphasis that once suffered for sins.
This man, according to Hebrews chapter number 10,
made one sacrifice for sin forever.
Hallelujah.
And what a blessing.
He sat down at the right hand of the throne of God.
But the Bible says, notice in verse 18,
The just for the unjust.
The just is Jesus.
The unjust is every other person that's ever walked upon the face of the earth.
The unjust.
He died for us.
The just for the unjust.
Why?
That he might bring us to God.
Being put to death in the flesh but quickened by the Spirit.
There are many other verses that we could look to this morning,
but I want to say to you from this verse of Scripture
that the only way that he could bring us to God
was through dying in our place.
It's the only way.
There's no other way that he could bring us to God.
He could not just arbitrarily decide that,
Oh yeah, I'm going to let all these people go to hell.
He had to die for us.
It was the only way for man to be reconciled
and we'll deal with that in just a few moments.
But notice with me a third reason.
Number one, my shepherd loves me.
Number two, my shepherd died for me.
Number three, my shepherd found me.
My shepherd found me.
You know, you've probably heard people use at times,
and I understand what they mean by it,
but they'll say something like this,
I found the Lord.
You've heard people say that, use that terminology.
And I believe truly the biblical record would reveal to us
that I really didn't find Jesus, he found me.
Amen?
The reality this morning is that we have a shepherd
that cares about us, a shepherd that loves us
and died for us and he found me.
I begin to think about my own life
and I begin to think about my childhood and my upbringing
and I begin to think about how the gospel was brought to me.
And maybe this morning you'd spend a few moments
and thinking in your own mind of how the gospel was brought to you.
Maybe the circumstances that led to you hearing the gospel for the first time.
Maybe it was somebody that God used at a workplace.
Maybe it was a neighbor.
Maybe it was a family member that introduced you to the Lord Jesus Christ.
I think about my children and my children have a different story than I have
because they were raised in a Christian home.
They were raised in a home where they heard the gospel from a young age.
They were raised in a home where we went to church from the day they were born
and they don't know anything different.
And some of you have that same testimony.
But some of us, we don't have that testimony.
I wasn't raised in church.
I didn't hear the gospel when I was a kid.
Someone said to me when I was about 12 years old,
do you want to go to heaven when you die?
And it's like, well, I mean, what's the alternative?
I don't want to go to hell.
Sure, I want to go to heaven.
But how was I going to get to heaven?
I had no idea how I was going to get to heaven.
I never understood why Jesus died.
I never knew that Jesus loved me.
But there was a man that shared the gospel with my dad.
He shared the testimony here before.
And because of that, I found out the truth of the gospel.
And in your life and in my life, I think about how Jesus found us.
The Bible tells us in Luke 19 in verse number 10,
and this description is wonderful
as we think about the truth that is found for us.
Of course, there's a parable about the,
as Jesus speaks to the folks there
and how the 99 and the shepherd would leave
to search for the one and so on and so forth.
But I find this morning that as I look at Luke 19
and I understand the account that is provided,
there's a man by the name of Zacchaeus in Luke 19.
And we're familiar with Zacchaeus.
Zacchaeus was a man that was not very well liked.
Let's put it that way.
And he was a man that was of little stature, the Bible tells us.
But he's a man that as we look at this text of Scripture,
he's a man that gets saved.
He has salvation.
But I want you to notice what Jesus says in Luke 19 in verse number 10.
For the Son of Man is come to seek and to save that which was lost.
To seek and to save.
Why did Jesus pass through Jericho on this particular day?
Because there was a sinner that needed to be saved.
Why did Jesus say in John chapter number 4,
I must needs go through Samaria?
Because there was a woman that was going to be at the well
that needed to hear the truth of the gospel.
Jesus found me.
I'm so thankful that my shepherd found me this morning.
Can you imagine this morning?
It's hard for me to even wrap my mind around it.
Can you imagine being lost?
I mean, not knowing that if you were to die today that you'd go to heaven.
I'm not talking about hoping that you'd go to heaven.
I'm talking about knowing.
Because the Lord is my shepherd.
In verse number 6, I shall dwell in the house of the Lord forever.
My shepherd, he loves me.
My shepherd died for me.
My shepherd found me.
He found me.
And he found you.
I don't know where he found you, but I know where he found me.
And I'm so thankful he found me.
Number 4 this morning, my shepherd cares for me.
It's amazing to me that he loves me.
He died for me.
He found me.
But then he cares about me.
I mean, he doesn't just leave me to my own resources.
He doesn't just leave me on my own.
No, he cares about every aspect of my life.
And he cares about you this morning.
We sing the song, no one ever cared for me like Jesus.
And I hope this morning that you can acknowledge that truth.
If you know the Lord Jesus Christ as your personal Savior,
you'd say, my shepherd cares about me.
When it seems like no one else cares.
No doubt there's times in your life that you might feel like no one cares.
No one even knows.
No one understands.
I would tell you this morning that Jesus cares.
I know he cares.
That's what the songwriter says.
The question is asked, it's a different song.
I spoke about no one ever cared for me like Jesus, but there's another.
Does Jesus care?
Yes, he cares.
I know he cares.
Why do I know he cares?
Because he's told me in his word again.
And that's a wonderful truth.
Remember, it's not based on your feelings.
It's not based on your emotions.
It's not based on your circumstances.
It's based on truth that God has given us in his word.
And this morning, I know that my shepherd cares for me.
Notice in 1 Peter 5, again, familiar verses of scripture.
But I hope this morning that when we consider these 10 truths,
and we'll look at 5 here this morning, and we'll look at 5 this evening.
But I hope this morning when you consider these things,
that you would walk through your life and say, man, my cup, surely, it runs over.
My cup runneth over.
God has been so good to me.
Listen, sometimes as God's people, we can complain with the best of them.
Amen?
We can go through life complaining and murmuring just like a lost person would.
In fact, there are times that some lost people might be more thankful than some of God's people.
Amen?
I know no one wants to admit that, but it's true.
But my cup runneth over.
It's perspective.
Notice in 1 Peter 5, in verse number 7, the Bible says,
casting all your care upon him, for he careth for you.
He didn't say cast some of your care on him.
He didn't say cast most of your care on him.
He said casting all.
Listen, he can handle it.
You can't.
He can handle it.
I can't handle it, but God can.
You know, it's an amazing thing that we can take it to Jesus.
Tell it to Jesus.
We can just take it.
it and tell it to him. We can cast our care upon him. You know, sometimes when we think
about that truth of leave your burden, like, you know, leave it there, imagery sometimes
in our minds would go to an old-fashioned altar and we pour our heart before God and
pour out, cast our burden upon him. But sometimes we get up from praying and we take it right
back with us. It's hard as human beings, our minds, it's hard. But he says, casting all
your care upon him. I hope you can see the imagery of that idea of casting something
down. I mean, I'm putting this at the feet of Jesus because he cares for me. He cares
for me. Notice in verse number, in Psalm 55, turn over if you will to Psalm 55, a sister
verse here to what we see in 1 Peter 5 and verse number 7. And thinking about this truth
this morning that Jesus, my shepherd, he cares for me. This morning he cares for you. He
cares for you. In Psalm 55, in verse number 22, the Bible says, cast thy burden upon
the Lord. Casting all your care upon him, we read in 1 Peter 5, 7, why? For he careth
for you. Here we find in Psalm 55 and verse 22, cast thy burden upon the Lord and he
shall sustain thee. He shall never suffer the righteous to be moved. Now let me think
about, let's look at this verse a moment. He didn't say, cast thy burden upon the Lord
and he might sustain thee. He didn't even say, cast thy burden upon the Lord and he
can sustain thee. Right? Listen, I'm thankful that he can, but if the verse just said that
he can, it wouldn't carry as much weight. Do you agree? Because certainly some people
can do some things, but it doesn't mean they're going to. Amen? People that can do some things,
but they don't do it. Here the Bible says, cast thy burden upon the Lord and he shall
sustain thee. You say, I just can't go anymore. Have you cast your burden upon the Lord? Because
the Bible says he shall sustain thee. Amen? I'm not seeking to be lacking any kind of
comfort or being compassionate, but I'm simply saying this morning that are we going to take
God at his word? Because God said in his word that he shall sustain us. He's the sustainer.
I'm thankful he's the giver of life, but he's the sustainer. Remember what he said in John
10? I've come to give them a life that they might have it more abundantly. Notice the
rest of the verse in verse 22. He shall never suffer the righteous to be moved. I'm thankful
that he'll sustain us. Sometimes part of the problem is that we're not doing the first
part of the verse. We're not casting our burden upon the Lord. We're not receiving that sustaining
power of God. We're not receiving what we could receive. Why? Because we're keeping
the burden ourselves. We're keeping the cares to ourselves, but God says, no, I want you
to know how much I care about you. I want you to know that you can cast your care upon
the Lord. Listen, this morning I'm thankful that I'm saved. I'm thankful that I'm heaven
bound, but I will say to you this morning that the moment that you got saved, all of
your cares did not just disappear. All of your problems did not cease. Your life did
not become perfect on this earth. Am I right? So isn't it good to know the Lord that sustains
you, that says cast your burden, that says cast your care? This morning, if you're not
sure of heaven, you've never trusted Christ as your savior. The reality is that when you
trust Christ, it doesn't mean he's going to fix all your problems immediately and everything
is just going to be, somebody said it this way, a bed of roses. I remember hearing that
many years ago and I said, well, you know that roses have thorns, right? And I don't
know that I want to be in a bed of roses anyway, amen? But I understand the imagery. I understand
the metaphor, the reason that they would use that statement. But this morning, listen,
understand that I'm thankful that I have someone that I know personally, the Lord is my shepherd
and I can cast my care upon him. I can cast my burden upon him. Why? Because he's my shepherd.
Because he's my God. He's my savior. And he's your savior. Is my life going to be problem
free? No. Listen, if somebody ever tells you that, they're lying to you. If someone tells
you that you trust Christ and your life's going to be problem free, they are lying to
you. Amen? One day, absolutely. When this mortal shall put off immortality or should
put on immortality, this corruption should put on incorruption, 1 Corinthians 15. Oh
yeah, at that time, I'm going to have no more problems. But until then, our lives are going
to have difficulties. But I know the shepherd, the Lord is my shepherd and I can cast my
burden. I can cast all my care upon him. Why? Because my shepherd cares about me. This morning,
my cup runneth over. My cup runneth over. Number five this morning, my shepherd provides
for me. My shepherd provides for me. You know, there's something interesting about sheep.
Turn back to Psalm 23, if you will. There's something interesting about sheep. Sheep are
really kind of helpless animals. They really are. They're defenseless. Sheep need a shepherd.
There's an enemy. We can read about the natural predators to sheep and you can see in the
scriptures even some of the examples that God gives us. But we have an enemy, Satan,
the devil. The Bible says that he walketh about seeking whom he may devour. And I'm
thankful that my God, my shepherd, he provides for me. He provides protection for me. He
provides everything that I need. And I think about the sheep as they are such needy animals.
And the shepherd, the shepherd provides for them. And here in Psalm 23 and verse number
1, the Bible says, the Lord is my shepherd. Notice the next words, I shall not want. I
shall not want. It's amazing how a shepherd, a good shepherd, takes care of his sheep.
Our God is a good shepherd. The Lord is the good shepherd. He's been good to us and he
provides for us. The Bible says in verse number 2 of Psalm 23, he maketh me to lie
down in green pastures. Listen, I'm thankful for the, again, the imagery that we see here
in this 23rd Psalm. He didn't just say in pastures, he said in green pastures. Representing
to us and understanding to us the sustenance and the nourishment that the sheep would receive.
Why? Because it's a green pasture. Notice it says this, he leadeth me beside what? The
still waters. Why the still waters? Because sheep can't drink from rushing waters. They
can't. They need still waters. This morning, we see how the shepherd provides. We see how
my shepherd provides for me. But I would submit to you this morning that as we look at this
phrase or these words of Scripture in Psalm 23 and where our mind is rushing to the truth
of understanding that my shepherd provides for me, I want you to understand this morning
that the greatest need of mankind is salvation. The absolute number one greatest need of mankind
is salvation, reconciliation, being reconciled to God. Why? Because our sin separates us
from God. Our sin separates us from God. You say, well my sin is not really that bad. No,
your sin is bad. I say that with all grace and humility because grace, because sin is
offensive to a holy God. You say, well how much sin separates me from God? One. You say,
but I've worked really hard to keep all of this and do all of these things. It's not
how it works. You can't be reconciled to God that way. James says if we've offended in
one point we're guilty of all. And we find here this morning that the greatest need of
every human being, the greatest need that you have this morning is to be reconciled
to God, to be saved. You say, pastor I'm saved. Well then your greatest need has been met.
And simply because of that truth we should say my cup runneth over. Because my greatest
need has been met. If you're here this morning and you've never trusted the Lord Jesus Christ
your personal Savior, you say I have no idea what this is all about. I don't have that
kind of assurance. I don't know that the Lord is my shepherd personally. I don't know if
I were to die today that I'd go to heaven. I mean I hope I would but I don't know for
sure. I would say to you this morning that he wants to save you today. He wants to provide
for you today your greatest need and save your soul. Because the Lord, the shepherd,
my shepherd, he provides for me. And he knows what our greatest need is. Listen we can go
through life and some people, what do you need? I need this and I need that and I need
this and so on. Listen our greatest need, mankind, most of them are not aware of their
greatest need. Most people today if you were to take polls and surveys they would talk
about needs that are temporal things, that are temporal things. And there are people
today that run around and try to meet temporal
needs. And I'm not saying that we ought not care about people and try to help them with
their temporal needs, but what I am saying is that if we don't ever tell somebody about
their greatest need and tell them how their greatest need could ever be met through Jesus
Christ, then we failed. We failed. The Lord Jesus Christ is the only one that could provide
reconciliation. Somebody said this, if our greatest need had been information, God would
have sent us an educator. If our greatest need had been technology, God would have sent
us a scientist. If our greatest need had been money, how many people think that in our world
today? Then God would have sent us an economist. If our greatest need had been pleasure, many
that live that way today, God would have sent us an entertainer. But our greatest need was
forgiveness. So God, He sent us a Savior. His name is Jesus. He's my shepherd. Notice
what the Bible says in 2 Corinthians chapter 5. We've read already in 1 Peter chapter
number 3 where the Bible says in that portion of Scripture to bring us to God. That He might
bring us to God. That act of reconciliation, of redeeming us and reconciling us. And we
find here in 2 Corinthians chapter number 5, notice what the Bible says, and we're going
to begin reading in verse number 18 of 2 Corinthians chapter number 5. And the Bible says, actually
back up to verse number 14. In verse number 14 the Bible says, for the love of Christ
constraineth us because we thus judge that if one died for all, then we're all dead.
And so He's talking about Jesus Christ. He died for us. Remember, my shepherd, He died
for me. And that He died for all, that they which live should not henceforth live unto
themselves but unto Him which died for them and rose again. Wherefore, verse 16, henceforth
know we no man after the flesh, yea, though we have known Christ after the flesh, yet
now henceforth know we Him no more. Therefore, if any man be in Christ, he is a new creature.
Old things are passed away. Behold, all things are become new. I'm so thankful to be in
Christ. I'm thankful for how God changed my life. He transformed me. He's going to talk
about salvation. Salvation is not reformation. It's transformation. It's not trying to clean
ourselves up, trying to become a better me. No, no. God transforms us. Why? Because He
quickens us. He makes us alive in the Holy Spirit of God and dwells us. And we find here,
notice in verse number 18, and all things are of God who hath, notice what it says,
reconciled us to Himself, how? By Jesus Christ, and hath given to us the ministry of reconciliation.
You know, for those of us that have been saved this morning, we're to live for Christ according
to verse number 15, but we also notice that He's given to us the ministry of reconciliation.
Again, we understand that my shepherd provides for me the greatest need that I have, the
greatest need that every person I come into contact with is to be saved, reconciled. And
He's given unto us the ministry of reconciliation. And we find, it says in 19, in verse 19,
to wit, that God was in Christ, reconciling the world unto Himself, not imputing their
trespasses unto them, and hath committed unto us the word of reconciliation. Now then, we
are ambassadors for Christ. As though God did beseech you by us, we pray you in Christ's
stead, be ye reconciled to God. Notice verse number 21, for He hath made Him to be sin
for us who knew no sin, that we might be made the righteousness of God in Him. Let me explain
to you verse 21, many of you know it. God the Father made Him, God the Son, to be sin
for us. He knew no sin, He's perfect, He's sinless, He's the just. But He took upon
Himself the sin of the world and paid the awful penalty so that we might be made the
righteousness of God in Him. See today, so many people are trying to be reconciled to
God through some other means. But there are no other means. There's no other way to be
reconciled to God. You say, but Pastor, I'm doing as good as I can do. I mean, I'm doing
all the good things that I know that I could do. You can't reconcile you to God. Because
the Bible says that we're not saved by works. We're not saved by works. For by grace are
you saved through faith and not of yourselves. It is the gift of God, not of works, lest
any man should boast. Paul said this in the book of Galatians, if righteousness came by
the law, then Christ is dead in vain. My Savior, my Shepherd did not die in vain.
He had to die so that we could be reconciled. He provides for us. Listen, I'm thankful for
all of His provision. I mean, He's been a good God. He's so good. He has provided to
us more than we could even fully comprehend. But my greatest need is met through Jesus
Christ, through my Shepherd. Your greatest need this morning is salvation. It's salvation
to have forgiveness of your sins, to know without any shadow of a doubt that heaven
is your home. Not because of anything that you have done, because you can't do it. Because
of what Jesus Christ did on the cross of Calvary, His death, His burial, and His glorious resurrection.
Listen, sometimes we go through life and people say, how are you doing? I was thinking about
this week. You know what I'm going to start saying, Ron? I'm going to start saying, my
cup runneth over. I really am. I mean, with God's help, if I can remember, I'm going to
start telling people, Armando, my cup runneth over. And you know what people are going to
be living with, what does that mean? Maybe open a door for an opportunity to be able
to share. Why? Because sometimes we go through life. I know Mr. Don, absolutely wonderful.
I mean, I visited Mr. Don in the hospital. And Mr. Regine, she's been there. I'll say,
Don, how are you doing? He's laying in the hospital and he says, absolutely wonderful.
And it's a blessing. But could I say that not everyone has that perspective? Sometimes
we go through life like, man, we just want to have a pity party. Things are so bad. No,
no. As a child of God, my cup runneth over. It's not even just full. It runs over. I love
the imagery. It runs over. I don't know who wrote the song, but Mike Clark sings the song,
I'm drinking from my saucer because my cup runs over. I like that. And this morning,
why would I say, why should you say that my cup runneth over? Well, because my shepherd
loves me. My shepherd loves me. My shepherd died for me. My shepherd found me. My shepherd,
he cares about me. Number five, my shepherd, he provides for me. And he provided the greatest
need, the need of salvation. This morning, if you're not sure of heaven, I want to invite
you to trust Christ today because your greatest need is salvation. This morning, if you've
been saved and you can say with the psalmist, the Lord is my shepherd, I would say to you
this morning, you should rejoice in that. You should be thankful in that. But you ought
to understand that God said that he gives you the ministry of reconciliation. And he
said to us that we are ambassadors, representatives, his witnesses. And he has committed unto us
this ministry, this word of reconciliation. This morning, we'll look at five more reasons
tonight. I hope that you'd fill out a whole lot more reasons on why you should say and
why I should say, my cup runneth over. Let's pray. Father, we love you. How we thank you
for loving us. Lord, I thank you for the word of God, the truth that's contained therein.
I thank you this morning for these five powerful truths. Lord, I know the list could go on
and on and on. This morning, I hope that each of us would truly evaluate our lives and we
would agree with the psalmist and we would echo the words of the psalmist and say, my
cup runneth over. Not that we would just say it to say it, but that we would truly
acknowledge the truth this morning that our cup runneth over. You've been so good to us.
Father, if there's one here this morning that's never trusted Christ as their Savior, they're
not sure of heaven. Maybe they've heard the message before, maybe they've sat in this
church for years. They've never trusted Jesus as their Savior. They're trying to get to
heaven through their own works, through some reason.
religion. And I pray this morning the Holy Spirit would help them to understand there's
only one way to get to heaven and his name is Jesus. I pray that for those that are here
that are saved, they've trusted Christ as their Savior, they're heaven bound. God would
you help us to take seriously the ministry of reconciliation that you have entrusted
us with, that we would be good ambassadors, good representatives. God I pray that you
would use us for your honor and for your glory. Help us to go through life as my cup runneth
over Christians. Would you move and work in these moments of invitation as only you can.
I pray that decisions would be made that would please thee and we'll thank you for it. In
Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me? At the end of each of our services we
have a moment of invitation where we invite you to respond. We don't ever seek to embarrass
anyone. We never call anybody out. But this morning maybe you don't know the shepherd.
You've never been saved. Would you come so that we could take a Bible and show you how
you could know for sure that heaven is your home? I would beg you not to leave here without
knowing for sure that heaven is your home. Maybe this morning you'd say, pastor I'm saved,
I've been born again, I know the shepherd. And I'm rejoicing because of it. This morning
maybe you need to come and ask God to help you in the area of being an ambassador. The
ministry of reconciliation that's been entrusted to each of us. Maybe this morning you want
to come and just thank God. Just rejoice a little while on why your cup runneth over.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.