A little over three months, actually, since we've been in the book of Colossians, and
I know that many of you take notes and have your notebooks, and if you want to mark down,
this is message number 10 through the book of Colossians, but message number 9 was on
March 14th.
And so I don't know if you want to put a little notation maybe in your notes so that you can
be able to go back and see the continuation, if you will.
But as we look at Colossians 2 this morning, we'll be looking at verses 11 through 15.
And notice what the Word of God says here, beginning in verse number 11 of Colossians
2.
In whom also ye are circumcised with the circumcision made without hands, and putting off the body
of the sins of the flesh by the circumcision of Christ, buried with him in baptism, wherein
also ye are risen with him through the faith of the operation of God, who hath raised him
from the dead.
Verse 13.
And you, being dead in your sins and the uncircumcision of your flesh, hath he quickened together
with him, having forgiven you all trespasses, blotting out the handwriting of ordinances
that was against us, which was contrary to us, and took it out of the way, nailing it
to his cross.
And having spoiled principalities and powers, he made a show of them openly, triumphing
over them in it.
Notice the last phrase of verse number 14.
We'll use it for our title this morning.
Nailing it to his cross.
We of course sang that wonderful, familiar hymn this morning.
It is well with my soul, and that third verse speaks about my sin, O the bliss of this glorious
thought.
My sin, not in part, but the whole, is nailed to his cross, and I bear it no more.
Isn't that wonderful?
And here we find that Paul is writing to these believers in Colossae, of course, if we could
take, since it's been so long since we've looked at Colossians, the book, and chapter
2 in particular.
We'll be reminded this morning by way of introduction that Colossians 2 begins with Paul expressing
his concern for the brethren.
In fact, he voices it this way.
He says in verse number 1 that he has this conflict.
He says, I have a great conflict for you.
And we understand as we begin to study Colossians chapter number 2 and read about this conflict,
this concern that Paul had for these believers, not only here at Colossae, but also those
in the city of Laodicea, we understand that he was concerned for them because the enemy
was active.
The enemy was working and the enemy was active, and Paul has this concern for the brethren,
and that concern leads him to the next several verses by which we took two messages to study
through, verses really 4 through 10, and we dealt with the subject matter of the warning.
Remember that the apostle Paul, as he highlighted and explained to the believers in Colossae
what his ministry was, he said that he was ministering and he was seeking to teach every
man, but that his ministry also included warning every man.
And as we look at Colossians chapter number 2, we see that Paul is issuing these warnings,
and Paul is seeking to help the believers understand how it is that the enemy works
and how it is that we as the people of God are to combat the enemy.
We find that the warning was issued, and of course it was their responsibility to take
heed to that which had been given.
We find that Paul would explain several things in our text that we're going to look at this
morning in verses 11 through 15 as to that which was accomplished by the Lord Jesus Christ
on the cross of Calvary.
I'm so thankful that the Lord Jesus Christ went to the cross, amen?
I'm so thankful that he took my place.
The plan of redemption was determined before the foundation of the world, and the price
of redemption was determined to be the precious blood of the Lord Jesus Christ, God in flesh.
And we understand that he came and he fulfilled.
He said when he hung upon that cross before he gave up the ghost, it is finished.
And I'm so thankful that as Paul would begin to share with these believers in Colossae
some of that which was accomplished at Calvary, it's right after he tells them in verse number
10, and we've used it for our theme this year, ye are complete in him, complete in Christ.
And some of that false teaching that was taking place there in Colossae that was prevalent
at this particular time would cause people to think that they needed something in addition
to Christ.
Yes, there are those that would give false teaching and they would say, well, Christ
plus your works, and so on and so forth.
But we find that these particular false teachers, they would speak about some level of maybe
mysticism and what have you, and the going deeper, if you will, and the way in which
some of these believers would have been influenced by this false teaching.
And Paul helps them understand, you're complete in Christ, you're complete in Christ.
Let me share with you what was accomplished at Calvary.
If you're taking notes this morning, notice number one with me.
Consider what Christ did for sinners.
In verses 11 through 14, the Apostle Paul will share with these believers in Colossae
what was accomplished on the cross of Calvary for sinners.
By the way, all men are sinners, amen?
And as we begin to look at this text of Scripture, we understand that Paul is writing to the
believers in Colossae, and as he's writing to these individuals, he reminds them of
what they were, but then he reminds them of what they are because of what Christ accomplished
at Calvary for sinners.
And as we begin to understand and unfold some of these things, again, as I mentioned a moment
ago, all men are sinners.
Yes, it's written to these believers in Colossae, but we understand that the truth that is contained
herein is truth that is applicable to every man, every human being that's ever walked
upon the face of the earth.
We understand, even as we would look at nature, why does an apple tree produce apples?
Because it's an apple tree, right?
Pretty simple truth, pretty simple understanding, and that apple tree does not produce peaches
because it's an apple tree.
And why is it that human beings sin?
It's because we're sinners.
And we're sinners, and therefore we sin, and there's this huge problem.
It's a condition that affects all mankind of sin.
We find that here sin would be dealt with at Calvary, and Paul is reminding them of
some of these things that were accomplished.
First we understand what we were.
Notice what he says here in verse number 13, and you being dead in your sins and in the
uncircumcision of your flesh.
Notice in verse number 14, blotting out the handwriting, but notice what it says here,
of ordinances that was against us, which was contrary to us.
If we could simply just highlight a couple of things with regard to the condition of
mankind, we'd understand that man is condemned already.
We understand that we're dead in our sins and in our transgressions.
We understand that we have this handwriting of ordinances that was against us, it was
contrary to us, and we find that as we would look at this truth of being condemned and
being dead in our sins, we find that we would simply be able to say this, we are guilty
before a holy God.
We're guilty.
I think about the nation of Israel, and you think about the truth of the Ten Commandments,
and it's interesting in Exodus 19 when Moses is confronting the children of Israel before
God would call him up to the mount in chapter number 20, but we find that God and Moses
had some interaction in chapter 19, and Moses has then some interaction with the people
of God, and the people say in Exodus 19, all that the Lord would command, we will do.
We find that it's in Exodus chapter number 20 that God gives those Ten Commandments.
We know that the law in its entirety is much broader than simply Ten Commandments, but
we find that they had said, whatever the Lord commands, we will do.
Now how did they do with that?
Not so well.
Why?
Because the law reveals the condition of mankind.
The law shows us that we're sinners.
The law shows us that we're condemned.
In fact, James says it this way in James 2, in verse number 10, when we think about this
truth with regard to the law, the Bible says, for whosoever shall keep the whole law and
yet offend in one point, he is guilty of all.
We find that the Word of God would teach us about our condition, and here Paul is reminding
these believers of their condition.
When the Gospel first came to them, how it was that God in His grace and His mercy brought
the truth to them because they were condemned already.
Remember what God says, the Lord Jesus Christ says this in John 3, after an interaction
with Nicodemus, we find in John 3, in verse number 16, a very familiar verse of Scripture
to us.
The Bible says, for God so loved the world.
Aren't you thankful for the love of God?
For God so loved the world that He gave His only begotten Son, that whosoever believeth
in Him should not perish, but have everlasting life.
Notice verse 17, for God sent not His Son into the world to condemn the world, but that
the world through Him might be saved.
He that believeth on him is not condemned,
but he that believeth not is condemned already,
because he hath not believed in the name
of the only begotten Son of God."
We are condemned already.
We're at enmity with God.
Romans 5 and verse 8 says that
God commendeth His love toward us
and that while we were yet sinners,
Christ died for us.
We find that 2 Corinthians 5 and verse 21,
as Paul is there sharing with the believers
in Corinth and expressing to them
all that Christ did for us
and the plan of redemption
and the imputed righteousness
upon the child of God.
He says,
"...for He," speaking of God,
"...hath made Him," speaking of Jesus,
"...hath made Him to be sin for us,"
notice, "...who knew no sin,
that we might be made
the righteousness of God in Him."
Peter says it this way.
If you take and turn to 1 Peter 4,
notice what Peter says here
with regard to the work at Calvary
and to the work that was accomplished.
1 Peter 3
I want you to notice verse 18.
1 Peter 3 and verse 18,
"...for Christ also hath once suffered for sins."
Notice this,
"...the just for the unjust,
that He might bring us to God,
being put to death in the flesh,
but quickened by the Spirit."
And so we find that Paul,
as he begins to speak to these believers in Colossae,
and after he'd given them warning
and dealing with some of the false teaching
that's taking place there,
he's going to remind them
what they are in Christ.
And before he begins to express to them
what they are,
he reminds them of what they were.
That they were dead in their sins
and their trespasses,
as he says to the believers in Ephesus.
That they had this handwriting of ordinances
that was against us,
that was contrary to us.
Listen, we were guilty.
There's no way that we could ever stand
and say, nope, I fulfilled all of it.
We're guilty.
As we begin to think about what we were,
we can rejoice greatly in what we now are.
And notice with me in this same passage here
in Colossians 2, in verse 13,
we've only read portions of these two verses
in our first aspect of this point,
but notice the Bible says,
"...and you, being dead in your sins
and the uncircumcision of your flesh,"
notice this,
"...hath He quickened together with Him."
That word quickened means to make alive.
And we understand the truth of the rebirth.
You must be born again.
And I'm so thankful for the truth
of the supernatural, the spiritual birth,
and the truth of being born again,
being redeemed by the blood of the Lamb.
And we find here that He says that you,
"...hath He quickened together with Him."
Then notice the final phrase of verse 13,
"...having forgiven you..."
What's that next word say?
Aren't you thankful for every word of God?
"...having forgiven you all trespasses."
Isn't it good to be forgiven?
I mean, honestly.
He didn't say He forgave you most.
He didn't say He forgave you some.
He said, "...forgiving you all trespasses."
Notice how He begins verse 14,
"...blotting out..."
Now notice it says,
"...the handwriting of ordinances
that was against us which was contrary to us,
and we understand that that handwriting
of ordinance was against us,
that we are guilty..."
Remember when they found the lady,
they said we've caught her in the very act
in this immorality,
and they were going there to accuse her
that they might stone her.
And what did Jesus do?
He wrote in the sand.
I don't know what He wrote.
I can only imagine what He wrote
were some of the sins that those very people
were guilty of.
And He says what?
The one that has no sin casts the first stone.
Amen?
I'm thankful that He's blotted out.
Listen, we're guilty.
The handwriting of ordinances that was against us,
that was contrary to us,
but He's blotted it out.
And you think about the way that He did that
we sang this morning.
Are you washed in the blood?
In the soul-cleansing blood of the Lamb.
It's through the blood of Jesus Christ,
His death, burial, and resurrection,
that that handwriting of ordinances
that was against us,
that was contrary to us,
it's only through His blood
that it can be blotted out.
And hallelujah for that.
We find that He says blotting out
the handwriting of ordinances
that was against us
and really carrying with it that idea
of what I mentioned in the beginning of the message
this morning,
how that Jesus said it is finished.
It is finished.
If you've ever had a mortgage,
if you've ever had any kind of a loan,
and it finally comes to the end
of the final payment,
and there's something that you get,
this promissory note when you receive the loan,
and then that promissory note
when it's paid in full,
they issue paid in full.
It's complete.
It's done with.
And here we find that this handwriting
of ordinances that was against us,
that was contrary to us,
that it was blotted out.
Notice what He says at the end of the verse.
He took it out of the way.
Nailing it to His cross.
Aren't you thankful for that?
We begin to think about what we were.
That we were dead in our sins
and our trespasses.
That we were condemned.
That we were guilty.
But when you think about what we are,
thinking that we've been made alive,
we've been quickened together with Him.
We have been forgiven
of all of our trespasses.
That they've been blotted out.
That He's taken it out of the way.
Nailing it to His cross
that now we can stand
and understand that we've been redeemed.
That we've been reconciled to God Almighty.
That we have been imputed
with the very righteousness of God Almighty.
The Bible tells us this in the book of Romans
in chapter 5 and verse 1.
I'll give you a moment to turn there.
We'll look at a couple of verses here
in the book of Romans.
But notice Romans 5.
We referenced a moment ago verse 8.
But I want you to look at verse 1
in Romans 5.
The Bible says this in Romans 5 and verse 1,
Therefore, being justified by faith,
we have peace with God
through our Lord Jesus Christ.
The only way to be justified is by faith
and we understand that the only way
to have peace with God
is through the Lord Jesus Christ.
I'm thankful for reconciliation
that when we were guilty and condemned
and we were distant and separated
from God Almighty,
that God in flesh, the Lord Jesus Christ,
reconciled us.
That we can enter into His very presence.
Notice chapter 8.
Notice what the Word of God says here
in Romans 8 and verse 1.
There is therefore now no condemnation
to them which are in Christ Jesus,
who walk not after the flesh,
but after the Spirit.
Isn't it wonderful to be in Christ?
To have understanding of what Christ did for us
at Calvary.
What He did for sinners.
The reality is that if we remove the truth
and the record of Calvary,
we're hopeless and helpless.
We are condemned.
But I'm thankful that Jesus did come
and that He did fulfill.
Remember, the book of Galatians tells us
that at the appointed time,
that when the fullness of time was come,
that God sent forth His Son.
And the Bible gives us very clear indication
as to why God sent forth His Son.
He sent forth His Son,
being made of a woman,
made under the law,
to redeem them that were under the law.
Why? Because we're guilty.
We're condemned already.
I'm thankful for what the Lord Jesus Christ
accomplished at the cross of Calvary.
Notice back in Colossians 2,
not only do we see as we consider
what Christ did for sinners here at Calvary,
not only do we notice the phrases
that are given to us in verses 13 and 14,
but we're mindful of that which is given to us
in verses 11 and 12.
Notice what He says in verse 11,
in whom also you are circumcised
with the circumcision made without hands,
and putting off the body of the sins of the flesh
by the circumcision of Christ.
All of a sudden now in verse 11,
this subject matter of circumcision comes up,
but Paul begins to deal with circumcision
from a different perspective.
Jewish people, of course,
would have had a very clear understanding
of circumcision as soon as they hear
the word being circumcised,
they immediately begin thinking
of the token of the Abrahamic covenant,
the circumcision of flesh,
but we find that it was not the Abrahamic covenant
that was being dealt with,
it was the new covenant,
and it was the circumcision of the heart.
And Paul is dealing here with that truth
of what Christ did,
and you think about conversion,
and he says here that you're circumcised,
notice this, with the circumcision made without hands.
He's not talking about the token
of the Abrahamic covenant.
That's not in his view, in his focus,
he's speaking about something entirely different,
something for the child of God,
the one that has been born again.
Again, he says that you're circumcised
with this circumcision made without hands
and putting off the body of the sins of the flesh
by the circumcision of Christ.
Isn't that wonderful?
This new covenant that has been introduced,
of course, the children of Israel
in the book of Jeremiah in particular,
they would have knowledge of the new covenant.
You read the book of Hebrews as we studied last year
and you see references to the new covenant.
You find here that Paul is helping these individuals.
Now, you remember that there were all sorts
of these false teachings with regard to circumcision.
In fact, it was in Galatians that they said
unless you're circumcised, you can't be saved.
And really, we find that that was dealt with
if you go back to the book of Acts
and you read and you understand the,
really the council that took place there in Jerusalem.
It's recorded for us, you don't need to turn there,
but it's recorded for us in Acts chapter number 15.
And there were some people that were saying this,
except you be circumcised after the manner of Moses,
notice they said, ye cannot be saved.
And Paul says, no, no, no, that's not true.
That's not true.
And they have this whole meeting and they determine,
yes, it's not true, it's not biblically accurate.
And so we find that they now here in Colossae,
it wasn't so much that they would be saying
that you had to be circumcised in order to be saved,
but having circumcision somehow elevates your position,
right, it elevates your standing with God.
But Paul says, no, no, no, you're complete in Him.
You're complete in Him and you have received
this circumcision that's entirely different
to that which they would deal with in the Old Testament
to that which was the token of the Abrahamic covenant
because you've been circumcised with that circumcision
that is made without hands, the circumcision of the heart.
By the way, throughout the Old Testament,
was it not clearly given to the children of Israel
that God was concerned about their heart?
You're doing all of these outward things.
You followed the token, the right of circumcision,
if you will, and you've done these things
and you've followed these feasts,
but your heart is far from me, right?
There you see it all throughout the Old Testament,
God's concern for the heart.
In verse number 12,
he deals with the subject matter of baptism.
He says, buried with Him in baptism,
wherein also you're risen with Him
through the faith of the operation of God
who hath raised Him from the dead.
Begin to think about the truth of baptism.
We find not only would the mode of baptism
be clearly revealed here as being that of immersion,
for the Bible says that you're buried with Him in baptism
and then risen with Him
through the faith of the operation of God.
And we understand that baptism is an outward expression
of an inward experience.
We understand this morning that baptism cannot save you
the same way that circumcision cannot save you.
And there are some, unfortunately,
that have misunderstood and misapplied
and they believe and they teach and practice
this thing of infant baptism
and thinking that somehow,
just like the children of Israel,
on eight days they would circumcise their boys,
that if you were baptized as an infant
that somehow you have this entrance
into this covenant with God
and it's foreign to the Bible.
You can't find it anywhere
within the pages of Scripture of infant baptism.
In fact, every person that you read of being baptized
in the Word of God is somebody that is an adult
that's made a decision,
someone that is able to acknowledge
that they have trusted the Lord Jesus Christ
as their personal Savior
and therefore they follow the Lord in believer's baptism.
We find that there are those
that have confused some of these things,
but Paul is helping these believers to understand,
again, what it was that Christ did for sinners at Calvary.
What was it that was accomplished at Calvary?
Why is it that there are so many songs
that we as the people of God sing about Calvary?
There are so many songs that contain within,
maybe if the title specifically doesn't deal with the cross
or with Calvary,
but the words within the songs are reminding us
of what Christ did at Calvary
and the impact that it makes for us as children of God.
I can only be a child of God because of Calvary.
Amen?
As we look at this portion of Scripture,
we can rejoice greatly in our standing with Christ.
Yes, we can be reminded of what we were,
but how we ought to rejoice in what we now are in Christ.
Number two this morning, if you're taking notes,
I want you to consider not only what Christ did for sinners,
but I want you to notice number two
and consider with me what Christ did to Satan.
In verse number 15, there's a clear indication
of how it is that Christ triumphed over Satan.
Now understand with me this morning
that the readers of this particular book,
when it was initially given,
they would have been familiar
with what they would be able to refer to as a Roman triumph.
They would be very familiar
with how the Romans would go into battle
and as they would be victorious
and as they would triumph over someone,
they would be understanding
of how they would come back with a parade
and all of the hoopla that would go with it
and how they would triumph over their enemies,
how that they would bring some enemies back with them
that would be shackled,
that would be behind the chariots, if you will,
that would be publicly shamed
and it would be a triumph for the Romans
and the particular general,
if you want to use that terminology,
that was able to be successful in battle.
They would have been familiar with that process.
They would have had an awareness
of that particular situation
and we find that I believe
that Paul would use that familiar event
to explain and illustrate to these believers at Colossae
and for us this morning
what it was that Christ did to Satan at Calvary.
The Bible says this in verse number 15,
and having spoiled principalities and powers,
he made a show of them openly,
triumphing over them in it.
We understand as we look at this verse of Scripture,
the reference to principalities and powers
and we're mindful of that phraseology
that Paul will use just a few pages back
in the book of Ephesians
when he's speaking to the church there at Ephesus
with regard to the spiritual battle
in which they're engaged in
and he tells them in Ephesians 6 in verse number 10,
finally, my brethren, be strong in the Lord
and the power of His might.
Put on the whole armor of God
that you may be able to stand
against the wiles of the devil.
And then he says this in verse number 12,
for we wrestle not against flesh and blood, notice,
but against principalities, against powers,
against the rulers of the darkness of this world,
against spiritual wickedness in high places.
And we find that he's speaking about
the wiles of the devil in verse number 11
and then he deals with in verse number 12
that hierarchical structure, if you will,
of those fallen demons
led by none other than Lucifer himself
and he says that they are principalities,
powers against the rulers of the darkness of this world.
We're fighting against spiritual wickedness in high places.
And in chapter number two of Colossians in verse number 15,
he says having spoiled principalities and powers.
That word spoiled carries with it the idea of disarming
or neutralizing an enemy.
Again, keep in mind that picture of the Roman triumph
and as the Roman soldiers would come in,
as they would have this parade, if you will,
in showing their victory,
they spoiled whoever this other people group was
and it was seen that they were left in a place
of being disarmed or neutralized.
Why?
Because they were in shackles behind the chariots.
And here the word of God says that Christ,
when he went to the cross of Calvary,
not only what he did for us as sinners,
but what he did to Satan,
that he spoiled principalities and powers.
Notice he made a show of them openly,
triumphing over them in it.
And so this idea of making a show of them openly
and triumphing over them,
again, to use the understanding
and the reference to a Roman triumph,
it was an open thing.
And the Roman soldiers were triumphing over
that people group that had been taken captive
and had been conquered, if you will.
And we find here that he says,
making a show of them openly,
he made a show of them openly,
triumphing over them in it.
How did he do that?
You understand that Satan,
and I believe all of the devils
and all of the demons,
when Christ was on the cross of Calvary,
they thought they had him right where they wanted him.
He would be defeated.
He would be conquered.
But up from the grave he arose.
And the Bible says that he made a show of them openly.
You know that his resurrection
was not something that was hidden?
He appeared to over 500 at one time.
You can read the references throughout the Word of God
how that he, the risen Savior,
made himself known and he revealed himself
to many people, in fact,
as you would look at the book of Acts
and think of Luke writing this particular book
to Theophilus, he says in verse number three of Acts 1,
to whom also he showed himself alive
after his passion, notice this phrase,
by many infallible...
full proofs, the evidence of His resurrection.
They did everything they could
to bar that tomb.
Did they not?
But Jesus conquered sin, death, and the grave.
We find that the Bible tells us
that this truth in Colossians 2
where the Word of God says
that He there in v. 15
made a show of them openly
triumphing over them in it,
that this is through the resurrection
and we can rejoice greatly
in understanding that we serve a risen Savior.
We find that the enemy has been defeated.
The enemy has been defeated.
But it's absolutely imperative
that we understand this morning
that though He is a defeated foe,
that He is active and He is attacking.
Remember, that's what Paul was concerned with
to start chapter number 2.
This is what caused Paul to have this great conflict.
It was because of the work of the enemy.
You understand that the enemy
works in a variety of ways.
But as we begin to think about
the fact that He's been,
as we notice here in v. 15,
that He's been conquered,
He's been defeated,
but we find that in the plan of God,
He's allowed Satan to have a certain level
of power that continues to exist to this day.
We understand that He's the prince
and power of the air.
The Bible says the God of this world,
little g, speaking of the devil,
that He hath blinded the minds of them
which believe not.
We understand that He's active
and He's attacking.
Revelation 12 and v. 12 says this.
Part of the verse. It's not the entire verse.
You don't need to turn there.
It says this, speaking of the devil,
having great wrath because He knoweth
that He hath but a short time.
What does that mean?
Well, the reality is that the devil knows
that He has a short time
because He knows what His demise is.
He knows what His end is.
And it's there in Revelation 20
that the Bible tells us
before we begin to read about
the great white throne judgment,
the Bible tells us this in v. 10,
and the devil that deceived them
was cast into the lake of fire and brimstone
where the beast and the false prophet are
and shall be tormented day and night
forever and ever.
That's not happened yet.
I wish it has.
Don't you?
But it hasn't.
And as we think about the truth
of Revelation 12 and v. 12,
that He has this great wrath
because He knoweth that He hath but a short time,
we're mindful of what it is that He's doing.
How is it that He's active
and what is it that He's doing
until we reach that time of Revelation 20
in v. 10 when He will be cast
in the lake of fire to be tormented
day and night forever and ever?
Again, I know many of us,
all of us would say,
I wish that happened already,
but it hasn't.
So what's He doing?
Well, number one,
He's seeking whom He may devour.
The book of 1 Peter is written to believers.
Turn over to 1 Peter if you will,
look at chapter number five,
but as you're turning to 1 Peter 5,
I'm going to remind you
that the book of 1 Peter is written to believers.
It's written to the people of God.
In fact, it's written to the people of God
that are scattered because of persecution.
The Bible begins in 1 Peter 1,
in verse number one,
where Peter says an apostle of Jesus Christ
to the strangers scattered throughout Pontius,
Galatia, Cappadocia, Asia, and Bithynia.
He then begins to talk to them
about their redemption,
about their salvation.
He says to them in verse number three,
blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ,
which according to His abundant mercy
hath begotten us again into a lively hope
by the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead
to an inheritance incorruptible and undefiled
and that fadeth not away,
reserved in heaven for you,
who are kept by the power of God
through faith unto salvation,
ready to be revealed in the last time.
It's written to save people.
You come to chapter number five
in the book of 1 Peter,
and Peter begins to express his concern
to the elders and he's addressing them
specifically to these leaders.
He gives them the instruction
of feeding the flock of God.
But I want you to notice
what he tells us in verse number eight
of 1 Peter chapter number five.
It's a familiar verse of Scripture to us.
The Bible says,
be sober, be vigilant,
because your adversary, the devil,
notice, as a roaring lion,
walketh about seeking whom he may devour.
He's active.
I'm thankful for what Christ did to Satan at Calvary,
but we must acknowledge as the people of God
that Satan is still active today.
I believe that he's probably more active
than he's ever been.
I believe that as we think about that truth
of Revelation 12, 12,
where it says that he has this great wrath
because he knows that his time is short,
that he hath but a short time.
I believe that, no, he does not know the hour
or the time of his demise,
but I believe that there's an understanding
and we see that he's working and he's active
and it's like he's working overtime.
And he's seeking whom he may devour.
You understand that as we look at this verse of Scripture
and understand the illustration
by which Peter would use,
he uses the analogy of a roaring lion.
A roaring lion.
If you ever watch and have the opportunity to see
maybe a video recording of a lion hunting
and how they devour their prey.
We find here that Satan seeks to devour.
I'm so thankful that Satan could never cause us
to go to hell.
If you've been saved, if you've been born again,
he can't take that.
We have an inheritance.
He started it in chapter one
that's reserved in heaven for us.
But we understand that he's active.
And we understand not only as we begin to think about
how he's active and what he's doing,
we'd understand that he is the accuser of the brethren.
We looked at Revelation 12, 12,
I quote a part of it to you,
but in verse number 10,
the Bible tells us that he is the accuser of the brethren.
And he is.
Maybe you have experienced times in which
the accuser of the brethren has knocked on your door.
Maybe there are times in which you have experienced
in which the one who seeks to devour the enemy
has knocked upon your door
that that temptation comes in your life.
As we begin to think about the truth
that Paul is giving to the believers in Colossae,
how we ought to rejoice greatly to understand
what it is that Christ did for sinners
and what he did to Satan.
But we must be mindful that though he spoiled them
and he made a show of them openly,
triumphing over them in it,
we understand that Satan is still active today.
He is a defeated foe.
It's amazing how a defeated foe
can get a foothold that turns into a stronghold.
We see it in the Word of God.
We find as the people of God,
as we try to take the truth of
Colossians chapter number two
and understand and rejoice in what Christ did for us
and also have an understanding that
though Satan has been defeated at the cross of Calvary
and though Satan has been rendered
in this sense of the word spoiled,
that there is this disarming or this neutralizing,
we know that we cannot,
we cannot engage him in battle in our flesh.
Can't.
And we understand that as the people of God,
that we still have the flesh.
How many of you are keenly aware of the fact
that you have a flesh?
And that your flesh still has some level of desires?
Right?
Paul talks about in the book of Ephesians
how that the flesh,
excuse me, the book of Galatians,
that the flesh is at enmity with the Spirit.
Right?
The flesh is at enmity.
There's a battle that goes on.
And so we understand this whole spiritual aspect
of what's going on
and we begin to think about as Bible believing Christians
as followers of the Lord Jesus Christ
and we can rejoice in some great promises of God's word
for when we engage with and we have that enemy
that is the accuser, the brethren
that's attacking and seeking to devour
that there are times in which we'll sin.
Have you ever sinned since you've been saved?
You laugh, why?
Because we all have.
Some of you sinned this morning, amen?
I mean, in the parking lot maybe.
I'm so thankful for the promises of God's word
with regard to forgiveness.
Take your Bibles under 1 John, if you will.
I think about the biblical Christianity,
we think about biblical Christianity
and there are so many pillars of biblical Christianity.
We speak about Baptist distinctives
and we talk about several of those
and what it is, why are you a Baptist?
And you can answer those questions
and understand that first answer to that question
would be that the word of God is the sole authority
for our faith and practice.
And you can look at all the Baptist distinctives
and kind of give you an idea.
as to what it is that a Baptist would believe and stand for.
But then we look at biblical Christianity
maybe a little bit broader from those Baptist distinctions
and say, what are some pillars of biblical Christianity?
And there are a lot of them.
But I would submit to you this morning
that two of those are forgiveness and restoration.
And for that, I am thankful.
Notice what John says here in 1 John chapter 1.
Again, we would understand even as we made reference
in the book of 1 Peter that John is writing to believers
the same way that Peter was writing to believers.
And as he's writing to these believers
in the book of 1 John, he says to them in verse number 8,
if we say that we have no sin, we deceive ourselves.
And the truth is not in us.
But notice this great promise in verse number 9.
If we confess our sins,
He is faithful and just to forgive us our sins
and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness.
If we say that we have not sinned,
we make Him a liar,
and His Word is not in us.
I know that we're so thankful for the promise of 1 John 1.9.
Mr. Don often will say 1 John 1.9.
He's speaking of this promise that God offers.
Listen, remember the Old Testament reveals to us
that God is plenteous in mercy.
That He is ready to pardon.
That He is ready to forgive.
We read into chapter number 2 here of 1 John,
and the Bible says,
My little children, these things write I unto you,
that ye sin not.
But then it says this, and if any man sin,
listen, it is desirous that we sin not.
Amen?
The closer we get to the Lord,
the more we walk with God,
the less we ought to be sinning.
Amen?
The desire is that we'd sin not,
but understand, contrary to what some people taught
hundreds of years ago,
you're never going to reach a place of sinless perfection.
It's just not going to happen
until we get to glory.
Amen?
When this mortal shall put on immortality,
when this corruption shall put on incorruption,
then, and only then,
will I no longer have a flesh
that will cause me to sin.
The enemy, right?
The way in which he comes.
And so, I guess if you want to call it
charge from John,
it is to sin not,
but then he says this,
see, I'm thankful for every word of God.
I'm thankful for the entirety of the Word of God,
because he says that you sin not,
but knowing and understanding,
even as we've read in chapter number one,
that we are sinners and we are going to sin.
He says, and if any man sin,
all of us,
we have an advocate with the Father,
Jesus Christ the righteous.
Aren't you thankful that you have an advocate?
Because you have an accuser of the brethren.
You have an accuser.
But you have an advocate.
You have an advocate.
And I'm thankful that when the advocate
stands up on our behalf,
that he can say something like this,
I paid for that.
Amen?
And if we confess our sins,
He forgives us.
He says that He removes them as far as the east
from the west.
That they're buried in the deepest sea.
Amen?
We believe the Word of God.
And see, as we look at the whole,
I'm thankful for the book of Colossians.
Trust me, as we're studying through it,
I'm encouraged and I'm strengthened and I'm helped.
I'm so thankful for what Christ did
for sinners at Calvary.
As Paul would share with these believers,
let me help you understand
that you are complete in Christ.
Let me help you understand
that these false teachers are coming
and saying that you need something more than Christ.
They wouldn't say you don't need Christ,
but you need something more in addition to
to reach higher planes and so on and so forth.
But Paul says, listen, Christ is all we need.
You're complete in Christ.
Here's what He accomplished at Calvary for sinners.
And here's what He did to Satan at Calvary.
But as we have the whole of the Bible,
and we understand that Satan was defeated foe,
that God has allowed him to have some level of reign
in this particular era.
We may not like it,
but we better learn the truth of it.
And he's the accuser of the brethren
and he's seeking whom he may devour.
But as the accuser of the brethren
and as the one that's seeking whom he may devour,
I'm thankful that if we sin or when we sin,
that we have an advocate.
An advocate with the Father.
This morning, I hope that we can rejoice greatly
in understanding what Paul explains
to the believers in Colossae
with regard to what Christ accomplished
at the cross of Calvary.
If you're here this morning
and you've never trusted Christ as your Savior,
maybe when we were singing,
are you washed in the blood?
You're not able to answer with confidence
that you've been saved, that you've been born again.
Today is the day of salvation.
The Lord Jesus Christ is the Savior
and He wants to save you.
But for us as the people of God,
would we rejoice in what Christ accomplished?
But also be mindful of the battle that still continues.
It's often been said,
in fact, I've mentioned it on a number of occasions.
As you read through the book of Romans,
you'll see it in particular,
that the Lord Jesus Christ,
He delivered us from the penalty of sin.
What's the penalty of sin?
Death.
The wage of sin is death, right?
And He delivered us from the penalty of sin.
He's delivered us from the power of sin.
Sin should no longer have dominion over you.
But we've not yet been delivered
from the presence of sin.
And we find that this great Bible truth,
this great biblical principle,
this biblical principle for Christianity,
is that we believe in the pillar
of forgiveness and restoration.
And we understand that with,
as a child of God,
that I have an advocate
that stands on my behalf.
You think about the legal terminology
and the legal understanding here,
that this advocate stands on my behalf.
And because we understand the truth
of substitutionary atonement,
He took my place.
And He took your place.
Nailing it to His cross.
I'm so thankful for what Christ did for us at Calvary.
Let's pray.
Father, how we love You this morning
and how we thank You for Your Word.
We thank You for that which was accomplished
over 2,000 years ago there
at the cross of Calvary.
We thank You for what You did for sinners
and for what You did to Satan.
And God, as we walk with You,
I pray that You'd help us to walk in the Spirit
so that we would not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
Help us, God, to be mindful that we have an enemy
that seeks to devour,
that is the accuser of the brethren.
And I pray that You'd help us to rejoice greatly
in knowing that we have an advocate with the Father,
the Lord Jesus Christ.
I pray, God, that You would help us
to rejoice in that truth.
If there's one that's not sure of heaven,
it's our prayer that today would be the day of their salvation.
The Holy Spirit of God would use the Word of God
to convict and convince of sin,
of Christ's righteousness and of judgment to come.
We pray that as we have a time of invitation,
that, Lord, You would work as only You can.
You would move, help us, Lord, to be responsive.
We pray that You'd be glorified through each decision.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would You stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's gonna play quietly on the piano.
And as she does, the altar is open.
If you're not sure of heaven,
we'd love to take a Bible and show you
how you can know for sure that heaven's your home.
Maybe you just need to come and ask the Lord to help you
as you walk this Christian life,
knowing that we have an adversary.
Maybe there's some sin that you need to come confess
and get that forgiveness and understand
that you have an advocate with the Father.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.