chapter number four this evening, Revelation chapter number four.
And over the last couple of Sunday evenings
that we were in the book of Revelation,
we dealt with verse one really,
taking two weeks looking at that,
dealing with the rapture and what have you.
And this evening as we begin making progress
through this fourth chapter,
we find that both the context and the setting
is clearly set forth in the opening verses.
We find, I'll begin reading in verse number one
just to get the entirety of the context.
The Bible says, after this,
and of course we have to understand
what is this that he's referring to.
And we think about the preceding text of scripture,
chapters two and three.
And as we look at those chapters,
they deal with the seven letters to the churches
and the churches throughout Asia and modern day Turkey.
So we find that he says, after this, I looked
and behold, a door was opened in heaven.
The first voice, which I heard
was as it were of a trumpet talking with me,
which said, come up hither
and I will show thee things which must be hereafter.
And immediately I was in the spirit
and behold, a throne was set in heaven
and one sat on the throne.
And he that sat was to look upon
like a jasper and a sardine stone.
And there was a rainbow round about the throne
in sight like unto an emerald.
I've titled the message this evening,
In Heaven, part one.
Why is it part one?
Because it's gonna be two or three parts
before we get through the entirety of this fourth chapter.
But I want you to remember, hold your place here,
just turn a page or two back in your Bibles
and go to the Revelation chapter one in verse number 19
and find as we begin to remind ourselves
now that God has provided in this book of Revelation
an outline for the book of Revelation.
Not every book of the Bible contains an outline
in the beginning of the book, but this one does.
And we find here in Revelation one,
in verse number 19, he says,
write the things which thou hast seen
and the things which are
and the things which shall be hereafter.
And so we find in this verse of Scripture
that God provides the three sections,
if you will, of the book of Revelation
and provides for us an outline
at the very beginning of this book.
And we find that the first section
is the things which thou hast seen.
And that's chapter number one.
Revelation chapter number one is that first section
of the book of Revelation,
the things which thou hast seen.
Then he says, and the things which are.
And we understand that to be Revelation two and three,
the churches that are being addressed,
the seven churches.
We studied through each of those letters
and we understand that these are local churches
that were in existence at the time of the writing.
They were literal churches.
We made it clear that they were not
all the churches that existed.
There were more than seven churches in existence
at the time of the writing of the book of Revelation.
But these are the seven churches
that God chose to send a letter to
and had given that instruction to John.
And we understand that it really is representative,
if you will, chapters two and three of the church age.
And we said this as we studied through chapters two and three,
as you look at the differences with the churches,
that they are not laid out in such a way
that the beginning of the church age
was every church was like the church at Ephesus
and the end of the church age,
that every church has to be like the church of the Laodiceans.
I believe that throughout the entirety of the church age,
and we don't know exactly how long the church age is.
It's been about 2,000 years at this point.
We don't know exactly the length of the church age.
But what we do know is that throughout the history
of the church, that there have been churches
that would be like each of these churches.
You can be a church in 2025
that is like the church of the Laodiceans,
or you could be like the church at Sardis
or Thyatira or Ephesus, et cetera, et cetera.
And so we find that the second section
of the book of Revelation is the things which are,
according to Revelation 119,
and that would be represented for us in Revelation 2 and 3,
dealing with the church age.
The third and final section of the book is,
as it's described in Revelation 1 and verse 19,
and the things which shall be hereafter.
And so we find that in verse number one
of chapter number four, he says after this,
that's the way that the verse begins,
but if you look at the end of the verse, he says,
and I will show thee things, notice,
which must be hereafter.
And so he said in Revelation 1 and 19
that he said to write the things which thou hast seen
and the things which are and the things
which shall be hereafter.
And now the Lord says in chapter four and verse number one,
I will show thee things which must be hereafter.
And so Revelation 4 and verse number one
begins the third section of the book of Revelation
and it ends in chapter 22.
We would say that this third section
of the book of Revelation is roughly divided
into three particular aspects.
The first one is the tribulation,
which is Revelation six through 19.
The second of that is the millennium,
which is Revelation 20.
And then you have eternity in Revelation 21 and 22.
In Revelation four and five,
what you have in this passage of scripture
is really the scene into the throne room of heaven.
In chapters four and five, you have where God
is providing us and providing John,
obviously the one who had the revelation.
He's giving to us an opportunity
to see into the throne room of heaven
and what a scene it is.
You read Revelation four and five, it's exciting.
Make you want to shout and praise the Lord
because our God is so good.
And we find that as we look at this text of scripture,
I've entitled it in heaven.
Why?
Because we find that the voice that he heard,
he says it were of a trumpet talking with me
in verse number one, come up hither.
And we said that in chapter number four
and verse number two, and immediately I was in the spirit
and behold, a throne was set in heaven.
And God allows for John to be transported to heaven.
And so we find that the timing is obvious.
The setting is obvious.
It's in heaven, according to chapter four
and verse number two.
And we talk about heaven,
he's talking about the habitation of God.
We can talk about the heavens,
meaning that which we can see in the skies
and the stars and what have you.
But we find that here in Revelation four,
when he talks about in heaven,
he's not talking about just being in the atmosphere,
being in the universe.
He's talking about the place where God dwells,
the habitation of God.
And so we find that as we look at this text of scripture,
even by way of introduction,
we find and we're reminded of the truth
that heaven is indeed a real place.
You know, there's some people today
that want to try to give this idea that heaven is not real.
It's just a figment of your imagination.
You make heaven whatever you want it to be
and you can have heaven on earth
and you hear that type of thing and so on and so forth.
But I want you to know this evening
that heaven is a real place.
And we find that not only is heaven a real place,
but as we look at the text
and we begin to unfold, unpack, if you will,
what's going on here,
we would say that heaven is a beautiful place.
And we would say that for all of eternity,
in heaven we'll be worshiping the Lord.
By the way, he is worthy of our worship.
He is worthy of our worship today
and he is worthy of our worship forever.
And we find that as we look at this text of scripture
and begin to think about heaven,
I've been asked, I'm sure that you have,
from time to time,
someone would ask a question like this,
what is heaven like?
If you're not careful when you answer that question,
you may just begin to talk about the streets of gold
and various aspects of descriptive things
that God gives us,
not only here in Revelation 4 and 5,
but you get to chapter 21 and 22
and you get some of that description that God gives
and you can begin to provide that description
and all of those things are true, God gave us that.
But I want you to understand
is that what makes heaven glorious
is the fact that our Savior will be there.
You can have the streets of gold,
you can have all, everything else
that is mentioned about heaven,
but if Jesus isn't there,
it's not really heaven.
Because what makes heaven heaven
is the fact that our Savior is there.
And what a blessing to understand
as we begin to walk through the verses
here in chapter number four,
we're just gonna kind of go
very kind of verse by verse
and look at what's taking place here
and begin to get a sense of the scene
in heaven and what God gives us.
The description that is provided
is so detailed.
We will not, this evening,
be able to deal with the entirety of it.
That's why I say it's part one.
We have the Lord's Supper that we'll be observing
and just quite honestly,
there's a lot in one text of scripture.
You say, well, it's only 11 verses of scripture.
That's true.
But oh, how much is contained
within these 11 verses of scripture.
And so first I want you to notice with me
that there is a throne.
Notice the first thing that John says
in verse number two, he says,
and immediately I was in the spirit.
And behold, notice what he says,
a throne was made.
was set in heaven, and one sat on the throne.
The first thing that John begins to describe,
and you can think about your life,
if you have the opportunity to go somewhere,
to see some place, and someone says,
describe that place to me, you're gonna begin to use
and describe with imagery and what have you
the place that you've seen.
And God tells us that in the text of Scripture
that John has written these letters,
of course, it's God speaking,
the Lord Jesus Christ to the churches,
and now he hears this voice and immediately
he's in the spirit, he's in heaven,
and what does he see?
A throne, a throne.
We begin to understand how this throne is described to us,
and we'll look at the fact that the Bible says in verse two,
and one sat on the throne,
and we'll get to that in just a moment,
but I want you to notice,
just begin to think about the throne that is there.
The Bible says in verse number three,
and he that sat was to look upon like a jasper
and a sardine stone,
and there was a rainbow round about the throne
and sight like unto an emerald.
And so as we begin to think about this throne
that John has the opportunity
as he's transported into heaven,
he's in the spirit, and he sees this throne,
and he begins to explain what he is seeing,
he tells us about the throne,
and he tells us in verse number three
that there is a rainbow round about the throne.
What's interesting?
Because we begin to think about the rainbow,
and the rainbow, listen, I understand
there's a lot of talk about rainbows today,
but I wanna talk about the biblical truth of the rainbow.
Turn back to Genesis chapter nine,
because we find that God had established with Noah,
with the Noahic covenant,
we find that God provided a rainbow.
He put his bow there in the sky, we see that,
and I want you to understand that the rainbow
represents for us and helps us to be reminded
of the fact that our God is merciful,
and that our God is faithful.
We understand that Noah, he was,
and you find him first mentioned in scripture
in Genesis chapter number six,
and the Bible describes him,
it says that he found grace in the eyes of the Lord,
it describes him this way in Genesis six,
in verse number nine,
these are the generations of Noah.
Noah was a just man and perfect in his generations,
and notice this, Noah walked with God.
We find that God announces to Noah
that he's going to destroy the earth
and all that he's created,
and we find that he provides this announcement of judgment,
why?
Because of the wickedness of humanity,
and his judgment is going to pour out upon his creation.
We find that the flood, the global flood is biblically true,
not only biblically, but you can find throughout research
and you can look at historical data,
you can look at geological data,
and you can find evidences of the flood all over this globe,
and we find that this evening as we look in Genesis
and we begin to think about the flood
and how God had provided with Noah the building of an ark,
and he tells them that it's in the ark
where there would be safety.
God tells them time to come into the ark,
and God then brings the judgment,
no one listened to Noah,
it was Noah, his wife, his three sons, and their wives,
there was no one that listened to the preacher Noah
as he's described later in the New Testament
as being a preacher of righteousness,
and we find that after God,
the Bible says that God remembered Noah.
The Bible tells us that God sent a wind
and the waters began to assuage,
and we find that he sends forth the various levels of birds
and you find that eventually in chapter number eight
that God gives to Noah the instruction to come off the ark.
He says in verse 16 of chapter number eight,
go forth of the ark.
What a great day that must have been, amen?
And we find that they come off the ark
and the first thing that they do,
the first matter of business was to worship God,
and you find in verse number 20 that they built an altar
and they offered burnt offerings on the altar.
You find that you enter into chapter number nine
and you see the Noahic covenant recorded for us,
and I'm not gonna read all of it,
but I want you to notice that God,
as he's providing the details of this,
he begins in verse number nine,
and I behold, notice what he says,
I establish my covenant with you
and with your seed after you.
The reality is that it was Noah, his wife,
three sons, and their wives,
and that was the entirety of the population of earth
after the flood, eight people, amen?
Peter confirms that, eight people.
And so he says, I'm gonna make a covenant with you
and with your seed after you.
That's all of humanity.
It's all of humanity.
Notice verse 10, and with every living creature
that is with you, of the fowl, of the cattle,
of every beast of the earth with you
from all that go out of the ark
to every beast of the earth,
and I will establish my covenant with you.
Neither shall all flesh be cut off anymore
by the waters of a flood.
Neither shall there anymore be a flood to destroy the earth.
Listen, that's what God said.
This was not Noah trying to make a deal with God
and say, please don't do this again.
This is God coming to Noah after Noah's off the ark.
He worships God, and he says,
I'm gonna make a covenant with you,
and here are the promises that I'm going to give.
Verse 12, God said, this is the token of the covenant
which I make between me and you
and every living creature that is with you
for perpetual generations.
Don't you love how that's worded?
Our God is outside of time.
He transcends time.
He is alpha and omega.
He's the beginning.
He's the end.
We find that he's able to make a covenant
that's for perpetual generations.
Why?
Because he himself is eternal,
and we find that he says, I do set, verse 13,
my bow in the cloud,
and it shall be for a token of a covenant
between me and the earth,
and it shall come to pass
when I bring a cloud over the earth
that the bow shall be seen in the cloud,
and I will remember my covenant,
which is between me and you
and every living creature of all flesh,
and the water shall no more become a flood
to destroy all flesh,
and the bow shall be in the cloud,
and I will look upon it
that I may remember the everlasting covenant
between God and every living creature of all flesh
that is upon the earth,
and God said unto Noah,
this is the token of the covenant
which I have established between me and all flesh
that is upon the earth.
When God made this promise to Noah,
he tells us that it was to perpetual generations.
He tells us that it's an everlasting covenant
in verse number 16,
not only to Noah, but to all flesh, all living creatures,
and we find that God says the token of this covenant
is that he would set his bow in the cloud.
You ever see rainbows?
Aren't they beautiful?
I mean, honestly.
You see a rainbow after a storm
and that light is coming through the atmosphere
just at the right angles,
and you see that beautiful, beautiful rainbow.
I have pictures on my phone
of some rainbows that I've seen,
but more than the beauty of a rainbow,
we're reminded of the promise of God,
reminded that our God is merciful,
reminded that our God is faithful.
God says this is what I'm going to do.
I will establish this,
and so when we see as we come to the throne
in Revelation chapter four,
as John begins to provide us with this description,
he says that there was a rainbow round about the throne.
I'm thankful that our God is faithful.
He's faithful.
I'm thankful that our God is merciful.
And no doubt as we look at this rainbow
that's described in verse number three,
that it reminds us of these attributes of our God.
We find again dealing with in Revelation chapter four,
the throne, he tells us in verse number six,
notice the Bible says in before the throne,
there was a sea of glass like unto crystal.
In the midst of the throne and round about the throne
were four beasts full of eyes before and behind.
And so we find that the second description
that is provided with regard to the throne
and what John is seeing,
he says that there's a rainbow round about the throne
in verse number three.
In verse number six,
he says there's a sea of glass like unto crystal.
I believe that this reminds us
to begin to think about the tabernacle
and then the temple in the Old Testament,
and to begin to think about the laver,
begin to think about the picture of the laver for cleansing
as the priests would go forth
and do their daily ministration.
And we understand that as we come to the New Testament
and how the word of God cleanses us.
And we find that truth in Ephesians chapter number five,
the Bible tells us this,
I actually read this verse a couple of weeks ago,
in Ephesians five and verse 26,
where the Bible says that he might sanctify and cleanse it,
speaking of the church, the bride of Christ,
with the washing of water by the word,
that he might present it to himself a glorious church,
not having spot or wrinkle or any such thing,
but that it should be holy and without blemish.
Begin to think about this scene that John sees
and the experience that he has
and now he's writing about it, we see this throne.
So we begin to ask ourselves,
and we don't know with 100% certainty,
I can tell you with 100% certainty
that in Revelation chapter 20,
that throne is the great white throne of judgment.
I can't tell you with 100% certainty
that this is the judgment.
the judgment seat of Christ, the bema seat, if you will,
as we'd refer to it, but it seems very interesting
when you begin to understand what's taking place
in the text of scripture, that the first thing
that John sees is this throne.
We won't have time this evening to look at the 24 elders
or the four beasts, I know that's what everyone's
interested in, and we'll look at those things next week.
Maybe, it might take two weeks to look at them.
Maybe there's the 24 elders next week and the four beasts.
I try to do it all in one and it's just
too much information, and so the reality is that
when you look at this throne and you look at the 24 elders
and they receive crowns and then they cast the crowns
and you think about the rewards that would be received
at the judgment seat, it's very likely, again,
I cannot say with 100% certainty, but it's very likely
that this throne that we're seeing here
could be representative to us as the judgment seat
of Christ, the bema seat.
We find that the Bible then, as we look at the text
of scripture, again, in verse number two,
he says that I saw a throne was set in heaven
and one sat on the throne.
So not only do we see the description of the throne,
but then we notice who sits upon the throne.
By the way, I'm thankful that my God is on his throne.
Amen?
You look at our world today and we can be led
to believe that things are all kinds of chaos
and confusion and falling apart, but my God reigns,
my God's on his throne, he's got everything under control,
he's not upset, he's not frustrated, he's in control.
He's on his throne.
We find that as we begin to look at the description
that is given as we notice the one who's on the throne
in verse number two, he says and one sat on the throne,
and then he begins to provide, in the next few verses
of scripture, some description with regard
to who's sitting upon the throne.
I believe that what is in view here, really,
in the throne room of heaven, on and around the throne,
is you see the eternal Godhead.
You see God the Father, God the Son,
and God the Holy Spirit.
You find that in verse number three, it says and he
that sat was to look upon like a jasper and a sardine stone
and you begin to think about the usages of those two stones
and it's always representative of being glorious.
And you can find that throughout portions of scripture.
You can find here that in verse number five,
it says and out of the throne proceeded lightnings
and thunders and voices and there were seven lamps
of fire burning before the throne,
which are the seven spirits of God.
And so we see that as we look at this description
that's provided to us and we begin to see the one
who's sitting upon the throne, that in verse number eight,
notice what it says.
It says of these four beasts, notice what they're crying out.
They rest not day and night saying, holy, holy, holy,
Lord God Almighty, which was and is and is to come.
We find that he's sitting upon the throne.
We find there that the son, the Lord Jesus Christ,
notice what he says, probably on the same page for you
in Revelation three and verse 21.
Notice what Jesus says as he's writing this letter
to the church of the Laodiceans.
It says to him that overcometh,
will I grant to sit with me in my throne,
even as I also overcame and am set down with my father
in his throne.
We find that Jesus is there, the Holy Spirit represented
by the seven spirits of God that is mentioned
in verse number five and we've previously studied
that phrase in chapter one in verse number four
and chapter three in verse number one
and we find that they're represented
the Holy Spirit of God.
Just think about this scene just for a moment,
what John is beholding.
We find that Revelation chapter number five
gives us some insight.
Look at verse six and seven as we begin to look
at what's happening and I don't wanna get too far ahead
of myself into the fifth chapter,
but I do want you to understand what John
is beholding here.
It says in verse six of Revelation five,
and I beheld and lo in the midst of the throne
and of the four beasts and in the midst of the elders
stood a lamb as it had been slain,
having seven horns and seven eyes,
which are the seven spirits of God sent forth
into all the earth.
And he, who is he in verse number seven?
Well, that's the lamb that stood in verse number six.
And he came and took the book out of the right hand of him
that sat upon the throne.
Who is that?
Well, that's God the father.
For we find that in verse number one,
it says and I saw on the right hand of him
that sat on the throne, a book written within
and on the backside sealed with seven seals.
And so we begin to see the Trinity, the Godhead,
the eternal Godhead is in view here
in this passage of scripture in chapter four
and chapter five.
We find that in the book of Daniel,
turn over to Daniel chapter number seven.
And we've mentioned before, as we've been studying here
through the book of Revelation,
that Daniel has much insight for us
with regard to studying through the book of Revelation.
Then Daniel chapter number seven,
I wanna draw your attention
to just two verses of scriptures.
We begin to just fully try to comprehend this scene
that John is beholding and that he's revealing to us
and God has preserved for us this evening
so that we too can rejoice and be encouraged
with knowing that one day we too will hear that voice
and we will be in the throne room of God.
What a blessing.
Daniel seven and verse number nine,
I beheld till the thrones were cast down.
The ancient of days did sit,
whose garment was white as snow
and the hair of his head like the pure wool.
His throne was like the fiery flame
and his wheels as a burning fire.
A fiery stream issued and came forth from before him.
Thousand thousands ministered unto him
and 10,000 times 10,000 stood before him.
The judgment was set and the books were open.
We find that Daniel's even providing
as he's looking here in this vision
and we're reminded of what a blessing it is
to think about our God sitting upon his throne.
We find that Isaiah,
and I want you to look in Isaiah chapter number six
and we'll just make a quick application here
in Isaiah chapter number six
and God allowed for Isaiah to have a vision as well
and it's recorded for us in this chapter in Isaiah six.
We do recognize it as being the call of Isaiah as well
but we find that the Bible says in verse number one
of Isaiah six, in the year that King Uzziah died,
I saw also the Lord sitting upon a throne,
high and lifted up and his train filled the temple.
The Bible says it stood, above it stood the seraphims,
each one had six wings, with twain he covered his face
and with twain he covered his feet
and with twain he did fly
and one cried unto another, said,
holy, holy, holy is the Lord of hosts,
the whole earth is full of his glory.
As you go back to Revelation chapter number four
this evening, I know that the question comes
and rises in the passage of scripture
about the 24 elders and the four beasts
that are around the throne
and we'll deal with all of that in the next week
or two depending on how quickly we can get through it
and we'll learn about that and we'll understand
but I want you to just get your mind this evening
around the reality of heaven
and around the picture that John describes for us,
the scene and what a scene it is.
Listen, it's easy for us as New Testament believers
to sometimes just get caught up in the things
of the monotony of life and just all that's going on
and we know that if someone were to ask us
if we've been saved by the grace of God,
if you were to die or you're going to heaven,
we have the assurance of that,
we know that we've been bought with a price,
we understand and we could say as Paul said,
to be absent from the body is to be present with the Lord
but the reality is that as we look at Revelation chapter four
and chapter five and over the next several weeks
as we look at these two chapters,
I want us to really grasp the fact
that this is our destination, this is reality,
this one day will happen and whether it's through
the rapture or through our death,
to be absent from the body is to be present with the Lord
and we will be as John was in this passage of scripture
immediately in the spirit and we'll have this same scene.
What joy, I hope tonight that we would be encouraged,
that we would have joy.
You know, there are certain things
that cause people to rejoice.
The world rejoices and has joy based on a whole host
of things, factors, circumstances
but Jesus reminds his disciples after they come back
rejoicing that the demons, the devils were made subject
of them, he said in this rejoice not, rather rejoice why?
Because your names are written in heaven.
And I want you to understand this evening
that no matter what happens to you, what happens to me,
if you've been saved by the grace of God,
you've been sealed under the day of redemption.
The Holy Spirit is the earnest of our inheritance
and heaven is a.
reality. It's our destination. And when we look at this past description and say,
oh man, look at what John got to see, you're gonna see it one day too. Amen?
You're gonna see, yes, the throne, but more importantly, you're gonna see the one
that's sitting upon the throne. You're going to have the opportunity as we
enter into chapter 5 to see the Lamb, the Lord Jesus Christ, the one who died for
us to stand and open that book. And we're going to, as they do in verses 8 and 9,
we're gonna stand and we're gonna rejoice and sing this song of what a joy
it is to be redeemed by the grace of God. Holy, holy, holy, Lord God Almighty. This
evening, heaven is a real place, but there's only one way to get there, and
it's through Jesus Christ. You know, a lot of people today like to talk about
heaven, and quite honestly, most people, if really pressed on the issue, would
probably say they hope they'll go to heaven when they die. They're doing the
best they can, trying to be a good person, do X, Y, Z, but the reality is that we
know biblically that there's only one way to heaven. Jesus said, I am the way,
the truth, and the life. No man cometh unto the Father but by me. Peter stands,
he heard that proclamation, and he stands and acts for and says, neither is there
salvation in any other. There's no other name under heaven given among men
whereby we must be saved. This evening, heaven is a real place. If you're saved
tonight, you're heaven bound. Praise God. Rejoice in that. But as we're reminded
even in Sunday school this morning, there are a lot of people that we know that
aren't going to heaven. They're lost. They're in darkness. They're blinded. And
as much as we rejoice in knowing that this is our destination, we must too have
a burden to reach the lost. Because one day, they will die also. And I'd hate for
them to see the throne that's described in Revelation 20. That's the great white
throne of judgment. That from that throne they hear that they're cast in a lake of
fire forever and ever. Tonight, rejoice that heaven is your home, and then be
motivated to go tell somebody else how they can know for sure that heaven is their
home. Let's pray together. Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. We thank
you for the opportunity that we have to study this book of Revelation and to be encouraged
this evening about the reality and the certainty of heaven. We thank you for that which is
described to us. And Lord, we thank you for saving us, that we can stand here with confidence
and assurance that heaven is our home. If there's one present, one tuned in via livestream
that's not sure of heaven, God, I pray that today would be the day of their salvation.
I pray they would not put it off any longer, no delays, or they'd get it settled. I pray
that you'd move and work as only you can. I pray, Father, that as we prepare here in
just a moment for the Lord's Supper, I pray, God, that you would help us to take even
now as a moment of examination, Lord, that we would truly enter into your presence and
examine with honesty and humility that we might be able to say there's nothing between
my soul and my Savior. I pray that you'd move and work as only you can, and we'll thank
you for it. In Christ's name we pray.