number 27 this evening, Genesis chapter number 27.
And last week, I preached a message
dealing with, from the book of Romans,
really missions and the Great Commission, if you will.
And we watched some update videos.
So it's been a couple of weeks
since we've been in the book of Genesis,
but last time we were in Genesis chapter number 26.
And at the end of the passage,
after we trace the life of the events there of Isaac's life
and the time that he spent in Gerar,
we found that, of course, Esau was married
at the end of the passage and he was 40 years old.
And that made Isaac 100 years old.
We know that the word of God tells us
at the end of chapter 25 that when they were born,
that he was 60.
And so therefore, we see that Isaac
would have been 100 years old at this particular time
at the close of Genesis 26.
As we enter into Genesis chapter number 27,
as best we can tell, somewhere between 30 and 40 years
have passed from the events in Genesis 26
until entering Genesis 27, 30 to 40 years.
If you really wanna nail it down,
it seems to be right around 37 years
that have passed between the end of chapter 26
and the beginning of chapter 27.
We find that at that particular time, of course,
it would make Isaac about 137 years old,
if it is right there at 37 years.
But he's somewhere between 130 and 140.
And the Bible tells us, beginning in verse number one,
and it came to pass that when Isaac was old,
and the Bible says that his eyes were dim
so that he could not see, that he called Esau,
his eldest son, and said unto him, my son.
And he said unto him, behold, here am I.
There's a great truth that is revealed to us
in verse number two.
The Bible says that he, Isaac, says to his son Esau,
behold, now I am old.
Notice when he says, I know not the day of my death.
You know, the reality is that that statement is true
for every single one of us.
I know not the day of my death.
It does not have to be that we're old.
It does not have to be that our eyesight is failing us.
If you look at the truth of what we find
in the book of Genesis, you'll find that Ishmael died
at 137 years old.
So if Isaac is exactly 137, coupled with the fact
that his eyesight has gone bad,
perhaps he's really thinking, I'm gonna die.
But the reality is that, as David said,
and I understand that David said this
because of him being hunted by Saul,
he made this statement,
there's but a step between me and death.
That's true for every one of us.
Every single one of us, there's a step between me and death.
The Bible tells us that our life is but a vapor
that appeareth for a little time and then vanisheth away.
We're not to boast ourselves of tomorrow
for we know not what a day would bring forth.
And we have these biblical truths,
these instructions, we're told to number our days,
and we find here that there's a great truth
in this statement, and how important it is
that we would be prepared for the day of our departure.
Paul was able to say, the time of my departure's at hand.
You know, we don't all have that privilege
of being able to know that the day of our departure's
at hand, to know that we've come to those final days
or moments of our life.
There are people that tragically die
in an instant every single day.
People that get up and they plan to go to the workplace,
and they plan to come home,
and they plan that everything's gonna go right,
and there's a fatal accident.
It happens all the time.
Brevity, the brevity of life,
and we see that in verse number two.
Obviously, that's not the entirety
of the passage this evening,
and you look at the whole of this chapter
that we're gonna study this evening.
It is interesting to note, however,
when you think about this statement of Isaac,
I know not the day of my death,
that in fact, he lives to be 180 years old.
Genesis 35 records for us that he was 180 when he dies,
and when you think about that,
that means that there were about 43 years
that he lived after he made this statement,
after the events that are recorded
here in Genesis chapter 27.
And we find that as we look at this passage of scripture,
when Isaac calls Esau, he calls him in verse number one,
he tells him that he knows not the day of his death,
and really, the purpose, if you will,
for calling Esau is revealed to us in verse number four.
We'll use it as our title this evening.
The Bible says, and make me savory meat such as I love,
and bring it to me that I may eat,
that my soul may bless thee before I die.
I've titled the message this evening
that my soul may bless thee.
In a previous message, I think it was a few weeks ago,
I mentioned about this family
that they're a dysfunctional family,
and I made that statement about this family,
and I said that we find that still today in our society
that the home family is under attack,
and unfortunately, there are many families
that are dysfunctional.
I find that that truth, that reality is on full display
in Genesis chapter 27.
The dysfunction of this family is on full display,
and God Almighty has recorded these events
for all of humanity to be able to read.
And as we look at this passage of Scripture,
I would say this right at the beginning,
that my heart is saddened by the carnality
and the deception that dominates this chapter.
The carnality and the deception
that dominates Genesis chapter 27.
And the reality is that there's a danger
for each and every one of us to live a life of carnality,
to give in to the temptation to deceive,
to scheme, and to take matters in our own hands.
And there's a temptation that each of us face,
and oh, how we need to trust the Lord
and allow God to be the sovereign God that He is,
and to work in and through our lives as only He can.
He can do much better than you can do.
You believe that tonight?
I believe that.
I believe that He's able to do in my life
and in my circumstances,
in my days of trouble and difficulty,
He's able to take care of it a whole lot better than I am.
But sometimes we wanna get our hand involved,
and we think we can figure it out.
We think we can come up with a solution.
As we look at the passage of Scripture,
I wanna share three thoughts this evening.
Notice with me, number one, the instruction given.
The instruction that is given first is from Isaac to Esau.
We see it in the beginning verses.
We've read some of them already.
Notice that he says, behold, in verse number two,
now I am old, I know not the day of my death.
Notice the instruction begins from Isaac to Esau
in verse number three.
He says, now therefore take, I pray thee,
thy weapons, thy quiver, and thy bow,
and go out to the field and take me some venison.
Notice what he says, and make me savory meat,
such as I love, and bring it to me that I may eat,
that my soul may bless thee before I die.
As I think about the instruction that is being given,
and I think about the perspective of Isaac,
I really would say that Isaac is operating on carnal ground.
Isaac is operating in this situation
where he is looking for, in these last moments,
think about it, he's gonna live for 43 more years.
We have the whole of scripture that we can read that,
but he thinks his time of departure is at hand.
And what's the number one thing he's concerned about
is go get me some meat that I can eat it
and enjoy this meat that I love.
Think about that for just a moment.
When you look at other patriarchs
and other heroes of the faith throughout the word of God,
in their final moments on this earth,
they take and they seek to impart
some great level of truth to those
that are coming behind them.
And Isaac is concerned about his last meal.
And then he adds on it that I may bless thee,
that my soul may bless thee before I die.
Let me ask this question.
Was it Esau's blessing that he was to receive?
God had already communicated, if you remember in our study
back in Genesis chapter number 25,
in verse number 23, the Bible said,
and the Lord said unto her, remember,
she inquired of the Lord, why?
Because of the struggle that was within her.
And she inquires of the Lord, and the Lord says to Rebekah,
two nations are in thy womb,
and two manner of people shall be separated from thy bowels.
And the one people shall be stronger than the other people.
And the elder, the elder, that's Esau,
the elder shall serve the younger.
That's Jacob, correct?
And so we find that Isaac is operating in carnality.
He's not following the plan or will of God.
He says, I wanna have this meat.
I wanna have this final meal, this meat that I love.
And then he says that my soul may bless thee before I die.
He's operating outside of the will of God,
but he's giving instruction to his son Esau.
And the Bible tells us that Esau responds.
As we look at the passage of scripture,
it says that Rebekah heard in verse number five,
when Isaac spake to Esau his son.
Notice what it says at the end of verse number five,
and Esau went to the field to hunt for venison
and to bring it.
Esau responded to the instruction.
Dad said to go out and get this venison and bring it back
and make it and bring it to me for this final meal.
And the Bible says that Esau does that,
that he goes out to the field to hunt for venison
and to bring it.
I believe that as you look at the life of Esau,
we've mentioned it in previous messages.
We mentioned it in chapter 25.
At the end of chapter number 26, I'll mention again this evening,
and you'll see that at the end of the passage in particular,
Hebrews 13 deals with it as well,
that Esau is really mainly concerned for temporal things.
He's minding earthly things.
Why is it that Esau so desperately wants a blessing?
He wants the blessing of temporal things.
He wants the land, he wants the goods, he wants the plenty.
We find that Esau receives the instruction
and he departs to fulfill that which had been given him.
We find that in verses 6-17,
that it's now Rebekah who will instruct Jacob.
Now remember, we've read before
how that Esau was loved by Isaac
and Jacob was loved by Rebekah.
I mentioned about the dysfunction in the family.
And now Rebekah's going to instruct Jacob.
Notice it tells us in verse number 5
that Rebekah heard when Isaac spake to Esau his son.
So Rebekah's listening in
and she hears what Esau is told to do
and so now she's going to jump in
and she's going to come up with this plan
and she's going to give instruction to Jacob.
It says in verse 6,
And Rebekah spake unto Jacob her son, saying,
Behold, I heard thy father speaking to Esau thy brother,
saying, Bring me venison, and make me savory meat,
that I may eat, and bless thee before the Lord before my death.
Now therefore, my son, obey my voice,
according to that which I command thee.
Go now to the flock, and fetch me from fence
two good kids of the goats,
and I will make them savory meat for thy father,
such as he loveth.
And thou shalt bring it to thy father,
that he may eat, and that he may bless thee before his death.
So we see the plan of Rebekah.
She is now giving this instruction to Jacob
and we find that Jacob is no doubt
understanding the instruction that's been given
and he offers an objection in verses 11 and 12.
It's interesting, however,
why he's making the objection to this plan.
Notice in verse number 11 that Jacob said to Rebekah,
his mother, Behold, Esau my brother is a hairy man,
and I am a smooth man.
This is going to be a problem.
But notice what he says in verse number 12.
My father peradventure will feel me,
notice what he says,
and I shall seem to him as a deceiver.
If you're going in and doing what this plan is,
you are a deceiver.
Amen?
It's not just that you appear to be a deceiver.
He says this,
and I shall bring a curse upon me and not a blessing.
Here's an interesting note.
Jacob's objection,
he was not concerned with whether the plan was right.
He was concerned on whether the plan was safe.
Isn't that sad?
There's no objection to the plan
on the merit of the plan being honorable and appropriate
and the plan being God honoring.
There's objection on the part of
I'm going to appear to be a deceiver.
It's unbelievable.
And we look and we find what's happening
and we find that to this objection
that Rebekah will respond.
And notice in verse 13,
his mother said unto him,
Upon me be thy curse, my son.
Only obey my voice and go fetch me them.
I want you to remember verse 13.
We'll come back to it at the end of the message,
but very interesting what Rebekah says here
as it all unfolds how tragic these words become.
In verse 14 it says,
And he, this is now Jacob,
he went and he fetched
and he brought them to his mother.
And his mother made savory meat such as his father loved.
And Rebekah took goodly garment,
raiment, excuse me, of her eldest son Esau,
which were with her in the house
and put them upon Jacob, her younger son.
And she put the skins of the kids of the goats
upon his hands and upon the smooth of his neck.
She gave the savory meat and the bread
which she had prepared into the hand of her son Jacob.
You think about the elaborate plan that is devised
and how that they took all of the steps
that they thought they could take
in order to deceive Isaac.
Esau's hairy and you're not.
We got a solution for that.
Isn't that sad?
And really when you see the instruction that's given
and you look at what's taking place,
again, as I mentioned, yes, it's true
that the instruction from Isaac to Esau
is carnal instruction
and it's not following the plan of God.
We find though, however, that as Rebekah
is instructing Jacob that once again
there's this dealing with problems
and issues in life and trying to scheme
and devise solutions in our own will
and our own power.
We find that this instruction is given
and the plan is carried out.
The Bible now leaves us in verse 17
where Jacob is now fully prepared.
He's got the garment on.
He's got the skins put upon him.
He's got that savory meat in his hand
and he's now going to go into his father.
We find the interaction if you're taking notes
in verse 18-40, the interaction recorded.
I want you to notice first of all
the interaction between Isaac and Jacob.
It begins in verse 18.
Notice the extent of deception
that we find in these first few verses
and he, Jacob, came unto his father
and said, my father.
And he said, hear my.
Who art thou, my son?
It's interesting because later on
he would speak about the voice
and he says, who art thou, my son?
He says, Jacob said unto his father.
Notice the deception.
It begins right away.
Let me make this statement.
One lie leads to more lies.
Your mom ever tell you that when you were a kid?
I remember hearing that when I was a kid.
They talk about the web of lies
and being caught in the trap
and you don't remember all the things
and how you've got to keep making all of these.
That's what happens in this passage.
He says, notice what Jacob said unto his father.
Number one, I am Esau, thy firstborn.
You're not.
You're lying.
By the way, how does God feel about lying?
What does the Bible tell us
about what God feels about lying?
He hates it.
You know in the seven things that God hates
that lying is twice in the list?
One of the Ten Commandments,
thou shalt not bear false witness.
Is that not what the Word of God says?
And so we find that he says,
I am Esau, thy firstborn.
Notice, I have done according as thou badest me.
First of all, he didn't bade you to do anything.
Correct?
Jacob did not receive any instruction from Isaac.
But he says, I have done according as thou badest me.
Arise, I pray thee.
Sit and eat of my venison.
Is it venison?
It's not even venison!
That thy soul may bless me.
And Isaac said unto his son,
this is terrible. It's tragic.
Honestly.
It's really on the edge of being blasphemous.
In verse 20, Isaac says unto his son,
he says, how is it that thou hast
found it so quickly, my son?
And he said, because the Lord thy God
brought it to me.
Now, he's gone to the level
of saying God has provided.
He's bringing God into his deceptive plan.
We never do that.
Be careful.
Because it's within every single one of us
to scheme and to devise
and to lean on our own understanding
and to rely on deception and whatever
and how far do we go?
It's tragic.
My heart is saddened at Genesis 27.
I said it in Sunday school this morning.
I told Holland, I was driving with her yesterday.
I said, this chapter, there's not a whole lot
of good in this chapter.
Everyone seems to be operating in the flesh
and the deception and the carnality, it's sad.
I would think that it's a passage of Scripture
that had they known that it would be recorded
for all of human history,
perhaps they would have operated in a different way.
Because the Lord thy God brought it to me.
How sad.
Verse 21, the Bible says that Isaac,
and Isaac said unto Jacob,
come near, I pray thee, that I may feel thee, my son,
whether thou be my very son Esau or not.
Now remember his eyes, right?
We found that in verse number one.
Remember he said that his eyes were dim
and this is what was one of those factors
that led to him feeling that his day of departure,
his day of death was soon.
Jacob went near unto his father and he felt him.
So what did he feel when he felt him?
Well, remember they devised that plan.
She put the skins of the kids of the goats
upon his hands and upon the smooth of his neck
according to verse number 16.
So it says that he touches them.
It says that whether they'll be my son
and Jacob, verse 22, went near unto Isaac, his father,
and he felt him and said, the voice is Jacob's voice.
The hands.
Well, the hands were the hands of Esau.
Verse 23, and he discerned him not
because his hands were hairy as his brother Esau's hands,
so he blessed him.
And he said, notice again, notice what Isaac says,
art thou my very son Esau?
And he said, I am.
I mean, at this point, we can study human history,
we can study the behavior of humans.
There comes a point where you go so far
that you just dig in and you just continue with your story.
No matter how far the trap has gone,
no matter how, he's digging in.
I am.
No, you're not.
Verse 25, he said, bring it near to me
and I will eat of my son's venison
that my soul may bless thee.
And he brought it near to him and he did eat
and he brought him wine and he drank
and his father Isaac said unto him,
come near now and kiss me, my son.
And he came near and kissed him
and he smelled the smell of his raiment.
Whose raiment was that, by the way?
It's not Jacob's raiment, it's Esau's.
Remember, it says in verse 15,
and Rebecca took goodly raiment of her eldest son Esau,
which were with her in the house,
and put them upon Jacob, her younger son.
And so he smells the raiment and blessed him and said,
see, the smell of my son is as the smell of a field
which the Lord hath blessed.
The blessing is given.
In verses 28 and 29, you find that the Bible says,
therefore God give thee of the dew of heaven
and the fatness of the earth and plenty of corn and wine.
Let people serve thee and nations bow down to thee.
Be Lord over thy brethren
and let thy mother's sons bow down to thee.
Cursed be everyone that curseth thee
and blessed be he that blesseth thee.
You notice that the last part of verse number 29,
really he's invoking the blessing that God gave to Abraham,
which would properly be sent down to Jacob,
but of course through all that's taking place here
in the deception, but he's giving this blessing.
In verses 28 and 29.
Now, before we move on,
I'd like to just make a couple of comments.
I've made these comments in previous messages,
one with regard to Abraham and Sarah's interaction
and how that Abraham lied and said that Sarah was his sister
and then we made the comment
when we looked at Isaac and Rebekah
and said that Isaac lied and said Rebekah was his sister.
And I believe that as we look at this passage of scripture,
as much as Isaac is planning to do the wrong thing,
he's opposing the will of God
that's already been revealed in Genesis chapter 25
with regard to the blessing that it still did not require
that Rebekah and Jacob scheme and dip down to the level
in which they came to in this passage of scripture.
What if, and I know it's a hypothetical,
I know that we cannot say with definitive answer
in this particular case,
but what if Rebekah and Jacob, aware of the plan of Isaac,
had sought the Lord in prayer and asked God to intervene?
Is God able to intervene?
Could God not keep Esau from finding any deer to kill?
As much as the Lord Jesus Christ
brought all the fish into the net,
he could have driven all the deer out of the woods.
Amen, I believe that.
And the reality is that God is able.
God could have prevented that Esau
ever even came back to the place.
God could have worked in the heart of Isaac
so that Isaac would have submitted
to the plan and will of God.
There are many things that could have happened
that could have brought honor and glory,
not only to God, but to this family.
But instead, there was scheming,
and there was deception, and there was carnality.
And it ends in tragedy.
Yes, the blessing is given,
but what tragic ending to the family
and all that takes place,
I'm thankful that in several chapters,
we'll read of the reunion of Jacob and Esau,
and what a blessing that is.
But notice here that the blessing is given
in verse 28 and 29, and it says in verse number 30,
and it came to pass,
as soon as Isaac had made an end of blessing Jacob,
and Jacob was yet scarce gone out
from the presence of Isaac, his father,
that Esau, his brother, came in from his hunting.
The Bible tells us that Esau now enters,
and again, as we would think about
the interaction that's recorded,
we now are going to see in these next several verses
the interaction between Isaac and Esau,
and it begins in verse number 31,
and he also had made savory meat
and brought it unto his father,
and said unto his father,
let my father arise in need of my son's venison,
of his son's venison, that thy soul may bless me.
And Isaac, his father, said unto him,
who art thou?
And he said, I am thy son, thy firstborn Esau.
And Isaac trembled very exceedingly, and said, who?
Where is he that hath taken venison and brought it me,
and I have eaten of all before thou camest,
and have blessed him?
Notice this, he says, yea, and he shall be blessed.
We don't understand, perhaps,
all of the nuances of the culture
and all that takes place with the blessing
and all that was wrapped up in verses 28 and 29,
and how this blessing was given,
but we find that Isaac, as he trembles
and as he sees a little bit of what's happening,
it's going to unfold further,
that he says, yea, and he shall be blessed.
When Esau heard the words in verse 34 of his father,
he cried with a great and exceeding bitter cry,
and said unto his father, bless me, even me also,
O my father.
And he said, thy brother came with subtlety,
and hath taken away thy blessing.
And he said, is not he rightly named Jacob,
for he hath supplanted me these two times?
Notice, he took away my birthright,
and behold, now he hath taken away my blessing.
And he said, hast thou not reserved a blessing for me?
And Isaac answered and said unto Esau,
behold, I have made him thy Lord.
And his brethren have I given to him for servants,
and with corn and wine have I sustained him,
and what shall I do now unto thee, my son?
And Esau said unto his father,
hast thou but one blessing, my father?
Bless me, even me also, O my father.
And Esau lifted up his voice and wept.
The book of Hebrews speaks about,
in chapter number 12,
I think I might have said Hebrews 13 earlier,
but in Hebrews chapter number 12,
when the Bible speaks about this event,
it speaks about Esau seeking it,
but what he was seeking was not repentance,
he was seeking a blessing.
He was seeking it with tears.
The Bible says, as you think about what's happening here
in verse 39 and 40,
there is a record of a blessing being given
to Esau from Isaac.
It says that his father answered and said unto him,
behold, thy dwelling shall be in the fatness of the earth
and of the dew of heaven from above,
and by thy sword shalt thou live
and shalt serve thy brother,
and it shall come to pass when thou shalt have the dominion
that thou shalt break his yoke from off thy neck.
I mentioned as we studied chapter 25 of the book of Genesis,
and we talked about those two nations
and two manner of people,
and we looked at that and we mentioned
how that there is recorded strife
between the descendants of Jacob
and the descendants of Esau
throughout the Old Testament.
The descendants of Jacob, of course, the nation of Israel,
the descendants of Esau, the Edomites.
And we read about the Edomites,
and in fact, you read often about the interaction
between the nation of Israel and the Edomites
and their fighting and their battles
and all that took place.
It's interesting at the end of verse number 40
that it says this,
it shall come to pass when thou shalt have the dominion
that thou shalt break his yoke from off thy neck.
Hold your place here,
but turn to the book of 2 Kings, if you will,
and I just wanna reference the fulfillment of this promise
or this aspect of the blessing that is given
in 2 Kings chapter number eight.
The Bible is recording for us here
in the middle section of this chapter,
the reign of Jehoram, King of Judah,
and he's the son of Jehoshaphat,
and it tells us in verse number,
look in verse number 19, it says this,
yet the Lord would not destroy Judah
for David, his servant's sake,
as he promised to give him all way a lie into his children.
In his days, and so in the days of Jehoram,
the Bible says that in his days, in verse number 20,
Edom revolted from under the hand of Judah
and made a king over themselves.
So Jehoram went over to Zear and all the chariots with him
and he rose by night.
and smote the Edomites which compassed him about. The captain of the chariots and the
people fled into their tents." There's this battle, all that's taking place in
verse 22. Yet Edom revolted from under the hand of Judah, notice this, unto this day.
Then Libna revolted at the same time. When you see that phraseology in the scriptures
unto this day, it very regularly means the time of the writing. You'll see it often
in the book of Joshua, unto this day. You'll read about the memorial at Gilgal, the one
in the midst of the Jordan, and they'll talk about them being there unto this day.
It's unto the day of the writing. And we find that he's speaking there in 2 Kings
about the revolt and really what we find in this passage back in Genesis 27, that it shall
come to pass when thou shalt have the dominion that thou shalt break his yoke from off thy
neck. And we find that, of course, if you look at the book of Obadiah, it's just
a short book, but there's many truths that are given in that Old Testament minor prophet
with regard to the Edomites and the descendants of Esau and how God would deal with them because
of their interactions with his people, the nation of Israel. And so we find this interaction
that's recorded. Again, it's a very unfortunate set of circumstances and you see all of the
scheming and all of the carnality and the deception that takes place, and Esau is in
this place, and he's left in this position. And, of course, Esau is no doubt, he's discouraged
by what's taken place. He, though he's carnal, he's not ever really minded anything of spiritual
value that we can read of in his life, though he's carnal, he was simply doing what his
dad told him to do. And things didn't work out well for him, and he receives this, really,
it's a blessing that is given, but not a blessing that was the desired blessing.
Think about this as we finish this evening and look at the remainder of the chapter in
verses 41 through 46, the impact on the family. The impact on the family, first we see it
in Esau. Notice what the Bible says in verse 41, and Esau hated Jacob. He hated Jacob because
of the blessing wherewith his father blessed him. Notice what Esau says in his heart, the
days of mourning for my father at hand, then will I slay my brother Jacob. That's unfortunate,
is it not? The reality is that the days of mourning for Isaac were not really at hand,
though Isaac thought he was going to die and through his communication to Esau, Esau believed
that Isaac would soon die. He'd lived for 40 plus more years, but you find the response
of Esau, his hatred towards his brother, his plan to kill his brother. The Bible tells
us in verse 42, in these words of Esau, her elder son were told to Rebekah. So here we
are, Rebekah once again gets some of this information. She's going to figure out how
to handle this that has now been brought to her attention. It says that she sent and called
Jacob her younger son and said unto him, Behold, thy brother Esau is touching thee, doth comfort
himself, proposing to kill thee. Now therefore, my son, obey my voice, arise, flee thou to
Laban, my brother to Haran. So now Jacob is going to have to depart because of the circumstances,
because of what's taken place, and he's going to have to depart. Notice what it says in
verse number 44, and tarry with him, notice these three words, a few days. Tarry with
him a few days, until thy brother's fury turn away. It wasn't a few days, was it?
You know the sad truth? Rebekah would never see Jacob again. She never saw her son again.
The words of verse number 13, I said to be mindful of those words, that his mother said
unto him, Upon me be thy curse, my son. Only obey my voice and go fetch me them. And now
because of the hatred that Esau has for Jacob because of the blessing, because of his purposing
to kill Jacob, Rebekah says, go to my brother and stay there a few days until Esau's anger,
until his fury turn away. Rebekah would never see her son again. She'd never see Jacob again.
Turned into years, in Genesis 31 and verse number 38, notice what I'm jumping right into
the middle of the text of Scripture, but Jacob says this, This twenty years have I been with
thee. Thy ewes and thy she-goats have not cast their young, and the rams of thy flock
have I not eaten. A few days, twenty years. It's a long time. The impact on the family.
By the way, during those twenty years, Jacob was deceived on more than one occasion, wasn't
he? It's unfortunate, all that transpired. In verse 45, she continues, Until thy brother's
anger turn away from thee, and he forget that which thou hast done to him, then I will
send and fetch thee from thence. Why should I be deprived also of you both in one day?
And so, she says, I'm going to send you there, but when his anger, when Esau's anger is turned
away from thee, and he forgets what's taken place, then I'm going to send for you, and
I'm going to bring you back. Again, that message, those messengers never went. But I want you
to find how the passage ends in verse 46, that Rebecca says to Isaac, I am weary of
my life because of the daughters of Heth. If Jacob take a wife of the daughters of Heth,
such as these which are of the daughters of the land, what good shall my life do to me?
And basically, what Rebecca does, and it leads into chapter number 28 with the departure
of Jacob, and how Isaac would respond to what Rebecca says, is Rebecca is basically
saying to Isaac, we don't want our son, Jacob, to marry the way that Esau married. Remember,
the Bible tells us at the end of chapter 26 that these wives that Esau took, that they
were a grief of mine unto Isaac and to Rebecca in Genesis 26 and verse number 35. Now, the
real purpose that she relays to Jacob for sending him away is because of the plan of
Esau to kill him. But now she comes into the presence of Isaac and says, let's send Jacob
away because we really want him to marry. And you find that the chapter is full of carnality,
deception, scheming, leaning on our own understanding from the beginning to the end of the chapter,
46 verses. And it's sad, is it not? And as I look at this passage of Scripture and I
try to dig it apart and say, okay, God, what do You want us to learn? The reality is that
as we go to the Word of God, He's always got lessons for us to learn. And there are times
in which we learn the behavior of an individual that is an appropriate behavior that we are
to model ourselves after that behavior. Remember what Paul said? He said, the things that you've
heard of me but the things that you've seen in me do. Paul says this to the believers
in Corinth. He says that to the believers in Philippi. To the believers in Corinth,
he says, be followers of me even as I'm a follower of the Lord. And we find that there
are some people that we can look to and we can look at their examples and we can learn
from their behavior and we can say, that is exemplary behavior that is worthy of taking
and applying and adopting those behaviors in my life. But then there's passages like
Genesis chapter number 27 that are just the opposite. These are things not to do. These
are examples that should be warnings to us, like what we find in the book of 1 Corinthians
when God says to the believers in Corinth, He says, listen, Paul is speaking to them,
and he says, listen, with many of them God was not well pleased. In other words, take
heed. Don't follow their example. Don't follow their behavior. And I hope this evening
that we can learn from some negative behavior in Genesis 27. And we can guard against in
our lives relying on our own understanding and thinking that we have to scheme. I said
this often throughout the last couple of chapters of the book of Genesis. Living by faith does
not require scheming. It just doesn't. We do not have to scheme in this life. We can
trust God. You say, but I don't see a way. Neither did they. You don't want to go down
that path. Amen? As soon as you allow that thought, I don't see a way, and I have to
start relying on my own understanding, you start going down a path that leads to poor
decision making apart from God this evening.
My heart is saddened by Genesis 27, I'm just being transparent with you this evening.
As I meditated upon this passage this week, and I read it again this afternoon, and I'm
like, this is heartbreaking to see so much carnality and deception in one chapter of
God's precious book by people that had previously inquired of the Lord.
When Isaac and Rebekah had no children, what did they do?
In Genesis 25, what did they do?
The two of them prayed, said, God, we have no children.
God blessed.
When Rebekah was, there's a struggle within the womb, she inquired of the Lord, and God
answered.
And how easy it is for us to rely on our own understanding, and to think that we need to
figure things out.
I don't know how God could have or would have worked in Genesis 27.
It's hypothetical.
Because the decisions were made that resulted in the consequences that are recorded.
But wouldn't it be interesting in your mind to just think about some of the other passages
of Scripture that we read and we see God moving and working in phenomenal ways and bringing
to pass those things that you'd say, we never could figure out how this was going to happen.
But God.
You ever read those statements in the Word of God?
You say, man, this is exciting.
Because God did what only God could do.
The Bible tells us in Psalm 78, and I'll end with this.
Psalm 78 is a long psalm.
And it deals primarily, it records a lot of the history of Israel and it goes through
a number of events.
Somewhere around verse number 41, the Bible says this, that they, the children of Israel,
limited the Holy One of Israel.
The unlimited God, the Almighty God.
What limited Him?
Their unbelief.
Their sin.
Their scheming.
This evening, I don't want to limit God.
I don't want to see what my plan can bring to pass.
Didn't work out well for them in Genesis 27.
For Rebekah and Jacob, their plan didn't work out well.
He received the blessing.
I want to see God's plan.
Amen?
See what God can do.
Because we serve the Almighty Creator of the universe.
And He is able, as I said this morning in Sunday school, to do exceeding abundantly
above all that we ask or think.
Joseph at once said, daddy, you forgot to emphasize that word all in Sunday school.
You talked about all the other words.
But all.
So Joseph, there you go.
All that we ask or think, amen?
He is.
We serve a great God.
Let's trust Him and let Him have His way.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
Thank You for loving us.
I know that it's so easy, perhaps easier for some than others, but it's so easy as humans
to want to take things, matters, into our own hands.
God, I pray that tonight You'd help us to learn from this passage of Scripture to rely
fully upon Thee, that we might see You do the impossible from our human perspective,
that we might see You do what we might not even be able to imagine.
Help us to live by faith without scheming, refusing to even start down that path.
Help us to simply trust You.
Well, thank You, God, for what You'll do in our hearts and lives as You teach us from
Your Word.
Would You move and work as only You can, for it's in Christ's name we pray.