Here in Mark chapter number five as we look at this passage of scripture this evening
I want to deal with the subject matter really the passage that we're looking at will record for us the
great miracle that took place the maniac Gadara and
This man's conversion and what-have-you and as we look at this passage of scripture
I want to read verse 19 to you and give you the
Titling kind of get into the message this evening in Mark 5 in verse number 19
The Bible says how be it Jesus suffered him not but saith unto him
Go home to thy friends and tell them how great things the Lord hath done for thee and hath
had compassion on
Thee I'm gonna preach a message this evening that I've simply entitled go and tell
Go and tell now as I was preparing the message and thinking about that title
I was reminded of days in grade school when we had show and tell let me remember show and tell
Yeah, somebody remember that right and you'd have show and tell and it wasn't very often. I don't remember
Having show and tell on a regular basis
in fact
I
tried to
in my mind remember some of the things that some of my
Classmates brought some of the things that I took for show-and-tell and I was coming up with a blank
And so it seems as if nothing was too, you know that life
impactful at a show-and-tell
In my elementary days in grade school
however
I know that what would happen is we'd go to school and really was kind of an exciting day and
You would go and you would prepare for what is it that I'm gonna take and you'd bring something in and you would show
Your classmates whatever that object was and then you would tell them about it and
No doubt there were times in which you'd try to find something that was unique
right something that not everybody else in the class would have and be familiar with and
want to take them something that was unique that you could show them and maybe be proud of and what have you and
you'd have the show-and-tell and you'd hear all of the students and what have you as
We think about the times in in grade school of show-and-tell and we think about those funny memories
I'm thinking this evening about the passage that is before us and the
Instruction that the Lord Jesus Christ gives to this man. He doesn't tell him to show and tell
In fact in Luke, he tells him to go and show them great things that the Lord has done
But here as it's recorded in Mark, he says go and tell
As I think about that message that Jesus gives to this man at Gadara
this maniac that had experienced the power of God a
mindful this evening of the
Responsibility that has been given to each of us as the people of God the children of God to go and tell
to go and tell
The reality this evening as we look at this passage of Scripture were reminded of the power of God
I'm so thankful that the our God is omnipotent that he has all power
I'm thankful that he did not simply declare to us that he has all power though
He did we find that he's demonstrated on a number of occasions throughout his word his great power
In fact as you read through the gospel accounts and you read the miracles of the Lord Jesus Christ
You find how that he's demonstrating his power over various things. He demonstrates his power over nature
He demonstrates his power over disease. He demonstrates his power
Such as this passage of Scripture over the demons and I'm so thankful that our God has all power
And he demonstrated that power we think about the miracles of Christ
And of course we can think about the miracles of the Bible in its entirety and you can see the power of God demonstrated
But you think about the impact that those miracles had not only on the ones that were the recipients
Personally of the the power of God, but those that saw those that were eyewitnesses of what God did
the power of God
We find in this passage of Scripture. The Bible begins in verse number one and
it says and they
Came over unto the other side of the sea into the country of the Gadarenes now
It's interesting because Jesus is with his disciples
And if you read the latter part of chapter number four, you find one of those
Instances in which the Lord Jesus Christ demonstrated his power over nature
It was there when they were in the midst of a storm and Jesus was asleep on a pillow and they came to him saying master
Carest thou not that we perish and we find that it was Jesus in this particular account that he stands and he says peace
Be still the Bible tells us that the wind ceased and there was a great calm
He then says to them why are you so fearful how is it that you have no faith they
Were fearing exceedingly they said one to another what manner of man is this that even the wind and the sea?
obey him
this was a a
Week in which they had experienced many amazing things much teaching and
many miracles
We find that we come to
chapter number five and we know that the chapter divisions are there for us and the Bible says that they came over under the other
side of the sea
They were instructed to pass over to the other side in verse number 35 of chapter number four
It says the same day when the even was come he says unto them
Let us pass over under the other side. There was a purpose for them crossing the sea
There was a purpose for them going to the the country of the Gatorades and that purpose was to meet this man that the
passage of Scripture deals with in its entirety and we find that this
Encounter is recorded for us and really in the first 18 verses of the chapter
We find if you were to take notes this evening
The man was converted and it's a lengthy passage that shares with us all of the interaction and all that takes place
The Bible tells us that when they got they arrived there to the country of the Gatorades
It says in verse number two and when he was come out of the ship
Immediately there met him out of the tombs a man
with an unclean spirit
And the Bible tells us of this interaction that this man with this unclean spirit
We often would refer to him as the maniac of Gadara that this man
Immediately upon the Lord Jesus Christ God in flesh
coming off of that ship this man meets him and the Bible tells us in verse 3 and
Following some things about this man some of his characteristics and some of his
Behavior it says who had his dwelling among the tombs
And no man could bind him. No not with chains
Because they had been often bound with fetters and chains and the chains had been plucked asunder by him and the fetters broken in
pieces neither
Could any man?
tame him
And always
Night and day he was in the mountains and in the tombs
crying and cutting himself
with stones
The picture that is painted of this man's behavior some of his characteristics in verses 3 through 5
Really would lead us to a place where you say I wouldn't like to meet that fella
Amen
Not someone that I would like to meet
Not someone I care to have interaction with we find the Bible says in verse number 6
But when he saw Jesus afar off he ran and worshipped him
And cried with a loud voice and said what have I to do with thee Jesus now son of the Most High God I
Adjure thee by God that thou torment me not
It's interesting. We've often said as you read through the gospel accounts the truth that the demons they understand who Jesus is
They know that he is God. They know
Who he is. In fact, you find that here they say to torment me not they
Understand the the plan of God they understand listen the devil knows that his time is short
the devil knows that he's gonna be cast in the lake of fire and he's gonna be tormented day and night forever and ever and
these
Demons here that had indwelled this particular man that possessed this man. They understand who Jesus is
The Bible tells us and James that the devils believe and
Tremble they know who Jesus is
Verse number 8 it says for he said unto him come out of the man thou unclean spirit and he Jesus asked him
What is?
thy name and
He answered saying my name is legion
for we are many
And he besought him much that he would not send them away out of the country now
There was there nigh unto the mountains a great herd of swine feeding and all the devils besought him saying send us
into the swine that we may enter into them and
forthwith Jesus gave them leave
The unclean spirits went out and entered into the swine and the herd ran violently down a steep place into the sea
there were about
2,000 and were choked in the sea and
They that fed the swine fled and told it in the city and in the country and they went out to see what it was
That was done. Now. I want you to consider put yourself in the place here in Gadara
If you will and understand what is happening as we find that Jesus and his disciples have crossed over
The sea as it's recorded for us at the end of chapter before and they arrived
into the country of the Gadarenes and we find
that as they begin to get off of the ship,
that this man that no doubt
they knew about this man
that had an unclean spirit.
The Bible tells us
that neither could any man tame him.
The Bible tells us that he was often
bound with fetters and chains.
And we understand that this man,
the people of Gadar had some knowledge of this man.
And they see what's happening
and the Bible tells us
that as the Lord Jesus Christ
is having interaction with this demon-possessed man,
he's speaking to the demon specifically.
And he says, what is thy name?
And the answer comes
and you find that they make a request.
They beseech the Lord
that they would not send them out away into the country.
They had this desire to enter into the swine.
And Jesus gave them leave in v. 13.
And what that reveals to us is again
that Jesus has all power.
Again, the demons did not have the choice
as to what they did or where they went
and how they went.
We find that Jesus gave them leave.
Jesus allowed this to happen.
He permitted it to happen.
Of course, we'd understand
with the Jewish culture
and the dietary restrictions
and all of those things,
though this particular region
would have been more Gentile than Jewish,
we find that no doubt
there were some things that were taking place
with the raising of these swine and what have you,
and Jesus would allow them, these demons,
to have the opportunity to go into these swine.
The Bible tells us that they entered into the swine
and notice what happens.
The herd ran violently down a steep place into the sea.
But the Bible tells us something interesting
in v. 14, it says,
and they that fed the swine fled.
They were holding it in the city, in the country,
and they went out to see what it was that was done.
There's some people that observe what took place.
They saw these swine that were over there
and I'm not sure how they were behaving
prior to these demons entering into them,
but as soon as these demons were cast out of this man
and entered into those swine,
the Bible tells us that they ran violently
down a steep,
and we find that they were choked in the sea.
They died. They ran violently.
They saw it and they went and they told some people.
They let them know what had happened.
And it's interesting that it says
they went out to see what was that was done.
Whoever it is that these that fed the swine,
whoever they told in the city and in the country,
there was a group of people that came back.
I want you to think about it in your mind's eye.
Put yourself there again
and understand what's happening
as the report had been given.
It's mindful as you look at various portions of Scripture
and you see how there are times
in which people would go
and share truth with others to bring them.
I think about the situation in John 4
when Jesus said, I must go through.
I must pass through Samaria.
And He meets the woman of the well.
And you remember that after that interaction,
she goes back and says,
come, see a man that told me all things ever I've done.
And there's a great host of people
that come back to where Jesus is
in John 4.
The Bible tells us in that passage of Scripture
that there were some that believed
because of the testimony of the woman.
But the Bible tells us that there were
a great number of people,
many more that believed
because of His own Word.
He spent two days teaching those people
that came back in John 4.
And here in Mark 5,
we're not told of the size of the crowd that returns,
but we find that as they would return
to the place in which these
that had fed the swine told them of,
that they came,
and notice what it tells us in v. 15,
and they come to Jesus,
and notice what it says,
and see Him that was possessed
with the devil and had the legion.
What does it tell us?
They see this man sitting
and clothed
and in his right mind.
And they were afraid.
There's a great change
in the life of this individual.
We find there's a great contrast
in v. 15 to what we read in v. 3-5
with regard to the characteristics of this man
and his behavior.
And we find now that this man
who had been in this situation
where he was dwelling among the tombs,
where he was not able to be bound,
this man now is sitting at the feet of Jesus.
He's clothed in his right mind.
No doubt, the people are perplexed.
No doubt, they've heard from these
that fed the swine what had taken place,
and they come and they see this scene.
And the Bible says that they were sore afraid.
They were sore afraid.
It says, "...and they that saw it told them
how it befell to him that was possessed
with the devil and also concerning the swine."
It's interesting as we begin to see
what's happening here in Mark 5
in the account that is given to us,
and we begin to see how these people
are just receiving this information,
but it's sad how they respond
to the information that they receive.
This man that had no doubt
had some level of being a nuisance
and they tried to bind him
and all of these things,
and now the man is sitting in cloth
in his right mind.
And Luke would tell us that he's sitting
at the feet of Jesus.
No doubt, he's being instructed
and he's receiving the truth
of the Word of God.
And we find here that the people
receive this message,
but they respond in this manner
in verse 17.
"...they began to pray him
to depart out of their coast."
Really what the Scriptures are telling us
is they wanted Jesus to leave.
They wanted Jesus to leave.
That He would depart out of their coast.
And then the Bible tells us this,
"...and when He was come into the ship,
that He is Jesus."
It then tells us that He that had been
possessed with the devil,
prayed Him that He might be with Him.
Now, as a side note,
as we would consider even as we looked
in the book of Hebrews not long ago,
and we dealt with some of those things
that should accompany salvation.
We speak about some birthmarks of the believer.
The reality is that as we are believers,
as our souls, we get saved
and we're born again
and we have that transformation,
we ought to desire to be with Him.
And we find here that this man,
as Jesus is going to depart,
He's come to Gadara for just a short period of time.
He came there for a purpose
and we find that the people of the city,
they begin to pray Him to depart out of their coast
and Jesus is getting onto the ship
and as He's planning to leave,
this one that was possessed of the devil
prayed Him that He might be with Him.
Now, I don't blame the guy for wanting to go with Jesus.
Do you?
If they wanted Jesus to leave
and this man had experienced the power of Christ
and he had experienced this transformation,
he wants to be with Jesus.
I think it's commendable.
But Jesus tells them no.
Jesus tells them no.
It's not because Jesus didn't want Him to be with them.
It's because Jesus was leaving a witness behind.
We find that the Bible says in v. 19,
how be it Jesus suffered Him not.
He didn't allow Him to come.
And then He gives them some instruction.
We see that the man was converted.
We now see that the man is commissioned.
I love the direct nature of what Jesus says to this man.
Again, Jesus has been there
and He's given some instruction.
The man wants to go to be with them.
And Jesus allows him not,
but gives him a commission.
He says this,
go home to thy friends
and tell them how great things
the Lord hath done for thee
and hath had compassion on thee.
Go and tell.
He told them where to go.
And He told them what to tell them.
Amen?
He had experienced something.
By the way, I mentioned this morning
as we referenced a portion of Scripture in Acts 16
that the message of that girl
that was possessed with a spirit of divination
that she was giving the right message,
but it was the wrong vessel.
Now we have a man that has been transformed.
He's been born again.
He's been converted.
And now, he is given the responsibility
to go and tell.
Go home to thy friends.
There was a responsibility
that was laid upon this individual.
This man that we often refer to
as the maniac of Gadara,
he was given this great responsibility.
and he was given this commission to go home to his friends and he's told to
tell them how great things the Lord hath done for thee I wonder this morning this
evening it's not morning anymore I wonder this evening has God done great
things for you I've been so good to us the truth of redemption the the miracle
of redemption the fact that I was lost and on my way to a Christless eternity
the book of Ephesians the Apostle Paul he deals with it this way that we have
no hope right we're strangers we have no hope but yet receive that message of the
gospel of Jesus Christ and we find that he's done great things for us the
truth of conversion it says and have had compassion on thee we often speak of the
fact that our Lord is compassionate I'm thankful that Jeremiah said his
compassions they fail not I'm thankful that often as you read the gospel
accounts you find that the Lord Jesus Christ is moved with compassion in fact
in the passage of Scripture in Matthew chapter 9 a passage a passage that we
often reference about the harvest being plenteous and the labors being few the
Bible tells us in verse number 36 of that portion of Scripture that when he
Jesus saw the multitudes he was moved with compassion on them why because they
fainted and were scattered abroad as sheep having no shepherd then saith he
unto his disciples the harvest truly is plenteous but the labors are few pray
therefore the Lord of the harvest that he will send forth laborers into his
harvest and here in our passage in Mark chapter number five this man has a
desire to depart to be with the Lord and Jesus suffered him not he allowed him
not but he gave him some very important direction the responsibility that is
laid upon this man is responsibility that he gladly accepted we see that
through his actions as is recorded in verse number 20 the Bible says and he
departed and began to publish in Decapolis how great things Jesus had
done for him and then the Bible says this and all men did marvel as we look
at the account that is before us this evening and we consider the the
commission that was given to this individual and we understand that Jesus
gave him specific instruction as to where to go and what to tell and how to
communicate these things to those that he would come into contact with it the
man immediately he received the instruction and he obeyed he departed
and began to publish I like the way that the Bible records for us how the man
just simply submitted to the authority of the Lord Jesus Christ okay this is
what you're leaving me to do I'll do it and the Bible says that he did exactly
as he was told he departed Jesus said go and he began to publish Jesus said tell
and he published in Decapolis how great things Jesus had done for him see this
evening God's done some great things for us I've often found not so much in
recent weeks or months but in time before Kovat is there was more
interaction and more opportunity to go out and speak with individuals and even
during this time of Kovat there have been unique opportunities just not as
many we find that it's my approach has changed slightly and the fact that as I
begin to speak with individuals I asked him if I can share with them what Jesus
did has done for me can I tell you what he's done for me can I tell you how he
changed my life can I tell you how and all of a sudden it's it's a different
response Joseph you've been door-knocking with me for years Joseph
been my partner and there's other folks that I've gone door-knocking with but
I've taken Joseph door-knocking many many many times and Holly will go with
the girls and they're always asked hey are you guys sisters and Joseph used to
say daddy why doesn't anyone ever think we're brothers I'll leave it alone amen
he's getting older now so I don't know I mean if he shaves his hair a little
shorter maybe somebody will I don't know in any case there have been times that
he's no doubt experienced as he's heard the interactions or the people that hey
my name is so-and-so you know go hey I don't ever introduce myself as pastor I
am Chris this is Joseph for Fellowship Baptist Church I'd like to invite you to
church you know any people accept that that's okay we're good honestly right how
many people we say that to all the time there was one day I can't remember the
exact day I probably have it in a note down in my office but I took a different
approach I said hi my name is Chris my son Joseph can I tell you how God
changed my life I like to share with you what Jesus has done for me you know that
on that day I had opportunity to speak more deeply with more people in one day
than I had in weeks combined of door-knocking here's a thought when I
invite somebody to church they already kind of have an idea of what church is
like they've already had in their mind perhaps an experience with church maybe
a bad experience I'm not going to church church is boring churches whatever they
think right whatever their experience has been whatever's led to their
conclusion with regard to church so immediately as I say I'd like to invite
you to church there's a certain something that takes place in them when
they hear those words but if I say to them can I tell you how God's changed my
life can I tell you how he's given me hope can I tell you how he's given me a
peace can I tell you all of a sudden there's man people don't have that stuff
people are looking for that and all of a sudden you have an opportunity to be
able to start sharing the great things that he God has done for me and the
Bible says all men did marvel I wonder in the last I don't know generation or
two in our churches where we have had so much impact sorry instruction wrong word
so much instruction on how to go so winning quote-unquote and we memorize
our little script as to what we're going to say and we go through our little
verses and I'm not I'm not seeking to be unkind but typically in that memorized
kind of sales pitch ish kind of a thing how many people have been turned off
Jesus told this man to go and tell them how great things the Lord hath done for
thee so I wonder this evening if we take the approach of not so much just trying
to go through some memorized script of how I'm supposed to invite somebody to
come and to visit our church and this that and the other thing is if I begin
to approach it in the manner of can I tell you what he's done for me can I
tell you how he changed my life because here's the amazing thing you have the
testimony of a transformed life this you don't have this guy's testimony amen you
know it's his testimony you don't have my testimony and I don't have your
testimony but you have a testimony I know it's amazing is that you can
speak passionately about what Christ has done for you why cuz it's real amen
and you're not talking about what he's done for somebody else though we can
maybe use some examples but you're talking about what he's done for you and
when you talk about what he's done for you and they see that it's genuine they
see that it's real have you ever dealt with some salespeople that you're just
like man this guy is just he is a sales guy right I don't want to be that guy
knocking on somebody's door I'm not trying to sell somebody the gospel it's
not for sale you can't buy it amen and so I don't want someone to get the
impression that I'm just going through some little you know sales pitch but let
me tell you what he's done for me let me tell you changes my life so I don't know
if you can remember when you were lost I can remember when I was lost I can
remember when I didn't have the peace that I have today I can remember when I
didn't have the purpose that I have today I can remember and I know that you
can remember as well most many of you and when you can remember those things
begin to share that and you say let me tell you what he's
is done for me,
and the impact that that can make on others.
All men did marvel.
I want to share with you,
go over to Luke 1 if you will.
It's a slightly different context
as to what is taking place here.
But I want you to read and hear the words,
the testimony that is given here.
We begin looking in verse 41.
It came to pass that when Elizabeth
heard the salutation of Mary,
the babe leaped in her womb,
and Elizabeth was filled with the Holy Ghost.
And she spake out with a loud voice and said,
Blessed art thou among women,
and blessed is the fruit of thy womb.
And whence is this to me,
that the mother of my Lord
should come to me?
For lo, as soon as the voice of thy salutation
sounded in mine ears,
the babe leaped in my womb for joy.
And blessed is she that believed,
and there shall be a performance of those things
which were told her from the Lord.
And look at what Mary says.
Verse 46,
My soul doth magnify the Lord,
and my spirit hath rejoiced in God my Savior.
For He hath regarded the low state of His handmaiden,
for behold, from henceforth all generations
shall call me blessed.
For He that is mighty
hath done to me great things,
and holy is His name.
I understand contextually what Mary is speaking of
is different than what we're dealing with this evening,
but I'd like to adopt the words of verse 49
and apply them to our lives
as far as conversion is concerned.
And I'd like to say that He that is mighty
hath done to me great things,
and holy is His name.
And I have the opportunity, the privilege
of being His representative.
And the thing that's amazing
is that in this particular account,
in Mark 5 that we're studying this evening,
the reality is that Jesus had not yet gone
to the cross of Calvary.
Jesus had not yet been in the tomb for those three days.
He'd not yet ascended,
raised from the dead and then ascended to heaven.
But we find that now as those events
are historically past,
that Jesus has paid for the sin of mankind
by going to the cross of Calvary.
He's been buried.
He's risen from the dead.
He's conquered sin, death, and the grave.
He's ascended into heaven.
And He's done something miraculous
in the fact that He's given us
the Holy Spirit of God.
And in so doing, He says this
when He gives the Great Commission
in Matthew 28,
in lo, I am with you always.
And so here's the amazing thing
is that when we look at this account
in Mark 5,
Jesus is still physically upon the earth.
And this man wants to go to be with Jesus.
He's getting on the ship.
And Jesus suffered him not.
He allowed him not.
He said, no, you need to go home to your friends
and you need to tell them,
here's your commission.
Here's what you're supposed to do.
And we find that the man immediately departs
and he goes and he tells.
We have the privilege of Jesus being with us.
He's left us here.
Notice in John 17.
We'll finish with this passage of Scripture,
but I want you to notice what Jesus is saying here
in John 17 as He prays just before
He would go to the cross of Calvary.
This really is the Lord's prayer
in John 17.
It's not the one that many refer to
as the Lord's prayer.
That would be a model prayer.
We find here in John 17
that Jesus is praying.
It says,
These words spake Jesus and lifted up His eyes to heaven
and said, Father, the hour has come.
Glorify Thy Son that Thy Son also may glorify Thee.
We don't have time to read the entire prayer.
I want you to skip down to verse 13.
And now come I to Thee
and these things I speak in the world
that they might have my joy fulfilled in themselves.
I have given them Thy Word.
The world hath hated them
because they are not of the world
even as I am not of the world.
I pray not that Thou shouldest take them out of the world,
but that Thou shouldest keep them from the evil.
They are not of the world
even as I am not of the world.
Sanctify them through Thy truth.
Thy Word is truth.
As Thou hast sent me into the world,
even so have I also sent them into the world.
And for their sakes I sanctify myself
and they also might be sanctified through the truth.
Neither pray I for these alone,
but for them also which shall believe on me
through their word,
that they all may be one
as Thou, Father, art in me and I in Thee,
that they also may be one in us,
that the world may believe that Thou hast sent me.
It tells us in verse 22,
in the glory which Thou gavest me,
I have given them that they may be one
even as we are one,
I in them and Thou in me,
that they may be made perfect in one,
that the world may know that Thou hast sent me
and hast loved them as Thou hast loved me.
Father, I will that they also
whom Thou hast given me be with me where I am,
that they may behold my glory which Thou hast given me
for Thou lovest me before the foundation of the world.
Oh, righteous Father, the world hath not known Thee,
but I have known Thee
and these have known that Thou hast sent me
and I have declared unto them Thy name
and will declare it
that the love wherewith Thou hast loved me
may be in them and I in them.
And we find that here as we would understand,
yes, as we look at the Great Commission in Matthew,
specifically as I referenced a moment ago,
Jesus gives the commission to us as the people of God
to the same people that we are to go.
He says, all power is given unto me in heaven and earth.
Go ye therefore, right?
And we understand the threefold purpose
or aspect of the Great Commission
that we're to win them to Christ,
baptize them and disciple them.
That's the fullness of the Great Commission,
but we go in the power of Christ.
But you shall receive power
after the Holy Ghost has come upon thee
in Acts chapter number one.
And we find that that instruction is given
to the disciples just before the ascension.
And he tells them that you're going to receive power,
that the Holy Ghost is gonna come upon you.
And he tells them that at that time,
and ye shall be witnesses unto me,
both in Jerusalem, Judea and on Samaria
and unto the uttermost part of the earth this evening.
Go and tell.
I like what Brother Hamilton said on Wednesday evening.
I remember as I, a number of years ago,
preached through the book of Philippians
and mentioned this same portion of Scripture
and how that Paul said,
for to me to live is Christ and to die is gain.
And he shares with us that difficult position that he's in
that he has this desire to go and to be with Christ,
which is far better.
I mean, listen, it's gonna be wonderful
when we get to be with Him, amen?
When we see Jesus, I mean, when we see Him face to face,
I mean, what a blessed reality
that as the people of God,
one day we will meet Him and we will be with Him forever.
But Paul said in Philippians one,
nevertheless to abide in the flesh is more needful for you.
In verse number 24 of Philippians chapter number one.
And Brother Hamilton spoke about that a little bit
on Wednesday evening and what a great reminder to us
that the Lord has left us here for a purpose.
Just like he left that maniac from Gadara
whose life was transformed by the power of Jesus Christ.
He said, no, I'm suffering you not.
He didn't allow him to get on the boat.
He said, no, you need to stay.
You need to go and tell your friends.
There's some people we need to go and tell, amen?
There's some people we need to go and tell.
The reality is that if Jesus didn't have a purpose
for us here upon earth, at the moment of salvation,
we'd just go ahead and be transported to heaven, amen?
And sometimes maybe in life you say,
man, I wish it was that way, but it's not.
He's got a purpose for us here.
And here's something that Brother Hamilton said,
and I'm gonna say something different, but in like manner.
He said this, it was impactful to me as your pastor.
It was this.
This life is the only life you have to live by faith.
That's what he said.
Once we get to heaven, we see him, sight, it's not faith.
Right?
Without faith, it is impossible to please him.
For he that cometh to God must believe that he is
and a rewarder of them that diligently seek him.
Hebrews 11 and verse number six.
Therefore, the just shall live by faith.
I'm living by faith, but I'm only living by faith now.
Amen?
It's the only time we have to live by faith is right now.
If I could say something different, but in like manner,
the only time you have to go and tell somebody
the great things that Jesus has done for you is now.
There aren't gonna be any lost people in heaven, right?
If I understand the Bible properly,
If you understand the Bible properly,
the Bible teaches us
that only saved people will go to heaven.
Amen?
So once we take our final breath,
once the trumpet of the Lord sounds,
whichever one happens first for us,
there will be no more opportunity
for us to go and tell somebody about Christ.
Right? You agree with that?
So go home and tell thy friends.
That's what He tells them.
Go home to thy friends and tell them
how great things the Lord hath done for thee
and hath showed compassion on thee.
And this evening,
the only life I have to tell anybody about Jesus
is this life.
Once it's over,
there's nobody for me to tell.
There's no more opportunities.
Oh, I will praise Him forevermore.
And so will you.
I mean, we'll be in His presence.
And what a wonderful thing that is.
But there's not going to be any more opportunities
to tell anybody about Jesus.
It's just this life
And so Jesus says to this man,
the people,
they said, we want you to leave.
And Jesus goes to get on the ship.
He said, I want to go with you.
He said, no.
He suffered them not,
but left them.
Left them as a witness,
as a light in that place.
And ye are the light of the world.
Right, and that's what He told us.
Matthew, the light of the world.
In fact, Paul mentions it the same way in Philippians,
that we are lights in this world.
Notice what Paul says,
we'll close with this.
I wasn't going to use this verse.
I said Philippians chapter number,
is it two or three?
Let me look real quick.
Philippians chapter number two.
Verse number 15.
That you may be blameless and harmless,
the sons of God, without rebuke,
in the midst of a crooked and perverse nation,
among whom you shine as lights in the world.
We're in the midst of a crooked and perverse nation now.
Not in heaven.
Amen?
Now.
I have in the margin of my Bible,
how bright is my light?
Because I am to be,
you are to be,
shining lights in this world.
Jesus said of John the Baptist,
that he was a bright and shining light.
I trust that would be the testimony for each of us
as God's people.
That we take this message,
go and tell.
Go and tell.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for this passage of Scripture in Mark 5.
We know that the truth is recorded
by Matthew and Luke as well.
God, we thank You for the way in which
this passage reveals to us
the conversion of this man.
This evening as we focus in upon
the commission for this man,
we make application in our own lives.
Lord, we understand that You've left us here for a purpose.
And that purpose is to go and tell.
I'm thankful that as believers
in what we would refer to as the church age,
that we go in the power
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
The power of the Holy Spirit.
I'm thankful You've given us the privilege
and opportunity to go and tell.
God, I believe that each person
that's here this evening
would readily testify of the great things
that You've done for us.
How You've changed our lives.
The miracle of salvation.
And how precious that is.
And God, I pray that we'd go
in the simplicity of that message
and share that truth with the lost and dying world.
That we'd simply be able to share with them,
can I tell you?
What the Lord's done for me.
Can I tell you how He's changed me?
I pray that You'd use us.
Give us courage and boldness.
Help us, Lord, to be faithful and obedient
even as this man,
who upon receiving the commission,
embraced it,
departed and published.
All men did marvel.
Help us, Lord.
I pray that You'd have Your will and way
in the time of invitation
that decisions would be made
that would please Thee
and we'll thank You for it.
In Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano.
As she does, the altar...