there with me, please, to Psalm 122. Not my message, but I'm glad to see you all here
tonight. Amen. Here we are on a Tuesday night. It's the third day of the revival meetings
and I'm thankful that you're here tonight. I praise the Lord for that. Thank you for
coming and being faithful to the house of God and supporting your fall revival meeting.
Psalm 122, it's another one of David's song of degrees. It's a Davidic psalm, certainly
put the music, and this is a particular psalm that I love, the first verse there. It says
David says, I was glad. See that? He said, I was glad when they said unto me, let us
go into the house of the Lord. Now I'll tell you, there's a, there's a message all of its
own right there. That'll preach real good. David said, I was glad. That word glad, there's
a very interesting word. In the Hebrew it's tzolmach and it means this. It means to be
merry, to exult, to be gleesome, to be cheerful, to be joyful, to be excited. Amen. It means
to come to the house of God with great expectation. When we come to church, we should come to
church expecting God to do something. And you know, God wants to show up in a meeting.
That's why we have prayer before the service. That's why we want to make sure we commit
and consecrate everything unto the Lord because we want the Lord to show up. We want the Lord
to do something. I remember years ago, evangelist Harold Vaughn said, it's good to be in town
when God shows up. And there's a lot of truth to that. And I'm glad that we've seen meetings
over the years where God has certainly showed up. And I'll tell you, it was a hallelujah
time and we thank the Lord for that. But David said, listen, I was glad when they said unto
me, let us go into the house of the Lord. So it's good for us to be here tonight. I've
already enjoyed the fellowship. We stood at the back door and we greeted people as they
came in and we've talked a little bit this evening and we've spent some time together
and just in fellowship. And I've enjoyed that. I don't know what I'd do without the fellowship
of God's people. I just say to my wife, I said, I sure am glad that I have you because
as we travel, us being together is a blessing because otherwise you get pretty lonely. And
so I'm glad that we have that companionship, that fellowship and that partnership in ministry.
My family is many miles away from us. They're all up in Alaska and all my daughters up there
and my son-in-law who pastors a church in Sterling, Alaska is up there. And then our
five grandchildren and our 14 great-grandchildren. And so we only get to see them maybe once
a year, maybe twice. And every once in a while they'll come down to California. They're smart.
Amen. They get out of there in the winter and either come to California or go to Hawaii.
Wowee, mawee. And so we don't get to go up there that much. And so we miss our family
and we don't have any family left in California. So it's just us and us too. And so I'm thankful
for the fellowship of my wife, but what a blessing family is. What a joy it is to be
able to fellowship with your family, but your family too. We're all part of the family of God.
And so we can gather together in this place and we can enjoy the fellowship one with another.
I've said this many times, I've been in 36 countries in the world in my lifetime.
And you can't go anywhere where you don't, you find brothers and sisters everywhere you go.
You find believers everywhere you go. It's amazing to me, you can find believers in some
of the most bizarre places. And it's a joy and it's a blessing to know that we have brothers
and sisters in Christ around the world that we can fellowship with. I found them in some pretty
interesting places. And so praise the Lord for that. Amen. The fellowship of the saints is a joy
and it's a blessing. So I'm glad that we're here tonight. I think we should be glad we are able to
come here tonight. I'm thankful for the liberty, the freedom we have in America to gather together
in this place and to have fellowship one with another. A lot of gallant men paid for our liberty
and our freedom with their blood on the battlefields of wars that have been fought
in this country to keep us free. And so we ought to thank God for that. We're a free people.
Now there's a lot of things going on in America today that people are getting concerned about.
They wonder how much longer we're going to have our freedom. Well, listen, we have freedom. We
are a free country. And as long as we have it, we ought to praise God for it. It's a precious thing.
It's a precious thing. Amen. If you've ever talked to anybody who came from a communist
country, you'll know when they come here, they realize what a joy it is to live in the United
States of America. I'm getting a little bit tired of people complaining about this country.
And by the way, we don't have to make excuses to anybody. We don't need to, listen, friends,
we don't need to ask the forgiveness of anybody. We've done so much for the world and we've been
so gracious to the world and we've shared our abundance with the world. So we have no apologies
to make. Would you agree with that? It's a wonderful thing to be an American. I thank God
that I was born here. And we have our brother and sister down here that came from countries down in
Central America and praise the Lord for them. And now they're here in our great country and
they're Americans. Praise the Lord. We're with a bunch of Filipino people in our home church,
and they're all Americans now, and they rejoice in that. And they all, hey, listen, let me tell
you what, on Veterans Day, all of our Filipino brethren are in their uniforms because 90%
of our men are retired from the United States Navy. So we praise the Lord for that. Amen.
We've got freedom and we have freedom that we ought to rejoice in. All right,
2 Timothy chapter four in your Bible tonight, that was free by the way, I just thought I'd
share that. 2 Timothy chapter four in verse seven, if you didn't already get it, I have a patriot,
I love my country. 2 Timothy chapter four in verse seven. We're going to start there tonight and
we're going to move over to the Old Testament in a minute. But 2 Timothy chapter four in verse
seven, I shared this verse along with one over in Acts chapter 20. Maybe we'll look at that just
in a minute as well, on Saturday with the men's prayer breakfast. But I want you to look at 2
Timothy four in verse seven. If you will, if you can, please let's stand out of respect for the
reverence and for the respect and reverence for the reading of God's word tonight. 2 Timothy
chapter four in verse seven. I'll read the one verse silently, then you can just follow along
silently, then we'll pray and get into the message God has for us tonight. Now the Apostle Paul
speaking here and says this, he said, I fought a good fight. He said, by the way, I've finished my
course and also I've kept the faith. But I want you to look at that word, the operative word there
in that particular verse of scripture is finished. Paul finished. And I believe he finished a lot
stronger than the way he started, but he finished. He never deviated from his course. He never
changed course. Now, perhaps along the way, he had to make some course corrections. And then I
suggest to you tonight that when we start talking about revival, revival really is a course
correction for many people that maybe have gotten off course and gotten going in the wrong direction
and not been heading in a direction that God has established for them in their Christian life.
And they need a course correction and they've gotten back on course. The Spirit of God has
nudged them back on the course again. Now, I don't know about you, but I want to finish strong.
I don't want to, listen, friends, I don't want to finish weak. I want to finish strong.
When my time comes to close my eyes in death and go be with the Lord Jesus, I want to be able to
say, I finished my course. That should be the desire of every Christian. We should want to
finish our course and we should want to finish it well. And I think that's an important thing.
It's a biblical imperative that we do so. Too many people are reversing course or getting
off course and going in the wrong direction. And we see a lot of that going on today. There's a
lot of apostasy going on today in the world, not just in America. And so we want to be good
course keepers. We're going to talk about that tonight by God's grace for just the next few
minutes. Father, we thank you, Lord, for the reading of that word tonight. We ask God you'd
meet with us now and that you would help us. Help me. I'm a needy preacher. I'm going to need
your help. If I'm going to preach this message tonight, the way you've impressed it upon my
heart. Spirit of God, do that which only you can do. And Lord, use me tonight as a vessel unto
honor. God, use me tonight to be your vessel. Lord, speak through me as your conduit. Lord,
I pray that you'd fill me with thy spirit and wipe my lips. God, help me not to say anything
tonight, but what it would bring praise and glory and honor to your name. We'll thank you for it
now in Jesus' name and for his sake. And to this I do say, amen and amen. Thank you. May be seated.
A couple of years ago, I began thinking about the big differences that
little things make. Have you ever thought about that? Have you ever thought about the big
differences that little things make? And I could probably give you a long list of all the
little things that we allow into our lives that end up being, making big differences. I mean,
it's amazing to me how big a list we could possibly come up with. And like I said, if I
really want to finish my course strong for the Lord Jesus Christ, I want to make sure that I
stay on track, to stay on course. I want to read this to you very quickly as I get into my message.
I happened to see this not too awful long ago and I pieced this together and I wrote it down so I
wouldn't forget it. And so I want to read this to you. In precision aeronautical navigation,
coursekeeping and maintaining the proper heading is critical if one expects to arrive at their
desired destination. Truly direction determines destination. Consider that if an aviator deviates
just one degree from the correct heading, he or she can miss the arrival airport by a considerable
distance. It is therefore vitally important that one stay exactly on course at all times.
Whether in nautical or aeronautical navigation,
one must stay the course without deviation if one is to arrive at his or her
exact destination.
Course keeping is vitally important and essential
in all types of navigation.
Getting off course by as little as one degree
in long range navigation can mean missing the mark
by hundreds of miles.
It is theorized that this is exactly what happened
to Amelia Earhart and Fred Noonan as they attempted
to circumnavigate the world in the late 1930s.
It is thought that faulty navigation placed them
75 miles or more from Howland Island
where they were to land for refueling.
Running out of fuel, they may have simply crashed
into the sea, which is what I personally believe they did.
But in precision navigation, there can be absolutely
no deviation from the prescribed course.
Many a ship has been run aground or been broken up
upon shoals and reefs when navigational charts
were not followed precisely.
By way of illustration, if off course by one degree
after one foot of travel, the target would be missed
by .2 inches.
After 100 yards of travel, the target would be missed
by 5.2 feet.
After one mile of travel, the target would be missed
by 92.2 feet.
If flying from San Francisco to Los Angeles,
the target would be missed by six miles.
Flying from San Francisco to Washington, D.C.,
the target would be missed by 42.6 miles,
placing the aircraft on the other side of Baltimore.
If flying around the globe from Washington, D.C. and back,
the target would be missed by 435 miles,
ending up in Boston.
If traveling to the moon, as did the astronauts,
flying the Apollo missions, and you were off course
by only one degree, the target destination would be missed
by 4,169 miles.
If one were able to fly to the nearest star
and there was a mere one degree course deviation,
the target would be missed by 441 billion miles.
One degree can make a phenomenal difference.
Yes, direction does indeed determine destination.
That's pretty amazing, isn't it?
All you have to do is get off course by one degree,
one degree of deviation from course,
and it can end you up in the wrong place.
You can end up at the wrong destination.
It can get you in an awful lot of trouble.
When I was taking flying lessons several years ago,
my flight instructor kept telling me all the time,
keep course, man, keep course.
Pay attention to your course.
Don't be deviating from course.
You do your cross countries, you better stay on course,
because it's a three-leg cross country.
And you're all by yourself, and you better be sure
that you properly navigate it.
That course that's been set before you,
you're getting up in the wrong place.
So deviation from the course in navigation
is a dangerous thing.
Just one degree can place you off course,
and you'd not arrive at your destination
as you're supposed to arrive to.
Now, that's an amazing thing.
But let me apply that to your Christian life
and my Christian life.
If you get off course by just the slightest little bit,
you're gonna end up in trouble.
You're gonna end up in the wrong place.
You're gonna end up doing the wrong thing.
Amen?
You're gonna end up displeasing God, by the way,
and we certainly don't wanna do that.
And any time we find ourselves drifting off course,
the most important thing for us to do
is to engage in a course reset.
We need to get back on course again.
Course correction is extremely important.
Over in Acts chapter 20,
and no need to go there in verse 24,
Paul said this, that his greatest desire
was that he might finish his course with joy.
And the ministry which I've received of the Lord Jesus
to testify the gospel of the grace of God.
He said, I wanna make sure that throughout
my entire ministry that I stay on course.
I don't wanna deviate from the course
that God has set for me,
so that I can finish my course with joy.
And it's not a very joyful thing
when you get yourself off course
and find yourself at the wrong destination.
Sin many times take you farther than you wanna go
and take you in places where you shouldn't be.
And it can cause you a heartache
that you just never thought you'd ever experience
in your life.
So for you and I, I think it's an important principle,
a very simple thing, but a mere one degree of difference
can cause us to have some pretty serious problems.
That's why God has given us
a navigation chart right here, amen?
It's better than any section chart I've ever seen.
Section charts, sometimes they make mistakes
in putting together these Jepson section charts,
but I'm gonna tell you what,
this is the best section chart in the world, man.
If you just follow this section chart right here,
just follow this right here, you'll never get off course.
This is why God has given us this word
as God's instruction manual,
it's God's owner manual for you and me.
Listen, I don't belong to myself.
When I got saved, I no longer belong to me.
I'm bought with a price, I belong to the Savior.
And he's my navigator.
God ought to be your navigator.
You ever seen people, the bumper stickers on their car
said God is my pilot and I'm the co-pilot?
No, no, listen, he's the navigator.
He's the one that navigates us to make sure that we,
if we would stay on track and stay on course,
we're gonna end up at the right destination.
Now, praise the Lord,
when you get saved by the grace of God,
you're going to end up in the right destination.
You're gonna end up in heaven, amen?
If you're saved by the grace of God, you're heaven bound.
But when it comes to the Christian life,
we ought to realize we can end up
heading in the wrong direction
and finish up our lives in a way
which is displeasing to the Lord.
And I don't know about you,
but when I stand before the Lord Jesus one day
and I have to give an answer
for that which has been done in my body,
that which has been done in the flesh,
whether it be good or bad,
I want to be able to say,
Lord, I did my best to keep course.
And when I got off course,
I tried to make course correction every time I could
and I consulted, I consulted the owner's manual
to make sure that I got back on course properly.
We need to stay on course.
Get off course by one degree and you've got problems.
Amen?
First Kings chapter 11.
There's nothing really profound about this.
It's just really, to me, it's just very, very practical
when you stop and think about getting off course.
First Kings chapter 11, a familiar passage of scripture,
but every time I read through this,
I see here's a brother got off course.
I mean, Solomon got way off course.
Now, it's an interesting thing
when you look at Solomon's life.
Remember what Solomon did?
If you look back in chapter three,
which we will go back there a little bit later on.
If you go back to chapter three,
you can see that Solomon asked God for what?
He asked him for wisdom.
Now, God would have given him anything that he asked for,
but he asked for wisdom.
He said, now, I'm just like a little child.
I don't know how to lead this life so great a people.
And Lord, if I'm going to do this,
if I'm going to lead these people, as did David, my father,
I'm going to have to have wisdom.
And God, I need your wisdom.
And I think that really pleased the Lord.
That he asked that of himself
rather than asked for riches and wealth
and all the things that a king would,
you would think that a king would be entitled to.
By the way, later on in life, God gave him that too.
God gave him wealth and God provided him with things
that were just absolutely marvelous things,
wonderful things.
I mean, he had amazing wealth.
They say that he may well have been
one of the wealthiest men that ever lived.
But somewhere along the line, Solomon got off course.
You know, look at this very quickly.
Look at 1 Kings chapter 11,
and I'm going to read down through this pretty quickly,
so stick with me.
By the way, let me do this.
Let's go over, if you look over,
we don't need to read the whole chapter.
If you look at 1 Kings chapter 10,
we know the queen of Sheba came to visit him
because she said, I've heard about your kingdom.
I've heard about your wealth.
I've heard about all that you have.
I've heard about everything associated with your kingdom.
She came to see for herself if it was true.
You remember she came, and what did Solomon do?
Well, he trotted out all of his wealth.
He trotted out all the things that he had,
everything that God gave to him.
He trotted all that out.
I think some pride was involved in that.
You can see, as you go down through chapter 10,
you can see how she saw this,
and she was amazed by what she saw.
I would have been amazed, and so would have you been,
to have been able to see all that God had blessed him with.
And by the way, God blessed him with it.
Hey, friends, let me tell you this.
We don't get wealth at our own hand.
Any wealth that we have comes from the hand of God.
And God told the children of Israel that.
He said, don't you think that you earned your own wealth,
and it came from you?
It came from me.
And anytime you get to thinking that it came from you,
you know, these self-made men, they say,
well, I'm a self-made man,
and nobody ever gave me anything.
Everything I have, I earned myself.
Let me tell you what, that is, as far as I'm concerned,
that's an arrogant statement.
Because even what the heathen has, God gave to him.
He didn't get that on his own.
And so I thank God for that.
God has blessed me.
I don't know how he's, I'm sure he's blessed you as well.
But he sees it, but she saw all this.
But look in 1 Kings 10, verse 24.
After he trots out all this wealth that he has,
and she sees all this, and it says,
all the earth sought the psalm,
and to hear his wisdom, which God had put in his heart.
And they brought every man as present,
vessels of silver and vessels of gold and garments,
and armor and spices and horses and mules,
arrayed year by year.
So people are just bringing all this wealth to him.
That's amazing.
Verse 20, and Solomon gathered together chariots
and horsemen, and he had 1,400 chariots and 12,000 horsemen,
whom he bestowed in the cities for chariots
with the king of Jerusalem.
And the king made silver to be in Jerusalem,
as stones and cedars made he to be as the sycamore trees
that are in the veil for abundance.
And Solomon.
had horses brought out of Egypt in linen yarn, and king's
merchants received a linen yarn at a price. And a chariot
came up and went out of Egypt, and six hundred shekels of
silver, and a horse for a hundred and fifty. And so all
the kings of the Hittites, and for the kings of Syria, did
they bring him out by their means." All right, now I'm
going to jump into chapter 11. We may come back and look at
this again. But, now I want you to see that word, but.
Anytime I see that word, but, in the Bible I say, well here
it comes, but. I look this word up, it appears many times
in the Bible. You see it throughout the Word of God,
this word, B-U-T, but. But, but, but, King Solomon, look
at this, loved many strange women. Now that word, stranger,
is an interesting word. If you look it up in the Hebrew it
means alien, it means heathen, it means pagan, also it means
harlot, it could mean harlot as well. So, he loved many
strange women. These were women who were pagan women, they
were heathen women, they weren't godly women, they
weren't Jews, these were women from alien countries, from
other nations. And so notice it says, and King Solomon loved.
Now the word love there is Ahab, or Ahab, and it's the
same basic word as Eros in the New Testament, it's a sexual
affection, or it's lust is what it is. So the love that he had
for these women wasn't agape love, it was lust. So he lusted
after these women. So he had a real woman problem. And he
wasn't the only one in the Old Testament that had a woman
problem. So, King Solomon loved many, he didn't say just a
few, it says many strange women. Look at this, watch now,
I want you to note this, we're going to go back and look at
this, many strange women together with the daughter of
Pharaoh. Oh, now you've got to mark that because we're going
to go back and take a look at that in a few minutes. Along
with the daughter of Pharaoh, women of the Moabites, the
Ammonites, the Edomites, the Zidonians, and the Hittites.
Watch now, of the nations concerning which the Lord said
unto the children of Israel, Ye shall not go in unto them,
neither shall they come unto you, for surely they will turn
away your heart. And of course we see in Exodus 34, 16 what
God has to say about that. God said, listen you don't want to
be marrying these pagan women, these heathen women from these
alien countries because what they're going to do when you
get involved with these women is, is they're going to turn
your heart away from the God of Heaven. So don't do it, He
said, don't do it. God said, don't do it. Now you can see
He's going off course, can you not? Now let me say this,
going off course has its consequences. It has serious
consequences. Every sin that you and I commit, every
deviation from the Word of God, every time we get off
course, I guarantee you there are going to be
consequences. Let me tell you Solomon is going to experience
some consequences. So verse 2 again, and let me, I want to
go back to verse 1, I want to read the two together,
But King Solomon loved many strange women, together with
the daughter of Pharaoh, women of the Moabites, Ammonites,
Idonians, Edomites, Idonians, and Hittites, of the nations
concerning which the Lord sent unto the children of Israel.
Ye shall not go into them, neither shall they come in
unto you. For surely they will turn away your heart after
their gods, little g, but Solomon claimed unto these in
love. So in other words he claimed unto them as a result
of his lust, the lust of his flesh, the lust of his flesh.
But I tell you what that's a dangerous thing. Amen. I've
told my wife I don't know how many times when we've been
counseling with people, especially with folks with
marital problems and perhaps there is infidelity going on.
And maybe there is, we've got young men that maybe have
gotten themselves involved with an ungodly young woman, or
vice versa. And I've said, listen, I've said to my wife
many times, boy this thing of the female flesh is a
powerful thing. It's a powerful thing. I wrote this down in
my Bible so I wouldn't forget it. For me I wrote it down.
Satan will exploit a man's weaknesses and employ devices
to turn his heart from God. And he'll do it every time he
gets an opportunity. So Satan has devised a multitude of
evils to turn the hearts of God's people away from him. He
wants to get you off course. The devil wants to get you off
course. And that's exactly what was happening with
Solomon here. Verse 4, For it came to pass, when Solomon
was old, that his wives, well let me go back, I missed verse
3. And he had seven, now if I had missed this we'd have been
in trouble. And he had 700 wives, princesses, and 300
concubines, and his wives turned away his heart. And this
brother, what was this brother thinking? This guy's got 1,000
women. What is he thinking? I'll tell you what, he had to
just, he had to be out of his mind. He's got himself 1,000
wives. Someone said, well he had a lot of trophy wives. Well, I
guess so. But he had 1,000 wives. That's a lot of
hosiery over the shower curtain, amen? I'm telling you
man, 1,000 wives. Hey, listen you've got more than one woman
in the house. You've got two women in the kitchen, you've
got a problem. I happened to be watching, we were in a hotel
and I turned the TV on, sometimes you wish you didn't
do that. But I turned the TV on and I got this thing on there
called, Sister Wives. I don't know if you've ever seen that.
But it's this guy, it's supposed to be a Reformed
Mormon that's practicing polygamy, because he said
Joseph Smith said it's ok. So, he's practicing polygamy and
he's got I think seven or eight wives, or whatever it is. And
they try to get on there and tell you that, oh, we never
have any issues with each other. We are not jealous of
one another. We all get along with each other. Well, they're
all lying. Amen. I've got an amen out of this crowd. Praise
the Lord, that's right brother, amen. I want to tell you
what, seven women in one household like that. I'm
talking about wives. These women are all wives, they're
supposed to be wives. Well, God never prescribed that. God
never authorized that. You go back to Genesis chapter 2 and
it's right there, one man for one woman for one lifetime.
God never authorized polygamy. He never did, but they did it
anyway in spite of what God said. And now you've got, this
guy's got seven wives in one house and he's sitting there
smiling, these women are all fighting over him. And I look
at this guy and I said, man I haven't got any idea why
anybody would fight over this dude. Amen. Man, he's one ugly
fellow. I mean I don't understand that. And these
gals are all fighting over this guy. And they say, oh, we've
got peace here. And I said, I don't believe that. I remember
my grandmother, bless her heart, she was an old Irish woman
and I was adopted, so I'm not Irish, I'm Scottish and French,
but what a combination that is. But my grandmother, my
mother's mother was Irish, her father was from County Cork,
Ireland, and my grandmother was jealous of her kitchen. And I
tell you what, you better not go in her kitchen when she was
cooking. And the women in the family knew better than going
there when she was cooking. And they would have Thanksgiving or
Christmas or whatever it was and she'd be in there putting
the feast together, take her two or three days to do it and
get all the fixings done and everything else. And if
anybody had a tendency to venture into the kitchen while
she's cooking she'd say, I can still hear her say, scat,
scat, scat, scat, get out of my kitchen, she'd say. You know,
and the men don't dare even go anywhere near that kitchen. I
tell you that right now. You wouldn't even think about going
in there and stealing something to eat. And I mean, that's just
the way it was. And so can you imagine having a thousand women
in one household? Now, he's collecting women. Now, I
collect high-end airplane models. I like airplane models,
amen. I collect die-cast cars and stuff like that. I'm just
still got a little of the, you know, the boy left in me. So, I
collect that stuff, but I guarantee I'm not collecting
women. One woman is enough, amen. Now, I'm not saying that
in a deleterious manner or in a negative manner. I thank God for
my wife. She's all I need. I don't need any other women
around. Praise the Lord, amen. She don't want any other women
around either, I'll tell you that right now. So, he had 700
wives, princesses, and 300 concubines. And his wives, all
these women, turned away his heart. For it came to pass,
when Solomon was old, that his wives turned away his heart
after other gods. And his heart was not perfect with the Lord,
his God, as was the heart of David his father. Boy, there's
an indictment right there. You know the Bible says that David
was a man after God's own heart. Now, in 1 Kings chapter 3 the
Bible says that Solomon loved the Lord, but he didn't love
God as much as his father did. I think David loved God much
more deeply, much more personally, much more
intimately. I don't think Solomon had that same
relationship with God that his father had. I think his
relationship was very different. And so, now he's been
turned aside by all these women, and by all this lust and
everything else. And the basic fact is, is now he's not only
just off one degree, now he's off course by a whole bunch.
Now, getting back on course again is difficult. You get,
friends, if you and I get too far off course sometimes to get
that course adjustment to get us back to where we need to be
can be very, very difficult, very difficult. And so, he's
now, he's not just off course, he's off course by a whole
bunch. He's off course by a whole bunch. And so, he's not
just off course by a whole bunch, he's off course by a
distracted. The devil has got his foot in the door. Satan
has done his dirty, dastardly work. He's employed devices
which turned away Solomon's heart from God. And now he's
way off course. Now let me say this, there is no way that
God is pleased with him in this situation. No way.
Someone said, well don't you think God winked at this? God
does not wink at sin. Well don't you think God was
exorcising His permissive will here? Listen, God doesn't
have a permissive will when it comes to sin. Sin is sin in
the sight of God and God hates sin. And we need to
recognize how much He does hate it. And so now he's way
off course and he's now had his heart turned away by
these women. Verse 5, For Solomon, now this is a sad,
sad statement here in Scripture. For Solomon went
after Ashtoreth, the goddess of the Zidonians, and after
Milcom, the abomination of the Ammonites. Now see that God
calls this false god of theirs an abomination. So
therefore it means to worship this god you had to engage in
abominable acts. Now I'm not going to describe to you what
they were because some of them are pretty terrible. But they
had to engage in abominable acts because this was an
abominable, abominable god, this false god. Now verse 6
look at this, this is sad. This man whom God gave all
this wisdom to and all this wealth to, look at this in
verse 6, And Solomon did evil in the sight of the LORD, and
went not fully after the LORD as did David his father. See
that backs up the statement I made to you a minute ago that
Solomon did not love God as deeply as did David. David
loved the Lord with all of his heart. Now did David sin? Did
he get off track? Did he get off course? Yes. But praise
the Lord David was known to make course corrections. I can
see it in Psalm 51 after that thing that he did with
Bathsheba and God broke him and he got right with the
Lord, amen. When he confessed that sin, when he repented of
that sin, when he turned away from that sin, when he
forsook that sin God restored him again to fellowship. He
made a course correction that he knew he needed to make in
order to get back to where he needed to be. Had he not done
that, that lack of being on course would have run him
smack into a wall somewhere and he'd end up crashed and
burned. So praise the Lord for that testimony. And by the
way, the man of God said to him, it's a good thing that
you made that course correction because if you had not
repented of your sin and got right with God you'd have been
a dead man because he said, now that you've repented surely
thou shalt not die. So that tells me that God had signed
His death warrant, and he wouldn't have lived past 50.
It was around the time that he did this thing with
Bathsheba. Now did it affect his life? Yes, things were
never the same again because there are consequences for
sin, and you have to live with those consequences. You've
got to live with them once you make that decision. Verse 7,
Then did Solomon, this is amazing to me as well, then
did Solomon build in high place for Chemosh the
abomination of Moab in the hill that is before Jerusalem,
and for Molech. Now it's an amazing thing, Molech they
used to do child sacrifice to Molech and they would burn
their children in the fire. Not only that but the Moabite
God, their greatest God of all was Dagon the fish god.
There were so many other gods that they worshipped, false
gods and all the rest that goes along with it that it's
amazing to me that Solomon got so far off course that he was
willing to worship these false gods. And by the way put not
on himself but the kingdom in jeopardy. Now hear this, if
you get nothing else let's get this. Listen I said this the
other day, your choices and my choices when we decide that
we are going to sin against God it doesn't just affect us
it affects others. In this case it affected his home, it
affected his offspring, it affected the nation, the whole
nation was affected by this and it brought consequences upon
them. Bad choices. Verse 8, And likewise did he for all his
strange wives. He did all this for these women which burnt
incense and sacrificed unto their gods. Let me say this he
did this for these women, he wanted to please these women
rather than please God. Isn't that something? I don't know
how many times I've seen young people get hooked up with the
wrong individual, the wrong mate. I've told young people
this for years in counseling this way for years. I've said
listen don't be out getting on this Christian mingle thing
and all these websites, all these chat rooms or whatever
it is they do, this internet stuff and do this internet
dating thing. Don't be out shopping for a spouse. You let
God bring His choice in a spouse to you. And make sure you
marry right and make sure you marry in the Lord or don't get
married. I had a young woman say to me she said, what's the
secret of your long marriage? You folks have been married a
long time. She was getting ready to get married. I said,
it's work. You work at it. And you determine in your heart
that once you get married you stay married. And if you don't
plan on staying married don't get married. Am I right? I
think so. So now look, verse 8, And likewise did he for all his
strings wise which burnt incense, and sacrificed unto
their gods. And the Lord was angry with Solomon, well do you
think? Because his heart was turned from the Lord God of
Israel, which He had appeared unto him twice, and commanded
him. By the way let me tell you this, God had given Solomon
more than enough revelation to know what was right. And had
commanded him concerning this thing that he should not go
after other gods, but he kept not that which the Lord
commanded. Wherefore the Lord said unto Solomon, Forasmuch
as this is done of thee, and thou hast not kept my covenant
and my statutes which I have commanded thee, I will surely
rend, that word rend in the Hebrew, ohabit means to tear
away or divide, I will surely rend the kingdom from thee,
and will give it to thy servant. I wish I had time to
just preach on that for a while. Notwithstanding in thy
days, I will not take it for David thy father's sake, but I
will rend it out of the hand of thy son. Howbeit I will not
rend away all the kingdoms, but will give one tribe to thy
son, for David my servant's sake, and for Jerusalem's
sake, which I have chosen. This is all leading up to the
divided kingdom. And the Lord stirred up an adversary unto
Solomon, Hadad the Edomite, and he was the king of the
seed of Edom. Now I want to read something to you here very
quickly, and then I'm going to look at 1 Kings chapter 3.
Just listen to this, When thou art come unto the land which
the Lord thy God giveth thee, and shalt possess it,
speaking to the children of Israel, and shalt dwell therein
and shalt say, I will set a king over me, like as all the
nations that are about me. Thou shalt in any wise set him
king over thee, whom the Lord thy God shall choose. One from
among the brethren shalt thou set king over thee, thou mayest
not set a stranger over thee, which is not thy brother. But
he shall not multiply horses to himself, nor cause the people
to return to Egypt, to the end that he should multiply
horses. Forasmuch as the Lord hath said unto you, ye shall
henceforth return no more that way. Listen, neither shall he
multiply wives to himself, that his heart turn him not away,
neither shall he greatly multiply to himself silver and
gold. Do you hear that? God said, listen, neither shall the
king multiply wives to himself, that his heart turn not away.
Oh, that's in Deuteronomy chapter 17. So, Solomon knew
this. Solomon couldn't cop out and say, I didn't know this,
God never told me this, I didn't know this was wrong. Come
on now, he knew it was wrong. He knew it was wrong when he
started doing it. He intentionally got off course.
It's like flying, you're flying the heading that's assigned to
you, or whatever heading you're supposed to be flying. And all
of a sudden you just decide, nope, not flying that way
anymore, I think I'll fly this way, or I think I'll fly this
way. And you get off the prescribed course, guess what?
You're not going to end up at your destination, and also too
you're liable to have a mid-air collision, or something else
is going to happen, or you're going to fly into weather.
There's all kinds of things you can do when you get off
course. Solomon knew what he was doing when he did it. And he
did it consciously, he did it intentionally, he did it
volitionally. It breaks my heart when I think about it.
Now, Solomon said, well I wouldn't do that, excuse me. Now
you might not gather yourself, sir you might not gather a
thousand wives and concubines. I don't know how you could ever
possibly do that in this day and age. I mean it would just,
well I guess some people might try to do that. But I mean
there is no way that most of us are ever going to even think
about that, but there are so many other areas where we get
off course. Listen to this, 1 Kings chapter 3 and verse 1,
someone asked me not too long ago, well, Brother Meshon where
did he get off course? Where did it start? When did he get
one degree off course, and get it in such a horrible
situation? 1 Kings chapter 3, verse 1, And Solomon made
affinity with Pharaoh king of Egypt, and took Pharaoh's
daughter, and brought her into the city of David, until he
had made an end of building his own house, and the house of
the Lord, and the wall of Jerusalem round about. Do you
see that? Before he had even asked for a
wisdom from the Lord, before he even got to that step, before it ever really got started,
right from the very get-go, he made affinity with Egypt. He became an ally to them, and
oh, and he took Pharaoh's daughter and brought her into the city of David. He violated the
Word of God right there. He disobeyed God right there. He disobeyed what was stated
in Deuteronomy and other places of Scripture, not necessarily that text I wrote to you.
They weren't supposed to marry into these foreign women and take strange wives unto
themselves. He knew what he was doing. He knew what he was doing. So that's where really
I think he got off course by just one degree, and he continued to go in that direction off
and on throughout his life, even though he had exercised great wisdom, and God blessed
him in so many ways, but yet in the end, what did he do? Not only did he disobey God,
but he ended up his life worshiping these false gods of these women that he gathered
unto himself and brought into his household. Man, he was way off course. Way off course.
We need to be good course keepers, friends. We need to make sure that we stay on course
because you get off course by just one degree, just one degree, and I guarantee you, you
are going to end up at the wrong destination. You're going to end up where God doesn't want
you to be. Remember what I said last night? The place to be is in the center of God's
perfect will. God's perfect will. I guess what I've done now, and really it should be
all of our prayer, I think, every day, my greatest desire when I lift my voice up in
God's prayer is this, Lord, please help me to stay in the very center of thy perfect
will. I never want to get out of God's will for me and for my life. Can you imagine how
it would affect not only your life and your ministry but your family? You know? You get
off into the wrong stuff, man, it can affect a lot of people. One sinner can do great harm
in a home, a family, a church. We need to stay on course. And there's so many of God's
people today that are off course, it's just egregious to me that people have gotten so
far off course. What has happened to the thinking of God's people today where they've gotten
themselves turned upside down and right side, they're not right side up anymore, they're
upside down. They see good as evil and evil as good or they support sometimes things they
shouldn't support or get involved in things they ought not get involved in and they don't
even think twice, how does this affect my relationship with God? How does it affect
my walk with God? How does it affect my prayer life? How does it affect my devotional life?
How does it affect my church life? How does it affect my family life? And sometimes people
just don't think the way they ought to think and they don't use biblical reason, they don't
use the course that God has set for them in the Word of God and they exercise human logic
and they somehow figure out and think that I think this is alright, I don't think this
is a problem. Oh, God won't mind if I do this. Remember what I said about me robbing God
of tithes when I first got saved? I had exercised human logic thinking that God understands.
No, God does not understand sin. When God says that we're supposed to be doing something
and He says this is the course that you are to get on and keep then that's what we ought
to do. And God sees anything less than that as sin. There's no gray area, it's black and
white. Someone said to me one time when I was in the military, I had one of my men say
to me, you know what your problem is? Your problem is you're just too black and white.
I said, in the business we're in my friend, you better believe everything is black and
white because the ordinance manual is written in blood and when we're handling explosives,
I'm going to tell you what friends, there's absolutely no room for error whatsoever, ever,
ever, ever. Well listen friends, we're talking about things of eternity, of eternal value.
We're talking about things that are related to our walk with God and our service for God
and how it affects and influences everybody else and we get so selfish and self-centered
sometimes that we don't realize and understand the choices we make affect other people and
we get off course by just a degree. It can lead us to all sorts of dangerous conclusions.
Don't, don't, listen, don't stay off course. Get back on course. You remember that old
adage my mother used to say it to me all the time, son, you need to straighten up and fly
right. Right? Straighten up and fly right or suffer the consequences. And you knew it was
coming. Amen? And I used to tell my daughter all the time, listen, if you don't straighten up,
fly right, we're going to get academic. I'm going to apply the Board of Education to the seat of
understanding and we'll, we'll correct the issue and the attitude. And God's, He's trying to
correct us. I mean, when He sees when we get off just one degree, He tries to get us back on
course. You know how He does that? How can you read the Word of God and not be corrected? How
can you come to church like this and hear the preaching and not be corrected? I want your pastor
on live stream. I know what he's preaching. Amen? You can't, there's no way you get away from it.
God is providing you with everything you need to know in order to stay on course. So you don't
want to straighten up and fly right. That's your problem. I got to quit. I had a guy come to me one
night at my church when I was pastoring. He said, you know what, pastor, I'm just not getting fed
here. I said, is that right? He goes, yeah, I'm not getting fed here. I said, well, you know what
the problem is? You're just not eating. So I'm not going to spoon feed you. You should be past
the pablum stage. And I said that to him graciously. I mean, as kindly as I could. But I said, brother,
listen, I've heard that all these years I've been in the ministry, I've heard that. That's just an
excuse. The truth of matter is, is you've got all course and you don't like it when the Word of God
points it out to you when something gets preached you don't like. He said, the truth of matter is,
I preached something today you didn't like. And you got your toe stepped on. Well, that's the
grace of God. God is doing everything He can to help us stay on course. And sometimes we reject
it. So you know what he did? He went someplace else to eat. And I can guarantee you he didn't
like what he got over there either. What do they think this is? They think there's a happy diner
here or something? No, we're preaching the Word of God. We're trying to help people to get on
course and stay there. All right, here's my question. We're going to stand a minute. Are you
on course? Or have you gotten off course? If there's any sin in your life that you're just
allowing to fester and you're letting the devil draw you off course, you need to get back on
course again. That's your responsibility. God says, if you will, I will. I mean, we just need
to make that course adjustment. Solomon would have been a whole lot better off had he done that. I
don't see that he did make a major course adjustment. Certainly not the way he should
have. And you can find men in the Bible that did. David was one, and there were others as well. Get
on course, amen? Let's straighten up and fly right. Let's all stand tonight with our heads
bowed, eyes closed. Let's stand as our sister comes to play the instrument for imitation season. I
don't know how God spoke in your heart tonight, but He sure has spoken to mine. I sure want to be