chapter 4, 1 John 4.
We'll be looking at v. 1-3 this morning.
1 John 4.
And looking at v. 1-3.
Notice with me in v. 1 of 1 John 4,
John, under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
says to these original recipients,
of course preserved for us this morning,
beloved, believe not every spirit,
but try the spirits,
whether they are of God.
For as many false prophets are gone out
into the world,
hereby know ye the Spirit of God.
Every spirit that confesseth that Jesus Christ
has come in the flesh is of God,
and every spirit that confesseth not
that Jesus Christ has come in the flesh
is not of God.
And this is that spirit of Antichrist,
whereof ye have heard that it should come,
and even now already is it in the world.
Of course, the subject of false teaching
has been previously discussed several weeks ago,
actually several months ago.
We looked at 1 John 2 in v. 18-27.
And as we looked at that passage of scripture
in v. 18 of 1 John 2,
the Bible says little children,
it is the last time.
And as you have heard that Antichrist shall come,
even now are there many Antichrists
whereby we know that it is the last time.
And John would continue through the end of the chapter,
really v. 27,
dealing with the subject of false teachers
there in the second chapter.
And then now again in the fourth chapter,
the subject is brought up once again.
Now we understand that our enemy is relentless.
We understand that not only is he relentless,
but we find that he's crafty, he's cunning.
And we find that his attack upon truth,
even as we studied last week,
is continuing to march on,
and he continues to undermine the truth
of the word of God.
But I am thankful that as we go to the word of God,
we find that God regularly reminds us
not only of the desire of the enemy,
but he also reveals to us the tactics of the enemy,
and then provides for us clear instruction
on how we deal with and defeat the enemy.
And we ought to rejoice in that this morning,
because it's not that God just told us
that they're false prophets and then false teachers
and then go figure it out.
We find that he's given us the truth
that these false teachers exist.
He's explained to us what their desire is
and what their tactics are.
And then he said, here's how you combat it.
Here's how you deal with it.
And here's how you defeat it.
As we look at the passage of scripture,
again, the revisiting of the subject matter
of false teaching, I've titled the message
from verse number one, try the spirits.
And as we think about the passage of scripture
and the subject matter that is before us,
let me say this, hold your place in 1 John chapter four,
we're gonna look at two verses of scripture
because I wanna acknowledge this morning
at the very beginning of the message,
what is it, this question to be answered,
what is it that we're really seeking to avoid?
Look in the book of Ephesians, if you will,
the book of Ephesians in the fourth chapter,
what is it that we're seeking to avoid?
Why does God continue to give us truth
with regard to the false teachers that exist
and their tactics and so on and so forth,
their desires to overcome?
And we find that God gives us in his word
what it is that we're trying to avoid,
what are we seeking to avoid through these messages?
Notice in Ephesians four and verse number 14,
that we henceforth be no more children
tossed to and fro and carried about
with every wind of doctrine by the slight of men
and cunning craftiness whereby they lie in wait to deceive.
That's what we're trying to avoid.
We're trying to avoid this instability
that you read of in verse number 14
where they're tossed to and fro
with every wind of doctrine by the slight of men.
It says in cunning craftiness,
they lie in wait to deceive.
And when we deal with the subject matter of false teaching,
when God exposes the false teachers,
when he gives us instruction for how to identify
and defeat false teaching,
we find that what we're seeking to avoid
is the pitfall that is spoken of here
of this lack of stability.
And what is it that we're trying to avoid?
But then also, what is it that we're seeking to accomplish?
Turn to the book of Colossians, if you will,
just a few pages over in your Bible,
Colossians chapter number one,
and I want you to see what it is
that we're seeking to accomplish.
What is it that we wanna avoid
is this lack of stability,
this being tossed to and fro.
What is it that we're seeking to accomplish?
Well, in the book of Colossians in chapter number one
in verse number 23, notice what the Bible says.
If you continue in the faith, grounded and settled,
and be not moved away from the hope of the gospel
which ye have heard,
and which was preached to every creature
which is under heaven,
whereof I, Paul, am made a minister.
You see a great contrast between Ephesians 4.14
and Colossians 1.23.
You find that in Ephesians 4, he's saying,
listen, we wanna avoid this being tossed to and fro.
We wanna avoid this instability.
We wanna avoid all of this false teaching
and being just going back and forth
between what it is that we believe.
And in Colossians, he says,
we wanna be grounded and settled,
and move not away from the hope of the gospel.
You see that which we're seeking to avoid,
but also what it is that we're seeking to accomplish.
You know, God wants us to be grounded and settled.
He wants us to know who he is,
and he wants us to know what he has spoken.
And we find that he's given us the word of God,
and we've been given precious instruction.
We find that today, even as our passage would tell us
of these false teachers that exist,
and there are many false prophets
that are gone out into the world,
and we find that God gives us this instruction
in 1 John chapter number four.
If you're taking notes this morning,
I want you to notice, first of all,
the exhortation to the believers.
The exhortation to the believers.
I believe this morning, as we look at verse number one,
there's really a twofold exhortation that is given to us,
and this is advice or counsel
that God is giving to the people of God,
those that have been born again,
those that are following the Lord Jesus Christ.
We find that this exhortation is given.
Notice in verse number one,
the first aspect of this exhortation,
believe not every spirit.
That's pretty simple, is it not?
Believe not every spirit.
We find that the second aspect of this exhortation
that God is giving to the people of God
and to us this morning,
is not only that we would believe not every spirit,
but then notice what he says, try the spirits.
Try the spirits.
Now that word try is a very interesting word.
It means to test, prove, or examine.
The idea of the word try is to determine
if something is genuine or authentic.
That's the idea behind the Greek word that is used here
that's translated in our Bibles, try.
Try the spirits.
That we're to test, prove, or examine them
for the purpose of seeking to determine
if something is genuine or authentic.
And we find that God has given this exhortation.
He's provided this counsel,
this advice for the people of God.
And we find that as he's provided this to us,
our response to the exhortation
ought to be that we take heed.
John says, beloved, believe not every spirit,
but try the spirits, whether they are of God.
We find that here this exhortation is given
and we are to try the spirits.
The word of God uses regularly
and in the era in which they would use
this original language,
we find that the word try would be used often
with regard to metals.
And they would try the metals.
They would seek to determine if the metals were pure,
if they were authentic, if they were genuine,
or if someone was trying to sell you a counterfeit.
That's how they would use the word.
Very regularly in daily business and administration,
they would use the same word in that manner.
And we find that God is telling us as the people of God
that we're to try the spirits.
We want to be able to examine.
We want to test and prove.
We want to determine that they're genuine,
that they're authentic.
We ask ourselves this question,
how is it that I try the spirits?
What is it that I would do?
How is it that I would be able to take heed
to this instruction that has been given?
And I find it's very interesting
as you conclude the third chapter of 1 John,
God gives us some great insight.
Now you understand this morning
that these chapter divisions
and the verse references were added
after the originals were given
for ease of being able to find and follow and read.
It'd be a challenging thing this morning
if I said just turn to the book of 1 John
and find where I'm reading.
And so we have these chapter divisions in these verses,
but if you look in chapter number three
and verse number 24,
and we dealt with this a couple of weeks ago,
it says, and he that keepeth his commandments
dwelleth in him and he in him.
Notice what he says,
and hereby we know that he abideth in us
by the spirit which he hath given us.
And we rejoice in the truth,
the reality of his abiding presence,
when we speak about the...
the Holy Spirit of God that is mentioned
in 1 John 3 and verse 24.
But when we understand the truth
of the indwelling of the Holy Spirit of God,
yes, He's the Comforter.
But He's also the Teacher.
He is the Divine Teacher.
And God in His awesome plan.
I mean, God is supreme.
He's nothing that He's not thought of.
Right? He's God.
And in His awesome plan,
He determined for New Testament believers
that at the moment of salvation,
the Holy Spirit of God would indwell us.
And as the Holy Spirit of God
indwells every believer today,
we find that yes, He is the earnest
of our inheritance.
We find the proof, if you will,
of our redemption is that the Holy Spirit of God
indwells the believer.
But we find that yes, He's our Comforter.
And we rejoice in that comfort.
And we often wonder as we would go through
the trials and difficulties of life,
how is it that someone that does not know
the God of all comfort,
someone that does not have the Comforter
that indwells them,
how do they deal with some of the things of life?
And we rejoice in having the Comforter.
But He's also the Teacher.
And He leads us into all truth.
And we ought to rejoice in that.
See, Jesus, as He's speaking to His disciples
in the book of John,
before He would go to the cross of Calvary,
we find that Jesus is giving them wonderful truth
with regard to the things that would take place
and the responsibilities that they would have
with regard to ministry.
And He's providing them with great instruction.
And He tells them about sending the Holy Spirit of God,
sending the Comforter.
And He mentions that in a few passages
in this section of the book of John.
But in John chapter number 16, in verse number seven,
He says this to the disciples,
"'Nevertheless, I tell you the truth.
"'It is expedient for you that I go away.
"'For if I go not away,
"'the Comforter will not come unto you,
"'but if I depart, I will send Him unto you.'"
And then we find that if you skip down just a few verses,
in verse number 13, it says,
"'How be it when He,'
now notice, it tells us that He's the Comforter
in verse number seven,
but another title that is given to the Holy Spirit
is provided in verse number 13,
"'How be it when He, the Spirit of truth, is come.
"'He will guide you into all truth.'"
Now, those words should be precious to us
as the children of God.
He didn't say that He might guide you into some truth.
He said that He will guide you into all truth.
And we ought to rejoice in that.
And as we look here at the passage of Scripture,
He continues and says,
"'For He shall not speak of Himself,
"'but whatsoever He shall hear, that shall He speak,
"'and He will show you things to come.'"
And we rejoice this morning
as we consider the subject from 1 John 4,
how is it that I try the spirits?
Well, it's the enabling of the Holy Spirit of God
that indwells us,
because He will guide us into all truth.
Listen, we must take God at His word.
We must believe that God has given us that which we need.
And as we run to the truth of John 16,
we ought to rejoice that,
listen, God, you told us to not believe every spirit.
You told us to try the spirits.
And there's this situation here.
There's something that I've been confronted with.
And Holy Spirit of God,
I need you to guide me into all truth.
Help me to understand, enable me.
We find that not only has He given us
the Holy Spirit of God
and the enabling of the Holy Spirit
to enable us to be able to try the spirits,
but we also find that we're to examine
by using the scriptures.
The word of God says to try the spirits.
Again, that word means to test, prove, or examine.
It's seeking to determine
whether something is genuine or authentic.
And so what do I use?
I use, not only do I have the Holy Spirit of God
that indwells me, He enables me,
but we also examine through using the word of God.
The word of God is our standard.
The word of God is the truth.
We dealt with that last week
as we spoke about the truth shall make you free.
And as we find this morning here
in 1 John 4, in this exhortation
that is given, this counsel or advice
that God is providing to His people,
He says, believe not every spirit,
but try the spirits.
I need to examine the scriptures.
I need the help, the enabling of the Holy Spirit of God,
but now as New Testament believers,
we have the whole canon of scripture.
He has given us the entirety of the word.
You understand, and many people get twisted up
with this today, but you understand
that the apostolic sign gifts,
as we would refer to those as,
that as you study the New Testament
before the scriptures were completed,
if you read 1 Corinthians chapter 13,
it's very clear at the end of the text of scripture,
when that as perfect as come,
then that which is in part shall be done away with.
And we find that these apostolic sign gifts
that were given were given for the purpose
of authenticating the message.
We don't need the apostolic sign gifts anymore.
Why?
Because we have that which is perfect.
We have the whole counsel, the whole canon of scripture,
and we are to examine the word of God.
So listen, this morning, the false teaching
that is prevalent, we find that the exhortation
is given to the people of God
that were to believe not every spirit,
were to try the spirits.
Why is it that God would give us this exhortation?
Well, it's because of, if you're taking notes this morning,
the existence of false teachers.
The existence of false teachers.
I believe this morning that the existence
of false teachers is what necessitates the exhortation
that we find at the beginning of verse number one,
here in 1 John chapter number four.
And we find that as you read the end of the first verse,
it says, it tells us why the exhortation is given,
because of the existence of these false teachers.
It says, because many false prophets
are gone out into the world.
So God gives us the answer as to why
the exhortation is needed.
Why it is that He's provided us with this exhortation
is because of the existence of these false teachers.
You understand this morning that the scriptures say this
in verse number one, because many false prophets
are gone out into the world.
There's not just one false teacher.
There are many false prophets.
He tells them in verse number three
at the end of the verse, it says this,
and this is that spirit of antichrist,
whereof ye have heard that it should come,
notice what it says, and even now already is it
the spirit of antichrist in the world.
The book of 1 John was written
near the end of the first century.
And here we are in 2022, and we find that the false teachers
have continued to multiply.
There are many false teachers, many false prophets.
As we begin to think about the existence
of these false teachers, we made mention
by way of introduction to 1 John 2 in verse number 18,
and it's there where it says,
even now are there many antichrists.
And we find that this spirit of antichrist
that John mentions in 1 John chapter number four,
this existence of false teachers,
that they are seeking to go and to permeate the world.
Last week, we mentioned in our study
of the truth shall make you free,
we said this, that there is a blinding from truth.
You know one of the ways in which the enemy
blinds people from truth?
False teachers.
You know the hardest truth to identify
is the one that's close, or excuse me,
the most difficult false teaching to identify
is the one that's closest to the truth.
Where is it?
They try to get it as close to the truth as they can,
but there's just a couple of nuances.
They mean something different by the words that they use.
I've often said this over the years,
that they, false teachers, they will use our vocabulary,
but not our dictionary.
What do I mean by that?
Well, they might use some of the same words
that we're familiar with,
but they mean something entirely different.
Have you been born again?
Well, we understand what it means to be born again,
and we would understand as we hear that terminology,
perhaps this morning your mind would race
to the book of John in the third chapter
when Jesus is speaking to Nicodemus,
that man that was full of religion, by the way.
And Jesus said to that religious leader,
he said, ye must be born again.
And Nicodemus said, how can a man be born again
when he's old?
Can he enter into his mother's womb a second time?
He's confused.
Jesus makes it very plain.
There is a physical birth, and there is a spiritual birth.
And that being born again is the spiritual birth,
the second birth.
You talk to some today, you use that terminology,
have you been born again?
Oh yeah, I've been baptized.
That's not what it means to be born again.
I'd ask if you were baptized.
Oh yeah, I've said my first Holy Communion,
I've done this, I've done that, some religious exercise.
But that's not being born again.
Being born again is.
understanding that we're dead
in our sins and our trespasses.
Understanding that we are guilty.
Amen?
For all have sinned
and come short of the glory of God.
And I'm guilty.
And because of my guilt,
because of my sin,
I stand under judgment.
He that believeth not is condemned already.
I stand under the judgment. Why?
Because our God is just.
And He's righteous.
And sin must be judged.
It must be dealt with.
And the penalty for sin is death.
But we recognize that God,
the same God who is just
and the same God who is righteous,
He's gracious and He's merciful.
And He paid the price for us.
And He went to that cruel cross
and He bled and died.
And the just for the unjust,
the truth of the vicarious
substitutionary atonement of Jesus Christ
on that cross of Calvary,
He shed His precious blood.
He died.
He was buried.
And He rose again.
Why? To pay for the sin of mankind.
We recognize that we're sinners
and there's a penalty,
but Jesus paid the price.
How we ought to rejoice in that.
And then we read where the Bible says,
for whosoever shall call upon
the name of the Lord shall be saved.
Sirs, what must I do to be saved?
Paul didn't tell them to get baptized.
After they believed on the Lord Jesus Christ,
then they were baptized.
Believers baptism by immersion.
I find that this morning
they use our same vocabulary,
but they use a different dictionary.
The existence of false teachers.
Listen, it's so prevalent
in our society today.
You must be careful of what you watch.
You must be careful of what you listen to.
Listen, you can type in
and in just a moment
you can go to YouTube
and you can find all sorts of things.
You have a question
about something biblically.
And listen, the the enemy is crafty.
He's cunning.
And there's all sorts of false teaching
that is just all over the Internet.
These false teachers that are on TV.
I'm not saying every preacher
that's on TV is a false teacher,
but what I'm saying is
believe not every spirit.
Try the spirits.
That's the exhortation.
Why?
Why does God give us the exhortation?
Because they exist.
And there are many false prophets
that have gone out into the world.
The spirit of Antichrist.
You heard that it shall come.
It's already here.
This was written many, many centuries ago.
We find that the enemy uses
the false teachers to blind men
from the truth.
Someone said this,
that the author of much
of the theology books
that are written today
or many of the theology books
would be Satan himself.
You say, what in the world is that?
That's a shocking statement.
No, because he wants to
send forth that false teaching.
You know, most false teachers,
as you look at the truth
of the Word of God,
and this is where we get the exposure,
if you're taking notes,
number three this morning,
the exposure of false teachers.
It's given to us here
how we can identify,
how we can expose the false teachers,
because where they mess up
is with Jesus.
False teaching,
the consistent point
in which they fail and they miss
is on the person of Jesus Christ.
Why is that?
Because it makes all the difference.
Do you remember when Jesus
said to the disciples,
he's there and he's speaking
to the disciples and he says,
listen, whom do men say that I am?
Peter's the one that stands up,
and Peter very quickly,
actually before Peter speaks up,
the disciples, they kind of offer an answer,
and there's many probably that speak up.
They say, well, some think
you're John the Baptist or Isaiah
or Jeremiah or one of the prophets.
Can I tell you this morning
that the false teachers don't care
if you think Jesus is a prophet?
The false teachers,
they don't care if you think
that that Jesus was a good man.
Jesus said, who do they say that I am?
Isaiah, Jeremiah,
one of the prophets, John the Baptist.
Then Jesus says, but whom say ye that I am?
And Peter then stands up and says,
thou art the Christ,
the son of the living God,
the Messiah, the promised one.
Paul would then later say to those
that he's speaking to in the book of Acts,
how that this Jesus whom I preach is Christ.
They knew who Jesus was as a person,
but they say he's let them know
that's Messiah.
He is Christ.
He is God in flesh.
And we find this morning
that many of the false teachers,
these false religious systems,
these false cults,
they get it wrong on Jesus.
They don't care if you think
that Jesus was a good teacher.
that Jesus was a prophet,
that he was.
They care if you believe that Jesus is God.
And this morning,
when we look at the text of Scripture
in First John, chapter four,
the exposure of false teachers
is provided for us.
Notice what the Bible says
in verse number two.
Hereby, no.
Now, remember, we looked at this word
at the end of chapter number three
in verse number 19.
Hereby, it says in hereby,
we know that we are of the truth.
And we mentioned this word hereby.
It means by this.
And we find here again
that we see this word.
No, God wants us to know.
He doesn't want us to be blinded.
He doesn't want us to be confused.
He wants us to know truth.
He is truth.
He's provided us with truth.
And the Bible says hereby, no.
Ye, the spirit of God.
Every spirit that confesses
that Jesus Christ has come in the flesh
is of God.
Here's the test that we're going to provide.
Here's the examining,
trying the spirits.
He says every spirit
that confesses that Jesus Christ
has come in the flesh is of God.
We think about the person of Jesus Christ
and we understand this morning
his incarnation, his deity
in his work of redemption.
And that's where they get it wrong
on the person of Jesus Christ,
who he is and why he came,
what he came to do, what he accomplished.
Listen, it's Christ alone.
It's not Christ plus our works.
That's false teaching.
It's not Christ plus Mary.
It's Christ alone.
Amen.
And we find here that he says this,
that this spirit of God
hereby know ye the spirit of God.
Every spirit that confesses
that Jesus Christ has come
in the flesh is of God.
Notice in verse number three,
he says every spirit that confesses
not that Jesus Christ
has come in the flesh is not of God.
Pretty plain, is it not?
Now.
The plainness of the teaching.
Is evident through this passage,
the difficulty for us
on believe not every spirit
and try the spirits
is the craftiness of the enemy.
That's where it becomes difficult.
That's why we so desperately need
to depend upon the Holy Spirit of God
to enable us to understand
these this process
of trying the spirits.
That's why it's so imperative
that we know the word of God
and we're able to run to the scriptures.
I've had conversations with people,
countless conversations with people
that have been blinded by false teaching
that have believed a lie
and they're so convinced of it
because of what they experienced.
And it's critical
that we as the people of God,
that we depend,
we rely upon the Holy Spirit of God
to guide us into all truth.
And we go to the word of God
as the standard.
Listen, your experience
and my experience
do not trump the word of God.
There are people today,
it's actually extremely popular today
when we look at some of the
Pentecostal movement
and some of that
that we find that's so prevalent
in our society today,
where it's a lot about experience
and about emotion.
And here's what I've experienced.
And by the way,
if you talk to someone
that's experienced some of those things,
you're never going to convince them
that they didn't experience
what they experienced.
I've tried.
You'll drive yourself crazy.
Why?
Because they experienced it.
Can I tell you this morning
that when Cornelius
received word from God,
that vision,
that didn't save him.
You know what Cornelius was told?
Send for Peter
and Peter will tell you.
Man, that's power.
You go to the word of God.
I've been to heaven
and I'm going to tell you
what heaven's all about.
We got people making movies
and writing books
and all sorts of things.
And people listen,
God's people are buying that stuff
and watching that stuff
and reading that stuff.
But you know what Paul said
after he was caught up
to the third heaven?
I'm not permitted to talk about it.
So if Paul couldn't talk about it,
you think some little kid
is allowed to talk about it?
I'm sorry, I don't buy it.
God's given us in his word
what heaven's about,
what he wants us to know.
know heaven is about.
And the things that He's not told us,
obviously we don't need to know.
Amen?
And listen, this morning when we look at this exposure
of false teachers, the instruction is simple.
The outworking, the going through the process
is what becomes difficult, why?
Because of the craftiness of the enemy.
Take your Bible and turn to the book of 2 Corinthians
in chapter number 11.
I want you to see the craftiness of the enemy
as God would give us this truth
in 2 Corinthians chapter number 11.
And I want you to understand that as the people of God,
we must take heed to the word of God.
We must understand and take heed to this exhortation
that starts the passage of scripture
in 1 John chapter number four.
Believe not every spirit, try the spirits.
Why?
Why this exhortation?
Because of the existence, there are many false prophets
that have gone out into the world.
And how are these false prophets, these false teachers,
how are they exposed?
We must depend and rely upon the Holy Spirit of God
to guide us into all truth.
We must use the word of God, examining the scriptures,
examining their teaching and their beliefs
and what they peddle according to the word of God.
Notice in 2 Corinthians 11 in verse number 13.
The Bible says this,
for such are false apostles, deceitful workers,
transforming themselves into the apostles of Christ.
Notice verse 14, and no marvel,
for Satan himself is transformed into an angel of light.
So what do we read in verse number 15?
Therefore, as we understand this truth,
as we understand these false apostles,
these deceitful workers,
we understand that they've transformed themselves
into the apostles of Christ.
We understand this morning that Paul says
to the believers in Corinth, listen, don't marvel at that,
for Satan himself is transformed into an angel of light.
Therefore, it is no great thing if his ministers
also be transformed as the ministers of righteousness,
whose end shall be according to their works.
The craftiness and the deceitfulness, listen,
I don't know where it originated,
but somebody has depicted that Satan runs around
with a pitchfork and a pointy tail.
You've seen it depicted that way.
That's just not Bible.
Listen, if he always appeared that way,
it'd be easy to identify him, right?
But he transforms himself into an angel of light.
Oh, this is where it becomes absolutely necessary
for us as the people of God to take heed
to this exhortation in 1 John chapter number four,
believe not every spirit.
You know how many people see some crafty work of the enemy,
some hocus-pocus nonsense that goes on,
and they say, well, they did this.
I had somebody tell me 10 years ago,
they said, well, pastor,
I just want you to know about this person.
They called me pastor.
They weren't a member of our church.
They said, pastor, I just want you to know
that this is what happened.
What do you think about this person?
I said, that's a false teacher.
They named the person by name,
and I said, they're a false teacher.
Well, I just want you to know
that there was some person there,
and it was a healing situation,
and they had a glass eye,
and that guy touched their forehead, and they could see.
I was like, you believe that?
I mean, that was my, I wasn't trying to be unkind,
but I was astounded at the fact that they believed that.
That's what they believed.
You know that many of those healing
situations that you read of, it's a bunch of nonsense.
Just do a little research.
It's nonsense, and by the way,
if you look in the New Testament,
anytime somebody was healed,
it didn't profit the person that healed them.
Amen?
You look at the faith healers today,
they're living in luxury,
and if they really had the gift of healing,
which they don't biblically,
listen, our God still heals,
but he doesn't use faith healers.
Okay, we must understand that this morning,
and if they really had the ability to heal,
why don't they go and show up at some places
where people are really sick?
Why do they turn away the people
that aren't gonna participate and play their little game,
and then they just put it on them?
Well, you just don't have enough faith.
Peter and Paul, you read in the book of Acts,
when they healed, you know what they,
when they healed, you know why?
Again, the sign gifts, it would authenticate their message.
Do you remember, turn back, if you will,
to the book of Acts, and let's look at this passage quickly
in closing this morning.
I want you to look in Acts chapter 28.
In Acts chapter number 28,
they had just been shipwrecked.
They end up on the island Melita,
and the Bible tells us that the people there
showed them kindness, but I want you to pick it up with me
in verse number three, that Paul was there.
Of course, he was the one that in Acts 27,
he told them not to go, and they went,
and they had that terrible storm.
They were shipwrecked.
Paul stood up and said, I believe God,
and all that transpired.
They get there to Melita,
and the Bible tells us that Paul, in verse number three,
gathered a bundle of sticks and laid them on the fire.
Notice the end of verse number three,
there came a viper out of the heat
and fastened onto his hand.
That's a problem.
That'd be a real problem for me.
I'd just have a heart attack, amen?
I'm just being honest with you.
You say, pastor, you have heart problems?
Not that I know of, but if I had a viper on me,
I'd have heart problems.
And the Bible says this, notice in verse number four,
and when the barbarians saw the venomous beast
hang on his hand, they said among themselves,
no doubt this man is a murderer,
whom though he hath escaped the sea,
yet vengeance suffereth not to live.
Paul's a murderer.
That's their conclusion.
But then Paul shakes it off.
Can you imagine?
It says this in verse number five,
he shook off the beast into the fire and felt no harm.
How be it they looked when he should have swollen
or fallen down dead suddenly,
but after they had looked a great while
and saw no harm come on him,
they changed their minds and said that he was a God.
In verse number seven, in the same quarters
were possessions of the chief man of the island,
whose name was Publius, who received us
and lodged us three days courteously.
And it came to pass that the father of Publius
lay sick of a fever and of a bloody flux
to whom Paul entered in and prayed
and laid his hands on him and healed him.
Notice the Bible tells us that he healed him.
There were others there in verse number nine
and you notice what's taking place.
And I believe with all of my heart,
as you look at Acts 28,
we don't have all the time to develop it this morning,
but the reason that Paul was able to heal them
and the reason that God allowed that
was so that it would authenticate the message
that he would preach the gospel to these people in Melita
and they would get saved.
And you read this over and over in the book of Acts.
Listen, these false teachers that we read of
as Paul was exposing them in 2 Corinthians 11,
listen, they want to transform themselves
into the ministers of Christ
because listen, it's no small thing.
We should not marvel because Satan himself
is transformed into an angel of light.
And so we must take heed, we must acknowledge here
in 2 Corinthians 11 that this takes place.
I talked to a man probably 18 years ago
and he said, yeah, I know I'm saved.
I said, how do you know you're saved?
That's wonderful, tell me how you got saved.
He said, well, I got home
and I was having a really bad time.
My wife and I were just dealing with almost getting divorced
and all this sort of thing
and work was going bad and all these things
and I sat on the corner of my bed after a long day at work
and as I sat in the corner of my bed, Mary walked in.
I thought Mary was his wife, honestly.
I was just, it was like 18 years ago.
I could almost take you to the door in Exton, Virginia
where I was when I knocked on the door of that person.
And he said, Mary walked in.
He was speaking of seeing some person, Mary,
the mother of Jesus is who he was speaking of.
And he said, Mary lifted my hand
and led me over to the window
and told me to look out the window.
In all sincerity, he said, come over here.
He said, I looked out my window and I saw right there
and there was Jesus and I know I'm saved.
He believed that experience with all of his heart.
He believed it.
There was nothing I could say to that man on that day
that would convince him
that he did not experience what he experienced.
But when we understand the whole of scripture,
we say, listen, no marvel.
For Satan himself transformed himself
into an angel of light.
Listen, Satan will do anything that he is permitted to do
because he's not God.
Satan will do anything he has permitted to do
to blind people from the truth.
And we find this exposure of false teachers.
Listen this morning.
It is so imperative for us this morning
to take heed to the exhortation of 1 John 4
in verse number one.
Beloved, believe not every spirit.
Don't see them.
some hocus-pocus and just, they must beno, no, believe not every spirit, try the spirits.
Examine them, test them, prove them for the purpose to determine whether they're genuine.
And we find that as we would rely upon the Holy Spirit of God and how we should rejoice
this morning and thank God this morning that He's given us the Holy Spirit who will lead
us into all truth.
He will lead you into all truth.
And how we should thank God that He's given us a Bible, the whole canon of Scripture,
and we examine Scripture with Scripture.
And we say, God, thank You for telling us about the false teachers, but thank You for
instructing us on how we're to deal with false teaching and how we can overcome, defeat false
teaching.
Listen, there are certain men crept unawares who turned the grace of God into lasciviousness.
There are people, and I don't want to over-exaggerate, you can do some research and I can tell you
some more things, but there are people that willingly take a position of church leadership
to deceive.
It happens.
There are people that take oaths to do it.
It's insane, but it's the work of the enemy.
And so John, under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God, he says, beloved, believe
not every spirit.
Try the spirits to see if they're of God.
And he gives us some instruction this morning, oh, I hope that we take heed to the exhortation
because false teachers still exist.
They're all over the place, but God's exposed them.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
I thank You for the Word of God.
I thank You for the Holy Spirit of God who indwells us, who is the Spirit of truth, who
leads us, guides us into all truth.
We acknowledge this morning the existence of false teachers, but God, we're thankful
that You've given us this truth for how we can know their tactics, but also have victory
and not be led astray.
As we mentioned by way of introduction, what we're trying to avoid is that lack of stability,
being tossed to and fro with every wind of doctrine.
We want to avoid that.
We want to be, as Paul said to the believers in Colossians 1 and 23, we want to be grounded
and settled, move not away from the truth of the gospel.
And God, I pray that You'd help us.
Help us to be careful with the things that we read.
Help us to be careful with the things that we watch.
Help us to be aware of the tactic, the craftiness of the enemy that lies in wait to deceive.
I pray that You'd move and work in hearts as only You can this morning.
Maybe this morning all of us should come and thank You for Your truth and for the Holy
Spirit of God.
Perhaps this morning there's one that's been given ear to false teaching.
They've been deceived.
Oh God, I pray that You'd help them this morning.
Help them to follow the exhortation that's given in this passage of Scripture.
God, if there's one that's not saved this morning, they've believed a lie of the enemy
with regard to what salvation really is.
God, I pray that today be the day of their salvation.
Would You move and work as only You can.
We'll give You the honor and glory for all that You'll do in our midst, for it's in Christ's
name we pray.
Would You stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
The end of each of our services we have a time of invitation, give you an opportunity
to respond as the Holy Spirit of God has used the Word of God in your life this morning.
Kimberly will play quietly on the piano and the altar is open.
If you're not sure of heaven, we'd love to take a Bible and show you how you can know
for sure that heaven's your home.
Maybe you just want to come and thank God.
Maybe you just want to come this morning and ask God to protect you from false teaching
that's so prevalent in our society today, and help you to follow the admonition that's
been given, the exhortation.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.