And I want you to know that being here is a blessing to me.
As an older pastor, I, young ladies,
that blesses my heart so much.
That not only did you sing,
that is one of my favorite songs,
that is a beautiful song,
but then to be diligent in playing the instruments as well,
that is a wonderful, wonderful thing.
That encouraged this old preacher, okay?
Thank you for that.
And then to see the sweetness
of the fellowship of this group.
I do not say this every church I go to,
and I don't say it to flatter you,
but what you have here is special.
And this is a wonderful church home.
You say, well, preacher, you don't know.
And I don't wanna know, okay?
I'm sure it's not perfect, you go here.
But I wanna tell you to have a church home
where you're loved, where you learn the word of God,
where young people serve.
It is a special thing.
And I don't say that again to flatter.
I say that to encourage you
to protect what God has given you.
Participate in what God has given you.
Because these are not everywhere.
Man, I preach in a lot of places,
and these kinds of church homes,
these kinds of church families,
I'm gonna step out of my way here.
This kind of preacher and his family are not everywhere.
And so just appreciate what God has allowed you
to be a part of, and really give your all
to sharing it with other people.
There are a lot of people in this community
that need a family like this is a family.
So thank you, it's encouraged me, and I mean that.
It's been an encouragement for me to be here.
Well, I met those 72-year-old newlyweds tonight,
and I told them my story about the 82-year-olds,
and they said they're gonna pass that up, no problem.
So, amen.
Take your Bible, if you would.
We're gonna go back to the Psalms one more time.
I promise, well, I'm not gonna promise,
because the Lord may change my mind,
but I will preach out of the New Testament
sometime this week, other than just Sunday school.
But the Psalms, I think, are very in tune for our times.
And I want you to know that we're going to Psalm 37 tonight.
I know that it is a well-known passage
that we're gonna study.
And to be quite frank with you, it's a very simple message,
but I think it has a very profound meaning and implication
for where we find ourselves in our generation today.
And I simply want to preach for a few minutes tonight
on this thought, why fret?
Why fret?
Boy, are we in a fretful generation.
Notice it with me in verse one, Psalm 37.
Again, a Psalm of David.
Fret not thyself because of evildoers,
neither be thou envious against the workers of iniquity,
for they shall soon be cut down like the grass
and wither as the green herb.
Trust in the Lord and do good.
So shalt thou dwell in the land
and verily thou shalt be fed.
Delight thyself also in the Lord
and he shall give thee the desires of thine heart.
Commit thy way unto the Lord.
Trust also in him and he shall bring it to pass.
And he shall bring forth thy righteousness as the light
and thy judgment as the noonday.
Rest in the Lord and wait patiently for him.
Fret not thyself because of him who prospereth in his way,
because of the man who bringeth wicked devices to pass.
Cease from anger and forsake wrath.
Fret not thyself in any wise to do evil.
I think God is saying something to us about fretting.
Don't you?
Let's pray and ask his help.
Lord, I'm grateful for the time you've given us
to be together tonight.
And I'm very grateful for the privilege
of being in this place, being with these people.
Thank you for that, for myself.
Lord, I pray now that you would use this time
and speak to our hearts from your word.
Teach us truth tonight.
And Lord, give us something that will help us
navigate this bizarre generation we find ourselves in.
Lord, above all, we want to be used of you
to try to be a help to those that are around us.
To try to point them to Christ.
And it is essential that we guard our testimonies,
our attitudes, so that they can see not the world in us
or a worldly reaction in us,
but so that they can see Jesus Christ in us.
Help us tonight, I pray, in Jesus' name, amen.
Why does the Bible address,
my title is Why Fret?
And it doesn't mean why do we fret,
it means why does God address fretting?
And I would suggest to you the reason
that God addresses fretting, names it by name three times
in that passage I read, is because we're guilty of it.
I think David was guilty of it at points of time in his life
and I think he realized as he was fretting
that it was not pleasing to the Lord,
nor was it helpful to those that he was trying to lead
or trying to minister to, for lack of a better term.
Sometimes I think we need to be very careful
to study specific words in our Bible reading
because there are shades of meaning
that maybe as we understand a word,
we don't get the full implication
of what God is saying to us.
And I want you to understand tonight
that fret is such a word.
When God tells us to fret not,
somehow in my mind I have the picture of fretting
as not real big worry, just little worry.
Just kind of bothered by it and you know,
you know I'm twiddling my fingers
and I'm a little bothered by that.
But I want you to understand that's not the full meaning
that God is saying.
What God is saying when he uses the word korah,
which is translated fret not,
it has the meaning of to be so consumed by something
that it makes us very angry.
To be so consumed by something
that it changes our countenance.
that it changes our perspective and our attitude.
It guides our response instead of the spirit
guiding our reaction or response.
And it can be such a something that we're so angry about
that it also instills and we live in fear
of that thing in our life.
And so God is saying, listen, I want you to be careful
that you don't allow seeing something in life
that makes you so fearful or so angry
that it changes your countenance
and changes your response, your reaction to that thing.
First question I ask tonight is this.
What is it that we fret about?
What makes us so angry as we live in this generation?
What is it that we're so fearful about
that we get angry and we get upset about it?
Let me mention a few things.
And I think this is first, maybe for my life,
and I hope you can identify in it too.
I fret over, I get upset with unfair things in life.
Unfairness.
Verse one tells us not to be envious
against the workers of iniquity.
I don't know about you, but it's easy to get upset
when people who seem to totally disregard God
seem to live prosperous, ideal lives.
Now maybe you have achieved perfection.
I'm not there yet.
And it still bothers me when I see people
who completely disregard the Lord,
have no space for the Lord in their life,
no fear of the Lord, no respect for his word,
and yet it seems like in life they seem to prosper.
I don't think I'm alone in that.
As a matter of fact, I can give you a number of examples
in the Old Testament.
I can find Habakkuk, that great prophet.
Preacher, you know one of the things
I always wished for as a pastor?
People would name their sons Levi and Elijah and Joseph.
I could never get a Habakkuk out of our congregation.
I don't know why.
Habakkuk cried out to the Lord and was upset with the Lord
because God seemed to be prospering the Chaldeans.
Babylon was prospering against Jerusalem and God was allowing Babylon to persecute the
Jew in Jerusalem and the Hebrew and Habakkuk got very upset with the Lord about that.
How can you allow that, Lord?
How, God, can you allow pagans to prosper when your own people are suffering?
I'll tell you how mad Jonah got about it.
Jonah got so angry with the Lord wanting to offer repentance and salvation or reformation
to the Ninevites that Jonah ran away from the Lord even after he obeyed the Lord and
went to Nineveh and he saw the Ninevites repent and he saw God bless their land.
You remember what he did, don't you?
He went up on the hill outside the city and pouted and was mad with God because God did
something he didn't want him to do.
He did something that he thought was unfair.
How can these violent people who oppose everything you are, God, and everything you tell me to
be in your word, how can these violent people be allowed to exist, be allowed to prosper
while so many of ours seem to suffer?
How about this?
Let's flip it around and let's examine a life like Job.
Job, a man who truly feared the Lord.
Job, a man who tried to be very careful to conduct his life in such a way as to honor
the Lord and then we watch that man decimated in his possessions, decimated in his family,
decimated in his own health and I'm just going to confess to you that sometimes even as much
as I have studied the Word, sometimes I'm just, I wonder God, why?
Why is that allowed to happen?
I think one of the things we have to do is remember the perspective of verse 2.
For they shall soon be cut down like the grass and wither as the green herb.
Get this statement, it's not deep but I think it will help.
Life always works out like God says it will.
I learned years ago that you had to be very careful about how you viewed our world and
your life and what perspective you took.
If we're not careful, we take a snapshot view of life.
We look at the moment that has got our attention and we make judgments about those lives based
on that snapshot.
It's like we walk around with a mind that is a Polaroid and we take the shot and we
make the judgment about that thing at that moment on that and I don't know if this is
a good analogy for a Fundamental Baptist pulpit but life is a full run movie.
And I have finally learned that the snapshot doesn't often tell the story, that you've
got to watch the full run of that life and the full run that proceeds from that event
and what you will learn at the end of that movie is that God is always right and what
God says will be will always be and the wicked never, ever, ever prosper.
They never do.
And you and I, when we allow ourselves to have hearts that get angry or get fearful
because of that moment in time, we end up interfering our entire relationship with the
Lord, our entire relationship perhaps with our family, our relationship with our church
because we have looked at a moment in the wrong perspective.
Let me give you this example.
For the sake of time I won't take you to Luke chapter 16 but in Luke chapter 16 a wonderful
story is given to us and it's the story of Lazarus and the rich man.
And Lazarus, that man was in such miserable shape in his life.
He was lame, he was covered with sores, he had no source evidently of a family that could
feed him or care for him and he sat daily at the door of that rich man and it says that
his highest aspiration was that he could eat of the crumbs of that rich man's table.
That rich man is described to us as one who fared sumptually, who dressed in a regal way
and my interpretation of that is, as I see him, is that he cared little for Lazarus being
there and if ever, not often, gave to his needs and just walked past him uncaring.
And we might sit there and say why?
How does God allow that until we get the end of the story?
And what do we find at the end of the story?
We find that Lazarus, that poor man who has suffered for those years of life is now in
the bosom of Abraham and now enjoys the blessing of being in the presence of the Lord and the
blessings of the eternal state and we find that rich man not wearing his regal robes
and not faring sumptuously in hell and we find him pleading, please can Lazarus just
dip his finger in water and just touch my tongue with that drop?
Can we go to my brothers so that they don't come to this place?
The point of the story is not to rejoice that the rich man is in hell.
It's actually not even to rejoice that Lazarus is in the bosom of Abraham.
It is to point out that what God says is true, is true!
And the wicked do not forever prosper and the righteous do not forever suffer.
And you and I have got to understand that what God says is going to be, is going to
be.
There's a second thing that upsets us and that is our perceived inactivity of God.
Why isn't God doing what I'm asking?
Why isn't God answering my prayer?
Because it's not apparent to us what God is doing.
And you and I assume because we don't see Him doing something that He's doing nothing
at all.
Habakkuk cried out to the Lord again.
He said, oh Lord, how long will I cry and that will not hear?
You know what the answer to that is?
Never.
He's heard every prayer you prayed Habakkuk.
He's heard every word you said.
He's understood every emotion you've expressed.
He's doing something that He's doing.
You haven't seen it yet.
I think of that time when the friend of Jesus, Lazarus, died.
Both Martha and Mary, before he died, when he was grievously ill, they sent to the Lord
and they said, your friend Lazarus is ill.
And Jesus knew.
But Jesus made the decision not to go to Bethany.
Not to go to his friend.
You say, well how cruel.
How cruel.
But we didn't see what God was doing.
We didn't know what He was doing.
Four days later, He makes the journey to Bethany, but it's too late.
He didn't come when we said He should come.
He didn't do it the way we said He should do it.
And so God has just been inactive.
He's just not answering prayer.
He's not hearing us.
When He does arrive at Bethany, Martha meets Him.
You remember what Martha says to Him?
Boy, if you'd have come, if you'd have done it my way, my brother wouldn't be dead yet.
My brother would still be living, but no, no, you didn't come.
Sometimes we're a little bit hard on Martha because she's so very much like us.
She's cumbered with care of everything around us.
And sometimes we make Mary a saint, and she's a great woman.
But can I remind you that Mary came with the same complaint to Jesus?
Not just Martha, but Mary, the sweet spirit that sat at His feet, Mary, the one who chose
the best thing, came and was bitter in her soul.
What I'm talking about tonight is not just for the carnal Christian.
Hey, I'm telling you that the mature Christian, the believer who is growing in the Lord, can
be prone to this anger with God, this fear that God has abandoned, this anger that God
is not doing what I want Him to do.
Mary came and said similar words to what Martha had said.
You didn't come.
You didn't do it how I thought you should do it.
You didn't do it in the timetable I laid out for you.
But in truth, though they didn't know what God was doing, God was not obligated to fulfill
fill their timetable, but God was always working.
Would you remember that?
I can't predict the future, but I'm telling you as dark as this world could become, God
is working.
I'm glad we won't be here in the midst of the tribulation, in the time of trouble that
is going to be so bad, but in the midst of that time of trouble, God is going to be working.
God knows where He's taking this thing.
You see, our third problem is that we're often ignorant of God's ways.
Make a few statements, and I'd suggest you write them down.
Get this, with God, timing is much more important than time.
I'll say it again, with God, timing is much more important than time.
Oh, Martha, you thought I delayed because I didn't care, but I'm doing something even
greater than you understand.
Mary, you thought I came after your devotion to me, you thought I came too late, but I'm
doing something you can't see.
Habakkuk, I've heard every prayer, I've been concerned about your heart, I've been
concerned about how you feel, but I'm doing something that you have not yet perceived.
God is always working, but God is doing things we can't see.
God prepares hearts.
God is working in lives that we don't know what He's doing.
We want Him to fix it now, but God is doing something in the hearts of people that we
know nothing about.
Why didn't God give me relief from that five years ago?
Why didn't God deal with that then?
Why didn't God help me then?
Because God was doing something bigger than you could conceive of at that time.
Not only that, God moves circumstances.
God knows how to bring things to perfection.
God knows what the perfect timing is.
God knows what He's doing in the hearts of people.
And I would suggest to you that God knew the right time to show up at Bethany and God knew
the right time for Jerusalem to go into captivity and God knew the right time for them to come
out and God knows the right time for the rapture and God knows the right time to meet your
need.
God knows the right time and though you cannot perceive what He's doing, He's doing it.
The second statement I'm going to make is this.
With God, character is more important than comfort.
You ever been so hurting in your life and you just wondered why God wouldn't give you
relief?
You just wondered why God wouldn't solve the issue, why God wouldn't make it okay?
Because God is more important that you learn what He is teaching.
God is more concerned that you are matured in what He's doing than you being comfortable
at the moment.
Tomorrow night, if God gives me liberty, I'm going to preach about the time that in God's
will, under God's direction, Israel marches right down to the Red Sea.
And He lets them sit there and think about where they are and you say, why would God
do that to His people?
Because He's teaching them something.
I love the book of Daniel and I love those three Hebrew children.
And when they're down on that plain of Dura and the command has come that when you hear
the sound of the music, you are to bow down before that image of Nebuchadnezzar.
And boy, they have been talking to one another.
They've been sorting it out in their own heart.
They know what their mothers and fathers back in the day were going through.
They've been talking to one another.
They've been sorting it out in their own heart.
They know what their mothers and fathers back in Jerusalem had taught them before they were
brought to Babylon.
And they've made the decision, we're not Babylonian, we're Hebrews and we're not bowing.
And that's a wonderful commitment.
I'm glad for their nerve in doing so.
But when that music started, I do want you to understand what they heard around them.
You know what they heard around them?
The thousands of other Hebrew children that had been brought and were bowing before that.
You know what I'd have done if I was God at that moment?
I'd have come down to those three Hebrew boys and I'd have said, man, I'm so proud of you.
I'm going to deliver you.
You have stood.
It's good.
We're good to go.
God bless you.
God didn't do that.
He allowed them to be arrested.
He allowed them to be brought before Nebuchadnezzar and experience his anger.
But they said to that king, hey, we don't know what our God's going to do, but we're not bowing
down to you as a God.
They said a little nicer.
Boy, if I'd have been God, preacher, I'd have come down and said, you guys are awesome.
You stood on the plain of Dura.
You stood before the king.
Come on.
I'm going to get you out of this mess.
But God didn't do that.
God allowed them to walk in and be thrown into a furnace seven times hot, so hot that
the ones that threw them in were killed at the mouth of that furnace.
And if I remember right, I think when they looked into that furnace, they didn't just
see the three men.
They saw a fourth.
And the Lord was in the fire with them.
And I want to tell you this.
These three boys came out of that fire, and their clothes didn't even have the smell of
smoke.
None of their clothes were ruined.
Not even a hair on their body or head were singed.
That's no big deal for me.
But they came out of there with a testimony that they would have never had had God intervened
before.
Were they uncomfortable?
You bet.
Were they scared?
Were they wondering if they'd been abandoned?
Probably so.
But I'm telling you, when they came out, they had a testimony of what God had done in their
life that they would have never had if God would have intervened too early.
Because God is more interested in our character than He is in us being comfortable.
Same thing with Daniel.
They passed that law.
Hey, you're not allowed to make a request of anybody but the king.
And Daniel said, ooh, that's an issue.
Because I'm going to pray to my God.
And you know the story.
He opened those shutters and looked east and began to pray to his God and was arrested
for it.
Boy, at that point, I'd have said, Daniel, you proved yourself, brother.
I'm going to make it okay for you.
God didn't make it okay.
He has a conversation with the king.
God doesn't make it okay.
He goes all the way to the lion's den and is cast in the lion's den.
And God shuts the mouths of the lion.
And the same thing could be said of him, of the three Hebrew children.
It was scary going in.
He didn't know what God was going to do.
He thought he might be ripped apart.
But when he came out, he had a testimony that he'd have never had had God intervened early.
Because God is more important in our character than our comfort.
Why have I carried this so long, preacher?
Why doesn't God do something?
Why doesn't God help me?
Why doesn't God end?
Why, why, why?
Because God is more important in building you, more concerned about building you than just
delivering you sometimes.
Not because he's mad at you.
It's because he's perfecting you.
He's building you.
One last statement.
Not in the message, just in this part, okay?
If we understood God's purpose, we would not panic at his plan.
If we understand God's purpose, let me put it this way, we're less inclined to panic
in the midst of his plan.
Because we know God is doing something to build us.
So what do we do?
Okay, those are principles, and we know that God works, and we know that he works on his
timetable, and we know that sometimes when we think he's inactive, he's actually working
all the time.
And we know we're ignorant of what all he's doing in all the lives, and including ours.
But what do we do to get through those times when it's so unfair, and when we see injustice?
What do we do when we're so fearful that it changes our response, our reaction?
And God gives us an outline, and I'll go through it quickly.
Notice it with me.
Trust in the Lord.
Verse 3 says, Trust in the Lord and do good.
So shalt thou dwell in the land, and verily thou shalt be fed.
That word trust means simply to put complete confidence in God.
The root of that word is the picture of coming into a place of refuge.
Hey, there are some things that we just have to leave to God, and no amount of our ingenious
scheming is going to solve them.
We've just got to wait on God to work.
Notice, not only are we to trust him with where we are, but I want you to see that the
evidence that we're trusting him is that we continue to do good.
Trust Him and do good.
So often I see people, not so often, but at times I see people
who are really going through something and the temptation
is to give up on the Lord. I'm telling you
whatever the trial is, whatever the circumstance is, whatever
the sorrow is, the important thing for a
believer to do is to do right.
To do good. The answer is
not outside of church. The answer isn't even another church.
The answer isn't some other way. The answer isn't
some new version. The answer isn't some new music. The answer isn't
some new person. The answer is do right!
How do I know I'm trusting God when I don't feel it?
How do I know that I'm trusting God when I'm hurting? How do I know
I'm trusting God and it's so unfair and it's obviously so unfair
and it's so unjust? How do I know I'm doing right? I continue to do good.
I do not let it control
me. I continue to trust God.
To serve God. To do right where God wants me to do
right. And God says, if you continue to do right,
you continue to trust me, you'll be fed.
We'll get to the end of this thing. It'll make sense.
I'll show you. But so often
we run thinking that God has abandoned us
so we'll abandon him. Not only are we to trust
the Lord, the Bible says, delight
thyself also in the Lord and he shall give
thee the desires of thine heart. I think
my opinion, that may be one of the
most misunderstood verses in all the Bible.
Here's how I interpreted that verse for years.
I have always desired a red Corvette.
Now, to be honest with you, I think now at my age
I could get in. I don't think I could ever get out of it.
But I've always wanted a red Corvette. And so Lord, I'm going to obey your
call to preach. I'm going to obey your call to start a church.
I'm going to obey your call to be the best kind of
study of the word and preacher that I can be.
You know what's always been the desire of my heart, Lord.
You know that red Corvette. Now I've obeyed you and I've done what you've asked me to do.
Where's my vet?
And probably one of the most destructive things God could have ever done in my life
was give me a Corvette. That's not what that
verse is saying. Delight yourself, Lord, and He'll give you whatever you
want. It's like a genie. You rub the lamp and
there's three wishes. You get what you want. You know what it is saying?
It's saying this. Make the Lord your delight
and you can have all you want.
You'll never be disappointed. Let me say it again.
Make the delight of your life the
Lord and you can have all the Lord
and all the mercy and all the grace
and all the blessings you want.
I'll be 74 in two weeks. I've been on a diet
73 years and 6 months. It has not kicked in yet.
But I've been on all kinds of diets. The one I hate the most
is where you weigh the food out
because four ounces of anything is not enough.
You know what I love about God?
I don't have to weigh it out. I can have all the God I want.
You say, well, how do you live in this
world and delight in the Lord?
You make Him your delight.
We were eating dinner tonight and Miss Holly, I love how she makes
vegetables. On that vegetable tray was
something that used to gag me. Broccoli.
You know what my mother said?
You're going to eat broccoli. You know what my father said? You're going to eat broccoli.
You know what I said? I'll eat it.
I love the stuff.
I'm not trying to be silly with it.
But I'm saying this to you.
The world has no answer for your contentment.
The world has no answer for your joy.
The world has no answer for your happiness.
We continue to look at it and the one thing that offers
absolute joy and contentment is our walk with God.
We have to find the time for it.
We have to struggle to find the time for it.
Thinking that we're going to be content by rushing to do all the rest
and maybe finding a moment for God somewhere later.
We've got to stop that.
Just as we were when we were new Christians. Just as we were when it was new.
You say, well, I've gotten past that stage.
Get involved in somebody else's life and make it about helping them
and not worrying about yourself. I'm just saying that God is our delight.
You can have all you want.
You say, well, I'd have to make myself do that.
Then make yourself do that.
And eventually you won't have to make yourself do that.
Not only that, it says commit your way unto the Lord in verse 5.
Commit thy way unto the Lord. Trust also in Him and He shall
bring it to pass. Commit very simply means to roll
together. It just means that you roll it together to the point
that you become one. And very simply what God is saying
is this. Just purpose in your heart that you're going to
go the direction I go. You're going to follow in my steps.
If I say do it, you're going to do it. If I say don't do it,
you're not going to do it. You're just going to commit your way
to walk with me, to follow me, to live for me.
And God says if you will commit your way
He'll bring it to pass. Trust in Him.
Follow Him. Walk with Him. Be one with Him.
And then last, God says rest
in the Lord. Now, I don't want
to try to be humorous here, but can I tell you what the literal meaning of
rest in the Lord is? Here it is. Be dumb.
Not be dumb. Be dumb.
Be quiet before the Lord.
Too much
of our walk with the Lord is us
telling the Lord. And much
more of our walk with the Lord is being silent
before Him and letting Him speak to us.
It is waiting on the
Lord. I see an injustice, Lord, and if you're not going to
act then I'm going to act because it's so... Stop.
Wait. Shut up.
Be quiet. Wait and see
what I do. We are so
prone to act. We are so prone to manipulate.
We are so prone to do ourselves. And the entire
truth is that the walk with God that we must
achieve is to be quiet.
Wait.
See what He is doing because He is doing
something good.
Wait on the Lord because those
that wait on the Lord shall renew their strength. Oh, they shall
mount up with wings as eagles. They shall run and not be weary.
They shall walk and not faint. I'll tell you what I see in that verse. I see
those three Hebrew children running out of the furnace saying, look what God
did. I'm glad He let us go through that.
That's hard to say. You don't know how I've been
hurt, preacher. No, I don't. But I'm telling you, God tells you if you'll
walk with Him and commit your way, He'll bring you through it. You don't know
what they did. I don't know what they did. But I'm telling you, you can come running out of the
furnace praising the Lord. I'm telling you, you can be drawn up out of the lion's
den praising the Lord if you will wait and let God
work. Stop being angry. Stop being fearful.
Stop being manipulative and let God do
what He's going to do. Rest.
I used to
hunt. I don't go hunting anymore. I have
grown wise in my older years. But I can remember going out
into the woods and getting in that tree stand at about
430 in the morning and I would have thoughts like
this. You're a moron. Because it is
so cold. And you're just so cold.
And I would think, oh, if the sun would just come up.
come up, if it would just hit a beam on my face, if it would just warm me a little, if
the sun, you know when the sun came up?
When God had time for the sun to come up.
I hope you understand what I'm saying there.
Things move at God's timing, and it's not up to us to get angry with God.
It's not up to us to be angry at this world.
It's not up to us to manipulate so that we get the outcome we want when we want.
It's not up to us to cry to the Lord, why aren't you doing something?
It's up to us to wait on the Lord, doing good, walking with Him, staying close to Him and
making Him the delight of our life, resting and waiting to see what He does.
And then I end with this, you know why?
Because the rest of the world is watching us.
And if we're fearful, and we're angry, and they know that we're believers, they're going
to think to themselves, I don't need more of that.
There's enough of that in the world.
I'm looking for something other than that.
And our testimonies must be of, man, it's tough, but I trust the Lord, and I'm going
to do good.
I'm going to do right.
Even to that person who wronged me, I'm going to do the right thing.
Even though I hurt, I'm going to do the right thing.
Even though sometimes I don't want to do the right, I'm going to do the right thing
because I'm trusting in God, and I'm going to make Him the delight of my life.
I may not have much money, I may not have good health, I may, I don't know, I may be
lacking a lot of things, but I'll tell you what, I can have all the God I want.
I'm going to commit my way.
So my feet want to go this way, I'm going to commit my way.
I'm going to walk with God and follow God.
And you know what I'm going to do?
I'm going to stop complaining.
I think complaining is the most tolerated sin in a Christian's life.
Complaining about what God is allowing in our lives, what God is allowing in our world,
don't you understand?
God is bringing it to an end for our good, and I'm going to rest, and I'm going to wait.
I'm going to trust Him, I'm going to see what He's doing.
And my testimony is going to be this, yeah that was bad, I don't know, but God is doing
something good.
Wait, and we're going to see that God is doing something good.
And I want to tell you, when we don't have a complaining spirit, and an angry spirit,
and a fearful spirit, and a mean spirit, the world is going to look at us because they're
angry, and because they're hurting, and because they're fearful, and then they can turn to
us and say, what do you have?
I have God.
I have the Lord.
Hey God, why do you tell us not to fret?
Because that's what the world does.
And we have got to be testimonies of trusting, and delighting, and committing, and resting
in the Lord.
With this I'm done.
Have I said that before?
It's going to get worse.
It's been a tough week in our world, in our country.
It's going to get tough.
It's going to be tough.
But we're not going to live with anger.
We're not going to live fearful.
It's not going to change our countenance.
We're not going to walk away from the Lord.
We're going to trust Him, and do the right thing.
We're going to delight in Him, and walk with Him even more than in the past.
We're going to commit our way, and whatever He tells us is right, we're going to be found
doing right.
And instead of trying to manipulate for our outcome, we're going to be quiet, and we're
going to wait on what He does.
And when He begins to work, we're going to find strength we never thought we had.
And we're going to find that God gives us fruit, and God gives us blessing, and God
gives us strength, and God gives us contentment and joy if we wait on the Lord.
Don't fret.
Would you pray with me?
Father, I thank you for these few minutes you've given us tonight, and I pray.
Lord, I often say, and I mean that these messages for me, and I just share them with those that
are here to listen, Lord, I know that in my heart it is so easy to be angry, it's
so easy to grow fearful, it's so easy for those things to grip my soul, and to govern
my reactions and my responses, and I don't want them to.
Lord, I want my testimony to be that in the midst of the most difficult things personally,
in the midst of the most difficult things generationally, culturally, that I have a
trust for you, that I can trust you.
And I'm not going to be a complainer, and I'm going to cease from anger, and I'm not
going to manipulate trying to get the outcome I want.
I'm just going to trust you.
So Lord, help us not to be the angry voices, the complaining voices, the fearful voices.
Help us to be the voices that direct people to a sovereign God, a personal God, a good
God, a creator God who is bringing this world to the end that He has purposed.
Lord, may we trust you.
And for those who have had a complaining spirit, an angry spirit, a fearful spirit, would you
break that in us tonight?
And may we be honest with you and come back to you and say, Lord, help me.
I don't want to be a fretter.
I don't want to be consumed with events, with things to where they control me.
I want to be controlled by your spirit, knowing that you are working our good.
Just before I conclude my prayer, I wonder if there might be one that would say, Preacher,
what you said about yourself tonight, being a fretter, it's true in my life as well.
God bless you.
I see that hand.
And I'm just asking for God's help.
I don't want to be angry.
I don't want to be the critic.
I don't want to be the cynic.
I don't want to be the complainer.
I don't want to be the fearful one that lives that way.
And just by an uplifted hand, Preacher, I'm asking, I'm acknowledging it to the Lord and
I'm asking His help.
God bless you.
Many hands.
Now, God knows our hearts.
God knows where we are and I want you to know that God wants to be a help to us.
So do what God tells you to do.
As we conclude our prayer and as we offer an invitation, let God help you.
Seek His help tonight.
Father, we are just people.
We're dust.
You know we are.
And yet you are so patient and long-suffering and merciful towards us that you'll meet us
in these moments.
And Lord, we don't want to be that critic, that complainer, that angry person.
We want to be that person that just has the testimony of trusting the Lord no matter how
difficult the circumstances seem.
So Lord, we want that not only for our own contentment, but because this is a hurting,
hurting, fearful, angry world.
They need to see somebody who can point them to the Lord where they can have peace in their
hearts.
Help us to be the picture of that peace, I pray.
In Jesus' name, amen.
Would you quietly stand to your feet?