number four this evening.
I mentioned this morning,
and you see it on the back of your bulletin today as well,
that this is going to be part one.
I think we're gonna be three weeks.
It might be four.
It just depends on how well you listen.
And no, just kidding,
how quickly I can get through the material.
I really don't wanna rush through this.
I think it's so important,
the subject matter that we're gonna deal with
over these next three or four weeks,
depending on how the Lord leads
and how much we're able to get through.
But the reality is that when we look
at this passage of scripture,
I'm not gonna deal really with the content of the miracle
and all the things that take place and what have you.
But I really want you to see,
if you were to look in Luke's gospel,
you can see a great event that takes place.
But here in Matthew chapter four,
I want you to notice in verse 19,
we're just gonna use this single verse of scripture
and kind of use it as a springboard
and go forth throughout the scriptures this evening
and really kind of lay a foundation, if you will.
Jesus says unto them, it says,
and he saith unto them, so Jesus is speaking.
He's talking to Peter and Andrew, his brother.
And it says this, follow me,
and I will make thee, make you fishers of men.
And of course, we know that by trade, by occupation,
they were fishermen.
In fact, you will find that as they were
giving the instruction throughout their lives
and with regard to the fish and all that they did,
we find that even as you think about this occupation
that they had, now Jesus, knowing their occupation,
knowing who they are, he says,
I'm gonna make you fishers of men.
And what a great term that Jesus uses.
They were catching fish for business purposes,
for obviously a source of food
and also to provide for themselves and their families
through an enterprise of selling and trading
and so on and so forth.
But now the Lord Jesus Christ, God in flesh,
says I'm gonna make you fishers of men.
We begin to understand as we have the whole of scripture,
as we begin to understand the life and ministry
of the Lord Jesus Christ
and what Jesus taught the disciples
during his earthly ministry
and then obviously having the whole of scripture,
we understand what is meant by being a fisher of men.
We understand the responsibility
that God has given us and given to these disciples
to go and to reach people, human beings,
with the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And we find this evening that as we take
and look at this over the next several weeks,
that really my desire is that we might be equipped
so that we can be effective and also consistent
in sharing the gospel
with those that we come in contact with.
There are times, no doubt,
we're not gonna take a bunch of surveys
and polls amongst the people that are here,
but there are times, no doubt,
that we have been in situations
where we have shied away from being able
to speak forth the truth of the gospel for some reason.
And what that reason might be
is going to vary from person to person,
whether there was some level of intimidation
because of others that were around,
maybe there was a measure of intimidation
because of the education level of the individual
that you were going to engage in,
maybe it was because of another religious persuasion
of that individual,
and I'm just not sure that I know
how to answer the questions,
I'm not going to be able to, I'm inadequate,
whatever the case may be.
The reality is that Jesus said,
follow me and I will make you fishers of men.
It is a work that the Lord Jesus Christ does in his people
that are faithfully following him.
And that's an important point for us to recognize,
even at the very beginning of this study
over the next few Sunday nights,
is that he told us to follow him,
and he says, I will make you fishers of men.
There is an equipping that God does
in the life of his people that cannot be explained,
it cannot be taught in a classroom,
it's something that God Almighty does
in the lives of those that are fully surrendered
and yielded to following him.
And it's something that there are times,
I've heard people say things like this,
it can't be taught, it has to be caught
in various types of terminologies that people will use,
but the reality is that our greatest duty
is to follow Christ, is to follow Christ.
And I would say this, that as we're following Christ,
and we're coming into his presence,
and we're spending time with him in his word,
and we're having that time of prayer that we're to have,
and we're truly following him,
that he does a supernatural work
that is far superior than someone
that would just go sit in a classroom
and try to get all of the how-to information,
but isn't following Christ.
Does that make sense to you this evening?
And the reality is that there are some,
listen, there are some that have quote-unquote seminars
on how to do what we're talking about this evening,
and there are some that would almost use tactics
that you would look at in the sales world
of how you can sell the gospel.
Can I tell you this evening, the gospel's not for sale.
It's not for sale.
It is not for you and it is not for me to sell the gospel.
No, we are to freely give the truth of the gospel.
Can we be equipped to be able to do it effectively,
so on and so forth?
Sure, but I'm not trying to,
and I'm not going to suggest
that we adopt the world's philosophies
and try to apply them to the Christian life
or to the church life
in order to try to have some kind of statistics,
and that's just not the way it works.
Listen, I am thankful this evening
that God gave us the opportunity
and the responsibility to be his representatives.
And so over the next few weeks,
tonight we're gonna deal with really the groundwork,
if you will, and kind of start there,
but over the next few weeks,
we'll deal with several different things.
Next week in particular,
we're gonna deal with really how to handle the conversation,
how to direct a conversation towards things of Christ,
not with regard to a sales tactic,
but with regard to if you're truly following Christ,
you wanna talk about him.
If you're truly walking with Christ,
if you're following him, then you wanna talk about him.
Let me tell you what Jesus is doing.
Let me tell you what he's done in my,
so on and so forth, right?
And so it's not something that we're trying to manufacture.
It's just an outflow of the fact that I'm following Jesus.
We begin to look at probably week three, maybe week four,
depending on how long the series goes.
It's just a mini series,
but in those either third or fourth week,
I'm gonna deal with how to be equipped.
See, we ought to be equipped.
It's not that we are not gonna be equipped.
God does a supernatural work in us,
but we ought to be equipped, but here's the danger,
and I'm gonna deal with this in great detail
in that third or fourth lesson, and that is this.
We don't seek to be equipped so that we can win arguments.
I touched on that a little bit this morning
in the message with regard to learning,
having a biblical perspective on contending,
when to contend, how to contend, where to contend.
We are to earnestly contend for the faith.
It is a truth of God's word,
but we must have wisdom in how we do that,
and the reality is that when I go
and try to engage somebody with the gospel,
when the Holy Spirit of God is leading me
to have a conversation with an individual,
it is not for me to try to determine through conversation
what their religious affiliation is and then attack that.
That's not gonna win you any kind of success whatsoever
because walls come up, barriers are set,
it becomes a, it's just a debate.
How would you feel if somebody approached you
on those grounds?
It's a real problem, and so we'll deal with that
in more detail in that third or fourth lesson
with regard to how to be equipped,
but the purpose for being equipped.
The purpose for being equipped is not
so that I can win the argument, so that I can,
no, the purpose of being equipped
is so that I have some level of idea
of where to go scripturally,
be able to share some verses that are pertinent,
not saying, oh, well, as a fill-in-the-blank,
you believe this, and here's what,
no, no, no, that's not gonna work.
You're attacking them, and it's not going to go well.
So this evening, as we set the groundwork,
if you're taking notes, number one,
we must first note the mission.
Note the mission.
Jesus says, follow me, and I will make you fishers of men.
It's interesting, their response, it says,
they straightway left their nets and followed him.
Isn't that wonderful, how they immediately followed
the Lord Jesus Christ, and we understand,
as you study through the Gospels,
and then, of course, throughout the New Testament,
Peter, in particular, is the text of scripture
throughout the Bible, will follow his life
and his ministry, they understood the mission,
they embraced the mission, they straightway,
immediately left their nets and followed him,
followed the Lord Jesus Christ.
Now, over the next several period of time,
years in their lives, they followed Christ
and Christ used them, he equipped them, he helped them.
Of course, Peter eventually would preach
on the day of Pentecost and have such a prominent role
in the early church, and we find that God used him mightily.
We must understand this evening,
the mission that is before us.
We know that it really is a mandate.
This mandate is clear, God has graciously provided
for us in each gospel and also in the book of Acts,
a record of this mandate.
In each gospel and in the book of Acts,
it's not said exactly the same way,
but the content, the idea of the mission
is clearly communicated.
We'll look here in Matthew's gospel, Matthew 28.
It's a text of scripture that we're familiar with.
In Matthew chapter 28, verses 19 and 20,
we'll start in verse 18 down through verse number 20.
Matthew 28, 18 through 20.
Notice as we are looking here to note the mission,
why do we even have this conversation?
Why do we even deal with this?
Well, because Christ has left us,
his people, with a mission.
He's given us a command.
It says in verse 18,
"'And Jesus came and spake unto them, saying,
"'All power is given unto me in heaven and in earth.
"'Go ye, therefore, and teach all nations,
"'baptizing them in the name of the Father
"'and of the Son and of the Holy Ghost,
"'teaching them to observe all things
"'whatsoever I have commanded you.
"'And lo, I am with you always,
"'even unto the end of the world.
"'Amen.'"
And so we find that this often we'll refer to
as being the great commission.
This is Matthew's record.
Again, each gospel, the book of Acts
can carry in those books this mission,
this mandate that God has given to us.
And it's really not confusing.
It's very straightforward.
The responsibility that has been given
to the people of God.
We must understand this evening
that God did not commission us,
nor when we go out, do we have the perspective
that we're trying to quote unquote force
our beliefs on other people.
There are times that we're charged with that,
we're accused of.
You're just trying to force your beliefs on other people.
I'm not trying to force my beliefs on anybody.
Listen, when I knock on doors,
if you've ever gone door knocking with me,
when I talk to people in a community,
if you've ever been around me when I do it,
I knock on the door, somebody comes to the door
and they say, hey, we're not interested.
I say, hey, listen, have a great day.
I'm not mad at them.
I don't argue with them.
I don't attack them.
I don't tell, no, I just, hey, have a great day.
Would you at least take this and read it later
at your convenience?
Sometimes they say yes, sometimes they say,
nope, I don't want it.
Okay, have a great day.
I'm not trying to force our beliefs on anybody.
We believe this evening in individual soul liberty.
We believe that every single person is a Bible truth.
It is a staple of our doctrine
that we believe every individual has a right
to believe whatever they want.
We don't believe in conversion by the sword.
We don't believe that you can force a personal choice
upon anyone to, you know, it's just not something we believe.
It is an individual person's decision.
With that individual soul liberty
comes individual responsibility and accountability.
They're responsible and they're accountable
for what they believe, what they choose to believe,
what they reject and what they receive.
They're responsible for that.
I'm responsible for seeking to try to give them the truth,
but it is not my job, nor is it your job
to force our teaching or our beliefs upon anyone.
Now, not every people group, not every denomination
under the broad term of Christendom
has that same philosophy, all right?
They just don't believe that.
And this evening, we believe
that Christ has given us a mission,
but remember that Jesus said,
hey, if they don't listen to you,
shake off the dust and go to the next place, right?
It's not my job.
Listen, I've sat, I've been in,
when I was in Bible college and other seminars
that I've gone to, I've heard people give statements
with regard to how you continue
to try to engage the person
after they tell you they're not interested
and you stick your foot in their door
and you do this and you do that.
That's just, it's just not smart.
I almost said something different.
It's just not smart.
It really isn't.
Why?
Because it's not being forced upon.
Do you know this evening that if you force somebody
to say, quote unquote, a sinner's prayer,
that the likelihood of them truly being converted
is very low?
You can't force it.
It's an individual choice.
You can't force your kids to be saved.
You can't force any other person to be saved.
We're not trying to force beliefs on anyone.
We're simply understanding the mission
that God has given to us
and we're seeking to fulfill that mission effectively
and consistently.
As a church, we have a responsibility.
Why do we have Saturday outreach?
Why is it that we're seeking to do that?
You say, I can reach people throughout the week.
You should.
When you go throughout your week,
you should be actively carrying gospel tracts with you
and seizing the opportunities that God would give you
to be a witness, to be his representative
in your neighborhood, in your workplace,
wherever God would give you an opportunity.
The reality, however, is that as a church,
so somebody says, well, I do that during the week
so I don't have to come on Saturday.
I'm not saying that you have to come on Saturday,
but I want you to understand why is it
that we have an organized outreach program.
As a church, God has put us in this community
to be a light in this community.
Amen, he's placed us here.
I've said often, you're never gonna find a missionary
on our missions board to Oakton, Virginia,
to Fairfax, Virginia, why?
Because God has placed us as his representatives,
his missionaries, if you will, in Oakton, in Fairfax.
And we should strategically and systematically
reach our community, our Jerusalem,
with the doctrine, with the gospel, right?
So if we're not taking and strategically
and systematically reaching our community,
our Jerusalem, with the truth of God's word,
with the gospel, then the reality is that you and I,
we may never come into contact with the guy
that lives a half a block from here.
We may never cross paths with that individual.
With the people, listen, when I first got here
and started knocking doors, there was somebody,
Manuel and Maria, a neighbor of yours.
I doubt that they still live there.
Two doors from where you currently live.
I knocked on their door.
Joseph was with me as my partner,
and we knocked on their door, and they argued with me
for about 10 minutes that there's no church
on Oakton Road.
I mean, they were absolutely adamant.
I drive the road every day.
I go to work that way.
I come home that way.
There is no church on Oakton Road.
It was like they were accusing me of lying.
And it was really kind of an interesting conversation.
And so, Ron, I tried to get creative,
and here's what I said at the end of the conversation.
I was like, listen, are you gonna go to work on Monday?
And they said, yes.
I said, how about this?
When you go to work on Monday,
about a half mile up the road,
when you turn onto Oakton Road, look to the right.
There's a little church, white church
that sits up on the hill.
And if it's there, will you come on Sunday?
And they said, well, I'm not gonna say that.
And I'm like, well, come on, you know?
And the reality is that, listen, we have neighbors.
Now, we live here now, and we've actively tried
to reach some neighbors.
We just have a brand new neighbor that moved in yesterday.
The moving truck was there yesterday.
So we're gonna purpose to go over there
and we're gonna try to take them a meal,
but not to think that we're poisoning them, right?
We live in a weird day.
25 years ago, a new person moves on the block.
Like, it's great to bring them an apple pie,
and like, hey, welcome to the neighborhood.
Today, people look at you like you're crazy.
And so it's a different era that we're living in,
but we wanna reach these people
because we have a responsibility.
So as a church, how are we gonna reach our community
and be purposed in it?
We have to understand and know the mission.
Number two, consider your motivation.
I believe this is an important foundational truth.
When we talk about this idea of being fishers of men,
what is our motivation?
I would say this.
Our primary motivation must be obedience to God
and love for God.
That is our primary motivation.
Our secondary motivation can be the condition of mankind.
But if we get that out of order, we get messed up.
If our primary motivation is the condition of mankind,
they reject you, they call you whatever,
they yell at you, they call the police on you,
whatever they do, all of a sudden,
your motivation's gonna dwindle quickly.
Because your motivation is people.
When your motivation, purely speaking,
you have pure motives that my motivation
is out of obedience to God and love for God.
That's why I wanna go and tell people
about the Lord Jesus Christ.
That's why I wanna share the gospel.
Note this in John 14, in verse 15,
we're familiar with the verse of scripture,
but it says, if you love me, keep my commandments.
Right, if you love me, keep my commandments.
We understand the commandment that's been given,
and so if we love him, we're to keep his commandments,
and this, no doubt, must be the primary motivation
for all that we do in life.
I've mentioned this in previous messages,
the idea of the audience of one,
the fact that all that we do is for the Lord Jesus Christ.
It's out of love for him and obedience to him
and to his word that we do what we do as believers.
I am thankful this evening that my involvement
in our.
reach, my involvement in trying to share the gospel with someone else, your involvement
with trying to share the gospel with someone else has zero to do with your position as
being a child of God.
We can't work our way to heaven, amen?
It's just not something we can do.
And we understand that biblically salvation is all Christ, Christ alone.
So I don't go and try to share the gospel with someone so that I can be saved, so that
I can go to heaven, no, we do it out of love for God and obedience to God.
It's important for us to understand that, that's our motivation.
I remember having a conversation with an individual and through the conversation they kept pushing
back but they stayed open and it was kind of an interesting dialogue and through that
conversation and interaction with that individual, at one point I finally looked at them and
I said this, listen, I'm going to heaven whether you do or not.
I've been saved by the blood of Christ.
I am heaven bound.
The deal is that I would like for you to go to heaven when you die because I understand,
I've read Revelation 20.
Have you read Revelation 20?
The scene of the great white throne judgment is not a pleasant scene in Revelation 20 verses
11 through 15.
It's a sad scene and the reality is that I've read that so I understand where lost man will
spend eternity according to what God's word says and so therefore I want this person to
go to heaven but I'm going to heaven whether they do or don't.
Whether they accept the message or not, I'm going to heaven, amen?
But I want them to go to heaven.
But my primary motivation can't be I want them to go to heaven, it's that I want to
obey Christ and it's important for us to understand that because if we get it in reverse order,
it will be short-lived.
It'll be short-lived.
Why?
Because rejection after rejection after rejection after rejection, you're going to say what's
the point?
No one wants to hear me.
No one cares.
No one listens.
No one does.
No, no, no.
If my primary motivation is obedience to God, love for my Savior, then I can keep going
and keep being faithful even if the rejections come.
Notice in Romans chapter 9 as we mentioned the secondary motivation is no doubt the condition
of mankind.
Notice what Paul says in Romans 9.
In Romans chapter number 9, in verse number 1, the Bible says this, I say the truth in
Christ I lie not, my conscience also bearing me witness in the Holy Ghost.
He briefly says that I have great heaviness and continual sorrow in my heart, for I could
wish that myself were accursed from Christ for my brethren, my kinsmen, according to
the flesh.
He says this in chapter 10 in verse number 1, brethren, my heart's desire and prayer
to God for Israel is that they might be saved.
He says later on in that passage, for whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall
be saved.
See, Paul was concerned for the condition of mankind.
He had, as he says in chapter 9, great heaviness and continual sorrow in his heart.
He desired for the people that he knew, that he understood were his kinsmen according to
the flesh, his brethren as he refers to them, that they needed to be saved.
And so it is a true motivation for individuals to understand that the condition of mankind,
but it's a secondary motivation.
The reality this evening is that everyone that you come in contact with is going to
spend somewhere forever.
They're going to be somewhere forever, every person that you come in contact with.
And when we truly understand, I wonder how many of us have this type of heart that Paul
does that I have a great heaviness and continual sorrow in my heart.
That great white throne judgment is going to be a sad situation.
Death and hell are cast into the lake of fire.
This is the second death, verse 15 of Revelation 20.
There's no opportunity to, well, I want to accept now, no, it's too late.
I've often said from the truth of Philippians that the reality is it's a matter of if not
when, or excuse me, when not if, I got that reversed.
When you confess that Jesus is Christ makes all the difference.
You will.
It's not a matter of if, it's a matter of when.
Because if you make that confession on this side of death, you'll spend eternity with
Christ in heaven.
But on the other side of death, you'll spend eternity in the lake of fire.
And so we understand the condition of mankind, but the reality is that we must be focused
and understand what our true motivation is, and our true primary motivation must be obedience
to God and love for Christ.
That's our motivation.
Why do you do what you do?
You know, so often we can be asked that question, we can think about the subject matter of motives.
There are people, no doubt, that judge other people's motives.
There are people that, unfortunately, do not even examine their own motives with regard
to various aspects of ministry.
Why do you play an instrument?
Why do you sing a song?
Why do you teach a class?
Why do you go and share the gospel with someone else?
Why do you pass out tracts?
Why do you give to church?
Why do you…all of those things that we could ask ourselves this evening, there must be
a pure motive of singular truth that I do it out of obedience and love for my God.
It must be the case.
And this evening, that is true with regard to the situation of being a fisher of men,
that I must understand, consider what is my motivation.
I would say this, number three, this evening, as we kind of wrap up this first introductory
kind of foundational message with regard to going and trying to reach people with the
gospel, number three, make it personal.
Make it personal.
I'm going to deal with that from two perspectives.
Number one, that you understand your personal responsibility to share the gospel.
There are some people, unfortunately, throughout the years, throughout the centuries that have
had the idea that it's only the job of, quote-unquote, a full-time pastor, evangelist, missionary,
whatever, to share the gospel.
But the reality is that this responsibility has been given to every one of God's children.
If you're saved this evening by the grace of God, then you have been given a personal
responsibility to be His representative.
And so when I talk about making it personal, we must understand personally, listen, there
are some, like, I'm not going to go to a church that doesn't, you know, have an outreach
program.
I mean, I don't intend to participate in the outreach program, but I'm not going to go
to a church that doesn't have one.
You understand what I'm saying?
And the reality is that somewhere along the line, we must understand the personal aspect
of this mission that's been given.
As a church, we talk about a church as made up of individuals that have been saved by
the grace of God, that have been baptized scripturally, that have joined themselves
together, voluntarily joined themselves together for the purpose of carrying out the gospel.
That's our job.
That's our duty.
That's our responsibility.
And we must take it personal.
And here's the amazing thing.
When we take it personal and we begin to go and try to reach the people that God would
bring into our sphere of influence, it's amazing how God blesses them and how God works
through that.
And so this evening, we talk about making it personal, understanding my personal responsibility,
but then also make it personal, meaning tell your story.
If you've been saved tonight, you have a story, you have a testimony.
If you've been saved tonight, you have a testimony.
Can I tell you this evening that you know your testimony better than anyone else?
You know your testimony better than anyone else.
Would you agree with that?
Now there might be somebody else that has heard you give your testimony that may be
able to share aspects of your testimony and be able to share when it was that maybe your
spouse or your children, when they got saved, and you might be able to share some things.
But the reality this evening is that you know your story best.
You know your story.
You know what God did in your life.
You know what God was doing leading up to that moment of conversion in your own life.
You know how he delivered you and how he gave you a peace and a joy and a purpose that you
didn't have before.
And without regard of how old you were when you got saved, the reality is that if you're
saved, you have a testimony.
There are some people that have the perspective that, well, my testimony isn't as good as
their testimony.
Nonsense.
You know why I say that's nonsense?
Because there's not one of us this evening that's the hero of our story.
All of us have something consistent in our story.
You know what it is?
Christ is the hero of our story.
Amen?
Well, I didn't live a life of sin.
Thank God that you didn't live a life of sin.
Because I can guarantee you, the people that are in the auditorium this evening,
people that you come in contact with that have lived a life of sin before they got saved,
they would stand and say, I wish I did not have to live that life of sin.
I wish I didn't have all that baggage and all of that.
Your story is powerful.
It's personal, but it's also powerful.
No one can tell your story like you can tell your story.
Because you know it best.
And when you begin to take it personal,
and you begin to share with someone what God was doing in your life,
and how He changed your life, listen, I often,
I've learned this a number of years ago,
I often, as I try to talk to people about the Lord,
whether it's door to door or whatever other avenue or arena God would give me,
I often try to deal with it this way.
I say, listen, can I tell you what Christ did for me?
Can I tell you how He changed my life?
I mean, it would just take a few minutes to share with you what He did for me
and how He changed my life.
You know, oftentimes people are interested to hear a story.
People will listen.
Listen, if I'm just trying to get them to come to church,
if I'm just trying to get them to,
man, they've gone to church, they know church,
they have, as soon as you say to somebody,
hey, I just want to invite you to come to our church,
do you know that immediately they have a thought in their mind what church is like?
Immediately.
Whether that's a bad experience or a good experience,
whatever the experience is, they have immediately
a thought in their mind with regard to what church is.
And if they have some level of affiliation to church,
why do I need to go to your church?
I go to my church.
I mean, I don't go often. I kind of haven't been there for a while.
I often will ask people, and I don't mean to embarrass them,
but when they say, oh, yeah, I go to church, I go all the time, that's wonderful.
What's your pastor's name?
Oh, man.
It's such a complicated name, I just can't remember it.
And it just makes me laugh inside, right?
I'm not trying to necessarily put them on the spot.
I'm just trying to find out what's going on
and what the certainty is with regard to their position.
And so here, when I make it personal
and I'm going through the process of telling my story,
not only is it personal, but it's powerful.
And here's the thing.
You should work on being able to share your story.
You should work on it.
If I could tonight give you a homework assignment,
and this isn't school, so I can't,
if I could make a suggestion,
if you don't already have a way in which you could
in just a few minutes share your story,
your testimony of salvation,
would I encourage you to work on that?
Work on it with your spouse.
Maybe with your children.
You know, it's important from time to time
for us to kind of just share our testimony.
Share our personal story,
our testimony of what God has done in our lives.
I've been in settings, I've been in situations
where I've said, hey, let's share our testimonies.
In fact, this happened in Holly's family
at Christmas a few years ago.
They wanted to start out by just mom and dad boys
sharing their testimony of salvation
and what God did in their life.
And they shared it, and it was great.
It was a good time.
Now, it's a big family.
They're like 38 people, man.
It's like a little church.
I'm being serious.
And mom and dad boys share their testimony,
and then it felt like as the Lord was really in that thing
that, well, why don't we have our children
share their testimony?
Actually, I think it started
with the sons and sons-in-laws.
Let's have the heads of the families,
let's have them share their testimony of salvation.
And so there are seven,
so we all start sharing our testimonies.
And then it was like, well, why don't the ladies
share their testimony?
And then what about the teenagers that are old enough?
Why don't they start sharing their testimony?
And you know that through that process,
one of the grandchildren that was old enough
realized they didn't have a testimony.
They realized that they weren't saved.
They couldn't share a testimony.
You know, just a short time later,
they trusted Christ as their Savior.
What a blessing.
And sometimes it's an opportunity to share,
but if you say, I don't even know what I would say,
then work on it.
Figure out how you can share your testimony,
how you can share it personally and powerfully,
because again, you're not the hero of your story.
The Lord is the hero of your story.
Sometimes I know people will use that phraseology,
I found him.
You didn't find him, he found you.
Amen?
He found me.
He loved me.
I didn't love him.
He first loved me.
I was his enemy.
But he loved me.
And he was gracious.
And listen, for me personally,
I had the opportunity to hear the gospel many, many times
before I ever trusted Christ as my Savior.
I wish tonight I would have trusted Christ as my Savior
the first time I ever heard the gospel.
But I didn't.
But you have a story.
Let me show you a couple of passages of Scripture.
Turn to the book of John, if you will.
We'll look at two passages and then be done this evening.
John chapter number 4.
As soon as I mention John chapter 4,
many of us are familiar with the text.
We understand the woman at the well.
And what a great passage of Scripture it is.
I don't really want to deal with the interaction
between Jesus and the woman.
I want to look at the woman and her story.
As we deal with this idea of making it personal,
notice in John chapter number 4, look in verse number 28.
The Bible says this.
The woman then left her water pot.
By the way, why was she there?
To get water.
She went back without her water pot.
Why?
Because something better happened than getting some water.
Amen?
I mean, this was transforming for her.
It was absolutely amazing for her.
And the Bible says that she left her water pot
and went her way into the city and saith to the men.
Notice what she says.
Come, see a man which told me all things that ever I did.
Is not this the Christ?
Then they, that's the people that she shared her story with,
went out of the city and came unto him.
Isn't that precious?
It's powerful.
All she did, I mean, listen, her message recorded in Scripture,
her message was not very lengthy.
It wasn't very theological.
She didn't have all that.
She just said, come and see a man.
And what does she say about this man that she is telling them to,
inviting them to come see, which told me all things that ever I did.
And then she says this.
Is not this the Christ?
Why did she have that perspective?
Well, just a few verses earlier, Jesus said,
I that speak unto thee am he.
She understood that Jesus, the man, the God-man,
this individual that met her that day, was the Christ, Messiah.
What a joy.
She goes to those people in the city and she offers an invitation,
and the Bible says that they went out of the city and came unto him.
Now, he obviously is going to talk to the disciples there
because as she leaves, they arrive.
And notice in verse number 38, the Bible says,
I sent you to reap that whereon you bestowed no labor.
Other men labored and you entered into their labors.
It's finishing up with the disciples in verse 39.
And many of the Samaritans of that city believed on him.
Notice what this says.
For the saying of the woman which testified,
he told me all that ever I did.
Many, I don't know how many,
but many of the Samaritans of that city believed on him.
Isn't that wonderful?
All because she made a decision to go tell a personal story,
a personal testimony.
All because she took and said, come, see a man.
Is not this the Christ?
He told me everything I've ever done.
And we find that these people responded to the invitation
and there were many that believed.
Now, the Bible says in verse number 40,
so when the Samaritans were come unto him,
they besought him that he would tarry with them,
and he abode there two days.
And many more believed because of his own word.
And said unto the woman, now we believe not because of thy saying,
for we have heard him ourselves and know that this indeed,
or that this is indeed the Christ, the Savior of the world.
But I want you to understand that because of the interaction,
listen, she still was part of that whole thing.
She's still part of it.
Your testimony this evening is powerful.
Take it personally.
Make it personal.
Notice in John chapter nine,
I referenced quickly this morning,
this portion of Scripture with regard to the religious leaders at the end
saying, are we blind also?
But I want to draw your attention just for a moment
to this man that was born blind.
The Bible introduces us in verse number one of chapter nine.
And as Jesus passed by, he saw a man which was blind from his birth.
And this man, through a miracle that took place,
Jesus tells him to go wash in the pool of Siloam
and he came seeing according to verse number seven.
And oh, what a scene unfolds in John chapter nine.
All the religious leaders and calling for the parents
and all that takes place.
And we find that this man, after being asked many times,
in verse number 25,
they called again.
And according to verse number 24,
then again called they the man that was blind
and said unto him, give God the praise.
We know that this man is a sinner.
They're talking about Christ being a sinner.
No, he's the sinless, perfect Lamb of God.
He's God in flesh.
But they called him again.
And it's almost, if I could read into the text
just a little bit this evening,
it's almost like he was overwhelmed and frustrated
with another line of questioning,
like he's being asked this again.
And notice in verse 25, he answered and said,
whether he be a sinner or no, I know not.
One thing I know, that whereas I was blind, now I see.
Then said they to him again, what did he to thee?
How opened he thine eyes?
We find that it says he answered them,
I have told you already and you did not hear,
wherefore would you hear it again?
Will you also be his disciples?
Now that didn't go over very well.
That was a real problem for these religious leaders, right?
That was not well received.
But can you see almost as being frustrated,
like why are you still asking me?
But I wanna just draw your attention to verse 25.
He says, look, I don't know how to answer all your questions
but one thing I know, I was blind and now I see.
Can I tell you that this miracle is still being talked about
at the end of chapter number 10?
It's still being talked about.
Excuse me, the end of chapter 11.
In chapter 11, the situation with Nicodemus,
I know I said chapter 10, sorry, chapter 11.
The end of the chapter, the Jews that are there,
they say in verse 37, those that were mourning
because of the death of Lazarus,
could not this man which opened the eyes of the blind
have caused that even this man should not have died.
This was an impactful miracle in John chapter number nine.
But this man stands, he says, look,
I can't answer all your questions
but this one thing I can tell you,
I was blind and now I see.
We understand that that was a physical condition.
He then later in the text of scripture
understands who Jesus is.
Jesus comes back to him and at verse number 38,
he says, Lord, I believe and he worshiped him.
What a joy.
Listen, I want you to understand this evening,
you may not be able to answer everyone's questions
but you really don't have to.
Can I tell you, I have been asked
some crazy off the wall questions.
I'm serious, man.
I have been asked some questions that I'm like, where?
Like, what have you been watching?
I've never, if you like Star Wars or that stuff,
like I'm not criticizing you, I've just never watched it
and I really have zero desire to watch it
but I wonder sometimes as some people
come up with these questions, I'm like, man,
they've been watching Star Wars for so long,
they've been watching something, man.
I don't know what they're watching
but they come up with all these weird scenarios
and hypotheticals and I don't even think
they believe what they're asking.
They're just trying to derail you.
They're just trying to detour you.
They're trying to avoid the subject matter.
There are many times I say, you know what,
that's a good question but can we deal with that later?
Sometimes people want you to answer every theology question
that they can throw at you.
I'm not suggesting that we should not be ready,
as Peter says, to give an answer to every man
of the hope that lieth within us
but what I am suggesting this evening
is that we must have wisdom
and we must be able to stand before,
listen, sometimes what happens is God's people
feel inadequate because they think
I can't answer the questions that may be asked of me.
Can I tell you that you can say like that blind man said,
I don't know but here's what I do know.
I was lost and now I'm found.
He said I was blind and now I see
but I'm speaking spiritually this evening.
I was lost and now I'm found.
I had no direction, I had no peace,
I had no joy, I had no confidence.
In fact, the very thought of dying scared me.
Terrified of the thought of dying.
I had no idea what would happen
and then it terrified me even more
after I had been exposed to the gospel
and I knew what would happen if I died without Christ.
I was miserable and then on that day
when God graciously saved my soul,
I haven't feared death.
I have a joy that I can't really explain.
I have a peace that I can't fully comprehend.
Why?
Because he saved me, he changed my life.
Can I tell you that sometimes being able to answer
all the crazy questions is actually more of a detriment?
Just gets you all in the weeds.
Seriously, sidetracked on stuff
that absolutely has nothing to do with the gospel.
With the gospel.
We're trying to get people to, lost people,
as I mentioned this morning from 1 Corinthians 2.14,
we're trying to get lost people, the natural man,
to understand spiritual things
before they've been born again.
I've been guilty of it.
Maybe you've been guilty of it as well.
It's frustrating because you're trying to get a lost person
to understand a spiritual truth
that they can't fully understand until they're born again.
Ye must be born again.
We must understand the mission.
God's given us this mission.
We must have proper motivation.
It's obedience to God, love for God.
And it's imperative that we make it personal.
It's my personal responsibility,
but it's also my personal testimony.
This evening, if you're saved by the grace of God,
you have a testimony, you have a story.
And your story is personal, but it's also powerful.
And if you don't, if you've not practiced
on being able to share your testimony, share your story,
can I encourage you this week, share your story.
Get with someone, talk to someone.
If you wanna share your story with me,
many of you, if you're a member here,
you've already shared your story with me
because you couldn't join the church if you didn't, amen.
But what I'm saying is that, listen,
it's good for us to be able to share our story.
It shouldn't be awkward for you to share your story
because Christ is the hero of my story.
And can I tell you what he did for me?
Can I tell you how he changed my life?
And it's amazing the open doors that God will provide.
Fishers of Men, part one.
Next week, we'll deal with another aspect of the how-to
and really getting into the nuts and bolts, if you will,
after we understand the foundation.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for the opportunity to be gathered this evening.
Thank you for the freedom to worship you.
Thank you for the freedom to go into our community,
to go into the marketplace, the workplace,
wherever it is that we are,
to have the freedom and the opportunity
to be able to be your representatives, your ambassadors.
And God, I pray that you'd help us to be equipped.
I pray, Lord, that you'd help us to have this understanding
of our personal testimony.
Lord, if there's some here this evening
that just have never really thought about
or never developed and worked on
being able to share their testimony,
God, I pray that you'd help them this evening
to be able to put down the thoughts
and to bring into memory,
to be able to share with others
the great work that you did in their life
in saving their soul.
I pray, God, that you'd bless the time of invitation.
I pray that through all that's said and done
that you alone will be glorified and we'll thank you for it.
In Christ's name we pray.