And we're so thankful for the truth of the word of God.
I'm so thankful that he went to that cruel cross.
He was buried in that borrowed tomb
and he rose in victory,
conquering sin, death, and the grave, amen.
And he is risen, hallelujah.
And what a joy.
And the bodily resurrection of the Lord Jesus Christ
is the cornerstone of our faith.
And I mentioned this morning during our outdoor service,
I read from the portion of scripture,
not only in the book of Matthew,
but also there in the book of 1 Corinthians
and looked at a portion of scripture
from 2 Timothy chapter number two.
But there in 1 Corinthians chapter number 15,
of course, we understand that Paul tells us
that if Christ be not risen,
then our preaching is vain, our faith is vain,
we are yet in our sins,
but now is Christ risen from the dead, amen.
And what a blessing.
It is the cornerstone of our faith
and we are rejoicing today in the certain knowledge
that God has given us that he ever liveth
to make intercession for us.
Luke 24, I'll be looking at verses 36 through 53.
And let me just read verse number 36
and then we'll get into the message this morning.
The Bible says, and as they thus spake,
Jesus himself stood in the midst of them
and saith unto them, peace be unto you.
As you can tell in the bulletin this morning,
I've titled the message, Jesus stood in the midst of them.
We'll be looking at Luke 24, verses 36 through 53.
But before we get there,
by way of introduction this morning,
I'd like to really kind of set the scene, if you will,
before we dive into our text this morning.
We understand that it's in Luke chapter number 23
that God provides for us a record of the trial,
the crucifixion, and the burial
of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ.
By the way, I'm thankful that he endured
such contradiction of sinners, amen,
for the joy that was set before him,
according to Hebrews chapter number 12.
And what a blessing to know that he took my place,
he took your place on that cruel cross,
and he paid for the sin of all mankind.
We find that it's in Luke chapter number 24
that as we begin reading this particular chapter
and the first few verses,
that God provides for us the record
of the resurrection of Jesus Christ.
The tomb, it could not hold him, amen.
And yes, he was buried there, yes, he died.
He was really dead.
He fully paid for the sin of mankind
and he went into that tomb.
But as the kids said, as we read earlier,
as we've been singing, the angel said,
he is not here, for he is risen.
As he said.
We find that it's there in Luke chapter number 24,
or in the beginning portion here,
that Jesus appears and we find the resurrection
and the angels giving information
to those that were at the tomb first.
And you read in verse number six,
he is not here, but is risen.
And then notice this, remember how he's spake unto you
when he was yet in Galilee.
This truth of the resurrection was something
that Jesus had spoken of often
throughout his earthly ministry.
And we find that he had made the declaration
that he would need to suffer
and he would pay for the sin of mankind,
but that he would rise in victory.
And we come to chapter number 24 and verse number 13,
and really verses 13 through 35,
provide for us the record of these two disciples
that are walking back on the road to Emmaus.
Now, as we think about the journey of these two disciples
and we notice their interaction with our risen savior,
we find that they're there, they had been in Jerusalem.
If you look at verse number 12 of Luke chapter number 24,
the Bible says, then arose Peter
and ran unto the sepulcher and stooping down,
he beheld the linen clothes laid by themselves
and departed wondering in himself
at that which was come to pass.
And behold, two of them went that same day
to a village called Emmaus, which was from Jerusalem,
about three score furlongs.
It's roughly 6.8 mile journey
that these two disciples would take.
And as they would return there to Emmaus,
of course, you think about all of the things
that have happened in these days
leading up to the record here in Luke chapter number 24.
In fact, as they're speaking with Jesus in verse number 18,
it says, and the one of them whose name was Cleopas
answering said unto him,
art thou only a stranger in Jerusalem
and hast not known the things
which are come to pass there in these days?
And he, Jesus, saith unto them, what things?
And they said unto him, concerning Jesus of Nazareth,
which was a prophet mighty indeed
and word before God and all the people.
You understand that he's so much more
than just a prophet.
Yes, he fulfilled the role of prophet, priest, and king,
but we understand that he is God in flesh.
It says in verse number 20,
and how the chief priest and our rulers
delivered him to be condemned to death
and have crucified him.
But we trusted that it had been he
which should have redeemed Israel.
And beside all this, today is the third day
since these things were done.
And as they're walking and conversing,
we find that Jesus, according to verse number 27,
beginning at Moses and all the prophets,
he expounded unto them in all the scriptures
the things concerning himself.
They got to their destination
and Jesus had made as if he was going to continue on his way
and they besought him to come into the home.
And we find that it's there in verse number 29
that they constrained him
and they asked him to tarry.
In verse number 30,
and it came to pass as he sat at meat with them,
he took bread and blessed it
and break and gave to them.
And verse 31, their eyes were opened and they knew him.
And he vanished out of their sight.
Can you imagine these two disciples?
What an amazing record that we have
by way of introduction to our text this morning.
And we find that the Bible says
that they begin to speak one to another
and they say this in verse number 32,
did not our heart burn within us
while he talked with us by the way?
And while he opened to us the scriptures,
they then quickly are going to return to Jerusalem.
The Bible says, now be mindful of the timeline here.
They've just walked nearly seven miles
from Jerusalem to Emmaus.
They declare to Jesus
that they wanted him to tarry with them.
Why?
In verse number 29,
for it is toward evening and the day is far spent.
But yet when they understood
that they had had this encounter with the risen savior,
the Bible tells us that at the same hour
in verse number 33,
they returned to Jerusalem.
As they returned to Jerusalem,
they found gathered the 11 there in verse number 33
and they make this declaration in verse 34,
the Lord is risen indeed,
and hath appeared to Simon.
And it says, as they told what things were done in the way
and how he was known of them in breaking of bread.
So really what's happening here
is they returned to Jerusalem.
They find the 11 disciples gathered together
and they begin,
can you see the passion and the enthusiasm?
I mean, can you imagine the excitement
that these two had
because of what they had just experienced
and the encounter that they had with their risen savior.
And the Bible says that they're speaking to these disciples
and it says in verse number 36,
and as they thus spake,
Jesus himself stood in the midst of them.
Can you imagine?
I mean, get the picture here this morning
in your mind's eye.
These disciples returned,
the 11 were not sure what they were doing,
but these two returned from Emmaus.
They had walked 6.8 miles to Emmaus
and they had spoken with the Lord Jesus Christ
and they turned and walked 6.8 miles back to Jerusalem.
And they say, guys, listen,
the Lord has appeared to us
and the Lord is risen indeed.
And as they're sharing this good news,
Jesus himself stood in the midst of them.
Awesome.
I mean, my mind cannot fully comprehend
the joy that must have flooded the hearts
of those two individuals.
We know what's gonna happen.
Jesus asked them why they're fearful
and so on and so forth of those 11.
But I think about the excitement.
Can you imagine?
As they're speaking and declaring this great message
and then Jesus himself is there.
You know, one day we will see him face to face.
What a glorious, wonderful day that will be.
And I'm looking forward to that day.
I'm looking forward to seeing my Savior.
He's alive forevermore and he's promised
that he's going to come back
and to receive us unto himself,
that where he is, we may be also.
As we look at our passage,
I want you to notice first of all,
if you're taking notes,
the appearance of the risen Savior.
In verses 36 through 43,
we see the appearance of the risen Savior.
It's of note, as I've mentioned now,
as they thus spake,
these two were speaking to the disciples
that are gathered there,
according to verse number 33.
And it says that Jesus stood in.
And Jesus Himself stood in the midst of them and saith unto them, Peace be unto you."
As you look at this scene and you find what's taking place, I want you to consider a few
things about the appearance of our risen Savior.
Notice number one, consider what He said.
Number one, He says, Peace be unto you.
In verse number 36, I'm so thankful for the peace of God.
We have peace with God through the Lord Jesus Christ, but we have the peace of God, which
passeth all understanding.
Jesus said this in John 14 and verse number 27, Peace I leave with you, my peace I give
unto you, not as the world giveth, give I unto you.
Let not your heart be troubled, neither let it be afraid.
Oh, I'm so thankful for the peace of God.
We're living in a world in which very few people understand the true peace of God.
And what a joy to know the peace of God.
We are commanded to let the peace of God rule in our hearts.
We find that the initial greeting of the Lord Jesus Christ, our risen Savior, as He appears
there in that place, He says, Peace be unto you.
We find that it then tells us of their response, but they were terrified and affrighted and
supposed that they had seen a spirit.
You understand that Jesus is going to, in just a few moments, help them understand that
they've not seen a spirit, but truly they are seeing the risen Savior.
His bodily resurrection from the dead.
He then says, as we're considering the things that Jesus says to them, in verse number 38,
He says this, Why are you troubled?
Why are you troubled?
And why do thoughts arise in your hearts?
We know the answer.
They do not provide an answer as to why they were troubled.
It tells us in verse 37 that they supposed that they had seen a spirit.
And we understand contextually what's going on here and why they're troubled.
But I ask you this morning, why are you troubled?
What is it that's troubled you?
No doubt, we're living in a time of much chaos and confusion and there are people that
are troubled.
But yet Jesus says, Let not your heart be troubled.
You believe in God, believe also in Me.
In My Father's house are many mansions.
If it were not so, I would have told you.
I go to prepare a place for you.
And if I go and prepare a place for you, I will come again and receive you unto Myself
that where I am, there ye may be also.
Let not your heart be troubled.
We serve the risen Savior.
He lives.
He's conquered sin, death, and the grave.
He's alive forevermore.
He is the Lord God omnipotent.
He'll never be defeated.
He's never made a mistake.
He knows where you are.
He knows where I am.
He knows what we're dealing with and yet He's still in control of everything.
Let not your heart be troubled.
Why are you troubled?
The answer for these disciples may be different than the answer that you would offer this
morning, but maybe some have come this morning with a troubled heart.
You're just troubled with the things in our world.
You're troubled with whatever's going on.
Can I say that Jesus says, Why are you troubled?
Can I tell you this morning that He'll give you peace as you get close to Him and enter
into His presence?
As you get into this book, He'll give you a peace that passeth all understanding.
It is an absolute joy to know the peace of God.
In the midst of turmoil, chaos, and confusion, we can have peace.
Some have wrongly described peace as being the absence of trouble.
You know that man is going to have trouble.
I just read the book of Job earlier this week.
Man that is born of woman has a few days and a whole lot of trouble, amen?
The reality is that we face trouble and tribulation and difficulty.
We understand that.
The reality is that peace is not the absence of trouble, rather peace is found in the very
presence of God Almighty.
Though the storm may be raging, though all seems to be out of control, we must recognize
that our God has everything under control.
In any moment, He can say as He stood upon that boat that day and said to those storms,
the winds and the waves, peace, be still.
His creation obeys Him.
Listen, one day the trumpet of the Lord is going to sound and all this craziness, God's
going to show that He's in control, amen?
His plan is going to be fulfilled.
No one is going to overcome and conquer our risen Savior.
He's victorious, amen?
Why are you troubled?
Do you notice what He says to the disciples?
Why?
Why are you troubled?
We find that He continues in the things that He says to the disciples, the appearance of
our risen Savior.
Verse 39, notice what He says, Behold my hands and my feet, that it is I myself.
Handle me and see.
What's He saying?
He's showing them the evidence.
He has conquered sin, death, and the grave, and He's alive forevermore, the bodily resurrection
of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ, and He says, listen, behold my hands.
What do the hands have?
The hands have the prints of the nails.
Behold my feet, that it is I myself.
Handle me and see.
And then notice what He says, For a spirit hath not flesh and bones, as ye see me have.
A spirit hath not flesh and bones, as ye see me have.
And it says this in verse number 40, And as He had thus spoken, He showed them His
hands and His feet.
Can you imagine being in this place?
It says in verse 41, And while they yet believed not for joy, and wondered, He said unto them,
Have ye here any meat?
You know, sometimes we too are slow to believe.
Sometimes we're like Gideon.
Lord, if you're really going to deliver me, if you're going to use me in this manner,
would you let there be some due here but not here?
And then God does it exactly as Gideon requested.
And then Gideon says, well, I'm going to need some more help on this.
Let's reverse it and let there be some due here but not there.
And then God does it.
See, sometimes we're slow to believe.
Sometimes we need some more supporting evidence, if you will.
And we find that Jesus, you know, aren't you thankful that our God is patient with
us?
Aren't you thankful that He gives us truth and He's long-suffering toward us?
And we find here in the text of Scripture not only what He said, but I consider what
He did as the Bible would say to us that it says that while they yet believed not for
joy and wondered, He said unto them, notice He says, have ye here any meat?
Now what's He going to do?
Well, we find that first He showed them His hands and feet, but now in verses 42 and 43,
He's going to eat before them.
It says this, and they gave Him a piece of a broiled fish and of a honeycomb, and He
took it and did eat before them.
He's giving them the evidence that it is, as He says in verse number 39, that it is
I Myself.
He's proving to them with more than sufficient evidence that He is the risen Savior.
We find that here as we would couple Luke's account and look at what the Bible would tell
us, and you don't need to turn there, but in Acts chapter number 1, we find that Luke
uses this terminology in verse number 3, to whom also He showed Himself alive after
His passion.
Notice this phraseology, by many infallible proofs, being seen of them forty days and
speaking of the things pertaining to the kingdom of God.
He gave them many infallible proofs, and as we look here in Luke's gospel and Luke's account,
we consider what He said, and we consider what He did.
We notice and we take note of the appearance of our risen Savior as we continue through
the passage of Scripture.
I want you to notice the assignment given in verses 44 through 49.
As we look at the assignment given, we find that first, before the Lord Jesus Christ will
explain the assignment, we find that He initially is going to remind them of what He had previously
taught, notice with me in verse number 44, and He said unto them, These are the words
which I spake unto you while I was yet with you, that all things must be fulfilled which
were written in the law of Moses and in the prophets and in the Psalms concerning me.
You read through the Old Testament and you read about the prophecies concerning not only
the coming of Messiah, but you read the prophecies with regard to the crucifixion of Messiah.
You read the prophecies not only of the crucifixion of Messiah, but you read the prophecies of
the resurrection of Messiah.
Remember, it's there in the book of Psalms, and He references there to the Psalms.
in this particular passage of Scripture, but we're finding the truth according to
Psalm 2 in verse number 7, I will declare the decree, the Lord hath said
unto me, thou art my son, this day have I begotten thee. You understand that he's
speaking of the resurrection there in Psalm 2. He's not speaking of the
first coming, the incarnation, he's speaking of the resurrection, and the
reason that we understand that and know that is as we compare Scripture with
Scripture, the Bible tells us in Acts chapter number 13, as the preaching of
the Word of God is going forth and Paul is preaching, what a great opportunity he
has. He says this with regard, it's right in the middle of his message, but in Acts
13 and verse 28, and though they found no cause of death in him, speaking of Jesus
the Messiah, yet desired they Pilate that he should be slain. And when they had
fulfilled all that was written of him, there you see that again, the fulfillment
of all those things that were written in the Old Testament, they took him down
from the tree and laid him in a sepulcher. But God raised him from the
dead, and he was seen many days of them which came up with him from Galilee to
Jerusalem, who are his witnesses unto the people. And we declare unto you glad
tidings, how that the promise which was made unto the fathers, God hath fulfilled
the same unto us their children, in that he hath raised up Jesus again, as it is
also written in the second Psalm, thou art my son, this day have I begotten thee.
By the way, those fellows there in Acts chapter 13, they got a
whole lot more than they bargained for when they gave Paul the opportunity to
preach. And he went ahead and just delivered a message, they said, if you
have anything to say, say on. And he said, all right, let's go, amen, and what a
blessing. And he gave the gospel, and he spoke about these proofs, these
fulfillments of these Old Testament prophecies, and we find that Jesus is
reminding them, the disciples back in Luke chapter number 24, in verses 44 and
45, he's reminding them of these things that he had previously taught. It says in
verse number 45, then opened he their understanding that they might understand
the Scriptures. Isn't that a blessing, to understand the Word of God? It's God's
Word, and he can open our understanding. We speak about illumining the Scriptures,
and we speak about the truth of Psalm 119, in verse 18, open down mine eyes that
I may behold wondrous things out of thy law. The entrance of thy words giveth
light, and what a joy to understand the Scriptures, the Word of God, and here we
find that Jesus, the risen Savior, he's reminding them of what he had
previously taught. Then he's going to explain to them what was
accomplished through his death, burial, and glorious resurrection. Notice with me
in verse number 46, he said unto them, thus it is written, and thus it behooved
Christ to suffer and to rise from the dead the third day. What was accomplished?
What was the purpose? We understand, as we studied last Sunday morning from 1st
Timothy, that the Bible says this is a faithful saying and
worthy of all acceptation, that Christ Jesus came into the world to save
sinners, of whom I am chief, and we spoke about the fact that Jesus was going to
save sinners. How was he going to do that? Through his death, burial, and
resurrection. You understand that if he just died and was buried but did not
arise, that he would not. It's evidence, the resurrection is evidence of the
acceptance of the payment that was made on the cross of Calvary. And we find
here that he did rise, and so you notice that he says it was written and it
behooved Christ to suffer and to rise from the dead the third day. Why? Notice
verse 47, and that repentance and remission of sins should be preached in
his name among all nations beginning at Jerusalem. The reality is that as the
Lord Jesus Christ is giving this assignment, before he gets to the details
of the assignment, we find that he reminds them of what he had taught, but
then he explains to them what was accomplished at Calvary and the
resurrection. What was it that was accomplished? Well, now we find that it is
finished as John would record when Jesus, before he took his final breath, he
declared, it is finished. We find here that he says that repentance and
remission of sins should be preached in his name among all nations beginning at
Jerusalem. We now have this story, the fulfillment of all of these Old
Testament prophets. You think about the amazing nature of all that has
happened with regard to the life and ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ, and
you consider with me the way that the Old Testament saints, by faith, would look
forward to the day that Messiah would come and to the Messiah going and
being our Passover. All of those offerings that they would offer and the
priests that would daily stand and minister and offering those same
offerings day by day, year by year, that could never take away sin, but it was a
picture of Messiah who would now come, and now as Jesus is proclaiming and
sharing with these disciples and with us what was accomplished, it's been paid for,
it's done, it's over, I have finished the work. Now go preach repentance of sins,
remission of sins, and what a joy and what a blessing. Aren't you thankful this
morning that you can declare that God loves individuals and that you can
declare that Jesus saves? They played this morning, we sang some wonderful hymns
this morning, but the song that they played for the offertory was what? It was
Jesus saves. And I'm so thankful for that declaration, and we can shout it out
and we can share it with individuals. Why? Because of what he did on the cross of
Calvary and what was accomplished. I'm so thankful that God, I was
praying this week and as I was just meditating upon all that he's done for
me and all that he is to me and just being a wonderful Savior, I was mindful
this week about the truth of only one way of salvation. I was reminded and I
was thankful, and I thank the Lord for this specifically, I was thankful that in
his wisdom that he did not determine that we could get to heaven by our own
works. He could have determined that. And then how would we ever know if we ever
did enough? How would we ever know? How could we ever have peace? How could we
ever have joy? How could we know when we royally messed it up how many good
things it just wiped out? You understand what I mean? Y'all ever have a bad day?
We watched Fireproof last night. How many of you have ever seen Fireproof? It's a good
movie. Oh, Caleb out there, I don't know what is Mr., what's his name? The Neighbor.
Mr. Rudolph. How many of y'all seen that movie, man? Mr. Rudolph was out there and
he's standing there and Caleb's beating that trash can, man, he had a bad day, you
know what I mean? And he says, Mr. Rudolph, and he says, Caleb, and then he tells
his wife, don't talk to that guy, you know? But he had a bad day. I'm so thankful it's
not about my own works. Man, what a terrible way it would be to live, not
knowing day by day, have I done enough? How could I ever know? Oh, I was thanking
Him this week that that's not the way of salvation because we'd never know. I was
thanking Him this morning that it's not just a pick-your-own-way and all roads lead
to. No. The truth of God's Word is that Jesus said, I am the way, the truth, and the life.
No man cometh unto the Father but by me. Peter stood in Acts chapter number four after
that great miracle in Acts chapter number three of that lame man that was healed. Oh,
how it caused a stir there in Jerusalem. He says, if we're called in question this day
of these things that have happened, I want you to know that by the name of Jesus Christ
of Nazareth, this man was made whole. It wasn't in Peter's power. It wasn't in John's power.
It was in the power of our resurrected Savior. Peter said, neither is there salvation in
any other. For there's no other name under heaven given among men whereby we must be
saved. And that God, in His infinite wisdom, devised a plan for redemption requiring the
blood sacrifice, and Jesus paid it all. Oh, how it's rejoicing to just be mindful of
that wonderful truth that we hold dear, that we are privileged to receive. And so Jesus
is explaining to them what was accomplished. Why did Jesus have to go to the cross? Because
there's no other way for a man to be redeemed. Why did He have to suffer such a horrific
death?
because he loves you and he paid for your sin we've been bought with a price
oh he says this is what was accomplished notice he finally will explain their
assignment notice with me in verse 48 it says and ye are witnesses of these
things oh he puts the responsibility right on him doesn't he I mean square on
their shoulders I want you to understand what I've accomplished I want you to
understand what has been accomplished in these days and paying for the sin of
mankind that now repentance and remission of sin should be preached to
all people to all nations beginning at Jerusalem and ye are witnesses of these
things I'm thankful that not only did he tell them that they were witnesses of
these things but they he told them that they would be empowered by God the Holy
Spirit notice in verse 49 and behold I send the promise of my father upon you
but tarry in the city of Jerusalem until you be endued with power from on
high we don't do the work of God our own power we go on the power of the Holy
Spirit of God we have the promise that Jesus said I am with you and we have the
promise there in Acts chapter number one in verse number eight but you shall
receive power after that the Holy Ghost has come upon you and you shall be
witnesses unto me both in Jerusalem and Judea and Samaria and to the uttermost
part of the earth and you find here notice the the purpose the assignment if
you will in verse number 47 that repentance and remission of sins should
be preached in his name among all nations beginning at Jerusalem how is
this monumental task going to be accomplished ye are his witnesses and we
go in the power of the Holy Spirit we notice the appearance of our resurrected
Savior I mean can you imagine it's late at night 11 are gathered I'm not sure
what they're discussing the Bible doesn't tell us but these two that
return from Emmaus with excitement the Lord has risen indeed and as they're
sharing these things Jesus himself appears he says it is me I mean look at
my hands look at my feet do you have any bread he eats and then he gives them an
assignment your witnesses of these things notice as we conclude the passage
of Scripture here in the book of Luke number three if you're taking notes
notice the ascension of our risen Savior and he in verse number 50 Jesus he led
them out as far as to Bethany and he lifted up his hands and blessed them and
it came to pass while he blessed them he was parted from them and carried up into
heaven can you imagine often we read the account in Acts chapter 1 of the
ascension of Jesus Christ they were standing there and just before their
very eyes at the end of those 40 days after he made these appearances and all
that takes place he ascends into heaven we know as we look at the whole of
Scripture that that's where he is even at this moment the right hand of the
Father ever live ever living as the Scripture saying Hebrews 725 that he
ever liveth to make intercession for us and it just the exact time he's coming
back for us what a blessed truth and we find that these disciples I mean think
about all that has happened and now the the Lord is is going to ascend back up
into heaven and the Bible says remember he said I go to my father it says that
they worshipped him and look at how they returned to Jerusalem in verse number 52
with great joy with great joy listen as we leave here in just a little while as
we go on our journey that we call life we ought to have great joy why because
we serve a risen Savior why because he's ascended to heaven and he's living to
make intercession for us why because one day he's coming back for me it is the
hope of every believer that we would see him face to face as I mentioned in our
outdoor service this morning hope is not some wishful thinking pie in the sky
hope is based upon truth that God has given us it is confidence based upon a
promise from God's Word that's hope that's Bible hope amen we have great
hope we ought to have great joy I mean listen there ought to be something
noticeably different about us in our behavior our actions and how we interact
with the things are going on in life why are you so different why does this not
cause you to be depressed and down and troubled man because my eyes are on
Jesus and he lives he's coming back for me people gonna think you're crazy man
and that's okay because they're gonna want some of what you have amen we find
in verse number 53 they return to Jerusalem with great joy according verse
52 and verse 53 and we're continually in the temple praising and blessing God
amen I want you to think just for a moment as we wrap up this morning I
want you to think about not only the importance of the Ascension of Jesus
Christ we see that record here but I want you to think about the impact of
all of these events not only the the appearance of our Lord and Savior the
assignment the Ascension I want you to think about the early church and we
don't have time this morning to really review much of the book of Acts but just
by way of brief overview you understand that these disciples they embrace the
assignment they embraced it it's interesting it's not recorded here in
in Luke's account but in Acts 1 the Bible tells us that those angels that
stood by as as Jesus was ascended up into heaven that that those disciples it
tells us in in Acts Luke also is the human penman of this book and we find
the Bible tells us in verse number 10 and that they look steadfastly toward
heaven I mean he was he was ascended in verse number 9 and when he had spoken
these things while they beheld he was taken up and a cloud received him out of
their sight in verse 10 while they looked steadfastly toward heaven as he
went up behold two men stood by them in white apparel which also said you men
of Galilee why stand ye gazing up into heaven this same Jesus know what it
says this same Jesus which is taken up from you into heaven notice shall so
come in like manner as you have seen him go into heaven
oh man I think the impact upon these disciples as you see they tarried in
Jerusalem as Jesus had told him and then they were endued with power from on high
and you find that they turned the world upside down why I believe that they
believe that Jesus was coming amen I mean it motivated them to service it
caught listen they loved the Lord and they had embraced the assignment and they
had heard from the angels that this same Jesus is coming back he didn't give
him a time and we know now that nearly 2,000 years has passed but doesn't make
the promise any less of a promise in fact we're a day closer every day amen I
don't know the day no man knoweth the day nor the hour so what the Word of God
says but man he's coming work for the night is coming oh we embrace the
promise we embrace the assignment I hope this morning as we celebrate Easter we
celebrate the resurrection we look at this account in Luke chapter number 24
that we can allow in our sanctified imaginations to see that setting of
those disciples gathered together the news that they had received in the
appearance of our risen Savior the assignment that was given later on his
ascension that we would have great joy knowing that we serve a risen Savior
there's no problem that you will ever encounter that's too big for God no
nothing I'm not saying that there's not gonna problem that you're gonna
encounter and by the way the problem might be too big for you but that's a
good thing amen you ever been in place we say I don't know what to do
everybody's been there except for God amen I look at this I mean I don't know
what to do I need wisdom we serve a risen Savior there's no problem there
might be problems too hard for me too hard for you there's no problem too
hard for God oh that we'd have joy that we would truly allow the the reality of
the resurrection to influence and impact our lives that we would live with a
certain level of excitement
joy and peace, because we serve a risen Savior, and we know that He's coming again. Amen?
The Lord Himself stood in the midst of them, and one day, one glorious day,
we shall see Him face to face. Let us pray. Father, we love You this morning.
Oh, how we thank You for loving us. How we thank You for Your Word.
No doubt in my mind that those that are gathered here this morning
believe that You have risen from the dead, conquering sin, death, and the grave.
Perhaps there's one, whether here or on livestream,
that's never trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as their personal Savior.
They've never accepted the free gift of eternal life.
Maybe today, Lord, we pray that it would be the day of salvation for that individual.
The Holy Spirit of God would convince them of their sin,
of Christ's righteousness, and of judgment to come. Lord, maybe there's one, maybe there's many
gathered here locally, tuned in via livestream, that are troubled.
Many things in our world seek to trouble.
We know that even the people of God can be impacted adversely. Jesus said,
why are you troubled? He said, before He would ever go to that cross, let not your heart be troubled.
Oh, God, I pray that You'd give us a peace that passeth all understanding.
I pray, God, that You would help us to embrace the assignment even as the disciples did.
Oh, that it would be said of us that we have filled this place with the gospel.
It's what they said of the disciples, you filled Jerusalem with your doctrine.
Oh, that they'd say that you filled Oakton and Vienna and Fairfax with your doctrine.
How glorious that would be. Lord, I pray that You'd empower us and that You would use us,
help us to have joy, peace, and hope. We pray that You'd move and work as only You can,
for it's in Christ's name we pray. Would You stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano. As she does, the altar is open. You can make
your pew and altar. You can come up here to this altar. Why don't you thank God?
Why don't you ask God to use you as we have this moment of invitation this morning?