All right, this is our midweek service and first Wednesday evening of January.
We're actually pre recording the message here on Tuesday morning, and I'll be sending out
an email with some information as to why we did things this way.
But of course, if you'd continue to pray for our family with the fact that we're exposed
to someone who tested positive with COVID, and we just trust that God would keep us safe
and certainly miss you.
And we're praying for you looking forward to seeing you soon.
And again, I'll be sending out an email, but we're going to start our service by singing
channels only one of my favorite hymns.
It's number 477, our hymnal and Joseph's going to help us lead in songs again, number 477
Channels only, blessed master, God with all thy wondrous power
Flowing through us, thou canst use us
Every day and every hour
Witnessing thy power to save me
Seeking free from self and sin
Thou who brought this to possess me
In thy fullness, Lord, come in
Channels only, blessed master
God with all thy wondrous power
Flowing through us, thou canst use us
Every day and every hour
Jesus, fill now with thy spirit
Hearts that will surrender, know
That the streams of living water
From our inner man may flow
Channels only, blessed master
God with all thy wondrous power
Flowing through us, thou canst use us
Every day and every hour
Well, amen, I appreciate Joseph's willingness to help out and lead songs
and certainly appreciate that and I want to encourage you
that we serve a great God and that he would use us
Isn't that amazing? Channels only
and to think about the fact that God would use us
and that he would fill us and he would enable us
and then he would use us for his honor and for his glory
and it is my desire that God would use me
and I trust that you have that same desire
We certainly thank the Lord for the opportunities of technology
and thankful for our team that has worked so tirelessly
over the last year, really more than that
but especially over this last year
in order to get all of these audiovisual things up to speed
so that we can do all of these things that we need to do
and very much appreciate their service in that capacity
Let's go to the Lord in prayer
Father, we love you and we thank you for loving us
We thank you for the blessings in which you have bestowed upon us
We thank you for your grace and your mercy
We thank you, God, for the word of God
We pray that you would just speak to our hearts as we open the scriptures
I pray that you would help us to be challenged and encouraged and comforted
I pray, God, that you would help us to make decisions that would please thee
I pray, Father, that you would help each one to be attentive and responsive
I pray that we'd be helped through thy word
We do think of those that are continuing to struggle with some health needs
Lord, we pray that you'd meet each need
that you'd be gracious and merciful
We thank you that you're the great physician
We thank you that you've given us the instruction
that if any are sick, that we're to pray
and God, we ask that you'd work in a distinct way as only you could
We pray that you would be glorified
We thank you and praise you for all that you'll do
For it's in Christ's name we pray, amen
I do want to encourage you to continue to pray
for Virginia and Yolanda and the Petersons
and then also if you would pray for the Ronnie
with his back and for his mom also, Miss Anne Hall
and we are certainly thankful for the way in which God has answered prayer
and shown himself faithful
and we serve a great God
I hope that you have been encouraged these last few days
as you have considered the new theme for this year
Complete in Christ
and what a blessing
and so excited about the prospect of going through the book of Colossians
and studying through that book verse by verse this calendar year
in our morning services on Sunday
and trust that you will be encouraged and strengthened
We do have daily devotionals and church calendars
and also sermon notebooks
with some instructions on how you'll be able to get those
and we've worked out a plan so that we can get those distributed
and I certainly apologize for the delay on being able to get those things distributed
but with this exposure to COVID we have to be extremely cautious
and I want to make sure that we're doing all that we're supposed to do
It is exciting as you pull up the driveway at church
to see the construction of the parsonage
and I want you to continue to pray
if you will for that project that things would continue to move forward
but it certainly is exciting to see a structure coming there
and looking forward to soon seeing that project completed
and being able to take occupancy
and your prayers are greatly appreciated
and I want to also remind you
to pray for the Savali family I mentioned on Sunday
about their situation there with the new church plant
and so if you would continue to pray for wisdom and direction
that God would just guide them and direct them
and it's exciting to see the hand of the Lord at work in that situation
and they've kind of, as Brother Savali has termed it
it's a fluid situation
and they have received yes and then no and then yes again
but we know that God is working
and we know that the cause of Christ is moving forward
the people of God are being encouraged
and so please do continue to pray
and we look forward to being able to provide you with more updates
as we receive those from Brother Savali
at this time we'll have our offering
and so I'll pray for the offering
thank you again for your faithfulness in giving
not only for the ministry here
as we seek to reach our community
but also in the supporting of missionaries around the globe
so that we could see the gospel move forward
Father we thank you for the privilege of giving
we acknowledge that all that we have is because of your grace
and because of your good hand of blessing that's been upon us
God we thank you for the opportunity
what a privilege it is to be able to give back to you
to participate in the work of God through our finances
I pray that you take and bless the offering
use it for the furtherance of the ministry here and around the globe
and we'll thank you for it
in Christ's name we pray, amen
♪
all right we're gonna sing our new theme song for 2021
Complete in Thee
we'll sing two verses Complete in Thee
♪
Complete in Thee, O work of mine
May take, dear Lord, the place of thine
Thy blood hath pardoned but for me
And I am now complete in Thee
Dear Savior, when before thy blood
All tribes and tongues assembled are
Among thy chosen will I be
At thy right hand complete in Thee
♪
Sweetly, Lord, have we heard thee calling
Come, follow me
And we see where thy footsteps falling
We will follow the steps of Jesus, where'er they go.
Though they lead o'er the cold, dark mountains, singing, we'll see.
For along thy shore comes mountains welling o'er thee.
Good Prince of Jesus, and make the pathway glow.
We will follow the steps of Jesus, where'er they go.
If they lead through the temple holy, preaching the word.
Or in homes of the poor and lowly, serving the Lord.
Good Prince of Jesus, and make the pathway glow.
We will follow the steps of Jesus, where'er they go.
Then at last, when on high he sees us, our journey done.
We will rest through the steps of Jesus, and at his throne.
Good Prince of Jesus, and make the pathway glow.
We will follow the steps of Jesus, where'er they go.
Well, amen.
Again, I'm so thankful for the blessings of being able to use the technology that God has given us.
And thankful for Holly playing the piano and Joseph being willing to lead the songs.
And certainly a blessing to me.
And I trust the service will be a blessing to you as well.
And we're very thankful for the opportunity of being able to continue in our series from Wednesday evening.
As we wrapped up last year, we were still dealing with the subject matter of sound doctrine.
And as we're looking at sound doctrine and dealing with all of those particular subjects that we've been dealing with.
We have had the opportunity to look at the doctrine of Christ.
And we have been looking here for a number of weeks now at the doctrine of Christ.
And the particular subject in which we're dealing with, this will be part three of a sermon series titled,
Jesus is all the world to me.
And we started that back on December the 9th.
And again, we had part one and part two.
And today we will finish up this three-part series as to Jesus is all the world to me.
And I kind of asked this question, if you were to say Jesus is all the world to you.
And someone said, why? Why is Jesus all the world to you?
What would you say? How would you respond to that question?
The reality is that we started looking at the doctrine of Christ in that great passage of Scripture in Matthew 16.
When Jesus asked the question to the disciples, he said, whom do men say that I am?
And we understand that when Jesus asked that question, that the response of the disciples reveals to us
that there was a great amount of confusion amongst the people.
Why? Because they responded and said, well, some say that you're John the Baptist, Isaiah, Jeremiah, one of the prophets.
And then Jesus looks to his disciples and he says, but whom do ye say that I am?
And Peter stands and what a great declaration when he said, thou art the Christ, the son of the living God.
And it's important that we understand who Jesus is, that he is God in flesh.
We understand that he is Messiah, the promised one, the anointed one.
We understand that he came with a purpose to live a perfect and sinless life,
to go to the cross of Calvary, to shed his precious blood,
to be buried in a borrowed tomb, to rise conquering sin, death, and the grave,
to be ascended to heaven where he lives even now, ever interceding for us.
And one day, one glorious day, he will come and receive us unto himself.
And what a joy it is to know the Lord Jesus Christ.
What a joy it is that we have this book, the Bible.
And the songwriter said, Jesus is all the world to me.
And I think about what Peter said.
Peter proclaimed there in Matthew 16, thou art the Christ, the son of the living God.
But then it was Peter that God used in the book of 1 Peter.
And I'd invite you to turn in your Bibles to 1 Peter, chapter number 2.
And I want you to notice what Peter says.
We use this portion of Scripture in our last study as well.
But it's so important for us to understand and to see how God would use Peter
and the way in which he would communicate this great truth to us.
The Bible says in verse number 3 of 1 Peter, chapter number 2,
if so be ye have tasted that the Lord is gracious.
I'm so thankful for the grace of God.
I'm so thankful that our God is gracious.
And then if you skip down to verse number 7, the Bible says this,
unto you therefore which believe, He is precious.
If you've trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as your personal Savior,
if you have believed and you've received Him as your Savior,
I believe this day that you would say, He is precious.
And we would say as the songwriter wrote that great hymn, Jesus is all the world to me.
Why?
Well, as we would recap just briefly the first two lessons from this series,
we said number one, because of who He is.
Because He is God.
We dealt with His humanity and we dealt with His deity,
that He is God in flesh, 100% man, 100% God.
And we see those attributes throughout the Gospel accounts
and we find that as a man He was tired and sleeping in the ship,
but as God He came and He said, peace be still, and the winds and the waves obeyed.
We said this, number one, that Jesus is all the world to me because of who He is.
Then we said this, because of His mighty power.
Because of His mighty power.
We see that as we study the Gospel records that the Lord Jesus Christ revealed His power
over demons, over disease, over death, over nature.
We find that as you would study the Gospel records,
that the book of Matthew ends by Jesus proclaiming
that all power is given unto me in heaven and in earth.
And I am so thankful that He did not simply declare that He had all power,
but that throughout His earthly ministry He demonstrated His mighty power.
We said this, number three, that Jesus is all the world to me
because of His death, burial, and glorious resurrection.
The fact that as we study through the records and the Gospels
with regard to the crucifixion of Christ,
that we would be mindful of the suffering of Calvary.
And we would understand that He did that for me, that He took my place personally.
That He loved me so much that He was willing to endure
that great conflict and contradiction of sinners so that we might be redeemed.
What a wonderful Savior.
I am so thankful that He went to that borrowed tomb
and that He rose, conquering sin, death, and the grave.
We then said this, number four,
Jesus is all the world to me because of His work today.
The Bible teaches us that He is our great High Priest.
The Bible teaches us that He is our Intercessor.
The Bible teaches us that He is our Advocate.
In fact, the Bible teaches us,
and it will be a segue into our final point in our message today,
that He is preparing a place for me.
And so we have looked at these four things
as to why Jesus is all the world to me,
because of who He is, because of His mighty power,
because of His death, burial, and resurrection,
because of His work today.
And number five, if you're continuing to take notes,
I would say this, because He's coming back for me.
Turn to the book of John, if you will,
and we'll be looking at a number of portions of Scripture
as we study through this final point of this lesson,
Jesus is all the world to me.
In John 14, a familiar portion of Scripture,
but I want you to look at the words of this portion
to be encouraged by what Jesus is telling His disciples
and by the truth that is then relayed to us
as the people of God.
We understand that Jesus had given instruction to the disciples
with regard to His soon crucifixion
at the end of chapter 13.
a new commandment that they should love one another
even as He loved them.
And He said this,
"'By this, by your love one for another,
shall all men know that you are My disciples.'"
And what a blessing.
We find that the news of Calvary
and His being glorified
would bring the disciples to a place
of having heavy, troubled hearts, if you will.
And John 14 begins by Jesus saying to these disciples,
"'Let not your heart be troubled.'"
What a great statement.
Let not your heart be troubled.
Why?
I mean, if He just stopped there
and did not give any reason
as to why the heart should not be troubled,
perhaps the disciples would have walked away
with troubled hearts.
But Jesus says to these disciples,
"'Let not your heart be troubled.
Ye believe in God, believe also in Me.
In My Father's house are many mansions.
If it were not so, I would have told you.
I go to prepare a place for you.'"
Notice this.
"'And if I go and prepare a place for you,
I will come again
and receive you unto Myself,
that where I am, there ye may be also.'"
Now, I hope that as we look at the words
of this very familiar passage of Scripture,
that your heart is rejoicing
at the very truth that Jesus,
the Son of God,
the King of kings and Lord of lords,
is going to return one day for you.
For all of us collectively as the saints of God,
but just to be mindful of the fact
that individually He's coming for me.
What a blessing!
What joy should fill our hearts!
We think about this statement,
Jesus is all the world to me.
And I hope that you would say that He is.
Perhaps, even as we've mentioned
throughout this series,
there are many other reasons that we could give.
This is not in any way, shape, or form
an exhaustive list.
But we find that as we look at these pages of Scripture
and begin to try to give an answer
as to why Jesus is all the world to me,
think about this, because He's coming back for me.
He loves me so much,
He's going to come back for me.
We look here at this passage
and I believe with all of my heart
that the words that Jesus spoke to the disciples
on this particular day at this moment
were a great source of encouragement.
They would face some difficult moments ahead
as they would watch as their Savior was crucified,
as they would endure the days
in which He was in that tomb.
And then to think of going to that tomb
and finding that it was empty.
The resurrection.
All of the thoughts that would flood their minds.
The emotions that they would deal with.
And then as Jesus was ascended up into heaven
as the book of Acts records for us
in Acts 1,
and the disciples stood there and they beheld.
They saw Him go up into heaven.
The Bible says that they looked steadfastly
toward heaven as He went up.
There were two men that stood by them
in white apparel and they said,
you men of Galilee, why stand ye gazing up into heaven?
This same Jesus,
which has taken up from you into heaven,
shall so come in like manner
as you have seen Him go into heaven.
Now, when these two men that were in white apparel,
angels I suppose,
as they gave this word of encouragement
to these disciples,
as they watched as Jesus was ascended up into heaven,
and they heard the message that said
this same Jesus which has taken up from you into heaven,
shall so come in like manner
as you have seen Him go into heaven.
I just wonder as I study
and I look at this passage of Scripture,
I wonder if their minds race back to that day
where we started in John 14,
when they heard Jesus say,
I will come again and receive you unto Myself.
That where I am, there you may be also.
Perhaps when they heard the message
from these angels,
that they were reminded of what Jesus had said.
How it encouraged them.
How it strengthened them.
I'm mindful of the work that God accomplished
through His servants in the book of Acts
and the early church as you read.
You see all that's taking place
and all of the progress
and the way in which the Gospel is going forward.
And we have to be mindful of the fact
that they were living with a keen awareness
of the soon return of their Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.
I would submit to you today
that the coming of the Lord draweth nigh.
Listen for the trumpet as the songwriter said.
I believe that Jesus is coming soon.
We do not know when He's going to come.
In fact, here even in this same passage of Scripture
when the disciples asked Jesus in v. 6
if He would restore again the Kingdom to Israel,
He said to them,
it's not for them to know the times or seasons
which the Father hath put in His own power.
Our job is to be faithful,
to redeem the time,
because the days are evil.
To be faithful followers of the Lord Jesus Christ.
To be doers of the Word.
To be faithfully engaged in the work of God
even as I preached on Sunday evening
engaged in the work.
We understand the imminent return of Christ.
Because He's coming back for me
is one reason I would give
that Jesus is all the world to me.
Turn to the book of 1 Thessalonians if you will
and listen to what Paul tells these believers
in 1 Thessalonica.
These individuals had been
dealing with all sorts of difficulty
and they were a good church.
A model church.
A faithful group of believers.
And Paul is going to give them instruction here
in 1 Thessalonians 4
that has brought encouragement to my heart many times.
He begins in v. 13, he says,
but I would not have you to be ignorant, brethren,
concerning them which are asleep.
That's referring to those that have died
as we'll find contextually in the passage of Scripture.
We understand that God wants us to be informed.
He does not want us to be ignorant.
He says that ye, sorrow not,
even as others which have no hope.
For if we believe that Jesus died and rose again,
even so, them also which sleep in Jesus
will God bring with Him.
For this we say unto you by the word of the Lord,
that we which are alive and remain
unto the coming of the Lord
shall not prevent them which are asleep.
For the Lord Himself shall descend from heaven
with a shout, with the voice of the archangel,
and with the trump of God.
The dead in Christ shall rise first.
Then, we which are alive and remain
shall be caught up together with them in the clouds
to meet the Lord in the air.
And so shall we ever be with the Lord.
It ends with these words, verse 18,
Wherefore, comfort one another with these words.
How comforting these words are.
How encouraging these words are
to understand that Jesus is going to return
and to think about the truth of verse 17.
I don't know, we don't know if we'll be alive at the rapture
or if we'll be one of those that is mentioned earlier
that the dead in Christ shall rise first.
We're not sure, but the excitement would be
if we were alive, verse 17,
then we which are alive and remain,
notice what it says,
shall be caught up together with them,
that's the saints that have died in Christ,
the dead in Christ,
in the clouds, notice this,
to meet the Lord in the air.
And then it says this,
And so shall we ever be with the Lord.
For all of eternity,
we'll have the great privilege of being with our Savior.
Isn't that wonderful?
It's encouraging. It's comforting.
It causes us to live life
and face the challenges of life
in a different manner.
Because we understand that we are strangers in pilgrims, right?
This world is not my home.
I'm just a passing through.
I'm not home, but I'm going home.
My citizenship is in heaven.
We are ambassadors,
as Paul says to the church in Corinth.
What a great privilege it is to know
that He's coming back for me.
The Bible continues to give us truth.
Turn to the book of Hebrews, if you will,
in regard to this promised return.
As we think about the promised return of our Savior,
we find that He...
Hebrews 9 and verse number 27,
a verse that we often will use
when we're speaking to people
about their need for Christ and for salvation.
This is,
"...as it is appointed unto men once to die,
but after this the judgment we find..."
Verse 28,
"...so Christ was once offered
to bear the sins of many,
and unto them that look for Him
shall He appear the second time
without sin unto salvation."
You notice that it says that He shall appear.
And I'm so thankful.
See, He's not going to have to come
another time to deal with sin.
He dealt with sin on His first coming.
We understand that He was born to die.
He was born as we just celebrated
the Christmas season
and spoke about the fact that He would come.
And we understood as Paul said
to the believers there in Galatia
that the Lord would come,
that God sent forth His Son.
When?
When the fullness of time was come,
that God sent forth His Son
made of a woman made under the law
to redeem them that were under the law
that would receive the adoption of sons.
How did He do that?
Redemption is through the blood of Christ.
And so sin has been dealt with
based on His first coming.
At His second coming,
He's not going to have to deal with sin
as far as the payment for sin.
And we find that we will have that privilege
at the rapture of the church
of being able to be with Him
for all of eternity.
In chapter 10 of the book of Hebrews,
in verse 37, notice what the Bible says.
For yet a little while,
and He that shall come will come,
and will not tarry.
Listen, Jesus came right on time
the first time.
When the fullness of time was come,
God sent forth His Son.
I just referenced that in Galatians 4
in verse number 4.
He's coming back right on time.
Sometimes we would say,
I wish it was sooner than later.
I'm ready for Him to come today.
I feel you. I understand.
But the reality is that He's coming
right on time.
And His time is perfect.
His timing is perfect.
We see that throughout the pages of Scripture.
We don't have time to deal with that.
But we understand that His timing is perfect.
And I love that the Bible says
that yet a little while,
and He that shall come will come,
and will not tarry.
Notice in James chapter 5,
we're going to make our way through
a few more portions of Scripture
that end in the book of 1 John.
And Lord willing, it will help us
to not only be encouraged,
but challenged as we're mindful
of this truth that Jesus is coming back for me.
In James 5, notice in verse 7,
Be patient therefore, brethren,
unto the coming of the Lord.
Behold, the husbandman waiteth
for the precious fruit of the earth
and hath long patience for it
until he receive the early and latter rain.
Be ye also patient.
Establish your hearts.
For the coming of the Lord draweth nigh.
As we look at verse 7 and understand
even as we just mentioned
that God's timing is perfect,
it tells us that the husbandman
waiteth for the precious fruit of the earth
and hath long patience for it.
We'd understand the picture there
of the agriculture reference that is given.
The way in which you sow, you plant,
you seek to cultivate,
and all that you do,
you water, etc.
So that you can receive that harvest.
And there's a requirement of patience
in receiving that harvest.
You don't plant today and reap tomorrow.
It doesn't work that way.
We think about the precious fruit of the earth
and we think about the souls
that would be saved
and just the joy of being able
to have one more person
have their name written in the Book of Life.
What a joy.
The Bible tells us in 2 Peter 3,
really as we think about that thought here
in James 5 and look at 2 Peter 3,
remember there were various scoffers
and things that were going on
during this particular time.
We see that it continues even today.
And one of the things that they would say
is where's the promise of His coming?
So thankful that He did promise
that He was coming.
And because He has not come
does not void the promise.
Because He did not say the day
or the hour that He would come.
He said He's coming and He's coming right on time.
And we find that Peter encouraged the believers
by telling them this in verse 9
of 2 Peter 3,
the Lord is not slack concerning His promise,
as some men count slackness.
But as longsuffering to us were,
not willing that any should perish,
but that all should come to repentance.
I'm so thankful that the Lord is not slack
concerning His promise.
You understand that God is not a man,
that He should lie.
We understand as we look at the pages of Scripture
and we are mindful of the truth
that our God is just a faithful God.
He's trustworthy.
He is dependable.
Paul said it this way in 2 Corinthians 1
and verse 20,
for all the promises of God in Him are yea,
and in Him, amen,
unto the glory of God by us.
Paul, as he's writing to Titus,
says this in hope of eternal life,
which God that cannot lie
promised before the world began.
Listen, God has given many, many promises.
You find that He always does
what He says He will do.
I'm mindful of that very truth
even as we're studying through the book of Genesis
on Sunday evenings.
You see how God had made promises.
And He always does what He says He will do.
We serve a faithful God.
He's promised to come back for us.
And we can rest in that promise
knowing that He will return.
Finish with me in 1 John 2.
We'll read through the end of the chapter
and into the first few verses of the 3rd chapter.
In 1 John 2 and verse 28,
the Bible says,
"...now little children abide in Him,
that when He shall appear..."
Do you understand the language that we've been using
as we've studied the pages of Scripture,
the various portions that we've looked at
in this study?
It's never terminology or verbiage
that would have any indication
of uncertainty.
Rather, each passage that we've looked to
has revealed to us through the verbiage that is used
the absolute certainty.
When He shall appear.
Not if He shall appear,
but when He shall appear.
The Bible says, "...and now little children abide in Him,
that when He shall appear,
we may have confidence..."
Notice this.
"...and not be ashamed before Him at His coming."
I hope that there's not one among us
that would be ashamed at the coming of the Lord.
It's possible though.
One of my duties as a pastor
is to teach, to feed the flock of God.
To warn.
To instruct.
I would say this, it's to prepare you.
To prepare you for the coming of the Lord.
To prepare you for the standing
at the behemoth seat of Christ.
To give you instruction from the Word of God.
I cannot make you obey the Word of God.
It would not be right for me to do that.
I can simply preach and teach the truth
that is contained within this Word
and encourage you.
Tell you that it's in your best interest to obey.
To be doers of the Word and not hearers only.
The Bible says that we would be not ashamed
before Him at His coming.
I hope that not one of us,
a Fellowship Baptist church,
would be ashamed at His appearing.
The Bible continues in v. 29,
"...if you know that He is righteous,
you know that everyone that doeth righteousness
is born of Him."
Notice v. 1 of chapter 3.
"...Behold, what manner of love
does the Father have bestowed upon us
that we should be called the sons of God."
Isn't that a precious title?
We're the sons of God.
Children of the King.
I'm a child of the King.
Complete in Christ.
"...Therefore, the world knoweth us not
because it knew Him not."
Beloved, now are we the sons of God.
And it doth not yet appear what we shall be,
but we know that when he shall appear,
we shall be like him, for we shall see him as he is.
And every man that hath this hope in him purifieth himself
even as he is pure."
It's important that we understand that word hope
in verse number 3 of chapter 3.
The word hope is used throughout the Bible.
In fact, Paul, as he's writing to Titus in Titus 2,
talks about the blessed hope and glorious appearing
of our great God and Savior, the Lord Jesus Christ.
We read about the word hope, and the biblical definition
of that word hope is to have that confidence.
Too often, we may allow the definitions
that are common today for our vocabulary
to influence our understanding of the Bible.
We might use that word hope today as a wishful thought,
wishful thinking kind of a manner.
I hope this happens, or I hope that happens.
But biblical hope is not in that vein.
Biblical hope is confidence.
What is it confident of?
It's confident of the promise of God.
We have this hope.
We have this confidence.
Because he said, why is it called the blessed hope?
Because it's based upon the truth
that God gave us, the very words that Jesus spoke.
And so we see that the Bible says
that we have this hope, and every man that hath this hope.
If you've been born again, if you're a child of God,
if you're a son of God, as it says here,
and you understand the teaching of Scripture,
if you understand that He is going to appear,
and you have that hope, notice the impact
that it has on our lives.
It says this, that He purifies Himself, even as He is pure.
Having that desire to be clean, to be pure.
We understand that we'll never reach a place
of sinless perfection.
But we understand that we have an advocate
with the Father.
We understand that our God is a God of forgiveness.
And we think about this truth of walking in the Spirit,
walking in the light as He is in the light.
This idea of purifying Himself, the idea of desiring
to be clean, to have no sin, to have no,
as the songwriter put it this way,
nothing between my soul and my Savior.
And we understand that the connection, if you will,
between 1 John 2, 28 and 1 John 3, verse number 3,
the way in which we can prevent being ashamed before Him
at His coming is by purifying ourselves.
I know I've mentioned this before,
but Holly was part of a music group in college.
And they would go and sing in various churches.
And one of the songs that they sang one of the years
that she was in the group was, Are You Ready?
And it would ask the question repeatedly through the song,
are you ready?
Are you ready?
Are you ready for the coming of the Lord?
I know that oftentimes we say, Lord,
we're ready for You to come back, but are we?
Is it that we're ready for Him to come back
because we want to escape the trials and difficulties of life?
Or is it that we're ready for Him to come back
because we're ready to be in His presence for all of eternity?
And we're ready to be in His presence and to see Him.
We understand that the Lord is going to come back.
What precious, precious promise.
I hope that the promise would not only encourage us,
I hope that it would challenge us.
That we would purify ourselves.
That we would seek to be clean, to have revival in our lives.
Listen, Jesus is all the world to me.
Where would we be without Him?
I mean, the reality is that He's God.
Why is Jesus all the world to you?
Because of who He is.
He's God.
Why is Jesus all the world to you?
Because of His mighty power.
The power displayed during His earthly ministry
over death, disease, demons, nature.
All power is given unto Him, He said, in heaven and earth.
Why is Jesus all the world to you?
Because of His death, burial, and resurrection.
Because He died for me.
He paid for my sin.
He did for me what I couldn't do for myself
and what no one else could do for me.
Why is Jesus all the world to you?
Because of His work today.
Because He's my great High Priest.
He's my intercessor.
He's my advocate.
He's preparing a place for me.
Why is Jesus all the world to you?
Well, because He's coming back for me.
He's giving me a promise.
And that promise helps me every single day
on this journey called life.
Because I know that today could be the day
that He's going to come back for me.
Oh, I trust that your heart has been encouraged
over these past few weeks
on Wednesday evenings, this three-part series,
Jesus is all the world to me.
We're going to order prayer
and then we're going to sing this song together.
Jesus is all the world to me.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
Thank You for loving us.
Thank You for Your Word.
Lord, I know that there's so many other reasons
that we could give as to why
You're all the world to us,
but I pray that as we've just used this sampling
of five reasons,
God, You would stir us up and encourage us.
Thank You for our church family.
I thank You, God, for the work
that You're doing in our lives.
I pray that You'd help us
continue to grow spiritually,
to walk close with Thee,
to honor Thee.
We'll thank You for it.
In Christ's name we pray,
Amen.