Hebrews chapter number two, last week we started this lesson, we ought to listen up.
We've been dealing with this subject matter here on Wednesday evenings, doing what we
ought to do, and just because we know what we ought to do doesn't mean we do what we
ought to do.
And last week we started with this thought of we ought to listen up, and I knew, and
I said from the start that I wasn't confident that we'd get through all of the material
last week, and we certainly did not.
And so tonight's kind of part two of that same lesson.
I'm going to very quickly give an overview of what we looked at last week in case you
were not here, and then we'll get into the follow-up this evening.
But we look at Hebrews chapter two and verse number one, the Bible says, therefore we ought
to give the more earnest heed to the things which we have heard, lest at any time we should
let them slip.
For if the word spoken by angels was steadfast, and every transgression and disobedience received,
a just recompense of reward, how shall we escape if we neglect so great salvation,
which at the first began to be spoken by the Lord, and was confirmed unto us by them that
heard Him, God also bearing them witness, both with signs and wonders, and with divers
miracles and gifts of the Holy Ghost, according to His own will.
And we focus on that first statement of the verse, number one, therefore we ought to give
the more earnest heed to the things which we have heard.
He says this, lest at any time we should let them slip, and we spoke about this idea
of giving the more earnest heed, that's why I've titled it We Ought to Listen Up, and
we said that we see that, therefore, to begin verse number one of chapter two, and we need
to determine why is it there?
What is it that was given to us in chapter one that is so important that he concludes,
he reaches this conclusion that we ought to pay attention, we ought to give the more earnest
heed, and so we went back to chapter one last week, we talked about the fact that the book
of Hebrews deals with the subject matter throughout the book, a theme, that Christ is better,
He is superior, in chapter one He deals with being superior to the angels, but we find
that the book begins in verse number one that says, God, who at sundry times and in divers
manners spake in time past unto the fathers by the prophets, but, notice verse number
two, hath in these last days spoken unto us by His Son, whom He hath appointed heir
of all things, by whom also He made the worlds, who being the brightness of His glory, and
the express image of His person, and upholding all things by the word of His power, when
He had by Himself purged our sins, sat down on the right hand of the majesty on high.
Now if those three verses don't make you want to shout and rejoice, I'm not sure what will,
and the reality is that we serve a great God, we have a wonderful Savior, He is worthy
of our worship and of our praise, and God reveals here that yes, He spoke, and we understand
all scriptures given by inspiration of God, and is profitable, and just because if you
have in your Bible, some people have a red letter edition Bible, listen, the red letters
aren't more inspired than the other words, because all scripture is given by inspiration
of God, but it is something when God in flesh came to earth, and He walked among them, and
He spoke, remember I said this, that those that heard Him often would say, no man spake
like this man.
He speaks with power and with authority, and that's because He's God, He is God in flesh,
and we find that the multitudes would come to hear Him, they would hear as they did in
Mark chapter number two, that it was noise, that He was in the city, and all people, they
wanted to go and hear Him, and they came, and they surrounded the house, there was no
room for anyone to enter in, because there was such a great group of people, and you
find throughout His earthly ministry, there were many that wanted to hear Him, and He
spoke with authority.
I'm thankful this evening that we have the scriptures, that we have the word of God,
and we found last week that we said this, that we need to recognize the danger, the
danger of what?
Well, the danger of not hearing, the danger of not giving the more earnest heed, as the
scriptures say here, the danger of not listening up, the danger of neglecting personal Bible
reading, of missing church services, of not hearing the truth that God wants us to hear.
We said this, the word hear and understanding of giving a, to that which we have heard and
that idea of hearing is not just to hear, but to hear with the purpose of doing, with
the intent of obeying.
It's similar to what Samuel was told to say from Eli, speak, Lord, for thy servant heareth.
And the idea was that he was listening, hearing, with the intent of obeying.
I'm going to obey, I'm going to apply, I'm going to take heed to what you have said.
And so we deal with, and we looked at a number of passages of scripture last week, dealing
with the fact that God has been faithful.
God has been faithful to give his word.
We study the Old Testament, we read multiple times how that God sent prophets and God gave
his word, but the people would not hear.
Can I tell you this evening that God has been faithful to preserve this book?
I am so thankful that God has preserved the Bible, that we can have in our hands today,
tonight a, the copy of God's precious word.
The truth of inspiration is so important for us to understand and it's so foundational
that we understand that scripture, all scripture is given by inspiration of God.
It's God breathed, but I want you to know this evening that inspiration without preservation
doesn't really help any of us today.
Because the originals are no longer with us, but God promised that he would preserve his
word.
And can I tell you that God always does what he says he will do and God has providentially
preserved his word and we have this evening the word, we have the scriptures and what
a blessing.
I think about Paul, even as he would write to Timothy and he says that from a child thou
hast heard the holy scriptures, thou hast known the holy scriptures, which are able
to make thee wise unto salvation.
No, Timothy didn't have the originals, but Timothy had the copies of the copies of the
copies that were from the originals.
And Paul said that that was scripture, that was God's word.
He says to those as he's concluding that he's writing and giving some instruction, he says,
bring these things to me, but especially the parchments.
Why?
Because he wanted to have those scriptures and I'm so thankful this evening.
And so if we understand the danger, if we recognize, acknowledge the danger and we're
dealing with the subject matter of we ought to listen up, then I believe, and what we'll
focus on studying this evening is how do we learn to listen?
How do we develop a plan for hearing, for listening, for the voice of God?
I made a statement a couple of weeks ago on Sunday evening as I preached about Elijah
that he heard the voice of the Lord.
We need to get in a place where we hear the voice of the Lord, that we understand that
as we open the precious pages of this book, that God is speaking to me as an individual,
that God loves me, that God has a message for me and I approach it that way.
And so how do we come to this place that we are going to, as we read here, we ought to
give the more earnest heed to the things which we have heard, less than any time we
should let them slip.
Is it just going to be this, I'm going to work harder?
No, I believe that we need to develop a plan.
And I'm going to share a few things with you this evening that I hope would be a help for
you.
And the first thought is this, it's four simple thoughts, this is not an exhaustive plan for
how we can develop this plan of learning to listen, but the first thought this evening
is that we must remember the authority of God's word.
We must remember the authority of God's word.
I want you to think about this, what we believe about the Bible, what we believe about the
book that you're holding in your hands this evening, will impact how you approach it.
If you just, listen, people have the idea, you can read articles online, you can listen
to people that will stand up and they'll speak for many, many lengths of time and hours and
they'll say this is not the word of God, this is just man's words about God.
Can I tell you this evening, if this is just man's words about God, it's really not that
helpful because you can have your opinion about God and I can have my opinion about
God and so on and so forth, but I'm thankful this evening that God said that he was going
to give the word and that all scripture is given by inspiration of God, that he providentially
preserved it, and it is God's word, and it's not man just writing about what they think
about God, it is God who is the creator of the universe telling us who he is.
And that's awesome.
And when we understand that this word, this Bible, that it's profitable, when we understand
that it's going to produce fruit, that it's going to be effective, it works in us.
Listen, I know this evening, you're here on a Wednesday evening at church, you've read
the Bible, you know that God's word is effectual, that it works in your heart, the entrance
of thy words giveth light, and what a joy to know the truth of this book, and we must
remember the authority.
Somebody has, and I think it's a lot of people.
over the years that have used this reference.
But the fact of the matter is that there are some
that have referred to the Bible
as being God's love letter to mankind.
And I think that's okay to refer to it that way.
I don't have a problem with that.
And the reality is that when they use that analogy,
they try to remind those that they're speaking to
of receiving a letter from a loved one.
Now, I know that today, the idea of letter writing
is kind of not as popular as it once was
because we have so many other means of communication.
But I want you to know that,
and most of us here this evening,
we remember when writing a letter
and dropping it in the box was the only way
to communicate with people on a regular basis.
I mean, it used to be that they charged you
by the minute to make phone calls.
You remember that.
You're old enough, just as I am,
to remember when you had to pay per minute
to make those phone calls.
And so you could drop those letters in the mail.
I remember while we're in college,
my kids, they crack me up.
They say, well, how old were you when you got a cell phone?
Much older than you are.
And by the way, I paid for it when I got it, amen?
And the reality is that we didn't have cell phones.
And so I'd go into the little mail room
where we went to college,
and I'd always go in to look at that box
to see if there was,
I didn't care if there was a graded report in there,
if there was some note from the dean in there.
No, I was looking for a note from Holly.
And if she had a note put in there,
and it was in there, guess what I did with that note?
I just set it aside and ignored it.
No, I read it.
And guess how many times I read it?
Multiple.
I didn't just read it one time.
Sometimes you try to read between the lines.
You know what I'm saying?
You try to figure out,
I wonder what she really means by that.
I wonder, and so on and so forth.
And you can understand, listen,
this book is from the God of the universe,
from our God, who loves us with an everlasting love,
who wants to communicate with us,
and he's given it to us.
And when I remember what this book is,
when I remember that this book is like no other book,
I have books all over my house,
I got books in my library,
I got books on my desk,
I got them in my drawer on my desk,
I got books all over the place,
but there's no book that I enjoy reading
as much as I enjoy reading this book.
There's no other book.
Listen, if I'm only gonna have time to read one book a day,
it's gonna be this one.
It's not going to be something else.
It's not gonna be some news or some whatever periodical.
No, this book is from by God to me as his child.
And I believe that when we come with that approach,
it's going to really help us to learn, to listen,
to have that ear to hear what God has for me.
Why?
Because God's speaking to me.
I understand that as we study the scriptures,
it's important to have proper hermeneutics
and to interpret the scriptures properly
and to understand who the letter or the book was written to
in the time and so on and so forth.
But this book is a divine book.
This book carries with it not only a message
to the original hearers,
but it carries with it a message to me
as God's child today.
And that's amazing.
And so we come from that position.
When I come from that position,
it leads me to my second thought this evening,
that I must then desire to hear from God.
Let me say this, not only desiring,
but expecting to hear from God.
I think about this.
I have had the opportunity in recent days
to be at conferences and hear folks preach.
I don't hear a ton of preaching
because I often am preaching,
but I do listen to some preaching.
I have opportunity to go to some conferences.
Of course, Sunday night, Brother Damastus preached.
And man, when I come to church,
I'm expecting to hear from God.
When I open my Bible to read each morning,
I'm expecting, I'm desiring to hear something from God.
If I don't have that desire,
if I don't have that expectation,
then I'm not really probably gonna hear from God.
I'm not going to, it's just gonna be,
yep, check the box, I got it done, I made it through.
But I want you to think about this.
Psalm 119 and verse 18,
we're familiar with the verse of Scripture.
The Bible says that the psalmist cries out,
"'Open thou mine eyes,
"'that I may behold wondrous things out of thy law.'"
You know how often it is?
Listen, I don't know how many times
I've read the Bible through,
and I don't say that for any prideful type of reason.
I just really don't know.
I read the Bible through multiple times a year.
I've preached through,
I have, as the pastor of Fellowship Adventist Church
for 13, a little over 13 years,
I've preached through like 29 books of the Bible, all right?
That's how many books I have preached through,
verse by verse, chapter by chapter,
but I still read it every day.
You know what I find?
There are times, Kevin,
that I read a portion of Scripture
that I just got done preaching,
and God shows me something that I never saw
the first time that I read it,
or the 50th time that I read it,
or even when I preached it
and studied to preach that message.
This book is awesome.
And I come to it expecting, desiring to hear from God.
I think about that verse that I quoted in Psalm 118.
I think about the reference to Samuel
by way of introduction this evening
when he said, "'Speak, Lord, for thy servant heareth.'"
And those are two prayers that I pray each day
when I open up my Bible and I begin to read.
I pray those two thoughts from Scripture,
Psalm 119 and verse 18, and 1 Samuel 3 and verse 10,
because I wanna hear from God.
I wanna hear from God.
Turn over if you go to Psalm 42,
and I want you to see the imagery that God gives us.
It's a text that no doubt you're familiar with,
but I want you to see it this evening.
In Psalm 42, verses one and two,
the Bible says,
as the heart panteth after the water brooks,
so panteth my soul after thee, O God.
Notice it says, my soul thirsteth for God,
for the living God.
When shall I come and appear before God?
I wonder if your soul's ever thirsted for God.
You need to hear from God.
You need a message from the Lord.
You're longing to have that communication from God,
and you go to his word and you receive it.
Listen, I've read accounts of individuals
that have not had the privilege
of having a Bible like you and like me.
They've been outlawed.
There are people that were killed, martyred,
burned at the stake simply for having a copy of the Bible.
There are people that were Christians
living under communist rule,
that the communist, even,
I mean, I'm talking just 100 years ago.
I'm not talking 400 years ago.
In portions of Europe,
you find that just 100 years ago,
somebody found with a Bible
how they would face great persecution,
be imprisoned.
I remember reading a story once
of a young girl that did not have a Bible,
but she attended a church where they preached the Bible,
and she so desperately wanted to have a Bible of her own
that she'd have the opportunity to read it,
to not just have to only be able to hear it
when she would go to church,
but that she'd be able to read it every day of her life,
and she enjoyed the opportunity to go to church
and to hear the preaching,
but man, she just longed to be able to read it every day,
and she asked the preacher if she could have the Bible
and she would take it each evening
and bring it back each morning,
and he didn't know exactly what she was doing.
He thought maybe that she was just reading
as much as she possibly could,
and she came back, and after a period of time,
he began to inquire.
She said, no, I'm not reading it
because if I just read it,
then I would just read it once and I'm done.
I am writing it down word for word
so that I can have my own copy.
Can you imagine?
Wow.
We have the Bible.
You know, sometimes when we have something,
we don't really appreciate what we have.
There are people all over the world tonight
that don't have a Bible.
They would do just about anything to get a Bible.
They don't have one,
and sometimes we have and we neglect,
and that's unfortunate,
and so what we must do as we're developing this plan,
yes, we have to start by understanding
who this book is from and what this book is,
and then we have that desire, that expectation
that I wanna hear from God.
I would say this, number three,
as we develop this plan,
we need to prepare to hear from God.
We need to take steps to prepare to hear from God.
How do I prepare?
Well, number one, I better prepare my heart.
The Bible talks of Josiah of having a tender heart,
and oh, how our heart needs to be tender
toward the things of God,
and as we approach the scriptures
that we are preparing to hear.
Deuteronomy 32 and verse 46,
the Bible says this,
and it's such a wonderful truth
in this text of scripture,
nearing the end of the children of Israel
preparing to enter into the land of promise,
and in Deuteronomy 32 and verse 46,
Moses, it says, made an end of speaking, verse 45,
and he said unto them,
set your hearts unto all the words
which I testify among you this day,
which you should command your children to observe.
to do all the words of this law.
And you notice it says, set your hearts onto all the words.
We have a prepared heart when we have that desire
in our heart, I wanna hear from God.
I wanna, I have that desire, but then I'm going
and I'm making the preparation, how am I gonna hear?
Listen, I wonder tonight, when you're speaking to someone,
do you desire that they're listening to you?
When you're speaking to somebody.
If you're talking to somebody, I don't know myself,
I'm gonna grab it, right?
But if you're talking to somebody
and as you're talking to them,
they're just doing this the whole time, does that annoy you?
I'm being honest, does it annoy you?
Do you think that they're listening to you?
No, and there are times in which I've been guilty of,
and I've said to some people, somebody's talking to me
and I said, listen, I'm not ignoring you,
I'm just trying to find something to be able to use
in our conversation and I try to be careful to do that.
Why?
Because I want the, I understand the person's talking,
they wanna have somebody that's listening to them.
Let me ask you this, when you pray,
do you want God to listen to you?
Do you want God to listen to you when you pray?
Yeah, no doubt.
I'm thankful for the promise that says,
call unto me and I will answer thee
and show thee great and mighty things
which thou knowest not.
But I'm mindful this evening,
the Bible says this in Proverbs 22 and verse 17,
bow down thine ear and hear the words of the wise
and apply thine heart unto my knowledge.
We need to think about the imagery of that verse
where it says bow down thine ear
and hear the words of the wise
and just the imagery that is given there
and of course we understand
that Solomon is writing to his son
but in a much more greater truth,
it is God writing to his people in the book of Proverbs
and we understand that God is giving us,
he has all wisdom, he is the all wise God
and we need to have prepared hearts, tender hearts.
We need to bow down our ears,
we need to listen and apply our heart
unto the knowledge that God would give us.
I think about our minds
and how we can clear our minds of distractions.
You know, it's easy to be distracted.
I dealt with that a few weeks ago on Sunday morning
of a good soldier and the reality is
that when we come into church,
anytime we come into church,
anytime that we open up our Bible to read our Bibles
in our personal Bible study,
you know that the enemy doesn't like that
and you know that distractions are gonna come.
How many of you have tried to witness to somebody?
You've either gone door knocking,
tried to witness to someone
or maybe you have had the opportunity
just in some other setting to try to witness to someone
and it seems like just as you're getting to the point
of being able to share the gospel with them,
there's some distraction.
I mean, it could be a phone call,
it could be a baby crying,
it could be as it happened to us on Saturday
that the person says,
well, actually I got something cooking on my stove
and it's on right now so I probably should go
and what am I supposed to say?
No, let your house burn down.
I mean, it's a tough thing
but the reality is that there are distractions
but it's for you as well.
You open up your Bible in the morning to read
and this happens and that happens
and this distraction and that distraction.
You come into church, especially on a Wednesday evening,
it's in the middle of a work week,
there's all sorts of things going on.
You had things at the office that were undone when you left
and there are things that you have to deal with tomorrow
and there's something going on with the kids
and there's something going on with whatever
and you can come with distractions
and you cannot even hear what God has for you.
So what do we do?
We prepare our hearts, we prepare our minds.
God, help me to eliminate the distractions.
Help me to be focused on what's at hand
because I know you have something for me.
Why?
Because when you come to our church,
you know the Bible's gonna be used
and so if the Bible's being used,
then God is going to speak to his people
and what a blessing that is
but the reality is that there's some preparation
on our part that we need to deal with.
I'm interested and amazed by some cultures
and it's not so common in the American culture
but I've witnessed it in America
and I've witnessed it by a number of other cultures
that as they enter into a church building,
the first thing they do is sit down and begin to pray.
They sit down and begin to pray
and then they stand up and they begin to worship.
Why?
I believe they're trying to get their heart prepared.
I believe they're trying to get focused on,
I'm here to worship God.
I'm not bringing in all those distractions of the world.
Let me say this, number four,
I believe that we need to predetermine
that we will agree with God.
Predetermine that we're gonna agree with God.
You say, well, I don't particularly like what I read.
I don't particularly like what I heard.
You're gonna agree with God or you're not?
You say, well, isn't there some middle ground?
No, not really.
You're gonna agree with God or you're not
and the reality is that if we predetermine,
we sing that song sometimes when we have a revival meeting,
we sing it before every message of the revival meeting.
I'll say yes, Lord, yes to your will and to your way.
I'll say yes, Lord, yes to your,
man, I just forgot the words.
With my whole heart, I'll agree
and my answer will be yes, Lord, yes.
When your spirit speaks to me,
that was the line that I missed.
When your spirit speaks to me with my whole heart,
I'll agree and my answer will be yes, Lord, yes.
You open your Bible at whatever time
you have your time with the Lord
and you come to church for church service,
you predetermine, I'm gonna agree with God.
I'm gonna take the truth that God has given to me
and I'm going to agree that God knows best.
I'm not gonna lean on my own understanding.
I'm not going to lean on the cultural understandings.
I'm not going to, no, I'm gonna agree with God.
Let me use an illustration if I could,
Jeremiah, if you will, chapter 42
and I won't have time to develop all of this.
I'm gonna just kinda pick through about a chapter and a half
very quickly this evening so that we have time for prayer
but in Jeremiah 42, I'm giving you an example here
to close this little, this message tonight,
this example that really helps us be mindful
of the fact that we need to predetermine to agree with God
but looking at an example here in Jeremiah 42
where they seemingly do that
but then they don't agree with God.
They disobey.
In Jeremiah 42, the Bible says in verse number two,
and said unto Jeremiah the prophet,
let we beseech thee our supplication be accepted
for thee and pray for us unto the Lord thy God
even for all this remnant for we are left
but a few of many as thine eyes do behold us
that the Lord thy God may show us the way
wherein we may walk and the things that we may do.
Now, is that a good request?
I mean, it's a good desire, is it not?
I mean, these people are coming to Jeremiah
and say, Jeremiah, pray for us.
We need to know what to do.
We need to know where to go and what to do.
And Jeremiah in verse four, the prophet said unto them,
I have heard you behold, I will pray to the Lord your God
according to your words and it shall come to pass
that whatsoever thing the Lord shall answer you,
I will declare it unto you.
I will keep nothing back from you.
Now that's a good prophet of the Lord, is it not?
He says, all right, I'm gonna pray for you.
And I'm gonna give you exactly what God says.
I'm gonna give you the example.
I'm not gonna hold anything back.
I'm gonna give you exactly what God says.
Then verse five, they said to Jeremiah,
the Lord be a true and faithful witness between us
if we do not even according to all things
for the which the Lord thy God shall send thee to us,
whether it be good or whether it be evil,
we will obey the voice of the Lord our God
to whom we send thee, that it may be well with us
when we obey the voice of the Lord.
After 10 days, the word of the Lord came unto Jeremiah
according to verse number seven.
And Jeremiah delivers the message.
He goes and he tells them, and again,
I don't have time to deal with all of this,
but we find that he gives them all of the information
that God had communicated to him
beginning in these verses that we see
that Jeremiah receives after those 10 days
and he calls in verse number eight,
the people back and he begins to deliver the message.
He's declaring it as he promised to do so in verse number four
he's keeping nothing back from them
as he promised in verse number four.
And we find that in verse number, look at verse number 20.
Let's back up in verse 19.
The Lord hath said concerning you, O you remnant of Judah,
go ye not into Egypt.
Know certainly that I have admonished you this day
for ye dissembled in your hearts
when you sent me unto the Lord, your God,
saying, pray for us to the Lord, our God,
and according unto all that our Lord,
the Lord, our God shall say, so declare unto us
and we will do it.
That idea that he says there,
ye dissembled in your hearts,
it means to disguise or to conceal.
It means to conceal one's true motives.
And now verse 21, I have this day declared it to you,
but ye have not obeyed the voice of the Lord, your God,
nor anything for the which he hath sent me unto you.
Now therefore, know certainly that ye shall die
by the sword, by the famine, by the pestilence,
in the place whether you desire to go into sojourn.
Look at chapter 43.
And it came to pass that when Jeremiah
had made an end of speaking at all the people,
all the words of the Lord, their God,
for which the Lord, their God had sent him to them,
even all these words.
Now, just understand,
I know I'm reading through this quickly,
but get the thought here.
These people come to Jeremiah.
Jeremiah didn't go to them, amen?
The people came to Jeremiah and they said to Jeremiah,
pray and ask God what we should do.
And here's our commitment.
We're going to obey what God says.
Jeremiah faithfully prays, he faithfully delivers,
but the people do not obey.
Jeremiah ends his speech in verse two.
The Bible says, then speak.
the son of Uzziah, the son of Azariah,
the son of Hoshiah, and Johanan, the son of Koriah,
and all the proud men, saying unto Jeremiah,
by the way, there's a key there in the proud men,
they said to Jeremiah, Thou speakest falsely.
The Lord our God hath not sent thee to say,
go not into Egypt to sojourn there.
Now, understand with me,
what they really wanted to do was go to Egypt.
You know what they were looking for?
They wanted somebody to tell them, go to Egypt.
And when Jeremiah said, don't go to Egypt,
they didn't like it.
So here's what I'm saying to you this evening,
we need to take and understand as we develop that plan
for how can I learn to listen,
and we see that we ought to listen up
when I approach the Bible,
when I understand that this is God's authoritative word,
it is God's letter, His message to me as His child,
I'm desiring to hear from Him,
I'm expecting to hear from Him,
I've prepared my heart, I've prepared my mind,
I've tried to eliminate the distractions as best I can,
but I must predetermine that I'm going to agree with God.
What God says, I'm going to do.
I'm going to agree with God.
It's one thing for us to say we're going to agree with God,
it's another thing that we agree with God,
that we take and we apply the truth
that God has given to us in His word.
Unfortunately, this group of people in Jeremiah 43,
they did not obey the voice of the Lord,
they did not obey the message
that God delivered through His man Jeremiah,
and it's a sad reality,
but we find that even today,
even as we look back at Hebrews chapter 2,
that it says this, and again,
the last part of that first verse,
he says this,
therefore we ought to give the more earnest heed
to the things which we have heard,
lest at any time we should let them slip.
Why do they slip?
Is it that we don't remember them,
or is it that we just simply don't want to
hearken unto the voice of the Lord?
You know, we live in a society
where a lot of people want to do what they want to do.
They want to be their own authority,
their own boss, their own person,
and as believers, as Christians,
we submit to the authority of this book.
Say, God, it's your word,
I want to hear from you.
I want to give the more earnest heed.
I don't want it to just,
I'm not looking for my ears being tickled,
I'm not looking for somebody to just tell me
what I want to hear,
I'm not looking for someone to just
tell me everything is going to be okay.
Sat in my office with somebody on Friday,
and I said, listen, it is absolutely wrong for us
as the people of God to put our arm around somebody,
whether physically or just, you know,
in a imagery kind of a way,
and say, oh, everything's going to be okay.
No, everything's not going to be okay.
Everything's not going to be okay.
Oh, you just be you,
and you just do what you think is right.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
God's given us a word.
He's given us the truth.
There's a song, I don't know the entirety of it,
I've only heard it sung one time.
It talks about preachers,
about standing with courage and with boldness,
and don't tell us what we want to hear,
but tell us what we need to hear.
You know, when we go to the Bible,
in your daily life, when you come to church
and you hear the Bible taught,
we need to have a plan on,
how am I going to hear from God today?
How am I going to, I'm coming prepared
so that I might hear something from God,
so that I might get the instruction that I need,
so that I can apply the truth in my life,
so that I can be conformed to the image of his dear son,
so that I can please him with my life.
We ought to listen up.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for your word.
I do thank you for the truth that's contained therein.
I pray, Lord, that you'd help us tonight.
We see the danger of not listening up,
of not giving heed to those who ignored,
to those who flat out would not listen,
to those who rebelled,
to those who denied the authority of the message,
to those who are scoffers and mockers.
We see all through the scripture,
all of these examples of those that would not hear.
God, I pray tonight that you'd help us to have a heart
that longs for thee,
or a desire to hear from thee.
I pray, God, that you would help us daily
as we open your word and each service
that we have the opportunity to attend,
Lord, that we'd have ears to hear.
We'll thank you for the work that you'll do,
for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Amen.
If you have your prayer bulletin with you this evening,
we'll start.