Hallelujah, Jesus ransomed me.
Why?
All are welcome.
You know, there's some people that we know,
there's some people that I know that you know personally
that could not sing this morning,
when the roll is caught up yonder, I'll be there.
They don't know.
There's some people that you know that I know
that can't say, Jesus ransomed me.
I don't even know what it means.
But all are welcome.
We have a great responsibility to tell them
of this wonderful, wonderful truth that Jesus saves.
And so thankful for those songs this morning.
First John chapter number five,
we'll be looking at verses six through 13.
The title for the message, the witness of God is greater.
And we'll see that statement in our text of scripture
as we come to the word of God
and we come to this passage of scripture.
Of course, all year I've been preaching on Sunday mornings.
We've taken some weeks off,
but we've been preaching through the book of First John
and we're nearing the end
as we are nearing the end of a calendar year.
And we have made it through thus far.
But I want you to be mindful this morning
of the fact of just thanking God
and having appreciation for what God has given us
and allowing us to have the word of God.
I believe that if we're not careful,
there are times in our lives
that we can take things for granted.
And if we're not careful,
when we take those things for granted,
we lack appreciation for those things.
And we're gonna take things for granted.
We take for granted, if we're not careful,
the fact that God has given us a Bible,
that God has given us a church
where the Bible is faithfully preached.
And we can take those things for granted week after week,
day after day in our lives.
And we can, if we're not careful,
have a diminished appreciation for what God has given us.
But I believe this morning
that as we understand the truth of the gospel,
as we understand the truth about who Jesus is
and about the plan of salvation,
we get to hear it so often and so regularly.
But I hope that it never loses
that impact in your life and in my life
when we hear the wonderful truth that Jesus saved,
that it continues to impact our lives,
that we, maybe I'll say it this way,
that we never get over it
and that we constantly live in a state of appreciation
for what God has done for us.
As we go to the book of 1 John,
as we've studied through this book,
there are several verses in the book of 1 John
that are very well known.
Could be argued as to which verses
are more well known than others.
But I would say this morning
that 1 John 5.13 definitely stands at the,
finds its place in the list of the most commonly known,
referenced verses in the book of 1 John.
It may not be at the top of the list,
but it certainly would find itself on the list
of the most known verses in the book of 1 John.
And the Bible says this in verse 13,
these things have I written unto you
that believe on the name of the Son of God,
that you may know that you have eternal life
and that you may believe on the name of the Son of God.
As we think about this verse of scripture
and we think about the security of the believer,
how thankful I am for this truth of this verse.
And no doubt when it says these things
have I written unto you,
that it would really capture the entirety
of the book of 1 John.
But this morning, we're going to look
at the immediate context of what John is writing
when he speaks about these things
within the immediate context.
Of course, broadly speaking,
it's the entirety of the book of 1 John.
But as we look at this text of scripture this morning,
we find that the Bible tells us,
notice in verse number nine,
if we receive the witness of men,
then notice the statement,
the witness of God is greater,
for this is the witness of God,
which he hath testified of his son.
And we'll look at the entirety of the passage,
but I want you to be aware of the fact this morning
that the witness of God is greater.
And I'm so thankful that God has given us
this record or this witness.
We'll see that both of those terms are used
throughout these verses of scripture
about the record that's been given,
the witness that has been provided.
And I'm so thankful to have the truth
of the Word of God.
If you're taking notes this morning,
notice first of all with me,
the record delivered.
The record delivered.
Begin reading with me in verse number six.
Notice what the Bible says.
This is He that came by water and blood,
even Jesus Christ.
Not by water only,
but by water and blood.
And it is the Spirit that beareth witness,
because the Spirit is truth.
For there are three that bear record in heaven,
the Father, the Word, and the Holy Ghost.
And these three are one.
Verse eight, there are three that bear witness in earth,
the Spirit, and the water, and the blood,
and these three agree in one.
As we begin to look at these verses of scripture
and understand the record has been delivered,
we ought to just pause right there
and say hallelujah that He's given us a record
that He's provided us with this witness
and it's been delivered.
As we begin to think about the record
that's been delivered,
there are a couple of things that I understand
in this passage of scripture
that are important for us to recognize this morning.
And number one is this,
the record that's been delivered is reliable.
It's reliable.
Aren't you thankful for that?
I don't want a record that is not trustworthy.
I don't want a record that is not reliable,
something that I can't trust, that I cannot depend on.
But when we look at the record that's been delivered,
as John is writing here to these believers,
he says to them, and we find by way of preservation
that God is saying to us
that the record that's been delivered is reliable.
It is trustworthy.
It is something that we stake our eternity on
and we ought to rejoice this morning
that we have a reliable record.
Notice what the Bible says about this record.
The Bible says in verse number six,
this is He that came by water and blood,
even Jesus Christ.
Notice, not by water only, but by water and blood.
And then it says this, and it is the Spirit.
That's a capital S.
Who's it referring to?
It's referring to the Holy Spirit or the Holy Ghost.
And it says the Spirit that beareth witness.
I'm thankful that the Spirit of God,
the Holy Ghost, bears witness.
And I'm thankful that because the Holy Spirit is,
when we think about the Trinity,
the third person of the Godhead, the Holy Ghost,
and the witness that He gives is reliable,
notice what it says, because the Spirit is truth.
There are so many people today
that are so confused about truth.
Can you know truth?
Is there truth?
They believe that truth is something
that would be described as being relative,
that it's your truth or their truth or my truth
or someone else's truth,
but I'm thankful that the Word of God
declares for us that the Spirit is truth.
And remember that Jesus Christ said this
in John 14 in verse number six,
I am the way, the truth, and the life.
No man cometh unto the Father but by me.
What a great declaration.
We find that the Bible says in John 17,
sanctify them by thy Word.
Thy Word is truth.
We begin to think about the Spirit bearing witness
and the Spirit being defined here
as being the, because the Spirit is truth,
because it is the Spirit that beareth witness
and because it is the Spirit that is truth,
then we know that this record that we have is reliable.
It is trustworthy, it's dependable.
Listen, I'm not interested in something
that's just potentially reliable.
I'm not interested in something
that has holes and has problems.
I'm thankful that God said that every Word of God is pure
and that He's given us a perfect book
and He's given it to us and He's preserved it for us.
And we understand as we look at the passage of Scripture
that there is unity and there is agreement
within the Godhead.
It tells us in verse number seven,
for there are three that bear record in heaven.
By the way, I'm thankful that at this time,
at the writing of the book of 1 John
and even now still at this moment,
that Jesus is in heaven.
He's ascended up into heaven.
We see that the Bible speaks about these three
that bear record.
The Word, the Bible says this,
the Father, the Word.
Who's the Word?
Jesus Christ and the Holy Ghost.
And these three are one.
There is agreement, there is unity amongst the Trinity.
And we find that Jesus Himself,
after His ministry here upon this earth,
after His death and His burial
and His glorious resurrection
and He ministered for 40 days
and then He ascended up into heaven.
And the Bible tells us that He's at the right hand
of the throne of God
and that He ever liveth to make intercession for us.
He was dead, but now He's alive
and He's alive forevermore.
And the Bible tells us that He's coming again.
Oh, what a glorious truth.
He has a perfect plan.
We find that He's given us this record
and obviously we could understand
that as John is writing to these believers
and under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
He's writing this book of 1 John
and He says that the record's been delivered,
that the record is reliable,
but I would broaden it this morning
to say of the entirety of it.
of this book has been delivered.
The entirety of this book is reliable.
Listen, we don't look to try to prove the Bible
through science or archeology or any other thing.
We say, no, as those things are discovered,
as those things are understood,
the Bible gives credit to what they've determined.
Amen?
And we say the Bible is true.
It's reliable.
Notice, as John would write,
it's very interesting, remember,
that John is dealing with some false teachers
that would be prevalent.
In fact, as you study the New Testament,
you find that the Bible regularly speaks
about these false teachers.
Just as there were false prophets in the Old Testament,
there would be false teachers.
And we find that they're active and they're working.
And as we studied the book of Colossians last year,
we mentioned how that Paul was writing
and he was giving great truth
and trying to help these people understand
the error of the Gnostics
and understanding the truth of the word of God.
And we find that John is dealing with the same thing.
The Gnostics are still active and things are taking place.
And we find that he had mentioned in 1 John 4,
in verse number one,
beloved, believe not every spirit,
but try the spirits, whether they're of God,
because many false prophets are gone out into the world.
We find that these false teachers were active.
And one of the false teachers, an early Gnostic,
that was very active and it seems very evident
that John, under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
is really dealing with one of the great errors of their way
in verse number six, was a guy by the name of Serenthes.
And Serenthes, the folks that would follow him
were Serenthenes, not to be confused with the Corinthians,
but the Serenthenes.
And he was an early Gnostic and he was teaching.
And really, as we've mentioned throughout the years,
and as we've looked specifically at 1 John
and chapter number four, we said this,
often as you look at the false teachers, what do they do?
They get it wrong on Jesus.
Can I tell you today that people still
are getting it wrong on Jesus?
And if you got it wrong on who Jesus is,
there's no hope of eternity as far as salvation
and having a home in heaven.
We find that, listen, we just spent almost two weeks
in a land where Jesus walked, where Jesus ministered,
where Jesus proved his deity.
We're in various places and yet there are countless,
countless scores of people that are blinded
and they have it wrong about Jesus.
Broke my heart to see so many people that are so close,
but they're lost, but they're lost.
Agrippa said to Paul,
almost thou persuadest me to be a Christian.
Almost isn't good enough, amen?
And it's the person of Jesus.
And this man, Serenthes, how he got it wrong
and what he would teach is that he would teach
that the Christ, meaning Messiah,
see, he said that Jesus was just a man.
He did not understand the incarnation.
He did not understand the deity of Jesus Christ.
And he said this, that at the baptism of Jesus,
that that's when the Christ descended upon him.
And then prior to the crucifixion,
the Christ left him, departed him.
And so we find that John is saying this,
and you think about the earthly ministry
of the Lord Jesus Christ,
it was inaugurated when?
At the baptism.
By the way, John knew who he was.
John the Baptist understood who Jesus was.
John the Baptist felt unworthy to baptize Jesus.
He said, there's one that comes after me
that is preferred above me and before me.
He said this, I'm not worthy to unloose his sandals,
the latches of his shoes.
And we find that he, John the Baptist,
he was the forerunner.
He understood who Jesus was.
But Jesus at his baptism at Jordan,
God the Father said, this is my beloved son
in whom I am well pleased.
The inauguration of the earthly ministry
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And you understand that he's always been God.
He left the throne room of heaven
and he came to this sin-cursed world.
And he's always been the God-man,
100% God and 100% man.
And we find that John is focusing here really
on dealing with the false teaching that's taking place.
And he's talking about the record of God being reliable.
He says, notice what he says,
this is he that came by water and blood even.
Notice what he says, Jesus Christ.
Why does every word of God is pure?
Why does he use the terminology that he does?
He doesn't just say that Jesus, he says Jesus Christ.
Remember when Paul was preaching in Thessalonica
and he says, this Jesus whom I preach unto you is Christ.
They understood who the man Jesus was,
but he was making sure they understood
that he is the Messiah,
that his name, the Lord Jesus Christ.
We find that Jesus, of course,
hung upon that cruel cross.
By the way, he had to,
in order to fulfill the plan of redemption.
The plan of redemption that was determined
before the foundation of the world.
When you read the book of Ephesians in the first chapter,
you find that God has clearly communicated to his people
that the plan of redemption was determined
before the foundation of the world.
How would people be saved that Jesus
would come to this incursed world
and that he would die in our place?
He would take on himself the form of a man.
He would suffer, he'd bleed and die.
We find that here, John, no doubt,
is exposing the false teaching of Serenthes.
And we find that as he would expose that false teaching,
he's saying, listen, God has given us a record
and the record that God has given us is true.
It is reliable.
We find that it's the spirit of God,
the Holy Ghost that bears witness
and the spirit is truth.
Notice not only that the record has been delivered
and that the record is reliable,
but I'd say this, the record is available.
Aren't you thankful that the record is available?
You know, it's one thing to say the record's reliable,
but you know, it's just, we don't know where it is.
Well, that'd be tragic, wouldn't it?
But the record is not available.
But the record is not only reliable,
but the record is available.
I mean, you're holding it in your hands this morning.
You're holding in your hands
the record that has been delivered.
You're holding in your hands the record
that God is speaking of that God graciously gave,
but then providentially preserved the record
so that you and I and countless millions of people
around this world today can have this reliable record
that's available to us.
Why do we put scriptures together?
Why do we support a printing ministry
such as Beacon of Truth?
Because there are millions upon millions upon millions
of people around the world that do not have yet
this record that's been given in their own native tongue,
in their own language.
And so we desire to help and to provide the resources
and the manpower so that Bibles and portions of scripture
can be given in their own language.
I said to many people this past week,
your English is good, and they would laugh
and they'd chuckle, and I'd say this,
it's much better than my Hebrew.
It's much better than my Greek.
I'm thankful that the Bible that I have is in English
because that's my native tongue.
Amen?
We find this morning, even within our congregation,
the folks that have a native tongue
that's different than English,
that now they've learned English and they read it
and they understand it and so on and so forth,
but the Bible's available in their language.
What a joy, what a blessing.
This morning, when we think about the truth,
the record has been delivered, that it's reliable, yes,
but it's also available to us.
Think about this, turn to the book of 1 Corinthians,
if you will, chapter 15.
Notice what Paul says.
Look at just a couple of verses this morning
in dealing with this truth
that the record is available to us.
In 1 Corinthians, chapter 15, we would often,
as we think about that chapter being mentioned,
we'd be aware of the fact
that it's the great resurrection chapter, and it is,
and I'm so thankful for the truth of 1 Corinthians 15,
but notice what Paul says, beginning in verse number one.
Moreover, brethren, I declare unto you the gospel,
which I preached unto you,
which also you have received, and wherein ye stand,
by which also you're saved,
if you keep in memory what I preached unto you,
unless you have believed in vain.
Notice what he says,
for I delivered unto you, first of all,
that which I also received,
how that Christ died for our sins,
according to the scriptures, and that he was buried,
and that he rose again the third day,
according to the scriptures.
Paul is saying, listen, I've declared something to you,
but what I've declared,
he uses the word declare in verse number one,
he uses the word deliver in verse number three,
but what he declared and what he delivered
was first what he had received,
and what he had received,
he then declared and delivered specifically,
contextually to the believers in Corinth,
and these believers in Corinth,
as Paul would take that missionary journey,
and he'd go to Corinth, and he faced opposition,
and he faced difficulty,
but the Lord appeared to him and said,
I have much people in this city,
sorry.
How encouraging that must have been for Paul to receive that message.
And he ministered there, and a church was established, and we know it's not a model
church.
They had many problems in the church in Corinth, but there were people in Corinth that were
saved because a message was delivered.
Because Paul had received it, and then Paul declared and delivered that message.
And the message that Paul delivered, the record that Paul gave to the believers in Corinth
as he went to that place, we find that it was available to them.
He then writes this under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God, and he sends this
letter to them so that they could receive further instruction.
What a joy.
In the book of Jude, it's just one chapter.
We find that Jude is giving us great truth, and it's a one-chapter book, 25 verses.
But man, the content of this book is so rich and so deep.
We find that Jude says this in verse number 3,
Beloved, when I gave all diligence to write unto you of the common salvation, it was needful
for me to write unto you and exhort you that you should earnestly contend for the faith,
notice the statement, which was once delivered unto the saints.
Aren't you thankful that the record has been delivered?
I'm so thankful this morning.
I think we should pause in our minds just for a moment and thank God that He's delivered
a record to us, and that the record that He's delivered, these things that are mentioned
in this passage, the witness as He used that word interchangeably for this record that
we can rejoice this morning, that it's reliable.
Every word of God is true.
Amen?
And it's available.
I've read today and last week and this last year, I've read as much of God's Word as I
wanted to, and so have you.
Amen?
Because it's available.
Sometimes it just sits on a shelf somewhere, and it's ignored, and how tragic that is,
because the record is, man, it's reliable, it's helpful.
The Bible says of itself that the Word of God is profitable.
Not profitable just sitting on a shelf somewhere, but profitable to me as a believer as I read
it, as I study it.
Yes, it taught me the truth of salvation.
We understand that He says in that same passage of Scripture, as Paul is speaking to Timothy,
that from a child thou hast known the Holy Scriptures, which are able to make thee wise
unto salvation.
Hallelujah.
But it's not just a book that teaches us about salvation, but it's a book that teaches us
about sanctification.
There's much that we speak of with regard to salvation, and if we're not careful, we
don't really discuss enough sanctification.
But those that have been born again, those that have been saved, we are to be sanctified,
set apart.
We're to be conformed to the image of His dear Son.
We're to be holy as He is holy.
Amen?
He left us an example that we should follow His steps, and we think about this process
of sanctification.
I'm thankful this morning that salvation is the miracle of a moment, amen?
That when you understand that you're lost and you're hellbound because of your sin and
that you are guilty, that Jesus Christ is the only Savior, and you place your faith
and trust in Jesus Christ, you can say, hallelujah, Jesus ransomed me.
Sanctification is a process.
Some have said this, it's a process of a lifetime, becoming like our Savior.
Every single day, drawing closer to Him, drawing nigh to God, becoming like Him.
You see, I'm thankful to be saved, but He saved us, and He's got a plan for us, amen?
And His plan is that we would be like His dear Son.
Read Romans 8, oftentimes we read verse 28, we know that all things work together for
good to them that love God, to them who are called according to His purpose, and we can
rejoice in understanding that Bible truth.
Sometimes we're going through the difficulties of life, we don't fully understand how it
all works, but we can rest in knowing that God has a plan and God has a purpose.
But we look at verse number 29, and it says that we've been predestined to be conformed
to the image of His dear Son.
That's God's plan for each and every one of us, is that we would be like Christ.
I'm so thankful that the record has been delivered.
It's reliable, it's available.
Let me say this, number two, by the way, I only have two points this morning, don't get
nervous.
A record delivered, number two, a response demanded, a response demanded.
You know, every man is going to believe someone or something.
You can read in Acts 27, we won't take the time to develop the thought, but in Acts chapter
number 27, they're going to sail, and Paul makes mention that it's not wise for them
to set sail.
He says that sailing was dangerous, and he says to them in verse number 10, "'Sirs,
I perceive that this voyage will be with hurt and much damage, not only to the lading
in the ship, but also to our lives.'"
And it then says this in verse number 11 of Acts 27, "'Nevertheless, the centurion believed
the master and the owner of the ship more than those things which were spoken by Paul.'"
And what did they do?
They departed, and they hit a terrible storm.
Everyone believes someone.
We've got to make sure we're believing the right someone.
Amen?
And the report has been delivered, but there is a response that is demanded.
We find that as this report has been delivered, he continues in verse number 9.
Notice where he says, "'If,' there's this word, this conditional word, "'if we receive
the witness of men,' then he says this, "'the witness of God is greater.
For this is the witness of God, which he hath testified of his Son.
He that believeth on the Son of God hath the witness in himself.
He that believeth not God hath made him a liar, because he believeth not the record
that God gave of his Son.
And this is the record that God hath given to us eternal life, and this life is in his
Son.
He that hath the Son hath life, and he that hath not the Son of God hath not life.
These things have I written unto you that believe on the name of the Son of God, that
ye may know that ye have eternal life, and that ye may believe on the name of the Son
of God.'"
And so as you read verses 9 through 13, you find in these verses of Scripture that there's
this contrast between those who have believed or received the record and those who have
rejected the record.
And as we look at this passage of Scripture, we find that this here, as John is writing
to these believers, he says to them, this record has been delivered, but it demands
a response.
Again, I would make it broad to the entirety of the Word of God.
God's Word has been given, and God's record has been provided, and it demands a response.
Really there's only two responses.
We either receive it or we reject it.
Those are the two responses.
And let me say this, it's an all or none kind of a situation, amen?
It's not a situation where you say, well, I like this part of the record over here,
so I'm going to receive that part, and this part over here, you know, I don't really like
that part a whole lot.
It kind of, eh, I'm going to ignore that, I'm going to reject that.
No, that's not how it works.
It's all or none, all or none.
Most people would gladly receive the part of the record that says God so loved the world,
but they reject so many other parts of it.
And we find this morning that God has given us this record.
Yes, John is speaking about what he's writing specifically, but we can very easily make
the application to the whole of Scripture, and as we understand that we've been the gracious
recipients of this record that God has given, there's a response that is demanded.
And I want you to see, for those that receive it, notice what he says specifically here
in the text of Scripture, for those that receive this record, this witness.
In verse number 10, he says this, he that believeth on the Son of God hath the witness
in himself.
And that's a great result of receiving the record that's been delivered.
As I respond, this response is demanded, as I receive the record, as I believe what
God has given me as being truth, and I receive the Lord Jesus Christ as my Savior, the Bible
says he that believeth on the Son of God hath this witness, the witness, in himself.
Who was the witness?
Back in verse number 6, it says this, this is he that came by water and the blood, even
Jesus Christ, not by water only, but by water and blood, and it is the Spirit that beareth
witness because the Spirit is truth.
So I have, the Bible says this, I have the witness in himself.
Guess what happened when you got saved?
The Holy Spirit of God took up residence.
Isn't that awesome?
We can talk about the difference between the indwelling of the Spirit of God and the…
filling of the Spirit of God.
And we understand the moment of salvation,
the Holy Spirit of God indwells us.
I didn't understand all of it when I got saved,
and you probably didn't understand all of it
when you got saved either.
But the Spirit of God, the Bible tells us
that our bodies are the temple of the Spirit of God,
which is in you, which you have of God.
We've been redeemed.
The Bible tells us that the Spirit is the earnest
of our inheritance in Ephesians chapter number one.
This morning, as I begin to understand
one of the results that are mentioned
in this passage of Scripture,
of having received the witnesses,
that now we have the witness within ourselves.
You know, the Bible talks about His Spirit
bears witness with our spirit.
You know, as you read the Word of God,
as you listen to the preaching of the Word of God,
as you hear people say different things,
as you're walking with the Lord,
as you're receiving the witness that God's given,
the record that God's given,
there are times in which your spirit bears witness
with what you're hearing, right?
His Spirit bears witness with your spirit
that this is truth.
There are other times that you might hear something
and you may not fully understand what's being said.
There's some things, nuances, whatever,
and the Holy Spirit of God is just not bearing witness
with your spirit that there's truth there.
There's a problem.
There's something here.
And His Spirit now lives within us,
and His Spirit bears witness with our spirit.
I'm so thankful for the ministry of the Holy Spirit of God,
the Holy Ghost that indwells us.
He empowers us, but He, the Bible says this,
He will guide us or lead us into all truth.
What a joy.
Notice what it says for those that receive this record.
Again, the response is demanded.
It says in verse number 11,
and this is the record that God has given to us,
eternal life, and this life is in His Son.
Listen, eternal life is in no one else
but the Lord Jesus Christ.
That's why Peter stood up and said,
there's no other name under heaven given among men
whereby we must be saved.
It says in verse number 12,
he that hath the Son hath life.
He that hath the Son hath life.
If we receive, if we respond to this record
that's been given with receiving it,
the Bible says that we have the Son, we have life.
I'm so thankful to have not only this temporal life,
but to have the truth of eternal life.
I'm so thankful that in this temporal life
that God will give us abundant life,
as He says in John chapter number 10.
What a joy it is to have this life.
You know, there are so many people that are living today
that are walking around
and they really have no purpose for their life.
They don't know what their purpose is.
One of the questions that so many people desire
to have an answer to is what is the purpose?
What is the purpose of life?
Why are we here?
People begin to answer that question
with all sorts of theories and ideas
and the ideologies that permeate our society
would provide them with answers that are so far
from what God has said in His word.
You know what the purpose is for your life
and for my life as believers?
Is to glorify my Father, which is in heaven.
That is the singular purpose of my life.
Now, when we understand the singular purpose of my life,
there's a lot of digging into the Word of God
to find out how I bring glory to my Savior.
How do I live my life in such a way that God is glorified?
You know what the Bible says of Jesus?
He always did that which pleased His Father.
Wow, what a testimony.
What a testimony.
This morning, listen, I'm thankful
that I understand a purpose for my life,
but there was a time in my life
where I did not understand a purpose for my life.
There was a time in my life before I got saved
that I thought, and many of you can relate,
you understood this as well,
that the purpose of living, the purpose of life
was that I could go and I could make
as much as I could possibly make
and have as good as I could possibly have
from a human perspective.
That's what I thought life was all about.
But then God saved my soul
and helped me understand that there's something far greater.
What shall it profit a man
if he gained the whole world but loses his own soul?
Money doesn't satisfy.
Jesus always satisfies.
What's the blessing, the result of receiving?
Well, we have the Holy Spirit within us,
we have the witness in Himself, we have life.
But then notice verse number 13.
These things have I written unto you
that believe on the name of the Son of God.
And then notice this phrase,
that ye may know that ye have eternal life.
Throughout the study of the book of 1 John,
we've made reference of how many times
He uses the word know, to have knowledge of,
to have that assurance.
And this morning as we look at what He says here,
that ye may know that ye have eternal life
and that ye may believe on the name of the Son of God,
I'm so thankful to have the knowledge,
the confidence of eternal life.
I'm so thankful this morning
that He's given us this record,
the record's been delivered.
And as we respond to this record by receiving it,
then His Spirit bears witness with my spirit
that I am a child of God and I have that assurance.
He says, I'm writing these things unto you
that have believed that ye may know
that ye have eternal life.
What a tragedy for people to go through life
and not have any confidence of heaven.
How many times we've spoken to individuals in our lives
as we sought to share the gospel
and they say something like this,
well, I hope I'd go to heaven when I die.
I'm just not sure.
And they struggle.
In fact, you find that there are people
that even would go to church
and they struggle with their salvation.
They struggle with whether or not they're truly saved.
Listen, God wants you to know that you know,
that you know, that you know that you're saved.
The devil is the one that wants you to doubt.
I would say this, that it's a battleground
and in that battleground,
He has the ability to cause us,
render us ineffective
when we don't even know if we're saved ourselves.
Because if you don't know,
you're going to have a hard time talking to somebody else
about how they can know.
Make sense?
Notice what Peter said in 1 Peter 1,
and I'll reference what Jesus said.
In 1 Peter 1,
the Bible says this in verse 3,
Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ,
which according to His abundant mercy
hath begotten us again into a lively hope
by the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead.
Aren't you thankful to be saved?
Verse 4, to an inheritance incorruptible and undefiled
and that fadeth not away, reserved in heaven for you.
Now that sounds pretty sure, doesn't it?
And then it says this in verse number 5,
who are kept by the power of God
through faith unto salvation,
ready to be revealed in the last time.
I've said it many times over the years,
if it were up to me to keep my salvation,
I would have lost it shortly after I got it.
But I'm kept by the power of God.
Jesus said this in John chapter number 10,
my sheep hear my voice and I know them.
And He says this, they follow me
and I give unto them eternal life
and they shall never perish.
Neither shall any man pluck them out of my hand, He says.
And you think about being secure in the very hand of God
and what a blessing to know the assurance,
to have the confidence.
Listen, it's not a prideful thing for us to say,
I know I'm going to heaven when I die.
You know why it's not prideful?
Because if you take the record that God has given,
if you ask me this morning,
are you sure that when you die you're gonna go to heaven?
Absolutely, 100% confident that I'm going to heaven.
And it's not prideful because it has nothing to do with me.
Has everything to do with what Jesus Christ did for me
on the cross of Calvary,
His death, His burial and His glorious resurrection.
And I glory in my Savior.
Notice for those that reject it,
because their response is demanded.
Those that reject the record that has been delivered,
notice in verse number 10, what strong language.
The Bible says, he that believeth on the Son of God
hath the witness in himself.
He that believeth not God hath made him a liar,
because he believeth not the record
that God gave of His Son.
What an indictment, making God a liar.
Our God is not a liar.
He's not a man that He should lie, amen?
In fact, what a joy to think about the way
in which Paul says this in the book of Titus.
He says, in hope of eternal life,
which God that cannot lie promised before the world began.
Let God be true and every man a liar.
And this morning, we find that those that would reject
the message that's been delivered,
this report that's been delivered
and how grateful we are that God has given us a report,
that God has given us the word of God
and that response is demanded.
And for those that reject it, they are without hope.
They've made Him a liar,
but the Bible says also this in verse 12,
they have no life.
Notice what it says, he that hath the Son hath life.
And he that hath not the Son of God hath not life."
Hath not life.
Oh, they're living a temporal life.
To use the term that was used when...was instrumental in seeing my dad saved, there are a lot of
dead people that are waiting to die.
What in the world does that mean?
They're dead spiritually waiting to die a physical death.
And he says, they have not life.
Listen, understand this morning that when you trust that Christ is your Savior, He gave
you everlasting life at that moment.
It's the gift of God, eternal life, everlasting life.
And this morning, when we look at the record that God has given to us and we see that God
says here in this passage of Scripture, this record has been delivered, and we see that
it's reliable, that it's available.
I hope this morning that we would thank God that He's given us the record, that He's given
us the Word of God, that it is reliable, that it is available, that I have it and I hold
it in my hand.
And then as we begin to think about a response that is demanded, and again, understanding
that it's an all or none kind of a situation, that we would respond to the record that He's
given us and this response is demanded, that we'd respond by taking heed to all of it,
to all of it, that we would search the Scriptures as we've been commanded to do so, that we'd
be students of the Word of God, that we would prove what is acceptable unto the Lord, that
we would take the Word of God and we would dig in and we'd say, listen, I want my life
to please my Savior.
God's Word speaks so much more than just about salvation.
Now I'm so thankful that the message of redemption is the message of the Bible.
I'm so thankful that throughout the Word of God, it is the main focus of the Scriptures
of redemption and the plan of redemption as it's been referred to by William Scroggie,
great theologian of yesteryear.
He referred to the Bible as being the unfolding drama of redemption.
And I love that phraseology.
I love the way that he referred to the Bible that way because it is the unfolding drama
of redemption.
You read the Old Testament and how it prophesies of Messiah who would come and then you read
how Messiah comes and how He fulfills and all that He does and then how the church moves
forward on proclaiming the message of redemption.
And I'm thankful for salvation through Christ, but you understand that the Bible speaks a
whole lot about sanctification as well.
The put off and put on principles of the Word of God, the taking heed to the Word of
God.
And this morning, God's Word requires a response.
You say, well, I've trusted Him as my Savior.
I am so thankful.
If you're here this morning, if you're tuned in via live stream, you've never trusted the
Lord Jesus Christ, your personal Savior.
Today is the day of salvation.
The record's been given, a response is demanded.
But maybe this morning you say, well, I've trusted Him as my Savior.
And that's about as far as you've gone.
Can I tell you this morning that He has given you a whole Bible and desires that you would
take heed to all of it, to respond in obedience to it, to walk in holiness, to walk in obedience,
to be doers of the Word, not just picking and choosing various portions, not taking
and throwing away a whole segment of God's Word and saying, well, that's not really for
us today.
No, no, God's given us the entirety of the Bible, and He intends for us to know and to
prove what is acceptable unto the Lord so that we could bring honor and glory to our
Savior.
I'm so thankful that the witness of God is greater.
I'm so thankful He's given it.
It's available.
It's reliable.
This morning we need to not only take heed to it ourselves, but then we need to propagate
that truth.
There's a lost and dying world.
The Sunday school lesson this morning, the song service today, oh, how my heart was burdened
about that truth of, listen, I'm thankful that we have the Word of God.
We get to hear it so often, but what do we do with it?
What do we do with it?
I stood on the banks of the Sea of Galilee, and I also stood on the banks of the Dead
Sea.
What a great contrast between those two bodies of water.
The Dead Sea is much larger than the Sea of Galilee, much larger, but nothing can live
there, it's dead.
Ten times the salt and other mineral levels are in the Dead Sea than are found in any
other sea.
Ten times the amount.
So yeah, you can float in it.
I hope you'd learn a greater lesson than just floating in it.
I didn't float in it, I had no interest in that.
It's dead because there's no outlet.
The Jordan River feeds the Sea of Galilee.
There are three other tributaries that form into the Jordan that feed the Sea of Galilee.
And then out of the Sea of Galilee is the Jordan.
You know where the Jordan goes?
To the Dead Sea.
You know how much life is in the Sea of Galilee?
Holly and I stood there to take a picture.
We sent some pictures to you guys, and we stood there to take a picture, and you could
hear the fish jumping out of the water.
I'm serious.
No wonder they use those nets to catch fish, man, there's all kinds of fish.
There's life in abundance.
That same river goes to the Dead Sea, and it's dead because there's no outlet.
I don't want to be a Dead Sea Christian.
Amen?
God's given us so much.
We respond to it, we believe it, but then there's got to be an outlet.
There's got to be somebody that I'm sharing the truth with, that I'm trying to reach and
trying to...
Why?
Because the message that we have is a life-giving message.
Oh, what great opportunity God has given us.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
Thank You for loving us.
Thank You for the record that's been delivered.
As we think about a response that's demanded, I pray that we'd respond in belief and trust
and faith, not only for salvation but even for sanctification as we understand the importance
of living in obedience to Your Word, that we would follow Your steps, that we would
live and walk in holiness.
God, if there's someone that's not sure of heaven, whether they're here or tuned in via
live stream, I pray that today would be the day of their salvation.
I pray for every child of God, Lord, I pray that You'd help us to thank You for the record
that's been provided to us, the record delivered, that it is reliable and available.
Help us to rejoice greatly in that truth.
God, help us to receive it, all of it, and then help us to give it.
Help us to be faithful, to proclaim the truth of Your Word.
I pray, God, that You would move and work in these few moments as we've been ready to
receive and now, as we have opportunity to respond, I pray, God, that Your name would
be exalted in every decision that is made, that You'd be glorified and we'll thank You
for it.
In Christ's name we pray.
Would You stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed, and no one's looking around this morning.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano, and as she does, the altar's open.
Not sure of heaven, we'd love to take a Bible and show you how you can know for sure that
heaven's your home.
Maybe you want to come and thank God for the record, the Word of God that's been given.
Maybe this morning there's areas that you have not been obedient to.
You received portions of it, but not others, and you want to come and get that right with
the Lord.
Maybe this morning you want to make a commitment to God to share the truth with others.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.