The book of Psalms, if you will, this morning, Psalm 34.
We'll be looking at the 34th Psalm, and we'll be looking at several verses within the psalm.
Not the entirety of the psalm, but we will kind of bounce through the portion of Scripture
this morning.
And I have often said over the years that what we believe to be true will impact how
we behave.
What you believe will impact how you behave.
I believe that snakes, especially poisonous snakes, are dangerous.
So therefore, I stay away from them.
I don't need to find out by experience that their bite is going to hurt and possibly kill
me.
And we believe certain things.
I believe in gravity.
How many of you believe in gravity?
And there are reasons when you are off of the ground.
Why?
Because you believe in gravity, so it impacts your behavior.
And we understand that to be true in life experiences, but we find this morning that
what we believe to be true about God will impact how we behave.
I've often said this as well.
It's equally true that how we behave reveals what we really believe.
How you behave reveals what you believe.
In fact, there are times in life that we could say to someone, don't tell me what you
believe.
I'll just observe for a little while, and I'll be able to pretty much conclude what
you believe.
Why?
Because our behavior will reveal what we believe.
Throughout this year, 2023, we have examined the character and nature of our God, and we
wholeheartedly agree with the psalmist when he proclaims that great is the Lord.
We serve a great God.
He is the God that created all things.
He's the God that sustains all things.
He is my Redeemer, my Savior.
He's my friend.
He cares about me.
He loves me.
He is a great God.
He has all power.
He has all wisdom.
He's everywhere present.
And we've had the opportunity through 2023 to really consider and discover how great
our God is.
And I wholeheartedly agree with the psalmist when he says, I know that the Lord is great.
And I hope this morning, after sitting through so many messages this year, maybe this is
the first time you're with us this morning, we have some folks visiting with us.
And I hope that you know, though you have not heard all of the sermons that I've preached
this year, that you too know and agree that God is great.
We consider the greatness of God and we are in, obviously as we look at the scriptures,
we see it throughout the pages of scripture, God's greatness being revealed to us.
But as we've studied and we've been able to have the opportunity to understand in a greater
detail how great our God is, I believe that that belief should impact our behavior.
The reality is that how I live my life is greatly impacted by what I believe about God.
This morning, as we consider over the next several weeks, really throughout the end of
the year, we're going to consider how God's greatness should impact my behavior.
How does the truth that God is great impact how you live?
How does it impact how I live?
What we know to be true about God, does it impact how I live my life daily?
And how does it impact how we live our lives daily?
For the next couple of weeks, we're going to look at this truth and be aware of the
subject matter that is before us and understanding that God's greatness should have an impact
on how we pray, how we pray.
You know, prayer is a unique privilege for every child of God.
In fact, we've been invited, an invitation has been extended to us to come boldly before
the throne of grace.
We find that our Savior, the Lord Jesus Christ, he ever liveth to make intercession for us.
We find that there's one God and one mediator, the man Christ Jesus.
I'm thankful that I have direct access to the throne room of heaven, that at any time,
for any reason, I can enter into the presence of the almighty God and pray.
That is a unique privilege for every child of God.
I would say that oftentimes, if we're not careful, it is a neglected privilege.
Many of us, if we'd be honest this morning, that our prayer lives are lacking.
For many of us, if we'd be transparent this morning, we would say the area of my Christian
life that really needs the most work is my prayer life.
Prayer is work, prayer is labor.
There are, listen, Satan doesn't like it when you pray, he doesn't like it when I pray,
he attacks, but I believe this morning that when we truly understand the greatness of
our God, that it will impact how we pray.
I wonder this morning, I don't want you to answer me, I don't want you to even answer
me later if you really feel the need to, I'd be certainly willing to hear you, but
I'm curious this morning, if we're to think about our prayer lives, what is it that you're
praying about?
What is it that I'm praying about right now today that only God can do?
That only God can do?
Sometimes our prayer lives can just be so shallow, just so temporal, of various things
But I wonder this morning, how are we praying?
What is it that you're praying about?
What is it that I'm praying about that's something that only God can do?
In other words, when God does it, it's extremely obvious and it's certain that we would only
be able to give God the honor and glory because we'd look at it and say, God did that.
That's beyond anything that I could do.
It's beyond what any of us could do collectively.
God did it.
And I just wonder this morning, what are we praying about?
What are we, God talks about, prove me in the book of Malachi, contextually with regard
to giving, but he says, prove me.
Listen, we serve the almighty God and he's able to do wonderful things.
As we look at Psalm 34, there's a phrase that I've used for our title this morning, this
poor man cried.
This poor man cried.
As we look at the 34th Psalm this morning, I want you to see how that David's belief
about God impacted his prayer life.
What he believed to be true about God impacted his prayer life.
Notice with me in verse number one of Psalm 34, the Bible says, I will bless the Lord
at all times.
His praise shall continually be in my mouth.
My soul shall make her boast in the Lord.
The humble shall hear thereof and be glad.
Oh, magnify the Lord with me and let us exalt his name together.
I saw the Lord and he heard me and delivered me from all my fears.
They looked unto him and were lightened and their faces were not ashamed.
This poor man cried and the Lord heard him and saved him out of all his troubles.
The angel of the Lord encampeth round about them that fear him and delivereth them.
Notice verse eight, oh, taste and see that the Lord is good.
Blessed is the man that trusteth in him.
I hope this morning that you know that the Lord is good.
I hope you know that he is good no matter what the circumstances are that you're facing
in life.
God is good and he is a good God.
He's a gracious God.
He's a merciful God.
He's a great God.
And the Bible says, blessed is the man that trusteth in him.
God wants us to trust him, to believe him.
And as we look at this portion of scripture this morning, we consider this thought with
regard to what we believe about God will impact how we pray, will impact our prayer lives.
I want you to notice in the life of David in these few verses, if you're, I'm gonna
answer three questions this morning, obvious questions, but I hope to be a help to you.
Number one, if you're taking notes, to whom did David cry?
To whom did David cry?
Well, the Bible says in verse number one that he says, I will bless the Lord at all times.
And so we find that he blessed the Lord according to verse number one, he gives further explanation
that his praise shall continually be in my mouth.
Listen, I hope this morning that you live a life of praise.
I hope this morning that you understand that there are countless, I mean, just the number
of reasons that we have to praise our God.
He is worthy of our praise.
And here the Psalmist says, David says his praise shall continually be in my mouth.
And by the way, he'd rather hear your praise than complain.
Amen.
And by the way, he hears you when you complain and when you praise.
And you can look at that in the scriptures and find the Bible says the people complained
and the Lord heard them there in the Pentateuch.
And we find here that David is saying, I'm blessing the Lord.
Notice in verse number two, he says that he's boasting in the Lord.
My soul shall make her boast in the Lord.
The humble shall hear thereof and be glad.
I believe this is the idea of exalting and magnifying the Lord.
What a blessing to boast in the Lord.
Listen, a lot of people that want to boast about themselves.
They want to talk about how good they are and how wonderful they are and how blessed
we are to know them and to be in their presence and so on and so forth.
But I want you to understand this morning that we serve a great God and we ought to
be boasting in our God.
We ought to be talking about how wonderful our God is.
We ought to be exalting him.
The Bible says that John the Baptist said he must increase and I must decrease.
And we find that the psalmist is boasting in the Lord.
Number three, he's magnifying the Lord
and he even extends an invitation to others.
He says, oh, magnify the Lord with me
and let us exalt his name together.
There's something awesome about corporate worship.
There's something amazing about the opportunity.
Listen, every day of your life,
you have the privilege of being able to enter
personally, privately into the presence of God
to magnify and exalt his name.
But when we gather together as the saints of God
to corporately magnify the Lord together,
there's something mighty sweet about that.
There's something that's a blessing about corporate worship
and what a blessing that we have
to magnify the Lord together.
And David's saying to those,
come magnify the Lord with me.
Let us exalt his name together.
Notice in verse number four, the Bible says,
I sought the Lord.
Are you seeking the Lord?
Notice the Bible says, and he heard me.
We find that in verse number six,
it says this poor man cried and the Lord heard him.
So I believe that in verse number four
and again in verse number six,
when David says, I sought the Lord,
when David says this poor man cried,
that what he's referring to in verse number four
and verse number six is prayer.
Because in both instances, David says the Lord heard him.
And so he says, I sought the Lord and he heard me.
This poor man cried and the Lord heard him.
Listen, I'm so thankful for the Bible truth
that God hears us when we pray.
I'm so thankful that God has given us example
after example.
I think of Solomon when he prayed to dedicate the temple.
And after that long prayer that's recorded,
that God responds to Solomon and says,
I have heard thy prayer.
I'm thankful that God tells Jeremiah,
call unto me and I will answer thee
and show thee great and mighty things,
which thou knowest not.
The Bible speaks about, I love the Lord.
Why?
Because he heard me.
He hears my voice.
He hears my prayer.
What a blessing.
And when I asked the question, to whom did he, David, cry?
He cried to the Lord.
He's blessing the Lord.
He's boasting in the Lord.
He's magnifying the Lord.
He's seeking the Lord.
It says in verse number six, this poor man cried.
It does not say this poor man cried unto the Lord,
but I think it's abundantly obvious in verse number six
that he was crying unto the Lord.
He was seeking and praying to the God of the universe.
Listen, we must never forget this morning
that our prayer is directed to our living savior,
that our prayer is directed to the Lord.
If you notice in your Bibles this morning,
if you have a King James Bible,
the word Lord in each of these verses is all caps.
That's signifying that it's Jehovah God,
the self-existent one.
And we begin to think about to whom David is praying,
and we think about and we understand this morning
that he's praying to the creator of the universe.
He's praying to the one that created everything
out of nothing.
He's praying to the one that said,
let there be light, and there was light.
He's praying to the one that the Bible recounts
as his work of creation and seeing the stars
that he made the stars also,
that he made man in his own image.
And you begin to think about the power
that's displayed through creation,
the wisdom that's displayed through creation,
and David is praying to the Lord.
And this morning, you too are praying to the Lord.
I think about this morning as we understand
the almighty God, El Shaddai,
as he introduces himself to Abram there in Genesis 17.
He is the almighty, the omnipotent,
the omniscient, the omnipresent God.
He is the one who rules and reigns.
He is the one that conquered sin, death, and the grave.
He is the one that lives forevermore.
He says in the book of Revelation,
I was dead, but I'm alive forevermore.
I think about the truth that this morning,
when you pray and when I pray,
when I spent time this morning in prayer,
I wasn't praying to some idol.
I wasn't praying to some image.
I wasn't praying to some dead deity.
No, I was praying to the living God who hears me,
who's able to do exceeding abundantly
above all that I ask or think.
And what a blessing to know
that David directed his prayer to God.
This morning, to whom did he pray?
I'm thankful that the God of the universe,
the God who loves the world,
cares about you and me.
He's an individual God.
He knows your hurts.
He knows your concerns.
He knows your problems.
And he cares about you.
And he loves you in spite of all of that.
And this morning, when we think about David
in this text of scripture,
we find that he's seeking the Lord.
See, I believe as we continue to look
through this passage of scripture,
we could answer this question,
number two, if you're taking notes,
why did David cry unto the Lord?
We answer the question, to whom did David cry?
He cried unto the Lord.
But then we ask the question, why did he cry?
Why did David cry unto the Lord?
I think if we're not careful this morning
that our immediate answer
or maybe the obvious surface answer
would be that we would say
that David cried unto the Lord
because he had problems.
David cried unto the Lord because he had troubles.
But I would submit to you this morning
that if we were to dig deeper,
if we were to think deeper
and really examine what's taking place
and giving an answer to that question,
I believe this morning that we would say
that David, the reason that he cried unto the Lord
is because of what he understood to be true
about the Lord.
See, he sought the Lord
because he believed that the Lord heard him.
He prayed, he cried unto the Lord
because he believed that God could do something
about his situation, about his circumstances.
He cries unto the Lord,
not just because of his troubles,
not just because of his problems.
He directs his prayer to the Lord
because of what or who he understands God to be.
We mentioned already that on two occasions
in verse four and verse six,
the Bible says that the Lord heard him.
And again, what a blessing that is
and the encouragement that we receive
from understanding that David sought the Lord,
he cried unto the Lord, and the Lord heard him.
But as we begin to think and answer this question,
why did he cry unto the Lord?
And if we only give that surface answer
with regard to because he had a problem,
well, we understand even in our lives,
our daily lives, that we have problems.
We have issues.
And there are times that we have to call upon someone
to give us assistance.
Ms. Marjorie's dealing with a plumbing issue
and she did not call an auto mechanic
for a plumbing issue.
Why?
You say, Pastor, that's kind of basic.
We understand that.
Listen, when you have a plumbing issue, you call a plumber.
You have an electrical issue, you call an electrician.
Am I right?
Right, you have a problem.
You have a toothache, you got a problem,
you go to the foot doctor.
No.
You don't call the podiatrist
when you got a problem with a tooth.
Why?
Because they're not qualified.
You say, but they're a doctor, but they're not qualified.
That's not their area of expertise.
Do you understand?
Listen, we deal with this every day of our lives.
Sometimes if we're not careful as Christians,
we have problems in our lives when we call somebody,
we try to get help from some source,
maybe a brother or sister in Christ, whatever it might be,
but we try to get help, we need this help or that help,
but I'm telling you this morning
that God is the one that we should pray to
because we understand who he is.
David, in this area of his life,
in this time of difficulty and all that was taking place,
why did he cry unto the Lord?
Simply because he had a trouble?
No.
Because he knew who God was.
And this morning, what leads you and I,
what leads us in the time of our crisis,
in the time of difficulty to pray to God
is that we know who God is.
What is it that impacts your prayer life?
How is it that we have a prayer life this morning
that we spend time in prayer?
Well, because of what we understand to be true about God.
When I understand who God is,
when I understand what he is capable of doing,
that is what leads me to a place
of seeking God's face through prayer.
See, if I really don't know the God of the Bible,
then why would I pray to the God of the Bible?
If I don't know that he could do all things,
why am I going to ask him to do something
that's beyond what I could even believe?
This morning, David cried unto the Lord,
not simply because of his troubles,
not simply because of his problems,
he cried unto the Lord because he knew the Lord.
He knew who God was.
He knew the character and the nature of God.
This morning, begin to think about my prayer life,
begin to think about your prayer life,
begin to examine your prayer life,
and begin to take that examination,
say, how is my prayer life today?
Do I really, does my prayer life really demonstrate?
does it really reveal that I believe that God is able? Does my prayer life really reveal
that God is omniscient, that He's omnipotent? If I examine my prayer life, what does my
prayer life reveal about what I believe to be true about God?
The third question that we'll answer this morning and spend most of our time here is
this, if you're taking notes, number three, what was the result of his cry? What was the
result of his cry? Well, we find in verse number four the Bible says, I sought the Lord
and He heard me. Then notice the rest of verse number four, and delivered me from all my
fears. We live in the midst of a people that at times will use this terminology. I remember
years ago, and I'm getting older and older, and I'm realizing that as I interact with
people and some of the things that I would think that happened just a few years ago
actually took place a whole lot longer than what I might remember. But the reality is
there used to be this, I don't even know if the clothing line is even around anymore,
but there was this, I remember in high school, no fear. You'd have these shirts that would
say no fear. And you would have this. And the reality is that though we live in the
midst of a nation and a people that sometimes try to portray that idea, I'm not afraid
of anything. We have a lot of fears. You know people fear the future. People fear the uncertainties.
People fear death. There are a lot of people that fear death. It's a natural thing to fear
death unless you've been saved by the blood of the Lamb. According to Hebrews 2, He's
delivered us from that fear. Why? Because I know that to be absent from the body is
to be present with the Lord. I remember being afraid of dying before I got saved. What I'm
saying to you this morning is that there's a lot of people in our world that have a lot
of fears. There's a lot of fear in our society. And David, for whatever reason, and you can
look at various ideas as to when it was that David actually penned this psalm, and regardless
of the particular timing, it seems quite obvious, whether it's the exact timing, that
it definitely was during the time in which he was running from Saul. Remember Saul was
seeking to kill David. And Saul not only desired to kill David himself, but he tried to get
his servants to kill David. He tried to employ the mighty men that he had in his army to
kill David. And David's on the run and all these things are taking place. And David says
this at one point as he meets with Samuel. He says, there's but a step between me and
death. And you begin to think about the turmoil and the difficulties in which David was facing.
And we find that here, the Bible says in verse number four, one of the results of David crying
unto the Lord, seeking the Lord, is that he, the Lord, delivered me from all my fears.
How is that possible? Listen, I can't deliver you from your fears. You can have fears and
you can come to me and say, pastor, I need your help. But the reality this morning is
that I am not capable of delivering you from your fears. But I know the one who can. And
one of the names that's ascribed to our God is that he is the Prince of Peace. He's the
Prince of Peace. We find that he gives peace. We understand that the Bible speaks about
great peace, have they which love thy law. The Bible speaks about God keeping us in his
peace as we keep our minds stayed upon him. And he is the Lord Jehovah. We find that he
is the Prince of Peace and he gives his children peace. We're able to have in the midst of
turmoil and difficulty and all of the things that are taking place in our lives and our
world today, we can have peace. God can deliver you from those things that might bring fear
in your life. Why? Because he is the giver of peace. This morning we understand and we'll
look at two aspects of this. The Bible speaks about having peace with God. And I'll say
this from Romans chapter 5 and verse number 1, there's only one way to have peace with
God and that's through the Lord Jesus Christ. There are times in your life, no doubt, there
are times in my life that I've heard people say something like this when I've spoken to
them about eternity and about death and they'll say something like this, I've made my peace
with God. Have you ever heard somebody use that phraseology? And I'll say to them, well
based upon what the Bible teaches, there's only one way to make peace with God and that's
through Jesus Christ. Often in my life I have experienced as people have used that terminology,
that is not what they meant when they said they've made their peace with God. But I'm
thankful to have peace with God. I'm thankful that because of the Lord Jesus Christ and
his substitutionary atonement on a cruel cross nearly 2,000 years ago that he offers peace
through his blood and we can have peace with God. Listen, we were enemies of God. We were
at odds with God but he reconciled us, he redeemed us and we now have peace with God
if we've been born again. But there's also the peace of God. The peace of God is the
different than peace with God. The peace of God is something that you experience daily
in your lives. As you walk in the Spirit, the Bible says the fruit of the Spirit is
love, joy, peace. That's what the Bible teaches us. The fruit of the Spirit, love, joy, peace.
And he gives us peace. Jesus said this in the book of John, in John chapter number 14
and what a blessing to think about this portion of scripture and you know that as you start
John 14, Jesus, he'd given some instruction in chapter number 13. He gave him the new
commandment about loving one another as he loved and we find that he then, as he had
given him information with regard to the cross that was just on the horizon, he says, let
not your heart be troubled. Why would Jesus say that to the disciples? Because they had
troubled hearts. He says, let not your heart be troubled. You believe in God, believe also
in me. In my Father's house are many mansions, if it were not so I would have told you. I
go to prepare a place for you and if I go, I will come again. Aren't you thankful for
that wonderful promise? And receive you unto myself that where I am, there ye may be also.
And he gave us that promise and he gives them that truth of not being troubled. But then
in verse number 27 of John 14, notice what Jesus says. Jesus says this to these disciples.
He says, peace I leave with you. And then notice this, my peace. You know some of the
modern translations take out that word my. Listen, I'm thankful to have God's peace.
The world tries to offer peace. You know what the world thinks about peace? It's the absence
of trouble. The world seems to think that peace is the absence of conflict. Am I right?
That's the world's ideology of what peace is. If I can come to a place of being void
of trouble and problem and conflict, then and only then I will have peace. I disagree.
We can have peace in the midst of great turmoil because we can have the peace of God. And
here's what Jesus says, peace I leave with you. My peace I give unto you. Not as the
world giveth, give I unto you. Let not your heart be troubled. Notice what it says, let
neither let it be afraid. What is it that David said? He said, I sought the Lord and
the Lord heard me and he delivered me, what, from all my fears. And here we find that Jesus,
he says let not your heart be troubled, neither let it be afraid. Why? Because I'm giving
you my peace. We find that the Bible teaches us in the book of Colossians that we're to
let the peace of God rule in our hearts. And you think about that decision of allowing
God's peace to rule in our hearts, we get the idea of the word umpire from that particular
word in the Greek and the idea of ruling. And often, no doubt, you've watched sporting
events at some point in your life and when you watch those sporting events, there's some
people that are on the particular field or in the arena or on the court, whatever the
particular sporting event that you're watching, and there's somebody that is the authority,
somebody that has the rule on that particular event. Normally, they're dressed a little
bit differently. You see them with stripes sometimes. They're referees and I remember
playing baseball, that was my main sport, and we'd call the umpire blue because often
they wore blue and we'd refer to them in that fashion. And listen, it doesn't matter how
much you argue and how much you debate, the reality is that they are the authority. You
say, pastor, they can now challenge calls. I understand because they are not perfect,
but our God is perfect. And he gives us a peace that is perfect and he says that we're
to let God's peace rule in our hearts. You say, pastor, did you see the headlines? Did
you see what's going on? Did you see this? What are we going to do about that? And what
about this? Let the peace of God rule in your hearts. David said I sought the Lord and He
heard me and He delivered me from all my fears. If it's causing you to be afraid, if it's
causing you to be afraid, if it's causing you to be afraid, if it's causing you to
be afraid, if it's causing you to be afraid, then you're in trouble.
to be anxious. God offers you the peace, His peace. We need to get in time with God. We
need to pray and seek His face and know that He's able. Why did David seek the Lord? Because
he knew God. He knew who God was. He knows who He is. You and I this morning, why do
we seek God? Because we know who He is. And then we'd say because we have fears. And He's
the Prince of Peace and He will give us peace. Notice with me in verse number 6, the Bible
says this there in Psalm 34, in verse number 6, not only did He say in verse number 4,
I sought the Lord and He heard me and delivered me from all my fears. But notice also in verse
number 6, this poor man cried and the Lord heard him and saved him out of all his troubles.
Do you have any troubles this morning? You say, Pastor, I don't have enough time. Neither
do I. Amen. But the reality is that man that's born of woman is a few days and full of trouble.
We have troubles, difficulties. Paul says it this way, there's a great and effectual
door that was opened but there are many adversaries. The work of God has always met with adversity.
Why? Because we have an enemy. Because we have an enemy. You read the book of Ezra and
Nehemiah. They're trying to do a work for God and they're met with adversity over and
over. You read the early church in the book of Acts as the history is provided to us as
they're seeking to go and give the gospel, they're met with adversity. And so we find
that David here, because of the circumstances in which he's dealing with but greater because
of he knows who God is, he cries unto the Lord and the Bible tells us again that the
Lord heard him but it tells us the result of David crying unto the Lord was that the
Lord saved him out of all his troubles. You know we have troubles in our lives that only
God can deliver us from. That only God can save us from. I think about the disciples
when they're there in the storm and Jesus is going to walk by. There's a couple of
different instances. There's one when he's in the boat asleep but there's another one
when they're in a storm and he's going to walk by. And the Bible tells us this, it's
a fascinating terminology that they were toiling and rowing. I hope your mind can get the picture
of that. If you're, I mean as much as you can possibly try to go and you're not making
any progress because the storm was so great they just couldn't get to where they were
trying to get to. They were toiling and rowing. Have you ever been there in life? I mean maybe
not on a body of water in a vessel but in life you've been toiling and rowing. And I
believe that Jesus, I believe that he would have passed right on by if they didn't invite
him on the vessel. You know why I believe that? Because God doesn't force himself upon
you or upon me. If you want to toil and rowing, sometimes he'll let you. But I'd rather invite
him in and see what he can do. Because he can do greater than I can do. He can do greater
than you can do. Why does David call on the Lord in the midst of his trouble? Because
he knows that he's the Lord God Almighty. He knows what God is able to do. He's experienced.
Listen, David, he testifies when he stands before Saul long before he's ever running
from Saul. He testifies before Saul as to the greatness of God. David, you're not able
to go fight against Goliath. I mean you're but a youth and he's a man of war from his
days. David, you can't do this. And David said, my God will deliver him into my hand.
There was a time when I was watching the flock. You understand what David testified, right?
He knew Jehovah God. And so in the midst of his troubles he prays to God because he knows
who God is. And when he prays to God he says God heard him. And he says that God delivered
him, saved him out of all his troubles. Listen, this morning nothing's too hard for the Lord.
You say, pastor, I've got this problem. I mean it's just a mountain. It's not too hard
for God. It's not too hard for God. There's nothing impossible with God. I'm thankful
that he's able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think. I'm thankful
this morning that when he said that he's the Lord God Almighty, he then asked the question,
is anything too hard for the Lord? Listen, there are some things in your life and there
are some things in my life that are too hard for us. You might be in the midst and experience
something right now. You say, this is beyond me. This is beyond me. I can't do this. You're
right. But God can. He wants you to seek him. He wants you to believe him. And this
morning when we begin to think about the prayer life of David as outlined here in Psalm 34,
and as he says, I mean it starts with adoration and praise and rejoicing, but he's seeking
the Lord. He's crying unto the Lord and he gives us that wonderful truth that God heard
him and God delivered him. This morning, as we begin to think about this result for
David in his life and how he experienced the mighty hand of God, and again, we do not know
for certainty exactly the timing, but if you were to look through that portion of time
in David's life as it's recorded for us in the book of 1 Samuel, you have the opportunity
to see a number of times in which God delivered him miraculously. Where God intervened and
God did something that David could not orchestrate. See, sometimes in life we try to kind of orchestrate
some things. We try to manipulate some things. We try to help work some things together.
But the reality is it's pretty sweet to see what God can do. Because God can do what we
cannot do and there are times in life, listen, there are times that sometimes if we're not
careful, we try to help God out. We pray and we try to give God the solution. Have you
ever been guilty of that? Say, God, here's my problem and here's a good way that you
could solve it for me. Let him be God. He's God. He knows better than you do. Notice a
quick example in 1 Samuel 23 if you want to turn back there. Just one example of a miraculous
way in which God delivered David. Again, I don't know the exact timing of the writing
of Psalm 34. There's some debate out there with regard to when it actually took place,
but it seems quite obvious and there's a level of agreement that it was during the time in
which David was running from Saul. And 1 Samuel 23 is one of those instances. It begins
when David was in a place, the Keilah, where the Philistines went against Keilah and David
inquired of the Lord and sought the Lord with regard to going and delivering this particular
city from the attack of the Philistines and God tells him to do so. And after David is
there, Saul finds out that David is in that place and he has this idea that he now can
have an opportunity to catch and kill David because of where he was located. And David
begins to inquire of the Lord because David heard that Saul was going to come and that
was seeking to destroy him and David asked the Lord if Saul was going to come and God
said yes, Saul's going to come. And then David asked the Lord if the people, the inhabitants
of Keilah, the men that he just delivered from the Philistines, if they would deliver
him to Saul and God says yes, they will. Can you imagine that? The people that you
just rescued are going to turn you over to the one that wants to kill you. That's what's
happening in the beginning of 1 Samuel 23. David, he leaves and he's going out in the
wilderness, the wilderness of Ziph and he's there and we find that Saul makes this statement
at the end of verse 23, that I will search him out throughout all the thousands of Judah.
In verse 25 it says that his men, Saul also and his men went out to seek David, to seek
him. We find that they're maneuvering for position if you will. In verse 26 the Bible
says that Saul went on this side of the mountain and David and his men on that side of the
mountain and David made haste to get away for fear of Saul. What did God deliver David
from according to verse number 4 of our text? All of his what? Fears. Verse number 6, all
of his troubles. And it says here in verse number 6 of our text of scripture in 1 Samuel
23 that David made haste to get away for fear of Saul. For Saul, notice the end of verse
26, and his men compassed David and his men round about to take them. I mean he's surrounded,
he's in a bad situation. He's afraid. Again, I don't know with certainty that this is where
the prayer of Psalm 34 came from, but it certainly fits. The Bible says in verse 27, but there
came a messenger. There came a messenger unto Saul. You see what's happening before this
messenger comes? What's David, David's running? What's Saul's purpose? I'm going to destroy
him, I'm going to kill him. He's not going to surround him. And a messenger comes. A
messenger comes. And the Bible says in verse 27, the messenger came to Saul saying, notice
what the messenger says, haste thee and come.
For the Philistines have invaded the land."
Who's Saul?
Well, he's the king.
He's got a responsibility.
And the Philistines have invaded the land.
Why?
Because Saul's out there hunting David, trying to kill David.
And the messenger comes.
As David and his men are surrounded, the messenger arrives.
And the Bible says the messenger says, haste thee.
I mean, there's no time to waste.
The Philistines have already invaded the land.
I would submit to you that this happened well in advance of the messenger arriving.
They had time to travel and what have you, and news did not spread like it does today.
And there had to be some time that passed.
And the Bible says in verse 28, wherefore, notice what the Bible says, Saul returned
from pursuing after David.
And I tell you this morning that David could not have brought that to pass.
Only God could do that.
And God worked in such a way in David's life.
Why?
Because David prayed.
David sought the Lord.
David cried unto the Lord.
Again, whether this timing is exactly the timing of Psalm 34 is not the point that
I'm seeking to make this morning.
I'm simply saying to you this morning that David understood that God is able, that David
understood that God could work beyond what he could even imagine.
God could use a messenger because the Philistines invaded the land to have Saul return from
pursuing after him.
We serve a great God who's able to do all things.
How does it impact our prayer life?
How does it impact us?
Do we pray like we serve an omnipotent God?
Do we pray like we serve an omniscient God?
How does what we believe about God impact our prayer lives?
I want to close with a wonderful truth from Psalm 34.
As we examine the life of David in these first several verses of Psalm 34, the amazing thing
to me and the application that I want us to walk away with this morning is that David
is sharing in the beginning of this portion of Scripture of Psalm 34 his personal experience.
He says, I sought the Lord.
He says, this poor man cried.
He's speaking about his personal experience that I sought the Lord, I cried unto the Lord
and God heard me and God delivered me.
He's giving a personal testimony.
He's testifying of his personal experience.
But I want you to take and look at verse 17 because in verse number 17, the Bible says
the righteous cry.
Who's the righteous?
Well, if you've been born again this morning, we sang a lot about being saved this morning.
If you've been born again this morning, you are righteous before God.
You are declared righteous.
In fact, it's not your righteousness, it's his righteousness that's been imputed upon
you.
The Bible tells us in 2 Corinthians chapter number 5 that he, God, hath made him Jesus
to be sin for us who knew no sin that we might be made the righteousness of God in
him.
What a blessing to be declared righteous.
The Bible says that the righteous cry and notice the Lord heareth them, but it doesn't
stop there, and delivereth them out of all their troubles.
Did you see it this morning in verse 17?
I mean, listen, I'm thankful for David's personal testimony.
I'm thankful for David's personal experience that he says, I sought the Lord, that he says,
this poor man cried and the Lord heard him and the Lord delivered him, listen, from all
of his fears, from all of his troubles.
Praise God.
But he says, the righteous cry, the righteous cry, and the Lord heareth them and delivereth
them, the righteous, out of all their troubles.
Listen, this morning, we can rejoice in what God did in the life of David, but we must
recognize that we serve the same God.
The Lord God omnipotent, the one who's able.
You say, but I got a problem.
I know the problem solver, if I could use that terminology this morning, with all reverence.
This morning, I understand we have troubles, I understand we have fears, we have difficulties,
but we serve the Lord God Almighty and he's able.
And what you believe to be true about God and what I believe to be true about God must
have an impact on my prayer life.
And I would submit to you as I started my way of introduction this morning, as I've
said so many times over the years, what you believe to be true impacts your behavior.
But it's equally true that your behavior reveals what you believe to be true.
I wonder this morning, if we were to honestly evaluate our prayer lives, would it reveal
that we believe that God is great?
Are we praying for the impossible?
I mean from a human perspective.
They're just too far gone.
Do you know the Savior?
Do you know what he's capable of doing?
Do you know his grace?
Do you know his mercy?
Listen, I'm thankful that he's long-suffering.
And by the way, you're thankful he's long-suffering when he's dealing with you as well.
Amen?
Listen, this morning we serve a great God.
We've dealt with it all year, great is the Lord and greatly to be praised.
But the impact that God's greatness has in our lives should be evidenced in our prayer
lives.
We're going to look at two more examples over the next couple of weeks of how the greatness
of God will impact our prayer lives.
And we're going to stick on this subject for a few weeks.
Why?
Because it's so necessary.
Listen, our God, the hand of God moves through the prayers of his people.
J. Sidlow Baxter made this statement about the prayers of man, and he said, listen, men,
they may spurn our appeal, they may refuse our words, but they're entirely hopeless against
our prayers.
I shared with you a testimony on Wednesday evening a couple of weeks ago about a man,
and I'll be generic because we're on live stream, I shared it during prayer time on
Wednesday evening about a man that for multiple times said, don't pray for me.
But the reality was that he really knew that the prayers that we were praying were having
an impact.
And quite honestly, he didn't like it, so he just wanted us to stop praying because
God was convicting him.
He needed to be saved.
That man's trust in Christ as a savior called me three weeks ago and said, pastor, will
you pray for me?
He's not here today, he hasn't been here in a while.
Would you pray for me?
What changed?
He's been saved and he knows the power of prayer.
Listen, we serve a God who hears and answers prayer.
And what we believe to be true will impact our behavior.
What is your prayer life?
What does my prayer life reveal about what we believe to be true about God?
David's prayer life revealed that he knew God was able.
He knew God was the Prince of Peace, that He could give him peace with all those fears.
He knew that God was able to do what he could not do.
This morning I'm so thankful that we serve a God who hears and answers prayer.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the privilege of prayer.
So often, I've admitted from this pulpit that it's easier to preach and talk about
prayer than it is to actually pray.
God I pray that we'd be people of the book, but I pray that we'd be people of prayer.
God I pray that our prayer lives would truly reveal what we believe to be true about you.
We've studied so many things.
We agree with the psalmist when he said, I know the Lord is great.
That truth of your greatness must impact our behavior, must impact how we pray.
Lord I pray that we truly examine ourselves, examine our prayer lives.
I pray that you'd guide us and direct us, Lord, help us to be men and women of prayer.
I believe it was the Queen of Scotland that feared more than any army the prayers of John Knox.
What a testimony.
God, I pray that we'd be people of prayer.
Would you move and work?
If there's one that's not saved, Lord, we'd love to take a Bible and show them how they
can know for sure that heaven is their home.
Lord, help us to do business with you this morning in these few moments of invitation.
Well, thank you for every decision that's made, for it's in Christ's name we pray.