We're not going to quite start there, but this is the principle in which I'm hoping
to encourage us with this evening.
In 1 Peter 5 and verse number 7, the Bible says, casting all your care upon him for he
careth for you.
And keep that in mind, that will be the content of the message this evening.
But before we get there, I want you to look at a truth in Luke chapter number 10, Luke
chapter number 10, and we'll also look at a principle over in the book of Philippians.
And I want you to look at this example in Luke chapter number 10 in the life and ministry
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And as the Lord is ministering, the Bible tells us here about an account, particular
day, an event that took place.
It says in verse number 38 of Luke 10, now it came to pass as they went that he entered
into a certain village and a certain woman named Martha received him into her house.
And she had a sister called Mary, which also sat at Jesus's feet and heard his word.
But Martha was cumbered about much serving and came to him and said, Lord, does thou
not care that my sister hath left me to serve alone?
Bid her therefore that she helped me.
Notice verse number 41, Jesus answered and said unto her, Martha, Martha, thou art careful
and troubled about many things, but one thing is needful.
And Mary hath chosen that good part, which shall not be taken away from her.
And I can deal with the entirety of this interaction that takes place here with Mary and Martha.
It's an account that we're somewhat familiar with, but I want you to notice what Jesus
said to Martha, Martha, Martha, thou art careful and troubled about many things.
And this word careful that is used here in Luke chapter number 10 and verse number 41,
it means to be anxious, to be troubled.
And we see that she of course was cumbered about with much serving according to verse
number 40, but she was careful and troubled about many things.
Now, keep that thought in that example of Martha, and then look at a truth in the book
of Philippians and chapter number four, and I want you to see the instruction that the
apostle Paul gives to the believers in Philippi.
And we understand, and many of us can identify perhaps with Martha this evening when Jesus
says that Martha, Martha, thou art careful and troubled about many things.
And there are times in our lives that we are careful, we are anxious and troubled about
many things.
Notice in Philippians chapter number four, in verse number four, the apostle Paul says
to the believers at Philippi, rejoice in the Lord always, and again I say rejoice.
Let your moderation be made known unto all men, the Lord is at hand.
Notice this in verse number six, be careful for nothing.
And that phrase is the title for the message this evening, be careful for nothing.
It's the same word that was used there when Jesus said to Martha in Luke chapter number
10 in verse number 41, Martha, Martha, thou art careful and troubled about many things.
And now Paul says to the believers at Philippi, be careful for nothing, be anxious or troubled
for nothing.
The reality is that the particular day and age in which we're living, we find that there
are many that are full of care, that are anxious and dealing with fear and anxiety
and all sorts of things.
And we see this very visible during this particular time of the pandemic, but the reality is that
this is something that has been ongoing for a long period of time.
People are troubled, they're careful, they're anxious.
And we find here that for God's people, we're not to be careful for all of these things.
We're not to have this anxiety and to be troubled.
We find that we've been given this instruction, be careful for nothing.
We many times could use the word worry and deal with it within this context of worrying
about things.
And the reality is that we have this truth.
The apostle Paul didn't just say, be careful for nothing and then move on to the next principle.
But notice why it is that we can be careful for nothing, why it is that we can avoid worrying.
The Bible says, but in everything by prayer and supplication with thanksgiving, let your
requests be made known unto God.
I want you to think about that truth in verse number six of Philippians four.
And really, if you're with us this morning, keep it in context, even with the message
that we dealt with this morning, that there was a recognition of that woman.
For that distraught, that troubled mother, she was in despair and she was desperate over
the situation with her daughter.
The daughter was grievously vexed with a devil.
And the Bible, or as we looked at that message and the Bible gave us the example of that
woman and the interaction with the Lord Jesus Christ, we find that she went to Jesus and
she made a request.
And we saw the reality of the fact that what she recognized about who God is and who the
Lord Jesus Christ is, that she then made this request.
Well notice what it says here, be careful for nothing, but in everything by prayer and
supplication with thanksgiving notice, let your requests be made known unto God.
So instead of being full of care, instead of having anxiety and being troubled, instead
of worrying about the situation, we as the people of God have the privilege of prayer.
We can go to God.
By the way, the amount of time that we would spend praying and seeking the face of God
about the situation that may cause us to be troubled and anxious, is far better spent
in prayer than in worry.
Someone said that worry is like a rocking chair, it'll keep you busy but won't get
you anywhere.
And the reality is that we have the privilege of going to God in prayer and understanding
several things about who God is, the one to whom we're praying to, the fact that he is
the Lord God Almighty, the Lord God Omnipotent, the fact that he rules and he reigns, that
he's eternal, that he's Alpha and Omega, that he knows the end from the beginning,
that he's able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think.
And so I have the opportunity, the privilege to go to God, understanding who he is and
what he's capable of doing and bringing my request unto him or I could worry about it.
Or I could worry, I could be careful.
And Paul says, be careful for nothing.
But in everything, by prayer and supplication with thanksgiving, let your request be made
known unto God.
Notice verse number 7 of Philippians 4, and the peace of God which passeth all understanding
shall keep your hearts and minds through Christ Jesus.
There's never a thing that I spend worrying about that results in peace.
Just more anxiety.
If you'd be honest, if there's something that you worry about, worrying about it doesn't
bring you any level of peace, of any calmness.
In fact, worrying about it tends to cause more problems.
Worrying, anxiety, being careful is not good for your health.
I mean, we can look at it from a medical perspective, I'm not a doctor so I'm not going to deal
with all of that, but there are some adverse physical things that happen when we're full
of care and worry.
And when we understand what Paul is saying to the believers here in Philippi, and we
begin to really take and apply these truths to our own lives, and understand that, listen,
I'm not going to worry about this thing, I'm going to go to God in prayer about this thing,
knowing that He's able to do something about it, and my worrying isn't going to change
it one bit, and then after I've spent that season in prayer, I've labored in prayer,
I've sought the face of God, not only with prayer and supplication, but with thanksgiving,
that even at the moment of making my request, I can thank Him for knowing that He will work
exactly as He knows best.
He may not work according to what I think should be done, but we can rest in the truth
that He will do what's right.
And then, I can have the peace of God.
You say, but does it mean that that thing is removed?
Not necessarily.
In fact, the storm could still be very much raging.
The trouble and the trial and the circumstances could be worse than they've ever been, but
we can have the peace of God.
Why?
Because He is the God of peace.
Because He's the Prince of peace.
And He said there in John, think about this truth in John chapter number 14, when He spoke
these words to the disciples.
He said, peace I leave with you.
My peace I give unto you, not as the world giveth, give I unto you.
Let not your heart be troubled, neither let it be afraid.
He says, you have heard how I said unto you,
I go away and come again unto you.
If you loved me, you would rejoice
because I said I go unto the Father,
for my Father is greater than I.
We understand that our Savior,
He has overcome the world and what a joy that is.
And it can bring peace in our hearts and our lives.
See, the truth that we find in Philippians,
we saw it illustrated there with Martha
during the earthly ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ
when she's cumbered about with much serving
and she says, Master, aren't you gonna tell Mary
to come and help me?
And he says, Martha, Martha,
thou art careful in trouble for many things.
One thing is needful and he refers to Mary
being in that position of worship and at the feet of Jesus.
And here we find that Paul is giving this instruction
to the believers that Philippi, of course,
preserved for us this evening
that we're to be careful for nothing.
See, if it just stopped there,
we might not know how can I do that?
How can I be careful for nothing?
Well, then I begin to look at what I just shared with you
at the rest of verse number six and verse number seven,
and it helps me come to that place.
In fact, the same word here in Philippians four
and verse number six is the same word
that we saw there in Luke 10 and verse number 41.
And now go over, if you will,
to 1 Peter chapter number five.
In 1 Peter chapter number five and verse number seven
gives us this great truth.
And I hope that I can package it for you this evening,
that it makes sense as we look here at the situation.
Listen, many of us can identify with Martha.
There are times in our lives, if we'd be honest,
that we have been careful for many things.
We've worried, we've had anxiety,
we've been troubled and anxious over the events
and the circumstances,
and we find that there's a truth
that is given to the book of Philippians
with regard to being careful for nothing
and how we are to pray and seek the face of God
and then have that peace that passeth all understanding.
But notice what Peter tells us in 1 Peter five
and verse number seven.
The Bible says, casting all, how much?
All your care upon him,
for he careth for you.
It's interesting as we look at this word here, care,
it is not the same Greek word
that is used in Luke and in Philippians.
That Greek word is careful,
but we find that this word care is the root word
for the word that we find in Luke and in Philippians.
And so we see there's the similarity there.
We understand that he's speaking about the same thing
of that worry of that being troubled
and being anxious.
And here we find that Peter says,
casting all your care upon him,
for he careth for you.
And the thing that is interesting
about this verse of Scripture,
it's a simple verse of Scripture.
You can memorize it quite easily,
but to live it is quite the difficult thing.
The word casting means to throw upon or to place upon.
I mean, can you get in your mind's eye
this choosing of words
and we understand that every word of God is pure
and we understand that all Scripture
is given by inspiration of God.
And as Peter is giving this message,
he says casting, literally to throw upon
or to place upon, casting all.
All is an interesting word.
It's a simple word.
I had a professor in Bible college
that often would say all means all
and that's all that all means.
And it means each, every, any, all, the whole,
all things, everything.
I mean, it's an inclusive word.
And we find that he says casting all your care.
Those things that you're caring about,
the ones that belong to you,
those items that would bring you a level of worry
and anxiety in your life,
the things that you are caring upon
that are taking your attention,
it says casting all your care upon him
who's he talking about?
Talking about God.
Remember, what did Paul say back in Philippians four,
be careful for nothing but in everything
by prayer and supplication with thanksgiving,
let your requests be made known unto God, right?
And we seek the face of God
and we understand that he is able
and we find that he then says in the peace of God,
which passes all understanding.
And so we find here that the truth from Peter
to the believers is to cast all your care upon him.
Now, I want you to understand
as we begin to look at this verse
in first Peter chapter five and verse number seven,
that these individuals that he is writing to,
the believers in the first century
that Peter is ministering to,
these are individuals that are dealing
with great levels of hardship.
These are individuals that are dealing
with the persecution under Nero
and they're dealing with all sorts of difficulties.
And we find that Peter tells them this
in first Peter one in verse number six,
wherein ye greatly rejoice though now for a season,
if need be you are in heaviness
through manifold temptations,
that the trial of your faith being much more precious
than of gold that perisheth,
though it be tried with fire
might be found unto praise and honor and glory
at the appearing of Jesus Christ,
whom having not seen you love
and whom though now you see him not yet believing
you rejoice with joy unspeakable and full of glory,
receiving the end of your faith,
even the salvation of your souls.
We find that as we would look here
at the folks that Peter is writing to,
he would tell them in chapter number four
in verse number 12,
beloved, think it not strange concerning the fiery trial,
which is to try you
as though some strange thing happened unto you.
See, the reality is these believers in the first century,
they were facing some serious situations.
They were facing things
that we cannot even begin to relate to.
In fact, as we read much of church history,
as we read the church history
that is contained in the Bible of the first century,
we read others that have written of church history
throughout the centuries
and we can begin to remember
and to see what our brothers and sisters
have endured and suffered throughout the centuries,
we find that many times
the things that we endure pale in comparison.
And to these people that Peter says,
though you're being tried,
though you're in this fiery trial,
casting all your care upon Him.
Why?
Why the instruction, Peter?
Why would you tell us to cast all of our care?
The reality is that it seems obvious
if you're telling somebody to cast your care
that we carry cares, right?
It's a human thing.
It's natural for us as human beings
to have this Martha syndrome
of being careful and troubled about many things
and having that worry and that anxiety.
There are some people that just in their DNA,
like just nothing seems to affect them.
I mean, they just go through life
and it just seems like, what is up with this person?
Like, it just seems like they have this
just island mentality all of the time,
like nothing ever, there's no urgency,
there's no care.
And then there's others that just seem like
it's in our DNA to just want to care about everything
and worry about every little detail.
You may fall somewhere in the middle,
but the reality is that we can understand
when this instruction is given,
casting all your care upon Him.
We have at times in our lives,
and for some of us more often than others,
we have that Martha syndrome
of being careful and troubled for many things.
What do we do?
How do we deal with it?
Well, we take what Paul says,
we take what Peter says,
we follow the instruction.
He says, casting all your care upon Him,
notice this wonderful promise.
We sang tonight,
standing on the promises to start our service.
And I mean, there are so many promises in the Word of God.
I mentioned already that it's Peter
that makes that statement that we have.
He actually says it in second Peter one in verse number four
whereby are given unto us
exceeding great and precious promises.
And it's amazing to me.
And actually, as you study first and second Peter
and see the way in which he uses the word precious,
you see this old fisherman that's using the word precious.
And he looks at these promises,
obviously we understand inspiration of the Bible,
but he uses this expression
to speak about the promises of God
being exceeding great and precious.
Notice this one here,
for He, God, careth for you.
He careth for you.
Now, the thing that's interesting,
as we look at the Bible,
as we look at our own lives,
is that God's interested in the individual.
I mentioned this morning by way of introduction,
we're looking at the gospel account there in Matthew
and Mark also gave us a record
of that particular interaction between that trouble.
mother and the Lord Jesus Christ that oftentimes throughout the Gospels we
have these opportunities to read through Matthew Mark Luke and John and to read
about the life and ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ and as we read about the
life and ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ there are times in which we see
him ministering to the multitudes right the multitudes are gathered in the
feeding of the 5,000 and the feeding of the 4,000 and there are times in which we
see the Lord Jesus Christ ministering amongst the multitudes the fact of the
matter is that the woman that had the issue of blood for 12 years I mean she
came through she wanted to just touch the hem of his garment he said who
touched me and the disciples are like I mean you're thronged with people what do
you mean who touched you we see him ministering to the multitudes we see the
Lord Jesus Christ and the interactions as I mentioned this morning with the
religious crowd describes the Pharisees the Sadducees the religious leaders of
the day and we see those interactions but oh how precious it is when we see
him interacting with the individual the individual I think about the times in
which you look at the gospel accounts and you see in John chapter number four
when he said I must needs go through Samaria right we speak of John 4 with
the woman at the well and you look at the particulars of that passage of
Scripture and really it would have been very unnatural for them to go through
Samaria in fact during that particular era Jews would go out of their way to
bypass they would be inconvenienced so they would not go through Samaria and we
find that Jesus says I must go through Samaria I must needs go to Samaria and
he goes and there's this woman at the well we find the disciples leave
remember he was they needed water and they needed food and they went to go get
some things and during that time he's interacting with whom an individual the
woman at the well we could see how that the maniac of Gadara and you look at the
fact of the Scriptures and if you follow the timeline of the life and ministry of
the Lord Jesus Christ they get on the ship and they go over and they come into
the coast of Gadara and there's that one man that maniac and we find that Jesus
ministers and this man that was naked and outside of his mind that was
possessed of demons because of the interaction that he had with the Lord
Jesus Christ he's made whole and you know right after that maniac is healed
and saved and then sitting at the feet of Jesus you know what they do they get
on the boat they leave for one the maniac of Gadara and we could go on this
this evening and we could look at a number of examples of dealing with the
the fact that Jesus is concerned for the individual and when I look at this verse
of Scripture and I find this truth casting all your care upon him for he
careth for you and I understand you being singular and plural at the same
time he careth for all of us collectively as his people but he cares
for me individual or individually as an individual and to understand that the
God of the universe that he cares about me that he is interested in my life
personally that he loves me personally I shared with the the family just last
week during our devotions and I've shared with you what we've been doing
with our family devotions in recent months and how that we've been selecting
an individual each day I'm pulling a name from a cup and that person gets to
read our devotional but also share some things from their own personal daily
devotions that day it's been so good and so rich and just precious and just
a few weeks ago I don't know maybe a week and a half ago actually my name was
pulled from the the cup and on that particular day I had read much of the
book of John in my own personal devotions and a truth that stood out for
me from John chapter 11 was a truth that I've known but just the way that the
truth hit me from the passage of Scripture there's many wonderful truths
that God gives us in John 11 with regard to his plan and so on and so forth but
we find the Bible when we think about the fact that God loves us as
individuals you know it's interesting when Lazarus was sick there in John
chapter 11 when his sister sent those servants you know what they said to the
Lord behold he whom thou lovest is sick he whom thou lovest is sick we find that
on several occasions here in John chapter 11 that the truth is revealed to
us with regard to the love that Jesus had for an individual for God so loved
the world we understand that truth and we rejoice in that truth but then when
we narrow it right in and say that means me individually and we find that
Peter says casting all your care upon him for he careth for you you know that
God wants you to cast your care upon him he does he doesn't want us to carry it I
think about this in the context of many things and we could look at the truth in
Matthew chapter 5 as Jesus is speaking there and giving the sermon sorry
Matthew chapter 6 the sermon on them out and as he's talking to them about not
being concerned about the things that they would eat or drink and so on and so
forth and the fact that they're to seek first the kingdom of God you know I I
don't want my kids to worry about how the food is going to be on the table or
how this is going to happen as a parent you don't want your children being
careful worrying about those things God is our Heavenly Father he doesn't want
us worried about the things of this world he wants us casting throwing down
placing upon he wants us to cast all of our care upon him why because he cares
for us he careth for you as an individual see sometimes in our lives we
suffer with the Martha syndrome we see it in Luke 10 in verse 41 we started
there this evening sometimes we suffer with that thing and we deal with that
we are careful troubled about many things oftentimes there are things that
we could never change way beyond our ability but even if there were things
that we could change we're not supposed to be careful about it we're not we're
supposed to worry about them and we take the instruction of Paul and of Peter and
we say to you this evening casting all your care upon him for he careth for you
what a great promise to know that God cares about you he cares about me and he
wants you to cast your care upon him what are you anxious about what are you
worried about would you spend that time in prayer instead of worrying about
instead of taking the time to worry and fret over it just spend that time in
prayer he's able to do something about it let your request be made known unto
God and then we can have the result that peace of God which passeth all
understanding worry has never produced peace in my life it just hasn't when I
was a kid my mom used to tell me I was a worrywart do you remember that yeah
that's why Brianna got that passed down amen and she's saying thanks thanks dad
throwing me right under the bus but when I was a kid my mom used to tell me all
the time I was a worrywart and I'd worry about things I don't even know why I'd
worry about things I'd worry about worrying about something and then after
you and I'm not saying that I've conquered it completely but man when you
get in the truth of the Word of God and you say this isn't something I have to
be careful about I don't have to worry about it it doesn't mean I don't care
about what happens just means I'm not gonna worry about it I'm not gonna be
full of that care anxiety and trouble why because I'm gonna go to God and let
him take care of it and let him deal with it I'm gonna cast physically that
process of casting all our care upon him now here's the here's the real catch
don't take it back right once you cast it upon him and you say I'm gonna I'm
gonna leave this with the Lord leave it there right don't leave from that place
of prayer and go ahead and take all those cares back with you no leave it
there let God work let God do what God can do casting all your care upon him
Paul said be careful for nothing father we love you we thank you for loving us
we thank you for the privilege of being able to gather together this evening
thank you for just the the truth of your word and I know that many of us can
relate to this Martha syndrome as we've kind of called it this evening there
are times in our lives we'd be honest that we are full of care we worry we are
troubled we have anger
anxiety, anxiousness.
Lord, would you help us
to follow the admonition of Scripture?
Would you help us to experience Your grace in this area?
Help us to recognize
that You care about us,
that You love us
as an individual.
We know that there are over 7 billion people
in the world today.
You are the Almighty God.
You care about us as individuals.
We can bring and cast our care upon You.
Would You help us, Lord,
to have the peace of God
which passeth all understanding?
We'll thank You for the work that You do in our hearts.
It's in Christ's name we pray,
Amen.