I'm thankful to have dual citizenship though. My citizenship is in heaven as well
Amen, and I am a pilgrim and a stranger in this land
And if you're saved you are as well and we are heaven-bound and what glory
That is but as far as our earthly citizenship, I am thankful to be an American
I am thankful for the freedoms that we enjoy but I want you to understand this morning that our freedoms are under attack
And I want you to understand this morning that there are many people even as we think about today and this weekend Memorial Day weekend
I had prepared this message early in the week Monday Tuesday
had finished up preparations for the message this morning due to knowing that the move was going to be at the end of the week and
All of that and I have in my notes. I wrote out on Tuesday
About the way in which many people in our society today. Look at this weekend this
Day as being nothing more than a long weekend as being nothing more
Than a day off a bank holiday if you will and in fact yesterday
The vice president of the United States of America said enjoy your long weekend and made no reference whatsoever
To Memorial Day now after a lot of backlash. She corrected it this morning
I'll give her credit for that and she sent out another tweet this morning thanking those that gave the ultimate
Sacrifice of their lives for our freedom
But just about 20 miles from here or less than 20 miles in Georgetown area of DC
There was a fake petition going around this weekend to cancel Memorial Day
The reason that was cited is that it only celebrated American imperialism and
Then there were some that when they were asked if they wanted to sign the fake petition they said well
No, I still want my day off
Look it up it this happened. I
Had this stuff in my notes and then I saw some news feeds and I'm like man. I mean this what's going on
I am thankful for those
That gave the ultimate sacrifice
for us to enjoy the freedom to assemble
The freedoms that we have been afforded and I'm so I listen America's not perfect
There's no church. That's perfect. There's no individual. That's perfect
I'm thankful that God and all of his perfection had a perfect plan to redeem mankind
And in that perfect plan he sent his son God in the flesh
To die on the cross of Calvary to pay for your sin and my sin and the sin of the world
He was buried in a borrowed tomb and he rose in victory
Conquering sin death in the grave one day one glorious day
We'll go to be with him and it'll be perfect in heaven. I know that America's got problems. I understand
But I'm thankful for the heritage that we have it's under attack. No doubt and there are many people
Unfortunately, I remember some of the songs that we sang my country tis of thee this morning
I remember singing that when I was in public school as a child
I
Remember as a child having some understanding not only because my dad served in the military but understanding Memorial Day and its significance
Not just the start of the summer vacations and a long weekend and a trip to the beach
but those that died
for our freedom and
This morning. I want to look at Psalm 103 and I understand that even
As we think about the holiday in our church on our calendar here in America and we think about this Memorial Day holiday and
Obviously, there are many memorials
I hope that many of you have had the opportunity to visit some of the more memorials that are not far from us
We're a unique location to be able to easily go and see some of those memorials and those memorials
Have been designed they've been set up with the purpose of preserving
the memory of a person or an event
And we find that these memorials really they're designed to be a reminder
you go and you walk down to some of these memorials and you are reminded of
Those that paid the ultimate price for our freedom
you go to the
Vietnam memorial to the wall down there and you see all of the names that are listed right and
it's a reminder for us as
We think about the rich heritage that we have as Americans
We understand this morning that as believers as followers of Jesus Christ
We have a rich heritage and and we find that throughout the Word of God
we have been given many references to memorials and to
Remembering and to beware lest thou forget
We find that the nation of Israel had been instructed to set up some memorials so they would remember in fact
The Passover was instituted to be observed annually so that they would remember how God delivered them from Egyptian bondage
So that would serve not only as a reminder
But that it would serve as a picture of Messiah who would one day come Christ our
Passover and take upon himself the sin of the world
We find that the nation of Israel as they would enter into the land of promise
After those wilderness wanderings as they would cross the Jordan that they had been instructed by God Almighty to set up
Memorials there was a memorial that was established in Gilgal
There was a memorial that was established and set up those twelve stones in the midst of the river and you understand that the instruction
That was given by God Almighty to Joshua and then to the children of Israel was to set up these memorials
So that in time to come when your children should ask what mean ye by these stones
You have an opportunity to say let me tell you what God did let me tell you how God worked
Let me tell you how we walked over that Jordan on dry ground
In fact, you may not be able to see it
But we set up a memorial right in the midst of the Jordan because that's where God let us cross over
We find that there are many references to
The children of Israel not only having memorials, but to be careful about not forgetting see as human beings we we forget things
Sometimes we forget important things
Sometimes we forget those things that we say we're not gonna forget this
We're gonna do whatever we can do to ensure that we remember something
The children of Israel prior to entrance into the land of promise in Deuteronomy chapter number six, they were told this beware
Lest thou forget
the Lord
What was it that they were to be careful of?
Well, they were going to go into a land where they were going to enjoy
The fruit of the vineyards that they did not plant they were gonna live in houses that they did not build
God said when you experience all of that goodness
Beware lest thou forget the Lord
And you say oh, how could we forget the Lord?
You know that the nation of Israel the Bible says that they forgot God days without number
Book of Jeremiah
We find that the indictment against Jeremiah or against the the nation of Judah by Jeremiah
Of course from the Lord was that they had followed after idols
Why did they follow after idols because they had forgotten the Lord?
They forsook the Lord they forgot the Lord and this morning as we look at this passage of Scripture
we find that it's a psalm that's ascribed to David and
Here is we would look at this passage. The Bible says bless the Lord. Oh my soul and
All that is within me bless his holy name
Now when you read verse number one that does not seem like it does not sound like
That it's some little kind of just go through the motions, whatever. No, he's saying
God's been good to us
They were singing that song this morning about being saved. They've tasted, you know, David said in Psalm
34 taste and see that the Lord is good and he is good and
Here the psalmist mean you you look at the passion. He says bless the Lord. Oh my soul and all that is within me
Bless his holy name
Bless the Lord. Oh my soul notice verse 2 and forget not all
His benefits
This morning. I'm going to preach a message that I've simply entitled from verse number 2 forget not all his benefits
How is it that we as the people of God? How is it that we as human beings that?
Often forget things how is it that we can forget not all his benefits?
What are some things that we can do as a nation as we've mentioned already?
We've established some memorials for the purpose of remembering
The nation of Israel they've established some memorials under the direction of God so that they would remember
Now we understand that as generations pass by
the knowledge of those things the remembrance of those things
Unfortunately can pass and
No longer be recognized by a new generation
The Lord's Supper table that sits before me this morning has this do in remembrance of me
first Corinthians chapter 3 11 for the church for us as New Testament believers
He's given us that that truth of observing the Lord's Supper that ordinance if you will
And it reminds us of what the Lord Jesus Christ did for us
And it shows us what he did for us till he returns
What a blessing.
So forget not all his benefits.
I want to just look at a few things, we'll be in a few passages, turn to Psalm 68, just
several chapters back, if you will, Psalm 68, and I want you to notice verse 19.
If you're taking notes this morning, first we must recognize all his benefits.
Until we recognize all his benefits, we're in a position where when the psalmist says
forget not all of his benefits, I've not yet recognized them, so how am I not going to
forget them?
And so as we look at this passage in Psalm 68, verse number 19, I want you to be mindful
of the goodness of God.
Notice what the psalmist says, blessed be the Lord, who daily loadeth us with benefits,
even the God of our salvation, Selah.
As we look at this verse, we recognize all of his benefits, obviously the verse before
us does not list all of his benefits, all of his blessings, all of his goodness to us,
but we are mindful of God's goodness in our lives, and we notice the psalmist as he says
blessed be the Lord, I want you to think about the words that are used, he says who daily
loadeth me with benefits.
Aren't you thankful for the daily?
I mean every day, his mercies are new every morning, amen?
His compassions, they fail not.
And I am so thankful that every single day, my God blesses me, it says this, he daily
loadeth me.
I mean I'm not sure what your mind's eye sees when you read verses like this, when you consider
the verbiage that is given, but I see some, this loadeth, right, I mean this isn't just
a little bit of a blessing, this isn't just a little bit of a benefit, it's not just scarce,
it's a load, amen?
And you think about the imagery that is here throughout these verses, and when we consider
this morning, we recognize all of God's benefits to us.
And we find that those benefits are daily, and that those benefits are loaded, again,
it's not with, they're not scarce, they're not reserved for I don't have that many and
so I have to be careful how I give them out, no, it's an abundance, God's goodness and
God's grace, and he loads you today, and he'll load you again tomorrow, and he'll load you
again the next day, and the day after, isn't that wonderful?
And then the psalmist says this, even the God of our salvation, Selah, we find that
word throughout the book of Psalms.
Sometimes in our fast-paced culture that we live in, we don't have time for Selah, right?
We're fast-paced.
We get all kinds of things going on, we're just, get it done, get it done, what's next,
what's next, what's next, Selah, just stop and meditate, take it in, my God daily loadeth
me with benefits.
We have to recognize this truth.
We have to not only recognize all of his benefits, but if you take and turn to Psalm 103, the
passage that we started in, number two, we must rehearse all his benefits.
See it's important that we recognize his benefits, but as we recognize them, we must then rehearse
them.
What does it mean to rehearse them?
Let's talk about them, amen?
There's a song many years ago, I remember a college group, let's talk about Jesus.
And the king of kings is he, amen, he is, and it went through all sorts of attributes
of our God, and it was a wonderful song that would just remind you of how good God is.
We notice in Psalm 103 that the psalmist says, bless the Lord, O my soul, and all that is
within me, bless his holy name, bless the Lord, O my soul, and forget not all his benefits.
Well, how do I forget not?
You know, if we daily recognize that he loads us with benefits, and then we rehearse those
benefits, those blessings, it's not likely that you're going to forget them, right?
Why?
Because you're rehearsing them.
What do you do to not forget something?
People have various things that they do, they, I try to be really good at not forgetting
people's names, and so what I will do is I'll try to associate their name with somebody
else that I know, that sort of thing.
When the Trejos came here, they have 11 children, and so I was trying to remember their names,
and so what did I do?
I rehearsed them.
And then I'm like, man, I don't know who's next.
Armando has that problem, and they're his kids, amen?
And the reality is that I would sit with the kids, with Joseph and Brianna and Juliana,
and I'd say, okay, tell me if I'm right.
Did I not do this?
I'm not joking with y'all, I did it, I said, all right, Brianna, tell me if I'm right,
quiz me.
And I'd try to list them all, and they're like, no, no, you got those two wrong, right?
And so I rehearsed them.
We do that in life with various things, but I wonder this morning, how often are we rehearsing
the benefits?
Forget not all his benefits.
So if I'm going to forget not, I better start rehearsing.
I recognize them, until I recognize them, I can't rehearse them.
But I recognize his benefits, and then I rehearse his benefits.
In our passage of Scripture, there are at least seven benefits that the psalmist mentions
here in Psalm 103.
Notice with me, the first is forgiveness.
Oh, aren't you thankful for the forgiveness of God?
I'm so thankful that the Bible tells us that with thee, with the Lord, there is forgiveness.
I'm thankful that the Word of God declares that our God is ready to pardon, He is ready
to forgive.
I'm thankful that the Word of God says that if we confess our sins, that He is faithful
and just to forgive us and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness.
It's a wonderful thing to be forgiven.
Amen?
Notice what the psalmist says in verse number three, who redeemeth thy life from destruction,
who crowneth thee with lovingkindness and tender mercies.
Notice in verse number ten, He hath not dealt with us after our sins, nor rewarded us according
to our iniquities.
For as the heaven is high above the earth, so great is His mercy toward them that fear
Him.
As far as the east is from the west, so far hath He removed our transgressions from us.
Oh, the forgiveness of God.
Daily, being mindful of the fact that He has forgiven you.
I'm thankful for that redemption, that one-time regeneration, the fact that we are redeemed
by the blood of the Lamb, and there is a day you must be born again.
Amen?
There's a day that we're saved, but once you're saved, you don't automatically stop sinning.
We're delivered at that moment from the penalty of sin.
The Word of God would teach us that at that moment, we're delivered from the power of
sin.
In that same passage in 1 John, the Bible says if you say you have no sin, the truth's
not in you.
You make God a liar.
And I'm thankful that every day that we can go to God and have forgiveness.
I understand being forgiven forever, having the penalty of my sin, being forgiven for
that and being heaven-bound.
But you know, daily, when that sin will hinder our fellowship with God, we go to God and
have forgiveness.
Notice number two, the provision of God.
Here, the psalmist again, he says, forget not all of his benefits, and then I believe
that he begins to rehearse several for us.
In verse number five, we notice the provision.
Notice this, who satisfieth thy mouth with good things, so that thy youth is renewed
like the eagles.
Hasn't God been good to us?
The Lord is my shepherd, I shall not want.
Amen?
We find that our God, His provision in our lives.
You think about the nation of Israel, how God miraculously provided for them.
I mean, as they had enjoyed manna in the morning, they were complaining in the afternoon that
we have no meat.
We hate this bread.
We loathe it, is what the Word of God says.
This we're back in Egypt, right, isn't that what they said?
See, God has been so good to us.
His provision is not just in, you know, food, but we're thankful for the food that He provides.
You think about the shelter and the raiment and all those things.
Remember there in Matthew chapter number six, as he goes through and he's teaching about
the provision, listen, God knows what you have need of.
It is He that has formed us and not we ourselves.
He made us as individual human beings that require some provision and He graciously provides
it.
He's been so good to us.
We see forgiveness.
We see provision.
Notice number three, deliverance in verse number six.
6, the Lord executed righteousness and judgment for all that are oppressed.
It says that the Lord is merciful in verse number 8, and gracious, slow to anger, plenteous
in mercy.
And we think about the way in which the Lord has provided deliverance, the nation of Israel
many times throughout the Psalms in particular, you'll find where the Bible talks about how
He was saved from His enemies.
He's not dealing with salvation as we would speak of redemption, but deliverance from
a particular situation.
And I'm thankful for God's deliverance in our lives.
We find that number 4, He speaks about direction.
Notice in verse number 7, He made known His ways unto Moses, His acts unto the children
of Israel.
You know, Moses was a faithful minister.
He was faithful to give the people of God the Word of God.
As God would speak to Moses, Moses would then speak to the people.
And as God would speak to Moses and then Moses to the people, you know what God was doing?
He was providing them with direction.
When I think about direction, I'm not just speaking about which way to go, though He
provided that direction as well.
Not only the way to travel when they would leave Egypt land, that God would provide them
with direction.
The Bible says that God led them, not this way, not that way, but God led them this way
exactly where they were supposed to go so that they could see the power of God.
But I think about His direction in providing us with the Word of God.
Thy Word is a lamp unto my feet, a light to my path.
The Bible provides direction for daily living.
How is it that we could know how to please a holy God?
How is it that we could know how to approach a holy God?
He's given us direction in His Word.
Oh, I'm so thankful.
You ever try to put something together without directions?
Sometimes we as men are guilty of saying, I don't need those directions, right?
And then all of a sudden when you're halfway through and it's not going together right,
you say, hey, hey, hey, Joseph, go get those directions.
I think we're going to need those.
Well, the Word of God is our direction manual.
I don't mean to use that in a disrespectful way.
I don't mean to be irreverent, but it does provide us direction for living.
What do I do? How do I do?
See, so many people want to look at this book as just being a book of rules,
of do's and don'ts, and they want to criticize this book,
but I'm thankful that God gave us this book.
Because when He says, don't do this because this is going to bring judgment,
I'm thankful that He revealed that to me instead of just letting me be judged.
Right? Praise God.
Number five, notice verse eight.
The Lord is merciful and gracious, slow to anger and plenteous in mercy.
Here in one verse of Scripture, we see the mercy, the grace of God.
We see His long-suffering, His slow to anger, His loving kindness toward us.
Oh, I'm so thankful for who God is.
I'm so thankful for His attributes that have been revealed to us in His Word.
And I understand that His attributes go much further than just verse number eight,
but as the psalmist is rehearsing some of these benefits,
remember, he says, forget not all of His benefits,
we recognize that He daily loatheth us with benefits.
And then we rehearse those things.
And he's saying, I'm thankful for who God is.
He's the Lord God Almighty.
He's merciful, He's gracious, He's slow to anger.
He's patient and long-suffering toward us.
Aren't you thankful for that?
Number six, I believe.
Compassionate.
Notice verse 13.
Like as a father pitieth his children, so the Lord pitieth them that fear Him.
For He knoweth our frame, He remembereth that we are dust.
As for man, his days are as grass, as a flower the field, so he flourisheth.
Verse 16, for the wind passeth over it and it is gone.
And the place thereof shall know it no more.
Notice in verse number 13, the Bible uses the word pitieth twice.
Like as a father pitieth his children, so the Lord pitieth them that fear Him.
This word pitieth means to love deeply, to be compassionate, to have tender affection
toward.
Oh, I'm thankful for God's compassion.
The Bible tells us that He's compassionate, the Bible tells us that He's full of compassion,
that His compassions fail not.
The Bible tells us of the Lord Jesus Christ during His earthly ministry that He was moved
with compassion.
I'm thankful for the truth in verse number 14, for He knoweth our frame.
He remembereth that we are dust.
Listen, there are times in which as human beings we just are, we find ourselves in a
position where we say, we just don't know what to do, we don't know where to go, we
don't know up from down, left from right, so on and so forth.
And God made us, He formed us, He knows that.
He knows our frame.
And He graciously meets our needs.
I believe that as we look at a verse like verse number 14, and He says He remembereth
that we are dust, of course a reference back to creation, and you'd be mindful of understanding
that without Him, we can do nothing.
He is the vine.
We are the branches.
We must abide in Him.
He knows our frame.
Listen, that problem that you have, that difficulty that you're dealing with, that emotional whatever
that's going on, and you're struggling, God made you.
And He knows you.
And He's compassionate.
Number seven, if you skip down to verse number 19, He rules and He reigns.
The Bible says, the Lord hath prepared His throne in the heavens, and His kingdom ruleth
over all.
And we live in a day like today, and it seems like things are so confusing, and there's
chaos that is just seeming to reign, and man, every day the headlines change, and we just
rest in knowing that our God, the Lord God omnipotent reigneth.
He rules and He reigns.
He's never been defeated, and He never will be.
You say, well what's going on?
God's in control.
I may not know everything, but I do understand that He's long-suffering, and sometimes He's
long-suffering to people.
When He's long-suffering to somebody else, we're like, come on, let's get going here.
But in my life, when I want God to be long-suffering, I want Him to be long-suffering, right?
God's not willing that any should perish, but that all should come to repentance.
Listen, I know that Jesus is coming back, and I pray that He comes back soon.
But you know, there are billions of people in our world that are lost, and He's not willing
that any should perish, but that all should come to repentance.
His timeline is perfect.
I don't know when He's going to return, but I know He rules and He reigns.
When you see people that shake their fist at God, when you see people that act as if
they're the ones that are in control, just remind yourself of what Pilate said to Jesus.
And Pilate said, don't you know that I have power to release you?
Or I have power to crucify you?
And what did Jesus say?
In a meek kind of response, He said, don't you understand that the only power you have
is the power I give you?
Amen!
The Proverbs, the wise man Solomon said that the heart of the king is in the hand of the Lord.
On Wednesday evening, Brother Maldolph preached from the book of Nehemiah, and he said, which
brother are you?
And he spoke of Nehemiah and Hanani, but you understand that in the preliminaries of that
message he shared with us how that God moved in the heart of Cyrus to have the people of
God return, that were in captivity.
Cyrus was His servant, He's the king, but God is the King of kings and the Lord of lords.
I look at Psalm 103, and I know we didn't exhaustively study this passage this morning,
but we find that the psalmist begins with this heart of praise, and it's passionate
praise.
It's bless the Lord, O my soul, in all that is within me.
Bless His holy name.
Bless the Lord, O my soul, and forget not all His benefits.
How am I going to not forget?
Rehearse them.
We recognize that He daily loadeth us with benefits, and then we rehearse those benefits.
At least seven.
You study Psalm 103, you might find more.
I kind of coupled several together in verse number eight, when I spoke about who God is.
But I'm going to tell you, the songwriter said, count your blessings, name them one
by one, and it will surprise you what the Lord hath done.
I wonder, when's the last time you were struggling, dealing with just living in this world?
And instead of complaining and murmuring, and woe is me, and I don't know what's going
on, just take out a sheet of paper and just start writing down the blessings of God.
one by one. One by one. See how many sheets you can fill up. See how far you
can get. I mean, we can spend much time just praising God for who He is. Being
mindful of His wonderful attributes. The psalmist in Psalm 150 made that clear
that we are to praise God not only for the things that He does, but we're to
praise God for who He is. I've said many times over the years that when we learn
to praise God for who He is, we will never lack reason to rejoice because He
never changes. He's immutable. And so when you begin to fill up your prayer time
with praise and you begin to start that time of prayer by praising God for who
He is, you're always going to have reason to rejoice. God, I don't understand this
situation I'm in, but I understand who you are. I don't know how you're gonna
deal with this, but I know that you have a plan. This surprised me, but it didn't
surprise you. Aren't you thankful for that? Have you ever been caught off guard?
You ever been surprised? Blindsided, if you will? You say, man, I didn't see that
coming. Listen, as vigilant as we try to be as human beings, there are times in
which we get blindsided. Because we're not omniscient. We don't know all things.
We're not eternal in the same sense that God is of being
outside of time and seeing the end from the beginning. There are times in which
things happen in our life we say, I didn't see that coming. I didn't
expect that. But when we know who God is, we can rest in knowing that it didn't
surprise Him. God has never said, I didn't see that coming. Never. Jesus Christ is
the Lamb of God slain before the foundation of the world. Before Adam and
Eve ever sinned in the garden, God knew they were going to sin and God provided
a way. Because our God is outside of time. He is Alpha and Omega. He has no beginning,
no ending. And He has never been caught off guard. See, the psalmist is rehearsing
the benefits. We recognize, we rehearse them. I'd ask this question, how is it
that we should, number three, what is our response to all His benefits? Well, we see
it in this passage. The response is one of rejoicing, of praise. The response is
one of just, just bless the Lord. He says, all that is within me, bless His holy
name. Notice what the psalmist says. Turn over to Psalm 116, if you will. Another
psalm here, and much praise is mentioned here. Again, if we were to take the time to
read through the entirety of the psalm, you would see that there are many
references here with regard to the blessings, the benefits of the Lord, who
He is, what He does. The Bible speaks of, in Psalm 116 and verse 15, precious in
the sight of the Lord is the death of His saints. Why? As we understand the
whole, the entirety of the Bible, to be absent from the body is to be present with
the Lord. But I want you to notice the question that the psalmist asks in verse
number 12. What shall I render unto the Lord for all His benefits toward me? What
is it that I shall render unto the Lord for all His benefits toward me? We once
again see this phrase, all His benefits. Remember, the psalmist said in Psalm 103
and verse 2, forget not all His benefits. Here he says, what is it that I shall
render unto the Lord for all His benefits? The psalmist said in Psalm 68, he did not
use that phrase, but he said, He daily loadeth us with benefits. And so here, the
psalmist asks an appropriate question, but you understand that in asking this
question, it's not as if we owe God something as far as, you did this for me
and so I have to pay you back with something. It's not really the idea. The
idea is that when I recognize all of His benefits and I rehearse all of His
benefits, my response is going to be one of praise and thanksgiving. My response
is going to be one of a life of surrender, that I recognize all that
He has done for me and I've daily rehearsed. And so we sing the song about
living for Jesus. Why? Because of all that He's done for me, because of all that He
is. Notice in verse number 17 of this passage here in Psalm 116, it says, I will
offer to thee the sacrifice of thanksgiving and will call upon the name
of the Lord. I will pay my vows unto the Lord now in the presence of all those
people. Notice verse 19, in the courts of the Lord's house, in the midst of thee, O
Jerusalem, praise ye the Lord. Psalm 117 is a very short psalm, two verses, but
notice these two verses in Psalm 117, O praise the Lord, all ye nations, praise
Him, all ye people, for His merciful kindness is great toward us and the
truth of the Lord endureth forever. Praise ye the Lord. We're living in the
midst of a time where people have said, what is truth? You can't know truth. Truth
is relative. Your truth, my truth, their truth. Nonsense. Truth is truth. Jesus
Christ said, I am the way, the truth, and the life. No man cometh unto the Father
but by me. His truth endureth forever. Aren't you thankful for that? You
understand the truth is constantly under attack, though. Why? Because Satan's a
liar. And so truth is constantly under attack, but truth endures because God
said it would. Begin to think about our response, the response of praise and
thanksgiving. We're mindful of the truth in 1 Thessalonians, turn of the New
Testament, if you will, in chapter number 5 of the book of 1 Thessalonians, and
it's a familiar verse of Scripture to us, but as we consider this morning, this
thought of the psalmist in Psalm 103, forget not all his benefits, I've
recognized them, I've rehearsed them, and what's my response? In verse 18, notice
with me in verse 16, it says, rejoice evermore. Pray without ceasing. In
everything give thanks. For this is the will of God in Christ Jesus concerning
you. I believe this morning that our response as the people of God to all of
his benefits is one of rejoicing, one of praise. Our God is worthy. The word
worship in our English language, it originally carried with it the idea of
worthship. He is worthy of our praise. He is worthy of our thanksgiving. And this
morning, as we would notice some parallels perhaps as I began the
meeting this morning and the introduction, if you will, to the message
with speaking about some of the sad realities of what we're living in in
2021 with regard to our nation and our heritage. And the fact that there's a
generation today that would literally sign a petition to get rid of a holiday
that exists because of the sacrifice of those that preserve the freedom
that we enjoy. And they're just clueless. That's probably the best word to think
of. They're clueless. In fact, and I don't know, I'm just gonna share what the
article said about this fake petition. I've never seen the movie Frozen, but
some of you have. The guy that was writing the article said that he's a
Marine but he has a daughter and he's watched Frozen too many times. But
evidently there's a snowman in that movie. Is that true? Come on, somebody
help me out. I know somebody's seen Frozen, right? Okay, there's a snowman,
Olaf or something like this, right? And he's singing a song about looking
forward to the summer. Is this true? Okay, now how stupid is that? That a snowman
is looking forward to the summer. He ain't gonna exist anymore. That was the
parallel that the person that wrote the article about these people signing this
fake petition. I thought, man, now you confirmed that that story is true
about Frozen. I'd never seen the movie. I think my kids were a little bit too
old when Frozen came out that I didn't have to sit there and watch it. But the
reality is that, listen, the same things happened in the Church of God. There's a
generation that has raised up that has forgotten all of his benefits. Listen, I'm
saddened at the state of our country that there are young people that do not
recognize the the ultimate price that was paid for the freedom that they
enjoy. I'm saddened by that. Breaks my heart. But as the Church of God, there are
some young people that were raised in church that are no longer in church.
They've walked away. They've turned their back.
They've forgotten the Lord.
Is that not sad to you?
Breaks my heart."
I said, what happened?
I don't know the answer to the question.
In fact, people that are much smarter than I am have written many books on it.
It's a problem that has been widely recognized in churches in America.
There's a poll that was recently taken that a high percentage of those within the Millennials
said they don't know and don't care if there even is a God.
But I just wonder sometimes about the state of the church.
We can see the state of our nation, it's sad.
Breaks our heart.
But what about the state of the church, that people could be raised up?
I mean, think about the nation of Israel.
Isn't that what happened with the nation of Israel?
Psalm, let's just think about Judges.
There was another generation that knew not the Lord.
What did they do?
They served Balaam.
Judges, go back and read it.
Generation that rose up after Joshua and all the elders, and they served Balaam.
Psalm 78 gives us the answer.
How is it that we ensure that a future generation would set their hope in God, not forsake God?
We have to rehearse His benefits.
We got to share with the generation, hey, our God is good.
Our God is real.
We got to have some memorials even as the people of God.
To come to this place where the psalmist says, forget not all His benefits.
I hope that the generation to come in our church, I hope that your children, that my
children, regularly hear us rehearsing the blessings of God.
That they regularly hear us talking about how good God is.
Listen, your kids don't need to hear you complaining about life and church and the
pastor's message.
No one would complain about that, I'm sure.
Amen.
Right, Armando?
But I'm just saying, what does that do?
What do you think that does to your children?
It doesn't help them.
It doesn't cause them to want to serve God.
It doesn't cause them to have that desire to go and do for the Lord all that He said
that we should do.
The Bible talks about, I believe it's in Psalm 106, I don't have it in my notes here, let
me just check to see if that's the right Psalm, and if not, we'll just keep on going forward.
I think it's in Psalm 106.
The Bible talks about here in Psalm 106 the way in which they talked and spoke badly about
the Lord and how they were doing that even within their tents.
And the reality is that they sang His praises, they believed, but then they soon forgot.
Look at verse number 13 of Psalm 106.
They soon forgot His works, they waited not for His counsel.
They lusted exceedingly in the wilderness and tempted God in the desert.
He gave them their request but sent leanness into their soul in verse number 15.
It talks about the way in which they changed things in verse 21.
They forgot God their Savior which had done great things in Egypt.
Wow.
They despised the pleasant land.
They believed not His word in verse number 24.
Look at verse 25.
But murmured in their tents.
Now for them, what was their tent?
Their home, their dwelling place, right?
And they murmured in their tents and hearkened not unto the voice of the Lord.
What do you think their murmuring did to that next generation?
Further and further away.
I understand that we have problems and difficulties, but can we not recognize this morning that
our God is good?
I mean, through the storms He's good.
He's got a purpose and a plan.
And so what happens sometimes in our lives is when we're in the midst of the storm, we
begin to complain and murmur because we're in the midst of it.
We don't know all that God's doing.
Then we get through the storm and perhaps we've learned that lesson, that lesson that
could only be learned in that storm.
We say, oh God, thank you for teaching me that lesson.
And I wonder if we've murmured about the storm and our children heard that, did we go back
and say, hey listen, I know I complained about that storm, but man, God taught me something.
Can I share with you what God taught me?
I'm not suggesting that we completely erase from their minds that murmuring, but you know
there's some times in which we need to go back and say, listen, God's been good to us.
This morning, the state of our nation is sad, but I would say that the state of our church,
broadly speaking, there's a generation that has forgotten the Lord, just as there's a
generation that has forgotten the sacrifice of many to preserve the freedom in this nation.
And today, we're challenged by this thought of the psalmist, forget not all his benefits.
I need to recognize them.
Oh, he daily loadeth me with benefits.
God's been good.
Every day, God's been good.
And then we rehearse them.
Let's talk about the Lord.
Let's talk about what he's done.
Maybe we get around the table and, hey, share testimony, share a blessing, what did God
do for you today?
How's God good to you today?
Because our response as we rehearse them, our response is one of, bless the Lord, oh
my soul, and all that is within me, bless his holy name.
Our God is worthy of our worship and our praise and our thanksgiving.
Forget not all his benefits.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We readily acknowledge this morning that you've been good to us.
We agree with the psalmist that you have daily loadeth us with benefits.
The psalmist asked that question, what shall we render unto the Lord for all of his benefits?
I believe an answer that is worth giving is one of praise and thanksgiving, adoration,
standing in awe of who you are.
God as we have seen in our nation, a generation that has risen up that has forgotten the sacrifice
of a former generation, I pray God that it would not be so in the church.
Not only would we be mindful of the freedoms that we have as Americans and the sacrifice
that was made to protect and preserve those freedoms, that we'd be mindful as the people
of God for all of your benefits, that our children, a generation to come, would set
their hope in God, they would serve you faithfully, they'd live for you.
I'm not sure, Lord, how you've worked in hearts and lives today, but I pray that you'd help
us to respond, help us to just thank you.
Perhaps there's one that's not sure of heaven, whether here or watching live stream.
The group sang about being saved this morning, we spoke about forgiveness.
I pray God that you would help them today to understand their need for Christ.
For we as thy people, help us to rejoice in thee.
Well thank you for all that you'll do, for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Eyes are bowed, eyes are closed.
Forget not all his benefits.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano, and as she does, the altar is open.
Maybe you just need to come to the altar this morning and just rejoice for a little bit.
Just thank God for his benefits.
Maybe as a family, right there in your pew, you just want to sit down or come to the altar
as a family and just say, let's thank God as a family for all his benefits, because
truly God has been good to us.
Forget not all his benefits.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.