5, and Lord willing, we're gonna finish
the book of 1 John this morning.
And we started it back in January,
studying through the book of 1 John
and our theme, Walking in the Light.
And we started this book and it's been our theme all year.
We've had the privilege of singing for all of our services
the theme song, I Walk and I Talk with the King.
And what a joy and blessing it is
to know the Lord Jesus Christ
as our personal savior.
And as we look at this portion of scripture,
I do trust that it'll be a blessing to you.
Of course, last week I preached a different message.
I wasn't in the book of 1 John,
but a couple of weeks ago,
we looked at verses 14 and 15
in 1 John chapter number five.
And as we looked at verses 14 and 15,
I dealt with the subject matter of confident prayer.
And the Bible says in verse 14,
and this is the confidence that we have in him,
that if we ask anything according to his will,
he heareth us.
And if we know that he hear us,
whatsoever we ask,
we know that we have the petitions that we desired of him.
As we concluded that message a couple of weeks ago,
we acknowledged the product of praying according to his will.
And we said this, that when we pray according to his will,
that he has told us that he would answer us.
And really the desire and what we see as the product
is a closer walk with the Lord.
I dealt with this.
I spent much time on this particular point
in the message a couple of weeks ago.
And really it's amazing how God has designed it as such.
When we pray according to his will,
we say, how do I know his will?
Well, we know his will through his word.
And so we get into the word of God
so that we can know how to pray according to his will.
And then as we pray according to his will,
he hears us and he answers us.
And when he answers us,
that encourages us because we've had answered prayer
and that encourages us.
And then we wanna pray more
because we wanna see more answered prayer.
And so we dig into the word of God more
so that we can know his will,
so that we can pray according to his will.
And then he answers our prayer.
And we think about this cycle
and we see how that God and his infinite wisdom
has designed it so that it draws us closer to him.
And we might be familiar,
some of us might be familiar with that song,
just a closer walk with thee.
And the songwriter said this,
not the entirety of the song,
but they said, just a closer walk with thee.
Grant it, Jesus is my plea.
Daily walking close to thee.
Let it be, dear Lord, let it be.
It ought to be the desire of every child of God
to have a closer walk with the Lord.
And we find that God has given us this truth in his word
with regard to the product of this answered prayer,
of this praying according to his will,
is that we'll have that closer walk with him,
have that sweet fellowship.
We understand that one of the themes
of the book of 1 John, as we've dealt with it all year,
is really the theme of fellowship.
And he deals with that in the first few verses
of the book of 1 John in the first chapter.
If you'll turn back there just for a moment
in verses three and four,
John immediately starts dealing with this subject,
this topic, if you will,
the theme of fellowship.
In verse three, he says,
that which we have seen and heard declare we unto you,
that ye also may have fellowship with us.
And truly, our fellowship is with the Father
and with his son, Jesus Christ.
And these things write we unto you,
that your joy may be full.
In verse number five, this then is the message
which we have heard of him and declare unto you
that God is light and in him is no darkness at all.
If we say that we have fellowship with him
and walk in darkness, we lie and do not the truth.
And what a joy it is to have fellowship with the Lord.
To be able to enter into his presence,
I was chatting via text with my father-in-law this week.
And as I was chatting with this past week,
I was chatting with him a little bit via text.
And we were talking about the trip
that Holly and I had recently made to Israel
and talking about the Garden of Gethsemane.
And of course, if you were here when I gave that overview
of our trip to Israel on Sunday night a few weeks ago,
I mentioned that really the Garden of Gethsemane
was probably the highlight of the trip.
I just truly enjoyed being there.
And when Jesus was in Jerusalem,
the Garden of Gethsemane was the place where he was.
It was his place.
John tells us that he resorted thither often.
And you just are in that place and what a blessing it was.
But here's what I said to my father-in-law.
And I wanna say it to you as well.
And I hope that it's a blessing to you.
And here's the truth.
As much of a blessing as it was
to be in the Garden of Gethsemane.
And as we were there, the group of us,
as Holly and I were there in the Garden of Gethsemane,
we sang together, we wept together, we prayed together.
It was amazing.
But here's what's even more amazing.
I don't have to go to the Garden of Gethsemane
to meet with my God.
And that's awesome.
Because I can meet with my God
and you can meet with your God anywhere,
anytime, for any length of time,
you can enter into his presence.
And that is awesome.
Don't misunderstand.
I'm thankful for the opportunity to have been there,
but I'm so thankful and so much more thankful
that I don't have to go there to meet with my God.
I met with him this morning.
I met with him right here this morning.
And I prayed for you from right here this morning.
And then I went into my office
and I met with him in my office,
at my desk, reading this book.
You met with him wherever you met with him.
I've met with him at Panera.
You say, at Panera, I have.
I've met with him at Chick-fil-A, praise God, amen.
You can meet with God anywhere.
And that's awesome.
And we look at this book
and we understand the theme of fellowship
and we understand that John has spent much time
going through and providing us with truth
in the book of 1 John
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God
to help us to know some things.
He wants us to know that we're saved.
I'm so thankful that God desires for his children
to know that they know that they know that they're saved.
Listen, I'm thankful that my parents,
and they're here this morning,
desired for my brother and I when we were growing up
that we knew that they were our parents,
that we were their kids, right?
I'm thankful that they didn't treat us
like we were somebody else's kids.
No, they made us know that we were their children.
We have three children, God's blessed us,
and we want our children to know
that God has entrusted us with them
and they're our children.
And God is my heavenly father.
He wants me to know that I'm his child
and he's given us evidences
that would help us to be able to have confidence
that we're saved,
that we don't have to go through life wondering,
am I saved, am I not saved,
am I going to heaven when I die?
Is it based upon this letter?
No, it's all based on the finished work of Christ
at Calvary, his death barrel and glorious resurrection.
We place our faith and trust in him alone
and he promised to save us.
And we can rejoice in that
and God wants us to know that.
Not only does he want us to know that we're his children,
but he wants us to know that we can have fellowship
with him.
He's never busy.
He's never too busy for you.
But he also wants us to know that there are some things
that can hinder that fellowship.
And as we conclude the book of 1 John,
I really believe that here in this portion of scripture,
we find really a warning of how our fellowship
with the Lord can be hindered,
but then we are reminded of the blessedness
of abiding in him.
And in verse number 19,
I'm going to look at verses 16 through 21 this morning,
but I want to draw your attention to verse 19,
give you the title, we'll jump right in.
In verse 19, it says this,
and we know that we are of God.
That word know is used so often in this book,
to know, to have that knowledge, that certainty,
that confidence.
You ever been in a situation where you know something?
I often say it this way to somebody,
I'll use Michael as an illustration,
I'll meet Michael and I'll say,
hey, Michael, are you 100% sure if you're to die
that you'd go to heaven?
Now that's not the first thing that I say to Michael,
but I say that to Michael and he says,
well, you know, I think so.
And I was like, well, God wants you to know.
And I'll say something like this.
Do you know that your name is Michael?
You know what everyone says to me?
Yes, they know what their name is.
And then I'll say this.
What if I told you your name was Tom, John,
I'll just pick a name.
Could I convince you that that's your name?
And they're like, no.
And they look at me like I'm crazy.
But I say in that same way that you know
that your name is Michael,
God wants you to know that you're his child.
He wants you to know that with confidence
and with certainty.
And here it says, and we know that we are of God.
We know that we are of God.
As we use that as our title this morning,
I mentioned that the passage starts out
with really a warning and helps us to understand
how that our fellowship with God can be hindered.
And if you are taking notes, notice with me,
number one, recognize the peril of sin.
Recognize the peril of sin.
In verse number 16, the Bible says this
in first John five and verse 16.
If any man see his brother sin a sin which is not unto death, he shall ask, and he shall
give him life for them that sin not unto death.
There is a sin unto death, I do not say that he shall pray for it.
All unrighteousness is sin, and there is a sin not unto death."
And you say, that sounds confusing.
Probably one of the most debated portions of Scripture in the book of 1 John, verse
16 and 17, and really as you go forward even into verse 18 as well.
But I hope that this morning that we can find that it's very clear what God is teaching
us here in these verses of Scripture.
In my own life, but also in the lives of my brothers and sisters in Christ, we must recognize
the peril of sin.
We find that he says in verse number 17 that all unrighteousness is sin, and we understand
that.
We understand this morning that as we go to the Word of God and we look to the Word of
God, that God defines what is sinful behavior, what is sin.
We must acknowledge that we have sinned before we could ever be saved, and we understand
the Bible says all have sinned and come short of the glory of God.
But here's the amazing thing, as we think about believers and we think about the sin
in the life of a believer and we understand that we've been saved by the blood of the
Lord Jesus Christ, we studied the first chapter and really into the second chapter of the
book of 1 John, and we were reminded of some wonderful promises that we need to rehearse
this morning.
Number one is this, there's a promise of forgiveness.
In 1 John chapter number 1 and verse number 9, he says, if we confess our sins, now remember
he's writing to save people, so after we're saved, we still sin.
Have you sinned since you've been saved?
Sure you have.
Does that mean that you're not saved?
That doesn't mean that you're not saved, but you've sinned since you've been saved.
Now you've been saved from the penalty of sin, but you've not yet been saved from the
presence of sin.
I'm thankful that we've been saved from the power of sin.
You don't, you no longer have to sin.
Sin no longer has dominion over you, as Paul says in the book of Romans, but we find now
that as we, as believers, when there's sin in our life, we have this great promise that
if we confess our sins, he, God, is faithful and just to forgive us our sins and to cleanse
us from all unrighteousness.
That ought to cause us to be thankful this morning, that we have this promise of forgiveness,
but not only a promise of forgiveness, but we have the promise in 1 John 2 and verse
number 1 that Jesus Christ the righteous is our advocate.
The Bible says this in 1 John 2 and verse number 1, my little children, these things
write I unto you that ye sin not.
And obviously as a child of God, I ought to desire to live a life of obedience.
When we baptize someone, you'll hear it this morning, that you're raised to walk in newness
of life.
And that desire on the part of a child of God to live a life of obedience, but we still
have this flesh and there still will be sin, but our desire should be that we sin not.
That's what he says, that you sin not.
But then he says this, and if any man sin, we have an advocate.
We have an advocate with the Father, Jesus Christ the righteous.
And I love this promise in 1 John 2 and verse number 1 that we have an advocate.
We really could look at that today and use the terminology of being a defense attorney.
And here's the amazing thing, and I said this months ago as we studied 1 John chapter number
2, that Jesus Christ the righteous, our advocate, our defense attorney, he does not argue our
innocence.
Why?
Because we're guilty.
How could he argue our innocence if we're guilty?
He doesn't argue our innocence, rather he acknowledges our guilt, but then says this,
I've paid for it.
Isn't that awesome?
Because the Lord, that we have an advocate with the Father, Jesus Christ the righteous.
And these are promises that are precious to us as believers, and we ought to understand
that and we ought to be encouraged by that.
As we go back to 1 John 5 and verse number 16, notice what he says, if any man see his
brother sin a sin, which is not unto death.
Now I'm going to try to unpackage this for you and help you this morning and help myself
as well.
He says this, he shall ask, it goes back to praying that we looked at in verses 14 and
15.
He shall ask, notice what it says, and he shall give him life for them that sin not
unto death.
So what's he saying?
Well, if we as brothers and sisters in Christ see a brother or sister sinning in error,
then we can engage in intercessory prayer for them that their fellowship might be restored.
We're praying.
Listen, we have, there are churches, we don't necessarily have this ministry in our church,
though we have certainly discussed and we pray one for another, but a prodigal prayer
list that people will deal with, a prodigal prayer ministry.
And we think about people, listen, we know people that are, they've erred, they've sinned,
and we are able to pray for them.
They've sinned a sin that's not unto death.
You say, what does that mean?
Well, we all sin.
Not every sin is a sin unto death.
By the way, aren't you thankful for that?
The church would have ceased to exist immediately, right?
There'd be no church today if every sin in the life of a believer was a sin unto death.
The church would just stop.
It would just, it would not exist.
And so he says, if you see a brother that sinned a sin that's not unto death, he shall
ask and he shall give him life for them that sin not unto death.
Really it's the idea of intercessory prayer.
By the way, Moses was a great example of this.
We don't have time to go back to the book of Exodus, but if we did, you can go to the
32nd chapter, and you can see specifically where Moses is, he is interceding on the behalf
of erring brothers and sisters of the children of Israel that were erring at that particular
time, and Moses prayed for them.
And we have in this passage of Scripture, as we mentioned last week or two weeks ago,
that if we ask anything according to his will, he heareth us.
Well, he just said here that if you see a brother sin that's a sin that's not unto death,
he shall ask, you pray for them.
You pray for them.
Not condemning them, but seeking to have their fellowship with God restored.
I've often said that two pillars of biblical Christianity are forgiveness and reconciliation.
And I am so thankful that our God forgives and he reconciles.
And what a blessing that is.
But we find that here in this text of Scripture that it does say to us at the end of verse
number 16, there is a sin unto death.
I do not say that he shall pray for it.
And so we look at this verse, and people always want to know, what's the sin unto death?
Well, actually, God doesn't define it.
How's that for an answer?
You say, we're waiting for an answer.
I don't know.
The Bible doesn't define what a sin unto death is.
There's some people that would try to look at blasphemy and what have you, but really
contextually in the book of First John, he's speaking about believers.
And so we find here that he says that there's a sin unto death.
I do not say that he shall pray for it.
The way that you would pray for a brother that sinned a sin that's not unto death.
He says, if there's a sin unto death, you don't pray for them in that same way.
Verse 17, all unrighteousness is sin, and there is a sin not unto death.
And so we try to unpackage this and understand what is a sin unto death, though God does
not define this sin, but we find that in his infinite wisdom and in his righteous judgment,
that he has made it known to us as his children, that it is possible for the sinning believer
to face physical death as a judgment.
Not only has he told us this, that there is a sin unto death, by the way, that ought to
cause us to be concerned and walk righteously, amen?
We find that there are a couple of biblical examples.
Turn back to the book of Acts, if you will, we'll look at New Testament examples, turn
to Acts chapter number 5, and we look in this passage, I'm not going to read the entirety
of it.
For your notes, if you want to write down verses 1 through 11, that's the entirety of
the portion of Scripture, but I will not take time to read all of the passage this morning.
Many of us would be familiar with the account here of Ananias and Sapphira.
The Bible tells us in Acts 5 in verse number 1, but a certain man named Ananias with Sapphira,
his wife, sold a possession.
And notice what they did in verse number 2, kept back part of the price, his wife also
being privy of it, and brought a certain part and laid it at the apostles' feet.
Peter said, Ananias, why hath Satan filled thine heart to lie to the Holy Ghost, to keep
back part of the price of the land?
Because it remained, was it not thine own?
And after it was sold, was it not thine own power?
Why hast thou conceived this thing in thine heart?
Thou hast not lied unto men, but unto God.
And Ananias, hearing these words, fell down and gave up the ghost.
You know what that means?
That means he died.
You say, he just lied.
I know, that's how we look at it.
Just a lie.
Everyone lies.
You better be careful.
Understand the seriousness of sin.
And here, the Bible says that he gave up the ghost, but notice the result of it.
It says, and great fear came on all them that heard these things.
By the way, if this happened in our midst, I think most of us would have great fear as
well.
It'd be a sobering reality to the importance of righteousness.
Amen?
Our God is holy.
It tells us that about three hours later in verse number 7 that his wife came in, she
didn't know what had happened, and she gave the same story.
And it tells us in verse number 10, then fell she down straightway at his feet and yielded
up the ghost.
She died as well.
And the young men came in and found her dead, and carrying her forth, buried her by her
husband.
Again in verse 11, it says that great fear came upon all the church and upon as many
as heard these things.
The establishment of the church in the book of Acts in the first century, and we find
that in this particular incident that really what's happening is sin is starting to creep
into the church.
And God deals with it very severely.
Why?
Because he's concerned about righteousness.
He's concerned about holy living.
And we find at the start of the church, when the church is just in its infancy, if we could
use that terminology this morning, we find that what God is doing is he's helping for
the church to understand the importance of holiness.
See, we don't want the church to be corrupted by sin.
And so God deals with it very severely.
We find that not only does he deal with it severely, but then he tells us in 1 Corinthians
chapter number 11, when we think about the church in Corinth and here in this portion
of Scripture.
In fact, I'll be preaching from 1 Corinthians 11 this evening as we observe the Lord's Supper.
But we find in 1 Corinthians 11, at the end of the passage of Scripture dealing specifically
with the Lord's Supper, the Bible says in verse number 30, for this cause, the fact
that people were drinking and eating unworthily the Lord's Supper, for this cause many are
weak and sickly among you and many sleep.
That word sleep, as we know, it means to die, all right?
Remember with Lazarus, when he was sick and Jesus said to the disciples, he's asleep.
And they said, well, listen, if he's asleep, then let him sleep.
And he spoke plainly and said, he's dead.
He's dead.
And here, the text of Scripture, this word sleep means to die.
And so there are people in Corinth that died because of their sin.
And so we find that as we look back in 1 John chapter number 5, that the Bible says that
there is a sin unto death.
I don't know what it is, but I don't really want to find out.
That make sense this morning?
And so the truth that God has revealed to us in understanding that in His infinite wisdom
and in His righteous judgment that He's made it known to us as His people that there is
a sin unto death, I don't want to play with sin.
And neither should you.
You guys know I don't like snakes.
I don't like any kind of snake.
I just don't.
But if it's poisonous, I definitely don't like it.
You will never find me, never will you find me messing with a rattlesnake, a copperhead,
any of that.
I'm just not going to do it.
Why?
Because that thing might bite me and it's poisonous and I might die.
And here's the truth.
I tell my kids this all the time.
If I got bit by a rattlesnake, I'd just have a heart attack.
There wouldn't be the whole thing of getting the anti-venom and all that stuff.
Just I'd have a heart attack and die.
And so the reality is that I'm not going to play with a rattlesnake because I understand
the danger.
In a real sense in the life of a believer, listen, I don't want to mess around and dabble
in sin.
All sin, all unrighteousness is sin.
It's a violation against the Holy God.
But I don't want to have from a human perspective an untimely death because God sees fit that,
hey, that's a sin unto death.
And he's going to remove me from this world or remove you from this world because you
have brought reproach against the name of God.
Someone used this illustration.
I thought it was a good illustration.
An illustration of children at a dinner party and the children misbehaving and the parent
saying eventually to the child, listen, if you continue that, I'm going to send you to
your bedroom.
I'm going to remove you from this place because you are bringing a reproach against our family.
You're not going to be permitted to be here.
In that type of a fashion, God in his infinite wisdom, he says, child, you're coming home
because you've sinned a sin unto death.
Now the amazing thing, D.L.
Moody used to say this all the time that when he spoke about the truth, well, I'll say that
just for a moment.
Let me say this.
Without recognizing the peril of sin, sin in the life of a believer hinders fellowship.
Sin in the life of a believer hinders fellowship.
When I have sin in my life, when you have sin in your life, it hinders our fellowship.
D.L.
Moody often said, sin will keep me from this book or this book will keep me from sin.
And the reality is in our lives, we ought to desire to walk righteously and wholly with
our God and understanding the peril of sin and understanding, listen, that sin, that
sin is going to hinder my fellowship with my God.
And so why would I want to hinder my fellowship with God?
I want to have that fullness of joy.
I want to be in his fellowship.
I want to be in his presence.
And we find here that sin in the life of a believer hinders fellowship.
Number two, sin in the life of a believer results in chastisement.
Now the Bible tells us whom the Lord loveth, he chasteneth.
In Hebrews chapter number 12, verses 5 through 7, you can read of chastisement there.
And I am so thankful that God chastens us.
He deals with us as children.
He chastens us because he loves us.
I don't like being chastened, but I'm thankful that God would chasten us.
And really, we ought to learn to be thankful for chastisement because it is a birthmark
of a believer, that God deals with us.
God says, you're my child, you're sinning, I'm going to chasten you.
Why?
Because I love you.
If you don't face chastisement, you better check to see if you're saved.
Hebrews chapter number 12 deals with that very specifically in verses 5 through 7.
We think about what John is relaying here and communicating to these believers that
he's writing to.
He says, recognize the peril of sin.
This is what hinders fellowship.
He says at the end of verse number 19, and the whole world lieth in wickedness.
No wonder he told us in 1 John 2 that we're to love not the world, neither the things
that are in the world.
No wonder that James would tell us that loving the world is enmity and that we cannot love
the world and love God at the same time and understanding this truth that he would deal
with.
And we find here that John says, the whole world lieth in wickedness.
Notice what else he says about the hindrance to fellowship, recognizing the peril of sin.
Verse 21, little children, keep yourselves from idols.
Amen.
You say, man, that's an interesting way to end the book of 1 John.
Little children, keep yourselves from idols.
Amen.
There's no, you read the Pauline epistles and you read about all the people that Paul
saying greet this one and greet that one and so on and so forth, grace and peace and mercy
and so on.
John says, under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God, little children, keep yourselves
from idols.
Amen.
Wow.
You know, John is writing from Ephesus.
That's where he's writing this book from.
And I want you to think about Ephesus being a center of idol worship.
We understand that Paul went into Ephesus and people were saved, a church was established
at Ephesus.
In fact, that church is written to in the book of Revelation, those seven letters that
are written back to the churches, the church at Ephesus being the first of those.
But we find that in Ephesus, it was a place of idol worship and Acts chapter number 19,
you don't need to turn there.
I just want to read two verses to you that describe for us the scene of idolatry in the
city of Ephesus.
In Acts 19 and verse number 28, they pronounce this.
They say, when they heard these sayings, they were full of wrath and cried out saying, great
is Diana of the Ephesians.
And then a few verses later in verse number 34, it says, but when they knew that he was
a Jew, all with one voice, about the space of two hours, cried out, great is Diana of
the Ephesians.
I don't know if you've ever really meditated upon that verse in Acts 19 and verse 34, but
I spent some time this week meditating upon that.
Two hours is a long time.
And the Bible says in verse 34 that for the space of two hours, all with one voice, cried
out, great is Diana of the Ephesians.
Wow.
The idolatry that was present there in Ephesus and Paul writing from the city of Ephesus,
no doubt, obviously under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God, this danger of
idols.
This morning, idolatry in our world looks different than it looked in John's world.
Idolatry here in our community looks different than it does in some places around the globe.
There are some places around the globe that when you talk about idolatry, you actually
see little figurines and you see little idols and incense being burned to these images and
so on and so forth.
And that would be very consistent with much of what you see of idolatry in the Old Testament
and even that which you would see in Ephesus.
But idolatry truly is anything that would take the place of God.
Anything in your life or my life that would take that first place.
The Bible tells us in Colossians chapter 1 that in all things, He, Christ, must have
the preeminence.
We find that.
for us, it could be my workplace. It could be our bank account. It could be our
health. It could be our children. It could be, you just start filling it in. You
start thinking about all these things. Sports. Man, we live in a world today
where sports can become an idol for people. And we find here this morning
that John is closing out this portion of Scripture and he says, listen,
there's some hindrances to fellowship. There's a warning that's being given
and we must recognize the peril of sin. Then we see the blessedness of abiding
in Him. So we recognize, we recognize the peril of sin, but then number two
this morning, remember the protection of God. As we continue to move forward, we
we see the warning of the hindrances of sin in our fellowship, but we then see
the blessedness of abiding in Him and we're reminded of the protection of God.
I'm so thankful that the Bible tells us here in verse number 18, we know that
whosoever is born of God sinneth not. Now I'll break that down in just a moment,
but I want to focus on the beginning part when it says we know that whosoever
is born of God. And I think about that phrase because in, and he started
the fifth chapter of the book of 1st John, he used that phrase born of God
twice. In verse number one of 1st John 5, he said whosoever believeth that Jesus
is the Christ is born of God. And then in verse number four, he says whosoever is
born of God overcometh the world. I dealt with this several weeks ago. What does it
mean to be born of God? It means that I recognize that I'm a sinner and that
Christ is the only Savior. And I receive Him as my personal Savior, understand
that He died for me, that He was buried, and then He rose again conquering sin,
death, and the grave. It's just as Jesus said to Nicodemus, marvel not that I say
unto you, unto thee, ye must be born again. Nicodemus was the one that came
to Jesus by night, and he says listen, marvel not that I say unto thee, ye must
be born again. And ye must be born again. If you've not been born of God, you've
only had one birth, that's the physical birth, and you have a birthday. But we
find that the importance of being born again, being born of God, and we find
that he mentions this truth in 1st John chapter number 5 of being born of God. He
said this in chapter 3 in verse number 1, that what manner of love, behold
what manner of love the Father hath bestowed upon us, that we should be
called the sons of God. Man, John chapter number 10, we're not going to take the
time to turn there, but we find in verses 27 through 30, the fact that we are
secure in the hand of God. My sheep hear my voice, and I know them, and I give unto
them eternal life, and they shall never perish. Those are precious words that
Jesus spoke that John would have heard with his own ears. And Peter would say
this in 1st Peter 1 and verse number 5, that we are kept by the power of God. So
Jesus says, and John and Peter both here, that we're secure in his hand, and Peter
says that we're kept by the power of God, and John speaks about being born of God
and that protection that we have that God gives us, and I am so thankful for
the protection of God. It says in verse 18, we know that whosoever is born of God
sinneth not. Now we've dealt with this in previous messages, but it's important to
note once again that the verb tense of the particular word is important and
gives us clarity. In previous messages in chapter 2 and 3, we dealt
with this in 1st John 2 and 3, but the verb here, when it talks about sinneth
not, is conjugated in the present tense. I'm not trying to be too difficult here,
but really what it indicates is ongoing action. So it doesn't mean that you'll
never sin, it means that you're not going to have that habitual sin in your life.
Why? Because we have been delivered from the power of sin, and we can overcome
through the Lord Jesus Christ. We're not going to clean up our own lives for
ourselves, but with God's power we can have victory over sin. We're to live in
victory. And so we find that that's what he deals with here, but then continue in
verse number 18, it says this, but he that is begotten of God keepeth himself, notice
what he says, and that wicked one toucheth him not. That's precious promise
that God gives us, and it's a reminder to us of the protection of God. Not
only does God keep his children, but we find that he gives us this truth that
that wicked one toucheth him not. Who's the wicked one? Our enemy, our adversary,
Satan. And the promise that is given is that our omnipotent Savior is in
control of all things, and he protects us, and though our God is omnipotent and has
all power, we understand this morning that our adversary is limited. Our God has unlimited
power, but our adversary is limited in his power. And let me say it this way, he is subject
to God. Read the book of Job. You find very plainly that the enemy, the adversary, the
wicked one is who he's referred to here, he is in subject to God Almighty. And it says
that he toucheth him not. That word, toucheth, means to adhere to or to cling to. It doesn't
just mean this touch like this. It means to hold on to, to cling, to grasp. And here,
the Bible says, listen, I'm so thankful that I'm secure in the hands of God, that I'm kept
by the power of God, and the wicked one, he cannot adhere to or cling to me. Yes, he's
gonna attack you, he's gonna send forth his fiery darts, all of those things, he's the
accuser of the brethren, but we have the protection of God. As we abide in him, we can rejoice
in the blessedness, and we can be reminded this morning of God's divine protection upon
his children, and that security that we have in Christ. I'm so thankful this morning, and
I hope that you're so thankful this morning to be reminded of this protection that God
gives us, and that the wicked one toucheth him not. I'm so thankful for the security
that God gives me. And I hope you're so thankful this morning for the security that God gives
you. See, I have children. Many of you have children. You know what we want to do for
our children? We want to protect them, provide them security. Right? Isn't that what you
want to do for your children? That's what I'm going to do for my children. But here's
the thing. I'm limited. So are you. Sometimes there's a danger that comes into the life
of my children, and I'm limited. I'm not everywhere at the same time, and neither are you. And
so they're in a place that I'm not, and there's a danger. How many times we as parents have
said, I wish I was there. Right? I'm not omnipresent, but my God is. I'm not omnipotent.
Sometimes I'm there when my children face danger, but I don't have the power, and neither
do you. I'm not capable of helping them, and how difficult it is, but my God is omnipotent.
He's omnipresent, and He's omnipotent. He's always there, and He's always able, and He
protects us. And I'm so thankful for that this morning.
Let me give you one final thought this morning. We need to rejoice for the provision of God.
We need to recognize the peril of sin. It hinders our fellowship with God. We must remember
the protection of God, and then we must rejoice for the provision of God. Notice with me as
we continue reading here in verse number 20 what a great verse of Scripture this is. He
uses the word know a few times here in this verse of Scripture, and again, how much God
wants us to know the truth. And He says this in verse 20, and we know that the Son of God
is come. Let me just pause right there as we talk about and rejoicing for the provision
of God this time of year. We speak about the incarnation, the birth of Christ. Listen,
I'm thankful that He provided Himself. He left the throne room of heaven. He left all
of the glory and all of the splendor of heaven, and though He was rich, He became poor for
our sakes, that we might be made rich. Think about that wonderful truth, and it says in
verse number 20, and we know that the Son of God is come. He already has come. It is
truth. It is settled truth that God was manifest in the flesh, that Jesus Christ, God in flesh,
that He came and He dwelt among us. Remember, John started the passage by talking about
in verse number 2 of 1 John 1, for the life was manifested, and we have seen it and bear
witness and show unto you that eternal life which was with the Father and was manifested
unto us. John says, I was an eyewitness. I heard, I saw, I handled of the word of life.
Man, that's awesome. And we ought to rejoice this morning that God was willing to provide
Himself. He came to the sin-cursed world.
We understand this morning that if He didn't come, there's no salvation apart from Jesus Christ.
Without the incarnation, there is no salvation.
But He came.
When the fullness of time was come, God sent forth His Son, born of the Virgin,
for what purpose? To redeem them that were under the law.
Oh, I'm so thankful that Jesus Christ, God's Son, God in the flesh, came.
He provided Himself.
Not only that, notice in verse number 20,
And hath given us understanding that we may know Him that is true,
and we are in Him that is true, even in His Son Jesus Christ.
This is the true God and eternal life.
Man, this is a powerful verse of Scripture.
We find that He provided Himself.
We find that He provided truth.
He has given us this truth here.
He talks about having understanding, knowing Him that is true.
The Bible says of Jesus Christ that He is truth.
He then speaks of His word as being truth.
This morning, we ought to rejoice in the fact that not only has He provided Himself,
but then He's provided truth.
If He did not provide and preserve this book, how would we know truth?
How would we even know that Jesus came?
But we have this record.
We have this book because He gave us truth.
We find that He's provided that to us.
We find that He provides understanding.
Did you see what it said there in 1 John 5 and verse 20?
It says, and hath given us an understanding.
I'm so thankful that He's provided this understanding,
and we understand this morning that this understanding comes through the Holy Spirit.
He says in John 16 and verse number 13 that He, the Holy Spirit,
He is the Spirit of truth, and He will guide us into all truth.
And we ought to be so thankful.
You say, how do you understand these things?
The Holy Spirit of God gives me understanding.
It's not that I'm smarter than somebody else.
It's not that you're smarter than somebody else.
It's not that we're, no, no, it's God that gives us understanding.
By the way, that keeps us humble.
Amen?
Keeps us humble.
We find here that He's provided Himself.
He's provided truth.
He's provided us with understanding.
I think about this in verse number 20.
Again, it says this, and we know that the Son of God has come
and hath given us an understanding.
Notice what this says, that we may know Him that is true.
Oh, I'm so thankful that He allows me to know Him.
He allows you to know Him.
You ever in a situation where somebody says,
hey, do you know so-and-so?
And really, if we were to answer the question accurately,
we would say we know about them.
We don't really know them.
Do you understand what I'm saying?
There's some historical figures, I mean, people that are alive today,
that we could say, hey, do you know so-and-so?
And you say, yeah, but we really just know about them.
We don't know them.
What is to know somebody intimately versus knowing about somebody?
Just a few weeks ago, I was at the funeral for Stephen Trout.
He was a dear friend of mine, and I heard people talking about
how they were friends with him, and really,
and I'm not saying this to be unkind or to be boastful or whatsoever,
but it had been years since they had talked to him,
and they really didn't know anything really knowing him.
They went to school with him. They knew about him.
It's a different thing when you know somebody,
when you know what somebody likes, when you know how somebody...
Do you understand what I'm saying?
And you know somebody.
And we think about this truth this morning,
that the all-powerful, almighty God of the universe
lets us know him.
That should just cause our mind to explode this morning, seriously.
Paul says in Philippians 3 that I may know him,
the power of his resurrection,
the fellowship of his sufferings he speaks about.
Begin to think about that truth this morning.
Moses said that I may know him.
I don't want to just know about God. I want to know him.
If I'm going to know God and I'm going to know him intimately,
it's because it's through this book.
How do I know him?
Well, he's revealed himself to us in the pages of Scripture.
I preached a message this week at school chapel
over at Fairfax Baptist Temple Academy,
and I preached from Proverbs 3.
In verse 26, the Bible says that the Lord shall be thy confidence.
And I said to those young people, I said,
how can you make God your confidence?
The Lord shall be thy confidence.
And I said this, part of the message, it wasn't the entirety of the message,
is that the only way God's going to be my confidence,
the one that I rely on, the one that I'm trusting,
is when I get to know him.
And I get to know him through this book.
And if the Lord shall be thy confidence,
and he's revealed himself to us in the pages of Scripture,
and we rejoice this morning because 1 John 5 and verse number 20
tells us that we may know him that is true,
and we, notice as it continues, are in him that is true.
Think about the truth that we can abide in him.
He said in John chapter number 15,
abide in me, and I in you.
And we can rejoice this morning
in the fact that I can abide in him.
See, when we close out this book, he ends it this way,
even in his son Jesus Christ,
this is the true God and eternal life.
I'm so thankful this morning that God has given us a record,
that God's given us his book, the Bible, the word of God.
And I must and you must recognize the peril of sin.
As we think about the importance of this book and the theme
and the subject of fellowship, and saying,
I want to have that fellowship with God,
and I see the product of answered prayer,
and praying according to his will is helping me to draw closer to him.
I don't want to hinder that fellowship.
And so John says, as God has given us a warning,
listen, sin is what's going to hinder that fellowship.
Oh God, help me to walk in the light.
Help me to walk in righteousness.
Help me to walk in holiness.
Help me to walk in truth.
Oh God, to not let anything between my soul and my Savior.
But then we can rejoice this morning
as we are reminded of the blessedness of abiding in him,
and we're reminded that God gives us this divine protection,
that we're kept by the power of God,
and that we can rejoice for his provision.
He provided himself, and thus provided salvation.
He's provided truth.
He's given us the word of God.
He's given us an understanding through the Spirit of God.
He's given us this morning the ability to know him,
and to abide in him.
That ought to cause us to rejoice greatly.
When we close a book like 1 John,
I hope that our study has caused us to desire
to draw closer to him,
that we would say, I want to walk in the light
as he is in the light.
And yes, I'm going to have fellowship with him,
but I'm also, according to the verse of Scripture,
going to have fellowship one with another.
What joy that God would give us such truth
and say, I want you to know these things.
Thank you, Lord. Thank you, Lord.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you this morning.
We thank you so much for loving us.
We thank you for the precious word of God.
We thank you, God, for how you have provided us
with a perfect preserved book.
We thank you for the Lord Jesus Christ,
for his perfect sinless life,
the perfect sacrifice.
We thank you for salvation through his name,
through his blood.
God, I pray that if there's one here this morning
that's not sure of heaven,
God, I pray that today would be the day of their salvation.
They'd get it settled.
They would not leave this place without knowing for sure
that heaven is their home.
God, I pray for every believer this morning.
Oh, God, I pray you would help us to beware,
to recognize the peril of sin.
Help us to walk with thee and to walk in the light
as you're in the light.
Help us, Lord, to rejoice as we remember your protection
and your provision.
I pray that you'd help us, Lord, to draw closer to thee.
Help us to come to that place, as the songwriter said,
that we truly would let nothing come
between my soul and my Savior.
Help us to abide in you.
Lord, use us for your honor and for your glory.
I pray that you'd work in hearts and lives as only you can
as we have opportunity to respond to you this morning.
I pray that every decision that is made would be honoring
and glorifying to thee.
We'll thank you for it.
Would you stand with me?