Oh, man, it's all true, but I'm thankful that the word of God continues
and says that he has a plan for us to be redeemed,
to be reconciled to God through the blood of Jesus Christ.
Isn't that wonderful?
And I'm so thankful this morning to be a Christian.
I'm thankful that the gospel came to my family,
that my dad heard the truth of the gospel.
And of course, the privilege that I have had to be saved
and then to walk with the Lord.
The reality is that when I trust that Christ and when you trust it,
Christ, is that we were delivered from the penalty and power of sin.
The penalty of sin is this for the wages of sin is death.
That's the penalty.
And that salvation, we were delivered from the penalty of sin.
That death that's being spoken of in Romans six is the second death.
And if you look at Revelation, the Bible tells us that
if we've been born again, that the second death has no power over us.
And that's glorious.
That is wonderful. Amen.
And it gives us a joy that's unspeakable.
It gives us a desire to live for him and to walk with him.
And it causes us to to to just interpret the things
in which we're dealing with on this earth, that I'm just a pilgrim and a stranger.
I mean, this world is not my home. Amen.
Aren't you thankful for that?
And what a blessing.
And we find that we were delivered from the penalty of sin.
We're also delivered from the power of sin.
The Book of Romans in the sixth chapter, we'll look at
at the end of the message this morning.
Paul says that sin shall no longer have dominion over you.
And what a blessing to know that God gives us the victory,
the strength to to overcome.
But the reality is that as we sojourn in this sinful world,
we still have this flesh.
Amen. Wouldn't you want to be wonderful
if when we got saved, like the flesh was just no longer part of us anymore?
I think it'd be a wonderful thing, wouldn't it?
You know, one day this mortal shall put on immortality.
Amen. This corruption shall put on incorruption.
What a blessing.
But until that day, you have the flesh and I have the flesh.
Amen. And Galatians five in verse number 17 tells us
that the flesh lusteth against the spirit.
They're at enmity, one against the other.
Have you found it to be so?
Amen. There's a great conflict that we deal with, right?
And we understand this conflict.
And the reality is that prior to salvation,
you really didn't have a conflict with your flesh.
Right. I mean, you just fed the flesh
and you just fulfilled the appetites of the flesh.
And there was no you were not quickened.
You were not made alive.
The spirit of God did not dwell within you.
And therefore you did not have the same conflict prior to salvation
that you currently do as a saved child of God dealing with your flesh.
You didn't have that conflict.
But now you have that conflict.
And we find that when we have that conflict
and we understand what God tells us with regard to that,
we can rejoice greatly that he's given us instruction
on how to deal with the flesh during this period of time
before we go to be with the Lord.
Now, one day, as I mentioned a moment ago, one glorious day,
we will be with him.
What a glorious day.
I shall see him. Amen.
These aren't just songs that cause you to kind of, oh, this is wishful thinking.
No, no. It is absolute truth that one day, one glorious day,
we will be in the very presence of God almighty.
Notice in First Corinthians 15, I want to begin reading
in verse number 39.
The study this morning is in Colossians three, and we'll make it there
in just a moment.
But notice in First Corinthians 15 in verse number 39,
all flesh is not the same flesh.
But there is one kind of flesh of men, another flesh of beast,
another of fishes and another of birds.
There are also celestial bodies and bodies terrestrial.
But the glory of the celestial is one in the glory of the terrestrial is another.
There is one glory of the sun, another glory, the moon,
another glory, the stars for one star differs from another star in glory.
So also is the resurrection of the dead.
It is sown in corruption.
Notice it is raised in incorruption.
It is sown in dishonor.
It is raised in glory.
It is sown in weakness.
It is raised in power.
It is sown a natural body.
It is raised a spiritual body.
There is a natural body and there is a spiritual body.
And so it is written.
The first man, Adam, was made a living soul.
The last Adam was made a quickening spirit referring to the Lord Jesus Christ.
Verse 46, how be it that was not first, which is spiritual,
but that which is natural and afterward that which is spiritual.
The first man is of the earth earthy.
The second man is the Lord from heaven and is excuse me, verse 48,
as is the earthy such one, they also that are earthy
and as is the heavenly, such are they also that are heavenly.
And as we have borne the image of the earthy,
we shall also bear the image of the heavenly.
Now this, I say, brethren, that flesh and blood cannot inherit
the kingdom of God, neither does corruption inherit incorruption.
Behold, I show you a mystery.
We shall not all sleep, but we shall all be changed in the moment
in the twinkling of an eye at the last trump for the trumpet shall sound
and the dead shall be raised incorruptible and we shall be changed
for this corruptible.
Notice this must put on incorruption.
Notice this mortal must put on immortality.
So in this corruptible shall have put on incorruption
and this mortal shall have put on immortality.
Then shall be brought to pass the saying that is written.
Death is swallowed up in victory.
Oh, death, where is thy sting?
Oh, grave, where is thy victory?
The sting of death is sin and the strength of the of sin is the law.
But thanks be to God, which giveth us the victory
through our Lord Jesus Christ.
Therefore, my beloved brethren, be steadfast, unmovable,
always abounding in the work of the Lord for as much as you know,
that your labor is not in vain in the Lord.
One day we're going to be with them.
The last trump is going to sound and we will be changed.
And this corruption shall put on incorruption and this mortal
shall put on immortality.
But until that day, you have the flesh and so do I.
So Colossians chapter number three.
To start this particular chapter is you'll be mindful
if you've studied along with us.
The Apostle Paul begins chapter number three by reminding
the people of God of their position.
Aren't you so thankful to understand your position in Christ
that we have been born again, that we're Christians, we're his children,
we've been adopted and we can cry Abba Father
and we have access to the very throne room of heaven
that that Jesus Christ is our advocate,
that we have this position.
And we understand that as we looked at those first few verses
of Colossians three, that when we're mindful of our position,
it will have an influence upon our pursuits, the things that I'm pursuing.
If you then be risen with Christ, seek those things which are above. Right.
We don't set our affection on these things of the earth,
but we're setting our affection on things above.
And so we find that Paul reminds these believers
to start this chapter of their position, their pursuits.
And now we find that as we enter into this next section in Colossians three,
that he Paul will provide critical instruction regarding our walk with God.
You know, I'm so thankful that God gives us truth
in his word with regard to how to walk with him.
How to behave ourselves.
What it is that pleases God and what it is that displeases God.
Aren't you thankful for that?
See, at times in our lives, maybe you've said it.
Maybe you've heard someone else say it.
I've heard scores of people say it when they seem to want to attack
biblical Christianity and they say it's nothing more than a list of rules
and do's and don'ts and so on and so forth.
But the reality is that I'm thankful that God in his infinite wisdom
and his grace and his mercy has revealed to us
the things that please him and the things that displease him.
For had he not provided us with those things, we would not know.
We'd be living and wondering, is this is this pleasing to God?
Is it not pleasing to God?
Paul says to the believers in Ephesus, prove that which is acceptable.
We're to prove all things.
Let the words of my mouth, right?
The meditation of my heart be acceptable in thy sight.
How do we know if it's acceptable in his sight?
And so Paul is going to enter into this critical text of Scripture
in which he deals with our walk with God.
As we examine this critical instruction this morning,
we'll be looking just at verses five through seven.
I want you to take note of a couple of things.
If you've already noticed in your bulletin this morning,
the title for the message is this, Crucify Your Flesh.
Crucify.
Your flesh.
Notice in v. 5,
Paul begins and says this,
"'Mortify therefore your members
which are upon the earth,
fornication, uncleanness,
inordinate affection,
evil concupiscence,
and covetousness,
which is idolatry.
For which things sake
the wrath of God cometh
on the children of disobedience,
in the which ye also walked
some time when ye lived in them.
Crucify your flesh."
I want you to notice as we look at this passage,
first of all, note how direct Paul is.
As we notice the statement that begins v. 5,
we find that the Apostle Paul
is using some very strong language.
He gets into the text
and he is using this strong language
from the beginning.
And he says,
"'Mortify therefore your members
which are upon the earth.'"
You say, man, that sounds kind of strong.
It is.
And we find these being very direct.
You know, sometimes we need to be direct with people.
Sometimes we need to be direct with ourselves.
Amen?
Listen, you go to the doctor
and you've been having some difficulties
and some problems,
and you just know that something
doesn't seem right within your body,
and you go to the doctor.
You want the doctor as they go
and they administer a whole host of tests
and they begin to analyze the results
and you want them to be direct with you.
What's going on, doc?
I mean, tell me what's going on.
Oh, everything's gonna be okay.
No, no, something's not right.
Be direct.
And Paul gets right after it.
The word mortify means to put to death.
It means to slay.
It really carries with it this context.
I want you to think about it in this regard.
It means this, to deprive of power.
How many of you have found that your flesh is powerful?
Yeah, your flesh has desires, amen?
And so when we're going to deprive of power,
and so he says, mortify.
Notice he says, therefore,
your members which are upon the earth.
What's he talking about?
He's talking about our flesh,
our members which are upon the earth.
Listen, at the moment of salvation,
if God so chose it to be so,
the moment you got saved,
he could have translated you directly to heaven.
At times, if we'd be honest with one another,
we'd say, I wish it were that way, right?
Because this world, man, sometimes it just gets, mm.
I don't know what that word is, but mm,
you know what I mean?
Are you following me?
You feel what I'm saying this morning, right?
And so the reality is that God hasn't chosen it
to be that way.
He says, you're in the world,
but you're not of the world.
He says that in that same passage in John 17,
as the Father hath sent me, even so send I you.
And so God in his infinite wisdom,
he has chosen that we as his people
are here as lights in a dark world.
You'd be mindful of the truth of John 13.
When Jesus washed the feet of the disciples,
why was it that he washed the feet of the disciples?
Because you get dirty in this world.
In that particular era, in that culture,
you would go and there'd be a bathhouse
in which you would go and you'd get bathed
and you'd get cleaned up,
but then you'd have to walk back to your residence,
and in so doing, as you'd wear those sandals,
your feet would get dirty.
You'd walk the same paths as all the other livestock walk,
and you could understand in your mind's eye
how that could be a dirty situation.
And we find that when Peter, he says,
no, no, no, Lord, you're not gonna wash me,
and Peter receives the answer from Jesus
that if I don't do this, then you're not any of mine,
and he says, well, then not my feet only,
but all of me, right, is that what he says?
What does Jesus say?
No, if you've already been washed,
if you've already been cleansed,
you've already had salvation,
then all we need to do now is wash your feet, why?
Because in this world, man,
we just have to live in this polluted world.
And if we don't deal with our flesh,
if we don't mortify our members which are upon the earth,
we're gonna deal with some real problems.
Understand, as we look here,
as we think about what was said earlier
when we talked about our position,
notice in verse number three what Paul says
to these believers in Colossae here.
He says, for ye are dead.
Now, that's positional, that's positional.
And so as we think about the positional truth
that Paul gives to these believers in verse number three,
for ye are dead, then we'd understand
that the practical response to that reality
of verse number three is that I'm to mortify, therefore,
our members which are upon the earth.
If I'm dead with Christ, if I'm dead,
then I need to then take that positional truth
and apply it practically in my life.
And the practical response to understanding
that ye are dead is that you mortify, therefore.
Remember, every time you see the word therefore,
you look and you find contextually why,
what is it that he's referring to?
The simple just quote or saying is when you see therefore,
find out what it's there for.
And he says, mortify, therefore,
your members which are upon the earth.
This is a personal responsibility.
Before Holly printed out the bulletin yesterday,
I asked her to change the title of the message.
Initially, I had entitled the message, crucify the flesh.
And the more I meditated upon the truth
and the more I prepared for the message,
I said, hey honey, you haven't printed
the bulletin yet, correct?
And she said, no.
I said, can you change that from crucify the flesh
to crucify your flesh?
Why?
Because it's a personal responsibility.
You understand this morning that I can't crucify your flesh
and you can't crucify my flesh.
Have you ever wanted to crucify someone else's flesh?
I'm not saying in a wrong way.
I'm not saying in an inappropriate way.
I'm saying that you've wanted to help them, right?
You see them walking in an erroneous way.
You see them fulfilling the lust of the flesh.
You see the enemy gaining an advantage
and you say, I wish I could do this for you.
But you know what?
You can't.
Because it's a personal responsibility.
Crucify your flesh.
Can you be mindful this morning
of what the Lord Jesus Christ said?
You don't need to turn there,
but perhaps you'd like to jot it down.
Matthew 5, 29 and 30.
I'm not gonna read the entirety
of either one of those verses.
But you'll be mindful of the verses
when I share with you what he says.
If your eye offends you, pluck it out.
If your hand offends you, cut it off.
You say, well, that's kind of strong.
Yeah, it is.
Just as Paul's instruction here,
mortify therefore.
I mean, put it to death, slay it.
I like the idea of depriving it of power.
Depriving it of power.
So we find, as we look at this instruction
and we begin in verse number five,
we find how direct Paul is.
He gets straight to the point.
I want you to also notice with me
how detailed Paul is.
See, in this passage of Scripture,
he's gonna call sin by name.
And by the way, if you think
you're gonna get away with it this morning,
just come back next Sunday.
Because the practicality of it
gets even more where the rubber meets the road.
You say, oh man, I dodged a bullet.
I'm not guilty of any of those sins.
Come back next week.
Because we'll deal with some more by name.
Right, because what's Paul saying?
Mortify therefore your members,
which are upon the earth.
Notice as we think about the detail,
he says this, fornication, uncleanness,
inordinate affection, evil concupiscence,
and covetousness, which is idolatry.
If we were to summarize the list
that's provided in verse number five,
perhaps we would summarize it by saying lust and greed.
Perhaps we'd summarize it by saying
impurity and covetousness.
But as we look, we find that Paul does not summarize.
We find that Paul uses details
and he's going to call sin by its name.
This morning, the first that's mentioned is fornication.
This word can be used very broadly
or it can be used very narrowly.
But in its broadest sense,
the word fornication means sexual immorality of any sort.
Sexual immorality of any sort.
And Paul begins there with fornication.
He then enters into the next word
that he uses, uncleanness.
Here again, dealing with sexual impurity,
dealing with lustful thinking.
Listen, do we not live in a society
in which we are bombarded every single day with these sins?
Is it not that we live in a society
that has made millions, billions of dollars
on these industries?
Why?
Because they know the desire of the flesh.
Why do they market things the way that they market things?
Because they know the desire of the flesh, right?
Listen, these folks in marketing, they're not dumb.
Really, the enemy understands
the way that our flesh operates.
My dad was preaching on.
Wednesday evening as he's going through Psalm 23,
and I'm enjoying the study, I trust that you are as well,
and I know that he's enjoying doing it,
and the reality is that he spoke about the sins
during the time of the life and ministry
of the Lord Jesus Christ,
and he spoke about the things that we deal with,
and really John summarizes it this way.
If we would look at sin as a whole,
it's really summarized in 1 John 2 and verse number 16,
it's the lust of the flesh, the lust of the eyes,
and the pride of life.
Within those three categories, you can fit everything,
and the lust of the flesh is serious.
So he says fornication, he says uncleanness.
Notice, inordinate affection.
Really, this carries with it the idea
of a depraved or evil passion.
Depraved or evil passion.
It is believed commonly that this particular phrase,
inordinate affection that would be used
in this particular era,
was really a way of speaking of homosexuality.
And no doubt, homosexuality is a depraved or vile passion.
Is it not?
You read Romans 1 and you understand.
Listen, homosexuality is nothing new.
It's not new for us in the 21st century.
I got a phone call from somebody while I was in Branson.
It was an unusual phone call,
and it turned even more unusual very quickly.
And that unusual phone conversation turned into questions
about various social things that are taking place
in our world that began to ask me about alcohol
and various things, and before long,
they began to ask me about the subject of homosexuality.
And they concluded, based upon their own understanding,
before I could even answer any question that they asked me,
they said this.
They said, well, you probably hate those people, don't you?
And I said, the reality is that I have no hate
for those people.
They're bound in sin.
I want them to be delivered by the Lord Jesus Christ.
Amen?
They need to be saved.
And they didn't understand all that I was saying.
It was a very, I'm telling you,
it was an unusual conversation.
I was standing in the park at Silver Dollar City
having this conversation, and I'm like,
what in the world is going on here?
I got a text message, call me as soon as you can.
I don't really know, none of you would even know
who this person is.
And this began to ask questions.
And listen, the common belief of religious,
quote-unquote, people is that someone that's caught up
in some sort of sin such as this, that we hate people.
We don't hate people.
We love people.
We desire to see people saved, amen?
And so, does it mean because we speak of what God's words,
I understand they're trying to label it as hate speech.
They're trying to use that against us,
but the reality is that when you tell somebody
of the error of their way,
is that hating them or loving them?
When you tell somebody of the error of their way,
and you tell them how that they can find forgiveness
and deliverance and how that they can have
that right standing with God,
is that hating them or is that loving them?
Oh, it's a message of love, amen?
And I'm so thankful that God has given us His Word.
And we desire to hold true to that which He's given us.
We find that the next phrase that's used there
is evil concupiscence.
It's not a, many of these words are not words
that we use or phrases that we use,
but this carries with it the idea of evil lusts,
specifically for that which is forbidden.
That's evil concupiscence,
this lust for that which is forbidden.
You understand that God has is that we look at His Word,
there are some things that He has forbidden us
from participating in.
Now here's the thing, He's not gonna make you not do it.
Amen?
Have you found it to be so?
Your flesh, remember those desires.
And you say that you're in, you fall,
you're in this situation,
you're saying I'm not supposed to be doing this.
How did I get here?
You ever wonder that?
Because you have the flesh, it's like I have the flesh.
We all have the flesh.
And so we find that He speaks about this evil concupiscence,
notice, to end the phrase, or to end the verse,
end covetousness.
Covetousness is dealt with all throughout the Scriptures,
we find it as the 10th commandment,
that we're not to covet.
We understand that here,
covetousness means greed, a want for more.
No contentment, really.
You know that we can be covetous,
and the reality is that 10th commandment of covetousness,
that single thing of covetousness
can cause us to break all of the other commandments.
And here's something that's interesting.
Did you notice the end of the verse in verse number five?
Here's what he likens it to, which is idolatry.
What do you think about when you think about idolatry?
Honestly, what do you think about?
Somebody tell me, what do you think about?
False god, a statue, right?
Yeah.
Psalm 135, the things that are made with the wood
and the things that are fashioned by man, right?
Those are the things you think about
when you think about idolatry, right?
You say, man, I don't have any idols.
I don't have anything like that in my house.
But Paul says covetousness, which is idolatry.
John says keep yourself from idols in 1 John.
And so we look here and we find that he says
that this covetousness is likened to idolatry.
Why is that?
Because the reality is that covetousness
will cause us that greed, that want for more,
will cause us to put things in the place of God.
Because I want something, whatever that something is.
Here, contextually dealing with the impurity
that is dealt with through all of these phrases
that are mentioned.
And that covetousness, he says it's idolatry.
Now, as we look at this passage of Scripture
and we notice as we look at verse number five
that Paul is very direct.
We find that Paul is very detailed.
And I ask myself this question and perhaps
you can ask the question this morning
or I'll ask it for you, why?
Why is it that Paul is so direct?
Why is it that Paul is so detailed?
Why is it that under the inspiration
of the Holy Spirit of God,
he had to use the words that he did?
You understand that every word of God is pure.
See, sometimes we don't want to crucify the flesh,
we want to coddle the flesh, right?
Because how many have ever heard that term
of comfort food, right?
You say, man, this is just gonna make me feel comfortable.
It's just gonna make me feel good, right?
Because I had a bad day, I had a whatever,
and then you have the comfort food
and then maybe you don't feel as good
as you thought you were gonna feel.
And especially if you get on the scale the next day,
you don't feel as good as you thought you were gonna feel.
Amen?
Holly got on the scale after we went on vacation.
She said, man, that wasn't good.
And I said, no vacation is good
unless you gain weight, amen?
And I got one suit I tried on,
it didn't fit me after going on vacation, you know?
I mean, it's just the way it works.
I'm gonna start working on that
and try to get that under control.
But the reality is that, listen,
we don't want to coddle our flesh.
We must crucify our flesh.
You know that I hate snakes.
There would be absolutely no reason
for you to keep a poisonous snake in your presence
and just allow it to be in your presence, right?
No way.
Well, I just kind of put that thing over in its place.
No, no, you better kill that thing, amen?
I mean, I'm being serious.
I know Dean stepped out.
I don't know where he went,
but it's a good thing he's not gonna get upset
with me this morning.
But you understand, I'm not trying
to simply relocate a poisonous snake.
I'm sorry, I'm not.
I'm trying to kill it.
I'm not trying to just coddle my flesh.
I need to mortify it.
I need to render it powerless,
to deprive it of its power.
And so why is it that Paul is so direct?
Why is it that Paul is so detailed?
I think for this reason.
Because Paul understood, number three this morning,
he understood how dangerous the flesh is.
He understood the dangers.
He understood how dangerous our flesh is.
Listen, we have an enemy.
And our enemy wants to devour us, correct?
He doesn't wanna just mess with us a little bit.
He wants to devour us.
He wants to destroy us.
And we find that as we look at the passage of Scripture
and we begin to understand how Paul is being very direct
and how Paul is being very detailed,
I can only conclude in my mind this morning
that it's because he understands the danger.
He understands how dangerous the flesh is.
Notice in verse number six of our text of Scripture,
it says this, for which things sake,
what is he talking about?
Those things that we just looked at in verse number five.
For those things, for which things sake, notice this,
the wrath of God cometh on the children.
of disobedience.
You understand that disobedience
leads to discipline.
What does the Word of God tell us?
You can read in Proverbs 3.
You can read over in Hebrews 13,
that whom the Lord loveth,
He chasteneth.
Amen?
In 1 Corinthians 11,
if we would judge ourselves,
but the reality is that as he goes through
and dealing there with the Lord's Supper,
he says for this cause,
why, they were eating and drinking unworthily
for this cause, many are sick and weakly among you
and some are asleep.
They've died.
I remember reading a book while I was in college
and the preacher that wrote the book,
and I don't remember the author,
but it was a preacher of yesteryear,
and he made this analogy as he dealt
with the sin in the life of a believer,
and he said this, he said that first,
God will bring conviction in your life.
And if you don't respond to the conviction,
God will bring chastening in your life.
And if you don't respond to the chastening,
God will bring a coffin in your life.
And I remember reading that when I was about 19 years old,
and I'm like, well, that's kind of strong, isn't it?
Begin to look at the truth of God's Word
and understand, listen, I'm thankful
that God is long-suffering.
I'm thankful that He's gracious and He's merciful
and He's ready to pardon.
His mercy endureth forever,
but you understand that our God is just,
and we must never, never mistake
God's long-suffering for God's approval, amen?
God never approved sin.
He died for sin.
What is it that Joseph said after Potiphar's wife
multiple times sought to cast her eyes upon her
and lie with me, lie with me, lie with me?
How then can I do this great wickedness
and sin against God?
See, that's how we gotta view it.
We gotta understand it in that fashion.
When David penned the repentant Psalm of Psalm 51
against thee, and thee only have I done this wickedness.
Restore unto me the joy of thy salvation
after he says, create me a clean heart.
And so we find that disobedience will lead to discipline.
Notice what he says here, the wrath of God.
I don't want God's anger or wrath.
Do you?
If you say, yeah, I'm signing up for that, you're crazy.
I mean, honestly, you are absolutely insane.
Read the Old Testament.
Read about how God judged.
Read 1 Corinthians 10.
These things are written for our example
and sample is what the word is there.
But read it and see how God judged.
And Paul says, for which things,
in the which, for which things sake,
the wrath of God cometh on the children of disobedience.
See, I'm no, as we understand this truth
and we understand God's righteousness
and we understand God's justice,
and we look at this and we understand
that he's speaking about the children of disobedience,
thankful, I'm not a child of disobedience anymore,
but if I behave in that manner,
then I'm going to also be in danger of God's judgment.
Amen?
I'm gonna be in danger of God.
What did God say to the children of Israel?
You know, many times we can,
the children of Israel, the Hebrew people,
they most represent us.
I mean, honestly, in so many ways.
You know what the Hebrew children thought
when they went into the land of promise?
They thought, man, look at how good we are
and we get all of this and it's so wonderful.
And God says, hey, listen, before you exalt yourself,
remember that because of the sin
and the iniquity of the people, they've been judged.
And by the way, note it down
that if you do the same things, you're gonna be judged.
Is that not, I mean, I know that's not, quote,
verse of the Bible, but in essence,
that's what God says to the children of Israel.
And what did they do?
They learned their ways.
They behaved in the same manner
in which the inhabitants of the land behaved.
And what happened?
Well, you read the book of Judges.
They were oppressed for long periods of time.
You read about in the books of history
of the Old Testament and some of the prophets as well
about how they were taken into captivity.
God's serious.
And Paul understood the danger.
So he talks about in verse number six
that disobedience will lead to discipline.
In verse number seven, notice where he says,
in the witchy also walk some time when you lived in them.
See, many times throughout the Word of God,
we'll see this phraseology of in times past, but now.
And we think here, though those words aren't all used,
he says, ye also walked some time,
in the witchy also walk some time when ye lived in them.
What's he talking about?
Their life prior to calvary, their life prior to conversion.
And here's the thing, the flesh has a desire,
and we understand that.
I've belabored that point this morning,
but if we understand that the flesh has a desire
and we understand that for whatever period of time
before we got saved, there were certain things
that our flesh gained an appetite for, correct?
And guess what?
Those things are going to continue
to be a thorn in your side.
Have you found it to be so?
Listen, I'm thankful that God can give us the victory,
and he can, and I'm thankful that God can deliver us,
and he will, but the reality this morning
is that when we understand what Paul is saying
in verse number seven, he's saying,
listen, in the witchy also walk some time.
These people that he's writing to,
perhaps some of them within the Church of Colossae,
they had been guilty of the very sins
that are mentioned by name in verse number five.
And when they had been guilty of those very sins
that are mentioned in verse number five,
Paul says, that's why you need to mortify your members
which are upon the earth,
because you had an appetite for those things,
and you have to have victory.
And the only way you're gonna have victory
is if you deal with the flesh.
How many of you like broccoli?
I like broccoli, it's like my favorite veggie.
How many of you like fruits and vegetables?
Listen, I like broccoli, I like cookies too.
Amen?
For a lot of our kids, if you put a cookie on a plate
and put some broccoli on a plate,
they're picking the cookie.
And guess what, sometimes we do the same thing.
Why?
Because I have an appetite for it, right?
How many of you have an appetite for sugar?
How many of you ever tried to cut sugar out of your diet?
You ever try to cut sugar out of your diet?
And you have this, listen, I am,
I can run with anybody for a one-week diet.
I'm telling you, I'm honest.
I can run a one-week diet like nobody's business.
I cannot have sugar at all for a whole week.
I can do the whole deal.
And then I'm like, let me just have a little bit.
Hey honey, now I ask Brianna,
hey Brianna, would you make a gallon of sweet tea?
And then I'm just gonna have eight ounces.
And before long, the whole gallon is gone.
I'm not talking about a week,
I'm talking about like a day and a half.
Why?
Because my body likes sugar.
Your flesh and my flesh likes to sin.
Paul understands the danger
and therefore he's direct and he's detailed.
Someone said this,
a church, a pastor was preaching on sin,
sort of like I'm preaching this morning.
And a man came to him after the service and said,
I don't think you need to be preaching this way
because sin in the life of a believer is different
than sin in the life of a lost person.
And the pastor with great wisdom said,
you're absolutely right, it's worse.
It's worse.
Amen.
Look at some passages with me in the book of Romans
if you will, Romans chapter number six.
Paul understood the dangers
and he gives us formula here.
Mortify therefore your members which are upon the earth.
Crucify your flesh.
In Romans chapter number six,
I want you to begin looking with me at verse number six
when Paul says this as he's writing the believers there,
he says, knowing this,
that our old man is crucified with him,
that the body of sin might be destroyed,
that henceforth we should not serve sin.
Skip down and look at verse number 11.
Likewise, reckon ye also yourselves to be dead indeed
unto sin, but alive unto God through Jesus Christ our Lord.
Let not sin therefore reign in your mortal body,
that you should obey it in the lust thereof.
Neither yield ye your members
as instruments of unrighteousness unto sin,
but yield yourselves unto God
as those that are alive from the dead
and your members as instruments of righteousness unto God,
for sin shall not have dominion over you,
for you're not under the law, but under grace.
Notice he says in verse number 11,
likewise,
and reckon ye also yourselves
to be dead indeed unto sin,
but alive unto God through Jesus Christ our Lord."
We're to be dead to sin,
but alive unto God.
This is a paradox of the Christian life.
And as I understand,
as he said in verse 6,
that my old man is crucified with Him,
that the body of sin might be destroyed,
that we should not serve sin.
Verse 17, look at it there.
Skip down and look at verse 17.
But God be thanked.
Notice when he says
that ye were the servants of sin.
You know, before you got saved,
you couldn't help yourself.
Honestly.
As much as you try.
That's why when we speak about salvation,
we say that it's not reformation,
it's transformation.
It's not that I'm trying to clean myself up.
It's not that I'm trying to go through
some program and whatever step program.
No. Salvation is transformation.
If any man be in Christ,
he is a new creature.
Old things are passed away.
Behold, all things are become new.
And it's a glorious transformation.
And so we find that prior to salvation,
we were servants of sin.
We could not help ourselves.
It says this,
but ye have obeyed from the heart
that form of doctrine which was delivered to you.
What's he speaking about?
He's talking about the Gospel.
You've obeyed the Gospel.
You've been saved.
You've been born again.
Now it says,
being then made free from sin,
ye became the servants of righteousness.
Now let me ask you,
if you're going to be a servant,
would you rather be a servant to sin
or a servant of righteousness?
Amen.
I mean, it seems pretty simple, does it not?
But if you're going to be a servant of righteousness
and not a servant of sin,
you better deal with your flesh.
You better reckon it to be dead.
Acknowledge it to be so.
Mortify therefore your members which are upon the earth.
Romans 7 verse 15.
Notice what Paul says.
See, Paul understood.
He gives us this passage of Scripture.
We often refer to it very passingly,
but I want to read it to you this morning.
As it's written,
it says in verse 15,
for that which I do, I allow not.
For what I would, that do I not.
But what I hate, that do I.
If then I do that which I would not,
I consent under the law that it is good.
Now then it is no more I that do it,
but sin that dwelleth in me.
For I know that in me,
that is in my flesh,
dwelleth no good thing.
For to will is present with me,
but how to perform that which is good I find not.
Can you relate to Paul?
You can relate to him, right?
Paul, I understand.
He says in verse 19,
for the good that I would, I do not.
But the evil which I would not, that I do.
Now if I do that I would not,
it is no more I that do it,
but sin that dwelleth in me.
I find in a law,
that when I would do good,
evil is present with me.
For I delight in the law of God
after the inward man,
but I see another law in my members,
warring against the law of my mind,
and bringing me into captivity
to the law of sin,
which is in my members.
Have you experienced this?
O wretched man that I am!
Who shall deliver me
from the body of this death?
I thank God
through Jesus Christ our Lord.
So then with the mind,
I myself serve the law of God,
but with the flesh, the law of sin.
Listen, I'm thankful that God gives the victory.
We talked about 1 Corinthians 15 and 57,
but thanks be to God which giveth us the victory.
Listen, the reality is that
we can relate with Paul.
We can look at this and say,
O wretched man that I am!
I mean, perhaps you're there right now
at this moment.
Perhaps you've been there this past week.
Maybe you'll be there this upcoming week.
Because why?
The fiery darts are going to be fired upon you.
The temptations to do evil,
the appeal to your flesh,
they're going to be there.
Mortify therefore your members
which are upon the earth.
For I know that in me that is in my flesh
dwelleth no good thing.
Your flesh is weak and my flesh is weak.
How foolish of us to think,
oh, well, I can just go over here
and experience this a little bit
and I'm going to be able to be strong.
There's a warning about that in 1 Corinthians.
In chapter 10.
You don't need to turn there.
We're going to look at some more stuff here
in the book of Romans.
But in 1 Corinthians 10 and verse number 12.
Wherefore, let him that thinketh he standeth
take heed lest he fall.
I've often used this analogy.
If a man's been saved
and he's saved out of alcoholism,
it'd be a really foolish thing
for that man to go to a bar to get a Coke.
Would it not?
Just make a choice not to go to that place.
Amen?
Because you know what you've dealt with
and you're going to go put yourself in that position
after years of being in bondage to that alcoholism
and you're going to put yourself there and say,
but I'm just going to get a Coke.
Get a Coke somewhere else.
Amen?
I mean, honestly.
It's foolish for us to put ourselves in positions
in which our flesh is going to receive that temptation.
That's why it's so imperative
that we walk in the very presence of God.
Listen, don't be embarrassed
by having to tell someone I can't go there.
It's just not good for me to go to that place.
It's not good for me to be exposed to those things.
I want to protect my eye gate.
Amen?
Don't be embarrassed by that.
Understand that you're mortifying your members.
You're dealing with your flesh.
And that's a good thing for us to do.
Romans chapter number 12.
Paul says this in verses one and two,
a very familiar passage of scripture.
I beseech you therefore brethren, by the mercies of God,
notice that you present your bodies a living sacrifice,
wholly acceptable unto God,
which is your reasonable service.
Notice this, and be not conformed to this world,
but be transformed by the renewing of your mind
that you may prove what is that good and acceptable
and perfect will of God.
Can I submit to you this morning
that if you've been saved out of a life of sin,
if you've been saved out of the world's philosophy
and the world's agenda and the world's thinking,
that it's really easy for you
to go back to worldly thinking?
It's a whole lot harder to get renewed in your mind.
Why?
Because you already know it.
You've already lived in it.
You already know the world's philosophy.
You already know the way that things,
do you understand what I'm saying?
And so this admonition in verse number two
of be not conformed to the world,
listen to this world,
the reality is that I've already come out of the world,
but that there's some things
that I still remember about the world,
and there's some things that my flesh very easily remember
and can get right back into, right?
It's a whole lot harder to say I'm gonna be renewed,
transformed by the renewing of my mind.
It requires that we spend time in this book.
It's like Paul said in Galatians two in verse number 20,
I am crucified with Christ.
Nevertheless, I live, yet not I,
but Christ liveth in me.
And he says this, he says,
the life which I now live in the flesh,
I live by the faith of the Son of God who loved me
and gave himself for me.
This morning, I believe that Paul,
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
was as direct and detailed in Colossians three
and verse number five as he was
because he understood the dangerous,
the fact that the flesh is dangerous.
He understood this danger.
And I wonder this morning,
do we understand the danger?
I believe this morning that the Holy Spirit of God
who reveals the truth lives within us.
Do you believe that?
And if he lives within us or since he lives within us,
he is able to enable us to apply the truth,
to live the truth because he lives within us.
You say, I'm just trying so hard.
Stop trying and start submitting.
Say, I'm just trying to do all this stuff.
Don't try to do it in your own power.
You're weak.
You're no match for Satan.
But as you walk in the Spirit,
we have this wonderful promise.
I mentioned Galatians five and verse number 17
where the Bible says that the flesh lusteth
against the Spirit.
But I want to close this morning
with this wonderful promise from Galatians five
in verse number 16.
Paul says, this I say then,
walk in the Spirit and ye shall not fulfill
the lust of the flesh.
You say, pastor, my flesh is lusting.
I know.
Don't feel like you're some weird person.
This battle that we have is a battle
that we have because of conversion.
And you're not unusual or weird
because you have this lust of your flesh.
the authority of the Word of God, if you walk in the Spirit, you shall not fulfill
the lust of the flesh." He goes on in this passage of Scripture and he says this in
verse 24, and they that are Christ's have crucified the flesh with the affections
and lusts. I ask you this morning, have you crucified your flesh? Maybe I should
say it this way, are you crucifying your flesh? I die daily. Listen, it's not a one
and done. I crucified my flesh back on whatever date. You better crucify that
bad boy again. You understand what I'm saying? He says, they that are Christ have
crucified the flesh with the affections and lusts. Crucify your flesh. I can't do
it for you and you can't do it for me. It's a personal responsibility. But Paul
speaks with such passion. He's so direct and he's so detailed because he
understands the dangers. And I wonder this morning, how many of us would say,
man, I need to deal with my flesh. I need to just let God be God and submit
myself to Him. See, we're to be strong in the Lord and the power of His might. Put
on the whole armor of God because we wrestle not against flesh and blood,
against spiritual wickedness in high places. And this morning you don't have
the power, neither do I, but the power lives within us. It's the Holy Spirit of
God. We need to resist. But before we can ever resist, we must submit. That's what
James says. Submit yourselves therefore to God. Resist the devil and he will flee.
Isn't that a wonderful promise? Listen, this morning Paul, very direct. And again,
if you say, man, I was able to get through that list without any problem,
come back next Sunday. Amen. Read ahead. You'll be like, man, if you're not here
next Sunday, I'm going to know that you read and you said, man, I don't want to
hear that message. That's going to hit way too close to home. Come back tonight.
We're going to look at Genesis chapter 20. You know what? Abraham, his flesh got
in the way in Genesis chapter 20. I'm going to deal with it tonight. The messages
will be related. And that's just God does that. I'm not smart enough to do all
that. But I hope that God would help us because each and every one of us, we deal
with the flesh. We deal with it. And we must mortify therefore your members
which are upon the earth. Let's pray. Father, how we love you this morning. How
we thank you for your word, for your instruction. God, I pray that somehow this
morning you've taken your precious word and you've ministered to your people. I
thank you for how you've ministered to my heart. And I pray that we would
crucify our flesh. That we'd understand the importance of this truth. Would you
work as only you can? We'll give you the glory. For it's in Christ's name we pray.
We just...