to make a difference, and Jude says of some having compassion, making a difference, and
I trust that God would use each of us to make a difference in our world, and we need a difference
in our world.
Amen?
And we are the light.
The Bible says that we're the salt of the earth, the light of the world, and what a
blessing to be the representatives, the ambassadors of the Lord Jesus Christ.
Joshua chapter number two, Joshua chapter number two this morning, and we have transitioned
from our first phase, if you will, for our theme for 2023, great is the Lord and greatly
to be praised, and really the first phase that we spent so many months on was discovering
God's greatness, and I'm so thankful that God has given us the complete word of God,
and He's given us within the canon of Scripture, He has revealed to us His greatness, and what
a wonderful truth that we can discover and make, be aware of as the psalmist said, I
know that the Lord is great.
Phase two, which we moved into last week, was declaring the greatness of God.
The psalmist says, I know the Lord is great, but this says, I will declare His greatness,
and what a great truth that we have of knowing how great our God is, but there's a world
that needs to know how great our God is, and we need to declare His greatness as we
finish up the calendar year, we will move into phase three when we deal with living
in light of His greatness, and how does His greatness, who He is, how great He is, how
does it impact how you live, how does it impact how I live, and that'll be phase number three,
but this morning is lesson two, message number two with this second phase, and last week
we looked at the proclamation of Jethro, and this week we're gonna look at the proclamation
of Rahab in Joshua chapter number two, and I understand as you study through the pages
of God's word, that there are many that proclaimed or declared the greatness of God, and I'm
not seeking to just be obscure for the purpose of being obscure, but I want to, as we look
at several of these examples, look at some folks that maybe we would not immediately
think of of people that declared the greatness of God. No doubt if I were to say to you this
morning, tell me some Bible characters that declared that God was great, Paul would be
on the list, and Isaiah, and Jeremiah, and no doubt Daniel would be on your list, and
Moses, and David, and so on and so forth, then I'm not saying that there's anything
wrong with any of those Bible characters that declared the greatness of God, in fact we
will study some of them. But you know it's impactful when you think about Jethro proclaiming
how great God is, and how Moses had an influence, an impact in his life, and he stands up and
proclaims that wonderful truth that we looked at last week, how he stands up and he makes
that proclamation after hearing all that God did and how God worked in the life of Moses
and in the children of Israel, and he says, now I know, he was convinced of, he had this
assurance of, as we come to Joshua chapter number two, really the text of scripture,
if we look at the entirety of it, we find that Joshua as he's preparing to enter into
and lead the children of Israel into the land of promise, that he sends two spies to the
city of Jericho. Now remember that Joshua was one of the twelve spies that was sent
by Moses into the land of promise, and that didn't work out so well, Joshua and Caleb
were the only two that brought back a faith-filled report, the other ten did not believe God,
they looked at the giants and they looked at the walled cities and said we're not able,
and they were discouraged and they influenced the entire nation of Israel, so much so that
when Joshua and Caleb stood up to still to calm the people and to tell them if the Lord
delight in us then God is able, they did not deny the existence of the giants, they did
not deny the fact that there were walled cities, they just knew how great God was and they
knew that God said and God would do. But we find that the people of Israel are ready to
stone Joshua and Caleb and they ended up wandering in the wilderness, but Joshua and Caleb were
too, I think about that wilderness wandering, the journeys, the forty years, and I think
about their expectation because they had the promise of God that they would enter into
the land of promise, and as they wandered along I think that they had their focus upon
seeing what God said that they would see, and Joshua now as Moses has died, he's the
leader humanly speaking of the nation of Israel, and he sends these two spies and he gives them
their responsibility to go there into Jericho. We find that the king of Jericho, the leader
in verse number two, is made aware of these two spies and what their mission is. They
organize a search party for the purpose of being able to find these spies and deal with
them accordingly, but according to verse number six, Rahab took them to the roof of her house
and she hid them with the stalks of flax and they were secure there, and we find that at
the end of chapter number two, the Bible tells us that these two spies, they return, according
to verses 23 and 24, and they bring back a report to Joshua and they deliver this message
to Joshua. But we find that between the spies entering and the spies returning, there's
this great interaction that is recorded for us between these two spies and this lady with
the name of Rahab. And as we look at this particular interaction from verses eight through
21 this morning, the focus of our study will be that portion of scripture, and we'll consider
this morning, as we did last week, the proclamation of Jethro, this morning, the proclamation
of Rahab. Notice with me, if you will, in verse number eight, we'll pick it up there,
the Bible says, and before they were laid down, she came up unto them upon the roof.
And so these two spies are there on the roof, I mentioned already in verse number six, that's
where they were safe, and she comes up to the roof and they're going to have this interaction,
this conversation. The Bible says in verse number nine that she said unto the men, I
know that the Lord hath given you the land, and that your terror is fallen upon us, and
that all the inhabitants of the land faint because of you. For we have heard how the
Lord dried up the water of the Red Sea for you when ye came out of Egypt, and what ye
did unto the two kings of the Amorites that were on the other side of Jordan, Sihon and
Og, whom ye utterly destroyed. And as soon as we heard these things, our hearts did melt,
but neither did there remain any more courage in any man because of you, for the Lord your
God, he is God in heaven above and in earth beneath. At the end of verse number 11 is
where you read that proclamation that we will focus our attention on this morning, where
Rahab says, for the Lord your God, he is a God in heaven above and in earth beneath.
As we look at this portion of scripture, I want you to notice with me, if you're taking
notes, number one this morning, notice what Rahab revealed. In verses eight through 11,
during this interaction, this conversation between Rahab and these two spies, we find
that Rahab revealed some things to them. In verse number 10, notice the phraseology where
Rahab says, for we have heard. That's not only Rahab, but that's the inhabitants there
of the city of Jericho, and we find that Rahab says we've heard, and she begins to explain
to these two spies what it was that they heard. Number one, they heard about the miraculous
Red Sea crossing. We read about that portion of scripture and that event that's given to
us and recorded for us in Exodus chapter 14, and what a mountaintop passage of scripture
Exodus 14 is, and you get to read about God's deliverance of his people out of Egypt and
how he miraculously parted the Red Sea, and how the children of Israel, they walked, the
Bible says, on dry ground, not mucky, muddy. No, it was dry ground. God worked a miracle,
and the Egyptians, they saw what happened, and they assayed to go after them, and God
caused the chariot wheels to come off, and they got stuck, and they were destroyed there
in the Red Sea, and God wrought wonderfully. In fact, in chapter 15 of the book of Exodus,
there's great rejoicing and singing that takes place, and here we find that Rahab,
one of the inhabitants of the city of Jericho, she says to these two spies, for we have heard.
What did we hear? We heard how the Lord dried up the water of the Red Sea. Notice where
it says, for you. The Lord did this for you when you came out of Egypt. Listen, I'm thankful
that God works for us. I'm thankful for what God does for us in our lives. And here Rahab
is saying, I understand, we have heard what God did for you, and I want you to notice
that she mentions about this miraculous Red Sea crossing and what a great miracle that
was, and we find that she continues in verse number 10 and speaks about the complete victory
over Sihon and Og, the kings of the Amorites, who were on the other side of Jordan, and
you can read back into the text within Numbers and Deuteronomy and read about the account
there and the victory, the complete victory that God gave. And so we find that it is a
as Rahab is having this interaction with these two spies,
that she reveals some things,
and first what she reveals is what she heard.
But then notice with me what she knew.
Now, we looked at verse number 10 to see what she heard,
but we look back at verse number nine to see what she knew.
What was the conclusion that she reached
based upon that which she heard?
Notice in verse number nine,
and she said unto the men,
"'Notice I know that the Lord hath given you
"'the land.'"
She knew that.
She was thoroughly convinced of that.
And notice that she says,
she uses the name Jehovah for God.
"'I know that Jehovah God, your God,
"'he hath given you the land.'"
And we find that she, Rahab, knew this.
She understood based upon that which she heard
and that which had transpired.
She knew, she was convinced,
and she reveals that to these two spies.
And then we notice the impact,
and notice in verse number nine,
the impact of what they heard and what she knew,
the impact, in verse number nine,
it says, "'And that your terror is fallen upon us,
"'and that all the inhabitants of the land faint
"'because of you.'"
Wow, that's impactful.
In verse number 11, it continues on.
Notice the phrase that says,
"'As soon as we heard these things.'"
I'm not sure, the Bible doesn't tell us
how word reached to the city of Jericho
with regard to the crossing of the Red Sea,
the miraculous event that took place
and God delivering his people from Egypt.
We do not know how they found out
about the complete victory there over Sihon and Og,
but they heard and they understood some things.
And the Bible says that as soon as we heard these things,
notice the Bible says this in verse number 11,
"'Our hearts did melt.'"
Our hearts did melt.
And it continues and says,
"'Neither did there remain any more courage
"'in any man because of you.'"
That's quite the impact, is it not,
of what they heard and what she knew,
the conclusion that she reached
based upon what she heard,
the Lord has given you the land,
that she tells these two spies
as she's revealing to them the condition, if you will,
the pulse of the people of Jericho
because of what's transpired.
Now, remember, the people of Jericho,
they're in a pretty nice, defensed, walled city,
are they not?
In fact, we read about the conquering of Jericho,
that particular city, and the walls
as they come past them about and so on and so forth.
And we find that as we look at this passage of Scripture,
and we understand that there were 10 spies
that had been sent out by Moses,
and they were concerned about the walled cities,
but these that are within the walled cities,
because of what they heard God did and how God worked,
they say that, "'Our hearts did melt,
"'neither did there remain any more courage
"'in any man because of you.'"
Wow, I wonder this morning,
as we notice in our text of Scripture,
what Rahab revealed to these two spies,
and the impact that the truth had
upon the inhabitants of Jericho,
the impact that it had on them,
that God would deliver them through the Red Sea,
that God would give them complete victory in Sihon and Og,
and how it impacted them, that their hearts did melt,
that the inhabitants of the land fainted because of them,
that they had no courage left in them.
I wonder, on the opposite side this morning,
how does it impact you and how does it impact me
when we see what our God's able to do?
Because you know what it should do?
It should give us faith.
It should give us expectation.
It should cause us to anticipate what is God going to do?
And we think about the impact on the inhabitants
of the land, but if we were to contrast it this morning,
when you think about those 10 spies,
and we know that it happened 40 years previous
when those 10 spies, they go in and they see the giants
and the walled cities and all that they see,
and they're discouraged and they are responding
in just a terrible way.
And God, in fact, says in Numbers 14,
when he's speaking to Moses,
how long will it be, e'er my people believe me?
All that God did for the children of Israel,
they experienced it firsthand,
and many of them had no faith and no courage,
and they weren't willing to go forward,
but yet the inhabitants of the land,
when they heard what God did, they were afraid.
They had no courage.
I wonder this morning, when we hear the wonderful accounts
of what God has done, when you read your Bible,
when you hear the preaching and teaching of God's word,
when you see what God is doing in the lives of others,
does it encourage you this morning?
Does it cause you to have your faith increased?
See, this morning, we're to live by faith, are we not?
The just shall live by faith.
How do we have faith?
How do we have our faith increased?
So then faith cometh by hearing,
and hearing by the word of God.
We know that the Bible says, for by grace are you saved
through faith, and that not of yourselves is the gift
of God, not of works as any man should boast,
but after we're saved, we're to live by faith.
We're to be people of faith.
You know, as God has given us the account here
in what's being revealed to these two spies from Rahab,
and we see the impact and the influence
that the report had upon those inhabitants,
I just wonder this morning, as we would look
at our own lives, as we would evaluate ourselves,
we ought to be some people of faith.
We ought to be some people that trust God,
that believe God.
Listen, we should not hear the reports that are going on
in our world today, and seeing the things that are going on,
and saying, oh, woe is me, we're so defeated.
No, no, we're on the winning side.
If God before us, who can be against us?
And we are more than conquerors through him that loved us,
and we understand this morning
that we are able to have victory,
but thanks be to God which giveth us the victory
through our Lord Jesus Christ.
Listen, I'm thankful that one day I'm gonna go to heaven,
but reality is that we can have victory
even here upon this earth.
God doesn't expect for you or for me
to live defeated Christian lives.
He doesn't expect us to live under the circumstances.
He doesn't expect us to live by sight.
No, we're to live by faith.
And as we read the biblical content
that he's provided us with,
that he gives us those truths
so that we would have our faith increase,
so that we would trust him, so that we would prove him.
Our God is trustworthy.
We sang this morning, great is thy faithfulness.
Aren't you thankful that God is faithful?
I'm thankful this morning that God will never forsake you.
He'll never forsake me.
I'm thankful that God is at work.
And this morning, as much as we can see
from the text of scripture,
the impact that was upon the inhabitants
of the land of Jericho, of the city of Jericho,
I just wonder this morning,
how does what God is doing and has done,
how does that impact you and I this morning?
Number two, if you're taking notes,
we notice, first of all, what Rahab revealed.
Number two, notice what Rahab declared.
We've already made mention of it
at the end of verse number 11.
This great declaration of Rahab,
where she declares to these two spies,
she says at the end of the verse,
verse number 11, for the Lord your God.
Now, it makes it very clear and very plain
who she's speaking of.
She's not speaking of any of the false gods of the land.
She's not speaking of any of those idols
that she would be aware of,
that the inhabitants of the land,
remember, they're warned, the children of Israel
were given warning about entering into the land
and the idols and the false idolatrous worship
that they would be faced with.
But here we find that Rahab says, for the Lord your God,
notice what she says, he is God in heaven above
and in earth beneath.
What a great statement, a great proclamation,
as she makes this declarative statement,
as she understands all that she has been made aware of
and all that she has grasped
as she's looking at these events that have unfolded
and she reaches this wonderful conclusion
and she declares with great certainty
that the Lord your God, he is God in heaven above
and in earth beneath.
You know what I think she's saying?
He's not like any other small G-O-D.
Moses, God speaks to Moses and says
that their rock isn't like our rock.
And I think what Rahab is recognizing,
what Rahab is declaring here is that yes,
I'm familiar with other quote-unquote deities,
I'm familiar with other idols and the false worship
and all of the pagan idolatry that's in the land,
but they're not like your God.
It's a wonderful proclamation.
This morning, we serve the living God.
Listen, we ought to rejoice this morning
in understanding who we.
We serve.
I know that it's typical that during the resurrection service and that Resurrection Sunday, Easter
Sunday is referred to it, that we'll sing those songs about He lives and Christ the
Lord is risen today and up from the grave He arose, but you understand that every single
Sunday we meet because we serve a risen Savior.
We meet on Sunday because it's the Lord's day, it's the first day, it's the day of the
resurrection and we meet because we serve a risen Savior.
And listen, our God that we serve, He is alive.
He is active.
He is able and this morning when we understand that, when we see what this proclamation is
from Rahab and we say, yes, that's my God.
He is the one that's able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think.
He is the one that is actively working in our world today.
He's the one that would use me and would use you to bring honor and glory to Himself.
Man, what a God we serve.
It's a privilege to know the God that we serve.
Listen, there are a lot of people around the world that are blinded.
The Bible says that the God of this world in 2 Corinthians chapter number 4, He had
blinded the minds of them that believe not, lest the light of the glorious gospel should
shine in unto them.
And I'm thankful this morning that God in His amazing grace and His mercy, He allowed
me to know Him.
He allowed you to know Him.
I wonder this morning, how did you first learn about God?
You know, sometimes I ask people if they're sure that they're going to go to heaven when
they die and they say, oh yeah, I'm a Christian.
Tell me a little bit more about that.
Well, I've just always been a Christian.
I was born a Christian.
You're not born a Christian.
You're born in enmity with God, biblically speaking.
And we begin to think about when the Lord made Himself known to us.
Some of us got saved young in life.
Some of us got saved in our middle ages, if you will.
Some got saved older in life.
But I wonder this morning, as we think about this proclamation, what Rahab declared to
these two spies in verse number 11, I wonder when it was in your life that you recognized
that the Lord God Jehovah is the only God.
And He is the only Savior.
He's the only way.
See, for some, you were taught that from the youngest of age.
For some in our church, those little children that are in the nursery and then go into the
children's church and are here for student ministries, they're learning from the earliest
of days who God is.
But, you know, when I was their age, when I was a young teenager, I didn't know who
the God of the Bible was.
I had no idea.
And some of you can relate.
Some of you can understand that you did not know who Jehovah God was.
But I wonder this morning, as we think about this truth and we think about this, what Rahab
declares to these two spies, I wonder this morning, when did you understand who Jesus
is, who God is?
And are you thankful this morning that He's made Himself known to you?
You think about the truth of the Apostle Paul in Athens, and he says that they're superstitious
and they had all of those various monuments and what have you, and they had this altar
to the unknown God.
And Paul says, as he goes in and speaks to those people, speaking about that particular
altar, he says, Him declare I unto you.
Listen, there was a time in your life, there was a time in Rahab's life where she recognized
that there's something different about the Lord your God.
There's a time that we realize, listen, God is true, God is real.
And I wonder, after we've recognized that, after we've been saved and we've been born
again by the grace of God, I wonder how often we're declaring how wonderful He is.
I wonder how often those words pass through our lips about how He's a wonderful Savior
and that we would lift up and exalt His name.
We notice in the text of Scripture what Rahab revealed.
We notice what she declared.
And I want you to notice with me number three what she requested.
Notice what Rahab requested.
In verse number 12, she'd made that great declaration in verse number 11.
And then she says, now therefore.
Notice what she says in verse number 12, I pray you, swear unto me by the Lord since
I have showed you kindness that you will show also, that you will also show kindness unto
my Father's house.
And notice she says, and give me a true token.
And that you will save alive my father, my mother, my brethren, my sisters, and all that
they have and deliver our lives from death.
The men answered her, our life for yours if you utter not this our business.
And it shall be when the Lord hath given us the land that we will deal kindly and truly
with thee.
Then she let them down by a cord through the window, for her house was upon the town wall
and she dwelt upon the wall.
She said unto them, get you to the mountain, lest the pursuers meet you.
Hide yourselves there three days until the pursuers be returned.
And afterward may you go your way.
The men said unto her, we will be blameless of this thine oath, which thou hast made us
swear.
Behold, verse 18, when we come into the land, thou shalt bind this line of scarlet thread
in the window, which thou didst let us down by.
And thou shalt bring thy father, thy mother, thy brethren, and all thy father's household
home unto thee.
And it shall be that whosoever shall go out of the doors of thy house into the street,
his blood shall be upon his head, and we will be guiltless.
And whosoever shall be with thee in the house, his blood shall be on our head, if any hand
be upon him.
And if thou utter this our business, then we will be quit of thine oath, which thou
hast made us to swear.
Verse 21, she said, according unto your words, so be it.
She sent them away and they departed, and she bound the scarlet line in the window.
As we look at this request that is made in her response to the agreement, we find that,
I would say this, that her faith is evidenced by her actions.
She truly believed what she declared.
She believed, as she said in verse number nine, I know that the Lord hath given you
the land.
She says in verse number 12, that I pray you, swearing to me by the Lord, since I have showed
you kindness, that you will save us alive, as you get into verse number 13.
And we find that she was thoroughly convinced, she was believing what she had declared, that
they truly were going to come in and conquer.
She's concerned.
We find that there's a plea that she gives, a plea for protection.
I want you to understand that she's not just concerned for her own self.
She's concerned for her family.
She's concerned for others.
And as we would make a spiritual application from this passage of scripture this morning,
and we'd understand the request that she's making to these two spies and the plea for
protection, I would say to you this morning that as we consider the application of being
saved, of being born again, that listen, if we're saved this morning, we ought to have
a concern for others.
We ought to have a burden for someone else to have salvation through the Lord Jesus Christ.
Why?
Because we understand that apart from being saved by the blood of Jesus Christ, man is
going to die and enter into a Christless eternity where they will spend forever in a place called
the Lake of Fire.
And we ought to have a burden that others...
That burden starts with our own family.
I think about the truth in the book of Luke as the interaction of Lazarus and the rich
man.
And the rich man is in hell and he's concerned about his brethren.
And what does he say?
He says, let Lazarus go back and speak to them because I don't want them to come to
this place, this place of torment.
We understand that in the text, his belief, that rich man's belief is that if one were
to rise from the dead, that his brothers would believe, but it's so clearly spelled
out in that portion of scripture that they have Moses and the prophets.
If they won't believe that, then they won't believe though one rose from the dead.
You know what that tells me?
There's power in this word.
We're born again, not of corruptible seed, but of incorruptible by the word of God, which
liveth and abideth forever.
I'm so thankful that God uses his word.
He's given us his complete canon of scripture and we can rest assured this morning that
he uses his word.
And as we look at her plea for protection, it's not just personal.
She's concerned for others, her family, and she's desiring that they would have this deliverance
when they would come into the land, that they would be delivered from death.
You know, so many people today, even as we would look at the actual understanding of
Joshua 2 with regard to the content, the physical death that would come to the inhabitants
of Jericho.
You know, there are a lot of people that we come into contact with every single day of
our lives.
that they are concerned about their physical well-being.
They're fearful of dying physically.
But so often there's little thought
that's given to the second death.
And this morning, as much as people would wanna be spared
from physical death, and we've seen in recent years,
not only in our country, but around the world,
we have seen how that self-preservation has been obvious
that people are so concerned about life
and being able to protect themselves.
I'm not saying that we should be haphazard.
I'm not suggesting that we shouldn't be concerned
about our health, but what I'm saying this morning
is that the immediate context of what we're dealing with
is the physical death, but we ought to understand
this morning that there is something that's far greater,
and that's the second death.
Notice there's an agreement that is made,
and the explanation is given in verses 14 through 20.
I will not read all of the verses of Scripture again
as I've read them just a moment ago,
but I want you to see a couple of things in particular.
Number one, I want you to notice in verse 18,
the Bible says, behold, when we come into the land,
listen, there was a certain expectation
that these spies had.
There was an understanding
that they were going to be returning,
that God did promise to give them the land,
and they would be returning.
It says, when we come into the land, notice what they say,
thou shalt bind this line of scarlet thread in the window,
which thou didst let us down by.
I want you to think about that line of scarlet thread.
In fact, there are records all the way dating back
to the first century where people, theologians and scholars,
if you will, would look at this scarlet thread
as a picture representing the very blood
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And so often as we look at the Old Testament
and we look at the typologies
and we look at the prophecies that are given,
there's no doubt in my mind that when you think
about this line of a scarlet thread,
that yes, this would identify her place,
but it also would reveal her faith.
And we find that she was given this instruction
in verse number 18.
The instruction not only was given with regard
to binding the line of scarlet thread in the window,
but notice what it continues to say in verse 18 and 19.
It says this, and thou shalt bring thy father
and thy mother and thy brethren
and all thy father's household home unto thee.
Verse 19, and it shall be that whosoever shall go out
of the doors of thy house into the street,
his blood shall be upon his head and we will be guiltless.
And whosoever shall be with thee in the house,
his blood shall be on our head if any hand be upon him.
As we begin to look at this verse of scripture
in verses 18 and 19 and think about the agreement
that is made that is explained here,
we find that not only do they speak about binding
this line of scarlet thread,
but we find that they make it abundantly clear
that there's only one place of safety.
There's just one place of safety.
What a great picture.
I think about the truth of God's word
with regard to even in the earliest pages
of the Old Testament pointing to the truth
of being one place for safety, for refuge.
I think about the ark.
The ark.
There's just one place of refuge, just one place of safety.
Eight people survived the flood, God's judgment.
All eight of those people were in the ark.
They were in the ark.
I think about the Passover and I think about the truth
of the instruction that God gives to the initial,
the immediate in the book of Exodus
with regard to the applying of the blood
and the 10th plague, the death of the firstborn.
And I find that when that Passover was instituted
that there was but one way to have safety,
to have deliverance.
If someone said, well, I understand what Moses said.
It's not a matter of ignorance.
It's just a matter of I'm gonna do it my way.
I think that I could do it this way.
I think I could change this and it doesn't,
why does it really have to be that way?
Because that's what God said.
So often people want to fight with God
instead of just submitting to God.
I think about this one, what about the brazen serpent?
Because of the complaining of the people,
God sent forth fiery serpents.
They were crying out.
God then instructed Moses to make a brazen serpent
and to fashion that serpent upon a pole
and to set it in the midst of the camp.
And he said that when somebody was bitten
that if they looked, we sing the song,
look and live, my brother, live.
Look to Jesus now and live, why?
Because it's a picture.
Jesus in fact referenced it in the book of John.
And we find that that brazen serpent,
somebody could have gotten bitten
by one of those fiery serpents
and they could try any way they wanted to,
they could do anything else in their power,
but if they didn't look to that brazen serpent,
they were gonna die.
People died.
But yet we find that there was just
a single place of safety, the ark.
There was just one way to spare death during the Passover.
That was in following precisely what God said
with the application of the blood.
We find that with the brazen serpent,
there's just one way to avoid death by those fiery serpents.
And we find it so true as you come to the New Testament
and understand the truth of the gospel,
that there's just one way to get to heaven.
We sing the song, one way God said to get to heaven,
Jesus is the only way.
Why do we say that?
Do we say that because we're narrow-minded?
Do we say that because we're just not
willing to accept other ideas or thoughts?
No, no, we say that because God himself said it.
Because the Bible says that Jesus spake and said,
I, singularly, I am the way
and the truth and the life.
No man cometh unto the Father but by me.
I understand this morning that there are many
that are changing that idea and they're saying,
well, you just need to be sincere in what you believe.
You just need to, no, no, you can be sincere
about whatever but be wrong.
There are many people today that are sincerely wrong.
It's not a matter of questioning their sincerity.
It's in what they're believing.
And this morning, we find that as this agreement
is made between these two spies in Rahab,
that they make it abundantly clear to her
that she had to bind this line of scarlet thread,
that there's only one place of safety,
just one place of safety this morning.
It was only those that would be in the house
that would be spared death.
Only those that were in the ark were spared death.
And I wonder, as the New Testament verbiage is used,
that we are in Christ.
I wonder this morning, are you in Christ?
Have you trusted the Lord Jesus Christ
as your personal Savior, understanding that you're a sinner
and that He is the only Savior?
If so, you have the assurance of heaven.
If not, today is the day of salvation.
What a joy.
We find that the evidence of Rahab's faith
is given to us in verse 21, where the Bible says that as,
now think about, get in your mind the picture
of what happened, she lets them down over the wall there,
according to verse number 15, and she let them down,
and then there's this conversation that takes place,
and they make the terms of the agreement.
And then it says in verse 21,
that according unto your word, so be it,
this is her speaking to them,
she sent them away and they departed.
And notice what it says,
she bound the scarlet line in the window.
You know what's significant to me about that?
She did it immediately, without delay.
Some people you talk to about Christ,
they say, let me think about it,
let me get back to you on that.
I'm not saying that I would ever twist anybody's arm,
but the Bible does say that today is the day of salvation.
We don't know what's on tomorrow.
You don't know what's on tomorrow.
Boast not thyself of tomorrow, in fact, the proverb says.
Why?
We don't know what a day will bring forth.
And so we find that she immediately puts this scarlet line,
this line of scarlet thread in her window.
And I want you to understand contextually,
in the book of Joshua,
they're not marching around the city at this point.
Understand they've not even crossed the Jordan River yet.
When the spies are sent,
they've not yet crossed the Jordan River,
and yet Rahab was so thoroughly convinced
that she put that line in her window,
that scarlet thread, immediately.
Now, that scarlet line, that scarlet thread,
that would, I mentioned already, identify her place,
but it also would reveal her faith.
I wonder, the Bible doesn't tell us,
and so it's just a I wonder type of a situation,
but I wonder if anyone asked Rahab,
what do you got that scarlet?
thread hanging out of your window for? Have you ever thought that? I mean, I
would probably ask. Rahab was in a position, she was there, her house was
a prominent place, and no doubt people knew who she was. In fact, when the Bible
talks about those spies entering in, where did the King of Jericho,
where did the Serf party first went? To her house. Why? Because they knew that
that's where the spies went. She tells them that they were sent out and so on
and so forth, but we find that she then has this scarlet thread that's
hanging out of her window. Hey Rahab, what's that scarlet thread for? I'd like
to think that at least somebody asked her that question, and I'd love to hear
how Rahab would respond to that question. Now, the Bible doesn't give us the record
of any of those types of interactions, but this morning, I want you to
understand that we as New Testament believers, no, we don't put a scarlet
thread out our window, but God has given us a responsibility to go and declare
who He is, to be His representatives, His ambassadors. We find this morning that
even as these young people just did a wonderful job singing that song called
to make a difference, understand this morning that each and every one of us
have been called to make a difference, to take up the truth of the gospel and
proclaim it to a lost and dying world. Why? Because we know the truth, and we
know that He's given us the mission, the responsibility. I want you to just
briefly go over, if you will, to Joshua chapter number 6, and I want you to see
that as we come to this chapter, we find that God gives the instruction. They've
already entered into the land, they've set up the memorials, the circumcision
of the people has taken place, and Jericho would be the first place that
they come to, and the Bible says that Jericho was straightly shut up because
of the children of Israel. None went out, none came in, according to verse number
1. The instruction is given with regard to encompassing the city about and all
that would take place, and all of that is given, but I want you to jump down all
the way to verse 17, if you will. The Bible says, "...and the city shall be
accursed, even it and all that are therein to the Lord." Notice what it says,
"...only Rahab the harlot shall live, she and all that are with her in the house,
because she hid the messengers that we sent. And ye, and any wives, keep
yourselves from the accursed thing that you make yourselves accursed when you
take of the accursed thing, and make the camp of Israel a curse and trouble it." We
find that the walls fell down flat, according to verse number 20. In verse
number 22, notice the Bible says, "...but Joshua had said unto the two men that had
spied out the country, Go into the harlot's house," who is that? That's Rahab,
"...and bring out thence the woman, and all that she hath, as ye swear unto her.
And the young men that were spies went in, and brought out Rahab." Aren't you
thankful for chapter number 6 that gives us the conclusion of what we read
in chapter 2? It says that they brought out Rahab, notice, "...and her father,
and her mother, and her brethren, and all that she had, and they brought out all
her kindred, and left them without the camp of Israel. And they burnt the city
with fire, and all that was therein." I want you to understand, look at verse 25,
"...and Joshua saved Rahab the harlot alive, and her father's household, and all
that she had. And she dwelleth in Israel even unto this day, because she hid the
messengers which Joshua sent to spy out Jericho." We notice the the proclamation
of Rahab, but I want you to see that the quote-unquote end of the story for Rahab,
we understand that she's in the genealogy of the Lord Jesus Christ, we
understand that she's mentioned in the book of Hebrews, and also in the book of
James, understand she's never given any kind of commendation for any dishonest
statements that she made, but always for her faith, and understand this morning
that the spies, they came back, and they took her out. Listen, one day my Savior's
coming back, and he's taking me out. Amen? Listen, the Bible tells us that Jesus is
coming again, and listen, if you're saved this morning, if you've trusted Christ as
your Savior this morning, understand that Jesus said, I will come again. And what's
he gonna do? I'm gonna, he says, that you're gonna be with me forever. Amen? The
Bible says that the dead in Christ shall rise first, then we which are alive and
remain shall be caught up together in the clouds to meet the Lord in the air.
And what a wonderful promise. Listen, that's my expectation, that's my end, is
that I'm gonna meet my Savior face-to-face. And that period of time
between Rahab having that interaction with those spies, and making that
proclamation that she made where she declares who she understood God to be,
and then she put that scarlet thread in her window, yes, identifying her place, but
more importantly, revealing her faith. And I want you to think about Rahab. Listen,
the Bible tells us in verse number one of chapter six that all the city was
shut up, no one went out, no one came in. But I think Rahab had a different
perspective. I think for the inhabitants of Jericho, listen, when the nation of
Israel compassed the city, there were probably all kinds of mixed thoughts as
to what was going on. But I think Rahab was anxiously awaiting. You know why? She
knew. She knew that her life would be spared. She knew that God had given the
land to the people of Israel. She understood all of those things, but she
had an expectation. And they marched around day number two. Can you imagine?
Again and again, and all that takes place, and then when those walls fall down
flat, God miraculously allowed for her house not to fall. It's amazing. Joshua
sent those messengers, and they brought Rahab and all of her family that was
there out. There's one place of refuge, of safety. This morning, we see the
proclamation of Rahab. She understood who God was, who God is. This morning, we see
all of the events that unfold with this interaction, and how encouraged we are.
And I just wonder, how are we doing on declaring, on proclaiming how great our
God is? Are we more like the 10 spies that just always kind of doubting, and
uncertain, and just kind of floundering around, and living by sight? Or are we
recognizing that God is able, that God has a plan, and God has a purpose, and
God will use us for His honor and for His glory? We serve a great God. He is God
above. He is the Lord God Almighty. He lives, and He reigns, and He will reign
forevermore. The Bible says, the Lord God omnipotent reigneth. And I'm so thankful
to serve a risen Savior. Let's pray together. Father, we love You. We thank
You for loving us. God, I pray this morning that if there's one that's
unsure of heaven, they've never trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as their personal
Savior. God, I pray that today would be the day of their salvation. I pray, Lord,
that if You would move and work in that individual's life, whether they're here
locally or tuned in via live stream, God, that they would not delay, that they
would respond in faith, and obedience, and trust the Lord Jesus Christ, His
finished work at Calvary, His death, burial, and glorious resurrection. They'd
be saved by the blood of Christ. Lord, I pray for every child of God. Lord, I
wonder this morning how Your truth truly impacts us, how understanding who You are
impacts the way that we live our lives. Are we actively proclaiming and
declaring to others how great You are? I pray, Lord, that You would help us to be
challenged by the life and testimony of Rahab. Lord, help us to have that kind of
faith. Lord, help us to expect, to anticipate Your soon return. Help us to
be busy about what You've called us to do. I pray that in these few moments of
invitation that You have Your will in way. You'd move and work in hearts and
lives as only You can. We'll be careful to thank You for all that You'll do. For
it's in Christ's name we pray. Would You stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are
closed, end of each of our services.