and this is our final message from our study throughout the year. Our theme of
course for 2020 looking unto Jesus and what a blessing as we've studied through
the book of Hebrews I trust that it's been a tremendous blessing to you as it
has been for me and it is certainly a little unusual this year it's the 29th
of November and we're finishing up the book in which I've been preaching
through on Sunday mornings and typically it's in December when I'm kind of
rushing along to try to finish up and so a little different of a feeling this
year and so I trust to be a blessing to you last week we looked at Hebrews 13
verses 7 through 17 and as we studied that portion of this chapter we were
confronted with the importance of praise of course we understand throughout the
Word of God that we have been instructed we have been given many examples of the
importance of praising the Lord and rejoicing greatly and we have many
reasons to rejoice we serve a wonderful God who is good all of the time and he
has revealed himself to us in his precious Word and what a blessing it is
of course as we read through the Psalms even as I mentioned last week we have
many opportunities to read and to be confronted with the rejoicing of the
psalmist and how encouraging it is to read through the book of Psalms and to
read the individual Psalms and to see how the the psalmist is rejoicing
greatly and he's declared even as I mentioned on Sunday evening last week a
number of times he declared that I will rejoice I will sing praise and we need
to have that same perspective in verse number 15 of Hebrews 13 the Bible says
by him therefore let us offer the sacrifice of praise to God continually
that is the fruit of our lips giving thanks to his name last week I preached
the message our lips giving thanks to his name part one today is part two our
lips giving thanks to his name as we looked at this passage and really as I
began to just meditate upon and I believe that the Lord has revealed ten
reasons in the last section of Hebrews 13 in verses 7 down through verse number
25 ten reasons that we ought to rejoice now we understand that the list that is
provided here or the ten things that you find within the verses here it's not an
exhaustive list in any way shape or form the songwriter got it right when he
said name your count your blessings name them one by one and it will surprise you
what the Lord hath done and the psalmist said that the Lord daily loadeth us with
benefits and we agree with that because we look at this passage of scripture we
find there are ten reasons to rejoice that these believers are being reminded
of these reasons to rejoice last week just very quickly to look at the first
five that we dealt with last week we saw number one we ought to rejoice for
spiritual leaders what a blessing that God has designed it that he has called
and equipped spiritual leaders and how they have influenced us I know I
mentioned last week how that there have been some in my life that have made a
great impact for which I am so thankful and even still to this day I am thankful
for the influence and the impact that those spiritual leaders had in my life
for their faithfulness some of them are still serving the Lord faithfully today
some of them are with the Lord and that is a tremendous blessing not only that
we should rejoice in spiritual leaders the immutability of the Lord notice in
verse number eight Jesus Christ the same yesterday and today and forever and we
spoke about the fact that our God is immutable he never changes and that
ought to cause us to rejoice we said that we ought to rejoice for the Word of
God I'm so thankful that God has given us his precious word we understand that
it's profitable that it is just a precious book and God has given it to us
so that we might be sound in our doctrine so that we might have our
hearts established so that we would not be tossed to and fro with every wind of
doctrine and I'm so thankful that God's given us his word the substitutionary
atonement of Christ and so thankful that Christ took my place that he paid the
price for my sin and for your sin and for the sin of the world and then we
finished up last week with number five our home in heaven and what a joy to
think about the the certainty of heaven the reality of heaven I read and I think
about the Apostle Paul and his perspective and often as he shares as
he's ministering to these churches that God gave him the opportunity to minister
to in these believers and he speaks about his desire to going and being with
the Lord to be absent from the body is to be present with the Lord and he
mentions many things of course we have the promise of the Lord Jesus Christ
himself and what a joy to know the certainty the reality of heaven this
morning as we finish up the passage of Scripture we'll look at at least five
more reasons here that we ought to rejoice begin looking in verse number
18 the Bible says pray for us for we trust we have a good conscience and all
things willing to live honestly but I beseech you the rather to do this that I
may be restored to you the sooner now the God of peace that brought again from
the dead our Lord Jesus that great shepherd of the sheep through the blood
of the everlasting covenant make you perfect and every good work to do his
will working in you that which is well pleasing in his sight through Jesus
Christ to whom be glory forever and ever amen and I beseech you brethren suffer
the word of exhortation for I've written a letter unto you in few words know ye
that our brother Timothy is set at Liberty with whom if he come shortly I
will see you salute all them that have the rule over you and all the Saints
they have Italy salute you grace be with you all amen as we look at this past
description I'm gonna I know it would be number six if you're continuing with
your notes from last week but I'm gonna just number on one through five again
this morning some weren't here last week didn't hear the first part of the
message and so this morning for part two of our lips giving thanks to his name
let me share with it with you this number one this morning the privilege of
prayer we ought to thank God for the privilege of prayer I notice in verse
number 18 the verse begins by saying these three simple words that no doubt
you have you have said these words you have heard people say these words when
the when the the writer says pray for us pray for us now I think about that and I
begin to meditate upon that just the thought of verse number 18 those first
three words and I think about the privilege of prayer that we have as the
children of God you understand this morning that prayer is a unique
privilege to the child of God I hear sometimes there are people in the world
that do not know the Lord they're not saved and of course our desire is to see
them saved and maybe they'll say something like this I'm thinking about
you my thoughts are with you but when we understand this morning that as a child
of God we have the unique privilege to enter into the very presence of the God
of the universe and seek his face in prayer it is amazing to think about the
privilege of prayer and this morning is the writer says pray for us and I'm
mindful of the recipients receiving this simple instruction that that they're to
pray one for another and as we engage in the ministry of intercessory prayer what
a blessing it is I'm sure that you've heard someone say to you at some point
I'll pray for you or I will be praying for you maybe you've even mentioned
those words and I wonder this morning those words are so easy for us to speak
but I wonder how often we really sit back and really grasp the significance
of prayer and the the privilege of prayer this morning I'm mindful of what
the disciples said to the Lord Jesus Christ in Luke 11 in verse number one
when they said Lord teach us to pray teach us to pray I'm mindful of what
James says in James 5 in verse number 16 the latter part of the verse the
effectual fervent prayer of a righteous man availeth much of course even here in
the book of Hebrews in chapter number 4 and verse number 16 let us therefore
come boldly under the thorn of grace that we may obtain mercy and find grace
to help in time of need I'm mindful of the Apostle Paul in the book of Ephesians
on two occasions in the book he writes to the believers in Ephesus and shares
with them that he's praying for them but he doesn't just say I'm praying for you
he tells them how he's praying for them we find this also in the book of
Colossians in the first chapter of the book of Colossians you find how that
Paul is praying for believers he's not even met he's just heard about their
faith he did not minister in Colossae but yet Paul is praying for those
believers in Colossae and he lets them know I'm praying for you and here's how
I'm praying for you it's very interesting that in the book of
Philippians as you look at the first chapter in fact why don't you turn there
the book of Philippians and notice what Paul says to these believers in Philippi
he says this to them in verse number three I thank my God upon every
remembrance of you and then he goes on to say this to these believers in verse
number four of Philippians 1 always in every prayer of mine for you all making
requests with joy I want you to notice a phrase in verse number seven when Paul
says this even as a meat for me to think this of you all look look what he says
because I have you in my heart he has them in their heart he's thinking about
them he says I'm thanking God upon every remembrance of you in verse number three
and then he tells them how he's praying for them in verse number four always in
every prayer of mine for you all making requests with joy
And I think about this privilege of prayer.
Not only does Paul share with those that he's writing to,
that he's ministering to, how that he's praying for them,
but you understand that even as we find here in Hebrews 13,
in verse number 18, how the Bible tells us, pray for us,
that Paul makes that request
to the believers at Ephesus as well.
In Ephesians chapter number six,
after he goes through the armor of God
and put on the whole armor of God,
and he talks about the importance of prayer,
but then he says, pray for me,
that I may speak the word with boldness.
And you look at how he's requesting that they pray
in Colossians chapter number four.
In chapter one, Paul tells the believers in Colossae,
I'm praying for you, but in chapter number four,
he says, pray for me, pray for us.
And as we think about this unique privilege of prayer,
I hope this morning that we really just take a moment
and just thank God for the opportunity to pray.
And that not only would we thank God
for the opportunity to pray,
but that we would spend time in prayer,
that we would not just understand the principle of prayer
and the privilege of prayer,
but that we'd actually practice,
that we'd actually engage in prayer as a child of God,
that we would pray one for another.
Paul says this in 1 Thessalonians chapter five,
brethren, pray for us, pray for us.
I got a phone call this morning.
It was very interesting.
I came to church early this morning.
And as I was sitting in my office, the phone rang.
And typically I would not be in my office
at that hour on a Sunday morning,
but I happened to be here this morning and the phone rang.
I did not recognize the number.
And I went to pick up the phone,
which is something, again, I normally wouldn't be there.
But even if I am in my office,
a lot of times I don't answer on Sunday morning
unless I know who it is.
And so I answered the phone anyway.
And I, good morning, Fellowship Baptist Church.
And the person on the other end of the phone said,
this is a church.
And I said, it is.
They said, I thought I was calling.
And they mentioned who they thought they were calling.
And I know who that person is.
And it's actually a missionary that we support.
And I said, well, we support that missionary.
I'm aware of that missionary family,
but this is not their sending church.
It's not their home church.
And they're not here today.
And he said, I was just calling
to let them know I'm praying for them.
I just wanted to let them know this morning
that I was praying for them.
Is there any way that you can get a message
to this missionary and let them know I'm praying for them?
And I hung up that phone and I got on my computer
and I sent an email to the missionary.
I said, I just wanted to let you know
that so-and-so called this morning.
I don't know who so-and-so is.
I've never met them before.
I have no idea who they are.
They live in a completely different state.
But I sent an email to the other side of the world
and said, this fella called our church this morning
and he wants you to know that he's praying for you.
I can only imagine that when that missionary
opens the email, now they're ahead of us in time
and so it will be later in the day for them,
in the evening, I can only imagine
that when he opened that email that he was encouraged.
Because I know that when someone tells you
that they're praying for you,
I know that when someone sends you a card
and lets you know that they're praying for you,
when somebody sends you that message
and says I'm praying for you,
I know how that impacts us.
It's a unique privilege of a child of God.
And we notice here it says pray for us
for we trust we have a good conscience
in all things, willing to live honestly.
I beseech you the rather to do this
that I may be restored to you the sooner.
And as we notice here again
in focusing in upon these reasons to rejoice,
I wonder this morning how often do we really stop
and just thank God for the privilege of prayer?
Thank you that I can enter into your presence
and commune with you.
It's an amazing opportunity.
Number two in our notes,
if you're looking here as we continue to move forward,
I want you to rejoice in this reality
of the resurrection of Jesus Christ.
In verse number 20, the Bible says this,
now the God of peace,
notice what it says that brought again
from the dead our Lord Jesus,
that great shepherd of the sheep
through the blood of the everlasting covenant.
I'm so thankful that he is the great shepherd.
And we've spoken often about the reality
that the Lord is my shepherd
as the Psalmist would say in Psalm 23.
And what a great truth that is.
And we're so thankful for it.
But as we look at verse number 20
and we focus upon the reality of the resurrection
of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ.
We spoke as we looked at the first section
of this last portion of Hebrews 13,
and we spoke about the substitutionary atonement
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And I'm thankful that he went to that cross of Calvary,
that he shed his precious blood.
And we understand biblically
that he was buried in a borrowed tomb,
but he rose in victory,
conquering sin, death, and the grave.
We often speak about the fact
that we serve a risen Savior and we do.
And how we ought to rejoice.
And listen, the reality of the resurrection
is not just reserved for the springtime
around the Easter holiday.
It is the cornerstone of our faith.
Paul says that if Christ be not risen,
then our faith and our preaching, they're vain.
And we notice, if you turn over to Matthew 28,
notice here the account that is given,
and I hope that it never bores you
to read about the record of the resurrection
of our wonderful Savior.
And we think about the significance.
Remember, Jesus had said that he would rise from the dead.
The disciples did not always understand
what he was speaking of.
They did not grasp the significance
of the instruction in which he would give them.
But we find that after the burial,
as it's recorded in chapter 27,
in verse number one of chapter 28,
the Bible says, in the end of the Sabbath,
as it began to dawn toward the first day of the week,
came Mary Magdalene and the other Mary
to see the sepulcher.
And behold, there was a great earthquake.
For the angel of the Lord descended from heaven
and came and rolled back the stone from the door
and sat upon it.
His countenance was like lightning.
His raiment white as snow.
And for fear of him, the keepers did shake
and became as dead men.
The angel answered and said unto the women,
fear not ye, for I know that ye seek Jesus,
which was crucified.
He is not here, for he is risen, as he said.
Come, see the place where the Lord lay,
and go quickly and tell his disciples
that he is risen from the dead.
And behold, he goeth before you into Galilee.
There shall ye see him.
Lo, I have told you."
What a blessing to think about the resurrection
of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.
We could reference the entirety
of 1 Corinthians 15 this morning
and understand that that chapter
is the great resurrection chapter
of all of the Word of God.
And you read through the 15th chapter
of the book of 1 Corinthians
and you see the significance of the teaching
of the resurrection of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.
Paul said this to Timothy.
He says this in 2 Timothy 2 and verse number eight,
remember that Jesus Christ of the seed of David
was raised from the dead according to my gospel.
It's a good thing for us to remember
that we serve a risen Savior.
It's a good thing for us to be mindful
of the fact that he conquered sin, death, and the grave,
and that he lives forevermore.
It's interesting if you read the book of Revelation
and really in the first few chapters,
you find that as those letters
are being sent to the churches in Asia
and the way in which the significance
of these letters in Jesus as he's speaking to John
and giving the content of these letters,
he speaks about the fact that he was crucified,
but he now lives and he lives forevermore.
And this morning, it ought to be a great influence
and a great impact in our lives
that we serve a risen Savior,
and we ought to thank him for it.
Listen, we ought to rejoice that we serve a risen Savior.
I mentioned last week how that as we looked
at those first five reasons to rejoice from Hebrews 13,
that these are reasons in which are really unchanging.
There's no one that's gonna change these reasons
that we have to rejoice.
You understand this morning that you could be flat
on your back in some place, maybe imprisoned
or in a hospital or wherever it is, and you can still pray.
They can't keep you from praying.
See, it's a reason to rejoice.
I can pray.
Call unto me, God told Jeremiah,
and I will answer thee and show thee great and mighty things
which thou knowest not.
Listen, no one's gonna change the fact
that Christ rose from the dead.
It's a settled fact of history.
He rose conquering sin, death, and the grave.
As much as they tried to keep him from raising from the dead,
as much as they went to Pilate and they said,
listen, we know that he said that he was gonna rise,
and so we need to make this tomb as sure as we can,
and he said, go ahead, you go and you set a watch
and you make it as sure as you can,
but there was nothing that could keep our Savior
from rising and conquering sin, death, and the grave.
This morning, we have reasons to rejoice
that I understand things around us are changing.
I understand that circumstances can be difficult,
but when we're mindful of the fact that we can pray,
we're mindful of the fact that we serve a risen Savior,
we have reason to rejoice,
and we know that we're to give thanks always for all things.
We understand that in everything,
give thanks for this is the will of God
and Christ Jesus concerning you.
Yes, we're to thank God and praise him for his mighty acts,
but also according to his excellent greatness.
We find number three back in Hebrews chapter 13.
In Hebrews 13, as we look here at our,
a third reason here in our second part of this study
as to how or why we should rejoice.
Notice as we continue reading,
and we see here in v. 21,
the Bible says,
"...make you perfect in every good work
to do His will,
working in you that which is well-pleasing
in His sight through Jesus Christ,
to whom be glory forever and ever, Amen."
I would say that a third reason for us to rejoice
as I look at v. 21 this morning
is for the privilege of serving the Lord.
You know it's a unique privilege to serve God.
The songwriter said there is joy in serving Jesus.
And I agree with the songwriter.
I believe that there is joy in serving Jesus.
Notice what it says,
"...make you perfect in every good work
to do His will."
We understand here that as we think about
doing His will and serving the Lord,
that it is a privilege,
but we also understand that it's for His glory.
The Bible says here,
"...working in you that which is well-pleasing
in His sight."
What a joy to know that He's working in us.
And we'd ask ourselves the question this morning,
are we allowing Him to have His way with us?
Are we allowing Him to do that work within us
that He desires to do?
Remember at the end of chapter number 12
in verse number 28,
we read and we studied this portion
where the Bible says,
"...wherefore we receiving a kingdom
which cannot be moved.
Let us have grace," notice,
"...whereby we may serve God acceptably
with reverence and godly fear."
You know, it's a unique privilege to serve the Lord.
And we notice here this morning
that as we look at this truth
that He's working in us,
it says, "...through Jesus Christ,"
at the end of verse number 21,
"...to whom be glory forever and ever.
Amen."
As we serve the Lord,
we're not serving Him to be recognized,
to receive any glory here upon this earth.
We're serving Him so that He might be exalted,
so that He might be magnified,
so that He would receive the glory
that is due unto His name.
Notice as we often would reference
in Ephesians chapter number two,
verses eight and nine,
"...for by grace are you saved through faith."
And we understand the significance
of that doctrinal teaching
that we're not saved by our works,
but we do find that verse number 10,
not as often quoted with verses eight and nine,
that the Bible says,
"...for we are His workmanship,
created in Christ Jesus unto good works,
which God hath before ordained
that we should walk in them."
We understand this teaching in Ephesians 2,
really verses eight through 10.
We understand the reality of salvation
that it's by grace through faith.
It is of nothing that you or I could do.
It's not by works of righteousness,
which we have done.
It's according to His mercy.
And we find here, however,
that because we are saved,
that we are to be engaged in good works.
Now understand with me this morning,
it's not so that we could keep our salvation.
That's settled.
I'm thankful that He said that,
my sheep hear my voice and I know them
and I give unto them eternal life
and they should never perish.
I'm thankful this morning the Bible tells us
that we have the reality of an inheritance
that is reserved in heaven for us.
It's undefiled and it fadeth not away
according to what Peter tells us.
And as we understand the significance
of serving the Lord,
the reality is that I serve Him
out of all that He's done for us,
out of an appreciation of His work in us
and He is the one that enables us to serve Him.
We understand this morning
that not everyone will serve in the same capacity.
I'm thankful this morning I don't have two left hands.
I'd be in a mess.
Amen?
The reality is that we find in the Word of God
that God has used the picture of the human body
with reference to the church.
And it's a body that's fitly framed together
and we think how that each individual member of a church
has a particular gift that God has given them.
And as we use that collectively and corporately,
we use those gifts for the honor and glory of God,
we're able to accomplish all that God desires
for us to accomplish.
And as we come together as a church
and we serve God with the gifts and the talents
that He's given us,
it's so that He alone would be glorified.
We understand that we're the light of the world.
Let your light so shine.
And we understand what Jesus says there in Matthew 5,
that men may see your good works,
but glorify your Father, which is in heaven.
Notice with me this truth in 1 Peter chapter number four.
In 1 Peter chapter number four,
as we looked at the first six verses
of the 13th chapter of the book of Hebrews,
we referenced 1 Peter four a couple of times.
In 1 Peter chapter number four,
this morning we'll look at verses 10 and 11
as we reference this reason to rejoice,
the privilege of serving the Lord.
In verse number 10, the Bible says this
in 1 Peter four and verse number 10,
as every man hath received the gift.
We understand this morning,
we speak about spiritual gifts
that at the moment in which we trust
that Christ is our Savior,
the Holy Spirit of God indwells us.
We understand that we're commissioned
and we're commanded to be filled with the Holy Spirit.
And we understand that as we look at the truth
of spiritual gifts that God equips
and gifts each individual.
And here it says, as every man hath received the gift,
notice what it says, even so minister
the same one to another as good stewards
of the manifold grace of God.
If any man speak, let him speak as the oracles of God.
If any man minister, let him do it
as of the ability which God giveth.
Notice this, that God in all things
may be glorified through Jesus Christ,
to whom be praise and dominion forever and ever, amen.
You have a spiritual gift, so do I.
And you've been given a unique privilege
of serving the Lord.
There are times in which we need to,
as we engage in serving the Lord,
we need to take that step back and say,
God, thank you for the privilege
of being able to serve you.
I understand sometimes it's tough,
it's work, it's challenging.
And we can get into the, oh, this is so much,
but if we just kinda change our perspective
just a little bit and say, you know what,
this is a unique privilege.
What an opportunity that I am allowed of the Lord
to serve the Lord God omnipotent.
I mean, we can serve him, what a joy.
What a blessing.
The reality this morning is that we really ought to rejoice
in any opportunity that God would give us to serve him.
And not just look for certain opportunities
that we think, oh, that would be a good one
for me to be able to be engaged and to get plugged in.
No, I just wanna serve God
because it's a privilege to serve him.
This morning, I wonder how often
we just take a step back and say,
you know what, Lord, thank you for letting me serve you.
I wanna rejoice for the privilege
of being enabled by you to serve you
so that you would be glorified.
It's interesting as we think about Paul,
and of course, Paul served the Lord
and we have a lot of scripture that's been written by Paul
and we understand that Paul has given us a great example.
He ministered greatly, but I wanna remind you
of what Paul says in 1 Timothy 1 and verse number 12.
He says, and I thank Christ Jesus, our Lord,
who hath enabled me, for that he counted me faithful,
putting me into the ministry.
Paul was rejoicing the privilege
that he had to serve the Lord.
And he understood that it was God who hath enabled him.
And this morning, we rejoice in the privilege
of serving the Lord.
Number four, back in Hebrews chapter 13,
as we continue looking in verse 22,
and actually there are several references
in these next few verses
with regard to this fourth point of ours,
the Bible says in verse number 22,
and I beseech you, notice,
brethren, suffer the word of exhortation,
for I have written a letter unto you in few words.
So as we looked at part of verse number 22 last week,
when we were speaking about the word of God,
verse nine and verse 22,
dealing with the word of God and how we ought to rejoice
and thank God for his word.
Verse number 23, know ye that our brother, Timothy,
is set at liberty, with whom, if he come shortly,
I will see you.
So notice in verse number 22 that he says,
and I beseech you, brethren,
notice in verse number 23,
he says that our brother, Timothy,
and then in verse number 24, it says,
salute all them that have the rule over you.
Notice this, and all the saints,
they of Italy, salute you.
As I look at these few verses of scripture,
I would say this, number four, reason to rejoice.
Rejoice for fellow believers, for the brethren,
for our brothers and sisters in Christ.
I understand as we look at the word of God here,
and we find that this book of Hebrews
has been written to believers there in the first century,
these Jewish believers,
and we understand as we've studied
the entirety of the book now,
we understand some of the difficulties
in which they were facing
and some of the pressures to return to Judaism,
and we find that the writer says,
I beseech you.
you brethren." We've referenced other portions of Scripture here through the
book of Hebrews, how that he refers to them as being brethren, brothers and
sisters in Christ. We find that he then speaks about a specific brother, Timothy,
in verse number 23, and that he's been set at liberty. We are familiar with
Timothy. We understand that Paul refers to Timothy as his son in the faith. We
understand that there are two letters that are written to Timothy, 1st and 2nd
Timothy, with instruction with regard to the ministry that God had given him, and
so we see the specific brother that is mentioned in verse 23, and then we come
to verse number 24, and he says, "...salute all them that have the rule over you,"
really a reference to the spiritual leaders that have already been referenced
in verse 7 and 17, and then he says, "...and all the saints." He's
talking about giving greetings to all the saints, and then he says this at the
end of verse number 24, "...they of Italy salute you." So what is he saying? There's
some believers over there in Italy that are sending their greetings as well. You
know, something that's unique, and I've not traveled extensively around the
world, but I've understood as I've had the opportunity to share testimony with
others and to hear them share their testimony,
Ms. Joyce has traveled extensively, and you hear those that would travel
extensively, and they would say something like this, "...no matter where I
went, I was able to find other believers. I was able to find brothers and sisters
in Christ that I could rejoice with." There are times in which we've had the
opportunity to be in the presence of other believers that maybe you've had
difficulty with communication because of language barrier, but you have that bond
in Christ. I remember when I was down in Mexico just a couple of years ago
visiting with the Wheeler family and ministering there and distributing all
sorts of literature, and on that missions trip I remember standing in the
auditorium of that church on a Sunday evening after the service, and I remember
standing there, and my Spanish is not very good, and their English was as good
as my Spanish, and so there was a real challenge in being able to communicate
one with another, and there was this dear brother that just stood there, and you
could just tell how he just wanted to engage in conversation with us, and you
could tell how that he just was overjoyed with excitement as to the work
that was being accomplished and all that was being done, and every once in a while,
probably every two or three minutes, he'd just start talking to us again, and we
still didn't understand what he was saying, but he just had that desire to
want to communicate, and we think about the brethren. Listen, there are believers
all over the globe, and we have the privilege as a local church to rejoice
and thank God one for another, our brothers and sisters in Christ. Well, we
ought to pray one for another, but aren't you thankful that God's given you some
fellow believers? Aren't you thankful for some brethren that are able to hear you
say, would you pray for me, and that they're able to say to you, I am praying
for you, and vice versa, that we're able to serve the Lord together as believers?
You remember Elijah, he kind of had that that it's only me syndrome, right? And we
can read of that, we won't take the time to go back to 1st Kings 19 and read all
that had transpired there, but he has that idea, I am the only one. God said,
Elijah, I just want you to understand there's 7,000 that have not bowed the
knee to Baal. And see, there were others. He felt like he was the only one. I'm not
sure if you've ever been in a place where maybe you felt like you were in
solidarity, that you were the only one, you're the only believer in a particular
location, but you're reminded that there are other brothers and sisters in Christ.
Just a few chapters back in Hebrews chapter number 10, notice the reminder
that we were given as we studied this portion several weeks ago in Hebrews
chapter number 10 and verses 24 and 25. The Bible says, "...and let us consider one
another to provoke unto love and to good works, not forsaking the assembling of
ourselves together as the manner of some is, but exhorting one another, and so much
the more as ye see the day approaching." I'm mindful as I look at these verses in
Hebrews 10 and verses 24 and 25, the way in which we need each other, the brothers
and sisters in Christ. On Tuesday evening we had prayer, praise, and pie,
and there were some that made reference and were thanking the Lord and speaking
about the church family and how we're a family. You know, I'm so thankful for that.
We understand that the reality is that we need to strive for unity and
that we need to recognize the blessing of being brethren, brothers and sisters
in Christ. We need to thank God for that and we serve God together and we thank
God for the privilege. The writer here is telling these believers that are
struggling with some difficulties, he says, listen, there's a lot of other
believers out there. There's a lot of brethren and we're saluting you and
we want you to have our greetings. You know when you read through the
epistles and you read about the names of the individuals that are mentioned,
you begin to read how that Paul, on a number of occasion, he'll mention a
number of folks at the end of the letters in which he writes, send my
greetings to this person and that person and salute this one and salute that one.
Man, it causes us to rejoice because there's believers all over the place.
I believe even as it was mentioned on Tuesday evening during our prayer, praise,
and pie, that a year like 2020 with so many of the restrictions and regulations
that it would help us to be mindful of how appreciative we really should be for
the brethren, the believers. And I'm so thankful that God would allow us
to serve him together and we need to be mindful of one another. We need to thank
God for fellow believers. Number five, the passage ends as many of our New
Testament books begin or end, speaking of grace or mercy, and we find here it ends
by saying, grace be with you all, amen. We ought to thank God for his grace, the
grace of God. We understand, even as we sang this morning, and how appropriate
amazing grace. I hope that Brother Don was able to be watching on live stream
this morning as that's his favorite song. And often over the years, as we would
sing any number that's anywhere remotely close to 187, he'd kind of wonder why we
didn't pick 187 on that particular day. Why has it got to be 186? Why has it got
to be 184? Why not 187? You know, he just loves the song. We really think about
God's amazing grace. It is amazing. It's abundant. We think about the grace of
God. And this morning, we ought to thank God for his grace. And as we think about the
grace of God, and we've mentioned on a number of occasions, not only his saving
grace, but his serving grace, his enablement as we serve him. We spoke
about earlier the privilege of serving the Lord and how God gives us grace.
Peter says that we'd be good stewards of the manifold grace of God, that serving
grace. We think about the way in which the epistle ends,
grace be with you all, amen. And it's interesting because the way that this
letter, this book of Hebrews begins is with God. God, who at sundry times and in
divers manners spake in time past unto the fathers by the prophets, and it ends
by a reminder of God's grace. Grace be with you all, amen. As we think about the
grace of God, I want to look here at Titus chapter number two. Why don't you
turn there with me? And as we look at Titus chapter number two and remind it
about some very important truth with regard to God's grace. We understand that
as Jude would write and give warning because it was needful for him to write
about these things because there were men, certain men, that had crept in
unawares, he tells us that one of the things that these false teachers did is
that they were turning the grace of our God into lasciviousness. And that word is
not often used today in our vernacular, but it means unbridled lust. And he says
this is a problem. We look at Titus chapter number two and God gives us some
really good instruction with regard to the grace of God. Notice in verse number
11 in Titus chapter number two, the Bible says,
for the grace of God that bringeth salvation hath appeared to all men.
Aren't you thankful that the Bible teaches us, for by grace are you saved
through faith? And God's saving grace. Notice, however, as Paul continues
writing to Titus here with regard to the subject matter of grace, he tells us
what grace teaches us. It says this in verse number 12, teaching us that denying
ungodliness and worldly lust, we should live soberly, righteously, and godly in
this present world. That's a powerful verse of Scripture. We're thankful that
we're under grace and not under the law. Amen?
and what a blessing to live on this side of Calvary, I'm so thankful for it, but we
understand this morning there are some that have violated the the teaching of
grace and they've kind of said something like those false teachers, that
unbridled lust, that lasciviousness, I'm under grace, I can do what I want, you
can't tell me, so on and so forth. Well here, the Word of God tells us, as we
would thank God for grace, that grace teaches us some things, it teaches us
some things that were denied, ungodliness and worldly lust. It teaches us how we're
to live, we're to live soberly, righteously and godly in this present
world. Then, of course, we're mindful of the great promise in verse number 13,
looking for that blessed hope and the glorious appearing of the great God and
our Savior, Jesus Christ. I'm so thankful for the grace of God. This morning I
believe that many of us, we could consider where we would be if it were
not for grace. In fact, there's a song that just after I got saved, when I was
living in California, I visited a Bible college and I remember a Bible college
singing a song, were it not for grace. And as the songwriter of that particular
song, and I don't know all the words to the song, but I remember part of the
chorus is that if it were not for grace, I would be on a hopeless road to
nowhere. And I thought, man, that's pretty accurate as to where our lives would be
going. Of course, we understand without Christ we would spend eternity in the
lake of fire. I'm so thankful for God's grace. This morning, as we finish the book
of Hebrews and we finish this 13th chapter and we come to verses 7 through
25, and we just kind of dissect and meditate upon all of these verses of
Scripture, we find that there are at least 10 reasons for which we ought to
rejoice. This morning, as God's people, we're to be a thankful people. We're to
be a rejoicing people. We're to be a people that do not live under the
circumstances, amen? We got our eyes upon Jesus, the author and finisher of our
faith. We understand that he has a plan and that his plan is perfect. He never
makes a mistake. He never has and he never will. Every promise that he has
given is sure, because he's not a man that he should lie. He's able to fulfill
all that he said that he would do. One day, he's coming again. These believers
had been reminded of that back in the ninth and tenth chapter about the soon
return of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ. As a preacher of yesteryear said,
we're a day closer than we've ever been, and it's true. We're closer today than
we've ever been. And this morning, we have reasons to rejoice, and I hope that as we
would meditate upon these 10 unique things that are mentioned in this passage
of Scripture, that we would understand that these are reasons to rejoice that
that no one's going to take away from us. On a day in which it seems as if
nothing seems to go right, I know we've all kind of had those type of days where
it seems like, what is going on? It'd be a good day to go back to bed kind of a
situation. But you know, we have reasons to rejoice. We have reasons to rejoice.
Our God's still upon the throne. You say, pastor, you're aware of the things that
are going on in the world? Sometimes I don't want to be aware of the things that are
going on in the world, amen? Listen, if you're too aware of the things going on in the
world, you get yourself in a sideways, and you get yourself all kinds of mixed up.
But we keep our eyes on Jesus, the author and finisher of our faith, understanding
that that he has a perfect plan, and he's given us his word. We ought to rejoice in
it this morning. Let's spend more time in prayer. Let's spend more time in his word.
Let's spend more time praying one for another, and rejoicing and thanking God
for these ten particular things that are mentioned in Hebrews 13, 7 through 25.
Say, God, I just want to thank you. I just want to thank you for who you are, for what
you've done, for these particular blessings that you've bestowed upon us
as your children, these privileges. Lord, you've been so good to us, and he really
has been. And oh, how we ought to rejoice. Remember the 15th verse, our lips giving
thanks unto his name. Think about that, your lips, my lips, our lips collectively giving
thanks to his name. He is worthy in everything give thanks, for this is the will of God and
Christ Jesus concerning you. Let's pray. Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. We
thank you for the opportunity to study this book of Hebrews. We understand that the believers
that are being written to here in this book, the original recipients, they were dealing
with some very challenging times, some difficulties, opposition, adversity, persecution. They've
been encouraged through this entire book to understand that Christ is superior. He's better.
We've been encouraged to look to Jesus, the author and finisher of their faith, of our
faith. They've been encouraged to rejoice. Lord, this morning as we look at the content
of this last section of Hebrews 13, I pray that you'd encourage us this morning, help
us to be mindful of these unique privileges that you've given us as your children, and
that God, we would rejoice in the privilege of prayer, the resurrection of our Lord and
Savior Jesus Christ, the opportunity to serve you for fellow believers and for your grace.
I pray God that if there's one present or one under the sound of my voice, perhaps even
watching live stream that does not know you as their personal Lord and Savior, they've
never trusted Christ. They do not know for sure that if they were to die today that heaven
is their home. It's our prayer that they would be saved, that they would trust Christ
as their Savior. For each of your children, God, would you help us to be mindful of these
unique privileges that you've given us and help us to rejoice greatly, that our lips
would give thanks to your name. I pray that you'd work during this time of invitation,
that you'd have your will and way in each life. We'll thank you for decisions that are
made, for it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed,
eyes are closed. No one's looking around. Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano,
and as she does, the altar's open. Make your pew an altar. Come up to this old-fashioned
altar. Maybe you just want to come and thank God for some of the things that we looked
at this morning. Perhaps there's something else the Lord laid upon your heart that you
need to be thankful for. As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.