Continue our study here through 1 Thessalonians 5,
eventually we'll be over in 2 Thessalonians 3 as well.
And these instructions that have been provided
to the church at Thessalonica,
I mentioned it's the title for our series
here on Wednesday evenings, Walk Worthy, Please God.
And I'm thankful that the church at Thessalonica
was a good church, a model church,
but we find that at the end of each letter
that God has Paul right to these churches.
We find that God gives them instruction.
He gives them these very concise statements of instruction
beginning in verse 12 of chapter five of the first letter.
We've been studying, we've made it through verse 18.
Tonight we'll be looking at verse 19.
And this is lesson number 12.
We've had the opportunity to take each of these
pieces of instruction.
And we know that as we take the word of God,
it tells us that it's profitable for us.
And as we apply God's word in our lives,
then we can walk worthy and please God.
And God does care how we live, how we walk.
And he wants us as individuals
and then obviously as churches to please him.
And I'm thankful that he's given us the instruction
so that we can know how we can please him.
He begins in verse 12, we beseech you.
And then we mentioned already, but in verse 14,
he says, we exhort you.
And so this evening, as we continue studying,
we find that the Bible says very simply
in verse number 19, quench not the spirit.
Quench not the spirit.
It's the title for the message this evening from verse 19.
The Bible tells us that lost men
can resist the Holy Spirit.
In fact, Stephen lays this charge
against the council that he's preaching to.
It's recorded in his sermon there in Acts chapter number seven
that they do always resist the Holy Ghost.
And that resistance, and we can understand
as Stephen is preaching, the conviction
that would be upon them and their resistance
to the work of the Holy Spirit.
We find that the Bible teaches that every believer
is indwelled by the Spirit of God.
At the moment of salvation,
we find that the Holy Spirit of God indwells us.
And the New Testament records for us
many aspects with regard to the ministry
of the Holy Spirit, the ministry of the Holy Spirit
in the life of a believer.
We understand that he is the divine teacher
and what a blessing to know that he guides us
into all truth and we find that he's the comforter
and we could go on and we look at the various aspects
of the ministry of the Holy Spirit of God.
But we find that the New Testament also gives us a warning
that as believers, according to Ephesians four
and verse number 30, we can grieve the Holy Spirit.
We can grieve the Holy Spirit.
In fact, Paul says this in Ephesians four
and verse number 30,
and grieve not the Holy Spirit of God,
whereby ye are sealed unto the day of redemption.
And so we find that that instruction is given there
and obviously when we sin, we grieve the Spirit of God,
the Holy Spirit.
And so we find here the second warning, if you will,
is given to us here in our text this evening
that as believers, not only can we grieve the Holy Spirit,
but we learn here that we can quench the Holy Spirit.
The Lord and his infinite wisdom,
and I'm thankful that God is the all wise God.
It's very interesting to me,
and I mentioned this briefly last Wednesday evening,
the placement of this verse of scripture.
Quench not the Spirit.
And we think about that word quench
and it carries with it the idea of to put out
or to extinguish.
And we think about the work of the Holy Spirit
and the lives of God's people.
We're indwelled by the Spirit of God,
but the Spirit of God will convict us
and he'll work in our lives
and he will give us that direction and what have you.
And we find that the Holy Spirit is active
and moving in the lives of his people
and God and his infinite wisdom
put this verse of scripture here
in 1 Thessalonians 5 and verse 19,
quench not the Spirit.
Immediately following three powerful commands
that we are given.
We are given these three powerful commands
in verse 16, 17, and 18,
and then we're told quench not the Spirit.
There's a little doubt in my mind
that these three commands in verse 16, 17, and 18
have brought conviction to many of God's people
over the centuries.
What are those three?
Well, we've studied them the last several weeks,
but number one, rejoice evermore.
Literally to rejoice at all times.
He says rejoice evermore, pray without ceasing.
In everything give thanks,
for this is the will of God and Christ Jesus concerning you.
And we find that as we look at these three powerful commands
these concise statements that we understand as individuals
and then we understand corporately as a church
that we are to be busy praising the Lord,
praising him at all times and praying about everything.
When we take those three commands of scripture,
if we take them and we read them and we understand them,
I believe that the Holy Spirit
would convict many of God's people.
Why?
Well, we have a hard time rejoicing at all times.
We have a hard time praying about everything,
pray without ceasing.
In fact, prayer is often neglected by God's people.
One of the greatest privileges that we have,
prayer is often neglected.
We find that there are many over the years
that you might say to them, I'll pray for you,
and they look at you as if that's all you're gonna do.
And really that's the greatest thing we could ever do.
We find this evening that the Holy Spirit of God,
all scripture is given by inspiration of God.
Holy men spake as they were moved by the Spirit.
We find that he says, quench not the Spirit.
Again, the word quench means to put out, to extinguish,
often be used if you think about a fire
and you think about the fire burning
and you were to dump cold water on that fire
and quench the fire and to extinguish it, to put it out.
So as I look at this passage of scripture this evening
and I think about this command, quench not the Spirit,
really I don't have points for it,
I've got a bunch of questions for you tonight.
And the lesson this evening is gonna be
in the form of questions.
And the first question that I ask you this evening
when we think about this command of scripture,
quench not the Spirit, number one,
and I want you to answer these questions
honestly to yourself.
Obviously, God already knows the answer,
but allow God to search you and to know your heart.
Number one, do you invite the Holy Spirit to convict you?
What do I mean by that?
Well, when you pray, when you read your Bible,
when you come to church, do you pray
that the Holy Spirit of God would convict you,
that he would not leave you to yourself,
that he would deal with you?
And see, as I read God's word each day of my life,
I don't pray exactly the same prayer each morning,
but I pray very similar things with regard
to Psalm 119 and verse 18,
Lord, open thou mine eyes,
that I may behold wondrous things out of thy law,
but I also pray that God would take his word
and that he would comfort me,
but also that he would convict me,
that God would teach me from his word
the things that I ought to be doing
that maybe I'm not doing,
the things that I ought not be doing that I am doing,
and we invite, listen, I desire the Holy Spirit of God
to work in my life, and the question tonight is,
do we ask God to convict us?
Do we ask him?
Do we invite him?
Do we welcome that conviction?
See, many times, unfortunately,
we can gain this improper approach or response,
I should say, to the thought of conviction.
We might be tending to fall on the side
that conviction's this bad thing.
No, conviction's a good thing.
It's good when God convicts us.
It's good when he's stepping on our toes,
when he's dealing with us about areas of our lives.
Why?
Because none of us are perfect.
Amen?
We all have room for growth.
We're to be like Christ.
That's our ultimate goal,
that we might be like him.
He left us an example that we should follow his steps,
and all of us are on this journey at a different level,
at a different place in our Christian journey,
but the reality is that none of us
are ever gonna reach a place of sinless perfection,
and there's room for God to work,
and we, as we go to the Bible,
yes, I'm thankful that God's word will give us comfort
in how we need comfort,
but at the very same time, God's word will convict us,
and the question this evening,
when we think about this statement,
quench not the spirit,
this command that's been given to us,
I wonder this evening,
what is your approach to God's word?
Do you invite the Holy Spirit to convict you?
Do you make that request?
I think of the psalmist.
Search me, oh God.
And what?
Show me if there be any wicked way.
That's what he says, Psalm 139.
And so as we begin to understand this invitation,
and understanding.
how the Lord works and how he uses his word. Number two this evening, a second question
for you. Do you expect the Holy Spirit to convict you? Are you expecting it? What do
I mean by that? You know, when you go to certain places, you have certain levels of expectations.
You understand as you're going to, maybe you're going for a meal, you're going to someone's
home for something and you have expectations. I wonder when you come to church, I wonder
when you approach that holy time with the Lord of spending time in his word, in those
daily devotions, are you expecting God to work? Are you expecting him to confront you
about some things? You've invited him to do so, but then you're expecting, I mean you're
looking for it, you're anticipating it. I wonder as we come to church, and I'm thankful
this evening that you're here obviously, but I begin to think about our approach to
church and as we enter into the house of God that we're coming and we're expecting to hear
from God. We come with that expectation, we're anticipating, I wonder what God has for me
in this service. I wonder how God is going to work in my life in this service. Does that
make sense to you this evening? Because God is a God that is obviously, he transcends
us and he's everywhere present. He loves all people, but God is a personal God. It's amazing
how God will work as we come inviting and expecting God to work. You know there are
times that God might work just through one of the songs. Plenty of times in my life that
we would just be singing songs and I almost could say, hey it'd be okay right now if we
just had an invitation after the singing. Why? Because God can use the songs. Why? Because
there are many of the, I mean the songs that we sing in our hymnals, the reason that we
use the hymnals that we do, those songs are biblically based and God will use them in
our lives. We find this evening that we ought to have that not only inviting God to convict
us but then expecting that he will. When we're reading the scriptures, expecting that God's
going to confront us on something. It's a good thing. Let me ask you this question,
number three this evening, do you give the Holy Spirit opportunity to convict you? It's
one thing to invite it or to expect it, but I wonder this evening is what kind of opportunity
do we give the Holy Spirit to convict us? What do I mean by that? Well, we ought to
be reading God's Word regularly. You know there's a danger when we talk about reading
God's Word where we can just get comfortable reading certain portions of scripture that
maybe are our favorite portions of scripture while we neglect other portions of scripture.
It's sad to me today how many people have this perspective and it's gaining great levels
of followers that we're New Testament believers, we don't need the Old Testament. That's baloney.
God wouldn't have preserved it for us if we didn't need it, amen? But God preserved it
for us. Not only did he preserve it for us, but he told us in the New Testament that the
things which were written aforetime were written for our learning and for our admonition. Now
this evening, admittedly, any one of us could probably name a book of the Bible that might
be our favorite book of the Bible, and that's okay. But what's not okay is to only read
that book of the Bible. Amen? It's not okay to just read the portions of scripture that
you're familiar with that you say, man, these ones, Psalm 23 really comforts me. You read
Psalm 23 every single day of your life, I'm glad it comforts you, but God gave us a whole,
he gave us 1189 chapters in 66 books. And he wants us to read all of it. You know, the
more you read the Bible, the more you know of portions of scripture that are probably
going to step on your toes than other places. Don't ignore those portions of scripture.
Regularly read the Bible. Have a plan for how you're going to read the Bible. And I
don't care what plan you use. I don't care if you follow the pattern that I like to follow.
That's my personality. That's what works for me. But the reality is that everybody ought
to be reading the Bible. If you're a child of God, you better read the Bible every day.
And that's giving opportunity to the Holy Spirit of God to convict you, because he uses
the scriptures to convict us. I would say this with regard to giving the Holy Spirit
opportunity to convict you, not only reading the Word regularly, but we need to be attending
a church regularly that preaches the Word faithfully. You know, there's plenty of churches
that you can go to today that can make you feel good. Just the way it is. I was reading
just earlier today about the truth in 2 Timothy chapter number 4, about itching ears. And
we have churches all across our landscape today that are catering to that group of people.
And it's just the way it is. It's unfortunate, but when we desire, when we understand, and
I'm getting to the thought here this evening with Quench Not the Spirit, listen, we need
to give the Spirit of God opportunity to work in our lives and to bring that conviction.
Now you're here this evening, so obviously you understand the importance of being in
church and being in a church that preaches the Bible. And as a pastor, as a preacher,
I seek the will of God with regard to the portions of scripture that I'm preaching.
I seek the Lord with regard to particular studies that we go through and how we approach
the scriptures. I was sharing with Joseph just the other night in family devotions,
and I had jotted down a few weeks ago, as I was sitting in the office, just the books
of the Bible that I have had the privilege that God has allowed me to teach or preach
through since I've been here. Man, it's been exciting. I've enjoyed it. I have to be careful.
Just like I say, don't just read the books that you are most, you know, familiar with
or that you like the most. I can't just keep going and preaching the same book of the Bible
every year. Why? Because we need all of it. We need all of it. And we find this evening
that I have learned in my own life and through the preaching ministry that when we preach
line upon line, precept upon precept, when we preach through books of the Bible, teach
through books of the Bible, man, the Holy Spirit of God has an opportunity to just kind
of hit everything that's in there. And that's good for us. We don't just skip over portions
of scripture. Well, they're not very popular today. That's okay. They're biblical. And
that's what we're worried about. So how is it that we give the Holy Spirit opportunity
to convict us? And then I get to this question and really dealing with this verse of scripture
this evening, and it's this, how do we respond to the conviction? How do we respond to the
conviction? So, we acknowledge this evening that we ought to be inviting and expecting
and giving opportunity for that conviction to come into our lives, but the question tonight
that really pertains to the verse of scripture that is before us with quench not the spirit
is how do we respond to the conviction? It's a great question. We have an invitation not
on Wednesday evenings, but on Sunday morning, Sunday evening, we have an invitation. And
the purpose of that invitation is to give opportunity for folks to respond. And I understand
that not everyone's comfortable with going to an old-fashioned altar. And some people
like to pray right where they are. Some people like to go home and pray about it. But I would
argue that once you leave here, that moment of how God was working in your life, circumstances
change in a hurry. Things get all kinds of just crazy with regard to this is going on
and that's going on and the kids are telling you this. And when are we eating? And is dinner
ready yet? And I'm starving. I'm going to die. I'm so hungry. And so on and so forth.
And guess what? Before you know it, you don't even really have any remembrance of what happened
maybe 30 minutes, an hour earlier, how God was working, how God was pinpointing something
in your life, how He was convicting you. And so if we invite the Holy Spirit to convict
us, if we're expecting it and we're giving opportunity, but we fail to respond properly
to it, what is it really worth? But we find this evening that we must respond properly.
We must refuse to quench the Spirit. There are times, no doubt, that the Holy Spirit
of God will bring conviction in our lives and it can be uncomfortable. Amen? Conviction
can be uncomfortable. It's designed to be so. Amen? Y'all looking at me like I'm crazy
tonight. Listen. Conviction is good. Chastisement is good. It proves that we're His children.
Amen? Conviction is good. I'd be concerned if God was never convicting me.
me. Honestly, I'd be concerned. Why? Because I know I'm not perfect. I've read enough of
the Bible to know I'm never going to be perfect this side of heaven. And so if I can go day
after day and read the Bible and never be convicted, I'm concerned about that. What's
going on? Why is there no conviction? And but I need to refuse to quench the Spirit.
Rather, I must rejoice that He's working, that He's dealing with me. I must rejoice
that He cares enough, He loves me enough to bring that conviction in my life to deal with
me. And as I rejoice, I then decide that I'm going to respond appropriately to that conviction.
And what is that appropriate response? Well, I would say that we ought to respond immediately
when the Holy Spirit of God is convicting us. Because those delays, it's amazing how
quickly the enemy can slip in there and kind of cause you to think, well, it's really not
that big of a deal. We begin to excuse and we begin to justify. Listen, we can go through
Scriptures this evening and we can look at examples of those that have gone before us
that have excused their sin. Remember a guy by the name of Saul? Right? It wasn't me.
It was the people. Right? That's what he said. But we can think about people that justify
their sin. We can think about people that try to hide their sin. And so, when the Holy
Spirit of God is convicting us, we must respond. And I believe that when we respond immediately,
it's best. That's why, again, on Sunday mornings and Sunday evenings, we have the opportunity
for that time of invitation so that it gives people an opportunity not only to have received
the Word of God, but then to respond to the Word of God. Because we don't want to have
that delay. In that moment of delay, in that time of delay, we can get so distracted. We
can forget about all that had taken place. I believe that not only must we respond promptly
or immediately, but I believe that it's important that we respond fully, completely. You know,
God's work in your life is an individual work. He's not going to work outside of the principles
that He's given us in His Word. God's never going to lead you to do something that's contrary
to His Word. We understand those principles that we could look to, but we find that God's
dealing with each of us as individuals. And so, as God is dealing with us as individuals,
we don't look around and say, well, am I the only one? Why aren't other people? No,
we sing the song, though none go with me, still I will follow. Right? And God is working
in our hearts and He's working in our lives individually, and as He is, we must respond
appropriately. We must deal with that time of conviction and say, God, have Your way
in my life. It's kind of that idea of waving that flag of surrender, being yielded to the
Holy Spirit. You know, it's important for us to understand this evening the importance
of being yielded and being surrendered. We can come to a place in our lives where we
no longer are yielded to the work that God is doing in our lives. We sit in a church
service but we're distracted the whole time wondering about this, that, or the other thing,
and when this is going to end, and how we're going to deal with, and I understand life
is full of all kinds of circumstances. It's easy to come to a church service distracted.
It's easy to be concerned about what the next thing is and what we need to do, and maybe
to, well, I'll deal with that later. The question is, does later ever really come?
Does later ever come? This evening, when we look at this truth that we find here in 1
Thessalonians 5 and verse 19, I believe the Holy Spirit of God, obviously God does all
things well and right, but He puts this quench not the spirit right in the midst of all of
this instruction, this concise instruction that's given to the church at Thessalonica.
I tend to believe, listen, you can read through these verses of Scripture from verse 12 to
28 in a matter of just a few minutes. We've spent at this point 11 weeks looking at just
half of these verses. You can read through them in just a few minutes, but in the midst
of them, quench not the spirit. And I just wonder this evening, as the church at Thessalonica
first received this letter, and they're reading these things, and you ever get to the point
where you read things quickly? Right? I'm not just saying that you're a fast reader,
just you read through things, and then you get to quench not the spirit. It kind of slows
you down a little bit, at least for me, because through these commands that God has given,
the conviction's coming. Rejoice evermore. I wonder tonight, I'm just asking myself,
but I'm asking it out loud, so therefore I'm asking you as well, how am I doing with that?
Rejoice evermore. Pray without ceasing. In everything give thanks, for this is the will
of God in Christ Jesus concerning you. Quench not the spirit, verse 19. So, as the Holy
Spirit of God would be using those commands, and obviously I didn't even look at all of
them because there are several beginning in verse number 12 of the commands that we read,
but we find that as we look at just the three immediately that precede this particular principle
or command of Scripture, quench not the spirit, man, there's great conviction that comes in
my life. Why? I don't think I'm the only one, but I'm guilty of not rejoicing at all times.
There are things that happen in our lives that cause us to complain, murmur, yeah? Pray
without ceasing. There are times that we fail to pray. We may try to do this, that and the
other all in our own strength and our own power. Say, hey, why don't we pray about this
after we've tried and exhausted all sorts of things? In everything give thanks. See,
tonight, quench not the spirit. God's working. God moves. The Holy Spirit of God indwells
every believer. And tonight, as we understand the truth of the indwelling of the Spirit
of God, He tells us in Ephesians that we can grieve the Spirit, but He tells us here in
1 Thessalonians that we can quench the Spirit. And He says, quench not the spirit. I hope
tonight that we would say, I don't want to quench the Spirit. I want the Spirit of God
to be working in my life. I desire Him to be convicting me. I desire when I come to
church to be challenged with what I should be doing, with how I should change something
in my life through whatever means it is that the Holy Spirit uses in the service, whether
it's the song service, the preaching, a combination of both, that I'm desiring the Holy Spirit
of God to work in my life and I do not want to quench His work. I want to respond to it
appropriately, immediately, completely, fully, letting God have His way in our lives. Again,
conviction sometimes can be looked at as being a negative thing. I argue tonight that it's
a wonderful thing when the Holy Spirit of God reaches down into the life of an individual
through whatever aspect of personal Bible reading, public worship in a church setting,
one-on-one conversation with brothers and sisters in Christ, and the Holy Spirit of
God convicts us. It's a good thing. And we must learn tonight, quench not the Spirit.
Respond. Respond in obedience. Search me, O God. Desire for Him to work and then respond
accordingly. Quench not the Spirit. Let's pray. Father, we love You. We thank You for
loving us. We thank You for Your Word tonight. And Lord, I pray that You would help us to
take this simple charge, exhortation, quench not the Spirit. God, I wonder this evening
how You're working in the lives of Your people. I mean in our daily walk with You as we read
Your Word. I pray that we read it each day. I pray that we read it fully, the entirety
of it. God, I pray that as we read Your Word that You would comfort us but also that You
would convict us. You would show us areas of our lives that we need to change, things
that we need to stop doing, things that we need to start doing.
that we might be holy in all manner of conversation,
that we might walk worthy and please Thee.
And God, I pray that as the Holy Spirit of God convicts us
as He works in our lives,
I pray that we would refuse to quench the Spirit.
I pray that we would determine that we'll respond,
respond in obedience, respond immediately, no delays,
respond fully, completely.
Though maybe others aren't responding in like fashion,
we understand that You work in our lives as individuals,
and we will stand before You as individuals.
God, I pray that You'd help us.
Blessed now through our time of prayer,
we thank You for the privilege of prayer.
I pray, God, that You'd be honored and glorified
through the remainder of the service.
For it's in Christ's name we pray, amen.
I think about that little song that we sing,
I'll say yes, Lord, yes, to Your will and to Your way.
I'll say yes, Lord, yes, I will trust You and obey.
And then the songwriter said this,
when Your Spirit speaks to me, you know what that is?
That's expectation, right?
I'm expecting that Your Spirit's gonna speak to me,
then my answer's gonna be what?
With my whole heart I'll agree,
and my answer will be yes, Lord, yes.
And what a great song that is, a little chorus that is.
Does anyone need a?