Wednesday of this calendar year, January 3rd, 2024,
was the very first message on this theme of walk worthy.
And here we are this evening on June the 26th,
and this is lesson number 22.
As we have studied, we've kind of made our way through
1 Thessalonians chapter five,
and now 2 Thessalonians chapter number three.
And we have been able to be helped
just as the church in Thessalonica
would have been helped through this instruction.
We too have been helped.
How many of you ever played the game Simon Says?
Come on, everyone's played the game Simon Says, right?
And what do you do?
Well, you do whatever Simon Says, right?
So Simon Says, pat your head,
and everyone's patting their head, right?
And if someone didn't know that you were playing Simon Says
and they had a video recording,
they think everyone looked like they're crazy,
all the different things that they're doing.
And we do it with the kids often
during vacation Bible school.
It's really kind of a nice game to fill some time
when you're trying to get some other kids in
and some of the classes are going long
or whatever's happening
and trying to gather everyone together.
And whoever's there, you begin playing Simon Says.
And I like to talk fast as it is,
and so that helps a lot with Simon Says
because you can just really get going
with all of your commands and all those sorts of things.
And all of a sudden you say, touch your head,
and you didn't say Simon Says,
and half the kids touched their head.
And what happens?
Well, they're out, right?
Is that how it worked when you played?
I know everyone's a winner today,
but listen, that's not how it works, amen?
And if you touch your head and Simon didn't say to do it,
you sit down, right?
That's what happens.
And eventually there's someone,
the idea of the game is that you play it long enough
that there's a winner.
Well, we understand that little game
that we play with kids
and all of us at some point in our life
have played that game.
Maybe you've even had the opportunity to be Simon.
And that's kind of a fun opportunity.
You get to give all the commands
and tell everyone else what to do.
And the reality is that it is an understood thing
that instruction is provided with the expectation
that it will be followed or applied.
Is that valid?
We understand it with Simon Says, a little tiny game,
but I'm talking now,
let's look at the biblical truth of instruction.
We can apply it as we will this evening,
spiritual instruction, but in any arena in life,
if someone is providing instruction,
the expectation of the instructor
is that that instruction is going to be received and applied.
Otherwise they feel like they're wasting their time.
And we find that unfortunately far too often
biblical instruction has been rejected
instead of being received.
We find that it's been ignored instead of being implemented.
Listen to these verses, if you will, with me,
and I'll read two verses from the Old Testament.
We're not gonna turn there, but listen,
in Psalm 81, in verse number 11, the psalmist says this,
God, of course, is giving the indictment
against the nation of Israel.
He says, but my people, listen to this,
would not hearken to my voice,
and Israel would none of me.
Listen, it wasn't that God didn't give the instruction.
It wasn't even that they didn't know the instruction.
It was that they would not hearken to my voice.
In 2 Chronicles 24, in verse 19, the Bible says this,
yet he sent prophets, plural, to them.
Now I like, listen, every word of God is pure.
He didn't just send one prophet to them.
He sent prophets to them.
And it says to bring them again unto the Lord.
Why was God doing that?
Why did he send prophets?
Well, because he wanted them to be restored.
He wanted to, listen, our God is full of grace and mercy,
and he is a forgiving God.
And so he sends the prophets
so that they would preach a message
so that they would bring his people again unto the Lord,
and they testified against them.
That's the prophets.
They testified against them, Israel.
But it says at the end of the verse,
but they would not give ear.
They would not give ear.
Now those are two sad indictments.
We could look at a score of other examples this evening.
There are so many references in God's word
where God faithfully provided instruction,
and yet his people ignored it instead of implementing it.
And that's a sad, sad thing.
And this evening, as we come to the end
of 2 Thessalonians 3,
and we look at this portion of scripture,
we find that Paul concludes this section of this book,
he specifically addresses how to deal with those,
according to verse number 14,
who obey not our word by this epistle.
I wanna give you a message this evening,
teach a lesson that I have titled this,
restoration versus excommunication.
Restoration versus excommunication.
And I think as we get through the message this evening,
I hope that you'll understand
why it is that I chose that title.
In verse number 14, the Bible says this,
and if any man obey not our word by this epistle,
note that man and have no company with him
that he may be ashamed.
Verse 15, yet count him not as an enemy,
but admonish him as a brother.
This evening, as we look at these two verses of scripture,
and we entertain this thought
of restoration versus excommunication,
we find that yes, there is a truth in God's word
with regard to biblical church discipline.
And as we make it through the text of scripture this evening
and provide you with thoughts tonight,
I want you to understand that the reality
is that any time we deal with a subject matter such as this
and deal with the broader subject of church discipline,
that I believe this evening
that the goal is always restoration.
The goal is never excommunication,
the goal is always restoration.
Now the reality is that restoration
is dependent on the offender,
on how they respond to the admonition,
how they respond to the correction to the instruction
on whether that restoration is possible.
But we as the people of God,
we that are not the offenders in the particular matter,
we must be understanding of the fact
that the goal is restoration.
By the way, I believe this evening
that the purpose reveals to us the very heart of God.
God's heart is a heart of forgiveness and grace
and mercy and restoration, that's God's heart.
And so we find that no doubt he would apply
and give the church instruction with regard to offenders
that would reveal his heart.
And so as we look at the text of scripture,
number one this evening, if you're taking notes,
the instruction to the believers.
So we find that throughout the text of scripture,
the apostle Paul started in verse number six
as we have studied for a number of weeks now here
in 2 Thessalonians chapter number three,
with regard to the command that he's giving
to the brethren.
He finished up as we studied last week in verse 13,
but ye brethren be not weary in well doing.
Listen, there were some people that were busybodies,
there were some people that were disobedient,
there were people as we look in this passage of scripture
that were walking disorderly.
And so what does Paul say in verse 13?
Well, to those that are doing right,
don't get weary as you're doing right, don't faint.
And we look last week at some tips
on how we can avoid growing weary.
He then immediately goes back to really the focus
of the section and that's dealing with those
that were not doing right,
those that were walking disorderly.
But he first is, he continues to address the believers
and I want you to note the instruction.
He says two things that they're to do.
And if any man obey not our word by this epistle,
note, it says number one, note that man, note that man.
And so I would say the instruction to the believers,
the first aspect that is given is that the individual
must be identified.
You must identify the individual.
Now, as we look again at the passage of scripture
and we've said this as we've studied through this letter,
that these believers in Thessalonica,
this is a church that's made up of people
just like our church is made up of people.
Now, this book of 2 Thessalonians
was not written to us specifically.
But we do understand that by way of preservation,
that the truth that God has in this book
is still very much applicable to every church,
including our church.
But we find that that church in Thessalonica,
they had people that were walking disorderly.
They had people that were busybodies
and Paul's writing it directly to them.
And it's almost one of those things
that you start looking around and be like,
am I one of those people that he's talking about?
Like, we know they're here, like,
because he's writing to them.
They're the original recipients.
And so we find that Paul, as he's speaking to the believers
and tells them not to grow weary in well-doing,
he then tells them how to handle
these that are walking disorderly.
And he says that they must be identified.
He says, note that man.
It doesn't end there.
The second piece of instruction is this,
and have no company with him.
Now, you might look at that and say,
well, that's kind of extreme.
It's Bible.
And we find that there is a time
that separation is important, that we understand.
Remember back in verse number six,
he said, now we command you, brethren,
in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ,
that you withdraw yourselves from every brother
that walketh disorderly, and not after the tradition
which he received of us.
And so now again, he mentioned in verse six
to withdraw yourself, and now he says,
have no company with him.
Now, this is a very important thing that we understand.
Now, in today's environment here
in the United States of America,
it's a lot different culturally than what it was
in Thessalonica in the first century.
There are still places around the globe
that culturally, they align more
with what the Thessalonians were dealing with
than what we deal with.
What do I mean by that?
Well, many times, especially in the first century,
but even still today around the world in many cultures,
if you become a follower of Jesus Christ,
you are excommunicated from the community.
You have no more opportunity to do business
as you had been doing business,
and many times even, listen, there are families today
that we have of missionaries that they have told us
that someone came to Christ, and when they trusted Christ
and decided that they were going to boldly be a follower
of Jesus Christ, that their family had a funeral service.
They just acknowledged them no longer.
It's been said of those that would be in a situation
of being in a business and how they would gain
their livelihood, that if you became a Christian
and you were a baker, well, all of a sudden,
people would stop buying your goods.
Why, because they're not gonna give you money
for your family because you're a follower of Jesus Christ.
Not only would people stop buying your goods,
but the people on the other end that were providing you
with raw materials, the flour, et cetera,
they would no longer provide you with those raw materials.
Why, so that you can't even produce your product.
Now, we don't deal with that in America.
Have any of you dealt with that in America?
The reality is in America, for many of the Christians
in America, you can live and survive
without your church family.
I would say you can't thrive without your church family,
but you can live and survive.
You can't thrive, though.
In this culture, this situation that would take place
in Thessalonica, when it says have no company with him,
well, now all of a sudden, that individual is no longer
accepted by those that he once was accepted by.
Why, because he's identified as a Christian.
But now he's not living as a Christian,
and so he does not find himself being able
to be in fellowship with the Christians.
That's a major problem.
A square peg in a round hole.
Do you understand what I'm saying?
And so we find that here, as God is providing
this instruction, when God is saying have no company
with him, we understand it doesn't end there.
We're gonna continue to look at the passage of Scripture
so that we can understand and find how God's heart
is revealed to us in this portion of Scripture,
but we find that the instruction to the believers
is important instruction for us to understand.
Listen, how does it make sense that if we look
at the passage of Scripture, and we say, okay,
let's just identify this person here,
or these people here, they are walking disorderly.
Now, what would constitute the charge
for us to say they're walking disorderly?
Well, there's been instruction given
that they haven't followed, is that fair?
So therefore, we say they're disorderly, right?
Why are they disorderly?
Well, because there was instruction provided
that's not followed, and then I am gonna not follow
the instruction that's given to me
on how to deal with the disorderly.
Do you follow what I'm saying this evening?
So all of a sudden, I look at a situation,
and I say, okay, this person did not obey the instruction,
they're walking disorderly, we know it,
they're a busybody, and then God says to those
that are not, he says, here's how you deal with them,
and we say, no, we don't wanna do that.
Which camp do we find ourselves in?
We then become disorderly.
Maybe not in the same exact way,
but we're not following the instruction.
Are you tracking this evening?
And when we look at this portion of Scripture,
we understand the heart of God.
Notice number two, we know in the first portion
of verse number 14, the instruction to the believers,
in verse number 14, that last phrase, number two,
if you're taking notes, the impact on the offenders.
Notice what it says, that he may be ashamed.
That he may be ashamed.
See, there's something about this behavior,
there's something about this action of those true believers
that are seeking to do right, following the instruction
of the Lord, and following the path that God has set forth,
that's going to have an impact on those offenders.
Now, the reality might be that some of the offenders
might say, who cares, I don't need you anyway.
But I think about a true follower of Jesus Christ,
who now, because of their behavior,
has had this situation where other followers
of Jesus Christ are going to have no company with them
because of their behavior, how does that affect you?
It says that they, that he, may be ashamed.
So we talk about shame, we talk about embarrassment,
we can look at the, in our culture,
we think more in the idea of guilty versus innocent.
But I want you to think about someone that's ashamed.
If you know why you're ashamed,
your behavior's going to change.
Why?
So that you're no longer ashamed.
Does that make sense?
And so we find here that in the text of Scripture,
that God helps us understand why is it that God is saying
to the believers, identify them, mark that man,
and also have no company with him,
that you are going to have and take this approach.
Why?
That he may be ashamed.
See, he didn't listen to the first admonition,
he didn't listen to the first warning,
he blew through the stop sign,
he continued to behave in a disorderly way,
and so the end step is that, okay,
we're gonna have to withdraw ourselves,
we're gonna have to have no company with you,
and that is going to have an impact.
Are you tracking?
I keep asking you because you look like
you're not tracking, all right?
This isn't necessarily an easy passage of Scripture, why?
Because we don't want to deal with it.
You know why we don't want to deal with it?
Because we're emotional.
But I like him, I like Armando.
I like going to his house, he makes good food.
And we have a campfire together,
and so I'm going to ignore,
and I'm not saying he's a troublemaker
or he's in that camp of walking disorderly,
but he's walking disorderly, and I say, but I like him.
And I'm still gonna, listen, we get emotions involved
and then we're not obedient.
The text of Scripture implies
that Armando's already been given warning,
he's already been given instruction,
but he continues to disobey,
he continues to disregard the instruction,
so then God says, okay, believers,
mark him and have no company with him
so that he might be ashamed,
thus changing his behavior,
thus enjoying fellowship once again,
not only with the believers,
but more importantly, with the Lord, amen?
But see, what happens is we wanna come to this position
of, well, you know, well, you know,
they're a really nice person,
and so we gotta look at what the Bible says.
Notice the instruction, the impact.
Number three, in verse number 15,
I want you to note the intended purpose.
Note the intended purpose,
and this is where we get the idea
for the title of the message this evening.
The Bible says this in verse 15,
yet count him, who's him,
it's that one that's been noted or marked,
it's that one that we're having no company with,
it's that individual that is a busybody,
that individual that is walking disorderly,
yet count him not as a busybody.
an enemy, but admonish him as a brother."
That's rich.
That's helpful.
Because in this text of Scripture, in this verse of Scripture, we see these two contrasting
words that are used, enemy and brother.
He says, count him not as an enemy, no, admonish him as a brother.
Now we understand that the Scripture says love your enemies, but I want you to understand
the use of the word here.
And I want you to understand in Philippians, when Paul is writing to the church at Philippi
and he says that there are those that are the enemies of the cross, okay, and as we
look here at this text of Scripture, it's saying, listen, this one that's walking disorderly,
if he's truly saved by the grace of God, if he's a child of God, he's heaven bound, we
treat him, we admonish him as a brother.
We don't count him as an enemy, though we've had to love him, them, whoever it might be,
because love corrects.
What did the Bible tell us about Jesus?
It says, whom he loveth, he correcteth, he chasteneth, right?
Is that what it tells us?
Listen, you know what a birthmark of a believer is?
You go ahead and you start sinning, and if Jesus, the Lord doesn't deal with you, you
better wonder what's going on.
I'm being, listen, my dad disciplined me.
I could tell you stories.
He never disciplined the neighbor kid.
Why?
Because the neighbor kid wasn't his kid, wasn't his responsibility.
And so God disciplines his children, he loves, love is corrective.
I've said this often, that love is best defined as being protective and not permissive.
In our society today, so many people want to say, well, love is love, and just let people
do what they want to do in the name of love, and so on and so forth.
They don't understand the word.
No one carries that out in other arenas of life.
You don't say, well, my kid, my child wants to go play on 66 at 7.30 in the morning, and
I'm going to let him do it because I love him.
No, you're not going to let him do it because you love him.
And this is love.
You say, it doesn't look like love.
It's hard.
But it's love.
Why?
Because we're trying to cause that erring brother to be restored, that erring sister
to be restored.
And God, who is the creator, who knows the heart, see, we don't know the heart.
God knows the heart.
God said, this is the prescription.
This is what you do.
So we know, it says, that we count him not as an enemy, but admonish him as a brother.
That word admonish is an interesting word.
It means to warn or to notify of a fault, but it also carries with it the idea of to
reprove with mildness.
To reprove with mildness.
Now, that's an interesting definition and understanding, this admonish him as a brother.
See, when we're going through this process, if we have to deal with this, listen, I am
the first to agree, this is not necessarily a desired path that a church or a pastor would
have to go down, but yet it's necessary at times.
When we say that we admonish him as a brother, we give this rebuke or this reproving with
mildness.
It's interesting that we look at this word and we couple it.
Look over at Galatians 6, if you will.
There's a great sister passage here in Galatians chapter 6 that helps us even understand this
a step further.
Notice in Galatians 6, in verse number 1, the Bible says, brethren, if a man be overtaken
in a fault, I want you to note the next words, ye which are spiritual.
Now, it's always interesting to me that there are people, and we can say this in a whole
number of circumstances, there are people that say, oh, I love Jesus.
Okay, well, He gave us some proof, evidences.
If you love me, keep my commandments.
If you love me, you're going to love your brethren.
I mean, you just start looking at what the Bible says and people can run around and say,
I love Jesus, but if they're disobeying His word, you have to say, hold on, the evidence
does not prove the claim, right?
There are people that say, I'm filled with the Spirit of God.
You know what Ephesians 5, 18 and 19 and 20 tell us?
It shows us what the evidence of being filled with the Spirit of God is.
And so anyone can say, I'm filled with the Spirit of God, but there's evidence in verse
19 and 20, and we say, okay, what is the evidence, okay?
And if that evidence is there and it supports the claim, here, we can look at that from
the state points, the perspective of someone saying, I'm spiritual, well, He says, ye that
are spiritual, ye which are spiritual, restore such and one in the spirit of meekness, considering
thyself, lest thou also be tempted.
He says, if a man be overtaken in a fault, He does not give the details with regard to
what that is, the specifics of it.
He's making it generally a general term because it's a variety of things that could take place
that a man is overtaken in a fault, but He then gives the direction, the instruction,
to ye which are spiritual, and He gives this charge to those that are spiritual.
He says, restore such and one in the spirit of meekness.
I've had situations over the years where I've received phone calls from other places of
ministry and various scenarios would be played out, and the reality is that more times than
I'd like to even remember that those that have been overtaken in a fault did not have
someone spiritual come and try to restore them.
It's like they were kicking them when they were down, criticizing them.
But He says, restore such and one, and He says in the spirit of meekness, and then He
tells us this, considering thyself, lest thou also be tempted.
I said this way back in the study of 1 Thessalonians chapter 5.
I said this as we began looking at that portion of Scripture where the Bible says that we're
to comfort and be patient in verse 14, support the weak, and I said this, you may be the
one doing the comforting this week, but you might be the one needing to be comforted next
week.
Someone said this, the only time we should look down at a brother that's been overcome
in a fault is when we're helping him up.
But oftentimes we look down at them because we're criticizing them and we're not restoring
them.
I want to conclude this evening by looking at Psalm 23 because I said this at the beginning
of the message and I'm going to say it again now.
I believe that the purpose, as we know in this third point this evening, we note the
intended purpose to not count them as an enemy but to admonish them as a brother.
Why?
Because the real purpose is restoration.
The real purpose here is to bring that one back into the fold.
Why is it that God, as I read those verses of Scripture from 2 Chronicles and from the
Psalms where God says He sent His prophets, why?
Because He wants them to return.
And so this purpose reveals the heart of God, that God is a restorer.
One of the kids, I think it was Natalie, said this on Sunday night when she gave her testimony.
She said that she learned some things about Jonah and one of the things that she learned
is that God is a God of second chances.
How many of you are thankful that God is a God of second and third and fourth and twenty-seventh
and you just keep on naming how many chances God is a God of?
Amen?
But let somebody offend us and it's like, hey, one and done, man.
You crossed it.
Seriously.
Look at Psalm 23.
We know it.
We could quote it tonight.
The Lord is my shepherd.
I shall not want.
He maketh me to lie down in green pastures.
He leadeth me beside the still waters.
But here's what I want you to look at in verse 3.
He restoreth my soul.
Listen, our God is a God of restoring.
What a joy.
Because when I got saved and when you got saved and from whenever that was until today,
all right?
For me, it's like 26, almost 27 years.
For each of us, it's a different amount of time.
But from that point until now, there's been some times I needed to be restored, and there's
been some times you've needed to be restored.
And so, when we look at the passage of Scripture in 2 Thessalonians 3 verses 14 and 15, we
must understand this difference between restoration and excommunication.
Unfortunately, there are some that are quick to excommunicate.
Just excommunicate.
But truly, what is the purpose of church discipline?
Truly, what is the purpose of noting that man and having no company with him, that he
might be ashamed and that that shame might change his behavior so that he could be restored?
No, if that individual refuses to change their behavior and continues to walk in disobedience
and continues to be disorderly, well, then we continue to have no company with them.
We continue to identify, to mark that individual and have no company with them.
Why?
Because they're not following the direction that's been given, and we better be following
the direction that's being given, or we're in the same camp as they are.
And so, this evening, I hope that we understand tonight the heart of God, and as we seek
to walk worthy and please God, as His children, we are to have the mind of Christ.
He said this in Philippians 2, let this mind be in you, which was also in Christ Jesus.
We're to have the mind of the Lord.
We're to be like Christ.
And our God is a God who restoreth my soul.
Paul says to those in the region of Galatia, restore such in one in the spirit of meekness,
considering your own self, lest ye also be tempted.
You know, it's interesting in 1 Corinthians 10, God is giving a truth there with regard
to His wonderful promise of providing a way of escape in verse 13, but it says in verse
12, wherefore let him that thinketh he standeth take heed lest he fall.
Take heed lest he fall, in 1 Corinthians 10 and verse 12.
This evening, if we're truly spiritual, we're going to work to restore such in one in the
spirit of meekness.
Communication versus excommunication.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
We thank You for the passage of Scripture.
We thank You for the truth of Your Word.
We thank You for these two sections of these two books that we've been able to study now
for these last six months.
And Lord, I've been helped, and I hope that our folks have been helped.
And Lord, help us to walk worthy, to please You, help us to live our lives in obedience
to Your Word, understanding the principle that we started out with tonight, that instruction
is provided to be followed, to be applied.
Help us, Lord, not to reject instruction, but help us to receive instruction.
Help us, Lord, not to ignore instruction, but to implement instruction in our lives.
We might be doers of the Word and not hearers only.
I pray, God, that You'd bless our time of prayer.
We thank You for the privilege that You've given to us to gather and to pray corporately.
And I pray, Lord, that You'd move and work as only You can.
We'll thank You for it.
In Christ's name we pray, amen.