Amen, and we have such a good God.
He has been so good to us.
And I told the teenagers this morning as we ended our class
that I got a little statement on my desk
that we thank God,
not because our circumstances are always good,
but because he is always good.
And I'm so thankful for the many blessings
in which he has bestowed upon me.
Of course, this week, and we are mindful
in the month of November here in America,
we celebrate Thanksgiving.
And it's always the fourth Thursday
of the month of November.
But I want you to be mindful of the fact
that long before our nation officially proclaimed
the holiday to celebrate God and his blessings
and so on and so forth,
we find that God instructed his people.
And God has, as you study the Bible,
given us instruction that we are to be thankful people.
We're to praise and to give thanks
and enters into his gates with thanksgiving.
And we understand there's many portions of scripture
that we can go to and we can read
that God has given us that instruction.
In fact, we find that consistently God is pleased
when his people give thanks and when they rejoice.
And we also find that as you study the word of God,
that you'll find that God is not pleased
when his people complain.
In fact, we finished our lesson this morning
with that truth from Numbers 11 in verse number one,
that the people complained and it displeased the Lord
and the Lord heard it and his anger was kindled
against them and God is not pleased when we complain.
But we did discover with the small group of us this morning
that all of us acknowledge that it's easier to complain
than it is to give thanks.
It's more natural to complain.
And part of that is our sin nature.
But also I think that there's times
in which we just take things for granted.
And I mentioned to them this morning and I'm repeating it
because I think it's worth us also considering this.
I think probably most of us this morning at some point
along our process of getting ready, flipped a light switch.
And we flipped that light switch
and we expected something to happen
when we flipped the light switch
and that was that the lights would turn on, right?
How many of you thank God for that this morning
when it happened?
Probably not any of us.
We just sometimes don't think about it,
we take it for granted.
I then said, how many of you brushed your teeth this morning
and I hope all of you did.
And you turned the faucet on and the water came out.
Have you ever been in a place
where the water didn't come out?
And you said, oh man, this is a problem, right?
But day after day and week after week,
we take things for granted.
And it gets us into a place where we're not mindful
about giving thanks and being a thankful person.
And we really have to be diligent and disciplined
in our walk with the Lord that we would be,
we would purpose to be someone who gives thanks.
Many times in the book of Psalms you'll find
that the Psalmist says,
I will bless the Lord at all times.
His praise shall continually be in my mouth.
Psalm 34 and verse number one.
But we see that I will statement,
that purpose, that resolve,
that I'm going to be an individual,
I'm gonna be a child of God that praises my God.
Why?
Because there is much to be thankful for.
We sang this morning that familiar Psalm
or hymn, excuse me, count your blessings,
name them one by one.
We find that as we go through
and we understand how the songwriter implores those
that are hearing or even singing that song
to name them one by one, to be reflective,
to be purposed and to be thankful.
And God is so good to us.
I quoted already Psalm 68, 19,
where the Bible says there in that portion of scripture,
the rejoicing, blessed be the Lord
who daily loadeth us with benefits,
even the God of our salvation, Selah.
And certainly this morning,
I think that we would agree
that God has daily loaded us with benefits.
He's been so very good to us.
This morning, as we look at Psalm 23,
I'm gonna really just look at verse number four,
I'll read the entire Psalm.
But this morning, I wanna remind you
and remind us of God's presence.
I'm so thankful for this biblical truth
that we find here in the book of Psalms,
we find it in other portions of scripture as well.
And Psalm 23 is a familiar passage of scripture,
a passage that is often recited and rehearsed.
And it's a precious portion of God's word.
And notice the Bible begins in verse number one,
the Lord is my shepherd, I shall not want.
He maketh me to lie down in green pastures.
He leadeth me beside the still waters.
He restoreth my soul.
He leadeth me in the paths of righteousness
for his namesake.
Yea, though I walk through the valley
of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil
for thou art with me.
Thy rod and thy staff, they comfort me.
Thou preparest a table before me
in the presence of mine enemies.
Thou anointest my head with oil.
My cup runneth over.
Surely, goodness and mercy shall follow me
all the days of my life.
And I will dwell in the house of the Lord forever.
Again, a familiar portion of scripture,
one in which I've preached from.
There's been times that I've preached from Psalm 23
as an entire message, getting through all six verses.
There's been times that I've done a series
through Psalm 23, and we've looked at it verse by verse.
And the reality is that it's a passage of scripture
that's packed with so much truth
that really helps us to understand the relationship
between us and our shepherd.
I've often said, as I come to Psalm 23,
that the Lord is the shepherd.
He is the good shepherd, the great shepherd,
the chief shepherd.
If you look in the New Testament,
you find all of those titles that would be ascribed
to the Lord Jesus Christ.
But here, the psalmist says, the Lord is my shepherd.
And the reality is that he is the good shepherd,
and as the good shepherd, he giveth his life for the sheep.
He is the chief shepherd, and he's gonna appear.
He is the great shepherd.
And we understand those wonderful truths and realities,
but we must recognize this morning the importance
of ensuring that the good shepherd is my shepherd,
that we have that personal relationship
with the Lord Jesus Christ.
We sang that song, Thank You, Lord,
and talk about being thankful for salvation,
which is rich and free.
I'm so thankful that the Lord Jesus Christ,
listen, it wasn't free for him, it was free for us.
The gift requires someone to pay the price.
I've often said to people out soul winning
and knocking doors and engaging people in conversation,
that the Bible says that the wage of sin is death,
but the gift of God is eternal life
through Jesus Christ, our Lord.
And a gift is something that you have to either receive
or you're gonna reject,
but the gift had to be paid for by someone.
The Lord Jesus Christ paid for the gift of eternal life
with his precious blood.
We're not redeemed with corruptible things,
as Peter would say,
but we're redeemed with the precious blood of Christ.
And this morning, before I even get into the message
and all the entirety of what we'll look at this morning,
if you're here this morning and you say,
I don't know that the Lord is my shepherd,
I can't say, as the psalmist says here,
the Lord is my shepherd.
Remember this in John chapter number 10,
the Lord Jesus Christ says, my sheep hear my voice,
and they follow me and I give unto them eternal life
and they shall never perish.
And I'm so thankful this morning that here 27, 28 years ago,
my life was changed forever
because the shepherd became my shepherd.
And I understood on that day that I was in need
of the only savior, the Lord Jesus Christ,
and you too this morning, if you're not sure of heaven today
can be the day of your salvation.
But let me draw for you this morning,
for those of us that are saved this morning,
if you look in verse number four,
yea, though I walk through the valley
of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil.
And then the next phrase is the phrase
in which I wanna focus on our attention this morning,
for thou art with me, thy rod and thy staff,
they comfort me.
For a few minutes this morning,
I wanna just simply meditate and muse upon that thought,
that truth, that reality, thou art with me.
Isn't it a precious truth of God's word?
We'll get to it eventually at the end of the message,
but over there in Hebrews,
the Bible talks about the fact
that I will never leave thee nor forsake thee.
In fact, oftentimes as we speak about promises
that God has given to us in his word,
we'll ask people for, hey, standing on the promises,
share some promises, and it seems as if that one
is one that is regularly mentioned that God is with us.
This morning as we really ponder the thought
and consider this morning that there's no place
that I can go away from the presence of God,
and one day I will be in his presence in heaven,
I'll see him face to face, and I look forward to that day.
But the reality is that he's promised to be with us today.
Thou art with me.
And I want you to think about God's presence
if you're taking notes this morning.
Number one, God's presence brings comfort.
God's presence brings comfort.
You know, we live in a world
in which there's so many things going on.
There's so many trials and difficulties
and things that can bring anxiety and worry
into the lives of people, including the people of God.
Listen, if worry didn't affect you,
then God wouldn't have to say be careful for nothing.
But because it does impact us,
and we do live in this world,
though we're not of this world,
we face circumstances, we face difficulties and trials
and what have you, and there are times
in which we have that time of maybe anxiety and worry
and we're fretting and so on and so forth,
but we find that God's presence brings comfort.
Can I encourage you this morning to understand
that even as we recognize the truth this morning
that God's presence brings comfort,
we see that oftentimes in the lives of even humans,
of children, when children are fearful,
they're afraid because of a circumstance,
many times all they really want is the presence
of mom or dad, and the presence of mom and dad
will bring them a measure of comfort
in that difficult situation.
We see it here in Psalm 23 in verse number four,
we think about the greater context.
Yea, though I walk through the valley
of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil.
There's not a period there,
it's not that I'm not gonna fear evil
just because I'm this person that's not gonna be afraid,
no, it's because thou art with me.
Thy rod and thy staff, they comfort me.
And the very presence of God brings comfort
in the lives of his people, and this morning
I'm thankful that our God is the God of all comfort,
we read that in 2 Corinthians chapter number one,
and what a blessing to know
that he is the God of all comfort,
but he brings comfort, he brings to the heart of his people.
Listen, remember Jesus said this,
let not your heart be troubled.
There are times in which you face circumstances
and situations in life that you can have a troubled heart.
The circumstances by which Jesus Christ
gave that statement to those disciples
was the fact that he let them know
he would soon go to the cross of Calvary,
and he explained to them all that would come to pass
in those days ahead, and he says,
let not your heart be troubled.
He goes on, in fact, turn over to John, if you will,
in chapter number 14, because we find a couple of verses
that we'll look within this text of Scripture
with regard to how God's presence brings us comfort.
He tells them not to be troubled.
We find that as he continues to develop the thought
throughout the passage and throughout
these couple of chapters.
Notice, if you will, in verse number 16 of John 14.
And I want you to consider with me
the reality of these disciples that Jesus is speaking to
and the way in which they had an opportunity
to walk with Christ personally during his earthly ministry.
It was a unique opportunity
that these men had at this season.
In fact, there's only a certain generation of people
that ever had the opportunity to see as an eyewitness
to the Lord Jesus Christ and his ministry and walk with him.
And these disciples had that opportunity
and Jesus is speaking to them.
And he tells them this in verse number 16,
and I will pray the Father
and he shall give you another comforter
that he may abide with you.
What does it say?
Forever.
Verse 17, as he continues, even the spirit of truth
whom the world cannot receive
because it seeth him not, neither knoweth him,
but ye know him for he dwelleth with you
and he shall be in you.
In verse 18, the Bible says,
I will not leave you comfortless, I will come to you.
Now, it's often throughout the scriptures,
throughout the gospels,
there's many references that you find
that really prove the deity of Christ.
Passages of scripture that maybe aren't the top tier,
if you will, that you would go to,
but it's interesting because it says here
that he's gonna send the comforter,
I'll give you another comforter in verse 16.
And verse 18, he says, I will come to you.
And we find as we begin to look here
at the truth of the Trinity,
the fact that God, the Father, God, the Son,
God, the Holy Spirit, here within the context,
we find that Jesus is speaking to these disciples
and he's telling them about the Holy Spirit of God,
the comforter, the spirit of truth.
We sometimes see him referred to as the Holy Ghost
and sometimes as the Holy Spirit,
but we find here that he says
that he may abide with you forever.
See, Jesus Christ was with them at that particular time.
And again, it was a unique opportunity
for those that were living at that time
and for these 12 that we would refer to as disciples
to be able to have that opportunity to walk with Christ.
But we have the Holy Spirit.
At the moment that you trust that Jesus Christ
is your personal savior,
the Holy Spirit of God came in and took up residence.
Your body is the temple of the Holy Ghost.
And we find that in 1 Corinthians chapter number six,
and we can rejoice in understanding
that Jesus is giving this truth.
And as he gives the truth,
he's speaking specifically about his presence,
giving comfort and refers to the Holy Spirit
as the comforter.
Look, if you will, in chapter 16
and look at verse number seven.
Again, as he continues to have this discourse
with his disciples leading to his crucifixion,
we find in verse number seven of chapter 16,
it says, nevertheless, I tell you the truth.
It is expedient for you that I go away.
Now understand with me,
the disciples weren't exactly excited
about the fact that Jesus was gonna go away.
The reality is that there were a bunch of discourse
and things that take place throughout the text of scripture
and they're dealing with this trying time,
this difficult time,
but Jesus says it is expedient for you that I go away.
Notice the rest of the verse,
for if I go not away,
the comforter will not come unto you,
but if I depart, I will send him unto you.
I'm thankful for the ministry of the Holy Spirit of God,
the Holy Ghost.
I'm thankful this morning
that he is the earnest of our inheritance,
that his spirit just,
it's a wonderful truth that we have
as New Testament believers.
His spirit bears witness with our spirit.
And we find this morning
that as you look at the whole of scripture,
that yes, there's times in which you look
at the Old Testament where the Spirit of God
would come upon individuals,
but then you would find that there were times
in which the Spirit of God
would depart from those individuals.
And we find this morning that we have the truth
and the promise that the Holy Spirit
is indwelling us as the people of God.
And what a blessing, the comforter has come.
We sing sometimes that wonderful hymn
and what a great truth it is.
And we find this morning,
this truth of God's presence bringing comfort.
Look, if you will, I mentioned earlier, Hebrews,
look at Hebrews chapter 13, if you will,
Hebrews chapter 13,
and we look at these two verses of scripture,
many times we simply quote the last part
of verse number five.
I will never leave thee nor forsake thee.
And it's not inappropriate that we would quote
that part of the verse,
but I want you to look within context
here in Hebrews 13, verses five and six.
And we look at these two verses of scripture
and we find that there's great truth
that is revealed to us as the people of God.
Notice in verse number five of Hebrews 13,
the Bible says, let your conversation
be without covetousness.
Now there's a whole sermon that you could preach
right there on that verse of scripture.
We live in a world that is a world that covets.
We live in a society that tries to approach you and me
and all those within its culture
to be someone that covets.
I need this, I need more, so on and so forth.
But he says, let your conversation,
your behavior, your lifestyle be without covetousness.
And then he says this, and be content
with such things as you have.
Paul said that he's learned in what sort of state he is
to be content and God's people are to be content,
not to be covetous.
And we find here that he says,
in the context of speaking about covetousness
and contrasting it with being content and having contentment,
he says this, be content with such things as you have,
for he hath said, I will never leave thee nor forsake thee.
Isn't that precious?
Why is it that we should not be covetous?
Why is it that we should be content?
Because we have the presence of God
and it gives us comfort.
We find, we talk about that song,
count your blessings that money cannot buy.
Listen, there are a lot of people that are looking
and they think they can throw money at things
to be able to get, listen, you can't buy comfort.
The Holy Spirit of God is the comforter
and our God is the God of all comfort.
And he can give us comfort in the time
of great trouble and difficulty.
And then we find verse number six as a response really
to the truth that is given to us
at the end of verse number five,
I will never leave thee nor forsake thee
so that we may boldly say,
the Lord is my helper.
And I will not fear what man shall do unto me.
That gives us comfort.
And also as we would bridge into the next point
of our message this morning,
not only does God's presence bring comfort,
but God's presence brings courage.
So you notice in verse number five and six of Hebrews 13,
not only the truth of the Holy Spirit bringing comfort
and that we can say the Lord is my helper.
Can you imagine the amount of comfort that gives us?
And we understand the Lord is my helper.
The one who created all things,
the one who said, let there be light,
he is my helper, the divine helper,
the one that's available, the one that's able.
And we find that it says, and I will not fear,
again, bridging really between the two thoughts this morning
that God's presence brings comfort,
but number two, God's presence brings courage
because I can say, I will not fear what man shall do.
I will only say the Lord's my helper
and I will not fear what man shall do unto me, that courage.
We see comfort, but number two,
we see God's presence brings courage.
You know, we need people of courage today,
people of courage to do what God has called us to do.
To be courageous doesn't mean that you have no fear.
To be courageous doesn't mean it's gonna be simple.
It just simply means that we believe God
and that we're going to do what God's called us to do.
Look, if you will, in the book of Joshua,
look at a couple of examples.
Actually, go back to Genesis.
We'll start in Genesis.
And let's look at a couple of examples this morning
of individual believers that were told about God's presence
and how it gave them courage
to do what God had called them to do.
I believe that God has a plan for each of us.
I believe that God's plan is perfect
and I believe that we need to know God's plan
and seek to do God's plan to fulfill it.
And I believe that as you look throughout the scriptures
that we'll look at a number of men this morning
that had been given an assignment, if you will,
or would be assigned a task,
and God reminds them and reassures them of his presence
and it would give them courage to be able to carry out
what God called them to do.
Jacob, here in Genesis chapter 46,
we find that he's been told
at this particular time in his life,
he had thought that his son had been killed
and he believed that he was dead,
but he finds out that Joseph is alive
and we find that Joseph had sent the brothers back
and sent them with the wagons and all the things
and with the instruction of coming back to Egypt
and bringing dad with them and all those things.
And we come to Genesis chapter 46.
The Bible says in verse number one,
and Israel took his journey with all that he had
and came to Beersheba and offered sacrifices
unto the God of his father, Isaac.
The Bible tells us in verse number two,
when God spake unto Israel in the visions of the night
and said, Jacob, Jacob, and he said, here am I.
Notice what God says beginning in verse number three.
He starts out by saying, I am God.
Isn't that good?
I am God.
That's how God begins to speak to Jacob.
And he says, the God of thy father,
fear not to go down into Egypt.
We find that Jacob does not voice his fear
as far as we have written within the canon of scripture,
but God knows your heart and he knows my heart.
And he tells Jacob to fear not because Jacob was fearful.
He says, fear not to go down into Egypt
for I will there make of thee a great nation.
Notice in verse number four,
I will go down with thee into Egypt.
Isn't that precious?
That God says to Jacob,
he doesn't just tell him to fear not.
He doesn't just tell him
that he's gonna build a great nation there,
but he says, I will go down with thee into Egypt.
And I will also surely bring thee up again
and Joseph shall put his hand upon thine eyes.
We see these promises that God makes in verse three and four
but one of the promises that God gives
is with regard to his presence.
He says, I will go down with thee into Egypt.
And Jacob, we know as you would continue to read,
you find that he comes and indeed he enters into Egypt
and we find later in the text of scripture
that as they come, there's a great reunion and embracing
that he says this in verse number 30 of the same chapter
and Israel said unto Joseph,
now let me die since I have seen thy face
because thou are yet alive.
The Bible says that he fell on his neck
in verse 29 and wept on his neck a good while.
It was a sweet reunion, a sweet embrace,
but I want you to be mindful of the fact
that as he was given this really responsibility,
this opportunity to go to Egypt, he's fearful.
He's in the place at this time
where God had promised him a land
and God's saying, go down into Egypt.
And he says, I will go down with thee.
What a blessing to know the presence of God,
to truly know the comfort that comes,
the courage that comes because why?
God is with me.
Thou art with me.
Notice, if you will, the life of Joshua.
Turn to Joshua chapter number one, if you would.
In Joshua chapter number one,
we fast forward in Israel's history
and we see that there's much that's taking place
and the wilderness wanderings have been fulfilled.
We looked at Jacob, they're going down into Egypt.
They'd be there and they'd be delivered
through the Egyptian bondage
and we understand their deliverance in the book of Exodus.
We read of that following their deliverance.
You read of their wilderness wanderings
and we understand that Moses would not be permitted
to take, to lead as the human leader,
the children of Israel into the land of promise
and God raises up Joshua.
And it's precious to me
as you enter into the book of Joshua,
you find that the book provides us
with just a wonderful account historically
of what took place with the children of Israel
entering into, conquering and inhabiting the land.
But there's a beautiful picture
throughout the book of Joshua
of really victorious Christian living
and how we can have victory.
I'm thankful this morning that we can have victory
through our Lord Jesus Christ.
We find here that as the task would be assigned
and no doubt a serious responsibility
that is given to Joshua,
we begin reading in Joshua chapter number one
and you find that here within the text of scripture,
God is going to reassure
and to promise Joshua of his presence.
Notice with me, if you will,
beginning in verse number one,
we'll read just the first nine verses,
but the Bible says this.
Now, after the death of Moses, the servant of the Lord,
it came to pass that the Lord spake unto Joshua,
the son of Nun, Moses' minister saying,
Moses, my servant is dead.
Now therefore rise, go over this Jordan,
thou and all this people unto the land,
which I do give to them, even to the children of Israel.
Every place that the sole of your foot shall tread upon,
that have I given unto you, as I said unto Moses.
From the wilderness and this Lebanon,
even under the great river, the river Euphrates,
all the land of the Hittites
and unto the great sea toward the going down of the sun
shall be your coast.
Now notice verse five,
there shall not any man be able to stand before thee
all the days of thy life.
As I was with Moses, so I will be with thee.
I will not fail thee nor forsake thee.
Isn't that wonderful?
See, did Joshua know that God was with Moses?
Sure he did.
I mean, Moses, remember he spent time with God.
He was on the Mount
and he had those opportunities to spend time with God,
so much so that he had to put that veil on, right?
Because his face shone and you see all of that.
And Joshua was the minister of Moses.
We read that in verse number one.
And if you look in the book of Deuteronomy
and other portions,
you begin to see that role that Joshua had.
And so Joshua was aware of the fact that God was with Moses,
but God says to Joshua, as I was with Moses,
so I will be with thee.
I will not fail thee nor forsake thee.
So what does he tell him?
What is the impact, if you will?
God's presence brings comfort,
but God's presence brings courage.
Notice in verse number six,
be strong and of a good courage.
For unto this people shalt thou divide for an inheritance,
the land which I swear under their fathers to give them.
Only be thou strong and very courageous
that thou mayest observe to do according to all the law,
which Moses my servant commanded thee,
turn not from it to the right hand or to the left,
that thou mayest prosper whithersoever thou goest.
Verse eight is a familiar verse.
This book of the law shall not depart out of thy mouth,
but thou shalt meditate therein day and night
that thou mayest observe to do according to all
that is written therein.
For then thou shalt make thy way prosperous
and then thou shalt have good success.
Verse nine, have not I commanded thee?
Be strong and of a good courage.
Be not afraid, neither be thou dismayed.
For the Lord thy God is with thee,
whithersoever thou goest.
This charge that's given to Joshua at the beginning,
the opening of this book that contains so much history
and so many exciting portions and exciting miracles of God
as they entered into the land and possessed the land,
we find that God on two occasions between verse five
and verse number nine, reassures his man,
his servant of his presence.
Joshua was one of those that went and spied the land,
was he not?
We read of the 12 spies and we sing the song with the kids
that 10 were bad and two were good.
And those two good spies are Joshua and Caleb.
And Joshua, in fact, not only at that particular.
but even later as he's encouraging various tribes
to possess the land that God has given to them.
He never doubts the difficulties that would be faced.
He never dismisses the realities of life,
but he simply says God is with us and that God is able.
It gives courage, God's presence.
See, when those 10 spies said there are cities
that are fortified, there are walled cities,
there are giants in the land, the sons of Anak are there,
and he says all of those things, these 10 spies,
Joshua and Caleb do not deny the report.
Why?
Because it was a true report.
They saw the walled cities, they observed the giants,
the sons of Anak, but they had a perspective
that was different, and that was that our God is able.
Our God is able.
And here is Joshua, after all of that period
of wilderness wanderings is now going to be,
I don't think he knew in Numbers 13 and 14
when he went to spy, I don't think he knew
that he would be the human man that would lead
the children of Israel into the land of promise.
But here he is, given this great task,
this great responsibility.
Yes, it was God that would do the work,
but there was a human leader, and his name is Joshua,
and God says, I'm with you.
And he reassures him of his presence.
And I believe that as you look through the book of Joshua,
you begin to see the courage, and again,
it's repeated in these verses of Scripture
to be courageous, to have courage,
and we find that it's the truth, the reality
of God's presence that would allow for God's man
to have courage to carry out the task that's been assigned.
Jeremiah, if you would, turn over to the book of Jeremiah,
chapter number one.
We're looking at really three different phases,
if you will, of Israel's history
by looking at these three individuals.
Jacob had been given a promise.
His name is changed to Israel.
He's been given a promise, and now he's gonna go to Egypt,
and it could be conflicting, but God says, I'll be with you.
I will go down into Egypt with you.
There in Egypt, I will build of thee a great nation.
I will make of thee a great nation,
and God gives that promise, and Jacob goes
as God would command and lead him to do so,
and he has that embrace, and we know that after his death,
his children carry him back, even as God said
that they would, and then we come to Joshua,
and we see what's happened in the progress
in Israel's history, and after that period of time
with Joshua, there's a lot that happens.
We have the period of the judges.
We have the period in which those folks
that generation that outlived Joshua,
and we see that period of the judges,
and you get into the prophets, and you get into the kings,
and you understand all that's taken place,
and now Jeremiah, as we come to Jeremiah chapter number one,
we find that he's ministering at a time
in which Israel, the 10 tribes of the north,
have already been taken captive.
They've been taken captive by the Assyrians.
It's happened long ago as far as Jeremiah's time
of prophecy is concerned, and now we're on the eve
of Babylonian captivity.
The people of God have rebelled greatly against God.
We find that the people of God, they had forgotten God,
they had served idols, they followed after these idols,
all that was taking place, and Jeremiah is called upon
to minister at that time.
What a difficult time.
The people didn't wanna hear him.
The people resisted his message.
The people wanted to kill him.
Amen?
I mean, they imprisoned him.
I mean, all the things that happened to Jeremiah,
and we find all of this that would happen,
and Jeremiah's ministering at this very difficult time.
God had promised the children of Israel a land,
but he also told them that if they disobeyed
that he would expel them from that land,
and we see that that's exactly what God did.
Why?
Because God's people were disobedient,
and we find that the Babylonian captivity
would be for 70 years.
The reason is because of the Sabbaths
and the fact that they didn't observe
like they were supposed to,
and God has given all of this instruction,
but I want you to think about Jeremiah.
Here in Jeremiah one, it's really the commission
of Jeremiah, and we read in verse number one,
it begins to tell us about the time and so on and so forth,
the days of Josiah in verse number two,
so that we can have a setting as to what's going on
with regard to the timing,
but I want to begin looking in verse number five.
Verse four says this,
then the word of the Lord came unto me saying,
verse five, before I formed thee in the belly, I knew thee,
and before thou came as forth out of the womb,
I sanctified thee, and I ordained thee a prophet
unto the nations, isn't that an encouraging verse
of scripture that really reminds us
of the sanctity of life?
The message this morning is not on abortion,
but oh, how wicked that sin is,
and our land is ripe for judgment
because of that evil, wicked sin.
We find that the Bible says in verse number six,
then said I, ah, Lord God, behold, I cannot speak,
for I am a child.
But the Lord said unto me, say not I am a child,
for thou shalt go to all that I shall send thee,
and whatsoever I command thee, thou shalt speak.
Don't you like how God responds to his excuse
as to why he can't do it?
Have you ever been in a situation where you try,
God, I can't do that.
Moses, it didn't work well for him, right?
It doesn't work well for Jeremiah,
Jeremiah says I'm just a child.
And God says, say not I am a child,
for thou shalt go to all that I shall send thee,
and whatsoever I command thee, thou shalt speak.
And so we find that God is telling Jeremiah
that you are to do this and you're not gonna have,
I'm not gonna accept your excuses.
Look at verse eight, be not afraid of their faces,
then notice this, for I am with thee,
to deliver thee, saith the Lord, for I am with thee.
Jeremiah was gonna have to preach some hard messages.
Jeremiah is gonna have to stand before people
that, as I mentioned a moment ago,
wanna kill him, imprison him, that resist him.
The false prophets that were prophesying at the time
that were itching the ears of the people
and they all wanted to flock after those false prophets
and say, well, these guys said this,
and here's what they're,
and Jeremiah, that's where he's ministering.
And God says, I am with thee,
to deliver thee, saith the Lord.
What a great promise, the reality of God's presence.
Listen, can I tell you this morning
that God was with Jeremiah when he was in his home?
God was with Jeremiah when he was in the palace,
when he was giving that word to the king?
God was with Jeremiah when he was in the dungeon?
Come on, amen?
God was with Jeremiah when he was in the pit?
Was he in the pit?
Come on, they had to let him out of the pit, did they not?
They put all those sheets or rags together
and they tied them up and they pulled him out of the pit.
God was with them in every one of those places.
By the way, was God with, we didn't deal with Joseph,
but was God with Joseph when he was at home?
Sure he was.
Was God with Joseph when he went out
to find his brethren?
Sure he was.
Was God with Joseph when he was with the folks
that bought him to bring him into slavery?
Yes.
Was God with them when he was in Potiphar's house,
when he was in the prison, when he was in the palace?
Come on.
God's presence, it brings comfort, it brings courage.
In verse nine of Jeremiah one,
the Bible says, then the Lord put forth his hand
and touched my mouth, and the Lord said unto me,
behold, I have put my words in thy mouth.
See, I have this day set thee over the nations
and over the kingdoms to root out, to pull down,
and to destroy, and to throw down, to build, and to plant.
Wow, what a task that Jeremiah would be given.
He would need courage.
And God says, I'm with you.
And I'm thankful for that promise.
As we look at these various aspects of Israel's history,
and we see Jacob, and we see Joshua, and we see Jeremiah,
I'm reminded this morning that God's given us a promise.
Yes, we looked at it in Hebrews 13 verse five and verse six,
but I want you to go to Matthew chapter 28, if you will.
In the context of what we're focusing on this morning,
and we're thinking about each of these individuals,
and really a task that's been assigned to them,
and we begin to understand that in each of these instances,
we can see how God's presence,
the promise of his presence,
would bring comfort and give courage.
We find that as we enter into the 28th final chapter
of the book of Matthew, that God records for us
what we often refer to as the Great Commission.
We find that the Great Commission is really recorded for us
in each of the Gospels, plus the book of Acts.
We see that God wanted to make sure
that his people knew what their mandate was.
Why did God leave us here?
Did he leave us here so that we could make a name
for ourselves, so that we could build a kingdom
for ourselves?
No, he left us here to be his witnesses.
And I think sometimes we lose sight of that.
We lose sight of that.
We have this perspective that's just different.
I was listening to somebody not long ago
when I was down at that Macedonia mission.
conference. And the man said this, he said, how many of you know your dad? That was kind
of an easy question. How many of you know your granddad? How many of you know your great-grandfather?
How many of you know your great-great-grandfather? How many of you know your great-great-great-grandfather?
And he just kind of went through this to like four or five greats. And he said this, I would
imagine that for most of us, not only do we not know them, we don't even know what their
name is. Now, unless you're into genealogies and lineage and that sort of thing, you probably
don't know your great-great-great-great-great-grandfather or grandmother's name and all that kind of
stuff. I don't. I have not a clue. And I heard the message and I didn't even go back and
look it up. I have no idea. And then he said this, if you have children, your children
know you. And if you are going to be blessed to have grandchildren, hopefully your grandchildren
will know you. But he said the same thing that's true of us not knowing our great-great-great-great-great-grandfather,
in a few greats from now, they're not going to know you. They're not even going to know
your name. You ever think about that? Sometimes we get so busy trying to build a kingdom,
build a name for ourselves here. And really, God didn't leave us here for that. He didn't
leave us here for that. There's very few people in history that are known generationally.
Very few people. Very few. George Washington is a name that we know in this country. But
I would beg to… There's billions of people on this planet that have no idea who George
Washington is. You know why? They're not Americans. Do you understand what I'm saying?
You go to some of these remote places around the world, it doesn't even have to be remote.
Just like I don't know who founded their country, who was the first president of their
country. I have no idea unless I've studied it and I'm interested in that. There are
very few people. But what do you do? We're to live for the name of Christ. He must increase,
I must decrease. It's all about Him. And when I come to Matthew 28 and understand the
mandate that God has given us to be His witnesses, I want you to notice what God says here.
Jesus, before His ascension, and we see what's happening. They come, they're worshiping.
In verse number 18, Jesus begins to speak to them. And here's what Jesus says. All power
is given unto me in heaven and in earth. That ought to cause you to rejoice right there.
He has all power. He doesn't have some limited. He's got all power. He says this. Go ye, therefore,
and teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and
of the Holy Ghost, teaching them to observe all things whatsoever I have commanded you.
I know it's not a period, but I'm going to stop there. It's a colon. I'm going to stop
there just for a moment. I want you to understand that in verse 19 and 20, up to the point in
which we've read, this is a task that's nearly impossible. That we're to go and we're to
go preach the gospel, we're to baptize people, we're to make disciples of people, we're to
go do all of this. This is a task that's overwhelming. We read in Acts, as Jesus would say it that
way, Jerusalem, all Judea, Samaria, the uttermost part of the earth. Begin to think about the
number of people that are on planet earth today. And even with all of the just amazing
opportunities that we have for travel and communication, the task is overwhelming. Just
as you would think about Joshua leading a people into a nation, into a land, that's
a walled land, a fortified land, a military people, giants in the land. Just as you think
of Jeremiah standing and preaching before people that don't want to hear him, that want
to imprison him and want to kill him. God told them, I'm with you. And God gave this
assignment, this mandate, and notice what he says as we continue reading verse 20, and
lo, I am with you always, even unto the end of the world. Amen. You know, that word lo
is an interesting word. Sometimes that word is just kind of overlooked and we maybe don't
skip it. We read it, but we just kind of skip through and just deal with it. But that word
lo is really kind of a word that would be used to grab someone's attention. Look, see,
behold, observe. That's kind of, and lo, right, like he's going to use that word to grab their
attention why the word was used to excite particular attention in the hearer to either
some object of sight or to a subject of discourse. That's how the word was used. That was the
purpose of using the word. By the way, every word of God is pure. Amen. And so when Jesus
says, and we have it recorded in our Bible, and lo, I am with you always, even unto the
end of the world. Amen. That word is to grab our attention, to excite the attention of
the hearer. Why? Of this particular subject of discourse that as we have this assignment
to go into all the world and preach the gospel to every creatures, it's recorded in Mark, to
hear, go ye therefore teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, the Son, the
Holy Ghost, teaching them to observe all things whatsoever I commanded you. God says this, I'm
with you. And lo, I am with you always, even unto the end of the world. Amen. His presence
gives me comfort, but His presence gives me courage to do what He's called me to do, to
fulfill the task that He's assigned for me. When Joshua's given a task, God says, I'm
with you. When Jeremiah's given an assignment, He says, I'm with you, for us as God's people.
In 2025, we've been given a task, we've been given an assignment, and God says, I am with
you. The psalmist, as he writes there in Psalm 23, I will fear no evil as I pass through
the valley of the shadow of death. Why? Thou art with me. This morning, God's presence,
if you're saved this morning, it's a reality. God's presence. And it should bring comfort
and it should bring courage to be able to do what He's called us to do, to carry out
the task that's been assigned to us. I'm thankful. Listen, there's so many things that
we should be thankful for. And I hope that you have a list that just keeps on going that
you would name them one by one. Thanking God for who He is, for what He's done. We have
such a wonderful God. But this morning, I want to just remind us to be thankful for
His presence and to understand what His presence, how His presence will impact us as His people.
That we would get, that we would receive the comfort in these troublesome days, difficult
days. So know God's presence is with me and it gives me comfort. That we'd have courage
to carry out and do what He's called us to do. Let's pray. Father, we do love you. We
thank you so much for loving us. We thank you this morning for your presence. We thank
you that it's real. God, we thank you this morning for the many promises you've given
us in your word with regard to your presence. We thank you, God, for the privilege of being
able to look at various characters within your word that received confirmation of this
reality of your presence and how it impacted them. This morning, I pray that you would
help us as your people to rejoice because of your presence in our lives. We'd have
that comfort and that courage. Lord, as we started this morning, we spoke about the Lord
being my shepherd and I'm so thankful to be saved. But maybe this morning there's someone
here that's not sure of heaven. Maybe they've heard many times that, God, you love them
and you want to save them and that they need to be saved. Lord, I pray that through this
message today that perhaps your Spirit has spoken to them, convicted them of their sin,
of Christ's righteousness, of judgment to come. Let it be willing to come so that we
could take a Bible and show them how they could know for sure that heaven's their home,
not leaving here without having that assurance. And God, I think about your people, those
of us that are saved this morning. We live in perilous times, difficult days. God, help
us to be reminded this morning and then to rejoice because of your presence. That as
we go through life seeking to do what you've called us to do, that we'd be reminded that
you're with us, that you would give us the comfort and the courage that we need. Help
us not to be troubled and to have anxiety and worry and help us to trust you, to trust
and rejoice in your presence. I pray that in these moments of invitation that you have
your will and way in the hearts of your people, help us, Lord, to now talk to you about what
you've talked to us about. Lord, that we'd come to the old-fashioned altar, we'd pray,
and Lord, that we would be doers of the word and not hearers only. Would you help us to
live anew with the reality of your presence? I pray that you'd move and work for it's in
Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed. Mark's
here up at the front. If you're a man not sure of heaven, take a Bible so you can know
for sure that heaven's your home.
Heaven's your home.
Holly's here in the front.
If you're a lady, not sure of heaven,
she'll take a Bible and show you.
I can know for sure that heaven is your home.
If you're saved this morning,
maybe you just need to come and thank God for His presence.
Maybe you've been living under the circumstances.
You've been dealing with some of that anxiety, fear,
worry, so on and so forth,
and you just need to come and thank God for the reminder.
Not that you forgot that He was with you,
but just the reminder that you'd rejoice
and thank Him for it and live each day
with the awareness that God is with you.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.