As you know, we've been preaching through the book of Genesis.
This is our 30th lesson, and in the last several weeks,
we have not been in the book of Genesis for our evening services.
In fact, last Sunday evening, we had a special cyber praise
and Thanksgiving and favorites, and it was a blessing.
I thoroughly enjoyed it.
And it was good to hear from our church family.
And you give testimony to the Lord.
Let the redeemed of the Lord say so.
And we appreciate the opportunity to hear your testimonies
and to sing those wonderful praises unto the Lord.
And it's been a number of weeks, though, that we've not been
in the book of Genesis.
In fact, in our last lesson, I mentioned that our next lesson
in Genesis would be on dinosaurs.
And I know that a lot of people are looking forward to that.
And I just didn't want to do it through live stream basically only.
And so the dinosaur lesson will come at some point.
And we're going to continue moving through the passage of scripture
that is before us this evening.
And I will make sure that I do preach that message
and share those things with you.
I trust it to be a blessing for those of you
that have been with us through the process.
We dealt with an entire lesson on really the impacts of the flood
and all of those things.
And we looked at the Grand Canyon and many other canyons
and had a very interesting, informative message on that subject.
And then in our very last study, we dealt with the Ice Age
and what some would say with regard to the Ice Age.
But as we have a biblical worldview and we take what God has recorded for us
in Genesis six, seven and eight and begin to interpret things accordingly,
we find that what they and when I say they, I mean
most modern science would tell us with regard to the Ice Age.
We find that there is a biblical approach
that we can take to that subject.
This evening, as we come to Genesis chapter nine,
we find and I'll title the message these first seven verses.
I've simply given a title this evening, Life After the Flood.
You'll recall that in Genesis chapter eight, we had the opportunity
to have the record that God provided us with of the day
in which Noah and his family came off the ark.
Of course, we know that the animals, they also made an exit.
And it's interesting, as you find near the end of Genesis chapter
eight in the beginning of the chapter, we find that God mentions
that he would cause a wind to pass over the earth and the waters assuaged.
And it was a lengthy period of time before the earth was dry.
And we come to verse number 13 of Genesis eight.
And the Bible says it came to pass in the six hundredth and first year
in the first month, the first day of the month, the waters were dried up
from off the earth.
And Noah removed the covering of the ark and looked and behold,
the face of the ground was dry.
And then it says in the second month, on the seven and twentieth day
of the month, was the earth dried and God spake unto Noah saying,
Go forth of the ark.
That had to be a wonderful day when they got to get off of the ark.
And they had been on the ark for a lengthy period of time and over a year.
And we find that he says, now, my wife, my sons and my sons, wives with me.
And of course, the animals made an exit as well, as I mentioned a moment ago.
And it's interesting after they exit the ark, after they were there.
And of course, safety was in the ark.
That was the place of refuge.
And we find that they came off the ark.
The first matter of business was worship.
We find at the end of chapter eight and verses 20
and verse number 20, specifically,
that the Bible gives us the record that Noah builded an altar unto the Lord
and he offered burnt offerings on the altar.
And what a way that they would begin life
after they would exit that ark that they had spent that length of time on.
And we find that the first matter of business was worship.
And, oh, it's important that we worship our God.
He is worthy of our worship.
And we find that the word in its original form
in the English language as it was first translated,
we find that it was actually translated worth ship and someone that was worthy.
And we find that our God is worthy and he is to be worshiped.
Now we find as we come to chapter number nine, that God would provide
some instruction with regard to living life after the flood.
We find that in chapter number nine, that the covenant that God will make
with Noah is recorded and really begins in verse number eight.
As we go through the remaining passage of Genesis nine,
we'll begin to study that on next Sunday.
That'll be the subject of our study.
But this evening, as we look at these first seven verses,
I want to preach a message that I've simply entitled Life After the Flood.
Notice in verse number one of Genesis nine, the Bible says,
and God bless Noah and his sons and said unto them,
be fruitful and multiply and replenish the earth.
And the fear of you and the dread of you shall be upon every beast of the earth
and upon every fowl of the air, upon all that moveth upon the earth
and upon all the fishes of the sea into your hand.
Are they delivered?
Every moving thing that liveth shall be meat for you,
even as the green herb have I given all things, given you all things.
Verse four, but flesh with the life thereof,
which is the blood thereof, shall ye not eat?
And surely your blood of your lives will I require
at the hand of every beast will I require it.
And at the hand of man, the hand of every man's brother,
will I require the life of man who so shed man's blood by him.
Shall his blood be shed from the image of God made he man
and you be fruitful and multiply,
bring forth abundantly in the earth and multiply therein.
As we look at this passage of Scripture and begin to consider
the instruction that God would give for living life on earth after the flood,
we notice, first of all,
that God gives them instruction with regard to reproduction.
We find that here in the passage of Scripture in verse number one
and again in verse number seven,
that you read this instruction to Noah and to his sons
to be fruitful and multiply.
And we find that he tells them to replenish the earth in verse number one.
In verse number seven, to be fruitful and to multiply,
bring forth abundantly in the earth and multiply therein.
And we find that God would provide this instruction.
You'll recall with me this evening
that it was only those that were within the ark that survived.
You remember that being in the ark was critical.
It was crucial for those that lived during that time.
In Genesis chapter number six,
if you turn back just a few pages in your Bibles and look at Genesis chapter number six,
you find that God is going to make the announcement,
the prophecy, if you will, with regard to that which he would bring to pass.
In verse number seven of Genesis six, the Bible says,
And the Lord said, I will destroy man whom I have created from the face of the earth,
both man and beast and the creeping thing and the fowls of the air,
for it repented me that I have made them.
We find that the Bible tells us that Noah found grace in the eyes of the Lord.
We find that God began to give him instruction.
It's interesting in verse number 13 of Genesis chapter number six
that God said unto Noah, The end of all flesh has come before me,
for the earth is filled with violence through them.
And behold, I will destroy them with the earth.
And the very next statement in verse number 14 is make thee an ark of gopher wood.
And we find that it was the ark in which God would instruct Noah on building this ark
where they would find refuge and safety within the ark.
There was only one door, as we mentioned, as we studied that passage of scripture.
And it's recorded for us in verse number 16.
And we find that on the appointed day, when God was ready to send the rain.
And of course, we understand that the deep was opened up, broken up.
And we find that God gave the instruction in Genesis chapter number seven
for Noah and his family to get into the ark.
It tells us in verse number seven, and Noah went in and his sons and his wife
and his son's wives with him into the ark because of the waters of the flood.
And what a blessing that we understand that God then tells us in verse number 16,
And they that went in, went in male and female of all flesh, as God had commanded him.
And the Lord shut him in.
There was safety in the ark.
And we find that all of those that were without the ark, that they would be destroyed.
And that is given to us in chapter six.
We find this truth of Noah and his family being there in that place of safety in chapter number seven.
And the Bible tells us the fulfillment of this, which God said would come to pass
is recorded for us in verse number 22 of Genesis seven, when the Bible says,
all in whose nostrils was the breath of life of all that was in the dry land died.
That's a global flood.
We've spoken about that often.
You find that it says all in whose nostrils was the breath of life
of all that is in the dry land died.
And so we find that based upon the fact that all human life died during that flood,
of course, the animals that were thought that were not on the ark.
ark, they died as well, except for those that were living within the waters. And
we find that here, as we come to the ninth chapter, after Noah and his family
exit the ark, after they make offering to the Lord, that the Lord speaks to them
and God blessed them, and God said, be fruitful and multiply and replenish the
earth. The Bible tells us that He said to bring forth abundantly in the earth and
multiply therein. I believe that God, as He would instruct them to be fruitful
and multiply, as He told them there in verse number 7 about the abundance and
about the multiplication, I believe that God blessed and God allowed them to bear
fruit abundantly. There are some that would be critics, they would
criticize some of that which is given with regard to the descendants and
some of the timelines, and they would argue about the number of people upon
the earth, and there's no way that you could have that many people that quickly
and so on and so forth, but we find that God is the giver of life, and we find
that God blesses, and here I believe that God, as He told them to be fruitful and
multiply, and He spoke about those words abundance and multiply, it's interesting
as we take that truth and look at a verse of Scripture in the book of Psalms, if
you will, in Psalm 107, and I'll give you a moment to turn there, but really in
Psalm 107 there's a whole lot of things that are being dealt with here in this
Psalm, and giving thanks unto the Lord for His good, for He is good, His mercy
endureth forever. It's the passage of Scripture where we get that phrase, let the
redeemed of the Lord say so, as we quote the first portion of verse number 2, and
we look through and many things are dealt with, but there's an interesting
truth that is given to us in Psalm 107 in verse number 38, and I will not tell
you this evening that this is specifically in reference to Genesis 9,
it's not, it's just a principle that God would give us that I believe could also
be applied to what we see in Genesis 9, where the Bible says, He blesseth them
also, so that they are multiplied greatly, and suffereth not their cattle to
decrease. You know, it's interesting if you would look at the exponential growth
of the nation of Israel from the time in which Jacob and his sons entered into
the land of Egypt, in the time in which Joseph was in the place of authority
where he was, and then when you come to the end of his life and the new Pharaoh
that rises up, and you think about the fear of the new Pharaoh because of the
amount of people, of the children of Israel, he was fearful, and God was able
to bless and greatly multiply, and he gives them instruction with regard to
reproduction. We notice that he not only deals with the subject of reproduction
and multiplying and replenishing the earth, but then we find that he gives
them instruction regarding their diet. I was joking with someone this afternoon,
and I said, it's an exciting passage of Scripture, for Noah and his family were
now permitted to eat meat, and that's a wonderful thing, amen? I like meat, and I
enjoy a salad every once in a while is okay, but I like meat. If you add chicken
to the salad, it makes the salad tolerable, you know? But here in verse
number two, there was, before he gets to the dietary thing in verse three, notice
in verse number two, there was going to be a distinct difference between the
life prior to coming on the ark and even the period of time in which they were on
the ark and then life after the ark with regard to the interaction between man
and beast. We find in verse number two that says, the fear of you and the dread
of you shall be upon every beast of the earth, and upon every fowl of the air,
upon all that moveth upon the earth, and upon all the fishes of the sea, into your
hand are they delivered. And we could see the dominion there, the dominance, if you
will, and we can understand that there's a distinction between the human kind and
the animal kind, as God would give us that truth even in Genesis chapter number
one with regard to the creation. And we come here and we see there's this
distinct difference as to the interaction between man and beast. We
understand today that interaction, and we understand the way in which there are
wild animals that are not safe for us to be around, and we could think about all
of the animals that were on the ark and all of those things that had taken place.
It's interesting, if you look to some of the passages in the Old Testament
prophets with regard to the prophecies of that which will take place during the
millennial reign of Christ, and how some of that will return to what it was prior
to this particular time that is mentioned in Genesis 9. This now
continues to be the case even through today, and we find that there is that
distinct difference between the interaction of mankind and beast. We then
see in verse number three, the Bible says, every moving thing that liveth, notice
this, shall be meat for you. And we find that here as we would discover that
there would now be a change in diet. He says this at the end of verse number
three, even as the green herb which I, excuse me, have I given you all things.
Now what is God referring to here in verse number three? He's speaking to Noah.
He's referring back to what he gave to Adam in the creation originally in
Genesis 1 in verse number 29. Notice what the Bible says there in the passage of
Scripture. He tells us, of course, in verse 27 about creating man in his own image.
And we come to verse 29, and God said, behold, I have given you every herb
bearing seed which is upon the face of all the earth, and every tree in the
world which is the fruit of a tree yielding seed, lotus, to you it shall be
for meat. And we find in verse 30, into every beast of the earth, every fowl of
the air, into everything that creepeth upon the earth, wherein there is life, I have
given every green herb for meat, and it was so. As we studied the passage of
Scripture in Genesis 1 and the record of creation, and we understood how God
created in order, and how he sustained his creation, and really the wisdom of
God that's on display in Genesis chapter number one. But we find here in Genesis
9, in verse number 3, is they would exit the ark, that this new life after the
flood would include a change in diet. We find that however this change would be,
that they were given a restriction according to verse number 4. It says, but
flesh with the life thereof, which is the blood thereof, shall ye not eat. And so
we find there's a restriction given, they're not to eat, they're not permitted
to eat it with the blood, according to verse number 4. We find that reference
about the life, the flesh with the life thereof, and the fact that the blood is
the life. And we'll see that this truth of the dietary changes that are mentioned
in verses 3 and 4 of Genesis chapter number 9 are further developed in the
book of Leviticus. And we understand that under the Levitical law that there
were many dietary regulations that were given, and these things will be expounded
upon there in the book of Genesis. It's interesting as we would think about
being New Testament believers, and we think about our place in the history of
mankind, and we'd understand that we're living in such a time in which we have
the opportunity to partake of those things that God has given us as far as
diet is concerned. There are some, however, that would teach in the last days, the
false teachers, as Paul would deal with in 1 Timothy chapter 4, that would
teach, they would command to abstain from meats. But the Bible says in verse number
3 of 1 Timothy 4, which God hath created to be received with thanksgiving of them
which believe and know the truth, for every creature of God is good, and
nothing to be received if it is received with thanksgiving. And we understand that
there are the dietary regulations for the nation of Israel that are given in
the book of Leviticus, and we find that as we look as New Testament believers,
that these truths that have been given to us as far as our diet, and the
fact that there would be some false teachers in the last days that would
give commandments with regard to abstaining from meats. By the way, it's an
interesting study to study some of the religious organizations that have some
of those restrictions and commandments, and how the Lord in His Word had given
prophecy concerning those things so that we could identify those that would be
false teachers. As we continue in Genesis chapter 9, and we look at the
instruction that is given, we find that He then, God, will give instruction to
Noah with regard to murder. It's interesting the instruction that God
gives. He gives them instruction about reproduction, He gives them instruction
about their diet, and then He gives them an instruction about murder. And really
as we think about this instruction that's given to them about murder, we
find that what God is doing is reminding them of the value of life. Why is life
valuable? Because God is the Creator. Because He is the giver and sustainer of
life. See, when you remove God from the equation, you've devalued life. That's
part of the problem in our society today. When we have devalued life, it's because
of this Darwinian mindset of evolution and what-have-you, and we therefore,
through
this false teaching and this false indoctrination
upon the new generation,
we find that this is devaluing life.
But God values life.
We find that as we look here
in these verses of Scripture,
that God will give specific commandment
with regard to the one that would be
guilty of murder.
Notice in v. 5,
"...and surely, your blood of your lives
will I require at the hand of every beast
and at the hand of every man's brother
shall I require the life of man."
Notice in v. 6 that He gives expounded truth.
"...whoso sheddeth man's blood,
by man shall his blood be shed."
Why?
"...for in the image of God made He man."
Remember in Genesis 1 and v. 27,
and really you could think about v. 26
along with it,
when God said,
let us make man in our image
after our likeness
and let them have dominion
over the fish of the sea,
over the fowl of the air,
and over the cattle,
and over all the earth,
and over every creeping thing
that creepeth upon the earth.
So, God created man in His own image.
In the image of God created He Him.
Male and female created He them.
We have been made in the image of God.
We find that that's the reminder
that God would give to Noah
when they would exit the ark
and after they would make offering
God's words to Noah,
the first level of instruction
that he would receive
after departing the ark
would include instruction
about the value of life.
"...whoso sheddeth man's blood,
by man shall his blood be shed.
For in the image of God made He man."
By the way, I'm thankful that God is the Creator.
I'm thankful that God gives us
a record of creation.
We understand and identify
the Lord as being the Creator.
In fact, one of the verses
that we've quoted often
during these past several weeks
is there from Psalm 121
where the Bible talks about,
"...I would lift up My knives into the hills
from whence cometh My help.
My help cometh from the Lord
which made heaven and earth."
And what a joy to know
that He is the Creator.
That He's my Creator.
I'm thankful that He's my Redeemer as well.
But we find that according to Romans 1,
that the people,
they want to deny God as being the Creator.
And this difficulty that enters
into the thought process of man,
and as we've said multiple times,
how the first 11 chapters of the book of Genesis
are so foundational
because of the truth that is contained therein,
and how it impacts the whole of Scripture.
We find that there's a concentrated effort
to attack the first nine chapters
of the book of Genesis
to undermine the authority of God's Word
to deny the fact that He is the Creator.
But we find often repeated,
not only in the book of Genesis,
but throughout the entirety of God's Word,
the reference and the recognition
that God is the Creator.
Now we understand,
as He would speak about the value of life,
we are given the grounds in this verse of Scripture
for capital punishment.
He said,
"...whoso sheddeth man's blood,
by man shall his blood be shed."
The grounds for capital punishment.
Notice, if you will,
if you turn to the New Testament,
Romans 13,
as God would give reference to the truth
with regard to human government.
And we're thankful that our God
rules in the affairs of man.
We're thankful as the truth of God's Word
tells us that the heart of the King
is in the hand of the Lord.
And what a blessing that is.
Our God is in control.
He has established government.
We find in Romans 13,
notice in verses 3 and 4,
the Bible says,
"...for rulers are not a terror to good works,
but to the evil.
Wilt thou then not be afraid of the power?
Do that which is good,
and thou shalt have praise of the same.
For He is the minister of God to thee for good.
But if thou do that which is evil,
be afraid.
For He beareth not the sword in vain,
for He is the minister of God,
a revenger to execute wrath upon Him
that doeth evil."
We find that here in the Word of God
that there is the grounds,
the truth with regard to this truth
of capital punishment.
It's an interesting reference
in Ecclesiastes 8 and verse number 11
where the Bible says,
"...because sentence against an evil work
is not executed speedily,
therefore the heart of the sons of men
is fully set in them to do evil."
Wow, what a powerful verse
in Ecclesiastes 8 and verse number 11.
We believe in proper process of justice
and the process in which that is to go through
and certainly determining the guilt of an individual.
But once that guilt is established,
the Bible would make it clear
that the execution of the sentence
should be done speedily.
We find that here in the Word of God,
this truth with regard to the value of life
and the grounds for capital punishment.
Yes, we understand that further details
just as the case would be
with regard to the dietary changes
that are mentioned in verses 3 and 4
that those things would be further expounded upon
on the book of Leviticus.
So also will this truth that we find here
given to Noah as he would exit the ark,
these things are further developed through the law.
Now I want you to consider with me
this fact that is given to us
that he speaks about capital punishment
and he speaks about murder.
Whoso sheddeth man's blood,
by man shall his blood be shed.
I want you to consider with me a few things.
Number one, go back to the book of Genesis,
excuse me, to the chapter just a couple before,
Genesis chapter number four,
and I want you to recall with me
what happened in the first family.
Of course, we know that God created Adam and Eve
and the Bible records for us in Genesis chapter number four
how that Eve, excuse me, Adam knew Eve his wife
and she conceived and bear Cain
and said, I've gotten a man from the Lord.
And she again bear his brother Abel.
The Bible begins to tell us about the time
in which they would bring an offering
and we've dealt with this several weeks ago.
And we find that we come here in Genesis four
to verse number eight.
The Bible says that Cain talked with Abel his brother
and it came to pass when they were in the field
that Cain rose up against Abel his brother and slew him.
The first murder is recorded in the Word of God.
By the way, there are many murders
that are recorded in the Word of God.
And this is the first of those murders that is recorded
where Cain slew Abel.
We find that in the same chapter
that the Bible records for us
that Lamech also was guilty of murder
where he says in verse number 23 of Genesis four
and Lamech said unto his wives, Ada and Zillah,
hear my voice you wives of Lamech,
hearken unto my speech
for I have slain a man to my wounding
and a young man to my hurt.
We find that Cain slew Abel
that Lamech as well was guilty
of this heinous crime of murder.
We come to the sixth chapter of the book of Genesis
that which would lead to the destruction of mankind
and the flood that would come upon the earth.
And we find that God says this
about the man that his own creation, man that he created.
It says in verse number five,
God saw that the wickedness of man was great in the earth
and that every imagination of the thoughts of his heart
was only evil continually.
Skip to verse 11 and the Bible says
that the earth also was corrupt before God
and the earth was filled with violence.
We find that reference again in verse number 13
right in the middle of the verse
where the Bible says the earth is filled
with violence through them.
So we find that this thing of murder
was taking place all the way back with Cain and Abel
and then with Lamech and then prior to the flood
all of the violence and all of the wickedness
that was taking place.
And we come as we look at this instruction
that is now given to the family of Noah,
Noah and his sons, the three sons of Noah,
four of the eight people that get off of the ark,
Noah and his three sons.
The Bible says that God spake to them,
God blessed Noah and his sons and said unto them.
He instructed them with regard to reproduction,
with regard to diet and with regard to the value of life,
with regard to the subject of murder.
Now we understand that decisions have consequences
and the groundwork, the foundation if you will,
for capital punishment is given here.
Whoso sheddeth man's blood, by man shall his blood be shed.
I mentioned this morning about the cities of refuge
and I wanna make just a quick reference to that
this evening in Numbers 35.
We won't deal with all of the additional details
that are given to us in the word of God
about the subject of murder,
but we find in Numbers chapter 35 in verses nine through 34
that God gives the instruction to Moses, excuse me,
with regard to these cities of refuge.
And it's interesting as we'd find
that which is given to us here
and the Bible speaks about when they would come
into the land, they established these cities of refuge
and this is given in Numbers 35.
We.
find the fulfillment after the children of Israel conquer the land, and after the
land is being divided, then in Joshua chapter number 20, the first nine verses
of that chapter, we find that God records for us the cities of refuge that are
established. But here in Numbers 35, in verse number 9, it says, the Lord spake
unto Moses, saying, Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them,
When ye be come over Jordan into the land of Canaan, then ye shall appoint
you cities to be cities of refuge for you. Notice that the slayer may flee
thither, which killeth any person, notice this phrase, at unawares. And they shall
be unto you cities for refuge from the avenger, that the manslayer die not
until he stand before the congregation in judgment. And of these cities which
ye shall give, six cities shall you have for refuge. Speaking about the cities of
the Levites, and these specifically being the cities of refuge, he says in
verse 14, you shall give three cities on this side Jordan, and three cities shall
ye give in the land of Canaan, which shall be cities of refuge. These six
cities shall be a refuge both for the children of Israel, and for the stranger,
and for the sojourner among them, that everyone that killeth any person
unawares, you see that word again, it was mentioned in verse number 11, again now,
that any person that would killeth any person unawares may flee
thither. And if he smite him with an instrument of iron so that he die, notice
this, he is a murderer. The murderer shall surely be put to death. On the grounds of
that which we've read in Genesis chapter 9, when God gave this instruction to
Noah after they would depart the ark, in verse 17 of numbers 35, it says, and if he
smite him with the throwing a stone, wherewith he may die, and he die, he is a
murderer. The murderer shall surely be put to death. In other words, I take a
stone, and my purpose in throwing the stone is so that I could hit you and
kill you. And he says there, in this text of Scripture, that if he smite him with
throwing a stone, wherewith he may die, and he die, he is a murderer. The murderer
shall surely be put to death. Verse 18, or if he smite him with an hand
weapon or wood, wherewith he may die, and he die, he is a murderer. The murderer
shall surely be put to death. The revenger of blood himself shall slay the
murderer. When he meeteth him, he shall slay him. But if he thrust him of hatred
or hurl at him by laying of weight, that he die, or an enmity smite him with his
hand, that he die, he that smote him shall surely be put to death. For he is a
murderer. The revenger of blood shall slay the murderer when he meeteth him.
And we go through this passage of Scripture, we see what's taking place, and
these that are guilty of that which is mentioned in these verses that we've
just read, they would be guilty of murder, and they shall be surely put to death
based upon, again, that which we find in Genesis chapter 9. We move forward and
begin to see what's happening, and who this city of refuge, or these cities of
refuge, were really for. In verse number 25, and the congregation shall deliver
the slayer out of the hand of the revenger of blood, and the congregation
shall restore him to the city of his refuge, whither he was fled. And he shall
abide in it unto the death of the high priest, which was anointed with the holy
oil. That's what I referenced this morning about the fact that our Lord, our
great high priest, the Lord Jesus Christ, he conquered death, he passed into the
heavens. Of course, under the Levitical priesthood, the priest died, and here is
a high priest, when he died, that one that found refuge in the city of refuge could
then return to their place of dwelling. It says in verse 26, but if the slayer
shall at any time come without the border of the city of his refuge, whither
he was fled, and the revenger of blood find him without the borders of the city
of his refuge, and the revenger of blood kill the slayer, he shall not be guilty
of blood. See, he had to stay in the city of refuge. That's where there was
protection. We find in verse 28, because he should have remained in the city of
his refuge until the death of the high priest. In verse 30, whoso killeth any
person, the murderer shall be put to death by the mouth of witnesses, but one
witness shall not testify against any person that caused him to die. Moreover,
you shall take no satisfaction for the life of a murderer, which is guilty of
death, but he shall surely be put to death. And you shall take no satisfaction
for him that has fled to the city of his refuge, that he should come again to
dwell in the land until the death of the priest. So ye shall not pollute the land
wherein ye are. For blood defileth the land, and the land cannot be cleansed of
the blood that is shed therein, but by the blood of him that shed it. Defile not
therefore the land which ye shall inhabit wherein I dwell. For I, the Lord, dwell
among the children of Israel. And so we find that these cities of refuge were
established for the one that would be in a situation where someone died, but
it was not with any premeditation. They were not a murderer. You see that in
verse number 22. But if he thrust him suddenly without enmity, or have cast
upon him anything without laying of weight, or with any stone wherewith a
man may die, seeing him not, and cast it upon him that he die, and was not his
enemy, neither sought his harm, then the congregation shall judge between the
slayer and the revenger of blood according to these judgments, and they
could flee to the city of refuge. And so we find as we would look, yes, there's
additional information that is given, and these truths are expounded upon
throughout the the Old Testament and throughout the law, but as Noah and his
family would exit the ark, as they would prepare for life after the flood, they
first make offering, they first worship the Lord, and then the Lord gives them
instruction. The Lord says, be fruitful and multiply. Why? Because only the eight
of them. Everyone else had been destroyed, because safety was in the ark. It was the
only place of refuge. It was in the ark. Tomorrow in our Joshua lesson, we'll look
at the truth there in Joshua chapter 2, when the spies make the agreement
with Rahab, and there was only one place of safety, and that was in the house. It
was an agreement that was made. Such is the case here in Genesis. We understand
that safety was only for those within the ark, and so these eight people now
come off the ark, these Noah, his three sons, and their wives, and we find that
they are given the responsibility with regard to reproduction. We find that
their diet is changed, and God gives them information with regard to these dietary
changes, and then God reminds them of the value of life, and he lays the groundwork
for capital punishment, that whoso sheddeth man's blood by man shall his
blood be shed. We find that God would then continue to speak unto Noah, as we
find in verse number 8, and God spake unto Noah and to his sons with him
saying, I behold, I establish my covenant with you. Next Sunday evening, the
subject of our study will be the covenant that God makes with Noah, and
what a joy it is to read of this covenant that is given to us in this
passage of Scripture, which we'll look at next week. This evening, life after the
flood. I'm thankful that God gives instruction to Noah and his children.
There were some things that changed. There was some instruction that was
needed to be given to them. Reminders, and we find that for us, as we live here in
2020, I'm thankful that God has given us the instructions for how to live life.
I was chatting with someone recently, and I said to them, I said, I am so thankful
that the Creator God, who's in control of all things, that He's given us His Word,
and He's informed us, He's instructed us on how we are to live our lives, so that
we can live our lives in such a way that we would please Him. Paul had a desire in
his life that he would please the Lord. Paul instructs Timothy and encourages
Timothy to live his life in such a way that he would please the Lord. I'm so
thankful that we can go to the Word of God, and we can understand what it is
that God would require of us so that we could live for Jesus, yes, as we sang that
song this evening, but we could live a life that is pleasing in His sight.
Father, we love You. We thank You for loving us. We thank You for Thy Word, for
the truth of Thy Word. We thank You for the instruction that You've given to
Noah and to his sons in this passage of Scripture, and I pray, God, that You would
help us to understand that Your Word has been given to us as instruction. I'm so
thankful that You would give instruction to Your people, that You do
not sit in the heavens and just look down upon mankind without giving us any
direction, without giving us any instruction, but God, that You've given us
Thy Holy Word, Thy Word that is profitable, Thy Word that guides us and
directs us, and Lord, I pray that we would live in submission, even as we sang the
song this morning, trust and obey, that we would be doers of the Word and not
hearers only. God, that we would live lives that are pleasing in Thy sight.
Thank You for this instruction that You gave to Noah. Thank You for recording it
for us so that we'd understand that which You gave them as they departed the
ark. I pray that You'd be glorified in our lives, that all that we say and do
would bring honor and glory to Thy name.
For it's in Christ's name we pray, amen.
We'll have a moment of invitation here.
Kimberly's going to play quietly.