and five, he provides for us,
he provides for the believers in Corinth,
but of course, as God's word has been preserved for us,
we find that we've learned many valuable lessons
and valuable aspects about the ministry
that God has given to us.
We understand, as we looked in chapter number four,
that there will be pressures in ministry,
and there will be pressures that will be internal,
there will be pressures that will be external,
but what I'm rejoicing for is that
though those pressures come,
we understand the provision of God,
our theme this year, God's grace is sufficient,
and we find that God's provision is there,
and it enables us to fulfill the work
that God has given to us.
As we enter into chapter number five,
we find that the ministry that we've been given
according to chapter four is defined for us
in chapter five as being the ministry of reconciliation.
And we spoke many weeks talking about that opportunity
that we have to be God's ambassadors,
and to find that there are human beings
are at enmity with God because of their sin,
and two parties that are at variance,
they need to be reconciled,
and we as ambassadors have been given
the ministry of reconciliation,
and we pray you in Christ's stead, be reconciled to God.
That's what verse 20 says in 2 Corinthians chapter five,
and I spoke about as we looked at that passage
about the position that we have as ambassadors,
and then we had a follow-up message to that subject matter
of being a faithful ambassador,
and the reality is that if you're a believer this morning,
then that means that you're an ambassador,
but what kind of an ambassador are we?
And what a blessing to understand that God has given to us
this ministry of reconciliation.
We believe that the ministry now,
as we come to this sixth chapter,
we find that Paul has explained it.
He explained the ministry.
He wants the people in Corinth and for us this morning
to embrace the ministry,
and then to engage in the work that God has given to us.
One of the wonderful things, I mean,
I would say probably the greatest thing about the work,
the ministry that God has given to us
is what we're reminded about
as soon as we enter into the sixth chapter.
Notice with me that verse number one tells us this,
we then, and then notice this phrase,
as workers together with him,
beseech you also that ye receive not
the grace of God in vain.
I've titled the message this morning there
from verse number one, workers together with God.
I believe that's the greatest part
or the greatest aspect of the ministry
that we as believers have been given
is that we are workers together with God.
And that's an amazing truth.
In fact, it's actually a truth that the Apostle Paul,
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
had shared with this church
in the book of 1 Corinthians.
Hold your place here in chapter six of 2 Corinthians,
but look back, if you will,
just very briefly to 1 Corinthians chapter number three.
We find that as the Apostle Paul
is writing to this church now for the second time,
that he reminds them that we are workers together
with him, with God,
and we find that he had previously given to them this truth
in 1 Corinthians three.
Notice, if you will, in verse number four,
what was happening in Corinth.
One was saying, I'm of Paul, another I'm of Apollos,
and he says, are you not carnal?
And then he says this, who then is Paul?
And who is Apollos?
But ministers, by whom ye believed,
even as the Lord gave to every man,
I have planted, Apollos watered,
but God gave the increase.
So then neither is he that planteth anything,
neither he that watereth,
but God that giveth the increase.
By the way, this is good perspective
for all of us as the people of God.
Paul, many of us would probably say
the greatest Christian that ever lived.
He says, who then is Paul?
Just a minister.
He says, as he's writing to Timothy later on,
he says that he's the chiefest of sinners,
but he says that we're nothing,
that God is the one that gives the increase.
We're ministering together.
Notice in verse number eight,
now he that planteth and he that watereth,
what does he say, are one.
Why?
Because we're workers together,
not only with each other, but with God.
It says, and every man shall receive his own reward
according to his own labor,
for we are laborers together with God.
Ye are God's husbandry, ye are God's building.
And so now as this church,
back in 2 Corinthians chapter six,
as Paul has spent this lengthy period of time
explaining to them the ministry,
he then shares with them this truth
that we are workers together with God.
It wasn't a new truth for them.
If they had read the first letter,
they'd already been aware of this principle of this truth.
And I do not believe for many of us here this morning
that this is a new concept or a new truth.
This is something that we're aware of.
But as we dig into the passage of scripture,
we find such pertinent information
that needs to be applied in our lives
as we seek to fulfill the ministry
that God has given to us.
We're a local church.
As a local church, Christ is the head of our church,
and we find that we have a responsibility
to do the work of Christ that he's left us to do.
We find that as Paul would speak to Timothy,
he tells us that we, the church,
are the pillar and ground of the truth.
We have a purpose, and we have a ministry
that has been entrusted to us.
I'm thankful for every missionary
that God gives us the opportunity to support
around the globe, and we're reminded regularly
about missions, and our missions conference
is coming up the first week of June,
and we're looking forward to all
that God has in store for us.
But I've often said it over the years
that what you will find on that missions map
in our missions directory booklet,
you will not find anywhere on that map
or anywhere in that booklet a missionary
to Fairfax, to Oakton.
And that's why we are the missionaries
in Oakton, in Fairfax, in Vienna, this area.
God has placed and planted us here for a purpose,
and it's his purpose, and we are engaged in this ministry.
If you look at the text of scripture
from verse number one, I want you to notice this
if you're taking notes, the partnership of the ministry,
the partnership of the ministry.
Now this is something that I've already alluded to
through way of introduction,
and we'll get through these first couple of points
fairly quickly this morning.
But we find the partnership of the ministry.
Paul says we then, it's very interesting,
near the end of the fifth chapter,
in fact in chapter four as well,
the apostle Paul speaks to the church in Corinth
with plural emphasis.
He's speaking to them about we and us,
and this partnership of ministry.
The apostle Paul is not just coming in
and saying I am, I do.
He says we, us, and understanding this partnership,
and he says we then, we are partners, co-laborers,
we are on the same team, having the same purpose,
and what a blessing to understand
that as the apostle Paul is writing
to this church in Corinth, he says we then,
notice what he says, as workers together with him.
We talk about the partnership of the ministry,
there's this necessity for cooperation,
that we would cooperate one with another,
that we understand that we're not
in competition one with another,
no, we are cooperating one with another,
and we are seeking not for our own glory,
but for his glory.
And we find that when we look at this
partnership of the ministry,
not only are we partners together,
but we're partners together with him, with God.
Now, I'm encouraged by this greatly.
Many times you've heard, no doubt,
various aspects of the importance of teamwork,
and partnerships, and so on and so forth,
and when I worked in the corporate world
for so many years, we had various aspects
of dealing with teams, and teamwork,
and what could be accomplished by the team
is so much greater than what could be accomplished
by the individual, and all of these statements
that would be made, and I understand
the reason for doing that.
But I want you to understand that
when we talk about the work of Christ,
that what's amazing about it is that
it's not just those of us that are gathered here
that are the teammates, or the partners,
that we are co-laborers, that we are
workers together with God.
The one who created all things,
the one who has all power, the one who has
all wisdom, the one who has a plan
that is greater than your plan, or my plan,
or our plan collectively, he is the one
that we're laboring together with.
Isn't that awesome?
I mean, if somebody told you that you could
enter into a business endeavor, and I in no way
want you to think that I'm speaking of the church
as being a business, but I'm simply using
an analogy this morning, if someone were to tell you
that you have an opportunity to enter
into a business endeavor, and that your partner
would have all power, that your partner
would have all wisdom, that your partner
would have all resources, you'd be crazy
not to enter into the endeavor with that individual.
Church is not a business, it's an organism.
It's God's work, and God says that we are
laborers together with him, with God.
What a blessing that we understand this morning
that the greatest work that's being done
on planet Earth today is the work that God
has accomplished.
through his local churches and we have an opportunity as a local church in
Oakton, Virginia to be part of what God is doing globally, to be part of what God
is doing in this world. We have an opportunity to support missionaries
around the globe. 67 I believe is the number that we're at right now.
Different works that we are having the privilege and the opportunity to not
only give financially to these missionaries but to pray for them, to
understand that they are doing the greatest work on planet Earth. The work
of speaking and engaging in the ministry of reconciliation is the greatest work
on planet Earth. Why? As someone said to me recently, the statistics are still
true, a hundred percent of the people die. We don't know when we're gonna die but
we understand as that appointed unto man wants to die after this the judgment.
And when you're engaged in the work of the ministry of reconciliation, you're
speaking to individuals about their need for Christ and about the
substitutionary atonement of the Lord Jesus Christ when he took their place
and their sin on that cruel cross and he paid that awful price so that they
could be redeemed. What an amazing truth. Remember what Jesus said as he gives the
Great Commission in Matthew's Gospel as it's recorded for us. He says all power
is given unto me in heaven and earth. Go ye therefore. And he tells about preaching
and baptizing and teaching the three aspects of the Great Commission but he
ends that passage of scripture by saying and lo I am with you always. Think about
that. The Lord Jesus Christ, the power of the Holy Spirit that we go in when we're
seeking to fulfill the ministry, we are partners together. He says at the end of
the verse notice he says we then as workers together with him beseech you
also that ye receive not the grace of God in vain. It'd be a sad thing to be a
recipient of God's grace in vain. See the Apostle Paul says that he wants to be a
good steward of the manifold grace of God. The reality is that we can speak of
God's grace with regard to saving grace but also with the aspect of serving
grace and his enabling and I'm thankful for God's grace and saving me for my
grace are you saved through faith and that not of yourselves it's the gift of
God not of works lest any man should boast but I'm also reminded of God's
serving grace that he's enabled us to serve him and the Apostle Paul he says
we beseech you that ye receive not the grace of God in vain. Oh that God would
use us in understanding this partnership of ministry. Number two if you're taking
notes as we look at verse two notice with me the urgency of the ministry. The
urgency of the ministry. The Apostle Paul is gonna quote from Isaiah 49 in
verse number two and he says this for he saith I have heard thee in a time
accepted and in the day of salvation have I succored thee behold now is the
accepted time behold now is the day of salvation. I referenced this verse of
scripture a number of times as we were working through chapter number five with
regard to the day of salvation when he says now is the day of salvation and
when I think about the urgency of the ministry I'm reminded first and foremost
yes there's an urgency with regard or on the part of the sinner that needs to be
reconciled. Why? Because they don't know when they're gonna take their final
breath. They don't know when they're going to enter into eternity and they
need not delay. There's a matter of urgency in fact in Isaiah 55 in
verse number six you don't need to turn there I'll read the verse for you but in
Isaiah 55 in verse number six the Bible says this seek ye the Lord while he may
be found call ye upon him while he is near. The Bible tells us in the book of
Philippians that every tongue is going to confess every knee is going to bow
and I've often said as we look at that text of scripture it's not a matter of
when it's a matter of if. Sorry not a matter of yeah so so when we it's not a
matter of if it's a matter of when I put that in reverse order so it's not a
matter of if you will confess that Jesus Christ is Lord you will bow before him
it's not a matter of if it's a matter of when and when makes all the difference
because if you make that decision to trust Christ as your Savior on this side
of eternity then you'll spend forever with God in heaven you'll be saved by
the grace of God but if you refuse you put it off and you die you'll still
confess that Jesus is Lord to the glory of the Father but it will be eternally
too late for you and if makes all the difference so we see the urgency of the
ministry of the ministry with regard to lost souls and their need to be
reconciled but really as I look at the text of scripture I don't only see I
would also say I don't primarily see that the urgency is on the part of the
sinner that needs to be reconciled I see in the text of scripture an urgency on
the part of the ambassador to deliver the message see because as ambassadors
were the ones that have been already reconciled to God we find that those of
us that have been given the the ministry of reconciliation are ones that have
already been reconciled according to verse 18 of chapter 5 and so we find
that there's an urgency on the part of the ambassadors to deliver the message
why because we know the truth we've been entrusted with the truth and there's an
urgency about it we find every day you read about people that that have entered
into eternity whether that's through some type of sickness or some accident
but we read regularly about people that are entering into eternity I mean we
read of tragic things we read of bridges that have been hit and collapsed and
and people were simply driving and expecting to go to the other side of the
bridge and before they could get to the other side they're in the waters we've
seen that happen recently we've seen of airplanes that are ready preparing to
land I mean literally just meters from the ground that are entering into
eternity listen life is fragile remember what James said what is your life it's
but a vapor that appears for a little time and then vanishes away you know
there's some people today that don't know the truth of what it means to be
reconciled to God there's an urgency on their part they need to be saved but how
can they hear how do they know that there to call upon him Romans 10 what a
precious truth for whoso shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved but
how are they gonna call on him in whom they've not heard the text goes on to
say how will they hear without a preacher I believe that as we look at
the text of scripture there's an urgency on the part of the ambassador to look to
deliver the message I won't take the time this morning but in Esther chapter
8 verses 13 and 14 you can read that jot it down and read it later but Nestor
chapter number 8 they're going to deliver a counter decree and it's very
interesting if you understand the whole context of the book of Esther there was
a day that was already circled on the calendar where Haman had had authority
and wrote law that all the Jewish people would be killed and God through a
miraculous set of events allows for a counter decree to be written by Mordecai
and Esther but that counter decree had to be published it had to be sent out to
these 127 provinces and if you read in Esther chapter 8 verses in 13 and 14 you
see how that they went out with haste they went with a a sense of urgency why
because they needed to get the message the counter decree to these people
listen we have a message Jesus saves Jesus saves we have a message that needs
to be delivered to a lost and dying world we need some urgency as we work in
this ministry in verses 3 through 10 and we'll spend the remainder of our
time here this morning I want you to see the conduct of the minister we've
noticed in verse number 1 the partnership of the ministry we've
noticed in verse number 2 the urgency of the ministry but in verses 3 down
through verse number 10 we see the conduct of the minister we begin to read
in verse number 3 it's a great truth that God gives us and we see the great
concern that the Apostle Paul has in verse number 3 as he says this giving no
offense in anything that the ministry be not blamed do you see the concern of
Paul's heart do you see that as he writes in verse number 3 he begins to
enter into this phase in these next several verses about the the conduct of
the minister as he ends the chapter of chapter number 6 he's going to speak to
them about the importance of separation what was he deals with that what
concord hath Christ with Belial light with darkness and he goes through all of
those things and and he speaks about separation and separation is important
but he begins by talking about the conduct of the minister we find that
Paul would say to Timothy that were to be a vessel that is meat for the
master's use we find that here Paul says
giving no offense. Notice when he says, in anything, that the ministry be not blamed.
I have written in my notes, you may not be the reason that someone gets saved. What do
I mean by that? Well, the Bible says some plant, some water, but God gives the increase.
You may not be the reason that someone gets saved. God may allow you to lead somebody
to Christ, and what a blessing that is. But you may not be the one, you may not be the
individual that God, or the reason that someone gets saved. But can I tell you that we better
behave in such a way that we are not the reason that someone doesn't get saved? We better
behave in such a way that somebody doesn't look at me or look at you and say, if that's
what it means to be a Christian, I don't want anything to do with it. Man, that's a heavy
weight. But you know, people are watching you. People are watching me. They're observing
our behavior. How do we act? What do we say? How do we deal with difficulties? How do we
treat people? Do we have grace? Do we have mercy? Are we loving? Jesus said that we're
to love our enemies. You begin to look at this, and Paul says, giving no offense in
anything, that the ministry be not blamed. The conduct of the minister is so important.
I've said this over the years, that when you look at the book of First Thessalonians,
I believe that you see this principle played out as Paul is ministering to this church
in Thessalonica, and he says to them that he, he says, you knew how I behaved while
I was there. And we often have heard this terminology that people don't care how much
you know until they know how much you care. You're not going to find a Bible verse or
a reference that says that, but I believe the principle is true in First Thessalonians
where Paul says, I cared for you as a nurse cherished her children. What a great imagery
that God gives to us of how Paul behaved himself. We begin to look at the conduct of the minister
in verses 4 and 5. We find that Paul begins to highlight not only what he personally had
endured as being a minister of the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ, but we find that
he provides for us in these couple of verses of scripture what we too can expect to endure
as we serve God. You know that when you try to serve God, when you want to live for Jesus,
not everyone's going to love you. Amen? But we do it not so that we can be loved of everyone,
we do it because we love Jesus. The Bible says in verse 4, but in all things approving
ourselves as the ministers of God in much patience, in afflictions, in necessities,
in distresses, in stripes, in imprisonments, in tumults, in labors, in watchings, in fastings.
Verse 4 and 5 list out a number of things. He talks about being, to have that idea of
patience, of persevering through some of the difficulties, the afflictions, the troubles
that would be endured. He talks about necessities and distresses and the persecution. He describes
the persecution as being stripes and imprisonments and tumults. I mean, these are things that the
minister of God must endure. The work and the hardships of ministry are provided for us at the
end of verse number 5 when he speaks about labors and watchings and fastings. I do not believe,
and many commentators agree, that when he speaks of fastings at the end of verse number 5,
he's not speaking necessarily of a voluntary fasting as when the Lord talks about when you
fast, when you pray. They believe, and I believe as well, that this is speaking about involuntary
fasting, because earlier he talked about in times of necessity. I mean, the apostle Paul
endured some things, and we begin to understand that as the minister of the Lord Jesus Christ,
as the one that's been entrusted with this ministry, as we are workers together with God,
that we must be careful that our conduct, that the conduct of the minister is God-honoring,
that we in no way bring reproach against the name of Christ or against the ministry,
that the ministry be not blamed, and there's some things that we're going to have to endure,
some hardships, some difficulties.
But we find in the next few verses that the apostle Paul shares with us how he endures those
things. See, it's one thing to look at verses 4 and 5 and say, man, these are things that we're
going to be faced with. How in the world could I ever? Physically, you can't. By yourself,
you can't. But notice how would he endure by pureness, by knowledge, by long-suffering,
by kindness, by the Holy Ghost, by love unfamed, by the word of truth, by the power of God,
by the armor of righteousness on the right hand and on the left. And we'll continue reading here
in just a few moments, but I want you to see that in verse 6 and verse number 7, that as the apostle
Paul begins to describe these attributes of the behavior of the minister, the one who's engaged
in the work that God has given to us by pureness and knowledge and long-suffering and kindness,
and what a blessing to be able to see the picture that is being painted, I think, of Stephen,
even as he's being martyred, and they saw his face as it had been an angel, and he's praying
that God would forgive them. It's amazing. You can't do that in your own power.
You can't do that in your own strength. There's some things that we're going to endure, but how
do we endure? I've picked four things from these verses of Scripture that I want to highlight this
morning. I don't have the time to elaborate on all of the things that are mentioned in verses 4
through 10, but four things in verses 6 and 7 that are so important that I want you to take note
of them specifically. In verse number 6, notice right in the middle of the verse, he says,
By the Holy Ghost. By the Holy Ghost. I believe this morning that we needless,
Lord, send a revival. We sometimes shy away from talking about the Holy Spirit, the Holy Ghost,
because maybe we have some level of concern about what some things are happening in some
Pentecostal movements and so on and so forth, but the Holy Ghost is God, and we find the Holy
Spirit, the Holy Ghost, we find the explanations that are given to us in His Word with regard to
our ministry and His ministry in and through us. Jesus Christ said, But ye shall receive power
after that the Holy Ghost has come upon you. The Bible tells us in Ephesians chapter 5 that we're
to be filled with the Holy Spirit. We understand this morning that at the moment of salvation,
and we dealt with this in chapter number 5, that we were indwelled by the Spirit of God. In fact,
we find that it is the earnest of our inheritance and that we have been given, according to verse
number 5, the earnest of the Spirit, and what a blessing to understand that we're sealed unto the
day of redemption. But I want you to understand this morning that we need God. And Paul says
that we're to be filled with the Holy Spirit. That's the idea of continuous filling. There's
a difference between the indwelling of the Spirit of God and the filling of the Spirit of God.
How much of the Holy Spirit do I have with settled at the day of my salvation? I got all
the Holy Spirit. The Bible tells us in 1 Corinthians 6 that our body is the temple
of the Holy Ghost, which is in you, which you have of God. But you know, day by day and moment by
moment, we're talking about the filling of the Holy Spirit of God. It really is this idea. How
much of the Holy Spirit does, how much does the Holy Spirit have of me? How emptied of self am I
and filled with the Spirit? You know, it's interesting as we consider, as the Apostle
Paul is speaking about what he's enduring and he talks about these things, and of course mentions
a number, but we notice in verse 6, by the Holy Ghost, in Zechariah 4, 6, the Bible says at the
end of that verse, not by might nor by power, but by my Spirit, saith the Lord of hosts.
By the Holy Ghost. Verse 7 tells us this, as we go back to 2 Corinthians 6, not only
we see in verse number 6 by the Holy Ghost, but in verse number 7 by the Word of Truth.
You know what's going to help you to endure? Yes, the Holy Ghost being filled with the Holy
Spirit of God, but number two is the Word of Truth, God's Word. Why am I resolved? Because I
have a book that is powerful, that is authoritative, and I believe what the book says,
and therefore I'm resolved. I'm committed. I have these convictions, and no matter what's
going to come, I'm going to continue moving forward. I'm going to...
Why? Because the Word of Truth, Jesus Christ said in John 17, in His high priestly prayer,
as we look at that passage of Scripture, He says that we're in the world, but we're not of the world.
He prays to His Father that we would not be delivered from the world, but that we would be in the world.
And He tells us, sanctify them through Thy Word. Thy Word is truth.
We find the power of God's Word.
You know, God's Word will convict us, but God's Word will comfort us.
How many times we've run to the Bible in times of difficulty, in times of trouble and trial,
and being overwhelmed, and God's Word comforts us. What a blessing.
I'm thankful that it convicts us, but I'm thankful that it comforts us.
Notice in verse 7, He says, by the Word of Truth, by the power of God.
Oh, that's a third key on how we endure. We endure by God's power.
Ephesians chapter number 6 reminds us to be strong in the Lord and the power of His might.
We find that it's not our strength. Jesus Christ said that without me ye can do nothing.
As we're seeking to fulfill the ministry that God has given to us, as we consider the conduct of the minister,
we find that there's some things that they're going to endure, but how does He do it?
How is it that we can endure the pressures of life?
How is it that we can read of missionaries and churches and other places of the world
that are facing great persecution, and yet they're marching on for the cause of Christ?
People are being saved. Lives are being changed. Why?
Because they understand that it's not by their own power, it's by God's power.
And He says this in verse 7, by the Word of Truth, by the power of God, by the armor of righteousness.
On the right hand and on the left.
If you were to read Ephesians 6, verses 13 through 18, we find that in the passage of Scripture,
God provides for us the truth of the armor of God.
And He tells us that we're to put on the whole armor of God.
How important it is that we understand that when we enter into this world,
as many have said in yesteryear, many preachers have made the claim,
in fact, Brother Cottle sings a song about it, I believe it was Tozer that made the statement
really kind of famous or well known, that the Christian life, that as we go in and engage in this world,
that it's best described not as a playground, but as a battleground.
And when we enter into this battleground, this battlefield, we better have the whole armor of God.
And Paul says by the armor of righteousness on the right hand and on the left,
that we put on the whole armor of God.
If you were to go into battle, if you were to go and to engage in some level of warfare,
you would be careful to have those pieces of armor on.
Hey, don't forget your helmet. We'd understand the significance.
You understand we're engaged in a battle.
And Paul says, how does the minister, how does the Christian, the laborer, how does he endure?
Well, by the Holy Ghost, by the word of truth, by the power of God, by the armor of righteousness.
In verses 8 through 10, we find that the apostle Paul begins to share some things that I believe
are insightful with regard to some of what he dealt with with some of those folks in Corinth.
Remember they were, as we looked at chapter 2 a number of months ago,
and preached a message on when you're misunderstood.
Remember they were, they had misunderstood Paul.
They said Paul was the kind of guy that he said one thing but meant something different.
He said his yea is nay and his nay is yay.
And he talked about being misunderstood when Paul said he was going to come visit them.
And he said this if the Lord will.
And God, through a number of circumstances, Paul was prevented from being able to go.
And so all of a sudden, they took this response and began to say these things about Paul.
And I believe that in verses 8 through 10, there's some level of connection
between what some of those in Corinth were saying with regard to the ministry of Paul.
But I think it's also applicable for us.
We find in verse number 8, he says, by honor and dishonor.
You know when you serve God, sometimes you'll be honored, but sometimes you'll be dishonored.
You won't be dishonored by God, but by man.
He says this by evil report and good report.
It doesn't mean that the minister, we're talking about the conduct,
doesn't mean that the minister is evil.
He said by pureness.
He's basically saying that sometimes people will bring an evil report against you.
By evil report, by good report.
As deceivers and yet true.
Don't listen to Paul. He's not telling you the truth.
Hey, don't listen to them.
And so sometimes people will look at us this way.
They'll make these claims just as they had towards the apostle Paul.
They will towards you and towards me as well.
Unknown and yet well-known.
But remember what Paul said as we read in 1 Corinthians 3.
Who then is Paul?
See, sometimes people are wanting to serve God just so that they can be well-known.
But Paul says as unknown and yet well-known.
The apostle Paul was experiencing where people said, who's Paul?
I mean, why are we listening to Paul?
And he's saying, listen, none of this stuff matters.
We're going to deal with these things as dying and behold, we live as chastened and not killed.
As sorrowful yet always rejoicing.
As poor yet making many rich.
As having nothing and yet possessing all things.
And really it's a perspective that we have when you look in verse 10.
He says as sorrowful but yet he says always rejoicing.
He says as poor yet making many rich.
He says as having nothing yet possessing all things.
It all comes down to perspective.
We find, we memorize the verse a few months ago and we will get to it shortly.
But in verse number 9 of chapter 8.
For you know the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ that though he was rich yet for your sakes he became poor.
That ye through his poverty might be rich.
And we find that Paul, he said that he had learned in whatsoever state he was to be content.
The Apostle Paul, I believe what he's saying in these verses of scripture.
Is that no matter what others thought.
No matter how they treated him.
No matter what occurred in his life.
He was committed to serving the Lord Jesus Christ.
He was committed to doing and fulfilling the work that God had entrusted him with.
How appropriate this morning that the young man sang, I am resolved.
That wasn't orchestrated.
I didn't ask him to sing that song.
But how appropriate when we think about the Apostle Paul and the text of scripture.
And we talk about the conduct of the minister.
Listen, why do we serve Christ?
Listen, there are times in which as we've said in America.
There's times that we can look and say it's convenient at times to be a Christian in America.
Now those times are changing, we see that.
But the reality is that for most of us here this morning.
Our Christianity in America has not really cost us a whole lot.
We've not really suffered much.
But what happens when the persecution comes?
Do we scatter? Do we give up? Do we say, not for me.
Or do we have that resolve?
As Paul has.
I'm going to do what God called me to do.
This morning, we are workers together with God.
God's given to us a ministry.
And as we look at the ministry that God has given to us.
And we consider this morning this message.
I hope that we would rejoice greatly in knowing that we can partner together for the cause of Christ.
And I'm hoping this morning that we would have a sense of urgency about doing the work that God has called us to do.
And I hope this morning that we would be careful to know that our conduct is so important.
It's important to have the right position for sure.
But oh how important it is to have the right disposition.
The right position and the right disposition.
The conduct of the minister matters.
God wants to use us. He wants to use you.
We are partners together.
We are workers together with God.
What a blessing and what a privilege.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
And we thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the privilege of being able to gather.
We thank you for the work that you have entrusted us with.
And God, we rejoice.
I pray that you'd use us, God, for your glory.
That you would give us opportunity to make a difference in our community, Lord, with the gospel, with the word of God.
I pray, God, that you would bless the time of invitation if there's one that's not sure of heaven.
I pray that today would be the day of their salvation.
I pray for the Christian, Lord, the one that's already been saved.
Lord, I pray that you'd help us to understand our responsibility in this ministry, this work that you've called us to.
I pray, God, that you'd help us to be resolved.
Move and work as only you can, and we'll be careful to give you the honor and glory.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
me. Heads are bowed, eyes are closed. At the end of each of our services we have a time
of invitation. We give you an opportunity to respond.