chapter number six. If you have your Bible with you this morning, Galatians chapter
number six. If you don't have a Bible
in one of the chairs in front of you, it might not be directly in front of you, but
somewhere in that row there should be some Bibles
underneath those chairs. Feel free to grab one of those.
Galatians chapter number six. We'll be looking at verses 7 through 10
here this morning and if you look at this text of Scripture with me
beginning reading in verse number seven, the Bible says this, be not deceived.
God is not mocked. For whatsoever a man soweth, that shall he also reap.
For he that soweth to his flesh shall of the flesh
reap corruption. He that soweth to the Spirit shall of the Spirit reap
life everlasting. And verse number nine says this,
and let us, and let us not be weary in well-doing. For in due season we shall
reap if we faint not. As we have therefore
opportunity, let us do good unto all men, especially
unto them who are of the household of faith.
The demands in life are real. At times they can seem overwhelming. Isn't
it true? Demand, the demands of life are real.
And at times we face difficulties and we face all these pressures and all these
various demands and it can seem as if it's overwhelming.
But it brings me great joy and it brings me great peace to know
that God knows. God knows our frame. He cares for us. He sustains us.
He's given to us all things that pertain unto life and godliness. He's given us a
Bible and in the Bible he's revealed himself
to us. He's revealed his plan for us and he's given to us the Holy
Spirit. If you're saved this morning, you've trusted Christ as your personal
savior and you know that heaven is your home.
Not only are you going to heaven but you've been delivered
from the penalty of sin but also from the power of sin
and the Lord wants to have a relationship with you and you get to
walk with him and enjoy his presence and to
have that assurance that you'll spend forever with him in heaven.
And he's given to you the Holy Spirit of God who indwells you and he
is the comforter. The Bible says the Holy Spirit is the comforter.
Yes, he guides us in all truth. He leads us in all truth. He is the divine teacher
and yes, he convicts us but I'm thankful that he
comforts us. And we find that it's of interest that
the apostle Paul here in Galatians chapter number six and
now he's not writing to an individual church. He's writing
to the churches in the region of Galatia. There's four of them
and those four churches were established during the first missionary journey
of the apostle Paul. When the Holy Spirit came to the church at Antioch and said
separate unto me Saul and Barnabas for the work
whereunto I have called them. And they went out and the church prayed
for them and as they went God used them and though they faced
great difficulty in each of the cities where they went, they faced
opposition and in facing opposition they were
run out of town but I want you to rejoice in knowing that even
though they faced opposition and though they were
ran out of town there were churches established
in those communities and Paul then went back in a second missionary journey and
revisited those churches to encourage them
and to strengthen them in their walk with the Lord
and now God is using him to write this letter
back to those four churches in the region of Galatia
and he's writing to them and he comes to the end and there's so much great truth
throughout the book but he comes to the end and
he tells them in verse number nine part of our text this morning
and let us not be weary in well-doing. It's of interest that he
says let us. So Paul is not only speaking to four
individual local churches but he includes himself.
He doesn't say for just them but even himself
because the reality is that there is a danger of growing weary.
We find that not only does Paul write this here to the churches in the region
of Galatia but if you have your Bible and keep your
spot here in Galatians 6 because we'll be back here and
kind of park here for the remainder of the service after we look at a couple of
verses by way of introduction but look at 2 Thessalonians if you will
chapter number three. In 2 Thessalonians chapter number three
Paul is now writing to the church in Thessalonica
and this particular church is a good church, a
model church, a church that according to 1 Thessalonians chapter number one
that from them sounded forth the word of the Lord. I mean they were actively
doing what God had instructed them to do but they
were facing opposition as well and they were facing difficulty and Paul
says listen I told you that you would encounter these things, I told you
before I left that you would suffer with these things. As best we know
from the the record in the book of Acts you would find that the
apostle Paul probably spent less than a month in the
city of Thessalonica and he was there for about three weeks
and yet there's this church that's established
and he gave them truth and he's writing to them and again a church that's
doing the work of the ministry, a church that's doing
good things, doing good and he says to them in 2 Thessalonians 3 in verse
number 13 but ye brethren be not
weary in well-doing. He said that the church is in the region
of Galatia. He says to them that let us
not be weary in well-doing. Now he's writing to the church in Thessalonica
and he says but ye brethren be not weary in well-doing.
Look at 2 Corinthians chapter 4 and then we'll make our way back to the
book of Galatians. In 2 Corinthians chapter number 4 I
want you to see how Paul giving a testimony now and discussing
his ministry, his work to the church in Corinth and as he's
writing to the church in Corinth and he's writing about his ministry and his
work he starts out chapter number four in
verse number one notice he says therefore
seeing we have this ministry. How did he get the ministry? Well he
was he was called by God. In Acts chapter
number 20 he makes it very plain that he received
this ministry from the Lord and he says here in 2 Corinthians 4
therefore seeing we have this ministry as we have received mercy
we faint not. We faint not. That word faint is actually the same Greek word
that's translated weary in the book of Galatians in the book of
second Thessalonians. It means the same thing
to be weary to grow faint and he says that we
have notice he says we have this ministry but aren't you thankful that he
says we have received mercy. God gives us the mercy and he says
that we faint not. Notice if you will in verse number 16 here in 2 Corinthians
chapter 4 he says for which cause we faint not
but though our outward man perish yet the inward man
is renewed day by day. When I look at the New Testament and I
see God using the apostle Paul to write to
churches four of them in the region of Galatia one
in Thessalonica so five local churches in the New Testament that receive this
instruction about not growing weary and well-doing
when I read of the apostle Paul writing of his own ministry
and his own work in 2 Corinthians chapter number four
he speaks about fainting not not growing weary
and so as I read all of those things and I consider those
truths and as we even experience and live
life we must recognize the danger of growing weary the danger
of growing weary. As we look at the text go back to
Galatians chapter number six if you will and as we look at the text I believe
that we it's important to to keep it within the context here
that's why we've read verse 7 down through verse number 10
because really he's dealing with a a thought here that's so important for us
and so as we consider this morning this truth of the danger of growing
weary I want you to consider with me number one
the principle explained in verses 7 and 8 of Galatians 6
we find that God uses the apostle Paul to explain a principle
the the principle that is going to explain is one in which we're very
familiar with in fact throughout the scriptures we find there
are many references to things that are easy for us to relate to
agriculture is one that's used repeatedly that of athletics or sports
is used repeatedly especially in the New Testament
but we find here that he's going to use this really
truth with regard to a that we could relate to of
agriculture he starts out in verse number seven notice he says be not
deceived now that's important for us to note
those three words as we begin looking at this principle
and it's altogether possible that people could be deceived
and we understand the deception we understand that we have an enemy that
he's a liar and he's a deceiver and we understand that he wants to deceive and
I've often said this that the worst deception is self-deception
the Bible says in James 1 even as we've been studying on Sunday mornings we've
taken a little time off but studying through the book of James that
we're not to deceive our own
And we think about here is the truth is getting ready to be given.
This principle is going to be explained.
And the Bible starts by saying, be not deceived.
Be not deceived. God is not mocked.
Now I'm thankful this morning that our God is gracious.
And I'm thankful that our God is merciful.
And I'm thankful this morning that He is love.
And I'm thankful this morning that He is long-suffering.
Amen? Aren't you thankful?
You've experienced the long-suffering of God and you better rejoice that our God is long-suffering.
But our God is just.
Our God is righteous.
Our God is holy.
And we find in the text that the Bible says, be not deceived.
God is not mocked.
And here's the principle.
We find it in verse 7 and 8.
Whatsoever a man soweth, that shall he also reap.
The principle, the law of sowing and reaping.
We see it in agriculture. It's very easy for us to relate to.
We understand the idea of sowing seed and then expecting to reap a harvest.
We understand the fact that we reap the same kind that we sow.
Amen?
You put a tomato seed in the ground and you're expecting to have a tomato plant.
By the way, our tomatoes are getting close. Amen. I'm looking forward to that.
But the reality is that you sow and you reap.
We find that you reap more than you sow.
Always reap more than you sow.
And we find here that there's a principle that is explained.
A law, really, that is of nature.
And we find it applicable even in the lives of God's people, the lives of humanity.
And he says, for whatsoever a man soweth, that shall he also reap.
Now, this morning, as we look at the text of Scripture,
my emphasis is actually going to be on the positive side, not on the negative side.
Now, the reality is that I have heard and I have even taught from this passage of Scripture
and focused primarily on the negative side.
And both are here, so it's essential to mention both.
But this morning, my desire, as God has really just moved and worked and led,
is to really focus on that positive side.
But the negative is true.
Where the Bible says in verse number eight, as the principle is explained,
he says, for he that soweth to his flesh shall,
notice it says shall, it is certain,
he shall of the flesh reap corruption.
That's the negative.
That's the reality.
Someone of yesteryear, preacher of yesteryear said
that sometimes God's people are sowing seeds to the flesh all week long
and then they come to church on Sunday and they pray for crop failure.
A lot of truth to that statement.
See, the negative is there.
He that soweth to his flesh shall of the flesh reap corruption.
How many of you have learned after you got saved that you still have the flesh?
Amen?
Listen, the flesh was not eradicated at the moment that you got saved.
But we do understand, the Bible tells us that we're to put off the old man
and we're to put on the new man.
In fact, in the preceding context, in chapter number five,
the Bible tells us to walk in the spirit.
Specifically, he says, and ye shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
So what does that teach us?
Your flesh and my flesh still has desires.
Amen?
But he says that if we walk in the spirit,
that we shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh.
And he goes on in that text of Scripture to explain the flesh and the works of the flesh.
And he talks about the spirit, the fruit of the spirit.
And so we see the negative aspect.
But then notice, if you will, with me in verse number eight again,
the focus this morning is on the positive side.
He says this, but he that soweth to the spirit shall of the spirit reap life everlasting.
Think about this idea of the negative and the positive,
the good seeds that he's speaking about here,
that we would be sowing and reaping, that we're sowing of the spirit.
He that soweth to the spirit shall of the spirit reap life everlasting.
And you begin to understand, as the Apostle Paul is writing to these believers
in the churches there in the region of Galatia,
and he's explaining this principle,
but he's getting ready to get to this point that we're going to focus on our message this morning
about growing weary.
And here's something that I've learned in life, and something that I've experienced,
and perhaps as we understand as we read the Scriptures,
as these churches in the region of Galatia,
as Paul writes to the church in Thessalonica,
as Paul reveals his own testimony to the believers in the church in Corinth,
that sometimes as we're doing good, that we're sowing the right kind of seed,
we're sowing to the spirit, as he says in verse number eight,
sometimes the reaping doesn't come on your timetable or on my timetable.
You understand what I'm saying?
You sow good things and you want to see the results.
You want to see it right now.
You want to see the fruit.
You want to experience the fruit.
And I understand we all like the fruit.
We all like the results.
But I submit to you this morning that sometimes, oftentimes,
the good seed takes longer to produce the fruit.
And so we see the principle explained.
Number two, I want you to see from verse number nine, the pitfall exposed.
The pitfall exposed.
See, I've titled the message this morning,
the danger of growing weary.
And we find here that in verse number nine,
especially in that first section of the verse,
we find that there's a pitfall that is exposed because Paul, very plainly,
he explains the principle.
It's not a principle that's difficult for us to understand.
But then he exposes this pitfall and he says this,
and let us not be weary in well-doing.
Let us not be weary in well-doing.
The idea of fainting, the idea of giving up,
the idea of maybe coming to the place and saying, is it even worth it?
Does anyone even care?
Is anyone even listening?
You understand what I'm saying?
Sometimes we can think about this even in the context of parenting.
How many times a child is being taught and instructed by their parent
and the parenting has taken effect and the parent comes to,
as the book of Psalms will talk about there, their wit's end,
and they look at their kids and they look at their spouse
and they say something like this,
will they ever get it?
If you're a parent, you may have been there at some point.
And you might look at those children and you might think,
man, they're never going to learn.
But you just keep doing right.
You just keep sowing those good seeds.
You don't give up. You don't walk away.
You don't say it's just not worth it. No, no, no.
And so this idea, see, we can think about it in parenting,
but I think about it contextually.
He's writing to churches that are doing the work of the ministry.
When he talks about here, let us not be weary in well-doing,
he is not talking about doing good things to earn salvation.
The truth of soteriology is settled through the New Testament.
It's abundantly clear that salvation is by grace through faith alone.
It's Christ alone.
The Apostle Paul, in fact, as he's writing to the churches
in the region of Galatia, there were some Judaizers that came in
and they were telling them things that they had to do to keep the law
in order to be saved or to stay saved.
In fact, we find that Acts chapter number 15
records the council at Jerusalem
that really centers around a lot of the things that were happening
in this region of Galatia.
And one of the things that they were saying is
if you're not circumcised after the manner of Moses,
you cannot be saved.
That's not true biblically,
but that's what these Judaizers were trying to promote
and trying to teach.
And so Paul very plainly explains to these churches,
these believers in the region of Galatia,
as he's writing this.
And I always think about Galatians 2 in verse 21
when he says, I do not frustrate the grace of God.
For if righteousness come by the law,
then Christ is dead in vain.
He then goes on and he says in chapter number 3
in verse number 21,
is the law then against the promises of God?
God forbid.
The law has a purpose.
But we find that the law, and even as he says here,
he says for if there had been a law given
which could have given life,
verily righteousness should have been by the law.
But the law cannot give life.
You know what the law does?
The law condemns.
The law reveals that you're a sinner.
Paul would say as he's writing
and he talks about his own testimony,
he says in the book of Romans
that I would not have known covetousness
except the law says thou shalt not covet.
Right?
So we understand the purpose of the law,
but we understand that the law cannot give life.
And so we begin to think about where he says here,
be not weary,
not grow or be weary in well-doing. The well-doing, it's not so that they can get
saved or stay saved, it's a result of being saved. Remember
Ephesians 2, that we are his workmanship created unto Christ Jesus. Remember in
the book of Titus that Paul talks about the fact that we're to be zealous of
good works. Again, not to get saved or to stay saved, but because I am saved. And so
these good works, this well-doing, he says let us not be weary in
well-doing, that as they're going forth and as they're seeking to do good and to
do right and to do the right thing, that at times in those moments there's this
pitfall that is exposed here that you can grow weary. Sometimes you look at
other people and you say, well they're not even doing these things and it seems
like they're happier, they have more, they have... Don't get distracted by that.
Settle on the truth of God's Word. Find yourself grounded on the promises that
God has given, because the reality is that at times, listen, the fruit doesn't
always come right away. There's a process. There's some fruit trees that take years.
You plant them and it takes years for the maturity of that particular tree to
grow and to produce fruit and you find this process and so when we see here
this pitfall exposed, listen, I believe this morning that it's something that
each of us must acknowledge. It's something to acknowledge. Listen, if it
was true of the churches in the region of Galatia, if it was true of the church
in Thessalonica, if it was true of the Apostle Paul, we must acknowledge this
morning that there is a danger in growing weary, in growing weary. And we
find that this is something this morning that I hope each of us would
acknowledge and for some it might be, hey listen, I've already grown weary, I've
already... What do you want me to acknowledge? I'm already there, wore the
t-shirt, wore it out, I've already been there. But what I'm saying this morning
is that contextually he's not talking about growing weary because of the
demands of your work. He's not talking about growing weary because of some
other, you know, influence in your life. He's talking about growing weary in the
sense of this subject of doing that which is right, doing the work of
the ministry. And he says there's this pitfall, there's something to acknowledge
and there's something not only to acknowledge but there's something to
avoid. So I can't avoid if I don't acknowledge. If I don't acknowledge that
there's a pitfall, I'm gonna have a hard time avoiding the pitfall. But when I
acknowledge that there's a pitfall, when I acknowledge the fact that God, all
scripture is given by inspiration of God, when I acknowledge that God led the
Apostle Paul to write these things and it's to multiple groups of people, then I
understand this morning that I must acknowledge that and then there's some
things I can do to avoid that. How can I avoid growing weary in well-doing? What
is it that I can do? What is it that you can do? As we're doing the right thing, as
we're doing the work that God has called us to do, again with regard to the church
in Thessalonica, he makes it abundantly clear in chapter number one how that
they were in samples to all that believe in Macedonia and Achaia, that
from them sounded forth the Word of the Lord. I mean, God was using them but they
were dealing with some difficulties and you can get to that place where you can
get weary. In 2026, it's not like many other times in history, we sometimes
paint for ourselves almost a picture that it's never been as bad as it is
today. I disagree with that wholeheartedly. There was a day and his
name was Noah, amen, when God saw the wickedness and he
destroyed, right? Genesis chapter number six. It was a pretty bad day, pretty bad
society in which Noah lived. You can think about the various times in history
and you can think about not only that example, other biblical examples and you
can look at these days, listen, some of the days in which even these that we read
of in the New Testament were facing with regard to the persecution and all the
difficulty. These were hard days, hard days. But I'm thankful that God's grace
is sufficient. Regardless of what day you live in, regardless of how challenging
the particular era and the culture is of that particular day, God is on his throne
and God's grace is sufficient and God can help us. Listen, it's important that we
don't come to this conclusion in 2026. Well, no one wants to hear. No one cares.
No one wants to know. No, listen, do not. We must acknowledge that pitfall.
We must avoid the pitfall. Let us not be weary in well-doing. And we find this,
the pitfall is exposed, but we want to avoid it. So what do we do?
Paul mentions that we obtain mercy. We find grace, as our memory verse this
evening from Hebrews 4 and verse 16, to help in the time of need.
And we notice here, you've acknowledged with me, if you're taking notes,
the principle explained, the pitfall exposed. But I want you to see number three
this morning, the promise embraced. The promise embraced. And this is where the
rubber meets the road, so to speak. This is for each of us this morning what we
must do. We find that he says in verse number nine, I've only read the first part
of the verse, and let us not be weary in well-doing. But then notice the promise.
He says this, for in due season, we shall reap if we faint not. In due season.
When's the due season? God knows. I don't know. God does. Amen?
I understand that there's, with regard to agriculture, and you plant things,
and you can understand. Holly was telling me just a little while ago how long the
watermelons take. Would you say a hundred days? A hundred days. That's a long time.
You see those watermelons, you might think they're ready to go, but no,
they're supposed to take a hundred days. And you see some of that. Listen,
there's some things that we can look to, and we can understand some of that process.
But when we see here that God says for in due season, I don't know the timing,
but I know the God who knows the timing. And what I must do is get my eyes on the
God who is eternal, the God who is immutable, the God who is working,
the God who knows all things and does all things well. In fact, even here in the book of Galatians,
he says when the fullness of time was come, God sent forth his son. Not a day earlier,
not a day later. It was right on time. And in fact, if they had studied Daniel's prophecy
and other portions of the prophets, they would have known exactly the timing as well.
Listen, his timing is perfect. Our timing is not. And I understand there are many times in
your life and in my life that we want to hurry up God. Amen? Seriously,
let's be honest with ourselves this morning. We want God to be on our timetable, on our timeline.
We want what we want. Listen, we live in a culture that absolutely promotes that kind of thinking.
Have it your way. Have it on your time. Get it right now. Instant gratification. That's the
culture that we live in. Is it not? I don't have the money for that. Here's a credit card offer
that we'll give you with 28.99% interest and you'll be able to pay for it for the rest of your
life. Right? That's the society that we live in. You can't afford it. I can help you afford it.
Because we can just go ahead and just pay. You can only afford $58. That's fine. We'll pay it for
God's time. Listen, the culture sometimes influences us to think a wrong way. In due
season. That's God's time. And it's always the right time. He says this, notice the promise,
we, notice the words, shall reap. We shall reap. It's certain. You sow the seed, you're going to
reap a harvest. Listen, God's word, we were talking yesterday even about passing all those John and
Romans and sometimes you can think, are they going to read them? Is it going to affect? Listen,
God said his word shall not return void. God said this, that the entrance of thy words giveth light.
I don't know. I just have to leave it up to God. Amen. I can't control all of the various aspects
and factors, but I understand this morning that listen, they can just read one little tiny part
of that thing. And even if they threw it down, even if they returned it, somebody told me that
they had an encounter yesterday and somebody took one and then went a little while and thought that
man, this is not what I want. It talks about Jesus and they gave it back to him. Listen,
even though they gave it back, God and the Holy spirit can work in that individual's heart and
that individual's life to understand, listen, they could have had a restless night last night.
Why? Because they just read one little thing about Jesus Christ and they don't.
They don't believe that he's the Messiah.
They don't believe that he's the one
that died for their sins,
that rose on the third day according to the scriptures,
that is coming back, hallelujah.
But God can use that.
And you might not ever know,
I might not never know, ever know,
but God knows and God keeps records
and he says, listen, ye shall reap.
Praise God for that.
This is a promise, but what I've titled the point
is the promise embraced
because sometimes we see the promises,
we can read the promises,
we can sing about the promises,
standing on the promises of Christ my Lord.
Listen, I'm thankful for the great hymn of the faith
and I'm thankful that even as Peter says in 2 Peter,
these exceeding great and precious promises,
listen, they're all positive with God.
Everything he's ever said he will do.
Sometimes we don't embrace the promise.
I mean, we might be in a setting,
we might be in a situation where we sing the song
and maybe at times I've even done this
that will jump up and I'll cut Dean off
and I'll say, hey, listen, before we sing that next verse,
somebody share a promise with me
and we'll share promises from the congregation
of the promise that he said,
I'll never leave thee nor forsake thee,
the promise that and we'll start going through
and listen, I'm so thankful
that sin shall no longer have dominion over us
and you just think about so many promises.
He said, I will come again.
Listen, I don't know when he's coming, but I know he is
and he's gonna come on time, amen.
And we can know the promises,
but then the difficulty comes in your life,
the difficulty comes in my life
and all of a sudden we don't embrace the promise.
There's something different about knowing the promise
and embracing the promise.
There's something drastically different
and we find here that he says,
notice and let us not be weary in well-doing
for in due season, we shall reap if we faint not.
Wouldn't you hate to drop out too early?
Honestly.
Listen, there's people that have done that.
Just drop out too early, they give up too early.
They got weary, they say, you know what, this isn't for me
and they never really got to see what God was doing
because they fainted, the danger of growing weary.
Look at verse 10, it's the embracing, the embracing.
He says, as we have therefore opportunity,
as we have therefore opportunity.
Can I tell you this morning that all of us have opportunity?
The opportunity is different for every one of us.
Absolutely, it's diverse but I would say that it's certain.
You have opportunity, I have opportunity,
your opportunities are different than my opportunities.
You're gonna go to a workplace tomorrow
and you're gonna see people that I might never meet
in my entire life, right?
I might go places tomorrow, there are things
that I might do that I'll meet people
that you'll never meet in your entire life.
There's gonna be opportunities that are presented to me,
opportunities that are presented to you
and this is the embracing of the promise
because he says, as we have therefore opportunity,
notice, let us do good.
So in verse number nine, he said,
let us not be weary in well-doing
and so we find that he then says in verse number 10,
as we have therefore opportunity,
let us do good unto all men,
especially unto them who are the household of faith,
those who are brothers and sisters in Christ
and we see this, the contextual impact
and really connection between verse nine with well-doing
and verse 10 with do good.
Again, it's not so that you can stay saved.
I'm thankful, listen, my salvation is secure.
It's as secure as it's ever gonna be
because I'm in the hand of the Lord Jesus Christ
and his hand is in the hand of the Father, amen?
I have reserved in heaven for me an inheritance
that is incorruptible and undefiled,
it fadeth not away, hallelujah, man.
Praise God.
I talked to a man yesterday,
down there in the Eastern Market
and man, he was a religious man.
I mean, super, super, super religious studying.
I mean, he was degrees and all sorts of things
and he was selling me some stuff
and I said, so let me ask you this.
Are you 100% sure if you're to die today, you go to heaven?
Oh no, you can't know that.
I said, really?
Why isn't that?
Shared some things with me and I said,
well, I'm sure you're familiar with Paul.
I referenced some things about Paul
and how Paul shares with us and through the scriptures,
his confidence of being with Jesus, hallelujah.
I'm thankful this morning that our salvation is settled
but God wants us to do good.
He wants us to do these, as he says,
not be weary in well-doing and he says, let us do good.
Do these, carry out the work of the ministry.
Carry out the work of the ministry.
And as we begin to think about the context
of all that's taking place here
and I understand that we're living in this day
and we have, yes, rejections and whatever happens
but we must embrace the promise to know
that God is doing something, that God is working
and I'm gonna just trust him.
I'm gonna embrace the promise.
I'm not gonna just look for results.
We live in a society
that not only promotes instant gratification
but we live in a society that is all about results.
It is a results-driven society.
What have you done for me lately?
Amen?
Professional sports teams, coaches get fired all the time
because they didn't bring home a trophy.
There was no championship that they brought home.
By the way, there's one
that gets the championship every year
and there's however many else that don't get it.
You know what I'm saying?
But it's about that results-driven society that we live in.
You look at corporations
and I worked in the corporate world for years
and it was all about metrics and metrics
and what are your numbers and what are your metrics
and what are you producing and what are your, I get it.
We live in a society that will inflate things
in order to show some type of results
because that's what people want.
But I can't produce results and neither can you.
The question is not how many people got saved,
the question is how much seed was sown.
Amen?
Because the Bible says that some plant, some water,
but God gives the increase.
I cannot, you cannot make somebody get saved.
But you can sow the seed.
You can water.
You can be involved in that process
and you can see God do what only God can do.
See, God knows our frame.
He knows we're frail.
He knows we're but dust.
And he knows that there's a potential,
the danger of growing weary in well-doing.
As we read not only here in Galatians but over there
in the passage that we saw in 2 Thessalonians,
he makes it abundantly clear that he says this,
be not weary in well-doing.
So the context again is all with regard
to doing the work of the ministry.
Maybe this morning you're a little bit discouraged
because you don't see the results that you'd like to see.
Maybe you get to the point, you say does it even matter?
Do they even listen?
No one even cares.
Can I tell you this morning,
let us not be weary in well-doing.
Let us embrace the promise.
Let us receive God's grace and God's mercy.
Let us focus on the one.
Listen, I'm not doing it for the results,
I'm doing it for God.
What a privilege to be a servant of the Lord.
What a privilege to be engaged in the work of the ministry.
See, we understand the work of the ministry
is not just for the pastor.
We understand Ephesians chapter number four,
that the pastor is given to the church,
is a gift to the church in order to equip the saints
for the work of the ministry.
And it's altogether possible that the individual
that's serving as the pastor could grow weary in well-doing,
but it's also possible that the congregants,
the members of a local church
can grow weary in well-doing.
It's of interest to me.
Listen, there are pastoral epistles in the New Testament.
First, second, Timothy, Titus, right?
Pastoral epistles, but then there's church epistles.
Do you notice that the instruction of not growing weary
is not written to Timothy and to Titus?
It's written to churches.
The churches in the region of Galatia
and the church in Thessalonica.
That should encourage us
because we're all engaged in the work of the ministry.
And God says, let us not.
Let us not be weary in well-doing.
Can I encourage you this morning?
God's working.
I don't know all that God's doing, but I know God's working.
And I know that he's not willing that any should perish, but that all should come to
repentance.
Listen, I'd like to see more people saved.
I'd like to see more people walk the aisle.
I understand.
Sometimes we get our focus on that, and sometimes we get our focus on that instead of the Lord.
You know exactly what happens is we fall in that pitfall.
We get weary.
Because we're looking at the results.
And God says, just get your eyes on me, looking unto Jesus, the author and finisher of our
faith.
This morning, there is a danger to acknowledge.
There's the danger of growing weary, and I want to encourage you this morning.
Keep on sowing to the Spirit.
Keep on sowing the good seed.
Because he says that in due season, we shall reap if we faint not.
Help us to embrace that, and to trust the Lord to do what only he can do.
Let us pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you so much for loving us.
We thank you for the privilege of being able to be your servants.
We thank you that you've given us a Bible, and you've given us with clarity the dangers
that we are faced with.
And God, I pray that as your people, that you would help us to not grow weary in well-doing.
Lord, help us to trust you.
Help us, Lord, to receive the grace and the mercy that we need.
Lord, help us, I pray, to keep on keeping on.
Help us to faint not.
I pray that you'd work in hearts and lives as only you can.
I pray that your name alone would be glorified through every decision that is made.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?