and be looking at verses 15 through 17 this morning Colossians chapter number 3 as we continue to make our way through this great book and
Of course starting in verse number 5 and down through verse number 14 over the last three weeks
We've had the opportunity to read
that detailed instruction that the Apostle Paul gives to the believers here in Colossi and of course by
Preservation to us as well and we've learned that there's some things to put off fornication
uncleanness inordinate affection evil concupiscence covetousness anger wrath malice
blasphemy filthy communication and lying what a list and
He said all these things you're to put off and then of course after you put those things off
He says put on therefore and that list included bowels of mercy kindness humbleness of mind meekness long-suffering
Forbearing one another forgiving one another and then he said of this above all these things put on charity
which is the bond of perfectness and
What a blessing to understand the principle that God has given us
Of course
We often reference it from Galatians 5 that were to walk in the spirit
So that we do not fulfill the lust of the flesh in here
I believe that it's a very practical passage of Scripture that teaches us what it is to put to walk in the spirit
of course in that passage in Galatians 5 the Word of God tells us the works of the flesh are manifest in this way and
Provides us with a list and this is the fruit of the Spirit is and defines for us gives us those nine
Attributes as to how the fruit of the Spirit is described. And so we find that here
The Apostle Paul is providing us with this
Application if you will I would say this now that we have put off all of those things that we mentioned really we'd say the
Old man, remember we used this phrase last week with his grave clothes
And now we've put on the new man with his grace clothes
We find that this now should be evidenced in our behavior
Doesn't that make sense if we've put off all these things if we've put on all these things
Remember 2nd Corinthians 5 if any man be in Christ, he's a new creature old things are passed away
Behold, all things are become new and as we walk in the spirit so that we do not fulfill the lust of the flesh
We find that that it should impact our behavior
It should be evident in the way that we live and I believe that that's exactly what we see as we finish up the third
Chapter of the book of Colossians. In fact, even going into the first verse of chapter number four
We find that this remainder of this chapter in the first verse of chapter 4 really deals with the behavior of the believer
In three particular areas this morning
We'll be looking at verses 15 through 17 and I believe in this passage of Scripture
That God is really dealing with the behavior of the believer in the church house in the church house
We find that next week
We'll be looking at verses 18 through 21 and in that passage of Scripture God deals with our behavior in the home
And then we find that in verses 22 through chapter 4 and verse number 1 that God deals with our behavior in the workplace
I made this statement last week as we look through the
the particular details that were to put on and we looked at that list and I made this statement that if we begin to
truly walk with God as we're called to do so and we truly would to
Put into practice this which we find in the passage of Scripture. I believe we could make a great difference in our world
Truly that people would see Christ in us
Amen, and that's what they need to see. They don't need to see that. Well, they're just like we are
They don't have anything else that we need how many times we've heard people say about the church when you invite them
Oh, it's just full of a bunch of hypocrites and so on and so forth and people have stories and accounts and experiences of
Dealing with Christians and being lied to and being taking advantage of and so on and so forth and those things ought not be
Amen, and we find it as we would live the Christ life
remember the plan of God is that we as his people would be conformed to the image of his Son that we'd be sanctified and
What a blessing to understand that God
Gives us in his word truth with regard to not only
What to put on and put off or put off and put on we should say but also how we are to behave or how those
Decisions would affect our behavior before we get into the passage
I'm reminded of what Paul said to Timothy over in 1st Timothy 3 in verse 15. He said but if I tarry long
That thou mayest know how thou oughtest to behave thyself in the house of God
Which is the church of the Living God the pillar and ground of the truth
Not everything that's called church today is church
amen, and
There is behavior that is appropriate in the church
And as we study this passage of Scripture in Colossians 3 verses 15 through 17
I would say this as we look at the title for the message behavior in the church house
I would say that our behavior in the church house should be characterized by five things and
Don't get too nervous that I have five points this morning
We'll go quickly through them
But I believe that our behavior should be characterized by the five things that we find in this portion of Scripture
Let me begin reading in verse 15. The Bible says this and the peace of God
Excuse me, and let the peace of God rule in your hearts to the witch
Also, ye are called in one body and be thankful. Let the Word of Christ dwell in you richly in all wisdom
Teaching and admonishing one another in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs
Singing with grace in your hearts to the Lord and whatsoever you do in word or deed
Do all in the name of the Lord Jesus
Giving thanks to God and the Father by Him with the help of God this morning. I want to give you these five character
Characteristics if you will on how our behavior should be characterized in the church house
I will say this the Apostle Paul is not
instructing these believers to practice something that he is not already doing personally and that's a wonderful blessing when you have the
opportunity to study the life of the Apostle Paul and you study his life and then you read his
Instruction to these believers as God would use him to pen much of the New Testament
We see that Paul was a man that as he said to the church in Philippi
not only the things that you've heard from me, but the things that you've seen in me do and
What a blessing to understand the instruction that is provided here number one
If you're taking notes our behavior in the church house should be characterized by peace by peace
Notice the Word of God says and let the peace of God
Rule in your hearts we find that it is the peace of God. It is not man's peace
It is not something that we try to conjure up in our own ways and try to figure out how to do this
It's not manufactured by us
It is the peace of God and God tells us here in the passage of Scripture that were to let it's the peace of God
Let God's peace notice rule in your hearts
The word rule carries with it the idea of being an umpire being a rule or the one that would oversee
You would think about the time of writing and you would think about some of those
games that would be played and how they would have
Officials and they would have the judges and how they were the ones that would rule over they would have the control of that
Particular event we're familiar with that when you think about various
Athletic competitions, in fact when Friday evening we're at a volleyball game and there was a there's supposed to be two referees
But there's only one and man
She did the best she could but she missed a whole bunch of calls
But guess what? She was the one that was ruling that court
It was her call and whatever call she made whether it was agreed upon or not
It stood and in the same manner we see that were to let the peace of God notice that word let
It's something that we need to be aware of and we need to allow God's peace to rule in our hearts
And I believe that we think about we're mindful of what Jesus said in John 14 in verse number 27
Of course as he's preparing his disciples for that day in which he would go to the cross of Calvary just a short time
from when he's speaking these words to his disciples and
He's already told them about not letting their heart be troubled and he's told them great things
But he tells them this in John 14 in verse number 27 peace. I leave with you
Then he says this
My peace I give unto you not as the world giveth give I unto you
Let not your heart be troubled neither
Let it be afraid. Oh in the house of God. We need to allow the peace of God to rule in our hearts
I understand that the Scriptures talk about the the peace of God
which passeth all
understanding we understand that he will keep us in perfect peace whose mind is stayed upon him and
What a blessing to know the peace of God. I
Believe contextually as we're thinking about the behavior in the church when he's speaking about the peace of God ruling in your hearts
we're thinking about a body of believers and
Remember, he'd already instructed him in the previous passage in verse 13 for bearing one another and forgiving one another
And now he says that we're to let the peace of God rule in our hearts and with that context and with that
Understanding I believe that we would understand that this is the same peace that we see in the life of Christ
During his earthly ministry and it should be seen in our lives
And I would say this
peace in this
and it's really the opposite of having conflict and division.
See, many people have the idea that peace is the absence of trouble,
but the reality is that we can be in the very midst of great trouble
and have the peace of God. Amen?
But we think about the peace of God in church,
and as we as a body of believers,
as we're allowing the peace of God to rule in our hearts,
it's going to result in not having conflict and division and schisms and so on and so forth.
Why? Because we're allowing the peace of God to rule in our hearts.
How often the people of God can be in contention one with another
and hinder the work of God,
or to let the peace of God rule in our hearts.
How do we do that? Well, that's the result of putting off and putting on.
As we put off all of those things, as we put on all of these things,
we get rid of the old man in his grave clothes,
we put on the new man in his grace clothes,
then that's evident in our behavior and we allow the peace of God to rule in our hearts.
See, it's opposite of what we see in the church in Corinth.
The church in Corinth is not a model church.
The church in Thessalonica is a good church, a model church,
but the church in Corinth is filled with problems and difficulties,
and Paul is correcting them in 1 Corinthians,
and he's giving them very straight instruction.
I'll mention this many years ago,
but I'll never forget being in a place down in Tennessee,
and I saw a church, and it was called the First Baptist Church of Corinth,
and I thought, those guys are crazy. They're out of their mind.
Why would you name your church the First Baptist Church of Corinth?
But they did.
And listen, here's how God tells us in his word about the church in Corinth.
See, they're not letting the peace of God rule in their hearts.
Look at 1 Corinthians 1.
Look at just a couple of verses.
Notice in verse 11, as Paul is beginning really still his introduction
and the purpose of his writing, he says this in 1 Corinthians 1 and verse 11,
For if it hath been declared unto me of you, my brethren,
by them which are of the house of Chloe,
that there are contentions among you.
In chapter 3, notice what he says in verse 1.
He says,
And I, brethren, could not speak unto you as unto spiritual,
but as unto carnal, even as unto babes in Christ.
I have fed you with milk and not with meat,
for hitherto you were not able to bear it,
neither yet now are you able.
Because you are carnal.
Notice the result of that carnality.
It says,
For whereas there is among you envying and strife and divisions,
are ye carnal and walk as men?
And he begins to describe that carnality being seen
in those that were saying,
I'm of Paul, I'm of Apollos, and so on and so forth.
And we understand the divisions that are mentioned there,
but we find that that is not the plan of God
for the behavior of the people of God in the church of God.
We're to let the peace of God rule in our hearts.
As we go back to Colossians 3,
and we notice the behavior that is listed here,
I believe not only should the behavior in the church house
be characterized by peace,
but it also should be characterized by unity.
Look back in verse 15,
the Bible says,
And let the peace of God rule in your hearts,
notice this,
to the which also ye are called in one body.
It's a blessed thing to have unity.
Amen?
Personally, I don't like division.
I don't like contention.
I don't like all of that stuff.
I like unity.
And the reality is that we understand,
as Paul would say to the church in Ephesus in Ephesians 4,
he tells them that they're endeavoring
to keep the unity of the Spirit
a bond of peace in Ephesians 4,
in verse 3.
And we think about this thing of unity,
he says here,
to the which ye are called in one body.
We've often mentioned the way in which we strive for
and we endeavor to keep the unity of the Spirit,
that unity is the result of walking with God.
Unity is the result of embracing the truth
of the Word of God.
Unity is not something, again, that we manufacture.
It's not something where we come to this place
of just deciding that everyone can hold hands
in this ecumenical movement.
We're just going to embrace the things that would unite us
and just forget about the things that would divide us.
No, unity is when we take the Word of God
and say this is the standard
and we're going to agree with God.
Amen?
And as I agree with God and as you agree with God
and each one of us agree with God,
then guess what?
We can have unity.
And we can have that spirit of unity in the church.
And what a blessing that is.
And we find that this is the plan of God.
This is the behavior that ought to be evidenced.
And we find characterized not only by peace,
but by unity.
Notice in Philippians 2.
Notice how Paul will describe this to these believers here.
And he's speaking to these.
We mentioned this portion of Scripture last week
as we spoke about humility and humbleness of mind.
But notice here in Philippians 2,
beginning in v. 1, he says,
if there be therefore any consolation in Christ,
if any comfort of love,
if any fellowship of the Spirit,
if any bowels and mercies.
Notice what Paul says.
Fulfill ye my joy.
How are they going to fulfill his joy?
Notice what he says.
That ye be like-minded.
Having the same love.
Being of one accord of one mind.
You know what the devil seeks to do
is he seeks to divide.
That's what the enemy does.
You can look at the church in Acts
and you can read about the church in Jerusalem
as the disciples started after the day of Pentecost
and all that took place there with the church
and the progress of the Gospel being preached
and souls being saved and the church growing
and God working mightily.
You find that they were in one accord.
You often see that phraseology that is mentioned.
And so what happens?
Well, the enemy comes in
and the enemy seeks to divide.
And the enemy is always about division.
The enemy does not want us as the people of God
to be united.
He wants us to be divided. Why?
Because if we're fighting with each other,
if we're divided in the church house,
then we're not doing what we're supposed to do.
We're not out there sowing the seeds.
We're not out there reaping the harvest.
We're not out there preaching the Gospel of Jesus Christ
to a lost and dying world. Why?
Because we're all focused on what's going on in the church
and what our little divisions and schisms
and I'm this and I'm that and you're this
and so on and so forth.
And all of a sudden,
we find that the enemy has been successful
on rendering the people of God useless.
That's the plan of the enemy.
To cause division.
You know, it's not said of the church in Corinth
that they were spreading the Word of God
the way that the church in Thessalonica was.
And you can read of these differences
and understand.
And so, when we begin to think about
this understanding of the plan of God
and how we put off those grave clothes
with the old man
and put on the new man with the grace clothes
and how our behavior will change
and we'll have that peace of God
ruling in our hearts
that will lead to unity amongst the brethren.
It's a blessed thing to have unity.
I don't like being at odds with anyone.
I mean, there are some people
that just seem to like contention.
You ever meet some people like that?
They just kind of thrive on it.
I don't get that.
I don't like contention.
I don't like division.
I like unity.
And I'm thankful that we have the Word of God.
Often times, I've spoken to people in my office
in various situations, counseling,
maybe some folks that have visited the church
that have questions about the church
and so on and so forth
or someone that has some disagreement
with something that they've seen
in our doctrinal statement
or some other situation.
And I'll say something to this effect.
Can we just agree to agree with God?
As Baptist people, we've said for centuries
that the Word of God is our sole authority
for faith and practice.
And so therefore, if it is the sole authority
for faith and practice,
if we agree with God,
let's see what God says.
And we just open the Scriptures
and let God be God
and let the Word of God say
what the Word of God says.
You know the Word of God isn't as difficult
as some people make it out to be.
They say, oh, it's too hard to understand.
Sometimes it's just that we don't want to understand it
because we don't want to apply it.
We don't want to do it.
We don't want to live it.
And here, as Paul has gone through
with this church and Colossians,
he's gone through all of this behavior
and all of this put off and put on,
he says now that our behavior
in the church house will be characterized
in this manner.
He'll deal with the home in our next section
and then in the workplace.
Why?
Because we're Christians 24-7.
It's not just Christians in the church house.
We're to be representatives of the Lord Jesus Christ
every minute of every day of our lives.
And that's why he deals with the church house,
the home, and the workplace.
And we'll get through those over the next couple of weeks.
Back in Colossians 3, notice,
not only should our behavior in the church house
be characterized by peace and unity,
I believe number three,
it should be characterized by devotion.
By devotion.
You know, there's a purpose when we come to church.
Our purpose is to exalt and magnify
the Lord Jesus Christ.
Our purpose is to teach the Word of God.
Again, as I mentioned by way of introduction,
not everything that's called a church is a church today.
And there's a lot of places in which, throughout our society,
where the Word of God just, quite frankly, is not being taught.
I'm thankful for those churches that are standing on the truth of the Word of God
and that are continuing to be faithful,
that are continuing to preach the Word of God.
But there's a great pressure in our society today
to kind of step away from some of those things
and not be so contentious and so dogmatic about what God says in His Word,
and let's just be love, and let's just embrace, and so on and so forth.
But I'm sorry, I believe this morning that love is going to tell us the truth.
Love is not permissive, love is protective.
We find here that as we enter into verse number 16,
we see this idea of devotion, where the Bible says,
let the Word of Christ dwell in you richly in all wisdom.
What a great phraseology.
Again, we see the word let, we see that in verse 15,
again in verse number 16, something that we're to do to allow the Word of Christ.
And we think about this word dwell when it says to dwell in you richly in all wisdom.
It means to abide in and influence.
Why is it that Paul would tell Timothy in 2 Timothy 4,
after he tells him about all of the things with regard to the last days,
and all of the perilous times that will be present in the last days,
and evil men and seducers waxing worse and worse,
and all of that, and he enters into the fourth chapter and he says,
preach the Word.
Preach the Word.
Why? Because we need the Word of God to be dwelling in us.
We need it to be influencing us.
We find that Peter would give the instruction to the elders,
the pastors in 1 Peter 5, to feed the flock of God.
What do we feed? We feed the Word of God.
That's our responsibility.
That's the responsibility of the pastor, to feed the flock of God.
And we find this idea of the Word of God,
let the Word of Christ dwell in you richly in all wisdom,
and we're allowing it to abide in us and to influence us.
I said this many years ago.
I didn't make up the phrase or the quote,
but someone said this,
thumbprints in the Bible are more important than footprints on the moon.
And I said, that's good.
Why? Because we're in the Word of God so that it can get into us.
I want to think and act biblically.
I want to be in a place where when something comes up in my life
and I'm looking at a situation, a decision that has to be made,
that I've allowed the Word of Christ to dwell in me richly in all wisdom,
that I can have that source of wisdom,
that Word of God that will give me the guidance and the direction that I need.
When I speak of devotion, I believe that it's a personal devotion,
but it's not only a personal devotion.
We find that it would be a corporate devotion.
The reality is that we individually, as the children of God,
we are to be seeking the Word of God.
We're to be feasting upon the Word of God daily in our lives.
That we should hunger and thirst after righteousness.
As newborn babes, that we would desire the sincere milk of the Word
that we may grow thereby.
That we would truly, as I preached several weeks ago,
say, as Samuel said,
speak, Lord, for Thy servant heareth.
That we're personally, each of us, each one, each member of the church,
that we are personally in the Word of God,
feasting upon the Word of God.
When's the last time someone in the church came to you and said,
hey, brother, hey, sister,
what's God been teaching you in your devotions this week?
How's God been working in your life?
It's not something very common that we practice in our lives.
We talk about all kinds of things, right?
We really do.
But for some reason, we avoid the conversation of,
hey, brother so-and-so, what did God show you this week in His Word?
How's God working in your life?
Several years ago, I was at a pastor's meeting.
I sat down to have lunch at this pastor's meeting.
It was a large pastor's meeting.
In fact, Kimberly's parents, we were there with them.
And we met a number of pastors that had never met before.
And Brother Sommerdorf kind of led the group that we were there with.
And there were hundreds of pastors that were at this particular conference.
And some had their spouses with them.
Some had staff members with them.
And I remember sitting down to have lunch.
And it was the very first day that we were there.
And there was a pastor.
I prayed for him this morning.
His name is Scotty Bockhaus.
Do you know Brother Scotty?
And Scotty Bockhaus.
And he's a pastor.
And we sat down to have lunch.
I'd never met the guy other than just introducing ourselves to one another.
We sat down for lunch.
And he said, so, brother, what's God been teaching you in His Word?
And I thought, that's good.
And I was able to share with him what God had been teaching me,
where I was in my personal devotions.
And then I asked him.
And, man, we had great fellowship.
We weren't just talking about the weather or the sports or the politics or whatever, right?
No.
Talk about how's God working?
How's He using His Word in my life, in your life?
It's that personal devotion.
I believe also that it's a corporate devotion.
Notice, as we come together for the purpose of worship of the Lord,
notice what he says in verse 16.
Teaching and admonishing one another in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs,
singing with grace in your hearts to the Lord.
That idea of teaching and admonishing.
It's instruction. It's warning.
It's the public ministry of the Word of God, as I'm doing even here this morning.
It's what Paul spoke about when he said in Colossians 1 and verse 28,
whom we preach, warning every man and teaching every man in all wisdom,
that we may present every man perfect in Christ Jesus,
whereunto I also labor, striving according to His working which worketh in me mightily.
And Paul was engaged in this behavior.
And he's saying to these believers in Colossae that if you've put off these things
and you've put on these things,
it should be evidenced in your behavior in first in the church house.
It should be characterized not only by what we find here with peace and unity,
but now with devotion.
I wonder how often we go through the process of self-examination.
We say, where am I in my walk with Christ?
Am I closer to God today than I was a year ago?
Am I closer to God today than I was a month ago, a week ago?
How's my devotion? What am I learning?
What have I learned publicly? What have I learned privately?
Notice what it says here, teaching and admonishing one another.
You know, there are a lot of one another commands in the New Testament
with regard to the people of God and the church of God.
That's why the church of God is a called out assembly, right?
I understand people use Livestream. That's not church.
Church is the assembling of God's people. Why?
Because how are we going to admonish and instruct one another
if we've not assembled together, right?
Now, I'm not against Livestream. We have it.
We have people that are watching and I'm perfectly fine with it.
But the reality is that we can't fulfill these responsibilities unless we assemble.
And so we assemble because we want to instruct.
We want to, as we find here in this verse of Scripture,
teach and admonish one another.
Iron sharpeneth iron.
That's what Solomon said in Proverbs. Iron sharpeneth iron.
And so as we have the opportunity to engage in this work
and we understand how we're to be instructing and warning one another,
there's some experiences that you've had that somebody else might not have
that you as a more mature believer might have the opportunity to instruct them
and to warn them and to give them truth from the Word of God.
And that's a wonderful thing.
It's a blessed thing when we have that spirit
not only of peace and unity, but of devotion.
God's house is a house of prayer. It's a spiritual house.
Church is not a club.
It's not just something that we just, okay, check it off the box.
I did church this week. No. So much more than that.
Not only do we see peace and unity and devotion,
but I believe that as we look down into verse number 17,
our behavior in the church house should be characterized by purpose.
By purpose. What do I mean by that?
I believe the purpose is to exalt and magnify the Lord.
Very plainly. That is the purpose.
Notice how he says it in verse 17,
"...and whatsoever ye do in word or deed..."
Now that's a pretty conclusive statement.
I mean a broad, far-reaching, all-inclusive statement.
He says, "...and whatsoever you do in word or deed,
do all in the name of the Lord Jesus."
I'm mindful of what John the Baptist said.
He must increase. I must decrease.
It's all about the Lord.
It's not about the individual.
It's not about making a name for ourselves.
It's not about someone looking at another brother or sister in the church
and putting them up on a pedestal.
No, it's about the Lord Jesus Christ being magnified and exalted in our midst.
It's about us giving testimony of how God has worked in our midst.
our lives. Listen, all that we are is, as Paul said, by the grace of God. I am what
I am by the grace of God. God's working in our lives. Where would we be this
morning if it had not been for Christ? Where would we be this morning if it
were not for the gospel coming to your home and to my home, right? It's all about
the Lord. And we come to church, we come with this purpose that we're to do all
whatsoever you do, in word or deed, do all in the name of the Lord Jesus. It's
His church and it's all about Him. In the video presentation, Brother Pate
referenced Matthew 16, 18, where the Lord Jesus Christ said, I will build my church
and the gates of hell shall not prevail against it. This is God's church and all
that we do is to be done for His honor and for His glory, that He might be
exalted and magnified in our midst. In Acts 20, in verse number 28, as Paul is
speaking to those leaders of the church in Ephesus, as he's on his way to
Jerusalem, he gives them much instruction. He desired to be able to see
them and, oh, the depth and richness of that which he communicates to these
church leaders in Acts 20. But I want you to notice in
verse number 28, Paul says this, take heed therefore unto yourselves and to all the
flock over the which the Holy Ghost hath made you overseers. Notice what he says,
to feed the church of God, but then it says this, which he hath purchased with
his own blood. It's His church. We sing the song more about Jesus, how
appropriate that song is, because it's really all about Jesus. Jesus is the
sweetest name I know. Amen? And we find that we come with that purpose when we
assembled this morning, when you woke up this morning, you had some purpose and
some desire that you're gonna be in church, and your purpose, hopefully, was
that you would come and that you would be able to worship the Lord and magnify
and exalt the Lord, that you'd be encouraged and strengthened through the
the singing of the great hymns of the faith, that you'd be encouraged and
strengthened and challenged through the preaching of the Word of God, that we
would come expecting to hear from God, anticipating how God would work in our
lives individually, and purpose to take what we hear and apply it in our lives,
that we would be doers of the Word and not hearers only. You know, there's some
people over the years I'm thankful that God has blessed, and we don't have too
much of this, at least not on a regular basis. It's happened from time to time.
When you're in any place for the length of time, not that 10 years is
extremely long, but really for the average of a pastor, it's a lengthy
period of time, and there are people that sometimes show up to church just to
criticize the sermon. People that listen online just to criticize the sermon.
You didn't come for the right purpose. You didn't come with the heart of all
that we do for the glory of God and how God might work in my heart and in my
life, and how he might allow me to be able to influence another brother or
sister in Christ. As you know, I attend regularly a pastor's meeting, the
Atlantic Independent Baptist Fellowship, and as I attend that pastor's meeting,
there are certain times, certain periods of time, where things are busier than
other times, and there are times in which, man, it's a tough deal for me to put on
my schedule to be out of the office and to go to a pastor's meeting, but
something that I understand is that not only do I need it, but sometimes somebody
else needs me to be there. And I can't tell you how many times I've been
encouraged by attending one of these pastor's meeting, but also how I've been
able to encourage someone else. As I travel to the pastor's meetings,
oftentimes I pray that the Lord would allow me to be a blessing. I pray,
understanding that there are some pastors that might be there that day that are
ready to submit their resignation, they're just done with the ministry,
they're fed up, they've been hurt, they've been whatever, and they're just done, and
that God would help me to be a blessing and an encouragement. You know, the same
thing is true in the house of God. Yeah, we come that God would work in our
hearts and lives, but the reality is that you, somebody else, might need you to be
here today, because you might have the opportunity to, as we find in verse
number 16, that teaching and admonishing, that them seeing your life and seeing
your purpose, and you could have that influence in someone else's life. What a
blessing. See, the church is a family. Church is a family. There's a family. We
have the opportunity to come together in that unity and with that purpose of, it's
not about the individual, it's about the Lord Jesus Christ, and it's about how can
we advance His kingdom, how can we better serve and please Him with our lives
corporately and collectively. And God places the individuals, even as Paul
would use the illustration of the body of Christ and each member having its
purpose, and we find that God assembles the church, He builds His church, but He
does so so that He would be glorified. We think about our own personal, the ways
in which God has given us spiritual gifts. We understand about the truth of
let your light so shine before men that they may see your good works, and what?
Glorify your Father which is in heaven. When we read about the truth, as we think
about those spiritual gifts that God has blessed us with, and we understand
that He's given them to us, it's not that we had any say in it, He's gifted us
individually, but we find it as we minister, and as we're good stewards of
the manifold grace of God, that the purpose of our ministry is that in all
things that the Lord Jesus Christ would be glorified, according to 1st Peter
chapter number 4. And that's the purpose. And so as we gather together, as we think
about the behavior in the church house, and we think about the truth that Paul
has given, that we have here in the Word of God, in Colossians 3 verses 5
through 14, and we say we've done all of those things, and now it's going to be
evidenced in my behavior in the church house, characterized by peace, unity,
devotion, purpose, and number five, to be characterized by praise. Be characterized
by praise. I skipped over a couple of the phrases because really I believe all
three of these verses deal with the subject of praise. It's a wonderful thing
to praise the Lord. Let me say this, He is worthy of our praise. Amen? In everything
give thanks, for this is the will of God in Christ Jesus concerning you. In
everything. You say, well that's kind of hard. God's good all the time. God is good
all the time. Amen? Taste and see that the Lord is good. David confessed and
proclaimed that he had delivered him out of all of his troubles. He didn't say
that he kept all of the troubles from ever happening. He said God's just been
good even through the storms. Amen? Notice what he says in verse number 15 when we
think about this idea of praise. He ends the verse of Scripture and says this,
and be ye thankful. And be thankful. I believe that in verse number 16 when we
look about the the statement there in Psalms and hymns and spiritual songs,
singing with grace in your hearts to the Lord, though the phrase
praise or thanksgiving is not found there, I believe that the the verbiage
that is used inhabits the idea of praise and thanksgiving. As we're singing and
we're praising the Lord, I'm so thankful for the great hymns of the faith that
remind us and reinforce for us great biblical truth. And we find that we
praise him through our singing. We'll see that in just a moment as we go over the
book of Psalms in closing. But notice at the end of verse number 17, he says
giving thanks to God and the Father by Him. You know, our behavior should be
characterized by praise. We ought not be woe is me type of Christians. I know that
there's been some reference, I think my dad referenced it, but that Eeyore kind
of syndrome. How many y'all know who Eeyore is? Right? Oh bother. Right? Like
everything's a problem, right? It's just, you know, he's just living under the
circumstances, right? But as the people of God, we live above the circumstances. We
understand that God is sovereign and he's ordained things and he's allowed
things and so I'm gonna just praise him. I'm just gonna thank him. Why? Because God
is good. He's good all the time. We find that we as the people of God are
to be giving thanks and praising him. You know one of the characteristics that God
gives us in his Word with regard to the perilous times is that people would be
unthankful. Unthankful. Do you not see that in the world in which we live? People
are unthankful. People think they deserve something. Listen, as the people of God we
recognize all that we have is because of God's blessing. All that we are and all
that we have is all because of God. And so therefore we ought to praise him. We
ought to bless his holy name. Psalm 103 says not only bless his holy name but
all that is within me bless his holy name.
holy name. I mean that's passionate praise, amen? And I understand we don't
swing from the rafters and all that kind of crazy stuff, but the reality is that
we ought to be passionate about our praise. Listen, we can be
passionate about a lot of things, can we not? We ought to be passionate about
praising our God. Why? Because He's good. Turn over to Psalm 100, if you will. We'll
finish with a couple of passages in the book of Psalms this morning. Psalm 100 is
a psalm that we're familiar with, and I won't read all the five verses here, I
just want you to notice in verse number four, it's a wonderful psalm, but notice
what he says here in Psalm 100 and verse number four, enter into his gates, how?
With thanksgiving. And into his courts with what? Praise. Be thankful unto him
and bless his name. Oh man, we come to church and we're saying, oh Lord, thank you.
Thank you that you, in your infinite wisdom, you designed a church, right? It's
God's plan. Church isn't man's plan. It wasn't some person that just thought up,
you know, we should have church. No, it's God's plan, and God's given us the
instruction. We say, thank you that I have the ability to go. It's not a,
I gotta go to church. No, it's we get to, and God has something for me, and we
enter into his gates, we enter with thanksgiving. That's why I've often
said that as we have our time of prayer, when we think about our personal devotion,
not only allowing, let the Word of Christ dwell in you richly in all wisdom, but
as we would spend time with God in prayer, that our prayer time ought to
be characterized, and really I believe our prayer time ought to be started with
praise and thanksgiving, that we just bless the name of the Lord, that we just
get caught up in how good he is. We ought to be thankful. We ought to praise him.
Notice Psalm 150, another familiar Psalm, but I want you to see, and I'm gonna read
the entirety of this Psalm. I did not count, but perhaps it would be a worthy
exercise to count the number of times praise is used in these just six verses.
Praise ye the Lord. Praise God in his sanctuary. Praise him in the firmament of
his power. Praise him for his mighty acts. Praise him according to his
excellent greatness. Praise him with the sound of the trumpet. Praise him with the
psalter and harp. Praise him with the timbrel and dance. Praise him with
stringed instruments and organs. Praise him upon the loud cymbals. Praise him
upon the high-sounding cymbals. Let everything that hath breath praise the
Lord. Praise ye the Lord. Wow. Just read Psalm 150 every day this week. Honestly.
Say, God help me to be a praising Christian. Help me to understand. Notice
when he says in verse 2, praise him for his mighty acts. Praise him according to
his excellent greatness. That we not only praise God for what he does, but we
praise God for who he is. And we dig into the Word of God and we find out those
attributes of our God and we just thank God that he's holy and he's just and
he's sovereign and he's omnipotent and he's omniscient and he's omnipresent and he's my
helper. He's a very present help in the time of trouble. He's Alpha and Omega, the
beginning and the end. He's the Lord God omnipotent who reigneth. He's coming
again. Oh man, we just get excited about praising him. Amen. He's worthy of our
praise. And we think about the way in which this passage of Scripture deals
with the behavior of God's people, specifically in the house of God. We say
how should our behavior be characterized? Peace. Let the peace of God rule in your
hearts. Unity in one body. Devotion. Let the Word of Christ dwell in you richly
in all wisdom, personally and corporately, teaching and admonishing one another. How
should it be characterized? It should be characterized with purpose. With purpose.
All that we do is so that God would be exalted and magnified. Remember what Paul
said at the end of that passage in Colossians 1 when he spoke about his
ministry of teaching and warning every believer. He gave us what the purpose was
that he would, that we would may, that we may present every man perfect in Christ
Jesus. See, because one day we're gonna stand before him. We have purpose. Our
purpose is to exalt and magnify Christ whether in word or deed whatsoever we do.
Amen. It's all for God's glory. And then we see it's to be characterized by
praise. Oh, that we just lift up and praise the name of our God. He is worthy. He is
worthy of our praise. Next week we'll see the behavior in the home. A home that
is God-honoring. You know, God has, God not only created the church or had the
idea for the church, he had the idea for the home. It wasn't man's idea. It's God's
idea. It's God's plan. And as we take the Word of God and we say, okay, this is what
the behavior in the church house is supposed to be. Now this is what the
behavior in a home is supposed to be. And we'll see that God deals with each of the
individuals within a home. I'm so thankful for the Word of God and the way
in which it instructs us and helps us so that we could understand how it is that
we're to behave ourselves. Remember what Paul said to Timothy, that thou mayest
know how thou oughtest to behave thyself in the house of God. And here we find
that as we put off that old man in those grave clothes and we put on that new man
in the grace clothes, that it will be evidenced in our behavior. Oh, that God
would help us. That God would help us to be conformed to the image of His Son. That
we'd walk in the Spirit and not in the flesh. Let's pray. Father, we love You. We
thank You for loving us. We thank You for the Word of God. Father, I pray that You
would help us this morning to understand the importance of our behavior in the
church house. That we'd understand that these things are not manufactured in our
flesh. That these things are the result of walking in the Spirit. These things
are the result of putting off the old man and putting on the new. We thank You
for the transformation that took place at our salvation. And God, I pray that You'd
help each one of us, each individual that's present this morning, to be
willing to crucify their flesh, to walk in the Spirit so we would not fulfill
the lust of the flesh. That we would say, as the Apostle Paul said, I am crucified
with Christ. That we'd live this life here on this earth for Your honor and for
Your glory. That we as a local assembly, Your church in this locale, God, we'd be
pleasing in Your sight. That our behavior be characterized with these
five truths that we find in this passage of Scripture. Would You work in hearts
and lives this morning? We pray the Holy Spirit of God would do what only He can
do. He would take the Word of God and minister the heart of Your people. That
decisions would be made that would please Thee. We'll give You the glory for
all that You'll do, for it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed. We'll have a moment of invitation. Kimberly's
gonna play quietly on the piano and as she does, perhaps the Holy Spirit of God
pricked your heart this morning and you need to come to this altar and ask God
to help you in some way. As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.