Tower of Babel, the Tower of Babel here in Genesis 11, verses 1 through 9.
Last week, as you will recall, we had the opportunity to examine Genesis chapter number
10, and as we studied through the 10th chapter of the book of Genesis, I made note that really
that passage of Scripture was providing us with an overview or a summary of the disbursement
of mankind, while we find in the first nine verses of chapter number 11 that the details
of that event are provided to us.
And so we begin to look at the 11th chapter, and this of course recording for us this subject
of the Tower of Babel, the disbursement of mankind.
Now you understand that as we've studied through these first 10 chapters, and now as we get
into the 11th chapter here of the book of Genesis, you've understood that we've mentioned
often that these 11 chapters of Genesis are under constant attack.
And we understand that those that we would maybe look at as being mockers and scoffers,
that they seek to undermine the foundation and authority of the Word of God.
And we find that they really attack the 11 chapters, the first 11 chapters of the book
of Genesis, and as they attack these 11 chapters and they deal with, even in chapter number
10, the genealogies that are provided here, the event in chapter 11, and then the subsequent
genealogy, and you find that as they attack all of these records that are given, that
not only in attacking the foundation, but again, we see the undermining of the authority
of God's Word.
Unfortunately, there have been many over the centuries that have caved in, that they've
given in to the pressures of the mockers and the scoffers, and they said, well, yeah, maybe
it could be that way, and maybe that is another possibility, and all of a sudden what you're
doing is you're putting holes in what God has told us, and then you go to other portions
of Scripture and say, well, how is that going to have any level of authority if this is
not authoritative?
And so, there's a plan, and we find that, of course, the enemy is behind that plan to
attack the Word of God.
We see it in Genesis chapter number 3, yea, hath God said, right?
And we find that that's what He says to Eve in the garden, and we find that that process
has continued on throughout the centuries.
As we come here, notice in verse number 1 in Genesis 11, the whole earth was of one
language and of one speech, and it came to pass as they journeyed from the east that
they found a plain in the land of Shinar, and they dwelt there.
And they said one to another, go to, let us make brick, and burned them throughly.
And they had brick for stone, and slime had they for mortar.
And they said, go to, let us build us a city and a tower whose top may reach unto heaven,
and let us make us a name, lest we be scattered abroad upon the face of the whole earth.
And the Lord came down to see the city and the tower which the children of men builded.
The Lord said, behold, the people is one.
They have all one language, and this they begin to do, and now nothing will be restrained
from them which they have imagined to do.
Go to, let us go down, and there confound their language, that they may not understand
one another's speech.
So the Lord scattered them abroad from thence upon the face of all the earth, and they left
off to build the city.
Therefore is the name of it called Babel, because the Lord did there confound the language
of all the earth, and from thence did the Lord scatter them abroad upon the face of
all the earth.
If you're taking notes this evening, I've simply entitled the message The Tower of Babel,
and number one in your notes this evening, notice the place.
It's given to us in verses one and two, again in verse number nine, and as we begin to do
some research and go back into the 10th chapter, we'll remind ourselves of the fact of this
one Nimrod.
We are introduced to him in verse number nine of Genesis 10, where the Bible says that he
was, and really verse number eight talks about that Cush begat Nimrod, he began to be a mighty
one in the earth.
He was a mighty hunter before the Lord, wherefore it is said, even as Nimrod, the mighty hunter
before the Lord, in the beginning of his kingdom was Babel.
And so we find here in verses one and two, the Bible tells us, it's giving us, setting
the scene, if you will, as to what's going on, and the Bible tells us that they journeyed,
and they found this plain in the land of Shinar, and they dwelt there.
The Bible tells us in verse number nine, therefore is the name of it called Babel.
And so we understand the place in which God is speaking of.
Now it's interesting as we begin to understand what's taking place and what's transpiring
here in these verses as we are introduced to Genesis chapter 11 and the Tower of Babel
and all that's taking place, we find that really there's a striking similarity between
what we begin seeing here in Genesis chapter 11 and what we read of in Revelation 17 and
18.
We'll make some reference to that as we go through the message this evening, but we find
that of course, even as we made note last week when we looked at this place called Babel,
when we look at Babylonia and Babylon, it's a word that is used familiar throughout the
Old Testament.
In fact, we find that the people of God, the nation of Judah, was taken captive by the
Babylonians.
And we can read of that, and we can understand Jeremiah, of course, prophesying on the eve
of captivity and all of those things that transpire.
And as we begin to think about the place Babel or Babylon, we find today that would be in
modern day Iraq.
And so that's the place in which is being spoken of here, and it's a place where they
found and obviously it was a place where they desired to stay and they dwelt there.
Now let's dig into the plan.
In verses three and four, we find there's a plan that is made, and it's interesting,
they use this terminology on two occasions, go to.
And you'll see in verse number three, it says, they said one to another, go to, and then
again in verse number four, and they said, go to.
You'll see that God will use that same vernacular in verse number seven as He begins to deal
with what it is that He's going to do, His response to their plan.
But we find that as we begin to dissect their plan and really understand what's taking place,
and it's almost as if that this, the people that are dwelling here, that they're gathered
together, there's some type of a meeting that takes place, and they're determining this
is the path in which we're going to go forward.
And they use that terminology, go to, and they say this, let us make brick, notice in
verse number three, and burn them throughly, and it begins to deal with the materials in
which they would use for their purpose of building.
It says that they had brick for stone and slime had they for mortar.
We find that not only did they desire to have the materials, but they explain, we find here
what their logic was and what it was that they were seeking to build.
It was a city and a tower, according to verse number four.
It says whose top may reach unto heaven, and notice this phrase, and let us make us a name.
And let us make us a name.
Now we find that it then says lest we be scattered abroad upon the face of the whole earth.
Now there are several observations that we make as we begin to look at verses three and
four and begin to dissect the plan that these people had here in this passage of Scripture.
Number one, you will know, obviously, that they sought no direction from the Lord.
There's no reference that we find in the passage of Scripture where they were seeking the face
of God with regard to this project, with regard to that which they were setting out to do.
Now we understand as God's people, and even as we study through the Scriptures, that you
find many times the people of God are requesting direction from the Lord.
They're seeking the face of God for direction.
We find ourselves in our lives as we pray about decisions and we pray that God would
lead us in a plain path, that he would give us clarity and wisdom with regard to the decisions
that we have to make.
We thank the Lord that he will provide leadership to us in our lives, but we find that here
as you read Genesis chapter 11, there is an obvious omission of anyone seeking direction
from the Lord God Almighty.
They are not seeking the face of God.
In fact, we would find that they really don't want God to be part of their plan.
We find that they were in direct rebellion to God's instruction.
See, in Genesis chapter 9, after Noah and his family got off of the ark, the end of
chapter number 8 records that for us, and it tells us that they made these offerings,
and what a blessing to understand how they behaved after they departed from the ark.
And we come to the ninth chapter of the book of Genesis, and God says this in verse number
1, and God blessed Noah and his sons and said unto them, Be fruitful and multiply and replenish
the earth.
And here we find that these individuals at Babel, that they have this idea, they say
at the end of verse number 4, lest we be scattered abroad upon the face of the whole earth.
They were in direct rebellion, in fact, to what God had given instruction to do.
We find that they sought to make a name for themselves.
We notice that phraseology in verse number 4, and let us make us a name.
It's a very significant aspect of what's going on here, because really what they're doing
is they're elevating man.
It's really this idea of humanism.
It starts all the way back here in Genesis chapter 11, and it's interesting, I looked
up a quick definition for humanism, and I'm going to share with you a thought from an
article that actually is in a magazine called The Humanist.
I've shared this in the past, but I think it's pertinent to the subject this evening.
Humanism is an outlook or system of thought that's attached to the humanist.
attaching prime importance to human
rather than divine or supernatural matters.
Humanist beliefs stress the potential value
and goodness of human beings.
They emphasize common human needs,
and they seek solely rational ways
of solving human problems.
Do we not see this mindset
in the society in which we live today?
Humanism, right?
It's very, very familiar to us,
and we see it as a very popular form of thinking,
and we find that here,
that in this beginning of chapter 11,
as we begin to think about the Tower of Babel,
one of what they were doing
is let us make a name,
let us make us a name,
and this idea of humanism elevating man.
And notice, as we would think about
this subject of humanism,
this is an article that's from the,
again, it's a periodical, a magazine called The Humanist,
and this article appeared over 30 years ago.
Now, you think about that.
This has been an agenda within our society
for a lengthy period of time,
but let me read this to you.
I'm gonna go through the length
of reading the entirety
of this particular section of the article.
It says, these people consider themselves
to be brave pioneers,
teaching the truth about man's origin
and facing death and extinction with valor.
They worship at the altar of Darwinian evolution.
They are, the writer says,
I am convinced more interested
in promoting their philosophy's anti-Christian agenda
than a scientific one.
Their agenda is very simple.
Get the biblical God out of the picture
and replace it with a humanistic worldview.
Man is the ultimate authority
to determine truth apart from God.
Darwinianism is arguably the most popular form of humanism.
Here's the exact quote.
It says this,
I am convinced that the battle for humankind's future
must be waged and won,
notice where they say,
in the public school classroom
by teachers who correctly perceive their role
as the proselytizers of a new faith,
a religion of humanity
that recognizes and respects the spark
of what theologians call divinity in every human being.
These teachers, what teachers?
The one in this public school classroom.
These teachers must embody the same selfless dedication
as the most rabid fundamentalist preachers.
Wow.
Says that they will be ministers of another sort,
utilizing a classroom instead of a pulpit
to convey humanist values in whatever subject they teach,
regardless of the educational level,
preschool, daycare, or large state university.
The classroom must and will become an arena of conflict
between the old and the new,
the rotting corpse of Christianity
together with all its adjacent evils and misery,
and the new faith of humanism.
And really we've seen that in our culture, in our society,
but it's nothing new.
There's nothing new under the sun, right?
We see all the way back here in Genesis
at the Tower of Babel, what are they trying to do?
It's this humanistic mind view,
let us make us a name, removing God,
really this kind of a one world order, if you will,
or system, which of course Satan is behind.
We find that Satan has always favored a one world system.
Why?
Because it's in that one world system
where he can centralize things
that allows for him to have an opportunity
to effectually seek control.
By the way, that's what Satan wants.
He wants control.
And if he can have a one world system,
and that's the goal of the evil one,
and we understand that during the millennial reign of Christ
that Jesus will rule and reign for 1,000 years,
but the counterfeit, the counterpart,
we find that Satan will seek to have government
and religious bodies under this one system, if you will,
and we find it starting all the way back here
in Genesis chapter 11.
And really we find that as we would consider
the role of Babylon throughout the history,
and we begin to think about the religious,
just the number of false religions
that have come out of Babylon,
you begin to see all of those things.
And then you come to Revelation 17 and 18,
and you begin to see there about the references
of not only religious Babylon, but commercial Babylon.
And we see that here,
it would seem that in Revelation 17 and 18,
it's not speaking about the specific geographical location
that is the same location as we find there
in Genesis chapter 11,
but we find that the system, if you will,
is the same idea,
and we find that it is still being controlled
by none other than Satan.
We'll make some notes of Revelation 17 and 18 here
in just a few moments,
but as we begin to see the plan that these individuals have
and we begin to see how that they have this plan
and it's going to be a plan
that they can see it to its fruition
and man, this is a good plan.
They've had their counsel, if you will,
and they've made their decisions.
No doubt, Nimrod has some part
within this entire situation for the Bible,
refers to him as being a mighty one in the earth
and a mighty hunter.
And we find that that carries with it
that idea of having this level of control and power.
They've made these decisions
as a result of perhaps a council type of a meeting
that they had as to what they were going to do
and here was their decision.
Here was their plan and it's unfolded for us.
The remainder of the passage in verses five through nine
deals with the punishment.
We've noticed the place, we see the plan.
Now notice the punishment.
Though man had excluded God from their plans,
it's interesting as we read the text of Scripture
that we see so clearly how that God is well aware
of all that is taking place upon His earth.
There's nothing hid from the Lord, amen?
Our God is omniscient, our God is omnipotent,
our God knows everything, He sees everything,
and we find that He is aware of that which is taking place.
It's interesting in verse number five
how that the author gives us really a view
of the fact that the Bible says
the Lord came down to see the city and the tower.
The reality is that God saw it and knew what was going on,
but we have this relational experience
that is given in verse number five
to help really see the interaction
that God Almighty has with His creation.
And it's as if, as we look at the passage,
it says that the Lord came down to see the city
and the tower which the children of men builded.
And we find that here, as we would look at this reference
and we would see what's happening,
we'd see the punishment that is given,
and we find that God is well aware.
Remember, they never consulted with God.
They never sought counsel from the face of the Lord.
We find that they simply made this decision.
They were going to go in this direction apart from God.
We don't need God, we don't want God,
was really their idea, their mindset.
Let us make a name for us and let us do this thing.
But God was well aware of all that was taking place.
It is interesting as a side note
before we get into all of the punishment that is given here,
it would seem that as we look at verse number 25
of Genesis chapter number 10,
and I made note of this last week,
the Bible tells us, and unto Eber were born two sons,
the name of the one was Peleg,
for in his days was the earth divided,
and his brother's name was Joctan.
And as we look at that phrase in verse number 25
with regard to Peleg, the Bible says,
in his days was the earth divided.
It's important for us to understand
a little bit of what's going on here
from a timeline perspective.
Why do we say that?
Because of a phrase that is given in verse number six,
we want to make sure that we have
a proper understanding of this.
Notice the Bible says in verse number six of Genesis 11,
and the Lord said, behold, the people is one
and they all have one language.
And this they begin to do.
Notice, and now nothing will be restrained from them
which they have imagined to do.
Now you understand that that is not God saying
that they could do something beyond the ability
for God to restrain them.
God is very able to restrain mankind.
He is all power.
He is the omnipotent one.
And so it's not a reference to the fact
that mankind was in this place of a unified agenda
that was not going to be able to be restrained from God.
Rather, as we would look at the timeline of what's going on
and we think about a godly influence,
not only through Noah, but through the sons of Shem,
and the inability of those, that godly influence
to have an impact upon this wicked agenda
that is being planned here in Genesis 11,
verses three and four.
There's this wicked agenda that's going forth.
Now, we understand that the reality is that,
well, let me back up and say this.
In Genesis chapter number 10, we see that the Bible tells us
that it was in the days of Peleg that the earth was divided.
Now, go further into Genesis chapter 11 with me,
and let me read.
I'm gonna get into this passage
in a couple of Sunday nights,
but let me begin reading in verse number 10.
We'll deal with the entirety in a couple of weeks,
but notice this.
It says, these are the generations of Shem.
Shem was 100 years old and began,
our facts add, two years after the flood.
Now, notice that, two years, right?
It's important that we note that,
two years after the flood.
Notice in verse number 11,
and Shem lived after he began.
Arphaxad 500 years begat sons and daughters and then Arphaxad lived 5 and 30 years, right?
And so we see that's 35 years after but there were two years
So now we're what we're 37 years after the flood you follow the timeline
So we're 37 years after the flood according to verse number 12
He lived after he begat Sela
403 years begat sons and daughters notice verse 14 and Sela lived 30 years and begat Eber now 30 years plus
37 is 67 right? We're good keeping track 67 years after the flood according to verse number 14
Verse number 15 Sela lived after he begat Eber 403 years
We got sons and daughters Eber lived 4 and 30 years and begat Peleg
So 4 and 30 years plus 67 years is 101 years. I do the math, right you mathematicians. We're good
Amen, so we're 101 years after the flood when Peleg was born
The Bible tells us in chapter number 10 in verse number 25 and his days was the earth divided
And so he was born a hundred and one years after the flood
The Bible tells us if you continue to read in the passage of Scripture in verse number 17 and Eber lived after he begat Peleg
430 years and begat sons and daughters
And then it tells us in verse number 18 and Peleg lived 30 years begat Reu and Peleg lived after we got Reu
209 years. So the total lifespan of Peleg is
239 years. Are you tracking? We're good. How do we get 239 years in verse 19?
You're looking like you're not good
209 years after he begat Reu and he was 30 years old and begat Reu and according to verse number 18
All right, we're good 239 years
So if he was born a hundred and one years after the flood and he died when he was 239, how old was he?
Or how many years sorry after the flood he died he was doing during now when he died not a trick question
How many years post flood are we?
340 right? We're 340 years post flood. We track in how many years did Noah live after the flood?
Interesting right look at the end of chapter number 9 chapter 9 in verse 28 and Noah lived after the flood
350 years
So it seemed very obvious that Noah was alive during this account of the Tower of Babel
I'm pretty confident that Noah would not have been supportive of their agenda
Okay, we don't see any reference in here of Noah's interaction
in fact
At the end of chapter 9 is the last that we see in recorded scripture of any real specifics with regard to the life of Noah
But we find that I will tell us that he lived
350 years after the flood if these events that we're looking at of the Tower of Babel if this took place
after the flood by
340 years at the most right because that's when Peleg died
340 years after the flood it says that it was in the days that the earth was divided in the days of Peleg
And so therefore it could be anywhere
Prior to 340, but definitely not further than 340 years
So therefore Noah was alive. No doubt. We find that he would not have been supportive of this agenda
Perhaps even as he was remember Noah was known as being what a preacher of righteousness, right?
Noah preached before the flood did he not we find that he was a preacher and he was
Preaching and we understand that people weren't responding to the message
And it was just Noah and his wife as three sons and their wives that got on the ark
We find that he was a faithful preacher
And so we find that as we begin to look at what's taking place here in chapter number
11 and verse number 6 the Bible says that nothing will be restrained from them, which they have imagined to do
I believe is in my as I begin to look at this begin to consider all that's taking place to begin to
Think about some that would be crying out
Maybe Noah and others of that godly line that would be crying out against the plan of this
Agenda that is going forth by Nimrod and these within Babel of all that's taking place
And yet we find that they were being drowned out
They were not being listened to and of course we find that even as we begin to study New Testament Christianity
We begin to understand the church age if we begin to look at what the Bible tells us
Let me make a mention to 2nd Thessalonians and let's look at this verse real quick and 2nd Thessalonians chapter number 2
in 2nd Thessalonians chapter number 2
We find that the Bible is giving some truth here with regard
To the last days these believers in Thessalonica had been deceived with regard
to the day of the Lord and some things that had been taking place and we find
That as we come into the second chapter here of the book of 2nd Thessalonians and verse number 5
Paul says remember ye not that when I was with you yet with you
I told you these things and now you know what withhold it that he might be revealed in his time for the mystery of iniquity
Doth already work
Only he who now let us will let until he be taken out of the way verse number 7 is
Referring to the Holy Spirit of God
When it talks about only he who now let us will let we think about the restraining power of the Holy Spirit of God
And it talks about this in in verse number 7 the mystery of iniquity doth already work and then it tells us in verse Marie
and then
shall that
wicked be revealed whom the Lord shall consume with the spirit of his mouth and shall destroy with the brightness of his coming if you
Look back in verses 3 and 4 of this same passage
You begin to see that he's talking about the midpoint of the tribulation
When the son of perdition should be revealed and so on and so forth and we can look back in Daniel 9 and see how all
of that
Maps out as being the midpoint of the tribulation. And so why do I make this reference?
Well, the reality is that there's a plan the mystery of iniquity doth already work
But as the church is here and as we are filled with the Holy Spirit of God and doing the work of God
There is a restraining power to what the wicked is able to accomplish
But we know that the wicked is against God. We understand that we understand their plan, right? It's a humanistic mindset
It's an agenda that is void of any reference to God any need for God, but we understand that man needs God, right?
we understand that man has been created in the image of God that
The that not only is God the creator
But he is the Redeemer of mankind and just as we'd find in Romans chapter number one
We don't time to go there this evening. We would find that they seek to
Come to a place where they can deny the existence of God so that they are not accountable to God as
We look back in Genesis chapter 11 begin to see this punishment and I begin to understand that this is very
Interesting when we see the power of God and you see what's happening now
I don't know the timeline exactly of how long or how far they got into their building process
but just in your sanctified imagination this evening just know that there's somewhere in the process of
Building this city and this tower and they're doing this work. They're they're making the brick. They're
Burning them through Lee. They have the slime from order. They're doing this again
I don't know how far into the process they are
We find that God is aware of what man is doing and we find that God's plan is
Simple and effective and it just makes me laugh. I mean God is so powerful
man is so
finite right and God is so
infinite begin to think about all of this plan of man and what they're doing here in battle and we're gonna do this and we're
Gonna do that. We're gonna make a name and it's like God's like I can just do one simple little thing and it all comes
To naught the power of God. It's such a listen. He doesn't destroy them
He could have we see what happened with the flood, right?
He doesn't destroy them, but we find that the plan is a simple yet effective plan notice in verse number seven
go to
Let us go down and there confound their language that they may not understand one another's
speech
Now, can you imagine I mean again my sanctified imagination, right? This is comical to me
Because I'm thinking in my sanctified imagination. We all ended work on Thursday afternoon evening
We finished up we got our much of the project done that we got done. We go home. We'll see in the morning
Here's the plan for tomorrow. We have all of this sort of thing. We get up Friday morning
We come to the job site and we can't understand each other
Would that be frustrating
Have you ever tried to talk to somebody that you couldn't speak their language and they couldn't speak your language
Have you come on it's frustrating
right
You you get on the phone
I remember the very first time and when I was in the corporate world the very first time I had to deal with a customer
That was from a foreign country and they were speaking as much English as they knew and I met you it was three words
And I had no idea where they were coming from what their language was and I was just all sorts of messed up and I
remember sitting in the office and I was talking extremely slow and
Extremely loud and I just kept saying the same and I just kind of smacked myself afterwards
I said it really doesn't matter how slow or how loud I speak if they don't understand English. They don't understand English, right?
It's just not gonna happen and you're trying to communicate
frustrating
Becky was telling us a story when they were here a couple of weeks ago
about when they moved to England and they were trying to get their power turned on and they were going through the process and
Shane came home from work and said so did you get everything taken care of with the power company? She said I think so
He's like, what do you mean you think so? She said I have no idea what they said on the phone
She said in fact as we were talking I said
I know that you're speaking English and so am I and I should understand you but I don't
They were both speaking English and they couldn't understand each other because of an accent
Shane in his
man style and I say that ma n n
We can handle this like just give me five minutes and I'll take care of this and make a phone call
All right, and Shane got on the phone. He's like, honey. I have no idea what they're saying
This is kind of comical, but can you imagine?
Going to the job site. I mean these people again. I don't know how long they had been working on the project
I don't know how long this has been going on the scriptures don't tell us but no doubt
They're somewhere into the project. They'd been working and they show up at the job site and now they can't communicate
God's plan is simple. It's very effective
We find that it resulted in the bit in the in the human beings being scattered, you notice in verse number eight
So the Lord scattered them abroad from thence upon the face of all the earth and they left off to build the city
It is estimated today
And really you can look at some different things as to the number of languages that are that out there today
Conservatively, it's about 6,500 languages. That's a lot of languages
I'm not a linguist in any shape way shape or form
Languages are not my gift being able to learn a language is not very simple for me
And I have tried and maybe I just need to put forth more effort
but I understand that out of these nearly 6,500 languages that many linguists as they would begin to
Dive in and to begin looking at languages and historical aspects and the origins of language and all that sort of thing
They typically look back to three main root languages and again, I'm not a linguist
I'm not into the study of linguistics, but I did do some research to just get some of those those ideas of where
The the secular linguists look to and where they kind of track things back
Of course, they deny Babel as being the existence of the source of the confounding of languages
it is quite interesting how that their study though reveals the
accuracy of what we read in the scriptures of Genesis chapter 11 in fact an
evolutionary mind view comes up very sure on explaining the origin of languages and
They have a very difficult time being able to understand how
Languages developed over the time over the history so on and so forth
And so we find that God's plan was very simple and yet it was super effective
We find that as we notice in verse number eight, they're scattered
They were left off to build the city verse number nine. Therefore is the name of it called Babel
Because the Lord did there confound the language of all the earth and from thence did the Lord scatter them abroad
upon the face of all the earth
Now the Hebrew word Babel carries with it the meaning of confusion or to confuse and we understand that based upon the languages
And the confusion of the languages the Babylonians prefer to use their meaning of the word
What is most acceptable to them and they define that it would mean the gate of God or the gate to God and that's very
Interesting is we're going to see the different worldviews in the different perspective and really a polytheistic
Perspective we begin to look at the Babylonians and all of their idols and what-have-you
Throughout the history and you begin to notice as we look at our passage of scripture this plan
that man had then they had this plan and they devised it and they had put it into motion and they were
moving forward and God comes and he simply
scatters them by
Changing confounding their language notice with me this thought
It really reminds us of how frail we really are
right
You know, one of the things has been interesting to me
During this pandemic that we've been dealing with over a number of months now is it reminds me of how frail
mankind is
It reminds me of how interconnected we are as a globe really a small world
with regard to all of the
Simple transmission from one continent to another but we understand the frailty of man and were reminded of the power of God
As we begin to think about this that happened at the Tower of Babel and how immediate it was
God just simply said I'm gonna go down and I'm gonna confound their languages BAM done
turn over to Revelation chapter 18 if you will I
Mentioned that we would make a few notes here of some things that are going on here in Revelation 17 and 18
We don't have time to have an in-depth study of these particular chapters
But we find that in chapter number 17
we would deal with really as we would describe it religious Babylon and really the the impact from a religious perspective and
The blasphemy that would come forth from Babylon and then you look at chapter 18 and commercial Babylon
And all that's taken place there
But I want you to look at something that is mentioned in Revelation 18 and verse number 10
The Bible says this standing afar off for the fear of her torment saying alas alas
the great city Babylon that mighty city
Notice this phrase for in one hour is thy judgment come
The Bible had said in verse number two and they cried
he cried mightily with a strong voice saying Babylon the great is fallen is fallen and has become the
habitation of devils and the hold of every foul spirit and a cage of every unclean and
Hateful bird and so we find here that the Bible says here about in one hour is thy judgment come
Remember in Genesis chapter 11 the judgment came quick. It was swift
God just said here's what I'm gonna do. God's plan was simple. It was effective
notice with me even with the power that is seen in Revelation 17 and 18 of
religious and commercial Babylon in the system in which it
Represents you would find and be reminded if you turn back to Daniel chapter number five of the truth that this happened once before
in Daniel chapter number five
We are understanding of a great feast that takes place though
Shazar is the king if you look in Daniel 5 in verse number 1
The Bible says that Belshazzar the king made a great feast to a thousand of his Lords and drank wine before the thousand
There's this great feast that's going on
And we begin to and we don't have time to look at the entirety of Daniel chapter number five
But we really find that the Babylonians they had
Believed that they were a city that though they had been under siege that they would not be conquered because of the amount of
supply that they were able to have his
historians tell us that many believe that they had nearly 20 years worth of supply for them to be able to live on and
The river Euphrates went right through the city. And so therefore they had water
They had some level of understanding of that that provision that would be there for them
And we find that the Bible tells us that as they're having this great feast
It says in verse number five in the same hour
Came forth fingers of a man's hand and wrote over against the candlestick upon the plaster the wall of the king's palace and the king
Saw the part of the hand that wrote
The Bible tells us the king's countenance was changed and his thoughts troubled him
So the joints of his loins were loosed and his knees smote one against another they were here about that
You know that phraseology of your knees. You're so nervous. Your knees are knocking together
Well, there's Belshazzar as he sees this hand upon the wall writing if you fast-forward through the end
We don't have time to look at the all of it
But notice in verse number 30 in verse number 31 the Bible tells us in that night
was Belshazzar the king of the Chaldeans slain and
Darius the Median took the kingdom being about three score and two years old
What did they do? Well, they blocked up the Euphrates River and diverted it and they came through on the riverbed
Historically, that's what they did
You begin to think about the fact that these things that we read of in the scriptures when you read in
Revelation 17 and 18 you begin to see about in one hour
Thy judgment has come and you can sometimes say man. How is that gonna happen? Because God is so mighty and
man is so fragile and
here in Genesis chapter 11 that truth is revealed to us and
Reminded of though man would devise their plan that God has all power
One final passage that I want to share with you this evening before we close. It's in the book of Psalms in Psalm chapter number 2
Psalm chapter number 2
Remember this plan of these in Babel it was a plan that was void it was void of any
Inclusion of God they did not seek the face of God. They did not include God in their plans
In fact, they were in rebellion to God
We would say that as they sought to make a name for themselves and elevate man that it was a humanistic
Perspective and we find in Psalm chapter number 2 the Bible says why do the heathen rage?
And the people imagine a vain thing the kings of the earth set themselves and the rulers take counsel together
against the Lord and against his anointed saying
Let us break their bands asunder and cast away their cords from us. Notice this he that sitteth in the heavens
shall laugh
The Lord shall have them in derision
Inderision then shall he speak unto them in his wrath and vex them in his
sore
displeasure
just a spoken word, the power of our God. We could continue looking and through
the passage and see some of that which is given, but we see that the
opposition to the Almighty God is really laughable. He that sitteth in the heaven
shall laugh and the Lord shall have them in derision. The very last revolt that we
read of in the Word of God is given to us at the end of chapter, really not the
very end, really the middle of chapter number 20 of the book of Revelation.
Remember during that period of time Satan is bound and then he'll be
bound during the millennial reign of Christ for that thousand years, but then
Satan is loosed for a little season. And as Satan is loosed for a little season, he
gathers up, there's this revolt against God. It's interesting as we would think
about the number of those that would revolt. The Bible says that their number
was as the sand of the sea, but God simply deals with this very quickly in
Revelation 20 and verse number 9. It says that they went up on the breadth of the
earth and compassed the camp of the saints about in the beloved city and
fire came down from God out of heaven and devoured them. Listen, God is never
going to be conquered. He's never going to be defeated. He is the Lord God
Almighty. He is King of kings, Lord of lords. Man, as we see even pre-flood, but
now as we look at post-flood, man in his plan has often sought under the
influence of satanic powers to make a plan void of God. Humanism. We see it in
Genesis chapter 11. We find that God very simply and quite effectively dealt with
the situation there at Babel, and he had them scattered. He confused their
languages. We find that as those family groups would leave, as we find that it's
recorded in Genesis chapter number 10, as that genealogy is provided that they
left and they were divided, that God was accomplishing his purpose. And again,
as we mentioned last week, as we begin to finish the 11th chapter, we won't deal
with it next week. Lord willing, we'll have our service outside next week. But
as we get back into Genesis on the following Sunday evening, we'll find that
at the end of chapter 11, God once again gives us the genealogy of the son of Noah,
Shem. We read part of that this evening, and takes us directly to Abraham. And
from there, throughout the remainder of scripture, we begin to see how that God
is dealing with the nation of Israel, with Abraham calling him out, the
Abrahamic Covenant, and all of those details that go forward. And you find
that scripture focuses in upon that line, which is the Messianic line. Of course, we
see, as one has said, it was, I believe, William Scroggie is the man that said
this, that the Bible, he referred to it as the unfolding drama of redemption. And
certainly that is the case. Let's pray together. Father, we love you. We thank
you for loving us. We thank you for the passage that is before us this evening,
for the opportunity that you've given us to study it and to see, really, the
historical account of what's taking place. But then even as we look at
scripture, compare scripture with scripture, we understand that this
account that is there in Genesis 11 is something that has been repeated
throughout the history of mankind, no doubt will be repeated again, even in the
last times, even during the tribulations we see in Revelation 17 and 18. And we
find that this thought of humanism, this practice of man seeking to make a
name for himself and living apart from God in resistance to God, Lord, that
that is a day and age in which we live. I pray that you would help us, as your
people, to be dependent upon thee. Help us to rely upon thee. Help us to understand
the importance of walking with thee. And Lord, help us to be bold in taking a
message that is not always well received in this particular day and age, but help
us to take the message of the gospel to a lost and dying world, that people will
understand that one day they will stand before the Lord God Almighty, the Creator,
and we thank you that you are our Redeemer. We pray that you'd bless this
time of invitation. We'll thank you for all that you'll do, for it's in
Christ's name we pray. Amen. Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are
closed. Kimberly's gonna play quietly on the piano. Maybe just want to thank God
for his plan and for the opportunity to be able to study his word and for the
privilege of being able to share the truth. As Kimberly plays, the altar is
open.