Psalm 62 this morning, Psalm 62, I'll be looking at the entirety of the psalm.
I just want to read a few verses by way of introduction, and then we'll get right into
the message this morning.
Here in Psalm 62, I'll give you a moment to turn there, and Psalm 62, I love the book
of Psalms.
It's an encouraging book.
It's a book in which we can go to and we can be encouraged and strengthened.
We learn many things about our God and about His character, His attributes that are revealed
to us through the book of Psalms.
I believe that as you read and study through the book of Psalms and maybe make it a part
of your daily routine, that as you're reading the scriptures, you're reading other portions
of the scriptures, but maybe reading a portion from the book of Psalms as well, and it just
encourages you and strengthens you.
We also have the unique privilege of being able to see the transparency of the psalmist,
and I believe that's helpful for us because we find that the psalmist, though many of
the psalms are ascribed to David, he did not write all of them.
We understand that it's scripture, so it's given by inspiration of God, but we understand
that as David, in many of the psalms, he would pour his heart out before the Lord, and he
would reveal to us his transparency, and I believe that it helps us in our daily walk
with the Lord as well.
And this morning, as we look at this psalm, notice in verse number one of Psalm 62, the
Bible says, "'Truly, my soul waiteth upon God.
From Him cometh my salvation.'"
Notice this, "'He only.'"
Maybe that's an important word for you to underline or circle, "'He only is my rock
and my salvation.
He is my defense.
I shall not be greatly moved.'"
Skip down and look at verse number eight.
The Bible says, "'Trust in Him at all times, ye people.
Pour out your heart before Him.
God is a refuge for us, Selah.'"
I want you to notice that second phrase in verse number eight.
We'll use it as our title this morning, "'Pour out your heart before Him.
Pour out your heart before Him.'"
We do not know for sure the timing of the writing of this particular psalm.
We understand that the psalm is ascribed to David.
If in your Bible you have little notations above the psalms, you'll notice that it says
a psalm of David.
It's historically been ascribed to David as the human penman of this particular psalm.
We find that the timing of some of the psalms is very easy to identify and see what circumstances
and what have you David may be dealing with and going through at the particular moment
of writing the particular psalm.
It's not crystal clear here in Psalm 62 as to exactly the timing in which David was writing
this particular psalm.
However, we believe that as you study the Scriptures and study through here, that it
would seem obvious or evident that the psalm was written during the time, the period if
you will, of Absalom's rebellion.
You'll remember that Absalom is the son of David and that Absalom, because of some events
that had transpired and some things that had taken place, and he goes through a process
of really stealing the hearts of the people of God, and we find that in just a little
while after doing that and going through that process, there's a revolt that Absalom takes
and he's seeking to really dethrone his father and become the ruler of Israel.
We find that through that event or through those events that David flees and all that
takes place, and that's not really the thought of what we're going to be dealing with this
morning, but we can read of those accounts and the record of that in the book of 2 Samuel
and you can see all that transpires.
We understand that even if that is not the particular instance in which this psalm was
penned, we do know that there are plenty of times in the life of David in which he
dealt with adversity, that he dealt with difficulty.
You'll remember early on in his life as he was, after he had been selected by God and
anointed by Samuel the prophet to be the next king of Israel, you understand that he served
under the leadership of Saul, and God had rejected Saul from being king over his people.
But it was not yet time for David to become the king of Israel, and there was a period
of really proving and just development and all sorts of things that David was dealing
with, and during that time, during that season in David's life, he dealt with much opposition
and much adversity.
Saul himself tried to kill David.
Saul tried to employ his men to kill David.
He tried to use the Philistines to kill David.
He did everything he could to kill David, yet God spared his servant.
We find that David was a man that was acquainted with difficulty and adversity, and David
was a man that learned that in the middle of a storm, in the time of adversity and difficulty,
that God is dependable, that God is trustworthy, that we run to God.
And as we look here, of course, David was not perfect.
He's a human.
He didn't always do everything perfect.
We can read of sin in the life of David as it's recorded in the Word of God.
We can read in times in which he did not respond to adversity, maybe in the most appropriate
way, but I believe that through all of those circumstances, and even as we would learn,
remember, there was a time in which David went to the land of the Philistines.
Did he not?
I think David learned through that, and as he pens the words of this psalm, as we have
the opportunity to see the heart of the psalmist, not only to see the heart of the psalmist
but the attributes of our God.
I believe that this psalm will help us this morning.
You say, pastor, I'm not dealing with a storm.
Just file it away, honestly, because I'm telling you that a storm will come in your life.
A period of difficulty will come in your life.
And we look here at this psalm, I want you to consider with me, first of all, the experience
of the psalmist.
Consider in the first seven verses how David is really just sharing his experience and
that which he had dealt with in his life, and the reality this morning is that many
of us have experiences.
We have lived life for a certain period of time, a certain number of years, and we have
certain experiences that we've dealt with in life.
And we find that in these first seven verses that as David is really rehearsing his experiences
and he's dealing with some of the troubles in which he dealt with in life, he's reminding
us how he trusted God, how he depended upon the Lord.
Notice in verse number one, truly, I like the way the psalmist starts, truly my soul
waiteth upon God.
Can I say this morning, that can be the hardest part of your storm.
The waiting.
God, what are you trying to teach me?
How long is this going to last?
When is this going to end?
And we're waiting on God.
And we're waiting for God to show Himself real, what He's able to do and what His purpose
is in that time.
And the psalmist says, truly my soul waiteth upon God, from Him cometh my salvation.
Now you understand in the book of Psalms that oftentimes the word salvation is used in what
we would understand as deliverance.
Not so much always being dealt with of our soul's salvation, our redemption from the
penalty of sin, though there are times in which that's dealt with, but really as you
look at the psalm you'd understand that he's dealing with deliverance.
The deliverance that he receives from God.
And we understand from Him, from the Lord, from the Lord God Almighty, from Him cometh
my salvation, the deliverance.
Listen, we may not always see and understand exactly how He's delivering, but we understand
that as we look at our life and maybe as we look back at some events and some experiences
that we would be able to say with the psalmist, truly my soul waiteth upon God, from Him cometh
my salvation.
Notice verse 2, He only is my rock and my salvation.
He is my defense.
I shall not be greatly moved.
What of this morning?
Can we say in sincerity and honest this morning in verse number 2 that God is, He only is
my rock, my salvation, He is my defense?
Notice what he says when he understands these realities, when he's understood this experience
that he's had.
He says, I shall not be greatly moved.
I believe that David through his experience and the many experiences that he had in life,
I believe that he had been strengthened by God.
What a joy to receive the strength that God gives His children.
See, we are weak, but He is strong.
Paul said after he'd besought the Lord thrice that God would deliver him from that thorn,
that God says, my grace is sufficient for thee.
You can read of that in 2 Corinthians chapter number 12, and he talks about God's strength
being made perfect in our weakness.
Think about the psalmist being strengthened.
See, the reality is that there are times in our lives in which we think about physical
strength.
But you know it's important that the inner man is strengthened.
Corinthians chapter number four the Bible talks about we faint not as you
read through that passage of Scripture and you deal with all of the
tribulations and distresses and trials and troubles that they dealt with that
Paul is referring to why does he say we faint not because our inner man is
strengthened it's renewed day by day see David was strengthened notice verse
number three how long will you imagine mischief against a man you shall be
slain all of you as a bowing wall shall you be in as a tottering fence you
notice the imagery that he uses with regard to those that would bring trouble
in his life at the end of verse number three he uses the the imagery of a
bowing wall in a tottering fence the the lack of stability the lanket lack of
strength the only excuse me look at verse number four they only consult to
cast him down from his excellency they delight in lies they bless with their
mouth but they curse inwardly see law you understand that the enemy is
relentless and ruthless and as he speaks here about some of that which is taking
place you notice in verse number four they only consult to cast him down from
his excellency they delight in lies the way in which we understand that truth is
no longer held in high esteem as it should be he says that they bless with
their mouth but they curse inwardly see law is what David experienced but notice
what he says in verse number five it's interesting how kind of he uses verses
one and two in verses five through seven as book ends if you will to what he says
in verses three and four with regard to some of the difficulty notice in verse
number five my soul wait thou only upon God for my expectation is from him you
know sometimes we got to have a little self-talk you don't know I'm saying
notice where he says in verse number six and verse number one truly my soul wait
if upon God and then he says in verse number five my soul wait thou only upon
God you ever want to take things in your own hands you ever want to try to
expedite the process and say let me get through this thing a little bit faster
let me help you Lord let me deal with this I can deal with this person faster
God than you seem to be dealing with this person and we can get this
situation resolved David has declared in verse number one that he's waiting upon
God but in verse number five he says my soul wait now only upon God listen we
need to remind ourselves to wait upon the Lord again it's not the easy thing
to do most of us this morning waiting is one of the things we least like about
life they don't like to wait so these bells ringing anyone else hear that
sound like a church bell ringing amen we don't have a church bell but it's not
like a church bell was ringing listen for the trumpet amen whoo that'd be
exciting notice for my expectation is from him are you expecting God to work
honestly the psalmist says in Psalm 119 it is time for thee O Lord to walk it's
actually not with someone I teen it's a couple chapters before I can't remember
exactly what chapter right now but it's a couple chapters before but he says
it's time Lord for thee to work and let me actually read the verse I think it is
some night 119 and the Lord just brought on my mind let me see if I can find it
here look at verse number 126 you don't have to look there but just jot it down
Psalm 119 126 it is time for the Lord to work for they have made void thy law
are you expecting God to work he says my expectation is from him what are you
expecting God to do you understand this morning that as we pray we pray to a God
who's able to exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think according to
what we find in Ephesians 3 in verse number 20 he says to Jeremiah call unto
me and I will answer thee and show thee great mighty things which thou knowest
not the psalmist says as he would just reveal to us the experience that he's
had in life he says listen my expectation is from him by the way I
like it when God works I like it when God works in such a distinct way that
you cannot confuse it with the work of man that you cannot come to a place
where you'd say oh well that's how they figured this out and that's how they did
that in fact in Psalm 109 in verse number 26 the psalmist cries out and
says help me O Lord my God Oh save me according to thy mercy that they may
know that this is thy hand that thou Lord has done it oh man I love to see
God work are you expecting God to work in your life my expectation it's from
him notice verse 6 he says again what we read in verse number 2 he only is my
rock and my salvation he is my defense I shall not be moved verse 7 in God is my
salvation and my glory the rock of my strength and my refuge is in God we
consider the experience of the psalmist we find not only was he strengthened I
believe that he was delivered you know that David experienced deliverance in
his life on a number of occasions we can read not only as we think about the
context perhaps of the writing of this particular psalm with the revolt of
Absalom but if you think over that's near the end of David's life if you look
over the entirety of David's life and you think about the way in which God
delivered him from the hand of the enemy the way that God miraculously delivered
him out of the the evil intent of Saul the way that God delivered him from the
Philistines I mean over and over you see that David experienced deliverance and
in 1st Samuel 17 when he goes to fight against Goliath what does he say he
says listen this is what the God that created all things the God of Israel he
is going to give victory he is going to give thy servant victory and you
understand that he David had experienced the deliverance of God Almighty I
believe that the psalmist as he would rehearse and recount his experience that
not only was he strengthened and delivered I believe that he was
encouraged you know it's encouraging when you see God work it's encouraging
when you're aware of what God is doing in your life and how God is is working
and moving it's encouraging to know that we serve a God who makes no mistakes
that we serve a God who is perfect and that we serve a God who has a plan and
it's a perfect plan it's a plan in which you and I will be developed as a plan
in which he will be glorified what a joy what a blessing I believe David was
helped we need to be helped you know the psalmist cries out help Lord I mean
you just see the transparency of the psalmist and you find that as we would
consider the experience of the psalmist that perhaps we can relate to some of
that which he dealt with I mean not to the same extreme in which David dealt
with but we can we can relate to troubles and trials and we can relate to
storms in our lives and we consider the experience of the psalmist but then
number two we consider the encouragement from the psalmist you know it's
interesting when when when the psalmist has an experience when he rehearses
these experiences that he has he now is in a unique position to offer
encouragement to other people you know God will use us he'll allow us to
experience some things and then use us to help others that we come in contact
with 2nd Corinthians chapter number one the Apostle Paul is speaking to these
believers in in Corinth and of course it's the second letter that he writes
to them but in verse number three of 2nd Corinthians chapter number one we find
that Paul is going to give some some really unique truth that is helpful for
us as the people of God in verse number three says blessed be God even the
father of our Lord Jesus Christ the father of mercies and the God of all
comfort aren't you thankful that he's the God of all comfort it says in verse
number four who comforted us in all our tribulation that we may be able to
comfort them which are in any trouble by the comfort wherewith we ourselves are
comforted of God you know God will allow us to experience some things in
life and then as the psalmist here in Psalm 62 experience some things and
rehearses that now he's going to give some encouragement notice what he's
going to encourage in verse number eight he says trust in him all at all times
notices ye people so now he's not really dealing with his own experience he's now
giving this word of encouragement this word of admonition if you will to those
that would be the recipients those that would read the psalm those throughout
the centuries including us this morning that have preserved in the perfect Word
of God this psalm that we can go to and we can be helped in David as he would
encourage the people he says number one trust in him at all times we believe
that every word of God
God is pure.
Amen?
He could have just said, trust in Him.
But I like the fact that he says,
at all times.
At all times.
Because the reality is that there are
some times in our lives
where the difficulty can almost become
so overpowering,
so difficult what we're dealing with in life,
that we find that this truth
in the very words of Scripture
would remind us that at all times,
in every circumstance,
in every situation that you face in life,
trust in Him.
You know, our God is trustworthy.
He is faithful.
He is dependable.
We think about the faithfulness of our God
when we think about the way
in which He has proven His character
and His attributes over and over.
Our God wants us to trust Him.
He wants us to exercise faith.
He that cometh to God must believe that He is.
It says there right before that,
without faith it is impossible to please Him.
For he that cometh to God must believe that He is
and a rewarder of them that diligently seek Him.
God asks Moses in the book of Numbers
after the spies go out
and they come back with that evil report
in Numbers 14,
God says to Moses,
how long will it be ere My people believe Me?
That they'll trust Me?
And you think about the way in which God
had proven Himself to that particular generation.
The mighty works that they saw
in the land of Egypt
and the mighty hand of God
in delivering His people from Egyptian bondage.
The miraculous deliverance across the Red Sea
and just the provision,
the manna and the water.
I mean, what amazing things
these people have experienced.
But when those ten spies say,
hey listen, the people that dwell in this land,
they're giants and the cities are fortified
and they have walls.
Well, we're not able to do it.
We begin to doubt.
God says how long will it be ere My people believe Me?
David here, as he would encourage the people,
and he says here,
trust in Him at all times.
You know, we are familiar with the truth
of Proverbs 3, verses 5 and 6
where the Bible says in that passage of Scripture,
trust in the Lord, how?
With all thine heart.
And it says lean not unto thine own understanding.
I'm not going to ask you to raise your hand,
but I would believe this morning
that if you would be honest,
leaning on our own understanding
is a challenge that we deal with.
We lean on our own understanding.
We try to analyze and figure things out
and we begin to lean on our own understanding
and so that's why we find in Proverbs,
trust in the Lord with all thine heart.
David says trust in Him at all times.
The good times.
The bad times.
See, life has a way of just kind of changing
and various things that happen
and circumstances that come our ways.
But who are we trusting?
Who are we trusting?
David says trust Him at all times.
Notice the encouragement,
not only trust in Him at all times,
but notice v. 8.
We've used it as our title this morning.
Pour out your heart before Him.
In your sanctified imagination,
in your mind's eye,
what do you see when you read those words?
Pour out your heart before Him.
I mean, you know,
God invites us to cast our burden upon Him.
God invites us to cast our care upon Him.
You look at Psalm 55 and v. 22.
You look at 1 Peter 5 and v. 7.
There's a reference in the Old and New Testament
about casting our burden,
casting our cares upon the Lord
knowing that He'll sustain us,
knowing that He cares for us.
And in my mind's eye when I read
pour out your heart before Him,
I see somebody that is just weeping
and pouring out their heart before God Almighty.
I mean, do you ever feel that way in life?
Do you ever feel like you just want to pour your heart out?
Sometimes we pour it out to the wrong people.
Sometimes we pick up the phone
and pour out our heart to a neighbor,
a family member, maybe to our spouse.
But I wonder this morning,
have we poured out our heart to God Almighty?
I mean, really just get into the quietness of our time.
Listen, God knows anyway.
But He wants us to verbalize it.
He wants us to come to Him
and to pour out our heart before Him.
See, God knows if you're struggling.
He knows if you're confused.
He knows if you just don't seem to
understand what He's doing.
He knows our frame.
He knows that we're but dust.
He says, pour out your heart.
Man, there are times that you can get alone with God.
Just pour out your heart.
And know that He loves you.
See, I can pour out my heart to Armando
and he might judge me.
Right?
Armando can pour out his heart to me
and he might be fearful that I'd use him
as an illustration from the pulpit,
which I never would do.
But you know there are pastors that do that kind of stuff.
What I'm saying is that we pour out our heart before God.
Man, if Armando pours out his heart to me
or I to him,
he's not going to be able to help me
and I can't help him the way that God
could help either one of us.
So the psalmist says,
pour out your heart before Him.
Notice in 1 Samuel 1.
It would have been easier to preach from Colossians 2
this morning, amen?
God just impressed this portion of Scripture
upon my heart this week.
I hope it helps somebody.
Verse 10 of 1 Samuel 1.
We're familiar with Hannah.
She was barren. She had no children.
If you understand some of the cultural implications
of that in this particular era,
it's a real heavy burden to have no children.
I mean, a major, major burden.
The Bible says in v. 10
that she was in bitterness of soul,
but look what it says,
and prayed unto the Lord and wept sore.
So much so that the Bible says in v. 11
that she vowed a vow and said,
O Lord of hosts,
if Thou wilt indeed look on the affliction
of Thine handmaid and remember me
and not forget Thine handmaid,
but will give unto Thine handmaid a man-child,
then I will give him unto the Lord
all the days of his life,
and there shall no razor come upon his head.
And it came to pass as she continued praying
before the Lord that Eli marked her mouth."
Eli sees she's praying here.
She's pouring out her heart before God.
Verse 13 says that now Hannah,
she spake in her heart,
only her lips moved,
but her voice was not heard.
Therefore, Eli thought she had been drunken.
He reached a wrong conclusion.
In v. 14, he says unto her,
How long wilt thou be drunken?
Put away thine wine from thee.
I wish he would have talked to his sons
the way that he talked to her.
That's a completely different subject matter.
But notice what she says in v. 15.
Hannah answered and said,
No, my Lord.
I am a woman of a sorrowful spirit.
I have drunk neither wine nor strong drink,
but have poured out my soul before the Lord.
You know what's amazing?
That v. 17 says that Eli answers her
and said, Go in peace.
The God of Israel grant thee thy petition
that thou hast asked of Him.
That's how far God is able to answer prayer.
He does answer prayer.
It's not just that He's able to answer prayer.
He does.
I've experienced in my life.
You've experienced in your life
how God answers prayer.
And here we find that Hannah,
she's pouring out her heart before the Lord,
and we find that in v. 20, it says,
Wherefore it came to pass,
when the time was come about
after Hannah had conceived
that she bear a son,
and called his name Samuel,
because I have asked him of the Lord.
She fulfilled her vow.
And I want you to just notice in v. 21,
the Bible says that the Lord visited Hannah
so that she conceived and bare three sons
and two daughters.
The child Samuel grew before the Lord.
God blessed her.
She poured out her heart before God.
I wonder this morning, as we read Psalm 62,
as we have noted the experience of the psalmist,
but then we see how that he would encourage the people.
He says, listen, trust in him at all times, ye people.
Pour out your heart before him.
Maybe this morning, one or many of us,
we just need to pour out our heart before God.
I mean, just get along with God.
Just talk to Him about the troubles,
the difficulties that you're dealing with.
Maybe there's a trouble in your home.
Maybe it's a relational trouble
that no one else knows about,
but you know about it.
Maybe there's trouble with a spouse.
Maybe there's trouble with children.
I just don't know what to do with these kids.
You ever been there? Amen.
If I could just, and you don't fill in the blank, right?
Because you don't want to just whatever.
Lord, I need help.
God created your son and daughter.
He can give you wisdom.
Maybe there's some older folks
that maybe you've got a child that's just wayward.
They're just away from God.
That's heavy.
You say, man, my heart is burdened.
Maybe you've got a loved one that's lost.
You say, man, God, I just want them to be saved.
You know that God wants them to be saved
more than you want them to be saved.
He's not willing that any should perish,
but that all should come to repentance.
Maybe there's a problem in your job.
Maybe there's a financial crisis that you're facing.
Maybe there's a health crisis that you're dealing with.
I don't know, but God knows.
Just pour it out before Him.
The psalmist gives good encouragement.
It's an admonition really, instruction.
He's encouraging the people.
Trust God.
Pour out your heart before Him.
Notice, not only do we consider the experience
and the encouragement,
but consider the explanation from the psalmist.
He's going to explain really,
not only from his own experience why he does this,
why he trusts in the Lord at all times,
why he would pour out his heart before God,
but he reveals to us and gives us explanation
as to why we should do that as well.
Notice the end of verse number eight.
God is a refuge for us.
Selah.
We've noted already a couple of times in this psalm
that the word selah is used in verse number four,
and then here in verse number eight,
and we notice throughout the book of psalms
that the word selah will be used regularly.
We understand what it means.
Stop.
Chew on it.
Meditate upon it.
Allow it to sink into your heart and your soul.
Understand the truth that God is revealing to you here.
Why should we trust in Him at all times?
Why should I pour out my heart before Him?
Well, number one, because He's a refuge for us.
I'm thankful that God was a refuge for David,
but God's a refuge for me and He's a refuge for you.
God is no respecter of persons.
He says that all throughout His Word.
And I'm so thankful that He's no respecter of persons
and that He, as we are His children,
as we have entered into a relationship
with the God of the universe
because of the sacrifice of the Lord Jesus Christ
on the cross of Calvary,
and I'm His child,
and if you've been saved, you're His child.
God is a refuge for us.
A shelter.
Protection from danger or distress.
You get that imagery in your mind
of God being that shelter for you,
that refuge for you.
Oh, what a blessing.
What an encouragement for us.
And as we find the explanation,
as David is saying here in this passage of Scripture,
what he's experiencing and encouraging others
to follow in like suit,
he's saying to them,
listen, God is a refuge for us.
Don't forget that.
Don't neglect,
as you go through the trials and troubles
and storms of life,
don't forget that in the midst of that storm
that we have a refuge and His name is Jesus.
We run to Him.
We get help.
We get protection.
Not only does the psalmist share with us
that God is our refuge,
in verses 9 and 10,
he really tries to give us a little explanation
of things that we could trust in
and that we ought not trust in.
So he says,
trust in Him at all times in verse 8,
but look at verses 9 and 10.
Surely men of low degree are vanity
and men of high degree are a lie.
To be laid in the balance,
they are altogether lighter than vanity.
Trust not in oppression
and become not vain in robbery.
If riches increase,
set not your heart upon them.
Listen, we ought not trust in man.
We ought not trust in riches.
Amen?
And the reality is that we understand
that he says trust in Him at all times in verse 8,
and then in verses 9 and 10,
he really shares with us
and with his audience there
originally when it's written,
he helps us understand that listen,
it's easy sometimes for us to trust in other people.
It's easy for us to trust in riches.
We live in one of the wealthiest counties
in all of America.
It doesn't mean that we're the wealthiest
of all of America,
but we just happen to live
in one of the wealthiest counties
in all of America.
But you understand there's a lot of people
in our community that are trusting in riches.
A lot of people in our world
that are trusting in riches.
Right?
He says listen, don't trust in man.
The help of man is vain.
God is our refuge.
Don't put your trust in man.
Man will fail you.
Trust in Him.
Don't trust in riches.
You know that riches can fail.
They make wings.
They fly away.
That's what the Bible says.
We find here that He's helping us understand
God is our refuge.
Notice in verse number 11
as He will give some further explanation.
God hath spoken once,
twice have I heard this,
that power belongeth unto God.
Not only is He going to explain to us
why we should trust in Him at all times
and why we should pour our heart out before Him.
Number one, because God is our refuge.
Number two, because God is omnipotent.
Power belongeth unto God.
Aren't you thankful for the power of God?
You know it's amazing when you read
throughout the Word of God.
I mean, you don't get long into the first chapter
of the book of Genesis
and you read about the power of God Almighty.
And you read throughout the pages of Scripture
and you read about the ways
in which God Almighty has displayed His power.
He's demonstrated His power.
Oh, it's a great joy and great benefit
that we have plenty of Scripture verses
that we can go to
to read how that God declares
that He has all power.
That there's nothing too difficult for Him
and He shares those truths with us,
but what a joy it is to not only know
that He's declared it,
but to know that He's proved it.
He's demonstrated it over and over and over.
You understand this morning
that the Lord God omnipotent reigneth.
He reigns.
He has all power.
I don't know what to do.
I mean, this situation is too...
It's not too big for God.
It's not too hard for God
because nothing's too hard for God.
And so the psalmist says,
listen, God is our refuge.
Listen, God is omnipotent.
He has all power.
The thing that we can't seem to figure out,
that storm that we're enduring,
that storm that you might encounter,
you understand that God has power over that storm.
He has purpose in that storm.
We find that here we are reminded
of the power of God,
that power belongeth unto God.
Jesus said when He gave the Great Commission
as it's recorded in Matthew,
chapter number 28,
all power is given unto Me
in heaven and in earth.
Not some power,
not most power,
but all power is given unto Me.
Our God is the mighty God,
the all-powerful, omnipotent God.
We have the privilege of knowing Him
and serving Him and trusting Him
and watching Him work
in ways that can only be explained
that God did it.
Notice verse number 12.
Also unto Thee, O Lord,
belongeth mercy,
for Thou renderest to every man
according to his work.
I'm so thankful that our God is merciful.
Our God is merciful.
We read throughout the pages of Scripture
about the mercies of God.
We read as you would study
the Word of God,
and really in the book of Psalms
as we've mentioned already,
how that you have the opportunity
to read about the attributes of God
and also the transparency of the psalmist.
You'll find many times throughout
the book of Psalms that God talks about His mercy.
His mercy endureth forever.
I'm so thankful that our God is merciful.
It's here that in Lamentations chapter 3,
if you want to turn there,
it's kind of interesting if you note it
on our bulletin this morning,
those of you that are watching live stream.
Of course, you didn't get one.
But on the front it says,
His compassions fail not.
A reference to this portion of Scripture
in Lamentations chapter 3.
Lamentations right after the book of Jeremiah.
I always like it when those guest speakers
say it's after Genesis and before Revelation.
Very helpful for you to find the book
that they're referring to.
Lamentations right after the book of Jeremiah.
Notice what Jeremiah will say
in verse 21.
This I recall to my mind.
Therefore, have I hope.
That's kind of interesting.
If you're familiar with the book of Lamentations,
you understand that Jeremiah lamenting
over the destruction of Jerusalem
and the captivity by the Babylonians
of the nation of Judah.
You read through all of that
in the book of Jeremiah,
and you read all that takes place.
In fact, you read the first couple of chapters
of the book of Lamentations.
You can see the weeping and the lamenting
because of all of the things that have taken place,
but we find it in verse 21 of chapter 3
that he says, this I recall to my mind.
Therefore, have I hope.
Notice verse 22.
It is of the Lord's mercies
that we are not consumed
because His compassions fail not.
They are new every morning.
Great is thy faithfulness.
Aren't those some precious verses of God's Word?
He says, when I recall this to my mind,
I have hope.
I have this expectation.
I receive this comfort.
And we find this morning
that as David would rehearse for us
and he would share some of his experience
and then he would give some encouragement
that listen, when you're dealing
with some adversity, some trouble,
some storms in your life,
trust in Him at all times.
Pour out your heart before Him.
Why?
Because God is your refuge.
Because God has all power.
Why?
Because God is merciful.
I mean, those are three really good reasons
that would lead the people of God
to trust God
and to pour out my heart before Him.
And he gives them this explanation.
And I believe that as we think about
the explanation that he provides,
perhaps we could even call it evidence
as to why we should follow
in the same pattern in which David followed.
Why we should pour out our heart before Him.
This morning,
perhaps you're in the midst of a storm.
I said it in the beginning of the message.
I don't know who coined the phrase.
You're either in the middle of a storm,
you've come through a storm,
or there's a storm on the horizon.
And we know that in life,
there are storms that we encounter.
And it just may be that today,
you're in the midst of a storm.
I mean, maybe no one will even know it.
You come in to church,
we know how to put on,
kind of, you know what I mean?
Maybe you're dealing with something that,
man, maybe the people in your home
don't even know about it.
You're just carrying a burden.
Just struggling in the middle of a storm.
What do we do?
If we're overwhelmed by these circumstances of life,
if we are in the midst of a storm,
what do we do?
Trust Him at all times.
Know that God's way is perfect.
You say, well, pastor, you don't understand.
This thing that I'm dealing with.
No, no, no.
You don't understand God.
And I don't say that without sympathy or compassion.
I say that because there are some storms
that we deal with in life,
but it's not that we have to understand the storm.
We have to understand the God of the storm.
We have to understand that He has a purpose,
a plan.
He always does that which is right.
Always.
He never makes a mistake.
So trust Him.
But then can I encourage you?
Pour out your heart before Him.
I mean, honestly.
It'll do you well.
It really will.
To just get along with God.
It doesn't matter how long it takes.
God doesn't, aren't you thankful?
He's not like, Brother Michael, I'm sorry.
He's not like a lawyer.
I'm sorry.
He doesn't start that clock.
You know, as soon as he picks up the phone,
the lawyer wants to start that little clock
to start billing you.
God doesn't put us on a timer.
Listen, if it takes you a few hours
to pour out your heart before Him,
it's okay.
It'll be good for you.
God knows all about it.
But I just believe that there's something
helpful for us as we pour out our heart before Him.
And just really get along with God.
This morning, I don't know what you're dealing with.
And to be real honest with you,
you don't know what I'm dealing with.
And I don't say that for anyone who gets in,
but I'm just saying we all deal with troubles.
We all have storms in life.
Amen?
What do we do?
How do we deal with it?
Psalm 61, the psalm just before
the psalm I preached from this morning.
It's interesting that you look at that particular psalm
and you can read some of the same things
that David is dealing with.
He says this in verse number two,
from the end of the earth will I cry unto thee
when my heart is overwhelmed.
Lead me to the rock that is higher than I.
Oh man, sometimes our heart is overwhelmed.
He says in verse number one of that psalm,
I can hear my cry,
but he says in verse number eight,
so will I sing praise unto thy name.
There's actually several psalms that you can go to
and you can look at and you can see
how that really the psalmist in chapter number 13
is a great one as well,
where you go from sadness to singing.
In fact, in Psalm 13,
the psalmist is struggling in another psalm
that's ascribed to David,
and he says, how long wilt thou forget me, O Lord?
Forever?
Do you ever feel that way?
David felt that way.
I mean, he's overwhelmed,
but then he says, I will sing unto the Lord
because he hath dealt bountifully with me in verse six.
We just need to pour our heart before God.
This morning, would you let God help you?
He is a very present help in the time of trouble.
Amen, that's what the word of God says.
And he wants to help you, just as he helped David.
You've experienced this help
in other situations in your life.
In this time, in this storm, let him help you.
Pour out your heart before him, let's pray.
Father, thank you for your word.
Thank you for using your word to encourage me this week.
God, I believe,
I believe this morning that there are many amongst us
that are dealing with storms.
And God, I pray that you would help us
to follow the encouragement that we receive in your word,
that we would trust in you at all times,
and that we'd pour our heart out before you,
knowing that you are the Lord.
Knowing that you are our refuge.
Knowing that you are all-powerful.
Knowing that your mercies are new every morning,
that they fail not by compassions,
that you are a merciful God.
Your mercy endureth forever.
Thank you for the help that you offer to your people.
Perhaps there's one this morning
that's in the structure of heaven,
whether here or watching live stream,
they've never trusted Christ as their personal savior.
They don't have that relationship with you.
They're dead in their sins and their trespasses.
They're alienated from you, God.
I pray this morning they'd be saved
before it's eternally too late.
I pray that you'd help your people today.
Thank you for helping me.
I pray that you'd be glorified
at this time of invitation.
I pray that we would just let you have your way.
Be still in the moment.
Let you work.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Kimberly, would you please?