Genesis chapter 24. And I am thankful for the Bible. And this evening we're going to look at
just the first 27 verses, a lengthy chapter. And we're going to get into it a little bit,
but we're only going to go through really the first third of this particular chapter this
evening. And as we really get into the text, I want to ask you a series of questions and
really not for you to answer out loud, but just to kind of start provoking your thought this evening.
How many of you know that you need God to lead you? I mean, you need God to lead you.
How many of you ask God to lead you? See, it's a good thing to know that you need God to lead you,
but it must be followed up with asking God to lead us. And then I ask this question, how many of us
follow when God leads? We recognize that we need His leadership. We pray for His leadership.
And then He gives an answer and we say, that's not really the way I thought I was going to go.
I think I'm going to go this way. Or how many of us really have that humility to,
I'm going to follow where He leads me, I will follow. And then I think of this,
how many of us pause to thank God for His leadership in our lives? The text before us
this evening here in Genesis 24 records a major event of Jewish history. What is that event? Well,
it's the marriage of Isaac. I mean, this is important. We understand the significance of
the text of Scripture and we understand all that's taking place. And Abraham, he's old and
he's well stricken in age and he's concerned about the marriage of his son, rightly so.
And I mean, this is a very important portion of Scripture. And we understand that, but I want you
to understand also that there's a powerful lesson that's tucked within this passage regarding a man
given a task that is near impossible and how God intervened. See, this evening there are times in
which we have things laid before us, responsibilities that we've been given, and we're trying to go
through life, want to please God, and we need God to lead us. And I've titled the message this
evening, The Lord Led Me, and we're going to get through all of it, but I want you to notice,
if you will, in verse 26 and 27, it'll be the very end of the message, but I'm going to read it by
way of introduction. In verse 26, it says, The man bowed down his head and worshiped the Lord, and he
said, Blessed be the Lord God of my master Abraham, who hath not left destitute my master of his mercy
and his truth. I, being in the way, the Lord led me to the house of my master's brethren. And I've
simply titled the message this evening, The Lord Led Me. The Scripture does not tell us who the man
is. In fact, as you read there with me in verse 26, it says, And the man bowed down his head. I
believe that it's probably Eleazar. If you disagree with that, that's fine. I'm not going to argue with
you over it, but as you study the Scriptures, I believe that's who this servant is. But again,
that's not really the point of the text. You will hear me often, though, throughout the message this
evening, referring to Eleazar, and that's why I'm going to refer to it that way. Again, if you
disagree, we could chat later, but don't turn me off just for that simple thought. But notice with
me, if you're taking notes, we're going to jump right into the thoughts, the points this evening.
Number one, Eleazar is assigned a great responsibility. He is given a responsibility.
As you read verses one through nine, the assignment given is of significant importance
and was really too great for him. Notice, if you will, in verse number one, the Bible says, And
Abraham was old and well stricken in age, and the Lord had blessed Abraham in all things.
And Abraham said unto his eldest servant of his house, I believe, again, that that's Eleazar. If
you go back to Genesis 15 and verse two, but again, it's not the point of the message this evening, so
that's why I'll refer to it that way. But it says that ruled over all that he had. And here's what
Abraham said to him. Put, I pray thee, thy hand under my thigh, and I will make thee swear by the
Lord, the God of heaven and the God of the earth, that thou shalt not take a wife unto my son of the
daughters of the Canaanites among whom I dwell, but thou shalt go into my country and to my kindred
and take a wife unto my son Isaac. In these first four verses, as we open up Genesis chapter 24,
we find that the assignment is given. This is a great responsibility. It's of significant
importance. I can't even begin to imagine the weight of such responsibility. I cannot fully
comprehend being in the position of Eleazar, nor can I understand being in the position of Abraham
to call in his servant and to assign such a task, this great measure of responsibility. We see the
heart of Abraham. We see the significance of what's taking place and the cultural aspects
where he tells him to put his hand under his thigh and all of this that's taking place. And we find
that Eleazar is hearing this task as it's being assigned to him. And we find that it's very
specific in verse 3 and 4 what the task is to find a wife, not in this place, but in this place.
But think about even knowing the general area in which he's to go to find a wife for his master's
son. There are many women in that place, many ladies that could possibly be the one. And this
is a task that is of significant importance, a task that is overwhelming, a task that truly is
too great for him. In fact, as you read verse number 5, it begins to see that Eleazar is
responding. And it seems as if there's a measure of doubt that Eleazar has. Notice he says in verse
5, and the servant said unto him, and so he responds to Abraham. And notice what he says,
peradventure the woman will not be willing to follow me unto this land. Must I needs bring
thy son again unto the land from whence thou camest. So Eleazar's thinking in such terms that
not only the task and how am I supposed to find the one, but
let's just say I find the one, how am I going to get her to come?
The doubt and the significance of this task. And I find that in verses 6 through 8 that Abraham
responds to his servant. It's so powerful what we read in verses 6 through 8. And really we see
the confidence of Abraham, the faith of Abraham. And we see in Abraham's response to Eleazar,
a man who had proven God, a man who knew the God of heaven, a man that had confidence that
God could lead. And that had such an influence and an impact on Eleazar. Notice in verse number 6
that Abraham responds and says this, beware thou that thou bring not my son thither again.
Notice what Abraham says in verse 7. The Lord God of heaven, which took me from my father's
house and from the land of my kindred and which spake unto me and that swear unto me saying unto
thy seed will I give this land. He shall send his angel before thee and thou shalt take a wife
unto my son from thence. And if the woman will not be willing to follow thee, then thou shalt be clear
from this my oath, only bring not my son thither again. We find in verse number 7 that Abraham goes
all the way back to really the call that God placed on his life and the promise that God gave.
And Abraham now, a man that is old and well stricken in age, according to verse number 1,
looks back briefly over his life. And you know what he sees? He sees that God's been faithful.
He finds that God has been leading him. Remember when, if you look at the text of scripture back
in Genesis chapter number 12, when you begin to see what's taking place that the Lord had said
in verse number 1 of Genesis 12 unto Abraham, get thee out of thy country and from thy kindred and
from thy father's house unto a land that I will show thee. Abraham was not told in Genesis 12
in verse number 1 exactly the destination where he would reach. He just simply knew that God said,
I'm going to bring you into a land. And we find that in verse number 4, so Abraham departed and
God led him. Abraham is going to speak to Eleazar. And as Eleazar raises this concern and this measure
of doubt, we find that Abraham thinks back to all of what God has done in his life. Can I tell you
this evening, God has worked in your life and God has worked in my life. And it's important that we
remember that God has led us and that gives us the confidence to know that God will continue to lead
us, that he knows best and that he will answer that prayer when we seek him for wisdom, when we
seek him for direction in our lives. We say, God, lead me in a plain path. I mean, make it abundantly
clear. Order my steps, Lord. We find that this task is assigned. It's a great responsibility,
but we understand that the confidence and faith that is revealed on the part of Abraham
here in verses 6 through 8 has a powerful impact upon Eleazar. Could I remind you this evening that
there are people that are coming behind us that need to see us trusting God and communicating to
a future.
generation how God has led us and how God has been faithful. Why? Because that
will lead them to placing their faith in God and putting their trust in God. This
evening we find that Eliezer is assigned this task. If you're taking notes, notice
number two, Eliezer makes a specific request. As you begin looking at what
takes place in verse 9, it says, And the servant put his hand under the thigh of
Abraham, his master, and swore to him concerning that matter. And the servant
took ten camels with the camels of his master, and departed, for all the goods
of his master were in his hand. And he arose and went to Mesopotamia, unto the
city of Nahor. In verse 11, he made his camels to kneel down without the city by
a well of water at the time of the evening, even the time that women go out
to draw water. And notice specifically in verses 12 through 14, look at this
specific request. The Bible says in verse number 12, And he said, He said, O Lord
God of my master Abraham, I pray thee, send me good speed this day, and show
kindness unto my master Abraham. Behold, I stand here by the well of water. The
daughters of all the men of the city come out to draw water. In
verse 14, And let it come to pass that the damsel to whom I shall say, Let down
thy pitcher, I pray thee that I may drink. And she shall say, Drink, and I will give
thy camels drink also. Let the same be she that thou hast appointed for thy
servant Isaac. And thereby shall I know that thou hast showed kindness unto my
master. Begin to look at this request, this specific request that Eleazar makes.
And I find this evening that prayer makes all the difference. Aren't you
thankful? I preached on Wednesday evening about the fact that thou called and I
answered from Psalm 81 that we have a God who hears and answers. We have a God
who delights in answering and showing himself mighty and powerful. But the
question that I have this evening as I look at the passage of Scripture and the
question that the Lord has just impressed upon my heart and challenged
me with is this tonight. Do we have the kind of faith to pray prayers like this?
I mean, specific. I mean, proving God kind of prayers. Not just generic praying, but
I'm talking about specific praying that we can see. Listen, we have a God in
heaven that can do all things. We have a God that is the God of the impossible.
There's nothing too difficult for him. And we find that Eleazar here as it
begins to to seek the face of God. We understand as we look here, I read the
prayer. It's a short prayer. There's nothing in this prayer that's
lengthy whatsoever. I would say that what characterizes the prayer is that it's
simple. It's specific, but it's full of faith. How are we to pray? Believing. Right?
We're to pray believing, having confidence that God can, that God is able. And we
find this evening, how many times do we read throughout the gospel accounts
where because of their unbelief, he did not many mighty works here. Why? Because
of their unbelief. And we understand this evening that as we look through even
portions of the New Testament and read that during the life and ministry of the
Lord Jesus Christ, it reminds us of the children of Israel in Numbers 14 when
they did not believe God. And I want you to look at the prayer here this evening
of this man Eleazar and see that it's simple. It's specific, but it's full of
faith. Notice he begins really worshiping, O Lord God of my master
Abraham. And he prays specifically, notice, send me good speed this day. The matter
was urgent. And he prays that God would hear and answer in haste, that God would
answer speedily, show kindness unto my master. And then he speaks about where he
is and the circumstances with regard to what's taking place in this particular
setting. And it says in verse number 14, and let it come to pass that the damsel
to whom I shall say, let down thy pitcher, I pray thee that I may drink. And she
shall say, drink. And I will give thy camels drink also. This is specific. I
mean, he's understanding the task, the significance of the responsibility that's
been laid upon him. But he makes a specific request believing that God is
able to answer specifically this request. Listen, I don't think Eleazar had a
desire to come back to Isaac with just any person. I think he truly desired to
ensure that he would bring back the one that God had for Isaac. And he understood
the significance of the event. He understood the responsibility that was
bestowed upon him. And he goes and he makes this specific request, understand
with me this evening that camels drink a lot of water. Camels drink a lot of water.
And to pray that this damsel that he would say to her, give me drink, that she
would respond by saying, drink, and I will give thy camels drink also. Understand
that as he's praying, he does not say that he's going to ask the damsel for
drink himself and also for drink for the camels. He simply says that he's going to
ask the damsel for drink and let her say, drink, and I will give thy camels drink
also. And notice what he says, let the same be she that thou hast appointed for
thy servant Isaac. So he's praying, listen, don't let just anyone answer in
this way. I'm praying specifically and I'm looking for a specific response from
the one that I'm going to say, notice he says that I shall say, let down my
pitcher that I may drink. And the one that I say that to, if she's not the right
one, how am I going to know that she's the right one? Because she's going to
respond in a very specific way in how he's praying. Do you see how he's proving
God? And I just wonder tonight, do we have, do I have that kind of faith to pray
that specific? When we pray generic prayers, did God answer? Did he not answer?
Do we really know? It's just a generic God bless them, whatever. Do you understand
what I'm saying? But when you pray like this, it shows faith. It shows faith.
Let the same be she that thou hast appointed for thy servant Isaac. And thereby,
notice what he says when she responds in that fashion, he's going to know that God
has answered and God has worked and God has revealed to him the one that he's to
take back to Isaac. And thereby shall I know that thou hast showed kindness unto
my master. I see the simplicity of the prayer, the specific nature of the prayer, the prayer
that's full of faith. He that cometh to God must believe that he is and that he's
a rewarder of them that diligently seek him. It says before, I quoted only the latter part,
without faith it is impossible to please him. God wants us to pray believing, pray in faith,
believing that God is able. I think about this specific request and I think about the
title of the message and what we'll get to in just a few moments when we see that
he makes that statement as we read by way of introduction that the Lord led me. You
know, sometimes when we pray, when we're asking for God's leadership or God's direction,
we're really just praying that God would place his stamp of approval on the way that
I want to go. Does that make sense? God, here's how I want to go, here's what I want
to do, and so would you put your stamp of approval on it because I want your stamp
of approval. And that's a lot different than just saying, God, lead me. Wherever, into
whatever situation, God, lead me. This is a really simple personal illustration, but
I hope that it will help you this evening to be able to understand what I mean by this.
How many of you believe this evening that God could change the direction of the wind?
I believe that. How many of you have ever blown leaves and it's been contrary? You
ever do that? But, you know, the Bible talks about they were toiling and rowing, the disciples,
and I always get a picture in my mind of them toiling and rowing. I mean, they're just doing
everything they possibly can do and they're just going nowhere. Why? Because the Bible
says that the wind was contrary. They're toiling and rowing. I was out here a few weeks ago
and I was blowing off the parking lot after doing some lawn care and I was blowing off
the parking lot and as I'm blowing off, and those of you that have done it up here, it's
windy up on the top of this hill. It's windy today everywhere, but on just calm, normal
days, you'll still have more wind.
up here just because of where we sit and it's not like we're on that high of a
hill but it's just the nature of where we are and so I'm blowing and I'm
blowing the the leaves off and the the grass clippings and whatever and I'm
trying to clean up the parking lot and it seems as if brother Marcus I'm
blowing it this way it's going good and then all of a sudden a big gust of wind
comes and blows it all back here and you know I got flushed just like you do and
I'm like seriously and here's what I prayed I said God would you make the
wind blow in this direction so that I could get this accomplished quicker now
I believe God could do that I have no doubt in my mind that God could do that
God didn't speak to me with an audible voice but but it's almost like he did
and here's what God taught me in that moment when I prayed that way it was
almost like God said to me why are you praying that way why not see how I'm
making the wind blow and you blow in that direction that's a simple personal
illustration I'm telling God can teach us lessons anywhere and God taught me a
lesson on the blacktop out there just a few weeks ago because what was happening
as I was praying God would you make it blow this way because this is the way I
want it to go and it was as if God said I'm blowing the wind the way that I'm
blowing the wind and why don't you start blowing the leaves the way that I'm
blowing the wind I begin to think about my own life and I begin to think about
the truth of God's Word there are times in our lives that we do the very same
thing God here's the direction I want to go and just bless me just put your stamp
of approval because that's what I want to do and God is saying no I want to
lead you this way instead of you just praying that that I would bless the path
that you've chosen why don't you truly seek my path I used this statement last
night at the men's meeting and I heard it last week it's not original with me
but oh how it just impressed upon my heart this great truth the the fellow
that I heard make the statement oftentimes we talk about God's will for
our lives and it's important that we understand God's will for our lives and
we endeavor that we want to do the will of God with our lives and there's plenty
of people that would answer the question what do you want to do with your life
and what is my will for my life and then we say no let's talk about what God's
will is for your life and here's what I heard and it was so impactful to me and
it was this a man said this instead of asking what is God's will for my life
how about we start saying my life is to do God's will not so much what is God's
will for my life but my life is to do the will of God and we find that Eliezer
here in this specific request he's praying with faith he's praying it with
simplicity it is extremely specific and he's he's full of faith God work in this
way make this task that is too great for me can I tell you this evening that life
is too hard for all of us life is too hard for every single one of us you say
listen I got it figured out you write a book get a podcast do something because
if you got it figured out people will flock to you I'm being sarcastic life is
challenging you ever been thrown a curveball in life a curveball
sure you have we all have I played baseball for years and I understand as
they would talk about that idea of life throwing a curveball and I remember how
many times I'd see as I played baseball in the older you got and the better the
pitchers got how you'd see these guys bailing out of the batter's box and
there's a curveball coming it's called for a strike because they weren't ready
for the curveball what is the what is if you don't know baseball that's perfectly
fine but what is the hitter have to do you gotta watch the hand you gotta watch
the release point you got to watch the the spin of the baseball and you can
tell if you're good you can tell it's a curveball as soon as it leaves the hand
of the pitcher you can tell now you can't see it breaking yet but you can
tell I caught for years and it gave me an advantage being a catcher seeing that
perspective pitch after pitch after pitch that when I got in the batter's
box it was a little bit easier to be able to see that life throws us curve
balls and there are plenty of times that it happens and we said I didn't see that
coming what I'm saying this evening is we need God to lead us and we need to be
specific about it he gives the specific this task is too great for me how in the
world am I gonna go into this place I'm gonna find a wife for my master's son
the pressure of such responsibility I need God I need God and he prays
specifically notice in first number 15 I love it and it came to pass it came to
pass before he had done speaking that behold Rebecca came out who was born of
Bethuel son of Milka the wife of Nahor Abraham's brother with her pitcher upon
her shoulder don't rush over verse 15 before he had done speaking in that
awesome how God is able to work what God is able to do before he had done
speaking here's what's transpiring in verse 16 and the damsel was very fair to
look upon a virgin neither had any man known her and she went down to the well
and filled her pitcher and came up and the servant ran to meet her and said let
me I pray thee drink a little water of thy pitcher and notice in verse 18 and
she said drink my lord and she hasted and let down her pitcher upon her hand
and gave him drink and when she had done giving him drink she said I will draw
water for thy camels also until they have done drinking now I don't know
sometimes we get surprised when God answers prayer has ever happened your
life I mean you prayed about something you prayed specifically about something
and then God answers and it's like we're surprised like that God did it no no God
is able and God delights in answering prayer he delights in showing himself
mighty and here Eliezer he runs he's with haste he goes and he says let me
have some water and in the Bible tells us that in verse number 19 that she says
to him after she had given him a drink I will draw water for thy camels also
until they have done drinking I can't imagine the thoughts and the emotions
that would go through Eliezer's mind at this particular moment the excitement
why this is exactly what he prayed she's the one remember he said thereby shall I
know that thou has showed kindness unto my master verse 20 and she hastened and
emptied the pitcher into the trough and ran again under the well to draw water
and drew for all his camels and the man wandering at her held his peace to wit
whether the Lord and made his journey prosperous or not it came to pass as the
camels had done drinking that the man took a golden earring of half a shekel
weight two bracelets for her hands of ten shekels of weight and said whose
daughter art thou tell me I pray thee is there room in my father's house for us
to lodge in there in verse number 23 verse 24 and she said unto him I am the
daughter of Bethuel the son of Milchah which was she barren to Nahor she said
moreover unto him we have both strong preventer enough and room to lodge in he
prayed specifically God answered God answered this evening as we think about
our own prayer lives how often is God answering our prayers I'm talking
specific prayers like this one I'm talking prayers that were proving God
that were seeking the face of God sometimes and please don't misunderstand
me I'm not suggesting this evening that there's a magic formula to prayer or
there's a certain period of time that you ought to spend in prayer in fact
you've heard me say over the years that sweet hour of prayer has been replaced
in our generation with just a little talk with Jesus and I think there's so
much truth to that and there's certainly an aspect of laboring in prayer and just
having that that that time and that just persistence in prayer but here it's just
a simple short there's nothing lengthy about it I think about Nehemiah if you
read Nehemiah 1 we won't take the time to go there but Nehemiah is praying he
gets a report and begins to pray and he's he's I mean he's seeking the Lord
and then he's in the presence of a hazardous and he's he's sad and the
Bible says and he prayed but it had to be like about a that long kind of a
prayer because he he didn't have time to go to his prayer closet didn't have time
to but he'd already prayed prior and then he prayed again just in that moment
and we find here that God worked and God answered and Eleazar sought the Lord he
was specific in his request and and he had this task he'd been given this
responsibility that was overwhelming that was daunting that was so
significant but he sought the Lord this evening your life and my life needs to
be led
by God. I asked you at the very beginning of the message, how many of you know that
you need God to lead you? I need God to lead me. You need God to lead you. We need God's
leadership. Listen, I don't know if you found it to be so, but we can make a mess of our
lives in a hurry. We really can. We can get on our own path and we can start doing things
our own way, and I mean it just can become a disaster in a hurry. I need God. You need
God. I find in the text of scripture not only this responsibility and this request, but
I want you to notice, number three, if you're taking notes, the Eleazar pauses to rejoice.
I hope this evening that as we read once again verses 26 and 27, I read it by way of introduction,
that we would take a moment to consider the response of Eleazar to answered prayer and
how he rejoices. The Bible says in verse 26, and the man bowed down his head and worshiped
the Lord. I mean, verse 26 again is not a long verse, but oh, what is captured in this
single verse of scripture, a man who is rejoicing. Why? Because God has answered prayer. He knew.
He had prayed so specific that it was absolutely certain, and we find that here in this text
of scripture that he bows his head, and then notice what he says in verse 27. As he bowed
down his head and worshiped the Lord, verse 27, he said, blessed be the Lord God of my
master Abraham, who hath not left destitute my master of his mercy and his truth. I, being
in the way, the Lord led me to the house of my master's brethren. He wasn't equipped
with a GPS as we are to know which home he should go to, to find a wife for his master's
son Isaac. But instead of having Siri or some other application on your phone that
would give you GPS directions, he had God. He had God. And he believed that God could
lead him directly to where he needed to be. And he pauses to rejoice and he says, I, being
in the way, the Lord led me to the house of my master's brethren. This evening, I
don't want you to miss the point that he took time to rejoice, that he took time to pause
and thank God for answering prayer. See, in our lives, yes, it's the month of November,
but we understand that though in our nation we have a holiday in this month that's Thanksgiving
that is, as the people of God, we're to be a thankful people. We're to give thanks all
the time. And our lives must be marked with thanksgiving, with times of rejoicing, that
when we pray and when God answers that we don't just keep rushing through, but we take
time to pause. Do you think, I believe, I can't, just my own opinion, I think if I were
in this situation, I would have wanted to haste to get to the house, to get the permission
to get back. But he pauses to rejoice. He pauses to bow down and to worship the Lord
and to recognize that God did this. In your life and in my life, God does answer prayer.
And how often do we stop and pause and just rejoice? Thank God for what he's done and
how he's worked and how he's answered that prayer. Notice, if you will, take your Bible
and turn to the New Testament, the book of Philippians, if you will. And we'll end with
this verse of Scripture tonight, but I want you to look very quickly here in Philippians
chapter number 4. We're familiar with many of the New Testament verses and principles
that teach us about giving thanks, and certainly those are worth our consideration and committing
to memory because we are to be a thankful people. But I want you to notice in verse
number 6 of Philippians 4, it's a familiar verse of Scripture. The Bible says this,
be careful for nothing, but in everything by prayer and supplication, notice it says,
with thanksgiving, let your requests be made known unto God. This evening, our praying
is important, but our rejoicing is important. That we take that time to pause and rejoice
and thank God for what he does in our lives and how he answers. And, you know, if you
keep reading, and we don't have time this evening, but if you were to keep reading through
our text of Scripture here in the book of Genesis, you'll find that as Eleazar carries
on and he continues on his journey, you know what he does? He rehearses exactly what God
did. He rehearses how God worked, the prayer that he prayed, and the way that God answered,
and he rejoices. He, in fact, says it this way in verse number 48, and I bowed down my
head and worshiped the Lord and blessed the Lord God of my master Abraham, which had led
me in the right way to take my master's brother's daughter unto his son. He further said this
in verse 50, the thing proceedeth from the Lord. Listen, when we pray specifically and
God answers, we can have that confidence. This is what God's will is. This is God's
path. You say, but it might not be the path that I've chosen. Yeah, I wanted the wind
to blow different with those leaves that day too. And I believe with all my heart that
God could have done that, but he taught me a different lesson that day. And for us tonight,
when we look at Genesis and we look at this account and we see, yes, this significant
event in Israel's history, but there's a lesson for each of us. Is God leading you? Do you
recognize that you need God's leadership in your life? Are you asking him to lead you?
Are you following when he does? See, the idea is not God, you tell me what you want
me to do and then I'll review it and decide if I want to sign up for that. That's not
the way that we look at it. The way that we look at it is God, here's my life. I'm going
to do whatever you lead me to do because I'm your servant. I belong to you. It's like writing
that blank check of our life. We just say, Lord, here's my life. Here I am, Lord. And
we need God to lead us. And when he does, we need to rejoice. What a great passage.
God led me. The Lord led me. And this evening, I hope that we'd be able to see in our lives
God's leadership. We'd be able to look back and say, the Lord led me. I know I'm where
I'm supposed to be. Why? Because God led me. I'm confident. I prayed and I sought the Lord
and I know that the Lord led me. And oh, we can rejoice and we can march forward knowing
that God led us. Let's pray. Father, we love you tonight. We thank you for loving us. We
thank you for your word. And Lord, many songs that we sing about where you lead will follow
and I have decided to follow Jesus and many others like them. Lord, we're thankful for
this example, this passage. I thank you for the faith of Abraham that impacted and influenced
Eliezer and I thank you for the prayer of Eliezer. And God, I pray that you'd help us
to pray with that kind of faith or to pray specific prayers. There'd be no doubt when
you answer that it's you that have answered. I thank you for his rejoicing that he took
that time to pause, to rejoice for what you did in his life and how you led and the kindness
that you showed. God, I pray that you'd help each of us tonight to recognize as Eliezer
did that life is too difficult for us. We need you, God. We need your leadership. We
need you to lead us day by day, step by step. God, I pray that you'd help us to surrender
to Thee. Lord, help us to trust Thee and to obey Thee. I pray that in the moment of
invitation that you'd have your will and way in the hearts of your people and we'll thank
you for it. In Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me?