Number four, it was several weeks ago
that I preached part one of this message.
And I know some folks have been wondering
about when part two was gonna be.
In fact, I've received a couple of text messages
over the past few weeks.
Is part two of that message gonna be this Sunday night?
And it was no, and no, and now here we are,
and it's part two, and I'm thankful for God's grace.
And last year, we talked about the grace of God
and God's grace is sufficient.
We spoke about the fact that God's grace,
His saving grace, for by grace are you saved through faith.
But then we focused and we talked about
His serving grace, His enabling,
and the grace of God that's been bestowed upon us.
And here in our text of scripture,
he says at the end of verse number 10,
as good stewards of the manifold grace of God.
And we wanna be good stewards of God's grace.
The Bible tells us that it's required in stewards
that a man be found faithful.
And we understand the role of a steward
and the responsibility of a steward
and the importance of a steward being found faithful.
And we wanna be good stewards of the manifold grace of God.
The gift that God has bestowed upon us,
we wanna use for His honor and for His glory.
And so I titled the message, Even So Minister.
We see it right in the middle of verse number 10.
And we looked at this again,
part one was several weeks ago,
but let me use, read the verses of scripture.
We'll dig in this evening.
In 1 Peter 4, in verse number 10,
the Bible says, as every man hath received the gift,
even so minister the same one to another,
as good stewards of the manifold grace of God.
If any man speak, let him speak as the oracles of God.
If any man minister, let him do it
as of the ability which God giveth,
that God in all things may be glorified
through Jesus Christ to whom be praise
and dominion forever and ever, amen.
And we examined several portions of scripture
a few weeks ago as we looked at part number one.
And really what we were seeking to do in that message
was to establish a foundational understanding
of spiritual gifts.
And here's just a quick overview of that first message.
If you were not here or because of the fact
that it's been several weeks
and I put the Sunday school class this morning,
our teen Sunday school class.
I said, hey, how was it last week
with brother Travis Campbell?
Oh, it was great.
I said, man, that's wonderful.
What did he preach on?
Man, I wish I had my notes.
Like none of them could remember.
And I'm not throwing them under the bus.
I'm simply saying we have so many things
that happen in our lives that we kind of,
and as they kind of sat there,
they were starting to remember certain things.
And then somebody said, oh yeah, he preached on this.
And that was in the morning.
No, no, no.
Somebody else, no, no.
That was in the evening.
And somebody else, no, no.
And it was just kind of,
and that's how we are as humans, right?
We just, we need to be reminded of some things.
And so we noted several things
that I think it's important that we rehearse this evening
as we go into part number two.
The first thing that we noted is this,
and we see it in verse number 10.
And that is that every believer
has been given a spiritual gift.
It says, as every man hath received the gift.
The gift here in 1 Peter 4 and verse number 10
is not the gift of salvation,
although salvation is the greatest gift
that any of us could ever receive.
It's the greatest gift that we possess.
The reality is that here, contextually,
he's not talking about the gift of salvation.
He's talking about spiritual gifts.
And he says, as every man hath received the gift.
And this is, the word man is referring to mankind,
every child of God.
It's not talking about the lost having received a gift.
It's talking about the people of God.
And so if you're here and you've been saved
by the grace of God,
you have been given a spiritual gift.
We also understood, and we focused on the fact
that it's the Holy Spirit who gives
to every man as he wills.
In other words, it's not that it's a buffet type
of a situation where we look down the line and say,
okay, here are the spiritual gifts that are available.
And I think this is the line that I'm going to get into
because this is the one that I'd really like.
No, the Holy Spirit of God giveth to every man
severally as he will.
And he doeth all things well, amen.
God doeth all things well.
The Holy Spirit is God.
And we know that as we understand the spiritual gifts
and the Holy Spirit, the Holy Ghost will give
that spiritual gift.
And it's appropriate, it's right.
It's not a situation where we say,
well, that's not the one I wanted.
No, God knows better than you do.
He knows better than I do.
And he gives the spiritual gifts
and he talks about the church being a body.
And as the body is joined together,
fitly joined together, and we find that as God
would equip his saints with the spiritual gifts,
that the body of Christ, as we use our spiritual gifts,
we bring glory to God as everyone is using the gift
that's been given to them.
One of the problems in the church in Corinth,
when I was having this conversation,
it's always interesting as a guest speaker,
I got done preaching last Sunday there in Hawaii
and I got done and several people,
they wanna talk to you and give you comments
about whatever, they appreciate the message,
so on and so forth.
And it was a real blessing to just kinda be used
of the Lord to be a blessing to those folks there.
And then you always can kinda tell
when somebody really wants to talk to you
a little bit more.
And this one person wanted to talk to me a little bit more
and I knew as soon as they started talking,
I need to make sure I find a way, a gap,
to be able to say, you need to talk to your pastor.
Why?
Because I'm not their pastor, amen?
I am a pastor, but I was not their pastor.
And the things that they were sharing with me,
they needed to be able to talk to their pastor.
And some of the things that they were sharing,
I then talked to the pastor, gave him a heads up,
hey, somebody came to me and here's what they talked
to me about, and I just wanted to let you know
that I pointed them to you and give you a heads up.
And they're like, well, why didn't you fix the problem?
Because that's not my job, amen?
And the reality is that one thing that I told him
to try to encourage him is that oftentimes
when we look at the church in Corinth,
it's the most carnal church in the New Testament.
It's a church that's being corrected for its error
with regard to spiritual gifts,
but yet oftentimes people want to run
to the book of First Corinthians
and withdraw certain portions of scripture
and set up teaching and doctrine that's erroneous.
And you're dealing with a carnal church
that's being corrected for their wrongdoing,
and you're gonna try to build doctrine on it.
It's a terrible mistake.
And so we find that the Holy Spirit
gives to every man as he wills.
And here's the thing, what happens
and what was happening in Corinth
is people were saying, well, I want that spiritual gift.
They were coveting after certain spiritual gifts.
The one that was kind of on the top of the list was tongues.
And you saw that there was absolutely a pride element
with regard to that, which is still prevalent today
within the modern day tongues movement.
And so we find that it's not that we would covet
some other gift that someone else has,
it is that we would understand
that the Holy Spirit of God has equipped me,
has given to me a spiritual gift
that is the right spiritual gift for me.
And so we find that we dealt with that last week.
We noted that the purpose of spiritual gifts,
really twofold purpose is this.
Number one and primary is to glorify God.
Here in 1 Peter chapter four and verse number 11,
it says, I'll just pick it up in the middle of the text
that God in all things may be glorified
through Jesus Christ to whom be praise
and dominion forever and ever, amen.
And so the primary purpose of spiritual gifts
is so that God would be glorified.
We understand that John the Baptist said he must increase,
I must decrease.
It's all about us as his people bringing glory to his name.
Whether therefore you eat or drink or whatsoever you do,
do all to the glory of God.
And as we minister, as we use that spiritual gift
that God has equipped us with,
it is to bring glory to God.
Not so that we could say, look at me, look at what I know.
We recognize it was God that gave it to us.
I have no ability aside from God's grace
being bestowed upon me.
And so we find that not only is the primary purpose
to glorify God, but secondarily,
the purpose of spiritual gifts is to edify the believers,
to build up the brethren.
The Bible says here in verse number 11,
if any man speak, let him speak as the oracles of God.
If any man minister, notice,
let him do it as of the ability which God giveth.
In verse number 10, it says,
even so minister, notice, the same one to another.
Throughout the portion of scripture
in the book of 1 Corinthians
as it deals with the subject of spiritual gifts,
you read chapters 12, 13, and 14.
And those three chapters,
and we looked at several verses last time
with regard to the spiritual gifts
there in the book of 1 Corinthians.
And we find that Paul repeatedly spoke to them
about edifying the brethren,
building them up and encouraging them.
And what an important role.
We understand that as we gather together,
when you think about the truth of church,
and yes, even as I mentioned during announcements
about some folks that haven't been able to be here
and have said, it's just not the same on live stream.
Listen, there are things,
this was a huge problem during COVID.
There are things, there are commands
that you and I cannot obey if we do not assemble.
Just impossible.
In Hebrews 10 in verse 25,
not forsaking the assembling of ourselves together
as the manner of some is,
but exhorting one another even so much more as you see.
see the day approaching, he said in verse number 24,
and let us consider one another to provoke unto love
and to good works.
These are things that we do as we assemble, as we gather.
These are things that as I use my spiritual gift,
as you use your spiritual gift,
we're edifying the brethren.
We defined the spiritual gifts as they're listed there
in Romans chapter number 12.
So that's kind of a quick overview of what we looked at
in part number one of this even so minister
and understanding how that spiritual gifts were defined
in the scriptures.
Now, as we make some application
and really kind of deal here with part two,
if you're taking notes, I would say number one,
discovering your spiritual gift.
And so here's the question that we have
as we look at the truth that God gives us
in Romans chapter number 12 with regard
to the spiritual gifts and the fact that he's given
to us a spiritual gift.
And we looked at the gift of prophecy,
the gift of ministry, the gift of teaching,
the gift of exhortation, the gift of giving,
of ruling and of mercy.
And we looked at those gifts and we dealt with,
explained each one of them.
And so when you begin to say, okay,
there's seven spiritual gifts,
according to Romans 12, verses three through eight,
how do I determine, how do I discover my spiritual gift?
If God has told me in his word that I have a spiritual gift,
if God has told me, and he has,
that he's given to every man
as every man hath received the gift,
then it becomes a responsibility of the individual
to discover what is my spiritual gift?
Let me say this.
If you don't know what your spiritual gift is,
it's likely you're not using it.
You say, well, that's pretty obvious.
Yeah, sometimes we need to state the obvious.
Because the reality is that God has given to us
a spiritual gift and I would say this,
we are accountable, we are responsible
for the spiritual gift that God has given to us
and we're responsible, we're accountable
to use that spiritual gift for God's glory
and for the edification of the body of Christ.
That's our responsibility.
That's what we're accountable for.
That's what we are going to,
that's one thing that we'll give an account for
because God has given it to us.
And so when I try to talk about
how do I discover my spiritual gift,
number one, I would say this, ask God to reveal it to you.
If God is the one that gave it to you
and God is the one that describes
and defines for us in the scriptures
what the spiritual gifts are,
then why wouldn't you ask him,
what spiritual gift do I have?
Would you make it known to me?
Would you make it clear to me what my spiritual gift is?
And when I begin to think about
and talk about this subject of spiritual gifts,
the reality is that there are some
and the scriptures tell us God doesn't want us
to be ignorant about this.
He wants us to be informed about this.
In fact, 1 Corinthians 12 begins with that very verbiage.
I don't want you to be ignorant.
I want you to know about this.
He's given it to us so that we would know
but I would say this, that for a large percentage
of just average, quote unquote, average Christians today,
there are a number of folks that have zero idea
whatsoever about spiritual gifts,
that they exist, that they have one.
They have no concept, no idea and it's important
that we not only know that spiritual gifts exist
but we determine what is my spiritual gift?
How has God equipped me?
How has he gifted me?
And ask him to make it known to you.
I would say this, thank God for the gift
that he's given you.
Once he reveals that to you, as you get alone
with the Lord, as you search the scriptures,
as you begin to meditate upon what those gifts are
and as God begins to reveal that to you,
thank him for it, not only thank him for it
but I would say this, embrace it, embrace it.
It's not a situation where we despise it.
Well, that really wasn't the one I was hoping to receive.
No, that we embrace it because that's the one
that God gave us and God knows you better
than you know you.
God knows and he equips properly and we embrace
that which he's given to us and then determine
that we'll use the gift for his glory.
I'll say this and I'm careful on how I say this
because I wanna make sure that we get the entirety
of what I'm saying.
There is, and it's a man-made thing, okay?
It's a man-made thing but there is a test
that I have, that I have on my computer downstairs
that I have several of you in here have taken this test,
I've given it to you and it is a test that helps us
to determine what our spiritual gift is.
Again, it's man-made, it's not, there's no,
it's not scripturally bound and all that sort of thing,
it's a man-made test.
I think actually Miss Holly with the young girls,
the teenage girls did this a few weeks ago
and they took that spiritual gifts test
and I would say this, it's a good guide
and I remember the first time I came across that,
I took it and I felt like it aligned exactly
what I had already believed the Lord had revealed to me
with regard to what my spiritual gift is
and so I believe this evening that if that would be
something that you'd be interested in,
I didn't bring and print out a bunch of them this evening
but I do have those available and I'd be happy
to either email it to you or print one out for you,
have it for you at the next service.
Why, because you need to discover
what your spiritual gift is
and if there's a, even if it's a man-made test,
a guide that could help us in discovering what it is,
then I wanna utilize that tool, why?
Because I wanna know what my spiritual gift is
and so it's important that we would discover
our spiritual gift.
Next, I would say this, number two,
develop your spiritual gift.
What do I mean by that?
Well, the reality is that God gifts us
and he holds us accountable but we need to develop
the gift that God has given to us.
I believe and I said this last week and,
or not last week but last time,
the reality is that when you look at that list
of seven items that are spiritual gifts
defined in Romans chapter number 12,
it's not that I have one of them
and I don't have to worry about the others.
I'm not accountable or responsible.
That's not the idea of spiritual gifts
but there will be one primary.
I believe that teaching is my primary spiritual gift.
I don't believe that I'm the best teacher in the world
or any of that sort of thing.
I do strive, however, to develop that spiritual gift
and to just equip myself.
How can I develop this?
How can I become more effective in teaching
if that's what I believe my spiritual gift is
then I wanna develop that.
I wanna be, it says here in 1 Peter chapter number four,
if any man speak, let him speak as the oracles of God.
If any man minister, notice, let him do it
as of the ability which God giveth.
The purpose is that God would be glorified
but I want to develop, I want to be
what God has called me to be
and I want to be able to develop that.
You think about this in the arena of the world
and we're dealing right now,
the Winter Olympics just opened
and some people will be watching the Winter Olympics.
I haven't seen any of it up to this point
but the reality is that those athletes
that compete either in the Winter or the Summer Olympics,
they have a particular skill and a particular ability
and they work tirelessly to perfect that, right?
I mean, they labor and they labor
and they miss out on all sorts of things.
They make so many sacrifices so that they can become,
in their mind, striving for a gold medal.
That's what their desire is.
We can see it in the world with regard
to maybe the company that you work for,
there's continuous improvement,
there's maybe there's some classes
that you can take for professional development and why?
Because I want to become better,
I want to be more proficient, I want to be more effective
in whatever my role is and we understand that in the world.
And so when we come to the work of God,
we ought to desire to be the best workers possible.
We ought to desire to be the most effective, why?
Because what we're doing is of eternal value, amen?
I mean, what we're doing, the church,
listen, it is the greatest organism,
we could use the word organization on planet Earth.
I believe that.
God has no backup plan, it's the church.
In this era, in this dispensation,
it is the local church, amen?
And so the local church ought to have the best workers,
the best equipped, the ones that are going to,
I want to take the spiritual gift that God has given me
and I want to develop that, why?
Because I want to use it for God's glory.
I don't want to develop it
so that I can get a promotion at work,
a lot of times that's the goal, right?
When you talk about professional development
and all those things that are going on,
I want to take these classes and I want to do these things,
why?
Because I want advancement.
No, when we talk about spiritual gifts,
I want to develop it so that God would be glorified,
so that I would be more effective
on doing the work that God has called me to do.
Notice, if you will, in 1 Corinthians chapter number 15,
we'll look at just a statement here from the apostle Paul
and then look at two instructions that he gives to Timothy,
one in 1 Timothy and one in 2 Timothy.
He, of course, refers to Timothy as a son of the faith
and we could kind of take that analogy, if you will,
that Paul is passing that baton to Timothy,
a son of the faith,
to kind of run the next leg of the journey,
knowing that he soon would depart.
as he mentions in 2 Timothy, but Paul himself,
before he makes these statements to Timothy
that we'll look at in just a moment,
notice what Paul says in 1 Corinthians chapter 15.
In 1 Corinthians chapter 15 in verse number nine,
the apostle Paul says,
"'For I am the least of the apostles,
"'that am not meet to be called an apostle,
"'because I persecuted the church of God.'"
Listen, this is scripture.
All scripture is given by inspiration of God.
This is not Paul just simply puffing himself up
with some false humility.
Paul was extremely humble.
Paul knew who he was.
Paul knew what Christ did for him.
Paul knew, I don't think he ever got over,
as he mentions at the end of verse number nine,
how he persecuted the church.
I think that bothered him.
He's thankful for the change that God brought in his life.
Therefore, if any man be in Christ, he's a new creature.
Old things are passed away.
Behold, all things have become new.
And Paul says, I'm the least of the apostles.
Now, for most of us, if we were to list out the apostles
in order by greatest to least, if we were to do that,
and I know that Paul says to the church in Corinth
that we're not to compare ourselves amongst ourselves,
but if we were to do that, for many of us,
Paul would be at the top of the list.
The humility is real, but then notice what he says
in verse number 10 that gives us some insight
with regard to not only the subject of spiritual gifts,
but to the idea of developing our spiritual gifts.
He says this in verse number 10,
but by the grace of God, I am what I am.
How many of you would echo that in your life?
I mean, if it were not for the grace of God.
I am so thankful that God's grace is sufficient,
that God's grace, I'm saved by his amazing grace,
but we think about the service and how he enables us
and he equips us for his service,
and he says, but by the grace of God, I am what I am,
in his grace, which was bestowed upon me,
notice what he says, was not in vain.
We saw in 1 Peter chapter four in verse number 10
as good stewards of the manifold grace of God,
and Paul says here in 1 Corinthians 15 in verse number 10
that God's grace that was bestowed upon him
was not bestowed upon him in vain.
It was not something that would be useless,
it was not something that God gave to him
and he just let it sit dormant.
Amen, does that make sense?
And notice what he says, his grace which was bestowed upon me
was not in vain, and then he says this,
but I labored more abundantly than they all.
Now understand something, he didn't labor for God's grace,
he labored because of God's grace.
There's an important distinction.
God's grace is not given to us because we work for it
and we earn it, no, God's grace is given to us,
it's bestowed upon us, and because he acknowledged the fact
that God had bestowed upon him grace,
it caused him, because of the grace,
he labored more abundantly.
You read throughout the passages of the New Testament
and you read about the missionary journeys
of the Apostle Paul and we can see
that he labored more abundantly.
We can see that he was willing to go,
when they said don't go to Jerusalem,
when they come and they bring the girdle
and you're gonna die, he said I'm willing to die.
He wanted to serve the Lord, he wanted to spend and be spent.
He wanted to live a life that was lived to its fullest
for the glory of God.
And he says that he labored more abundantly than they all,
yet not I, but the grace of God which was with me.
So again, he refers again to the grace of God
and how it was God's grace that was enabling him,
that was equipping him, that was empowering him,
and he says I want it to develop,
I want it to be, if I could use this terminology,
and I don't necessarily love the terminology,
but I think we could relate to it, we can understand it,
I wanna be the best Christian I can be.
I wanna be the best servant of God that I can be.
I wanna do, I wanna be my very best for Jesus.
Does that make sense?
After all that he's done for me,
listen, I know at times we've used,
and we live in a place here in Northern Virginia,
so many government people, and we've used the phrase,
it's good enough for government work,
and you've heard that at some point in your life,
and the reality is that it's not good enough
for God's work, amen?
We oughta be the best that we can possibly be,
we oughta develop that spiritual gift.
There's not this idea, I'm gonna mail it in.
No, this is eternal work that we're engaged in.
Somebody that I, a pastor friend that I know,
he makes this statement often,
and I think it's a very interesting statement,
and I don't use it, I don't say it often,
but he says this, and it's a reminder for himself,
that this moment in history is unlike any other moment.
He's talking about this very minute,
because here's the reason,
all of us that are gathered in this room tonight,
at this time, under these circumstances,
will never meet again.
The same exact people, with the same exact circumstances,
and so every moment that God gives us to minister
is a unique moment, and it's an eternal moment,
it's not just a, well, I'm just gonna kinda,
again, mail it in, no, I wanna develop,
I wanna be the best that I can be for God's glory,
not for our own recognition, and God knows our motives,
man may question your motives,
but if your motives are pure, God knows,
and you don't have to be so concerned
about what other people think,
it's about bringing honor and glory to God,
because I'll say this,
somebody's gonna question your motives,
you always gotta shine the brightest,
or whatever they wanna say, don't worry about that,
because I wanna be the best for Jesus, amen?
And you wanna wanna be the best for Jesus too,
whatever gift he's given to you.
Notice what he says,
so he talks about his own personal experience,
but then notice what he says to Timothy
in 1 Timothy chapter four,
we'll look at a passage here, a verse in 1 Timothy,
and then a verse in 2 Timothy,
and developing your spiritual gift,
you find out what it is,
you have to discover it before you can develop it,
I discovered that my spiritual gift was teaching,
so I began reading books on teaching,
why, I wanna be effective,
I wanna have an understanding of how to teach,
what it means to teach, so on and so forth,
and so we come here to 1 Timothy chapter four,
in verse 14, and he says this,
notice what Paul says to Timothy, his son of the faith,
he says, neglect not the gift that is in thee,
which was given thee by prophecy
with the laying on of the hands of the presbytery,
so I want you to notice that first phrase in verse 14,
neglect not the gift that is in thee,
here's what happens too often,
is people neglect the gift that's in them,
and at times it's based on ignorance,
like they truly just don't know
that they have a spiritual gift,
they truly, no one has ever taught them,
no one has ever dealt with the passages of scripture
that deal with spiritual gifts,
and so they themselves are ignorant,
they have no concept, no idea that they're spiritual gifts,
but then there's other times,
as Paul is saying to Timothy here,
you know that you have a spiritual gift,
but don't neglect it, don't neglect it,
he tells them this in 2 Timothy,
notice in chapter one,
in 2 Timothy chapter one in verse number six,
he's talking about the faith
and as he calls things to remembrance,
but then he comes to verse number six,
and notice what Paul says in 2 Timothy 1.6,
wherefore I put thee in remembrance,
he says this, that thou stir up the gift of God,
which is in thee by the putting on of my hands,
that's the same gift that he talked about
in 1 Timothy 4 and verse 14,
and so he says that you stir it up,
that literally the word stir up means to rekindle,
Timothy no doubt was dealing with a hard task
that was given to him,
he's left there in Ephesus,
there's all sorts of things that are going on,
God had told the apostle Paul
and it had been revealed to Paul
that after his departure,
as he talked to those leaders there at Ephesus,
that there would be some that would come in,
that would be grievous wolves
that would seek to devour the flock,
and all these things are going on,
the false teaching and so on and so forth,
and listen in those circumstances,
it's easy to become discouraged,
is it really worth it,
is it really being effective,
is my labor really helping anyone,
can I just remind you of a great promise
of 1 Corinthians 15 verse 58,
he says your labor is not in vain in the Lord,
amen, therefore my beloved brethren,
he starts being steadfast, unmovable,
always abounding in the work of the Lord,
why, for as much as you know
that your labor is not in vain in the Lord,
there are times that the enemy will wanna discourage you,
it's not worth it,
no one's listening,
no one cares,
no one, no, no, no,
your labor is not in vain in the Lord,
we never know the opportunity that might be before us
and being able to impact somebody
and what they might do for the cause of Christ,
you can read of great heroes of the faith
that we've spoken of and you've heard of
and you've possibly read books about D.L. Moody
and C.H. Charles Spurgeon and these other folks,
and those two come to my mind very quickly,
but if you were to look back
and you would think about some of the unknown named people
from our perspective and from history
that faithfully serve the Lord
and use their spiritual gift
that God used.
them to be able to encourage, to see these young men saved and called to the ministry
and used of God instead of Delamuti that he shook two continents for the cause of Christ.
It's amazing.
And simply saying this evening that when Timothy is in a state of dealing with much that he's
facing in the ministry, that Paul says to him, I put thee in remembrance that thou stir
up the gift of God to rekindle.
I preached a message at a church.
They asked me to come for a revival meeting over there in Oaksville, Victory Baptist Church.
Their evangelist had to change their schedule.
And I spoke a little bit, not from this passage, but what is revival?
It really is a rekindling.
Revival is not for the lost people, but can I tell you what happens sometimes?
You've ever had a bonfire, you've ever had a fire in a fire pit.
If you, if you stay there long enough, it burns out and you know those embers sometimes
are super hot embers and there just needs to be a little stirring.
Put some more wood on it and stir it up a little bit.
And man, all of a sudden, have you ever done that before?
And you see how that thing will just rage with flames once again.
And Paul is saying to stir up, to rekindle.
And so I want to develop my spiritual gift.
I want to be a good steward of the manifold grace of God.
I don't want it to be that his grace was bestowed upon me in vain.
I want to labor more abundantly than they all.
I don't want to neglect it.
I want to stir it up.
I want to develop.
And then I would say this, finally, deploy it.
Deploy your spiritual gift.
What do I mean by that?
Use it.
You've discovered what it is, you've sought to develop it, then use it.
What is the purpose of the spiritual gift?
Well, again, to bring glory to God, to edify the believers.
And so if we've discovered and we've sought to develop, but then we're not using it, then
we're not being a good steward of the manifold grace of God.
We're not doing what God has called and equipped us to do.
God gave you the gift and he expects you to use it.
There are times in which people have been recipients of gifts and it's as if the gift
was given to them to sit on a shelf as a collector item and to possibly gain some value
in time.
And there are times in which people, and perhaps for even some of us this evening, you've seen
things that have been sold for large sums of money that you're like, man, I played with
those things when I was a kid.
And only if it had stayed in the box, only if it had stayed unused, it might be worth
something.
That the spiritual gifts are not to be kept within the box, so to speak.
They're to be used for the glory of God.
That's how they are to be effective and that's how God is going to bless the work that he's
called you and called me to do.
So when we deploy our spiritual gift, when we understand that God expects us to use it,
that we look for those opportunities to use our spiritual gifts.
I remember speaking to someone a number of, probably three years ago at this point, I
was speaking to someone and talking about spiritual gifts and dealing with the particular
spiritual gift that they believed that they had and it really was the gift of exhortation.
And as we were talking and going through this, I began to ask that individual, how do you
think you could use that gift of exhortation?
And we began to talk about some particular opportunities and some ways to use that gift.
And then I walked them down in the basement, down to a bookshelf that has all kinds of
cards on it.
And I said, here are a bunch of cards.
They're at your disposal.
You use them as you'd like to.
Why?
Because if your gift is exhortation, write a card to somebody and exhort them, encourage
them, lift them up.
And I don't know.
I never checked back.
Did they do it?
Did they use them?
Did they go get their own cards?
I don't know.
But I'm trying to help them.
Hey, here's, you've identified your gift.
You want to develop that.
Now use it.
Use it for God's glory.
Why?
Because God gave it to you to be used.
And so where is it to be used?
It's to be used in the local church.
So we look for those opportunities.
You come to me as the pastor.
You say, hey, I want to do, I want to use, and God's given me this gift and I want to
be able to use this for God's glory.
And what a blessing.
I thank the Lord for those within our congregation that use their spiritual gifts to not only
bring glory to God, but to edify the believers.
And we make ourselves available.
We seize the opportunities.
Why?
Because I want to use it.
You know, it's really difficult for me.
There's been times in which I've had super busy times and my schedule is seeming always
busy.
But someone, hey, will you preach this meeting or will you do this?
It's hard for me to say no.
Why?
Because God gave me a gift and I want to be able to use it.
Listen, I don't want to be in a place where we don't have church services because, well,
you know, things are changing and we're just not having night services or this.
No, I know so many people that are canceling church services and here we are adding one
on Wednesday morning.
It's a situation where what I'm saying is that when you know what it is and you've developed
it, you ought to long to use it.
It's not to be stored up.
It's not something that we just kind of keep in a box somewhere.
It's something that we use for God's glory.
And when we do so, not only will God be glorified, not only will the believers be edified, but
I truly believe this, you'll have joy.
You'll have joy.
We sing the song, there is joy in serving Jesus.
It doesn't mean that it's not work.
Serving the Lord is work.
Amen?
And some people have asked me over the years and some people that have taught and preached
in my absence have commented on how challenging it is to, how can you develop so many messages
a week, week after week after week?
Listen, it's labor, but it's joy.
I'm telling you, it's joy.
I absolutely love it.
Why?
Because I know that this is what God equipped me to do.
I know that it's what God gifted me to do.
And I don't say that pridefully, I say that humbly, that to God be the glory.
I want to do it for God's glory and I love doing it.
Is it labor?
Is it work?
Absolutely.
But I promise you, you'll have joy because there's joy in serving Jesus.
We understand that the spiritual gifts as they've been described, defined in God's Word,
and I say, I want to now discover what is my spiritual gift.
And I want to develop this.
Why?
Because I want to use it.
I want to be the best that I can be, not so that anyone would look at me and say, they
should be lifted up.
But also that people would say, this is God's grace.
That God would be glorified and then deploy it, use it for God's glory.
Look for those opportunities, seize those opportunities to be used for God's glory.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you so much for loving us.
We thank you for the spiritual gift, Lord, that you've given to each of us.
We thank you for the truth of your Word.
And I pray that you would help us as your people, Lord, to truly desire to know what
our spiritual gift is, that God, you would reveal it to us.
If maybe there's some here tonight that just don't know what their spiritual gift is, God,
I pray that you would just lay upon their heart a desire to know it, Lord, to be able
to discover what their spiritual gift is.
Maybe there's some that know what their spiritual gift is, but they're just simply not using
it, God, at this time for your glory.
I pray that you'd stir us, Lord.
Help us, even as Paul instructs Timothy, to stir up the gift that is in us, to rekindle,
to redetermine that we will use the gift that you've bestowed upon us for your glory, that
we would be good stewards of the manifold grace of God.
I pray that in the moments of invitation that you'd have your will and way, that you would
work in hearts and lives as only you can, and we'll thank you for it in Christ's name.
We pray.