by the ensemble, and up here in Kimberly,
wonderful special, appreciate that piano and violin.
And then I have come by the way of the cross.
There's no other way, amen.
And it's only by the way of the cross,
and praise the Lord, I made that comment
when I was preaching last week,
and I think that was a catalyst for Brianna.
Actually, on Wednesday night, I think I said it twice,
and she began to look at that song,
and I appreciate her and Holly singing that this morning.
If you have your Bible with you,
1 Corinthians chapter number 15 this morning,
and this is a chapter in the word of God
that is known as the resurrection chapter,
and of course, we won't take the time
to go through the entire chapter this morning.
We'll look at the first nine verses
through the message today.
We've had the opportunity, if you've been here,
for the sunrise service, and then of course,
for this service, during the sunrise service,
we had four young men read
from each of the gospel records,
the account of that first morning,
the resurrection morning, when they arrived at the tomb.
We had Matthew, Mark, Luke, and John all read this morning,
and then Brother Ron read there in Acts
this morning as well.
As we come to 1 Corinthians chapter 15,
let me just read a few verses,
and we'll get into the message this morning.
Beginning in verse number one,
1 Corinthians chapter 15, in verse number one,
notice as Paul begins to write, he says this,
moreover, brethren, I declare unto you the gospel,
which I preached unto you, which also ye have received,
and wherein ye stand, by which also ye are saved,
if ye keep in memory what I preached unto you,
unless ye have believed in vain.
Then notice verses three and four.
He's gonna give us what the gospel is in verse three.
For I delivered unto you, first of all,
that which I also received,
how that Christ died for our sins
according to the Scriptures,
and that he was buried, and that he rose again
the third day according to the Scriptures.
We'll get through verse number nine this morning,
but let me just say this by way of introduction.
We find in these few verses of Scripture
that Paul, once again, is reminding and declaring
to these believers the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
The word gospel, it means good news,
and we find that Paul would say it this way
in Romans chapter number one.
I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ,
for it, the gospel, is the power of God unto salvation
to everyone that believeth,
to the Jew first and also to the Greek,
and we find here that Paul says,
I preached unto you in verse number one,
which also ye received,
in verse number two, by which also ye are saved.
When the apostle Paul, on his missionary journey,
came to the city of Corinth,
we find that it was under the direction of the Lord
that led him to go to Corinth,
and he arrives there, and he comes preaching the gospel.
Why?
Because sinners need the gospel, amen?
Why is it that the Lord Jesus Christ
gave the Great Commission after he resurrected,
after he arose, conquering sin, death, and the grave?
He gives the marching orders to his disciples,
to us, of course, by way of continuation
with regard to the marching orders of the local church,
and that is to preach the gospel to every creature,
and we take the gospel because it is the good news
of Jesus Christ that he, here it is in verses three and four
that he died for our sins,
that he was, verse number four, buried,
and that he, number three, rose again the third day,
according to the scriptures,
and so we find the gospel summarized here
in these simple verses of scripture.
It is that God so loved the world
that he gave his only begotten son
that whosoever believeth in him should not perish,
but have everlasting life, and these people in Corinth,
they heard, as the apostle Paul came in,
the preaching of the gospel,
and these people, they heard the message,
and they recognized, obviously,
as you study through the book of Acts
and see what was transpiring there
during the missionary journey,
and then looking at the letters that he writes,
they received the preaching, he says that in verse number one,
and they stand, why?
Because they were saved by the grace of God.
Listen, there is nothing that can save you,
there is nothing that can save me, but the gospel.
It is the power of God unto salvation,
Christ alone, period.
Not God and his grace, plus your works.
No, it's not by works of righteousness,
which we have done, but by his mercy,
he hath begotten us, he saved us.
You can't cover your sins, you can't pardon your sins,
only the blood of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And we find that the apostle Paul,
as he begins writing in this 15th chapter,
he refers to them as brethren,
he knows that they're saved,
but he's reminding them of the gospel.
Can I tell you, we ought never forget
that we're saved by the grace of God.
Amen.
Brother Fernando was in here yesterday morning
before the outreach, and he asked me about a song,
he's looking at the songbook,
and he asked me about a song,
and I said, oh, I love to tell the story.
Isn't that a wonderful song?
And you know, it's a reminder,
as we would sing a song like that,
but we're loving to tell the story of what?
Of the gospel, if you look at that song
and you understand the gospel that is there,
and I'm so thankful for the truth of the gospel
that we have it, and that's where we stand.
This morning, if you're here
and you've never heard of the gospel,
if you're here, you've never received
the Lord Jesus Christ as your personal savior,
can I tell you this morning
that what you need is to be saved?
That's what you need.
We don't need religion, we don't need, you know,
some kind of good works and baptism
and this and that and so on and so forth,
none of that can save you.
Salvation is through Christ alone.
He paid it all.
He said this before he came off the cross,
paid in full, it is finished.
And hallelujah, it is finished.
There's nothing you can do, there's nothing I can do.
You say, yeah, but I wanna,
man sometimes has this idea
that I need to earn something,
I need to work for something,
but you can't work for something
that's already been paid for.
You just accept it by faith.
And God loves you and he doesn't want you
to spend eternity in the lake of fire.
Your sin has a penalty.
Sin, the wage of sin is death.
But the gift of God is eternal life
through Jesus Christ, our Lord.
And as we come to this 15th chapter
of the book of 1 Corinthians,
we read about the resurrection
and it's the cornerstone of our faith.
In fact, in this text of scripture
and not really that we'll look at this morning
because it's further into the chapter,
but we find that Paul argues that if Christ be not risen,
then both our faith and our preaching is vain.
But he declares, well, let me say this,
not only is our preaching and our faith vain,
but he says this worse yet
is that we would still be in our sins.
He says it this way in verse number 17,
and if Christ be not raised,
your faith is vain, ye are yet in your sins.
But he says this in verse 20,
it's not part of the text
that we're gonna really dive into this morning,
but look at verse number 20,
he says with authority and with confidence,
but now is Christ risen from the dead
and become the first fruits of them that slept.
We serve a risen savior.
It gives us hope as I spoke about this morning
in our sunrise service,
and we find that we had that opportunity,
that first song that we sang this morning
in this nine o'clock service, Christ arose.
He tore the bars away, amen.
Listen, the grave, it could not hold him,
and he rose conquering sin, death, and the grave.
Right now, at this very moment,
our savior, the Lord Jesus Christ is alive and well.
He's in heaven, and the Bible teaches us
that he's interceding for us.
And one day, one glorious day, he's coming back for us.
We heard as Ron read from Acts chapter number one
in verses one through 11,
how that he made himself known,
the many infallible proofs,
and for 40 days, he was teaching,
he gave the great commission,
but then he ascended to heaven,
where he remains to this very day,
seated at the right hand of the throne of God,
and again, making intercession for us.
But here's what the angels there said to the disciples
as they looked steadfastly into heaven.
While he went up, they said,
this same Jesus shall so come in like manner.
He's coming back.
I don't know the day nor the hour, neither do you,
and if someone says they do, they're lying.
Amen?
No one knows the day nor the hour,
but man, he's coming back, and I'm looking forward to it,
and it gives us great confidence and great hope.
And so I'm thankful this morning
for this portion of scripture
that reminds us of the gospel.
Now, as we get into it, in verse number five,
the Bible says that he was seen of Cephas,
then of the 12, after that he was seen of about five.
500 brethren at once of whom the greater part remain under this present, but some are fallen asleep
After that he was seen of James then of all the Apostles and last of all he was seen of me
Also as of one born out of due time for I am the least of the Apostles that I'm not meet to be called an Apostle
Because I persecuted the Church of God
I've simply titled the message this morning the grave could not hold him and as we look at this portion of Scripture
I want to remind you of just two very important things number one if you're taking notes
Just be reminded of this the promise of the resurrection the promise of the resurrection
I want you to take your Bibles return back to the Old Testament in the book of Psalms
And look at two verses here in the book of Psalms, and we read about the promises that God made throughout the scriptures
But here we consider the promise of the resurrection
Here in Psalm chapter 2 in verse number 7 the Bible tells us and here prophesies with regard to
The resurrection of the Lord Jesus Christ. It says this I will declare the decree
Verse 7 the Lord hath said unto me thou art my son
this day
Have I begotten thee?
Now as you compare Scripture with Scripture you find and stay there in the in the book of Psalms
We look at another Psalm in just a moment
But you find that the truth of what he says there this day have I begotten thee again comparing Scripture with Scripture
You understand that this is speaking of the resurrection in fact in verse number 33 of Acts 13
It says God hath fulfilled the same unto us their children and that he hath raised up
Jesus again as it is also written in the second Psalm thou art my son
This day have I begotten thee we read it also in the book of Hebrews again
You don't need to turn there
but in Hebrews 1 in verse number 5 we read again this truth that what's the psalmist is promising and prophesying of is
The resurrection for in Hebrews 1 in verse 5. It says for unto which of the angels said he at any time
Thou art my son this day have I begotten thee and again
I will be to him a father and he shall be to me a son
So we see the promise all the way back in the Psalms
We find that not only here in Psalm 2, but look in Psalm 16
The Bible says in Psalm 16 in verse number 10 again looking at this truth of the promise of the resurrection
We see it in the Old Testament and in Psalm chapter 16 in verse number 10. The Bible says for thou
Will not leave my soul in hell
Neither will thou suffer thine holy one to see
corruption
Many of us are familiar with Isaiah 53 and I want you to take a moment to turn there and often as we read
Isaiah 53 we think and and recognize the the truth of the the Lord Jesus Christ the
Suffering Lamb of God and we see it beautifully painted here in
Understanding what he would do for the sin of humanity and how he would pay for the sin of the world
in fact in verse number 4 of Isaiah 53
The Bible says surely he hath borne our griefs and carried our sorrows
Yet we did esteem him stricken smitten of God and afflicted
But he was wounded for our
transgressions he was bruised for our
Iniquities the chastisement of our peace was upon him and with his stripes
We are healed all we like sheep have gone astray
We have turned everyone to his own way and the Lord hath laid on him the iniquity of us all
He was oppressed and he was afflicted
Yet he opened not his mouth
He is brought as a lamb to the slaughter and as a sheep before her shearers is dumb
So he opened not his mouth
verse 8 he was taken from prison and from judgment and
Who shall declare his generation?
For he was cut off out of the land of the living for the transgression of my people was he stricken?
And he made his grave with the wicked and with the rich in his death because he had done no violence
Neither was any deceit in his mouth
And so you see verse 8 the death the verse 9 the burial in verse number 10
It says yet it pleased the Lord to bruise him
Why because he was paying for the sin of humanity
The only way for sin to be dealt with was through the Lord Jesus Christ God and flesh dying in our place
He says this he hath put him to grief when thou shalt make his soul an offering for sin
He shall see his seed and then look at this phrase he shall
prolong his days and the pleasure of the Lord shall prosper in his hand
He was not gonna stay dead
He was gonna rise and he did we see the promise as we look in the book of Psalms
We see it here that he shall prolong his days
You see the death the burial in the resurrection in Isaiah 53 and how beautiful it is
But not only do we see the promise of the resurrection in the Old Testament
I want you to consider the words of Jesus Christ himself. Look in the Gospel of Matthew if you will
Look at two portions of scripture in the Gospel of Matthew and then two over in the Gospel of John
But look at first at Matthew chapter 16, if you will Matthew chapter number 16
In Matthew chapter number 16, there's a question that Jesus asks that
Is such an important question and it's a question that still today needs to be answered
By every individual person and the question is simply this who is Jesus?
He asks it this way in verse number 13
Whom do men say that I the Son of Man am and so Jesus asked the disciples who are people?
saying that I am and the answer comes back and they said well some say that thou art John the Baptist and
Some say that thou art Elias and others Jeremiah's or one of the prophets we see that in verse number 14 and and this was the common
Understanding of those that were there in the in the time of Christ. They had all of this varying perspective
Can I tell you that still exists today?
You take a survey you talk to people who is Jesus? Well, Jesus a prophet. No, he's more than a prophet
Well, Jesus was a good man. No, he's more than a good man
Well, Jesus was a you start filling the blank who is Jesus and the truth is that Jesus is God
He is God in flesh and
Today there are still people that will answer the question the way that those in the first century
Well, some say that thou art
John the Baptist Elijah the prophets Jeremiah
Whomever it may be and you talk to people and I've often done this in in soul winning interactions
I've said listen, can I ask you a question that Jesus asked while he was on this earth?
Here's the question. They asked who am I who do men say that I am then he says to the disciples in verse number 15
He says this he says but whom say ye that I am
They respond well Peter responds thou art the Christ the Son of the Living God and what a great
declaration that that Peter makes there in verse number 16 as he
Acknowledged and understood the truth and he said this Jesus responds and says this blessed art thou Simon Barjona
For flesh and blood hath not revealed it unto thee but my father which is in heaven
And we find that this truth of how the Lord
Confirms truth to us and how the Father made this known revealed this to Peter. What a blessing
But Jesus on the heels of this interaction. He made a great promise
He said that he would build his church and the gates of hell shall not prevail against it
But then he tells them this in verse number 21 on the heels of this
Interaction of whom do men say that I am whom say ye that I am I'm gonna build my church and he goes through this
Wonderful revelation to these disciples and in verse 21, it says from that time forth
So Jesus beginning at this moment after this interaction
He says from that time forth began Jesus notice what it says
to show
unto his disciples
how that he must go unto
Jerusalem and
suffer many things of the elders and chief priests and scribes and be killed and be raised again
The third day in that awesome
Jesus himself as he's ministering to his disciples as he has this interaction with them
He then says to them listen, I want you to understand
I want you to be aware of the fact that that I must go to Jerusalem and that when I get to Jerusalem
I'm gonna suffer many things and I'm gonna be put to death, but I'm gonna rise again
Hallelujah, we find in Matthew chapter number 20 look there if you will just a few pages over but we find that here as
Jesus again is speaking in verse 17
The Bible says this and Jesus going up to Jerusalem took the twelve disciples apart in the way and said unto them so again
He's speaking to his disciples and he says behold we go up to Jerusalem
And the Son of Man shall be betrayed
under the chief priests and under the scribes and they shall condemn him to
death and shall deliver him to the Gentiles to mock and to scourge and to
crucify him and the third day he shall rise again." Did you see in verse 18 and
19 the word shall? The Bible said there in verse number 18 that he was gonna go
and that they shall condemn him to death and shall, verse number 19, deliver him to
the Gentiles but then he says and and he shall rise again. This is a promise of
certainty. This is a word that is used to communicate certainty of something
transpiring. We find that he did not say I might go to Jerusalem and this might
happen. No, this shall happen. Man, hallelujah. Now understand the disciples
didn't really catch all of this when all that had transpired. In fact, when you
read the the records of that first morning, that resurrection morning, how
that they were distressed and overwhelmed and all that was going on
and then it says then remembered they his words. And so we find here that Jesus
is communicating effectively to his followers as to what was going to
transpire. Now he's speaking of something that would happen in the
future. We look back at something that happened in the past and we find that we
have the same level of confidence and certainty that these disciples would
have through hearing those words of the Lord Jesus Christ and I'm so thankful
that Jesus communicated this. He made the promise with regard to his death and his
burial in his resurrection to his disciples. Look in John chapter number
two if you will. In John chapter number two and I'll just briefly mention this
portion of Scripture for we looked at it last week but in John chapter number two
in verses 19 through 21 Jesus here is beginning his earthly ministry and we
find that over the last period of time chapter one reveals twice where John the
Baptist says behold the Lamb of God which taketh away the sin of the world
and there's interactions that take place and we find that Jesus now with the
religious leaders that are gathered together he says in verse number 19 to
these he says Jesus answered and said unto them destroy this temple and in
three days I will raise it up. Verse 20 the Jews they said this forty and six
years was this temple in building and wilt thou rear it up in three days but
he spake of the temple of his body so what did he say to these Jewish people
he said destroy this temple in other words put me to death and he knew that
would happen he was born to die and the Bible says and in three days I will
raise it up. John chapter number 10 the passage that deals with Jesus being our
good shepherd I'm thankful that he is our shepherd the Bible says in the book
of Psalms and Psalm 23 probably one of the most familiar Psalms of all of the
Psalms the Lord is my shepherd hallelujah in fact because of that
personal relationship that David had with the shepherd that he could say that
he would dwell I shall dwell in the house of the Lord forever that's how the
Psalm ends and I've often said that there's a direct connection between
verse 1 and verse 6 of Psalm 23 you can only say I will dwell in the house of
the Lord forever if you can also say the Lord is my shepherd he's the shepherd
but is he my shepherd is he your shepherd we find that the New Testament
reveals to us that he is the good shepherd that he is the great shepherd
and he is the chief shepherd we don't look at what all of those are
communicating to us but here in John chapter number 10 he's communicating the
fact that he's the good shepherd and as the good shepherd what the good shepherd
does is he gives his life for the sheep in John chapter number 10 the Bible says
this in in verse number let's look at verse number 10 the thief cometh not but
for to steal and to kill and to destroy I am come they might have life and they
might have it more abundantly I am the good shepherd and the good shepherd
giveth his life for the sheep verse 12 but he that is an hireling and not the
shepherd whose own the sheep are not see it the wolf coming and leaveth the
sheep and fleeth and the wolf catcheth them and scattereth the sheep the
hireling fleeth because he is an hireling and careth not for the sheep
verse 14 again I am the good shepherd and know my sheep and am known of mine
the father knoweth me even so know I the father and I lay down my life for the
sheep he said in verse number 11 that the good shepherd giveth his life for
the sheep in verse number 15 I laid down my life for the sheep and notice
in verse number 16 and other sheep I have which are not of this fold them
also I must bring they shall hear my voice and there shall be one fold and
one shepherd therefore doth my father love me because I lay down my life and
then notice these words that I might take it again no man verse 18 taketh it
from me but I lay it down of myself I have power to lay it down and I have
power to take it again this commandment have I received of my father I'm so
thankful that he laid down his life but I'm so thankful that he raised it up
again that he did not stay dead he rose conquering sin death in the grave and so
we see the promise of his resurrection but I want you to notice number two the
proof of his resurrection the proof of his resurrection and we find that here
as we look and we read earlier in Acts chapter number one that it was by many
infallible proofs see the Lord wanted to make sure this thing was known abroad he
understood the way that the enemy would work and he understood the way that
anybody would try to deny the reality of the resurrection he knew the
significance of the resurrection and so the proof is given to us we find first I
would say this and we'll look at five different areas in which we look at the
proof of the resurrection number one at the tomb at the tomb hey we won't read
all of the records but in Matthew chapter number 28 we read of Matthew's
gospel giving to us the record of the resurrection at the tomb that morning
and the Bible says in verse number one of Matthew 28 in the end of the Sabbath
as it began to dawn toward the first day of the week came Mary Magdalene and the
other Mary to see the sepulcher and behold there was a great earthquake for
the angel of the Lord descended from heaven and came and rolled back the
stone from the door and sat upon it his countenance was like lightning and his
raiment white as snow and for fear of him the the keepers did shake and became
as dead men notice the verse 5 it says the angel answered and said unto the
women fear not ye for I know that you seek Jesus which was crucified he is not
here for he is risen as he said come see the place where the Lord lay huh I mean
listen the proof of his resurrection is there at the tomb that morning early as
they came and they were other gospel records revealed to us that they're kind
of having this conversation who's gonna move the stone it's too big for us and
what's going to happen and all of these types of things and they went with the
preparation the idea of that's what they would do is prepare the body but we find
that Jesus was already risen he had conquered sin death in the grave we see
it at the tomb we see it the proof with the disciples on the road to Emmaus I
love Luke chapter 24 and look there if you will in the gospel of Luke in
chapter number 24 we read I don't have the time to read all of it but but to
summarize and to get to where we're going to be here in Luke chapter 24 as
you're turning there these disciples are walking on the way to way to Emmaus it's
an almost seven mile journey from Jerusalem to Emmaus they're walking
there and their countenance is sad because of all the things that had
transpired in Jerusalem and they're talking about those things and they're
sad and Jesus shows up and they don't know that it's Jesus when he shows up
there and begins to walk with them and he's walking with them and they their
eyes they did not know that it was Jesus and we find that as he's walking with
them he's hearing what they're saying and he's interacting with them and he
begins to the Bible tells us he begins to expound unto them all things in the
scriptures concerning himself and as he's giving this this teaching
opportunity as he's giving this truth to these these disciples on the road to
Emmaus we find that they finally finish their journey and they arrive home and
Jesus would have just kept on going according to the text but they invited
the Bible says that they constrained him in verse 29 saying abide with us for
this toward evening and the day is far spent he went into Terry with them and
it came to pass in verse
as he sat at meat with them,
he took bread and blessed it and break and gave to them.
And look at verse 31, it says this,
and their eyes were opened and they knew him
and he vanished out of their sight.
And they said one to another,
notice what they say in verse 32,
did not our heart burn within us?
When?
While we talked with us, while he talked with us,
by the way, and while he opened to us the scriptures.
You know what they did?
They turned around and went right back to Jerusalem.
6.8 miles, they just walked that.
They say in verse number 29 that it was evening
and it was toward evening and the day was far spent.
But they turn around and go right back to Jerusalem, why?
Because they're so excited,
the joy that they have in seeing the resurrected Christ.
And they go back to deliver the message.
Do you know what they find when they get there?
They find that the disciples are gathered there
and there's this, we use the phrase,
the Lord is risen indeed, and we see it in verse number 34.
The proof of the resurrection.
His disciples in John chapter number 20.
You'd look at the disciples as they're gathered here
in John chapter number 20.
You begin to notice here,
the Bible says that it was the same day
as we're looking at that day, that resurrection day.
The events that took place at the tomb,
the encouragement to come and see the place where he lay,
but then go quickly and tell his disciples.
We find here in John chapter number 20, in verse number 19,
the Bible says then the same day at evening.
So this is the resurrection day, but now it's evening.
The Bible says being the first day of the week
when the doors were shut,
where the disciples were assembled for fear of the Jews.
The Bible says came Jesus and stood in the midst
and saith unto them, peace be unto you.
And when he had so said,
he showed unto them his hands and his side.
Then were the disciples glad when they saw the Lord.
Then said Jesus to them again, peace be unto you.
As my father hath sent me, even so send I you.
We find that, yes, at the tomb and the record
that is given to us in each of the gospels.
Yes, we see the disciples on the road to Emmaus,
but now we see the disciples that are gathered here
in John chapter number 20.
We find that the Bible specifically tells us
that Thomas was not with them.
Thomas wasn't there that day.
The Bible says in verse 24, but Thomas,
one of the 12 called Didymus,
was not with them when Jesus came.
Now in that unfortunate,
he wasn't where he should have been.
The Bible says in verse 25,
the other disciples therefore said unto him,
we have seen the Lord, but he said unto them,
except I shall see in his hands the print of the nails
and put my finger into the print of the nails
and thrust my hand into his side, I will not believe.
You know, there's some people today
that still have that kind of perspective of Thomas.
Not gonna believe.
They're looking for some fantastic demonstration
of some miraculous whatever.
And the reality is that when you look at the Scriptures,
God has given to us a completed word.
In fact, the Bible tells us as the interaction
that takes place there with the rich man and Lazarus
that he desires that Lazarus go back from the dead
and go talk to his brethren.
But the Bible says that they have Moses and the prophets.
If they won't believe them,
neither will they believe though one rose from the dead.
And we begin to look at the truth
of what we find in the Scriptures
with regard to Thomas saying, I will not believe.
He had this determined perspective.
It reminds me of Naaman in 2 Kings chapter five.
You don't need to turn there.
But Naaman had this leprosy and he had this confidence
that there was an opportunity to be healed.
And he comes to Elisha,
and Elisha doesn't even come out and do anything.
He just tells him to go dip in the river seven times.
You know what Naaman's gonna do?
He's gonna go back home.
Because he said, I expected the man of God
to come out and like call and do this big display.
And thankfully, one of the servants said,
won't you just do what he said?
And he did seven times and guess what?
The leprosy was gone.
Hallelujah.
I mean, praise the Lord.
And so there's some today that still say I will not believe.
But God's given to us all of this evidence,
all of this proof.
And he says this, and I'm thankful for the grace of God.
I'm thankful that our God is long suffering toward us.
And the Bible says in verse 26,
and after eight days again, his disciples were within,
and notice what it says, and Thomas with them.
I'd love to preach a message just on that,
but I don't have time this morning.
Listen, he missed it the first time.
He made sure he was there the next time, amen?
And he didn't know that God,
the Lord was gonna come again,
but he was there and he's gathered together.
Then came Jesus, the doors being shut
and stood in the midst and said, peace be unto you.
Then notice the grace of our God.
In verse 27, then saith he to Thomas.
He said, reach hither thy finger and behold my hands.
And reach hither thy hand and thrust it into my side.
And be not faithless, but believing.
Thomas answered and said unto him, my Lord and my God.
Wow, what an interaction that Thomas had this day.
Eight days after, a week later after the resurrection,
they're assembled there and Jesus appears
and we find that he declares my Lord and my God.
By the way, those that might argue that Jesus is not God,
we find very plainly even in this text
where Thomas says my Lord and my God,
surely if Jesus knew that he was not God,
he would not let someone call him God.
You're not gonna let anyone call you God.
I'm not gonna let anyone call me God.
I know I'm not.
And I'm pretty sure you know that you're not, amen?
And the reality is this, Jesus knew exactly who he was.
Throughout the Gospels, he allows worship to take place
after he says that the only one to be worshiped is God.
And then yet he allows people to worship him, why?
Because he's God, praise the Lord.
And so we find that Thomas here has this opportunity
and he declares my Lord and my God.
And notice what Jesus said to him in verse 29.
Thomas, because thou hast seen me, thou hast believed.
Blessed are they that have not seen and yet have believed.
We have the scriptures.
Listen, I would think that would refer to us.
I've not seen the Lord.
I've not seen the risen savior.
But man, we have the Bible and we believe the record
of God's word that we serve a risen savior.
Now get back to 1 Corinthians 15
and we'll be done this morning.
But look at 1 Corinthians 15.
As we look at the proof of the resurrection,
Paul had declared the gospel to them
and he gives them the truth of the death,
the burial and the resurrection.
But then we speak of the many infallible proofs.
We speak of the proof of his resurrection,
the evidence that he is risen indeed.
And we find that in verse number five, he begins,
Paul, starting here and down through verse number eight,
he begins to share a record of the evidence,
the proof of the resurrection.
He says this after he makes the declaration
that he rose again the third day,
according to the scriptures,
and that he was seen, verse number five, of Cephas, Peter.
Then of the 12, all of the disciples.
And then it says in verse number six,
after that, he was seen, notice what the Bible says,
of above 500 brethren at once.
It's a good sized crowd.
And he appears to them.
And the Bible doesn't stop there,
but notice what the Bible says,
of whom the greater part remain unto this present.
You know what that means?
It means they're still alive.
The writing of the book of 1 Corinthians,
it's only been 25-ish years since the resurrection,
and those 500 people that he appeared to at once,
that the greater part of them were still alive.
So guess what?
You could still go talk to them as an eyewitness account
of seeing the resurrected Christ.
He ends verse number six by saying,
but some are fallen asleep.
In other words, part of those 500 had died.
Not all of them were still alive,
but the greater part of them.
Wow, the proof, the evidence that we have.
And Paul continues, and he says in verse number seven,
after that, he was seen of James,
then of all the apostles, verse eight.
And last of all, he was seen of me also
as of one born out of due time.
By the way, that's the truth of Paul being an apostle.
He saw the resurrected Christ.
And it says in verse number eight,
last of all, he was seen of me also
as of one born out of due time.
due time. Now remember, Jesus appeared to him. The road to Damascus, that bright
light show. Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me? Who art thou, Lord? Lord, what
wilt thou have me to do? In Acts chapter number 9. And Jesus appeared to him.
And then the Bible tells us that Paul gives the testimony that he had
the opportunity that when he had, and he was preaching and giving the truth of
his doctrine, he says that he didn't receive it of man, neither was taught it
by man, but by the revelation of Jesus Christ in Galatians 1 and verse number
12. He says I'm the least of the Apostles, then I'm not meet to be called an
Apostle, because I persecuted the Church of God. Listen, this morning if Jesus is
not risen, our preaching is vain, our faith is vain, and we're still in our
sins. But Christ is risen, and we have hope. We have the assurance. There's the
promise. Listen, God never fails on a promise that he makes. Every promise of
God is certain, is sure. That's why when 2nd Peter talks about those scoffers
and mockers about the Lord coming back, he says the Lord is not slack concerning
his promises. Some men count slackness. Listen, Jesus the Lord is gonna do
exactly what he said he would do. And when he told his disciples, when he
revealed to them that he would go to Jerusalem, that he would die, that he
would be buried, and that he would rise again, he did all of it. He didn't just
fulfill the promise that he would go to Jerusalem. He didn't just fulfill the
promise that he would be crucified. He didn't just fulfill the promise that he
would be buried, and then it ends. No, he fulfilled the very promise to the end
that he rose again. And indeed, we serve a risen Savior. And since we serve a risen
Savior, we talked in the seven o'clock service about the hope that we have. We
ought to live with the hope of the resurrection. Every day of our lives we
ought to be reminding ourselves, he lives. He lives. I serve a risen Savior. My hope
is in Jesus. And I know that we have certain songs that we sing on Easter
Sunday, Resurrection Sunday, but the reality is every single Sunday we gather
because we serve a risen Savior. We gather on the first day because it was
the day that he rose from the dead. And every day of your life, and every day of
my life, we need to walk in the resurrection power of the Lord Jesus
Christ. The promise is there, and the proof is there. And he, as we look
at the gospel, the death, the burial, and the glorious resurrection, he did it all
to pay for the sins of humanity. To pay for the sins of humanity. And we must not
miss that. This morning, if you're not sure of heaven, today is the day of
salvation. Don't leave here without knowing for sure that heaven is your
home. I plead with you. I beg you. We're gonna have an invitation in just a
moment. When we do, people will have their heads bowed and their eyes closed so that
no one would be embarrassed. We'll have someone up here, a man up here, that if
you're a man, we'll have Mark meet with you. If you're a lady, have my wife meet
with you. Holly, be able to take a Bible and show you could know for sure that
heaven is your home. I don't want anyone to leave here without knowing for sure. I
can't make you, but man, I'd rejoice with you. I'd love for you to know for sure
that heaven is your home. Why? Because the gospel is the power of God unto
salvation to everyone that believeth. I remember the day that I got saved. What a
wonderful day it was. I was born again. My life was changed forever. And I hope
this morning, for those of us that are saved, that we remember that and that we
go in the power of the resurrection. You say, oh, all this stuff is bad. Listen, he
lives. He lives. He's got a plan for you and a plan for me. He's coming back for
us on our worst day. He lives. And on our worst day, we're not going to hell.
Hallelujah. He lives. Praise God. Go out today with that glorious message. He
lives. The grave could not hold him. Let's pray. Father, we do love you this
morning. We thank you so much for loving us. Thank you for the privilege of being
able to gather together. Thank you for the promise of the resurrection, not only
in the Old Testament, but by the Lord Jesus Christ himself during his earthly
ministry. Thank you for the proof that we read as we look through the scriptures.
And Lord, we thank you that today we can have that confidence, that assurance
that you live, that you conquered sin, death, and the grave, that you're alive
forevermore. Thank you for saving my soul. God, I pray for every Christian here,
everyone that's been born again. They've recognized that they're a sinner and
that you're the only Savior. There's nothing they could do to save themselves
and they trust that Christ is their personal Savior. God, would you help us to
go in the power of the resurrection? Would you help us to have that great joy
knowing that we serve a risen Savior? Would you help us to spread the message
far and wide that Jesus saves? Father, I acknowledge that there may be someone
here this morning, whether they're here present or tuned in via live stream, that
may not know for sure that heaven is their home. In fact, the thought of dying
brings them fear and concern because of the uncertainty. God, I pray that the Holy
Spirit in this very moment would convict them of their sin, of Christ's
righteousness, and of judgment to come. They would come in the moment of
invitation here. They'd get it settled. They'd accept Jesus Christ as their
personal Savior. I pray, Father, that you would work in these moments of
invitation. Thank you for the Word. We pray that it would now, that we would
respond in obedience. We'll give you the glory for all that you'll do. For it's in
Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
No one's looking around. We don't want anyone to get embarrassed. But if you're
not sure of heaven this morning, Mark is here with a Bible. Holly's here with a
Bible. We'd love to take a Bible and show you how you could know for sure that
heaven is your home. I don't want you to leave here without knowing that. You say,
I'm just not sure. Get it settled. These things have I written unto you that
you believe on the name of the Son of God that you may know that you have eternal
life. Maybe you're a Christian here this morning. You've trusted Christ. Maybe you
just want to come and pray. Thank God for the resurrection. Thank God for the power
of the resurrection. Ask Him to help you every day to live with that joy, with
that hope. As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.