Number 11, and as you take a moment
to grab your Bible and turn there,
I just wanna once again thank the church
for your support of our young people.
It is the future of our church,
and we need to invest and influence
and pray for the young people,
and so I wanna encourage you to pray for these
that have made decisions and certainly thankful
for what God has done in this past week
and how God is working in their lives.
Hebrews chapter number 11, I referenced briefly
at the end of the message this morning
as we looked at Hebrews 12, one and two
in closing the message this morning,
I referenced some about this 11th chapter
here in the book of Hebrews.
We've often referred to, I'm sure you've heard somebody
refer to this passage as being the hall of faith chapter.
Many would refer to those that are written here
and named in this chapter as the heroes of the faith,
and we see that these are individuals
that were called by God to fulfill
what God had for them as individuals.
By faith, they obeyed the Lord,
they finished, fulfilled what God had for them,
and it certainly is encouraging to read this chapter
and to be encouraged by what God has done in their lives,
but even before you get into all of the real,
maybe well-known events, I notice a statement
in verse number five that just captured my attention
as we were praying for our young people
throughout the week, being at teen camp,
and as I was preparing the message this morning
and just looking even in our Sunday school class
this morning with the life of Samuel
and how the Bible says that Samuel judged Israel
all the days of his life, and he was faithful to serve God,
though he had a ministry that was taxing, no doubt,
traveling from city to city and judging the people,
and yet, because of his connection to God,
we find that he was able to serve God
all the days of his life.
If you look in the passages I mentioned
in Sunday school this morning,
the key to that portion of scripture
is that in Ramah, his hometown,
he built there an altar unto the Lord,
and how important worship is in our time with God.
I was so just disappointed to hear the statistic
that Brianna shared that the average,
I'm not sure who they survey
when they come up with those statistics.
I wasn't called, I'm sure that many of you were not called,
but it's so frightening to me to think
that there would be any group of people
that would claim to be followers of the Lord Jesus Christ
and the average time spent in prayer to be two minutes.
That's sad.
There's a book that I was made aware of back in 1997,
and that book was on a very prominent display
in a Christian bookstore,
and that book was entitled
How to Pray in Nine Minutes and 59 Seconds,
and I thought how horrible of a title of a book that must be
that we're gonna try to squeeze God
into less than 10 minutes.
The reality is that now two minutes
is what this statistic is,
and yet the reality is that we can spend
as much time with God as we want.
What a privilege.
I'm so thankful that God doesn't say time's up, next.
We just enter into his presence,
bring our petitions before his throne.
As I look at this passage of scripture,
I've used the title from verse number five.
He had this testimony.
Look at what the Bible says in Hebrews 11 in verse five.
And by faith Enoch was translated
that he should not see death and was not found
because God had translated him for before his translation,
he, Enoch, had this testimony.
Notice that he pleased God.
I wonder this evening if someone were to summarize my life,
if someone were to summarize your life
with just one statement,
that's all they were allowed to have,
was one statement to summarize your life,
I wonder what it would be.
I wonder how somebody would summarize.
I'm not asking how you would summarize your life.
I'm asking how someone else might summarize your life.
And then if we take it even a step further,
we can ask ourselves this question,
how would God summarize our lives?
Because here God is giving us a summary statement
of the life of Enoch.
We know the Bible says in the book of Genesis,
if you were to go back there,
we won't take the time to do so.
But Enoch walked with God and he was not for God took him.
Huh, what an amazing testimony.
As I think about the summary statement
that's found here in our passage of scripture,
the Bible says he had this testimony,
four simple words that he pleased God.
We really could say it's three words, he pleased God.
Wow, what an incredible testimony.
These three words that are provided to us in Hebrews 11
in verse number five, he pleased God.
I believe that those three words, this testimony of Enoch,
those words are insightful.
They reveal to us something about Enoch's walk with God.
They reveal something to us about the seriousness of Enoch
seeking to please the Lord with his life
and having that single mindedness.
I think about Enoch and I think about us today,
how much we have that he did not have.
We have the whole Bible.
We have the Holy Spirit of God that indwells us.
And Enoch had this testimony, he pleased God.
Not only is the testimony that's given here
in Hebrews 11 in verse five insightful,
I believe it should be impactful to each of us
as we evaluate this testimony, as we ponder the thought
of what's really the full meaning of this statement
that he pleased God, that we too as a child of God,
that we would say that it would be our desire
that God would summarize our lives
with those same three words, that they pleased God,
that they pleased God.
See, this evening we must, as we look at the day and age
in which we live, we must avoid the temptation
to please ourselves.
We live in a society that's pumping our minds full
of the idea that you just live your life
to please yourself and you do what makes you feel good
and you do what brings you that fulfillment.
That is not biblical, that is not having
a biblical worldview and we must avoid the temptation.
We find that there are those, in fact, Paul says this
in Philippians two, in verse number 21,
when he's speaking about sending Timothy
to the church in Philippi, he says of others,
he says the reason he's sending Timothy is because he knew
that Timothy was like-minded and would naturally care
for their estate, but he says for all seek their own
and not the things which are Jesus Christ.
I think this evening that what Paul,
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
acknowledged to the believers in Philippi
of those that were seeking their own is certainly true
even in the day and age in which we live.
So many are just seeking to please themselves.
There's a danger in trying to please others.
People live their lives trying to please someone.
The only one that we should really desire to please is God.
And the reality is that if we walk with God
and we have that testimony that he pleased God,
then God's gonna take care of all the other things.
See, I'd rather have the testimony of Enoch
that he pleased God and maybe disappointed some other people
than to please some other people and disappoint God.
As I think about this testimony of Enoch
in these three simple words that he pleased God,
I wonder this evening how it could be said of you
and how it could be said of me that we would please God.
How could we live a life that's pleasing to God?
Have you ever had maybe an employer, a supervisor,
that you sought to please and found it
to be quite frustrating because you just didn't know
what you could do to please that person?
It didn't seem to matter from day to day,
things would shift and change
and maybe they had a shifting type of personality
and you did something yesterday that pleased them
but today it's not satisfactory
and it's frustrating and it just can be infuriating
because some people come to the end of themselves
and I just don't know what to do to please you.
People can feel that way.
Can I tell you this evening,
we don't ever have to feel that way with God.
You know why?
He's given us a full Bible and he's told us
within the pages of this wonderful book what pleases him
and he's told us those things that do not please him
and we ought to be thankful for that.
We ought to rejoice in knowing that God has given us
in his word the revelation of not only himself
but of those things that please him
so that we can take note as we study
through the pages of this book
and as we read and meditate upon the truth
that's contained therein and we find that these things
please God and these things displease God
that we can personally apply those things in our lives
so that why?
So that we can have that testimony that we please God.
that we please God.
As I think about this testimony of Enoch, I am mindful of the Apostle Paul and his concern
for those that he had the opportunity to minister to, and this evening I just want to share
two thoughts with you with this idea of pleasing the Lord within the parameters, if you will,
of the ministry of the Apostle Paul.
Of course, God used Paul in a great way, and Paul is a man that desired to please the Lord.
We looked at Philippians 2.21, but in 1.21 he says, for me to live is Christ and to die
is gain.
And I think that summarizes a life testimony of the Apostle Paul that he was living his
life in such a way that his single focused desire was to please God.
I don't think Paul was concerned about pleasing Peter.
I don't think Paul was concerned about pleasing Timothy or fill in the blank.
Paul was concerned about pleasing God, singularly.
As we understand the Apostle Paul in his own life and his ministry, God used him to
serve and minister a number of people.
Churches that were established through missionary journeys, churches that were contacted and
written to under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God so that they would grow in their
faith, and Paul, as we look at his writing and we look at his ministry and God gives
us a picture, a glimpse into the heart of Paul, I notice this evening within the context
of this subject matter of pleasing God, if you're taking notes, number one, I want you
to consider with me the concern of the Apostle Paul.
I want you to think about the Apostle Paul and his concern for those that God would give
him the opportunity to minister to.
Look over the book of Ephesians, if you will, and as we look at the book of Ephesians and
understand here what's taking place and looking at the ministry of the Apostle Paul and we
find here that Paul has this understanding that as he is writing to these and as he's
had the opportunity to minister to these individuals, that he speaks about hearing, receiving a
report with regard to their walk with God.
Now why is that important?
Well Paul was praying for these believers.
Often you find in the letters that he writes that he's writing to them and he shares with
them how he's praying for them, but you also find that Paul is concerned on receiving a
report to know how they're doing, to understand how their walk with God is, how they've been
able to endure the attacks of the enemy.
When you look at the believers in Thessalonica, he deals with that specifically, and we find
that Paul, it's revealed to us his concern.
Notice with the believers in Ephesus, in Ephesians 1 and verse 15, the Bible says this,
Therefore I also, after I heard of your faith in the Lord Jesus and love unto all the saints,
cease not to give thanks for you, making mention of you in my prayers, and then we find that
Paul begins to, and we're not gonna unwrap all of what he prays throughout the end of
the chapter, but we find that Paul specifically is saying I'm praying for you.
But when I think about the concern of the Apostle Paul, I want you to understand that
in the particular time, they don't have the technology that we have today, and Paul is
interested in receiving a report from these believers at Ephesus.
He wants to know how they're doing in their walk with God.
He wants to, he's interested, he's concerned to know if these believers at this church
in Ephesus that he was privileged, allowed of God to see planted and established, he
wants to know are they continuing in the faith, are they walking with God, are they
pleasing the Lord.
We find that Paul no doubt sends and he's interested in receiving words so that he can
hear this report.
We find in the book of Philippians that Paul is writing to this church, again that he had
the opportunity to be able to see established, and we find that Paul mentions even in the
first chapter again to the believers at Philippi in Philippians 1 and verse 27, notice what
he says, only let your conversation be as it becometh the gospel of Christ, that whether
I come and see you or else be absent, notice what he says, I may hear of your affairs,
that you stand fast in one spirit with one mind, striving together for the faith of the
gospel.
Paul says, listen, whether I'm there or I cannot come, I desire to hear.
I want to receive this report, I want to be aware of the fact that you're serving and
pleasing the Lord.
As best we can tell, in the book of Colossians, Paul is writing to a group of people that
he never had the privilege of actually personally ministering to.
The church at Colossae is not a church that Paul had the privilege of starting and establishing,
but we find that Paul hears about their faith, he receives word about this group of believers
in the city of Colossae, and we find that Paul, when he heard about their walk with
God, it was encouraging to him, and he then sends a letter, yes, under the inspiration
of the Holy Spirit of God, but in that letter, he reveals to them how he's praying for them
that they would please God, that they would serve the Lord, that they would stand fast,
that they would continue in the faith.
Notice the Bible says in Colossians 1 and verse number 3, we give thanks to God and
the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, praying always for you, since we heard of your faith
in Christ Jesus, and of the love which you have to all the saints, and we find that the
Apostle Paul, if you were to read verses 9 through 14, you can see the content really
of how he's praying for their growth.
Notice specifically in verse number 10, that ye might walk worthy of the Lord unto all
pleasing.
What's Paul's concern for these believers in Colossae?
That they would have the testimony that Enoch had, that they pleased God.
He's praying to that end, that they would walk worthy of the Lord unto all pleasing.
Notice it says, being fruitful in every good work, and increasing in the knowledge of God.
It's a great study to study the prayers of the Apostle Paul, and then to take as we learn
how Paul prayed for believers, and to incorporate those same truths in our prayer lives.
So often, if we're not careful, our prayer time consists of more temporal things one
for another, than spiritual things.
And we find that as you would read the prayers of the Apostle Paul, as he's writing to these
believers, that they are full of spiritual truth.
He's praying for their spiritual growth.
He's praying here that they would be fruitful in every good work, as it's already been said
by our missionary and by Brianna during the testimony time.
We don't do good works to get saved or to stay saved.
As you study through the pages of God's precious Word, you find that salvation is a free gift.
He didn't just put a down payment on your salvation.
He paid for it all.
There's nothing you can do to earn or to keep your salvation.
We are kept by the power of God, and for that we must rejoice.
But we find that Paul is concerned that these believers in Ephesus, in Philippi, in Colossae,
that they would have this testimony that they pleased God.
Notice in the book of 1 Thessalonians, I mentioned earlier how Paul is so concerned for this
group of believers.
It's interesting when you see the heart of the Apostle Paul here with the group of believers
in Thessalonica.
And you know that his time was short there in Thessalonica.
Those that were against him and the enemy, they ran him out of town very quickly.
But we find that in 1 Thessalonians 2, in verse number 12, notice the Bible says that
you would walk worthy of God, who hath called you into his kingdom and glory.
Think about that.
Again, pleasing God, that he pleased God, that's what it said of Enoch.
Here he says that they would walk worthy of God.
I do not think that it would be inappropriate to say that those terminologies could be used
synonymously.
That they'd walk worthy of God, that they would please God.
And we find here that Paul has that desire, he has that concern for these believers in
Thessalonica.
In chapter 3, in verse number 1, it says,
Wherefore, when we could no longer forbear, we thought it good to be left in Athens alone
and sent Timotheus our brother and minister of God and our fellow laborer in the gospel
of Christ to establish you and to comfort you concerning your faith.
Why?
That no man should be moved by these afflictions for yourselves.
Know that we are appointed thereunto, for verily when we were with you, we told you
before that we should suffer tribulation, even as it has come to pass, and ye know.
For this cause.
Notice what Paul says.
When I could no longer forbear, I sent to know your faith.
And that's concern on the part of the spiritual leader, the apostle Paul.
Why does Paul care?
Because he knows they're going to stand before Christ one day.
And he wants them to be able to have that testimony that they pleased God.
Did Paul have that desire himself?
Absolutely.
But Paul had that desire, that concern for those that God would enable him to minister
to.
He continues in verse number five and says,
Lest by some means the tempter have tempted you and our labor be in vain
We have an enemy
We have an enemy and the Bible tells us the enemy is seeking whom he may devour
That's what the enemy is doing. He's active
And we find that Paul I love the language in verse number five when he says when I could no longer forbear
I mean Paul was in a position. He's like I just need to know
I need to know how they're doing. He's not concerned about a physical condition. He's concerned about their spiritual well-being
It's interesting to me that so often in our lives today
Even in our everyday conversation with brothers and sisters in Christ our conversation primarily consists of how are you doing?
temporally
It's
Not very common that even a brother or sister in Christ has a conversation with another brother or sister in Christ
Hey, how are your devotions going? How's your time with God?
What are you reading? How's God working in your life?
Seems like those are questions that almost we act as if are off limits in conversations
Brethren, it ought not be the case. I
Remember in 2018 meeting a pastor that I'd never met before and
Kimberly, you know pastor Scotty Buckhouse
I think when your family was traveling you
Met him and I met him in 2018 never met them fella before my life brother Armando
We sat down at a big table and he sat across from me to eat lunch and I just met him. Hi, I'm Scotty
Hi, I'm Chris just met him
Sit down to eat lunch. We prayed and he said brother. How are your devotions? What's God teaching you in his word?
And I was excited by that. I
Was encouraged I wasn't offended by that and we had one of the best conversations
Talking about what God's teaching us in our own lives
It was awesome
But you know how rare that is
So rare, but Paul says I could no longer forbear
I just had to know how they were doing why because he's concerned that they're pleasing God
It wasn't concerned how they were doing financially how the job was going how this was going how that how are you doing spiritually?
How are you doing spiritually?
Not only do we see the concern of Paul
Quickly, we see the charge from Paul
Paul gives a charge to those that he's ministering to that aligns with his concern for them
and we find again as we look at some of these same passages scripture go back if you were to the book of
Ephesians in chapter 5
And notice what the Bible says
Ephesians 5 as we consider the charge of the Apostle Paul
Why would he say this to these believers that he's writing to these?
Saints at Ephesus, why would he say these things because he wants them to have the testimony that they please God
And he says to them in in Ephesians 5 and beginning in verse number one be therefore
followers of God as dear children follow the Lord and
Walk in love as Christ hath also hath loved us and hath given himself for us an offering and a sacrifice of God for a
sweet-smelling
savor he then goes through a number of things to avoid and to
To not be partakers of and then he says this notice as we
Look at the the statement in verse number 10. He says proving what is acceptable unto the Lord
So what's he saying to these believers of Ephesus?
Listen you have a responsibility to prove
What is pleasing what is acceptable unto the Lord?
here are some things that you ought not do in fact as you look and you study here in the in the previous chapter in
Ephesians chapter before you find beginning in verse 17 down through the end
he talks about this principle that we see in the book of Colossians as well the put off put on principle and
Why is the Apostle Paul telling these believers in Ephesus to put off these things and to put on these things
Why is he telling them to prove what is acceptable unto the Lord for this purpose?
They please God
We read Colossians 1 10 already turn to the book of 1st Thessalonians and we'll look there very quickly
At what the Apostle Paul says to these that he needed to know their affairs he needed to know what was
Going on in their lives spiritually
We find that in 1st Thessalonians 2 in verse number 4
Notice what Paul says it's a great perspective that he had for ministry
He says but as we were allowed of God to be put in trust with the gospel
Even so we speak not as pleasing men, but God which triath our hearts
so keeping in mind that Paul is sharing with them their his perspective of the
Privilege that they had that they were allowed of God to be entrusted with the gospel
Even as we have been allowed of God to be entrusted with the gospel
But you notice that he says that he wanted to please God
He doesn't want to please men but look at chapter 4 in verse number 1 because he gives them a charge
It wasn't enough for the Apostle Paul to just have the personal desire that he would please God
But he wanted to give a charge to those that he was spiritually
Ministering to that they too would please the Lord notice in verse number 1 of chapter 4 furthermore
Then we beseech you brethren and exhort you by the Lord Jesus
That is he as he have received of us notice when he says how ye ought to walk and to please God
So you would abound more and more
What's his desire that they would please God
His charge to them is that they would live their lives in such a way that they would please the Lord
Let me close with this charge in 2nd Timothy. We're familiar with chapter 2 in verse number 2
When the Apostle Paul is giving this charge to Timothy his son in the faith and he speaks to him about
the importance of influence and generational influence
but we notice that in the same chapter that the Apostle Paul is is giving a charge to Timothy and even to
Us this evening and to all of those that God has enlisted into his army that we would please him notice in verse number 3
Of 2nd Timothy 2 the Bible says thou therefore endure hardness as a good soldier of Jesus Christ
No man that worth and tangle with himself with the affairs of this life notice that he may please him who hath chosen
Him to be a soldier
Paul says I want to give you this charge that you please God
Paul was concerned about the spiritual well-being of those that God enabled him to minister to and
Then he gives the charge
Live your life in such a way that you please the Lord
You know, we sang several songs today in fact about heaven kind of interesting how
that worked together and
We will see him one day face to face
What a wonderful wonderful Bible truth that is
But I wonder this evening if we'll hear that we pleased God
As
We think about how our life might be summarized
I think about the teenagers and being at camp and all of the the pressures that they have at the
time that they're in in life and
Do this and do that and chase this and do what makes you all of those things that they hear
I'm to please God
But it's not just teenagers
from the youngest to the oldest
To every child of God
It ought to be that our desire
Is to have the testimony?
That is said here of Enoch he had this testimony he pleased God
He pleased God
I'm not asking you to summarize your life. I'm not asking us to
Proclaim our own goodness
I'm saying as we evaluate. I've said this so often from this pulpit
Self-examination requires humility and honesty
It's easy for us to just say oh, yeah, I'm pleasing God
Take some time evaluate
Prove what is acceptable unto the Lord, you know proving is is a process
It was used that term in Ephesians 510 that's used with metal work
And you're proving those metals and you're you're heating them up to get the the impurities out and all that's taking place
and that's the term they would understand that and
God says to us proving what is acceptable unto the Lord. How do we do that?
Compare scripture with scripture
Here's this thing that I'm thinking about doing or this okay
How does it please God does it not please God and I'm gonna prove what is acceptable unto the Lord. It's a process
It's work
But it's worth it. Why because we can have this testimony
They pleased God. I hope tonight as we think about this
simple statement in Hebrews 11 5
Absolutely, just captivate at my attention this week. I just couldn't get away from it and
I just wonder tonight
Do we really have a desire?
That our lives are pleasing to God above everything else that it would be
be said of us that we have this testimony that we please God. Let's pray. Father, we
love you. We thank you for loving us. Thank you for the testimony of Enoch. Thank you
for the complete canon of Scripture. You've given us truth. You've revealed to us those
things that please you. You've revealed to us those things that do not please you. God,
I pray that we'd have that desire that above all else we would please you. Help us, God,
to prove what is acceptable in the sight of God. I pray that as we have a moment of invitation
tonight, I pray, Lord, that you'd work in hearts and lives. Help us, Lord, to be honest
and humble. Help us, Lord, to truly seek to live our lives in such a way that it would
be a Philippians 121 for me to live as Christ, not a Philippians 221 that all seek their
own. I pray, God, that you would move and work as only you can. We'll thank you for
every decision. For it's in Christ's name we pray.