Number eight, I know that America is not perfect.
There is no nation that is perfect.
We understand that to be the case,
but I am so thankful that in God's providence,
He allowed this nation to be founded.
And again, for as many of its wrongs,
there's so many rights.
And so thankful our land is under attack.
Amen.
And there are many that would love to see America destroyed,
not only from without, but from within.
And I am thankful for the way that God has used this nation
over the years in the history of our nation.
You think about the missionaries that have gone out
from America all across this globe,
preaching the gospel of Jesus Christ,
the freedom that we have had in this land
to assemble together, to proclaim the truth of the gospel.
And what a blessing.
You know, you can leave here this afternoon
and you can go out and you can find someone
and you can talk to them about Jesus.
And you don't have to be afraid.
You don't have to fear any kind of persecution.
You're not gonna be in prison for it.
I understand they might not like it.
I know there are many people that do not like it,
but the reality is that we have freedom to do that.
And that is wonderful.
And I'm so thankful for that.
The freedom that we celebrate as Americans,
I believe is both unique and special.
And we think about that,
the truth that many around the globe today,
they do not know what it is to live
in a country such as ours.
They do not know what it is to have the freedoms
that we so regularly take for granted.
We understand there are many millions upon millions
of people around the globe that desire to come to America.
And what draws them here?
What is it that they're looking for?
And you think about those freedoms
that we just are so grateful to enjoy.
But the reality this morning is that as a child of God,
the freedom that we have in America pales
in comparison to the freedom that we have in Christ.
And I'm thankful for the freedom that we have in America.
Don't get me wrong.
But the freedom that we have in Christ is so much greater.
And the reality this morning is that the freedom
that we have in Christ, that freedom is offered,
it is available to any human being
without regard of what their citizenship status might be.
You think about people all across this globe,
you think of some of the darkest,
some of the most strict nations upon the face of this earth,
they have no freedoms whatsoever,
but yet they can have freedom through Christ.
And that is precious, that is powerful.
And we ought to rejoice in that freedom that Christ offers.
In John chapter number eight, our text for this morning,
we'll look at a number of passages of scripture,
but we find that Jesus is speaking here
to some religious leaders, and often as the case was,
there'd be debate and dialogue.
And we find here in this text of scripture,
we'll pick up right in the middle, in verse number 32,
notice the proclamation of Jesus.
He says, and ye shall know the truth,
and the truth shall make you free.
They answered him, these religious leaders,
these men that he's speaking to, they say,
we be Abraham's seed,
and we're never in bondage to any man.
How sayest thou, ye shall be made free?
Jesus answered them, verily, verily, I say unto you,
whosoever committeth sin is the servant of sin.
And the servant abideth not in the house forever,
but the son abideth ever.
If the son therefore shall make you free,
ye shall be free indeed.
I've adopted the latter statement in verse number 32
for our title this morning.
The truth shall make you free.
As we find this word free that is used
in our text of scripture and other places in the scripture,
we'll look at a few of those verses here
by way of introduction.
We find that this word free means to set at liberty,
more specifically it means to set at liberty
from the dominion of sin.
And you find contextually as Jesus is speaking
to these religious leaders,
and he says, ye shall know the truth,
and the truth shall make you free,
they immediately respond by saying,
we're not in bondage to any man.
Now we'll deal with that in just a moment
because they had been deceived,
and we understand their error here
as they make this statement.
But you find that Jesus very appropriately
and very quickly, he deals with the fact
that he's speaking to them about the freedom
from the bondage, the dominion of sin.
We find that, and we'll be back in Romans
in John here in just a moment,
but turn to the book of Romans, if you will,
in chapter number six.
I just wanna look at a couple of other references
where we see this truth of freedom through Christ,
the freedom that he offers, this being free,
being set at liberty from the dominion of sin.
We find here in Romans chapter number six
in verse number 18, notice what the word of God says.
Being then made free from sin,
you became the servants of righteousness.
Now it's interesting because in verse number 17,
it says, but God be thanked that ye were
the servants of sin, but ye have obeyed from the heart
that form of doctrine which was delivered you.
Being then made free from sin,
you became the servants of righteousness.
I'd rather be a servant of righteousness
than a servant of sin, amen?
And the reality is that if we look at this passage
in Romans six and look at these two verses of scripture,
we understand that we're all servants.
You're either a servant of sin
or you're a servant of righteousness.
And we find that we've been delivered,
we've been made free if you've trusted Christ,
if you've obeyed from the heart that form of doctrine
which was delivered you.
What is that form of doctrine?
That's the gospel.
Remember, Paul says in Romans chapter one
that he was ready to preach the gospel
to them that are at Rome also.
He says, I'm not ashamed of the gospel of Christ,
for it is the power of God unto salvation
to everyone that believeth,
to the Jew first and also to the Greek.
And we find that he says you've obeyed,
you've believed the truth of the gospel,
you've placed your faith and trust
in the finished work of Christ at Calvary,
his death, his burial, his glorious resurrection,
and no longer are you a servant of sin,
but now you're a servant of righteousness.
Skip down a few verses and notice in verse number 22,
it says this, but now being made free from sin
and become servants to God,
ye have your fruit unto holiness
and the end everlasting life.
Aren't you thankful for the gift of God
which is everlasting life,
eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord.
In Romans chapter number eight,
just a couple of pages over,
we find that in verse number one,
he says there is therefore now no condemnation
to them which are in Christ Jesus
who walk not after the flesh but after the spirit.
Notice verse two, for the law of the spirit
is life in Christ Jesus, notice,
hath made me free from the law of sin and death.
And then of course we read in the book of Galatians,
in Galatians chapter number five,
in fact the book of Galatians deals much
with the liberty that we have in Christ
and the way in which these religious leaders,
these Judaizers in particular,
they were trying to bring them back under the law
but they've been set free,
and we find that in Galatians five in verse number one,
notice what Paul says to the churches
in the region of Galatia, he says,
stand fast therefore in the liberty
wherewith Christ hath made us free
and be not entangled again with the yoke of bondage.
If you've been made free,
why do you wanna be entangled with the yoke of bondage?
But when we understand our freedom,
our liberty in Christ, we find that in verse number 13
of this same chapter that Paul goes on to say,
and he says this, for brethren,
ye have been called unto liberty,
only use not liberty for an occasion to the flesh,
but by love serve one another.
You know the reality is that there are some in that day
and some to this day,
they speak about their Christian liberty
as if it's a license to live any way they wanna live.
But the reality is that liberty in our land,
liberty is not that you can live
any way that you wanna live,
and liberty in Christ is not that we can live
any way that we wanna live.
In fact, because I've been free from the bondage of sin,
the dominion of sin, sin no longer has dominion over me
because I have this liberty in truth,
the idea, the biblical truth of liberty
is that now and only now can I actually serve God.
And yet we have people running around
pretending that they have liberty,
I'm not under the law, I can live however I wanna live,
I can do whatever I wanna do,
I can dress how I wanna dress,
I can live how I wanna live,
I can do what I wanna do,
and the reality is that this book
is often ignored when we take that approach.
And oh, how important it is that we understand
the liberty and the freedom that we have in Christ,
and we find that here,
that as Jesus is speaking to these religious leaders,
he tells them you shall know the truth
and the truth shall make you free.
Free from what?
It has that meaning of being set at liberty
specifically from the dominion of sin.
If you're taking notes this morning,
let me say this, number one,
there is a blinding from truth.
There's a blinding from truth.
You understand this morning that as we look
even at this passage of scripture in John chapter number eight
we find that truth has the power to make men free.
but because of the power of truth to make men free,
we find that Satan desires to blind mankind from the truth.
And we find that there's a blinding from truth.
Why is it that we see that in our text of Scripture
in John chapter number eight,
that when Jesus says that ye shall know the truth
and the truth shall make you free,
that the answer, the immediate response,
is we be Abraham's seed.
And we're never in bondage to any man.
How sayest thou, ye shall be made free?
They immediately start thinking of something
completely different than what Jesus is speaking of,
and even in their response, it shows their ignorance.
It shows that they are actually responding
to something different than what Jesus is speaking of,
and at the same time, they are being deceitful
about their history.
They say we're of Abraham's seed,
we've never been in bondage.
Really?
Really.
Do you not remember the time in Egypt?
Were they not in bondage?
Did they not cry out to God,
the children of Israel while they're in Egypt,
did they not cry out to God for deliverance?
Did they not see God work miraculously and come,
and yes, his grace and his mercy was on display
to the Egyptians, for he showed them over and over
of his power through those plagues.
And eventually, he delivered his people
from the bondage in Egypt.
You look at the history of the nation of Israel,
not only the Egyptian bondage,
but you begin to think about the time,
the period of the judges, they're in great oppression
over and over by various people groups and nations.
You come to the 10 tribes of the north,
the nation of Israel, and they're taken captive
by the Assyrians.
Just a short time later, Judah,
the two tribes of the south are taken captive
and in bondage and captivity by the Babylonians.
You find that even at the very time of the writing,
the ministry of Jesus Christ,
as Jesus is speaking to these very religious leaders,
and they say we've never, we're never in bondage
to any man, it was the Romans that controlled them.
You see how they're blinded?
They're blinded from the real truth that Jesus is getting to
the fact that they're, the deliverance,
the freedom from the dominion of sin,
but we find that even in their blindness,
they're not acknowledging the fact even of their history.
And this morning, as we think about the spiritual
significance of this passage of scripture,
the freedom that Christ gives us,
being set at liberty from the dominion of sin,
we find that mankind continues to be blinded.
We find that as we would speak to people today
about the truth of the gospel,
the power of the gospel to save sinners,
the power of truth to deliver someone,
to set them at liberty from the dominion of sin,
you have individuals that have been blinded
that do not believe they have any problem.
But the reality is that sin is a universal condition.
Every single person upon the face of the earth
that is alive at this very moment has a problem with sin.
We've either been forgiven and we're bound for heaven,
or we're still dead in our trespasses and our sins.
And we find this morning that Satan desires
to control the minds of mankind,
to blind them from the truth of the gospel.
Notice in the book of 2 Corinthians, if you will,
in chapter number four,
as we begin to think about the blinding from truth,
and we find that Paul is speaking here
to these believers in Corinth,
and he gives them this very just insightful truth
in verse number three, down really through verse number seven
with regard to the ministry that God has given us.
Notice what he says in verse number three,
but if our gospel be hid, it is hid to them that are lost.
Can I say this this morning?
Our gospel has been hid for too long.
We find that there's this blinding from truth,
but there's responsibility on the part of the people of God
to proclaim the truth of the gospel,
and if our gospel is hid, it is hid to them that are lost.
This truth of the condition of our world today,
the condition of our nation today,
there are many times in which we can sit around
and we begin to point fingers
at what all of the causes are
for why we're in the condition that we're in,
and why we're facing the things that we're facing,
but if we'd be honest about it this morning,
the church better stand up and take some responsibility.
Because if our gospel be hid,
it is hid to them that are lost.
Why would we expect lost people to act like saved people?
It's hard enough to get saved people
to act like saved people, amen?
But the reality is that lost people,
the Bible tells us, Paul says to the believers in Corinth,
that the natural man receiveth not the things
of the Spirit of God for their foolishness unto him,
neither can he know them, why?
Because they are spiritually discerned.
I cannot expect a lost person to behave,
to legislate like a saved person.
The reality is that our gospel in this nation
has been hid for way too long.
Notice what he says in verse number four.
In whom the God of this world, that's Satan,
in whom the God of this world hath blinded the minds
of them which believe not,
lest the light of the glorious gospel of Christ,
who is the image of God, should shine unto them.
For we preach not ourselves.
Aren't you thankful for that?
It'd be lousy if we preached ourselves.
But Christ Jesus the Lord, in ourselves your servants,
for Jesus' sake, for God who commanded the light
to shine out of darkness, hath shined in our hearts
to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God
in the face of Jesus Christ.
But we have this treasure in earthen vessels
that the excellency of the power may be of God
and not of us.
And the reality this morning is that we're living
in a time, we're living in an age in which there's
this blinding from truth that's been so from the beginning
but we see it exponentially greater today.
And we see the God of this world is blinding the minds
of them which believe not.
We find that he uses a variety of means.
I believe this morning that organized religion
is one of the means in which the enemy uses
to blind people from the truth.
You think about the number of denominations
and the number of so-called churches
and all of these world religions and you begin
to look at all of these things that are going on
and all of the variety of teachings
and the approach that is given and you find
that mankind is left confused and frustrated.
And it's the enemy that's blinding the minds
of them which believe not.
There is a blinding from truth.
Notice not only is there a blinding from truth
but I would say this this morning,
there is a battle for truth.
There's a battle for truth.
We begin to think about what's taking place
and I've often mentioned from this pulpit
especially over the last several years
the fact that we are engaged not in cultural warfare
though people will seek to say that
and they'll seek to peddle that idea,
the reality is that we are engaged in spiritual warfare.
And as we're engaged in spiritual warfare
we find that there's a battle for truth.
I am thankful this morning that truth stands.
I am thankful that truth, see oftentimes what happens
is the individuals that are attacking biblical truth,
biblical Christianity, the person of Jesus Christ,
the people that are attacking,
they're asking us to defend truth.
But so often what happens is we fail to cause them
to defend their positions.
And the reality is that truth stands.
And we find here this morning that as we look
at the word of God we find that there has been
a relentless attack on truth from the beginning.
You go all the way back to the Garden of Eden,
you go all the way back to the record
that God gives us in Genesis chapter number three
and you read in the first four verses of Genesis three
how that the truth that God had given to Adam and Eve
has been attacked and there has been a relentless attack.
Truth has been relentlessly attacked.
It's amazing to me how many attack Jesus Christ.
Why is Jesus always attacked?
Because he is truth.
Why is it that in a day and age in which we live
that it seems as if people really don't care
if you use the word God but if you start talking
about Jesus Christ now that's a different situation.
We find that in Genesis chapter number three,
turn over there quickly,
we're familiar with the text of scripture
but I want you to notice that here in Genesis chapter
number three we see the first assault if you will,
the battle for truth and we understand the simple command
that God had given back in Genesis chapter number two
in verses.
16 and 17, the Lord said this, and the Lord God commanded the man, saying, Of every tree
of the garden thou mayest freely eat, but of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil,
thou shalt not eat of it, for in the day that thou eatest thereof, thou shalt surely die."
It's a simple command with known consequences.
It's truth.
And we come to Genesis chapter number 3.
The Bible begins in verse number 1, and it says this, Now the serpent, that's the enemy,
that's Satan, now the serpent was more subtle than any beast of the field which the Lord
God had made.
And he said unto the woman, Yea, hath God said, Ye shall not eat of every tree of the
garden.
Do you notice how the initial attack on truth is simply by planting a seed of doubt?
Simply planting a seed of doubt.
Yea, hath God said?
And the woman said unto the serpent, We may eat of the fruit of the trees of the garden,
but of the fruit of the tree which is in the midst of the garden, God hath said, Ye shall
not eat of it, neither shall ye touch it, lest ye die.
And notice in verse number 4, an on, a full out assault on truth, And the serpent said
unto the woman, Ye shall not surely die.
But God said, In the day that ye eat thereof, thou shalt surely die.
Wonder why John 8 records where Jesus says that you're of your father the devil, that
he's a murderer and he's a liar from the beginning.
And we find here in Genesis chapter number 3 that the Bible then, Satan begins to, listen,
you understand he never denies the existence of God.
We've got a bunch of atheists running around today that deny the existence of God, but
Satan doesn't deny the existence of God.
In fact, James tells us that the devils, they believe in tremble.
You look at the ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ, when He walked upon the face of the
earth, when there were those that were demon-possessed that were in the presence of Jesus, they knew
who Jesus was, and they said, Have you come to torment us before our time?
Because not only do they know who Jesus is, but they know what their end is.
We find that here, Satan does not deny the existence of God, he questions the goodness
of God.
He says this in verse number 5, For God doth know that in the day ye eat thereof, then
your eyes shall be opened, and ye shall be as gods, knowing good and evil.
God's holding something from you that's good for you, basically is what Satan is saying.
God knows that in the day you eat this, it's going to open your eyes, illuminate you.
And God's withholding something good from you.
Listen, today it just goes something like this, God wants you to be happy.
God wants you to just be you.
Do what makes you happy, because that's what God wants.
That's not what God says.
There is a battle for truth, and the battle rages.
Notice in the book of Romans, we've looked at several verses already in the book of Romans,
but notice in Romans chapter number 1, in Romans chapter number 1, I want you to notice
this morning as we're considering this truth, that truth, the truth shall make you free.
Yes, I'm thankful for the truth that we have as Americans, but if we'd be honest this morning,
that as the people of God, the freedom that I have in America pales in comparison to the
freedom that we have in Christ.
There are missionaries all across that missions board that we support that are living in places
all across this world that they do not have a Bill of Rights, they do not have a United
States Constitution, but they have freedom in Christ.
And by the way, many of those missionaries are doing a whole lot more for the cause of
Christ than Americans are, and we have freedom.
It's amazing.
Notice what he says here in Romans chapter number 1.
We don't have time to look at the entirety of the passage, but really if you look at
verse 18 down through verse number 32, you just see just amazing disobedience to the
illumination of who God is and what God has given them.
Notice in verse number 24, wherefore God also gave them up to uncleanness through the lust
of their own hearts to dishonor their own bodies between themselves, who changed the
truth of God into a lie, and worshiped and served the creature more than the Creator,
who is blessed forever, amen.
Do we not see this in our land today?
That they changed the truth of God into a lie.
And still to this very day, there is a battle for truth.
They try to take the truth that God's given, they try to change it into a lie, tell us
something different.
The Bible tells us that they worshiped and served the creature more than the Creator.
We see that in our society, do we not?
Really as you look at the entirety of this section of Romans chapter number 1, you find
that they deny the existence of God because really they don't want to be accountable to
God.
We find that there's this battle for truth as we consider this morning the battle for
truth that rages in our land, that's raged since Genesis chapter number 3.
We would find that the admonition that we read of from Jude in verses 3 and 4 is an
admonition that we need to apply in our lives today.
Jude begins writing this short letter, and it's interesting because Jude is going to
write this letter and it tells us that he was going to write about the common salvation.
I mean, what a joyful subject to discuss the salvation that we have through the Lord Jesus
Christ, the unity that we have as brothers and sisters in Christ because of that salvation
through Christ, and he says in verse number 3, Beloved, when I gave all diligence to write
unto you of the common salvation, notice it says it was needful for me to write unto you
and exhort you that you should earnestly contend for the faith which was once delivered unto
the saints.
Why?
What's the need here, Jude?
Why do we need to earnestly contend for the faith?
Why is it that we need to get involved in this battle for truth?
Why do we need to engage in the fight for truth?
Notice what he says in verse number 4, For there are certain men crept in unawares, who
were before of old ordained to this condemnation ungodly men, turning the grace of our God
into lasciviousness, and denying the only Lord God and our Lord Jesus Christ.
It's interesting.
It's the truth that will make you free, the grace and mercy of the Lord Jesus Christ,
and here in verse number 4, it says of these men that crept in unawares, these false teachers,
that they're turning the grace of our God into lasciviousness, unbridled lust.
Do what you want.
God wants you to be happy.
That's just not what the Word of God says.
He actually says this, If you love me, keep my commandments.
If you love me, keep my commandments.
He says this, flee from fornication.
That flies in the face of the society in which we live in today, does it not?
And we find that we go to the Word of God, listen, there's a blinding from truth, but
there's also a battle for truth.
And we must acknowledge those two things this morning, but finally this morning as we wrap
up our time, I want you to acknowledge this morning with me the blessing of truth.
I'm so thankful this morning for the passage of Scripture in John chapter number 8, where
Jesus is standing there before those religious leaders, and he's giving them this powerful
truth that this morning is our focus of our message.
He says, Ye shall know the truth, and the truth shall make you free.
Listen, this morning we must acknowledge the blessings of truth.
I am so thankful this morning that not only to live in a nation of freedom, but to have
the truth of God's Word, the freedom that His Word offers us.
You know, it'd be a horrible thing to live in a nation that has freedom void of the truth
of God's Word.
What does that freedom really get us?
Because the reality is that the Bible tells us that man goes to his long home.
I don't care how long you live here on the earth, it's a short time compared to eternity.
I'm going to live to be 100, man, compared to eternity, that's just that long, right?
I understand sometimes we think, man, that's a long time.
Sometimes a week can be a long time, right?
I mean, you get into the life and you're like, man, it just seems like it's dragging.
But in comparison to eternity, it's nothing.
And to live in a nation that has freedom void of the freedom that Christ offers, no thank
you.
I'd rather live in a land that has no freedom, but has the freedom that Christ offers.
And we find this truth this morning as we acknowledge the blessing, listen, we ought
to rejoice this morning because God has providentially preserved truth for us.
Notice he says, ye shall know the truth.
In John 17, here in just a few chapters, we find that Jesus would say this, sanctify them
through thy word.
word is truth. I'm thankful this morning that we can know the truth. I'm thankful
this morning that someone was faithful to deliver the truth to you, that
someone was faithful to deliver the truth to me. I'm thankful that we then
have the privilege and the opportunity to deliver the truth to someone else.
Because it is the truth that makes men free. And we find here this morning that
God has providentially preserved truth for us. I wonder this morning, when's the
last time you thanked God for His Bible, His Word? Every single day when I get
into this book I start by saying, God thank you for the Word of God. Thank you
for preserving this book so that I could read it. Thank you that I have it in my
language, that I can read it. Then I begin to pray, God would you teach me
out of this book? God would you help me to understand it? The Holy Spirit's the
teacher. Open thou mine eyes that I may behold wondrous things out of thy law.
Speak Lord for thy servant heareth. Lord teach me thy truth and Lord help me to
walk in thy truth. That's our approach to the Bible. Listen, I am so thankful this
morning that God's given us a Bible. I honestly, I don't know where we'd be
without a Bible. There are people all across the world that do not have Bibles.
There are some that have Bibles that neglect them, that just sit on a table,
sit on a bookshelf. And yet there are people all across the globe that do not
have the Word of God. This morning we ought to thank God for the blessing of
truth, that He has providentially preserved His Word for us. He said to
these religious leaders, you shall know the truth and the truth shall make you
free. I'm thankful this morning that the truth has been preserved for us and that
as we've been given the truth of the gospel that we have been set free. If you
have obeyed, as Paul says there to the believers in Rome, if you've obeyed the
truth that was delivered, then you have been set at liberty, you have been made
free from the dominion of sin. We ought to rejoice in that. Number two, as we
think about acknowledging the blessing of truth, we ought to rejoice that Jesus
is truth, that He is truth. Of course, He stands in John 14, a verse that we often
would quote, and He says, I am the way, the truth, and the life. No man cometh unto
the Father but by me. You know today that there are statistics that are floating
around that say of those that are professed Christians, now I have an idea
of what that means in my head, and you probably do as well, but the next
statement causes me much confusion. They say that of professed Christians, about
one-third say that Jesus is the only way to heaven. That's perplexing to me. I
don't understand that, but yet I find that there was a church that
unfortunately had in its name Baptist, that was in New York City a number of
years ago, that the pastor stood up and said this idea as he's preaching, he says
the idea that Jesus is the only way to heaven is irrelevant and it's just not
true, and when he made the statement you could hear the applause of the
congregation. Unbelievable, I heard it with my own ears.
Unbelievable, because Jesus said I am the way, the truth, and the life. No man
cometh unto the Father but by me. Peter, who would have heard Jesus speak those
words, would stand before the religious leaders in Acts 4 and he'd say neither
is there salvation in any other. There's no other name under heaven given among
men whereby we must be saved. The name of Jesus. You read the book of Philippians
and you read how the Bible tells us about the Lord taking on the form of a
servant and going to the cross. He humbled himself, he became obedient unto
death, even the death of the cross, but God also hath highly exalted his name
and given him a name which is above every other name. And it's at the name of
Jesus that every tongue will confess, every knee is going to bow, that Jesus
Christ is Lord. It's not a question of if, it's a question of when, because every
knee will bow and every tongue will confess. And I will say this this morning,
you've heard me say it before, when makes all the difference. You profess that
before you take your final breath here on earth, heaven is your home. If you deny
that truth and you enter into a Christless eternity, and I believe that at the Great
White Throne Judgment, you will acknowledge that Jesus is Lord. I hope this morning
that you've made that proclamation, you've understood, listen, the truth has
made us free. The truth is Jesus. Not only the truth being His Word, but the truth
is Jesus. Remember in the verse that we read there in Galatians 5, in verse
number 1, where the Word of God says this, He says,
Stand fast therefore in the liberty wherewith Christ hath made us free, and
be not entangled again with the yoke of bondage. Finally this morning, as we
acknowledge the blessing of truth, as we rejoice that God's given us truth in His
precious Word, as we rejoice that Jesus Himself is truth, as we acknowledge this
morning that there's a blinding from truth, that there is a battle for truth,
we must purpose to proclaim the truth. As a nation, right or wrong, not part of this
discussion, but as a nation, as you look at the history of our nation, we've gotten
involved in conflicts all across the globe, and many times we've tried to give
them freedom. Could I say to you this morning that as the people of God, we
must have a burning zeal to deliver the message that we're speaking of this
morning, that Christ gives freedom. I appreciate the fact that we would want
other countries and other people groups to have freedom. I appreciate that, but if
they only have freedom from tyranny, if they only have freedom from some
dictator, if they only have freedom from some whatever-you-want-to-say-the-
condition-is-that-they're-dealing-with, but they do not have the freedom that
we're speaking of this morning, they will simply live, perhaps live a life of
pleasure, and then face a Christless eternity. That's the reality of it. And
this morning, as we understand the stakes and what's going on, and the
truth of what's before us this morning, we find that there are many today that
remain in bondage. There are many today that continue to be blinded from truth,
and they remain in bondage. They've not been set at liberty. They've not been
made free from the truth that God has given us. They've not been set free
from the bondage of sin. But this morning, I'm thankful to say that truth
still works. Jesus still saves. The truth is still powerful. If our gospel be hid,
it is hid to them that are lost. Paul encouraged the believers in Ephesus in
Ephesians 4 and verse 15 to speak the truth in love. Paul gave the command, the
admonition, the charge, if you will, to Timothy in 2 Timothy chapter number 4. He
tells them to preach the word. Oh, he also let them know that there was going to
come a time when they weren't going to endure sound doctrine. But it did not
change the instruction. Paul didn't say to Timothy, hey, listen, Timothy, you preach
the word until they don't want to hear it. No, no, he just said preach the word. Be
instant, in season, out of season, reprove, rebuke, exhort with all longsuffering and
doubt. That's what he told them to do. This morning, we as the people of God, if
our gospel be hid, it is hid to them that are lost. We sing the song with the kids.
Sometimes I think we ought to sing kids' songs more. Honestly, this little light of
mine, I'm going to let it shine. Let it shine, let it shine, let it shine. Don't
let Satan blow it out, hide it under a bushel, no. Let it shine till Jesus comes. I'm going
to let it shine. I have decided to follow Jesus. No turning back, no turning back. Though
none go with me, still I will follow. That's what we sing with the kids. But somehow along
the way, we become adults and we think, well, we forget some of those songs. This morning,
there's a blinding from truth. We see it in our world today. There's a battle for truth.
But this morning, we rejoice in the blessing of truth. The fact that we have truth, man,
we ought to rejoice. The fact that the truth has set us free, it's made us free, oh, we
ought to rejoice. But you know, if you have a neighbor...
a coworker, a relative, that they're still in bondage, wouldn't you like for them to
be made free?
Right?
Does that make sense?
You want them to be made free, and you have the truth that has the power to make them
free.
That's amazing.
And yet sometimes we just don't say it.
We just don't share it.
We just don't give it.
And they remain in bondage.
This morning, Jesus stood before those blinded religious leaders.
In fact, in chapter number nine, after the healing of the man that was born blind, they
say, are we blind also?
Yep, absolutely.
Spiritual blindness.
And spiritual blindness is a whole lot worse than physical blindness.
This morning, the truth shall make you free.
When you celebrate this weekend and you rejoice in being in the land of the free, and you
think about the freedoms that we have as Americans, you ought to be thankful for that.
But we must acknowledge this morning that those freedoms pale in comparison to the freedom
that we have in Christ.
Let me say this.
In my lifetime, some of my freedoms as an American might not be enjoyed any longer.
It's possible.
But nobody can take my freedom that I have in Christ.
It's powerful.
This morning, we need to proclaim, purpose to proclaim the truth, because the truth sets
men free.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
This morning, I'm so grateful to know You, the way, the truth, and the life.
As my personal Savior, I thank You that You've given us Thy Word, and Thy Word is truth.
And God, this morning as we acknowledge, it's nothing new that there's a blinding from truth.
Nothing new that there's a battle for truth.
We see it all around us.
God, I pray that as we rejoice in the blessing of truth, that we would not only be thankful
for what You've given to us, but that we would have a genuine concern for our neighbor, our
coworker, our relative.
So often, there are movements, even in our society today, of wanting to provide some
level of opportunity or liberty to some people.
And yet, as Your people, as the children of God, sometimes we fail to recognize the importance
of giving truth that would set men free from the dominion of sin, that they might pass
from death unto life, no longer being the servant of sin, but the servant of righteousness,
no longer heading for a Christless eternity in the lake of fire, but having eternal life
in Your presence.
Oh, God, would You help us to have a renewed passion, help us to have a renewed vision,
not to get behind some cause, but to lift up the name of Christ.
We pray that You'd move and work in these moments of invitation.
If there's one that's not sure of heaven, oh, God, I pray that today would be the day
of their salvation.
Your people all across this auditorium this morning, Lord, would You work in our hearts.
We don't want to just be stirred, we want to be changed.
We don't want to just be hearers, we want to be doers.
I pray that You'd move and work in these moments of invitation, for it's in Christ's name we
pray.
Would You stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Holly's going to play quietly on the piano.
As she plays, the altar is open.