We are more than conquerors through Christ,
and yes, we do have an enemy, and yes, they do.
The enemy desires to devour us
as we find in 1 Peter chapter number five,
but I'm thankful for many verses of scripture
that were coming to my mind
even as we were singing that song this morning,
that greater is he that is in you
than he that is in the world, amen?
And submit yourselves therefore to God,
resist the devil, and it says he will flee, amen?
And we sang a couple of songs this morning
by way of our congregational singing,
all hail the power of Jesus' name,
a mighty fortress is our God,
and if you looked at the bulletin this morning,
Proverbs 18, 10 is on the front,
the name of the Lord is a strong tower, amen?
And that bulletin was not selected because of the songs,
the songs were not selected because of the bulletin,
and that's just how God orchestrated it for this morning,
and I love it when God works that way,
and someone asked me, they said,
they looked at the front of the bulletin,
and they said, I see the songs,
was this bulletin picked for this?
No, it's just how it worked, amen?
We buy the bulletins, they come to us
in a pack of 13 weeks at a time,
so you get a quarterly bundle of these bulletins,
and they get in a stack,
and Holly just goes week one, week two, week three,
that's how it just works, and she has them that way,
and then Dean picks the songs,
Dean never sees the bulletin until he comes to church, amen?
And praise the Lord,
and I'm thankful that we serve a great God, amen?
And I mentioned about 1 Peter chapter number five,
where the Bible says that our enemy desires to devour us,
but we read, and we often will quote verse number eight,
but verse number nine says,
whom resist steadfast in the faith,
knowing that the same afflictions are accomplished
in your brethren that are in the world.
It ought to remind us to pray one for another, amen?
In fact, as you read the truth in Ephesians,
chapter number six,
with regard to putting on the whole armor of God,
you read about the fact that we're engaged
in spiritual battle and all that's going on,
and how we're to put on the whole armor of God,
you get to the end after all the pieces of armor,
and it talks about praying one for another,
and what a blessing to know that we have folks
that are praying for us as we're engaged
in the spiritual battle.
I believe it was Tozer that said it well.
He said this, that the Christian life is best defined
or described as a battleground, not a playground.
And I hope that you have discovered that to be the truth.
It is a battlefield, a battleground,
and I'm thankful to be on the winning side, amen?
James chapter number one this morning,
if you have your Bible with you,
James chapter number one,
and thankful for the word of God,
and what a blessing that God would give us His word
and reveal to us the wonderful truth that He does.
We find that as we've been studying
through the book of James last week,
we were in first John three,
and dealing with the subject that Jesus loves even me.
This week, we're back to the book of James,
our book study for the calendar year of 2026.
And we are looking here, doers of the word is our theme,
and thankful for the book of James.
James, as we mentioned in the beginning of our study here,
immediately addresses the subject of trials
as he opens the letter.
We've said this multiple times
with regard to the book of James.
It's a book that is very practical in nature,
and the importance of spiritual maturity
and taking what we believe to be true
and then practicing it.
How do we apply God's word in our lives
that we'd be doers of the word?
He deals with the subject of trials,
and we discover this that all of us have faced
or will face trials.
It's something that as human beings, we deal with,
we face trials as believers, we face trials,
but we have a different perspective when facing trials
because we understand that God has given to us his word
and he's revealed truth to us
that helps us as we face the trials that we face in life.
And so throughout the first section of this book,
we've learned several things with regard to trials.
Number one, we've learned that we ought to expect trials.
Trials are gonna come in your life and in my life.
And you say, pastor, I'm in the midst of one right now.
I understand, and we understand the scriptures teach us
that we're to expect trials.
We understand that trials come in various ways
and they come at various times.
Rarely is the trial ever come the same way,
and they come in variety of ways and a variety of times.
And you might find that at times a trial will come
and you might say something like this,
this is not the time for this.
You ever felt that way?
And you say, man, I don't have time for this right now.
And we can sometimes have that perspective,
but we understand that God's given to us these truths
that will help us as we face trials.
What about this truth?
God has a purpose in the trial.
Oh, that'll help us, amen.
We're not just going through the trial for no good reason.
We're going through the trial
because God has a purpose in that trial.
At times, the purpose is that he is going
to demonstrate his power.
He's going to reveal something to us about his person,
and that should cause us to rejoice.
At other times, and sometimes both working
in the same trial, it's to develop us as his people,
to grow us, to help us to trust him more
and to lean on him more, to believe him more.
And we also have learned that we need God's wisdom
when we're experiencing trials, amen.
We need the wisdom of God.
And I'm thankful that God has promised
to give wisdom to those who ask.
As we come to verse number 12 this morning,
it's interesting because the passage with regard to trials
kind of concludes here in verse number 12.
And I'll say this, with a sermon on the mount kind of a tone
and it's regarding the individual that endures.
Now, remember, if you think about the sermon on the mount,
blessed is, and you read about all of those things.
And we come to verse number 12 of James one,
and the Bible says,
blessed is the man that endureth temptation.
For when he is tried, he shall receive the crown of life,
which the Lord hath promised to them that love him.
As we look at verses two through 12,
we understand that the word temptation is used
dealing with trials.
And we find that in verses 13 through 15,
the word tempted is used repeatedly and dealing with,
and you understand the context,
a different type of temptation
than the temptation that we read of in verses two through 12
the temptation that we deal with in verses two through 12
are temptations as we talked about these trials
and understanding that they come, they're not sinful.
They are to reveal to us God's power
and God's purpose and his plan.
And we find that they're to develop us as his people.
In verses 13 through 15, as we'll study next week,
that's dealing more with sinful aspect.
And the context helps us to understand that.
And so as we look here in verse number 12,
it's important that we know that James is not saying
that a sinner is saved by enduring trials.
That's not what he's saying.
What he's saying is that a believer
who endures trials will be rewarded.
There's a great difference.
It's not that, oh man, I've endured all of this
and I've gone through all of this.
And sometimes you talk to somebody,
are you gonna go to heaven when we die?
Well, let me tell you what happened.
And they had this thing going on in their life
and they made it through.
And so therefore, man, I'm gonna, no, no, no.
Salvation is through Jesus Christ.
There's a moment in which you recognized you were a sinner.
He's the only savior.
And you trust that Christ is your savior.
And you were born again.
And we understand that James is not suggesting
you're teaching here that a sinner is saved
by enduring trials, but rather as a believer
that endures trials, we will be rewarded.
I've titled the message simply,
as you see in the bulletin today, Enduring Trials.
As you're looking at verse number 12,
I want you to note first of all with me the conduct.
Note the conduct of the individual
who is mentioned here in our verse of scripture.
The Bible says, blessed is the man
that endureth temptation.
For when he has tried, he shall receive the crown of life,
which the Lord hath promised to them that love him.
We notice two things about the conduct
of the individual that is mentioned in verse number 12.
Now understand, in verse number two,
that James, as he starts this section
and now is going to conclude the section,
he starts it by saying, my brethren.
And understanding that he's writing to believers.
And he says, my brethren, count it all joy
when you fall into divers temptations.
And he's going to give all of the truth
that I just briefly summarized by way of introduction,
those principles that we've learned
as we've studied through this portion of scripture.
And now he comes to the concluding statement
in verse number 12 and wrapping up the section.
And he reveals to us the conduct of the individual
that yes, has gone through trials, but has endured.
We read that it says, blessed is the man that endureth.
And I want you to focus just a moment
as you think about the conduct of this individual
on the one that endureth.
The word means to remain.
It means to abide.
It means to persevere.
It really carries with it this idea
of no retreat and no fleeing.
You know, sometimes what happens in the midst of a trial,
people get the pressure and they retreat.
They give up.
They throw in the towel.
They say, what's.
What's it worth?
And they get discouraged and all of those things happen,
but we find here when we note the conduct of the individual
that is given to us in verse number 12,
the Bible says,
blessed is the man that endureth temptation,
that the trial comes,
but there's this aspect, this conduct of enduring,
understanding that I'm gonna remain,
I'm gonna keep my eyes on Jesus.
We're reminded of the truth in Hebrews chapter number 12,
of looking unto Jesus, the author and finisher of our faith
and understanding that he has a plan and he has a purpose
and I'm going to endure through the trial by God's grace
and with God's help.
It's not that in myself, I just have this ability to endure.
No, it's through God's working in my life
and understanding the biblical principles
that God has revealed to us.
It really carries with it,
the idea to hold fast to your faith in Christ,
even in the midst of trials.
There are times if you'd be honest
and we're not gonna have anyone
share publicly a testimony,
but if you'd be honest and you'd evaluate your own life,
there's probably been at some point in your Christian life
that you were enduring it,
you were going through a trial and it was heavy
and it was difficult
and maybe the thought crossed your mind,
is it even worth it?
Maybe the thought of quitting crossed your mind.
Listen, I know people that have quit
and I'm sure you do as well.
People that in the midst of a trial,
that remember the trial was not designed,
we focused on this a couple of weeks ago,
the trial is not designed to defeat us
or to destroy us or to discourage us.
No, the trial is designed to enable us to grow
and to flourish and to be used of the Lord,
but at times because of the human nature that we have,
that we face those trials and it can be so overwhelming
that we're ready to just quit.
But here the Bible says,
blessed is the man that endureth temptation.
It's a sad thing when I see individuals,
believers that are discouraged and on the brink of quitting.
I know pastors that have quit
and I'm sure that you do as well.
They just got so overwhelmed in the work of the ministry
and so overwhelmed with problems and whatever it might be
and they just got discouraged.
Every time I go to a pastor's meeting,
I don't go to them every single month,
but there is a pastor's meeting
that I try to hit as often as I can.
It's held once a month
and I go as often as I can possibly go.
But as I pray, as I'm traveling to those meetings,
I always pray this way,
Lord, there's probably somebody that's gonna be there
that's ready to quit.
God, would you help me to be able to be an encouragement
and a blessing to that individual?
Would you help me to be able to know what to say,
to try to keep them in the fight?
Listen, the devil wants you to get discouraged and quit.
The devil wants you to drop out.
He wants you to become a casualty.
That's what the enemy wants.
But in the midst of the trial,
we find the conduct of the individual
that's mentioned in verse number 12
that James is writing here.
He says, blessed is the man that endureth.
And we find here not only the conduct
of the one that endures to persevere,
to remain, to abide, to stay close to God.
You know, in the midst of the trial,
that's when you need God the most.
Amen?
You know what happens?
I see it so often, what happens,
somebody's in the midst of a trial.
I mean, the most difficult trial
maybe they've ever endured and they've had in their lives
and they do this, they come apart from church.
They come apart from God.
They don't come to church.
Why?
Because they're so burdened and they're so heavy
and they feel like I can't.
And listen, that's when you need church the most.
They don't read their Bible.
Why?
Because they're in the midst of this trial
and they're overwhelmed and they're heavy.
No, that's when you need the Bible the most.
Amen?
And what happens is sometimes we take exactly
the opposite approach of what we should be taking,
that I need more.
I need to be in God's presence.
I need to have more from God.
Listen, there's something that God can do
in the midst of the trial in your life
through the fellowship with the brethren,
through the preaching of the word.
You read the Bible.
Listen, there's times when your heart is overwhelmed
and maybe your mind is just not where it ought to be,
but you keep reading the Bible
and you keep reading the Bible
and you keep going to church and God will help you.
We need it.
We don't need to come apart and say,
you just don't know how bad it is.
No one may know how bad it is, but God does.
And can I tell you something that's,
and I know it might not make somebody feel good,
but let me just be honest with you.
The reality is it doesn't really matter
if anyone understands how hard it is.
It doesn't matter.
What really matters is that God knows.
You know why that matters?
Because if for some reason I can understand
exactly the heartache that you have,
I can't really do a whole lot about it.
Amen?
So even if I could fully understand the severity
of the difficulty that you're facing,
I can't really help like God can.
Amen?
And sometimes we can get overwhelmed.
Just nobody understands.
No, no, God understands.
And he's the only one that matters.
Amen?
And we need to understand that.
We need to have that concept in our minds
to realize that God understands
and that God is able to help us to endure
through the temptation, through the trial.
Notice at the end of the verse, the Bible says this,
which the Lord hath promised.
Notice what it says, to them that love him.
We not only notice the conduct of this individual
that's mentioned in verse number 12,
that they're enduring,
but we understand that the scriptures say here
that they love God.
Oh, I'm so thankful.
Last week, we focused on the entire message
of the truth that God loves me.
In fact, I titled the message last Sunday morning,
Jesus Loves Even Me.
What a blessing to understand the love of God
and to have Paul praise for the believers in Ephesus
that they would comprehend God's love,
that they would truly understand
and it's sad when you think about the church at Ephesus
for the indictment against them in the book of Revelation
when the letter is written
is that they left their first love.
And here we find that the scriptures tell us
of this one that is mentioned in verse number 12
that not only is their conduct one of enduring,
but we find that their conduct is one that they love God.
What does it mean to love God?
Understand 1 John plainly teaches us that we love him
because he first loved us.
And we understand that the Bible continues to teach us
in the book of 1 John that when we love him,
we keep his commandments.
There is evidence, proof positive evidence
that God gives us in his word, whether or not we love God.
Anyone can run around and have a t-shirt, a hat,
a bracelet or whatever that says, I love Jesus.
You can buy them, you can get them.
But the scriptures give us evidence
of what it means to love Jesus, to love God.
And we find that as we understand this individual
and we begin to comprehend the truth
that the Bible says to them that love him.
I asked the question this morning, do we really love God?
Now think about this, if I understand God's love for me
and in response to God's love for me, I love God.
And I understand within the context
of what we're looking at here in James chapter number one,
that I'm going through a trial.
I'm, as it says, I've fallen into,
according to verse number two, this divers temptations.
I'm facing a trial in my life,
but as I'm facing the trial in my life,
I'm reminded of a very important truth
and that is God's love for me.
Paul asked the question in Romans chapter number eight,
what can separate us from the love of God?
We won't take the time to look there,
but at the end of Romans chapter number eight,
the scriptures go through a whole list of things
and then tell us that no, there's nothing
that can separate us from the love of God.
Listen, the trial that you're enduring,
the trial that you're facing,
the trial that's got you upside down and overwhelmed.
Let me remind you that God loves you,
but when you understand God's love for you,
then you love him.
And when I love God and I have that desire
to keep his commandments and I love him
in the best possible way that I could love him,
then I don't wanna give up,
I don't wanna throw in the towel,
I don't wanna miss what God has for me, why?
Because I love God.
And I believe the truth of verse number 12,
though it's dealing with the trials contextually,
verses two through 12, dealing with the trials that we face,
verse 13 through 15, dealing with the temptations,
the sinful aspect.
Can I tell you that the truth of verse number 12,
really the last part with regard to them that love him,
them that love God, carries with it a dual application.
Not only does it help me to endure the trials that I face,
but can I say this and really a preview
to next week's message?
When I love God, it's gonna keep me from sin.
Because I love God more.
I love God more.
And we see, as we'll look at the temptation
that contextually is dealt with in verse.
verses 13 through 15 with the subject of sin.
How do we know that?
Because it says that it bringeth forth sin
and sin what is finished bringeth forth death.
And so we understand that's a different type of temptation
than what is dealt with in verses two through 12.
And we find that the context helps us to understand that.
But I wanna remind you this morning
that as we look at the trials that we face,
I mean, just living life and going through storms
and difficulties and trials,
we must remember that God loves us,
but we must love God, we must love Him.
And if I love Him, not only can I endure
through the trial of life, but it will keep me from sin.
It'll keep me from sin.
I use this illustration,
I'll probably use it again next week.
But the reality is that we live in a world
that obviously sin is just all around us
and it bombards us.
But when sin enters and there's some temptation to sin,
we have a choice, amen, we have a choice.
And if you love God more,
if your love for God is what it ought to be,
it'll keep us from that sin.
It'll help us to endure through the trials,
but also keep us from the sin
that temptations can bring.
So we note the conduct,
the individual that is mentioned here in verse number 12
is an individual that endures.
Listen, it's not that, have you ever had this idea?
Well, they just never have any problems.
You know, maybe somebody, you know,
I've had people say this to me, all right?
Counseling situations, I've had people say,
well, pastor, you just don't understand
because you don't have any problems.
I've had people say that to me.
Sometimes I don't have any problems,
I just don't share my problems.
We all have trials, we all have storms.
They all come in different ways and at different times.
And we have to come to the place
where it's not that we look at somebody and say,
well, look at how well,
they just must never have a bad day.
They just never have a problem.
Just the enemy must not know their address.
I mean, they just never have a trial, no.
It's that they have a perspective
that's a biblical, godly perspective.
And in the midst of the trial, they're not gonna quit.
They're not gonna throw in the towel.
And they understand what God's done for them
and what God's purpose is in that thing.
And they're gonna keep plowing, keep on keeping on, amen?
1 Corinthians 15, verse 58,
be therefore my beloved brethren be steadfast,
unmovable, always abounding in the work of the Lord.
For as much as you know that your labor
is not in vain in the Lord, praise God.
We not only note the conduct, but we note the condition.
And I've alluded to this throughout the message
and so I'll be quick on this point here.
But notice the condition of the individual.
The Bible says, blessed is the man
that endureth, notice, temptation.
This individual that is being spoken of in verse number 12
is one that is dealing with being tried.
The Bible says, blessed is the man
that endureth temptation for when he is tried.
There is a trial that is taking place.
There is some storm in the life of the individual
that is being mentioned here in verse number 12
of our text of scripture.
And we find the condition of the individual.
There's a trial.
It's something that they're facing.
We don't know the details of it.
Again, the scriptures are clear to understand
and communicate to us that there are a variety
of temptations and a variety of times
and so on and so forth.
And we find that in verse number two,
the Bible says, my brethren, count it all joy
when you fall into divers temptations.
Knowing this, remember, there's some things
that God wants us to know.
There's some things that God wants to be just ingrained
in our heart and in our mind.
And he's given to us a Bible and I'm so thankful.
Oftentimes what I find with individuals
that their lives are falling apart
and they're dealing with a trial
and they don't have the ability to endure,
they really have an absence of God's word in their lives.
Somebody noted this, that a Bible that's falling apart
probably belongs to someone whose life isn't.
And man, there's a lot of truth in that.
And I'm thankful.
Listen, the Bible is to be read and reread and reread
and to be ingrained into the hearts of his people.
Why?
Because he wants us to know some things.
He wants us to be confident of some things.
He doesn't want us to be ignorant.
Often throughout the scriptures, my brethren,
he says, I would not that you be ignorant, concerning,
and I'll give whatever it is that the subject is
that's being dealt with in here.
He says, knowing this, that the trying of your faith
worketh patience, but let patience have her perfect work,
that ye may be perfect and entire, wanting nothing.
I mean, that truth of spiritual maturity,
that God is working in your life,
and through that trial, there's growth opportunity,
and there's the ability to understand God
in a more intimate way, knowing this.
So the condition of this individual
that is mentioned in verse number 12
is the condition of someone that's in a trial.
It says that for when he is tried,
no doubt, you face trials, and you thought,
I don't wanna go through that again.
No more trials, please.
But we find this truth, look over in 1 Peter, if you will,
and I wanna remind you, in 1 Peter chapter number one,
the Bible tells us, and again, gives us some insight
with regard to the subject of trials
that's important for us to be aware of.
Let me read, I was gonna start in verse six,
but I wanna begin in verse number three,
because I wanna remind you of all that God's done for us,
and how much He loves us, what His plan is for us.
The Bible says, blessed, in verse number three,
be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ,
which, according to His abundant mercy,
hath begotten us again into a lively hope
by the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead.
Aren't you thankful to be saved?
He says, in verse number four,
to an inheritance incorruptible and undefiled,
and that fadeth not away, reserved in heaven for you.
Listen, one day, we're gonna put off this mortal, amen?
And we're gonna go into the presence of our Lord
and Savior Jesus Christ forever and ever,
and the Bible says that we have an inheritance,
and that inheritance, the Bible says, is incorruptible,
it's undefiled, it fadeth not away,
it's reserved in heaven for us.
I love the language of verse number four.
It encourages me, it gives me great hope.
And we find that He says, in verse number five,
who are kept by the power of God
through faith unto salvation,
ready to be revealed in the last time.
Listen, I'm thankful to be kept by the power of God.
The Bible tells us in John chapter number 10
that Jesus says that His sheep know my voice,
and He knows them, and He says,
I give unto them eternal life,
and they shall never perish.
But then He gives us this truth that we're in His hand,
and that His hand is in the Father's hand.
Praise God.
Listen, the trial is not designed to destroy you,
but to develop you.
And this is what God wants us to understand.
We're kept by the power of God.
We have this expected end.
In verse number six, notice it says, we're in.
Now, it's important that we understand that God,
in His perfect wisdom and knowledge,
as He's giving Peter,
all scripture is given by inspiration of God,
and here in 1 Peter, as He's penning the words,
that God gives the truth of verses three through five
in preparation for the truth that comes in verse number six.
Knowing that we're saved, and we're secure,
and that God has a plan, and we have a future,
and we have this inheritance, He says, we're in.
Ye greatly rejoice, though now for a season.
Listen, the reality is that we can sing about heaven,
and we can look forward to heaven,
but we're living in the here and now.
Amen?
Listen, I'm thankful for every truth
that God gives us in His word about heaven.
I truly am.
I'm thankful for every truth that God gives us in His word
about the rapture, about the tribulation,
about the millennial, about the eternal state.
I'm thankful for all of it.
I'm thankful for the prophecies.
I'm thankful to study through the book of Revelation,
and all that we have in the Old Testament
with the major and minor prophets
concerning all of those things
that are going to come to pass.
I am thankful for that, but we live today.
We live today.
It's good for us to look forward to the fact
that I'm gonna see Jesus one day face to face,
and when I see Him, I'm gonna be like Him.
We looked at that a little bit last week
in 1 John chapter number three,
and every man that hath this hope purifies himself,
even as he is pure.
Man, I'm thankful that one day, because He saved my soul,
I'll be like Him, and I will forever be with Him.
But that's one day in the future.
I'm living today.
So Peter tells these folks that are scattered abroad
in 1 Peter because of the persecution
that's coming through Nero.
Remember, it's different than the folks
that are being written to in the book of James.
They're dealing with trials and difficulties
because of the persecution really that came from the Jews.
We looked at that in the very beginning
of our study of the book of James.
You follow the path through the book of Acts
and you see the persecution of those
that James is writing to is very different
than the persecution that those that Peter's writing to.
But they're both dealing with trials.
And Peter says, you're gonna be with God forever
because you got saved, praise the Lord.
Wherein you greatly rejoice though now,
though now, though now for a season.
If need be, you're in heaviness
through manifold temptations.
I have the only phrase in verse number six
that I have underlined in my Bible is if need be.
There's some verses that I underline the entire verse.
There's some verses that I circle a word
and maybe just one word or just a phrase
or maybe a couple of phrases and connect them and whatever.
If you're in the habit of writing your Bible,
you have a certain aspect of what you do
and it makes sense in your mind.
I have those words if need be because it helps me.
Because only God knows what I need.
Because if it was up to me, I would never need it.
Amen, would you agree with that?
If it were up to you, you would never need it.
And you wouldn't grow much either.
If need be, God knows.
He says you're in heaviness through manifold temptations.
And then he says this, that the trial of your faith
being much more precious than of gold that perisheth,
though it be tried with fire,
might be found unto praise and honor and glory
at the appearing of Jesus Christ.
Listen, one day I'm gonna see him in our trials.
Listen, the songwriter said this,
it will be worth it all, amen?
When we see Jesus, it will be worth it all.
Just one glimpse of his dear face, hallelujah.
At the end of the book in 1 Peter chapter number five,
notice the Bible says this in verse number 10.
But the God of all grace who hath called us
into his eternal glory by Christ Jesus,
after that ye have suffered a while,
make you perfect, establish, strengthen, settle you.
To him be glory and dominion forever and ever, amen.
This is very similar language to what we read
in James chapter number one,
that we understand that the purpose in the trial
is that we're to, it's working for our good,
it worketh patience, but let patience have her perfect work
that ye may be perfect and entire, wanting nothing.
In here, Peter says, after that ye have suffered a while,
make you perfect, establish, strengthen, settle you.
The one that endures, listen,
they're going through a trial,
but they have a perspective of understanding
what God has revealed to us in the purpose for that trial
and what God's trying to do.
We finished up 2 Corinthians last year
as we looked at the study
through the book of 2 Corinthians
and dealing with the subject of God's grace is sufficient.
And as we looked at that,
we saw in the concluding portions of 2 Corinthians 13
that Paul is praying for the spiritual maturity.
He's wishing, he's praying for their perfection.
But then he tells them, be perfect.
And I said this at the end of last year,
it's a good thing that the spiritual leader
is praying for the spiritual maturity
of those that they're ministering to,
but there's a responsibility of the individual believer
to apply God's word in their lives.
It's great that someone's praying for you
and we ought to pray one for another.
And it was good that Paul was praying
for their spiritual maturity,
but there were some things that they had to do.
And Paul puts that responsibility on them.
And we find here, not only do we note the conduct,
but we see the condition that the one,
they're in a trial,
this individual that's mentioned in James 1
for when he has tried and they're facing it,
they're dealing with it.
Peter will talk about,
we won't look back there at this point,
but in chapter four,
he talks about the think it not strange
concerning the fiery trial.
Again, the diversity of the trials,
sometimes we could say the intensity of the trials.
God's not trying to break you.
He's not trying to destroy you.
He's trying to develop you.
And I'm thankful that God loves us enough
to develop us.
To develop us.
He doesn't just leave us.
He desires that we would grow and that we would mature.
And I'm thankful, listen,
there are times when people can share testimonies
of something that was going on in their life
and how God used that thing to bring them back to Him.
Praise God.
You say, man, I was at the lowest point
I've ever been in my life.
But God, praise God.
We find here not only the conduct
and the condition of this individual,
but I want you to note the confidence.
God wants us to be confident of some things.
In fact, in Sunday school this morning,
I referenced a familiar verse for some of us.
In fact, I think some of you,
it's your favorite verse of scripture, Philippians one,
in verse number six, where the scripture's saying,
being confident of this very thing,
that he which hath begun a good work in you
will perform it until the day of Jesus Christ.
God wants us to be confident of some things.
He wants us to have this confidence.
And here we find that in verse number 12,
there's the confidence of this individual.
Notice, first of all, the Bible says, blessed.
Blessed is the man that endureth temptation.
And so we find that the first measure of confidence
that we can look at of the individual
that's enduring temptation,
they're in the midst of it, they're enduring,
they're loving God, they're facing all of these things,
but the Bible says that they're blessed.
And I want you to understand,
and I want you to remember this morning,
that the world doesn't define blessed the way that we do,
the way that God does.
The world's definition for blessing
and the world's definition for being a blessed individual
is very different than what God's definition would be,
than what our definition should be.
I mentioned this last night in the Valentine's banquet,
and I feel led of the Lord
to mention it again here this morning.
There was a funeral that Holly went to on Thursday.
She went to a funeral on Wednesday and on Thursday.
By the way, both of those funerals
were just homegoing services.
Both individuals served God,
had great testimonies of salvation.
I mean, live for the Lord.
That's an exciting funeral.
I mean, listen, it was a worship service.
I watched the one on Thursday
because they had it available via live stream,
and it was like, it was a two-hour church service, man.
It was awesome.
Praise God.
But sometimes we think about being blessed.
What does it mean to be blessed?
The world looks at it differently than what we look at it.
How much do you have?
What position do you hold?
A lot of times that's how they,
I'm blessed because I have this, because I have.
In that funeral, something was said about the deceased
and all the lives that they touched.
They touched my life.
They retired from the ministry, pastored for years.
Him and his, the wife was the one that died.
Started a church, had a Christian school.
I mean, just countless number of lives that they touched.
After they retired, they traveled
to just go and try to be an encouragement
and a blessing to pastors.
I remember getting a phone call.
Pastor, man, this is, gave me their names,
and we're gonna be coming through your area,
and we just wanna take your family out to dinner.
We just wanna encourage you.
And I thought, well, that's different.
Praise the Lord.
I mean, I didn't grow up in their church.
I didn't grow up in their Christian school.
They, we had a great time, a fellowship.
They just wanted to encourage.
They mentioned some statistics of how many they felt
when they ministered, how many pastors were discouraged,
and it was well north of 50%.
And that's just what they did in their latter years.
They just wanted to spend and be spent.
And that's what they were doing, living for the Lord.
And there were people that were touched.
They said that the wife, the one who died,
that together, husband and wife,
they had a list of 300 or so pastors
that they prayed for every day.
I was on that list, and that encourages me.
But it also reminds me, as the pastor said,
there's a gap now, because there was somebody
that was interceding that's now in God's presence,
and we need some people that will be people of prayer.
Man, that's true.
But I know I was on the list.
I'd get a text every once in a while.
We'd get a happy birthday or a happy anniversary.
I mean, it was encouragement.
But I say this to talk about being blessed.
Their blessing was different
than how other people look at blessing.
And I said this to the folks last night
at the Valentine's Banquet.
The son-in-law of the deceased
went with the father-in-law to the bank,
because the deceased, the wife,
she took care of all the finances.
And so son-in-law's gonna go and help father-in-law
figure out what's going on.
And they sit down with the banker,
and he's like, look, we have no idea.
She took care of everything.
We just need you.
to help us with accounts," so on and so forth, and the banker said, kind of in a jokingly
way, said, you'll be happy to know that they had a savings account with one penny, literally,
one penny.
You know what the husband said?
We had plans to split it, to be spent doing the Lord's work.
There were hundreds upon hundreds upon hundreds upon hundreds, thousands that probably were
watching online that their lives touched, that they ministered to, that they were willing
to spend and be spent, and can I tell you that they were blessed.
They were blessed.
They didn't have a lot of monetary blessing, and that's sometimes what our world looks
at, but could I tell you I'd rather have that kind of blessing than to have a bank
account with billions upon billions like some people in our world have?
I'd rather have that kind of blessing.
So the Bible tells us of the confidence of the one that endureth temptations, that's
enduring through the trials of life, that they'll be blessed.
Listen, God knows and God sees and He knows our frame, He knows that we're but dust, and
His blessing is different than what the world looks at as blessing.
You have no idea in the trials of life that you're going to face, the people's lives,
that God would allow you to touch.
But if you give up, if you quit under the pressure, it's not worth it.
You're not going to touch those lives.
You're not going to have that blessing, right?
There's a man that I spoke with years ago, he's a Fairfax County fire marshal, my favorite
people.
They come and do fire inspections here, and sometimes it's exciting and sometimes it's
exciting.
I won't go into all the details of some of the experiences I've had, but it's been fun.
But on one particular occasion, it was during COVID actually, I've never seen the man ever
again.
There's not that many fire marshals in Fairfax County, and I've never seen that guy prior
to, never seen him after.
He came here and did one inspection.
The guy that we have now has been here like four times, and I wish he's only been here
once, if you get what I'm saying.
It was during COVID, we walked through those doors, got not even a full step in.
He was in front of me and he says, Preacher, I just have one question.
Are God's people meeting?
No, he said this, are you having church?
And I kind of said, well, yeah.
He's like, no, no, no.
I want to know, are God's people meeting together in God's house?
And here's my initial thought.
I'll be honest with you, this is a setup question.
Setup question.
We're in the midst of COVID.
This guy is trying to get us in trouble, right?
Just being honest.
And I said, yes, sir, we are.
Because we were.
We're having church.
We didn't stop having church.
And he turned around and he said, I am so glad to hear that.
He said, you know how many churches I go to in this county that aren't having, they're
not assembling?
And he's just, and he was, and I said, well, this is, I think this is going to be good.
He said, what's that map over there?
And I began to explain it to him.
And then he told me a story.
He said, it was kind of funny because he started out the story this way.
He said, do you know why I'm a fire marshal?
I just met you like five minutes ago.
How would I have any clue how you're, why you're a fire marshal?
Right?
I have no idea.
He's like, let me tell you the story.
And I'll give you the very condensed version.
Had some family in New York that had died and they had a responsibility to go clean
up a property.
And him and his siblings and some cousins and just a whole group of people were up there
cleaning up this property.
And accidentally, inadvertently, his brother caught him on fire.
He had second and third degree burns all over his body.
Just absolutely terrible.
If you've ever been burned, you know the pain.
I mean, you've just been barely burned and you know the pain.
He began to share with me that through that trial in his life, he was already a saved
person.
But he shared with me his perspective on that thing.
And he said this, he said, you know, as I laid in the hospital bed, he said, I was in
the worst pain I've ever experienced in my entire life.
He said, but on more than one occasion, I had the opportunity to share the gospel with
a doctor.
I had the opportunity to share the gospel with a nurse.
I had the opportunity to share the gospel with other patients.
And he said, you know, there's some people that are saved today because of what I went
through.
And then he said this.
He said, I'd do it again tomorrow if it meant that I could share my faith and people would
get saved.
Man, that just...
Because so often we're just like, no, I don't want trials.
I don't want to deal with the difficulties, I don't want the storms of life.
But what is God trying to do?
He says, blessed is the man that endureth temptations, for when he has tried, he shall
receive the crown of life.
And we'll get to that in just a moment, which the Lord hath promised to them that love him.
But I want you to think about being blessed.
The way that God defines being blessed is different than what the world defines.
And God will allow us at times to go through these trials they're under, if need be, as
we looked in 1 Peter chapter number one, and he allows these things in our lives.
And if we endure, we have the opportunity to minister and impact other people.
Not only do we grow, not only do we see and learn new things about God and understand
in a greater way who our God is, but God will use us in the midst of that trial and we'll
be blessed as we endure.
But if we give up and we say, this isn't fair.
How many times do you hear people say, life isn't fair?
Man, all the time.
It's like a catchphrase for the last generation.
Life isn't fair.
Get over it.
Amen?
How many of you learned at a young age life wasn't fair?
Come on.
Life is what it is.
But when we face that trial, if we have that approach and that pity party and the woe is
me, then God's purposes aren't realized.
He says, blessed is the man that endureth temptation.
We're talking about the confidence.
Listen, God has something good, for we know.
For we know.
Romans 8 verse 28.
Sometimes we just start with the all things work together for good to them that love God,
but the verse truly starts with, for we know.
For we know.
Remember we looked at knowing this in verse number three?
God wants us to know that all things do work together for good to them that love God, to
them who are the called according to His purpose, and He wants us to understand that God has
a purpose.
Not only is He blessed, but He's rewarded.
I started out the message this morning by saying that this passage is not talking about
a lost man being saved because of enduring trials, but that a saved man will be blessed
because of enduring trials, will be rewarded.
And we find here in verse number 12 that the Bible says He shall receive the crown of life.
And what a blessing to think about that truth, that God has crowns that will be given for
those at the judgment seat of Christ.
I'm thankful, by the way, because of being saved that I'll be at the judgment seat of
Christ and not at the great white throne judgment.
The great white throne judgment is a judgment that only lost people will be at, and there's
only one result of that judgment, and that is the lake of fire.
We think about the judgment seat of Christ, there are crowns, and we don't have the time,
but there's five references of different crowns that are mentioned throughout the New Testament.
And the question really, when we think about this, the truth that God gives, that He shall
receive the crown of life.
Listen, that's something beyond right now today's recognition.
It's not about getting the applause of our fellow humans, it's about getting the applause
of Christ and understanding here that I will stand before Him, but for the one that endureth
temptation not only will their life be blessed, but then we see not only the here and now
being blessed, but of course most focused on the eternal being rewarded, the crown of
life.
It's mentioned also to the church in Smyrna, if you were to look in Revelation 2, we won't
take the time to look there, but you see it mentioned.
And really the question, when I think about the confidence of this individual, I ask this
question, what kind of reward do you desire?
Because the Bible says we'll be rewarded.
Notice if you will, I'll close with this, 1 Corinthians chapter 9.
1 Corinthians chapter 9, look at these verses of Scripture with me as the Apostle Paul is
writing and he's given us a perspective that I think is helpful with regard to understanding
these crowns.
It doesn't mention the crown of life specifically here, we see that in James and again in Revelation,
but I want you to notice what Paul says.
In verse 23 of 1 Corinthians 9, the Bible says this, and this I do for the gospel's
sake that I might be partaker thereof with you.
Know ye not that they which run in a race run all.
and receive it the prize, so run that you may obtain.
You know, he would be talking about the Isthmus Games
and all that, they'd be very familiar what was going on.
Right now, we're involved in the Winter Olympics.
Those folks that are competing in the Winter Olympics,
they're competing so that they could win a medal.
Am I right?
I've heard, I don't watch very many of the Olympics,
but I saw this thing, the aerial jumping,
those people were absolutely insane.
Amen, jumping like 65 feet in the air,
doing 14 flips, and then landing.
Absolutely insane.
I don't know, I asked this question,
how did somebody figure out they could do that?
Like, how many broken bones do you get?
Like, I don't know, like my mind
just goes crazy with that, right?
But the reality is that I heard them say this,
I watched a few minutes of that just the other night,
and here's what I heard the commentator say repeatedly.
They trained four years for three seconds.
I heard it repeatedly.
And by the way, the crown that they get,
if they get the crown, the medal,
it's just corruptible, right?
And so Paul says that they that run, run to obtain.
They're competing so they could win.
Contrary to our current environment
of everyone gets a trophy,
no, there's a winner and there's a loser, amen?
And here it says in verse 25,
and every man that striveth for the mastery
is tempered in all things.
Now, they do it to obtain a corruptible crown,
but we, an incorruptible.
Listen, we live for eternity.
We don't live for the temporary.
We live in the temporary, we live in this world,
but our attention, our focus, our perspective
is to be on eternity, amen?
And it changes everything.
When we have the right perspective,
when we have the biblical perspective,
it will enable me to endure the trials,
the temptations that I'll face,
I'll be blessed by God, I'll be rewarded by God,
and I want God's blessing.
I want God's reward.
It doesn't matter, listen, it should not matter to you
what accolades some man can give you.
It should matter, and I understand,
and I'm not saying that you shouldn't be concerned
with regard to doing a good job and being the best
that you can be and all of that sort of thing.
I think that's commendable and it's appropriate.
Why?
Because whatsoever thy hand findeth to do,
do it heartily as unto the Lord.
And if you follow that principle,
you will be recognized temporally.
But that's not the focus.
The focus is to have God's blessing,
to have God's favor upon our lives.
We ask the question, what kind of reward do you desire?
I desire God's favor.
Don't quit, don't quit.
Somebody asked me this years ago.
It was a Bible college professor.
I believe it was William Jeffcoat,
a man that we support as a missionary right now.
And he asked a group of us in the class that day,
what will it take to stop you?
What will it take to stop you?
In other words, what will it take to make you quit,
to stop serving God, to give up?
Can I tell you this morning, the answer should be nothing.
I could tell you story after story.
You could read them yourselves as well.
You read the Fox's Book of Martyrs.
You read of other martyrs, people that faced such cruelty.
As they were literally being burned alive,
they were singing praise unto God.
They're testimonies of how God used them in that moment
as they endured that great fiery trial.
This morning, enduring trials, we all face them.
We all face them, we all deal with them.
The question is whether we endure through the trial.
It's not gonna be by your strength or by my strength,
it's by Him working through us and enabling us
as we have that perspective and that approach
that we understand that God has a purpose
and I love Him because He first loved me.
I don't know what you're dealing with.
And quite honestly, not that I don't wanna be able
to pray for you, but the reality is that I don't need
to know because God knows.
Whatever it is that you're facing,
can I tell you this morning,
can I encourage you this morning, endure.
Don't give up, stay in the fight.
The enemy wants you to be a casualty.
He wants to devour you.
But our God has a good plan and a good purpose for us
and He's not trying to destroy us, but to develop us.
Let us pray.
Father, we love you.
Thank you so much for loving us.
Thank you, God, for the truth that you give us in your word.
If we didn't have the Bible,
we would not know the things that we discussed this morning.
In fact, we might be like the friends of Job
that we read of, that didn't have a complete understanding
of what we now have having a whole Bible.
God, I pray that you would help each one
that's here this morning.
Lord, I know that we face trials.
In fact, I'm aware of some that are going
through some trials.
And Lord, I pray that you'd give us the grace
and the strength and the help that we need.
Help us to have our minds focused upon you and your word,
our hearts completely surrendered to thee.
Lord, help us to love you in response to your love for us.
Help us to trust you, to follow you.
Help us to abide in thee.
Lord, I pray that you would help us now
as we respond to what we've heard,
to how your spirit has moved and worked,
that Lord, you would help us to apply truth in our lives.
Well, thank you for the work that you'll do
for us in Christ's name, we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
We'll take a moment for an invitation.
Maybe this morning you're just in the midst of a trial.
You just need to have some time alone with God.
Some time alone with God.
Help me, Lord, I need your help.
Maybe you know somebody that's going through a trial
and you need to pray for them.
Maybe you just want to come and ask God,
I'm not in a trial right now,
but I know trials are gonna come.
Help me to endure.
Help me to have the spiritual maturity.
Help me to have the perspective that I need
to endure the trials of life.
I do not want to become a casualty.
I do not want to quit in the face of opposition.
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.
Christ is born.