I'm Philippians, the book of Philippians chapter number 4.
And in just a very few moments I'm going to begin reading in verse number 15 of the chapter
and be reading through verse number 19.
I do want to encourage you, if you would please, to leave your Bibles handy.
We're going to be using them throughout the course of the Bible message this evening.
So good to see you. Thank you for coming.
I appreciate you going the extra mile to be here tonight.
As you know, I was telling the pastor earlier in the week
when I was pastoring the first church that I was blessed to pastor,
I would be so busy looking around trying to see who wasn't there
that I'd often take for granted those that went the extra mile to be there.
And so some of you worked really hard today and some of you had a day off
and you worked even harder on your day off than you have at work.
You're going to have to go back to work to get a break.
But you made church a priority tonight and that encourages your preacher,
your preacher's wife, their family,
and that is encouraging to your fellow brothers and sisters in Christ.
So thank you so much for being here tonight.
Let me say before we read the text out of the book of Philippians,
chapter number 4 this evening,
Cassie and I want to thank you not only for your prayerful
but for your financial support every single month.
You have certainly sent once again unto our necessity
and I want you to know how grateful we are.
We could not do what God has put in our hearts to do
without pastors like your precious pastor
and without churches like the Fellowship Baptist Church.
And Cassie and I are so grateful.
Thank you for allowing us to be a part of your missions outreach here.
And thank you so much for helping us even recently
with our trip coming up to Brazil.
A lot of folks may not realize that all of the trips that I make like that abroad
are at our own expense.
And so again, we could not do that without the help of our supporting churches.
And so we're very, very appreciative.
We're very, very grateful.
Thank you for such a wonderful place to stay this week
at the prophet's chamber over here.
I call it the land down under.
We're having a wonderful time in the land down under.
And we're just enjoying the friendship and the fellowship of our friends
right here at the Fellowship Baptist Church.
Now on the way out, if you would please,
if you'd be so kind to come by the table,
we have Macedonia's latest Focus on the Field magazines.
These magazines are absolutely free of charge.
And if you'd pick one up on the way out tonight, I'd appreciate it.
I tell folks everywhere I go, Brother Ryan,
these magazines are million sellers.
We've got a million in the cellar.
And if you could help us get them out of there and to your house,
we would appreciate that.
And so I've got this one.
I think I've got a little bit left of another one back there as well,
another edition.
Again, they're absolutely free of charge.
And if you'd pick up a prayer card and remember to pray for us,
we certainly would appreciate that.
And then I don't normally say anything about the music,
but I've just learned that if I don't say anything about it,
people don't even know we have music available.
Every song that I've been blessed to sing this week has been recorded,
and we have CDs back there, but we also have jump drives.
You know, we're discovering that all of the cars these days,
they don't even have CD players anymore.
Now some of us in the building, we can remember cassette tapes.
Can you remember that?
Some of you young folks have to Google that.
But some of you older folks, some of us can remember eight tracks, amen.
And I'll just stop right there.
But I have jump drives of all of the music as well.
I see some wives nudging their husbands right there, I'm telling you.
And so all the jump drives are available.
And a while back, some of those real techie guys in the office,
they took all of my recordings over the course of the last 15 years,
and they put them on one jump drive.
And this one jump drive right here on just that little jump drive
has 15 years' worth of recordings.
That's about 12 full-length CDs.
That's over 120 songs recorded.
And Cassie will be glad to talk to you about that.
That's 12 CDs for about the price of seven.
And that pretty much just covers our cost for doing it.
And the Lord has been so good since we've been in missions
and on the road every week for the last 12 years.
God has worked through our CD sales to put all of the gas in our vehicles.
And these days, that's a special blessing.
And we're so very grateful.
Well, have you found your place in the book of Philippians?
If so, and if you're able, would you please stand
as we read the Word of God together.
Your pastor and pastor's wife were so kind to take us to brunch today.
We had wonderful food, and the fellowship was even better.
And I'm so thankful for your precious pastor and his family
and their friendship to our family.
And boy, didn't you enjoy the good preaching last night.
Brother Ryan, boy, what a great message.
I'm so impressed with Brother Ryan.
I text Brother Alton Beal last night after the service,
and I said, look, give that young man a raise. Amen.
Of course, I have yet to hear anything back.
No, he did text me back and say, hopefully, I'll get to see you later this week.
So we're hoping Brother Beal will make it before the conference is through.
Philippians chapter 4 and verse 15, we'll read the text
and then consider the context of the Apostle Paul's writing
throughout the introduction of the message tonight.
Paul writes in verse 15 of Philippians chapter 4,
Now ye Philippians know also that in the beginning of the gospel,
when I departed from Macedonia,
no church communicated with me as concerning giving and receiving,
but ye only.
For even in Thessalonica ye sent once again unto my necessity,
not because I desire a gift,
but I desire fruit that may abound to your account.
But I have all, and abound.
I am full, having received of Epaphroditus
the things which were sent from you,
an odor of a sweet smell, a sacrifice,
acceptable, well-pleasing to God.
But my God shall supply all your need
according to His riches in glory by Christ Jesus.
Again, I want to encourage you, if you would please,
to leave your Bibles handy.
We're going to be using them throughout the course of the message tonight.
And I don't often say this, but let me just say this tonight.
There's a reason why I say that.
Leave your Bibles handy.
And here's why I say that.
When it comes to missions, when it comes to world evangelism,
when it comes to reaching the world with the gospel,
I have an opinion.
But God did not call me to preach my opinion.
I'm not here to tell you what I have to say about world evangelism.
I want to take that Bible and show you what God has to say.
That's why I say, leave your Bibles handy.
We're going to be using them tonight throughout the course of the message
as I preach on the fall the opportunity that wasn't missed in missions.
Let's pray.
Father, thank you for your inspired, inerrant, infallible, impeccable word.
And, Lord, what a joy it is to know it's indestructible as well.
And, Father, we would all be very, very wise from the pulpit
to the last chair in the building to not only be hearers but doers of thy word.
Now, Father, I'm nothing without thee,
and I long to be a blessing to these, your precious people.
So I pray, therefore, you would cleanse me of sin and self
and fill me with your precious Holy Spirit.
If you could make a preacher out of me tonight, or if you would,
I sure would appreciate it.
I need you tonight, and I thank you for helping me.
In Jesus' name I pray, amen.
Thank you so much for standing.
Please be seated.
As you study Paul's epistle to the church of Philippi,
one thing will become abundantly evident.
Paul had a special place in his heart
for his friends in the Macedonian colony of Philippi.
And his friends at Philippi had a very special place in their heart
for the apostle Paul.
Paul loved the church of Philippi.
Of course, this wasn't the largest church that Paul was acquainted with.
It certainly wasn't the wealthiest church.
However, it would eventually become one of the most strategic churches
in the New Testament record
because this, ladies and gentlemen,
was the church that refused to miss its opportunity in missions.
Please allow me to call your attention if I may to verse 15 again.
Here in verse 15,
Paul makes a promise to the church of Philippi.
It's a striking comment that is worthy of our consideration tonight.
Paul writes, Now ye Philippians know also, that in the beginning of the gospel,
when I departed from Macedonia, no church communicated with me as concerning
giving and receiving, but ye only.
Now please, please don't misunderstand.
Paul isn't saying here that no other church ever supported him at any time
during his missions endeavors, because we know from studying his epistles
in the New Testament of the Bible, they certainly did.
However, here in verse 15, he is calling our attention to the fact
that at the earliest stage of his missions ministry,
when the work that God had called him to do was young and vulnerable,
during that particular season of his ministry,
no other church entered into partnership with him
in a structural, repetitive sense of giving and receiving,
but this church, the church of Philippi.
When Paul needed support the most,
Philippi alone stepped forward to help.
Others had opportunity, but failed to take advantage of it.
But not this church, not the church of Philippi.
The church of Philippi was the church that refused to miss its opportunity in missions.
According to the text before us, when other churches remained silent,
this, ladies and gentlemen, was the church that spoke up.
When other churches hesitated, this is the church that helped.
When others missed the moment, this, ladies and gentlemen,
was the local New Testament church that seized the moment.
And therefore I must say, this local New Testament church
set a tremendous example for the Fellowship Baptist Church of Oakton, Virginia.
Hear me this evening, Christian friend.
Today, as we continue this Missions Emphasis Week,
you and I have set before us a great, may I say again,
a great opportunity.
And the opportunity that I'm speaking of
is the opportunity to invest in world evangelism.
It's an opportunity that, according to the Bible,
pays great dividends, not only here on the earth below,
but even more importantly, in glory itself.
However, I believe it's just as vitally important for me to remind you
that opportunity isn't permanent.
Can I say that again?
Opportunity isn't permanent. Oh, no, no.
Opportunity passes.
Churches can miss it.
Believers can miss it.
God's people, they can miss it.
And therefore God sent me here tonight to implore each and every one of you,
please don't miss it.
Please allow me an opportunity to remind you
that what we do for Christ, we must do quickly.
There is no time for delay.
In fact, delayed obedience is nothing less than disobedience.
Jesus said in the Gospel of John chapter number 4,
Say not ye there yet four months, and then cometh harvest?
Behold, I say unto you, lift up your eyes and look on the fields,
for they are white.
Jesus said they are white already to harvest.
That word white here in John chapter 4
isn't referring to purity, but rather to ripeness.
Do you see what Jesus is doing in the Gospel of John chapter 4?
Jesus, in essence, in the minds of his disciples,
he is painting a picture.
The word white here is referring to the fact
that the crop has reached a very decisive moment.
And to delay the harvest ultimately means loss.
Here Christ is deliberately contrasting
human calculation with divine urgency.
The disciples were no doubt thinking in terms of agricultural timelines
while Christ was speaking of spiritual opportunity.
And do you realize in essence what our Savior is saying to the disciples
in John's Gospel?
He is saying to them then what he is leading me to tell you tonight.
What we do for Jesus, the souls we win for Jesus,
the churches we plant for Jesus,
those we make a difference in,
in the days to come, friend, we best get busy doing it.
Don't miss your opportunity.
According to the text we've read together tonight,
the church of Philippi didn't miss it.
And I'll be praying for the remaining portion of this week
that neither will you.
Please allow me to call your attention if I may to just a few truths
directly from the text tonight
concerning the opportunity that wasn't missed in missions.
First of all, notice when I look into these verses of Scripture
I see number one, a singular partnership.
I see a singular partnership.
Notice again if you would please what Paul writes in verse 15.
Paul writes, now ye Philippians know also that in the beginning of the Gospel
when I departed from Macedonia, no church,
watch this next word now, don't miss it, communicated.
No church communicated with me
as concerning giving and receiving,
but ye only, again, notice the word communicated.
The word communicated in verse 15
carries the idea of fellowship.
carries the idea of partnership
or of joint participation.
The word communicated assures us tonight, ladies and gentlemen,
this was not a casual charity
that the Philippian believers had involved themselves in.
Absolutely not.
It was most definitely a covenant cooperation.
It was not a partnership formed out of convenience,
but rather out of commitment.
And let me tell you why.
We know having read and studied the book of 2 Corinthians chapter number 8
that Philippi was one of those Macedonian churches
that gave sacrificially to Paul's missions efforts.
According to 2 Corinthians chapter 8
the Macedonians gave in spite of some things.
Do you remember?
They gave in spite of great affliction, the Bible says,
and they gave in spite of deep poverty.
Do you know why they gave in spite of some things?
I'll tell you why.
They were committed to making a difference in the lives of others
through the ministry of the apostle Paul.
Since they were giving out of great affliction and deep poverty,
can you just imagine how very easy it would have been
for this church to say,
let somebody else give.
Let somebody else partner with Paul.
We don't need to partner.
I mean, we're suffering great affliction.
We're living in deep poverty, not just poverty,
but the Bible specifically mentions deep poverty.
If any local New Testament church had a right,
and may I say a reason to say,
let somebody else give,
this church had a right and a reason to.
But they refused to say that.
If they were anything like some of the independent,
fundamental, temperamental Baptists that I've been blessed to pastor
for over two decades, they would say something like this.
Have you ever heard this?
Why in the world are we sending all this money to Paul
when we need it right here?
Don't get me started right there.
How many times are we going to send Paul another offering
when we need the money right here in our own church?
Oh, but not these Philippians.
They didn't say any of those things.
Do you know what the church of Philippi said?
This local New Testament church said,
if no one else will, we will.
If no one else will give, we will give.
If no one else will partner with Paul, we will partner with Paul.
I see a singular partnership here in the text.
This local New Testament church refused.
Let me say it again.
They refused to assume that someone else would give,
that someone else would shoulder the load.
Let me say it like this, and I'm moving tonight.
The church of Philippi chose a singular partnership.
over silent passivity.
That's why I say that we see a singular partnership in the text.
We not only see a singular partnership,
we secondly see a sacrificial participation.
Notice again, if you would please, verses 16 through 18.
Paul writes,
For even in Thessalonica ye sent once again unto my necessity,
not because I desire a gift,
but I desire fruit that may abound to your account.
But I have all and abound.
I am full, having received of Epaphroditus
the things which were sent from you,
an odor of a sweet smell,
a sacrifice acceptable,
well-pleasing to God.
And so yes, we see a singular partnership in verse 15,
but in verses 16, 17, and 18, I submit to you,
the text teaches us about a sacrificial participation.
Again, please allow me to remind you
that whatever contribution this church would have made to Paul,
it certainly would have been a sacrifice.
I want you to understand this church was not giving
to Paul's missions ministry
because they had 10,000 extra dollars in the missions account.
They were not giving because they could afford to give.
No, 2 Corinthians chapter 8 again teaches us
they were living in deep poverty.
That's why when Paul mentions their offering,
he never mentions the amount of it,
but only the sacrifice of it.
Notice a few things God, through the pen of the apostle Paul,
is careful and may I say very deliberate to teach us
about the church of Philippi's giving.
First of all, it was prompt.
The Bible goes to great lengths to teach us
that this church gave early
when other churches missed their opportunity.
Other churches missed it, but not this church.
Their giving was prompt.
Their giving was persistent.
What did Paul say in verse 16 about their giving?
Paul commends them in verse 16 for sending once and again,
once and again unto his necessity.
Doesn't that sound an awfully lot like what you do
every single month when you send your mission support out?
You send once and again unto the necessity
of missionaries around the world.
Your giving, as was the church of Philippi's giving,
is persistent.
The church of Philippi's giving was purposeful.
They may not have been able to preach like Paul,
but they could have a part in Paul's preaching,
and therefore again, verse 16 teaches,
they sent once and again unto whose necessity?
Unto Paul's necessity.
They may not have been able to plant churches like Paul,
but they could have a part in Paul's church planting,
and therefore according to verse 16,
they sent once and again unto Paul's necessity.
Their giving, according to the Bible, was purposeful.
Then their giving was proven.
Paul made it clear in the text
that the church didn't,
he didn't desire the church's offering
for his own personal benefit or for his own pleasure, oh no,
but rather that fruit would abound to whose account?
To their account, to the church's account,
and therefore proving to us, listen now,
God keeps really good records.
Their giving was proven.
And then God goes the extra mile in the text
through the pen of the apostle Paul
to teach us their giving was precious.
Now we know that their giving was precious
in the sight of God as a result of what the Holy Spirit
led Paul to write in verse 18.
Notice verse 18.
But I have all, and abound.
I am full, having received of Epaphroditus
the things which were sent from you,
an odor of a sweet smell,
a sacrifice acceptable, well-pleasing to God.
Don't miss this tonight.
How many times have you and I read
right over these verses of Scripture
and ultimately miss what the Bible is teaching us here?
The church of Philippi's giving
was precious in the sight of God.
Paul compared the church's offering
to an odor of a sweet smell,
a sacrifice acceptable, well-pleasing to who?
To God.
Do you see what Paul is doing here in the text?
Don't miss this.
Paul moves the church's financial gift
out of the economic realm
and puts it into the realm of worship.
This is helping me tonight
concerning my own missions giving.
Notice the phrase, an odor of a sweet smell.
That phrase comes directly from the Old Testament
sacrificial system.
Repeatedly, especially in the book of Leviticus,
you would read how the offerings
that were pleasing unto the Lord
were described as a sweet savor unto the Lord.
When a sacrifice was placed on the altar
and as the sacrifice was consumed by fire,
the rising smokes from the altar
symbolized complete and total surrender.
It spoke of devoted worship
and God's acceptance of the sacrifice.
Now in light of that truth,
what Paul is doing in verse 18
was assuring his friends
in the Macedonian colony of Philippi
that their gift might have reached him on the earth.
But while it was reaching him on the earth,
even more importantly, it was reaching God in heaven.
Let me put it like this.
Their missions offering became incense.
Their mission support became worship.
And their generosity became a fragrance,
a sweet smelling savor in the nostrils of God.
You see, so many people
miss their opportunity in missions giving
because they only assume
that missions giving is horizontal
and horizontal only.
They assume that our church gives to missions
and that's all they see,
horizontal giving from the church to the missionary,
from the church to the missionary.
That's why I call your attention
to the fact that their giving was precious in the text
because in Philippians chapter 4,
God, through the pen of the apostle Paul,
makes it abundantly clear
that missions giving isn't just horizontal
from the church to the missionary,
from the church to the missionary.
Oh, no, no, no.
The Bible teaches that missions giving is vertical
from the church to God.
I'm about to get happy tonight
and lose my dignity.
While you're giving horizontally,
God makes it abundantly clear
you are giving vertically.
Your missions check, your missions support,
your missions offering,
it becomes a sweet-smelling savor
in the nostrils of God.
No wonder Paul declared in their text
that their gift was a sacrifice,
acceptable, well-pleasing to who?
Somebody help me tonight.
To God.
Not to the missionary, but to God.
Not to the pastor or the missions director,
but to God.
You see, it's important that we realize tonight, church,
when you and I give to World Evangelism,
it is not merely funding.
It is not merely obligation.
It is not merely church budgeting.
It is worship.
Our missions giving becomes a fragrance in heaven,
a sacrifice on the altar,
a delight to God himself.
That's why I say, and by the way,
I say it without apology,
that failing to give to missions
is not only a missed opportunity of investment,
even more importantly,
it's a missed opportunity to worship.
What leaves our hands in obedience
will rise before God in worship.
And that's why my prayer is this week
for Fellowship Baptist Church,
please don't miss it.
Don't miss your opportunity to give, yes,
but don't miss your opportunity to worship.
So we see a singular...
partnership in the text. We see a sacrificial participation
in the text. But finally in verse 19, I see one other
thing. One other thing that's certainly worthy of our
attention tonight, because in Philippians chapter 4 and
verse 19, we see a secured promise. But my God shall
supply all your need according to His riches in glory by
Christ Jesus. Now I'll tell you what I felt impressed of
what the Lord to do. I want to back up and read verse
number 19 again and encourage each and every one of you
if you would please to read the verse audibly with me.
Would you read it with me? Let's read it together,
shall we? But my God shall supply all your need according
to His riches in glory by Christ Jesus. Now give me a
few minutes to preach real plain right here. Please
allow me an opportunity to remind you that this secured
promise wasn't made to the entire world. In fact, let me
preach even plainer. This secured promise in
Philippians 4.19, it isn't a promise made to the entire
family of God. It isn't. You can quote it all you want to
quote it, but don't take the verse out of the Bible. Don't
take it out of context. Philippians 4.19, this secured
promise was not given in isolation. It was given, are
you listening? If you're listening, say amen. It was
given in the context of committed missionary
partnership. Philippians 4.19 isn't a promise that can be
claimed by the stingy. Now you can quote it all you want to.
You can take it out of context, but you can't claim
Philippians 4.19 if you are a stingy, ministry-mizing
believer. Context, context, context. Philippians 4.19 was
a promise made to a local church that sacrificially gave
to make a difference in the lives of others. Philippians
4.19 was a promise that was made to a local church that
had a vision of reaching others with the same Gospel that
had changed their own lives. So when the church of
Philippi stepped in during a very critical, during a very
serious season of the Apostle Paul's missions, endeavors,
God Himself stepped in and promised to supply this
church's every need. It really is this simple. The church
supplied the missionaries' need and God supplied theirs. God
gave through them to give what He would never give to them to
keep. Their opportunity became their blessing. That is exactly
why if you back up in verse 15, you'll see that Paul not only
spoke of giving in verse number 15, but in the same verse of
Scripture, Paul also spoke of receiving. Do you see? I like to
call it God's circle of blessing. Giving and receiving,
giving and receiving, giving and receiving. That is exactly
what Paul spoke of in verse 15. And therefore when any church
refuses to miss its mission's moment, the Bible teaches that
heaven records the fruit and God Himself assumes the
responsibility of meeting that local church's needs. And
therefore my prayer is that each and every one of us would
be able to say in the years to come, should the Lord's day is
coming, when there was a need, when there was an opportunity,
when there was a door open for the sake of the Gospel, when
we partnered, we stepped up, we refused to assume that some
other church, some other group will do it. No, no. We refused
to miss our opportunity in world evangelism. I'll sum up the
message tonight by saying it like this. Don't miss it. I went
to our pastor not long ago. Cassie and I are sent out of the
People's Baptist Church of McDonough, Georgia. And we had
our missions conference back in November. In fact, we partnered
with Macedonia and had Macedonia's biannual national
conference, and our church hosted our national conference.
But at the same time, it was our home church's missions
conference as well. And so Cassie and I prayed about our
missions offering for the year, and we made a brand new missions
offering commitment last November. And after we made our
commitment, I went straight to my pastor, and I said to my
pastor, preacher, thank you for allowing me an opportunity
through my local church to give over and above my regular tithes
and offerings so that others could hear the Gospel. And if
you're wondering why I did that, I did that because I wanted him
to know I don't want to miss my opportunity. I don't want to
miss my opportunity not only to invest, but I don't want to miss
my opportunity to worship. Don't miss it tonight. I was preaching
at the Lighthouse Baptist Church in Seagrove, North Carolina,
where my dear friend Michael Poindexter serves as the pastor
and has for many years. After I finished preaching that night,
I encouraged the church family of the Lighthouse Baptist Church
to not miss their opportunity in missions. After the service was
over, there was a young lady in the church, and she came to
Pastor and Mrs. Poindexter, and she said, look, I'm just going
to be honest with you. In the past, I've missed it. I've had
an opportunity to invest. I've had an opportunity to worship.
I've had an opportunity to give horizontally, but also
vertically, and I've missed it. But pastor, that lady said that
night, with the help of the Lord this year, I'm not going to
miss it. I'm not going to miss it. I pray that you'll not miss
it as well. You've listened so well. Would you bow your head
with me? My Father, in Jesus' name tonight, oh how grateful I
am for your Word that teaches us about the opportunity that
wasn't missed in missions. Oh, I'm thankful for those that made
up the local church in the Macedonian colony of Philippi
that refused to miss their opportunity. Lord, if they would
have missed their opportunity, I would not have had this message
to preach tonight. And Lord, you have shown us directly from the
pages of your precious Word tonight, both the blessing and
the benefit of refusing to miss our opportunity in missions.
Lord, I don't know. Maybe there is someone here at Fellowship
Baptist Church, and they would say, like that dear lady at the
Lighthouse Baptist Church in Seagrove, North Carolina, in the
past I've missed it. And I can't get that opportunity back. But
as she said, Preacher, thank you for yet another opportunity this
year. And by your good grace, I'm not going to miss it this
year. Maybe someone here at the Fellowship Baptist Church needs
to make that same
commitment this year. And so I pray for Pastor Mann as he comes to close the
service as you lead him to do so that you would give him both wisdom and
discernment and I'll give you glory and honor and praise in Jesus name, Pastor.
Would you stand with me? Heads are bowed, eyes are closed. The message and the
challenge has been direct. Kimberly will play quietly on the piano. Let's be doers
of the word and not hearers only.