number thirty-five this evening, Genesis chapter number thirty-five,
and we'll be looking at verses one through fifteen this evening, Genesis chapter thirty-five
verses one through fifteen. It's hard to believe we've been in the study of the
book of Genesis here on Sunday evenings for quite some time. This is the seventy-fifth
message
that I have preached from the book of Genesis and we're in chapter thirty-five
and uh... there's only
uh... fifty chapters so maybe we'll, I think we'll make it to a hundred
messages on the book of Genesis
and uh... my uh... my uh... notebook that I have on my iPad for this sermon
series
I handwrite my notes and then use the iPad for them. I'm on page
number two hundred and twenty-six
uh... of notes and so uh... if you keep notes just on Sunday night you'll fill up
a sermon notebook that we pass out for just the book of Genesis
uh... but we're thankful for this wonderful book, a book of foundations
a book that is so important, a book that's constantly, especially the first
eleven chapters, constantly under attack
and I'm thankful for the record that God has given us. As Jacob, you'll remember
from back in Genesis chapter number twenty-eight, Jacob fled from his homeland
of course there were a number of circumstances surrounding his departure
from his homeland. Esau said he was going to kill him because of the
uh... the blessing and so on and so forth but we find that as he left his homeland
that he had an encounter with God
at Bethel.
We find that God
records for us as he would leave his homeland, as he would journey
to head to Paddan Aram, that he has that encounter with God
and uh... if you look at Genesis chapter twenty-eight, we're not going to look there this
evening specifically
but you might want to note it down to reference back to verses ten through
twenty-two
and you'll see that encounter
that that Jacob had with God at Bethel.
We find that Jacob spent several years in Paddan Aram, of course we know
that there are all sorts of events that take place there and uh... initially his
mother said go back to that place for just a few days until your brother's
anger
is subsided and then returned and it was years later
when he finally receives word from God as it's recorded in Genesis chapter
thirty-one
that he is to return to the land
of his fathers.
We find that Jacob was obedient to that instruction that God gave in Genesis
chapter thirty-one
and as he obeys the Lord we find and we've studied over the last several
weeks
uh... that eventually he would have that reunion and a wonderful reunion it
was
with his brother Esau.
There was a great concern leading up to the reunion and of course the
uh... circumstances surrounding the original departure were still fresh in
the mind and
Jacob was concerned that Esau would kill him and the family and so on and so
forth and
of course when he found out that
uh... he sent those messengers ahead and they said well Esau's coming towards you
he's got four hundred men with them
and uh... that just increased his anxiety level
and uh... but what a wonderful reunion that God
uh... gives us the account of
and we find that
uh... as Jacob returned and has that reunion
uh... prior to before he actually meets with Esau we find that he's at a place
called Mahanaim
and he's there at that place and then after the reunion
he goes to a place called Succoth and eventually to Shalem
which is the city of Shechem. Of course last week we studied Genesis chapter
thirty-four
and we dealt with the unfortunate events that are recorded for us there in Genesis
and we find after those unfortunate events
the Bible picks up in Genesis thirty-five
and God speaks to Jacob and notice what God says in verse number one
of Genesis thirty-five
and God said unto Jacob
Arise
go up to Bethel
and dwell there
and make there an altar unto God that appeared unto thee when thou
fleddest from the face of Esau
thy brother
I've titled the message this evening Returning
to Bethel
I want you to think about all of the things that had taken place in the life
of Jacob and we've studied
those events from chapter twenty-eight now to chapter thirty-five
and so many events, so many circumstances have taken place in the life of Jacob
but now God appears to Jacob and God speaks to Jacob
and says arise and go up to Bethel
and dwell there. If you're taking notes this evening I want you to notice with
me first of all the preparation
for the journey
the preparation for the journey. If you're gonna take a trip you prepare for
a trip. Typically we got some folks that are traveling this week. We have some
folks that due to the nature of their travels they made certain preparations
in preparing to depart for all that would take place
and we find here that in the text of scripture that God gives us
a record of the preparation
for the journey. Notice in verse number two after
Jacob receives word from God he hears
very distinctly what God says. There's no
difficulty on interpreting verse number one of Genesis thirty-five
arise
go up to Bethel
and dwell there
and pretty straightforward instruction that God gives
and we find that he tells him to make there an altar unto God
and he says that appeared unto thee when thou fled us from the face of Esau thy
brother
then notice what Jacob does as we note the preparation in verses two
three and four
the Bible says in verse number two
then Jacob said unto his household
and to all that were with him
put away the strange gods that are among you
and be clean and change your garments. As we think about the preparation for the
journey
I would note first of all what Jacob requested. We see this in verse number two
the request is made
it's very interesting that Jacob says to his household notice first of all what
he says
put away
the strange gods
that are among you
I want you to think about if you would
take and turn back to chapter number thirty-one
and you remember that as they would depart from Paddan Aram after
Jacob received that word from the Lord that he was to return to his
kindred and to his
the land of his fathers we understand that that departure was met with some
adverse circumstances
but the Bible told us in that portion of scripture
that Rachel stole
the idols
the Bible tells us in verse number nineteen and Laban went to shear his sheep
and Rachel had stolen the images
that were her father's
as you look down in verse number thirty-one
the Bible says that Jacob answered and said to Laban because I was afraid for I
said peradventure thou wouldest take by force
thy daughters from me verse thirty-two with whomsoever
thou findest thy gods
let him not live
it seems pretty obvious from that statement
that Jacob had no knowledge that Rachel had stolen the idols
he loved Rachel no doubt in my mind that if he would have known
that Rachel had those idols he would not have said this to Laban
but we find that he says to Laban with whomsoever thou findest thy gods let him
not live before our brethren discern thou
what is thine with me and take it to thee
for Jacob knew not that Rachel had stolen them
and Laban went to Jacob's tent, to Leah's tent, and to the two maidservants' tents
notice it says but he found them not
then went he out of Leah's tent notice it says and entered into Rachel's tent
she knew what was in her tent
she was well aware
she devises a story, a plan
in order to keep hidden from Laban what she had stolen
by the way you might be able to hide something from someone else but you
can't hide anything from God
God's telling us about what took place
in his record the Bible
it says now Rachel had taken the images and put them in the camel's furniture
and sat upon them
and Laban searched all the tent but found them not she said to her father
let it not displease my Lord
that I cannot rise up before thee for the custom of women is upon me
and he searched but found not
the images
they were there he just didn't find them
now we come to chapter thirty five
we read about these
strange gods that are among you
it seems pretty obvious to me that
the idols that were taken
are now at some point after Laban had searched and after the
the journey that had taken place and I've kind of outlined by way of introduction
the places in which Jacob and his family have been
up to this point in Genesis thirty five
after departing from Paddan Aram and
at some point perhaps those idols made their way out into the family and
perhaps also with the people of the land that there was some interaction
with that they picked up some idols some false gods
this is tragic
but first order of business in preparing for this journey
to go to Bethel was Jacob saying put away the strange gods
that are among you
if I could criticize Jacob for just a moment
I would say that he should have told them to put the strange gods away
before God ever gave him instruction to go to Bethel
it's unfortunate that as he would
take the strange gods that were provided
that he did not destroy them
we'll note that in just a moment
but I find that it's commendable as much as I would criticize him for not doing
it prior it's commendable that in preparation for going to Bethel
he recognizes there's some things that need to happen
the first
order of business is we need to get rid of these strange gods. We need to get rid of
these idols. And we understand that today and we think about the images that were there
that were stolen by Rachel, as it's said in Genesis chapter 31, and we can think of
lots of different examples of idols. But we find that the sin of idolatry is so common
within the Old Testament and we often see this snare, if you will, with the children
of Israel. But, you know, the Bible tells in the New Testament, it says this, keep yourselves
from idols. As John is writing in the epistle of John, he says, keep thyself from idols
in 1 John 5. And the reality is that we understand this evening that in the book of Colossians
God tells us this, that in all things the Lord Jesus Christ is to have the preeminence.
An idol doesn't have to be some little image that someone burns incense to or bows down
to. That's what our mind thinks of. That's what comes into our mind's eye when we think
about an image or an idol. But the reality is an idol is anything that takes God's place.
An idol can be a workplace. How many have made money in idol? Position? Power? Sports?
Oh, there's many idols today. We don't like so much talking about idols. We like to think
about maybe some Eastern religions and the way that they have idols and criticizing, but
the reality is that even here in the United States there are plenty that have idols. And
Jacob says before we go to Bethel, the first thing we need to do in preparation is we need
to put away the strange gods that are among you. I want you to notice that he also made
this request in verse number 2. The Bible says this, and be clean and change your garments.
Isn't that interesting? You understand that here as we're looking in the book of Genesis,
this is before the law, this is before all of the instruction that we read in the book
of Leviticus and all of those things with regard to approaching God and worshipping
God and all of the particulars with regard to how you would approach God and the sacrifices
and all of those things. And we find that Jacob says not only do we need to put away
the strange gods that are among you, but he says be clean and change your garments. Why
is it that he would make reference to being clean and changing their garments? Well here's
why. You know what Bethel is? It's the house of God. That's what it means. That's what
the word Bethel means. And basically what Jacob is saying as we look at verse number
2 is we're going to the house of God and we need to get rid of some idols and you need
to get clean and you need to change your garments. So often today people would criticize
and say that you're pharisaical and legalistic and so on and so forth if you have any measure
of standards. And the reality is that you can come just as you are. No one would ever
turn your way. Isn't that an amazing thing that we would understand that we're coming
into the presence of God? We're going to worship God. And as I'm coming to a holy place where
I preached this morning on Moses there in the book of Exodus in the third chapter, that
ground was not holy ground because Moses was there. It was not holy ground because it was
a bush that was burning. It was holy ground because God's presence was there. We come
to worship God. Jacob says you need to get rid of those idols and you need to get cleaned
up and you need to change your garments. That's powerful because we're going to the house
of God. See, notice as we look here at this request we then see that he makes, he reveals
some truth to his family. I'm not sure how much of this he had revealed to them prior
to this particular record but we find that as he tells them what to do in this preparation,
he makes this request, that then he reveals some truth in verse number three. The Bible
says, and let us arise and go up to Bethel and I will make there an altar unto God. What's
the purpose of making the altar? It's to worship God. That's why we're going there. Why do
we go to church? I understand that this isn't the church here in Genesis chapter 35 but
I understand this evening that we assemble together. The church is a called out assembly.
It's a body of believers and we come for the purpose of worship. Church isn't a club. Amen?
It's not a club. I understand. I'm thankful that we're a family and I'm thankful that
we can have fellowship one with another but the reality is that church is to worship God,
to have an encounter with God Almighty. When I come to church, I want to come to church
to hear from God. I want to come to church so that God would step on my toes and change
me and help me to be conformed to the image of his dear son. I want to come to worship
him, to bless his holy name because he's wonderful and he's worthy of our praise. That's why
we come to church, to worship. You come to church and say, man, I got to see so and so.
I got to have fellowship with so and so. We did this. We did that. But if you didn't worship,
you missed the whole purpose. You missed the whole purpose. And we find here that he reveals
that here's where we're going but notice what he says. He says, and I will make there an
altar unto God. Notice what he says, who answered me in the day of my distress. Jacob did not
forget that God heard him and that God answered him. And he says that God answered me in the
day of my distress. And I'm looking at this portion and I'm thinking about how Jacob is
revealing this truth to his family. Again, I'm not sure had he revealed this earlier
and how much he had revealed to his family. But he says now as they're preparing to go
to Bethel, he says, listen, I'm going to make a request. You need to prepare for getting
to the house of God, for worshiping God. But I want you to know that this God that we're
going to worship, my God that we're going to worship, you see he's not like those idols.
What the Bible says about idols, you can read in the Psalms, you can read in other portions
of Scripture, that they're made by man's hands. They have ears but they hear not. That's what
the Bible says. You think about the situation with Elijah there on Mount Carmel. He says,
you can call out to your gods, the God that answers my fire, let him be the true God.
Those worshipers of Baal, they cried out and they cried out and they cut themselves and
they did all sorts of things but Baal never answered. Why? Because Baal is a false god.
And here we have Jacob that says, he answered me in the day of my distress. Not only that,
he says, and was with me in the way which I went. God's presence is made known at the
end of verse number 3. Jacob says, not only did he answer me, but he was with me. Aren't
you thankful for God's presence? What a joy to think about how Jacob is revealing this
truth. See, the reality is that as we look at Genesis chapter 35, see Jacob has already
been to Bethel before. And now he's returning to Bethel. He knew what it was to be in Bethel.
He knew what happened in that place. If you look at Genesis 28, we don't have the time
this evening but in verses 10-22 and you see the time when he's in Bethel and you look
at what's taking place there and I'll just read, I'll reference one verse of scripture.
The Bible says this, that Jacob awaked out of that dream that he had and he said this
in verse number 16, surely the Lord is in this place and I knew it not. Listen, what
happened in Bethel, Jacob was never going to forget. And now he's going back to Bethel.
And as he's returning back to Bethel, he's telling his family, hey listen, we need to
prepare for worship. We need to get rid of these idols. We need to get cleaned up. We
need to change our garments because we're going to worship and the God that we're going
to worship, he answered me. He heard me when I prayed and he answered me and he was with
me. Wow, precious. We find the response in verse number 4. By the way, I'm thankful they
responded the way that they did. It says in verse number 4, and they gave unto Jacob all
the strange gods which were in their hand and all their earrings which were in their
ears and Jacob hid them under the oak which was by Shechem. He should have destroyed them.
You know what they did in Ephesus? They took all those books and they burned them. You
know, some of the kings of Israel, they took, as you would have a bad, excuse me, the kings
of Judah, not of Israel because there's no good kings in Israel after the divided kingdom.
But after the divided kingdom, you had some good kings in Judah. You'd have a good king
that would rise up and he'd clean out the house of the Lord from all the idols and sometimes
they'd just kind of put them to the side. And then there'd rise another wicked king
and they'd take all those idols and put them back into the house of God. But there's times
in which they burned them and they caused them to be made into dust and got rid of them.
Listen, it doesn't do any good to keep an idol around. Destroy it, get rid of it, burn
it. But we find that they respond to the request that Jacob makes in verse 2. They respond
in obedience.
in verse number four.
So now they're ready for the journey.
They're ready to depart.
And we find that it begins verse number five
and says, and they journeyed.
The preparation phase was complete.
You take a trip, you make all the preparation,
and then at some point you depart.
There's a departure time.
We find that the preparation for the journey is completed.
If you're taking notes, number two,
I want you to see the protection for the journey,
the protection for the journey.
Notice in just in verse number five,
we see this, the Bible says this, and they journeyed.
And notice what it says, and the terror of God
was upon the cities that were round about them,
and they did not pursue after the sons of Jacob.
Just a single verse of scripture,
but it reveals to us the protection of Almighty God.
I'm so thankful.
As you think about Jacob,
he's a man that's often concerned about things.
He's a fearful man.
He's constantly operating and functioning
and making decisions based upon fear.
In fact, in Genesis chapter 34 and verse number 30,
remember after the unfortunate circumstances there
of what happened in Shechem,
the Bible says this in verse 30 of Genesis 34.
And Jacob said to Simeon and Levi,
you have troubled me to make me to stink
among the inhabitants of the land,
among the Canaanites and the Perizzites,
and I being few in number.
Now, keep that in mind.
It says, and I being few in number,
they shall gather themselves together against me
and slay me, and I shall be destroyed, I and my house.
The children of Israel at this particular time,
it's not the million that leave,
the large quantity that leave the exodus,
just a small group of people.
Jacob says that we're few in number,
but we find here that the Bible says
that the terror of God was upon the cities
that were round about them.
This is God's divine protection.
Jacob, because of what he recognized
about the power of the people groups there
in the land that he was dwelling in and all that took,
he felt like he was vulnerable.
He felt like there was a lack of defense
that they had themselves,
but the reality is that God can provide divine protection.
We often speak about,
and I mentioned even on Wednesday evening,
that the Bible says that the horse is prepared
for the day of battle, but safety is of the Lord.
Listen, I believe in taking the preventative measures
necessary to provide for safety and what have you,
and I believe in making good decisions,
but ultimately, safety is of the Lord.
We find here that the Bible says
that the terror of God was upon the cities
that were round about them.
Isn't that amazing how God worked?
So much so that the Bible says they did not pursue
after the sons of Jacob.
Though they were departing
and though they were few in number
and though maybe from a human perspective
they were vulnerable to attack,
we find that God moved and God worked.
God is able.
And I rejoice in this single verse of Scripture
in Genesis 35 because it helps us to understand
and to rest in the fact that our God is able to protect us.
Sometimes we can go through such great measures,
trying so many things, but fail even to just pray
and ask God.
Think about the truth of praying a hedge
of protection upon someone.
We have not had the opportunity recently
in recent time to sing the song,
but I think Holly and the girls sang the song many times,
a wall of prayer, a wall of prayer.
You think about how God can provide
that protection that we need.
Listen, you need protection.
I need protection.
The people in the land there,
there was a very possible scenario
that they would be attacked given all of the circumstances,
but God protected.
Listen, we live in a crazy world.
We really do.
Craziness.
People that are taking advantage of the elderly.
Videos all of the time that you see on the news nowadays
of some elderly individual leaving a place of business
and being knocked in the head from behind and so on.
It's nonsense.
There was a time in America
where young people respected the elderly.
They'd never think, it never crossed their mind
to do something like that.
We live in a world that's lost its mind,
but God is able to protect us.
We need to pray for God's protection daily.
We see how God works.
I've read of missionary stories,
accounts that missionaries have given from the field
of people that set out to destroy the missionariness family
to come and burn down their house and kill them.
When they arrive, they said we could do nothing
because there were armed men all around your property.
Missionaries say, what are you talking about, armed men?
I believe they're angels.
Sometimes you have the opportunity to hear
the other end of the account where there was someone
that God awakened in the middle of the night
to pray for a specific missionary.
Listen, if God ever prompts you to pray for a missionary,
man, you ought to pray for that missionary.
So I don't know what I'm praying for.
God knows why.
He's praying God put a hedge of protection about them.
God take care of them, meet their needs,
whatever the situation is.
God is able, God is able.
We see the preparation for the journey.
We see the protection for the journey,
but I want you to see finally this evening
the purpose for the journey, the purpose for the journey.
When God calls and gives direction,
you can rest assured that he has a purpose in it.
The purpose is revealed to us in the text of scripture.
It wasn't just that God thought,
well, Jacob, you've been there long enough,
it's time to move to another place,
and so let me get, no, there's a purpose.
We find that our God always moves with purpose.
He always gives his children direction
on purpose and with purpose.
As we had the opportunity last year,
Holly and I for a couple of weeks to be there in Israel,
it was amazing to me to stand in the places
where we stood and to have the opportunities
and to rehearse in my mind the biblical accounts
that I knew that took place in these particular areas
that we stood and to have it all come together
and say, that's why Jesus did that here.
I get the purpose now.
I could see it, I could understand it.
And this evening, as we look at this portion of scripture,
we find that God reveals to us the purpose.
We notice already in verse number one
that he says, go to Bethel and dwell there,
and he says, and make there an altar unto God.
So notice with me in verse number six,
the Bible says, so Jacob came to Luz,
which is in the land of Canaan, that is Bethel.
He and all the people that were with him,
and he built there an altar.
He obeyed what God told him to do.
God said, go to Bethel, dwell there, and build an altar.
And the Bible tells us in verse six that they arrived,
they had safe traveling mercies,
they had protection along the way,
and they get to the place, they reach their destination,
and as they reach their destination,
we find that he builds there an altar.
It's exactly what God told him to do.
The Bible says that he called it, notice,
he called the place El, Bethel,
because there God appeared unto him
when he fled from the face of his brother.
Now, I'm not sure if you've ever visited a place
that something significant took place in your life
at that location.
I mean, it's a location where there was something
that was just life-altering type of an event
that took place.
That's what happened at Bethel the first time.
And now Jacob is back in that place.
Can you imagine with me the memories
that would flood his mind of that time
that he was there in Bethel?
It had been a couple of decades since he's been there,
and we think about that time that has transpired
between the first time it was at Bethel
and now the second time,
perhaps there's some changes in the landscape,
perhaps there's some things that have shifted
and some things that are different,
but I think about Jacob being in that place,
and I think about maybe him thinking about
where he pillowed his head when he had that dream
and where he poured out that offering
and all that took place,
and we find that he's now back in Bethel,
and he put that altar, and he called it El Bethel,
and it says, because there God appeared unto him
when he fled from the face of his brother.
God gives us in verse number eight
the record of the death of Deborah, Rebekah's nurse.
It says that Deborah, Rebekah's nurse,
died and was buried beneath Bethel under an oak.
The name of it is called Alan Bakuth.
But notice as the dialogue continues back
to the situation of Jacob and the family there in Bethel,
it says in verse number nine.
And God appeared unto Jacob again when he came out of Paddan Aram and blessed him.
So we know, as we begin to put all of this together this evening, we know that God appeared
to Jacob at Bethel before he went to Paddan Aram.
We read that.
We referenced it already in Genesis chapter 28, and we know that Jacob had that encounter
with God, but now the Bible specifically says that God appeared unto Jacob again when he
came out of Paddan Aram and blessed him.
And so we find that God is appearing to him, so we look at the purpose of the journey.
He built that altar.
What's the purpose?
Worship.
Singularly stated, the purpose is worship.
We find that as he is there and he's built this altar and there's worship that is taking
place and God then appears, and notice it says at the end of verse number 9, and blessed
him.
Think about the blessings of God.
In verse number 10 it says, and God said unto him, Thy name is Jacob.
Thy name shall not be called anymore Jacob, but Israel shall be thy name.
And he called his name Israel.
That's a reference back to Genesis chapter 32, the night that he wrestled with the angel
of the Lord, and we read and studied that weeks ago, and we find that there's a confirmation
here with regard to not only the name change, but as we continue to move forward to the
Abrahamic covenant.
Notice in verse number 11, and God said unto him, I am God Almighty.
Be fruitful and multiply.
A nation and a company of nations shall be of thee, and kings shall come out of thy loins
in the land which I gave Abraham and Isaac.
To thee I will give it, and to thy seed after thee will I give the land.
Think about the confirmation that God gives to Jacob, the blessing that is received.
You note with me this confirmation of the Abrahamic covenant, and he says to him here
in this portion of scripture, he says in verse 11, I am God Almighty.
You know, that name for God is El Shaddai, and the first time God ever used that name
in the book of Genesis is when he's speaking to Abraham in Genesis chapter 17 in verse
number 1.
And as God appears to Abraham in that particular text of scripture, he says, I am the Almighty
God.
And after God revealed himself to Abram as being the Almighty God, he would then shortly
thereafter ask Abraham, this question, is anything too hard for the Lord?
No, nothing's too hard for God.
And it's interesting to me that as we look at this confirmation of the Abrahamic covenant,
that the seed is in view in verse number 11, the land is in view in verse number 12, and
we find that the Bible tells us that God went up from him in the place where he talked with
him.
And notice, and Jacob set up a pillar in the place where he talked with him, even a pillar
of stone, and he poured a drink offering thereon, and he poured oil thereon, and Jacob called
the name of the place where God spake with him, Bethel.
I want you to think about the worship.
As we look at this portion of scripture, and we think of all that's taken place in the
life of Jacob, we see in verse number, there at the end there in verse number 14, this
drink offering again.
This is prior to the book of Leviticus and all of the requirements with regard to offerings
and so on and so forth, but we find that Jacob, he pours out this oil there, this drink offering,
again, understanding worship.
God is worthy of our worship.
He is worthy of our worship.
Begin to think about God being worthy of our worship and looking at what's taking place
here in Genesis chapter 35, I'm reminded of just the amazing aspect of what takes place
in Jacob's life.
In Genesis 28, he's at Bethel, and now again in Genesis chapter 35, he's at Bethel.
There's a lot of things that happened in between, a lot of circumstances that took place in
his life and difficulties and troubles and all sorts of things that take place, but we
find in Genesis 28, now here in Genesis 35, that he's at Bethel and he's worshiping God.
He's worshiping God.
We find that God alone is worthy of our worship.
So we're going to think about Bethel and being the name Bethel, meaning the house of God.
We're going to think about how we worship God.
The Bible says in John chapter 4 that they that worship Him must worship Him in spirit
and in truth.
All that is called worship today is not really worship.
You understand that, right?
All that is called worship today is not really worship because it must align with God's Word.
See, some people have the idea that I can approach God any way I want.
You're wrong.
There's only one way to approach God and it's the way that He said.
God is God and He's the one that has determined how mankind would approach Him.
I'm thankful that He took the first step and He provided the sacrifice because man must
come by the way of the cross.
We sing the song.
You've got to come by the way of the cross.
There's no other way.
If we're going to worship God, we must worship Him in spirit and in truth.
We must recognize that He is a thrice holy God and as we enter His presence, as we look
at the pages of Scripture and we observe those that worship God, that have an encounter with
God, they're always broken.
There's a sense of soberness amongst the people as they enter into the presence of God.
Worship doesn't...today it's almost like these people have the idea that worship requires
dimming lights and doing all sorts of crazy things.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
They that worship God must worship Him in spirit and in truth.
And we must approach God on His terms.
Jacob worships God.
There was preparation.
I've referenced throughout the message this evening about the journey.
I finished with the purpose for the journey and I want to focus our attention as we close
this evening to this idea of worship and understanding that there was preparation for worship.
The whole purpose of the journey was to go to a place that's called the house of God
and to set up an altar to worship God.
That was the whole purpose.
When I think about coming to and looking at New Testament biblical Christianity, looking
in 2023 and we have a service schedule, we call it a morning worship service, an evening
worship service, I wonder this evening how much preparation takes place in our lives
to worship God.
Yesterday, Tim and I prayed right here after the men's prayer breakfast and Tim and I both
prayed that we would have prepared hearts for the services today.
Tim prayed first.
I was impressed to hear a young man pray that way.
I was.
I hope I'm not embarrassing you.
I was impressed by it because, you know, on Saturday evenings there should take a time
where we kind of wind down a little bit, begin to focus our minds on tomorrow's the day,
the Lord's day.
And I want to be ready to worship God.
I want to be ready to worship God.
We do our best.
We were much better at it when we were younger and had younger kids.
But Saturday evenings we'd lock it down like after 6 o'clock.
Why?
I don't want to be dragging my kids tired into church because it's the Lord's day.
There was some
We talked about the word of preparation, to prepare.
It's in advance, right?
That's what the word means.
It's the understanding.
There's preparation.
And how am I preparing?
See, when I'm preparing to worship, it begins, I would say, for us today as New Testament
believers on Saturday evening.
I don't want to drag in the church on Sunday morning, tired, and I understand you got kids
and something happens and there's whatever, but I want to protect my calendar.
I want to protect my schedule.
I don't want to be out until 11, 12, 1 o'clock on Saturday evening and then be like, yeah,
you know, I think I'm going to skip this and maybe I'll just
No, no.
I want to worship.
This is worthy of our worship.
And when I come to the house of God, I want to be ready to worship.
Some of that preparation, get clean.
Take a shower, sure, but get clean, get a clean heart.
God, I want to enter your presence.
I want to worship you in spirit and in truth.
I want you to be pleased with my sacrifice, with my offering that when we
We come to the house of, you know, giving is part of worship.
We prepare our hearts to give unto the Lord.
And there's all this preparation, and we see it in the beginning of Genesis 35.
And I hope that as we look at this text of Scripture that we see that worship takes place.
But oh, how important that preparation is.
Oh, how important that preparation is.
I trust that God would help us in 2023 to see God for who He is, to understand that
He is worthy of our worship, and that we would be prepared when we enter into the house of
God to meet with God and to worship God.
I hope that when you drive here on Sunday morning, when you drive here on Sunday night,
you have this heart of expectation, anticipation, we're gonna meet with God, we're gonna meet
with God.
And I want God to challenge me and speak to me and meet with me, that preparation.
Why do we pray before our services the way that we do?
Well, the Bible says the house of God is to be a house of prayer.
That time of prayer, those couple of minutes of corporate prayer, has been implemented
so that we would pray that God would meet with us.
It's not to pray for some sick relative.
Now, I'm not criticizing you if you've done that.
What I'm saying is that that is specific prayer time for God meet with us.
God work in my life first, and then in the lives of those that are gathered.
We have come to worship.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for a place called Bethel, the house of God.
I believe this evening that this place was special to Jacob.
God, as we look at this Old Testament account of this man and his family as they journeyed,
God, I pray that you'd help us in our own lives, that we would worship you in spirit
and in truth.
God, we'd understand that you're a holy God.
You're worthy of our worship.
I hope this evening that we would prepare to worship you.
We'd make the decisions necessary, maybe even difficult decisions, in that process of preparation,
so that we would be ready to worship.
I pray that you'd move and work in these moments of invitation as only you can.
I pray, God, that decisions would be made that would please me.
We'll thank you for all that you'll do, for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand?