Jesus saves and a world needs to hear that truth.
Amen.
And he has called us and given us the great privilege
and responsibility of being his representative.
Second Chronicles chapter 28,
Second Chronicles chapter number 28 this morning.
And we of course just finished our missions conference
and what a wonderful conference it was.
And as I was experiencing the conference,
hearing the preaching from God's word
and being challenged in my own life
and being encouraged by the missionaries that were here,
being encouraged by many that I had conversation with
from within our congregation and discussions
and testimonies about how God was moving and working
and what a blessing.
I was encouraged and the Lord just kept bringing me back
to this portion of scripture
in Second Chronicles chapter number 28.
And I look at this passage of scripture this morning
and I am thankful.
I'll say right at the beginning of the message this morning,
I'm thankful that God uses people
and that God uses individuals.
Sometimes we might think,
well, there's really nothing I can do.
I'm just little old me and I just can't make a difference.
No, as a child of God, you have Christ in you,
the hope of glory and God will use you for his honor
and for his glory to make a difference
in the place where he has you.
If it were just you, if it were just me,
that'd be a different story.
But after salvation, the Holy Spirit of God
and dwells in Christ in us,
man, it's a whole different situation.
And I am thankful that God uses individuals.
The fact of the matter is that you could read
through the scriptures and you could look
at a whole host of examples in God's word
where God used individuals.
We could not only look to biblical history
and the canon of scripture,
but we could look at modern history.
We could look at the volumes of history
that have been written about church history
and Christian history.
And you can read of God using individuals,
some people that just desired that God would use them.
They recognize that they were a channel
and that God could use them to bring honor and glory
to the Lord alone.
And what a blessing to consider this morning
that he wants to use us, that he would use us.
And this morning, as we look at this portion of scripture
in 2 Chronicles chapter number 28,
the portion of scripture that we're going to examine
provides with us a glimpse into the life of a prophet
by the name of Oded.
I will have mentioned to you that this is a prophet
of the Lord, excuse me,
that we really know very little about.
His name means restorer.
That's what his name means, restorer.
And I think about this text of scripture,
and it's interesting to me how this man, Oded,
comes on the scene of scripture
during the reign of Ahaz in Judah.
We, of course, can look at a number of folks.
One of the names of scripture that's very familiar to us
is a prophet by the name of Elijah.
And it's very interesting
if you were to read 1 Kings chapter 17,
how Elijah just, he's on the scene.
And here's this man, Elijah, a prophet of the Lord
that stands before the king of Israel
and delivers a message of judgment.
And I mean, he just appears on the pages of scripture
in 1 Kings 17 and verse number one.
Well, here, when we think about this man, Oded,
there is another man by the name of Oded in the scriptures.
It's a different man than what we're reading here.
But we read this man, Oded,
and the Bible tells us about this man
that is a prophet of the Lord.
And he comes on the pages of scripture
during the reign of Ahaz in Judah.
Now, understand with me
that this is well after the divided kingdom.
Just to give you the setting, if I can, just for a moment,
we'll look at the first eight verses by way of introduction
and really just see what's going on
historically at this particular time.
But understand that after the kingdom divided,
of course, the nation of Israel, 12 tribes,
the first king, Saul, followed by David,
followed by Solomon.
And then after the reign of Solomon,
by the way, those reigns were about 120 years,
about 100 years or so.
And we find that then comes after the reign of Solomon,
you have the divided kingdom.
From that point forward,
you'll read throughout the scriptures,
you'll read of Israel and you'll read of Judah.
Israel is the tribes, the nation of the North,
the 10 tribes, the Northern kingdom.
And Judah is the Southern kingdom, two tribes of the South.
I would say of the nation of Israel, the Northern kingdom,
that after the division, after the reign of Solomon,
that it was a slippery slope downward the whole way.
There were really no good kings in Israel.
They all were wicked and evil and did terrible things.
On the contrast, when you look at the nation of Judah,
you will find in Judah's history
that there were periods of time when they had good kings.
They had kings that feared the Lord,
that walked in the ways of the Lord,
that sought to do what God had commanded them to do.
And when you read about those good kings,
you'll see periods of time in Judah's history
where they experienced revival.
And amazing things happen.
When we begin to think about some of the good kings,
you begin to think about Jehoshaphat,
you think of Hezekiah, you think of Josiah.
Ahaz is not one of them.
He's not a good king.
He's a wicked man, he's a wicked king,
and he's king of Judah.
See, just as they had some good kings,
they had quite a few bad kings,
just like Israel, the northern kingdom, had.
And we find that at this particular time
in Israel's history that Judah has Ahaz
reigning as their king,
but up in Israel, the northern kingdom,
a fellow by the name of Pekah is reigning as king.
He also is a wicked man.
We see that Pekah is the king that's reigning
at the northern kingdom.
Ahaz is reigning in Judah, the southern kingdom.
But there are two other people groups
that are important for us to understand
in the background of this particular text of scripture,
and that is a man by the name of Rezin.
And Rezin is the king of Syria.
And then you also have Tiglath-Pilneser,
who is the king of Assyria.
And so you have the Syrians and you have the Assyrians.
Eventually, the Assyrians obviously take and capture
Assyria, and then eventually they take the northern kingdom.
In fact, during the reign of Pekah,
during the same period of time,
is when the Assyrian captivity began.
It's not in its full stage,
but it's when the Assyrian captivity began
of the northern kingdom.
We'll understand from our Bible history
and studying through the scriptures
that Israel was taken captive, the northern kingdom,
by Assyria, whereas the southern kingdom, Judah,
was taken captive by the Babylonians.
And as we look at this portion of scripture,
it's important for us to understand
some of those players in history, if you will.
Israel's king, Judah's king,
Syria and Assyria's rulers or kings.
And we find that as we come to this portion of scripture,
again, the setting is provided to us
in verses one through eight,
and Ahas is a wicked king.
Notice what the Bible tells us about this man,
and understand with me this morning
that God makes it very clear
that he would bring judgment because of the wickedness.
We understand this morning, the Bible says,
that God is a righteous God and he loves righteousness.
We understand that the Bible says,
righteousness exalteth a nation,
but sin is a reproach to any people.
And we find that the sin of Ahas and the people of Judah
would bring the distinct hand of judgment upon them.
In verse number one, the Bible says,
Ahas was 20 years old when he began to reign,
and he reigned 16 years in Jerusalem,
but he did not that which was right
in the sight of the Lord, like David his father.
For he walked in the ways of the kings of Israel
and made also, notice the first indictment against him
in verse number two, he made molten images for Balaam.
We understand that their sin with Israel and Judah
very consistently throughout the scriptures,
a sin of idolatry.
And we understand that God said
during the giving of the 10 commandments,
thou shalt have no other God before me.
Thou shalt make no graven images.
And we find that the Bible tells us
that this man Ahas in his reign of Judah,
that he made also molten images for Balaam.
Notice the word in verse number three,
it says, moreover, in addition to this,
and it begins to list the indictment against Ahas
in the nation of Judah,
I have written in the margin of my Bible,
the slippery slope of sin.
Listen, sin is dangerous.
Hebrew says it this way with regard to sin,
the deceitfulness of sin.
And we find that as we look at these first eight verses
here and really the first six verses
that gives us the indictment against Ahas
in the nation of Judah,
you see the slippery slope of sin,
and it's so dangerous.
Listen, sin is not something to mess with.
Sin is not something to play with.
We need to make sure that in our lives
that we're seeking to walk godly, holy lives,
pleasing unto our Lord,
that we would be unspotted from the world.
I'm thankful that the Bible tells us that,
listen, there's not gonna be a place of sinless perfection
in our lives until we get to glory,
but we should be sinning less.
And the Bible says that when we sin,
that we have an advocate with the Father,
Jesus Christ, the righteous.
We find here that the Bible says,
moreover, in addition to making these molten images
for Balaam,
Notice it says that he burnt incense in the valley of the sun of Hinnom.
Notice this. This is mind-blowing to me.
And burnt his children in the fire.
Wow.
It says, after the abominations of the heathen, whom the Lord had cast out before the children of Israel,
he sacrificed also and burnt incense in the high places and on the hills and under every green tree.
Notice the last statement of verse number 6. I'll come back to verse 5 in just a moment.
But the very last statement of verse number 6 says this,
Because they had forsaken the Lord God of their fathers.
Wow. What an indictment.
And we find that this is the setting.
This is the backdrop for this man Oded that we're going to really study this morning
and look at his life and look at his courage.
And we find that Ahaz, this wicked king of Judah, is leading Judah into all of this wickedness,
this sin that is prevailing, and we find that the Bible tells us that judgment would come.
Notice, if you will, in verse number 5, the Bible says,
The Lord his God delivered him into the hand of the king of Syria.
That's Rezin. I mentioned some of these other people in the by way of introduction that I wanted us to be familiar with,
and that is Rezin.
And the Bible says,
And they smote him and carried away a great multitude of them captives.
God does not tell us the exact number that are taken captive by the Syrians,
but we see here in the text of Scripture that that's where the judgment of the Lord begins.
And then notice it says,
And brought them to Damascus, and he also was delivered into the hand of the king of Israel,
who smote him with a great slaughter.
Now that's Pekah, king of Israel.
And the Bible says in verse number 6,
For Pekah the son of Amalia slew in Judah,
notice what this says,
and 120,000 in one day, which were all valiant men.
Why? Because they had forsaken the Lord God of their fathers.
So Rezin, king of Syria, has taken a host of people captive back to Syria, to Damascus.
We find that then Pekah comes in,
and Pekah in one day, 120,000 valiant men are killed.
In verse number 7, it begins to highlight to us some of the key people, if you will, that were slain.
It says,
And Zichri, a mighty man of Ephraim, slew Maseah, the king's son,
and Azraqam, the governor of the house, and Elkanah, that was next to the king.
Notice in addition to killing these 120,000 people in one day,
now this is Pekah, king of Israel, against Judah, king of Ahaz.
Excuse me, Ahaz, king of Judah.
And we find that the Bible tells us in verse number 8,
And the children of Israel carried away captive of their brethren 200,000,
women, sons, and daughters, and took also away much spoil from them,
and brought the spoil to Samaria.
Samaria is the capital city of the northern kingdom.
Israel is referred to it as.
And we find that according to verse number 6,
120,000 valiant men were slain by Pekah, the king of Israel.
And then in verse number 8, they take 200,000 captive.
That's a large number of people.
The journey that they would take to bring them back to Samaria,
the king of the northern kingdom, Israel,
we find they would take this journey.
And I want you to understand, as we think about the time,
and the culture, and all of those things,
that oftentimes when a people group would conquer another group,
and they would come back to their hometown, to their capital,
as would be the case with this situation,
there's a big fanfare that's taking place.
There's great excitement that's taking place.
Why? You've brought these captives back, but you've also brought the spoils.
And there's a certain setting that we must understand
as we look at these first eight verses of 2 Chronicles 28,
and you see the great wickedness that's taking place.
You see these valiant men that have not only slain,
but now taken captive this large host,
and they bring all of this spoil,
and they're entering into Samaria.
No doubt in my mind there's a measure of fanfare that's taking place.
There's some excitement because the military's returning,
and they're returning triumphantly,
and they're returning not only with captives, but with spoil.
And notice verse number 9.
But a prophet of the Lord was there.
But a prophet of the Lord was there whose name was Oded.
He just comes on the pages of Scripture.
He's a prophet of the Lord, man of God.
I've titled the message you've seen in the bulletin,
The Courage of Oded.
Begin to think about the background that we've read in these eight verses,
and we come to verse number 9, and we see this man
that appears on the pages of Scripture seemingly out of nowhere.
And we see the wickedness,
and we see the power of the nation of Israel,
and we see what's taking place, and then there's this man Oded.
If you're taking notes this morning, I just have two thoughts for you.
The first one is this.
I want you to notice the opportunity.
The opportunity.
You'd say, Pastor, you're going to call it an opportunity that Oded had?
Oh yeah, it was an opportunity.
It was an opportunity that many of us perhaps
would not really look at as being an opportunity.
Because you begin to think of all that's taking place
and all of this great thing, but you find that Oded is there,
and he's just an individual, but he's a prophet of the Lord.
And the Bible tells us, notice in verse number 9,
but a prophet of the Lord was there whose name was Oded,
and he, Oded, he went out before the host
that came to Samaria and said unto them.
Now, I can't even hardly imagine in my mind's eye,
my sanctified imagination, trying to see this scene.
200,000 captive.
120,000 that were slain.
So this is a large contingency of the army of the nation of Israel
that's returning from this battle.
They're returning, they have 200,000 captives with them,
all of the spoil, and then here comes Oded,
and he comes and he stands right in front of them.
Wow.
And he takes and he says, and I believe with boldness,
he said unto them, Behold, because the Lord your God,
the Lord God of your fathers was wroth with Judah,
he hath delivered them into your hand,
and ye have slain them in a rage that reacheth up unto heaven.
See, God was judging Judah because of their wickedness.
But Oded is going to deliver a message to Israel
about their own sin.
And about God's hand of judgment that would come upon them.
Notice as we continue and looking here in verse number 10,
the Bible says, And now ye purpose to keep unto the children of Judah
and Jerusalem for bondmen and bondwomen unto you,
but are there not with you, even with you, sins against the Lord your God?
Listen, Israel, don't think that you're righteous
because God delivered Judah into your hand.
You have sins.
And he says that you intend, notice in verse number 10,
he says that you purpose to keep unto the children of Judah and Jerusalem
for bondmen and bondwomen unto you.
By the way, that was a violation of the law.
It was a violation of the law, a clear violation of the law.
We don't have time to go back to Leviticus 25,
but if you go back there you can read through that chapter
and you can see a number of times in Leviticus 25
where God specifically says that they should not make bondmen of their brethren.
That's exactly what they're going to do.
And notice Oded, he then says, he says this in verse number 11,
Now hear me therefore, can you see this?
Now hear me therefore, and deliver the captives again,
which ye have taken captive of your brethren,
for the fierce wrath of the Lord is upon you.
What does he tell him?
Well, I would say this, he went before the host,
he stands there according to verses 9 through 11,
I said I want you to note the opportunity.
I would say it this way, he sees the opportunity.
Not only did he see it, but he seized it.
And he takes advantage of the opportunity that God gives.
I cannot even begin to understand how much boldness and courage
this must have required on the part of Oded
to go stand before this great host of people and to deliver this message.
But I want you to understand this morning that he spoke to them the word of God.
He spoke to them the message that God had previously delivered
and he's faithful to give that message.
I would say this, that he was obedient to the Lord.
And in his obedience he operated with faith,
with courage, and with boldness.
And he stood before this great host that had just experienced a great victory
and the wickedness that had permeated the land.
I mean not only do you have Israel with all of their wickedness and sin,
but you also have Judah with all their wickedness and sin as we just read.
And then this man of God is going to come.
and deliver this message.
I want you to notice very clearly
that he stands there and not only
does he tell them what they've done wrong,
but he tells them how to correct it.
In verse number 11, he says,
now hear me therefore,
and deliver the captives again
what you have taken of your brethren.
Return them.
This is the course of action
that Oded delivers to these valiant men,
to these that have been successful in battle.
And he says this to them at the end of verse number 11,
for the fierce wrath of the Lord is upon you.
For the fierce wrath of the Lord is upon you.
I want you to notice with me,
as we begin to think about this man, Oded,
and how he just comes on the pages of scripture
and delivers such a clear message.
A message that he stands up and delivers
with faith and courage and boldness.
I believe this morning that we need some individuals
that will stand up for the Lord.
That we will operate by faith,
trusting that God is able to use his people
as they deliver the message of his word.
I would say this, that we need to operate with courage.
I think about Joshua,
and you read the first chapter of the book of Joshua
and how God tells Joshua repeatedly to be courageous.
You think about having courage,
and I would say to you this morning
that courage does not mean the absence of fear.
There's some people that have the idea
that courage means that you have no fear.
It's really not, that's not entirely what courage means.
Courage means that we do what's right no matter what.
There might be some fear,
but you have courage to say I'm gonna do what's right.
I don't know, and I don't want to overstate it this morning,
but when I look at this portion of scripture
and I see Oded standing before this great host,
I think, man, I don't, could I do that?
Could you do that?
I mean, this mighty group of people that are wicked,
that are ungodly, that have just had great victory,
that are bringing all this great number of people captive
in all the spoils, and Oded gets out there,
and listen, there's no stammering and stuttering.
There's no beating around the bush.
He's just straight as an arrow.
Here's the message from God.
And he says in verse number 11, now hear me therefore.
I mean, I can just see this man standing there
with courage and boldness.
God uses this message in this man
to accomplish something amazing.
And that's what we look at in this passage of scripture.
We see the opportunity, but number two,
I want you to notice not only the opportunity,
but I want you to notice the outcome.
Notice the outcome.
Now, the reality is that we have the privilege
of looking at this portion of scripture
of an event that took place thousands of years ago,
and we have the opportunity to be able to read the outcome.
But for you and for me, every day
when God gives us opportunities to stand in his stead,
to stand by faith and to speak with courage and boldness,
we don't always know what the outcome's going to be.
I would submit to you this morning
that Oded did not know what the outcome was going to be.
He just did what was right.
As a prophet of the Lord, he said,
I'm gonna seize this opportunity.
And as we look at the outcome of this text of scripture,
it's recorded to us in verses 12 through 15.
In verses 12 and 13 reveals to us,
it records for us the response of the leaders.
Notice the Bible says this in verse number 12.
Then certain of the heads of the children of Ephraim,
and so these are the leaders,
these heads of the children of Ephraim,
Azariah, the son of Johanan,
Barakiah, the son of Meshelamoth,
and Jehezekiah, the son of Shalom,
and Amasah, the son of Hadlai,
stood up against them that came from the war.
They don't stand up against Oded.
They stand up against those that came.
And notice in verse number 13,
notice what they say to them.
Ye shall not bring in the captives hither.
What gave them that idea, Oded?
That was exactly the message that he delivered to them.
And he says, for whereas,
notice in the remainder of verse number 13,
we have offended against the Lord already.
Ye intend to add more to our sins and to our trespass,
for our trespass is great,
and there is fierce wrath against Israel.
Wow.
The outcome immediately is positive.
Oded delivered this message in boldness and in courage,
and we find that the leaders,
they immediately respond by saying to these
that were coming, no, no, no,
you can't bring them in here.
We've already offended against the Lord.
Now we're going to add more to our sins
and to our trespasses.
And it says this, for there is fierce wrath against Israel.
Again, we find that that's exactly in line with the message
that Oded had delivered to these people.
They heard the man of God stand up
and speak the word of God.
You know, I wonder this morning,
it seems as if there's a lack of a fear of God in our nation.
You think that this morning?
No.
There's a lack of people fearing the Lord.
But I would say this,
it's not only a lack of lost people fearing the Lord,
it's a lack of God's people fearing the Lord.
There are things that believers do.
Talk about this passage of scripture dealing with sin,
outlining the sin of Ahaz here in the nation of Judah.
They begin to think about the sin,
the things that people,
God's people have just gotten comfortable with.
There's no fear of God.
And maybe, just maybe if we'd have a fear of God
and we'd stand up in boldness and proclaim
the truth of God's judgment,
that maybe some other people would begin
to get the fear of God as well.
How many times we see,
listen, God's in control of everything, you believe that?
Listen, I believe that America in my lifetime,
I believe that America has faced the divine judgment of God.
There have been what we often refer to as natural disasters.
I believe that's God's hand of judgment
upon a people that have forsaken the Lord,
upon a people that have turned their back on God.
They try to explain it away, global warming.
It's an easy way to get the attention off
of something spiritual.
I'm not gonna preach a message this morning
on global warming,
but I want you to understand that it's nonsense.
And I want you to understand this morning
that the Bible teaches us if you just go back to Genesis
and read the Noahic Covenant,
it really destroys everything with regard to global warming.
And you understand this morning
that our God is in control of all things.
And the reality is that his hand of judgment
has been upon this people, this land, why?
Because of our sin.
But we find that the New Testament tells us
that judgment must begin where?
At the house of God, the house of God.
Listen, we need to have a healthy fear of God.
And we find here that these wicked people in Israel,
they hear the message of a prophet of God that stands up
and they say, hey, listen,
we need to change course of action here.
You're not bringing those people in here.
No, no, we don't want, we've already sinned
against the Lord.
We've already offended against him.
We don't need to add more sin.
And there's fierce wrath against Israel.
So we see the outcome initially in verses 12 and 13
with the response of the leaders.
But I want you to see the response of the armed men
according to verse number 14.
The Bible says here,
so the armed men left the captives in the spoil.
Now they're going to benefit from the spoil, are they not?
You think about the victor as they come in
and as they begin to enjoy the victory
and all of the fanfare and all that takes place
and they are held in some kind of prestigious position
because of what they were able to accomplish
and not only the captives that they brought back,
but also all of that great spoil.
And the Bible says that these armed men,
they left the captives and the spoil
before the princes and all the congregation.
Just leave it there.
Just leave it.
I believe as you look at verse number 14,
again, not to embellish the text of scripture
or what's taking place, this particular account,
but it says that in verse number 14
that they left it before the princes,
and all the congregation.
Oded didn't have a private meeting and Stanton,
no, no, he was just out there
with the whole group of people that came
and he just spoke the word of God
with courage and boldness.
God used him.
I want you to notice with me
the significance of verse number 15.
in our text of scripture.
It's in this verse of scripture
that we read of the release and the return of the captives.
In fact, the Bible tells us it's amazing
how this all takes place.
The Bible says in verse number 15,
the men which were expressed by name rose up
and took the captives and with the spoil
clothed all that were naked among them
and arrayed them and shot them
and gave them to eat and to drink
and anointed them and carried all the feeble of them
upon asses and brought them to Jericho,
the city of palm trees, to their brethren.
Then they returned to Samaria.
That's amazing to me, verse number 15.
They didn't just say at the gate of Samaria,
okay, we've changed our mind because of what this guy said.
We're not gonna bring you in here.
You guys can just go back.
It's not what they did.
The Bible tells us in verse number 15
that they took all those captives
and those that were naked among them,
they clothed them with that spoil that they had taken
and they arrayed them, they shot them,
they gave them to eat and to drink.
I mean, they're taking care of these people.
What a great contrast to how they were originally coming
to the gate of Samaria.
And then the Bible tells us,
notice it says that they anointed them
and carried all the feeble of them upon asses
and brought them to Jericho.
So these people then returned the captives back to Jericho.
They take the journey, the number of miles that it is,
the treacherous terrain and all of the Judean wilderness,
and they take these people back to Jericho.
The Bible identifies it being the city of palm trees.
And if you've ever been to Jericho,
you understand why it's called that.
You're in the middle of nowhere, the Judean wilderness,
you come over the horizon,
all of a sudden you see all these trees,
and it's amazing the sight that you'd see,
and it's referred to even here as the city of palm trees.
It says, to their brethren, then they returned to Samaria.
They returned to Samaria, who's they?
It's those people that are from Israel
that had come and slain and taken captive.
And now they return these and they go back.
I would submit to you this morning,
what a passage of scripture.
I would say to you this morning that 200,000 people,
that's a lot of people,
200,000 people were directly impacted
because of the obedience of one man, Oded.
One man, an individual.
An individual that said,
in the face of all that he was facing,
this great host of people and all of the wickedness,
he said, I'm gonna obey God.
I'm just gonna obey God.
And he stands up with boldness and with courage,
and he delivers a message,
and because of his obedience,
200,000 people are returned.
How many of those people may have had families
that were still back in Judah?
I have no idea.
I have no idea what those 200,000 people did
after they got back to Jericho.
But I would submit to you this morning
that those 200,000 people would have been thankful
that Oded stood up and delivered a message.
Don't you think?
Can you imagine if you were part of that captive group?
You knew what was taking place when you were traveling
from your hometown up to Samaria.
You understood what your future would look like
as being a captive.
You understood several things with regard to being
taken away from your home.
And then things change.
Perhaps you were close enough
within the sound of the voice of Oded.
You heard him say what he said.
Maybe you say, who's that speaking?
I don't know who that is.
But man, he's speaking with boldness.
He's a prophet of the Lord.
He's speaking the word of God.
And God is working through him.
And God worked through him in such a way
that those people, those heads of the children of Ephraim,
those armed men,
we're not gonna mess with Oded.
We're gonna do what he said.
We're gonna send these people back.
It's amazing to me.
The difference that one man made.
Sometimes in our lives we think,
well, can I really make a difference?
What could God really do with me?
I don't, and we start offering excuses kind of like Moses.
I'm thankful.
And I believe that these 200,000 are thankful that Oded
didn't make an excuse.
That Oded said, I'm just an individual,
but I serve a mighty God.
I'm just an individual, but God can use me.
I'm thankful this morning that God wants to work through us
to accomplish through our lives
more than we could ever accomplish on our own.
Far greater.
It's said of D.L. Moody that he desired to,
well, it's said of him that he shook two continents
with the gospel.
Speaking of North America and Europe.
It's said of D.L. Moody's ministry
that over a million people came to know Christ
because of his ministry.
If you know anything about D.L. Moody,
he was a man that according to what our society
and what our culture would say, he was an unlearned man.
He didn't have an advanced education,
but he got saved.
God, the Holy Spirit lived within him.
And he was just fully surrendered to God.
And he just said, God, I want you to use my life.
I want you to use me, God, for your honor and for your glory.
There were people that would come to D.L. Moody.
I mean, preachers that were contemporaries with him
and they would want to know the quote unquote secret
of his success.
I mean, people would hear that D.L. Moody was preaching
and they'd flock to hear him preach.
It wasn't necessarily because he was a great orator.
It's because he had the power of God.
You think about the Lord Jesus Christ when he was teaching,
when he first comes on the scene in his earthly ministry
and they say, no man spoke like this man.
He speaks with authority.
See, D.L. Moody was a man that had the power of God upon him.
It's said in one particular account that I've read
over the years of D.L. Moody,
it said that he was there in his office
and somebody asked him that question,
the secret of his success,
and he went over to a window that overlooked the city
and he just looked down and he said,
see all those people, that's,
God's called me to reach those people.
He was on a heart for people.
Why, because he knew that people were
facing the judgment of God.
See, Oded knew that Israel was under the,
yes, Judah, because of their wickedness,
faced the judgment of God,
but Israel, you're gonna face the great wrath of God as well
because they're in a very real sense this morning
that we come in contact with people every single day
that are under the wrath of God.
They're under the wrath of God.
If you read John chapter number three,
the Bible makes it very clear.
In fact, let's go there and read it.
John chapter number three,
and we're gonna, I was planning to just finish up
on the book of Jude, but let's look at John three
just very quickly.
Of course, in John chapter number three,
we're very familiar with the verse number 16.
For God so loved the world that he gave
his only begotten son that whosoever believeth in him
should not perish, but have everlasting life.
What a wonderful verse of scripture.
We find that Jesus came to seek and to save
that which was lost.
The Bible continues in verse number 17.
It says God sent not his son into the world
to condemn the world, but that the world through him
might be saved.
But look at verse 36 in John chapter number three.
We don't have time to read the entirety of it,
but look at verse number 36 of John chapter number three,
the last verse of this chapter.
The Bible says this.
He that believeth on the Son hath everlasting life.
And he that believeth not the Son shall not see life,
but the wrath of God abideth on him.
The wrath of God abideth on him.
There's a sentence of eternal damnation.
It's upon every individual that's not trusted Christ
as their savior.
And you and I come in contact with those people
every single day.
And I understand there's a lot of them that
they don't think they need what we have.
They don't want to hear what you have to say.
But I believe that this morning,
we need to have the power of God in our lives.
Like Oded did.
We need to just determine that we're gonna say,
we're gonna be God's spokesman.
We're gonna do what he's called us to do.
Turn to the book of Jude, if you will.
And as we get alone with God,
and we have the touch of God upon our lives,
I'm not talking about some kind of mystical thing.
But I'm just saying we spend time in the presence of God.
I want you to think about those disciples
in Acts chapter number four,
when that religious group of people were trying to,
after they'd already kept them in ward overnight,
and they're going to bring these accusations against them.
And the Bible says that Peter stands up
and he speaks with great boldness.
And the Bible says that they took knowledge of them
that they had been with Jesus.
There was an obvious impact
that was made upon that religious group
because they said, these men, they're atheists.
ignorant and unlearned, but they've been with Jesus. People need to know that we've spent
time with God. Listen, you can't fake it. You can't fake it. Let me say this, you can't
expedite it. There's not any instant, you ever have instant mashed potatoes? How many
of you like instant mashed potatoes better than regular mashed potatoes? I mean, you're
crazy if you do. You haven't had Holly's mashed potatoes, amen? But I'm telling you what,
I like mashed potatoes, but I don't want those instant things. I really don't. You say, well,
they're creamier, they don't have lumps. I like the lumps. Amen? I know they're real.
We live in an instant society. I don't like instant coffee. Try to put those grounds in
there. It's disgusting. I just not drink coffee if I have to drink instant coffee. Honestly,
you cannot expedite time with God. You can't. You've got to get into His presence. Be still
and know that I am God. And when you get into His presence, people can tell that you've
been with God. Oded, who's used of the Lord to make a difference. An individual, 200,000
people, amazing to me. But I want you to see from Jude 22, so many people say, can God
use me to make a difference? The answer is yes. God can use you. I want you to notice
what the Bible says. In Jude, it's only one chapter, verse 22, and if some have compassion,
making a difference. And others, save with fear, pulling them out of the fire, hating
even the garment spotted by the flesh. Oded had courage. We need courage today. We need
courage. We need boldness. We need to spend time with God. And God will use us to make
a difference in people's lives. I would encourage you, I've encouraged myself, to ask God to
use us for His honor and for His glory. That He would use us to make a difference. Not
for ourselves, but for His glory. As best we can tell from that portion of Scripture
in 2 Chronicles 28, Oded did not benefit one thing by standing up and declaring the message
of God. But there are 200,000 people that were directly impacted because of his obedience.
I'm not telling you this morning that God will use you to impact 200,000 people, but
I'm saying He could. He could. Only eternity is going to tell how God will use us. Very
few people know the name of the man that led D.L. Moody to the Lord. Very few people know
the man that was preaching when Charles Haddon Spurgeon went into that church and got saved.
God's economy is different than our economy. God knows. He keeps good records. And I trust
that this morning, just as we look at Oded, this, probably this morning, and I'm not saying
this to be, as an insult, but probably this morning, many of us have no idea who Oded
was before he came to church today. So, yeah, maybe I heard about that guy. What did he
do? Why? Because he's not a significant character in God's Word. That portion that we just read,
that's pretty much everything that you're going to read about Oded. He was a prophet
of the Lord. God used him to make a difference. Let's pray. Father, we love you. Thank you
for loving us. I thank you that you have a plan. You have a plan to make yourself known
amongst the nations. You have a plan. And that plan includes us. It's amazing to consider
this morning that you would use us for your honor and for your glory. That you would use
us to make a difference in people's lives. God, as we have just recently come off our
missions conference and now as we read this portion of scripture from the life of Oded,
God, I pray that you would help us this morning to be fully surrendered to thee. God, that
we'd get into your presence. That we'd have your touch upon us. That we'd be filled with
the power of the Holy Spirit of God. That we'd go forth with in obedience, with courage
and boldness. We'd make a difference in this lost and dying world. Natalie played a special
part. People need the Lord during our missions conference. What a great song. What a reminder
to us. People do need the Lord. God, you've chosen us. You've allowed us the privilege
of being able to tell those people about you. I pray then in the few moments of invitation
this morning that you'd have your will in way. I pray God that decisions would be made
that would bring honor and glory to thy name. That would help us all to be conformed to
the image of your dear son to impact eternity. I pray that you'd do in these few moments
what only you could do. For it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me?