Our prayer from this very first service of the Missions Conference this year.
Lord, would you give us your heart for souls.
Lord, give us your heart for our lost neighbor, for our lost friend,
our lost co-worker or family member.
Lord, give each and every one of us your heart for souls
that all the world may know.
In Jesus' name I pray. Amen. Amen.
Well take your Bible if you would please and turn with me to the Gospel of Luke.
Luke chapter number 23.
And with the Lord's help I'm going to read just one verse of Scripture this morning
that I could not get away from while seeking God's perfect will
for the first service of your Missions Conference.
I guess about 95-97% of the messages I preach are expository messages.
But this morning I've just got a topical thought that again I could not get away from
while seeking God's perfect will for the service.
Sometimes preachers ask, preacher are you an expository preacher or are you a topical preacher?
And my answer is yes.
Let me tell you what I believe about this Bible.
I believe this Bible is so powerful that God could use any portion of it
to convict the heart of the sinner and to change the life of the saint. Amen.
And that's what we're trusting the Lord is going to do this week during the Missions Conference.
Luke chapter number 23.
If you're able, would you please stand as we read this one verse of Scripture together.
Luke chapter 23 and verse 33.
The Word of God says,
And when they were come to the place which is called Calvary,
there they crucified Him, and the male factors, one on the right hand and the other on the left.
With the help of the Lord, I'd like to preach on this thought this morning,
compelled by Calvary.
If what I'm getting ready to preach doesn't compel you to reach the world with the gospel,
then I will say nothing else this week that will.
Calvary ought to motivate us to make a difference in the lives of others.
Father, bless our time of Bible study. In Jesus' name I pray. Amen.
Thank you so much for standing. Please be seated.
As you study your Bible, you'll discover there were many places that played a role
in the earthly ministry of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ.
There, of course, was the place of Christ's birth.
A little town called Bethlehem or the House of Bread.
There was the place called Nazareth where our Savior would grow into a man.
We also read of important places that Jesus visited during His earthly ministry as well.
There were those Judean hillsides as well as the shores of the Sea of Galilee.
There were the synagogues in the villages as well as the great temple in the capital city of Jerusalem.
Oh, but I believe it's vitally important for each of us to remember
that all of the places I've just mentioned were merely steps along the way.
Steps that would eventually lead our Lord to the place
that we've read about here in our text this morning.
And that, ladies and gentlemen, is this place called Calvary.
Now we know that to be the case because the Bible teaches us
that every step that Jesus took on the earth was a step
that would ultimately lead Him to an old rugged cross
on a hillside just outside of Jerusalem called Calvary.
And when you study the Word of God, you'll discover that even the Lord Jesus Himself alluded to that truth.
Matthew chapter 16 and verse 21 says,
From that time forth began Jesus to show unto His disciples
how that He must go into Jerusalem and suffer many things of the elders and chief priests and scribes
and be killed and be raised again the third day.
Matthew chapter 17 verses 22 and 23 says,
And they shall kill Him and the third day He shall be raised again.
While the very morning that Christ laid His life down on the cruel cross of Calvary,
Jesus spoke of the place as He told Pontius Pilate.
According to John chapter number 18 and verse 37,
To this end was I born, and for this cause came I into the world.
And therefore I would be the very first to agree with you
if you were to try to convince me this morning that Calvary was prophesied by the Scriptures.
I would agree with you because that most definitely is the case.
Calvary really was prophesied by the Scriptures.
But according to the Bible, Calvary was not only prophesied by the Scriptures,
Calvary was proclaimed by the Savior.
And the reason that I want to drive that point home this morning
is because that it is a scripturally based truth
that assures each and every one of us at the Fellowship Baptist Church this morning
that Calvary, the cross, and the blood that Jesus shed there
for the sins of the world did not slip up on God.
Calvary did not take God by surprise.
Absolutely not.
As our Savior was suspended between heaven and earth on an organ cross,
the Christ Holy God of glory did not lean over the banister of heaven
and declare with a furrowed brow,
Oh no, this messes my plans up altogether.
What in the world am I going to do?
Absolutely not.
The Bible teaches us in Revelation chapter 13 and verse 8
that our Savior, the lovely Lord Jesus,
was a lamb slain from the foundation of the earth.
And that assures each and every one of us this morning
that God had a plan to carry out at this place called Calvary.
That assures us that God had a purpose to fulfill at this place called Calvary.
That assures us this Lord's Day that God had a people in mind to deliver
by what would ultimately take place on the cross of Calvary.
There Christ's sinless, spotless, satisfying blood
would be shed for your sins, for my sins,
and for the sins of a lost and dying world.
There He would become like us so we could become like Him.
He would go hungry so our spiritual hunger could be fed.
He would cry from the cross,
I thirst so that our spiritual thirst could be quenched.
There on the cross of Calvary Jesus would be literally stripped naked
so that you and I might be clothed in His righteousness.
Someone said on one occasion, and I agree,
God gave heaven's best for the world's worst
so that the world's worst might know heaven's best.
So I can say this morning and be scripturally correct in saying
I know I'm getting older.
I turned 60 just a few months ago.
Now I know that surprises you.
I don't look a day over 29.
I know that, but I turned 60 years old
and I may be getting older,
but you're listening to one preacher preach this morning
that I'll never be over the hill
because the hill that I'm talking about
is the place that I'm preaching about this morning
where the Bible says,
and when they were come to the place which is called Calvary,
there they crucified Him.
Can I share a few things with you about the cross of Calvary?
I want to invite you, if you would please,
to take a trip with me by faith to a hill called Golgotha.
And as we see Jesus suspended on the old rugged cross there,
there are a few things that we can notice about this place
by way of introduction to the message.
When you study your Bible, you'll discover that Calvary
was a place of vicious suffering.
No picture has ever truly depicted
the viciousness of Calvary.
suffering that took place on the cross of Calvary. Calvary was a
place of vicious suffering. Calvary was a place of vicarious
substitution. Jesus took the beating that I deserved. Jesus
bore the load that I deserved. Calvary was a place of vicarious
substitution. Oh, but let me say this morning, Calvary was a
place of victorious splendor because it was there that God,
as only God could have done, turned tears into triumph. God
turned darkness into light. God turned suffering into splendor.
God took hurt and turned it into help. He took pain and turned it
into provision. Can I tell you what our thrice holy God did on
the cross of Calvary? God took gory and he turned gory into
glory. And when God turned gory into glory, you certainly
understand why God led the apostle Paul to pen Galatians
chapter 4 and 6 and verse 14 where the Bible says, but God
forbid that I should glory save in the cross of our Lord Jesus
Christ by whom the world is crucified unto me and I unto
the world. Paul said in first Corinthians chapter one and
verse 18 for the preaching of the cross is to them that
perish foolishness, but unto us, which are saved, it is the
power of God. Do you know what that tells me about the ministry
of the apostle Paul? Paul was motivated by Calvary. Paul was
compelled by Calvary. He was moved by the sacrifice that was
made on the cross so that he, a one-time persecutor of the
church, could be set free from his sin. And now after all these
years, since Paul's writing, Calvary is still motivating
God's people today. Calvary is still moving God's people today
to serve the Lord, to put God first. And it is Calvary,
ladies and gentlemen, that compels us to reach a lost and
dying world with the gospel. Three things about the cross of
Calvary that should compel us to do more than we've ever done
to reach the world with the gospel. First of all, I want
you to know number one, the reason for Calvary compels me to
be saved. And the reason that I want to make that perfectly
clear this morning is because I would not be true to my calling
to just assume that every single person under the sound of my
voice has been saved this morning. You might have made
your way to the house of the Lord and you do not know the
Lord Jesus Christ as your personal savior. Yes, I want to
reach D.C. with the gospel and I certainly want to watch, reach
Uruguay with the gospel, but I want to reach you with the
gospel. And that's why I want you to listen to all of the
message, but I really, I really want you to listen to the first
point of the message. The reason for Calvary compels me to be
saved. You see, ever since our forefather Adam's fall in the
garden of Eden, God has allowed but one way, and let me say
only one way, for sinful men to approach him. And that is
through and by the shed blood of sacrifice. Now the Bible
teaches us that from the very beginning, from the earliest
pages of the Bible. Let me give you one for instance, Genesis
chapter 4. You read of God accepting Abel's offering while
rejecting his brother Cain's offering. Now I don't encourage
you to turn there. Let me read just a few verses out of Genesis
chapter 4. And in the process of time it came to pass that Cain
brought to the fruit of the ground an offering unto the
Lord. Verse 4, And Abel, he also brought of the firstlings of his
flock, and of the fat thereof. And the Lord had respect unto
Abel, and to his offering, verse 5, but unto Cain, and to his
offering he had not respect. And the Bible says that Cain was
very wroth, and his countenance failed. Now let's address this
question, shall we? What's the problem with Cain's offering?
Was there a problem with the quality of Cain's offering?
Absolutely not. In fact, let me tell you what I believe. I
believe that Cain brought the very best fruit of the ground
that he had to the Lord. I'll tell you what I believe. I
believe he wanted to impress God by bringing God the very best
fruit of the ground that he had. So there is no problem with
quality. Well since there's no problem with quality, is there
a problem with quantity? Maybe Cain didn't bring enough
offering. Nope. No problem with quality. No problem with
quantity. So if there's no problem there, how about
quickness? Maybe Cain was a little late bringing his
offering. No, there's no problem with quickness. So
preacher, if there's no problem with quality, quantity, or
quickness, why does the Bible go to such lengths to teach us
that God would accept Abel's offering while rejecting Cain's?
Now, there's a lot of great preaching canon therefore should
be done here. I don't have time to do it. Can I give it to you
in a nutshell? Cain's offering was a bloodless offering. Are
you listening? I'm condensing several hours worth of preaching
into about two minutes here. Do you know what Cain's offering
represented? The best that man could do. Do you know what Cain's
offering teaches us? Cain's offering teaches us, ladies and
gentlemen, the very best that you and I could do isn't good
enough to forgive us of our sins and to cleanse us from our
unrighteousness. The Bible teaches that even our
righteousness is as filthy rags in the sight of God. Now that's
our righteousness. Can you imagine what our
unrighteousness is? Therefore, God rejected Cain's offering. It
was a bloodless offering. I personally believe since faith
cometh by hearing and hearing by the Word of God, God made it
abundantly clear to Abel and to Cain alike concerning what he
expected as far as an offering was concerned. Cain heard the
Word, but he did not heed the Word and he wanted to do it his
own way. But Cain was rejected. Abel, on the other hand, brought
on the firstling of his flock, which was a type or a picture of
he that John the Baptizer identified as the Lamb of God,
which taketh away the sin of the world. Cain brought a bloodless
offering while his brother Abel brought an offering of blood.
Abel's offering was accepted because it was accepted on the
basis of blood. And can I say to you, that's why we can sing the
song, What can wash away my sin? Nothing but the blood of Jesus.
What can make me whole again? Nothing but the blood of Jesus.
Again, I feel right at home here so I'm going to preach real
plain. Hold on now. I want you to hear what I'm getting ready
to say. There are not many ways to heaven. There is only one way
to heaven. And it's through and by the one that said in the
gospel of John chapter 14 and verse 6, I am the way, the
truth, and the life. No man, and that includes you, and that
includes me. No man, Jesus said, cometh unto the Father, but by
me. Again, let me just preach real plain. You'll get to
heaven through and by the shed blood of Jesus Christ or you'll
never get there. The reason for Calvary compels me to be saved.
Now in light of that, secondly, the reason for Calvary compels
The reaching of Calvary compels me to serve.
No, I do not serve the Lord to be saved.
I serve the Lord because I have been saved.
But when it comes to my service for the Lord,
I want to go on record by saying there is something that moves me to serve the Lord.
There is something that compels me to serve the Lord.
The reaching of Calvary compels me to serve.
And I say that because as much as I can and therefore should rejoice over the fact that Jesus died for me,
I ought to remind myself and remind myself often that Jesus died for the world.
Hear me this morning, Calvary is the theological engine of world evangelism.
Our burden for mission should flow from the cross of Calvary.
And therefore I can put it like this,
I can and therefore should rejoice in the fact that Calvary reaches me,
but I should never cease to remember the fact that salvation that was procured on the cross of Calvary
through the shed blood of our Savior is offered this morning to whosoever.
The message of Calvary, Christ's sacrificial death,
His shed blood is a message that God longs and in fact yearns for this lost and dying world to hear.
2 Peter 3 and verse 9,
The Lord is not slack concerning His promise, as some men count slackness,
but is longsuffering to us where not willing that any should perish,
but that somebody help me preach, all should come to repentance.
That assures us this morning, Calvary reaches whosoever.
Calvary not only reaches the king of the palace, Calvary reaches the beggar on the street corner.
Calvary not only reaches the mayor, Calvary reaches the meter maid.
Calvary reaches the white man, the black man, the yellow man, the brown man.
Calvary reaches the world.
That's why Romans chapter 10 and verse 13 declares,
For whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved.
Revelation 22 latter portion of verse 17,
And whosoever will, let him take the water of life freely.
1 Timothy chapter 2 and verse 4 teaches us that God would have all men to be saved
and to come unto the knowledge of the truth.
Now in light of those truths, God has commanded, are you listening?
He has commanded the church to go.
It isn't a suggestion to be ignored.
It is a command to be obeyed.
And friend, you can rest assured, Christ's last command should never cease to be our first concern.
And so if you're wondering this morning, preacher,
why all this fuss about a missions conference?
Preacher, why does the Fellowship Baptist Church of Oakton, Virginia go to such great lengths
to host missionary families and encourage you to not only continue what you're doing for missions,
but to, by the good grace of God, do more in the days to come?
I'll tell you why.
Because according to this Bible, where there is a creature,
God intends for there to be a preacher.
A preacher with a mandate to go.
A preacher with a mission field into all the world.
A preacher with a message and preach the gospel.
A preacher with a ministry to every creature.
The reaching of Calvary compels me to serve.
The reaching of Calvary compels me to live for Jesus.
The reaching of Calvary compels me to share with others the same gospel that has changed my life.
The reaching of Calvary compels me to serve.
And finally this morning, the rejoicing of Calvary compels me to shout.
Now I realize I said it earlier,
but I got such preach inside of me, I think I'll explode if I don't say it again.
Calvary, yes, it was a place of vicious suffering.
It was a place of vicarious substitution.
But let me assure you again, Calvary was a place of victorious splendor.
Because it was there on the cross as Jesus hung there.
The Bible teaches us that he would reach up with one hand and take the hand of his thrice holy heavenly father.
And he'd reach down with his other hand and take a hold of you.
And take a hold of me.
And bring the two of us together at this place called Calvary.
It was there that both sin and Satan would be vanquished and redemption and righteousness would be forever claimed.
It was there that heaven would meet hell in the most spectacular battle of all time.
And friend, it was there that heaven would claim the eternal victory over hell
for all those that would trust the Lord Jesus Christ as their personal savior.
And when you consider that, you'll begin to understand why God used the songwriter of old to pen these words.
Victory was won at Calvary.
Victory that gave me liberty.
Now I can live eternally.
For victory was won at Calvary.
You've listened so well. Would you bow your head with me? Let's pray together.
Oh my father, I'm so appreciative for the finished work of the Lord Jesus on the cross of Calvary.
Lord, it makes me want to say along with the songwriter, nothing in my hand I bring.
Simply to Christ's cross I cling.
My only hope of heaven is through and by your blood that was shed on the cross of Calvary.
And so Lord, I just want to stop right here and say, I sure do thank you.
Thank you. Thank you for your shed blood.
Thank you for your eternal salvation.
Thank you that when I could not produce an offering that would be acceptable,
Jesus went to the cross and shed his blood there so that he could make me acceptable in your eyes.
And for that I'm so grateful.
Thank you, Jesus. Thank you so very much.
And now in light of what you have done for us all, if anything ought to motivate us to reach the world,
it's the cross that we've seen yet again with an eye of faith this morning.
And in fact, Lord, it really is as I have said earlier, if that doesn't motivate us to go,
if that doesn't motivate us to give, if that doesn't motivate us to get missionaries to the field,
then Lord, I know nothing else that will be said or done here this week will.
And so my Father, I pray that you would help each and every one of us to open our eyes of faith
and to take a fresh look at the cross of Calvary yet again.
Now I pray for Pastor Man that you'd give him both wisdom and discernment
as he comes to extend the invitation as you lay upon his heart to do so.
And I'll give you glory and honor and praise in Jesus' name. Preacher.
are closed if you're here this morning you're not sure of heaven today is the
day of salvation very first point that we dealt with you need to be saved if
you're not sure of heaven you come we'll have a man take a Bible if you're a man
and show you how you could know for sure that heavens your home if you're a lady
we'll have a lady take a Bible and show you I can know for sure that heaven is
your home if you're not saved the invitation for you this morning is to be
saved if you're here this morning and you know the Lord Jesus Christ is your
personal Savior it's a good thing to be reminded to be compelled by the truth of
Calvary to share the gospel with a lost and dying world that others would know
that all the world may know Kimberly's gonna play quietly on the piano and as
she does the altar is open let's be