with a bad back today and unable to be here.
And so if you'd pray for Doc,
I know that he'd appreciate that.
The book of 3rd John,
the book of 3rd John all the way in the back of your Bible,
3rd John, Jude and Revelation,
and just a very short letter, just 14 verses.
We're just gonna look at the first eight verses this morning
and I'm thankful that God has given us his word.
I'm thankful that the Bible reveals God to mankind.
I'm thankful that within the pages of this precious book,
that God has provided us with the details
regarding his plan.
I'm thankful that God has a plan.
And you know, have you ever had a plan
and somebody kind of messed with your plan
and kind of changed things up?
No one's gonna change God's plan.
I'm thankful that God has a plan
and his plan will come to pass.
And we find that within the pages of the Bible,
that God has also chosen to record for us
the interactions between God and man.
We find that obviously not all of the interactions
between God and man are recorded
within the pages of this book,
but we do find that God has given us insight
as to how God had an impact in the lives of these believers,
those that we read of,
that we might refer to as the heroes of the faith
and what have you.
We have the opportunity to be able to see how the truth,
how God's revelation had an impact in their lives.
We find, of course, this morning
that there are some Bible characters
that are more familiar than others.
And if we were to go around the room this morning
and ask each individual that's here,
who is your favorite Bible character?
I'm sure we'd have a variety of answers,
but we'd probably have some duplicates as well
because we have some characters within the Bible
that are very well known.
Others, like the one that we'll look at this morning,
there's not a whole lot that God tells us
about these individuals.
As we think about the first eight verses
to the short epistle of the book of 3 John,
we see and we note the testimony of a man named Gaius.
Now we see that there's a few other references
within the New Testament
to an individual holding the name Gaius.
It is really difficult for us to be able to tell
if this is the same Gaius
that's mentioned in the book of Acts
or if it's a different one.
It would seem to be it's a different one,
but for sake of argument this morning,
we are not 100% sure.
It seems as if, as you study the scriptures,
that this Gaius that John is referring to
in the epistle of 3 John is a different Gaius
than the ones that are mentioned earlier
and God gives us some insight with regard to this man.
And I believe that as we study these eight verses
that God would challenge us this morning
with regard to his testimony.
It's interesting to note how John refers to this man.
He refers to him as the well-beloved Gaius.
And then John also makes it known and declares publicly
that he, John, loved Gaius.
And we understand we're to love the brethren.
And so as we look at this portion of scripture
and we begin to understand what's taking place,
it may be, as you look at verse number two,
it seems as if this man Gaius had some physical illness
that is hinted to in verse number two,
but we will see with great clarity
that even if he had a physical illness,
that he was thriving spiritually.
And what a blessing to think about someone
that is doing well spiritually.
The fact of the matter is that we may be hindered physically.
We may have some difficulties as we age
and so on and so forth.
We have some difficulties with our failing health
and strength and physical capabilities.
But what a blessing to know
that even if the physical is suffering,
that we can be thriving spiritually.
And as we look at this portion of scripture,
I've simply entitled from verse number one,
our title for the message this morning,
the well-beloved Gaius.
Notice the Bible says this in beginning in verse number one,
the elder, John, unto the well-beloved Gaius,
whom I love in the truth.
Beloved, I wish above all things
that thou mayest prosper and be in health,
even as thy soul prospereth.
For I rejoiced greatly when the brethren came
and testified of the truth that is in thee,
even as thou walkest in the truth.
I have no greater joy than to hear
that my children walk in truth.
Beloved, thou doest faithfully whatsoever thou doest
to the brethren and to strangers,
which have borne witness of thy charity before the church,
whom if thou bring forward on their journey
after a godly sort, thou shalt do well.
Because that for his name's sake,
they went forth taking nothing of the Gentiles,
we therefore ought to receive such
that we might be fellow helpers to the truth.
As you look at this portion of scripture,
I wanna note really five things this morning
that I trust will be an encouragement to you
as we study the life of Gaius,
to be challenged by his testimony
and to be comforted in knowing that God uses individuals.
If you take notes this morning,
notice number one with me,
Gaius was obedient to God's word.
The Bible says in verse number three,
notice it says, for I rejoiced greatly
when the brethren came and testified
of the truth that is in thee,
even as thou walkest in the truth.
Now we understand as we look at this statement here
in verse number three,
when we consider the obedience of Gaius,
that his obedience was evident
to those to whom he was serving.
They could see in his life that he was an individual
that was obedient to the word of God.
He had a good testimony publicly,
no doubt if publicly he was obedient to the word of God
and we're looking at the passage of scripture
and seeing how his soul was prospering,
that privately he must have been obedient
to God's word as well.
And begin to think about this obedience of this man Gaius
and understanding that it was evident,
it was obvious to those with whom he served.
But we also know in verse number three,
that the Bible says that it was reported by the brethren.
Notice it says, for I rejoiced greatly
when the brethren came and testified
of the truth that is in thee,
even as thou walkest in the truth.
Let another man praise thee, the Bible tells us.
And we find here in this text of scripture
that Gaius was not writing back to John
and saying, John, I just want you to understand
how obedient I am in my life.
And I want you to know, John, that I'm more obedient,
that no, no, the brethren brought this report to John.
As the brethren brought this report to John,
and we understand the obedience of this man Gaius,
that it was obvious, it was evident
to those with whom he served,
but it was reported by the brethren.
I do not believe this morning that Gaius was a man
that was looking for acceptance.
I do not believe that Gaius was a man
that was looking for accolades.
No, I believe Gaius was a man who simply loved the Lord.
And because he loved the Lord, he obeyed God's word.
The Bible is a precious book that's been given to us.
We understand that it's been preserved.
And you think about the supernatural work of God,
not only in giving us the Bible through the truth
of all scriptures given by inspiration of God
and that divine revelation,
but we understand that he's divinely preserved
his word for us, and we have the Bible
and how precious and profitable it is to us.
And we understand that the scriptures tell us in Psalm 19,
if you were to read through really verse seven
down through verse number 11,
and all how the Bible describes itself
in those portions of those verses of scripture.
And we find that the Bible tells us
that we do well if we take heed.
And we are to take the warnings and we're to obey.
We understand that the principle of obedience
is a principle that is found
throughout the entirety of God's word.
You begin to read of the situation there,
the account of Cain and Abel.
And you find that Cain is told if thou doest well,
shalt thou not be accepted.
In other words, if you obey,
if you follow the prescribed path, you'll be accepted.
Obedience always leads to blessing.
I want you to notice it's interesting as you know,
in verse number three, again, as we're speaking
about the obedience of this man Gaius,
that his obedience had a profound impact
upon the Apostle John.
Notice what John says in verse number three,
for I rejoiced greatly.
John, what is it that would cause you to rejoice greatly?
I'm rejoicing greatly because there's a man over there,
Gaius, someone in whom God had given me an opportunity
to influence and to have some part of influencing his life.
And he's walking in the truth.
He's obedient to God's word.
And John the Apostle is saying this truth
has caused me to rejoice greatly.
No doubt as we find in verse number four,
a verse of scripture that has often been used
when we speak about parenting,
where John says I have no greater joy
than to hear that my children walk in truth.
And you'd understand that we can look at that truth
from verse number four and apply it to parenting.
And no doubt there's great joy that comes in the heart
and the life of a parent when a child is doing what's right
and walking in truth.
But you understand that.
Biblically, he's not talking about being a parent.
He's speaking about the spiritual relationship
between John and Gaius, and he says,
listen, I have no greater joy
than to hear that my children walk in truth.
John was rejoicing greatly because of the obedience
of an individual believer.
Look at a few verses with me, if you will.
Turn back to the Gospel of John,
and look at John chapter number two.
The Gospel of John, and John chapter number two.
We'll look at just a few verses here this morning
with regard to the subject matter of obedience,
and noting the obedience of Gaius in our text of scripture
in the short epistle, 3 John.
But notice in John chapter number two,
this is the first miracle, the beginning of miracles,
there at the wedding in Cana.
But I wanna draw your attention to just a single verse
of scripture within this miracle,
and it's a statement that is made by Mary.
Notice in verse number five, his mother, Mary,
saith unto the servants, whatsoever he saith unto you,
do it.
That's pretty straightforward, isn't it?
Now, contextually, it's with regard
to the particular miracle that's taking place in Cana.
We understand that, but understanding
by way of application this morning,
that Jesus is God, he's God in flesh,
and we find that he's given us the written word of God,
and as we have the Bible in our hands this morning,
whatsoever he saith unto you, do it.
That settles a whole lot of things, doesn't it?
We've often said in counseling,
privately, in public preaching,
I've often said to individuals that, listen,
we must first agree that we're gonna agree with God,
because if we can agree that we're going to agree with God
and with God's word and what God said,
then that settles a whole lot of things,
because no longer is it your position or my position
or my interpretation or your interpretation.
No, we're gonna go to the Bible
and find what the Bible says,
and Jesus is here ministering,
and Mary says to the servants,
whatsoever he, Jesus, saith unto you,
servants, do it, do it.
Notice, if you will, in Luke chapter number six,
Luke chapter number six,
and this verse of scripture
is a convicting verse of scripture.
In fact, I remember a number of years ago,
Brianna just graduated from high school,
so it was, I think she might have been in fifth grade,
maybe sixth grade, so it was six, seven years ago
that she was over at Heritage Christian School
and she was singing a song as part of Odax,
and part of that song that they were singing
was really taken from this truth
in Luke chapter number six and verse number 46,
and I remember hearing that song.
I'd never heard the song before.
I've never heard it since then,
but what a great song that gives the truth
of this verse of scripture.
Notice in Luke six and verse 46,
notice Jesus says this,
why call ye me Lord, Lord,
and do not the things which I say?
That's convicting.
Jesus is saying, why are you calling me Lord,
but you're not obeying me?
You're not doing the things which I say.
Verse 47, whosoever cometh to me
and heareth my sayings and doeth them,
I will show you to whom he is like.
He is like a man which built a house and digged deep
and laid the foundation on a rock,
and when the floods arose,
the stream beat vehemently upon the house
and could not shake it,
for it was founded upon a rock,
but he that heareth and doeth not
is like a man that without a foundation
built a house upon the earth
against which the stream did beat vehemently,
and immediately it fell,
and the ruin of that house was great.
You find that Jesus asked that piercing question,
why call ye me Lord, Lord,
and do not the things which I say?
See, Gaius was a man who was obedient to the word of God.
I said this a moment ago that I do not believe
that Gaius was looking for acceptance or accolades.
He was not trying.
He wasn't vying for a position within the church.
I believe that he was simply a man that loved God,
and out of his love for God came obedience to God's word,
and that's what Jesus tells us in John 14 and 15.
He says, if you love me, keep my commandments.
If you love me, keep my commandments.
We see that is repeated by John in 1 John 5,
that he says that same thing again
that John would have heard Jesus say
there in John 14 and verse 15.
We find that in 1 John 5 and verse number three,
John says this, for this is the love of God,
that we keep his commandments,
and his commandments are not grievous.
I'm so thankful that God has given us his word,
but how imperative it is that we obey his word,
that we are doers of the word and not hearers only.
It is absolutely imperative.
It's not enough to have the right Bible.
It's not enough to talk about having the Bible.
We must be doers of the word.
We must be obedient to God's word,
and with obedience to God's word comes blessing.
No doubt we find that the key, if you will,
to Gaius having, as John refers to it,
as a soul that prospereth, is his obedience to God's word.
Gaius was obedient to the word of God.
Number two, if you're taking notes back in 3 John,
I want you to notice with me, number two,
that Gaius was a servant.
He was a servant.
As we look here at the short letter of 3 John,
we do not have a complete record
of the service of this man, Gaius,
but we find that the summary statement
that is given to us in verse number five
is of great significance, and it's a powerful truth.
Notice what the Bible says in verse number five
with regard to this man, Gaius,
being a servant of the Lord.
It says, beloved, thou doest faithfully
whatsoever thou doest to the brethren and to strangers.
I want you to think about this statement
in considering the service and the fact
that Gaius is a servant.
By the way, it's a great thing to be a servant of the Lord.
You find that as you study and you read
through the New Testament,
that a number of the New Testament letters
that you'll read, the books in the New Testament,
they'll start out by the author mentioning
that they are a servant of the Lord.
And what a great privilege to be a servant
of the King of Kings and Lord of Lords.
And we find that he's a good master
and he's worthy of our service.
And we find that the Bible says there in verse number five,
thou doest faithfully whatsoever thou doest.
Now, last Sunday evening, we had an introduction
to the life of Joseph from Genesis chapter 37.
And one of the points that I made in that introduction
was that Joseph was a man that worked.
He was a man that was working, hardworking.
And we noticed some of that from Genesis 37.
And I talked about the fact that work is good.
And we find that the Bible says,
whatsoever thou doest faithfully whatsoever thou doest.
And I see this faithful servant of the Lord.
I don't believe, again, that Gaius was a man
that was serving just if certain people were around
and watching and observing.
I remember when I worked in the corporate world,
there would be times in which you'd be in the office there
and then all of a sudden,
the people that were goofing off and doing whatever,
they quickly get back to their desk
and pretend as if they're working.
Why?
Because one of the bosses enters into the building.
That's nonsense.
Really, it is.
As a child of God, we are serving God.
And we serve the Lord.
And we find that here, that his service,
he was a faithful servant of the Lord.
That thou doest faithfully whatsoever thou doest.
But I want you to notice the latter part
of verse number five, to the brethren, to the brethren.
Now, we can understand that.
We can understand brothers and sisters in Christ.
And we can understand the service
that maybe he would be involved in on serving one another
and loving one another and so on and so forth.
And that relationship of brother and sister in Christ.
But the Bible says to the brethren and to strangers,
to strangers.
It's impactful when we begin to think about the service
of Gaius and understanding that he was a servant.
He just, I believe, was a man that was privileged
to be able to serve God.
And he wasn't serving for any recognition.
He wasn't serving so that he could get
some level of promotion, if you will.
He just was privileged to serve God.
And he did whatever he did faithfully.
And he did it to the brethren and to strangers.
We're gonna think about that phraseology
with regard to his service.
And I would say that it's quite evident
from the way in which the description is given to us
that his service was first to the Lord.
His service was first to the Lord.
It wasn't that he was just serving this individual
or these individuals.
No, he was serving the Lord.
And as he was serving the Lord,
God would give him opportunities.
And he was mindful of the fact that he was serving Christ.
He was serving his master.
And what a wonderful blessing it is
to be a servant of the Lord.
I would say number three this morning,
as you look at this.
this portion of scripture that you'll notice
that Gaius was not only a man that was obedient
to God's word, a man that was a servant of the Lord,
but Gaius was generous.
Gaius was generous.
I believe that the Lord had blessed him.
Again, we don't know a lot about this man
and his background and so on and so forth,
but it seems as if, as you would look
at the text of scripture, that the Lord
had blessed this man and he desired
to be a blessing to others.
In fact, he desired to use his resources
for God's work and for God's glory.
As you look in verse number six,
the Bible says, which have borne witness
of thy charity before the church,
whom, if thou bring forward on their journey
after a godly sort, thou shalt do well,
because that for his namesake they went forth,
taking nothing of the Gentiles.
And so, to get a little background
as to what's taking place, we would see
that the hospitality of Gaius is on display
in verses six and seven, and his generosity
is being referred to in verses six and seven.
There were these preachers, these servants
of the Lord that would travel through,
and as they were traveling through,
they would need assistance.
They would need somebody to help them
on their way to get to the next place,
to be able to serve and minister in the next location.
And we find that the Bible would tell us
that Gaius was a man that was involved
in helping in those particular situations.
The phrase in your Bible that says
in verse number six, bring forward on their journey.
Now, that's a five-word phrase in English,
but it's just one Greek word.
And that single Greek word that is translated
for us, bring forward on their journey,
literally carries with it the idea
of fitting someone out for all
that is necessary for a journey.
Now, think about that.
Someone's taking a journey.
These traveling preachers, they're taking this journey,
and there were some needs that they had
in order to get from where they were
to where they were supposed to be ministering,
and there were certain needs that were necessary
in order to allow them to take that journey.
And that word means, to bring forward on their journey,
means to fit them out, to provide the things necessary
for that journey, whether they be supplies,
whether they be lodging, whatever it might be,
that those things are being supplied.
I see the generosity of this man, Gaius.
I begin to think about this man's generosity,
and I would say that he was a man
that was storing up treasure in heaven.
He was storing up treasure in heaven.
Turn to the book of Matthew, if you will,
in chapter number five, Matthew chapter number five.
Someone made the comment to me this past week
about something with regard to the stock market
and something about, man, you could have made
a lot of money in this particular day
in the stock market or whatever it was.
And the reality is that we understand
that things quickly can change.
When you think about the truth this morning
with regard to all that takes place
with our economy and so on and so forth,
but the Bible teaches us that we can lay up
for ourselves treasures in heaven.
I think I said Matthew five, but it should be Matthew six.
Did I say five?
And my apologies, Matthew chapter number six.
Matthew chapter number six.
In verse number 19, the Bible says this.
Lay not up for yourselves treasures upon earth
where moth and rust doth corrupt
and where thieves break through and steal.
Now, I believe that there is a level of being prudent
and understanding the importance of retirement
and what have you, and we understand those things.
I've said this before from the pulpit.
I don't say it to be mean or unkind,
but the reality is that there's a danger
in a society like ours where there's so much emphasis
placed upon retirement planning
and very little emphasis that's placed
upon eternal planning.
And the reality is that you may
or may not ever have retirement years.
Some of you say I'm already enjoying them, hallelujah.
But for some of us, we may never have retirement years.
We just don't know.
There's but a step between us and death.
As it appointed unto man wants to die
after this the judgment, but there's also the truth
that the trumpet of the Lord shall sound at any time, amen.
And I'm looking forward to hearing
the trumpet of the Lord sound.
And so we are not sure of retirement,
but we are sure of eternity.
And here, Jesus in his instruction here in Matthew six,
he says with regard to laying up treasures,
notice in verse number 20,
but lay up for yourselves treasures in heaven
where neither moth nor rust doth corrupt
and where thieves do not break through nor steal,
for where your treasure is, there will your heart be also.
I would tell you this morning
that it is absolutely possible
that you can plan for retirement here on this earth,
but also be planning for eternity,
and you can be storing up treasure in heaven.
It's not an either or.
You can do both.
You can be wise and you can prepare for retirement
here on this earth, but you can be actively generous
in your giving to God and to his work.
And by the way, that's God honoring.
I begin to think about this thought
of storing up treasure, laying up treasure in heaven,
sending it in advance,
and all that God is able to do with it.
And I said it's not an either or, we can do both,
but it requires that we live within our means.
It might require that we don't have
all of the newest things that come down the pike.
We live in a society that constantly is bombarding us
with all of the newest, fanciest,
you need this, you need that, you can't live without it.
And the marketing ploys of our society
are of course very in your face,
and they're very good at what they do,
otherwise they wouldn't be given the kind of monies
that they're given on an annual basis.
But the reality is that we can do both.
Gaius was a man who was generous.
He was providing and helping those
that were serving the Lord.
Notice what the Bible says
in 2 Corinthians chapter number nine.
In 2 Corinthians chapter number nine,
it's a familiar verse of scripture,
but I want you to notice what God tells us
with regard to giving.
And by the way, I'm so thankful that God has blessed us.
And we have been blessed beyond measure,
and it's an absolute privilege
that I have an opportunity to give back to God
a portion of what he has graciously blessed me with.
I thank God for the opportunity to give to the work of God.
He says in 2 Corinthians nine in verse number six,
but this I say, he which soweth sparingly
shall reap also sparingly,
and he which soweth bountifully shall reap also bountifully.
Every man according as he purposeth in his heart,
so let him give.
Notice what it says, not grudgingly or of necessity,
for God loveth a cheerful giver.
God loveth a cheerful giver.
Someone that I often pray that God would help us
to give cheerfully and appropriately.
And we look at that, listen, it's not that I have to give,
it's not that I'm holding on to that offering so tight
that it's hard for me to part.
No, no, I get to give to God's work.
What a privilege.
Personally, we won't take time this morning to go there,
but maybe you wanna jot it down in your notes.
I believe that 1 Chronicles chapter 29
is probably within the whole of scripture,
the greatest illustration of someone
that's giving cheerfully, and that's David.
In 1 Chronicles chapter 29, you go back there
and you read it later today or this week,
and you read that text of scripture,
and you see for yourself
that that is a wonderful illustration example
of a man that was giving cheerfully.
And by the way, if you understand within the context
of 1 Chronicles 29, that David was giving for a temple
that he would never see and never worship God in,
but he was given for the next generation.
What a blessing, what a blessing.
In Philippians chapter number four,
the Bible teaches us about those that were giving
to the work of mission, specifically the church at Philippi
here in the ministry of the Apostle Paul
in Philippians chapter number four.
As I think about the work of the ministry
and the Apostle Paul faithfully serving the Lord
and how God would use the church at Philippi,
we find that God gives in this text of scripture
some wonderful promises and realities
with regard to our giving.
Notice what Paul says beginning in verse number 14
of Philippians four, as he's writing to this local church,
notwithstanding you have well done
that you did communicate with my affliction.
Now you Philippians know also
that in the beginning of the gospel
when I departed from Macedonia,
no church communicated with me
as concerning giving and receiving, but ye only.
For even in Thessalonica,
ye sent once again unto my necessity,
not because I desire a gift,
but I desire fruit that may abound to your account.
But I have all and abound, I am full,
having received of Epaphroditus
the things which were sent from you.
Notice how this offering is described
at the end of verse number 18,
an odor of a sweet smell, a sacrifice acceptable,
well-pleasing to God.
But my God, verse 19, shall supply all your need
according to his riches in glory by Christ Jesus.
I believe that as we look at the life of Gaius
and we note as we're looking at his testimony
here in third John, that yes,
he was a man who was obedient to God's word.
He was a man that was a servant.
He was a man that was generous.
He was a man that gave so that others could go.
And he was a man that I believe that his generosity,
his sacrifice was an odor of a sweet smell,
a sacrifice that was acceptable
and well-pleasing to God Almighty.
What a blessing.
As you study and look at the life of Gaius here
in 3rd John, sounds like a guy that we'd like
to be able to know and worship the Lord with.
I mean, a good servant of the Lord,
a faithful follower of the Lord Jesus Christ.
As we look at his testimony,
turn back to 3rd John, if you will.
And let me just note two other things quickly
as we close this morning.
I want you to notice with me number four,
if you're taking notes, that Gaius was a man
that was involved in the work of God.
He was involved in the work of God.
As we know, as we look at the scripture,
we find that the Bible would tell us
how that he was walking in truth in verse number three,
how that in verse number five,
thou doest faithfully whatsoever thou doest
to the brethren and to the strangers.
And so he is personally involved in the work of God.
The Bible tells us which have borne witness
of thy charity before the church.
If thou bring forward on their journey
after a godly sort, thou shalt do well
because that for his namesake,
they went forth taking nothing of the Gentiles.
We therefore ought to receive such.
Notice that we might be fellow helpers to the truth.
When I think about the involvement of Gaius
and how Gaius was a man who was involved
in the work of God, his involvement,
as you know at the end of verse number eight,
makes him a fellow helper to the truth.
Now I like that terminology as we would think about
the way in which God would use us to be fellow helpers,
fellow laborers to the truth.
And we find that God's perspective
is different than man's perspective,
that Gaius was not the man that was actually
the traveling preacher, if you will,
but he was involved on helping the traveling preacher
to get to where he needed to be.
And God says he was involved in the work
and that he was a fellow helper to the truth.
When I think about Gaius being a man
that was involved in the work of God,
I think about it this way, be a participator.
Don't be a spectator.
You know, some people like to just sit
on the sidelines and watch, it drives me crazy.
You watch a game, you watch something,
man, I wanna get involved, I wanna participate.
You know, these guys out here for the,
every once in a while we have different activities
and during a recent celebration,
they're playing cornhole out here.
I don't wanna stand there for two hours
and watch them play cornhole, I wanna play.
I wanna participate.
I watch them play basketball.
I'm not that great, I'm getting old, I know,
but I wanna play, I wanna get involved,
I wanna participate.
When it comes to church, when it comes to the work of God,
it's a wonderful thing to be involved in God's work,
to be a participator, not to be a spectator,
not to just sit on the sidelines,
but, well, there's not a whole lot I can do.
Find out what you can do and do it
because God has a purpose for us,
God has a plan for us.
We're speaking with a man years ago
and he had a list of I can't do this
and I can't do this and I can't do this
and I said, listen, let's forget about that list
that you've prepared and let's just focus
on the things you can do because the reality
is that we're not interested in talking
about all the things you can't do,
but let's figure out what we can do
because God has equipped us and what a blessing it is
to be a participator, to be involved in the work of God.
We mentioned already John chapter number two
and verse number five earlier when the mother
of Jesus, Mary, she said, what sort of he saith unto you,
do it, and it's interesting as you look
at that portion of scripture that the Bible tells us
how the servants, they knew what had taken place,
but the servants which drew the water knew
is a statement in verse number nine
and they were involved in the work.
I think about the disciples.
We can read of the many miracles of the Lord Jesus Christ
and we can see how the Lord Jesus Christ worked
in just amazing ways, but there's certain miracles
that Christ performed that he used his disciples.
I think about the feeding of the 5,000.
Think about the feeding of the 4,000,
but if you just focus on the feeding of the 5,000
for just a moment, we find that God told the disciples
to have everyone sit down, right?
Now what was the perspective of the disciples?
It would have been a long day.
I mean, they were tired.
The purpose that Jesus said, let's go to a desert place,
who remembers why?
To rest, to rest, but when they went to rest,
there were some people that got there before them
and Jesus spent all day ministering to them
and those disciples, what did they say?
Send them away that they may get something to eat.
They don't want to be bothered with it.
You ever feel that way?
You can get weird, you can get tired, send them away
and Jesus says, give ye them to eat.
We don't have anything.
What do you want us to do?
Through a series of circumstances, they find a small lunch
and the Lord says, have them all sit down
and they all sit down, they have them sit in companies
and it's very orderly how it's done.
We find that Jesus blessed and multiplied,
but if you read the text of scripture,
you know what has to happen?
The disciples come to Jesus, they get the bread and the fish
and they distribute to the people
and then they go back to Jesus
and they get the bread and the fish
and they go and they distribute to the next group of people.
Is that not what happens in your Bible?
That's how it says in my Bible, that's what happens.
So guess what those disciples were doing?
They're participating in the work of God.
Now let me ask you this, could God have just supernaturally,
bam, there's a plate of food in everybody's lap?
I mean, sure enough, if he multiplied it the way he did,
he could have done whatever he wanted to do,
but you know what he decided to do?
I'm gonna use these disciples.
You know what God's still doing today?
Listen, God doesn't need us, but he's chosen to use us
and that is a truth that I don't know,
I've been saved now for 25 years,
almost 26 years I've been saved serving the Lord.
I don't know that I will ever be able to wrap my mind
around the truth that God would use us.
It's an amazing truth that God would use us,
but in God's plan and in God's wisdom,
he determined that he would use his children
and what a privilege and honor to serve the master,
to be involved in the work.
See, there's something about being involved in the work
that's different than just observing the work.
Somebody went out yesterday with us
and they contacted me and they said,
I just have so much joy
because I was able to go and share the gospel with someone.
Involved in the work, doing the work.
Somebody might be able to hear that,
that's an observer that's, wow, that seems exciting,
but it's a different experience altogether
when you're involved in the work.
And Gaius was a man that was involved,
he was involved in God's work.
Number five, very simply,
more of a summary statement than a point actually,
Gaius was exemplary, he was exemplary.
If I could say it this way,
he is a model follower of Christ.
I hesitate on using the terminology
of being a model Christian,
but we do know that God has given us in his word
the truth that Jesus is our example
and we understand that it makes it very plain.
Peter writes that Jesus left us an example
that we should follow his steps.
And so we understand that Jesus is the greatest example.
But you understand that the apostle Paul said,
be followers of me even as I also am of Christ.
You understand that Paul said to the believers
in Philippi in chapter four,
just before what we read just a moment ago,
he says that the things that you've heard
and seen in me do.
And so we find that this man Gaius,
when I look at his testimony and again,
a man that God doesn't tell us a whole lot about.
I mean, if you were to study the life of Paul this morning,
there's so many more things that you find
in God's record in his Bible about the apostle Paul
and so little about this man Gaius,
but yet what God has chosen to record for us
and to provide us record with this morning
of this man Gaius, man, he's exemplary.
And God chose to record it for a purpose.
And I believe this morning that as much
as we can be encouraged by studying about this man Gaius
and understanding how God would use this individual
and how he was a man that was obedient.
He was a man that was a servant.
He was a man that was generous.
He was a man that was involved.
And we look at his life and we rejoice
just as John was rejoicing.
He says, listen, I'm rejoicing greatly
because of the record, the report that I'm receiving.
We can rejoice this morning, but oh that God would help us to look at the life of Gaius
and say, God would you use me in the same way that you used Gaius?
See Gaius was just a man that made himself available to God and said where I am with
what I have, I just want to serve God.
I want to be obedient to His Word.
Though his health may have been failing, as you would note in verse number two, that his
soul was prospering, he was doing quite well spiritually.
And I'm thankful that we can thrive spiritually.
I've said this before, we're as close to God as we want to be.
We are as close to God as we want to be.
We spend as much time with God in His Word and in prayer as we really want to.
Oh, I just don't have any time.
If you've got a smart phone like I do, it tells you how many minutes you've spent on
your phone all week, hallelujah, right?
Listen, we've got time for all kinds of things, really.
Gaius, when we look at his testimony, it's exemplary.
He's a believer that just was all in.
A believer that though he doesn't say it, Paul says it, I am crucified with Christ.
I think it fits with Gaius.
He's a man that just wanted to serve God.
This morning, we need some people of God, some men of God, some women of God that would
have these same type of character traits evident in their life, obedience to God's
Word.
Why call you me Lord, Lord and do not the things that I say?
That we just understand we're servants and what a privilege it is to be a servant of
the Lord, that we'd be generous.
I want to lay up treasure in heaven.
I want to be used of thee.
I thank you for giving me the resources that you did, that you have, so I might be used
of thee.
Oh, that we'd be involved.
God, what's the place that you have for me?
What can I do in your work?
How can you use me?
Gaius was a man that was exemplary.
I thank God for his testimony and I trust this morning that we would be challenged to
walk in obedience to God.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the privilege that we have of being able to gather together, having a
Bible, reading of those who have gone before us and the testimony of this man, Gaius.
I'm thankful.
I'm challenged.
And I pray that as we've examined your word this morning, that you'd help us in this moment.
God, help us to be doers of the word and not hearers only.
Help us, yes, to rejoice in the testimony of an individual named Gaius.
Help us to examine our own lives, determine the level of obedience and service in our
lives personally.
God, I pray that you'd use us.
I pray that as we have a few moments of invitation, you'd help us to have a heart of submission
and obedience to you.
Lord, that you'd have your will in way, that we'd be doers of the word and not hearers
only.
Well, thank you for all that you'll do.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Eyes are out and eyes are closed.
No one's looking around this morning.
We'll have an opportunity to have an invitation.
Maybe you want to make your altar or your seat, your pew an altar.
Maybe you want to come to this old-fashioned altar.
But as Kimberly plays, the altar is open.