All right, we're having our midweek service.
We're pre recording it again, like we did last week.
And I'll be emailing out a link on YouTube for you to be able to watch the service we're
pre recording so that the rest of the week, we will not be in the church building, and
other folks will be able to come in and take care of things because of the quarantine protocol.
But certainly thankful for technology that we're able to do this thankful for Holly and
the kiddos helping out with all the aspects of the service, we do trust it to be a blessing
to you.
And we're going to sing a couple of songs.
The first one is this God will take care of you.
And it's number 579 in our hymnal God will take care of you
God will take care of you
Through every day or all the way
He will take care of you
God will take care of you
Through days of toil and hardships
When dangers reach your path of sin
God will take care of you
Through every day or all the way
He will take care of you
God will take care of you
All you may need He will provide
Nothing you ask will be denied
God will take care of you
Through every day or all the way
He will take care of you
God will take care of you
No matter what may be the test
When weary or hung upon His breast
God will take care of you
Through every day or all the way
He will take care of you
God will take care of you
Through every day or all the way
He will take care of you
God will take care of you
Thank you for the opportunity to have that calm rest and assurance that God will take care of you.
He is able and what a blessing and so thankful for the opportunity to have service
And thankful for just the blessings that God has bestowed upon us individually and corporately.
Let's go to the Lord in prayer.
Father, we do love you and we thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the privilege of being able to worship you.
We thank you for the work that you did in our hearts and lives on Sunday.
And God, we pray that as we once again open your word today, Lord, I pray that you would challenge us and convict us and comfort us.
I pray, God, that you'd help each one to be attentive and responsive.
I pray, God, that the word of God would minister to our hearts.
We thank you for this hymn, Lord, this song that had been written many years ago
that even still ministers to the hearts of your people today.
And God, I pray that you would help us to rest in the truth of what the songwriter was writing about.
Lord, we thank you for the promise in the book of 1 Peter in the 5th chapter
that we can cast all our care upon you knowing that you care for us
and what great comfort that is and what great joy, peace, and rest it brings to our hearts.
We do pray that you'd watch over those that are dealing with health issues.
We pray, God, that you'd touch bodies, give healing.
We pray, God, that you would be exalted and magnified through all that's said and done throughout this service.
For it's in Christ's name we pray, amen.
I do want to encourage you to continue to pray, if you will, for the Peterson family
and for Virginia and Yolanda and also for the Cooks and the Currys.
And if you would, continue to pray for Brother Ronnie Hall.
He, of course, has been dealing with back and hip trouble
and it's been extremely painful for him at times and he's seeming to improve some.
And so if you would continue to pray for Brother Ronnie, I know that he'd appreciate that.
And then if you'd pray for Brother Manuel, he is scheduled to have surgery next week.
And so we're praying that he'll receive this week all of the clearances from the doctors
that he needs to receive in order to go forward to have the surgery.
And that's going to be just a very, we're praying, a very successful shoulder surgery.
Obviously, there'll be some time of rehab and all that sort of thing.
And so we'll need to be praying for Brother Manuel for several weeks now
with regard to all of those things.
But we are trusting that it will give him relief from the pain in which he's been dealing with
and give him more mobility.
And I know that the Fesdechian family greatly appreciates your prayers.
I do want to encourage you to pray for some of our missionaries and then also some church planters.
And I know that I've shared with you over the last several months about a couple of church planters.
One of them is Brother Ben Webster at Newport News Baptist Church.
And they are still looking to be able to get into their own property.
And they've had a few obstacles that have come in their way.
But God is greater and God is able.
And so if you would pray for wisdom and direction for the Newport News Baptist Church
and Brother Ben Webster and the church family there that God would give clarity
with regard to the decisions that need to be made.
And that he would open up the doors and make things clear to them.
I know they'd appreciate that.
And then there's a new church planter that I have just recently been made aware of
and had the opportunity of meeting.
And his name is Brother Zach Hauser.
And he's planted a church up in Delaware.
And God is working and God is moving.
And we're very thankful.
It's exciting to hear about churches that are being established in our region.
And then also, of course, around the globe.
Please do continue to pray for the Savali family and the situation there in Samoa
with their church plant.
And I hope to be able to get some information from Brother Savali here this week
with regard to the meeting with the tribal leaders and the Mamali and all of that
that needs to take place.
But I know that he greatly appreciates your prayers.
Do pray, if you will, for Brother Paul Mershon.
I mentioned last year a number of meetings have been canceled.
And this is continuing.
Of course, they're based out in California.
They continue to have more and more travel bans and restrictions
and various things going on there in the state of California.
And so if you'd pray for Brother Mershon and his wife, Linda,
that God would just give them wisdom and direction with regard to their meeting schedule.
I know they'd greatly appreciate that.
And then also pray for Brother Hummel and Beacon of Truth.
And I spoke with Brother Hummel just the other day.
And they're doing well.
They had an assembly to start the year.
It was a Saturday assembly.
And then had church with that congregation on Sunday.
And a brand-new church, brand-new.
Actually, the church itself is only about two years old.
And it was their first time of having a scripture assembly.
And so that was exciting news to hear about a brand-new church
that's getting involved with the ministry.
And they had their first assembly.
And they enjoyed it so much that they said it's something that they want to do regularly,
such as what we have done.
And they're inquiring about purchasing staplers
and being able to get all of the supplies
and things that they need to do on a regular basis.
And so that was encouraging to me.
Obviously, very encouraging to Brother Hummel.
And so if you would pray for the Beacon of Truth Baptist Ministries, they have had some
meetings canceled that they had scheduled here in the first quarter of 2021.
So if you would pray for wisdom and then also they're seeking to get that facility completed
up in Bedford.
I know that Brother Hummel shared some things with you all when he was here back in December
and they are moving forward.
He was sharing with me kind of the timeline on some of the additional things that need
to be done.
But it's very exciting to hear about the work that's being done and the progress that's
taking place and looking forward to being able to hear about the completion of that
project and being able to schedule our first trip to go up to Bedford to put scriptures
together and to be a blessing and a help to the Beacon of Truth Baptist Ministries to
get the word of God around the world.
Continue to pray for the parsonage and the project is completing.
In fact, as we're recording here, this message, the men are out there working and they are
making good progress.
The trusses, it's my understanding, will be installed tomorrow and looking forward to
being able to see the structure just making more and more progress day by day.
And so thank you for your prayers for that project.
Let's go to the Lord in prayer as we'll have a time of offering and I do thank you for
your faithfulness and giving what a privilege it is to give to the Lord.
And let's pray.
Father, we thank you for the privilege of giving.
We thank you for the faithfulness of your people and Lord, we thank you and acknowledge
the plan that you have for the financing of the local church through the people of God.
And I pray that you'd help us to give cheerfully and appropriately, that you'd bless the gift
and giver.
Lord, that you'd use the funds for the furtherance of the ministry here and around the world.
For it's in Christ's name we pray, amen.
All right, we're going to sing our theme song, Complete in Thee.
Let's sing, All Your Anxiety.
Is there a heart, Lord, bound by sorrow?
Is there a life weighed down by care?
Come to the cross, each burden bearing.
All your anxiety, leave it there.
All your anxiety, all your care.
Bring to the mercy seat, leave it there.
Never a burden ye cannot bear.
Never a friend like Jesus.
No other friend so keen to help you.
No other friend so quick to hear.
No other place to leave your burden.
No other one to hear your prayer.
All your anxiety, all your care.
Bring to the mercy seat, leave it there.
Never a burden ye cannot bear.
Never a friend like Jesus.
Come and at once, delay no longer.
He is entreaty, kind and sweet.
You need not fear a disappointment.
You shall find peace at the mercy seat.
All your anxiety, all your care.
Bring to the mercy seat, leave it there.
Never a burden ye cannot bear.
Never a friend like Jesus.
Well, amen.
Both of those hymns were greatly encouraging to my heart today,
and I hope to yours as well.
And what a blessing to know that we can.
We have someone, our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ,
that we can take our burdens to and leave them with him.
You know, we're living in the midst of great anxiety.
We see, we hear of reports all around us of those that are dealing with anxiety,
and they're anxious over the things that are taking place in our world.
They're anxious for many reasons.
And I'm thankful as a child of God that though we're in the world, we're not of the world.
And I'm thankful that when the world seems as if it's falling apart,
that we can have that peace that passeth all understanding,
that we can rest in him knowing that he cares for us,
that we can take our anxiety, our cares,
and take it to the mercy seat and leave it there,
knowing that he is able to help.
I'm so thankful that the Bible teaches us
that our God is a very present help in the time of trouble.
He is our helper.
There are times in which maybe all we can do is say as the psalmist said,
Help, Lord!
And I'm thankful that he is able to help.
He's ready to help.
He is the creator of all things.
He spoke it all into existence.
He sustains it all by his own power.
And he's my God, my Savior.
What a blessing.
Romans chapter number 1 is where we'll be for our study here this evening.
I love to tell the story.
It will be the title of the message today.
And Romans chapter number 1.
And as we begin to kind of think of where we are with regard to our study here,
this is a doctrinal study that has been kind of a side study of the book of Titus.
We started a study in our adult Sunday school class through the book of Titus a number of months ago.
Actually, it's almost been a year ago,
but that was suspended for a period of time as we did not have Sunday school with the pandemic and what have you.
And then when we resumed our student ministries,
we returned to our study with here in the sanctuary on the book of Titus.
And Titus chapter 2 and verse number 1 says,
but speak now the things which become sound doctrine.
We understand the importance of doctrine.
We understand the source of doctrine.
And we've taken for now a number of weeks and looked at some doctrinal things.
In fact, we've been dealing with the doctrine of Christ and where we started our study on the doctrine of Christ was in Matthew chapter number 16.
It was in that passage of Scripture in which the Lord Jesus Christ speaking to his disciples.
He says, whom do men say that I, the son of man am?
And he asked that question, what a very important question, a pertinent question, no doubt.
We find that as they would hear the question and then give response that in their response,
it reveals to us that there was a level of confusion amongst the people in the day of Jesus's time.
We find that he had walked upon the earth.
His earthly ministry was moving forward.
And there were many that knew about Jesus.
They knew of the miracles that he had performed.
They heard about Jesus.
But unfortunately, there was some confusion with regard to who he is.
When he asked the question to the disciples, they say, well, some say that you're John the Baptist.
Some say that you're Jeremiah, Isaiah, one of the prophets, so on and so forth.
And through their response, we've noted and we've dealt with the confusion.
I've said this, that that same level of confusion exists today.
The question that Jesus asked to His disciples nearly 2,000 years ago is a question that
still needs to be asked today.
Who is Jesus?
Who is He?
Today the answers may vary from the answers that were given by the disciples on that particular
day.
And there would be some that would say, well, He's a teacher.
He's a prophet.
He's a good man.
There are various answers that may be provided.
But I'm thankful for what Peter stood and proclaimed, thou art the Christ, the Son of
the living God.
Why did Peter proclaim that?
Well, because Jesus said, whom do men say that I, the Son of Man, am?
And he received their answer and understood the confusion of the people.
But then he says, but whom say ye that I am?
And Peter proclaimed with confidence and courage that Jesus is the Messiah, the anointed one,
the promised one.
And what a joy it is to know Him.
What a privilege it is to know the Lord Jesus Christ, that He is God in flesh, that He is
my Savior.
We went and spent several weeks dealing with the subject matter from the song, Jesus is
all the world to me.
We asked the question, would you say that Jesus is all the world to you?
If you would, and someone were to say why, what would your answers be?
In no way was our study exhaustive.
We simply looked at a few reasons from the Word of God as to why we might say that Jesus
is all the world to me, because of who He is, because of His mighty power, because of
His death, burial, and resurrection, because of His work today, and because He's coming
back for me.
Oh, those are just a few reasons as to why Jesus is all the world to me.
But as we continue with the thought of the doctrine of Christ and understanding that
we as saved people would stand and proclaim that Jesus is all the world to me, that we
would know and could answer the question appropriately as Peter did, that we know that He, Jesus,
is the Christ, the Son of the living God, He's God in flesh.
There is a world of people that do not know who Jesus is.
They don't know Him.
Some know about Him.
Unfortunately, as we move further and further away from the truth of the Word of God, as
our society seeks to stamp out any references to God or Christianity, there are a number
of young people that they have no idea even about Jesus.
Thus, I love to tell the story.
It's a song that's very familiar to most of us.
In fact, we had the privilege of singing this song on Sunday.
And I just want to read one verse of the song as we get into the lesson.
It's verse number three where the Bible says,
I love to tell the story, tis pleasant to repeat.
What seems each time I tell it more wonderfully sweet.
I wonder if that's true for us.
Each time you tell the story of Jesus and His love, does it grow sweeter and sweeter?
You recognize what He did for you, how He saved your soul.
It continues, I love to tell the story, for some have never heard.
The message of salvation from God's own Holy Word.
I do not seek to correct the songwriter, but I would say that when it says for some have
never heard, it's probably more accurate to say many have never heard.
There are many in our world today that have never heard the message of salvation from
God's own Holy Word.
Therefore, we sing as the redeemed of the Lord, I love to tell the story.
And I wonder, do you love to tell the story?
If you love to tell the story, that would mean that you're telling the story.
Amen?
It's not fair for me or for any one of us to say I love to tell the story or to sing
I love to tell the story, and yet never tell the story.
That would be hypocrisy, but the reality is that we ought to love to tell the story because
it did so much for me, as the songwriter said in another one of the verses.
That story is the story of salvation, of Jesus and His love.
Notice with me in Romans chapter number one, we'll look at three verses of Scripture, verse
14, 15, and 16, and I will let you know it's in Bible study, so we'll be in a number of
different passages of Scripture, so get your fingers ready.
And as we look through these three verses, really they'll be used as our points for our
outline and our message this evening.
The Bible says this, Paul is speaking, it says in verse number 14, I am debtor both
to the Greeks and to the barbarians, both to the wise and to the unwise.
So as much as in me is, I am ready to preach the gospel to you that are at Rome also.
For I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ, for it is the power of God unto salvation,
to every one that believeth, to the Jew first and also to the Greek.
As we look at this passage of Scripture and use it as our basis for our outline in this
study, I love to tell the story.
I would say this, number one, we should recognize the privilege.
You know, it is a unique privilege that we have as the people of God to repeat the story,
the gospel of Jesus Christ.
What a unique privilege.
I understand it's a responsibility, and we must not forget that it is a responsibility.
It is a responsibility for every child of God to give the gospel.
The great commission, as I said on Sunday morning, is our mission.
The great commission is that we would go into the world and preach the gospel to every creature,
and that responsibility is laid upon every single person that has been born again.
It's our duty.
It's our responsibility.
But I would say as we consider the subject matter and think about this song, I love to
tell the story, could I help you and help myself understand that it is a privilege,
and we need to recognize the privilege that God would give us to be the bearers of good
news, that God would use us to be the servants, the individuals to proclaim the gospel message.
Think about those shepherds.
I preached about them back in December.
Those shepherds, we examined the passage of Scripture, and we observed some things
about those shepherds, and they received that message unto you.
There was some good news of glad tidings, and that message was given to them, but it
was to be to all people.
What a privilege was theirs to go and share with others the message that they had received.
And we note that in verse number 14 of Romans 1, Paul says, notice what he says, I am debtor
both to the Greeks and the barbarians, both to the wise and to the unwise.
See, we need to recognize the privilege that is ours to tell the story.
I want you to remember of what the disciples said, turn back to the book of Acts, if you
will, in chapter number 5.
In Acts chapter number 5, early on in the advancement of the gospel in Jerusalem, many
wonderful things are taking place, but there's opposition, persecution, threats, beatings,
all sorts of things, imprisonment, all these things going on.
But I want you to notice and remember what the disciples say.
In Acts chapter number 5, in verse number 28, the accusers, the opposition, they said
this to the disciples, did not, we straightly command you that you should not teach in this
name.
And behold, ye have failed.
You filled Jerusalem with Your doctrine
and intend to bring this man's blood upon us.
Oh, that it would be said that we filled
our Jerusalem with the teaching of Jesus Christ,
with the Gospel.
Oh, what a blessing I'm told
of a church in California
that is so consistent on getting into their community
to preach the Gospel and to share the Gospel
with their community.
They have a purpose and a plan,
a strategy if you will,
to reach their community.
And they've been so committed and so faithful
that there are people within the community
that have made signs and put on their doors,
if you're from such-and-such a Baptist church,
we're not interested.
I like it.
I don't like that the people aren't interested.
But what I like is that the church
has taken the responsibility
and the privilege of going with a system
and with a plan
and strategically going to reach their community.
What a blessing.
It says in v. 29 of Acts 5,
then Peter and the other apostles answered and said,
we ought to obey God rather than men.
The God of our fathers raised up Jesus
from Yisra'el and hanged on a tree.
Him hath God exalted with His right hand
to be a Prince and a Savior
for to give repentance to Israel
and forgiveness of sins.
And v. 32, we are His witnesses of these things.
We're His witnesses.
They were eyewitnesses.
They were the witnesses
and we are witnesses.
And what a privilege to be a witness
to go and to proclaim the message,
the story, the greatest story ever told.
The story of Jesus and His love.
The story of redemption
through the blood of Christ.
And we're privileged to be able to take that message.
Paul says to the believers in 2 Corinthians 5
that we're ambassadors.
You know, to be an ambassador is a privileged position.
And as the children of God,
God calls us as His people
because we are ambassadors.
We understand that our citizenship is in heaven.
I'm a pilgrim and a stranger.
I'm not home, but I'm going home.
This world is not my home,
as the songwriter said.
Jesus said that we're in the world,
but we're not of the world.
And we understand that we are ambassadors.
We've been entrusted with a responsibility
and it is a privilege
to represent the Lord Jesus Christ.
Notice what Paul says in 1 Corinthians 9.
You'll notice two statements of Paul.
One here in 1 Corinthians
and then another over in 1 Thessalonians.
But notice what Paul says in 1 Corinthians 9
when we consider and recognize the privilege.
I love to tell the story.
It is a privilege to tell the story.
To proclaim the Gospel.
That God would use us.
Paul says this in 1 Corinthians 9
verse 16 and 17,
"'For though I preach the Gospel,
I have nothing to glory of,
for necessity is laid upon me.
Yea, woe is unto me
if I preach not the Gospel.
For if I do this thing willingly,
I have a reward.
But if against my will,
a dispensation of the Gospel
is committed unto me.'"
Paul says,
"'Woe is unto me if I preach not the Gospel.'"
He says,
"'If I do this thing willingly,
I have a reward.'"
It's a privilege to take the Gospel.
We notice what Paul says
in 1 Thessalonians 2.
Take and turn over that passage if you will.
Paul had the privilege of going
into the town of Thessalonica
and delivering the Gospel.
Seeing a church established.
Best we can tell,
he was not there for any lengthy period of time.
He spent a significant amount of time
in Ephesus and in Corinth,
but in Thessalonica,
he was not able to spend much time there
because of the opposition.
But I want you to notice what he says.
And focus upon the verbage,
the terminology that Paul uses
when he's speaking to these individuals
in verse 1 of chapter 2.
It says,
"'For yourselves, brethren,
know our entrance in unto you
that it was not in vain.'"
By the way,
if we consider that last phrase
of verse 1,
and we couple it with 1 Corinthians 15
and verse 58,
our work is not in vain in the Lord.
Amen?
He says,
"'Our entrance in unto you
that it was not in vain.'"
Listen, there are times
in which you might take the Gospel to somebody
and you think,
man, they weren't interested.
And you walk away perhaps discouraged,
but you have to understand
that as Paul said to the believers in Corinth,
that some plant some water,
but God gives the increase.
The Holy Spirit of God
is able to use the Word of God
and work in the heart of the individual.
He says,
"'It was not in vain.'"
Verse 2,
"'But even after that we had suffered before
and were shamefully entreated,
as you know, at Philippi,
we were bold in our God
to speak unto you
the Gospel of God with much contention.'"
And so they had boldness
in spite of this continued persecution
that they were dealing with.
If you go back to the book of Acts
and you read in Acts 16 and 17
and read all that was taking place
in Philippi and Thessalonica
as he references those two places
in particular here in these verses of Scripture,
you find that he says
that even in light of those things,
we were bold in our God.
Now that's important for us to understand.
We go in the power of the Holy Spirit of God.
It's Jesus Christ that gave the commission
and said, I will be with you.
It says this in verse 3,
"'For our exhortation was not of deceit
nor of uncleanness, nor in guile.'"
Notice this phrase,
"'But,' in verse 4,
"'as we were allowed of God
to be put in trust with the Gospel,
even so we speak,
not as pleasing men,
but God which trieth our hearts.'"
You notice what he says
in the beginning of verse 4,
"'But as we were allowed of God
to be put in trust with the Gospel.'"
You understand that God has allowed us
to be put in trust with the Gospel?
The church, as Paul is writing to Timothy,
is the pillar and ground of the truth.
And as individual believers,
we've been allowed of God.
He's given us this privilege.
Paul says, I am debtor.
I am privileged.
When I think about the song,
when I think about the question
that Jesus asked
and the confusion that existed
in the day of Christ,
and I think about the world
in which we currently live
and the confusion that exists
with regard to the question,
who is Jesus?
I'm mindful of the fact that God
has given us the privilege
of not only knowing Him,
but the privilege of preaching the Gospel,
of telling the story.
What a joy.
I recognize the privilege.
And then I would say this, number two,
we need to make it a priority.
We need to make it a priority.
A priority to tell the story.
I mean, we need to plan to tell it.
We need to have a plan.
We need to have an approach.
We need to have it as a priority.
It must be upon our minds. Why?
Because if it's not,
we're not going to do it.
It's not going to happen by accident.
We have to plan for it.
By the way, we plan for things
that are important.
Mostly.
We understand the process of planning.
There are some people that are planners
and they are very extensive
in their planning.
I heard recently someone said
that people spend more time
in a calendar year planning
for their annual vacation
than they spend planning anything
with regard to their walk with God.
Wow.
See, we need to plan.
We need to make it a priority.
We have organized outreach
as a church family
where we systematically, strategically
seek to reach our community.
And that's important.
Something to be part of.
Something that you're planning
and making a priority.
I'm going to put this time on my schedule,
on my calendar to go and make Christ known.
But then in your everyday life,
we just make it a priority
that I'm looking for opportunities.
I'm asking God to give me opportunities
to tell the story,
to share with others what Christ did for me
and what He could do for them.
Notice, back in Romans 1,
Paul says this in v. 15,
So, as much as in me is,
I am ready to preach the Gospel
to you that are at Rome also.
He says I am ready.
And that's where I get this idea
of making it a priority
of planning to give the Gospel
and to be a witness
that we would not only ask God
to give us the opportunities
and pray that He would open up doors
open up opportunities that we'd be looking for those opportunities and then
that we would seize those opportunities to tell the story, to preach Christ. Go
back to the book of Acts, if you will, in chapter 17. In Acts chapter number 17,
this is the account in which they arrive in Thessalonica. We just mentioned in
1 Thessalonians chapter number 2 of the entrance into. But I want you to just
note a few things about the terminology that God gives us as Paul would enter
into the city of Thessalonica and as we would see that he made it a priority in
his life to tell the story, to preach the gospel. In Acts 17 and verse number 1, the
Bible says, Now when they had passed through Amphipolis and Apollonia, they
came to Thessalonica where was a synagogue of the Jews. And Paul, notice
this phrase, as his manner was. Went in unto them and three Sabbath days
reasoned with them out of the Scriptures, opening and alleging that Christ must
needs have suffered and risen again from the dead. And that this Jesus whom I
preach unto you is Christ. We notice what it was that he preached, it was the
gospel. But we notice that little phrase in verse number 2, as his manner was.
When Paul got into a new city, what was at the top of his list? Paul, what is it
that you want to do in this city? What is it that you want to set out to
accomplish? I want to go find out where there's some people assembled so I can
give them the truth of the gospel. We understand that in Philippi there was no
synagogue that was there, and so he goes and he finds Lydia and those that were
gathered over by the river. You can read of that in Acts chapter number 16. In Acts
chapter number 17, when they get to Thessalonica, there is a synagogue that's
established. There were enough Jewish men in that city to establish a synagogue. So
what does Paul do? As his manner was, he's going to where they are and he's going
to meet with them, and he's going to reason with them out of the Scriptures.
He's going to tell them how that Christ must needs have suffered. He goes back to
the Old Testament, he talks about the prophecies of the Messiah that would
come, and the suffering that he would endure, and how that he would pay for the
sin of mankind. And he says that this Jesus whom I preach unto you is Christ.
And he's made it a priority. He's going to preach Christ as his manner was. The
people that were upset with Paul in Philippi send a group of people over to
Thessalonica, and man, there's all kinds of trouble that's brewing, and Paul is
sent to leave, and the Bible tells us in verse 14, and then
immediately the brethren sent away Paul to go, as it were, to the sea. But Silas
and Timotheus abode there still, and they that conducted Paul brought him unto
Athens, receiving a commandment unto Silas and Timotheus for to come to him
with all speed they departed. Now while Paul waited for them at Athens, his
spirit was stirred in him when he saw the city wholly given to idolatry. Paul
is there, and he's in Athens because of all the trouble that he's endured, and
they send him there in order to really kind of get some R&R, if you will, if we
could use that terminology, and to be removed from all of the persecution and
things that were taking place, and the the anger of the individuals. And the
Bible tells us in verse number 5 of Acts 17 that the Jews, which believed not
moved with envy, took unto them certain lewd fellows of the baser sort, gathered
a company, set all the city on an uproar, and assaulted the house of Jason, sought
to bring them out to the sea. I mean, it was a big deal. So Paul is now in
Athens, and as he's in Athens, he sees a city that's wholly given to idolatry. The
Bible says, therefore, in verse 17, disputed he in the synagogue with the
Jews, and with the devout persons, and in the market daily with them that met with
him. It was a priority for Paul. It was a priority. We won't take the time, but as you
go through the pages of the book of Acts, and you trace the steps of the Apostle
Paul, you'll find that he had opportunity to stand before the Sanhedrin, and then
he has opportunity. I call it opportunity because God allowed for it to happen. It
was under difficult circumstances, adverse situations, but he stood before
Felix, and he stood before Festus, and he stood before Agrippa. What does he do? He shares the
gospel. It was a priority for Paul. Do you understand that Paul's number one
priority was not to get released? That wasn't his number one priority. Now, that
might have been my number one priority. It may have been your number one
priority. Hey, it's not fair that I'm in these chains, in these bonds. It's not
fair that I'm in this position where I'm in. No, no, his number one priority was to
seize the opportunity to understand that God had him there in that place, and he
had an audience. He had an opportunity to preach Christ, and he made it a priority
in his life. The church in Thessalonica, we've mentioned much about them in this,
our second point of our study, but the church in Thessalonica made it a
priority as well. As the Bible tells us in 1 Thessalonians 1, gives us some
insight about the church in Thessalonica and their fervency in giving the gospel.
It says in verse 7 and 8 of 1 Thessalonians 1, so that you were in
samples to all that believe in Macedonia and Achaia. For from you sounded out the
word of the Lord, not only in Macedonia and Achaia, but also in every place your
faith to God were to spread abroad, so that we need not to speak anything.
That's encouraging, that there is a local church that was involved, engaged in
preaching the gospel. Just as the Apostle Paul had made it a priority, as soon as
he gets into the city of Thessalonica, he goes to the synagogue and he meets with
the Jews and he begins to reason with them out of the scriptures and he
gives them the truth of the gospel, he preaches Christ. It was a priority for
Paul and those people that got saved. The Bible tells us, I read the passage that
talked about the ones that believe not, but the Bible says in verse 4 of Acts 17,
and some of them believed. There was a church that was established and that
church, those individual believers, they then made it a priority to preach the
gospel, to give the truth, to say as the songwriter said, I love to tell the
story. Can I tell you what Jesus did for me? Can I tell you how Jesus changed my
life? Can I tell you how much he loves you and what he'd like to do for you? See,
we recognize the privilege and then we make it a priority. Finally, if you're
taking notes, recognize the power. Recognize the power. Back in Romans
chapter number 1, Paul has said, I am debtor in verse 14. He says in verse
number 15, I am ready. And in verse number 16 he says, for I am not ashamed. I'm not
ashamed of the gospel of Christ. Why? For it, the gospel of Christ, is the power of
God unto salvation to everyone that believeth, to the Jew first and also to
the Greek. If I could make just a side note statement with regard to verse
number 16, we'll focus upon the power of the gospel and I'm so thankful and it's
so important that we recognize the power, but can I say to you that we need not to
be ashamed of the gospel of Christ. It's becoming more and more common in our
society that people would say to us, well you shouldn't talk about that and you
shouldn't share your opinions and so on and so forth. Listen, let's not be ashamed
of the gospel of Jesus Christ. I hope that we would have, even as we've looked
and traced some things about the Apostle Paul, that we'd have the same
perspective. That we understand the message of the gospel. We understand what
it's done for us. We understand the privilege that is ours. We've made it a
priority. See, I'm not gonna be ashamed. I understand that not everyone's gonna
listen to me. I wish everyone would. I wish people understood the, just the
power of the message that we have and how liberating it is and how important
it is. Listen, there's a world in darkness. They're in darkness. They need what we
have. I understand that they don't think they need it. I understand they're not
aware of the fact that they need what we have, but biblically speaking we know
that they do. And this message is powerful. It is the power of God unto
salvation.
to everyone that believeth,
to the Jew first and also to the Greek.
We read, as we started the book of Colossians,
on Sunday morning in verse number 6 of chapter 1,
how that the gospel produces fruit.
It's powerful.
We understand, as we would read the truth
and often quote the reference in 2 Corinthians 5
in verse number 17,
if any man be in Christ, he's a new creature.
The power of the gospel.
I want you to consider what Paul says in Galatians 1
about his own testimony.
And this, of course, is written to the churches in Galatia,
those churches and those cities
during the first missionary journey.
I preached about that a little bit on Sunday evening
about the church in Antioch
and how they were used to send forth the first missionaries.
They go to Antioch and Pisidia, Iconium, Lystra, Derbe.
And here in Galatians 1,
notice what Paul says in verse number 22.
The Bible says this,
and was unknown by face unto the churches of Judea,
which were in Christ.
But that, it says this,
but they, those believers in Judea,
they had heard only that He,
which persecuted us in times past,
now preacheth the faith
which once He destroyed,
and they glorified God in me.
Paul understood the power of the gospel in his own life.
He knew what Christ did for him.
And I would submit that you know what Christ did for you.
You know the power of the gospel.
I talk to people sometimes,
but it's just not, I just can't be saved.
It's just not for me.
It's just, you know, you don't know what I've done.
You don't know what a sinner I am,
and so on and so forth.
And I often think of what the songwriter said.
I don't know what a sinner you are,
but I know what a Savior He is.
The Apostle Paul testifies
that He was the chief of all sinners.
That Christ Jesus came into the world
to save sinners of whom I am chief.
That's what Paul said.
And we understand the power of the gospel.
And Paul said, if you know, in verse 23 of Galatians 1,
if you know the contrast in times past,
now preacheth the faith.
What He was and now what He is
because of the power of the gospel.
Go back to the book of Acts, if you will.
We'll close here in Acts chapter number nine.
And I just want to read a few verses to you
about the conversion of Paul.
We know that his name is still Saul
here in Acts chapter number nine.
It would be changed to Paul in Acts chapter number 13
during that first missionary journey.
And here in Acts nine, we read of the conversion.
And I want to read a couple of verses
at the beginning of Acts nine,
and then I'm going to skip to verse number 20.
And I want you to see the difference.
It says in verse number one of Acts nine,
and Saul, yet breathing out threatenings and slaughter
against the disciples of the Lord,
went unto the high priest
and desired of him letters to Damascus, to the synagogues,
that if he found any of this way,
whether they were men or women,
he might bring them bound unto Jerusalem.
Paul was going with a mission.
He was trying to stamp out
these that were following Christ.
We'll skip the next several verses
that rehearse for us and record for us his conversion,
because I want you to see what the Bible tells us
in verse number 19 and 20.
It says, and when he, Paul, Saul,
that is his name here at this time,
when he had received me, he was strengthened,
then with Saul certain days with the disciples
which were at Damascus,
and straightway he preached Christ in the synagogues
that he is the Son of God.
What happened to this man, Saul?
I mean, he's breathing out threatenings.
I mean, he's ready to go to Damascus.
He's received letters in order to have the authority
to arrest those that would be of this way,
that he could take them and bring them bound
back to Jerusalem, and yet then we find
that he's preaching Christ in the synagogues,
that he is the Son of God.
Well, the Gospel's powerful.
Along the way on the road to Damascus,
there was a bright light that shined from heaven.
And here's a voice, Saul, Saul,
why persecutest thou me?
And Saul says, who art thou, Lord?
Jesus says, I am Jesus, whom thou persecutest.
And Saul would then say, Lord, he, Lord,
what wilt thou have me to do?
He recognized that Jesus is Lord.
In fact, the Bible tells us Paul would be used of God
to pen the words in the book of Philippians
that we've often mentioned, that in the name of Jesus,
every knee should bow, things in heaven,
and things in earth, and things under the earth,
and every tongue should confess that Jesus Christ is Lord
to the glory of God the Father.
Saul confessed that in Acts 9.
He understood the power of the Gospel.
Why is it that we love to tell the story?
Well, it's a privilege.
I am debtor.
I'm allowed of God.
We need to make it a priority to tell the story.
We need to plan to do so.
This year, maybe after this message,
you should sit down and ask the Lord to help you
to devise a plan on how you're gonna get the Gospel out.
Maybe when you come to church on Sunday,
you need to grab a handful of Gospel tracts.
We have them in our lobby,
available for you to take and distribute.
Maybe you wanna take some John and Romans this year
and share them with your neighbors.
However the Lord might impress upon your heart,
but make it a priority.
Plan to get the Gospel out,
and then recognize the power of the Gospel.
What did it do for you?
Changed my life.
The day in my life when my direction changed entirely,
just as it did for Saul in Acts 9.
I didn't go and straightway preach the Gospel
as quickly as he did,
but my life was changed.
It was a new creature because of the power of the Gospel.
And we understand that the Gospel has the power
still today to change lives.
Jesus saves, we sing the song.
And what a great song it is.
Jesus saves, he does.
But they need to know about the Savior.
Oh, that God would help us
to take the Gospel to every creature.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the privilege,
once again, of studying your Word.
What a joy to have the Bible.
I pray, God, that you would help us
as we consider the content of this message.
Help us to recognize the privilege
of sharing the Gospel of Jesus Christ.
Help us, God, to make it a priority.
Help us to recognize the power
of this message that we proclaim.
I pray that as you would work in our hearts individually
and as a church corporately,
God, we would see many souls saved this year.
I pray that you'd move and work as only you can.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Amen.