This is our 18th lesson on this subject matter
of walk worthy, please God.
And we've mentioned as we've studied
through this fifth chapter of the book of 1 Thessalonians,
we started in verse number 12,
this evening we'll finish the chapter.
And as we first started this series on Wednesday evenings,
I mentioned that we'll study the fifth chapter,
the last portion of the fifth chapter of 1 Thessalonians.
And then once we're done there,
we'll go over to 2 Thessalonians chapter number three
and look at the latter portion of that text.
In both of those portions of scripture,
we find that God would use the Apostle Paul
to give instruction to the local church.
As this instruction is given to the local church,
the church at Thessalonica,
we understand that God has provided this instruction
so that the believers would have that information,
they'd understand what is acceptable unto the Lord,
and they would strive to walk worthy and please God.
As we close this book,
we find, I believe, three elements of a healthy church.
If you're taking notes tonight,
I've titled the message this evening, A Healthy Church.
The goal of every believer, every individual believer,
the goal that you should have
is that you would please the Lord with your life.
How do we please the Lord?
We live a life that is aligned
with the principles of God's word.
Healthy believers make a healthy church.
And you're not gonna have a healthy church
with unhealthy believers.
And so we strive to have a church
that would be referred to as being a healthy church.
And if we're going to have a healthy church as individuals,
we must be healthy believers.
We must be taking and applying the truth of God's word
into our lives.
Last week, we dealt with intercessory prayer from verse 25,
where the Bible simply says, brethren, pray for us.
This week, we'll look at verses 26 through 28,
look at these three elements of a healthy church.
The Bible says this,
greet all the brethren with an holy kiss.
I charge you by the Lord that this epistle be read
unto all the holy brethren.
The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you, amen.
Number one this evening, a healthy church is unified.
A healthy church is unified.
Notice what the Bible says in verse 26,
greet all the brethren with an holy kiss.
We understand the book of Ephesians tells us
that we ought to strive for unity.
We must have that desire,
endeavoring to keep the unity of the spirit
and the bond of peace,
according to Ephesians chapter four in verse number three.
We find that in verse number 13 here,
1 Thessalonians five, the last phrase says,
and be at peace among yourselves.
And so now we come to verse number 26,
and the Bible says greet all the brethren with an holy kiss.
And I say that a healthy church is a unified church.
And we find that this particular greeting
that is mentioned in verse number 26
was obviously culturally accepted
for this area in Thessalonica.
In fact, today in many parts of the world,
this would still be a greeting
that would be culturally appropriate.
Now here in the United States of America,
if you grew up here,
we're not greeting one another with an holy kiss.
But the reality is that we might shake hands,
we might give a hug, whatever it might be.
But we understand that as we look at this verse of scripture
and we see the unity in this culturally appropriate greeting
but what I really want you to focus on
when I think about and the reason
that I give the point of unity
is that the Bible says notice that little word all.
Greet all the brethren with an holy kiss.
See, the local church is made up
of saved baptized believers, individuals.
When a person comes and they say,
hey, pastor, I would like to join the church.
My first question is tell me about when you got saved.
Let me understand your testimony of salvation.
And then after I hear the testimony of salvation,
talk to me about when you were scripturally baptized.
The local church is made up of individuals
but those individuals that are members of the local church
are to be saved and baptized scripturally.
We find that with that truth
that we are brothers and sisters in Christ.
We are a family.
And we find here that God likens the church
in the book of First Corinthians to a body.
And you think about the picture,
the imagery if you will of a body
and he talks about the church being a body
that's fitly joined together.
And you find this evening that when Paul is writing
to this church in Thessalonica,
he's already spoken to them
about the importance of brotherly love.
He's already spoken to them
about the importance of loving one another.
Turn back to the fourth chapter if you will
and look at verse nine and also in verse number 10.
And we see that the apostle Paul deals with this subject
of brotherly love.
Now remember the Lord Jesus Christ in John chapter 13
said a new commandment I give unto you.
What was that commandment?
That you love one another,
not as you would love yourself, Old Testament,
but as I have loved, New Testament.
And we find that he then says this,
the Lord Jesus Christ says by this, by what?
Your love one for another,
that all men are gonna know that you are my disciples.
And so we find here that Paul is writing
to this local church in the fourth chapter
and notice in verse nine, he says,
but as touching brotherly love,
notice what he says, ye need not that I write unto you.
Why?
For ye yourselves are taught of God to love one another
and then notice this statement in verse number 10,
he commends them.
He says, and indeed ye do it toward,
notice this phrase, all the brethren,
which are in all Macedonia,
but we beseech you brethren,
notice what he says, that ye increase more and more.
Don't get comfortable with where you are,
don't allow yourself to become stagnant, no increase.
We find that he says, the apostle Paul,
he commends them as he talks about brotherly love,
he says that indeed you do it toward all the brethren.
Now, as we come to the fifth chapter, this closing section,
he says, greet all the brethren with an holy kiss.
And so we find when we think about the unity
of the local church and we understand
that a healthy church is a unified church, why?
Because we have no differences of our backgrounds,
our upbringings, our personalities,
no, it's because we're unified in Christ.
It's because we take and we embrace the truth of God's word
and it is God that gives unity.
We find this evening that as we would consider
where the apostle Paul says,
greet all the brethren with an holy kiss,
I believe that that statement helps us to understand
that there are to be no cliques, no clubs.
See, sometimes you think about a church
and if you're not careful,
church can kind of have its little groups of people,
its little cliques, quote unquote,
if you want to use that terminology,
but the reality is that we are a family.
We're brothers and sisters in Christ
and we're to greet all the brethren.
Does it mean that we might not have a personal draw
to some individuals more than others
because of some of those personality type things?
Sure, that might be the case,
but not at the expense of excluding others.
Does that make sense this evening?
And so we find that as a church, a healthy church,
there's gonna be a church that's unified
where he says greet all the brethren with an holy kiss.
Why?
Because we're all part of the family of God.
We're all part of the local church.
We're all brothers and sisters in Christ
and I think about the truth again
and as we mentioned a moment ago
at the end of verse number 13
where the Bible says and be at peace among yourselves
and as we looked at that text of scripture
several weeks ago, we talked about
the responsibility of the local church,
the responsibility of the pastor,
but also the responsibility of the local church
and how we're to have that peace.
There's to be no divisions
and to be no schisms amongst the body.
The church in Corinth is obviously corrected
because of their divisions and because of their schisms
and by the way, what was one of the main causes
of those schisms and divisions?
I'm of Paul, I'm of Apollos, I'm of Cephas, right?
And so what are they doing?
They're having these cliques,
these little segmented sections, if you will,
of no, no, Paul says greet all the brethren
with an holy kiss.
A healthy church is gonna be a church
that has unity, that is unified.
Number two, I would say this,
a healthy church places a priority on the scriptures.
A healthy church places a priority on the scriptures.
See, in verse number 27,
notice what the Bible says, I charge you.
Now this phraseology is important for us to understand.
Paul is not making a suggestion here.
Paul is really giving a command.
He says, I charge you.
I'm giving you this instruction.
Now remember when he began in verse number.
12, this closing section, he says, we beseech you.
We noticed in verse number 14, he says, we exhort you.
But now in verse number 27, he says, I charge you.
It's not just a suggestion.
See, the reality is that the church
is the pillar and ground of the truth.
And we find that he says, I charge you by the Lord.
What's the charge, what's the command?
That this epistle be read unto all the holy brethren.
So again, we see the reference to all,
not some segmented group within the church,
not the quote unquote religious leaders
or the clergy, the pastors.
No, we find that it's to be read
unto all the holy brethren.
See, God's word is for every believer.
It's for every person.
God so loved the world.
We understand the truth of that declaration in John 3, 16.
And God says that the entrance of his words giveth light.
I'm so thankful for the impact that this book,
the Bible, has made in my life.
I'm so thankful that the entrance of thy words giveth light.
I'm thankful, the truth that we find
in 2 Corinthians chapter number four,
the fact that the God of this world
hath blinded the minds of them which believe not,
lest the light of the glorious gospel
should shine in unto them.
And we find that the Bible continues in that text
and says that we have this treasure in earthen vessels.
And if our gospel be hid, it says previous,
it's hid to them that are lost.
And so we find that a healthy church
not only is gonna have unity,
is gonna be a unified church,
but we find that a healthy church
places a priority on the scriptures.
Paul gives a charge to Timothy
at the end of 2 Timothy in the fourth chapter.
Right after he gives that great declaration
about all scripture is given by inspiration of God,
and it's profitable, and he goes through
and he gives this wonderful declaration
about the means by which we receive this book, the Bible.
Through inspiration, it's God's word.
And then he says, preach the word, preach the word.
The pastor has the responsibility,
according to 1 Peter 5, to feed the flock of God.
What does it mean to feed the flock of God?
It doesn't mean that we set up a buffet every week
and have various types of entrees for you to partake.
No, it means that the preacher, the pastor,
he has a responsibility to take this book,
to study it himself, to develop, to understand,
and then to teach and to preach God's word.
In the book of Ezra, we find that the Bible teaches us
really a pattern that they read the word of God distinctly,
they gave the sense and made the people,
caused the people to understand it.
That's the responsibility of the preacher.
The Bible talks about there when the first deacons,
if you will, in Acts chapter number six
and all that was taking place,
and you find that Peter and the others,
they stand and they say, listen,
it's not reason that we should leave the word of God
and serve tables, no, what were they gonna do?
They were gonna give themselves continually to prayer
and to the ministry of the word.
And so we find here that when Paul says,
I charge you by the Lord that this epistle be read
unto all the holy brethren.
Now we understand today in 2024,
that this book is part of the canon of scripture.
And so just as this letter,
this epistle was written to a local church,
it's God's word, it's been preserved,
it's part of the canon of scripture,
and it's to be read and it has been read
through the centuries to local churches.
And believers have been helped by the context,
the content, excuse me, of this book, this epistle.
And so Paul says that this book, this epistle
is to be read unto all the holy brethren.
I'm thankful for God's word.
Someone asked me years ago,
and I'd only been pre-pastoring here for just a few years,
and they said, you know,
how do you come up with these messages?
And it was actually, it was a legitimate, you know,
question that the individual had.
And I said, well, you know,
if it was up to me to come up with the content,
I'd have run out a long time ago.
But God has given me the responsibility
to simply preach his word.
And so I go to God's word and I study it
and I seek to understand it so that I then can come
and deliver to preach the word.
I'm thankful that God has given us his word.
Could you imagine if we didn't have the Bible?
Man, everything that you know about God
is because we have a Bible.
The Bible tells us that the heavens
declare the glory of God.
You might be able to see from creation that there is a God,
but you would not know the attributes of God
by simply looking at creation.
I'm thankful that this book provides for us
all that we need to know.
The Bible says that he's given us all things
that pertain unto life and godliness.
As we look back in the beginning of 1 Thessalonians
in the first chapter, we find that in verse number one
that Paul says that he's writing Paul and Silvanus
and Timotheus unto the church of the Thessalonians.
He says in verse number two,
we give thanks to God always, notice this,
for you all, making mention of you in our prayers.
And so Paul was writing under the inspiration
of the Holy Spirit of God to the entire church
and to every believer, and he says he gives this charge
that this epistle be read unto all the holy brethren.
It wasn't to be reserved for just a certain group
within the church, it wasn't to have this distinction
between clergy and laity, if you will,
and to say no, you can't read the Bible.
No, he says it's to be read, it's to be read.
And I'm thankful.
A healthy church is a church that places a priority
on the scriptures.
The truth of the matter is that when a church
deviates from God's word, when a church doesn't have
an emphasis placed upon the preaching and teaching
of God's word, it really just becomes
any other kind of club, entertainment.
The reality is that God's given us this book
and it's profitable and it is to be a priority
in our church.
I love preaching and teaching the Bible, I love the Bible.
And the reality is that I enjoy singing, I love to sing,
and I love fellowship and prayer and so on and so forth,
but when we come together, we need to have the preaching
of God's word, because it's God's word that changes life,
that changes lives.
I remember reading a billboard many years ago
in Lancaster County, Pennsylvania, said many books
can inform, but only the Bible can transform.
That was a powerful statement, one that set in my mind
that I remember all these years later.
So we find that Paul says, greet all the brethren
with a holy kiss, this unity that should be evident
in a church that is a healthy church.
He continues and says, I charge you by the Lord
that this epistle be read unto all the holy brethren,
a priority that is placed upon the scriptures.
Number three, in verse number 28, a healthy church
acknowledges their need for God's grace.
Where would we be without the grace of God?
Aren't you thankful tonight that our God is gracious?
Oh, he's so gracious.
We find that the Bible concludes, as in fact,
many of the epistles, as you study through
the New Testament, he says in verse 28,
the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you, amen.
We sing Amazing Grace, of course, Don and I haven't been
here for a number of months now with health issues,
but Mr. Don's favorite song, Amazing Grace,
it's got a tie that has the words of the song,
and I know I've said it before, but anytime you get
into the 180s, Amazing Grace in our hymnal is 187,
you sing any other number in the 180s,
and you can hear Mr. Don say, why not 187?
And, well, because there's some other good songs
in the 180s in our songbook, but the reality is that
God's grace is amazing.
We ought to be thankful tonight for the grace of God.
We understand tonight that we're saved by grace,
for by grace are you saved through faith.
Wow, the saving grace of God.
I'm thankful tonight that our God is gracious.
We find that not only are we saved by grace,
but we find that it's the grace of God
that enables us to serve.
We find that as we were to look through the scriptures,
as we begin to understand in 1 Corinthians 15,
in verse number 10, the apostle Paul says,
he says this, by the grace of God, I am what I am.
We find that as you.
and Peter talks about serving, and the spiritual gifts,
as every man hath received the gift,
even so let him minister.
And then he says this, it's in 1 Peter chapter four
in verse number 10, if you wanna jot it down.
He says this, as good stewards
of the manifold grace of God.
God's gifted every believer.
It's a biblical truth.
1 Corinthians deals with it, Romans deals with it.
We find 1 Peter, that Peter's dealing with it.
In every believer, if you're born again this evening,
you have been given a spiritual gift,
and God says that as we understand the spiritual gift
that he has given to us, that we are to be good stewards
of the manifold grace of God.
I wanna be a good steward of God's grace
that has been bestowed upon me.
Not simply the saving grace, but again,
the grace of God that enables us to serve him.
I think about God's grace, and we understand,
I mentioned a moment ago about it being amazing.
You understand that the Apostle Paul
in 1 Timothy one, in verse number 14,
he speaks of the grace of God,
and he refers to it this way, that it's exceeding abundant.
I like that phraseology.
God's grace is exceeding abundant.
But I want you to think about this aspect as well,
when we consider that a healthy church
acknowledges their need for God's grace.
We understand that it's God's grace that saves us,
it's God's grace that enables us.
Again, Paul says in 1 Corinthians 15, 10,
but by the grace of God, I am what I am.
See, God's grace has been bestowed upon us.
He continues and says this in that verse of scripture
in 1 Corinthians 15, 10, and his grace,
which was bestowed upon me, was not in vain,
but I labored more abundantly than they all,
yet not I, but the grace of God which was with me.
And so we think about the coupling of this truth
in Paul's testimony in 1 Corinthians 15, 10,
coupled with 1 Peter four in verse number 10
that we're to be good stewards
of the manifold grace of God.
I believe that the Apostle Paul was a good steward
of the grace of God that had been bestowed upon him.
This evening, we too must be good stewards.
We recognize that where would we be
without the grace of God?
I mean, we understand that we wouldn't be saved
without the grace of God,
but then you think about his grace that enables us to serve.
How could we serve him without his grace?
A healthy church recognizes,
acknowledges their need for God's grace,
and I believe that's why the Apostle Paul closes
so many of the epistles with the reminder
of the grace of God, be with you,
because it's a reminder that we need God's grace.
We need his grace every day in our lives.
I want you to consider also,
when we think about the grace of God,
recognize tonight that God's grace is sufficient.
2 Corinthians chapter 12 is a passage of scripture
that is familiar to many of us,
and oftentimes we will quote a portion
of this scripture, of this passage.
We find that the Apostle Paul
in 2 Corinthians chapter 12,
he's giving a testimony,
and he talks about a vision,
and this vision that he had,
and he says in verse number four
how that he was caught up into paradise
and heard unspeakable words,
which it is not lawful for a man to utter.
Of such in one will I glory,
yet of myself I will not glory,
but in mine infirmities, verse six,
for though I would desire to glory,
I should not be a fool,
for I will say the truth,
but now I forbear,
lest any man should think of me above that
which he seeth me to be,
or that he heareth of me.
And lest I should be exalted above measure
through the abundance of the revelations.
Notice what Paul says.
He recognizes that he could have got prideful
because of the abundance of the revelations.
He said in verse six,
for though I would desire to glory.
Why?
That's just a fleshly human tendency.
When you got saved,
when I got saved,
when Paul got saved,
the flesh wasn't eradicated.
The flesh has to be crucified,
and so your flesh still has desires,
your flesh still has those,
and he says though I would desire to glory,
I should not be a fool.
He says that through these abundance of revelations,
that though and lest I should be exalted above measure
through the abundance of the revelations,
verse seven,
notice what he says,
there was given to me a thorn in the flesh.
The messenger of Satan to buff at me,
notice why,
lest I should be exalted above measure.
Then notice what Paul says in verse number eight.
For this thing,
I besought the Lord thrice,
that it might depart from me.
And Paul was consistent,
fervent, if you will.
He says I besought the Lord thrice,
that it might depart from me.
Now, could God have caused this to depart from him?
He can do anything.
Paul is the one that God used to write
that wonderful promise in Ephesians three,
now unto him,
which is able to do exceeding abundantly
above all that we ask or think.
But notice what God says in verse number nine,
God's answer to Paul,
when Paul besought the Lord
with regard to this thorn in the flesh,
God said my grace is sufficient for thee.
My grace is sufficient for thee.
For my strength is made perfect in weakness.
You know, most of us don't physically,
we don't emotionally,
we don't want to show any vulnerabilities of weakness.
Right?
We don't want that to be perceived by others
that there's some measure of weakness,
but God says that his strength is made perfect in weakness.
He says my grace is sufficient for thee.
God is no respecter of persons.
And if God's grace was sufficient for Paul,
God's grace is sufficient for every one of us.
And we recognize a healthy church,
and remember a healthy church
is made up of healthy individuals.
I mean, a church is made up of people.
The church is not the building, it's the people.
The people are saved and baptized individuals
that make up the church,
and a healthy church is going to acknowledge
their need for the grace of God, for God's grace.
Paul says this after he receives the answer
that God gives at the end of verse number nine,
most gladly therefore will I rather glory
in my infirmities that the power of Christ
may rest upon me.
Therefore, notice what he says,
I take pleasure in infirmities,
in reproaches, in necessities,
in persecutions, in distresses for Christ's sake.
For when I am weak, then am I strong.
What is it in that moment of weakness
that would make someone strong?
It's the grace of God.
It's God's strength,
his strength being made perfect in our weakness
because his grace is sufficient.
This evening, a healthy church is a unified church.
No schisms, no divisions, a unified church.
Unified because we have no differences
of background, of personalities.
No, unified because we embrace the same truth.
We accept and we believe the same truth
and therefore God gives us unity.
A healthy church places a priority on the scriptures.
It's God's word that must be taught
and preached and believed, practiced.
As a Baptist, we often will say
that the Bible is our sole authority
for faith and practice.
Well, if the Bible is our sole authority
for faith and practice,
there must be a priority placed upon the scriptures.
It must be taught, it must be learned,
it must be understood, it must be applied.
And so we find that a healthy church
places a priority in the scriptures.
And number three, these three elements
that we see in these three concluding verses
is that a healthy church acknowledges
their need for God's grace.
By the grace of God, I am what I am.
Where would we be without God's grace?
We must acknowledge that we need God's grace
every day of our lives.
And I'm thankful that God's grace is sufficient,
that God gives it.
I know I said this a number of weeks ago,
but sometimes if we're not careful,
we can play these hypothetical mind games.
And we can put ourselves in a position of,
man, I don't know how I could ever handle such and such.
Maybe you hear of someone that has suffered,
has experienced some tragedy or some just adversity.
And you say, I don't know how I could handle that.
The reality is that we should not play
those hypothetical type of mind.
games because God gives us His grace in the moment that we deal with whatever we deal
with.
And we don't have to think about how could we ever, no, no, we trust that God will give
us the grace in the very moment that we need His grace.
I don't know if you've ever read Foxe's Book of Martyrs or any portion of it or if you've
read of any martyrs of the faith.
But you'll read of individuals that literally are being burned alive singing the praises
of God.
How?
I can't, no, no, in the moment that we need God's grace, God's grace is sufficient.
I believe that's the only way that you could explain those types of testimonies, that you
could explain any of those tragic events outside of the grace of God is sufficient.
And I'm so thankful for that wonderful promise that God has given a healthy church.
Healthy church is made up of healthy believers.
Every believer should have the desire to live their life in such a way that God would
be pleased.
That we could say, as we've used for the title of this series, walk worthy, please God.
What a joy that God has given us the instruction so that we know how we can please Him, how
we ought to walk.
The church in Thessalonica was given this instruction.
God graciously has preserved it for us so that we too today can understand how we can
walk worthy and please God.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the privilege that you've given us to hear the gospel.
God thank you for those that have been faithful before us to deliver the truth, the gospel
of Jesus Christ.
Thank you for those that, Lord, suffered greatly, persecution, great adversities, but they continued.
They remained steadfast.
Lord, I thank you for my salvation.
I thank you for those that are gathered this evening that have trusted you as their personal
Lord and Savior.
And God, I pray that as we consider the instruction from 1 Thessalonians chapter 5 this evening,
as we conclude that text and consider a healthy church, God, would you help us to take all
that we've learned over these many weeks and apply it, that we'd be doers of the word and
not hearers only, that we would be a church that's a healthy church.
Lord, that you would use us to reach our community with the gospel, that you'd use us to continue
to support the work of missions, global evangelization.
Lord, I pray that you'd use us for your honor and for your glory.
Bless now the time of prayer.
We thank you for the privilege at the end of our Wednesday night service that we can
pray together, intercessory prayer, corporate prayer.
God, we know that you hear and answer.
You've given us wonderful promises.
I pray, God, that you would bless our time, that you'd be honored and we'll thank you
for it.
In Christ's name we pray, amen.