As you study the book of Psalms, you'll find that many times, I mentioned this in Sunday
school this morning, we're looking in Psalm 34, but you study the book of Psalms and you
have the opportunity to really get insight into the heart and the life of the psalmist.
And many times you read the Psalms and you see the transparency of the psalmist.
You understand that he's a man just like we are humans and we face difficulties just as
he faced difficulties.
And you see that he is, many times David is the one that is the human payment.
He's not written all the Psalms, all scripture is given by inspiration of God, but God would
use David to pen a number of the Psalms.
And we find that God gives us great insight into the man, the life of David.
As we study the Psalms, as we read the Psalms, we can be encouraged through the content of
God's word in the book of Psalms.
Several years ago, I don't do it every year.
I read through the Bible a couple of times a year personally in my devotions.
And then other times I'll read it through a couple of times a year, but I'll read the
book of Psalms every month.
And if you read five Psalms a day, you can read through the book of Psalms every month
of the year.
And I've done that several years.
I'm not doing it this year, but I've done that several years.
I know a lot of people do the book of Proverbs, one proverb a day.
You go through the book of Proverbs every month of the year.
I've done that as well.
And when you read through the book of Psalms and you do five a day, man, you get encouraged
and it's just exciting to read the book of Psalms.
And I know that some have said, well, what happens when you get to Psalm 119?
You set aside more time to read that day, man.
And that's a good thing, by the way.
And you read through the book of Psalms and your heart is encouraged when you read the
book of Psalms.
But you also find that as you read the book of Psalms, that you'll be challenged.
Get the opportunity to read about the life and the behavior of the Psalmist.
And you have just an opportunity to be encouraged, but also to be challenged.
And I'm thankful when God's word challenges his people.
I'm thankful when God's word challenges me personally.
And we find that as we come to Psalm 54, just as the cases with many of the Psalms, you
find that there is a particular event that is the background or the setting for that
particular Psalm.
Now with some of the Psalms, it's a debate and there's a couple of options maybe with
several of the Psalms where it could have been written during this time in David's life
or maybe it was this time in David's life.
There are several Psalms that are pretty clear with regard to the timing, the setting for
the particular Psalm, and it is believed and commonly held to that Psalm 54, that the
setting for this Psalm is 1 Samuel 23.
That's why I've brought you to 1 Samuel 23 by way of introduction to just quickly go
through 1 Samuel 23, excuse me, so that we could quickly go through and get the setting,
get the background for this Psalm as we begin to understand that David declares in the midst
of this wonderful song, I will praise thy name.
And we find that the setting is at Keilah in 1 Samuel 23, and in the first five verses,
I won't take time to read all of 1 Samuel 23, it would be the entirety of the message,
but you find that in the first five verses of 1 Samuel 23, that God not only directs
but enables David and his men to deliver the city of Keilah from the Philistines.
We know that the Philistines were a consistent foe, an arch enemy, if you will, of the nation
of Israel, and you find that God would enable David, he gave clear direction to David to
go to Keilah and to fight and to deliver Keilah, and David obeyed the word of the Lord, and
David saw God work and God blessed in a very special way, and you find that as you move
through the text of Scripture, that in verses six through eight, that the Bible tells us
that Saul would come to the place of Keilah, and Saul had this thought, he had this perspective
that David was now in this situation in Keilah, and he was, opportunity was there for Saul
to go and to catch him.
He says at the end of verse number seven, for he is shut in by entering into a town
that hath gates and bars, and so Saul thought, this is my opportunity, I now can get David,
and we find that in these verses that Saul calls the people together, and Saul would
come down, and David then inquires of the Lord, and David asks God, is Saul going to
come, number one, and number two, are the people of Keilah going to deliver me to Saul?
God answers those prayers, and God tells David, yes indeed, Saul is on his way, and yes indeed,
the inhabitants of Keilah will deliver you into the hands of Saul.
Now that's a little bit disappointing, isn't it?
When you think about David going to the city of Keilah, and delivering those very people
from the Philistines, and yet when David's life is going to be in jeopardy, because Saul
is coming and seeking to kill David, that the people that were delivered by David would
turn him over to his enemy.
David leaves the city of Keilah, we find that as he leaves the city of Keilah, the Bible
tells us in verse number 14 that Saul was going to seek David every day.
It says that David abode in the wilderness in strongholds, and remained in a mountain
in the wilderness of Ziph.
And so this is the location where he is, and it says this, that Saul sought him every day,
but God delivered him not into his hand.
Saul would say this in verse number 23 at the end of the verse, that I will search him
out throughout all the thousands of Judah.
I've often wondered if with the same intensity that Saul sought David, if he would have sought
the Lord with that same level of intensity, how different his life would have been.
We find that he's seeking to find David, why?
So that he could kill David, and so David is there in the wilderness of Ziph according
to verse number 14, and then these that are the inhabitants of this area, the Ziphites,
they come to Saul in verse number 19, and notice what they say.
Then came up the Ziphites to Saul, to Gibeah, saying, Doth not David hide himself with us
in strongholds in the wood, in the hill of Hakaliah, which is on the south of Jeshamon?
Now therefore, O king, come down according to all the desire of thy soul to come down,
and our part shall be to deliver him, David, into the king's hand.
So now understand what's taking place.
He's in the wilderness of Ziph, and Saul is seeking him every day.
Saul's purpose, his goal daily is to find David so that he might kill David, and we
find that he's in the wilderness of Ziph, and Saul is in this place, and obviously not
his hometown, not his backyard, so to speak, and so the inhabitants of the wilderness of
Ziph, the Ziphites, they understand what's taking place, and they come to Saul, and they
say, Saul, our part, because we know this area, this, you know, you've heard the phrase
that somebody say, they know it like the back of their hand, you've heard somebody use that
phraseology, well, this was their backyard, this was their area, and these Ziphites, they
say to Saul, you let us do our part, and we will deliver David into your hand.
This is what David's dealing with.
The Bible tells us that Saul's seeking for him, notice in verse number 25, David is surrounded,
the Bible says that Saul also and his men went to seek him, and they told David, wherefore
he came down into a rock and abode in the wilderness of Maon, and when Saul heard that,
he pursued after David in the wilderness of Maon, and Saul went on this side of the mountain,
and David and his men on that side of the mountain, and David made haste to get away
for fear of Saul, notice what the Bible says at the end of verse 26, for Saul and his men
encompassed David and his men round about to take them.
Wow, what circumstances, but God delivered.
In verse number 27, it says, there came a messenger unto Saul, and this messenger comes
to Saul, and he says, haste thee and come, for the Philistines have invaded the land.
I don't know how long it took the messenger to get to the wilderness of Ziph, but I am
reminded in this passage of Scripture that God's timing is perfect, because David was
completely surrounded, and Saul's purpose was to kill David, and in that moment, a messenger
comes.
When did the Philistines invade?
Not at that moment.
There had to be a period of time for that invasion to take place, for that messenger
to get from there to where Saul was to bring news, and God tells us in verse number 28,
wherefore Saul returned from pursuing after David.
This is not the end of David's trials.
This is not the end of Saul's pursuit of David.
In fact, as you get into the 24th chapter, you read about being there at En Gedi and
all the things that take place, but you find that David is dealing with these adverse circumstances
that we read of here in 1 Samuel 23, and that is the backdrop for our passage that
we're studying this morning in Psalm 54.
So now take and turn over to the book of Psalms, and Psalm 54, I ask you to hold your place
there, and I want you to notice, and I'm going to quickly give an outline for this particular
psalm.
It begins in verses one and two with a prayer for deliverance.
Notice what the Bible says.
David says, save me, O God, by thy name, and judge me by thy strength.
Hear my prayer, O God, give ear to the words of my mouth.
This is a prayer of deliverance.
I believe I read this text of Scripture, and there's a measure of urgency in the lips of
David as he's praying, save me, O God.
We just read 1 Samuel 23.
We understand the circumstances surrounding the writing
of this particular psalm,
and certainly he would pray with a measure of urgency.
You find that the psalmist will pray
in other portions of scripture, help Lord.
He says, save me.
I want you to notice he says,
by thy name and judge me by thy strength.
I'm so thankful that God has the ability to deliver.
I'm so thankful that he is a very present help
in the time of trouble.
Not only is he available, he's able,
and we can rejoice in that,
and we can take what the psalmist said in Psalm 121
and lift up our eyes under the hills
from whence cometh our help,
knowing with confidence and with assurance
that our help cometh from the Lord,
which made heaven and earth.
We sang about how great thou art.
He is the creator God.
He said, let there be light, and there was light.
He spoke all things into existence
by the power that he has,
and he is your helper, he is my helper.
Man, isn't that awesome?
It begins with a prayer for deliverance.
We find that in verse number three,
he reveals the circumstances in which he's dealing with.
Notice what he says,
for strangers are risen up against me,
and oppressors seek after my soul.
They have not set God before them, Selah.
You think about the circumstances,
we've mentioned in 1 Samuel chapter 23,
not only was Saul and his men seeking for David,
but we find that the people of Kelah
that he had just delivered,
they were willing to turn David over to Saul.
We find that he escaped so that that would not happen,
and then these inhabitants of the wilderness of Ziph,
the Ziphites, they say, hey, Saul,
we're gonna help you out.
We'll deliver him into your hand.
And David says that strangers are risen up against me,
and oppressors seek after my soul.
They have not set God before them, Selah.
We find that not only does he reveal his circumstances
in verse number three,
but he recognizes that God is his helper in verse number four.
Notice what he says, behold, this is precious,
God is mine helper.
The Lord is with them that uphold my soul.
Listen, this morning,
I hope that you're recognizing that God is your helper.
I hope that you recognize that as you go through this life
that you're not going through it alone.
I'm thankful that the Bible teaches us
that the Holy Spirit of God indwells us.
that he'll never leave us nor forsake us.
I'm thankful that he is our helper.
And we find that David acknowledges this truth,
and he recognizes that God is my helper.
Listen, David was a very skillful military man.
David was a man that had accomplished much.
He had defeated Goliath,
and we find that he had killed numbers of Philistines.
He had just delivered the city of Kelah,
but David recognized it wasn't him, it was God.
And oh, how important that is for our lives,
for your life and for my life,
that David says the Lord is mine helper.
We find that as we continue to move through the Psalm
in verse number five,
there's an expectation of deliverance.
He said, he shall reward evil unto mine enemies.
Cut them off in thy truth.
We find that he's speaking with expectation.
He shall reward evil unto mine enemies.
What God is going to do.
Listen, I'm so thankful that our God is on the throne.
I'm so thankful that even in the darkest of times,
though we may not understand what God is going to do
or how God is going to work,
we may look at the situation,
at the circumstances being unfavorable,
that there's no way out but God.
How thankful I am for the times
in which you read the word of God
and you read those two words, but God.
But God.
We find that in verse number six,
God reveals to us a commitment on the part of the Psalmist
to praise the name of the Lord.
Notice what he says, I will freely sacrifice unto thee.
I will praise thy name, O Lord, for it is good.
I've used that phrase in verse number six
in the middle of the verse for our title this morning.
I will praise thy name.
We find that in verse number seven,
David recalls past deliverance.
Notice what he says in verse five.
He said, he shall reward evil unto mine enemies.
But in verse number seven, he says,
for he hath delivered me out of all trouble
and mine eye hath seen his desire upon mine enemies.
You know, it's a good thing for us to rehearse
and to recall what God has done.
It is a beneficial thing.
It's a beneficial practice.
We sing, I think we'll sing the song tonight,
count your blessings, name them one by one.
And to begin to think about and recall
the way in which God has worked
and what he has done in the past,
not only does it put you in a state of worshiping God
and praising him and exalting him,
but it also gives you a sense of expectation
of what God is going to do because God is still at work.
God is still on his throne.
You say, but pastor, I'm going through this situation.
I'm going through that situation.
And David was going through a situation
in Psalm 54 as he wrote these words.
And every single person has circumstances
and situations that they're dealing with.
And it is not our job to compare my trials
and your trials and someone else's trials,
but understand that God is greater than all of our trials
and that God has a plan and God has a purpose.
And we find that as we enter into this thought
from Psalm 54 and noticing what the psalmist says,
I will praise thy name, I wanna take just the remainder
of our time this morning and examine three aspects
of the psalmist and his praise.
Three aspects of the psalmist and his praise.
Number one, if you're taking notes this morning,
I want you to understand that the psalmist
was purposed in his praise.
The psalmist was purposed in his praise.
Notice what the Bible says, I will praise thy name.
I will, that idea of being purposed is to be deliberate,
to be intentional.
The reality is that just as the psalmist
and you can study the Psalms and we'll look at a few verses
here in just a moment, but you can study the Psalms
and you can find where the psalmist is purposed
in his praise, he's deliberate, he's intentional.
And you and I this morning, we too must be purposed
in our praise.
For many of us, I taught in Sunday school this morning
from Psalm 34, I will bless the Lord at all times,
his praise shall continually be in my mouth.
And we talked about the fact in this morning
in our Sunday school class that the reality
is that for many of us, our default setting
is not praise, it's complaint.
That's our default setting as human beings.
I think it was Brother Armando that gave the answer
to the question this morning in Sunday school
that we complain about the weather.
And you heard about all the snow in Buffalo
and then you heard Brother Michael give the report
of all the rain in Scotland.
72 inches, I can't even comprehend that in a month.
But we complain when it's hot, we complain when it's cold.
Listen, many times our default setting is not praise.
Our default setting is complaint.
And the reality is born again believers
with the spirit of God living within us,
we need to be purposed in our praise
and we need to get to the place that our default setting
no longer is complaint but is praise, why?
Because of any man being Christ, he's a new creature.
Old things are passed away, behold,
all things have become new.
And I come to the place now where I'm looking at my life
and my circumstances, my difficulties, my trials,
my adversities, I'm looking at them through the lens
that God is good, that God has a purpose,
that God has a plan, that God is on his throne,
that God is up to something, he's working.
Listen, God is moving and God is working.
And we, listen, when I look at 1 Samuel 23
and you can look at that passage and say,
man, that's unfortunate that David
had to deal with all of that.
I'm thankful that I get to read about it.
Why, because my heart's encouraged.
When I read about what David dealt with in 1 Samuel 23,
when I read about how God delivered his servant
that was surrounded by those that wanted to kill him
and God allowed for some other things to take place
so that Saul returns.
And it's awesome to see our God at work.
We find that the psalmist, as you study his life,
you'll find that he's purposed in his praise.
Look over at Psalm 108, if you will.
Look at a few verses of scripture this morning
and look at the heart of the psalmist
and his praise, he's purposed.
In Psalm 108, beginning in verse number one,
the Bible says this, Psalm 108 and verse number one,
oh God, my heart is fixed.
I will sing and give praise even with my glory.
Awake, psaltery and harp.
I myself will awake early.
I will praise thee, oh Lord, among the people
and I will sing praises unto thee among the nations.
Why, notice what he says in verse number four.
For thy mercy is great above the heavens
and thy truth reacheth under the clouds.
Our God is.
He's merciful.
Our God has given us truth.
And here the psalmist, another psalm that's ascribed to David, he says that my heart is
fixed.
He says that I will sing and give praise.
He says, I will praise Thee, and I will praise Thee among the people, and I will sing praises
unto Thee among the nations.
He's not fearful to praise God publicly, amen?
By the way, we need to praise God publicly.
Let people know how good our God is.
Let people know what your God has done for you, and how He's saved you, and how He's
blessed you, and how He's worked in and through your life.
We find that the psalmist's purpose, notice in Psalm 139, we're familiar with Psalm 139
in this portion of scripture, but we find that the psalmist says, when you think about
the, again, the intentional, the deliberate perspective of the psalmist with regard to
praise, notice what he says in Psalm 139 in verse number 14, I will praise Thee.
Why?
For I am fearfully and wonderfully made, marvelous are Thy works, and that my soul knoweth right
well.
I will praise Thee.
You read Psalm 150.
We won't take time to read it this morning, but if you read Psalm 150, you'll find that
the psalmist says, let everything that hath breath praise the Lord.
Praise ye the Lord.
And as you read, it's only six verses in Psalm 150, but as you read Psalm 150, you will find
that the psalmist is understanding that I'm going to praise God, first of all, for who
He is, and then I'm going to praise God for what He has done.
Listen this morning, if we learn to praise God for who He is, we will never lack reason
to rejoice.
Why?
Because He's immutable.
He never changes.
Your circumstances change.
You might be on a mountaintop today.
You might be in the valley today.
Your circumstances are ever-changing, but God is consistent.
God is constant.
God is immutable.
He is the same yesterday and today and forever, and we find that He is gracious and He is
merciful and He is loving toward us, and we think about all of His attributes, and we
think about learning to rejoice in who He is.
He's good.
We sang this morning, how great thou art, our God is great.
This morning, we find that the psalmist, as we study, we read through the Psalms, we find
that He was purposed in His praise, and I, too, we, too, must be purposed in our praise.
We must be deliberate.
We must be intentional.
We must make it a part of our lives, not just going through some rote religious activity,
not just going through the motions, but purposefully every day.
As the psalmist said in Psalm 118 and verse 24, this is the day the Lord hath made.
We will rejoice and be glad in it, but that guy cut me off, but I got, somebody said they
got a flat tire.
I got this.
I got that, but it's the day the Lord hath made, and I'm going to rejoice because God
has a plan and God has a purpose.
Now, bear this with me.
The psalmist, not only was he purposed in His praise, but number two, the psalmist was
persistent in his praise, persistent in his praise.
I would say this.
No matter the circumstances, no matter how I feel, no matter how you feel, no matter
what circumstances you deal with, you ought to praise God, amen?
He's worthy of our praise, and the psalmist was persistent.
David was persistent in his praise.
We find that as we begin to look at the truth that God is good, He's good all of the time,
and He's worthy of our praise, and we find that our circumstances I mentioned a moment
ago may change, but God never changes, and we find that we're to praise Him persistently.
You know, there are times in our life when things seem to be going well, when things
seem to be on that mountaintop, so to speak, type of an experience, and it seems like it's
easy to praise God in those types of circumstances.
When you're in the valley, it's a little bit more challenging, but we must be persistent
in our praise because God is good on the mountaintop, and God is good in the valley.
You know what I've learned in life?
Some of the hardest times in the valley end up being some of the sweetest times you'll
ever have with the Lord.
You get to know God in a much more personal, intimate way when you're in the valley.
You really do.
You say, pastor, you're saying you want to be in the valley?
No.
I'm just telling you by experience, the valley is a sweet place to be with the Lord, and
sometimes God will take us into the valley so that we can learn to trust Him, so we can
learn to depend on Him, so we can learn that He is who He says He is.
You can't live life on the top of the mountain 24-7, 365.
God took His servants into the storm.
God will take us into storms, and you learn so much about Him.
Psalm 52, remember the circumstances as you're turning to Psalm 52.
Remember the circumstances, the setting for this particular psalm here in Psalm 54, the
setting of 1 Samuel 23.
The men of Kelah that had just been delivered going to turn David over to Saul, Saul seeking
for him, the Ziphites saying, hey, we'll help you find him, and David says, I will.
Praise thy name, O Lord, for it is good.
He's persistent in his praise.
In Psalm 52, in verse number 9, the Bible says, I will praise thee.
Notice what it says, forever, because thou hast done it, and I will wait on thy name
for it is good before thy saints.
Notice that little phrase, forever.
I will praise thee forever.
He's worthy.
Listen, you understand in a real sense, when we think about the truth of forever, that
we will praise Him for all of eternity.
You read the book of Revelation, you begin to see the throne room of heaven in Revelation
4 and 5 and see what's taking place, and you say, we will praise Him forever and ever.
But forever begins now.
I'm going to praise Him persistently, perpetually.
His praise shall be on my lips.
He says, I will praise thee forever.
Yeah, but David, your circumstances are going to change.
Yes, but God doesn't, and I will praise Him forever, amen?
He's persistent.
Notice in Psalm 113, in verse number 3, look at a couple of other psalms here, but Psalm
113 and verse number 3, notice what the Bible says.
I'll begin in verse number 1, as the psalmist is giving this instruction here, in verse
number 1 of Psalm 113, he says, praise ye the Lord, praise, O ye servants of the Lord,
praise the name of the Lord.
Seem like he wants us to praise Him, amen?
Verse 2, blessed be the name of the Lord from this time forth and forevermore.
Notice verse number 3, from the rising of the sun unto the going down of the same, the
Lord's name is to be praised.
Who's the one doing the praising?
The people of God, right?
And so, you notice, he says, from the rising of the sun unto the going down of the same,
the Lord's name is to be praised.
And, listen, don't be the naysayer and say, okay, so when the sun's not out, I don't have
to praise Him.
That's not what he's talking about, amen?
And we get the idea, as we look at the psalmist here, and we look at the truth of the Word
of God, that we're to be persistent in our praise.
The psalmist said this, and you don't need to turn there, but in Psalm 145, in verse
number 2, the Bible says, every day will I bless thee, and I will praise thy name forever
and ever.
The next verse says, great is the Lord, and greatly to be praised, and His greatness is
unsearchable.
And the psalmist says, I will praise the Lord every day will I bless thee, and I will praise
thy name forever and ever.
It's not only being purposed, but it's being persistent in our praise.
It's understanding that every single day that God is the same, and that God has a plan and
a purpose.
And we find that as we look at the Word of God, in 1 Thessalonians chapter 5, the Bible
says, rejoice evermore.
In Philippians chapter number 4, the Bible says, rejoice in the Lord always, and again
I say rejoice.
We find that Paul was a man that God would use to pen those letters, those letters to
those churches about rejoicing, but Paul was a man that rejoiced.
It's interesting as you read the letters that Paul writes under the inspiration of the Holy
Spirit of God, if you read the beginning section of each of those letters, you find very consistently
that Paul is praising God.
Paul is being thankful.
He's writing to the church in Corinth, by the way, not a model church, and he talks
in 1 Corinthians 1 about thanking God who is faithful.
That's what he says.
God is faithful.
I've got to deal with a whole lot of nonsense in the church in Corinth, and he's going to
give it to them in the book of 1 Corinthians.
There's correction that is needed, but he begins by saying, I'm praising God because
He's faithful.
We sing, great is thy faithfulness.
All our God is faithful.
We must be purposed in our praise, just as the psalmist was.
We must be persistent in our praise, just as the psalmist was, and I will say this,
we must be passionate in our praise, just as the psalmist was.
The psalmist was passionate in his praise.
Notice what he says in Psalm 9 in verse number 1.
I love the phraseology here,
and it's certainly convicting.
As we begin to see what's taking place,
and we find that the psalmist is revealing to us
this passion in which he would praise the Lord.
In fact, as you study the life of David,
and you see what's taking place in his life,
and you begin to look at various aspects of his life,
as you read the book of 1 Samuel,
you see a man that passionately prays God.
Amen?
I mean, he's passionate about it.
Do you remember the scene when they're bringing
the ark back to Jerusalem?
I mean, there is rejoicing that is taking place.
I mean, it is a big deal, and there is passionate praise.
We find that the psalmist said this in Psalm 9,
in verse number one, I will praise thee, O Lord,
notice what it says, with my whole heart.
I will show forth all thy marvelous works.
My whole heart.
It's passionate.
It's not half-hearted praise.
It's not praising God because someone's making me
praise God, it's praising him because he's worthy
of my praise, and he deserves our praise,
and he's been so abundantly good to us,
and I'm gonna praise him with my whole heart.
You say, but other people are gonna say.
Doesn't matter.
You watch sporting events.
Those people go crazy for some sports team
because they won some game.
That in the light of eternity isn't gonna matter at all.
I remember sitting in a church in England five years ago,
and the setting in England is different than it is here.
In fact, as you go to churches in America,
you find that there's different settings, even America.
We're kind of in a little bit of an in-between,
but man, if you go down south, man,
they're shouting and praising God and amen
as you're preaching, and they're preaching from the pew
as you're preaching from the pulpit.
I mean, they're excited about praising God, amen.
You get up into New England, and it's very proper,
and very, we're somewhere in the middle,
but over in England, I mean, it was just extremely formal
and just very different.
I remember standing up to sing,
and we stood up to sing that first song,
and we had the hymnal, and man, I don't sing on tune,
but I sing loud, man.
God said, make a joyful noise unto the Lord,
and I stood up to sing, and it was like
I was the only one singing in the place.
I was like, whoa, I gotta lower it down a little bit, right?
And it was just the way it was.
And I remember talking to our missionary, Jared Clement,
and I said something to him about, we're just talking.
I wasn't criticizing.
I was just inquiring, and he said, well, you know,
they're just, the English people,
they're just not very passionate, and so on and so forth.
I was like, I've seen clips of them watching football,
soccer, those guys are nuts, right?
Listen, we ought to be passionate for our God, amen,
with my whole heart.
I'm not saying be fleshly, be carnal.
I'm not saying hang from rafters and crazy stuff,
but I'm saying it ought to be a wholehearted worship.
The psalmist says, I will praise thee,
but he says, with my whole heart.
In Psalm 86, in verse number 12, the psalmist says this,
and again, just being consistent with this thought
of being passionate, he says,
I will praise thee, O Lord, my God, with all my heart,
and I will glorify thy name forevermore.
Some of you would know the name of Matthew Henry.
He's a theologian of yesteryear that God used
to write a commentary series.
I very rarely look at Matthew Henry's commentary.
Some people have it, I have a copy of it.
I very rarely use, I don't use commentaries a ton,
but there's an account in the life of Matthew Henry
that some of you may be familiar with,
and it goes well with this thought
of I will praise thy name.
I will praise him, I'll be purposed,
just as the psalmist was.
I will be persistent, I will be passionate.
The account goes like this,
that Matthew Henry, one day, he was robbed.
A man came and pulled a weapon on him
and robbed him of his wallet.
It was a very unfortunate situation,
but Matthew Henry went home
and began to journal about that situation,
and he had determined in his heart
that he was gonna praise God.
Prior to this event ever happening,
he had purposed, I'm gonna praise God,
just as we preach this morning,
just as we look at the example of the psalmist.
He began to write, and it's said that in this account
that he writes, I'm thankful that I was the one
that was robbed and not the one doing the robbing.
Hmm.
Okay.
He says, I'm thankful, listen to this,
I'm thankful that they took everything I have,
but it wasn't much.
I'm thankful that they just robbed me and didn't kill me.
Yeah.
There were other things on his list,
but those are the three that I'll share with you.
And I want you to think about that perspective.
We read of David and his praise.
We see the event in 1 Samuel 23.
We read of Paul and of his praise,
even in Acts 16, when they're beaten and imprisoned
and they're praising God.
We see a man named Matthew Henry
that was robbed one day.
I've never been robbed.
I hope to never be robbed.
But if I'd be honest with you this morning,
and if you'd be honest with me this morning,
if you were robbed on the way here,
that probably would not be the first three things
out of your mouth, and probably wouldn't be
the first three things out of my mouth.
Can we be transparent this morning?
But we need to get to the place where the psalmist is.
See, I'm gonna be purposed in my praise.
I'm gonna be intentional and deliberate about praising God,
because God is good.
I'm gonna be persistent, no matter the circumstances,
no matter what's going on, from the rising of the sun
to the going down of the same.
I'm gonna praise his name from this day forth and forever.
I'm going to praise my God.
And I'm gonna be passionate about it.
With my whole heart, I'm gonna praise him.
See, whether you're on the mountaintop
or you're in the valley, God wants to hear your praise.
Someone wrote the song years ago,
God Wants to Hear You Sing, and he does.
He wants to hear your praise, and he's worthy of it.
And oh, that God would help us this morning.
I said it in Sunday school to close the Sunday school hour.
As God's people, we don't need a federal holiday
to cause us to be thankful.
I am thankful that we have a federal holiday on our calendar
that causes us to be more aware of
and focused on at this time of year.
I'm thankful for that.
But the reality is that every single day,
we ought to be thanking God.
Oh, that God would help us to not be caught up
in the culture and the society of being an unthankful people
or a complaining people,
but that God would help us to praise his name.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
How we thank you for loving us.
We thank you for the word of God.
We thank you for the truth contained therein.
We thank you for the example of the psalmist.
And Lord, as we look at the example of the psalmist,
we are challenged.
I pray that you would help each of us, Lord,
to be purposed, to be persistent,
to be passionate in our praise of thee.
Lord, perhaps there's one here that's not sure of heaven.
They've never trusted the Lord Jesus Christ
as their personal savior.
If they were to die today,
they do not have assurance that heaven is their home.
Oh God, I pray that the Holy Spirit of God
would speak to the heart of that individual
and help them to understand their need for Christ.
I pray they'd understand that, God, you love them.
You sent your son to die for them.
He suffered, bled and died.
He was buried in a borrowed tomb,
but he rose conquering sin, death, and the grave.
He's alive forevermore.
And he is the savior of the world.
God, if there's one in that condition
that needs to be saved,
I pray that you would give us an opportunity
to take a Bible and show them
how they could know for sure that heaven's their home.
Lord, I pray for Christians this morning
that are gathered together.
Oh God, I pray that you'd help us in this area of our praise.
Lord, I pray that you'd help us to respond now
to that which we have heard.
I pray that you'd move, work as only you can.
We'll thank you for every decision that's made
for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?