Chapter number three, Joseph was gonna sing with them,
but then we remembered that he was taking care
of the sound this morning,
and so he wasn't able to sing with them,
but it was a blessing hearing them practice that this week
and kind of singing it, and I love that song.
I'm so thankful that God has given us his word.
Second Timothy chapter number three,
if you've already looked at the back of the bulletin
this morning, we're gonna be dealing,
kind of shifting into a new series, if you will,
of how God has revealed his greatness.
We spent much of the year so far,
through the month of January
into the beginning of February,
dealing with the truth that creation
reveals the greatness of God,
and we looked at a number of passages
dealing with the truth of creation,
and then over the last two weeks,
we dealt with the fact as we would apply
that great truth in our lives,
that the creator God is my helper,
and what a blessing to know that the God
who spoke it all into existence is our helper personally,
and I'm thankful for that application.
This morning and over the next several weeks,
we're gonna shift our attention to the Bible,
and I'm thankful that God has given us a Bible,
and I believe as I will preach over the next several weeks
that as we hold in our hands this great book,
that it reveals to us that our God is great,
the way in which he gave it,
the way in which he's preserved it,
and all that's contained therein,
I believe that inspiration,
as we'll focus on this morning specifically,
that inspiration reveals the greatness of God.
The content of the Bible
obviously reveals that God is great,
but the means by which God gave us the Bible
reveals how great he is.
Let me understand this morning
that God could have just dropped a Bible out of the sky
and said, here it is, here's the Bible,
but he chose to reveal it to us over a period of time,
and we'll focus and share some of those statistics here
in just a moment,
but we find this truth of progressive revelation,
if you will,
and we see how God in his infinite wisdom,
how he gave us what we hold in our hands this morning,
what we hold so dear and so precious,
and by the way, if you take this away, everything crumbles,
because everything that we know to be true about God
is a direct result of what we know
that he's given to us in this book,
and so it's absolutely imperative that we understand
the truth that is contained therein and what it is.
I mentioned this several times
a couple of Sunday nights ago
as we finished up with a final message on Ask the Pastor
until we resume in the summer,
but we dealt with a number of things,
and I said it many times at the end of the message
that it's absolutely imperative
that we know what this book is
and then what this book says,
because if we do not have an understanding
of what this book is,
then what it says is open for debate,
but when we understand what this book is,
all of a sudden, this book is authoritative.
It's not open for debate.
It's not open for discussion.
We're not looking for any new revelation.
As they sang in the song,
there are many over the years
that have tried to water it down,
that have tried to change it,
but God's word endures.
God's word marches on, and I'm so thankful.
The Bible, as some have said,
is the greatest book of all time.
I agree.
It is estimated that about five billion copies of the Bible
have been sold, making it the best-selling book of all time.
Not only is it the best-selling book of all time,
but we would, as you look at the statistics,
you would find that it is the most translated book
of all time.
We obviously work with Beacon of Truth,
trying to get the Bible, the word of God,
around the world so that people can have the Bible
in their own language, so that their heart language,
the Bible would be available to them.
Unfortunately, still today, in 2023,
there are millions and millions of people
around the face of the world
that do not have the full Bible in their native tongue.
That's why the work is so important
to get the Bible translated.
We look at this quote.
Charles Ryrie said this,
that the Bible is the greatest of all books.
To study it is the noblest of all pursuits.
To understand it, the highest of all goals.
I would agree this morning
that the Bible is the greatest of all books.
Many books can inform,
but only this book can transform.
Of all the books that I have in my library,
and I have quite a few,
of all the books that I've ever read,
and I've read quite a few,
this book stands alone.
This book is like no other book that I've ever read.
The content is precious.
We'd ask the question this morning is this,
what is it that sets this book apart from any other book?
What is it that makes this book, the Bible,
the Word of God,
the best-selling and most translated book of all time?
It's this very simple truth
that God, who alone is great,
is the author of this book.
And that's what sets this book apart from any other book.
And that's what makes this book so precious.
This morning we will note
that I believe,
and as we look at the passage of Scripture,
that inspiration reveals to us
the greatness of God.
Notice with me in 2 Timothy chapter number three.
Begin reading in verse number 14.
The Bible says,
but continue thou in the things which thou hast learned
and hast been assured of,
knowing of whom thou hast learned them,
that from a child thou hast known the Holy Scriptures,
which are able to make thee wise unto salvation
through faith which is in Christ Jesus.
By the way, I'm thankful for the message of salvation.
The message of salvation in the pages of Scripture.
How is it that we could know how to get to heaven?
Well, because God's given us
the truth of salvation and redemption
in the pages of this book.
Then notice in verse 16,
all Scripture, not some, not most,
but all Scripture.
Very wise Bible college professor would say often,
all means all, and that's all that all means.
He said, that's pretty simple.
I know, he said it all the time.
Because the Bible says all Scripture
is given by inspiration of God.
Notice what it says,
and it's profitable for doctrine,
for reproof, for correction,
for instruction in righteousness,
that the man of God may be perfect,
throughly furnished unto all good works.
Thus, Paul would give Timothy a charge
in the fourth chapter.
We know that the chapter divisions were inserted later
for our ease of being able to find
and reference portions of Scripture.
But he gives a charge to begin the fourth chapter,
and he says this in verse number two,
preach the word.
Why?
Because of what he just told us the word is.
And this morning, as we begin to think about this truth
of holding in our hands the precious Bible,
someone said this, I thought it was just so perfect
how they summarized this truth,
referring to the Bible as the word of God
is the most complete and impressive acknowledgement
of its significance,
reminding us that we should regard the Bible
as God speaking to man.
It's God's word.
This message from God to humanity
is the most powerful and trustworthy book ever written.
God assures us throughout the Bible
that these are His very words.
I'm thankful this morning that God's given us a Bible.
As we think about the greatness of God
and how inspiration reveals to us the greatness of God,
if you're taking notes,
I want you to consider with me the process of inspiration.
What is the process of inspiration?
The Bible tells us here in verse number 16
of 2 Timothy 3 that all Scripture
is given by inspiration of God.
As we begin to think about this statement of inspiration
and how all Scripture has been given in this manner,
we would ask ourselves this question,
what is the process?
How did God do this?
And the reality is that He answers that for us
in 2 Peter chapter number one.
Hold your place here, if you will,
in 2 Timothy chapter number three,
but turn over to 2 Peter chapter number one.
And it's interesting because Peter is the human penman
to the book of 2 Peter,
containing his name here in the particular epistle.
He is the human penman,
but remember all Scripture is given by inspiration of God.
And as Peter is writing
in this particular passage of Scripture,
we'll actually visit this passage again in a few weeks
and look at this passage in its entirety.
But notice what Peter is saying.
He talks about the fact
that we have a more sure word of prophecy,
and he speaks with regard to an experience
that he had on the Mount of Transfiguration.
If you think back to the ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ,
Peter, James, and John had the privilege
of going out on the Mount of Transfiguration with Jesus
and seeing Jesus in that time
and hearing the voice of the Father.
And Peter references this particular account
in this passage of Scripture,
and he speaks about hearing the voice of God Almighty,
but he says that we...
have a more sure word of prophecy. Notice what he says in verse number 19, we have also
a more sure word of prophecy, whereunto ye do well that ye take heed, as unto a light
that shineth in a dark place until the day dawn and the day star arise in your hearts.
And then he's going to answer the question that we've posed this morning in verses 20
and 21, and that's with regard to the process of inspiration. If God tells us that all Scripture
is given by inspiration of God, how did God do that? This reveals His greatness. It says
in verse 20, knowing this first, that no prophecy of the Scripture is of any private interpretation.
For the prophecy came not in old time by the will of man. That's important for us to understand.
It's not that Isaiah just decided one day, I'm going to write Scripture. It's not that
Jeremiah or one of the other prophets just decided on a whim, on their own, that they're
going to write Scripture. No, the Bible says that the prophecy came not in old time by
the will of man. But holy men of God spake as they were moved by the Holy Ghost. We've
got to think about this truth of inspiration. The Bible is not man's words. Many people
today would make that false claim about the Bible. They would say, hey listen, the Bible,
that's just a bunch of people that wrote the Bible. How can you trust that? No, they
don't understand what the Bible is. The Bible is not just a compilation of individuals of
men that wrote things. No, the Bible is God's Word. And all Scripture is given by inspiration
of God, and we find this morning that He used men to record His Word. He used men to record
His Word. The word inspiration literally means God-breathed. We think about the truth
of inspiration, and we'll deal with this also when we deal with the subject of preservation
next week, but when we think about the truth of inspiration, we would believe and hold
to that the Bible teaches clearly this truth of verbal plenary inspiration. You say, I've
not heard that term before. I'm not familiar with that term. The word verbal means the
very words. The very words. And the word plenary means the entirety of it. So when we think
about the Bible, the Word of God that we hold in our hand this morning, and we think about
this truth of inspiration, the Bible says that all Scripture is given by inspiration
of God, that it's the entirety, the whole of the Bible, and it's the very words. God
did not just give thoughts. He did not just tell Paul, write on this subject, or tell
Isaiah to write on this theme, or Ezekiel to write on this thought. No, God gave the
very words. It's important for us to understand that this morning, because again, before we
are going to talk about what the Bible says, we must understand what the Bible is. And
as we consider the truth of inspiration this morning, we see that inspiration reveals to
us the greatness of God. Consider with me a truth from the book of Deuteronomy in chapter
4. And you don't need to turn there. I'll read the verse for you. You can if you want.
But Deuteronomy chapter 4, of course God is preparing His people for entrance into the
land of promise, and He's using Moses. And Moses is given this final charge, and it says
in verse number 1 of Deuteronomy 4,
Now therefore hearken, O Israel, under the statutes and under the judgments which I teach
you, for to do them that ye may live, and go in and possess the land which the Lord
God of your fathers giveth you. Notice what He says,
Ye shall not add unto the word which I command you, neither shall ye diminish aught from
it, that ye may keep the commandments of the Lord your God which I command you.
God's concerned about the very word. A jot and a tittle is what the Bible speaks about,
that heaven and earth shall pass, but not a jot nor a tittle from God's Word is going
to pass. And we find this morning that God has given the individual words. That's important
for us to understand, because we cannot just take a pen knife and just start carving things
out of the Bible that we say we just don't like or doesn't kind of fit with what we want
to do. No, every word. I've often said over the years, I'm reminded of times in Bible
college and preparation, even in high school, with term papers that were required to be
written, and how often you were told that you had to have a paper written that contained
a certain number of words. I'm not sure if you had that experience as I did, but I remember
having that experience, and I remember coming to a place where I'd have that paper just
about written, and you'd check your word count and find out that you were short. I got to
know a lot of different words that I could just kind of plug in and just fill. Admittedly,
I did that. Can I tell you this morning that this book has no filler? No filler. No one
told God how many books, how many words, how many verses, how many chapters. No, no. God
gave us exactly what He wanted us to have. And that's why we understand with this truth
of verbal plenary inspiration that every word is important. And we study the Word of God.
We study and we learn and we're helped and we're encouraged and we're strengthened. We
find this morning that He speaks about the whole of the Bible. In the New Testament,
you know that Jesus often referred to the Old Testament. We find that Paul, in 1 Corinthians
chapter number 10, in referring back to the Old Testament through the things that were
written before. He says this in verse number 11 of 1 Corinthians 10, now all these things
happened unto them for in samples, and they are written for our admonition upon whom the
ends of the world are come. Romans, Paul says the same thing over in Romans about the things
that were written aforetime were written for our learning. And I'm thankful this morning
that as we look back, and even in our text of Scripture this morning, in 2 Timothy chapter
number 3, when Paul is giving Timothy this charge and he's giving him this instruction,
he says that from a child, in verse number 15, thou hast known the Holy Scriptures, which
are able to make thee wise unto salvation through faith, which is in Christ Jesus. And
what Paul would be referring to is the Old Testament. He refers to them as being Holy
Scriptures. He then tells Timothy in chapter number 4 to preach the Word. He's referring
to the same thing, the Bible, the Word of God, the Scriptures. And we find here this
morning that he gives us this truth and he reveals to us that every word and then the
entirety is given by inspiration of God. All Scripture is given by inspiration of God.
Now how does this truth of inspiration reveal the greatness of God? Well you recognize this
morning that as we look at this book that we hold in our hands that there are about
40 different human penmen over a span of time of about 1,500 years, three different languages
and three different continents, yet we have one perfect book. It's amazing. It's amazing.
I'm not sure how many people are in the auditorium this morning, but if we were to just have
a topic been given to each of us that we would write a one page, not a certain number
of words, but just write one page on a particular subject, I'm sure we'd come up with some contradictions
amongst ourselves. Over 1,500 years, 40 different people, three different languages, three different
continents and you have one complete perfect book. Why? Because of the author. Because
inspiration reveals the greatness of God. That God is able to take the different personalities
of the human penmen and he's able to communicate his very word to us. It's amazing. You think
about God's greatness being revealed in that manner. This morning as we think about the
process of inspiration, I want you to consider with me number two, the product of inspiration.
The product of inspiration. Because the Bible is given by inspiration, it is literally the
word of God and is therefore profitable. Notice what it says in 2 Timothy 3 and verse number
16. Because the scripture is given by inspiration, and we've looked there just for a moment,
the process of inspiration, you find that the truth is given to us with regard to the
product of inspiration. Because it is God-breathed, because it is the word of God, it is profitable.
It is profitable. There are certain things that we look to and we gain a measure of profit
from something and we can think about owner's manuals and how-to type of books. And the
reality is that if you were to get a particular manual on something, you had a particular
product that you were trying to operate and you wanted to operate that thing properly,
you would hope to have a manual written about that product by someone who knew something
about the product. Make sense? Right? Otherwise, it's probably not going to be really profitable.
So I can be very helpful. Hey, would you write a manual on how-to? And you're like, I've
never done that before. How am I supposed to write a manual on that? When I worked at
Sikorsky in the corporate world for a number of years, we would have standard operating
procedures. Many of you in the workplace, you understand standard operating procedures
and instructions. We'd also have work instructions. And I was regularly tapped and would…
within our department to write work instructions.
The idea of writing a work instruction at Sikorsky
was that someone that was considered
to be a subject matter expert in a particular area
would write a work instruction that someone
that had no knowledge of that particular field or work
could take that work instruction and complete the task.
That was the objective.
That's what we're seeking to do.
And I had the privilege during that period of time
to author several work instructions,
and we'd go through the process,
and it was quite enjoyable, actually.
We look at this book that we hold in our hands this morning.
It is given by inspiration.
Therefore, it is God's word, and it is profitable,
because God is the creator.
He knows everything.
He has all wisdom, and he has all power,
and so he's given us exactly what we need
within the pages of this book.
We find that here in 2 Timothy 3 and verse number 16,
he specifies in four different areas
how God's word is profitable.
Notice he says it's profitable for doctrine, for teaching.
We speak about doctrine.
Let me say this.
Doctrine matters.
Doctrine is important.
We find that the book of Titus is written,
if you were to read just the first chapter
and enter just a couple of verses
in the second chapter of the book of Titus,
you'll find three or four different references
that Paul is making to Titus about sound doctrine.
In fact, here, even within the context
of this passage of Scripture,
he says how the Bible is given by inspiration of God
and is profitable for doctrine.
He then says this in verse number two.
Preach the word of chapter four.
Be instant in season, out of season.
Reprove, rebuke, exhort.
Notice when he says with all longsuffering and doctrine,
for the time will come when they will not endure
sound doctrine, but instead, after their own lusts,
shall they keep to themselves teachers having itching ears.
Far too often today, doctrine is set aside
as people seek to say, well, let's just have unity.
The best way to have unity is to agree on this book.
Let me rephrase that.
It's not the best way to have unity.
It's really the only way to have unity
is by agreeing as to what God has said in this book.
We must be students of the book.
We often understand that we would speak about our faith.
Our faith.
The Bible says that we're to earnestly contend
for the faith that was once delivered,
that body of doctrine, that teaching,
and the Bible is given by inspiration of God
and therefore, the Bible is profitable for doctrine.
As a Baptist person, we would say, without any shame,
the Bible is our sole authority for faith and practice.
Why do you believe what you believe?
Well, let's look at what the Bible says.
And as we agree as to what God has given us in his word,
because God's word is authoritative
because it's given by inspiration,
it is therefore profitable for doctrine.
Notice he says this.
Not only is it profitable for doctrine,
but it's for reproof.
You know, reproof, to reprove someone,
to rebuke someone is to expose error.
It shows us, the Bible,
because it's given by inspiration of God,
the product of inspiration is that it's profitable.
It's profitable for doctrine,
but it's also profitable for reproof.
It shows us where we're wrong.
Before you began reading the Bible,
before you trust that Christ is your savior,
maybe you had ideas and thoughts about spiritual matters,
about heavenly things.
And then you got saved and you started reading the Bible
and you found out, man, I was wrong about some stuff.
I, like many people, had this idea, my belief.
I don't know where I got the belief.
I can't pinpoint that anyone ever sat me down
and taught me this, but my understanding,
if you were to ask me before I trust that Christ
is my savior, before I started reading the Bible,
hey, if you're to die, you're gonna go to heaven.
My thought, my belief, my understanding
of how I would get to heaven is by being a good person.
I kind of had this idea that if my good deeds
outweighed my bad deeds,
that somehow I would gain entrance to heaven.
I know a lot of people that still think that today.
A lot of people that I talk to and ask them about heaven,
that that's their understanding, that's their belief.
But you know what?
This Bible exposed that error.
Because the Bible says,
not by works of righteousness, which we have done,
but according to his mercy, he has saved us.
The Bible says, for by grace are you saved through faith
and that not of yourselves, it's the gift of God,
not of works, lest any man should boast.
And I had to be confronted with the truth
that what I thought was wrong.
But why was it wrong?
Because of this book.
Because this book is God's word
and it's given by inspiration and it's profitable,
not only for doctrine, but for reproof,
and it exposes error.
We could go on and on with error that's exposed,
but I need to move forward.
Notice it says this, for correction.
For correction.
I'm so thankful for this.
Because not only does God's word expose error,
but it corrects us.
Isn't that wonderful?
I mean, isn't it a terrible thing
when someone says, nope, that's wrong?
Okay, well then tell me how to do it right.
Correct it, right?
So God says, no, through his word,
he exposed the error in my thinking
with regard to salvation,
but then also at the same time gave me the truth
of salvation, corrected my wrong thinking.
Isn't that wonderful?
It's a blessing.
Sometimes, watching some basketball yesterday,
been watching a lot of basketball
over the last couple of months with the kids,
both Joseph and Brianna playing,
and going to a lot of games,
and sometimes a ref will keep calling a violation.
It's always exciting.
Sometimes they get whistle happy.
Let's just play the game, you know?
And sometimes, every once in a while,
Brianna didn't do it this year, she did it last year,
she kept getting called for this violation.
It wasn't a foul, just getting called for travel.
So in between quarters, she went to the referee
and she said, can you tell me what I'm doing wrong?
That referee was the authority on that court.
And you keep calling me for a travel,
but I wanna understand how am I traveling
with what I'm doing?
And guess what the referee did?
Explained it to her,
so that she could correct
and thus not get called for the violation.
God's word is profitable for doctrine,
for reproof, for correction.
How to correct that which is wrong,
that which has been exposed.
But then also the Bible says,
for instruction in righteousness.
How to stay right.
How to live a life that pleases God.
For instruction in righteousness.
I'm thankful that God's given us this book,
and this book provides us with instruction for living.
You wanna know how to be a good husband?
Read the Bible, seriously.
You say, oh, I got this really good book
on so-and-so wrote about being a good husband.
I'm not suggesting that there's not
any other good books out there,
but I'm suggesting that if you read other books
and not this book, you failed to get the proper source.
If someone's gonna write a book on being a father,
being a husband, being a wife, being a mother,
being fill-in-the-blank,
they better have gotten some truth from this book first.
Amen?
Dean's got a book on the back desk over there,
or on the back table, about how to song lead.
I've never read the book.
I'm sure there's some good things in there.
But you have to understand that we're talking about
song leading, we're talking about in the context
of a church, that there are some spiritual truths
that need to be understood before you're going
to just write about how to lead singing.
In the context of pleasing God,
in the context of doing things decently and in order,
in the context of they that worship him, John 4,
must worship him in spirit and in truth.
We find that the word of God is profitable.
The Bible not only is profitable,
the product of inspiration, but notice what the Bible says
in 2 Timothy 3 and verse 17.
The Bible equips the child of God.
He says that it's profitable for these things,
for doctrine, for reproof, for correction,
for instruction in righteousness.
Then notice verse 17, that the man of God may be perfect,
throughly furnished unto all good works.
The Bible equips the child of God.
It equips us.
I'm so thankful for the equipping.
I'm so thankful that the Holy Spirit of God
who lives within me, the Holy Spirit of God,
if you've been saved this morning that lives within you,
that he will guide you into all truth
and that he will help you to be in that place
where you're equipped, where you're complete
and throughly furnished unto all good works.
We mentioned on Wednesday evening,
as we've studied through Psalm 37,
a couple of different references
where the psalmist says, do good.
We ask the question this way, how do you know what's good? Who determines good? God alone.
The only one who is good, He's the one that determines what is good.
And we find this morning that the Bible is profitable, the Bible equips.
But the truth of inspiration, we talked about the process of inspiration, the product of inspiration,
and we think about the truth that it's profitable, that it equips us.
But I want you to consider this morning that the truth of inspiration results in several things.
Number one, it results in this, that this book, the Bible, is pure. It's pure.
In Proverbs 30 and verse number 5, it's a precious verse that deals with the fact that the Bible is pure
and also deals with the truth that we mentioned about verbal plenary inspiration.
The Bible says this in Proverbs 30 and verse number 5, every word of God is pure.
He is a shield unto them that put their trust in Him.
The psalmist says this in Psalm 119 and verse number 140,
thy word is very pure, therefore thy servant loveth it.
Whew, man, it's a pure book.
Everything that is contained within the pages of this Bible from Genesis 1-1 through Revelation 22-21,
it is absolutely pure in everything that is contained therein.
And we look at the Bible and we understand that the Bible says that all Scripture is given by inspiration of God.
And because it is the word of God, it's pure.
There are some that say they don't agree with what God's word is.
So then they have difficulty with what God's word says because they don't agree with what God's word is.
We talk about the word of God being pure, the Bible being pure.
It is pure in all that it records.
The record that is provided is reliable.
It is trustworthy.
How do we know what happened?
We dealt with Hezekiah a couple of weeks ago.
How do we know what Sennacherib and Rabshakeh really said?
How do we know if it's true?
How do we know if Hezekiah didn't just make something up, if Isaiah was just making something up?
No, every word of God is pure.
So what Sennacherib and Rabshakeh said we can trust and we can say is a reliable source because every word of God is pure.
How do you know what happened in the garden?
We look at Genesis chapter number 3.
Is Genesis 3 foundational?
It's absolutely foundational.
If we don't have Genesis chapter number 3 understood, so many things fall apart.
But in Genesis chapter number 3, the Bible says that the serpent, who's more subtle than any beast of the field,
he enters into the garden and he says,
yea, hath God said.
How do we know if that's true?
Because every word of God is pure.
And the record of Genesis 3 is given to us.
Yes, it's the serpent that's speaking to Eve, but God has recorded it to us in the Bible because all scripture is given by inspiration of God.
Thus, the Bible is pure.
It is trustworthy.
It is reliable.
And we can say we understand with absolute certainty what happened in the garden in Genesis 3.
Why? Because God's given us a record.
He's given us a pure record.
The psalmist said this in Psalm 33 in verse number 14.
Notice what the Bible says, excuse me, verse number 4 in Psalm 33 and verse number 4.
For the word of the Lord is right and all his works are done in truth.
I'm thankful this morning that I can trust this book.
It's pure.
Every word of God is pure.
And we couple that and we understand that all scripture is given by inspiration of God.
And since all scripture is given by inspiration of God, this is the word of God and God's word is pure.
It is a trustworthy, reliable record that God has given to us.
And that's the product of inspiration.
Not only is it pure, we would say this, this book, the Bible, is incapable of error.
It's incapable of error.
By the way, I'm thankful for that truth.
We live in a time today that so many people want to say, well, this is an error and that's an error and there's a problem over here.
I read a theologian of yesteryear many, many years ago.
I don't remember who it was at this point.
But he said this, if you think the Bible's got a mistake, then you're wrong.
You're mistaken.
And he said, you need to go back to the drawing board.
You need to dig in.
You need to study more.
See, there are nuggets that God has given us within his word.
As we study it and we dig in and we don't just look at some surface thing.
By the way, this morning, the reality is that there are so many things that can be found on the internet.
Be careful about the internet.
I mentioned this on Wednesday evening.
Oh, how careful we must be.
I've spoken to some people over the last couple of years that have come to me with errors, contradictions.
People that I know, and I'm not saying this prideful here boastfully, I know from their testimony, all right, so I'm not saying something that they've not said, that they don't read this book.
They don't read the Bible.
And yet, they're going to come to me with some contradictions of some, this verse says this, but way over here in this chapter, it says this.
Say, where did you find that?
And all of a sudden, if you just go on Google and type in biblical contradictions, it's like the first two that pop up.
That's where they found it.
And be careful, because God's word is incapable of error.
Why?
Because our God is perfect, and our God is incapable of error.
Titus, in chapter 1 and verse number 2, says this, the book of Titus 1-2,
and hope of eternal life, which God that cannot lie promised before the world began.
I'm thankful that God is truth.
He cannot lie.
This book, the Bible, is incapable of error.
Why?
Because it's God's word.
See, if you write something, if you say something, if you speak as much as I speak, you're going to say something wrong.
We're humans.
But God is perfect.
He has given us a book that's perfect, because all Scripture is given by inspiration of God.
This book, because of the truth of inspiration, we talked about the process and the product,
because of the truth of inspiration, this book is authoritative.
It's authoritative.
See, notice what the psalmist says, and we'll finish here in Psalm 19.
Notice what the psalmist says.
We talk about this book being authoritative.
In Psalm 19 and verse number 7, the Bible says,
The law of the Lord is perfect, converting the soul.
The testimony of the Lord is sure, making wise the simple.
The statutes of the Lord are right, rejoicing the heart.
The commandment of the Lord is pure, enlightening the eyes.
The fear of the Lord is clean, enduring forever.
The judgments of the Lord are true and righteous altogether.
Notice verse 10 of Psalm 19.
More to be desired are they than gold, yea, than much fine gold.
Sweeter also than honey and the honeycomb.
Moreover, verse 11, by them is thy servant warned, and in keeping of them there is great reward.
God's Word is authoritative because of what it is, because it's God's Word.
Begin to think about people, humans, interactions that we have, one with another.
Someone's word that might be authoritative.
Someone that has some position of authority.
The word that they give is authoritative because of the position that they hold.
We understand that in life. We deal with that.
I mentioned a reference a moment ago about on the basketball court.
The coaches can disagree, the players can disagree,
but that guy with that black and white striped shirt and that whistle,
he is the authority on that court.
Like it or not, it's just the way it works.
We can think about a number of positions that people hold and the word that they speak having authority,
but I want you to understand that God is the eternal God.
He's the omnipotent God. He rules. He reigns.
He is the Lord God Almighty, and He's given us the Bible.
And because He's given it to us by inspiration, because every word of God is pure,
because of the truth of inspiration, then we understand that this book is authoritative.
You can say, I disagree with it.
That's up to you.
You've got a problem with God because God's Word is authoritative.
God's Word is authoritative.
I think this morning that it's in our best interest as we find in Psalm 19 and also in
2 Peter 1, it's in our best interest to take heed.
It says, moreover by them is my servant warned.
You know, warnings are good for us.
People get warnings.
We're familiar with warnings, by the way.
Go home this afternoon and you look at some products that you have at home and you look
at the labels, especially cleaning supplies, warning labels, right?
We're familiar with warnings.
I was sharing with someone this past week about warnings.
We see warnings on the road.
Bridge out ahead.
Aren't you thankful for that warning?
Can you imagine if no one took the time to put the sign up, you just kept on driving?
It'd be a problem.
God's given us warnings in His Word.
Moreover by them is my servant warned.
This is this, and in keeping of them, there is great reward.
Wow.
Who's the reward come from?
The one who gave us the book.
He said this to Joshua, this book of the law shall not depart out of thy mouth, but thou
shalt meditate therein day and night.
Why?
Why is it so important that this book not depart out of my mouth?
Why is it so necessary that I meditate in it day and night?
Because it's God's Word.
Then shalt thou find good success, have thy way prosperous and find good success.
Think about the truth of Psalm 1.
He shall be like a tree that's planted by the river.
Who is it?
The one that meditates on the Word day and night because they understand what it is.
This morning, we thank the Lord for giving us the Bible.
What a blessing.
This book, someone said this, this book is the mind of God, the state of man, the way
of salvation, the doom of sinners, the happiness of believers.
Its doctrines are holy, its precepts are binding, its histories are true, its decisions are
immutable.
Read it to be wise, believe it to be safe, practice it to be holy.
This morning, I believe that inspiration reveals the greatness of God.
God used, we talked about the process, 40 men, over 1500 years, 3 languages, 3 continents
to give us one complete pure book.
It's precious and it reveals to us how great God is that He could do that.
The one that transcends time, the one that's outside of time was able to do that because
all scripture is given by inspiration of God.
This morning, I hope that we have a newfound appreciation for the Bible.
We'll talk about it as we go over the next few weeks of understanding how God's greatness
is revealed through giving us the Bible, but then what is my response to it?
We already gave a little indication of that with Joshua 1 and verse number 8.
How I approach the Bible, what I do with the Bible, how I live by the precepts that are
contained there and why?
Because I understand it's from God.
It's not just Paul speaking, it's not just Isaiah speaking, it's not just David speaking,
it's God speaking because all scripture is given by inspiration of God.
What a joy, what a blessing that every day you have the opportunity in your life to open
up this book to hear from God, to hear from God, to be benefited because it's profitable,
to be helped.
This book is precious.
This book is the greatest of all books because God, who alone is great, is its author.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you.
Thank you for loving us.
We thank you this morning for the Bible.
We thank you that in your infinite wisdom, you determined that you would give us the
Bible.
You would give us your word.
I thank you that the Bible says of itself that we're to take the sword of the Spirit,
which is the word of God, that your word is quick and powerful and sharper than a two-edged
sword, that your word endures forever.
Forever, O Lord, thy word is settled in heaven.
Heaven and earth shall pass away.
All this book will endure.
Man shall not live by bread alone, but by every word of God.
Lord, I pray this morning, you'd help us to see your greatness revealed through inspiration.
We'd understand with a newfound appreciation how precious this Bible is.
I pray, God, that you would help us to allow it to be profitable in our lives for doctrine,
for reproof, for correction, for instruction.
God, I pray that we'd be equipped, thoroughly furnished.
Pray, God, that we would submit ourselves, understanding the authority of this book.
It's pure, free of error.
Oh, how thankful each of us ought to be this morning to have a Bible.
I pray, Lord, that if there's one that's not sure of heaven, Lord, we spoke this morning
how the Holy Scriptures make thee wise unto salvation, the truth that's contained therein
with regard to eternal life.
Lord, I pray that if one's not sure of heaven, that we'd have an opportunity to take a Bible
and show them how they could know for sure that heaven's their home.
Lord, someone this morning, many that may be struggling with a variety of areas in their
lives, because of understanding the preciousness of this book, it's been given by inspiration
of God.
It is the very Word of God, and it's profitable for us.
God, you would help us that you'd meet the needs that are represented amongst the congregation
this morning, understanding that we must run to your Word to get the answer, to understand
the path that should be before us.
I pray, Lord, that you'd move and work in this few moments of invitation as only you
can.
I pray that decisions would be made that would please thee, for it's in Christ's name we
pray.