Chapter number nine, and I mentioned to you last week,
we did not get through the entirety of the message.
And so this is Daniel 70th week, part two,
and we'll look at some of this in Daniel nine,
give a brief overview with regard
to what we looked at last week,
and then finish up with some thoughts this evening.
Daniel chapter number nine.
I mentioned this last week that as we get into
and we continue further into the book of Revelation,
that really the book of Daniel is a key
that unlocks much understanding
with regard to the book of Revelation.
All scripture is given by inspiration of God.
The Bible tells us that no scripture
is of any private interpretation.
And so we compare scripture with scripture.
And when you come to these end times,
eschatology type things,
and you look at the end times events,
there is so much that the Bible deals with
and information that is given to us.
And it's certainly a blessing,
even as we read in the book of Revelation
to study prophecy,
God's put it in the canon of scripture
so that we would be aware of,
but we must understand that it's absolutely necessary
that we have a balance in our lives.
We can get way out of balance
by just focusing so much on eschatology
and all the end times things that we fail to do today,
the things that we're supposed to do.
And so there's gotta be a balance
and God's given us the truth so that we would know it,
but we must understand that he's given us
a responsibility today to be his ambassadors,
his representatives.
I was chatting with someone recently
and I'm thankful for the truth that Jesus is coming.
We don't know when, but we do know that he's coming.
And whenever that moment will take place,
there's not another lost person
that I'll ever share the gospel with.
There's not another prayer that I'll ever pray.
There's not another dollar I'll ever give to missions.
It's all gonna be the things of this time,
this opportunity that we have today
to do those things will be no longer.
Yes, it will be glorious, will be in his presence
forevermore, we'll be worshiping him
and what a blessing that will be,
but we have much work to do.
In Daniel nine and verse 24,
I'll read the verses of scripture
with regard to Daniel 70th week.
The Bible says this,
70 weeks are determined upon thy people
and upon thy holy city to finish the transgression
and to make an end of sins
and to make reconciliation for iniquity
and to bring in everlasting righteousness
and to seal up the vision and prophecy
and to anoint the most holy.
And so verse 24 is kind of an overview
of the entire prophetic aspect of this particular vision.
The details are then given to us in verse 25,
know therefore and understand.
Again, God wants us to know,
he wants us to have that understanding
that from the going forth of the commandment
to restore and to build Jerusalem
unto the Messiah, the Prince,
shall be seven weeks and three score and two weeks.
The street shall be built again
and the wall even in troublous times.
And after three score and two weeks
shall Messiah be cut off, but not for himself.
The people of the Prince that shall come
shall destroy the city and the sanctuary
and the end thereof shall be with a flood
and unto the end of the war desolations are determined.
And he shall confirm the covenant with many for one week,
that's the Antichrist.
And in the midst of the week,
he shall cause the sacrifice and the oblation to cease
and for the overspreading of abominations,
he shall make it desolate even until the consummation
and that determined shall be poured upon the desolate.
And so last week we talked about this,
went through it, we talked about the prophecy
specifically being in regard to the nation of Israel.
He says this is in verse 24,
70 weeks are determined upon thy people
and upon thy holy city.
So the Jewish people, the city of Jerusalem,
we asked when the clock starts and we see in 25,
in verse 25, from the going forth of the commandment,
we went over to the book of Nehemiah
and we noticed the fulfillment of that
and understanding when the clock started
and looking at those first 69 weeks,
the seven weeks with regard to the rebuilding
as we see there in verse number 25,
the restoring and rebuilding of Jerusalem
unto the Messiah, then 62 more weeks after that,
Messiah would be crucified
and we looked at all of those things and we said this,
understanding being on this side of history
and looking back, that the 69 weeks
were fulfilled literally, we have every reason
to expect that the 70th week
will be fulfilled literally as well.
And so we have that understanding,
we said this, that if it was not to be fulfilled,
we mentioned there's a gap and that gap
is what we're living in, the church age,
the gap between the 69th and 70th week, why?
Well, because if not, the 70th week
would have ended in AD 37
and obviously, we're well past AD 37
and therefore, we understand that there's a gap
and it's an unknown period of time
and so it's almost like the clock started
but then the clock stopped when Messiah,
the Lord Jesus Christ was crucified
and of course, his resurrection and ascension
and we have the church age and then what is it
that when is it that that 70th week will resume
is when the peace treaty is set forth,
we understand the rapture of the church,
the Antichrist appears, the peace treaty,
we mentioned last week that the Antichrist will appear,
he'll make that seven year pact
and then in the midst of the week,
as we read just a moment ago in verse 27,
that pact will be broken and then we see
at the end of the seven years of tribulation,
the fulfillment of Daniel's 70th week
that the Lord Jesus Christ, Revelation 19
will return with his saints
and will establish his millennial reign.
Now, I preached all that in like 55 minutes last week
and I just gave you like a four minute overview, okay?
And if you weren't here last week, maybe go back,
it's on the internet and you can listen to the whole message
I just gave you a quick overview, why?
Because if I went through it all again,
we would still have part two to continue next week
and I really don't wanna do that
and so we tried to give that to you very quickly.
The really, the ending thought with regard to
Daniel's 70th week is to try for us to understand
as we study the scriptures to have an understanding,
what is the purpose of Daniel's 70th week?
What's the purpose of the tribulation?
And I said this a couple of times last week
and it's important that we kinda get this deep into our
hearts and into our minds.
So often people wanna talk about when is the rapture?
And of course we know the Bible specifically says
that no man knows the day or the hour
and yet the question continues to be one
that's asked and debated and so on and so forth.
But we come to the place and I often have said
that before we answer the question when,
we really have to understand why is there a rapture?
Why is there a tribulation?
If I can understand why there's a tribulation
and I can understand why there's a rapture,
that helps me understand when the rapture will take place.
Now don't misunderstand me, not when as in a day,
but when as in the timeline.
Does that make sense?
And so we have that there's these various thoughts,
if you will, theologically.
I don't recommend that you go watch the internet
and look this stuff up.
I recommend that you study the Bible
and let the Bible be our teacher and our guide.
But there are really three different views
with regard to when the rapture will take place.
A pre-tribulation rapture,
meaning that the rapture takes place
and then Daniel's 70th week.
There's a position that is a mid-tribulation rapture
at the three and a half year mark.
And then there's a position that's a post-trib rapture
at the end of the seven years
is when the rapture will take place,
the seven years of tribulation.
Now we understand as we look through
and try to answer the question when,
again, not a date, but sequence-wise, timeline-wise,
when is that going to happen?
We really have to answer the question,
why is there a tribulation?
Why is it that God has given to us in his word
this information about the 70th week?
What is it that God is doing?
And why is there going to be a rapture?
We look specifically,
and it's been a couple of months ago now,
but in Revelation chapter number four,
it's really a beautiful picture of the rapture.
In chapter two and chapter three of the book of Revelation,
you're reading about the seven churches in Asia.
You read about the seven churches,
they're literal churches.
We studied, we understood the letters that were written,
the messages that were given,
how they represent churches
throughout the entirety of the church age.
And then in chapter number four, John is caught up.
He's in the throne room of heaven, chapter four and five,
giving us that parenthetical, if you will,
with regard to a pause,
with regard to the sequence of events
where chapter six will begin the seven seals,
that start of the tribulation.
And we find John is in the throne room of heaven
and all the worship and all that's taking place
in Revelation four and five.
And so you read everything about the local church
in chapter two and chapter three.
And then there's this picture of the rapture
to begin chapter four.
And you don't read about the church again
until chapter 19, when the saints are coming back.
with the Lord Jesus Christ.
And so we begin to understand some of what's taking place
as you study the scriptures.
Let me make a couple of comments
before I get into the three purposes this evening.
And number one, let me say this,
when you study the scriptures,
you're gonna see references to the day of Christ
and the day of the Lord.
And you'll see those references,
and it's important that we understand
that both of those start at the same time,
at the beginning of the 70th week.
But really what's happening is when the Bible
is talking about the day of Christ,
it's talking about the events
that are taking place in heaven.
When it talks about the day of the Lord,
he's talking about the events
that are taking place on earth.
And so if we don't understand that,
we can kind of get that convoluted and confused
with regard to what are these events
that are being referred to,
what's taking place and what's going on here.
I mentioned at the very beginning
of the study of the book of Revelation,
that the book of Revelation gives us these scenes,
there are scenes in heaven,
there are scenes on earth,
and some of those things are taking place simultaneously,
but because it's written for us,
they cannot be written simultaneously,
they have to be separated by verses and chapters, why?
Because otherwise it'd be super confusing
if you're trying to write it simultaneous.
And so those scenes will be at times in heaven,
and those would be things with regard to the day of Christ,
whereas the things on earth,
those earthly events would be referring
to the day of the Lord.
Let me also say this,
the scriptures plainly teach
that there's a time in which Jesus is coming for his saints,
and a time in which Jesus is coming with his saints.
So when we understand that,
that's very different,
to come for something, to come with something.
And so we find that the Bible teaches us,
if you were to read the book,
look at 1 Thessalonians, turn over there,
let's look at the verses.
In 1 Thessalonians chapter number four,
we find here that the Bible is going to give us this picture,
this teaching with regard to the rapture of the church,
and Paul is giving this instruction
to the church in Thessalonica.
There's some that will say,
the word rapture is not even in the Bible.
Yeah, but the word rapture means to be caught up
in the Greek word is there,
where we get the word rapture,
we find that here in verse 17, caught up.
And so we see that,
and it's really of no consequence
that the English word is not there.
You know, the English word for dinosaur
is not in the Bible either.
You know that, right?
Dinosaur is not in the Bible.
Does anyone know why the word dinosaur is not in our Bible?
Is it because dinosaurs don't exist?
That they didn't exist?
No, does anyone know the reason?
The word didn't get invented until the 19th century,
like 1840 or something like that.
And so the word wasn't even around in the English vocabulary
and so that's why it's not in our Bibles.
Doesn't mean that we think dinosaurs didn't exist
and so on and so forth.
And so it's a very weak argument,
but in 1st Thessalonians 4 in verse 13,
the Bible says,
but I would not have you to be ignorant brethren
concerning them which are asleep,
that you sorrow not even as others which have no hope.
For if we believe that Jesus died and rose again,
even so them also which sleep in Jesus
will God bring with him.
For this we say unto you by the word of the Lord,
that we which are alive and remain
unto the coming of the Lord
shall not prevent them which are asleep.
For the Lord himself shall descend from heaven,
notice the Lord himself shall descend from heaven
with a shout, with the voice of the archangel,
with the trump of God.
The dead in Christ shall rise first,
then we which are alive and remain,
notice shall be caught up together with them in the clouds
to meet the Lord in the air.
And so shall we ever be with the Lord,
wherefore comfort one another with these words.
So that's when Jesus is coming for his saints.
We see this also,
if you were to look at 2nd Thessalonians 2
and verse number one where Paul says,
now we beseech you brethren
by the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ
and by our gathering together unto him.
And so this is when he's coming for his saints.
We then see that the Bible says
that he's gonna come with his saints.
Stay here in chapter, in 2nd Thessalonians,
look in chapter three and look here,
actually, sorry, 1st Thessalonians chapter three
and verse number 13 to the end,
he may establish your hearts unblameable in holiness
and even our father at the coming
of our Lord Jesus Christ, notice, with all his saints.
And so there's a distinction
between when Jesus comes for his saints
and when he comes with his saints.
If you look in the book of Revelation,
you'll see in Revelation four,
kind of the picture of the saints being raptured
and then in chapter 19, guess what?
We're coming back with Jesus
and you're gonna have the battle of Armageddon
and all that will take place
and we're coming back with him.
And so it's important that we understand that.
There's another important thing
that it's vital that we recognize
in 2nd Thessalonians chapter number two,
I read verse number one, but look at the context here
of what Paul is saying to the church in Thessalonica.
He tells them, now we beseech you brethren
by the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ
and by our gathering together unto him
that you be not soon shaken in mind or be troubled
neither by spirit nor by word nor by letter
ask from us as that the day of Christ is at hand.
Let no man deceive you by any means
for that day shall not come
except there come a falling away first
and that man of sin be revealed the son of perdition.
And so again, that would be referencing back to Daniel nine
and understanding the starting of that 70th week
that we're speaking of Daniel 70th week
at the midpoint of the tribulation,
we see in verse number four,
who opposeth and exalteth himself above all
that is called God that is worshiped
so that he as God sitteth in the temple of God
showing himself that he is God.
You look at Daniel nine 27, we read it a moment ago
and you see that exactly spoken of here
in 2nd Thessalonians two and verse four.
But now notice specifically what Paul says
in verses five through seven, he says,
remember ye not that when I was yet with you,
I told you these things.
Sometimes we forget, you ever forget
and you need to be reminded of something
and Paul says, remember, I told you these things,
but he's gonna remind them, he says in verse six
and now notice what he says,
ye know what withholdeth that he might be revealed
in his time and he gives further revelation
with regard to what he's speaking of in verse six
there in verse seven,
for the mystery of iniquity doth already work.
We find that John and we'll look there in a moment
says that there are many antichrists, right?
But he talks about the antichrist
and the spirit of antichrist and so on and so forth
and so he says, for the mystery of iniquity
doth already work, only he who now letteth will let
until he be taken out of the way.
2nd Thessalonians two and verse seven
is such an important verse for us to really understand
where we find that the Bible says
only he who now letteth will let
until he be taken out of the way.
One of the ministries of the Holy Spirit of God
is he is the restrainer and not only the restrainer,
but we understand that he is greater
than the evil forces that are working in our society today,
the antichrist, the spirit of antichrist
and we see that in fact, we often quote
the wonderful promise in the book of 1st John,
look there quickly in 1st John chapter number four
and I want you to see it's a promise
that we often quote just part of the verse
and here's how it goes,
greater is he that is in you than he that's in the world
and we love referencing that and we ought to,
but look in 1st John four,
the Bible says in verse number one,
beloved, believe not every spirit,
but try the spirits whether they are of God,
why, because many false prophets
are gone out into the world.
Hereby know ye the spirit of God,
every spirit that confesseth that Jesus Christ
has come in the flesh is of God
and every spirit that confesseth not
that Jesus Christ has come in the flesh is not of God
and this is that spirit of antichrist,
whereof ye have heard that it should come,
notice and even now already is it in the world,
ye are of God little children and have overcome them,
why, because greater is he that is in you
than he that is in the world
and so we find that the scripture there again,
when we compare scripture with scripture,
but 2nd Thessalonians chapter two,
only he who now letteth will let
until he be taken out of the way,
where's the Holy Spirit today?
Is in the believer, right?
The Bible says that the moment of salvation
that we are indwelled by the Holy Spirit of God
and with that indwelling,
we understand that we are the temple of the Holy Ghost,
which we have of course again,
the earnest of our inheritance at the moment of salvation
and so when the rapture of the church takes place
and all believers are removed,
the Holy Spirit indwells the believers in the Holy Spirit,
the one who now letteth will be taken out of the way.
What does that allow for?
Well, that allows for the antichrist
that reveals to start the 70th week
to have his way during that 70th week of Daniel's prophecy.
What do I mean by that?
Well, if you were to read in Revelation 11,
we're not gonna take the time,
but Revelation 11, verse number seven,
Revelation 13 and verse number seven,
it speaks not like we see here in 1 John 4
where the believers are overcomers
because greater is he that is in us
than he that is in the world,
but you read in Revelation 11 and Revelation chapter 13,
where the believers are being overcome.
There's a great contrast in what's taking place.
And so these things are helpful for us to be able
to understand again as we compare Scripture with Scripture
and begin to understand.
No man knoweth the day nor the hour.
Just very briefly, the reality is that if it were mid
or post, if we know what happens to start the 70th week,
you can identify the midpoint.
In fact, there are very specific things
that the book of Revelation discusses
that will take place at the midpoint of the tribulation
and also at the end of the tribulation.
So therefore, if it were mid or post,
every man could actually know the day and the hour.
Why?
Because you can do the math and you can figure it out.
It's a seven year period of time.
It's very easy to do.
And so we understand that.
So I said all that, that was all free.
That was not part of the notes last week.
That was not part of the purpose,
but I thought let's go ahead and fill the time up
and deal with some more things.
And so that is some helpful things for us
with regard to understanding this timeline.
So what is the purpose of the 70th week?
We know that Jeremiah refers to
at the time of Jacob's trouble.
We understand what is taking place.
Now remember, as we look here and try to identify
what is the purpose, a couple of,
I'm gonna give you three thoughts.
Look at Isaiah chapter 13.
The first one is this.
It's God's wrath and judgment upon rebellious man.
God's wrath and God's judgment upon rebellious man.
Does it mean that God's not judging today?
No, it just means that that time is marked distinctly
by God's wrath and God's judgment upon rebellious man.
Look in Isaiah 13 in verse number nine.
The Bible says this.
Behold, now notice it says the day the Lord cometh.
Now the day the Lord, that's gonna refer to events
that are taking place on earth, right?
The earthly events, we said that a moment ago.
Behold, the day the Lord cometh,
cruel both with wrath and fierce anger
to lay the land desolate and he shall destroy
the sinners thereof out of it.
For the stars of heaven and the constellations thereof
shall not give their light.
The sun shall be darkened and is going forth
and the moon shall not cause her light to shine.
And I will punish the world for their evil
and the wicked for their iniquity.
And I will cause the arrogancy of the proud to cease
and will lay low the haughtiness of the terrible.
It's pretty direct as to the purpose there
in just a few verses of scripture
with regard to God's wrath and God's judgment.
Number two, it's to reveal man's true nature.
What do I mean by that?
Well, look at Revelation nine and just so you know,
the first two purposes are very short.
It is the third purpose that will be
the lengthy one this evening.
And so Revelation chapter nine,
it reveals man's true nature,
really a purpose of the tribulation.
See, as we look here and we consider,
and again, as we begin studying through next week
as we look at chapter six and continue through
our study in the book of Revelation,
we'll see all of these things taking place.
This is actually the sixth trumpet.
So we have the seven seals judgments
that are already passed at this point of time
in the book of Revelation.
And then this is the time of the sixth trumpet.
And so you think about all of the judgment
that's already been poured out
and you look in Revelation nine in verse 20,
and it says this,
and the rest of the men which were not killed by these plagues
yet repented not of the works of their hands,
that they should not worship devils and idols of gold
and silver and brass and stone and of wood,
which neither can see nor hear nor walk,
neither repented they of their murders
nor of their sorceries nor of their fornication
nor of their thefts.
What are we seeing?
Well, man, even in God's judgment being poured out
is still standing in rebellion against God.
And it's really revealing the true nature of humanity.
And we see that it's not the only place
that's mentioned in Revelation,
but as we study through,
we'll make various references to that particular purpose.
Really the purpose
that I wanna focus our attention on this evening
is that it's the Lord is preparing Israel for her Messiah.
All right, the Lord is preparing Israel for her Messiah.
Now we understand that the prophecy
said that Messiah would be cut off.
The true Messiah, Jesus Christ is the Messiah.
The Jews rejected Jesus, right?
The Jews rejected him, he came to his own
and his own received him not.
We read that in John chapter number one.
We read that they,
when they're standing there before Pilate,
they cry out, crucify him.
You can read all of the various accounts in the gospels
with regard to the crucifixion
and all that was taking place.
And Pilate, of course, was trying to allow Jesus
to not have to go through this.
He wanted to say, I find no fault in him
and kind of wash his hands of it.
But they begin to cry out.
And what did they cry?
They said, away with him, away with him, crucify him.
Pilate saith unto them, shall I crucify your king?
And they said, we have no king but Caesar.
And that's in John chapter 19 in verse number 15.
And so we find that the Jewish people, the Jewish nation,
they rejected Jesus Christ as being their Messiah, all right?
When Paul preaches and he goes to the synagogues
during the various ministries
in which he's going and preaching,
the Bible tells us that he reasons out of the scriptures
and what does he do?
He says, the Jesus that I'm preaching to you, he is Christ.
The Jesus, the man that they knew,
that they were familiar with, Jehovah is salvation,
God incarnate, that he is the Messiah,
the anointed one, the son of God.
But they rejected him.
So you know that Israel, at this particular time
and after their rejection, they, as we look,
and I want you to turn to the book of,
well, look at the book of Romans.
We'll look there first.
And in Romans chapter number 11,
we see a very important truth and teaching
that God gives us with regard to Israel.
Now, the church is a mystery.
And Paul mentions that.
You read the book of Ephesians
and you talk about the mystery of the church
and the church is a mystery in this sense,
that the church is gonna be made up of Jews and Gentiles.
How, what do we mean by that?
Well, the church is made up of individuals
that have trusted the Lord Jesus Christ
as their personal savior.
How does a Jewish person get saved?
How does a Gentile get saved?
There's only one way for anyone to get saved
and that's by the way of the cross, amen.
And you're not going to heaven
because of your particular ancestry.
You're not having this, well, you're Jewish,
so you get a free pass.
No, the Jews and Gentiles alike,
we're all saved the same way.
We gotta come by the way of the cross
and understand that Jesus Christ is the Messiah,
that He is the Son of God.
He died for our sins.
He was buried.
He rose again and He offers eternal life.
And so the church would be this mystery.
The church doesn't replace Israel, okay?
I mentioned that last week.
I said this last week that Persia is not going anywhere,
but neither is Israel, okay?
We understand as we study some of these things
in the world events and we're gonna,
one side wants to erase one side from the map
and the other side wants to erase,
neither are being erased from the map.
It's just not gonna happen.
Why?
Because we have Bible prophecy.
We have understanding that God has given to us
with regard to these end times.
And so when we think about the church as this mystery,
Jew and Gentile, it's the bride of Christ.
So the rapture, He's coming back for His bride.
He's coming back for the church.
Praise God.
I'm thankful to be part of the church.
And the church is the organization,
the organism that Jesus is using at this hour
in this time in that gap between the 69th and 70th week.
And we're blessed to be part of the church.
Hallelujah.
But what's gonna happen is that the Jews today,
those that have not been saved,
they're looking for Messiah,
but they're gonna accept the Antichrist.
That's what's gonna happen.
They're gonna accept Him as their Messiah.
That's why the peace treaty, the pact,
that's why all that stuff's gonna happen
because they're looking for their Messiah.
And by the way, as we study through the book of Revelation,
you're gonna see all sorts of things
that the Antichrist is gonna do to deceive, right?
And they're going to embrace and they're gonna accept.
And then of course, he's gonna break that peace treaty
and all the things that are gonna take place.
But we find that Romans 11 gives us this insight
with regard to really the purpose of the tribulation,
preparing Israel to receive her Messiah.
And notice in verse 25,
we don't have time to read all of Romans 11.
I would encourage you to do that.
But in Romans chapter 11,
it's talking about the branch and it being grafted in
and what a great picture, how we were grafted in.
Why? Because of their unbelief.
In fact, look at verse 20.
It says, well, because of unbelief, they were broken off
and thou standest by faith.
Be not high-minded, but fear.
For if God spared not the natural branches,
take heed lest he also spare not thee.
And we see this amazing teaching with regard to the church.
But then look at verse 25.
He says this, for I would not brethren,
that ye should be ignorant of this mystery.
So what do we understand right away
as Paul is beginning to explain this?
It's a mystery. What does that mean? It's not been previously known.
So it's now being revealed, this idea of progressive revelation,
and he says, I don't want you to be ignorant.
I want you to be informed. I want you to be learned. I want you to understand this.
So notice he says that you should be ignorant of this mystery.
I would not, brethren, that you should be ignorant of this mystery,
lest you should be wise in your own conceits.
By the way, the Bible says in Romans 1, professing themselves to be wise, they became fools.
We don't need to over-spiritualize the scriptures. We don't need to do all of that crazy stuff.
No, we just accept the Bible for what it is as the Word of God.
And notice at the end of verse 25 that blindness, in part, is happened to Israel.
This is a spiritual blindness. You remember in John 9 when Jesus healed the man that was born blind?
And at the end of the passage, the Jewish people that are there, they say this,
are we blind also? And the sad reality of that is that they could see physically,
but they were blind spiritually. And spiritual blindness is so much worse than physical blindness.
Remember the Bible tells us in 2 Corinthians chapter number 4
that the little g God of this world hath blinded the minds of them which believe not,
lest the light of the glorious gospel should shine unto them.
Now the nation of Israel as a people, because of their rejection of Messiah,
there's this blindness that has happened. Now understand it says in part.
So what does that reveal to us? Well, it reveals to us that Jewish people still can be saved today.
Hallelujah. Listen, you understand that when Paul, he's writing it, he was Jewish.
Right? We're good? Like he was Jewish. And he's writing it. Not only was he Jewish,
but he said in chapter 10, brethren, my heart's desire and prayer to God for Israel is that they
might be saved. And so obviously he believed that they could be saved, that the blindness was in
part. Again, it's not all of them, but this blindness, it's a real thing.
And it's been for 2000 years now, generationally passed down. And he says this blindness in part
happened to Israel, but then notice the last phrase, until the fullness of the Gentiles be
come in. And so he's revealing here again, this timeline, if you will. And then we look in verse
26 and it says this. And so all Israel shall be saved. As it is written, there shall come out of
Zion, the deliverer and shall turn away ungodliness from Jacob. Now, Jacob, it's interesting every
time the term Jacob is used, it's really dealing with not only Israel, but Israel in its rebellion.
And so we find that he says in verse 27, for this is my covenant unto them. When I shall take away
their sins as concerning the gospel, they are enemies for your sakes, but as touching the
election, they are beloved for the father's sakes, for the gifts and calling of God are without
repentance. God made promises and God is going to fulfill his promises. As wicked as Israel is today,
and they are, they're in rebellion, they're in rejection, they're still God's people.
And that's hard for some people to accept. And I understand that. But the Bible, we have to trust
what the Bible says. And so it says in verse 30, for as ye in times past have not believed God,
yet they now obtain mercy through their unbelief. Let me reread that. For as ye in time,
times past have not believed God, yet have now obtained mercy through their unbelief.
Even so, have these also now not believed that through your mercy, they also may obtain mercy
for God hath concluded them all in unbelief, that he might have mercy upon all. So we read this
portion of scripture and we come to verse 26. And I read the entire context there in verse 26.
And so all Israel shall be saved. There are false teachers that have gotten onto platforms that they
get great, great numbers of people that watch them. And they use that verse of scripture out
of context and say, Jewish people are saved. It's not what it teaches. Here's how we know that.
Look at the book of Ezekiel very quickly, Ezekiel chapter number 20. And I hope to kind of wrap this
all together and help us really grasp this evening with regard to God preparing Israel to receive
her Messiah, to receive the Lord Jesus Christ. So in Ezekiel chapter 20,
we'll begin reading in verse 33.
And the Bible says this, as I live, saith the Lord God, surely with a mighty hand and with stretched
out arm and with fury poured out, will I rule over you. And I will bring you out from the people
and will gather you out of the countries wherein ye are scattered with a mighty hand and with a
stretched out arm and with fury poured out. And I will bring you into the wilderness of the people
and there will I plead with you face to face, like as I pleaded with your fathers in the wilderness
of the land of Egypt. So will I plead with you, saith the Lord God, and I will cause you to pass
under the rod and I will bring you into the bond of the covenant. And I will purge out from among
you the rebels and them that transgress against me. I will bring them forth out of the country
where they sojourn and they shall not enter into the land of Israel. And ye shall know that I
am the Lord. Again, the purpose, God preparing Israel to receive Messiah. Verse 39, as for you,
O house of Israel, thus saith the Lord God, go ye, serve ye everyone his idols and hereafter also,
if you will not hearken unto me, but pollute ye my holy name no more with your gifts and with your
idols. For in mine holy mountain, in the mountain of the height of Israel, saith the Lord God,
there shall all the house of Israel, all of them in the land serve me. There will I accept them
and there will I require your offerings and the first fruits of your oblations with all your holy
things. I will accept you with your sweet savor when I bring you out from the people and gather
you out of the countries wherein you have been scattered and I will be sanctified in you before
the heathen. And ye shall know that I am the Lord when I shall bring you into the land of Israel,
into the country for the which I lifted up mine hand to give it to your fathers. And there shall
you remember your ways and all your doings wherein you have been defiled and you shall loathe
yourselves in your own sight for all your evils that you have committed. And ye shall know that
I am the Lord. This is the third time we're reading that statement. When I have wrought with you for
my namesake, not according to your wicked ways or according to your corrupt doings, O ye house of
Israel, saith the Lord God. So turn back to Romans. We see what's taking place there in this Ezekiel
prophecy. We see Romans 11 with regard to what we've read a moment ago with regard to verse 25
and 26. He says that blindness in part has happened to Israel until the fullness of the Gentiles be
come in. And what is the timing of that? How is that all going to happen? We find again that the
blindness is partial, it's temporary. The fullness of the Gentiles, that full number of Gentiles that
will be saved. Remember in 2 Peter chapter 3, the Lord is not slack concerning his promise,
as some men count slackness, but is long-suffering to us-ward, not willing that any should perish,
but that all should come to repentance. And so the fullness of the Gentiles is going to come in
and that's when the church age, quote-unquote as we know it, ends. Tribulation. Israel. The time of
Jacob's trouble. Focus specifically on Israel, preparing Israel for her Messiah. So when it says
in verse 26, and so all Israel shall be saved as it is written, there shall come out of Zion the
deliverer and shall turn away ungodliness from Jacob. Understand that during that seven years,
remember there's the 144,000 witnesses, there's the two witnesses, everything that's taking place
is Jewish, Jewish, Jewish. Why? Because God's dealing with Israel to prepare them for their
Messiah. They rejected him the first time, they're going to accept the Antichrist, but he's preparing
them for his second coming at the end of the seven years, what we refer to there in Revelation 9,
when Jesus is coming all the way back to earth. All right, the battle of Armageddon is going to
take place, all that's going to transpire there, but what's going to happen during their seven
years of tribulation, billions of people are going to die. You say that's, why'd you say that? Well,
when you study through and you see the percentage of one-fifth of the part of the population died,
one-fourth of the part of, like billions of people are going to die. It's going to be absolutely
horrible what's going to happen during the seven-year tribulation. And billions of people
are going to die. God's dealing, he's pouring his, his wrath and his judgment upon a rebellious man.
He's revealing man's true nature, but ultimately he's dealing with Israel to prepare them for their
Messiah. And what's going to happen at the end?
of the tribulation, when it says,
and so all Israel shall be saved,
those that get all the way to the end of the tribulation,
they will accept and acknowledge that Jesus is Messiah,
and they will accept him.
So when he comes back, Revelation 19,
all that takes place,
they're going to accept their Messiah, by the way,
will be with him at that point,
and then he will establish his millennial reign.
Why is that important for us to understand?
Well, because the only people
that enter into the millennial reign
that are still in their flesh
are people that were saved Israel.
Chapter 11, verse 26,
when they enter from the tribulation into the millennial,
these people are saved.
So it's not saying, as again,
some false teachers have tried to propagate
that if you're Jewish, you're saved,
and they referenced this verse of scripture,
that's not true.
Every person for all have sinned
and come short of the glory of God.
In fact, even here in Romans,
he talks about the fact that they,
meaning the Jewish people,
that what it was given to them,
they had the oracles of God.
It says, what advantage then hath the Jew?
Or what profit is there in circumcision?
Chapter three, verse one and two,
much every way chiefly because that unto them
were committed the oracles of God,
but they rejected.
So during that 70th week of Daniel,
what is God doing?
He's specifically working to prepare Israel
to receive Messiah, and they will.
Those that are alive at the end,
they will receive Messiah
through all the other events that take place,
including the battle of Armageddon.
Those that do not accept Christ
will die during the tribulation.
And then those people enter into
the millennial reign of Christ.
That's how the population
rebuilds during the millennium.
Through those people that enter in
from the tribulation, do you ever wonder,
how's there a rebellion at the end of the millennial reign?
At the end of the thousand years,
there's this great rebellion that takes place.
It's because, yes, when they enter
into the millennium, they're saved,
but then as they produce and reproduce
and they have children,
their offspring, though a child
is gonna die at 100, and you see
the longevity of life and all those things,
there's gonna be a huge rebellion
at the end of the millennium,
and that's gonna be quenched very quickly.
You read that in Revelation 21.
Though Satan is bound for the thousand years,
Jesus Christ is ruling and reigning
for those thousand years.
He leads that rebellion when he's released
for a short season, and then Jesus deals with it,
it's settled, and then we enter into eternity
as you look through, well, you have
the great white throne judgment there
in chapter 20, then you enter into eternity,
and so why do I say all that?
Because we cannot clearly have the opportunity
or the ability to say, when are these things
gonna happen?
Again, I'm not talking date,
I'm talking sequence of events,
so don't misunderstand when I say when.
I'm talking sequence, not date,
and when we talk about the sequence,
pre, mid, post, understanding the why
helps us understand the when.
Does that make sense?
And we find that the purpose that God
is having this 70th week, remember,
70 weeks are determined upon thy people
and thy holy city.
That's what the prophecy is in Daniel 9.24.
It's to Daniel, his people are the Jews,
his holy city is Jerusalem.
And so none of these weeks, the 70th week included,
are not with regard to the church,
because the church is not spiritual Israel.
The church did not replace Israel.
You see so many things today with teaching
of replacement theology and dominion theology.
These are not sound teachings that you can find.
Oh, I understand they have great followings
and all of these things, but you have to twist
and take out of context so many portions of scripture
in order to come to these particular positions.
And so when we understand, okay, God's dealing with Israel,
that's the primary purpose of the tribulation.
So we then can identify, okay, the church is raptured
pre-tribulation, and those things that are taking place,
the day of Christ, those heavenly events,
while the day of the Lord, earthly events are taking place.
And so as we enter into Revelation 6,
starting next Sunday evening, and we begin to look
as those seals are first being opened,
the first one opened in Revelation 6,
and we begin to see the seals open,
this is the 70th week of Daniel's prophecy
from Daniel chapter number nine.
And as we study through it, we'll make references back
and we'll be able to see the scriptures
as you compare scripture with scripture,
how God will give us the truth that we need to understand.
And again, it's not so that we, listen,
we're not trying to set any dates, that'd be foolish,
all right, only a foolish individual would do that
because we know the scriptures say,
no man knoweth the day nor the hour,
but it does as we get closer and closer,
as we see the day approaching, and Hebrews 10.25
tells us that, speaking about gathering together
and so much more as you see the day approaching,
it reminds us that we have more work to do.
Just talking to a man on Thursday, Friday afternoon,
he's 81, 82 years old, and I said, how are you?
And I've known him for a number of years,
he said, I'm old, man, and I said, just like that,
I'm old, man, and he's a pastor, he's a preacher,
and he's like, it just reminds me I gotta work harder
because I don't have much time.
And he's saying that because of his age
and the fact that he recognizes
that soon he'll pass into eternity,
but can I say to every single one of us,
we just really don't know how much time we have.
We don't know.
You don't have to be 80 to die,
you don't have to be 90 to die, you can die as a child,
I mean, we understand that truth,
but we also recognize that Jesus is coming soon,
and there's a great work to be done.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love you, we thank you so much for loving us,
and God, I pray that you'd help us
to have an understanding of your word
and to be able to be settled and grounded
in the truth and the faith.
We thank you that you've given to us a Bible,
and Lord, we thank you for what you've revealed to us.
I pray that you'd help us to be good students of your word,
that we would take and apply the truth of your word
in our hearts and our lives, that you would help us, Lord,
even as we seek to understand some of these things,
to not be ignorant of these things,
Lord, help us to recognize
that you have given us a responsibility today
to exalt and magnify the Lord Jesus Christ,
to proclaim the gospel to every creature,
and I pray that you'd help us to be found busy
doing the work of the Lord.
I pray that in the moment of invitation,
that you'd work as only you can.
Help us, Lord, to just thank you
for what you've revealed to us,
and help us, Lord, to commit to you
that we will live day by day for your honor
and for your glory, and we'll thank you for it.
In Christ's name we pray.