of Hosea. And Isaiah, Jeremiah, Lamentations, Ezekiel, Daniel, Hosea. All right. So Hosea
chapter number 10, the first of what we'd often refer to as being the minor prophets.
And we are looking at this portion of scripture here this evening. And we'll actually look
at several different references here in the book of Hosea. And in just a couple of weeks,
as I mentioned this morning and mentioned again this evening, during our time of announcements,
we will have our annual revival meeting. And I'm of the opinion that every member,
every regular attender, and every visitor of Fellowship Baptist Church should be prepared
spiritually for a revival meeting. I mentioned it this morning, and I told you that I would
say it again this evening. Revival is not something that is scheduled. Revival is not
something that is voted upon. And there's a pastor, he's actually back in evangelism
now. He was an evangelist, and then he went into, I think he pastored, evangelist, pastored,
and now he's evangelist again. But Lou Rossi, some of you might know that name, and Lou
Rossi was holding a revival meeting at a church in Texas years ago and had scheduled that
meeting. And the church had contacted him leading up to the meeting. And about six months
ahead of time, they contacted him and said, we're excited, we're going to have revival,
we've put it on the calendar. And Brother Rossi said, okay, praise the Lord, we're looking
forward to being with you, and so on and so forth. And they said, no, no, we're really
going to have revival, we put it on the calendar. And he thought, okay, yeah, we're going to
be there. And about two months beforehand, they contacted him and said, Brother Rossi,
we had a business meeting, and we voted that we're going to have revival. And he said,
that sounds kind of silly, but that's what this little church, that was their mindset.
And Brother Rossi said, you know, you can't schedule, you can't vote on having revival.
But when he got there, he didn't know the church, the first time he was ever going to
be in the church, he found that it was a church that was hungering and thirsting after God.
A church that did not know how to actually articulate a body of believers, didn't know
how to articulate necessarily how hungry they were for a moving, a stirring of the Spirit
of God. And the best that they knew how to articulate and communicate to Brother Rossi
their heart was that we've scheduled it and we even voted on it. And we know that we could
listen to something like that and say, you can't vote on having revival. But their heart
was in a place that they were longing to hear from God. They were prepared spiritually.
For a number of years, and you know, it's, this is our annual revival meeting. There's
been a couple of years that we've not had a revival meeting because of extenuating circumstances.
But typically in the fall, we revival meeting in the spring, we have a missions conference.
And for a number of years, those first few years of pastoring, I kind of would shy away
in the weeks leading up to the missions conference of saying anything about missions, the weeks
leading up to the revival meeting, saying anything about revival. Why? Because the missionaries
were going to deal with that. The evangelists were going to deal with that. I kind of shied
away because I don't want to preach from the same text or maybe even say the same thing
that someone else is going to come in and say. And God, several years ago, did a work
in my heart and helped me to understand the importance of the position that I have as
the pastor to ensure that we as a church, as a body, as much as I can, help us to be
prepared for those special meetings. And I had a conversation with Brother Mershon a
number of years ago and shared these things with him. And he said, Brother, he said,
the best thing you can do as a pastor is preach on these things leading up to a special meeting
so that the people in the congregation are ready. He said, I go to churches and you know,
many of you know Brother Mershon, he's been here. He said, I go to churches and I find
that there are some churches that are revival resistant. He said, but then I find some churches
that are revival ready. He said, when I go to a church that's revival ready, I always
find out that there's some preparation work that took place and the people are ready.
And so this evening, I believe that it's imperative that we as the people of God are prepared
and that we truly desire as individuals and then corporately, we truly desire for God
to do a work. I was chatting with someone just this week and they were not speaking
specifically about Fellowship Baptist Church. They were speaking more in general terms,
but they made this comment to me. They said, the church is sick. The church is sick. You
know, if you look at the landscape of America and if you look at the landscape of the church
Christendom, broadly speaking, I understand why the person made the comment that they
did. We have churches so-called that no longer stand upon the authority of God's Word. Churches
that no longer follow the truth, the teaching of God's Word. And the church as a whole is
sick and some have described the church in America as being anemic. Some have described
it as being powerless. And then on the exact opposite flip side of those observations,
there are some that have observed and they've understood that there are some churches that
have perfected how to function almost like a corporation. And that's not what God's will
is either. And we're not a corporation. We are the body of Christ. And yes, there are
business things that have to take place, etc., etc. But God is a spirit and they that worship
Him must worship Him in spirit and in truth. And I am thankful for various tools that we
can have to be able to prepare us. But the reality is that we have a responsibility to
reach our world with the gospel. We have a responsibility to do something for God. This
is our time. It's our time. And we can curse the darkness or we can light a candle. Amen?
You say, Pastor, you know how bad it is in the world. It's terrible. I understand. And
lots of wickedness going on. But our God is on the throne. He's got a plan for us and
His word is powerful and His word works. Amen? It's effective and we're thankful for that. As
we look at this text in Hosea 10, I'm going to read one verse and give you the title and then
get into the message this evening. But in verse number 12, I want you to notice, and we'll come
back to this as we get to the end of the message this evening, but God says through the prophet
Hosea to Israel, He says, sow to yourselves in righteousness, reap in mercy, break up your
fallow ground, for it is time to seek the Lord, till He come and reign righteousness
upon you. Notice verse 13. You have plowed wickedness. You have reaped iniquity. You
have eaten the fruit of lies, because thou didst trust in thy way in the multitude of
thy mighty men. You know, the church that's described in Revelation 3 that we studied
several weeks ago, the church of the Laodiceans, was a church that was full of all sorts of
things. They were increased with goods and the Bible concludes that they said this, they
were in need of nothing. And God had a different perspective about the church of the Laodiceans
and we read in that text, and you don't need to turn there, but it's quite interesting and
I just preached on it a few weeks ago, but you find that He says, thou sayest, I am rich
and increased with goods and have need of nothing. And then it says this, and knowest
not that thou art wretched and miserable and poor and blind and naked. They were deceived.
Self-deception. It's the worst form of deception is self-deception. We find that this evening
as we look at Israel here is Hosea God is using and we won't take the time to develop
all of what's taking place here in the book of Hosea, but I want you to, if you're taking
notes this evening, to first, and we'll get to verse 12 in just a few moments, it'll be
really our second point, but note with me the indictment. Note with me the indictment.
As we begin reading chapter 10, we find that God begins the chapter by saying this. Notice
in verse number one, notice the first phrase, Israel is an empty vine. Now, you can see
the imagery immediately here in chapter number 10 and how this analogy and imagery plays
throughout the entirety of the chapter, but we begin in verse number one and God says
to the prophet Hosea, speaking of Israel, Israel is an empty vine. Now, what do you
think of when you think of a vine? You think of a vine that's going to produce fruit and
an empty vine is not the desire, it's not the purpose, and we find here that we understand
that as God is speaking here and he's bringing this indictment upon the nation of Israel
that he begins speaking about Israel being an empty vine. Notice, he bringeth forth fruit
unto himself. According to the multitude of his fruit, he hath increased the altars. According
to the goodness of his land, they have made goodly images. Then notice this aspect of
the indictment. He says their heart is divided. When I notice in verse number one when he
says Israel is an empty vine, it's not that they had no fruit, it's that they were bringing
forth fruit unto themselves. It's not that they did not have multitude because it says
according to the multitude of his fruit, he hath increased the altars.
And these altars are for these false gods, these idolatrous forms of worship.
And then he says in verse number two, their heart is divided.
I preached a message last Sunday morning about what is God doing in your heart.
And I spoke about the importance of the heart and about God moving in our heart and how
Paul noticed in Titus how God had put the same earnest care in the heart of Titus for
you as he's writing there in 2 Corinthians chapter number eight and verse number 16.
We find that God is concerned about your heart and my heart.
And here he says of Israel, they have a heart that's divided.
Jesus would go on to say that you can't serve God and mammon.
Amen?
Is that what he says?
But what's the picture there?
The picture is a divided heart.
And we mentioned last week on Sunday morning about those that serve God with a perfect
heart or with a whole heart and those that did not serve the Lord with a perfect heart,
their heart would be divided.
He says, now shall they be found faulty.
He shall break down their altars.
He shall spoil their images.
Notice verses three and four as the indictment continues, he says, for now they shall say
we have no king because we feared not the Lord.
What then should a king do to us?
They have spoken words, swearing falsely in making a covenant.
Thus judgment springeth up as hemlock in the furrows of the field.
The judgment would spring up.
Why?
Because of these words, these words as it's mentioned in verse number four that are swearing
falsely in making a covenant and this judgment would come.
We find that the indictment continues in verse five, the inhabitants of Samaria shall fear
because of the calves of Beth Avon for the people thereof shall mourn over it and the
priest thereof that rejoiced on it for the glory thereof because it is departed from
it.
Verse six, it also shall be, it shall be also carried into Assyria for a present to King
Jerob.
Ephraim shall receive shame and Israel shall be ashamed of his own council.
As for Samaria, her king is cut off as the foam upon the water.
The high places also of Avon, the sin of Israel shall be destroyed.
The thorn and the thistle shall come up on their altars and they shall say to the mountains,
cover us and to the hills, fall on us.
Notice verse nine, the Bible says this, O Israel, thou hast sinned and then notice this
phrase from the days of Gibeah.
There they stood.
The battle at Gibeah against the children of iniquity did not overtake them.
It is in my desire that I should chastise them and the people shall be gathered against
them when they shall bind themselves in their two furrows.
We notice in verse number nine, the Bible says, O Israel, thou hast sinned.
We find there's many times in which God will say that to his people.
We find that in Joshua, when they're going to take possession of the land, when they
have that defeat at Ai, that God says to Joshua, Israel hath sinned.
We find that because of the sin of Achan, that the entirety of Israel was impacted.
Thirty-six men lost their lives and here we find that God is saying to his people once
again, O Israel, thou hast sinned, but then he adds this phrase from the days of Gibeah.
It's very interesting because you begin to look at the timing here of the writing of
the book of Hosea in the reference of the days of Gibeah.
You really have to go all the way back to the period of the judges.
Now very quick overview of Israel's history.
God called Abram out of the Ur of the Chaldees.
He gave him a promise of a seed and of a land and we understand that Joseph went down to
Egypt as a slave and Jacob went there as well and God told Jacob not to fear going into
Egypt for there I will build of thee a great people and we find that they're there in Egypt.
Pharaoh dies and all that takes place and then God raises up Moses and God's gonna deliver
his people out of Egyptian bondage.
Thus we read the book of Exodus and we read of the time in which the children of Israel
leave Egyptian bondage and God delivers them out on high hand and shows his power.
We find that through the leadership of Moses, God's plan was to lead his people out of Egypt
and into the land of promise but in the book of Numbers, you read chapters 13 and 14, there
was doubt, there was fear, there was unbelief and we find that the ten bad spies, they influenced
the entire congregation that they would not enter into the land.
For 40 years they wandered in the wilderness and God then raised up Joshua and Joshua was
gonna be the human leader that would take the children of Israel into the land of promise
and God fulfilled all of those things and Joshua and his generation dies and you enter
into the period of the judges.
We find that the book of Judges and Jeff has been teaching in the Sunday school class in
the fellowship hall through the book of Judges and you find that there's this oft repeated
cycle in the period of judges for Israel's history and they have a time in which they
seem to be doing well and then they follow after idols and God brings a people group
to oppress them and that people group would vary based on the particular time of the book
of Judges and God would raise up some people group to judge his people, to oppress them
and through periods of being oppressed and all that would take place they would cry unto
God and God would raise up a judge.
God is faithful and God is gracious and he's merciful and he would raise up a judge and
provide deliverance and for a season, a period of time and it would vary the number of years
they would have peace and they would seem to be on the right path if you will and before
long they would repeat that cycle over and over and again in the book of Judges.
We find that after the Judges there's a period of the prophets if we would refer to it that
way and Samuel kind of just kind of taking and bridging that gap of Israel's history
and then we know that there was a period of the kings and here in the book of Hosea the
period of the kings is certainly a period that's taking place, Israel having a king
but we know that that first king was Saul and followed by David etc. etc. and so we
see very quickly this history and Hosea is writing just before Israel is being taken
captive.
They had at least three periods or three kings, Saul, David and Solomon, roughly 120 years
between those three kings where there was a united kingdom and after the reign of Solomon
there's a divided kingdom and we see Israel to the north and Judah to the south and Israel
had no good kings, Judah had periods of revival but Israel is the main audience for the book
of Hosea.
Why do I give you all of that history because you have to go all the way back to the period
of Judges to understand the statement that God is making to Israel.
And he says to them here in Hosea 10 in verse number 9, O Israel thou hast sinned from
the days of Gibeah.
He's referencing back to an event that took place.
Turn back to Judges 19 if you will and we see this event that took place in Judges 19
followed by in Judges 20 and 21 with the situation with the Benjamite war and we won't take time
to deal with all of that this evening but we see in chapters 20 and 21 the result of
this wickedness but I want to just read a few verses of scripture to you from Judges
19 so that you can see why God says that Israel they've sinned and he says from the days of
Gibeah.
And we find here in Judges 19, begin reading with me if you will and again we can't take
all of the time to look at the entirety of the context here but in verse number 20 the
Bible says, And the old man said, Peace be with thee.
Howsoever let all thy wants lie upon me, only lodge not in the street.
And so he was showing kindness to this individual.
They were traveling and his wife and it says in verse 21, So he brought him into his house
and gave provender unto the asses and they washed their feet and did eat and drink.
Now as they were making their hearts merry, behold, the men of the city, notice how the
Bible describes them, certain sons of Belial, beset the house round about and beat at the
door and spake to the master of the house, the old man, saying, Bring forth the man that
came into thine house that we may know him.
That's wicked.
It's ungodly.
I won't get into all the details.
We've got children in here this evening but understand this is wickedness.
By the way, this is what happened with Lot, is it not?
Go all the way back to Genesis and you can read the situation with Lot, it's the same
exact thing that happened.
And we find here that these sons of Belial, these wicked men, they surround the house,
they beat on the door and they say, Bring forth the man that came into thine house that
we may know him.
Notice verse 23, And the man, the master of the house, went out unto them and said unto
them, Nay, my brethren, nay, I pray you, do not so wickedly.
seeing that this man is coming to mine house,
do not this folly.
Behold, verse 24,
here is my daughter, a maiden, and his concubine.
Then I will bring out now and humble you them
and do with them what seemeth good unto you,
but unto this man do not such, so vile a thing.
There's a wickedness.
You can keep reading.
I'm not going to this evening for sake of time,
but you can keep reading through this chapter
and the next two chapters,
and you can see in the book of Judges the wickedness,
and what is God saying in this indictment?
He says you're an empty vine.
Oh, it's not that you don't have fruit.
It's simply that you have fruit for yourself.
It's not that you don't have an increase
or a multitude of fruit.
It's that you do it for the increase of the altars,
this idolatry.
He tells them that their heart is divided.
They have false speaking.
They've spoken words swearing falsely and making a covenant,
and he says plainly in verse nine,
you've sinned from the days of Gibeah.
We find that also in Hosea 9 in verse number nine,
there's a reference to the days of Gibeah.
Notice, and maybe on the same page for you
in Hosea 9 in verse nine,
they have deeply corrupted themselves
as in the days of Gibeah.
Therefore, he will remember their iniquity.
He will visit their sins.
And so we find that there's this indictment.
We read of these things here in chapter number 10,
but I want to just take a quick moment
to look at a few other verses here in the book of Hosea.
Go a few chapters back, if you will,
into Hosea chapter number four,
and I want you to see what God says to his people.
In Hosea 4 in verse number one,
hear the word of the Lord, you children of Israel.
Now, we understand that we ought to hear
the word of the Lord,
but we ought to be doers of the word
and not hearers only, correct?
James 1 in verse 22.
Hear ye the word of the Lord.
Aren't you thankful that God's faithful
to give the word of the Lord,
that God loves and God confronts
and God sends a prophet and a messenger
and someone to herald the truth of God's word?
Why?
Because he loves us.
God gave his word by inspiration.
He divinely preserved his word
so that we would have it this evening.
And here is the prophet is speaking to Israel.
He says, hear the word of the Lord,
ye children of Israel, for the Lord,
notice what it says,
the Lord hath a controversy
with the inhabitants of the land
because there is no truth nor mercy
nor knowledge of God in the land.
He continues here in the next couple of verses
mentioning several things
with regard to the characteristics of the day,
but I want you to move forward
to verse number six, if you will,
and notice what the Bible says.
My people are destroyed for lack of knowledge.
But notice this next phrase,
because thou hast rejected knowledge.
It's not that God's word wasn't available,
it's that God's people rejected God's word.
You know, just as they did in the nation of Israel,
we too can be guilty of this tonight.
We can hear the word of the Lord, but reject it.
We can say, oh man, that was really good for so-and-so,
I hope they were here and heard it.
That, oh man, so-and-so need that message,
can I get a copy of it so I can send it to him?
They rejected the word of God.
Notice in verse six, I also, I will also reject thee,
that thou shalt be no priest to me,
seeing thou hast forgotten the law of thy God.
I will also forget thy children,
as they were increased, so they sinned against me.
Therefore will I change their glory into shame.
You know, verse seven is a very insightful
verse of scripture.
The Bible says, as they were increased,
so they sinned against me.
And Brother Mark, this morning in his Sunday school class,
he talked about this very thing
of the danger of prosperity.
And he went to Deuteronomy chapter eight,
you could look at chapter six, seven, and eight,
look at all that section of Deuteronomy.
And God gives a warning to his people repeatedly
in that portion of scripture,
that when you come into a land and you have houses
that you did not build, you have vineyards
that you did not plant, you're increased with goods,
your wealth increases, all of these things,
then beware, lest thou forget the Lord.
You know what Israel did?
They forgot the Lord.
God blessed them, God gave them,
and God was so good to them,
but they just went on living for themselves.
And sometimes if we're not careful,
we can look at Israel and instead of learning from them,
we can simply criticize them,
though at the same time, we're doing maybe differently,
but we're basically doing the same thing that they're doing
or that they did.
And he said that they were increased,
but he says, as they were increased,
so they sinned against me.
Verse eight, they eat up the sin of my people
and they set their heart on their iniquity
and there shall be like people like priests
and I will punish them for their ways
and reward them their doings.
You know, you cannot get away from the principle
in God's word of sowing and reaping.
It's a law of nature.
It's a law of God.
And he says, I will punish them for their ways
and reward them their doings.
In verse 18, their drink is sour,
they have committed whoredoms.
Notice the word continually.
Her rulers with shame do love, give ye.
Notice, if you will, over in chapter seven,
I mean, we could look at so much here
in this portion of scripture, in this book of Hosea,
but notice in chapter seven, in verse number 14,
notice what God says.
And they have not cried unto me with their heart.
When they howled upon their beds,
they assembled themselves corn and wine
and they rebel against me.
You know, the Bible says in 1 Samuel
that rebellion is as the sin of witchcraft.
Some people rebel against God.
And you know, remember, in that same text of scripture,
it's Saul that's rebelling against God in 1 Samuel 16,
and we find that, chapter 15, excuse me,
and we find that as Saul is rebelling against the Lord,
he's thinking, he's self-deceiving himself,
he's thinking that he's obeyed the commandment of the Lord,
and Samuel comes, yes, 1 Samuel 15,
and Samuel comes and says,
what mean ye the bleeding of the, right, the sheep?
He hears, you didn't obey the Lord.
And in that same text, we find the truth
that rebellion is as the sin of witchcraft,
but we also find the truth,
to obey is better than sacrifice.
To obey is better than sacrifice.
Because what did Saul,
how did he try to excuse his disobedience?
He excused his disobedience by saying,
we've saved the best so that we can make an offering.
No, no, no, to obey is better than sacrifice.
Well, I'm serving God, I'm doing this.
No, to obey, to obey.
Chapter eight and verse 14,
for Israel hath forgotten his maker.
Can you imagine that?
Jeremiah speaks about the people of God
have forgotten me days without number.
It's a sad commentary.
Jeremiah is prophesying years after Hosea,
since they're not contemporaries one with the other.
Jeremiah is prophesying to Judah
on the eve of their captivity.
Here, Hosea is prophesying to Israel
We find some similarities.
And here, Hosea says this message,
as he's speaking of the word of the Lord,
for Israel hath forgotten his maker,
and buildeth temples,
and Judah hath multiplied fenced cities,
but I will send a fire upon his cities,
and it shall devour the palaces thereof.
As we begin to understand the indictment
as we're looking at these verses of scripture this evening
and looking at this truth and we note the indictment,
I believe tonight that the indictment
reveals something very important to us.
What the indictment reveals to me,
and I hope what it would reveal to you as well,
is that God knows.
God knows.
No one from Israel wrote God a letter and said,
here's what we're guilty of.
No, God knew.
God sees.
God knows the heart.
God knows what you're doing in your secret place.
He knows the things that are going on.
And we have relational issues,
and we have personal conflict,
and we have disobedience in our heart,
in our lives here and here,
and we have a divided heart.
We got all these things going on, and God knows.
The indictment against you and against me
and against the church in 2025
would probably read differently
than the indictment against Israel in Hosea chapter 10.
But I wonder this evening, would God look at your life?
Would God look at my life?
Would God look at our church and say,
he has a controversy with us?
There's a problem.
See, God knows.
Somebody made this comment to me years ago.
In fact, John Feudo made the comment to me.
He went over to Cape Verde for a missions trip,
and he made this comment when he came back.
He said, you know, the difference between them and America,
Cape Verde, the people there in America,
is that in America, we have money to cover up our problems.
And he said, there, they don't have any money,
and it's just right in your face,
all of the sin and the wickedness and the turmoil.
on the problems.
Some of you have visited countries like that.
But you know, the reality is that sometimes what we do,
if we're not careful, we know how to put on the suit,
we know how to put on the smile,
we know how to come into the, and do our duty,
do our work, do whatever it is,
but oh, there's conflict, there's friction,
there's sin.
See, the Bible talks about sin being in the camp,
and it affects the whole.
Can I remind you this evening, I remind myself tonight,
that God is never okay with sin.
Our God is a holy God.
And our God, who is a holy God,
said that we are to walk in holiness,
that we are to be holy as he is holy.
And there are times in which we look at the scriptures
and the scriptures hit us right in the face.
And we know there's something we gotta deal with.
The Holy Spirit might prick our heart,
and we just say no, and we quench,
and we grieve the Holy Spirit.
We don't deal with the things that we need to deal with
because we think God's just gonna be okay with it.
But what starts happening
is we start losing the blessing of God.
I don't wanna live without the blessing of God.
I don't wanna just go through life getting by.
I want God's favor.
I want God's blessing.
I truly desire this evening for myself
and for our church family
that there would be nothing between my soul and my Savior.
That we could say, as Paul says in Acts 24 and verse 16,
that I hereby exercise myself to do what?
To have always a conscience void of offense
toward God and toward men.
Sometimes we deceive ourselves.
Oh, I'm right with God, but you're wrong with your family.
You're wrong with your friends.
You're wrong with your church family.
No, no, hold on a minute.
Paul says, I'm exercising to be right with God,
but also to be right with others.
Conflict, it's terrible, it's terrible.
I preached a message not long ago on a Sunday morning
of how to handle strained relationships.
What did I say in that message?
Listen, we all deal with it in life at some point,
but how do we deal with it?
And sometimes we say, well, we ignore it.
That's for somebody else.
No, Lord, that's for me
because I want your blessing in my life.
Listen, I know the indictment against me
and against us tonight would be different
than the indictment against Israel in Hosea 10,
but I just wonder tonight, what would it be?
What would God say about your life?
You know how many people in the last two years,
we only got 10 minutes and I gotta get through the message,
but in the last two years,
I've had person after person after person
call me or sit in my office
about this one sin of pornography.
Can I tell you, it's wicked, it's ungodly.
God is never okay with it.
If you look at the statistics,
it's not just men that are affected with pornography.
You look at the statistics, it's awful.
And I don't speak about it often from this pulpit,
but the reality is that it's killing our churches.
It is absolutely destroying our homes.
It's awful, wicked, vile.
There was a stretch last year in about six months
that I dealt with people that were in their teen years,
their 20s, their 30s, their 40s, their 50s, and their 60s,
all with the same problem.
They weren't all from our church.
There have been people that have come to our church,
they visit our church one time
and they say, I gotta meet with you,
and I find out that I meet with them
and their life is absolutely destroyed
because of one thing, pornography.
And they say, I just need help.
But you know what?
They don't come back to church,
so they don't really get the help that they need.
They want a quick fix for their problem.
There's no quick fix.
But I'm telling you this evening
that God knows all that stuff.
God sees all that stuff.
What would the indictment be
on the 21st century church tonight?
We see what it is of Israel, but what is it of us?
We have conflict.
Oh, personal conflict isn't that big of a deal.
It is a big deal.
It's a big deal.
And sometimes we think, well, it's not,
my sin isn't that big.
You messed up because the Bible says if I confess my sin,
if I say the same thing about it,
I agree with God that it's wickedness.
Joseph said it this way.
How can I do this great wickedness and sin against God?
You know, it's a great study if you do a contrast
between the life of Joseph and David
with regard to the temptation that each of them faced.
Joseph put on his running shoes,
lost his coat, but retained his character.
David, who is that woman?
Bring her to me.
Oh, well, she's the wife of Uriah.
Hello, warning sign, bring her to me.
He goes on to not only commit adultery, but murder.
Listen, God is holy.
I don't know what the indictment would be in your life,
but I want to examine my life to know what is God?
Does God have a controversy with me?
Is there something in my life,
is there something in your life
that's withholding the blessing of God?
It reveals to me this evening that God knows.
Notice not only the indictment,
but very quickly this evening,
back in our text in Hosea 10, we note the instruction.
We read it already in verse number 12.
God knew their condition.
He knew that judgment was on the horizon.
However, we find that God in his grace and his mercy,
he instructs the people of Israel.
Notice as we begin looking at verse 12,
and we read it by way of introduction,
that that principle, that law of sowing and reaping
is mentioned to us to begin the verse,
sow to yourselves in righteousness, reap in mercy.
Then he tells them this, notice this phrase,
it's used as the title of the message this evening,
break up your fallow ground.
The idea of this phrase in Hosea 10 in verse number 12
is that they needed to prepare their hearts.
See, their hearts were hard.
Remember, their heart, according to verse number two,
was divided.
And God says, break up your fallow ground.
And I love, and God is all wise,
but he uses for us here in Hosea 10 in verse number 12,
a relatable analogy.
See, the natural process
with regard to having a garden
or having a farm and all acres and acres,
however the size of it might be,
the natural process is that the soil needs attention
before the seed is put in.
You know, the soil has a tendency to get hard.
That's what happens.
Weeds grow.
How many of you got a garden this year?
How many of you have a garden and you pulled weeds at all?
How many of you noticed that after you pulled the weeds,
a few days later, it seems like you go out
and you're like, what in the world is going on?
I told Holly, we made an agreement.
I would help get the garden put in
and she would weed the garden.
That worked well.
And the reality is that the weeds, they just keep coming.
You know, the Bible says that Solomon
in the book of Proverbs,
that he went by a field that was overgrown.
And he learned a lesson from it.
You know, we can learn lessons from the fields.
You can learn lessons from just doing simple earthly tasks.
And if you go, we're nearing the end.
September 1st is tomorrow.
We're nearing the end of our typical gardening season
here in our region.
And before long, we'll take the last of our fruits
from our gardens and we will enjoy them.
And then all winter long,
you know what's gonna happen to your soil and to my soil?
It's gonna get hard.
And you know what's gonna happen in the spring
is after the hard winter, and it doesn't really matter,
even if we have a mild winter,
it still happens that the soil gets hard.
And we go out there in the spring
and all of a sudden in the spring,
we just go out there, we take a pack of seeds
and we just throw them down and that's it.
That's all we do.
What's gonna happen?
Probably nothing.
You're not gonna go out there and expect to have fruit,
to have those vegetables, to have that.
No, why?
Because you gotta do some stuff to the soil.
You gotta prepare the soil.
Our soil, at least here, we got a high amount of clay
in our soil.
So Dean, the master gardener,
when we first started our garden, he said,
pastor, you gotta put some peat moss in that thing.
Why?
Because it'll help keep it from clumping up so much
and the roots can take and grow deep and get the water.
And so, listen, in the spring.
you know what we do? We work on that thing. We work on it. Why? Because we want to get
a harvest. And God uses this relatable analogy that these people could understand even more
than we can. I'm not a farmer, don't claim to be one. I think, we talk about being in
Idaho, man, those people live right off the land, Montana. I'd probably die. I'm just
being honest. I mean, I don't know how to do that stuff. They say, oh man, just go out
and kill this animal and kill that animal. I wouldn't know what to do with it, man. I
get my meat pre-prepared at Walmart, praise the Lord. Somebody else does all that for
me. But you understand, like, they would understand this. Break up your fallow ground. Prepare
your heart. And what are we doing to prepare our heart? What do we do each day when we
approach the Lord? I've made this comment before, and I just observe it. I'm not singling
out a particular region of the world, but I find it more prominent with the Asian community
that when they go into a church, they immediately sit down and begin praying before the service
even begins. I've seen it often. And I'm not suggesting that no other culture or people
group do that. One thing that we started in our church was having a time of prayer before
our services. Why? Because I want my heart to be ready. I've made known that that time
of prayer is not to pray for the person that's sick, the person that's got this ailment or
that ailment or this thing or that travel. No, it's God, work in my heart in this service.
Do something, Lord. It's really the purpose of that prayer time. But break up your fallow
ground. Because if it's hard, if it's hard, the soil's not ready, your heart's not ready
to receive the seed, to take in that root. And the reality is that you and only you
know the condition of your heart. And I understand, listen, the Bible says the heart is deceitful
and desperately wicked. Who can know it? The Lord searched at the heart. He tries the rains.
He knows. And here this evening, the soil needs preparation in order to yield a harvest.
And your heart and my heart break up your fallow ground. Needs to be preparation, work
to be done. Notice as you continue reading the instruction in verse number 12, the Bible
says, for it is time to seek the Lord. You know, there are so many things that humans
seek or pursue. If ye then be risen with Christ, seek those things which are above.
Amen? Colossians chapter number 3. The reality is that there are so many things that we can
seek or pursue. But I'm reminded of what Jesus said to Martha in Luke 10 in verse 42, only
one thing is needful. Only one thing is needful. Seek ye first the kingdom of God. Amen? Seek
the Lord and he shall be found. You know, sometimes, and I'm probably going to preach
a message on this at some point, so just a preview. I got this thought a few weeks ago
and just been kind of, sometimes they just simmer in my mind for a while and I just kind
of got to meditate on it. But you know, when we think about seeking something, sometimes
we play hide and seek, right? Sometimes we hide something because we don't want it to
be found. But sometimes we hide something because we want somebody to find it. God says
in Isaiah that He was hiding, but not because He didn't want to be found, but because He
wanted His people to seek Him, to seek Him. Are we hungering and thirsting after righteousness?
As the deer panteth after the water brook, so panteth my heart after Thee, O Lord. Right?
My soul followeth hard after Thee, O Lord. It's time to seek the Lord. He says, till
He come and reign righteousness upon you. God knows you. He knows me. If we allow Him
tonight, He'll expose what needs to be dealt with in our lives. Search me, O Lord. If we
come to God with that attitude, why? Because I want to be prepared. I want to be ready.
I want to see God do something great in my life. See, God is no respecter of persons
and sometimes we look at how God used certain people and why did God use this person that
way? Or why did God use that person that way? Or, oh, that God would use me like He
used Paul. God uses people that are usable. I'm going to preach a message next week on
Sunday morning from 2 Corinthians 8. Meet for the Master's Use. I know that that phrase
comes from the book of Timothy, 1 Timothy, but we understand here that as we look at
that passage, we need to be meet for the Master's Use. What kind of people does God
use? We'll see God do something in my life, in your life. Will we follow the instruction
as we see the indictment, but then we see the instruction, will we follow it? Will we
get along with God? Will we break up our fallow ground? Will we ask God to search us? Will
we take the necessary steps? God, you put your finger on this thing in my life and I
got to deal with it. Or, we ignore it. Sadly, Israel's response seems to be one of ignoring
or rejecting. Why? Because we know historically that shortly after the prophet's ministry,
they were carried into captivity. They were carried into captivity. But you know, it's
kind of interesting. Nineveh was the capital of Assyria. And we know the book of Jonah.
And Jonah disobeyed God, but then eventually obeyed God. And by the way, you don't want
the experience of Jonah so that you would obey God. Amen? Wouldn't it just be better
to obey God straight away? Praise God. Jonah had an awful experience. And then he obeyed
God. And he got into Nineveh. And you know the message, it was very simple and straightforward.
Yet 40 days and Nineveh shall be destroyed. I believe with all my heart that Nineveh is
going to be destroyed in 40 days because that's what God said through the prophet. But you
know what they did in Nineveh? They repented. They repented. And God, His grace and His
mercy and He spared judgment for a time. When Israel was taken captive shortly after
the writing of the book of Hosea, the ministry of this prophet, when they were taken captive,
you understand that they came, the Assyrians came after Judah as well. Sennacherib, Rabshakka,
we're familiar with those characters. They come and they talk to the king, Jehoshaphat,
and understand all that's taking place. King Hezekiah is the king of Judah at the time.
And they come to Hezekiah and all that was taking place. And guess what? Judah didn't
get taken into captivity. They got serious about seeking God. Israel, the message is
to them. But tonight, the message is to us. Will I be prepared for revival? Do I really
want God to do something in my heart? Am I really surrendered and yielded? God, whatever
You want. We sang tonight, follow on. I will follow. Just, Lord, surrender. Just whatever
You want. Lord, help me to be clean. I've used the analogy before. I don't want to be
cleaner. I want to be clean. Because cleaner is not good enough. You can have something
that's really dirty and you can just dust it off with a hanky, with something else.
Just let me dust that thing off. And here you go. It's cleaner, but it is not clean.
Creating me a clean heart. Oh, that God would do a work in our hearts. Help us to be prepared.
Break up your fallow ground. Lord, we love You. We thank You for loving us. We thank
You for the Word. Lord, as we consider the indictment tonight, it reveals to us that
You know. God, I don't know all that's taking place in the lives of these that are gathered
tonight. But God, I know that You do. You know each of us. You know everything about
us. God, if there's any sin in our lives, would You help us to deal with it? God, if
there's maybe even some of the sin that we mention by name this evening. Sin that some
would categorize as being big sin and others that would categorize as being little sin.
Lord, help us not to have those categories, but help us to understand that sin is an offense
against Thee as a holy God. And help us to be clean. Lord, do a work in us. Help us to
do business with You. Help us not to quench and grieve the Holy Spirit. Help us to follow
the instruction. To break up our fallow ground, to seek You with our whole heart. Lord, I
pray that You'd move and work as only You can. And we'll give You the glory for it's
in Christ.
In Jesus' name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.