and I'll be looking at a passage of scripture, really a character that God
gives us the opportunity to read about from this text of scripture that is
familiar to many of us. In fact, I am going to guarantee this evening that the
youngest among us are going to know this character, right? James up here, he's gonna
know, and Zachary and Natalie, they're gonna know the character, and they're
gonna be excited about it, and I'm sure that many of you will know him as well.
As we look at Luke chapter 19, we're gonna look at verses 1 through 10. The
title of the message is this, A Man Named Zacchaeus. James, do you know who Zacchaeus
is? Zacchaeus was a wee little man, amen? And so I told you they'd know Zacchaeus,
right? Natalie and Zachary, you guys know about Zacchaeus, you sing the song, and
you've heard this passage of scripture, no doubt, as you've had the opportunity
in Sunday School, Children's Church, Awana, whatever, maybe at home, in the car,
sometimes, maybe too often for the parents liking, singing the song over and
over and over, but the reality is that as we look and study the Word of God,
especially as we read through the gospel accounts here, we find that God gives us
the opportunity to be introduced to a number of people. There are times in
which we are introduced to folks that had just brief passing interactions with
the Lord Jesus Christ, and there are times in which we find that some of the
characters that were introduced to throughout the gospel records, they had
multiple interactions, prolonged interactions with the Lord Jesus Christ,
and we find that as we would go to these texts of scripture, that there are times
in which we will find some of these characters that are more well-known than
others. Of course, when we think about Zacchaeus and this particular text of
scripture, again, he's a Bible character that is known by many, and I think
mostly because of the song that is sung about him and about his life, and we find
here in Luke 19, I want to read the first couple of verses, we'll get into the
study this evening. The Bible says this,
"...and Jesus entered and passed through Jericho." And it says this in verse number
two, "...and behold, there was a man named Zacchaeus, which was the chief among the
publicans, and he was rich." Look at verse number 10, skip down if
you will. The Bible says in verse number 10, "...for the Son of Man," speaking of
Jesus, "...is come to seek and to save that which was lost." As we look at this
passage of scripture, we've titled the message, A Man Named Zacchaeus. If you're
taking notes this evening, I want you to notice first how Zacchaeus is described.
Notice how the scriptures describe this man to us. We find that the Bible begins
in verse number one by telling us about Jesus, who would enter and pass through
Jericho. Now, we understand the fact that Jesus had folks that were well aware of
his life and ministry. In fact, as you study the life of Christ, you'll find
that on a number of occasion, there are people that desired to go and be where
Jesus was. They wanted to hear him teach. Mainly, they wanted to receive the
bread, the miracles, be partakers of those things. And we find here that in verse
number one, that God sets the scene for us to tell us that Jesus was coming and
he was going to pass through Jericho. This is the home place of this one,
Zacchaeus, and thus we're introduced to Zacchaeus. And the Bible tells us this,
the description is given here in verse number two. Notice what it says, first of
all, that Zacchaeus, which was the chief among the publicans. I want you to notice
that in the first level of description that is given to us about this man,
Zacchaeus, is we're told about his position. We are told that this man,
Zacchaeus, was chief among the publicans. Now, no doubt if you've read the Gospels
and you've read about the interactions between the Jewish folks and the
publicans, the publicans were not well-liked. The publicans were tax
collectors, and they were tax collectors for the Roman government, and as such,
they would not have had a great deal of popularity amongst the Jewish people.
And we find that these tax collectors, they would, of course, be ridiculed and
looked down upon, but they did have a level of power, and they did have this
authority. And we find that the Bible says that this man, Zacchaeus, as we're
introduced to him, as we're reading the description of him, that he was the chief
among the publicans. I want you to understand that though he might not have
been popular amongst the Jewish people, that this man prospered in his position.
This man had position. And the Bible ends in verse number two by saying this,
and he was rich. Not only did he have position, but this man had possession.
And we find that as we would look at the description of this man as it's given to
us in verse number two, this man Zacchaeus, that we're told that he is
chief among the publicans, that he has this position. We're told that he is rich,
that he has these possessions. As James told us to begin the study this evening,
that Zacchaeus was a wee little man, we read in verse number three that he
sought to see Jesus, who he was, and could not for the press notice because he was
little of stature. And so he was little of stature. We see that description given
to us in verse number three. But I want you to focus upon these first two
elements that are given to us in verse number two with regard to how this man
is described. And I want you to understand something when we enter into
this passage of Scripture. I want you to understand this evening that there are a
number of people that may not have the name Zacchaeus, but fit the description
of Zacchaeus. They may not have that name. In fact, I've never met an individual
named Zacchaeus. I don't know if you have, but I've never met... I didn't go to school
with anyone named Zacchaeus. I never went to Bible college with anyone named Zacchaeus.
I've never met somebody named Zacchaeus. But I would say to you this
evening that when we notice how this man is described in verse number two as
having position and having possession, that there are many today that fit the
the same characteristics as this man Zacchaeus. In fact, there are many
today that they strive to have what Zacchaeus had. They're looking for
position. They're looking for possession. They believe that if they can get
position, if they can get possession, that it will bring some level of joy, that it
will bring some level of satisfaction in their lives. If I could just get that
promotion. Oh, but you didn't know that with that promotion comes a whole lot of
headache, a whole lot of responsibility. But we think we want that
position. Oh, if I could have those possessions, if I could just have that,
whatever that thing is, it would bring me some level of satisfaction. And we live
in the midst of a generation that are seeking position and possession. And as
we look at the description of Zacchaeus, we find that this could describe your
neighbor. This could describe my neighbor. It could describe your co-worker. It
could describe a family member, someone that's looking for position, that's
looking for possession. But I want you to notice not only how Zacchaeus is
described, but I want you to notice number two this evening, what Zacchaeus
desired. What did he desire? As we read verse number three in our text of
Scripture, the Bible says this, and he, speaking of Zacchaeus, sought to see
Jesus, who he was, and could not for the press. So you understand that there were
a great host of people that were gathered together with the knowledge
that Jesus would pass through that way, that Jesus had entered, as it says in
verse number one, and that he would pass through Jericho. And no doubt there was a
great number of people that had gathered together, and the Bible tells us that he
could not for the press. And as we have found, even as you look in the
Gospel of Mark, and you don't need to turn there, but in Mark chapter number
two, the Bible describes to us the miracle of the man that was born of four,
and we're told about that particular miracle that these men desired to bring
their friend to Jesus, and they knew that Jesus was in the house. But the Bible
says that when they brought him there, there was no way that they could get
in, and so they had to go up on the rooftop, and they had to lower him down
through the roof. And so there were many times in the life and ministry of Jesus
Christ that there was a great host of people that would gather, and here on
this particular day, as they heard that Jesus was passing that way, and that he
was going to pass through Jericho, that there was a great host of people that
came, but Zacchaeus desired something. No doubt in my mind this evening that
Zacchaeus had heard some things about Jesus. If he had not heard some things
about Jesus, I'm not thinking that he has any desire to go see him. But because he
had heard some things about Jesus,
he had a desire to go see him.
about Jesus. He desires to see Jesus. Notice what it says. I think these three
words are of great importance. The Bible says, and he sought to see Jesus who he
was. Can you imagine being Zacchaeus in hearing about Jesus and hearing about
the miracles and hearing about the feeding of the five thousand and hearing
about the lame man that was able to walk the blind man that could now see the
death man that can now hear. And you begin to hear these things and you say I
want to know who this man is. And the Bible says that he sought to see Jesus
who he was. He's God. He's God in flesh. He came to seek and to save as we read
in verse number 10 already. But he comes and he manifests the Father. He makes
known his his deity and we find that through those miracles. Remember John the
Baptist when he's in prison he said sent some disciples and said ask Jesus are
are you the water do we look for another. And Jesus said tell him this and what he
did is he gave him truth from the Old Testament prophecies regarding the
Messiah and what he would do and say tell him that the lame walk and the
deaf hear and the blind see. And now Zacchaeus he hears that Jesus is coming
through his own town. He's got the position. He's got the possession. The
Bible tells us that he was the chief among the publicans. The Bible tells us
that he was rich but he was wanting. The Bible says that he sought to see Jesus
who he was and could not for the press because he was little of stature. And so
he turned around and went home and said well I tried. No. That's what the Bible tells us.
We find that he was determined to see Jesus. We understand his determination. We
can zero in on verse number four and we can gauge the level of determination by
the actions that he took. The Bible says that he ran before and he climbed up
into a sycamore tree to see him for he was to pass that way. Now I understand we
sing the song with the kids and it's like it's a fun song but I want you to
think about Zacchaeus and we see how he's described but notice what he
desires. He's going to want to see Jesus and there's so many people and because
of his stature he just can't see. Have you ever gone to a parade? I mean pre-COVID
right? Back in in ancient days in 2019 when there were parades and you could go
and I remember a number of years ago Samantha I don't know how many years ago
it was but you rode the the horse and the parade here in Fairfax City and I
remember going down there and we walked and walked and walked and we're trying
to get there and we're trying to move around and try to be able to see where
Samantha was gonna be riding the horse. Do you remember? And you know the the
reality is that there were some that were little kids that when certain
people were going by they're trying to push to the front. You're trying to get
on higher ground. Zacchaeus was determined to see Jesus and so he ran
ahead and he found a tree and he climbed up in the tree because he knew that
Jesus was gonna pass that way and he wanted to see him. He wanted to see who
he was. We find that this evening as we think about the description of Zacchaeus
and I've said to you this evening that the description is provided to us in
verse number two could be suitable to describe your neighbor, your co-worker,
your friend, your relative that they're seeking and maybe they have position in
possession but I find this evening and we speak about it often that no one and
no thing will satisfy like Jesus. Nothing will. The enemy tries to convince the
unregenerate man that they can satisfy their longings through a whole host of
things but they're left wanting and when I look at this passage of Scripture and
I think about what this man Zacchaeus desired and you say look at all of the
things that he had. Yeah but he didn't have Jesus. He didn't have remember this
morning I was speaking about a whole host of things actually and one of the
things that I mentioned in the message this morning was about the peace and the
joy that we have through Jesus and that that joy no man can steal from you. No
man can take your joy. The Bible tells us about a peace that passeth all
understanding. In this man Zacchaeus though he had position though he had
possession he's wanting and he desires to see Jesus who he was. As we look at
the passage of Scripture and we think just for a moment of Zacchaeus in these
first four verses of Luke 19 as he's introduced to us in the Word of God and
we find how he's described and what he desires I wonder this evening how many
people you come into contact with how many people I come into contact with
that would fit this description of being wanting. Now they might not know that
it's Jesus that they're missing. You understand that. Zacchaeus no doubt had
heard about Jesus. That's why he desired to see him who he was and this evening
there might be some people in your sphere of influence that don't know that
what they're missing is Jesus but God's allowed you to be in their sphere of
influence so that as you magnify and glorify the Lord Jesus Christ in your
life that they realize that the position and the possession that they have leaves
them wanting and they want what you have. They want Jesus. They want to know more
about this Jesus. So you understand this evening don't we think about the
responsibility that has been given to us as the children of God as being
ambassadors representatives of being those that would go out and sow the seed
of the gospel that we have this response. Listen we're not salesmen. We're not
trying to just build some kind of numbers in some type of following. No.
We're trying to tell people about the Lord Jesus Christ that has done
something for them that no other could ever do. And this man Zacchaeus we find
that he is described and we find that his desire is revealed to us. As we look
at verses 5 through 10 I want you to notice number 3 if you're taking notes I
want you to notice what Jesus declares. We notice how he is described in what he
desires and then Jesus is going to speak. And I want you to notice a host of
things that Jesus declares in this passage of scripture and I hope this
evening that it would have a profound impact in your life and in mine. The
Bible says in verse number 5, and when Jesus came to the place he looked up and
saw him and said unto him Zacchaeus. Now stop right there. Can you imagine being
Zacchaeus? You never met Jesus before. You didn't know who he was. In fact you
heard that Jesus was coming through your town and you heard about some of the
miracles that Jesus had performed and you heard about some of these amazing
things that that had been taking place and this man named Jesus and now he's
coming through Jericho and you want to see him and you try to make your way to
see him and you've left your duties for the day to be able to see Jesus but
you're too short. And so you run and you get into a tree and you knew that Jesus
was gonna pass that way and the Bible says that when Jesus came to the place
that he looked up and he saw him and said Zacchaeus. He called him by name. I
love that because we find that Zacchaeus, he's never met Jesus before. He wants to
see him and Jesus says Zacchaeus. Now can you imagine? I hope this evening I
understand that we know about Zacchaeus and we we can sing the song most of us
you could sing it better than I could. But the reality is in that moment, can
you imagine how Zacchaeus must have felt? I mean he didn't expect for Jesus
to stop and speak to him. He didn't expect to have this interaction that he's
going to have with the Son of God with God in flesh and we find that Jesus
comes to the place and he looks up and he says Zacchaeus. I mean I'm amazed that
Zacchaeus heard the rest of what Jesus said. I mean honestly, the Bible says that
Jesus continues when we think about what Jesus declares. First he spoke his
name. What a precious truth. In fact if you were to look into the gospel
accounts of the resurrection of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ and you would
read about Mary in the tomb and she thought she had supposed that he had
been the gardener. She said if you just tell me where you've laid him and she
Jesus turns and says Mary. And at the spoken name of Mary she said, Master.
He's a master.
He knows who we are.
And Zacchaeus is up in that tree.
And Jesus says, Zacchaeus?
And then He says,
make haste and come down.
Now, I'm not sure if He jumped out of the tree
or what He did,
but I don't like climbing trees personally.
I never did.
I never climbed trees as a kid.
My dad's afraid of heights
and he passed that on to me,
and now my brother flies airplanes,
and so I don't understand how all that thing works.
But the reality is that I just never was a tree climber.
I like going into the mountains.
I like climbing mountains.
I've gotten myself in places
where I didn't know how to get back down
because I scaled up
and I was really in a pickle.
But I never climbed trees.
I just didn't.
But I think about this man, Zacchaeus,
as he climbed into this tree,
and then Jesus says,
make haste and come down.
For today, I must abide at thy house.
I mean, I hope this evening, again,
I understand that we know this account,
but can you imagine being Zacchaeus?
I read this just a few weeks ago
as I was reading through,
and I don't know how many times I've read Luke.
I don't know.
I know this year, in 2020,
I've read it at least five times.
Just this year.
I'm not saying that I pat myself on the back.
What I'm saying to you
is that when I read it just a couple of weeks ago,
I just stopped dead in my tracks.
And I thought about Zacchaeus
and how he must have felt.
And the emotions that he must have experienced.
When Jesus spoke his name
and then said, make haste, come down,
I must abide at thy house.
This is not what he expected.
Would you agree?
This is not a situation where Zacchaeus says,
hey, master, I made a meal.
I have it prepared.
I want you to come back.
This is not how it happened.
Zacchaeus had a desire to see Jesus, who he was.
Jesus knew who Zacchaeus was.
Can I tell you that the seeking Savior
will never miss an appointment with a seeking sinner?
And we find that Zacchaeus is there in that tree
and all he's expecting from my perspective
as I read the Scriptures,
I believe that all that he's expecting on this day
is to simply see Jesus.
And Jesus stops and speaks his name
and says, come down because I have to be,
I must abide at thy house.
Today, I must abide at thy house.
I can't imagine the excitement I have
as I look at verse number six.
I can see how the Bible describes it,
but I'm wondering this evening
how Zacchaeus actually experienced it.
And to think the Bible tells us in verse number six
that he, speaking of Zacchaeus,
that he made haste and came down
and received Him joyfully.
I don't know how far Zacchaeus was from his house.
I don't know where this tree was.
I don't know how far of a journey,
of a walk they had to make to get to his house,
but we find that Zacchaeus
follows the direction of the Lord.
He made haste and came down
and received Him joyfully.
Can I tell you this evening
that Zacchaeus could have stayed in that tree?
Right? He could have.
That would have been really a monumental mistake.
The height of stupidity.
I mean, honestly,
I don't use that word often,
but I think it's appropriate in this particular context.
I mean, it really would have been
a missed opportunity.
For him to desire to see,
oh, you know, I didn't clean the house this morning.
You know, people make excuses.
Do they not?
Listen, I don't know how many people
I've shared the Gospel with in my life.
Not enough.
But I know that there are times
in which I've shared the Gospel with people
and they make excuses.
They don't have time. Not now.
Some other time. Some other situation.
Whatever it might be.
I'm thankful that Zacchaeus didn't make an excuse.
I'm thankful that as we understand
what's taking place,
that Zacchaeus has this opportunity
where he hears his name spoken,
he receives the command of the Lord,
and he makes haste.
He comes down and he receives Him joyfully.
You know that Jesus
does not force Himself upon anyone.
He doesn't.
He doesn't force Himself upon anyone.
In fact, if you're His child today,
He didn't make you read His Bible today.
Right? He didn't make you.
He didn't make you come to church.
He made a decision.
Don't you agree?
He wants to have fellowship with you.
He wants to feast with you.
He wants to have that fellowship
around His Word.
He wants to minister to your needs.
He wants to enjoy that time of communion
through prayer.
But He doesn't force it.
He doesn't make you.
And He didn't force Himself upon Zacchaeus.
He said to Zacchaeus, come down.
Make haste. Come down.
And He says this,
Today, I must abide at thy house.
And he, Zacchaeus, received Him joyfully.
Notice what it said in v. 7.
And when they,
some of those that were part of that press
that prevented Zacchaeus from being able
to get up and see Jesus
that resulted in him having to climb up
into that tree,
these folks saw it and they all murmured,
notice what they said,
that he was gone to be guessed
with a man that is a sinner.
As if they weren't.
But you understand that the religious leaders
of the day, they were so full of themselves,
the scribes, the Pharisees, the Sadducees,
they were so full of themselves.
In fact, the text of Scripture
would reveal to us in a previous passage
where the man stands and says,
I'm so thankful I'm not like this publican.
Here's what I do.
I fast and I do this and I tithe
and so on and so forth.
And we find here that these
that are gathered there,
this group of people,
they murmured and they said of Jesus,
the Son of God,
that He is gone to be guessed
with a man that is a sinner.
It's too bad that they
did not recognize their own condition.
It's too bad that they didn't show up
on the streets of Jericho
with the same desire that Zacchaeus had.
Amen?
The Bible says that Zacchaeus stood.
I don't know if that means that he fell
and had to stand up. I don't know.
I don't want to read into it.
I'm just saying the Bible says that he stood
and said unto the Lord,
Behold, Lord...
Now, I want you to understand
this manner in which Zacchaeus refers
to the Lord Jesus Christ.
He calls Him Lord.
We find that as we have mentioned
and we've dealt with in previous studies
throughout the years of ministry here,
the Bible tells us in the book of Philippians
that God hath highly exalted Him
speaking of Jesus in Philippians 2
and verse 9,
given Him a name which is above every name,
that in the name of Jesus,
every knee should bow,
things in heaven and things in earth
and every tongue should confess
that Jesus Christ is Lord.
To the glory of God the Father.
You know what Zacchaeus is doing here?
He's recognizing that Jesus is Lord.
He's recognizing that He is the Messiah.
That He is God in flesh.
We mention this when we study and read
about the passage of Scripture
with the conversion of Saul
and Saul says,
who art thou Lord?
And the Lord said,
I am Jesus whom thou persecutest.
It is hard for thee to kick against the pricks.
And then Saul at this time,
he responds and he says,
Lord, what wilt thou have me to do?
And here Zacchaeus in Luke 19
and verse 8,
he said, behold, Lord,
the half of my goods I give to the poor,
and if I have taken anything from any man
by false accusation,
I restore him fourfold.
I want you to understand
that in verse 8,
the actions that Zacchaeus takes,
the things that he says he's going to do,
that's not what brought him salvation.
That's the result of his salvation.
That is the outworking of his changed life.
The power of the Gospel to transform a life.
Listen, when you trusted Christ as your Savior,
there were some things that changed.
There were some things that you started to do
that you desired to do in obedience to God
that you had not done when you were lost.
Why? Because now,
I'm not doing it to get saved,
to stay saved.
I'm doing it because I am saved.
And we find here that Zacchaeus says,
Lord, the half of my goods I give to the poor,
and if I have taken anything from any man
by false accusation,
I restore him fourfold.
Notice what Jesus says as we continue with this thought.
of our final point, what Jesus declares.
In v. 9, notice what Jesus says.
This day is salvation come to this house.
For so much as he also is a son of Abraham.
As we begin to notice what is declared
by the Lord Jesus Christ,
we find that in v. 9
that Jesus declares that salvation
has come to the house of Zacchaeus.
And we find that then,
Jesus makes this declaration of verse
that we read by way of introduction
this evening in v. 10,
a verse that some no doubt have memorized
where the Bible says that the Son of Man
has come to seek and to save
that which was lost.
What a great declaration we find
in v. 10 of our text of Scripture this evening.
We begin to see what Jesus is declaring
that He is the Messiah
and that He came to seek and to save
that which was lost.
I'm so thankful that He's the seeking Savior.
I'm so thankful this evening,
as I mentioned a moment ago,
that the seeking Savior will never
miss an appointment with a seeking sinner.
Zacchaeus desired to see Him who He was,
and we find that Jesus stopped at that tree
at the place where He was.
He spoke His name.
He gave Him direction.
The Bible says that He went to His home
and He then declares that salvation
has come to that home.
And then Jesus says,
this is the purpose for My coming,
to seek and to save that which was lost.
As we look at these ten verses this evening,
I believe that we can rejoice
in several things.
I believe that we can be encouraged
with several things.
I believe that we should be challenged as well.
Why should we rejoice?
Because salvation has come to the house of Zacchaeus.
The Bible tells us that there's rejoicing in heaven
and the angels rejoice in heaven
when a sinner repents.
So when we read about somebody getting saved,
when we hear about somebody getting saved,
we have the opportunity to hear somebody
give a testimony about being saved,
we ought to rejoice.
We can be encouraged this evening
that God has created mankind
with a need for God.
This man had position,
and he had possession,
but he was wanting.
You know, we've been given a message to deliver
that is a message that will bring
a level of contentment and satisfaction
to mankind that nothing else is able to do so.
Nothing else can satisfy like Jesus.
And that ought to encourage us this evening
to know that there are times,
listen, there are times I think about this man Zacchaeus
and as I was preparing the message
and thinking about it,
I wondered how many people that I have come in contact with
that their name wasn't Zacchaeus,
but how he is described in our text of Scripture
would fit the people that I've come into contact with
that they have position,
that they have possession,
and maybe in my life and perhaps in yours as well,
that we have thought,
well, they really don't need what I have.
They're really not interested in what I have to give them
with what I have to share with them.
There are times in which in my own life
and perhaps in yours as I would be transparent
with you this evening,
that we look at certain people and say,
well, they really don't need what we have.
We know that they do,
but we make the excuse for them thinking
that they're not gonna be interested in hearing.
There are times,
and if you wanna tell me that I have little faith,
feel free,
there are times in which I will knock on somebody's door
to share the Gospel with them
with the full expectation of hearing I'm not interested.
Why?
Because I'm thinking in the wrong way.
I'm thinking about the position and the possessions
that these individuals have,
and I think they're not gonna be interested
in what I'm trying to share with them.
And there are other times in which I knock on the doors
and maybe I have this expectation,
same kind of house, same area, same everything,
and I can't understand why they wouldn't wanna listen.
It really just, what's our frame of mind?
How are we dealing with things?
What are we comprehending?
See, what I'm thinking this evening is,
has there been a time in my life,
has there been a time in your life
when you made the excuse for someone else?
When maybe you thought, you know, they really don't,
they're not gonna be interested in hearing this.
But God has designed each person
with a need for God.
And we have a lot of people in our world
that are missing that.
They don't know Him.
They've never been born again.
They may, on the outside,
look like they have everything put together.
They have the position, the title,
they have the possessions.
They're keeping up with the Joneses
or whomever you wanna say that they're keeping up with,
but they're empty.
They're wanting.
And we can be challenged this evening
because this seeking Savior who came to this earth
to seek and to save that which was lost,
to pay for the redemption of mankind,
to go to the cross of Calvary,
to shed His precious blood,
to be buried in a borrowed tomb,
to rise in victory,
has given each one of us a commission,
a mandate, a responsibility
to go and preach the gospel to every creature.
And when we consider that this evening,
we consider what a great privilege it is.
Well, it's a responsibility, no doubt,
but you know it's a tremendous privilege
to be able to share Christ with someone,
to share with them what Christ has done for you
and what He could do for them.
I think about Zacchaeus.
Do you think he talked about what happened on this day?
I mean, I'm not trying to be extra biblical this evening,
but I'm just asking,
do you think that after an experience
like what we read about this evening,
do you think that Zacchaeus probably talked about that?
I would think so.
We know that Saul talked about his conversion regularly.
I mean, every time he had the opportunity
to stand before people and to give an answer,
he says, I find it great that I can speak today.
I think this is a great opportunity.
And what does he do?
He gives his testimony about his conversion,
about his salvation.
And I think that Zacchaeus,
I mean, I would have loved to hear Zacchaeus
tell the story firsthand, wouldn't you?
I mean, honestly, I've done my best
to try to be in the text this evening,
but I wonder how it would sound from Zacchaeus' perspective
to hear him talk about the excitement
at the moment when Jesus stopped.
I mean, what's going through his mind?
Why is he stopping?
Oh, he's looking at me.
I mean, can you understand?
He begins to share all the things that Jesus,
again, I don't know how long the walk was to his home.
I don't know what transpired.
I know how Zacchaeus responds,
and I know what Zacchaeus declares that he's going to do.
And I know what Jesus declares
about salvation coming to his house.
And I just wonder this evening,
how many people Zacchaeus shared this with?
I wonder this.
I mean, can you, just for a moment this evening,
understand that as a publican,
as a chief among the publicans,
that he would have taken many things by false accusation?
Those are what they were known for.
Your taxes are this much,
but I'm gonna charge you this much
because that's how I make my money.
That's what they did.
That's how it worked.
And so Zacchaeus says,
behold, Lord, the half of my goods I give to the poor.
If I've taken anything from any man by false accusation,
I restore him fourfold.
If we could do just a role play
just for a moment this evening,
can you imagine being a poor person
and Zacchaeus coming to you and saying,
here, I wanna give you this?
Why?
Because Christ changed my life.
I mean, there was this day,
and he goes through the whole story
about what happened.
Can you imagine being one of the people
that he took something from by false accusation
that he charged many people?
Zacchaeus, I just paid my taxes last month.
Like, what are you here for?
I mean, seriously, right?
Can you?
He says, I'm not coming to collect taxes today.
I'm coming to restore to you
that which I took from false accusation.
What?
Zacchaeus, you've been coming here all the time
taking tax money from me.
He was a chief amongst the publicans.
He wasn't new at this game.
No doubt, he was known amongst the people.
Zacchaeus, what happened to you?
Let me tell you what happened to me.
Jesus was coming through Jericho,
and I wanted to see who he was.
There were so many people, I couldn't see him.
So I ran up, and I got up into a tree.
And you know, Jesus stopped, and he spoke my name,
and he said he was gonna come to my house.
And he changed my life.
That's the testimony of this man.
But you have a testimony too.
And I think this evening
that Zacchaeus probably talked about this quite a bit.
I mean,
He's just excited about being saved.
And I believe this evening that there are probably people in heaven today because of
the testimony of Zacchaeus.
I believe that.
And I wonder tonight, how many people are in heaven because of my testimony?
How many people are in heaven because of your testimony?
I mean, do we really see and understand what Christ has done for us?
I understand you might not have climbed in a tree, I get it.
But there was a day that you got saved.
And we ought to talk about that day, and we ought to share with people, because listen,
there are people like Zacchaeus that you come into contact with.
Oh, they have the position, they have the possessions, but they're empty.
And we can relate to Zacchaeus in both the beginning and the end of the passage that
we look at.
And I want to be challenged this evening to be faithful in sharing my testimony and sharing
with others what Christ did for me, because He changed my life.
And if you're saved tonight, He changed your life.
And those people that Zacchaeus interacted with, I'm just bringing you money back that
I took wrongly.
Can you imagine?
You're what?
Yeah.
God changed my life, and He can change your life too.
Let's pray.
Father, we love You.
Thank You for loving us.
I pray that You would work in hearts and lives tonight as only You can.
We see how this man is described and what he desires, and we see what Christ declared.
God, I'm challenged tonight, personally.
I think I'm challenged as much tonight as I was just a few weeks ago when You just stopped
me in this passage of Scripture.
Lord, I pray You'd help us tonight to rejoice in our salvation, to rejoice in knowing that
You are the seeking Savior.
Help us to be challenged tonight, to share our testimony.
I wonder if we really would allow that question to probe our hearts, to be honest about answering
that question.
How many people are in heaven because of my testimony?
You've called us to be Your ambassadors.
You've commissioned us to go and to preach the gospel to every creature.
I pray the Holy Spirit of God would have His will in way this night.
First, in Christ's name we pray, would You stand with me, heads are bowed, eyes are closed.