two this morning, James chapter number two.
And we'll be looking at verses 25 and 26 this morning
as we finish the second chapter of the book of James.
And been studying here on Sunday mornings
through the book of James, our theme for 2026,
doers of the word.
And I hope that you've been taking the principles
of God's word and implementing them in your life,
that we would live by faith,
that we would be doers of the word.
We remember as we're looking here at this portion
of James chapter number two,
that there's a principle that James establishes
in verses 14 through 20.
And he says this in verse 18,
"'Yea, a man may say thou hast faith and I have works.
"'Show me thy faith without thy works
"'and I will show thee my faith by my works.'"
And we've said this, that the principle
that's established in verses 14 through 20
is really being illustrated in verses 21 through 26.
And we find, as we looked last week,
the example of Abraham in verses 21 through 24.
And then this morning, we'll look at the example of Rahab.
And we've said this, that simply put,
to summarize the principle,
your behavior is the evidence of what you believe.
Real faith, true faith, works.
There's not a contradiction here in the text of Scripture
with regard to how an individual is saved.
Really, we understand that this portion of Scripture
is very complementary with other portions of Scripture,
that we would understand that salvation,
genuine conversion, is only and always by faith.
However, we also understand that genuine conversion
produces fruit.
And it's important that we understand that often,
as we look at the portions of Scripture,
and we went through them a few weeks ago,
where the Lord Jesus Christ even spoke
about the fruit of an individual,
and Paul talked about the fruit of an individual
and the good works of those that have been born again.
Oftentimes, those that would try to insert
some controversy in the text of Scripture,
some contradiction, they do not understand
that one is speaking about the means by which we're saved
and then the product of what happens after we're saved,
that we are God's workmanship, amen?
And we are to do good works.
And so we find that here,
in the text of Scriptures, we continue,
I've titled the message last week,
Living by Faith Part One,
and so you already knew today, Living by Faith Part Two.
And let me just say this,
there's a couple of songs that we're familiar with,
and I hope maybe if I quote a little bit of these songs,
it will help us really understand and evaluate our lives
based upon the principle that's being taught here
at the end of James chapter number two.
How many of you know the song Trust and Obey?
Trust and Obey, right?
So trust, we could talk about faith is believing God,
faith is taking God at his word,
it's trusting that God will do what God hath said.
So we trust, we have faith, and therefore we obey.
Trust and obey, for there's no other way
to be happy in Jesus but to trust and obey.
That's the little chorus there.
But then think about this,
some of you know the little song
that we sing with the children oftentimes in Sunday school,
junior church, vacation, Bible school, obedience.
Obedience, we spell it out, O-B-E-D,
we go through the whole thing,
and the little kids, man, they're in kindergarten,
they know how to spell obedience
because we sang the song with them 105 times, right?
And the teacher's like,
how do you know how to spell that word?
Well, let me tell you about a song
that we were singing, right, and amen.
And obedience is the very best way
to show that you believe, right?
It's what the song says.
Now, the song is based on biblical truth,
and so we're not trying to take a song
and elevate it above the Bible.
I'm simply trying to prove to you
and show you this morning that these songs that we sing,
they reinforce Bible teaching, Bible truth,
and so we sing with these young people,
and we should sing it even as older people.
Obedience is the very best way to show that you believe,
doing exactly what the Lord commands, doing it happily.
Then it says this, action is the key.
Do it immediately, joy you will receive.
And so we're gonna think about these little choruses
and these songs that we sing,
and they're really taking the Bible truth
that we've looked at these last few weeks
that we are saved by faith.
We're not saved by works, we're saved by faith,
and we understand there's no other way to be saved.
Jesus paid it all, and there's only one way to be saved,
and that's to come to the Lord Jesus Christ,
and we're saved by grace through faith,
and we understand that works cannot save us,
works cannot keep us, but because we're saved,
we do good works, amen?
And we see, and as I mentioned at the conclusion last week,
instead of us dismissing the text of Scripture,
instead of us saying there's an apparent contradiction,
or some denomination uses the portion of Scripture
to teach false doctrine,
it doesn't mean that we dismiss the text,
it means that we understand, and we dig deeper,
and we say, why did God,
all Scripture is given by inspiration of God.
This isn't just James sitting around one day
and deciding he's gonna write something.
This is God's word, it's inspired, it's preserved,
and we haven't, so okay, instead of dismissing,
why don't I take the time to try to understand it,
number one, and then number two, evaluate my own life,
and say this, what about my actions,
what about my good works, my behavior,
what is it revealing to those around us?
Because the reality is that your behavior
is the evidence of what you believe.
Now, we find that James, very Jewish writing
to a very Jewish audience in this original recipients,
we would understand this, and I said it last week,
that when James starts talking about the example of Abraham
in verses 21 through 24,
that original group of recipients,
they would have immediately understood
Abraham is held in high regard,
and they would have understood, as we examined last week,
that James is speaking about two different events
in the life of Abraham that are separated
by at least 25 or 30 years.
And so what he's saying,
when he talks about the offering of Isaac,
that that happened 25 or 30 years after what we read
about the fact that he believed God,
and it was imputed unto him for righteousness,
and so we see that the evidence, the proof of his faith
was seen in his actions, his good works.
So now we come to the example of Rahab.
Again, another familiar account.
You look in the book of Joshua,
we'll be there in just a few moments,
and we find that this is another obvious reference
with regard to a relatable teaching
and understanding of this Jewish audience.
And so we find in verse number 25,
notice he says, likewise.
In like manner, I'm gonna use another illustration
to prove the point that I'm trying to prove,
to help us to be those that are living by faith.
Now remember, these people are facing persecution.
This is different than the persecution of Nero.
This is the persecution from the Jewish people,
the religious leaders of the day.
And if you begin reading in the book of Acts,
and you see all the persecution that's taking place,
and how as the church is growing,
and souls are being saved, that the religious leaders,
they're threatening, they're imprisoning,
they're beating the disciples, the apostles,
and we see all that's taking place.
And here, you think about this idea
of what happens to your behavior when there's persecution.
If you're not careful, you try to go undercover.
Right?
So this audience that they're saved people,
we've already established that he's writing to save people,
they're dealing with a lot of difficulty,
a lot of persecution, and James is saying,
live out your faith.
Yeah, but that means everyone's gonna know I'm a Christian,
and I'm gonna suffer for it.
Live out your faith, amen?
Because what's inside has to come out.
Because we find that genuine conversion produces
genuine conversion produces fruit.
So he says, likewise also, was not Rahab the harlot
justified by works when she had received the messengers,
and had sent them out another way?
For as the body without the spirit is dead,
so faith without works is dead also.
So we said this last week, and it's important
that we recognize the truth here again,
the definition, we found that Abraham, in verse 21,
it says, was not Abraham our father justified by works?
We see in verse 25, likewise.
also was not Rahab the harlot justified by works?" And we said, what does that word
mean? Let's understand the word. And we understand that oftentimes the word
means to render or declare righteous. And that's typically how we would use the
word, the first kind of definition of the word. But we also understand that the
word carries with it this idea of to show or to exhibit one to be righteous,
to make evident, to show in a clear manner. And so we find that here as James
is writing about the justification of Abraham in verse 21 and of Rahab in
verse 25 of their works being justified by their works, it's saying this is the
evidence of their faith. Their works is the evidence of their faith. So I want
you to consider, let's go back to Joshua chapter number 2. If you're taking notes
number one this morning, consider what Rahab received. Consider what Rahab
received. So back in Joshua chapter number 2, you might be familiar here with
the text of Scripture, but we find that God has given some instruction here and
Joshua's gonna send some some spies in. There are two spies that are gonna go in
to Jericho. And we find, we'll pick it up there in verse number one and read
through the account. And I want you to notice what she received. And Joshua the
son of Nun sent out of Shittim two men to spy secretly, saying, Go view the land,
even Jericho. And they went and came into an harlot's house named Rahab and lodged
there. And it was told the king of Jericho, saying, Behold, there came men in
hither tonight of the children of Israel to search out the country. The king of
Jericho sent unto Rahab, saying, Bring forth the men that are come to thee,
which are entered into thine house, for they be come to search out all the
country. The woman took the two men and hid them, and said thus, There came men
unto me, but I wist not whence they were. And it came to pass about the time of
shutting of the gate, when it was dark, that the men went out, whither the men
went I won't not. Pursue after them quickly, for you shall overtake them. But
she had brought them up to the roof of the house, and hid them with the stalks
of flax, which she had laid in order upon the roof. The men pursued after them the
way to Jordan under the fords. And as soon as they which pursued after them
were gone out, they shut the gate. And before they were laid down, she came up
unto them upon the roof. Now we're gonna see here, we see the the dialogue of kind
of what had transpired. And let me say this, Rahab is not commended for lying.
She's commended for hiding the spies. Amen? Some people try to twist some
things in Scripture. Listen, lying thou shalt not bear false witness. Some people
try to justify situational ethics. Amen? And say, well it was okay for Rahab to
lie, and so it's okay for me to lie. Wrong. Wrong. Amen? You say, yeah, but look what
happened. I see what happened. But you know how we could read Joshua 2? I don't
know how we could read Joshua 2 if she had just said, yeah, the spies are here.
Could God have protected them? Absolutely. Just like when Abraham went in and said,
Sarah's my sister. I think he could have walked right up in there in Egypt and
said, she's my wife. What are you gonna do about it? And we'd read it differently.
And God is God. He is able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we
ask or think. Amen? Do you remember when Elisha prayed that God would cause all
the army to be blinded? And what happened? They were blinded. Amen? Because we serve
a great God. Now let me say this about Rahab. She had a whole lot less
revelation than you have. Amen? So before you start taking Rahab as a reason that
it's okay for you to lie, you better make sure you read more Bible. Now that was
all for free. Nothing to do with the message, to be honest with you. All right?
So let's get back to it. What did Rahab receive? Look in verse number 9. And she
said unto the men. So now she's talking to these two spies. And here's what she
says. I know that the Lord hath given you the land. Now do you see the the word
Lord there? It's all capital. That's Jehovah. So she says, I know that the Lord
hath given you the land, and that your terror is fallen upon us, and that all
the inhabitants of the land faint because of you. That's really because of
what God was doing. God said that he would do this. Amen? And we find that
there. She's rehearsing here, and she's being able to share with us the report
of what she had heard. Notice what it says in verse number 10. For we have
heard. We have heard. What did they hear? Notice it says this. How the Lord dried
up the water of the Red Sea for you when you came out of Egypt. Now we know about
reading about the crossing of the Red Sea. I mean a great miracle. Amen? How God
brought his people out. And we understand that he brought them out to bring them
in, but because of their unbelief, they had to wander for 40 years before they
come to this point where they're coming into the land. But we find that she heard.
She says, we have heard. So they receive this report, word spread, and they receive
this report, and she says this, how the Lord dried up the water. She recognized
that it was God who moved. It was God who worked. It was God who worked
miraculously. It was not the children of Israel that had some great ingenuity to
figure out how to cross the Red Sea. No, it was God that told Moses to simply take
that staff, that rod, and to lift it up, and God parted the Red Sea, and they
walked on dry ground. Amen? And then the Egyptians, they said, well, let's get them.
And then God said, go ahead and raise that thing again, and closed up the
waters, and they were all destroyed. Amen? Exodus 14, go and read and praise the
Lord. And guess what? Rahab and the people in Jericho and the people in the land,
they heard that. And it says, and what ye did unto the two kings of the Amorites
that were on the other side, Jordan, Sihon, and Og, whom ye utterly destroyed.
Verse number 10, and that rehearses for us some of what happened with regard to
those two battles with Sihon and Og, because they would not receive, and Moses,
and through the instruction of the Lord, and the victory that they had.
And so we find that it says in verse number 11, and as soon as we heard these
things, our hearts did melt, neither did there remain any more courage in any man
because of you, for the Lord your God, he is God in heaven above and in earth
beneath. And so we begin to understand what Rahab received. She received testimony.
She had been given some opportunity to hear about the God of the universe,
the God, the Lord God Jehovah, the Lord God Almighty. She begins to hear this
report. She didn't have as much as you have. She didn't have as much as I have,
but what she received was enough to give her an understanding that he's God. Amen?
We talked about Abraham on Wednesday, where the Bible tells us that God appeared
to him, and God spoke to him, and he came out of the earth, the Chaldees.
And we understand that Abraham did not know everything about God at that moment
that he would know about God, because it was later in the life of Abraham,
after he obeyed and left, that God continued to reveal himself to Abraham.
But what God revealed as God appeared, the God of glory appeared
unto our father Abraham. That's what Stephen says in Acts chapter number 7.
And whatever it is that God revealed, how he appeared to him, it was enough for
Abraham in the earth, the Chaldees, in a pagan society to understand he's God.
He's God. And so we have here that this Rahab, this inhabitant in Jericho,
by the way, there's a lot of people in Jericho. It's not just Rahab.
She says, we have heard, not only they, but we see that she said that the terror
in verse number 9, that your terror has fallen upon us, and that all the inhabitants
of the land faint because of you. Do you remember what happened
with the Gibeonites? When the Gibeonites come in Joshua chapter number 9,
they come over to Joshua, and they say, we're from a far country.
And they're very deceitful. And by the way, the enemy is always deceitful.
And when this enemy comes, the enemy begins to tell the Gibeonites,
when they talk about coming from a far country, they rehearse some of the things
that God did, but they didn't speak of the more recent things that God was doing
in order to try to deceive Joshua and the elders that they truly were
from a far country. So why am I saying that? Well, they received something.
Can I tell you that you received the word of God? What do we do with it?
What do we do with it? Remember, we started out looking at Jesus
when he was teaching there a couple of weeks ago, and we...
used that illustration from Matthew where he talks about teaching and he
talks about the foolish man and the wise man. They both received. And so we see
here that Rahab received something. She received a report of what God did. Not
only what God did, but what God's plan was. Notice she says that the Lord hath
given you the land. So what she received, but then consider how she responded. She
responded in a proper way to what she had heard, to what she received. Again, as
we look at the text of Scripture, as best we can tell, there's no one else in the
land that responds the way that she does to what she heard. Amen? So she responds
by saying, I know that the Lord hath given you the land. So think about this.
We have heard, but I know. Amen? Listen, we hear the Word of God. You can read it
on your own. You can hear it preached as you're gathered here today. But the
reality is that there are some that will hear and do, and there are some that
will hear and just kind of go on and check a box, I finished that thing,
whatever. But here's the reality, is that she says, I know that the Lord, again
Jehovah, she says at the end of verse 11, for the Lord your God, He is God in
heaven above and in earth beneath. What a great declaration. Now she declares this,
she recognizes this, she responds verbalizing to these two spies as we're
reading, starting in verse number nine. She's talking to the two spies, and she's
giving this information to the two spies. It's not that the two spies come into her
house and say, listen, here's who we are, and here's what God has done for us, and
here's what we plan to do. No, no. She says to them, hey, we've already heard.
Amen. Isn't that awesome? And we see her faith. So her faith, listen, I would
argue this morning that she had faith before those two spies ever showed up.
Amen. What's James talking about in James chapter number two? Well, in James
chapter number two, he says, likewise also was not Rahab the harlot justified by
works when, when she had received the messengers and had sent them out another
way. So yes, Joshua chapter two is the record of her receiving the messengers,
the spies, and sending them out another way, but understand that she heard long
before the two spies ever showed up. She responded long before the two spies ever
showed up. Now she's verbalizing it when they are there in her presence. She has
somebody to talk to. And she is, is declaring, I believe here, her faith.
She's, let me say this, she's accepting God's plan. You know what the problem is
often today for, uh, I shouldn't say the problem, a problem, uh, for, for many
people today, we don't accept God's plan. God reveals to us his plan and his word,
and we don't accept it and we want to resist it. We want to fight against it.
And, and, and we find here that Rahab, she accepts God's plan. She's in a land,
she's in a fortified city, but she says, I know that God's given you this land.
Wow. That's impactful. And guess what? It's going to be for her benefit that she
accepts God's plan. You can fight against God's plan, but you're not going to win.
Amen? The heathen rage, Psalm 2, right? And, and, and, and God laughs when the
heathen rage. And here's the reality this morning is that God has a plan. God has a
plan for, uh, this era, for this time in history. God has a plan for our church.
God has a plan for us individually, and we can resist the plan. We can fight it.
We can, uh, just dismiss it, or we can embrace the plan. We can accept.
This is what God's plan is for us. And it's always best for us. We sing the song.
It's, uh, we ought to let the Lord have his way. Amen? And I say this all the time.
It's best, it is always best to let God have his way in your life. God does not force you
to accept his plan. God did not force Rahab nor anyone else in Jericho to, to accept his
plan. He doesn't, he doesn't force us as his people to accept his plan. You read throughout
the scriptures how many times he pleads with Israel in the Old Testament that they would
just listen, that they would just obey, that they would just hearken to his voice. And
here's what God says, I will do these things for you, but you would not, not accepting
the plan of God. And so we find the, the response of Rahab is, is noted for us and we can rejoice
in seeing how she responds. Notice in verse number 12, as she then says, now, therefore,
so based on what she understands to be true, based upon what she had heard, what she received
and how she had faith in the God of the universe, she says, now, therefore, I pray you swear
unto me, verse number 12, swear unto me by the Lord, since I have showed you kindness,
that ye will also show kindness unto my father's house and give me a true token. Now, it's
interesting to me that right away, Rahab has concern for other people, specifically her
family, but she has concern for others. Amen? Listen, when you place your faith and trust
in the Lord Jesus Christ, when you understood the truth of heaven and hell, and you understand
the truth of eternity, and you got saved by the grace of God, did God give you a burden
of heart for others? Now, what about my family? Man, if they didn't accept Christ as their
savior, that means they're going to spend eternity in a lake of fire. Right? I've had
people ask me, why do you care about me? Why do you care? Why are you out here doing this?
Why are you talking to people about this? It's, it's uncomfortable because I know the
truth. Because I know the truth. We can't make anyone get saved. It's a choice they
have to make. But, oh, if we know the truth, we ought to desire that I have a burden of
heart for others. What did she know? She knew that they were going to come in and destroy
Jericho because God gave them the land. So, all of a sudden, she's got to, it's not just
save me. She says, actually, my father's house and give me a true token. She's concerned
about her family. I know some of us have family that aren't saved. Man, if you got
kids that are young and not yet to the age of salvation where they could understand,
I hope you're praying that they get saved at a young age. I pray for our grandkids.
I pray for them that they'd get saved at a young age and that they'd serve the Lord all
the days of their lives. I pray that for them. I want to be saved early. She says in
verse 13, and that you will save alive my father, my mother, my brethren, my sisters,
and all that they have and deliver our lives from death. And then answered her, our life
for years, if you utter not this our business, and it shall be when the Lord hath given us
the land. Guess what they did? They confirmed what she believed. They confirmed what she
heard and how she responded that it was true when the Lord hath given us the land that
we will deal kindly and truly with thee. Notice in verse 15, then she let them down by a cord
through the window for her house was upon the town wall and she dwelt upon the wall.
And she said unto them, get you to the mountain, lest the pursuers meet you and hide yourselves
there three days until the pursuers be returned. And afterward, may you go your way. And the
men said unto her, we will be blameless of this thine oath, which thou hast made us swear.
Behold, when we come into the land, look at this in verse 18, thou shalt bind this line
of scarlet thread in the window, which thou didst let us down by, and thou shalt bring
thy father, thy mother, thy brethren, and all thy father's household home unto thee.
And it shall be that whosoever shall go out of the doors of thy house into the street,
his blood shall be upon his head, and we will be guiltless. And whosoever shall be with
thee in the house, his blood shall be on our head, if any hand be upon him. And if thou
utter this our business, then we will be quit of thine oath, which thou hast made us to
swear. And she said, verse 21, according unto your word, so be it. And she sent them away,
and they departed and noticed the end of verse 21, and she bound the scarlet line in
the window, the blood, the blood, the representation, the scarlet line. He says in verse 18, this
line of scarlet thread in the window. And it says that she bound at the end of verse
number 21, the scarlet line in the window. Guess what that was? That was a testimony
of her faith. That was a testimony that she was accepting and believing what they said.
And we have it for us as a testimony all throughout the ages of being able to read
this portion of scripture to be reminded of the
of the Lord Jesus Christ. Without shedding of blood, there is no remission.
Amen? And we find that He had to go to that cruel cross. He suffered and He
bled and He died. Why? Because He paid for the sin of humanity with His precious
blood. We're not redeemed with corruptible things such as silver and
gold and so on and so forth. No, we're redeemed with the precious blood of
Christ in whom you have forgiveness through His blood, even the forgiveness
of sins. Hallelujah. And we find here that the response of Rahab, man, she
ought to be commended and she is being commended. And we find that it's an
exemplary type of response. And I ask myself the question and I ask you this
morning to ask yourself, how do we respond to God's Word? How do we respond
to God's Word? The Scriptures don't tell us and so just give me a little
liberty here this morning. Do you think other people saw the line of scarlet
from her window? It wasn't there yesterday but it's there today. Hey Rahab,
what's up with that? Now she wasn't gonna tell them the business, right? But there
are some things that she could tell them about the Lord. Amen? Listen, when you got
saved, if any man be in Christ, he's a new creature. Hope things are passed away
behold all things have become new. We're not trying to be undercover agents, man.
We're different and we're supposed to be different. Somebody ought to look at your
life and your behavior because your behavior is the evidence of your faith
and say, why do you do that? I noticed that every time we have lunch you pray
before you eat in the workplace and you might be the only one to do it and that's
okay. Because Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego stood up tall when they played
the music. Amen? They didn't bow down and tie their shoe and try to play this
situational ethics of I'm not really, I'm not really, tie their sandal, I'm not
really, you know, bowing down for the image, I'm just taking care. No! I think
they stood up as tall as they ever did because we're not gonna bow. Amen? We're
different. By the way, the world needs something different. They don't need more
of what they have. Amen? They got enough nonsense in the world. They need
something different. We live in a time where people are hopeless. They're lacking
joy. I'm talking about true joy. They're trying to, I mean, you look at some of the
statistics of the substance abuses and things that are going on in our
society and how people are trying to cope with all the heartache and all of
the difficulty. They need to see something different. They need to see
that you're different and that I'm different. Amen? We see how, we see what
Rahab received, we see how she responded. I want you to consider with me number
three this morning how Rahab was rewarded. How was Rahab rewarded? Well
remember, we've looked at Hebrews 11 and verse 6, you don't need to turn there, but
the Bible says, but without faith it is impossible to please him. For he that
cometh to God must believe that he is and that he is a rewarder of them that
diligently seek him. God blesses faith. When we believe him, trust him, we trust
and we obey. We have faith and that faith is evidenced by our works. And when we
trust him and we obey him, God blesses. I was thinking about this when we took our
offering earlier this morning. You know, that's a matter of faith. Yes, it's a
matter of obedience, but when you give, you're giving by faith. You're trusting
God, you're obeying God, and you're trusting that God can allow the, if we
can just use a tithe this morning, that's a simple calculated number. Amen?
Ten percent. Now, we find that the New Testament talks about that we're to be a
cheerful giver. The Bible talks about in the same passage that if we give
sparingly, we're gonna reap sparingly. We give bountifully, we'll reap bountifully.
Listen, do we believe God? So here, let's just take the ten percent number, let's
just take that number this morning and say this, here's what you're trusting,
here's your faith. Your faith is that God is going to allow my 90% to go further
than the 100%. God is going to take and he's going to use that 90%. Why? Because I
have faith in what God has said. I'm gonna trust him and it's evidenced by I
put that offering in the offering plate. That's the evidence. I believe that
God will take care of me, but I don't put anything in the offering plate. Do you
believe it or do you not? I'm not trying to get somebody to give more this
morning, I'm just simply saying I was met with it this morning when I
stood over there and I walked over here and I dropped it. Listen, it's faith and
it's obedience, it's works. I'm believing God. By the way, God is debtor to no
man. God will take care of you. God will bless. I have seen it, I have experienced
it personally. God is good. God will take care of you. And it's faith. It's faith.
And it's works. I'm putting it in. I'm obeying. It's faith and it's works. And
then we see that God rewards. So look at the reward of Rahab. I would say this as
I consider how Rahab was rewarded, three aspects of it. Number one, I would say
she was rewarded immediately. Immediately. Look in Joshua chapter number six, if you
will, in verse 21 through 25. We won't take the time to read the entirety of
Joshua chapter number six, but in Joshua chapter number six, it's when they
start marching around the walls of Jericho. Now, can you imagine being the
inhabitants and watching these guys? They walked around once today. What's going on
with that? And then tomorrow they walk around once more. What's going on? I mean,
it's kind of a, what's going on here? Guess what? It was the fact that they
obeyed what God said. What kind of military plan is this? No, it was just
here's what God said. And we're going to just trust him. Amen? And then guess what
happened? The walls fell down flat. Verse 21, if you look here at how Rahab was
rewarded immediately, it says in verse 21, and they, well, let me read verse 20.
So the people shouted when the priest blew with the trumpets, and it came to pass
when the people heard the sound of the trumpet, and the people shouted with a
great shout that the wall fell down flat. So the people went up into the city,
every man straight before him, and they took the city, and they utterly destroyed
all that was in the city, both man and woman, young and old, and ox and sheep and
ass with the edge of the sword. But Joshua, verse 22, had said unto the two
men that had spied out the country, go into the harlot's house and bring out
thence the woman and all that she hath as ye swear unto her. The young men that
were spies went in and brought out Rahab and her father and her mother and her
brethren and all that she had, and they brought out all her kindred and left
them without the camp of Israel. It says in verse number 24, and they burned the
city with fire and all that was therein, only the silver and the gold and the
vessels of brass and of iron, they put into the treasury of the house of the
Lord. And Joshua saved Rahab the harlot alive in her father's household and all
that she had, and she dwelled in Israel even unto this day, because she hid the
messengers which Joshua sent to spy out Jericho. She was rewarded immediately.
Think about it. What did the the spies say at the end of chapter 2? We read it a
moment ago. They said this, hey, there's only safety in the house. Amen?
Guess what? As we look in Joshua chapter number 6 and we read who was delivered,
who was saved, I'd say this, thank God that she had some influence on her
family. We talked about that with Noah a few weeks ago on Wednesday. Hey, Noah
preached. Everyone saw Noah. He couldn't build the ark in his garage. It's
huge. Everyone saw what he's doing. They're mocking him, whatever's going on, but his
family was in the ark. He had influence over his family. And I said this when we
dealt with that a couple of weeks ago. I think that his family was thankful that
he obeyed God. I think the family here of Rahab were thankful that she obeyed
God, because they too were saved. They were delivered. There's safety only in
one place. Well, I don't really believe that. I'm going to go ahead and try this.
Okay? Okay? Right? Listen, I don't believe that that Jesus is the only way.
I can't force you. If I could force you, it's not genuine anyway. We don't believe
in conversion by force. We just don't believe that. Why? Because it's a heart.
It's an individual matter that you make a decision. And so you can make the
decision that you're going to reject. He came to his own and his own received him
not. But as many as received him, to them gave he the power to become the sons of
God, even to them that believe on his name. We sang this morning, only a sinner
saved by grace. Listen, I'm thankful that
I'm a sinner saved by grace.
I'm a joint heir with Jesus Christ.
Hallelujah, behold what manner of love
the Father hath bestowed upon us
that we should be called the sons of God.
To God be the glory.
Amen, he saved me.
But there's some I've talked to and they say,
well, I'm just gonna try this thing over here.
I'm gonna do this thing over here.
On the authority of God's word, there's only one way.
Jesus said, I am the way, the truth and the life.
No man cometh unto the Father but by me.
Peter then, after he heard that,
stands before those religious leaders and says,
neither is there salvation in any other.
For there's no other name given among men under heaven
whereby we must be saved.
Rahab had influence in her family.
Praise God for that.
And we see the reward immediately, her and her family.
But let me say this.
I want you to think about her reward historically.
Historically.
Let me have you look in Matthew chapter number one
and then we're gonna run back to the Old Testament.
But I want you to look in Matthew chapter number one first.
In Matthew chapter number one,
we have here the genealogy as it's provided here
in Matthew's gospel.
We see it in Luke as well.
Okay.
Look in verse number five.
In Matthew one and verse number five,
the Bible says in Salmon begat Boaz of,
do you see what it says there?
I know the spelling's a little bit different
because of the Greek versus the Hebrew, but that's Rahab.
That's Rahab.
And Boaz begat Obed of Ruth and Obed begat Jesse.
You know who Jesse begat?
David.
Amen.
Think about this reward historically.
We see it immediately.
But historically, run back to Ruth with me if you will.
Ruth chapter number four.
In Ruth chapter number four,
we read similar to what we just read there
in the genealogy of the Lord Jesus Christ.
But I want you to see in verse 13
of Ruth chapter number four,
the Bible says this.
So Boaz took Ruth.
Of course, the kinsman redeemer,
what a beautiful picture in the book of Ruth.
And we don't have time to develop all that this morning.
But oh man, it's a beautiful picture
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And we find that Boaz took Ruth.
And it says, and she was his wife.
And when he went in unto her,
the Lord gave her conception and she bare a son.
And the women said unto Naomi,
blessed be the Lord which hath not left thee this day
without a kinsman, that his name may be famous in Israel.
And he shall be unto thee a restorer of thy life
and a nourisher of thine old age.
For thy daughter-in-law, which loveth thee,
which is better to thee than seven sons, hath born him.
And Naomi took the child and laid it in her bosom
and became nurse unto it.
The women, her neighbors, gave it a name,
saying, there's a son born to Naomi,
and they called his name Obed.
And we know that Naomi here, that's the grandmother.
All right, Ruth is the mother.
It says, and his name is Obed.
He is the father of Jesse, the father of David.
These are the generations of Pharaohs.
Pharaohs begat Hezron, Hezron begat Ram,
and Ram begat Amminadab, and Amminadab begat Nashon,
and Nashon begat Salmon, Salmon begat Boaz,
and Boaz begat Obed, and Obed begat Jesse,
and Jesse begat David.
Begin to think about the descendants historically
of this one Rahab because of her faith,
because of her faith.
Boaz, Obed, Jesse, David.
But eventually you go down the line
and you see Jesus, amen, historically.
Listen, your faith today, when you trust God today,
God will bless, He will reward.
Sometimes that reward is seen immediately,
but sometimes it might take many, many years,
maybe generations before it's really seen,
the impact of your faith.
But God rewards.
God bless you and say, I want to see it right now.
Sometimes that fruit takes a while.
Listen, there are people that have planted vineyards
that have never benefited from the fruit personally
because they knew the amount of time
that it would take for those fruit trees to produce.
Years, you ever read about Johnny Appleseed?
I mean, honestly, sometimes you can kind of,
but I mean, he was planting apples all over the place,
not for his own benefit, but for the benefit of others.
And then all of a sudden somebody shows up
to a place where Johnny Appleseed was
and there's an apple tree, years later.
And they're like, man, I could use an apple.
You understand what I'm saying?
It took years.
David laid up and prepared for a temple
that he would never worship God in.
He had faith in what God said.
God said, David, you're a man of war.
I'm not gonna let you build it,
but I'm gonna have your son build it, Solomon.
So David believed God.
He had faith.
He trusted that what God said was true.
So then what did David do?
Well, he prepared for the temple.
Why?
Because he believed what God said.
So his actions prove that he believed.
Does that make sense this morning?
And so he stored up, he prepared,
he gave of his own resources, he encouraged others to give.
And guess what?
When Solomon is there and it's time
for Solomon to build a temple,
everything he needs to build the temple is there.
David never worshiped God there.
He never saw it built.
But generations of people worshiped God there.
Listen, don't get so concerned about,
well, what is happening right now?
Listen, God is God.
And we see historically, there's a reward for Rahab.
I would say this as well.
You think about the eternal,
we say immediately, historically, eternally.
Listen, Rahab, since the time of her life,
God has chosen to record it in the pages of Scripture
for all of the history of humanity to be able to read it.
But then guess what?
She's gonna be with the Lord for all of eternity.
So we begin to understand as James is dealing
with these believers in the first century church,
they're dealing with all kinds of external pressures
and all kinds of persecution
and all sorts of things going on.
And James is saying, hey, listen, to these believers,
listen, we've been saved.
He said it in James chapter number one,
in verse number 18, of his own will,
begat he us with the word of truth
that we should be a kind of first fruits of his creatures.
We've been saved by the grace of God.
For by grace are you saved through faith
and that not of yourselves.
It is the gift of God, not of works,
lest any man should boast.
And I've been saved by faith.
But James says to these believers
that are maybe dealing with some conflict, why?
Because if I really live out my faith,
I'm gonna suffer.
So I'm just gonna go undercover so no one really knows.
No, James says, no, no, no.
You say you have faith.
Show me your faith by your what?
Your works, because your works are the evidence
of what you believe.
You know what's amazing to me this morning?
In America, we have great freedoms.
I really don't know that we'll always have
the same level of freedom that we have.
I'll be 46 in a couple of months
and I still consider myself to be young,
not as young as I used to be,
especially if I go out and try to play basketball
or something every once in a while,
I feel like, okay, I'm not as young as I was.
But I still consider myself young.
My kids are telling me, 46, you're in your late 40s.
You're almost 50.
And I'm like, come on, man.
The mid-40s are like 44, 45, 46.
Nope, nope, nope, 46 is late 40s.
I mean, they got me, you know.
I'm like, come on, I still feel young.
It may be in my lifetime that we don't have
the kind of freedoms that we have today.
I don't know.
But I do know in countries around the world
that have zero religious freedom and liberties,
I can't say the names of some of them
because we're on live stream right now,
but we have missionaries today in countries
that they could literally be killed for assembling.
You know what they did this morning?
They assembled.
You know what they did?
They sang songs.
They sang hymns.
They rejoiced.
They praised the Lord.
They were living out their faith.
Listen, in the danger of the persecution,
in the danger of whatever, but they.
something changed in them and what's in them has to come out because genuine
conversion produces fruit. And so James is not presenting some different path
for salvation. James is simply saying, hey you're saved, now live for Jesus. You're
saved, now take the truth and live it. Trust and obey. Obedience is the very
best way to show that you believe. How do we know? As I look at David, listen, David's
not an example that's used here in James 2, but I use the example of David with
the temple this morning. How can I stand before you and say that his work showed
his faith? Well because we see the principle all throughout scripture.
Because how you behave and how I behave is the evidence of our faith. So what do
we do? We evaluate our lives. We evaluate our lives. What about my behavior last
week demonstrated to anybody that I came in contact with that I was a follower of
Jesus Christ? That I was a Christian? Was there anything about my behavior last
week that showed my faith? We evaluate our lives and it's good for us to
evaluate our lives. Let a man examine himself. Search me, O Lord. Amen? And we
evaluate and say, listen, I want people to know through my behavior that
I'm a believer. Now it doesn't mean that it's just this idea of this, I'm
gonna not open my mouth ever. No, because we open our mouth, we speak the
truth of the gospel. But here's the reality, the message of your life better
match the message of your lips. Remember what Paul said, the things you heard but
the things you seen in me. And the message of his lips, the message of his
life were consistent. So we evaluate ourselves and this morning let's live by
faith. Trust and obey. Put in practice the principles of God's Word. Let's pray
together. Father we love you. We thank you so much for loving us. We thank you for
the examples in your word. We thank you for the challenge as we have the
opportunity to look at these portions of scripture and see how you've worked in
the lives of those that have gone before us. And Lord it encourages us but it
challenges us. And Father I pray that in the moments of our invitation this
morning that you would move and work in hearts and lives as only you can. If
there's one under the sound of my voice that's not sure of heaven, God I pray
that today they'd be saved. That they would not leave here without knowing for
sure that heaven is their home. God I pray for those that are born again. We've
been saved by your grace Lord. I pray that you'd help us to evaluate our
lives or to really determine what about my behavior shows that I've been born
again. Because genuine conversion produces fruit. And God I pray that you
would help us in the stillness of the moment to examine our lives, to evaluate
our lives, and to respond in obedience. Well thank you for the work that you'll
do. For it's in Christ's name we pray.