if you have your Bible with you, Psalm 139.
And after you find your place there at Psalm 139,
turn over to the book of Genesis
in the first chapter as well.
Genesis chapter number one,
we'll be looking at portions
of both of these passages this morning.
And we'll look at some other portions of scripture as well.
But these will be the main places
where we will find ourselves this morning.
As you've noted, perhaps,
on the back of the bulletin this morning,
the title of the message is from Psalm 139
and verse number 14, a very familiar verse of scripture.
And the title of the message,
I am fearfully and wonderfully made.
And as we continue to recognize the greatness of God
as revealed through creation,
this morning we will address the creation of man.
I believe that the record of creation
that's found in Genesis chapter number one
reaches a climax on day number six,
when we read about God making man in his own image.
I've often referred to,
and I believe it's an accurate reference
to refer to the creation of mankind
as mankind being God's most treasured creation.
And I'm so thankful that God provides us
with the record of the origin of man.
Of course, it's something that is often debated
and something that we find
many people have offered their opinions,
but I'm thankful that God has given us his word.
And his word is authoritative.
His word is trustworthy, for it is pure.
And he was the one that was there in the beginning
and he gave us a record of what he did.
And we can rejoice in that.
We find that as we've mentioned in previous weeks,
as we've dealt with this subject of great is the Lord,
and really our endeavor in the beginning of 2023
is to recognize God's greatness.
And we find that God's greatness
is revealed through creation.
And we've spent several weeks now on that subject
and seeing how God's greatness is revealed through creation.
And we've mentioned that God's great power,
he's omnipotent and his great power is revealed
as we study the truth of creation.
We also mentioned that his great wisdom,
that he is omniscient.
He has all power and he has all wisdom
and we can rejoice in those truths
and we see how great he is.
We then mentioned that creation reveals to us
that not only is our God omnipotent and omniscient,
but our God is a God of order.
And we can rejoice in that this morning
and understanding that he does all things well.
Next week we'll look at the truth
that all things are upheld by his own power
and what a blessing that is.
But God created Adam and Eve,
as I mentioned this truth of God being a God of order,
God created Adam and Eve with the ability to reproduce
and thus provided them with instruction
to be fruitful and multiply.
We find that the record of Genesis,
and I hope that as we look at both of these passages
this morning that it will make good sense to us
and we'll be encouraged and we'll be challenged
through what God has given us in his word.
But the record in Genesis really provides us
with the record of the origin of man.
Where did man come from?
Well, God made man.
And we'll read that in just a few moments
in Genesis chapter number one.
And we find that that record in Genesis
provides us with the origin of man.
But then the record that we find here in Psalm 139,
I believe provides us with the wonder
of subsequent reproduction.
We find that God created man in his own image,
Adam and Eve in the garden.
And then we find that God gave them
the ability to reproduce.
And as we look here in Psalm 139,
we see the wonder of subsequent reproduction
that is mentioned to us and what a blessing it is
to understand that I am fearfully and wonderfully made.
Notice in Psalm 139 in verse number 13,
and we'll read down through verse number 18,
the Bible says this.
For thou hast possessed my reins.
Thou hast covered me in my mother's womb.
I will praise thee for I am fearfully and wonderfully made.
Marvelous are thy works and that my soul knoweth right well.
My substance was not hid from thee
when I was made in secret and curiously wrought
in the lowest parts of the earth.
Thine eyes did see my substance yet being unperfect.
And in thy book, all my members were written,
which in continuance were fashioned
when as yet there was none of them.
How precious also are thy thoughts unto me, O God.
How great is the sum of them.
If I should count them,
they're more in number than the sand.
When I awake, I am still with thee.
As we know from our passage of scripture this morning,
and we'll look at Genesis one as well,
but I want you to notice with me, number one,
that we are made by God, we are made by God.
And I'm thankful that the testimony of the psalmist,
notice what he says, I will praise thee,
why in verse number 14,
for I am fearfully and wonderfully made.
And we find that he gives this individual perspective
when he says, I will praise thee
for I am fearfully and wonderfully made.
And no doubt this morning that each and every one of us
can have this same personal individual perspective
that we have been made, we have been designed,
uniquely designed by God.
And for that, we ought to rejoice
just as the psalmist says, I will praise thee
for I am fearfully and wonderfully made.
And we rejoice in that very truth.
We find that the Bible tells us in Psalm 100
in verse number three, a great truth.
It says, know ye that the Lord, he is God.
It is he that hath made us and not we ourselves.
We are his people and the sheep of his pasture.
Notice in Genesis chapter number one,
I asked you to hold your spot there,
but you come to the crowning point,
the climax, if you will, of creation.
On day number six, we read how that God
is going to create, it says in verse number 24,
God said, let the earth bring forth the living creature
after his kind, cattle and creeping thing
and beast of the earth after his kind.
And it was so.
God made the beast of the earth after his kind
and cattle after their kind and everything
that creepeth upon the earth after his kind
and God saw that it was good.
But then I want you to notice in verse 26,
notice what the Bible says, and God said,
let us make man in our image.
After our likeness, let them have dominion
over the fish of the sea and over the fowl of the air
and over the cattle and over all the earth
and over every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth.
So God created man in his own image.
The image of God created he him,
male and female created he them.
As we know here in Genesis one in verses 26 and 27,
that God gives us the origin of man
and we find that we're made in the image of God.
We find here this morning that we're made
with body, soul and spirit.
We are eternal beings and we are capable
of communion and fellowship with God.
We're uniquely designed by God,
created in his image and it says after our likeness.
And think about that wonderful truth of how God made man.
We find that as we come to Genesis chapter number two
and there are people that try to take just issue
with the difference in Genesis one and Genesis two.
We find that Genesis one gives us a quick overview record
of how of what God created on which day.
Genesis chapter number two kind of brings that focus in
and tells us how he created man.
We find that if you were to think about maybe
the difference of a floodlight versus a spotlight.
I think it's a great analogy where Genesis one
is kind of this floodlight if you will
of here's what God did one through six days
and here's what he created and then the spotlight comes
in Genesis chapter number two when God speaks
about how he formed man.
Notice in verse number seven the Bible says
and the Lord God formed man of the dust of the ground
and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life
and man became a living soul.
Isn't that awesome?
God tells us how he did it,
how he formed Adam there in verse number seven
and then we find that the record is given
with regard to the creation of Eve in verse number 18.
The Bible says that the Lord God said it is not good
that the man should be alone.
I will make him and help me for him
and praise the Lord for that amen
and I am thankful for my wife.
I am thankful for Holly and the Bible says
in verse number 19 out of the ground the Lord God
formed every beast of the field and every fowl of the air
and brought them unto Adam to see what he would call them
and whatsoever Adam called every living creature
that was the name thereof and Adam gave names
to all cattle verse 20 and to the fowl of the air
and to every beast of the field
but for Adam there was not a fowl and help me for him.
So notice it says that the Lord God caused a deep sleep
to fall upon Adam and he slept and he took one of his ribs
and closed up the flesh instead thereof
and the rib which the Lord God had taken from man
made he a woman and brought her unto the man
and Adam said this is now bone of my bones
and flesh of my flesh.
She shall be called woman because she was taken out of man
and what a joy and what a blessing to see the record
of the origin of man and how God has given us
that record that we are made by God.
As we go back to Genesis chapter number, excuse.
to Psalm chapter 139, again, I've mentioned already
that there in Genesis 1, we really are provided
with the origin of man, but here in Psalms,
we are provided with the wonder of subsequent reproduction.
The end of chapter number two there,
we find that God tells them to be fruitful and multiply,
and we come to Psalm 139 and we read verses 13
and following, you begin to see the wonder
of subsequent reproduction and this truth
that we are made by God.
I was sharing with Brianna last night
as we're driving home from a basketball game,
we were talking about, she actually brought up to me
how she was working on a devotion
from this particular passage of scripture
and that she was working on developing and what have you,
and I said, that's funny, I'll be preaching.
Actually, she knew, Holly had mentioned to her
when she was talking to Holly about the devotion
that, hey, that's what daddy's preaching on on Sunday,
and I told her last night, I said, you know,
I dug in and studied this passage really in a deeper way
than I ever have before, and really,
we're just this past week just meditating
and meditating on this portion of scripture,
and it's so awesome how God made us
and how he knows us in the truth of that question
that people are so just debating today
of when does life begin?
God's word answers the question.
Notice with me, back in Psalm 139,
notice what the Bible says in verse number 13.
For thou hast possessed my reins.
You know that word reins is an interesting word.
You know what that word refers to?
It refers to our internal organs, the kidney.
When he talks about it in plural sense,
he's talking about all of those internal organs,
and you notice here that he says,
for thou hast possessed my reins.
Thou hast covered me, where?
In my mother's womb.
He will use, in verse number 15,
when he speaks about there in that verse of scripture
about where life is developed,
the subsequent reproduction,
he refers to it as the lower parts of the earth,
and we find that he's referring to that place,
and you notice here that as we see my reins,
that reference to the kidney, the internal organs,
you find in verse number 15 that he says,
my substance was not hid from thee.
That word substance means my bones or my skeletal structure.
He says my substance was not hid from thee
when I was made in secret and curiously wrought.
Notice that phrase in verse number 15.
This is a word that would often be used
in reference to someone that was working in needlework
or someone that was an embroiderer,
someone that was very skillful
with weaving things together and what have you,
and you begin to notice how he says
that we were curiously wrought
and how God really dealing with here
this skillful aspect of human life.
It's said, it's my understanding,
and I did some research to confirm this,
that the human body, if you were to take all of the veins
and all of that, that it's so long
that it could wrap around the earth twice
from one human being.
Your arteries and your veins.
That's amazing.
You see the, he says we're curiously wrought.
That word used of that one that would work in embroidery
and in needlework and the skill of those individuals.
Wow.
But then he says this in verse number 16.
Thine eyes did see my substance yet being unperfect.
Now it's interesting, in our English translation,
we find the Bible says my substance yet being unperfect.
That's five words in English,
but you know that's just one Hebrew word.
One Hebrew word.
You know what that word means?
It's only used here in all of the Bible,
and it means embryo.
That's what it means.
We find here that David is giving testimony.
He says I am fearfully and wonderfully made.
We find that he says that my reigns are referenced
to the kidney, the internal organs, my substance,
my bones, my skeletal structure,
that I'm curiously wrought, the skill of God's handiwork,
that I'm fearfully and wonderfully made.
My substance yet being unperfect, literally the embryo,
and we find all of this takes place,
according to verse 13 and verse number 15,
where?
In the mother's womb.
We see the origin of man in Genesis chapter number one.
When God formed man, God created man,
but we see the wonder of subsequent reproduction
here in Psalm 139, and we find the testimony is given,
and we recognize with great clarity and great certainty
that we are made by God.
We can firmly and accurately declare
that life begins at conception.
Without apology.
He says in verse number 14, notice,
he says marvelous are thy works.
I've never gone to medical school.
I've done a little research,
and it is absolutely amazing when you study,
when you study the reproduction
in everything that has to take place
in order for life to come.
It's amazing, absolutely fascinating,
and we find that it is marvelous, wonderful, extraordinary.
It's what the word means, and this morning,
we find that David, as he's rejoicing here
and understanding, he says, listen,
I understand, first of all, that I'm made by God.
Notice this as we look here.
Not only are we made by God,
but I want you to notice, number two,
we are known by God.
We are known by God.
It's interesting, last week in Psalm 147,
we stood in amazement at understanding
that the Bible record in Genesis 1
simply says that he made the stars also,
and we gave estimate with regard
to how many stars there are in the universe
and all of that, and we said that it's interesting
in Psalm 147, and we stand in amazement
to know the truth that God, he knows their number,
and he calls them all by their names.
But you know, he didn't die for a star.
He died for you, and he died for me.
So if he knows the number of the stars
and he knows their name, and he calls them all
by their name, I'm so thankful this morning
to know that I'm known by God,
and you are known by God, and he knows everything
about us, and even though he knows everything
about us, you know what's amazing?
He still loves us.
He knows everything about us.
Notice as the psalm begins in verses one through four
of Psalm 139, the psalmist says this,
O Lord, thou hast searched me and known me.
Thou knowest my down-sitting and my up-rising.
Notice what he says, thou understandest
my thought afar off.
Thou compassest my path and my lying down,
and art acquainted with all my ways,
for there's not a word in my tongue,
but lo, O Lord, thou knowest it all together.
We'll stop and just meditate on the truth
that we're known by God.
He knows us.
He knows our name.
He knows our thoughts.
He knows what we're dealing with.
He knows where you are right now in your life.
He knows everything about you.
It's interesting, as we understand this truth,
look over at the book of Matthew, if you will,
look at two verses of scripture.
In Matthew chapter number nine, I'll say this,
that he knows our thoughts.
Some of us have a hard time remembering our thoughts.
Amen?
The older we get, it seems like the easier
we forget our thoughts.
And someone said, I had a train of thought,
I just don't know where it derailed.
And the reality is that God knows our thoughts.
In Matthew nine, in verse number four,
notice what the Bible says.
Actually, I'll begin in verse number one.
It says, and he entered into a ship and passed over
and came into his own city.
And behold, they brought him to him,
a man sick of the palsy, laying on a bed.
And Jesus, seeing their faith,
sent him to the sick of the palsy.
Son, be of good cheer.
Thy sins be forgiven thee.
Behold, certain of the scribes said within themselves,
this man blasphemeth.
Why would they take that perspective?
Well, they say, as it's recorded in another gospel,
that they said only God can forgive sins.
By the way, that's true.
But Jesus is God.
Thus, Jesus could say, thy sins are forgiven.
And we find that the Bible tells us in verse number four,
and Jesus, knowing their thoughts,
said, wherefore think ye evil in your heart?
Now, can you imagine how they must have responded
when they heard Jesus say,
why are you thinking what you're thinking?
They'd not yet made it public.
They'd not verbalized their thoughts,
but Jesus knew what they were thinking.
He knows our thoughts.
I remember teaching a...
passage of scripture, I think it was this one,
it might have been the account in Mark,
was teaching this in vacation Bible school
probably back in 2012.
A little boy sitting in my class
as I was teaching that class and we were downstairs,
actually in the classroom now where
the nursery, nursing room is,
that was a classroom back then,
there wasn't a door there to join the two rooms.
And I was sitting there and I was teaching
and I talked about how God knows our thoughts.
There's a little boy sitting in our class
about nine years old, eight years old,
and it just absolutely blew his mind.
I mean, he sat in absolute awe of
God knows what I'm thinking.
Yeah, he does.
He knows our thoughts.
He knows everything about us.
I want you to think about this.
I said we look at two verses here
from Matthew, turn to chapter number 10.
The Bible tells us that he knows
the very hairs on our head.
And you want to talk about getting detailed.
You want to talk about how well he knows us.
The Bible says in Matthew 10 in verse number 30,
but the very hairs of your head are all numbered.
That's fascinating.
See, we could only estimate last week
when we looked at the stars,
we could only estimate their number.
We do not know for certainty or accuracy
the number of stars.
We estimate based on what science tells us
as to what they have been able to project
the number of stars to be,
but we say that God knows their number
and he calls them all by their name.
But then when we begin to think about us
as individuals and how much he knows us,
remember, we're made by him,
but we're known by him.
He knows the very number of the hairs on your head.
I've often said as I've looked at that passage,
he's got to do subtraction for me.
And for some, he's doing addition and multiplication,
but someone reminded me recently
of how little hair I have.
In fact, it was the guy moving the chairlift
and I said, listen, man, I'm not gonna help you
if you're gonna keep picking on me, you know?
But the reality is that God knows the number
and he doesn't just know about the number.
He knows the number.
Think about that.
There's like eight billion people in the world today.
It's okay.
Our God is great.
He's got all knowledge, all wisdom, all power,
and he knows the very number of the hairs on our heads.
We're known by God.
We're made by God.
And then let me say this.
We are valued by God.
Notice what the Bible says back in Psalm 139.
I want you to look at verses 17 and 18.
I want you to consider with me this morning
that life is a precious gift from Almighty God.
We thank God for the life that he gives,
but we can rejoice in knowing
that though we have this physical life
that he valued us so much that he died
so that we might have eternal life.
The gift of God is eternal life
through Jesus Christ, our Lord.
And how we ought to rejoice this morning
in understanding that we are valued by God.
Notice what the Bible says in verse 17.
After the psalmist in verses 13 through 16
is rejoicing in understanding that we're made by God
and the wonder of this subsequent reproduction
and how God knows us and all that he does
and how he fashions and so on and so forth.
And he says in verse 17,
how precious also are thy thoughts unto me,
O God, how great is the sum of them.
If I should count them,
they are more in number than the sand.
When I awake, I am still with thee.
What did you think about last week?
We talked about the stars and the number of them.
Now you look at the number of the sand.
He says, if I should count them,
they are more in number than the sand.
You ever try to count sand?
Why would you try?
You must be outside of your mind, right?
I mean, you wanna talk about somebody being bored?
That takes it to a whole new level.
I think I'm gonna go over here and count sand.
Really?
I don't think anyone's ever said that.
I said I don't think anyone's ever said that, all right?
Because it doesn't make sense in my mind.
But the psalmist says,
how precious also are thy thoughts unto me, O God,
how great is the sum of them.
If I should count them,
they are more in number than the sand.
When I awake, I am still with thee.
You know, I'm so thankful that we're valued by God.
See, God made us, God knows us,
and we are valued by God.
Begin to think about this truth this morning
in looking what the psalmist says
and understanding how God knows us
and how God has us on his mind.
And we've often mentioned about the example
of the Apostle Paul praying for the believers in Philippi
and looking at that truth.
And Philippians one of how he refers to them
and how he's talking about praying for them.
And we've often, as we've looked at that passage
of scripture, we've said, why is Paul saying,
I thank God upon every remembrance of you?
Why is he thinking about them?
He says, because I have you in my heart in verse number seven
and the thoughts that he has of them,
the people in Philippi, those believers
are because he has them in his heart.
And I rejoice in understanding this morning
that God loves me with an unconditional love
with an everlasting love.
And he's thinking, he has thoughts about us
and his thoughts are precious
according to what the psalmist says.
And we this morning begin to understand
that my life is valued by God.
What a blessing.
You understand this morning that every life
is valued by God and we understand that biblically
for really two basic reasons.
Number one, we're made by God.
If we're not made by God,
the value of life decreases exponentially.
If Darwinian evolution is true,
then life really has no value.
And you understand that the perpetuity of that teaching
and the seeking to influence a generation of people
that do not value life, why?
Because life is just some random chance
and it's the survival of the fittest
and so on and so forth.
And if Darwinian evolution is true,
then life really has no value.
But God made man.
We're made by God.
We're valued by God.
And I am so thankful this morning that life has value
because life is the direct result of God's handiwork.
And God made man and man has value
because we've been made by God.
We've been made in the image and the likeness of God.
We're eternal with body, soul, and spirit
and the opportunity, the ability to be able
to commune with God and have fellowship with God.
Wow, it's absolutely amazing.
It's no wonder today
that it seems as if we continue to read
of tragic loss of life.
Perhaps you saw on your phone this morning,
just as I did, of another mass shooting
that took place overnight in California.
And we continue to see this in our society
and around our globe, but we continue to teach
that life really has no value.
No wonder they behave the way that they do.
But this morning, as the people of God,
we understand that we are valued by God,
that God loves us, that God thinks about us,
that we are valued by God, why?
Because we're made by him.
We have great value because we're made in the image of God.
We're to have dominion, if you read the text with me
in Genesis chapter one, over all of the other creation.
That's what God's design is.
We live in a time in which there are many
that value the creation more than the creator, right?
The creature more than the creator,
and they value the creature more than human life.
It's amazing.
It's Romans one being worked out, it really is.
And we find this morning that we're made by God,
that we're known by God, that we're valued by God.
I said for two reasons, number one,
that we're made in the image of God,
but think about this, number two,
that Jesus Christ, who is God, died for mankind.
You know how much value that places on your life,
on the life of man, that God robed in human flesh,
went to the cross of Calvary, shed His precious blood
so that you could be redeemed.
so that I could be redeemed. Does that not show great value? Does that not show worth?
We begin to think about the value of things when we talk about different things in our world today.
We're going to talk about the value of something and what someone would be willing to pay.
Oftentimes, you'd hear somebody say, well, this is worth x. Well, it's really only worth that
if someone's willing to pay that. Right? Would you agree? And so we find that today,
we begin to think about, well, what was paid for me? God died for me. The Lord Jesus Christ
came to this sin-cursed world. He lived a perfect and sinless life, and he went to a cruel cross,
and he bled, and he suffered, and he died for me, for you. What value
he placed upon his creation, upon mankind. Wow. This morning,
I stand in awe of thinking about human life, the gift of life. But I stand in awe
and understand the value that God has placed on each and every one of us,
being willing to die for us. Look at the verse. It's a familiar verse, John 3,
in verse number 16. It's a verse that many could quote, no doubt.
But in John 3, in verse number 16, the Bible says this,
for God so loved the world that he gave his only begotten Son.
We sang it this morning, whosoever will. It says here that whosoever believeth in him
should not perish, but have everlasting life. For God sent not his Son into the world to condemn
the world, but that the world through him might be saved. Why? Because he valued.
Listen, you understand that Jesus was the Lamb of God slain before the foundation of the world.
In eternity past, if we look at it from that perspective, from our human perspective,
God designed a plan for you and I, for mankind to be redeemed. Yes, for us to be created,
but he knew that we'd fall because he knows all things. And he knew that man would need to be
redeemed. And the plan of redemption was developed by God. God would take on human flesh and die.
He would rise, conquering sin, death, and the grave. It says in John 3, in verse 36,
he that believeth on the Son hath everlasting life. And he that believeth not the Son shall
not see life, but the wrath of God abideth on him. I'm so thankful this morning that God loved me
and God valued me. I'm thankful that he made me. I'm thankful that he knows me. I'm thankful that
he valued me. You know, in Romans chapter number 5, we mentioned Romans 10 earlier this morning
after we sang that song, Whosoever Will, but I want you to notice over in Romans chapter number
5, if you will, the Bible gives us great truth in this passage. We can't read all 21 verses
with regard to the sin of mankind and the sin entering into the world of Adam and all that
takes place, but I just want to look at a couple of verses here in Romans 5. Notice in verse number
1, the Bible says this, therefore being justified by faith, we have peace with God through our Lord
Jesus Christ. Think about that truth of justification. He says that we're justified,
how? By faith, not by works. We're justified by faith. And we understand this morning that
that work of justification, it's recognizing that Jesus Christ is God and he died on a cruel cross
and he was sinless and he was perfect and the just for the unjust and he went to that cruel cross
and he bled and he died and he suffered and he was buried but he rose again and we're justified
by faith. And then he says this, we have peace with God. How? Through our Lord Jesus Christ.
Because the reality is that before we placed our faith, before we were justified by faith,
we were at enmity with God. There was no peace between me and God, there was enmity between me
and God. I needed to be redeemed, I needed to be reconciled. Why? Because my sin, your sin,
is a barrier between us and God. And it has to be dealt with. And I can't resolve my own sin.
You can't resolve your own sin. I can't resolve your sin for you. And you can't resolve my sin
for me. Only Jesus. Only Jesus. And that's why he says, listen, we were at enmity, but he says
we have now, we have peace with God. Why? Because we've been justified by faith, so we've trusted
the Lord Jesus Christ, our personal Savior. It's not by works of righteousness which we have done,
but according to his mercy he hath begotten us. For by grace are you saved through faith and that
not of yourselves. It is the gift of God, not of works, lest any man should boast. And we find
that we're justified and we have peace through the Lord Jesus Christ. There's no way to have
peace with God apart from Jesus. It's impossible. But this morning, we rejoice in knowing that we
can have peace with God because of Jesus. Glory, hallelujah. He valued us. He died for us. It says
in Romans 5 and verse 3, but God commendeth his love toward us in that while we were yet sinners,
Christ died for us. We're his enemies.
But he died for us. Why? Because he loves us, because we're valued by God. And this morning,
I hope that as we look at this passage in Psalm 139, a familiar passage of Scripture,
we often read the words of verse number 14, I am fearfully and wonderfully made.
I am fearfully and wonderfully made. We hear it often, and it's good.
But when we really dig into the passage, I hope this morning that we recognize we're made by God.
We're not made of ourselves. God gives us the record of the origin of man in Genesis 1,
how He formed Adam from the dust, and then He breathed into his nostrils the breath of life.
Reminds me of one of our missionaries over in Senegal, the Medes. You know, in America,
so often we say, we love you with all my heart. Right? You ever use that expression?
You know what they say in Senegal? I love you with all my nose.
You say, what? Yeah, Medes' nose. You know why they say that? Because they believe the record
of Genesis 1, that God breathed into the nostrils of man the breath of life. And so, the greatest
way they could express in their culture and their understanding how loving someone
is, is to say, I love you with all of my heart. And so, in Genesis 1,
with all of their nose, not heart, because that's where the life came from. It's pretty interesting,
pretty fascinating. We read of God giving the record of the origin, but then He said,
be fruitful and multiply. And so, in creating Adam and then using a rib and causing that deep sleep
He then tells the first created human beings, Adam and Eve, He says, be fruitful and multiply.
And so, in creating them, the God of all power and all wisdom, He gave them,
because He's a God of order, the ability to reproduce. And the record of Psalm 139 gives us
the wonder of subsequent reproduction. How does it work? And we read in the text of Scripture
that we're made by God. God knows the internal organs, the skeletal structure, the embryo.
When does life begin? At conception, in the womb. Why do we value life? Because God values life.
Because life, man, is made in the image of Almighty God.
And because we're made in the image of God, there's value.
And then God died for man. Jesus Christ, the Lamb of God. Oh, how thankful we ought to be.
For He hath made Him to be sin for us, who knew no sin, that we might
be made the righteousness of God in him. It's like Corinthians 5 and verse 21. This morning,
I hope that we rejoice in knowing the truth that we're made by God, that we're known by
God, and that we are valued by God. I hope this morning that as we understand those truths,
that we would take and understand that the truth of redemption is so closely related
to what we're dealing with this morning and how we ought to recognize the need to be redeemed.
If you've not trusted Christ as your Savior this morning, understand that God loves you
and he values you and he died for you so that you could be redeemed, so that you could have
your sins forgiven, so that you could know that heaven is your home. We live in a world
today that's debating so many of these things. The origin of man, when does life begin? These
things are being debated. They're debated regularly. And many of our young people are
being given an answer different than what I proclaimed this morning from this pulpit
from this book. We cannot have our head in the sand. We must recognize this morning that
life does have value. And we must, as I mentioned that we're made by God, we can accurately
and firmly declare that life begins at conception. We're not to be ashamed of that. We fight
for that. There's a stain on America, on the world, with the shedding of innocent blood.
We find this morning that we must proclaim to a group of people, a young generation that's
rising up that does not understand that life has value because they've been taught Darwinian
evolution. They've been taught that there is no God. They deny that Jesus died to save
anybody. But we look at the truth of the Word that God has given us and we say, thank God
for the plan of redemption. Thank God for the value of life. I'll say this in closing,
just so you understand, I'm not, I haven't lost my mind this morning. I listened to an
excerpt. It was a lengthy excerpt. It wasn't just a, you know, five-second sound bite.
It was a lengthy excerpt from a man teaching at the Arizona State University, professor.
He was teaching, large class that he was teaching, and he said this in his classroom. He said,
this idea that Jesus died for you is ridiculous. And then he went on to say this because he
was teaching this idea of evolution. He said that a star had to die for you so that you
could have life. That's what he said. That's what's being taught in our education system.
That's what's being taught. I'm so thankful that Jesus died for me. I'm so thankful that
I was, I am, and you are fearfully and wonderfully made. What did the psalmist say? I will praise
thee for I am fearfully and wonderfully made. He knows me. He knows everything about me,
but he still loves me. He still loves me. If you're saved this morning, what a great,
great privilege that we have to tell someone else God loves you. He loves you. He values you. He
made you, and he died for you because he loves you so much. This morning I am fearfully and
wonderfully made. Let's pray together. Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. How we
thank you for the record that you've given us as we've looked at these two portions of Scripture
this morning and see the origin of man, the wonder of subsequent reproduction. And Lord,
I pray you'd help each and every one of us to rejoice in the truth that we are made by you.
We are known by you, and we are valued by you. Lord, I pray this morning that if there's one
that's never trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as their personal Savior, whether they're here locally or
they're tuned in via live stream, they do not have assurance of heaven, I pray this morning that today
would be the day of their salvation. That they would recognize, God, you love them, that you died
for them. They would place their faith and trust in the finished work of Christ at Calvary. I pray
for every child of God, each one that's here this morning that's been saved. We've been justified,
we have peace with God through the Lord Jesus Christ. I pray, Lord, that you would help us to
rejoice and praise you as the psalmist said. I pray that you'd help us to proclaim this message
far and wide. We're seeing an attack. God, we must stand up for righteousness, for the truth
of your word. And I pray this morning that you'd give us boldness, give us power. I pray, Lord,
that you'd help us to be good representatives and witnesses of you. I pray that in these moments
of invitation that you'd move and work as only you can. We'll give you the honor and glory for
every decision that's made. For it's in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand?