There is a fountain filled with blood, praise God for that.
I've been blessed by the music this morning.
I trust that you have as well.
And I'll say this, you know this, I don't pick the songs.
Brother Dean leads the songs.
I've given him the liberty to be able to pick the songs
throughout these years.
Every once in a while, when it comes to special services
and revival meetings and missions conferences,
we work together, but regularly he picks the songs.
And Dean, there's not a better song
that God could allege you to this morning
for our text of scripture than it is well with my soul.
And you think about the difficulties,
if you're familiar with that hymn and Horatio Spafford
and the lost tragic Chicago fire,
and then sending his family and the disaster at sea
and all that took place,
but he was able to have God's grace is sufficient.
We've been dealing with it all year.
It's our theme for 2025, God's grace is sufficient.
He's able to pen those words that is well with my soul.
And that song has ministered to countless,
countless, probably millions of Christians
that that song has ministered to since it's writing.
And I'm so thankful this morning and it goes so well.
Second Corinthians chapter 12, this morning,
we'll look at verses nine and 10.
Last week, we looked at this text of scripture
and we dealt with as we're studying through this book,
Second Corinthians, our priority on humility
and how it was a blessing that the apostle Paul
is able to speak to the church in Corinth
and he's able to talk to them about visions and revelations.
But then he talks to him about a thorn
and he talks to him about an answer.
And we looked at those three things last week
and specifically I spent some time dealing with a thorn
because the reality is as much as the visions
and revelations were a blessing from God,
the reality is that the thorn too was a gift from God.
It was a blessing from God
because that thorn was given to him.
The Bible tells us he says it twice,
lest I should be exalted above measure.
And there's a priority that God places on humility.
The Bible tells us that God resisteth the proud,
but giveth grace to the humble.
And had those revelations and visions
caused the apostle Paul to be prideful,
it would have resulted in God resisting him.
But God gave him as a gift this thorn
that would keep him humble,
that would keep him in a place
lest he be exalted above measure.
And I believe this morning just as I preached last week
that we ought to thank God for the thorn.
He's informed the church not only of the visions,
the revelations, the thorn,
but he informed them of the answer
that God gave to his request for deliverance.
In fact, he besought the Lord thrice, the Bible tells us,
and he was desiring the prayer request is simple.
It's straightforward.
There's nothing complicated
that it, the thorn, might depart from me.
We find that as the apostle Paul sought the Lord
and received an answer from God,
by the way, aren't you thankful that you can pray?
Aren't you thankful that you have a God
who hears and answers,
that is able to do exceeding abundantly
above all that we ask or think?
And I believe this morning with all my heart,
even as I mentioned last week,
that God could have removed the thorn.
It was within God's power to have that thorn removed,
but God chose instead really to do something
that I believe is even greater,
and that is this, to give his grace
and to ensure his servant that it, his grace, was sufficient.
And these verses of scripture are so profoundly impactful
in the lives of God's people,
and we live today in a society
that really prioritizes comfort,
that prioritizes pleasure.
We live in that kind of a society.
We find that as the last days are described
in 2 Timothy chapter three,
and we've looked at, as we look at 2 Corinthians 12,
we've seen some of these things.
We talked about boasters,
and the scriptures talk about boasters
in 2 Timothy chapter three.
It talks about those that are lovers of pleasure
more than lovers of God,
and we find that we live in a culture and a society
that prioritizes comfort, that prioritizes pleasure,
but we find that as we look at the perspective
of the apostle Paul in these verses of scripture,
that it stands in stark contrast
to the philosophy of the day.
I believe that this portion of scripture,
like many others, are a challenge to us.
God gives us his word to comfort us,
to convict us, to challenge us,
and all at the same time, God's word is able to do that.
I'm thankful that God's word is powerful
and that it's profitable and that God uses his word,
and God uses his servants.
There are times in which we're looking at the apostle Paul,
and as you study the New Testament,
and you study his life,
there are times in which we think of Paul
in a manner in which Paul would not want us to think of him.
We don't, sometimes we don't say it,
but maybe we have that perspective
that he's some kind of a super Christian
and so on and so forth,
and Paul would not want people to think that way of him.
In fact, he says that he's the chiefest of sinners.
He says even in the text of scripture
in 2 Corinthians chapter 12 at verse number six,
lest any man should think of me above that
which he seeth me to be or that he heareth of me.
Paul understood the importance of humility,
but when we look at the apostle Paul,
and many times we look at some of the perspectives of Paul
as he shares his heart under the different writings
to churches and to individuals,
and he's giving to us truth,
and we really see that this is how God was working
in the life of an individual,
and here's what I'm thankful for this morning.
Right at the beginning of the message,
here's what I'm thankful for.
God is no respecter of persons.
God will work in your life
in the same way he worked in Paul's life.
God will use you in the same way that he used Paul.
You know what's different?
Paul made himself available to God.
Paul has that mindset.
We often quote at Galatians 2.20,
I won't quote the whole verse,
but he says I am crucified with Christ.
Living that crucified life,
understanding that for me to live as Christ
and to die is gain,
and Paul had this eternal perspective
that so impacted every aspect of his life.
What happens sometimes if we're not careful
is that we can get our focus off of the eternal things
and onto the temporal things
because we do live in this world,
though we are not of this world,
and we find that there are times
in which we can become distracted,
and here as we look at the passage of Scripture
in verse nine and 10,
I really wanna focus this morning
on how Paul responded to the answer
that he received from God.
Sometimes we get an answer like Paul did
that may not be the answer we were looking for.
How do we respond?
Well, let me ask you this.
Have you ever seen a toddler respond to no?
Have you ever witnessed that?
Do they like it?
Generally speaking, does a toddler like no?
No.
Does a teenager like no?
I mean, we can just keep going this morning, amen?
I mean, does an adult, does a senior citizen?
We don't like no.
We want what we want.
Am I telling the truth this morning?
Our little granddaughter, two and a few months old,
I know like no.
She already has figured it out, all right?
When Juliana says no, Nova is like,
no, that's not the answer I was looking for.
She wants the yes.
How do we respond when God says no?
When God gives an answer that's different
than what we were looking for?
I know that none of us would lay down on the floor
and throw a temper tantrum like a toddler would,
but God sees your heart.
And maybe internally, you're throwing a temper tantrum
when God doesn't answer the way that you want Him to answer.
And the reality this morning is that when we look
at this passage of Scripture,
God provides us with a perspective
that is worthy of our review.
And I trust that it would impact us this morning.
There are times in which we read of the life of Paul
when he says in Philippians,
I have learned in whatsoever state I am there with
to be content.
And I've often said to you that I can't say like Paul said,
I have learned, but what I try to say is I am learning.
I look at this passage of Scripture and I say,
God, I want to be able to say this.
But the reality is I don't know
that I'm there every day of my life.
Notice what he says in verse number nine,
and he, God says to Paul, and he said unto me,
this is the answer to the request,
God, would you let it depart from me?
My grace is sufficient for thee.
Notice what he says,
for my strength is made perfect in weakness.
Most gladly, this is what Paul's response is
to the answer that God gives.
Most gladly, therefore, will I rather glory
in my infirmities,
that the power of Christ may rest upon me.
Verse.
Verse 10, Therefore I take pleasure in infirmities, in reproaches, in necessities, in persecutions,
in distresses, for Christ's sake.
For when I am weak, then am I strong.
This is Paul's response to the answer that God gave.
This is Paul truly embracing the promise that God gave in the answer because God's promise
in the answer is my grace is sufficient for thee.
He didn't say that it might be.
He didn't say that I hope it will be.
He said my grace is sufficient for thee.
And then he said this for my strength, God's strength is made perfect in weakness.
Paul says this at the end of verse number 10.
He says that the power of Christ may rest upon me.
Let me ask you this morning, do you want God's power?
Do you want God's power?
I mean, do you truly desire that whatever is necessary that you will give yourself as
that vessel that I would say, as the songwriter said, I surrender all because truly I want
God's power to rest upon me.
I recognize that without him I can do nothing, that without him I am nothing, and I need
God and I desire that God's power would rest upon me.
That's what Paul says.
I've asked the question by way of title this morning, in what do you take pleasure?
In what do you take pleasure?
Let's look at it this morning.
Notice if you're taking notes, number one, notice what Paul declared.
Paul makes this declaration.
He truly believed what the Lord told him, and he says most gladly therefore.
He says in verse 10, therefore I take pleasure, and you see that the therefore is in verse
number nine as well as verse number 10, and as Paul would use that word therefore, he's
referring back to the answer that God gave.
He was seeking God.
He was seeking that God would give him the deliverance that he was asking for, and God's
answer comes, my grace is sufficient for thee, for my strength is made perfect in weakness,
and Paul says most gladly therefore, based upon what God has said, most gladly.
Isn't that interesting?
He didn't just say therefore I will.
He didn't just say gladly I will.
He said most gladly therefore, I, will I, rather glory in my infirmities that the power
of Christ may rest upon me.
Notice in verse number 10, therefore I take pleasure in, and he's going to list five things
that he takes pleasure in.
As we look at the declaration of the apostle Paul, and we look at those two statements
in verse nine, in verse number 10, they reveal to us a man whose heart is surrendered to
God.
They reveal to us a man who is fully embracing the promise that God has given.
I mean he's all in.
He believes God.
He understands just as he would declare as we look at his life, and we find as he's there
and in that ship, and in that storm, and the angel comes and tells him that God's going
to provide deliverance, and there's been no vision of the sun, or the moon, or the stars.
I mean it's been so terrible, and men have no hope that they would survive, and Paul
stands up and says I believe God.
That it will be as he said, why?
Because Paul knew I know in whom I have believed.
And I am persuaded that he is able.
Are you persuaded this morning that God is able?
Paul embraces this truth, and he says most gladly therefore will I rather glory in mine
infirmities.
Therefore I take pleasures.
Notice as Paul begins to state in verse number 10 these five areas in which he'll take pleasure.
He says in infirmities.
This is weakness.
This is when you're feeble.
He says in reproaches, the hurt, the harm, the injury.
He says in necessities, there in verse number 10, this level of calamity, this need.
He says persecutions.
A persecution is something that inflicts pain.
The persecutor is seeking to persecute, to inflict pain upon someone.
And he says in distresses.
The word distresses literally means extreme affliction, dire calamity.
But I want you to notice something in verse number 10, that as the apostle Paul is writing
and he's giving to us his response, he's making this declaration with regard to how he's going
to respond and embrace the promise that God has given in this answer.
You notice in verse number 5 the tense of each word.
The tense of each word plural.
Is it true?
He says infirmities, reproaches, necessities, persecutions, distresses.
It's not just that I would therefore take pleasure in infirmity, a one and done kind
of a situation, one moment of persecution, one moment of distress.
No, Paul understood this is my lot, this is, I'm going to take pleasure as many times
as it comes, as much as it's repeated, I'm going to take pleasure, I'm going to glory
in this.
Why?
Because I believe God's answer.
I believe that God's grace will be sufficient at every moment.
It doesn't matter that God didn't say it would be sufficient one time.
It will be sufficient every time.
And Paul uses these plural tenses of the words to be able to communicate to us this perspective
that he has and I believe this morning that it's important for us to understand and to
say how is it that I too could have that perspective?
How is it that I too could have that type of declaration?
How is it that God would work in my life and that I would be so surrendered and so yielded
to God that I too would say most gladly, therefore, will I rather glory in my infirmities
than I would come to the place that I would say, therefore, I take pleasure in these things.
This is not a list that you would find by any person today that would speak about if
they were having a seminar, a topic of what do we take pleasure in.
This list would not sell tickets.
Amen?
But could I ask you this morning, does this list contain the things that humans face?
Absolutely.
This is where life gets real.
People today are painting pictures that are fake of their lives.
I mean social media gives you the opportunity to be able to paint a picture that's so far
from reality and everything looks good on the outside but on the inside, I mean, it's
just falling apart.
Listen, as Christians, we understand this morning that we face difficulties.
Job makes it plain, man that is born of woman is a few days and full of trouble and we understand
there are difficulties.
When you got saved, when I got saved, there was not a promise that was attached to that
that you would never have a problem anymore.
It was simply that we're heaven bound and that God is now my helper.
That God now and the Holy Spirit of God indwells me that my body is the temple of the Holy
Ghost that I know that He is with me and that He will sustain me and what a joy and what
a blessing.
But I want you to understand this morning that Paul makes this declaration.
He's not declaring this for someone to look at him as being a super Christian.
He's simply declaring what God has done in his life.
He's simply revealing to the people in Corinth that God gave me this answer and I'm embracing
the answer and I'm trusting that what God said is true and that in the moment when I
face those difficulties, when I face whatever category of issue that he mentions in those
five categories, that God's grace will be sufficient.
That God's strength will be made perfect in my weakness.
Remember the words of the Lord Jesus Christ back in Matthew chapter number five.
The Lord Jesus Christ there, we look at it, we talk about the Beatitudes and notice what
Jesus says in Matthew chapter number five.
I'll read verse one and two and then skip down to verse ten.
But the Lord Jesus Christ in verse number one of Matthew five, in seeing the multitudes,
He went up into a mountain and when He was set, His disciples came unto Him and He opened
His mouth and taught them, saying, and we're familiar with the text of Scripture.
I want you to notice particularly verses ten through twelve.
The Bible says, blessed are they which are persecuted for righteousness' sake, for theirs
is the kingdom of heaven.
Blessed are ye when men shall revile you and persecute you and shall say all manner of
evil against you falsely for my sake.
Rejoice and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in heaven, for so persecuted
they the prophets which were before you.
This is not an easy lesson.
If you're...
Like me, you like people to like you.
Amen?
I don't like people to not like me.
I don't want people to want to do me harm.
Am I being honest this morning?
We want people to like us.
But we understand that we, as Christians, as disciples,
as followers of the Lord Jesus Christ,
that we have the truth that God has given us
with regard to the spiritual warfare that we're engaged in.
And Jesus said this to his disciples,
if they hate me, they're going to hate you, right?
He said, look, don't think it's strange
when they are going to do this to you.
Why? Notice what they did to Jesus.
We look at the text back in 2 Corinthians 12.
And as I look at the declaration of the Apostle Paul,
I wonder, could I make that declaration?
Could you make that declaration?
Think about some of the things that Paul suffered.
We don't know all of them.
But we know that there's a list in chapter 11
that we studied a few weeks ago.
We know that as you study the book of Acts
that you read during the missionary journeys
of various things that happen in the life of the Apostle Paul.
And as you look at those things and you find that Paul's saying,
I'm going to take pleasure in these things.
I'm going to rejoice in glory in these things.
I'm reminded of what John Bunyan said.
You might be familiar with John Bunyan.
And of course, Pilgrim's Progress, he was a nonconformist.
He opposed the Church of England.
And because of that, because he faithfully preached the gospel,
he was put into prison.
Before his conversion, he was a notorious sinner.
But after being saved, Bunyan did all that he could to spread the gospel.
He preached wherever he could, often in fields, barns, homes, so on and so forth.
But he did not have a license from the Church of England at that time.
There was a religion act of 1592.
And anyone that would have more than five non-family members assemble,
they were in trouble.
History would tell us that Bunyan could have been released by recanting his position,
but he refused.
Instead, he spent a total of 12 years in prison
before finally being released under a declaration of the king
that freed prisoners of conscience.
But here's what John Bunyan wrote,
just a simple statement that he wrote after many of his experiences.
Here's what he said,
Therefore, I bind these lies and slanderous accusations to my person as an ornament.
It belongs to my Christian profession to be vilified, slandered, reproached, and reviled.
And since all this is nothing but that, as God and my conscience testify,
I rejoice in being reproached for Christ's sake.
What a declaration.
He said, I rejoice for being reproached for Christ's sake.
What will help you, what will help me
to be able to take the same perspective that the Apostle Paul has
in 2 Corinthians chapter number 12
is to recognize that my life is in the hands of God.
To recognize, as I quoted partially already,
I am crucified with Christ.
Nevertheless, I live, yet not I, but Christ liveth in me.
In the life that I now live, I live in the flesh.
The life that I now live, how do I live it?
By the faith of the Son of God who loved me and gave himself for me.
Aren't you thankful that Jesus loved you and died for you?
He gave you life.
And we find this morning that as we begin to understand that perspective
of the Apostle Paul, we find that he mentioned it earlier here
in the book of 2 Corinthians.
Turn back, if you will, to chapter number 4.
Notice as Paul is writing to the church in Corinth
in previous chapters, and he begins to kind of touch
on some of what he's going to further expound on
through the book in chapter 11 and 12,
but we find in chapter number 4 that he begins to explain the ministry.
He says in verse 1,
Therefore, seeing we have this ministry, as we have received mercy,
we faint not. How is it that we faint not?
It's because God sustains us.
It's because God enables us.
It's because of God's grace.
He says here in verse number 16,
For which cause we faint not, but though our outward man perish,
yet the inward man is renewed day by day.
Notice verse 17 and 18.
This helps us in understanding what Paul declares in 2 Corinthians 12, 9 and 10.
In chapter 4, verse 17,
For our light affliction.
I preached this several months ago,
but I often think about and am convicted by
the perspective of the Apostle Paul,
understanding everything that he faced,
and he said, For our light affliction.
But, notice what he says,
Which is but for a moment.
Notice what he says,
Worketh for us
a far more exceeding
and eternal weight of glory.
Do you see what Paul is saying?
This perspective that Paul has is going to help him
be able to make the declaration that he does in 2 Corinthians 12.
He makes the declaration that he does because he has this perspective
that he gives in 2 Corinthians 4,
that this is a light affliction.
It's but for a moment.
In light of eternity.
It's nothing.
But sometimes we're so temporally focused
and just give a parting thought to eternity
instead of being eternally focused
and giving a parting thought to this temporal world.
The songwriter said, This world is not my home.
I'm just a passing through.
Amen? My treasures are laid up somewhere beyond the blue.
Listen, I'm going to heaven one day.
I don't know when it is, but I look forward to seeing my Savior face to face.
The writer of Hebrews in chapter 11 says that we're strangers in pilgrims.
Hallelujah.
I'm thankful that my citizenship is in heaven.
Amen?
And I can't wait to get there.
I can say, as Paul said, for me to live is Christ,
but to die is gain.
He says this in verse 18 of 2 Corinthians 4,
While we look not at the things which are seen.
Can I tell you this morning that's so hard.
Why?
Because they're right in front of you.
You're being faced with them every day.
But he says, While we look not at the things which are seen,
but at the things which are not seen.
That takes spiritual discipline.
It takes surrender in the life of a believer
to come to the place of that position of,
I'm not going to look at these things which are seen,
but I'm going to look at that which is not seen.
He says this, For the things which are seen are temporal.
I'm reminded of what John says in 1 John chapter 2.
Love not the world, neither the things that are in the world.
He goes on to say this, that the things of the world,
they're going to pass away.
But he that doeth the will of God shall abide forever.
And we find here that he says that the things which are seen are temporal,
but the things which are not seen are eternal.
Paul said at the end of verse 17,
that this affliction that he calls light affliction
that is seemingly at every turn in Paul's life,
that he says is but for a moment,
that it worketh for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory.
And he says at the end of the really discourse, if you will,
to the church in Corinth here in 2 Corinthians 12,
he says, I receive this answer and I'm going to gladly,
most gladly therefore will I rather glory in my infirmities.
Therefore I take pleasure in infirmities and reproaches
and necessities and persecutions and distresses.
Notice, for Christ's sake, for when I am weak, then am I strong.
Do you want God's power to rest upon you?
I do. I truly do. I want God's power.
I don't want to serve God in my own power.
The reality is that if I try to serve God in my own power,
I get what my flesh can produce, and it's not much.
I want God to work through me.
I want to be a vessel that's fit for the master's use.
And we find here that as we look at what Paul declared,
we then notice what Paul discovered.
Look in the text, if you will, and we'll look at some other places,
but I want you to see what Paul discovered.
Here's what he discovered in a nutshell.
He discovered that what God said is true.
Have you discovered that in your life?
Listen, it's easy to doubt.
It's easy to hear the preaching and teaching of God's Word.
It's easy for us to read the Bible and to think,
well, that was a different time, that was for him, that was whatever.
But I want you to understand that Paul discovered that what God said is true.
Can I tell you, there's a lot of people that have discovered throughout the Scriptures
that what God said was true.
Amen?
There are people that doubted.
God says, let's see whose Word's going to come to pass.
Those false prophets are my Word.
Guess whose Word came to pass?
God's Word.
We find that God's Word stands.
God's Word stands.
And God's Word will come to pass.
And we find that we ought to come to that place where Paul came,
that we also come to that place where God came.
will make that declaration and then discover that what God said is true.
God will do what he said he would do.
And Paul, I believe that he learned in his life that God's grace is sufficient.
He learned at every turn, at every trial, at every difficulty, that God's grace is sufficient.
He learned that God sustained him.
He mentioned already in 2 Corinthians chapter 4, as we read it just a moment ago, we faint
not.
Why?
Because the inward man perished, the inward man is renewed day by day.
How is that inward man renewed?
Through God, through his word, through his spirit.
And I need the inward man to be renewed.
And so do you.
There are times in which, if we're not careful, we spend so much time and energy and focus
on the external and give just a little bit of time to the internal.
The internal is so important.
It is true that the Bible says bodily exercise profiteth little.
So there is a profit in bodily exercise.
But compared to godliness, we've got to keep that thing in the right balance.
Amen?
Notice what Paul discovered.
I believe that he discovered that the power of Christ, in fact, rested upon him.
Do you believe, as you read through the Scriptures, do you believe that God's power was evidenced
in the life of Paul?
Absolutely.
God's power was evidenced in Paul's life.
As he goes forth and he preaches the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ, he preaches it with
power.
But you shall receive power after the Holy Ghost has come upon you.
And Paul was a man that was filled with the Holy Ghost.
I'm not elevating Paul, I'm just simply saying that Paul learned that what God said was true.
He discovered that God's power would rest upon him.
God said that his strength is made perfect in weakness and Paul learned that.
He learned that God's grace is sufficient and he learned that God's power would rest
upon him.
This morning, we too must make this discovery.
Notice if you will a few examples, yes, in the life of Paul, but let's look at a few
Scriptures.
Turn back to the book of Acts in chapter 5, if you will, and we'll look at just a few
examples this morning of others that also had the same perspective, that rejoiced in
times of difficulty and hardship and persecution, who had the same perspective that the Apostle
Paul had, but then also looking at some biblical truth that will help you and will help me
to have the same perspective.
Notice in Acts chapter 5, the disciples had been facing increased adversity.
It begins to intensify.
They face this persecution.
There's all sorts of things that are going on.
There was the day of Pentecost and there were 5,000 saved and then there was a multitude
saved.
I mean, God is working and the preaching of the gospel is going forward and we find that
now these disciples are in a place where they're being confronted once again by those
religious leaders of the day, and they've been beaten.
According to verse number 39, it says, but if it be of God, you cannot overthrow it lest
happily be found even to fight against God.
Those are the words of Gamaliel in verse number 40.
To him, they agreed.
The him is Gamaliel who gave the counsel, the they is the religious body that was bringing
this persecution and they agreed.
And the Bible says when they had called the apostles, notice the next three words, and
beaten them.
Now I believe the Bible here provides for us the record that they were beaten.
I believe that this was not like that little slap on the hand that sometimes our justice
system does.
I believe this was a beating that was intended to keep them from ever speaking the name of
Jesus again.
It didn't work, but I think that's what they were trying to do.
They were trying to inflict as much pain as they possibly could to beat these men so that
they would think twice or more than twice before they ever would open their mouth again
and preach the gospel, because the pain that was inflicted upon them would be so fresh
in their minds that they would not dare do that again.
And the Bible says that they beat them, they commanded that they should not speak in the
name of Jesus and let them go.
In verse 41, the Bible says that they departed from the presence of the council.
Notice what the Bible says, rejoicing, why?
That they were counted worthy to suffer shame for His name.
That's an amazing perspective.
This is a perspective that I humbly say to you this morning is missing from 21st century
American Christianity.
It is missing in my life, in our lives.
It is missing.
And we find that the Bible says that they went out after they had been beaten, after
they had been commanded not to speak anymore in the name of Christ, and they went out rejoicing,
praising God, that they were able to be beaten to suffer for the name of Christ.
It says in verse 42, and daily, in the temple, that's public, amen, that's the public arena.
By the way, you know who was up there at the temple all the time?
Those same religious leaders.
That council that was the ones that wanted to silence them, that really if they had their
way they'd like to kill them.
In the temple, public, and in every house, private, they ceased not to teach and preach
Jesus Christ.
You know, this generation in the book of Acts, the Bible says previous in chapter 5 that
they filled Jerusalem with their doctrine.
Later on in chapter 17 it will say that these that have turned the world upside down have
come hither also.
And we find that if you look at the first century church, you look at the disciples,
the apostles, you look at those early believers in the first century, they literally took
the gospel to the known world.
The persecutions were intense.
They were consistent.
I mean, the religious leaders, they sought to silence, but they had a resolve and they
had a perspective that was so biblical and so precious that they went forward.
And because of their obedience and because of their resolve, the gospel eventually, if
you trace the history, eventually it goes through Europe and then to us.
And I know that's a big fast forward in history, but understand with me this morning that because
they had resolve, and we find here that it's that same perspective that Paul shares in
2 Corinthians chapter 12.
You know what those apostles and those disciples learned?
They learned that God's grace is sufficient.
It wasn't written in 2 Corinthians 12 yet.
Paul is not even saved yet in Acts chapter 5.
But the truth, the biblical truth, though it was not articulated in the same way that
it is in 2 Corinthians 12, 9, and 10, it was lived out by the lives of these disciples.
They knew that God's grace was sufficient.
They experienced it.
They knew that God's strength was made perfect in weakness.
Do you see the apostle Paul?
In fact, many times the church at Corinth, as we've studied the book of 2 Corinthians,
they have attacked Paul for his weak stature, his weak bodily presence.
But what does Paul say?
That his strength is made perfect in my weakness.
That was the promise that God gave.
That was what he discovered to be true.
Look if you will at 1 Peter chapter 4, and chapter 4 of the book of 1 Peter.
Now Peter is writing to these that have faced great persecution.
These that have been scattered abroad because of the persecution of Nero.
So if you begin to look at the timeline, if you will, of Acts chapter 5, and really the
early stages of the church in Jerusalem, and the big scattering hasn't happened yet.
It comes in chapter number 8, and you find that they're in Jerusalem, and God is working,
and you fast forward 40 years, 50, 40 years roughly to coming to 1 Peter, and these during
the time of Nero, these are being scattered abroad, and Peter's ministering to them.
They're in need of encouragement.
They're in need of comfort, and they're facing all of these hardships, and Peter says this
in 1 Peter chapter number 4, notice in verse number 12,
Beloved, think it not strange concerning the fiery trial which is to try you, as though
some strange thing happened unto you.
But rejoice, inasmuch as ye are partakers of Christ's sufferings, that when his glory
shall be revealed, ye may be glad also with exceeding joy.
That's looking to that eternal perspective, is it not?
Verse 14, if ye be reproached for the name of Christ, and that's what we found over in
2 Corinthians chapter 12 and verse 10, for Christ's sake, it says if you be reproached
for the name of Christ, happy are ye.
That word happy is oftentimes translated happy or blessed.
Happy are ye, for the spirit of glory and of God resteth upon you on their part he is
evil speaking of, but on your part he is glorified.
You want God to be glorified in your life?
Be found faithful but let none of you suffer as a murderer as a thief or as an evildoer as a busybody and other man's
Matters now he kind of injects verse number 15 to say look there's some suffering that can take place in life a believer
That's not the for Christ's sake kind of suffering
This is the kind of suffering because you messed up you sin you got and we're not talking about that kind of suffering
We're talking about suffering for righteousness sake we're talking about suffering for Christ's sake he goes back to verse 16 yet if any man suffer as
Christian let him not be ashamed, but let him glorify God on this behalf
We find that Paul
Peter excuse me had mentioned in the the truth that he would write to these
Individuals in the second letter that he writes to them he talks about the fact that for a period of time they
Sorry, it was in the first chapter in the first book in the first chapter
He talks about for if a need be for a period of time they would have these trials
He refers to it as a fiery trial in chapter number four and he talks about in chapter number one how that it would
bring forth
How God was working and to bring forth that which only God could do and we think about Paul or excuse me Job
In the Old Testament when I'm tried I should come forth as
gold
And we begin to look here at these
examples of really
The the believers in the early church, and then these in first Peter that have been scattered abroad, and what are they doing?
They're rejoicing
Peter says rejoice don't think it's strange rejoice
Happy are ye you're blessed
See
The perspective that's gonna happen help us this morning, and I got to go quickly here you see you've already been going quickly
the
Purpose
That God has
Is gonna help us understand the perspective
See, I believe this morning that God has a purpose
And everything that he does
God has a purpose and God is at work
Let me remind you of two biblical truths before we close this morning
And I hope that these biblical truths will help you and help me to be able to have this declaration that Paul has
This declaration that most gladly therefore will I rejoice?
That would bring us to the place where we could say therefore I take pleasure in
And it's these two biblical principles look at Philippians 1
And I won't belabor the point here if you were here last Sunday night
Brother Morrow preached from this passage of Scripture, and I absolutely love Philippians 1 in verse number 12
It's helped me so much in my Christian life
Paul understood a truth
But he wanted the people in Philippi to understand the same truth
see this morning as
We're looking at this declaration we say what led Paul to making this yes
There was an answer that God gave and he embraces it
But there was some experience that he had he understood that God was at work
And he understood that God had a purpose and he wants others to have the same understanding in verse 12 of Philippians 1
He says, but I would have
Excuse me, but I would
Ye
Should understand brethren Paul said I want you church to understand this important truth
And he says this that the things
Which happened unto me?
Think about the list of things
That's not
Rejected here in Philippians 1, but when you study the scriptures, you know all the things that Paul suffered and he says that the things
Which happened unto me have fallen out rather?
Unto the furtherance of the gospel
What is it that God might allow in your life or my life
for the furtherance of the gospel
That we may say I don't I don't want that thing in my life, I don't like that thing in my life
I don't want to have to go to the I'll use a simple illustration
I don't want to have to go to the mechanic because my car broke down
I don't want to have to go to the doctor because I have this ailment
But understanding that there's a mechanic that needs Jesus and there's a doctor that needs Jesus and maybe God would allow
That's just a light affliction. It's just a little
Hiccup in our schedule when we have a mechanical issue, but but I know we can get so sideways with it
We get so frustrated with it. We can why?
And we could possibly miss the opportunity that God has for us that that person is a person that yes is working a job
That's making a living but it's a person that needs the gospel of the Lord
Jesus Christ and could God entrust you could God entrust me to be faithful in that situation
To be one that would be in that situation and say, okay Lord. I know you're in control
I know God that you have a purpose. I didn't ask for this. I didn't sign up for this. I didn't neglect the maintenance
I didn't neglect taking care of myself, but here I am and this happened in God
How are you going to use this situation that you would be glorified?
it's a perspective that
that is often missing but so
Biblical look if you will at Romans chapter 8 and I know Romans 8 is a familiar passage of Scripture
But I'm gonna go way beyond the verse that we often quote
In Romans chapter 8 in verse number 28
Notice what the Bible says and we know
Those are three words that sometimes are missed when we quote Romans 8
Sometimes we say all things work together for good. We just kind of start there
But I want you to know that Paul says and we know
This is the confidence that we need to have and we know that
most things
Is that what your Bible says? If it is get rid of it and get a new one. Amen, and
We know that all
Things now when the Spirit of God the Bible all Scripture is given by inspiration of God. Amen
We track him. It's been perfectly preserved providentially preserved
We have God's Word and when God says that all things he means all
things
There's no exception. There's no well pastor. You don't understand. No, no, no all things
Amen, and we know that all things work together for good to them that love God to them who are the called according to his purpose
For whom he did for know he also did predestinate to be conformed to the image of his son
Conformed to the image of his son that he might be the firstborn among many brethren moreover
Whom he did predestinate them. He also called and whom he called them
He also justified and whom he justified them. He also glorified. What shall we say to these things?
What shall we then say to these things if God before us?
Who can be against us?
He that spared not his own son consider that God spared not his own son
But he sent Jesus to die for you and to die for me
He that spared not his own son, but delivered him up for us all
How shall he not with him also freely give us all things who shall lay anything to the charge of God's elect?
It is God that justified verse 34. Who is he that condemneth?
It is Christ that died yea rather that is risen again
Who is even at the right hand of God who also make an intercession for us?
who shall separate us from the love of Christ shall tribulation or distress or
persecution or famine or nakedness or peril or sword now
I know verse 35 is not an exact replica of the verse that we read in 2nd Corinthians 12 10, but there's some similarities
Amen, and Paul says shall these things separate us from the love of Christ verse number 39. Excuse me
Let's look at verse 36 as it is written
For thy sake we are killed all the day long. We are accounted as sheep for the slaughter. Nay in all these things
We are more than conquerors through him that loved us for I am persuaded. I
Mean to be persuaded
Absolutely convinced. You're not gonna change my mind for I am persuaded
That neither death nor life nor angels or principalities nor powers nor things present nor things to come now
that's a pretty good list and
In case you thought you had some wiggle room. He says nor height nor depth nor any other creature
Shall be able to separate us from the love of God, which is in Christ Jesus our Lord
Aren't you thankful for that biblical truth God's working God's working God has a purpose you say
But I'm dealing with some trials. I'm dealing with some afflictions. I'm dealing with some distresses some necessities
Listen understand that God says that his grace is
Sufficient will you embrace it this morning?
Will you embrace it like Paul did will you declare as Paul did?
Do you want God's power to rest in your life? Do you want God to use you for his glory?
It's amazing what God can do in the life of a vessel that is fully surrendered to him. I
Heard the song it's from the car family
Says it was written in 2017
The song is titled this. Thank you for the storm
Thank you for the storm
It's a blessing when I see the dark clouds parting
Can you agree with that when the rain is gone and the Sun is breaking through? I?
Anticipate when life will just be normal just to close my weary eyes and rest in you
My heart can rest so easy when there's blue skies
when the wind is gone and rain is not in sight,
how I long to hang my sword above the mantel
and away from harm and distant from the fight,
but I wouldn't know, I wouldn't know your peace
without the hard times.
Or be thankful for relief without the pain.
I wouldn't love the light if it were not for darkness,
or appreciate the sun without the rain.
How could I understand forgiveness without failure?
Or feel the warmth of love without the bitter cold?
How could I hold your healing hands without affliction
and be blessed to see your mercies all unfold?
Sure, it's a blessing to be safe, secure, and warm,
but Lord, I want to thank you for the storm.
Imagine as Peter sat in prison.
He may have paced the floor with chains around his feet,
and in his mind, the devil taunted as he whispers,
the battle's lost, and this is your defeat.
But that's not really what Peter did.
The Bible tells us he was sleeping between those soldiers.
He goes on, then his mind went back to that night in the tempest
when the master spoke and winds and seas obeyed,
and remembered that storm calming all around him,
he could rest in that dark prison unafraid,
and say, I wouldn't know your peace without the hard times,
or be thankful for relief without the pain.
They're sweet trophies.
I'm going to skip down through the course.
They're sweet trophies that remind me of all you do.
Sure, it's a blessing to be safe, secure, and warm,
but Lord, I want to thank you for the storm.
There are storms in life.
A preacher of yesteryear said,
you've either just come through one,
or you're in the midst of one,
or there's one brewing on the horizon.
If you've lived life for any period of time,
you know there's a lot of truth to that statement.
In what do you take pleasure?
Paul gives us a perspective that's so powerful,
that's so needed in 21st century American Christianity,
that we would truly believe what God has said to be true,
that his grace is sufficient,
and that his strength will be made perfect in weakness.
Let's pray.
Lord, we love you.
We thank you so much for loving us.
We thank you for your word.
God, I pray that you'd move in hearts and lives as only you can.
I pray that we'd be responsive.
Folks have listened so well.
And Lord, I pray that at this time,
when we have this invitation,
that we are responding in obedience to be doers of the word.
God, maybe someone's in the midst of a storm.
Maybe someone's been struggling,
thinking life isn't fair,
complaining and bitter,
not outwardly, but inwardly,
throwing that temper tantrum
because they don't like the answer that you've given.
God, would you help us this morning to embrace your word,
to trust it to be true.
I pray that we'd live, not for our glory,
but God, for your glory,
that you would use us to reach others
with the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
I pray that as we have the moment of invitation,
Lord, that you would move freely in our hearts
and that we'd respond.
And we'll thank you for what you'll do.
For it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano.
If you're not sure of heaven,
we'll take a Bible and show you how you can know for sure
that heaven is your home.
Maybe you're going through a storm,
you need to come and thank God
for what he's doing in your life.
Maybe you need to come and surrender and yield.
However it is that God may have worked in your heart,
as Kimberly plays, the altar is open.