Baptist nap, you should be chipper and ready to go.
And we had spaghetti and meatballs today
and all the trimmings that went with it.
And we enjoyed a good meal over there at the pastor's house.
I'll tell you what, his wife is gonna make me fat.
One of the things that happens to us as we travel
is that we eat so much on the road.
We're not big eaters, but when we are out
in the revival meetings, everybody wants to feed us.
And so you don't wanna be unkind
and you don't wanna be rude,
so eat everything in sight, amen?
And so we'll go back a little heavier than we came.
So I had to go back on some kind of a diet
and get on that exercise bike again, I guess.
But praise the Lord, we sure have been enjoying ourselves
with the mans and they've been gracious to us.
And it's a blessing to have the house over here.
And they've got that nice prophet's chamber downstairs.
We're very comfortable down there and we're enjoying it.
And so we're thankful for that.
It's a blessing.
It's a nice little respite for us to get away
and be able to spend time together down there
during the course of the day.
And Lyndon and I have enjoyed that a great deal.
I want you to turn tonight to Jeremiah's Lament,
chapter three, Jeremiah's Lament, chapter three,
the book of Lamentations, chapter three in verse 22.
Jeremiah chapter three in verse, or Lamentations rather,
Lamentations chapter three in verse 22.
Familiar or past the scripture,
many of you may even have this memorized.
I know I do, but I do love this, these two verses.
And we're gonna look at these tonight as we begin.
And if you would please, would you stand with me
out of respect for reading of God's holy
and foul on earth and inspired word, amen.
Lamentations chapter three in verse 22.
I'm gonna read two verses.
We'll pray.
We'll get into the message that God has for us tonight.
The Bible says this, it is of the Lord's mercies.
It's of the Lord's mercies that we're not consumed.
Why?
Because his compassions fail not, amen.
Now, I like this.
It says they are new every morning.
So he's constantly renewing them.
They are new every morning.
And then he says this, great is thy faithfulness.
What a wonderful passage of scripture this is.
Let me read it again.
It's of the Lord's mercies that we're not consumed.
That we're not consumed because his compassions fail not.
They are new every morning, great is thy faithfulness.
I encourage myself with that.
It's listen, we serve a merciful God.
For God is good and his mercies endure forever.
Aren't you glad for that?
If we didn't have a merciful God,
I tell you where most of us would all be tonight.
I sure am glad he's merciful to us.
So we're gonna look at some things tonight.
I trust be a help, encouragement and blessing to you.
Father, we thank you for the reading of thy word.
Add your blessing now to it.
Help your servant tonight.
As I try to readily divide the word of truth,
please fill me with thy spirit, oh God.
And meet with us tonight.
I pray you to bind the strong man
as you put a hedge of protection about us tonight.
There will be no satanic disturbance here in this place.
The devil will not find any place in here tonight.
But God, I pray that you would just protect us
and give your angels charge over us.
Father, we thank you for the gathering
of your people tonight.
Bless our time together.
We'll thank you now for it in Jesus' precious
and holy and wonderful name.
And this I do say, amen and amen.
Thank you, may be seated.
Turn with me if you will please to Psalm 103.
Psalm 103.
Another great passage of scripture.
I love the Psalms.
It's a Psalm of David.
And of course, most of the Psalms were put to music.
This was God's hymn book.
And I mentioned to men yesterday
that the Psalms were written by David or Asaph.
And Psalm 90, as far as we know,
is the only Psalm written by Moses.
And of course, the theme there
in the center of that Psalm is time.
Now, beloved, let me say this tonight
before I get moving here.
You know, we ought to be found redeeming the time
for the days of evil.
You know, we're inveterate time wasters, we Americans.
We waste a lot of time.
We waste a lot of time on things that really don't matter.
I don't know what it was,
but when I turned 55 many years ago now,
I told the Lord, I said, Lord, listen,
I don't wanna be involved in anything that doesn't matter.
I don't wanna be involved in anything that wastes my time.
I don't wanna be involved in anything
that takes me away from the principle thing in life,
and that's living for you.
And so I made that promise to God,
and I don't know why it was, it happened at 55.
In fact, I heard Dr. Roloff say the same thing,
that when he turned 55, he said,
I just got to the point
where I just didn't wanna be found wasting time.
And yet, if you would look at Dr. Roloff's life,
all his life, he was busy for the Lord.
So I don't know what it was he thought was distracting him,
but he didn't seem to me like a distracted man.
But we are a distracted generation.
This is one of the most distracted generations
that I can think of in my lifetime.
And I'm sure that if we were to look at the sum total
of the years that we have been a nation,
and we look at our churches and look at God's people,
I'd say that we've always had a certain amount
of distraction in every generation,
but this is a really distracted generation.
I'll give you several examples.
One of them is social media.
The social media is really bad for our time.
And my pastor says all the time,
you need to get off Facebook
and get your face in the book, amen?
And I think there's truth to that, and I use Facebook.
I post something on there every day.
I write little articles and I put them on there
and just share some thoughts every day on Facebook.
You can use those social media outlets for the glory of God,
but it can be a distraction.
You know, all the rest of it, TikTok and Instagram
and all the rest of that business, even the internet,
people get on the internet and spend all day
just roaming around and doing Google searches
for who knows what.
And then of course, there's the television
and there's movies and there's all kinds
of other distractions.
A lot of people have hobbies that take them away
from the things of God.
Now there's nothing wrong with having hobbies.
I know a lot of people that are obsessive about golf,
and I can't understand that.
Bunch of grown men chasing a little ball around the field.
That's never figured for me,
but I know that people enjoy that game
and there's nothing wrong with that game.
But sports has become the God of America
and we know that people are so absorbed
and so immersed in sports.
It's sports, sports, sports.
When I got up here, I was with a rental car,
I'm looking for Christian radio stations
or something to listen to.
And I was doing the automatic seek on the radio
and it seemed like about every other station
was a sports station.
And they had ASPN one, two, three, four, and five
and whatever else today.
And so people are so absorbed with and saturated
by the things of this world.
I'm talking about God's people here
that we're a distracted generation.
And we need to get back to things of the Lord.
We need to focus on God, amen,
because we don't have a lot of time.
Bible says life's but a vapor.
And I mean, it just goes quick.
And you get down to the point where I'm at now
and some of the others here tonight that are older than me,
you look back at it and you say, man, where did it go?
And sometimes you wish you hadn't wasted
some of the time you wasted.
And so let's use God's time that he's given.
By the way, time is God's gift to us.
You get out of bed in the morning,
put your feet on the floor, that's a gift of God, amen.
You got up, you put your feet on the floor,
you drew a breath and you stood up
and you got ready for the day
and you went out into the day and got going
and you're still alive, that's God's gift.
Life is God's gift to us.
Why should we waste that?
And many of you have occupations you're involved in,
some are retired, praise the Lord.
Someone said to me recently, are you gonna retire?
I said, no, I'm just gonna refire.
They said, I thought you were retired.
I said, no, I'm just tired.
So I mean, it's just the way it is.
But you know what I'm saying,
we ought to be found redeeming the time.
But Psalm 103, I'm gonna begin in verse one,
read down through this, make some comments about it,
then we're gonna move around just a little bit
in the word of God tonight.
But in Psalm 103 is inspired by the Holy Spirit.
David writes this, he said,
bless the Lord, O my soul,
and all that is within me, bless His holy name.
Bless the Lord, O my soul,
and forget not all His benefits.
Amen.
Don't you think that our God's a beneficent God?
You know, when I was in the military,
we're all talking about benefits.
And we call it, we said, I'm gonna get my bennies.
That's what we call it, bennies.
I'm gonna get my bennies, amen.
We're gonna do our 20 years or 30 years,
whatever it is, gonna retire and get our benefits.
And we always are talking about benefits.
Let me tell you what, there's no greater benefit
than what comes at the hand of God.
And by the way, he's not just talking
about material things here.
Certainly we are blessed with material goodness.
There's no two ways about that.
I don't know about you, but I'm getting three meals a day.
I got a roof over my head.
I got Raymond on my back.
I got transportation.
Praise the Lord, and God's allowed me
to be able to earn a little money
over the course of my life,
and He's provided for my needs, amen.
And so God has blessed me
with those kind of material benefits,
and I thank God for that.
It all comes at the hand of the Lord, amen.
We say my house, no, it's God's house.
We say my car, no, it's God's car.
We say my this and my that.
I mean, we're so possessive,
and we had to remember that everything we have
comes at the hand of God.
God gave me everything I've got.
It's the Lord's, and it's to be used
for His honor and glory.
But He's speaking about the spiritual benefits
here as well.
We certainly have been the benefactors
of all manner of spiritual blessings,
and I praise God for that.
Blessed Lord, oh my soul, and forget not.
See that, what it says?
Forget not, don't forget.
He told the children of Israel,
look, if you've got wealth,
remember where it came from.
Don't forget where it came from,
who gave it to you.
Forget not all its benefits.
Verse three, who forgiveth all thine iniquities.
I won't say that word all.
What a wonderful word that is.
He forgiveth all.
giveth all thine iniquities, who healeth all thy diseases,
who redeemeth thy life from destruction,
who crowneth thee with loving kindness and tender mercy,
so satisfy thy mouth with good things,
so that thy youth is renewed like the eagles, amen?
The Lord executeth righteousness and judgment
for all that are oppressed.
He made known his ways unto Moses,
his acts unto the children of Israel.
Oh, I love verse eight.
It says, the Lord is merciful and gracious.
Slow to anger.
Notice what it says, and plenteous in mercy.
He will not always chide,
and neither will he keep his anger forever.
Hold back his anger.
He will not, he hath not dealt with us after our sins,
but I'll tell you what, we ought to be glad for that,
nor reward us according to our iniquities.
For as the heaven is high above the earth,
so great is his mercy toward them that fear him.
As far as east is from the west,
so far hath he removed our transgressions from us,
like as a father pitieth his children,
so the Lord pitieth them that fear him.
I like this, for he knoweth our frame,
he remembereth that we are dust.
What a wonderful psalm this is.
I'm gonna stop there.
I could read it a little bit further,
but I'm gonna stop right there.
Now, I want you to see this.
I've noticed several things about this psalm
up into verse 14, and this is what I've noticed.
In verse three, the Bible says clearly
that he's a forgiver.
It says, our God's a forgiver.
I thank the Lord that I'm forgiven of my sin.
Amen?
And I thank God that as a Christian,
when I sin against him, I know I can go to him,
and I can lay my sins out before him
and ask his forgiveness for that which I've done,
repent of my sin, to confess my sin, to forsake my sin.
Lord, forgive me for what I've done.
Forgive me for what I've said.
Forgive me for the way I've behaved.
And listen, my God is a forgiver.
He's in the business of forgiving.
But I tell you what, when I got saved by the grace of God
on April the 7th, 1974, at 11 o'clock at night,
one of the things that I know for sure is God forgave me.
But I'll tell you, it's like the burden of sin
came off of me, and I knew that I was
in the army of the forgiven, amen.
I knew that I'd been washed in the blood of the Lamb,
praise the Lord, and I knew that he had washed away
all of my sins.
What a glorious thing it is to know that we're forgiven.
In verse three, I also see it says he's a healer.
I'm reminded that God is Jehovah Rapha, the God that heals.
And they're not talking about just physically healing,
no, he does heal physically.
But he heals us of all our iniquities and all our sins.
It's spiritual healing that he is giving reference here
to the most.
But he does, he is still in the healing business,
and he can heal physically.
I praise the Lord for that.
I won't go into the whole thing and give detail.
We know a lady had seven tumors in her abdomen,
and they said she had a couple months to live.
She was 30-some years old.
Go home and kiss your kids and say goodbye to your husband
and put your things in order because you're gonna die.
And she said, well, I want a second opinion.
This was a Navy doctor told her this,
and of course, they'd done everything they could
to try to treat her,
and they couldn't do anything for her anymore.
They sent her back here to Oak Knoll Naval Hospital
in San Francisco, and she got a second opinion.
The oncology department did a workup on her.
They saw the PET scans, the CAT scans, the MRIs,
the x-rays and everything.
They saw all the workup, all the blood work
and everything else, and they started from scratch
and did it again.
And at the end of the week, they said, we don't understand.
You haven't got a tumor in your body.
Not one single tumor was there.
And she'd been completely healed by the grace of God.
And I'll tell you, she had gone to the men of the church
before she left Japan, and she said,
I want you guys to do what the Bible says
in the book of James.
Would you lay hands on me and pray over me
and anoint me with oil?
That's biblical.
Now, the oil doesn't heal, it doesn't cure.
The oil represents the Holy Spirit and the word of God,
and she was just putting her life,
just trusting her life to the Lord
and saying, God, whatever you're willing to do,
whatever your will is, I want your will in my life.
If it's your will to heal me, amen.
If it's not, well, praise the Lord.
The ultimate healing is going home and be with Jesus.
Amen.
And God healed her, and I'm gonna tell you,
he still can heal.
In verse four, we see this.
The Bible says he's a redeemer.
He has redeemed my soul.
He's a redeemer.
Because of the blood of Jesus on the cross in Calvary,
he is a perfect redeemer that satisfies God's demand
against me when I put my faith and trust in him
and receive him as my personal Lord and Savior, amen.
He's my redeemer.
In verse four, it says he's a crowner.
He's the crowner, amen.
In verse five, it says he's the satisfier.
Well, I'll tell you what I know about you,
but he satisfieth my soul.
Amen.
He ought to satisfy your soul, amen.
If you're saved, he's your satisfier.
At number five, or verse five, he's the renewer.
God maketh all things new.
Well, I praise the Lord for that.
Now, listen, when we have revival, that's a time of renewal.
It's a renewing experience.
When I got to, I experienced a personal revival in 1991,
and it was almost like getting saved.
I mean, now you can't get saved again, again, again,
again, again, amen.
Once saved, always saved.
And by the way, you can't lose your salvation.
I praise the Lord for that.
But it was a good thing when I experienced revival,
and it renewed me.
In verse six, we see he's the righteous.
Well, I sure am glad he's the righteous, amen.
In verse eight, we see he's the merciful.
We're gonna talk about that in a minute.
And then we see in verse eight also, he's the gracious.
Well, I don't know about you,
but my God's been gracious to me.
He's been gracious.
And then last of all, in verse 13,
I'm sure there's more here.
This is just some of the wonderful attributes of God.
In verse 13, the Bible says he's a pitier.
He looked down on this poor boy, and he took pity on me.
Amen.
I tell you, the Holy Spirit of God
had me under conviction for six long months
before I got saved.
But I tell you, I've been running from God all my life
and didn't get saved at 27.
And I tell you what, God was merciful to me,
and he would not let me go
without me hearing the gospel over and over and over again
throughout my life.
And I just rejected God out of hand
because I wanted to live my own life
the way I wanted to live it.
I was just rebellious.
I just made my decision I was gonna live for sin.
And I lived all out for the devil.
Now, I will not tell you the things I did
because I don't wanna give glory to him,
I wanna give glory to God, amen?
I'm not gonna glorify what the devil did in my life,
I wanna glorify God for what he did in my life.
And one night I bowed my head in repentance,
and I turned away from my sin,
and I turned to Jesus Christ,
and I put my faith in him,
and I got washed in the blood of the Lamb, amen?
And I became a new creature in Christ.
I've been the same since.
And now I've been saved almost half a century.
Isn't that a wonderful thing, to be saved that long?
Now, some of you have been saved longer than me.
I've talked to someone not too long ago,
they've been saved like, I think, 70-some years.
If you're here tonight, and you're in your 90s,
my brother, and you got saved when you're 10,
man, you've been saved 80 years,
if that was your testimony.
So, you know, really, when it comes down to it,
being saved a half century is a wonderful thing.
And you know what, I've never gotten over it.
You never get over it.
Because you become a new creature in Christ,
and all things have been made new.
You have new desires, you have new wants,
and the main thing you wanna do is you wanna serve,
and you want to honor, and you wanna glorify your Savior.
Amen.
Now, let me say this.
As I look down through this, I gotta tell you,
there's one word that stands out to me.
You know what it is?
It's the word mercy.
And of all these attributes of God
that I mention here tonight,
it calls him the merciful in verse eight,
the word mercy stands out.
So of all the attributes of God
that stand out to me, it's mercy.
And by the way, he delighteth in mercy,
takes pleasure in mercy,
he's pleased to do it,
he's moved to bend down and extend mercy to us,
we poor sinners.
It's his desire to demonstrate mercy toward us,
and I noticed this, and I wrote it down
because I sometimes forget these things
now at this point in my life,
but I noticed there are 346 verses
in the word of God containing the words mercy,
mercies are merciful.
So 346 times in my Bible, in the King James Bible,
346 times God mentions the word mercy
in one form or another.
That's how often he speaks of it.
Grace is receiving what we do not deserve,
and mercy is not receiving what we do deserve.
Amen, I praise the Lord for that.
Now here's the thing that I wrote,
I had to write this down
because I didn't want to lose this one.
There is not one verse of scripture
that declares that God takes delight in wrath.
Did you hear what I just said?
There's not one verse of scripture
anywhere in the Bible that says
that God takes delight in wrath.
Now it doesn't mean that God is not a God of wrath
because he does demonstrate wrath,
and he certainly demonstrates judgment,
but God delights in mercy.
He doesn't delight in wrath.
That's the kind of God I serve.
Yes, that's my King, that's my God,
that's my Redeemer, that's my Savior,
that's my Lord, amen?
He is a God, ultimately, he is a God of mercy.
Turn in your Bible, if you will, please, with me quickly.
I gotta keep moving here
because I want to jump over in the New Testament.
Go over to Micah, chapter seven.
Let me show you this.
Micah, chapter seven.
Micah, chapter seven, verse 18.
This is a wonderful verse.
It says this.
Who is a God like unto thee that pardoneth iniquity,
that passeth by the transgression
of the remnant of his heritage?
He retaineth not his anger forever because, look at this,
because he delighteth in mercy.
Do you see that?
It says he delighteth in mercy.
Going on to the next verse, I read this in verse 19.
He will turn again, he will have compassion upon us,
he will subdue our iniquities,
and that will cast all their sins into the depths of the sea.
But when I read what he says here,
it says he delighteth in mercy.
I just want to have a hallelujah fit.
I mean, just think about that.
Think of the weight of that statement,
the magnitude of that statement where God says,
hey, listen, I, God,
God, delight and mercy.
That's what he says.
I think it was a missionary who wrote this down, he said, mark those words, he delighteth
in mercy, and you will not find a single verse anywhere in the book that says he delighteth
in wrath and judgment and punishment, not a verse anywhere in the whole book from cover
to cover, from Genesis to Revelation, you won't find a single verse that teaches or
says that God delights in judgment or punishment or wrath.
But you can find many places which either stay plainly or clearly indicate, just as
it does here in Micah 7, 18, that he delighteth in mercy.
It is his joy to show mercy to fallen man.
Can you imagine that?
And I don't know about you, but I'll tell you something, when I think about it, it just
absolutely and positively stultifies my brain.
I just have to sit and wonder.
I just have to consider this, muse upon this, meditate on it, think about it.
Why would God want to show mercy to me?
I know me, and I know who I was, and I know what I did.
And I wonder sometimes, why, oh God, would you want to show mercy to me, an old wicked
sinner?
We were in a fellowship one night, and there was a group of us that get together after
church, we used to call it an afterglow back in the 70s, and we were sitting around in
someone's living room with a fire going in the fireplace, and we were just having coffee
and stuff and talking.
And they went around the room, and everybody gave their testimony.
On those days, I gave them a whole testimony, scared everybody to death, amen.
And one of the men in the room, Al Kiefer was his name, he was a dear brother.
I got to speak at his funeral, and I miss him.
Brother Al Kiefer said this, he said, well, you know what, he said, I was raised in a
Christian home, I went to Christian school, he said, I went to Bible college.
He said, I never tasted many of the sin that some of you people have tasted.
He said, I've never drank, never smoked, he said, I never used foul language, he said,
I never ran around with women of ill repute, I never did any of these things, I never had
an immoral life.
He said, well, I'll tell you something, if I had to die without Jesus Christ, I'd go
in the same hell you'd have gone to if you'd not been saved.
We need to think about that.
There's too many people that live a so-called moral life that are dying in their sins and
going to hell, see?
So God's been merciful to all of us.
He's been merciful to every last one of us, amen?
Missionary James Dearmore said this, he said, but though he caused grief, yet will he have
compassion according to the multitude of his mercies, for he doth not afflict willingly,
nor grieve the children of men.
God does not grieve nor afflict men willingly, but he does so only upon great provocation.
You realize how, hey, listen, do you realize how long-suffering God is?
You realize how patient God really is with us?
And when he does chastise, you realize how gentle he is, at least in the initial stages
of that, amen?
He's gentle.
He's good to us in so many ways.
Listen to this, trusting in mercy implies a cessation from all excuses and excuse-making.
The moment you trust in mercy, you give up all apologies and excuses at once and entirely,
for these imply a reliance upon God's justice.
An excuse or apology is nothing more nor less than an appeal to justice, a plea designed
to justify our conduct.
Trusting in mercy forever implies that we have ceased from all excuses forever.
The very thing that mercy does is to set aside the execution of the penalty of the law.
Now Charles Finney said that.
Now that's an interesting statement.
Mercy involves this, it's the setting aside of the execution of the penalty of the law.
And when you stop and think about salvation, that's exactly what it is.
The penalty of the law is set aside when we're saved by the grace of God, all because of
the blood of Jesus.
What can wash away my sins?
Nothing but the blood of Jesus.
What can make me whole again?
So precious is the flow that washes, cleanses white as snow.
No other fount I know, nothing but the blood of Jesus.
Amen?
Praise the Lord for the precious blood of the Lamb of God which taketh away the sin
of the world.
I want you to go to Luke chapter 15, we're going to go over there and I'm going to go
down through a portion of this text with you tonight and we'll finish up there.
Luke chapter 15 verse 11.
Now the two examples given, the two parables given before this parable are just a little
bit different than this one and I'm going to go down through this just over the next
few minutes and just share some thoughts with you about this particular scenario that the
Lord Jesus gives us here in Luke chapter 15 beginning in verse 11.
Now it reads this way, and he said a certain man had two sons.
Now you know we're talking about the prodigal son here.
And you know the story of the prodigal son.
But he said a certain man had two sons.
So these boys had sons yet.
Okay, they were this man's sons.
By the way, this man represents in type, shadow, and figure God the Father.
Represents my God, amen?
And it said a certain man had two sons.
The younger of them said to the father, father give me the portion of my goods that fall
to me and he divided unto them his living.
Now he made a demand, he said now listen daddy, I'll tell you what, I want my inheritance
and I want it now.
And he was very impudent and arrogant about this and his demand, I believe that.
This was a young man that was self-centered, he was living for himself, he didn't care
about anything or anybody else but him.
And he said I want my inheritance and I want it now.
And the father didn't resist that and he didn't say no, listen son, you cannot have your inheritance
until I'm dead.
And when I'm dead and gone then you can go and make your claim on your inheritance as
can your brother.
But in the meantime, you're not due or owed anything.
So you're not going to get it.
So now we've got this young man who's imposing his will upon his father's will.
Think about that.
Have you ever done that?
Have you ever dictated to God the terms of your life?
Sometimes in prayer we tell God what we think He ought to do.
Now God I tell you what I think you ought to do, you may not pray that way exactly but
sometimes we do that.
We don't pray thy will be done, we pray my will be done.
And so we make demands on God.
I've actually heard people pray that way.
And we have no right to make demands on Him and we have no right to tell Him what to do.
We have no right to impose our will on God's will.
And yet sometimes people do that.
And so now here we see this boy imposing his will upon the will of his father.
It's not his father's will to give him this money, not at this point in his life.
For number one, he realized this boy couldn't handle that money and number two, he knew
that he would take it and use it for all the wrong reasons because he knew the character
of his son.
Think about that.
Does God not know the character of every one of us here in this room tonight?
God knows my character, He knows your character.
He knows what we can handle, when we can handle it.
And I can just see the picture, the scenario here.
He said, all right.
He said, that's what this boy wants.
I'm going to go ahead and let him have it.
Sometimes God will give us what we want, what we demand and teach us through the process
of how badly it turns out, how stupid we really are.
Excuse the word stupid, but it's a good Greek word, stupido, amen?
I mean, it's really stupid.
And really he's imposing his will on his father's will.
It's not his father's will to give him this money and just let him go out and do whatever
he wants with it.
God doesn't just want me to go out and do whatever I want.
I belong to him.
I'm his child.
I'm his son.
I'll tell you what, God has sometimes just let me get myself my own messes because he
knew that was the only way he was going to learn.
Stupido.
Boy, I want to tell you, I got myself into some really big messes in my life.
If tonight I were to stand up here and give you testimony of some of the really dumb things
I've done in my Christian life, you'd probably laugh at it, but to me it wasn't very funny
at the time because God took me to task.
He said, all right, he said, if that's what you want and you're going to make that demand,
I'll go ahead and I'll meet that demand and then you come back and tell me how that worked
out.
Is everybody on board with me here?
Amen.
Come on now, somebody give me a testimony here.
I'm telling you, it's the exact way it is.
And so he said, now, okay, he said, I'll tell you what, son, I'll go ahead and give you
what you want.
So it says, he said, a certain man had two sons, the younger of them said, father, father,
give me the portion of goods that fall to me.
And he divided unto them his living.
So it wasn't this boy's money, it was the father's money, and he divided unto him his
living.
This boy didn't earn a penny of it, not a cent.
And not many days after, the younger son gathered all together and took his journey into a far
country and there wasted his substance with riotous living.
Now notice what he did.
He took his father's inheritance, his father's wealth, he gathered it all together, packed
his bags, and took a journey into a far country.
In other words, he was getting as far away from his father as he possibly could.
He didn't want to be under his father's authority anymore, and I don't know how old this boy
was when this whole scenario unfolds, but he took his father's inheritance, that inheritance
which his father gave to him, and he went into a far country and got as far away from
his daddy as he possibly could.
But I tell you this, I don't think he went off into a godly place.
That far country he chose was a heathen place, I guarantee it, because we'll see in a minute
what went on there.
He went into a pagan country, took his father's wealth.
went into a pagan country, and by the way, let me say this, he knew better.
He knew better.
He knew that what he was doing was wrong.
He knew that from the very get-go.
I know he knew that, so he took this money, his wealth, and he wasted it.
He wasted it.
He wasted his substance with riotous living.
Now you ought to do a word study on the word riotous.
It is not good.
I mean, it was wine, women, and song, and it was honky-tonk all the time, and he probably
got himself into some really bad business with the wrong kind of people, and he got
himself into a situation that he probably wished, after he got into it, probably wished
he'd get out of it, but he was probably enjoying it because the flesh likes sin.
I want to tell you something tonight, friend.
You're running from God, and you're giving everything you possibly can to your flesh.
You can't sit here and tell me that your flesh don't like sin.
Your flesh likes sin.
By the way, many times the flesh is the biggest enemy you have.
We blame everything on the devil, and sometimes he has nothing to do with it.
You know, we say, well, the devil made me do it.
There used to be a comedian by the name of Chip Wilson.
He used to do a skit.
He'd always say, well, the devil made me do it.
Well, you know what?
The truth of the matter is, a lot of times the devil didn't make you do anything, and
by the way, the devil can't make you do anything you don't want to do.
Did you hear me?
You have to cooperate with Satan.
So the devil gives you satanic suggestion, listen, if you don't say no to him, he'll
keep working until you give in, because your flesh loves sin.
That's why you can never give in to the flesh.
The Bible says the flesh profiteth nothing, and it doesn't.
So verse 14, look at this, and when he spent all, so I mean, he went on a binge, man.
I mean, he spent all this money, every single bit of whatever he had, he spent it, and when
he spent all, there arose a mighty famine in the land, and it began to be in want.
Well, I guess so.
I guess so.
By the way, someone said to me, well, you know, he went out full, and he came back empty.
No, he went out empty.
And he came back empty.
Yeah, he had money, he had material things, but he went out empty.
Emptier than when he went out.
It began to be in want, verse 15.
And he went and he joined himself to a citizen of that country.
And he sent him into his fields to feed swine.
Now, you stop and contemplate that for a minute, and think about that for a minute, and say,
no, wait a minute.
You mean to tell me this Jewish boy was feeding pigs?
Yeah, he was feeding pigs.
So this man in this far country, because he had nothing, he was empty, he had nothing
to eat even, he said, okay, I'll give you a job, you can go out here in the field and
feed my pigs.
And he lowered himself that much that he was willing to go and feed pigs and get into the
pigsty.
I'm going to tell you what, your sin will take you farther than you want to go.
The Bible says the way of the transgressor is hard.
And so here this poor boy is, and he's done wrong, and he's wasted his substance on riotous
living, he's run from God, he's run from home, he's run from everything he knows is
right and good, and now he ends up in a pigsty.
That's really a picture of sin, friends.
Sin is nothing more than a figurative pigsty.
That may be a real pigsty.
And I can hear him saying this now.
I can hear him saying, how did I end up here?
How did I end up here?
Well, God didn't put him there.
He was there by his own choice and his own volition.
He was there because he decided to run from God.
Now he's in a pigsty.
You know, I'll tell you, life can be a pigsty.
There have been a lot of places I've been in my lifetime where I can say, man, I'll
tell you what, this ain't even fit for pigs.
There's a lot of places in this world not fit for pigs.
And there he is in a pigsty.
Well, he's sitting in the middle of that pigsty, I begin to think about this, and what
am I going to do?
Well, how am I going to get out of this?
I mean, this is a terrible situation, and this is a real mess is what it is.
And verse 16, and he would fain have filled his belly with a husk that the swine did eat,
and no man gave unto him.
Nobody even gave him the pig food.
But look at verse 17.
Everybody with me?
And when he came to himself, that's a good place to come to.
And when he came to himself, someone said to me, in fact, it was Dr. David Earnhardt,
I'll never forget this.
He said, you read that verse there, preacher said, doesn't that tell you that really sin
is a form of insanity?
I don't know about that.
I never thought about that.
I didn't look at it as a form of insanity.
I have always thought of sin as a matter of rebellious self-will and just disobeying God
and disobeying His Word.
But when you come down to it, you think this guy was completely beside himself with sin.
And he came to himself, and that was a good thing to come to.
Now watch.
And he came to himself and he said, how many hired servants of my father's have bread enough
and spare, and I perish with hunger?
Oh, we go back to that old Greek word again, stupido.
Now, it's maybe Hispanic.
Am I right?
Is it Spanish?
Whatever it is, he's just dumb.
Amen?
He just stopped and thought about that and said, man, I'm just dumb, man.
He said, look where I've ended up.
Now verse 18, here's the blessing.
I will rise and go to my father.
I rejoice when I read this.
Now, I know you can apply this past the scripture all the way.
Some people say, well, it's a picture of an unsaved individual, and others say, no, it's
a picture of a young man out of fellowship with God and backslidden.
It's a child of God.
He says he has sonship and he's got a father.
I tend to see a real revival message in this, I really do.
And he said, listen, he said, I will rise and go to my father.
He always knew he could go home.
He always knew that he could go home.
He always knew that that which he'd run from, he could go back home.
He could go back to his father.
Why?
Because he knew the character and nature of his father, that his father is a God of mercy.
Amen.
Now, you got that right, class.
God is a God of mercy and he's a God of forgiveness.
And he said, well, he said, I've spent all my money, I've wasted all my substance from
my life.
He said, I'm living here out in a pig pen and nobody will feed me, but I can go home.
You know, as that light went on.
See now, his running is over.
It come to an end.
He was done running.
Now he's going to run, but he's going to run in the right direction.
He's running from sin and running to God.
Running from sin and running to God.
That is by the way, the essence of revival.
There's no difference.
There's no difference to me personally.
There's no difference when, when you and I got saved by the grace of God, we ran from
sin and self and we ran to God for his mercy and we got saved.
Am I right?
All right.
Now listen, it's the same thing in revival.
We run from sin and we run from self and our rebellion and our disobedience and our coldness
and our lethargy and apathy, spiritual lethargy and apathy, and we run to God and we get revival.
We do what the Bible says we need in order to experience renewal.
And what a wonderful thing it is.
And God's always willing and ready to extend mercy.
I sure am glad I serve a God with a tender heart.
God of mercies.
There's too much of this preaching today about this God in heaven that wants to beat everybody
up all the time and he's just going to take a baseball bat and whoop up on you and if
you don't do exactly right, he's just going to drop you dead in your tracks and all this
business.
I've heard people say, well, if you don't get this right, God is going to kill you.
Well, listen, God can take our lives from us if we disobey him.
There's a sin on the death.
We know that's true.
But because God is a merciful God, he's not the kind of God that many times we see some
fundamentalists say he is.
Now, I'm a fundamentalist, but I'm just telling you, some fundamentalists are fighting fundamentalists
and they have a picture of God that's not the picture of my God, because my God's a
God of mercy.
Yes, he's a God of judgment, he's a God of wrath, but he does not delight in wrath.
He delighteth in mercy.
That's the kind of God I serve.
That's my King.
That's my Jesus.
Amen?
And I know that he loves me and I know he cares about me.
And it's just like with my daughter when she was growing up.
Now she's like, I can hardly believe my kid's 56 years old almost.
And when I look at her when she's growing up, we loved our child.
She was our only child.
We loved her and she was precious to us.
But we didn't let her get away with sin.
We didn't let her get away with wrongdoing.
We were very patriotic in our home.
We applied the stripes and she saw the stars, amen?
She knew she was disobedient, she had it coming.
But along with the punishment or correction came mercy.
And by the way, biblical correction in a child's life is not child abuse, it's child correction.
There's a right way of doing it and a wrong way to do it.
And so my God takes delight in when I do wrong, when he has to deal with me, he takes delight
in doing it in such a way whereby he gives me an opportunity to respond before he has
to step things up because he's merciful.
He's merciful, amen?
And I think about that and I think, well, praise the Lord how good God really is to
us because he is indeed a wonderful God of mercy.
So you knew you could go home.
So verse 18, I've got to keep moving.
I'm almost...
done, I will rise and go to my Father, and I will say unto him, Father, I have sinned
against heaven and before thee, before thee. Now that's repentance. That's the beginning
of repentance right there. That's an admission of sin. That's the acknowledgement of sin.
The first step in revival and the first step in getting right with God is to acknowledge
my sin. David said, I acknowledge my sin, it's ever before me in Psalm 51. So that's
the acknowledgement of sin. That's where repentance starts. Verse 19, I'm no more worthy to be
called thy son. Make me as one of the hired servants. That's humility. That's humility.
Verse 20, and he rose and came to his father, but when he was a great way off, his father
saw him and in compassion ran and fell on his neck and kissed him. Now that's interesting
because here this boy, and by the way, he may have been a little hesitant on his way
home, but here this boy is coming down the path and his father is waiting for him at
the gate. He probably every single day looked down that pathway coming to the house and
he was praying and said, oh God, speak to my boy and cause my boy to see how wrong he
is and how wicked he has been and how sinful he is and God bring him home that I can restore
him once again to his rightful place. And here comes that boy up the lane. The boy didn't
run to his daddy, his daddy ran to him and threw his arms around his neck and kissed
him and showed him love and mercy. That's my God right there. That's my Jesus right
there. That's my king. That's who I serve. That's the kind of God I serve. Amen? So get
that picture in your mind what a precious picture it is. Now watch as we go on. We're
almost done. And it said here in verse 21, and the son said to him, father, I've sinned
against heaven and on thy side and am no more worthy to be called thy son. Now that's prayer
there too. That's reference to prayer. And by the way, brokenness comes in here. But
the father said to his servants, bring forth the best robe and put it on him and put a
ring on his feet and bring on his hand and shoes on his feet. That's restoration. So
here we see repentance, humility, prayer, brokenness and restoration. All one section
here. Verse 23, and bring hither the fatted calf and kill it and let us eat and be merry.
For this my son was dead. Just like he was dead, it was like he was dead and gone. Now
look at this, and is alive again. Do you know what? That is exactly what revival means.
The word revival means to live again. That's what it means. He's alive again. And what
a wonderful statement that scripture is. He was lost and he's found and they began to
be merry. Now you look at the rest of it and you can look at the second son. He was also
prodigal but from a different direction. He was just a pompous, self-righteous individual
what he was. But here's the thing I want you to see. We can always go home. God is
always willing and ready to extend mercy to us and yet we don't deserve it but he's a
God of mercy. And when you and I run from God and we run hard, in fact I ought to preach
on Jonah this week. I've had Jonah in my heart here for I don't know how long. I ought to
preach on Jonah this week if God lets me do it. The thing is that we run sometimes from
God and we try to run hard and fast as far away from him as we can get but he's always
still there. He hasn't gone anywhere. God's always where he's always been, where he always
will be. Who's doing the running? Well we're doing the running. When I was pastoring, pastor,
I don't know how many people I've had sit across my desk and they'd come to me for counsel
and they'd say, man this has happened and that's happened, this is going on and that's
going on. And 99% of the time I could sit there and say, well you know what your problem
is? You're running from God. Stop running. Quit your running. You know and they'd look
at you like, well how do you know I'm running? Yeah, you're running. That's what you're doing
because you know what I can tell because I'm your pastor and I've been watching you live
your life and I've been watching what you've been doing and I've seen the things you've
done and I know what you're doing. One thing you're doing is you're skipping out of church
and you're not faithful to the house of God like you used to be and you're putting other
things, you have other priorities in life instead of the Lord and I can see that your
family's in trouble and I see your kids, your kids are falling apart and how can you
sit here and tell me you're not running from God? People are running from the Lord. We
live, hey listen friends, we live in a nation running from God. And we've seen influence
of that here in God's house too. But we always know this, we always know we can go home.
We can always come back. God said come back. You know in Malachi chapter 3 God says this,
He said if you will I will. The you will I will principle, God said if you will I
will. He said if you'll come back I'm ready to restore you. You first. You're the ones
going to have to come home to me. But it's a simple message but you get it so profound.
God is a merciful God. He delighteth in mercy. Now some of you are not, I don't know tonight
what's going on in your life, I have no idea. This is a revival meeting, so we're talking
about revival here. It's not an evangelistic meeting, it's a revival meeting. Revival is
for God's people. Evangelism is for the people that need to be regenerated. We're not talking
about regeneration this week, we're talking about revival. Now we will bring the gospel
out certainly. We want people to be saved that are not saved that are here. But my ministry
is mostly revival where it's revival ministry and God's people need to be revived. So you
may be here tonight and there may be things going on in your heart. You know that there's
something not right there. You know there's some sin in your life. There's something you're
covering up perhaps. I don't know. God knows. You know. Unless you've so deceived yourself
you don't see it. And that's possible. But maybe there's someone here tonight who's got
secret sin in your life. You're just running and hiding from God and you're just wasting
your life. You're not experiencing the joy of the Lord. You're not experiencing the fruit
of the Spirit. You're not enjoying the things that God has for His children. Man, quit your
running. Stop running. Come to yourself. And come back to God. God says come back.
Come back. I never forget, as long as I live, I stood in the pulpit one night in the church
years back. There was a story that I heard years ago that Ron Comfort related. I'll never
forget it, but I applied it a little differently. And I could see God just standing over the
battlements of heaven, the parapets of heaven, and saying, come back. Come back. Come back.
Come back. He wants His church back. He wants His people back. He wants every child of God
that's running, He wants them back. If you're a prodigal, come back. Come back. Come back.
You need to examine your own heart tonight. Oh yes, we can look at the prodigal and say,
yeah, there's a lot of people running from God that need to be saved. And you can get
that certainly out of this passage of Scripture as well. There's no question about that. I
tend to agree with J. Vernon McGee, and I'm not always in agreement with what he taught
years ago, but I will tell you this. See, I think he's right about this text right here.
You're dealing with a boy that had sonship. And he said, you come back, and I'll tell
you what, I'll restore you. I'll put the ring on your finger, and I'll put the robe upon
you, and we'll have a fatted calf, and we'll have a good hallelujah time, amen, because
this son of mine that was running from me is back. He's been revived. Amen. What a wonderful
thing it is to experience a Holy Ghost revival. When the Spirit of God falls fresh upon us,
when I'll tell you what, you can't explain it on the earthly plane. When the Spirit of God
falls fresh upon us, man, it's a hallelujah time. It's a joy. It just reverberates through a church.
Many times it starts with one person. I've seen a church send its teenagers off to youth camp,
and some of those kids get a good old-fashioned dose of Holy Ghost revival, and they come back
to church. It spreads through the church like wildfire, because the parents get under conviction.
Now their kids are living for the Lord. And if parents aren't, and the parents get under
conviction, get right with God. You can build a whole revival meeting on what happens sometimes
in teen camps. They have to really wonder what's wrong with the adults, you know. Amen. Amen. I've
delivered God's message. Let's all stand tonight. Would you stand with me, please?
Get our heads about nice and close tonight as our sister comes to play the instrument. We're
going to just have a simple time of invitation of God's spoken in your heart tonight. Now,
listen, let me say this. If you're not saved, you ought to come tonight. If you don't know
that you're saved, you don't know you're saved, it's a no-so thing. You ought to come tonight,
and let us take the Word of God and show you from the Bible how to know Jesus as your personal
Savior. For Christian night, this message was for us, really. It's a revival message, and God says,
come back. He said, I'm a merciful God. You can always come home. You can always come back. When
we come to ourselves, we can always come back. As the instrument begins to play and God speaks
to your heart tonight, the altar's open, you just step out and come. Just bow on your knee here and
say, oh, God, my heart's been spoken to tonight, and I want to make some things right with you.
Just step out as the instrument begins to play. How about you, my friend?