Last week, we looked at this same portion of Scripture.
This is part two.
And if you were here last week,
and if you weren't here last week, it's online,
and you'll get part one before you get part two,
and go and listen to it.
But last week, we noted how that the psalmist
expressed his love for the word of God.
And we looked through Psalm 119,
and we noted several reasons that led to the psalmist
declaring his love for the Bible.
I believe this morning that each and every one of us,
every child of God, ought to echo the words of the psalmist,
that we too would stand as the psalmist does in Psalm 119,
in verse number 97, and say,
O how love I thy law!
God's word is precious, and we ought to love it.
We ought to thank God for it.
And the reality is that as we've studied for several weeks now
the truth regarding the Bible,
and how God gave us the Bible,
our theme is great is the Lord,
and we discover God's greatness in a number of ways,
but we said that inspiration reveals the greatness of God.
We said that preservation reveals the greatness of God.
And when we understand the truth of inspiration and preservation,
we understand that we have a more sure word,
and we ought to stand and say, I love God's word.
And we find this morning that as we look at this portion of Scripture,
and we think about this declaration of the psalmist,
I wonder this morning, as we would think about the psalmist,
and I gave preview to this last week,
but I wonder this morning if there would be sufficient evidence
to support the claim.
See, the reality is that the psalmist stands up and says,
O how love I thy law!
And each of us this morning could echo their words, those words,
but I wonder this morning if there would be sufficient evidence
to support the claim.
I believe that as we look at the portion of Scripture in Psalm 119,
and we'll look at a number of verses this morning,
I find and I believe this morning that you will find and you will discover
an overwhelming amount of evidence
that would support the claim of the psalmist.
See, we can say anything.
We can claim anything.
But there ought to be evidence that would support our claim.
I want you to notice, we've looked at verse 97,
but notice that verse 159,
and we'll use this verse as a springboard into the message this morning,
as we look at a number of verses from Psalm 119,
but I want you to notice what the Bible says,
what the psalmist declares in Psalm 119 in verse 97.
He says, O how love I thy law!
It is my meditation all the day.
But notice in verse 159.
Notice what the psalmist says.
He says, Consider how I love thy precepts.
Quicken me, O Lord, according to thy lovingkindness.
Notice the first phrase.
He says, Consider how I love thy precepts.
You'll understand as you study through the 119th Psalm
that there are many words that the psalmist uses
to define the same book, the Bible, the word of God,
the portion of Scripture that they had.
Of course, they did not have the complete canon of Scripture.
He refers to it as thy word, thy precepts, thy testimonies,
thy statutes, and so on and so forth.
And you find here that the psalmist says,
Consider how I love thy precepts.
Now, he's declared his love in verse 97.
In fact, we looked at a number of verses last week
in which he declares his love for the law of the Lord.
But now in verse 159, the psalmist says,
Consider how I love thy precepts.
That word consider is interesting,
and that word consider means this.
It means to see, to look at, to inspect, to perceive.
So I want you to think about Psalm 119 and verse 159
when the psalmist says, Consider how I love thy precepts.
He's really saying this, inspect, look at, examine,
see my life, and consider my behavior
and how my behavior supports my claim.
Consider how I love thy precepts.
I will note as we study Psalm 119 this morning,
10 evidences from this portion of Scripture
that I believe provide us with the evidence necessary
to support the claim of the psalmist.
And then I will challenge each of us this morning
to examine our own lives.
As we'd come in here and say,
I love the Bible, I love God's word.
I hope you would say that this morning.
I hope every single person would say,
I love God's word, I love the Lord, and I love his word.
But is there evidence in my life,
is there evidence in your life that would support that claim?
Notice with me, number one, if you're taking notes,
again, there's 10 of them.
I was thinking about this this morning.
If I was praying this morning, I said,
Man, if I just spend a couple of minutes on each appointment,
we're past our time.
And so I'm gonna try to get through it quickly this morning.
I do hope that it'll be a blessing to you.
And notice with me, number one, this morning,
the psalmist has a desire to learn the word.
Listen, if you love God's word,
you ought to have a desire to learn God's word.
And we find here that the psalmist,
look in verse number seven,
and again, we'll just kind of march through Psalm 119,
and we'll look at a number of verses of Scripture.
But notice what the Bible says.
I will praise thee with uprightness of heart
when I shall have learned thy righteous judgments.
Verse 12 says, Blessed art thou, O Lord.
Notice where he says a very simple prayer.
Teach me thy statutes.
Why does the psalmist over and over throughout the Psalm,
in fact, if you look at verse 26, he says,
I have declared my ways and thou heardest me.
Teach me thy statutes.
And you'll find repeated on a number of occasions
in Psalm 119 where the psalmist says,
teach me thy statutes, teach me thy law, teach me thy word.
Why does the psalmist desire to learn?
Well, because he loves the word of God.
He loves the Bible.
And if we love the Bible,
we ought to have a desire to learn what it says.
Amen.
And we desire to learn.
And we find that the psalmist has expressed to us
in this Psalm, this desire to learn.
And we find that in the New Testament,
the Bible says that we desire the sincere milk of the word,
that we may grow thereby.
It says this in 1 Peter 2, in verse number two,
as newborn babes desire the sincere milk of the word
that ye may grow thereby.
And the reality this morning is that we don't just desire
that milk of the word as newborn babes,
but as we develop that appetite for God's word,
we come to the place where we say, I desire to learn.
I want to learn God's word.
You know, every day of your life, every day of my life,
God will teach us his statutes.
He will teach us his word.
And we need to have that teachable spirit.
In fact, I believe this morning that if we love God's word,
that we will have a desire to learn the word of God.
Notice with me, number two, not only a desire to learn,
but number two, a commitment to obey.
A commitment to obey the word of God.
Listen, it's important to learn,
but learning without obedience is really not of any use.
We find that the Bible teaches us that we are to be doers
of the word and not hearers only.
The idea of learning the Bible and learning the word of God
is not so that we can win some Bible trivia game.
It's not so that we can just have a bunch of knowledge
and be puffed up.
No, the idea of learning the Bible,
learning the word of God, is to obey it.
And so we find that the psalmist has a desire
to learn the word of God,
but he also has a commitment to obey the word of God.
Notice with me in verse number eight of Psalm 119,
the Bible says this,
I will keep thy statutes.
Oh, forsake me not utterly.
Notice in verse number 33 what the psalmist says,
teach me, O Lord, the way of thy statutes,
and I shall keep it unto the end.
We see in verse number 33,
both of these first two points that we've looked at
this morning where he says teach me,
but then he says I shall keep it.
And this commitment to obey the word of God.
What I've mentioned about Samuel in the past
when he says speak, Lord, for thy servant heareth.
The idea of that word here, it carries with it
if you were to study that word out,
it means to hear with the intent of obeying.
It means to give heed with the purpose of obeying
the message that we receive.
See, as we come to a place of gathering,
as we have the opportunity four times a week
to gather together as the people of God
and to learn the word of God
and have a commitment to obey the word of God.
By the way, we find that a church is responsible,
a church is a body of believers called out assembly
and we find that the pastor has been given
the responsibility to preach the word.
If the word is not being taught, not a place I'd go.
Amen?
Honestly, the Bible is to be taught.
It doesn't matter what my opinions are,
it doesn't matter all of those things,
but we need to be lifting up and exalting
the Lord Jesus Christ and teaching this book
and we find that as we come,
why do we pray before the services?
We're praying, God, would you teach me?
Would you work in my life?
I come with this attitude of expectancy,
desiring to hear from God.
I often say this, that we need to be ready to receive,
but also ready to respond.
Lord, how would you speak to me through your Word today?
Maybe God spoke to you through a song already this morning.
And God just uses the songs that are based on scriptural truth, and He uses His Word
in our hearts and our lives, and we have that commitment to obey the Word of God.
Number three this morning, the psalmist has a plan to memorize the Word of God.
He has a plan to memorize the Word of God.
Why would I memorize it?
Well, because I love it.
And if I love the Bible, if I love God's Word, then I memorize God's Word, and memorizing
is evidence that I do love it.
Notice what he says in verse number 11, a verse that's very familiar to many of us.
Thy word have I hid in mine heart, that I might not sin against thee.
He's purposed.
He has a plan to memorize God's Word.
I know that oftentimes when we think about memorization, we think about the children,
we think about Sunday school, and we think about Awan and other children's ministries,
and the importance of hiding God's Word in their hearts and lives.
But I want you to understand that as the psalmist gives us this truth here, we find that because
he loves the Bible, because he loves the Word of God, he says, I'm going to hide His Word
in my heart.
Every child of God ought to be memorizing God's Word.
You say, well, I just don't have that great of a memory.
Ask God to help you.
I mean, listen, if you only memorize a verse a year, praise God for a verse that you memorized.
Amen?
I know sometimes we set goals, we say, man, I'm going to memorize a verse a week.
I'm going to memorize 52 verses this week, and we get into about week number eight or
ten of the year, and we can't remember any of the first seven, eight verses that we've
memorized, and we're just kind of a mess.
Listen, make goals that are achievable.
God, by your grace and with your help, I'll memorize a verse a year, a verse a month,
a verse a quarter, whatever it might be, but God, would you help me memorize your Word?
Why?
Because I love it.
I want you to think about what he says.
He says, I have, notice what he says, thy Word have I hid in mine heart, that I might
not sin against thee.
I think it's interesting he used that word that he's hid the Word.
He knows where it is.
It's in his heart.
He's purposed.
He's got this plan to memorize the Word of God.
Our children are memorizing verses.
I know that in Holly's class on Wednesday evening, they're working on memorization.
I know that the children's church that's even downstairs now, how often they come up and
they'll sing for us and they'll rehearse, recite verses of Scripture.
Man, that's wonderful.
But this morning, I wonder, am I memorizing God's Word?
Are you memorizing God's Word?
If I love it, I want to memorize it.
Why?
Because I want to be able to recall it.
When I've memorized God's Word, then I can recall it.
Maybe in that moment of temptation as we find in the wilderness with the Lord Jesus Christ,
when that temptation comes, he's able to say, it is written.
That's a good read.
Look, he says that I might not sin against thee.
God provides that way of escape.
Oh, a plan to memorize.
He memorizes because he loves.
Notice with me number four, a plan not only to memorize, but a plan to meditate on the
Word.
A plan to meditate on the Word of God.
Notice in verse 15, I will meditate in thy precepts and have respect unto thy ways.
He says in verse 23, princes also did sit and speak against me, but thy servant did
meditate in thy statutes.
Of course, we're familiar with verse 97.
We've used that last week as our main verse of getting into this portion of scripture.
Oh, how love I thy law.
It is my meditation all the day.
And the psalmist says this in Psalm 119 verse 148, mine eyes prevent the night watches that
I might meditate in thy Word.
This thing of meditation is important.
We find often throughout the Psalms where you'll read this word selah, and you think
about that word selah, and oftentimes in our society today, many of us don't have time
for selah because we're in a hurry, and we're trying to get through things and trying to
get on to the next thing, and we got more things to do today than we could ever actually
accomplish today, and we're so task-oriented, we have so many things going on.
But the psalmist says, thy Word is my meditation.
He's got a plan to meditate on the Word of God.
That's why I believe it's important that we begin our day with reading the Bible.
And I understand that some people say, I'm just not a morning person, I don't get anything
out of it if I read it in the morning, and so I read it in the evening, and I say, good,
it's good that you read God's Word.
But we find this morning it's amazing to me that as we read the Word of God in the morning,
how it can be our meditation throughout the day, how we can take that time.
See, God says, be still and know that I am God.
We have a hard time being still, we have a hard time meditating on the Word of God.
See, today we live in a time in which things are so fast-paced, but then we also have the
other aspect where people are teaching and promoting this idea that meditation is getting
into some quiet place somewhere where you remove every thought from your mind and you're
just kind of in this moment of, mm, just nothing.
That's not real meditation.
And the psalmist says, what I'm going to meditate on is Your Word, it is my meditation.
You know, we're really good, you think about this idea of meditation and the word Selah,
just chewing on it, having it go over and just permeate our mind and just saturate our
minds.
And it's a wonderful thing to be thinking upon the truth of God's Word.
You know, somebody can offend us, somebody can hurt us, somebody can do us wrong and
all of a sudden that thing, that action, that comment just kind of replays in our head over
and over and over and over and over and over and we just begin to think about what that
person did and how they said and I can't believe and so on and so forth.
And it's just, oh, that's how we should have God's Word in our mind, just constantly replaying
in our heart and our mind, meditating on God's Word.
Notice with me number five, I find this evidence to support the claim of the psalmist that
he says, oh, how love I thy law.
I would say number five, the psalmist has the discipline to search the Word, to study.
Notice with me in verse number 94, notice what the Bible says.
He says, I am thine, save me for I have sought thy precepts.
The word sought there means to seek, but it doesn't just mean to seek, it means to seek
with care.
You ever look for something?
I mean, you're seeking for something.
You misplaced it.
Has that ever happened to anyone?
Come on.
And you're seeking for it, right?
And you're seeking with care, right?
You're diligent and you want to find that thing.
Well, here the Bible says that the psalmist says, I have sought thy precepts.
The idea of searching the scriptures, the idea of studying the scriptures, the Bible
says, study to show thyself approved unto God, a workman that needeth not to be ashamed,
rightly dividing the word of truth.
The Bible says, as Jesus is dealing with some people during his earthly ministry, he said,
search the scriptures, for in them you think that you have eternal life, but they are they
which testify of me, in John chapter number five.
And the reality is that God's Word does testify of the Lord Jesus Christ.
Jesus started with those disciples on the road to Emmaus and Luke.
He started where?
With Moses and the prophets, and he expounded all things from the scriptures concerning
himself.
We find this morning that the psalmist, he says, I have sought thy precepts.
What makes the psalmist, what is it that motivates the psalmist?
What is the driving factor in the life of the psalmist that makes him search to seek
with care God's Word?
Well, he loves it.
He loves it.
And it's God's Word that reveals who God is.
You say, I'm so thankful that God is gracious.
How do you know that God is gracious?
Well, because he told us that he's gracious.
But I wonder this morning, if each of us had the responsibility, we were given a sheet
of paper, say, with a list of maybe 25 different attributes of God, I mean, attributes that
I think each and every one of us would agree to, attributes that each of us would be familiar
with, and we'd say, is God gracious?
Yes or no?
Yes.
Give me a verse that proves it.
How many of us could put a verse down?
Is God merciful?
Yes or no?
Yes.
Give me a verse.
Did God ever sin?
Yes or no?
No.
Give me a verse.
I'm not saying give me a verse like I'm the teacher, but I'm saying that's how we're supposed
to search the Scriptures, that we know it, not just that we know about the attributes
of God, but we know them, that we can get into this book and that we can say, I know
that God is great, and I know that God is gracious, and I know that God is merciful,
and I know that God is perfect.
I know that God, fill in the blank, because I have verses of Scripture, because I have
sought.
I've sought it, I've searched it, I've studied it, because I love the Bible.
So I would say this, as I mentioned the point, the discipline to search the Word, it requires
discipline.
It requires discipline.
It's easy to just hear somebody else tell us something, but the discipline for us ourselves
to go and to search and to study the Word of God.
I would say this, number six, the Bible tells us that the psalmist makes this declaration
that the Word of God was his delight.
Why was it his delight?
Well, because he loved it.
And the evidence of his love for God's Word was that it was his delight.
You know, it's kind of interesting if somebody says, I love, fill in the blank, maybe somebody
says they love their spouse, but they never spend time with their spouse.
You say, what's going on with that?
That's kind of weird, right?
If you love your spouse, you're going to spend time with your spouse.
I love the church, and you never can find them.
You say, how much do you really love the church?
You don't come.
You understand what I'm saying?
I love pizza, but I haven't eaten it in three years.
Well, how much do you really, I mean, you understand.
But the psalmist says, I love God's Word, and therefore God's Word is my delight.
The word delight means to affect with great pleasure, to bring joy.
Listen, I hope this morning that God's Word brings joy in your life.
When you read it this morning, even as I mentioned last week, that God's Word all at the same
time will convict us and comfort us.
It's amazing, this book that we hold in our hands, that we're privileged to have.
Notice in verse number 16, notice what the psalmist says in Psalm 119 and verse 16.
The Bible says this, I will delight myself in thy statutes.
Then he says this, I will not forget thy word.
That's an interesting statement, is it not?
In fact, there are many times within the psalm, this psalm, that he says something about not
forgetting thy word, thy statutes, and that's an interesting statement.
But I believe that as he would meditate upon the truth that God had given him, it will
help him not to forget it.
But I want you to see that he says, I will delight myself in thy statutes.
He says again in verse number 24, thy testimonies also are my delight and my counselors.
What is it that brings you joy?
What is it that brings you satisfaction?
What is it that brings you pleasure?
There are some today that based upon a particular team that they follow, having success brings
them a measure of joy, brings them a measure of delight.
I remember speaking to a man years ago, and he was dealing with a problem with alcohol,
and I remember having this conversation with this individual and asking him, what is it
that caused him to drink?
And here's what he said to me.
He said the team that he followed lost, and I thought, what in the world?
I mean, it just, that's how it hit me.
But the team that he followed lost, and he turned to the bottle because he was looking
for some joy, some pleasure, some satisfaction in a victory, by the way, that doesn't even
matter in light of eternity.
This morning, the psalmist says, thy word, thy testimonies are my delight.
Not only are they my delight, they're my counselors.
And I wonder this morning, would we say that God's word brings joy in our lives?
He says in verse 47, notice, and I will delight myself in thy commandments, which I have loved,
which I have loved.
Look over at verse 174, there's a number of other ones, but we'll just kind of skip around
here.
And he says, nearing the end of this psalm, he says in verse number 174, I have longed
for thy salvation, O Lord, and thy law is my delight.
It is my delight.
What did the psalmist say in Psalm chapter number 1?
We are familiar with this psalm.
The Bible says, blessed is the man that walketh not in the counsel of the ungodly, nor standeth
in the way of sinners, nor sitteth in the seat of the scornful, but his delight is in
the law of the Lord, and in his law doth he meditate day and night.
And God's word is his delight because he loves it, and when he makes the statement that it's
his delight, when we read and we look at his behavior, we find that it being the Bible,
the Scriptures, the commandments, the testimony being his delight gives evidence that he loves
God's word.
Number seven, he longed for God's word.
He longed for God's word.
Notice in verse number 125 of this psalm, back in Psalm 119, and notice verse 125, notice
what he says, I am thy servant, give me understanding that I may know thy testimonies.
I want you to think about this idea of longing for the testimonies, and he says that I may
know.
He says give me understanding that I may know thy testimonies, and we think about this longing
for God's word.
Have you ever been in a time, in a place where maybe you had an emergency come up, there's
something that took place and your day was interrupted and you were not able to start
and follow your, maybe your routine of getting into the Bible first thing in the morning
because of some emergency that came up, and man, it's happened to me.
I've gotten phone calls before from some members that have dealt with some difficulties, some
health things or whatever it's been, and I need to go to the hospital first thing in
the morning, and it's just kind of affected my schedule.
It happens.
I'll find myself in the afternoon, I can't wait to get to my time with God.
I long to read the Bible.
I'm longing for God's word.
See, have you ever skipped a meal?
I mean physically, you've skipped a meal.
We're down there in South Carolina, and I think it was on Tuesday or Wednesday, we didn't
have any lunch.
I think it was Tuesday, and Holly looked at me and she said, I'm hungry.
She said, I just need some meat.
That's what mommy said.
No, she never says she needs meat.
In fact, there's been times we've gone out to dinner and she orders a veggie plate.
I said, what is a veggie plate?
You get to pick five veggies.
No thank you.
I pick five meats, I'm for it, amen?
But she picked five veggies, you know?
And she said, I'm hungry.
Why?
Because we skipped a meal.
She's ready for dinner.
Listen, if you skip a meal, you get a reminder.
Your body reminds you.
You skip several meals, your body reminds you.
I wonder this morning how it is if our time with God is delayed for some reason.
Our ability to read and to get into the Bible is interrupted because of something that happens
in life.
And I understand there are interruptions, there are times in which we cannot control
those circumstances.
Now, there are times in which we can.
There are times in which we can say, no, I'm not going to deal with that right now because
I am spending time with God.
But there are times that we just can't do that.
Do you understand what I'm saying?
It happens in life.
But if that happens, I wonder, do we long for it?
Are we anxious to get to our time with God and His Word?
Do we long for God?
Do we long for His Word?
I would say this, He valued God's Word, number eight.
He valued God's Word.
The Bible tells us in verse number 128, He says this, He says, Therefore, I esteem all
thy precepts concerning all things to be right, and I hate every false way.
Verse 127, excuse me.
He says, Therefore, I love thy commandments above gold, yea, above fine gold.
I used this verse of Scripture last week and I mentioned that many people today love gold.
They do.
They love gold.
Gold represents wealth.
We find that many people love, and many people will go through great lengths in order to
obtain wealth, in order to obtain some status, and we find here that the psalmist says, no,
I want you to understand that I love thy commandments above gold, yea, above fine gold, and because
I love thy commandments above gold, above fine gold, therefore, I esteem all thy precepts
concerning all things to be right, and I hate every false way.
And so we see these two verses together, and we see verse 128 where He says about esteeming
the Word of God.
I esteem all thy precepts concerning all things.
And we know that Job, he mentioned about esteeming the Word of God, and as we think about that
Word of esteem, and we dealt with this last week, and we focused upon the truth of that,
and thinking about the place that we, the emphasis and the place that we have on God's
Word.
We esteem it.
We value it.
We find here that the psalmist says because of his love for God's Word, he's going to
esteem, but notice what he says.
I love how he words this in verse number 128.
He says, I esteem.
all thy precepts concerning all things.
Now that's pretty conclusive, all-inclusive, excuse me.
I mean, he's including it all, right?
He's saying I love all thy precepts.
Not just certain ones, I'm not just picking certain ones.
You ever go to a buffet?
You go to a buffet and what do you do?
Well, there's certain things you like
and there's certain things you don't like.
And you go heavy on the things that you like
and you skip over the things that you don't like.
Right, isn't that how it works at a buffet?
You pick and choose, correct?
That's not how we approach God's Word.
We don't approach God's Word
the way that we approach a buffet.
We don't approach God's Word with saying,
well, I really like this, but nah, that's not really for me.
I've heard people say today, many times over the years,
I've heard people make the statement,
well, you know, the Old Testament
really isn't for us anymore.
You know how much you miss?
By the way, the New Testament says of the Old Testament
that it was written for our admonition.
That's what he says.
Not only for our admonition, but also for our learning.
Wow.
Groups of people that just remove it.
There's a popular preacher, Andy Stanley.
Popular man, wrong man.
You know what he said about the Old Testament?
We need to unhitch from the Old Testament.
That's what he said about the Old Testament.
And now you begin to look at some of their teaching,
there's no wonder that they unhitch
not only from the Old Testament, but from all of God's Word.
Seriously, it's a disaster.
This morning, the psalmist says,
I esteem all thy precepts.
Notice what he says, concerning all things.
Wow.
God addresses the issues of life in His Word.
He does.
God uses His Word to address the issues of life.
And the psalmist says, I esteem all thy precepts
concerning all things, notice what he says, to be right.
Now that's important that we understand that.
Why, because your opinion's not right,
my opinion's not right, our culture's not right.
Now if it's right, it's only because
it aligns with God's Word.
Because God's Word is what is right.
And the psalmist says that he esteems all thy precepts
concerning all things to be right.
You think about some of the all things.
I mean, again, that's encompassing.
Everything that we would face in life,
the Bible says this, that we're to keep our hearts
with all diligence, for out of it are the issues of life.
In Proverbs chapter number four.
And you think about all things that we'd face.
Today there are questions about all sorts of things
that say, well, what does God's Word say?
Because I esteem that all thy precepts
concerning all things to be right.
We're not gonna discard God's Word.
We're not gonna say, well, you know, times have changed
and things are different now
and we need to be more open-minded
and we need to be more inclusive
and we need to be, no, no, no, no.
We need to be biblically correct.
I know that's not popular today.
I understand that.
I do not have my head in the sand.
But we must be biblically accurate.
We must be biblically correct.
You know, it'd be a sad thing to conform to this world
and forsake God's Word and then stand before Him one day.
I don't wanna do that.
So the psalmist says that he values,
he esteems all thy precepts
concerning all things to be right.
Notice the Bible tells us, number nine,
if you're taking notes, that he stood in awe of God's Word.
It means to revere it.
In verse number 161,
it says, princes have persecuted me without a cause,
but my heart standeth in awe of thy Word.
Well, this morning, how much do we revere God's Word?
Have we come to that place where we're standing in awe
of what God has given us in His Word?
We find that the Bible tells us in Psalm 138,
in verse number two, he says,
I will worship toward thy holy temple
and praise thy name for thy loving kindness
and for thy truth, for thou hast magnified thy Word
above all thy name.
Listen, we ought to stand in awe of who God is.
We find that the psalmist declares that in Psalm 34.
The Bible teaches us, excuse me, Psalm 33,
in verse number eight, let all the earth fear the Lord.
Let all the inhabitants of the world stand in awe of Him.
We ought to stand in awe of God,
but we ought to stand in awe of His Word to revere it.
We find number 10, that the psalmist,
what evidence do we have to support the claim?
Oh, how love I thy law.
Really?
Really, you love the law of the Lord?
You love God's Word?
He says, yes, I love it, and consider how I love it.
We find number 10, that he purposed to speak God's Word.
He purposed to speak God's Word.
Notice in verse 172 of Psalm 119,
the Bible says this in verse 172,
my tongue shall speak of thy Word
for all thy commandments are righteousness.
My tongue shall speak of thy Word.
See, he loved God's Word, and he meditated upon God's Word,
and all of these other things that we've looked at,
and it leads to him saying,
I'm purposed to speak of God's Word.
Look over at Psalm 37.
We studied this for those that are
in our Wednesday evening prayer and Bible study here
that are not in some other class.
We studied this, but if you're in another class,
I wanna draw your attention to this
and remind those that were here for that message,
this truth in Psalm 37.
Notice what the Bible says in verse 30
and also in verse number 31.
Again, the psalmist is saying
that he's purposed to speak the Word.
It says in verse number 30 of Psalm 37,
the mouth of the righteous speaketh wisdom,
and his tongue talketh of judgment.
Why does he speak the way that he does?
Well, the answer is found in verse 31,
the law of his God is in his heart.
The law of his God is in his heart.
So no wonder his mouth is going to speak of wisdom
and his tongue is going to talk of judgment
because God's Word, his law is in his heart.
And it's in his heart because he loves it.
Remember the point that we looked at
that he had a plan to memorize God's Word.
He said, oh, how love I thy law,
but we find that as we study through Psalm 119,
we see all of these evidences that are provided to us,
scattered through this psalm,
that help us to see how the psalmist,
there's overwhelming evidence to support the claim
that he loves God's Word.
And this morning, I wonder in my life,
I wonder in your life,
I wonder if we were to take the time this morning
to just evaluate our own lives
and looking over just the last week or the last month
or maybe just this calendar year,
these two and a half months that we've had in 2023
and say, is there evidence in my life
that would support the claim that I love God's Word,
that I love God's Word?
See, the evidence is overwhelming
in support for what the psalmist declared,
the expression of his love,
but the evidence of his love.
I'm gonna read to you an account of an individual,
his name is William McPherson,
and some of you may have heard of this individual
at some point,
but this man was a superintendent of a stone quarry,
and as he was working there
and he was successful in his work and what have you,
he's working, obviously working in a stone quarry,
there's some danger that's there,
and he had, unfortunately, there was a blast
that took place at this stone quarry,
and he was in the wrong place,
and he was severely injured.
Through this blast and through this injury,
this man lost his eyesight
and both of his hands in the explosion.
I want you to think about being in that position.
No eyesight, no hands.
I'm thankful that for folks that are blind,
there's Braille.
In fact, you can get Braille Bibles.
They have those.
And someone that's blind can still have the opportunity
to, with a Braille Bible, read the Bible.
In fact, some of you might know the name of Don Forrester.
He was a pastor down in Fredericksburg
at Faith Baptist Church for a number of years.
And I remember the first time
ever heard him preach was on a CD and I had no idea that he was blind. I'd never met the
man before and somebody as soon as I got to Virginia gave me a CD of his because I was
taking a trip to the Grand Canyon and said, hey, Brother Forster preached about his trip
to the Grand Canyon, why don't you listen to this on the way? And I did and I had no
idea that he was blind. And I'm hearing him talk about all these things and then I find
out that he's blind and it was very interesting as somebody would have to detail things to
him and explain things and so on and so forth. But then I heard him preach in person. Phenomenal.
Has anyone ever, you've ever been in a setting where Don Forster preached? My dad, anyone
else? He stands up there, he's completely blind and he has, and he just, he uses his
hand right here and I mean, it's phenomenal. But this man lost both of his hands. No eyesight,
no hands. But this man, William McPherson, was determined to read the Bible. He was determined
to read the Bible. So here's what he did. He learned how to read raised letters with
the tip of his tongue. He learned how to read raised letters with the tip of his tongue.
It is said that William McPherson read through the Bible four times with the tip of his tongue.
That's phenomenal. That's phenomenal. But that's the testimony of somebody that said,
I love God's Word. And though I've lost my eyesight and though I've lost my hands, I
want to read God's Word. Unfortunately, surveys have been taken for years now. Surveys, I'm
not sure who they survey, but surveys have been taken for years of people that claim
to be Christians. And again, I say claim to be because I don't know who they're surveying.
They ask the question how often they read their Bibles. They ask the question of how
many have read their Bible through once, not just in a year, but in their lifetime. And
consistently those statistics are sad as to how few ever read the Bible from Genesis
to Revelation. I'm not talking about, and again, I don't know the people, so I don't
know if they're saved. They claim to be Christians. But here's a man that's lost his eyesight
in both of his hands and it's said that four times with the tip of his tongue he read the
Bible from cover to cover. And we can look at that and we say, that's amazing. That's
just the evidence of an individual that loves God's Word. What would cause him to have that
kind of love for God's Word? Well, he understood what it was. He understood that God's Word
was God's Word. All Scripture is given by inspiration of God. He understood that it
had been preserved. He understood that it was profitable. He understood all that we've
looked at these past few weeks and he said, I need to read the Bible. And I'm not sure
how I'm going to be able to read it, but I need to read it. And he learned to read letters
with the tip of his tongue. Unbelievable. Amazing. But the evidence of a man that loved
God's Word. This morning we've looked at ten things from Psalm 119 that I believe, and
I think you could find more, but I believe they reveal to us, they provide for us evidence
that supports the claim when the psalmist says, oh how love I thy law. It is my meditation
all the day. Because we can make any claim we want, but is there evidence to support
the claim? I believe this morning that the answer to that question for the psalmist would
be yes. Absolutely there is evidence that supports the claim that the psalmist expressed
when he said, I love God's Word. But what about our lives? What about my life? What
about your life? Is the evidence there? Does the evidence support the claim? I love God's
Word. I love God's Word. Those ten things, I'm not going to repeat them, but I do want
you to evaluate your own life. Ask the Lord to help us this morning. Do I really love
God's Word? Let's pray. Father we love you. We thank you for loving us. We thank you for
the testimony of the psalmist and as we've noted last week how he expressed his love
for thy Word. We looked at a number of reasons that led to his declaration as to why he would
say, oh how love I thy law. But now this morning as we look at the evidence that supports the
claim. God I pray that you would help each of us this morning to evaluate our own lives.
That we would examine our own lives and we would be honest in our evaluation. That we
would be humble in our evaluation. I say that I love God's Word. But is the evidence
there to support the claim? We thank you for the testimony of Mr. McPherson. No doubt he
loved thy Word. And God I pray that through your Word this morning you would cause us
to have a greater appreciation for your Word, a greater love for your Word. That the evidence
would be just so obvious in our lives that even others that would look at us and say
man they must really love the Bible. They love God's Word. They're always talking about
it. Lord I pray that you would help us this morning. Work in hearts and lives as only
you can. We'll thank you for the work that you'll do for it's in Christ's name we pray.