For Proverbs chapter number four and as you're turning there
We're looking at verses 1 through 13 from this passage of Scripture many countries around the world observe Father's Day
The specific date varies. In fact, a lot of countries will celebrate Father's Day today the third Sunday in June
Of course, that's when we as the United States of America, that's when we observe Father's Day
But we find that in many regions of the world
there are many countries that observe a day on their calendar each and every year to recognize Father's Day and
That date may vary but here of course as I mentioned a moment ago today is Father's Day
In the United States the first observance that we can tell from what we look at in history was in June of 1910 out in
Washington State in fact and
It kind of went on for a little while and some of the clergy members to use that term
As it was used in the particular article they made decisions that they would preach a message on fathers and they would
Address it in in like fashion is what they had done with Mother's Day and what have you?
but it would did not become a permanent national holiday until 1972 and
That really isn't that long ago, of course for a number of years
It was observed before, you know from 1910 until 1972, but it was not an official
Holiday in the United States of America until made a permanent national holiday until 1972
the purpose as it stated is this to honor fatherhood and paternal bonds as well as the influence of fathers in
society
The reality is that as we go to the Word of God
We find that back in the book of Deuteronomy in the sixth chapter that Moses gave very specific
Instruction to the role of fathers on influencing their families for the Lord and that responsibility was given
of course the children of Israel if you think about the book of Deuteronomy and obviously if you've been with us through the
Study of the book of Joshua
You understand that Moses is preparing that generation for entrance into the land and all of the things that they would become
You know be able to see and all that they would conquer and the things that they would now be
Exposed to and so on and so forth and we find that God used Moses to give some very important
Instruction to that generation and as you read the sixth chapter in particular
There is very direct instruction that is given to fathers
It is interesting if you were to study that passage of Scripture that there is an emphasis
placed upon the fathers knowing the truth and living the truth and
Then teaching the truth and by the way when we go in that order, we're much more effective
when our message of our life
Matches the message of our lips and that's why I think there's such an important emphasis that is placed in Deuteronomy chapter number six of
Those fathers knowing the truth
Living the truth and then teaching the truth as we look at the book of Proverbs
We have the opportunity from a human perspective. Obviously, it's the Word of God. It's divinely inspired
But humanly speaking we have the opportunity the privilege of you will to read of the instruction of a father
In fact, that's the title for the message this morning the instruction of a father
you'll see that in verse number one of chapter number four and it's interesting if we look at the
Specifics as to what's taking place in the book of Proverbs. You see that Solomon is speaking to his children in particular
Rehoboam and we find that instruction is being given it's being passed on
In fact in our text of Scripture this morning in chapter number four
You'll find that Solomon references how that his father David taught him you can look at the passages of Scripture
At the end of the life of King David and you can see first Kings chapter number two in particular
you can see where he calls for
Solomon and he gives them instruction and we find that
Solomon here in the book of Proverbs is providing this instruction for his children in particular for Rehoboam
But really there's a much greater
truth that is found within the book of Proverbs more than Solomon sitting down and speaking to his children or to his child we
find that God our Father is
Speaking truth to us as his children, you know, it's an absolute blessing to say I'm a child of God and
By the way, there are many people that make the claim that they're a child of God
And so let me help you understand that you can only be a child of God if you've been saved by the blood of the crucified
One there's some people that would like to purport this idea that we're all the children of God
We understand that God is the Creator
But you understand that you enter into that relationship of him being our father and we being his children
Only through redemption through the blood of Jesus Christ
But as many as received him to them gave he power to become the sons of God
Amen, and what a blessing I'm so thankful for the truth of God's Word with regard to that
And so this morning as we study this passage of scripture in Proverbs chapter 4 and we know the instruction of a father
Will deal specifically with how Solomon is seeking to influence his children
But more broadly speaking we must not miss the the truth of the application that God our Father
Has given us instruction and we must take heed to it our lives
Should be characterized by obedience to the instruction of our father
Amen, our life should be characterized by
obedience to the instruction of our heavenly father
We see that truth that is revealed to us in the book of Proverbs with regard to the human relationship
Between Solomon and his son and about the importance of taking heed and obeying and following and keeping and so on and so forth
but on a much higher plane a much more important perspective is that we would
understand that our heavenly father has given us instruction in this book that we call the Bible and all that our lives would be
characterized by obeying the word
Therefore this morning as we look at the passage of scripture. Yes, there is a charge to the fathers humanly speaking our
Responsibility there's a charge to the children their responsibility to receive the instruction that's been given to them
But really as we look at the the the application for each and every one of us say I'm not a father
I'm not a child living at home anymore. That's okay
Because if you're a child of God
There is rich truth in this passage of scripture for each and every one of us and I hope that we would make the decision
To say yes Lord. Yes, which one obey
I mentioned a passage of scripture not long ago. I don't remember exactly which message it was that I was preaching
It may have been a Joshua lesson for all I know. I'm not sure exactly
I didn't go back and look it up as to when I made the statement, but it was in John chapter number two at the
Miracle there at Cana and Mary comes to those
Servants and they say she says to them speaking of Jesus whatsoever. He saith unto you
Do it I love the simplicity of that statement
Isn't it? Isn't it? It's simple right whatsoever. He saith unto you
Do it and oh that we would have that perspective notice in our passage of scripture
The Bible says this I'll read the entirety and then we'll break it down this morning verse number one here
Ye children the instruction of a father and attend to no understanding
For I give you good doctrine
Forsaking not my law for I was my father's son tender and only beloved of the in the sight of my mother
He taught me also and said unto me let thine heart retain my words keep my commandments and live
Get wisdom get understanding
Forget it not neither decline from the words of my mouth forsake her not and she shall preserve thee
Love her and she shall keep thee wisdom is the principle thing
Therefore get wisdom and with all thy getting get understanding
Exalt her wisdom and she shall promote thee
She shall bring thee to honor when thou dost embrace her
She shall give to thine head an ornament of grace a crown of glory shall she deliver to thee
Here, oh my son and receive my sayings and the years of thy life shall be many
I've taught thee in the way of wisdom
I have led thee in right paths when thou goest thy steps shall not be straightened and when thou runnest
Thou shalt not stumble take fast hold of instruction
Let her not go keep her for she is
Thy life now when we read this passage of scripture
Strictly from the perspective of Solomon speaking to Rehoboam we say well, this is good instruction
Solomon didn't always follow the instruction he gave
Amen, in fact in my own personal Bible reading this morning the the place in which I started this morning
Just where I was was in first Kings dealing with how he Solomon loved many strange women and all that situation with the
Idolatry and what-have-you and so we find that if we read the passage of scripture strictly from that perspective
We'll glean some things but we won't glean the fullness of what we're looking at
if we take that perspective that God our Heavenly Father is
Giving us instruction and we understand we break down the passage of scripture. Oh how rich it becomes as
We look at the passage we see first of all the responsibility of the father
we understand that as I mentioned back in Deuteronomy chapter number 6 and we could look at the examples of
of those that were even recorded for us in the book of Genesis and
the instruction of Adam, no doubt, to his family, and you can deal with Noah, and
you can deal with Abraham, and so on and so forth, then
you can understand that there was a responsibility and there was a
fulfillment of responsibility in many of those cases
to give instruction, to teach
the children. As we think about the responsibility of the Father, I notice the
message of His lips.
When I speak about His, specifically, contextually, dealing with Solomon,
and we'll make the application, but notice what he says.
Solomon says, hear ye children, notice the instruction of a father.
Well, if they're gonna hear it, he's speaking it. Is that too far of a stretch?
Amen? And so, the message of his lips,
the instruction that he's giving through his speech, he says,
hear ye children, the instruction of the Father, and attend to no
understanding.
Notice what he says, for I give you good doctrine, forsake ye not my law.
Notice that as we consider,
he says again, in verse number 10, hear,
O my son, and receive my sayings, and the years of thy life
shall be many. And so, we see this idea of the message of His lips. In fact, if we
were to take a quick survey
through several chapters of the book of Proverbs, notice with me, in Proverbs
chapter number one,
in verse number eight, notice what the Bible says here in the first chapter of the book of
Proverbs.
It says, my son, notice again, hear
the instruction of thy father, and forsake not the law
of thy mother. In chapter two, in verse number one,
my son, if thou wilt receive
my words, and hide my commandments with thee.
We notice in chapter three, in verse number one, my son, forget not my law,
but let thine heart keep my commandments. We've read the passage in chapter number four.
Notice in chapter five, my son, attend
unto my wisdom, and bow thine ear
to my understanding. I like that. In my mind's eye, my sanctified imagination,
when I read Proverbs 5, in verse number one, and I see the
expression to bow thine eye,
or excuse me, thine ear, to my understanding.
That purposed hearing and listening.
Bow thine ear to my understanding. Notice in chapter number seven,
in verses one through three, my son, keep my words and lay up my commandments with
thee.
Keep my commandments and live in my law as the apple of thine eye.
Bind them upon thy fingers. Write them upon the table of thine heart.
If you skip down to verse number 24, it says, hearken unto me now, therefore,
O ye children, and attend to the words, what does it say?
Of my mouth. The message of his lips.
We notice here that Solomon, no doubt, had instructed his children,
specifically Rehoboam, in focus here within the context of the book of Proverbs,
and we find that he's given them the message of his lips, and I'm thankful
that I can understand biblically as we make the spiritual application
that our Heavenly Father has given us
a written word. It's a perfect book.
It is a preserved book. It is a powerful book.
The Bible tells us that it is a profitable book. Amen?
And we look at the Word of God. It is precious.
The psalmist says, yea, more to be desired are they than
gold, yea, than much fine gold. The instruction that we've received, the
written Word of God. I understand that God's not speaking to
us audibly, but you know it'd be a good idea for us as we sit down and read the
Word of God to act as if God is speaking these
words to us, because the Bible says all Scripture is
given by inspiration. What does the word mean?
God breathed. Amen? And if all Scripture is given by
inspiration of God, we're thankful that we have the written Word of God that's
been preserved for us, but our Father, can I tell you, He's
given us good doctrine. I mean, that's what He says in verse
number two. He says, for I give you good doctrine, forsake ye not my law.
Listen, we understand the instruction of the book of Proverbs.
Can I tell you that God has given us good doctrine?
In the same verse of Scripture in 1 Timothy chapter number four, when the
Bible says all Scripture is given by inspiration of God,
we find that it tells us that it's profitable for
doctrine. Amen? And we understand doctrine's important. You say, but
doctrine divides. Then so be it. Don't think I'm looking for fights or
anything like that, but I'm just saying, doctrine is important. Amen?
We cannot, we must not embrace the ideas of some of our liberal brethren that
have the ecumenical idea that we can set aside doctrine and seek
to have unity in the things that we agree on. It
doesn't work. It does not work, brethren. It's not
possible. What gives us unity is that we support
and embrace the same truth. God is the one that gives us unity
as we embrace this book. Amen? Notice the message of His lips
as we've mentioned here in Proverbs 4, but I want you to think about the
message of His life. We don't necessarily see it here within
the context of Proverbs 4. We do find that He mentions in
verses 3 and 4 how that He, Solomon,
received instruction from his father David,
and He says to him in verse 4, He taught me also and said unto me,
let thine heart retain my words, keep my commandments, and live.
In fact, if you were to study the life of Solomon prior to
the situation with all that took place with all of his wives and concubines and
all of the idolatry that is recorded, you find that He walked with the Lord.
You know, if you look at the first 20 years of the reign of Solomon
as the King of Israel, and you look at the building of His own
house, and then the building of the temple, and you see all that's taking
place, you find in those passages of Scripture,
what did Solomon ask for when the Lord appeared to him? Wisdom.
Give me understanding that I might lead
your people. I mean, you look at some amazing things and the influence of
David and his life in his early years, and I'm thankful for that, but I want you
to notice what Solomon says in Proverbs 23 and verse number 26.
We'll get back to chapter number four here in just a moment, but I want you to
see what is said here, and it's so
powerful, and it's so important for us to understand,
and it goes right along with what I mentioned in Deuteronomy chapter number
six, the instruction that Moses gave to the
fathers. Listen, you have to know the truth. You have to live the truth,
and then you propagate the truth. You deliver the truth.
If you miss B, you have a hard time with C.
If you're not living the truth, you have a hard time
teaching the truth. Many times we'll be viewed as being hypocritical.
Amen? Why? Because you're telling me to do something that you aren't
doing yourself. We find in Proverbs 23 and verse number
26, the wise man says, my son,
give me thine heart, but notice the rest of the verse,
and let thine eyes observe my ways. I wonder how many times I've read
that verse of Scripture, and I've wondered
this truth I don't need to request of or grant permission to anybody to
observe my ways. What do I mean by that? My ways are
being observed anyway. My children in particular, they're
observing my ways, and it must be that the message of my
life is in line with the message of my lips.
When I think about this truth spiritually, it causes me to rejoice
greatly. If I could adopt the words of Brother
Hummel, he said, I hear, I feel a preaching, a shout coming on, right?
And the reality is that we have the written Word of God,
but we have the living Word of God. John chapter number one, in the beginning
was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God.
Verse number 14, the Word became flesh and dwelt
among us. We have the living Word of God. Jesus Christ said, I am the way, the
truth, and the life. No man cometh unto the Father but by
Me. Jesus said often during His earthly
ministry to His disciples in particular, you see it in the
call of His disciples, He would use these two words,
follow Me. We find that as He's speaking about being His disciple,
He says that we're to deny ourselves, we're to take up our cross, and we are to
follow Him. Amen? The reality is, I believe
that one of the reasons in which we struggle so greatly with following the
Lord Jesus Christ is because we've not first denied ourselves
and we've not, number two, taken up His cross.
It's going to be a hard thing for me to follow Christ if I'm not denying myself.
Look at what Peter says in 1 Peter. You don't need to turn there, I'll read it
for you, but in 1 Peter chapter number two,
in verse number 21, the Bible says this. Now think about Peter.
Peter walked with Christ. Amen? He saw the life of the Savior. He saw the
Messiah. He walked with them. Peter is there at
the mount of transfiguration. I mean, Peter has experienced amazing things in
his life as he was an eyewitness. John uses that
terminology in 1 John chapter number one,
how that we are eyewitnesses of these things.
And we find that Peter says this in 1st Peter 2 and verse number 21 for even here unto where you called
Because Christ also suffered for us leaving us an example
That you should follow his steps
So we have as we think about the responsibility of the father
Can I tell you that there are times in which as a father I have failed physically speaking
I have failed to give the proper instruction the words of my lips have not been appropriate perhaps and giving the instruction that I need
To give the message of my life. Maybe has failed from time to time and if we'd be honest we understand
We're not perfect
But can I tell you that God has perfectly fulfilled the responsibility that he laid upon himself to give us
Good doctrine to give us instruction
To give us direction for our lives
So often we find that people are searching and they're looking and they want direction and they just want to know what God wants them
To do get into the book
The book gives us the truth the book gives us the answers
Amen
We're looking in the wrong places sometimes
We're looking for direction and counsel from the wrong source
In fact, I'll be dealing with that tonight in our message. Come back. You'll love it. Amen. It'd be great. Praise the Lord
God's given us good doctrine
He's given us the written Word of God
He promised that he'd preserve his word and he has and for that we ought to rejoice
But he's also given us the living Word
when God
Became man. He's the God man. You read Philippians chapter number two, and it just kind of blows your mind
We understand as we've even studied through the book of Hebrews
the truth of the incarnation of our Messiah and the fact that he lived a perfect sinless life for those
Three or so years a little over three years upon this sin curse world and what do you do?
He left us an example
you read the gospel records and I hope as you read Matthew Mark Luke and John and you begin to read about the life and
Ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ and you see how he behaved. Listen, I understand that at times we use these cute little cliches
What would Jesus do most people that wear a band around their wrist that says?
WWJD or they have it on the back of their car. They don't know what Jesus would do because they've not read this book
I'm what I feel like preaching this morning. I
mean seriously
How is it that we have been given not only the perfect Word of God?
But we've been given the example of God in flesh and yet so often we fail to receive the instruction
To hear the instruction
See because we see as it's described in chapter number four the book of Proverbs
It's the instruction of a father. It's good doctrine
It's in the way of wisdom according to verse number 10
Notice what he says in verse 10 and 11 in the passage of scripture that we're looking at this morning
He tells us this truth
He says here
Oh my son and receive my sayings and the years of my life shall be many notice verse number 10
I have taught thee in the way of wisdom
You know that our God is the all-wise God
We use the word to describe his wisdom that he is
Omniscient he's all-knowing
He said if any of you lack wisdom let him ask of God. Why would we ask God because he has all wisdom
Amen, that's why he doesn't tell us to go ask somebody else
I'm kind of glad he didn't tell you to go ask the pastor. I
Don't have all wisdom, but I know the one who does and
When people do ask me for counsel, I seek and purpose to give counsel that is based upon the truth of this book
Doesn't matter what my opinion is
matters what God says
Notice what he says not only have I led thee in the way of wisdom
I are taught thee in the way of wisdom, but notice the end of verse number 11
I have led thee notice what it says in right
Paths can I tell you this morning that God will never lead you wrong?
You may lead yourself wrong
You may deceive yourself and you may lead yourself wrong you may justify some things
But God will never lead you wrong
Can I tell you this morning that the Holy Spirit of God will never lead you to do something contrary to the written Word of God?
He won't
God is leading us in right paths
He's given us the truth and I'm so thankful this morning to find how that yes
we can look at Solomon and we can look at Rehoboam and we can look at this physical relationship of father and son and we
Can rejoice in the responsibility that he understood and that he fulfilled
But when I look at it from a spiritual perspective and I understand that I'm a child of God and he's my heavenly father
And oh, he's a good father
He's given me good doctrine he has given me truth
We find the response of children number two
the responsibility of the father
The response of children notice again as we look at our passage of scripture in verse number one notice these words
Here ye children the instruction of a father and attend to no understanding notice again in verse number 10
Hear oh my son and receive my sayings and the years of thy life shall be many
You know
The reality is that we will understand as we look at the passage of scripture
this truth of hearing the purpose in which these words are used throughout the book of Proverbs of
Hearing is not so that you can just gain some level of understanding, but it's so that you would apply the truth in your life
So often we speak about being doers of the word and not hearers only
But can I tell you that Jesus said on more than one occasion he that hath an ear let him hear
We find it in the letters that are written to the churches in
There in Asia in the book of Revelation chapters 2 and 3 he mentions often about hearing
You're not gonna do it if you've not heard it
You're not just gonna like accidentally obey God
We're at enmity with God
We get saved and we get sanctified through the truth of the Word of God and we
Understand the response of a children of the children listen
We need to hear the Word of God so then faith cometh by hearing and hearing by the Word of God
It is good to sit under the sound of the preaching of the Word of God
I'm glad that you're here this morning. Amen, honestly
I
I'm glad that I thank God regularly. I don't fully understand it. In fact, I argued with God about it
I don't understand why he called me to the ministry. I
Really don't I don't understand why but I'm thankful he did and I'm thankful that he's enabled me
But the reality is that we need to hear the Word of God
We need to hear the truth. We need to hear the instruction of a father and he's given us good instruction
He's given us the Word of God
We find that it says in verse number two this for I give you good doctrine notice this response of the children
Forsake ye not my law
It's a sad thing when a child of God says yeah, but that doesn't apply to me
We better be careful forsake ye not my law
God's given us his word. He's given us good doctrine. Oh
That was for a different culture you understand the Bible is cross-cultural
It works in any country of the world
Why because he's the God of the universe
Amen and
We find here that as we continue to think about the response of the children notice in verse number seven
Wisdom is the principal thing
therefore
get wisdom and
With all by getting get understanding what's the picture that you see in verse number seven? There's some work some effort
To get wisdom to get understanding to you know what Jesus said in John chapter number five
He said let me read it to you because I'm gonna not quote it properly because I wasn't planning to reference this verse of scripture
But in John 5 in verse number 39, he says search the scriptures why for in them you think
They have eternal life, but then he says this they are they which testify of me
You know what Jesus did in Luke chapter number 24 when he walked with those disciples
That were going back to Emmaus. He started at Moses and the prophets and he's found expounded all things
concerning himself
This morning as we understand this truth of wisdom being the principal thing and the
Wiseman saying therefore
Listen if wisdom is the principal thing and it is based upon the authority of the Word of God
therefore get wisdom
It's not just gonna fall out of the sky and land on your lap
You know, you got to dig into this book
There are times in which I read passages of scripture, I don't know how many times I
Was gonna preach through the book of Hebrews this year and I'm working on it
I'm working on it, but prior to preaching through the book of Hebrews
I don't know how many times I read the book of Hebrews over my walk with God
But I know that I purposefully
read the book of Hebrews
37 times between October and December in
preparation of the messages on the book of Hebrews
Just in its entirety, just starting in chapter number 1 and reading through chapter 13.
And the next day, starting in chapter number 1 and reading through chapter number 13.
And then, as I preach and prepare the messages,
you know how many times I read the passage that I'm going to preach?
I can't number it for you.
Why? I'm trying to get it. I want to understand it.
I want to dig into the Word of God.
There are passages of Scripture...
Have you ever come across a passage and say, I'm not sure what that means?
Come on, if you haven't, I need to talk to you.
And maybe you need to come up here and preach.
But there are times in which you come to a passage of Scripture and say,
God, I don't know what you mean.
I don't know what you're trying to tell me.
I don't understand the truth that you're trying to reveal.
And you wrestle with it, and you work, and you work, and you work.
And the Holy Spirit of God, who's our Teacher, He reveals truth to us.
The Bible's awesome.
But we've got to work. We've got to work.
The Bible tells us to study to show thyself approved unto God.
A workman, amen, that needeth not to be ashamed, rightly dividing the Word of truth.
And we understand, listen, it's work.
I had the privilege of visiting with someone this week,
and as I went to visit with them,
I noticed that there was some information there with regard to some memorization cards.
I thought, man, that's great. Working on memorizing the Word of God.
Began to have conversation about that particular thing that I saw.
And as we're talking about it, I said, you know, I get asked all the time,
how can you memorize Scripture?
And my consistent answer is W-O-R-K.
It takes work to memorize the Word of God.
It really does.
And the older you get, or the more you try to memorize, the more work it takes.
Just takes work.
Sometimes we forget that, but he says, get wisdom, get understanding, labor for it, work for it.
Notice what he says back in Proverbs 4, in verse number 13,
take fast hold of instruction.
I mean, does your mind, when you read these words,
does it not give you some pictures, some images of what we're to do?
Take fast hold of this instruction.
He says this, notice, let her not go.
Can I tell you that if you found truth in the Word of God,
you better not let it go for anything.
I don't care who comes down the road.
I don't care what they try to teach.
If you have the truth of the Word of God, you better hold on to it.
Don't compromise on it.
Don't change.
No, no, let's search the Scriptures, let's understand what the Word of God says.
And we find, he says, take fast hold here of instruction.
Let her not go.
Keep her, for she is thy life.
In Proverbs 13, in verse number 1, the Bible says,
a wise son heareth his father's instruction.
But I want you to think about that truth and couple it with chapter 28, in verse number 7,
whoso keepeth the law is a wise son.
So now listen, if you look at Proverbs 13, in verse number 1,
it says a wise son heareth his father's instruction.
So we get some information about a wise son.
What does he do? He hears the instruction.
But we understand some more information about a wise son in Proverbs 28, in verse number 7,
whoso keepeth the law is a wise son.
So it's not just hearing, it's keeping, it's doing.
We think about the application for us this morning.
We see the truth that God's given us good doctrine.
He's given us the written Word of God. He's given us the living Word of God.
And how is it that we respond?
Are we hearing the instruction?
Are we understanding that this book is profitable?
That I need the content of this book every day of my life?
I don't just need the Bible when I have a problem.
In fact, if we get a regular routine of getting into the Word of God,
then maybe when the problem comes, we already have the answer.
Why? Because God's been preparing me. God's been feeding me. He's sustaining me.
And that problem comes, we say, man, God, I'm so thankful
that You gave me that truth that I read just a few days ago.
You knew that I needed that, because You knew what was coming in my life.
That's how God works. Now, sometimes He lets something come
that we didn't have that preparation for.
And we search the book. We get into the Word of God.
God, help me. Give me wisdom.
Notice the result. We see the responsibility of the Father,
the response of the children. Notice the result. I love it.
The Bible tells us several things within the passage in Proverbs 4.
In verse 6, notice first of all it says this,
Forsake her not, and she shall preserve thee.
Love her, and she shall keep thee.
Wisdom is in reference here as we look at the portion of Scripture.
And we notice, wisdom shall preserve thee.
You know that God's instruction as we hear it and as we obey it,
that it protects and guards us from troubles and evils?
It does. God's designed it that way.
Listen, as a father, humanly speaking,
are there some things that you instructed your children with
so that it would keep them, protect them, preserve them
from some troubles and evils?
Sure. Why did you tell them not to play in the middle of the road?
Because it's dangerous.
I was chatting with somebody just yesterday,
and I was talking to them about the dangers of outlets
and how almost every child I've ever witnessed
somehow or another has a magnet for a wall outlet.
It's amazing.
It's like it's just calling their name.
Somebody's made a lot of money on that
by getting all those covers and all those things,
and then you get the covers that are child-proof
and you can't get the crazy things out to be able to use the outlet.
Amen, Joseph?
He said to me the other day,
how do you get this crazy thing out of here anyway?
It's kid-proof. No, just kidding.
The reality is that when I said that to the individual,
they said, man, I'm going to protect all of my outlets
because I don't want my kid putting something in there.
Yeah, why?
Because you're trying to protect them.
And when you tell Johnny or Susie, don't put it in there,
you're trying to keep them, to preserve them.
So guess what?
When God gives us the instruction that He's given us,
when we hear it and when we follow it,
can I tell you that one of the results that we see here in Proverbs 4
is that it will protect and guard us from any troubles and evils?
The reality is that it shall preserve thee.
There are some things that we just understand biblically
that we take and make decisions based on.
There are some things I'm not going to do,
some places I'm not going to go, so on and so forth.
Why? Because there's biblical command and it's preserved me.
It has. Amen?
If you'd be honest, I hope that you could say it's preserved you.
Because that's what the Word of God says.
If you hear it and you keep it, it shall preserve thee.
It's going to keep us, it's going to protect us and guard us.
Number two, what is the result that we see?
In verse 8 and 9, notice it says,
Exalt her and she shall promote thee.
She shall bring thee to honor when thou dost embrace her.
She shall give to thine head an ornament of grace,
a crown of glory shall she deliver to thee.
I see here in verses 8 and 9 that wisdom shall promote thee.
And really in my mind's eye, I see the truth of blessings.
You know what, and we're going to look at the passage,
Lord willing we'll have time.
In Deuteronomy, actually we won't look in there,
we'll skip that, I don't have time.
But in Deuteronomy 11, let me just give you what it says.
This day what I do, I lay before you a blessing and a curse.
Right? Is that what the Bible says?
Those of you that are familiar with Deuteronomy 11,
it's what it says.
A blessing if you obey.
A curse if you disobey.
I mean, it's pretty straightforward, right?
And so guess what?
God has attached in His Word blessings to obedience.
It's just the truth.
Why is it that we have the blessing,
the certainty of heaven?
Because we obeyed the Gospel.
Amen?
We heard the Gospel, we believed it,
we accept that Christ is our Savior.
Because Jesus Christ died on the cross for us,
He was buried, He rose in victory,
and we understood that truth and it was delivered to us,
and we obeyed the truth of the Word of God.
We obeyed the Gospel.
But throughout our lives, we think about when we exalt wisdom,
when we are hearing and doing and following the instruction
or understanding that God has given us the written Word of God,
He's given us the living Word of God,
that the blessings are going to come.
This evening when we deal with the subject matter
in which we're going to deal with,
we'll see it particularly in the passage
that we'll be dealing with tonight.
Number three, notice in verse 10,
"'Hear, O my son, and receive my sayings,
and the years of thy life shall be many.'"
The Bible says the way of the transgressor is hard.
We find that as we look at this,
and we understand the longevity, length of, and quality of life.
You know, I'm so thankful for the truth of eternal life.
I really am.
I am so thankful for the promise that the Bible says.
The Bible tells us that the gift of God is eternal life
through Jesus Christ our Lord.
John 6 and verse 23, what a blessing.
But can I tell you that in John 10 and verse number 10,
he tells us that he came to give us life
and that we might have it more abundant.
You know, he's given us the truth of the word of God
that we can have not only length of days,
but we can have quality of days, abundant life.
I'm thankful that we have everlasting life
and the truth of God's gift of salvation,
but we have that abundant life, that quality of life.
Not only do we see these three items,
notice in verse number 12,
as we think about a fourth result,
the Bible tells us when thou goest,
now understood contextually,
you're going in the way that I've guided you.
You're going with the truth that I've given you.
You've heard the instruction.
You've received the instruction.
You're doing the word of God.
You're obeying the truth that I've given you.
Then when you go, thy step shall not be straightened,
and when thou runnest, thou shall not stumble.
The idea there of thy step shall not be straightened
has the idea of being impeded.
And we understand that it says
that when thou runnest, thou shall not stumble.
I'm thankful that the truth of God's word
will prevent us from dealing
with some of the pitfalls of life.
Some of the obstacles and hardships
that life can bring our way,
we can avoid those things.
We can be delivered,
preventing us from having to endorse
some of those things.
Why? Because we've taken heed to the instruction.
Now, I'm not saying to you this morning
that you'll avoid every trouble,
because we understand that there are times
in which actively obeying God's instruction
leads you directly into a storm.
You say, pastor, you're crazy.
No, just look at the disciples.
It was God in flesh, Jesus Christ,
that said get in a boat and go over the Sea of Galilee,
and they got in the boat, and they got in,
and they had a storm.
They were obedient.
They weren't disobedient.
I mentioned on Wednesday evening
as we spoke about the when we shall see Christ,
another title of the song,
when we see Christ, when we see Jesus.
Man, what a blessing.
I love the song.
I think Ms. Joyce, she's asked me a couple of times,
at my funeral, I want that song.
Amen?
Why?
Because she understands
that when she takes her final breath here,
that she'll be immediately in heaven with her Savior,
and she'll see Him face to face, and what a blessing.
But the song talks about
when all of life's trials are passed.
And I mentioned this on Wednesday evening.
Those of you that were here,
some that were watching via live stream,
I made the statement that the troubles and trials,
the storms of life,
I'm so thankful that one day they will soon be over.
They will all be over.
And what a blessing.
But can I tell you that sometimes
we must come to this understanding
that in the midst of the storms,
God has a purpose,
that He would be glorified,
that we would be developed
in the very midst of the storms.
God's in control.
Do we believe that God's in control?
If He is,
if we are following His instruction,
if we're doing what He's told us to do,
if we're being good receivers of instruction,
if we're responding properly,
then He's going to give us that guidance
and direction that we need.
And we see these results
and what blessed results they are.
Oftentimes when we look at the results,
whether contextually
in what we're dealing with this morning,
or maybe some other area of life,
we say, yep, I want those results.
We know what the problem is?
We don't want the process.
We're an instant society.
Amen?
But to get the results,
we must follow the process.
We must hear and receive.
We must respond properly.
The truth of the matter
is that this book sitting on a shelf
somewhere all week and collecting dust,
though it is the most important,
most profitable book in all of the world,
it's doing you nothing.
Because you're not reading it.
You're not following it.
You're not obeying it.
I think, I don't remember who it was,
I think it might have been Charles Ryrie.
It might have been somebody else,
so don't fact check me on it
because I'm telling you up front,
I can't remember exactly who it was that said it.
But he said this,
on one page of Scripture,
I have more life transforming truth
than in all of the volumes
of the Encyclopedia Britannica.
I thought, man, I like his perspective.
I do.
Now, you young people,
I know you don't have volumes
of Encyclopedia Britannica
because we have Wikipedia
and they stopped actually printing it
a number of years ago,
but the reality is that God's Word
is full of good instruction, good doctrine,
and oh, that we just hear it and receive it.
Let me close with two passages of Scripture,
Psalm 19.
We're familiar with Psalm 19.
The Bible begins with,
the heavens declare the glory of God,
the firmament showeth forth His handiwork.
What a blessing.
Think about the beauty of creation,
how it reveals there's a Creator.
As we look at the passage of Scripture,
it quickly moves from the truth of creation
to the truth of God's written Word.
Of course, as we think about this passage
being the Old Testament,
the law of the Lord, the books of Moses,
we find that the Bible begins in verse number seven.
It says, the law of the Lord is perfect,
converting the soul.
The testimony of the Lord is sure,
making wise the simple.
The statutes of the Lord are right,
rejoicing the heart.
The commandment of the Lord is pure,
enlightening the eyes.
The fear of the Lord is clean,
enduring forever.
The judgments of the Lord are true
and righteous altogether.
More to be desired they than gold,
yea, than much fine gold.
Sweeter also than honey and the honeycomb.
Moreover, don't miss verse number 11,
moreover, by them.
What is them?
What's he been referring to the whole time?
The law of the Lord.
By them, by the truth of the Word of God,
is thy servant warned.
You hear, unfortunately, a generation today,
I just don't like church and the Bible
because it's got all those thou shalt nots.
I'm thankful God gave us a bunch of thou shalt nots.
You know why?
It's preserved me.
It's prevented me from dealing with some hardships.
Why?
Because God said thou shalt not.
God, I understand that in your wisdom
you told me not to do this,
and by your grace and with your help,
I'm not gonna do it.
Notice, by them is thy servant warned,
and in keeping of them,
there is great reward.
The keeping of them.
See, we're warned, but then we keep it.
Notice Deuteronomy chapter 30.
I preached short last week,
and I'm gonna preach longer today.
I'm not, I'm just teasing.
I didn't really preach short last week.
In fact, Joseph was doing the sound last week,
and he was rooting for me to go another minute longer
because I preached 58 and a half minutes.
I never preach that long.
But Hebrews chapter number seven
was just such a technical passage of scripture,
and I didn't wanna break it up,
and so I almost got to a full hour,
and he was cheering for just a little bit more, Daddy.
And so thank Joseph, amen?
He's not doing sound today,
but Deuteronomy chapter 30,
notice in verse number 10,
and I'll finish with this passage.
Notice the first word, if.
Deuteronomy 30 and verse number 10.
If.
It's an important word.
Just two letters in our English language,
but oh, what a message they carry.
If thou shalt hearken unto the voice of the Lord thy God.
To keep his commandments and his statutes,
which are written in this book of the law.
And if, we see it again,
thou turn unto the Lord thy God
with all thine heart, with all thy soul.
For this commandment, which I command thee this day,
notice this, it is not hidden from thee,
neither is it far off.
Aren't you thankful that we have the word of God?
We have it.
I'm not saying this to pat myself on the back,
but you ought to be thankful
that you got a church and a pastor
that preaches the word of God.
Because the reality is that you can go long and far
around this nation
and you can find a dearth of good Bible preaching.
I'm just saying, preach the Bible.
Notice verse number 12.
It is not in heaven that thou shouldest say,
who shall go up for us to heaven and bring it unto us,
that we may hear it and do it.
Neither is it beyond the sea that thou shouldest say,
who shall go over the sea for us and bring it unto us,
that we may hear it and do it.
No, the reality is that if you want to hear it and do it,
it's available.
Some people say, if I just knew what to do.
Like all of the flashing lights and everything,
like if you just knew what to do, here you go.
Amen?
Notice verse 14, but the word is very nigh unto thee,
in thy mouth and thy heart thou shouldest,
that thou mayest do it.
See, I have set before thee this day,
life and good and death and evil.
In that I command thee this day to love the Lord thy God,
to walk in his ways, to keep his commandments
and his statutes and his judgments,
that thou mayest live and multiply.
And the Lord thy God shall bless thee in the land
whither thou goest to possess it.
But look, we see that word again, if.
But if thine heart turn away so that thou wilt not hear,
but shall be drawn away and worship other gods
and serve them,
I deny.
unto you this day, that ye shall surely perish,
and that ye shall not prolong your days upon the land,
whither thou passest over Jordan to go to possess it.
I call heaven and earth to record this day against you,
that I have set before you life and death, blessing
and cursing.
Therefore, choose life, that both thou and thy seed
may live, that thou mayest love the Lord thy God,
and that thou mayest obey His voice,
and that thou mayest cleave unto Him, for He is thy life,
the length of thy days, that thou mayest dwell in the land
which the Lord sware unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac,
and to Jacob, to give them."
The sad reality is that even as we've
studied through the book of Joshua,
we're in the midst of the land being divided
and the inheritance for each of the tribes,
and so on and so forth.
And we think about the passage of Scripture,
we think about the truth of the fullness of the book of Joshua,
they go into the land.
God brings them in.
God gave them warnings.
Joshua gives messages, the warnings
that are contained therein.
You know what the sad reality is?
They were judged because of their disobedience.
They didn't always stay in their land.
The promise of a remnant that returned after the Babylonian
captivity, I thank God that it happened.
But you understand, the Assyrians came in,
and a little while later, the Babylonians come in.
Why?
It wasn't because God wasn't able to preserve His people.
It was because His people forsook
the instruction He gave them.
They served idols.
They did all sorts of wickedness,
and the judgment of God came.
And they were warned of that.
And this morning, as we think about the instruction
of a father, I'm thankful for the instruction
that I received from my earthly father.
I'm thankful for the opportunity and the responsibility
that I have to give instruction to my children,
physically, humanly speaking.
I wish I could say I always responded properly
to the instruction I received from my father, but he's here,
and I'm not interested in lying.
I didn't always receive it properly.
And if you did, never mind.
Let me say this.
Biblically speaking, our God has given us
the written word of God.
He's given us good instruction, the instruction of a father,
our heavenly father.
It's good doctrine.
He said, how are you going to respond to it?
I said this in the beginning of the message this morning,
and I'm going to close with this thought.
Our lives, as God's people, as God's children,
our lives should be characterized by obedience
to the word of God.
Should be characterized by obedience to the word of God.
That we are doers of the word, not hearers only.
That we're digging into the book.
You know, I see statistics all the time.
I get periodicals and magazines.
I don't read half of them.
I don't have time.
Why?
Because I'd rather read the Bible than all that stuff,
and so I'm not going to change my Bible reading
time to read all of that.
But I do get a bunch of things, and I do read many of those.
And when you start reading the statistics of people
that claim to be Bible-believing regular attenders of church
that are asked the question, have you ever
read the Bible completely cover to cover,
and you see that a large percentage of them
say no, it's a problem.
And then when you say to the people that
say they do read it cover to cover,
and you say, OK, how many days a week do you read the Bible?
Do you have a plan?
Do you have an overwhelming majority of people
have no plan?
Now, I will readily admit I've never
been called by any of those people,
and I've never participated in the surveys.
And I understand statistics and the way they work
and how you can make them say what you want them to say,
but I would say there's a problem.
If that is any representation of reality,
and I'm sad to say that I'm sure it is,
then what God has given us as good instruction,
unfortunately, His people have said, I'm OK.
I'm going to figure this out myself.
It's not really for me.
And then we wander around, and we flounder around.
We deal with problems and troubles and difficulties,
and we wonder why.
God's given us His word.
Oh, that we would hear it and receive it,
and that we would get it, that we'd labor for it,
that we would hold onto it, lay hold of it, let it not go,
forsake it not, but be doers of the word.
The instruction of a father.
Humanly speaking, I'm thankful that Solomon
gave some instruction of Rehoboam.
Spiritually speaking, I'm thankful
that our Heavenly Father has given us a perfect book.
It's changed my life.
It's helped me in so many ways.
And I'm sure that you could stand and testify
of how the book has helped you as well.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for this day, Father's Day,
that we can think about the responsibility,
humanly speaking, of instructing the children
that you would bless us with.
And Lord, what a blessing.
We're so thankful for that charge that we can receive.
Thankful for the truth with regard to the children,
how they respond to it.
Thank you for the results that you carry forth and show us
in your Word.
In a much greater, far more important aspect,
we understand that the book of Proverbs records for us
the instruction of our Heavenly Father
to us as your children.
And God, as we examine the truth of this passage of Scripture,
I pray that you'd help us to examine it
from that perspective.
This is God my Savior, my Father.
I'm His son, His child, and He's given me this instruction.
Oh God, would you help us to have
our lives characterized by obedience to Thy Word?
We take the simplicity of that truth in John 2.
Whatsoever He saith unto you, do it.
God, help us to be doers of the Word and not hearers only.
Help us, Lord, to understand the treasure that you've
given us in your Word.
Just how powerful and profitable it is,
how it gives us the answers for all of life's questions.
Lord, help us to roll up our sleeves and labor, work,
dig in to get the wisdom that you have for us.
I pray that this morning, if there's
one that's not sure of heaven, whether they're here locally
or they're tuned in via the live stream,
I pray they'd understand that the Lord Jesus Christ, God
in flesh, died for them, was buried in a borrowed tomb,
and rose in victory, conquering sin, death, and the grave.
He said, I am the way, the truth, and the life.
No man cometh unto the Father but by me.
The Holy Spirit of God would convict you
of sin, of Christ's righteousness, of judgment
to come.
Maybe this morning there's one that says,
I've never been saved.
I don't know.
The Lord is my Savior.
Would you trust Him today?
Today is the day of salvation.
Understand there's nothing good that you can do.
It's all in what Jesus did.
Lord, I pray that you'd work in that individual's heart.
We think about those that are here, Lord, that are saved.
We're your children.
Those that are logged on watching
that are your children, God, would you
help us to receive the instruction,
obey the instruction?
Help us, Lord, to recognize what we
have in the written word of God, in the living word of God,
the Lord Jesus Christ.
There would not be just some cliche
that we throw around of what would Jesus do,
but that through studying thy written word
and studying the life of Christ through the Gospels,
that we would have an understanding of how He
behaved, what He did, that we might follow His example.
Help us, Lord.
Work in and through our lives.
We'll thank you for the decisions that will be made,
for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano.
Maybe you want to pray in your seat.
Maybe you want to pray in your chair.