And we're going to continue our thought that we've had here for about seven weeks on Wednesday
evening.
This is lesson number seven with regard to doing what we ought to do.
And the series, James chapter four will be this evening, but this series has been designed
to help us do the things we ought to do.
In other words, it's designed to affect our behavior, to influence how we behave.
That our behavior would be such that we would be doing the things that God has commanded
or instructed us to do.
Each lesson really leads us to a time of honest evaluation in our lives where we determine
based on what God has specifically told us in his word that we ought to do this.
Then I honestly and humbly examine my life, encourage you to examine your life to determine
are we doing what we ought to be doing?
The principles that are given to us need to be taken heed to.
We need to take and pay attention to apply the truth in our lives, making necessary adjustments.
You think about life and there are times in which we got to make adjustments along the
way.
We were flying home late Monday night, early into Tuesday morning and as we were flying
over Cuba, there was a great storm to the east of where we were flying and the pilot
had to continue to make adjustments to his flight plan.
How did I know that?
Well, I had a window seat and I could see the lightning out to the east, number one.
Number two, I could feel the plane changing routes and then number three, I had this thing
right in front of me that had the flight pattern and we got to Cuba and we made this big kind
of U and then we continued going north.
And he had to make adjustments on the go, why?
Because it really is not good to fly through a storm with lightning and so on and so forth.
It can really not only do some structural damage, but obviously have a great impact
on your instrument panels and all the electrical components within an aircraft.
And so there were adjustments that needed to be made.
We understand that as we live life, there are times in which there need to be adjustments
in our lives.
We get going along in life and we're going on our path and we don't even maybe acknowledge
that we are going in a direction or doing something that might not be exactly what we
ought to be doing and then we hear the teaching and the preaching of God's word.
We read our Bibles and our daily devotions and we see that God says, we ought to be doing
this and we evaluate and then we make adjustments.
What does that really summed up to be?
Well, that's being a doer of the word and not a hearer only.
We find that James begins in chapter number one, talking about that very thing that we
so often quote, that we ought to be doers of the word and not hearers only.
Unfortunately, there are many times in Jesus likened this thought that there are many times
in life that people hear, but they don't make the adjustments.
They don't apply, they don't do.
And Jesus said that individual that hears, but does not apply, well, they're foolish.
And he likens them to a foolish man.
I think that it's silly for us, for an individual to be told what we ought to do.
To be told in God's holy, inspired, preserved word that here's what you ought to do and
for us to be like, yeah, but I don't want to.
This doesn't really make a whole lot of sense, but you know there are a lot of people that
live that way.
They hear, they don't do any evaluating and they do no adjusting.
They just continue on carrying on just as they always have and just keep on that trajectory.
This evening as we look at this portion of scripture, it's our seventh lesson.
The first week we talked about men ought always to pray.
We talked about the fact that men, excuse me, that we ought to obey God rather than
men.
That we ought to grow spiritually.
What are we doing to grow spiritually?
Are we purposefully doing something in our lives that we would grow spiritually?
That we're challenging ourselves with regard to our Bible reading, our prayer time, our
Bible memorization, that we're growing closer to God, that we're increasing in our knowledge
of God.
To know God is to know His word.
And how we need to increase in our knowledge of God to grow spiritually.
We ought to walk humbly and to walk in humility.
God says that He resisted the proud, but He gives grace to the humble.
And we said this, we ought to proclaim the gospel.
And this week, this past week, we had the opportunity to participate, as I mentioned,
five different special or designated times on their calendar while we were there to go
out on some level of outreach throughout the week.
And it was a real blessing.
There was a purposed, a clear purpose of their church making an emphasis on outreach.
You saw a passion from their folks.
They were passionate about proclaiming the gospel, about sharing the truth of God's love
with those that they would come into contact with.
Not last Wednesday, but the week before, I taught on this, that we ought to love one
another.
We ought to love one another.
So we find this evening as we come to this familiar passage of scripture, the Bible tells
us in James 4, verses 13 through 15 will be our text for this evening.
Notice the Bible says, go to now ye that say, today or tomorrow, we will go into such a
city and continue there a year and buy and sell and get gain.
Verse 14, whereas you know not what shall be on the morrow, for what is your life?
There's even a vapor that appeareth for a little time and then vanisheth away, for that
ye ought to say, if the Lord will, we shall live and do this or that.
I titled the message this evening, we ought to seek the Lord.
We ought to seek the Lord.
We find that in life we understand that there are decisions that we have to make and there
are times in which those decisions face us and we might look at those decisions as this
is a big decision, I need to seek the Lord.
I need to know the will of the Lord with regard to this decision.
Can I say to you this evening, we need to seek the Lord for direction in every area
of our life and every decision that we make.
It's not just the big decisions that all of a sudden I need God's input on and I need
God's will and God's direction, no, I need God's direction at every turn, at every step
of my life and so do you.
We find in the text of Scripture, again, a familiar passage of Scripture, as we think
about this thought, we ought, he says in verse 15, for ye ought to say, if the Lord will,
we shall live and do this or that.
And so kind of dealing with this thought that we ought to seek the Lord, why?
So that we would know the will of the Lord.
You know, sometimes we talk about the will of the Lord and you'll hear that phraseology
and people will have this idea, well how can I know God's will as it's some mystical thing
that God is trying to hide from us.
Let me say this by way of introduction, to know the will of God, we find that God has
given us in his word many revealed truths that are his will.
In fact, you find some verses of Scripture that specifically say this is the will of
God.
And so if it can't be any more plain than that, I'm not sure what else it would say.
And so we find that going into the truth of God's word reveals to us the will of God for
the people of God.
Sometimes we talk about, well what's God's will for me individually, personally, what
does God want me to do?
And we see that there's the revealed will of God that is the, broadly speaking, the
will of God for all people of God, all the children of God.
And I would say this, that we cannot ignore the will of God that has been plainly given
to us as we say, well I want to know what God wants me to do here.
Hey, start doing the will of God that is already revealed and he will continue to reveal more
to you.
Paul and Barnabas were already serving in the church at Antioch when God revealed his
will for them to go on the missionary journey.
They were already doing what God had revealed to them and as they're doing it, God reveals
more specifically of what they're to do.
We find that they're desiring to go and to preach the gospel on a subsequent missionary
journey.
Are we going to go here?
Are we going to go there?
God shuts the door, God shuts the door, and then God gives clear direction, here's where
I want you to go.
And we find that we seek the will of the Lord.
We seek the Lord to know his will.
In verse number 13, if you're going to take notes this evening, I would say this, I notice
in verse number 13 the first thought, the routine of life.
The routine of life.
Do you ever get stuck in a rut?
Do you ever get stuck in the routine?
Just the monotony of life, if you will, just the routine that we have and I understand
sometimes when we speak about routine, we speak about it in a positive sense and this
evening I understand that there are some aspects of routine that are positive and it's necessary
and we want to have structure and so on and so forth, but when I begin to think about
verse number 13 and I think about the routine here, really what's happening is these individuals,
these are believers that are being written to, that they're making plans, making decisions,
going through life, the routine of life, without any consideration whatsoever as to what God's
will is.
Their consideration is really just...
just how it could benefit them,
what they might be able to gain,
how they might be able to,
and they're just not even for a moment,
as you look at the text of scripture,
it seems as if they're not even considering
what the will of the Lord might be
in seeking the face of God.
Notice in verse 13,
go to now ye that say,
here's what they're saying,
today or tomorrow,
we will go into such a city.
So they're saying,
here's what we're gonna do,
here are our plans,
we're gonna go to a city,
whether we go today or tomorrow,
we're gonna make this decision,
we're gonna go to a city,
and then notice this phrase
right in the middle of the verse,
and continue there a year,
continue there a year.
What are they gonna do while they're there?
Well, it says buy and sell,
and get gain,
and get gain.
And so they thought this was a decision
that's based upon the economic possibility
that I can go to this place,
I can travel there with the goods,
the business savvy that I have,
the goods that I'm able to produce,
whatever it might be with regard
to the timing of the writing,
and we think about it in our own lives,
obviously, we live in a different time and culture
than what they had here in the book of James.
But they're saying,
we're gonna go there,
we're gonna continue there for a year,
and we're gonna buy and sell,
and we're gonna benefit from this,
we're gonna get gain.
And they're making these plans,
they're going through the routine of life, if you will,
and this is something that perhaps
they had done many, many other times,
this is something that they were used to.
I don't know when it was that these individuals
trusted Christ as their savior,
I don't know if they had already been in business
for years beforehand,
or what the exact circumstances are,
but I know that the Bible allows us
to take a principle and then make the application.
To take a principle and then make application.
And the reality is that there are times
in which people trust Christ as their savior,
and they think that they're gonna continue to live
by the same rules that they used to live by,
and following the same decision-making process
that they used to live by,
but understand that if any man is in Christ,
if they're a new creature,
old things are passed away,
behold, all things are become new.
With the way that I made decisions before I got saved
should be different than the way I make decisions
after I got saved.
And we find that this evening,
though it may be true that they could travel
to this particular city,
that they could go to this place,
that they could buy and sell,
and they could gain,
the reality is that it seems as if
the text of scripture is addressing these individuals
because they're not having God
as part of the decision-making process.
They've not sought the will of the Lord.
I know there are times in which I've said to people
over the years,
they'll tell me of a decision that they've made,
and I'll say something like this,
did you seek the will of God on this?
Did you seek the face of God?
Did you pray about this?
And I remember one time,
and it was years and years ago,
and probably 12 and a half,
it was just within six months or so of us being here,
12 and a half, maybe more years ago,
and someone said they were gonna go find another church,
and I said, that's great.
I said, did you pray about that?
And they said, that's what they said.
They said, silence.
There was no answer.
I said, because if you prayed about it
and you believe that's the will of God,
then I'm all for it.
And that made them kind of like,
they didn't expect that answer.
They had not prayed about it.
They had not sought the face of God about it.
They just were going to make a decision.
And the reality is that sometimes in life,
that's how we can go through life.
We just make decisions.
Something happens, something's done that we don't like,
or whatever it might be,
and we just make a decision apart from seeking the Lord.
And so we find that here, there's the routine of life.
These people are just going through the routine of life,
just making the decisions,
just making the decisions based upon whatever factors here
it looks like for the economic gain that was possible
based upon the context of the verse.
But the reality is that in our lives,
we can do the same thing.
We can get stuck in the routine of life
and just going through the decision-making process
and really making decisions
without ever really consulting with God,
without ever really seeking the face of God.
What does God want me to do?
What does God want me to do in this situation?
Sometimes we make such an emphasis with young people.
What does God want you to do with your life?
And that's such an important question for a young person,
but I would say this,
it's such an important question for every aged person.
Why?
Because God has a plan and a will for our lives,
regardless of what stage we are in in life,
if God has not taken us home to glory,
God has a will and a purpose for our lives.
What does God want me to do?
Verse number 14, number two, the reality of brevity.
These people are going to receive
really some correction in verse number 14.
I don't think this is what they were probably thinking
that they were going to hear.
Ye that say, these are some people that are,
obviously, they're a known group of people
that are making these decisions.
Today or tomorrow, we're gonna go into such a city,
continue a year, buy, sell, and get gain.
Maybe they expected to hear James say,
hey, best of success to you.
Sometimes we use the phraseology, good luck,
I hope everything goes well, I hope you have success.
Nope, James says,
whereas you know not what shall be on the morrow.
Well, that's kind of a wake-up call, isn't it not?
I mean, they said today or tomorrow, we're gonna go.
Not only are we gonna go today or tomorrow,
but we're gonna stay there for a year.
James says, under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
you know not what shall be on the morrow.
Not only do you not know what's gonna be on the morrow,
you're making plans for the year.
You're gonna stay there, buy, sell, and get gain,
but there's gotta be this reality of brevity
that is brought up and brought to the attention
of the individuals, and they're going to be given
what I would refer to here as profitable counsel.
We find that here, James says,
ye know not what shall be on the morrow.
You know, isn't that true for every one of us?
How many of you have plans for tomorrow?
Don't be embarrassed if you do.
I have plans for tomorrow.
We have plans for tomorrow, right?
But the reality is that we don't know
that we have tomorrow, is that true?
Now I understand we make plans, we go through that process,
but we ought to be seeking the will of God in our plan
as we make our plans, but we find here
that we can make plans knowing and seeking the Lord
and knowing the will of God as we make our plans,
but we must keep in our minds the reality of brevity,
the fact that we don't know what's on the morrow.
We don't know.
I often say this, David makes the statement in 1 Samuel,
and I understand the context as to why David
said what he said.
He said, there's but a step between me and death.
And why did David say that?
Well, Saul made it his singular purpose in life
to kill David, and Saul tried to kill David himself
when he had no success.
He tried to enlist others to kill David.
Obviously, he tried to get the Philistines to kill David.
I mean, he did all that he could do,
and he was seeking David in all the coast of Israel.
He was doing everything he could possibly do to kill David,
and yet David says, am I but a dead dog?
I've not done anything.
David had opportunity, he did nothing,
and he says to Samuel, there's but a step
between me and death.
Now, that was a real situation for David
where he was on, I mean, he was being hunted,
and so he understood, there's but a step
between me and death.
Can I tell you, though, that's true for all of us.
It's true for all of us.
There are people, I was getting alerts on my phone
when I was in Panama of accidents that took place
in northern Virginia and shut down roadways
and people were killed in those accidents.
It happens every day.
And so the reality of brevity is brought to our attention
in verse 14, it's brought to the attention
of these within the group that are being addressed,
those that James is writing to.
He says, listen, you know not what shall be on the morrow,
and then he asks this question, for what is your life?
I wonder, do we ever really sit down
and consider what is our life?
I remember asking somebody this question
a number of years ago.
In fact, there was a period of time
where I'd ask this question repeatedly
at different people that I've spoken to.
I've not asked it recently,
but I remember asking a man
as I was sharing the gospel with him,
I said, listen, 500 years from now, what's gonna matter?
And he looked at me and he said, 500 years?
I was like, yeah, 500 years from now,
what's gonna, what in your life
is gonna amount to anything?
And he's like, nothing.
No one's even gonna know that I lived.
And I'm like, yeah, pretty much.
I mean, unless you do something extremely significant
to change the course of history,
you're not gonna be remembered 500 years from now.
But what we do for Christ, oh man, that's gonna count.
That's going to matter.
That's gonna make a difference, amen?
And you can talk about whatever car you bought,
whatever size house you lived in,
whatever, whatever, whatever,
but all that stuff is just not gonna matter.
And we find that he asked this question,
what is your life?
What is your life?
And then he gives an answer.
It is even a vapor that appears for a little time
and then vanisheth away.
Can you imagine, can you put yourself in the shoes of these that are being addressed in verse 13?
Go to now ye that say, there were some people that were saying, they were there,
and they were saying, here's what we're going to do,
we're going to either today or tomorrow, we're going to go into such a city,
we're going to continue a year, we're going to buy, sell, and gain.
And then they read this counsel from James where James says,
what is your life? It's even a vapor that appears for a little time and then vanishes away.
Can you imagine, can you put yourself in their shoes? What a wake-up call.
What a reality that, hey, I don't know what's going to happen tomorrow,
yet alone a year from now. Now, some of us make plans even a year from now.
I have plans for next year. As many of you know, I'm a planner.
I was asked to preach a Bible conference for somebody last week,
and they asked me three weeks before, and I said, brother, I'm going to be in Panama.
I made those plans way, way, way long ago, and so they sent me an email today and said,
how was the trip, or a text message, how was the trip to Panama?
I said, it was great. I said, how was your Bible conference?
They said, it was good, but we really would like for you to come.
And I was like, listen, I'm not trying to be unkind, but I plan things in advance,
so if you really want me to come, you better let me know the dates as soon as you know what they are.
And not that I get asked to preach a lot, but I do have things on the calendar,
but I don't put those things on the calendar without seeking the will of the Lord, number one,
and I don't put them on the calendar presuming that I'm actually going to be here.
I don't know, and you don't know. And these individual believers,
this group that were making these plans, they are given this profitable counsel,
and it is a reality that every one of us must acknowledge in our lives.
Indeed, our life is brief. It's illustrated here as a vapor. We find that Psalm 102 and
verse number 11 illustrates our lives as being a shadow, and we understand the brevity of life.
How many times you live, I remember when I was a teenager, many of you can remember back to
being a teenager in school, and you felt like time kind of just stood still, and you could not
wait for the school year to get over. I wasn't one that really loved school a whole lot. I did
well and so on and so forth, but man, it just felt like the school year would take forever.
And then you become an adult. Somebody said this, it feels like time is faster. Do you ever feel
that way? Now here, the reality is that time is no faster. It's a second is a second, a minute is a
minute, an hour is an hour. It's not getting any faster, but life just seems like, man, you blink
and you look back. Next, not this Saturday, but next Saturday, Nova's gonna be one. We're gonna
be celebrating her one-year birthday, and it's like, man, I remember like it was just yesterday
when we were being told that she, we all can relate to those things. You have family dynamics
that you can relate to those things, and it's amazing how quickly time goes. Sometimes you talk
to some of these young people and they say, I can't wait to be, and they'll name an age because
I just want to be done with this, and you're like, hold on, it's going to come fast enough, right?
Just enjoy this stage in your life. And so the reality of brevity, number three, verse number 15,
what should our response be to this truth, our response to this truth? We see
the routine of life, the reality of brevity, and now we see our response.
Notice in verse 15, for that ye ought to say. See, they were saying, according to verse number 13,
go to now ye that say. Here's what they were saying. Today or tomorrow we will go into such
a city and continue there a year and buy and sell and get gain. And James, after giving them
this profitable counsel with regard to the brevity of life, he says, for that ye ought to say. Let me
correct, let me make an adjustment to how you're dealing with life. Because you're living life a
certain way, you're doing what you've always known to do, you're doing maybe what other people are
doing, you're doing what's customary, what's culturally acceptable, and you're saying what
everybody else is saying. But you're a Christian, you're a child of God, you belong to Christ, and
your life is in his hand, and he has a purpose and a will for you. And so here's what you're saying,
but here's what you ought to say. Do you see how he makes that connection from verse 13 to 15?
In between, he gives the profitable counsel. He says, here's what you're saying, ye that say,
for that ye ought to say, verse 15. And so here's what James is going to tell them that they ought
to say, if the Lord will, we shall live and do this or that. So we find that James is giving
counsel again by way of introduction. I talked about hearing these messages in these lessons,
and not just because I'm delivering them, but as we study the Word of God, that we have the
opportunity to come face to face with truth that God has revealed to us. And we find that God says,
here's what you ought to do. What do we do when we read that? What do we do when God reveals
a truth, a principle, that we ought to be doing in our lives? Do we evaluate? Do we make the
adjustments that are necessary? James is really kind of forward, in a forward way, making the
adjustment for them. It's like we get opportunity to sit in a private counseling session with these
individuals. Though we do not know their names or know who they are, we know they're real people,
and James knew their situation. He says, here's what you're saying, but here's what you ought to
say. You need to make an adjustment on your perspective in life, because you're making
decisions, you're making plans, without ever even consulting the Lord to know the will of God.
And so what does James do? He corrects them. He reminds them of the brevity of life. He helps
them to have this perspective that is so important for the people of God to have, and then he says,
after acknowledging the truth of the brevity of life, after acknowledging the fact that you don't
know what's on the morrow, here's what you should say, if the Lord will. If the Lord will, we shall
live and do this or that. I would say this tonight, when we think about our response to the truth,
number one, we should acknowledge God's gift of life. We should acknowledge God's gift of life.
I'm thankful for the gift of God, which is eternal life, and I'm thankful to be a possessor of
eternal life, that I've been saved by the grace of God, but I also recognize that every day that I
have physical life is a gift from God. Every day is a gift from God, and we ought to thank
God for the gift of life, and we ought to cherish God's gift of life. We ought to be thankful for
the days that God gives us. We ought to rejoice in the fact, the psalmist said in Psalm 118,
in verse 24, this is the day the Lord hath made. We will rejoice and be glad in it, and it's that
decision that the psalmist is making, that I'm going to rejoice because this is the day the
Lord hath made, and we're not going to live under the circumstances. No, we're going to keep our
eyes on Jesus, the author and finisher of our faith, and we're going to keep on keeping on.
We're going to do the will of God, and we're going to cherish the gift of God that he gave us in
physical life. I would say this, and obviously it's the thought throughout the evening,
what should our response be? Our response should be that we seek God's will for our lives, that we
seek the face of God, that we determine this little phrase that is given to us in verse 15,
if the Lord will, this determination of what God's will is for our lives. The reality is that
this phrase, if the Lord will, this should not, it cannot simply be a Christian cliche that we use.
It must be our perspective in life. There's a young man that on Wednesday evening I met in
Panama for the first time. Their services on Thursday night were going out soul winning,
and he walked up to me, and he's a Panamanian. I mean, he looks Panamanian, and he walked up to me
with almost perfect English and said, I'm Julius Caesar. And I was like, because very few people
had English that was extremely easy to understand, and I was like, all right, Julius Caesar, here we
go. I said, you know English? I mean, he was, man, he could speak English great. And I got to talk
with him, and then he ended up being my soul winning partner that evening, and we had a great
night. And he shared with me that he was engaged to get married, and he was planning to get married
in February. And so I did not know this, but I had met the fiance earlier, but I did not have
put the two together. And so the next day I put the two together that that's the fiance of this
guy, so on and so forth. Her name is Lily. And I said to Lily, I said, so you're getting married?
And she said, I said, when are you getting married? And I don't know if she said this to anyone else
that was in the group, but here's her answer to me. If the Lord will, I'm going to get married in
February. And I thought to myself when she said that, I was like, you know, she's not using that
as a cliche. She was being honest and sincere that between now and February, there's a number
of months and she doesn't know. It's a plan that they've made. She's accepted.
He proposed, she's accepted the proposal,
she said yes, she's got a ring, they're gonna make plans.
Someone was actually from the group inquiring,
I think it was on Sunday night after the service
or after the meal and heading back to the hotel,
inquiring about the plans and what the cultural aspects are
of weddings in Panama and so on and so forth
and getting some information and it was good,
but she had this perspective, if the Lord will.
Oh, how we need to have that perspective in life.
It's not just a cliche.
We make plans, but we make plans
according to the will of God.
We do not make plans based upon the opportunities,
we make plans based upon the will of God.
The opportunity for these individuals,
according to what we can gather from verse 13,
is that there was a place where no doubt
their goods were needed, that they felt like
there was an avenue where they could buy, sell, and gain.
But the economic opportunity was not the determining factor
for their decision, it could not be, it must not be,
it must be what is the will of God.
See, because they're now saved people
that belong to Christ.
We are bought with a price,
Paul says this in 1 Corinthians 6, we are not our own.
Now let me ask you, when we talk about the idea
of being bought with a price, what does that mean?
It means that we're saved.
If I could boil it down to a very simple statement,
when Paul says that we're bought with a price,
it means that we've been saved, that we've accepted
the gift of God which is eternal life,
that Jesus paid it all, and we are bought with that price.
He paid for our salvation.
And he says you're not your own.
Now here's the amazing thing.
Somebody said this years ago, I remember reading in a book,
they said too many people in American Christianity today
want a savior but they don't want a Lord.
They don't want a master.
They want a savior.
So they want the I've been bought with a price
but they don't want the I'm not my own.
But you understand that there are one and the same.
If I'm bought with a price, I'm not my own, amen?
And so it cannot be that we simply want a savior
and say no, I don't want a Lord or master.
Jesus in fact said this, why call you me Lord, Lord
and do not the things that I say?
Well that's an indictment.
He says you're calling me Lord but yet you're not doing
the things that I say.
And so here the response of the people of God
here as James is writing to these individuals
in the first century but for us tonight in 2024
that we look at our lives and we make decisions
and no doubt each of us are faced with decisions
every day of our lives whether it's a decision
with regard to a job opportunity, a decision with regard
to a moving, a location, a residence, whatever it might be,
there are decisions that we make and we find in life
that sometimes it says man there are bigger decisions
and smaller decisions but understand that decisions
are going to be made and we must know the will of the Lord.
What does God want me to do?
What is God's will?
You know there are times in which God will not give you
a peace about a decision.
You ever been there before?
You feel like there's something you want to do
and God just doesn't give you a peace about it.
He doesn't give you that peace.
Oftentimes as I'm praying and seeking the Lord
and I say stuff like this to God and you can think
I'm crazy if you want but I'm just being honest
and transparent, I say God I'm just dumb
and I need to know real clear and plain
because I can't figure it out, amen.
Like just beat me over the head with a four by four
and make it clear and because I want to know
what the will of the Lord is and I pray that God
would give me peace in the decision.
That he'd give me peace.
No doubt you've been in a place where you've started
to make a decision and God just gave you an uneasiness
in your spirit, he didn't give you that peace.
And that's God communing with us and helping us
and you know what, I don't have a peace about this.
This isn't the direction that I need to go in.
This isn't the decision I need to make.
And so again the perspective, our response to the truth
that is given to us in this text of scripture
must be that we determine that we are,
we ought to seek the Lord.
What does God want me to do?
What is God's will with regard to this situation?
And then I make the decision based upon the will of God
and I live for the glory of God.
I live out the plan that God has for me.
It says that you ought to say if the Lord will,
we shall live and do this or that.
God has a will for your life, he has a will for my life,
he has a will for all of us.
For many, obviously for all of us that are saved tonight,
there are many things that we could say
are the consistent revealed will of God for all of us.
It's God's will for us to go to church, amen.
Somebody said are you gonna go to church
when I'm gonna pray about it?
You don't really need to pray about it.
God said go to church.
It's not something you pray about,
it's just a matter of obedience.
Then we go down the line and begin to see
should I take this job or this job?
There's no verse in God's word that's gonna tell you
what job you should take.
It's just not there.
But you seek the face of God.
You determine I wanna know the will of God.
God, would you give me wisdom?
Would you give me understanding?
Would you make it clear to me?
I want to be in the place where you want me to be.
I wanna do your will.
I don't wanna make the decision
based upon whatever these factors may be.
When I went to work at Sikorsky Aircraft Corporation,
I had another job offer on the table the same day
that was for about $20,000 more a year.
God gave me no peace for that job.
God gave me peace for the other job.
I don't know why.
If you look at it from a backup perspective,
you say man, that one's got more money,
it's got more opportunity, it's got,
but I don't know why God didn't give me a peace about it,
but he didn't, and God gave me a peace about this job,
that job at the time, 17 years ago now,
and that's where, that's how God led.
Sometimes we take the factors
on how we determine the decision-making process,
and we adopt a lot of the world's philosophies.
You ever hear somebody say put all the pros on one side
and all the cons on the other side?
That's how you make decisions?
Anyone ever hear somebody say that?
No, no, as a Christian, that's not how we make decisions.
We make decisions based on what is the will of God?
What does God want me to do?
We need to seek the Lord.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for your word.
Thank you for this wonderful counsel
that you give us in James,
and I pray that you'd help us, Lord.
Again, it's a familiar passage of scripture,
and we've considered the passage before
from other perspectives,
and focus on the brevity of life,
and it's there, and it's clear,
and God, we're thankful that you've given us that truth,
but I do pray that tonight you'd help us,
and we see in that 15th verse,
for that ye ought to say, if the Lord will,
we would do this or that.
Lord, I pray that you would help us to seek your face,
to seek your will.
Lord, that we would not use it as a cliche,
but that we would earnestly, sincerely desire
to know your will for our lives.
Help us to walk in obedience.
Help us, Lord, to evaluate
and to make adjustments that are needed.
Well, thank you for what you'll do.
For it's in Christ's name we pray, amen.
All right, on the back of the prayer bulletin,
anyone need a prayer bulletin before we?