8, we'll be looking at verses 7 through 15 this evening, and let me just read a couple
of the verses to you.
We'll get into the passage of Scripture that is before us this evening.
2 Kings 8, we'll be looking at verses 7 through 15.
The Bible says this in verse 7,
And Elisha came to Damascus, and Ben-Hadad the king of Syria was sick, and it was told
him, saying, The man of God is come hither.
As we continue to trace the steps of Elisha, we now find him in Damascus.
The city of Damascus is the capital of Syria.
It was located about 130 miles northeast of Jerusalem.
Of course, we understand that there was much interaction and work that took place during
the ministry of Elisha in the region of Samaria, which of course is north of Jerusalem as well.
But we find that he's now in Damascus.
During the time of studying the life of Elisha, in fact, even as we studied the life and ministry
of Elijah, we had the opportunity to see many interactions between the Syrians and the children
of Israel.
Of course, the name Ben-Hadad has become somewhat familiar to us as we've studied these passages
of Scripture, and we've read about the way in which the Syrians had laid siege against
the nation of Israel, against the city of Samaria, and we read that in great detail
in chapter 6 and chapter 7, the effects, the impact of that siege that was laid against
the people of Israel, the city of Samaria.
And so we have, of course, had several interactions with Ben-Hadad, the Syrians, and their interactions
with the children of Israel.
Ben-Hadad, the king of Syria, he had knowledge of Elisha.
In fact, we understand through the passages that we've studied—we'll reference some
of it back in chapter number 6 this evening in a little while—but we understand that
it was during that time in his life, in the life of Ben-Hadad, that there was some real
interaction between him and Elisha.
Of course, you'll recall that it was in that passage of Scripture that Elisha was telling
all of his secrets of all of his plans that he was making with regard to the military
campaign.
And so we find here that as we look at the passage of Scripture that is before us, that
this one, Ben-Hadad, the king of Syria, he is now made aware, he is informed of the fact
that the man of God, Elisha, has come to Damascus.
As we look at the passage of Scripture, I want you to notice first of all with me—well,
let me do this.
Let me read verse number 11.
The Bible says this,
"...and he settled his countenance steadfastly until he was ashamed," notice this,
"...and the man of God wept."
The title for this evening's message is simply—adopt it from verse number 11 of
our text—the man of God wept.
That being Elisha, of course, as we get through the passage this evening, we'll understand
why it was that he wept, the man of God wept.
If you're taking notes, number one, the condition of Ben-Hadad.
In verses 7 and 8, the Bible gives us, reveals to us, the condition of the king of Syria.
We notice immediately in verse number 7, the Bible says that Elisha came to Damascus
and Ben-Hadad, the king of Syria, was sick.
And it was told him, saying,
"...the man of God is come hither."
So we understand immediately, as we begin the passage of Scripture that is before us
this evening, we understand immediately that there is a physical ailment that Ben-Hadad
is dealing with.
He is sick.
He refers to it as a disease at the end of verse number 8,
"...shall I recover of this disease?"
We do not know all of the specifics and details as to what it is that Ben-Hadad is dealing
with, but we are aware of the fact that this condition is serious.
This sickness that he's dealing with is a serious condition.
It's one in which he's uncertain that he would recover from, one that might take him to the
grave.
We understand, as we'd study through the Scriptures and we'd see the references of Ben-Hadad
in other portions of Scripture, no doubt he was an elderly man at this point.
He'd been engaged in a number of battles and what have you.
And so we find that he has this sickness.
It's interesting that as we consider the condition of Ben-Hadad, that yes, we notice his physical
condition and the ailment that he's dealing with, but I also suggest to you this evening
that Ben-Hadad was not just sick, but he was seeking.
It's interesting to understand how at times, and really throughout Scripture, you see various
references of this, but we could even identify these things in our own lives, in the lives
of our loved ones, people that we've had interaction with through our lives.
But we understand that he is seeking.
He's seeking for answers.
He's in a position, if I could call it, of desperation because of this physical ailment
that he's dealing with.
And we find that it leads him to seek the man of God.
It's interesting as we would consider verse number 8, it says this, remember, he has just
been informed that the man of God has come hither.
In verse number 8, notice what the king says to his general, if you will, Haziel.
It says, and the king said unto Haziel, take a present in thine hand and go, meet the man
of God, and inquire of the Lord by him, saying, shall I recover of this disease?
We find that the condition of Ben-Hadad physically leads him to a place of seeking.
We find that he's made aware of the fact that the man of God has come, and so he calls immediately
for his general.
He calls for Haziel to come, and he says to take a present and to go and meet the man
of God.
It's interesting to me to really note the change in Ben-Hadad in this particular passage
of Scripture from when we last saw his interaction with Elisha.
You remember back in chapter number 6, I referred to it a moment ago, but in chapter number
6, in verses 8 down really through verse number 23, 24, you begin to see some things that
are happening here with the way in which the Syrians warred against the children of
Israel.
And the Bible tells us that as Ben-Hadad was making the plans, and he was setting up his
strategic moves for battle against the children of Israel, that it was Elisha that was informing
the king of Israel as to what the next move was, where they were going to be located,
and this thing caused much distress in the heart and soul of Ben-Hadad.
He was absolutely sure that there was a traitor in their midst.
Somebody was taking and revealing his military strategy to the king of Israel, to his enemy.
And in fact, Ben-Hadad says this at the end of verse number 11, "'Will you not show me
which of us is for the king of Israel?'
Of course, one of his servants comes and says, actually, none of us are for the king of Israel,
but here's what's happening, "'Elisha, the prophet that is in Israel, telleth the king
of Israel the words that thou speakest in thy bedchamber.'"
We studied this several weeks ago, and you'll remember that Ben-Hadad was not very pleased
with this development, and so what does he do?
He sends a great host of people to find out where Elisha is as he knew the location.
He sends them.
The Bible tells us that they go to Dothan.
Remember it was the servant of Elisha that went out early in the morning and saw the
great host of people, and Elisha said, don't worry, there's more for us than there are
for them.
And it was then that Elisha prayed that God would open the eyes of his servant and give
him that vision, and we find that Ben-Hadad, at that point, he did not have good feelings
toward Elisha.
He wanted to have Elisha captured from Dothan and brought back to him to be able to have
some interaction with him.
I'm sure it would not have been awfully polite and convenient.
But we find that now, at this particular stage, when this one Ben-Hadad is sick and nigh unto
death, he begins to have a change.
He's seeking.
And we notice the way in which he refers to Elisha.
In verse number 8 of our text of Scripture in 2 Kings 8, the Bible says that he says
to Haziel, take a present in thine hand and go, meet the man of God.
He then says this, inquire of the Lord by him, saying, shall I recover of this disease?
As we look at the way in which Ben-Hadad would refer to Elisha and the inquiries that would
be made of him, we understand, at least at some level, the impact that Elisha had made
in the life of this individual.
See, Ben-Hadad understood that Elisha was a man of God.
Ben-Hadad understood that Elisha served the Lord God of the universe.
You'll remember that during the life and ministry of Elisha, there were other interactions that
had taken place, and of course, there was Naaman that had gone, and that whole situation
with being a leper and all of the remarkable events that took place in 2 Kings 5.
There's no doubt Ben-Hadad, as he was the one that wrote the letter to the king of Israel
with regard to those things, and so now, at the end of his life, when he's dealing with
this sickness and we consider the condition of this one Ben-Hadad, I not only see him
as being sick, but I see him as seeking.
It's interesting to me.
look at this passage of Scripture,
I begin to consider the way in which people
seek even still today.
There are times that events come into the lives of individuals
that cause them to seek the Lord, that
cause them to look for some type of an answer.
The reality is that we have, I have
had the experience in my life, and I'm
sure that you've had the experiences in your life
where you've had opportunities to speak to people,
whether it's a co-worker, a family member, a neighbor,
whomever it may be, and you have opportunities
and you think it's not working, it's not effective,
they're not listening.
But it may just be that God might allow something
in the life of that individual that
will cause them to recognize that you're a child of God
and that they can seek some direction and counsel from you.
There are people that, when I worked in the corporate world,
there were people that would come
and they would have difficulties,
and they'd show up at my desk, people
that otherwise I'd never really had much interaction with,
and they'd come and they'd say, would you pray for me?
There's a situation they're dealing with.
There's something that's going on.
And they knew that this person was a Christian,
that they believed in the power of God,
that they believe that God answers prayer.
And the reality is that we find in Ben-Hadad
here in this passage of Scripture, yes, he's sick,
but it's led to seeking.
He finds out that, hey, Elisha's in Damascus.
And immediately, he says, Haziel, get a gift,
go meet the man of God, and inquire of him.
Find out, am I going to recover of this disease?
We not only notice the condition of Ben-Hadad,
but we notice the conversation with Haziel.
Haziel obeys the direction of King Ben-Hadad.
It says in verse 9, so Haziel went to meet him.
And so we find that he immediately
responds to the direction given to him
from his superior, from the king.
And it says that he took a present with him,
even of every good thing of Damascus.
Notice this, 40 camels' burden.
That's a large present.
I mean, that's significant.
And sometimes we can just kind of breeze over
some things in Scripture, you know,
you never really stop and consider.
But this is a serious present
that is being brought to Elisha.
Remember, the king said,
take a present in thine hand.
Well, he didn't take it in his hand.
He put it on 40 camels.
That's pretty significant.
And we find that the Bible says
that it was 40 camels' burden,
and came and stood before him and said,
notice what he says,
thy son, Ben-Hadad.
Isn't that interesting?
The way in which he refers to Ben-Hadad.
He doesn't say, the royal king of Syria, Ben-Hadad.
No, thy son, Ben-Hadad.
It says here, yes, that he is king of Syria.
But he notes first, thy son, Ben-Hadad, king of Syria,
hath sent me to thee saying,
shall I recover of this disease?
It was a simple request.
There's a conversation that takes place.
We find here in v. 10 specifically
the conversation at this point
between Elisha and Haziel
is a conversation regarding Ben-Hadad specifically.
And we find that in v. 9 and 10
that this conversation is in regard
to the king of Syria.
And it's a simple question.
Shall I recover of this disease?
Notice what it is that Elisha says in v. 10.
Elisha said unto him, go.
Say unto him, thou mayest certainly recover.
Howbeit, the Lord hath showed me
that he shall surely die.
And you might scratch your head and say,
what in the world?
What is going on?
Elisha says, thou mayest certainly recover.
Howbeit, the Lord hath showed me
that he shall surely die.
The reality is what Elisha is saying here
in this response to Haziel
is that it would not be the disease
that would kill the king.
See, we find as we go through the text of Scripture
that it would be Haziel that would kill Ben-Hadad.
It would not be the disease.
In fact, Ben-Hadad could have recovered
from this disease,
but Haziel would not permit it to be so
because he would take matters into his own hands
and he would kill Ben-Hadad.
We'll read of it in just a few verses.
And so we find that Elisha says to him
with regard to the conversation with Ben-Hadad,
he says, thou mayest certainly recover.
Howbeit, the Lord hath showed me
that he shall surely die.
Notice what Elisha does in v. 11.
It's interesting to read the verse of Scripture
and consider if you could put yourself
in the presence of these individuals
as they're having this conversation.
It says that he settled his countenance
steadfastly until he was ashamed.
The man of God wept.
It would appear as we look at v. 11
that Elisha stared at Haziel
until he was ashamed.
Just a period of silence.
We don't know how long.
But he just stared at Haziel.
He settled his countenance steadfastly
upon him until he was ashamed.
We find that the man of God, Elisha,
he begins to weep.
We begin to study through the passage
and we'll understand the cause
for which Elisha would weep
as it's revealed to us in v. 12.
Because it's here in v. 12
that Haziel says to Elisha,
why weepeth my Lord?
Some would think as you're reading through this
as you would consider the interaction,
as you consider the conversation
up to this particular point,
some may believe or think,
obviously as you read the whole text,
you wouldn't understand this,
but if you stopped here,
you might think that Elisha was weeping
because of the death of Ben-Hadad.
Or the knowledge of the fact
that Ben-Hadad would surely die.
But the reality is that the conversation
that he has with Haziel
that was dealing with specifically Ben-Hadad
now changes direction
and he begins to speak about Israel as a nation.
We find that in v. 12,
Elisha answers him and he answered.
Notice what he says,
because I know the evil that thou wilt do
unto the children of Israel.
We find that Elisha now turns
the direction of the conversation.
As he's speaking to Haziel,
he begins to share with him
the reason for which he's weeping.
He says it's because of the knowledge that I have.
And the knowledge that I have
is the evil that you, Haziel,
are going to do unto the children of Israel.
He describes it, he says,
their strongholds wilt thou set on fire.
And their young men wilt thou slay with the sword.
And wilt dash their children
and rip up their women with child.
Elisha had been given this knowledge from the Lord.
And Elisha knew the wickedness that Haziel would do
and for that reason, Elisha's weeping.
He had shared the information about Ben-Hadad.
The reason initially for the interaction
between Elisha and Haziel
was the condition of Ben-Hadad.
It was the whole reason that they're even meeting together.
We find that the conversation quickly changes
from Ben-Hadad to Haziel and the nation of Israel
in future events that would come to pass.
Haziel immediately responds to Elisha in v. 13.
He says, but what is thy servant? A dog?
That he should do this great thing?
And notice what Elisha answered.
The Lord hath showed me
that thou shalt be king over Syria.
So we find that here in v. 13,
the conversation that first began with Ben-Hadad specifically
and his condition turns to Israel as a whole
and the events that would happen in the near future.
And then we find it begins to deal specifically with Haziel
and his place of leadership there as being king of Syria.
You'll remember back in 1 Kings 19,
if you hold your place here in 2 Kings 8
and just quickly go back to 1 Kings 19,
and you'll remember that it was in this passage of scripture
that Elijah, excuse me,
had experienced in chapter number 18,
great victory over the worshipers of Baal
and all that had transpired in the fire that came from heaven.
But it was in chapter number 19
that he heard about the threat of Jezebel.
And he, of course, was overwhelmed.
And we find that God comes to Elijah
and He tells him that He has work for him to do.
In other words, God says to Elijah,
Elijah, I'm not done with you yet, Elijah.
And some of that which is said to him in verse number 15 of 1 Kings 19, the Lord said unto
him, Go, return on thy way to the wilderness of Damascus.
And when thou comest, anoint Hazael to be king over Syria.
And Jehu, the son of Nimshi, shalt thou anoint to be king over Israel.
And Elisha, the son of Shaphat of Abel-meholah, shalt thou anoint to be prophet in thy room.
Just in the next few verses, you begin to see the appointment of Elisha and of course
the calling and all that took place.
We studied that many months ago.
But you'll see here that Hazael, Elijah had been given that prophecy back in 1 Kings 19.
And now it's time for this one, Hazael, he's now going to be the king of Syria.
And God says through the prophet Elisha, he says, the Lord hath showed me that thou shalt
be king over Syria.
So he, Hazael, back in 2 Kings 8, look at verse number 14, the Bible says that he departed
from Elisha.
Notice he came to his master who said to him, what said Elisha to thee?
Can you, in your mind's eye, can you see the spirit, if you will, of Ben-Hadad awaiting
an answer?
I mean, you consider, as we mentioned at the beginning of our message this evening, the
condition of this man, and you consider what he was dealing with in this disease, and he
sent Hazael, he knew that Elisha was there, he had been informed that the man of God had
come hither, and we find that there was some level of anxiety, if you will, anxiousness
on waiting the return of Hazael, what's the answer that I'm going to receive?
And we find that immediately in verse number 14, upon Hazael returning from his conversation
with Elisha, the man of God, the servant of the Lord, that Ben-Hadad immediately, what
said Elisha to thee?
He wants to know, what is the word from the man of God?
He answered, he told me that thou shouldest surely recover.
Now, is that the whole message?
No.
It's not the whole message.
In fact, Elisha said, thou mayest certainly recover, how be it the Lord hath showed me
that he shall surely die.
It would not be the disease, however, that would take the life of Ben-Hadad, it would
be Hazael, the thought of becoming the king of Syria and all that would go along with
that.
And we find that here, after he gives them this false report in verse number 15, it says
it came to pass, notice these words, on the morrow.
I mean, Hazael didn't waste any time.
The Bible says that he took a thick cloth and dipped it in water and spread it on his
face so that he died, and Hazael reigned in his stead.
It's interesting as we look at the passage of Scripture and we see the condition of Ben-Hadad
and we obviously have made point already this evening, not only of his sickness, but of
his seeking, it reminds me tonight of how important it is to be that faithful witness,
to be the faithful, the salt and the light that the Lord's called us to be.
Because we just never know when something's going to take place in somebody's life that's
going to cause them to seek for some amount of truth.
See, we can interact with people in such a way that we can be assured that when they
have a time of trouble in their lives, we will not be the person they call.
What do I mean by that?
We can be ugly and nasty and we can be rude and forward and unkind and we can have the
wrong disposition and we can tell people some things that we probably shouldn't tell
them that will turn them off and they will probably never contact us.
But if we have a proper spirit, if we try to show them the love of Christ, there are
times in which I've said to people when we've gone out door knocking, we've not been able
to do it in a while because of all that's going on, how I long to be able to interact
with people and not have to be so concerned about if I'm sharing some kind of germ with
them or them with me and all of that sort of thing.
But the reality is that we're in that position now.
But I've often said that we've had people that have rejected us, I've had more people
to reject than have received.
But here's my goal in every situation is to leave an open door of opportunity.
My prayer is that we can leave a gospel tract on somebody's door, in somebody's hand, we
can leave a word of witness and when they deal with that time of heartache, when they
deal with that disappointment and that discouragement, when they deal with the death of a loved one,
whatever the tragedy might be, that they would recall there was somebody that showed me kindness
and love and genuine concern.
How many times have we said to people, listen, the reality is that I'm not trying to gain
anything by sharing the gospel.
I'm trying to obey the Lord first and foremost and number two, I'm trying to keep you from
going to the lake of fire.
Amen.
And the reality is that we seek to be able to have another opportunity.
Not only may we personally have another opportunity, but what about the Christian that comes behind
us?
Listen, I've been in situations and scenarios where the Christian that went in front of
me did a poor job and caused me great grief on trying to reach somebody with the gospel
of Jesus Christ.
Why?
Because the person that had interaction with them before that was a Christian left a bad
taste in their mouth.
The way that they treated them, the words that they said, so on and so forth.
I'm thankful that though Elisha at just a few chapters before, several years perhaps
earlier could be viewed by Ben-Hadad as Elisha's the enemy.
He's telling the secrets.
He's given the intel to the king of Israel.
Go get him.
And they send this great host to Dothan to take Elisha and to bring him back.
But at the time of his dark hour, he hears that Elisha has come hither, and what does
he say?
Go to the man of God.
Inquire of him.
Take a gift with you, but inquire of the Lord by him saying, shall I recover of this disease?
I hope that we would understand that great truth from verses 7 and 8 and really the approach
of Elisha.
Then as we consider the latter part of the text of Scripture and we think about this
situation which caused the man of God, Elisha, to weep, I want you to understand that this
prophecy that is given that these things will come to pass just as the man of God said.
He mentioned in verse number 12, because I know the evil that thou wilt do unto the children
of Israel, their strongholds wilt thou set on fire, and their young men wilt thou slay
with the sword, and wilt dash their children and rip up their women with child.
It caused the man of God to weep.
Turn over, if you will, to chapter number 10.
Look at what the Bible tells us.
Remember, at the end of our passage of Scripture there in verse number 15, Hazael began to
reign.
It says that he reigned in his stead.
In chapter 10 of 2 Kings in verse number 32, the Bible says, in those days the Lord began
to cut Israel short, and Hazael smote them in all the coast of Israel, from Jordan eastward,
all the land of Gilead, the Gadites, the Reubenites, the Manassites, from Aror, which is by the
river Arnon, even Gilead and Bashan.
If you're studying with us the book of Joshua and you're on track with the lessons that
we're doing, you'll see that this is the inheritance for the two and a half tribes on the east
side of Jordan, the tribe of Reuben, Gad, and the half tribe of Manasseh.
And that's what's being referenced here specifically as to how Hazael smote them in the coast of
Israel.
Turn again over to chapter number 13, if you will.
A little lengthier portion of Scripture to understand exactly all that was taking place.
Notice in verse number 1 of chapter 13, in the three and twentieth year of Joash the
son of Ahaziah, king of Judah, Jehoahaz the son of Jehu began to reign over Israel in
Samaria and reign 17 years.
He did that which was evil in the sight of the Lord and followed the sins of Jeroboam
the son of Nebat, which made Israel to sin, he departed not therefrom.
The anger of the Lord was kindled against Israel and he delivered them into the hand
of Hazael king of Syria, and in the hand of Ben-Hadad the son of Hazael all their days.
And Jehoahaz besought the Lord and the Lord hearkened unto him, for he saw the oppression
of Israel, notice, because the king of Syria oppressed them, that's Hazael.
It says in verse number 5, and the Lord gave Israel a savior so that they went out from
under the hand of the Syrians and the children of Israel dwelt in their tents as before time.
Nevertheless, they departed not from the sins of the house of Jeroboam who made Israel sin
but walked therein and there remained the grove also in Samaria, that's the parenthetical
there in verses 5 and 6.
Notice in v. 7,
"...neither did he leave of the people
to Jehoahaz, but fifty horsemen,
and ten chariots, and ten thousand footmen,
for the king of Syria had destroyed them
and had made them like the dust by threshing."
Look at v. 22,
"...Yet Haziel, king of Syria, oppressed Israel
all the days of Jehoahaz."
Yes, indeed, it was the wickedness
of the children of Israel,
the sin of the children of Israel
that would bring these things to pass,
but we find that Elisha, the man of God,
he knew.
He had been given the information
from the Lord God of the universe.
We find that the Bible tells us
that the man of God wept.
What caused him to weep?
That which he knew was going to happen.
Now, we understand that these things
would transpire in just a short period of time
in the history of Israel.
We can read them now on this side of the history
to see how they came to pass.
To see how Haziel, as the king of Syria,
brought these things upon the children of Israel
and the destruction in which he wrought.
Can I tell you that today,
if we could make application for us
with regard to these things,
and we understand that this is
the historical context in which
it's being dealt with,
but can I tell you that there are some future events
that you and I know about?
God's given us His Word with regard to eschatology.
Amen?
What's eschatology?
The study of future things.
We know that as we read the New Testament,
in fact, reading the Old Testament,
some of the prophecies that are contained therein
with regard to the prophetic events
and the prophetic calendar,
and you read those coupled with the New Testament,
you read the book of Revelation,
listen, we know some things that are going to happen.
You've read about the tribulation, haven't you?
We know what's going to happen.
We know the destruction.
The devastation.
I'm thankful as a child of God
that I won't be here to experience it.
Amen?
But there are some people that you know
and there are some people that I know
that are not saved.
They're not part of the church.
They're not going to be raptured out of here.
Worse than that, however,
is what we read in the book of Revelation
in the 20th chapter
with regard to the great white throne judgment.
You say, pastor, why are we making this application?
Because the man of God wept
because he knew of some physical things
that were going to happen,
some destruction that was going to come
in the hand of Haziel.
Can I tell you that when you read
Revelation 20,
it ought to cause you as a child of God to weep.
To understand that the Bible tells us
that the dead, small and great,
they stand before God.
The books are opened.
They're judged out of what book?
The book of life.
And whosoever is not found written therein
was cast in the lake of fire.
This is the second death.
If you read Revelation 20, verses 11-15,
it will break your heart.
It ought to cause us to weep.
Because every single person
that does not trust the Lord Jesus Christ
as their personal Savior
will stand at that great white throne judgment.
And based upon the authority of the Word of God,
they will be cast in the lake of fire.
Just as these events that are recorded here
would cause the man of God to weep.
I wonder tonight,
what would it be that would cause us to weep?
What would it be to cause us to
understand the reality
of what God has revealed to us
is going to come to pass?
It's not a possibility.
It's a certainty.
We understand that.
We believe that.
These things that had been revealed to Elisha,
they were not but a possibility.
He knew that it was certain
because God had revealed it to him.
And it caused him to weep.
And I just wonder this evening,
when we look at the big picture of things
and we begin to understand
all of what God has given us,
and the knowledge that He has given us,
what He's revealed to us
with regard to not only the end times,
but the great white throne judgment,
I wonder how does it impact me?
I wonder how does it impact
each one of God's people?
Does it cause us to have
a broken heart?
Does it cause us to weep?
To think about people that we know,
that we interact with.
I understand that we can't make everybody trust Christ.
And I wish sometimes we could.
Don't you?
We can't. It's not possible.
It's a decision they have to make.
But I can be a faithful witness.
I can have a broken heart.
I can go forth bearing precious seed
with tears, right?
And I see the man of God, Elisha,
in this passage of Scripture,
weeping over some events
that are going to take place.
His second death, by the way,
is of serious nature.
This evening, the man of God wept.
Father, we love You.
We thank You for loving us.
We thank You for the testimony of Elisha
and the way in which he was able to have interaction
with Ben-Hadad.
And though at times, no doubt,
Ben-Hadad probably would have liked
to have seen Elisha dead,
we find that in his last moments,
Ben-Hadad sent to inquire
the man of God.
We thank You for the testimony, influence, and impact
that Elisha had.
And Lord, as we think about this conversation
that took place
and the specifics of the conversation,
and we think about the man of God, Elisha, weeping,
we understand what caused him to weep.
We see as recorded history
how those events in fact did come to pass.
God, I wonder tonight
when the last time is that we have wept
because of those things which You've given us,
the knowledge that we have.
When Elisha was asked by Haziel,
why are you weeping?
He said, because I know.
There's some things that we know
as Your people
that cause us to rejoice greatly.
There's some things that we know as Your people
that should cause us to weep.
God, I pray that You'd help us
with a heart of compassion
to obey Your commandment
to preach the gospel to every creature.
Help us, Lord.
We'll thank You for it.
In Christ's name we pray,
Amen.