Kimberly, they'll be leaving bright and early.
Actually, it'll be dark when you leave tomorrow morning,
but we use the expression bright and early.
Their flight leaves real early tomorrow morning,
so you pray for them.
Of course, as we've mentioned several times
here in the last week, brother Sommerdorf's dad,
so Kimberly's grandfather,
went home to be with the Lord last week,
and so the funeral is on Friday,
and so if you would pray for the Sommerdorf family.
My great aunt passed away yesterday,
and I got the information today,
and I was told that for years, unknown to me,
for years, she has said that she wants me
to preach her funeral, and I found that out today.
I found out she died yesterday, and I found out today,
and so I'm assuming on Saturday,
I'm gonna be making a trip up to New Jersey
to preach a funeral for my great aunt,
and if you would pray for that, I would appreciate it,
and we got a number of family members that are not saved,
a number of family members that come together for funerals,
as perhaps many of you have that same situation,
and I'll preach the gospel.
She was a lady that I believe,
through conversation with her,
she knew the Lord as her Savior,
so we're thankful for that,
but I know we have a lot of family members
that do not know the Lord as their Savior,
and so we certainly would appreciate your prayers
with regard to that.
First Thessalonians chapter number five this evening.
First Thessalonians chapter number five,
and be looking at verse number 15.
Of course, over the last several weeks,
this is actually lesson number eight,
as we have studied through this very concise,
yet applicable instruction that God gives
to the church at Thessalonica
at the end of this particular letter.
Again, the end of chapter number three of the second letter,
we find another list of bullet point instruction,
if you will, and we've gone through each Wednesday evening
looking at these pieces of instruction
as we've sought to be able to apply
this truth in our lives.
The Christian life, we know,
must be lived through the power of the Holy Spirit.
You try to live the Christian life in your own flesh,
your own power, it's gonna be frustrating,
and this is the truth that God did not design
that we would live the Christian life
in our own flesh, in our own power.
Remember, Jesus said in John 15,
without me, ye can do nothing,
and it's very interesting how often we find in the scriptures
that God instructs us to not do certain things
that would be natural to do in our flesh,
and so he instructs us not to do those things,
and then there are things that God instructs us to do
that naturally we don't wanna do in our flesh,
and why do we find those instructions?
Well, because God says this is what pleases me,
and so he instructs us accordingly,
and then we understand that we must live in dependence
on the Lord and the power of the Holy Spirit
in order to do the work that God has called us to do.
We must die to self, we must walk in the Spirit.
It is imperative that we are emptied of self
so that we can be filled with the Holy Spirit of God.
You're not gonna be, we understand the truth,
the teaching that we are indwelled with the Spirit of God
at the moment of salvation,
but understand, though we received all of the Holy Spirit
at the moment of salvation that we'll ever have,
the reality is that he doesn't have all of you
or all of me on any given day,
and so we must yield ourselves,
we must be dead to self, emptied of self
so that we can be filled with the Holy Spirit.
We find here in 1 Thessalonians 5 and verse 15,
notice the Bible says this.
See that none render evil for evil unto any man,
but ever follow that which is good,
both among yourselves and to all men.
Hold your place here and turn to the book of Romans,
if you will, Romans chapter 12.
I wanna take a look at the instruction
that is given here in Romans chapter number 12
that really is a sister passage of scripture
with what we've just read in 1 Thessalonians 5.
Notice in Romans 12, beginning in verse number 17,
notice what the Bible says.
Recompense to no man evil for evil.
Provide things honest in the sight of all men.
If it be possible, as much as lieth in you,
live peaceably with all men.
Notice 19, dearly beloved, avenge not yourselves,
but rather give place unto wrath,
for it is written, vengeance is mine,
I will repay, saith the Lord.
Therefore, if thine enemy hunger, feed him.
If he thirst, give him drink.
For in so doing, thou shalt heap coals of fire on his head.
Verse 21, be not overcome of evil,
but overcome evil with good.
This is not natural.
It's not natural for your flesh or for my flesh,
but we find that the Lord gives us this instruction,
and as he gives us this instruction,
it reveals to us how desperately we need the Lord
in order to fulfill the instruction that he's provided.
Notice with me, I wanna mention two portions
of scripture principles, if you will,
from the book of Proverbs,
and then we'll get back to 1 Thessalonians chapter five.
Turn over very quickly, if you will, to Proverbs 24,
and look at verse number 29 with me,
Proverbs 24 and verse number 29.
The Bible says here, say not, I will do so to him
as he hath done to me.
I will render to the man according to his work.
You find in chapter 25, maybe on the same page there
as Proverbs 24, verse 29, but in chapter 25
and verse number 21, notice what the Bible says.
If thine enemy be hungry, give him bread to eat,
and if he be thirsty, give him water to drink.
Does it sound like Romans chapter 12?
We just read it a moment ago.
Sounds awfully similar.
Verse 22, for thou shalt heap coals of fire upon his head,
and the Lord shall reward thee.
As we look at these portions of scripture
and turn back to 1 Thessalonians chapter five,
and we find that God is giving this instruction
to this local church, and he says,
see that none render evil for evil unto any man,
but ever follow that which is good,
both among yourselves and to all men.
No doubt in our lives, and maybe you experience this
personally before you trust that Christ is your Savior,
and we see it as we live life,
there are people that have the idea,
I'll do good to you as long as you do good to me,
and if you do evil to me, I'll do evil to you,
and it's kind of like that situation.
That's not how God has instructed believers to live,
and we find in this portion of scripture,
I'm gonna use a title from the verse
over in Romans chapter number 12, verse 21,
the title overcome evil with good.
Overcome evil with good.
I notice two principles here,
really we're gonna look at these tonight,
and I hope that as we make application
that we'd be challenged in our walk with the Lord,
remember the title for this entire series
is Walk Worthy, Please God,
and so we notice number one, if you're taking notes,
a principle of grace, a principle of grace.
He says, see that none render evil for evil unto any man.
No doubt the people, the church members
of the church at Thessalonica,
as they interacted with people in the society,
we've already talked about the way
in which they suffered persecution,
and they were dealing with all sorts of things,
and no doubt they had interactions with people
where people treated them wrong.
And here, the Lord, the Holy Spirit of God
is the author of scripture.
He says, see that none render evil for evil,
notice, unto any man.
We find that the word see is an interesting word
for it really carries with it the idea
in this particular context of looking
at this verse of scripture is take heed.
In fact, the same Greek word is translated take heed
in Matthew 18 in verse number 10.
We're not gonna turn over there.
It's a different, it doesn't have anything to do
with this lesson this evening,
but we see that the word is translated that way.
And so the idea as we look at verse 15,
why is it that we need to be careful?
Why is it that we need to take heed?
Well, I believe the reason is because your flesh
desires to react in a certain way.
And my flesh desires to react in a certain way.
Someone said this as I was considering
and looking through things here.
It says if somebody punches you,
the first thing you wanna do is punch them back.
Right, we all can relate and understand that.
And so we need to take heed.
We need to, as it says here,
see that none render evil for evil unto any man.
Your flesh has a desire to react in situations
in a certain way.
And we find that as we look at this portion of Scripture
and with God's help, we can be gracious.
Again, it's a principle of grace,
and we can respond as opposed to reacting.
And see, there's always a situation
when you deal with things in life,
when I deal with things in life,
are we reacting to that thing
or are we responding to that thing?
There's a difference between reacting and responding.
And we find this evening that here,
this principle of grace where he says,
see that none render evil for evil unto any man.
We are to be gracious.
In fact, we find that even in our speech,
Paul encourages the believers in Colossae
that they're to let their speech be,
what, it's supposed to be gracious,
seasoned with salt, right?
He says in Colossians 4 and verse number six,
let your speech be always with grace.
If we'd examine our speech,
if we would listen to the things that we say,
no doubt there are times in which our speech
is not always with grace.
And we're to be gracious.
I've heard people say I want to give him a piece of my mind and I'll jokingly respond
make sure it's not the last piece.
And the reality is that we need to always, as he says in Colossians 4 and verse 6, speak
with grace.
Let me say this tonight, to be gracious is to be like Jesus.
To overcome evil with good is to be like the Lord.
Do you remember what Jesus endured when he was going to the cross of Calvary?
Do you remember all that he suffered?
And yes we understand as he suffered and he bled and died he was paying for our sin but
we understand that as he was reviled he reviled not again.
We find that the Lord Jesus Christ he said this, Father forgive them for they know not
what they do.
Can you imagine the grace?
We understand that our God is gracious and as his people we too are to be gracious.
Look over if you will to 1 Peter chapter number 2, I referenced a portion of one of the verses
here that we're going to look at in 1 Peter chapter number 2.
But notice with me beginning in verse number 21 as we think about this principle of grace,
this principle of grace.
You know God's people are to be gracious people.
I'm thankful that we serve a gracious God and that we have received grace and then we
too are to give grace, we're to be gracious.
In 1 Peter 2 and verse 21, notice what the Bible says, for even here unto were ye called.
Because Christ also suffered for us.
Notice what it says, leaving us an example that ye should follow his steps.
Now if it ended there we could say yes as we examine the life of Christ we understand
that he left us an example, there's so many things we could study within the life of Christ
and say what an example that is to us.
But we find that the Holy Spirit of God in this portion of scripture zeroes into something
specifically with regard to the example that he's speaking of.
Notice in verse 22, who did no sin, neither was guile found in his mouth.
We understand the just for the unjust as he'll say in chapter number 3.
We find that it says this in verse 23, who when he was reviled, reviled not again.
When he suffered he threatened not, but committed himself to him that judgeth righteously.
You know so often if we're not careful as we live in this world and we deal with individuals
and we have interactions and we deal with hardships and difficulties, we can be tempted
to respond in the flesh because we want to get even, we want to get back this idea maybe
if you could look at this portion of scripture with the thought of one that would be seeking
revenge.
And yet we find that the Holy Spirit of God so often as he's speaking to his people in
the New Testament, as he's giving us the word of God, he's writing to us and he's giving
us instruction that at the face value we look at it and say how in the world could
I do this?
Well you can't apart from the power of the Holy Spirit of God.
And Christians are to be different.
You know I think that's one of the problems that we have in America today is that so many
Christians have, Christians quote unquote because probably a lot of them aren't even
saved people, but they've so assimilated to the world and they want to be accepted by
the world, they don't want to ruffle any feathers so to speak, that there's no difference.
They don't see any difference in our behavior.
I was sent some email or I was sent some videos and I saw them and I talked to a pastor friend
about one of them yesterday, but I was given some videos of some quote unquote churches
in America that a couple of weeks ago on Super Bowl Sunday, some of the things that happened
in their churches in the name of Christianity, it was absolutely appalling.
It was blasphemous.
They were literally kicking a Bible on the platform like it was a football.
That's unbelievable to me.
We're called to be different.
What did Jesus say in Matthew 5?
Look if you do good to those that do good to you, like even the publicans do that.
Publicans are to be different.
And so he says, see that none render evil for evil unto any man.
You want to see just how alive your flesh is?
Let somebody treat you wrong, amen?
And you're going to find out in a hurry how alive that old man can be revived, amen?
You let somebody treat you wrong and it's amazing.
You can, I'm telling you, I've experienced, you can be walking in the spirit, you can
be singing the sweet songs from our hymnal and just rejoicing in the Lord, and then somebody
does something and man that old man is just like, bam.
I mean he's alive and well, but we're to crucify him.
We cannot do this in our own power.
The instruction that we find is instruction that helps us recognize how desperately we
need the Lord.
He said, and we'll look at it in John 15, we'll look at the two verses at the end, but
without me you can do nothing.
Notice a principle of grace, notice number two as we look at the remainder of the verse
of Scripture in 1 Thessalonians 5 and verse 15, a pursuit of good.
A pursuit of good, notice what he says, but ever follow that, which is good, literally
the idea of follow that is pursuing after, and so he says, but ever follow that which
is good.
Then he says this, both among yourselves, remember who's he writing to, he's writing
to the church at Thessalonica, so among yourselves, but then notice he says, and to all men.
And so we are to be doing good, not only doing good, but pursuing good.
The word good, it carries with it that idea of that which is upright, that which is honorable.
How do we determine what is good?
Is it for your determination?
Am I the standard?
No, God is the standard.
And when we understand that we're pursuing and we're seeking to do that which is right,
that which is upright and honorable, that which is pleasing to God, he says that we're
to do good, we're to follow after, but ever follow that which is good, both among yourselves
and to all men.
Looking, again, not only doing what's good, but pursuing good.
And notice he says, not only among yourselves, but to all men.
So we see this principle of grace that we find at the beginning of chapter 5 and verse
number 15, see that none render evil for evil unto any man, but then we see this pursuit
of good, and we understand, remember the Lord Jesus Christ during his earthly ministry,
one man comes to him and calls him good.
He says, why callest thou me good?
And we find this evening that we live in a society where they call evil good and good
evil.
We understand that.
The prophets speak of that, and no doubt we live in that situation.
I had to be on the phone today with someone from Fairfax County, and I said, so and so,
with all due respect, I want to make a comment that I do not want you to respond to, because
I wasn't trying to get them in trouble.
But what they were telling me was absolutely ludicrous.
And I said, what you're telling me is you're violating our constitutional rights to live
out our faith.
It's bizarre.
But we're to do good.
We're to do good.
God determines what is good.
We live in a society that is upside down.
I mean, they don't have the right moral code.
And we find that as we go to God's Word, we can't be influenced by the society, by the
culture.
We can't say, well, everyone else is doing it.
You ever hear somebody say that?
Your kids want to do something, and you say, well, why do you want to do that?
Well, everyone else is doing it.
I remember with our children, because it was said to me, they said, well, if, my parents
said, if your brother jumps off a bridge, are you going to jump off a bridge?
I don't know if any of you heard that when you were growing up or said that to your children.
So, I said that to Joseph one day, and he says, with all sincerity, he says, yes.
And I said, Joseph, if your sister jumps off the bridge, are you going to jump off the
bridge too?
And he's like, yes.
I said, bud, did you understand the question?
He says, yes.
She's going to need help, so I'm going to try to help her.
And I thought, well, that just fell apart on me.
I mean, it's just terrible, right?
Like, what do you say?
But we notice when God says that we're to pursue that which is good ever, but ever follow
that which is good, don't allow the society in which we're living where everyone else
is doing it, and it just seems to be accepted.
Maybe even people within churches, those that call themselves believers and Christians,
they're doing these things and say, well, I guess it's okay.
No, no.
We need to go to God and figure out what's good.
Live accordingly.
I said this, to be gracious is to be like Jesus.
Let me say this, to do good is to be like Jesus.
Notice in Acts chapter 10, if you will, in Acts chapter number 10, we find that we pick
ourselves up in this portion of Scripture where Peter is preaching.
Why is he preaching?
Well, because Cornelius had a vision,
and in that vision, Cornelius is told to send for Peter,
and Peter at the same time is having that vision, right?
He's hungry and he has this vision,
and God instructs him to go with these
that would come to the house, and we find that he does,
and as he finds himself there,
the Bible tells us, as they enter in Caesarea
in verse number 24, that Cornelius waited for them
and had called together his kinsmen and near friends.
I mean, this is an awesome opportunity.
Cornelius is gonna hear, listen,
the angel could not tell Cornelius how to be saved.
All the angel could do was tell Cornelius
where he had to go in order to get the true message,
and so Peter comes, and we find that as he arrives,
there's this crowd here that's gathered,
and the introduction has gone on.
Notice, if you will, pick it up with me
in verse number 33, immediately therefore I sent to thee,
this is Cornelius speaking,
and thou hast well done that thou art come.
He's talking to Peter.
He says at the end of verse 33,
now therefore are we all here present before God
to hear all things that are commanded thee of God.
Then Peter opened his mouth.
What an easy sermon to preach.
I mean, honestly, Cornelius has done all the work
to gather all the people and said,
we're here to hear what you have to say,
and he opens his mouth and begins to preach,
and what does he begin to preach?
He begins to preach about the Lord Jesus Christ.
By the way, that's our message, preaching Christ.
Amen?
We find that he says this.
Notice, I'm gonna jump right in the middle of his message.
He then gets into the death, burial, and resurrection,
but notice in verse 38,
a pursuit of good is our thought
from 1 Thessalonians 5, 15.
I said to do good is to be like Jesus.
Notice in verse 38 how God anointed Jesus of Nazareth
with the Holy Ghost and with power
who went about doing good
and healing all that were oppressed of the devil,
for God was with him, and we are witnesses of all things,
which he did both in the land of the Jews
and in Jerusalem, who they slew
and hanged on a tree.
Him, God raised up the third day and showed him openly,
and so we see that he preaches the gospel,
but notice in verse 38, he says,
who went about doing good.
Who went about doing good.
The instruction there in 1 Thessalonians
is that we're to ever follow that which is good,
that we're to be pursuing good.
You're only gonna determine what is good
as you dig into God's word and you decide
that God will have the authority and the standard
for determining what is good and right,
that which is upright and honorable.
How is it that we're to live,
and what is it that we're to do
in this perverse generation in which we live?
We live in a crooked and perverse generation.
Paul said that to the believers in Philippi.
And so we find that we live in that situation,
but we're to shine as lights in a dark place,
and that's what we're to do.
And so we find that here, Paul is giving this instruction
of the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God
to the church at Thessalonica,
and he says there's this principle of grace
and there's this pursuit of good,
and we find that in both of those truths
that are given in verse 15 of chapter five,
that really what Paul is saying
to the believers in Thessalonica
and what God is saying to us tonight
is that we're to be like Jesus.
That's not what Christians are supposed to be.
Why were they first called Christians in Antioch?
Well, because they were like Christ.
And we find that we as Christians,
someone said this, I like your Christ,
but I don't like your Christians.
He went on to say this,
the reason why he made that statement
is because your Christians are nothing like your Christ.
Now that's a heavy indictment, is it not?
He said, I like your Christ, but not your Christians.
Why?
Because your Christians are nothing like your Christ.
We've lost our way, we've lost our identity.
If we're standing up on a platform,
kicking a Bible around,
and that would never happen here, I understand that,
and I think for all of us that are here this evening,
that if you found yourself in a church like that
on a Sunday morning by accident,
I hope you would get up and walk out, amen?
But the reality is that there are,
this is happening all around America.
It's sickening.
You know, it's interesting, C.H. Spurgeon said this,
and C.H. Spurgeon, I don't know, 150 years ago roughly,
somewhere in that ballpark,
and so C.H. Spurgeon said this,
what's happening too often,
it was a downgrade controversy,
you can read about it, all this stuff that's going on,
but he made this statement, he wrote an article about it,
really a great statement,
and once thought what was happening,
he said, the church is entertaining the goats.
If it was true then, oh, how it's become true today.
And you know, there are these churches that think,
well, we have a big crowd.
So what?
It's not about the number of people.
It's about, listen, God is the one
that determines how we worship, amen?
Not everything that's called worship today is worship.
He said you're to worship me in spirit and in truth.
And he is a holy, reverent God.
What happened when the boys tried to offer
some strange fire in the Old Testament?
They died.
What happened when they decided
they were gonna move the ark on the cart
and Uzzah's gonna hold it?
What happens?
He dies, right?
We serve a holy God.
We have to enter into his presence accordingly.
And so what Paul is saying is that we're to live like Jesus.
We're to be like Jesus.
Because to be gracious is to be like our Savior.
To do good is to be like our Savior.
And so look in John chapter 15.
I said we'd finish here and I want you to notice.
We're gonna read five verses
and then we'll be done this evening.
We'll get into our prayer time.
In John 15 and verse number one,
no doubt you're familiar with the portion of Scripture,
but I think it's important that we read it
and we get it just solidified in our minds
once again this evening.
Jesus says, I am the true vine.
My father's the husbandman.
Every branch in me that beareth not fruit,
he taketh away.
And every branch that beareth fruit,
he purgeth it, that it may bring forth more fruit.
Now you're clean through the word
which I have spoken unto you.
Abide in me and I in you.
Notice that the branch cannot bear fruit of itself
except it abide in the vine.
No more can he except you abide in me.
We understand this from a physical perspective.
How many of you, well, I don't wanna have you
raise your hands because maybe you get in trouble,
but some people probably bought flowers
for their spouse on Valentine's Day.
And you bought those flowers
and man, they were probably beautiful
when you picked them up and you took them home
and they looked real nice.
But today, a week later, they probably don't look as nice.
Maybe you've already had to throw them out.
Maybe you got them from somewhere
where they just didn't last
as long as you'd hoped that they'd last.
Why is it that they die?
Why do the petals fall off?
Why do they droop over and turn colors?
Well, because they've been severed, right?
They've been cut from the source,
the vine that gives them life.
So you can change the water, you can put the food in,
you can do all the stuff that you wanna do,
but it's gonna just be short-lived.
So Jesus uses this illustration,
it'll be very easy for people to understand and relate to,
and he says in verse number five,
I am the vine, ye are the branches.
By the way, it's a good thing for us
to recognize and remember our place.
We are not the vine, he is the vine.
Sometimes we think we're the ones
that are in control of my life, I'm gonna do,
no, no, we're just the branch, he is the vine.
He is the vine, and he says this,
he that abideth in me and I in him,
the same bringeth forth much fruit,
for without me ye can do nothing.
You know what I fear?
I fear that a lot of people really don't believe that verse.
I fear that a lot of people actually think
they can do a lot of things without God.
I really do.
But can I tell you this evening,
it's only by God's grace
that you can even take your next breath.
Only by his grace you can take your next breath.
Our God is gracious, our God is a good God.
He went about doing good.
So what is Paul saying in verse 15
of 1 Thessalonians chapter number five?
Well, we must die to self.
It's absolutely imperative that we're filled
with the spirit of God, that we do as Paul said,
I am crucified with Christ, I die daily,
so that we might walk in the spirit
because I cannot do the work
that God has called me to do in my own flesh.
It's not natural.
And so he says we're to be like Christ,
we're to be like Jesus.
He left us an example, according to 1 Peter 2,
that we should follow his steps.
And those that named the name of Christ
were to be different, were to behave differently.
People were able to see our lives
and to see how we live,
to see that we can overcome evil with good.
I often, as I think about this truth
in 1 Thessalonians five and verse 15,
and also there in Romans chapter 12,
I often think about David
as David was being continually hunted by Saul.
And Saul, the Bible says, made David his enemy continually.
There were opportunities that David had
where he could have taken the life of Saul.
Saul. There are opportunities that David had where actually others said they would take
the life of Saul. And David says, I'm going to leave it in God's hands. His day will
come that he goes into battle. Did that happen? Absolutely. And guess what? David didn't
have any blood on his hands. Because David took that high road. David's not perfect.
But I think about David in the context of this. Because though Saul made David his enemy
continually, David never really looked at Saul as being his enemy. He said, who have
you come out to fight? A dead dog? What's he saying? Like, I'm not going to fight you.
I'm not going to take your life. And when he did cut off part of the garment of Saul,
after he calls and shows that he could have taken his heart, he was convicted over that.
What a great picture for us tonight. And so we're to see that no man render evil for evil
to any man. We're to ever follow after that which is good. Not only among ourselves, but
to all men. Principle of grace and a pursuit of good. Really, boil it all down, it's just
to be like Jesus. Let's pray. Father, we love You. We thank You for loving us. Thank You
for Your many blessings. Thank You for the instruction that You give us. And Lord, I
pray that in the simplicity of the instruction, as far as understanding it, Lord, that we'd
apply it. That we would determine that we will live like Christ. Understanding that
we cannot do it in our own power. We must be filled with the Holy Spirit of God. The
Spirit in the flesh there at enmity one with the other. And so God, I pray that You'd help
us to abide in You. I pray, God, that You'd help us to walk in the Spirit. Help us to
live as Christians. To live like Jesus. To follow the example that was left for us. When
He was reviled, He reviled not again. Lord, help us to overcome evil with good. I pray
that You'd bless our time of prayer. We thank You for the privilege. I pray that You'd work
in a distinct way. We'll thank You for it. In Christ's name we pray. Amen. Anyone need
a prayer bulletin tonight? You did not get one on your way in? Anyone need one?