and our series here on Wednesday nights
for a number of weeks now has been this thought,
doing what we ought to do.
And I know that I've said it often,
but it's worth repeating
at the beginning of each of our lessons,
just because we know what we ought to do
doesn't mean we do what we ought to do.
And have you ever had your child
or maybe a young person that you were watching
and you were in charge of,
and you said, why did you do,
didn't you know that you're not supposed to do that?
Well, yeah, I knew I wasn't supposed to do it,
so why'd you do it?
Well, because I wanted to.
And how many of you were in school when you were kids,
you weren't allowed to chew gum in class?
Anyone have that rule?
Not allowed to chew gum in class, all right.
How many of you chewed gum in class anyway?
Some of you better raise your hand, amen,
because I know you chewed gum in class
even though you weren't supposed to,
and you swallowed it even though your mom said
that it was gonna take you seven years to digest it
and all that nonsense, right?
And the reality is that just because you knew
you weren't supposed to doing what we ought to do,
we don't always do it just because we know it,
and we think about that with life in general.
But then when we come to the truth of God's word,
I'm so thankful that God in his omniscience
and his grace, his mercy, he gave us his word
and he told us, here's how you can be saved,
here's how you can know me,
here's how you can live to please me.
Isn't that awesome that God would let us know that?
I was thinking about this today
and thinking about the truth of prayer
and what a privileged prayer is
and how God hears us when we pray
and he answers us and it's such a blessing.
I begin to think about this as I was thinking
about the book of Acts this morning
and reading through several chapters there
and just thinking about how the prayers of God's people
revealed what they knew to be true about God.
And I begin to think about this when we pray,
God, would you be gracious to this person?
Why is it that we pray that way?
Well, because we know that God's given us his word
and he's revealed to us that he's a gracious God.
Does that make sense?
And we begin to think about how we pray
and we pray according to his will,
according to what the scriptures teach us
and how we're to pray and when we pray according to his will
we know that he hears us and he's going to answer
and we can rejoice in that but we find that God
has not just given us his word so that we could know him,
although that's wonderful.
He did not just give us his word
so that we could know the way of salvation,
although that's wonderful,
but he also gave us his word
so that we would know how to please him,
that we could live in such a way
that our lives would be pleasing in his sight.
We've looked at a number of these ought to statements
throughout the New Testament and last week
we started a kind of a mini series within the series
from 1 John chapter two.
I read several verses last week
but let me just jump right into verse number six,
the key verse, if you will, for this thought here
that is just going to kind of control our study here
for the next couple of weeks.
In verse number six, the Bible says he that saith
he abideth in him ought himself also so to walk
even as he walked.
Now I mentioned last week that we ought to walk
as Christ walked, that's the title of the lesson,
last week part one, this week part two
and I said this, that when we come to this verse
of scripture, it really requires the Bible student
to then do some research, to do some study
because if the truth is that we ought to walk
as he walked, then I need to study the scriptures
to find out, well, how did Christ walk?
How did he live his life?
We mentioned this, that oftentimes in the Bible
we see that phrase of our walk,
it's referring to how we live our lives,
it's not the actual gait of our step
and the posture of our walk, it's how we live our lives,
it's our behavior and so we find that here this evening,
we're gonna look at a couple of more things,
last week we talked about the fact that Jesus walked wisely
and how we need wisdom, we need God's wisdom
as we live and walk in this world
and then we said that he walked humbly
and what great truth with regard to the humility
of the Lord Jesus Christ, God in flesh,
that he humbled himself and so often,
we are reminded of the importance for us
as the people of God to also walk humbly,
to be clothed as Peter said in humility.
This evening, again, part number two,
so really number three within the miniseries,
number one this evening, Jesus walked purposefully,
he walked purposefully and let me consider this this evening
as we look back at the scriptures,
turn back if you will to Matthew chapter four
and I want you to look at a number of things,
just as we did last week, I'm gonna make a statement
with regard to how Jesus walked
and then go to the scriptures and seek to illustrate,
to show you why is it that we're saying
that he walked wisely,
why is it that we're saying that he walked humbly?
Tonight, why would I make this declaration
that he walked purposefully?
Well, we find that as you study the life of Christ
and we have these four gospel records
that God has given to us,
that we have the privilege of being able to see
how Christ lived his life.
We find in Matthew chapter number four,
the Bible says in verse number 23,
and Jesus went about all Galilee,
notice what it says, teaching in their synagogues
and preaching the gospel of the kingdom
and healing all manner of sickness
and all manner of disease among the people
and his fame went throughout all Syria
and they brought unto him all sick people
that were taken with divers diseases and torments
and those which were possessed with devils
and those which were lunatic
and those that had palsy and he healed them
and there followed him great multitudes of people
from Galilee and from Decapolis and from Jerusalem
and from Judea and from beyond Jordan.
And so we find that Jesus, he went about all Galilee,
it says in verse 23 and it tells us
that as we consider this thought tonight
that he walked purposefully,
that as he went about Galilee,
notice he was teaching in their synagogues.
It tells us that he was preaching
the gospel of the kingdom
and it tells us that he was healing all manner of sickness.
We find that because of his teaching
and his preaching and his healing,
that there's a great multitude of people
that begin to follow him
and we find that in verse 25,
it tells us that there followed him
a great multitudes of people
and it says not only from Galilee
but from Decapolis, from Jerusalem,
from Judea and from beyond Jordan.
Think about the word being spread
about how Jesus was teaching and preaching and healing
and the Bible says in verse number one of chapter five
and seeing the multitudes,
he went up into a mountain
and when he was set, his disciples came unto him
and he opened his mouth and taught them saying
and we see the Sermon on the Mount,
we begin to read the Beatitudes we often refer to
and again, we see that Jesus walked purposefully.
He didn't just walk about just without any purpose.
You ever see somebody that seems like
they're going around life without any purpose?
They just kind of have no real direction,
there's no purpose in their life.
I find that Jesus walked purposefully.
Notice in Matthew chapter nine,
the Bible tells us this,
just a few pages over in your Bibles there,
Matthew chapter nine in verse number 35
and Jesus went about all the cities and villages
teaching in their synagogues
and preaching the gospel of the kingdom
and healing every sickness
and every disease among the people
and so again, we find very similar
to what we read in Matthew chapter number four
that as Jesus went about all the cities and the villages,
notice he's going and he's teaching again,
he's preaching and he's healing.
He's going with purpose.
He's going on purpose and with purpose.
I'm thankful this evening
that our God always moves with purpose.
I'm thankful this evening that God always has a purpose.
We can go through life,
have you ever been in a situation say,
I don't know why I'm dealing with this,
I don't know what the purpose of this is
and maybe we'll never know this side of heaven
but we can rejoice in knowing that if we don't know
that we can rest in knowing that our God has a purpose
and it may be years before we ever find out
what that purpose was.
I was sharing with somebody a testimony
just a couple of weeks ago
about how my dad got orders when I was living in Nevada
courtesy of the Marine Corps to move down to California
and it was the last place he wanted to go.
He'd been in the Marine Corps for 20 years.
He was going to basically go to his last duty station
before he retired, everyone knew that
and he said, I'll go anywhere in the world
but I don't wanna go to California
and so guess where he got to go?
California and we got to go there
and you know, it was really challenging.
It was challenging for me.
I was going to my senior high school.
There were a lot of challenges with regard to that
with sports and athletics, academics,
all of that sort of thing
but the reality was that we moved
and I didn't understand all of the reasons why we did
but we did and I got saved
within about three months of moving to California
and then after I got saved, God called me to the ministry
and then after I got called to the ministry,
God put me together with Paul Merchant as my pastor
who's still a mentor to me today
who God then used 13 years later that connection
to bring me to this church to be the pastor.
It's absolutely amazing how God works
and so we see that even still today,
we can rejoice in knowing that our God has purpose
but we even see it as we look at the scriptures
and look at the life of Christ,
he moved, he walked.
purposefully, Mark chapter number one.
Look there if you will, Mark chapter number one,
and we'll get to one more passage of scripture,
Mark chapter one, and the reality is that we could look
at tons of portions of scripture this evening
to deal with this subject of the Lord Jesus Christ
moving and walking with purpose.
In Mark chapter number one in verse number 16,
it says, now as he walked by the Sea of Galilee,
he saw Simon and Andrew his brother casting a net
into the sea, and they were four, they were fishers.
And Jesus said unto them, come ye after me,
and I will make you to become fishers of men.
I think about this call that he issues here
to Peter and Andrew to be disciples,
and how Jesus purposefully walked by the Sea of Galilee.
Now we know that he knows everything, amen.
He knows everything, he's the all-knowing, all-wise God,
and there's nothing that surprises him,
there's nothing that he's ever, man, I didn't know that,
I didn't think of that, no, he knew the thoughts
of the religious leaders as they gathered,
he knew the thoughts of the disciples,
he said to them on more than one occasion,
why reason ye among yourselves?
So he knew, and he walked with purpose to that place,
and as Peter and Andrew were casting a net
because they were fishers, that was their trade,
that was their occupation, he says, come ye after me.
We read it in Matthew, he says, follow me.
And we find that he says, I will make you
to become fishers of men.
He moved with purpose.
I want you to think about John chapter number four,
a text of scripture that is always so impactful to us
as we look at the Gospel of John and see how Jesus
was working to help his people understand the truth
of all people needing to hear the Gospel,
and we come to the fourth chapter of the book of John,
the Bible says in verse number one,
when therefore the Lord knew how the Pharisees
had heard that Jesus made and baptized more disciples
than John, though Jesus himself baptized not,
but his disciples, he left Judea
and departed again into Galilee.
Now, if you're going to go from Judea to Galilee
as a Jewish person, there was a set route
that you would take.
There was a way that you would go
and you would never go through Samaria.
It just was the way it was.
And why?
Well, the woman at the well says this to him,
why is it that you ask me of water?
The Jews have no company with the Samaritans.
There's this divide, this prejudice,
and we look at that and we understand that it says
in verse nine, for the Jews have no dealing
with the Samaritans.
They would literally go out of their way.
They would take a longer journey in order to avoid Samaria.
How many of you ever take a trip
and you take the shortcut, right?
And sometimes you try to outsmart your GPS.
You ever try to do that and you find out
that the GPS actually was smarter than you were
and was taking you on the route that it was on purpose.
I remember talking to a little kid years ago
and I asked how a trip was and they said it was really good.
We took the long cut and I thought that was quite comical
to hear the child use that terminology.
What do you mean by taking the long cut?
Well, my dad missed the turn and we took the long way.
And I mean, it just right out there, you know,
and it was quite comical, but really the Jews,
that's what they would do.
They would go out of their way to avoid Samaria.
But notice in verse number four, the Bible says,
and he must, needs go through Samaria.
Why?
Well, because he walked purposefully.
He walked purposefully.
We find that he comes and you're familiar with the account.
Then cometh he to a city of Samaria,
which is called Sychar, near to the parcel of ground
that Jacob gave to his son Joseph.
Verse six, now Jacob's well was there.
Jesus therefore being wearied with his journey,
sat thus on the well and it was about the sixth hour.
Then cometh a woman of Samaria to draw water
and Jesus saith unto her, give me to drink.
Now we don't have time this evening
to look at the entirety of the fourth chapter
of the book of John, but I believe tonight I could say,
and most of us are familiar with it,
that you would agree with me,
that her life was never the same after this interaction.
And what a joy to think about how Jesus walked purposefully.
That though so many, if they're going to go
from Judea to Galilee, they would go a certain route.
They would avoid at all costs going through Samaria.
No, Jesus said that he must needs go through Samaria.
He walked with purpose.
I think about the woman at the well and her being saved,
but also the people of the city that heard and came,
and not only from her testimony,
but from hearing as Jesus stayed there for two days
and teaching and preaching
and how many came to know the Lord.
Man, isn't that awesome?
He walked purposefully.
And so if we understand this evening,
the truth of 1 John 2 in verse number six,
where the Bible says, again, just as a reminder,
he that saith he abideth in him
ought himself also so to walk even as he walked.
And so if we can look at the scriptures,
and again, there's a number of other portions
of scripture that we could go to,
and we could prove tonight that Jesus walked purposefully,
then it should be said of us as the people of God
that we too should walk purposefully.
We should have purpose.
I wonder this evening,
sometimes people ask this question,
what is the purpose of life?
What is, why are we here?
You know, it's kind of interesting
when you hear people ask that question,
and depending on their worldview,
you get a varied kind of answer.
And people have all sorts of ideas and thoughts
with regard to why they're here and what their purpose is.
But I would submit to you
that as a child of God this evening,
that we should not have any stuttering or stammering,
it should not be any difficulty for us
to be able to answer with confidence and clarity
what our purpose is.
Because our purpose can be summarized very easily
as we read the truth of 1 Corinthians 10,
and verse number 31, where the Bible says,
whether therefore you eat, or drink,
or whatsoever you do,
do all to the glory of God.
Is that what your Bible says?
That's what my Bible says.
And so if we could take that verse of scripture tonight
and use that verse as answering the question,
what is my purpose?
What's the purpose of my life?
What is it that I'm doing?
And no doubt there are times, I mean,
businessmen, those in corporate America,
they've struggled because they've kind of,
if you kind of use that terminology
of being in the rat races,
they would use that analogy of just
how high up the ladder can I climb?
How much can I make?
What titles can I attain?
And reality sets in.
There's always somewhere else to go.
There's always someone else competing.
And what is our purpose?
I had a professor in Bible college
that I remember with great clarity,
him coming into class one day
with just a different countenance.
You ever notice somebody that has a different countenance
and you try to figure out,
okay, what's going on?
Remember, Nehemiah had a countenance.
His countenance was sad.
It was sorrow of heart is what the king said.
And we find that you can tell,
you can read people, you sometimes,
especially if you know them,
you can just see them and say,
hey, what's wrong?
Like, I can just tell there's something not right.
And I remember the professor walking in
and this just sobriety that was over him
and we began to inquire and we found out
that there were just some things
that he had been talking about
with regard to purpose.
And he was just overwhelmed with the fact
that God saved him and God called him to the ministry.
And he was just so full of emotion over that.
And here's why.
He began to tell us the account of his life
and how he grew up in a home where they weren't saved.
They didn't go to church,
except for a couple of times a year,
kind of the special holidays and that sort of thing,
and went to college and trained for a particular field.
He was in the engineering field
and that's what he was gonna do.
And he said that he was a design engineer
working on things and machinery and so on and so forth.
And he got this job and man,
he thought he was at the top of the world
and all these things out of college
and successful several years at the same company.
And they had this big ceremony
where they had worked on designing this new machine
and they were taking out all of the old stuff
and putting in the new
and they had this big ribbon cutting ceremony
and all these things.
And as all of this is happening,
just a few weeks prior, he got saved.
Somebody invited him to church
and he went to church and he got saved.
And all he had been living for was that type of an event.
But something changed in his heart and his life.
And he knew that that wasn't what life was all about.
And God was working in his heart,
calling to the ministry and so on and so forth.
And he said, I stood at that ribbon cutting ceremony
and here's the thought that just was so impressed on my heart
is that one day, another group of people are gonna come in
and they're gonna take out the machines that I helped design
and they're gonna implement new machines
and they're gonna have a ribbon cutting ceremony
and it's gonna happen over and over and over again.
And God used that in his life to help him understand and solidify the call.
Now, we understand not everyone's called to the ministry.
But for him, he'd been struggling with that.
I mean, right after he got saved, God was dealing with him calling to the ministry,
and he was really struggling with that.
And he said, look, what is life all about?
Is this what I want to do?
And the reality is that God was calling him.
Again, God's not calling everyone to the ministry.
But what we must understand is that wherever we are, if we're an engineer, if we're a doctor,
if we're in economics, finance, medicine, whatever field we're in, that God has for us,
that whatsoever we do, we do it for his glory.
Whatsoever thy hand findeth to do, do it heartily as unto the Lord and not unto men.
And so we find that at some point in life, as we recognize, what is my purpose?
And how do I walk purposefully as Jesus did?
How do I fulfill the purpose of whether therefore you eat, drink, or whatsoever you do,
do all to the glory of God?
I think about that verse of Scripture.
In fact, several weeks ago, in our marriage class, I used that verse of Scripture
as one of the points in our lesson.
And I said this, it's always an interesting verse of Scripture, because for me,
the thought of eating or drinking is just a, you almost don't think about it.
I mean, it's just a natural, you have to, right?
I mean, your body reminds you if you don't.
And it's just kind of almost a mundane kind of a thing.
But God says, whether you eat or drink or whatsoever you do, do all to the glory of God.
And so how do I do it to the glory of God?
How do I walk with that purpose, understanding the purpose?
Mark 16, 15, a verse that we are very familiar with,
a verse that some of the liberal Bible folks today try to take out of the Bible,
textual critics, and they try to discount the closing portion of Mark 16.
Many of them will explain away the Great Commission from the other books as well.
But we find Mark 16, 15, that Jesus makes it very plain to the disciples,
and he said unto them,
go ye into all the world and preach the gospel to every creature.
And the reality is that we have a unique privilege and opportunity.
We've been allowed of God to preach the gospel.
Now, does it mean that everything I'm going to do every single day of my life,
all I'm going to do is go and preach the gospel?
No, but the reality is that God has us in places,
and he allows us to come into contact with people that we are the light to those people.
We have the opportunity to share the gospel with those individuals.
I mentioned on Sunday evening, we sang that song, bringing in the sheaves,
and what a wonderful song that is.
It starts out by sowing in the morning, sowing in the evening, right?
And the song starts that way because you're not going to bring in the sheaves
if you're not first sowing.
It makes sense, right?
And the songwriter understood something about agriculture
is using that analogy in the song, and so we understand.
And I was convicted as I was reading that song earlier in the day,
and I mentioned it on Sunday.
I was reading, I was sitting here on the pulpit as I prayed in the morning,
and as I was reading through the words of the song, I was convicted,
and I asked myself this question,
when is the last time I even tried to share the gospel with someone?
If that's what our purpose is, we have to ask ourselves the question,
so sometimes we ask the question,
when's the last time you led somebody to Christ?
One of the difficulties with that question is I don't have a control over that
because the Bible says that some plant some water, but God gives the increase.
So I have to leave that part in God's hands.
I can't control whether or not I could lead somebody to Christ,
but the reality is that I better be sharing the gospel.
Now, I can't force anyone to listen to the gospel,
but am I even trying to share the gospel?
Am I trying to sow the seed?
The folks that I come in contact with,
the people that I rub shoulders with throughout the week,
are those people, do they know that I'm a Christian?
Have I ever tried to share the gospel with them?
That's our purpose.
Think about this, John chapter number 15.
The Bible says this, I'll give you a moment to turn there,
and John 15 is a familiar passage.
It's kind of interesting.
It goes right along with this truth in 1 John
because in 1 John chapter 2 and verse number 6,
the verse that we're using as our lesson key verse,
it says, he that saith, he abideth in him.
Now, in John chapter number 15, what's the thought here?
Abide in me, right?
We see it in verse number four,
abide in me, and I in you,
as the branch cannot bear fruit of itself,
except it abide in the vine,
no more can you except you abide in me.
And so, he that abideth in me, verse number five,
if a man abide not in me, verse number six,
if ye abide in me, verse number seven,
and so we see that 1 John chapter 2 speaks about this,
the one that says he abides in him.
Remember, the evidence has to support the claim,
and that's why it says that he himself also sort of walk
even as he walked or as Christ walked.
So, we come to John 15,
and we begin to see this truth that God gives us
with regard to being the vine and we are the branches.
It's interesting, he says, I am the true vine.
I am the true vine.
And my attention recently was just captivated
on that thought, the true vine.
Listen, there's a lot of false things out there today,
but I'm thankful that my savior, that my Jesus,
he is the true vine.
The Bible says in verse number one,
and my father is the husbandman,
every branch in me that beareth not fruit,
he taketh away, and every branch that beareth fruit,
he purgeth it, that it may bring forth more fruit.
Now, understand, who's the one that gives the fruit?
It's God that gives the fruit, but he's using us, right?
Some plant, some water, God gives the increase.
And he says that he purgeth it, verse number two,
that it may bring forth more fruit.
Verse number three, now ye are clean through the word,
which I have spoken unto you.
Abide in me, and I in you,
as the branch cannot bear fruit of itself,
except it abide in the vine.
No more can ye except ye abide in me.
Now we understand that principle and that truth.
And so the importance of abiding,
if I'm gonna produce fruit,
if I'm gonna be a fruit bearer,
I must abide in the vine.
Verse five, I am the vine, ye are the branches.
He that abideth in me, and I in him,
the same bringeth forth much fruit.
For without me he can do nothing.
And so if you notice, if you go through
the few verses of scripture here,
in verse number one, excuse me, verse number two,
it says that if he beareth not fruit,
and then it says in every branch that beareth fruit.
And so you see, it's just bearing fruit.
But then at the end of verse number two,
it says that he purgeth it, that it might bring forth,
what does it say?
More fruit.
And then by the time you get down to verse number five,
it says that he that abideth in me,
and I in him, the same bringeth forth much fruit.
So in verse number two, we go from fruit to more fruit,
to verse number five, much fruit.
And we find this, remember, what did Jesus say?
We looked at Mark one,
when he purposefully walked along the sea
so that he could call Peter and Andrew.
He said, come, and he said,
I will make you to be fishers of men.
Now, what does it mean to be a fisher of men?
We use the term sometimes soul winning,
and we talk about going out.
The proverb says, he that winneth souls is wise.
And we go out, we share the gospel,
we preach the truth of the gospel
so that people can know that they have a choice.
I said this on Sunday morning in Sunday school.
John chapter number one,
he came to his own and his own received him not.
Verse 12, but as many as received him,
to them gave he power to become the sons of God,
even to them that believe on his name.
And so it's very interesting
because they received him not,
and then those that received him,
every single person on the face of the earth,
every person that you know, that you work with,
that you have any kind of activity with,
they have a choice.
But what really burdens my heart
is how many of them don't even know
that they have a choice.
They don't even know
because they've not heard the gospel.
They don't know that they have a choice
to reject or receive.
They obviously, what does the truth say
in John three in verse 36?
Look, if you don't, you're condemned already, right?
The preacher years ago preached a message,
what do you have to do to go to hell?
And the answer was nothing
because we're condemned already.
And so there's countless millions of people
on our planet today that have no idea.
They don't know the choice that they have.
And I feel like as believers
and I challenge my own life, my own self,
am I walking with purpose,
understanding the main purpose, right?
What is the main purpose?
Now, remember he said in first Corinthians 10 31,
whether therefore you eat or drink,
whatsoever you do, do all to the glory of God.
We're speaking here in John 15
about this bringing forth fruit.
Jesus walked purposefully.
He called people and said, follow me.
I will make you to be fishers of men.
It's God doing the work in us
as we abide in him, as we yield ourselves to him,
as we also walk purposefully.
Continue now in John 15 verse number six,
if a man abide not in me,
he has cast forth as a branch and is withered
and men gather them and cast them into the fire.
and they are burned.
If you abide in me and my words abide in you,
you shall ask what you will and it shall be done unto you.
Now notice verse number eight.
It's where I've been trying to get to
with this whole thought going through these verses.
Herein is my father glorified.
Now 1 Corinthians 10 31, do all the glory of God.
So here in John 15 and verse number eight,
herein is my father glorified.
Here's how he's glorified, that ye bear much fruit.
So shall you be my disciples.
How do I bear much fruit?
Well, he said, follow me and I'll make you
to be fishers of men.
He said, abide in me.
And so there's this yielding, there's this understanding.
What is my purpose?
Why is it that God has left me here?
And yes, I have to work a job.
Yes, I have to do these things
and I have these responsibilities and these duties,
but I can't lose sight in the midst of all of those things
that I have a greater purpose.
And that purpose is to make Christ known,
to make Christ known.
Notice in Colossians one, in verse number 18,
Colossians one, in verse number 18,
it's a familiar verse of scripture,
one in which we ought to commit to memory.
And we see that really beginning in verse 15,
a great truth with regard to a great description
with regard to our Lord.
I actually begin reading it there in verse 15
in Colossians one.
Notice the Bible says this,
who is the image of the invisible God,
the firstborn of every creature,
for by him were all things created that are in heaven,
that are in earth, visible and invisible,
whether they be thrones or dominions
or principalities or powers,
all things were created by him and for him.
And he is before all things,
and by him all things consist.
And he is the head of the body, the church.
And this is a great verse of scripture
talking about the polity of the church.
And we're saying, listen, there's no other person
that's to be the head of the church.
Why do we have an issue with the state government church,
a state-run church?
Because there's no other head of the church.
It's Jesus that is the head of the church.
Notice who is the beginning, the firstborn from the dead.
Then notice this, that in all things,
he might have the preeminence,
that he might have the preeminence,
literally having first place.
First John ends by saying,
my little children, keep yourselves from idols.
We find that an idol is anything
that gets in the place of God.
Idols can vary from culture to culture,
from family to family, a different thing.
Somebody can idolize something that another person does not.
And we see here that the scriptures say that in all things,
he, Christ, might have the preeminence.
By the way, when you start reading in verse number 15,
obviously, previous even to that,
he talks about the fact that we've been redeemed
through his blood, that's how we have forgiveness.
He's our savior.
But then you see this great description of who our God is,
and then it says that he might have the preeminence.
Well, absolutely, that just makes sense,
knowing who he is, that in my life, in your life,
he should have the preeminence.
And so this evening, when we look at this thought
of walking, we ought to walk as Christ walked.
We find that he walked wisely, he walked humbly,
as we looked at last week, but tonight,
we consider this truth that he walked purposefully.
If you study the gospels and you study through
the ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ,
he was always moving with purpose, always.
John 9, he saw a man that was born blind.
It was an opportunity.
You come to John chapter 11, and you find there
that he's made aware of the fact that he whom thou lovest
is sick, and what did he do?
He stayed there, he delayed, he didn't go.
Why?
Well, because he knew what he was gonna do.
And he tells his disciples, he said,
all right, it's time to go.
And they said that Lazarus was asleep.
Well, if he's sleeping, then that's good.
I mean, he's sick, let him sleep.
And he said, Lazarus is dead.
And then he says this, I am glad for your sakes
that I was not there, to the intent that you might believe.
We could go on and on this evening with just
example after example, in the life and ministry
of the Lord Jesus Christ, where he walked purposefully.
As I consider that truth this evening,
coupled with this ought to command
from 1 John chapter two, in verse number six,
I examine my own life, and I say,
am I walking with purpose?
Today, did I walk with purpose?
When I went about the various things that I went about,
did I have purpose in what I was doing?
Was there ever something that I did
that was to bring glory to God,
that there was the purpose of my day, of my activity?
Because Jesus always walked purposefully.
And tonight, if we're gonna walk as Christ walked,
then we too, we must walk purposefully.
Why am I doing the things that I'm doing?
Why am I, we could ask ourselves, we gotta answer,
am I doing it for the glory of God?
How can I do it for the glory of God?
Is there a way that I can approach this task,
this responsibility, and fulfill the responsibility
at the same time of bringing glory to God?
Because we need to, as Christ did, walk purposefully.
Father, we love you, we thank you for loving us,
we thank you for your word tonight,
we thank you for the example of the Lord Jesus Christ,
and Lord, I pray that you'd help us tonight.
Lord, help us not to lose sight
of why you have left us here.
Lord, help us to move and walk with purpose
just as our Savior did.
We thank you for the privilege of prayer,
we thank you that you hear and answer prayer.
We ask God that you would bless our time,
I pray that you'd be honored and glorified,
for it's in Christ's name we pray, amen.