Bible, aren't you? And what a blessing to have the Word of God, to know the truth that God has provided us with in His Word and the
instruction that He's given to us. In Romans chapter number 6, we'll jump in here in just a moment, but I want you to understand the
Christian life is a journey. And how many of you have realized that? It's a journey walking with the Lord. Amen. In fact, in John 15, the
Lord Jesus Christ instructs His followers to abide in Him. We find in the book of Galatians that we, as the people of God, are
instructed to walk in the Spirit. We find that we are reminded in the same text of Scripture that the Spirit and the flesh are
contrary the one to the other. And I know that each of us, if you've been saved for any period of time, you have learned that the Spirit
and the flesh are at enmity one with the other. They are contrary one to the other. The Bible talks about, in Ephesians chapter number 2,
about the lust of the flesh or the desires of the flesh. And the reality is that when you got saved, your flesh was not eradicated and there
are still desires of the flesh, but we are to walk in the Spirit, the Bible says, and we should not fulfill the desires of the flesh. And so
what a great promise that God gives us. We find in the book of Ephesians, as well as the book of Colossians, that we, as the people of God,
are instructed to put on the new and to put off the old. And we find in our text this evening in Romans chapter number 6, we're going to look at
verses 1 through 19 this evening. And as we look at this text of Scripture, you're going to find the word yield used several times. And the word
yield is an important word. We could ask ourselves this question tonight, what does it mean to yield? How many of you drive on the roads around here
and you find very commonly that people do not know what the yield sign means? And you see that all the time, they don't understand what yield means.
And we find that sometimes we go through the Christian life, we look here in Romans chapter 6 and we see the use of this word, we may not fully
understand what it means to yield. Let me ask this question, is it a natural thing to yield? It's not natural. It's not natural. The word yield means to
submit, to give way, or to give place. That's what it means. Now we're instructed in the text of Scripture, I've titled the message this evening from
verse number 13, that we're to yield ourselves unto God. Yield yourselves unto God. I ask the question, is it natural to yield? And honestly this evening, the
subject, the thought of yielding, goes against the flesh. Not only does it go against the flesh, but it goes against the culture that we live in. We live in a
culture that feeds the desires of the flesh. We live in a culture, we live in a society that tells you, that tells me, that tells our young people, be what you want to be.
Do what you want to do. Do what feels good. If it pleases you, then do it. Is that not the society, the culture that we live in? And we find this evening that as the
people of God, as saved individuals, we come to Romans chapter number 6, and we find this truth that we are to yield ourselves unto God. That we're not to be the master of my own life.
My flesh, your flesh, wants to rule. Wants to sit on the throne of your heart, of your life. But we find that we have a Savior. We have a good Savior, a good master, a good Lord, and He
deserves to have preeminence in our lives. He deserves to have that place of ownership, and that we would yield to Him. Notice in the text of Scripture, if you're taking notes, number 1 this evening, and it's going to be verses 1 through 14.
I'm going to get through it kind of quickly this evening, but I want you to notice the counsel. Eventually we'll get through verse 19, but on this first thought this evening, I want you to notice the counsel that is given.
And we see that in verses 1 through 14. Notice the way the Bible begins in verse number 1, what shall we say then? Shall we continue in sin that grace may abound?
Now he's referring back, remember the chapter divisions are added for the ease of our finding passages of Scripture. The chapter divisions, the verse divisions, they were not in the originals.
It's not how they were given, but they were provided to us. Could you imagine tonight if we all tried to get to Romans chapter number 6 without having chapter and verse divisions? It'd be quite difficult.
And so we're thankful for them, but we notice at the end of chapter 5, in verse number 20, notice what the Bible says, moreover the law entered that the offense might abound, but where sin abounded, grace did much more abound.
Aren't you thankful for that truth? Someone said this, a songwriter said, I don't know what a sinner you are, but I know what a savior he is. And what a joy to know the amazing grace of our God.
It says in verse 21, that as sin hath reigned unto death, even so might grace reign through righteousness unto eternal life by Jesus Christ our Lord.
So then he's going to answer a question that he's given here in verse number 1 of chapter 6, what shall we say then? Shall we continue in sin that grace may abound?
God forbid, that's the answer in verse number 2. See, there are some that don't understand the grace of God. In fact, the false teachers that are creeping in according to the book of Jude, they turn the grace of God into lasciviousness.
And that word means unbridled lust. Do what you want, be what you want, because the grace of God allows for that. That's not what the grace of God allows for.
According to Titus chapter number 2, the grace of God hath appeared to all men, teaching us that denying ungodliness and worldly lust, we should live godly and soberly and righteously in this present world.
And so that's what the grace of God teaches us, but we find that they turn the grace of God into lasciviousness.
So Paul says, no, that's not the idea. Though we are rejoicing the fact that where sin did abound, that grace did abound much more, we rejoice in that, but we don't continue in sin that grace may abound.
God forbid, notice verse 2, how shall we that are dead to sin live any longer therein?
Notice he's beginning to reveal to us and help us to understand our position in Christ and who we are and understanding that he says in verse 3,
We are buried with him by baptism into death, that like as Christ was raised up from the dead by the glory of the Father, even so we also should walk in newness of life.
We use this verse of scripture every time I baptize someone I say, are you sure of heaven, have you trusted Jesus Christ as your personal savior?
And if they say yes I have, and by the way I've already asked them before I get them into the water to make sure, I've already had that conversation, but I say,
based upon your profession of faith, I now baptize you in the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghost, buried in the likeness of his death, raised to walk in newness of life.
The Bible says, if any man be in Christ, he's a new creature, old things are passed away, behold, all things are become new.
And we find here that he's telling these believers about the truth of the new life in Christ in verse 5,
for if we have been planted together in the likeness of his death, we shall be also in the likeness of his resurrection, knowing this.
Notice what he wants us to know in verse 6, this is something that is to be known.
Remember, as we study the Bible, God does not want his people to be ignorant.
He wants us to be informed, he wants us to know things, and he says, knowing this, that our old man is crucified with him, that's Christ, the picture there,
that the body of sin might be destroyed, that henceforth we should not serve sin, for he that is dead is freed from sin.
Now, if we be dead with Christ, we believe that we shall also live with him, and so I'm to be dead to sin, but alive unto God.
It's amazing as we look here, remember the apostle Paul said, I am crucified with Christ, nevertheless I live, yet not I, right?
Galatians 2.20, he's giving that truth, he's really, in one verse of scripture in Galatians 2, he's summarizing all that he's giving here in Romans 6.
And we find in verse number 8, now if we be dead with Christ, we believe that we shall also live with him,
knowing that Christ being raised from the dead dieth no more, death hath no more dominion over him.
Aren't you thankful for that? He conquered sin, death, and the grave, and he is alive forevermore.
Revelation says, I am he that was dead, but I'm alive forevermore. Hallelujah, we serve a risen savior.
Verse 10, for in that he died, he died unto sin, what does it say? Once.
Remember what Hebrews 10 said? For this man after he offered one sacrifice for sin forever, he sat down.
Why? The work was finished, he said, it is done, it is finished, it's complete. Hallelujah.
We find that it continues and says, but in that he liveth, he liveth unto God.
Now notice as we get into the council here, the apostle Paul in these first 10 verses is helping the believers,
helping these that he's writing to, helping them.
as we have the Bible preserved for us
to understand our position.
And the counsel is clear.
He says this in verse 11,
likewise reckon ye also yourselves
to be dead indeed unto sin,
but alive unto God through Jesus Christ our Lord.
Let not sin therefore reign in your mortal body
that you should obey it in the lust thereof.
And here's the counsel, verse 13,
neither yield ye your members
as instruments of unrighteousness unto sin,
but yield yourselves unto God
as those that are alive from the dead
and your members as instruments of righteousness unto God,
for sin shall not have dominion over you,
for you're not under the law, but under grace.
These are some wonderful verses of scripture.
God gives us this counsel in verse number 13
that we're to yield ourselves unto God.
He tells us in verse 14
that sin shall not have dominion over you.
You know that when you were lost, you were bound by sin.
You're bound by sin.
But we find that when we trust that Christ is our savior,
not only were we delivered from the penalty of sin,
which is death,
but we were delivered from the power of sin.
He says here, for sin shall not have dominion over you.
We were bound by sin.
We were under the dominion of sin,
but in Christ, we are dead to sin.
We're alive unto God.
We find that we've been delivered from the penalty
and from the power of sin.
We find the truth, though,
that we've not yet been delivered from the presence of sin.
Sin is still here.
You sin today.
Amen?
We sin.
But he says here that sin shall not have dominion over you.
What a great promise that God has given to us,
that he has given us the victory.
But thanks be to God,
which giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.
And so we find the counsel is given,
I believe this evening, that the counsel is clear.
He tells us that as we would understand our position
in Christ, that what we should do
is yield ourselves unto God.
Notice he says in verse 13,
if you consider the entirety of the counsel,
neither yield ye your members
as instruments of unrighteousness unto sin,
but yield yourselves unto God
as those that are alive from the dead
and your members as instruments of righteousness unto God.
And so that's counsel, that's instruction,
that's what we are instructed to do.
And so we find that we notice the counsel,
but as we continue through the text of Scripture
in verses 15 and 16, number two,
I want you to notice the choice.
Notice the choice.
You know, God has given to his creation, humanity, free will.
There's a lot of confusion about free will.
And I do not believe,
in fact, I had a conversation with somebody today,
I believe 100% in my mind,
it makes total sense that God is fully sovereign
and he knows all things
and he knows the end from the beginning
and he has foreknowledge, he has all knowledge,
he is supreme, he is sovereign, he is God.
And at the same time, he gave man free will.
I believe that those two things can be in perfect harmony.
Why?
Because God made it so.
And so God made it so and he gave us that free will.
And you think about the way that he gives us free will,
he provides us, he provides you and me
and these that are originally receiving this letter
from Paul and every child of God
that would read the book of Romans,
they, God gives to them, gives to us valuable counsel.
But he doesn't make us do it.
He gives you a choice.
He gives me a choice.
You know, someone, I've been asked the question many times
over the years and not that I'm an expert,
I've only pastored now for a little over 13 years,
it's not that long of a time,
but oftentimes I will be asked,
in fact, we're in Panama, I was asked the question
by a couple of the young men.
They said, what's the hardest thing about pastoring?
And there's a lot of hard things about pastoring.
There's the list is various and so many different things,
but one of the hardest things
is watching people make bad decisions.
You know what a hard thing as a parent
is watching a child make a bad decision.
It's hard as a parent.
If you've had children that have made bad decisions
and you gave them the counsel, you laid out for them,
but you could not make the decision for them
and you watch them make a bad choice, a bad decision,
that's hard.
And at some point, there's nothing you can do about it.
There's absolutely nothing you can do about it.
Listen, God gives us free will.
As a pastor, I have the responsibility
of preaching the whole counsel of God,
giving the truth of God's word,
but I can't make anybody do anything.
Amen?
It's a choice of the individual.
And we find this evening
that as we look at this passage of Scripture,
that God provides us with this valuable counsel,
but he does not force us to heed it.
I want you to consider, hold your place here,
we'll be right back into the book of Romans,
but look over at 2 Peter chapter one, just for a moment,
and as you're turning to 2 Peter chapter number one,
I wanna read a verse of Scripture to you there,
but I also, I don't want you to turn to Psalm 19,
if you want, you can if you're quick,
but Psalm 19, I wanna read a couple of verses to you there
as we get back over to 2 Peter chapter one
here in just a moment,
but I want you to see that in Psalm 19,
I don't have time to read all of it,
but it begins in verse seven,
speaking about the law of the Lord being perfect
and gives all of these attributes
and various workings of God's word and how it's effective.
In verse number 11, it says,
"'Moreover, by them is thy servant warned,
and in keeping of them, there is great reward.'"
You can warn people, but you can't force people.
Do we agree with that tonight?
You can warn them, but you can't force them.
And notice in 2 Peter chapter one,
Peter's writing, and in this particular text of scripture,
beginning in verse 16, he's writing about
being on the Mount of Transfiguration.
I mean, what an amazing opportunity
that Peter, James, and John had
to be there on the Mount of Transfiguration.
I can't even fully grasp how amazing that must have been,
but we find that he mentions that in verse 16,
and we see it at the end of the verse,
he says, but we're eyewitnesses of his majesty,
and he goes through and he's talking about
the word of God that we have here,
that no prophecy came, not by the will of man,
but holy men of God spake, in verse 21,
as they were moved by the Holy Ghost,
but I wanna draw your attention to verse 19.
Notice what Peter says,
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
he says, we have also a more sure word of prophecy.
Now, Peter, God, of course, is the author of scripture,
and God precedes the statement of us
having a more sure word of prophecy
by revealing that Peter heard the voice of God
on the Mount of Transfiguration,
and then Peter says, but we have,
we have also a more sure word of prophecy,
and then notice the center of this verse,
it says, whereunto ye do well, that ye take heed,
and then notice how he illustrates
what it means to take heed,
as unto a light that shineth in a dark place
until the day dawn and the day star arise in your hearts.
You know, this evening, if we were to lose power,
and if the emergency lights,
if we were in here for any length of time,
and the battery backup of the emergency lights failed,
and it was completely dark in here,
the shades were pulled down,
and it was stormy, and it was dark,
and we did not have any bearing of our orientation,
I guarantee you this evening,
that if in the midst of that great darkness,
if someone turned on a light,
that your attention would go to the light.
So it would happen.
Without you thinking about it,
you immediately would look to the light,
and so Peter says that you do well,
that you take heed thereunto.
It is in our best interest,
and so here, back in Romans chapter number six,
when we notice the choice that counsel is given,
it's valuable counsel,
but we find that there's a choice that has to be made,
and so then notice in verse 15,
what then?
Shall we sin because we are not under the law,
but under grace?
God forbid.
Verse 16.
Know ye not that to whom ye yield yourselves servants
to obey, his servants ye are to whom ye obey,
whether of sin unto death,
or of obedience unto righteousness.
So do you see the choice in verse 15?
In verse 13, he says neither yield ye,
and then he says, but yield yourselves.
He's giving them counsel.
He's telling them what to do,
but in verse 16, he's saying,
know ye not that to whom ye yield yourselves servants
to obey.
This is the choice that every believer has to make.
Are we gonna yield ourselves to God?
By the way, let me say this.
As we note in verse 15 and 16,
and we consider the choice that is before
every child of God,
the principle of yielding to God is a,
It's a recurring decision.
You know, when you got saved,
it was a moment in time,
and you were born again.
You're not being born again.
Born again is not a process.
Salvation is the miracle of a moment.
Sanctification, practical sanctification,
not positional sanctification,
but practical sanctification,
if I can make that distinction this evening,
the practical aspect of sanctification
is really the process of a lifetime.
It's not the miracle of a moment,
it's the process of a lifetime.
It's that we continually yield ourselves unto God,
moment by moment, day by day.
In fact, I said that yielding to God
is a recurring decision,
but you understand that in your life and in my life,
that we might have to yield to God
multiple times in a single day.
Why?
Because decisions are going to be put before us,
and there's going to be an opportunity
for you to yield to yourself
to what you want to do,
or to yield to God.
And here the Bible says that there's a choice.
I believe that it's clear the choice
that God would want his children to make.
I believe that it's clear
that Paul made it abundantly clear
of the choice that he, as a spiritual leader,
would like for these readers,
these recipients of this letter,
the choice for them to make.
But at the end of the day,
God's given us a free will,
and the choice is yours.
You know what Moses, God,
says to the people in Moses writes?
He says, you're going to make a choice.
Deuteronomy 11.
I set before you a blessing and a curse.
Is that not what God said in Deuteronomy 11?
We read it, we see it, we understand it.
What about Joshua, in Joshua chapter 24?
Choose you this day whom ye will serve.
Is that not what it says?
But as for me and my house,
we will serve the Lord.
See, Joshua said, I've made a choice,
but I can't make the choice for you.
I'm going to make the choice,
and I'm going to lay out the reason
that you ought to make the same choice that I'm making,
and I believe if you read Joshua 24,
that's clear, that Joshua says,
look, let me help you understand
why you should make the same choice that I'm making.
You know what all the people said?
We're going to serve God.
You read it, that's what they say.
And so we find this evening there's a choice,
but that choice is just, it's not a one and done.
Like salvation, you write down the date
that you got saved, and man, you can rejoice
in your spiritual birthday,
and you can know that you're born again,
but with regard to yielding to Christ
multiple times in a day,
you may have to make that decision.
Nope, I'm going to yield to God.
I'm bought with a price.
I belong to Him.
Notice with me as we conclude
looking at verses 17 through 19,
we're going to look at a couple of other,
just one other passage quickly,
but notice the consequences of this choice.
The consequences, we find that there's a choice to be made,
but the consequences are given to us.
It says, but God be thanked.
Notice what it says in verse 17,
that ye were the servants of sin,
but ye have obeyed from the heart
that form of doctrine which was delivered you.
Isn't that exciting that we were,
but we are not any longer?
He says it in past tense.
Ye were the servants of sin.
I was, you were, I was, everyone.
Listen, Ephesians chapter two makes it abundantly clear
that we all were in that same situation.
It was not something that was unique to you
or to some other person.
No, he says that we all had our conversation
in times past in the lust of our flesh,
fulfilling the desires of the flesh and the mind,
and were by nature the children of wrath even as others.
That was our lot, that was our situation.
Ephesians chapter two, and you look there in that passage
and you see the truth that is given to us
in verse number three.
But God, verse number four, who is rich in mercy,
praise the Lord, for by grace are you saved through faith.
Verse number eight, right?
What a joy to understand this truth of salvation,
but the choice that we make
that we would yield ourselves unto God.
He says that you were the servants of sin,
but you have obeyed from the heart that form of doctrine
which was delivered to you.
Understand with me tonight that the truth of salvation
is so much more than just escaping hell.
Did you catch that tonight?
It's important.
Why is it important?
Because some people have this idea that salvation,
the only real reason anyone needs to be saved
is so they would escape like a fire, escape hell.
Though that is true that we would,
if you're saved by the grace of God,
you're not gonna go to the lake of fire, hallelujah.
But he didn't save us so that we could live for ourselves.
He didn't save us so that we could walk in sin
and continue to fulfill the lust
and the desires of the flesh.
No, he saved us so that we might be like Christ.
If you read Romans chapter eight in verse number 29,
he predestined us to be conformed
to the image of his dear son.
Christ in me, the hope of glory.
That's the idea.
And so salvation is not just,
I had a man tell me, this was before I even got saved.
I was about 13 years old.
My parents had gotten saved.
We're at the church, Grace Baptist Church
in Jacksonville, North Carolina.
And there was this young Marine,
actually a bunch of young Marines that were there.
They were talking about being saved.
And this one guy, he was talking about all kinds of sin
and wickedness, he was talking, he was just bad talking.
He's at church, he's right out in the parking lot.
I was like a 13 year old kid
and I was there standing there with him.
And this guy was talking about all kinds of immorality.
And thankfully there were some other young Marines
that were saved by the grace of God
and called him out on it and said,
hey, hey, hey, why are you talking about that stuff?
Why are you doing that kind of stuff?
And you know what he said?
I remember it just like it was yesterday.
He said, listen, as long as I'm going to heaven,
I don't really care, I'm just gonna do what I wanna do.
You know what I'd say?
I'd question whether that man's really saved.
You know why I'd question if he's really saved?
Because the Bible says,
if any man be in Christ, he's a new creature.
All things are passed away,
behold, all things will become new.
It doesn't mean that we don't have the desires of the flesh
but it means that the Holy Spirit of God is living in us.
And it means that God said,
for whom the Lord loveth, he chasteneth.
Amen, is that what your Bible says?
Well, my Bible says he corrects us,
he chastens us because he loves us.
And so we're not what we used to be.
Praise the Lord for that.
Notice in verse 18, back in Romans six,
being then made free from sin,
you became the servants of righteousness.
By the way, I'd rather be a servant of righteousness
than a servant of sin, amen.
You see that contrast between verse 17 and 18.
I would much rather be a servant of righteousness
than a servant of sin.
And verse 19 says this,
I speak after the manner of men
because of the infirmity of your flesh.
For as you have yielded your member servants
to uncleanness and to iniquity unto iniquity,
even so now yield your member servants
to righteousness unto holiness.
I believe in verse 19, it really goes with the first point
this evening of the counsel that is given to us.
And Paul is saying, listen, you have in the past,
before you got saved,
you yielded your member servants of uncleanness
unto iniquity unto iniquity.
But now that you're saved,
now yield your member servants
to righteousness unto holiness.
In verse 13, however, we do see that the Bible says,
neither yield ye your members
as instruments of unrighteousness unto sin.
So we still can yield to the wrong thing.
It's not an automatic.
You can still yield to yourself,
you can still yield to sin,
you can still yield to unrighteousness,
but the counsel, the compelling truth of Romans six
is yield yourselves unto God.
And you know when we do that, God is glorified.
God is glorified.
That's the ultimate consequence is that God is glorified.
Why?
Because we're yielding ourselves to him.
What does it mean to yield?
Again, the word means to submit, to give place
or to give way.
And we're acknowledging that he is my Lord and my master,
that he is the one that is to be receiving the honor
and the glory and the praise, and it's all about him.
And I'm yielding to him.
My life, Lord, is yours to control.
It's what the songwriter said.
And what a great song.
Living for Jesus, we sing the hymn.
What a great hymn.
And we find this evening that here,
when we come to the place
that we're yielding ourselves to God,
that we understand that God is going
to receive the honor and the glory.
We sang this evening, Dare to be a Daniel.
Dare to be a Daniel.
I want you to turn over to Daniel chapter three,
if you will.
It's not really about Daniel.
It's about his three friends in Daniel chapter number three.
Daniel, of course, we find the great truth in Daniel six
of the prayer and what have you.
But in Daniel chapter three,
we see that Nebuchadnezzar set up this great statue
and he wanted the image and everyone's gonna bow
because he's gonna play the music
and all that's going to happen.
and then I won't be able to take the time
and go through all of Daniel chapter number three
this evening.
If you're not familiar with it,
I would encourage you to go back and read it.
But there are three men, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego,
and these men did not regard the command of the king.
We're not gonna bow.
But you're gonna go in a fiery furnace,
but we're not gonna bow.
Why?
Because God gave us instruction
that we're not to have any other gods before him.
We're not to bow to any images or to any idols,
and we're just not gonna bow.
But you know what the penalty is?
You're aware of, I'm gonna actually play the music again,
and we're gonna give you another opportunity,
really is kinda what Nebuchadnezzar decides to do.
And these three guys, they say, look, you can,
I'm gonna paraphrase, it's not written this way,
but basically they say, you can play the music all day,
we're not gonna bow.
And they say this.
If you're gonna send us in there,
I want you to know that our God whom we serve
is able to deliver us.
Man, what a great, powerful statement in verse 17.
And then he says this in the same verse.
Notice, if it be so, our God whom we serve
is able to deliver us from the burning, fiery furnace,
and he will deliver us out of thine hand, O king.
But if not, be it known unto thee, O king,
that we will not serve thy gods,
nor worship the golden image which thou hast set up.
Our God is able.
I'm thankful that our God is able
to deliver us from anything.
There are times, however, that he chooses
not to deliver us from something, but through something,
as is the case here in Daniel chapter three.
It could have been that God delivered these three
from ever having to go into the fiery furnace.
It could have been.
But you know, we wouldn't be talking about it tonight,
probably.
We're talking about it tonight because God delivered them
through the fiery furnace.
And I want you to see what the king of Babylon says.
Notice in verse 28, after the end of everything,
and he's astonished, and he says, what's going on here?
We threw three guys in, bound, and now they're loose,
and walking around, and there's a fourth,
and what is going on?
And we find in verse 28, notice what Nebuchadnezzar says.
Then Nebuchadnezzar spake and said,
blessed be the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego,
who hath sent his angel and delivered his servants
that trusted in him, and have changed the king's word,
notice what it says, and yielded their bodies,
that they might not serve nor worship any God
except their own God.
In a very real way, they yielded themselves to God.
They said, we're not gonna bow.
But you're gonna die, but we're not gonna bow.
I may die, but I'm gonna die pleasing God.
Amen?
I read a book while I was away.
I wrote a book while I was in Panama.
I read a book this past week,
and I actually finished it up today,
and Patrick Hamilton is a man
that I was reading about in this book.
It wasn't a book about him specifically,
but he was referenced in this book,
and quite honestly, I didn't know anything about the man,
but he was burned at the stake in the year 1528
at the age of 24 years old.
He was in Scotland, and of course,
if you understand anything about the church history
at that time, there was much persecution
against any that would preach the gospel
of the Lord Jesus Christ,
that salvation is by grace alone and Christ alone,
that the authority of the scriptures
and really the rebellion against the state church
and all of that stuff that was going on, of course,
in the very time in which you would read
of the Reformation taking place in Germany and what have you
but then in Scotland, there was a great stronghold,
a lot of persecution that took place,
and this man, Patrick Hamilton at the age of 24 years old
was burned at the stake in the year 1528.
He actually, for a period of time,
after he got saved, he was preaching the gospel,
and I mean, there's all kinds of persecution issues,
he went to Germany for a period of time,
and probably if he had stayed in Germany,
he probably would not have been martyred,
but he believed that he had family back in Scotland
that needed to hear the gospel,
and he believed that that family back in Scotland,
that their only real hope of hearing the gospel
would be if he went back and preached the gospel,
but he knew that if he went back and preached the gospel,
that it would mean that he would probably die.
Now think about that this evening.
These are things that we don't really have to consider
in America today, amen?
But he believed that that would be happening,
so he was given an invitation, according to what I read,
he was given an invitation from the university to come back
and to be able to preach the gospel.
That was a setup, all right?
Basically, what they wanted him to do
was come back and preach the gospel
so they would have public opportunity to say,
we've all heard you publicly,
now we're gonna kill you for this
because you're violating the state church.
So he knew it was a setup, but he came back anyway,
and for five weeks, he preached the gospel.
Many, many people got saved.
In fact, he started sharing the gospel
with his family members and went through the whole community,
every family member that he could talk to,
other people as well, preached for five weeks.
Five weeks, that's it.
People got saved.
It was burned at the stake.
And here, I'm gonna read to you an exact quote
of what was given, of what I was reading,
because when we yield ourselves to God,
God is glorified.
Sometimes we don't see the immediate results.
We see it in Daniel 3.
Nebuchadnezzar says, there's no God like this God.
We find that here in this case of Patrick Hamilton,
there were some immediate results, or fruit, if you will.
And here's what the account says,
that his burning, when he was burned at the stake in 1528,
had been particularly gruesome.
And here's why it was particularly gruesome,
because they had green wood,
and the wind was blowing the fire away from his body.
I can't even fully comprehend being tied to a stake,
being burned at the stake.
It's green wood, so it doesn't burn well.
And the wind is blowing the fire away from you.
So it was hours that he was there,
physically in torment, being burned alive
for preaching the gospel.
But he yielded himself to Christ.
He yielded himself to Christ.
And it says that, as a result,
he burnt for six awful hours.
How many of you have ever burned yourself on the stove?
What do you do immediately?
I mean, do you hold it there and say,
one 1,000, two 1,000?
No, like you immediately, it's a reaction.
Is it not?
Six hours.
The account goes on to say that people
who had previously heard him preach the gospel
saw in those hours the reality of his faith
and the grace of God.
The result was that so many people responded
by trusting Christ that one of the adversaries
that actually called for this man to be burned at the stake,
here's what he said.
He said, we should do this no longer.
Why?
Because if we continue to burn people at the stake
and others that are onlooking see the grace of God
and respond by being saved, it's counterproductive.
We're not getting the results that we want.
But you know what Patrick Hamilton did?
He yielded himself to God.
Tonight, I don't think any of us are being asked
to yield ourselves to God in that same fashion.
None of us.
But can I tell you, tomorrow, this evening,
there are gonna be things that come up in your life.
Are you gonna yield yourself to God?
Or are you gonna yield to self, the pressures of others,
whomever it may be that we yield to?
But we see in a real sense in Romans chapter six,
yield yourselves unto God.
And as we do, God will be glorified.
The series here on Wednesday night
is doing what we ought to do.
You do not see in Romans six the word ought.
It's not there.
But I think if you'd give me a little bit of liberty,
I could easily say this evening,
we ought to yield ourselves unto God.
I believe that it's good counsel
that God gives us, valuable counsel.
But every one of us, we have a choice.
And you're gonna have a choice tomorrow, multiple times.
Are you gonna yield to God?
Yield to yourself?
Yield to someone else?
Oh, that God would help us to yield ourselves to him
so that he would receive all the honor and the glory,
which is due unto his wonderful name.
Because we serve a great God and he's worthy of it.
He's worthy of it.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for your word, the truth that's contained therein.
And I pray, Lord, that you'd help me.
I pray that you'd help each of us, Lord,
to yield ourselves to you.
Lord, that we would set our affection on things above,
not on things of the earth.
God, we'd understand that we're dead to sin,
but alive unto you.
Thank you for saving us.
We pray, God, that you'd use us,
that we might bring honor and glory to thy name.
Bless our time of prayer. We do thank you for the privilege. I pray that you'd be honored
and glorified for it's in Christ's name we pray. Amen.