number nine this evening, Daniel chapter number nine.
If you did not receive one of the little maps outlines,
if you will, there are some in the back.
Does anyone not have a copy of this outline
of a map of the book of Revelation?
Anyone need one?
There's still some in the back, anyone?
All right, a couple of people.
Hey, Brother Joel, can you help me out?
They're right there.
Can you grab them and pass out as many as we can
that we have copies left?
And I wanna make sure that you have that.
It's not really something that you'll reference
during the message this evening per se,
but it's a resource that I wanna give you
that you can keep and reference back to
with regard to our study through the book of Revelation.
Anyone else need one?
Raise your hand nice and high.
If you want another one, go ahead.
You don't have to share.
And so Brother Magnus wants one there.
And so let's get those all distributed.
They do me no good collecting dust
on the back table there, amen?
And anyone else?
Anyone else?
All right, if you have young eyes,
you're gonna struggle to read that.
If you have not so young eyes,
you'll definitely need a magnifying glass to read that.
And we tried to make it as big.
I tried to make it as big as I could on the paper,
and it's as big as I could get it.
And so I hope that'll be a blessing to you.
My parents were watching via live stream last week,
and we had the opportunity to have lunch with them on Monday.
And so I took a couple of copies with me,
and I said to my mom when I got there,
I said, hey, I brought these in case you want them.
She's like, you read my mind.
And I'm like, it's impossible.
I can't do that, amen?
But I wanna make sure that everyone that wants one has one,
and appreciate the opportunity
to be able to give you some resources such as that.
If you have any questions, let me know about that.
If you want it emailed to you, I could do that as well.
And that might allow you to be able to blow that up
and see some of the details
maybe a little easier on your computer there.
Daniel chapter number nine
is where we'll be this evening.
Last week, we took the entirety of our service
to examine the passage there in Revelation chapter number five.
We started by talking about the scroll,
and then of course our Savior,
and then the song as you conclude
Revelation chapter number five.
And I mentioned as I was preaching last Sunday evening
that most likely the scroll of Revelation five
is the book of prophecy that Daniel was commanded to shut up.
And we looked at that in Daniel 12 last week,
did some comparisons and what have you.
But we also mentioned this.
If you look in the beginning of Revelation five,
the Bible says that the scroll there
was sealed with seven seals.
As you begin reading Revelation chapter number six,
you find that it begins with the first seal being opened
and then each subsequent seal thereafter
until they're all opened.
And here in Daniel chapter number nine
in verses 24 through 27,
it provides us with a prophecy
that I believe is important for us to understand
as it pertains to the book of Revelation,
and specifically with regard to the 70th week,
the seven year tribulation.
I said this as well last week,
and that is when we talk about the tribulation,
we talk about the rapture,
and we talk about all of those things
with regard to eschatology and end times.
And the importance for me is I've studied the scriptures
and trying to answer the question regarding the timing.
So many people wanna know about the timing,
and I believe that it's best
that we answer first,
why is there going to be a tribulation?
Why is there going to be a rapture?
And when we can answer those two questions biblically,
then I believe it helps us to be able to say when.
Now I'm not saying when as in setting a date,
but I'm saying when as in the sequence of events.
Does that make sense?
And is it the tribulation followed by the rapture?
Is it the rapture followed by the tribulation?
And so on and so forth.
And so it's more about the sequential order of the events,
not setting a time for the events.
So we answer the question why,
and it helps us then be able to dig in
and answer the question when.
This, in verse number 24, I'm gonna read the portion,
I'm gonna read verse 24 through 27 of Daniel nine,
and then get into it this evening.
Notice in verse 24, Daniel, by the way,
if you start looking in Daniel one,
it says in the first year of Darius,
the son of Ahasuerus, of the seed of the Medes,
which was made king over the realm of the Chaldeans.
In the first year of his reign,
I, Daniel, understood by books the number of the years
whereof the word of the Lord came to Jeremiah the prophet,
that he would accomplish 70 years
in the desolations of Jerusalem.
And that's dealing with the captivity,
the Babylonian captivity, the prophecies of Jeremiah.
He says that regarding to the Jeremiah the prophet,
and so on and so forth, and Daniel's reading that,
and he understood that it would be a 70-year captivity.
And there now, at the end of that 70 years,
Daniel's understanding this.
Daniel then immediately begins to pray.
We don't have time to read the entirety of Daniel nine,
but in verse three, he begins to seek the face of the Lord.
The Bible says that he's praying, he's fasting,
and he's seeking the Lord for answers
with regard to all that is taking place.
The answer comes at the end of the chapter
by way of this prophecy that we'll look at.
And notice the Bible says, in verse number 24,
70 weeks are determined upon thy people
and upon thy holy city to finish the transgression
and to make an end of sins
and to make reconciliation for iniquity
and to bring in everlasting righteousness
and to seal up the vision and prophecy
and to anoint the most holy.
Notice verse 25, how it begins.
Know therefore and understand
that from the going forth of the commandment
to restore and to build Jerusalem
unto the Messiah, the Prince,
shall be seven weeks and threescore and two weeks.
The street shall be built again
and the wall even in troubleless times.
And after threescore and two weeks
shall Messiah be cut off, but not for himself.
And the people of the Prince that shall come
shall destroy the city and the sanctuary
and the end thereof shall be with a flood
and unto the end of the war,
desolations are determined.
Verse 24, and he shall confirm the covenant
with many for one week.
And the he in verse 27, dealing with the Prince
at the end of verse number 26,
and in the midst of the week,
he shall cause the sacrifice and the oblation to cease.
And for the overspreading of abominations,
he shall make it desolate, even unto the consummation
and that determined shall be poured upon the desolate.
As you look in verse number 24,
I'm not gonna read it again,
I just read it a moment ago.
But verse number 24 of Daniel nine
provides a general overview of this entire prophecy.
Verses 25, 26, and 27 then provide us with more details
with regard to the specific events
and the number of weeks between those particular events.
The 70 weeks that are mentioned here,
literally it means 77s,
and we understand it to mean 490 years.
It's not 70 weeks as in 490 days.
We know that all of the events that are recorded here
with regard to the prophecy
were not fulfilled in those days,
but we find that it would be 490 years.
Historically, by the way,
490 years of increments for Israel's history
are seen in a variety of ways.
Number one, between Abraham and the conquest is 490 years,
between Joshua and the kingdom is 490 years,
and between David and the captivity is 490 years.
And so we find here that when you begin reading verse 24,
70 weeks, 77s, the reference is with regard to 490 years.
By the way, Daniel was already thinking about years
according to verse number two that I read earlier,
and so we find that this gives us the opportunity
to understand the timeframe.
Now, we have the privilege
of being on this side of the prophecy,
and therefore, we can look back at history,
at the portion of the prophecy
that's already been fulfilled,
and conclude with certainty that it's 490 years,
not 490 days.
And there's no way that the events
that are recorded here in Daniel 9
were concluded or fulfilled in 490 days,
and so we see that it's specifically dealing with 490 years.
Now, that's important, again,
as we begin to unlock the truth of the book of Revelation
and how the book of Daniel gives us kind of a key
to understanding what we're going to study
here in the weeks ahead in the book of Revelation.
Understand all scripture is given by inspiration of God,
but also no scriptures of any private interpretation,
and so the Bible is to be interpreted by the Bible
as we compare scripture with scripture,
and what an opportunity that we have before us
with having the entire canon of scripture.
It's also important to note that the prophecy
that is given to us in Daniel 9, verses 24 through 27,
is specifically regarding the nation of Israel.
Notice again, specifically in verse 24,
Daniel's the one praying.
We mentioned as you start the chapter
that Daniel's the one that's recognizing,
he's understanding things, he's praying,
he's seeking for answers.
It says that he's informed and he's given this truth.
And notice in verse 24, the Bible says 70 weeks are determined upon thy people.
Of course, we understand that Daniel was Jewish,
and therefore the prophecy is specific with regard to the people of Daniel, which would be Israel.
Furthermore, it continues and says, and upon thy holy city.
So we understand another reference, not only upon thy people,
but we see that it says upon thy holy city, that being Jerusalem,
and understanding again the specifics with regard to this particular prophecy.
Now the big question that we must answer is when does the clock start?
490 years from what? 490 years till what?
How do we determine? How do we figure that out?
And by the way, the God who is eternal, he's the one that has provided this prophecy,
this revelation to Daniel that's been recorded for us.
And verse 25 specifically gives us the key that starts the clock.
Notice in verse 25 again, he starts out by saying, know therefore and understand.
And then notice the very next statement that from the going forth of the commandment
to restore and to build Jerusalem.
And so that's the first, that's what starts the clock.
That commandment that would be given with regard to rebuilding,
not rebuilding the temple, but we find that it says specifically
from the going forth of the commandment to restore and to build Jerusalem.
And so it's important that we see the distinction because there are many decrees.
Cyrus gave a decree. We see some decrees that are given.
And where do we start the clock for this first period of seven weeks?
Those seven weeks would relate to 49 years.
And we find that as you begin to look at this and understand the commandment that would go forth,
we read of it in the book of Nehemiah.
Turn over, if you will, to Nehemiah chapter number two.
Nehemiah chapter two.
And I want you to notice, of course, Nehemiah is there and he's sent for a report
according to chapter number one.
He's in captivity, but he's asked, how are things going?
Give me a report of the city and so on and so forth.
And he receives word and it breaks his heart.
He's seeking the Lord. He's praying. He's mourning.
The Bible says that he wept and he fasted and all of these things are taking place.
And then in chapter number two of the book of Nehemiah,
we find that Nehemiah, as the king's cupbearer, that he would go before King Artaxerxes.
And when he goes before King Artaxerxes, the Bible says, it tells us,
and it came to pass in the month Nisan in the 20th year of Artaxerxes the king.
And so you can specifically see in verse number one of chapter two
that God is giving us a specific time frame with regard to what's happening.
So there's no ambiguity. There's no need for speculation.
He's telling us the timing of Artaxerxes and the timing in which Nehemiah comes into his presence.
You can look at other records and be able to determine that this is 444 BC.
So notice it says that wine was before him, the latter part of verse two,
and I took up the wine and gave it unto the king, fulfilling his duties and obligations.
And it says now I had not been before time sad in his presence.
Wherefore, the king said unto me, why is thy countenance sad?
Seeing thou art not sick, this is nothing else but sorrow of heart.
Then I was sore afraid and said unto the king, let the king live forever.
Why should not my countenance be sad when the city, the place of my father's sepulchres,
lieth waste and the gates thereof are consumed with fire?
Verse four, then the king said unto me, for what dost thou make request?
So I prayed to the God of heaven.
Verse five, and I said unto the king.
That was a quick prayer, but he'd already spent much time in prayer according to chapter one.
And it reminds us of the importance of praying and how God hears and answers.
It says, I said unto the king, if it please the king and if thy servant have found favor in thy sight,
that thou wouldest send me unto Judah, unto the city of my father's sepulchres, that I may build it.
All right, so where does he want to go? He wants to go to the city.
We find that he's giving reference, as you look back to chapter number one,
as I mentioned a moment ago, that he was inquiring specifically at the end of verse number two concerning Jerusalem.
Of course, as we look at Daniel chapter nine and look at all that's taking place.
So Nehemiah standing before Artaxerxes makes the request in verse number five,
and we read in verse number six that the king said unto me,
the queen also sitting by him, for how long shall thy journey be?
And when wilt thou return?
So it pleased the king to send me and I set him a time.
Moreover, I said unto the king, if it please the king,
let letters be given me to the governors beyond the river that they may convey me over till I come into Judah.
And a letter unto Asaph, the keeper of the king's forest,
that he may give me timber to make beams for the gates of the palace,
which appertain to the house and for the wall of the city and for the house that I shall enter into.
And the king granted me according to the good hand of my God upon me.
And so we find as we read here in Nehemiah chapter two,
that we're reading about this starting of the clock when it says in Daniel nine in verse number twenty five,
know therefore and understand that from the going forth of the commandment to restore and to build Jerusalem unto the Messiah,
the prince shall be seven weeks and three score and two weeks.
The street shall be built again and the wall even in trouble as times.
And so as you read the latter part of verse twenty five,
when the Bible says the street shall be built again and the wall even in trouble as times,
I don't have time this evening to read the entirety of Nehemiah chapter four, five and six.
But if you were to go back or if you're familiar with those portions of Scripture,
you will find that it was built in trouble as times.
And so you find that here is where the clock is going to start.
And it's those first seven weeks.
It's the commandment, the issuing of the commandment was given as we read there in Nehemiah chapter two.
It's fulfilled in Nehemiah chapter four, Nehemiah chapters four through six.
And we find that that would be seven weeks or forty nine years.
Now, the second part of that verse twenty five is an additional sixty two weeks.
And that's dealing with the Messiah being crucified.
Of course, we understand Messiah being the Lord Jesus Christ, though he came to his own and his own received him,
not Jewish people, the nation of Israel as a whole.
They rejected the Lord Jesus Christ as being their Messiah.
They were the ones that cried out, crucify him.
We have no king but Caesar.
You can read that. You can understand that.
But we find that that would be sixty two weeks or four hundred and thirty four years.
Now, it's interesting if you take the seven weeks and you take the sixty two weeks and you start at the place that we spoke of in Nehemiah,
four forty four B.C. and you add those four hundred and eighty three years, you come to thirty A.D.
And you find that it's speaking here about the fact that Messiah would be crucified in verse twenty six.
It says that in after three score and two weeks shall Messiah notice what it says, be cut off, but not for himself.
The sacrifice of the Lord Jesus Christ on the cross of Calvary, his was a substitutionary atonement.
He didn't die for his own sins. He died for the sins of the world, the just for the unjust.
We are reminded where the Bible tells us that he hath made him to be sin for us who knew no sin,
that we might be made the righteousness of God in him.
And so we see the fulfillment of that as we find the reference here in verse twenty five and twenty six.
Now, it's interesting because I want you to consider a couple of things with regard to this prophecy and with regard to the timing.
And so we're looking at sixty nine weeks, the seven weeks and the sixty two weeks, these two events.
And we're looking at the fulfillment of this. When does the clock start?
He says in verse twenty five, it starts when that commandment goes forth.
And we begin to see and we look at that and the God that gave the prophecy, we see that it's fulfilled.
Now, here's something interesting.
If you begin to understand what we're looking at this evening and then couple it with what we read of in the Gospels,
even about the birth of Christ, you begin to think about the wise men.
Right. And you begin to think about what they would have been privy to with regard to having the scriptures.
And you read in Matthew chapter number two with regard to a passage that we normally deal with at the Christmas season.
But this records for us that these wise men came to Jerusalem and they said,
Where is he that is born King of the Jews?
For we have seen a star in the east and are come to worship him.
When they finally get to Bethlehem as they follow the star, they rejoice with exceeding great joy.
And the Bible tells us that they enter in and they worship Jesus by presenting him gifts.
By the way, the gifts that they offer, gold, frankincense, and myrrh,
would not only remind us of his proper place as being King, but his purpose of dying in our place.
And it's absolutely phenomenal when you see that.
Not only do we see the wise men, but I want to remind you in Luke chapter number two of Simeon and Anna.
And if you look over in Luke chapter number two, and I want you to just consider this tonight
as you think about the timing of all that's going on with regard to Daniel's prophecy
and looking at the years going forward and these weeks being fulfilled as they had been prophesied.
We read in Luke chapter number two, again, a portion that we often look to during the Christmas season.
But look, if you will, at verse number 21.
The Bible says, and when eight days were accomplished for the circumcision of the child,
his name was called Jesus, which was so named of the angel before he was conceived in the womb.
When the days of her purification, according to the law of Moses, were accomplished,
they brought him to Jerusalem to present him to the Lord.
By the way, they're following the law as it's been prescribed.
They're doing all that they're supposed to do.
It says in verse 23, as it is written in the law of the Lord,
every male that openeth the womb shall be called holy to the Lord
and to offer a sacrifice according to that which is said in the law of the Lord,
a pair of turtle doves or two young pigeons.
Verse 25, and behold, there was a man in Jerusalem whose name was Simeon.
The same man was just and devout.
Notice what it says, waiting for the consolation of Israel and the Holy Ghost was upon him.
And it was revealed unto him by the Holy Ghost that he should not see death
before he had seen the Lord's Christ.
Isn't that exciting?
You begin to think about Simeon having all the records that he would have had
being this Jewish man and understanding Daniel's prophecy,
understanding the going forth of the commandment.
Those 49 years were fulfilled just as they said they would be.
And then you have these other 62 weeks, these years that would be fulfilled.
And here the Holy Ghost using God's word, no doubt, is confirming to him.
And it says in verse 27, notice it says here,
and he came by the Spirit into the temple.
And when the parents brought in the child Jesus to do for him after the custom of the law,
then took him up in his arms and blessed God.
Man, what an exciting record that God gives us of this event
and the fulfillment and Simeon being there and all that's taking place.
But there's also Anna.
Look down at verse number 36, if you will, in Luke 2 and verse 36.
And there was one Anna, a prophetess, the daughter of Phanuel of the tribe of Asher.
She was of great age and had lived with a husband seven years from her virginity.
And she was a widow of about four score and four years,
which departed not from the temple,
but served God with fastings and prayers night and day.
Verse 38, and she coming in that instant gave thanks likewise unto the Lord
and spake of him to all them that looked for redemption in Jerusalem.
Why were they looking for redemption?
Because of the prophecy.
And you begin to understand that not only the prophecies that we're reading here of Daniel 9,
there are plenty of other prophecies with regard to the coming of Messiah,
how was it that they knew after the inquiry that was made,
where is he that is born King of the Jews, the going ghetto, and Bethlehem of Judah,
for thus it is written in the prophets.
And they reference back to Micah chapter 5 in verse number 2.
So as we begin to look at all of these things and piece it all together,
we find that the first 69 weeks of this prophecy have been fulfilled literally.
Not only do we see that they've been fulfilled literally,
but we also acknowledge that there's an obvious gap between the 69th week and the 70th week.
Why do we know that or why do we conclude that?
Well, because of the additional seven years of that 70th week
were to just be tacked on to the end of the 69th week without any delay
or without any gap as we'd refer to it.
You would find that that would take us to 37 AD
and the prophecy that Daniel records that's given to him,
that revelation in Daniel 9, 24, 27, would be completed, but it's not.
And so therefore, it seems quite obvious that there is a gap between the 69th and 70th week.
You ask, how long is the gap? I don't know.
You ask, why is there a gap? Because when Messiah was cut off,
it's like the clock stopped as far as those weeks of this prophecy are concerned.
What started the clock was the commandment going forth.
What stopped the clock was the Messiah, our Lord, being cut off, the substitutionary atonement.
And we find that there's this gap and we begin to look at the gap.
I would say it this way, that we're living in the gap.
We don't know how long the gap is.
We'd refer to it as being the church age.
And how long is the church age?
Well, it started at Pentecost and it ends with the rapture.
And so we don't know exactly how long it is, but we're in that period of time as we speak.
All of that is introduction. And it's 646. Amen.
And all of that is really to bring us to the 70th week that begins in Revelation chapter 6.
And don't worry, the introduction is the bulk of the message this evening.
And we'll get into all of these things as we study through the book of Revelation here on Sunday nights going forward.
But we find that the, remember, the beginning of Revelation chapter 4,
John is caught up and we recognize that being a picture, a type, if you will, of the rapture.
The church is mentioned in Revelation 2, in Revelation 3, and then there's no more reference of the church.
And we find that the rapture takes place, Revelation 4 and 5, as we've mentioned, as we've studied through those two chapters,
that really is a parenthetical, if you will, when it's giving us a scene in heaven as to what's going on.
And as we talked about in the very beginning of our study of the book of Revelation,
the book of Revelation will address events going on in heaven, events going on on earth.
But we find that some of those things might be taking place simultaneous as you're writing it.
You can't really write those things simultaneous because it would be extremely confusing.
So Revelation 4 and 5 are this parenthetical that's giving us the scene in the throne room of heaven,
all of the worship that's taking place, all the things that are unfolding for us.
And then we come, as we studied last week in Revelation chapter 5, that scroll and it's sealed.
And remember, John wept much. Why? Because there was no one that was found that was worthy.
But then he begins to rejoice. Why? Because Jesus, the one who had prevailed,
the one who had been slain, but now is alive, the one who bled and died, and he redeemed us,
and all that we looked at, and the scroll is going to be opened as you read Revelation 6 and verse number 1.
That's the first seal being opened. And so we find that going forward,
those additional seals will be open, and they're open very quickly in rapid succession,
as best we can tell as you look at the scriptures. So here's the point.
If the 69 weeks, or not if, but since the 69 weeks have been fulfilled literally,
we then expect that the 70th week will be fulfilled literally as well.
In other words, let me say it this way, there's no need to spiritualize the 70th week of Daniel's prophecy.
And sometimes what happens when you start talking about eschatology, and you start talking about
prophecy and the fulfillment of prophecy, sometimes there's a means, if you will, a mode of interpretation
that's not a literal interpretation, but they try to spiritualize things. But if 69 weeks,
or since the 69 weeks have been fulfilled literally, we would have every reason to believe
and to expect that the 70th week would also be fulfilled literally. Now, we talk about the 70th week.
The Bible says, as we pick it back up in Daniel 9 and verse 26,
and after threescore and two weeks shall Messiah be cut off, but not for himself,
and the people of the prince that shall come, notice it says shall destroy the city and the sanctuary.
Some people misinterpret the prince in verse 26 there as being the Lord, but the behavior is not,
it's not the Lord. That's not what he's going to do. This is antichrist. And so it says,
and the people of the prince that shall come shall destroy the city and the sanctuary,
and the end thereof shall be with a flood, and unto the end of the war desolations are determined.
And then it says, and he shall confirm. And so he, the prince that...
mentioned at the end of verse 26 is, and this is where we understand how God is
revealing to us this 70th week that we're speaking of, of Daniel's prophecy.
69 are behind us, there's a gap that we're living in, and there's the 70th
week that we expect to be fulfilled. Literally seven weeks we refer to it as
the tribulation. When we begin to understand the tribulation, we understand
that the tribulation, according to verse number 27, is really divided into two
parts. There's the first half, and there's the second half. Just as we said what
starts the clock for the first seven weeks, those 49 years, the going of the
commandment, we could ask the question, what starts the 70th week? Well, the
rapture. The rapture takes place, that 70th week begins the seven years of
tribulation, and that seven-year period of time is gonna be separated, divided, if
you will, in two, three and a half years, three and a half years. How do we know
that? Well, the Bible says, and in the midst of the week. And so there's
something very specific that's going to happen at the midpoint of the
tribulation. At the midpoint of the tribulation, that specific thing that's
gonna happen is not the rapture. That thing that's going to happen is the
agreement is going to be broken. And so what is it that the Antichrist does when
he first comes on the scene? We find that the rapture takes place, the
Antichrist comes on the scene, and as we look in verse 27, the first thing that he
does is he makes a seven-year pact or agreement. We find that it says, and he
shall confirm the covenant with many for one week. This is a covenant, a pact, a
treaty, a peace treaty, a peace agreement. We use various words to describe that,
but that's what the Antichrist is going to do at the start of the 70th week, the
tribulation. Now, I've often said this, and it's important that we recognize this, we
look at various things, and obviously right now we're dealing with an
extremely hot time in the Middle East. And you see what's going on in the news
and all the things that are taking place, and you begin to see all of that
and understand the great turmoil that's there, and all of the fighting. And by
the way, it is a tragic thing when life is lost, and we ought not rejoice in
that. And we understand that people are dying, and when somebody takes their
final breath here, that means they enter into eternity. And when we understand the
truth of the Scripture, that ought to cause us to be concerned for the souls
of humanity. I will say, as I said even to the men yesterday on the men's prayer
breakfast, and it's not a political statement, it is a biblical statement,
Persia, Iran is Persia, and Persia is not going anywhere. Okay? Persia is a major,
major player at the end times world events. And so Persia is not going
anywhere, and we find that there's all sorts of things going on, and all the
rhetoric, and all of the threats, and so on and so forth. But understand that in
order for the Antichrist to come and make this amazing pact and peace treaty,
there's got to be great turmoil. You have no turmoil, you need no peace agreement.
Does this make sense? And so we find, and again, it's not that we're sitting here
and like, oh we're so worried. No, things are not falling apart, things are falling
in place. We may have some level of concern, maybe some have a level of
anxiety, you're watching the news too much, and you need to read the Bible
more, but the reality is that yes, there's crazy things going on in the world, but
those things don't surprise God. It's all falling into place. I don't know when the
rapture is going to happen, I don't know how much needs to be set up before the
rapture takes place, but I know everything's coming into proper
alignment. And we begin to look here, and we see this 70th week, and it starts with
that Antichrist making that seven-year pact, but we also find that
there's three and a half years into it. Notice it says, and he shall confirm the
covenant with many for one week. And in the midst of the week, so at the midpoint,
it says that he shall cause the sacrifice and the oblation to cease. So
there's going to be a temple. You say, no, there's not going to be a temple. There's
going to be a temple. You say, but what about the Temple Mount? There's going to
be a temple, all right? I don't know how it's all gonna play out, I don't know how
the Antichrist is gonna make the agreement, and all the players are gonna
be involved, but the reality, and listen, if you watch and you understand what's
going on, they're ready for the temple. I mean, they got all the things in place
that they need. They will boast about how quickly they can build it once they
get the green light. They're not gonna get the green light until the Antichrist
comes, and that peace treaty is given, and we find that it's going to be set up,
it's going to be built, and there will be offerings that are made, sacrifices that
are made, but at the midpoint, he's gonna cause the Antichrist, the sacrifice, the
oblation to cease for the over spreading of abominations. Listen, he shall make it
desolate, even into the consummation, and that determined shall be poured upon the
desolate. You ever hear that term, the abomination of desolation? And this is
what we read. Paul's talking to the church in Thessalonica about this in
2 Thessalonians chapter 2. In fact, why don't you turn there and look at it
quickly with me this evening. I'm not gonna finish the message this evening. I
realize I got a lot more notes than I thought I had on the last situation here,
but that's okay. And 1 Thessalonians chapter 2, we'll do a part 2 next week,
and the blessings of being a pastor that you can say, we will continue, and what a
blessing. And I remember when I used to preach for my pastor and fill in, you had
to say it all, or you weren't gonna have another opportunity for a couple of
months before you preached again, and so that is a difference in an opportunity
that I am thankful for. In chapter number 2 of the book of 2 Thessalonians,
the Bible says in verse number 1,
Now we beseech you, brethren, by the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, and by
our gathering unto him, that you be not soon shaken in mind or troubled, neither
by spirit nor by word nor by letter as from us, as that the day of Christ is at
hand. Let no man deceive you by any means. For that day shall not come except there
come a falling away first, and that man of sin be revealed, the son of perdition.
Verse 4, Who opposeth and exalteth himself above all that is called God, or
that is worship, notice this, so that he as God sitteth in the temple of God,
showing himself that he is God. That's the midpoint of the tribulation. We find
that that pact is going to end at that midpoint. It's broken, and we find
that at the end, those last three and a half years of the tribulation, by the way,
also referred to as the time of Jacob's trouble, again a reference with regard to
Israel, that at the end of that seven years, the Lord Jesus Christ, our Messiah,
if you read Revelation 19, will return with his saints, not for his saints, but
with his saints, and establish his millennial reign, the millennial kingdom
of Christ. It is a literal thousand-year reign, and it will be established. You
read Revelation 19, and you see all that's taking place. Revelation 20, that
Satan will be bound for those thousand years, and all that transpires there, and
so we find that the Lord Jesus Christ will establish his millennial reign. It's
important, and I emphasize that he returns with his saints, because you have
to acknowledge, as you study the New Testament, that the Scriptures plainly
say that there's a time in which Jesus is coming for his saints, and there's a time
in which he's coming with his saints. And coming for and coming with are two
different things, and we see that as the rapture followed by the return. By the
way, there's other aspects of that that are important to understand. At the
rapture, Jesus comes, and we meet him in the air. At the end of the seven-year
tribulation, when he comes back with his saints, his foot actually comes down and
is on the Mount of Olives, and all that takes place according to Zechariah
chapter 14. And so we find that these things will happen. This 70th week, again,
we're in the gap. We don't know exactly, we're not trying to say when it will
happen, but we know when the clock starts at the rapture, that seven-year period of
time, known as the tribulation. During that period of time, and next week
we'll deal with the purpose. Really, there's threefold purpose that we're
gonna look at as to why there's going to be this seven-year tribulation. Again,
that helps us with answering the when, but understand that in Revelation
chapter 6 and verse number 1 is the first seal, and the seven seals go
through Revelation 8 and verse number 6. Then you have the seven trumpets, and
those seven trumpet judgments start immediately in Revelation 8, verse number
7, and go through Revelation 9 and verse 21. Then there's some things that are
recorded for us in the next several chapters of the book of Revelation. Again,
things that we will study and we will work through, but you then find the seven
vials or the seven bold judgments begin in Revelation 15 verse 1 and go through
chapter 16 and verse number 21, and those are, if you will, those three sets
of seven major judgments that are going to take place during the
the tribulation.
Next week, we will look at the purpose of the tribulation.
Why is it that God has recorded,
why is it that this prophecy is given to Daniel
in Daniel chapter number nine,
with regard to all of these things,
with regard to the timing this 70th week.
Again, as we understand the purpose
and why God is going to do this,
it helps us to answer the question when,
but I believe that it's also important
with all of that, which I've shared this evening,
it's important for us to understand the timeline
and to understand what's taking place,
because we will begin reading Revelation six
in verse number one,
and you begin to see that it just immediately starts
after we have all that worship that's going on
in chapters four and five,
and I saw when the lamb opened one of the seals,
and bam, that's what we're gonna be seeing
with the tribulation.
This is the first of those,
and by the way,
it's a preview for a couple of weeks from now.
If you look at some online things,
they'll try to tell you that the one that's coming
there in Revelation six, one and two is Jesus Christ,
and that is a lie.
That is the antichrist,
and it's important that we interpret scripture properly,
and there's so many things out there.
In fact, I listened to somebody,
before I started teaching the teen Sunday school class,
I was kind of bouncing back and forth,
and we're sitting in Brother Mark's class,
and somebody in the class, I won't say who,
though I remember who it was,
they said, you know, I was so confused
because I did a quick search
of who this is in Revelation six,
and it said it was Jesus.
No, it's not.
It's the antichrist,
and so where do we get our doctrine?
From the Bible, amen?
We wanna be sound in the faith.
We wanna have sound doctrine.
We get it from the word of God,
and we understand that is the antichrist.
Again, we'll look at that in a couple of weeks.
Next week, the purpose of the tribulation.
I know I gave a lot of information this evening,
a lot of things with regard to the prophecy.
I believe it's important,
and it helps us understand
as we're going to begin digging
into this period of time
that Revelation talks about,
we're gonna see all of these things
that are happening, great destruction,
and judgment, and all that's unfolding,
and we have to understand
why these things are taking place.
Why has God given this to us
so that we can have an understanding
of this 70th week that, as I mentioned already,
will be fulfilled literally
just as the other 69 weeks
have already been fulfilled?
Let's pray.
Father, we do love you.
We thank you so much for loving us.
We thank you for your word.
We thank you that we can study your word.
We thank you that your word is true,
that your word is accurate,
and we thank you, God,
that you have given it to us,
even as you mentioned in that portion
of scripture to Daniel,
to know and to understand,
and yes, there are times
in which we come to portions of scripture
that are more difficult
than other portions of scripture,
but, God, I pray that you'd help us
to be students of the word
and that you'd help us not to be tossed
to and fro with every wind of doctrine.
Lord, help us to be grounded and settled.
Lord, I pray that you'd help us
to have a clear understanding
of these things that we will study
through the book of Revelation.
I pray, Father, that in the moment
of invitation this evening,
perhaps some just wanna thank you
for your blessings and, Lord, for your word,
however it is that you may have worked
in hearts and lives,
would you help us tonight to be responsive?
Well, thank you, God, for what you'll do
for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand?