3, James chapter number 3, and the portion of scripture that's before us this morning
is exceedingly applicable. It's something that's so important for every single one of
us and I've mentioned this many times as we've been studying here on Sunday mornings through
the book of James and that is this, that the book of James is an extremely practical book.
By the way I'm thankful that God's word is practical, it's applicable. We study the
scriptures and we want to find out what is God revealing to me, what is God expecting
for me to apply in my life from the portion of scripture that I've read, what should I
stop doing based on what I've read, what should I start doing based upon what I've read. So
we find that as we look here at the book of James, again being extremely practical in
nature, talking about the subject of spiritual maturity, growing in our walk with the Lord.
We find that we come to James chapter number 3 and as we begin studying this portion of
scripture we find that the principle that was really given to us in James 1 and verse
19 will be further developed in the first 12 verses of James chapter number 3. So let
me remind you that James 1 and verse 19 says this, wherefore my beloved brethren, let every
man be swift to hear, notice this, slow to speak, slow to wrath. And so the subject that
is before us in James chapter number 3 verses 1 through 12 is really the subject about our
tongue and about the words that we use. We find that I've titled the message Guard Your
Tongue, the Bible has much to say about our words. In fact as you study through the scriptures,
specifically if you study the book of Proverbs, there's much that's given to us in the book
of Proverbs about our words. In fact we'll look at a number of those verses even this
morning as we begin to think about how much God's word says about our words. I think that
if we'd be honest this morning that we'd recognize how much we need the instruction.
Not only how much we need the instruction but how much we need the Lord's help to guard
our tongue. Have you ever said something and then regretted it? If not, if you're here
this morning and you've never said anything that you've not regretted I'll let you preach
this morning. I mean honestly, I'll sit down and you can preach. But I think every one
of us, if we're honest before the Lord, there's been something that we've said that we say,
man I wish I didn't say it that way. Or maybe you say I wish I didn't say it at all. Right?
Have you ever heard the expression that you open mouth and insert foot and you say I've
done that before, you know what I mean? And the idea of thinking before we speak and we
say, man my tongue got so far ahead of my thought process it was just going, right?
We're just speaking. And the reality is that we need God's help in this area of guarding
our tongues. As we look at James chapter number 3 and we look at this portion I'll begin reading,
I'll just read the first four verses and then we'll get through verse number 12 this morning.
But notice the Bible says this, my brethren, be not many masters, the idea is a teacher,
knowing that we shall receive the greater condemnation. For in many things we offend
all. If any man offend not in word, the same is a perfect man, complete, enable also to
bridle the whole body. Behold, we put bits in the horse's mouths that they may obey us,
and we turn about their whole body. Behold, verse 4, also the ships, which though they
be so great and are driven of fierce winds, yet are they turned about with a very small
helm whithersoever the governor listeth. I'll read verse 5 as well, even so the tongue is
a little member, and boasteth great things. Behold, how great a matter a little fire kindleth.
If you've lived for any period of time, you know the danger that your tongue can get you
in. Amen? We know the importance as being a child of God of guarding our tongue. If
you're taking notes this morning, I want you to, number 1, acknowledge the impact. Acknowledge
the impact. We find in verse number 1 that the Bible begins talking about the words and
using our words, be not many masters, and the idea of being a teacher. He says in verse
number 2 that in many things we offend all. If any man offend not in word. And so we find
that immediately to start the chapter, he's talking about the use of our words. And I
said this several weeks ago, it was actually the beginning of the month of April on Wednesday
evening. I was talking about our words, and I did some research, and it says that the
average person, and I understand that we're not all average, and I understand there are
various things that will impact the average for each of us, and there are variables. But
it says that the average individual speaks 10 to 16,000 words every day. That's a lot
of words. You say I'm nowhere near that. Well remember, there are variables. Men, women,
I won't say any more there. Occupation, right, personality. I speak more words than probably
most of you speak because of what I do. And Joseph said to me this week, he said you just
talk too much. And what he was saying about that was about my voice. You can hear my voice
kind of struggling a little bit. He said you just need to not talk for a day. And he's
like that's going to be impossible for you. And the reality is I go and I meet with people,
and I talk to people on the phone and all kinds of things, right. But we understand
the use of our words. Now let me say this. We talk about acknowledging the impact. Our
words are powerful. Our words are powerful. And we find that this morning when we look
at that statistic and that average of 10 to 16,000 words each day, I would say this
as we begin to try to really nail down in the time in which we live, the era in which
we live. Yes, there are spoken words, but I want you to think about the words that we
use. It's not always our spoken words. Think about your written words. Think about the
way that we write words today. I mean there was a day that you had to write a letter,
right. You had to actually physically put it in an envelope and put it in the mail and
put postage on it. Now it cost almost a dollar to put a stamp on an envelope. And we find
that there's written letters. But what about text messages? What about emails? What about
social media posts? Our words. You say well I didn't speak those words yet, but you wrote
those words. How many of you ever sent a text message or you were trying to send a
text message and you say you know what, it would be better to make a phone call on this
because sometimes the tenor of the message doesn't really go through properly on a text
message. Social media posts, we're like I can delete it. It's there somewhere. Someone
can find it. We've seen that proven over and over. Sometimes people get behind a computer
and they just start going crazy on that keyboard and just words are just flying out. And we
have to acknowledge the impact of our words. We find in verse number five that it says
it's a little member. The tongue is a little member. And we understand again the context.
They didn't have email and text messaging and they didn't have social media posts and
all of that. But we need to make it applicable to us and our lives today. Well I didn't speak
anything verbally. I just wrote it. No, no, no. The principle is still there. And so we
find that as we look here it says it's a little member. The tongue is a little member. And
boasteth great things. Notice it says behold how great a matter a little fire kindleth.
And then in verse six it says and the tongue is a fire. A world of iniquity. I mean how
many times we've said something and maybe even as the words are coming out we're saying
man I shouldn't have said it that way. And then it turns into a big old discussion, argument,
whatever word you want to use. And we think about the impact of our words. We must acknowledge
it says that it's a fire in verse number six. A world of iniquity. So is the tongue among
our members that it defileth the whole body and setteth on fire the course of nature and
it is set on fire of hell. Wow. The impact of our tongue, of our words. We must acknowledge
the power. It says in verse number eight the tongue can no man tame. Notice how it describes
it as an unruly evil full of deadly poison. Your words make an impact on others. Your
words make an impact on others. It's amazing how quickly we can tear somebody down with
our words. But we also understand how we can build somebody up with our words. Why? Because
there's power in our words.
We must acknowledge that this morning.
We must acknowledge the impact.
Look at the book of Proverbs, if you will.
And I'm gonna start in chapter 18
and then go back to chapter 15,
because I really want to look at this verse first,
in Proverbs 18 and verse 21.
We'll look at a few different portions
of the book of Proverbs here this morning.
But notice as we acknowledge the impact here
this morning of our words,
in Proverbs 18 and verse number 21,
notice what the Bible says.
Death and life are in the power of the tongue.
They that love it shall eat the fruit thereof.
So think about this.
Death and life are in the power of the tongue.
The impact of our words.
Your words are powerful.
My words are powerful.
Your written words, your spoken words,
those social media posts, they're powerful words.
Death and life are in the power of the tongue.
In chapter 15 of the book of Proverbs,
turn a few pages back in your Bible there
and notice as we would think about it
from a positive perspective,
the Bible says this in Proverbs 15 and verse 23.
A man hath joy by the answer of his mouth
in a word spoken in due season.
Notice what it says.
How good is it?
Have you ever had that situation
where someone just gave you a word
and it was like, man, it was a perfect.
It was what I needed in that moment.
And how good is it?
I mean, it encouraged me.
It gave me the hope and the confidence
and the encouragement that I needed
for whatever I was facing,
for whatever I was dealing with.
And man, that word that is spoken in due season.
He says in chapter 25 in verse number 11, look there.
Again, I know we're turning to several different places,
but I want you to think about
and acknowledge the impact of our words this morning.
In Proverbs 25 in verse number 11,
the Bible says a word fitly spoken
is like apples of gold in pictures of silver.
Isn't that a great analogy?
A word fitly spoken.
The appropriateness.
Again, as we talk about that word in due season
and the impact that it could have on someone.
Listen, there are people that are hurting.
There are people that need a voice, a word of encouragement.
The Bible tells us that we're to edify, we're to build up.
And we many times can do that through our words.
And it's not always a spoken word
because we live in this era of history
where so many of our words are communicated,
not verbally, but they're written.
And I want us to really focus on that this morning.
The impact.
In chapter 26 here in the book of Proverbs,
there's two important principles that we see here
with regard to more from a negative perspective.
We saw the positive in chapter 15 and 25.
And obviously these are not exhaustive lists
of all the portions of scripture
that you could look to with regard to our words.
But notice what the book of Proverbs says
in Proverbs 26 in verse number 20.
It says where no wood is,
there the fire goeth out.
Does anyone have a difficulty understanding that?
You've experienced that at some point,
you ever have a fire?
And maybe, I remember when Holly, my in-laws,
were living in Pennsylvania, they had a wood stove.
And they would try to heat their house with that wood stove.
And my father-in-law would sleep on the couch
in the living room and he'd set an alarm
and he'd get up all hours of the night to do what?
To fill that wood stove with wood.
Why?
Because where there's no wood, the fire goes out.
Where there's no fire, there's no heat.
Right?
There were, they have seven children.
Not all seven of them were there at that time.
There were five of them there.
There's a family of seven.
And my father-in-law took the responsibility.
He wanted to make sure.
And so we understand this principle
that where no wood is, there the fire goeth out.
You're at a campfire and you're trying to have a bonfire
and it's trying to die down.
And you're like, hey, go get some more wood.
We need more wood on the fire.
But notice what the rest of the verse says.
So, where there is no tailbearer, the strife ceaseth.
See, we can acknowledge and understand very easily
the first part of verse 20.
But then we get to the last part of verse 20
and we're like, eh.
No, no, it's a Bible principle that God gives us.
Where no tailbearer is,
so where there is no tailbearer, the strife ceaseth.
You think about the world of iniquity,
the strife, the difficulty that our tongues,
our words can get us into.
In verse 22, a couple of verses later,
it says the words of a tailbearer are as wounds
and they go down into the innermost parts of the belly.
When I was a kid, and I'm sure for some of you as well,
you remember hearing that little thing
about sticks and stones may break my bones,
but words will never hurt me.
That's a lie.
It's a lie.
Because words hurt.
The Bible says the words of a tailbearer are as wounds
and they go down into the innermost parts of the belly.
I'm sure that, again, living life for any period of time,
there have been times that you've had words spoken to you
or given to you in some form that have encouraged you.
And I'm sure that you've had words that have hurt you.
But if we then look at our own selves,
there have been times that we have communicated words,
verbally or otherwise,
that have encouraged and edified others,
but also have hurt others.
Holly did an illustration a number of years ago
with our children about the impact of our words
and I don't have the materials before me
to do the illustration object lesson for you,
but I hope you have an imagination better than mine
because I can imagine it and my imagination is very good.
If you can think about a piece of wood,
we bring up here on the platform this morning,
you put a piece of wood here
and you have this piece of wood
and it's a solid piece of wood,
it's a good piece of wood.
And you take some nails
and you say that those nails are like our words.
And you drive those nails into that piece of wood.
And the words that you regret,
the words that you wish you had not spoken,
the words that maybe hurt someone,
you then take those words out of that piece of wood.
What's left?
There's a scar.
The wood is marred, right?
So sometimes we say, well, I just take that,
I say something in anger
and we just say, no, no, it has an impact.
We have to acknowledge the impact this morning
of our tongue, of our words.
That's why we say, guard your tongue.
Because sometimes if we're not careful,
we can just come to a place
where we just begin to just speak
and just, man, I'm gonna give him a piece of my mind.
Don't do it.
Guard your tongue.
Think about it.
Pause.
Process it.
And so we find that here
as we begin reading James chapter number three,
we notice first that we must acknowledge the impact.
Number two, if you're taking notes, let me say this,
we need to avoid inconsistencies.
Avoid inconsistencies.
Back in James chapter number three,
notice as James continues here,
through the portion of scripture,
he's gonna give us, beginning in verse number nine,
these inconsistencies.
And we as the people of God must be careful
to avoid inconsistencies.
What I mean by inconsistency,
I don't speak out of both sides of my mouth.
A double talker, you ever hear that phraseology?
They speak out of both sides of their mouth.
What do they mean?
Well, when I'm with this group of people right here,
I say one thing,
but when I'm with this group of people over here,
I say something different,
and the two are inconsistent, right?
Have you ever seen that?
If you've not ever seen that, you've not lived long.
You're not paying attention.
Your head is in the sand.
You know what I'm saying?
Because people do it all the time.
But as God's people,
we're to avoid inconsistencies with our speech.
Notice the truth in verse number nine.
Notice what James says.
Therewith, meaning with our tongue, with our words,
bless we God, even the Father.
Now, should we bless the Lord?
Oh yeah, the psalmist says, bless the Lord.
Oh my soul, in all that is within me,
praise His holy name.
He's worthy.
Man, that's a good use.
That's a proper use.
But it says this, and therewith, curse we men,
which are made after the similitude of God.
He goes all the way back to Genesis chapter number one
with that statement.
Because God said, let us make man in our own image.
And we find that here, the reference
at the end of verse number nine
is another reference to the truth of creation
that humans have been made in the image of God.
And here James says, therewith, with our tongue, again, the idea of avoiding the inconsistencies
of what is James doing, he's pointing out the inconsistencies.
He's exposing the inconsistencies amongst their behavior, their use of their words and
he's saying we need to avoid this.
Look in verse number 10, out of the same mouth proceedeth blessing and cursing.
So we find that James, again, is exposing the inconsistencies and we're saying here
this morning that as they're exposed and as we study the portion of scripture that we
ought to avoid the inconsistencies.
Let your yay be yay and your nay be nay.
Amen?
I mean, listen, we got to come to a place where we're going to avoid that inconsistency.
We're not going to be caught in a situation.
By the way, when we speak the truth, it really helps us to avoid inconsistencies.
You know what I'm saying?
It's going to start being that tail bearer, the one that's going to make up stories and
we're going to, no, no, no, we get all kinds of in trouble.
I remember as a kid, you told us lies are like a spider's web, a web of lies, and you're
not smart enough to remember all the lies you told.
How many of us know that's true?
We've experienced that.
We've seen that.
Notice the pointed conclusion that James makes when he talks about these inconsistencies
at the end of verse number 10.
Very plainly, I mean very straightforward, my brethren, these things ought not so to
be.
What is he saying?
Well, remember, he's talking to Christians, believers.
He said in verse number three, my brethren, we find that here he's talking about contextually
in verse number nine, therefore, bless we gods, we're talking about people that understand
using their words, their tongues to praise the Lord, but he says that there's this inconsistency
and so what does he conclude?
My brethren, talking to believers, these things ought not so to be.
Listen, we can come to a place where we can expect the inconsistencies amongst the lost
people.
I'm not giving them a pass or saying that it's okay or any of that sort of thing, but
the reality is we can expect that, but it's the people of God.
We need to avoid the inconsistencies.
We need to understand how important it is that what we say is absolutely true, that
it's calculated, deliberate, that we speak plainly and honestly and we avoid the inconsistencies.
Now as we look here at the passage of Scripture, we not only see and acknowledge the impact
of our words and we notice and understand the fact that we're to avoid inconsistencies,
but now number three I want you to analyze with me the illustrations.
James uses in these twelve verses of Scripture a series of illustrations and I believe that
he uses these illustrations in order to solidify the principle that's being taught.
As I look at the four illustrations that are used here in this portion of Scripture, I
find that he uses illustrations that are both relatable and understandable.
We find that the first illustration is found in verse number three.
Notice what the Bible says, So the first illustration that he is going
to use is that of a horse and the bridle or the bit.
Now how many of you know, does anyone have a guess, how much does a horse, the average
horse, how much does it weigh?
Does anyone know?
Say it again?
Not quite that much.
About a thousand pounds is the average size horse.
Now obviously you can get into the Clydesdales and some of those other ones and they get
even bigger, but the average size horse is about a thousand pounds.
Does anyone have a guess on how much a bridle weighs?
Less than a pound, at most a pound, like ten to sixteen ounces for a bridle.
So think about this illustration.
The Bible says in verse number three, Behold we put bits in the horse's mouths.
Now I'm not a horse rider, alright, I've done it one time, I'll do it again when I come
back with Jesus, according to Revelation 19, amen?
It's just not really my thing.
Not really, I mean, Samantha rode horses, she likes riding horses, some of you might
ride horses, it's great, it's wonderful, it's just not my thing, alright?
I didn't feel comfortable the whole time, but I did it, but you know what I learned?
You got that little bit in that big beast and you can do this and it goes that way.
You can pull back on that thing, he doesn't like it.
So notice what he says here, he says, Behold we put bits in the horse's mouths, why?
That they may obey us.
Now, that horse is a whole lot stronger than I am, right?
That horse is a lot more powerful than I am, but I got this ten to sixteen ounce bit in
its mouth and it obeys me.
Notice what he says, and we turn about their, what does it say?
Whole body.
Now when we think about this and we understand the illustration, this was something they'd
be familiar with, they'd understand, they'd be able to relate to this.
And so James is using the illustration, we'll get to it at the end when we look at all the
illustrations that are used and we understand that James says even so, in verse 5, the tongue
is a little member.
So he's trying to help us understand this principle that he's putting forth and really
to solidify what's being taught.
So we see first he uses a horse and a bridle.
The second one is found in verse number 4, he says, Behold also the ships, which though
they be so great, are driven of fierce winds, yet are they turned about with a very small
helm, whithersoever the governor listeth.
Now I'm not a ship guy either.
I do some research, amen?
Been on a boat a couple times, that's really not my thing either.
And the reality is that I did some research and it says this, that rudders, really kind
of what he's talking about here with a helm, are relatively small steering mechanisms.
Only they're 1 one-hundredth, get this, to one ten-thousandth the size of the ship they
control.
One one-hundredth to one ten-thousandth, alright?
Now you think about that and you think about the size of the ship versus the size of the
helm or the rudder and how that he says here in verse number 4, he says that he uses that,
he says, Yet they are turned about with a very small helm, notice this, whithersoever
the governor listeth.
He can take that boat where he wants to take that boat.
Now again, I'm not a boat guy.
I tried to drive a boat once, or you don't drive it, I don't know what you call it, but
you try to move that thing, amen?
And we're out on the water, we're at Deep Creek, somebody might have been over there
in Maryland, beautiful place, we rented a boat one time, this was years ago, and so
we decided it was time for lunch so we're going to go up to the dock.
You're laughing already, man.
Man it would have been better for me to just put an anchor out and try to swim, man, it
was terrible.
I'm trying to get that thing up against the dock and I'm just not, it's just not my thing.
Because guess what I was doing, I was kind of trying to deal with it like it was a car.
But man, just a little bit of a turn and that thing responds.
And then what starts happening, you start over-correcting.
That's what I started doing anyway because I'm not really qualified in that.
It's amazing, they actually rent a boat without any experience whatsoever, I don't know what
they're thinking, man.
But the reality is this, the principle is relatable, it's understandable.
One one-hundredth to one ten-thousandth the size, but it turns that ship, the governor,
the captain of the ship has the ability to move that thing into port and to maneuver
even in the open water, it's amazing.
He says in verse number seven, for every kind of beast and of birds and of serpents and
of things in the sea is tamed and hath been tamed of mankind, again that's something I
think that individuals could relate to, but he says this in verse eight, but the tongue
can no man tame is an unruly evil full of deadly poison.
I'll make the statement now, I'll probably come back to it again, but this is the portion
in verse seven and eight that reminds us of how much we need God.
The Bible says that all of these beasts and birds and all this that's all been tamed and
hath been tamed of mankind, but the tongue, notice what it says, can no man tame.
15, without me you can do nothing. That's what Jesus said in John 15. As much as you
want to try in your own power, in your own strength, you're not going to tame your tongue.
But with God's help, with God's help, we can have that ability to guard our tongue
and not have to have the regrets of, why did I say that? I shouldn't have said that. I
need to go apologize, but I'm too prideful to apologize, so it's just going to continue
to be a problem. You understand what I'm saying? That's how life works. We say things that
we shouldn't say, we hurt people that we love, we use our tongue in that manner, and then
pride wells up and we refuse to apologize because these two words, I'm sorry, are hard
for people to say, and then it continues to be a problem. We see it all over the world.
And so we find that we need God's help in this area. We need God's help. Notice the
third illustration, or fourth if you're using verse 7 as illustration, but notice if you
will in verse number 11. He used the illustration of a fountain. Notice this very simple question.
Doth a fountain send forth at the same place sweet water and bitter? Well, what's the answer?
No. And so we find that James again, he's using these illustrations that are relatable,
that are understandable. These are not complicated things. He's trying to get his readers, he's
trying to make sure that we understand the principle that he's teaching. Obviously all
Scripture is given by inspiration of God, and God wants to help us with this instruction.
So he used the example of a fountain. He uses the example in verse number 12 of agriculture.
Can the fig tree, my brethren, bear olive berries? Either a vine, figs. Now as he's
using this illustration of agriculture here in verse number 12, again the people would
understand. It's relatable. It's something they understand. It's almost laughable, if
you will, for James to say to some of these people, can the fig tree, my brethren, bear
olive berries? No. Of course not. But what's he doing? He's driving home a point. We analyze
the illustration so that we can understand with greater clarity the point that James
is making. He says, so can no fountain both yield salt water and fresh at the end of verse
number 12? So what's he saying? Well remember, as we analyze these illustrations, he's reminding
us in the first two illustrations of how something so small can have power over something much
greater. A bit and a horse. A helm and a ship. And what does he say? Well, even so the tongue
is a little member that boasteth great things. Your tongue and my tongue is not the biggest
thing in our body. But it's powerful. Oh, it is powerful. Some people think about the
power of the pen. The pen is just the expression of the tongue. Right? So we're talking about
our words this morning. It's in all forms, whether they're spoken or written. And so
we come to this and we see that James wants the people and God wants us today to understand
that my tongue is little, but oh, it boasteth great things. And how, notice, great a matter
a little fire kindleth. I'm not sure if you've ever been in a situation, you've read something
about a fire that got out of hand. Thought it could be controlled and before long it's
just beyond your ability. Most of us would be familiar with at least some of the details
of the great Chicago fire. The number of buildings that were lost, lives that were lost, economic
impact on the city, devastating. Started in a barn. Got out of hand. And the reality
is that we have to understand as James is illustrating in that first section, dealing
with those first two illustrations, that your tongue is little, but man, it's powerful.
We analyze the illustrations. He then uses the last two illustrations for what purpose?
For us to understand that, listen, a fountain doesn't have sweet and bitter water and that
a fig doesn't bear olive berries and a vine doesn't bear figs. Why? Because he's trying
to help us to understand the inconsistencies. Therefore, therewith bless we God, even the
Father, and therewith curse we men. No, it ought not be because the fountain doesn't
produce sweet and bitter. As he says in verse number 12, the fig doesn't bear olive berries
and the vine doesn't bear figs. And so why are there inconsistencies? Do you see how
he's using the illustrations? I mean, he's making it abundantly clear. So what do we
do with this? Again, we mentioned at the very beginning of the message this morning that
the book of James is extremely applicable, extremely practical. I've said it, but I need
to bear repeating it, or it bears being repeated. We need God's help. Guard your tongue. We
need God's help. I can't do it on my own. You can't either. If you're not careful, something's
going to happen this week. Something might happen this afternoon. Something could happen
in the parking lot before you leave here that just gets you in a place where you were walking
in the Spirit and now the flesh has been revitalized. You ever deal with that? Listen, the old man,
we're to reckon him to be dead, but have you learned in your life that the old man can
resurrect pretty quick? You know what I'm saying? Just let somebody do something and
it just kind of rubs you the wrong way, and then bam, all of a sudden the old man is awake
and alive and well, and you just start speaking. I know I need God's help. Let me say this.
We really need to pray and ask God not only to help us, but we need to have that desire,
the determination that I'm going to honor the Lord with my tongue. He said in James
1, I said that this is really the further development of the principle that we're to
be swift to hear, slow to speak, slow to wrath. Sometimes it's okay to be quiet. Just don't
say anything. But they're going to think, I don't care what they think, it'd be better
to honor God by guarding your tongue. Amen? Again, I used that expression a few minutes
ago and we've all heard it. Maybe we've used it. I'm going to give them peace of my mind.
You better be careful. You better be careful. We're to be slow to speak. We want to have
words that are acceptable. We want to have words that are appropriate. Let's get a few
principles throughout God's word to help us this morning to know how can I apply this?
Okay, I acknowledge, pastor, I hear this morning, I see what's going on. I acknowledge the impact.
My tongue, my words, they're powerful. I get it. I acknowledge the impact of my words.
I want to avoid the inconsistencies. I don't want to speak out of both sides of my mouth.
I understand the illustrations and we've looked through them and analyzed them. I get it.
I understand the illustrations. But now what? What do I do? How do I guard my tongue? Look
at the book of Psalms. We'll look at three chapters, three references in the book of
Psalms. Psalm 19 to begin with. And then we'll look at two New Testament principles. Give
you five verses, six verses this morning to help us apply the truth that James is dealing
with in James 3 that I hope will help us to guard our tongues. Psalm 19 and verse number
14. Notice the prayer of the psalmist here. Let the words of my mouth and the meditation
of my heart be acceptable in thy sight, O Lord my strength and my Redeemer. You know
that God hears the words that we speak? God knows the words that we speak. He knows how
we use our tongue. He knows if there's an inconsistency that we bless God on Sunday
morning and we're cursing men the rest of the week. He knows that. He's aware of that.
So we do when we come to God and we say, Lord, let the words of my mouth and the meditation
of my heart be acceptable in thy sight, O Lord my strength and my Redeemer. By the way,
it really only matters if it's acceptable in God's sight.
That's all that really matters, is that it's acceptable in God's sight.
Notice in Psalm 39.
So it starts with a prayer, that desire, I want my words to please the Lord.
Listen, if you pray that way, I told the teens in Sunday school this morning, if you pray
every day, Lord, I want to please you with my life today, and you have that desire, I
want to please God today, then as you go throughout your day, you're going to think about every
decision that you make, whether it's going to please God or not.
So the impact of our praying, leading into our decisions, well if we pray, Lord, let
the words of my mouth be acceptable, then I'm going to be more aware of the words that
I'm using.
Is this acceptable?
Notice in Psalm 39, in verse number 1, I said, I will take heed to my ways, notice this,
that I sin not, with what, with my tongue.
I will keep my mouth, with what, with a bridle, while the wicked is before me.
Isn't it interesting that here in Psalms, he talks about keeping the mouth with a bridle,
but we read in James about the horse and the bridle.
And here he says, listen, that I sin not with my tongue, that I sin not with my tongue.
You know, the reality is that it is very easy to sin with our tongue.
You don't need to turn there, but in Proverbs 10 and 19 it says, in the multitude of words
there wanteth not sin, but he that refraineth his lips is wise.
What's he mean by that?
Well, sin is not lacking.
Where there's more words, there's more potential for sin.
The lips of the righteous, according to verse number 32 of Proverbs 10, know what is acceptable.
Man, that's a good truth.
The words of the, the fact that we, God, as we would be in his word, we understand
what's acceptable, what's appropriate.
So here in Psalm 39, that I sin not with my tongue.
Notice in Psalm 141, I love Psalm 141 in this verse, as it applies to the subject that we're
looking at this morning, with our words, with our tongue.
Psalm 141, in verse number three, notice what the psalmist says, set a watch, O Lord, before
my mouth.
Keep the door of my lips.
Isn't that a good prayer?
I mean, Lord, I want you to set the watch.
Lord, I want you to keep the door of my lips.
Help me not to say things that are just kind of, I'm in my flesh and I just said something
because they needed to hear something.
No.
Set a watch, O Lord, before my mouth.
Keep the door of my lips.
How does this look practically?
Listen, there's been times in your life, no doubt, that you've experienced it where you're
in a situation, you're in this interaction with someone, perhaps, and you're ready to
say something and God's just kind of, nope, don't say that, it's not appropriate, it's
not God honoring.
Sometimes we just say, I'm going to say it anyway, because we're in our flesh and the
old man is going to, I'm trying to be relatable this morning, because this is something that
all of us need.
We deal with this every day of our lives.
Ten to 16,000 words a day, say, I don't talk that much.
Maybe you tweet a lot, do they even use that word anymore?
I don't know if they even use that word.
Now it's X, it's not Twitter anymore, right, it's X.
I don't have any of that stuff, but you post, right?
Just push stuff out there, push stuff out there.
Send emails.
Have you ever done this?
I don't know if you've ever done this before.
Have you ever done this where you hit reply all but you only meant to hit reply?
At work, I'm talking about in the workplace.
I did it one time, I learned a lesson.
There was this customer that was a pain in the neck, I mean royal pain in the neck.
So I sent an email, I thought, to the outside sales rep.
I said, what's up with this guy?
That's all I said, thankfully that's all I said.
I mean he was beating us up on price, on delivery, I mean he was just killing, we couldn't make
a 1% profit, it was terrible.
And I simply said to the outside sales guy, what's up with this guy?
And then all of a sudden I got this reply, what's up with this guy is blah, blah, blah,
blah, blah.
And I was like, oh, how did he get that email?
And I look back, I hit reply all.
Man, I don't think I've ever done that again.
I learned a lesson.
But I'm glad I didn't say something that was worse, you know what I'm saying?
So when we look here, we say God, I want you to set a watch, I want you to keep the door.
I don't want to say things that are going to get, it's not just about getting in trouble,
that's not going to bring honor and glory to thee.
Because my words are powerful.
My words are impactful.
Notice in the book of Ephesians, we'll close with two New Testament principles.
Ephesians chapter number 4, two verses that are worthy of our consideration with regard
to this subject this morning.
Verse 4 and verse 15.
The Bible says this, but speaking the truth, how?
In love.
May grow up into him in all things, which is the head, even Christ.
Sometimes we're good at speaking the truth, but sometimes we're not good at speaking the
truth in love.
It's really kind of dealing with the delivery of our words.
Having compassion with what we're speaking.
We find in verse number 29 of this same passage in Ephesians 4, the Bible says, let no corrupt
communication proceed out of your mouth.
Let how much?
Let no corrupt communication proceed out of your mouth.
Some of you might have got saved a little bit later in life, and there's some vocabulary
that you need to get rid of.
You understand what I'm saying?
Is that clear enough?
We can all relate with that?
Do I need to be more specific?
There's some vocabulary that ought not be part of the vocabulary of a believer.
Amen?
There's some words that are no longer part of the vocabulary of the individual, maybe
got saved a little later in life, and there were some words that you used often, but I
don't use those words anymore.
Why?
Because they're not appropriate words.
They're corrupt words.
Let no corrupt communication proceed out of your mouth.
I was in a meeting one time when I worked in the corporate world, and we left the meeting,
and before I even got back to my office, a colleague had contacted one of the people
that worked for me and said, that was a rough meeting, and I think Chris was really upset
because he cursed.
And I got back to my office, and the person was there to talk to me, and I was like, hold
on a minute.
Like, Chris does not curse.
And the co-worker said, I didn't believe it for a second.
I'm not saying that to pat myself on the back, I'm just simply saying, that ought to be your
testimony.
We don't talk that way.
I've hung up on people that wanted to just use a bunch of profanity.
Listen, if you can't speak more intelligent than that, I'm not having the conversation
with you.
If those are the only adjectives you know, you need to increase your vocabulary.
You understand what I'm saying?
So let no corrupt communication proceed out of your mouth.
My mom used to say she did not like that word that we use for be quiet that's not as kind
as be quiet.
She didn't like that phrase.
And she was telling us she was going to give us a mouthful of pepper.
I'm serious, man.
She was serious about it.
And he says, let no corrupt communication proceed out of your mouth, but that which
is good to the use of edifying, that it may minister grace unto the hearers.
Isn't that good instruction?
I mean how profitable this instruction is.
It says this in Colossians 4, we'll end here, Colossians 4, notice in verse number 6, Colossians
4 and verse number 6, the Bible says this, let your speech be, what's that next word?
Away.
I love it how God just gives us instruction that's just like, there is no wiggle room.
You know what I'm saying?
Let your speech be always with grace, seasoned with salt that you may know how you ought
to answer and respond.
every man. Sometimes in order to properly follow the instruction of Colossians 4, 6,
you need to take some time before you reply to some people. You know what I'm saying?
Why? So that you can respond properly. So that you can follow the instruction, the admonition
that God has given that your speech will be with grace, always with grace, seasoned with
salt, that you may know how you ought to answer every man. Have you ever typed out a text
or an email and deleted it before you sent it because you said, I shouldn't do it that
way? Guess what that is? That's taking this principle and really applying it in your life.
Sometimes you type it out because you're like, you just, I just need to reply and man, I'm
just going to, and then your fingers start going. If you can type, I can type fast, man.
And sometimes that thing just starts rolling and you start getting that email going and
then you're like, you know what? This is not honoring to God. This is not appropriate.
Did I use wrong language? No, no, no, but I just wasn't building up. Do you understand
what I'm saying? I'm not saying that we have to be cowardly and not deal with things that
we need to deal with. I'm just simply saying that we got to be careful and guard our tongue.
We need to speak the truth. There are times in which you do need to stand up and speak
up and say the truth, but you need to speak it in love. It's not about us coming to a
place where we say, well, I guess I just can't say anything. I got to be a doormat. No, no,
we can speak the truth. We can speak appropriately and godly. Jesus did. Amen? And so can you,
and so can I. The problem is this right here. It's our flesh. See, Jesus did no sin. He
was just. He was perfect. Our old man still has to be put off and we need to put on the
new. And what happens so often why we get in so much trouble with our tongue is because
of our flesh. It's because of our flesh. It's because we're not depending on the Lord. We
need Him. We need Him. The tongue can no man tame, but with God's help, with God's help,
we can speak words that are acceptable and pleasing in His sight. This morning, the truth
is so important. It is a truth that every single one of us need to be reminded of. Because
every day we use words. Every day we use words. And are those words impactful? Are those words
helpful? Absolutely. How are we using our words? Are there inconsistencies? Do we speak
to one crowd differently than we speak to another crowd? So we really just need to examine
our own selves. Say, Lord, I need your help. I need your help. I can't do this on my own.
I need to guard my tongue. Let's pray. Father, we love you. We thank you for loving us. We
thank you for the privilege of being gathered here this morning and thank you for the applicable
instruction that James provides us with here. Thank you for your help in this area. At some
point in each of our lives, we struggle with our words. Help us, Lord, to guard our tongue.
Help us to apply the truth that we've examined this morning. As we go throughout this day
and this week, there will be certain circumstances that we will encounter where these very principles
need to be applied. And I pray that you would help us. In this time of invitation, I pray
that now we'd be doers, responding in obedience, maybe coming to this altar and just pleading
Lord for your help. Maybe we're able to acknowledge that, man, we've not used our tongue appropriately.
There's been some inconsistencies. I've caused a lot of trouble with my tongue, maybe in
my own home, amongst my family, in my workplace, wherever it might be. God, would you help
us to be doers of the word and not hearers only. We'll give you the glory for all that's
done. For it's in Christ's name we pray.