in this wonderful book, the book of Genesis.
50 chapters, and it's been a long time.
This is message number 103.
I mentioned that during the morning service today.
103 messages through this book,
and some of them were multiple part messages
based upon just the content of what we were dealing with.
But of course, as we've mentioned throughout the study,
the series over these number of years,
that the book of Genesis is so foundational.
It is so important.
We find that in our world today,
that really the content of the first 11 chapters
of the book of Genesis is regularly under attack.
And it's regularly under attack
because if the enemy can cause the individual
to doubt the record of Genesis one through 11,
then the reality is that the enemy
can get anybody to doubt any portion of God's word.
If he is not the creator,
then how do we know he's really the redeemer?
And really, that's the path that they go down
in trying to cause doubt and uncertainty
with the Genesis record.
I'm thankful that the creator God gave us
this wonderful book of beginnings,
and it begins in the beginning God.
What a wonderful book, what a wonderful content.
And then of course now we end with the life of Joseph.
I've titled the message, So Joseph Died.
And as we begin to look at this passage of scripture,
the Bible tells us in verse 22,
and Joseph dwelt in Egypt, he and his father's house,
and Joseph lived in 110 years.
And Joseph saw Ephraim's children of the third generation.
The children also of Mekir, the son of Manasseh,
were brought up upon Joseph's knees.
And Joseph said unto his brethren,
I die, and God will surely visit you
and bring you out of this land,
and to the land which he swore to Abraham,
to Isaac, and to Jacob.
And Joseph took an oath of the children of Israel,
saying, God will surely visit you,
and ye shall carry up my bones from hence.
So Joseph died, being 110 years old.
They embalmed him, and he was put in a coffin in Egypt.
I wanna remind you if you wanna take and turn over quickly,
but you don't need to, but in Psalm 116,
God gives us a precious verse of scripture.
In Psalm 116, it's a verse that we often will turn to
at the time of a loved one that departs,
enters into eternity.
The Bible says in Psalm 116, in verse number 15,
precious in the sight of the Lord
is the death of his saints.
Precious in the sight of the Lord
As we begin to think about this portion of scripture
and ending the book of Genesis,
we find that for the majority of the last 13 chapters
of the book of Genesis,
we have traced the steps of the life of Joseph.
He comes on the scene in chapter 37.
We're introduced to this exemplary Bible character.
He's 17 years old in Genesis chapter 37
when he comes on the scene.
We find that the Bible would record for us
many aspects of his life,
and as we come here to Genesis chapter number 50,
we're told that Joseph is 110 years old.
It's very interesting because the text of scripture
that I read to you beginning in verse 22 this evening
and through the end of the chapter,
really this portion of scripture
covers about 53 or 54 years of Joseph's life.
Joseph's dad died, Jacob.
We read of that and we studied that
the last couple of messages in the end of chapter 49
and the beginning of chapter number 50,
but we find that from the death of Jacob
until the death of Joseph,
it's about 54 years that passes,
and we find that there's really not much
that's given to us with regard to the life of Joseph
during those 54 years.
But I think about the content that is given to us
with the life of Joseph.
As we begin to think about his life
and we begin to think about the example that he is,
and of course, many of you know,
I've said it over the years,
that Joseph is my favorite Bible character,
and thus, when God blessed us with a son,
we named him Joseph,
and the reality is that when you study the life of Joseph,
it's an amazing account,
a record that God gives us of a life that is well-lived,
a life that is exemplary,
a life that is marked by several things.
In fact, we're gonna look at those things this evening.
It is a life that as you look at the record
that God provides,
there's really no sin that's mentioned.
It doesn't mean that Joseph was sinless,
it's just not recorded for us.
There are many Bible characters that you can go to
and you can study their lives
and you can see the content of the life that's recorded
and the blessings and the great triumphs in their life,
but then also troubles and difficulties and sin
and what have you,
but here in the life of Joseph,
though many difficulties are recorded,
we don't read of any sin in the life of Joseph.
He was a man that walked with God.
He was a man, I believe, that pleased God.
He was a man that lived a life
that had no doubt a major impact
amongst those that he came in contact with.
I wonder this evening as we,
even at the very beginning of the message tonight,
we're gonna look at four things about the life of Joseph.
I wonder this evening if my life,
if your life had this kind of record provided
and for generations of people to be able to examine
and to read your life story,
what would people walk away with?
What would they summarize?
How would they summarize your life
if they were to read as we have the opportunity
to read of the life of Joseph
as it's recorded for us by God in his precious word?
What is it that we summarize?
How is it that we conclude?
What is it that we learn?
And I wonder tonight if our lives
were under the microscope in that fashion,
what would people say of you?
What would people say of me?
I have four thoughts for you this evening
that I hope would be a blessing,
things that mark the life of Joseph.
And as we look at his life
and we find that we come here to the end
and we see his death recorded for us,
I'd like to say this, number one,
that Joseph's life was a life marked by obedience.
His life was a life marked by obedience.
By the way, God expects obedience from his children.
Not only does God expect obedience,
but I would say it this way, God deserves obedience, amen?
It is appropriate for our God to expect
that we as his people would obey him.
It's a honorable thing for us as the people of God
to take the truth that God has given to us
and to live it, to obey it, to practice what God says,
to be doers of the word and not hearers only.
When I think about this life
being a life marked by obedience,
I would say first and foremost
that Joseph learned to obey God.
He learned to obey God.
By the way, that's the most important thing
that any of us could learn is learning to obey God.
That we just determine we're gonna obey God,
that we're not gonna live a life of rebellion,
we're not gonna live a life in distance
from what God has said for us to do,
that we're simply going to live a life of obedience,
that we're gonna determine that with God's help
and by God's grace, we're going to obey.
You know, it's very interesting, all of us can obey.
Not all of us can do the same thing.
Not all of us can,
Lydia was in here playing the piano before church tonight
and I said, Lydia, have you ever heard me play the piano?
And she kind of looked at me sideways,
like, what are you talking about, you play the piano?
I said, oh yeah, I got a couple songs
and I came over here and I played a couple of partial songs
that I know just a few notes of, right?
And I was just kind of messing with Lydia a little bit,
but the reality is I don't play the piano.
But I can obey God, even though I don't play the piano.
See, there's things sometimes we begin to look at,
well, I can't do this or I can't do that,
but all of us can obey and God gives us the strength
and the capacity to obey His commands.
God never gives us instruction
that He does not give us the ability to obey, amen?
He enables us, it is His enabling.
I preached this on Wednesday evening
there from the book of 1 Thessalonians,
you look at all of that instruction,
how could I ever do this?
You can't, but faithful is he that calleth you,
who also will do it.
And He works in us and through us and He enables us
and we find that as we look at the life of Joseph,
that his life is marked by obedience.
Yes, first and foremost to the Lord,
I see it in his life that he was obedient to his dad.
His dad sent him on errands,
his dad gave him responsibility
and yet we find that even in his life,
he obeyed that instruction.
I believe that he was obedient,
don't specifically call it out in this fashion,
but I believe that he was obedient
to those who were in authority over him.
I think that when he was in Potiphar's house,
that he was obedient, he made himself subject
to the authority that was over him.
I believe that was in prison.
Why is it that he came to the position that he came to?
I believe that he was an obedient individual
because ultimately he understood
that he was obeying the Lord, he was obeying the Lord.
You know, we all have people in authority over us.
There are people that say, I can't wait
until I can get to a place of authority
and nobody is gonna tell me what to do.
I remember I was in Bible college.
Sometimes Bible colleges are known for a bunch of rules
and I found this out in life
that every rule is there for a reason.
The most crazy rule you can think of in a rule book,
there's somebody that did something somewhere along the way
that resulted in that rule being put in the rule book.
This is how it works.
And sometimes you can let your mind wander
and you can wonder, I wonder where this rule came from,
right, I wonder what some knucklehead did
that came up with this rule being put in place.
And I remember in Bible college, there's one young man
and he said, I'm tired of all these rules.
I'm tired of people telling me what to do.
I'm going to the Marine Corps.
He was about 19 years old.
My whole life, I feel like I grew up in the Marine Corps
because I was born and my dad was a Marine.
I went to college, my dad's a Marine.
He didn't retire until my middle
of my freshman year in college.
And he said, I'm going to the Marines.
And I was like, good luck with that, man.
So much for I don't have to do
what anyone tells me to do, right?
The reality is that obedience
is a good trait of God's people.
We're obedient, we're obedient.
Turn to the book of 1 Samuel chapter 15, if you will.
It's a portion of scripture that's familiar to many of us.
In 1 Samuel 15, we read of Saul and his partial obedience.
And you've often heard me say that partial obedience
is really nothing more than disobedience.
The command that was given from the Lord
through Samuel to Saul was very plain and very clear.
And yet we find that Saul did not obey
the command that had been given to him.
Samuel comes on the scene
and Samuel is aware of the disobedience,
not only because of the word of the Lord,
but because of what he could hear and observe himself.
He knew of the disobedience of Saul.
And I just wanna draw your attention,
we're not gonna read the entirety of the text
or even much of it, just a verse of scripture.
Notice in verse 22, the Bible says,
and Samuel said,
hath the Lord as great delight
in burnt offerings and sacrifices.
Why is it that Samuel says that?
Well, because Saul tries to excuse his disobedience
by saying we're gonna make an offering,
we're gonna make a sacrifice.
And so I'm gonna justify my disobedience
by saying that I'm making a sacrifice.
Listen, there's no justification for disobedience.
The proper response to disobedience is confession.
That's the proper response, confession.
God, I disobeyed, I sinned and we confess and we forsake.
He continues and says,
hath the Lord as great delight
in burnt offerings and sacrifices
as in obeying the voice of the Lord.
Behold, to obey is better than sacrifice
and to hearken than the fat of rams.
To obey is better, to obey is better.
Think about the life of Joseph,
a life that's well-lived,
a life that here in Genesis 50 comes to an end,
110 years old, and I believe it was a life
that was marked by obedience.
I wonder tonight if we were to examine our lives,
if others were to examine our lives,
would they say of us that our life is marked by obedience?
Is it clear in our lives that we're obedient people,
that we obey the Lord,
that our life is marked by obedience,
that not just occasionally they happen to obey,
but they are an obedient follower of Jesus Christ?
Number two this evening, the life of Joseph,
not only a life marked by obedience,
but I would say this, a life marked by troubles,
a life marked by troubles.
You know, the reality this evening
is that Joseph faced a number of troubles in his life.
We're familiar with them,
we've studied them now over these past several months
of studying the book of Genesis
and particularly this last portion of the book of Genesis
and we find that his life had many troubles,
but we find that in our lives,
that our lives too have many troubles.
Listen, trouble is never an excuse to disobey.
Trouble is never an excuse to just quit
and throw in the towel and say,
you know what, it's not worth it.
I got all these problems and all these troubles
and no one understands and woe is me
and I have a right to, no, no, no.
Trouble is no excuse to disobey the Lord.
Trouble is no excuse to give up on following the Lord.
Job says this in Job chapter 14,
a verse that we're familiar with,
man that is born of woman is a few days and full of trouble.
And you say, man, I found that to be the case.
That is my new life verse and my life is full of troubles.
The reality is that trouble,
sometimes we get our own selves in trouble, amen.
We do crazy things and get ourselves in trouble
and it's our own fault, it's our own doing.
But other times life just has troubles.
There's just troubles in life.
There are difficulties, there's those that oppose us.
I think about Joseph here as we think about his life.
I think about the troubles that he had with his brothers.
Really, was there anything that Joseph did
that resulted in that trouble?
No, Joseph didn't go asking for it.
Joseph didn't mess up and get himself in trouble, no.
Joseph was obedient to his father.
Joseph was, he was the one that received
the coat of many colors.
He didn't go ask his dad for it.
He wasn't trying to compete for it.
As best we can tell from scripture,
there was no competition among the brothers
for who would get the trophy, if you will,
be the recipient of this coat of many colors.
No, Jacob bestowed it upon him
because he was his really favorite son,
if we're honest with scripture.
And he was the son of his old age and he gave him that.
And his brothers hated him
and his brothers could not speak peaceably unto him.
And he goes out following the command of his father.
As you study through the scriptures
and you find that he goes to sea
to bring a report back to dad
and they see him afar off and they conspire against him.
Let us kill him.
Here comes that dreamer.
Let's see what's gonna happen.
Let's see what's gonna come of these dreams.
And Joseph just happens to come upon them
and they snatch him and they tear that coat off of him
and they throw him into a pit
and they're planning to kill him.
They sell him into slavery.
Think about those troubles.
It's really nothing that he did wrong
that resulted in those troubles.
They were just troubles that came in his life.
He gets sold into slavery,
ends up in Egypt in a foreign land.
And we find that he's there,
that he's purchased by Potiphar and he's a servant.
Really he's of great position within the house of Potiphar.
He says so much so that there's none greater
in the house than me.
What a great position.
But Potiphar's wife came after him.
She lied about him and he ends up in prison.
He didn't do anything wrong.
In fact, he did everything right.
Amen?
Biblically speaking, he did everything right.
I often, and I said it during the message of that chapter,
he lost his coat, but he retained his character.
Better to lose his coat and be falsely accused
than to jeopardize his walk with God.
He said, how then can I do this great wickedness
and sin against God?
The trouble came, he ends up in prison and we understand.
And again, when we think about the life of Joseph,
when we think about a life marked by troubles,
listen, we have troubles in our lives.
Sometimes our own doing,
but many times outside of our control,
just things that happen.
The enemy attacking and the enemy trying to cause us
to stop serving the Lord.
I think about Psalm 34, it's a precious Psalm of David.
David makes two powerful statements in this chapter
with regard to troubles.
The first one is this in Psalm 34 in verse number six.
He says, this poor man cried and the Lord heard him
and saved him out of all his troubles.
Now David had some troubles that were not of his own doing.
David had some troubles that were the result
of his own doing.
All right, really you can look at David's life
in two aspects and you can see some of the troubles
that David had, they're his own doing.
Some of the troubles that David had, he had nothing to do.
He didn't ask to be anointed to be the king.
He didn't ask to go and to be in the place where he was
there with Saul, to be hunted by Saul
and all of those things.
And we find that he says, this poor man cried
and the Lord heard him and saved him out of.
all of his troubles, but I want you to skip over, you see that in verse 6 of Psalm 34,
look at verse 19 if you will.
I find the truth of verse number 6, I'm actually going to back it up and look at verse 17,
but I think of the truth of verse number 6 where David is sharing his testimony, he's
testifying of his own personal experience.
This is my experience, I had troubles but God heard me when I cried and God delivered
me.
The Bible says this, the righteous cry, and the Lord heareth and delivereth them out of
all their troubles.
Notice this verse 18, the Lord is nigh unto them that are of a broken heart, and save
it such as be of a contrite spirit.
Many are the afflictions of the righteous, but the Lord delivereth him out of them all.
And I'm so thankful that though we have trouble in life, we have a God who is greater.
We have a God who has purpose.
We have a God that in the midst of the trouble he can bring to pass great things.
If we simply remain faithful, if we simply remain steadfast, if we simply remain obedient
and keeping our eyes on the Lord, even in the midst of the trouble and the difficulty,
we can see God work.
We see that in the life of Joseph.
We see a man who walked with God in spite of the troubles, in spite of the difficulties.
I mean I think about the time in prison and we don't know exactly how long Joseph was
in prison, but we know that he was forgotten in prison for two years.
How long was he in prison before the butler and the baker came into prison and had the
dream?
We don't know for sure the timeline, but we know that after the butler and the baker were
delivered and the butler was told, remember me, and given that instruction, the text begins
that two years, after two years, that's when Pharaoh had a dream.
That's when the butler remembered about his experience in prison with Joseph and the dream
that he had and the dream that the baker had and the interpretation thereof.
We find that Joseph, during that two years, as best we can tell from Scripture, he just
continued to walk with God.
He just continued to do what he was supposed to do, praise the Lord, in the midst of trouble
and the midst of difficulty.
He didn't run a campaign, woe is me, I'm here and I don't deserve to be here and I've been
falsely accused and imprisoned and so on and so forth.
No, he just was obedient to the Lord and he was used of God in that place.
The Bible tells us the Lord was with him.
We find a life marked by obedience and a life marked by troubles.
I would say this, number three, a life marked by blessing, a life marked by blessing.
You want blessing in your life?
Better learn to obey, amen, because the result of obedience is blessing.
You say, but pastor, you just said that Joseph obeyed the Lord and there were troubles.
Yeah, I did say that.
Listen, not everything that we call a blessing is really a blessing.
And not everything the world would identify as not being a blessing is not a blessing.
I'm thankful, listen, the psalmist says that he rejoiced for being afflicted.
Why?
Because it was then that he learned the statutes of the Lord.
Some of us wouldn't look at being afflicted as being a blessing, but I would submit to
you this evening that indeed it was a blessing.
Because if we learn more about our God in that time of difficulty, then to God be the
glory that he allowed us to experience that.
Brother Armando shared with me not long ago how that during that trial of great health
trial when he was in Guatemala and thought he was going to die, how close he got to God
during that time.
We find this evening that we could look at the life of Joseph and yes, it's not contradictory
to say that it was a life marked by troubles, but also a life marked by blessing.
God knows his people, God has a plan for his people, and God blesses obedience.
I begin to think about the position of Joseph.
In Genesis chapter 41 and verse number 43, God tells us that Pharaoh made Joseph ruler
over all the land of Egypt.
When Joseph was in that pit, when Joseph was in that prison, he really didn't know that
he would one day be in a palace and be the ruler over all the land of Egypt.
We know that because we are familiar with the account of the life of Joseph because
we've read it and we've studied it and so we're familiar with it.
But I want you to, even as I mentioned this morning, consider that first read of the life
of Joseph, if you will.
And as you're reading the life of Joseph and you see him in the pit and you see him in
the prison and you see all that's taking place, and then you find how that eventually he comes
to the palace, it's amazing how God orchestrated all of those circumstances.
In fact, the reality is that had the butler remembered Joseph prior to the Pharaoh having
the dream, the Pharaoh probably couldn't care less that there was a man in prison that could
interpret dreams.
Why?
He had plenty of magicians and astrologers and those that he would go to for interpreting
of dreams, but it was at the very moment that he had a dream and there were none within
Egypt that could interpret.
The butler says, I remember.
And with haste they bring Joseph and they bring him into the presence.
He cleans himself up and he comes in the presence and Pharaoh says, I understand that you can
interpret dreams.
And Joseph says this, he says that it's not in him, it's not in me, but God shall give
Pharaoh an answer of peace.
What a great testimony.
God brings Joseph to this place of position and we find that Pharaoh so much so in understanding
the interpretation and the plan that is set forth, he says that he was going to set this
man Joseph in charge.
Why?
Can we find such a one as this is, a man in whom the Spirit of God is?
And he sets him in charge.
He tells him that only in the throne would Pharaoh be greater.
Joseph was 30 years old when this took place.
We find that he had this blessing of a position.
We find that God blessed him with family in the same chapter.
We're told of the wife that he receives but also of his two sons and the Bible tells us
in Genesis 41 and verse 50, unto Joseph were born two sons before the years of famine came
which Asenath, the daughter of Potiphar, a priest of Ahon, bear unto him.
And Joseph called the name of the firstborn Manasseh.
Names meant something very significant during Bible times, sometimes still today, and some
cultures names carry great significance in their meaning.
Unfortunately, in many of our American culture ideas, we pick our names because we like the
name.
We don't want much significance or thought that is put into the particular name.
We find that the Bible says that he named him Manasseh.
Why?
For God said he hath made me forget all my toil in all my father's house.
The name of the second called Ephraim, notice this, for God hath caused me to be fruitful
in the land of my affliction.
Isn't that a great statement?
You know, you can be fruitful.
You can have the blessing of God no matter where you are.
It's amazing.
We've now been in Northern Virginia for 13 years and I remember many years before we
ever moved to Northern Virginia saying something like this, who would ever want to live in
Northern Virginia?
I remember passing through this corridor on many a time visiting family, my brother's
station in North Carolina and we in Pennsylvania where we lived and we'd have to drive through
this corridor, this 95 corridor, right, going through the beltway and all of that.
And it didn't seem to matter what time of day you ever made the journey, you always
figured you'd hit traffic in Northern Virginia.
You always try to time it and, you know, miss the traffic.
People ask me now after living here all these years, how's traffic?
It's bad all the time.
I mean, there's just really not a good time to go.
It's just the way it is.
And then you try to jump on the expressway and you might as well just, I don't know,
run over your paycheck or something if you're going to pay for the tolls and it's crazy.
But I remember saying, who would ever want to live there?
I remember saying that, I'm being honest with you.
And then I remember when God orchestrated and we found out about this church in Oakton
and I thought, man, I've told this story before but I thought that's a sweet little name of
a town named after a tree, right, an oak tree.
And in my mind's eye I had a picture of Oakton being something like what you would see in
the southwestern part of our state, just kind of a quaint little town, nice little,
you know, whatever.
And then I looked it up on the internet and I said to Holly, this might as well be Washington,
D.C.
And sure enough.
But God called us here.
And you know.
You know, the reality is that as many people as we've met over the years, I was talking
to somebody not long ago, to our children actually, in the time that we've had the
privilege of being here, we've had, I believe the number now is 56 different families that
have joined the church over these years.
And out of the 56 families that have joined the church, 34 of them have moved away.
And you begin to think about that, why, what happens?
You know how many people say, I don't like it here?
They want to move.
That's just the idea, they get here and they say, I don't like the pace of life, I don't
like this, I don't like that, so on and so forth.
Listen, God has us here for a reason.
God has us here for a reason.
You know the world is in our backyard?
The world is in our backyard.
You can meet people from every continent, save Antarctica, I've never met anyone from
there, but you can meet people from all over the globe.
What a great opportunity.
See, we need to be careful of how we view things, and we need to understand that God
can bless.
God has you here for a season and for a reason.
And we begin to understand that this is where God wants me and this is where God has me,
and as we're in the place where God has us, that God can make us fruitful and allow us
to have blessing.
What a joy to know that we're in the place where God has us, even if we might call it
the land of our affliction.
I don't refer to it that way, I love it.
I never thought I would say that I love Northern Virginia, but I really did.
There are certain aspects of it that drive you crazy, you just kind of get used to it.
But the reality is that I'm thankful that Joseph understood that he could have the blessing
of God and be fruitful in the place where he was.
I think about the life marked by a blessing, even in the reunion with his family.
If you were to read, and we've studied in recent weeks, the 46th and 47th chapter of
the book of Genesis, when Joseph reveals his identity to his brothers and says to have
dad and the family come, and it would be in the place of Egypt that Joseph would provide
for them a place, and he would sustain them, and how you read of the reunion with his father,
and what joy.
I mean, just even looking at the reunion with his brothers, the ones who hated him, the
ones that sold him into slavery, but there's a sweet reunion that God records for us in
the 46th chapter of the book of Genesis, and then you read at the end where Jacob comes,
and what a blessing to consider the opportunity that God gave him, and how the obedience of
Joseph through his life, it's a life that's marked by a blessing.
We mentioned this just a few weeks ago in Genesis chapter 49, when Jacob, dad, has all
the boys brought before him.
He begins in verse 22, speaking of Joseph, and he says that Joseph is a fruitful bow,
even a fruitful bow by a well, whose branches run over the wall.
The archers have sorely grieved him, and shot at him, and hated him, but his bow abode in
strength.
The arms of his hands were made strong by the hands of the mighty God of Jacob.
On fence is the shepherd, the stone of Israel.
What a blessing to think about Joseph's life, a life that's marked by a blessing.
I would say finally this evening, the life of Joseph is a life that is marked by faith.
Life that is marked by faith.
We come to this 50th chapter, and we find that Joseph, the Bible tells us that he's
110 years old, and he says to his brethren in verse 24, I die.
Very similar to what we've read with regard to Jacob, knowing that he would soon die,
and he calls for his family to be in his presence, and he gives that final request, and puts
his feet back up in bed and dies.
And Joseph says to his brethren, I die.
But I want you to see what Joseph says, and how we see that his life was a life marked
by faith.
The Bible says that he says in verse 24, God will surely visit you, and bring you out of
this land unto the land which he sware to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob.
Joseph took an oath of the children of Israel, saying, God will surely visit you, and ye
shall carry up my bones from hence.
So Joseph died being 110 years old, and they embalmed him, and he was put in a coffin in
Egypt.
Begin to think about the faith of Joseph, and a life that's marked by faith.
We see it in these statements, and he believed that God would do what God said he would do.
He believed that God had promised to Abraham, and to Isaac, and to Jacob a land.
He believed, even as God had shared with Jacob in chapter 46, before Jacob would leave
that land and go to Egypt, that God said to Jacob, I am God, the God of thy father, fear
not to go down into Egypt, for I will there make of thee a great nation, and I will go
down with thee into Egypt, and I will also surely bring thee up again, and Joseph shall
put his hand upon thine eyes.
Genesis 46, three and four.
And Joseph believed that.
Joseph did not live long enough to see it come to pass, but his eye of faith, he says
in verse number 24, and again in verse 25, notice he says, God will surely visit you.
I mean, confident faith, expecting that God will do what God said he will do.
Not only was he convinced that God would visit and bring the nation into the land that
he promised, but he says in verse number 25 that he took an oath of them, saying, carry
up my bones from hence.
You know, it's not until Joshua chapter 24 that we read of that being fulfilled, and
we find that after, if you think about Genesis chapter 50, and you think about the period
if you enter into the book of Exodus where there's another pharaoh, another king of Egypt
that rises up that doesn't know Joseph, and all that generation dies, and you begin to
think about the Egyptian bondage and all that takes place, and eventually you come to the
place of the Exodus and the deliverance from Egypt land, followed by what?
The wilderness wanderings.
Though God never intended that that would be the plan, his plan was to deliver them
from Egypt into the land, because of their disobedience and lack of faith, they wandered
in the wilderness, but we come to the book of Joshua, and the book of Joshua provides
us with that record of the entrance into, the conquering of, the inhabiting of the land
of the nation of Israel, the land of Canaan, that land of promise.
And we find that as God would give to us the book of Joshua, and we find that we come to
the end of the book, and the Bible tells us in verse 29 of Joshua 24, and it came to
pass after these things that Joshua the son of Nun, the servant of the Lord, died being
a hundred and ten years old.
They buried him in the border of his inheritance in Timnath Sarai, which is in Mount Ephraim
on the north side of the hill of Gash, and Israel served the Lord all the days of Joshua,
and all the days of the elders that overlived Joshua, and which had known all the works
of the Lord that He had done for Israel.
And notice verse 32, the bones of Joseph, which the children of Israel brought up out
of Egypt, buried they in Shechem, in a parcel of ground which Jacob bought of the sons of
Hamor, the father of Shechem, for a hundred pieces of silver, and it became the inheritance
of the children of Joseph.
That's a long time that passes, but Joseph's bones are taken out of Egypt.
We find that they're brought into this burying place that God tells us of in Shechem, in
Joshua 24 and verse 32, but I want you to think about a life marked by faith.
It's interesting, for Joseph finds himself in the Hall of Faith chapter, sort of the
book of Hebrews, if you will, the 11th chapter, and we'll end here this evening.
We think of Hebrews chapter 11, we've often referred to this chapter as the Hall of Faith
chapter.
Those that, by faith, they believed God and how they were moved and what they did and
so on and so forth, and we find that Joseph, the statement that we read in Genesis 50,
is recorded for us in Hebrews chapter 11.
It tells us this in Hebrews 11 and verse 22.
By faith Joseph, when he died, made mention of the departing of the children of Israel
and gave commandment concerning his bones.
By faith he believed God.
The Bible tells us the just shall live by faith.
Amen?
The Bible tells us in this chapter, in Hebrews chapter 11 and verse number 6, without faith
it is impossible to please Him.
For he that cometh to God must believe that He is, and that He is a rewarder of them that
diligently seek Him.
God desires that His people would live a life of faith, that we believe God.
I believe the most simple definition of faith is believing God, taking God at His Word.
It doesn't mean that you can understand how everything's going to work out, it just means
that you believe God.
I think of Paul when he's in the storm, the end of the book of Acts, and he stands and
he simply says, I believe God, that it shall be as it was revealed unto me.
There was an angel that stood by him and told him of the deliverance that would come to
pass.
And in that particular storm they were hoping and wishing for the day, they thought for
sure they were all dead men, but he said, I believe God.
Not one will be lost.
And you know what?
They made it ashore.
None of them lost their lives.
This evening we think about the life of Joseph, we end this wonderful book, the book of Genesis,
a life that's marked by obedience, a life that's marked by troubles, a life that's marked
by blessing, and a life that's marked by faith.
I wonder tonight if each of us were to examine our own lives, better yet if someone to read
your story, what would they walk away with?
See, most of us are probably pretty glad that God didn't record our story for countless
generations of people to study, amen?
But if He did, how would someone conclude your life?
What would the summary statements be that are made of your life?
I hope that it could be said, even as it's said of Joseph, as we make these conclusion
type statements, it's a life marked by obedience, troubles, yes, blessings, abundant, a life
of faith.
He believed God.
Oh, that God would help us to have faith.
Oh, that God would help us to obey Him, to just follow Him.
You say, but the troubles, yes, the troubles will come.
Keep your eyes on Jesus, the author and finisher of our faith.
He's got a plan.
He does, He doeth all things well.
We serve a great God.
Joseph, 54 years summarized in just a few verses of Scripture, an exemplary Bible character,
one in which we look at his life and we say, oh, that God would allow me to be used in
like fashion.
Let's pray together.
Father, we love You.
Thank You for loving us.
Thank You for Your Word, the truth that's contained therein.
We thank You for the life of Joseph.
I pray, Lord, that You'd help us to be men and women of faith, men and women of obedience.
Help us to be used of Thee.
I pray, Lord, that in this moment of invitation that You'd have Your will and way.
Lord, maybe there's someone that's been living in disobedience, Lord, someone that's tried
to justify some of their disobedience.
Oh, I pray, Holy Spirit, that You'd convict them and help them, Lord, to respond not by
justification but respond with confession.
Lord, help us to have faith.
Help us to live by faith.
I pray that You'd increase our faith.
Help us to believe You.
I pray that You'd move and work as only You can for it's in Christ's name we pray.
Would You stand with me?
Heads are bowed, eyes are closed.
Holly's going to play quietly on the piano, and as she does, the altar is open.