and uh... he was kinda of my mindset there's no reason to cancel church
whoever can make it can make it those that can't can't
and uh... that's what he decided to do
and uh... there are several other church in the area that canceled and so they
knew he was having service so a bunch of them came but there's still kind of a
light crowd
and uh... he was up on the platform but they were kind of just meeting on one
side of the auditorium and
uh... he forgot that he was on the platform and he went to walk over where
the song leader was and he tumbled right down the steps
and uh... he said that video went viral
and uh... he said it was more hits than any other video the church ever had out
and so i don't want to do that amen
and uh... anyway colossians chapter number three
colossians chapter number three will be finishing up the third chapter
and entering into the fourth chapter this morning
and uh... we'll be looking at chapter three verse twenty two down through the
first verse of chapter number four
and as we conclude this portion of scripture this part of the book of
colossians
we're mindful that the third chapter of the book of colossians it started
with a reminder of our position in christ and i'm so thankful
to be in christ i'm so thankful to be a child of his amen
and the reality is that we as we studied the first portion of colossians three
we understood
that my position
will impact my pursuits
what am i pursuing in life
and when i understand my position will understand this world is not my home
amen i'm just passing through
i'm so thankful to know
that heaven is my home that i'm a stranger in a pilgrim
i'm not home but i'm going home amen
and uh... the reality is that our position will impact our pursuits
we then looked at the next section and it was a weighty section in colossians
three
dealing really with the process of sanctification
and it is the plan of god that the child of god would be conformed to the image
of the lord jesus christ
and uh... his dear son and we are to be like christ and
as we go through the christian life we understand that it's not in my power
it's not in your power to live the christian life
it's christ in us it is walking in the spirit
so that we do not fulfill the lust of the flesh and we went through a number
of truths that were provided in that section of colossians three
and then really the last several lessons we've dealt with now how does
that impact my behavior
how is it
that your behavior how is it that my behavior
in our daily lives is going to be impacted
by the truth that is given to us in this chapter in colossians three
if i follow the instructions if i put off the old man the flesh and i
put on the new man the spirit if i'm walking in the
the spirit so that i'm not fulfilling the lust of the flesh by the way that's
not just for ten thirty on sunday morning
that is for our lives that is every day of our lives
we represent the lord jesus christ and we understand again that it's not our
own power
it's through his power
we looked at the truth of how this would impact our behavior
in the church house
we understand the church in corinth they
had all kinds of problems and divisions and schisms and they were
i'm of paul and i'm of apollos and all of this debate and division that was
present
that is not the plan of god that is not pleasing to the lord
and so we find that there's behavior
uh... in the church house that will be impacted as we follow the instruction we
then
look at the section dealing with in our homes
a home where the lord is glorified and i'm so thankful
that god instituted the home that god designed the home that god
has provided instruction for the home
as we look at that particular message and dealt with that section here in
colossians three
we understood that it's god that designed the home
and therefore it is god that is the authority with regard to the operation
of the home
we can debate it
we can fight it
we can resist it we can try to listen to somebody else and some other
authorities we can listen to culture
and society
but the reality is that god is the authority
and is in our best interest to just simply submit
to what god has said
and we can have a home where god is honored
this morning
we'll be looking at our behavior in the workplace
you say man even the bible deals with our behavior in the workplace absolutely
because god's word deals with every area of our lives
we understand that as we look at this particular passage of scripture
that the terminology will be used with that relationship between servants and
masters
and though that relationship doesn't exist in the same context in which we
deal with in this particular
era in which this was written i believe that it would be appropriate for us to
make the application
with regard to our behavior in the workplace
how is it that we behave in the workplace what is it
as i've understood my position in christ and its impact at my pursuits as
i've understood
the process of sanctification if i
put off the old man and i put on the new man if i'm walking
in the power of the holy spirit of god so that i'm not fulfilling the lust of my
own flesh
that should be seen
in our workplace
and as we look at this passage of scripture there's great truth that is
given to us that i believe
will help us and i'll mention this at the end of the message as well this
morning
but i truly believe that if we would take
the principles that god provides us with
in his word and apply them
in our lives specifically dealing here
uh... with this aspect of our behavior in the workplace i believe it could be a
catalyst for revival
i really do
because the people that you work with the people that see you on a daily basis
they need to see that mystery that paul spoke of in colossians one
do they see christ in you
the hope of glory
do they see something different about us when we're in that workplace we're
dealing with those uh... various aspects of of being in the corporate world do
they see
in us something different do they see christ in you
the hope of glory
or is that reserved to just the church service times and then
uh... we just kind of put that off and then we go into the corporate world and
now i'm working in corporate america
it ought not be and we find here
uh... great truth that is given to us notice if you will
uh... as we begin the passage of scripture in verse number twenty two
the bible says this servants obey
in all things your masters according to the flesh not with eye service as men
pleasers
but in singleness of heart fearing god
and whatsoever you do do it heartily as to the lord and not unto men
knowing that of the lord you shall receive the reward of the inheritance
for you serve the lord christ
but he that doeth wrong shall receive for the wrong which he hath done
and there is no respect of persons
masters given to your servants that which is just and equal
knowing that you also have a master
in heaven
as we begin to look at this portion of scripture i'd say number one examine the
principle god gives us a principle here
in verse number twenty two that is worth our examination
again as we look at this passage of scripture and deal with the servants and
the masters i'll be looking
uh... this morning at making the application of the servant to that of
the employee
as we think about the principle that is given here we find first of all there's
a principle of obedience
a principle of submission
we find that he says obey in all things
your masters according to the flesh
the reality is that you and i do not have to work for the company that we
work for
but if we make a decision to work for the company in whom we work for
and they have standards they have rules then we must follow those rules
we must obey we must submit it is a responsibility that we have
as a child of god
and i understand this morning that we live in a time in which those things are
hotly debated i understand all that's taking place
uh... with regard to the overreach and so on and so forth but the reality
is that we understand that god has given us a principle
and i believe that as we examine the principle and we begin to understand
how this principle is played out and how it's effective in our lives
and being able to reach others with the gospel
we find that here as he says not only this truth of obedience but i believe
that we also see a very important principle that is given to us in verse
number twenty two
and that is a principle of integrity
you know we live in a day and age in which integrity is missing
there are people that do not operate with integrity
we find here that it says at the end of the verse
not with eye service as men pleasers
now think about that statement
there are plenty of folks that no doubt you've heard the
the phraseology the cliche that has been around for
uh... no doubt decades that while the
cats away the mice will play you've heard that
it's something that we've become familiar with their times in which as i
worked in the corporate world
uh... there would be folks that would be doing all sorts of things that were
not in line with what the job duties were
with what the responsibilities were
but as soon as the boss came into the room as soon as the boss came into the
area in which those employees were
all of a sudden they straighten up and they're gonna start doing what they're
supposed to be doing
often i heard it i i can tell you how many times i heard
uh... when i work in the corporate world you gotta look busy
what do you mean look busy?
you're either doing your job or you're not
amen
if you're getting paid to do a job you ought to have integrity and you ought to work
you ought to be the
The reality is that the Christian in the workplace,
they ought to be the best employee that that workplace has.
Honestly, ought to be the absolute best employee.
Why?
Because the principle is that we're not doing this
with eye service as men pleasers.
Because I live in a completely different realm.
I live in the heavenlies, if you will.
I'm seated already positionally.
Remember, the chapter begins with our position in Christ.
And that position impacts my pursuits.
I'm not trying to please my boss,
I'm trying to please my Savior.
Amen?
And as I please my Savior,
and as I do what I'm supposed to do in the sight of God,
then the outflow of that,
one of the results of that is that my employer
also is going to be pleased.
We find here that the Bible says,
not with eye service as men pleasers,
but notice what it says,
but in singleness of heart, fearing God.
How often we lose the principle
that is given to us here,
and we get into the workplace,
and we just begin to perhaps be impacted and affected
by those in which we work with,
and by their lack of integrity,
their lack of purpose,
and their lack of hard work,
and it will rub off on the child of God.
Oh, you're just an overachiever,
always trying to please, blah, blah, blah.
People say that kind of stuff.
Why?
Because they don't get it.
They don't understand that we have a Bible
that teaches us not only how we behave in the house of God,
not only how we behave in our homes as families,
but also how we behave in the workplace.
And as I understand the principle
that is given to us in verse number 22,
I find that it's a principle of obedience,
a principle of integrity.
We're not seeking to simply please men.
We're seeking to please our God.
In singleness of heart, fearing God.
Man, that's precious.
And it really leads us,
not only as we look at the principle,
but if you're taking notes,
I want you to notice number two,
that we're to embrace the perspective.
I understand that as we work in the work world,
as we work in the corporate environment,
there are times in which we will be adversely affected
and perhaps ridiculed because of our integrity,
because of our work ethic.
And there will be folks that will seek to attack us,
but we must embrace the perspective that is given
in the next two verses of Scripture.
When I have a proper, I will say this,
a biblical perspective, it makes a world of difference.
If I ask myself the question, why am I here?
Or maybe I ask myself this question,
and we'll deal with this at the end of the message as well,
who am I here for?
Why does God have you where he has you?
Why did God give you the job that he gave you?
Those are questions that we begin to ask ourselves,
and we understand the perspective that is given here,
and as we have that biblical perspective,
it makes a world of difference.
Notice what it says in verse 23.
And whatsoever ye do.
Now, that's pretty all-inclusive, is it not?
Amen?
I mean, and whatsoever you do.
Find some wiggle room.
I mean, well, that doesn't apply here.
Well, that doesn't apply.
No, whatsoever you do.
Whatsoever you do.
Do it how?
Notice what he says, heartily.
Heartily.
You ever hear somebody say, well, that's good enough
for government work?
Right?
Oh, that's good enough.
You ever have that?
Man, somebody just mails it in, so to speak,
just kind of takes it easy.
Well, what's our perspective
when we think about the work environment?
What is it that God is telling us?
As I look here, it says, whatsoever you do,
do it heartily, with not half-heartedness,
not just it's good enough for government work,
or not just I'm a better employee than my coworker,
because it's not about comparing ourselves
amongst ourselves.
I believe that we can even use,
adopt what Paul says to the Corinthians in that violation.
We can adopt that even into the application
of in the workplace.
I'm not seeking to just compare myself to my coworker,
and by the way, if I wanna do that,
I'm probably gonna find the worst coworker that I have
to compare myself with then.
But the Bible says that we're to do it heartily.
Notice what it says.
As to the Lord, and not to men.
As to the Lord.
What a great perspective.
When you go to work, when you engage at that workplace,
when you understand that God has placed me here
for his purpose, for his glory,
and I'm doing this job that I'm doing for him.
As to the Lord.
You know, that's gonna change your perspective,
because all of a sudden, you're not gonna view your boss
the same way that you currently view your boss,
because it's not about your boss.
Oh, there's still things that you have to deal with,
there's still things that you're gonna have to manage,
and so on and so forth, but all of a sudden,
you say, well, I'm not really working for that person,
I'm working for God, as to the Lord.
I'm doing this for my Savior, I'm doing this for my Master.
I'm seeking to have a good testimony for God in this place.
And I do it as to the Lord, not unto men.
It is absolutely possible that we could get,
we could receive the accolades of man,
and yet displease God.
It's possible.
We begin to think about this particular perspective
that is given to us, and I believe this morning,
that it's important when we think about a perspective,
that we would embrace it.
That we would say, this is how I want to have my focus
when I get up and I go into the workplace,
when I, this week, tomorrow, as I go into the workplace,
I wanna have this perspective,
I wanna embrace this perspective.
I guarantee you, the enemy's gonna fight you.
I guarantee you, something's gonna happen,
and it's gonna cause you that moment of frustration,
and then you just kinda can take a step back
and say, listen, I'm doing this not as a men pleaser,
I'm doing this heartily as to the Lord.
Notice in verse 24, knowing that of the Lord,
ye shall receive the reward of the inheritance,
and then notice this last phrase,
for ye serve the Lord Christ.
You serve the Lord Christ.
I want you to think about this.
We, as Bible believers, as those that have trusted Christ
as our Savior, we're saved, we're heaven-bound.
The reality is that I'm going to heaven.
I'm not looking to just receive a plaque
with my name on it in the front office.
I'm not looking for that corner office
for some level of accolades.
It's fine to be accomplished, and it's fine to pursue
and to have that recognition,
but ultimately, my perspective is the fact
that I'm serving Christ and I'm going to heaven one day.
And I can get so busy with trying
to pursue the corner office,
I can get so busy with trying to get my name on a plaque
and with all of the recognition and accolades
that could come in the workplace,
I can get so busy with those things
that I have in my mind compartmentalized spiritual
from carnal, if you will.
Carnal's a bad word to use,
but just the everyday monotony of life,
and saying, well, this is the workplace,
and therefore, I really don't have
any responsibilities here.
No, God has placed you there.
You are the light in your workplace.
We begin to understand how this perspective
will demand our best.
It will demand that we understand
that we're living for Christ
and we're serving the Lord Christ.
This is really, this truth is given to us in every area.
We look at the application here
with regard to the workplace
and we think about our behavior in the workplace,
but as I am working at the church house,
I'm cutting grass, I'm cleaning the church house.
Man, I'm doing that for the Lord.
I'm doing it for Christ.
And as I finish up the job, the task that's at hand,
I look back and I say, would my Savior be pleased with that?
Did I do my best?
Did I put in, did I do it as a men-pleaser
or did I do it with singleness of heart,
fearing God, serving God?
It'll change how we operate, it really will,
when I recognize that I'm doing it for the Lord.
Number of years ago, I would not mention
the individual's name for sake of embarrassment,
for some may know who they are,
but a number of years ago, I remember sitting
and watching an individual
and as they were doing some work here at the church
and they could not get a piece of machinery to work
that they were trying to get to work
and they were trying to blow off the parking lot
with all of the debris after cutting grass
and they could not get the unit to work
and literally, I saw on the cameras,
the individual with a broom to sweep the parking lot.
Wow, I thought, man, would I do that?
Or would I just be like, man,
I couldn't get the thing to start, I'm sorry.
But they were like, you know what?
I think, I never actually spoke to the individual about it,
but I think the perspective was, I'm doing this for God.
I'm doing this for God.
I went out and helped get the machine started
so they could use the blower and not have to push.
Could you imagine sweeping this parking lot?
I've shoveled this parking lot more times
than I could count,
but I can't imagine sweeping the parking lot.
But that perspective is a perspective,
listen, they didn't know anyone was even watching or knew.
They're doing it for God.
I like that perspective.
Romans 12 and verse number 11, the Bible says this,
in this portion of Scripture,
when we think about the responsibility,
it says in the workplace,
not slothful in business,
fervent in spirit, serving the Lord.
Not slothful in business.
Again, when we understand the principle
that is given to us in verse 22,
with regard to obedience, submission, integrity,
and then we see this perspective,
this biblical perspective that I'm working not for man,
I'm working as to the Lord.
I understand that I serve the Lord Christ,
then we find that I cannot be slothful in business.
It's going to demand my best.
It's going to require that I give it my all.
Not because I'm looking for accolades from man,
but because I'm serving my Savior.
We find that as we continue looking
at the portion of Scripture,
that not only do we see the need
to examine the principle, embrace the perspective,
but I find that we're to eliminate partiality.
In verse 25 and then in verse number one
of chapter number four,
we find that we're to eliminate partiality.
You'll remember that the subject of partiality
was addressed in verse number 11.
It was back there where Paul said
where there is neither Greek nor Jew,
circumcision nor uncircumcision.
Barbarians get thee in bond nor free,
but Christ is all and in all.
We come to verse 25 of this third chapter
and the Bible says,
but he that doeth wrong shall receive
for the wrong which he hath done.
Notice this phrase,
there is no respect of persons.
Verse one, master is given to your servants
that which is just and equal,
knowing that ye also have a master in heaven.
No doubt, there have been times in our lives
where we have observed partiality in the workplace.
No doubt, there's times in which someone
gets preferential treatment because of their last name,
because of their relationship with the boss,
because they go golfing with the CEO,
whatever the circumstance is,
we have witnessed, we have observed
partiality in the workplace.
But the biblical truth is that our God
is no respecter of persons
and therefore we, as his people,
should be no respecter of persons, amen?
There's some that sit within the congregation,
there are some that are listening via livestream today,
that you find your place in a place of supervision
in the workplace, that you find that your position
is one in which you have individuals
that would be responsible, accountable to you
as a supervisor, manager,
some level of executive leadership or management,
whatever it may be, and the reality is that
it is absolutely essential that there is
no respect of persons,
that we understand that our God is no respecter of persons
and therefore we are to be no respecter of persons.
We see it in our society,
but it doesn't make it right, amen?
In fact, there are many times in which
we'll observe partiality and it will bother us.
We find that God has given the truth here
in this portion of Scripture that there should be
no partiality, we're to eliminate the partiality.
There should be fairness in punishment as well
as in reward.
Notice what it says in verse 25,
but he that doeth wrong shall receive for the wrong
which he hath done.
Verse number one, master is given to your servants
that which is just and equal.
And so we understand this truth of fairness
not only in punishment, but also in reward.
Notice over in the book of Galatians, if you will,
hold your spot here in Colossians.
We'll be back in just a moment,
but look in Galatians chapter number six.
And I want you to see what we find here
in this portion of Scripture with regard to the truth
that God gives us.
He is, again, no respecter of persons
and I am thankful that he's given us that truth
in his word and we too are to be no respecter of persons.
It says in Galatians six and verse number seven,
be not deceived.
God is not mocked, for whatsoever a man soweth,
that shall he also reap.
There are consequences for our actions.
It's just the way it works, amen.
And we understand in our lives the importance
of this truth of us understanding it before God,
but us also carrying judgment out in like fashion.
Notice in verse number eight, there is oftentimes
as we think about verse number seven,
we think about it strictly in the negative context.
But if you look at verse number eight of Galatians six
with verse number seven, you find that the principle,
may I say law, that is established here
is a principle or law that is both positive and negative.
It's easy to focus on the negative,
but the reality is that verse number eight reveals to us
that it's both positive and negative.
It says, for he that soweth to his flesh
shall of the flesh reap corruption.
That's negative, all right?
That's not a good deal.
You don't want that fruit.
That's the individual, as a preacher of yesteryear said,
that there are people that claim to be followers of Christ
that sow seeds of wickedness Monday through Saturday,
and then come to the church house on Sunday
and pray for crop failure.
That's a great quote.
It's foolish.
They sow seeds of wickedness,
and then they pray for crop failure.
No, God says, for he that soweth to his flesh
shall of the flesh reap corruption.
But he that soweth to the Spirit
shall of the Spirit reap life everlasting.
That's positive.
And so the law, the principle that God has established
of sowing and reaping,
we understand biblically
that there's a negative aspect of that,
but there's a positive aspect of that.
And the reality is that we need to be sowing good seeds
so that we're reaping a good harvest, amen?
So that we don't have to worry
about praying for crop failure.
We can say, man, I want the crop to come in,
and I want it to come in good.
I mean, I want it to be plentiful.
Why?
Because I've sown some good seeds,
and I'm looking for that good harvest, amen?
And we find that here we're to be no respecter of persons.
We must eliminate partiality.
As we think about this truth in Colossians chapter three,
to end the chapter and to begin the fourth chapter,
we think about our behavior in the workplace.
And yes, there's principle, there's perspective.
We're to eliminate this partiality.
But I would submit to you this morning
that I believe that our behavior in the workplace,
as I mentioned by way of introduction,
can be, may I say should be, a catalyst for revival.
I wonder this morning if we could just for a few moments
as we conclude the service
and think about this aspect of our behavior in the workplace
and we think about the truth that God has given us
and we say, how does this truth apply in my life?
I wonder this morning if when we would consider ourselves
those that are employees this morning,
those that have a place of employment,
whether you're at the bottom of the corporate ladder
or you're at the top of the corporate ladder, matters not,
but you have a place of employment,
there's some place that you'll go,
perhaps even tomorrow,
and you'll go to that place of employment.
I wonder this morning
if we would begin to consider ourselves missionaries.
Not a missionary to a country,
but a missionary to a company.
Understanding that God has placed us there.
I read a book, I actually finished it yesterday,
it's called The Business Revival.
It's written by an individual
that probably doesn't believe everything biblically
as I believe or as you would believe,
but it's written by an individual that believes,
he's trusted Christ as a savior
by his testimony in the book,
and he believes that God hears and answers prayer
and he believed that God had him in his place of employment
for a greater reason than just making a living.
And man, it's a great book.
I'd encourage you to get it and read it.
Again, I would not endorse
all of what he would believe biblically or theologically,
but what God has done through this man
and this perspective of how God is able to work is amazing.
And really the thought this morning
that I'm not just a missionary to,
or I'm not looking at just a missions map
saying these are the missionaries that we support
that are going to foreign countries,
but I wonder this morning, what if we could,
what if we took the time to put together
some sort of internal document of the companies
that our members are missionaries to?
And we began to pray one for another
the way that we pray for our missionaries.
Begin to think about, I'll use myself as an example,
when I worked in the corporate world
that I worked for Sikorsky Aircraft Corporation,
what if I had a group of people in the church
that I attended during that period?
the period of time of my life
that they prayed for the missionary at Sikorsky.
The way that they prayed for the missionary in Scotland.
You see how it changed our perspective?
We begin to see that God has you in that place
for a reason, for a time, for a purpose.
And it's so much greater
than just making a living.
So often we get caught up in the corporate world
and all the culture and the society.
We understand that God can take care of us
any way He chooses to take care of us.
Amen?
He used a raven to feed His prophet.
God can take care of us.
In this particular era, in this particular time,
we find that often He uses a place of employment
in order to take care of us,
but we must understand
that it's not about just making a living.
The author of this book, he says it this way.
He said, I think it's great.
Do you have a desire to make a difference
or just to make a mortgage payment?
That was a quote from his book.
That's what he says.
And it's making that difference.
And see, oftentimes what happens,
and again, as we begin to think about
this portion of Scripture
and begin to think about our perspective
and all that takes place,
I wonder this morning how many people
in our place of employment,
how many people that we've come into contact with,
and perhaps we've worked at this place
for a short period of time,
perhaps we've worked there for a long period of time,
how many people in that particular place of employment
know that you're a follower of Jesus Christ?
I'm not suggesting this morning
that we steal the time of our employers
and we're there seeking to simply propagate the gospel
and being a bad employee.
No, I'm suggesting that we're good employees,
the best employees,
but I'm suggesting that, hey,
is there somebody that you're praying for in your workplace?
Is there somebody that you know
that's dealing with a problem,
that's dealing with,
how many of you,
I'm not gonna ask you any names,
but I am gonna ask you to raise your hand,
how many of you know somebody
that you work with that's lost?
Everybody that has a job,
now, I can't raise my hand
because I work with Holly,
and she's saved, amen.
But the reality is, listen,
if you work somewhere,
you probably know a lost person, right?
Have you ever prayed for them?
Do you have a list of coworkers?
Maybe start with the one that bothers you the most.
Seriously.
Because guess what?
God hears and answers prayer.
You don't have to neglect one minute on the clock
of working for your employer
to do what you're supposed to do
to pray for a coworker.
Pray that God would open up a door,
give you an opportunity.
And when you embrace the perspective
that we dealt with earlier in the message,
as we are doing what we're doing
not for the boss,
but for the Lord,
when somebody says,
man, this boss, I can't stand,
he's just a tyrant,
he's this, he's that,
blah, blah, blah, blah,
I could share stories with you
from the corporate world.
I worked in the corporate world for years.
I understand what that difficulty is like.
I may not understand your specific person,
but we can just exchange names.
Because you're always going to find someone
that's that way.
But I wonder this morning,
do they see Christ in us,
the hope of glory?
Do the coworkers understand that,
listen, how can you deal with this guy,
blah, blah, blah?
I'm looking beyond that person
because I'm working as unto the Lord,
not unto men.
I believe this morning,
it's interesting,
I planned to preach this message several weeks ago.
In fact, it was the week after
Brother Savalle was here
that I was planning to preach this message,
and through a series of circumstances,
the Lord led me to preach a message
on the return of Christ.
And then last week,
we had a baby dedication.
But I believe that it's very interesting
how that we look at this passage of Scripture
this morning,
and I believe that there's a direct correlation,
connection, if you will,
to the message that I'll be preaching this evening
from Genesis 21.
And I will not deal with much of that
because I'll be preaching it this evening,
but Abimelech says this of Abraham in Genesis 21
in verse number 22,
God is with thee
in all that thou doest.
And I just wonder this morning,
we think about the workplace,
the behavior in our workplace,
I wonder this morning,
is there anyone
that we work with that would say of us
what Abimelech said of Abraham?
God is with thee
in all that thou doest.
Do they see God's hand of favor upon us?
Do they see that there's something different about us?
The reason that I believe
that this is a catalyst for revival,
our behavior in the workplace,
a catalyst for revival,
is because there are connections
that you have in your workplace
that God can allow
because of various relationships
for you to be able to share the gospel with them
and they get saved
and they get added to the church
and amazing things can happen.
Do you know that when I go and knock on someone's door,
they don't know who I am
and they probably don't want me there?
I have no relationship with them whatsoever
and I'm gonna go there
and I'm gonna try to reach them with the gospel
but you have people that you work with
that there's a level,
your neighbors is another aspect,
we won't deal with that this morning,
but the people that you work with,
there's a relationship there.
You pray for them and you work
and you ask God to open up doors of opportunity
and I understand there are times we say,
oh, there's no way that's gonna happen.
Do you believe God?
Do you believe that God is able
to do something in your workplace?
Do you believe that God is able to use you,
that he planted you there?
Again, the question was asked by this author
in the book that he wrote that I just finished yesterday,
who am I here for?
He gives the testimony that he had a career change
and in his career change,
as he started in the new place of employment,
he had some struggles and things that he was dealing with,
with just trying to learn a new industry
and so on and so forth,
but the reality is that he wanted to have this perspective,
who am I here for?
Not only to answer that question that I'm here,
God has placed me here,
but did God place me here in order to reach certain people
with the gospel?
The answer is yes, because we're his ambassadors, amen?
And just as we look at that missions map
and we focus upon and we speak about the importance
of world missions and I'm for it and I'm behind it
and I give to missions every month
and I love missions and we pray for our missionaries
and we're excited to hear updates from our missionaries
about what God is doing and how God is working.
But wouldn't it be encouraging if next Sunday
or eight Sundays from now,
there's someone sitting in the pew next to you?
Says, oh, nice to meet you, this is one of my coworkers.
Let me share with you how God worked and what God did
and how God opened doors.
Man, that's what it's about.
It's not about just making a living.
And so often we live in this culture,
we live in this society that we can gain that perspective.
I understand that culture and society is beating us up
every single day, I understand that.
And it's very easy to get our eyes shifted
from what the biblical principle is
and get into the monotony of life,
to the monotony, the mundane behavior of I just go to work,
I'm just in and out and I'm just doing.
No, no, God has you there for a purpose.
When I understand this morning that whatsoever I do,
I do it heartily as to the Lord, not unto men.
I'm seeking to please God.
And you know, God can move us wherever he wants to move us
and he can give us employment wherever he wants
to give us employment and we seek to be,
even in that place, his representative.
Are there challenges?
Absolutely.
You know why there are challenges?
Because the devil doesn't want you to do it.
So there'll be challenges.
But the reality is that we can pray to the God of heaven
who can move in hearts and lives
and can bring to pass amazing things.
Listen, you might not be able to talk to your coworker
about the Lord in certain settings
because of the task at hand
and the responsibility of being a good employee,
but if you get a lunch break,
there's nothing that says
that you can't have lunch with someone.
And here's the thing, and this is,
God's been helping me in this,
not only through just a variety of means,
talking with some of our missionaries
and learning some things
about some of what our missionaries are dealing with
and some of the difficulties that they have faced
and so on and so forth is that,
maybe what we do is we just spend consistent time
in prayer for an individual
before we start trying to beat them over the head with Bible.
And just pray that God would soften their heart,
that God would allow things in their lives
that will help them to understand their need for Christ.
Maybe it's your neighbor.
or maybe it's a family member that we just pray for.
Within the context of this text of scripture,
maybe it's a co-worker.
When we ended the revival meeting,
Pastor Edwards made this statement on one of the nights,
I think it was Tuesday evening.
He asked this question about God placing someone's name
on your heart to pray for.
And I just wonder this morning,
as you think about your workplace,
and you think about the context of this particular message,
maybe there's a decision that we need to make
that, you know what, I've kind of lost focus a little bit.
I've kind of lost my way in the workplace.
I've gotten caught up in the politics of work.
The office politics and the office whatever.
And I've not really been working heartily as to the Lord.
I've not really been the employee that I ought to be.
You know that, God knows that.
But maybe this morning,
maybe God would put someone's name on your heart.
And you just wanna make a commitment to God,
I'm gonna pray for them.
And I'm gonna pray that God will open up
a door of opportunity.
I believe with all of my heart that when we pray
that God will open opportunities and we make a commitment
that will seize those opportunities,
that those are prayers that God delights in answering.
Oftentimes it's easy to see an opportunity going
then coming.
We say, man, I missed that opportunity.
But if we're specifically engaged in praying for a coworker
and praying that God will open their heart
to the truth of the gospel and praying
that God would give us the opportunity.
I had plenty of times where I had coworkers
that would come to me and say, say it in different ways.
I know you're a, I had somebody say,
I know you're a man of the cloth.
And the world is that, man.
Anyway, they'd say it different ways.
But they'd say, you know what?
We just found out somebody's got cancer,
somebody's got my this, my that.
Would you pray for me?
Because God works in the hearts of people.
And if you begin to pray for those opportunities
and you begin to pray for that one
that God will put on your heart and mind,
and you faithfully do that,
and you're the best worker that you can be
because you're serving Christ,
God will open up doors of opportunity.
And you may be the one that they come to
and say, would you pray for me?
You can pray for them.
You see how that door just got opened for God to work.
And of course, the greatest need that anyone needs,
the greatest need that any individual has
is the need for salvation.
Oftentimes, it will be a need for health,
it'll be a need for finances,
it'll be a need for marriage,
it'll be a need for fill in the blank
that will bring them to the place of realizing
they're falling apart, their life is a mess.
And then, ultimately, through conversation
and through biblical truth,
they'll realize what they really need is Christ.
What they need is Christ.
And God has you in your place.
I would not do it for sake of the fact
that we're on live stream,
but if I could, if I knew,
I don't even know everywhere that people work in our church,
but if I knew the name of each employer,
in my heart and in my mind,
it's we have a missionary to fill in the blank,
a missionary to fill in the blank,
a missionary to fill in the blank.
These are the missionaries from our church
that this week, that tomorrow,
get to go into all of those workplaces
and let your light shine.
We tell the kids, we sing it with the kids.
This little light of mine, I'm gonna let it shine.
Hide it under a bushel.
No!
But man, we go to the workplace,
we say, man, I left that light at home
because I am, right?
But we're his representatives, we're his ambassadors.
And I believe this morning in the culture,
in the age in which we're living,
that this truth about our behavior in the workplace
can be the catalyst to revival in our world
because we go all over the place,
all of our different respective places of employment,
and we can reach people with the gospel.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you this morning.
We thank you for loving us.
God, we thank you for your Word
and how your Word gives us instruction
truly in every area of our lives.
This morning, as we focus our attention
upon this portion of Scripture
and deal with our behavior in the workplace,
I thank you for the places of employment
that you've given to our church family,
the places in which you have chosen
to plant them,
not solely for the purpose of making a living,
for the purpose of being your representative.
There are souls that daily come in contact
with those that are sitting in this building
and those that are listening via live stream
that do not know the Lord Jesus Christ.
Lord, as we faithfully pray for our missionaries,
pray this morning that you would help us
to faithfully pray for one another
with the thought that we go as missionaries
not to a foreign country, but to a company.
God, I pray that you'd help us to be
the employees that we're to be.
Would you help us to operate with integrity,
singleness of heart?
Would you help us in whatsoever we do
to do it heartily as unto the Lord, not unto men?
Would you help us, God, to exalt and magnify you
in our lives and even in the workplace?
Put that name of that coworker
on folks' hearts this morning.
I pray that we would make a commitment
to pray faithfully and diligently
that you would open up doors of opportunity,
that those opportunities would be seized.
Lord, you'd help us to see souls saved and lives changed.
But truly, this could be a catalyst for revival.
We pray that you'd seal every decision,
that you'd work as only you can.
We'll thank you for it, in Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand?